GEODE ._MA    AN IJVgERN'ATIONAL JOURNAL OF SOIL SCIENCE  VOL 33 (1984)    EDI TOR-IN-CHIEF    R W SImonson, College Park, Md.    EDI TORIA L BOARD    P W Arnold, Newcastle upon Tyne  J Bennema, Wageningen  E. Besoam Monasterto, Santtago  G H Bolt, Wagenmgen  G. Brummer, Klel  P Bullock, Harpenden  B T. Bunting, Hamdton, Ont  J.V.J Carvalho Cardoso, Lisbon  F E. Clark, Fort Collins, Colo  R B Darnels, Washington, D C  F. de Conmck, Ghent  J.M. de Vilhers, Pietermarltzburg  R Dudal, Rome  A.E. Erickson, East Lansing, Mtch_  J.J. Fr=ptat, Heverlee  W H. Gardner, Pullman, Wash  D J. Greenland, Manilla  F.J. Hingston, Wembley, W A.  A Hoyos de Castro, Madrid  R.F Isbell, Aitkenvale, QId.  Y. Ishizuka, Sapporo  M L. Jackson, Madison, Wisc  M Jamagne, Ardon  J J. Jurinak, Logan, Utah    E J Kamprath, Raletgh, N.C  V Kovda, Moscow  J. L,~g, As  P F. Low, West Lafayette, Ind.  A.F MacKenzie, Ste Anne de  Bellevue, Que.  F Mancml, Florence  J.A McKeague, Ottawa, Ont  F R Moormann, Utrecht  L A Nelson, Raletgh, N C  S Pawluk, Edmonton, Alta.  D.A Rennie, Saskatoon, Sask.  F. Rtchard, Uttikom  R.H Rust, St Paul, Mmn.  G K Rutherford, Kingston, Ont  M Schnttzer, Ottawa, Ont  U. Schwertmann, Muntch  F J Stevenson, Urbana, III  D. Swartzendruber, Lincoln, Nebr.  R S Swift, Canterbury  I Szabolcs, Budapest  A van Wambeke, Ithaca, N Y.  D H. Yaalon, Jerusalem    ELSEVIER  AMSTERDAM - OXFORD - NEW YORK - TOKYO                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        