Geoderma, 33 (1984) 219--226                                                  219  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CLASSIFICATION OF FIVE PEDONS NEAR AFGOI, SOMALIA*    D.L. MOKMA and O.H.D. ABDULLA  Department of Crop and Soil Sciences, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI  (U.S.A.)  (Received June 6, 1983; accepted after revision March 27, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Mokma, D.L. and Abdulla, O.H.D., 1984. Classification of five pedons near Afgoi,  Somalia. Geoderma, 33: 219--226.    Five pedons representing the major soils on the Central Agricultural Research Sta-  tion located on the Shabelle River floodplain near Afgoi (Somalia) were described and  sampled. The samples were analyzed for particle-size distribution, pH, calcium carbon-  ate equivalent, electrical conductivity and sodium adsorption ratio. According to Soil  Taxonomy, three pedons were classified as Udic Chromusterts, very fine, isohyper-  thermic; one as a Udic Chromustert, fine isohyperthermic; and one as a Typic Usti-  fluvent, fine-loamy isohyperthermic. Four of the pedons were classified as Chromic  Vertisols and the fifth as a Calcaric Fluvisol according to legend of the FAO-Unesco  soil map of the world.    INTRODUCTION    There is a great need for basic soil information in Somalia if this country  is to reach its goal of self-sufficiency in staple food grains (Kaplan et al.,  1977). The purpose of this study was to add to the basic soil information  in Somalia by determining some physical and chemical properties and  classifying the major softs on the Central Agricultural Research Station  (CARS) which is located on the Shabelle River floodplain near Afgoi.  FAO (1968) prepared a reconnaissance soil map for about the southern  one-third of the country (20,860,000 ha). Sixty-six soil types and land  types were mapped. Hunting Technical Services (1969) mapped the softs  in the Balad and Mordile irrigation project areas located along the ShabeUe  River. Soils were classified as Udic Chromusterts, Udorthentic Chromusterts  and Typic Ustifluvents.    *Published as Michigan Agric. Exp. Stn. Journal Article No. 10530.    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    220    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Study area    Somalia is located on the Horn of Africa between about 1 to 12  latitude and about 41-51 longitude. CARS is located about 33 km  northwest of Mogadiscio, the capital of Somalia, and 3 km east of Afgoi  (Fig. 1). It lies at about 28'20"N latitude and 457'35"E longitude.  CARS covers about 400 ha with 60 ha developed for experimental pur-  poses under irrigation. The entire station is located on the floodplain of    /   42'  A    -s~.,~l,,~          ~.  7        %  /  Algol  Mogachsclo  5"  0           300  K~Iometers  ~,        ~o~    Bf    /  N           UCvf    12       ,1  &gt;      /       UCvf  "~   ,             8                   .2         UCf  \  '\    0    200  Meters    Fig. 1. A. Location of Central Agricultural Research Station (CARS) near Afgoi. B.  Locations of the five pedons (1--5) on soil map of CARS. UCvf = Udic Chromusterts,  very-fine,  isohyperthermic; UCf= Udic  Chromusterts, fine, isohyperthermic; TUfl=  Typic Ustifluvents, fine-loamy, isohyperthermic.    221    the ShabeUe River. The softs were developed in the fine-textured, recent  alluvium. These materials were derived mainly from the erosion of soils  developed  from carbonate-rich materials (Veredchenko and Gusenkov,  1965; African Social Studies Programme, 1973).  There are two rainy seasons in Somalia. The "Gu" is the longer, more  dependable and occurs during April to June. The "Der" is the shorter,  frequently has little rainfall, and occurs during October to December.  The mean annual precipitation at CARS is 536.3 mm with irregular dis-  tribution (Fig. 2). The soils are considered to be dry in some parts of their  moisture control section for more than 90 cumulative days each year but  are moist in some part for more than 180 cumulative days or continuously  moist in some part for 90 consecutive days. Therefore soils in the CARS  area have an ustic moisture regime (Soft Survey Staff, 1975).    30     20  O       Temperature    w            ,    )    i    |    e   1    )    ;  g      F     M     A     M     J     J      A      S     0      N     D    120    i00    8o  60  z  4o ~    20    MONTHS  Fig. 2. Mean monthly temperature and mean monthly rainfall for CARS (mean of 23  years)   The mean annual air temperature at CARS is 27.0 with a mean Decem-  ber through February temperature of 27.4 and a mean June through  August temperature of 25.6 (Fig. 2). Therefore, soils in the CARS area  have an isohyperthermic temperature regime (Soil Survey Staff, 1975).  Five pedons which were representative of the soils on CARS were de-  scribed (Table I) and sampled for analysis in the laboratory. The locations  of the five pedons are shown in Fig. 1.    222  TABLE I  Morphological properties of the soils    Horizon  Depth      Texture*~  Munsell Color             Structure*  (cm)    Moist       Dry    Boundary*    Pedon 1  Ap         0--30   c            5YR 3/2    5YR 3/3  lcsbk        as  A12       30--60   c            5YR 3/2    5YR 3/3   2cabk         cs  A13       60--90    c            5YR 3/2    5YR 3/3   2vcabk        gw  A14       90--120  c            5YR 3/2    5YR 4/3   3m and csbk  as  C1        120--135  c           7.5YR 3/2   7.5YR 5/4   2msbk        gw  C2        135--200  c            5YR 3/2   7.5YR 4/2   3msbk        --  Pedon 2  Ap          0--30    c           7.5YR 3/2   7.5YR 5/4   lcsbk         as  A12       30--94   c           7.5YR 3/2   7.5YR 5/4   3vcsbk        as  A13        94--107  c           7.5YR3/2   7.5YR5/4   3msbk        as  C1        107--120  c           7.5YR3/2   7.5YR4/2   2fsbk         as  C2        120--128  I            10YR 5/4       --        0m            ai  C3       128--140  c           10YR 4/3      --       3msbk        aw  C4        140--200  l            7.5YR4/4       --        0m            --  Pedon 3  Ap          0--30   c            5YR 3/2    5YR 4/3   1 and 2msbk  as  A12       30--85    c            5YR 3/2    5YR 4/3   2msbk        aw  C1         85--97    c           7.5YR 4/2   7.5YR 5/4   2fsbk         aw  C2         97--107  sil           5YR 3/2   7.5YR 7/4   0m           as  C3        107--119  sil           5YR 3/2   7.5YR 7/4   lmsbk        as  C4        119--141  sic          10YR 5/1       --        2mcpr         as  C5        141--205  sl           10YR 5/4      --       0m           --  Pedon 4  Ap          0--25    c             5YR 3/2     5YR 5/3   2c and vcgr   as  A12       25--90   c            5YR 3/2    5YR 5/3   lcsbk         cs  AC        90--200  c           7.5YR 4/4      --        lvcsbk        --  Pedon 5  A1          0--50    sicl        7.5YR 4/2   7.5YR 6/4   lmsbk        aw  C1         50--75   l           7.5YR 7]4      --       0m           as  C2         75--130  sicl          5YR 3/2    5YR 3/3   2f and msbk  as  C3       130--140  sil         7.5YR 7/4      --       0m           as  C4       140--200  sil           5YR 3/2      --       2f and msbk  --    *~ Symbols used are given in Soil Survey Manual (Soil Survey Staff, 1951).    METHODS    Laboratory analyses of the soil samples were performed on the less  than 2-mm material. Particle size analysis was done by the hydrometer  method (Day, 1965). The pH was measured electrometrically on a satu-  rated paste (Richards, 1954). Calcium carbonate equivalent (CCE) was    223    determined by acid neutralization (Richards, 1954). Electrical conduc-  tivity was measured on the saturation extract (Bower and Wilcox, 1965).  Sodium adsorption ratio (SAR) was determined on the saturation extracts  (Richards, 1954).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Physical and chemical measurements    Pedon 1 has 70--82% clay in all horizons with 72% clay in the control  section (25--100 cm) (Table II). Pedons 2 and 3 have 72 and 69% clay  in the control sections but have coarser materials below the control sec-    TABLE II    Some physical and chemical properties of the soils    Horizon  Depth      Sand       Silt         Clay             pH  CCE.1  EC.2          SAR*~  (cm)       (0.05--    (0.002--   (&lt;:0.002 mm)        (%)     (mmhos/cm)  2.0 mm)   0.05 mm)  (%)  (%)     (%)    Pedon 1  Ap         0--30     2         24         74              7.9  16       3.2            2.8  A12       30---60     7          23          70               7.8  15       1.3             3.1  A13       60--90     9          21          70               7.8  27       2.1             2.4  A14       90--120    0          18          82               7.8  20       2.1             3.1  C1        120--135    3          27          70               7.9  28       0.7             2.1  C2        135--200    0          19          81               7.8  --        3.2            3.0  Pedon 2  Ap         0--30     7         35         58              7.8  26       1.1            1.7  A12       30--94     0         26         74              7.8  23       1.5            3.3  A13       94--107    4          34         62               7.7  10       1.4            2.6  C1        107--120    7          26         67               7.8  16       1.2             2.5  C2        120--128  46          36          18               7.8  21       0.7             1.6  C3        128--140  14          27          59               7.5  20       1.6             3.2  C4        140--200  38          49          13               7.4  --        1.9             4.6  Pedon 3  Ap         0--30     4         28         68              7.9  22       0.1            0.3  A12       30--85     2         25         73              3.0  20       1.8            9.3  C1         85--97     2          35         63               7.8  24       6.5           15.0  C2         97--107  16          62          22               7.9  23       9.5           21.0  C3        107--119    4          72          24               7.9  32      10.0           20.0  C4        119--141    3          47          50               7.9  29      10.1           16.0  C5        141--205  66          25           9               8.0  --        7.0           14.0  Pedon 4  Ap          0--25    17          39          44               7.6  20       1.1             3.5  A12       25--90    14          37          49               7.7  12       1.6           11.0  AC         90--200  11          39          50               7.6  29       5.0           13.0  Pedon 5  A1          0--50    13          44          38               7.8  20       3.2             1.4  C1         50--75    43          38          19               7.6  18       5.5             1.0  C2         75--130  14          48          38               7.8  18      I0.0            5.4  C3        130--140  27          65           8               7.6  18       8.5            2.6  C4        140--200  11          67          22               7.8  19      12.0            8.0    * ~ CCE, calcium c~rbonate equivalent.  ,2 EC, electrical conductivity.  ,3 SAR, sodium adsorption ratio.    224    tion. Pedon 2 has coarse-loamy material below the control section and  pedon 3 stratified fine-silty, fine and coarse-loamy materials. The family  particle size class of pedons 1, 2 and 3 is very fine. Pedon 4 is fine through-  out with 49% clay in the control section. The family particle size class  of pedon 5 is fine-loamy in the control section with a clay content of 32%.  Stratification of fine-loamy and coarse-loamy materials occurs below the  control section. Clay contents reported for pedons in the Goluen soil ranged  from 54 to 68% in the control section (FAO, 1968).  Reactions in all pedons are slightly to moderately alkaline (Table II).  This reflects the limited leaching capability of the ustic moisture regime  and the carbonate-rich parent materials. Reactions reported for pedons  in the Goluen soil ranged from 7.4 to 8.3 (FAO, 1968).  Calcium carbonate equivalents range from 10 to 32% for all horizons  (Table II). Lower horizons of pedons 1 and 3 had higher CCE's than upper  horizons. Pedons 2 and 4 had irregulardistributions of carbonates. In pedon  5 carbonate contents are nearly constant throughout the profile. The car-  bonate contents of these five pedons are similar to those reported in pre-  vious studies (FAO, 1968; Hunting Technical Services, 1969).  Electrical conductivities of the horizons range from 0.7 to 12.0 mmhos  per centimeter (Table II). The conductivities of pedons 1 and 2 are low  with no well-defined distribution pattern. Pedons 3 and 4 have low con-  ductivities in the upper 85 cm and medium to high conductivities at lower  depths. Pedon 5 has high conductivities throughout.  Conductivities were also determined on all horizons collected from  a 110 m grid sampling over the developed 60 ha. Mean conductivities in-  crease with depth (Table III). In the upper meter 98% of the samples were  nonsaline or slightly saline (EC values less than 8 mmhos/cm, Table IV).  Therefore, no major salinity problems are expected in these softs at this  time. Yields of some crops, however, may be restricted (Richards, 1954).  The EC's of the lower meter in each pedon are higher, 19% of the sam-  ples had EC values above 8 mmhos/cm.  Sodium adsorption ratio values indicate no sodium hazard in pedons  1, 2 and 5 (Table II). There are no sodium hazards in the upper horizons  of pedons 3 and 4. In the lower horizons of these two pedons there are    TABLE III    Electrical conductivities of soils in the developed portion of CARS    Depth in profile          No. of     EC (mmhos/cm)  samples    Mean    Range    Horizons in 0--50 cm    108        1.65  Horizons in 0--1 m       186        2.26  Horizons in 1--2 m      101        4.61    0.45--5.0  0.45--10.0  0.70--16.0    TABLE IV  Percent of samples in three ranges of electrical conductivity    225    Depth in profile    Range of EC (mmhos/cm)    0-4      4-8      8-16  Horizons in 0--1 m     84        14         2  Horizons in 1--2 m     59        22        19    low to medium sodium hazards. Most horizons of the pedons in the Goluen  soil had no sodium hazards but some lower horizons had low sodium  hazards (FAO, 1968). High salt concentrations in the lower horizons of  soils along the Juba River were thought to be a relict of the lagoon-delta  stage during the Tertiary period and not the result of modem salt accu-  mulations (Veredchenko and Gusenkov, 1965).    Classification    Pedons 1, 2, 3 and 4 have cracks that are at least 1 cm wide at a depth  of 50 cm. They also have intersecting slickensides between 25 cm and  1 m. Therefore, they are all classified as Vertisols (Soft Survey Staff, 1975).  Pedons 1, 2 and 3 are classified as Udic Chromusterts, very fine, isohyper-  thermic and pedon 4 as a Udic Chromustert, fine, isohyperthermic. No  mineralogical determinations were made on these softs. From the high  shrink-swell displayed by these softs, the mineralogy is most likely mont-  morillonitic. Softs along the Shabelle River in Ethiopia (Donahue, 1972)  and part of Somalia (Hunting Technical Services, 1969; Virgo, 1981) have  also been classified as Vertisols."  Pedon 5 does not have the properties of Vertisols. It haa no diagnostic  horizon other than an ochric epipedon. A cambic horizon is absent as  evidenced by the C1 and C3 horizons lacking structure (Table I) and the  uniformity of calcium carbonate equivalent (CCE) (Table II). Therefore,  this pedon is considered an Entisol (Soft Survey Staff, 1975). Because  the C2 and C4 horizons have darker colors than the C1 and C3 horizons  it is assumed this pedon has an irregular decrease in organic carbon and  therefore it is classified as a Fluvent at the sub-order level. With an ustic  soil moisture regime, this pedon is classified as an Ustifluvent. This pedon  lacks low chroma mottles and cracks and has a light colored A1 horizon.  Pedon 5 is therefore classified as a Typic Ustifluvent, fine-loamy, isohyper-  thermic.  The very fine isohyperthermic Udic Chromusterts are the dominant  softs at CARS, 70% of the area (Fig. 1). About 26% of the station is com-  prised of fine, isohyperthermic, Udic Chromusterts. Fine-loamy, isohyper-  thermic Typic Ustifluvents comprise only 4% of CARS and are located    226    in a channel remnant. Udic Chromusterts and Typic Ustifluvents were  two of the four subgroups found on the Balad and Mordila irrigation project  areas (Hunting Technical Services, 1969).  Pedons 1, 2, 3 and 4 are all classified as Chromic Vertisols in the FAO-  Unesco soil map of the world legend (FAO, 1974) because they have moist  chromas greater than 1.5 in the soil matrix throughout the upper 30 cm.  Pedon 5 is classified as a Calcaric Fluvisol because it is calcareous through-  out the 20 to 50 cm depth and is developed in recent alluvial deposits.    REFERENCES    African Social Studies Programme, 1973, Kit on Ethiopia. African Social Studies Pro-  gramme, Nairobi, Kenya, 80 pp.  Bower, C.A. and Wilcox, L.V., 1965. Soluble salts. In: C.A. Black (Editor), Methods  of Soil Analysis, 2. Agronomy, 9: 933--951.  Day, P.R., 1965. Particle fractionation and particle size analysis. In: C.A. Black (Editor),  Methods of Soil Analysis, 1. Agronomy, 9: 545--567.  Donahue, R.L., 1972. Ethiopia: Taxonomy, Cartography and Ecology of Soils. African  Studies Center, Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, 44 pp.  Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), 1968. Agriculture and water surveys, Somalia.  Final Report, Vol. III. Landforms and Soils. FAO, Rome, pp. 6--171.  Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), 1974. Fao-Unesco Soil map of the world,  1:5,000,000, Vol. I. Legend. Unesco, Paris, 59 pp.  Hunting Technical Services, 1969. Project for the Water Control and Management of  the Shabelle River, Somalia, Vol. V. Soils and Agriculture. Hunting Tech. Serv.,  Herts, England. pp. 17--52 and 83--166.  Kaplan, I., Dobert, M.K., McLaughlin, J.L., Marvin, B., Roth, N.M. and Whitaker, D.D.,  1977. Area Handbook for Somalia. U.S. Gov. Printing Off., Washington, D.C., 392 pp.  Richards, A.L. (Editor), 1954. Diagnosis and Improvement of Saline and Alkali Soils.  U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook No. 60, pp. 83--126.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook No. 18,503 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook No. 436, 754 pp.  Veredchenko, Y.P. and Gusenkov, Y.I., 1965. Soils of the Guiba River Valley in Equa-  torial Somalia. Soy. Soft Sci., 1965: 1166--1175.  Virgo, K., 1981. Observations of cracking in Somali Vertisols. Soil Sci., 131: 60--61.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractFive pedons representing the major soils on the Central Agricultural Research Station located on the Shabelle River floodplain near Afgoi (Somalia) were described and sampled. The samples were analyzed for particle-size distribution, pH, calcium carbonate equivalent, electrical conductivity and sodium adsorption ratio. According to Soil Taxonomy, three pedons were classified as Udic Chromusterts, very fine, isohyperthermic; one as a Udic Chromustert, fine isohyperthermic; and one as a Typic Ustifluvent, fine-loamy isohyperthermic. Four of the pedons were classified as Chromic Vertisols and the fifth as a Calearic Fluvisol according to legend of the FAO-Unesco soil map of the world.