Geoderma, 34 (1984) 229--250                                                     229  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    RECENT AND ANCIENT TRACES OF SCARAB BEETLE ACTIVITY IN  SANDY SOILS OF THE NETHERLANDS    LIJBERT BRUSSAARD.1 and LEX T. RUNIA.2  Dept. of Soil Science and Geology, Agricultural University, P.O. Box 3 7, 6700 AA  Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Received October 25, 1983; accepted after revision June 28, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Brussaard, L. and Runia, L.T., 1984. Recent and ancient traces of scarab beetle activity in  sandy soils of The Netherlands. Geoderma, 34 : 229--250.    Traces of burrowing activity by the scarab beetle Typhaeus typhoeus in sandy soils of  The Netherlands are described. These traces include mounds of sand deposited on the  surface and open and back-filled burrows in the soil. Other back-filling traces are  described from two types of sandy soil in The Netherlands. By analogy with the traces  from T. typhoeus these are interpreted as resulting from scarab beetle activity.  Preliminary measurements have been made of the amounts of soil deposited on the  surface by T. typhoeus. In favourable habitats the quantities are as high as 450 kg ha-~  annually.  The disturbance of sandy soil profiles by scarab beetles is calibrated by their back-  filling traces with the help of literature data on fossil beetle remains and original data on  clay illuviation. The disturbance is shown to be mainly of Preboreal and post-Atlantic age.  Clay configurations in back-filling traces associated with lamellae support the conten-  tion that the lamellae were formed by clay illuviation.    INTRODUCTION    This paper describes traces of activity from scarab beetles living in sandy  soils of The Netherlands. To date no mention has been made of the  conspicuous, locally abundant and probably most persistent of those traces,  viz. the traces of back-filling of burrows by the beetles. We will utilize the  back-filled burrows to calibrate the disturbance of the soil by the beetles.  Biological homogenization, i.e. the reworking of soil by animals resulting  in the disruption or obliteration of soil lamination was described as an    *1Present address and reprint requests: Institute for Soil Fertility, P.O. Box 30003,  9750 RA Haren, The Netherlands.  *2Present address:  Albert Egges van Giffen Instituut voor Prae- en Protohistorie,  University of Amsterdam, Singel 453, 1012 WP Amsterdam, The Netherlands.    0016-7061/84[$03.00   O 1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    230    important process in soil formation by Hoeksema and Edelman (1960).  Recently, interest in the effects of animals on soil has been growing (Hole,  1981; Bal, 1982; Hoogerkamp et al., 1983). Scarab beetles or their larvae,  however, have only rarely been mentioned. For example, traces from the  June beetle, not specified in detail, are mentioned by Ahlbrandt et al. (1978)  as common and abundant, respectively, in two out of eleven inland dune  fields in the U.S.A. Valiachmedov (1977) mentioned scarab pupal chambers  as traces in Sierozem soils in the Soviet republic of Tadshikistan, and  Ratcliffe and Fagerstrom (1980) report the open burrows of scarabs as  traces.  Finally, Kalisz and Stone (1984) measured the mixing of sandy soils of  north-central Florida (USA) by scarab beetles.  This paper is the second of a series evaluating the contribution of scarab  beetles to the past and present genesis of sandy soils.    TRACES OF ACTIVITY FROM THE DUNG BEETLE TYPHAEUS TYPHOEUS    We have chosen the dung beetle Typhaeus typhoeus (Linnaeus, 1758) as a  model trace-making scarab beetle, because it burrows down to 1 m and in  some cases even deeper. T. typhoeus is associated with sandy soils, as are  most scarab beetles of its kind.  Fig. 1 schematically shows the results of the activity of a pair of dung  beetles in the soil. The behaviour of the beetles has been described by  Brussaard (1983).  A "trace" has been defined as "an individually distinctive biogenic  structure, especially one that is related more or less directly to the  morphology of the organisms that made it: tracks, trails, burrows, coprolites,  fecal castings and similar features, fossil or recent" {Frey, 1973). Among the  most conspicuous, though ephemeral, traces of activity are the sand mounds  on the soil surface, measuring approximately 5 cm in height and 10--15 cm  in diameter. They arise when the beetles push up the sand while excavating  a burrow for nesting. If the soil profile is known, the composition of the  mound gives a rough indication of the depth the beetles have reached.  The number of mounds in 37 plots measuring 25 m2 each in heathland  with a sparse and low vegetation near Maarheeze (southern part of The  Netherlands) was found to be as high as 40 but commonly around 7 per 25  mr in 1975. Extrapolation yields a number of 2800 mounds ha-1.  The amount of sand transported to the surface was 120 -+ 22 g per dung  beetle nest (n = 14) in a 36.75-m~ plot near Wijster (northern part of The  Netherlands) in 1979 and 163 -+ 83 (n = 8) in another 49-m2 plot near  Wijster in 1980. Extrapolation yields amounts of sand deposited on the  surface of 457 and 266 kg ha-l, respectively.  After the burrow is made, dung is transported from the surface into the  soil to provision the brood chamber with food for the larvae. The parent  beetles seal in each dung sausage by back-filling the burrow leading to the    depth(cm)  $4 -[    10    16    22    28    34    40    46    store room    /  "i l :t,   ,'t;          lo mm  I  I  i  I  I  !t:  I   I  t~  I  I I    58                                             ~  64- '{f~              ~ ~-,&lt;~  o  7 0 i~ a~sia~ugs sandln   o  76  |'I'      g       age  "   brood  chamber  82 --I~~ o--egg chamber    Itl'  1  I  It~- path followed  i ~   by emerging beetle  1  1  L    231    88-    94-    ~edge of frame    100  Fig. 1. Nest of Typhaeus typhoeus.    232    Fig. 2. Back-filled part of a burrow leading to a dung sausage (not visible) of Typhaeus  typhoeus in a sandy subsoil. In this case the back-filling sand was scraped away from dif-  ferently coloured horizons higher in the profile, thus accentuating the meniscate infilling.    233    dung with sand for a distance of several centimetres. A meniscate layering  results from the firm packing movements of the beetles (meniscate = resem-  bling a crescent-shaped body). The meniscate layering is accentuated when  the sealing sand is alternately scraped away from differently coloured hori-  zons nearer the soil surface (Fig. 2). Back-filling traces also come about  when the newly hatched adults make their way to the surface through the  soil. This has been observed in rearing cages with glass walls in the laboratory  (Brussaard, 1983).  After sealing the uppermost dung sausage the beetles leave the remaining  part of the shaft open for a distance averaging 40 cm. The number of open  burrows at a depth of 15 cm may be as high as 50 m-2 {Fig. 3) and is thus  considerably higher than the number of sand mounds at the surface.  In contrast to the sand mounds, the back-filled burrows and, presumably  to a lesser degree, the open burrows, persist in the soil as traces.    Fig. 3. Open Typhaeus typhoeus shafts at a depth of 15 cm below the surface.    ORIGIN OF BACK-FILLING TRACES IN SANDY SOILS    The stratification in sandy soils is often disturbed below 70 cm by finger-  wide streaks, usually vertical, but sometimes oblique or horizontal. Evidence  that these are back-filling traces from scarab beetles will be presented,  following some details about the soils in which we have found the traces.  The features are most conspicuous in two types of sandy soil. Firstly, the    234    profile shown in Fig. 4. This is a Humic Podzol (FAO, 1974), overlain by a  thin layer of drift sand.  The parent material is aeolian Cover Sand. From the lower part of the  profile to approximately 125 cm below the surface this is Younger Cover  Sand I, deposited during the Earlier Dryas, a Late Weichselian stadial lasting    Holocene  drift sand    Younger  Cover Sand II    laye  Younger  Cover Sand I    Fig. 4. Humic Podzol near Ijsselstein, The Netherlands (coordinates topographical map  386,500/190,900). The vertical or oblique whitish streaks are back-filled scarab beetle  burrows. For further explanation see text.    235    from 12,000 to 11,800 BP (Zagwijn, 1975). Between 125 and 25 cm below  the surface is the Younger Cover Sand II, deposited during the Younger  Dryas, a Late Weichselian stadial lasting from 11,000 to 10,000 BP (Zagwijn,  1975). Up to 25 cm below the surface the sand is humic Holocene drift  sand. The Podzol that developed in the Younger Cover Sand II is of  Holocene age.  Approximately 125--130 cm below the surface is a pallid layer, the so-  called Usselo layer, which developed during the AllerSd period (11,800 to  11,000 BP), an interstadial phase of no sedimentation (Van der Hammen,  1951 ; Hijszeler, 1957).  The Cover Sands were deposited with a horizontal or, in some places, a  criss-cross  stratification (Van der  Hammen,  1951;  and pers. comm.,  1984). The stratification below 70--110 cm is locally disturbed by the  finger-wide streaks, which we studied (whitish in Fig. 4). Three lines of  evidence indicate that these are back-filling burrows from scarab beetles.  Firstly, their diameters (14.0 mm -+ 1.5, n = 50) are virtually the same as  those of recent traces made by Typhaeus typhoeus {14.2 +- 0.7, n = 12)  (Brussaard, 1983). Secondly, their infillings are clearly meniscate (Fig. 5).    Fig. 5. Horizontal cross-section at 1.20 m below the surface through a profile similar to  that in Fig. 4. Near Venray, The Netherlands, coordinates topographical map 396,275/  194,500. Note meniscate layering within the burrow and uniform diameter of burrows.  (The contrast with the soil matrix has been accentuated by fixation in the soil peel.)    237    Thirdly, they only rarely branch. The Usselo layer is characterized by various  amounts of small pieces of charcoal. Charcoal is also present in the traces  above and below the Usselo layer, indicating that they are filled with trans-  located Usselo sand. The Usselo layer with the traces has been observed from  Denmark south to Belgium and eastwards to Poland (Chmielewska and  Chmielewski, 1960, cited in Van der Sluijs and Maarleveld, 1963) wherever  the overlying Younger Cover Sand II is thick enough to have prevented the  Usselo layer from being obliterated during Holocene pedogenesis. Where the  Usselo layer is present the traces are seldom absent. The traces can be  inferred by analogy from photos in several publications showing the Usselo  layer: Van der Hammen (1951), Hijszeler (1957), Maarleveld and Van der  Schans (1961).  The second profile showing the features considered to be back-filling traces  is developed in sands of the rivers Rhine and Meuse (Fig. 6). It has been  classified as a Leptic Podzol (FAO, 1974). It consists of cross-bedded,  stratified, fluviatile sand with gravel lenses, overlain from 1.05 m upwards by  terrace sand, reworked by wind during the Late Weichselian. In this type  of soil lamellae are much in evidence. Lamellae are "subsoil layers which  contain more clay than the layers above or below them" (Dijkerman et al.,  1967). The lamellae are disturbed by predominantly vertical finger-wide  streaks. Here again, their diameters (14.2 mm +_ 1.3, n = 12) are virtually  the same as those of Typhaeus back-filling traces, their infillings are clearly  meniscate and they only rarely branch.  We have also observed such traces in The Netherlands near Lochem  (coordinates topographical map 462,100/220,000) where lamellae have  developed in the aeolian Cover Sands. One of us (LB) also observed the  traces in sandy soils with lamellae in the Nyirseg region in eastern Hungary in  1981. Similar traces can be inferred by analogy from photos published by  Tiixen {1964) of profiles with lamellae in West Germany.  Lamellae are well known from various parts of the U.S.A. (Dijkerman et  al., 1967) but to date we have not seen any reports of back-filling traces left  by scarab beetles in sandy soils of the U.S.A. Such traces can be inferred by  analogy, however, from figs. 6 and 7 in Dijkerman (1965), which are photos  of profiles developed in very fine sandy loam and loamy fine sand in Orleans  County, New York. We also suspect that Plate 4A, an Alfic Udipsamment,  in Soil Survey Staff (1975) shows the traces.    AGES OF BACK-FILLING TRACES IN SANDY SOILS    In this section we shall try to date the traces and calibrate the disturbance  of the sandy soils by the beetles.    Fig. 6. Leptic Podzol in river terrace sand near Geysteren, The Netherlands, coordinates  topographical map 395,000/201,600. Note lamellae, disturbed by back-filled scarab  beetle burrows. For explanation see text.    238    Circumstantial evidence indicates that most of the traces described in the  preceding section are ancient. Firstly, in the profile of Fig. 4, with traces  below the Podzol, the Podzol itself is largely intact, whereas it could be  expected to be disturbed by back-filling traces if the scarab beetle activity  were recent. Secondly, the vegetation on soils with traces is often too dense  for scarab beetle activity nowadays.  More conclusive results on the ages of the back-filling traces follow from  two more lines of evidence, which will be discussed below.    Evidence from fossil beetle remains    A suitable environment for larger herbivores, on which dung beetles of the  size of Typhaeus or Geotrupes are dependent, has been present in northwest  Europe since at least c. 5000 BP, i.e. from the Atlantic onwards. From that  time increasing areas were becoming less densely forested, park-like or even  open (e.g. Van der Hammen and Bakker, 1971). Finds of beetle remains in  14C-dated soil samples from several places in Britain support the hypothesis  that dung beetles were present during most of this period (Fig. 7). No  remains of beetles the size of geotrupids were found from the preceding ages  with a forested landscape, the Boreal and the Atlantic (8800.--5000 BP)  (Osborne, 1972). One of the reasons may be that in general the ground cover  was too dense. This is unfavourable for most of the dung beetles (Landin,  1955; Brussaard, 1983 ; Kalisz &amp; Stone, 1984). The dwindling of populations  of larger herbivores during the afforestation of the landscape (Kurt~n, 1968)  may also have played a role.  In contrast with the Boreal and the Atlantic, remains of scarab beetles the  size of geotrupids have been found from the first Holocene period, the  Preboreal (Fig. 7), which was initially treeless. One of us (LTR) has observed  back-filling traces in a Bronze Age barrow and in postholes in archaeological  excavations, suggesting that they were formed in the Subboreal or Sub-  atlantic.  One observation supporting the contention that a number of the traces  originated in historical time can be added to Fig. 7. De Bakker (1979)  described an anthropogenic soil with an A1 horizon thickened by age-long  use of manure-impregnated sods. Back-filling traces disturb the boundary  between the (A1 + A2) pb horizon and the underlying horizon. The agri-  cultural practice of gradually raising the A1 horizon only began some 800--  1000 years ago and therefore this type of trace cannot be any older.  In conclusion we infer from the available data that the back-filling traces    Fig. 7. Climatic variation during the Holocene and finds of remains of large scarab beetles.  Each dot indicates a ~4C-dated sample. Arrows refer to samples not indicated by dots,  which could only be dated approximately. Number of specimens of beetles indicated in  brackets, if exceeding 1. Temperature curve from Osborne ( 1976).    J   0  C  1,000  2.000    3~oo    ~,000    ~000    ~000    Preliminary temperature   Scarab beetle remains  fluctuation  curve  Glacier  I&lt;--cd warm--&gt;/     maxima    Source    239      ....  ~(;otr, z,~pe:~  o~,rnal~:~,~  Coope &amp;  Osborne,1967    ---         (;~oLr~q)ee  :~pfn/gc'r'               ---~-- ~:~7o~n:~p(,~                                        Osborne,  1979         ~     ( (;cotr~p~,~: vernon[?  Osborne,  1969  ~-_      ~+ G.~,~.   (&gt;1361)  ]  "'"-.` : ~i,;o[(.,.,;'..:~'.T,~o~(r, th.    2000    8.ooo    ~ooo    10.000    I                ~Melo~ontha              Osborne,  1974  -   -'l  af.  hippoaa,~tani (2-3)  -~'' "~  ~Otrz~p~s ,~p.   (2-5)    ...............  MeLolontha  hippo&lt;'~asta~i  Osborne,  1980  ~-  ............  Geotn~pen sp.                Coope &amp; Brophy,  1972    20 4OI  m 601  %  =  801  looq  12o~    Average  8    A  July temperature/  British  12       16       20 terminology           Flandrian  ~-~       ] Windermere         Interstadial  Upton  Warren  [nterstadial  Complex  I  \   Chelford  ~              Interstadial  /  !  I  I  I  I  I  I  I  \  \  \  \  ~] Ipswichian  Interglacial    E  European                Fossil  scarab  terminology              beetle remains         Source  Holocene  = Bblling+Allerbd     Geotrupes sp.          Osborne,  1972    Denekamp  Coope, Shotton  Hengelo            /-Geotr~pes sp.              &amp; Strachan,1961  /~  ~-Geotr~p~s s~.          Morgan   1973  Moershoofd~  .~ Oeotr~pe~  sp.          Coope &amp; Angus,1975  L  + Geotrup~s  spinigen  Br~rup  .........  Geotn~pes spin,gem   Coope.  1959  oP  G.  stemcorari~s    Amersfoort    Eemien ---      ........  ~feloZontha              Coope,  1974  me ~o iont ha    0    241    may well have come about during the Preboreal and from the closing of the  Atlantic onwards.  All the back-filling traces we observed were in Weichselian deposits and  we now turn to the question of if and when traces were formed during the  period preceding the Holocene.  Remains of geotrupid dung beetles have only been found in samples from  the relatively warm interstadials (Fig. 8), although the stadials were sampled  to the same extent (G.R. Coope, pers. comm., 1981). This fits in well with  the rapid decrease towards the present subarctic zone in the number of dung  beetle taxa and in the number of places from which they have been recorded  (Lindroth, 1960).  Part of the traces described from Fig. 4 protrude upwards from the  Usselo layer and, consequently, date from a period later than the AllerSd,  i.e. after c. 11,000 BP.  As indicated above, scarab beetles the size of geotrupids probably could not  stand the climate during the Younger Dryas stadial, c. 11,000--10,000 BP,  which was temperate subarctic and probably had a permafrost (Van der  Hammen et al., 1967; Zagwijn, 1975). As corroboration, a soil sample taken  in The Netherlands at the type locality of the Usselo layer yielded no sign of  geotrupid-like or similarly sized scarabs from the Younger Dryas period  (G.R. Coope, pers. comm., 1981). Hence, the traces disturbing the Usselo  layer do not pre-date the Holocene Preboreal.  We conclude from the availble evidence that the traces of back-filling by  scarabs  were  not  formed  during the Pleistocene stadials. The traces  penetrating the Usselo layer were probably formed during the early  Preboreal transitional period to a warmer climate.    Evidence from clay illuviation phenomena    In this section we offer further support for the conclusions reached in the  former section by dating the clay illuviation in and around the back-filling  traces that are associated with lamellae (Fig. 6).  To discriminate between the relative ages of the back-filling traces  associated with the lamellae, we shall distinguish three cases, which, for the  sake of convenience, are classified in terms of interpretation:  (1) Traces formed during clay illuviation. Under micromorphological  examination these traces show plasma with reworked clay (encircled in Fig.  9} plus in-situ (this means without disturbance after deposition) clay (bridge  cutans, arrowed in Fig. 9) whereas in the undisturbed lamella only in-situ  clay is found (Fig. 10). Reworking is attributed to scarab beetle activity.    Fig. 8. Variations in the average July temperatures in lowland areas of the southern and  central British Isles since the Eemian interglacial, in relation to finds of large scarab beetle  remains. Some 25 samples were studied from deposits covering the whole Weichsel.  Temperature curve from Coope ( 1977 ).    242    Fig. 9. Detail from within a back-filled scarab beetle burrow disturbing a lamella, with  skeleton grains, plasma with reworked clay (e.g. encircled part of photo) and illuviated  clay in situ (bridge cutans, arrowed). Samples for micromorphological inspection were  taken in the vicinity of the profile shown in Fig. 6. Coordinates topographical map  201,425/395,125. Thin section, half-polarized light.    (2) Traces formed before the onset of clay illuviation. In the absence of  other diagnostic characteristics these are the traces that show no reworked  clay when examined micromorphologically. When examined macroscopical-  ly, the traces contain an in-situ layer of illuviated clay, distinguishable from  the adjacent lamella by being thinner (arrowed in Fig. 6), or by partly or  wholly following the meniscate infilling within the trace {Fig. 11, middle and  right, respectively}.  (3) Traces formed after termination of clay illuviation. Under micro-  morphological examination the clay in these traces shows up as reworked  clay only.  In the discussion we shall return to the assumption of a pedogenetic origin  of the lamellae.  Our macroscopic and micromorphological inspection of traces associated  with lamellae showed that case 1 (beetle activity during clay illuviation) was  the most common, followed by case 3 (beetle activity after clay illuviation).  Case 2 (beetle activity preceding clay illuviation) was by far the least com-  mon.  Since the Eemian interglacial, two climate regimes conducive to clay  migration in sandy soils have prevailed at the latitude of northwest Europe    243    Fig. 10. Detail from within an undisturbed lamella with illuviated clay in situ, no1  reworked. Compare with Fig. 9. Thin section, half polarized light.    (literature overview in Schrbder, 1979). The first, temperate climatic condi-  tions with a forested vegetation during the Boreal and Atlantic, will not have  favoured scarab beetle activity, as witnessed by the lack of fossilized beetle  remains from those periods (Fig. 7). Hence, coincidence of scarab beetle  activity and clay illuviation during those periods seems unlikely. Secondly,  clay migration may have occurred in soils under the frigid or cryic  temperature regime with periods of sudden snow melt that prevailed during  the Allerdd, Bolling and possibly in earlier Weichselian interstadials and  during the early Preboreal, whenever the frost or permafrost disappeared  from the soil. A reasonable number of fossilized scarab beetle remains has  been reported from these periods (see pp. 238 and 241; Figs. 7 and 8).  To conclude, the available evidence points to concomitant clay illuvia-  tion  and  scarab  beetle  activity  during the interstadials of the Late  Weichselian and during the early Preboreal. On p. 239 we concluded from  the evidence of disturbance of the Usselo layer that scarab beetle activity  may well have occurred during the early Preboreal. Further evidence that  scarab beetle activity was important in the Preboreal is presented by the pro-  file near Lochem, mentioned earlier on p. 237. It shows Younger Cover  Sands I and II, separated by the Usselo layer at a depth of 1.50 m and, more-  over, this soil contains lamellae. The uppermost lamella, which had traces in    Fig. 11. Lamella in sandy soil near Horst, The Netherlands; coordinates topographical  map 200,100/388,250. Within the extreme right burrow the illuviated clay follows the  meniscate layering just below the lamella (see arrow); within the burrow in the centre of  the photo part of the clay follows the layering within the burrow (see arrow) and part of  it links up with the lamella (see dashed arrow). Scale in cm. For further explanation see  text.    this profile, was observed in and slightly above or below the Usselo layer. This  clearly points to a post-AllerSd, and hence presumably Preboreal period, of  clay illuviation and concurrent scarab beetle activity.    Conclusions    The back-filling traces preserved in sandy soils probably originate from  scarab beetle activity. Most of the evidence strongly suggests that scarab  beetles were absent during the Late Weichselian stadials and that scarab  beetle activity and clay illuviation occurred concurrently during the early  Preboreal period of ameliorating climate and possibly also during the Late  Weichselian interstadials. Scarab beetles seem to have been absent or at least  less common during the Boreal and Atlantic, because of unsuitable habitat,  but reappear from the Subboreal onwards. These periods of scarab beetle  activity determine the ages of their back-filling traces.    245    DISCUSSION    In our attempt to describe and explain traces from scarab beetles in sandy  soils we have touched upon such divergent disciplines as zoology and  pedology. The effort seemed worthwhile, because there is a great need for  scientists from these disciplines to co-operate to achieve a better understand-  ing of soil-forming processes. Some of the issues likely to arise from those  fields are anticipated below.  (1) There are some organisms that are of similar size to the scarabs  mentioned and which also burrow into the soil, e.g. wolf spiders (Lycosidae),  mole-crickets (Gryllotalpidae) and the larger tiger beetles (Cincindelidae).  Back-filling of burrows has not been described in these groups, however, as  far  as  we  are  aware.  It  has  been  described  in  cockchafer  larvae  (Scarabaeidae-Melolontinae) (Schwerdtfeger, 1939), but if the traces did  originate from those organisms, their diameters would range between 5 and  15 mm, because the larvae of different stages differ considerably in girth.  No such range occurred in the traces we described. Back-filling of burrows  has also been described in cicada nymphs (Cicadidae) by Hugie and Passey  (1963) in soils formed in loess in the U.S.A. Here again, considerable ranges  in  the  diameters of the back-filled burrows (7.5--20 mm) occurred,  depending on the stages of the nymphs. No such range was present in the  traces we described and, moreover, a European equivalent of such cicadas  is not known to us.  (2) We expect back-filling traces of species other than those mentioned  in the present paper to be found in the future and in different types of soil.  Judging from their way of life, scarabaeid dung beetles from the Phanaeini  tribe, widely distributed in the southern and central parts of the U.S.A.  (Fincher, 1973), are likely to back-fill parts of their burrows in sandy soil,  as the numerous geotrupids in that part of the world probably do, although  Kalisz and Stone (1984) make no mention of back-filling traces from  Peltotrupes. Likewise, the many species of scarabs whose pupal chambers  Valiachmedov (1977) found up to 1.20 m below the surface in light  Sierozem soils will form back-filling traces.  (3) In densely packed sandy soils plant roots often cannot penetrate the  soil below 25 cm. The disturbance of the soil stratification by scarab beetles  might enable plant roots to penetrate considerably deeper.  (4) Extrapolation of the data mentioned on the amounts of soil deposited  annually on the surface by T. typhoeus to amounts per hectare suggests that  up to 500 kg ha-1 is not exceptional in favourable habitats. The figure for  Peltotrupes youngi is 3-7 times higher in favourable habitats in Florida  (Kalisz and Stone, 1984). Because the latter species burrows up to 5 times as  deep as T. typhoeus the mixing of the upper 1 m of the soil seems fairly  comparable in both species. Additional data are required to check this  possibility.  (5) If, as we argue, many of the observed back-filling traces were made by    246    scarabs during the early Preboreal, they must have been started from the  present-day surface in soils that have not been covered by Holocene drift  sands. There is a marked difference, however, between the depths to which  scarabs in The Netherlands usually burrow nowadays (up to c. 80 cm below  the surface} and the depths at which we observed most of the ancient traces:  70--135 cm below the surface and some even deeper. We suggest that the  reason for this difference could be that we only observe the ancient traces  from the rare specimens that burrowed to extreme depths. Their traces have  been preserved, whereas the traces from beetles that burrowed to more usual  depths have been reworked by successive scarabs or through biological  homogenization by other animals or roots.  (6} Our observations that in-situ clay follows the meniscate layering  within back-filled burrows or links up with the adjacent lamella as a layer  thinner than the lamella itself support the pedogenetic origin of the lamellae.  Recent micromorphological evidence of clay migration in northwest  European river terraces during the Late Weichselian is given by Miedema et  al. {1983). Schr~Sder {1979) has also shown that clay illuviation is present in  Late Weichselian and Preboreal soils in northwest Europe, but is virtually  absent in the younger soils. As a corroboration, Van Vliet and Langohr  (1983} conclude that clay illuviation occurred before the Holocene in the  soils they studied. The authors cited above also note that under forest,  currently active drainage pores lack recent illuvial bodies of well-oriented  fine clay.  As regards the periods of concurrent operation of clay illuviation and  scarab beetle activity, the evidence from these studies supports the Late  Weichselian interstadials and early Preboreal rather than the Atlantic.  A pedogenetic rather than a geogenetic origin of the lamellae can be  inferred from the morphology, both macroscopic and microscopic, of the  lamellae: in Fig. 6 the course of the lamellae is largely horizontal wherever  the bedding of the sand is criss-cross. In thin sections of the lamellae many  ferri-argillans (some bridge-forming) are visible, pointing to clay illuviation  as the process of formation.  (7) Van Geel and Kolstrup (1978) propose that there has been a steady  increase in the emission of solar energy since the Upper Pleniglacial or that at  any rate the emission of solar energy has not been limiting for the ameliora-  tion of the climate. The Late Weichselian and early Holocene oscillations in  climate would then have arisen from retarded changes and varying intensities  in west--east air circulation. Van Geel et al. (1981} give a different inter-  pretation for one of these phases, as an alternative to a climatic oscillation,  viz. the Rammelbeek phase of Van der Hammen (1971} (9,850--9,700 BP).  This phase is an interlude between the first Preboreal phase (Friesland phase  of Behre (1966} {10,150--9,850 BP)} and the Preboreal proper. The  Rammelbeek phase is characterized by a sharp decline in the ratio of  arboreal:non-arboreal pollen. This may point to a dry period, but the  alternative proposed is that large numbers of mammals were driven to the  north in front of the advancing tree line.    247    In spite of any such advance the herbivores would have retarded the pace  of afforestation by grazing. As long as most of the trees were kept away,  herbs and grasses were favoured by the ameliorating climate. Herbivores  therefore became abundant. Finally, the herbivores lost more and more  terrain to the trees and were driven further northwards and most of the  species were even driven to extinction (Kurt~n, 1968). The abundance of  dung is supported by the high percentage of nettle (Urtica) in the pollen  record from the Rammelbeek phase (Van Geel et al., 1981). Nettle is  known to have high nutrient requirements. The interpretation of Van Geel  et al. (1981) is attractive in the context of our study because it would  account for an associated great abundance of dung beetles in the early  Preboreal.  It is tempting to extend the speculations made by Van Geel et al. (1981)  to the point where the abundant dung beetles, by reworking the soil, helped  prepare the way for tree roots to penetrate the deeper layers, so that the  pace of reafforestation was considerably accelerated. This would mean that  the Late Glacial herbivores ultimately helped dig their own graves by means  of the dung beetles! But even if we forgo the speculation, there is still much  evidence available for our conclusion that the ancient back-filling traces  were formed by scarabs during the relatively warm periods preluding the  Holocene and again after the Atlantic.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Many thanks are due to Prof. Dr. L.J. Pons, Dr. S. Slager and Ir. K.J.  Hoeksema for suggesting the subject of the present study and for numerous  and highly stimulating discussions, including those on the manuscript. We are  also very grateful to Ir. R. Miedema, Dr. P.J. den Boer and Dr. J.C. Dijker-  man for critically reading the manuscript and for helpful discussions. Dr. H.  de Bakker (Wageningen) and Dr. K. Schwan (Amsterdam) kindly provided us  with a number of localities showing the Usselo-layer.  Drs. A.D. Verlinde (Amersfoort) kindly allowed us to open up the type  locality of the Usselo layer, which is normally inacces~cible. Special mention  should be made of the visit one of us (LB) made to Dr. G.R. Coope and Mr.  P.J. Osborne (Birmingham). They provided us with all the data on fossil  beetle   remains.  Their  willingness  and  hospitality  are  gratefully  acknowledged.  This study would have been impossible without the technical skill of G.J.  van de Waal, who prepared the thin sections and soils peels. Ing. Th. Pape  kindly helped us with the photography, G. Buurman and P.G.M. Versteeg  prepared the figures, Mrs. G. van Dinter-Deuring typed the manuscript and  Mrs. J. Burrough-Boenisch corrected the English.    248    REFERENCES    Ahlbrandt, T.S., Andrews, S. and Gwynne, D.T., 1978. Bioturbation in aeolian deposits.  J. Sediment. Petrol., 48: 839--848.  Bal, L., 1982. Zoological Ripening of Soils. Pudoc, Wageningen, 365 pp.  Behre, K.E., 1966. Untersuchungen zur sp~:tglazialen und frilhpostglazialen Vegetations-  geschichte Ostfrieslands. Eiszeitalter Gegenwart, 17: 69--84.  Brussaard, L., 1983. Reproductive behaviour and development of the dung beetle  Typhaeus typhoeus. Tijdschr. Entomol., 126: 203--231.  Chmielewska, M. and Chmielewski, W., 1960. Stratigraphie et chronologie de la dune de  Wit6w, distr, de Leczyca. Biul. Peryglacjalny, 8: 133--141.  Coope, G.R., 1959. A Late Pleistocene insect fauna from Chelford, Cheshire. Proc. R. Soc.  B, 151: 70--86.  Coope, G.R., 1974. Interglacial Coleoptera from Bobbitshole, Ipswich, Suffolk. J. Geol.  Soc. Lond., 130: 333--340.  Coope, G.R., 1977. Fossil coleopteran assemblages as sensitive indicators of climatic  changes during the Devensian (Last) cold stage. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B, 280:  313--340.  Coope, G.R. and Angus, R.B., 1975. An ecological study of a temperate interlude in the  middle of the last glaciation, based on fossil Coleoptera from Isleworth, Middlesex. J.  Anita. Ecol., 44: 365--391.  Coope, G.R. and Brophy, J.A., 1972. Late Glacial environmental changes indicated by a  coleopteran succession from North Wales. Boreas, 1: 97--142.  Coope, G.R. and Osborne, P.J., 1967. Report on the coleopterous fauna of the Roman  Well at Barnsley Park, Gloucestershire. Trans. Bristol and Cloucs. Arch. Soc., 1967:  84--87.  Coope, G.R., Shotton, F.W. and Strachan, I., 1961. A Late Pleistocene fauna and flora  from Upton Warren, Worcestershire. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B, 244: 379--417.  De Bakker,  H.,  1979.  Major Soils and Soil Regions in The Netherlands. Pudoc,  Wageningen, 203 pp.  Dijkerman, J.C., 1965. Properties and Genesis of Textural Subsoil Lamellae. PhD. Thesis.  Cornell Univ., New York, 139 pp.  Di]kerman, J.C., Cline, M.G. and Olson, G.W., 1967. Properties and genesis of textural  subsoil lamellae. Soil Sci., 104: 7--16.  FAO, 1974. FAO--Unesco soil map of the world, 1:5.000.000. Unesco, Paris.  Fincher, G.T., 1973. Nidification and reproduction of Phanaeus spp. in three textural  classes of soil (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae). Coleopt. Bull., 27 : 33--37.  Frey, R.W., 1973. Concepts in the study of biogenic sedimentary structures. J. Sediment.  Petrol., 43 : 6--19.  Hijszeler, C.C.W.J., 1957. Late Glacial human cultures in The Netherlands. Geol. Mijn-  bouw, 19: 288--302.  Hoeksema, K.J. and Edelman, C.H., 1960. The role of biological homogenization in the  formation of Gray-Brown Podzolic soils. Trans. 7th Int. Congr. Soil Sci. (Madison,  Wisc., U.S.A.), 4: 402--405.  Hoogerkamp, M., Rogaar, H. and Eijsackers, H.J.P., 1983. Effect of earthworms on grass-  land on recently reclaimed polder soils in The Netherlands. In: J.E. Satchell (Editor),  Earthworm Ecology. Chapman and Hall, London, pp. 85--105.  Hole, F.D., 1981. Effects of animals on soil. Geoderma, 25: 75--112.  Hugie, V.K. and Passey, H.B., 1963. Cicadas and their effect upon soil genesis in certain  soils in southern Idaho, northern Utah and northeastern Nevada. Soil. Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 27: 38--82.  Kalisz, P.J. and Stone, E.L., 1984. Soil mixing by scarab beetles and pocket gophers in  North-Central Florida. Soil. Sci. Soc. Am. J., 48: 169--172.    249    Kurt6n, B., 1968. Pleistocene mammals of Europe. Weidenfeld and Nicholson, London,  317 pp.  Lindroth,  C.H. {Editor), 1960. Catalogus Coleopterorum Fennoscandiae et Daniae.  Entomologiska Shllskapet, Lund, 476 pp.  Maarleveld, G.C. and Van der Schans, R.P.H.P., 1961. The morphology of the Cover  Sand of the Guelders Valley. Tijdschr.  Kon. Ned. Aardrijksk. Genootschap, 78:  22--34 (in Dutch with Eng. summ.).  Miedema, R., Slager, S., Jongmans, A.G. and Pape, Th., 1983. Amount, characteristics  and significance of clay illuviation features in Late Weichselian Meuse terraces. In: P.  Bullock and C.P. Murphy {Editors), Soil Micromorphology, 2. Soil Genesis. AB  Academic Publishers, Berkhamsted, pp. 519--529.  Morgan, A., 1973. Late Pleistocene environmental changes indicated by fossil insect  faunas of the English Midlands. Boreas, 2: 173--212.  Osborne, P.J., 1969. An insect fauna of Late Bronze Age date from Wilsford, Wiltshire. J.  Anim. Ecol., 38: 555--566.  Osborne, P.J., 1972. Insect faunas of Late Devensian and Flandrian age from Church  Stretton, Shropshire. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B, 263: 327--367.  Osborne, P.J., 1974. An insect assemblage of early Flandrian age from Lea Marston,  Warwickshire, and its bearing on the contemporary climate and ecology. Quat. Res.,  4: 471--486.  Osborne, P.J., 1976. Evidence from the insects of climatic variation during the Flandrian  period: a preliminary note. World Archaeol., 8: 150--158.  Osborne, P.J., 1979. Insect remains. In: C. Smith (Editor), Fisherwick: The reconstruc-  tion of an Iron Age Landscape. Brit. Archaeol. Rep., Brit. Ser., 61: 85--110.  Osborne, P.J., 1980. The Late Devensian--Flandrian transition depicted by serial insect  faunas from West Bromwich, Staffordshire, England. Boreas, 9 : 139--147.  Ratcliffe, B.C. and Fagerstrom, J.A., 1980. Invertebrate lebensspuren of Holocene flood-  plains: their morphology, origin and paleoecological significance. J. Paleontol., 54:  614--630.  SchrSder, D., 1979. Bodenentwicklung in sp~tpleistoz~nen und holoz~nen Hochflut-  lehmen des Niederrheines. PhD. Thesis, Bonn, 296 pp.  Schwerdtfeger, F., 1939. Untersuchungen ~ber die Wanderungen des Maik~fer-Engerlings  (Melolonlha melolontha L. und Melolontha hippocastani F.). Z. Angew. Entomol.,  26: 215--252.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic Classification for Making and Inter-  preting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric., Agriculture Handbook 436,754 pp.  Tlixen, R., 1964. Die Schrift des Bodens. In: M. Schwind (Editor), Schrift des Bodens  -- Sprache neuer Malerei. Schriften der Humboldtschule Hannover, 1 : 11--29.  Valiachmedov, B., 1977. Spuren der Lebenst~tigkeit yon Bodenwirbellosen als diagnos-  tische Merkmale f'dr Subtypen von Grauen WilstenbSden in Tadshikistan. Pedo-  biologia, 17 : 60--69.  Van der Hammen, T., 1951. Late Glacial flora and periglacial phenomena in The Nether-  lands. PhD. Thesis, Leiden, 183 pp.  Van der Hammen, T. 1971. The Upper Quaternary stratigraphy of the Dinkel Valley.  In: T. van der Hammen and T.A. Wijmstra {Editors), The Upper Quaternary of the  Dinkel Valley. Meded. Rijks Geol. Dienst, 22 : 59--72.  Van der Hammen, T.-and Bakker, J.A., 1971. Former vegetation, landscape and man in  the Dinkel Valley. In: T. van der Hammen and T.A. Wijmstra (Editors), The Upper  Quaternary of the Dinkel Valley. Meded. Rijks Geol. Dienst, 22: 147--158.  Van der Hammen, T., Maarleveld, G.C., Vogel, J.C. and Zagwijn, W.H., 1967. Strati-  graphy, climatic succession and radiocarbon dating of the Last Glacial in The Nether-  lands. Geol. Mijnbouw, 46 : 79--95.  Van der Sluijs, P. and Maarleveld, G.C., 1963. Cover-sand ridges from the Late Dryas time  in Zealand Flanders. Boor Spade, 13:21--26 (in Dutch with Eng. summ.).    250    Van Geel, B. and Kolstrup, E., 1978. Tentative explanation of the Late Glacial and early  Holocene climatic changes in north-western Europe. Geol. Mijnbouw, 57: 87--89.  Van Geel, B., Bohnke, S.J.P. and Dee, H., 1981. A paleo-ecological study of an Upper  Late Glacial and Holocene sequence from De Borchert, The Netherlands. Rev. Palaeo-  bot. Palynol., 31: 367--448.  Van Vliet, B. and Langohr, R., 1983. Evidence of disturbance by frost of pore ferri-  argillans in silty soils of Belgium and northern France. In: P. Bullock and C.P. Murphy  (Editors), Soil Micromorphology, 2. Soil Genesis, AB Academic Publishers, Berkham-  sted, pp. 511----518.  Zagwijn, W.H., 1975. Indeling van het Kwartair op grond van veranderingen in vegetatie  en klimaat. In: W.H. Zagwijn and C.J. van Staalduijnen (Editors), Toelichting bij de  Geologische Overzichtskaart van Nedertand. Rijks Geologische Dienst, Haarlem, pp.  109--114 (in Dutch).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractTraces of burrowing activity by the scarab beetle Typhaeus typhoeus in sandy soils of The Netherlands are described. These traces include mounds of sand deposited on the surface and open and back-filled burrows in the soil. Other back-filling wraces are described from two types of sandy ooil in The Netherlands. By analogy with the traces from T. typhoeus these are interpreted as resulting from scarab beetle activity.Preliminary measurements have been made of the amounts of soil deposited on the surface by T. typhoeus. In favourable habitats the quantities are as high as 450 kg ha−1 annually.The disturbance of sandy ooil profiles by scarab beetles is calibrated by their back-filling traces with the help of literature data on fossil beetle remains and original data on clay illuviation. The disturbance is shown to e mainly of Preboreal and post-Atlantic age.Clay configurations in back-filling traces associated with lamellae support the contention that the lamellae were formed by clay illuviation.