Geoderma, 34 (1984) 251--259                                                     251  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CONTRIBUTION  OF  INORGANIC  POLYPHOSPHATES  TO  MIGRATION  OF ELEMENTS IN A GREY FOREST  SOIL, U.S.S.R.    A. YU. KUDEYAROVA and M.Z. KVARATSKHELIYA  Institute of Soil Science and Photosynthesis, Academy of Sciences of the USSR, 142292  Pushchino, Moscow Region (U.S.S.R.)  (Received August 22, 1983; revised version accepted September 5, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Kudeyarova, A. Yu. and Kvaratskheliya, M.Z., 1984. Contribution of inorganic polyphos-  phates to migration of elements in a grey forest soil, U.S.S.R. Geoderma, 34: 251--259.    The role of polyphosphates added to soil or synthesized in place in mobilization and  migration of some elements in a grey forest soil was examined by three approaches. All  included applications of polyphosphoric and/or orthophosphoric fertilizers. First, samples  of soil placed in cylinders in the field were extracted to determine the quantities of Ca,  Mg, Mn, Zn, Fe and P in simple and complexed forms. Second, parallel samples were  placed in small lysimeters designed to allow leaching of complexed but not simple forms  of the elements. Leachates were analyzed at intervals for 85 days to measure losses of P,  Fe and C. Third, samples of fallow soil were monitored for 6 weeks to estimate natural  synthesis of polyphosphates following application of orthophosphate fertilizer. Numbers  of bacteria and fungi were determined in a laboratory study in samples of soil incubated  with Ammophos granules for indications of the role of micro-organisms in synthesis of  polyphosphates,  Evidence obtained through the three approaches indicates that addition of ammonium  polyphosp.~ate intensifies the mobilization and movement of P, Fe and C in a grey forest  soil. Furthermore, application of ammonium orthophosphate promotes synthesis of poly-  phosphates in the field with consequent opportunities for increases in migration. Num-  bers of bacteria and fungi in soil fertilized with orthophosphate suggest that micro-  organisms play a role in the natural synthesis of polyphosphates.    INTRODUCTION    Inorganic condensed phosphates have been identified in a number of softs  {Anderson and Russell, 1969; Pepper et al., 1976; Kudeyarova, 1981a) but  little attention has been given to their roles in soil processes. That may  follow because the quantities present are very small. At the same time, poly-  phosphates are integral components of the phosphorus cycle in soils and  hence can be expected to occur widely. Microbial metabolisms may generate  polyphosphates (Kulaev, 1975). Furthermore, these compounds may be the  result of a great variety of chemical reactions in softs {Griffith, 1977). Linear    0016-7061/84/$03.00 984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    252    polyphosphates are known to form complexes with metals at the same levels  as do EDTA and salts of nitrilotriacetic acid (Nevolin, 1971). Compounds  that form complexes with elements such as iron are important in migrations  of elements in soils. Consequently, it seems possible that polyphosphates  may contribute to the migrations of certain soil elements by complexing  them from both the soil solution and solid phases. In complex forms, the ele-  ments could remain in solution and migrate with percolating waters.  Additions of commercial fertilizers based on superphosphoric acid might  increase the formation of polyphosphate complexes and thus indirectly  promote the migration of metals. The purpose of the present investigation  was to examine the possibility that polyphosphates contribute to the migra-  tion of certain elements in soils.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil sample    A large sample was collected from the humus horizon (A1) of a virgin grey  forest soft. The horizon was a silty loam with a pH in water of 5.15 and in  i N KC1 of 4.57, hydrolytic acidity of 5.9 me./100 gm, total C of 1.1% and  0.84 mg/100 gm of P soluble in 0.2 N HC1. The full sample was passed  through a 4-mm sieve to remove coarse aggregates and plant residues.    Experimental and analy tical procedures    Experiment No. 1. Plastic cylinders 20 cm in diameter and 42 cm long  were placed in a trench 40 cm deep in the field. The part of each cylinder  below 20 cm was then filled with the sieved soil material. The uppermost  20 cm were next filled with 10 kg of soil material after it had been mixed  with fertilizer. Three fertilizer treatments and four replicates of each were  used. Elements applied were NK, NKPortho and NKPpoly. The N, K and P  were added as NH4NO3, KC1 and either ortho- or polyphosphate of ammo-  nium. Application rates for N, K and P, respectively, were 8.0, 6.6 and  10.5 mg/100 gm of soil material. The rate for N includes amounts in both  nitrates and phosphates. The cylinders were kept at approximate field mois-  ture capacity. The fertilized and unfertilized portions of soil in each treat-  ment were sampled three months after the experiment was started. Those  samples were air dried and ground to pass a 1-mm sieve for subsequent  analyses.  Experiment No. 2. Lysimeters with a diameter of 15 cm and a height of  45 cm were used. The bottom 20 cm of each cylinder were filled with alter-  nate 2-cm layers of cation-exchange resin KY-2 in the Hform and anion ex-  change resin ~3- IOYI in the OH- form and a mixture of equal parts of  aluminium oxide and of quartz sand that had been washed with HC1 and  H20 (Kaurichev and Nozdrunova, 1960). A 2-cm layer of quartz sand was    253    next placed on top of the sorbent materials. The uppermost part (25 cm) of  each cylinder was filled with 6 kg of soil material after it had been mixed  with fertilizers. Four fertilizer treatments with three replicates of each were  used, namely, NK, NKPortho, NKPpoly and NKPpoly plus CaCO3. The applica-  tion rates for N, K and P, respectively, were 30.0, 12.5 and 65.4 mg/100 gm.  CaCO3 was applied in one treatment in sufficient quantity to neutralize  hydrolytic acidity. Forms of fertilizers were the same as in Experiment No.  1. The rates of phosphorus application were chosen to simulate conditions  created in softs in the vicinities of particles of phosphate fertilizers.  Percolates or leachates from the lysimeters were collected for 85 days.  Water was added at first to bring the soil materials to 50% of water-holding  capacity. Subsequently, atmospheric precipitation was the only source of  water. The leachates were analyzed for total and mineral P (ortho- and poly-  forms), Fe and C. Amounts were totaled for the first 10 days and again for  the following 75 days.  Natural synthesis of polyphosphates. Natural synthesis of polyphosphates  was determined in fallow soil in the NK and NKPortho fertilizer treatments of  Experiment No. 2. After the fertilizers were applied, samples of the surface  0--20 cm layer of soil were taken once per week or per fortnight. Samples  were carried immediately in closed containers to the laboratory, and the  analyses for ortho- and poly- forms of P were made within 2 h. Samples were  not dried prior to analyses. Monitoring of the fallow soil continued for six  weeks.  Microbial populations. Samples of the humus horizon of a grey forest soil  were incubated for 14 days with and without additions of Ammophos  granules in Petri dishes. There were six replicates of each treatment. Tech-  nique of the experiment was analogous to those described by Bouldin and  Sample (1959) and Kudeyarova (1981a,b). After incubation soil portions  taken at distances of 0.5--1.5 cm from Ammophos granules were used for  microbial counts. Microbial numbers were quantified by the spread plate  technique.  Analytical procedures. Amounts of six elements extracted by various rea-  gents and pH values were determined at the end of three months for the soil  samples in Experiment No. 1. Soil pH was measured electrochemically with a  glass electrode in 1 N KC1 extract (soil--solution ratio of 1:2.5). Ca and Mg  were extracted with 1 N NaC1 (decantation} and estimated with EDTA titra-  tion. Mn and Zn were extracted with 1 N KC1 (soil--solution ratio of 1:2.5)  and determined by atomic absorption spectrophotometry. Fe2and Fe3 were extracted with 0.1 N H2SOa (soil--solution ratio of 1:10) and deter-  mined by the o-phenanthroline method. Iron-containing complexes were  destroyed by acidification up to 1.3 N HC1 combined with digestion at  100 for 20 min. Differences in amounts of iron prior to and after digestion  were considered to be those present in stable complexes. Contents of total  and water-soluble C in the samples were measured by potassium dichromate  oxidation.    254    Procedures to determine amounts of Fe and C in the extracts of soil mate-  rials in Experiment No. 1 were also used to determine those elements in the  leachates from the lysimeters in Experiment No. 2.  Hydrolysis of the condensed forms of P in leachates was carried out in an  acid medium (1.3 N HC1) by heating in boiling water for 20 min. Amounts  of the poly-form were considered to be the differences between values of  mineral phosphorus determined before and after hydrolysis. Total P was  determined in aliquots of leachates after digestion with a mixture of concen-  trated H:SO4 and 57% HC104 {mixture with a ratio of 10:1). Concentrations  of inorganic P in ortho-form in the solutions were determined colorimetri-  cally by the method of Murphy and Riley as modified by Watanabe and  Olsen {1965). Organic P was calculated as the difference between total and  mineral (ortho- plus poly-forms) phosphorus.  Soil samples taken periodically from the NK and NKPortho treatments of  Experiment No. 2 were extracted with 0.2 N HC1 {soil--solution ratio of 1:5)  for determination of mineral phosphorus in ortho- and poly-forms. The sus-  pension was shaken for 1 min and allowed to stand for 15 min. It was then  filtered and the amounts of P in solution were determined by the procedure  described in the preceding paragraph.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Data on soil materials in cylinders    The pH values of soil samples taken in Experiment No. 1 are given in  Table I. The pH decreased in the cylinders that received phosphorus fertil-  izers as compared to the NK treatment, with the largest decrease occurring in  those samples treated with polyphosphates. These decreases are attributed to  processes of complex formation such as occur in the development of chelates  (Martell and Calvin, 1952).    TABLE I    Solubilizing effect of polyphosphates on some elements (Experiment No. 1 )    Fertilizer   PHKc1  Ca      Mg         Mn      Zn        Fe in mg/100 gm soil  treatment                                                     material (0.1 N H2SO4  extract)    me./100 gm         rag/100 gm        before        after  soil material         soil material       destruction    destruction  (1 N NaCl extract)  (1 N KCI extract)  of complexes of complexes    NK          4.50     10.6     7.2          2.0       0.07       3.81            4.66  NKPortho   4.38     10.4     7.4          3.6       0.09       5.13            6.61  NKPpoly    4.17     12.8     3.6          4.4       0.22       3.11            9.87  LSD at  0.05 level  --         0.7     0.8         0.5      0.08      0.86           0.98    255    The amounts of Ca, Mg, Mn, Zn and Fe extracted from the soil samples in  this experiment are also given in Table I. The data permit certain inferences  about the stability of complexes of those ions with polyphosphates.  The data for Ca, Mn and Zn indicate that polyphosphate promoted solu-  tion of the three soil elements without forming stable complexes. The ele-  ments are released from complexes readily; destruction of them is not neces-  sary. Because stable complexes are not formed, the possibilities for migration  of Ca, Mn and Zn in such forms are believed to be so small as to be insignifi-  cant.  In contrast to Ca, Mn and Zn, Mg and Fe form extremely stable com-  plexes with polyphosphate ions. The amounts of Mg extracted from samples  were about half as large for the orthophosphate as for the polyphosphate  treatments. Similarly, the amount of iron extracted from the samples was  lower prior to destruction of complexes from the polyphosphate as com-  pared to the orthophosphate treatments. After destruction of complexes,  however, the extracted amounts were highest for the cylinders that received  polyphosphates. These findings are consistent with the well-known capacity  of pyrophosphate ions to form stable complexes with metal ions. That  capacity is the basis of methods for the extraction of iron and organic matter  from soil samples (Alexandrova, 1960; Bascomb, 1968). Consequently, we  concluded that the mobilization of iron in the samples was due to the forma-  tion of stable polyphosphate complexes. Those would in turn predispose  both phosphorus and iron to be leached into deeper horizons of soils: Kude-  yarova (1981a) had previously demonstrated profound migration of phos-  phorus from upper to lower horizons of soils fertilized with polyphosphates.  Mobility of organic carbon was also affected by treatment with polyphos-  phate fertilizers {Table II). The amounts of water-soluble carbon in the  cylinders receiving polyphosphate fertilizer were more than twice as large as  in the cylinders getting no phosphate fertilizer. The greater mobility of  carbon because of polyphosphate is further indicated by a comparison of  quantities of total C within and below the fertilized layers of the three    TABLE II    Carbon mobility in relation to applications of P fertilizers (Experiment No. 1)    Fertilizer          Water-soluble C       Total C in mg/100 gm soil material  treatment          within  fertilized              within                below  layer                  fertilized              fertilized  (in mg/100 gm soil)   layer                  layer    NK                  3.8                   1153                  1073  NKP,,rtho            4.5                   1133                  1093  NKPpoly            10.2                     974                   1194  LSD at 0.05 level   1.1                     88                    88    256    fertilizer treatments. The amounts were lower in the fertilized part and  higher in the deeper unfertilized parts of the cylinders getting polyphos-  phate. We attribute these differences to downward migration of water-  soluble carbon.    Data on leachates    Direct evidence for migration of P, Fe and C was obtained by analyses of  leachates from lysimeters in Experiment No. 2. The sorbent layers of anion  and cation exchangers in the lower parts of the lysimeters would permit  passage of compounds of a complex nature but not simple ions. Quantities  of the several elements leached out of the lysimeters were therefore con-  sidered to have been in complex forms. Cumulative amounts of P, Fe and C  found in the leachates after intervals of 10 and 85 days are given in Table III.    TABLE III    Leaching of phosphorus, iron and carbon in the form of complex compounds (rag per lysimeter)    Fertilizer     Total P     Organic P  Mineral P                  Total Fe    Fe in         Total C  treatment                                                                         highly stable  ortho          poly                       complexes    NK        0.1510.12  0.1110.08  0.03/0.03   0.01/0.01  0.55/0.38  0,18/0.10    4.16/1.36  NKPortho   0.67/0.62  0.57]0.55  0.05/0.04   0.05/0.03  1.74/0.72  1,02/0.39   46.39/34.79  NKPpoly    3.80/3.58  0.41/0.33  1.58/1.53    1.81/1.72  3.24/2.17  2.21/1.69    96.11/74.41  NKPpoly  + CaCO3     0.30/0.25  0.2010.17  0.06/0.05    0.04/0.03  1.16/0.70  0.44/0.44   32,50/22.80    LSD at 0.05  level         0.05        0.05        0.05         0.06        0.09        0.08           1.14    Note: The numerator shows the data for 85 days, and the denominator shows the data for the first  10 days of the experiment.    The amounts of phosphorus in leachates were six times as large for the  polyphosphate as for the orthophosphate treatments, provided CaCO3 was  not added with the former treatment. The migration of phosphorus was  mainly in mineral forms as shown by the combined portions of the element  in the ortho- and poly-forms. Condensed phosphates were predominant.  When CaCO3 was added with the polyphosphate, the amounts of P in the  leachate were reduced sharply, falling back to the approximate levels for the  orthophosphate treatments. The reduced leaching of phosphorus associated  with additions of CaCO3 is attributed to sorption of P compounds on sur-  faces of carbonate particles, as described by Yanishevsky (1978).  Amounts of organic phosphorus in leachates from lysimeters with ortho-  phosphate or polyphosphate treatments were almost the same. Small losses  of phosphorus from soil of the NK and NKPortho treatments were mainly in  organic forms.  Amounts of Fe and C in the leachates were appreciably greater from lysi-  meters to which phosphorus fertilizer had been added (Table III}. Amounts    257    were about twice as high for polyphosphate as for orthophosphate treat-  ments. Additions of CaCO3 with polyphosphates reduced amounts of Fe  and C in leachates but did not eliminate them.  The patterns of losses of Fe and C in the leachates during the 85 days  indicate migration in more than one form, especially Fe. Leaching continued  for all 85 days but was greater the first 10 days. Thus, the maximum losses  occurred during the same period as did those of phosphorus. Moreover, the  losses of both Fe and C were appreciably greater from lysimeters that re-  ceived polyphosphates than orthophosphates, provided CaCO3 was not  added as well. A major share of the leached iron could be detected only after  acid hydrolysis, indicating that the element was a component of stable com-  plexes. We concluded therefore that much of the iron leached from the lysi-  meters the first 10 days was in complex form with polyphosphates. Losses of  iron continued throughout the duration of the experiment, however, after  the leaching of phosphorus had diminished greatly. We postulate that the  continued losses of iron were in the form of complexes with organic matter.  Losses of carbon also continued for the 85 days, and the role of organic  matter in the migration of iron in soil profiles is well known (Kaurichev and  Nozdrunova, 1960).  The data from the two experiments indicate that additions of phosphorus  fertilizers, especially those containing polyphosphates, to acid softs can result  in formation of iron-phosphate complexes subject to migration in perco-  lating waters. Applications of inorganic condensed phosphates as fertilizers  may thus promote leaching of elements from soils under some conditions.    Natural synthesis of polyphosphates    Like the condensed phosphates in fertilizers, natural polyphosphates may  also play roles in the mobilization and migration of elements in acid soils.  Amounts of these compounds are usually small, but fair quantities may accu-  mulate under favorable conditions (Pepper et al., 1976; Kudeyarova, 1981a).  Moreover, the compounds are active.  Data on the dynamics of polyphosphate in a fallowed grey forest soil are  given in Table IV. These are for 6 weeks during the summer. Maximum syn-  thesis of polyphosphates was observed in the first half of July. Part of these  phosphates were pyroforms, identified by chromatographic separation of  phosphates in soil extracts. Maximum amounts of condensed phosphates in  the soil of lysimeters which had not received phosphorus fertilizer were  0.70 mg of P per 100 g of soil material as contrasted to 6.54 mg/100 g in  lysimeters to which orthophosphate had been added. The orthophosphate  treatment stimulated synthesis of condensed phosphates in the soil. Similar  data had been obtained earlier in a laboratory study with samples of a grey  forest soil (Kudeyarova, 1981a). In the immediate surroundings of an  Ammophos granule the amount of phosphorus in the form of polyphos-  phates was 7.41 mg/100 g soil materials.    258  TABLE IV  Dynamics of polyphosphate accumulation in fallowed grey forest soil (P as mg/100 gm  oven-dry soil material)    Fertilizer             Sampling dates June and July  treatment                                          -  -    12.06             28.06                2.07                9.07             23.07    NK                                          0.06                0.09                0.52                0.70                0.22  NKPor tho               0.17        1.57        6.28        6.54        5.41    LSD at 0.05 level                         0.11    Note: Fertilizers were applied on 8 June 1981.    Possible roles of microorganisms in the natural synthesis of polyphos-  phates in soils are indicated by the numbers of bacteria and fungi given in  Table V. High concentrations of phosphorus in the vicinities of Ammophos  granules stimulated bacterial growth and apparently inhibited reproduction  of fungi. Interruption of the process of cell division because of imbalance  among nutrients in the growth medium is known to be required for synthesis  of polyphosphates (Kulaev, 1975; Harold and Sylvan, 1963; Weimberg,  1975). The apparent restriction of growth of fungi suggests that the poly-  phosphates were synthesized by the fungal cells. The combination of data in  Tables IV and V further suggests that the microbial population is a prime  factor in the natural synthesis of inorganic condensed phosphates in soils.  Such synthesis can be intensified by additions of orthophosphate fertilizers.  The resulting accumulations of polyphosphates then provide opportunities  for the formation of complexes which can in turn intensify the mobilization  and migration of certain elements in grey forest soils.    TABLE V  Total microbial population at the sites of phosphorus fertilizer granules (incubation of  soil with fertilizer during 14 days at 30)    P                       Bacteria population,  fertilizer                million per gm oven-dry  soil material    sapro-         oligo-  phytic         trophic    Colonies of fungi,  Separate  thousand per      groups  gm oven-dry  soil material    Without P                5.5           29.3  Ammophos             10.5           67.1    49           24  40            7    LSD at 0.05 level        3.8           10.6              4                   4    259    REFERENCES    Alexandrova, L.N., 1960. Use of sodium pyrophosphate for the extraction of free humic  substances and their organomineral compounds from soil. Pochvovedeniye, 2:90--97  (in Russian).  Anderson, G. and Russell, J.D., 1969. Identification of inorganic pyrophosphate in  alkaline extracts of soil. J. Sci. Food Agric., 20: 78--81.  Bascomb, C.L., 1968. Distribution of pyrophosphate-extractable iron and organic carbon  in soils of various groups. J. Soil Sci., 19: 251--268.  Bouldin, D.R. and Sample, E.C., 1959. Laboratory and greenhouse studies with mono-  calcium, monoammonium, and diammonium phosphates. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 23:  338--342.  Griffith, E.J., 1977. Condensed phosphates from abiotic systems in nature. In: C. Pon-  namperuma, (Editor), Chemical Evolution of the Early Precambrian. Academic Press,  New York, N.Y., pp. 61--67.  Harold, F.M. and Sylvan, S., 1963. Accumulation of inorganic polyphosphate in Aero-  bacter aerogenes. J. Bacteriol., 86: 222--231.  Kaurichev, I.S. and Nozdrunova, E.M., 1960. Inventory of migration of some compounds  in soil using lysimetric chromatographic columns. Pochvovedeniye, 12:30--35 (in  Russian).  Kudeyarova, A. Yu., 1981a. Polyphosphates and phosphorus cycle in soils. In: Problems  of Soil Science. Soviet pedologists to XII Intern. Congress of Soil Sci. Nauka, Moscow,  pp. 97--102.  Kudeyarova, A. Yu., 1981b. Aluminium phosphates as products of transformations of  fertilizer phosphorus in an acid soil. Geoderma, 26 : 195--201.  Kulaev, I.S., 1975. Inorganic polyphosphates and their physiological role. Nauka, Moscow,  32 pp. (in Russian).  Martell, A.E. and Calvin, M., 1952. Chemistry of the Metal Chelate Compounds. Prentice-  Hall, New York, N.Y., 613 pp.  Nevolin, F.P., 1971. Chemistry and Technology of Synthetic Detergents. Food Industry,  Moscow, 424 pp. (in Russian).  Pepper, I.L., Miller, R.H. and Ghonsikar, C.P., 1976. Microbial inorganic polyphosphates:  factors influencing their accumulation in soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 872--875.  Watanabe, F.S. and Olsen, S.R., 1965. Test of an ascorbic acid method for determining  phosphorus in water and NaHCO~ extracts from soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29:  677--678.  Weimberg, R., 1975. Polyphosphate levels in nongrowing cells of Saccharomyces mellis as  determined by magnesium ion and the phenomenon of "~berkompensation". J. Bacte-  riol., 121 : 1122--1130.  Yanishevsky, F.V., 1978. Agrochemistry of liquid complex fertilizers. Nauka, Moscow,  208 pp. (in Russian).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractThe role of polyphosphates added to soil or synthesized in place in m mobilization and migration of some elements in a grey forest soil was examined by three approaches. All included applications of polyphosphoric and/or orthophosphoric fertilizers. First, samples of soil placed in cylinders in the field were extracted to determine the quantities of Ca, Mg, Mn, Zn, Fe and P in simple and complexed forms. Second, parallel samples were placed in small lysimeters designed to allow leaching of complexed but not simple forms of the elements. Leachates were analyzed at intervals for 85 days to measure losses of P, Fe and C. Third, samples of fallow soil were monitored for 6 weeks to estimate natural synthesis of polyphosphates following application of orthophosphate fertilizer. Numbers of bacteria and fungi were determined in a laboratory study in samples of soil incubated with Ammophos granules for indications of the role of micro-organisms in synthesis of polyphosphates.Evidence obtained through the three approaches indicates that addition of ammonium polyphosphate intensifies the mobilization and movement of P, Fe and C in a grey forest soil. Furthermore, application of ammonium orthophosphate promotes synthesis of polyphosphates in the field with consequent o opportunities for increases in migration. Numbers of bacteria and fungi in soil fertilized with orthophosphate suggest that micro-organisms play a role in the natural synthesis of polyphosphates.