Geoderma, 27 (1982) 209--223                                                      209  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    IS THERE HOLOCENE REDDENING (HEMATITE FORMATION) IN  SOILS OF AXERIC TEMPERATE AREAS?    U. SCHWERTMANN, E. MURAD and D.G. SCHULZE  Lehrstuhl fiir Bodenkunde, Technische Universita't Miinchen, D-8050 Freising-Weihen-  stephan (F.R.G.)  (Received February 15, 1981; accepted July 30, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Schwertmann, U., Murad, E. and Schulze, D.G., 1982. Is there Holocene reddening (hema-  tite formation) in soils of axeric temperate areas? Geoderma, 27: 209--223.    Alfisols on calcareous glacial gravels in the northern forelands of the Alps, between the  Upper Rhine Valley in the west and Eastern Bavaria in the east, show rubified Bt horizons.  Their redness decreases from west (2.5 YR) to east (10 YR), paralleling decreasing tem-  perature and increasing rainfall.  Detailed mineralogical studies by M}Sssbauer spectroscopy and differential X-ray diffrac-  tion demonstrated the presence of hematite in association with goethite. Concentrations  of hematite decrease from west to east with decreasing temperature. No hematite was  detected in the non-calcareous residues of calcareous C horizons.  Alfisols on silty glacial material in the immediate vicinity of the reddish soils have yel-  low-brown (10 YR) Bt horizons and are hematite-free. We conclude that rubification (hema-  tite formation) is possible under an axeric climate provided a suitable pedoclimate exists.    INTRODUCTION    Soils with hues of 7.5--5 YR and redder owe their reddish colour mostly  to hematite (a-Fe203), whereas soils with hues of 10 YR and yellower usually  contain goethite (a-FeOOH) and are free of hematite. The geographical distri-  bution of red (hematitic) and yellow-brown (hematite-free) soils appears to  be closely related to climate, increasing temperatures apparently favouring  the formation of hematite (rubification*'). Thus, moving away from the  equator, a border line can be imagined to exist beyond which hematitic soils  are no longer being formed under the present climatic regimes.  Because of the widespread occurrence of red softs of pre-Holocene age, only  soils formed on Wilrm (Weichselian, Devensian, Wisconsinan) or Holocene  sediments can provide an unequivocal answer to the question put forth in the  title.    *' In this paper rubification is defined as pedogenetic hematite formation resulting in red-  dish soil colours.    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    210    Torrent et al. {1980) found the youngest terrace of the Esla river in north-  ern Spain, with hematite-bearing soils, to have an age of approximately 3300  years. The climate of this area (mean annual temperature 11.5 and precipi-  tation 450 mm) is sufficiently warm to induce hematite formation. Recent  dune sands formed in a sub-humid climate of Israel with ca. 20 and 400  mm (Dan et al., 1968/69) show similar reddening.  In contrast, where reddish soils occur in Europe outside of the Mediter-  ranean area, they are usually associated with pre-Holocene, somewhat warmer  climates (Catt, 1979; Chartres, 1980). Yet, Alfisols with reddish Bt horizons  are developed on calcareous, sandy to gravelly glacial moraines and fluvio-  glacial stream sediments of Wiirm age in the cool northern foreland of the  Alps. During geological mapping of the area around Munich, i.e. in the east-  ern part of the northern Alpine foreland, Koehne and Nicklas (1914) first  noted the existence of such reddish softs on fluvio-glacial gravels. Krauss  (1922) called these softs "Blutlehme" (blood loams) because of their red  colour. More recently, Schmid (1962) drew attention to the widespread oc-  currence of such "Blutlehm" in Upper Bavaria.  Penck and Briickner (1901--1909) first observed such reddish soils in the  western part of the northern Alpine foreland. Detailed descriptions of the  latter were given by Werner (1964) and, particularly for those developed in  the Upper Rhine Valley between Breisach and Basel, by Moll (1970) who  called them "rubifizierte Braunerden". The B horizons of these softs may be  as red as 2.5 YR and their clay fractions contain approximately 5% dithionite-  extractable Fe.  The climate of this area generally becomes cooler (11-~ 7 mean annual  temperature) and moister (500--600--800--1200 mm mean annual precipita-  tion) from west to east, and also from north to south as higher Alpine eleva-  tions are approached. Geologically, glacial and flucio-glacial Wiirmian deposits  of widely differing textures dominate (Fig. 1).  The occurrence of these reddish softs appears to depend both on climate  and parent material. On coarse, sandy-gravelly deposits the degree of redness  of the Bt horizon decreases from west to east, parallel to the change in climate.  The widespread occurrence of gravelly sediments in this area makes the soils  particularly suited for obtaining an impression of the climatic conditions which  result in rubification.  The effect of parent material is also obvious. In the immediate neighbour-  hood of reddish softs on coarse, gravelly material, Alfisols with yellowish (10  YR) Bt horizons are developed on silty to clayey moraines (Diez, 1967; Jerz,  1968; Wilke, 1975). Inasmuch as both soil types have been formed under the  same general climate, these differences must result from differences in the  pedoclimate {soil moisture and temperature) caused by differences in texture.  The iron oxide mineralogy of these soils, which is of fundamental impor-  tance for the phenomenon of reddening (Torrent et al., 1980), has not yet  been described. This lack of information results mainly from the difficulty of  detecting the iron oxide minerals at the low concentrations involved. In the    211    ~                          STUTTGART  ScHWm ~/~ L~Lp-q'~I ~'i,~,~:y~ ~    :(-" )-'%    Fig. 1. Simplified map of the distribution of Wiirm moraines (vertical hatching) and fluvio-  glacial gravels (terraces; horizontal hatchirg) in southern Germany. Sample localities  (numbers) are also indicated.    present study MSssbauer spectroscopy, a sensitive, element-specific method  that permits the identification and characterization of iron oxides to below  1% Fed and a differential X-ray diffraction procedure, which results in an im-  proved detection limit (Schulze, 1981), have been used to describe the iron  oxides of these soils.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil samples    Samples from Bt horizons of Alfisols were taken across the Alpine foreland  from the Upper P~hine Valley in the west to about 50 km E of Munich in the  east (Fig. 1 and Table I). Typical Parabraunerde profiles on gravelly moraines  and fluvio-glacial sediments are between 50 and 70 cm thick, and have 20--25  cm A horizons with 15--25% clay, followed by 10--25 cm Bt horizons with  30--45% clay immediately overlying the calcareous parent material (Diez,  1967; Jerz, 1968; Moll, 1970; Wilke, 1975). Under forest vegetation the A  horizons are strongly acid (pH ~&lt; 4). The Bt horizons usually have pH values  between 6.0 and 6.8 but may occasionally be more acid.  Samples were collected mainly from reddish (7.5--2.5 YR) Bt horizons.  For comparison some samples were also taken from the yellowish Bt horizons  of softs formed on silty moraines in proximity to reddish softs on coarse  gravels (W1583, 132, W1997). The samples were air-dried and the &lt;20 or  &lt; 2/~m fractions separated after ultrasonic dispersion in water. Crushed sam-  ples of the C horizons (calcareous gravels) of five profiles were decalcified by  dropwise addition of 1 N HC1 at pH values above 4. The insoluble residues  were washed and dispersed with NaOH at pH 9.5, and the clay fractions ob-    TABLE I    to  b-a  tO    Description of samples, arranged from E to W    Sample   Locality          Parent * 1   Climate* 2  No.                        material    aC)   T7      Pa  (ram)    Soil*a         Properties of clay fraction.4                l~atio*~  P7    colour        colour        Fed   Fe  Fe/   Fed    Hm/  (%)   (%)   Fed   (N).S  (Hm +  (%)  Gt)    W 1854   E nsisheim  (Almme)       G       10.3  19.5   578  127     Hil~zfelden,  N~mbreisach     G       10.3  19.5   578  125a     Siren            G          8.0   16.5    750  132    L'weridorf/  Stoekach       G        8.3  17.8   814  W240   ~na~meh/  Lm~d~e~       G        7.4  16.6  1021  Wil-1    Epfach/  Schongau        G          6.5  16.0  1379  Wil-3a   Stillern/  Lamisberg        M          7.5  16.5  1379  W1997   ditto            M          7.5  16.5   1379  W1583   Kempten         M          7.6  17.2   1187  162      Puch/M'dnchen    G          7.5   17.2   1067  163     Brunnthal/  M~nchen         G          7.9  17.6  1125  W1947   Wagserb urg       G          7.6  17.2    998    74   5 YR3/4      5 YR4/6     4.94   0.80   0.16   n.d,   0.29  74   5 YR4/4      5 YR4/6     2.09   0.32   0.15    2.71  0.32  96   5 YR4/8      5 YR3/6     3.83   0.38   0.10   11.3   0.09  112  10 YR4/4      7.5 YR4/4   3.85   0,99   0.26   n.d.   0  151   5 YR4/4      7.5 YRS/4   4.83   0.49   0.10   13.9   0.03  187 7.5 YR4/4      5 YR4/4     4.64   0.40   0.09   11.7   0.08  187   7.5 YR4/4   7.5 YR4/4  4.51  0.51  0.08 13.5  0.03  187  10 YR5/6    10 YR5[6    3.08  0.46  0.15  n.d.   0  146  2.5 Y4]4   10 YR4]4    3.43  0.40  0.12  n.d.   0  149  7.5 YR4/4   7.5 YR4/6  5.27  0.81  0.15  12.1  0.05  162  7.5 YR4/4   7.5 YR4/6  5.42  0.43  0.08  15,0  0.06  152  7.5 YR4/4   7.5 YR4/4  5.91  0.51  0,09  14.9  0.04    *' G= fluvioglacial gravel, M = moraine; *: Ta, T~, Pa,  "3 Munsell, moist; .4 except 127,125a and 132 (&lt; 20  Hm = hematite, Gt = goethite.    PT: average annual and July temperatures and precipitation, respectively;  pro); ,s after NaOH-treatment; ,6 as determined by M~ssbauer spectroscopy;    213    tained by sedimentation. Total iron oxides (Fed) were determined in a dithio-  nite-citrate-bicarbonate (DCB) extract (Mehra and Jackson, 1960) and oxalate-  soluble iron (Feo) was measured in an acid ammonium oxalate extract (Schwert  mann, 1964) using a Perkin Elmer 420 atomic absorption spectrometer. In  selected clay samples, the iron oxides were concentrated by boiling the clay  fractions for 1 h in 5 N NaOH (Norrish and Taylor, 1961).    M~ssbauer spectroscopy    MSssbauer spectra were taken using a STCo/Rh source mounted on a loud-  speaker-type drive system. Spectra were run at room temperature and after  cooling both source and absorber to 120 and 4 K in a cryostat. Absorbers  consisted of ca. 100 mg of sample, spread uniformly over an area of 2 cm2 in  a plexiglas holder. The transmitted radiation was registered with a propor-  tional counter and fed into a 1024 channel analyzer. Counting proceeded un-  til sufficiently good statistics, visually monitored with an oscilloscope, had  been attained. The data were folded, plotted and Lorentzian curve fits carried  out by a computer procedure. Pure metallic iron served as a standard for  velocity calibration and as reference material for isomer shifts.    Differential X-ray diffraction    X-ray diffraction data were obtained using CoK~ radiation and a Philips  PWl040 vertical goniometer equipped with a graphite monochromator. Dif-  ferential X-ray diffraction (DXRD) diagrams were obtained by subtracting  step-scanned powder diffraction patterns of samples obtained before selec-  tive dissolution of the iron oxides from patterns obtained after selective dis-  solution by DCB. Instrumental settings and procedural details are given by  Schulze (1981).    RESULTS    M6ssbauer spectra    At room temperature MSssbauer spectra of the soils consisted essentially  of a strong Fe3doublet of isomer shift 5 = 0.35 ram. s-1 and quadrupole  splitting AEQ = 0.61 mm s-1, a weaker Fe2doublet with 8 = 1.07 and  AEQ = 2.72 mm s-1, and occasionally a subordinate magnetically split sextet  (magnetic hyperfine field Hi = 497 kOe), see Figs. 2a, 3a. The Fezdoublet  can be assigned wholly and the Fe3doublet partly to silicate-bound iron.  The hyperfine field of the sextet is indicative of hematite of rather poor  crystaUinity and/or high Al-substitution (Janot and Gibert, 1970). The main  part of the Fe3doublet also results from iron oxides. Because the parameters  of most trivalent iron oxides in the superparamagnetic state are similar, mix-  tures of these cannot be analyzed on the basis of such spectra, even at high  resolution.    98    96.  100"    99    -10        - 5    100    --    98  o=    J    I  0           B  b    29SK         120K    4K  i              i  5       10    VELOCITY  (mm.s-I)    fur[  stole    b    Layer  Siticotes  Ouartz ~  Gill30)  +  Hm (I04)  fs = 50                                   "  x',~Xv~ OXRD  24                2.6             28           3.0  ' J   4'5    , ~    ,     ~     ,   ,,     ,, -~---a--r-  ........   ....  , A  40                      35    BlCoKa )    215    At 4K all iron oxides possess magnetically split MSssbauer spectra. At this  temperature the spectra of the samples consisted of one or two magnetically  split sextets and (usually) two doublets. Both doublets can be attributed to  silicate-bound iron. Of the magnetically split sextets, the outer one has a  hyperfine field, Hi, of 531 +- 1 kOe. This is lower than that observed for pure,  bulk hematite (ca. 540 kOe) but higher than those of other pedogenic iron  oxides (Murad and Schwertmann, 1980). This component can therefore be  attributed to hematite, the reduced hyperfine field being the outcome of  poor crystallinity and/or Al-substitution. Similar hyperfine fields have been  described for soil hematites from other localities (Simopoulos et al., 1975;  Bigham et al., 1978). The observed quadrupole splitting of ca. 0.2 mm s-1  shows that the hematites have not passed through the Morin transition. This  spin-flip transition, at which the quadrupole splitting changes sign and mag-  nitude, is suppressed in particles smaller than 200 h (Nininger and Schroeer,  1978) or when Fe is noticeably substituted for by other elements such as A1  (Srivastava and Sharma, 1972). The lack of a Morin transition is thus in agree-  ment with the reduced hyperfine field. The inner sextet has an average hyper-  fine field of 496 + 3 kOe and a quadrupole splitting of 0.23 mm s-1. These  parameters are typical for rather poorly crystallized and/or Al-substituted  goethite. On the basis of DXRD line positions, poor crystallinity appears to  be the more likely explanation.  To obtain an indication of the relative concentrations of hematite and  goethite in the silt and/or clay fractions, the ratios of the intensities of the  corresponding sextets were determined. As a control measure, similar mea-  surements were also carried out on one synthetic and three natural samples,  the hematite/goethite ratios of which had been determined by X-ray diffrac-  tion (pers. commun, by N. K~impf; this institute, 1981).  As hematite/goethite ratios decrease, the hematite component of the 4 K  spectra becomes correspondingly weaker. At values of this ratio below 0.1 it  often proved necessary to impose additional restrictions on the fitting sub-  routine, e.g. fix line widths, isomer shifts and/or quadrupole splittings (see  Table II) to properly fit the hematite sextet. The lowest ratio at which hema-  tite was found in the presence of goethite was about 0.03. MSssbauer spectra  of hematite-rich, tiematite-poor, and hematite-free samples are shown in  Figs. 2a, 3a and 4a. Parameters resulting from fits of these samples are given  in Table II.    Differential X-ray diffractograms    Conventional X-ray diffractograms indicate the presence of goethite and/or  hematite in a few selected clay fractions with 3--5% Fed by a peak at about  2.70 A (goethite 130 + hematite 104). This peak was significantly more in-    Fig. 2. Sample W1854 (Ensisheim/Alsace). a. MSssbauer spectra taken at 295, ca. 120  and 4 K; b. diffractometer tracings of original and DCB-treated sample, and DXRD diagram.    o    i  &lt;  r~  f-...  c'n    o    TRANSMISSION  (%}  s ~,'J ,i                   J    ~o  .o    91g    TABLE II  Mbssbauer parameters of selected samples    217    Sample   T(K)      5 (Fe)       AE0        W        Hi       lrel  W1854       295   0.37 *      0.21 *      0.7 (2)    502 *    0.05(1)  0.36(1)    0.63(1)    0.59(1)   --     0.88(1)  1.03(2)    2.7 *     0.5 *     --     0.07(1)  ca. 120  0.38(2)    0.19 *     0.6 (1)   512(2)  0.09(2)  0.33(2)    0.20(4)    1.57(8)   464(4)  0.45(3)  0.33(1)    0.69(1)    0.72(2)   --     0.40(1)  1.22(5)    2.7 *     0.27 *     --     0.06(1)  4  0.36(1)    0.18(1)    0.40(3)   530(1)  0.21(2)  0.35(1)    0.22(1)    0.81(2)   498(1)  0.51(2)  0.33(1)    0.63(2)    0.74(3)   --     0.25(1)  1.24(9)     2.7  *      0.35 *      --      0.02(1)    W240    295   0.37 *     0.21 *     0.5 (2)   505(3)  0.04(1)  0.35(1)    0.60(1)    0.44(1)   --     0.91(1)  1.09(2)    2.68(3)    0.30(4)   --     0.05(1)  ca.  120   0.35(9)      0.2  *       0.4  *     526(8)   0.01(1)  0.35(1)    0.19(3)    1.83(5)   453(1)  0.41(1)  0.36(1)    0.65(1)    0.59(1)   --     0.51(1)  1.09(2)    2.91(4)    0.35(3)   --     0.08(1)  4  0.34(3)    0.18(7)    0.4 *    532(3}  0.02(1)  0.36(1)    0.24(1)    0.76(1)   493(1)  0.65(1)  0.34(1)    0.64(1)    0.65 *    --     0.30(1)  1.18(5)    2.7 *     0.35"     --     0.03(1)    W1583   ca. 120    0.35(1)    0.24(3)    1.63(5)   447(1)  0.44(1)  0.35(1)    0.71(1)    0.61(1)   --     0.44(1)  1.13(1)    2.89(2)    0.49(2)   --     0.12(1)  0.35(1)    0.25(1)    0.65(1)   496(1)  0.62(1)  0.33(1)    0.70(1)    0.84(3)   --     0.31(1)  1.16(2)    2.89(4)    0.51(6)   --     0.06(1)    *Parameter fixed.  Isomer shifts (8), quadrupole splittings (AEQ) and widths (W} given in mm s-I, magnetic  hyperfine fields (Hi) in kOe. Errors on last digit given in parentheses.    tense after the NaOH treatment (Fig. 3b), corresponding to a concentration  of the Fe oxides by a factor of 2.5--3, as indicated by the Fed(N) values in  Table I. Distinction of goethite and hematite, however, which is the objec-  tive of this study, could not be achieved even after this concentration. In the  differential X-ray diffractograms, however, the strong interference at 2.55 A  from the clay minerals is removed, thus permitting identification of goethite  by its lll-peak at 2.45 h and hematite by its ll0-peak at 2.51 A.    Fig. 3. Sample W240 (Ramsach/Landsberg). a. Mbssbauer spectra taken at 295, ca. 120  and 4 K; b. diffractometer tracings of original and DCB-treated sample, DXRD diagram,  and diffractometer tracing of NaOH-treated sample.    218    o~-~  "-. ~"                     ~  I~    "~ o=  ~ =l b,-  (%]   NOISSII~S NV~IJ.    219    Results from DXRD diagrams, which were obtained for six representative  samples, are in excellent agreement with those obtained from MSssbauer  spectroscopy. The DXRD diagram from sample W1854 (Fig. 2b) contains the  diagnostic peaks for both goethite and hematite. DXRD diagrams for samples  W1578 (Fig. 4b) and W1997 show only peaks due to goethite, with the ratio  of areas of the goethite lll-peak to that of the 130-peak being between 1.8  and 2.0. This agrees very well with the values of 1.8--2.2 for the ratio  I(~11 + 040)/I130 obtained from 34 pure, synthetic goethites (the 040 peak  must be included because it is not resolved from the 111 peak in the DXRD  diagrams).  Samples W240 (Fig. 3b), W1947 and Wil-3a at first glance appear to con-  rain only goethite. The small amount of hematite detected by MSssbauer  spectroscopy, however, is shown by DXRD by an abnormally low ratio of  1.0--1.4 for I~ ~1/I130. The (strongest) hematite 104-line contributes to the in-  tensity of the goethite 130-line, with which it is coincident, causing the I ll 1/  I130 ratio to decrease.    Hematite content and soil colour    Torrent et al. (1980) found the redness R (Hurst, 1977) of soils from  Spanish river terraces to be linearly correlated with the hematite contents. As  shown in Fig. 5, the softs from this study - with only two exceptions -- match  the samples from Spain. This, again, shows that the red colour of these softs  results from hematite.    w    15'    10   Torrent et o[ 1%0 (-2ram}  Thqs pQper (-2&amp;~2Opm)  /  v    1'0            210  PER CENT OF HEMATITE    Fig. 5. Relationship between redness rating after Hurst (1977) and hematite concentra-  tion.    220    Iron oxides in the parent material  The increase in redness from east to west, i.e., parallel to the present-day  climate, strongly suggests that the soil hematites were formed in situ and are  not derived from the parent material. As a control measure, clay fractions of  noncalcareous residues of the C horizons of five profiles were analyzed  chemically for Fed and by MSssbauer spectroscopy for Fe oxides (Table III).  The hue for all these residues is 10 YR, and Fed values range between 0.8 and  3.8%. In agreement with the colour, MSssbauer spectra of selected samples  show goethite to be the only Fe oxide mineral. From this it can be concluded  that the hematite occurring in these soils is of pedogenic origin. The release  of 85--170 mg Fe/kg during the HC1 dissolution of the carbonate rocks (at  pH values &gt; 4), indicates that the pedogenic iron oxides may have been in  part derived from Fe(II) in these carbonates, released during decalcification.    TABLE III    Colour, Fed content and iron oxide mineralogy of the &lt; 2 ~m fraction of non-calcareous  residues of limestone gravels (= C horizons) of selected profiles  Locality         C horizon    Fe dissolved     Colour       Fed   Iron oxides  of sample     by 1 N HCI      moist        (%)   (MSssbauer)  No.           (mg/kg)    Hirtzfelden       127         n.d.             10 YR6/3    0.78  goethite  Chalamp~       *             170             10 YR5/4    3.72   goethite  Epfach          Wil-1         159             10 YR3/3    3.84  goethite  Stillern          Wil-3a          85              10 YR4/3     2.71   n.d.  Stillern          1997          134              10 YR4/3     2.53   n.d.    *Corresponds to W1854, Ensisheim (see Table I).    DISCUSSION    Sensitive laboratory techniques such as MSssbauer spectroscopy and dif-  ferential X-ray diffraction allow the detection of small amounts of hematite  associated with goethite in samples with as little as 2--3% Fed. Because the  intensity of redness increases with the hematite content, the red colouration  of the B horizons of these Alfisols results from hematite, not from ferrihy-  drite or other iron oxides. This observation is supported by the generally low  Feo/Fed ratios of these soils and confirms earlier results (Schwertmann and  Lentze, 1966; Torrent et al., 1980).  How red must a soil be so that hematite can be detected? In the present  study hematite could be readily identified in samples as red as or redder than  5 YR. In the 7.5 YR samples minor amounts of hematite were also detected.  In these, however, it often proved necessary to impose additional restrictions  upon the MSssbauer fit to properly quantify this mineral.    221    The results clearly indicate that hematite has been formed in soils on Wi]rm  sediments, i.e., during late glacial and/or Holocene pedogenesis, and is not in-  herited from the parent material. The amount of hematite formed appears to  depend upon both climate and parent material: as temperatures increase and  precipitation decreases from east to west in the study area, the softs become  redder and richer in hematite (Table I). The influence of parent material is  demonstrated by the occurrence of reddish softs on gravels next to yellowish  soils on silty materials. Although the macroclimate is the same for both soil  types, the pedoclimate may be quite different. No quantitative soil tempera-  ture data are available for such soil pairs. The more permeable soils developed  on gravel can, however, be expected to be generally drier, so that less water  will be evaporating from them. They are therefore probably warmer than  their counterparts on less permeable silty material, where pseudogley phe-  nomena are common. In the reddish softs of the Upper Rhine Valley, tem-  peratures of up to 56 at 5 cm and up to 30 at 30 cm depth were mea-  sured during the warmest time of the year (Moll, 1970). It thus appears that  in a limiting climate with respect to rubification, it is the climate in the soil  itself which eventually determines whether rubification will take place.  These observations are in agreement with the concept that the formation  of hematite from ferrihydrite will be favoured over that of goethite with in-  creasing temperature because this (1) promotes the dehydration of ferrihy-  drite, and (2) accelerates the decomposition of organic matter so that Fe  released from primary sources, such as silicates or carbonates, will be precip-  itated as ferrihydrite rather than organically complexed. The calcareous and  aerobic environment of these softs will further enhance the decomposition of  organic matter (Fischer and Schwertmann, 1975; Schwertmann and Taylor,  1977).  Higher temperatures than those currently observed, leading to increased  hematite formation, may have existed during some stages of the Wiirm glacia-  tion or, more likely, the Holocene period. The placement of the red soils into  a warmer interval within the Wfirm glaciation as done by Schmid (1962) for  the Bavarian soils and by Marocke (1962) for those of the Upper Rhine Val-  ley is hardly tenable on the basis of climatic and stratigraphic considerations.  Because the red soils occur only on late glacial, but not on silt-covered Holo-  cene terraces of the Lech valley, Diez (1968) -- in agreement with Fink (pers.  commun., 1980" 1) _ inferred these to have been formed between the final  ice retreat and the beginning of the Holocene period (16 000--10 000 B.P.).  Brunnacker {1957), Moll {1970) and Wilke (1975) believe the warm and dry  so-called Boreal (9000--7500 B.P.) to have been the most active period of  rubification. Finally, archaeological evidence led Lais (1940) to conclude  that rubified soils already existed in the Late Neolithic.  The existence of an interval during the Holocene that was warmer than  the present is, however, not universally accepted. Whereas Menke {1980)    ,1 Prof. Dr. J. Fink, Geographisches Institut, Universit~t Wien.    222    believes July temperatures in NW Germany to have been warmer by 2 dur-  ing the Boreal than at present, Frenzel (1978), after careful analysis of all  criteria, doubted the existence of a warmer period in the SW parts of central  Europe. On the basis of glacier end moraine and tree line data, Patzelt (1973)  also found no reliable indication of such a warm period in the Austrian Alps.  It is therefore not possible to decide definitely whether rubification has been  limited to a past interval of the Holocene period or, as assumed by Moll  (1970), is still taking place at present.    CONCLUSIONS    Holocene formation of hematite in soils appears to have been possible even  under a temperate, axeric climate with mean annual temperatures as low as  7. A prerequisite for hematite formation in this climate is a coarse, highly  permeable (calcareous) parent material, resulting in a pedoclimate warm  enough to induce the formation of this mineral. It thus does not seem neces-  sary to invoke the existence of warmer interglacial intervals to explain the  rubification of soils in central Europe (Cart, 1979; Chartres, 1980).    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors are indebted to Dr. F~E. Wagner (Physik Department, Tech-  nische Universit~it Milnchen) for making the MSssbauer measurements at 120  and 4 K possible. Samples and information were kindly provided by Prof.  W. Moll (Giessen), Dr. G. Schmid and Dr. F. Schmidt (both Miinchen), and  Dr. B.-M. Wilke (Bayreuth). Valuable comments on the Holocene climate  were made by Prof. J. Fink (Wien), Prof. G. Roeschmann (Hannover), and  Dr. B. Menke (Kiel).  Thisstudy has been supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft  under grant Schw 90/29.    REFERENCES    Bigham, J.M., Golden, D.C., Bowen, L.H., Buol, S.W. and Weed, S.B., 1978. Iron oxide  mineralogy of well-drained Ultisols and Oxisols, 1. Characterization of iron oxides in  soil clays by MSssbauer spectroscopy, X-ray diffractometry, and selected chemical  techniques. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 816--825.  Brunnacker, K., 1957. Die Geschichte der B~den im jiingeren Pleistoziin in Bayern. Geol.  Bavarica, 34:95 pp.  Catt, J.A., 1979. Soils and Quaternary geology in Britain. J. Soil Sci., 30: 607--642.  Chartres, C.J., 1980. A Quaternary soil sequence in the Kennet valley, central southern  England. Geoderma, 23: 125--146.  Dan, J., Yaalon, D.H. and Koyumdjiaky, H., 1968/69. Catenary soil relationships in Israel,  1. The Netanya catena on coastal dunes of the Sharon. Geoderma, 2: 95--120.  Diez, Th., 1967. Erl~uterungen zur Bodenkarte von Bayern 1:25000 Blatt 7931 Landsberg  a. Lech. Bayer. Geol. Landesamt, Miinchen, 124 pp.  Fischer, W.R. and Schwertmann, U., 1975. The formation of hematite from amorphous  iron (III) hydroxide. Clays Clay Miner., 23: 33--37.    223    Frenzel, B., 1978. Postglaziale Klimaschwankungen im siidwestlichen Mitteleuropa. Erd-  wissensch. Forsch., 13: 297--322.  Hurst, V.J., 1977. Visual estimation of iron in saprolite. Geol. Soc. Am. Bull., 88:174--  176.  Janot, C. and Gibert, H., 1970. Les constituants du fer dans certaines bauxites naturelles  ~tudi~es par effet MSssbauer. Bull. Soc. Fr. Mineral. Cristall., 93: 213--223.  Jerz, H., 1968. Erl~iuterungen zur Bodenkarte von Bayern 1:25000 Blatt 8134 KSnigsdorf.  Bayer. Geol. Landesamt, Miinchen, 151 pp.  Koehne, W. and Niklas, H., 1914. Erl~/uterungen zur Geologischen Karte des KSnigreichs  Bayern 1:25000 Blatt 713 Baierbrunn. K~nigl. Oberbergamt, M~nchen, 100 pp.  Kraus, E., 1922. Der Blutlehm auf der siiddeutschen Niederterrasse als Rest des post-  glazialen Kli.m. aoptimums. Geognost. Jh., 34: 169--222.  Lais, R., 1940. Uber rotgef~bte postglaziale BSden im Gebiet des Oberrheins. Germania,  24: 157--166.  Marocke, R., 1962. Datation des formations p~dologiques fossiles et actuelles de la ter-  rasse rh~nane wiirmienne du Sud d'Alsace. C.R. Acad. Sci., 254: 3116--3118.  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a dithio-  nite-citrate system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7: 317--327.  Menke, B., 1980. Vegetationskundlich-Skologisches Modell eines Interglazial-Glazial-  Zyklus in Nordwestdeutschland. Phytocoenologica, 7 : 100--120.  Moll, W., 1970. Beitriige zur Genese und systematischen Stellung rubefizierter Parabraun-  erden aus alpinen Schottern und Geschieben. Freiburg. Bodenkundl. Abh., 3:180 pp.  Murad, E. and Schwertmann, U., 1980. The MSssbauer spectrum of ferrihydrite and its  relations to those of other iron oxides. Am. Mineral., 65: 1044--1049.  Nininger, R.C. and Schroeer, D., 1978. MSssbauer studies of the Morin transition in bulk  and microcrystalline ~-Fe~O3. J. Phys. Chem. Solids, 39: 137--144.  Norrish, K. and Taylor, R.M., 1961. The isomorphous replacement of iron by aluminium  in soil goethites. J. Soil. Sci., 12: 294--306.  Patzelt, G., 1973. Die postglazialen Gletscher- und Klimaschwankungen in der Venediger-  gruppe (Hohe Tauern, Ostalpen). Z. Geomorphol. Suppl., 16: 25--72.  Penck, A. and Brtic.kner, E., 1901--1909. Die Alpen im Eiszeitalter. Leipzig, 3 vols.  Schmid, G., 1962. Uber Parabraunerden mit Blutlehmcharakter aus diluvialen Schotter-  und Moriinenablagerungen Siidbayerns. Z. Pflanzenern~ihr., Diing., Bodenkd., 99: 21--  36.  Schulze, D.G., 1981. Identification of soil iron oxide minerals by differential X-ray dif-  fraction. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 45: 437--440.  Schwertmann, U., 1964. Differenzierung der Eisenoxide des Bodens durch photochemische  Extraktion mit saurer Ammoniumoxalat-LSsung. Z. Pflanzenern~hr., D~ng., Bodenkd.,  105: 194--202.  Schwertmann, U. and Lentze, W., 1966. Bodenfarbe und Eisenoxidform. Z. Pflanzen-  ern~ihr., Diing., Bodenkd., 115: 209--214."  Schwertmann, U. and Taylor, R.M., 1977. Iron oxides. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Weed  (Editors), Minerals in Soil Environments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Madison, WI, pp. 145--  180.  Simopoulos, A., Kostikas, A., Sigalas, I., Gangas, N.H. and Moukarika, A., 1975. MSss-  bauer study of transformations induced in clay by firing. Clays Clay Miner., 23: 393--  399.  Srivastava, J.K. and Sharma, R.P., 1972. Magnetic dilution effects on Morin phase transi-  tion in hematite. Phys. Status Solidi (b), 49: 135--146.  Torrent, J., Schwertmann, U. and Schulze, D.G., 1980. Iron oxide mineralogy of some soils  of two river terrace sequences in Spain. Geoderma, 23: 191--208.  Werner, J., 1964. Grundztige einer regionalen Bodenkunde des sfidwestdeutschen Alpen-  vorlandes. Schriftenreihe Landesforstverw. Bad.-Wi~rtt., 17:91 pp.  Wilke, B.-M., 1975. Bodenchronosequenzen aus Lockersedimenten der Lechterrassen. Z.  Pflanzenern~ihr. Bodenkd., pp. 153--171.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractAlfisols on calcareous glacial gravels in the northern forelands of the Alps, between the Upper Rhine Valley in the west and Eastern Bavaria in the east, show rubified Bt horizons. Their redness decreases from west (2.5 YR) to east (10 YR), paralleling decreasing temperature and increasing rainfall.Detailed mineralogical studies by Mössbauer spectroscopy and differential X-ray diffraction demonstrated the presence of hematite in association with goethite. Concentrations of hematite decrease from west to east with decreasing temperature. No hematite was detected in the non-calcareous residues of calcareous C horizons.Alfisols on silty glacial material in the immediate vicinity of the reddish soils have yellow-brown (10 YR) Bt horizons and are hematite-free. We conclude that rubification (hematite formation) is possible under an axeric climate provided a suitable pedoclimate exists.