Geoderma, 34 (1984) 101--114                                                     101  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PHYSICAL ASSESSMENT OF A SOIL WITH RESPECT TO ROOTING  POTENTIAL    P.H. GROENEVELT, B.D. KAY and C.D. GRANT  Department of Land Resource Science, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, NI G 2W1  (Canada)  (Received October 21, 1983; accepted after revision July 2, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Groenevelt, P.H., Kay, B.D. and Grant, C.D., 1984. Physical assessment of a soil with  respect to rooting potential. Geoderma, 34: 101--114.    The potential suitability of a soil to accommodate growing roots was assessed on the  basis of: (1) the existing pore space available for unobstructed root growth; and (2)  the obstruction offered to a growing root by the soil matrix. The former was evaluated  by measuring the air permeability of undisturbed soil cores, equilibrated at a chosen  water tension. The latter was evaluated by measuring the spectrum of the tip resistance  encountered by a slowly penetrating fine probe.  The influence of cropping history on this potential suitability was examined by  comparing the same soil with two different cropping sequences (corn grown continuously  for five years and forages grown for three years followed by two years of corn). Measure-  ments were started shortly before the forages were plowed under.  Air permeabilities were higher for the plots on which forages had been grown, indi-  cating greater potential suitability for unobstructed root growth. The penetration ex-  periments showed that the average resistance to deformation of root-sized pores was  equal for the two cropping patterns. The average bulk density was higher in the con-  tinuous corn plots than in the plots on which forages had been grown. After analysis  of our data we postulated that the effect of the higher bulk density was offset by lower  aggregate strength in the continuous corn plots. Implications of this hypothesis are  discussed.    INTRODUCTION    Concern about the possible deterioration of soil structure due to pro-  duction of row crops such as corn in a monoculture system has prompted  renewed interest in the "measurement" of soil structure. Aspects of soil  structure which are considered to be significant to root development include  the pore geometry and the resistance of the soil matrix to deformation.  In addition, the stability of these characteristics under wetting/drying  and freezing/thawing conditions and the stability under mechanical stress  introduced by tillage and other production operations must be considered.  Decreasing stability implies a temporal variation in the characteristics which    0016-7061/84/$03.00    1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    102    are significant to root development. This paper addresses two of these  characteristics: pore geometry and resistance of the soil matrix to deforma-  tion. The objective of this report is to introduce new developments in  methodology for measuring these characteristics and to illustrate their  sensitivity to factors such as tillage, freeze/thaw and cropping history.    APPROACH    Of the various approaches used to characterize soil structure, none alone  "indicates directly the ease with which fine pores can be enlarged, or the  continuity of channels which are freely accessible to plant roots" (Russell  and Goss, 1974). A combined examination of pore geometry and resistance  to deformation is a juxtaposition of measurements which may provide a  closer picture of what plant roots "see".    Pore geometry    The concept of assessing pore geometry by means of air permeability  measurements is well-known (cf. Hillel, 1980, p. 281). Buehrer (1932)  deals extensively with the methodology and the interpretation of the results  in terms of soil structure. Kirkham (1946) deals with the theory and discus-  ses the experimental conditions. Janse and Bolt (1960) elaborate on the  merits of air permeability measurements. Ball et al. (1981) used air per-  meability measurements in conjunction with gas diffusion measurements  to characterize the geometry of the air-filled porosity, in particular as  affected by different tillage treatments. Ball (1981a, b) employed increasing-  ly complex geometric models in order to calculate air permeabilities and  diffusivities.  In view of our concern with structural requirements for potential root  growth, we wish to examine the geometry of only that part of the pore  body in which unobstructed root growth can take place. We therefore  consider only those pore spaces which have an effective diameter larger than  a chosen root diameter.    Resistance to deformation    Plants in the field, however, cannot be assured of unobstructed root  growth. Whenever the growing root is confronted with pores that do not  have the right geometry, the root will exert pressure on the matrix of the  soft in order to rearrange the pore space. The soil matrix will resist this  rearrangement (Barley, 1962).  Methodology to characterize the resistance of the soil matrix to de-  formation by a growing root should take into account as many of the unique  features of root development as possible. These include: root size, a lubri-  cation system, an ability to develop both axial and radial pressures, velocity  of root tip advancement, and perhaps most significantly an ability to seek out    103    pores of appropriate size and resistance to deformation.  A penetrating probe is the normal tool used to characterize resistance  to deformation. The mechanical behaviour of the soil around a penetrating  probe is rather complicated. In the immediate vicinity of the probe the soil  is subject to plastic failure and further away the soil is subject to elastic  compression (cf. Farrell and Greacen, 1966). Therefore, it seems mandatory,  in order to simulate root penetration, that the diameter of the probe ap-  proximates the diameter of the growing root as closely as possible. Fine  probes, ranging from 1770 to 5140 pm in diameter, were used by Taylor  and Gardner (1963), Barley et al. (1965), Waldron and Constantin (1970),  Bradford et al. (1971), Voorhees et al. (1975) and Bradford (1980). In  order to approach the diameter of a growing root tip even closer, we used  a 150-~m-diameter probe.  The possibility of introducing a lubrication system or of having both  axial and radial expansion as suggested by, for example, Abdalla et al.  (1969) is limited when a probe diameter of 150 ~m is considered. Evidence  suggests, however, that these factors are important and should be considered  if future penetrometers are being designed to simulate root growth (Russell  and Goss, 1974; Mulqueen et al., 1977; Whiteley and Dexter, 1981).  No consensus exists on the influence of rate of advancement on penetro-  meter resistance (Thomas, 1965; Eavis, 1967; Cockroft et al., 1969; Brad-  ford et al., 1971; Gerard et al., 1972; Voorhees et al., 1975; Bradford,  1980; Whiteley et al., 1981). In view of the conflicting evidence in the  literature, in this investigation the rate was arbitrarily fixed at approxima-  tely 10 cm/h.  A penetrometer with the same dimensions as a growing root, which  is also flexible and capable of seeking out pores of the appropriate size  and resistance to deformation, is not readily conceived. Such a requirement  may not be necessary, however, if tip pressures can be measured to deter-  mine the probability of encountering zones which are readily penetrable.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    In 1978 a crop rotation experiment was started on a Gleyed Melanic  Brunisol (or Aquic Eutrochrept) which had a silt loam texture in the plough  layer. Prior to the experiment the field had been in brome grass for eleven  years. A randomized complete block design  was established with four  replications planted in corn (indicated as C-plots) and four replications  planted in a mixture of brome grass and alfalfa (indicated as BA-plots).  In November 1980 all plots were plowed and in May 1981, and following  years, all plots were planted in corn.    Air permeability measurements    Air permeability measurements were made on samples obtained from  the plots in:    104    Sept. '80 (before plowing; forages and corn still standing)  Nov. '80 (two weeks after plowing; before winter freeze-up)  April '81 (after thaw and before tillage); June '81 (after tillage and plant-  ing; corn at 6--7th leaf stage)  Sept. '81 (before plowing; corn still standing)  Nov. '81 (two weeks after plowing; before winter freeze-up)  April '82 (after thaw); June '82 (after tillage and planting; corn at 5th  leaf stage)  July '82 (middle of growing season)  Nov. '82 (two weeks after plowing; before winter freeze-up).  At each sampling time up to Nov. '81, four undisturbed cores per rep-  hcation were taken from each of the two rotations. Starting in April '82  the number of cores from each replication was increased from four to  eight. A few samples were rejected in the lab because of mechanical failure  induced by handling;the total number of samples per treatment used in the  calculations is included in Tables I and II when different from 16 or 32.    TABLE I    Average air permeability, /~, and average air-filled porosity, fa, at different times for brome/alfalfa  (BA-plots) and continuous corn (C-plots)    Sampling             /~                                     f-a  time       (cm3 air X cm-2 bulk X s-1)                    (cm3 air cm-3 bulk)    BA-plots       C-plots        SED* i         BA-plots       C-plots        SED* l    Sept.'80   0.434(n=14)  0.218(n=14)  0.111(d)      0.128(n=14)  0.124(n=14)  0.019(NS)  Nov. '80   3.544        2.523        0.493(d)     0.294        0.243        0.025(d)  Apr. '81   1.905(n=15)  1.213       0.115(a)     0.231(n=15)  0.178        0.009(b)  June '81   0.741          0.260          0.255(d)       0.184          0.104          0.026(NS)  Sept.'81   0.697          0.547          0.276(NS)     0.128          0.112          0.017(NS)  Nov. '81   1.475          0.781          0.139(b)       0.174          0.133          0.013(c)  Apr. '82   1.667        0.783        0.261(c)      0.196        0.141         0.023(c)  June '82   0.625(n=31)   0.419          0.231(NS)     0.146(n=Sl)   0.132          0.012(NS)  July '82   0.438         0.242         0.145(d)      0.125         0.110         0.014(NS)  Nov. '82   2.937         1.370         0.428(b)      0.182         0.120         0.O19(b)    * ISED: standard error of the mean difference between the BA-plots and C-plots = +(2 s2/n)s; where  s2 is the block treatment mean square with 3 d.f. and n = number of samples per treatment. (a),  (b), (c), (d): mean difference between BA-plots and C-plots significant at the 0.01, 0.05, 0.1 and 0.2  probability levels, respectively: (NS): mean difference not significant at the 0.2 probability level.    The cores were 5 cm in diameter and 5 cm long, taken from 5 to 10  cm below the soil surface. In spite of the fact that the cores were fairly  small, it was felt that all but the very largest cracks were sampled adequately.  The samples were saturated and subsequently equilibrated at 50 cm water  suction. This suction, S, corresponds to an effective pore diameter, de, of  60 pm, according to de (cm) = 0.3/S. This value was chosen because the  smallest diameter of a growing corn root tip was assumed to be 60 ~m.  Air permeability coefficients, K, were measured by the constant head  method (Tanner and Wengel, 1957) and calculated from:    105    F= K Ah/L  where F is the measured flux of air (cm3air cm-2bulk sec-1), Ah is the air  pressure difference (cm H20) over the soil sample, which was kept constant  at 14 cm H20 pressure, and L is the length of the soil sample (5 cm).  After the air permeability measurements, the water content of each  soil core was determined. The air filled porosity, fa, was then calculated from  the water content and the bulk density, assuming a particle density of  2.65 g cm-3.    TABLE II  Average values of K_/fa and K/f~ at different points in time; (averages based on calculations for each  core, not on I~ and fa values)    Sampling              (K/fa)                                K/(10 f~)  time                    (cm bulk X s-I)                       (cm-3 air cm4 bulk X s-l)    BA-plots       C-plots        SED* 1         BA-plots       Coplots        SED.1    Sept.'80   3.32(n=14)  1.67(n=14)   0.975(NS)    26.3(n=14)   19.2(n=14)    7.25(NS)  Nov. '80  11.93        9.84         2.07S(NS)    41.3         40.7          9.49(NS)  Apr. '81    8.10(n=15)  6.36         0.898(d)     36.1(n=15)   34.6          7.42(NS)  June '81    5.09        1.68         1.753(d)     41.5         12.7         18.81 (NS)  Sept.'81    5.70        3.12         2.751(NS)    60.0         19.6         37.72(NS)  Nov. '81    9.15        4.75          1.861(c)      66.8          34.8          22.98(NS)  Apr. '82   8.18       4.60         0.943(b)     44.1         29.7          2.19(a)  June '82    3.33(n=31)  2.41           1.060(NS)     19.3(n=31)    14.5            4.64(NS)  July '82    2.72         1.62          0.698(NS)     19.3          13.5            3.67(NS)  Nov. '82   15.22         8.56          2.762(c)      52.8          60.4          20.77(NS)    *ISED: standard error of the mean difference between the BA-plots and C-plots = +(2 s2/n)s; where  s2 is the block X treatment mean square with 3 d.f. and n = number of samples per treatment. (a),  (h), (c), (d): mean difference between BA-plots and C-plots significant at the 0.01, 0.05, 0.1 and 0.2  probability levels, respectively; (NS): mean difference not significant at the 0.2 probability level.    Penetration measurements    Penetrability measurements were made on one undisturbed soil core  per replicate. These cores were taken in the summer of 1981 from each of  the two rotations. The cores were 5 cm in diameter and 2.5 cm long, taken  from 5 to 7.5 cm below the soil surface. The cores were saturated and  subsequently equilibrated at 50 cm water suction. Soil moisture is known to  influence penetrometer resistance; however, because the penetration process  is so time~onsuming, it was decided that measurements would be taken at  50 cm water suction only. Presumably, if the method is sensitive to manage-  ment practices, it should be able to detect differences over a range of soil  moisture suctions. Each core was penetrated 14 times at different locations  in a grid pattern. The probe was a right circular cylinder with a diameter  of 150 ~m. It was driven into the soil at a constant velocity of 9.4 cm h-1  to a depth of i cm. The resistance to penetration was measured continuously  by a strain gauge and recorded on a strip chart. A schematic drawing of the  set-up is presented in Fig. 1.    106  I Motor driven I  Nee~  Penet~  [~  Strain  G  auge    :     Power  Supply  Amplifier @=~  and Recorder~    Fig. 1. Schematic drawing of the micro-penetrometer system.    RESULTS    Air-filled porosity and air permeability    The results from the measurements of the air-filled porosity and the  air permeability at 50 cm water suction are presented in Table I. The re-  ported values of fa and ~: are the averages of 16 cores (Sept. '80 to Nov.  '81), or 32 cores (April '82 to Nov. '82), except where indicated otherwise.  The average values of K/fa and K/fa2 were also calculated (Table II).  These values are based on calculations for each core separately (they cannot  be calculated directly from the g and fa values in Table I). The rationale  for these calculations will be presented when the data are discussed.  McIntyre and Tanner (1959) recommend that, because air permeability  data usually have skewed populations, they should either be log-transformed  before parametric analysis of variance or be analyzed by nonparametric  techniques (e.g. the Mann-Whitney U Test), which avoid population as-  sumptions. Log-transformation and square-root-transformation could not  normalize all data sets. The parametric analysis of variance (t-test) was  therefore performed using untransformed data and the results were com-  pared with those of the nonparametric Mann-Whitney U Test. The two  tests agreed. Therefore, we report in Tables I and II only the results of  the more stringent parametric analysis.    Penetration resistance    Each penetration produced a graph of total resistance as a function of  depth of penetration (Fig. 2). The trend toward a continual increase in  total resistance with depth was typical. A similar trend was found when the  soil core was penetrated from the bottom upward. This indicated that of  the two component resistances encountered by the probe, the tip resistance  and the sliding friction along the shaft, the latter must have accounted for  a large portion of the total resistance. We were interested only in the tip    107    resistance. We now wish to define in general the "Percentage Linear Pene-  trability", PLP, as the percentage of a linear trajectory through the soil,  for which the actual tip resistance is lower than a set critical value. Ex-  perimentally the tip resistance may be obtained by subtracting the frictional  resistance from the measured total resistance. In the present case the fric-  tional resistance was estimated by assuming first that it increased linearly  with depth of penetration and second that the probe encountered no tip  resistance at some point where it entered a void. The tip resistance is then  expressed by the difference between the total and frictional resistance lines  in Fig. 2.    ca  uJ 3J  r.c  3  wuJ 2.0.  tr  ca 1.5-  n  ~__ 1.0-  0.7-  0.5-  0.3"  !-'-  II  Z  _o  I..-  rr  F.-  ul  Z  ul  0..  J  I--  Z  _o  t-  O  rr"  U_                  Total      ~5.o        Resistance Line  ~zri?t i ?,p ?~    10.0    ,6.2  5.0    '3.0  .2.0    rl  uJ  O  z  ,&lt;  09  uJ  rr  _1  ,&lt;  I-  o  I--    1.0    i          i          i          i      0  018     o.'s     o14     o.2     o  DEPTH OF PENETRATION  (cm)  i    Fig. 2. Recorder output trace for a sample needle penetration, with the total and tip  resistances (MPa) as a function of the depth of penetration (crn).    For different arbitrarily chosen values of tip resistance, (0.1, 0.2, 0.3,  0.5, 0.7, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0 and 5.0 MPa), the portion of the I cm penetration  depth for which the actual tip resistance was less than the chosen value  was determined. This was done by measuring the parts of the chosen line  located above the actual tip resistance and expressing the sum as a per-  centage of the total depth of penetration. The thickened parts of the 2.0  MPa line in Fig. 2 represent this portion for a chosen value of 2.0 MPa tip  resistance. In this case the PLP is about 60%.    108    PLP values for different chosen tip resistances for one soil core are plotted  in Fig. 3. The solid line is drawn through the average values of all 14 pene-  trations. This graph can be used in the following ways.  (1) If we choose 1.0 MPa tip resistance as a critical value, Fig. 3 shows  that 70% of the 1 cm linear depth of this core is penetrable. This PLP  can be plotted versus the bulk density, BD, of that core (cf. Fig. 4: BD =    100-.    80-  7    60-  ,~  40-  7   20  0  0.1         0.2    0.3      0.5   0.7   1.0    1.5  2.0    3.0      5.0  TIP PRESSURE (MPa)  Fig. 3. Percentage linear penetrability for a sample soil core as a function of critical  tip pressure values (MPa).    W  ~- 60  I-  &gt;-  I-  J   4O  II  I-  w  Z  uJ  D_  rr  20  W  Z  .J                                            r--  Corn c--,o  - 0.996  ~,~.~ o~   Brome/Alfalfa ,~,,,,,~  - 0.966  \    i      1  110   '   112   '   1.4       116   '   1.8  BD ( 9 /Cm3 )    Fig. 4. The percentage linear penetrability at 1.0 MPa critical tip pressure as a function  of the bulk density (g/cm3) for the two soils.    109    1.13 g cm-3, and PLP = 70%). A similar point can be found for each of the  eight cores analysed; these eight points are plotted in Fig. 4.  (2) If we choose 30% penetrability as a critical minimum value of PLP  required for root growth, then Fig. 3 predicts that the root must be able  to exert a tip pressure of about 0.36 MPa. The relationship between the  required tip pressure and BD is plotted in Fig. 5 using the points for 30%  penetrability from each of the eight cores analysed. A value of 30% for the  required minimum PLP to accommodate root growth may seem rather low.  As pointed out by Boone and Kuipers (1970), however, "only a minor part  of the soil needs to be in a favourable state for root development".    1.2-    il  //  //  Corn  BromelAIfalfa ~--,~    1.0  &gt;-  ._J  cr  t-  ILl  z 0.8  LU  rr  ~C  I, JJ  Z  0.6  o~  I.--  Q.  ~ 0.4  u.l  o9  W  o. 0.2  (3.  I--    ~.0       C2   '   1~4   '   1.6  BD (9/crn3)    Fig. 5. Tip pressure (MPa) required to have 30% linear penetrability as a function of  soil bulk density (g/cm3).    Linear regression of the data points presented in Fig. 4 showed a strong  relationship between PLP and BD. For the C-cores, r2 = 0.992 and for  the BA-cores, r2 = 0.933. The slopes of the two lines (-121.49 for C and  -121.61 for BA) are nearly equal; covariance analysis showed that they are  not significantly different (F = 0.000027; df = 1,4). The intercepts of the  two lines, however, are significantly different at the 5% probability level  (F = 14.10; df = 1,5).    110    DISCUSSION    Air-filled porosity and air permeability    Table I shows that the g: and fa values were consistently higher for the  BA-plots. Due to the large variability, however, less than half the differences  were significant at P = 0.10. Significances at the P = 0.20 level were in-  dicated solely for illustrating trends. The differences tended to be greatest  in November after ploughing and in April subsequent to thawing. It appears  that the effect of the cropping history on the above physical properties  lasted for more than two years after the initiation of identical management.  The magnitude of K is influenced by the magnitude of fa, as well as by  the size distribution, the continuity and the tortuosity of the air-filled pores.  It is of interest to investigate whether differences in K values can be at-  tributed solely to differences in air-filled porosity or whether they should  be attributed, in part, to the other geometrical aspects of the air-filled  pore space. We can isolate such differences by dividing K either by fa or by  fa2. One would expect values of K/fa not to be different only when differ-  ences in air-filled pore space are made up of pores with the same size dis-  tribution and continuity, because then each additional amount of geo-  metrically similar air-filled pore space will contribute proportionally to K.  Therefore, division of K by fa for each core should remove this proportional  effect. If, on the other hand, the difference in air-filled pore space is due to  changes in the sizes of all pores, with pore continuity remaining the same,  then, according to Poiseuille's law, values of K/fa2 should not be different. If,  however, the continuity of pores is affected by management, differences  in K cannot be assessed on the basis of differences in fa only.  Several of the K/fa values in Table II are different for the two manage-  ment practices, although the levels of significance are lower than for the g  values. This suggests that the larger R values observed on the BA-plots  probably did not arise from increased porosity at constant pore size dis-  tribution and continuity.  The K/fa2 values show no statistically significant differences with the  exception of April '82. This suggests that the differences in K could be  explained by uniformly larger pores in the BA-plots, assuming equal pore  continuity. Pore size distribution data are presented in Table III. The air-  filled porosity was subdivided into two classes: larger pores (de &gt; 250 #m)  and smaller pores (250 #m &gt; de &gt; 60 gm). The percentages in these classes  were calculated from the moisture contents at saturation and at 12 cm  and 50 cm suction. In general, the porosities in both classes were greater for  the BA-plots than for the C-plots.  For the particular soil they studied, Hamblin and Tennant (1981) found  that the graph of log K versus water content was linear with the intercept  a function of tillage condition. They pointed out, however, that "in other  softs with more strongly developed ped structures and hysteresic behaviour,    111    no general relationship between water content and Kair necessarily occurs".  It is physically more plausible to plot log K versus fa instead of water con-  tent. Doing so we found that the regression lines for the two treatments  were not significantly different, but that most data points for the two  treatments occupied distinctly separate parts of that regression line. Because  regression analysis does not describe the distribution of points along the  line, neither the intercept nor the slope of the regression line were useful  to describe the responses of the soil to the two treatments.    TABLE III    Pore size distributions at different points in time; the data for 1981 are the averages of 16  separate soil cores (not those for which fa and K were determined); the data for 1982  are the averages for the 32 cores for which fa and K were determined    Sampling  time    Pores &gt; 250 #m diam.    Pores 60--250 ~m diam.    BA        CORN    SED*'        BA      CORN  SED.I    Apr. '81  14.33%  11.40%  1.88(NS)   7.40%  5.53%  0.62(c)  June '81   5.82     5.62    0.88(NS)   6.55    5.65    1.06(NS)  Nov. '81  10.94    7.39   1.90(d)    5.07   4.43   0.50(d)  Apr. '82  11.72    7.95   2.03(c)    7.86   6.17   1.30(d)  July '82  6.51    6.09   0.92(NS)   5.94   4.89   1.23(NS)    * ISee Table If.    Penetrability    The resistance to penetration is due to two factors: (1)the incompres-  sibility of primary soil particles, resulting in an inverse proportionality be-  tween resistance and dry bulk density and (2) the friction between primary  particles and aggregates during relative movement. The distinction between  these two components was made by Wiersum (1957) and by Aubertin and  Kardos (1965).  The penetrability data show that a higher BD resulted in a lower per-  centage penetrability at a certain tip pressure (Fig. 4) and in a higher re-  quired percentage penetrability (Fig. 5). The intercept of the lines in Fig. 4  is likely determined by the structural strength of the soil. One may argue  that, at equal BD, greater aggregate strength results in a lower percentage  penetrability at a certain critical tip pressure. This leads to the conclusion  that the C-plots had a lower aggregate strength (for aggregates ~&gt; 150/~m  diameter). Fig. 4 shows that at any BD value the PLP at 1.0 MPa tip pressure  was 11% higher for the C-plots than for the BA-plots (vertical distance be-  tween the two regression lines). Similarly, at equal PLP the BD was 0.10  g/cm3 higher for the C-plots than for the BA-plots (horizontal distance  between the regression lines). The average BD of the four C-cores was 1.39    112    g/cm3; for the BA-cores the value was 1.33 g/cm3. The average percentage  linear penetrability at 1.0 MPa tip pressure was 47% for the C-plots and  44% for the BA-plots. This suggests that the difference in PLP, which may be  expected from the difference in BD, was slightly overcompensated by the  aggregate strength effect. This result indicates that soil management influen-  ces the strength of "macro-aggregates" (&gt; 150 gm). Tisdall and Oades  {1982) found that the stability of macro-aggregates (&gt; 250 gm) is also  influenced by management. Because sampling was performed only once,  the strength data represent a limited picture of the soil strength character-  istics during the growing season.    CONCLUSIONS    The variability in the K data indicated that replication needed to be  approximately doubled in order to detect a statistically significant treat-  ment difference. Despite the large variability in the K data, four of the ten  sampling dates indicated that there was a treatment difference; another  four of the ten dates showed a consistent trend which was significant at the  P &lt; 0.20 level and only two of the ten dates indicated that no treatment  difference existed.  Calculation of K/fa and K/~a ratios appears to be a useful technique for  determining whether differences in K can be attributed solely to differences  in fa or whether they should be attributed to other geometrical aspects of  the air-filled pore body such as pore size distribution, tortuosity and con-  tinuity. Our results indicate that, assuming equal pore continuity between  treatments, the brome--alfalfa treatment seemed to stabilize and maintain  uniformly larger pore sizes than the corn treatment. No explanation is of-  fered for the apparently inconsistent result in the April '82 data. The im-  plication for potential root growth is that the treatment which creates a  soil matrix with a uniformly larger pore size distribution and equal con-  tinuity will offer the greater potential for unobstructed root growth.  The micropenetrometer provides information about soil strength at the  same scale roots may "see" it. The PLP analysis was considered particularly  useful to assess the importance of bulk density on potential root growth.  Average PLP values showed little difference between the two sets of plots:  the PLP at 1.0 MPa tip pressure for the C-plots was 47% and for the BA-  plots 44%. When the PLP of each soil core, on the other hand, was plotted  as a function of the bulk density, two significantly different lines occurred.  The slopes of these lines were equal but the intercepts were significantly  different. Inasmuch as the intercept of the "corn"-line was higher, one  may deduce that the soil with the corn history had a lower macro-aggregate  strength. With respect to the average PLP of the BA-plots, the average  PLP of the C-plots was 11% higher due to lower aggregate strength (dif-  ference in intercept) and 8% (= -121.5 0.064) lower due to higher BD,  resulting in a net gain of 3%. One may now speculate as to the relative im-    113    portance of the two components. It could be argued that root penetration  is hampered more by higher bulk density than by greater aggregate strength,  because roots need not follow linear pathways and can grow around strong  aggregates. If this is the case, one may conclude that because of the lower  BD values in the BA-plots, growing roots could face fewer obstructions in  the BA-plots than in the C-plots.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We thank Dr. R.W. Sheard for the opportunity to sample his rotation  plots and Dr. O.B. Allen, Mr. F.J. Leij and Mr. R.G. Donald for their as-  sistance with the calculations and statistical analyses.  Financial support is acknowledged from the Natural Sciences and En-  gineering Research Council of Canada.    REFERENCES    Abdalla, A.M., Hettiarachi, D.R_P. and Reece, A.R., 1969. The mechanics of root growth  in granular media. J. Agric. Eng. Res., 14: 236--248.  Aubertin, G2. and Kardos, L.T., 1965. Root growth through porous media under  controlled conditions, I. Effect of pore size and rigidity. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  29: 290--293.  Ball, B.C., 1981a. Modelling of soil pores as tubes using gas perrneabilities, gas diffusivities  and water release. J. Soil Sci., 32: 465--481.  Ball, B.C., 1981b. Pore characteristics of soils from two cultivation experiments as shown  by gas diffusivities and permeabilities and air-filled porosities. J. Soil Sci., 32: 483--  498.  Ball, B.C., Harris, W. and Burford, J.R., 1981. A laboratory method to measure gas  diffusion and flow in soil and other porous materials. J. Soil Sci,, 32: 323--333.  Barley, K.P., 1962. The effects of mechanical stress on the growth of roots. J. Exp.  Bot., 13: 95--110.  Barley, K.P., Farrell, D.A. and Greacen, E.L., 1965. The influence of soil strength on the  penetration of a loam by plant roots. Aust. J. Soil Res., 3: 69--79.  Boone, F.R. and Kuipers, H., 1970. Remarks on soil structure in relation to zero-tillage.  Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 18: 262--269.  Bradford, J.M., 1980. The penetration resistance in a soil with well-defined structural  units. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 601--606.  Bradford, J.M., Farrell, D.A. and Larson, W.E., 1971. Effect of soil overburden pressure  on penetration of fine metal probes. Soil. Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 12--15.  Buehrer, T.F., 1932. The movement of gases through the soil as a criterion of soil struc-  ture. Ariz. Agric. Exp. Station, Tech. Bull., 39, 57 pp.  Cockroft, B., Barley, K_P. and Grescen, E.L., 1969. The penetration of clays by fine  probes and root tips. Aust. J. Soil Res., 7: 333--348.  Eavis, B.W., 1967. Mechanical impedance and root growth. Proc. Agric. Eng. Symp.,  Silsoe, England, pp. 1--11.  Farrell, D.A. and Greacen, E.L., 1966. Resistance to penetration of fine probes in com-  pressible soil. Aust. J. Soil Res., 4: 1--17.  Gerard, G.J., Mehta, H.C. and Hinojosa, E., 1972. Root growth in a clay soil. Soil Sci.,  114: 37--49.    114    Hamblin, A.P. and Tennant, D., 1981. The influence of tillage on soil water behaviour.  Soil Sci., 132: 233--239.  Hillel, D., 1980. Fundamentals of Soil Physics. Academic Press, New York, N.Y., 413 pp.  Janse, A.R-P. and Bolt, G.H., 1960. The determination of the air-permeability of soils.  Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 8: 124--131.  Kirkham, D., 1946. Field method for determination of air permeability of soil in its  undisturbed state. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 11: 93--99.  Mclntyre, D.S. and Tanner, C.B., 1959. Abnormally distributed soil physical measure-  ments and nonparametric statistics. Soil Sci., 88: 133--137.  Mulqueen, J., Stafford, J.V. and Tanner, D.W., 1977. Evaluation of penetrometers for  measuring soil strength. J. Terramech., 14: 137--151.  Russell, R.S. and Goss, M.J. 1974. Physical aspects of soil fertility -- The response of  roots to mechanical impedance. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 22: 305--318.  Tanner, C.B. and Wengel, R.W., 1957. An air permeameter for field and laboratory use.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 21: 663--664.  Taylor, H.M. and Gardner, H.R., 1963. Penetration of cotton seedling taproots as in-  fluenced by bulk density, moisture content, and strength of soil. Soil Sci., 96: 153--  156.  Thomas, D., 1965. Static penetration tests in London clay. Geotechnique, 15: 174--  180.  Tisdall, J.M. and Oades, J_M., 1982. Organic matter and waterstable aggregates in soil.  J. Soil Sci., 33: 141--163.  Voorhees, W.B., Farrell, D.A. and Larson, W.E., 1975. Soil strength and aeration effects  on root elongation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 948--953.  Waidron, L.J. and Constantin, G.K., 1970. Soil resistance to a slowly moving penetro-  meter. Soil Sci., 109: 221--226.  Whiteley, G_M. and Dexter, A.R., 1981. The dependence of soil penetrometer pressure  on penetrometer size. J. Agric. Eng. Res., 26: 467--476.  Whiteley, G~I., Utomo, W.H. and Dexter, A.R., 1981. A comparison of penetrometer  pressure and the pressure exerted by roots. Plant Soil, 61 : 351--364.  Wiersum, L.K., 1957. The relationship of the size and structural rigidity of pores to  their penetration by roots. Plant Soil, 9: 75--85.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractThe potential suitability of a soil to accommodate growing roots was assessed on the basis of: (1) the existing pore space available for unobstructed root growth; and (2) the obstruction offered to a growing root by the soil matrix. The former was evaluated by measuring the air permeability of undisturbed soil cores, equilibrated at a chosen water tension. The latter was evaluated by measuring the spectrum of the tip resistance encountered by a slowly penetrating fine probe.The influence of cropping history on this potential suitability was examined by comparing the same soil with two different cropping sequences (corn grown continuously for five years and forages grown for three years followed by two years of corn). Measurements were started shortly before the forages were plowed under.Air permeabilities were higher for the plots on which forages had been grown, indicating greater potential suitability for unobstructed root growth. The penetration experiments showed that the average resistance to deformation of root-sized pores was equal for the two cropping patterns. The average bulk density was higher in the continuous corn plots than in the plots on which forages had been grown. After analysis of our data we postulated that the effect of the higher bulk density was offset by lower aggregate strength in the continuous corn plots. Implications of this hypothesis are discussed.