Geoderma, 33 (1984) 101--118                                                  101  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    EFFECTS OF ACIDIC AND BASIC PARENT MATERIALS ON  FORMATION OF SOME SOILS IN QUEBEC (CANADA)*    C.R. DE KIMPE1, M.R. LAVERDIEREl, J. DEJOU~ and P. LASALLE3   Agriculture Canada, Station de Recherches, 2560, boul. Hochelaga, Sainte-Foy, Quebec  GIV 2J3 (Canada)  ~ INRA, Station d'Agronomie, 12 Av. de l'Agriculture, 63039 Clermont-Ferrand Cedex  (France)  3 Minist$re de l'Energie et des Ressources, Gouvernement du Qudbec, 1620, boul. de  l'Entente, Sainte-Foy, Quebec G1 V 4N6 (Canada)  (Received June 8, 1983; accepted after revision December 29, 1983)    ABSTRACT    De Kimpe, C.R., Laverdi~re, M.R., Dejou, J. and Lasalle, P., 1984. Effects of acidic and  basic parent materials on formation of some soils in Quebec (Canada). Geoderma,  33: 101--118.    Five profiles developed on basic or acidic parent materials were sampled in southern  Quebec, Canada. Physical, chemical and mineralogical properties were determined. Among  the three profiles developed on basic parent materials, one formed in disaggregated  metabasalt whereas the two others developed in preglacial saprolites derived from the  metabasalt, as indicated by till cover in a nearby area. In the lower part of the latter  profiles, the saprolites had a loamy texture and the mineralogical plus chemical data  indicated very slight changes with respect to the metabasalt. In these profiles, CBD-  extractable Fe content was &gt; 1% in most horizons, and the pyrophosphate-extractable  Fe was generally higher in the Ah than in the B horizons. In the profiles developed on  acidic till, CBD-extractable Fe was &gt; 1% only in the B horizons, which also contained  the maximum of pyrophosphate~extractable Fe. In the latter profiles, free Fe and A1  sesquioxides were associated with the clay fractions whereas in the former profiles, one  third of the Fe came from the sand and silt fractions.  Chlorite was the dominant phyllosilicate in the basic material and it was transformed  into interstratified minerals and smectite. Several hypotheses about smectite formation  and distribution were discussed. In the profiles developed on acidic till, illite and chlorite  were the major phyUosilicates and, through weathering, transformed into interstratified  minerals, vermiculite and smectite.  Major differences in the properties of the profiles developed on the two parent mate-  rials were not reflected by current soil classification.    INTRODUCTION    The effect of parent material on soil genesis and properties has been recog-  nized for a long time. It is, however, the interrelation between parent material  and the climatic factors that will determine, among other characteristics,    "* Contribution Nr. 240    0016-7061/84/$03.00    1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    102    the texture, the depth of weathering, the mineralogical transformations,  the base saturation and the potential fertility in the resulting soil profile  (Simonson, 1959). Better understanding of this interaction in limited areas  may thus contribute to improve our knowledge on soil formation processes  and to develop evolution concepts for soils in a broader region.  In Quebec, the widespread occurrence of acidic to neutral parent materials  (Clayton et al., 1977) led many workers to study the genesis of podzolic  soils. The concepts of formation of these soils have been summarized by  McKeague et al. (1978) and of Spodosols by McKeague et al. (1983). On  the contrary, few studies were devoted to soil formation on basic materials  in Quebec (De Kimpe and Zizka, 1973; De Kimpe et al., 1973). Soil forma-  tion on serpentinitic and mafic materials was described in Maryland (Cleaves  et al., 1974; Rabenhorst and Foss, 1981; Rabenhorst et al., 1982), thus  under a climatic environment different from that prevailing in the Appa-  lachian Highlands.  In order to determine the influence of contrasting parent materials on the  reactions which occur during horizon differentiation, it is more appropriate  to establish these relations in a limited area. The effects of basic and acidic  parent materials on the development of soil profiles in a small area of south-  ern Quebec are thus of interest and are presented in this report.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Site location and parent materials    The sampling area was located in the Appalachian Highlands, 125 km  east of Montreal, Quebec, approximately 457'N and 725'W, near  Lake Orford (Fig. 1). The dominant vegetation consisted of deciduous  trees, mainly maple and beech, with few conifers. The elevation at the  sampling sites was approximately 300 m and the annual precipitation about  1000 mm, with a mean annual temperature of 5.6. In this area, volcanic  rocks (basalt) on the eastern slopes of Mounts Orford and Chagnon were  metamorphosed into metabasalts (De RSmer, 1958; St-Julien, 1963) and  these were later transformed partly into saprolites. During the Wisconsinian  glaciation, the ice flowing towards the southeast (McDonald and Shilts,  1971) eroded the area and till derived from Cambrian and Ordovician shales  and sandstone (St-Julien, 1963) was deposited over most of the region  (Lasalle, 1983). Different parent materials were therefore exposed to post-  glacial weathering.    Soil profiles and methods    Profiles. Sampling sites were selected in order to provide a sequence from  basic to acidic parent materials: sites 1 and 2 were located on the north  aspect of a hill where no till was present. Site 1 was near the top of the hill    103    Fig. 1. Topographic map (1 : 50000) of Lake Orford area showing the sampling sites.  Basal grid: 1 km and elevation in feet,    whereas site 2 was located lower on the slope. Site 3 was in the saprolite  adjacent to a till deposit. Site 4 was located in the till near site 3 where  depth to saprolite was 1.0 m. Site 5 was located in the till on a south aspect  and metabasalt was present at a depth of about 1.2 m.  At each site, sampling was made according to horizons. Descriptions  of profiles 3 and 5 follow terminology from Canada Soil Survey Committee  (1978):    104    Site 3 on saprolite  Ah  (0--5 cm) Dark brown (10YR 3/3 m), light yellowish brown (10YR  6/4 d) silty loam; fine granular; loose; abundant medium to fine roots:  some gravel; smooth boundary; pH (H20) 4.8.  Bfl  (5--25 cm) Dark yellowish brown (10YR 4/4 m), light yellowish brown  (2.5Y 6/4 d) silty loam; medium granular; friable; plentiful fine roots;  some gravel; diffuse boundary; pH (H20) 5.0.  Bf~  (25--70 cm) Yellowish brown (10YR 5/6 m), light yellowish brown  (2.5Y 6/4 d) silty loam; fine subangular blocky; firm; few roots; some  gravel; clear boundary; pH (H20) 5.2.  BC  (70--90 cm) Light olive brown (2.5Y 5/4 m), light yellowish brown  (2.5Y 6/4 d) silty loam; coarse subangular blocky; firm; slightly hard~  no roots; more gravel than above; diffuse boundary; pH (H20) 5.7.  C   (90--120 cm) Light olive brown (2.5Y 5/4 m), pale yellow (2.5Y 7/4 d)  silty loam; coarse subangular blocky; firm, hard; no roots; more gravel  than above; pH (H20) 6.0.  Metabasalt was observed at a depth of about 2.5 m.  Site 5 on till  Ahe (0--10 cm) Dark brown (7.5YR 3/2 m) grayish brown, (10YR 5/2 d)  loam; single grain to fine granular; many bleached grains (salt and  pepper effect); loose, very friable; abundant medium to fine roots;  clear boundary; pH (H20) 4.1.  Bfl  (10--35 cm) Dark yellowish brown (10YR 4/4 m), yellowish brown  (10YR 5/4 d) loam; fine granular; very friable, soft; plentiful roots;  gradual boundary; pH (H20) 4.6.  Bf2  (35--50 cm) Olive brown (2.5Y 4/4 m), light yellowish brown (2.5Y  6/4 d) loam; medium to fine granular; friable, slightly hard; some  gravel; few roots; diffuse boundary; pH (H20) 4.9.  C   (50--120 cm) Olive brown (2.5Y 4/4 m), pale olive (5Y 6/3 d) loam;  medium to coarse subangular blocky; firm, hard; some gravel; no roots;  pH (H20) 5.5.    Methods. Analytical methods were those described by McKeague (1978)  and they will be referred to by the appropriate index number: particle-size  analysis: pipette method (2.11); pH: 1:1 soil:water ratio {3.13) and in  0.01 M CaC12 (3.11); Fe and A1 oxides: extraction with citrate-bicarbonate-  dithionite, CBD (3.51), acid ammonium oxalate (3.52) and sodium pyro-  phosphate (3.53); cation exchange capacity: in 1 N NH4OAc (3.32); organic  carbon:wet oxidation (3.613). Munsell colors were taken on the &lt; 2-mm  fraction of each soil sample.  For the mineralogical analysis, the fine earth was treated with H202 only  to remove the organic matter. The soil suspension was then adjusted to  pH 9.5 with NaOH and shaken overnight. Sand was recovered by wet sieving,  clay was separated from silt by sedimentation and centrifugation, and  recovered by freeze-drying. Mineral identification was performed with a    105    Philips diffractometer (CoK~ radiation, 50kV, 15mA, lO/min) using Mg-  and K-saturated oriented specimens (5.22). Subsequently, clay subsamples  were treated with CBD (3.51) to remove the free sesquioxides and selected  samples were again analyzed by X-ray diffraction to complete mineral  identification.  Total chemical analyses of the &lt; 2-ram fractions were performed at the  Geology Department, University of Clermont-Ferrand, France.    TABLE I  Physical properties of the profiles    Horizon             Depth      Color         2-1    lm0.5  0.5--0.25  0.25--0.1   100--50  50--20  20--S   5--2  2--0.2  &lt;0.2  (cm)      (moist)        mm     ram       mm        mm       um     p m     um    um    pm     ~m  METABASALT    Site 1  Ah  Aej  Bm1  Bm2-BC  Site 2  Ah  BF  BC  C  Site 3  Ah  B?I  Bf2  BC  C    Site 4  LH+(Ahe)  Bhf  Bf  C  Site 5  Ahe  071  Bf2  C    0- 20   7.SYR 3/2       9.7      5.6      5.5      10.3  20- 45    2.SY  4/4       9.0     12.0     12.9      17.5  45- 68     IOYR 5/4       3.3      9.0     12.7      17.1  68+      2.5Y  5/4       8.7     15.3     15.6      17.5    O-   15           IOYR   4/4                4.1              4.}              3.9              11.1  15- 45     IOYR 5/6       5.9      5.5      4.2       6.1  45- 55    2.5Y  5/4       4.8      6.0      5.1       7.7  55+      2.5Y  5/4       9.2     10.7      7.9       8.3    O-  5     IOYR 3/3       1.7      1.1      1.6       4.3  5- 25     10YR 4/4       2.9      3.7      4.2       7.3  25- 70     IOYR 5/6       3.2      5.2      5.5       7.9  70- 90    2.5Y  5/4       3.0      4.9      4.8       6.4  90-120   2.5Y  5/4       ).1      4.9      5.6       8.8    ACIDIC MATERIAL    10-  0      5YR 2.5/I  n.d.*     n.d.     n.d.      n.d.  O-  5   7.5YR 3/2       2.3      3.1      4.G       9.2  5- 42   2.5Y  5/4       5.7      6.1      7.4      11.9  42- 80    2.5Y  4/2       6.3      7.1      9.3      15.5    O- 10   7.5YR 3/2       2.8      3.9      7.4      14.9  10m 35     IOYR 4/4       5.1      4.8      7.3      13.1  35- 50   2.5Y  4/4       6.7      5.4      B.1      14.4  50-120        2.5Y     4/4                5.9              5.8             8.5              15.5    8.2      7.5  17.4  10.0  15.8    10.0  8.9      6.6  13.1    6m7   8.2     5.1  10.9      6.7  16.0   B.O   8.8     7.5  8.B      6.6  11.2    5.5   5.7     5.1    6.G     17.0  23.8  12.8  13.1     3.1  6.5     15.5  24.0  13.5  15,0     3.8  11.1     27.0  21.1    9.7   5.3     2.2  7.2     14.6  1B.6  12.3   9.4     1.8    5.9     10.5  31.7  30.9   8.3     4.0  7.9     15.9  27.6  16.3  11.5     2.7  7.4     15.5  26.5  16.2  11.1     1.5  6.8     14.7  28.1  18.4  10.4     2.5  8.5     15.9  27.3  15.S   7.6     2.8    n.d.    n.d.  n.d.  n.d.  n.d.   n.d.  8m~     17.9  24.5  11.7  10.5     7.8  10.1     19.0  19.6  10.0   8.1     2.1  13.0     23.9  15.5   5.1    3.1     1.2    13.4     18.9  18.0   8.3   6.9     7.5  12.0     19,1   17.7   6.3   7.8     6.8  13.3     21.9  15.5   4.5   5.0     5.2  14.4     20.3  15.2   4.5   4.1     5.8    *  n.d.   r~t determined    106    RESULTS    Texture of the &lt; 2-mm material at site 1 was generally coarser than that  at sites 2 and 3 (Table I). Sand was the dominant fraction in the former  profile whereas silt was higher in the latter ones. In profile 1, gravel amounted  to more than 50% below 45 cm but generally to less than 10% at the corre-    TABLE II  Chemical properties of the profiles    Horizon    Extractable sesquioxides    In less than 2mm soil            In clay fraction  pH       Org. C     Fec8D  Feo  Fep  AIc80  A1o  Alp     Fec8D       AIcBD        Soil           Clsy  (O.01M    (~)      (~)   (~)  (~)   (~)   (~)  (~)    (~)       (~)    (meq/lOg g)  (meq/lO0 g)  CaCl2)    CEC    METABASALT    Site 1             4.83       11.4  Aej          5.14        0.7  ~1          5.17         1.2  8m2-8C        5.09        0.3  Site 2  Ah           4.22        4.7  BF       5.02     2.9  BC           5.06        0.5  C           5.39         1.0  Site 3             4.12       11.6  8fI          4.46        2.4  Bf2          4.63        1.3  8C           4.79        0.6  C           4.92        0.4    Site 4    ACIDIC MATERIAL    LH+(Ahe)     3.84     29.7  Bhf         3.66        6.2  BF           4.53        2.0  C           4.89        0.2    Site 5    Abe          3.40        3. I  BF1          4.03        3.2  8f2          4.32        1.7  C           4.66         1.8    3.2    2.1   1.1    0.5    0.5  0.2      12.3         1.8  1.1    0.8  0.3   0.2   0.2  0.1       7.3         1,3  1.8    1.3  0.6   0.3   0.3  0.2       5.6        1.1  1.3    0.8  0.2    0.1    0.1  0.1       5.4        0.7    2.2    1.4  0.6   0.5   0.5  0.4      10.0        2.4  2.8    1.9  0.7    1.0    1.0  0.6      10.9        3.6  0.7   0.5  0.2   0.2   0.2  0.1       4.2        1.5  1.3    1.0  0.6   0.3   0.4  0.2       9.2        2.2    1.7    1.6  1.0   0.4   0.5  0.4       9.4        2.9  1.8    1.4  0.6   0.8    1.1  0.8       6.9        3.8  1.7    1.3  0.5    0.6   0.8  0.5       6.1         2.7  1.1    1.0  0.2   0.3   0.4  0.2       3.5         1.2  0.9   0.9  0.2   0.2    0.3  0.1       3.2        O.R    0.8    0.4  0.3   0.1    0.1  0.1       nd         nd  1.9    1.2  0.9   0.2   0.2  0.2      10.5        1.4  1.3    0.8  0.5   0.8    1.1  0.5       7.3        4.8  0.7   0.3  0.1    0.1    0.2  0.1       2.6        0.8    0.8   0.3  0.3   0.1    D.1  0.1       5.3        0.5  2.3    1.8  1.5   0.6   O.B  0.4      17.0        3.0  1.0   0.7  0.5   0.6   0.7  0.4      10.3        4.8  0.7    0.4  0.1    0.1    0.2  0.1       4.4        0.7    58.5          40.5  11.2          23.8  11.5          24.0  6.2          21.1    28.7          27.1  23.7          20.4  7.8          21.8  18.1          31.8    49.0          58.0  19.5          47.0  14.0          45.1  13.6          41.3  12.5          43.9    107.0  33.7  15.2  2.7    17.0  20.0  11.5  3.8    nd  59.4  46.2  27.7    81.2  36.3  24.5  22.3    nd = not determined  tr = traces    107    sponding depth in profiles 2 and 3. Profiles 4 and 5 were loamy in texture,  and were especially high in particles in the diameter range of 250 to 5 #m.  The pH values, measured in 0.01 M CaCI2 were lower than 4.0 in profiles  3, 4 and 5 and also in the surface horizons of profiles 1 and 2 (Table II).  The organic carbon content generally decreased with depth but secondary  maxima were observed in some Bm and Bf horizons.  The amounts of citrate--bicarbonate--dithionite (CBD)-- and oxalate  (O)--extractable Fe generally exceeded 1% in the samples from profiles 1--3,  with maxima in the B horizons, whereas this percentage was reached only    TABLE llI    Total chemical analysis of the various samples (in %)    HORIZON                SiO2      AI203     Fe203      FeO      TiO2     MnO      CaO      MgO      K20      Na20     H20    METABASALT*  Site 1  Ah  Aej  Bm1  Bm2-BC  Site 2  Ah  BF  BE  C  Site 3  Ah  BfI  Bf2  BC  C  ACIDIC MATERIAL**  Site 4  LH + (Ahe)  Bhf  Bf  C  Site 5  Ahe  BfI  8f2  C    49.91     16.24      3.22      6.99     1.70     0.16     9.02     7.96     0.62     4.18      tr    46.30     14.74     11.43      0.94     1.69     0.82     4.81     6.62     0.39     2.60     7.97  48.25     15.84      5.53      6.07     1.89     0.22     7.24     9.23      tr      3.88     1.00  46.83     17.35     10.21      2.69     1.82     0.22     6.49     9.05      tr      3.62     1.41  48.01     15.73      5.02      6.29     1.76     0.20     7.76     9.31      tr      4.14    0.88    50.01     19.04      3.33      7.86     1.84     0.15     4.70     7.34     0.40     A.01     2.18  45.99     19.71      8.35      4.51     1.67     0.13     4.34     8.02     0.28     3.67     2.95  47.80     17.86      5.43      5.33     1.68     0.18     7.04     9.14    0.16     3.99     0.89  44.10     19.14      7.08      6.23     1.61     0.22     6.02    10.86     0.32     3.23     1.88    47.05     16.24     12.53       tr      1.79     0.26     4.60     7.03     0.32     3.71     5.34  48.15     18.A9      0.30     10.90     1.88     0.27     4.76     8.08     0.39     3.76     2.83  49.00     18.24      2.76      8.48     1.83     0.28     4.53     8.31     0.27     4.10     2.31  47.02           18.34             0.98           10.34           1.87           0.19           5.12           9.60           0.16           3.95           1.88  46.24     18.26      0.21     11.16     1.90     0.19     6.23     9.50     0.16     4.01     1.48    75.23     10.89      3.88      1.25     1.48     0.09     1.18     1.58     2.06     2.29     0.44    n.d.      n.d.       n.d.      n.d.     n.d.     n.d.     n.d.     n.d.     n.d.     n.d.     n.d.  70.11     11.17      6.73       tr      1.77     0.08     2.22     1.48     1.48     2.62     2.74  59.86           15.35              4,46              3.62           1.41           0.13           3.16           5.33           1.31            3.05           1.89  74.49     10.67      3.87      1.32     1.12     0.09     1.32     1.32     2.08     2.34     0.69    80.87      8.63      3.20       tr      1.28     0.02     0,70     0.53     1.54     1.70     1.21  71.97           10.89              5.29              1.42           0.98           0.05           0.87           1.25           1.58           1.85           3.00  75.08     10.95      2.32      2.75     1.11     0.06     1.05     1.79     1.84     2.00     1.52  75.97     11.11      3.88      1.18     1.84     0.09     2.04     1.84     2.04     2.24     0,18    *   Mean of 3 rock samples  **   Mean of 2 C horizons    108    in Bhf and Bf horizons from profiles 4 and 5. Maxima of pyrophosphate  (P)--extractable Fe occurred in the surface horizons of profiles 1--3 and in  the Bhf and Bf horizons of profiles 4 and 5. In all profiles, A1 contents in  the three extracts were generally &lt; 1% and the maxima were observed in  the B horizons. CBD-extractable Fe and A1 contents in the ~ 2-pm fractions  presented a distribution similar to those of the entire soil samples but the  amounts were larger.    Z~    7  J    i  2                                                         ~q  R                 f  I                    f  t                     i                "   :                    t        il        ,      Ji\ /'  5                 L                                           '  i         '   .! ..   i ;\/,    J  "    '~'~"       :]  x 2,5    0.35         0.4              0.5        nm     0.7             1         t.4  1.8  30                            20     e                    10    Fig. 2. XRD patterns of the clay fractions of Ae (tracings 1--3) and Bm2 (tracings 4--6)  horizons of profile 1 after Mg-saturation + glycerol (1, 4), K-saturation and heating at  300 (2, 5), K-saturation and heating at 550 (3, 6).    109    Cation exchange capacities (CEC) of the soil horizons ranged from 2.7  to 107 meq./100 g with the highest values corresponding to the organic  matter-rich horizons (Table II). The range of CEC values for the clay samples  was from 20.4 to 81.2 meq./100 g.  Total chemical analyses of the parent materials and of the &lt; 2-ram ma-  terial (Table III) indicated major differences between the two groups of  profiles, especially the low SiO2 contents and the high contents of A1203,  Fe203 + FeO and of basic cations in the samples 1--3 with respect to samples  4 and 5.    x2.5    0.35         0.4             0.5        nm    0.7            1        1.4  1.8    30                            20      e                    10  Fig. 3. XRD patterns of the clay fractions of Ahe (tracings 1--3) and C (tracings 4--6)  horizons of profile 5 after Mg-saturation + glycerol (i, 4), K-saturation and heating at  300 (2, 5), K-saturation and heating at 550 (3, 6).    110    Mineralogical analyses were performed mainly on the &lt; 2-~m fraction  with some additional tests carried out on the sand and silt separates. In  profiles 1--3 developed on basic material, feldspars were identified in the  clay fraction and the amount increased with depth. Trace amounts of quartz  were found in the surface horizons and the intensity of the peaks decreased  with increasing particle-size. Chlorite was the major phyllosilicate (Fig. 2).  Basal reflections at 1.4, 0.7 and 0.35 nm were sharp and intense. Smectite  and an interstratified mineral were also detected in these profiles. Smectite  was identified by the expansion of the 1.4 nm peak to 1.8 nm upon glycerol  solvation. This reflection was generally broad and weak except in the lower  horizon of profile 1 where it was strong. The interstratified mineral was  identified by heating treatment. The 1.4-nm peak collapsed to 1.25--1.18  nm at 300 and 1.18--1.08 nm at 550. Lepidocrocite was observed only  in profile 1 and identified by the 0.627-nm reflection that disappeared upon  heating at 300. It was present in trace amounts in the Aej and Bmj  horizons but the peak was intense and sharp in the lower horizon.  The mineral assemblage in the profiles developed on till was different  (Fig. 3). Primary minerals, quartz, feldspars and amphiboles were present  in all samples and the contents generally increased with depth. In the lower  horizons of the two profiles, trace amounts of talc and serpentine were  identified by their specific reflections at 0.93 and 0.736 nm, respectively,  which were stable independently of the treatments. Chlorite and illite were  present as major constituents but their contents decreased towards the  surface. Smectite was present in the Ae horizons of profiles 4 and 5 and  minor amounts were also detected in the upper B horizons. Vermiculite  was identified in profile 5 by the ready collapse of the 1.4-nm reflection  to 1.0 nm upon K-saturation. Interstratified minerals were detected by the  shift of a reflection from 1.4 nm to about 1.2--1.1 nm upon K-saturation  and heating. Finally, traces of kaolinite were detected by IR spectroscopy  in the Ae horizons of these two profiles.    DISCUSSION    Parent materials    Differences in texture between the samples collected at site 1 and those  from sites 2 and 3 (Fig. 4) were related to saprolite formation and ice action  in this area. This was supported by field observations and laboratory results:  the presence of a till blanket over the saprolite at site 4 indicated that the  saprolite had been formed before Wisconsinian glaciation. Striations on  nearby outcrops suggested intense erosive action by the glaciers. Well-crystal-  lized chlorite (Fig. 2) which was the dominant phyllosilicate in the lower  horizons of the three profiles, was already present in the metabasalt (De  R~mer, 1958) and the chemical composition of the material in the C horizons  of profiles 2 and 3 (Table III) showed only slight differences with respect    100  90  80  70  60  ~ 50  ~40                                              ~ ~ ~  20  10  0                                                                                 ---"  2000 1000  500   250        100    50         20                  5            2                                 .2  (iJrn)  Fig. 4. Cumulative curves for &lt; 2-mm size-fractions of the parent materials.    100     5o    %%    ANORTHOSITE    ................  GRANITE  ~'~  ......  GABERO  .~  ......  METABASALT  ~               -  GNEISS    \    ~. \\  I  o...  \  s    111    2000         200          20           2            ,2  (IA m)  Fig. 5. Cumulative curves for &lt; 2-mm size-fractions of saprolites from different materials  in Quebec   112    to the metabasalt rock. Yet, the texture of this saprolite was as fine or finer  than that of several saprolitic deposits previously analyzed (Fig. 5) and  which showed strong alteration (Clement and De Kimpe, 1977; Dejou et al.,  1982a, b; Lasalle et al., 1983). The following hypothesis was therefore pro-  posed: a saprolite formed at the exper se of the metabasalt at least before Wis-  consinian glaciation. The upper part of this material may have been strongly  altered as in other deposits, but this is not relevant to the present discussion.  It was very likely, however, that when the ice scoured the area, much of the  saprolite was removed and only protected sites such as sites 2, 3 and 4  (in this case below the till) presently demonstrate the existence of the  preglacial saprolite. At site 1, which was on top of the hill, the saprolite,  if initially present, was removed by the glacier and the disaggregation and  decomposition of the metabasalt resulted from postglacial weathering.  Till at sites 4 and 5 was typical of a material transported by a glacier.  It was loamy in texture (Table I) and contained rounded gravel and pebbles.  The mineral assemblage corresponded to that commonly found in the  Appalachian region (Kodama, 1979) but, in addition, it also contained some  talc and serpentine (Fig. 3). The presence of these minerals indicated a  local origin for the till (McDonald, 1967) and transportation from neigh-  bouring areas.  From the above discussion, it appeared that two sets of profiles, 2, 3 on  one hand and 4, 5 on the other hand, would be adequate for comparing  the influence of parent materials on profile development. Indeed, the ab-  sence in the saprolite of any mineral typical of strong alteration (kaolinite,  gibbsite, goethite) indicated that the two types of parent materials, saprolite  and till, were comparable from the points of view of alteration stage of  minerals and texture (Fig. 4).    Evolution of the profiles    Chemical weathering was a major process in the evolution of the profiles.  Significant relations were found between the pH (H20) values of the &lt; 2-mm  material and the total CaO (r = 0.748**), CaO + MgO (r = 0.877**) and  CaO + MgO + Na20 (r = 0.811"*) determined by total chemical analysis  for the samples of profiles 1--3 (Fig. 6 and Table III). Grant (1969), from  a relation between the pH values of slurries obtained by grinding granitic  rock samples at various stages of alteration in the presence of water and the  contents of basic cations, Na, Ca, K and Mg in the rock, suggested that  abrasion pH be used as an index of chemical weathering. It was therefore  concluded that a lesser degree of chemical evolution was reached in profile  1, in which pH values were higher than in the other two profiles developed  on saprolite. No correlation was found between pH (H20) and (CaO, MgO,  Na20) contents for the profiles developed on till, because of the smaller  number of samples and the variability in composition inherent to till material.  In profile 5, however, there was a decrease of basic cation content and of  the pH values towards the surface.    113    X    o/  07"    ,;   i?   1.   1;   17   2;  IX)    Fig. 6. Relations between pH and percentages of total CaO (o), CaO + MgO (A) and  CaO + MgO + Na20 (o) for all samples from profiles developed on basic parent material.    Mobilization of Fe and Al and translocation of these cations as organo-  metallic complexes are important features of the evolution of soil profiles  (Soil Conservation Service, 1975; Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978).  CBD-extractable Fe and Al values were generally larger in profiles 1--3  than in profiles 4--5 (Table II) and this was also true for average values  (Table IV). Maxima of CBD-extractable Fe, however, were observed in the  A horizons of the profiles developed on basic material whereas they occurred  in the B horizons of the profiles developed on acidic parent material. With  respect to total Fe and A1 contents (Table III), more Fe (23.0% vs. 16.3%)  and A1 (3.0% vs. 2.6%) were mobilized in the latter set of profiles than in  the former (Table IV).  Differences in the amounts and distribution of organometallic complexes  were also observed between the two sets of profiles. In profiles 1--3, the  percentages of free sesquioxides involved in organometallic complexes were  about 40%, almost uniformly distributed in the profiles, with slight maxi-  ma in the A horizons (Table IV). In profiles 4--5, on the contrary, the  average proportions exceeded 50%, with well defined maxima in the B  horizons. Furthermore, the (Fe + A1)p/Org. C ratios in the horizons which  contained the maxima of these complexes corresponded to 0.15 and 0.37  for the A horizons in profiles 1--3 and the B horizons of profiles 4--5,  respectively. This was most likely related to the nature of the organic com-  pounds, as a larger proportion of humic and fulvic acids may be expected  to be present in the B horizons (McKeague et al., 1983).  Percentages of CBD~xtractable Fe and Al determined in the clay fractions  (Table II) were compared with the percentages determined on the &lt;~ 2-mm    114    material and then recalculated to account for the relative contents of clay.  In all profiles, most of extractable-A1 in the &lt; 2-mm materials was accounted  for by the aluminum found in the clay fraction. This was also true for the  extractable-Fe in the soils developed on acidic parent material, whereas  for the soils developed on saprolite, one-third of the extractable-Fe on the  average was extracted from the sand and silt fractions, probably as a result  of the large Fe content present in the basic parent material.    TABLE IV    Average contents of free and combined sesquioxides (in %)  HORIZONS                 Fec8D        Fep         AIc80        Alp            (Fe+Al)p         Fecj      AI~  (Fe+AI)cBD        Fetot      Altot  Basic parent material    All horizons                1.66        0.52          0.42        0.30              40  A                       2,05        0.75         0.40        0.28              42  B                       1.50        0,43         0.47        0.36              38  C                       1.10        0.40         0.25        0.15              41    Acidic parent material    All horizons                1.18        0.53          0.33        0.24              51  A                       0.80        0.30          0.10        0.10              44  B                                                   1.63                   0.85                      0.55                   0.38                                56  C                       0.70        O.10         0.10        0.10              25    16.~     2.6    23.0       3.0    Evolution of the profiles was also considered from the point of view of  the mineralogical assemblages and their changes within the profiles. In those  developed on basic parent material (1--3), chlorite was the most abundant  phyllosilicate. The sharp and intense reflections indicated a well-crystallized  mineral, which resulted from the earlier metamorphism of the lava (St-  Julien, 1963). Chlorite was thus the dominant weatherable mineral during  profile development. It was transformed initially into interstratified minerals  and finally into smectite. Smectite reflection at 1.8 nm was generally weak  and broad except in profile 1 where the most distinct peak was found in  the lower horizon. This observation prompted several hypotheses on source  of the smectite:  (a) Deposition as airborne dust. The presence of quartz traces in the upper  horizon of the profiles and its decrease in coarser fractions indicated the  addition of some material on top of the profiles. Although such an origin  for smectite had been reported elsewhere (Coen and Arnold, 1972), it does  not explain the distribution of smectite in the three profiles, especially  the accumulation in the lower part of profile 1.  (b) In-situ formation and translocation. Smectite would be formed in the  upper horizons at the expense of chlorite as indicated above and it would  be transported down the profile. The absence of clay films on partings and    115    of a significant increase of &lt; 0.2-pm particles in the lower with respect to  the upper part of profile 1 (Table I) provide little support for this hypothesis.  (c) In-situ formation and accumulation. Some observations were con-  sistent with this hypothesis. In the lower part of profile 1, pH measured in  H20 was above 6.0, the material was mixed with more than 50% of disaggre-  gated metabasalt fragments and internal drainage conditions were poorer  than above and than in the other profiles. Evidence for a change in the  drainage conditions was the presence of well-crystallized lepidocrocite (Fig.  4), commonly associated with reducing conditions (Schwertmann and  Thalmann, 1976). The (CaO + MgO + Na20) content was somewhat higher  than in the other horizons. Microsite conditions were thus favorable for  the formation of smectite (Grim, 1968). Until better evidence becomes  available, however, hypotheses a and b can not be rejected as they might  contribute to an explanation of the presence of smectite in these profiles.  Clay mineral assemblages in the horizons of profiles developed on till  were much like those described in other soils formed on similar material  in the Appalachian Highlands (De Kimpe and McKeague, 1974; Kodama,  1979). Chlorite and mica decreased rapidly towards the surface and were  replaced by interstratified minerals and vermiculite, and by smectite in the  surface horizons. Primary minerals such as quartz, feldspars and amphiboles  were present in low amounts and their contents also increased with depth.  The presence of trace amounts of talc and serpentine was related to the  occurrence of serpentinized peridotite in the area (De R6mer, 1958). In  profiles 4 and 5, the rapid decrease of chlorite towards the surface was  consistent with their more advanced evolution with respect to profiles 1--3  (Figs. 2 and 3).    Classification of profiles    Under good to moderately good drainage conditions, podzolization is  the dominant soil-forming process in Quebec on parent materials with a  texture coarser than clay (Clayton et al., 1977). In profiles 4 and 5, de-  veloped on acidic till, the B horizons met the criteria of the Podzolic order  (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978). In profile 4, the upper B horizons  contained over 5% organic carbon and the profile was classified as a Ferro-  Humic Podzol whereas profile 5 corresponded to a Humo-Ferric Podzol.  The presence of metabasalt at a depth of about 1 m did not affect the evo-  lution of these soils. They were comparable to a number of Podzolic soils  from the Appalachian Highlands (De Kimpe and McKeague, 1974). In these  profiles, none of the B horizons met the spodic horizon criteria (Soil Conser-  vation Service, 1975). The limiting factor was the (Fe + A1)p/clay content  i&gt; 0.2, that was too low in these profiles as in many other Podzolic soils  (McKeague et al., 1983). In the U.S. system of soil classification, the soils  were thus Inceptisols.  Major differences were observed in profiles 1--3, which developed on basic    116    material and presented, (at least profiles 2 and 3) a texture comparable to  those of profiles 4 and 5. The parent material contained about 21% CaO +  MgO + Na20. Leaching of these basic cations out of the profiles was ex-  tremely low in profile 1 and somewhat higher in profiles 2 and 3 where  about 25% of these cations were removed from the A and B horizons (Table  III), probably because of the finer texture of the material (Table I). These  profiles were at an early stage of weathering, as indicated by the Parker  index value (Fig. 7) based on the proportions of alkali and alkali-earth  cations present (Parker, 1970). The mineralogical assemblage also indicated  a low degree of mineral transformation. CBD-extractable values were high  and the B horizons of profiles 2 and 3 contained enough organometallic  complexes (pyrophosphate-extractable Fe and A1) (Table II) to meet most  morphological and the chemical criteria of the Podzolic B horizon (Canada  Soil Survey Committee, 1978). Profiles 2 and 3 were thus classified as  Humo-Ferric Podzols in the Canadian system of soil classification. This was  rather surprising when the properties of these soils, summarized above, were  considered. The classification criteria take into consideration the characteris-  tics of the B horizon only without any reference to the C horizons and in  these two profiles the fine textures and the high contents of Fe and A1 were  responsible for the large amounts of extractable sesquioxides. Profile 1,  with a texture coarser than those of profiles 2 and 3 was classified as Sombric  Brunisol. The three profiles were Inceptisols in the U.S. system of soil  classification.    100    X  Z  - 75  U,I  v    "'4  x    "-..  ~. __-               .'3.---2  ",|    ~0     |         I         l         I         I         I         I         I  R        C       BC      Bf2      Bfl      Sm     Aej      Ah  Fig. 7. Parker index evolution for the three profiles developed on basic parent materials.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS  To S. Cantagrel and F. Couturid, Geology Department, University of  Clermont-Ferrand, France, for the total chemical analyses. To R. Rivard,  Agriculture Canada, Sainte-Foy, for technical assistance.    117    REFERENCES    Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classification. Can.  Dep. Agric. Publ., 1646. Suppl. Serv., Can., Ont., 164 pp.  Clayton, J.S., Ehrlich, W.A., Cann, D.B., Day, J.H. and Marshall, I.B., 1977. Soils of  Canada, I. Soil Report. Can. Dep. Agric., Ottawa, 243 pp.  Cleaves, E.T., Fisher, D.W. and Bricker, O.P., 1974. Chemical weathering of serpentine  in the eastern piedmont of Maryland. Geol. Soc. Am. Bull., 85 : 437---444.  Clement, P. and De Kimpe, C.R., 1977. Geomorphological conditions of gabbro weather-  ing at Mount Megantic, Quebec. Can. J. Earth Sci., 14: 2262--2273.  Coen, G.M. and Arnold, R.W., 1972. Clay mineral genesis of some New York Spodosols.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 342--350.  Dejou, J., Clement, P. et De Kimpe, C.R., 1982a. Importance du site dans la g~n~se des  min~raux secondaires issus des alterations superficielles. Exemple des granites et  gabbros du Mont M~gantic, Quebec, Canada. Catena, 9: 181--198.  Dejou, J., De Kimpe, C.R. et Lasalle, P., 1982b. Evolution g~ochimique superficielle  naissante des anorthosites -- cas du profil de Chateau-Richer, Quebec, Canada. Can.  J. Earth Sci., 19: 1697--1706.  De Kimpe, C.R. and McKeague, J.A., 1974. Micromorphological, physical and chemical  properties of a podzolic soil with a fragipan. Can. J. Soil Sci., 54: 29--38.  De Kimpe, C.R. and Zizka, J., 1973. Weathering and clay formation in a dunite deposit  at Asbestos. Can. J. Earth Sci., 10: 1533--1540.  De Kimpe, C.R., Tabi, M. and Zizka, J., 1973. Influence of basic material on soil genesis  in the Thetford-Black Lake area, Province of Quebec. Can. J. Soil Sci., 53: 27--35.  De R6mer, H., 1958. Rapport pr~liminaire sur la r~gion du Lac Orford. Districts ~lectro-  raux de Brome, Shefford et Sherbrooke. Min. Mines, Quebec R.P., 372:11 pp.  Grant, W.H., 1969. Abrasion pH, an index of chemical weathering. Clays Clay Miner.,  17 : 151--155.  Grim, R.E., 1968. Clay Mineralogy. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 596 pp.  Kodama, H., 1979. Clay minerals in Canadian soils: their origin, distribution and altera-  tion. Can. J. Soil Sci., 59: 37--58.  Lasalle, P., 1983. G~ologie des s~diments meubles de la r~gion d'Orford. Min. En. Ressour.  Quebec, 1 carte.  Lasalle, P., De Kimpe, C.R. et Laverdi~re, M.R., 1983. Alteration profonde pr~glaciaire  d'un gneiss ~ Charlesbourg, Quebec (Canada). Geoderma, 31: 117--132.  McDonald, B.C., 1967. Pleistocene Events and Chronology in the Appalachian Region  of Southeastern Quebec, Canada. Ph.D. Thesis, Yale Univ., 161 pp.  McDonald, B.C. and Shilts, W.W., 1971. Quaternary stratigraphy and events in south-  eastern Quebec. Geol. Soc. Am. Bull., 82: 683---698.  McKeague, J.A. (Editor), 1978. Manual on Soil Sampling and Methods of Analysis. Can.  Soil Surv. Comm., Can. Soc. Soil Sci., 212 pp.  McKeague, J.A., De Coninck, F. and Franzmeier, D2., 1983. Spodosols. In: L.P. Wilding,  N.E. Smeck and G.F. Hall (Editors), Pedogenesis and Soil Taxonomy, II. The Soil  Orders. Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 217--252.  McKeague, J.A., Ross, G.J. and Gamble, D.S., 1978. Properties, criteria of classification  and genesis of Podzolic soils in Canada. In: W.C. Mahaney (Editor), Quaternary Soils.  Geo Abstr., Norwich, pp. 27--60.  McKeague, J.A., Wang, C., Coen, G.M., De Kimpe, C.R., Laverdi~re, M.R., Evans, L.J.,  Kloosterman, B. and Green, A.J., 1983. Testing chemical criteria for spodic horizons  on Podzolic soils in Canada. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 47 : 1052--1054.  Parker, A., 1970. An index of weathering for silicate rocks. Geol. Mag., 501--504.  Rabenhorst, M.C. and Foss, J.E., 1981. Soil and geologic mapping over mafic and ultra-  mafic parent materials in Maryland. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 45: 1156--1160.    118    Rabenhorst, M.C., Foss, J.E. and Fanning, D.S., 1982. Genesis of Maryland soils formed  from serpentinite. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 607--616.  Schwertmann, U. and Thalmann, H., 1976. The influence of [Fe(II)], [Si], and pH on  the formation of lepidocrocite and ferrihydrite during oxidation of aqueous FeCl.  solutions. Clay Miner., 11: 189--200.  Simonson, R.W., 1959. Outline of a generalized theory of soil genesis. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 23: 152--156.  Soil Conservation Service, ]975. Soil Taxonomy. Agriculture Handbook, 436. U.S. Dep.  Agric., Washington, D.C.  St-Julien, P., 1963. G~ologie de la R~gion d'Orford--Sherbrooke, Quebec. Ph.D. Thesis,  Fac. Sci. Universit~ Laval, 369 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractFive profiles developed on basic or acidic parent materials were sampled in southern Quebec, Canada. Physical, chemical and mineralogical properties were determined. Among the three profiles developed on basic parent materials, one formed in disaggregated metabasalt whereas the two others developed in preglacial saprolites derived from the metabasalt, as indicated by till cover in a nearby area. In the lower part of the latter profiles, the saprolites had a loamy texture and the mineralogical plus chemical data indicated very slight changes with respect to the metabasalt. In these profiles, CBD-extractable Fe content was &gt; 1% in most horizons, and the pyrophosphate-extractable Fe was generally higher in the Ah than in the B horizons. In the profiles developed on acidic till, CBD-extractable Fe was &gt; 1% only in the B horizons, which also contained the maximum of pyrophosphate-extractable Fe. In the latter profiles, free Fe and Al sesquioxides were associated with the clay fractions whereas in the former profiles, one third of the Fe came from the sand and silt fractions.Chlorite was the dominant phyllosilicate in the basic material and it was transformed into interstratified minerals and smectite. Several hypotheses about smectite formation and distribution were discussed. In the profiles developed on acidic till, illite and chlorite were the major phyllosilicates and, through weathering, transformed into interstratified minerals, vermiculite and smectite.Major differences in the properties of the profiles developed on the two parent materials were not reflected by current soil classification.