Geoderma, 24 (1980) 17--23                                                      17  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    TRACE ELEMENTS IN SOILS AROUND LLECHRYD, DYFED, WALES    R.I. BRADLEY  Soil Survey of England and Wales, Harrogate (Great Britain)  (Received September 16, 1978; revised version accepted October 23, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Bradley, R.I., 1980. Trace elements in soils around Llechryd, Dyfed, Wales. Geoderma,  24: 17--23.    This study reports the levels of five trace elements in a rural non-mineralized area of  Dyfed, Wales. The area is thought not to have been polluted industrially, but threshold  values, above which soils would be contaminated, are presented. The trace-element con-  tents are similar in the main soil series and particle-size groups because of the common  source of all the drift deposits: Lower Palaeozoic mudstone and sandstone. The areal dis-  tribution of the elements is shown using computer-drawn maps and the patterns discussed.    INTRODUCTION    The aim was to investigate the amount and distribution of Pb, Cu, Zn, Cd  and Ni in soils around Llechryd, Dyfed (Fig. 1). The underlying Lower  Palaeozoic mudstone and sandstone are non-mineralized. It is, therefore, a  suitable district in which to establish normal background levels for the ele-  ments in soils on these sediments, and to estimate the threshold value above  which contamination would be suspected. Having established mean and back-  ground values, the areal distribution of the data was studied.  Previous trace-element work in West Wales has been in the heavy-metal  contaminated area east of Aberystwyth (Alloway and Davies, 1971}, in north-  west Pembrokeshire {Bradley et al., 1978} and more generally in west Dyfed  {Davies and Roberts, 1975}. These results were compared with those from the  Llechryd area, which does not have a history of heavy-metal mining. There  are three main soil series in the district {Bradley, 1980). Typical brown podzol.  ic soils (Avery, 1973} of the Manod series and cambic stagnogley soils of the  Cegin series are fine loamy or fine silty softs in drift from Lower Palaeozoic  mudstone and sandstone. The Hallsworth series comprises pelo-stagnogley  soils in clayey till, derived mainly from the local mudstone and sandstone.    18                       j yl  ...:                   ~' ~.~  FED     i                 .I"  Cardig~ "1   I_ Newcastle       :\     L-"~" Emlyn          :.:.:          ",~  "                           :            ~*L ~...,.  * Carmarthen  :...'il                   "~' ' ~"~  ...."                        "-~  ~   ......i=   '"                                                            I"  10   0   10  20  30  40 miles    Fig. 1. Location of study area.    METHODS    Sampling    As part of the soil survey of the 100 km2 of Ordnance Survey sheet SN 24  (Llechryd), soil descriptions were made and samples taken at 121 sampling  points at 1-km intervals at the National Grid intersections. At each site a 1-kg  sample of soils was taken in the Ap horizon (Hodgson, 1974), at 5--15 cm depth  from the surface using a trowel.    Laboratory analysis    Pb, Cu, Zn, Cd and Ni were measured using the method of analysis reported  by Davies and Roberts (1975). It is based on Warren and Delevault's {1960)  method which is commonly used by geochemists in pollution and prospect-  ing surveys. Approximately 10 g of soil, ignited at 430 for 24 h, were ex-  tracted with 20 ml of analytical-grade concentrated nitric acid for 30 min at  ll0. After evaporation the soil was extracted with a further 20 ml of con-  centrated acid. Following a second evaporation, 100 ml of 0.01 M nitric acid    19    were added and the whole warmed at 50 for 15 min prior to filtering. The  filtrate was then analysed by atomic-absorption spectrophotometry using an  EEL 240 spectrophotometer. The method extracts approximately 80% total  Pb, 60--80% total Cu and 100% total Zn compared with physical methods.  B.E. Davies (personal communication, 1979) found that data on soils from  west Wales obtained by the method are reproducible. This is probably because  of the broadly similar soil parent materials and particle-size classes. When the  soils were analysed by X-ray-fluorescence spectrometry, some differences  were found, namely chemical extraction accounted for 88% Pb, 66% Cu,  75% Zn and 100% Ni (C. Wilkins, personal communication, 1976).  Soil reaction (pH) was measured following equilibration of 1 part air-dry  soil in 2.5 parts 0.01 M calcium chloride solution.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The means and standard deviations for all the variables were calculated and  the 95% confidence limits derived {Table I). The upper 95% limit is often  regarded as the geochemical threshold above which contamination is suspected  and the values between the 95% limits as the background level.  The coefficients of variation for each element, based on 20 repeated analyses  of subsamples from the same bag of topsoil are given (Table II). The results  were normally distributed. The smaller the coefficient, the more precise the  analyses. The values of the coefficient of variation, except for cadmium, are  similar to other values quoted in the literature. In a recent study, Shan Singh    TABLE I    Means, standard deviations and 95% confidence limits for trace elements, loss on ignition  and pH    Mean  Standard  Mean of      Standard  deviation  transformed  deviation of  data ~         transformed  data    95% Confidence limits~    Lower   Upper    Lead3        41      --         3.66           0.30            17        87  Copper      11      --        2.34          0.42             4        24  Zinc         73     22          --            --             29      117  Cadmium     1.1    0.3        --            --             0.5       1.7  Nickel       20      --        2.90          0.39             8       40  Loss on  ignition   9.2   --        2.20         0.29           5.0     16.2  pH          4.6    0.6       --           --             3.4      5.8    I Transformation using logarithms to base e. 2 Equivalent to upper and lower threshold  values; derived from means and standard deviations for Zn, Cd and pH and from antilogs,  of transformed means and standard deviations for Pb, Cu and Ni. 3 Pb CU Zn Cd Ni in ~g/g  oven-dry soil; loss on ignition as %.    20  TABLE II  Coefficients of variation    Mean  Standard   Coeff. of  deviation  variation    Pb           41.7   2.4          5.8  Cu          12.4   0.8          6.5  Zn          84.9   6.4          7.5  Cd            1.4   0.4         28.6  Ni           21.4   2.8         13.1  Loss on  ignition    7.4   0.5          6.8    standard deviation  Coefficient of variation =                    x 100; n = 20.  mean  Trace elements in ug/g oven-dry soil, loss on ignition as percentages.    (1977) suggested that great care is needed in reporting low levels of cadmium  as up to 50% may be lost through absorption by filter papers. This, together  with interference from Mg and Na when using the EEL 240, with its lack of  background correction and single beam, is probably the reason for the large co-  efficient of variation of cadmium in this study.  In order to fulfill the requirements of Student's t-test rigorously, transforma-  tion of the data for Pb, Cu and Ni, which were very skewed in distribution, us-  ing logarithms, made them approximately normal. Transformation was not  necessary for Zn and Cd.  Division of the data according to soil series, parent material or particle-size  class did not give any significant differences. The means for these sub-divisions,  when compared using Student's t-test, were not significantly different from  the overall means. The only exception was that Manod soils (fine loamy, typic-  al brown podzolic soils) had significantly more Ni than Hallsworth soils (clayey,  pelo-stagnogley soils) (t = 2.68, p &lt; 0.01}. In other areas trace-element dif-  ferences between series have proved significant (for example, see Bradley et  al., 1978). It is suggested that total trace elements in the topsoils (Ap horizons)  in the Llechryd district are similar because parent materials of the soils are from  the same source rocks.  Occasional high levels of trace elements were noted, suggesting that one or  two sites may be polluted. Generally, the levels are below the local threshold  for pollution (Table I) and well below those calculated for Denbighshire (Nicol  et al., 1970b) and Derbyshire (Nicol et al., 1970a) on similar parent materials.  The average values (Table I) are compared with data from other non-con-  taminated parts of west Wales in Table III. This shows the variability of esti-  mates and the necessity of using local data when assessing sites of possible pol-  lution. The average amounts of Pb and Zn are the same in Llechryd and north-  west Pembrokeshire, but Cu and Ni are significantly higher in Pembrokeshire.    TABLE III  Trace elements in soils in western Wales related to those in the Llechryd area    21    Element                   Area    Llechryd*~          N.W. Pembrokeshire.2   W. Dyfed.3    Pb                           41   15*4         37 13                  37   11  Cu                           11    4            36 8***              13    5  Zn                           73   22            7121                  94  33**  Cd                            1.1  0.3          n.d.                        1.5 -+  0.3***  Ni                         20   9           29  8***             n.d.  Number of samples         42                 157                      70    *~ For Manod series. * 2 For well-drained soils from Lower Palaeozoic sediments (Bradley  et al., 1978). ,3 For well-drained soils from Lower Palaeozoic sediments (Davies and  Roberts, 1975). ,4 All trace element contents in ug/g.  *Significantly different from the Llechryd data at 5% level; **significantly different from  the Llechryd data at 1% level; ***significantly different from the Llechryd data at 0.1%  level.    When compared with data from other surveys, some similarities and some dif-  ferences were found. For instance, similar levels of Pb have been found in  Oxford (Beckett et al., 1978) and Derbyshire (Nicol et al., 1970a). In Canada,  (Frank et al., 1976} levels of Zn and Ni are not significantly different but  there is less Pb and more Cu. Data from the United States (Shacklette et al.,  1971) show similar Ni levels but again less Pb and more Cu. There appears to  be a general enhancement of Pb in British soils compared with those from  North America (Davies and Holmes, 1972).  To compare the areal patterns of the trace elements, the data were display-  ed using SYMAP (Laboratory for Computer Graphics, 1968}, a computer  program that produces contour maps on the computer's line printer. Each  map shows a distinctive distribution pattern, each one different from the  others. However, none of the patterns was readily identifiable with establish-  ed patterns of soft, wetness class, or relief. Examples, reduced from the origin-  al 1:35,700 scale are given in Fig. 2. There is a pattern of slightly higher  amounts of Pb (41--100 pg/g) following the broad line of the Teifi valley  (Fig. 2a). However, only one sample point was in alluvium and in many places  the floodplain is bounded by cliffs up to 45 m high. Although there are other  patterns of higher values, none is associated with soil or wetness class. Copper  and Zn show low values around Penparc in the soil associated with glacio-  fluvial sand. There are, however, non-sandy areas also low in Cu and Zn. The  distribution of Cd shows a distinctive pattern of higher values (1.1--2.4 ~g/g}  through the centre of the district. This is not related to known soil features.  The range of values for the various elements determined in this area indi-  cates the levels that can be expected in an incontaminated district. In compar-  ing results from other parts of Britain and North America, care is required to    22    b. Loss on ignition    a. Lead    C l Nickel  Level                      2          3          ~          5    .............  *** ,Jn~CnEm~o eA~e.e~#LaQ IIIIIIIII  Symbols  ....  ~  ......  ++z+**+ nn~n3~on(] oBsess.e8 111151111    .........  +.,.+,++rJn~eO0o0~ aOO~PgAOA Illllllll    .........  *+*+++*+* {10O~0000 ~oeeeoA~e IIIIIIIII    N    d. Cadmium    5 km  I    Pb  #g/g  LOI   o  Ni  #g/g  Cd  ~tg/g    1            2           3            4            5  20-30    30-40    40-50    55-74    74-120  3.0-8.8   6.8-9.1   9.1-12.3  12.3- 15.8  15.8-38  8-12     12-17     17-25     25-35    35-52  0.4-0.8   0.8-1.1   1.1-1,4    1.4-1,7     1.7-2.4    Fig. 2. Distribution of trace elements using SYMAP. a. Lead: logarithmic transformation,  5 unequal classes, b. Cadmium: 5 equal classes, c. Nickel: logarithmic transformation, 5  equal classes, d. Loss on ignition: logarithmic transformation, 5 unequal classes.    23    ensure that the data are derived from similar analytical techniques and parent  materials.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    This work formed part of a M.Sc. thesis submitted to the University of  Wales, under the supervision of Dr. B.E. Davies and partly financed by UKF  Fertilizers Ltd. I thank Dr. R. Webster for help and guidance in computing,  P. Loveland for mineralogical analysis and C.C. Rudeforth, B. Clayden and  C. Wilkins for constructive comments on the manuscript.    REFERENCES    Alloway, B.J. and Davies, B.E., 1971. Trace-element content of soils affected by base-  metal mining in Wales. Geoderma, 5: 197--208.  Avery, B.W., 1973. Soil classification in the Soil Survey of England and Wales. J. Soil Sci.,  24: 324--338.  Beckett, P.H.T., Wollan, E., Cawse, P.A., Hislop, J.S. and Williams, D.R., 1978. The use  of grasses as indicators of environmental pollution. Plant Soil, 49: 691--695.  Bradley, R.I., 1980. Soil in Dyfed, V: sheet SN 24 (Llechryd). Soil Surv. Rec., 63.  Bradley, R.I., Rudeforth, C.C. and Wilkins, C., 1978. Trace elements in the soils of north-  west Pembrokeshire. J. Soil Sci., 29: 258--270.  Davies, B.E. and Holmes, P.L., 1972. Lead contamination of roadside soil and grass in  Birmingham, England, in relation to naturally occurring levels. J. Agric. Sci., Cambridge,  79: 479--484.  Davies, B.E. and Roberts, L.J., 1975. Heavy metals in soils and radish in a mineralized lime-  stone area of Wales, Great Britain. Sci. Total Environ., 4: 249--261.  Frank, R., Ishida, K. and Suda, P, 1976. Metals in agricultural soils of Ontario. Can. J. Soil  Sci., 56: 181--196.  Hodgson, J.M., 1974. Soil Survey Field Handbook. Soil Surv. Tech. Monogr., 5.  Laboratory for Computer Graphics, 1968. Reference Manual for Synagraphic Computer  Mapping, 'SYMAP' Version 5. Harvard University, Mass.  Nicol, I., Thornton, I., Webb, J.S., Fletcher, W.K., Horsnoul, R.F., Khaleelee, J. and  Taylor, D., 1970a. Regional geochemical reconnaissance of the Derbyshire area. Inst.  Geol. Sci., U.K., Rep., 70]2.  Nicol, I., Thornton, I., Webb, J.S., Fletcher, W.K., Horsnai, R.F., Khaleelee, J. and  Taylor, D., 1970b. Regional geochemical reconnaissance of the Denbighshire area. Inst.  Geol. Sci., U.K., Rep., 70/8.  Shacklette, J.T., Hamilton, J.C., Boerngen, J.G. and Bowles, J.M., 1971. Elemental compo-  sition of surficial materials in the conterminous United States. U.S. Geol. Surv. Prof.  Pap., 574-D.  Shan Singh, S., 1977. Considerations on sorption of cadmium during laboratory operations.  Can. J. Soil Sci., 57: 217--219.  Warren, H.V. and Delevault, R.E., 1960. Aqua regia extractable copper and zinc in plutonic  rocks in relation to ore deposits. Trans. Inst. Min. Metall., 69(9): 495--504.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractThis study reports the levels of five trace elements in a rural non-mineralized area of Dyfed, Wales. The area is thought not to have been polluted industrially, but threshold values, above which soils would be contaminated, are presented. The trace-element contents are similar in the main soil series and particle-size groups because of the common source of all the drift deposits: Lower Palaeozoic mudstone and sandstone. The areal distribution of the elements is shown using computer-drawn maps and the patterns discussed.