353    Structure and Function of Northern Coniferous Forests --An Ecosystem  Study. T. Persson (Editor). Ecological Studies, No. 32, Swedish Natural  Science Research Council (NFR), Stockholm, 1980, 609 pp.,  SwK. 290.00 (incl. air mail postage).    The book is the first comprehensive documenation of the studies included  within the Swedish Coniferous Project. It contains 37 single papers, all of  them dealing with aspects of the structure and the functional processes of  Scots pine (Pinus sylvestris L.) forests which cover more than 40% of the  whole country. The project, started in 1972 with field studies, was conducted  in Central Sweden in a 160-years-old mixed mature stand of pine and spruce  and on 6 sites with stands of pines of different age, height and density (age  species up to an 120 year old stand incl. clear fellings of pine).  This interdisciplinary ecosystem research project can be seen as the second  generation of such projects following those of the International Biological  Programme of 1964--1974. The results of the field studies are the basis for  many mathematic models which describe the structure and processes of the  stands, of single trees but also of organs such as needles, roots etc. They also  describe the processes in the atmosphere inside and above the stands, as well  as the soil processes. They therefore give a basis for predictions.  After an introductory description of the project, of the features of the in-  vestigation sites and of the handling of data and of the simulation used tech-  nique, mostly original papers on the results of field studies are presented,  but some review papers are also included. The book is divided in two main  groups of papers: The forest ecosystem with the different processes and the  theoretical approaches to forest functioning. The first main chapter with  the abiotic processes, i.e. the results of the field studies on local climate,  micrometeorological conditions inside and above the stands and within the  soil layers. The hydrological aspects including evapotranspiration of the  stands, are described as well as all important energy exchanges.  Sixteen papers on plant and vegetation processes represent the central part  of the whole project and hence of the book. They deal with the growth of  the stand, the single trees as well as organs such as needles, roots and shoots.  The studies were made under natural conditions, but also with use of fertil-  izers and irrigation, so that water and nutrients were not limiting factors. To  understand the primary net production, all physiological processes, e.g. photo-  synthesis, respiration and transpiration are included. Detailed analyses of  tree and stand growth and on the annual carbon budget are given as well as  of field studies on insect consumption and on the mutual relationships be-  tween needle-eating insects and Scots pine.  The high production of fine roots noted -- more than 50% of the assimi-  lates formed was used for growth and maintenance of the root system --  also indicates unexpected results. The possibility of generalizing the results  and hence of extrapolating results from one site to a whole region is also  shown. The studies were made and the results demonstrated with different    354    time scales, from the gaseous exchange (hours) to the long-term growth of  the stands (years). All these studies on plant processes give the basis for the  later described mathematical models.  Within the next subchapter, 9 papers are devoted to different soil pro-  cesses, especially within the mature pine stand. Initially the problems started  with single topics: the leaching of carbon, nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium  in litter humus and mineral layers, the decomposition of different types  of substrates under given climatological conditions, the mineralization of  CNP from substrates, input and output of easily available nitrogen, the in-  fluence of soil organisms on the decomposition and mineralization, etc.  Finally interest is focused on synthesic work which is found in the last  main chapter devoted to the theoretical approach and in which the processes  like the seasonal dynamics of different soil processes, the influx of nutrients  through precipitation, nitrogen fixation and nutrient transport are described  by models, as well as the biomass dynamics of the soil animal populations  and their relation to carbon retention and release. The models also deal with  the climatic influence on carbon and nitrogen transformation in the soils,  with emphasis on the balance between nitrogen leaching and uptake by plant  roots.  The last chapter presents also other simulation models from the micro-  climatological and hydrological conditons in the stands, including the differ-  ent energy exchanges and gaseous transport in tree growth.  This documentation is a substantial contribution toward a better under-  standing of plant growth within stands -- which can be found so widely dis-  tributed -- and their regulation by ecological factors. The documentation is  well balanced in the different chapters, which are very well coordinated. The  project represents an excample of how ecosystem studies have to be made in  the future: starting with many coordinated field studies of the governing  abiotic factors, of the reactions of the plants and vegetation and summarizing  and synthesising by mathematic modeling. Without such modeling, many un-  solved and open problems cannot be seen. A better understanding of the  dynamics of the plant-biomass process is obtained in this way. Finally, the  proof is demonstrated that such studies are necessary also to understand  human impacts on ecological systems and their consequences, e.g. by the  aciditation of precipitation. This book will be a valuable tool for everyone  who is starting ecological investigationgs of stands and vegetation covers --  also in other climates and with other types of vegetation.    J. VAN EIMERN  (GSttingen)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   