Geoderma, 30 (1983) 303--322                                                    303  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed In The Netherlands    THE CHARACTERIZATION OF THE SHAPE OF MINERAL GRAINS  IN THIN SECTIONS OF SOILS BY QUANTIMET AND BESI    E.B.A. BISDOM and D. SCHOONDERBEEK  Netherlands Soil Survey lnstttute, P O. Box 98. 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for pubhcation February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Blsdom, E.B.A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1983. The characterization of the shape of mine-  ral grains m thin sections of soils by Quantimet and BESI. Geoderma, 30: 303--322.    Silt-sized mineral grains were analysed for their shapes or forms m thin sections of soils  using backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) and an image analyzer (Quantimet  720). Thin work was done with an image-editor and required manual editing of the shape  of mineral grains on the dmplay screen of the Quantimet. Shape analysis of coarse and  fine silt grains could thus be performed at magnifications of 240 and 480.  The shape of the mineral grains could be characterized by five parameters: area (A),  perimeter (Pe), largest and smallest Feret's diameters (Fmax and Fmin), lobation ratio  (Lr) and indentation ratio (lr). A relation was found, however, between the A/Pe ~ ratio  and the Lr and lr ratios. Consequently, shape analysis of mineral grains can be done by  measuring three of the five parameters, l.e A, Pe and Fmax/Fmm. These parameters,  however, are still not able to reproduce the shape of individual mineral grains and images  of them therefore remain necessary.  Several of the 54 mineral grains were found to have different shapes but the same A~  Pe 2 ratio. An explanation for this phenomenon is given by using a theoretical model in  which two-dimensional forms change their shapes from a circle (A/Pe2 = 79) to a line  (A/Pe : = 1). Form separation of mineral grains with the same A/Pe 2 ratio can be done by  using the Fmax/Fmln ratio.  The measurement of the shape of the mineral grains, the theoretical model and obser-  vation of the mmrographs of the individual mineral grains, made it possible to draw a  diagram with shape classes which can be used for shape classification purposes. Know-  ledge gathered in soil mmromorphology on shape analysis of pores and soil aggregates has  also been used to obtain boundaries of shape classes in the diagram. The present study is  intended both as a proposal as to how two-dimensional shape clasmficatton can possibly  be done, and as a work-model. The boundarms of the shape classes can easily be adjusted  if data from forthcoming studies require it.    INTRODUCTION    Shape or form analysis of mineral grams in thin sections of soils, in con-  trast to shape analyms of pores (voids), has hardly been done. Virtually all  our knowledge on shape analysis is derived from the study of pores in soils  using transmitted light microscopy and an image analyzer (Jongerius, 1974;  Ismall, 1975; Murphy et al., 1977; Bouma et al., 1977, 1979). Only pores    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V    304    larger than 30 um could be measured with this technique due to the thick-  ness of a thin section which usually approaches this value. If backscattered  electron scanning images (BESI) are used (Bisdom and Thml, 1981), pores  smaller than 30 ~m can also be measured by an image analyzer (Jongenus  and Bisdom, 1981). Shape analysis of pores that are smaller and larger than  30 um can thus be done with an image analyzer (Quantlmet 720).  In the present investigation, the BESI-Quantlmet technique could also be  used for shape analysis of mineral grains; after establishing the magmfica-  tyons to be used with Quantimet measurements, and after a procedure had  been worked out to obtain measurable forms of the mineral grams. A more  comphcated objective, on whmh little knowledge was amassed during the  study of the shape of pores, became apparent during the study of shape data  on individual mineral grains. This objective was to find a way to indicate  how the measured two&lt;iimensional shapes are related to each other. A solu-  tion to this problem, based on the BESI-Quantlmet technique, is presented  in this study.  The insight into how two-dimensional forms can be related to each other,  gave a better understanding of shape classification problems. This allowed  the introduction of a simple classification with shape classes. It became ap-  parent that the parameters which can be measured by Quantimet, cannot re-  produce the actual forms of mineral grains. Images of the mineral grmns  therefore remain necessary.  In order to explain various matters assocmted w~th shape analysis, the  more theoretmal aspects of the present study and a theoretmal model are dis-  cussed In the section on materials and methods together with techmcal de-  tails. Shape data of the measured mineral grains are presented in the section  on results.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    SEM--Quantimet    The present study on the shape of mineral grains has been done with an  image analyzer (Quantimet 720) using backscattered electron scanning im-  ages (BESI) made with a Jeol-JSM-35C scanning electron mmroscope (SEM).  The SEM was equipped with a backscattered electron detector of the semi-  conductor type which contained two solid state detectors. BESI obtained  with the BE-detector was of sufficient quality to allow shape analysis of  minerals in thin sections of soils which consisted of thin layers of sandy, silty  and clayey materials. Shape measurements were done with the image editor  of the Quantimet, which meant that manual editing of the shape of mineral  grains on the display screen of the image analyzer was necessary.  If BESI are used for shape analysis, a much thinner layer -- predominantly  just underneath the surface of the thin section and a few micrometres think  -- is portrayed than Is possible with transmitted light microscopy (Blsdom    305    and Thiel, 1981). This allowed the study of pores both smaller and larger  than 30 pm by Quantimet (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). In the present  study, both coarse and fine silt-sized grains were selected for shape analysis  and several were smaller than 30 ~m (Fig. 1). Shape analysis of pores smaller  and larger than 30 pm had shown that the measured porosity could vary  with the magmflcation of BESI. This indicated that attention has to be prod  to magmfications of BESI used for shape analysis of mineral grains by  Quantimet.    Fig. 1. Silt grains in stratified sandy soils of The Netherlands. 54 mineral grains were mea-  sured by Quantimet in this hackscattered electron scanning image.    Image-edzting of mzneral grains and magnifzcattons to be used for shape  analyszs    Imtlally, in order to obtain correct magnifications for shape analysis,  Quantimet measurements were done from BESI on sand- and silt-sized mine-  ral grains at 120, 240 and X 480. It was found that most grains needed  image~editing before shape measurements could be done. Many grains exhib-  ited small dark grey to black areas internally. These small areas usually re-  presented very shallow and somewhat deeper situated areas m the mineral  grain and were called internal undeep pores In Fig. 2A. These internal un-  deep pores had to be excluded from measurements which concerned the ex-  ternal shape of mineral grams (Fig. 2B) and this was done with the image  editor of the Quantimet.    306  ~/ outer laver    /  a ~  ,        ,%,/,,,: ,,  ,,/     ,m of g  .......  I'~~'  //~'////prior rel ', S p ' a y  ........  ' i~/.~/.- '  /                         ~ rote nal pore  ,/~            interrlal undeep     ,~             covered  .,q/.       .,Q,'    thm outer        /  ,     ,,y  ........ /   )             ':'o::r:~ oo,e  Internally and  -                             externally covered  ral qram    Fig. 2 Schematic illustration of the image-editing of a mineral grain. A A grain as it ap-  pears on the display screen of the Quantimet. B. Covering of internal pores. C. Covering  of the thin outer layer if the surface of the grain slopes down. D. Completely edited gram    The second problem which had to be examined was the position of the  boundary of the vague outer nm of several mineral grains (cf. Fig. 1). This  can be explained using the data given in Table I. The two internally covered  mineral grains, which were taken as an example, gave area and perimeter  measurements whmh were different at the three magnifications. Image-edit-  ing of the periphery of the mineral grams was therefore necessary; a proce-  dure whmh was called external covering (Fig. 2C). The results of measure-  ments done on the same mineral grains as m Table I, but internally and ex-  ternally covered, are given in Table II. What is measured is given in Fig. 2D.  All area measurements were similar, but the perimeter at X 120 magnifmation  was different from those at X 240 and 480. Consequently, ratios derived    TABLE I    Two internally covered mineral grains (the same as m Table II) measured at different  magnifications    Mineral        Magnifi-       Area (A)      Perimeter     A/Pe2         Lobation  gram          cation         (urn2 )         (Pe)           1000        ratio  (~m)                      (Lr)    1           20        631         224         12          2 53  1           240        539         274          7          3.37  1           480        517         364          4          4 54  2           20        256          87         34          153  2           x 240        243         103         22          1 89  2           x480        199         166          7          3 33    307  TABLE II  Two internally and externally covered mineral grains (the same as in Table I) measured  at different magnifications    Mineral       Magnifi-      Area (A)      Perimeter     A/Pe2         Lobation  grain         cation        (urn~ )        (Pe)          1000       ratio  (.m)                       (Lr)    1           x120       698         153         30          1.64  1           240       695         169         24          1.82  1           80        687         167         24          1 81  2           20       286         100         28          1.68  2           240       312         121         21          1.96  2           480       295         122         20          2.01    from these parameters, i.e. A/Pe2 and the lobation ratio (Lr), were similar  at 240 and 480 magnifications.  Finally, some explanation needs to be given as to why several mineral  grains have vague outer boundaries. If a mineral has sharp edges, the outer  rim will usually be the same on BESI and on the display screen of the  Quantimet. However, many grains have sloping edges. These minerals have  a rim which gradually becomes vague on BESI and vanishes if the surface of  the grain is situated below the detection limit for backscattered electrons.  This vague rim of the mineral grain has lighter to darker grey colours on  BESI and it are these darker colours which may cause detection difficulties  for the Quantimet if no help is given by the image-editor. The external cover-  ing of the mineral grain is done by comparison of the image on the display  screen of the Quantimet with BESI. Shape analysis of mineral grains has thus  become possible using the BESI-Quantimet technique. An example of the  image~editing of three mineral grains is given m Fig. 3.    Theoretical aspects of shape measurements with the BESI-Quantimet tech-  nique    Parameters used for shape analysis  Five parameters have been used to characterize the shape of mineral  grains, viz. area (A), perimeter (Pe), largest and smallest Feret's diameters  (Fmax and Fmin), lobation ratio (Lr) and indentation ratio (It). Of these,  the Feret's diameter is a diameter which can be measured in a horizontal,  vertical and two diagonal directions. The largest and smallest Feret's dia-  meters are indicated by Fmax and Fmin.  The lobation ratio or "Lappungsquotient" was mentioned by Kubiena et  al. (1961) and used for shape analysis of pores and soil aggregates by Beck-  mann (1962). The latter author defined Lr as the ratio between the peri-  meter of the actual surface of a soft component and the circumference of a    308    Fig, 3. Different steps in xmage-editing of three mineral grains. (a) A grain with shallow  and discontinuous internal pores; a thin outer layer is not present, (h) Internally covered.  (c) A second gram with a thin outer layer but without internal porosity. (d) Externally  covered (e) The third grain with internal pores and a thin outer layer (f) Internally and  externally covered mineral grain    309    circle with the same area. Small values of Lr approach the form of a circle  (Lr = 1), whereas larger values are associated with more lobate forms. The  indentation ratio can be regarded as a ratio which is similar to the lobation  ratio, whereby indentations are used instead of lobes.    The relation between area, perimeter and lobation ratio  The definition of the lobation ratio (Lr) allows this ratio to be related to  the area (A) and perlmenter (Pe) using the equation:  Lr= / 1   X A/Pe2  This is a significant relation between Lr and A/Pe2 ratios, because both  have been used for shape analysis. Seven shape classes were defined by Beck-  mann (1962), using the lobation ratio and light microscopy for shape anal-  ysis of aggregates and pores (cf. Fig. 4). Three shape classes, which axe not  indicated in Fig. 4, were used to define the shape of pores (voids) by Quanti-  met (Jongerius, 1974; Murphy et al., 1977; Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981).  This was done by measuring the area and perimeter of the pores and by cal-  culating the A/Pe2 ratio used for shape analysis. Rounded voids had A/Pe2  i&gt;40, vughy vo]ds ratios &lt;40 and/&gt;15, and planar and digitate voids ratios  &lt;15.    A/Pe2  x 1000    80-  70  ~RP EDGED"  60.  50-   VERY  WEAKLY   "~  40-     LOBATE  30-  WEAKLY  20  i1       MODERATELY LOBATE  1                  STRONGLY LOBATE                ~~  VERY STRONGLY LOBATE  EXTREMELY LOBATE                            ~~  100            lg0             2bO            2;0            abo   45O ' sbo ' BSO '  500     700     900  Lr  Fig. 4. Shape classes as defined by Beckm~mn (1962). These are based on the lobation  ratio ("Lappungsquotient") and were related to area (A) and perimeter (Pe)determined  by Quantimet (cf. text). "Sharp-edged" is indicated with inverted comm~, because MI  measured mineral grains of this shape class had no sharp edges and were rounded.    310    If the two shape classifications are compared, there is little conformation  of terms. A problem may even exist, because rounded voids had an A/Pe2  ~&gt;40 and Beckmann lndmated that "sharp-edged" forms were present with  Lr = 1.2 to 1.0, equivalent with A/Pe2 ratios of 55 to 79. In wew of this,  it was necessary to have a closer look at the shapes of two-dimensional  fzgures (forms) and how these are related to each other.    Shape analysis of two-dtmensional figures  Due to the equation given above, Lr and A/Pe2 ratios could be related to  each other and the curve in Fig. 4 could be drawn. Shape analysis of mineral  grains, which zs discussed in the section on results, indicated that various  grains with different forms can have the same A/Pez ratio and are therefore  plotted m the same point of the curve m Fig. 4 (cf. Fig. 9). To explain this  phenomenon, a theoretmai model was made m which two-dimensional forms  change from a disc (circle) to a line (Figs. 5 and 6). Three horizontal se-  quences of forms with rounded and sharp edges are shown in Fig. 5, whereas  forms with lobes and indentures were l~rtrayed on a curve (a curve which  suggests the curve m Fzg. 4) m Fig. 6.  All figures start at the left wzth a disc that has an A/Pe2 ratio of 79. This  is the ratio for a disc with a circle as periphery. If the disc is hand-drawn,  the perimeter becomes more irregular, the perimeter increases and the ratio  may decrease to 74. The form of the disc can change in various ways (cf.  Figs. 5 and 6) until a line zs reached with an A/Pez ratio of one. If this line  is sufficiently thm and long enough, the ratio may even decrease below one.  Hand-drawn hnes are usually thicker, somewhat irregular and rather short.  Consequently, the ratio can increase to about three for such hand-drawn  lines. All other two-dimensional forms, if classlfzed according to the A/Pe2  ratio, are situated on the curve of Fig. 4 between the points which represent  a circle (A/Pe2 = 79, Lr = 1) and a line (A/Pe2 = 1, Lr = 9).  Only a few figures have been drawn in Figs. 5 and 6, whereby the figures  with lobes and indentations are found m Fig. 6. A/Pe2 ratios are indicated  below each figure and a special case Is present m Fig. 5B, i.e. with the ratios  of the central three figures. The first ratio is that of a disc with one line as  a wing and the second ratio between brackets, of the disc with two wings.  The addition of a second line to the disc gave a significant decrease in the  A/Pe2 ratios.  All ratios decrease from left to right in Figs. 5 and 6. It is interesting to  note, that a few ratios are the same but represent different forms, e.g. the  figures with an A/Pez ratio of twelve of Figs. 5A, 5B and 6A. If these forms  were plotted on the curve of Fig. 4 they would all be represented by the  same point. A second example, with A/Pe2 ratios of seven, is given in Figs.  5C and 6A. This point would be plotted below the point with a ratio of  twelve on the curve of Fig. 4.  The above result indicates that, with the use of A/Pe2 ratios for shape  analysis, various forms (figures) can be represented by one point of the curve    311    in Fig. 4; except for the extremities of the curve occupmd by the disc (circle)  and line. To subdivide the figures of one point of the curve, other parameters  than area, perimeter, or lobation ratio should be used. This can usually be  done by measuring Feret's diameters, i.e. the Fmax/Fmin ratio.    II    63    I  4r    12                1    79    44 (30)    12(6)    29(16)    16    7              I    70    Fig. 5. From dmc (circle) to line for two-dimensional forms with rounded and sharp-  edged peripheries. The values of A/Pe2 ratios are indicated underneath the figures. The  two numbers in B, underneath three figures, represent the value of the A/Pe2 ratio of a  circle with one line and of a circle with two hnes (between brackets).    79    63    79    64    @Q    1    Fig. 6. From disc (circle) to line for two-dimensional figures with lobes (A) and indent-  ures (B). The values of A/Pe2 ratios are indicated underneath the figures.    312    Shape classification of two-dimensional figures    Shape classification of two-dimensional figures with A/Pe2 ratios can be  understood best if attention is paid to the periphery or perimeter of such  forms. Small changes in the perimeter, rather than small changes in the area,  will result in changes of the A/Pe2 ratio. This increase in perimeter can be  done in various ways (cf. Figs. 5 and 6). For example, in Fig. 5B, a disc can  obtain a small ratio if sufficient lines (wings) are added to it. In Fig. 5B, the  area of the disc was decreased simultaneously. However, the disc can also be  maintained at the size of the left figure m Fig. 5B. By adding larger lines  (wings) to the larger disc, the perimeter can be made to mcrease so much,  that the disc shlfts to the right of Fig. 5B. During such a shift, A/Pe2 ratios  can be arrived at which are equal to the ones associated with the smaller  discs in Fig. 5B. In other words, one can shift a large disc with larger wings  from the left to the right In Fig. 5B until it has the same A/Pe2 ratio as a  smaller disc with smaller wings. These two figures (forms) can then be  plotted as one point in Fig. 4.  The above manipulation can also be done with other figures. In Fig. 5A,  the first three figures are a disc, a square and a rectangle. The addition of  hnes (wings) to the disc can decrease the A/Pe2 ratio to that of the square or  rectangle and, if desired, even farther to the right in Fig. 5A. If lines are  added to the square, the A/Pe2 ratio can be brought above the rectangle and  reach the same ratio. In this way, one has placed three figures at the place in  which only the rectangle is visible In Fig. 5A, i.e. the rectangle itself, the  square with wings, and the disc with longer wings. All three figures have an  A/Pe2 ratio of 41 and represent figures of the same point of the curve in  Fig. 4.  The increase In perimeter of a certain figure can also be obtained by ad-  ding lobes (Fig. 6A) or indentations (Fig. 6B) to a central disc. Such lobes  and indentations can have various forms and sizes. It is understandable, how-  ever, that a large number of very small lobes and indentations will increase  the perimeter of a form more than is done by the addition of a few lobes  with a large area. The consequence was already indicated above with the  hand-drawn circle, that had an A/Pe2 ratio of 74 mstead of 79 for the ideally  drawn circle (disc).  The lobe w~th a larger area can also change form towards a spme, e.g. the  figures with A/Pe2 ratms of twelve and seven in Fig. 6A. The longer and  thinner the spine, the more it approaches the form of a line and thus the  larger the perimeter and the smaller the area of the spine. By using this prin-  ciple, one can move the figure with a ratio of twelve to the right in Fig. 6A.  This is done by making the spmes longer and thinner, whereby the core of  the figure, a disc, can be maintained at the same size. In this way this figure  can also obtain an A/Pe2 ratio of seven instead of twelve. The result is that  two different forms are found for a point on the curve of Fig. 4 with an  A/Pe2 ratio of seven.    313    The above examples should suffice to explain why so many two-dimen-  sional figures (forms) can be represented by one point on the curve of Fig. 4  and how such forms are related to each other. The explanation on two-  dimensional form-developments, using A/Pe2 ratios, also explains why the  use of names in shape classifications can only serve very specific objectives.  If one point of the curve of Fig. 4 can represent many two-dimensional  forms, this means that a whole shape class -- which occupies a part of the  length of the curve in Fig. 4 -- represents an enormous number of forms. It  also means that many unexpected shapes may m reality form a part of a  shape class; forms whmh at first sight have no relation to each other.  The theoretical model for two-dimensional forms, in which A/Pe2 ratios  and lobation ratios have been used, together with the results of measure-  ments of the 54 mineral grains (cf. section on results) and of shape analysis  done of pores and soft aggregates in earlier rmcromorphological studies, gave  the diagram in Fig. 7. This diagram is proposed as a working-model for two-  dimensional shape classification of soil constituents in thin sections of soils.  Only Roman numerals are given for shape classes. The only shape class-  boundaries which are recognizable at this point of the paper, are the ones  used in the study of pores (voids), i.e. A/Pe2 = 40 and 15. The other  boundary-ratios were mainly chosen after studying the shapes of 54 silt-sized  mineral grains which are discussed in the next section. The shape classifica-  tion of two dimensional forms (Fig. 7) is only a proposal which could be  A/Pe2  x 1000  80-  75-  63-  III  56-  40  3O  v,  VII  vm                             ~~  0  1 O0            1 '50            2'00            2'50            3 '(30   4 ;0 ' 6 fO0 ' 8 ;0 r  5 O0   7 O0   9 O0  Lr, lr    Fig. 7. Suggested shape classes for two-dimensional forms. The classes can be used for  A/Pe2 ratios alone, or in combination with lobation and indentation ratios.    314    used as a working-model until more data on shapes of soil constituents have  been obtained.    RESULTS    Area and perimeter    54 silt-sized mineral grains were investigated in this study and their area  and perimeter have been plotted m Fig. 8. Most grams demonstrated an in-  crease m perimeter when the area increased. Jongerms (1974) used the  A/Pe2 ratio for the characterization of the shape of voids and the same is  done here for mineral grains. The A/Pe2 ratios of the 54 mineral grmns have  been plotted on the curve of Fig. 9, which is part of the curve of Fig. 4, be-  cause no ratios of silt grains fell into the other shape classes. Beckmann's  names for shape classes have been indicated in Fig. 9.    A{~,rn21  lO0!  8O  60-    40~    OI  - "  0  10    i   r  3O    A(um2)  1100!    B  900  700t           %~i' C_  ~00~                           ~000l  !  300 ~                                       1 500  L--'  r    ,         100                                         1000     i    i    p    I    I    [    ~    I  50            0  50    1(]0  '  1,50  r  200        0 150    200    250    300  Pe(~m)                                         PP(/~ rn)                                          Pe(#m)    Fig 8 The relation between area and perimeter is illustrated in diagrams A to C The peri-  meter usually increases w~th area but there are exceptions.    The bar-scale at the top of Fig. 9 indicates in which area class each of the  54 mineral grains of Fig. 9 is situated. The numbers of the grains start at the  left of the bar-scale and increase, together with the area, towards the right.  The total number of grams in each area class can also be read. The largest  number of mineral grains was measured in the area classes 5--10 pm2 and  500--1000 #m2. The numbers on the curve in the diagram indicate that larger  and smaller grains can be present in each of the shape classes.  A number of representative micrographs of silt grains, from each of the  shape classes m Fig. 9, is given in Fig. 10 and Fig. 11, e and f. The internally  and externally image-edited grains of Fig. 10, a--d represent Beckmann's  "sharp-edged" shape class, Fig. 10, e--h the very weakly lobate shape class,  Fig. 10, 1--1 the weakly lobate shape class, and Fig. 11, e and f the moderate-  ly lobate shape class.    315    A/Pe2  x 1000  B0-  70-  60- "S H:::  50  40.  30  20  10-  0  O0    4,23  "SHARP ~10,11  EDGED"'~5  49  ~,6, 24  ~4  VERY WEAKLY    __~IB 17 21  2o- "~s~:]7  LOBATE           7~.~1~ 2S,26  9'12~ 3"'~ 29,35,54    NUMBERS OF MINERAL GRAINS  ,       I  26o   ~o   ,~o   r~o ''/lobo  2ooo  3ooo  AREA (.=m2)    13J "~l,~l,,27_,3B ,47  18 28,33,44  30~....~.,.,..~34,40  ~aB  WEAKLY LOBATE                                   ~,~,a~,~B  53 -7"~ .41,46  ~      ~   48  MODERATELY LOBATE                                  31,42-"    1'10   1 '20   1 '30   1 '40   1 50   1 '60   1 '70   1'80   1 '90   2100   2'10   2'20   2'30   2 40  kr    Fig 9 Part of the diagram shown in Fig. 4 on a different scale. All measured mineral  grains are mdmated with a number which corresponds to the ones on the bar-scale. Thts  bar-scale mdmates to whmh area-class each number belongs.    Each of the mineral grains in Figs. 10 and 11 has a number. This is also  given because it allows the use of Fig. 9, These are: 14 (Fig. 10a), 10 (Fig.  10b), 19 (Fig. 10c), 5 (Fig. 10d), 49 (Fig. 10e), 24 (Fig. 10f), 51 (Fig. 10g),  25 (Fig. 10h), 28 (Fig. 10i), 30 (Fig. 10j), 40 (Fig. 10k), 41 (Fig. 101), 43  (Fig. lle) and 39 (Fig. llf).  A few remarks can be made concerning the shape of the silt grains and the  names of shape classes given by Beckmann (1962). Rounded and egg-shaped  minerals, which could be weakly lobate, were present in Fig. 10, a--d. These  forms were not "sharp-edged", as is the name of the shape class to which the  silt grains belong. Sharp-edged grains and grains with lobes were present in  Fig. 10, e--h; the very weakly lobate shape class. One gram in this class had  larger lobes (cf. Fig. 10g) but most of the lobes were still weakly developed.  One or more sharp edges were found on the periphery of most grains. Beck-  mann's term weakly lobate seems difficult to apply to the shape of the mine-  ral grmns in Fig. 10, i--l. The lobes of the silt grains have become larger and  several have an irregular form. Embayments are present and some of the  mineral grains have indentations. Two representatives of the moderately lo-  bate shape class (Fig. 11, e and f)   had very different forms. Grain lle  demonstrates an increase in indentation and many lobes, whereas gram llf  is very elongated, weakly platy, with several smaller lobes.    316    Fig. I0. Examples of shape classes in Fig. 9 Rounded to weakly lobated mineral grams m  the "sharp-edged" shape class (a--d); sharp edges and lobes in the very weakly lobate  shape class (e--h); and the latter forms and indentations m the weakly lobate shape class  (1--1). Representatives of the moderately lobate shape class are present m Fig 11, e and f    Feret's diameters    The shape of most mineral grains can be characterized by using A/Pe2  ratios, the lobation ratio and micrographs. There are grains, however, which  have different shapes but the same A/Pe2 or Lr ratio. Grains with these char-  actenstics are shown in Fig. 11, a--d and data from measurements given in  Table III. In such cases, one can introduce Feret's diameters (Jongerius and  Bisdom, 1981). The largest and smallest grain diameters can be determined  together with those at angles of 45and 135 For shape analysis, the ratio  between the largest Feret's diameter (Fmax) and the smallest one (Fmin) is  taken.    317    Fig. 11. Shapes of mineral grains in Table III The Fmax/Fmm (the largest and the smal-  lest Feret's diameter) ratio can be used to separate grain-pairs a and b or c and d; grains  which have similar A/Pe2 ratios but a different shape. Fmax/Fmln can also be used to  separate elongated forms of mineral grains (f) from grains with a smaller Feret's ratio (e).    Grain-pair a and b in Fig. 11 has virtually the same A/Pe2 ratio, i.e. 34 and  33 and Lr of 1.53 and 1.55 (Table III). If Fmax/Fmin is determined these  are 1.49 and 1.72. The same can be done for grain-pair c and d of Fig. 11 (cf.  Table III). Consequently, grains with a similar A/Pe2 ratio could be separated  from each other by usmg the ratio Fmax/Fmin.    318    TABLE III    Separation of mineral grams with virtually the same (grain-pairs a--b and c--d) A/Pe:  ratios and Lr values by using Fmax/Fmin, the ratio of the largest and smallest Feret's  diameter, grains e and f axe minerals with the highest lobation values (smallest A/Pe2  ratios) in Fig. 9, of which the elongated form of mineral f is well expressed in a high  Fmax/Fmin ratio    Mineral      Mineral      A            Pe           A/Pe2  grain code   grain        (urn2 )       (urn)        x 1000  in Fig. 11   in Fig. 9    Lr       Fmax/Fmm    a             44           542          126          34           1.53     I 49  b            47           717          146          33           1 55     1.72  c            41           515         157         21           1 99    1 03  d          46         591        169        21         1.97    2.55  e          43         539        175        18         2.13    1 25  f             39           410          169          14           2.36    4.72    A,Pe2  x I000  70  ,1 03  50J               ~&amp;l 33,1 40,1 31  I VERY .          /    ....  ~ UOn~_Y',%1 67,2 O0           /  2 00,1 43,1 81 ~' 1~I,.~,.1  404  .....  c           ~ =,-%.~-~%'n~@,lJ _6B,1 93  I   z:~1 88~,42,1""~, ~n 41,1 65  2_.=~J C~k,1~29,1 36,1 72  I                      1 25 1 63 2 24.1 53 )'~-,..~ 2 59 1 72  304                                '    '~'    2 02  WEAKLY LOBATE          202 1 1~   _ 3~03 2 55  263,1  20                                               "~'- ~'-1~421~6~" ~="f'~3   1 25  MODERATELY LOBATE                               ~2  10-    O0   1'10   1'20   130   1140   1~0   160   170   1RO   190   200   210   ?20   ~7~1    40  Lr    Fig. 12. Fmax/Fmin ratios of individual mineral grains; their position corresponds with  that of the 54 mineral grains in Fig. 9. Ratios  of 2.00 (suggested as a minimal ratio for  elongated or platy forms) and higher are underhned    Another possibzlity for using Fmax/Fmin, is to differentiate between  elongated (platy) and rounded forms. An elongated grain is present in Fzg.  llf and a more rounded one in Fig. lle. The elongated grain has a ratio of  4.72, whereas the grain m Fzg. 11e has only 1.25. Elongated forms of mme-  ral grains m Fig. 11 seem to start m gram b with a ratio of 1.72. A better ex-    319    ample of an elongated form is found in grain d with a ratio of 2.55 and the  best one in f with the very high ratio of 4.72. No elongated forms can be  distinguished in Fig. 8, a, c and e with Fmax/Fmin of 1.49, 1.03 and 1.25.  This seems to indicate that the ratio Fmax/Fmin can separate elongated  mineral grmns from the ones which are more rounded or quadrangular.  The next step was to observe all the mmrographs of the 54 silt grains and  to plot all Fmax/Fmm ratms ,n Fig. 12. It was found that elongated forms  are clearly dlscernable at Fmax/Fmin = 2.00 and higher. This value is on the  safe side and it may well be that a somewhat smaller value will be favoured  m the future. The plotted ratios in Fig. 12 show that the Fmax/Fmin ratms  of two and more may occur in all shape classes, except the one called "sharp-  edged" by Beckmann (1962). The mineral grains in Fig. 12 have been  plotted on the same curve and in the same points as in Fig. 9. The numbers  of the pomts with Fmax/Fmm ratios can therefore be found in Fig. 9.  The first mineral gram with Fmax/Fmin = 2.00 occurred in Beckmann's  very weakly lobate shape class. It is gra, n number 8 of Fig. 9. A second grain  with number 37 had the same ratio, etc. Only the very elongated forms of  minerals which were found in this study occur m Figs. 11f and 3d. Both  grains, which are virtually platy, have Fmax/Fmm &gt;4, viz. 4.72 (Fig. 11f)  and 4.22 (Fig. 3d). The rounded grains m Beckmann's "sharp-edged" shape  class had an Fmax/Fmm of 1.46 or less (Fig. 12).    Shape classzfication of mmeral grains and voids    The suggested shape classification (Fig. 7) has already been introduced as  a working-model in the section on materials and methods together with the  theoretical background. Two boundary-ratios of A/Pe2 = 40 and 15 have al-  ready been included in Fig. 7 and are based on shape classification of voids.  What has to be explamed now is the reason why the other boundaries in  Fig. 7 were suggested; these are mainly based on knowledge obtained m the  present investigation.  For reasons whmh have already been explained, shape classes are indicated  using Roman numerals. Class I has the upper boundary at A/Pe2 = 79 (Lr =  1.00); this represents a circle (disc) which is smooth. The lower boundary  was placed at A/Pe2 -- 75 (Lr = 1.05). This can be a circle with a somewhat  Irregular periphery, but also a polygon with a large number of angles. A regu-  lar polygon with eight angles has a ratio of about 75. Both rounded and  sharp-edged forms can therefore be present. Very small lobes and indenta-  tions may also occur.  The lower boundary of class II was placed at A/Pe2 = 63 (Lr = 1.12}. This  represents a square with sharp edges and other forms. The lobation ratio and  the mdentation ratio are still small and so are most lobes and notches of the  mineral grams.  Class III has its lower boundary at A/Pe2 = 56 (Lr = 1.19). This is a rect-  angle with a 1 : 2 ratio for the sides. It was chosen because it has Fmax/    320    Fmin = 2.00. This point on the curve of Fig. 7 should represent the first  elongated (somewhat platy) form on the curve. Rounded forms with smaller  lobes and indentures were still dominantly represented in the invest:gated  mineral grains.  Class IV is the first in whmh sharp-edged mineral grmns have been found.  The sharp edges could occupy a larger part of the periphery of the grams.  Rounded forms had decreased significantly m the silt grains and were large-  ly replaced by lobes of different sizes. Indentations were present but, as was  the case with the first three classes, attracted less attention than the lobe-  forms. The lower boundary of this shape class was placed at A/Pe2 = 40 (Lr  = 1.41); a boundary whmh is the upper limit of vughs and the lower one of  more or less rounded voids. The first elongated mineral with Fmax/Fmm =  2.00 was observed in this shape class and had A/Pe2 = 45.  Class V has a lower boundary at A/Pe2 = 30 (Lr -- 1.63). It is an arbitrary  boundary between the rat:os 40 and 15 in whmh vughy voids are present.  The only reason is to obtain a smaller shape class. Indentations on mineral  grains attracted attention for the first time. The indentations could have  various sizes and forms. Lobes, some of them rather large, were also found.  Elongated grains were present. Sharp edges could occupy several discontinu-  ous and small parts of the periphery of mineral grains or one or more longer  distances.  Class VI has a lower boundary which coincides w:th that of vughs, v:z.  A/Pe2 = 15 (Lr = 2.30). Indentations and lobes have become somewhat more  irregular than in class V. Indentations of mineral grams could cut deep Into  these. More grains than m class V were elongated and had an Fmax/Fmin  ratio greater than two. Sharp edges seemed to occupy discontinuous and  small parts of the penphery of the grains and fewer longer distances than in  class V. Theoretically, however, platy forms w:th sharp edges can be present  in this class.  Class VIII has been separated from the former class because, like class I, it  vo:ds from planar and digitate voids. The lower boundary of this class was  placed at A/Pe2 = 5 (Lr = 3.99). Platy forms are common, but star-shaped  forms can also occur according to theoretical considerations explained in the  section on materials and methods. Cracks with smooth or more irregular  walls will fall into this class as long as they are thin. As soon as the crack is  widened, to give a relatively large area, it will form part of class VI.  Class VIII has been separated from the former class because, like class I, it  should represent some extreme forms which end as a line with an A/Pe2 = 1  (Lr = 8.92). Long and thin platy forms are represented. Theoretically, how-  ever, a circle (disc) with one or more long to very long needles can also fall  into this class. All forms with a very large perimeter, compared with the en-  closed area, can be placed in this class.    321    CONCLUSIONS    Shape analyms of mineral grains in thin sections of soils can be done with  BESI and Quantimet. Manual work with the image-editor of the Quantimet  720 is necessary to define the often complex peripheral forms of the grains.  All silt grains whmh were represented in Fig. 1 were measured, except those  which extended beyond the boundary of the backscattered electron scanning  image. The magnifications which could be used for the shape analysis of the  grains were 240 and 480. In the present case 480 was chosen because  this allowed an easy internal and external covenng of the mineral grains with  the image~ditor.  Area (A), perimeter (Pe) and Feret's diameters of 54 silt-sized mineral  grams were measured. The lobation ratio (Lr) could be related to the A/Pe2  ratio with a formula. The indentation ratio (Ir), if defined in the same way  as the lobation ratio, can also be related to the A/Pe2 ratio. A diagram was  made of A/Pe2 and Lr, and provisional shape classes were introduced. All  forms of the measured mineral grains could be distinguished indiwdually us-  ing A/Pe2 and Fmax/Fmin. Reproduction of the shape of individual mineral  grams is not possible with these parameters, however, and micrographs of  each mineral therefore remain necessary.  Eight shape classes, the boundaries of which were based on knowledge ob-  tained during former shape analysis studies of voids, the present mvestiga-  tion of silt-sized mineral grains and from a theoretical model, are given in  Fig. 7. It was demonstrated with the theoretical model that all two-  dimensional forms can be placed between two extremes, i.e. a circle (A/Pe2 =  79) and a line (A/Pe2 = 1). A number of examples was given in the theoreti-  cal model of the changes m forms with decreasing A/Pe2 ratios. This allowed  some understanding of the type of two-dimensional figures which can be ex-  pected in certain shape classes, i.e. in a certain range of A/Pe2 ratios. Mea-  surements also mdicated that the same Fmax/Fmin ratios could occur m  different shape classes and that these were therefore not specific for one  shape class. The Fmax/Fmin ratio, however, can be used to separate elon-  gated (planar forms) (Fmax/Fmin &gt;~ 2) from other forms.  The present study has succeeded in relating different two-dimensional  forms, based on A/Pe2 measurements. Relatively few of the possible shapes  were, however, encountered in the present investigation and consequently  the suggested boundaries of the shape classes in Fig. 7 may have to be  changed when more shape data become available dunng subsequent studies  of soil constituents. It could be practical to introduce different boundaries  for shape analysis of minerals, voids, soil aggregates, etc. However, this will  not change the pnnciple of two-dimensional shape analysis whmh has been  discussed. The present shape study also indmates that shape analysis may  require relatively large magnifications, due to the necessity of correct peri-  meter measurements of especially smaller soil particles and voids.    322    REFERENCES    Beckmann, W., 1962. Zur Mikromorphometne von Hohlraumen und Aggregaten im  Boden. Z. Pflanzenernahr, Dung. Bodenk., 99 (144): 129--139  Bisdom, E.B.A and Thiel, F., 1981 Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-  EDXRA. In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks  1st Workshop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed  Soil Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A., Boersma, O., Jager, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1977. The func-  tion of dlfferent types of macropores during saturated flow through four swelhng soil  horizons. Soil Sci. Soc. Am J., 41(5): 945--950.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1979 Calculation of saturated hydraul-  ic conductivity of some pedal clay soils using micromorphometric data. Soil Sci Soc  Am. J., 43(2): 261--264.  Ismail, S.N.A., 1975. Micromorphometrm soil-porosity characterization by means of  electro-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720). Neth Soil Surv. Inst, Wageningen,  Soil Surv. Pap., 9:104 pp.  Jongerius, A., 1974. Recent developments in soil micromorphology. In: G.K. Rutherford  (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proceedings of the 4th International Working Meeting on  Soil Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont. pp. 67--  83.  Jongerius, A. and Btsdom, E.B.A., 1981. Porosity measurements using the Quantimet  720 on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils In: E.B A  Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks 1st Workshop of the  International  Working-Group  on  Submicroscopy  of  Undisturbed Soil Materials  (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documenta-  tion (Pudoc) Wageningen, pp. 207--216.  Kubiena, W., Beckmann, W. and Geyger, E., 1961. Zur Methodtk der Photogram-  metrischen Strukturanalyse des Bodens. Z. Pflanzenernahr., Diing. Bodenk , 92(137 ).  116--126.  Murphy, C.P., Bullock, P. and Turner, R.H., 1977 The measurement and charactermation  of voids in soil thin sections by image analysis, Part I. Principles and techniques Soil  Scl., 28 (3): 498--508                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractSilt-sized mineral grains were analysed for their shapes or forms in thin sections of soils using backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) and an image analyzer (Quantimet 720). This work was done with an image-editor and required manual editing of the shape of mineral grains on the display screen of the Quantimet. Shape analysis of coarse and fine silt grains could thus be performed at magnifications of x 240 and x 480.The shape of the mineral grains could be characterized by five parameters: area (A), perimeter (Pe), largest and smallest Feret's diameters (Fmax and Fmin), lobation ratio (Lr) and indentation ratio (Ir). A relation was found, however, between the APe2 ratio and the Lr and Ir ratios. Consequently, shape analysis of mineral grains can be done by measuring three of the five parameters, i.e. A, Pe and Fmax/Fmin. These parameters, however, are still not be able to reproduce the shape of individual mineral grains and images of them therefore remain necessary.Several of the 54 mineral grains were found to have different shapes but the same APe2 ratio. An explanation for this phenomenon is given by using a theoretical model in which two-dimensional forms change their shapes from a circle (APe2 = 79) to a line (APe2 = 1). Form separation of mineral grains with the same (APe2) ratio can be done by using the FmaxFmin ratio.The measurement of the shape of the mineral grains, the theoretical model and observation of the micrographs of the individual mineral grains, made it possible to draw a diagram with shape classes which can be used for shape classification purposes. Knowledge gathered in soil micromorphology on shape analysis of pores and soil aggregates has also been used to obtain boundaries of shape classes in the diagram. The present study is intended both as a proposal as to how two-dimensional shape classification can possibly be done, and as a work-model. The boundaries of the shape classes can easily be adjusted if data from forthcoming studies require it.