Geoderma, 24 (1980) 275--281                                                   275  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Abbott, P.L. Paleolithic artifacts or naturally-broken quartzite clasts, San Diego area, California [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 377,  1979. The Geological Society of America, 92rid annual meeting.  Ajaty, G. L.; Ketner, P.; and Duvigneand, P. Terrestrial primary production and phytomass: in Scope  13; The global carbon cycle (Bolin, B., editor; et aL), p. 129-181, illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons,  Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  Amundson, D. C.; and Wright, H. E., Jr. Forest changes in Minnesota at the end of the Pleistocene:  Ecological Monographs (Ecological Society of America). Durham, North Carolina., Vol. 49, No. 1, p.  1-16, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Anderson, L. W. Weathering rinds as a relative age indicator and late glacial chronology of Mt.  Timpanogos, Wasatch Range, Utah [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 265-266, 1979.  The GeologicalSociety of America, Rocky Mountain  Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Anderson, T. F. Oxygen isotope evidence for the low-temperature alteration of oceanic basalts; a  reassessment [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol.  11, No. 7, p. 379, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92rid annual meeting.  Atzet, T. Description and classification of the forests of the upper Illinois River drainage of southwestern  Oregon: 222 p., Doctoral, 1979, Oregon State Univ., Corvallis, Oreg. arailablefro~'Univ. Microfilms.  Axelrod, D. I.  Age and origin of Sonoran desert vegetation:  California Academy of Sciences,  Occasional Papers. San Francisco., No. 132, 74 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Babu, D. K.; and van Gennehten, M.T. An initial value problem for the horizontal in/titration of water:  Water Resources Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 867-  872, illus., 1979.  Bacon, J. R.; and Ure, A.M. The correction of interference effects in the determination of the rare earth  elements and hafnium by spark-source mass spectrometry: Analytica Chimica Acta. Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 105, p. 163-176, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Bartlett, D. S. Spectral reflectance of tidal wetland plant canopies and implications for remote sensing:  253 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Delaware, Newark, Del. available frotrr Univ. Microfilms.  Bennett, B. G. Environmental aspects of americium: 216 p., Doctoral, 1979, New York Univ., New  York, N.Y. available frorrr Univ. Microfilms.  Berglund, B. E. The deglaciation of southern Sweden 13,500-10,000 B.P.: Boreas; An International  Journal of Quaternary Geology. Oslo., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 89-117, tables, charts, sketch maps, 1979.  Blrkeland, P. W.; Burke, R. M.; and Walker, A. L. Variation in chemical parameters of Quaternary  soils with time and altitude' Sierra Nevada' Calffnia [abstr']: Geological Society of America, Abstracts  with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 388, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, 92rid  annual meeting.  Bouwer, H. Soil water hysteresis as a cause of delayed yield from unconfined aquifers: Water Resources  Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 965-966, illus., 1979.  Bowers, P.M. The Cantwell ash bed, a Holocene tephra in the central Alaska Range: Alaska, Division  of Geological and Geophysical Surveys, Geologic Report (formerly Alaska, Division of Mines and  Geology, Geologic Report). College., No. 61 (Short notes on Alaskan geology, 1978), p. 19-24, illus. (incl.  tables, sketch map), 1979.'    276    Boyle, R. W. The geochemistry of gold and its deposits (together with a chapter on geochemical  prospecting for the element): Canada, Geological Survey, Bulletin. Ottawa., No. 280, 584 p. (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps, tables, plates), 1979.  Brakenridge, G. R. The impact of climatic change on floodplain sedimentation, soil formation, and  eolian activity in southern Missouri [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Voi. 11, No. 7, p. 393, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Brakensiek, D.L. Empirical equations for some soil hydraulic properties: Water Resources Research  (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 989-990, tables, 1979.  Bramryd, T. The effects of man on the biogeochemicai cycle of carbon in terrestrial ecosystems: in  Scope 13; The global carbon cycle (Bolin, B., editor; et aL), p. 183-218, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map),  John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  Browning, G.M. Development for and of the universal soil loss equation: in Universal soil loss equation;  past, present, and future (Peterson, A. E., editor; et aL), Soil Science Society of America, Special  Publication. Madison, Wisconsin., No. 8, p. 1-5, 1979.  Bruekner, W. D. Geomorphology of the Avalon Peninsula, Newfoundland; a guide hook comprising  itineraries and explanatory notes for six field trips followed by a systematic summary: Newfoundland  and Labrador, Mineral Development Division, Report. St. John's., Vol. 79-4, 42 p., illus., 1979.  Burns, S. F. Influence of snow cover on alpine soil distribution of the Indian Peaks region, Colorado  Front Range [abstr.]:  in Abstracts for the Fifty-fifth annual meeting of the Southwestern &amp; Rocky  Mountain Division, American Association for the Advancement of Science and the Colorado-Wyoming  Academy of Science including the Colorado-Wyoming Chapter of the American Association of Physics  Teachers and the Colorado Chapter of the National Association of Geology Teachers (American  Association for the Advancement of Science), Colorado-Wyoming Academy of Sciences, Journal., Vol.  11, No. 1, p. 57, 1979.  Burns, S. F. Buried soils beneath alpine snowbanks may date the end of the Altithermal [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 267-268,  1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section. 32nd annual meeting.  Butzer, K. Implications of Border Cave skeletal remains for later Pleistocene human evolution: Current  Anthropology; a World Journal of the Sciences of Man (Wenner-GTen Foundation for Anthropological  Research). Chicago., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 28, 1979.  Campbell, J. A. Nutrient losses and related processes in a seasonally-operated septic bed soil under  favourable conditions: Doctoral, 1979, McMaster Univ., Hamilton, Ont., Canada. amilablefrortL'Univ.  Microfilms.  Carrara, P. E.; and Ebling, S.J. Rates of surface lowering and wind aggradation as determined from  buried trees, Browns Park, Colorado [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 268, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain  Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Colman, S. M. Clay minerals in weathering rinds and impfications for rates and mechanisms of B-  horizon formation [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado.,  Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 404, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Custer, S. G.; Kinnard, P.; and Wyatt, G. M. Regional identification of saline seep recharge areas in  Stillwater County, Montana [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 269, 1979. The Geological Society ofdmerica, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd  annual meeting.  Daneeis, P.; and Vogel, D. E. Acid igneous rocks of the Stavelot Massif, a case of pre-Hercynian  weathering: Geologie; Bulletin de la Societe Beige de Geologie. Brussels., Vol. 87, No. 3-4, p. 215-222,  illus. (incl. tables), 1978 [1979].  Deelman, ,L C.  Low-temperature synthesis of anatase (TiO2):. Neues Jahrbuch fuer Mineralogie,  Monatshefte. Stuttgart., No. 6, p. 253-261, 1979.  Deevey, E. S.; Rice, D. S.; Rice, P. M.; et al. Mayan urbanism; impact on a tropical karat environment:  Science (American Association for the Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., Vol. 206, No. 4416,  p. 298-306, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.    277    Dethier, D. P. (investigator). Geology and limnology of the Alpine Wilderness Area [abstr.]: U.S.  Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1150, p. 90, 1979.  Dickinson, K. A. (investigator). Uranium and thorium content in weathering profiles of the Catahoula  Tuff, South Texas coastal plain [abstr.]: U. S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia.,  No. 1150, p. 44, 1979.  Dickinson, K. A. (investigator). Uranium in central Colorado soil profiles [abstr.]: U. S. Geological  Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1150, p. 44, 1979.  Duffee, E. M.; Allen, W. J.; and Ammons, H. C. Soil survey of Jackson County, Florida: 157 p., illus.  (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1979.  Egginton, P. A. Mudboil activity, central District of Keewatin: in Current research, Part B, Paper -  Geological Survey of Canada. Ottawa., No. 79-1B, p. 349-356, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Elvidge, C. D.; and Moore, C.B. A model for desert varnish formation [abstr.]: Geological Society of  America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 271, 1979.  The Geological  Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Euler, R. C.; Gumerman, G. J.; Karlstrom, T. N. V.; et aL The Colorado plateaus; cultural dynamics  and paleoenvironment: Science (American Association for the Advancement of Science). Washington,  D. C., Vol. 205, No. 4411, p. 1089-1101, charts, sketch maps, 1979.  Filipek, L. H.; and Owen, R.M. Geochemical associations and grain-size partitioning of heavy metals  in lacustrine sediments:  Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 26, No. 1-2, p. 105-117, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Flenley, J. R. The equatorial rain forest; a geological history:  162 p., illus., Butterworths, London,  United Kingdom, 1979.  Florin, M. B. The Younger Dryas vegetation at Kolmaarden in southern central Sweden: Boreas; An  International Journal of Quaternary Geology. Oslo., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 145-152, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), 1979.  Flynn, D. J.; and Joslin, R.V. Soil survey of Franklin County, Vermont: 176 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils  maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  Forbes, S.; Bounds, G. P.; and West, T. S. Determination of selenium in soils and plants by differential  pulse cathodic-stripping voltammetry:  Talanta; an International Journal of Analytical Chemistry.  Pergamon Press, New York -Oxford., Vol. 26, No. 6, p. 473-476, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Foster, G. R. Sediment yield from farm fields; the universal soil loss equation and on farm 208 plan  implementation: in Universal soil loss equation; past, present, and future (Peterson, A. E., editor; et aL),  Soil Science Society of America, Special Publication. Madison, Wisconsin., No. 8, p. 17-24, 1979.  Freyer, H. D. Atmospheric cycles of trace gases containing carbon: in Scope 13; The global carbon  cycle (Bolin, B., editor; et aL), p. 101-128, illus. (incl. tables), Johl~ Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1979.  Fritz, A. Pollenstratigraphische Probleme des Spaet- und Postglazials in Kaernten [Problems of pollen  stratigraphy of late and post-glacial time in Carinthia]:  in Arbeitskreis fuer Palaeobotanik und  Palynologie, Neuntes Treffen (Schaarschmidt, F., editor), Courier Forschungsinstitut Senckenberg  (Senckenbergische Naturforschende Gesellschaft). Frankfurt am Main., No. 37, p. 34-35, 1979.  Garland, G.G. Asymmetry in Drakensberg valleys; an alternative point of view: South African Journal  of Science (South African Association for the Advancement of Science). Johannesburg., Vol. 75, No. 3,  p. 138-139, illus. (incl. sect.), 1979.  Gillette, D. A.  Environmental factors affecting dust emission by wind erosion:  in Saharan dust;  mobilization, transport, deposition (Morales, C., editor), p. 71-91, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  Gough, L. P.; Shaeklette, H. T.; and Case, A.A. Element concentrations toxic to plants, animals, and  man: U. S. Geological Survey, Bulletin. Reston, Virginia., No. 1466, 80 p., 1979.  Grout, M. Amount and rate of Holocene cirque erosion, northern Sangre de Cristo Mountains, Colorado  [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6,  p. 273-274, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.    278    Guckian, W. J.; and Garcia, R.N. Soil survey of San Patricio and Aransas counties, Texas: 122 p., illus.  (incl. tables; soils maps h24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1979.  Gulleher, A. Marshes and estuaries in different latitudes: Interdisciplinary Science Reviews. Heyden  &amp; Son, London., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 158-168, illus., 1979.  Hall, R. D.; and Roy, W.R. Weathering characteristics and soft development of glacial deposits at Bull  Lake, Wyoming [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado.,  Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 274, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual  meeting.  Hauge, C. J.; Furniss, M. J.; and Euphrat, F. D. Soil erosion in California's Coast Forest District:  California Geology (California Division of Mines and Geology). Sacramento., Vol. 32, No. 6, p. 120-129,  illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Hempel, L. Wenn der Boden zun Skelett abmagert; Die Lebensbasis der Mittelmeerlaender ist in Gefahr  [When soil is reduced to a skeleton; the livelihood of Mediterranean peoples is in danger]: Umschau  in Wissenschaft und Technik. Frankfurt am Main., Vol. 79, No. 13, p. 405-411 (incl. English sum.), 1979.  Holt, R. F.; Timmons, D. R.; and Burwell, R.E. Water quality obtainable under conservation practices:  in Universal soil loss equation; past, present, and future (Peterson, A. E., editor; et aL), Soil Science  Society of America, Special Publication. Madison, Wisconsin, No. 8, p. 45-53, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Hsu, W. W.; Liebhardt, W. C.; Cotnoir, L.; et a[  Potassium release by some Delaware softs:  Communications in Soft Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-Basel., Vol. 10, No. 7,  p. 1037-1055, tables, 1979.  Jackson, L. E., Jr. New evidence for the existence of an ice free corridor in the Rocky Mountain foothills  near Calgary, Alberta, during late Wisconsinan time: in Current research; Part A, Paper - Geological  Survey of Canada. Ottawa., No. 79-1A, p. 107-111, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1979.  Juo, A. S. R.; and Kang, B. T. Effect of liming on the availability of three rock phosphate sources in  two West African Ultisols: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New  York-Basel., Vol. 10, No. 7, p. 993-1003, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Kalvels, J.; and Boden, P.M. Soil survey of Dewey County, South Dakota: 108 p., illus. (incl. tables;  soils maps h24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  Kempe, S. Carbon in the rock cycle: in Scope 13; The global carbon cycle (Bolin, B., editor; et aL), p.  343-377, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  King, K., Jr.; and Bada, J.L. Effect of in situ leaching on amino acid racemisation rates in fossil bone:  Nature. London., Vol. 281, No. 5727, p. 135-137, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Kovda, V. A. Soil cover; an irreplaceable asset of nature: Interdisciplinary Science Reviews. Heyden  &amp; Son, London., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 149-154, illus., 1979.  Kujansuu, R. Maaperakartoitus [Soil mapping]: in Geologiliiton Kartoitussymposio, Geologi (Suomen  Geologinen Seura--Geologiska Sallskapet i Finland). Helsinki., Vol. 31, No. 5, p. 70-72, 1979.  Kurklnen, I.; and Niemela, J.  Rapaumahavainto kauhajoella ['Weathered bedrock in Kauhajoki]:  Ge01ogi (Suomen Geologinen Seura--Geologlska Sallskapet i Finland). Helsinki., Vol. 31, No. 5, p. 79-  81 (incl. English sum.), plate, sketch map, 1979.  La Brecque, J.J. Decomposition and determination of aluminium and silicon in Venezuelan laterites  by atomic absorption spectroscopy: Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 26, No. 3-4, p. 321-329, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Liebhardt, W. C.; Spoljaric, N.; Hsu, W. W.; et aL Potassium release characteristics and mineralogical  characteristics of some Delaware softs: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel  Dekker, New York-Basel., Vol. 10, No. 7, p. 1025-1035, tables, 1979.  Louis, H. Zur reliefentwicklung in der Oberpfalz und im Bayerisehen Wald, 1978 [Relief development  in the Upper Palatinate and the Bavarian Forest]:  Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften,  Mathematisch-Naturwissenschaftliche Klasse, Sitzungsberichte. 'Munich., Vol. 1978, p. 47-52, sketch  map, 1979.  Lundlholm, B.  Ecology and dust transl~rt:  in Saharan dust; mobilization, transport, deposition  (Morales, C., editor), p. 61-68, illus. (incl. sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1979.    279    Mabee, B. S. The use of magnetite alteration as a relative dating technique for Quaternary deposits;  preliminary results [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 278, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Seen'on, 32nd  annual meeting.  Marehand, D. E. (investigator). Quaternary deposits and soils of the Central Susquehanna Valley in  Pennsylvania [abstr.]: U. S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1150, p. 64-  65, 1979.  Mare.hand, D. E.; and Harden, J. W. (investigators). Quaternary deposits and soils, Sierra Nevada  foothills [abstr.]: U. S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1150, p. 85-86,  1979.  Meland, A. C. Soil survey of Lawrence County, South Dakota: 173 p., illus. (incl. tables; softs maps  1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, D. C., United States, 1979.  Moidenhauer, W. C. Erosion control obtainable under conservation practices: in Universal soft loss  equation; past, present, and future (Peterson, A. E., editor; et aL), Soil Science Society of America, Special  Publication. Madison, Wisconsin., No. 8, p. 33-43, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Mopper, K.; and Degens, E.T. Organic carbon in the ocean; nature and cycling: in Scope 13; The global  carbon cycle (Bolin, B., editor; et aL), p. 293-316, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), John Wiley &amp; Sons,  Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  Morris, S.E. Holocene facies of the Blanca Massif, southern Colorado [abstr.]: Geological Society of  America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 297, 1979.  The Geological  Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Mosley, M. P. Streamflow generation in a forested watershed, New Zealand:  Water Resources  Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 795-806, illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Mosser, C.; and Gense, C. Elements traces dans des kaolinites d'alterations a Madagascar [Trace  elements in weathered kaolinites from the Malagasy Republic]: Chemical Geology; an International  Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 26, No. 3-4, p. 295-309 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Muhs, D. R. Geomorphic implications of late Quaternary Paleosois on the Palos Verdes Peninsula,  California [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol.  11, No. 6, p. 297, 1979. The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Nathwani, J. S.; and Phillips, C. R. Adsorption of 226Ra by soils, I: Chemosphere. Pergamon Press,  Oxford-New York-Paris., Vol. 8, No. 5, p. 285-291, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Nathw~mi, J. S.; and Phillips, C.R. Adsorption of 226Ra by soils and the presence of Ca2+ions; specific  adsorption, II: Chemosphere. Pergamon Press, Oxford-New York-Paris., Vol. 8, No. 5, p. 293-299, illus.  (incl. table), 1979.  Neal, H. L. Soil survey of Jasper County, Mississippi: 87 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, D.C., United States, t979.  Onstad, C. A.; Young, R. A.; Otterby, M, A.; et aL Sediment yield modeling for 208 planning: i~  Universal soil loss equation; past, present, and future (Pete,son, A. E., editor; et aL), Soil Science Society  of America, Special Publication. Madison, Wisconsin., No. 8, p. 25-32, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Palaeky, G. J.; and Sena, F. O. Conductor identification in tropical terrains; case histories from the  Itapicuru greenstone belt, Bahia, Brazil: Geophysics (Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Journal).  Tulsa, Oklahoma., Vol. 44, No. 12, p. 1941-1962, illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1979.  Paterson, J.H. North America; a geography of Canada and the United States, 6th edition: 463 p., illus.  (incl. sketch maps), Oxford Univ. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Peterson, A. E.; Swan, J. B.; Stelly, M. (editors); et aL Universal soil loss equation; past, present, and  future: Nov. 13-18, 1977, United States. Soil Science Society of America, Special Publication. Madison,  Wisconsin., No. 8, 53 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Pytkowicz, "R. M. Excess crustal calcium problem: Geochemical Journal (Geochemical Society of  Japan). Nagoya., Vol. 13, No. 1, p. 15-17, illus. (incl. table), 1979.    280    Robb, L.J. The distribution of granitophile elements in Archaean granites of the eastern Transvaal, and  their bearing on geomorphological and geological features of the area: University of the Witwatersrand,  Economic Geology Research Unit, Information Circular. Johannesburg., No. 129, 14 p., illus. (incl. geol.  sketch maps), 1979.  Robinson, A. R. Sediment yield as a function of upstream erosion: in Universal soil loss equation; past,  present, and future (Peterson, A. E., editor; et aL), Soil Science Society of America, Special Publication.  Madison, Wisconsin., No. 8, p. 7-16, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Roy, W. R.; and Hall, R.D. Glacial geology of the South Boulder River valley, Tobacco Root Range,  Montana [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11,  No. 6, p. 300, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Sarnecki, J. C.; Phillips, C. M.; and Wem-ich-Verbeek, K. J. Ecology, stratigraphy, resources, and  geochemistry of Boston Peak Bog 1, Latimer County, Colorado [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 6, p. 300-301, 1979.  The Geological Society  of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 32nd annual meeting.  Sayward, J. M. Small-scale testing of soils for frost action and water migration: U. S. Army, Cold  Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory, Special Report. Hanover, New Hampshire., No. 79-17,  20 p., illus., 1979.  Schafer, W. M.; Nielsen, G. A.; Dollhopf, D. J.; et aL Soil genesis, hydrological properties, root  characteristics and microbial activity of 1- to 50-year-old stripmine spoils: 212 p., illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1979. (Rep. No. EPA-600/7-79-100) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Selfleser, G. H.; Pohling, R.; and Meyer, B. 813C record in an undisturbed forest soft: Zeitschrift fuer  Naturforschung. Tuebingen., Vol. 34a, No. 1, p. 119-120, illus., 1979.  Schmidt, W.; and Dietl, F. Bestimmung yon Cadmium in Boden- und Sedimentaufschiuessen und -  extrakten  mit  der flammenlosen  Atomabsorption  in  Zirkonium-beschichteten  Graphitrohren  [Determination of cadmium in soil and sediment extracts and effluents by means of tameless atomic  absorption with zirconium coated graphite tubes]: Zeitschrift fuer Analytische Chemie. Berlin., Vol. 295,  No. 2-3, p. 110-115 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Schalle, J. A.; Mega, J.; and Beckhart, R. Ion exchange dating of sediments on the Gaftinas River  [abstr.]: in Abstracts for the Fffty-fLfth annual meeting of the Southwestern &amp; Rocky Mountain Division,  American Association for the Advancement of Science and the Colorado-Wyoming Academy of Science  :~ncluding the Colorado-Wyoming Chapter of the American Association of Physics Teachers and the  Colorado Chapter of the National Association of Geology Teachers (American Association for the  Advancement of Science), Colorado-Wyoming Academy of Sciences, Journal., Vol. 11, No. 1, p. 16,  1979.  Senesi, N,; Polemio, M.; and Lorusso, L. Content and distribution of arsenic, bismuth, lithium, and  selenium in mineral and synthetic fertilizers and their contribution to soft: Communications in Soil  Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-Basel., Vol. 10, No. 8, p. 1109-1123, tables, 1979.  Sollee, D. D.; Huff, R. B.; and Carter, IL N, Distribution of manganese in roadside soft [abstr.]: inThe  f'u"ty-second annual meeting of the South Carolina Academy of Science (Cowley, G. T., editor), South  Carolina Academy of Science, Bulletin. Columbia., Vol. 41, p. 70-71, 1979.  Sollid, J.L.;andSoerbel, L. DeglaciationofwesterncentralNorway: Boreas; An International Journal  of Quaternary Geology. Oslo., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 233-239, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Summerfield, M.A. Origin and palaeoenvironmental interpretation of sarsens: Nature. London., Vol.  281, No. 5727, p. 137-139, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Swihart, G. H.  Experimental freeze-thaw weathering of granite [abstr.]:  The Maine Geologist  (Geological Society of Maine, Newsletter). [Lewiston]., Vol. 5, No. 3, p. 3, 1979.  5th annual spring  meeting of the Geological Society of Main~  Szekielda, K.H. Potential use of satellites for assessing pools and fluxes of the carbon cycle on Earth:  in Scope 13; The klobal carbon cycle (Bolin, B., editor; etaL), p. 379-402, illus. (incl. sketch maps), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1979.  Terrell, D. J.; Pal, S.; Lopez M., M.; et aRare-earth elements in basalt samples, Gulf of California:  Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 26, No. 3-4, p.  267-275, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.    281    Thornber, M. R. Supergene alteration of sulphides; V, Laboratory studies on the dispersion of Ni, Cy,  Co and Fe: Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. PubL Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 26,  No. 1-2, p. 135-149, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Trudeau, P.N. Ecology of barrier beaches in South central Maine (Popham Beach State Park, Reid State  Park, and Small Point Beach): 412 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Massachusetts, Amherst, Mass. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.  Tyler, N. Stratigraphy, origin, and correlation of the Kanye Volcanic Group in the West-central  Transvaal: University of the Witwatersrand, Economic Geology Research Unit, Information Circular.  Johannesburg., No. 130, 14 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), 1979.  Udo, E. J.; and Fagbami, A. A. The profile distribution of total and extractable zinc in selected Nigerian  soils: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-Basel., Vol. 10,  No. 8, p. 1141-1159, tables, sketch map, 1979.  Van Valen, L.; and McLean, D. M. Floras and oxygen:  Science (American Association for the  Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., Vol. 205, No. 4412, p. 1301-1302, 1979.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                