Geoderma, 30 (1983)135--147                                                     135  Elsevier Science Publishers B V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    EFFECT OF POTASSIUM ON SOIL STRUCTURE IN RELATION TO  HYDRAULIC CONDUCTIVITY    Y. CHEN, A BANIN and A. BOROCHOVITCH  The Seagram Center for Soil and Water Sciences, The Hebrew Unwersity of Jerusalem,  PO Box 12, Rehovot, 76100 (Israel)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Chen, Y., Banin, A. and Borochovitch, A., 1983. Effect of potassium on soil structure in  relation to hydraulic conductivity. Geoderma, 30' 135--147    The effect of exchangeable K on soil structure and permeability has been studied. A  loamy sand, a light clay and a heavy clay soil were leached with solutions adjusted to  potassium adsorption ratios (PAR) of 0.0, 0.72, 3.74 and =. Exchangeable K percentage  (EPP) and hydraulic conductivity (HC) were measured on the leached soils. SEM observa-  tions on undisturbed soil samples were used to evaluate changes in soil structure and pore  size.  EPP values for the three soils ranged as follows" 0.8--1.3, 5 5--9.2, 16.0--21.0 and  58.0--76.0 for PAR's of 0.0, 0.72, 3.74 and =, respectively. HC increased slightly (20%)  up to EPP values of about 20% for the loamy sand and heavy clay soil, while a decrease  in HC corresponding to any increase of EPP was observed for the light clay soil. This soil  was richer in illite and also exhibited higher affinity for K*. At the highest EPP values  (58.0--76.0) HC of the three soils decreased to about 20% of the values measured for the  Ca2saturated soils.  SEM observations were performed and Ca2+ saturated soils compared with the K+  enriched ones. Ca2+ treated loamy sand exhibited discrete clay aggregates located in the  spaces between sand particles or attached to them. K enrichment resulted in the forma-  tion of a dense network of clay microaggregates filling up the pore space The micro-  aggregate structure of the two Ca2clay soils changed to a dense layer composed of much  smaller particles following K+ enrichment. Pores were mostly smaller than 10 ~m in the  Ksoil compared to several tens of microns in the Ca~+ form.  SEM observations and the fact that clay content did not vary with depth suggest that  dispersion of clay microaggregates and their rearrangement in situ were the major  mechanisms involved in HC reduction, rather than long-range clay migration and the for-  mation of a clay enriched layer with impeded drainage.    INTRODUCTION    Soil permeability is recognized as a major factor in soil management. The  effect of the exchangeable cation species on soil permeability with particular  emphasis on the deleterious effects of Na+ vs. (Ca2+ + Mg2+) are well    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    136    documented (e.g.U.S. Salinity Laboratory Staff, 1954; Quirk and Schofield,  1955). Fewer reports on K+ effects on soil permeability have been pubhshed  and results seem to vary or conflict, possibly due to differences in soil  mineralogy and sample preparation procedures. Generally, soil permeablhty  relates to exchangeable cations in the following order: Ca ~ Mg ~ K ~ Na.  However, differences m the relative values of permeability have been  reported: Mg &gt; K ~ Na (Reeve et al., 1954); Ca ~ Mg ~ K -- Na (Quirk and  Schofleld, 1955), Ca &gt; K &gt; Na (Gardner et al., 1959); NH4 = K &gt; Na  (Martin and Richards, 1959), and Ca = Mg &gt; K &gt; Na (clay loam) and Ca &gt;  Mg &gt; K = Na (clay) (Ahmed et al., 1969). In contrast, some researchers  report larger aggregates of greater stabihty in K +-saturated soils than m those  saturated with divalent cations: K &gt; Ca = Mg &gt; Na (Cecconl et al., 1963);  K ~ Ca (Ravina, 1973); suggesting that K+ m the exchange sites has  favorable effects on soil permeability.  The major mechanisms involved in the decreases in permeablhty due to  monovalent exchangeable cations are swelhng, dispersion and clay migration  which affect the hydraulic conductivity (HC) of the soil (Quirk and  Schofield, 1955). The relative importance of these mechanisms is a matter  of controversy. Chen and Banin (1975) suggest that clay dispersmn, detach-  ment of clay from sand particles and their rearrangement in situ are the  major mechanisms responsible for reduction In HC m sodic sandy soils. Clay  dispersion resulting in aggregate destruction was found to be the major  mechanism causing HC reduction in a sodic clay soil (Chen and Banin,  1975). On the basis of these observations, it has been suggested that short-  and long-range clay migration can be distinguished (Chen, 1975; Chen and  Banin, 1975). According to these investigators, in situ clay parttcle rearrange-  ment following aggregate destruction and resulting pore-size reduction is  considered as short-range migration, whereas the downward movement of  clay, which often leads to the formation of an impeded layer, is considered  as long-range migration.  Since Kis a major nutritional element for plants, enrichment of K+ in  the exchange sites due to fertilizer practice can be expected. Heavy K fertilizer application is a common practice in greenhouse agriculture and  leads to soil exchangeable Klevels which are much greater than those  of field soils. The purpose of this study was, therefore, to investigate the  effects of K + on the permeability of soils commonly used for greenhouse  agriculture in Israel.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils    A loamy sand, a light-clay and a heavy.lay sod were sampled at Rehovot,  Timorim and Yagur, respectively, m Israel. These soils pose permeability  problems when used as greenhouse soils. Chemical and physical properties of  the field soils were determined as follows: cation exchange capacity (CEC)    137    and adsorbed cation species by displacement with 1 N sodium acetate and  1 N ammonium acetate, respectively (U.S. Salinity Laboratory Staff, 1954);  particle-size analysis by the hydrometer method (Van der Watt, 1966);  organic matter by a wet-combustion method (Black et al., 1965); and CaCO3  content by a calcimeter method (Black et al., 1965). The mineralogical com-  position of the clay fraction was determined using methods described by Gal  et al. (1974).  The potassium adsorption ratio (PAR) was calculated as:  PAR = K/[(Ca + Mg)/2] ~                                 (1)  where K and (Ca + Mg) are the corresponding ions concentrations in meq/1.  Gapon's constant (KG) was calculated as:  KG = [K/(Ca + Mg)]/PAR                                  (2)  where K, Ua and ~g are the quantities of the corresponding exchangeable  cations in meq/100 g soil.    Hydrauhc conductivtty measurements on soils equdibrated to required  exchangeable K percentage (EPP).    The soils were air-dried, crushed and staved through a 2 mm sieve. PVC  pots (2.8 1 capacity) were used as permeameters (McNeal and Reeve, 1964).  The pot-permearneter and the HC measurement system and procedure are  described by Chen and Banln (1975).  Leaching solutions were prepared by dissolving chloride salts of K and  Ca2+ to give PAR values of 0, 0.72, 3.74 and ~ at K+ Ca2concentrations  of either 1 N or 0.02 N. To prevent microbial growth in the soft 50 ppm of  HgC12 were added to the leaching solutions. The compositions of the leaching  solutions are given in Table I. The treatments were designated as K1, K2, K3  and K4 corresponding to increasing PAR values of the leaching solutions.  Leaching was initiated by applying the solution to the top of the soil  and flooding the surface until a head of about 4---6 cm of solution was  established. The solution level was thereafter maintained at this level by use    TABLEI    Compositions of the leaching solutions    Treatment    PAR    Kconcentration (meq/1)   Ca2concentration (meq/1)  0.02 N        1 N           0.02 N     1 N    K~            0 00     0.00             0.00      20 00      1000.00  K2               0 72       2.14              15.80        17 86         984.20  K3               3.74       8.85              80.20        11.15         919.80  K4            ~       20.00         1000.00       0.00          0.00    138    m    o~  r,j ,.,    ~o    o    0  aO  eo  ~   c,i   o.    Qo  o  r:.    O   r.O   ~.    ~1  L,%  t'-    c~1   uo   go    139    of Mariot-bottles. The leaching was thus conducted under saturated con-  ditions at a gradient of 1.3--1.5 cm/cm.  Soils were equilibrated by passing 20 1 of the 1 N solution followed by  10 1 of the 0.02 N solution. HC measurements were performed toward the  end of the leaching process while the 0.02 N solutions were passing through  the soil. After equilibration and HC measurements, excess solution was  allowed to drain out and soil samples taken for CEC, exchangeable cation  species determination, and SEM observations. CEC was also determined on  soil sections of the K4 treatments at depths of 0--5, 5--10 and 10--14 cm  as a measure for the possible formation of a clay-rich layer.    SEM observations    The total depth of the saturated soft in the pot was sampled using a  2.5-cm internal diameter cork borer. The sampler with soil was submerged  in liquid nitrogen, which rapidly froze the wet soft. The sample was released  by rubbing the outside of the tube to warm it. The frozen soil core was then  sheared parallel to its axis by applying pressure with a pair of pliers, exposing  a fresh undisturbed soil surface normal to the top of the cylinder. The frozen  sample was glued using Duco cement onto an aluminum stub with the ex-  posed surface facing upward, freeze-dried, and coated with carbon and gold.  A Jeol model JSM 35 C scanning electron microscope was used to obtain  micrographs at magnifications of 160 and 1600.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Properties of the soils    Chemical and physical properties of the three softs studied are presented in  Table II. Soil texture varied from loamy sand to heavy clay (International  Society of Soil Science classification). Properties related to clay contents  such as moisture content of air-dried soils and CEC, vary accordingly. CaCO3  content is small in the sandy soil and much greater for the clayey soils. The  organic matter content is very small in the sandy soil and somewhat greater  in the light clay. The exchangeable K percentage of the natural soils does  not exceed 5.8%.  The mineralogical properties of the softs are presented m Table III. Mont-  morillonite comprises the major fraction followed by kaolinite. Illite which  is of special interest due to its Kfixation properties, comprises about 10%  of the sandy loam and heavy clay soils and 16% of the light clay soft.    Exchangeable cation species and capacity    General. Exchangeable Kcontents and percentages, CEC and KG of the  leached soils are summarized in Table IV. EPP values for a given PAR treat-    140  TABLE III  Mmeralog,cal composition of the clay fraction    Soil         llhte    Montmordl     Kaohmte    Free oxldes (%)                                 CaCO~  locahon     (%)     I%)             q%)                                                           (%)    SIO     Fe,O,    AI:O~    MnO:     total  (/ 10 '~)  RehovoI     10       56               26            1 9      4 2        0 4        3          6 5        1 5  T~monm     16       47               19            2 6      2 2        0 3        4          5 1      13 5  Yagur        11       58               17            2 7      2 3        0 4        2          5 4       9 0    ment differed somewhat among the soils, possibly due to differences in their  illite content. In each soil KG decreased with increase of PAR and of EPP  due to saturation of the K +-preferring sites. The data show that CEC values  for the various PAR treatments within a single soil did not differ signifi-  cantly. However, some reduction m CEC due to Kfixation took place m  soils treated with solutions of PAR = ~. This is confirmed by comparing  CEC-data of the field soils (Table II) with those of the soils treated with  solutions of PAR = ~o (Table IV).    TABLE IV    Exchangeable K  CEC, EPP and KG of the leached sods (means of triphcates)    Soil        Treatment   Solution   Exchangeable K  CEC           EPP   KG  location                 PAR       (meq./100 g)     (meq/100 g)   (%)    (I/mole)~    Rehovot    K~           0 00         0 1               11 0              0 8  K2           0.72         0 6              11.0              5.5   2.57  K3             3 74          1 9                 11.6              16.0   1 61  K4           ~           6 0              10.7            58.0   0.51    Tlmorim    KI           0 00        0 4              33.6             1 3  K2             0.72          3 1                 33.7                9 2   4 48  K3             3 74          7.2                 34.8              21.0   2.28  K4          ~          23 4              29 9            76.0   1.17    Yagur    K1          0.00        0.4              52 9             0.8  K2             0.72          3 4                 54.1                6.4   3.02  K3             3 74         10 8                 51.4              21.0   2.25  K4             ~            39.4                 50.6              71_0   0.91    Measurements of CEC as a function of soil depth m the permeameter, for  the K4 treatments showed the following ranges (data in meq./100 g):  Rehovot 10.3--10.7; Timorim 29.9--30.2; and Yagur 49.9--50.6. These data  show that the clay contents (assessed by CEC) are practically constant with  depth, suggesting that long-range clay migration and the formation of an  impeded clay layer did not take place.    141    Effect of potassium on hydraulic conductivity. Relative HC data (HC of  the K1 treatment for each soil taken as 1.0) are plotted against EPP in Fig. 1.  The curves for the Yagur and Rehovot soils are similar, both exhibiting I-J0  increase up to EPP of about 20% and a steep decrease in HC with further  increase of EPP. The Timorim soft responds differently to an EPP increase,  HC decreasing with any increase in EPP. Small EPP-effects on soil  permeability thus seem to be different among the softs and relate to structural  or compositional factors which are not well understood at this time. It seems  that at small EPP's Kmay have positive effects on HC in some soils,  possibly due to interlayer adsorption on ftlite resulting in the stabilization of  microaggregates. The differences in response of the various soils could not be  correlated with any of their measured chemical or mineralogical properties.  We therefore feel, that further research is required to elucidate Keffect  on soils at low EPP's. However, large EPP values produced deleterious effects  in the three soils studied. Moreover, in one of the softs in this study  (Timorim) EPP values below 25% resulted in soil deterioration.  Of interest is a comparison of the effect of Na(Chen and Bantu, 1975)  with that of K The loamy sand in the two studies originates from very  close locations, belong to the same soil type and differ somewhat in clay  contents. The light-clay soil from Timorim in this study resembles the  Kefar Menachem soil  (Chen  and  Banin,  1975). Timonm and Kefar  Menachem soils belong to the same sod type and resemble in clay  i     I     i     l     I     I     I     l   | 4 --         It                  REHOVOT                 --  &gt;-  )IK/ I \        /}"C \  ~&gt; 12.-  I--  (D  O t0  Z  0  L)  _o os  J  ,,  OC 06  Q  3,-  "r  04  ILl  _&gt;  I--  &lt;~02  _I  tlJ  e,-  o     I    I    I    I    I    I    I    I  0             I0            20            30           40           50           60           70            80  EXCHANGEABLE POTASSIUM PERCENTAGE (EPP)  Fig. 1 Relative hydraulic conductivity vs EPP (average + standard deviation).    142    mineralogy, CaCO3 content and other chemmal properties. Whereas 15% of  exchangeable Nareduced HC by 80% {relative HC = 0.2), 60%-75% of ex-  changeable Kwere required to cause a similar reduction suggesting that the  deleterious effect of potassium is less than that of sodmm. This is in accord  w~th earher reports (Reeve et al., 1954; Brooks et al., 1956; Gardner et al.,  1959; Ahmed et al., 1969)    SEM observatzons. SEM observations on the effect of increased exchange-  able Kpercentage on sml fabmc are presented in Figs. 2--4. Only the two  extreme treatments, K, and K4, are presented for each sml. Sand partmles  coated and interspersed with clay material can be seen in the low-magnifica-  tion micrographs of the sandy soil (Rehovot: Fig. 2). The Ca:+-treated sml  (K,) shows discrete, rounded clay aggregates in the pore space between the  much larger sand particles, but most of the clay microaggregates are attached  to sand partmles. Pores as large as 100 ~m can be seen. Potassium-enrichment  (K4) resulted m the formation of a dense continuous network of clay  particles filling the pore space between the sand partmles, thus reducing the  average pore size. The higher magmfication shows discrete clay aggregates  coating the sand particles m the Ca2+ soil, whereas a large number of small  aggregates forming a network are seen on the K4 micrograph.  In the two clay soils the low-magnification micrographs show a contmuous  mass of fine material mixed with larger particles, with no obvious difference  between the Ca2soil and the Kenriched one. However, at the higher  magnification the dispersion effects of the adsorbed Kare seen. In the  Timorim Ca:sml (Fig. 3) discrete mlcroaggregates are seen with pores of  5--10 ~m m size between them. In the Kenriched soil many small clay  aggregates are seen, causing a reduction m the average pore size to 0.5--2 ~m.  Very similar changes were found m the Yagur clay soil (Fig. 4). These  changes in particle arrangement and pore-size distributmn correspond well  with the HC changes and must be due to high Kenrichment.  The number of published investigations of SEM studies on Kaffected  soils is small, and it is thus difficult to draw comparisons with our work.  Ravina (1973) presented SEM mlcrographs of Ca~and Ksaturated clay  fractions extracted from a Grumusol. Preparation methods were destructive  and air-drying was apphed after the Kenrichment and prmr to the SEM  observations. Ravma (1973) concluded that more points of contact between  particles could be seen in the K+ saturated clay and, therefore, a coarser  structure formed, This is not in accord with our observations. We believe  that the preparation procedures of the soils are of major importance. There-  fore, we studmd samples which were undisturbed and not allowed to air-  dry once leaching had started.  Chen and Banin (1975) showed the effects of Naon soil structure which  were similar to those of Kalthough more extreme, albeit the effect of Na appeared  at  a  much  lower monovalent exchangeable ion percentage  (10--16%). It appears that the degree of structural damage in soils con-    143    A    ~o  0    144    2   0    145    0  n~  _=  &gt;  g~  o$  e~  o  E~  .o    146    taming 60--75% exchangeable Kis comparable with that occurring with  10 -16% exchangeable Na+.  Bisdom (1981) In his review article on the application of submicroscopic  techniques in soil micromorphology has emphasized the importance of SEM  as a tool to improve understanding of soil structure and soil--water relation-  ships. This work provides SEM evidence for structural changes due to  exchangeable K + and illustrates the mechamsm involved at high EPP's. Our  observations strengthen the hypothesis of Chen and Banin (1975) that dis-  perslon of the fine soft fraction (mostly clay aggregates) and its rearrange-  ment in sItu to form a dense network of particles with smaller pores between  them is the major mechanism for HC reduction, rather than massive clay  migration and the formatmn of an Impermeable layer.    REFERENCES    Ahmed, S, Swindale, L.D. and EI-Swaify, S A, 1969. Effects of adsorbed catlons on  physical properties of tropical black earths, 1. Plastic limit, percentage stable aggregate  and hydraulic conductivity J Soll ScI., 21 255--268  Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981. A review of the application of submmroscopic techniques m soil  micromorphology, I_ Transmmsion electron mlcroscope (TEM) and scanning electron  microscope  (SEM).  In  E.BA.  Bisdom  (Editor),  Submicroscopy of Solls and  Weathered Rocks Center for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation, Wageningen,  pp 67--116.  Black, C.A, Evans, D.D, White, J L, Ensminger, L.E. and Clark, F.E. (Editors), 1965  Methods of Soil Analysis Am. Soc. Agron, Madison, Wl, Monogr., 9, 1349--1353;  1393--1396  Brooks, R H, Bower, C_A. and Reeve, R C, 1956. The effect of various exchangeable  cations upon the physical conditions of soils. Soil Sci Soc. Am. Proc, 20 325--327  Cecconi, S , Salazar, A. and M. Martelli, M, 1963 The effect of different cations on the  structural stability of some soils Agrochimica 7 185--204.  Chen, Y, 1975 Evaluation of montmorillomte behavior and particle structure as a model  for swelling and flow impediment in soils Ph D Thesm, The Hebrew University of  Jerusalem.  Chen, Y and Banin, A., 1975 Scanning electron microscope (SEM) observations of sod  structure changes induced by sodium-calcium exchange in relation to hydraulic con-  ductivlty. Soil Sci, 120 428--436  Gal, M, Ravikovitch, S  and Amiel, A J, 1974. Clay mineral distribution and origin in  the soft types of Israel J. Soil Sci , 25:79--89  Gardner, W.R, Mayhugh, M S., Goertzon, J O  and Bower. C.A, 1959. Effect of  electrolyte concentration and ESP on diffusivity of water in sods Soil Scl , 88' 270--  274  Martin, J.P and Richards, S J., 1959  Influence of exchangeable H, Ca, Na, K and NH,  at different H levels on certain physmal properties of soils. Soil Sm Soc Am Proc ,  23 335--338  McNeal, B L and Reeve, R.C., 1964. Elimination of boundary-flow errors m laboratory  hydraulic conductivity measurements. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc , 28' 713--714  Quirk, J P  and Schofield, R K , 1955. The effect of electrolyte concentration on soil  permeability. J Soil Sci , 6. 163--178_  Ravina, I , 1973  The mechanical and physical behavior of Ca-clay sod and K-clay soil  Ecol_ Stud., 4 131--140    147    Reeve, R.C., Bower, C.A., Brooks, R.H and Gschwend, F.B., 1954. A comparison of the  effects of exchangeable Na~ and Kupon the physical conditions of soils. Soil Sci  Soc. Am. Proc., 18: 130--132.  U.S. Salinity Laboratory Staff, 1954. Diagnosis and Improvement of Saline and Alkah  Soils. USDA Handbook 60, pp. 100--101.  Van der Watt, H.V.H., 1966. Improved tables and a simplified procedure for soil particle  analysis by hydrometer method. S. Aft. J. Agric., 9: 911--916.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   AbstractThe effect of exchangeable K+ on soil structure and permeability has been studied. A loamy sand, a light clay and a heavy clay soil were leached with solutions adjusted to potassium adsorption ratios (PAR) of 0.0, 0.72, 3.74 and ∞. Exchangeable K+ percentage (EPP) and hydraulic conductivity (HC) were measured on the leached soils. SEM observations on undisturbed soil samples were used to evaluate changes in soil structure and pore size.EPP values for the three soils ranged as follows: 0.8–1.3, 5.5–9.2, 16.0–21.0 and 58.0–76.0 for PAR's of 0.0, 0.72, 3.74 and ∞, respectively. HC incrased slightly (20%) up to EPP values of about 20% for the loamy sand and heavy clay soil, while a decrease in HC corresponding to any increase of EPP was observed for the light clay soil. This soil was richer in illite and also exhibited higher affinity for K+. At the highest EPP values (58.0–76.0) HC of the three soils decreased to about 20% of the values measured for the Ca2+ saturated soils.SEM observations were performed and Ca2+ saturated soils compared with the K+ enriched ones. Ca2+ treated loamy sand exhibited discrete clay aggregates located in the spaces between sand particles or attached to them. K+ enrichment resulted in the formation of a dense network of clay microaggregates filling up the pore space. The microaggregate structure of the two Ca2+ clay soils changed to a dense layer composed of much smaller particles following K+ enrichment. Pores were mostly smaller than 10 μm in the K+ soil compared to several tens of microns in the Ca2+ form.SEM observations and the fact that clay content did not vary with depth suggest that dispersion of clay microaggregates and their rearrangement in situ were the major mechanisms involved in HC reduction, rather than long-range clay migration and the formation of a clay enriched layer with impeded drainage.