Geoderma, 30 (1983) 233--242                                                     233  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in the Netherlands    FABRIC   SEQUENCES   AS   RELATED   TO   GENETIC   PROCESSES   IN  TWO ALBERTA SOILS    S PAWLUK  Department of Soil Science, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alta (Canada)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Pawluk, S., 1983. Fabric sequences as related to genetic processes m two Alberta soils.  Geoderrna, 30: 233--242.    Terminology based on fabric sequences as proposed recently by Brewer (1979) was  found useful for describing mmrofabrics in Alberta soils since it established a basis of  study compatible with field morphological descriptions. The recognized fabric sequences  were: gramc, fragmm, chlamydic, and iunctic. Each sequence represented a continuum  of fabric types distinguished on the basis of related dmtributlon between fine and coarse  materials.  Attempts have been made to unify specific fabric types within each of the sequences  on the basis of material composition and genetic processes Since soil horizons were  pedogenically generated as well, they in turn could usually be characterized by a single  dominant fabric sequence. In our studies we found the granic sequence of fabric to  characterize mull layers. The fragmic fabric sequence was more common in subsurface  horizons of fine texture. The chlamydie fabric sequence was best developed in spodic  and argillic horizons of coarse texture. A well developed iunctic sequence was found  in moder as well as in coarse textured highly calcareous horizons. Fabric types within  each of the recognized sequences were highly variable in time and/or space within their  respective horizons.    INTRODUCTION    A problem frequently experienced in micromorphology has been the  demonstration of its usefulness for gathering information applicable to other  disciphnes within the field of soil science. This paper is concerned with its  applicability to pedogenetic studies.  Advantage is taken of recent emphasis placed on related distribution  between fine and coarse material for describing spatial arrangement in  soil fabrics. Brewer (1977) mtroduced the terms "f-member" and "f-matrix"  to explain related distribution between these kinds of material. He defined  "f-members" as recognizable entities that may be simple or compound but  that occurred as discrete units. In some cases "f-members" were observed to  have a particular relationship with finer material referred to as "f-matrix".    0016--7061/83/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Scmnce Publishers B.V.    234    Based on such relationships Brewer, in 1979, introduced terminology for  four principal sequences of fabrm description, each representing a continuum  of fabric types. These were: granlc*~ (granlc-granoidic-granoidm porphyrm-  porphyric); fragrmc ,2 (fragmic-fragmoldlc-fragm oldic porphyric-porphyric );  chlamydic ,3  (orthogranic-chlamydic-plectlc-plectlc porphyric-porphyric),  and iunctic.4  (orthogranlc-lunctic-iunctic porphyric-porphyric). In many  respects this terminology represents an approach similar to that originally  proposed by Stoops and Jongerlus (1975). In all four sequences, fabric  of the porphyric type was shown to dominate as contact among f-members  and between f-members and f-matrix increased to a point where f-members  appeared to be embedded in the f-matrix  Terminology based on fabric sequences has proved to be exceedingly  useful for describing mlcrofabrms of soils in the Alberta (Canada) region.  It provided a basis for study readily compatible with field morphological  investigations and permitted a broadening in the range of generalization  in fabric descnptxon. Furthermore, the fabric types within each of the  defined sequences were found to be genetically related and since soil hori-  zons were similarly pedogenically generated, each defined soil horizon was  characterized by a single dominant fabric sequence. Thus, it was possible  to consider the fabric sequence as a genetically related, single, identifiable  characteristic of the soil horizon. When greater detail required recognition  of specific zones of fabric type within a  soil horizon or subhorizon, the  dominance of each fabric type within a specified sequence was considered  for further subdivision.    FABRIC SEQUENCES AND SOIL DYNAMICS    Analy tical approach    Fabrics were generally dynamic and fabric types readily changed within  their respective sequences in response to soil processes and environmental  forces. Therefore the detailed characterization of fabric type within se-  quences included an evaluation within the complete framework of a dynamic  soil system and transient tendencies in response to pedogenic forces.  In order to study the dynamic relationships within fabric sequences, it  proved useful to monitor a number of site parameters for assessing the  mechanisms involved. The dynamic properties monitored were as follows:  (1) seasonal soil moisture and heat fluxes; (2) seasonal variability in bio-  logical populations and their activity; (3) transport of suspended and dis-    .i Discrete unaccommodated simple or compound units of plasma and skeleton grains  including pedological features; shows variable packing or coalescence.  *~ Dmcrete accommodated or partially accommodated compound umts including ped-  ological features, shows variable packing or coalescence.  .3 Coatings of f-matrix on f-members with variable coalescence to form "brldges".  ,4 F-matrix shows variable packing in spaces between adjacent f-members.    235    solved solids with the aid of field gravity lysimeters and canopy collectors;  (4) seasonal groundwater flow patterns and water table fluctuations; (5)  seasonal changes in pH, redox and pore water salt concentrations; (6) micro-  morphological changes in fabric type within soil material and parent material  cores embedded at different depths in the pedon (used for monitoring  pedogenic trends).  The static characteristics and properties recorded were as follows: (1)  morphological features; (2) physical, chemical, and mineralogical attributes  (3) micromorphologmal features using microscopic and submicroscopic  techniques, using EMA (electron microprobe analyzer), SEM-EDXRA  (scanning electron microscope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer) and XRD  (microcamera).  Two fabric sequences, with appropriate model examples are used to dem-  onstrate the relationships that were observed between fabric types and ob-  served dynamics in two Alberta soils. Sampling was carried out in spring,  summer and autumn where control for seasonal variabihty was desired.  Soil monoliths (7 X 7 80 cm) were collected and used for the preparation  of a continuous array of 5 X 7 cm thm sections.    Mullgranlc sequence    The soil pedon depicted in Fig.la was representative of the Typic  Cryochrept from an alpine site in the Sunshine Basin, Banff, Alberta. The  A1 horizon provided an excellent example of the granic sequence found m  soils with mull surface layers. In this case it was referred to as the mull-  granic sequence. The mullgranic fabric type (Fig. lb) was readily identi-  fiable within this sequence. The units were largely compound, discrete,  packed loosely and comprised of intimately associated organic and mineral  matter. Some fecal pellets were also present. These were the f-members;  there was no f-matrix present. Zones of mullgranoidic fabric type (Fig. lc)  were also evident. The mull f-members were more closely packed and were  partially coalesced. Where strong coalescence between f-members was  observed the fabric type approached a vughy porphyric and was considered  to be a muUgranoidic porphyric intergrade (Fig. ld). In some zones distinct  compound units were no longer discernable but the forms of coalesced  units were generally evident within the f-matrix; this was identified as  porphyric fabric (Fig. le).  The mullgranm sequence in A1 horizons of Alberta softs had variable  expression of fabric types. The proportion of each fabric type and its degree  of expression varied seasonally during which time one fabric type could  be altered to another within the same sequence. Depending on processes  marked shifts in dominance of fabric type had been observed according  to the following:  muUgranic ~ mullgranoldic ~ mullgranoidic porphyric ~- porphyric  A number of factors were implicated in these changes and could result    236    Fig.1. The mullgranic sequence within the A1 horizon of a Typm Cryochrept a. section  of pedon of a Typic Cryochrept; b. mullgranic fabric; c. mullgranoidic fabric, d. mull-  granoidm porphyric fabric, e. porphyric fabric, f. isobanded granoidlc fabric, g. granic  units within lsobanded granoidm fabric.    237    in shifts either to the left or right m the sequence. The following were ob-  served to produce shifts to the right; (1) seasonal compaction; (2) raindrop  dispersion followed by drying; (3) increase in clay content; (4) waterlogging;  (5) some species of earthworms?  Shifts to the left within the mullgranic sequence were produced by the  following: (1) increase in soil faunal activity; (2) other biological forces  e.g., root exudates; (3) cyclic freezing and thawing; (4) cultivation; (5)  wetting and drying.  Seasonal changes in fabric type within the mullgranic sequence were  especially obvious for the mull layers of fine texture where mullgranic fabrics  dominated in the sprmg and softs were generally friable.  Porphyric types dominated in the autumn and consistency was much  more firm. Spring and autumn freeze-thaw cycles played a major role in  moving dominance toward the mullgranm type. Cultivation also produced  mullgranic fabric types but the size and shape of f-members were highly  irregular and not always well defined. Tillage did not appear to be the  best mechanism for producing mullgranic fabrics. Earthworms were also  prolifm producers of mullgranic fabric types. However, under certain con-  ditions, mullgranoidic porphyric types could form through an overproduc-  tion of recalcitrant organic substances.  Major changes in pedogenic forces were shown to produce intergrades  to other fabrics not recognized within the sequence. For example, severe  compaction accompanmd by freeze-thaw resulted in isobanded granoidic  intergrades (Fig. lf). In this case modifying genetic processes were further  discerned by utilizing submicroscopic techniques. Some of the mullgranic  umts (Fig. lg) appeared as domains of yellowish-brown isotropic gel much  hke organic plasma with pleistoplasmatic related distribution (Bal, 1973).  Other mullgranic units comprised domains of similar appearance but also  showed variable anisotropic properties. In order to analyze these domains  submicroscopically, cover slips were removed and the slides were sectioned.  A section was then polished and carbon-coated for the microprobe. The  microprobe used was a Cambridge Geoscan in the C.S.I.R.O. laboratories  in Adelaide operated by Dr. K. Norish. The microprobe was equipped  with a high-resolution transmitting microscope that permitted accurate  identification and centering of the beam. After completmn of the mmro-  probe analyses the epoxy-impregnated soft section was peeled away from the  glass slide and mounted in a Philips X-ray microcamera with a 60-micron  collimator for crystallographic identification.  Analyses for the isotropic domain (Fig. 2) showed a high alumina and low  silica content; the main components were amorphous to X-rays. Only  weak diffraction lines were evident from small quantities of associated  fine-grained quartz. Sodium-pyrophosphate dissolution suggested complex-  ing with humic constituents. This material was believed to constitute a  weathering component of the volcanic ash identified in the silt fraction.  On the basis of the X-ray diffraction pattern and chemical composition    238    Section P 412 A1 Horizon    Target: Yel|owiQh brown tsotropic nodule (grantc unit}  MicrOprobe Analyses  K.   0.25  Mn.    0,01  Ca    0.30  Fe     2.14  Mg     0.04                                                      -~  A!  24,64  S~   9.32  Na    0.2=  oxide total  ,70,40  .....  = ,:_  ......  Fig 2  EMA and XRD analyses of yellowish brown isotropic granic umt from the A1  horizon of the mullgramc sequence  Section 412 A1 Horizon    d/(A) ]I  1  3.34  ~'W      ~  3.16 w  2.24 vw    Target: YelJowish brown antsotroplc nodule (grenic unit)  Microprobe Analyses        dtn (~.) [  %  K .   10.89       10,0  s  Mn.    0.05        4.47 s  Ca.    0.07        3.34 m  Fe,   0.49       2.8? vs  Mg.   o.o2  AI.    7.59  SI.  31.34  Na.   O,Q4  oxide to4~.  95.44                    ---       :~ *   -  Fig 3. EMA and XRD analyses of yellowish brown anlsotropic granic unit from the A1  horizon of the mullgranlc sequence    Fig. 4. The chlamydic sequence within the pedon of a Molhc Cryoboralf a section of  pedon of a Mollic Cryoboralf, b. orthogranlc fabric; c rnatrichlamydic fabric; d matri-  plectlc fabric; e. plectic porphyric fabric.    239    240    the anlsotropic mullgranic unit (Fig. 3) was readily identified as a domain  of micaceous material, dominantly muscovite.    Chlamydtc sequence    The chlamydlc sequence of fabrics related to the distribution of f-mamx  around f-members as coatings and formation of bridges between them  (Brewer, 1979). The dynamic relationships between fabric types within  this sequence were observed as follows:  orthogranic matrlchlamydic ~ matriplectic ~ matriplectic porphyric  porphyric  The fabric sequence was generally characteristic of subsurface honzons  m coarse textured soils. All horizons below the A1 of the Mollic Cryoboralf  pedon developed from eolian sand, as depicted in Fig 4a, had microfabrics  dominantly within the chlamydic sequence.  Orthogranic fabric types (Fig. 4b) were found m isolated zones within  the C honzon. The "ortho" f-members were made up entirely of loosely  packed skeleton grains although pedorehcts and lithorelicts were also pre-  sent. The grams were generally bare in this case or only with thin partial  coatmgs that reflected a minor chlamydic component. Matrichlamydic  fabrics (Fig. 4c) characterized the lower eluviated horizon, the transition  between the A and B and were also observed in the parent material. The  f-matrix was observed as continuous coatings on f-members. While fabrics  were similar, differences m composition of f-matrix reflected very different  processes withm horizons. Matrlplectic fabrics (Fig. 4d) dominated in the  argillic B horizon. Coatings of f-matrix on the f-members were broadened  out to form bridges between closer members.  Although most of the matrix material in the sandy argillic B horizon  was illuwal in origin, observed extinction patterns showed lack of uniformity    Fig 5. SEM micrograph showing bimodal orientation for f-matrix in matriplectlc fabric.    241    in orientation and composition. SEM micrograph (Fig. 5) supported bimodal  orientation patterns for the f-matrix around and between f-members. It ap-  peared that these fabric types did not originate entirely by thickening of  arglllans where clays remained oriented parallel to the surface of the f-  member. The fact that the clays in the bridges were oriented perpendicular  to the surface suggested another mechanism, perhaps withdrawal of moisture  from capillary films through evapotranspiration losses.  Line scans made with SEM-EDXRA (Fig. 6) across a matrix bridge be-  tween f-members suggested that the plasma comprised a mixture of com-  ponents with considerable variation in Si/AI/Fe ratios over short distances  (in this case 40 microns). The foregoing was supported by lysimeter studies.    AL    SI    0            keY               10    AL    ~T 1 1-  0            keV                10    SI    AL    FE    0           keV                 10  Fig.6. SEM-EDXRA line scans of regions depicted in Fig.5, showing variability in plasma  composition over a distance of 40 microns.    242    Leachates from the eluvlated horizon were found to contmn significant  quantities of amorphous orgamc matter, iron, and aluminum as well as  clay minerals in the colloidal fraction. The separation of constituents within  the plasma suggests both podzolizatlon and lessivage contributed to the  processes of sod formations, each acting independently.  Plectra porphyric intergrade fabrics (Fig. 4e) were characteristic of hor-  Izontal bands within the argfthc B horizon. The f-matrix coatings were  broad, strongly coalesced and frequently completely filled the voids. In  porphyrlc fabrics the f-members were completely embedded in the f-matrix.  Development of the fabric sequence appeared to reflect partmle-slze  distribution and colloidal transport in the soil. Eluviation resulted in fabrics  toward the orthogranlc type while llluvlation produced fabrics toward  the matrlplectlc porphync and porphyric types. However, a similar sequence  of fabrics was also observed m porous argftlaceous sandstones derived  through sedimentary processes. Similar related distribution patterns were  also shown to be derived through freeze-thaw processes and by wetting and  drying    CONCLUSION    Other sequences of fabric also showed specific relationships between  processes and fabric type. Comprehensive studies to discern a better ap-  preclation of the dynamms wlthin these fabric sequences should prove  useful in understanding the genesis of the softs and should assist in better  planning of their management.    REFERENCES    Bal, L., 1973. Mieromorphologmal Analysis of Soils. Soil Survey Papers 6 Soil Surv. Inst.,  Wageningen, 174 pp  Brewer, R , 1977. Micromorphology of a euchrozem from Talavera, Queensland. CSIRO  Aust. Div. Soils, Dlv. Rep., 18  Brewer, R_, 1979 Relationship between particle size, fabric and other factors in some  Austrahan sods. Aust J. Sod Res., 17  29--41  Stoops, G. and Jongerius, A., 1975. Proposal for a micromorphological class,fication  of soil materials, 1 A classification of the related distributions of fine and coarse  particles. Geoderma, 13_189--199_                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractTerminology based on fabric sequences as proposed recently by Brewer (1979) was found useful for describing microfabrics in Alberta soils since it established a basis of study compatible with field morphological descriptions. The recognized fabric sequences were: granic, fragmic, chlamydic, and iunctic. Each sequence represented a continuum of fabric types distinguished on the basis of related distribution between fine and coarse materials.Attempts have been made to unify specific fabric types within each of the sequences on the basis of material composition and genetic processes. Since soil horizons were pedogenically generated as well, they in turn could usually be characterized by a single dominant fabric sequence. In our studies we found the granic sequence of fabric to characterize mull layers. The fragmic fabric sequence was more common in subsurface horizons of fine texture. The chlamydic fabric sequence was best developed in spodic and argillic horizons of coarse texture. A well developed iunctic sequence was found in moder as well as in coarse textured highly calcareous horizons. Fabric types within each of the recognized sequences were highly variable in time and/or space within their respective horizons.