Geoderma, 33 (1984) 119--134  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    119    EVALUATION OF PHOSPHORUS SORPTION BY AN ALLOPHANIC SOIL    JAIME II~IGUEZ and ROSA Ma VAL  Departamento de Edafologfa, Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad de Navarra, Pamplona  (Spain)  (Received January 15, 1982; revised version accepted December 15, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Ifiiguez, J. and Val, R.M., 1984. Evaluation of phosphorus sorption by an allophanic soil.  Geoderma, 33: 119--134.    Solutions containing different P concentrations were equilibrated with samples of an  allophanic soil from Navarra (Spain) to determine whether P sorption conformed qualita-  tively and quantitatively to the Langmuir, Freundlich and Sokolowska isotherms.  Phosphorus sorption conformed to the Langmuir isotherm. When the sorption data  were plotted according to the conventional and Hofstee forms, two linear relationships  were obtained. At the lower equilibrium P concentrations the K1 parameter determined  by regression analysis was higher than those corresponding to higher equilibrium P con-  centrations. The values obtained for K~ and K2 by the conventional and Hofstee equa-  tions were different. A procedure for evaluating the coefficients for higher equilibrium P  concentrations was proposed. The K1 and K2 values so obtained allowed us to generate  an experimental curve by addition of calculated adsorption data. This suggests that the  curve-splitting technique is satisfactory.  The sorption data also conformed to the Freundlich and Sokolowska equations, but in  the latter it was necessary to evaluate two different sets of parameters.  The same experimental data can be adjusted to the three different equations, in one  case with only one set of constants and in the other two cases with two different sets of  parameters, one for the lower P concentrations and the other for the higher ones. Besides,  to fit the experimental data to the Langmuir and Sokolowska equations, it was necessary  to split the isotherm into two regions and these two regions were different for  the Langmuir and the Sokolowska equations. This suggests that the parameters do not  have any chemical signification and that they are only "curve fitting".  A study of the effect of pH on the P sorption indicated that low pH notably increased  the P sorption.  The soil samples had very high phosphate sorption capacity probably due to the very  large specific surface and reactivity of the allophane.    INTRODUCTION    Andosols are widely distributed in the world and possess many special  properties such as low bulk density, high water holding capacity, high humus  content and large phosphate adsorption capacity. Their clay fractions mainly    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    120    consist of allophane, with the chemical formula m SiO:, A1203, /l H20,  where m = 1--2, but considerable variation in chemical composition has been  reported (Yoshinaga et al., 1968; Wada, 1978). Yoshinaga et al. (1968)  reported the existence of small but significant amounts of Fe.  Allophane adsorbs cations and anions from neutral salt solutions. Many  attempts have been made to clarify the reaction mechanisms of soil com-  ponents with anions, especially phosphate, because of its practical impor-  tance in agriculture.  Interactions of anions with allophane involve three different reactions:  non-specific adsorption, specific adsorption and decomposition of the al-  lophane induced specifically by adsorbed anions. The non-specific adsorp-  tion refers to adsorption of anions by simple coulombic interaction with  positive charges on A1--OH~ or Fe--OH~ groups. The specific adsorption  refers to incorporation of the anion as a ligand in the coordination shell of  an A1 or Fe atom (Wada, 1978). (These reactions have been extensively  studied for hydrous Fe oxides.) The induced decomposition of the al-  lophane signifies the precipitation of A1 or Fe compounds.  The results obtained by Imai et al. (1981) about the kinetics of adsorption  and its associated calorimetry, suggest that in allophanic soils very high in  organic matter, the organo-mineral complex seems to form a rather open  microstructure such that phosphate ions at low P additions are adsorbed on  relatively low energy surfaces only. When larger amounts of P are added,  more P-reactive surfaces are exposed; the loosely bound organic matter is  progressively displaced by the phosphate ions. With the largest P additions,  the adsorption is attributed to the nucleation, precipitation and recrystal-  lisation of aluminum phosphate (Imai et al., 1981).  Significantly, the adsorption capacity of allophane at higher phosphate  levels is directly related to the aluminum content of the sample (Theng et al.,  1982).  Regardless of the mechanism involved in the reaction the quantitative  description of soil--phosphate interactions is important for predicting phos-  phate fertilizer requirements of soils and critical levels in solution or as labile  phosphate in soils for optimum plant growth.  The Langmuir and Freundlich equations are often used to describe the  quantity/intensity relationships between solid and solution phase phosphates  in soils (Harter and Baker, 1977; Mead, 1981). The lack of agreement be-  tween phosphate adsorption data and these equations caused Syers et al.  (1973) to use a two-surface Langmuir equation.  The Freundlich equation has been criticized because it is an empirical  equation, with the constants having no physical meaning (Holford et al.,  1974). This equation has been rigorously derived by Sposito (1980). This  derivation requires only the applicability of the Langmuir equation to each  kind  of  adsorption sites regardless of the details of the adsorption  mechanism.  The Sokolowska isotherm is derived assuming that the Langmuir isotherm    121    is valid for individual (homotattic) sites and the energetic heterogeneity of  adsorption sites. The distribution of adsorption centers is supposed to be  continuous.  These three equations are based on the adsorption of ions on the solid  surfaces but none of them regard the possibility of secondary precipitation  phenomena.  Veith and Sposito (1977a, b) and Sposito (1982) have shown that the fit  of experimental sorption data to the Langmuir equation gives no informa-  tion concerning the chemical mechanism of the sorption reaction. Then it  follows that the parameters in the Langmuir equation, as deduced from a  statistical Langmuir plot of empirical data, will not have any particular  chemical meaning unless it has shown independently that only adsorption,  and not secondary precipitation, has occurred.  Also, any sorption reaction for which the distribution coefficient is a  finite and decreasing function of the amount sorbed and will extrapolate to  zero at a finite value of this sorbed amount can be represented mathematical-  ly by a two-surface Langmuir equation.  The purpose of this work was to determine the capacity of allophanic soil  samples to sorb inorganic P and to evaluate the applicability of the Langmuir,  Freundlich and Sokolowska equations in describing phosphate adsorption  isotherms. No attempt has been made to give any chemical interpretation to  the different equations.  In order to find a useful curve fitting isotherm equation for the data this  paper introduces a modification of the Langmuir two-surface equation pro-  posed by Syers et al. (1973). Different ways of plotting the Langmuir equa-  tion can produce different numerical values for the parameters.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The sampled soil, an Andaquept (Andosol), has been described in detail  elsewhere (Ifiiguez and Barrag~n, 1974; Barrag~n and Ifiiguez, 1976), so only  the more pertinent information is given here. It is located at the north of  Navarra (Spain) at an altitude of 1,000 m, under beech forest and under a  humid climate (total precipitation 1,850 mm, annual average temperature  15.7). The predominant mineral is allophane, accompanied by vermiculite,  illite and biotite. The A horizon is 80 cm thick, very homogeneous in color  (10 YR 2/1 to N 2 moist color). Soil samples were obtained from this sur-  face horizon. The soil samples were air-dried in the laboratory and material  passing a 0.2 mm sieve was used for all analyses.  The physical and chemical properties are summarized in Table I.  Isotherms for the sorption of inorganic phosphate were obtained by shak-  ing 2 g of soil material with 20 ml of phosphate solution containing ap-  propriate amounts of NH4H2PO4 in 40 ml polypropylene tubes. The max-  imum addition was 0.5 mmol P/g of soil. The native adsorbed phosphate  evaluated by the Bray and Kurtz (1945) method was 30 ~g P/g of soil.    122    TABLE I  Some properties of soil samples    pH                  Organic C    Exchangeable cations (meq./100 g)        Ext. acidity  (%)                                                       (meq./100 g) H+    H20     KCl IN                    Ca      Mg      Na      K       A1  4.8     4.4         7.05         0.21    1.10    0.15    0.06    2.70    30    Bulk density     Surface area     SiO~ extracted (%)              AI203 extracted (%)  (1/3 bar)        (m2/g)    Segalen (I)    Dith-Citr (2)     Segalen (i)    Dith-Citr (2)  0.54             270              7.20           4.75             8.20           7.40    Fe:Oa extracted %    Segalen (1)    Dith-Citr (2)  2.90           3.30             30    Native adsorbed P (3)  (pg/g soil)    (1) Segalen (1968): 16 alternative extractions with OHNa and HCI.  (2) Aguilera and Jackson (1953) for Fe; Hashimoto and Jackson (1960) for Si and A1.  (3) Bray and Kurtz (1945).    After shaking for an hour the suspensions rested for 24 h, with occasional  shaking, in a bath at 25 -+ I. Then, the suspensions were centrifuged and  the supernatant solutions analyzed for P and the pH was measured. The  amount of sorbed phosphorus was calculated from the difference between  the amount of phosphate added and that remaining in solution after the  sorption step. Further experiments were carried out after pH adjustment of  the samples with HC1.  The molybdate--vanadate method (Chariot, 1966) was used for the deter-  mination of dissolved inorganic phosphorus in the solutions and absorbance  was measured at 460 pm using a Hilger spectrophotometer.    EVALUATION OF EXPERIMENTAL DATA    The Langmuir adsorption equation,  K1K2c  x/m -  1 +Klc  can be written,  x/m = K2 - (x/m)/Klc                                                  (1)  where x/m is the quantity of P sorbed per unit of mass, c is the equilibrium P  concentration, and K1 and K2 are constant parameters. This equation so  arranged is commonly referred to as the Hofstee equation (Hofstee, 1952). A  plot of x/m versus x/m/c gives a straight line, from which K2 can be eval-  uated directly (y -- intercept) and K~ from slope-1.  The Langmuir equation can also be arranged  c/x/m = (1/K1K2) + c/K2                                               (2)    123    A plot of c/x/m versus c gives a straight line, from which K2 (slope-1)  and K1 (gradient/intercept) can be obtained.  Regression analysis was used to check all the straight lines obtained with  eqs. 1 and 2. The statistical significance of the correlation coefficients for  c/x/m versus c, or for x/m versus x/m/c was the criterion by which the fit of  the data to the Langmuir isotherms was tested.  The two Langmuir transformations of the isotherm to the linear form will  often produce two straight lines (Syers et al., 1973). This suggests the ex-  istence of two regions on the isotherm, each of which can be described by a  Langmuir relationship. So, the Langmuir equation becomes:  I I     glIIg21Ic  K1 K2 c  x/m -          +                                                   (3)  1 + g~c    1 + g~c  where superscripts I and II refer to each of the straight lines (region I and II,  respectively). Eq. 3 has been used in soil studies (Syers et al., 1973; Holford  et al., 1974).  The Langmuir on, surface equation assumes that the K1 and K2 param-  eters are constant for any equilibrium P concentration. The Langmuir two-  surface equation assumes for the constants two sets of values, corresponding  to the two regions of the isotherm.  In order to calculate K1 and Ks values for part II, Syers subtracted the KI  value from each of the x/m values for the data points in part II and cal-  culated a new regression equation for the corrected values for c/x/m against  the original c values.  When this procedure was followed, however, the c/x/m values tended  toward infinity because x/m approached zero when the c value decreased,  and the c value was always greater than zero. So, Shuman (1975) found that  the curve became erratic because the x/m values were so low, and Syers  concluded that it may be necessary to disregard low corrected c/x/m values  in part II, because these values may be subject to appreciable error.  In the use of eq. 3 we have based our calculations on a mathematical  model founded on the traditional method of solving the linear transforma-  tion of the basic adsorption, eq. 2 and calculating the parameter values by a  linear regression method.  In order to calculate K~II and K~, it was necessary to subtract from each of  the x/m values for the data points in part II the respective calculated values  for the first term of eq. 3.  It was possible to generate the sorption curve by adding the x/m values  corresponding to the two members of eq. 3, but it was necessary to subtract  a c' value from all the c values of part II in order to calculate the second  term values.  Eq. 3 becomes:  gIgIc   g~IIg2II(c - c')  x/m -          +                                                    (4)  1 + g[c   1 + glII(c - c')    124    where c' is the equilibrium P concentration at which the two straight lines.  representing part I and part II, intersect. For part I, the second term that had a  negative value was not considered. It was not possible to generate the iso-  therm by adding the values of the two members of eqs. 3 or 4, if c was not  so corrected. This correction does not have easy physical significance.  The Freundlich equation, the oldest sorption equation in the literature on  soil phosphate, is normally written as  x = a'c1In  from which:  logx = loga + (l/n) log c                                               (5)  permits a linear test plot where a and 1In are constants. Hayward and  Trapnell (1964) have shown that this equation corresponds to a model of  sorption in which the affinity term decreases exponentially as the amount of  adsorption increases. The constants in eq. 5 were calculated by simple linear  regression techniques.  In order to evaluate the validity of the Sokolowska equation, the exper-  imental adsorption isotherm was fitted to the equation:  0 = [a/(a + u)] ~                                                         (6)  where the degree of occupation of sites, 0, is equal to (x/m)/N; where N is  the sorption maxima; a is the molar ionic activity, u is a constant related to  the standard chemical potential and 7 is a parameter that signifies the hetero-  geneity of sorption sites (Sokolowska et al., 1980). The Sokolowska equa-  tion assumes the continuous variation of sorption energy as the P equi-  librium concentration increases.    RESULTS    The standard error of the duplicate measures was obtained using:  a = (E((Xi- Yi)/2)2/n)1/2  where X and Y are duplicate values and n the number of duplicate deter-  minations.  Thus, the standard error for the pH 7 curve was a = 0.0081 (n = 16). The  experiments were carried out at three different pH values. The standard  deviations for the pH values 3,  5 and 7 were 0.45, 0.48 and 0.21,  respectively.  The amount of native phosphorus was similar to that found by Holford  (1980). This amount was irrelevant when compared with the total amount of  P sorbed by the soil samples and it was not taken into account for fitting the  isoterms.    P concentration &lt;~ 1 10-2 mmol/ml    The sorption isotherms for different pH values are shown in Fig. 1. The  capacity to sorb added P increased with a decrease in soil pH.    125    A  0  E  E  '10  Ul  'I0  0    0.15    0.10    0.05    pH5  //  /    0.002         O.OOl.         0.006        0.008        0.01    c P (mm01/m[)    Fig. 1. Isotherms for sorption of added inorganic P by soil at different pH values (P con-  centration ~ 1.10-~ mmol/ml).    m  x  o'1  E  u    PH7  pH5    c P (mmollml x103)    Fig.  2.  Langmuir isotherms for P sorption at different pH values (P concentration   1.10-2 mmol/ml).    2     l,     6     8     I0    126    When the sorption data were plotted according to the Langnmir equation  a linear relationship was obtained (Fig. 2). P sorption conformed to the  Langmuir isotherm. The graphical resolution of the sorption data was carried  out to get the best fit, using regression analysis to check all the straight lines  obtained. The slope-~ and intercept were used to calculate K, and K2. The  calculated K~  and Ks values for the different pH values are shown h~  Table II. The corresponding r values were all highly significant. The values  obtained for K~ are very different. K2 values, however, are rather uniform.  Therefore, the pH of the soil suspension has influence on K1 but not on K2.  The Kj values are much greater when the solution becomes more acid.    TABLE II  K1 and K2 obtained by the conventional Langmuir equation at different pH values. P  concentration ~&lt; 1 10-: mmol/ml    K1               K2               r (1)  (ml/mmol)    (mmol P/g)    pH 7           421.5                 0.185                   0.975  pH 5         2775.2                 0.166                   0.992  pH 3      38968.3                 0.254                   0.986    (1) All correlation coefficients have significance at the 1%o level of probability.    P concentration &gt; 1 10-2 mmol/ml    The sorption isotherms are shown in Fig. 3. Here also the capacity to sorb  added P increased for the same concentration values with a decrease in pH.  When the sorption data were plotted according to the Langmuir equation  (eq. 2) two linear relationships were obtained (Fig. 4), each of which can be  described by a Langmuir relationship.  Owing to the large amounts of P uptake for this soil material, we have  calculated the various isotherm parameters only for the data at pH 7, cor-  responding to the smallest sorption.  The Langmuir coefficients calculated from the equations for the best-  fitting straight lines are shown in Table III. We have also tried the resolution  on three or more straight lines but the correlation coefficients have minor  significance.  Following the procedure outlined above, we recalculated the values of  x/m and c for part II and computed a new regression for c/x/m versus c  (Fig. 4 and Table III). This corrected regression was used to calculate the  coefficients for part II of the curve. This procedure allowed evaluation of  part II parameters K1 and K2 without interference from part I. In addition,    127    h0    pH 3  /  ~/ p H S  E   0.5            .  .                                               / pH 7  E  ,.~                                                              :  o  ul  "0  O  Q..  06s        0i0         0.;s         o~o  c P (mmol/ml)  Fig. 3. Isotherms for the sorption of added inorganic P at different pH values (up to a P  concentrat'ion of 0.20 mmol/ml).    0.5,  0.4                                                             pH 7  A  E   0.3  .~                                       pH5  E  X  ---   0.2,  u.                                                                                pH3  0.1  0.os       0i0       o is       020  c P (mmol/ml)  Fig. 4. Langmuir isotherms for P sorption at different pH values (up to a P concentration  of 0.20 mmol/m]; pH 7: A, original values; B, corrected values for part II.)    0.5    TABLE III    Comparison of K1 and K~ for parts I and II obtained by conventional ioriginal and cor-  rected values) and Hofstee equations  Part I      Part II                    Hofstee method  original    corrected    part I      part lI  values      values    KI (ml/mmol)   385.1       19.12      14.66        729.9      24.45  K2 (mmol/g)       0.185     0.602      0.39          0.153     0.545  r (1)                 0.99      0.99        0.937         0.939     0.888    (1) All correlation coefficients have significance at the 1%o level of probability.    it was possible to generate the original curve by adding the values obtained  by the curve-splitting technique (Fig. 5). The curve so obtained showed a  sharp inflection in the concentration at which the two lines representin~  parts I and II joined. The K~ values were always much greater than the K~  values.    0.4    ~f  J       0.3  o  E  E  --   0.2  u  ..1=1  -~   O.I    128    0.05          0.I0          0.15  c  P (rn mollml)  Fig. 5. Observed values (e) and Langmuir-predicted P adsorption curve using corrected  values by the proposed procedure.    129    The K1 and K2 values obtained by the Hofstee method are also presented  in Table III. The graphical representation x/m versus x/m/c and the values  for the regression equation are shown in Fig. 6. The straight lines obtained  from the K values calculated by eq. 2 are also represented. The K values were  different, depending on the procedure used. The existence of two straight  lines with different K~ and K2 values, however, was also evident.    E  E  E    0.5   0.~    0.3    0.2    0.1    \o\  "'x~" x  x/m= - 0.0/~09 xlmlc + 0.5/~52    10    2"0                 3'0    xlmlc  (mllg)  Fig. 6. Phosphorus sorption data plotted as x/m vs. (x/rn)/c. The two continuous lines  correspond to the values obtained by the Hofstee equation, and the dashed lines to that  obtained by the conventional equation.    The comparison of the diverse K values obtained showed that the K1  parameter obtained by the Hofstee procedure (y-intercept of the curve) was  0.698 mmol/g and was thus lower than that calculated using eq. 2,  0.787 mmol/g. Both values for the K2 constants of part I and part II ob-  tained from the Hofstee representation (Fig. 6) were also appreciably lower  than those obtained from the regressions in Fig. 4. The K1 constants cal-  culated from eq. 2 were lower than those calculated from eq. 1.  The experimental sorption data were also fitted to eq. 5. The Freundlich  equation closely predicted the actual phosphate sorption, and a linear trans-  formation of the data produced one straight line (Fig. 7). The goodness-of-fit  was tested by simple linear regression. The values obtained were: slope 0.439,    130    and intercept 1.292, and the linear regression coefficient, r = 0.97, was  significant at a 0.001 level.  The experimental sorption data were also fitted to the equation proposed  by Sokolowska (eq. 6). The values obtained for the constants are shown in  Table IV. It was not possible to generate the original curve assuming the  same constants for u, 7 and N for all levels of P concentration. The exper-  imental points deviated from the predicted curve at high levels of concentra-  tion; for these high values it was necessary to calculate new constant values.    2.8  2.6       2.4  x  ~     2.2  2.0  o  E  E    1.~  ..o     1.6  c..  0  o..    I./.  o      1.2    Y  r = 0.97    0           I           2           3  log [Plmmlcc (x10.O00)  Fig. 7. Observed values (e) and Freundlich-predicted P sorption (--).    The fit was excellent when the equation for the curve was solved in two  portions (Fig. 8). Because of the difficulty of a linear transformation of the  curve, the goodness of fit was only tested by visual inspection.  The concentration 0.08 mmol/ml splits the isotherm in two regions  (Fig. 8). It was very different from 0.0195 mmol/ml equilibrium P con-  centration at which the two Langmuir straight lines representing part I and  part II intersected (Fig. 4).    TABLE IV    Sokolowska parameters for regions I and II  u (mmol/ml)   -~       N (retool/g)  Region I     0.037          0.82    0.473  Region II   0.09           0.97    0.715    131    0.5    0.~.    '~  0.3  o  E  E  --  0.2  "D  U  a   0.1  O.    t  /    I    o.os          o.io          o.is  c  P (m mol/ml}  Fig. 8. Observed values (e) and Sokolowska-predieted P adsorption curve obtained using  the different parameters showed in Table IV. (Region I continuous line; region II dashed  line).    The N value for region II was 0.715 mmol/g that compared favorably  with  the values  obtained using the Langmuir equation (0.787 and  0.698 mmol/g).  The heterogeneity parameter, % was higher in region II than in region I.    SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS    The P sorption by samples of the Andosol was much higher than those  encountered by other workers (Gebhardt and Coleman, 1974; Rajan and  Watkinson, 1976; Wada and Gunjigake, 1979).  We have compared the validity of three isotherms: Langmuir, Freundlich  and Sokolowska, to explain the phosphate sorption behaviour of an  Andosol. Sorption data conformed to the Langmuir adsorption isotherm as  indicated by the highly significant correlation coefficients for c/x/m versus c  and x/m versus x/m/c. The adsorption isotherms were resolved into two  linear portions. These results allowed computation of the K2 and K1 con-  stants of the Langmuir equation.  The gradientAntercepts of the lines were very different for various pH  values; at low concentrations the KI value was 6 times greater for pH 5  than for pH 7 and 90 times for pH 3.  The values obtained for the Langmuir constants differed according to the  procedure used (Hofstee or conventional).    132    The K2 values were higher for part lI than for part 1 and th~ K~ values for  part I were between 20 and 30 times greater than those for part 1!.  The proposed procedure for calculating K~  and K~ valm~s for part lI  permitted construction of the original experimental curve. This suggests that  the curve-splitting technique is satisfactory.  The uncorrected value for K:II should approach the addition of KI and  K:II obtained by the correction procedure. In fact good agreement was  obtained between these two values (0.622 mmol/g and 0.575 mmol/g,  respectively).  The Langmuir two-surface equation was far superior to tile one-surface  equation for fitting soil phosphate sorption data, which agrees with the  findings of Holford et al. (1974).  The Freundlich equation also closely predicted the actual phosphate  sorption better than the Langmuir one-surface equation. A linear trans-  formation of the data produced one straight line (Fig. 7).  The Sokolowska procedure permitted generation of the experimental  isotherm. It was necessary, however, to split the curve in two regions and to  calculate different parameters for low and high concentrations. The two  regions so obtained were different from those derived by the Langmuir  procedure.  Therefore, these observations suggest that the Langmuir two-surface, the  Freundlich and the Sokolowska equations would have been adequate to  describe the experimental process.  The same experimental data can be adjusted to the Freundlieh equation  with only one set of constants and to the Langmuir and Sokolowska equa-  tions with two different sets of parameters, one for the lower and the other  for the higher P concentration. In addition the two latter equations split the  isotherm in two regions that are different. These facts indicate that the  parameters have no chemical signification and that they are only "curve  fitting" parameters. Besides, different ways of plotting the Langmuir equa-  tion (Hofstee or conventional) can produce different numerical values for  the parameters, specially for the K1 constant.  Because of the large capacity for P sorption by the soil samples and the  irrelevant amount of native exchangeable P, it is possible that at low-equi-  librium P concentrations the sorption data fit well the Langmuir one-surface  equation. It is necessary to reach very-high-equilibrium P concentrations to  need the Langmuir two-surface equation to explain P sorption.  When the Langmuir two-surface, the Freundlich and the Sokolowska  equations are tested, the data fitted very well up to an equilibrium P con-  centration of 0.20 mmol/ml.  The high P concentrations used could make possible precipitation of P as  aluminum phosphate. The Langmuir equation can not be used to determine  whether adsorption or precipitation (formation of secondary minerals) is  occurring during anion fixation reactions in soils. The parameters in the  Langmuir equation can not be interpreted in terms of surface reactions  without additional independent evidence.    133    REFERENCES    Aguilera, N.H. and Jackson, M.L., 1953. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. J., 17: 359--364.  Barrag~in, E. and Ifiiguez, J., 1976. Weathering of clays minerals in a Navarre Andosol  (Spain). Clay Minerals, 11: 269--272.  Bray, R.H. and Kurtz, L.T., 1945. Determination of total organic and available forms of  phosphorus in soils. Soil Sci., 59: 39.  Charlot, G., 1966; Les m~thodes de la chimie analytique. Analyse quantitative min~rale.  Masson et Cie, Paris.  Gebhardt, H. and Coleman, N.T., 1974. Anion adsorption by allophanic tropical soils, III.  Phosphate adsorption. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 263--267.  Harter, R.D. and Baker, D.E., 1977. Applications and misapplications of the Langmuir  equation to soil adsorption phenomena. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 1077--1080.  Hashimoto, I. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Rapid dissolution of allophane and kaolinite--  halloysite after deshydration. Proceedings of the 7th National Conference on Clays  and Clay Minerals. Pergamon Press, London.  Hayward, D.O. and Trapnell, B.M.W., 1964. Chemisorption. Butterworth and Co. Ltd.,  London, 2rid ed.  Hofstee, B.H.J., 1952. On the evaluation of the constants Vm and Km in enzyme re-  actions, Science, 116: 329--331.  Holford, I.C.R., 1980. Adsorbed phosphate in soils and sediments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.,  44: 441.  Holford, I.C.R., Wedderburn, R.W.M. and Mattingly, G.E.G., 1974. A Langmuir two-  surface equation as a model for phosphate adsorption by soils. J. Soil Sci., 25:  242--255.  Imai, H., Goulding, K.W.T. and Talibudeen, O., 1981. Phosphate adsorption in allophanic  soils. J. Soil Sci., 32: 555--570.  Ifiiguez, J. and Barrag~n, E., 1974. Andosuelos desarrollados sobre filitas en Ulzama  (Navarra). An. Edaf. Agrobiol., 33: 1055--1069.  Mead, J.A., 1981. A comparison of the Langmuir, Freundlich and Temkin equations to  describe phosphate adsorption properties of soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 19: 333--342.  Rajan, S.S.S. and Watkinson, J.H., 1976. Adsorption of selenite and phosphate on an  atlophane clay. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 51--54.  Segalen, P.,  1968. Note sur une m6thode de determination des produits min6raux  amorphes. Cahiers ORSTOM, Pedologie, 1: 105.  Shuman, L.M., 1975. The effect of soil properties on zinc adsorption by soils. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 454--458.  8okolowska, Z. and Szczypa, J., 1980. Adsorption isotherms for weak acid anions in  soils. Geoderma, 24: 349--361.  Sposito, G., 1980. Derivation of the Freundlich equation for ion exchange reactions in  soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 652--654.  Sposito, G., 1982. On the use of the Langmuir equation in the interpretation of "adsorp-  tion" phenomena, II. The "two-surface" Langmuir equation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46:  1147--1152.  Syers, J.K., Browman, M.G., Smillie, G.W. and Corey, R.B., 1973. Phosphate sorption by  soils evaluated by the Langmuir adsorption equation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 37:  358--363.  Theng, B.K.G., Russell, M., Churchman, G.J. and Parfitt, R.L., 1982. Surface properties  of allophane, halloysite and imogolite. Clays Clay Miner., 30: 143.  Veith, J.A. and Sposito, G., 1977a. Reactions of aluminosilicates, aluminum hydrous  oxides, and aluminum oxide with o-phosphate: the formation of X-ray amorphous  analogs of variscite and montebrasite. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 870--876.  Veith, J.A. and Sposito, G., 1977b. On the use of the Langmuir equation in the inter-  pretation of "adsorption" phenomena. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 697--702.    134    Wada, K., 1978. Allophane and imogolite. In: T. Sudo and S. Shimoda (Editors), Clays  and Clay Minerals of Japan.  Kodansha Ltd., Tokyo, and Elsevier, Amsterdam~  pp. 147--187.  Wada, K. and Gunjigake, N., 1979. Active aluminum and iron phosphate adsorption ir~  Ando soils. Soil Sci., 128: 331--336.  Yoshinaga, N., Yotsumoto, H. and Ibe, K., 1968. An electron microscope study of soil  allophane with an ordered structure. Am. Miner., 53: 319--323.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractSolutions containing different P concentrations were equilibrated with samples of an allophanic soil from Navarra (Spain) to determine whether P sorption conformed qualitatively and quantitatively to the Langmuir, Freundlich and Sokolowska isotherms.Phosphorus sorption conformed to the Langmuir isotherm. When the sorption d data were plotted according to the conventional and Hofstee forms, two linear relationships were obtained. At the lower equilibrium P concentrations the K1 parameter determined by regression analysis was higher than those corresponding to higher equilibrium P concentrations. The values obtained for K1 and K2 by the conventional and Hofstee equations were different. A procedure for evaluating the coefficients for higher equilibrium P concentrations was proposed. The K1 and K2 values so obtained allowed us to generate an experimental curve by addition of calculated adsorption data. This suggests that the curve-splitting technique is satisfactory.The sorption data also conformed to the Freundlich and Sokolowska equations, but in the latter it was necessary to evaluate two different sets of parameters.The same experimental data can be adjusted to the three different equations, in one case with only one set of constants and in the other two cases with two different sets of parameters, one for the lower P concentrations and the other for the higher ones. Besides, to fit the experimental data to the Langmuir and Sokolowska equations, it was necessary to split the isotherm into two regions and these two regions were different for the Langmuir and the Sokolowska equations. This suggests that the parameters do not have any chemical signification and that they are only Ã¢Â€Âœcurve fittingÃ¢Â€Â.A study of the effect of pH on the P sorption indicated that low pH notably increased the P sorption.The soil samples had very high phosphate sorption capacity probably due to the very large specific surface and reactivity of the allophane.