Geoderma, 18 (1977) 251--263                                                    251  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SESQUIOXIDIC COMPONENTS OF SELECTED TAIWAN SOILS    P.M. HUANG1, M.K. WANG2, M.H. WU~, C.L. LIU2 and T.S.C. WANG3  'Department of Soil Science, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Sask. (Canada)  2 Department of Soil Science, National Chung Hsing University, Taichung (Taiwan)  3 Taiwan Sugar Research Institute, Tainan (Taiwan)  (Received July 27, 1976; accepted February 25, 1977)    ABSTRACT    Huang, P.M., Wang, M.K., Wu, M.H., Liu, C.L. and Wang, T.S.C., 1977. Sesquioxidic com-  ponents of selected Taiwan soils. Geoderma, 18: 251--263.    Twenty two surface soils, representing six parent materials and four soil groups, were  sampled in Taiwan for the present study.  Except in the soil derived from volcanic ash, the sesquioxidic components and rela-  tively easily extractable Si were present only in small amounts in the NaOAc and H202-  NaOAc extractable fractions. In addition to Fe, both Si and A1 were present in the di-  thionite-citrate-bicarbonate extracts in considerable amounts, indicating that Si and A1  were either present separately or in association with Fe in the sesquioxidic fractions of  the soils. The amounts of Si, A1 and Fe extracted by the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate  and boiling KOH treatments differed from sample to sample, indicating that they are im-  portant variables in the nature of the soils studied.  The amounts of the ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe, representing the non-  crystalline sesquioxidic products of relatively recent weathering, also differed with parent  materials and pedogenic processes. The statistical data indicate that the ammonium oxa-  late-extractable A1 and Fe are related to the contents of organic matter but not to acidity  and the contents of clay. The percentage distribution of the extractable A1 in the &gt; 2 ~m  fractions of the selected soil samples ranged from 22.0 to 52.5% and that of the extract-  able Fe from 11.1 to 38.1%, indicating that the active non-crystalline A1 and Fe compo-  nents in the non-clay fractions deserve close attention in the study of pedogenesis and  other soil physicochemical reactions in relation to soil fertility and environmental protec-  tion.    INTRODUCTION    Non-crystalline inorganic components of soils are often qualified by the  term "active", indicating their importance in soil processes (Mitchell et al.,  1964). The principal forms of non-crystalline inorganic materials which occur  in soils are the oxides and hydrous oxides of silicon, aluminum, iron, and  others, either separately or combined. Non-crystalline inorganic materials  are either residual from the parent material or physical, chemical and bio-  chemical weathering products of crystalline minerals during pedogenesis.  These non-crystalline inorganic components may be adsorbed on mineral    252    surfaces or exist as discrete particles (Huang and Lee, 1969; Huang and  Kozak, 1970; Wada and Harward, 1974). To date, research work on these  components has been virtually restricted to the clay fractions of soils (Wada  and Harward, 1974). Information on the distributiori and nature of these  components in the non-clay fractions still remains to be documented.  In Taiwan, considerable efforts have been devoted to the study of crystal-  line components of soil colloids (Juang, 1967; Chang, 1969; Leung and Lai,  1969; Juo et al., 1971; Yang and Chi, 1973). A great deal has been learned  from these studies regarding crystalline clay minerals of those soils. In view  of the recognized significance of non-crystalline inorganic components of  soils in pedogenesis, physicochemical reactions, and transformations of  nutrients and pollutants in soils (Mitchell et al., 1964; Rich, 1968; Wada and  Harward, 1974; Huang, 1975; Kinniburgh et al., 1976), and the relatively  high weathering intensity of the environment in Taiwan (Leung and Chen,  1966) which is conducive to accumulation of these components, there is  an urgent need to gain further insight into the nature of these inorganic mate-  rials in different particle size fractions of the soils.  The objective of this study was to examine the sesquioxidic components  of selected Taiwan soils derived from various parent materials under dif-  fering pedogenic processes. Advancement of this knowledge would pave the  way to understanding further the chemistry of sesquioxidic components of  soils and their significance in soil processes.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Twenty-two surface soils (Ap horizons) were sampled in Taiwan for the  present study. Two of them were developed from sandstone alluvial sedi-  ments, three from sandstone and shale alluvial sediments, seven from slate  alluvial sediments, three from mudstone alluvial sediments, six from the  diluvial deposits of the Quaternary Period and one from volcanic ash. Ex-  cept for the Yangmingshan soil which was developed from volcanic ash and  used as a reference sample, the rest were from important agricultural areas.  General descriptions of the soils studied are presented in Table I.  The soil samples were air dried and passed through a 2-mm sieve. The pH  was determined in a 1:1 soil: water paste (Jackson, 1958), organic matter by  the Walkley--Black method (Jackson, 1958), and texture by the hydrometer  method (Day, 1965).    Sequential treatments    One gram of &lt; 0.5-mm air-dried soil sample was subjected to certain se-  quential treatments, namely, NaOAc (pH 5), H202-NaOAc (pH 5), dithionite-  citrate-bicarbonate (Jackson, 1956) and boiling KOH (Dudas and Harward,  1971). In the NaOAc, H~O2-NaOAc, and boiling KOH extracts, A1, Fe and  Si were determined without pretreatments of the extracts. In the dithionite-    253    &lt;    0    C~  ~a  ,=     0  0    ._=  .~o    ~'~      ~ ~  ~u2   a~  ..2                                                            ~   ~:~  In  In    22              SoS o~  ~NNNNN N N NNNNNNN o o  o   ~  ~  0  0   0     0   0     0    0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0                                   ~    254    citrate-bicarbonate treatment, 100 ml of each extract was transferred to a  250-ml polyethylene conical flask and air was bubbled through the extract  for 4 hours or more to oxidize any remaining dithionite (Weaver et ai., 1968).  Si and Fe were determined in the oxidized dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate ex-  tract. For the determination of A1 in the oxidized extract, citrate was de-  stroyed (Weaver et al., 1968) to eliminate its interference in the colorimetric  determination of A1. After the boiling KOH treatment, the residue was sub-  jected to the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate treatment again; Fe was deter-  mined in the oxidized extract. In all the analytical determinations, A1 was  determined by the aluminon method (Hsu, 1963) with the addition of thio-  glycolic acid, Fe by the 1,10-phenanthroline method (Jackson, 1958), and  Si by the blue molybdosilicic acid method as modified by Weaver et al. (1968).    Ammonium oxala te treatment    The total soil  One gram of ~ 0.5-mm air-dried soil sample was treated with 50 ml of  0.2M ammonium oxalate (pH 3) solution in a 100-ml polyethylene tube  in darkness (Schwertmann, 1964). The suspension was shaken for four hours  and then centrifuged. A 10-ml aliquot of the supernatant together with 5 ml  of concentrated HNO3 and 0.5 ml of 18N H2SO4 were digested to dryness  (past fuming) on an electric hotplate. 10 ml of 0.5N HC1 was added to the  residue. The acid suspension was digested at 80--90C for half an hour. An  aliquot was then analyzed for A1 and Fe by the aluminon method (Hsu, 1963)  with the addition of thioglycolic acid and the 1,10-phenanthroline method  (Jackson, 1958), respectively.    Various size fractions  A &lt; 2 mm air-dried soil sample was dispersed by using Sonifier Cell Dis-  ruptor Model W-140-E. The instrument was equipped with a sonabox to  decrease cavitation sound. For dispersion of soils, this instrument was oper-  ated at 80% efficiency and with the tip of the probe about 2 cm below the  surface of the soil suspension (Genrich and Bremner, 1972). Dispersion was  performed by vibrating 10 g of sample in 25 ml of water for 15 min. The  soil--water suspension was contained in a 50-ml beaker and kept below 20  during the ultrasonification period by cooling in cold water.  The dispersed soil sample was separated into &lt; 2, 2--5, 5--20, 20--50, and  &gt; 50 um fractions (Jackson, 1956), The various size fractions were extracted  by the ammonium oxalate method (Schwertmann, 1964) and the extracted  A1 and Fe were determined as stated above. To compute the percentage  distribution of the ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe in the various  size fractions of a soil sample, the sum of the extractable A1 or Fe of individ-  ual size fractions of a soil sample was calculated by taking the weight of  each particle size fraction into account.  The correlation coefficients were calculated for the amounts of ammonium    255    oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe versus pH values and contents of clay and  organic matter. The amounts of ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe  were also plotted versus contents of organic matter to illustrate the scatter  of data.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The pH values, textures and contents of organic matter of the soil samples  are shown in Table II. The pH values range from 4.3 to 8.1, the textures  from sandy loam to clay loam, and the contents of organic matter from 0.81%  to 17.78%.  The data on the sequential treatments of entire soil samples are presented  in Table III. The amounts of Si, A1 and Fe extracted by the NaOAc (pH 5)  and H202 followed by the NaOAc (pH 5) are generally low except in the  Yangmingshan soil sample. This indicates that, except for the soil derived  from volcanic ash, the sesquioxidic components and relatively easily extract-  able Si are only present in small amounts in the NaOAc and H202-NaOAc  extractable fractions.    TABLE II    Selected properties of the soil samples    Soil              Depth     pH   Texture*   Organic  (cm)                         matter  (%)    Pinglin           0--20      4.4  sl           1.09  Tsutzekerng     0--25      6.3  sl           2.02  Shuechia         0--15      8.1   sil           1.34  Chiali            0--20      8.0   1            0.92  Shiewshui        0--15      6.9  sicl          2.77  Yuanlin          0--18      7.1   sil           1.44  Hsihu            0-15      7.9  sil           2.62  Neipu            0-18      6.4   sil           4.32  Chawchou       0-15      6.3  sil           2.61  Tsutien          0-12      5.0  sil           2.11  Pingtung         0-30      6.0   sil           2.21  Taikang I        0--24      6.9   sic          3.10  Taikang II       0--18      6.7   sicl          1.84  Hsinying         0-30      8.1   siel          1.81  Hengchun        0-15      7.6   cl           3.61  Minhsiung I      0-19      4.3   sil           1.64  Minhsiung II     0-16       5.1   sil            1.41  Tatushan I       0-30      6.9   1            1.60  Tatushan II       0-20       4.4   sl            0.81  Minhsiung III    0-17      4.8  1            1.08  Laupei           0-20      4.5  sicl          2.31  Yangmingshan   0--30      6.0   sl          17.78    *sl = sandy loam; sil = silt loam; 1 = loam; sicl = silty clay loam; sic -- silty clay; el =  clay loam.    256    ,-1  &lt;    e~  e.  ~4  0  C~    o    ~0~    .2  ?  z  ~    0    ~.:~-~ o  .~  ~.~ ~ ,-..~ ~  ~z~~:    o  0  e~  0  2  ~4  0  e~  0  .~_  7~    257    In addition to Fe, both Si and Ai are present in considerable amounts in  the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate extracts from the soil samples (Table III),  indicating that Si and AI are present either separately or in association with  Fe in the sesquioxidic fractions of the soils. A1 and Fe may be bonded to-  gether by the hydroxyl bridging mechanism (Jackson, 1965). Silicon can be  associated with the sesquioxidic compounds through coprecipitation of  Si(OH)4 with hydroxy-A1 and -Fe ions followed by the condensation reac-  tion involving hydroxyl groups (Luciuk and Huang, 1974). The amounts  of the Si, Al and Fe extracted by the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate method  differ significantly from soil to soil; the Taikang soil is next to the Yang-  mingshan soil in amounts of extractable A1 and Fe. ThQ Tatushan soils  (Ultisols) contain lower amounts of the extractable A1 and Fe than the  Taikang soil (Alfisols). It is clear that the Taikang soil is the highest in  amounts of dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate-extractable Al and Fe among the  important agricultural soils studied. These sesquioxidic components deserve  close attention in the management of soil resources, in as much as they have  important effects on physicc&gt;chemical properties and the nutrient status of  soils (Mitchell et al., 1964; Wada and Harward, 1974).  The amounts of boiling KOH-extractable Si, A1 and Fe from the soil  samples also differ from sample to sample (Table III), implying that non-  crystalline Al- and Fe-silicates are also significant variables in the nature of  the soils studied. Among the soils studied, the Suechia soil derived from  sandstone and shale is the lowest in amounts of the boiling KOH-extractable  Si and A1. In the Yangmingshan, Taikang and Hsinying soils, the amount of  Fe extracted by the boiling KOH treatment is significantly higher than in the  others.  Although the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate and boiling KOH treatments  for differentiating the total sesquioxidic components and nomcrystalline A1-  and Fe-silicates, respectively, merit further refinement, the data obtained  from the treatments (Table III) provide useful information on the relative  amounts of these materials in the soils studied.  The amounts of A1 and Fe extracted from the soil samples by the am-  monium oxalate method (Schwertmann, 1964) also differ (Table IV). The  Yangmingshan soil derived from volcanic ash has the highest amounts of  ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe. Among those important agricul-  turally, the Laupei, Hengchun and Taikang soils have higher amounts of e~-  tractable Al. The Entisols derived from slate and the Alfisols from mudstone  and from sandstone and shale are generally high in amounts of extractable  Fe. The Entisols derived from sandstone and shale and the Alfisols from the  Quaternary diluvial deposits are in general relatively low in extractable Fe.  Except for the Laupei soil, the Ultisols studied have relatively low contents  of ammonium oxalate-extractable Fe (Table IV). The relatively high value for  the Laupei soil is probably attributable to its finer texture (Table II). The  generally low contents of the extractable Fe in the Ultisols can be partially    258    TABLE IV    The amounts of the A1 and Fe in ppm extracted from entire soil samples by the  ammonium oxalate method  Soil              AI      Fe    Ent~o~  Sandstone    Sandstone and shale    Slate    Pinglin             498    1,297  Tsutzekerng       758    3,615    Shuechia          585    3,688  Chiali             558    2,033    Shiewshui         684    4,151  Yuanlin            452    5,547  Hsihu            417    5,047  Neipu             535    3,208  Chawchou         767    5,667  Tsutien           529    2,841  Pingtung          302    2,516    Alfisols  Mudstone    Sandstone and shale  Diluvial deposits of  the Quaternary Period    Taikang I       1,248    4,979  Taikang II         858    4,354  Hsinying          433    1,017    Hengchun       1,227    7,458    Minhsiung I       615    2,683  Minhsiung II      446    2,063    Ul t is o ls  Diluvial deposits of  the Quaternary Period    Tatushan I        404      892  Tatushan II       563    1,013  Minhsiung III      746    1,927  Laupei          2,323    3,271    Inceptisols  Volcanic ash  Yangmingshan   5,000   16,881    attributed to their age. The ammonium oxalate is an extractant for non-crys-  talline sesquioxidic components of relatively recent weathering (Lundblad,  1934; Mitchell et al., 1964; Schwertmann, 1964). The soils derived from the  Quaternary diluvial deposits are relatively much older compared with those    259    TABLE V  Correlations between the amounts of the A1 and Fe extracted by the ammonium  oxalate method and the pH values and contents of clay and organic matter    Correlation pair    Correlation coefficient    A1 versus pH                  0.17.1  Al versus clay                0.20* 1  A1 versus organic matter      0.76*2  Fe versus pH                  0.26.1  Fe versus clay                0.10.1  Fe versus organic matter     0.75*2    ,1 Not significant.  ,2 Significant at 1% level.     ooi  230Qt    E   ~soc  o 1250   looo  o  750  E 500  E  &lt;    250    Alluvial sediments Of sandstone  0 Alluvial sediments of sandstone and shale  X Alluvial sediments of slate  O Alluvial seaiments of mudstone  E] Diluvial deposits of the quaternary period  Volcanic ASH    0  0     []       x  x  D  x  DXDO         o     t    ~     ~     ;.     ~"    ~'8  Organic matterj %  Fig.1. The relationship between the amounts of organic matter and ammonium oxalate-  extractable Al; the regression equation for A1 versus organic matter is Y = 416.3 + 141.1x,  where x represents contents of organic matter and y those of At    260    derived from the alluvial sediments (Leung and Chen, 1966). Much of the  weathered non-crystalline Fe oxides of the Ultisols derived from the Quater-  nary diluvial deposits may therefore have been converted to crystalline Fe  oxides through a long pedogenic process. This agrees with the general theory  that ageing is an important parameter in the crystallization of sesquioxidic  compounds (Hsu and Ragone, 1972; Luciuk and Huang, 1974).  The amounts of non-crystalline sesquioxidic components are expected to  differ from the alluvial sediments of sandstone, shale, slate, and mudstone,  diluvial deposits of the Quaternary Period and volcanic ash (Rankama and  Sahama, 1950; Jackson, 1964, 1965). Furthermore, in view of the differ-  ences in pedogenic processes involved in these soils (Leung and Chen, 1966),  the contents of their sesquioxidic components are also expected to differ.  Therefore, the observed differences in the amounts of the ammonium oxalate-  extractable A1 and Fe among the soil samples (Table IV) are attributable to  the combined effects of parent materials and pedogenic processes.  The differing contents of ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe of the  soil samples were compared with their pH values and clay and organic matter  contents (Table V). Except for the relationships between extractable A1 and  Fe and organic matter (Table V; Figs.l, 2), further relationships are not evi-    17000I  16000t  8OOO"     7000   6ood  o   50O0  u 4000  '~ 3000  E  E  200C    1OO0    Alluvial sediments of sandstone  O Alluvial sediments of sandstone and shale  X Alluvial sediments of slate  Q AUuvial sediments of mudstone  [] Diluvial deposits of the quaternQry period  Volcanic ASH    X  X    X  Q    Q  X  0    Q  X  []     % o    D   QO    Orgor~c rnc~, %    Fig. 2. The relationship between the amounts of organic matter and ammonium oxalate-  extractable Fe, the regression equation for Fe versus organic matter is y = 2,254.3 +  498,3x, where x represents contents of organic matter and y those of Fe.    261    dent. This indicates that the ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe are  associated with organic matter but not with acidity and clay of the soils.  Moreover, this also indicates that the clay fractions may not be the predom-  inant reserves of non-crystalline products of relatively recent weathering.  To extend the data obtained by the statistical treatment of the relation-  ships between contents of ammonium oxalate-extractable A1 and Fe and the  clay fraction, the distribution of the extractable A1 and Fe in the various  size fractions of the selected soils was examined (Table VI). Both extractable    TABLE VI  Distribution of the A1 and Fe extracted by the ammonium oxalate method in various  size fractions of the selected soils    Size fraction     A1                        Fe  (~m)    ppm    % distrib,        ppm       % distrib.    Suechia  &lt;2             2,631   70.1              22,100     65.3  2--5               469     5.6               4,734      6.2  5--20              198     7.6               2,393     10.3  20--50              156   12.5               1,438     12.8  &gt;50               89    4.2               1,047       5.5    Neipu  &lt;2                          1,109       47.5                             11,943           61.9  2--5               198   16.3               1,531     15.3  5--20              109   17.1                 656     12.4  20--50              104   17.0                 369      7.3  &gt;50                              63          2.1                                   813             3.2    Taikang I  &lt;2            1,500   78.0             11,031     88.9  2--5               854   18.7               2,031      6.9  5--20               52     1.5                 766      3.4  20--50              195     1.8                 266      0.4  &gt;50           115    0.1            2,424     0.4    Tatushan H  &lt;2             1,118   62.9               5,609     81.2  2--5               521     7.0                 978      3.4  5--20               47     1.6                 297      2.7  20--50             320   23.1                 244      4.5  &gt;50            44    5.5              250     8.2    Minhsiung I  &lt;2          2,265  75.8           12,344    83.0  2--5               250    4.0               1,859      6.0  5--20               83    4.1                  531       5.2  20--50              297   13.6                 500      4.6  &gt;50            78    2.6              188     1.2    262    A1 and Fe are present in a series of particle size fractions. The amounts of  extractable A1 in the &gt; 2 pm fractions of the selected soil samples range  from 22.0 to 52.5% and those of the extractable Fe from 11.1 to 38.1%  (Table VI), showing that the non-crystalline sesquioxidic components due  to relatively recent weathering are not only present in the clay fractions  but also in the non-clay fractions in very significant amounts. This finding  significantly extends the studies on the non-crystalline clay constituents of  soils as summarized by Wada and Harward (1974). Because the recently  weathered products of a non-crystalline nature are very active in soil processes  (Mitchell et al., 1964; Rich, 1968; Wada and Harward, 1974), it is sug-  gested that more attention be paid to the nature and properties of non-  crystalline inorganic components of a series of size fractions of soils both  from the viewpoint of pedogenesis and that of soil physicochemical reac-  tions pertaining to soil fertility and environmental protection.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The first author was a Visiting Professor to the Department of Soil Science,  National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan. This study was sup-  ported by the National Science Council (Taiwan) Grant 64B-0409-04(07).  Contribution No. R194, Saskatchewan Institute of Pedology.    REFERENCES    Chang, J.M., 1969. Profile and clay mineral studies of Brown Forest soils in Taiwan.  Soils Fertilizers (Taiwan), p. 64.  Day, P.R., 1965. Particle fractionation and particle-size analysis. In: C.A. Black (Editor-  in-chief), Methods of Soil Analysis, Part I. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wisc., pp. 545-567.  Dudas, M.J. and Harward, M.E., 1971. Effect of dissolution treatments on standard and  soil clays. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 134--140.  Genrich, D.A. and Bremner, J.M., 1972. A revaluation of the ultrasonic vibration method  of dispersing soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 944--947.  Hsu, P.H., 1963. Effect of initial pH, phosphate, and silicate on the determination of  aluminum with aluminon. Soil Sci., 96: 230--238.  Hsu, P.H. and Ragone, S.E., 1972. Aging of hydrolyzed iron (III) solutions. J. Soil Sci.,  23: 17--31.  Huang, P.M., 1975. Retention of arsenic by hydroxy-aluminum on surfaces of micaceous  mineral colloids. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 271--274.  Huang, P.M. and Lee, S.Y., 1969. Effect of drainage on weathering transformations of  mineral colloids of some Canadian Prairie soils. Proc. Int. Clay Conf., 1: 541--551.  Huang, P.M. and Kozak, L.M., 1970. Adsorption of hydroxy-aluminum polymers by  muscovite and biotite. Nature, 228: 1084--1085.  Jackson, M.L., 1956. Soil Chemical Analysis -- Advanced Course. Published by the  author, Univ. of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisc.  Jackson, M.L., 1958. Soil Chemical Analysis. Prentice-Hall, Engtewood Cliffs, N.J., 498 pp.  Jackson, M.L., 1964. Chemical composition of soils. In: F.E. Bear (Editor), Chemistry  of the Soil. Reinhold, New York, N.Y., pp. 71--141.  Jackson, M.L., 1965. Clay transformations in soil genesis during the Quaternary. Soil  Sci., 99: 15-22.    263    Juang, T.C., 1967. Clay mineralogical studies of Taiwan sugarcane soils. Soils Fertilizers  (Taiwan), pp. 14--22.  Juo, A.S.R., Chi, C.L. and Wu, M.H., 1971. Clay mineralogical studies of certain rice  soils in southern Taiwan. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 831--834.  Kinniburgh, D.G., Jackson, M.L. and Syers, J.K., 1976. Adsorption of alkaline earth,  transition, and heavy metal cations by hydrous oxide gels of iron and aluminum. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 796--799.  Leung, K.W. and Chen, T.T., 1966. Soils of Taiwan. J. Agric. Assoc. China, 20: 1--25.  Leung, K.W. and Lai, C.Y., 1969. Soil development study of red-yellow podzolic soils  in Taiwan. 3. Study of the clay minerals of yellowish brown latosols in the northern  part of Taiwan. Soils Fertilizers (Taiwan), p. 61.  Luciuk, G.M. and Huang, P.M., 1974. Effect of monosilicic acid on hydrolytic reactions  of aluminum. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 235--244.  Lundblad, L., 1934. Studies on podzols and brown forest soils. Soil Sci., 37:137--155.  Mitchell, B.D., Farmer, V.C.and McHardy, W.J., 1964. Amorphous inorganic materials  in soils. Adv. Agron., 16: 327--383.  Rankama, K. and Sahama, Th.G., 1950. Geochemistry, 5th printing. The University of  Chicago Press, Chicago, Ill.  Rich, C.I., 1968. Applications of soil mineralogy in soil chemistry and fertility investi-  gations. In: G.W. Kunze, J.L. White and R.H. Rust (Editor), Mineralogy in Soil  Science and Engineering. SSSA Spec. Publ. Set. No.3. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Inc., Madison,  Wisc., pp. 61--90.  Schwertmann, W., 1964. The differentiation of iron oxide in soils by a photochemical  extraction with acid ammonium oxalate. Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Dung. Bodenkd., 105:  194--201.  Wada, K. and Harward, M.E., 1974. Amorphous clay constituents of soils. Adv. Agron., 27:  211--260.  Weaver, R.M., Syers, J.K. and Jackson, M.L., 1968. Determination of silica in citrate-  bicarbonate-dithionite extracts of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 497--501.  Yang, T.C. and Chi, C.L., 1973. Evaluations of the profile development of a Taiwan clay  soil. Bull. Assoc. Soil Sci. Nat. Chung-Hsing Univ., 1: 17--22.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                AbstractTwenty two surface soils, representing six parent materials and four soil groups, were sampled in Taiwan for the present study.Except in the soil derived from volcanic ash, the sesquioxidic components and relatively easily extractable Si were present only in small amounts in the NaOAc and H2O2- NaOAc extractable fractions. In addition to Fe, both Si and Al were present in the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate extracts in considerable amounts, indicating that Si and Al were either present separately or in association with Fe in the sesquioxidic fractions of the soils. The amounts of Si, Al and Fe extracted by the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate and boiling KOH treatments differed from sample to sample, indicating that they are important variables in the nature of the soils studied.The amounts of the ammonium oxalate-extractable Al and Fe, representing the noncrystalline sesquioxidic products of relatively recent weathering, also differed with parent materials and pedogenic processes. The statistical data indicate that the ammonium oxalate-extractable Al and Fe are related to the contents of organic matter but not to acidity and the contents of clay. The percentage distribution of the extractable Al in the &gt; 2 μm fractions of the selected soil samples ranged from 22.0 to 52.5% and that of the extractable Fe from 11.1 to 38.1%, indicating that the active non-crystalline Al and Fe components in the non-clay fractions deserve close attention in the study of pedogenesis and other soil physicochemical reactions in relation to soil fertility and environmental protection.