377    CONTENTS VOL. 35, 1985    Strengths of a densipan, humus-pan and clay-pan in a Spodosol developed under  kauri (Agathis australia) and the implications for soil classification  N. Wells and R.D. Northey (Lower Hutt, New Zealand)  ..................  1  Description of soil thin sections: an international comparison  C.P. Murphy (Harpenden, Great Britain), J.A. McKeague (Ottawa, Ont.,  Canada), L.M. Bresson (Thivernal-Grignon, France), P. Bullock (Harpenden,  Great Britain), M.J. Kooistra, R. Miedema (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  and G. Stoops (Ghent, Belgium)  ..................................  15  Faster methods of liquid-phase acetone replacement of water from soils and  sediments prior to resin impregnation  C.P. Murphy (Harpenden, Great Britain)  ............................  39  Shrinkage and Atterberg limits in relation to other properties of principal soil types  in Israel  C.W. Smith, A. Hadas, J. Dan and H. Koyumdjisky (Bet Dagan, Israel)  ........  47  In Memoriam Felix E. Richard  .....................................  67  Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  69  Shapes of aggregates from tilt layers of some Dutch and Australian soils  A.R. Dexter (Glen Osmond, S.A., Australia)  ..........................  91  An assessment of EDTA as an extractant of organic-complexed and amorphous  forms of Fe and AI in soils  J.A. McKeaque and P.A. Schuppli (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  .................  109  The phenolic acid content of cashew leaves (Anacardium occidentale) and of the  associated humus layer, Senegal  I. KSgel and W. Zech (Bayreuth, Bundesrepublik Deutschland)  .............  119  Distribution of elements in some Fe--Mn nodules and an iron-pan in some gley  soils of New Zealand  B.S.W. Dawson, J.E. Fergusson (Christchurch, New Zealand), A.S. Campbell  and E.J.B. Cutler (Lincoln, New Zealand)  ...........................  127  Effects of air-drying on the adsorption and desorption of phosphate and levels  of extractable phosphate in a group of acid soils, New Zealand  R.J. Haynes and R.E. Swift (Canterbury, New Zealand)  ..................  145  Short Communication  A scanning electron microscopy study of the interaction between sludge organic  components and clay particles  L. Metzger (Bet Dagan, Israel) and M. Robert (Versailles, France)  ............  159  Book Review  Productivity of Sahelian Rangelands: A Study of the Soils, the Vegetations and  the Exploitation of that Natural Resource, by N. de Ridder et al. -- A.  Singer  ...................................................  169    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  171  Using simulation to define moisture availability and trafficability for a heavy  clay soil in The Netherlands  J.H.M. WSsten and J. Bourns (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  ...............  187  Potassium release on drying of soil samples from a variety of weathering regimes  and clay mineralogy in China  Jia Xian Luo (Nanjing, P.R.C.) and Marion L. Jackson (Madison, Wisc.,  U.S.A.)  ..................................................  197  Bonding and oxidation state of iron in humic complexes extracted from some  Greek soils  Ch.S. Kallianou and N.J. Yassoglou (Athens, Greece)  ....................  209    378    The ages and soils of two levels of "rafia" surfaces in central Spain  R. Espejo Serrano (Madrid, Spain)  ................................  223  Effects of bituminous emulsions on retention and release of some chemical  elements in two soil samples  N. Salem, M. Verloo and M. de Boodt (Ghent, Belgium)  ..................  241  Mercury contents of some Greek soils  C. Haidouti (Athens, Greece), V. Skarlou (Attikis, Greece) and F. Tsouloucha  (Larissa, Greece)  ............................................  251  Discussion  Estimating relative ages from iron-oxide/total-iron ratios of soils in the western Po  Valley, Italy -- a discussion  E.B. Alexander (San Francisco, Calif., U.S.A.)  ........................  257  Estimating relative ages from iron~xide/total-iron ratios of soils in the western Po  Valley, Italy--a reply  E. Arduino (Torino, Italy)  ......................................  259  Book Reviews  Evaluation of Fertility by Plant and Soil Analysis, by D. and V. Davidescu -- A.  van Diest  .................................................  261  Desert Vegetation of Israel and Sinai, by A. Danin -- N.E. West  ...............  261  Soil Analysis, Instrumental Techniques and Related Procedures, by K.A. Smith  (Editor') -- G.S.P. Ritchie  ......................................  262  Applied Geomorphology -- Geomorphological Surveys for Environmental  Developments, by H.Th. Verstappen --M.G. Anderson  ...................  263    Erratum  ....................................................  265  Announcement  ...............................................  267  Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  269  Micromorphology of recent and buried soils in a semi-arid region of northwestern  India  M.-A. Courty (Talence, France) and N. F4doroff (Grignon, France)  ..........  287  Differences in silica release from softs of two Scottish associations as assessed by  trimethylsilylation  B.F.L. Smith and B.D. Mitchell (Aberdeen, Great Britain)  .................  333  A comparison of four different humus types in Norway using chemical degrada-  tions and CPMAS ~3C NMR spectroscopy  G. Ogner (As, Norway)  .........................................  343  Book Reviews  Pedogenesis and Soil Taxonomy, I. Concept and Interactions, by L.P. Wilding,  N.E. Smeck and G.F. Hall (Editors) -- D.E. Pettry  ......................  355  Pedogenesis and Soil Taxonomy, II. The Soil Orders, by L.P. Wilding, N.E.  Smeck and G.F. Hall (Editors) -- D.E. Pettry  .........................  356  Gaseous Loss of Nitrogen from Plant--Soil Systems, by J.R. Freney and J.R.  Simpson (Editors) -- V. Van~ura  .................................  356    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  359                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            