Geoderma, 32 (1984) 157--158                                                     157  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reoew    Advanced Techniques for Clay Mineral Analysis. J.J. Fripiat (Editor).  Developments in Sedimentology, 34, Invited papers presented at the  Symposium held during the 7th International Clay Conference, 1981,  Bologna and Pavia. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 1981, 234 pp., U.S. $42.50,  Dfl. 100.00.    The editor of this timely volume, a research worker of international  standing in spectroscopic studies of clay minerals and their surfaces, is well  placed to know the requirements of researchers in the many fields that  utilize specialist physical techniques. He has brought together the expertise  of nine {including himself) specialists, in a very readable volume that has  mostly achieved his goal of imparting information about the problems  to which the techniques may be addressed, the experimental results achieved  and their physical meaning. Some chapters do contain too much theory  however.  Seven of the nine chapters involve spectroscopic techniques that here-  to-fore may have been considered esoteric by clay scientists, but the reader  will rapidly discover the inherent value of these methods in clay mineral  studies.  By contrast, the opening two chapters concern more conventional meth-  ods. In the first of these, R.C. MacKenzie has produced an impressive sur-  vey of the many thermal methods currently available, but more impor-  tantly he has given much sound advice on their applicability to studies  not only of bulk clay minerals but also of their surfaces.  In Chapter 2, J.P. Eberhart, although dwelling somewhat longer on  theory than the editor might have wished, has nevertheless provided a  few good illustrations of how far electron microscopy has advanced, par-  ticularly with the advent of computerized methods of image enhancement.  However, he gives fewer explanations of text and figures than the aver-  age reader requires for comprehension, particularly when the references  cited are private communications.  The group of chapters on spectroscopic methods is opened by P.L. Hall  in Chapter 3 on neutron scattering techniques. In an intrinsically diffi-  cult topic to handle, the author devotes too much space to theory and  too little to describing in a simpler straight-forward way, the kind of re-  sults obtainable and what they mean. Nevertheless, the ability of the four  types of neutron scattering experiment to yield information on such di-  verse topics ranging from pore sizes and lattice defects to vibrational mo-  tion of adsorbed molecules shows the potential which the method has  for many branches of clay mineral research.  The next three chapters -- NMR by W.E.E. Stone, MSssbauer by B.A.  Goodman, and ESR by T.J. Pinnavaia -- strike an ideal balance between    158    theory and applications, and provide the book with a nucleus of the more  recent and readily available techniques for the clay scientist. In their dif-  ferent ways they provide related information about the environment.s  of a range of nuclei in various locations in clay minerals. All three can  be used to study site occupancy, while MSssbauer can also readily distin-  guish and quantify the valence states of iron. By studying the protons  in water molecules in hydration shells around an exchange cation, NMP  has the ability to determine the orientation of these cations at the mineral  surface. ESR also provides information in this area by examining ti~e orien-  tation of the principal axis of a probe molecule that contains a paramag-  netic nucleus. From the many examples of their applications, these meth-  ods are proving particularly useful in clay research, but most importantly  the authors do not conceal the limitations of the techniques.  The next two chapters on uv visible----near infrared spectroscopy and  far infrared spectroscopy are the first of their type to be published in rela-  tion to clay mineral research. In Chapter 7, R.A. Schoonheydt gives a  well balanced account of how diffuse reflectance methods compare with  photoacoustic  spectroscopy  m  providing measurements of the  surface  acidity of clay minerals using organic molecules as probes. The mobility  of adsorbed species can also be assessed, and this is part of the theme of  Chapter 8, by J.J. Fripiat. tte shows how the low frequency vibrations  of exchange cations in smectites and zeolites can provide a wealth of in-  formation on the nature of the adsorption sites and the stability of the  cations on them. The final chapter on E.S.C.A. by P. Canesson contains  a good balance of what this method of surface analysis can do and what  it cannot. It can provide quantitative compositional analyses of the sur-  face layer of minerals, and because of this high selectivity for the surface,  the method provides an ideal means of studying adsorption phenomena  by observing changes in binding energies. It is not a method for analysing  trace amounts of surface components and it cannot distinguish between  different coordination states of the same element. Nevertheless it is proving  to be a very powerful method for studying adsorption of both organic  and inorganic species.  The chapters are all well written and contain few errors, but the book  suffers from the wide range of type faces and spacings used by the indi-  vidual authors, tt is however such a comprehensive collection of physi-  cal methods of analysis and is so reasonably priced that it will be widely  acquired and appreciated.    J.D. RUSSELL  (Aberdeen)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           