131    courses as estimated by interception and consumptive use models are com-  pared. Readers will undoubtedly be impressed by the magnitudes of differ-  ences among model estimates, and may feel compelled to question some of  the rather optimistic workshGp conclusions. Differences in model estimates  of seasonal evapotranspiration {highest estimates more than twice as great as  the lowest) are most remarkable; models that agreed more closely with  "measured" values {actually Bowen ratio estimates) are implicitly given a  superior rating.  An "unsuspected and remarkable discrepancy" was found between energy  and water balance estimates of evapotranspiration; accumulated totals, from  27 May to 2 September, were 350 mm {energy balance} and 150 mm (water  balance). The energy balance estimate was obtained using the Bowen ratio  method and interpolations by an energy exchange model; the water balance  estimate was derived from measurements of.precipitation and soil moisture,  and indirect estimates of percolation by a soil water model ("no direct  measurements ef percolation were made"). The discrepancy is "explained"  by questioning the equality of tral~sfer coefficients for heat and water vapor  (as assumed in the Bowen ratio method), which is interpreted to mean that  "the discrepancy thus found indicated that, for forests, fundamentals in  micrometeorological theory must be revised."  The magnitude of the reported discrepancy between water and energy  balance estimates of evapotranspiration is indeed "remarkable", but it will  undoubtedly elicit explanations that do not challenge micrometeorological  theory. For example, regional studies show that, for similar latitudes and  climate in Sweden, annual evapotranspiration is of the order of 325 ram,  most of which would occur during the May--September period (see  Budyko's Climate and Life, 1974, or T~le World Water Balance by Baum-  gartner and Reichel, 1975). Micromc~eorologists and hydrologists alike  may therefore think to question the J~dra~ts water balance estimate (150  mm), and to suggest that perhaps the unmeasured subsurface flows that  may move horizontally as well as vertically {both up and down) could  explain much of the apparent; discrepancy.    RICHARD LEE  (Morganto~n, Va.)    Pattern and Process in a Forested Ecosystem. F.H. Bormann and G.E. Likens.  Springer-Verlag, New York, Heidleberg, Berlin, 1979, xi 253 pp., DM 42.00,  US $ 23,10.    "What goes up must come down" helps explain the northern hardwood  forest ecosystem described in this book. Pattern and Process is a presenta-  tion of the structure, functions and development of a forest in the context  of a "Shifting-Mosaic Steady State" conceptual model of ecosystem devel-    132    opment. This is the second volume resulting fxum fifteen years of work by  the authors and their numerous colleagues at the Hubbard Brook Experi-  mental Forest in New Hampshire, U.S.A. The first volume, Biogeochemistry  of a Forested Ecosystem (Springer-Verlag, 1977), presented details of the  status and flows of w~.ter and nutrient elements in a northern hardwood  forest watershed-ecosystem where studies were begun in 1963.  The eight chapters of thi:~ book contain a well-balanced mixture of research  observations, ecosystem theory, pertinent history of the study region, new  ideas, and practical suggestions for forest harvest and landscape management.  The material is logically presented, beginning with explanation of a model  of forest dynamics based on the detailed case history information compiled.  This conceptual model is comprised of four phases of northern hardwood  forest development following a severe disturbance, such as clearcutting or  windthr~J+: of a ~ignificant ruea of the forest: (1) reorganization; (2) aggra-  dation, or rapid regrowth; (3) transition to a different vegetation and biomass  composition; anti, finally (4) a shifting-mosaic steady state.  The authors make it clear that the model, as developed, applies only to  the northern hardwood forests which have been the basis of their studies.  However, they validly assert that some of the general relationships among  living and dead biomass, forest floor, mineral soil, hydrology and nutrient  element dynamics which are documented in their studies provide useful  working hypotheses for considering other forest ecosystems. The objectives  to provide generalizable ideas and to write '"for the reader interested in the  ecology of ecosystems rather than for the ecosystem specialist" make this  book especially interesting to those concerned with broad ecosystem con-  cepts and their relationships to specific soil processes.  Of particular interest to soil ecologists is the presentation of vegetation  dynamics as they relate to biogeochemical processes, which were documen-  ted in detail in the previous volume (op. cir. ). Detailed discussions of eco-  system processes caused by forest cutting, which influence movement of  nitrate ions and cations through the system, provide useful insight into the  complex relationships among forest trees, organic horizons and mineral soil.  For example, the "critical element ratio shunt" is a concept developed to  explain changes in concentrations of dissolved nutrients in stream water as  functions of C/N and element/phosphorus ratios. These ratios change as  microbial activities in the forest floor respond to vegetation changes. Rela-  tionships between vegetation, forest floor and erosion dynamics are ex-  plored in a useful system~ context. Graphs, photographs, tables, and schemat-  ic illustrations are well-used to provide clarification of text and integrative  summaries of the complex relationships discussed.  From the viewpoint of overall contributions to ecology, the "shifting-  mosaic steady state" concept is perhaps most important. This concept is that  the mature northern hardwood forest is a mosaic of pa~ches of vegetation  in various phases of development: reorganization; aggradation; transition;  steady state. This patchiness, rather than a continous forest of a single com-    133    position, is a much more realistic, functional description of the characteris-  tics of this, and probably many other, forest ecosystems. Tke implications  of this concept for forestry, watershed management and other aspects of  land management are quite different from those of a continuous, "climax"  ecosystem. In a watershed context, this concept enables understanding of  ecosystem processes, e.g., flows of energy, nutrients and water, resulting  from a mosaic of vegetation patches in various developmental stages.  Two mild limitations of this volume deserve comment, from my view-  point. The authors, as do many of us dealing with ecology and other science,  on sevelal occasions succumb to the recurring malaise of anthropomorphism;  e.g., "...structures or strategies are developed to resist or cope with these  destabilizing forces," (p. 6). I think that ecologists "cope" and that eco-  systems "respond"!  The second liraitation is of more scientific significance. This is the repeated  assertion, usually tacitly stated, that any loss of nitrogen, or any element,  from the system that is caused by ecosystem disturbance degrades the po-  tential productivity of the system. This idea is most strongly developed in  relation to loss of nitrogen from decomposing forest floors following clear-  cut forest harvesting. The assertion, most pointedly stated on p. 224 in the  final chapter, "Forest Harvest and Landscape Management", is that a forest  ecosystem must restore harvest-caused losses of nutrients to pre-harvest  levels in order to regain its optimum potential productivity. The argument  further maintains that unless precutting nutrient levels are regained, a general  deterioration of the system could occur with successive harvests. This idea  is a useful, testable, conservative hypothesis, but is not a fact documented  by this study. An alternate, equally viable, hypothesis is that a northern  hardwood forest ecosystem contains more nitrogen {or other element) than  is needed for optimum productivity, and that some loss of an element fo!-  lowing harvest will not, in fact, degrade future productive potential. I think  that the latter hypothesis is equally worthy of presentation to scientific,  land management, and environmental communities in order to preclude  over-reaction to potential dangers of forest harvesting. Certainly, both  hypotheses should be tested before land management schemes place us on  irreversible paths of ecosystem deterioration.  Professors Bormann and Likens have provided a critically-considered and  well-written synthesis of integrated, multi-disciplinary research on a timely  topic. The book will provide stimulating reading for all scientists dealing  with issues of forest land management.    JAMES R. BOYLE  (Wilsonville, Ore.)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          