Geoderma, 28 (1982) 57--61  57  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Short Communication  PODZOLIZATION OF SOILS UNDER INDIVIDUAL TREE CANOPIES  IN SOUTHWESTERN BRITISH COLUMBIA, CANADA    C.B. CRAMPTON  Department of Geography, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, British Columbia, V5A  1S6 (Canada)  (Received May 22, 1981; accepted February 17, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Crampton, C.B., 1982. Podzolization of soils under individual tree canopies in south-  western British Columbia, Canada. Geoderma, 28: 57--61.    On Burnaby Mountain in the coastal rainforest of British Columbia there are con-  centric, circular belts of podzolized soils around the stems of douglas fir and western hem-  lock trees. The most acid soils occur near each stem, and soils showing the greatest con-  trast in chroma between the eluvial and illuvial horizons occur beneath the periphery of  the canopy of each tree. These circular belts of soils appear to be associated with limited  flow of a very acid water from precipitation down a stem and much greater flow of less  acid water from the periphery of the canopy.    INTRODUCTION    Soil surveys have been undertaken at selected localities in southwest  British Columbia. On sandy ridge sites podzolized soils are widespread. Map-  ping these soils is difficult, however, because of an apparent, very localized  distribution. Hence, micro-site studies around individual trees were under-  taken.  Burnaby Mountain is located in the outskirts of Greater Vancoucer in  southwestern British Columbia. It is a cuesta landform created by Eocene  sandstones and conglomerates dipping gently southwards. The cuesta plateau  has a maximum elevation of 365 m, and on the north side it slopes steeply  to sea level in Burrard Inlet. The mean annual precipitation across the plateau  top is about 2000 ram. The coastal rainforest of southwestern British Colum-  bia mantles the mountain. The forest was logged around the turn of the  century but some young conifers survived to become approximately 80-year  old dominants in the present mixed species forest.    METHOD    This study reports soil profile observations below 32 douglas fir (Pseudo-    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    58    tsuga menziessi (Mirb. Franco) and 32 western hemlock (Tsuga heterophylla  (Raf.) Sarg.) trees with stem diameters of 76 cm (DBH) and greater, within  an area of about 3 km2 across the plateau top of the mountain. Below each  tree a line of profile pits had been dug, one pit as close as was practical to  the stem of each tree, a second beneath the mid-canopy position and a third  under the periphery of the tree canopy (henceforward, referred to as the  periphery).  Systematic profile descriptions included measurements of the horizon  thicknesses, the horizon colours recorded in terms of the MunseU notations  and the pH values determined colorimetrically, using bromcresol green and  chlorphenol red indicators. The soils examined under the tree canopies were  podzolized in that they had podzolic Bf or Bhf horizons and leached Ae  horizons, and were classified as Eluviated Dystric Brunisols, Orthic Humo-  Ferric Podzols and Orthic Ferro-Humic Podzols (Canada Soil Survey Com-  mittee, 1978). Approximate equivalents in the legend for the FAO-UNESCO  Soil Map of the World are Leptic Podzols, Ferric Podzols and Humic Podzols,  respectively (FAO, 1974).  Within the area of many of the sites examined as described a douglas fir  or western hemlock tree of smaller diameter from 20 to 40 cm was also  examined in the same way, so that any edaphic changes thought to be wrought  by the more mature trees could be compared with edaphic conditions present  before the trees matured. A similar examination was also conducted around  western red cedar (Thuja plicata Donn.), broadleaf maple (Acer macrophyl-  lum Pursh.) and western balsam poplar (Populus trichocarpa Torr. &amp; Gray.)  trees for comparison.    RESULTS    A reasonably consistent pattern of profile differences, particularly in soil  colours, beneath individual tree canopies, was observed during fieldwork,  mostly because environmental changes from site to site were minimized by  keeping the study area small. Thus, it has been possible to illustrate the  typical profile distribution (Fig. 1), the field variations nowhere obliterating  the basic pattern. The eluvial Ae horizon of the middle profile was very thin  in places. The clarity of horizonation was the same for douglas fir and west-  ern hemlock, with greater contrast between horizons than below western  red cedar, which contrast was more distinct than below broadleaf species  such as broadleaf maple and western balsam poplar.  pH values throughout the profiles were most acid near the stem of a tree  (3.8 in the LFH organic horizon with a standard deviation of 0.06, increas-  ing to 4.6 in the parent material or BC horizon with a standard deviation of  0.10), almost as acid beneath the periphery of a tree canopy (4.0 in the  organic horizon with a standard deviation of 0.07, up to 5.0 in the parent  material with a standard deviation of 0.11), and least acid in the site midway  between a tree stem and the periphery of the canopy (except in the parent    59    THE AVE~(~E OF 192 PROFILES BELOW 64 DOUGLAS FIR AND WESTERN HEMLOCK TREES    TREE STEM    CANOPY EDGE    m~  \    10 CM   ]    PH    COLOUR    3.8                LF  4.0   IOYR 3/2       AI  4.3  7.5YR 4/4  BI  BC  4.6  DRIER PROFILE, DARKENED WITH HUMUS.    PH    COLOUR  4.1    4,3  IOYR 4/2    4.6  7.5YR 5/6    4.8    LF  AE    BF    PH    COLOUR  4.0  4.2  4.5    IOYR 5/2  7,5YR 5/8    5,0  WETTER PROFILE, APPARENTLY CLEAR  OF HUMUS.    Fig. 1. Typical, average soil profiles distributed between a tree stem and the periphery of  the canopy on and around the plateau of Burnaby Mountain. The central profile is inter-  mediate in character and, therefore, in horizon symbolization between the profile nearest  the tree stem and the profile under the periphery of the canopy.  material) (Fig. 1). The typical profile near a tree stern showed the least con-  trast in chroma between the eluvial Ae and iUuvial Bhf horizon (10YR 3/2  or very dark grayish brown and 7.SYR 4/4 or brown to dark brown, respec-  tively) compared with the contrast in chroma between the eluvial and il-  luvial horizons beneath the periphery of the canopy (10YR 5/2 or grayish  brown and 7.SYR 5/8 or strong brown, respectively). Penetration of dark  organic particles and associated stains down into the profile were greatest  near the stern of a tree, considerably modifying the chroma of the iiluvial  horizon, and least near the periphery.  After a rainshower the soil profile situated against a tree stem was normal-  ly the driest of the three sites. Even after a heavy rainstorm only trickles of  water were observed down the bark as stemflow. In contrast, under the  periphery of a tree canopy the stream of precipitation after a heavy shower  could be sufficiently intense to produce a circle of erosion in the litter layer.  The soil profile situated between a stem and the periphery was normally of  intermediate wetness. Evidently, the form of a douglas fir or western hem-  lock tree directs most rain passing through a tree canopy towards the outer  part, to produce a concentration of precipitation below the periphery.  This soft distribution pattern was progressively less well expressed below  trees with progressively smaller stem diameters, and so results from these  smaller trees have not been included.    60    INTERPRETATION    Abrahamsen et al. (1977) reported that rainfall penetrating a tree canopy  became more acid, mainly due to the washing of absorbed deposits and the  leaching of excreted metabolites, the acidity of stemflow being about twice  that prevailing half-way between the stem and the outer perimeter of the  canopy. The quantity of stemflow differed with the form of a tree, being  greatest for a broadleaf species such as birch, less for a pine and least for a  spruce tree with its very different branching system. Hutchinson and Roberts  (1981) found that the stemflow down a douglas fir tree to the ground was  only 2% of the total precipitation. Gersper and Holowaychuk (1970) found  moderately acid soil horizons resulting from stemflow down broadleaf trees,  the pH in the subsoil increasing away from the stem of a tree to a distance of  300 cm (about the distance sampled away from each tree on Burnaby Moun-  tain). Mahendrappa (1974) found the stemflow from rainfall down certain  conifers very acid. Gibbs (1980) has commented on the sandy "egg cup"  Podzol profiles commonly found around the stems of mature Kauri trees  growing in New Zealand, the characteristic leached horizon of the Podzol in-  creasing in thickness towards the stems. Crampton (1980) found on Belcarra  Mountain adjoining Burnaby Mountain that in sandy soils long dry periods  promoted increased acidity throughout the profiles of Podzols, extending  down into the parent material, compared with softs saturated with water ac-  cumulated over several consecutive seasons.  If these observations are applied to softs on Burnaby Mountain, they sug-  gest the hypothesis that rainfall passing through a tree canopy is acidified and  can then be associated with podzolization in the soils below. This water is  concentrated as stemflow mostly below the canopies of broadleaf species,  but the flow is most acid down the stems of conifers. Acidification through-  out sandy profiles increases as the soils become drier.  To continue the hypothesis, the canopy catchment of a douglas fir or  western hemlock tree acidifies and concentrates the rainwash into a peri_pheral  curtain of water which flows through the underlying soft, where it appears to  be associated with the maximum colour differentiation between the eluvial  and illuvial horizons in Podzols. Compared with the peripheral flow, the  volume of stemflow is much smaller but acidification is much more intense.  The relatively drier soil conditions near a tree stem combined with the more  acid nature of the little water that does percolate through the soil appears to  be associated with an observed greater penetration of organic particles and  associated stains through more acid profiles, which partially mask the normal-  ly strong colour of the illuvial horizon. The less well developed concentric  edaphic zoning around less mature trees suggests that the zoning is produced  by the growth of the trees, especially of conifers inasmuch as the zoning is  less well developed around broadleaf species of all ages.    61    CONCLUSIONS    During soil mapping in the area of Burnaby Mountain the most difficult  boundary to map has been that between different kinds of podzolized soils  because of their apparent very local distribution. It seems that this localiza-  tion of distribution has been partly caused by the differentiation of water  flow and acidity through the canopies of different trees, producing differing  concentric, circular zones around tree stems. This distributional pattern dif-  fers with the size of the tree and so can be expected to change with time.    REFERENCES    Abrahamsen, G., Horntvedt, R. and Tveite, B., 1977. Impacts of acid precipitation of  coniferous forest ecosystems. Water, Air Soil Pollut., 8: 57--73.  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classification. Canada  Department of Agriculture, Publ. 1646, 164 pp.  Crampton, C.B., 1980. Variations of pH with annual cumulative precipitation in acid  forest soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 60: 385--387.  FAO, 1974. FAO--UNESCO Soil Map of the World, Vol. 1, Legend. UNESCO, Paris,  59 pp.  Gersper, P.L. and Holowaychuk, N., 1970. Some effects of stemflow from forest canopy  trees on chemical properties of soils. Ecology, 52: 691--701.  Gibbs, H.S., 1980. New Zealand Soils. Oxford University Press, Wellington, 386 pp.  Hutchinson, I. and Roberts, C.R., 1981. Vertical variation in stemflow generation. J. Appl.  Ecol., 18: 521--527.  Mahendrappa, M.K., 1974. Chemical composition of stemflow from some eastern Canadian  tree species. Can. J. For. Res., 4: 1--7.                       AbstractOn Burnaby Mountain in the coastal rainforest of British Columbia there are concentric, circular belts of podzolised soils around the stems of douglas fir and western hemlock trees. The most acid soils occur near each stem, and soils showing the greatest contrast in chroma between the eluvial and illuvial horizons occur beneath the periphery of the canopy of each tree. These circular belts of soils appear to be associated with limited flow of a very acid water from precipitation down a stem and much greater flow of less acid water from the periphery of the canopy.