317    currently unanswerable questions are raised about topics such as roots,  plant-associated microbes, and community responses to CO2.  Scientists were free to work in various topical discussion groups. Each  group presents a brief summary of the current status of our knowledge  plus a set of recommendations for necessary research. There seems to be  agreement that plants will benefit from rising CO2 levels since CO2 is the  major substrate for constructing a plant. Indeed plants may grow more  effectively at elevated CO2 levels but use reasonably close to current levels  of other nutrients such as H:O or nitrogen. However, these holistic answers  are not truly known because few long-term plant studies on growth, al-  location, partitioning, or reproduction have been conducted at elevated  CO: levels. No studies are available covering several life cycles of a plant  nor are any short- or long-term community studies available.  CO: and Plants is a concise set of statements outlining our current level  of understanding of the responses plants, plus associated microbes, to  CO2 as they live, grow, and reproduce in this biosphere. In addition the  uncertainties about plants and rising CO2 levels are listed along with potenti-  ally fruitful research topics which should help us to predict future responses  to CO2 of the largest CO2 metabolism factory of the world, namely plants.    CLANTON C. BLACK, JR.  {Athens, GA)    Elements of Soil Physics. P. Koorevaar, G. Menelik and C. Dirksen. Develop-  ments in Soil Science, 13, Elsevier, Amsterdam--Oxford--New York--  Tokyo, 1983, XIV + 228 pp., US $ 32.00 (U.S. and Canada), Dfl. 75.00  (hardcover).    This book, presenting a rigorous, complete and consistent treatment of  concepts, definitions and relationships of physical processes occuring in  soil, is meant to be not only a first introduction in soil physics but also  an auxiliary source for an advanced study. It represents a very valuable  textbook with a particular attention paid to problems studied at agricultural  universities.  The origin of the book goes back to lectures held at the Department of  Soil Science and Plant Nutrition of the Agricultural University, Wageningen,  The Netherlands. Further, some material has been added for use in M.Sc.-  courses on Soil Science and Water Management at the Agricultural University  for students from developing countries.  The need to improve the examination of students and to make this book  particularly suitable for self-study and rapid reference has led the authors  to the introduction of a total of 235 questions and detailed answers. The  book contains seven proper chapters, an epilogue, written by G.H. Bolt,  and three apendices.    318    The first chapter contains a general description of the composition of  soils, of the specific area of soil particles, of the interaction between solid  and liquid phases as well as of that between solid phase particles.  In the second chapter, the authors introduce the concepts of forces,  equilibrium in force fields and potentials in static equilibrium which are  then used to describe hydrostatic equilibrium in the gravitational field and  define the components of the hydraulic potential in three equivalent forms,  namely the potential on mass basis, that on volume basis as well as that on  weight basis.  The third chapter deals with static equilibria in soils. The authors discuss  the static equilibrium of soil water and soil systems. An elementary descrip-  tion of the binding of water in a capillary is used to explain the capillary  binding of water in soils. Then the relations between the height of capillary  rise, the surface tension, the radius of curvature of the meniscus in a capil-  lary, the radius of a capillary and the contact angle are derived. The sig-  nificance of the hydraulic potential of soil water at static equilibrium is  discussed in detail and the full-capillary zone above the ground-water table  is defined where the pressure potential is higher than the air-entry value of  the largest capillaries. The authors explain working principles of piezometers  and tensiometers with vacuum gauge and with mercury manometer. Then  the measuring range of tensiometers is discussed and the influence of non-  atmospheric pressure of the soil gas phase on tensiometer readings illustrated.  For solving problems of water flow in unsaturated soils, the tensiometer  pressure potential is suitably divided into two components, namely the  matrix potential, resulting exclusively from the soil matrix, and the pneu-  matic potential, due to the soil gas pressure in excess to atmospheric pres-  sure. The water retentivity curve or function is defined and the water re-  tentivity function of a coarse sandy soil with grains of more or less equal  size is presented.  Also is shown the hysteresis manifested by the difference between the  characteristic produced by progressive extraction of soil water from sat-  uration (desorption) and that obtained by gradual addition of water to  air-dry soil (absorption). The authors explain the schemes of the apparatus  for determination of soil water characteristics at high matrix heads and  pressure membrane apparatus for measuring desorption characeristics at  low matrix heads.  Osmotic binding of water and the various components of the soil water,  the various components of the soil water potential in the double layer and  in the vapour phase are also described and the static equilibrium of the  soil system in connection with the soil pressure and intergranular pressure  is discussed.  Based on the results developed in the first three chapters, the authors  present in the fourth chapter the general concepts of transport processes  in soils showing the basic similarities between transport of water, gas and  heat. In this chapter, presenting mathematical formulations of transport    319    processes, the continuity equation and other partial differential equations  for the flux density, flow, gas diffusion and heat conduction are derived and  the corresponding initial and boundary conditions discussed.  The fifth chapter deals in detail with the flow of water in soil. The authors  describe first the phenomena connected with the flow of water in saturated  soils such as saturated hydraulic conductivity, intrinsic permeability, steady  downward flow in the homogeneous soil and layered soil, steady upward  flow and intergranular pressure.  Further, the basic features of the flow of water in the unsaturated soil  are described concerning the unsaturated hydraulic conductivity, steady  upward and downward flow of water in the unsaturated soil, as well as the  horizontal and vertical infiltration.  The sixth chapter treats the conditions of the gas transport in soil, namely  the amount and composition of the soil air, equilibrium conditions for the  soil air, gas diffusion, etc.  In the seventh chapter, dealing with the heat transport in soil, the authors  describe first the termal soil properties such as the volumic heat capacity  and heat conductivity and then discuss the features of the steady heat  conduction in the dry soil as well as the effects of the cyclic variation  and stepwise increase of surface temperature. Finally, they deal with the  heat balance of the soil surface, thermal regime of upper soil layers and  combined heat and water vapour transport such as the isothermal and non-  isothermal water vapour diffusion, evaporation and evapotranspiration.  The epilogue, written by G.H. Bolt, completes suitably the presented  results and statements and appraises the additional understanding needed  for analysing and managing the functions of soil in the real world. The  basic problems of ecology are briefly discussed and a simplistic sketch is  presented, indicating the intimate connections between crop productivity  and physical soil properties, within constraints of climatic conditions and  human activity. The author also discusses the importance of computers for  the possibilities for predictive applications of soil physics.  The three appendices contain mathematical formulations of the laminar  flow of liquids in a cylindrical tube and of Poisseuille's law, the Boltzmann  transformation of the equation for horizontal infiltration and the detailed  derivation of the equation for the infiltration process based on the Green  and Ampt model.  This book represents an extremely valuable manual for students and  professionals in the fields of soil science, agricultural engineering, micro-  meteorology,  hydrology,  civil  engineering,  ecology and environmental  science. It is characterized by a very clear, intelligible and well-arranged  presentation and exact formulation of all fundamental problems of soil  physics.    A. MYSLIVEC  (Prague)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     