294    Geochemistry of Colloid Systems for Earth Scientists. S. Yariv and H. Cross.  Springer Verlag, Berlin, 1979, 450 pp., US $ 60.-, DM. 110.00.    In their preface to the book the authors state "... It would be useful at  this stage to attempt to summarize the progress made and to try to examine  what col.loid science has contributed and could further contribute to geo-  chemistry". Considering the amount of work done in this field and the grow-  ing awareness of its importance, the authors took on themselves an impor-  tant, but formidable task. The book covers the whole gamut of geochemical  colloid systems from low to high temperature environments and from atmo-  spheric through terrestrial to manne environments. The book is organised  into ten chapters. Some of them deal with general physico-chemical proper-  ties of colloidal systems -- kinetics, surface chemistry, interactions between  solid particles dispersed in colloid systems. Others deal with specific geo-  chemical themes -- clay minerals, silica, organic materials, and finally with  the colloid geochemistry of argillaceous sediments. The organization of the  chapters does not always follow a logical s~quence, although the internal or-  ganization is quite orderly. The authors have succeeded quite well in their  message of emphasizing the importance of colloid systems in geochemistry.  One can only be surprised that no such book was published before. The pio-  neering and unconventional approach to a multi-disciplinary subject should  be highly praised. But then again, such broad view suffers from some imbal-  ances. In their (commendable) enthusiasm the authors have used the term  "colloids" for systems which are not usually defined as such. Examples can  be found in the treatment of organic matter in sea water where the authors  discuss dissolved and particulate organic matter in the same breath as col-  loidal organic matter. The same is true in the chapter on rheology which in-  cludes discussion of sands.  All in all the book is recommended to practicing geo-scientists of every  brand and flavour. Although the book is based on a graduate course, the  price of the book will probably put it beyond the reach of most students,  but it should find its way to every library of soil science and geoscience.    A. NISSENBAUM  (Rehovot)    Environment Impact Assessment, Pr.inciples end Procedures, SCOPE 5, 2nd  ed. R.E. Munn (Editor}. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, 1979, 190 pp.,  7.50.    It is certainly unusual to be asked to review a book in 1980 with its earliest  reference dated 1967 and most references later than 1973, but that is a re-  flection of its topicality, in the best possible sense. It is also a reflection on                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               