Geoderma, 34 (1984) 261--280                                                        261  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    WEATHERING OF HORNBLENDE, PLAGIOCLASE AND CHLORITE  IN META-DOLERITE, AUSTRALIA    R.R. ANAND and R.J. GILKES  Department of Soil Science and Plant Nutrition, University of Western Australia,  Nedlands, W.A. 6009 (Australia)  (Received February 3, 1984; accepted after revision October 2, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Anand, R.R. and Gilkes, R.J., 1984. Weathering of hornblende, plagioclase and chlorite  in meta-dolerite, Australia. Geoderma, 34: 261--280.    Weathering of meta-dolerite by alteration of hornblende, plagioclase feldspars and  chlorite occurs in a West Australian saprolite. Chlorite alters to randomly interstratified  chlorite--vermiculite and goethite. Lath-shaped goethite crystals are arranged in a hex-  agonal pattern on chlorite flakes with the b-axis of chlorite parallel to the c-axis of the  goethite.  Feldspars and hornblende dissolve congruently producing etchpits within  which halloysite crystallizes from solution. Ilmenite alters to microcrystalline anatase  via pseudorutile.  The contents of Fe, Mg, Ca, Na, Si, K, Mn, Ba, Sr, Cu, Ni, Zn and Co decrease whereas  those of Al, Ti, Cr, V and Ga remain approximately constant during weathering. These  chemical changes are explained by reference to the properties of the primary minerals  and their various alteration products.    INTRODUCTION    Weathering of doleritic rocks consisting mostly of amphiboles and plagio-  clase feldspars has been reported by several workers (e.g., Loughnan and  Golding, 1957; Clemency, 1975; Bettenay et al., 1980; Ildefonse, 1980).  A great variety of weathering products of amphiboles (e.g., goethite, chlo-  rite, chlorite--saponite, talc--chlorite, brown mica, iron montmorillonite  and gibbsite) and feldspars (e.g., illite, halloysite, kaolinite, gibbsite and  montmorillonite) have been reported. Differences in chemical macroenviron-  ments from profile to profile or in microenvironment within a single soil  profile may account for the development of different alteration products  from a single primary mineral species. Most studies have involved the deter-  mination of changes in fabric, mineralogy and chemistry of whole ma-  terials; little attention has been given to the detailed alteration mechanisms  of individual mineral species. This paper examines the alteration of horn-  blende, feldspar and chlorite during weathering of a meta-dolerite in south-  western Australia.    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    262    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Samples of rock and various materials developed from meta-dolerite  were obtained from a railway cutting at Jarrahdale, 45 km southeast of  Perth, southwestern Australia. The laterite profile at this site has been  described in detail by Sadleir and Gilkes (1976) and is about 10 m deep.  It consists of the following distinct zones: meta-dolerite parent material,  saprolite (5 mm thick), weathering zone (5 ram), loose material (5 cm),  white pallid zone clay (4 m), irregular brown nodular concretions (2 m),  loose brown nodular hard cap (2 m) and red-brown breccia-like pisolitic hard  cap (2 m) (Fig. 1). The contact between rock and saprolite is sharp and the  rock is fully altered within 5 cm (loose material zone) where all primary  minerals with the exception of quartz have been replaced.    0     ~Q  eQ  ~    Q   S~  (./ o O~  ~OQ i,i       @UQ  2  b. ~^OgU. I  4  ~  t  0  II    I  ~t!   f  I     0  !  6  5    ~  t  5      -  I0  hA  A   ^  ^  A    Red-brown  breccia-like  pisolite hardcap    Loose  brown,  nodular hardcap    Irregular,  brown,  nodular  coneretion~  /  Mottled/  red-  white/  cla~  /  /  /    Me ta-  dolerlte    !   .  .   |  1  s  j%  "'A  ~" A  A              '~.  "A-'A /~ .      ~.A . A~  A  ,A  ^  ^    Loose material - 5 G 6/1  (greenish grey) and 5 Y 8/1  (white); sand clay    Weathering zone - 5 G 6/1  (greenish grey);  lo~y sand  Saprolite - 5 Y 7/2 (light  grey) and 5 Y 8/i (white)  bleta-dolerite - 7.5 YR N/5  (grey)    Fig. 1. Generalized morphology of the profile.    Hornblende and feldspar grains at different stages of alteration were  separated from bulk samples of rock, saprolite, weathering and loose ma-  terial zones which had been disaggregated by gentle shaking in water. X-ray  diffraction patterns of separated grains were made using a Gandolfi single  crystal camera (Gandolfi, 1967). Samples of whole material were impreg-  nated with resin and polished thin sections were made for optical examina-  tion and electron microprobe analysis. X-ray diffraction patterns of random  powders of whole material were obtained with a Philips diffractometer  with Fe filtered Co Ks radiation. Semiquantitative determination of secon-  dary minerals in whole materials were made by thermogravimetric (TG)    263    analysis of 10 mg samples in flowing air at heating rate of 10/min (Perkin  Elmer TG 52). Both weight loss (TG) and differential weight loss curves  (DTG) were obtained.  Basally oriented preparations of clay (&lt;2 pm) on porous ceramic plates  were analysed by XRD after various pre-treatments (Brown, 1961).  Whole materials were analysed for major and minor elements by X-ray  fluorescence spectrometry after fusion in lithium borate--lithium carbonate  flux (low dilution fusion) following the method of Lee and McConchie  (1982). The major element composition of hornblende, feldspars, ilmenite  and chlorite was determined on polished thin sections of whole material  using an ARL-SEM Q electron microprobe. Minor element composition  of separated grains of hornblende, feldspars and ilmenite was determined  by dissolving the samples in a mixture of HC104 and HF acids and analysing  by atomic absorption spectrophotometry using a Perkin Elmer instrument.  The fabric of whole material and of separated grains of altered horn-  blende and feldspars was investigated using a scanning electron microscope  (SEM, Philips PSEM 500). Specimens were mounted on aluminium stubs  and coated with a 150 A-thick layer of platinum in a vacuum evaporator.  Platinum shadowed carbon replicas of broken surfaces of feldspar grains  were prepared to provide high resolution images of the fabric of alteration  products by transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The clay size frac-  tions of whole material and separated grains were examined under the TEM  and the minerals identified using selected area electron diffraction (SAD)  with the Hitachi HU IIB instrument.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Mineralogy of whole material    Optical~ X-ray diffraction and thermogravimetric data showed that meta-  dolerite and saprolite consisted of hornblende (47%), plagioclase feldspars  (30%), chlorite (10%), quartz (10%) and ilmenite (3%). Halloysite (15%),  chlorite (10%), hornblende (40%), plagioclase feldspars (25%) and quartz  (10%) were present in the weathering zone. The loose material consisted  of halloysite/kaolinite (45%) and gibbsite (5%) together with hornblende,  feldspar, quartz and chlorite. In the pallid zone halloysite/kaolinite (70%),  gibbsite (12%) and quartz were the dominant materials. Iron oxides were  not detected by XRD due to their low abundance (about 5%). Halloysite  (10 A) and halloysite (7)k)/kaolinite which are the first alteration products  of feldspars and hornblende increased in abundance with distance from  parent material.  Weathering of hornblende is accompanied by a colour change from  dark green in fresh hornblende to pale green in weathered hornblende  which is due to loss of iron (Deer et al., 1962b). Feldspars showed a cloudy    264    265    appearance in the initial stages of alteration and in later stages of alteration  both hornblende and plagioclase feldspars are replaced by a porous matrix  of fine grained alteration products (Fig. 2A). Ilmenite grains were altered  first to pseudorutile and then to leucoxene grains.  X-ray diffraction patterns of the clay fractions of saprolite material  after various pretreatments showed the presence of chlorite and randomly  interstratified chlorite--vermiculite. Hornblende and plagioclase feldspars    TGA-14*,   ^  OTG     [~0:2o~\  -"""4 /     6D    I  I           j           I           I           J           J          d  720     600    500   400   300   200   1 0  40  TEMPERATURE  Fig. 3. Thermogravimetric curves of saprolite material (A), weathering zone (B), loose  material (C)and pallid zone (D). TGA = thermogravimetric analysis; DTG = differential  thermogravimetric analysis. Total weight loss (%) and temperatures of DTGA maxima  are indicated.    Fig. 2. Micrographs of whole materials. (A) Optical micrograph of weathering zone  showing alteration of feldspar (1) and hornblende (2) to fine grained material; and  opaque mineral is altered ilmenite (3). (B) Scanning electron micrograph of meta-dolerite  showing massive, irregular surfaces of primary mineral grains. (C, D) Scanning electron  micrographs of loose material showing aggregates of tubular halloysite crystals (1).  (E, F) Scanning electron micrographs of pallid zone showing aggregates of platy crystals  of kaolinite or gibbsite (1) and few tubular crystals of halloysite (2).    266    were also present. The clay size fraction of the weathering zone consisted  of chlorite, chlorite--vermiculite, halloysite, goethite, gibbsite, hornblende  and feldspars.  The TG and DTG curves for saprolite material {Fig. 3} showed a water  loss at 610 due to dehydroxylation of chlorite (Ross and Kodama, 1976).  The small loss of water at 50 is probably due to adsorbed moisture.  The meta~lolerite and saprolite gave similar TG and DTG patterns. The  DTG curves for the weathering zone showed water losses at 70 255  270 470and 620. These can be attributed to losses of moisture ad-  sorbed onto halloysite and water of hydration on the interlayer cation  of the vermiculite layer in chlorite--vermiculite (70) {Ross and Kodama,  1976); dehydroxylation of gibbsite and goethite (255and 270) (Barshad,  1965); dehydroxylation of halloysite/kaolinite (470) {Tan and Hajek,  1977) and dehydroxylation of chlorite {620). The loose material showed  major losses at 65 due to adsorbed water and 490 due to dehydroxyla-  tion of halloysite/kaolinite. Water losses at about 60 275and 500  for the pallid zone clay correspond to adsorbed and interlayer water in  halloysite, to dehydroxylation of gibbsite and to dehydroxylation of hal-  loysite/kaolinite, respectively.    Morphology of whole material and clay fractions    The meta~lolerite consists of primary mineral grains with massive, ir-  regular surfaces (Fig. 2B). The loose material is comprised of primary min-  eral grains in a highly porous clay matrix consisting mainly of aggregates  of tubular halloysite crystals (-0.8 pm) {Fig. 2, C and D). The pallid zone  consists mostly of platy subhedral crystals of kaolinite and gibbsite (~0.25  ~m) with some tubular halloysite crystals (Fig. 2, E and F).  Saprolite clay consists mostly of tubular halloysite crystals (Fig. 4A)  with an average length of ~0.43 pm, platy ~0.2 pm crystals of chlorite  and large irregular fragments of hornblende and feldspars. The loose ma-  terial contains identical tubular halloysite and a few subhedral to euhedral  hexagonal -0.1 pm crystals of kaolinite/gibbsite (Fig. 4B). The pallid    Fig. 4. (A) Transmission electron micrograph of clay fractions of saprolite showing  tubular halloysite (1), platy crystals of chlorite (2) and anhedral fragments of feldspar  and hornblende (3). (B) Transmission electron micrograph of the clay fractions of loose  material showing tubular halloysite (1) with occasional platy crystals of kaolinite/gibbsite  (2). (C) Transmission electron micrograph of the clay fraction of the pallid zone showing  partially unrolled halloysite crystals (1), almost completely unrolled halloysite crystals  (2) and platy hexagonal crystals of kaolinite/gibbsite (3). (D) Transmission electron  micrograph of chlorite from rock. (E) Its SAD pattern showing hko net of reflections  with d(060) = 1.53 A typical of a trioctahedral clay mineral. (F) Chlorite grain from  saprolite exhibiting moir~ patterns. (G) Its SAD pattern demonstrating that the particle  consists of an aggregate of several flakes.    267    ,0.3um,       268    zone clay consists of partly unrolled to completely unrolled ~0.7 t~m tubular  halloysite crystals (Fig. 4C} and platy ~0.2 /~m crystals of kaolinite or  gibbsite.  In the saprolite and loose material halloysite is mainly tubular whereas  in the pallid zone halloysite occurred mostly as platy particles with rolled  edges or as partly unrolled tubes. These differences in halloysite morphology  between horizons may be due to dehydration of halloysite in the pallid  zone (Bates, 1971; Churchman and Carr, 1975).    Alteration of primary minerals    Chlorite  Several chlorite crystals from the meta-dolerite parent material were  analysed on the electron microprobe and their chemical composition (Table  I) corresponds to the structural formula:  (Mg2.40 Fe2+2.26 Al~.:7 Mno.o3)(Al~.26 Si2.74)01o (OH)8  i.e. the chlorite is ripidolite (Deer et al., 1962b).    TABLE I  Chemical composition of fresh and altered grains    Feldspars  Pseudo-     Hornblende   Chlorite  Ilmenite  Pseudomorphs  morphs of                                      of ilmenite  feldspars    SiO2 (%)    51.02    41.31       52.07       25.20   --         0,65  AI203 (%)    30.52     36.90         3.86         19.20       0.06      2.40  CaO (%)     12.89     0.45      11.40        0.13   --       --  Na:O (%)     4.16     02 7       0.41       --      --       --  K:O (%)       0.12  .....  FeO* (%)    --        --          15.70        26.31     43.90     5.50  MgO (%)   --       --        13.80      14.00     0.01   --  TiO~ (%)  ....  52.1     88.00  MnO (%)    --        --           0.22        0.35      2.81     0.02  Zn (ppm)     10         5          110            40        240        75  Cu (ppm)     80        20          130            30        150        70  Cr (ppm)      8        15          170           350       450      770  V (ppm)    12      22        390         --      650    1260  Co (ppm)      5       &lt;5           70           -        110      &lt;20  Ga (ppm)     35        60           10           n.d.         25        50  Ba (ppm)    190        50           95           n.d.        410      450  Ni (ppm)   --       --        130        200      130      50  Sr (ppm)    410        25          105           n.d.       --         --  Zr (ppm)    --         --            70           n.d.      1300     2400    *Total iron expressed as FeO.    269    Electron diffraction patterns of irregular platy chlorite crystals consist  of the hko net of reflections (Fig. 4, D and E). The 060 spacings of several  patterns were measured using a gold internal standard and found to be  1.534 _+ 0.003 which is in agreement with XRD results and typical of  ripidolite. Moire patterns were commonly observed on chlorite crystals  (Fig. 4F) which indicates that layers within chlorite crystals are present  at different orientations. The SAD patterns from such crystals (Fig. 4G) gave  spotty ring patterns supporting this interpretation (Gard, 1971).  Chlorite in saprolite and weathering zone has altered to randomly inter-  stratified chlorite--vermiculite and goethite. Chlorite--vermiculite in K-  saturated samples after heating at 600 for 1 h gave peaks at 11.8 and  10.6 A indicating that two distinct types of interstratification occurred  containing approximately 60% and 80% vermiculite layers respectively  (calculated using the theoretical predictions of MacEwan et al., 1961).  Several studies of the experimental weathering (Ross and Kodama, 1976)  and natural weathering (Herbillon and Makumbi, 1975; Gilkes and Little,  1972; Coffman and Fanning, 1975) of chlorite have also identified this  type of alteration. Coffman and Fanning (1975) described the alteration  of chlorite to chlorite--vermiculite and goethite and also showed that the  chlorite--vermiculite subsequently altered to kaolinite. Stevens and Wilson  (1970) reported the alteration of chlorite to kaolinite and iron oxides.  In this present study, halloysite and kaolinite were not observed on residual  fragments of chlorite or chlorite--vermiculite so that alteration to halloysite/  kaolinite is unlikely to be by replacement of chlorite. Thus alteration prob-  ably  proceeds via complete dissolution and subsequent crystallization  of halloysite/kaolinite from soil solution within the general soil matrix  rather than within the chlorite grain.    Plagioclase feldspars  The average chemical composition of plagioclase feldspar in the meta-  dolerite is:  (Si2.3s All.6s)(Cao.63 Na0.36 K0.0~)O8  (Table I)  which corresponds to the composition of labradorite (Deer et al., 1962c).  Single altered feldspar grains from the saprolite and weathering zones con-  sist of mixtures of plagioclase feldspar and halloysite. Single crystal X-ray  diffraction patterns of altered feldspar grains demonstrated a random dis-  tribution (i.e. a ring pattern) of halloysite and kaolinite crystals within  the grains so that the structure of feldspar does not control the orientation  of halloysite crystals. TG analysis of highly altered feldspar grains showed  that on average they contained 26% hydrated halloysite, 60% dehydrated  halloysite and/or kaolinite and 14% feldspar.  Surfaces of partly altered feldspar grains contain abundant elongated  etchpits (Fig. 5A) indicating that congruent dissolution is the major mech-  anism of feldspar weathering. The development and growth of etchpits is    270    E iii~i!ii!~ilili~i!iii~iiiiiii   ~!i'~~i!iiiiiiyi!i~i!~ii~  i!~i~ i~! ~i i~ ~iiii~!ili~i~i~i~!i!~ii~ !~ ~   ~ ~    271    believed to be the common mode of weathering of feldspars both under  field and laboratory conditions (Berner and Holdren, 1979). Felted masses  of tubular -0.7 pm halloysite crystals have crystallized from solution onto  the surface of feldspar grains (Fig. 5, B and C). Halloysite tubes from the  weathering zone  (Fig. 6, E and F) are generally elongated along their  b-axes, as has been observed by Honjo et al. (1954).  The chemical composition of single feldspar grains and their associated  fine grained alteration products (called pseudomorphs in Table I) was  determined on polished thin sections by electron microprobe analysis.  There is an increase in concentration of aluminium, a reduction in con-  centration of silicon and almost complete loss of sodium and calcium on  alteration of the feldspars. In the analysis of the whole material of the  pallid zone the small amounts of calcium and sodium are due to residual  unaltered feldspar. After making the corrections for these residual feldspars,  the silicon to aluminium molar ratio for the alteration product of feldspar  grains is 0.97 which indicates the dominance of halloysite and/or kaolinite  {molar ratio I) with little or no gibbsite (ratio zero).    Horn blende  The chemical composition of hornblende (Table I) corresponds to the  structural formula:  (Si7.60 Alo.4o)(Alo.26 Mg3.00 Fe2+l.gl Mno.o3)(Cal.79 Na0.11)022 (OH)2  SEM photographs of separated grains of hornblende show that dissolu-  tion has been the major weathering mechanism leading to pronounced  etching along cleavage planes. Etched grains commonly exhibit a toothed  appearance (Fig. 5D) which has been reported by other workers (e.g. Walker,  1967; Waugh, 1978; Berner and Schott, 1982). Selected area electron  diffraction patterns of these toothed fragments consist of rows of hkn reflec-  tions (Fig. 5, E and F). These fragments are elongated along the c-axis  which is in agreement with the findings of Berner and Schott (1982) who  considered that etchpits are developed mainly on dislocation outcrops  which are always aligned with the long axis parallel to the c-axis of the  crystal.    Fig. 5. (A) Scanning electron micrograph of slightly altered feldspar from saprolite  showing a highly etched surface. (B) Scanning electron micrograph of altered feldspar  from the weathering zone showing abundant tubular halloysite crystals. (C) Replica  electron micrograph of partially altered feldspar from the weathering zone showing a  felted mass of tubular halloysite crystals on a feldspar surface. (D) Scanning electron  micrograph of slightly altered hornblende showing that etching has produced a toothed  formation. (E) Transmission electron micrograph of a toothed hornblende fragment.  (F) Correctly oriented SAD pattern of hornblende fragment showing it to be elongated  along its c-axis.    272    ,02~m.    273    It appears from the SEM photographs that, as in the case of feldspar  in the same samples, the hornblende crystals simply dissolve congruently.  In weathered feldspar grains, all A1 and some Si are retained as porous  aggregates of halloysite/kaolinite which eventually replace the entire feldspar  grain. The volume of halloysite/kaolinite produced from plagioclase feldspar  is about 80% of the volume of the parent feldspar so that a porous aggregate  replaced the massive feldspar grain. Hornblende grains are not replaced  in this way because of the low aluminium content of hornblende, thus the  grain simply disappears. Assuming that all of the A1 in hornblende is resid-  ual, only about 6% halloysite/kaolinite would replace a hornblende grain  which is insufficient to fill the space previously occupied by hornblende  crystal. Some authors (e.g., Leneuf, 1959) have reported hornblende grains  being replaced by secondary iron oxyhydroxides; this has not occurred  in this profile.    Ilmeuite  The first alteration product of ilmenite is pseudorutile which develops  via a solid state reaction in patches and layers throughout ilmenite grains  (Grey and Reid, 1975} and this is then replaced by anatase by a dissolu-  tion--crystallization process. Clay minerals and gibbsite crystallize within  pores in the completely altered grains as has been described elsewhere  (Anand and Gilkes, 1984).    Properties of goethite  Following the method of Norrish and Taylor (1961) measurement of  spacings of goethite reflections shows that no A1 substitution has occurred  in the goethite present in the weathering and loose material zones. Fitz-  patrick and Schwertmann (1982} also found that goethite in saprolite  contains little A1 substitution which they suggested is due to the relatively  low degree of weathering as indicated by the low gibbsite content of sap-  rolite. In adjacent lateritic profiles developed on granite, goethite in the  acidic saprolite (pH 4.8) has 15--23 mole % A1 substitution. The pH of  the weathering zone for meta-dolerite is 6.5 and this relatively high value  may reduce the activity of A1 relative to the more acidic materials and  thereby reduce incorporation of A1 into goethite (Fitzpatrick and Schwert-  mann, 1982).    Fig. 6. Transmission electron micrographs and SAD patterns of goethite and halloysite  from the weathering zone. (A) An aggregate of lath-shaped crystals of goethite (1).  (B) Hexagonal SAD pattern of material shown in A indicating that crystals resting on  (100) faces, are organised in a hexagonal fabric and are elongated along the c-axis. (C)  An aggregate of goethite crystals (1) arranged in a hexagonal pattern on a chlorite flake  (2). (D) Its SAD pattern. Reflections due to goethite and trioctahedral chlorite are  shown. (E) Tubular halloysite crystal. (F) Its indexed SAD pattern showing that the  halloysite crystal is elongated along the b-axis.    274    Line broadening measurements from X-ray diffraction patterns showed  that the average crystal size of goethite is about 600 h which is supported  by electron microscope observations. Goethite occurs as aggregates of  very small lath-like crystals in the clay fractions of the weathering and  loose material zones. Goethite crystals are frequently arranged in hexagonal  arrays {Fig. 6A) so that electron diffraction patterns consist of ohl reflec-  tions showing that these crystals are resting on (100} faces and are elongated  along their c-axis (Fig. 6B). Synthetic goethite is often acicular with the  c-axis lying along the needle axis (Van Oosterhout, 1960) and natural  occurrences of small, lath-like goethite crystals resembling those described  here have been reported by Beutelspacher and Van der Marel {1968) and  Gilkes and Suddhiprakarn (1979).  Fig. 6C shows a chlorite crystal coated with a raft-like aggregate of hex-  agonally-arranged goethite crystals. The SAD pattern {Fig. 6D) consists  of a net of sharp hko reflections from the chlorite together with goethite  reflections in the form of broad arcs corresponding to a quite well-oriented  hexagonal arrangement of goethite crystals. This pattern shows the b-axis  of chlorite to be parallel to the c-axis of the goethite crystals. The presence  of many small goethite crystals in a hexagonal arrangement is demonstrated  by the association of 002 and 061 goethite reflections on the same axis.  This organization of goethite upon the chlorite substrate is identical to  that described by Gilkes and Suddhiprakarn (1979) for goethite on a mica  substrate in weathered biotite grains. Goethite is a common alteration  product of chlorite (Bain, 1977; Ross et al., 1982) but this preferred orien-  tation of goethite crystals has not been described previously.    Chemical composition of whole material and separated primary mineral  grains  There are marked differences in the behaviour of elements during weather-  ing {Table II), however, groupings can be made of elements that behave  similarly. The following affinity groups could be identified for this par-  ticular profile:  Group 1 -- A1, H20, V, Zr, Cr, Ga, Ti  Group 2 -- Mg, Fe, Ca, Na, K, Mn, Ba, Sr, Co, Cu, Zn  Group 3 -- Si  The first group is retained, the second group is lost and only some Si is  lost during weathering. The behaviour of the major elements during weather-  ing is consistent with the mineralogy described above. The changes in com-  position away from the fresh meta~olerite are simply due to increasing  replacement of primary minerals by halloysite, kaolinite, gibbsite and  anatase.  The chemical changes leading to the formation of the pallid zone by  weathering of individual primary minerals can be described quantitatively  in the form of a chemical budget assuming: (1) that A1 is fully residual;  (2) the abundance and alteration pathways of minerals can be determined    TABLE II  Composition of whole samples of various horizons developed on meta-dolerite    Horizon            SiO2      TiO2      Al~O3   Fe203   MgO      CaO     Na20      K~O       L.O.I.  (%)     (%)     (%)    (%)    (%)     (7o)    (%)     (%)     (%)    Rock               50.7     1.40    14.2    12.0     7.82   11.7       1.96     0.62    1.0  Saprolite             50.4      1.81     13.9    11.3      7.10   10.7       1.75      0.58     1.7  Weathering zone      49.6      2.93     22.6      6.0      1.91     7.1       0.98      0.45     4.9  Loose material       49.2      3.84    26.2     2.8     0.80     2.1       0.02      0.40   14  Pallid zone           45.2      3.30    32.7      1.5     0.25    0.55      0.02      0.26   18    Horizon           Mn       Ba        V       Zr       Sr        Co      Cr        Cu        Ga      Ni       Zn  (ppm)   (ppm)   (ppm)  (ppm)  (ppm)   (ppm)  (ppm)   (ppm)   (ppm)  (ppm)  (ppm)    Rock              1370     120      320      85     165      60      110      190      16      110     80  Saprolite          1010     100      370      95     130      45      130      175      20      100     70  Weathering zone    530      50      485     125      85      20      170      140      30       90     50  Loose material      180      40      570     150      70        5      240      100      44       50     20  Pallid zone           80      20      770     195      10      --       280        85      55       35      5    276    optically and by XRD and TGA; and (3) only five minerals (hornblende,  feldspar, quartz, chlorite and ilmenite) are present in the parent rock.  On the basis one gram of meta-dolerite alters to 0.44 g of the pallid zone  as is illustrated in Fig. 7A. Assuming isovolumetric weathering (Millot,  1970}, about 0.50 ml of alteration products in the pallid zone occupy the  1.0 ml previously occupied by meta-dolerite, thus the porosity is 50%.  This highly porous structure is clearly seen in SEM pictures of the pallid  zone (Fig. 2, E and F). The contributions to the total porosity by the  alteration products of the various primary mineral are depicted in Fig. 7B.  The behaviour of major elements during weathering is illustrated by  the quantitative budget allocating each element to the primary minerals  and their alteration products (Table III).    A    0 0.1  C    i    I   }    l    l    l    I \" ,'X.-'~  0.3 i  0.5    a7    IO.9 i 110  F              H  01  gm  B    0              A~O'~5               t-o  .~    tpe  el O:  t  .     .   bf DO  \ . 0....  ~"        t '  e'* "  \ ..o.,...  }      \-'~\~." o  ,,.,  HIK  \     X Q_'~; PORES',,':  \  o  o.1     0.3   I 0.5    o.7    / o.9 / 1.o  C          F             H  Q J  ml  Fig. 7. A mass and volume balance for the alteration of feldspars, hornblende, chlorite,  quartz and ilmenite to secondary minerals in pallid zone (A) weight basis (B)volume  basis. F = feldspars; H = hornblende; C = chlorite; Q = quartz; I = ilmenite; A = anatase;  H/K = halloysite/kaolinite.    TABLE III    A comparison of the calculation of major elements distribution in feldspars (F), hornblende (H), chlorite (C), quartz (Q)  and ilmenite (I) and their alteration products for one gram of meta-dolerite (R) and 0.44 g of pallid zone (P) weathering  products with analyses of the whole material    Rock       Pallid   AlR      Alp      SiR      Sip       CaR      Cap      MgR     Mgp      NaR      Nap  zone    F   0.30    g      0.23g      0.0485       0.0495       0.0717       0.0443       0.0276       0.00074    --                  --                  0.00926     0.0003  H   0.47    g      0.04 g      0.0096       0.0095       0.1142       0.0096       0.0384       --                  0.0386       --                  0.0014       --  C   0.10    g      0.05g      0.0101        0.0101       0.0118       0.0103       0.00001     --                  0.0083       --                  --                  --  Q   0.10    g      0.10g      --                  --                  0.0467       0.0467  ......  I  0.03  g   0.02g   --         0.0002  ........    1     g   0.44 g   0.068     0.069     0.244     0.110     0.066     0.00074  0.047     -         0.011     0.0003  Whole material       0.075     0.075     0.237     0.092     0.083     0.0017   0.046     0.0006   0.014     --  Rock       Pallid   KR       Kp       TiR      Tie      FeR      Fep  zone    F 0.30  g   0.23g   0.0003  H   0.47    g      0.04g      --  C 0.10  g   0.05g   --  Q   0.10    g      0.10g      --  I  0.031 g   0.02 g   --    w    1     g   0.44 g   0.0003   --  Whole material        0.005     0.0009    --         --         0.0572   --  --         --         0.0204   --  0.0093   0.0105   0.0103   0.00077  0.0093   0.0105   0.088     0.00077  0.0083       0.009          0.085          0.0045    bO    278    A minor element budget could not be calculated because distinct pseudo-  morphs of hornblende did not occur and so could not be separately anal-  ysed. There is good agreement between the analysed amount of an element  in the whole material samples of rock and pallid zone and the calculated  contribution from separated fresh and altered grains of the constituent  minerals. Much of the Na and about 35% of the Ca are derived from plagio-  clase feldspars whereas hornblende contributes 47% of the Ca. These two  elements are lost during weathering. Silicon present in quartz is retained,  and in the altered feldspars, hornblende, and chlorite much of the Si (70%)  remains in halloysite and kaolinite. In the meta-dolerite, most Mg (84%) is  present in hornblende and is lost on weathering. Ilmenite is the main source  of Ti in the meta&lt;lolerite and Ti is retained in leucoxene grains as micro-  crystalline anatase.  The behaviour of minor elements may be attributed to weathering of  specific primary mineral species present in the rock. About 55% of the  Mn in the meta-dolerite is present in hornblende (Table I) whereas 45%  is in ilmenite. Manganese is lost during the alteration of hornblende to  clay minerals and of ilmenite to anatase. Manganese does not substitute for  Ti in anatase (Hartman, 1959} and A1 in clay minerals and gibbsite. Feld-  spars are the main carriers of Sr (75% of the Sr is in feldspar} and Ba (50%}  (Table I}, and these elements are both lost during weathering (Yaalon  et al., 1974}. Strontium and Ba substitute for Ca and Na in feldspars and  hornblende but are unable to substitute for A1 or Si+4 in clay minerals  and are therefore released to soil solution during weathering. Most of the  Zr (65%), Co (55%} and some Cu (35%} are present in hornblende. Feld-  spars (15%) are also important carriers of copper. These elements are lost  once they are released by dissolution of hornblende and feldspars and  are not incorporated into secondary minerals.  Gallium (70%) is mainly contributed by feldspars and substitutes readily  for A1 in feldspars and both clay minerals and gibbsite. Hornblende is  the main source of Cr (70%) and V (60%), and these elements are retained  within secondary minerals (Shiraki, 1978). Zirconium is mostly present as  zircon. The increased water content is due to formation of halloysite,  kaolinite and gibbsite.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We are grateful to Dr. B.H. Smith for his helpful comments on this manu-  script.    REFERENCES  Anand, R.R. and Gilkes, R.J., 1984. Weathering of ilmenite in a lateritic pallid zone.  Clays and Clay Minerals, 32: 363--374.    279    Bain D.C., 1977. The weathering of ferruginous chlorite in a podzol from Argyllshire,  Scotland. Geoderma, 17 : 193--208.  Barshad, I., 1965. Thermal analysis techniques for mineral identification and mineralog-  ical composition. In: Methods of Soil Analysis: I. Physical and mineralogical prop-  erties, including statistics of measurement and sampling. Am. Soc. Agron., Wisc., pp.  699--742.  Bates, T.F.,  1971. The Kaolin Minerals. In: J.A. Gard (Editor), The Electron-Optical  Investigation of Clays. Mineralogical Society, London, pp. 109--157.  Berner, R.A. and Holdren, G.R., 1979. Mechanism of feldspar westhering, II. Observa-  tions of feldspars from soils. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 43: 1173--1186.  Berner, R.A. and Schott, J., 1982. Mechanism of pyroxene and amphibole weathering,  II. Observations of soil grains. Am. J. Sci., 282: 1214--1231.  Bettenay, E., Russell, W.G.R., Hudson, D.R., Gilkes, R.J. and Edmiston, R.3., 1980.  A description of the experimental catchments in the Collie area, Western Australia.  CSIRO, Aust. Div. Land Resour. Manage. Tech. Pap., 7 : 1--36.  Beutelspacher, H. and Van der Marel, H.W., 1968. Atlas of Electron Microscopy of  Clay Minerals and their Admixtures. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 333 pp.  Brown, G., 1961. The X-ray Identification and Crystal Structures of Clay Minerals. Min-  eralogical Society, London, 543 pp.  Churchman, G.J. and Cart, R.M., 1975. The definition and nomenclature of halloysites.  Clays Clay Miner., 23: 382--388.  Clemency, C.V., 1975. Simultaneous weathering of a granitic gneiss and an intrusive  amphibolite dyke near Sao Paulo, Brazil, and the origin of clay minerals. Proc. Int.  Clay. Conf. Mexico, July 16--23, pp. 15--25.  Coffman, C.B. and Fanning, D.T., 1975. Maryland soils developed in residuum from  chloritic metabasalt having high amounts of vermiculite in sand and silt fractions.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 723--732.  Deer, W.A., Howie, R.A. and Zussman, J., 1962a. Rock-Forming Minerals, Vol. 2, Chain  Silicates. Longmans, London, 379 pp.  Deer, W.A., Howie, R.A. and Zussman, J., 1962b. Rock-Forming Minerals, Vol. 3, Sheet  Silicates, Longmans, London, 270 pp.  Deer, W.A., Howie, R.A. and Zussman, J., 1962c. Rock-Forming Minerals, Vol. 4, Frame-  work Silicates, Longmans, London, 435 pp.  Fitzpatrick, R.W. and Schwertmann, U., 1982. Al-substituted goethite -- an indicator  of pedogenic and other weathering environments in South Africa. Geoderma, 27:  335--347.  Gandolfi, G., 1967. Discussion upon methods to obtain X-ray powder patterns from a  single crystal. Mineral. Petrogr. Acta, 13: 67--74.  Gard, J.A. (Editor), 1971. The Electron-Optical Investigation of Clays. Mineralogical  Society, London, 383 pp.  Gilkes, R.J. and Little, I.P., 1972. Weathering of chlorite and some associations of trace  elements in Permian phylites in southeast Queensland. Geoderma, 7: 233--247.  Gilkes, R.J. and Suddhiprakarn, A., 1979. Biotite alteration in deeply-weathered granite,  II. The oriented growth of secondary minerals. Clays Clay Miner., 27: 361--367.  Grey, I.E. and Reid, A.F., 1975. The structure of pseudorutile and its role in the alter-  ation of ilmenite. Am. Miner., 60: 898--906.  Hartman, J.A., 1959. The titanium mineralogy of certain bauxites and their parent  minerals. Econ. Geol., 54: 1380--1405.  Herbillon, A.J. and Makumbi, M.N., 1975. Weathering of chlorite in a soil derived from  chloritoschist under humid tropical conditions. Geoderma, 13: 89--109.  Hon]o, G.N., Kitamura, N. and Mihama, K., 1954. Study of clay minerals by single  crystal electron diffraction diagrams -- the structure of tubular kaolin. Clay Miner.  Bull., 2: 131--141.  Ildefonse, P., 1980. Mineral facies developed by weathering of a meta-gabbro, Loire-  Atlantique (France). Geoderma, 24: 257--273.    280    Lee, R.F. and McConchie, D.M., 1982. Comprehensive major and trace element analysis  of geological material by X-ray fluorescence, using low dilution fusion. X-ray Spec-  trometry, 11: 55---63.  Leneuf, N., 1959. L'alt~ration des granites calcoalcalins et des granodiorites en C6te  d'Ivoire foresti~re et les sols qui en sont d6riv~s. Th~se Sciences, Paris, O.R.S.T.O.M.,  210 pp.  Loughnan, F.C. and Golding, H.G., 1957. The mineralogy of commercial dyke clays in  the Sydney district. J. R. Soc. N.S.W., 41 : 85--91.  MacEwan, D.M.C., Ruiz Amil, A. and Brown, G., 1961. Interstratified clay minerals.  In: G. Brown (Editor), The X-ray Identification and Crystal Structures of Clay Min-  erals. Mineralogical Society, London, pp. 393--446.  Millot, G., 1970. Geology of Clays. Springer Verlag, Berlin, 429 pp.  Norrish, K. and Taylor, R.M., 1961. The isomorphous replacement of iron by aluminium  in soil goethites. J. Soil Sci., 12: 294--306.  Ross, G.J. and Kodama, H., 1976. Experimental alteration of a chlorite into a regular  interstratified chlorite--vermiculite by chemical oxidation. Clays Clay Miner., 24:  183--190.  Ross, G.J., Wang, C., Ozkan, A.I. and Rees, H.W., 1982. Weathering of chlorite and  mica in a new Brunswick podzol developed on till derived from chlorite-mica schist.  Geoderma, 27: 255--267.  Sadleir, S.B. and Gilkes, R.J., 1976. Development of bauxite in relation to parent mate-  rial near Jarrahdale, Western Australia. J. Geol. Soc. Aust., 23: 333--344.  Shiraki, K., 1978. Chromium -- Behaviour during weathering and alteration of rocks.  In: K.H. Wedepohl (Editor), Handbook of Geochemistry. Springer Verlag, Berlin,  24-G-1.  Stevens, J.H. and Wilson, M.J., 1970. Alpine podzol soils on the Ben Lawers Massif,  Perthshire. J. Soil Sci., 21 : 85--95.  Tan, K.J. and Hajek, B.F., 1977. Thermal analysis of soils. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Weed  (Editors), Minerals in Soil Environments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Madison, Wisc., pp.  865--884.  Van Oosterhout, G.W., 1960. Morphology of synthetic sub-microscopic crystals of   and 7-FeOOH and 7-Fe203 prepared from FeOOH. Acta Crystallogr., Sect. B, 13:  932--935.  Walker, T.R., 1967. Formation of red beds in modern and ancient deserts. Geol. Soc.  Am. Bull., 78: 353--358.  Waugh, B., 1978. Diagenesis in Continental red beds as revealed by Scanning Electron  Microscopy. In: W.B. Whalley (Editor), Scanning Electron Microscopy in the Study  of Sediments. Geoabstracts, Norwich, pp. 329--346.  Yaalon, D.H., Brenner, I. and Koyumdjisky, H., 1974. Weathering and mobility sequence  of minor elements on a basaltic pedomorphic surface, Galilee, Israel. Geoderma, 12:  233--244.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractWeathering of meta-dolerite by alteration of hornblende, plagioclase feldspars and chlorite occurs in a West Australian saprolite. Chlorite alters to randomly interstratified chlorite-vermiculite and goethite. Lath-shaped goethite crystals are arranged in a hexagonal pattern on chlorite flakes with the b-axis of chlorite parallel to the c-axis of the goethite. Feldspars and hornblende dissolve congruently producing etchpits within which halloysite crystallizes from solution. Ilmenite alters to microcrystalline anatase via pseudorutile.The contents of Fe, Mg, Ca, Na, Si, K, Mn, Ba, Sr, Cu, Ni, Zn and Co decrease whereas those of Al, Ti, Cr, V and Ga remain approximately constant during weathering. These chemical changes are explained by reference to the properties of the primary minerals and their various alteration products.