Geoderma, 26 (1981) 323-327  323  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam - Printed in The Netherlands    Short Communication    DIFFERENCES IN STRUC'T'URE OF ORGANIC MATTER IN N TWC SOILS  AS DEMONSTRATED BY ' 3C CROSS POLARISATION NUCLEAR  MAGNETIC RESONANCE SPECTROSCOPY WITH MAGIC ANGLE  SPINNING    MICHAEL A. WILSON, PETER F. BARRON and KUALA M. GOH    Department of .foil Science, Lincoln College, Canterbury, (New Zealand)    School of Science, Griffith University, Nathan, Qld. (Australia)    Department of Soil Science, Lincoln College, Canterbury (New Zealand)    (Received January 13, 1981; accepted June 17, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Wilson, M.A., Barron, P.F. and Goh, K.M., 1981. Differences in structure of organic matter in two soils as demonstrated by '3C cross polarisation nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy with magic angle spinning. Geoderma, 26: 323-327.     Spectra of two whole soils have been recorded by cross polarisation n.m.r. spectroscopy with magic angle spinning. Magic angle spinning allows detailed structural comparisons between the types of organic carbon in whole soils to be made. Sufficient resolution  achieved to show that the two soils differ considerably in polysaccharide content.    INTRODUCTION     '3C-n.m.r. spectroscopy has become a powerful tool in elucidating the structure of organic substances in ;solution, including humic substances (Vila et a1.,1976; Ogner, 1979; Wilson, :1951). Obtaining a'3C-n.m.r. spectrum of an organic solid, however, presents more difficulties. The techniques used on solutions yield broad, generally structureless lines because of the strong "C--H dipole interactions. In addition, problems associated with long relaxation times result in low sensitivity. Recent developments in n.m.r. spectroscopy have allowed high-resolution '3C spectra of solids to be recorded. The method differs from conventional '3C-n.m.r. spectroscopy in a number of ways. First, much more proton decoupling power is needed to decou.ple the direct dipolar interactions that exist in solids. Secondly, carbon signals are obtained by transfer of polarisation from the more polarised proton spins, thereby increasing the '3C sensi-    *' Current address: CSIRO, Division of ;Fossil Fuels, P.O. Box 136, North Ryde, Australia 2113.    0016-7061/81/0000--0000/$02.50 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company  324    tivity. Signals obtained by this technique, however, are still relatively broad compared with those obtained by conventional '3C-n.m.r. spectroscopy because of chemical shift anisotropy.   Useful qualitative information can still be obtained on the aromaticity (fraction of aromatic carbon) of soil samples (Baryon et al., 1980; Wilson, 1981).   It should be possible to remove most of the remaining line broadening by rapidly spinning the sample about an axis at an angle of 544' (the magic angle) with respect to the static magnetic field so that the spectra should be nearly as well resolved as in solution n.m.r. This is the first step necessary to develop methods to analyse for various types of organic carbon without its destruction or extraction from the soil. The first 13C-n.m.r. spectrum of a soil sample (Maungatua silt loam) ob'ained with magic angle spinning was recently reported by Baryon and Wilson (1981).   In this paper, we report the spectra of two further soil samples (Te Kopuru and Okarito soils) with magic angle spinning. These two soils are of interest because the structure of organic matter is believed to be different in them from that  Maungakta silt loam. (Goh and Williams, 1979; Wilson et al., 1981). Organic matter in Maungatua silt loam is highly aliphatic, whereas that in the Bh horizon of Te Kopuru sand appears to be more aromatic. For the A horizon of the Okarito soil, we were not able to tell whether much of the carbon was in aromatic or carboxyl form. We believe that magic angle spinning will bring out the differences in structure of organic matter among samples of the three soils and at the same time permit better analyses of the forms of carbon in the Okarito sample.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION     Some information on the two soils and on the samples is given in Table I. Fig. 1 shows the '3C-n.m.r. spectra of the organic matter of two soils without magic angle spinning. Three structural types of carbon can just be resolved.    TABLE I    Characteristics of soils    Soil Horizon pH Carbon Parent New Zealand    (1:2.5 ratio (%) material classification    with water)  Okarito A 4.2  6.0 Glacial Gley Podzol       gravels  Te Kopuru sand Bh 5.0 12.7 Pleistocene Northern Sand     sand Podzol  0-Alkyl    (a)    Aromatic/   Carboxyl'    200 0  h13 C (PPM)    325    ( b)    Ia--Alkyl    710 180 150 120 90 60 30 0    N (PPM)    (a)    210 180 150    19    12    170 90 60 !0 0   h (PPM)    Fig. 1. 22.6 MHz'3C-CP - spectra of whole soils. Spectra were obtained using H, fields of 7.8 and 31G- for 'H and '3C. Between 10 K and 100 K scans were collected. (a) Okarito A horizon; (b) Te Kopuru By, horizon.    Fig. 2. 75.5 MHz'3C-CP-MAS spectra of whole soils. (a) Okarito A horizon; (b) Te Kopuru Bh horizon. Spectra were obtained at rotor speeds of 3.5 to 4 kHz. This is sufficient to remove chemical shift anisotropy. Between 30 K and 40 K scans were collected. Signals designated* are artefacts from rotor. Contact time was 1mS.    Aliphatic alkyl carbon bonded to the other carbon atoms can be resolved at chemical shifts (b ) less than 50 ppm. Aliphatic carbon bonded to oxygen atoms can be recognised at chemical shifts between 50-105 ppm, and aromatic and carboxyl carbons are present at chemical shifts &gt;105 ppm. The line widths of individual 13C resonances in solids are of the order of 10-200 ppm and are unsymmetrical when magic angle spinning is not employed. Consequently, there is considerable overlap between signals from various carbon types. Hence the spectra in Fig. 1 are at best only a rough qualitative indication of the various carbon types in soils.  326     Fig. 2 shows the spectra of the organic matter of the same soils with magic angle spinning. Line widths of individual carbon atoms in these spectra are of the order of 1 or 2 ppm. Hence the observed broad signals are due to the large variety of carbon types present and not due to chemical shift anisotropy. Clearly, the spectra show considerable detail concerning the types of carbon in the two soils. Although aromatic, alkyl and o-alkyl types of carbon are not clearly resolved, the spectra show distinct peaks which can be assigned to various carbon types.   The resonance at 16 ppm arises from methyl groups terminal to alkyl chains and also, in part, from material used as rotor. The resonances between 29 and 32 ppm arise from carbons in methylene chains and confirm that polymethylene is an important component of soils (Grant, 1977).   In the two examples shown here, however, methylene chains appear to be a more important component of the Okarito A horizon than the Te Kopuru Bh horizon.   There are a number of other important differences between the spectra of the two soils. Clearly the signal at 73-74 ppm is more predominant in the Okarito soil than in the Te Koparu soil. The peak at 103-104 PpJ.IJL :Z present in the Ojkarito soil but absent or hidden by the envelope in the Te Kopuru soil. These two signals arise from mono-oxygenated and di-oxygenarted alkyl carbon of polysaccharides (Stothers, 1972). Hence the data demonstrate that the amounts of polysaccharides are much greater in the Okarito sample than the Te Kopuru sample.   The '3C-n.m.r. spectrum of the organic matter of Okarito soil is of particular interest because humification in this soil may be slow because of the wet conditions. (Goh et al., 1981). The molecular weight distributions of the extractable organic matter in this soil are bi-modal, consisting of a large proportion (75%) of large molecules (&gt; 200,000 MW) and a smaller proportion (25%) of small molecules (&lt; 10,000 MW). Because humification is expected to produce a Gaussian distribution of molecular weights, the results suggest that humification is slow. The '3C-n.m.r. data presented in this paper supports this hypothesis. Large amounts of polysaccharides indicate that breakdown of cellulose material is incomplete.   The spectra from both soil samples contain resonances at about 180 ppm which can be assigned to artifacts from rotor material (polymethylmethacrylate). Thus, it is impossible to comment on the carboxyl content of the two sails. Quantitative estimations of aromaticity (fraction of aromatic carbon) of the two soils are also not possible because aromatic and aliphatic signals may be enhanced to a different extent by the cross polarisation process and because of the unknown contribution of spinning side bands. Our results do show, however, that the organic matter in both Te Kopuru and Okarito soils have somewhat similar aromaticities. The proportion of signal ascribed to aromatic carbon (105-160 ppm) is similar in the two soils (21% of the signal from Okarito and 25% 1f the signal from Te Kopuru). This suggests that both Okarito and Te Kopuru soils contain much more  327    aromatic carbon than the highly aliphatic Maungatua soil (Baryon and  Wilson, 1981).    REFERENCES    Baryon, P.F. and Wilson, M.A., 1981. Humic soil and coa:t structure study with magic-angle spinning '3C CP-N.M.R. Nature, 289: 275-276.  Baryon, P.F., Wilson, M.A., Stephe-as, J.F., Cornell, B.A. and Tate, Ii.R., 1980. Cross polarisation "C-n.m.r. spectroscopy of whole soils. Nature, 286: 585-587.  Goh, K.M. and Williams, 11!R., 1979. Changes in molecular weight distribution of soil organic matter during soil development. J. Soil Sci., 30: 747-755.  Goh, K.M., Williams, M.R. and Wilson, M.A., 1981. Chemical nature of organic matter in a New Zealand Spodosal as revealed by gel filtration chromatography chemical and "C N.M.R. spectroscopic analysis. Soils with Variable Charge Conference, Massey University, New Zealand, Programme and Abstracts, pp. 88-89.  Grant, D., 1977. Chemical structure of humic substances. Nature, 270: 709-710.  Ogner, G., 1979. The ("C) nuclear magnetic resonance spectrum of a methylated humic acid. Soil Biol. Biochem., 11: 105-108.  Stotlaers, J.B., 1972. Carbon-13 NMR Spectroscopy. Academic Press, New York, N.Y.  Vila, F.J., Lentz, H., Ludemann, H., 1976. F.T.-C13 nuclear magnetic resonance spectra of natural humic substances. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Comm., 72: 1063-1069.  Wilson, M.A., 1981. Application of N.M.R. spectroscopy to the study of soil organic matter. J. Soil Sci., 32: 167-186.  Wilson, M.A., Barron, P.F. and Goh, K.M., 1981. Cross polarisation "3C-N.M.R. spectroscopy of some genetically related New Zealand soils. J. Soil Sci. In press.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractSpectra of two whole soils have been recorded by cross polarisation n.m.r. spectroscopy with magic angle spinning. Magic angle spinning allows detailed structural comparisons between the types of organic carbon in whole soils to be made. Sufficient resolution is achieved to show that the two soils differ considerably in polysaccharide content.