Geoderma, 33 (1984) 1--12                                                           1  Elsevier Science Publishers, B V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    EFFECTS OF SURFACE MANAGEMENT ON RUNOFF AND SOIL  EROSION FROM SOME PLOTS AT MLINGANO, TANZANIA    E_L.N NGATUNGAx, R. LAL~ and A.P URIYO:  J National Sod Servzce, Mlingano, Tanga (Tanzania)   Internatzonal Institute of Tropzcal Agrtculture, lbadan (NIgerza)  (Received March 22, 1983, revised version accepted September 14, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Ngatunga, E,L.N., Lal, R. and Urwo, A.A, 1984. Effects of surface management on  runoff and soil erosion from some plots at Mingano, Tanzania. Geoderma, 33. 1--12    Effects of four soil management treatments on runoff and erosion were investigated  for a Rhodic Ferralsol using 10m 2m runoff plots estabhshed on natural slopes of 10,  19 and 22% at Mhngano, Tanzama. The soil management treatments studied were bare  fallow, plowing, straw mulch at 6 ton/ha and natural grass cover. The annual soil loss  respectively for 10, 19 and 22% slopes was 37.8, 92.8 and 88.2 ton ha-' for bare fallow,  13.6, 37.9 and 23.5 ton ha-1 for plowed, 0.12, 0.19 and 0 18 ton/ha for mulched, and  0 08, 0.14 and 0.10 ton ha-1 for grass cover treatments. The soil erodibility factor (K)  computed from the annual soil loss was 0.160, 0 153 and 0.121 for soils of 10, 19 and  22% slopes, respectively. The K factors estimated from the nomogram were 0.09, 0.085  and 0.110, respectively. Out of the 793 mm of rains received, the annual runoff loss,  respechvely, for 10, 19 and 22% slope was 11 9, 15.4 and 13.0% for bare fallow, 5.5,  7.4 and 5.1% for plowed; 0.7, 0.7 and 0.5% for mulched, and 0.2, 0.4 and 0.3% for  grass cover treatment.    INTRODUCTION    The objective of this report is to describe the effects of four surface  management treatments on runoff and erosion for a soil at Mlingano, Tan-  zania, and to relate erosion to soil propertms and rainfall characteristms.  An attempt is also made to evaluate the soil erodlbllity factor (K) and to  relate erosion hazard to a range of erod~bility indices. This research informa-  tion is important for the region because the soils on the slopes of the Usam-  bara Mountains m Tanzania are highly susceptible to erosion (Watson, 1973;  T.W.M.P., 1976). Yet httle research reformation is available regarding  properties that influence soil erosion and on management practmes to com-  bat it.  The inherent susceptiblhty of a soil to water erosion, expressed as factor  K m the Universal Soil Loss Equation (Wischmemr and Smith, 1965), is  defined as the average annual soil loss (A) in short tons per acre per umt of    0016-7061/84/$03 00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B V    eroslvlty factor R (Enghsh unit). Soft erodlblhty (K) can be determmed-  (1) directly by field measurements under natural rainfall using the "unit  plot" techmque (Wischmemr and Smith, 1961); (2) by rainfall mmulator  (Meyer and McCune, 1958); or (3) by estlmaUon from soil properties using  a nomograph (Wischmemr and Mannermg, 1969; Wlschmeier et al., 1971).  In tropmal Afmca a few studies have been conducted on the relation be-  tween erodibfllty and soft propert,es under different systems of management  (Lal, 1976; Roose, 1977). Furthermore, few attempts have been made m  the tropms to evaluate the apphcabfilty of the nomogram m estimating  soft erodlbillty.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The study was conducted at the Mmgano Agmcultural Research InsUtute  whmh m located at 510'S 3952'E and has an elevation of 180 m above  sea level. The Institute is mtuated m the foothills of the Usambara Mountain  Range and the countryside within a few kilometres of the station is dmsected  by shallow valleys whmh are on the average about 30 m deep. The edges of  the valleys are mostly gently slopmg and are therefore cultivated. The crops  grown are sisal, bananas, maize, beans and upland rice in the valley bottoms  The predommant chmate is savanna (KSppen, 1931), with slight annual  fluctuations m ambmnt temperature and relative humidity. The mean  annual rainfall is about 1150 mm, with biomodal distribution. The short  rainy season (Vuli) lasts from September to December and the long rains  (Masika) from March to June. The Vuli rains are assocmted with the north-  eastern monsoon winds and the Masika rains with the cool southeast mon-  soon. The soils of Mhngano area have been derived from basement complex  rocks,  metamorphics including gramte--gnelss--schists complexes. Their  major minerals are feldspars, b,otlte, hornblende, garnet and quartz (Mllne,  1937).  The soils at the experimental sites were classified as Rhodm Ferralsol  according to the FAO--Unesco Soil Map of the World (1977). These soils  are deep (&lt; 2 m), well drained and dusky red to red, are fmable and have  sandy clay loams texture m the surface layer. The clay fraction is dominated  by kaolinite and sesquioxldes (Srivastava, 1976). On the valley slopes the  soils are Chromic and Fermc Luvmols. These soils are shallow, well drained  and free textured and have friable conmstency. The softs in the valley bot-  toms and depressions are Gleym Luvisols. They are shallow sandy clays,  with a friable consistency and a weak subangular blocky structure (FAO/  Unesco, 1977).    Plot mstallatmn    Runoff plots (10 m 2 m) were established at three rotes with natural  slopes of 10, 19 and 22% in September 1979 before the onset of the short    rains. Each site had eight runoff plots. The plots were first cleared of natural  vegetation, then hoed, harrowed and finally raked to provide a fine tilth.  Plots were kept free of weeds and any other vegetation. After plot demarca-  tion and tillage, each of the plots was enclosed by corrugated iron sheets.  These sheets acted as retaming walls, preventing runon from entering the  plot while permitting runoff to be dramed through an outlet located near  the downstream end of the plot. Toward the ends of the plots, the sheets  were attached to troughs that diverted runoff and soil sediment into storage  tanks installed at those lower ends.  The following four surface management treatments were rephcated  twice.  (1) Bare fallow: these plots were plowed, harrowed, frequently raked  and kept free of weeds or vegetation cover. The soil loss data from these  plots was used to compute the erodlblhty factor K.  (2) Straw mulch: After plowing and harrowing, these plots received  straw mulch at 6 ton ha-1. The mulch was apphed twine per year.  (3) Plowed plots: These plots were plowed rough up and down the slope,  and the surface was left cloddy without harrowing or any secondary tillage  operations.  (4) Grass cover: These were control plots left undisturbed under natural  grass cover.    Determination of soil loss    After each erosive ramstorm, the volume of runoff and sediment that  had collected in the storage drums was determined by means of a precalibrat-  ed measurmg rod. After the volume was recorded, the contents of the drums  were thoroughly stirred, and a 1-1itre sample taken to determine sediment  density and for chemical analysis. Sediment density was determined by  filtering through Whatman No. 1 filter paper. Sediments on the filter paper  were oven-dried at 105C.    Determination of soil physical properties    A 200-g sample of dry soil aggregates, obtained from each plot before the  experiment, was used for wet sieving with a nest of sieves of 4, 3.5, 3.0 and  2.5 mm. Coarse gravel &gt; 2 mm was expressed as gravel content on percent-  age by weight. Partmle size distribution was determined by the pipette  method {Day, 1965).  The followmg structural mdmes were also computed.  % (silt + clay) untreated samples (Middleton,  (1) Dispersion ratio (DR) as:  % (silt + clay) treated samples        1930).  % sand  (2) Clay ratio (CR) as:                (Bouyoucos, 1935).  % (silt + clay)    dispersion ratio  (3) Erosion ratio (ER) as:  colloidal content/moisture equivalent'  where colloidal content is the sum of the percentage of organic matter +  clay and moisture equivalent is moisture content held at 0.3 bar suction.  Mlddleton (1930) combined the colloid content/moisture equivalent ratio  with the dispersion ratio and considered this index to be an accurate measure  of soil erodiblhty. For this ratio a value of 10 was thought to be a significant  boundary between "erodlble" and "non-erodible" softs.  (4) M-Parameter as a product of percentage of silt + very fine sand times  percentage of silt + very fine sand + sand &gt; 0.1 ram. Wischmemr and Smith  (1978) reported that where the silt fraction does not exceed 70% erodiblh-  ty varies approximately as the 1.14th power of the silt content.  The rainfall charts of a daffy recording raingage were analyzed to compute  the eroslvlty factor R for the period between August 1979 and July 1980.  The rainfall erosivlty factor R was computed according to three indices:  EI3o (Wlschmeler et al., 1958), Aim {Lal, 1976) and KE &gt; 1 (Hudson, 1971)  These indices were computed as follows'  (1) EI3o index is a compound factor and is obtained as a product of the  kinetic energy of the storm (E) and the 30-minute intensity (I30).  (2) KE &gt; I index is a summation of the kinetic energy of individual  storms falling at intensities oxceeding 25 mm h-1  (3) Aim index is a product of rainfall amount (A) in cm with the maxi-  mum intensity (Ira) in cm h '  Regression equations were developed that related soil erosion and runoff  with the three erosivlty indices.    RESULTS    Ram fall eroswtty    Erosive rains occur at Mhngano primarily during October--November m  the Vuli season and during April--May in the Masika season. A total of 793  mm of rain were received during the year of the study, which is about  30% less than the long-term average. In the Vuli season 515 mm were receiv-  ed and in the Maslka season 278 mm. The erosivity indices computed for 16  erosive rainstorms are shown m Table I. The erosivity index Aim was sig-  nificantly correlated with EI3o (r = 0.83**) and KE &gt; 1 (r = 0.84"*~.    So,l eroston    The effects of surface management treatments on soil loss for individual  rainy seasons and as an annual total are shown in Table II. The annual soil  loss was greatest from the bare fallow plots and least from the natural grass-  cover treatments. Soil loss from the mulched plots was equivalent to that    TABLE I  Characteristms of sixteen erosive rainstorms at Mlingano during the study period    Date         Amount    Eroslvlty index  (cm)    EI3o/100              AIm/lO0     KE &gt; 1  (m ton-meter ha-1)     (cm2 hr-1)     (m ton ha-~ cm-~)    17 10 79      3.60        11.08                   12.96         7 75  21  10.79            3  38                16.02                                         7  10                --  8 11.79      3.80        26_17                   11.21          8 87  10.11  79            3  55                  6  51                                         5  34                --  11 11 79      1.50        11 91                    7 20         3 97  29 12 79      1.07         5 65                    2.70          2 64  24 1 80       2 15        20 66                    7 93          5.60  25.1_80               1  30                   2.46                                         1  24                --  30,1 80       4 45        48 99                   19.22        11 34  28280               1  80                  079                                         540                   395  10 4.80               1  80                24  38                                         9.18                   4  78  18.4.80       1 25         7 70                    3 60          3.08  25 4  80               4 00                23  90                                      16.00                   8.85  29 4.80               3  10                49.07                                      17  98                   8.46  10 5.80       3.37        12 76                    8_09        --  15 5 80       2 50         3 53                   10 50         5 89    Total        42 62      271.6                  145 7         75 2    TABLE II  Effects of surface treatments on soil loss (ton ha-1)    Season            Slope (%)    Soll loss due to different treatments    bare      mulched     plowed  fallow    grass  cover    (a) Vuh    (b) Masika    Annual soil loss    10                       10.1             0 04                      3 9                0.03  19           26.1      0.06          8 3        0 04  22           21.2      0.08           7.8        0 04    10                       27.8             0 08                      9  7                0.05  19                       66.7             0  11                   29.6                0  10  22           62.9      0.10         15.7        0.06    10           37 8      0.12         13 6        0.08  19           92.8      0.19         37.9        0.14  22                       88.2             0.18                   23.5                0.10    ,&lt;    "0  o  ,-C  o  o  C  0       o  0J  0  "0  C  ~0  o  o    0    0J    oooo   oooo      ooo    ~0~0    00~0    ~0~0  III      I      ~1      I'll    ~0~0  ~0~0  oooo    .*~.  ~0  d6od    c0 ~:t~ 0  coO0~  ~oo    000    0   ~0~0     Nooo    *~ ~  0     0000    ~0~0    ~0~0    ~0~0  ~0~0    ~000    ~0~0  II      I      111[      Irl,    ~0~0  ~0~0  0000    0000    oooo    lirl    0000    III    o    0b    Irl    Ol    from the grass-cover treatment, indmating that a mulch rate of 6 ton ha-1  can provide effective erosion control even on steep slopes of up to 22%. The  cloddy surface of the plowed treatment decreased soil loss by 64, 59 and  73%, compared with the bare fallow treatment involving plowing, harrowing  and frequent raking.  The soil loss caused by the ninth storm, which occurred on 30 January  1980, ranged from 8.3 to 22.1 ton ha-1 m the bare-fallow treatment, from  0.03 to 0 05 ton ha-~ in the mulched treatment, from 3.4 to 7.5 ton ha-~ m  plowed plots and from 0.02 to 0.03 ton ha-1 m the grass-cover treatment.  Correlation coeffmients and regression equations relating soil loss per  storm to different erosivlty indices are shown in Table III. The correlation  coefficients of the soil loss from the natural grasscover treatment for any of  the erosivlty mdices were either low or not significant. The soil losses from  the other treatments were significantly correlated with the EI3o and AIm  indices and to a lesser extent with the KE &gt; 1 index.    So~l erodibtltty    The soil erodlbflity factor K, computed as a ratio of the annual soil loss  from the bare plot to the annual EI3o index, was 0.160, 0.153 and 0.121 for  soils of 10, 19 and 22% slopes, respectively. The soil erodibihty factor  computed from the nomogram was 0.09, 0.085 and 0.110, respectively.  The K factor estimated by nomogram was lower than the field value by  44, 45, and 9% for soils of 10, 19 and 22%, respectively.  The soil characteristics that usually affect erodlbility are shown m Table  IV. The correlation and regression analyses of these soil characteristics  with the field measured erodtbility factor K shown in Table V indicate  that there Was a significant negative correlation between erodibllity and the  percentage of water-stable aggregates (&gt; 4 mm) and a positive one between  dispersion ratio and erosion ratio.  Erodibility computed on bare plots is indicattve of the maximum or the  potential erosion hazard for the soil. Soil conservation planning is, therefore,  done in relation to this maxnnum risk. With normal cultivation, however,  the soil is partly covered and the erosion hazard is less than under bare fal-  low. The effectiveness of a measure for erosion control is judged in terms  of the ratio of soil loss from a cultivated to a bare fallow plot.    Water runoff    Data on the effect of surface management on water runoff in soils of  different slopes are shown in Table VI. These data indicate that the annual  runoff was greater on the bare plots than on the plowed, mulch and grass-  cover treatments, in that order. The relative mean annual runoff for the  treatments m the same order was 100, 46, 6 and 2 on a soil of 10% slope;  100, 48, 4 and 2 on one of 19% ; and 100, 39, 3 and 2 for plots with 22%    TABLE IV  Physical and chemical properttes of composite samples of surface 0--15 cm layers from  runoff plots at three locations    Soil property                              Slope    10%         19%        22%    Organic carbon (%)                          2_3          2 6          2 4  Total bases (meqmv/100 g)                 7 0          6 8          8 5  Bulk density (g cm-3)                        1 1           1 2          1 l  Water stable aggregates "  4 mm (%)        23.1         16 2         31 2  Water stable aggregates 2.5--4 mm (%)     10 1         11.6         12 6  Gravel content (%)                           0.5          1 5         17_7  Dry staving aggregates ,. 4 mm (%)         65 1         50 9         60 2  Silt (%)                               13.2        10 8        14.3  Sand (%)                                36 4        44 8        42 4  Clay (%)                           50.0       43 8       42 3  Dispersion ratio                              0 95         0 99         1 I 1  Clay ratio                                    0 58         0 82         0.75  Erosion ratio                                 0 49         0 58         0.62  Silt + very fine sand (%)                    16 8         15 5         19_7  M factor                                   841.8        896.1      1137_1    TABLE V  Simple correlatton and regression equations relating erodibihty with soil propertms    Independent  parameter    Regression equation    slope       intercept    correlation  (m)        (b)           coefflcmnt  (r)    Water stable aggregates  "-- 4 mm (%)             0 021     +0 392      -0 98**  Clay content (%)           0.006    -0.129       0_91  Gravel content (%)          0 003     +0 167        0 93  Dispersion ratio            -0.326     +0 481        0.98**  Erosion ratio              --0.395     +0.372        0.95*  M parameter               -0.0002    +0 311        0.94    slope, respectively. The maximum runoff was observed m the plots of 19%  slope. There was more runoff loss during Masika than Vuh rains, although  the amount of ramfall received m the Maslka season was only 54% of that  received m the Vuh season. With continuous cultivation, however, runoff  and soil erosion may increase due to degradation of soil structure.  The runoff loss from bare, mulched and grass-cover treatments was s~g-  nificantly correlated with all three eroslvity indices, although the correlation  coeffmmnt with the KE ~ 1 mdex was low (Table VII). The runoff from  the plowed treatments was not correlated with any of the erosivity mdmes,    TABLE VI  Effect of surface management on runoff    Season    Slope     Bare  %    Mulched         Plowed         Grass cover    mm of            mm of           rnm of         mm of  water     %       water    %     water   %     water   %    Vuh    Maslka    Annual    10                   96               36         0.7               0.2            3.9            1.2      0.7            03  19                 108               6.3         1.2               05            3.8            14      0.8            03  22        15.1       5.7     0.8       03      3.6      14   06      0.2    10                41.0             25.6          2.1                1.3         20.2          12  6      0.3            0  2  19                48.9             30 5          1.7                1.1         27  9          17  4      0  7            0.4  22        40.2      25.6    1.1       0.7    18 0     11.3   0.5      0 3    10                 50.6             11  9          2 8               0 7         23.3            5  5       1.0            0.2  19                 65  7             15.4          2.9               0.7         31.6            7  4      1  5            0.4  22        55 2      13.0     1 9       0.5    21.6      5 1   1 1      0_3    probably because of the high surface detention capacity and rough soil  surface. Soil loss and water runoff were significantly and positively correlat-  ed with one another (Table VIII). Once again, the correlahon coeffmmnts  were generally low for the plowed treatments for all three slopes studied.  Soll loss per unit of runoff was generally greater for bare and plowed  plots than for mulch and grass-cover treatments. In the bare treatment the  soil loss: runoff raho was also higher for the 19 and 22% than for the 10%  slope.    GENERAL DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION    Both runoff and erosion were effectively controlled by mulching and  grass cover. The C factor, computed as a ratio of the runoff or soil loss  from these treatments with that from bare plots, is shown in Table IX. It  is apparent that soil erosion from mulched plots was 250 to 500 times less  and runoff 14 to 36 times less than that from the bare treatment. Similarly,  the soil erosion from grass-cover plots was 330 to 1000 times less and the  runoff 14 to 167 times less than that from the bare treatment. Even the  rough and cloddy soil surface decreased the soil loss from 2.5 to 4 times  and the runoff from 1.8 to 4.5 times, compared to the bare treatment.  There are some agronomic implications of these results. If these steep  lands must be used for cultivating arable crops, then the agronomic prac-  trees of mulching, and frequent use of grass cover in crop rotations should  be advocated to conserve soil and water.  The nomogram underestimates the erodlbility of Mlingano softs. Ap-  propriate modifications are necessary before it can be recommended for  these soils. Antecedent soil moisture content, slaking and crusting, and Fe    "0  0  0  e~  e~  &gt;   .~    o    [..,    0000  0000   0000  t    Mdoo  oooo  oooo  +l+t  +1   +l+t    0~00   0000   ~000    ddd~  dd~d  dooo    0~00  0000    0~00  0000   0000    m..~.~O.    ~..0.~.~.    ~O.m.o.    0~00  0000   00~0    TABLE VIII  Correlation and regression equations relating soil loss (Y) with runoff (X)    11    Slope     Treatment    Regression equation  (%)    m       b           r    10    19    22    Bare           0 855   -0.336     0.82**  Mulched      0 043   +0.000     0 95**  Plowed       0 531   +0.075     0.76**  Grass cover   0 067   +0.001     0.71"*    Bare           1.127   -1.293     0.93**  Mulched      0.051   +0.002     0 85**  Plowed        1.084   +0.230     0.72**  Grass cover   0 108   -0.001     0.91"*    Bare           1.749   -0.524     0.87**  Mulched      0.090   +0.0005   0 93**  Plowed       0.647   +0.596     0 49*  Grass cover   0.096   -0.001     0.95**    TABLE IX  C factors for runoff and soil loss  Season  Slope   Treatments  (~)  mulched            plowed             grass cover    soil     runoff     soil     runoff     soil     runoff    Vuli    Masika    Annum    10      0.004   0.068      0.389   0.324      0.003   0.072  19             0.002       0.074             0.319       0 223             0.002       0.046  22              0.004       0.053             0.369       0.239             0.002       0.043    10      0.003   0 052      0.348   0.492      0.002   0.006  19             0.002       0.036             0.443       0.570             0.001       0.014  22      0.002   0.028      0 249   0.449      0.001   0.013    10      0.003   0.055      0.359   0.460      0 002   0.019  19      0.002   0.045      0.408   0.481      0 002   0.023  22      0.002   0.035      0.266   0.392      0.001   0.021    and A1 contents are some of the soil characteristics that should be considered  in evaluating the K factor from a nomogram.  ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS  The authors would like to acknowledge with thanks financial assistance  received during this study from the International Institute of Tropical    12    Agrmulture, Ibadan, the Research and Publications Committee of the Univer-  sity of Dares Salaam and the Ministry of Agrmulture, the United Repubhc  of Tanzania.    REFERENCES    Anonymous, 1980  Preliminary SOIl Survey Report for Mlingano  Sod Survey Section  National Soil Service, Agric. Res  Institute Mlingano. Ministry of Agriculture, Dar  Es Salaam  Bouyoucos, C.J_, 1935 The clay ratio as a cntermm of susceptibility of soils to erosion  JA. Soc Agron., 27:738--741  Day, P R , 1965. Particle fractionation and particle size analysis  In  C A  Black et al  (Editors), Methods of Soil Analysis, Agron Monogr  9, Am. Soc. Agron, Madison,  Wlsc., pp. 545--566.  FAO--Unesco, 1977  Soil Map of the World, Vol  VI, Afrma Unesco, Paris, 229 pp_  Hudson, N W, 1971 Sod Conservatlon, Batsford, London  Koppen, W , 1931. Outline of Climatology. Walter de Gruyter, Berhn, 2nd ed  Lal, R., 1976 Soil Erosion Problems on an Alfisol m Western Nigeria and Their Control  Monograph No 1, I.I.T A , Ibadan.  Meyer, L D. and McCune, D L, 1958. Rainfall simulator for runoff plots. Agric Eng ,  39:644--648  Middleton, H F , 1930. Properties of soil whmh influence erosion U.S D.A. Tech Bull ,  No. 178  Milne, G,, 1937  Sod type and sod management in relation to plantation agrmulture m  East Usambara. E Afr. Agric For J , 3 7--10.  Roose, E J, 1977  Use of the Umversal SOd Loss Equation to predict erosion m West  Africa  In  Anonymous, Soil erosion- Prediction and control  SOIl Cons  SOc_ Am  Spec Publ , 31 60--74.  Srivastava, N.C , 1976  Soils of Tanzania A Revision of Soil Survey Work 1928--1976  Ministry of Agriculture, Dar es Salaam  Tanga Water Master Plan (T W.M.P ), 1976  Vol. IV, Soils. Published jointly by the  German Agency for Technmal Cooperation and the Ministry of Water, Energy and  Minerals, Dares Salaam.  Watson, R., 1973. Conservation problems, pohcies and origins of the Mlalo Basin Re-  hablhtation Scheme, Usambara Mountains, Tanzania. In  A. Rapp et al. (Editors),  Soil Erosion and Sedimentation in Tanzania. Res Monogr. No. 1, BRALUP, University  of Dar Es Salaam, pp. 22--227  Wlschmeier, W.H and Smith, D.D. 1961. A universal soft loss estimating equation to  guide conservation farm planning. Trans., Congr Int. Soil Sol. Soc., 7th, 1 418--425  Wlschmemr, H.W. and Smith, D D., 1965 Predicting rainfall eromon losses from crop-  land east of the Rocky Mountains. Agric Handbook No. 282, U S D.A , Washington,  D.C, 47 pp.  Wlschmeier, W.H and Mannering, J V., 1969. Relation of soil properties to its erodibflity.  Soil Sci Soe. Am. Proc . 33 131--137  Wischmeier, W.H. and Smith, D.D., 1978 Predicting rainfall erosmn losses. A guide to  conservatmn planning Agric. Handbook No. 537, U.S.D.A., Washington, D C  Wischmemr, W H, Smith, D.D and Uhland, R.E , 1958. Evaluation of factors in the soft  loss equation Agrm. Eng., 39. 458--462.  Wlschmeier, W.H, Johnson, C.B and Cross, B.V., 1971. A soft erodibility monograph for  farm land and construction sites J Soil Water Conserv , 26 189--193.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractEffects of four soil management treatments on runoff and erosion were investigated for a Rhodic Ferralsol using 10m × 2m runoff plots established on natural slopes of 10, 19 and 22% at Mlingano, Tanzania. The soil management treatments studied were bare fallow, plowing, straw mulch at 6 ton/ha and natural grass cover. The annual soil loss respectively for 10, 19 and 22% slopes was 37.8, 92.8 and 88.2 ton ha−1 for bare fallow; 13.6, 37.9 and 23.5 ton ha−1 for plowed; 0.12, 0.19 and 0.18 ton/ha for mulched; and 0.08, 0.14 and 0.10 ton ha−1 for grass cover treatments. The soil erodibility factor (K) computed from the annual soil loss was 0.160, 0.153 and 0.121 for soils of 10, 19 and 22% slopes, respectively. The K factors estimated from the nomogram were 0.09, 0.085 and 0.110, respectively. Out of the 793 mm of rains received, the annual runoff loss, respectively, for 10, 19 and 22% slope was 11.9, 15.4 and 13.0% for bare fallow; 5.5, 7.4 and 5.1% for plowed; 0.7, 0.7 and 0.5% for mulched; and 0.2, 0.4 and 0.3% for grass cover treatment.