359    CONTENTS VOLUME 33, 1984    Effects of surface management on runoff and soil erosion from some plots at  Mlingano, Tanzania  E.L.N. Ngatunga (Tanga, Tanzania), R. Lal and A.P. Uriyo (Ibadan, Nigeria)  ......  1  The nature and origin of aeolian mantles of central northern Nigeria  G. McTainsh (Brisbane, Qld., Australia)  ..............................  13  Estimating relative ages from iron-oxide/total-iron ratios of soils in the western  Po Valley  E. Arduino, E. Barberis, F. Carrazo and M.G. Forno (Torino, Italy)  ............  39  Amounts and forms of micronutrient cations in a group of loessial grassland soils  of New Zealand  R.J. Haynes and R.S. Swift (Canterbury, New Zealand)  ...................  53  Characteristics of soils of a toposequence in northeastern Iraq  M.S. Hussain, T.H. Amadi and M.S. Sulaiman (Sulaimania, I.raq)  ..............  63  Book Reviews  Handbook on Soil Resistivity Surveying -- Interpretation of Data of Earthen  Archaeological Sites, by C. Cart -- M.A. Keech  .........................  83  Principles of Soil Chemistry, by Kim H. Tan -- M.G.M. Bruggenwert  .............  83  Cyclic and Event Stratification, by G. Einsele and A. Seiiacher (Editors) --  L. Calembert  ...............................................  85  Soil Erosion, by D. Zacher -- S. Judson  ................................  85  Aridic Soils of Israel: Properties, Genesis and Management, by J. Dan, R. Gerson,  H. Koyumdjisky and D.H. Yaalon -- A. Singer  .........................  86  Books and Bulletins Received  ......................................  88    Soil formation as affected by pit and mound microrelief in Massachussetts, U.S.A.  P.L.M. Veneman, P.V. Jacke and S.M. Bodine (Amherst, Mass., U.S.A.)  .........  89  Effects of acidic and basic parent materials on formation of some soils in Quebec  (Canada)  C.R. de Kimpe, M.R. Laverdi~re (Sainte-Foy, Que., Canada), J. Dejou  (Clermont-Ferrand, France) and P. Lasalle (Sainte-Foy, Que., Canada)  ........  101  Evaluation of phosphorus sorption by an allophanic soil  J. Ifiiguez and R.Ma Val (Pamplona, Spain)  ..........................  119  Nature, formation and effects of soil crusts formed by water drop impact  J. Tarchitzky, A. Banin, J. Morin and Y. Chen (Rehovot, Israel)  .............  135  Extraction of silver from soils and its determination by atomic absorption  spectrometry  K.C. Jones, P.J. Peterson (London, U.K.) and B.E. Davies (Aberystwytb,  Wales, U.K.)  ...............................................  157  Book Review  Cycling of Carbon, Nitrogen, Sulfur and Phosphorus in Terrestrial and Aquatic  Ecosystems, by J.R. Freney and I.E. Galbally (Editors) -- R.T. Heath  .........  169    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  171  Effects of slope length on erosion of some Alfisols in western Nigeria  R. Lal (Ibadan, Nigeria)  .......................................  181  Quantitative relationships between morphology and current soil hydrology  in some All'tools in semiarid tropical Australia  R.J. Coventry and J. Williams (Townsville, Qld., Australia)  ................  191  Classification of five pedons near Afgoi, Somalia  D.L. Mokma and O.H.D. AbduUa (East Lansing, Mich., U.S.A.)  .............  219    360    Verdichtung von Proben eines Dystrandepts und Palehumults aus S~dchile  (Compaction of samples of a Dystrandept and a Palehumult from Southern  Chile)  A. Ellies und J. Gayoso (Valdivia, Chile)  ............................  227  Intrapedal cutans -- Experimental production of depositional (illuviation)  channel argillans  J.B. Dalrymple and S.P. Theocharopoulos (Reading, Great Britain)  ...........  237  Effects of variations in contact times and copper contents in a 13C CPMAS NMR  study of samples of four organic soils  C.M. Preston (Ottawa, Ont., Canada), R.L. Dudley, C.A. Fyfe (Guelph, Ont.,  Canada) and S.P. Mathur (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  .......................  245  Book Reviews  Fundamentals of Soil Mechanics, by B.M. Das -- J.L. Chameau  ...............  255  Dictionary of Geotectonics, by S.H. Somerville and M.A. Paul -- M.E. Popeseu  .....  256  Dictionary of Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering, by J.A. Barker --  M.E. Popescu  ..............................................  256  Constituents and Properties of Soils, by M. Bonneau and B. Souchier (Editors)  --D. Dent  ................................................  257    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  259  A preliminary length factor for erosion on steep slopes in Guatemala and its use  to evaluate "curvas a nivel"  M. Akeson and M.J. Singer (Davis, Calif., U.S.A.)  ......................  265  Relationships between phosphate sorption and iron oxides in Alfisols from a  river terrace sequence of Mediterranean Spain  F. Pefia and J. Torrent (C6rdoba, Spain)  ............................  283  Aluminum speciation and equilibria in soil solutions of a Haplorthod in the  Adirondack Mountains ( New York, U.S.A.)  M.B. David and C.TDriscoli (Syracuse, N.Y., U.S.A.)  ...................  297  Mineralogy of clay fractions of some soils on loess in northern France  J. Jamagne (Olivet, France), F. de Coninck (Ghent, Belgium), M. Robert  (Versailles, France) and J. Maucorps (Laon, France)  .....................  319  Book Reviews  Temperate Deserts and Semi-Deserts, by N.E. West (Editor) -- H. Lieth  ..........  343  Soil Micromorphology, 1. Techniques and Applications; 2. Soil Genesis, by  P. Bullock and C.P. Murphy (Editors) -- S. Pawluk  ......................  344  Principles and Applications of Soil Geography, by E.M. Bridges and D.A.  Davidson (Editors) --T.H. Cooper  ................................  346    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  349                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               