Geoderma, 30 (1983) 253--270                                                    253  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V. Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SEM-EDXRA STUDIES OF PRECIPITATES WHICH CLOGGED A  WATER-TUBE FILTER    E B.A. BISDOM and A. JONGERIUS  Netherlands Sod Survey lnstitue, P 0 Box 98, 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bisdom, E.B.A. and Jongerius, A., 1983. SEM-EDXRA studies of precipitates which  clogged a water-tube filter. Geoderma, 30:253--270    Light microscopic, submicroscopic and XRD (X-ray diffraction) analyses were done  of precipitates whmh had clogged a water-tube filter. Several zones, mostly consisting  of amorphous and poorly crystalline materials, could be distinguished. SEM-EDXRA  (scanning electron microscopy -- energy dispersive X-ray analysis) indicated that sulphur,  copper, iron and zinc were usually represented and that calcium was less common. Light  microscopy and XRD indicated the presence of calcite and gypsum.  Corrosion of copper filter segments could be demonstrated by flakes which peeled  off, small fragments adjacent to the segments, and a jagged appearance of the edges. A  little sulphur was found at the edges of the filter segments together with copper. More  sulphur was present in the flakes whmh, together with copper, formed covellite accord-  ing to XRD analyses. Rather massive precipitates could be deposited on the disintegrat-  ing flakes. Precipitates of younger zones were usually less massive and exhibited a variety  of forms.    INTRODUCTION    Precipitates from the surface of a water-tube filter, (courtesy of the Dune  Water Works, The Hague, The Netherlands) whmh was regularly used be-  tween 1937 and 1951 to raise water from a reservoir, were studied. The core  reached us in 1976 and came from an environment which, according to  available well data, was permanently submerged. The tube and the precipi-  tates were photographed immediately after armval (Fig. 1). Some of the pre-  cipitate was subsequently removed m order to observe the build-up of the  copper filter itself (Fig.2).  The central part of the filter was cleaned thoroughly to show the holes  in the pipe. The original precipitate, which was coloured brownish yellow to  orange-red, is still observable at the top part of the filter. It would seem to  be iron hydroxide when observed with the unaided eye. Between this top  part and the central part of the filter with holes, one can observe that the  entrances to the filter were clogged. The aim of the present study was to in-  vestigate the precipitates and to analyse them.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevmr Scmnce Publishers B.V.    254    Fig.1. Internal and external precipitates on a water-tube filter The precipitates have  clogged the openings of the filter    The first results of submicroscopic studies of these precipitates were  given m a Dutch report (Blsdom and Jongerms, 1979). Part of a paper on  man-made (man-reduced) precipitates also discussed some of the present  work (Blsdom, 1983).    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The materials studied have been partly described above. The following  can be added. The topography of the precipitates on the outside of the tube  was irregular, as was the case with precipitates that were deposited inside  the tube. The thickness could be 1 cm or more and the uppermost parts  of the deposits often formed isolated islands. The outgrowths of precipi-  tates on the external part of the filter could be rather rounded, whereas  similar materials inside the tube were sometimes better crystallized. The  latter often resembled goethite. It was clear, however, that in sltu research    255    Fig.2. A partly cleaned section of the filter is present in the middle of the photo. No  materials were removed from the top part of the tube. Clogged pores can be observed  between the two mentioned parts of the water-tube filter.    of undisturbed samples was necessary to obtain more insight into the com-  position of the precipitates and their relation to the copper filter of the  water tube. This was done in the following way.  Thin sections of the metal filter and the precipitates were prepared,  following the method described by Jongerms and Heintzberger (1975).  Polyester resin was added to the materials to be studied, and thin sections  prepared after the samples had hardened. These thin sections were then  studied with the light microscope. This indicated that considerable isotropic  material was present, i.e. amorphous material and not cubic crystals. Also,  various substances seemed to be only poorly crystallized. XRD analyses  were done (courtesy Dr. Breeuwsma, Netherlands Soil Survey Institute)  and gave, together with light microscopic observations, some idea about  the nature of the crystallized materials in the precipitates.    256    Submmroscopy was applied to study especially the amorphous materials  and also to test crystalline materials for their chemical elements. The in-  strument used was a Jeol-JSM-35C scanning electron microscope with a  backscattered electron detector of the semiconductor type. The SEM was  equipped with an EDAX 9100 system with an ECON windowless detector  for the detection of chemical elements.    RESULTS    General    A schematic drawing was prepared (Fig.3) which gives some idea of the  complexity of precipitates on and between the copper filter segments.  Five areas are indicated, vlz. area a (Fig. 4a) and area b (Fig. 5) m the in-  ternal part of the copper filter segment, areas c (Fig. 6a) and d (Fig. 7)  externally from the segment, and area e (Fig. 8) between the two filter  segments. The quality of the backscattered electron scanning images (BESI)  is often not very high at these lower magnifications. This is partly due to  high amounts of amorphous materials which are often difficult to portray.  The quality of such micrographs can frequently be improved using higher  magnifications, by reduction of the shadowing effects and optimization of  materials contrast in BESI.  Each of the areas a--e in Fig.3 has been subdivided into zones. Area a  had six zones, starting with zone A I nearest to the surface of the copper  filter segment (this segment is absent in the micrographs of areas a and b  because it sprang away during preparation of the thin section), The same  order of zones was maintained in areas b--e, with the zones with the smallest  number nearest to the filter segment (the segment(s) is visible in the micro-  graphs of these areas because they were made from a polished block in which  the copper filter segments remained during the grinding process). Area e  had two filter segments, and zones with smaller numbers were therefore  present twine. The zones with the higher numbers E IV and E V merged  and the precipitates in them finalized the clogging process which occurred  at the entrance of the water-tube filter between two filter segments.    Matertals m areas a--e    All areas were analysed with EDXRA (energy dispersive X-ray analysis}  which can detect chemical elements up to magnifications of 10,000  Fig.3. Schematic croas-section of the water-tube filter. Five areas (a--e) were distingmsh  ed. Each area contained zones in which the chemical elements are indicated. Areas a ant  b were located inside the tube, areas c and d externally, and area e between two filt~  segments in the clogged entrance of the tube. The numbers of figures that are given belo,  have also been indicated behind the areas, e.g. area a (Fig 4)    257    v    5-,  _2C  ~_~  m        m   m    m  i    &gt;-i          I~1  ::1           I~1  IN    ,5 ,5    E  m    ,&lt;&lt;    ~E  ~a    c  ~  ~  _ =- _&gt;  w w w w w  ~ggg~    JJl  &gt;     w w ~ w m    ~  E~  x c  uJ o    i   A  o    o    c c  =  m  E    c c  m  m    E  ~r  _C C  ii   8    2 ,5 ,~    (Blsdom et al., 1975, 1976). Point analyses, whmh allow the detection of  the heavier chemical elements m a spot with a diameter of 1 ~m, and X-ray  images, which give the distribution of the chemical elements in a micrograph  and were of importance for the subdivision of the areas into zones, were    1    IIQ   It~   II,   i8~   i~e    259    Fig.4. Backscattered electron scanning image (BESI) of area a with six zones (a). Circles  in the micrograph indicate how a linear traverse was made using point analyses. Special  attention was given to zone A I adjacent to the copper filter segment -- this segment is  absent because it sprang away during preparation of the thin section. Part of zones A I  to A III of micrograph (a) has been enlarged in (b). X-ray images of S, Ca, Fe, Cu and Zn  (c to g) give the distribution of chemical elements in micrograph (a). Point analyses  (h to n) indicate a variety of chemical elements found in the zones of area a.    made. One relatively complete EDXRA analysis procedure has been included  for area a (Fig.4), but some of the point analyses were omitted. A few re-  marks are given below about each of the zones in the different areas  (cf. Fig.3) and the chemical composition of these zones is discussed.    A rea a  Six zones were recognized in area a (Figs.3 and 4a). Some of the zones  are clearly visible on the micrograph because they are white (Fig.4a). An-  other indication that zones exist is found in the distribution of chemical  elements in the X-ray images (Fig.4, c--g) and in point analyses (Fig.4, h--n).  The observations done with a light microscope were also of importance to  establish zones and to determine the larger minerals.    260    Zone A I (Fig.4a) contained flakes of the copper filter segment (absent  m this mmrograph). Point analyses demonstrated that sulphur, copper,  calcmm and ~ron were present m this zone. The flakes themselves contained  mainly copper and sulphur with some iron. XRD analyses of the materials  close to the surface of the tube indicated that covellite (CuS) was present.  This, and EDXRA measurements of flakes m other areas, suggest that the  flakes consist of covelhte on which iron hydroxide had sometimes precipi-  tated. The calcium could form calcite (CaCO3) and calcmm and sulphur  gypsum (CaSO4.2H20); measurements of oxygen were not done. The pres-  ence of calcite and gypsum, associated with the flakes, was confirmed by  light microscopy.  An enlarged view of part of the zones A I to A III m Fig.4a is given in  Flg.4b. Needle-shaped forms are present m zone AII and contain S, Fe  and Cu. The rather massive material of zone A IlI, which extends into zone  AII, contamed the same elements but more sulphur and less copper occur-  red. The quantity of ~ron was rather small except for a few microareas.  Most of these materials were poorly crystalline to amorphous. No determina-  tion of the compounds present could therefore be made by XRD analysis  SEM-EDXRA analysis could only provide an estimate of the relative quan-  tltms of the heavier chemical elements which were represented in the pre~  cIpitates and flakes. Consequently, no quant~tatwe analyses are given m  this study.  Zone A IV contained calcite which was measurable as calcium by EDXRA  and was determinable by light microscopy. The concentrations of calcium  are indicated well in the X-ray image of Flg.4d Zone A V also contained  sulphur, Iron and copper. One point analysis, however, indmated the replace-  ment of copper by zinc Zone A VI contained no copper and iron was the  principal element  Some sulphur was also represented. Light mmroscopy  and XRD analyses indicated that predominantly poorly crystalhne ~ron  hydroxides were represented m zone A VI    Area b  Five zones were distinguished in area B (Figs.3 and 5). The zones were  less easy to recognize than m area a. This can be illustrated by the rater-  fingering of zones BIII and B V. Zone B IV occurred adjacent to the void  and followed a different direction from that of the other zones  Zone B I includes several flakes of the original filter (absent m this mmro-  graph). The elements zinc and sihcon were added to sulphur, copper, Iron  and calcium found m the zone with flakes (zone A I) of area a. Calcite and  gypsum were also present in zone B I  Zone B II contained the same ele-  ments as in zone B I with the exception of calcium. The amount of copper  was somewhat less than m zone B I. The morphology of the components  m zones B II (needles) and B III (an amorphous and massive precipitate)  was different but the chemical elements found in them were tile same.  Zone B IV was situated adjacent to a void and contained calcium, iron,    261    Fig.5. BESI of area b with five zones. The copper filter segment itself is absent (cf ex-  planation Fig.4). A relatively large gypsum crystal was found in zone B IV    silicon and zinc. Calcite and gypsum were present. A relatively large gyp-  sum crystal was also found. Zone B V contained silicon, sulphur, iron and  zinc. Poorly crystalline iron hydroxides were mainly found in the outer  part of zone B V which was close to the free flowing water mass inside the  tube.    Comparison of areas a and b  A comparison of areas a and b mslde the tube showed that copper was  present closest to the wall of the filter segment. The reverse was the case  with iron which reached the highest concentrations away from the wall of  the tube near to the free flowing water. Both elements, however, occurred  in most zones. Zinc was usually present m small quantities but formed a  major element in zone A V. Sulphur was normally present in the zones  nearest to the wall of the tube and became less abundant in zones away  from this wall. The element Si was only found in small quantities in area b.  The flakes in zone B I were less corroded than in zone A I. Covellite was    262    represented in both zones and so were calcite and gypsum. Silicon and zinc  were added in zone B I to the elements found in zone A I. Some elements  were also added to the ones in zones A II and A III, but zones B II and B  III had similar morphologies, i.e. needles m zones AII and B II and mas-  sive precipitate in zones A III and BIII. Zone A IV with calcite and zone  B IV with calcite, gypsum and elements such as iron, silicon and zinc, were  not comparable. Zone B V was comparable with zones A V and A VI, es-  pecially the subzone with iron hydroxides nearest to the free flowing water  reside the tube.    A rea c  Area c contained six zones (Fig.3 and Fig.6a). The central part of Fig. 6a  has been enlarged in Fig.6,b--d. The copper filter segment is now present,  because submicroscopic work was done on a polished block in which the  copper filter segment could be retained during the grinding procedure. As  a consequence the process by which flakes were produced from the filter  segment could be studied.  The corroded copper filter segment is represented by zone C I (Fig.3)  and visible in Fig.6b. Other micrographs of this zone were presented in  figs.9--13 of Bisdom et al. (1983a). The edge of the filter segment is indent-  ed. EDXRA measurements indicated that the filter only gave copper if  analysed reside the segment away from the edges (Flg.6e). Analyses of the  edge itself, often coloured whitish along a very small line, demonstrated a  little sulphur together with copper (Fig.6f). It is not known whether this is  already covellite.  Zone C II (Fig.6, a and b) was the zone with flakes derived from the  filter segment. The contmuation of the peeled off flakes is demonstrated  well in Fig.6a. A more detailed view m Fig.6b indicates that the flakes can  either stay rather straight over some length or become bent. Pomt analyses  showed that the amount of sulphur had increased in the flakes (Flg.6g),  compared to sulphur at the edge of the copper filter segment. It was assumed  that covellite was present m the flakes.  Zone C III (Fig.6, a and b)can be compared to the zones with needles  on the inside of the tube. The flakes have mainly disappeared and pre-  cipitates appear in quantity. Some zron appeared viz. nearest to the wall  of the tube (Fig.6h). The outer part of this zone still contained copper in  significant quantities together with sulphur and more iron (Flg.6i). The  zones C III and C II were rather porous.  Fig.6. BESI of area c with six zones (a). The copper fdter segment is represented here  and in Figs.7 and 8, because submicroscopic work was done on a polished block The  middle part of (a) has been enlarged m (b) to (d). Point analyses (e) to (I) mdmated that  a little sulphur was present in the corroded edge of the filter (f) and that the amount of  sulphur had increased m the flakes which were derived from the copper filter segment.  Iron appeared in zone C III (cf. Fig.3) and was subsequently represented in all younger  zones    263    ~m    jl i   it 4   il i  Joo    ";" ,                7s ~%    i  iol   ie4   ~~6  ~a    I  I| ~   je 4   Jl 6   Je e    s    264    Zone C IV (Flg.6,a--c) contamed a few rather massive layers on top of  whmh grew forms in which concentric rings can be discerned. Similar forms  and more or less dendritic patterns were found in figs.14--15 of Bisdom et  al. (1983a). The precipitates contamed iron, sulphur and copper. Zinc,  which appeared m zone C III, was also present both in this zone and in the  younger ones. The zinc could be present m small patches.  Zone C V (Fig.6,a, c and d) also seemed to start with a massive layer,  which was not continuous. The composition of the precipitates is similar  to those in zone C IV. This is also the case for the precipitates in the re-  mainder of zone C V, some of the materials of which had a honeycomb  structure.  Zone C VI (Fig.6,a and d) is the youngest zone m the precipitates with a  position farthest away from the filter. A heterogeneous morphology was  exhibited by the precipitates in which various pores occurred. Only the  outermost zone of C VI had a somewhat different composition. The pre-  cipitates contained predominantly iron with small quantities of $1, S and Zn.  The zone could be compared to zone A VI of area a inside the tube m  which iron hydroxides occurred.    Fig.7  BESI of area d with slx zones and a quartz pebble which is stuck in the opening  of the filter Only the youngest zones bend around the pebble    265    A tea d  Area d (Fig.7) contained six zones and a quartz pebble stuck into an  opening of the filter. Only zones D IV and D V bent around the quartz  pebble. The older zones stopped when they reached it. Emplacement of  the quartz pebble is thought to have occurred at an early stage, possibly  during emplacement of the tube or just after. It is also possible, however,  that emplacement of the quartz pebble occurred during the deposition  of zone D V; the first zone to bend around the pebble.  Zone D I shows the corroded edge of the filter segment and zone D II  shows flakes derived from this segment. Sulphur and copper were present,  starting with a little sulphur at the edge of the segment and more sulphur  in the flakes. A relatively massive zone, part of which was not affected by  corrosion, has broken away from the filter segment in zone D II. This mas-  sive band disintegrated into various flakes at some distance from the tube  and in the same zone DII.  Zone D III, the zone with needles or finger-like outgrowths, occupied  only part of the micrograph (cf. Fig.3). The more massive rings of zone D  IV touched the flakes of zone D II in the other part of the micrograph.  Sulphur, iron and copper were represented in zones DIII and D IV. Zn was  only measured m zone D IV. Zone D V contained sulphur, iron and copper.  The precipitates were porous and a honeycomb  structure was present m  some of the materials, Zone D VI was more massive and contained iron  and sulphur. The presence of iron hydroxide is probable.    Comparison of areas c and d  The comparison of both areas is rather easy because most of the zones  can be recognized in areas c and d. One of the main differences is that zone  DIII is not continuous, whereas zone C III is. Also, zone C IV has a rather  massive basis and this is not the case in zone D IV.  Corrosion of the tube was indicated by a little sulphur at the edge of the  filter segment. The edge itself was frequently mdicated by a whitish line  which contained the sulphur when subjected to point analyses. The flakes  were well developed m both micrographs.  The distribution of chemical elements indicated that copper was mostly  present close to the tube and iron m the youngest zones away from the fil-  ter. Iron was not found in zones C I, C II, D I and D II. Sulphur was always  present but least in zone C VI. It is envisaged that iron hydroxides were  present in the external part of zone C VI and in zone D VI. Due to the  work with a polished block, however, transmitted light microscopy could  not be done. Identification of iron hydroxide was therefore mainly done by  comparison with zone A VI. Zinc was present in zones C III to C VI of  area c but only m zone D IV of area d.    Area e  Area e (Fig.8) covers the entrance of the tube between two copper filter  segments, and therefore has a double set of zones (Fig.3). Precipitates have    266    Ftg.8 BESI of area e with five zones. The zones can be compared to those of other areas  (cf. Fig.3). The youngest zones of precipitates on two filter segments merged and clogged  the entrance of the tube.    clogged the entrance of the tube. Five zones could be distinguished, i.e.  three related to each of the two filter segments and two which had merg-  ed together. Zones E I contained the edges of the corroding filter segments  with some S and a high quantity of copper. Zones E II contained the flakes  with more sulphur than copper. The massive zones E III were mainly depos-  ited directly on top of zones EII without the zone with needle shapes.  Zones E III contained sulphur, iron, copper and zinc. No well-developed  concentric rings were found.  The central part of the entrance of the tube with zones E IV and E V,  demonstrated a kind of arrested flow structure which has been drawn in  Fig.3. Zone E IV contained sulphur, iron and zinc, and extended between  the two E III zones from one segment to the other. Zone E V did not pene-  trate into the internal part of the tube. It extended into the external part  of the tube and was surrounded on three sides by zone E IV. Zone E V con-  rained less iron and more sulphur than zone E IV. Zinc was present in small  quantities in both zones. Zone E V was porous if compared to zone E IV.  The latter zone was denser and contained a few larger pores as well as small  ones.    Comparison of area e with areas a to d  Zone E I is comparable to zones C I and D I. No eqmvalent to zone E I  can be found on the internal part of the tube because no filter segment  was represented after preparation of a thin section. Zone EII, however, is    267    equivalent to zones A I and B I with flakes and to zones C II and D II. The  massive zone E III can be compared to zones A III and C IV, whereas less  massive or dense precipitates were found in zones B III and D IV. Zones  E IV and E V were similar in morphology and composition to zones A VI,  B V and C VI.    Fig.9. BESI of the corroded corner of a copper filter segment, flakes and precipitates  (a). The central part of (a) was enlarged (b) and X-ray images of sulphur (c), iron (d)  and copper (e) were made (cf. text).    268    XRD analysis  XRD analysis demonstrated that covelhte (CuS) was the pnnclpal con-  stituent of the inner zones close to the filter segment, whereas iron hydro-  xide was the main constituent m the outer zones with the highest zone-  numbers. Calcite (CaCO3) and gypsum (CaSO4"2H20) were also determin-  ed. Siderite (FeCO3), quartz (SiO2) and sulphur (S) were also recognized.  The identification of cuprite (CuO2), magnesium ferrite (MgFe204), chal-  copyrite (CuFeS2) and akageneite (~-FeOOH) was not certain. XRD analysis  did not indicate compounds with zinc, although this element was represent-  ed above trace element quantities according to SEM-EDXRA analysis. It  is therefore possibly present m an amorphous form.    Flake-development at the corner of a filter segment  An example of the development of flakes at the corner of a filter seg-  ment is given in Fig.9a. The Images were made from the lower left comer  of the copper filter segment which is situated on the left in Fig.3. No sche-  matic drawing was made in this case. Only details of the inner zones are  given. It is clearly visible that the zone with flakes bends around the comer  of the filter segment and that the massive zone was deposited immediately  on top of the flakes (Fig.9a).  A detail of the central part of Fig.9a is given in Fig.9b. X-ray images of  the area in the latter micrograph were made of sulphur (Fig.9c), iron (Fig.  9d) and copper (Fig.9e). The distribution of iron in Fig.9d indicated that  this element was represented in the zone with flakes; similar to zones A I  and B I with flakes inside the tube but different from zones C II, D II and  E II with flakes because no iron was detected in these zones with EDXRA.    CONCLUSIONS    The study of precipitates on filter segments of a tube mdicated a rather  complex environment in which a variety of reactions have taken place. XRD  and light microscopic analyses were able to identify a number of minerals  m the precipitates which were predominantly comprised of amorphous  and poorly crystalline materials. The latter precipitates could be analysed  for their chemical elements by SEM-EDXRA and enlarged by SEM to ob-  serve the morphological detail.  Various zones were identified in areas a--e. Copper was represented in  larger quantities close to the tube, both inside and outside. Iron was most  represented in the youngest zones away from the filter segments. A simi-  lar distribution was found in the clogging precipitates at the entrance to  the filter. Copper could occur in all zones and a little iron could be present  in the flakes close to the tube. Usually, however, the flakes contained only  copper and sulphur. These elements were also found by XRD analysis in  covellite (CuS). The corrosion of the copper filter segments themselves  was indicated by indented edges. A thin whitish line could often be observ-    269    ed along the edges. Point analyses mdicated a little sulphur together with  copper in this line. The amount of sulphur had increased in the flakes  which were derived from the filter segments.  Sulphur was a very common element in most zones and probably formed  a number of compounds with copper, iron and zinc. Only covellite was  indentified, however, near to the tube and in the inner zones. Poorly crystal-  line to amorphous iron hydroxides occurred in the outer and youngest  zones, both inside and outside the tube. Calcite and gypsum were also form-  ed, I.e. only Inside the tube, and in an environment which was constantly  submerged according to the available well data.  The investigation of amorphous and poorly crystalline materials with  SEM-EDXRA demonstrated the presence of various heavy elements and  sulphur. To obtain additional information work should be done with EMA  (electron microprobe analyzer} or SEM-WDXRA {scanning electron micro-  scope -- wavelength dispersive X-ray analyzer) -- instruments not used in  this study. If quantification of all elements, including trace elements, is also  required, SIMS (secondary ion mass spectrometry) should be used (Bisdom  et al., 1977, 1983b; Henstra et al., 1980). The latter submicroscopic tech-  nique, however, is even more costly than the electron microscopic ones  and can therefore only be applied if considered of prime importance for  the success of a major project.    REFERENCES    Blsdom, E.B.A., 1983. In situ microanalysis of man-made precipitates m soil beneath a  landfill and on the surface of a water-tube falter. In: R. Hallberg (Editor), Environ-  mental Biogeochemistry. 5th International Symposmm on Environmental Biogeo-  chemLstry, 1981, Stockholm Ecological Bulletins, 35: 547--553.  Bisdom, E.B.A. and Jongerius, A, 1979. Onderzoek naar verstoppend materiaal m een  waterleidingbuis m.b.v, hchtmicroscopie, REM-EDAX en r6ntgendiffractie (in Dutch).  Report No. 1471. Netherlands Sod Survey Institute, Wageningen, 15 pp.  Bisdom, E.B A , Henstra, S, Jongerius, A. and Thiel, F, 1975. Energy dispersive X-ray  analysis on thin sections and unimpregnated soil material. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 23(4)  113--125  Bmdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Hornsveld, E.M., Jongerms, A. and Letsch, A.C., 1976 Wave-  length and energy dispersive X-ray microanalysm with EMA and SEM-EDXRA on thin  sections of soils. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 24(4): 209--222.  Bisdom, E B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerius, A., Brown, J.D., yon Rosenstiel, A.P. and Gras,  D J., 1977. Light and heavy element detection in thin sections of soils with the ion  mmroprobe  mass  analyzer  (IMMA).  Neth.  J.  Agric.  Sci.,  25(1).  1--13.  Blsdom, E B A. Thiel, F., Volbert, B. and Jackrnan, J., 1983a. Variations in backscat-  tered electron (BSE) images with a Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM)as applied  to mineral grains and excrements in a podzol, to precipitates on a water-tube filter  and to bauxite. Geoderma, 30: 93--116.  Bisdom, E.B.A , Henstra, S., Werner, H.W., Boudewijn, P R, Knippenberg, W.F., Grefte,  H A.M. de, Gourgout, J.M. and Migeon, H.N., 1983b. Quantitative analysis of trace  and major elements in thin sections of soils with the secondary ion microscope (Ca-  meca). Geoderma, 30: 117--134.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractLight microscopic, submicroscopic and XRD (X-ray diffraction) analyses were done of precipitates which had clogged a water-tube filter. Several zones, mostly consisting of amorphous and poorly crystalline materials, could be distinguished. SEM-EDXRA (scanning electron microscopy — energy dispersive X-ray analysis) indicated that sulphur, copper, iron and zinc were usually represented and that calcium was less common. Light microscopy and XRD indicated the presence of calcite and gypsum.Corrosion of copper filter segments could be demonstrated by flakes which peeled off, small fragments adjacent to the segments, and a jagged appearance of the edges. A little sulphur was found at the edges of the filter segments together with copper. More sulphur was present in the flakes which, together with copper, formed covellite according to XRD analyses. Rather massive precipitates could be deposited on the disintegrating flakes. Precipitates of younger zones were usually less massive and exhibited a variety of forms.