Geoderma, 32 (1984) 339--345                                                     339  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    IRON MOBILIZATION BY HEATHLAND PLANT EXTRACTS    G.C. FISHER and OI-LAI YAM  Department of Geography, Bedford College (University of London), London, NW1 4NS  (Great Britain)  (Received October 19, 1982; revised version accepted June 27, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Fisher, G.C. and Oi-Lai Yam, 1984. Iron mobilization by heathland plant extracts. Geo-  derma, 32: 339--345.    Aqueous extracts of leaves and shoots of Calluna vulgaris, Erica tetralix, and Betula  pendula were reacted with iron compounds in the laboratory. Extracts of B. pendula were  found to be most active in solubilizing iron. The iron mobilizing capacity of extracts of  C. vulgaris depended upon plant age, season, and soil conditions. C. vulgaris shoots were  found to be more readily leached of their soluble organic matter than those of B. pendula  but yielded little soluble inorganic material. C. vulgaris extracts were the most acid (pH  4.2--4.5) of those examined.    INTRODUCTION    In many areas of Western Europe podzolic soils (Avery, 1980) are  associated with heathlands, the vegetation of which is usually dominated by  Calluna vulgaris. There is historical ecological evidence, for example from  Britain (Dimbleby, 1962) and France (Guillet et al., 1975) that at some sites  the arrival or increase of C. vulgaris in post-glacial time was linked to the  spread and intensification of podzolization. An initial stage in podzolization  (Russell, 1973, p. 715) is the accelerated solubilization of iron in upper,  aerobic, soil horizons, a process variously attributed to the complexing and  chelating effects of acids and polyphenols derived from the leaf canopy and  litter (Bloomfield, 1970), or the action of fulvic and humic acids of mor  humus (Schnitzer and Kahn, 1972). There is continuing evidence of the in-  fluence of the chemical character of canopy drip upon podzolization, for  example Johnson and Siccama (1979) found a close relationship between the  capacity of throughfall from different tree species to mobilize iron from  ferric nitrate and the depth of the A2 horizon beneath the trees, and Cramp-  ton (1982) related the spatial pattern of podzolization to attributes of  throughfall. The present work partly follows the methodology of Bloomfield  (1953, 1970). A pilot study involved the simulation of canopy drip through  the making of aqueous extracts of shoots of C. vulgaris, the testing of their    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    340    iron-mobilizing capacity, and the examination of how this varied with season  and plant age. Later the activity of C. vulgaris extracts from plants on differ-  ent soils was compared with those of Erica tetralix, a common plant of wet  heathlands, and Betula pendula, a tree species which often invades un-  managed British heathlands bringing about improvements in the biological  and base-status of the soil (Satchell, 1980a).    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Material came from sites m Surrey, England, approximately 35 km south-  west of London, where heathland has developed over sands and gravels of  Tertiary or Pleistocene age. For the pilot study, whole plants of C. vulgaris  and the associated shoot litter were collected approximately every six weeks  over one year from contiguous 1 m: plots on seven separate dry heathland  sites on three areas at Chobham (sites 1A, 1B, 1C, SU994637; sites 2A, 2B,  2C, SU970660) and Ockham (site 3, SU825888). The sites provided a vege-  tational time sequence, and at the start of the work, C. vulgaris at area 2  was in a pioneer growth phase (1.5 years), at area 1 in a building phase (6  years) and at area 3 in a late mature/degenerate phase (25 years). Rooting  patterns and edaphic conditions were similar on all plots, the soils being  sandy humo-ferric podzols or sandy humo-ferric gley podzols with gleying at  depth (Avery, 1980). Microphylls and short shoots, and shoot litter of C.  vulgaris were used to produce aqueous extracts with 5% weight to volume  (w/v) by the boiling method of King and Bloomfield (1968). Replicated 100  ml sterile extracts were mixed with 0.1 g of fresh hydrous ferric oxide gel  and mobilized, dialysable, iron periodically determined by atomic absorp-  tion spectrophotometry over a 34 day period. The pH's of leaf extracts were  also determined.  In the second phase of the study, vegetation was sampled between Oc-  tober 1980 and April 1981 at sites on Chobham Common, Surrey  (SU994637) where C. vulgaris was growing on two markedly different soils  and in association with other plant species. A dry heathland area (X) carried  C. vulgaris in a building growth phase, with young B. pendula invading, on a  shallow humo-ferric gley podzol. An adjacent wet valley-bottom area (Y)  carried an association of C. vulgaris, E. tetralix and Molinia caerulea on a  typical gley podzol, with 10 cm of peat at the soil surface. In both areas  thirty 1 m2 vegetation sampling plots were randomly located, although there  was some selective sampling of B. pendula because of its scattered pattern  of occurrence. All plants were approximately eight years of age. B. penduIa  leaves collected in December 1980 were senescent. Fresh ericaceous shoots  and B. pendula leaves were soaked for 24 h in water, and then replicated,  10% w/v sterile extracts reacted aerobically in flasks with 5 g of iron-coated  quartz sand (3% by weight of dithionite/citrate extractable iron). After eight  days mobilized iron was determined by atomic absorption spectrophotom-  etry. The pH's of all extracts were again determined.    341    Determinations were made of the total amounts of readily soluble or-  ganic and inorganic matter in leaves of C. vulgaris and B. pendula collected  in October 1980 from all 30 plots in area X. The method involved finding  the total dry and ashed weights of leaves before and after soaking in cold  water for 24 h.  Where relevant the results were subjected to statistical testing. In those  cases where the samples were small and there was evidence of non-normal  distributions, non-parametric tests (Siegel, 1956) were preferred to param-  etric methods.    RES ULTS    In the production of aqueous extracts, the use of fresh rather than dried  C. vulgaris was justified by initial experiments, which showed drying at  105 approximately halved the activity of picked materials; also the activi-  ty of litter extracts was only a small fraction of that of fresh material  (Table I). Results of iron-mobilizing experiments for the eight sampling  months of the pilot study are in Table II. C. vulgaris extracts were least  active in winter and early spring, although differences in autumn values for  1978 and 1979 also suggest marked year to year variations. Friedman's non-  parametric two-way analysis of variance by ranks was applied to data in  Table II to test if sampling time affected iron-mobilizing capacity of ex-  tracts; the null hypothesis was rejected at the 0.1% significance level. Plant  age was also found to have a significant effect because testing between sites    TABLEI    Comparisons of the activity of extracts of fresh shoots, dried shoots and plant litter of  C. vulgaris.1    Site  Oct. 1978:               March 1979:  fresh  dried  litter     fresh  dried  litter    1A      50.3       33.0      14.0             40.0      22.0      3.8  1B       55.6      34.0      18.0             27.5      18.8      3.5  1C       73.8       31.6      15.3             38.9      22.0      9.3  2A      63.2      33.0      18.5             42.2      13.4      --  2B       70.0      60.0      24.0            43.7       23.0      --  2C   79.5   20.8    9.6      39.7   23.2   --  3          38.8       21.2      14.2            41.9      18.0       1.6      61.6   33.4   16.2      39.1   20.1   4.5    .1 Figures are maximum amount of iron dissolved in mg per 100 g dry weight of plant  material (bulked samples of plant material, averages of replicate determinations).  Sites 1A, 1B, 1C. C. vulgaris, building growth phase.  Sites 2A, 2B, 2C. C. vulgaris, pioneer growth phase.  Site 3, C. vulgaris, mature/degenerate growth phase.    342  TABLE II  Maximum amount of iron solubilized from hydrous oxide by extracts of C. vulgaris shoots; local and  grand means expressed in mg per 100 g of dry plant matter    Site   6.10.78  16.11.78   23.1.79  22.3.79  23.4.79  5.7.79  23.8.79  20.9.79  (rag)     (rag)      (rag)     (rag)    (rag)    (rag)   (rag)    (mg)    1A    50.3      40.3        36.7      40.0      61.1      67.1    65.0      34.4      49.7  1B         55.6            39.0                36.8            27.5            45.1            48.6         43.0            42.0            42.2  1C    73.8      44.9        29.0      38.9      37.7      42.7    48.8      42.7      44.7  2A        63.2            49.7                28.3            42.2            68.9            57.0         57.1             54.3             51.9  2B    70.0      58.3        50.1      43.7      71.1      58.0    58.4      58.6      58.5  2C    79.5      50.4        46.7      39.7      64.2      62.6    62.0      53.2      57.3  3            38.8            36.7                35.0            41.9            45.9            54.2         54.0            31.0            42.2         61.6      45.6        37.4      39.1      55.6      55.7    55.5      45.2      49.5    with the Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed ranks test showed a significant  difference (5% level) between pioneer C. vulgaris (site 2) and plants at other  sampling sites, but not between building and mature C. vulgaris.  The results of the study which compared C. vulgaris extracts with those of  other species and those of C. vulgaris from different soils are in Table III.  Iron mobilization from the sand used in these studies was much less than  from the reactive ferric oxide used in the pilot study. B. pendula leaves col-  lected from plants in the dry heathland area (X) produced greatest iron  solubilization, greater than that by extracts of C. vulgaris from the same  area. Extracts of C. vulgaris shoots from the wet heathland (Y) were more  active than those of the same species from the dry area, and more active than  those of E. tetralix. Statistical pairwise comparisons using the Mann-Whitney  U test (two-tailed) showed that in October and December 1980 differences  between the activities of extracts of C. vulgaris (X) and B. pendula (X) were  significant (p = 0.1%), as were those between C. vulgaris (Y) and E. tetralix  (Y) (p = 1.0%). There were also significant differences between extracts of    TABLE III    Means and ranges of iron (in mg per I00 g dry plant material) mobilized from sands by  aqueous extracts of shoot and leaf sample    Species    B. pendula    C. vulgaris    C. vulgaris    E. tetralix  (mg)        (mg)        (mg)        (mg)  Area X       Area X       Area Y       Area Y    Oct. 1980    12.0        6.1         9.9         5.1  (16.0--7.9)  (8.9--3.8)   (13.5--5.9)  (11.3--3.7)  Dec. 1980      8.0          2.4           4.2           3.4  (10.7--4.0)  (4.0--1.6)   (8.1--2.8)   (7.9--2.1)  April 1981     1.4          1.7           2.9           1.9  (4.0--1.1)   (4.1--1.0)   (4.9--1.9)   (3.6--1.2)  Control       2.0 ppm    343    C. vulgaris plants from different soils in October (p = 5%) and December  (p = 0.1%). All differences found in April 1981 were non-significant.  All leaf extracts were moderately acid, with those of C. vulgaris the most  acid. Mean pH values for C. vulgaris extracts made over the year of the pilot  study were: area 1, pH 4.25; area 2, pH 4.5; area 3, pH 4.4. Mean pH values  over the 6-month comparative study were: C. vulgaris (X) pH 4.5, C. vulgaris  (Y) pH 4.2, E. tetralix pH 4.3, B. pendula pH 4.8. The only statistically sig-  nificant difference (t test, p = 5%) was between pH's of extracts of C. vulga-  ris and B. pendula from the dry heathland (X).  The study of the leaching of shoots of C. vulgaris and leaves of B. pendula  showed C. vulgaris gave darker, more viscous extracts containing significant-  ly (t test, p = 0.1%) more readily soluble organic material (mean value 19%  of total leaf dry weight compared with 15%). The total inorganic material  (ash) of C. vulgaris shoots was 5% of total shoot dry weight, that of B. pen-  dula 6% of total leaf dry weight, a non-significant difference. The readily  soluble inorganic material, however, was 36.6% of the total ash weight for  B. pendula, but only 8.4% of the ash of C. vulgaris, a highly significant dif-  ference (t test, p = 0.1%).    DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    C. vulgaris is an evergreen, with short shoots persisting for up to four  years, yet a seasonality was apparent in the iron-solubilizing capacity of its  shoot extracts, with very low activity in winter and early spring, increasing in  summer and persisting at a high level until late autumn. Thus it seems  probable that the evergreen habit of the dominant does not, in itself, lead to  an exceptionally high annual input of active soluble organic matter into  heathland soil.  Previous studies of iron mobilization by leaf extracts or throughfall have  not examined the effects of whole plant age, largely because the usual spe-  cies investigated have been long-lived trees. This study showed an effect with  actively growing, pioneer C. vulgaris producing significantly greater iron  mobilization than older plants. The importance of this in the field, however,  is likely to be limited by the very open canopy and low green shoot biomass  of pioneer C, vulgaris (Chapman et al., 1975) which reduces the opportuni-  ties for intercepted precipitation to dissolve active organic material.  Differences in soil conditions are reflected in plant biochemistry and  hence the character of canopy drip (Davies, 1970). Extracts of C. vulgaris  plants from wet heath sites were more active in iron solubilization than those  from plants in dry heathland. Despite its wide ecological tolerance C. vulgaris  is more likely to be under stress on very wet soils, and such a condition of  stress can lead to increased plant production of polyphenols, thought by  many workers to be very active in iron mobilization (Davies, 1970).  B. pendula leaf extracts produced, on average, twice the iron mobilization  produced by extracts of C. vulgaris shoots. This is the reverse of what might    344    be expected inasmuch as invasion by B. pendula is often associated with de-  creased iron movement in British podzolic soils (Dimbleby, 1962). Bloom-  field (1970) noted, however, that many deciduous trees, seldom associated  with podzolic soils, produced leaf extracts which caused intense iron mobili-  zation under laboratory conditions. Whether or not an effect occurs in a  real soil system depends on the biological and chemical status of the soil.  Acidity and lack of biological activity promote the reaction of leaf extracts  with iron and aid the persistence of chelates and complexes (Bloomfield,  1953, 1970). The existence of such conditions in the soil depends partly  upon the chemical composition and degradability of the plant litter. It was  found that C. vulgaris water extracts were more acid than those of B. pendu-  la, and its shoots, when leached, released less mineral material and more  organic matter per unit time. These results may be compared with some of  Nykvist (1963) who found Betula litter released 10.7% of its water soluble  substances and 33% of its total inorganic matter in 24 h of leaching, but that  coniferous needle leaf litter yielded much lower amounts of inorganic  matter, like C. vulgaris, but in contrast also very little organic material.  Bruckert and Jacquin (1973) found C. vulgaris canopy drip to be of pH 3.5  and rich in phenolic acids; the more acid value than those reported here is  probably due to site differences and the use of throughfall rather than  standardized water extracts. Water-soluble tannins are known to be much  more abundant in shoots of C. vulgaris than leaves of B. pendula, making  the acid litter unpalatable to earthworms (Satchell, 1980a, b), and such  tannins form stable complexes with proteins which delay litter breakdown  (Handley, 1961) and generally inhibit microbial activity. Gallardo et al.  (1975) found water extracts of C. vulgaris litter to be richer in phenolic  compounds than those of Fagus sylvatica and the litter slower to decay. The  consequence of the chemical character of C. vulgaris litter is that it persists  for several years, whereas most Betula leaves disappear from the soil surface  in months (Williams and Gray, 1974). The present study indicates that iron  mobilization under C. vulgaris may be due more to the acidity and mineral  release characteristics of the canopy and litter, producing conditions favour-  able for the formation and persistence of chelates in the soil, than to any  exceptional ability of its throughfall alone to mobilize iron.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    We thank Mrs. M. Onwu for assistance with the analytical procedures.    REFERENCES    Avery, B.W., 1980. Soil cl~ification for England and Wales (Higher Categories). Soil  Surv. Tech. Monogr, No. 14, Harpenden, 67 pp.  Bloomfield, C., 1953. A study of podzolization, Part 1. J. Soil Sci., 4: 5--16.    345    Bloomfield, C., 1970. The mechanism of podzolization. Welsh Soils Discussion Group,  Report No. 11, pp. 112--132.  Bruckert, S. and Jacquin, F., 1973. Contribution a l'~tude de la condensation decompo-  s~ organique au cours de l'humification en milieu podzolique. Bull. Ecole Nat. Supe-  rieure Agron. Nancy, 13: 28--35.  Chapman, S.B., Hibble, J. and Rafarel, C.R., 1975. Net aerial production by Calluna vul-  garis on lowland heath in Britain. J. Ecol., 63: 233--258.  Crampton, C.B., 1982. Podzolization of soils under individual tree canopies in south-  western British Columbia, Canada. Geoderma, 28: 57---61.  Davies, R.I., 1970. The podzol process. Welsh Soils Discussion Group, Report No. 11,  pp. 133--142.  Dimbleby, G.W., 1962. The Development of British Heathlands and their Soils. Claren-  don Press, Oxford, 120 pp.  Gallardo, J.F., Schwartz, C. and Jacquin, F., 1975. Evolution in vitro d'hydrosolubles de  litieres de Calluna vulgaris et de Fagus sylvatica au cours d'humification en milieu  acide. Bull. Ecole Nat. Superieure Agron. Ind. Alimentaires, 17: 61--64.  Guillet, B., Rouillier, J. and Souchier, B., 1975. Podzolization and clay migration in spo-  dosols of eastern France. Geoderma, 14: 223--245.  Handley, W.R.C., 1961. Further evidence for the importance of residual leaf protein com-  plexes in litter decomposition. Plant Soil, 15: 37--73.  Johnson, A.H. and Siccama, T.G., 1979. Effect of vegetation on the morphology of Wind-  sor Soils, Litchfield, Connecticut. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 1199--1207.  King, H.G.C. and Bloomfield, C., 1968. The effects of drying and ageing tree leaves on  the ability of their aqueous extracts to dissolve ferric oxide. J. Soil Sci., 19: 67--76.  Nykvist, N., 1963. Leaching and decomposition of litter. Stud. For. Suec., 3: 1--31.  Russell, E.W., 1973. Soil Conditions and Plant Growth. Longman, London, 10th ed.,  849 pp.  Satchell, J.E., 1980a. Soil and vegetation changes in experimental birch plots on Calluna  podzol. Soil Biol. Biochem., 12: 303--310.  Satchell, J.E., 1980b. Potential of the Silpho Moor experimental birch plot as a habitat  for Lumbricus terrestris. Soil Biol. Biochem., 12: 317--323.  Schnitzer, M. and Khan, S.U., 1972. Reactions of humic substances with metal ions and  hydrous oxides. In: Humic Substances in the Environment. Marcel Dekker, New York,  N.Y., pp. 203--251.  Siegel, S., 1956. Nonparametric Statistics for the Behavioral Sciences. McGraw-Hill, New  York, N.Y., 312 pp.  Williams, S.T. and Gray, T.G., 1974. Decomposition of litter on the soil surface. In: C.H.  Dickinson and G.J.F. Pugh (Editors), Biology of Plant Litter Decomposition, Vol. 2.  Academic Press, London, pp. 611--632.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractAqueous extracts of leaves and shoots of Calluna vulgaris, Erica tetralix, and Betula pendula were reacted with iron compounds in the laboratory. Extracts of B. pendula were found to be most active in solubilizing iron. The iron mobilizing capacity of extracts of C. vulgaris depended upon plant age, season, and soil conditions. C. vulgaris shoots were found to be more readily leached of their soluble organic matter than those of B. pendula but yielded little soluble inorganic material. C. vulgaris extracts were the most acid (pH 4.2–4.5) of those examined.