Geoderma, 27 (1982) 355--356                                                     355  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Books and Bulletins Received    Avery, Brian, W., 1980. Soil Classification for England and Wales (Higher cate.  gories). Soil Survey of England and Wales, Technical Monograph No. 14,  67 pp.  Beinroth, F.H., Ikawa, H. and Uehara, G., 1979. Classification of the Soil  Series of Hawaii in Four Systems: A Guide for Correlating Tropical  Soils. Hawaii Agricultural Experiment Station, Miscellaneous Publication  166 (BSP Tech. Rep. 2), 55 pp.  Benchmark Soils Project, 1979. Development of the transfer model and soil  taxonomic interpretations on a network of three soil families, Progress  Report 2 (January 1978--June 1979). Department of Agronomy and Soil  Science, University of Hawaii and Department of Agronomy and Soils,  University of Puerto Rico, 80 pp.  Buson, Christian, 1979. Un approache p~dologique du probl~me de  l'6pandage: Caracterisation hydrique des sols bruns sur schistes briov6riens  de la r6gion de Vire (Calvados) -- Effect des 6pandages de laiterie sur les  sols et les eaux. Laboratoire de Science du Sol de I'ENSA--INRA, Rennes,  118 pp.  Curmi, P., 1979. Alteration et differenciation p~dologique sur granite en  Bretagne: Etude d'une topos6quence. Laboratoire de Science du Sol de  l' ENSA--INRA, Rennes, 176 pp.  Le Calvez, Laurent, 1979. Gen~se des formations limoneuses de Bretagne  central: Essai de modelisation. Universit~ de Rennes, INRA--ENSA, 214  PP.  Camargo, M.N. and Beinroth, F.H. (Editors), 1978. Proceedings of First  International Soil Classification Workshop, Brazil, June 20--July 1, 1977.  EMBRAPA (Empresa Brasileira de Pesquisa Agropecuaria Vinculada ao  Ministerio da Agricultura, Servicio Nacional de Levantamento e Conser-  vacao de Solos), Rio de Janeiro, 376 pp.  Lag, J. (Editor), 1980. Geomedical aspects in present and future research.  Universitetsforlaget, Oslo, 226 pp.  Peterson, Frederick, F., 1981. Landforms of the Basin and Range Province  Defined for Soil Survey. Nevada Agricultural Experiment Station Tech-  nical Bulletin 28, 52 pp.  R.E. Phillips, G.W. Thomas and R.L. Blevins (Editors), 1981. No-Tillage  Research: Research Reports and Reviews. University of Kentucky, College  of Agriculture and Agricultural Experiment Station, Lexington, Kentucky,  151 pp.  Silva, James A. (Editor), 1981. Experimental designs for predicting crop  productivity with environmental and economic inputs for agrotechnology  transfer. Developmental Paper No. 49. Hawaii Institute of Tropical Agri-  culture and Human Resources, University of Hawaii, 184 pp.    356    Smalley, I.J. and Davin, J.E., 1980. The first hundred years -- A historical  bibliography of New Zealand loess, 1878--1978. New Zealand Soil Bureau  Bibliographic Report 28, 166 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     