Geoderma, 31 (1983) 289--299                                                         289  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    STRUCTURING OF SOME BASIC PEDOLOGICAL PROCESSES    GEORGES PEDRO  Institut National de la Recherche Agrotmmique, Laboratoire des Sols, C.N.R.A.,  78000 - Versailles (France)  (Received October 25, 1982; revised version accepted March 23, 1983)    ABSTRACT  Pedro, O., 1983. Structuring of some basic pedological processes. Geoderma, 31 : 289--299.    In the first section, the author presents a detailed analysis of fundamental processes  of pedological evolution in the light of the latest findings as to biogeochemical, mine-  ralogical and granulometric aspects of pedogenesis on crystalline aluminosilicate rocks.  This analysis is based on the nature of various geochemical weathering phenomena, on  the one hand, and on problems related to the organization of plasmic elements (p~do-  plasmation) and their possible transfers as particles, on the other. With reference to the  latter aspect, two major types of "pedogenesis" may be considered: "associative" pedo-  genesis in which plasma-skeleton links are kept, and "dissociative" pedogenesis in which  plasma~skeleton links are disrupted and plasma is redistributed.  Then, in the second section, a structuring of fundamental pedogenetic processes is pro-  posed, based on the observation of three major phyla at the earth surface.  Phylum I: Process with predominant biogeochemical evolution without plasma forma-  tion or with plasma destruction.  Phylum II: Process with predominant biogeochemical evolution with plasma formation  and reorganization in situ.  Phylum III: Process with predominant textural evolution with plasma mobilization  and redistribution.    INTRODUCTION    Pedological classification systems have been largely of a genetic type, i.e.,  keyed to processes thought to govern soil formation. The systems have all  been unsatisfactory to some extent, however, because genetic processes were  not fully known and described. During the present century, most soils of the  world have been examined (cf. the FAO-UNESCO Soil Map of the World,  1975). The knowledge of pedogenetic phenomena has also been greatly im-  proved. A framework is therefore being proposed here as a "reference  scheme" for considering pedological processes. Such a framework should in-  clude the genetical processes that interfere with the development of "ortho-  typic soils", i.e., those due to the simplest options of nature, without how-  ever considering that such a structure should correspond to a classification  system directly usable for soil mapping.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    290    SOME   BASIC   PROCESSES   OF"   PEDOLOGICAL   EVOLUTION:   TENTATIVI':   ttlEI~  ARCHIZATION    I shall discuss only processes involved in the genesis of organomineral  soils, i.e. soils with normal development (erosion- and water-free)generated  at the expense of aluminosilicate crystalline rocks. I will not consider histo-  sols, hydromorphic soils, soils developed on vitreous volcanic rocks (ando-  sols) or calcareous rocks, which can be analysed in the same way. Soils units  covered in this study are listed in Appendix I (FAO-UNESCO nomenclature;  Soil Taxonomy; Classification frangaise).  Every pedological evolution consists essentially of two major types of phe-  nomena:  (1) Phenomena corresponding to the weathering of primary (weatherable)  minerals, the release of various elements and their possible recombinations to  give new organic and mineral constituents stable in this medium, therefore  characterizing the evolution. The weathering phenomena are essentially geo-  chemical and mineralogical processes.  (2) Phenomena developing during or after weathering related to the ar-  rangement of soil constituents, their organization and their redistribution in  pedological horizons. As they are more typically "pedological" phenomena,  they have been gathered under the expression "pedogenesis", but that term  covers more mechanisms than mentioned in this study. As defined, pedo-  genesis implies that the biosphere is involved in particular with incorpora-  tions of primary (plant residues) and secondary (humic constituents) organic  materials.    Weathering processes    These phenomena are essentially biogeochemical, leading to the partial or  total release of the elements and their movement in solution, so that the  chemical composition of the soil horizon is quite different from that of the  parent material. On that basis, two major cases can be defined according to  whether a fraction of the elements in solution stays independent or is recom-  bined to give new minerals making up the so called plasma. The primary  minerals that are not weathered form the skeleton.  (1) Weathering does not induce the formation of secondary minerals  (plasma); it even causes the destruction of secondary constituents that may  have existed initially. Thus, the superficial evolution can be regarded as a  mere solubflization, so that a characteristic horizon will be formed with  primary minerals in fine (slightly or not weathered). It will therefore not be  equivalent to an altered product but to a residue of weathering, whence its  characterization by the symbol E (or A2). The weathering process which, in  that case, is equivalent to a preponderantly physico-chemical action can be  characterized according to the nature of the attack. There are three main  pathways:  (a) A strongly acid and complexing attack due to organic acids which ef-    291    fect the extraction and elimination of all the aluminum and iron (and all the  other cations -- Mg, Ca, Na, K  ....  ), i.e., acidocomplexolysis.  (b) A strongly alkaline effect generally caused by the occurrence of so-  dium carbonate solution with preferential dissolution of alumina and also  silica, i.e., alkalinolysis.  (c) An attack of clays likely to happen at the interfaces when the soil is  alternately marked by an excess of wetness and an excess of desication. This  attack results from the action of strongly acid cations such as Fe ("ferro-  lysis", Brinkman, 1970) or even protons coming from immediate dissocia-  tion of water adsorbed in very slightly hydrated materials, i.e., xerolysis  (Chaussidon and Pedro, 1979).  (2) In the second case, weathering is reflected by the occurrence of new  minerals which are clays possibly accompanied by substances such as ferric  hydrates, calcium carbonates and humic components. The characteristic  horizon which is here a real altered product is then characterized by typical  paragenesis (i.e., association of two or more minerals forming in the same  conditions). Then, the problem consists in characterizing all the mechanisms  and different methods responsible for the formation of different types of  plasma (cf. Pedro, 1966, 1968; Pedro and Sieffermann, 1979).  (a) In hot and wet climates, for instance, weathering resulting from the ac-  tion of water more or less charged with CO2 (hydrolysis) is intense, which  leads to rapid destruction of weathered minerals and to massive neoforma-  tion of secondary minerals such as clays and ferric hydrates (accumulation of  iron and aluminum in situ), whence the individualization of the so called  "crust of weathering" (Boulet, 1978).  Various kinds of paragenesis can occur according to the degree of hydro-  lysis. Starting, for example, from a strong hydrolysis and then reducing its  intensity, 1 have observed successively formation of gibbsite (allitisation},  kaolinite (monosiallitisation) and smectites (bisiallitisation or bisialferritisa-  tion) (Pedro, 1966) with different parageneses (Table I).  (b) Under climates where hydrolysis is less aggressive because they are  either wet but too cold or warm but too dry, weathering is of moderate de-  gree with weatherable minerals remaining for a long time in the horizons and  with slight individualization of clays. In that case, the argilous plasma con-  sists of inherited phyllites from the parent rock. These phyllites can undergo  inter- and intrafoliar changes in the course of evolution. In other words, neo-  formations sensu stricto hold a minor place {Pedro, 1976} and affect only in-  dependent ferric hydrates, humic constituents, calcium carbonate and the  like.  As most of the inherited phyllites are 2/1 minerals, differentiation can  mainly be based on adsorbed cations (nature and degree of hydration of ele-  ments in interfoliar postions: Ca, Na, H, A1OH...) and on the occurrence of  non-silicate minerals (e.g., CaCO3).  In hydrolytic conditions with iron and aluminum remaining in situ, the    292  TABLE I  Parageneses characteristic of pedogeneses with massive neoformation of secondary consti-  tuents    Geochemistry of weathering            Characteristic parageneses    Total desilicification and  dealkalinisation    Partial desilicification and total  dealkalinisation    Partial desilicification and  dealkalinisation    Gibbsite and ferric hydrates  (Allitisation)    ( 1/1 ) kaolinite and ferric hydrates  (Monosiallitisation)    (1/1 ) kaolinite and (2/1) smectite Fe  (2/1) smectite AI - Fe    following associations can be obsePced when going to the most arid and  closed milieu:  (Phyllite 2/1) Ca  (Phyllite 2/1) Ca - CaC03  (Phyllite 2/1) (Na,Ca)  ....  CaCO3  Conditions corresponding to moderate acidolysis lead to aluminum redis-  tribution and individualization of aluminized phyllites (Al-vermiculites and  intergrades) of the type:  (Phyllite 2/1) AIOH  Finally, weathering with individualization of secondary minerals may lead  in that case to two kinds of plasma (Fig. 1).    Intense weathering    Moderate weathering    :   Neoformed plasma  (Gibbsite-Kaolinite-Smectite)  :   Inherited and transformed  plasma  (Phyllites 2/I)    Fig. 1. The two major types of weathering plasma.    "Pedogenesis" phenomena    With regard to the evolution of the mineral fraction, the problem is the  organization of constituents in relation to each other, in particular of those  concerning the distribution of plasma (secondary) as related to the skeleton  (primary), the variations in structure of the material evolving and, possibly,  the transfer of the plasma elements into the solid phase. It is the latter point,  however, which permits the distinguishing of two major pedologic fields  (Fig. 2).    293    Without any plasma  transfer into the solid phase,  ASSOCIATIVE Pedogenesis  W_i~h plasma transfer  into the solid phase,  i.e.,  OISSOCIATIVE  Pedogenesis    i .e.,    Fig. 2. Two major ways of pedogenesis.    (1) Associative pedogenesis without plasma transfer into the solid phase.  Pedogenesis is associative because of the structuring of plasma after its indi-  vidualization in situ (pedoplasmation) and leads to a congenitally stable or-  ganization where plasma and skeleton remain associated within the level  undergoing evolution. This horizon roughly represents the so called weather-  ing B, horizon (B), which can be characterized according to the nature of  plasma, itself derived from the type of weathering (see first section). There-  fore, various alternatives can be encountered as listed in Table II.  Such a pedologic evolution appears under comparatively buffered climates  where surface horizons are marked neither by an excess of wetness (leading  to saturation) nor by an excess of desiccation. Thus, these climates may be  more or less aggressive from the biogeochemical point of view but always  poorly perturbing from the energetic point of view because pF of the soil  varies very little (2--3) during the year. Therefore, the plasma--skeleton as-  sociation is maintained upon pedoplasmation (i.e., formation of soil plasma  during the transformation of weathered rock to B horizons, cf. Flach et al.,  1968).    TABLE II    Main processes characteristic of "associative pedogenesis"    Process                                     Nature of plasma    Ferrallitisation  Ultraferrallitisation  Ferrallitisation s. 1.    Sialferritisation  With Fe only in smectite (s.l.)  With Fe and Al in smectite (s.s.)    Siallitisation  Humosiallitisation  Fersiallitisation  Calcosiallitisation  Alcalic-Calcosiallitisation    {Allite} {Fe203, nH,O }  {Kaolinite -- (Allite)} {Fe,O3, nH~O}    (Kaolinite } {Smectite Fe }  {Smectite (Fe -- A1) }    {Phyllite 2/1 ~Ca " Humus (Fe)  {Phyllite 2/1 ]ca {FeaO3, nH20 }  {Phyllite 2/1 }Ca {CaCO3 }  (Phyllite 2/1 }Na {CaCO3 }    Aluminosiallitisation                     {Phyllite 2/1 }AIOH  {Fe203, nH20 }  Feraluminisation    294    (2) Dissociative pedogenesis with plasma transfer into the solid phase. This  generally happens under more contrasted climates which are perturbing from  the energetic point of view (here depending of the season, the pF of a sur-  face horizon may vary from 0.1 to 5). Under these conditions, the organiza-  tion resulting from weathering tends to be destabilized, at least in superficial  horizons, whence follows a dissociation between the elements of skeleton  and plasma. After their release, the elements can be redistributed either with-  in the profile or outside of the profile, so that the evolution is characterized  in the surface horizons by losses of clays and iron to various degrees.  In this type of pedogenesis, the plasma--skeleton dissociation "always pre-  vails over plasma constitution. In the most frequent case when weathering  leads to the individualization of a "clay-ferric hydrate" system (frequent  in warm temperate and tropical areas), two great fields can be distinguished  depending on whether the plasma--skeleton dissociation occurs while the  integrity of argilo--ferric plasma is maintained or whether it results from a  clay--iron disjunction (cf. Chauvel, 1977; Chauvel et al., 1977).  (a) If clay--iron bonds persist, the whole weathering plasma will move, the  direction and intensity of its movement depending on the milieu.  The translocation is then essentially vertical if pedoclimatic conditions do  not produce superficial or subsuperficial (hypodermic) flowing ("lessivage").  "Lessivage", however, may appear in the whole profile, thus resulting in  the development of eluviated soil in situ. It may also occur only in the upper  part of the profile with a deposit in the subsurface horizons, which thus turn  into altero-illuvial (Boulet, 1978) or argillic B (FAO nomenclature, 1975)  horizons.  By contrast, when pedoclimatic conditions cause the destabilization of  surface horizons with an epidermic flowing, the plasma elements may be car-  ried away superficially in a lateral direction. That corresponds to a sort of  "selective erosion" (cf. Roose, 1980) which is now called "appauvrissement  de surface" or superficial impoverishment. Plasma is lost from surface hori-  zons whereas subsurface horizons are in fact B horizons of alteration.  (b) Any disjunction of clay--iron bonds within plasma will encourage  plasma-skeleton dissociation. Thus, plasma mobility will be increased, but  clay and iron will behave disjunctionally and may migrate separately.  The different cases mentioned can be observed together with iron segrega-  tion, leading to recrystallization of iron constituents to a state of better crys-  tallized oxides and to phenomena characteristic of concretion formation. In  the present state of knowledge however, it is not possible to proceed to a  more thorough analysis.  On the basis of the above analysis, even though partial and rather incom-  plete, I will try to structure some pedological processes and to distinguish  some pedogenetic phyla.    295    DETERMINATION   OF  MAIN  PEDOGENETIC  PHYLA  CHARACTERISTIC  OF  THE  SURFACE OF THE EARTH    Certainly, the different processes discussed above for weathering as well as  for "pedogenesis:' never occur alone and in a monotonous manner at a spe-  cific point of the earth surface. As a general rule, however, one of the pheno-  mena prevails. Therefore, the hierarchization of pedologic knowledge can be  performed by refering to the prevailing phenomenon. As for the major crite-  rion that will be used to distinguish each of the great pedologic phyla, I shall  refer to plasma which is actually the central point of pedologic phenomena.  In this perspective, three main phyla may be recognized (Fig. 3).  I    Absence of plasma  formation  (or  imperceptible formation)]  during evolution and  some destruction of preexisting  plasmic   minerals  II    Plasma  formation with plasma-skeleton bonds  persisting    Ill    Plasma  formation and  redistribution due  to  plasma-  skeleton disjunction    Fig. 3. Main pedologic phyla proposed.    Phylum I: Absence of plasma formation (or imperceptible formation) during  evolution and destruction of preexisting plasmic minerals    The pedologic evolution results from the action of a biogeochemical, ag-  gressive and dissolvent weathering that is therefore fully "aplasmogenic" in  the A horizons.  With reference to the three mechanisms described on pp. 290--291, three  major processes may be related to this phylum (Table III).  In all the cases, evolution produces strongly differentiated soils having  prominent horizonation. They can be termed "sols d'alt6ration diff6renci6s"  {soils with differential alteration).    TABLE Ill    Processes of Phylum I    Acidocomplexolysis  Alkalinolysis    Xerolysis -- Ferrolysis    Podzolization (Podzols -- Spodosols)  Solodization (Solods)  (Solodic planosols)  (Auto) planosolization (Planoaols)    296    Phylum H: Plasma formation with remaining plasma--skeleton bonds    Pedological evolution still proceeds from biogeochemical action but leads  here to plasma individualization. Therefore, it is typically "plasmogenic".  According to the nature of plasma, different processes can be observed as  mentioned above. They are listed in Table IV.  In this great phylum of the so-called "sols d'alt6ration s.s." {soils with uni-  form alteration), the profiles are usually poorly differentiated geochemically,  except for the feraluminization process (see Table IV for explanation} and  when CaCO3 transfer into solution is intense.    TABLE IV    Processes of Phylum II    (a) With plasma of neoformation  Ferrallitlsation    Sialferritisation    Soils with kaolinitic weathering  (sols ferrallitiques -- ferralsols-nitosols...)    Soils with montmorillonitic weathering  (sols bruns eutrophes-vertisols)    (b) With plasma of interited and tramfformed kinds (type 2/1) in order of decreasing  acidity    Feraluminization  (Moderate podzolization)    Sols bruns acides -- cryptopodzoliques et  ocres podzoIiques  (spodic B)    Humosiallitlsation                       Sols bruns  (Brunification)                       (cambic B )    Fersiallitlsation    Calcosiallitisation    Alkalic calcosiallitisation    Sols rouges fersiallitiques  (non-lessiv6s)    Soils with calcareous profile (more or less  differentiated )  (B Ca)  Chernozem -- kastanozem  Sois isohumiques    Sols bruns alcalis~s  (natric B)    Phylum III: Plasma formation and redistribution due to plasma--skeleton  disjunction    The pedological evolution which characterizes this phylum is marked  mainly by the preponderant transfers into a solid phase. Soils produced    297    generally show textural differentiation. Thus, the basra processes are here  "lessivage", "appauvrissement de surface" and formation of concretions.  They can, at least theoretically, affect different plasmic materials of the  soils of Phylum II when the initial organization becomes unstable. Present  knowledge is not enough to propose better structuring of pedologic pheno-  mena.  Soils such as Luvisols or Alfisols, Acrisols or Ultisols and Solonetz belong  to this phylum.    CONCLUSION    The purpose of this study is to show that in all the situations pedogenetic  knowledge can be structured around the predominant genetic process regard-  less of its nature. For a long time, the type of biogeochemical evolution  (though poorly explained) had priority over transfers into the solid phase  {clay translocation). The latter has been difficult to understand dynamically  and so far, people tended to detect such transfers only from granulometric  data and profile individualization with strong textural differentiation (with-  out microscope observations). Actually, such a way of proceeding is ques-  tionable due to the existing convergence in nature. The discussions indicate,  that strongly differentiated soils may result either from the absence of plas-  ma formation (Phylum I), or from the individualization of a plasma which  will be redistributed afterwards (Phylum III). Therefore, it is necessary to  take into account the predominant mechanisms of pedological evolution, as  proposed in the three major phyla (Table V).    TABLE V    Major pedologic phyla -- their nature and relationships to soil profile morphology    Phylum    Preponderant evolution         Soils  I           Preponderant biogeochemical  evolution without plasma  formation (Aplasmogenic  phylum)    II    III    Preponderant biogeochemical  evolution with plasma  formation and in situ re-  organization (Plasmogenic  phylum with associative pedo-  genesis)    Preponderant textural evolu-  tion due to plasma mobiliza-  tion and redistribution  (Plasmogenic phylum with  dissociative pedogenesis)    Strongly differentiated soils with pro-  eminent horizonation  Sols d'alt~ration diff4renci~s  (Soils with differential alteration)    Sols d'altdration s.s. (geochemically  poorly differentiated)    Soils with textural differentiation  (with gradual transition)    298  APPENDIX I  Major soils units concerned by evolutive processes considered in this study    Soil units:                   Orders:                Classes:  FAO - UNESCO             Soil taxonomy         Classification franqaise,  (1975)                (1975)            CPCS (1967)    (V) Vertisols  (S) Solonetz  (K) Kastanozems  (C) Chernozems  (H) Phaeozems  (M) Greyzems  (B) Cambisols  (L) Luvisols  (D) Podzoluvisols  (P) Podzols  (W) Planosols  (A) Acrisols  (N) Nitosols  (F)Ferralsols    AI fisols                (Ill)  Vertisols  Aridisols               (VI) Sols isohumiques  Inceptisols             (VII) Sols brunifi4s  Mollisols               (VIII)Sols podzolis~s  Spodosols             (IX) Sols ~ sesquioxydes  Ultisols                (X)  Sols ferrallitiques  Vertisols               (XII) Sols sodiques  Oxisols                      (sous-classe 2)    REFERENCES    Boulet, R., 1978. Toposdquences de sols tropicaux en Haute-Volta. Equilibres et d~s-  ~quilibres p~dobioclimatiques. ORSTOM M~m., 85, 272 pp.  Brinkman, R., 1970. Ferrolysis, a hydromorphic soil forming process. Geoderma, 3:  199--206.  Chaussidon, J. and Pedro, G., 1979. RSle de l'~tat hydrique du syst~me poreux sur  l'dvolution du milieu. R~alite de l'alt~ration dans les syst~mes ~ faible teneur en  eau. Sci. Sol, 2/3: 223--237.  Chauvel, A., 1977. Recherches sur la transformation des sols ferrallitiques dans la zone  tropicale ~ saisons contrut~es. ORSTOM Travaux Documents, 62,532 pp.  Chauvel, A., Bocquier, G. and Pedro, G., 1977. Les mt~canismes de la disjonction des  constituants des couvertures ferrallitiques et l'origine de la zonalit~ des couvertures  sableuses dans les r~gions intertropicales de l'Afrique de l'Ouest. Sci. G~ol. Strasbourg  Bull., 30: 229--233.  Chauvel, A. and Pedro, G., 1978. Sur l'importance de l'extr~me dessiccation des sols  (ultradessiccation) dans l'~volution p~dologique des zones tropicales ~ saisons contras-  t~es. C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris, 286, D, pp. 1581--1584.  C.P.C.S., 1967. Classification des sols. Paris, 96 pp.  F.A.O., 1975. Ldgende de la Carte Mondiale des Sols Unesco, Paris, Vol. I, 62 pp.  Flach, K.W., Cady, J.G. and Nettleton, W.D., 1968. Pedogenic alteration of highly weath-  ered parent materials. Trans. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 9th, Adelaide (Australia), IV, pp.  343--351.  Pedro, G., 1966. Essai sur ia caract~risation g~ochimique des diff~rents processus zonaux  r~sultant de l'alt~ration superficielle. C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris, 262, D, pp. 1828--1831.  Pedro, G., 1968. Distribution des principaux types d'alt~ration chimique i la surface du  globe. Presentation d'une esquisse g~ographique, Rev. G~ogr. Phys. G~ol. Dyn., X, pp.  457--470.  Pedro, G., 1976. Sols argileux et argiles. Sci. Sol, 2: 69--84.    299    Pedro, G. and Sieffermann, G., 1979. Weathering of rocks and formation of soils. In: F.R.  Siegel (Editor), Review in Modern Problems of Geochemistry. UNESCO, pp. 39--55.  Roose, E., 1980. Dynamique actuelle de sols ferrallitiques et ferrugineux tropicaux  d'Afrique Occidentale. Etude exp~rimentale des transferts hydrologiques et biologi-  ques de mati~res sous v~g~tations naturelles ou cultiv~es. ORSTOM, Tray. Doc., 587  PP.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agriculture Handbook No. 436,754 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractIn the first section, the author presents a detailed analysis of fundamental processes of pedological evolution in the light of the latest findings as to biogeochemical, mineralogical and granulometric aspects of pedogenesis on crystalline aluminosilicate rocks. This analysis is based on the nature of various geochemical weathering phenomena, on the one hand, and on problems related to the organization of plasmic elements (pÃƒÂ©doplasmation) and their possible transfers as particles, on the other. With reference to the latter aspect, two major types of Ã¢Â€ÂœpedogenesisÃ¢Â€Â may be considered: Ã¢Â€ÂœassociativeÃ¢Â€Â pedogenesis in which plasma-skeleton links are kept, and Ã¢Â€ÂœdissociativeÃ¢Â€Â pedogenesis in which plasmaÃ¢Â€Â”skeleton links are disrupted and plasma is redistributed.Then, in the second section, a structuring of fundamental pedogenetic processes is proposed, based on the observation of three major phyla at the earth surface.Phylum I: Process with predominant biogeochemical evolution without plasma formation or with plasma destruction.Phylum II: Process with predominant biogeochemical evolution with plasma formation and reorganization in situ.Phylum III: Process with predominant textural evolution with plasma mobilization and redistribution.