Geoderma, 24 (1980) 299--307                                                      299  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    BACKGROUND LEVELS OF MINOR ELEMENTS IN SOME CANADIAN  SOILS*    J.A. McKEAGUE and M.S. WOLYNETZ  Land Resource Research Institute;  Engineering and Statistical Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, Ont. (Canada)  (Received July 10, 1979; accepted February 29, 1980)    ABSTRACT    McKeague, J.A. and Wolynetz, M.S., 1980. Background levels of minor elements in some  Canadian soils. Geoderma, 24 : 299--307.    Background levels of some minor elements in 173 samples (53 soils) widely dispersed  in Canada are summarized and discussed in relation to data for other soils in Canada and  elsewhere. Mean levels (ppm) for the 173 samples are: Cr 43, Mn 520, Co 21, Ni 20, Cu  22, Zn 74, Se 0.3, Sr 210, Hg 0.06 and Pb 20. These are similar to means reported for  soils of the United States and, with some exceptions, for world soils. Levels of several of  the elements studied differed significantly among physiographic regions.  The Ae (eluvial) horizons of Podzolic, Gleysolic and Luvisolic soils were markedly de-  pleted, relative to the associated C horizons, of Mn, Co, Ni, Cu ; depletion of Cr, Zn, Pb  and Sr was less striking.  Though levels of some minor elements are significantly correlated with other soil prop-  erties such as clay, organic C, Fe, etc., predictability of the levels of most minor ele-  ments from other soil properties is not good. One notable exception is that Sr in non-  calcareous samples can be estimated from Ca.    INTRODUCTION    Levels of minor elements in uncontaminated soils remote from orebodies  (background levels) are of interest for several reasons: such data are one  aspect of the basic characterization of soft; minor elements are part of the  nutritional chain from soil to plants to animals (including man); data on  background levels are essential to' an assessment of the degree of soil contam-  ination with minor elements from industrial and urban wastes.  The purposes of this paper are to present the current information on back-  ground levels (totals) of several minor elements in Canadian mineral soils,  and to indicate relationships between soil genesis and levels of elements in  various horizons of uncultivated soils. Some general relationships are indi-    *LRRI Contribution no. 42; ESRI Contribution no. I-111.    0016-7061/80/0000-0000/$02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    300    cated between levels of elements and physiographic region, and between  levels of certain minor elements and other soil properties.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils    The samples of uncultivated softs were available from previous studies of  soil classification and genesis. McKeague et al. (1979) reported location,  classification, sampling depth and other information. The widespread distri-  bution (Fig. 1) and nature (Table I) of the softs are shown. Samples of the  air-dry material that passed a 2-mm sieve were ground to pass a 300-mesh  (47 pm) sieve. Between 1 and 5 samples were analyzed of each soil; the  maximum would include Ah, Ae, upper B, lower B and C horizons; the  minimum was one C horizon of a Regosolic soft. A total of 173 samples from  53 soils were analyzed and reference soil samples were used as checks.    $  I  3         ,~                                        ~ ~    o            778.  ~                              2f          ' "    "   57~    Fig. 1. Location of sampling sites. The numbers indicate the number of sites in the  general area.    TABLE I  Number of soil sites by physiographic region and soil order*  Region       Order  Brunisolic    Chernozemic  Cryosolic     Gleysolic    Luvisolic    Podzolic    Regosolic    Solonetzic    Appalachian                                              5             2             6  Canadian  Shield                                    2                                        2  St. Lawrence  Lowlands     3                                           5             3             2  Interior  Plains         5             3                            2             3             1  Cordilleran   2                                           1                            4    *Classification is according to the Canadian system (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978).    Co  O    302    Chemical analysis    Minor elements, except Se, were determined by acid dissolution of the  samples and atomic absorption; Se was determined fluorimetrically  (L~vesque and Vendette, 1971). Details of the methods were reported by  McKeague et al. (1979). Results are reported on the basis of oven-dry  (110) soil weight.    RESULTS    The range (Table II) is based on all published data for Canadian soils as  summarized by McKeague et al. (1979). Commonly the mean is below the  midpoint of the range, indicating a somewhat skewed distribution. Data for  some softs close to orebodies, for contaminated soils, and for a few unusual  samples are not included. Examples of the latter are an apparently uncon-  taminated soil with a mercury level of 14 ppm (McKeague and Kloosterman,  1974) and a placic horizon with 15% Mn (McKeague et al., 1968). The mean  values for soils of the United States are those of Shacklette et al. (197ta, b)  for the 200-mesh (&lt;75 #m) fraction of 863 subsurface soil samples. Values  for world soils from Aubert and Pinta (1977) are "ranges of average means".  Mean levels of all minor elements studied except Zn and Se differed signif-    TABLE II  Common ranges and means of minor element levels (ppm) in Canadian soils in com-  parison with means of U.S.A. and world soils    Element      Canadian soils              U.S.A.       World soils (means)  soils  range.I       mean.2       (mean)       Vinogradov   Aubert and  Pinta    Cr             10--100      43            53           200           100--300  Mn         100--1200   520         560         850         500--1000  Co              5--50       21           I0             8           10--15  Ni               5--50        20            20            40            20--30  Cu              5--50       22           25           20           15--40  Zn             10--200       74            54            50            50--100  Se            0.03--2          0~26          0.45          0.01  Sr              30--500     210           240           350  Cd.3             &lt;1                                                    0.5  Hg          0.005--0.1         0.059         0.071         0.01  Pb               5--50        20            20            10            15--25    .1 The range reported includes some 90% of all data reported in the literature for  Canadian soils (McKeague et al,. 1979).  ,2 The mean is the arithmetic mean of data for the 173 samples in this study.  .3 Cd values for all samples analyzed were 0.3 ppm (limit of detection) or below.    TABLE III  Mean levels (ppm) of minor elements by region.1    303    Appalachian.2  Canadian.2  St. Lawrence*~ Interior.2    Cordilleran*:  Shield       Lowlands      Plains  (45)        (12)      (40)        (34)      (19)    SEM.3    Cr   33b            19a         51c            38b         78d          6.2  Mn 401a           430a        660b           377a        787b          73.5  Co   18ab           19ab        24b            15a         34c          2.2  Ni    18a              12a           18a              18a           40b            3.2  Cu   17ab            11a          19b            215         46c           3.0  Zn   81a               54a            80a               64a            73a            13.8  Se 37 0.24a             0.18a         0.24a             0.31a         0.30a          0.026  Sr   71a           417d        303dc          ] 74b        280c          19.9  Hg 33 0.08b          0.11b  32  J.03a     25  0.04ab      0.06ab      0.026  Pb   21b            21b         25b            15a         16ab          2.5    ,1 Within a row, means with no common superscript are significantly different at the 5%  level using the Student t test.  ,2 The no. in parentheses is the no. of samples from the region, excluding those with  carbonates. All elements were determined in all samples with the following exceptions:  Se in Appalachian, 37 values; Hg in Appalachian, 33 values; Hg in St. Lawrence Low-  lands, 32 values; Hg in Interior Plains, 25 values.  ,3 Standard error of the mean based upon the minimum no. of observations in the row (12).    icantly (5% level) among regions (Table III). Thus, for example, samples  from the Cordilleran ~egion had higher levels of Cr, Co and Ni than samples  from other regions and samples from the Appalachian region had significant-  ly less Sr than those from other regions. The limited number of samples from  each region (Fig. 1) must be considered before extrapolating these trends.  Levels of most minor elements were significantly correlated with levels of  other elements or other soil properties such as clay (Table IV). For random  samples from normally distributed populations, a correlation coefficient of  0.3 is significant at the 1% level if there are more than 70 observations (Steel  and Torrie, 1960). Subject to that condition, all of the correlations reported  in Table IV are highly significant. Correlation coefficients between Hg and  other variables were all below 0.3; those for Zn and Pb were only slightly  higher. On the other hand, correlation coefficients for Co, Ni, Cr and Sr with  some of the other variables exceeded 0.6.  Stepwise linear regression analysis was used to test the feasibility of esti-  mating minor element levels from other soil properties. Equations for most  of the elements accounted for less than half of the variability. Much of the  variability of Co and Ni, however, was accounted for by non-carbonate Mg in  some groups of samples and, with data for 23 calcareous samples removed,  Sr was predictable from Ca data (McKeague and Wolynetz, 1979). For the  23 calcareous samples, the correlation between Sr and Ca was only 0.31.    304  TABLE IV  Correlation coefficients between minor element levels and levels of other soil proper-  ties* 1    Org. C Clay Al  Fe  Ti  Ca Mg Cr  Mn Co Ni  Cu Zn Se  Sr  Hg Pb  Cr      .62  .59 .50    .30 .74  0~.59~  Mn             .46 .47              .35  Co        .50  .66 .58 .32     .76 .6  Ni         .40   .49 .49          .69 .64 .48 .73  Cu         .53   .43 .43              .64 .41 .67 .70  Zn                  .31 .37              .33~                 ~,~  Se  .58              .50                   .33              .36  Sr               .43          .87 .37  Hg  Pb  .30  ,1 Numbers of pairs of data points are: 92 for clay--Hg, 109--113 for clay with other  variables and between 130 and 149 for all other pairs. Data for calcareous horizons and  Hg values above 1000 ppm were omitted. Only values of 0.3 or greater are shown. If  the data were normally distributed, the values would be significant at the 1% level.  Since the correlation matrix is symmetric only values below and to the left of the  "diagonal line" are included.    TABLE V  Mean ratios of levels of elements in the Ae and B horizons to those of the associated C  horizons*    Element    Podzolic (11)         Gleysolic (10)         Luvisolic (6)    Ae         B          Ae         B          Ae         B    Cr           0.79       1.3        0.79       0.79       0.76       1.5  Mn         0.53       0.71       0.50       0.82       0.55       0.91  Co          0.58       0.90       0.50       0.77       0.67       1.0  Ni          0.47       0~93       0.37       0.73       0.47       0.93  Cu          0.45       0.65       0.42       0.57       0.56       1.4  Zn          0.60       0.93       0.69       0.93       0.74       1.2  Se          1.0        6.6        1.4        1.8        1.8        3.0  Sr         0.71      0.64      0.90      0.90      0.70      0.81  Hg         2.2       1.5       1.5       1.0       0.5       1,5  Pb         0.75      1.2       0.65      0.90      0,86      1.0    *~ The number of pedons of each order is indicated in parentheses after the name of the  order.    305    Two examples of linear regression equations accounting for high proportions  of variation are:  Sr (ppm)  = 75 + 63 Ca (%), 76%, (139 non-calcareous samples)  Ni (ppm)  = 1.7 + 35.5 Mg (%), 81%, (40 samples from the Appalachian  region)  In most other cases, however, the best linear regression equation accounted  for a much lower percentage of the variability; furthermore, the above equa-  tion for Ni did not fit the data from the other regions.  Levels of most minor elements determined were depleted in Ae horizons  compared to the associated B and C horizons (Table V); the two exceptions  were Se and Hg. The depletion of the Ae horizons of Podzolic and Gleysolic  soils are about equal and perhaps slightly greater for several elements than  that of the Ae horizons of the Luvisolic soils studied. In general, the B hori-  zons of Podzolic and Gleysolic soils are somewhat depleted of minor ele-  ments relative to the associated C horizons; exceptions to this are Se and Hg.  The B horizons of Luvisolic soils, on the other hand, tend to be enriched  relative to the associated C horizons.  For the five pedons having Ah, B, C sequences, on the other hand, the A  and B horizons were either enriched or only slightly depleted of the elements  studied relative to the C horizon (Table VI).    TABLE VI    Ratios of levels of elements in Ah and B horizons to those in the associated C horizons.1  Cr     Mn    Co      Ni       Cu      Zn     Se     Sr       Hg     Pb  Ah   1.5    1.7    0.91     0.92    0.93     1.5    1.7    0.87     1.6    1.0  B    1.7    1.2    0.96    1.1      0.91    1.4    2.1    1.0      1.0    1.0  ,1 Based on data for 5 pedons; 2 Podzolic, 1 Brunisolic, 1 Chernozemic and 1 Solonetzic.    DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    Mean minor element levels reported for Canadian softs are similar to levels  of Shacklette et al. (1971a, b) for the less than 75 pm fraction of subsurface  soil samples from the United States. Many are similar also to estimated  means for world soils but there are some notable differences. For example,  our mean values for Cr is 45 ppm; Vinogradov (1959) estimated 200 ppm. In  the case of Se, our mean value of 0.30 ppm is 30 times that estimated by  Vinogradov. World means for some elements probably differ from Canadian  means because our soils are only slightly weathered relative to soils devel-  oped in ancient materials. Another factor that might account for some of the  differences in estimated means is the fact that Vinogradov's estimates were    306    made many years ago. Current instrumentation and methodology presum-  ably facilitate more accurate determination of trace constituents of soils.  For a few elements, the concentration in a given soil sample can be esti-  mated from other data for that sample. The best example of this is the esti-  mation of Sr from non-carbonate Ca (McKeague and Wolynetz, 1979).  Estimates of Co and Ni from Mg and Fe data are reasonably good for some  regions. However, overall success at estimating levels of a given element from  other properties of the same sample was limited. Such estimates are of only  minor practical significance because the task of dissolving the soil sample is  more time consuming than that of determining an additional element or two  by atomic absorption.  The striking depletion of several elements in Ae horizons demonstrates the  significance of soil morphology in studies of soil geochemistry. If the soils  had been sampled by standard depth increments, this relationship would not  have emerged. Leaching of minor elements from Ae horizons of Podzolic  soils in Canada was documented years ago by Wright et al. (1955) and  Presant (1971). A striking feature of the data presented herein is the indica-  tion that the Ae horizons of Gleysolic soils are as strongly depleted as those  of Podzolic soils. This may indicate that periodic reducing conditions with  leaching may be as effective as organic complexing of metals and leaching in  the translocation of minor elements in soils.    ACKNOWLEDGMENTS    We acknowledge the contributions of J.D. Desjardins who did the chem-  ical analysis and of the Cartography Unit LRRI for preparing the figures.    REFERENCES    Aubert, H. and Pinta, M., 1977. Trace Elements in Soils. (Transl. by L. Zuckerman and  P. Segalen. ) Elsevier~ Amsterdam.  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classification. Can.  Dept. Agric., Publ. 1646.  L~vesque, M. and Vendette, E.D., 1971. Selenium determination in soil and plant mate-  rials. Can. J. Soil Sci., 51: 85--93.  McKeague, J.A. and Kloosterman, B.K., 1974. Mercury in horizons of some soil profiles  in Canada. Can. J. Soil Sci., 54: 503--507.  McKeague, J.A. and Wolynetz, M.S., 1979. Ca--Sr relationships in Canadian soils. Can. J.  Soil Sci., 59: 445--449.  McKeague, J,A., Damman, A.W.H. and Heringa, P.K., 1968. Iron-manganese and other  pans in some soils of Newfoundland. Can. J. Soil Sci,, 48 :-243--253.  McKeague, J.A., Desjardins, J.G. and Wolynetz, M,S., 1979. Minor elements in Canadian  soils. Agric. Can., Ottawa, LRRI Publ. 21.  Presant, E.W., 1971. Geochemistry of iron, manganese, lead, copper, zinc, arsenic, anti-  mony, silver, tin and cadmium in soils of the Bathurst area, New Brunswick: Geol.  Surv. Can., Bull. 174.    307    Shacklette, H.T., Hamilton, J.C., Boerngen, J.G. and Bowles, J.M., 1971a. Elemental  composition of surficial materials in the conterminous United States. U.S. Geol. Surv.  Prof. Pap. 574D.  Shacklette, H.T., Boerngen, J.G. and Turner, R.L., 1971b. Mercury in the environment-  surficial materials of the conterminous United States. U.S. Geol. Surv. Circ., 644: 1--5.  Steel, R.G.D. and Torrie, J.H., 1960. Principles and Procedures of Statistics. McGraw-Hill,  New York, N.Y., 481 pp.  Vinogradov, A.P., 1959. The Geochemistry of Rare and Dispersed Chemical Elements in  Soils, 2nd ed. Consultants Bureau, New York, N.Y.  Wright, J.R., Levick, R. and Atkinson, H.J., 1955. Trace element distribution in virgin  profiles representing four great soil groups. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 19: 340--344.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractBackground levels of some minor elements in 173 samples (53 soils) widely dispersed in Canada are summarized and discussed in relation to data for other soils in Canada and elsewhere. Mean levels (ppm) for the 173 samples are: Cr 43, Mn 520, Co 21, Ni 20, Cu 22, Zn 74, Se 0.3, Sr 210, Hg 0.06 and Pb 20. These are similar to means reported for soils of the United States and, with some exceptions, for world soils. Levels of several of the elements studied differed significantly among physiographic regions.The Ae (eluvial) horizons of Podzolic, Gleysolic and Luvisolic soils were markedly depleted, relative to the associated C horizons, of Mn, Co, Ni, Cu; depletion of Cr, Zn, Pb and Sr was less striking.Though levels of some minor elements are significantly correlated with other soil properties such as clay, organic C, Fe, etc., predictability of the levels of most minor elements from other soil properties is not good. One notable exception is that Sr in noncalcareous samples can be estimated from Ca.