Geoderma, 30 (1983) 1--20                                                           1  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V , Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SUBMICROSCOPY    AND    CHEMISTRY    OF    HEAVY-METAL-  CONTAMINATED  PRECIPITATES  FROM  COLUMN  EXPERIMENTS  SIMULATING CONDITIONS IN A SOIL BENEATH A LANDFILL    E.B A. BISDOM1, A. BOEKESTEIN2, P. CURMI3, P. LAGAS4, A.C. LETSCH5,  J.P.G. LOCH', R. NAUTA' and C.B. WELLS7  1 Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)  2 Techmcal and Physical Engineering Research Servzce, 6700 AJ Wagenzngen (The  Netherlands)  3 INRA, Laboratoire de Science du Sol, 65 Route de St Brieuc, 35042 Rennes, Cedex  (France)  4 Natzonal Institute for Water Supply, 2060 AD Leidschendam (The Netherlands)  s Energy Research Foundation, 1 755 ZG Petten (The Netherlands)  6 Phd~ps, Application Laboratory-Electron Optics, Industrial Equipment Division, Budd-  ing TQ 111-p, Eindhoven (The Netherlands)   CSIRO, Prwate Bag No. 2, Post Office, Glen Osmond, S.A. 5064 (Australia)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bisdom, E.B.A., Boekestein, A., Curmi, P., Lagas, P., Letsch, A.C., Loch, J.P.G., Nauta,  R and Wells, C.B., 1983. Submicroscopy and chemistry of heavy-metal-contaminated  precipitates from column experiments simulating conditions in a soil beneath a land-  fill. Geoderma, 30: 1--20.    The first results of a cooperahve research project of IWGSUSM (International Work-  rag-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials) ave discussed. Wet chemistry  of heavy metals which precipitated during column experiments, simulating conditions in  a soil beneath a landfill, was studied. To compave these data of bulk chemistry with in  situ microchemistry of the same heavy metals, thin sections were made. Using the normal  technique of impregnation, problems are encountered in the hardening process. However,  if gamma radiation is used, an absorbed dose of 5Mrad (50 kGy) was sufficient to havden  the polyester resin.  The first thin sections of the upper 30 cm of a sandy column have now been studied  with SEM-EDX_RA (scanning electron microscope--energy dispersive X-ray analysis) and  initial quantification was tried out using EMA (electron microprobe analysis) and SEM-  WDXRA (scanning electron microscope--wavelength dispersive X-ray analysis). The first  results demonstrate that the heavy-metal-containing cutans (coatings on the walls of voids  and on the surfaces of mineral grains) are brown and black when studied with the light  microscope. The brown ones contain the smallest amounts of heavy metals and the black  ones the largest amounts. Coatings of polluted precipitate ave usually only present on  part of the larger mineral grains; they can be concentrated in small bands, whereby smal-  ler grains are often completely coated, or occur isolated on the surface of a small number  of grains. Brown cutans also often contain fragments of black cutans. The distribution of  Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn and Pb is extremely heterogeneous. Often this heterogeneity is already  present in measurements of precipitates on the surface of one mineral. This indicates a    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    rather extreme variety in composition of the pollutants, even on a mlcroscale, and em-  phasises that submmroscopm techmques are certainly necessary to obtain detailed m sltu  mformatmn The use of a step by step approach and the acquisitmn of numerous data  should eventually allow a good understanding oF the processes at work. STEM (scanning  transmission electron mmroscope)   EDXRA measurements at magnifications larger than   ] 0,000 are of considerable help    INTRODUCTION    The National Institute for Water Supply of the Netherlands has done re-  search, using laboratory columns, on the behavlour of heavy metals beneath  landfills, viz. in soil and groundwater. The study was carried out at the re-  quest of the Netherlands Ministry of Health and Environmental Protection.  The results of these physicochemmal investigations will eventually be used  for soil protection measures. The Netherlands Soil Survey Institute sampled  the columns and studied the precipitates with light microscopy and sub-  mmroscopy m thin sections. Other organizations joined the cooperative re-  search project at a later stage.  The first steps to quantify the polluted precipitates in thin sections, were  done with SEM-EDXRA. Subsequently, EMA (electron mmroprobe analysis)  and SEM-WDXRA (scanning electron microscopy -- wavelength dispersive  X-ray analysis) were carried out using virtually the same material in different  thin sections prepared from the same sample. To obtain analyses at magnifi-  cations larger than 10,000, STEM-EDXRA (scanning transmission electron  microscopy -- energy dispersive X-ray analysis} was done. Such very high  magnifications are important becauseSEM-EDXRA (scanning electron mmro-  scopy - energy dispersive X-ray analysis) has a maximum magnification of  10,000 (Blsdom et al., 1975, 1976).  The present samples were taken from the upper 30 cm of one of three ex-  perimental columns, viz. a column filled with calcareous dune sand. Harden-  mg of the samples raised considerable problems, presumably because of  similar heavy metals in pollutant and catalyst used for the hardening of the  plastm. At present a new method has been introduced at the Netherlands  Soil Survey Institute which allows the hardening of the samples using gamma  radiation (cf. below).  This paper must be regarded as a first approximation showing an in sltu  pmture of an intricate problem which can only be solved by combining  knowledge and techniques of various disciplines. A great deal of attention  has been given here to the results of column experiments which simulate con-  ditlons in a soft beneath a landfill (Loch et al., 1981; Lagas and Loch, 1981).  Mathematical models (Van Eijkeren and Loch, 1981) are being developed to  describe the transport of polluted materials in soils.  The column experiments were mitiated to test the results of earlier re-  search of the landfill Ambt-Delden in the Province of Overijssel, The Nether-  lands. Wet chemistry had demonstrated that the presence of fatty acids in    leachates from the landfill affected the behaviour of heavy metals. Conse-  quently, column experiments were set up in which leachates were applied  both with and without fatty acids but always with the heavy metals iron,  nickel, copper, zinc and lead. Various interesting results were obtained with  the experimental approach which lasted seven months. Control of the experi-  ments was enhanced by periodic sampling and analysis of the soil solution at  several depths m the columns.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Experimental set-up    Experimental columns were made of grey polythene with a length of 140  cm and a diameter of 18 cm (Fig. 1). Five tap-points were made in the wall  of a column at 20 cm intervals (Lagas and Loch, 1981). A perforated poly-  ~hene tube of 18 cm length penetrated from each tap point into the column.  These perforated tubes were positioned alternatively perpendicular to each  other. The percolation rate was 1.6 cm day-~ (Loch et al., 1981).  A total of 3 columns were percolated with this leachate, viz. the column  with calcareous dune sand, one with the same sand and dispersed fine clay,  and the third with sand and clay aggregates. The clay aggregates had a dia-    Fig. 1. Experimental column 1 with calcareous sandy material and polluted precipitates.  Five tap-points and the position of the associated polythene tubes, which cross the poly-  thene column at 90to each other, are discernable.    meter of 2 to 4 cm. The sand/clay ratio of the columns with clay was 10 : 1.  The column from which the present thm sections were derived was treated  with synthetic landfill leachate without fatty acids.    Composzt~on of the input solution    The leachates applied to the columns are similar to the actual leachate at  the Ambt-Delden landfill. In these experiments the methanogenic phase in a  landfill (cf. Hoeks, 1978) was simulated by using leachates without fatty  acids, containing the same heavy metals as the Ambt-Delden leachate (Lagas  and Loch, 1981, Loch et al., 1981}. This leachate was synthesized and its  composition is indmated in Table I.    TABLE I    Composition of the input solution used in the experiments (g/l)    Ascorbm acid                            1.8  Chloride                               9.2  Sulphate                               2.0  Total carbonate                        0.18  Sodium                                  1 6  Potassium                             0 8  Ammonium                            0.7  Calcmm                                 1.6  Magnesmm                            0.49  Iron                                   1.40  Manganese                             0.055  Copper                                0.064  Zinc                                   0.065  Lead                                   0.208  Nickel                                 0.059    During the experiment ascorbm acid was added as a redox buffer in order  to keep the redox potential of the solution low. The pH of the pore water  was 5.7 during the experiment and a redox potential of 150 mV could be  maintained. The concentrations of Fe, Zn and Mn in the input solution were  substantially higher. This high concentration of heavy metals was chosen to  allow a comparison of the behavlour of the metals and to obtain measurable  concentrations In the percolate.  The reasoning for synthesizing a percolate with this composition was  mainly to obtain a known and constant composition of the leachate m the  laboratory. Percolate from the field was not acceptable because production  and composition of percolate in a landfill is not constant.    Analysis of percolates and solid materials    The procedure used for the chemical analysis of soil solution (percolate)  and the results have been described by Lagas and Loch (1981). Percolation    was terminated after seven months. The soil material m the columns was  drained to field capacity and subsequently frozen. The sampling for chemical  analysis of the solid materials was done every 5 cm. Sand and clay aggregates  were sampled separately. Separate samples were also taken for XRD analysis.  Soluble salts and exchangeable adsorbed cations of the solid materials  were extracted with a 0.5 M BaC12-solution (Loch et al., 1981). Subsequent-  ly, the precipitated and strongly adsorbed forms of the metals and other  cations were extracted with 0.1 N HC1. Metal concentrations in the extracts  were determined by atomic absorption spectroscopy.    The preparation of thin sections and the use of gamma radiation to harden  the polyester resin    Plastic impregnated samples, taken from the column with calcareous dune  sand (Figs. 2 and 3) and other types, raised considerable problems or were  impossible to harden with the method described by Jongerius and Hemtz-  berger (1975); a procedure commonly used for the preparation of thin sec-  tions of soils. Recent experiments with gamma radiation at the Netherlands  Soil Survey Institute to harden the present samples, proved that this could  be done in two days if the absorbed dose was 5 Mrad (50 kGy) or more.  The gamma radiation is obtained from a plate-shaped source in which a  number of bars with Cobalt-60 are placed in a rack. Each bar is able to pro-  v:de 1,000 Curies (37 1012 Bq) or more, depending on the type of installa-    Fig. 2. Rings of predominantly black polluted precipitate just after defrosting of the col-  umn    Fig. 3 A 15 8 5 cm metal sample box was used for sampling the tubewhmhhada  diameter of 18 cm The box penetrated 5 cm into the polluted sand and will allow the  preparation of a thin section with 15 cm length and 8 cm width.    tion used. The best way to operate with success is to use the "train" prin-  ciple whereby samples move several times past the radiation source with  intermittent rest-periods of an hour or more.  The gamma Irradiation method was also used for samples of the Nether-  lands Soil Survey Institute and of the International Soil Museum which had  not hardened m the past. Most of the samples hardened sufficiently for the  preparation of thm sections. Further tests should be made, however, to ob-  tain detailed knowledge on possibilities to harden various types of soft sam-  ples usmg plastics and gamma radiation. Samples from which the monosty-  rene or acetone diluter of the polyester resin have been removed, can thus  be hardened quickly. Such samples include those of saline and volcanic soils  plus heavy metal-polluted and oil-impregnated samples. The impression is  that the new method also gives harder samples in which the soft material is  less easily destroyed and which carries less grinding powder. Additional tests  will be performed to get an idea of the complete range of possibilities,  amongst whmh the possibility to work at different temperatures during  gamma irradiation of the soil samples. The present tests also proved that  pieces of thin sections, which did not harden completely, do so upon gamma  irradiation.    TRANSPORT  AND  RETENTION  OF  HEAVY  METALS  IN  THE  SOIL  --  RESULTS    Former results    A number of results from earlier work are of importance for the present  interpretation of analytical data obtained from the column experiments.  Clay minerals play a major role in the retention of heavy metals transported  through a soil or experimental column. Such ions are usually present at very  low concentrations when adsorption takes place on colloidal surfaces and  under these conditions a very low reversibility of the process is possible be-  cause of preferential adsorption by chemmal bonding (Harmsen, 1977).  Soil organic matter, especially humic and fulvic acids, can also adsorb  heavy-metal cations. This adsorption and that on oxides and hydroxides of  Mn, Fe and A1 is of a chemical nature (Bar-Yosef et al., 1975).  The mobility of copper in soils is usually very low. Strong complexatlon  of copper with soil humlc acid has been reported (Sposito et al., 1976}. If  sulphides of heavy metals can form in the leachate of the landfill, they may  precipitate in the underlying soft profile.  Under equilibrium conditions (Lagas and Harmsen, 1980) and when fatty  acids are present m a concentration of 0.3 mol/1, heavy metals in the soil can  be present in larger percentages than monovalent positively charged, un-  charged and negatively charged complexes. The effect is that the precipita-  tion and adsorption of the metals as cations is severely reduced.    Results of the column experzments    Precipitation of iron, nickel, copper, zmc and lead was demonstrated.  Breakthrough curves (Lagas and Loch, 1981} indicated that copper and lead  remained predominantly m the columns. Physicochemical processes are  thought to be responsible for the retalnment of copper and lead.  Iron, nickel and zinc percolated through the columns together with sulph-  ate at the start of the experiment. After six to eight weeks the nickel, zinc,  iron and sulphate concentrations decreased in the percolate. Apparently,  sulphate-reducing bacteria triggered the precipitation of iron, nickel and  zinc in the form of sulphides. There was probably not enough sulphide to  precipitate all the iron as FeS. Possibly Cu and Pb were also precipitated as  sulphides.  Further physicochemical information on the behaviour of metals in the  columns during experiments will be discussed in a follow-up paper at the  1982 workshop of IWGSUSM in Paris. By then a great deal of the distribu-  tion of Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn, Pb and S over column one will also have been studied,  together with some of the other columns using light mmroscopy and sub-  microsocpy. This distribution, measured by SEM-EDXRA-WDXRA, STEM-  EDXRA and EMA, can then be compared with chemical measurements of  bulk water samples and light microscopic observations.    ,    Results of submtcroscopic and hght rntcroscopic studies of precipitates    Only the upper part, v~z the top 30 cm, of one column with calcareous  dune sand has so far been examined with SEM-EDXRA (Blsdom et al.,  1981a, Bisdom, 1983). The middle sample, at a depth from 15 to 20 cm, was  also analysed by EMA, SEM-WDXRA and STEM. The other two samples  came from depths 0--5 cm and 25--30 cm.    Light mzcroscopy  Light mmroscoplc observations demonstrated that only very httle precipi-  tate (grain cutans, coatings) was present on the surface of the mineral grains  and on the wall of pores in the upper 5 cm of the experimental column. Car-  bonate was hardly found m the upper 5 cm. Precipitates were abundantly  present at a depth of 15 -20 cm and carbonate was still virtually absent.  Both polluted precipitates and separate carbonate grams were found at a  depth of 25--30 cm in the column.  Detailed reformation on the distribution of the pollutants with depth will  follow m a later paper when more samples have been hardened and prepared  into thm sections. So far, light microscopy has demonstrated the presence of  two types of cutans m the samples, VlZ. black and brown ones. The colours  of the samples m the columns, immediately after sampling, were predomi-  nantly black m a reductlve environment. During preparation of the samples  oxidation of some of them took place. Colour changes were observed during  the drymg and treatment of samples, e.g. from black to green and brown.  After preparation of thin sections only brown and black cutans or mix-  tures of them were observed with the light microscope in pores and on the  surface of mineral grams. The brown polluted material was predominantly  isotropic whmh usually indicated poorly crystalline or amorphous materials.  The black cutans remained black under crossed polarizers and no further m-  formation was obtained with transmitted light.  Bands with brown and black cutans were found m the lower two thin sec-  tions. Mixtures of the two types of cutans were frequently present between  such bands. No special position of black and brown material has yet been  found in mixed cutans and grain cutans. Even on the surface of one mmeral  gram very heterogeneous mixtures of black and brown cutamc polluted ma-  terial could be found, often with diffuse boundaries. Only one hght micro-  scopm mlcrograph is shown (Fig. 4) of different types of cutans because they  become similar m appearance when printed in black and white. To obtain  additional information on the nature and composition of the precipitates,  submicroscopy was used, VlZ. SEM-EDXRA, SEM-WDXRA, EMA and STEM-  EDXRA.    SEM-EDXRA  EDXRA analysis of the brown and black cutans indicated that black  cutans (Fig. 5) contained S, Fe, N1, Cu, Zn and Pb, whereas less elements    Fig. 4. Brown cutans (polluted precipitates) in pores and on the surface of mineral grains.  Black cutans (coatings) and mixed brown and black cutans are similar m appearance when  printed in black and white. Plane polarized light.    were found in the brown cutans, i.e. usually S, Fe and Ni (Bisdom et al.,  1981a; Bisdom, 1983). When a mixture of brown and black cutans occurred,  the number of elements increased in such precipitates. Apart from these ele-  ments Al, Si, CI, K and Ca were also found. A1 and Si are constituents of the  soil and were not present in the fluids used m this expemment. Measurements  of such elements m point analyses indicate therefore either a protrusion of  the mineral grain at a shallow level underneath the cutan or the presence of  the A1 and Si in clay minerals, microcrystaUine materials or amorphous sub-  stances.  Cutans having a very irregular distribution of heavy metals may show this  in BESI (Bisdom and Thiel, 1981). They usually represent mixtures of black  and brown cutanic materials. Experience has shown that poorly crystalhne  and amorphous materials may cause problems in BESI (backscattered elec-  tron scanning images) portrayal of materials in thin sections. This is probably  also the case for the predominantly brown cutanic materials which usually  raise problems in BESI-portrayal. This electron microscopic behaviour would  support the light microscopic analysis of isotropm amorphous brown cutanic  materials in thin sections. It also indicates that BESI portrayal of mixed  brown and black cutanic materials mainly concerns the black material.    10    Fig. 5. SRM-EDXRA of a black heavy-metal-contaminated cutan on the surface of quartz  grains and in the periphery of pores. The first ~mage gives a backscattered electron scan-  rang image (BESI) Concentrations of white in the three X-ray images give the distribution  of Si, S and Fe in the precipitate and minerals. Point analyses indicate the presence of  heavy metals such as Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn and Pb and variability of these elements m the preci-  pitate present on one mineral grain.    A special case of the effects of pollutants from a landfill on soil compo-  nents is given in Fig. 6. It is a shell fragment consisting of aragonite which  shows precipitation of pollutants both on its surface and internally. Both  black and brown pollutants are found in the shell in the form of discontinu-  ous concentric rings. Absorption of the pollutants by the aragonite probably  occurred along very small pores, cleavages and dislocations, because no larger  microcracks were detected in the shell with BESI or with secondary electron    11    images (SEI). A larger number of point analyses were made in six evenly  spaced traverses over the width of the shell fragment, including precipitates  on the periphery of the shell fragment. They indicated that microchemical  differences could exist in one concentric ring.  The adsorption of pollutants by carbonate and sometimes in the cracks of  quartzes indicate that minerals may store polluted substances for longer or  shorter times. This will probably be in smaller quantltms than storage by  clays or organic matter, but may be a factor when reclamation of polluted  soils is planned.    EMA and SEM-WDXRA  Electron microprobe analysis (EMA) and scanning electron microscopy-  wavelength dispersive X-ray analysis (SEM-WDXRA) were done on the thin  section from 15 to 20 cm depth to obtain semi-quantitative microchemical  analysis results with the help of a number of standards. No definite figures  can be given here, however, because of the extreme heterogeneity which  could be present in one cutan. These semi-quantitative analyses demon-  strated the presence of somewhat more heavy metals than $EM-EDXRA did  m the brown cutans, viz. less than one weight per cent for Ni, Cu, Zn and  Pb. The Fe was present in much larger quantities than the other heavy metals  in the brown cutans, viz. from 12 to 17 wt.%. The distribution of these ele-  ments and of A1, Si and S is given in the X-ray images of Fig. 7. Part of the  brown cutan is vaguely recogmsable around the blackish quartz grain in the  absorbed electron image made with EMA (Cameca MS 46).  The black cutans comprise much more Cu (up to 15 wt.%) than the brown  cutans according to some analyses. Pb can be present up to 3 wt.%, while NI  and Zn usually stay below 1 wt.%. Fe is somewhat higher than in the brown  cutans, viz. up to 19 wt.%. The amount of sulphur was also higher in the  black cutans than m the brown ones, but has only been measured so far with  SEM-WDXRA. Only a part of the black cutan, which extends between two  mineral grains which are not visible on the micrograph, is visible in black in  the absorbed electron image of Fig. 8. The real width of the cutan is por-  trayed in the white band of the X-ray image of Fe. Apart from the heavy  metals Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn and Pb, X-ray images of Si and S are also given.  To obtain microanalytmal results which mclude the quantification of trace  elements in the cutans, one should use ion microscopy (Bisdom et al., 1977,  1983; Henstra et ai., 1980, 1981}. Another method, which gives no quanti-  tative results at present but which can indicate the presence of trace ele-  ments, is laser microprobe mass analysis (Bisdom et al., 1981b). So far, how-  ever, none of these techmques has been used in this cooperative research  project.    STEM-EDXRA  The scanning transmission electron microscope--energy dispersive X-ray  analyzer (STEM-EDXRA), a Philips EM 400T, was used to study microvaria-    12    Fig  6. BESI of shell fragment with surrounding fragments of mineral grains, the other  parts of which are situated outside the micrograph. X-ray images of SL Ca and Fe. Vari-  ous point analyses to illustrate compositional differences in the discontinuous concentric  bands of polluted material which invaded the shell fragment.    13    14    Fig. 7 EMA of a brown cutan The cutan Is vaguely present on the surface of a mineral  gram m the absorbed electron image. X-ray images of Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn and Pb (polluting  heavy metals), S, Al and Si were made    tlons in chemmal elements m a black cutan {Fig. 9). This can be done at  higher magnifications than the 10,000 possible with SEM-EDXRA. In the  present case good micrographs stopped at a magnification of X 25,000, be-  coming vague at higher ones. A number of point analyses, two of which are  shown in Fig. 9, were made m the black cutan at 25,000 and demonstrated  peaks of predominantly Fe and Ni for the heavy metals. The peaks for Cu,  Zn and Pb were very small but present. Other elements were AI, Si, S, C1, K  and Ca. The peak of Si, to the right of the small Al-peak, is not indicated due  to computer programming and insufficient space for the symbol of the    15    Fig. 8. EMA of a black cutan in a void which extends between two mineral grams that are  not visible in the absorbed electron image. X-ray images of Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn, Pb, S and Si.    element. The totality of peaks showed a similar configuration for all point  analyses and height differences of the peaks for the individual elements in  the four points were small.    XRD  To obtain an idea whether crystalhsed forms are also present m the black  and brown cutans, the precipitate was concentrated for XRD (X-ray diffrac-  tion) analysis (Breeuwsma and Balkema, 1981). Most of the loose samples  contained PbS (galena) while FeS (mackinawite) was represented m the larg-  est number of samples. No crystalhsed forms of Cu, Zn and Ni were found    16    Fig 9. STEM-EDXRA of a black cutan on the surface of a quartz grain. BESI at various  magnifications up to 25,000 At 12,500 and 25,000 small partmles can be discerned  in predominantly poorly crystalline and amorphous polluted precipitate Point analyses  show that Fe and N1 were the dominant heavy metals in this precipitate, with less Cu, Zn  and Pb. Other elements in the black cutan were A1, Si, S, C1, K and Ca.    17    with XRD analysis. The reason why PbS formed and no CuS, ZnS and NiS,  was because of the possibility to incorporate the small Cu2 Zn2and Ni2 ions in the FeS lattice whilst the Pb2ion was too large and therefore com-  bined with S to galena. This explanation may be applicable to a number of  cases but the real picture seems to be somewhat more complicated according  to hght mmroscopic and submicroscopic analysis. For example, Cu can be  found in some samples in such quantities that they are comparable to the  quantity of iron. Consequently, not all the copper can be stored in the FeS  lattice under such circumstances. Also, the existence of black and brown  cutans, with differences In composition, cannot be established with XRD  analysis. The same is true for microchemical analysis of poorly crystallised  and amorphous materials, when only studied with XRD-techmques. The  strength of the latter technique IS, however, that we get significant informa-  tion about the identity of the crystallised forms in the pollutants.  XRD analysis showed that galena and mackinawite can be found in the  cutans and grain cutans of polluted material which precipitated on mineral  grains and in voids. The mlcrographs m Fig. 9 indicate that small crystalhtes  are possibly present in the black cutans at magnifications of 12,500 and  25,000. Such microcrystallites, after concentration procedure to obtain  sufficient material, are probably the PbS and FeS found by Breeuwsma and  Balkema (1981) with XRD analysis. Under natural conditions these micro-  crystalhtes are embedded in poorly crystallised and amorphous materials as  indicated by light microscopy and submicroscopy.    Discussion  When the chemical elements in the brown and black cutans are com-  pared, SEM-EDXRA analysis indicated that S was present in both cutans and  less heavy metals in the brown cutans. SEM-WDXRA and EMA analysis  demonstrated that virtually all chemical elements found in the black cutans  can also be present In the brown ones. SEM-EDXRA only found Fe and Ni  in the sample at a depth of 15--20 cm in the experimental column (Bisdom  et al., 1981a; Bisdom, 1983). It was indicated, however, that more sensitive  techniques could also possibly show the presence of Cu, Zn and Pb in the  brown cutans. This was indeed the case with SEM-WDXRA and EMA, but  the brown cutans retained less heavy metals than the black ones. Light  microscopic observations have indicated that mixtures of brown and black  cutans also exist. This probably indicates a genetic relation between the  brown and black cutans. The isolated black flecks usually had a composition  similar to that of black cutans, whereas the surrounding or adjacent brown  materials showed the common composition with less heavy metals. This  mixed occurrence of black and brown material in one cutan is thought to  indicate that the black cutans possibly represent a brown cutan in which the  crystallisation of heavy-metal sulphides has occurred to a degree at which  FeS and PbS formed. The black colour of the cutan could then be explained  by the presence of considerable quantities of very small crystallltes of FeS  and PbS in the cutanic material.    18    Finally, somethmg must be said about the other elements whmh can be  measured in black and brown cutans, viz. A1, $1, C1, K and Ca. These ele-  ments are not found by XRD analysis but frequently measured with sub-  mmroscopic techniques. Various posslbflltms exist to explain the presence of  these elements. The one chosen for the moment lmphes that the elements  possibly represent minute quantities of clay minerals and mmrocrystalline  materials m the black cutans especially, or form part of the poorly crystal-  hne and amorphous material of black and brown cutans.    CONCLUSIONS    In the column expemments the conditions were similar to those of the  methanogenyc phase m the landfill. Metal sulphides precipitated in the col-  umn and thin sections from the upper 30 cm were made for m situ analysis  of the precipitates (cutans). This was done with hght mmroscopy, SEM-  EDXRA-WDXRA, EMA and STEM-EDXRA. It gave m sltu information on  the mlcrochemistry and on the constituents of gram cutans (coatings) and  cutans on the walls of voids. These data could be compared with the ones  from XRD done on bulk samples after concentration of the pollutants to  obtain sufficient material for analysis. XRD indicated the presence of FeS  (mackmawite) and PbS (galena), while wet chemical and submlcroscoplcal  analysis found, m addition, Cu, Zn, Ni and S.  Some of the Cu, Zn and N1 may be incorporated in the FeS lattice, but  the Cu concentrations in the cutans were sometimes too high. Consequently,  CuS could possibly also form if crystalhsatlon takes place m such minor  quantities that the amount of material is too small for XRD analysis. The  same may be true of ZnS and N1S but in still smaller quantities than CuS. A  lot of poorly crystallised and amorphous material is usually present m both  types of cutans as indicated by hght microscopy and submicroscopy.  Brown cutans were usually isotropic when observed with the light micro-  scope and did not give good quality BESI (backscattered electron scanning  images) or secondary electron images (SEI). With the EMA the brown cutan  became vaguely visible using an absorbed electron image (Fig. 7). This indi-  cates a poorly crystalline or amorphous state of the material. The brown  cutans had less heavy metals than the black ones as far as quantity is con-  cerned. Not all the brown cutans had Cu, Zn and Pb but Fe and N1 could  usually be found together with S.  Black cutans exhibited small partmles when analysed with the EM 400T,  an apparatus which can operate as a SEM, TEM and STEM coupled with  EDXRA at low and very high magnifications. These particles were mter-  preted as probably being the minerals galena and mackinawlte m the form of  mlcrocrystalline material which coloured the cutan black. Apart from the  PbS and FeS minerals, the black cutans also contained Ni, Zn and Cu in  minor quantltms but frequently a little more than was present in the brown  cutans. Only Fe reached 12--17 wt.% m the brown cutans, while Ni, Cu, Zn    19    and Pb stayed below 1 wt.%. Iron in the black cutans could be 18 wt.%,  copper up to 15 wt.% and lead 3 wt.%. Ni and Zn remained below 1 wt.% in  the black cutans. Black cutans were interpreted as being a further stage In  cutan development than brown ones because they exhibit crystallised very  small materials and can be present as flecks in a brown cutan with very vague  boundaries between brown and black substances. In the black cutans, how-  ever, a lot of poorly crystallised and amorphous materials is still visible when  observed at high magmfications of 25,000 or more.  The polluted heavy-metal-containing solutions were also observed to in-  vade a shell fragment and to form virtually concentric and continuous bands.  The composition of the precipitate in the shell is similar to that found in  black and brown cutans, and, like these, can be extremely heterogeneous  over mlcrodistances in the same band. Such measurements can only be made  with submicroscopic techniques for in situ analysis.  Future submicroscopic and light microscopic investigations will concen-  trate on the manner in which cutans (coatings, precipitates) are distributed  in the three columns, I.e. with respect to mineral grains, clays and voids  (pores). These data will help to develop mathematical models to describe  the transport of polluted materials in soils. In situ analysis of the chemical  elements in the cutans will be compared with physicochemical data obtained  from percolates and solid soil materials.    REFERENCES    Bar-Yosef, B., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1975. Zinc adsorption and diffusion in goe-  thite. J. Soil Sci, 26: 1--21.  Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981. Light microscopic and submmroscoplc analysis of thin sections of  soils. Agron. Abstr., p. 196.  Bisdom, E B.A., 1983 In situ microanalysis of man-made precipitates in soil beneath a  landfill and on the surface of a water-tube filter. In' R Hallberg (Editor), Environmen-  tal  Biogeochemistry.  5th  International  Symposium  on  Environmental  Biogeo-  chemistry, 1981, Stockholm. Ecol. Bull., 35:547--553  Bisdom, E.B A and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  in thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-EDXRA  In  E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st  Workshop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed  Soil Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wagenmgen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerius, A. and Thiel, F., 1975. Energy-dispersive X-ray  analysis on thin sections and unimpregnated soil material. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 23(4)'  113--125.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Hornsveld, E.M., Jongerius, A. and Letsch, A.C., 1976.  Wavelength and energy dispersive X-ray microanalysis with EMA and SEM-EDXRA  on thin sections of soils. Neth. J. Agrm. Sci., 24(4)' 209--222.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerius, A., Brown, J.D., yon Rosenstiel, A.P. and Gras,  D.J., 1977. Light and heavy element detection in thin sections of soils with the ion  mmroprobe mass analyzer (IMMA). Neth J. Agrm. Sch, 25(1): 1--13.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Heintzberger, G. and Lagas, P., 1981a. SEM-EDXRA measurements on  thin sections of heavy metal contaminated soil samples from column experiments In:    20    W van Dul]venbooden, P. Glasbergen and H. van Lelyveld (Editors), Quality of  Groundwater Proceedings of an International Symposium, Noordwijkerhout, 1981  Studies in Environmental Science. Vol 17. Elsevmr, Amsterdam, pp. 489--493.  Blsdom, E B.A., Henstra. S., Jongerius, A., Hemen, H J and Meier, S , 1981b. Chemmal  element detection m thin sectmns of softs with the laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500). Neth J. Agnc Sct , 29(1) 23--36  Bisdom, E.B A, Henstra, S., Werner, H W, Boudewijn, P, De Grefte, H A.M., Knippen-  berg, W F, Gourgout, J M and Migeon, H N, 1983 Quantitative analysis of trace and  other elements m thin sectmns of soils with the secondary ion microscope (Cameca)  Geoderma, 30 117--134 (this Issue)  Breeuwsma, A and Balkema, W., 1981 Mineralogisch onderzoek naar de preclpitatie van  zware metalen in percolatmproeven met vuilstortwater Report No 1593 Netherlands  Soil Survey Institute, Wagenmgen, The Netherlands, 23 pp.  Harmsen, K, 1977. Behaviour of heavy metals m soft. Agmc. Res_ Rep 866 Centre for  Agricultural Pubhshing and Documentation (Pudoc), Wagenmgen, 171 pp.  Henstra, S, Bisdom, E.B A, Jongerms, A, Morgan, A.E., Werner, H W. and De Grefte,  H A M, 1980  Quantitative analysis on thin sections of soils by secondary ion mass  spectrometry In P Brederoo and V E. Cosslett (Editors), Electron Microscopy 1980  Proceedings of the 7th European Congress on Electron Microscopy including the 9th  International Conference on X-ray Optics and Mmroanalysis, The Hague, Vol. 3. Anal-  ysis  Seventh European Congress on Electron Mmroseopy Foundation, Leiden, pp.  224--225  Henstra, S., Blsdom, E B.A  and Boekestein, A., 1981. Submicroscopic techmques for  m situ mmrochemlcal analysis of soils, III. Destructive techmques In E B A. Blsdom  (Editor}, Submmroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submmroscopy of Undisturbed Soft Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wagenmgen  Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentatmn (Pudoc),  Wagenlngen, pp. 55--65_  Hoeks, J, 1978. BlochemLsche afbraakprocessen blj composteren en storten van vaste  afvalstoffen ICW-Nota 1103, Wagenmgen, 15 pp.  Jongerius, A. and Hemtzberger, G, 1975  Methods m soil micromorphology  A tech-  tuque for the preparation of large thin sections. Soil Surv Pap., 10 Netherlands Soil  Survey Institute, Wageningen, 48 pp.  Lagas, P and Harmsen, K , 1980 Complexering van zware metalen in vullstortpercolaat  (Delden)  RID-Report CBH 80-01  Natmnal Institute for Water Supply, Leldschen-  dam, 43 pp.  Lagas, P. and Loch, J P G., 1981 Column experiments on the behawour of heavy metals  in soil. RID-Mededehng, 81-2. National Institute for Water Supply, Leidschendam,  96 pp  Loch, J P G , Lagas, P. and Harmg, B.J A.M , 1981. Behaviour of heavy metals m soil be-  neath a landfill, results of model experiments. In  W. van Duijvenbooden, P Glas-  bergen and H  van Lelyveld (Editors), Quahty of Groundwater. Proceedings of an  International Symposium, Noordwtjkerhout, The Netherlands, 1981. Studies in En-  vironmental Science, Vol. 17 Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 545--555. (Also in Sci. Total  Environ., 21 (1981) 203--213 )  Sposlto, G , Holtzclaw, K.M. and Baham, J., 1976 Analytical properties of the soluble,  metal-complexing fractions in sludge-soil mixtures 2. Comparative structural chemistry  of fulvic acid. Soil Scl Soc Am. J., 40 691--697  Van Eijkeren, J.C.H and Loch, J.P G, 1981. Modellering van Bodemverontreiniging. RID  Jaarverslag. In press                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractThe first results of a cooperative research project of IWGSUSM (International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials) are discussed. Wet chemistry of heavy metals which precipitated during column experiments, simulating conditions in a soil beneath a landfill, was studied. To compare these data of bulk chemistry with in situ microchemistry of the same heavy metals, thin sections were made. Using the normal technique of impregnation, problems are encountered in the hardening process. However, if gamma radiation is used, an absorbed dose of 5Mrad (50 kGy) was sufficient to harden the polyester resin.The first thin sections of the upper 30 cm of a sandy column have now been studied with SEM-EDXRA (scanning electron microscope—energy dispersive X-ray analysis) and initial quantification was tried out using EMA (electron microprobe analysis) and SEM-WDXRA (scanning electron microscope—wavelength dispersive X-ray analysis). The first results demonstrate that the heavy-metal-containing cutans (coatings on the walls of voids and on the surfaces of mineral grains) are brown and black when studied with the light microscope. The brown ones contain the smallest amounts of heavy metals and the black ones the largest amounts. Coatings of polluted precipitate are usually only present on part of the larger mineral grains; they can be concentrated in small bands, whereby smaller grains are often completely coated, or occur isolated on the surface of a small number of grains. Brown cutans also often contain fragments of black cutans. The distribution of Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn and Pb is extremely heterogeneous. Often this heterogeneity is already present in measurements of precipitates on the surface of one mineral. This indicates a rather extreme variety in composition of the pollutants, even on a microscale, and emphasises that submicroscopic techniques are certainly necessary to obtain detailed in situ information. The use of a step by step approach and the acquisition of numerous data should eventually allow a good understanding of the processes at work. STEM (scanning transmission electron microscope) — EDXRA measurements at magnifications larger than x 10,000 are of considerable help.