 Song exposure during juvenile dispersal in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows  Evolution of intelligence and vocal mimicking  The biology of bird-song dialects  Song dialects and mate selection in montane White-Crowned Sparrows  Song learning in montane White-crowned Sparrows: From whom and when?  Social interaction, sensitive phases and the song template hypothesis in the White-crowned Sparrow  Song learning in birds: Diversity and plasticity, opportunities and challenges  The time of habitat selection by birds  Long-term persistence of song dialects in the Mountain White-crowned Sparrow  Birdsong: From behavior to neuron  Nonlocal male Mountain White-crowned Sparrows have lower paternity and higher parasite loads than males singing local dialect  Cultural and genetic evolution in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows: Song dialects are associated with population structure  Physiological and behavioural responses of female Mountain White-crowned Sparrows to natal- and foreign-dialect songs  A comparative approach to vocal learning: Song development in White-crowned Sparrows  Song &ldquo;dialects&rdquo; in three populations of White-crowned Sparrows  Culturally transmitted patterns of vocal behavior in sparrows  The Mountain White-crowned Sparrow: Migration and reproduction at high altitude  Reproductive cycle and nesting success of Mountain White-crowned Sparrow (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha ) in the central Sierra Nevada  Postfledging dispersal, habitat imprinting, and philopatry in a montane, migratory sparrow  Song overproduction and selective attrition lead to song sharing in the Field Sparrow (  Spizella pusilla  )  Song overproduction, selective attrition and song dialects in the White-crowned Sparrow  Learning by instruction or selection: Implications for patterns of geographic variation in bird song  Selection-based learning in bird song development  A comparative approach to vocal learning: Intraspecific variation in the learning process  Late song learning in Song Sparrows  Selective attrition and individual song repertoire development in Song Sparrows  Song of chingolo,  Zonotrichia capensis , in Argentina: Description and evaluation of a system of dialects  Song dialects in several populations of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha ) in the Sierra Nevada  Population structure and social behavior: Models for testing the ecological significance of song dialects in birds  Factors influencing song development in the White-crowned Sparrow (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  )  Song development in the White-crowned Sparrow: Modification of learned song  Vocal dialects and their possible relation to honest status signaling in the Brown-headed Cowbird  Current address: Department of Biology, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, USA  Current address: FDR Medical Services, Orchard Park, New York, USA  Current address: Department of Environmental Science and Policy, University of California, Davis, California, USA  Current address: Department of Biology, University of Texas&ndash;Pan American, Edinburg, Texas, USA  The degree to which local song structure reflects the singer's population of origin is a long-standing and contentious issue. Young songbirds that settle to breed outside their natal song-dialect area may learn to produce nonnatal dialect by hearing and memorizing these songs during juvenile dispersal. We quantified adult singing rates in a population of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha ) in the Sierra Nevada in 2 yr, and compared them with the arrival schedule of juveniles not hatched on the study area. Our results show that opportunities for juveniles to learn new (nonnatal) song types become highly limited during the premigratory dispersal phase, because adult singing rates are very low by the time nonlocal juveniles begin to arrive. Thus, if individuals learn nonnatal songs during dispersal, they must do so hearing relatively few repetitions of the unfamiliar dialect.  El grado al que la estructura local del canto refleja la poblaci&oacute;n de origen del ave que canta es un tema pol&eacute;mico de vieja data. Las aves canoras j&oacute;venes que se establecen y reproducen por fuera del &aacute;rea de su dialecto natal podr&iacute;an aprender a producir el dialecto no natal al escuchar y memorizar cantos durante la dispersi&oacute;n juvenil. Cuantificamos las tasas de canto de adultos en una poblaci&oacute;n de   Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha  en la Sierra Nevada por dos a&ntilde;os y las comparamos con las fechas de llegada de aves juveniles que no eclosionaron en el &aacute;rea de estudio. Nuestros resultados muestran que las oportunidades para que los j&oacute;venes aprendan nuevos tipos de cantos (no natales) es &aacute;ltamente limitada durante la fase de dispersi&oacute;n pre-migratoria,debido a que las tasas de canto de los adultos son muy bajas en el momento en que los j&oacute;venes no locales empiezan a llegar. Entonces, si los individuos aprenden cantos no natales durante la dispersi&oacute;n, deben hacerlo escuchando relativamente pocas repeticiones del dialecto no familiar para ellos.   Palabras clave:  canto, dialecto, dispersi&oacute;n juvenil, aprendizaje,   Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha   Song learning in oscine passerines is an important process whereby individuals develop a species-specific repertoire of communication signals. The form of a mature song typically depends on the timing of exposure to stimuli during a young bird's sensitive phase. Sensory deficits or disruptions during this critical period of song learning can have severe consequences for the development of appropriate adult song ( Marler 1970 ,  Konishi 1985 ). Although the precise timing and mechanism of song learning varies across species ( Brenowitz and Beecher 2005 ), the general model for song development incorporates an early sensitive phase when juveniles are most sensitive to tutor song ( Konishi 1985 ,  Catchpole and Slater 2008 ). In age-limited learners, including the White-crowned Sparrow (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  ), songs memorized during this critical period will be &ldquo;crystallized&rdquo; into a permanent adult repertoire ( Marler and Tamura 1964 ,  Marler 1970 ). In such cases, juvenile birds may memorize adult song as fledglings prior to migration, months before establishing breeding territories ( Nelson et al. 1995 ,  2001 ).  In many songbirds, inter-individual variation in song is grouped into distinct geographic dialects based on shared vocal features ( Baker and Cunningham 1985 ). Several hypotheses have been proposed to explain the establishment and maintenance of dialects, including the &ldquo;genetic adaptation hypothesis&rdquo; ( Marler and Tamura 1962 ,  1964 ,  Nottebohm 1969 ), the &ldquo;social adaptation hypothesis&rdquo; ( Payne 1981 ; also see  Rothstein and Fleischer 1987 ,  Nelson 2000 ), and the &ldquo;epiphenomenon hypothesis&rdquo; ( Andrew 1962 ). These hypotheses have both proximate and ultimate elements that are interrelated, which makes it challenging to evaluate them as strict alternatives. Resolving this general problem is an issue for a separate review; for our purposes here, it is sufficient to note that both the genetic adaptation hypothesis and the social adaptation hypothesis suppose a reproductive advantage to individuals singing the common local song form, but the ultimate cause of that reproductive advantage differs under the two hypotheses, as do the predictions each makes about the proximate basis of dialects. Specifically, the genetic adaptation hypothesis predicts that (1) males generally do not disperse far; (2) those that disperse cannot modify their song after the end of an early critical period during which they memorized their natal song form; and, as a result, (3) song type is an honest indicator of males' region of origin and can be used by females to choose males that possess locally adapted gene complexes&mdash;hence the name of this hypothesis. By contrast, the social adaptation hypothesis allows at least some males to disperse widely but predicts that these can modify their song&mdash;socially adapt&mdash;to match the common form in whatever area they end up settling. Under this hypothesis, there is no restriction to gene flow, and no advantage to females of selecting males with locally adapted gene complexes; nevertheless, females prefer males that sing the common song form of the area. This preference may be based on some developmental mechanism with a deeper evolutionary origin, such as females developing song preferences based on early experience with song, or females possessing some innate preference for the most frequent song type (see  Payne 1981 ). The epiphenomenon hypothesis is a null alternative: Conforming to a local dialect has no adaptive significance, and dialects exist only as an unavoidable consequence of reasonably accurate learning of song combined with very limited dispersal in some species.  The Mountain White-crowned Sparrow (  Zonotrichia leucophrys  oriantha ) is a migratory, age-limited song learner that breeds seasonally in the subalpine meadows of the Sierra Nevada and Rocky Mountains, USA ( Morton et al. 1972 ). Geographically distinct and temporally stable dialect regions have been documented for this subspecies ( Orejuela and Morton 1975 ,  Harbison et al. 1999 ). Breeding territories are established in late spring, and nesting continues through midsummer. Newly fledged juveniles become independent and increasingly mobile at &sim;1 month posthatch, entering a juvenile dispersal stage at &sim;50 days of age ( Morton et al. 1991 ). Dispersing juveniles that were followed until departure on fall migration moved 2&ndash;5 km ( Morton et al. 1972 ). Whether this is far enough to carry them into a new dialect area would depend on how close their natal territory is to a dialect boundary. Radio-tagged juveniles sometimes moved &le;10 km, some into new dialect areas, before disappearing entirely (T. P. Hahn personal communication). Premigratory juvenile dispersal is thought to be an adaptive behavior that allows juvenile birds to evaluate habitat conditions and prospective breeding territories prior to their return as first-year breeders ( Brewer and Harrison 1975 ,  Morton et al. 1991 ).  One consequence of premigratory juvenile dispersal in  Z. l. oriantha  is that young birds can disperse into dialect regions near their hatch sites (nonnatal dialect areas) and may return the following spring to breed in these areas. Within each dialect area, a minority of males sing songs characteristic of other sites ( Baptista and Morton 1988 ,  MacDougall-Shackleton et al. 2002 ). At Tioga Pass, these include the dialects of Virginia Lakes (&sim;10 km away), Molybdenite Creek (&sim;30 km), Mammoth Lakes (&sim;30 km), Sonora Pass (&sim;40 km), and 1 individual singing a Ruby Mountains, Nevada, dialect (&sim;400 km). This provides further evidence that some individuals disperse beyond their natal dialect area boundaries and also indicates that at least some birds that settle outside their natal dialect area retain their natal dialect instead of learning to produce that of their new breeding area ( Baptista and Morton 1982 ). Juvenile birds that settle outside their natal dialect region do have opportunities to encounter and memorize those nonnatal song types; for instance, prior to dispersal, they could learn from the few adult males that sing unusual songs in any given area. Young males tend not to acquire unusual song types, however, even if sung by their own fathers ( Baptista and Morton 1988 ). Alternatively, learning might occur during the premigratory dispersal phase as young birds move through new dialect areas. Under this scenario, juveniles could memorize multiple dialects during the sensitive phase and subsequently prune their repertoires early in the first breeding season through countersinging and other interactions with neighboring males ( Baptista and Morton 1988 ,  Nelson 1992 ,  2000 ,  Nelson and Marler 1994 ,  Nordby et al. 2007 ). New song dialects might also be acquired primarily during early adulthood, when birds return from spring migration to settle in a breeding territory within a new dialect area. It is also possible that exposure to nonnatal dialects occurs during migration and on the wintering grounds.  Here, we address a key requirement of the social adaptation hypothesis, specifically that males have the opportunity to acquire nonnatal song during dispersal. Such learning requires that juveniles dispersing outside their natal dialect area encounter singing adults in the new dialect area. To determine whether this actually occurs, we quantified the amount of  Z. l. oriantha  song produced over the course of two breeding seasons, with particular focus on the period when dispersing juveniles began to arrive. We compared these singing rates to the dispersal schedule of juvenile birds. If nonnatal dialects are memorized during dispersal prior to fall migration, adult song must still be produced during the juvenile dispersal phase. Thus, the present study represents an important step in distinguishing the mechanisms involved in the establishment and maintenance of dialect regions.  Tioga Pass Meadow (TPM) is a subalpine meadow (3,000 m elevation; approximately 0.5 &times; 1.0 km) in the eastern Sierra Nevada (Mono County, California, USA). The population of  Z. l. oriantha  breeding at TPM has been the subject of long-term study since 1968 ( Morton 2002 ). The site supports &sim;50 breeding pairs and is characterized by patches of conifer forest (mainly   Pinus contorta  ), dense patches of willow (  Salix   spp.), open subalpine meadow, and talus slopes extending upward along the periphery.  We quantified song rates during the breeding seasons of 1997 and 2004, recording counts of  Z. l. oriantha  song at the study site. Counts were conducted from a centrally located observation point from which singing males were audible from all parts of the study area, including densely populated high-quality and more sparsely populated peripheral areas. Sampling extended from the middle of the nesting period in July through fledging and the beginning of juvenile dispersal in August. Importantly, the timing of our census captured both the period of peak song production and the period of premigratory dispersal by juveniles. This allowed us to describe the intensity of  Z. l. oriantha  singing in relation to the phenology of premigratory dispersal.  Singing rates during the dawn and dusk choruses were quantified throughout the breeding season. Dawn chorus counts began with the first song of the day, or at &sim;0500 hours late in the season, when singing was minimal. Dusk chorus counts began 1 hr prior to sunset and extended until &sim;0.5 hr after sunset. Periodically, song counts were quantified over a full day. Full-day counts began and ended with the dawn and dusk choruses and included every alternate hour in 1997, and every alternate half-hour in 2004. Song counts in 1997 were performed by a single observer (S.G.C.). Counts in 2004 were done simultaneously by two observers (W.W.H. and P.L.R.).  In both 1997 and 2004, nests on the study area were located through exhaustive searching, and all nestlings were banded prior to fledging. In 1997, juvenile birds were captured using seed-baited Potter traps placed at standard trapping sites on the study area. Birds with &ge;60&percnt; first basic plumage (brown and tan crowns, no body streaking) were considered to be &ge;50 days of age ( Morton et al. 1991 ). Given that juveniles begin dispersing at &sim;50 days of age ( Morton et al. 1991 ,  Morton 2002 ) and that all locally born birds had been banded as nestlings, these individuals with &ge;60&percnt; or greater first basic plumage were considered of nonlocal origin (i.e. not born on the study area, though not necessarily from outside the Tioga Pass dialect area).  Trapping data on the arrival of juvenile dispersers at TPM were not available for 2004. Therefore, to relate the appearance of juvenile dispersers with song rates on TPM that year, we took advantage of data from seven breeding seasons (1979, 1980, 1981, 1982, 1984, 1985, and 1986) to extrapolate a juvenile dispersal curve for 2004. Trapping effort was comparable across years. On TPM, the beginning of the breeding season depends strongly on climatic conditions, including the amount of snowpack on the meadow that year. However, the phenology of nesting and breeding follows a reliable timetable in relation to the first clutch in any given season. Thus, the date on which the first clutch was initiated is a good checkpoint for the reproductive patterns of birds in a given year: It is a strong predictor of subsequent reproductive events such as fledging dates, molt onset, and, critically, juvenile dispersal ( Morton 2002 ). To determine the likely trajectory for the captures of nonlocal juvenile dispersers in 2004, first clutch dates were obtained from the 7 yr of past trapping data. We extrapolated three time points in relation to the date of the first clutch, June 1, 2004: the expected arrival date of the first nonlocal juvenile; the date by which 50&percnt; of the season's nonlocal juveniles should have arrived; and the date by which 90&percnt; of the season's nonlocal juveniles should have arrived (see  Table 1 ). Variation between years in the lengths of these intervals most likely reflects variation between years in breeding synchrony.  Phenology of the arrival of nonlocal juvenile Mountain White-crowned Sparrows in a population at Tioga Pass Meadow, eastern Sierra Nevada, California, 1979&ndash;1986. Dates and the number of days in relation to when the first clutch was laid are given for the first juvenile capture of the season, 50&percnt; of juvenile captures, and 90&percnt; of juvenile captures. Capture dates for 2004 are derived from the mean of previous years' dates.  Song production rates were high early in the breeding season. Daily song rates were elevated throughout the day, with peaks at dawn and dusk. Singing rates declined sharply as the season progressed ( Figure 1 ). For example, 3,396 songs were tallied over a cumulative period of 6.5 hr on July 8, 2004, whereas over that same duration on July 26, 2004, only 21 songs were tallied.  Daily profiles of song production by adult male Mountain White-crowned Sparrows on Tioga Pass Meadow, eastern Sierra Nevada, California, from 3 days in 1997 and 2004. Singing was initially concentrated at the dawn and dusk choruses and declined as the season progressed.  The distribution of song production across the day also changed. Although a substantial proportion of early-season song occurred during the middle of the day, levels of midday singing decreased in late July, concentrating the majority of song production at dawn and dusk ( Figure 1 ). Thereafter, singing rates fell more rapidly around dawn than at dusk, shifting the bulk of daily song into the dusk chorus ( Figure 1 ). For example, on July 8, 2004, we counted 1,006 songs during the first hour of the dawn chorus and 457 songs during an hour at dusk. By July 26, 2004, only 3 songs were counted during the first hour of the dawn chorus and 14 songs were counted during an hour at dusk.  The arrival of nonlocal juveniles onto the TPM site was consistent over many years. The first nonlocal juveniles were captured between August 1 (1981) and August 22 (1982), and new young birds continued to appear until late September or early October. The first nonlocal juvenile appeared, on average, 65.4 &plusmn; 2.9 days after the first clutch was initiated, in any given year; 50&percnt; and 90&percnt; of the total number of nonlocal juveniles captured in any given year had appeared by 89.4 &plusmn; 2.6 and 101.0 &plusmn; 3.7 days after the first clutch was initiated, respectively (means &plusmn; SE;  Table 1 ).  There was minimal overlap between periods of greatest singing and of premigratory juvenile dispersal in  Z .l. oriantha . In both 1997 and 2004, song rates on TPM had fallen dramatically by late July, before the first dispersing juvenile would have arrived. In 1997, the highest song counts occurred nearly a month prior to the arrival of a nonlocal juvenile. Similarly, in 2004, song production throughout the season did not overlap substantially with the extrapolated pattern of nonlocal juvenile captures ( Figure 2 ).  The arrival of nonlocal juvenile Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (gray circles) on Tioga Pass Meadow, eastern Sierra Nevada, California, in 1997 and (extrapolated) in 2004, occurred after the peak of adult song production for the season (black squares).  Singing rates across the breeding season, together with aggregate data on juvenile dispersal, indicate that song production declines markedly before juvenile birds begin dispersing. Thus, by the time juvenile birds begin to move off of their natal territory and disperse into potentially nonnatal dialect areas, the opportunity to hear nonnatal dialects is diminishing rapidly. The first nonlocal juvenile to reach TPM in August of 2004, for example, would have heard only &sim;3 repetitions hr &minus;1  of Tioga Pass dialect (July 26, 2004), a small fraction of the &gt;500 repetitions hr &minus;1  of natal song heard by locals prior to dispersal. By September, singing rates have dropped to essentially zero (T. P. Hahn personal observation during multiple hours per day running trap lines throughout the study area, and checks during expected dawn and dusk chorus times). Moreover, for the majority of nonlocal juveniles, the above scenario may actually overestimate the amount of exposure to nonnatal dialects. This is because the dispersing juveniles most likely to arrive at TPM while adults are still singing at all are also the most likely to be juveniles from areas immediately adjacent to the study site&mdash;that is, from the same dialect region ( Morton et al. 1991 ). Dispersers from outside the Tioga Pass dialect area would be likely to arrive even later, when singing rates have dropped even more. We do not have data on the number of dispersers that actually come from outside the Tioga Pass dialect area, but the regular presence of a small number of adults singing nonlocal dialects (including both geographically adjacent dialects, e.g., the Mammoth Lakes, Sonora Pass, and Virginia Lakes dialects, and dialects from hundreds of kilometers away, such as the Ruby Mountains, Nevada, dialect) confirms that at least some nonlocal birds disperse to and settle at Tioga Pass. How many breeding adults singing Tioga Pass song were born in other dialect areas and subsequently learned and crystallized Tioga Pass song is unknown, but one individual singing a nonlocal dialect in his yearling breeding season changed his song to a Tioga Pass song in his second year ( MacDougall-Shackleton 2000 ).  In  Z. l. oriantha , the sensitive period for song learning by tape tutoring (less potent than live tutoring; see below) occurs relatively early, peaking at days 30&ndash;40 after hatch ( Nelson et al. 1995 ), whereas juvenile dispersal typically begins around day 50 after hatch ( Morton et al. 1991 ). Thus, although juveniles would typically hear relatively massive quantities of natal song during the peak of their sensitive period, individuals subsequently dispersing outside their natal dialect area would hear only a very few repetitions of nonnatal song during this dispersal phase.  Is this degree of exposure sufficient for dispersing juveniles to memorize the foreign dialect? In studies of song learning,  Z. l. nuttalli  are often tutored using up to hundreds to thousands of song repetitions during the sensitive phase (e.g.,  Marler 1970 ,  Petrinovich 1985 ,  Petrinovich and Baptista 1987 ), quantities consistent with the amount of song production prior to the bulk of juvenile dispersal. On the other hand, at least when tutored during the sensitive period, some individual  Z. l. nuttalli  were able to produce good replicas of tutor song after exposure to 252 songs (at a frequency of &ge;12 songs day &minus;1 ;  Petrinovich 1985 ). This minimal degree of exposure is more similar to the song environment experienced by free-living  Z. l. oriantha  during the dispersal period.  Nevertheless, if dispersing  Z. l. oriantha  are to learn nonnatal dialects prior to migration, they must surmount two difficulties. First, song learning would need to occur well past the peak of their sensitive phase (see above). Second, this learning would have to be based on hearing very few repetitions of song in relation to what they heard early in the season. These challenges need not be insurmountable and may be alleviated by contextual and social cues. The presence of live tutors, for instance, can increase the potency of the stimulus and facilitate song learning, even after the early sensitive period for tape tutoring has closed:  Z. l. nutalli  raised in the absence of adult song until 50 days of age were subsequently able to learn song from a social tutor ( Baptista and Petrinovich 1984 ), and Song Sparrows ( Melospiza melodia ) exposed during both the sensitive period and in later months to different sets of live tutors were able to learn songs after their sensitive period, when both tutor sets sang at similarly high rates ( Nordby et al. 2001 ).  Our results highlight that in  Z. l. oriantha , juveniles dispersing into foreign dialect areas hear relatively few repetitions of nonnatal song. Further studies into dialect acquisition during juvenile dispersal should consider that foreign song exposure is not only limited, but (1) occurs past the sensitive period and (2) is preceded by substantially greater amounts of natal song during the sensitive period. Thus, whether and how low levels of song exposure after the peak of the sensitive period and during premigratory juvenile dispersal might contribute to consistent, well-developed adult song remains an open question. Experimental studies using realistic rates of song exposure at different ages, as revealed by the present study, would help clarify how much new song learning is occurring in these birds after dispersal begins.  Limited (but existent) opportunities to learn nonnatal dialect during juvenile dispersal may help to explain why song dialects are significantly, but weakly, associated with population genetic structure in Sierra Nevada Mountain White-crowned Sparrows ( MacDougall-Shackleton and MacDougall-Shackleton 2001 ). That is, dialects are associated with some reduction in gene flow, as expected under the genetic adaptation hypothesis, but explain only a small proportion of genetic variation, as if the social adaptation hypothesis also applies. Female preferences for local song dialect may thus result in selecting mates of local origin in most, but not all, cases. Alternatively, the lack of strong genetic differentiation among Sierra Nevada dialect boundaries may reflect a lack of female preference for local dialects at this geographic scale. Female White-crowned Sparrows from Sonora Pass prefer their natal dialect over other, geographically distant and acoustically distinct dialects (e.g., from the Rocky Mountains) but not over acoustically and geographically closer dialects from within the Sierra Nevada ( MacDougall-Shackleton et al. 2001 , E. A. MacDougall-Shackleton personal communication). Thus, weak genetic differentiation across Sierra Nevada dialect boundaries may result from dispersing males' limited ability to conceal their nonlocal origins, from a lack of female choosiness at the scale at which most dispersal occurs, or from a combination of these factors. Further work is needed to discriminate among these possibilities. However, our findings show that for the social adaptation hypothesis to apply, males must be capable of learning novel dialects on the basis of exposure to very few song repetitions at a relatively advanced age.  Financial support for this work came in part from a National Science Foundation (NSF) Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant (IBN-9801580) to E.A.M.-S. and T.P.H.; from NSF grant IBN-0235911 to T.P.H.; from the Department of Biology, Occidental College; and from the Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Princeton University. 