 Effects of climate change on the evolution of Brown Creeper (  Certhia americana  ) lineages  The crucial role of the accessible area in ecological niche modeling and species distributional modeling  Fifty-fourth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union Check-list of North American Birds  The internal climate variability of HadCM3, a version of the Hadley Centre coupled model without flux adjustments  The Community Climate System Model version 3 (CCSM3)  Allozyme variation in the three extant populations of the narrowly endemic cycad  Dioon angustifolium  Miq. (Zamiaceae) from North-eastern Mexico  Predicting species distribution: Offering more than simple habitat models  Very high resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areas  Niche shifting in response to warming climate after the last glacial maximum: Inference from genetic data and niche assessments in the chisel-toothed kangaroo rat (  Dipodomys microps  )  The mating system and genic diversity in Martinez spruce, an extremely rare endemic of Mexico's Sierra Madre Oriental: An example of facultative selfing and survival in interglacial refugia  Revisiting Wallace's haunt: Coalescent simulations and comparative niche modeling reveal historical mechanisms that promoted avian population divergence in the Malay Archipelago  Diversification in North American arid lands: Niche conservatism, divergence and expansion of habitat explain speciation in the genus Ephedra  Niche lability in the evolution of a Caribbean lizard community  Cryptic diversity in a widespread North American songbird: Phylogeography of the Brown Creeper (  Certhia americana  )  Isolation-driven divergence: Speciation in a North American songbird (Aves: Certhiidae)  Is gene flow promoting the reversal of Pleistocene divergence in the Mountain Chickadee (  Poecile gambeli  )?  Summer birds of the Rincon Mountains, Saguaro National Monument, Arizona  Sky Islands  Does niche divergence accompany allopatric divergence in  Aphelocoma  jays as predicted under ecological speciation? Insights from tests with niche models  Detecting natural influence on surface air temperature change in the early twentieth century  Projected climate change effects on Rocky Mountain and Great Plains birds: Generalities of biodiversity consequences  Phylogeography is not enough: The need for multiple lines of evidence  Ecological niche conservatism: A time-structured review of evidence  Rethinking receiver operating characteristic analyses in ecological niche modeling  Maximum entropy modeling of species geographic distributions  The  Anolis  lizards of Bimini: Resource partitioning in a complex fauna  Grinnellian and Eltonian niches and geographic distributions of species  Comparative phylogeography of unglaciated eastern North America  Phylogeography of the White-breasted Nuthatch ( Sitta carolinensis ): Diversification in North American pine and oak woodlands  Niche models tell half the story: Spatial context and life-history traits influence species responses to global change  Speciation in the White-breasted Nuthatch ( Sitta carolinensis ): A multilocus perspective  Locating Pleistocene refugia: Comparing phylogeographic and ecological niche model predictions  Environmental niche equivalency versus conservatism: Quantitative approaches to niche evolution    Certhia americana   Bonaparte. The known birds of North and Middle America  Phylogeography of the California Gnatcatcher (  Polioptila californica  ) using multilocus DNA sequences and ecological niche modeling: Implications for Conservation  Submitted November 26, 2013; Accepted May 18, 2014; Published August 6, 2014  Understanding how distributions of species change through time allows evaluation of hypotheses about factors shaping biogeographic patterns and evolutionary trajectories of genetic lineages. Ideally, such studies would assess whether population genetic processes are associated with geographic distribution shifts, loss or gain of distributional area through time, or fragmentation of distributional areas, information that can now be derived via ecological niche modeling. We examined the distributional changes through time in lineages and populations of Brown Creeper ( Certhia americana ), a widespread North American bird, to test biogeographic and population genetic hypotheses. In two populations with genetic support for population bottlenecks, Monterey County in California and the Sierra Madre Oriental in Mexico, ecological niche models indicated range contractions and increased fragmentation since the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM). Projections of niche models to the future suggested continuation of range contractions and fragmentation. Of the 3 major allopatric lineages of Brown Creeper (eastern North America, western North America, and southern North America and Central America), the most stable through time was the southern lineage, which corresponds with increased genetic diversity. The potential geographic distribution of the western lineage has remained stable in size but not location since the LGM, corresponding with a genetic signal of isolation by distance. The eastern lineage experienced range contractions during the LGM, likely resulting in the contemporary lack of genetic structure within the lineage. Finally, there is limited evidence of potential range overlap during the LGM between the western lineage and the other 2 lineages, although the overlap is limited to the Arizona sky islands between the west and south lineages. These results suggest that ecological niche modeling and population genetic data may be used as mutual predictors when investigating phylogeographic patterns and processes.  Entender c&oacute;mo las distribuciones de las especies cambian a trav&eacute;s del tiempo permite la evaluaci&oacute;n de hip&oacute;tesis sobre los factores que modelan los patrones biogeogr&aacute;ficos y las trayectorias evolutivas de los linajes gen&eacute;ticos. Idealmente, estos estudios permitir&iacute;an evaluar si los procesos gen&eacute;ticos poblacionales est&aacute;n asociados con los cambios en las distribuciones geogr&aacute;ficas, p&eacute;rdida o ganancia de &aacute;rea de distribuci&oacute;n a trav&eacute;s del tiempo, o la fragmentaci&oacute;n de &aacute;reas de distribuci&oacute;n&mdash;esta informaci&oacute;n puede ahora derivarse mediante el modelado del nicho ecol&oacute;gico. Examinamos los cambios en la distribuci&oacute;n a trav&eacute;s del tiempo en linajes y poblaciones de   Certhia americana  , un ave ampliamente distribuida en Am&eacute;rica del Norte, para evaluar hip&oacute;tesis biogeogr&aacute;ficas y de gen&eacute;tica de poblaciones. En dos poblaciones con evidencia gen&eacute;tica de cuellos de botella poblacionales (Condado de Monterrey, California y Sierra Madre Oriental, M&eacute;xico), los modelos de nicho ecol&oacute;gico indicaron contracciones del rango y aumento de la fragmentaci&oacute;n desde el &Uacute;ltimo M&aacute;ximo Glacial (UMG). Las proyecciones a futuro de los modelos de nicho sugirieron la continuaci&oacute;n de las contracciones y la fragmentaci&oacute;n del rango. De los tres mayores linajes alop&aacute;tricos de   C. americana   (este de Am&eacute;rica del Norte, oeste de Am&eacute;rica del Norte, y sur de Am&eacute;rica del Norte y Am&eacute;rica Central), el m&aacute;s estable en el tiempo fue el linaje sur, que corresponde a aumentos en la diversidad gen&eacute;tica. La distribuci&oacute;n geogr&aacute;fica potencial del linaje del oeste permaneci&oacute; estable en tama&ntilde;o pero no en ubicaci&oacute;n debido a que el UMG coincidi&oacute; con una se&ntilde;al gen&eacute;tica de aislamiento por distancia. El linaje este experiment&oacute; contracciones del rango durante el UMG, resultando probablemente en la falta contempor&aacute;nea de estructura gen&eacute;tica al interior del linaje. Finalmente, existe poca evidencia de superposici&oacute;n potencial del rango entre el linaje del oeste y los otros dos linajes durante el UMG, aunque est&aacute; limitado a las islas del cielo de Arizona entre los linajes oeste y sur. Estos resultados sugieren que el modelado del nicho ecol&oacute;gico y los datos gen&eacute;ticos poblacionales pueden ser usados como predictores mutuos cuando se investigan los patrones y procesos filogen&eacute;ticos.   Palabras clave: Certhia , conservadorismo de nicho, cuello de botella poblacional, filogeograf&iacute;a, fragmentaci&oacute;n, modelado de nicho ecol&oacute;gico  The spatial distributions of genetic lineages are of paramount concern to the field of phylogeography ( Avise 2000 ). Understanding how distributions change through time, in size, and in other characteristics allows evaluation of hypotheses about factors shaping evolutionary trajectories of multiple genetic lineages. Over the past decade, newly developed methods (e.g., ecological niche modeling) have allowed biologists to characterize a species' existing ecological niche based on known occurrence locality information and associated environmental data. Ecological niche modeling methods can support and enrich genetic data from phylogeographic studies, although for most species these methods are limited to biogeographic (macro), not landscape (micro), scale questions ( Guisan and Thuiller 2005 ) owing to limited data availability ( Peterson 2009 ).  Studies using ecological niche modeling and multilocus genetic data have become more common as more methods and data become available (for examples, see  Zink et al. 2013 ,  Walstrom et al. 2012 ). Multilocus genetic studies allow investigation of population genetic processes such as population expansions, population bottlenecks, and gene flow between evolutionary lineages. Incorporating ecological niche modeling allows testing whether these population genetic processes are associated with distributional shifts (e.g., during Pleistocene glacial cycles;  Jezkova et al. 2011 ), loss (or gain) of potential distributional area through time ( Jezkova et al. 2011 ), or fragmentation of populations ( Lim et al. 2011 ).  Over time, environmental characteristics change, driving landscape changes, as with Pleistocene glacial cycles influencing habitat shifts and changes in North America (e.g.,  Waltari et al. 2007 ). Assessing corresponding spatiotemporal shifts in distributions of species via these correlational approaches requires, at least initially, assumptions of niche conservatism through time of the species under investigation, such that species will either track habitat or risk extinction. Thus, in contemporary allopatric species (or lineages), niches must be tested to establish whether they have been conserved over relevant time periods. Here, we focus on niche conservatism, or retained ancestral traits, of large-scale climatic tolerances (scenopoetic factors) that may limit distributions ( Sober&oacute;n 2007 ).  Although niches of allopatric species may seem different, they may remain constant (but broad) given the environment(s) available to them. For example, a species inhabiting the eastern deciduous forests of North America may seem, superficially, to inhabit a different niche than a species in North America's western coniferous forests. However, these species may share the same niche characteristics given the suite of environmental characteristics in their geographic region, with different lineages &ldquo;expressing&rdquo; different parts of a broad niche.  Recent methods ( Warren et al. 2008 ,  McCormack et al. 2010 ) allow comparison of niches between species by quantitatively considering the available background environment. In addition to niche conservatism or divergence, interpretation of species' niche models should consider the context of the organism's dispersal capabilities and life history characteristics (e.g.,  Swab et al. 2012 ), which provide more robust conclusions than simple interpretation of distributional models. For example, in birds, appreciable distances may separate fragmented &ldquo;islands&rdquo; of habitat, but the populations may still be effectively connected if dispersal ability is sufficient to link them genetically.  The Brown Creeper (  Certhia americana  ; Aves: Certhiidae) is a common and widespread resident of North American mature, old growth coniferous, and mixed coniferous&ndash;deciduous forests. Currently considered a single biological species ( AOU 1983 ,  Chesser et al. 2013 ), the Brown Creeper shows significant genetic structure in both mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA;  Manthey et al. 2011a ) and nuclear DNA (nDNA;  Manthey et al. 2011b ). Concordant patterns of genetic structure between datasets identify 3 allopatric lineages: southern (southern Arizona south to Honduras), western (western mountain ranges of the United States and Canada), and eastern (eastern forests of United States and Canada). The earliest phylogenetic split in the species separates temperate and subtropical populations, coinciding with the largest difference in morphology (overall body size and coloration;  Webster 1986 ), while morphological differences between eastern and western populations are largely clinal. The basal lineages separated &sim;1.50 million years (0.80&ndash;3.01 MYA highest probability density &lsqb;HPD&rsqb;) ago, while the eastern and western groups within the northern lineage separated &sim;0.6 MYA (0.37&ndash;1.23 MYA HPD) ago ( Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ).  Population genetic data reveal that gene flow between lineages of Brown Creeper is limited, while gene flow within lineages is prevalent ( Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ). Two populations (Monterey County, California, and Sierra Madre Oriental, Mexico) show evidence of population bottlenecks ( Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ). Multiple allopatric lineages, estimates of divergence and gene flow, and varied population genetic patterns (e.g., bottlenecks;  Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ) thus make Brown Creeper populations an excellent system for using ecological niche modeling to illuminate biogeographic processes driving observed evolutionary trajectories.  To investigate how distributional changes have affected the evolution of the Brown Creeper, we created ecological niche models for its 3 lineages and projected them to past (Last Glacial Maximum; LGM) climatic conditions. The goals of this study were to (1) investigate patterns of niche conservatism (or divergence) between lineages; (2) investigate potential distributional overlap between lineages (e.g., did they persist in allopatry during the LGM?); and (3) identify changes in distributional range size, location, and patchiness through time, as they relate to population genetic characteristics.  To examine the effects of distributional changes on population genetic characteristics, we investigated the following null hypotheses: (H1 0 ) locations with genetic evidence of population bottlenecks have experienced range contractions and increased distributional fragmentation since the LGM and will continue this trend into the future; (H2 0 ) lineages that have higher inter-population genetic structure will be more stable through time; and (H3 0 ) evidence of potential geographic connectivity between lineages will be limited.  Georeferenced data associated with scientific specimens were obtained from ORNIS ( http://olla.berkeley.edu/ornisnet/ ), an online portal to data associated with museum specimens in North America, and from the literature ( Manthey et al. 2011a ). Occurrence points within 10 km of each other were omitted to avoid over-sampling identical and closely neighboring raster cells. After data reduction, 1,557 occurrence points were used, including 659, 281, and 617 points for the eastern, southern, and western lineages, respectively (Appendix  Figure 4 ).  We obtained 19 &ldquo;bioclimatic&rdquo; layers from the WorldClim database ( Hijmans et al. 2005 ;  www.worldclim.org ), which contains worldwide precipitation and temperature information, including minima, maxima, and ranges of values. Only 11 layers were included in our analyses (Appendix  Table 5 ), however, owing to high correlation between some of the variables ( R  &gt; 0.8). Past environmental layers for the LGM (21,000 years before present) were drawn from model outputs from the Community Climate System Model (CCSM3;  Collins et al. 2006 ) and the Model for Interdisciplinary Research on Climate (MIROC;  Nozawa et al. 2005 ). Additionally, future layers were downloaded for the time periods of the 2020s, 2050s, and 2080s for 3 scenarios of climate change (A1b, A2a, and B2a) using 2 global climate models, the Third Generation Coupled Global Climate Model (CGCM3.1; Environment Canada) and the Hadley Centre Coupled Model (HadCM3;  Collins and Tett 2001 ). These layers were downloaded from the International Centre for Tropical Agriculture ( Ramirez and Jarvis 2008 ).  Occurrence data and environmental layers were analyzed in Maxent ( Phillips et al. 2006 ), which integrates occurrence data with environmental data to identify environmental conditions associated with occurrences. In Maxent, we applied default settings while using 3 occurrence-point datasets based on the eastern, western, and southern groups of Brown Creepers (Appendix  Figure 4 ). Each occurrence dataset included 80&percnt; of the original locality data, with 20&percnt; excluded for model evaluation. For each lineage, we ran 50 bootstrap replicates to assess effects of occurrence dataset variation on model outputs. The training region for each lineage was defined as any area within 200 km of occurrence points for that lineage; following training, models were projected to the entire continent of North America for LGM, current, and future conditions. Future models were included to assess trends in populations experiencing bottlenecks. Models were thresholded (transformed to binary output) for visualization as inclusive of 90&percnt; of the training occurrence data.  Model evaluation was performed using the partial ROC method of  Peterson et al. (2008) . For each lineage, we ran 1,000 bootstrap replicates, each using 50&percnt; of the test data. We ran this analysis twice for each lineage, setting the threshold of acceptable omission error to 10&percnt; and 5&percnt; for each run; values consistently &gt;1 indicated model performance above null expectations.  Using the environmental niche model testing method ENMTools ( Warren et al. 2008 ), Schoener's  D  statistic (a measure of niche overlap;  Schoener 1968 ) was calculated between each pair of niche models. This statistic calculates the similarity of raster data for each cell and is standardized to provide values between 0 and 1 over the entire extent examined. Higher values indicate a greater amount of overlap between models.  To test niche conservatism, as compared to conditions available across the accessible area, we used ENMTools' Background Similarity Test tool with 100 replicates for each comparison. This test determines whether partially overlapping populations (in this case lineages) are more similar or different from one another than would be expected given the environmental conditions available to each lineage. The available space for each lineage was defined conservatively as sites within 200 km of occurrence points of the lineage. We used this background space as a conservative estimate of environments to each lineage over recent evolutionary time (as compared to a generational dispersal capability). We used a conservative estimate here to reduce the chances of spurious conclusions of niche divergence owing to an overly large background space ( Barve et al. 2011 ).  Output of the background tests included 2 null distributions: the expected values of overlap between lineage A's empirical model and lineage B background models (models of randomly selected points from lineage B's available space), as well as the expected values of overlap between lineage B's empirical model and lineage A background models. If overlap observed between the 2 empirical models fell within these null distributions, we did not reject the null hypothesis that the lineages' niches are no more similar or different than would be expected by chance. Alternatively, empirical overlap less than (or greater than) the null distributions led us to reject the null hypothesis and support niche divergence (or conservatism).  In addition to the ENM background testing method, we used a principal component analysis (PCA) method to test niche similarity compared to available habitat (as described by  McCormack et al. 2010 ). The null hypothesis of this test is that observed niche divergence (D O ) is equal to background environmental divergence (D BE ). Niche conservatism is supported if D O  &lt; D BE , while niche divergence is supported if D O  is significantly different ( t -test) between lineages and D O  &gt; D BE . Using all occurrence points and 1,000 background points per lineage (and their associated environmental data values), we performed PCA to obtain principal component axes that describe the environmental variation available to all Brown Creeper lineages. We used as many PCs as were necessary to investigate the majority of the variance in the data (until a PC did not explain 3&percnt; of the variance in the data). For each PC, we tested ( t -test) whether occurrence data for each lineage differed significantly.  T -test significance values were corrected for multiple comparisons using a Bonferroni correction ( Miller 1966 ). Using a custom script in  R , the mean difference between lineages (i.e. D O ) was compared to the mean difference of a null distribution of background samples (i.e. D BE ) for each PC and pairwise comparison of lineages.  When measured within a lineage, as opposed to between lineages as described in the preceding section, the statistic  D  can be used to measure niche stability through time. In this context, a higher value indicates relatively more stability than a low value, which would indicate less stability through time. Because of this, we used ENMTools to calculate  D  between time frames within the same lineage (e.g., between the LGM and contemporary models for each lineage).  In addition to testing within lineages, we measured overlap of models for all pairwise comparisons between lineages at LGM and contemporary conditions. These measures assess whether levels of allopatry changed (or will change) between time periods. Additionally, overlap between lineages was assessed by measuring the number of pixels designated as presence for both lineages in each pairwise comparison.  To calculate fragmentation, or the patchiness of potential space for each lineage, we used the following multistep process (similar to number of disjunct core areas &lsqb;NDCA&rsqb; statistic;  McGarigal et al. 2012 ). First, we measured total area as the number of pixels in the raster for each model classified as presence in the binary model output. Second, we calculated the total number of patches inclusive of at least 100 pixels. Although this threshold is arbitrary, we applied it because of the high variability in number of small (&lt;100 pixels) patches between contemporary and projected conditions. Next, we determined the number of patches assuming 2 levels of connectivity, 5 km and 10 km, which provided different levels of assumptions regarding the distance that may be trivial to Brown Creepers to traverse between nearby patches on a generational basis. Finally, we calculated patchiness, or fragmentation, as total area divided by the number of patches. All values were reported as relative to contemporary conditions with no dispersal between patches (i.e. values &lt;1 indicate a model less fragmented than the current model and vice versa).  In addition to investigating patterns in the 3 lineages, we also investigated 2 populations that have undergone population bottlenecks ( Manthey et al. 2011b ). The first of these populations consists of birds from the Sierra Madre Oriental; we defined the area of this population as bounded by a polygon with corners at: (1) 21.67&deg;N, 99.77&deg;W; (2) 21.67&deg;N, 98.20&deg;W; (3) 25.99&deg;N, 99.84&deg;W; and (4) 25.99&deg;N, 101.41&deg;W. The second population investigated is in Monterey County, California, defined as the area within 200 km of the sampled population at 36.33&deg;N, 121.58&deg;W. For these populations, we calculated total area and fragmentation using identical methods to those described in the preceding paragraphs, including future projections as well as LGM projections.  Ecological niche models of the 3 lineages ( Figure 1 ) accurately reconstructed the breeding range of Brown Creepers. The models performed well, both quantitatively and qualitatively. All area under the curve (AUC) ratios at acceptable omission thresholds of 5&percnt; and 10&percnt; were &gt;1.5, well above null expectations ( Table 1 ). When compared qualitatively to breeding maps from the North American Breeding Bird Survey, the sum of the 3 lineages seemed nearly identical, aside from a small area in southern Wisconsin which seems to have been overestimated in the model.  Ecological niche models for Last Glacial Maximum and Contemporary periods for the 3 lineages of Brown Creeper ( Certhia americana ). Suitable areas are colored black and gray in maps. For projected models, because 2 different climate models were used for projection, areas with prediction from 1 of 2 models is colored gray, with agreement between both models colored black.  Range of AUC ratios in the partial ROC testing of the models for each lineage. Omission thresholds of 10&percnt; and 5&percnt; were used.  Models for the LGM varied between lineages and climate models ( Figure 1 ). While the western and southern lineages were relatively stable between LGM and current conditions ( Figure 1  and  2 ), the eastern lineage experienced large shifts in suitable geographic space. Niche models for the LGM differed between climatic models (CCSM and MIROC), mostly in the eastern lineage ( Figure 1 ), where the CCSM model predicted only 2 small refugia in parts of North Carolina and Louisiana, while the MIROC model predicted a wide swath of suitable habitat.  Patterns of ( A ) relative niche stability, ( B ) overlap between lineages, ( C ) relative area, and ( D ) relative fragmentation of Brown Creeper. LGM patterns are the average of the MIROC and CCSM climate model predictions.  Overlap between lineages showed largely different patterns, both currently and in the past ( Figure 2 ). Overlap was measured using  I , Schoener's  D , and the number of pixels designated as presence (from the binary maps) for both lineages in each pairwise comparison. These measures were all positively correlated ( R  2  &gt; 0.86,  p  &lt; 0.001, for all pairwise comparisons); therefore, only one is reported in  Figure 2 . Generally, the southern and eastern lineages have had little geographic overlap through time, especially considering the accessible area to each lineage. The southern and western lineages have had moderate amounts of overlap in northern Mexico, Arizona, and New Mexico ( Figures 1  and  2 ), although this has decreased through time. Lastly, the most varied patterns of overlap through time are between the eastern and western lineages; current overlap is relatively low, but during the LGM there was extensive potential overlap in Texas.  Niche similarity between lineages was assessed using 2 methods, both of which consider each lineage's niche within the context of the available environment to that lineage. The first method, which is model-based, identified varied patterns of similarity between lineages ( Table 2 ). There was partial evidence for niche divergence between the eastern and other lineages, while comparisons between the south and west identified patterns of niche conservatism.  Results of niche divergence testing using a model-based method (Background Similarity Tests) in ENMTools. Observed values of model overlap were compared to overlap between empirical (e.g., West) and replicates of background models (e.g., East&lowbar;bg). C and D indicate significant patterns of niche conservatism or divergence, respectively. Observed overlap between models was: East&ndash;West (0.092), East&ndash;South (0.016), and South&ndash;West (0.078).  Niche similarity was also investigated using a PC-based analysis. PCA identified 5 PCs explaining a modest proportion of the variance in the environmental data of occurrence and background points (&sim;3&percnt; or more). In the 2 largest PCs (with &sim;70&percnt; of the variance of the data), patterns of niche conservatism ( Table 3 ) matched those of the model-based method's results in the preceding paragraph. Again, the eastern lineage showed evidence of niche divergence, while comparisons between the west and south lineages identified niche conservatism ( Table 3 ). PCs explaining less variance included varied results of niche divergence and nonsignificant results ( Table 3 ). Because the southern and western lineages remain conserved relative to one another (in model-based and the first 2 PCs), and only comparisons involving the eastern lineage indicate niche divergence, the simplest explanation is differentiation of the eastern lineage from the ancestral trait. This pattern is reinforced in a phylogenetic context because the western and eastern lineages together are sister to the southern lineage, suggesting an ancestral niche more similar to the western and southern lineages.  Results of niche divergence testing using a PCA-based method. Observed mean values between lineages are shown above the range of values observed in the background testing replicates (in parentheses). C and D indicate niche conservatism or divergence, respectively. Proportion of variance explained of each principal component is shown in parentheses on the header line.  The 3 Brown Creeper lineages show varied patterns of changing relative area and fragmentation when comparing contemporary and LGM models. The 3 lineages have had varied patterns of expansion or contraction since the LGM ( Figure 2 C;  Table 4 ). One model for the eastern lineage, the CCSM model of the LGM, indicated relatively no potential habitat (&lt;1&percnt; of contemporary area;  Figure 1 ). Because of this,  Figure 2 C and  2 D were edited to include only the MIROC LGM model for the eastern lineage.  Relative area and fragmentation of each model (compared to current) during the LGM for the 3 lineages and 2 populations (SMO &equals; Sierra Madre Oriental; Monterey &equals; Monterey County, California). All values of relative area and fragmentation are the average of both climate models for each scenario (e.g., CCSM and MIROC models for the LGM). For the eastern lineage, the relative area of the CCSM model was &lt;1&percnt; of the current model and was not used in the average because of exponentially increasing fragmentation estimation. Fragmentation is also reported with connectivity between habitat &ldquo;islands&rdquo; of 5 km and 10 km relative to present fragmentation with no connectivity.  Similar to relative area, the 3 lineages showed mixed trends in fragmentation through time; the eastern and southern lineages indicated increased fragmentation since the LGM, while the western lineage indicated slightly decreased fragmentation ( Figure 2 D;  Table 4 ).  The 2 populations that have experienced a population bottleneck, Monterey County, California, and the Sierra Madre Oriental, showed similar patterns, although they vary in their similarity to the lineage they are nested within ( Figure 3 ;  Table 4 ; Appendix  Table 6 ). These 2 populations exhibited evidence for greatly reduced potential area and much greater fragmentation since the LGM. Under future climate models, both populations will likely undergo range contractions and increased fragmentation of available habitat ( Figure 3 ; Appendix  Table 6 ).  Patterns of relative area and fragmentation of niche models for the Sierra Madre Oriental population in Mexico. Inset map shows topography and encased area magnified in part A. ( A ) Predicted occurrence for projected models; future climate models for the A2a climate scenario; ( B ) trends of relative area and fragmentation (average of 2 climate models) under the 3 scenarios of future climate change.  Niche conservatism is commonly observed among recently diverged animal taxa (see review by  Peterson 2011 ). Alternatively, other studies have shown taxon groups to exhibit little or no relationship between ecological similarity and phylogenetic relatedness (e.g.,  Anolis  lizards;  Losos et al. 2003 ) or mixed patterns of niche conservatism and divergence between lineages (e.g.,  Ephedra  shrubs;  Loera et al. 2012 ).  While visual inspection of the 3 Brown Creeper lineages' niche models suggest they are nonidentical, 2 independent tests accounting for the available background environment for each lineage support varied patterns of niche conservatism and divergence ( Tables 2  and  3 ). Similar patterns have been shown in  Aphelocoma  jays, where niche models of lineages ( McCormack et al. 2010 ) seem visually divergent, but when available background environment is considered have varied patterns of niche conservatism and divergence.  Because the tests of niche similarity identify niche conservatism between the western and southern lineages ( Tables 2  and  3 ), we are confident in assuming that niches remained similar during the climatic fluctuations of the Pleistocene. Because the eastern lineage exhibits patterns of niche divergence from the western and southern lineages, projections for this lineage should be interpreted with caution. However, niche divergence in this lineage potentially took place over a long time period (e.g., since lineage divergence, or 0.37&ndash;1.23 MYA); therefore, projections since the LGM (&sim;22,000 years before present), a much shorter time scale, still present interpretable data.  Our first hypothesis (H1 0 ) stated that populations with genetic evidence of population bottlenecks have experienced range contractions and increased distributional fragmentation since the LGM. The Monterey County, California, population shows decreased potential geographic space and increased fragmentation since the LGM; this provides a mechanism for a current bottleneck in this area, with little-to-no incoming gene flow from other populations in the western lineage. This is in contrast to the LGM models, where the central valley of California would likely have provided suitable climatic conditions for the Brown Creeper ( Figure 1 ), allowing for gene flow between Monterey County and other populations in the western lineage.  Similarly, the Sierra Madre Oriental population has experienced decreased range size and increased fragmentation since the LGM ( Figures 1  and  3 ). Additionally, during the LGM, and in contrast to current conditions, these populations potentially exhibited connectivity with other populations in the southern lineage, likely with populations to the south (e.g., Eje Volc&aacute;nico Transversal of Central Mexico) based on coalescent analyses ( Manthey et al. 2011b ). This pattern of elevational expansion in colder climates and contraction during interglacials has been identified in geographic and genetic studies of several pine species ( Ledig et al. 2000 ,  Gonz&aacute;lez-Astorga et al. 2005 ) and birds associated with pines (Pygmy Nuthatch &lsqb;  Sitta pygmaea  &rsqb; and Steller's Jay &lsqb;  Cyanocitta stelleri  &rsqb;; G.M. Spellman personal communication) of the Sierra Madre Oriental.  Under potential future scenarios, these 2 populations will continue to experience decreases in potential suitable range and increased fragmentation ( Figure 3 ; Appendix  Table 6 ). While similar between both populations, these patterns seem especially drastic under all climate models in the Sierra Madre Oriental ( Figure 3 ) and would likely impact many montane species. Pine species, especially those already exhibiting limited ranges (e.g.,  Ledig et al. 2000 ,  Gonz&aacute;lez-Astorga et al. 2005 ), as well as species relying on these montane pine forests for habitat (e.g., Pygmy Nuthatch and Steller's Jay) would likely exhibit similar responses to the changing climate in the Sierra Madre Oriental, necessitating this locality as a target for conservation of the existing pine forest.  Our second hypothesis (H2 0 ) stated that lineages with higher within-clade genetic structure would have been relatively stable through time. Repeated movement within a lineage would have brought populations together, promoting gene flow and preventing inter-population divergence. Since the LGM, the southern lineage remained the most spatially stable ( Figure 2 A) while exhibiting a decrease in potential distributional area ( Figure 2 C;  Table 4 ). Contemporary populations of southern Brown Creeper live in the sky islands of the major Mexican mountain chains, separated by environments unsuitable for colonization. As expected under H2 0 , the southern lineage exhibits the most private haplotypes or alleles in both mtDNA and nDNA ( Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ). Similarly, within the southern lineage is the largest signal for among-population (rather than within) variation in analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) analyses ( Manthey et al, 2011a ). Additionally, the pattern of distributional expansion during the LGM is consistent with expected patterns of elevational shifts in species distributions during Pleistocene climate fluctuations ( McCormack et al. 2009 ). These patterns may suggest that some, or all, southern Brown Creeper populations have undergone population size contractions since the LGM. MtDNA data support a similar pattern; as many (50&percnt;) of the populations in the Mexican clade differ significantly from the pattern of an expanding population ( Manthey et al. 2011a ).  The western lineage remained relatively stable in potential distributional area and fragmentation ( Figure 2 ;  Table 4 ), although less so than the southern lineage; however, Rocky Mountain populations likely experienced displacement ( Figure 1 ). Following glacial retreat, populations of the Rocky Mountains were able to expand toward the current distribution, likely the cause for evidence of isolation by distance in the west ( Manthey et al. 2011a ). Other species of western North American birds show patterns both similar and contrasting to those of the western Brown Creeper. The Mountain Chickadee (  Poecile gambeli  ) was shown to have a similar pattern of movement south and westward during the LGM ( Waltari et al. 2007 ,  Manthey et al. 2012 ). Conversely, the Blue Grouse ( Denragapus obscurus ), which exhibits a similar distribution to Brown Creeper and Mountain Chickadee, underwent range expansion during the LGM ( Waltari et al. 2007 ).  The eastern lineage was the most displaced ( Figure 2 A) and most fragmented ( Figure 2 D;  Table 4 ) of all lineages during the LGM, as well as having the largest change in total area between current and LGM conditions ( Figure 2 C;  Table 4 ). Patterns of displacement and range-area instability likely led to a lack of significant genetic structure seen between contemporary populations (from mtDNA AMOVA analyses;  Manthey et al. 2011a ). Disparate patterns of stability between the eastern and other lineages ( Figure 2 A) may be a manifestation of the eastern lineage's relative ease to track suitable climate latitudinally since the LGM; conversely, more montane lineages (western and southern) may have been more likely to track suitable habitat elevationally, as was seen in modeled climate-change responses of Rocky Mountain and Great Plains bird species ( Peterson 2003 ).  Similar patterns of large changes in area, fragmentation, and displacement during the LGM are found in the eastern lineage of the White-breasted Nuthatch ( Sitta carolinensis ;  Walstrom et al. 2012 ); in this species, there is a lack of significant genetic structure between contemporary populations following post-glacial expansion ( Spellman and Klicka 2007 ,  Walstrom et al. 2012 ) matching the pattern seen in the eastern lineage of the Brown Creeper. Conversely (although comparing only spatial, and not genetic, data), other eastern species show patterns of LGM refugia ranging from a single, tiny refugium (e.g., the pygmy salamander &lsqb; Desmogathus wright &rsqb;;  Waltari et al. 2007 ) to large and widespread refugia (e.g., red-backed vole &lsqb;  Myodes gapperi  &rsqb; and five-lined skink &lsqb; Eumeces fasciatus &rsqb;;  Waltari et al. 2007 ). This information supports the hypothesis that species with different habitat preferences experienced vastly different responses to the LGM in eastern North America ( Soltis et al. 2006 ).  Finally, we hypothesized (H3 0 ) that evidence of potential geographic connectivity between lineages would be limited. Potential overlap between the western and southern lineages, during contemporary and LGM conditions, occurs in Arizona, New Mexico, and northwestern Mexico. While not strong evidence for complete isolation, these patterns suggest connectivity between the western and southern lineages may occur somewhere in the sky islands between the Rocky Mountains and the Sierra Madre Occidental, in the cline between tropical and subtropical forests. This region represents the only known location of hybridization between the Rocky Mountains Brown Creeper (  C. a . montana ) and the Sierra Madre Occidental (  C. a . albescens ) subspecies in the Rincon Mountains of southern Arizona ( Marshall 1956 ).  Similarly, LGM models of eastern and western lineages do not exhibit complete allopatry. During the LGM, a much higher level of overlap occurred between these lineages ( Figure 2 B), with a potential &ldquo;bridge&rdquo; of habitat connecting the lineages in Texas ( Figure 1 ). If this pattern occurred during multiple glacial maxima of the Pleistocene, it could explain diversification of the Brown Creeper into the forests of eastern North America during a period of connectivity (0.37&ndash;1.12 MYA). However, a lack of fossil data in  Certhia  precludes verification of whether any  Certhia  were in eastern North America prior to this time period. This pattern of connection in the southern United States during the LGM between the eastern and western lineages ( Figure 1 ) may also explain the persistence of gene flow or retention of ancestral genetic variation observed within these lineages (mtDNA and nDNA structure, but lacking nDNA fixed differences;  Manthey et al. 2011b ).  The best example of isolation manifested in the ecological niche models occurs in Central America and southern Mexico. Here, suitable regions in Guatemala, Honduras, and Chiapas, Mexico, are separated from all other regions of the southern lineage by unsuitable regions in the Isthmus of Tehuantepec during contemporary and LGM conditions ( Figure 1 ). This pattern is manifested in genetic data, which show strong, yet shallow, genetic structure in both mtDNA and nDNA ( Manthey et al. 2011a ,  2011b ).  We performed ecological niche modeling on 3 allopatric lineages of Brown Creeper, with additional emphasis on 2 populations with genetic evidence for population bottlenecks. We identified mixed patterns of niche conservatism and divergence between lineages, although only comparisons with the eastern lineage included evidence for niche divergence from other lineages. In the 2 populations with genetic evidence for population bottlenecks, ecological niche models indicated potential geographic distribution range contractions and fragmentation since the LGM, with projections of models into the future suggesting continuation of population contraction and fragmentation. Patterns of genetic differentiation within lineages correspond with geographic and potential size stability since the LGM. The southern lineage has remained relatively stable since the LGM, with a gap at the Isthmus of Tehuantepec between northern and southern populations (current and LGM) manifesting in strong genetic structure across this boundary. The western lineage remained stable in potential distributional size but not geographic space, evident as a pattern of isolation by distance in genetic data. The eastern lineage was the least stable in potential geographic space and location since the LGM, resulting in a lack of any genetic structure with the clade. Together, the genetic and ecological niche modeling data provide synergistic evidence to describe the processes driving the patterns in phylogeographic data.  We thank J. E. McCormack and V. B. Arroyo for methodological discussion as well as A. T. Peterson for providing helpful comments on the manuscript. This project was funded by NSF DEB 0814841 (Spellman) and 0815705 (Klicka). The specimen occurrence data was provided, via ORNIS, by the following institutions: American Museum of Natural History, California Academy of Sciences, Canadian Museum of Nature, Delaware Museum of Natural History, Denver Museum of Nature and Science, Field Museum of Natural History, Kansas University Natural History Museum, Illinois State University Natural History Collections, Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History, Museum of Southwestern Biology, Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, Royal Ontario Museum, Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History, San Diego Museum of Natural History, University of Alaska Museum of the North, University of British Columbia Beatty Biodiversity Museum, University of California at Los Angeles, University of Michigan Museum of Zoology, and the Yale University Peabody Museum.  Training (above) and testing (below) locality points for the niche models of the eastern (black), western (red), and southern (light blue) lineages.  Environmental layers (&ldquo;bioclimatic&rdquo; layers), and their descriptions, used in ecological niche modeling.  Relative area and fragmentation for the two populations with genetic evidence of population bottlenecks. All values are relative to current model with no connectivity. 