Genetic diversity of a tropical rainforest understory bird in an urban fragmented landscapeMedian-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogeniesModelled atmospheric temperatures and global sea levels over the past million yearsSynergies among extinction drivers under global changeCatastrophic extinctions follow deforestation in SingaporeHabitat loss and extinction in the hotspots of biodiversityEcology predicts levels of genetic differentiation in Neotropical birdsThe current refugial rainforests of Sundaland are unrepresentative of their biogeographic past and highly vulnerable to disturbanceHeavy extinctions of forest avifauna in Singapore: Lessons for biodiversity conservation in Southeast AsiaThe effects of extreme forest fragmentation on the bird community of Singapore IslandMolecular systematics of the Malagasy babblers (Passeriformes: Timaliidae) and warblers (Passeriformes: Sylviidae), based on cytochrome <italic>b</italic> and 16S rRNA SequencesjModelTest 2: More models, new heuristics and parallel computingMolecular systematics and diversification of the Asian scimitar babblers (Timaliidae, Aves) based on mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequencesArlequin suite ver 3.5: A new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and WindowsQuantifying biodiversity: Procedures and pitfalls in the measurement and comparison of species richnessRapid flooding of the Sunda Shelf: A late-glacial sea-level recordExtinction debt at extinction thresholdDating of the human&ndash;ape splitting by a molecular clock of mitochondrial DNAIdentification of birds through DNA barcodesHow closely do measures of mitochondrial DNA control region diversity reflect recent trajectories of population decline in birds?Balancing biodiversity in a changing environment: Extinction debt, immigration credit and species turnoverComprehensive DNA barcode coverage of North American birdsExtinction debt: A challenge for biodiversity conservationClustalW and ClustalX version 2DnaSP v5: A software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism dataMultilocus analysis of the evolutionary dynamics of rainforest bird populations in Southeast AsiaMitochondrial dating and mixed support for the &ldquo;2&percnt; rule&rdquo; in birdsSurviving with low genetic diversity: The case of albatrossesExperimental evidence for extreme dispersal limitation in tropical forest birdsPhylogeny and biogeography of the core babblers (Aves: Timaliidae)Biodiversity hotspots for conservation prioritiesA landscape genetics approach for quantifying the relative influence of historic and contemporary habitat heterogeneity on the genetic connectivity of a rainforest birdGENALEX 6: Genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and researchGENALEX 6.5: Genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research-an updateDNA evidence shows vocalizations to be a better indicator of taxonomic limits than plumage patterns in <italic>Zimmerius</italic> tyrant-flycatchersGenetic variation in Asiatic lions and Indian tigersDefining corridor functions for endemic birds in fragmented south-temperate rainforestA comparison of bird communities of two fragmented and two continuous Southeast Asian rainforestsTropical lowland rainforest birds on a highly urbanized island: Monitoring, losses and lessonsSoutheast Asian biodiversity: An impending disasterPrimers for a PCR-based approach to mitochondrial genome sequencing in birds and other vertebratesUse of Amazonian forest fragments by understory insectivorous birdsEstimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzeesMEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0Primers for amplification and determination of mitochondrial control-region sequences in oscine passerinesForecasting agriculturally driven global environmental changePleistocene refugia in an arid landscape: Analysis of a widely distributed Australian passerineA viable herd of genetically uniform cattleMaps of Pleistocene sea levels in Southeast Asia: Shorelines, river systems and time durationsCalibrating the avian molecular clockThe vegetation of Singapore&mdash;An updated mapPersistence of babbler (Timaliidae) communities in Singapore forestsAnalyzing the genetic diversity of a population can be useful in identifying some of the silent effects of habitat fragmentation. We examined and compared 4 mitochondrial loci of the near threatened Short-tailed Babbler (<italic>Pellorneum malaccense</italic>), a rainforest understory bird, between a highly fragmented population in Singapore and populations from elsewhere in the Sundaic region. We found that the fragmented Singaporean population is genetically impoverished, with &lt;20&percnt; of the intrapopulation genetic diversity present in a comparable sample from Borneo within intact forest. Differences in haplotype diversity among Singaporean sites of occurrence suggest that there may be extremely poor genetic diversity and connectivity among Singaporean subpopulations. These findings highlight the importance of connectivity in maintaining population genetic diversity in urban tropical forest patches. Our results also corroborate previous findings that there are 3 deeply diverged lineages of Short-tailed Babbler across the Sundaic region.El an&aacute;lisis de la diversidad gen&eacute;tica de una poblaci&oacute;n puede ser &uacute;til en la identificaci&oacute;n de algunos de los efectos silenciosos de la fragmentaci&oacute;n del h&aacute;bitat. En este estudio examinamos cuatro loci mitocondriales de <italic>Pellorneum malaccense</italic>, un ave casi amenazada del sotobosque de bosques lluviosos, y los contrastamos entre una poblaci&oacute;n &aacute;ltamente fragmentada en Singapur y poblaciones de otras localidades en la regi&oacute;n de la Sonda. Se encontr&oacute; que la poblaci&oacute;n fragmentada de Singapur est&aacute; gen&eacute;ticamente empobrecida, y cuenta con menos del 20&percnt; de la diversidad gen&eacute;tica encontrada en una muestra comparable de una localidad en Borneo con bosques intactos. Las diferencias en la diversidad haplot&iacute;pica entre sitios en Singapur sugieren que la diversidad gen&eacute;tica y la conectividad entre sub-poblaciones del &aacute;rea podr&iacute;an ser extremadamente pobres. Estos resultados resaltan la importancia de la conectividad en el mantenimiento de la diversidad gen&eacute;tica de las poblaciones dentro de parches urbanos de bosques tropicales. Nuestros resultados corroboran evidencia previa sobre la existencia de tres linajes de divergencia profunda en <italic>Pellorneum malaccense</italic> a trav&eacute;s de la regi&oacute;n de la Sonda.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> deriva gen&eacute;tica, extinci&oacute;n local, poblaciones peque&ntilde;as, Sondalandia, viabilidad poblacional.The island of Singapore (103&deg;50&prime;E, 1&deg;20&prime;N), lying within the Sundaic biodiversity hotspot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Myers1">Myers et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Brooks1">Brooks et al. 2002</xref>), stands out as the most urbanized country in the rapidly developing region of Southeast Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi3">Sodhi et al. 2004b</xref>). It is one of the most densely populated countries in the world, with an average of &gt;7,000 persons km<sup>&minus;2</sup>. Since 1819, &gt;95&percnt; of Singapore's original vegetation cover has been lost to urbanization; &lt;10&percnt; of the remaining forest is primary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Brook2">Brook et al. 2003</xref>). Over 50&percnt; of the remaining local biodiversity is now restricted to forest reserves, which cover &lt;0.25&percnt; of Singapore's total land area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Brook2">Brook et al. 2003</xref>).Habitat loss and fragmentation have a variety of effects on species diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Tilman1">Tilman et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Jackson2">Jackson and Sax 2010</xref>). Although immediate changes in species composition are often well documented following habitat loss, silent processes such as extinction debt are frequently overlooked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Hanski1">Hanski and Ovaskainen 2002</xref>). Extinction debt can operate over many years, during which deleterious factors act to decimate remnant populations in a habitat. These factors include invasions by alien species, habitat deterioration, edge effects, and reduced population genetic diversity within small populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Brook1">Brook et al. 2008</xref>). Many forest-dependent species in Singapore and other recently urbanized areas may currently undergo extinction debt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Kuussaari1">Kuussaari et al. 2009</xref>). However, to our knowledge, no avian genetic studies have specifically addressed this phenomenon in tropical urbanized areas&mdash;indicating an urgent research need.The Short-tailed Babbler (<italic>Pellorneum malaccense</italic>, previously classified as <italic>Malacocincla malaccensis</italic>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Moyle1">Moyle et al. 2012</xref>) is one of the few truly forest-dependent species not currently listed as threatened in Singapore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Yong1">Yong 2009</xref>), although it is listed as globally &ldquo;near threatened&rdquo; by the IUCN. This insectivorous understory bird appears to be declining in numbers because of habitat destruction throughout its range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-BirdLifeInternational1">BirdLife International 2001</xref>), which includes the Thai-Malay peninsula, Sumatra, Borneo, and smaller satellite islands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>). In Singapore it occurs only within a few of the more sizable and interconnected remnants of the island's nature reserves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi2">Sodhi et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Yong1">Yong 2009</xref>). These remnants were contiguous until the early 1990s, which may explain the present distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi2">Sodhi et al. 2004a</xref>).Median-joining haplotype network of Short-tailed Babblers superimposed on map of Sundaland, with species range shaded in pale yellow (BirdLife International). Circles represent ND2-cytb concatenated haplotypes. Circle size is proportional to number of individuals sharing a haplotype, with the smallest circle representing 1 sample and the largest representing 11 samples. Each color represents a sampling locality, with red-pink shades representing various Singapore localities, orange representing peninsular Malaysia, yellow representing Sumatra, blue shades representing Sarawak localities, and green shades representing Sabah localities (the Tawau Hills samples are highlighted by diagonal lines). Refer to Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t05">Table 5</xref> for details on each haplotype. Individuals from multiple localities sharing a haplotype are depicted as appropriately shaded pie slices. Hatchmarks on branches correspond to a nucleotide change (a difference of one base pair is however not shown as a hatchmark). Branch length is not proportional to number of nucleotide changes between haplotypes. Map obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.maps-for-free.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.maps-for-free.com</ext-link>Map showing position of the Central Catchment Nature Reserve (CCNR) within Singapore, locations within the reserve where Short-tailed Babblers were sampled, and the frequency of COI&ndash;cyt <italic>b</italic>&ndash;ND2&ndash;D-loop haplotypes. Numbered localities are (1) Upper Seletar Reservoir Park (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 6), (2) Upper Peirce Reservoir Park (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 10), and (3) Southern CCNR (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 12). Size of circle corresponds to sample size. For details on each haplotype, see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t05">Table 5</xref>. Map modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Yee1">Yee et al. (2011)</xref>. One of the sampled reserves, Bukit Timah Nature Reserve, is not shown because of lower sample size.Understanding connectivity between patches in forest-dependent species such as the Short-tailed Babbler is important for ensuring their survival in urbanized and increasingly fragmented landscapes. Insectivorous understory species are known to be poor dispersers, so dispersal barriers can easily result in small, isolated populations susceptible to genetic drift (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Burney1">Burney and Brumfield 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Pavlacky1">Pavlacky et al. 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lim1">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref> analyzed the evolutionary history of Short-tailed Babblers across the Sundaic region but had limited sampling from highly fragmented patches such as Singapore. Other studies have looked into the population demographics and distribution of the Short-tailed Babbler within Singapore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi1">Sodhi 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi2">Sodhi et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Castelletta2">Castelletta et al. 2005</xref>), but were conducted without recourse to molecular methods to scan for signals of low genetic diversity.Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) haplotype number and diversity data can reflect demographics of avian populations that have undergone declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Jackson1">Jackson et al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, we investigated the placement of the Singaporean population within a phylogenetic framework and compared levels of mtDNA population-genetic diversity between Singaporean and other regional populations. In particular, we directly contrasted the Short-tailed Babblers of Singapore island with a comparable Bornean population from intact forest. We also made comparisons among the Singaporean subpopulations to identify those at particular risk.Short-tailed Babblers have a limited distribution in Singapore, and we chose study sites that had confirmed sightings of the species. Targeted mist-netting was done between April 2013 and January 2014 at 3 old, secondary forest fragments within the Central Catchment Nature Reserve (CCNR) and 1 fragment within the Bukit Timah Nature Reserve (BTNR). Sites within the 2 nature reserves covered during this period include Southern CCNR (with 4 different sampling localities), Northern CCNR (comprising Upper Peirce Reservoir Park, Upper Seletar Reservoir Park, and multiple sampling localities within each park) and Dairy Farm Nature Park (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Forest fragments within the Western Catchment could not be surveyed because they are restricted military training areas.Blood samples from live captured birds were obtained by brachial venipuncture. An ethanol-soaked cotton swab was used to sterilize the area surrounding the brachial vein. A TERUMO 1-cc TB Syringe was then used to pierce the brachial vein, and blood was collected using 50-&mu;L Drummond Short-Length Microcaps heparin-free capillaries. Blood was then transferred to a 2-mL Eppendorf tube containing 50 &mu;L of 100&percnt; ethanol and topped up such that the blood:ethanol ratio was between 1:15 and 1:20. Pressure was applied to the puncture using the ethanol swab following blood collection in order to clot the wound. Blood was not collected from birds displaying brood patches or juvenile characteristics. Any feathers shed during processing of birds were also collected in zip-lock plastic bags because the calami often contain small quantities of extractable DNA. The Eppendorf tubes and zip-lock bags were labeled and stored in a freezer at a temperature of &minus;20&deg;C in order to prevent degradation of DNA. Birds were fitted with alloy bands bearing unique numbers on their tarsus; this provided a technique for tracking birds and identifying recaptured individuals to avoid resampling of the same individual. Following processing, birds were released at the site of capture. A total of 29 individuals were sampled: 28 from CCNR and 1 individual from BTNR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). A total of 2,614 mist-netting hours were completed in Singapore over the whole study period.Additional mtDNA sequences from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lim1">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref> were downloaded from GenBank for Short-tailed Babbler populations from across the region (for full sample list, see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t05">Table 5</xref>). Besides Singapore, areas sampled included Terengganu in peninsular Malaysia (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4) and Lingkung district in Sumatra (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2), as well as several localities in Sarawak (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 21) and Sabah (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17) on the island of Borneo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>).DNA extractions were made with GeneAll DNA Purification kits, following the protocol for body fluid in ethanol. Polymerase chain reactions (PCR) were conducted in a C1000 Thermal Cycler for 4 different mitochondrial genes, using the following primers and conditions: Cytochrome oxidase subunit 1 (CO1) was amplified following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Hebert1">Hebert et al. (2004)</xref>; the hypervariable mitochondrial control region (D-loop) was amplified following (1995); NADH dehydrogenase subunit 2 (ND2) was amplified following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. (1999)</xref>; and cytochrome <italic>b</italic> (cyt <italic>b</italic>) was amplified following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Cibois1">Cibois et al. (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Dong1">Dong et al. (2010)</xref>, using the conditions stated for ND2. PCR amplifications were done in 20-&mu;L reaction volumes, which comprised 2 &mu;L 10X <italic>Taq</italic> PCR buffer, 1.2 &mu;L MgCl2 (25 mM), 1 &mu;L of each primer (10 &mu;m), 0.4 &mu;L Fermentas <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase, 2 &mu;L mtDNA template, and 11.6 &mu;L MilliQ water. PCR product cleanup was done using ExoSAP-IT, and the BigDye Terminator version 3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA) was used to cycle-sequence the samples. Sequences were obtained by capillary electrophoresis using an Applied Biosystems 3130xl Genetic Analyzer.DNA sequences were assembled with CodonCode Aligner version 4.1 and aligned with MEGA version 6.06 using ClustalW (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Larkin1">Larkin et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Tamura2">Tamura et al. 2013</xref>). Two subsets of data were created using the sampled loci. The first subset (2,418 base pairs &lsqb;bp&rsqb; in length), which maximized the number of loci analyzed, focused on Singaporean samples and involved the concatenation of all 4 loci previously mentioned (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 24); the second subset (1,208 bp in length), which maximized the number of individuals analyzed, included samples from different parts of the Sundaic region and involved the concatenation of 2 genes, ND2 and cyt <italic>b</italic> (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 79). The Chinese Hwamei (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Garrulax canorus</named-content></italic>) was used as an outgroup. MEGA was employed to construct phylogenetic trees using maximum parsimony (MP) and maximum likelihood (ML). For each analysis, 1,000 bootstrap replicates were run. MP was run with all sites used for gap treatment, with tree bisection and reconnection as the tree search method and with all other settings in default mode. The program jModelTest 2.1.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Darriba1">Darriba et al. 2012</xref>) was used to determine the best evolutionary model for each data subset for ML analysis. The first subset was analyzed using the TrN &plus; G model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Tamura1">Tamura and Nei 1993</xref>) and the second using the HKY model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Hasegawa1">Hasegawa et al. 1985</xref>). ML tree topologies were verified using GARLI version 2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Zwickl1">Zwickl 2006</xref>). All trees were visualized using FigTree version 1.4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Rambaut1">Rambaut 2006</xref>).GenAlEx version 6.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Peakall1">Peakall and Smouse 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Peakall2">2012</xref>) was used to generate haplotypes from each data subset. For subsequent analyses, any positions with missing data or ambiguity codes were deleted from the entire dataset, and GenBank samples with imprecise locality data were ignored. Network version 4.6.0 (Fluxus Technology, Clare, Suffolk, UK) was used to generate haplotype networks to determine population genealogies using a median-joining algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Bandelt1">Bandelt et al. 1999</xref>). For further analysis, the samples were broadly divided into populations originating from 5 different regions: Singapore, peninsular Malaysia, Sumatra, Sabah, and Sarawak. DnaSP version 5.10.01 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Librado1">Librado and Rozas 2009</xref>) was used to calculate <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, raw sequence divergence, and nucleotide diversity between and within populations across the Sundaic region and between and within subpopulations across 3 localities in Singapore (Upper Seletar Reservoir Park, Upper Peirce Reservoir Park, and Southern CCNR). Distribution of variation within and among populations in Southeast Asia was estimated using analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) in ARLEQUIN version 3.11 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Excoffier1">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>), using the settings of pairwise differences and 3,000 permutations.In order to contrast Singaporean haplotype diversity with that of a comparable regional population, subsampling and rarefaction techniques were used. We compared Singapore with an overseas locality of similar size with intact forest, namely the Tawau Hills in Sabah. The island of Singapore (~580 km<sup>2</sup> in area prior to modern land reclamation and with a human population as small as 10,000 at the start of the 19th century; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Crawfurd1">Crawfurd 1830</xref>) was fully forested until recently and, thus, would have been similar with respect to population size and dynamics to the forest block of Tawau Hills (4&deg;27&prime;7.62&prime;&prime;N, 117&deg;56&prime;53.90&prime;&prime;E; ~20 km latitudinally and ~25 km longitudinally). Both forest tracts were part of a larger forest matrix during the past few thousand years; Singapore was connected to present-day Sumatra ~9,000 yr ago and to peninsular Malaysia &lt;6,000 yr ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Bintanja1">Bintanja et al. 2005</xref>). Thus, we expect that differences in Short-tailed Babbler population genetics between both sites are mostly due to recent habitat conversions in Singapore. The Singaporean population was subsampled and rarefied following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Gotelli1">Gotelli and Colwell (2001)</xref>, using 100 bootstrap replicates in each case. Network 4.6.0 was used to draw haplotype networks for the 2 populations in order to visualize differences in population structure.Both ML and MP analyses generated similar majority-rule consensus topologies. Three well-supported clades were formed, with the western populations (Singapore, peninsular Malaysia, and Sumatra) emerging as an independent clade nested within the Sarawak clade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The Sabah clade was sister to and deeply diverged from the western and Sarawak clades, respectively. Within the western clade, the Sumatran and peninsular Malaysian populations were respectively resolved as sister to the Singapore population. The nestedness of the western clade within Sarawak may be an artifact of low resolution from sequencing loci from a single linkage group; thus, it has poor ML bootstrap support (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The parsimony network generated similar results, with 3 broad clades formed across Southeast Asia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Single-locus trees generated similar tree topologies and are not shown.Phylogram of regional populations of Short-tailed Babblers from across the Sundaic region. Major nodes are annotated with maximum-likelihood/maximum parsimony values.Results from the AMOVA showed that the overwhelming majority (87.23&percnt;) of mtDNA variation occurred among rather than within clades (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t01">Table 1</xref>). Observations of deep divergence between clades were corroborated by a matrix of raw sequence divergences (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>), with 10&ndash;30 times more divergence between clades than between populations within the western clade. Raw sequence divergence between populations of the western clade and Sarawak was consistently &lt;4&percnt;, whereas that between the western clade and Sabah exceeded 9&percnt;, underscoring the deep divergence of Sabah (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>).Hierarchical analysis of molecular variance of 3 clades of Short-tailed Babbler: West, Sabah, and Sarawak. Populations within the West clade include Singapore, Sumatra, and peninsular Malaysia.Matrix of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> (above diagonal), raw sequence divergences among regional populations (below diagonal), and raw sequence divergences/nucleotide diversity within clades and populations (along diagonal, bold) of Short-tailed Babblers.A total of 39 different haplotypes were identified across Southeast Asia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>), with the highest haplotype diversity occurring in Sabah and the lowest in Singapore (0.971 and 0.794, respectively; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t03">Table 3</xref>). Low sample sizes in peninsular Malaysia and Sumatra made it difficult to assess diversity across these sites. None of the haplotypes occurring in Singapore were found in any other region.Comparison of genetic diversity markers across selected clades and populations of Short-tailed Babblers.The Short-tailed Babblers in Singapore appeared to be genetically impoverished, showing limited population structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>). This observation is supported by intrapopulation sequence divergence values that are &lt;20&percnt; of those obtained from populations in Sabah and Sarawak (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>), as well as comparatively low levels of nucleotide diversity and polymorphic sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t03">Table 3</xref>). Comparison of haplotype diversity between Singapore and Tawau Hills in Sabah showed that the latter had higher relative haplotype diversity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f04">Figure 4</xref>). Additionally, the maximum pairwise difference observed between individuals sampled from Singapore was 2 bp out of 1,208 bp (0.00166&percnt;), compared to 11 bp (0.00911&percnt;) for Tawau Hills. The Tawau Hills dataset displayed a much more unbiased distribution than the Singapore dataset, with 7 haplotypes formed from the 9 individuals sampled, no dominance of any one haplotype, and more structure between haplotypes. By contrast, Singapore haplotype distribution was skewed, with ~19 individuals (almost 60&percnt; of the total sample size for the island) belonging to the 2 most common haplotypes and limited structure seen within the haplotype network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f05">Figure 5</xref>).Rarefaction curve to compare haplotype diversity between Short-tailed Babblers from Singapore and Tawau Hills, based on cyt <italic>b</italic>&ndash;ND2 sequences.Median-joining haplotype network for Short-tailed Babblers from (<bold>A</bold>) Singapore and (<bold>B</bold>) Tawau Hills, based on cyt <italic>b</italic>&ndash;ND2 sequences.Five additional haplotypes were identified for Singapore following the concatenated 4-locus analysis, with 7 of the ~2,500 bp proving to be variable. Almost 30&percnt; of the Singaporean individuals belonged to a single haplotype (STBH3, represented by red in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>), while 5 individuals were singletons possessing unique haplotypes. Despite comparable sample sizes, Northern CCNR displayed twice as many haplotypes as Southern CCNR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Additionally, 6 of the northern haplotypes were unrepresented in the southern population. STBH3 was the dominant haplotype identified in Southern CCNR but was represented by only 1 sample from the Northern CCNR. Based on this analysis, Upper Peirce Reservoir Park appeared to possess the greatest haplotype diversity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Comparatively higher <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values between the Northern CCNR localities (Upper Peirce Reservoir Park and Upper Seletar Reservoir Park) and Southern CCNR further highlight the isolation of the Southern CCNR fragment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t04">Table 4</xref>).Matrix of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> (above diagonal), raw sequence divergences among Singaporean localities (below diagonal), and raw sequence divergences/nucleotide diversity (along diagonal, bold) within Singaporean localities, respectively.Mean sequence divergence between Sabah and other populations was 8.5&ndash;9.6&percnt;, a figure far exceeding mtDNA coding gene divergences often observed between avian sister species, which average around 4.3&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Hebert1">Hebert et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Kerr1">Kerr et al. 2007</xref>), corroborating previous findings of a deep Sabah divergence by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lim1">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref>. Based on the mitochondrial clock rate of ~2&percnt; divergence Ma<sup>&minus;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lovette1">Lovette 2004</xref>), it appears that the last time there was gene flow between birds in Sabah and elsewhere in the region was &gt;4.5 mya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>). The universality of this clock has been hotly debated but is validated for a wide range of avian taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Weir1">Weir and Schluter 2008</xref>) and is here used for temporal divergence estimation.A lack of shared haplotypes across regional sampling localities and high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values suggest that there may be no pronounced recent gene flow among the 3 clades, corroborating previous observations by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lim1">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref>. This is consistent with the hypothesis of high levels of lineage divergence in sedentary tropical forest birds with low dispersal rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Moore1">Moore et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Burney1">Burney and Brumfield 2009</xref>).The Sundaic region lies on a shallow continental shelf and has a complex geological and climatic history. During the Pleistocene (starting 2.6 mya), cyclical changes in climate have affected the region by causing the sequential rise and fall of sea levels and corresponding changes in the total immersed land area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Hanebuth1">Hanebuth et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>). Models reveal that a large block of lowland evergreen rainforest existed at the center of the shelf between peninsular Malaysia and what today forms the islands of Sumatra and Borneo, potentially allowing for gene flow between the regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Cannon1">Cannon et al. 2009</xref>). Despite the frequency of land connections over the past 2.8 million years, levels of sequence divergence indicate that differentiation of the population in Sabah from the other 2 clades predates the Pleistocene. This means that enough differences accumulated before the Pleistocene era between Sabah and the other 2 clades to prevent any detectable gene flow between them, even when they may have occupied adjacent geographic space during glacial maxima.The case is different for Sarawak and the western clade. Sequence divergence values (3.6&ndash;3.9&percnt;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>) suggest that gene flow occurred between these clades up until approximately 1.8&ndash;2.0 mya at the beginning of the Pleistocene, and then ceased or eased off, possibly due to a gradual accumulation of differences during each allopatric isolation event that eventually led to reproductive isolation.Based on the mtDNA distances (0.6&ndash;0.9&percnt;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>), populations forming the western clade date back to divergence events as recent as 300,000&ndash;400,000 yr ago (Late Pleistocene), which is strong evidence for the Singaporean, peninsular Malaysian, and Sumatran populations together forming a distinct, genetically more cohesive clade. This finding is unsurprising given the shallow, narrow straits and short distances that separate these land masses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>).The genetic distinctness of the 2 Bornean clades, originally highlighted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Lim1">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref>, may indicate that these clades represent true biological species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Mayr1">Mayr 1942</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Wheeler1">Wheeler and Meier 2000</xref>), given that they appear to have been genetically isolated from peninsular and Sumatran populations since at least the Early Pleistocene. Further investigation into the bioacoustics and morphology of these forms is ongoing and will demonstrate whether Short-tailed Babblers form multiple cryptic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Rheindt1">Rheindt et al. 2008</xref>).In the 2-gene regional analysis, Singaporean samples accounted for only 13&percnt; of the haplotypes that were identified across Southeast Asia, despite forming 42&percnt; of the total sample size for the study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The Singaporean population appears to be a genetically cohesive unit, displaying &lt;20&percnt; of the intrapopulation variability seen in the Tawau Hills population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Singapore and Tawau Hills would have possessed similarly sized forest tracts and, thus, similar populations until as recently as 200 yr ago; on a longer time scale, both were fragments of larger forests belonging to the Sundaic landmass. The sequence divergence values between Singapore, Sumatra, and peninsular Malaysia are similar to those between samples collected from within Sabah or Sarawak (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>). This shows the cohesiveness of the western clade on larger time scales and provides a context for interpreting the exceptionally low intrapopulation variability seen in the current Singapore population, when compared to Tawau Hills.Analysis within Singapore revealed that subpopulations in Northern CCNR have twice the haplotype diversity of subpopulations in Southern CCNR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). At this spatial scale, haplotypes are usually evenly distributed across habitat patches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Toon1">Toon et al. 2007</xref>). The absence of such a pattern may indicate that there is limited exchange between the northern and southern regions of the CCNR, possibly because subpopulations are constrained to fragments as a result of their inability to disperse across barriers such as reservoirs and golf courses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>).It has been shown that low genetic variability does not affect all taxa equally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Visscher1">Visscher et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Milot1">Milot et al. 2007</xref>) and may be a characteristic of a species that experienced an ancient population bottleneck (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Shankaranarayanan1">Shankaranarayanan et al. 1997</xref>). However, given the high degree of genetic variability of Short-tailed Babblers in a comparable population in Tawau Hills in Sabah (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f04">Figure 4</xref>), there is evidence supporting the inference that the genetically impoverished nature of the Singaporean population is mostly a result of human-induced fragmentation and decreasing population size over the past 2 centuries (along with its recent status as an island, which reduces dispersal rates). The reduced population size and fragmented landscape could have resulted in loss of genetic diversity through genetic drift. One might argue that an ancient bottleneck affected only the western clade of the species. However, this inference seems unlikely given the intrapopulation sequence divergence values obtained from samples from Terengganu in peninsular Malaysia (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4), which are more than double the pairwise sequence divergence levels observed in the Singapore population (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t02">Table 2</xref>).Although Short-tailed Babblers are forest dependent, and their original habitat is primary Sundaic rainforest, they have shown some adaptability across their range and have been known to utilize tracts of secondary forest. Although the CCNR forms one administrative entity, primary or old secondary forest patches within it are fragmented and isolated (&gt;100 m) from each other by reservoirs, golf courses, and other barriers associated with an urbanized matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Castelletta1">Castelletta et al. 2000</xref>), resulting in a fragmented distribution of the species across the reserve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Yee1">Yee et al. (2011)</xref>, primary lowland dipterocarp forest (118 ha), old secondary forest (995 ha), and freshwater swamp forest (283 ha)&mdash;the 3 vegetation types that Short-tailed Babblers are most likely to utilize&mdash;cover only 1.92&percnt; (1,396 ha) of Singapore's total land area. In a highly urbanized environment such as Singapore, patch size and continuity between good-quality forests appear to be the most important factors in ensuring the persistence of forest-dependent species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sodhi3">Sodhi et al. 2004b</xref>). Tropical-forest birds may be reluctant to cross matrices as narrow as 100 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Stouffer1">Stouffer and Bierregaard 1995</xref>); thus, geographically proximal forest patches connected by wide, good-quality corridors may be the solution to allow forest species in Singapore to survive as metapopulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-Sieving1">Sieving et al. 2000</xref>). Poor dispersal abilities of the forest-dependent babblers mean that small populations in forest fragments can no longer be buffered against inbreeding and local extinctions by individuals dispersing from larger patches, as shown by the current skewed distribution of haplotypes across the CCNR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Using direct comparisons with Tawau Hills population, we showed that the Singaporean population of Short-tailed Babblers is genetically impoverished (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-3-447-t03">Table 3</xref>). Such findings bring to attention the requirement for good connectivity between remnant forest patches in Singapore and other urbanizing nations. Enhanced connectivity of good-quality forest within the fragmentation zones of CCNR and BTNR is required in order to establish gene flow between subpopulations on the island, which may help buffer against the decline of population genetic diversity. Efforts must be made in countries with the adequate means and resources, such as Singapore, to preserve the little remaining rainforest cover in a well-connected network in order to increase the efficiency of conservation. The establishment of such corridors will aid in the survival of many taxa suffering from fragmentation and low population sizes.We thank G. Tang, N. Ng, E. Cros, A. Wee, D. Tan, R. Kolandavelu, Y. F. Chung, and R. Teo for field and lab support, as well as numerous volunteers who aided us with field work. We are grateful to S. Rajathurai for his advice on locations at which to mist-net Short-tailed Babblers. We thank J. Ascher and R. Meier for constructive comments.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This research was funded by the National University of Singapore (NUS) Faculty of Science and Department of Biological Sciences through grants WBS R-154-000-570-133 and R-154-000-583-651, respectively.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> National Parks Board of Singapore is acknowledged for facilitating fieldwork under permit RP13-019-2. Lab and field work were conducted in accordance with NUS's Office of Safety, Health and Environment regulations.Complete list of Short-tailed Babbler samples that we analyzed, from populations across the study region. Asterisks denote DNA extracted from samples comprising feathers only. Institutional abbreviations: ANHU &equals; Anhui Normal University, KUNHM &equals; University of Kansas Natural History Museum, LSUMNS &equals; Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science, NUS &equals; National University of Singapore, and UWBM &equals; University of Washington Burke Museum.