Population estimates for tidal marsh birds of high conservation concern in the northeastern USA from a design-based surveySeaside Sparrow, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content></italic>Arctic Shorebirds in North America: A Decade of MonitoringPlanning for sea-level rise: Quantifying patterns of Saltmarsh Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus caudacutus</named-content></italic>) nest flooding under current sea-level conditions<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus caudacutus</named-content></italic>. The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, Version 2014.3<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Laterallus jamaicensis</named-content></italic>. The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, Version 2014.3Bioregional monitoring design and occupancy estimation for two Sierra Nevadan amphibian taxaNest-site selection of Willets in a New Jersey salt marshEffective use of data from marshbird monitoring programs for conservation decision-makingStandardized North American marsh bird monitoring protocolA unified strategy for monitoring changes in abundance of birds associated with North American tidal marshesForecasting the effects of accelerated sea-level rise on tidal marsh ecosystem servicesLandscape-level sampling for status review of Great Basin redband troutA removal model for estimating detection probabilities from point-count surveysunmarked: An R package for fitting hierarchical models of wildlife occurrence and abundanceCall-response surveys for monitoring breeding waterbirdsEngineering away our natural defenses: An analysis of shoreline hardening in the USNest site selection and nesting success in saltmarsh breeding sparrows: The importance of nest habitat, timing, and study site differencesEgg and chick fates during tidal flooding of Saltmarsh Sharp-tailed Sparrow nestsTidal marshes: Home for the few and the highly selectedBehavioral and morphological diversification in Sharp-tailed Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus caudacutus</named-content></italic>) of the Atlantic CoastSeaside Sparrow, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content></italic>Wintering distributions and migration of Saltmarsh and Nelson's Sharp-tailed sparrowsBreeding birds of northeast saltmarshes: Habitat use and conservationRedefining range overlap between the Sharp-tailed Sparrows of coastal New EnglandThe impact of climate change on the world's marine ecosystemsA generalization of sampling without replacement from a finite universeHurricane-induced failure of low salinity wetlandsA sampling design framework for monitoring secretive marshbirdsThe potential for significant impacts on Chesapeake Bay from global warmingLandsat imagery shows decline of coastal marshes in Chesapeake and Delaware baysSea level rise and prescribed fire management: Implications for Seaside Sparrow population viabilityspsurvey: Spatial survey design and analysisLimits on the adaptability of coastal marshes to rising sea levelNesting habits of the Clapper Rail in New JerseyHow well do consistently monitored Breeding Bird Survey routes represent the environments of the conterminous United States?Blackwater 2100: A strategy for salt marsh persistence in an era of climate changeHabitat Suitability Index Models: Clapper RailWillet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tringa semipalmata</named-content></italic>)Performance of species occurrence estimators when basic assumptions are not met: A test using field data where true occupancy status is knownThe Sharp-tailed Sparrows of the Atlantic CoastResponses of coastal wetlands to rising sea levelUse of structured decision making to identify monitoring variables and management priorities for salt marsh ecosystemsDifferential habitat use by Acadian Nelson's Sharp-tailed Sparrows: Implications for regional conservationSharp-tailed SparrowVegetation succession and herbivory in a salt marsh: Changes induced by sea level rise and silt deposition along an elevational gradientPopulation status of North American grassland birds from the North American Breeding Bird SurveySeaside Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content></italic>)Application of genealogical-concordance principles to the taxonomy and evolutionary history of the Sharp-tailed Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus caudacutus</named-content></italic>)The Breeding Bird Survey: Its First Fifteen Years, 1965&ndash;1979Population declines in North American birds that migrate to the NeotropicsSalt marsh vegetation change in response to tidal restrictionGeneralized estimators of avian abundance from count survey dataClapper Rail (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rallus longirostris</named-content></italic>)Hotspot of accelerated sea-level rise on the Atlantic Coast of North AmericaModeling the influence of changing storm patterns on the ability of a salt marsh to keep pace with sea level riseProjected effects of sea-level rise on the population viability of Seaside Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content></italic>)Concordance between morphological and molecular markers in assessing hybridization between Sharp-tailed Sparrows in New EnglandLandscape context influences salt marsh bird diversity and area requirements in New EnglandHome range sizes and habitat use of Nelson's and Saltmarsh sparrowsFlood tides affect breeding ecology of two sympatric Sharp-tailed SparrowsSources of measurement error, misclassification error, and bias in auditory avian point count dataPower to detect trends in abundance of secretive marsh birds: Effects of species traits and sampling effortSpatially restricted surveys over time for aquatic resourcesVariance estimation for spatially balanced samples of environmental resourcesSpatially balanced sampling of natural resourcesClapper Rail populations of the middle Atlantic statesRecent observations on Maryland birdsBirds of Maryland and the District of ColumbiaStaying alive on the edge of the earth: Response of Seaside Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content></italic>) to salt marsh inundation, with implications for storms, spills, and climate changeThe Willets of Georgia and South CarolinaDownload Seamless Wetlands Data by StateNational Gap Analysis Program (GAP) Protected Areas Data PortalGenetic barcode RFLP analysis of the Nelson's and Saltmarsh sparrow hybrid zoneRelationship of phenotypic variation and genetic admixture in the Saltmarsh&ndash;Nelson's sparrow hybrid zoneA recent breeding record of the Saltmarsh Sharp-tailed Sparrow in Gloucester County, VirginiaWillet nesting in sphagnum bog in eastern MaineIncorporating climate change with conservation planning: A case study for tidal marsh bird conservation in Delaware, USAThe US Fish and Wildlife Service's National Wetlands Inventory projectStatus review of Chesapeake Bay marsh lands and breeding marsh birdsCurrent address: U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Charleston, South Carolina, USATidal marsh loss to anthropogenic environmental impacts and climate change, particularly sea level rise, has and will continue to cause declines in tidal marsh bird populations. Distribution patterns of tidal marsh birds are generally known, yet we lack detailed knowledge of local abundance and regional population sizes, which limits our ability to develop effective conservation strategies that will mitigate the impacts of marsh loss. We designed and implemented a probabilistic sampling framework to establish a regional marsh bird monitoring program, and collected baseline information for breeding tidal marsh birds in the northeastern USA (Maine to Virginia). We sampled 1,780 locations in 2011&ndash;2012 to provide regional population estimates for 5 tidal marsh&ndash;specialist birds. We estimated that there were 151,000 Clapper Rails (<italic>Rallus crepitans</italic>; 95&percnt; CI &equals; 90,000&ndash;212,000), 117,000 Willets (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tringa semipalmata</named-content></italic>; 95&percnt; CI &equals; 88,000&ndash;146,000), 5,000 Nelson's Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus nelsoni</named-content></italic>; 95&percnt; CI &equals; 1,000&ndash;9,000), 53,000 Saltmarsh Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. caudacutus</named-content></italic>; 95&percnt; CI &equals; 37,000&ndash;69,000), and 230,000 Seaside Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. maritimus</named-content></italic>; 95&percnt; CI &equals; 174,000&ndash;286,000) in northeastern tidal marshes. Our baseline assessment can be used to identify local habitat patches important to regional populations for each species and to prioritize conservation actions in targeted areas to maximize tidal marsh bird persistence. The flexibility and probabilistic design of our sampling framework also allow for integration with other monitoring programs (e.g., the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Salt Marsh Integrity Program and National Park Service Vital Signs Monitoring Program) so that inferences for these species can be made at multiple spatial scales.La p&eacute;rdida de marismas por causa de impactos ambientales antropog&eacute;nicos y cambio clim&aacute;tico, particularmente el aumento del nivel del mar, continuamente ha causado declives en las poblaciones de aves de marismas. En general los patrones de distribuci&oacute;n de aves de marismas son conocidos pero a&uacute;n falta conocimiento detallado de la abundancia local y de los tama&ntilde;os poblacionales regionales, lo que limita nuestra habilidad para desarrollar estrategias de conservaci&oacute;n efectivas que mitiguen los impactos de la p&eacute;rdida de marismas. Dise&ntilde;amos e implementamos un marco de muestreo probabil&iacute;stico para establecer un programa regional de monitoreo de aves de marisma y recolectamos informaci&oacute;n b&aacute;sica de las aves de marismas en el noreste de EEUU (Maine a Virginia). Muestreamos 1789 ubicaciones entre 2011 y 2012 para presentar estimados regionales de tama&ntilde;o poblacional de cinco aves especialistas de marismas. Estimamos 151000 <italic>Rallus crepitans</italic> (95&percnt; IC &equals; 90000-212000), 117000 <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tringa semipalmata</named-content></italic> (88000-146000), 5000 <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus nelsoni</named-content></italic> (1000-9000), 53000 <italic>A, caudacutus</italic> (37000-69000) y 230000 <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. maritimus</named-content></italic> (174000-286000) en los marismas del noreste. Nuestra estimaci&oacute;n base puede ser usada para identificar parches locales de h&aacute;bitat importantes para las poblaciones regionales de cada especie y para priorizar las acciones de conservaci&oacute;n en &aacute;reas espec&iacute;ficas para maximizar la persistencia de las aves de marismas. La flexibilidad de nuestro marco de muestreo y el dise&ntilde;o probabil&iacute;stico tambi&eacute;n permiten su integraci&oacute;n con otros programas de monitoreo (e.g. el Programa de Integridad de Marismas del Servicio de Pesca y Fauna Silvestre de EEUU, y Signos Vitales del Servicio de Parques Nacionales) para que tales inferencias puedan hacerse en m&uacute;ltiples escalas espaciales.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> abundancia, aves de marisma, dise&ntilde;o de muestreo, marisma, monitoreo, noreste de EEUU, poblaci&oacute;nTidal marshes are dynamic ecosystems with a history of large-scale degradation due to human impacts, including development, hydrologic alterations (e.g., ditching and tidal restrictions), grazing and agriculture, pollutants, and introduced species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Daiber1">Daiber 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Batzer1">Batzer and Baldwin 2012</xref>). Anthropogenic activities continue to pose immediate threats to tidal marsh viability, and climate change is predicted to exacerbate the loss and deterioration of these coastal habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Greenberg1">Greenberg 2006</xref>). Tidal marshes are sensitive to climate change primarily through accelerated sea level rise and increased coastal storm severity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Morris1">Morris et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Schuerch1">Schuerch et al. 2013</xref>). Increases in the severity and frequency of flooding events and changes in salinity affect vegetation structure and zonation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Roman1">Roman et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Olff1">Olff et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Howes1">Howes et al. 2010</xref>), and temperature increases alter food-web dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-HoeghGuldberg1">Hoegh-Guldberg and Bruno 2010</xref>). Elevated sea levels coupled with low sediment supply and vertical accretion rates convert tidal marshes to open water, a process that has been occurring in some marsh systems for decades (e.g., Blackwater National Wildlife Refuge; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kearney2">Kearney et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kearney1">Kearney 2008</xref>). The impacts of climate change and persistent anthropogenic environmental threats jeopardize tidal marshes globally, collaterally affecting ecosystem services and habitat-specialist flora and fauna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Craft1">Craft et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kirwan1">Kirwan et al. 2010</xref>).Loss of tidal marsh habitat threatens the population viability of tidal marsh birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver1">Shriver and Gibbs 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Gjerdrum1">Gjerdrum et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver5">Shriver et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kern1">Kern and Shriver 2014</xref>) and contributes to the sensitivity of these birds to climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NorthAmericanBirdConservationInitiativeUSCommittee3">North American Bird Conservation Initiative U.S. Committee 2010</xref>). Reliable population abundance and trend estimates are necessary to identify priority areas and strategies for conservation before populations decline rapidly and are threatened with extinction. North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) data have been used to estimate population trends for many landbird species in the USA and to identify species in need of immediate conservation action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Robbins1">Robbins et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Robbins2">1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Peterjohn1">Peterjohn and Sauer 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NorthAmericanBirdConservationInitiativeUSCommittee2">North American Bird Conservation Initiative U.S. Committee 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NorthAmericanBirdConservationInitiativeUSCommittee3">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NorthAmericanBirdConservationInitiativeUSCommittee4">2014</xref>). The BBS, however, is a roadside-based survey, which inadequately samples emergent wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Gibbs1">Gibbs and Melvin 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lawler1">Lawler and O'Connor 2004</xref>), thereby limiting the application of BBS data to estimating marsh bird population trends.The regional and local abundance of 5 tidal marsh birds breeding in northeastern North America (Clapper Rail &lsqb;<italic>Rallus crepitans</italic>&rsqb;, Willet &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tringa semipalmata</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, Nelson's Sparrow &lsqb;<italic>Ammodramus nelsoni</italic>&rsqb;, Saltmarsh Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. caudacutus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, and Seaside Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. maritimus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) is presently unknown. This information gap, and concerns about their status, contributed to the identification of these birds as Species of Greatest Conservation Need in the Wildlife Action Plans of multiple states (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NewHampshireFishandGameDepartment1">New Hampshire Fish and Game Department 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-DelawareDivisionofFishandWildlife1">Delaware Division of Fish and Wildlife 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NewJerseyDivisionofFishandWildlife1">New Jersey Division of Fish and Wildlife 2008</xref>). At the global scale, the Saltmarsh Sparrow is listed as Vulnerable due to the species' small, heavily fragmented range and continuing decline in suitable habitat (IUCN Red List; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-BirdLifeInternational1">BirdLife International 2012a</xref>); the species' global breeding range is limited to the northeastern USA.Here, in an attempt to address a fundamental information need, we applied the approach proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Johnson1">Johnson et al. (2009)</xref> to monitoring tidal marsh birds in northeastern USA marshes from Maine southward to Virginia (hereafter, the Northeast). This approach was successfully piloted by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and 7 state wildlife agencies (Florida, Idaho, Kentucky, Michigan, New York, Ohio, and Wisconsin; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Brady1">Brady and Paulios 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Seamans1">Seamans 2011</xref>), and was considered a cost-effective and appropriate sampling protocol for monitoring marsh birds. Data collected using this design can be incorporated into an adaptive management program that integrates monitoring with management and directs research in order to address emerging conservation questions, such as how to mitigate the impacts of climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 2010</xref>). A coordinated, region-wide effort using standardized protocols within a single sampling design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway1">Conway 2011</xref>) is required to estimate marsh bird population trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver3">Shriver et al. 2004</xref>) and to compare species abundances across Northeast marsh systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway2">Conway and Droege 2006</xref>). The goals of this project were to provide the information necessary for the states in the New England/Mid-Atlantic Coast Bird Conservation Region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-NorthAmericanBirdConservationInitiativeUSCommittee1">North American Bird Conservation Initiative U.S. Committee 2000</xref>) to protect regionally important habitats for tidal marsh birds and to provide a consistent platform for tidal marsh bird monitoring. Our objectives were to: (1) develop a sampling framework to inventory tidal marsh birds in the Northeast; (2) establish the foundation for long-term monitoring; and (3) provide population estimates for the Clapper Rail, Willet, Nelson's Sparrow, Saltmarsh Sparrow, and Seaside Sparrow.We conducted this research in tidal marsh habitat from Maine to Virginia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-f01">Figure 1</xref>) during the 2011&ndash;2012 breeding seasons (April&ndash;July). Coastal marshes from the Canada&ndash;Maine border to Cape Cod, Massachusetts, on the Gulf of Maine are classified as Acadian coastal salt marsh (NatureServe ID: CES201.578; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Comer1">Comer et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Ferree1">Ferree and Anderson 2013</xref>). These polyhaline marshes are interspersed throughout the rocky sections of the Gulf of Maine coast along the ocean shoreline and estuary mouths. Acadian coastal salt marsh is dominated by the graminoids <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spartina patens</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. alterniflora</named-content></italic>, and includes patches of other graminoids (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Juncus balticus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">J. gerardii</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Puccinellia maritima</named-content></italic>) and forbs (e.g., <italic>Limonium carolinianum</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Plantago maritima</named-content></italic> var. <italic>juncoides</italic>). Acadian coastal salt marshes typically occur as small patches, but may be more extensive where topography allows, although they are rarely as extensive as tidal marshes elsewhere along the U.S. Atlantic Coast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Comer1">Comer et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Ferree1">Ferree and Anderson 2013</xref>). Currently, the average patch size of Acadian coastal salt marsh is 2 ha and the largest single patch is 337 ha, compared with 4 ha and 7,877 ha, respectively, for Northern Atlantic Coastal Plain tidal salt marsh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Anderson1">Anderson et al. 2013</xref>). Northern Atlantic Coastal Plain tidal salt marsh extends from Cape Cod, Massachusetts, to the mouth of the Chesapeake Bay, and intermittently along the southern coast of the Gulf of Maine to southern Maine (NatureServe ID: CES203.519; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Comer1">Comer et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Ferree1">Ferree and Anderson 2013</xref>). This intertidal system occurs on the bayside of barrier beaches and along the outer mouths of tidal rivers where saline to mesohaline conditions are not strongly affected by freshwater flow. Northern Atlantic Coastal Plain tidal salt marshes also are dominated by the graminoids <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. patens</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. alterniflora</named-content></italic>, but tend to have more <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Distichlis spicata</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Salicornia</named-content></italic> spp. than Acadian coastal salt marshes, as well as more developed upland borders containing shrubs such as <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Iva frutescens</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Baccharis halimifolia</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Juniperus virginiana</named-content></italic>, with an herbaceous layer of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Panicum virgatum</named-content></italic>.The sampling universe for surveys of tidal marsh birds in the northeastern USA, delineated into subregions. Subregions are composed of 40 km<sup>2</sup> hexagons containing estuarine intertidal emergent marsh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Cowardin1">Cowardin et al. 1979</xref>). Subregion boundaries were developed based on suggestions by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway2">Conway and Droege (2006</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref>). State abbreviations: CT &equals; Connecticut, DC &equals; District of Columbia, DE &equals; Delaware, MA &equals; Massachusetts, MD &equals; Maryland, ME &equals; Maine, NC &equals; North Carolina, NH &equals; New Hampshire, NJ &equals; New Jersey, NY &equals; New York, PA &equals; Pennsylvania, RI &equals; Rhode Island, VA &equals; Virginia, VT &equals; Vermont, and WV &equals; West Virginia.Subregions used for sampling stratification for surveys of tidal marsh birds, and summary statistics describing the sampling universe (number of 40 km<sup>2</sup> hexagons and marsh area &lsqb;ha&rsqb;) and sampled area (number of hexagons, marsh area &lsqb;ha&rsqb;, and number of survey points) in the northeastern USA. Subregion boundaries were developed based on suggestions by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway2">Conway and Droege (2006</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-f01">Figure 1</xref> for subregion map and state abbreviation definitions).We used a 2-stage cluster sampling design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Thompson1">Thompson 2012</xref>) with generalized random-tessellation stratified (GRTS) sampling at each stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens1">Stevens and Olsen 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens2">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens3">2004</xref>) to distribute survey points following recommendations for sample selection developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Johnson1">Johnson et al. (2009)</xref>. The GRTS survey design emphasizes a spatially balanced sample; a sample is dispersed such that the spatial density pattern of the sample closely mimics the spatial density pattern of the environmental resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens1">Stevens and Olsen 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens2">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens3">2004</xref>). The 2-stage cluster design requires a geographic division of the study area and separate selection protocols for the 2 types of sampling units: primary sampling units (PSUs; hexagons) and secondary sampling units (SSUs; survey points). We used a North American continental hexagon grid (40 km<sup>2</sup> hexagons) to generate the PSU sampling universe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Seamans1">Seamans 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Brown1">Brown and Olsen 2013</xref>). We used the hexagons for logistical reasons to maximize efficiency of access to survey points. We selected the subset of the continental grid that included all hexagons located in the 10 Northeast coastal states that contained Estuarine Intertidal Emergent Wetland (E2EM; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Cowardin1">Cowardin et al. 1979</xref>) as designated by state wetland geospatial data from the National Wetlands Inventory (NWI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Wilen1">Wilen and Bates 1995</xref>, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service National Wetlands Inventory 2010). We compiled and processed the E2EM geospatial features in ArcGIS 9.3 (ESRI, Redlands, California, USA) to develop a single spatial layer of salt marsh in the Northeast. Northeast hexagons that contained salt marsh became the sampling universe for the selection of PSUs. We did not divide the sampling universe further by wetland size (small and discrete or large and extensive) or by accessibility, as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Johnson1">Johnson et al. (2009)</xref>, because the NWI layer that we used for the entire region digitized very small polygons of tidal marsh that were effectively part of the same larger marsh, and because we could not determine wetland accessibility prior to sampling.We used the spsurvey package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kincaid1">Kincaid and Olsen 2012</xref>) in program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2014</xref>) to select hexagons and survey points. We divided the hexagon sampling universe into 8 mutually exclusive strata (subregions; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-f01">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref>); subregion boundaries were based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway2">Conway and Droege (2006)</xref> and were generally delineated by major geomorphological features (e.g., Long Island, Delmarva Peninsula, and Chesapeake Bay). In Stage 1 of our 2-stage design, we selected 3 independent samples of hexagons using a GRTS survey design for a finite resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens1">Stevens and Olsen 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stevens3">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Brown1">Brown and Olsen 2013</xref>). First, we selected all hexagons containing federally managed marsh (USFWS and/or National Park Service &lsqb;NPS&rsqb;); second, we selected a stratified equal probability sample of hexagons with state-managed marsh; and third, we selected a stratified equal probability sample of hexagons from the entire sampling universe. We then pooled the hexagons selected by the 3 independent samples to create our PSUs. Hexagons with federally managed marsh had highest priority for selection because the USFWS and NPS conduct tidal marsh bird surveys and are likely to continue to do so into the future. Within each subregion, we randomly selected up to 25 hexagons that contained tidal marsh on state lands, and up to 25 hexagons from the entire sampling universe; we excluded hexagons that contained &lt;10 ha of marsh from both samples. In the third sample, we also selected 10 extra hexagons within each subregion in the event that core sampling hexagons could not be sampled due to marsh inaccessibility (e.g., denied access, impassible terrain, or absence of habitat). We used the Protected Areas Database (U.S. Geological Survey 2011) to identify hexagons that contained tidal marsh on USFWS, NPS, and state lands. Final sampled hexagons were limited to a subset of selected hexagons due to time and financial constraints.In Stage 2 of our 2-stage design, we used an equal probability sample to randomly locate 10 survey points and 10 extra survey points in the NWI-delineated marsh in each selected hexagon. To make comparisons with previous bird surveys, we acquired the coordinates of existing tidal marsh bird survey points from historical and ongoing projects (20 projects total; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t02">Table 2</xref>), and retained existing points located within selected hexagons. We used ArcGIS (ESRI, Redlands, CA, USA) to combine the existing point locations with the randomly generated points, such that all points were at least 400 m apart following the minimum distance recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway1">Conway (2011)</xref> to maintain spatial independence. Once the historical and contemporary, randomly selected points were identified, we ground-truthed all sampling points, prioritizing points with historical survey data. We ground-truthed the established points first (if the hexagon possessed them), and then the randomly located survey points followed by the extra survey points, until we had identified up to 10 survey points in accessible, appropriate saltmarsh habitat in each selected hexagon. Survey points consisted of a mix of wetland edge and marsh interior locations, and were accessed by foot, vehicle, and nonmotorized or motorized boats.Historical and ongoing studies with existing marsh bird survey points in the northeastern USA. Studies are listed by organization type, then from north to south. &lsquo;Y' indicates that historical points were resurveyed in 2011 and/or 2012, and &lsquo;N' indicates that no points were resurveyed. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-f01">Figure 1</xref> for state abbreviation definitions.We delineated habitat patches to estimate species abundance within discrete, biologically relevant spatial areas and to allow for comparisons in abundance patterns across the region. We used the NWI E2EM spatial layer developed for the survey sampling design to define saltmarsh habitat patches. We used ArcGIS to create a 50-m buffer around the marsh polygon features. Polygons with buffers that intersected were considered to be the same patch based on home range size and movement estimates for Nelson's and Saltmarsh sparrows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver4">Shriver et al. 2010</xref>). We assigned each patch a unique ID and recorded the state (e.g., Maine, New Hampshire), subregion (e.g., Coastal Maine, Cape Cod&ndash;Casco Bay), longitude, latitude, and area.We used the North American Marsh Bird Monitoring Protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway1">Conway 2011</xref>) to estimate the abundance of our 5 focal species within our study region (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="dx.doi.org/10.1650/CONDOR-15-30.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Appendix A</ext-link>). At all survey points, we conducted 5-min passive point counts divided into 1-min intervals, followed immediately by a sequence of 30-s marsh bird broadcasts. A single observer conducted surveys from 30 min before sunrise to ~11:00 AM and visited each sampling point 2&ndash;3 times from April 15 to July 31 in both 2011 and 2012. The seasonal timing of survey visits was adjusted for latitudinal differences in the timing of breeding across the subregions (see <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="dx.doi.org/10.1650/CONDOR-15-30.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Appendix A</ext-link>). We did not survey during high winds, sustained rain, or heavy fog. During each survey, we estimated the number of individuals for each species detected in 3 distance categories: 0&ndash;50 m, 50&ndash;100 m, and &gt;100 m.We used the unmarked package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Fiske1">Fiske and Chandler 2011</xref>) in program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2014</xref>) to estimate species abundance in each surveyed patch. We estimated the abundance of each species using detections from the 0&ndash;50 m distance interval and the 0&ndash;5 min passive sampling period. We subset the data spatially (within 0&ndash;50 m) to reduce variability in our samples, analyzing detections closest to the observer where the ability to correctly identify species is greatest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Simons1">Simons et al. 2009</xref>). We subset the data temporally (within 0&ndash;5 min) to standardize the survey sampling and analysis procedure across the region and to make direct comparisons between subregion estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Miller1">Miller et al. 2015</xref>). We estimated abundance using a general multinomial-Poisson mixture model (the &lsquo;multinomPois' function; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Royle1">Royle 2004</xref>). We accounted for each species' detection probability (<italic>p</italic>) with the time-of-detection method using our 5 1-min intervals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Farnsworth1">Farnsworth et al. 2002</xref>). We developed separate models for each species, following unique combinations of species&ndash;subregion&ndash;year (e.g., Clapper Rail&ndash;Long Island&ndash;2011, Clapper Rail&ndash;Coastal New Jersey&ndash;2011, Seaside Sparrow&ndash;Coastal New Jersey&ndash;2011, Seaside Sparrow&ndash;Coastal New Jersey&ndash;2012, etc.). For all models, we treated the unique patch ID as a site covariate to estimate species abundance by patch. Therefore, our models are based on stacking data from repeated survey visits, such that our effective sites are derived from the 2&ndash;3 survey visits at each sampling point. We assumed that detection probability was constant within the 50-m radius circle and across the 1-min intervals for a single survey visit for a species, but heterogeneous in other instances (i.e. among survey visits, species, subregions, and years). Because models were individually tailored to species&ndash;subregion&ndash;year combinations, we limited the modeling of detection probability to a function of survey visit number (modeled as a factor) to control for seasonal differences in detection rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Farnsworth1">Farnsworth et al. 2002</xref>). We also assumed population closure for sampling during the breeding season. The general structure of our abundance models was: Abundance(PatchID), <italic>p</italic>(SurveyVisit). When an abundance estimation model did not converge for a patch, we applied the global mean abundance estimate for the same year to that patch. We averaged the 2011 and 2012 patch abundance estimates to calculate mean patch abundance for each species. We estimated the total patch abundance for each species within each patch by converting the mean patch abundance based on the area sampled (the 50-m radius point-count circle) and multiplying by patch area.We used the &lsquo;total.est' function in the spsurvey package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kincaid1">Kincaid and Olsen 2012</xref>) to estimate the population size for each species within each subregion and region-wide. The &lsquo;total.est' function estimates population totals for single-stage or 2-stage samples using the Horvitz-Thompson estimator and estimates confidence bounds using a normal distribution multiplier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Horvitz1">Horvitz and Thompson 1952</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-DiazRamos1">Diaz-Ramos et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kincaid2">Kincaid et al. 2015</xref>). We calculated population totals (with 95&percnt; confidence intervals) for each species using the total abundance within each patch as the response value. We used the &lsquo;intersect' geoprocessing tool in ArcGIS to calculate patch area within each hexagon because tidal marsh patches could be present in multiple hexagons.For a 2-stage sample, &lsquo;total.est' requires a final adjusted Stage 1 weight (&ldquo;wgt1&rdquo;) and a final adjusted Stage 2 weight (&ldquo;wgt&rdquo;) for each site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kincaid2">Kincaid et al. 2015</xref>). We defined the final adjusted Stage 1 weight as the inverse of the hexagon sample inclusion probability. Because we selected 3 independent samples of hexagons, a hexagon could potentially be selected up to 3 times depending on the level of protection for marsh within the hexagon, and therefore have up to 3 possible inclusion probability values. Hexagons with federally managed marsh had an inclusion probability of &ldquo;1&rdquo; because each hexagon had a 100&percnt; chance of being selected, and inclusion probabilities for hexagons included in the 2 equal probability samples (state lands sample and entire sampling universe sample) depended on the strata. We attributed to each hexagon the inclusion probability for the highest level of marsh protection that the hexagon contained in order to calculate Stage 1 weight. The final adjusted Stage 2 weight for each site equaled the site's final adjusted Stage 1 weight divided by the probability of selecting the site (site area divided by hexagon marsh area, multiplied by the number of survey points sampled within the hexagon; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Dambacher1">Dambacher et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Brown1">Brown and Olsen 2013</xref>). We modified Stage 2 weights using the final sample size of survey points to reflect the number of instances that a site could have been selected during actual bird sampling in each hexagon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Dambacher1">Dambacher et al. 2009</xref>). We restricted the lower limit of the final adjusted Stage 2 weights to &ldquo;1&rdquo; and used the simple random sampling variance estimator in &lsquo;total.est' to calculate joint inclusion probabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-DiazRamos1">Diaz-Ramos et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kincaid2">Kincaid et al. 2015</xref>).We estimated population sizes within species' breeding ranges: Clapper Rail, south of 41.3390&deg;N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Rush1">Rush et al. 2012</xref>); Nelson's Sparrow, north of 42.8520&deg;N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hodgman1">Hodgman et al. 2002</xref>); Saltmarsh Sparrow, south of 44.0753&deg;N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hodgman1">Hodgman et al. 2002</xref>); and Seaside Sparrow, south of 42.9185&deg;N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Post1">Post and Greenlaw 2009</xref>). We estimated the number of Willets for all Northeast tidal marsh patches because Willets breed throughout the entire region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lowther1">Lowther et al. 2001</xref>). We report population estimates and 95&percnt; confidence intervals to the nearest 1,000 (or 100, where applicable).The primary sampling universe across all subregions (Coastal Maine to Eastern Chesapeake Bay) consisted of 1,110 hexagons containing 280,722 ha of salt marsh (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref>). The number of hexagons in each subregion ranged from 88 in Delaware Bay (59,956 ha of salt marsh) to 212 in Eastern Chesapeake Bay (78,337 ha of salt marsh). Because we stratified our sampling effort independent of the extent of salt marsh in a subregion, a large sample of total hexagons did not necessarily indicate a large quantity of salt marsh. We excluded 259 hexagons (973 ha of salt marsh) from the initial GRTS hexagon selection because these hexagons each contained &lt;10 ha of marsh.We sampled 277 of the 1,110 total hexagons (25&percnt;; 135,043 ha of salt marsh). The number of hexagons surveyed in each subregion ranged from 22 in Eastern Chesapeake Bay to 44 in Cape Cod&ndash;Casco Bay (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref>). Marsh managed by state agencies occurred in 127 of the surveyed hexagons; 60 surveyed hexagons contained both state and federally managed marsh; and an additional 32 surveyed hexagons contained marsh managed by federal agencies only. Of the 92 surveyed hexagons containing federally managed marsh, 63 hexagons contained USFWS-managed marsh, 23 hexagons contained NPS-managed marsh, and 6 hexagons contained marsh managed by both agencies.We sampled 1,780 survey points in the sampled hexagons. Surveyed points included 1,314 new points and 466 historical points from 18 of the 20 prior projects (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t02">Table 2</xref>). The number of survey points in each subregion ranged from 119 points on Long Island to 340 points in Cape Cod&ndash;Casco Bay (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref>). The distribution of survey points on public vs. private lands was 45&percnt; and 55&percnt;, respectively. We sampled 1,642 of the survey points in 2011; 1,714 of the points in 2012; and 1,575 of the points in both years.We delineated 8,405 saltmarsh habitat patches in the Northeast (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t03">Table 3</xref>). Total patches per subregion ranged from 166 patches in Delaware Bay to 3,341 patches in Eastern Chesapeake Bay. Delaware Bay had the fewest and largest patches (360 &plusmn; 145 ha &lsqb;all areas reported as means &plusmn; SE&rsqb;). Patches north and south of Delaware Bay in Coastal New Jersey and Coastal Delmarva also were large and shared similar average area dimensions: ~500 patches in each subregion, with a mean area of 95 &plusmn; 27 ha. Cape Cod&ndash;Casco Bay also contained ~500 patches, but patches were smaller (38 &plusmn; 8 ha). Mean patch areas were smaller still on Long Island (14 &plusmn; 1 ha) and in Eastern Chesapeake Bay (23 &plusmn; 9 ha). In Coastal Maine and Southern New England, more than 1,000 saltmarsh patches were &lt;10 ha.Number of saltmarsh habitat patches in the northeastern USA, number of patches sampled, and estimated abundance of tidal marsh&ndash;specialist birds during the breeding season, 2011&ndash;2012, by subregion (north to south) and region-wide. NA &equals; not applicable, i.e. species does not breed regularly in that subregion. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-f01">Figure 1</xref> for subregion map and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t01">Table 1</xref> for descriptions of subregion boundaries.We detected Clapper Rails from Southern New England south to Virginia. We estimated that there were 151,000 Clapper Rails (95&percnt; CI &equals; 90,000&ndash;212,000) in the Northeast. Coastal Delmarva supported ~51&percnt; of the estimated population (77,000 birds, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 23,000&ndash;131,000; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-t03">Table 3</xref>). We detected Willets in all subregions and estimated that there were 117,000 Willets (95&percnt; CI &equals; 88,000&ndash;146,000) across Northeast saltmarsh patches. We estimated the greatest abundance of Willets in Coastal New Jersey (36,000 birds, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 15,000&ndash;57,000). We estimated that there were 5,000 Nelson's Sparrows (95&percnt; CI &equals; 1,000&ndash;9,000) in the Northeast, with Coastal Maine supporting 60&percnt; of the estimated population (3,000 birds, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 1,000&ndash;5,000). We detected Saltmarsh Sparrows in all subregions and estimated that there were 53,000 Saltmarsh Sparrows (95&percnt; CI &equals; 37,000&ndash;69,000) in the Northeast. We estimated the greatest abundance of Saltmarsh Sparrows in Coastal New Jersey (20,000 birds, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 7,000&ndash;33,000). We estimated that there were 230,000 Seaside Sparrows (95&percnt; CI &equals; 174,000&ndash;286,000) in the Northeast. Eastern Chesapeake Bay supported the greatest number of Seaside Sparrow individuals (93,000 birds, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 66,000&ndash;120,000).Here, we provide the first comprehensive assessment of the distribution and abundance of tidal marsh&ndash;specialist birds in the Northeast, USA, and lay the foundation for systematic region-wide monitoring. Our population estimates can be used to determine regional responsibilities for priority species, and provide baseline population sizes for estimating trends over time. Federal and state wildlife agencies and nongovernmental organizations already have used our initial sampling results for assessing species status, updating state Wildlife Action Plans, and informing conservation planning (e.g., identifying Important Bird Areas and target sites for marsh migration; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lerner1">Lerner et al. 2013</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Wiest2">Wiest et al. 2014</xref>).Clapper Rail population size was greatest in the Coastal Delmarva and Coastal New Jersey subregions, which are dominated by extensive back-barrier lagoon marsh systems. On the East Coast of the U.S., Clapper Rails were most abundant in low tidal salt marsh that is flooded at least once daily and dominated by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spartina</named-content></italic> spp. of moderate height (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Meanley1">Meanley 1985</xref>), habitat characteristics indicative of back-barrier lagoon marshes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Mangold1">Mangold (1974)</xref> found that Clapper Rails in New Jersey tended to use natural and ditched marsh habitats with short-form <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. alterniflora</named-content></italic>, followed by areas of tall-form <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. alterniflora</named-content></italic>; few Clapper Rails were detected in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. patens</named-content></italic>. Clapper Rails nest in emergent wetlands or scrub&ndash;shrub mangroves, typically within 15 m of a tidally influenced waterbody (e.g., ditches, creeks, streams, rivers, and embayments; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lewis1">Lewis and Garrison 1983</xref>), although many East Coast nests are found within 5 m of water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kozicky1">Kozicky and Schmidt 1949</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stewart1">Stewart 1951</xref>). Clapper Rail subspecies <italic>crepitans</italic> breeds from southern New England to southern North Carolina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Rush1">Rush et al. 2012</xref>) and is more common in the southern states that serve as both breeding and wintering grounds for the northeastern population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Meanley1">Meanley 1985</xref>). Our results were consistent with the expected broad distribution and abundance patterns of the subspecies; our greatest abundance estimate was in one of the most southern subregions in our study area (Coastal Delmarva).Willets were widespread in the Northeast; the Eastern Willet subspecies <italic>semipalmatus</italic> has a large latitudinal breeding range, extending along the Atlantic and Gulf coasts of North America and to the West Indies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lowther1">Lowther et al. 2001</xref>). Willet abundance was greatest in Coastal New Jersey, with this subregion containing 31&percnt; of the total population. Combined, 3 subregions (Coastal New Jersey, Delaware Bay, and Coastal Delmarva) contained 75&percnt; of the regional Willet population. We caution that Willet numbers may be overestimated if the presence of observers attracts individuals into the survey area, as has been found for other nesting shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Bart1">Bart and Johnston 2012</xref>). By using only data from a 50-m radius around each point, we expect this problem to be minimal, but additional work to investigate the potential role of inflated detection rates is warranted for this species. In addition, some conservation practitioners do not consider the Willet a tidal-marsh specialist in more southern states, including Virginia, as the species is often found nesting in short vegetation behind dunes or on bare ground (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Tomkins1">Tomkins 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Douglas1">Douglas 1996</xref>). Willets also have been documented nesting in habitats other than saltmarsh in more northern states (sand dune areas with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammophila breviligulata</named-content></italic> in New Jersey; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Burger1">Burger and Shisler 1978</xref>; 1 record in a sphagnum bog in Maine; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Wells1">Wells and Vickery 1990</xref>) and in Nova Scotia (open fields and pastures near marshes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Tufts1">Tufts 1986</xref>); however, nesting habitat in the Northeast remains predominantly salt marshes with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. alterniflora</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. patens</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Lowther1">Lowther et al. 2001</xref>).Nelson's Sparrow population size estimates were consistent with the known North American extent of the breeding range of the Acadian race <italic>A. n. subvirgatus</italic>, which breeds in salt marshes from Quebec, Canada, to the northeastern shore of Massachusetts, USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Greenlaw3">Greenlaw and Woolfenden 2007</xref>). At the southern end of the range, the subspecies occurs sympatrically with the Saltmarsh Sparrow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Montagna1">Montagna 1942</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Greenlaw1">Greenlaw 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hodgman1">Hodgman et al. 2002</xref>); the overlap zone extends from the Weskeag River in South Thomaston, Maine, to Parker River National Wildlife Refuge in Newburyport, Massachusetts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hodgman1">Hodgman et al. 2002</xref>). Hybridization between Nelson's and Saltmarsh sparrows has been documented in the overlap zone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Rising1">Rising and Avise 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hodgman1">Hodgman et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver2">Shriver et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Walsh1">Walsh et al. 2011</xref>), and hybrids potentially occur in all marshes where the 2 species coexist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver2">Shriver et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Walsh1">Walsh et al. 2011</xref>). In the putative hybrid zone, &ldquo;pure&rdquo; individuals are difficult to distinguish from introgressed individuals by morphology alone; at the southern end of the zone, individuals confirmed to be hybrids using genetic testing were identified as Saltmarsh Sparrows in the field based on morphological characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver2">Shriver et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Walsh1">Walsh et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Walsh2">2015</xref>). More research across the hybrid zone is needed to determine whether there is a bias toward either sparrow phenotype; moreover, the effect of introgression on vocalization remains unstudied. Hybridization has clear implications for detecting species accurately from visual markers and possibly vocal cues during point counts. Technicians surveying in the hybrid zone may falsely record an introgressed individual as a &ldquo;pure&rdquo; individual, leading to underestimates of hybrids and overestimates of the parental species. Additional research on hybrids will help to improve Nelson's and Saltmarsh sparrow population estimates and distribution mapping, as well as assist conservation practitioners with weighing the role of hybridization in species conservation and in evaluating possible strategies to protect genetically &ldquo;pure&rdquo; populations.We estimated that 37&percnt; of the total Saltmarsh Sparrow breeding population occurred in the Coastal New Jersey subregion and 17&percnt; in the Eastern Chesapeake Bay subregion. Three northern subregions (Cape Cod&ndash;Casco Bay, Southern New England, and Long Island), where the distribution of salt marsh habitat begins to decline, supported 28&percnt; of the total Saltmarsh Sparrow population. The Saltmarsh Sparrow's total population size prior to our study was estimated to be between 30,000 and 50,000 individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Elphick1">Elphick et al. 2009</xref>). The difference relative to our current point estimate of 53,000, however, does not represent a population increase, but rather results from the use of a formal sampling approach, as opposed to a crude extrapolation from a single state's data. In addition to supporting a large proportion of Saltmarsh Sparrows, Eastern Chesapeake Bay supported 40&percnt; of the regional Seaside Sparrow population. Combined, the subregions in the mid-Atlantic (Coastal New Jersey, Delaware Bay, Coastal Delmarva, and Eastern Chesapeake Bay) supported 97&percnt; of the Seaside Sparrows in the Northeast, consistent with the core of the breeding range for the subspecies <italic>A. m. maritimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Post1">Post and Greenlaw 2009</xref>). Seaside Sparrows occurred on Long Island and in Southern New England, but overall population sizes were relatively low. In New York, the Seaside Sparrow is considered a rare and local breeder in the state's maritime areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Arbib1">Arbib 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Greenlaw2">Greenlaw 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-McGowan1">McGowan and Corwin 2008</xref>), although rare presence in noncoastal marshes has also been documented (on the Hudson River; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Bull1">Bull 1974</xref>). Seaside Sparrow breeding populations in New England are localized and disjunct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Post1">Post and Greenlaw 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Kamm1">Kamm et al. 2013</xref>), and our results aligned with this distribution and low abundance. The species is rarely detected in Maine and New Hampshire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Post1">Post and Greenlaw 2009</xref>); we detected 1 individual in Maine at Scarborough Marsh in 2011.Where bird populations are likely to persist into the future given sea level rise and marsh loss is one of today's most critical questions for tidal marsh bird conservation. For the endemic Saltmarsh Sparrow, population growth is likely limited by frequent nest failure from tidal flooding and coastal storm events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver5">Shriver et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Gjerdrum2">Gjerdrum et al. 2008</xref>), and the effects of climate change are expected to exacerbate flooding impacts on Saltmarsh Sparrow reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Bayard1">Bayard and Elphick 2011</xref>). Coastal marshes may keep pace with sea level rise by transgressing upslope through marsh accretion; however, marshes north of the last glacial maximum (roughly from Long Island northward) have fewer opportunities for marsh transgression given the steeper elevational gradient to surrounding uplands. The extent of hard shoreline barriers (e.g., development, infrastructure) from New Jersey to Massachusetts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Gittman1">Gittman et al. 2015</xref>) further hampers the potential for transgression. Moreover, rates of sea level rise exceed global averages across most of the Saltmarsh Sparrow's breeding range, including much of our study region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Sallenger1">Sallenger et al. 2012</xref>).Habitat patches that support high abundances of tidal marsh&ndash;specialist birds support other coastal bird species of conservation concern that are susceptible to the same major threats. For example, Lanes Island in Shinnecock Bay, New York, supports a high density of Willets and also provides habitat for colonies of both state-listed Common Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>) and federally endangered Roseate Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. dougallii</named-content></italic>; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 1997). East Coast U.S. tidal marshes are also important for wintering American Black Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>) and the globally Near Threatened Black Rail (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Laterallus jamaicensis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-BirdLifeInternational2">BirdLife International 2012b</xref>); both species are of high conservation concern across their range and breed locally at low abundances in the Northeast. Our sampling yielded too few detections to estimate abundance for these species, thus additional monitoring is needed to assess their breeding status in Northeast marshes. Future monitoring should also include the western shore of the Chesapeake Bay; our survey efforts were limited to the eastern shore, but marshes throughout the Bay are known to support tidal marsh birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Watts1">Watts 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2007</xref>). There are historical records of Saltmarsh &lsqb;Sharp-tailed&rsqb; Sparrows breeding along the Chesapeake Bay's western shore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Bailey1">Bailey 1913</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stewart2">Stewart and Robbins 1947</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stewart3">1958</xref>); however, more recent surveys have detected only a single individual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-OBrien1">O'Brien 1996</xref>) or nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Watts1">Watts 2004</xref>) in marshes that previously were commonly occupied. Comprehensive surveying of the western shore is needed to evaluate the present distribution and abundance of marsh birds and to identify the importance of the area's tidal marshes in a regional context. Extending tidal marsh bird surveys to encompass the remainder of eastern North America is clearly also important for global assessments of species other than the Saltmarsh Sparrow. Ongoing evaluations of current and historical priority marsh bird areas, especially in the context of priority areas for other vulnerable coastal bird species, will further help to direct the allocation of limited conservation funds, facilitate habitat management strategies and decisions, and focus future monitoring efforts on targeting information gaps.An important overall consideration for our approach is that we estimated bird abundance based on the single, broad habitat type of estuarine emergent marsh, and did not distinguish among saltmarsh vegetation zones (i.e. low marsh, high marsh, salt pannes, and terrestrial border; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Bertness1">Bertness 1999</xref>). Bird use of saltmarsh vegetation zones, and of adjacent habitats such as tidal flats and beaches, differs by species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Hanson1">Hanson and Shriver 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Nocera1">Nocera et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver4">Shriver et al. 2010</xref>), and marsh birds are typically concentrated in particular areas, leading to high spatial variation in abundance within a marsh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conway2">Conway and Droege 2006</xref>). Our population estimates reflect species abundances across all saltmarsh habitat, regardless of species dependence on particular vegetation zones. Although these design-based estimates should be robust, some are quite imprecise, particularly for species that are patchily distributed or restricted to particular zones. Geospatial data that delineate zones with a high degree of accuracy are needed to capture the heterogeneity found in salt marshes and to allow for the estimation of abundance at finer habitat scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Correll1">Correll 2015</xref>). A model-based approach that integrates geospatial habitat data and other covariates known to influence marsh bird distributions may provide more precise abundance estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Wiest1">Wiest 2015</xref>).Our survey would not have been possible without a collaborative, large-scale approach, the foundation of which was the unified sampling framework. We found many partners throughout the region interested in assisting with these surveys, given that sampling locations had been selected through a spatially balanced, hierarchical, probabilistic sampling design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2009</xref>). The marsh bird sampling framework provided the foundation for multiple state and federal agencies and nongovernmental organizations to collaborate and simultaneously address local and regional information needs. At the local scale, the sampling effort (number of points) can be intensified to make inferences at the marsh unit scale related to management actions, while providing information regarding species distribution and abundance at the regional scale. The framework affords monitoring programs the ability to coordinate at multiple scales and to be integrated into adaptive management schemes, thereby fulfilling an information need for these birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Steidl1">Steidl et al. 2013</xref>). At the regional scale, efforts are underway to use this sampling platform as the model for a marsh bird monitoring program in U.S. tidal marshes in the Gulf of Mexico (M. S. Woodrey personal communication). At the local scale, our sampling framework has been successfully integrated with the USFWS Salt Marsh Integrity Program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Neckles1">Neckles et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Neckles2">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Shriver6">Shriver et al. 2015</xref>) and will be used to assess ongoing projects designed to enhance coastal marsh resiliency following Hurricane Sandy. Implementation of this framework at coastal National Wildlife Refuges provides resource managers with reliable inferences for tidal marsh birds and can inform habitat management decisions within the context of local tidal marsh restoration projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Neckles2">Neckles et al. 2015</xref>), while maintaining the integrity of the original regional sampling design.Our results provide estimates of the distribution and abundance of tidal-marsh specialists, information that is necessary for identifying the relative importance of local habitat patches to regional populations. Our ability to identify key marshes for these species, detect changes in species distribution and abundance, relate changes to anthropogenic and climate-based impacts, and effectively respond to those changes will determine the future course of tidal marsh bird conservation. While developing our regional sampling framework, we established the Saltmarsh Habitat &amp; Avian Research Program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.tidalmarshbirds.org" xlink:type="simple">www.tidalmarshbirds.org</ext-link>), with the goal of advancing tidal marsh bird conservation. As part of this effort, we identified existing projects with historical marsh bird survey data in the Northeast and integrated a subset of the historical sites into the sampling frame. This approach provides the opportunity to estimate changes in species abundance over time and to determine the regional trajectory of marsh bird populations, as well as to examine the long-term effects of marsh degradation from human impacts on bird abundance. Additionally, historical population trend information can be compared with long-term water level observations (e.g., NOAA sea level trends) and aerial photography or remote sensing of marshes to evaluate climate change impacts, in particular sea level rise. When tidal marsh birds are surveyed at regular intervals, such monitoring can provide opportunities to assess marsh bird responses to coastal storms, including storm avoidance and marsh recolonization rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-274-Stouffer1">Stouffer et al. 2013</xref>). Long-term monitoring programs such as the USFWS Salt Marsh Integrity Program and the NPS Vital Signs Monitoring Program provide the data necessary to evaluate existing pressures and potential threats to tidal marsh bird populations. With spatially extensive, long-term data we can determine how anthropogenic and climate-related changes to marsh habitat will affect the distribution and abundance of tidal marsh bird populations and target conservation actions in areas with high bird abundance where marshes are most likely to persist.We thank state, federal, and nongovernmental biologists and their organizations for help with field logistics, support, and permission to work on the lands they manage. We also thank the numerous private landowners who granted us permission to work on their properties and supported our research. We are grateful to the 2011 and 2012 Saltmarsh Habitat &amp; Avian Research Program (SHARP) survey field crews for help with data collection, as well as the Courtney Conway lab for playback sequences, and Anthony Olsen and Mark Seamans for assistance with the sampling design and spsurvey package. Douglas Johnson, Mark Woodrey, and Jane Austin provided valuable reviews that greatly improved this manuscript, and all are warmly acknowledged. The research findings and conclusions in this article are solely those of the authors.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Financial support was provided by a Competitive State Wildlife Grant (U2-5-R-1) via Federal Aid in Sportfish and Wildlife Restoration to the States of Delaware, Maryland, Connecticut, and Maine. Additional funding was provided by Northeast Regional Conservation Needs Grant 2010-03 and National Science Foundation RAPID Grant DEB-1340008. No funders had any input into the content of the manuscript nor required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> We followed the standardized North American marsh bird monitoring protocol: Conway, C. J. (2011). Standardized North American marsh bird monitoring protocol. Waterbirds 34:319&ndash;346.<bold>Author contributions:</bold> B.J.O., C.S.E., T.P.H., and W.G.S. conceived the research idea and design, and supervised the research; W.A.W., M.D.C., B.J.O., C.S.E., T.P.H., D.R.C., and W.G.S. collected data and conducted the research; W.A.W., M.D.C., and W.G.S. developed and designed the methods; W.A.W. and W.G.S. analyzed the data; W.A.W., M.D.C., B.J.O., C.S.E., T.P.H., and W.G.S. wrote the paper and/or substantially edited the paper; and B.J.O., C.S.E., T.P.H., D.R.C., and W.G.S. contributed substantial materials, resources, and/or funding.