Opposing demographic histories reveal rapid evolution in grebes (Aves: Podicipedidae)A new look at the statistical model identificationReview of wintering by Eared Grebes in the southeastern United StatesConservation genetics of the threatened Horned Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps auritus</named-content></italic> L.) population of the Magdalen Islands, Qu&eacute;becUsing radio telemetry to describe the fall migration of Eared GrebesNesting records of the Eared Grebe in MexicoBEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling treesRelaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidenceBayesian coalescent inference of past population dynamics from molecular sequencesDiversification of Neoaves: Integration of molecular sequence data and fossilsArlequin ver. 3.0: An integrated software package for population genetics data analysisComparative ecology of Peruvian grebes: A study of the mechanisms of evolution of ecological isolationEcological character displacement and character release in grebes PodicipedidaeThree endangered South American grebes (Podiceps): Case histories and the ethics of saving species by human interventionThe decline and probable extinction of the Colombian Grebe <italic>Podiceps andinus</italic>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selectionA simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihoodDating of the human&ndash;ape splitting by a molecular clock of mitochondrial DNACharacterizing the time dependency of human mitochondrial DNA mutation rate estimatesEvidence for time dependency of molecular rate estimatesRapid band wear in Eared Grebes and other saline lake birdsThe abundance of the Eared (Black-necked) Grebe as a recent phenomenonAutumnal migration of Eared Grebes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content></italic>) through southwestern Wyoming: A key to assessing the size of the North American populationMovements of Eared Grebes indicated by banding recoveriesA technique for capturing Eared Grebes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content></italic>)Optimizing migration in a reluctant and inefficient flier: The Eared GrebeBayes FactorsComprehensive DNA barcode coverage of North American birdsA phylogeographic and population genetic analysis of a widespread, sedentary North American bird: The Hairy Woodpecker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides villosus</named-content></italic>)Fossil grebes from the Truckee Formation (Miocene) of Nevada and a new phylogenetic analysis of Podicipediformes (Aves)A survey of Paleogene birds in AsiaThe post-Pleistocene population genetic structure of a western North American passerine: The Chestnut-backed Chickadee <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Poecile rufescens</named-content></italic>DnaSP v5: A software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism dataNorth American migrants in the State of Veracruz, Mexico: A summaryPhylogenetic systematics and biogeography of hummingbirds: Bayesian and maximum likelihood analyses of partitioned data and selection of an appropriate partitioning strategyAdditions to the birds of the Republic of ColombiaPopulation genetics and evaluation of genetic evidence for subspecies in the Semipalmated Sandpiper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris pusilla</named-content></italic>)Approximate Bayesian inference with the weighted likelihood bootstrap (with discussion)A first molecular phylogenetic study of grebes (Aves: Podicipedidae)Best practices for justifying fossil calibrationsMigratory patterns and population structure among breeding and wintering Red-breasted Mergansers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mergus serrator</named-content></italic>) and Common Mergansers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. merganser</named-content></italic>)jModelTest: Phylogenetic model averagingModel selection and model averaging in phylogenetics: Advantages of Akaike Information Criterion and Bayesian approaches over Likelihood Ratio TestsGenetic signals of demographic expansion in Downy Woodpecker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides pubescens</named-content></italic>) after the last North American glacial maximumContinent-scale genetic structure in a boreal forest migrant, the Blackpoll Warbler (<italic>Setophaga striata</italic>)The role of historical and contemporary processes on phylogeographic structure and genetic diversity in the Northern Cardinal, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cardinalis cardinalis</named-content></italic>The drivers of tropical speciationPhylogeography of the White-breasted Nuthatch (<italic>Sitta carolinensis</italic>): Diversification in North American pine and oak woodlandsBayesian selection of continuous-time Markov chain evolutionary modelsStatistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphismMEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0Some probabilistic and statistical problems in the analysis of DNA sequencesA multi-locus inference of the evolutionary diversification of extant flamingos (Phoenicopteridae)High latitudes and high genetic diversity: Phylogeography of a widespread boreal bird, the Gray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>)Convergence and divergence in the evolution of aquatic birdsFire and ice: Genetic structure of the Uinta ground squirrel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spermophilus armatus</named-content></italic>) across the Yellowstone hotspotDivergent timing and patterns of species accumulation in lowland and highland Neotropical birdsIce sheets promote speciation in boreal birdsEared Grebes nesting in the Valley of MexicoTemperate origins of long-distance seasonal migration in New World songbirdsCurrent address: Centre of Evolutionary and Ecological Studies, Marine Evolution and Conservation Group, University of Groningen, Groningen, The NetherlandsGrebes (Aves: Podicipedidae) are a threatened family containing species that vary widely in demography. Podicipedidae includes several species that are either rare and confined to a single lake basin, or abundantly distributed across several continents. The most speciose genus, <italic>Podiceps</italic>, particularly the eared grebe lineage, best reflects this curious demographic pattern by representing the most abundant of extant grebes, several critically endangered species, and a recently extinct species. Here, we obtained genetic data from 3 mitochondrial markers to make phylogenetic and population genetic inferences about the eared grebe clade. Using DNA from tissue, feather, skin, and toe pads, our sampling encompassed all species and subspecies, including the extinct Colombian Grebe (<italic>Podiceps andinus</italic>) and migratory and resident populations of the North American Black-necked Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic>). Bayesian inference yielded novel insights into the dynamics of this group, particularly the recent ecological isolation and incipient speciation of the Colombian and Junin (<italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>) grebes, as determined from limited genetic divergence and rapid evolution of plumage color and bill shape (elongation, deepening of the culmen). DNA barcode and cytochrome b distances supported these inferences. Population genetic and divergence time analyses further revealed that the abundance of the North American Black-necked Grebe is likely associated with mid-Pleistocene dispersal from South America followed by late Pleistocene expansion during a time when hypersaline lake habitat accommodated large populations of staging birds. In conclusion, the demographic variation among species in the eared grebe group can be explained by recent ecological speciation of both a sympatric and an allopatric nature. Future investigation is warranted to determine whether this pattern of speciation and associated rapid phenotypic divergence can be extended to other grebe taxa.Los Podicipedidae son una familia amenazada que incluye especies que var&iacute;an enormemente en su demograf&iacute;a. Los Podicipedidae incluyen varias especies que o son raras y est&aacute;n confinadas a una &uacute;nica cuenca de un lago, o est&aacute;n distribuidas abundantemente a lo largo de varios continentes. El g&eacute;nero <italic>Podiceps,</italic> que es el que contiene m&aacute;s especies, particularmente el linaje &ldquo;con penachos&rdquo;, es el que mejor refleja este curioso patr&oacute;n demogr&aacute;fico, pues incluye las especies actuales m&aacute;s abundantes, varias especies en peligro cr&iacute;tico y las especies recientemente extintas. En este estudio, obtuvimos datos gen&eacute;ticos a partir de tres marcadores mitocondriales para hacer inferencias filogen&eacute;ticas y de gen&eacute;tica poblacional sobre los <italic>Podiceps</italic> con penachos. Usamos ADN proveniente de tejidos, plumas, piel y almohadillas de los dedos para abarcar a todas las especies y subespecies, incluyendo la especie extinta <italic>P. andinus</italic> y las poblaciones residentes y migratorias de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic>. Las inferencias bayesianas brindaron nuevas ideas sobre la din&aacute;mica de este grupo, particularmente sobre el aislamiento ecol&oacute;gico reciente y la incipiente especiaci&oacute;n de <italic>P. andinus</italic> y <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, determinada por una divergencia gen&eacute;tica limitada y la r&aacute;pida evoluci&oacute;n del color del plumaje y la forma del pico (elongaci&oacute;n y profundizaci&oacute;n del culmen). El c&oacute;digo de barras de ADN y las distancias del <italic>cytochrome b</italic> apoyan estas inferencias. La gen&eacute;tica poblacional y los an&aacute;lisis del tiempo de divergencia revelan adicionalmente que la abundancia de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic> est&aacute; probablemente asociada con una dispersi&oacute;n a mediados del Pleistoceno desde Am&eacute;rica del Sur seguida por una expansi&oacute;n a fines del Pleistoceno durante un per&iacute;odo en que el h&aacute;bitat hipersalino del lago soport&oacute; grandes poblaciones de aves. En conclusi&oacute;n, la variaci&oacute;n demogr&aacute;fica entre las especies de <italic>Podiceps</italic> con penachos puede explicarse por especiaci&oacute;n ecol&oacute;gica reciente de naturaleza tanto simp&aacute;trica como alop&aacute;trica. Es necesario realizar futuras investigaciones para determinar si este patr&oacute;n de especiaci&oacute;n y de divergencia fenot&iacute;pica r&aacute;pida asociado puede extenderse a otros taxa de los Podicipedidae.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> especies incipientes, expansi&oacute;n demogr&aacute;fica, filogenia, forma del pico, PodicipedidaeGrebes (Aves: Podicipedidae) are a small, cosmopolitan family of aquatic birds composed of a modest 22 species in 6&ndash;7 genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>). While representative grebe taxa have been included in ordinal-level molecular phylogenetic studies, population genetic investigations have been limited to relatively small populations of the Great Crested Grebe (<italic>Podiceps cristatus</italic>) in New Zealand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Robertson1">Robertson and Gemmell 2002</xref>) and the Horned Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. auritus</named-content></italic>) in eastern Canada (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Boulet1">Boulet et al. 2005</xref>). The relative lack of genetic investigation of grebes at the population level is surprising, given that grebes display extensive variation in population structure, geographic distribution, demography, and conservation status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-ODonnel1">O'Donnel and Fjelds&aring; 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>). Differences in population structure and demographic history are expected to leave distinct genetic footprints. Alongside confirmation (or rejection) of expected genetic footprints, e.g., reduced genetic diversity and gene flow in demographically declining species, population genetic studies inform the tempo of genetic divergence among and within species. This temporal information is especially useful for grebes, given the paucity of reliable fossils constraining divergence time among species, and it also allows for interpretation of the rate of bill shape evolution. Bill shape in grebes is known to correspond closely with feeding specialization, and is rapidly modulated by competitive interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa2">Fjelds&aring; 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">2004</xref>).<italic>Podiceps</italic> is the largest and most recently diverged genus within Podicipedidae and is often divided into 2 clades, the horned or crested grebe clade (3 species) and the eared grebe clade (5 species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>). Species in the horned grebe clade maintain relatively widespread, Holarctic distributions, whereas species in the eared grebe clade largely inhabit the New World and are marked by characteristic ear plumes on the sides of the head. Grebes in the eared clade represent a curious pattern of demography, being composed of either abundant, widespread species (including the most abundant of all grebe species, the Black-necked Grebe &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>&rsqb;), or of rare species with confined distributions. The latter category includes several critically endangered species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa3">Fjelds&aring; 1984</xref>), such as the Hooded Grebe (<italic>P. gallardoi</italic>) in the southern Andes that displays a bill specialized for feeding on larger invertebrates; the Junin Grebe (<italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>), which is confined to Lake Jun&iacute;n in Peru and is thought to have evolved from a population of Silvery Grebe (<italic>P. occipitalis</italic>) trapped in a late Pleistocene glacial refuge, leading to divergence in feeding specialization through character displacement in the bill (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa2">Fjelds&aring; 1983</xref>); and the recently extinct Colombian Grebe (<italic>P. andinus</italic>). <italic>P. andinus</italic> was discovered in the Bogot&aacute; and Ubat&eacute; wetlands of the Eastern Andean Cordillera of Colombia in the 1920s. In 1945, this grebe was observed year-round on Lake Tota, slightly farther north in Colombia, and by the late 1950s was classified as a new subspecies of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>. Prior to its extinction, <italic>P. andinus</italic> was classified as a full species based on differences in bill length and plumage, having chestnut coloration on its neck and ear-plumes and a grayish crown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Collar1">Collar et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa4">Fjelds&aring; 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">2004</xref>). Specialized to feed on small invertebrate prey, the rare eared grebes depend heavily on shallow lakes with very high densities of such prey, and avoid lakes with large fish populations that may control the trophic systems of wetlands. They are therefore mainly found in isolated wetlands or in regions with many ephemeral wetlands where they can move among lake basins and breed in those which are in an early successional stage. Outside the breeding season, migratory species may congregate in huge numbers in some saline lakes with extraordinary densities of brine-shrimps or brine-flies.Genetic investigation of the highly abundant North American subspecies of the Black-necked Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic>) is of special interest due to uncertainty about the extent of gene flow among populations using different migratory routes and the historical timing of population expansion. Specifically, mark&ndash;recapture studies of banded <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> have revealed 2 primary, multistaged migration pathways: (1) from breeding sites in the western Great Basin to the Salton Sea and the Gulf of California with a multimonth stopover in Mono Lake in northeastern California, and (2) from breeding sites in the eastern Great Basin to the Salton Sea and the Gulf of California with a multimonth stopover in the Great Salt Lake, Utah (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl4">Jehl and Yochem 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Boyd1">Boyd et al. 2000</xref>). Studies suggest that ~99&percnt; of all <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> inhabit these 2 staging lakes following the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl3">Jehl and Johansson 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl6">Jehl et al. 2003</xref>). A third hypothesized pathway includes direct migration to the Gulf of Mexico from breeding sites in the easternmost portion of the range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl4">Jehl and Yochem 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Banks1">Banks and Clapp 1987</xref>). Additional support for these pathways is limited due to the difficulty of capturing, banding, and resighting bands on a bird that performs nocturnal migrations and spends the majority of its time in and on the water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl4">Jehl and Yochem 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl5">1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl1">Jehl 1990</xref>). For these reasons, genetic investigation may better elucidate the extent of genetic differentiation (i.e. long-term genetic isolation) among individuals using the 3 migratory pathways. Nonmigratory, resident populations of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> have also been documented. However, little is known about these populations and distribution maps vary as to where they are located. Most support for a distinct population exists in the Valley of Mexico, where individuals have been documented in the highland lakes near Veracruz, Mexico, in breeding plumage during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Loetscher1">Loetscher 1955</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Dickerman1">Dickerman 1969</xref>). Evidence of nesting and downy young has also been recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Dickerman1">Dickerman 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 1988</xref>), but unique morphological differences are absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Dickerman1">Dickerman 1969</xref>). If this geographically isolated population has been relatively stable over time, it too, like the populations using the distinct migratory pathways, may harbor unique genetic variation detectable with molecular tools.Here, we employ molecular genetic techniques and morphometric measurements of bill dimensions to: (1) determine phylogenetic and population genetic diversity in the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>, (2) assess presence of genetic structure among different migratory and resident populations of the North American Black-necked Grebe, (3) relate diversity in bill shape to feeding specialization (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa1">Fjelds&aring; 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa2">1983</xref>), and (4) explore possible connections between genetic diversity and diversity in feeding ecology.To investigate the phylogenetic relationships and biogeographic history of eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>, we evaluated all species and subspecies in the eared grebe clade. Tissue, skin, and toe pad samples were acquired from museum collections or in the field, including samples from 15 of the 16 known specimens of <italic>P. andinus</italic> (2 of which were used by R. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-MeyerdeSchauensee1">Meyer de Schauensee &lsqb;1959&rsqb;</xref> to describe the species). <italic>Rollandia rolland</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps grisegena</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. auritus</named-content></italic> were included as outgroup taxa.To evaluate the demographic history and genetic diversity of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, we acquired skin and primary-feather samples from throughout the subspecies' range, with emphasis on the staging lakes and on acquiring adequate numbers of samples from each proposed migratory pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Primary sampling locations included Mono Lake, California, and salt retention ponds near Great Salt Lake, Utah. Skin samples were acquired from museum collections and feathers were collected by rehabilitation employees of the trona industry in Green River, Wyoming. Sequences from GenBank were included in our analysis when available (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-t01">Table 1</xref>).Distribution and sampling locations of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic> (Black-necked Grebe) and <italic>P. andinus</italic> (Colombian Grebe). <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> is distributed throughout North America, represented by 3 shaded regions showing its breeding range (yellow), wintering range (blue), and putative year-round locations (orange). Hypothesized migratory pathways are indicated by colored arrows, and sampling of representative taxa from these pathways are represented by colored, filled circles, where the smallest circle represents <italic>n</italic> &equals; 1. The open black circle represents the sampling distribution of the putative resident population in the Valley of Mexico, and the open red circle represents the sampling size and former distribution of the extinct <italic>P. andinus</italic> in South America.For phylogenetic analysis we used the full protein-coding cytochrome b (cyt b) gene (1,143 base pairs &lsqb;bp&rsqb;) and the protein-coding &ldquo;barcode&rdquo; region of the cytochrome oxidase I (COI) gene (699 bp). We used a portion (5&prime; end) of the noncoding control region (367 bp) to evaluate the historical demography and genetic diversity of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic>. Primers for cyt b and COI were designed to target small (200&ndash;250 bp) overlapping fragments (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-t02">Table 2</xref>). The control region primers were designed in 2 grebes for which whole mitochondrial genomes are published in GenBank, <italic>Tachybaptus novaehollandiae</italic> (NC&lowbar;010095) and <italic>Podiceps cristatus</italic> (NC&lowbar;008140). Primers were designed in the conserved glutamine tRNA gene (GluF) flanking the 5&prime; end of the control region, and in a conserved region of the 12S rRNA gene (12S30R) flanking the 3&prime; end of the control region. Primers amplified only 3 of 7 tested grebe species, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. auritus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. grisegena</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. major</named-content></italic>, and therefore internal primers 550R and 530F were designed based on these sequences to target shorter fragments to enhance the likelihood of amplification in the eared grebe clade. Overlapping internal primers (CR3F, CR4R, and CR5F) were designed within the GluF-550R fragment and used in this study based on an alignment of the GluF-550R fragment in <italic>P. n. nigricollis</italic> and <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>.Samples (~25 mg) were digested in 320 &mu;l lysis buffer ATL (Qiagen, Valencia, California, USA) and 80 &mu;l proteinase-K (10 mg ml<sup>&minus;1</sup>) at 56&deg;C. Following complete digestion, DNA was isolated using a standard phenol-and-chloroform&ndash;based isolation method, and DNA pellets were dissolved in an elution buffer containing Tris-EDTA. DNA isolated from the skin, feather, and toe pad samples underwent an additional purification step using the PowerClean DNA Clean-Up Kit (MoBio Laboratories, Carlsbad, California, USA).Amplification of target DNA sequences was carried out by PCR in a Peltier thermal cycler (MJ Research PTC-225; Bio-Rad, Hercules, California, USA). PCRs were completed with an initial 3 min at 95&deg;C, followed by 38 cycles of 30 s at 95&deg;C, 38 s at 50&deg;C, and 50 s at 72&deg;C, followed by 10 min at 72&deg;C and subsequently at 4&deg;C. Each 50 &mu;l reaction contained 2.5&ndash;50.0 ng of DNA, 31.0 &mu;l of dH<sub>2</sub>O, 5.0 &mu;l of 10&times; taq reaction buffer, 5.0 &mu;l of 20 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 1.0 &mu;l of 10 mM dNTP, 0.2 &mu;l of 5u &mu;l<sup>&minus;1</sup> Taq DNA polymerase (USDNA Biotech, Fort Worth, Texas, USA), and 2.6 &mu;l of both the forward and reverse primer at 5 mM. Amplification of target DNA was confirmed by gel electrophoresis in a 2&percnt; agarose A gel. Target DNA was purified for sequencing using 0.34 &mu;l exonuclease, 0.68 &mu;l shrimp alkaline phosphatase, and 0.68 &mu;l dH<sub>2</sub>O for each 10 &mu;l of PCR product, and run in a thermal cycler at 37&deg;C for 30 min, followed by 80&deg;C for 15 min and an indefinite amount of time at 4&deg;C.DNA sequencing was outsourced to Macrogen (Seoul, South Korea), and sequences were manually trimmed and cleaned, primer sequences removed, and consensus sequences aligned (and verified by eye) using Sequencher 4.8 (Gene Codes Corporation, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA) prior to analysis. Phylogenetic analysis was carried out using maximum parsimony (MP), maximum likelihood (ML), and Bayesian inference (BI) tree-building methods. MP trees for cyt b, COI, and the concatenated dataset (cyt b &plus; COI) were constructed in PAUP&ast; 4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Swofford1">Swofford 2003</xref>) using a heuristic search method and a tree-bisection-reconnection (TBR) branch-swapping algorithm with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. The control region gene tree was also constructed in PAUP&ast;; however, this tree construction was performed using the &ldquo;fast&rdquo; stepwise-addition method and no branch-swapping algorithm due to the large number of taxa (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 97). This dataset was rooted with <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> and <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> based on results (reported herein) from the cyt b and COI analyses.ML trees for cyt b, COI, and the concatenated dataset (cyt b &plus; COI) also were constructed in PAUP&ast; using a heuristic search method and a TBR branch-swapping algorithm with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. Each dataset, however, was run with different parameters based on results from jModelTest 0.1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Guindon1">Guindon and Gascuel 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Posada1">Posada 2008</xref>) evaluated with standard Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Akaike1">Akaike 1974</xref>), which penalizes for increasing the number of parameters in the model, taking into account not only goodness of fit but also the variance of the parameter estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Posada2">Posada and Buckley 2004</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-t03">Table 3</xref>).BI trees were constructed in BEAST 1.5.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Drummond1">Drummond and Rambaut 2007</xref>) and its companion programs BEAUTi 1.4.8, LogCombiner 1.4.8, and TreeAnnotator 1.5.3. Each dataset was run under different models of nucleotide substitution and site heterogeneity depending on results from jModelTest (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-t03">Table 3</xref>). In BEAST, however, there are only 2 nucleotide substitution models available, the General Time Reversible (GTR) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Tavare1">Tavar&eacute; 1986</xref>) and the Hasegawa-Kishino-Yano (HKY) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Hasegawa1">Hasegawa et al. 1985</xref>); therefore, the best model out of these 2 options was chosen. Each dataset used empirical base frequencies, a relaxed (uncorrelated lognormal) molecular clock model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Drummond2">Drummond et al. 2006</xref>) without a fixed rate of nucleotide substitution, and a Yule process speciation tree model.Bayes factor analyses were also conducted in Tracer 1.5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/" xlink:type="simple">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link>) to statistically determine whether to partition each dataset by codon position to allow for different rates of nucleotide substitution at the first, second, and third codon positions, even though Bayes factors have been criticized as favoring the most parameterized (i.e. most partitioned) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-McGuire1">McGuire et al. 2007</xref>). Bayes factor marginal likelihoods were estimated using the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Newton1">Newton and Raftery (1994)</xref> with the modification proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Suchard1">Suchard et al. (2001)</xref>. Results were analyzed using the posterior likelihood trace with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. A 2 ln Bayes factor &gt;10 was considered highly significant in this study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Kass1">Kass and Raftery 1995</xref>). Each dataset (cyt b, COI, and concatenated &lsqb;cyt b &plus; COI&rsqb;) was therefore partitioned by the 3 codon positions in these analyses (2 ln Bayes factor &equals; 295.76, 182.43, and 458.50, respectively), although partitioning did not influence topology.For the control region gene tree, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic> were analyzed with the HKY &plus; I &plus; G model, with empirical base frequencies, a relaxed (uncorrelated lognormal) molecular clock model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Drummond2">Drummond et al. 2006</xref>), and a constant size coalescent tree model. Each BI analysis for every mtDNA marker was run for an MCMC chain length of 1 &times; 10<sup>7</sup> with a 10&percnt; burn-in, logging parameters every 1 &times; 10<sup>3</sup>, and was repeated twice for a total chain length of 3 &times; 10<sup>7</sup>, to ensure that independent analyses converged on the same result. The BEAST results were analyzed in Tracer 1.5 to evaluate convergence and to ensure normal distributions of parameters and effective sample size (ESS) values &gt;200. A consensus tree was built for each dataset from the tree files of the 3 independent runs in TreeAnnotator 1.4.8, with a 10&percnt; burn-in, targeting a maximum clade credibility tree and node target heights (ages). Consensus trees for each dataset were viewed and edited in FigTree 1.2.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/" xlink:type="simple">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>).Because well-constrained fossils (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Parham1">Parham et al. 2012</xref>) are unavailable for internal calibration of the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> clade, 2 separate approaches were used to ascertain divergence times. To estimate divergence times for the entire eared grebe clade based on the protein-coding mtDNA loci, constraints were used based on node age estimates from a dataset including samples of all grebe genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ogawa1">Ogawa et al. 2008</xref>). Fossil constraints on this larger dataset included the earliest known crown (modern) grebe <italic>Thiornis sociata</italic> (8.7 myr, 65 myr; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ksepka1">Ksepka et al. 2013</xref>) and the earliest known stem flamingo <italic>Paleolodus</italic> (31 myr, 65 myr; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-vanTuinen1">van Tuinen et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ericson1">Ericson et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Torres1">Torres et al. 2014</xref>), which provided age range estimates for nodes in this study's analysis. Both of these fossil lineages correspond to recommended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Parham1">Parham et al. 2012</xref>) justifications for fossil calibration, while the slightly older Early Miocene <italic>Miobaptus</italic> and Late Oligocene grebe material from Kazakhstan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Kurochkin1">Kurochkin 1976</xref>) remains either formally undescribed or an uncertain member of crown Podicipedidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ksepka1">Ksepka et al. 2013</xref>). Priors were therefore set at 2 nodes, the root age (6.28 myr, 14.34 myr) encompassing all <italic>Podiceps</italic>&ndash;<italic>Rollandia</italic> species, and the time to the most recent common ancestor of the eared grebe clade and the <italic>Rollandia</italic> taxon set (5.82 myr, 13.42 myr).We used a different approach to approximate sublineage ages from the faster control region, to date the time of population expansion and historical gene flow events in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic>. This dataset was instead analyzed with a fixed rate of nucleotide substitution of 2.05&percnt; per million years. This rate was estimated by accounting for a faster substitution rate in the control region compared with the mutation rate for cytochrome b in BEAST (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-vanTuinen2">van Tuinen et al. 2008</xref>). Because this approach is likely more approximate, we discuss how divergence time inference is affected when accounting for different scenarios of time-dependent mutation rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ho1">Ho et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Henn1">Henn et al. 2009</xref>).Measures of molecular diversity in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> were obtained in Arlequin 3.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Excoffier1">Excoffier et al. 2005</xref>) under the Tamura and Nei model, with a gamma alpha value of 0.012 based on jModelTest results and AIC calculations. Polymorphic sites, nucleotide diversity (&pi;), and mean number of pairwise nucleotide differences were calculated in Arlequin. Haplotype diversity was calculated in DnaSP 5.10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Librado1">Librado and Rozas 2009</xref>). To analyze the geographic distribution of the genetic diversity in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, the control region gene tree was evaluated and a hierarchical analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) was performed in Arlequin. Geographic populations were defined based on hypothesized isolation and/or restricted gene flow, including the nonmigratory, resident population in the Valley of Mexico (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 5) and individuals from the eastern portion of the range representing the putative eastern migratory pathway (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 5). AMOVA calculations were conducted by computing a minimum spanning network among haplotypes under a pairwise difference model, with a gamma alpha value of 0.012 obtained from jModelTest and AIC calculations. A fifth population was defined to evaluate the level of genetic differentiation in the Colombian Grebe; the calculations were performed using the same criteria, although with a gamma alpha value of 0.023. Estimates of intraspecific and nearest neighbor distances based on cytochrome oxidase I were calculated using the K2P model (Kimura-2-parameter model in MEGA 4; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Tamura1">Tamura et al. 2007</xref>), as is standard practice in DNA barcoding (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Kerr1">Kerr et al. 2007</xref>).To evaluate the historical movements and population growth of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, a mismatch distribution and Tajima's <italic>D</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Tajima1">Tajima 1989</xref>) and Fu's <italic>F<sub>s</sub></italic> tests of selective neutrality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fu1">Fu 1997</xref>) were completed in Arlequin under default settings, with 1,000 simulations. In addition, the Bayesian skyline plot, which calculates the effective breeding population size through time, was completed in BEAST 1.5.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Drummond3">Drummond et al. 2005</xref>) and constructed in Tracer 1.5. Based on the control region phylogeny presented herein, <italic>P. andinus</italic> was included in this analysis. Control region sequence data were analyzed under a coalescent Bayesian skyline tree model and a relaxed (uncorrelated lognormal) molecular clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Drummond2">Drummond et al. 2006</xref>), with a fixed rate of 2.05&percnt; substitutions per million years. Priors on the root height, <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic> (0.48 myr, 1.74 myr), were also specified based on the estimate obtained from the control region phylogeny. The model of nucleotide substitution used for the dataset was the HKY &plus; G model in MEGA based on jModelTest results and AIC calculations. The dataset was analyzed for an MCMC chain length of 2 &times; 10<sup>7</sup> with a 10&percnt; burn-in, logging parameters every 2 &times; 10<sup>3</sup>, and was repeated for a total chain length of 4 &times; 10<sup>7</sup>.Bill measurements were obtained from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content></italic> (all subspecies), <italic>P. andinus</italic>, <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> (all subspecies), <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, and <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> by visiting collections in Europe (Amsterdam, Berlin, Copenhagen, Leiden, Paris, Vienna), North America (Chicago, Raleigh, San Francisco), and South America (Bogot&aacute;, Buenos Aires, Lima, Medell&iacute;n). Total culmen length (from the base of the mandible), width, and depth (at the base of the culmen) were measured for a total of 240 specimens archived as museum skins using 200 mm (8 inch) digital calipers with 0.01 mm accuracy (model &num;1478, General Tools, New York City, New York, USA). All measurements were taken by one person (M. van Tuinen) using a single set of calipers, with the exception of measurements from grebes from Colombia. These latter measurements (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17) were performed by P. Pulgarin using comparable digital calipers with the same accuracy, and the measurements were verified by digital re-estimation from photographs using a scale marker and the ruler tool in Photoshop 12.0 (Adobe Systems, San Jose, California, USA). Estimation error between measurers was estimated to be &lt;5&percnt; based on triplicate repeat measurements on a subset (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 50) of specimens. Quantitative analysis was performed in JMP 10.0 (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina, USA). Measurements (in mm) were first log-transformed, and ellipsoids were constructed based on 50&percnt; data point coverage. The significance of different mean values was tested using the ANOVA Tukey test.Complete DNA sequences from 2 protein-coding mitochondrial markers were obtained for representative individuals of each subspecies to reconstruct a phylogeny across the entire eared grebe clade. The gene trees of cyt b and COI were largely in agreement with one another, as reflected by increased nodal resolution in a combined partitioned analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). In both trees, <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> fell out as the earliest diverging lineage among the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>. Then, sister to <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> was the clade containing 2 sister species groupings, 1 with <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> and <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, and 1 with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic>. Divergence time estimates from this partitioned analysis suggested a likely Pliocene divergence of eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f02">Figure 2</xref>B), with splitting into the <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> &plus; <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> &plus; <italic>P. andinus</italic> clades commencing in the early Pleistocene. <italic>P. andinus</italic> formed a monophyletic group in the cyt b tree, reciprocally monophyletic to <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, but nested within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> as a whole. In the barcode tree, however, <italic>P. andinus</italic> was not monophyletic. <italic>P. occipitalis</italic>, <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> also did not form monophyletic groups in these gene trees (analyzed separately or jointly). Thus, we chose next to sample faster-evolving mitochondrial DNA sequences from a larger number of grebes. Using this extended sampling approach in the mitochondrial control region, the extinct <italic>P. andinus</italic> was placed firmly within <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, while displaying mostly unique haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f03">Figure 3</xref>).Estimates of phylogeny and divergence times in the eared grebe clade. (<bold>A</bold>) Concatenated phylogeny (cytochrome b &lsqb;cyt b&rsqb; and cytochrome oxidase I &lsqb;COI&rsqb; gene partitions) of the eared grebe clade with estimates of divergence times (time scale in millions of years, Ma), including the 95&percnt; confidence intervals estimated using program BEAST (blue node bars). (<bold>B</bold>) Summary of divergence times for the numbered nodes and node support values.Population genetic analysis of the North American Black-necked Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic>) and Colombian Grebe (<italic>P. andinus</italic>). Bayesian inference control region (367 bp) phylogeny with maximum parsimony bootstrap values, maximum likelihood bootstrap values, and Bayesian inference posterior probabilities, respectively, in brackets at nodes. Filled blue, green, and purple circles represent Black-necked Grebe individuals from the 3 migratory pathways (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f01">Figure 1</xref>), and the open black circles represent Black-necked Grebes from the putative resident population in the Valley of Mexico. Open red circles represent Colombian Grebe individuals. Also shown are clades II and I, highlighted in the 2 insets on the right, representing 2 clades that are placed directly basal to the North American Black-necked Grebe&ndash;Colombian Grebe grouping. Clade II includes representative samples from the Old World nominate subspecies <italic>P. n. nigricollis</italic> of Europe, Africa, and Asia; Clade I includes representative Junin Grebes (<italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>) and Silvery Grebes from subspecies <italic>P. occipitalis occipitalis</italic> (Argentina) and <italic>P. o. juninensis</italic> (Peru and Colombia). Control region data suggest a lack of geographic structure in the North American subspecies of the Black-necked Grebe and paraphyly of all 4 grebe species shown.The mismatch distribution of control region sequence data from <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> (including <italic>P. andinus</italic>) was unimodal, with no indication of multiple, genetically distinct populations. However, the coalescence of <italic>P. andinus</italic> haplotypes was more recent than that of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, showing a maximum separation of 2 base pairs. When analyzed separately, both mismatch distributions showed a signal of expansion but with different modes. The control region gene tree also revealed no clear genetic structure in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>. The lack of genetic structure was supported by AMOVA calculations when comparing individuals from the nonmigratory, resident population in Mexico with all other individuals (pairwise <italic>F<sub>st</sub></italic> &equals; &minus;0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.53), and when comparing individuals from the eastern portion of the subspecies range excluding (pairwise <italic>F<sub>st</sub></italic> &equals; &minus;0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.57) and including (pairwise <italic>F<sub>st</sub></italic> &equals; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.57) the resident individuals from Mexico. Despite a lack of genetic differentiation among individuals of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, genetic diversity analyses revealed high levels of haplotype and nucleotide diversity in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic> (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-t04">Table 4</xref>).Further demographic analysis of the control region sequence data supported the hypothesis that there was a population expansion in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>. The mismatch distribution revealed that the observed data closely emulated a simulated distribution of a population that had undergone expansion, with the greatest number of individuals differing by 3 mutations. With negative values, Tajima's test of selective neutrality (<italic>D</italic> &equals; &minus;1.75, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02) and Fu's test of selective neutrality (<italic>F<sub>s</sub></italic> &equals; &minus;26.37, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) also suggested a population that had undergone recent expansion. The Bayesian inference skyline plot analyses supported this interpretation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f04">Figure 4</xref>). When taking the phylogeographic, mismatch, and BI skyline information together, it can be summarized that <italic>P. andinus</italic> coalesces deeply within the history of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f04">Figure 4</xref>, arrow 2), close to the common ancestor of all extant <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> (presumably the first to colonize North America; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f04">Figure 4</xref>, arrow 1) and before the expansion of both of these grebe (sub)species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f04">Figure 4</xref>, arrows 3 and 4). This temporal pattern may reflect either that the recolonization of South America from the north that yielded <italic>P. andinus</italic> took place soon after the colonization of North America, or that the founding population size was large enough to preserve ancestral polymorphism. Both scenarios stress the evolutionary significance of historic dispersal. The differing signals of expansion in North America for <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> vs. in Colombia for <italic>P. andinus</italic> likely reflect unique in situ demographic responses. The disparity in timing between these events cannot be conclusively pinpointed due to uncertainty in mutation rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f04">Figure 4</xref>, arrows 3 and 4 vs. arrows 3' and 4'), but approximates the late Pleistocene.Bayesian inference skyline plot of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic>. Two alternative Bayesian inference skyline analyses are shown here, labeled with 4 focal demographic events for this lineage, which includes the founding of the now extinct <italic>P. andinus</italic>. Point 1 depicts the time of initial coalescence of extant <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>; Point 2 depicts the time of divergence between <italic>P. andinus</italic> and <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>; Points 3 and 4 depict the times of demographic expansion of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic>, respectively. From uncertainty in mutation rate calibration due to potential mutational time-dependency, events 3 and 4 are possibly younger (3' and 4') than the ages estimated from a strict molecular clock with a single mutation rate (3 and 4). Shown in light blue is the Holocene period from 10,000 yr ago to present. Effective population size is shown multiplied by generation time (&times; Tau).Bill measurements indicated extensive overlap among subspecies and 3 of 5 species in all 3 dimensions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f05">Figure 5</xref>; <italic>Podiceps gallardoi</italic> not shown). However, these measurements also highlighted the distinctly longer bill of <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> (the Junin Grebe), with no overlap observed between this species' measurements and those of its sympatric congener, <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> (the resident Silvery Grebe; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Secondly, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> subspecies showed increasing bill measurements, from smallest in <italic>P. n. gurneyi</italic> to intermediate in <italic>P. n. nigricollis</italic> and largest in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, with some overlap among subspecies. The measurements of <italic>P. andinus</italic> extended that trend further, showing an even longer bill, with no overlap observed with any other grebe (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) except its closest relatives in North America (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.44). Alongside a longer bill, the bill of <italic>P. andinus</italic> was significantly wider and deeper (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) than that of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>, thus signifying a unique position in 3-D space. In identical fashion, from measurements of the few available specimens (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 3), the bill of <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> was significantly deeper and wider (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) than the bills of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. occipitalis</italic>, but, unlike <italic>P. andinus</italic>, trended toward a shorter bill length.Alternative views of the 3-dimensional morphospace of bill shape in species and subspecies of the eared grebe clade. (<bold>A</bold>) 3-D view facing the length (<italic>x</italic> axis) and depth (<italic>y</italic> axis) dimensions. (<bold>B</bold>) 3-D view facing the length (<italic>x</italic> axis) and width (<italic>y</italic> axis) dimensions. Bill length, width, and depth measurements among species and subspecies in the eared grebe clade reveal significant overlap among the Black-necked Grebe (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content></italic>) and Silvery Grebe (<italic>P. occipitalis</italic>) species and subspecies. This figure also reveals clear divergence of both the Colombian Grebe (<italic>P. andinus</italic>) and the Junin Grebe (<italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>) in bill morphology in the trend toward a longer and deeper bill. This divergence suggests that there was strong selective pressure on the founding populations to fill alternative ecological niches to already resident grebe species, supporting a relatively recent speciation event relative to the other eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>.Molecular reconstruction of the relationships among eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> supports previous hypotheses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>) in suggesting <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> as the basal lineage sister to a well-supported clade encompassing <italic>P. occipitalis</italic>, <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, <italic>P. andinus</italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>. Within this clade, however, classifications are ambiguous, as species and subspecies do not show reciprocal monophyly for currently established species. On the subspecific level, this could be a result of incomplete lineage sorting due to ancestral polymorphism or limitations of the genetic markers that we chose for this analysis. Yet on the species level we would not expect to see this polyphyly except under a model of recent and rapid speciation; <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>, for example, does not form a monophyletic group in any of the trees generated in this study, despite the fact that field studies unambiguously confirm that it is specifically distinct from the sympatric <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa1">Fjelds&aring; 1981</xref>). Interestingly, however, control region sequence data do reveal with high support that the small and isolated <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> population in the Colombian Andes represents an unrecognized divergent lineage, and therefore further investigation may reveal a novel grebe taxon. Comparisons of bill shape are thus of special interest in this regard. Colombian <italic>P. o. juninensis</italic> bill dimensions do not differ significantly from those of other conspecific populations, being most similar to measurements from the population in Jun&iacute;n. Yet, estimates fall at the low end of shape variation in all 3 dimensions. More study is needed to ascertain whether a genetically isolated population indeed exists, and to what extent it differs in bill shape and plumage.In North American birds, the minimum genetic distance between 2 species at the COI barcode locus averages 4.3&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Kerr1">Kerr et al. 2007</xref>). Among eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>, the average genetic distance between <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> and <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> ranges from 0.3 to 1.1&percnt;, and between <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> from 1.3 to 2.5&percnt;. These distances support recent, rapid divergence relative to other North American birds. Previous hypotheses have proposed that <italic>P. andinus</italic> may represent a relict population of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>, suggested by its less derived and melanic plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>). Based on the recent divergence of <italic>P. andinus</italic> and its derived phylogenetic placement presented herein, the classification of <italic>P. andinus</italic> as a full species would necessitate the unsubstantiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Konter1">Konter 2012</xref>) elevation of <italic>P. n. nigricollis</italic> and <italic>P. n. gurneyi</italic> to species status, thus supporting a model of rapid evolution among the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> that is at odds with taxonomic practice. Based on the totality of the data, which shows distinctness of <italic>P. andinus</italic> in mitochondrial haplotype, bill shape, ecology, and biogeography, we therefore conclude that this taxon illustrates a case of incipient speciation in grebes, with a high degree of retained ancestral polymorphism in the mitochondrial markers.Bill length differences can evolve rapidly in grebes through competitive character displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa1">Fjelds&aring; 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa2">1983</xref>). For example, bill length in <italic>P. occipitalis</italic> is the same throughout its geographic range except at Lake Jun&iacute;n, where it shares habitat with the ecologically similar <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> and <italic>R. rolland</italic>. In this study, we revealed significant overlap in bill length, width, and depth among the subspecies of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. occipitalis</italic>; however, in <italic>P. andinus</italic> and <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> there was a trend toward a longer and deeper bill, while in <italic>P. gallardoi</italic> the trend was toward a shorter and deeper bill (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>). These differences suggest that the evolutionary pressure to exploit an ecological niche distinct from other grebes inhabiting the same wetland is driving divergence in bill morphology and feeding ecology.The dynamic and varied South American landscape lends itself to diverse evolutionary processes that promote divergence in avian taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Smith2">Smith et al. 2014</xref>). Our study reveals rapid recent divergence among the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic>, and estimates for the timing of the diversification of these species fall within the Pleistocene, supporting glacial fragmentation and land bridge formation as potential drivers of grebe dispersal and speciation. An increase in diversification rates during the last million years is hypothesized to have resulted from direct fragmentation of habitat by glaciers and altitudinal migration of vegetation from climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Weir2">Weir and Schluter 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Weir1">Weir 2006</xref>). The distribution of <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> on Lake Jun&iacute;n, a known ice-free refugium during the ice ages, lends support to the role of Pleistocene climate change in the divergence of the eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa1">Fjelds&aring; 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">2004</xref>).Recent studies on the population genetics of North American birds reveal that many taxa harbor cryptic genetic structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Spellman1">Spellman and Klicka 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Smith1">Smith et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Lait1">Lait et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ralston1">Ralston and Kirchman 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-vanEls1">van Els et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Miller1">Miller et al. 2013</xref>). Based on 2&ndash;3 hypothesized migratory pathways and evidence of nonmigratory populations, it is conceivable that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic> also harbors a cryptic population structure. Here, however, multiple lines of evidence reveal a large and wide-ranging population that underwent a rapid expansion with relatively unrestricted gene flow across its range. Other North American birds that have undergone recent population expansions include Semipalmated Sandpipers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris pusilla</named-content></italic>), Chestnut-backed Chickadees (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Poecile rufescens</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Lait1">Lait et al. 2012</xref>), Red-breasted Mergansers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mergus serrator</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Pearce1">Pearce et al. 2009</xref>), and Downy Woodpeckers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides pubescens</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Pulgarin1">Pulgarin and Burg 2012</xref>), with emphasis placed on Pleistocene climate change as the causal agent of expansion. Our timing estimate for the expansion of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> supports a Pleistocene role as well.This expansion may have been conditional on the ability of eared <italic>Podiceps</italic> to exploit the enormous uncontested food resources in hypersaline and alkaline lakes (as seen in <italic>P. gallardoi</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>, and <italic>P. occipitalis</italic>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Fjeldsa5">Fjelds&aring; 2004</xref>) outside the breeding season. Because of the late-Pleistocene emergence of these habitats in western North America, it has been hypothesized that the abundance of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> is a relatively recent occurrence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Jehl2">Jehl 2001</xref>). The Bayesian skyline plot places the time of expansion of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> at ~0.05&ndash;0.48 myr. The estimates of divergence time and effective population size are somewhat questionable due to uncertainty related to time dependency of the mutation rate in the mitochondrial control region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Ho1">Ho et al. 2007</xref>). However, the skyline plot supports a rapid increase in population size toward the present that is further supported by the mismatch distribution and the Tajima's <italic>D</italic> and Fu's <italic>F<sub>s</sub></italic> tests of selective neutrality. Confirmation is needed with nuclear markers, which are less prone to time-dependent mutation rates, to reject the hypothesis that population expansion occurred during an older emergence of suitable habitat.Given that our data suggest a panmictic population in North America, the existence of distinct migratory pathways in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic> suggests that these pathways are relatively new or that they are not strictly defined, allowing for alternative routes to suitable wintering habitat near the Gulf of Mexico. In regard to the nonmigratory population in Mexico, evidence of nesting and downy young would suggest a loss of migratory behavior, mirroring an established trend in North American migratory songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Winger1">Winger et al. 2014</xref>); however, unique genetic haplotypes were not present in the population, again suggesting either that the population is relatively new and unique mutations have yet to accumulate, or that this is another example of the flexible nature of the species and that some individuals forego migration to utilize favorable breeding habitat in Mexico.Phylogenetic and population genetic comparisons of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> (North American Black-necked Grebe) with <italic>P. andinus</italic> (Colombian Grebe) reveal that extraordinary population size in <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> is tied to Pleistocene climate change and likely to the appearance of hypersaline habitat in North America. The clustering of mtDNA haplotypes of <italic>P. andinus</italic> with this subspecies suggests that <italic>P. andinus</italic> represents a recolonization of South America from North America by an ancestral group of grebes at a time early on in the diversification of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic>. The morphological (plumage) and ecological (bill shape) distinctness of <italic>P. andinus</italic>, along with mostly unique DNA barcodes (albeit paraphyletic with regard to <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. nigricollis</named-content></italic>), was subsequently achieved. Thus, we conclude that the now extinct <italic>P. andinus</italic> represented a newly established lineage and incipient species among Podicipedidae. Furthermore, and consistent with a tendency for rapid speciation in grebes, <italic>P. andinus</italic> may represent one of several incipient species, as is indicated by DNA barcode data on <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic> (Junin Grebe; this study) and the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aechmophorus occidentalis</named-content></italic>&ndash;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. clarkii</named-content></italic> (Western Grebe&ndash;Clark's Grebe) complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Kerr1">Kerr et al. 2007</xref>). Additional multilocus sampling will be required to confirm this pattern. In summary, historic habitat change likely explains both the high present abundance of <italic>P. n. californicus</italic> and the distinctness of <italic>P. andinus</italic> and <italic>P. taczanowskii</italic>. The rapid ability of grebes to respond functionally to new habitat, due to plasticity in bill shape and flight ability, may therefore have facilitated species divergence in the Podicipedidae.We would like to thank Joseph Jehl for valuable feedback throughout the completion of this project and for establishing contact with the Wyoming trona industry, and Julie Lutz who generously provided us with feather samples. We would also like to thank Brian Arbogast, Stuart Borrett, and Steve Emslie for comments on the manuscript, and Juan Amat and the many museum collections, which included the Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University (YPM), Zoological Museum of the University of Copenhagen (ZMUC), The Burke Museum of Natural History and Culture at the University of Washington (UWBM), University of Michigan Museum of Zoology (UMMZ), Delaware Museum of Natural History (DMNH), Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science (LSU), Bell Museum of Natural History, University of Minnesota (BMNH), Texas Cooperative Wildlife Collection, Texas A&amp;M University (TCWC), North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences (NCMN), Institute of Natural Sciences at the National University of Colombia (ICN), Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (ANSP), Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago, Illinois (FMNH), and the American Museum of Natural History, New York, New York (AMNH) for access to specimens.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This research was supported by start-up funds to M.V.T. at the University of North Carolina, Wilmington. The funders did not have input into the content of the manuscript, nor require approval before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Required museum specimen holding permits were obtained for the USA by M.V.T., and for South America by J.F. and P.R.P.Specimen acquisition information of the taxa utilized in our genetic study, including museum collection, accession number, collection location, and specimen type.Primer sequences used in this study for the amplification of target genetic markers in the eared grebe clade, including the mitochondrial DNA cytochrome b and cytochrome c oxidase I gene regions, and the 369 bp (base pairs) portion of the control region.Phylogenetic tree analysis parameters of the eared grebe clade based on results from jModelTest 0.1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Guindon1">Guindon and Gascuel 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-771-Posada1">Posada 2008</xref>). Cytb &equals; the mitochondrial DNA cytochrome b; COI &equals; the protein-coding &ldquo;barcode&rdquo; region of the cytochrome oxidase I gene.Comparison of measurements of genetic diversity for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podiceps nigricollis</named-content> californicus</italic> and <italic>P. andinus</italic>.