Evolution of supraorbital ossification in CharadriiformesPhylogenetic relationships and divergence times of Charadriiformes genera: Multigene evidence for the Cretaceous origin of at least 14 clades of shorebirdsOsteologiaThe scaling of eye size with body mass in birdsThe scaling of eye size in adult birds: Relationship to brain, head and body sizesThe eBird/Clements Checklist of Birds of the World, version 6.9Canonical and principal components of shapeA revision of the Lari (Aves, Charadriiformes) from the early Miocene of Saint-G&eacute;rand-le-Puy (Allier, France)The salt gland of the Herring GullProcedures for the analysis of comparative data using phylogenetically independent contrastsFunctional ecology of saltglands in shorebirds: Flexible responses to variable environmental conditionsEye shape and activity pattern in birdsThe allometry and scaling of the size of vertebrate eyesIndices of anseriform body shape based on the relative size of major skeletal elements and their relationship to reproductive effortEvolution of bill size in relation to body size in toucans and hornbills (Aves: Piciformes and Bucerotiformes)The evolution of cerebrotypes in birdsThe global diversity of birds in space and timeShape, relative size, and size-adjustments in morphometricsThe roles of head movements in the search and capture strategy of a tern (Aves, Laridae)Higher-order phylogeny of modern birds (Theropoda, Aves: Neornithes) based on comparative anatomy: I.&mdash;Methods and charactersHigher-order phylogeny of modern birds (Theropoda, Aves: Neornithes) based on comparative anatomy. II. Analysis and discussionRemoving allometric effects of body size in morphological analysisMesquite: A Modular System for Evolutionary Analysis, version 2.75Vision and touch in relation to foraging and predator detection: Insightful contrasts between a plover and a sandpiperFlight distance and eye size in birdsSize allometry: Size and shape variables with characterizations of the lognormal and generalized gamma distributionsPhenotypic integration: Studying the ecology and evolution of complex phenotypesThe salt-secreting gland of marine birdsEndocranial anatomy of the Charadriiformes: Sensory system variation and the evolution of wing-propelled divingSystematics and evolution of the Pan-Alcidae (Aves, Charadriiformes)Anatomical and physiological adaptations of the nasal glands in Charadriiformes birdsThe phylogeny of the AlcidaeA supertree approach to shorebird phylogenyEye size, foraging methods and the timing of foraging in shorebirdsThe deep fovea, sideways vision and spiral flight paths in raptorsPhylogenetic analysis of morphological data on 92 species in the order Charadriiformes showed that increased supraorbital ossification (SO) has evolved independently at least 4 times in this clade. Principal component analysis of size-corrected skeletal measures showed that an evolutionary increase in SO was associated with a body plan in which the cranium, humerus, and sternum were relatively large. A mass-corrected measure of the axial length of the eye was positively correlated with a mass-corrected measure of cranium length, both in the raw data and in phylogenetically independent contrasts. By revealing an association between the evolution of SO and increased relative size of the eye and flight-associated skeletal elements, these results support the hypothesis that an increased reliance on visually guided foraging in flight or diving has been a major selective factor favoring the evolution of increased SO in Charadriiformes.L'analyse des donn&eacute;es morphologiques de 92 esp&egrave;ces de Charadriiformes, dans un cadre phylog&eacute;n&eacute;tique, a montr&eacute; qu'une ossification supraorbitaire (OS) accrue a &eacute;volu&eacute; ind&eacute;pendamment au moins quatre fois dans ce clade. Une analyse en composantes principales de mesures squelettiques corrig&eacute;es pour la taille a montr&eacute; qu'un accroissement &eacute;volutif de l'OS &eacute;tait associ&eacute; &agrave; un sch&eacute;ma corporel dans lequel le cr&acirc;ne, l'hum&eacute;rus et le sternum &eacute;taient relativement gros. Une mesure corrig&eacute;e pour la masse de la longueur axiale de l'&oelig;il &eacute;tait positivement corr&eacute;l&eacute;e avec une mesure corrig&eacute;e pour la masse de la longueur du cr&acirc;ne, &agrave; la fois dans les donn&eacute;es brutes et dans les contrastes phylog&eacute;n&eacute;tiquement ind&eacute;pendants. En r&eacute;v&eacute;lant une association entre l'&eacute;volution de l'OS et une augmentation de la taille relative de l'&oelig;il et des &eacute;l&eacute;ments squelettiques associ&eacute;s au vol, ces r&eacute;sultats supportent l'hypoth&egrave;se qu'une d&eacute;pendance accrue &agrave; l'&eacute;gard de la qu&ecirc;te alimentaire guid&eacute;e par la vue, en vol ou en plong&eacute;e, a &eacute;t&eacute; un important facteur s&eacute;lectif favorisant l'&eacute;volution d'une OS accrue chez les Charadriiformes.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> sch&eacute;ma corporel, reconstruction des caract&egrave;res, limicoles, ossification supraorbitaireIn a study of the visual field of 2 species in the order Charadriiformes, the Red Knot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content></italic>) and the European Golden-Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pluvialis apricaria</named-content></italic>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> associated aspects of cranial morphology with differences in feeding strategy between the 2 species. They reported a greater field of binocular vision in the Red Knot than in the European Golden-Plover, which they suggested represents an adaptation to visually guided probing with the bill in the Red Knot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma 2009</xref>). By contrast, the European Golden-Plover has relatively large eyes, supported by a bone that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> named the &ldquo;supraorbital aliform bone&rdquo; (os supraorbitale aliforme). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> suggest that the large eyes of the European Golden-Plover represent, at least in part, an adaptation to nocturnal feeding.The Charadriiformes form a large and ecologically diverse order of birds including 3 suborders (Charadrii, Lari, and Scolopaci), in which distinct lineages have adapted convergently to similar ecological niches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Colwell1">Colwell 2010</xref>). Supraorbital ossification (SO) broadly similar to that observed in the European Golden-Plover has been reported in other species in this order, particularly in suborder Lari (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Strauch1">Strauch 1985</xref>). Indeed, although the homology of such structures has not been studied, some form of SO occurs in birds belonging to a number of orders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Livezey1">Livezey and Zusi 2006</xref>). Comparative analysis thus has the potential to shed light on the evolutionary origin of SO and its role as a component of a suite of morphological and behavioral adaptations.The tremendous diversity of body plans seen in birds reflects the numerous distinct ecological niches to which birds have adapted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Feduccia1">Feduccia 1996</xref>). The relative measurements of major skeletal elements can yield simple quantitative indices of overall body plan, which can be used to test comparative hypotheses regarding ecological adaptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes1">Hughes 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes2">2014</xref>). Here, I survey the pattern of SO in 92 species in Charadriiformes, representing all 3 suborders. I then relate the patterns of SO with body plan, thereby shedding light on the ecological forces that may influence this trait.I examined skeletal specimens (from the Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois, USA, and the U.S. National Museum of Natural History, Washington, D.C.) of 92 species in Charadriiformes (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link> and Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f01">Figure 7</xref>). The cranial morphology, including SO, was examined on at least 1 adult male and 1 adult female of each species and on other individuals if available. Taxonomy and nomenclature followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Clements1">Clements et al. (2014)</xref>. Subspecies designations were used when museum specimens were identified to subspecies, and all specimens used for a given species were derived from the same subspecies. The selection of species was based on the availability of at least 1 adult male skeleton and at least 1 adult female skeleton, with the goal of sampling as much of the diversity of Charadriiformes as possible. All 3 suborders (Charadrii, Lari, and Scolopaci) were represented by multiple species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>). Phylogenetic relationships (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>) were assumed to follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Jetz1">Jetz et al. (2012)</xref>. Many, but not all, clades in this tree were supported in the phylogeny of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas1">Thomas et al. (2004)</xref>. One major exception is that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Jetz1">Jetz et al. (2012)</xref>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Baker1">Baker et al. (2007)</xref>, placed Stercorariidae as a sister group to Alcidae. On the other hand, the comprehensive morphology-based phylogeny of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Livezey2">Livezey and Zusi (2007)</xref> agreed with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas1">Thomas et al. (2004)</xref> regarding the placement of Stercorariidae. Because of this and other discrepancies, I conducted separate analyses assuming (1) the phylogeny of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref> and (2) the phylogeny of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas1">Thomas et al. (2004</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f01">Figure 7</xref>).Phylogenetic relationships of the 92 charadriiform species used in this study, based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Jetz1">Jetz et al. (2012)</xref>. Character state of supraorbital ossification is indicated as follows: open circle &equals; partial; solid circle &equals; full.The following 9 skeletal measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Baumel1">Baumel and Witmer 1993</xref>) were made by digital caliper on 1 adult male and 1 adult female of each species in the sample (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>): (1) maxilla, measured from the dorsal junction of the maxilla with the cranium to the tip of the bill (rostrum maxillare); (2) cranium, measured from the nasofrontal hinge to the posterior end (prominentia cerebellaris) of the cranium; (3) sternum length (sternum L), measured from apex carinae to margo caudalis; (4) sternum width (sternum W), measured just anterior to the base of the trabeculae laterales; (5) humerus, measured from the apex of caput humeri to the caudal edge between condylus ventralis and processus flexorius; (6) synsacrum length (synsacrum L), measured from the anterior edge of ala preacetabularis to the tip of the posterior projection of the ilium; (7) synsacrum width (synsacrum W), measured just posterior to foramen ilioischiadicum; (8) femur, measured from facies articularis antitrochanterica to sulcus intercondylaris; and (9) tibiotarsus, measured from the proximal point of facies gastrocnemialis to incisura intercondylaris. To obtain an average value for each species that incorporates at least some of the within-species variation, the male and female measurements were averaged to yield a single mean value of each measurement for the species.Mean body-mass values (g) for each species were obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Dunning1">Dunning (2008)</xref>. When mean values for males and females were given separately, the mean of those 2 means was used. For 1 species in the sample (<italic>Nycticryphes semicollaris</italic>), data were not available in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Dunning1">Dunning (2008)</xref>; for this species, I used the midpoint of the body-mass range provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-delHoyo1">del Hoyo et al. (1996)</xref>. Axial lengths (AL) of the eyes of 48 of the species in the sample were obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Howland1">Howland et al. (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Moller1">M&oslash;ller and Erritz&oslash;e (2010)</xref>.I defined SO operationally as the possession a bony ridge or ridges extending over the rear and/or top of the orbit, showing evidence of fusion to the frontal bone and having a maximum width equal to at least one-fifth the width of the skull (i.e. the distance between the outer rims of the frontal bones on either side of the skull) measured at the apex of the orbit. Species were placed into 3 categories: (1) SO was scored as absent (A) in species in which the rim of the frontal bone formed a smooth curve from processus postorbitalis to the most dorsolateral edge of os lacrimale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>A). (2) SO was scored as full (F) in species in which SO covered &gt;50&percnt; of the rim of the orbit between processus postorbitalis to the most dorsolateral edge of os lacrimale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>B&ndash;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">2</xref>D). This character is illustrated for Alcidae in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Strauch1">Strauch (1985</xref>: fig. 3B), for the European Golden-Plover in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref>, and for the Mew Gull (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus canus</named-content></italic>) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-DePietri1">De Pietri et al. (2011</xref>: fig. 3D). (3) SO was scored as partial (P) in species in which SO covered &lt;50&percnt; of the rim of the orbit, at the rear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f05">Figure 3</xref>). This character is illustrated for Alcidae in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Strauch1">Strauch (1985</xref>: fig. 3A), for the Brown Noddy (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anous stolidus</named-content></italic>) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-DePietri1">De Pietri et al. (2011</xref>: fig. 3B), and for the Arctic Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna paradisaea</named-content></italic>) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-DePietri1">De Pietri et al. (2011</xref>: fig. 3C).Crania of (<bold>A</bold>) Sanderling (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris alba</named-content></italic>), (<bold>B</bold>) Common Ringed Plover (<italic>Charadrius hiaticula</italic>), (<bold>C</bold>) Great Skua (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Stercorarius skua</named-content></italic>), and (<bold>D</bold>) Common Murre (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>). Supraorbital ossification is indicated by arrows. Scale bars are in millimeters. Photo credit: G. MayrCrania of (<bold>A</bold>) Atlantic Puffin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Fratercula arctica</named-content></italic>), (<bold>B</bold>) Sooty Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Onychoprion fuscatus</named-content></italic>), and (<bold>C</bold>) Eurasian Oystercatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Haematopus ostralegus</named-content></italic>). Supraorbital ossification is indicated by arrows. Scale bars are in millimeters. Photo credit: G. MayrMeasurements were corrected for body size in 2 ways: by Mosimann transformations and by mass-corrected measures.Size-corrected transformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Mosimann1">Mosimann 1970</xref>) were computed from the natural logarithm of the mean value (for male and female) of the 9 skeletal measurements. Where <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic> are the individual measurements, let <italic>z<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; ln&lsqb;<italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic>/<italic>G</italic>(<italic>x</italic>)&rsqb;, where <italic>G</italic>(<italic>x</italic>) is the geometric mean of the 9 measurements within each species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Mosimann1">Mosimann 1970</xref>). The resulting values (<italic>z<sub>i</sub></italic>) are referred to here as &ldquo;<italic>Z</italic>-variables.&rdquo; Principal component analysis of the <italic>Z-</italic>variables was used to provide size-independent indices of body shape for each species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Darroch1">Darroch and Mosimann 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Jungers1">Jungers et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes1">Hughes 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes2">2014</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Jungers1">Jungers et al. (1995)</xref> reviewed various size-corrected measures of body shape used in morphometrics and advocated the approach employed here.The transformation proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Lleonart1">Lleonart et al. (2000)</xref> was used to obtain measures corrected for body mass. For any measure <italic>Y</italic> having an allometric relationship with another measure <italic>X</italic>, the transformation <italic>Y<sub>i</sub></italic>&ast; &equals; <italic>Y<sub>i</sub></italic>&lsqb;<italic>X</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic>&rsqb;<italic><sup>b</sup></italic>, where <italic>X</italic><sub>0</sub> is the mean of the <italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic> values and <italic>b</italic> is the allometric exponent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Lleonart1">Lleonart et al. 2000</xref>). The latter transformation was applied both to AL and to the 9 skeletal measures. In the case of the 9 skeletal measures, the resulting transformed values were highly positively correlated with the <italic>Z</italic>-variables (not shown). Therefore, only analyses based on the <italic>Z</italic>-variables are reported here for the 9 skeletal measures. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Lleonart1">Lleonart et al.'s (2000)</xref> transformation was used for AL and was used in addition to the <italic>Z</italic>-variables for comparisons between AL and skeletal measures.Because the assumption of statistical independence made by most conventional statistical tests is not warranted in the case of data derived from phylogenetically related species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Harvey1">Harvey and Pagel 1991</xref>), statistical analyses involving the <italic>Z-</italic>variables and principal components derived from them were conducted in 2 ways, by randomization tests and by explicitly phylogenetic analyses, neither of which required the assumption of independence.Each randomization test involved creating 10,000 pseudo-datasets by sampling (with replacement) from the data. For comparison of 2 means, the absolute difference between the mean values in the observed data was compared with the distribution of absolute differences in the pseudo-datasets. For tests of correlation coefficients, the absolute value of the correlation coefficient in the observed data was compared with the distribution of the absolute values of correlation coefficients observed in the pseudo-datasets.Ancestral character reconstruction for SO was conducted by maximum parsimony in Mesquite version 2.75 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Maddison1">Maddison and Maddison 2011</xref>), assuming the phylogenetic tree of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>. For purposes of parsimony reconstruction, 2 species in the order Gruiformes, the Gray-throated Rail (<italic>Canirallus oculeus</italic>) and the Common Crane (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Grus grus</named-content></italic>), were used as an outgroup.Phylogenetically independent PDAP contrasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Garland1">Garland et al. 1992</xref>) were estimated in Mesquite, using arbitrary branch lengths. For each variable used in PDAP contrasts, the correlation between the absolute values of contrasts and their standard errors was used to test for adequacy of standardization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Garland1">Garland et al. 1992</xref>); no significant correlations were found.All reported <italic>P</italic> values are 2-tailed. Means are reported &plusmn; SE. Statistical analyses were conducted in Minitab version 15 (see Acknowledgments).Most members of the suborder Scolopaci, as well as the Cream-colored Courser (<italic>Cursorius cursor</italic>) in the suborder Lari, showed SO character state A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>). The Pectoral Sandpiper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris melanotos</named-content></italic>) provides an example of this type of cranial morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>A), very similar to that reported for the Red Knot by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> suggested an association between the lack of SO and forward-directed eyes; but the woodcocks (genus <italic>Scolopax</italic>), in spite of having eyes backward-directed rather than forward-directed, resembled most other Scolopaci in lacking SO.A cranial morphology (corresponding to the F state of SO) similar to that described for the European Golden-Plover by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref>, including an alate supraorbital bone, was seen in all species in the family Charadriidae examined here, as illustrated by the cranium of the Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>B). The F state was also seen in several lineages of suborder Lari; examples include the South Polar Skua (<italic>Stercorarius maccormicki</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>C) and the Common Murre (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f04">Figure 2</xref>D).In addition to the F character state of SO, certain members of all 3 suborders showed the P state. In puffins (genera <italic>Cerorhinca</italic> and <italic>Fratercula</italic>), the ossification took the form of an alate bone at the rear of the orbit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f05">Figure 3</xref>A). The terns (Lari: Sternidae) showed a somewhat similar postorbital ossification, although with a less sharply defined alate form (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f05">Figure 3</xref>B). In the oystercatchers (Charadrii: Haematopodidae), there was also postorbital ossification, although without any sign of an alate form (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f05">Figure 3</xref>C). A similar pattern was also seen in the Collared Pratincole (<italic>Glareola pratincola</italic>), although the one other species in the family Glareolidae included in the present dataset, the Cream-colored Courser, showed no SO.Using Gruiformes as an outgroup to determine the ancestral state of SO in Charadriiformes, A was inferred to be the ancestral state of the order (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f06">Figure 4</xref>). Although several nodes were ambiguous, there was evidence that increased SO has evolved independently in each of the 3 suborders. In Scolopaci, there has been an A&rarr;P transition in the branch leading to the most recent common ancestor (MRCA) of <italic>Numenius</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f06">Figure 4</xref>). Although the character state of the MRCA of Lari could not be determined, the results supported the hypothesis that the common ancestor of Scolopaci and Lari had character state A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f06">Figure 4</xref>); this, in turn, implied that SO evolved independently in these 2 suborders. Assuming the phylogeny of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>, there was at least 1 transition within Lari to greater SO: namely, a P&rarr;F transition in the branch leading to the MRCA of <italic>Rissa</italic>, <italic>Leucophaeus</italic>, and <italic>Larus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f06">Figure 4</xref>). Finally, because the analysis supported the hypothesis that A was the character state of the common ancestor of the 3 charadriiform suborders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f06">Figure 4</xref>), the results supported a further independent evolution of SO in Charadrii.Parsimony reconstruction of the evolution of supraorbital ossification (SO) character state (A &equals; absent, P &equals; partial, or F &equals; full) in Charadriiformes. Clades uniform with respect to SO are condensed. Plus sign on a branch indicates an increase in SO. When a node was ambiguous for 2 character states, both are shown (e.g., &ldquo;AP&rdquo;).Assuming the phylogeny of Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f01">Figure 7</xref>, independent evolution of SO in each of the 3 suborders was again supported (Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f02">Figure 8</xref>). In addition, on the basis of the latter phylogeny, 2 additional transitions to increased SO were reconstructed within Lari: (1) an A&rarr;F or P&rarr;F transition in the branch leading to the MRCA of Stercoraridae; and (2) a P&rarr;F transition in the branch leading to the MRCA of the genera <italic>Alca</italic>, <italic>Alle</italic>, <italic>Brachyramphus</italic>, <italic>Cepphus</italic>, <italic>Synthliboramphus</italic>, and <italic>Uria</italic> (Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f02">Figure 8</xref>).Together, the first 2 principal components (PC1 and PC2) extracted from the correlation matrix of the <italic>Z</italic>-variables accounted for 52.9&percnt; of the variance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t01">Table 1</xref>). PC1 contrasted the relative length of the maxilla and tibiotarsus and the relative width of the synsacrum with the other measurements. Species scoring high on PC1 were thus species with relatively long bills and legs. The species receiving the 4 highest PC1 scores were the Black-necked Stilt (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Himantopus mexicanus</named-content></italic>), the Black-winged Stilt (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. himantopus</named-content></italic>), the American Avocet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Recurvirostra americana</named-content></italic>), and the Short-billed Dowitcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Limnodromus griseus</named-content></italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>). The species receiving the 4 lowest PC1 scores were all in the Alcidae: the Ancient Murrelet (<italic>Synthliboramphus antiquus</italic>), the Crested Auklet (<italic>Aethia cristatella</italic>), the Thick-billed Murre (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria lomvia</named-content> arra</italic>), and the Razorbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Alca torda</named-content></italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>).Variable loadings on the first 2 principal components (PC1 and PC2) derived from transformed skeletal measurements of 92 species in the order Charadriiformes.PC2 primarily contrasted the relative lengths of cranium and humerus with the relative lengths of tibiotarsus, femur, and synsacrum (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t01">Table 1</xref>). Thus, species with high PC2 scores had relatively large head and humerus but relatively short legs. The 4 highest PC2 scores were found among the Sternidae: in the Black Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chlidonias niger</named-content> sumatrensis</italic>), the Common Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content> hirundo</italic>), the Black Noddy (<italic>Anous minutus melanogenys</italic>), and the Least Tern (<italic>Sternula antillarum antillarum</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>). The 4 lowest PC2 scores were found in a much more taxonomically diverse group, with representatives of all 3 charadriiform suborders: the Gray-breasted Seedsnipe (<italic>Thinocorus orbignyianus</italic>), the Crested Auklet (<italic>Aethia cristatella</italic>), the Snowy Sheathbill (<italic>Chionis albus</italic>), and the African Jacana (<italic>Actophilornis africana</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-274.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>).The 92 species were placed in 3 groups based on SO: A (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 36 species), P (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 26), and F (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 30). The mean PC1 score in the A group (1.006 &plusmn; 0.172) was significantly greater than that in the P group (&minus;0.677 &plusmn; 0.315; randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and significantly greater than that in the F group (&minus;0.620 &plusmn; 0.335; randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). On the other hand, the mean PC1 score did not differ significantly between the P group and the F group (randomization test; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). The mean PC2 score in the A group (&minus;0.431 &plusmn; 0.169) was significantly less than that in the P group (0.778 &plusmn; 0.354; randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but did not differ significantly from that in the F group (&minus;0.157 &plusmn; 0.195; randomization test) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). The mean PC2 score also differed significantly between the P group and the F group (randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.011; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). Thus, the A group was characterized by generally high PC1 scores and low PC2 scores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). The P and F groups showed similarly low PC1 scores but were distinguished by the generally high PC2 scores in the P group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>).Mean (with SE bars) of PC1 and PC2 scores in the 3 clusters of charadriiform species based on supraorbital ossification character state: absent, partial, or full.The basis for these differences among the 3 groups was further examined by comparing means of the <italic>Z</italic>-variables between groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t02">Table 2</xref>). The A group was distinguished from the P and F groups by having significantly smaller relative length of the cranium, significantly smaller relative length of the humerus, significantly smaller length of the synsacrum, and significantly greater relative length of the femur (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t02">Table 2</xref>). The A group also showed a significantly greater relative length of the tibiotarsus than the P group and a significantly greater relative length of the maxilla than the F group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t02">Table 2</xref>). The P and F groups were distinguished by relatively greater maxilla length in the former and relatively greater tibiotarsus length in the former. Thus, the A group was distinguished from the P and F groups by a relatively small cranium and humerus, whereas the P group was characterized by a relatively longer cranium and shorter legs than the A and F groups.Size-corrected measures (means &plusmn; SE) of the relative size of skeletal elements (<italic>Z</italic>-variables) in charadriiform species categorized on the basis of supraorbital ossification (A &equals; absent, P &equals; partial, and F &equals; full; NS &equals; nonsignificant).In order to examine the relationship between cranium size and eye size, I tested for correlation between the mass-corrected AL of the eye and the mass-corrected length of the cranium for 48 species for which AL data were available. There was a highly significant positive correlation between the 2 variables (randomization test, <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.666, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f08">Figure 6</xref>). Similarly, there was a highly significant positive correlation between mass-corrected AL and the <italic>Z</italic>-variable for cranium length (randomization test, <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.496, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Assuming the phylogeny of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>, there was a positive correlation between phylogenetically independent PDAP contrasts in mass-corrected AL and those in mass-corrected cranium length (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.439, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002). Likewise, there was a positive correlation between PDAP contrasts in mass-corrected AL and those in the <italic>Z</italic>-variable for cranium (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.368, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.042).Plot of the mass-corrected axial length (AL) of the eye versus the mass-corrected length of the cranium for 48 charadriiform species (randomization test, <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.666, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Alternative phylogeny of 92 species in the order Charadriiformes, based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas1">Thomas et al. (2004)</xref>.Reconstructed changes in supraorbital ossification in the order Charadriiformes, assuming the phylogeny of Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f01">Figure 7</xref>.Assuming the phylogeny of Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f01">Figure 7</xref>, there was a significant positive correlation between PDAP contrasts in mass-corrected AL and those in mass-corrected cranium length (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.425, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004). Likewise, there was a positive correlation between PDAP contrasts in mass-corrected AL and those in the <italic>Z</italic>-variable for cranium length (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.552, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Thus, the differences between the 2 phylogenies did not affect the positive relationship between AL and relative cranium size.The 48 species with AL data included 28 from the A group, 4 from the P group, and 16 from the F group. Mean mass-corrected AL was significantly greater in the F species (12.9 &plusmn; 0.4 mm) than in the A species (11.0 &plusmn; 0.2; randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Mean mass-corrected AL was likewise significantly greater in the F species than in the P species (11.0 &plusmn; 1.6 mm; randomization test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.04).A phylogenetic approach indicated that SO has evolved independently at least 4 or 5 times in the Charadriiformes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> hypothesized that SO in the European Golden-Plover is associated with large, laterally directed eyes, which in turn are associated with nocturnal foraging. The present analysis revealed an association between SO and a relatively long cranium, as well as a relatively long humerus and large sternum, as reflected in low PC1 scores (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). The association of SO with a relatively long cranium is consistent with an association between SO and the possession of large, laterally directed eyes. Moreover, the present results also showed a strong positive correlation between mass-adjusted AL of the eye and mass-adjusted cranium length, thus supporting an association between SO and relatively large eyes. A positive correlation between head size and eye size is generally observed in birds, but this correlation mainly reflects the effect of overall body size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Brooke1">Brooke et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Burton1">Burton 2008</xref>). The present finding of a positive correlation between eye AL and cranium length in Charadriiformes, even after controlling for the effect of body size, represents the first such report in any avian order. This correlation was seen in phylogenetically independent contrasts as well as in the original data, indicating that the coevolution of cranium length and eye size has been a persistent tendency throughout the evolutionary history of the order.Species lacking SO tended to have relatively long bills and legs, as indicated by high PC1 scores (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f07">Figure 5</xref>). This result is consistent with the association proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma (2009)</xref> between the absence of SO and a pattern of foraging behavior involving wading in shallow water, in which the bill is guided either tactilely or by partially forward-directed eyes. In addition, the present analyses provided evidence that charadriiform species lacking SO have relatively small eyes in relation to body size.The frequent evolution of increased SO in the order Charadriiformes implies that selection favoring this trait has acted repeatedly on diverse lineages within the order. Although nocturnal foraging may be one selective factor favoring the maintenance of relatively large eyes and, thus, of SO in certain charadriiform species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas2">Thomas et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hall1">Hall and Ross 2007</xref>), the present results argue against it as a general explanation for the evolution of SO in the order as a whole. Increased SO has evolved independently in groups not known for nocturnal foraging, including the family-level taxa Haematopodidae, Chionidae, Stercorariidae, and Laridae and the subfamily Alcinae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Thomas2">Thomas et al. 2006</xref>).Several studies have compared the relative size of the eyes or of brain regions important for vision (the optic lobes or optic tecta) across various sets of avian taxa, including some evidence regarding Charadriiformes. The factors found to be associated with relatively large visual structures appear to be related mainly to an important role of flight in foraging. Species that rely on predation guided by vision in flight have relatively large eyes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Brooke1">Brooke et al. 1999</xref>) and relatively large optic tecta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Iwaniuk1">Iwaniuk and Hurd 2005</xref>). Consistent with this finding, physiological studies support the importance of large, laterally directed eyes in the detection of movement by visually guided predators, including terns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Land1">Land 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Tucker1">Tucker 2000</xref>). Conversely, the evolution of flightlessness in the Alcidae has been associated with reduction in the relative size of the optic lobes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Smith1">Smith and Clarke 2012</xref>).The limited data available from Charadriiformes show larger relative optic tecta in 1 tern species (Sternidae) and in 2 plover species (Charadriidae) than in 2 sandpiper species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Iwaniuk1">Iwaniuk and Hurd 2005</xref>). These findings are consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Martin1">Martin and Piersma's (2009)</xref> comparison of visual fields and feeding strategies in the European Golden-Plover and the Red Knot. The present analyses revealed an association in Charadriiformes between relatively large eyes and a relatively large sternum and long humerus. In Charadiiformes, a relatively large sternum and long humerus are likely to have been associated with increased reliance on flight in foraging&mdash;and, in Alcidae, also with wing-propelled diving (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Smith2">Smith and Clarke 2014</xref>). The present results show that a relatively large cranium, relatively long humerus, and relatively large sternum are also associated with SO. This suggests, in turn, that an increased reliance on visually guided foraging in flight or diving has been a major selective factor that has favored the repeated evolution of SO in Charadriiformes.Although some degree of SO is typical of marine species in suborder Lari, the present results do not suggest a strong relationship between the presence of SO and reliance on salt secretion by the nasal glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-SchmidtNielsen1">Schmidt-Nielsen 1960</xref>). The size of the nasal gland in relation to body mass shows substantial within-species variability in Charadriiformes, depending on the salinity of the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Gutierrez1">Guti&eacute;rrez et al. 2012</xref>). Both plover species possessing SO and sandpiper species lacking SO show an essentially identical pattern of substantial increase in nasal-gland mass when foraging in marine coastal habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Gutierrez1">Guti&eacute;rrez et al. 2012</xref>). The nasal-gland mass in coastally foraging plovers and sandpipers was measured at ~0.1&percnt; of body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Gutierrez1">Guti&eacute;rrez et al. 2012</xref>), comparable to values reported for marine members of Alcidae and Laridae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Fange1">F&auml;nge et al. 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Staaland1">Staaland 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Peaker1">Peaker and Linzell 1975</xref>). Among the 21 charadriiform species whose nasal glands were examined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Staaland1">Staaland (1967)</xref>, the highest ratio of nasal gland to body mass (0.12&percnt;) was in the Red Knot, which lacks SO; this ratio is substantially higher than those reported for guillemots (genera <italic>Cepphus</italic> and <italic>Uria</italic>), the Razorbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Alca torda</named-content></italic>), and the Dovekie (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Alle alle</named-content></italic>), all marine taxa scored as having the F state of SO in the present study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>). Conversely, it is of interest that SO is only partial in some marine taxa in this order (e.g., terns and some alcids; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-f03">Figure 1</xref>), covering only the rear of the orbit and thus little of the nasal glands. Nonetheless, it remains a viable hypothesis that the size and shape of SO may reflect adaptation to use of the nasal glands in salt excretion by certain marine taxa in this order.The combined effect of multiple selective pressures acting on a suite of individual phenotypic traits can result in a coevolutionary process giving rise to a distinctive multidimensional phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Pigliucci1">Pigliucci 2003</xref>). As a consequence, the adaptive significance of any individual trait is likely to be best understood in the context of other traits with which it is associated to form such a phenotypic complex. The results of the present study illustrate the usefulness of measures of the relative size of avian skeletal elements for deriving simple indices of body plan (such as principal components) that can reduce complex, multidimensional patterns to a linear scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes1">Hughes 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-685-Hughes2">2014</xref>). Examining the associations between such indices and other morphological, physiological, ecological, and life history traits can, in turn, be used to help formulate and test hypotheses regarding the adaptive significance of complex adaptive phenotypes. Furthermore, the present study illustrates the power of a comparative approach, in contrast to studies focused on only a few species, for testing hypotheses regarding the adaptive significance of complex phenotypic patterns.I am grateful to the staffs of the Field Museum of Natural History, especially B. Marks, and the U.S. National Museum of Natural History, especially B. Schmidt, for access to specimens. I am grateful to G. Mayr for the use of his photographs and for numerous comments that improved the manuscript. Minitab software is available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.minitab.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.minitab.com</ext-link>).Measurements of skeletal specimens of 92 species in the order Charadriiformes examined for this study (from the Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois, USA, and the U.S. National Museum of Natural History, Washington, D.C.) Available at doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1642/AUK-14-274.1" xlink:type="simple">10.1642/AUK-14-274.1</ext-link>