Patterns of genetic and morphological divergence reveal a species complex in the Plain Wren (<italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>)Phylogeography and biogeography of the Lower Central American Neotropics: Diversification between two continents and between two seasOn a second collection of birds made in Chiriqu&iacute;, by W. W. Brown, JrAvifaunal interchange across the Panamanian isthmus: Insights from <italic>Campylorhynchus</italic> wrensThe role of historical and local factors in determining species composition of the highland avifauna of Costa Rica and western Panam&aacute;Comparative mtDNA phylogeography of Neotropical freshwater fishes: Testing shared history to infer the evolutionary landscape of Lower Central AmericaRapid evolution of animal mitochondrial DNAA model to explain ecological parapatryGloger's rule, feather-degrading bacteria, and color variation among Song SparrowsBird diversity and abundance on two different shade coffee plantations in GuatemalaThe behavior and natural history of <italic>Chartergellus</italic>, a little-known genus of Neotropical social wasps (Vespidae Polistinae Epiponini)The Clements Checklist of Birds of the World, version 6.6The geologic evolution of the Central American isthmusThe role of tropical dry forest as a long-term barrier to dispersal: A comparative phylogeographical analysis of dry forest tolerant and intolerant frogsThe duetting behavior of Pacific coast Plain WrensThe Great American Interchange in birds: A phylogenetic perspective with the genus <italic>Trogon</italic>Using regional comparative phylogeographic data from snake lineages to infer historical processes in Middle AmericaTaxa described by Allan R. Phillips, 1939&ndash;1994: A critical listNotes on birds of the province of Bocas del Toro, PanamaArlequin (version 3.0): An integrated software package for population genetics data analysisIsthmian&ndash;Pacific moist forestsCentral American dry forestsBiodiversity of Costa Rican salamanders: Implications of high levels of genetic differentiation and phylogeographic structure for species formationBird populations in rustic and planted shade coffee plantations of eastern Chiapas, M&eacute;xicoA review of hypotheses for the functions of avian duettingDNA barcoding will often fail to discover new animal species over broad parameter spacePanamanian dry forestsProblems with mitochondrial DNA as a marker in population, phylogeographic and phylogenetic studies: The effects of inherited symbiontsThe T&aacute;rcoles Line: Biogeographic effects of the Talamanca Range in Lower Central AmericaFamily Troglodytidae (wrens)Phylogeographic breaks in low-dispersal species: The emergence of concordance across gene treesA new species of wren (Troglodytidae: <italic>Thryophilus</italic>) from the dry Cauca River Canyon, northwestern ColombiaHistorical biogeography of the Isthmus of PanamaMitochondrial dating and mixed support for the &ldquo;2&percnt; rule&rdquo; in birdsMiddle Miocene to present plate tectonic history of the southern Central American Volcanic ArcThe complex song duet of the Plain WrenNesting and breeding behavior of the Plain Wren (<italic>Thryothorus modestus zeledoni</italic>)Duet singing and repertoire use in threat signalling of individuals and pairsHow feather colour reflects its melanin contentPhylogeography of the Rufous-tailed Hummingbird (<italic>Amazilia tzacatl</italic>)The Gray Hawk (<italic>Buteo nitidus</italic>) is two speciesA distributional survey of the birds of HondurasGeomorphic and exhumational response of the Central American Volcanic Arc to Cocos Ridge subductionAnalyzing colorsThe genetic basis of adaptive melanism in pocket miceTerrestrial ecoregions of the world: A new map of life on EarthDiagnosability versus mean differences of Sage Sparrow subspeciesGeographic variation of genetic and behavioral traits in northern and southern T&uacute;ngara frogsSpeciation in the Emerald Toucanet (<italic>Aulacorhynchus prasinus</italic>) complexPattern, process, and rigor meet classificationMrBayes 3.2: Efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model spaceKeel and tarsus length may provide a good predictor of avian body sizeThe birds of Costa Rica: Distribution and ecologyEvaluating the role of contracting and expanding rainforest in initiating cycles of speciation across the Isthmus of PanamaMany species in one: DNA barcoding overestimates the number of species when nuclear mitochondrial pseudogenes are coamplifiedA rapid bootstrap algorithm for the RAxML web serversCryptic speciation in a Holarctic passerine revealed by genetic and bioacoustic analysesPhylogeography of the pygmy rain frog (<italic>Pristimantis ridens</italic>) across the lowland wet forests of isthmian Central AmericaPhylogeography of a morphologically diverse Neotropical montane species, the Common Bush-Tanager (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chlorospingus ophthalmicus</named-content></italic>)The Great American Biotic Interchange in birdsCalibrating the avian molecular clockDevelopmental plasticity and the origin of species differencesThe Great American Biotic Interchange: Dispersals, tectonics, climate, sea level and holding pensPhylogeography of the harlequin beetle-riding pseudoscorpion and the rise of the Isthmus of PanamaCurrent address: Division of Birds, Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History, Washington, D.C., USAWe used morphometrics, plumage color, and mitochondrial DNA to reconstruct the phylogeography of the Plain Wren (<italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>), an abundant bird species of low to middle elevations throughout Central America. Sampling the full geographic range of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic>, we uncovered significant phenotypic structure in size, shape, and plumage color that mirrored deep genetic divergences in mitochondrial DNA. This structure was mostly concordant with the 3 most broadly recognized subspecies of Plain Wren (<italic>C. m. modestus</italic>, <italic>C .m. zeledoni</italic>, and <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>), but a potentially undescribed taxon exists in the highlands of Central Belize. We also found evidence of a cryptic phylogeographic break on the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica, between the southernmost populations and the widespread northern populations. This latter discovery likely represents a significant expansion of the known range of the traditionally Panamanian subspecies <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>, corresponding to a transition between major ecoregions. Topology tests suggested that northern populations of the nominate taxon likely dispersed south into Lower Central America, with subsequent isolation and diversification. We also explored the possible role of adaptation in the phenotypic divergence of the &ldquo;Canebrake Wren&rdquo; (<italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>) as a result of isolation in the more humid environments of the Caribbean Slope. Our data and analyses suggest that the Plain Wren may consist of multiple biological species that have been diverging since geophysical upheavals in the lower half of Central America approximately 2&ndash;3 mya.Empleamos la morfometr&iacute;a, el color del plumaje y el ADN mitocondrial para reconstruir la filogeograf&iacute;a de <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>, una especie de ave abundante de elevaciones bajas y medias a lo largo de Am&eacute;rica Central. Luego de muestrear el rango geogr&aacute;fico completo de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content>,</italic> descubrimos una estructura fenot&iacute;pica significativa en tama&ntilde;o, forma y color del plumaje que reflej&oacute; divergencias gen&eacute;ticas profundas en el ADN mitocondrial. Esta estructura concord&oacute; en su mayor&iacute;a con las tres subespecies m&aacute;s ampliamente reconocidas de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> (<italic>C. m. modestus</italic>, <italic>C .m. zeledoni</italic> y <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>), pero existe un tax&oacute;n que potencialmente no ha sido descripto en las tierras altas del centro de Belice. Tambi&eacute;n encontramos evidencia de una ruptura filogeogr&aacute;fica cr&iacute;ptica en la ladera Pac&iacute;fico de Costa Rica, entre las poblaciones m&aacute;s australes y las poblaciones m&aacute;s ampliamente distribuidas del norte. Este &uacute;ltimo descubrimiento probablemente representa una expansi&oacute;n significativa del rango conocido de la subespecie tradicional de Panam&aacute;, <italic>C. m. elutus,</italic> correspondiendo a una transici&oacute;n entre las principales ecorregiones. Ex&aacute;menes de topolog&iacute;a sugieren que la poblaci&oacute;n del norte del tax&oacute;n nominado probablemente se dispers&oacute; hacia el sur en la parte baja de Am&eacute;rica Central, con el subsecuente aislamiento y diversificaci&oacute;n. Tambi&eacute;n exploramos el posible rol de la adaptaci&oacute;n en la divergencia fenot&iacute;pica de <italic>C .m. zeledoni</italic> como resultado del aislamiento en los ambientes m&aacute;s h&uacute;medos de la ladera Caribe. Nuestros datos y an&aacute;lisis sugieren que <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> puede estar integrado por m&uacute;ltiples especies biol&oacute;gicas que han estado divergiendo desde los levantamientos geof&iacute;sicos en la mitad baja de Am&eacute;rica Central hace aproximadamente 2 a 3 millones de a&ntilde;os.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ADN mitocondrial, Am&eacute;rica Central, biogeograf&iacute;a hist&oacute;rica, filogeograf&iacute;a, morfometr&iacute;a, plumajeThe dynamic geophysical history of Central America has resulted in a rich biota, including many endemic taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-PueblaOlivares1">Puebla-Olivares et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Barrantes1">Barrantes 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Weir2">Weir et al. 2009</xref>). Accordingly, many previous phylogeographic studies have investigated the role of historical biogeography in shaping the terrestrial biodiversity of Central America. These studies have focused on a variety of taxa, including highland vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-GarciaParis1">Garc&iacute;a-Par&iacute;s et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Weir1">Weir et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-ChavarriaPizarro1">Chavarr&iacute;a-Pizarro and West-Eberhard 2010</xref>), lowland terrestrial invertebrates and frogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Zeh1">Zeh et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Crawford1">Crawford et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Wang1">Wang et al. 2008</xref>), snakes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Daza1">Daza et al. 2010</xref>), and freshwater fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Bermingham1">Bermingham and Martin 1998</xref>). Studies of lowland bird species have tended to focus on the isthmian region and the effect of the closure of the Isthmus of Panama as a catalyst for divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Barker1">Barker 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-DaCosta1">DaCosta and Klicka 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Miller1">Miller et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Smith1">Smith et al. 2012</xref>). Here, we explore the phylogeographic patterns of one of the most widespread bird species in Central America, the Plain Wren (<italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>).<italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> can be found in both xeric and mesic environments from sea level to 2,000 m, from extreme southern Mexico to central Panama (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Monroe1">Monroe 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Wetmore1">Wetmore et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Ridgely1">Ridgely and Gwynne 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Howell1">Howell and Webb 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Brewer1">Brewer 2001</xref>). Within this range, it thrives as a generalist insectivore in natural second-growth habitats (e.g., forest edge and canebrake) and human cultivation and disturbance habitats (e.g., gardens, coffee plantations, and roadside scrub) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Eisenmann1">Eisenmann 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Wetmore1">Wetmore et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Greenberg1">Greenberg et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Calvo1">Calvo and Blake 1998</xref>). Interestingly, at both the northern and southern ends of its range, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> is replaced by 2 ecologically similar troglodytids. To the north the Happy Wren (<italic>Pheugopedius felix</italic>) abruptly replaces <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> at the Isthmus of Tehuantepec, and in the south the congeneric Buff-breasted Wren (<italic>C. leucotis</italic>) gradually replaces it near the Isthmus of Panama. Similar ecologies, and the pattern of geographic replacement among these 3 species, suggest that interspecific competition influences the distribution of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> to some extent. Regardless, the simultaneously restricted yet expansive range of this species makes it a fitting system for investigating phylogeographic patterns in Central America.Map of Central America, showing the range of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> with traditional subspecific distributions. Dots indicate localities of specimens used in morphological analyses, and triangles indicate localities where genetic samples were also obtained. Numbered populations correspond to those in the text and are indicated with superscripts in <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>: (1) Jac&oacute;, Prov. Puntarenas; (2) San Isidro de El General (San Luis, Tres Piedras, Tinamastes); (3) Upala, Prov. Alajuela; and (4) R&iacute;o Reventaz&oacute;n, Prov. Lim&oacute;n (Huecos and Linda Vista).Geographic variation in size and plumage coloration has led to the recognition of as many as 5 subspecies within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref>): the widespread form, <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Cabanis1">Cabanis 1860</xref>) from Chiapas, Mexico, south through the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica; <italic>C. m. roberti</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Phillips1">Phillips 1986</xref>) in El Salvador; <italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Phillips1">Phillips 1986</xref>) in Honduras; <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Bangs1">Bangs 1902</xref>) in southwestern and central Panama; and <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Ridgway1">Ridgway 1878</xref>) from the Caribbean Slope of southern Nicaragua south through Costa Rica to western Panama. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Clements1">Clements et al. (2014)</xref> recognized all 5, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Dickinson1">Dickinson (2003)</xref> recognized only 4 (treating <italic>roberti</italic> as a synonym of nominate <italic>modestus</italic>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Monroe2">Monroe and Sibley (1993)</xref> recognized only 2 (treating <italic>elutus</italic> as a synonym of nominate <italic>modestus</italic>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Brewer1">Brewer (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma and Brewer (2005)</xref> recognized 2 subspecies, treating <italic>roberti</italic> and <italic>vanrossemi</italic> as synonyms of <italic>modestus</italic>, but they also treated <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> as a separate species altogether (&ldquo;Canebrake Wren&rdquo;) because of its conspicuously larger size and grayer coloration, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Ridgway2">Ridgway (1904)</xref>.Here, we use data on genetic, morphological, and plumage-color variation to investigate geographic patterns of differentiation within the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> complex and to determine whether this variation corresponds to current subspecific boundaries. We also explore how the geophysical history of Central America has played a role in shaping these patterns.In June&ndash;July 2011, we collected samples of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> from 26 localities across Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref>). All skins and tissue samples are deposited in the collections of the University of Wyoming Museum of Vertebrates and the Museo de Zoolog&iacute;a, Universidad de Costa Rica. From various natural history museums, we also acquired skins and tissue samples of individuals collected throughout the range of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Full locality information from all sampled individuals is available in <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>.For all specimens with tissue samples (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 113 individuals), we extracted genomic DNA from ~25 mg of pectoral muscle using a DNeasy extraction kit (Qiagen, Valencia, California, USA) following the manufacturer's protocols. For each individual, we amplified the second and third subunits of the mitochondrial nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide dehydrogenase (ND2 and ND3, respectively) gene using the following polymerase chain reaction (PCR) conditions in a 10-&mu;L reaction: ~20 ng template DNA (1 &mu;L of DNA extracts), 5.9 &mu;L H<sub>2</sub>0, 1 &mu;L 10X Buffer, 1.6 &mu;L MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 &mu;L each of primers (L10755 and H11151 for ND3; L5215 and H1064 for ND2), 0.2 &mu;L dNTPs, and 0.1 &mu;L <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase. The thermocycling profile was as follows: an initial 95&deg;C denaturation step for 4.5 min, followed by 35 cycles consisting of a 30-s, 95&deg;C denaturation step; a 30-s, locus-specific annealing step (54&deg;C for ND2, 48&deg;C for ND3); a 1-min, 72&deg;C extension step; and a final extension of 5 min at 72&deg;C. To check for amplification, we electrophoresed 2.5 &mu;L of each PCR product on a 1&percnt; agarose gel.Products from successful PCR amplifications were cleaned with ExoSap and cycle-sequenced in both directions in 5-&mu;L reactions using 1 &mu;L of 5X sequencing buffer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA), 0.12 &mu;L of 10 mM primer, 1 &mu;L of template, and 1 &mu;L of Big Dye Terminator Cycle-sequencing Kit version 3.1 (Applied Biosystems). We cleaned cycle-sequencing reactions using the BigDye XTerminator Purification Kit (Applied Biosystems) and electrophoresed the cleaned products on an Applied Biosystems 3130xl Genetic Analyzer. We also cycle-sequenced ND2 using internal sequencing primers (CMI-1: CCCGAAAAATCCTAGCCTT and CMI-2: GTTTTAGGGCTTTTATTGA) following the same protocol.We aligned and edited all sequences using Geneious version 5.6.4 (Geneious, Auckland, New Zealand) and concatenated the data from ND2 and ND3 into a single dataset for phylogenetic analyses. To facilitate comparisons between our Bayesian and maximum likelihood (ML) analyses, we used a GTR &plus; gamma model of sequence evolution in all phylogenetic inferences. We used both MrBayes version 3.1.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Ronquist1">Ronquist et al. 2012</xref>) and RAxML version 7.2.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stamatakis1">Stamatakis et al. 2008</xref>) to infer phylogenetic relationships. We ran the MrBayes analyses using 2 partitioning schemes. First, we partitioned the data into individual loci (ND2, ND3). Second, we partitioned the data by codon position. In each partitioning scheme, each partition had the same model of sequence evolution (GTR &plus; gamma). Using uninformative priors, we ran 5 replicate analyses, each with 2 chains, for 20 million generations. We sampled trees every 5,000 generations and excluded the first 50&percnt; of sampled trees as burn-in. We examined plots of likelihood scores during the runs to ensure that stationarity had been reached.The ML analyses were conducted using RAxML, using the GTR&plus;G model for each partition (by gene). To find the best-known likelihood tree, we performed 200 independent inferences and then assessed support for the phylogeny with the greatest likelihood using 2,500 bootstrap replicates. We also used RAxML to perform topology tests (see below). For all phylogenetic analyses, we used <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Troglodytes aedon</named-content></italic> as an outgroup (GenBank: ND2 &equals; GU816855, ND3 &equals; GU816821).We investigated patterns of within- and among-population variation, using 2 methods of defining populations. First, we adhered to taxonomic limits based on traditional subspecies descriptions (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>); then we used a revised taxonomic breakdown based on results of the phylogenetic results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f02">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">3</xref>). For both methods of population designation, we calculated measures of within- and among-population genetic diversity and structure of our ND2 dataset using ARLEQUIN version 3.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Excoffier1">Excoffier et al. 2005</xref>).Map depicting the geographic distributions of major clades of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>, based on our genetic and morphological analyses.Phylogeny of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> based on a concatenated ND2/ND3 dataset (1,316 bp) using a Bayesian analysis; the maximum-likelihood analysis produced an identical topology. Nodal support values are given (Bayesian posterior probabilities and likelihood bootstrap values, respectively) for major clades only. Traditional subspecies limits are indicated by name, whereas clade designations (referred to in the text as &ldquo;Clade 1,&rdquo; &ldquo;Clade 2,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Clade 3&rdquo;) are indicated on the far right.Digital calipers were used to measure wing chord, tail length, tarsus length, hallux length, bill length (from nares), bill depth (at nares), bill width (at nares), and bill width (at base) from 282 specimens (for details, see <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>) using established protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Baldwin1">Baldwin et al. 1931</xref>). All measurements were taken to the nearest 0.1 mm and then corrected for body size using tarsus length as a proxy for size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Senar1">Senar and Pascual 1997</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t01">Table 1</xref>).Mean (&plusmn; SD) values of unadjusted morphological and plumage color traits in subspecies of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>. Breakdown of subspecies follows taxonomic limits identified using phylogenetic analysis.We quantified plumage color using digital photography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Montgomerie1">Montgomerie 2006</xref>). Photographs were taken of the ventral and dorsal surfaces of a subset of specimens (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 87; for details, see <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>) with standardized color swatches included in each photo. Raw photos were uploaded into Adobe Photoshop version CS5, and color values were adjusted to as close to the values specified on the standardized color swatches as possible (within 10/255 RGB values). Photos were then uploaded to ImageJ version 1.46r26; feathers from the tail, back, crown, breast, and flank plumage regions were selected manually. Color values of all pixels were then averaged and converted to values of hue, saturation, and brightness (HSB) in the R statistical package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t01">Table 1</xref>). This technique is especially practical for quantifying color values in regions that possess fine-scale patterns, such as those found in the tails of these wrens, which make repeatability more difficult under other methods.Multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) was used to test for significant differences in our morphometric and plumage-color datasets, and univariate analyses (ANOVA) were used to investigate single trait divergences. Groupings in our morphometric and plumage color data were based on traditional subspecies distributions (<italic>modestus</italic>, <italic>elutus</italic>, <italic>zeledoni</italic>, <italic>roberti</italic>, and <italic>vanrossemi</italic>) along with clades identified in our phylogenetic analyses (Clades 1, 2, and 3; see below). Because of our small sample sizes for <italic>roberti</italic> and <italic>vanrossemi</italic>, we did not include those subspecies in the plumage-color MANOVA. Significance values were based on a 95&percnt; confidence interval. Shape and color differences between males and females, and between adults and juveniles, were also analyzed to test for bias; juvenile specimens were removed from further analysis. Only adult males were used in analysis of size (e.g., tarsus).Additionally, principal component analysis (PCA) was conducted separately for shape and color data, using the prcomp package in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2011</xref>) to determine the relative placement of each taxon in morphometric and plumage-color space. Shape measurements were normalized for standard deviation. Hue, saturation, and brightness were analyzed separately for each plumage region. Following PCA, eigenvalues were converted to percentage explained and were plotted accordingly.We also reevaluated subspecific limits within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic>. As of this publication, the current distributional limits and validity of subspecies are based solely on subtle plumage differences, which, to the best of our knowledge, have not been thoroughly quantified.The genetic dataset consisted of 1,316 base pairs (bp) (ND2: 935 bp; ND3: 381 bp) from the 113 individuals from which we had tissue samples. Regardless of the partitioning scheme, whether by gene or by codon position, the MrBayes analyses produced the same phylogeny. Furthermore, the Bayesian and ML phylogenetic analyses identified 3 strongly supported clades (i.e. Bayesian posterior probability &ge;0.99 and ML bootstrap &gt;70&percnt;) within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Hereafter, we refer to the 3 clades identified by the phylogenetic analyses as Clade 1, Clade 2, and Clade 3. The clades were largely concordant with the phylogeographic breakdown revealed in our morphometric results.Clade 1 included the majority of the <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">3</xref>); that is, those from southwestern Mexico in the north to the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica in the south. This clade also included individuals collected from within the distribution of <italic>roberti</italic> and <italic>vanrossemi</italic>. Clade 2 corresponded to the traditional distribution of <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> but also included individuals from the southwestern half of the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica, with the transition occurring somewhere between the populations sampled in the vicinity of Jac&oacute; and those from San Isidro de El General in the central Pacific Slope of Costa Rica. Clade 3 included individuals collected from throughout the distribution of <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> (i.e. the Caribbean Slope of Costa Rica and Bocas del Toro, Panama; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">3</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>).Our analyses also identified potential, but limited, gene flow between <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>. In Costa Rican populations, all individuals fell into their expected categories, with the exception of UWYMV 2730 from Upala (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>), which had a mitochondrial haplotype belonging to Clade 1 despite sharing phenotypic similarities with other individuals from Upala that were part of Clade 3. A pair from another site (UWYMV 2738, 2739), along the canyon of the R&iacute;o Reventaz&oacute;n (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>), was shown to be a mixed pair according to our mitochondrial haplotype data (Clades 1 and 3, respectively).Although the relationships among individuals within these 3 clades were not always strongly supported, both the monophyly of the 3 clades and the relationship among them were (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">Figure 3</xref>). To explore the relationship among the 3 clades in greater detail, we used RAxML to test for differences among the 3 possible rooted trees (inferred tree: &lsqb;Clade 1, (Clade 2, Clade 3)&rsqb;; alternate topology 1: &lsqb;(Clade 1, Clade 3), Clade 2&rsqb;; alternate topology 2: &lsqb;(Clade 1, Clade 2), Clade 3&rsqb;). The inferred tree was a significantly better explanation of the data than either of the 2 alternative topologies (LnL scores: inferred tree, &minus;3,948.82; alternate topology 1, &minus;3,980.32; alternative topology 2, &minus;3,981.92; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). For the topology tests, we did not constrain the relationships among individuals within the 3 primary clades, but only the relationships among the 3 primary clades.Our analyses of within- and among-population genetic variation mirrored the results from the phylogenetic analyses. Regardless of whether we classified individuals as <italic>C. m. modestus</italic>, <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>, or <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> on the basis of traditional subspecies criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Dickinson1">Dickinson 2003</xref>) or as Clade 1, Clade 2, and Clade 3 on the basis of the clades that we identified, the vast majority of the genetic variation present in the ND2 data is found among populations (92&percnt;), and very little is found within populations (8&percnt;) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t02">Table 2</xref>). Exact tests of population differentiation among the 3 groups were all significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 in all cases), and among-population <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values were high (&gt;0.6 in all cases) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t03">Table 3</xref>). Within each group, genetic variation was highest in Clade 1 and lowest in Clade 3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t03">Table 3</xref>).Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) among groups of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>.Within-taxon nucleotide diversity, within- and between-taxa mean pairwise differences, and between-taxa <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values for subspecies of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>, calculated from the ND2 dataset. For the mean pairwise differences, the values on the diagonal represent within-taxon results and the values below the diagonal represent between-taxa results.Although our morphometric analyses revealed substantial variation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t01">Table 1</xref>), most of the variation is driven by significant variation in body size (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Table 4</xref>, &ldquo;tarsus length&rdquo;). Once trait measurements were adjusted for body size, morphological differentiation in shape was tested among populations throughout the range of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic>, using both MANOVA and pairwise ANOVA. Significant differences in shape and size variation did not strictly conform to the subspecies. Rather, phylogeographic breaks in phenotypic characters were found (1) between populations of northwestern and southwestern Costa Rica at the confluence of Clades 1 and 2, (2) between a population in central Belize and the surrounding <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> populations in Guatemala, and (3) between populations of Clade 3 and all other <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">5</xref>). The phenotypic distinctiveness of populations belonging to the subspecies <italic>C. m. roberti</italic> and <italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic> was not supported by our data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">5</xref>).Pairwise significance values determined using a one-way ANOVA of morphological measurements. <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> populations are grouped according to all historically recognized subspecies (columns 4 and 5) and by the newly determined taxon limits between <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> (columns 1&ndash;3). El Salvadoran (<italic>C. m. roberti</italic>) and Honduran (<italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic>) populations were tested against surrounding populations of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic>. In the far right column, we treated one unnamed group separately, a seemingly isolated population in central Belize that differs in bill size from other populations. Significant values are in bold.Pairwise significance values determined using a MANOVA of morphological measurements. <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> populations are grouped according to all historically recognized subspecies (rows 1&ndash;5) and by clades identified in our phylogenetic analyses (rows 6&ndash;9). El Salvadoran (<italic>C. m. roberti</italic>, &ldquo;rob&rdquo;), Honduran (<italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic>, &ldquo;van&rdquo;), and Belizean populations were tested against surrounding populations of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> (&ldquo;mod&rdquo;) (&ldquo;elu&rdquo; &equals; <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>; &ldquo;zel&rdquo; &equals; <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>). Significant values are in bold.The greatest degree of variation in shape existed between Clade 1 and the 2 southernmost clades (Clade 2 and Clade 3; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">Table 5</xref>). The break in variation is especially evident in tail length, with a significance level exceeding all other pairings in our morphological dataset (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Table 4</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Figure S1</ext-link>).Plumage coloration suggested a pattern slightly different from that uncovered by morphometrics. Although our analyses of individuals from Clades 1 and 2 indicate significant differences in plumage color (despite being virtually inseparable in the field), the majority of the variation is between these 2 clades and the distinctly darker Clade 3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">5</xref>).This modest discrepancy in pattern between shape and color is also evident in our PCA. Morphometric variation was shown to be greatest within Clade 1, as well as between Clade 1 and other <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f04">Figure 4</xref>A). Tail length and bill depth represented the largest sources of variation in PC 1 and 2 based on shape. By contrast, PCA based on colorimetric data indicates that Clade 3 is distinct from Clades 1 and 2, with saturation of breast and hue of tail, back, and flank being the primary contributors to the first 2 principal components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f04">Figure 4</xref>B).Plot of principal component scores showing the arrangement of subspecies of <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> in morphometric space (left) and colorimetric space (right). Gray triangles &equals; Clade 1, black boxes &equals; Clade 2, and black circles &equals; Clade 3.We present the first rigorous characterization of geographic variation in <italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic>, using genetic, morphological, and plumage color data from a thorough sampling of available specimens. Despite being cryptically colored, mitochondrial genetic divergence between subspecies of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> was revealed to be extensive (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t03">Table 3</xref>). Most (92&percnt;) of the variation in our mitochondrial DNA dataset was explained by variation among taxonomic groups; the rest was found within the groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t02">Table 2</xref>). The mean pairwise divergence between Clade 1 and Clade 3 was 6.7&percnt;, whereas estimates between Clades 2 and 3 and the widespread Clade 1 were greater, and roughly equivalent, at ~7.6&percnt; for our ND2 dataset (935 bp). Individuals sorted strongly into monophyletic groups reflecting traditional 3-way taxonomic divisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Dickinson1">Dickinson 2003</xref>), with the exception of populations from the southern Pacific Slope of Costa Rica. Individuals from this area grouped with the clade primarily associated with <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> (Clade 2), despite being found in areas previously considered to be within the distribution of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>).Our topology tests suggest that populations in Lower Central America (Clade 2 and Clade 3) were most likely derived from the widespread northern populations (Clade 1; see below). We submit that ancestral populations invaded from north to south, where they were subsequently isolated. An event separating <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> into northwestern and southeastern populations (Clade 1 / Clade 2 &plus; Clade 3) would likely have preceded a separate event that stimulated divergence between the southeastern populations (Clade 2/Clade 3). A molecular clock of 2&percnt; divergence Ma<sup>&minus;1</sup> for protein-coding mitochondrial data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Brown1">Brown et al. 1979</xref>) is often used in phylogeographic studies. Applying a more recent adjustment by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Weir3">Weir and Schluter (2008)</xref> of 2.1 &plusmn; 0.1&percnt; Ma<sup>&minus;1</sup> sets the initial divergence event between 3.45 and 3.80 mya, and the second event at 3.05&ndash;3.35 mya. However, previous calibrations for such rates of molecular evolution have shown a tendency to overestimate time since divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Lovette1">Lovette 2004</xref>). Taken at face value, these divergence estimates coincide roughly with a period of biogeographic upheaval that culminated in the closure of the Isthmus of Panama (ca. 3&ndash;4 mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Weir2">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Woodburne1">Woodburne 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Leigh1">Leigh et al. 2014</xref>) and the final uplift of the Cordillera de Talamanca (ca. 2&ndash;3 mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-MacMillan1">MacMillan et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Barrantes1">Barrantes 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Morell1">Morell et al. 2012</xref>).Multivariate analyses revealed significant levels of phenotypic divergences among populations of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic>, roughly corresponding to the traditional taxonomic distributions of subspecies <italic>modestus</italic>, <italic>elutus</italic>, and <italic>zeledoni</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">Table 5</xref>). Nevertheless, the pattern was even more discernible among the 3 primary clades (Clades 1, 2, and 3) identified in our phylogenetic analyses. For example, Clade 1 and Clade 2 are more different from each other in morphology than are the traditional subspecies <italic>modestus</italic> and <italic>elutus</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">Table 5</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Figure S1</ext-link>).Highlighting significant single-trait polymorphisms in shape, such as bill depth and tail length, may lead to insights into how phenotypic divergences between these taxa may be shaped by adaptation. For instance, the patterns observed in plumage color and size for Clade 3 may indicate local adaptation by <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> to a more humid and less variable environment within its limited Caribbean Slope range. From comparisons of the HSB values of plumage coloration, we detected a shift in the ratio of pheomelanin to eumelanin pigment types in <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2005</xref>). This is consistent with Gloger's rule and with patterns in other bird systems in which eumelanins seem to confer a selective advantage to populations occupying more humid climates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Nachman1">Nachman et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 2004</xref>).By contrast, the 2 parapatric clades on the Pacific Slope (Clades 1 and 2) are remarkably similar in plumage despite significant morphometric differences and deep genetic divergences across a sharp phylogeographic break. This similarity of plumage coloration may be explained by the reorganized expression of preexisting traits, or by conservation of traits via different developmental pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-WestEberhard1">West-Eberhard 2005</xref>).Although the rise of the Cordillera de Talamanca may explain the temporal and geophysical isolation of <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> on the Caribbean Slope, it cannot easily explain the deep and unexpected divergences observed between <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> populations on the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica, for which no contemporary barriers to dispersal seem to exist. The presence of this deep genetic break in the absence of contemporary barriers suggests a historical barrier that no longer exists. One potential cause of this vicariance was the Nicaraguan Depression and consequent seaway. Pliocene sediments of a marine origin suggest the presence of a Pacific&ndash;Caribbean seaway in this lowland corridor near the present-day border of Nicaragua and Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Coates1">Coates and Obando 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Daza1">Daza et al. 2010</xref>). This seaway could have served as an effective barrier to dispersal for low-vagility bird species at a time roughly concordant with the estimated genetic divergence between these 2 clades.Nevertheless, the location of the break in the central Pacific of Costa Rica does coincide with the presence of an ecotone between 2 major ecoregions in Lower Central America: the Central American Dry Forests (CADF) of northwestern Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Fund2">Fund and Hogan 2013</xref>) and the Isthmian&ndash;Pacific Moist Forest (IPMF) of southwestern Costa Rica and Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Olson1">Olson et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Fund1">Fund and Hogan 2012</xref>). In fact, the distribution of Clade 2 populations reflects a closely tied but not exclusive relationship to the IPMF ecoregion. This phylogeographic break is shared with at least 2 other animal taxa in central Pacific Costa Rica: a lowland frog, <italic>Physalemus pustulosus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Prohl1">Pr&ouml;hl et al. 2006</xref>), and the Gray Hawk/Gray-lined Hawk (<italic>Buteo plagiatus</italic>/<italic>B. nitidus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Millsap1">Millsap et al. 2011</xref>). Overall, 27 bird species have their northernmost distribution at, or around, this area (C. Sanchez personal communication).The CADF/IPMF ecotone is the most likely and convenient place for the genetic transition between these 2 clades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Crawford1">Crawford 2007</xref>). However, results from our mitochondrial data suggest that the actual transition between Clade 1 and Clade 2 is abrupt and does not perfectly reflect the transition zone of these 2 ecoregions, which is located around the R&iacute;o Grande de T&aacute;rcoles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Kohlmann1">Kohlmann and Wilkinson 2007</xref>). The fact that other Clade 2 populations occupy habitats with equivalent or greater aridity in Panama (e.g., the eastern Azuero Peninsula; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Hogan1">Hogan 2013</xref>) suggests that distributions in this taxon are not strictly tied to the IPMF ecoregion. The precipitous juxtaposition of these clades may be better explained by negative interactions consistent with competitive exclusion between ecologically similar species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Bull1">Bull and Possingham 1995</xref>).Given the arrangement and degree of the phylogeographic breaks between the populations and subspecies of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic>, we suggest a reassessment of taxonomic limits. Pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values between the 3 most widely accepted of these taxa (Clades 1, 2, and 3) are similar to those of other troglodytid complexes that have recently been described and split at the species level (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Toews1">Toews and Irwin 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Lara1">Lara et al. 2012</xref>).The geographic distribution of Clade 3 is congruent with that of <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> and can be confidently equated with this taxon. However, our genetic analyses uncovered a mismatched haplotype (UWYMV 2730, Upala, Costa Rica) and a hybrid pair (R&iacute;o Reventaz&oacute;n, Costa Rica) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figure 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-15-8.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>), as well as a pair of <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> (UWYMV 2733, 2734) from the R&iacute;o Reventaz&oacute;n at 200 m higher than the typical elevational limits of this taxon. These specimens suggest that gene flow between <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> exists, although it appears to be greatly constrained geographically and may be a recent phenomenon due to the recent westward expansion of <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> in recent decades following the clearing of former forest habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>). Duetting characteristics in these 2 taxa have been shown to be similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Slud1">Slud 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Cuthbert1">Cuthbert and Mennill 2007</xref>), but differences in vocal quality have been noted and are detectable in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma and Brewer 2005</xref>). Differences in timing and manner of breeding between <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-MarshallBall1">Marshall-Ball and Slater 2003</xref>) may further constrain interbreeding and enhance assortative mating. Morphometric and colorimetric differences also seem to be highly conserved outside of these narrow contact zones. The taxonomic status of the &ldquo;Canebrake Wren,&rdquo; <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>, has long been debated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Stiles1">Stiles and Skutch 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma and Brewer 2005</xref>). Now, enough evidence has accrued for the &ldquo;Canebrake Wren&rdquo; to be recognized as a distinct species.The geographic distributions of Clades 1 and 2 were largely congruent with those of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>, respectively, with the exception of populations found in the southern half of the Pacific Slope of Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f03">3</xref>). We suggest redrawing the range of <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> to include these populations at least as far north as the vicinity of San Isidro de El General, San Jose, Costa Rica. Contact with the widespread taxon (Clade 1, <italic>C. m. modestus</italic>) is likely due to contiguous habitat transition and lack of any meaningful vicariant barriers between these and confirmed Clade 1 populations. Nevertheless, our genetic data provided no evidence of gene flow through shared haplotypes near the zone of contact, as would be expected in a system of interbreeding taxa. Despite the phenotypic resemblance of these taxa caused by very similar coloration, the same break was also apparent in our morphological dataset, where we uncovered significant differences in shape, size, and subtleties of plumage color (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t05">5</xref>). This abrupt transition recalls other parapatric systems where competitive exclusion maintains a sharp zone of contact between 2 ecologically similar species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Bull1">Bull and Possingham 1995</xref>). Moreover, in studying duetting vocalizations in this species, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Mann1">Mann et al. (2003)</xref> noted that substantial differences in duetting pattern existed between those previously described for <italic>C. m. elutus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Farabaugh1">Farabaugh 1983</xref>) and those of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> and <italic>C. m. zeledoni</italic>. More specifically, the structure of the <italic>elutus</italic> song differs primarily in the crucial introductory phrases, which prompt female participation in the duet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Mann1">Mann et al. 2003</xref>). Substantial differences in song have been shown to be a good predictor of taxonomic status under the framework of the biological species concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Remsen1">Remsen 2005</xref>). The complex nature of these duetting songs may accelerate reproductive isolation by amplifying male&ndash;female incompatibilities, because of the need for precise coordination in synchronization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Hall1">Hall 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-MarshallBall2">Marshall-Ball and Slater 2004</xref>). In light of these differences, along with our new evidence of a sharp phylogeographic break in genotype and phenotype, we propose the elevation of the traditionally Panamanian subspecies of Plain Wren, <italic>C. m. elutus</italic>, to full species status.In our phylogenetic analysis, birds from El Salvador (<italic>C. m. roberti</italic>) and Honduras (<italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic>) did not form clades, either separately or together (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-f02">Figure 2</xref>). In fact, they were embedded within populations of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic>. Neither did our analyses support the claims that were the basis of Phillips's original morphology-based reasoning for their classification as separate taxonomic units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Phillips1">Phillips 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Dickerman1">Dickerman and Parkes 1997</xref>). Phenotypically, we found birds from El Salvador and Honduras to be undiagnosable between each other and surrounding Plain Wren populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Patten1">Patten and Unitt 2002</xref>). For these reasons, we recommend that <italic>C. m. roberti</italic> and <italic>C. m. vanrossemi</italic> be subsumed into the taxon that surrounds them on all sides, <italic>C. m. modestus</italic>.Lastly, we want to acknowledge an interesting population in the Cayo District of Central Belize. Although no known modern tissues of this population currently exist in natural history collections, we were able to obtain phenotypic measurements from a group of adult specimens from the Cayo District (LSUMNS). We found significant differences in bill size (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t04">Table 4</xref>) and plumage color (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-t06">Table 6</xref>) between these birds and populations of <italic>C. m. modestus</italic> in surrounding Guatemala. Specimens and available occurrence data hint that this population is isolated and restricted to the areas in and around the Mountain Pine Ridge Forest Reserve and San Ignacio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Edwards1">Edwards 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Jones1">Jones 2003</xref>). Although more individuals may be needed for measurement, we deem it likely that this population represents a distinct, nonclinal taxonomic unit within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. modestus</named-content></italic> that has yet to be described.Pairwise significance values determined using a one-way ANOVA for plumage color measurements. Comparisons were made between the 3 major subspecies according to the newly determined taxon limits, and measurements for each plumage region are given separately as Hue, Saturation (Sat.), and Brightness (Bri.). Significant values are in bold.Of course, suggested changes in taxonomy based on genetic data from a single locus should be considered in light of problems associated with this approach (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Hurst1">Hurst and Jiggins 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Kuo1">Kuo and Avise 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Hickerson1">Hickerson et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Song1">Song et al. 2008</xref>). Nevertheless, given the significant differences across all analyzed datasets, we are confident that our single-locus genetic dataset does not substantially misinform our suggested taxonomic revisions.<italic>Cantorchilus modestus</italic> provides a striking example of how cryptic breaks can go undetected, even in a relatively well-studied avifauna such as that of Costa Rica. It also demonstrates the importance of phylogeographic studies in determining the true diversity occurring in the lowlands across Costa Rica and western Panama, where phylogeographic analyses were previously lacking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-795-Bagley1">Bagley and Johnson 2014</xref>). The Plain Wren species complex is also a prime candidate for future studies investigating the interplay between neutral divergence and adaptation in driving reproductive isolation. Moreover, investigations into the roles of behavior and song in reproductive isolation in this species could lend insight into how phenotypic factors can be catalysts of speciation.We thank the following institutions for generous access to their natural history collections: Academy of Natural Sciences (Philadelphia); Field Museum of Natural History (Chicago); University of Kansas Natural History Museum (Lawrence); Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science (Baton Rouge); Marjorie Barrick Museum (Las Vegas); Museo de Zoologia, Universidad de Costa Rica (San Jos&eacute;); and National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution (Washington, D.C.). Permission to undertake research in Costa Rica was granted by Sistema Nacional de Areas de Conservaci&oacute;n (SINAC) and by Comisi&oacute;n para la Gesti&oacute;n Ambiental (CONAGEBio). G. Barrantes at Museo de Zoolog&iacute;a, Universidad de Costa Rica, granted us access to facilities. We also thank D. Ocampo and E. Carman for assistance in carrying out fieldwork, and E. Berlin for lending us access to his home and private property. Methodology for color analysis was designed on the basis of insights from D. Thomas. Valuable suggestions and critiques on the manuscript were provided by C. Benkman, D. McDonald, M. Murphy, and C. Dove.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Our work was funded by the University of Wyoming.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Research was conducted in compliance with University of Wyoming IACUC protocol 20140314MC00080-03.