Association between nest defense and egg rejection behavior of Brown-breasted Bulbuls (<italic>Pycnonotus xanthorrhous</italic>)Cuckoo adaptations: Trickery and tuningAn experimental study of co-evolution between the cuckoo, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cuculus canorus</named-content></italic>, and its hosts. II. Host egg markings, chick discrimination and general discussionThe frontline of avian brood parasite&ndash;host coevolutionAdvances in the study of coevolution between avian brood parasites and their hostsCuckoos versus hosts in insects and birds: Adaptations, counter-adaptations and outcomesForeign egg retention by avian hosts in repeated brood parasitism: Why do rejecters accept?Aggression to dummy cuckoos by potential European cuckoo hostsAntagonistic antiparasite defenses: Nest defense and egg rejection in the magpie host of the Great Spotted CuckooLong-term coevolution between avian brood parasites and their hostsCuckoos combat socially transmitted defenses of reed warbler hosts with a plumage polymorphismDiversity of parasitic cuckoos and their hosts in ChinaCoevolution in action: Disruptive selection on egg colour in an avian brood parasite and its hostReject the odd egg: Egg recognition mechanisms in parrotbillsNest defenses and egg recognition of Yellow-bellied Prinia against cuckoo parasitismDifferent lines of host defense against parasites may be antagonistic or have additive benefits. For example, nest defense and egg rejection behaviors are important adaptations against brood parasitism in hosts that have been subject to much attention and numerous studies. However, the relationship between these 2 defensive behaviors within a single host population has hardly been elucidated. We investigated the correlation between nest defense and egg recognition behavior in Brown-breasted Bulbuls (<italic>Pycnonotus xanthorrhous</italic>) by conducting dummy and artificial-parasitism experiments. Our results illustrate that in Brown-breasted Bulbuls, rejecters of parasite eggs were more aggressive toward a cuckoo dummy than acceptors, which was opposite to the results of a previous study. We discuss the possible explanations for consistent and antagonistic defenses at the individual level of hosts and suggest that accumulated experience, sufficient to recognize harmful objects, may account for our results in Brown-breasted Bulbuls.Los diferentes tipos de defensa de los hospederos frente a par&aacute;sitos pueden ser antagonistas entre s&iacute; o tener beneficios aditivos. Por ejemplo, los comportamientos de defensa de los nidos y de rechazo de los huevos son adaptaciones importantes contra el parasitismo de cr&iacute;a en hospederos, que han recibido mucha atenci&oacute;n y han sido ampliamente estudiados. Sin embargo, la relaci&oacute;n entre estos dos comportamientos defensivos en una sola poblaci&oacute;n rara vez ha sido esclarecida. Investigamos la correlaci&oacute;n entre la defensa de los nidos y el comportamiento de reconocimiento de los huevos en <italic>Pycnonotus xanthorrhou</italic> conduciendo experimentos de parasitismo artificial usando modelos. Nuestro estudio ilustr&oacute; que los individuos de la especie <italic>P. xanthorrhou</italic> que rechazan huevos eran m&aacute;s agresivos contra los modelos de cucos par&aacute;sitos que los individuos que los aceptan, contrario a lo encontrado en un estudio previo. Discutimos las posibles explicaciones de las defensas consistentes y antag&oacute;nicas al nivel del hospedero, y sugerimos que suficiente experiencia acumulada para reconocer objetos peligrosos podr&iacute;a explicar los resultados en <italic>P. xanthorrhou</italic>.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> acumulaci&oacute;n de experiencia, <italic>Cuculus saturatus</italic>, nivel individualSelection pressure as a response to brood parasites may alter animal phenotype and behavior. In the coevolutionary interaction between obligate brood parasites and their hosts, the parasites exert strong selection pressure that provokes the hosts to evolve defensive strategies, among which nest defense and egg rejection are the most general and important adaptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies2">Davies 2011</xref>). Nest defense is regarded as a frontline defense, in which hosts recognize and attack adult parasites to prevent them from approaching their nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Feeney1">Feeney et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Feeney2">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang4">Yang et al. 2014b</xref>). Egg rejection is a subsequent defensive stage, with the host recognizing and rejecting parasite eggs from their nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies3">Davies and Brooke 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang3">Yang et al. 2014a</xref>). Although both these stages of defense have received much attention, the relationship between them has rarely been tested. For example, many host species are intermediate rejecters of nonmimetic eggs, in which both rejecters and acceptors of parasite eggs coexist within a single population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler2">Soler 2014</xref>). Generally, moreover, not all the host individuals within a population exhibit attacking behavior toward parasitic cuckoos that approach their nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Roskaft1">R&oslash;skaft et al. 2002</xref>). In other words, different host individuals generally do not show identical responses to the same object. Nevertheless, such variation in host behaviors is regarded as a reasonable and comprehensible phenomenon that can be explained by the personality of different individuals and by moderate selection pressure from brood parasitism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Rothstein1">Rothstein and Robinson 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>). However, the relationship between egg rejecters&ndash;acceptors and attacking&ndash;nonattacking individuals has received little attention from researchers. Understanding such a relationship within a population is important for advancing our knowledge about cuckoo&ndash;host coevolution, because host individuals that possess effective defenses against cuckoo parasitism are the component of a population that actually exerts selection pressure on parasitic cuckoos and promotes the latter's evolution of counteradaptations. We performed cuckoo dummy and artificial-parasitism experiments to investigate the association of nest defense with egg recognition in Brown-breasted Bulbul (<italic>Pycnonotus xanthorrhous</italic>), a potential host of Himalayan Cuckoo (<italic>Cuculus saturatus</italic>) in China.The study was conducted in Kuankuoshui National Nature Reserve (hereafter &ldquo;KKS&rdquo;; 28&deg;10&prime;N, 107&deg;10&prime;E) and the Baihuahu area (hereafter &ldquo;BBH&rdquo;; 26&deg;40&prime;N, 106&deg;31&prime;E) of Guizhou Province in Southwest China, during April&ndash;August, 2013&ndash;2014. The KKS study area is situated in a subtropical moist broadleaf mixed forest, interspersed with abandoned tea plantations, shrubby areas, and open fields used as cattle pasture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang2">Yang et al. 2010</xref>). The BBH study area is an island park in the suburban area of Guiyang, the capital city of Guizhou Province. Brown-breasted Bulbuls build nests on shrubs and lay eggs with dense violet-colored markings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Several cuckoo species breed sympatrically in both study areas, including Large Hawk-Cuckoo (<italic>Hierococcyx sparverioides</italic>), Common Cuckoo (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. canorus</named-content></italic>), Himalayan Cuckoo, and Lesser Cuckoo (<italic>C. poliocephalus</italic>). No parasitism has been detected in Brown-breasted Bulbuls in either area, but we have found that the Brown-breasted Bulbul can recognize nonmimetic foreign eggs (T. Su et al. personal observation). It may be a host of Himalayan Cuckoo, given that another species in the family Pycnonotidae that breeds in a sympatric area was found to be parasitized by Himalayan Cuckoo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang1">Yang et al. 2012</xref>).Example of an experimentally parasitized Brown-breasted Bulbul nest.The experimental process was designed following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref>. A white model egg, made with polymer clays to mimic the egg phenotype of Himalayan Cuckoo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang1">Yang et al. 2012</xref>), was introduced into each Brown-breasted Bulbul nest on the day after its clutch was completed. The experimentally parasitized nests were monitored for 3 days to record the responses of hosts, which were classified as &ldquo;rejection&rdquo; if model eggs were ejected, pecked with traces, buried, or deserted (left cold in the nest); and as &ldquo;acceptance&rdquo; if model eggs were incubated or kept warm in the nest. Generally, a duration of 6 days is used for parasitism experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>), but we used a duration of 3 days for responses because a previous study (C. Yang et al. personal observation) had shown that the rejection events in these 2 Brown-breasted Bulbul populations all occurred within 3 days. Furthermore, this allowed us to conduct the subsequent dummy experiment in the early incubation period of the host nests; this timing was necessary because a previous study had shown that the rejection behavior of hosts can change after the early incubation period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Moskat1">Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2014</xref>). Therefore, Brown-breasted Bulbuls were classified as rejecters or acceptors after the parasitism experiment and subsequently received the cuckoo dummy experiment on the third day after the parasitism experiment. For this experiment, a dummy Himalayan Cuckoo (2 dummies were used) was mounted near each nest at a distance of 0.5 m and pointed toward it. An observation session of 15 min was conducted when the host parents appeared within 5 min after the dummy was mounted. The responses toward the dummy were classified as (1) attack, (2) mobbing, (3) alarm, or (4) no aggression.We used Fisher's exact test to compare responses to model eggs or the dummy between populations and between rejecters and acceptors. We also used logistic regression to investigate the relation between acceptor&ndash;rejecter responses and the 2 dummies, location (KKS or BBH), egg laying date, and clutch size. We used IBM SPSS 20.0 (IBM, Armonk, New York, USA) for statistical analysis, and SigmaPlot 12.0 (Systat Software, San Jose, California, USA) to make figures. Significance level was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and all statistics are 2-tailed.Experimental parasitism was performed in 39 nests in KKS and 27 nests in BHH. The rejection rates of model eggs were 64.1&percnt; and 48.1&percnt; in KKS and BHH, respectively. Responses to both the model eggs and the cuckoo dummy were consistent between the KKS and BBH populations (model eggs: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 1.66, df &equals; 1, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.217; cuckoo dummy: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.60, df &equals; 2, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.168). Therefore, we combined the responses to the cuckoo dummy in rejecters and acceptors between KKS and BBH. We found that 34.2&percnt; of rejecters attacked the cuckoo dummy, compared with 10.7&percnt; of acceptors. Mobbing behavior accounts for 21.1&percnt; and 7.14&percnt; of responses in rejecters and acceptors, respectively. The most frequent response in acceptors was producing alarm (82.1&percnt;), which was almost twice as frequent as in the rejecters (44.7&percnt;). Rejecters were found to be more aggressive than acceptors toward the cuckoo dummy (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 9.23, df &equals; 2, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.011; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Logistic regression also indicated that only the responses to model eggs (acceptor&ndash;rejecter) predicted the responses to the cuckoo dummy (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,64</sub> &equals; 9.27, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003).Comparison of responses to a cuckoo dummy by rejecter (black bars) and acceptor (gray bars) Brown-breasted Bulbuls in Kuankuoshui National Nature Reserve (KKS) and the Baihuahu area (BHH).Our results show that the rejection and attacking behaviors of Brown-breasted Bulbuls were positively correlated, and that rejecters were much more aggressive toward the cuckoo dummy than acceptors. This result differs from that of a previous study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref>, which suggested that selection pressure on the former stage of defense may block the defense in the latter stage (i.e. that there is a negative correlation between rejection and attacking behaviors). By contrast, some studies have predicted an opposite adaptation between different stages of defense: that one line of defense may facilitate the evolution of another stage of defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Kilner1">Kilner and Langmore 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Feeney1">Feeney et al. 2012</xref>). To date, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al.'s (1999)</xref> study is the only study similar to ours that has tested the relationship between nest defense and egg rejection behaviors at the individual level in brood parasite&ndash;host systems.Although the present study is similar in experimental procedure to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al.'s (1999)</xref> study, the results are opposite. We suggest 2 possible explanations for this difference in results. First, we used cuckoo dummies, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref> tested the nest defense of hosts by setting up real cuckoos near host nests. The advantage of using real cuckoos in a nest defense experiment is obvious. However, the behavior of live birds is uncontrollable in empirical experiments, though <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref> emphasized that they had trained the birds to keep quiet. For example, it is impossible to keep live birds immobile; the cuckoos could turn their heads to adjust their sight at any time and would behave differently according to different responses from different hosts and to differences in the surroundings (e.g., different hosts have different nest locations). In other words, the disadvantage of using live cuckoos is the high risk of unrepeatability of the experiment. By contrast, the posture and behavior of dummies are controllable and researchers can place them in an identical manner toward host nests. In fact, cuckoo dummies are the most general method for testing host nest defenses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies2">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Roskaft1">R&oslash;skaft et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Yang4">Yang et al. 2014b</xref>). One recent study even used balsa wood models of cuckoo morphs to obtain a novel conclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Thorogood1">Thorogood and Davies 2012</xref>). Therefore, our use of dummies rather than real birds may help explain why our results differed from those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref>.A second possible explanation arises from the use of different cuckoo&ndash;host systems in the 2 studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref> used Eurasian Magpie (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pica pica</named-content></italic>) and Great Spotted Cuckoo (<italic>Clamator glandarius</italic>). Most Great Spotted Cuckoos use the aggressive nest-defense behavior of Eurasian Magpies to their own advantage: While the adult magpies are pursuing the male cuckoos to drive them from their territory, the female cuckoos lay their eggs in the unguarded nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>). Such parasitic behavior in Great Spotted Cuckoos is considerably different from that of <italic>Cuculus</italic> species, which generally approach host nests secretly to avoid detection. In this situation, nest defense would be more adaptive for Eurasian Magpie hosts that lack another line of defense (i.e. egg recognition); but for Eurasian Magpies able to recognize parasitic eggs, staying in the nest and not behaving aggressively against cuckoos might be a better option. Furthermore, nestling Great Spotted Cuckoos are not ejectors, whereas nestling Common Cuckoos are (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Davies1">Davies 2000</xref>). Therefore, the selection pressure and the manner of selection may not be identical between the Eurasian Magpie&ndash;Great Spotted Cuckoo and Brown-breasted Bulbul&ndash;Himalayan Cuckoo systems, which may have given rise to the difference between our results and those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Soler1">Soler et al. (1999)</xref>. Moreover, Eurasian Magpies are corvids with higher sociality than Brown-breasted Bulbuls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-delHoyo1">del Hoyo et al. 2015</xref>). A previous study found that nest defense behavior in hosts can be transmitted by social learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-231-Thorogood1">Thorogood and Davies 2012</xref>). Therefore, different host species may respond differently to the same study procedure because of different phylogenies. Our two suggested explanations for the contrasting results are not mutually exclusive, and one or both of them may be useful in interpreting this discrepancy, but the exact cause is unclear.Our results indicate that in Brown-breasted Bulbuls, rejecters of parasite eggs may be experienced and older individuals that have accumulated sufficient experience to recognize harmful objects such as foreign eggs and cuckoos. Correspondingly, some host individuals express antagonistic defenses because most brood-parasite individuals may be able to overcome the first line of nest defense and thus a second, more efficient, line of defense has evolved in some individual hosts. Because of the associated costs, the ancestral defense may be lost in individual hosts that have the second line of defense, but retained in individuals that lack the second defense. In summary, our results illustrate a positive correlation between different stages of defense in Brown-breasted Bulbuls&mdash;which, we suggest, is explained by the accumulation of experience at the individual level of the host.We thank J. Huo and N. Niu for their assistance with fieldwork.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (no. 31260514 to C.Y.; nos. 31272328 and 31472013 to W.L.) and by the Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University (NCET-13-0761 to C.Y.). None of the funders had any influence on the content of the submitted manuscript, and none of the funders require approval of the final manuscript to be published.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> The experiments comply with the current laws of China, where they were performed. Fieldwork was carried out under permission from Kuankuoshui National Nature Reserve, Guizhou, China. The authors declare that we have no conflict of interest.<bold>Author contributions:</bold> W.L. and C.D. conceived the idea, design, and experiments. T.S. and G.L. performed the experiments. C.Y. and T.S. analyzed the data. C.Y. and W.L. wrote the manuscript, and all authors approved the submission.