From critically endangered to least concern?&mdash;A revised population trend for the Kittlitz's Murrelet in Glacier Bay, AlaskaStatus and distribution of the Kittlitz's Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>) in Kenai Fjords, AlaskaStatus of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in RussiaA poster child for global warmingEvaluating population trends of Kittlitz's Murrelet in AlaskaThe status and distribution of Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in northern AlaskaUsing geographic information systems to compare non-uniform marine bird surveys: Detecting the decline of Kittlitz's Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>) in Glacier Bay, AlaskaOceanography of Glacier Bay, Alaska: Implications for biological patterns in a glacial fjord estuaryThe status, distribution, and ecology of inshore-feeding alcids (<italic>Cepphus</italic> guillemots and <italic>Brachyramphus</italic> murrelets) in the North Pacific&ldquo;Anchoring&rdquo; and research priorities: Factors that depress bird population estimates?Seeing past the red: Flawed IUCN global listing for sea turtlesChanges of glaciers in Glacier Bay, Alaska, using ground and satellite measurementsEstimation of freshwater runoff into Glacier Bay, Alaska and incorporation into a tidal circulation modelKittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> population trend in Prince William Sound, Alaska: Implications of species misidentificationMonitoring Kittlitz's Murrelets in Glacier Bay National Park: 2010 annual report. Natural Resource Technical Report NPS/SEAN/NRTR&mdash;2011/441Line transect surveys for murrelets: Accounting for incomplete detection and identificationRiverine organic matter and nutrients in southeast Alaska affected by glacial coverageGlaciers as a source of ancient and labile organic matter to the marine environmentBreeding ecology of Kittlitz's Murrelets at Agattu Island, Aleutian Islands, AlaskaA review of selected surveys of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in Alaska: Lessons learnedDistribution and abundance of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in selected areas of southeastern AlaskaUnderstanding abundance patterns of a declining seabird: Implications for monitoringDistribution, abundance, and population trends of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in Prince William Sound, AlaskaChanges in distribution and abundance of Kittlitz's Murrelets <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> relative to glacial recession in Prince William Sound, AlaskaDistribution, population status and trends of Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in Lower Cook Inlet and Kachemak Bay, AlaskaStatus and distribution of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> along the Alaska Peninsula and Kodiak and Aleutian islands, AlaskaThe path from grey literature to red lists<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>&mdash;Kittlitz's Murrelet. Version 7.1Engineering Statistics HandbookFarewell to the Glacier Murrelet?Status and trend of the Kittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in Glacier Bay, AlaskaTemporal and spatial variability in the distribution of Kittlitz's Murrelt in Glacier BayEstimating seabird densities from vessel transects: Distance sampling and implications for strip transectsEstimating density from surveys employing unequal-area belt transectsKittlitz's Murrelet <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> in the Kodiak Archipelago, AlaskaJudgment under uncertainty: Heuristics and biasesThreatened and endangered species&mdash;Short-tailed Albatross (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria albatrus</named-content></italic>)The dilemma of accuracy in IUCN red list categories as exemplified by hawksbill turtles (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Eretmochelys imbricata</named-content></italic>)Foraging distances of radio-marked Marbled Murrelets from inland areas in southeast AlaskaCurrent address: Anchorage, Alaska, USAThe Kittlitz's Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>) has been proposed for listing under the U.S. Endangered Species Act, and is classified as critically endangered by the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN). A significant portion of the global population occurs in Glacier Bay, Alaska, where steep population declines have been previously reported. To further examine Kittlitz's Murrelet population trends we replicated a 1993 survey in 2009 and 2010 using the same lead observer, the same transect lines, and similar methods. We found the number of Kittlitz's Murrelets unchanged since 1993. Other seabird surveys were conducted in Glacier Bay between 1991 and 2008 by federal agencies, using a variety of sampling designs. We added our surveys to previously published surveys, correcting for percentage of murrelets identified to species to enable comparison. When all surveys were analyzed collectively, the Kittlitz's Murrelet population showed no significant trend between 1991 and 2010 (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.51). A power analysis showed high power (&gt;0.99) to detect a decline had the population truly been declining at a rate of &minus;11&percnt; per year, allowing us to reject the prior published conclusion of decline rates of &minus;10.7&percnt; to &minus;14.4&percnt; per year in Glacier Bay. The prior result of murrelet population decline was driven by a high population estimate from an isolated, nonstandard survey in 1991. Our three surveys in 1993, 2009, and 2010 provide a direct long-term comparison of standardized surveys, and show a more comprehensive picture of the Kittlitz's Murrelet population trend in Glacier Bay. We suggest the previous conclusion of a declining trend was influenced by anchoring bias, which attached undue certainty to the initial observation. The revised population trend in Glacier Bay indicates Kittlitz's Murrelets are not at imminent risk of extinction.Se ha propuesto poner a <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> en la lista de especies en peligro de extincci&oacute;n bajo la Ley de Especies en Peligro de Extinci&oacute;n de los Estados Unidos, y est&aacute; clasificada como &ldquo;en peligro cr&iacute;tico&rdquo; por la Uni&oacute;n Internacional para la Conservaci&oacute;n de la Naturaleza (UICN). Una parte importante de la poblaci&oacute;n global se encuentra en la Bah&iacute;a Glacier, Alaska, donde se han reportado marcadas disminuciones poblacionales. Para investigar m&aacute;s a fondo estas tendencias poblacionales, replicamos en el 2009 y 2010 un muestreo originalmente realizado en 1993, utilizando el mismo observador principal, las mismas l&iacute;neas de transecto, y m&eacute;todos similares. Encontramos que el n&uacute;mero de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> no ha cambiado desde 1993. Otros muestreos de aves marinas se realizaron en la Bah&iacute;a Glacier entre 1991 y 2008 por agencias federales, utilizando una variedad de dise&ntilde;os de muestreo. Sumamos nuestro muestreo a los muestreos previamente publicados, corrigiendo por el porcentaje de <italic>Brachyramphus</italic> identificados a especie para hacer que los conteos fueran comparables. Analizados colectivamente, la poblaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> no muestra tendencia poblacional alguna a lo largo del per&iacute;odo entre 1991 y 2010 (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.51). Un c&aacute;lculo de poder mostr&oacute; un poder alto, &gt;0.99, para detectar un declive si la poblaci&oacute;n realmente estaba disminuyendo con una tasa de &minus;11&percnt; por a&ntilde;o, permiti&eacute;ndonos rechazar conclusiones previamente publicadas indicando tasas de disminuci&oacute;n de &minus;10.7 a &minus;14.4&percnt; por a&ntilde;o en la Bah&iacute;a Glacier. Las conclusiones previas fueron influ&iacute;das por un estimado alto que result&oacute; de un muestreo aislado y no est&aacute;ndar realizado en 1991. La incorporaci&oacute;n de nuestros tres muestreos proporciona una comparaci&oacute;n directa a largo plazo de muestreos estandarizados, y una tendencia m&aacute;s completa para <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic> en la Bah&iacute;a Glacier. Sugerimos que la previa conclusi&oacute;n de tendencia poblacional fue influ&iacute;da por un sesgo de ancla, el cual asigna certeza excesiva a la observaci&oacute;n inicial. La tendencia poblacional actualizada en la Bah&iacute;a Glacier indica que esta especie no est&aacute; en peligro inminente de extinci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> Alaska, anclado, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>, Bah&iacute;a Glacier, tendencia poblacionalThe Kittlitz's Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus brevirostris</named-content></italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f01">Figure 1</xref>) is a small alcid that is widely but patchily distributed from the northern Gulf of Alaska to the Arctic Ocean, and occurs on both the Russian and Alaskan shores of the Bering Sea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Surveys for Kittlitz's Murrelets are necessarily conducted at sea, because the species nests solitarily, often many kilometers inland and above the tree line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day3">Day et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kaler1">Kaler et al. 2009</xref>). In 2004, the species became a candidate for listing under the Endangered Species Act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS2">USFWS 2010</xref>) following reports of steep population declines in several core areas of its range, including Glacier Bay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Robards1">Robards et al. 2003</xref>), Prince William Sound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz2">Kuletz et al. 2003</xref>), and Kenai Fjords (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt 2003</xref>). These declines led the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) to elevate the status of the Kittlitz's Murrelet to critically endangered, a designation connoting extremely high risk of extinction in the wild (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-IUCN1">IUCN 2012</xref>). The critically endangered classification applies to species with very small populations (e.g., &lt;250 individuals), very small range size (e.g., &lt;100 km<sup>2</sup>), or rapidly declining populations (e.g., &gt;80&percnt; decline in the last 10 years or 3 generations; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-IUCN1">IUCN 2012</xref>). The trigger in the case of Kittlitz's Murrelets was a perceived range-wide population decline exceeding the 80&percnt; threshold. The reported declines have been speculatively linked to receding glaciers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz2">Kuletz et al. 2003</xref>), leading some researchers to predict that the Kittlitz's Murrelet may be the first avian species to succumb to the effects of rising global temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt1">Piatt and Kuletz 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Cubie1">Cubie 2008</xref>). The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) predicted that the Kittlitz's Murrelet could disappear in Prince William Sound by &sim;2010 and in Glacier Bay by &sim;2045, given the estimated steep rates of decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Denlinger1">Denlinger 2006</xref>).Since the initial reports were written, questions have been raised about the quality of early surveys and their suitability as baselines for trend analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day1">Day 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hoekman1">Hoekman et al. 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff 2012</xref>). In most areas, recent surveys and new trend analyses have reversed or lessened the previous concerns about steep population declines in Kittlitz's Murrelets. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Arimitsu1">Arimitsu et al. (2011</xref>) concluded that population declines originally reported for the Kenai Fjords region (&minus;83&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt 2003</xref>) could not be verified due to methodological differences among early surveys. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff (2012</xref>) suggested the &minus;13&percnt; per year decline reported in Prince William Sound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz1">Kuletz et al. 2011a</xref>) was likely to have been confounded by misidentified birds, and their reanalysis found no statistically significant decline. An initial indication of a 90&percnt; population decline in the Malaspina Forelands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kissling1">Kissling et al. 2007a</xref>) was later revised to uncertain status due to insufficient surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kissling2">Kissling et al. 2011</xref>). In northern Alaska, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day2">Day et al. (2011</xref>) found no evidence of population change between historic (1970&ndash;1999) and recent (2000&ndash;2009) surveys, and limited data from the western Aleutian Islands hints at population stability over recent decades, with no evidence of the steep population declines that have been reported elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Madison1">Madison et al. 2011</xref>). In 2010, the USFWS reported statistically significant declines in Kachemak Bay of &minus;20&percnt; (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01) in the inner bay and &minus;43&percnt; (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01) in the entire bay, and considered these &ldquo;among the most robust trend estimates available&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS2">USFWS 2010</xref>:12). However, this conclusion was later changed to: &ldquo;densities of Kittlitz's Murrelets in late-summer surveys tended downward but statistically were stable&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz3">Kuletz et al. 2011b</xref>:93). In a review of all Alaska surveys, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day1">Day (2011</xref>) concluded that the older data being used for baseline population estimates suffered severe methodological, sampling, and other problems, and were not adequate for concluding the species had undergone catastrophic declines across large parts of its range.Glacier Bay in Alaska supports the largest monitored population of Kittlitz's Murrelets. Recent line transect surveys conducted over 91&percnt; of the bay's waters by the National Park Service estimated the number of Kittlitz's Murrelets on the water at 7,477 &plusmn; 1,119 SE in July of 2011, and 16,469 &plusmn; 2,581 SE in July of 2012 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hoekman3">Hoekman et al. 2013</xref>). When expanded to all bay waters, the extrapolated estimated population in 2012 exceeded 18,000 individuals, not including birds in flight or on nests. In comparison, the size of the global population is poorly known. The species ranges over a large area and, where it has been surveyed, not all birds are available to count (on the water) or are detected by observers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hoekman2">Hoekman et al. 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS4">USFWS 2011b</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Ewins1">Ewins et al. (1993</xref>) estimated that there were 25,000 to 100,000 Kittlitz's Murrelets worldwide, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-NatureServe1">NatureServe (2013</xref>) estimates that there are 10,000 to 100,000 birds worldwide. Summing survey results leads to an estimated total of 30,000 to 57,000 birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS3">USFWS 2011a</xref>). Other reports and websites cite earlier USFWS estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Denlinger1">Denlinger 2006</xref>), which range from 9,000 to 25,000 birds. Assuming that the true worldwide population lies somewhere between 50,000 and 100,000 birds, Glacier Bay's 18,000 birds represent a significant portion (18&percnt;&ndash;36&percnt;) of the global population.One of the earliest reports of steep declines for this species came from Glacier Bay, where Kittlitz's Murrelet density along the shoreline in 1999 and 2000 was found to be much lower than the estimated density from a 1991 shoreline survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Robards1">Robards et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Drew1">Drew and Piatt 2008</xref>). The inferred population decline hinged on a density estimate obtained within a limited stratum (waters within 200 m of shore) that normally contains a low percentage (&sim;10&percnt;) of the overall population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Drew2">Drew et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). Inferences in this case were therefore hampered by the possibility that the trend was an artifact of a shifting distribution between the nearshore and offshore strata between years. To address the question of total population change in combined strata, we used a survey that the USFWS conducted in Glacier Bay in 1993 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Lindell1">Lindell 2005</xref>). This survey sampled all waters of the bay, including proportional coverage of nearshore and offshore waters, by using straight-line transects that angled shore to shore, sampling appropriately across the nearshore density gradient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff2">Kirchhoff 2011</xref>). By replicating this previous survey in 2009 and 2010, we hoped to provide a stronger inference about the population trend for the entire bay and avoid the issues that complicated earlier comparisons of nonstandard surveys (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Drew1">Drew and Piatt 2008</xref>). In this paper, we present the results of our 1993, 2009, and 2010 surveys, compute a population trend that includes these surveys within an overall time series, and discuss the conservation implications of our findings.Glacier Bay is a large, tidally mixed estuary on the mainland of southeast Alaska. The fjord is surrounded by mountainous terrain with significant ice cover and has many sources of fresh water, including fluvial runoff from melting glaciers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hill1">Hill et al. 2009</xref>). Although Glacier Bay was completely ice-covered 250 years ago, today the marine waters are essentially deglaciated following one of the most rapid tidewater glacier retreats on record (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hall1">Hall et al. 1995</xref>). About 70&percnt; of the fresh water entering Glacier Bay proper comes from streams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hill1">Hill et al. 2009</xref>), most of which are carrying glacial runoff. The runoff from these sources carries abundant nutrients in readily available form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hood1">Hood and Scott 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hood2">Hood et al. 2009</xref>). High-nutrient inputs, combined with bathymetric and tidal mixing, sustain unusually high levels of phytoplankton throughout the spring and summer months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hooge1">Hooge and Hooge 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Etherington1">Etherington et al. 2007</xref>) and support notable numbers of secondary consumers and marine predators, including seabirds, marine mammals, and fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Robards1">Robards et al. 2003</xref>).A set of 37 transects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f03">Figure 3</xref>) was surveyed 5 times: once in 1993, 3 times in 2009, and once in 2010. Vessels navigated between the start and end points of each transect by autopilot to ensure accurate, unbiased replication. In 4 of the 5 surveys, observers made counts from the cabin top (&sim;4 m above sea level) of &sim;17 m vessels traveling at &sim;16 km h<sup>&minus;1</sup>. One survey in 2009 was conducted from the foredeck (&sim;3 m above sea level) of a smaller vessel (&sim;11 m) traveling at &sim;12 km h<sup>&minus;1</sup>. In all surveys, 2 observers counted all murrelets sitting on or flushing from the water within 150 m of the transect centerline. Flying murrelets that intersected the 300-m wide strip were also counted. For each transect, we recorded observer names, time spent surveying the transect, sea state (Beaufort scale), and vessel speed. Transects were discontinued if waves exceeded &sim;0.6 m or poor visibility made it difficult to count and identify birds.It can be difficult to distinguish Kittlitz's Murrelets from Marbled Murrelets (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. marmoratus</named-content></italic>) in the field, and mistakes in identification have been offered to explain unusual results in some areas (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz3">Kuletz et al. 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff 2012</xref>). A particular strength of this study was participation by the same lead observer (J. Lindell) to ensure consistent standards for identification and distance estimation across all 3 surveys. Observers in the 1993 study used sight boards installed on the vessel to determine the distance to the edge of the 150 m strip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Lindell1">Lindell 2005</xref>). In 2009 and 2010, observers used a laser range finder on birds to fix the boundaries of the strip. Binoculars were used to aid identification, and communication between observers was allowed to minimize missing or double-counting birds. Although observers counted other seabirds as well as murrelets in 1993, murrelets took precedence, with the goal of getting accurate murrelet identification and counts.Population estimates in different survey years can be influenced by a number of design and methodological factors. We minimized these factors in our 3 surveys by using similar survey design, methods, vessels, and lead personnel. However, we also compared our survey estimates in 1993, 2009, and 2010 with published population estimates from 7 other years, collected using a variety of transect layouts and methods (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). We considered survey timing, bird detection, and species identification rates in all surveys, and indicate where adjustments were warranted to enable direct comparison.Our surveys in Glacier Bay were conducted coincident with the peak in summer murrelet abundance, which is the preferred time to survey this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kissling3">Kissling et al. 2007b</xref>). Median survey dates were June 23 (1993), July 6 (2009), and July 4 (2010). Other surveys in Glacier Bay were also conducted during or near the summer peak (survey dates from June 7 to July 15), with the median date of most surveys falling in late June (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Drew2">Drew et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) did not include our 2009 and 2010 surveys in their analysis because they took place in the first week of July instead of in late June. To check for possible date-related bias, we reviewed the temporal patterns of Kittlitz's Murrelet abundance as reflected in weekly surveys in the upper arms of Glacier Bay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Romano1">Romano et al. 2007</xref>). Slightly higher numbers might be expected in early July because nesting birds are completing incubation and returning to the water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff2">Kirchhoff 2011</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Romano1">Romano et al. (2007</xref>) found similar densities in June and July, and considerable week-to-week variation in densities and distribution of birds. Thus, because the overall densities between June 15 and July 15 did not show a strong trend, we considered surveys conducted within the late June to early July time period to be comparable.An assumption with strip transects is that 100&percnt; of the birds within the strip are detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Buckland1">Buckland et al. 2001</xref>). This assumption is not necessarily met with murrelets, which are small and can be easily missed, especially in less than calm water. However, the exact percentage of birds detected will vary depending on factors such as sea state, weather, strip width, and survey platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Ronconi1">Ronconi and Burger 2009</xref>). Although a significant percentage of murrelets likely go undetected in a typical strip survey, we have no reason to expect that this percentage increases or decreases systematically over time. Most trend analyses for this species are derived from strip transects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Drew1">Drew and Piatt 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz1">Kuletz et al. 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz3">2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>), which, in theory, provide useful inferences about population trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Ronconi1">Ronconi and Burger 2009</xref>). We assume the same.If observers do not assign murrelets to species, or mistakenly identify them, significant bias in population estimates can result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hoekman2">Hoekman et al. 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff 2012</xref>). In some surveys, crews leave a variable fraction of murrelets unidentified, with these birds later prorated to species based on the ratio of birds identified to species in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff2">Kirchhoff 2011</xref>). The 1993 survey was specifically focused on murrelets, and observers were instructed to identify 100&percnt; of tallied murrelets to species. This raised the possibility that when faced with an uncertain identification, observers might have been biased toward the more common species (Marbled Murrelet; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). To address this potential bias, we assumed that the percentage of birds that were hard to identify in 1993 was similar to the percentage of birds left unidentified in all other survey years (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 25&percnt;, SE &equals; 6&percnt;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 9 years, including 1991, 1999&ndash;2003, and 2008&ndash;2010). Assuming the hard-to-identify birds in 1993 were all recorded in the field as Marbled Murrelets, we reassigned them into an unidentified category, and prorated them to species using the standard method used on all other surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff2">Kirchhoff 2011</xref>). The effect of this adjustment increased the estimated population of Kittlitz's Murrelets in 1993 by 35&percnt;, from 3,262 to 4,397 birds.Mean Kittlitz's Murrelet density was computed by ratio estimator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Stehman1">Stehman and Salzer 2000</xref>) and converted to population size assuming 1,258 km<sup>2</sup> of marine waters in Glacier Bay. The 95&percnt; confidence limits were estimated using a bootstrap technique that randomly resampled from the individual transects 10,000 times with replacement and with the original sample size of 37 transects. The suspected pattern of decline was exponential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>), so we transformed the dependent variable (Kittlitz's Murrelet population size) with a natural log transformation, which resulted in a linear regression. We analyzed the population data for trends using a weighted least squares model of the transformed data, which weights each survey year by the inverse of its variance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Quinn1">Quinn and Keough 2002</xref>). The advantage of weighted least squares models is the ability to handle regression situations in which the data points are of varying quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-NIST1">NIST 2012</xref>). These weighted models have been used to assess trends of Kittlitz's Murrelets in Prince William Sound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz1">Kuletz et al. 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff 2012</xref>) and Glacier Bay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>).We conducted a power analysis using all 10 survey years. For each survey year we assumed that variance was known and that estimates were unbiased. The asymmetrical confidence limits indicated that we should conduct our simulations using asymmetrical probability distributions unique to each survey year. For each year, we used ObsMean to represent the observed population estimate, LCL to represent the bootstrap lower confidence limit, and UCL to represent the bootstrap upper confidence limit. Random numbers from a uniform distribution between 0 and 1 were converted to simulated population estimates using a cumulative normal distribution function. If the random number was below 0.5 then the normal distribution was assumed to have a coefficient of variation (CV) equal to (ObsMean &minus; LCL)/(2 &ast; ObsMean). If the random number was above 0.5 then the CV was assumed to be equal to (UCL &minus; ObsMean)/(2 &ast; ObsMean). Rarely was a simulated population estimate &lt;300, and in those cases the value was truncated at 300. The simulated population estimates were transformed by taking their natural logs, following which a weighted least squares linear regression was computed. Weights were assigned as the inverse of &lsqb;(Ln(UCL) &minus; Ln(LCL))/4&rsqb;&circ;2. The alpha level for testing whether the slope was significantly different from 0 was 0.05. Two thousand iterations were used to compute power.Based on our strip surveys, the estimated population of Kittlitz's Murrelets in Glacier Bay, Alaska, ranged from 4,397 to 6,421 birds between 1993 and 2010 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-t01">Table 1</xref>). Although point estimates increased with each of our surveys, with just 3 years of data and relatively wide confidence intervals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f04">Figure 4</xref>) we cannot conclude that the population has significantly increased.We added our 3 population estimates to 7 other published population estimates for Glacier Bay that were derived from strip transects (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-t02">Table 2</xref>). When considering all surveys together, including 1991, the weighted least squares regression model showed a declining trend of &minus;2&percnt; per year, which was not significantly different from zero (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.51). The untransformed data and back-transformed regression line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f05">Figure 5</xref>) show the relative magnitude and variance of each survey, and highlight the high mean and low precision of the 1991 estimate. The addition of the 1993, 2009, and 2010 surveys changes the conclusion from that of a population in steep decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>) to a population that shows no evidence of significant change.We had high power (&gt;0.99) to detect a population decline had the population been declining at a rate of &minus;11&percnt; per year. Therefore, the conclusion that the population was declining between &minus;10.7&percnt; and &minus;14.4&percnt; per annum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>) was rejected. The data also showed reasonable power (0.80) to detect a change had the population been declining at &minus;5&percnt; per annum. Although the population in Glacier Bay is clearly not in steep decline, smaller changes may be occurring that the historic surveys do not have the statistical power to detect.This study is the only one to have compared Glacier Bay murrelet populations within the entire bay over a long time period (1993&ndash;2010) using the same design and similar methods. This comparison gives no indication of a population decline since 1993. When all other survey years are considered, including the first survey in 1991, the slope of the trend line is not significantly different from zero, suggesting no evidence of population change. Using a subset of these surveys, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) reached a very different conclusion, finding the Kittlitz's Murrelet population in Glacier Bay to have declined by 89&percnt; between 1991 and 2008, at a constant rate of at least &minus;10.7&percnt; per year. That conclusion could only have been reached with a large survey gap between 1991 and 1999, which gave high leverage to the initial survey, and allowed speculation about the form of the decline over subsequent data-free years.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) excluded our 1993 survey because the percentage of Kittlitz's Murrelets counted was lower than that of other surveys, presumably signaling that misidentification had occurred. Our 2009 and 2010 surveys were excluded by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) because they were conducted in early July rather than late June. Our examination of Kittlitz's Murrelet densities in Glacier Bay during late June and early July showed no consistent or large difference during that timeframe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Romano1">Romano et al. 2007</xref>). With respect to the lack of unidentified birds in the 1993 survey, we assumed that the maximum possible bias had occurred (i.e. all hard-to-identify birds were labeled as Marbled Murrelets) and adjusted the estimate accordingly. This increased the Kittlitz's Murrelet estimate for 1993 by a little more than 1,000 birds and raised the percentage of Kittlitz's Murrelets in the survey from 7&percnt; to 10&percnt;, which is &sim;5 percentage points lower than the percentages recorded in 2009 and 2010. Species ratios can be skewed by large influxes of foraging Marbled Murrelets on some days and in some years (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Whitworth1">Whitworth et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff1">Kirchhoff 2008</xref>); thus, such variation should be expected. Nevertheless, we accepted that assigning species of hard-to-identify birds may have been biased, and adjusted the estimate accordingly.In Glacier Bay, the two surveys that dictated our interpretation of the population trend were the first two&mdash;1991 and 1993. The all-bay population estimate for Kittlitz's Murrelets in 1991 was 33,612 birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). Two years later, the USFWS survey found 4,397 birds, which is in the mid-range of all subsequent strip-transect estimates (2,325&ndash;6,421). We have described our 1993 survey in some detail. It is also worth considering the 1991 survey and reasons why it appears as an outlier.While the high density of Kittlitz's Murrelets in nearshore waters in 1991 might be explained by imprecise shoreline-following transects that stray away from shore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kirchhoff2">Kirchhoff 2011</xref>), &sim;90&percnt; of the 1991 population estimate was derived from relatively few crossing transects in offshore waters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). Sampling in the offshore stratum, as mapped by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>), showed disproportionately high sampling in the upper arms of Glacier Bay. This sampling design will have returned a positively biased population estimate in 1991, because Kittlitz's Murrelets were much more common in the upper bay in that year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt2">Piatt et al. 1991</xref>).When sampling intensity is extremely light, as it was offshore in 1991, a single observation can have tremendous influence on the overall population estimate. In 1991, the transect with the highest density of Kittlitz's Murrelets had 458 birds km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f02">figure 2</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. 2011</xref>). This single transect contributed 19,876 Kittlitz's Murrelets, or 58&percnt;, to the 1991 bay-wide population estimate. Thus, confidence in the overall 1991 population estimate is low because the bulk of the estimate was derived from sparse convenience sampling in the offshore stratum, and most of the birds were detected on a single transect. This is reflected in the 95&percnt; confidence limits in 1991, which spanned 7,882 to 79,472 Kittlitz's Murrelets.While possible errors in counts and species identification cannot be known or corrected today, the variance associated with a survey can be factored into the analysis. Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) and this study used a weighted least squares regression that discounted less precise surveys. The 1991 survey received relatively low weight in both analyses because it was imprecise. Although suspected errors in surveys can be accommodated by adjusting results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz3">Kuletz et al. 2011b</xref>), or excluding the suspect surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kuletz1">Kuletz et al. 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hodges1">Hodges and Kirchhoff 2012</xref>), we chose to include all surveys in the weighted least squares model. The only adjustment was to the 1993 estimate, correcting for the maximum possible bias in assignment of hard-to-identify birds.&lsquo;Anchoring' is a term that has been used to describe the practice of placing undue faith in an initial observation, and judging subsequent observations against it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Tversky1">Tversky and Kahneman 1974</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Farmer1">Farmer (2008</xref>) cited anchoring with respect to population estimates for two shorebird species of conservation concern, noting the easy acceptance of initial data showing low population sizes and high resistance to later surveys showing larger populations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Webb1">Webb (2008</xref>) noted that sea turtle researchers had a similar tendency to treat inference in a biased way, accepting as fact any inference that populations of sea turtles were declining, but demanding high levels of proof before accepting evidence that they were increasing. We suspect that the opinion of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Piatt3">Piatt et al. (2011</xref>) regarding our 1993, 2009, and 2010 surveys was colored by how our results meshed with the &lsquo;anchor' of the 1991 survey and by previously published reports of an ongoing exponential decline.Initial estimates often become accepted despite many well-known biases and uncertainties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Webb1">Webb 2008</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt (2003</xref>) concluded that the Kittlitz's Murrelet population declined 83&percnt; in Kenai Fjords between 1976 and 2002. They used only the field-identified murrelets for this analysis, even though the first survey identified 100&percnt; of murrelets to species and later surveys assigned as few as half to species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt 2003</xref>). Other methodological differences further inflated the first population estimate relative to that of subsequent surveys. The initial survey used 2 observers, stationed on an elevated platform aboard a large vessel, and counted every bird seen with no defined strip width. Subsequent surveys were conducted primarily from small inflatable boats, sometimes with only one observer, using a defined strip width. These differences made it difficult to fairly compare counts from the first and subsequent surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Nishimoto1">Nishimoto and Rice 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt (2003</xref>) came to their conclusion by assuming all birds counted on the initial survey (no strip width) were actually within a 150-m half-width strip, that observers on high and low platforms missed the same number of birds, and that the percentage of murrelets left unidentified and omitted from the density calculation did not materially affect population estimates. All 3 assumptions are demonstrably false. However, because the resultant 83&percnt; population decline in Kenai Fjords (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-VanPelt1">Van Pelt and Piatt 2003</xref>) matched the reported declines in Glacier Bay and Prince William Sound, it was presented as confirmation of a range-wide phenomenon, accepted uncritically, and continues to be cited in listing petitions, agency reviews, and on conservation websites today. In reality, the methodological differences prevented any meaningful comparison of Kittlitz's Murrelet numbers among the surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Arimitsu1">Arimitsu et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day1">Day 2011</xref>).We agree with other researchers that monitoring this species is inherently difficult because of its clumped distribution, risk of misidentification, low detection rates, and influence of ephemeral environmental factors on distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kissling3">Kissling et al. 2007b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS4">USFWS 2011b</xref>). More surveys (years), more intensive surveys (transects), and better-quality surveys (distance sampling, transect orientation) are needed to estimate population size and trends for this species with acceptable accuracy and precision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kissling3">Kissling et al. 2007b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day1">Day 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Hoekman1">Hoekman et al. 2011a</xref>).We believe that the precautionary principle in conservation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Cooney1">Cooney 2004</xref>) is an important and appropriate paradigm. However, in the extreme, it can result in misplaced conservation priorities and may subtract from critical conservation needs elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Farmer1">Farmer 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Webb1">Webb 2008</xref>). We suggest that anchoring has played a key role in the conservation status of Kittlitz's Murrelet until recently. This is a bird that numbers in the tens of thousands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS3">USFWS 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-NatureServe1">NatureServe 2013</xref>), is distributed across the North Pacific from Russia to southeastern Alaska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Day3">Day et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS4">USFWS 2011b</xref>), and forages and nests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-f06">Figure 6</xref>) in areas with and without glaciers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Stenhouse1">Stenhouse et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Kaler1">Kaler et al. 2009</xref>, Artuhkin et al. 2011). In comparison, another Pacific seabird, the Short-tailed Albatross (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria albatrus</named-content></italic>), declined from an estimated 5 million birds to fewer than 50 by the 1940s, and in 2001 numbered just 1,200 birds in 2 colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-USFWS1">USFWS 2001</xref>). That species is rated as &ldquo;vulnerable&rdquo; to extinction by IUCN, 2 ranks below the critically endangered rating for Kittlitz's Murrelets. Such incongruous assessments erode the credibility and effectiveness of the IUCN rating system. Problems appear most prevalent with long-lived species assigned under the declining trend criterion. Estimates of historic abundance for such species tend to be subjective, with weak or poorly documented protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Mrosovsky1">Mrosovsky and Godfrey 2008</xref>). A species may still be quite abundant and widely dispersed even after a suspected large decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-1-24-Godfrey1">Godfrey and Godley 2008</xref>).As surveys continue for Kittlitz's Murrelets with improved coverage, methods, and analyses, we are finding a general pattern of more birds, broader habitat use, and trends of less concern than first thought. Continued assessment of their population status and trends is important. We did this for Glacier Bay, a place containing the single largest population in the species' range, and found no evidence of decline. While this finding in and of itself may not warrant reverting back to &ldquo;least concern&rdquo; status for Kittlitz's Murrelets, it raises questions about whether this species is truly endangered. We hope this paper stimulates further discussion and a fresh view of the global conservation status of the Kittlitz's Murrelet.<bold>Note Added in Proof:</bold> On October 3, 2013, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service published their 12-month finding on the petition to list the Kittlitz's Murrelet under the Endangered Species Act. The Service concluded: &ldquo;Our review of the best available scientific and commercial information indicates the Kittlitz's Murrelet is not in danger of extinction (endangered), nor likely to become endangered in the foreseeable future (threatened), throughout all or a significant portion of its range. Therefore, we find that listing the Kittlitz's Murrelet as an endangered or threatened species under the Act is not warranted at this time&rdquo; (Federal Register Volume 78, Number 192, page 61800).We thank the National Park Service for encouraging and supporting this survey work. In addition to the authors, observers on the 2009 and 2010 surveys were D. J. Albert, D. S. Albert, S. McAllister, D. Parent, T. Parent, M. Smith, and S. Wright. J. Koehler provided support in 2009 with logistics and planning, as well as supervising crews on the ground. Special thanks to M. Lundsten, captain of the vessel <italic>Gravina</italic>, for providing a safe and efficient platform for these surveys. S. Gende of the National Park Service and 4 anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments on the manuscript. Our research was funded jointly by Audubon Alaska and the Wildlife Diversity Program, Alaska Department of Fish and Game. The findings and conclusions in this manuscript are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the Alaska Department of Fish and Game or the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.The Kittlitz's Murrelet pursues prey like this Pacific herring (<named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple"><italic>Clupea pallasii</italic></named-content>) by &ldquo;flying&rdquo; underwater using their wings for propulsion. Fish-holding behavior seen here often precedes a flight inland to feed a chick on the nest. Photo credit: Milo BurchamThe global distribution of the Kittlitz's Murrelet. Highest at-sea densities of Kittlitz's Murrelets are found in association with recently deglaciated environments in the eastern portion of the bird's range, including Glacier Bay, Alaska.Location of 37 transects surveyed for Kittlitz's Murrelets in 1993, 2009, and 2010 in Glacier Bay, Alaska (at the scale at which the map is drawn, two transects are too close together to distinguish).Estimated population (solid symbols) and 95&percnt; confidence intervals for Kittlitz's Murrelet in Glacier Bay, Alaska, in 1993, 2009, and 2010. Open symbols in 2009 are estimated population size from each of 3 independent surveys.Estimated population and 95&percnt; confidence intervals for Kittlitz's Murrelet in Glacier Bay, Alaska, 1991&ndash;2010. The slope of the dashed regression line is not significantly different from zero (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.51).The Kittlitz's Murrelet nests solitarily on sparsely vegetated or unvegetated scree-fields, talus slopes, and barren ground in coastal mountains. Nests are difficult to find and monitor, so population trends hinge on at-sea surveys. This bird sits on a nest in Cape Krusenstern National Monument, north of the Arctic Circle in northwestern Alaska. Photo credit: Nick HajdukovichCounts of all murrelets (TOTAL), Marbled Murrelets (MAMU), Kittlitz's Murrelets (KIMU), and unidentified murrelets (UNMU); calculated prorated Kittlitz's Murrelet (prorated KIMU); and estimated total KIMU population by survey year in Glacier Bay, Alaska.Kittlitz's Murrelet population estimates in Glacier Bay, Alaska, by year. The 1993 estimate has been adjusted for estimated unidentified murrelets, prorated to species.