 Marion Jenkinson AOU Service Award 2014, to Sara R. Morris  The Marion Jenkinson AOU Service Award is given to an individual who has performed continued extensive service to the American Ornithologists' Union, including holding elected offices but emphasizing volunteered contributions and committee participation. Recipients are selected by the AOU Executive Committee. The award consists of a framed certificate and an honorarium, and honors Marion Jenkinson Mengel, who served the AOU as treasurer and in other capacities for many years.  The 2014 award is presented to outgoing AOU Secretary Sara Morris for her significant contribution of service to the AOU. Having become an AOU member as a graduate student in 1990, Sara was voted an Elective Member in 2004 and a Fellow in 2010. She has served on numerous AOU committees, including the Web Committee (2006&ndash;present), Finance Committee (2005&ndash;2006), and Student Awards Committee (2002&ndash;2003).  We are particularly grateful to Sara for her past eight years as secretary of the AOU. In this role, she has served as the instant calendar, planner, bylaws expert, organizational fiend, true thinker, and voice of reason on all issues facing the AOU Executive Committee and the Council. She is truly remarkable.  Sara is also currently first vice-president of the Wilson Ornithological Society and will be its next president. Thus, she will be missed on the AOU Council and Executive Committee.  We owe Dr. Sara Morris a tremendous debt of gratitude for her dedication to the AOU. We believe that Marion Jenkinson would be proud as well.  This award is given to an individual who has performed continued extensive service to the AOU, including holding elected offices but emphasizing volunteered contributions and committee participation. Recipients are selected by the AOU Executive Committee. The award honors Marion Jenkinson Mengel, who served the AOU as Treasurer and in other capacities for many years. The award consists of a framed certificate and an honorarium. 