Peripheral androgen action helps modulate vocal production in a suboscine passerineSex hormones and the female voiceSinging rate and female attraction in the Pied Flycatcher: An experimentTestosterone affects song modulation during simulated territorial intrusions in male Black Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus ochruros</named-content></italic>)Phylogeny and diversification of the largest avian radiationFemale choice for male motor skillsSteroid hormone receptor expression and action in boneAndrogen effects on vocal muscle structure in a teleost fish with inter- and intra-sexual dimorphismVocalization evoked from the optic lobe of a songbirdRelative contributions of collagen and elastin to elasticity of the vocal fold under tensionHormones and midbrain mediation of courtship behavior in the male Ring Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Streptopelia risoria</named-content></italic>)Effects of testosterone metabolites and estrogen in the midbrain control of courtship behavior in the male Ring Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Streptopelia risoria</named-content></italic>)Testosterone implants alter the frequency range of Zebra Finch songsTestosterone and its effects on courtship in Golden-collared Manakins (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>): Seasonal, sex, and age differencesBehavioural and morphological dose-responses to testosterone and to 5&alpha;-dihydrotestosterone in the castrated male Japanese QuailVocalization activity at leks of six manakin (Pipridae) species in eastern EcuadorSuperfast muscles control song production in songbirdsLimb muscles are androgen targets in an acrobatic tropical birdA possible explanation for the peripheral selectivity of a novel non-steroidal pure antiandrogen, Casodex (ICI 176,334)&ldquo;Casodex&rdquo; (ICI 176,334)&mdash;A new, pure, peripherally-selective anti-androgen: Preclinical studiesThe preclinical development of bicalutamide: Pharmacodynamics and mechanism of actionTestosterone affects the acoustic structure of the male call in the Grey Partridge (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perdix perdix</named-content></italic>)Androgen and the elaborate courtship behavior of a tropical lekking birdPeripheral androgen receptors sustain the acrobatics and fine motor skill of elaborate male courtshipSong correlates with social context, testosterone and body condition in male Barn SwallowsIntegrative physiology of fundamental frequency control in birdsRole of syringeal muscles in controlling the phonology of bird songThe influence of testosterone on the development and fixation of the form of displays in two age classes of young Black-headed GullsAvian brains and a new understanding of vertebrate brain evolutionSuppressive function of androgen receptor in bone resorptionTestosterone and avian life histories: Effects of experimentally elevated testosterone on behavior and correlates of fitness in the Dark-eyed Junco (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Junco hyemalis</named-content></italic>)A suboscine bird (Eastern Phoebe, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sayornis phoebe</named-content></italic>) develops normal song without auditory feedbackExperimental manipulation of testosterone and condition during molt affects activity and vocalizations of male Blue TitsUsing temperature to analyse temporal dynamics in the songbird motor pathwaySpecificity of gonadal hormone modulation of cholinergic enzymes in the avian syrinxSexual selection on plumage and behavior in an avian hybrid zone: Experimental tests of male&ndash;male interactionsFunction of song in Scott's Seaside Sparrow, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content> peninsulae</italic>The influence of testosterone on territorial defence and parental behavior in male free-living Rufous Whistlers, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pachycephala rufiventris</named-content></italic>Androgen receptor in rat skeletal muscle: Characterization and physiological variationsAndrogen receptor immunoreactivity in skeletal muscle: Enrichment at the neuromuscular junctionFeature weighting in species song recognition by the Field Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella pusilla</named-content></italic>)Testosterone triggers growth of brain vocal control nuclei in adult female canariesTestosterone induction of song in photosensitive and photorefractory male sparrowsA sex-dependent influence of testosterone on the dorsomedial neuronal population of the Japanese-quail intercollicular nucleusAndrogen alters the dentritic arbors of SNB motoneurons by acting upon their target musclesDifferential sensitivity to androgens within a sexually dimorphic muscle of male frogs (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Xenopus laevis</named-content></italic>)Songbirds tune their vocal tract to the fundamental frequency of their songTelencephalic aromatase but not a song circuit in a sub-oscine passerine, the Golden-collared Manakin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>)Coordinated and dissociated effects of testosterone on singing behavior and song control nuclei in canaries (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Serinus canaria</named-content></italic>)Sex steroids and their actions on the birdsong systemHormones and the neuromuscular control of courtship in the Golden-collared Manakin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>)Syringeal specialization of frequency control during song production in the Bengalese Finch (<italic>Lonchura striata domestica</italic>)Effects of long-acting testosterone treatment on free-living Pied Flycatchers, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>, during the breeding periodPlumage brightness predicts male mating success in the lekking Golden-collared Manakin, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>Somatosensory feedback modulates the respiratory motor program of crystallized birdsongExperimental alteration of male song quality and output affects female mate choice and pair bond formation in Zebra FinchesAndrogens and estrogens induce seasonal-like growth of song nuclei in the adult songbird brainSteroid receptors in the adult Zebra Finch syrinx: A sex difference in androgen receptor mRNA, minimal expression of estrogen receptor alpha and aromataseLateralization and effects of adult androgen in a sexually dimorphic neuromuscular system controlling song in Zebra FinchesInspiratory muscle activity during bird songResearch resource: The androgen receptor modulates expression of genes with critical roles in muscle development and functionAndrogenic activation of intracellular androgen receptors (AR) influences avian vocal production, though this has largely been investigated at the level of the brain. We investigated the influence of predominantly peripheral AR on vocal output in wild Golden-collared Manakins (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>). In this suboscine species, males court females by performing acrobatic displays and by producing relatively simple <italic>chee-poo</italic> vocalizations. To assess whether peripheral AR influences the acoustic structure of these vocal signals, we treated reproductively active adult males with the peripherally selective antiandrogen bicalutamide and then measured phonation performance. Inhibiting AR outside of the central nervous system increased the duration of the <italic>chee</italic> note and decreased the fundamental frequency of the <italic>poo</italic> note. This treatment caused no discernable change to <italic>chee-poo</italic> frequency modulation or entropy. Our results show that activation of peripheral AR mediates note-specific changes to temporal and pitch characteristics of the Golden-collared Manakin's main sexual call. Thus, our study provides one of the first demonstrations that androgenic action originating outside of the brain and likely on musculoskeletal targets can modulate avian vocal production.La activaci&oacute;n androg&eacute;nica de los receptores de andr&oacute;genos (RA) intracelulares influye en la producci&oacute;n de vocalizaciones en las aves, aunque muchos de los trabajos que han investigado este asunto lo han hecho a nivel cerebral. Investigamos la influencia de los RA, predominantemente en la periferia, sobre la producci&oacute;n vocal en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>. En esta especie de ave suboscina, los machos cortejan a las hembras haciendo despliegues acrob&aacute;ticos y produciendo vocalizaciones relativamente simples (<italic>chii-pu</italic>). Para determinar si los RA perif&eacute;ricos influyen en la estructura ac&uacute;stica de estas se&ntilde;ales vocales, tratamos machos adultos reproductivamente activos con bicalutamida, un antiandr&oacute;geno perif&eacute;ricamente selectivo, y luego medimos el desempe&ntilde;o de fonaci&oacute;n. La inhibici&oacute;n de los RA por fuera del sistema nervioso central increment&oacute; la duraci&oacute;n de la nota <italic>chii</italic> y disminuy&oacute; la frecuencia fundamental de la nota <italic>pu</italic>. Este tratamiento no caus&oacute; cambios discernibles en la modulaci&oacute;n de frecuencias del llamado ni en su entrop&iacute;a. Estos datos muestran que la activaci&oacute;n de los RA perif&eacute;ricos produce cambios espec&iacute;ficos de cada nota en las caracter&iacute;sticas temporales y tonales del principal llamado sexual de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. vitellinus</named-content></italic>. Por lo tanto, nuestro estudio provee una de las primeras demostraciones de que la acci&oacute;n androg&eacute;nica que se origina por fuera del cerebro, probablemente en blancos m&uacute;sculo-esquel&eacute;ticos, puede modular la producci&oacute;n vocal en las aves.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> canto de aves, comportamiento social, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>, m&uacute;sculo esquel&eacute;tico, receptores de andr&oacute;genos, siringe, sistema m&uacute;sculo-esquel&eacute;tico, sistema nervioso perif&eacute;rico, sistemas de control del canto, testosteronaAndrogenic hormones act via intracellular androgen receptors (AR) to influence vertebrate social behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-AdkinsRegan1">Adkins-Regan 2005</xref>), and avian vocal production is a prime example of this trait. In some species, vocalizations are acoustically complex and require exquisite coordination between (1) central systems that govern sensorimotor and motor programming and (2) peripheral systems that govern the generation of sound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Schlinger1">Schlinger 1997</xref>). In passerine birds, for example, males sing and/or call to attract mates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Catchpole1">Catchpole and Slater 2008</xref>), and research has shown that androgens influence such behavior by changing the number of times that individuals sing and/or call (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Silverin1">Silverin 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Nowicki1">Nowicki and Ball 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Ketterson1">Ketterson et al. 1992</xref>, P. G. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-McDonald1">McDonald et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Kurvers1">Kurvers et al. 2008</xref>), as well as the acoustic structure or makeup of these songs and/or calls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Deviche1">Deviche and Schumacher 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Groothuis1">Groothuis and Meeuwissen 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fusani1">Fusani et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Galeotti1">Galeotti et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cynx1">Cynx et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Apfelbeck1">Apfelbeck et al. 2012</xref>). However, in general, we know relatively little about where and how androgens act within the body to mediate acoustic parameters of bird songs and calls.Most studies that have examined how androgens influence avian vocal production have focused at the level of the brain. The midbrain nucleus intercollicularis (nICO), for example, is an androgen-sensitive premotor region that regulates the calls of many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Brown1">Brown 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cohen1">Cohen 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cohen2">Cohen and Cheng 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Panzica1">Panzica et al. 1991</xref>). Additionally, in oscine songbirds, a higher-level song-control system underlies the learning and production of complex songs (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Jarvis1">Jarvis et al. 2005</xref>), and androgenic hormones modulate this system in a way that presumably influences when and how songs are produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Nottebohm1">Nottebohm 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Tramontin1">Tramontin et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Sartor1">Sartor et al. 2005</xref>). Despite this focus on the brain, it is also possible that androgens signal via AR in peripheral parts of the body. Musculoskeletal systems, for instance, can express abundant AR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Michel1">Michel and Baulieu 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Brantley1">Brantley et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Regnier1">Regnier and Herrera 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Bland1">Bland 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Kawano1">Kawano et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Monks1">Monks et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Feng1">Feng et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Wyce1">Wyce et al. 2010</xref>), and some of the tissues that compose these systems are essential for avian vocal production. The avian vocal organ, the syrinx, is a prime example: It not only expresses AR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Wade1">Wade and Buhlman 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Veney1">Veney and Wade 2004</xref>) but also influences acoustic parameters of vocal output, such as fundamental frequency (<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>), frequency modulation (FM) and entropy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Goller2">Goller and Suthers 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Riede1">Riede et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Elemans1">Elemans et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Secora1">Secora et al. 2012</xref>). Thus, in principle, this means that androgens have the capacity to act not only on the brain, but also on the musculature and cartilaginous structures that influence vocal filtering and production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Deviche1">Deviche and Schumacher 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fusani1">Fusani et al. 1994</xref>). To date, such effects have been studied infrequently.Here, we examine how activation of AR mainly outside of the central nervous system (CNS) influences acoustic production in the Golden-collared Manakin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manacus vitellinus</named-content></italic>). This suboscine passerine species inhabits Panamanian rainforests. Males regularly perform elaborate courtship displays that involve mechanical &ldquo;wing-snaps&rdquo; and rapid dancing routines over the forest floor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Schlinger2">Schlinger et al. 2013</xref>). As part of this sexual repertoire, males also broadcast simple <italic>chee-poo</italic> calls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-f01">Figure 1</xref>), although such vocalizations are produced independently of physical maneuvering. Females use the <italic>chee-poo</italic> in choosing mates, which suggests that these calls are adaptive and that their underlying mechanisms are influenced by sexual selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Barske1">Barske et al. 2011</xref>). Thus, like many other manakin species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Duraes1">Dur&atilde;es et al. 2011</xref>), Golden-collared Manakins utilize vocalizations as an important component of their reproductive and territorial behavior.Narrow-band spectrograph of a <italic>chee-poo</italic> call from a reproductively active adult male Golden-collared Manakin.To inhibit AR primarily in the periphery, we treated reproductively active adult male Golden-collared Manakins with the antiandrogen bicalutamide (BICAL). This pharmacological agent blocks AR peripherally without affecting AR centrally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Freeman1">Freeman et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Furr1">Furr 1989</xref>). We have verified that BICAL acts in a peripherally selective manner in the study species, in that it significantly disrupts the expression profiles of known androgen-dependent genes peripherally but does not significantly affect expression of androgen-dependent genes in the brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Additionally, we have shown that, within days of treatment, BICAL decreases the rates at which males perform wing-snaps and courtship dances; BICAL administration does not, however, significantly influence the rate at which males produce <italic>chee-poos</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Those results suggest that inhibition of peripheral AR changes the physicality of male courtship behavior. Given that the syrinx (the avian vocal organ) of the Golden-collared Manakin expresses large amounts of AR compared with other passerine species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Feng1">Feng et al. 2010</xref>), we asked, in the present study, whether blocking AR in peripheral tissues that contribute to phonation, such as the syrinx, over the same period similarly disrupts acoustic production.To address this question, we assessed the acoustic features of the <italic>chee-poos</italic> recorded from those wild males treated with BICAL or control implants (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). We specifically focused on measurements of <italic>chee-poo</italic> pitch (<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>), degree of sound change over time (FM), and tonal purity (entropy), because these characteristics can be affected by peripheral sound-generating structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Goller2">Goller and Suthers 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Riede1">Riede et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Elemans1">Elemans et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Secora1">Secora et al. 2012</xref>). We also measured the duration of the notes within the <italic>chee-poo</italic>.We studied reproductively active adult male Golden-collared Manakins during the height of the breeding season (February&ndash;April) at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Gamboa, Panama. Birds were captured via passive mist netting and then weighed, uniquely leg-banded for future identification, and randomly assigned to 1 of 2 treatment groups. In the first group, males (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 6) received a time-release implant that emitted 0.25 mg day<sup>&minus;1</sup> of the peripherally selective antiandrogen BICAL for 21 days (Innovative Research of America, Florida, USA; dose &equals; 12.5 mg kg<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup>). In the second group, males (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 6) received a control implant that was identical in every way but emitted no BICAL. Implants measured 1.6 &times; 5 mm (height &times; diameter) and were placed subcutaneously on the bird's back at the base of its neck. Implantation procedures are described in detail elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fusani2">Fusani et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Notably, implantation is quick (&sim;2 min) and does not complicate the birds' health or activity levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>).Birds came from a total of 7 leks, with at least 2&ndash;10 birds lek<sup>&minus;1</sup>. In 5 of these leks that contained &ge;4 displaying males, we used 2 birds lek<sup>&minus;1</sup> (each of these birds was assigned to a different treatment group). In 2 of these 7 leks that contained &le;3 displaying males, we used only 1 bird lek<sup>&minus;1</sup>. In one instance, this bird was assigned to the BICAL group, and in the other instance this bird was assigned to the control group. Ultimately, we obtained data from 4 males group<sup>&minus;1</sup>, given that some males (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2 group<sup>&minus;1</sup>) did not <italic>chee-poo</italic> during the tape-recorded observational session (see below).In vertebrates, BICAL acts as a potent antiandrogen that blocks AR exclusively outside of the CNS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Freeman1">Freeman et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Furr1">Furr 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Furr2">Furr and Tucker 1996</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Freeman1">Freeman et al. (1989)</xref> injected animals with radio-labeled BICAL and found significant accumulation of radioactivity in all of the peripheral organs examined, but not within the brain. Moreover, treatment with modest amounts of BICAL (sufficient to block peripheral AR) had no effect on the androgen-dependent mammalian hypothalamic&ndash;pituitary&ndash;gonadal axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Freeman1">Freeman et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Furr1">Furr 1989</xref>). As noted above, we had previously validated the efficacy of BICAL in the study species by examining central and peripheral androgen-dependent gene expression: The BICAL-treated birds appeared to be healthy and displayed the same overall activity and locomotor abilities as nontreated birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>).After implantation, males were immediately released onto the lek from which they were captured. Each bird returned to its respective display arena, and some individuals were witnessed displaying within minutes of implantation and release.Each bird was observed for a 10-day period after implantation. We selected this time frame because past work had shown that BICAL inhibited display behavior beginning on the first day after treatment and through the following 10 days thereafter (these data, including the frequency of <italic>chee-poo</italic> production, are provided in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Each observation session lasted 30 min, occurring between 0700 and 0900 hours and between 1200 and 1630 hours, when the birds' activity levels were highest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Stein1">Stein and Uy 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fusani2">Fusani et al. 2007</xref>). Observers sat &sim;10 m from the display arena and provided birds with a 15-min habituation period before collecting data. In a randomly selected subset of observation sessions over the 10-day period, <italic>chee-poos</italic> were tape-recorded using a Sennheiser microphone (K6 series, model ME66) and a Sony TC-D5M Professional tape recorder (sample rate &equals; 48 KHz; 16-bit dynamic range). Sound files were digitized from the recorder using Audacity Audio Editor. Multiple <italic>chee-poos</italic> from each individual were recorded (range: 3&ndash;6), and only <italic>chee-poos</italic> that were definitively determined to be from the focal animal were used for analysis.We used Praat Phonetics software to generate spectrograms of each <italic>chee-poo</italic> (window length &equals; 5 msec; dynamic range &equals; 70 dB), and from these we measured both the duration and the <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> of each note. Duration was determined by selecting the beginning and end of each note with the cursor; we carefully avoided inclusion of the echo at each note's end. The <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> for each note was computed by averaging <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> measurements determined (via Praat) at 10-msec intervals along each note's base (fundamental) frequency band. Finally, we used the free, open-code software Sound Analysis Pro to calculate the FM and Weiner entropy of each note.For each acoustic variable, we used a separate general linear mixed model to examine the effects of both BICAL treatment and note (<italic>chee</italic> vs. <italic>poo</italic>). As such, BICAL treatment and note were included in each model as a fixed factor, whereas bird identity was also included as a random factor. Significant interactions were followed by a calculation of the percent change between control and BICAL treatment for each note. We were unable to collect large numbers of <italic>chee-poos</italic> from each focal individual across the entire 10-day observation period, so we were unable to include treatment time in our model as a fixed factor.The <italic>chee-poo</italic> is a 2-note call in which a <italic>chee</italic> note always precedes a <italic>poo</italic> note (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-f01">Figure 1</xref>). On average, the <italic>chee</italic> note by itself is shorter in duration than the <italic>poo</italic> note. The <italic>chee</italic> note also has a higher <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> and greater entropy than the <italic>poo</italic> note. There is, however, no discernable difference in FM between these 2 separate notes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-t01">Table 1</xref>).Sound characteristics of the Golden-collared Manakin's <italic>chee-poo</italic> vocalization and linear mixed-model results for the effects of bicalutamide (BICAL) treatment and note (<italic>chee</italic> vs. <italic>poo</italic>). Statistical results in bold denote significant effects (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) of each model.Although BICAL treatment does not induce a singular main effect on any of the measured acoustic parameters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-t01">Table 1</xref>), this antiandrogen does exert note-specific effects on specific acoustic characteristics. Namely, both the duration and <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> of the <italic>chee-poo</italic> are influenced by a significant BICAL &times; note interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-t01">Table 1</xref>). With respect to call duration, this effect is driven by a BICAL-induced increase in the duration of the <italic>chee</italic> by &sim;21&percnt; (&sim;20 msec), with virtually no effect on the duration of the <italic>poo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). The magnitude of this note-specific change in duration is greater than the likely error in measuring the onset and offset of sound in relatively low signal-to-noise ratios, which in our experience is &sim;3 msec. Next, for call <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, BICAL has a negligible effect on the chee but decreases the <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> of the <italic>poo</italic> by &gt;5&percnt; (&sim;115 Hz; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-f02">Figure 2</xref>B). Neither FM nor entropy is affected by a BICAL &times; note interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-t01">Table 1</xref>).Note-specific changes in acoustic parameters of the <italic>chee-poo</italic> after bicalutamide (BICAL) treatment. (<bold>A</bold>) Percent change in the length, or duration, of each note. (<bold>B</bold>) Percent change in the fundamental frequency (<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>) of each note.We examined how AR influences the structure and sound features of the Golden-collared Manakin's adaptive <italic>chee-poo</italic> call. We found that by using BICAL to block AR in a peripherally selective manner, we changed the call's temporal and pitch characteristics. These results suggest that activation of AR populations outside of the brain and spinal cord has the ability to mediate acoustic properties of a vocal signal in this species. Our results also show that BICAL treatment does not affect other sound elements of the <italic>chee-poo</italic>, such as the degree of frequency change over time (FM) and/or tonal purity (entropy). Effects on entropy may, in theory, be difficult to discern, because our recordings were obtained from animals in nature, a setting which is relatively more &ldquo;noisy&rdquo; than a controlled laboratory environment. However, metrics such as FM should be easily detected from wild birds in field settings; the absence of any effect of BICAL on this vocal parameter therefore points to the generally selective influence of BICAL on vocal output. In other words, the blockade of AR outside of the CNS does not induce a dramatic change in the <italic>chee-poo</italic> itself, but instead subtly changes the way in which certain components of vocal signals are produced. Our results provide compelling evidence that peripheral activation of AR plays a role in guiding avian phonation more-or-less independently of central activation of AR.BICAL does not affect acoustic output by suppressing an individual's health or by altering its social motivation, the latter of which is likely driven by central actions of androgen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fusani2">Fusani et al. 2007</xref>). Previous studies of these birds show that BICAL treatment does not change the rates at which males broadcast <italic>chee-poos</italic> around their lek (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>) and has no effect on an individual's activity, feeding behavior, and general social arousal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Thus, BICAL treatment appears to drive the observed effects on sound characteristics of the <italic>chee-poo</italic> by inhibiting androgenic activity via AR on peripheral substrates that are either directly or indirectly related to sound generation.Birds given BICAL not only increase the duration of <italic>chee</italic> notes by &sim;20 msec (21&percnt;), but also reduce the <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> of <italic>poo</italic> notes by &sim;115 Hz. These findings are consistent with other work that similarly shows androgen-dependent changes in the acoustic &ldquo;content&rdquo; of vocal production. In male Black Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus ochruros</named-content></italic>), for instance, inhibition of androgenic and estrogenic action induced shifts of &sim;300 Hz in frequency parameters of aggressive song (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Apfelbeck1">Apfelbeck et al. 2012</xref>). Likewise, in male Zebra Finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>), long-term testosterone implantation caused a &sim;100 Hz decrease in the <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> of directed sexual song (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cynx1">Cynx et al. 2005</xref>). Given that the effects reported in these past studies generally mirror, in magnitude, those reported here, it is tempting to conclude that the peripheral AR influences song production in numerous avian species.Equally interesting is that the effects of BICAL on acoustic output occur within days of treatment, which is consistent with BICAL's impact on physical display behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Fuxjager1">Fuxjager et al. 2013</xref>). Nonetheless, this result stands in contrast to work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cynx1">Cynx et al. (2005)</xref>, which showed that some effects of testosterone on acoustic output require a month to emerge. This difference may result from interspecific variation in AR expression in peripheral sound-producing tissues such as the syrinx, given that Golden-collared Manakins express more AR mRNA in this organ than Zebra Finches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Feng1">Feng et al. 2010</xref>). Of course, we cannot rule out the possibility that effects of BICAL on manakin vocal production differ in other ways in response to longer-term AR blockade.These data raise two important questions: (1) Where do androgens act in the periphery to influence vocal duration and pitch? and (2) What do androgens do to these tissues to effectuate such changes? Musculoskeletal systems that modify sound production include the syrinx, expiratory and intercostal muscles, and upper vocal tract (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Wild1">Wild et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Suthers1">Suthers et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Goller1">Goller and Riede 2013</xref>); thus, these tissues may be substrates on which peripheral AR influences vocal production. We suspect that the syrinx is the prime organ through which this occurs, because it sits at the tracheo&ndash;bronchial junction and controls intertracheal sound-generating labia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Goller1">Goller and Riede 2013</xref>). The muscles and labia of the syrinx contain AR, which makes these tissues susceptible to functional and/or morphological changes in response to androgenic action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Veney1">Veney and Wade 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Feng1">Feng et al. 2010</xref>). Blocking syringeal AR may therefore alter (1) the ability of the organ's musculature to appropriately control labial movement during expiration and/or (2) the structural constitution of the extracellular matrix and epithelium that make up and determine the labia's oscillatory (i.e. sound-generating) properties. Both of these tissues respond to steroid hormones, including androgens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Luine1">Luine et al. 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Abitbol1">Abitbol et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Wade1">Wade and Buhlman 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Chan1">Chan et al. 2007</xref>).These results do not exclude the possibility that activation of peripheral AR modulates central systems that regulate manakin vocal production. Stimulation of AR in skeletal muscle can influence the morphology of innervating motor neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Rand1">Rand and Breedlove 1995</xref>), such that inhibition of peripheral AR may change the properties of the retrograde signaling that underlies muscle&ndash;CNS feedback. These effects may influence how the <italic>chee-poo</italic> is produced and may even explain the change in call duration, given evidence that the brain controls this acoustic variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Long1">Long and Fee 2008</xref>).In Golden-collared Manakins, circulating testosterone is elevated at the onset of the breeding season and activates display behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Schlinger2">Schlinger et al. 2013</xref>). We suspect that elevated androgen levels act to fine-tune acoustic performance. As a consequence, BICAL treatment likely induces a peripherally specific &ldquo;nonreproductive&rdquo; state by blocking AR exclusively outside of the brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Day1">Day et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Schlinger2">Schlinger et al. 2013</xref>). The shifts in acoustic parameters that we document here appear to deviate significantly from the apparent natural variation that otherwise exists in control birds, even though the magnitude of these changes in and of themselves is relatively small. Birds listening to the calls of treated males are therefore likely to perceive such differences in acoustic content that we document (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Nelson1">Nelson 1988</xref>), and this may explain why information from the <italic>chee-poo</italic> is supposedly used both by females in choosing mates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Barske1">Barske et al. 2011</xref>) and by males in competing with one another (D. B. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-McDonald1">McDonald et al. 2001</xref>).It is more difficult to assess how acoustic content affects <italic>chee-poo</italic> function, because we know so little about how note duration, <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, FM, and entropy are related to female choice and/or male&ndash;male interactions. Most studies that have attempted to manipulate these acoustic parameters did so in a way that simultaneously altered other factors intrinsic to male quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-McDonald2">McDonald 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Alatalo1">Alatalo et al. 1990</xref>). Work on Zebra Finches has avoided this limitation and shown that gross manipulations of vocal production dramatically shape courtship success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Tomaszycki1">Tomaszycki and Adkins-Regan 2005</xref>). In the case of the <italic>chee-poo</italic>, we expect that call duration and <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub> similarly contain salient information that is relevant to social interactions, including the solicitation of female copulations. In particular, these features of the call may be honest indicators of male quality, given that they are guided by androgenic action, which is considered &ldquo;costly&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Ketterson1">Ketterson et al. 1992</xref>).Our results highlight that androgens are capable of modulating the song of a suboscine passerine. Most work investigating the effects of sex steroids on vocal performance have utilized oscine passerine birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Barker1">Barker et al. 2004</xref>). One of the main functional characteristics that distinguish these suborders is the inability of suboscine birds, including Golden-collared Manakins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Saldanha1">Saldanha et al. 2000</xref>), to learn songs during development and the lack of any defined song-control system in the brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma and Konishi 1991</xref>). In suboscines, it is likely that androgens act primarily on the midbrain nICO to drive the motor programming of call production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cohen1">Cohen 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-327-Cohen2">Cohen and Cheng 1982</xref>). It is also possible that suboscine birds rely on androgenic mediation of peripheral substrates as a means of sound control. Future work should more closely consider the contributions of peripheral and central androgenic action on avian vocal production, particularly in the suboscine avian suborder.We thank F. Goller for thought-provoking discussions of the data, as well as K. Longpre for assistance implanting birds. We thank M. Rensel for guidance with the statistical methods. Finally, we thank the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute (STRI) and its administrative staff for their assistance with this project, as well as Autoridad Nacional del Ambiente and the Autoridad del Canal de Panama for permission to conduct the studies. Animal Care and Use Committees at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), and STRI approved all the methods used. M.J.F. was supported in part by a National Institutes of Health Training Grant (T32 HD007228, awarded to the Laboratory of Neuroendocrinology at UCLA). A National Science Foundation grant (IOS-0646459, to B.A.S.) supported this research.