 Characteristics within and around stopover wetlands used by migratory shorebirds: Is the neighborhood important?  Ecological neighborhoods: Scaling environmental patterns  Zero-inflated model with application to spatial count data  Spatiotemporal scaling of North American continental interior wetlands: Implications for shorebird conservation  Broad-scale relationship between shorebirds and landscapes in the Southern Great Plains  Habitat use by migrant shorebirds in saline lakes of the Southern Great Plains  Grazing systems, ecosystem responses, and global change  Landscape context matters: Local habitat and landscape effects on the abundance and patch occupancy of collared lizards in managed grasslands  Is bird incidence in Atlantic forest influenced by landscape patterns at multiple scales?  Rural land-use trends in the coterminous United States, 1950&ndash;2000  A multi-scale examination of stopover habitat use by birds  Waterbird communities in managed wetlands of varying water depth  History of wetlands in the conterminous United States  Response of aquatic invertebrates to vegetation management and agriculture  Behavior of migrant shorebirds in the playas of the Southern High Plains  Ecology and management of migrant shorebirds in the Playa Lakes Region of Texas  Foraging strategies and niche dynamics of coexisting shorebirds at stopover sites in the Southern Great Plains  Behavior of migrating sandpipers at North Dakota prairie potholes  Scale-dependent habitat use by fall migratory birds: Vegetation structure, floristics, and geography  Estimating shorebird numbers at migration stopover sites  Effects of the broad scale on shorebird movements at spring migration stopovers  Ecological costs of livestock grazing in western North America  Ecological effects of ranching: A six-point critique  A multi-scale analysis of species-environment relationships: Breeding birds in pitch pine-scrub oak (  Pinus rigida - Quercus ilicifolia  ) communities  Zero-altered and other regression models for count data with added zeros  Habitat selection by nonbreeding, migratory land birds  Behavioral and physiological reactions to environmental variation in bird migration: A review  Prairie wetland complexes as landscape functional units in a changing climate  The importance of landscape context for songbirds on migration: Body mass is related to habitat cover  Zero-inflated Poisson regression with an application to defects in manufacturing  Ecological principles for the design of wildlife corridors  Zero tolerance ecology: Improving ecological inference by modeling the source of zero observations  The effects of habitat on vigilance of shorebirds: Is visibility important?  Small tidal channels improve foraging opportunities for  Calidris  shorebirds  Mechanisms of en route habitat selection: How do migrants make habitat decisions during stopover?  Habitat requirements during migration: Important link in conservation  Stopover ecology of intercontinental migrants: En route problems and consequences for reproductive performance  Use of wetlands by spring-migrant shorebirds in agricultural landscapes of North Dakota's Drift prairie  Mesonet  Oklahoma Comprehensive Wildlife Conservation Strategy  The spatial extent and relative influence of landscape-level factors on wintering bird populations  Dealing with overdispersed count data in applied ecology  Migration stopovers and the conservation of Arctic-breeding Calidridine sandpipers  Implications of different shorebird migration strategies for habitat conservation  On determining the significance of ephemeral continental wetlands to North American migratory shorebirds  Toward conservation of mid-continent shorebird migrations  Migrating shorebirds and habitat dynamics at a prairie wetland complex  Scale dependent effects of landscape context on three pollinator guilds  Waterbird responses to experimental drawdowns: Implications for the multispecies management of wetland mosaics  The influence of patch and within patch factors on species presence and abundance: A review of focal patch studies  Forecasting agriculturally driven global environmental change  Effects of local and landscape level variables on wetland habitat use during migration through the Rainwater Basin  Shorebird use of South Carolina managed and natural coastal wetlands  Spatial scaling in ecology  2000 years of drought variability in the central United States  Zero-inflated negative binomial mixed regression modeling of over-dispersed count data with extra zeros  Current address: Kansas Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, USA  Wetland stopover use by migratory shorebirds is concurrently influenced by habitat characteristics within a stopover site and characteristics related to the broader context surrounding the stopover site. To conserve wetland habitats essential for shorebird migration through the interior of North America, we need to understand how these dual scales influence stopover use. We surveyed &gt;14,000 wetlands within 10 broad-scale landscapes in north-central Oklahoma from 2007 through 2009 to determine how characteristics within (intra) and surrounding (context) wetlands influence the density and species richness of migrating shorebirds at stopover sites. We used zero-inflated modeling and an information theoretic framework to separately examine and then compare the relative importance of intra-habitat variables and habitat context variables in explaining use of stopovers. We observed 38,288 migratory shorebirds of 29 species. Shorebirds were least likely to occur in isolated, small, steep-sided wetland habitats. Among intra-patch variables, shorebird density and richness were best explained by wetland habitat area, slope, and the cover and height of vegetation within a wetland. Shorebird density and richness were more than 2 times higher in large wetland habitats (i.e. &gt;3.3 ha), and both decreased with increased vegetation and slope. The density of wetlands within 1.5 km of a stopover site had the greatest impact on shorebird density and richness among patch context variables. As habitat density increased from 0.07 to 1, shorebird abundance and richness increased by &gt;200&percnt;. Shorebirds were positively related to grazing pressure but negatively related to forest/shrubland, urban/suburban development, and grassland land cover contexts. When compared to models with intra-habitat variables, models containing habitat context variables better explained migratory shorebird density and richness. We conclude that characteristics related to the broader context surrounding a wetland stopover sites strongly influence stopover use by migratory shorebirds. Conservation and management of shorebirds migrating through the continental interior should aim to provide large expanses of sparsely vegetated and shallow habitats within stopover sites and focus on open landscapes that contain high densities of stopover habitats.  El uso de humedales como sitios de parada migratoria por parte de aves playeras se ve influenciado simult&aacute;neamente por las caracter&iacute;sticas del interior de un sitio de parada y las caracter&iacute;sticas relacionadas con el contexto m&aacute;s amplio que rodea al sitio de parada. Para conservar los humedales esenciales para la migraci&oacute;n de aves playeras a trav&eacute;s del interior de Norteam&eacute;rica necesitamos entender c&oacute;mo estas dos escalas influencian el uso de los sitios de parada. Hicimos censos en &gt;14000 humedales dentro de tres paisajes a gran escala en el centro-norte de Oklahoma entre 2007 y 2009 para determinar c&oacute;mo las caracter&iacute;sticas del interior (intra) y alrededor (contexto) de los humedales influyen en la densidad y riqueza de especies de las aves playeras en los sitios de parada migratoria. Usamos modelamiento con inflaci&oacute;n de ceros y un marco te&oacute;rico de teor&iacute;a de la informaci&oacute;n para examinar separadamente y luego comparar la importancia relativa de las variables del interior del h&aacute;bitat y del contexto al explicar el uso de los sitios de parada migratoria. Observamos 38288 aves playeras migratorias de 29 especies. Las aves playeras tuvieron menor probabilidad de estar en humedales aislados, peque&ntilde;os o con lados empinados. En cuanto a las variables intra h&aacute;bitat, la densidad y riqueza de aves playeras fueron mejor explicadas por el &aacute;rea del humedal, la pendiente y la cobertura y altura de la vegetaci&oacute;n dentro del humedal. La densidad y riqueza de aves playeras fue m&aacute;s de 2 veces m&aacute;s alta en humedales grandes (i.e., &lt;3.3 ha), y ambas disminuyeron con el incremento en la vegetaci&oacute;n y en la pendiente. La densidad de humedales en un radio de 1.5 km alrededor de un sitio de parada migratoria tuvo el mayor impacto en la densidad y riqueza de aves playeras entre las variables del contexto. A medida que la densidad de humedales aument&oacute; de 0.07 a 1, la abundancia y la riqueza de aves playeras se increment&oacute; en m&aacute;s de 200&percnt;. Las aves playeras se asociaron positivamente con la presi&oacute;n de pastoreo, pero negativamente con los desarrollos forestales y urbanos y con la cobertura de los pastizales. Al ser comparados con los modelos con variables intra-h&aacute;bitat, los modelos que inclu&iacute;an las variables del contexto explicaron mejor la densidad y riqueza de aves playeras migratorias. Concluimos que las caracter&iacute;sticas relacionadas con el contexto que rodea los humedales de parada migratoria influyen fuertemente en el uso de estos sitios por parte de las aves playeras migratorias. La conservaci&oacute;n y el manejo de las aves playeras que migran a trav&eacute;s del interior del continente deber&iacute;an apuntar a proveer grandes extensiones de h&aacute;bitats someros y con poca vegetaci&oacute;n dentro de los sitios de parada migratoria y enfocarse en paisajes abiertos que contengan altas densidades de humedales.   Palabras clave:  aves playeras, contexto del paisaje, Grandes Planicies del Sur, humedales de pradera, migraci&oacute;n, modelamiento con inflaci&oacute;n de ceros, uso de h&aacute;bitat  Understanding the factors that influence migrant shorebird use of wetland stopover sites in the Great Plains has important conservation implications for this group of birds ( Skagen and Knopf 1993 ,  Skagen 2006 ). For shorebird species reliant on wetland resources, large-scale land use change and loss of wetlands ( Dahl and Allord 1996 ,  Brown et al. 2005 ) combined with forecasts of further wetland loss and degradation ( Johnson et al. 2010 ), climate change ( IPCC 2007 ), and more intensive agricultural practices ( Tilman et al. 2001 ) have raised serious questions about the ability of these birds to maintain current migration patterns and population sizes ( Skagen 2006 ). Given the considerable physiological and environmental challenges that birds encounter during migration ( Moore et al. 1995 ,  2005 ), predictions of further unprecedented changes to the contemporary landscape of the Great Plains highlight the urgency to understand the current stopover-use patterns of migrant shorebirds. This information may prove critical to developing effective conservation strategies for these migratory birds.  Generally, shorebirds associated with wetland habitats during migration select wetland areas that are shallow, sparsely vegetated, and contain considerable mudflat ( Colwell 2010 ). For shorebirds migrating through the Great Plains, these intra-wetland characteristics have been shown to significantly influence their stopover use ( Davis and Smith 1998a ). Other studies of shorebirds in the region have examined the influence of both intra-wetland characteristics and landscape variables surrounding wetlands (i.e. patch context variables;  Niemuth et al. 2006 ,  Webb et al. 2010 ). Although a few studies have found relationships between patch context variables and the occurrence and abundance patterns of migrating shorebirds at a wetland stopover, patch context variables typically do not affect these patterns as strongly as intra-wetland characteristics ( Skagen et al. 2005 ,  Niemuth et al. 2006 ,  Webb et al. 2010 ).  Whether the presence or abundance of organisms is explained by characteristics at an immediate location or the area surrounding that location poses an interesting ecological question that is a major focus of ecological research ( Thorton et al. 2011 ) and presents important land management implications for many species ( Lindenmayer and Nix 1993 ,  Steffan-Dewenter et al. 2002 ,  Blevins and With 2011 ). Several studies have found that the occurrence and abundance patterns of some bird species during breeding and wintering periods respond more to the characteristics of the surrounding landscape than to local attributes ( Pearson 1993 ,  Grand and Cushman 2003 ,  Boscolo and Metzger 2009 ). Additionally, abundance and mass gain of migrant birds have been shown to increase with the amount of suitable habitat in the landscape surrounding stopover sites ( Buler et al. 2007 ,  Ktitorov et al. 2008 ,  Albanese and Davis 2013 ). Furthermore, empirical evidence suggests that initial stopover selection by migrant birds is based on the broad-scale composition of potential habitat ( Buler et al. 2007 ,  Albanese and Davis 2013 ), which may possibly preclude the use of some areas with suitable habitat at finer scales. Understanding the influence of broad-scale and fine-scale habitat characteristics is critical for development of conservation strategies for shorebirds migrating through the Great Plains.  The highly variable and often extreme weather patterns indicative of the Southern Great Plains cause stopover habitats used by migrant shorebirds to be dynamic and unpredictable in space and time ( Skagen and Knopf 1994 ,  Albanese et al. 2012 ). The presence of habitat conditions suitable for shorebird stopovers are erratic within wetlands, and the distribution of wetland sites that provide suitable stopover habitat are continuously shifting within the landscape. Shorebirds seem to have responded to these patterns by dispersing widely throughout the region during migration and relying on ephemeral habitats ( Skagen and Knopf 1993 ,  Skagen et al. 2008 ). To accommodate shifting distributions of wetland habitats and shorebirds within the region, studies of migratory shorebird stopover use need to be conducted over large geographic extents ( Skagen et al. 2005 ) and at scales appropriate to this wide-ranging life history stage ( Addicott et al. 1987 ,  Wiens 1989 ).  Count data from stopovers used by migrating shorebirds, especially those migrating through the interior of North America, can include a high proportion of sites with no birds because of the widespread, erratic, and shifting distribution of both shorebirds and suitable wetlands. Such datasets are referred to as zero-inflated because they contain more zero values than would be expected for distributions traditionally used to model count data (i.e. Poisson or negative binomial;  Lambert 1992 ,  Heilbron 1994 ). Zero-inflated count data frequently exhibit overdispersion when using a Poisson distribution for modeling because there is often more variability than allowed by the equality of mean and variance implicit to this model ( Yau et al. 2003 ). In the case of shorebird stopover use patterns, failure to account for zero inflation and overdispersion may result in biased parameter estimates and measures of uncertainty. At worst, this problem can lead to incorrect inference and inappropriate recommendations for shorebird conservation. Recently, zero-inflation modeling methods have been developed that are capable of addressing these problems ( Martin et al. 2005 ,  Zuur et al. 2009 ). Application of analytical approaches such as zero-inflated modeling should improve the robustness, certainty, and level of inference of analyses using shorebird count data.  We studied migrant shorebird richness and abundance patterns among thousands of wetland stopover sites in the Southern Great Plains. Specifically, we surveyed potential wetland stopover habitat patches for shorebirds during spring and fall migration periods among 10 broad-scale landscapes in north-central Oklahoma, USA. We determined the relative importance of intra-patch variables (i.e. variables measured within a focal wetland habitat patch) and patch context variables (i.e. variables measured in the land area surrounding a focal wetland habitat patch) in explaining migratory shorebird abundance and species richness patterns in wetland stopover habitats using multi-model inference in an information theoretic framework.  The 24,372 km 2  study area is located within the Southern Great Plains, covering 10 counties in north-central Oklahoma ( Figure 1 ). The region is characterized by flat topography dominated by large areas of intensively managed cropland and grassland with broadly dispersed suburban and urban development, remnant patches of mixed grass prairie, and small forest stands ( Oklahoma Department of Wildlife Conservation 2006 ,  Albanese and Davis 2013 ). A mixture of palustrine, riverine, and managed wetlands that contain hydroperiods ranging from ephemeral to ostensibly permanent occur in the region. Managed wetlands include large reservoirs and smaller wetlands constructed for waste treatment or water storage for irrigation and livestock watering. The region is subject to extreme dry and wet periods ( Woodhouse and Overpeck 1998 ); extended drought conditions can severely limit wetland habitat within landscapes, whereas severe weather events can rapidly inundate large areas.  Study area and landscapes in north-central Oklahoma, USA. The locations of study landscapes within the study area are given with an enlarged landscape illustrating the extent and distribution of the potential shorebird habitat patches surveyed.  Although some shorebird species breed within the region and some shorebird migrants may use uplands and wetlands as stopover habitat, we restricted our research to those species that migrate through the region and primarily rely on and were observed foraging within wetland habitat during migration. We defined wetland shorebird habitat as areas of saturated substrate and shallow water (water depth &lt;16 cm) within wetlands and adjacent to wetland edges ( Davis and Smith 1998a ). Non-habitats were considered areas that did not meet these criteria (i.e. dry upland areas).  We randomly established ten 10 km radius circular landscapes within the study region ( Figure 1 ). Landscapes of this size were used because &gt;90&percnt; of the known foraging flight distances of shorebirds during stopovers in the region were &lt;10 km ( Farmer and Parent 1997 ). We quantified the area of potential shorebird habitat within each landscape using 2 methods. Initially, we used ESRI's ArcGIS 9.0 (Environmental Systems Research Institute, Redlands, CA) GIS software to assemble 1.0 m resolution 1:12,000 digital ortho-image quarter quadrangles (DOQQs) from 2000, 2003&ndash;2006, and 2008. Although data varied among landscapes, below average precipitation and less wetland habitat characterized the 2004, 2005, and 2006 images, while above average precipitation and abundant wetland habitat characterized 2000, 2003, and 2008 images ( Oklahoma Climatological Survey 2011 ). Within each landscape, we visually examined the entire extent of each DOQQ within the annual series at a 1:10,000 scale. When a discrete patch of potential habitat was identified, we delineated the broadest contiguous extent of habitat among the annual series of DOQQs as a polygon. The area within these polygons formed potential habitat patches within landscapes ( Figure 1 ). Because of logistical constraints, we did not delineate discrete potential habitat patches &lt;1,000 m 2  or areas within channeled waterways &lt;30 m wide. In addition, field surveys of all landscapes and habitat patches used in the final analysis were conducted with 1 m 2  color ortho images to evaluate and revise habitat delineations. All additional habitat patches identified during surveys and any patch boundary refinements were continuously updated in the GIS.  Shorebird surveys were conducted from March through May in 2007, 2008, and 2009 and from July through October in 2007 and 2008. Previous research has suggested a maximum average residency period of 10.5 days for shorebirds during a stopover event within the Great Plains ( Skagen and Knopf 1994 ,  Farmer and Durbian 2006 ,  Skagen et al. 2008 ); therefore, we divided each spring and fall migration period into four 23-day survey intervals to ensure independence among our survey data. We surveyed 13 to 15&percnt; of the total area of potential habitat within each landscape for shorebirds once during each survey interval. For each landscape, we randomly (without replacement) selected a unique sample of potential habitat patches to survey during each survey interval.  Shorebird surveys were conducted during daylight hours from a vehicle or on foot, depending on the visibility or location of the patch. We waited 5 minutes before initiating a survey to limit any disturbance. Initially, we recorded the presence or absence of shorebird habitat within the patch. Habitat was considered absent if habitat patches were completely dry or if they were completely inundated with water &gt;16 cm in depth. If habitat was present, the patch was surveyed for shorebirds. Each patch &le;1 ha was surveyed for 5 minutes during a visit, and equal time was added for each additional hectare (see  Albanese 2011  for details). Shorebirds were observed with a 10 &times; 60 spotting scope or 8 &times; 40 binoculars. All shorebirds observed in a patch were identified and counted.  Habitat measurements were also collected at each patch during each shorebird survey. Measurements were grouped into 2 types: intra-patch and patch context ( Table 1 ). Intra-patch measurements were collected within a focal patch, and patch context measurements were collected from the area surrounding the focal patch. For variables that included cover estimates, a traditional cover-class scheme was used that included the following cover classes: 0&percnt;, 1&ndash;5&percnt;, 6&ndash;25&percnt;, 26&ndash;50&percnt;, 51&ndash;75&percnt;, 76&ndash;95&percnt;, and &gt;95&percnt; (e.g.,  Braun-Blanquet 1964 ,  Daubenmire 1968 ). Cover-class midpoints were used in the analysis. The patch context variable habitat density was estimated post hoc using field data and the GIS of potential shorebird habitat within landscapes. A kernel function was used to estimate the density of shorebird habitat surrounding each habitat patch during each survey interval. We incorporated probability estimates of the presence of different habitat types within each landscape during each survey interval into the kernel density function (see  Albanese et al. 2012  for details). Habitat density at a 1.5 km spatial scale was used in this analysis because this scale best described the observed occurrence patterns of shorebirds among landscapes ( Albanese et al. 2012 ).  Description of the intra-patch and patch context variables measured at wetland and adjacent habitat units surveyed in north-central Oklahoma, USA, 2007&ndash;2009.  An exploratory analysis of the dataset revealed a large proportion of zero values for shorebird density and species richness (84.2&percnt;) and overdispersion (&Oslash; &equals; &gt;2). To account for these issues, we used zero-inflated negative binomial models (ZINB;  Zurr et al. 2009 ) to separately relate shorebird density and richness within habitat patches to either intra-patch or patch context variables. Using this approach, counts of shorebirds and species within a habitat patch were modeled as a product of both migratory shorebird occurrence and shorebird density or richness. In ZINB, a zero-inflated logistic regression portion modeled the probability that shorebirds were absent from a habitat patch, and a negative binomial regression portion modeled the density and richness of shorebirds within habitat patches as well as the absence of shorebirds under certain covariate conditions.  Models of shorebird density and richness that contained either intra-patch or patch context variables were modeled separately using ZINB with maximum-likelihood estimation. Correlations among intra-habitat patch and among patch context explanatory variables were examined; no variables were strongly correlated ( r  &lt; 0.4). The explanatory variables shorebird habitat area (HAREA), vegetation cover and dominant height (VEG), shallow water and saturated substrate cover (WATMUD), and dominant slope (SLOPE) were included in both portions of the global intra-patch models, and the explanatory variables habitat density (HDENS), dominant land cover (LANCON), crop cultivation (CROP), and grazing pressure (GRAZE) were included in both portions of the global patch context models ( Table 1 ). Among the patch context variables, the variables LANCON and CROP were coded as nominal variables for the analysis (i.e. each level or state of a nominal variable was assigned a unique value, and these were compared in the analysis to the designated base state of the variable). For the multi-level LANCON variable, land cover types were contrasted against the wetland land cover type (mean &equals; 36.1). We used an information theoretic approach with multi-model inference to identify which models best explained observed patterns in the density and species richness of migratory shorebirds ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). The alternative models in each candidate set included all possible additive combinations of the variables in each portion of the global model and a null model set (R &equals; 625). Initially, we included observer, year, and season variables in each candidate set, but because these variables did not contribute to these models, we excluded them from the final analysis.  We used Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) to compare the relative ability of alternative models to explain observed patterns ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). We calculated the &Delta;AIC and the AIC weight of each model in the set to evaluate models and select the most parsimonious models among the candidate set. We considered all models with a &Delta;AIC &lt; 6 to have support, but only selected models when the AIC value for a model was less than the AIC values of all the simpler models within which they were nested ( Richards 2008 ). We validated the top model selected in each candidate model set by ensuring the lack of any pattern between plotted Pearson residuals against fitted values and each explanatory variable. We used AIC weights ( w i  ) to calculate model-averaged parameter estimates, summed Akaike weights, unconditional standard errors, and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CI) for each parameter estimate ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). To determine the direction and magnitude of effects sizes for explanatory variables, we calculated mean standardized parameter estimates. All analyses were conducted using R 2.12.1 (R Development Core Team, Vienna, Austria) and SAS 9.1 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC) software.  During the 5 migration periods of this study, we surveyed 14,444 potential shorebird habitat patches. Shorebird habitat was present in 8,337 of the patches at the time of a survey. The mean size (&plusmn;SD) of shorebird habitat patches was 0.56 ha &plusmn; 0.97, but the presence of shorebird habitat on the landscape was variable depending on climatic conditions prior to and during the migration period. Generally, shorebird habitat patches were predominantly covered with shallow water (mean &equals; 70&percnt; &plusmn; 0.25), sparsely covered (mean &equals; 26&percnt; &plusmn; 0.3) with short emergent vegetation (e.g., 44&percnt; of the patches contained vegetation &lt;0.5 m tall), and had a relatively flat profile (e.g., 72&percnt; of the patches contained slopes &lt;20&deg;). Shorebird habitat was most often embedded within grassland, pasture, and cropland land cover types (34&percnt;, 17&percnt;, and 15&percnt; of the patches, respectively), and 61&percnt; of the patches were surrounded by areas with active crop cultivation and or grazing.  Shorebirds were present in 15.8&percnt; of 8,337 potential habitat patches with habitat present at the time of a survey. We observed 38,288 migratory shorebirds that included 29 species ( Table 2 ). Of these, 22,571 shorebirds were observed during the 3 spring migration periods, and 15,717 shorebirds were observed during the 2 fall migration periods. The mean number (&plusmn;SD) of shorebirds present in a habitat patch at the time of a survey was 4.61 &plusmn; 36.20, and mean species richness was 2.15 &plusmn; 1.64 when shorebirds were present.  Range in the total number of each migratory shorebird species encountered among individual habitat patches during spring and fall migration periods in north-central Oklahoma, USA, 2007&ndash;2009. Shorebird habitat was defined as shallow water (&lt;16 cm) and saturated substrate within and surrounding wetlands.  Migratory shorebird density and richness responded similarly to intra-patch characteristics. The most parsimonious models to explain the density and richness of migratory shorebirds within habitat patches both contained the explanatory variables HAREA and SLOPE in the logistic regression portions and HAREA, VEG, and SLOPE in the count portions of the top model ( Table 3 ). These models were &gt;2 times more plausible than the next top models in each set. In the logistic regression portions of both models, the summed Akaike weights of the variables WATMUD and VEG were relatively low, and the 95&percnt; CI of the model-averaged parameter estimates for these variables included zero ( Figure 2 ), indicating that these variables were not well-supported predictors of migratory shorebird absence. Conversely, the variables HAREA and SLOPE were important predictors of shorebird absence and exhibited strong effects on the occurrence of migratory shorebirds. The probability of the absence of a migratory shorebird from a habitat patch was greatest (&gt;0.6) when values of HAREA were small (&lt;800 m 2 ). The probability of a shorebird absence was lowest (&lt;0.01) when values of HAREA were &ge;3,300 m 2  and values of the variable SLOPE were low (&lt;20&deg;).  Zero-inflated negative binomial regression model-selection results for shorebird density and species richness count data dependent on inter-patch or patch context variables in north-central Oklahoma, USA, 2007&ndash;2009. Variable codes are provided in  Table 1 . The AIC value and Akaike weight ( w i  ) for each top model among the shorebird density and shorebird richness candidate model sets are listed. Models with &Delta;AIC &lt; 6 are given for shorebird density model sets.  Relative effect size of intra-patch (top row) and patch context (middle row) explanatory variables (standardized model-averaged coefficients, mean &plusmn; SE) on the absence and density (black bars) or richness (white bars) of migratory shorebirds within shorebird habitat patches in north-central Oklahoma, USA, 2007&ndash;2009. The relative importance of each explanatory variable is given above each bar. Bars with lines indicate model-averaged parameter estimates with 95&percnt; confidence intervals that did not include zero. The abbreviation codes and description of each explanatory variable are given in  Table 1 . (bottom row) The relative effect size of each land cover type in the dominant land cover explanatory variable on the density or richness of migratory shorebirds within shorebird habitat patches. This variable was an important predictor in the negative binomial count portion of the patch context models and was analyzed as a nominal variable with land cover types contrasted against the wetland land cover type.  The explanatory variables HAREA, VEG, and SLOPE were included in the count portion of the models in the &ldquo;best model&rdquo; sets of shorebird density and richness ( Table 3 ). Those variables were also well supported as important predictors of both shorebird density and richness ( Figure 2 ). The top model explaining shorebird density also included the variable WATMUD, but confidence limits included zero. In the top model explaining the variation in shorebird density, density increased with HAREA (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.74 &plusmn; 0.04) and decreased as VEG (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;1.62 &plusmn; 0.07) and SLOPE (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.9 &plusmn; 0.15) increased ( Table 3 ). The beta coefficients in the top model of species richness indicated that richness was also positively related to increased HAREA (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.39 &plusmn; 0.03) and negatively related to increased VEG (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.47 &plusmn; 0.04) and SLOPE (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.17 &plusmn; 0.06). VEG had the greatest relative effect on shorebird density and richness among explanatory variables; however, the effect of these variables was consistently greater on shorebird density than species richness ( Figure 2 ).  Migratory shorebird density and species richness also responded comparably to patch context characteristics. The most parsimonious models to explain density and richness of migratory shorebirds within a habitat patch using patch context variables only included the explanatory variable HDENS in the logistic regression portion of the model ( Table 3 ). The probability of absence of migratory shorebirds from a habitat patch was greatest when HDENS was low (&lt;0.07;  Figure 2 ).  The variables HDENS, LANCO, and GRAZE were well supported predictors in the count portion of the top models of migratory shorebird density and richness. Among context variables, only the relative effect of HDENS was greater on species richness than on shorebird density ( Figure 2 ). Shorebird richness was most strongly influenced by HDENS (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 4.93 &plusmn; 0.48) and was higher with greater HDENS and GRAZE (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.12 &plusmn; 0.04). Similarly, shorebird density was also positively related to increased HDENS (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.71 &plusmn; 0.08) and GRAZE (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.29 &plusmn; 0.08). For the nominal variable LANCON, the forest/shrubland, grassland, and developed land cover types were negatively related to shorebird density and richness when compared to the wetland land cover type, while cropland, barren, and pastureland had no effect ( Figure 2 ).  For both migratory shorebird density and richness, the AIC value of the top model selected from the candidate model set that included patch context variables was lower than the top model selected from the candidate model set that included intra-patch variables ( Table 3 ). These results suggest that given the data and candidate model sets, the top models containing patch context variables were better models of migratory shorebird density and richness than the top models containing intra-patch variables.  Our analysis of wetland stopover use by migratory shorebirds within the Southern Great Plains revealed that shorebird density and richness increased with habitat area and declined with greater vegetation structure and slope within wetland habitats. Additionally, small habitat areas and habitats dominated by steep slope angles were identified as sources of zero inflation among intra-patch variables. Previous studies have also reported a positive association between shorebird habitat area and migratory shorebird occurrence and abundance within wetlands ( Taft et al. 2002 ,  Skagen et al. 2005 ,  Webb et al. 2010 ); however, we are unaware of any studies that have examined the influence of slope on wetland stopover use by migratory shorebirds. A possible explanation for the negative association of migratory shorebirds with slope may be that wetland habitats dominated by steep slope angles were often characterized by an invariant water depth profile, which may limit shorebird habitat along shorelines. Greater topographic variation within a wetland broadens the diversity of foraging depths available to shorebirds and increases shorebird diversity and abundance within wetlands ( Colwell and Taft 2000 ,  Taft et al. 2002 ). Additionally, although feeding is the primary behavior exhibited by shorebirds during stopovers in the Great Plains ( Davis and Smith 1998b ,  DeLeon and Smith 1999 ), shorebirds increase the amount of time engaged in vigilance behaviors when foraging in habitats that are visually obstructed ( Metcalfe 1984 ). Consequently, shorebirds may not use steep-sided wetlands because of a greater risk of predation. Moreover, the increased vigilance may come at the expense of time spent feeding.  In our study, greater vegetation structure seemed to restrict species richness and number of shorebirds within wetland habitat. Several other studies within the Great Plains have reported a negative relationship between increased vegetation structure within a wetland and use by migrating shorebirds ( Weber and Haig 1996 ,  Davis and Smith 1998a ,  Niemuth et al. 2006 ). Specifically, Farmer and Durbain (2006) found that attributes related to vegetation structure decreased the probability of shorebird detection within a wetland. Among our sites, 13.6&percnt; of the area surveyed with habitat present contained characteristics related to vegetation structure (&gt;5&percnt; vegetation cover and vegetation height &gt;0.5 m;  Albanese 2011 ) similar to those characteristics found to depress the detection of migrant shorebirds in their study. However, the ZINB model used to analyze our data was designed to account for false negatives in both occurrence and count data caused by detection errors ( Zurr et al. 2009 ). While we suspect any negative bias in our data is minimal, we encourage some caution when interpreting our results; some bias may exist within our data among sites with increased vegetation structure because those sites are more likely to have undetected birds. Additionally, we suggest further examination on how vegetation may differentially influence the abundance and detection of shorebirds within wetlands in other parts of the midcontinental interior of North America.  Our results suggest that the amount of shallow water and saturated substrate within shorebird habitat was a poor predictor of shorebird density and species richness. While other studies have demonstrated the potential importance of available mudflat and shallow water to stopover use by migrating shorebirds ( Davis and Smith 1998a ), we suggest that we failed to find a relationship because we included many different shorebird species in our analysis. The overall shorebird community may respond less to differences in water depth and mud exposure than individual species because shorebird species have different niches along a water depth continuum ( Davis and Smith 2001 ).  We found that wetland stopovers in low habitat density conditions were the source of zero inflation among the patch context variables. Habitat density (suitable habitat within 1.5 km) was an important predictor of shorebird density and richness within wetland stopover sites. Other studies examining stopover-use patterns of shorebirds migrating through the Great Plains have also reported a positive relationship between wetland area in the surrounding landscape and shorebird distribution patterns within wetlands ( Skagen et al. 2005 ,  Niemuth et al. 2006 ,  Webb et al. 2010 ). These findings further support the idea that initial stopover selection by migrant birds may be made using broad-scale assessments of potential habitat composition ( Jenni and Schaub 2003 ,  Buler et al. 2007 ,  Albanese and Davis 2013 ). As a result, choice of low density wetland habitat patches may occur infrequently. Given the substantial spatiotemporal variation in the distribution of wetland resources in the Southern Great Plains, migrating shorebirds may use broad-scale habitat density as a coarse-level cue for initial stopover selection. This simple, opportunistic strategy minimizes both the risk of not locating any suitable resources and the energetic costs associated with locating suitable resources among wetlands once a stopover site is selected.  Grazing pressure in the area surrounding a wetland habitat patch was also an important predictor of shorebird density and richness. We offer several explanations for this positive association. First, within the Great Plains, grazing has been shown to increase the biomass of some wetland invertebrate taxa. In Rainwater Basin wetlands in Nebraska, grazed wetlands enhanced invertebrate diversity when compared to unmanaged wetlands and wetlands managed with other common methods such as disking and mowing ( Davis and Bidwell 2008 ). Abundant and diverse invertebrate prey resources associated with grazing may positively affect the use of these wetland habitats by migrant shorebirds because aquatic invertebrate abundance has been shown to influence shorebird use of wetlands ( Davis and Smith 1998a ,  Andrei et al. 2008 ). Second, grazing decreases plant biomass and can create a mosaic of open and vegetated patches within and around wetlands that may be attractive to shorebirds. Wetlands with an interspersion of open and/or sparsely vegetated areas have been associated with increased use by migratory shorebirds ( Davis and Smith 1998a ,  Webb et al. 2010 ). Last, shorebirds were often observed foraging among livestock within wetlands and along shorelines during this study.  We hypothesize that the movements of livestock may increase the exposure of aquatic invertebrates to foraging shorebirds. Specifically, livestock foot traffic may suspend benthic invertebrates in the water column making them more accessible for gleaning shorebirds. Additionally, livestock foot traffic may also enhance sediment penetrability for shorebirds that rely on pecking and probing techniques to capture benthic invertebrates. A study of shorebirds using a stopover site along the Coquille River Estuary in Oregon suggests that  Calidris  shorebirds, which rely on pecking and probing techniques, preferentially foraged along channels because the sediment was easier to probe ( Miller and de Rivera 2014 ). We recommend further investigation into the relationship between stopover use by migratory shorebirds and grazing of wetlands within the Southern Great Plains. However, we also recognize potential negative impacts of grazing on water quality and the wetland community ( Fleischner 1994 ,  Freilich et al. 2003 ,  Asner et al. 2004 ).  When compared to shorebird habitat in a wetland context, several land cover types were negatively associated with shorebird density and richness. Developed and forest/shrubland cover exhibited the strongest negative effects to migratory shorebird abundance and richness. We also found a negative relationship between the abundance and richness of shorebirds and habitat patches in a grassland context. We suggest that the negative influence of these land cover types on shorebirds may be attributed to a preference by many shorebird species for open habitats with minimal visual obstruction ( Metcalfe 1984 ,  DeLeon and Smith 1999 ,  Colwell 2010 ). The land cover contexts negatively associated with shorebird density and richness were frequently characterized by less open conditions. Developed lands often contained relatively tall man-made structures, forest and shrubland contained tall woody vegetation (&gt;2.5 m), and grassland (in the absence of disturbance) contained aboveground vegetation cover throughout the year that was often characterized by tall glades of grass. Conversely, pasture, barren, and cropland land cover types encompassed shorebird habitat patches in open conditions comparable to those present in a wetland context. Pastures often experienced intense livestock grazing and frequent vegetation removal for livestock forage. Barrens predominantly lacked vegetation cover. The dominant crop within the study area was winter wheat (  Triticum   sp.), which is low in stature during much of the spring migration period. Winter wheat fields are also typically tilled in late summer, which provides an open habitat during the fall migration period.  Results from other studies examining the response of migrant shorebirds within the midcontinental interior of North America to the land cover context of wetlands have been equivocal ( Skagen et al. 2005 ,  Webb et al. 2010 ). However, these studies measured the area of cropland and grassland within buffers ranging from 1 to 10 km, and the amount of land cover within these buffers may not have reflected the dominant land cover type immediately adjacent to the focal wetlands. Our results suggest that shorebirds may respond to the land context of a wetland stopover at finer scales that are more proximal to the focal patch than previously considered. Thus, to fully understand these patterns we recommend that future research consider the full range of scales at which land cover context may influence wetland stopover site selection and use by migratory shorebirds.  To conserve wetland stopover sites essential for shorebirds to successfully complete migration through the Great Plains of North America, it is first necessary to have a clear understanding of the basic habitat requirements of these species during this period. Our study identified habitat context variables, when compared to within habitat characteristics, as important if not superior predictors of migratory shorebird density and richness within wetland stopover sites. Our results highlight the need for further investigations into the potential role of landscape context variables in explaining en route shorebird occurrence and abundance patterns. Furthermore, we encourage the use of zero-inflated modeling to explicate the abundance patterns of these migrants from count data containing many zero values.  With this modeling approach, we were able to explain the en route abundance and richness patterns of migrant shorebirds and make strong inference on the importance of different wetland stopover site characteristics. Additionally, we identified several sources of zero inflation that, when considered, may enable more efficient monitoring and research techniques and better facilitate conservation efforts for these species. For example, several studies have suggested that broad-scale characteristics are used as initial stopover site selection cues ( Hutto 1985 ,  Moore and Aborn 2000 ,  Deppe and Rotenberry 2008 ). Small and discrete wetland habitats may be below the spatial threshold used for initial selection, and these habitats may remain consistently unused even if all other habitat attributes are suitable as a stopover site for shorebirds. Thus, these wetland habitats may be of limited value to shorebird conservation and monitoring programs with restricted resources.  Conservation and management of migratory shorebirds in this region should aim to provide wetland stopover sites with large expanses of saturated and shallow water habitat that is sparsely vegetated and shallowly sloped. These stopover sites should be in areas with the potential to provide high-density habitat at a 1.5 km scale, imbedded in an open land cover context. In addition, our results suggest grazing could be a potential management technique for enhancing wetlands as stopover sites for shorebirds. Because our analysis included a wide range of the shorebird species that migrate through the region, these management recommendations should be generally applicable and benefit diverse shorebird assemblages. We recommend that comparable research be conducted in other portions of the Great Plains to aid in the refinement of these conservation recommendations.  S. D. Fuhlendorf, B. Luttbeg, S. K. Skagen, P. D. Vickery, and D. A. Haukos provided valuable reviews that greatly improved this manuscript. We would also like to thank the thousands of private landowners for access to their properties. We thank field assistants R. Torres-Cervantes, L.W. Elmore, and A. Nealis, and we especially thank S. D. Albanese, S. K. Albanese, K. Andersson, and S. Sullivan for their tireless dedication.   Funding statement:  This study was funded by an Oklahoma Department of Wildlife Conservation State Wildlife Grant administered through the Oklahoma Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit. We gratefully acknowledge additional support provided by Department of Natural Resource Ecology and Management at Oklahoma State University, Great Plains Landscape Conservation Cooperative, U.S. Geological Survey, and U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service.   Ethics statement:  We followed approved, standard protocols for surveying shorebirds and did not affect shorebirds during surveys. 