 Carotenoid coloration predicts escape performance in the House Finch ( Haemorhous mexicanus )  Male plumage coloration affects dominance and aggression in female house finches  Sexual selection in the Zebra Finch   Taeniopygia guttata  : Condition, sex traits and immune capacity  Effects of carotenoid supply on escape flight responses in zebra finches,   Taeniopygia guttata    Developing an evolutionary ecology of fear: How life history and natural history traits affect disturbance tolerance in birds  Avian pigmentation  Flocking is an effective anti-predation strategy in redshanks,   Tringa totanus    Age- and sex-related morphological and physiological differences influence escape capacity in House Sparrows (  Passer domesticus  )  Metabolism, nutrition, and function of carotenoids  Multimodel inference in ecology and evolution: Challenges and solutions  Geometry for the selfish herd  Are carotenoids a red herring in sexual display?  Female house finches prefer colourful males: Sexual selection for a condition-dependent trait  Plumage coloration is a sexually selected indicator of male quality  Proximate basis of variation in carotenoid pigmentation in male House Finches  House Finch (  Carpodacus mexicanus  )  An easy, inexpensive method to quantify plumage coloration  Mate choice, male quality, and carotenoid-based plumage coloration  Carotenoid-based plumage coloration predicts resistance to a novel parasite in the house finch  The vitamin A&ndash;redox hypothesis: A biochemical basis for honest signaling via carotenoid pigmentation  Influence of dietary carotenoids on plasma and plumage colour in the house finch: Intra- and intersexual variation  Sexual selection on locomotor performance  Faster lizards sire more offspring: Sexual selection on whole-animal performance  How does selection operate on whole-organism functional performance capacities? A review and synthesis  Is carotenoid ornamentation linked to the inner mitochondria membrane potential? A hypothesis for the maintenance of signal honesty  Endurance in exercise is associated with courtship call rate in decorated crickets,  Gryllodes sigillatus   The relationship between physical condition and social status in pupfish   Cyprinodon pecosensis    Horn size predicts physical performance in the beetle  Euoniticellus intermedius  (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae)  Sexy birds are superior at solving a foraging problem  The capacity to escape from predators in   Passer domesticus  : An experimental study  The relationship between male ornamentation and swimming performance in the guppy,   Poecilia reticulata    Structure of social networks in a passerine bird: Consequences for sexual selection and the evolution of mating strategies  Costly sexual signals: Are carotenoids rare, risky or required?  Interspecific variation in the use of carotenoid-based coloration in birds: Diet, life history and phylogeny  Dietary antioxidants and exercise  Sex-specific nest defense in house sparrows (  Passer domesticus  ) varies with badge size of males  Individual variation in behavioural plasticity: Direct and indirect effects of boldness, exploration and sociability on habituation to predators in lizards  Sexual selection, growth compensation and fast-start swimming performance in Green Swordtails,   Xiphophorus helleri    Stress responsiveness, age and body condition interactively affect flight initiation distance in breeding female eiders  What does carotenoid-dependent coloration tell? Plasma carotenoid level signals immunocompetence and oxidative stress state in birds&mdash;A meta-analysis  Carotenoid-based signals in behavioural ecology: A review  Agonistic behavior in the House Finch. Part I: Annual cycle and display patterns  Antipredator strategies of house finches: Are urban habitats safe spots from predators even when humans are around?  Does dewlap size predict male bite performance in Jamaican  Anolis  lizards?  Current address: Department of Animal Ecology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden  Carotenoid coloration has been repeatedly shown to serve as a sexually selected signal of individual quality. Across different species, individuals showing brighter carotenoid-based signals have been found to have superior foraging abilities, to recover faster from diseases and, in general, to enjoy a better body condition. Experiments with birds have also shown that carotenoid supplementation can enhance flight performance, allowing birds to take off faster from the ground. Healthy, agile individuals should be better prepared to avoid predators, so it could be expected that individuals displaying brighter carotenoid-based coloration would show a higher escape ability from predator attacks. To test this prediction, we measured the escape ability of male House Finches ( Haemorhous mexicanus ) from a human with a net in a large aviary and related the escape ability of each individual to its breast coloration. Males with redder feathers showed a higher individual ability to escape than duller individuals. The superior flight performance of redder birds would be an important asset in escape from predators, as well as when foraging or maintaining a territory. In the specific case of the House Finch, the higher escape ability of redder individuals could be the reason for their higher overwinter survival rate.  Se ha demostrado que las coloraciones basadas en carotenoides funcionan como una se&ntilde;al sexual de calidad individual. En diversas especies, se ha visto que los individuos que muestran una coloraci&oacute;n basada en carotenoides m&aacute;s brillante muestran mejores habilidades a la hora de forrajear, se recuperan antes de enfermedades y, en general, disfrutan de una mejor condici&oacute;n f&iacute;sica. Tambi&eacute;n se ha podido constatar experimentalmente que una suplementaci&oacute;n de carotenoides en la dieta produc&iacute;a mejoras en el vuelo de las aves, al ser capaces &eacute;stas de despegar m&aacute;s r&aacute;pido del suelo. Un individuo m&aacute;s &aacute;gil y de mejor salud deber&iacute;a estar potencialmente mejor preparado para escapar de predadores, de modo que podr&iacute;a esperarse que individuos que muestran una coloraci&oacute;n basada en carotenoides m&aacute;s brillante deber&iacute;an ser mejores escapando del ataque de un predador. Para probar esta predicci&oacute;n, medimos la habilidad de escape de machos de  Haemorhous mexicanus , al ser perseguidos por un humano con una red en un aviario, y relacionamos la capacidad de escape de cada individuo con la coloraci&oacute;n del plumaje del pecho. Los machos de plumas m&aacute;s rojas mostraron una mayor capacidad individual de escape. Esta mejor capacidad de vuelo podr&iacute;a no s&oacute;lo ser una valiosa habilidad contra predadores, sino tambi&eacute;n podr&iacute;a ofrecer importantes ventajas a la hora de forrajear o mantener un territorio. En el caso espec&iacute;fico del  Haemorhous mexicanus , esta mayor capacidad de escape podr&iacute;a ser la causa de la mayor supervivencia invernal de los individuos de plumas m&aacute;s rojas.   Palabras clave: Haemorhous mexicanus , condici&oacute;n, capacidad aer&oacute;bica, selecci&oacute;n sexual, depredaci&oacute;n, capacidad de escape  Locomotor performance is a key component of survival for many species of animals. Moreover, because courtship behavior, competition for females, or the maintenance of a territory are often determined by locomotor performance, sexual selection can play a role in shaping locomotor evolution ( Husak et al. 2006 ,  Husak &amp; Fox 2008 ). Secondary sexual traits can evolve to signal whole-organism performance abilities, and such traits can function in male&ndash;male competition, e.g., the horn of the beetle  Euoniticellus intermediu  ( Vanhooydonck et al. 2005 ) or the dewlap of several  Anolis  lizards ( Lailvaux et al. 2005 ). Prospective females could also benefit from assessing and selecting on ornamental traits that signal, for instance, a higher endurance, a greater aerobic capacity, or a better locomotor performance ( Irschick et al. 2008 ). For example, courtship call rate is related to endurance during exercise in the decorated cricket  Gryllodes sigillatus  ( Ketola et al. 2009 ) and swimming performance is associated with the blue nuptial coloration of male Pecos pupfish   Cyprinodon pecosensis   ( Kodric-Brown &amp; Nicoletto 1993 ), with the size of the sword of male green swordtails   Xiphophorus helleri   ( Royle et al. 2006 ), and with the carotenoid coloration of male guppies   Poecilia reticulata   ( Nicoletto 1991 ).  Carotenoid pigments are the basis of many ornamental displays of animals ( Olson and Owens 2005 ). These pigments cannot be synthesized de novo by animals but must be ingested ( Brush 1978 ). Therefore, carotenoid coloration depends on the quantity and/or quality of the food ( Goodwin 1986 ) and on the physiological ability of individuals to process carotenoids ( Olson &amp; Owens 1998 ). Consequently, carotenoid coloration has been considered as a signal of nutritional status, foraging ability, and general condition of the individual ( Hill 1999 ,  Hill and McGraw 2006 ). There is experimental evidence of positive effects of carotenoids in many aspects of animal health ( Svensson and Wong 2011 ). For instance, carotenoids have been related to cognitive function ( Mateos-Gonzalez et al. 2011 ), disease recovery ( Hill and Farmer 2005 ), immunocompetence, and prevention of oxidative damage ( Powers and Deruisseau 2004 ,  Simons et al. 2012 , but see  Hartley and Kennedy 2004 ). According to a recent hypothesis, the aerobic capacity of an individual could be also related to its carotenoid coloration, given that the metabolism of carotenoid pigments in the production of ornamental coloration is intimately linked to cellular respiration ( Hill and Johnson 2012 ,  Johnson and Hill 2013 ).  These beneficial effects of carotenoids have a joint potential to influence important whole-animal performance abilities such as locomotor performance. In fact,  Blount and Matheson (2006)  observed that carotenoid supplementation enhanced takeoff performance in Zebra Finches   Taeniopygia guttata  . These results agreed with previous experiments in which  Birkhead et al. (1998)  observed that Zebra Finches whose carotenoid-based red beaks were redder evaded capture better than those with duller beaks. It could be expected that birds with brighter carotenoid-based plumage would show better escape abilities.  Male House Finches ( Haemorhous mexicanus ) have carotenoid-based plumage that varies from pale yellow to bright red, which they acquire after a complete prebasic molt in the late summer/early fall ( Hill 1992 ). This coloration reflects the nutritional condition of its bearer ( Hill et al. 1994 ), and several experiments have demonstrated that it is used as a primary criterion in female mate choice ( Hill 1990 ,  1991 ). In this study, we tested the prediction that male House Finches showing redder carotenoid-based breast plumage would show greater evasion abilities. To do so, we simulated aerial predator attacks by pursuing birds in an enclosure with a hand net. We then related the escape ability of each individual to its plumage coloration.  During January 10&ndash;24, 2011, 16 male House Finches were captured on the campus of Auburn University, Auburn, Alabama, USA, in traps baited with seed. The hue of breast feathers was assessed by visually comparing feather color to plates in  Kornerup and Wanscher (1983) , which is a repeatable method of determining feather hue ( Hill 1998 ). Feather hue is correlated to carotenoid availability in this and many other species ( Hill et al. 1994 ,  Simons et al. 2012 ). Birds were measured for wing, tail, and tarsus length, given a metal leg band with a unique number, and transported 2 km to an outdoor aviary (3 m wide &times; 2.5 m high &times; 3.8 m long). Birds were maintained on a diet of mixed seeds and water. Experiments started in June 2011.  House Finches are highly social birds that form flocks outside the breeding season ( Hill 1993 ). In previous studies ( Moreno-Rueda 2003 ,  De Neve et al. 2010 ), the escape ability of birds was examined by observing the rank order in which birds of a captive flock are captured by a researcher. This method takes into account the flocking behavior that has evolved in many bird species in response to predation pressures, a behavior that can reduce the chances of predation by increasing confusion and dilution effects ( Hamilton 1971 ,  Cresswell 1994 ). However, flock dynamics and accidental interference among birds can mask individual abilities. To determine the escape performance of our experimental birds, we obtained two kinds of measurements: capture rank order from an experimental flock of 16 male House Finches and individual capture time in isolation of these same birds.  Capture rank order was estimated by placing all birds in a common enclosure (3 m wide &times; 2.5 m high &times; 3.8 m long). Following the protocol described in  De Neve et al. (2010) , FMG entered the room with a 30-cm&ndash;diameter butterfly net and positioned himself in the middle of the enclosure. Birds immediately reacted to this action as they would in front of a real predator: flying away as far as possible from the threat. As space and perches were limited, some birds would end up being in more exposed spots, at the edges of the flock. In that moment, the experimenter attempted to capture one bird from the flock, aiming for the closest or easiest individual. To capture each bird, FMG tried to position the net over the individual when it was perched. If that individual managed to evade the net, the experimenter would not continue chasing the same individual, and would pursue instead another bird within reach, doing so until a bird was captured. Flight initiation distance (FID), that is the distance at which an animal takes off from a potential predator, is used as a proxy for boldness ( Blumstein 2006 ,  Rodr&iacute;guez-Prieto et al. 2011 ,  Seltmann et al. 2012 ), so individual differences in fear/boldness could potentially determine the distance at which a bird is perched from the predator in this setup. However, given the length of the enclosure (3.8 m), the experimenter was at all times at a closer distance than usual FIDs for House Finches (e.g., figure 2 in  Valcarcel and Fern&aacute;ndez-Juricic 2009 ); this factor created constant movement and escape interferences among birds, which makes very unlikely that boldness could have an effect on which birds were closer to the experimenter at any given time.  Upon capture, each bird was confined in a transport cage within the enclosure and its band number and capture order were noted. Using this procedure, FMG captured 6 individuals in a row and relocated them in individual enclosures (1.5 m wide &times; 2.5 m high &times; 3.8 m long). After a 60-min rest, he performed another capture shift in the common enclosure, capturing 6 more individuals from the main flock, relocating them in individual enclosures. The last 4 birds of the flock were captured in a third capture shift after 90 min, a slightly longer rest to compensate for the fact that they had already been chased twice before. Each capture shift lasted no more than 25 min.  To estimate individual capture time, tests were run in the individual enclosures. FMG entered each individual enclosure, positioned himself in the middle, and proceeded to capture each individual with the same sweep net from the previous test. In the same manner, the experimenter tried to position the net over the bird as soon as it perched. Capture, in every case, took place when the perched bird failed to take off before the sweep net was over it. FMG had already ample experience in the use of a sweep net, so his capture performance was not likely to improve or decrease over the course of the experiment. Despite being less realistic than a setup with a real predator, this method avoided ethical problems and provided more control over the &ldquo;predator&rdquo; motivation. The effort needed to capture a bird in a small enclosure is almost negligible, so it was possible to chase the bird without pause, from the start of the attempt until the bird was finally captured. This approach ensured a relatively standardized effort, which helped to control involuntary biases. Total capturing time for each individual was measured using a stopwatch, and ranged from 22 s to 290 s. After each capture, birds were relocated to a common enclosure. No bird was injured as a result of the experiment.  We used an information-theoretic approach following  Grueber et al. (2011) . Two global models, including all measured variables, were defined to generate model sets for each of the two experiments. Both the relationship between capture rank order and color score, and the relationship between individual capture time (log-transformed to meet normality) and color score were fitted in two multiple regressions ( glm  in R, family &equals;  gaussian ). There was no significant correlation between tarsus, wing, and tail lengths (Pearson's product-moment correlation; wing&ndash;tail:  P  &gt; 05,  r  &equals; 0.17; wing&ndash;tarsus:  P  &gt; 0.1,  r  &equals; 0.38; tail&ndash;tarsus:  P  &gt; 0.5,  r  &equals; 0.16), so they were included as covariates in both global models as they might affect takeoff and flight ability. Diagnostic plots were inspected to ensure normality of residuals in both models.  We standardized the input variables of these two global models using the  standardize  function in the  arm  package in R ( Gelman et al. 2013 ). This package includes tools for data analysis using regression and multilevel/hierarchical models. The  standardize  function standardizes regression predictors by centering and dividing by 2 SD.  Then we generated model sets for each analysis, including null models, using the function  dredge  in the  MuMIn  package ( Barto&nacute; and Barto&nacute; 2013 ). From the full model sets we selected &ldquo;top model sets&rdquo; using a 95&percnt; confidence threshold. Finally, we computed the model-averaged parameters, using the function  model.avg  in  MuMIn  package ( Barto&nacute; and Barto&nacute; 2013 ). All statistical analyses were conducted in R 3.0.0 ( R Development Core Team 2013 ).  Capture rank order and individual capture time in isolation were moderately correlated measures (Pearson's product-moment correlation:  n  &equals; 16,  r  &equals; 0.53,  P  &equals; 0.034; Spearman's rank correlation:  n  &equals; 16,  r s   &equals; 0.49,  P  &equals; 0.055). An ANCOVA, with experiment (individual capture time or capture order) as grouping factor, color score as dependent variable, and standardized time/order as independent variable, showed that the interaction between experiment and color score was not significant ( P  &lt; 0.5). This result indicates that the standardized slopes of color score on capture rank order (&beta; &equals; 0.357 &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.32) and color score on individual capture time (&beta; &equals; 0.674 &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.286) did not differ significantly.  There was no significant effect of coloration, tarsus length, wing length, or tail length in the capture order of male House Finches ( Table 1 ). The highest-ranking model could not be distinguished from the null model, given that the difference in corrected Akaike Information Criterion (AIC c ) was less than 2. The model-averaged parameter estimate for all the variables overlapped zero ( Table 2 ), so there is little evidence that any of these explanatory variables affected capture order.  Top models for capture order, resulted from the model average after selection of a 95&percnt; confidence model set. Models in the set are arranged from best to worst based on the difference in AIC c  values between the best model and competing models (&Delta;AIC c ). AIC weights (AIC w ) are the relative likelihoods of a model given the data, and evidence ratios (ER) are the relative likelihood of each model versus the best model.  Standardized coefficients of model predictors, after model averaging of the top candidate models (95&percnt; confidence) (see  Table 1 ). Table includes estimates, relative importance (&Sigma;, sum of Akaike weights of the models in which the predictor was present), unconditional SE, and 95&percnt; confidence interval (CI) for estimates. Parameter estimates have a significant effect when the 95&percnt; CIs do not include zero.  Top models for individual capture time, resulting from the model average after selection of a 95&percnt; confidence model set. Models in the set are arranged from best to worst based on the difference in AIC c  values between the best model and competing models (&Delta;AIC c ). AIC weights (AIC w ) are the relative likelihoods of a model given the data, and evidence ratios (ER) are the relative likelihood of each model versus the best model.  However, birds with higher color scores took longer to capture in the individual enclosures than birds with duller colors ( Figure 1 ). The highest-ranking model (Table&thinsp;3) included only color score. The difference in AIC c  between the best model and the alternative models was larger than 2, indicating that they can be discriminated. The model-averaged parameter estimate for color score did not overlap zero ( Table 4 ), indicating a significant effect of this variable on capture time.  Relationship between color score of the different individuals and time required to capture each one (log transformed). The line represents the regression slope.  Standardized coefficients of model predictors, after model averaging of the top candidate models (95&percnt; confidence) (see  Table 3 ). Table includes estimates, relative importance (&Sigma;, sum of Akaike weights of the models in which the predictor was present), unconditional SE, and 95&percnt; confidence interval (CI) for estimates. Parameter estimates have a significant effect when the 95&percnt; CIs do not include zero (highlighted in bold).  As predicted by the hypothesis that red carotenoid coloration is a condition-dependent signal of individual quality ( Hill 1990 ), we observed that male House Finches with redder plumage coloration were harder to capture with a sweep net than birds with duller colors.  In contrast to the significant relationship between individual escape performance and coloration, we found no significant relationship between capture rank and feather color, despite both measures being moderately correlated. We speculate that the lack of relationship between rank order of capture of House Finches and their feather color stems from the interference among flock members that obscures individual ability. When 16 House Finches are being chased in a cage, they frequently crowd onto perches and into corners. The vision and movements of some birds are impaired. When a single bird is chased in a cage following our protocol, in contrast, probably the ability to continue to fly is what determines capture time. Hence, individual capture time is a measure that will better reproduce individual performance, which is in turn reflected by the sexual carotenoid-based signal.  In our trials, all birds were captured when they were perched and failed to take off before the experimenter attempted to put a sweep net over them. Thus, birds that managed to take off faster and perched for shorter periods were probably better able to evade capture, which could indicate that these birds had a greater aerobic capacity than males with less-red plumage. A recent hypothesis proposes that carotenoid coloration links to performance because the metabolism of carotenoid pigments in the production of ornamental coloration is intimately linked to cellular respiration ( Hill and Johnson 2012 ,  Johnson and Hill 2013 ). Our results could suggest that the potential greater aerobic capacity of redder birds is derived from a more efficient cellular respiration ( Hill and Johnson 2012 ,  Johnson and Hill 2013 ).  Carotenoid coloration has also been hypothesized to reflect other aspects of condition beside cellular respiration including energy stores, reduced oxidative stress, and enhanced immunocompetence ( Svensson and Wong 2011 ,  Simons et al. 2012 ). Any one of these aspects of condition could explain the relationship between carotenoid coloration and capture evasion. Carotenoids could also have a direct effect on flight performance.  Blount and Matheson (2006)  reported that birds that had been supplemented with carotenoids improved their takeoff capability, a skill that seemed to be of importance in our experiments. Even though our birds were maintained with the same diet, individual variation in absorption or allocation of pigments could result in some individuals having access to more circulating carotenoids. These individuals could then take advantage of the potential beneficial effects of carotenoids, such as reduced oxidative muscle damage, enhanced motor performance or cognition processes, and improved immune defense ( Blount and Matheson 2006 ,  Svensson and Wong 2011 ,  Simons et al. 2012 ).  In addition to simply allowing them to avoid being captured and killed, the greater escape ability of redder male House Finches could confer on them important fitness advantages when defending their nest against predators ( Reyer et al. 1998 ). Better flight ability could also enable more efficient foraging, which could in turn result in better parental care. This advantage would grant direct benefits to female House Finches choosing redder males ( Hill 1990 ).  Female House Finches are dominant over males ( Thompson 1960 ) and more aggressive toward drabber males ( Belthoff and Gowaty 1996 ). This higher aggression could be a reason for drabber males to change social groups more frequently than the more stable redder males ( Oh and Badyaev 2010 ). The stability of redder males in social groups could be driven by a social female preference for males with higher foraging and antipredator abilities. Ultimately, the lower female aggression toward redder males, and their more efficient foraging and better antipredator abilities, could jointly explain the higher overwinter survival rate of redder House Finches ( Hill 1991 ,  Belthoff and Gowaty 1996 ).  We thank A. J. Pate for his help during the experiments and Andrew Arnold and Meagan Duval for help capturing birds. We thank Mirjam Amcoff, Bj&ouml;rn Rogell, and G&ouml;ran Arnqvist for statistical advice. Mirjam Amcoff, Fredrik Sundstr&ouml;m, Gregorio Moreno-Rueda, Keith Tarvin, and two anonymous reviewers made helpful comments on the manuscript. This work was funded by NSF grant IOS0923600 to G. E. H. and F. P. I., and BES-2007-16320 grant to F. M. G. (Spanish Ministry of Science and Technology). Birds were maintained under USFWS migratory bird permit MB784373-2 and Alabama State permit 2010000072968680 and IACUC project 2011-1939. The authors declare no conflict of interest. 