Winter survival of female American Black Ducks in Tennessee, USAInformation theory and an extension of the maximum likelihood principleThe effects of winter weather on the behavior and energy reserves of Black Ducks in MaineThe role of predator removal, density-dependence, and environmental factors on Mallard duckling survival in North DakotaUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's information criterionAge determination of American Black Ducks in winter and springStress response in wintering Green-winged TealSurvival rates of female Mallards wintering in the Playa Lakes RegionCarryover effects and climatic conditions influence the postfledging survival of Greater Sage-GrouseEvidence for Black Duck winter distribution changeWinter survival of female American Black Ducks on the Atlantic CoastIdentification and synthetic modeling of factors affecting American Black Duck populationsAnalysis of individual- and time-specific covariate effects on survival of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Serinus serinus</named-content></italic> in north-eastern SpainProgram MARK: A Gentle Introduction, thirteenth editionEffects of capture and handling on survival of female Northern PintailsSurvival of female Northern Pintails wintering in southwestern LouisianaUsing an electronic compass to determine telemetry azimuthsMovement distances and habitat switching by female Mallards wintering in the lower Mississippi Alluvial ValleyHabitat use by female Mallards in the lower Mississippi Alluvial ValleyFactors affecting winter survival of female Mallards in the lower Mississippi Alluvial ValleyHabitat and resource use by waterfowl in the northern hemisphere in autumn and winterEffects of hunting season structure, weather and body condition on overwintering Mallard <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> survivalMallard response to experimental walk-in and shooting disturbanceAn adjustable radio-package for ducksPintail and Mallard survival in California relative to habitat, abundance, and huntingSurvival of Dusky Canada Goose goslings in relation to weather and annual nest survivalAgricultural seed biomass for migrating and wintering waterfowl in the southeastern United StatesExploring ecological relationships in survival and estimating rates of population change using Program MARKInfluence of climate on annual survival of Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>) breeding in North AmericaDirect and indirect effects of winter harshness on the survival of Mallards <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> in northwest EuropeThe North American Bird Banding Manual, Volume 1Winter waterbird and food dynamics in autumn-managed moist-soil wetlands in the Mississippi Alluvial ValleyEffects of body weight and age on the time of pairing of American Black DucksFull-annual-cycle population models for migratory birdsAn evaluation of condition indices for birdsAn introduction to habitat use and selection by waterfowl in the northern hemisphereWithin-winter movements: A common phenomenon in the Common Pochard <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aythya ferina</named-content></italic>When and where does mortality occur in migratory birds? Direct evidence from long-term satellite tracking of raptorsSources of variation in waterfowl survival ratesSources of variation in survival and recovery rates of American Black DucksThe effects of hunting on survival rates of American Black DucksRmark&mdash;An alternative approach to building linear models in MARKMorphometric indices of body condition in birds: A reviewVariation in home-range size and movements of wintering dabbling ducksOn finding the source of a signalPredation risk and unpredictable feeding conditions: Determinants of body mass in birdsA hierarchical model for regional analysis of population change using Christmas Bird Count data, with application to the American Black DuckEndogenous loss of body mass by Mallards in winterSurvival of American Black Ducks radiomarked in Quebec, Nova Scotia, and VermontSurvival of postfledging female American Black DucksDistributional responses of Canvasback ducks to weather and habitat changeEstimating carcass fat and protein in Northern Pintails during the nonbreeding seasonSurvival of female Northern Pintails wintering in the Playa Lakes Region of northwestern TexasDeveloping a Management Model of the Effects of Future Climate Change on Species: A Tool for the Landscape Conservation CooperativesFactors affecting the distribution of Mallards wintering in the Mississippi Alluvial ValleyBlack Ducks: Harvest, Mallards, or habitat?Spring-migration ecology of Northern Pintails in south-central NebraskaEffects of harness transmitters on behavior and reproduction of wild MallardsWinter philopatry in migratory waterfowlWeather-dependent survival: Implications of climate change for passerine population processesPredation risk and fasting capacity: Do wintering birds maintain optimal body mass?Testing optimal body mass theory: Evidence for cost of fat in wintering birdsPopulation ecology and harvest of the American Black Duck: A reviewMultiple weather factors affect apparent survival of European passerine birdsEvidence of climate change effects on within-winter movements of European Mallards <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>Evaluating the validity of using unverified indices of body conditionWeather-related indices of autumn&ndash;winter dabbling duck abundance in middle North AmericaCross-seasonal effects and the dynamics of waterfowl populationsCarryover effects associated with winter location affect fitness, social status, and population dynamics in a long-distance migrantFood habits of Bald Eagles in MaineAnnual and seasonal survival of adult female Mottled Ducks in southern Florida, USAProgram MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsImpact of winter stress on Mallard body compositionBody mass variations in disturbed Mallards <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> fit to the mass-dependent starvation&ndash;predation risk trade-offEvidence of the trade-off between starvation and predation risks in ducksComposite analysis of Black Duck breeding population surveys in eastern North AmericaCurrent address: Kennedy Waterfowl &amp; Wetlands Conservation Center, Belle W. Baruch Institute for Coastal Ecology and Forest Science, Clemson University, Georgetown, South Carolina, USAMany migratory bird species, including the American Black Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>; hereafter black duck), face challenges to their survival during winter due to potentially limited resources and high energetic demands. These winter processes can be especially important for the population dynamics of migratory species. Despite stabilization of the overall black duck breeding population, historical declines continue for black ducks wintering in the Mississippi Flyway. It remains unclear if declining abundance in this region reflects high winter mortality. We radio-tagged 111 females in the Tennessee National Wildlife Refuge (TNWR), a major wintering area for mid-continent Mississippi Flyway black ducks, from December to February of 2010&ndash;2012 to estimate winter survival and investigate factors that may influence survival rates, including body mass, age, hunting period, and weather. Winter survival (0.83&ndash;0.85) was greater than or comparable with previous estimates for black duck populations in North America. Generally, birds with greater body mass had higher survival than birds of lesser body mass; a bird 100 g heavier than one of average body mass had 18&percnt; greater interval survival. We also found that body mass had a greater influence on survival during late (nonhunting) periods and a more severe winter, when resources potentially were limited. For example, a bird with a body mass 100 g above average had 9&percnt; greater interval survival than one of average body mass during the winter of 2010&ndash;2011, but in the subsequent milder winter, the heavier bird had similar survival to the bird of average body mass. Our results suggest that winter mortality is not a primary factor contributing to declining abundance of black ducks in the TNWR. If this reflects the general pattern in the Mississippi Flyway, declining regional abundance may be driven by movement patterns or cross-seasonal effects rather than winter mortality.Plusieurs esp&egrave;ces d'oiseaux migrateurs, dont <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>, font face &agrave; des d&eacute;fis pour leur survie en hiver en raison des ressources limit&eacute;es et des demandes &eacute;nerg&eacute;tiques &eacute;lev&eacute;es. Ces processus hivernaux peuvent &ecirc;tre particuli&egrave;rement importants pour la dynamique des populations d'esp&egrave;ces migratrices. Malgr&eacute; la stabilisation de la population reproductrice globale d'<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. rubripes</named-content></italic>, des d&eacute;clins historiques persistent pour les populations hivernant dans la voie migratoire du Mississippi. Il demeure incertain si le d&eacute;clin de l'abondance dans cette r&eacute;gion refl&egrave;te une mortalit&eacute; hivernale &eacute;lev&eacute;e. De d&eacute;cembre &agrave; f&eacute;vrier 2010&ndash;2012, nous avons &eacute;quip&eacute; 111 femelles de radio-&eacute;metteurs au Tennessee National Wildlife Refuge (TNWR), un quartier d'hivernage majeur pour les individus de cette esp&egrave;ce de la voie migratoire du Mississippi dans le centre du continent, afin d'estimer la survie hivernale et d'examiner les facteurs qui peuvent influencer les taux de survie, dont la masse corporelle, l'&acirc;ge, la p&eacute;riode de chasse et les conditions m&eacute;t&eacute;orologiques. La survie hivernale (0,83&ndash;0,85) &eacute;tait plus &eacute;lev&eacute;e ou comparable &agrave; celle des estimations ant&eacute;rieures pour les populations d'<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. rubripes</named-content></italic> en Am&eacute;rique du Nord. G&eacute;n&eacute;ralement, les oiseaux ayant une plus grande masse corporelle avaient une survie plus &eacute;lev&eacute;e que les oiseaux de plus faible masse corporelle; un oiseau plus lourd de 100 g qu'un autre de masse corporelle moyenne avait une survie 18 &percnt; plus &eacute;lev&eacute;e. Nous avons aussi trouv&eacute; que la masse corporelle avait une plus grande influence sur la survie au cours des p&eacute;riodes tardives (sans chasse) et d'un hiver plus rude car les ressources &eacute;taient potentiellement limit&eacute;es. Par exemple, un oiseau avec une masse corporelle de 100 g au-dessus de la moyenne avait une survie de 9 &percnt; plus &eacute;lev&eacute;e qu'un autre de masse corporelle moyenne au cours de l'hiver 2010&ndash;2011, mais lors de l'hiver subs&eacute;quent, plus doux, l'oiseau le plus lourd avait une survie similaire &agrave; celui de masse corporelle moyenne. Nos r&eacute;sultats sugg&egrave;rent que la mortalit&eacute; hivernale n'est pas un facteur principal contribuant au d&eacute;clin de l'abondance d'<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. rubripes</named-content></italic> au TNWR. Si cela refl&egrave;te le patron g&eacute;n&eacute;ral de la voie migratoire du Mississippi, le d&eacute;clin de l'abondance r&eacute;gionale peut &ecirc;tre caus&eacute; par des patrons de mouvements ou des effets trans-saisonniers plut&ocirc;t que par la mortalit&eacute; hivernale.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>, hiver, masse corporelle, conditions m&eacute;t&eacute;orologiques, chasse, mod&egrave;les de destin&eacute;e connue, voie migratoire du MississippiThe nonbreeding period is challenging for many bird species because of potentially limited resources and high energetic demands, and low survival during winter can disproportionately affect fitness and population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robinson1">Robinson et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Klaassen1">Klaassen et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Hostetler1">Hostetler et al. 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">Rogers 2015</xref>). For most Nearctic ducks, this period extends nearly 8 mo and includes significant biological and social events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Weller1">Weller 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robertson1">Robertson and Cooke 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre and Bolen 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis4">Davis et al. 2014</xref>). Accessible, quality food and disturbance-free areas are essential resources for wintering waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Whyte1">Whyte and Bolen 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Legagneux1">Legagneux et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dooley2">Dooley et al. 2010b</xref>). The survival of waterfowl in winter can be greatly affected by age, habitat conditions, body condition, hunting-related effects (e.g., disturbance, direct mortality), and the availability of sanctuary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">Krementz et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore1">Longcore et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dooley1">Dooley et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis3">Davis et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis4">2014</xref>).Once the most harvested and abundant dabbling duck in eastern North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Blandin1">Blandin 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Devers1">Devers and Collins 2011</xref>), the American Black Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>; hereafter black duck) declined precipitously between the 1950s and 1990s, falling from ~750,000 in 1955 to ~288,800 birds in 2014 in the Mid-winter Waterfowl Survey (MWS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-USFWSU.S.FishandWildlifeService1">USFWS 2014</xref>). Harvest and hunting-related disturbance, competition and introgressive hybridization with Mallards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>), and loss and degradation of habitat are among the most implicated possible causes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rusch1">Rusch et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Nudds1">Nudds et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy2">Conroy et al. 2002a</xref>). Research into factors possibly influencing declines in black duck populations is especially important in the Mississippi Flyway, where the steepest declines have occurred. Changes in black duck populations have not been uniform throughout the species' range, and both breeding and winter survey data reveal contrasting population trends, with declines in southern, western, and central sectors of the range, but stabilization or slight increases in northeastern areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Link1">Link et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Brook1">Brook et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmerman1">Zimmerman et al. 2012</xref>). There was a 2-fold decrease in the MWS population index for black ducks in the Atlantic Flyway between 1955 and 2014 (582,453 to 269,000 birds), while the index for the Mississippi Flyway showed a 9-fold decrease during the same period (178,400 to 19,700 birds; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fronczak1">Fronczak 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-USFWSU.S.FishandWildlifeService1">USFWS 2014</xref>). Despite extensive research on black ducks in North America, limited information exists on factors affecting winter survival of black ducks in the Mississippi Flyway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">Krementz et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Chipley1">Chipley 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb 1997</xref>). However, there is some evidence to support differential winter survival between adults and juveniles, and also potential negative effects of body condition, hunting, and weather severity on black duck survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">Krementz et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Chipley1">Chipley 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb 1997</xref>).The state of Tennessee has supported the most wintering black ducks in the Mississippi Flyway in more than half of the years from 1955 to 2014, averaging ~33,851 birds from 1955 to 1999, but decreasing 76&percnt; to an average of ~8,108 birds for 2000&ndash;2013 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fronczak1">Fronczak 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-USFWSU.S.FishandWildlifeService1">USFWS 2014</xref>). Tennessee National Wildlife Refuge (TNWR) and Cross Creeks National Wildlife Refuge historically held the most wintering black ducks in Tennessee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Sanders1">Sanders 1995</xref>), with the TNWR having &gt;50&percnt; of black ducks in the state, or ~22&percnt; of black ducks in the Mississippi Flyway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fronczak1">Fronczak 2012</xref>, R. M. Wheat personal communication). However, black ducks wintering in the TNWR have declined as well, from ~20,000 birds in 1964 to 2,913 in 2015 (R. M. Wheat personal communication).Listed as a &ldquo;Species of Greatest Conservation Need&rdquo; by 74&percnt; of the states in the Mississippi and Atlantic flyways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Devers1">Devers and Collins 2011</xref>), conservation and research initiatives to increase black duck populations are priorities for government agencies, conservation organizations, and hunters, because of the economic, ecological, and cultural significance of the species. Given concerns over declining black duck populations in the Mississippi Flyway and specifically in the TNWR, a major wintering area for mid-continent Mississippi Flyway black ducks, our objectives were to: (1) determine contemporary winter survival estimates of black ducks, and (2) evaluate biotic and abiotic factors that may be affecting black duck survival in the TNWR.Our primary study area was the Duck River Unit (DRU; 35&deg;57&prime;30N, 87&deg;57&prime;00W) of the TNWR in western Tennessee (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The DRU is the largest (10,820 ha) of 3 wetland complexes comprising the TNWR (20,784 ha). Primary resources in the DRU include: (1) seasonally flooded, emergent herbaceous (i.e. moist-soil) wetlands (594 ha); (2) cooperatively farmed row crop agriculture (673 ha); (3) impounded open water areas (537 ha); (4) woody sloughs, scrub&ndash;shrub, and bottomland hardwoods (2,016 ha); (5) uplands dominated by oak (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Quercus</named-content></italic> spp.) and hickory (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Carya</named-content></italic> spp.; 2,468 ha); and (6) portions of the Kentucky Reservoir (3,458 ha) and Duck River (777 ha). Crops grown in the TNWR include corn, millet, grain sorghum, winter wheat, soybean, and clover. Interior levees divide the DRU into 14 managed impoundments, and an outer perimeter levee helps protect impoundments from flooding by the Kentucky Reservoir and Duck River. Waterfowl hunting is not permitted in the TNWR, but hunting occurs on surrounding private and public lands. Most roads within the DRU are closed to foot and vehicular traffic from November 15 to March 15 annually.Land cover map of Tennessee National Wildlife Refuge's Duck River Unit in Humphreys County in western Tennessee, USA, winter 2010&ndash;2011.We baited and deployed swim-in traps and rocket nets in the DRU from November through early February of 2010&ndash;2012 in areas where black ducks were consistently observed. Swim-in traps were constructed of 1.5 m tall, 2.5 &times; 5.0 cm welded wire, and roofed with 5 &times; 5 cm plastic mesh. We baited areas around swim-in traps and rocket nets with a combination of whole kernel corn, wild bird seed mix, chufa tubers, and milo, beginning November 15 each year. All captured male and female black ducks were transported to DRU headquarters to be banded, but only females were radio-tagged.We banded all black ducks with U.S. Geological Survey standard aluminum tarsus bands and aged birds by wing plumage characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Carney1">Carney 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Ashley1">Ashley et al. 2006</xref>). Females were weighed with a 2.5-kg Pesola spring scale (Pesola AG, Baar, Switzerland) and only instrumented if a 23-g, harness-type, VHF transmitter (Model A1820, Advanced Telemetry Systems, Isanti, Minnesota, USA) was &lt;3&percnt; of an individual's body mass (~900 g; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dwyer1">Dwyer 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Gustafson1">Gustafson et al. 1997</xref>). Only one captured female was released without a transmitter because she did not meet the weight requirement. Transmitters were equipped with mortality sensors that doubled the signal pulse rate after 8 hr of inactivity. After marking females, we placed them in crates and left them undisturbed for ~1 hr before releasing females and males at trap sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox1">Cox and Afton 1998</xref>). We commenced data collection on the third day postrelease to avoid possible biases associated with acclimation to transmitters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis2">Davis et al. 2009</xref>). All transmitters were deployed by February 3 in both winters.We determined the survival status and locations of a subsample (i.e. randomly selected without replacement) of radio-tagged female black ducks daily, 6 days per week (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis1">Davis and Afton 2010</xref>). The subsample of radio-tagged ducks was tracked diurnally and nocturnally within a 24-hr cycle using vehicles equipped with roof-mounted, 4-element, null-peak antenna systems (Advanced Telemetry Systems, Isanti, Minnesota, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox3">Cox et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Pearse1">Pearse et al. 2011</xref>). We also equipped vehicles with Global Positioning System units (Trimble GeoXM handheld, Trimble Navigation Ltd, Sunnyvale, California, USA), laptops with Location of a Signal software (LOAS 4.0.3.8, Ecological Software Solutions, Hegymagas, Hungary), and electronic compasses (Azimuth 1000R, KVH Industries, Middletown, Rhode Island, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox3">Cox et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis1">Davis and Afton 2010</xref>). Electronic compasses were calibrated to within &plusmn;0.5&deg; of known locations of beacon transmitters, and crew members were trained to use the tracking system and triangulate beacon transmitters until they were able to maintain a standard deviation &le;3&deg; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis2">Davis et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis1">Davis and Afton 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Pearse1">Pearse et al. 2011</xref>).Upon detecting radio-tagged ducks, we recorded Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) coordinates of the tracking vehicle and &ge;3 azimuths in LOAS to estimate locations and 95&percnt; confidence ellipses, based on a maximum-likelihood estimator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lenth1">Lenth 1981</xref>) and a bearing standard deviation of 3&deg; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis2">Davis et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis1">Davis and Afton 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Pearse1">Pearse et al. 2011</xref>). If necessary, we obtained additional azimuths until confidence ellipses were within 1 habitat type or detection vantage points were exhausted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis2">Davis et al. 2009</xref>). If &gt;3 azimuths were recorded, the combination of bearings that resulted in the smallest confidence ellipse was used for analyses. Additionally, we conducted aerial surveys in a Cessna 172 equipped with strut-mounted, 4-element antennas when radio-tagged ducks were not detected via ground reconnaissance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Gilmer1">Gilmer et al. 1981</xref>). When a mortality signal was detected, we immediately located the transmitter, recorded the location, and determined cause of death if possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox1">Cox and Afton 1998</xref>).We used the following explanatory variables in our known-fate survival models: year (winter 2010&ndash;2011 or 2011&ndash;2012); female age (hatch and second year &lsqb;HY&rsqb; or after hatch and after second year &lsqb;AHY&rsqb;); regression residuals of body mass at capture on the date of capture (see below); hunting period (during hunting or posthunting season); and weather (minimum temperature &lsqb;&deg;C&rsqb;, rainfall &lsqb;mm&rsqb;, snowfall &lsqb;mm&rsqb;, and a weather severity index &lsqb;WSI&rsqb;).Waterfowl experience endogenous changes in body mass throughout winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Hepp1">Hepp 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Loesch1">Loesch et al. 1992</xref>). Because we captured and measured the body mass of females from December to February each winter, we accounted for endogenous changes in mass by evaluating linear and polynomial regression models of body mass at capture on the date of capture and used the residuals from the best model in our survival analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lancaster1">Lancaster 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb 2014</xref>). We used <italic>F</italic>-tests to compare null (i.e. intercept only), linear, and polynomial regression models relating body mass at capture to the date of capture for each year. When evaluating regression models of body mass at capture (<italic>m</italic>) on the date of capture (<italic>d</italic>), we detected an interaction between date and year of capture on body mass by analysis of covariance (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,109</sub> &equals; 7.3, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Therefore, we determined the best model for each year separately. We detected neither an effect of age (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.77) nor an interaction of age by date of capture (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.84) on body mass, so we did not include models incorporating age in subsequent comparisons of regression models.For the winter of 2010&ndash;2011, neither linear (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.87) nor polynomial (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.48) regression models explained variation in body mass better than the null model (<italic>m</italic> &equals; 1201 &minus; 0.1<italic>d</italic>). For winter 2011&ndash;2012, a second-order polynomial regression model (<italic>m</italic> &equals; 1426 &minus; 19.6<italic>d</italic> &plus; 0.3<italic>d</italic><sup>2</sup>) fit better than null (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) or linear (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.002) models; however, a third-order polynomial regression model did not fit better than the second-order model (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.33). Based on these analyses, we used residuals from the null model for the 2010&ndash;2011 winter and residuals from the second-order polynomial regression model for the winter of 2011&ndash;2012. After the most appropriate model was identified, we used Fligner-Killeen and Shapiro-Wilk tests to test for homogeneity of variances and normality of residuals, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Crawley1">Crawley 2013</xref>).Body condition indices of waterfowl can vary by season, species, sex, and among populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Miller1">Miller 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Sparling1">Sparling et al. 1992</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Schamber1">Schamber et al. (2009)</xref> recommended using body mass alone instead of unvalidated indices because adjustment with a structural measurement often provides little improvement for prediction of body fat than body mass alone, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-White2">White (1994)</xref> concluded that body mass adjusted by structural measurements was of little value for predicting body fat of black ducks in the TNWR. Thus, we did not adjust body mass by any structural measurements. We also did not adjust body mass to account for esophageal contents, which may have introduced additional variation that was unaccounted for in our analysis. However, because all traps and rocket nets were baited similarly, we assumed that the presence and amount of esophageal contents were random among birds and that body mass at capture was an adequate index of relative condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Blomberg1">Blomberg et al. 2014</xref>).We modeled the effects of weather on survival by including covariates for rainfall (RAIN), minimum temperature (TMIN), snowfall (SNOW), and the weather severity index (WSI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Schummer1">Schummer et al. 2010</xref>). The WSI incorporates mean daily temperature, snowfall, and snow depth into a single index value, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Schummer1">Schummer et al. (2010)</xref> demonstrated its usefulness in examining the effects of temperature on energy expenditure of waterfowl and resource availability. We acquired weather data from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's National Climatic Data Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gis.ncdc.noaa.gov/map/viewer/#app=cdo" xlink:type="simple">http://gis.ncdc.noaa.gov/map/viewer/&num;app&equals;cdo</ext-link>) and the Southern Regional Climate Center (Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA) for the Global Historical Climatology Network&ndash;Daily (GHCND) weather station in Camden, Tennessee (14.5 km west-northwest of the DRU). We retrieved any data missing from the Camden weather station from the GHCND weather station in Mt. Moriah, Tennessee (7.2 km west of the DRU). Despite the Mt. Moriah station being closer to the DRU than the Camden station, we did not use the Mt. Moriah data because that station had more missing observations than the Camden station. Missing mean daily temperature values (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2 of 200 days) were calculated by using the median between 2 dates for which data existed. Because each interval over which survival was estimated represented multiple days, we used the mean value of daily weather covariates for each interval. We calculated WSI for each day and subsequently calculated the mean WSI value for each interval. We standardized all covariates to facilitate maximum-likelihood estimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Franklin1">Franklin 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cooch1">Cooch and White 2013</xref>), and looked for correlation amongst covariates using Pearson's product-moment correlation test. The covariates TMIN and SNOW were correlated (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.31, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.013, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 62), so we did not include them together in any models. We did not detect a correlation between WSI and RAIN (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.12, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.36), and thus we included them together in models.We created a binary covariate to represent whether hunting occurred during a monitoring interval (HUNT &equals; 1) or not (HUNT &equals; 0). Hunting occurred daily outside the TNWR from December 4, 2010, to January 30, 2011, and from December 3, 2011, to January 29, 2012, so we coded each interval during those periods as hunted. Youth hunts occurred on February 5&ndash;6, 2010, and February 4&ndash;5, 2011; we coded February 4&ndash;6 as hunted in both years. We did not divide the intervals to more accurately reflect hunting occurrence because it took 4 days to record locations for all radio-tagged ducks at that time.We used the R 3.0.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>) package RMark 2.1.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Laake1">Laake and Rexstad 2013</xref>) to construct known-fate models in program MARK 7.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>) to estimate survival rates of radio-tagged female black ducks and to explain variation in rates relative to explanatory variables. We modeled winter survival from December 11, 2010 to March 17, 2011 (30 encounter occasions), and from December 19, 2011 to April 1, 2012 (32 encounter occasions). Survival was estimated over uneven intervals (i.e. 2&ndash;4 days) instead of daily intervals because we were only able to locate all females and determine their status (i.e. alive or dead) every 2&ndash;4 days. Mortalities that occurred &le;4 days after radio-tagging were excluded from survival analyses to avoid mortality bias associated with capture and radio-tagging (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox1">Cox and Afton 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dooley1">Dooley et al. 2010a</xref>).We used an exploratory, sequential modeling approach to avoid overfitting the data while evaluating models incorporating covariates of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fleskes1">Fleskes et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Amundson1">Amundson and Arnold 2011</xref>). Additionally, we avoided using a comprehensive, global model as the basis for model selection because only 12 mortalities were included in analyses, which did not support heavily parameterized models (e.g., global or fully time-dependent models). In the first step of model selection, we compared the constant (i.e. null) survival model and additive and interaction models incorporating year (YEAR), female age (AGE), and regression residuals of body mass at capture on the date of capture (MASS). We included AGE and MASS in the first step of model selection because these covariates often influence individual survival of waterfowl in winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz1">Krementz et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Anderson1">Anderson 2008</xref>). We also included YEAR in the first step because of the interaction that we found between body mass residuals and year. The constant survival model and models with informative parameters that ranked above the constant survival model were included in subsequent steps of model selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fondell1">Fondell et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). We tested for the effects of HUNT and weather covariates in subsequent steps to account for additional variation in survival rates of black ducks. We included models with HUNT in the second step and models with RAIN, TMIN, SNOW, and WSI in the third step of model selection, in addition to the constant survival model and those models supported from previous steps. Estimates of dispersion in the model set ranged from 0.4 to 1.2, so we used <italic>&ccirc;</italic> &equals; 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zuur1">Zuur et al. 2009</xref>).To evaluate models, we used Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>), Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), and the difference from the top model in AIC<sub>c</sub> (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Akaike1">Akaike 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We used RMark to model-average parameter estimates from models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2 in the final step of model selection to account for model selection uncertainty in survival estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). Seasonal survival estimates were calculated as the product of all interval survival estimates for the period of interest, and the variance of the product was calculated using the Delta method in RMark (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cooch1">Cooch and White 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Laake1">Laake and Rexstad 2013</xref>). We present 85&percnt; confidence limits for survival and &beta; estimates because variables that exclude zero with 85&percnt; confidence intervals are supported by model selection with AIC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>).We radio-tagged 113 female black ducks (43 AHY and 70 HY birds) in the DRU during the winters of 2010&ndash;2012. Females were radio-tagged during December (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 27, 16), January (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 20, 31), and February (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17, 2) in the 2010&ndash;2011 and 2011&ndash;2012 winter, respectively. Though we began catching male black ducks in November, we did not capture any females until mid-December each winter. The mean body masses of radio-tagged adult (1,211 &plusmn; 124 g &lsqb;mean &plusmn; SD&rsqb;) and juvenile (1,210 &plusmn; 123 g) black ducks were similar across winters. However, mean body mass was greater in the 2011&ndash;2012 winter than the 2010&ndash;2011 winter for adults (1,236 &plusmn; 145 g vs. 1,199 &plusmn; 102 g, respectively) and juveniles (1,226 &plusmn; 147 g vs. 1,198 &plusmn; 101 g, respectively).We documented 14 (12&percnt;) black duck mortalities during the study period, including 9 deaths in the winter of 2010&ndash;2011 and 5 in 2011&ndash;2012. Mortalities occurred in December (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 1), January (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2), February (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 1), and March (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 1) in the 2010&ndash;2011 winter, and in January (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 5) in the winter of 2011&ndash;2012. In the 2010&ndash;2011 winter, 1 black duck was depredated by a raptor, but the cause of mortality for the other 8 black ducks could not be determined because we were unable to inspect carcasses before they were scavenged. In the winter of 2011&ndash;2012, all 5 mortalities were harvests, from 10 Mile Pond Conservation Area, Missouri, USA (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2); Camden WMA, Tennessee (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2); and private land adjacent to the Duck River, Tennessee (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 1). Through reports of band recoveries, we also discovered the fates of 10 black ducks that survived the winter during which they were radio-tagged, but were later harvested. These birds, which were harvested in Ohio, Michigan, Ontario, New York, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Tennessee, were not included as mortalities in our analysis because they survived through the study period.We estimated winter survival for 111 radio-tagged female black ducks (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 62 in 2010&ndash;2011 and <italic>n</italic> &equals; 49 in 2011&ndash;2012). We incorporated model selection uncertainty into survival estimates by model-averaging estimates from the models YEAR&ast;MASS, MASS, HUNT&ast;MASS, and the null model, all of which had &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2. Estimated survival rates for radio-tagged female black ducks during the hunting season were 0.90 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.84, 0.97; 17 intervals) for the winter of 2010&ndash;2011 and 0.91 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.86, 0.96; 15 intervals) for the winter of 2011&ndash;2012 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f02">Figure 2</xref>). During the nonhunting season, estimated survival rates were 0.94 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.89, 0.99; 13 intervals) for the 2010&ndash;2011 winter and 0.91 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.85, 0.97; 17 intervals) for the 2011&ndash;2012 winter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Overall, survival rates for the winters of 2010&ndash;2011 and 2011&ndash;2012 were 0.85 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.75, 0.95; 17 intervals) and 0.83 (85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.73, 0.92; 15 intervals), respectively.Survival rates of female American Black Ducks in western Tennessee, USA, during the winters of 2010&ndash;2012 determined by model-averaging 3-day interval survival estimates from the models YEAR&ast;MASS, HUNT&ast;MASS, MASS, and the constant survival model. YEAR &equals; Winters 2010&ndash;2011, 2011&ndash;2012; MASS &equals; Residual values from the best regression model of body mass of female black ducks at capture on date of capture, and HUNT &equals; Dummy variable for each day, coded as 0 &equals; not hunted and 1 &equals; hunted.In the first step of model selection, the best-supported model among 12 candidate models was YEAR&ast;MASS (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t01">Table 1</xref>). The univariate MASS model also ranked above the constant survival model. Models with AGE were not supported and were thus excluded from subsequent steps of model selection. For step 2 of model selection, we retained models from step 1 with a &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2, which included YEAR&ast;MASS and MASS, and we incorporated HUNT into a set of 8 candidate models. The YEAR&ast;MASS model again was the most supported in step 2, and models retained from step 1 and HUNT&ast;MASS received some support (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t02">Table 2</xref>). The YEAR&ast;MASS &plus; HUNT model also ranked above the constant survival model; however, we did not retain YEAR&ast;MASS &plus; HUNT in the subsequent step of model selection because it included an uninformative parameter (i.e. HUNT; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t02">Table 2</xref>). In the final step of model selection, we retained the YEAR&ast;MASS, MASS, and HUNT&ast;MASS models from step 2 and incorporated weather covariates into a set of 44 candidate models. Models with weather covariates were not supported, and weather parameters neither improved the rankings of models nor knowledge derived from them (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t03">Table 3</xref>). The best-supported model was YEAR&ast;MASS, yet uncertainty persisted among competitive models (i.e. &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2). The YEAR&ast;MASS model had only 14&percnt; of the total Akaike weight (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t03">Table 3</xref>). Evidence ratios indicated that YEAR&ast;MASS was 2.7 times more likely than MASS, 2.9 times more likely than HUNT&ast;MASS, and 3.1 times more likely than the constant model to be the actual best model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t03">Table 3</xref>).Top models from analysis of year, age, and body mass covariates in relation to survival of radio-tagged female American Black Ducks in western Tennessee, USA, winters 2010&ndash;2012. Only models that ranked above the constant survival model are shown. <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criteria adjusted for small sample sizes, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the relative likelihood of model (<italic>i</italic>) based on the AIC<sub>c</sub> value, and Dev is model deviance.Top models from analysis of a daily hunting covariate and selected covariates from the first step of model selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t01">Table 1</xref>) in relation to survival of radio-tagged female American Black Ducks in western Tennessee, USA, winters 2010&ndash;2012. Only models that ranked above the constant survival model are shown. <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criteria adjusted for small sample sizes, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the relative likelihood of model (<italic>i</italic>) based on the AIC<sub>c</sub> value, and Dev is model deviance.Top models from analysis of weather and selected covariates from previous model selection steps (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t01">Tables 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t02">2</xref>) in relation to survival of radio-tagged female American Black Ducks in western Tennessee, USA, winters 2010&ndash;2012. Only models that ranked above the constant survival model are shown. <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criteria adjusted for small sample sizes, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the relative likelihood of model (<italic>i</italic>) based on the AIC<sub>c</sub> value, and Dev is model deviance.Results from the YEAR&ast;MASS model indicated that the effect of body mass at capture on survival of female black ducks varied by year. Although there was no statistical difference in survival between years (&beta;<sub>YR2</sub> &equals; &minus;0.20, 85&percnt; CL &equals; &minus;1.27, 0.88), there was a positive effect of body mass on survival in the winter of 2010&ndash;2011 (&beta;<sub>MASS</sub> &equals; 1.30, 85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.55, 2.05) and a negative effect of body mass on survival in the 2011&ndash;2012 winter (&beta;<sub>YR2:MASS</sub> &equals; &minus;1.51, 85&percnt; CL &equals; &minus;2.45, &minus;0.57; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Weather conditions in the winter of 2010&ndash;2011 generally were more severe (e.g., colder temperatures, less precipitation in early and mid-winter, and greater snowfall) than in the winter of 2011&ndash;2012 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t04">Table 4</xref>), which could explain why the effect of body mass on survival was greater in the 2010&ndash;2011 winter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f02">Figure 2</xref>), despite not detecting any effects of weather or year on survival of black ducks overall. We also did not detect an effect of age on survival. Results from the MASS model indicated a positive effect of body mass on survival overall (&beta;<sub>MASS</sub> &equals; 0.47, 85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.00, 0.95). Additionally, results from the HUNT&ast;MASS model indicated that the effect of body mass on survival varied between hunting and nonhunting periods. Although there was not a statistical difference in survival between hunting and nonhunting periods (&beta;<sub>HUNT</sub> &equals; &minus;1.02, 85&percnt; CL &equals; &minus;2.27, 0.24), there was a positive effect of body mass on survival following the closure of the hunting season (&beta;<sub>MASS</sub> &equals; 1.49, 85&percnt; CL &equals; 0.52, 2.45) and a negative interaction between period and body mass (&beta;<sub>HUNT:MASS</sub> &equals; &minus;1.43, 85&percnt; CL &equals; &minus;2.43, &minus;0.33; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Monthly summaries of Global Historical Climatology Network&ndash;Daily (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gis.ncdc.noaa.gov/map/viewer/#app=cdo" xlink:type="simple">http://gis.ncdc.noaa.gov/map/viewer/&num;app&equals;cdo</ext-link>) weather data recorded at Camden, Tennessee, USA, for the period November 2010&ndash;March 2012.Overall winter survival estimates for female black ducks in our study (0.83&ndash;0.85 over 3 mo) were greater than or comparable with estimates from other recent studies of radio-tagged dabbling ducks, which ranged from 0.54 to 0.70 for Mallards (4&ndash;6 mo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dooley1">Dooley et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis3">Davis et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lancaster1">Lancaster 2013</xref>), 0.81 to 0.96 for Florida Mottled Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. fulvigula</named-content> fulvigula</italic>; 2 mo during the hunting season; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Varner1">Varner et al. 2014</xref>), and 0.31 to 0.93 for Northern Pintails (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. acuta</named-content></italic>; 4&ndash;6 mo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Cox2">Cox et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Moon1">Moon and Haukos 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Anderson1">Anderson 2008</xref>). Additionally, our survival estimates exceeded most reported rates for other black duck populations in the Mississippi (0.49&ndash;0.66, 2&ndash;3 mo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb 1997</xref>) and Atlantic flyways (0.37&ndash;0.77, 2&ndash;4 mo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore2">Longcore et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore1">2000</xref>) during the postfledging, fall migration, and winter periods. Our survival estimates were somewhat lower than those reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Chipley1">Chipley (1995</xref>; 0.94&ndash;1.00, 3 mo), who also radio-tagged female black ducks in the TNWR. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Chipley1">Chipley (1995)</xref> estimated survival rates for females that were radio-tagged after exposure to a 30-day hunting season, whereas we calculated survival rates for ducks during the hunting (60 days) and posthunting seasons. Although we did not assess food acquisition by or body nutrient composition of black ducks, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-White2">White (1994)</xref> suggested that female black ducks may have greater winter survival in western Tennessee because of increased energy reserves compared with black ducks wintering farther north in the Mississippi and Atlantic flyways.Body mass is often used as an index of an individual's energy reserves and overall condition, and maintaining sufficient reserves is essential for winter survival of birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Labocha1">Labocha and Hayes 2012</xref>). We found that survival generally increased as body mass at capture increased; a bird of average body mass had ~18&percnt; lower interval survival than a bird 100 g heavier on the same date of capture. These results corroborate the findings of several studies of black ducks and Mallards in different wintering regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore2">Longcore et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Bergan1">Bergan and Smith 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Davis3">Davis et al. 2011</xref>). However, for wintering birds a tradeoff exists between minimizing predation and starvation risks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lima1">Lima 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>). While lean birds spend less time and energy foraging to maintain fat reserves than heavier birds, the former may have lower fat reserves available to sustain them through fluctuations in food availability, weather, and disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lima1">Lima 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>). Conversely, heavy birds may have greater reserves to endure environmental fluctuations than lean birds, but also may have greater exposure to or decreased capability to escape from predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lima1">Lima 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer1">Zimmer et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer2">2011</xref>). Thus, an optimal body mass for overwintering birds is an intermediate body mass that minimizes predation and starvation risks while maintaining some fat reserves and escape capabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lima1">Lima 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>).The effect of body mass on female black duck survival differed between winters in our study, which may be related to the concept of optimal body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lima1">Lima 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy3">Conroy et al. 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer1">Zimmer et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer2">2011</xref>). For example, a duck with a body mass 100 g above average had 9&percnt; greater interval survival than a duck with average body mass on the same date of capture during the winter of 2010&ndash;2011, but a heavier bird had slightly lower survival than an average one during the following winter. Optimal body mass in waterfowl may decrease in response to predation risk, likely to facilitate escape from and reduce exposure to predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer1">Zimmer et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Zimmer2">2011</xref>), or if resources are predictable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers1">Rogers 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">2015</xref>). A decrease in optimal body mass and thus lower survival for heavier ducks, such as during the hunting season of 2011&ndash;2012, may have been related to greater resource predictability in the winter of 2011&ndash;2012 because of milder temperatures and greater precipitation than in the winter of 2010&ndash;2011. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb (1997)</xref> speculated that radio-tagged black ducks in Ohio with greater body mass had lower survival because they ventured more frequently from sanctuaries into areas with increased hunting risk. However, movement data from our study did not appear to support <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb's (1997)</xref> hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb 2014</xref>).Alternatively, contrasting effects of body mass on survival may have been related to food availability within the sanctuary of the DRU during winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-McClanahan1">McClanahan 2015</xref>). Hunting pressure surrounding the DRU contributes to reduced use of habitat outside the DRU during the hunting season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb 2014</xref>), which may increase demand for available resources in the DRU as winter progresses. One hypothesis is that black ducks with below-average body mass may be able to sustain themselves until hunting-related risks have passed, as it is less energetically costly to maintain a lower body mass, whereas depleting and dynamic food resources in the DRU and other exploited habitats may induce ducks with above-average body mass to seek food or other resources outside the DRU, despite risks to survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Loesch1">Loesch et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Keller1">Keller et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-McClanahan1">McClanahan 2015</xref>). Food resources during the posthunting season in late winter have been diminished greatly by foraging and natural decomposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Foster1">Foster et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Hagy1">Hagy and Kaminski 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-McClanahan1">McClanahan 2015</xref>), and decreased survival for ducks of below-average body mass could be related to these within-winter changes in resource availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-McClanahan1">McClanahan 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Rogers2">Rogers 2015</xref>). Studies refining estimates of available resources in the TNWR are needed to determine the actual availability of food resources throughout winter, especially within emergent and scrub&ndash;shrub wetlands, which were strongly selected by black ducks radio-tagged in the TNWR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-McClanahan1">McClanahan 2015</xref>).Weather may affect habitat use, movements, food availability, and behavior, and thus, indirectly, the survival of birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Bennett1">Bennett and Bolen 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Nichols1">Nichols et al. 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Whyte1">Whyte and Bolen 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Lovvorn1">Lovvorn 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robinson1">Robinson et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Sauter1">Sauter et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Salewski1">Salewski et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez et al. 2014</xref>). A direct link between survival and weather has been difficult to demonstrate empirically for wintering ducks because of complicated indirect effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore2">Longcore et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Dooley1">Dooley et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Gunnarsson1">Gunnarsson et al. 2012</xref>; cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb 1997</xref>). Despite not detecting an effect of weather covariates on the survival of black ducks, which may be partially explained by few mortalities during our study, we observed almost twice as many mortalities during the winter of 2010&ndash;2011, which was more severe than the winter of 2011&ndash;2012 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-t04">Table 4</xref>). For example, in the winter of 2011&ndash;2012, compared with the winter of 2010&ndash;2011, we observed higher temperatures and more rainfall, which can create additional wetlands and provide more food resources, increasing accessibility to those resources because of less snow or ice cover, and thereby potentially reducing mortalities. Colder temperatures and increased snow and ice in the winter of 2010&ndash;2011 may have restricted access to critical resources for black ducks, thus resulting in our observations of more mortalities and birds with below-average body mass having lower survival than during the following milder winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Albright1">Albright et al. 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>). Furthermore, indirect effects of weather conditions (e.g., poor body condition due to decreased food availability) could increase the vulnerability of black ducks to predation or other sources of mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Todd1">Todd et al. 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Albright1">Albright et al. 1983</xref>). Harsh weather conditions also may exacerbate stress on birds related to carrying radio-transmitters, and increased weight loss during already stressful conditions may lead to more mortalities, such as in the 2010&ndash;2011 winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Pietz1">Pietz et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Robb1">Robb 1997</xref>).Both additive and compensatory hunting mortality have been demonstrated for black ducks, and different populations and sex and age groups are at differential risk of hunting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz2">Krementz et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore1">Longcore et al. 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">Krementz et al. (1988)</xref> found no evidence to support compensatory hunting mortality in black duck populations in the Mississippi Flyway, and their results for female black ducks in the Tennessee River region indicated additive hunting mortality for this population. While previous research has linked black duck survival to exposure to hunting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz2">Krementz et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore2">Longcore et al. 1991</xref>), we did not detect a difference in survival between hunting and nonhunting periods, which may have been due to the small number of mortalities that occurred during this study. However, hunting was a source of mortality for female black ducks in our study (winter 2011&ndash;2012, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 5; seasons after radio-tagging, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 10). Similarly, despite not finding a statistical effect of age on survival of female black ducks, 10 of 14 mortalities recorded during our study were juvenile females; indeed, several studies have demonstrated lower survival of postfledging, juvenile black ducks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz2">Krementz et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Krementz3">1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Longcore2">Longcore et al. 1991</xref>).Our results suggest that the TNWR is an important wintering area for black ducks in the Mississippi Flyway, and we speculate that winter mortality is not a primary factor contributing to declining abundance of this species in the refuge. While fewer black ducks wintering in the TNWR may be related to a shift in the species' range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Link1">Link et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Brook1">Brook et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-NationalAudubonSociety1">National Audubon Society 2013</xref>), it is unclear what factors might be influencing this shift (e.g., climate change, habitat quantity and quality, competition with Mallards). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Newcomb1">Newcomb (2014)</xref> reported potential differences in habitat use between surviving and dying black ducks, but this comparison was limited by a paucity of mortalities. Thus, we recommend determining habitat-specific survival during winter to identify &ldquo;suitable&rdquo; habitats (i.e. those promoting survival; sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Fretwell1">Fretwell 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Kaminski1">Kaminski and Elmberg 2014</xref>) for black ducks, as well as identifying any possible resource limitations that could be inducing competition with Mallards or increased exposure to hunting. Additionally, although survival did not differ between hunting and posthunting periods in our study, black ducks were exposed to hunting pressure at more northerly latitudes before arriving on their wintering grounds. Mortality rates during other periods of the annual cycle, such as migration, can influence annual survival rates and population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Klaassen1">Klaassen et al. 2014</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that potential carryover effects from migration into winter and subsequent breeding periods be investigated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Sedinger2">Sedinger et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Sedinger1">Sedinger and Alisauskas 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Hostetler1">Hostetler et al. 2015</xref>) for black duck populations in both flyways, which may be increasingly important as this species' range continues to shift to the northeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Link1">Link et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-Brook1">Brook et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-33-NationalAudubonSociety1">National Audubon Society 2013</xref>).Our project would not have been possible without the support of all TNWR personnel, especially C. Ferrell, R. Wheat, and D. Zabriskie. S. Bard, S. Bearden, R. Corlew, A. Fish, C. King, and T. Peterson provided critical assistance in the field with data collection. We extend special thanks to B. E. Davis, J. Martin, and M. Schummer for their counsel, and also to A. Monroe for statistical assistance and for providing comments on earlier drafts of this manuscript. We would also like to thank two anonymous reviewers for comments and suggestions that greatly improved our manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Our research was funded by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Mississippi State University, the Forest and Wildlife Research Center (FWRC), University of Tennessee Institute of Agriculture, and the Central Hardwoods Joint Venture. None of our funders had any influence on the content of the submitted or published manuscript and did not require approval of the final manuscript to be published.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Our manuscript has been approved for publication as FWRC WFA401, and our capture and handling protocol was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) at Mississippi State University (&num; 10-070).<bold>Author contributions:</bold> K.C.N., J.B.D., R.M.K., and M.J.G. conceived the idea, design, and experiment; K.C.N. collected the data and conducted the research; K.C.N., J.B.D., R.M.K., and M.J.G. wrote the paper; and K.C.N. designed the methods and analyzed the data.