 Variables associated with detection probability, detection latency, and behavioral responses of Golden-winged Warblers (  Vermivora chrysoptera  )  Reproductive success and habitat characteristics of Golden-winged Warblers in high-elevation pasturelands  Variables associated with nest survival of Golden-winged Warblers ( Vermivora chrysoptera ) among vegetation communities commonly used for nesting  A hierarchical model combining distance sampling and time removal to estimate detection probability during avian point counts  Estimating territory and home-range sizes: Do singing locations alone provide and accurate estimate of space use?  Lme4: linear mixed-effects models using Eigen and S4. R package version 1.1-7  Aggressive responses of male sedge warblers (  Acrocephalus schoenobaenus  ) to playback of species song and sympatric species song, before and after pairing  Golden-winged Warbler (  Vermivora chrysoptera  )  Field tests of the Rosenberg-Blancher method for converting point counts to abundance estimates  Golden-winged Warbler Atlas Project  Counting birds: The problem of variable hearing abilities  Statistical approaches to the analysis of point count data: A little extra information can go a long way  A removal model for estimating detection probabilities from point-count surveys  Singing behavior of Blue-winged and Golden-winged warblers and their hybrids  Reproductive isolating mechanisms in the Blue-winged Warbler&ndash;Golden-winged Warbler complex  Responses of Blue-winged Warblers and Golden-winged Warblers to their own and the other species' song  Effect of number, kind and order of song elements on playback responses of the Golden-winged Warbler  Evolution and bird sociality  Space and habitat use of breeding Golden-winged Warblers in the central Appalachian Mountains  Discrimination behavior and hybridization of the Blue-winged and Golden-winged warblers  MCMC methods for multi-response generalized linear mixed models: The MCMCglmm R package  MCMC methods for multi-response generalized linear mixed models: The MCMCglmm R package  Male song variation and female mate choice in the Golden-winged Warbler  Simulated birdwatchers' playback affects the behavior of two tropical birds  The singing behavior of Golden-winged Warblers  Design of song playback experiments  Pseudoreplication in playback experiments, revisited a decade later  Detection probability of Golden-winged Warblers during point counts with and without playback recordings  Effects of point count duration, time-of-day, and aural stimuli on detectability of migratory and resident bird species in Quintana Roo, Mexico  Sound transmission and its significance for animal vocalization. I. Temperate habitats  Using audio lures to improve Golden-winged Warbler (  Vermivora chrysoptera  ) detection during point-count surveys  The Partners in Flight Handbook on Species Assessment  Population Estimates Database, version 2013  Monitoring bird populations by point counts  An international standard for a mapping method in bird census work. International Bird Census Committee  Effect of time of day on bird activity  Setting numerical population objectives for priority landbird species  Golden-winged Warbler Status Review and Conservation Plan  Observer differences in the North American Breeding Bird Survey  Sensitivity analysis of North American bird population estimates  Distance software: Design and analysis of distance sampling surveys for estimating population size  Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; 90-day finding on a petition to list the Golden-winged Warbler as endangered or threatened  Working lands for wildlife  Extensive rangewide mitochondrial introgression indicates substantial cryptic hybridization in the Golden-winged Warbler (  Vermivora chrysoptera  )  Program MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animals  Is there an ideal behavioural experiment?  Seasonal response of Wood Thrushes to taped-playback songs  Detection probability during point counts and its associated variables are important considerations for bird population monitoring and have implications for conservation planning by influencing population estimates. During 2008&ndash;2009, we evaluated variables hypothesized to be associated with detection probability, detection latency, and behavioral responses of male Golden-winged Warblers in pastures in the Monongahela National Forest, West Virginia, USA. This is the first study of male Golden-winged Warbler detection probability, detection latency, or behavioral response based on point-count sampling with known territory locations and identities for all males. During 3-min passive point counts, detection probability decreased as distance to a male's territory and time since sunrise increased. During 3-min point counts with playback, detection probability decreased as distance to a male's territory increased, but remained constant as time since sunrise increased. Detection probability was greater when point counts included type 2 compared with type 1 song playback, particularly during the first 2 min of type 2 song playback. Golden-winged Warblers primarily use type 1 songs (often  zee bee bee bee  with a higher-pitched first note) in intersexual contexts and type 2 songs (strident, rapid stutter ending with a lower-pitched buzzy note) in intrasexual contexts. Distance to a male's territory, ordinal date, and song playback type were associated with the type of behavioral response to song playback. Overall, ~2 min of type 2 song playback may increase the efficacy of point counts for monitoring populations of Golden-winged Warblers by increasing the conspicuousness of males for visual identification and offsetting the consequences of surveying later in the morning. Because playback may interfere with the ability to detect distant males, it is important to follow playback with a period of passive listening. Our results indicate that even in relatively open pasture vegetation, detection probability of male Golden-winged Warblers is imperfect and highly variable.  Considerar la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n durante los puntos de conteo y sus variables asociadas es importante para monitorear las poblaciones de aves y tiene implicancias para la planificaci&oacute;n de la conservaci&oacute;n, ya que influencia las estimaciones poblacionales. Durante 2008&ndash;2009, evaluamos aquellas variables que se suponen asociadas con la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n, la latencia de detecci&oacute;n y las respuestas comportamentales de los machos de   Vermivora chrysoptera   en los pastizales de la Reserva Forestal Nacional Monongahela, West Virginia. Este es el primer estudio de la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n, la latencia de detecci&oacute;n y las respuestas comportamentales de los machos de   V. chrysoptera  , utilizando puntos de conteo y conociendo las localizaciones territoriales y las identidades de todos los machos. Durante puntos de conteo pasivos de 3 min, la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n disminuy&oacute; a medida que aument&oacute; la distancia a los territorios de los machos y el tiempo desde el amanecer. Durante los conteos por punto de 3 min empleando la reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados, la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n disminuy&oacute; a medida que aument&oacute; la distancia al territorio de los machos, pero permaneci&oacute; constante a medida que aument&oacute; el tiempo desde el amanecer. La probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n fue mayor cuando los conteos por punto incluyeron la reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados de tipo 2 comparados con los de tipo 1, particularmente durante los primeros 2 min de reproducci&oacute;n de cantos de tipo 2 previamente grabados. Los individuos de   V. chrysoptera   usaron principalmente cantos de tipo 1 (usualmente  zee bee bee bee  con una primera nota m&aacute;s aguda) en contextos intersexuales y cantos de tipo 2 (estridente con un tartamudeo r&aacute;pido que termina con una nota zumbido de baja frecuencia) en contextos intrasexuales. La distancia al territorio de un macho, el n&uacute;mero de fecha ordinal y la reproducci&oacute;n de tipos de canto previamente grabados se asociaron con el tipo de respuesta comportamental ante la reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados. En total, la reproducci&oacute;n de ~2 min de cantos de tipo 2 previamente grabados puede aumentar la eficacia de los puntos de conteo para monitorear las poblaciones de   V. chrysoptera  , al aumentar la visibilidad de los machos para su identificaci&oacute;n visual y contrarrestar las consecuencias de censar al final de la ma&ntilde;ana. Debido a que la reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados puede interferir con la habilidad para detectar a machos distantes, es importante que luego de la reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados siga un per&iacute;odo de escucha pasiva. Nuestros resultados indican que incluso en pastizales relativamente abiertos, la probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n de los machos de   V. chrysoptera   es imperfecta y altamente variable.   Palabras clave:  canto, distancia, estaci&oacute;n, estimaci&oacute;n poblacional, puntos de conteo, reproducci&oacute;n de cantos previamente grabados, tiempo  The Golden-winged Warbler (  Vermivora chrysoptera  ) is listed as endangered in Canada ( http://www.sararegistry.gc.ca ), is undergoing status review for listing in the United States ( U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2011 ), and is one subject of a multi-million-dollar conservation partnership between the U.S. Natural Resources Conservation Service (USNRCS) and Fish and Wildlife Service ( USNRCS 2012 ), necessitating continued monitoring efforts. Unfortunately, Golden-winged Warbler detection probability during point counts, including the North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS), typically is highly variable and &lt;1.0 ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2008 ,  McNeil et al. 2014 ). The birds' high-frequency (6&ndash;9 kHz) song, which they sing infrequently even during peak breeding times ( Ficken and Ficken 1967 ,  Highsmith 1989 ), degrades quickly over distance ( Marten and Marler 1977 ) and may be difficult to detect, depending on observer age and experience ( Emlen and DeJong 1992 ). As a result, investigators sometimes propose using audio playback of conspecific songs (hereafter &ldquo;playback&rdquo;) during point counts to increase detection probability ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  McNeil et al. 2014 ), defined as the probability of an observer detecting an individual bird during a point count.  Golden-winged Warblers have 2 song types, each with considerable variation ( Harper et al. 2010 ). The type 1 song, an introductory note followed by 3 lower-frequency notes, is used primarily in intersexual contexts (Highsmith 1989) but elicits strongest intrasexual responses (Ficken and Ficken 1973). Type 1 song may serve as an isolating mechanism between Golden-winged and Blue-winged warblers ( V. cyanoptera ; Ficken and Ficken 1968, Gill and Murray 1972). Type 2 song is used primarily in intrasexual contexts, such that during agonistic encounters the proportion of type 1 song decreases and the proportion of type 2 song increases. Interspecific discrimination of type 2 song is poor for Golden-winged and Blue-winged warblers ( Gill and Murray 1972 ,  Highsmith 1989 ). Golden-winged and Blue-winged warblers and their hybrids may sing either or both of the parent species' type 1 songs, and type 2 songs can be indistinguishable among species ( Confer et al. 2011 ), making aural identification problematic in areas of sympatry. Use of 1.3 min ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ) and 3 min ( McNeil et al. 2014 ) of type 1 playback resulted in increases of 0.07&ndash;0.19 and 0.22 in detection probability, respectively. Detection probability may increase with playback duration ( Kroodsma 1986 ), but detection latency, defined as the amount of time elapsed to initial detection of an individual bird, has not been studied in Golden-winged Warblers. Measuring detection latency, as opposed to conducting point counts with different playback durations, could help establish a standard playback duration and listening interval for this species by determining how long it takes for males to respond. A comparison of detection probability using playback of both song types also has not been completed. Overall, a better understanding of detection probability with playback is needed to improve monitoring efforts for Golden-winged Warblers.  Golden-winged Warbler singing rates decrease as the breeding season progresses, especially after pairing ( Ficken and Ficken 1967 ,  Highsmith 1989 ), resulting in seasonal decreases in detection probability during point counts ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ). As such, point-count results may be biased by when they are conducted (e.g., BBS routes in West Virginia, USA, generally conducted during May 27&ndash;July 7; T. R. Fox personal communication). Measuring detection probability at different times during the breeding season can improve monitoring efforts by revealing the times of the season with the greatest detection probabilities and the consequences of surveying outside of this window.  Partners in Flight population estimates, which were derived from BBS data and were considered when prioritizing conservation efforts ( Rich et al. 2004 ,  Panjabi et al. 2005 ), originally relied on the assumption that all male Golden-winged Warblers present within 200 m of point-count locations were detected during a 3-min point count without playback ( Rosenberg and Blancher 2005 ). However, the species' peak singing times do not coincide well with the BBS seasonal sample period ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ).  Confer et al. (2008)  used BBS-style point counts in southern New York and detected only 3&percnt; of Golden-winged Warblers. Additional tests of the &ldquo;200-m assumption&rdquo; are needed because other studies ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2008 ) did not explicitly test for associations between detection probability and distance or include pasturelands, a relatively open shrubland cover type used for nesting in the central and southern Appalachian regions ( Aldinger and Wood 2014 ,  Aldinger et al. 2015 ). Only after further tests of the 200-m assumption, under various conditions representative of those found along BBS routes, can we arrive at more accurate estimates of population size for Golden-winged Warblers ( Partners in Flight Science Committee 2013 ).  We designed our study to examine detection probability, detection latency, and implied perfect detection of behavioral responses within 200 m of point-count locations, the presumed maximum detection distance for male Golden-winged Warblers, with the objective of improving population estimates that are based on assumptions related to point-count sampling ( Rosenberg and Blancher 2005 ). We evaluated associations of detection probability, detection latency, and behavioral responses with (1) distance, (2) observer, (3) use of playback, (4) playback type, (5) time since sunrise, and (6) time of season. This study represents an important contribution to the literature on detection probability because our empirically derived (rather than theoretically derived) estimates of detection probability provide a better understanding of the magnitude and variability of previous estimates ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2008 ,  McNeil et al. 2014 ) and because our methods could be applied to other species.  We studied 6 fenced pastures (334 ha; 800&ndash;1,200 m elevation) on the Monongahela National Forest in West Virginia, USA: 4 pastures (99 ha; range: 7&ndash;41 ha) near Elkins, Randolph County, during 2008&ndash;2009 and 2 pastures (117 ha total fenced area; range: 56&ndash;179 ha) near Marlinton, Pocahontas County, during 2009. Annual (May 15&ndash;October 15) low-intensity grazing by cattle and horses and periodic mowing maintained the shrubland stage of succession. Based on manual digitization of aerial photographs, vegetative cover types were patchily distributed within pastures and included grass and herbaceous vegetation (range: 5&ndash;30&percnt;), raspberry and blackberry (  Rubus   spp.; range: 5&ndash;10&percnt;), shrub and sapling (range: 30&ndash;80&percnt;), and canopy tree (&gt;10 cm diameter at breast height &lsqb;dbh&rsqb;; range: 5&ndash;40&percnt;) cover surrounded by contiguous closed-canopy forest (trees &gt;10 cm dbh). Dominant plant species included sweet vernalgrass (  Anthoxanthum odoratum  ), goldenrod (  Solidago   spp.), devil's darning needles (  Clematis virginiana  ), blackberry, hawthorn (  Crataegus   spp.), and black locust (  Robinia pseudoacacia  ). Most Golden-winged Warbler territories were near the perimeters of the pastures, where the dominant cover type transitioned from grasses to shrubs to contiguous closed-canopy forest. To delineate areas for Golden-winged Warbler point counts and territory mapping, we defined &ldquo;territory vegetation&rdquo; as patches &ge;0.2 ha of herbaceous (range: 45&ndash;75&percnt;), shrub (range: 45&ndash;75&percnt;), and canopy (range: 5&ndash;45&percnt;) cover adjacent to a closed-canopy forest ( Confer et al. 2011 ).  We initially established point-count locations on a 100 &times; 100 m grid overlain on each pasture. We eliminated point-count locations that were not within Golden-winged Warbler territory vegetation or that were close enough to other point-count locations that males might be double-counted. The final remaining point-count locations (2008,  n  &equals; 12; 2009,  n  &equals; 28) were &ge;263 m apart. The number of point-count locations per pasture (range: 2&ndash;9) depended on the amount of territory vegetation available in each pasture. Because all territory vegetation on the 6 pastures was within 200 m of a point-count location and pastures were surrounded by nearly 100&percnt; closed-canopy forest with open understory (trees &gt;10 cm dbh), we assumed that males generally were present and detectable within the estimated maximum detection distance of 200 m ( Rosenberg and Blancher 2005 ). Radio-tagged males on these pastures were in territory vegetation 98&percnt; of the time ( n  &equals; 488 telemetry locations;  Frantz et al. 2015 ). Even males that entered forested areas generally would still be within 200 m of point-count locations because of the close juxtaposition of territory vegetation and forest.  During May 1&ndash;9 of each year, K.R.A. trained all observers together as a group. We observed male warblers in the field, examined field-guide illustrations, and listened to song recordings to practice identification of  Vermivora  species by sight and sound. To practice identification of individual male warblers, we practiced reading color-band combinations using binoculars and compared plumage and song characteristics of neighboring male warblers. We practiced distance estimation by estimating known distances. To apply the aforementioned training and to practice interpretation of behavioral responses to playback, we conducted practice point counts as a group and compared our results at the end of the point count. Practice-group point counts served to help standardize point-count results among observers.  Observers ( n  &equals; 3 in 2008,  n  &equals; 6 in 2009,  n  &equals; 6 different observers total) conducted 2 types of 6-min variable-radius point counts (Appendix  Table 5 ) at each point-count location during each of 3 periods ( n  &equals; 6 counts point &minus;1  year &minus;1 ). Each 6-min point count included a 3-min passive-listening portion (passive subcount) and a 3-min playback portion (playback subcount) using either type 1 or type 2 song. The 3 periods were early (May 10&ndash;21), middle (May 22&ndash;June 2), and late (June 3&ndash;15). They coincided with (1) the peak breeding season of Golden-winged Warblers in this part of West Virginia (2008&ndash;2014; earliest egg date &equals; May 9 &plusmn; 1.5 &lsqb;SE&rsqb; days, latest active nest &equals; June 23 &plusmn; 2.2 days; K. R. Aldinger personal observation); (2) Golden-winged Warbler Atlas Project (GOWAP) survey dates (May 10&ndash;June 15,  Cornell Lab of Ornithology 2008 ); and (3) the BBS, which generally occurs during June in West Virginia (T. R. Fox personal communication). We conducted point counts only during periods of clear, calm weather. We visited point-count locations during 0550&ndash;1005 hours EDT but in a different order on each visit to balance the possible effect of time since sunrise.  We defined a &ldquo;pasture survey&rdquo; as visiting all the point-count locations in a single pasture during a single period using a single point-count type (type 1 or type 2 song). We completed a pasture survey ( n  &equals; 60) in 1&ndash;4 visits (1.3 &plusmn; 0.1 visits) spanning 1&ndash;6 days (1.6 &plusmn; 0.2 days) with 1 point-count type (type 1 or type 2, order determined by coin flip), then repeated the pasture survey with the remaining point-count type 1&ndash;5 days (2.0 &plusmn; 0.2 days) later (here and below, results are presented as means &plusmn; SE). Because of the limited number of point-count locations with breeding populations of Golden-winged Warblers, we used a repeated-measures design whereby we visited each point-count location under all 6 treatment combinations ( Wiley 2003 ).  We recorded the 1-min interval when each male was initially detected and all subsequent 1-min intervals in which males were detected. We estimated initial detection distance to the nearest 5 m and checked our estimates by recording the bird's location on an aerial photograph and measuring the distance using a scale bar. We recorded whether detections were visual and the male's color-band combination if detected visually (46&percnt; of 219 detections were visually confirmed during the point count). If we could not visually confirm a male's color-band combination during the point count and we were unable to visually confirm the male's color-band combination while traveling between point-count locations, we used the male's location, individual variation in song (e.g., different numbers of notes or changes in pitch) and singing behavior (e.g., singing type 2 songs exclusively), and our detailed records of the number and location of territories based on almost daily visits (see below) to infer the male's identity. We recorded behavioral responses to playback if they occurred during the playback subcount. Possible behaviors ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2011 ) included approaching the speaker, initiating type 1 or type 2 songs or chipping vocalizations, shortening (fewer notes than in prestimulus songs) or lengthening (more notes) songs, singing a whisper song (a quiet version often given during agonistic encounters or in the presence of a female), switching song type, increasing the rate of singing, and other territorial displays (e.g., slow undulating moth-flight, flaring crown feathers, and circling the speaker). Observers interpreted and recorded all behavioral responses in the field.  We broadcast songs at a volume similar to that of an undisturbed singing male Golden-winged Warbler and at a low enough volume to avoid audible distortion or feedback from the speaker (no. 277-1008, Radio Shack, Fort Worth, Texas, USA). In prestudy field tests, observers could hear type 1 and type 2 song broadcasts at distances of ~120 m in territory vegetation.  We captured males in mist nets using playback of songs of 6 different male Golden-winged Warblers and a decoy to avoid habituation to playback. We marked males with unique combinations of colored leg bands (44&percnt; of males in 2008 and 76&percnt; of males in 2009). Unmarked males generally were neighbored by marked males, allowing the lack of color bands to serve as a mark. At least every other day during May and June, 2008&ndash;2009, from dawn to 1400 hours EDT, we searched all available territory vegetation (64 ha with 4 observers in 2008; 165 ha with 6 observers in 2009) and recorded locations of males either on printed maps of 2007 National Agriculture Imagery Program imagery or on Garmin eTrex global positioning system units (typically accurate to &lt;5 m). We used point-count locations as a spot-mapping grid ( Bibby et al. 2000 ) to ensure that we searched all territory vegetation available on each pasture. To avoid collecting locations not representative of a male's breeding territory, during territory mapping we watched individual males for behavioral cues (i.e. fledgling feeding, frequent or extended extraterritorial movements, and lack of singing and territorial defense) that suggested the completion of their nesting period. We delineated a territory when we observed a male on &ge;3 visits over &ge;8 visits to a pasture ( Robbins 1970 ). Between nest searching ( Aldinger and Wood 2014 ), territory mapping, and point counts, we made &gt;8 visits to each pasture and recorded locations of individual males ( n  &equals; 59 males, 65 territories) on 9.0 &plusmn; 0.7 days. We were confident that all territorial males were mapped and counted and that all territories were located within the pastures. We created minimum convex polygons (MCPs) for each male using 100&percnt; of the locations recorded during its nesting period (i.e. after establishment of a territory and before fledging young). Dates of all locations were within the mean nesting period of May 9&ndash;June 23 for these pastures (K. R. Aldinger personal observation). We considered our MCPs as approximations of the principal defended areas of the breeding territories of male Golden-winged Warblers ( Anich et al. 2009 ,  Frantz et al. 2015 ). For all males, we measured the distance from the center of the male's MCP to the nearest point-count location.  In 2010, we collected blood samples from phenotypic Golden-winged Warblers ( n  &equals; 22) on the same pastures as part of a collaborative study on genetic introgression among   Vermivora   spp. using mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA). We used the results of the genetic analysis to gauge the level of genetic introgression among phenotypic Golden-winged Warblers included in the study.  We included male Golden-winged Warbler phenotypes ( n  &equals; 59 males,  n  &equals; 65 territories,  n  &equals; 219 detections) in analyses and excluded Blue-winged Warbler (0 males, 0 territories, 1 detection) and hybrid (2 males, 2 territories, 6 detections) phenotypes. For modeling of detection probability, detection latency, and behavioral responses, we formulated our models at the individual level, such that an individual male Golden-winged Warbler's detection status, detection latency, or behavioral response during a subcount was a function of independent variables measured at the time of that subcount. This approach relied on the assumption that we accurately identified which males were detected or not detected during each subcount. We specified male and pasture IDs as random effects in all models because we sampled each male and pasture during each time of season (early, middle, and late) and with each point-count type (type 1 and type 2 song). Six color-banded males were known to be present in both years. When we detected an individual male during multiple point counts during a pasture survey ( n  &equals; 20 duplicate detections), we retained only the detection with a behavioral response related to territory defense or a shorter detection distance to the center of the male's MCP.  For all models, when we detected a specific male during a pasture survey, we assigned to that male the ordinal date and time since sunrise of the subcount during which the male was detected. When we failed to detect a specific male during a pasture survey, we assigned to that male the ordinal date and starting time since sunrise of the subcount nearest to the center of that male's MCP for the pasture survey during which the male was not detected. To calculate time since sunrise, we subtracted the subcount start time from the local sunrise time. We obtained daily sunrise times annually for Elkins and Marlinton, West Virginia, from the U.S. Naval Observatory ( http://aa.usno.navy.mil/data/docs/RS&lowbar;OneYear.php ). For all males, our distance variable was the distance from the center of the male's MCP to the nearest point-count location. We considered differences statistically significant at &alpha; &le; 0.05.  We ran 2 separate models to evaluate detection probability during passive subcounts (hereafter &ldquo;passive detection probability model&rdquo;) and playback subcounts (&ldquo;playback detection probability model&rdquo;). We used logistic mixed-effects models in package &lsquo;lme4&prime; version 1.1-7 ( Bates et al. 2014 ) in program R version 3.1.2 ( R Development Core Team 2014 ) to model associations between detection status and distance, observer, ordinal date, playback subcount type (type 1 and type 2; for playback subcounts only), time since sunrise, and year. We considered each male a Bernoulli trial wherein a male could be detected (&ldquo;1&rdquo;) during &ge;1 min during a subcount or not detected (&ldquo;0&rdquo;) during a subcount.  We ran 2 separate models to evaluate detection latency during passive subcounts (hereafter &ldquo;passive latency model&rdquo;) and playback subcounts (&ldquo;playback latency model&rdquo;). We used Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo multinomial logistic mixed-effects models in package &lsquo;MCMCglmm' version 2.21 ( Hadfield 2010 ) in program R to model associations between detection latency and distance, ordinal date, playback subcount type (type 1 or type 2 song; for playback subcounts only), time since sunrise, and year. We followed  Hadfield (2009)  to set up and run the latency models, and we used the least-informative proper priors. We set the number of iterations to 100,000 preceded by a burn-in period of 15,000 iterations. We chose the &ldquo;categorical&rdquo; family in &lsquo;MCMCglmm' and assigned each response to 1 of 4 mutually exclusive latency categories: not detected, minute 1, minute 2, and minute 3. We set the &ldquo;not detected&rdquo; category as the baseline for comparison.  To model associations between behavioral responses during playback subcounts and distance, ordinal date, playback subcount type (type 1 or type 2 song), time since sunrise, and year (hereafter &ldquo;behavioral response model&rdquo;), we used the same parameters and process described above for the playback latency model ( Hadfield 2010 ). We assigned each behavioral response to 1 of 4 mutually exclusive behavioral response categories: vocal response (initiate type 1, 2, or chipping; increase singing rate; whisper; shorten or lengthen song; switch song type), territorial response (approach audio device and territorial display), elaborate response (both a vocal and territorial response as described above), and no response (either detected but without an apparent response to playback or not detected, because both represent a lack of detectable response). We set the &ldquo;no response&rdquo; category as the baseline for comparison.  Male Golden-winged Warblers began arriving and establishing territories on April 26, 2008, and April 28, 2009. We delineated 27 Golden-winged Warbler territories in 2008 and 38 in 2009, representing 59 different males. We observed presumed breeding pairs in 59&percnt; of territories (all Golden-winged Warbler &times; Golden-winged Warbler pairs), based on social pairing criteria in  Will (1986) , although we may have underestimated pairing rate based on nest discovery rates on these pastures in later years ( Aldinger and Wood 2014 ). Thus, we did not include pairing status in our analyses. On these pastures in 2010, no phenotypic Golden-winged Warblers ( n  &equals; 22) had Blue-winged Warbler mtDNA (L. M. Stenzler, Cornell Lab of Ornithology, personal communication).  Mean detection probability of male Golden-winged Warblers during passive subcounts was 0.45 &plusmn; 0.02 and decreased as distance to a male's MCP center increased ( Figure 1 A) and as time since sunrise increased ( Figure 1 B). Detection probability during passive subcounts was not associated with observer, ordinal date, or year ( Table 1 ).  Mean marginal predicted detection probability (black lines) of male Golden-winged Warblers in pastures in the Monongahela National Forest, West Virginia, USA (2008&ndash;2009) as functions of ( A ) distance from the center of a male's minimum convex polygon to the nearest point count location and ( B ) time since sunrise during passive subcounts and ( C ) distance from the center of a male's minimum convex polygon to the nearest point count location during playback subcounts. Gray lines represent predicted probabilities for individual males ( n  &equals; 59). The rug plots along the x-axes (black bars) show the proportion of samples across the range of distances and times.  Parameter estimates, precisions, and probabilities from logistic mixed-effects models of detection probability during passive and playback subcounts of male Golden-winged Warblers in pastures in the Monongahela National Forest, West Virginia, USA (2008&ndash;2009), as a function of distance to the male's minimum convex polygon (MCP) center, observer, ordinal date, playback type (type 1 or type 2 song; for playback subcounts only), time since sunrise, and year. We specified male ( n  &equals; 59) and pasture ( n  &equals; 6) IDs as random effects. Values in bold are statistically significant.  Mean detection probability during playback subcounts was 0.45 &plusmn; 0.02 and decreased as distance to a male's MCP center increased ( Figure 1 C). Type 2 playback subcounts (0.52 &plusmn; 0.02) had greater detection probability than type 1 subcounts (0.39 &plusmn; 0.02). Detection probability during playback subcounts was not associated with observer, ordinal date, time since sunrise, or year ( Table 1 ).  Using passive subcounts, most males were not detected ( n  &equals; 213), followed by detections during minutes 1 ( n  &equals; 128), 2 ( n  &equals; 32), and 3 ( n  &equals; 17). Parameter estimates ( Table 2 ) for latency models can be interpreted as the log odds of detection in minute 1, 2, or 3 compared with no detection (the baseline). For example, using the passive latency model, a 1-unit increase in distance was associated ( P  &equals; 0.003) with a decrease in the log odds of detection during minute 1, compared with no detection in the amount of 0.011. Distance to a male's MCP center, time since sunrise, and year were negatively associated with the likelihood of detection during minute 1, compared with no detection ( Table 2 ).  Parameter estimates (with 95&percnt; confidence limits in parentheses) and probabilities from Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo multinomial logistic mixed-effect models of detection latency during passive and playback subcounts of male Golden-winged Warblers in pastures in the Monongahela National Forest, West Virginia, USA (2008&ndash;2009), as a function of distance to the male's minimum convex polygon (MCP) center, ordinal date, playback type (type 1 or type 2 song; for playback subcounts only), time since sunrise, and year. We specified male ( n  &equals; 59) and pasture ( n  &equals; 6) IDs as random effects. Values in bold are statistically significant.  Using playback subcounts, most males were not detected ( n  &equals; 213), followed by detections during minutes 1 ( n  &equals; 112), 2 ( n  &equals; 36), and 3 ( n  &equals; 29). Distance to a male's MCP center and year were negatively associated with the likelihood of detection during minutes 1, 2, and 3, compared with no detection ( Table 2 ). We were more likely to detect males during minutes 1 and 2 with type 2 playback subcounts than with type 1 playback subcounts ( Table 2 ).  Among behavioral response types, the most common was no response ( n  &equals; 266), followed by elaborate response, which included both a vocal and territorial response ( n  &equals; 49); vocal response ( n  &equals; 45); and territorial response ( n  &equals; 30). Parameter estimates ( Table 3 ) for the behavioral response model can be interpreted as the log odds of observing elaborate, territorial, or vocal responses compared with no response (the baseline). For example, a 1-unit increase in ordinal date was associated ( P  &equals; 0.008) with a decrease in the log odds of elaborate response, compared with no response in the amount of 0.058. Distance to a male's MCP center and ordinal date were negatively associated with the likelihood of elaborate response compared with no response ( Table 3 ). Distance to a male's MCP center and ordinal date were negatively associated with the likelihood of territorial response compared with no response, and territorial responses were more likely using type 2 subcounts ( Table 3 ).  Parameter estimates (with 95&percnt; confidence limits in parentheses) and probabilities from a Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo multinomial logistic mixed-effects model of behavioral response category as a function of distance to the male's minimum convex polygon center (MCP), ordinal date, and playback type (type 1 or type 2 song), time since sunrise, and year, in male Golden-winged Warblers in pastures in the Monongahela National Forest, West Virginia, USA (2008&ndash;2009). We specified male ( n  &equals; 59) and pasture ( n  &equals; 6) IDs as random effects. Values in bold are statistically significant.  This is the first study of male Golden-winged Warbler detection probability, detection latency, or behavioral response to have known territory locations and identities for all males. Mean detection probability values for our passive and playback subcounts were imperfect and generally equal ( Figure 1 A,  1 C). Passive subcounts were within the range of comparable studies, whereas playback subcounts, particularly type 1 subcounts, were near the lower end of the range of comparable studies ( Table 4 ). In part, we attribute our lower values of mean detection probability during playback subcounts to the fact that we recorded detections while playback was being broadcast, as opposed to after the playback. We further add that our study design was biased toward increased detection probability, in that our point-count observers had prior knowledge of male locations and singing behavior from territory mapping and passive subcounts that occurred immediately before our playback subcounts. Thus, in contrast to other studies, we did not see a pronounced difference in Golden-winged Warbler detection probability between passive and playback subcounts. Nonetheless, our results add to the growing knowledge that detection probability during 3-min point counts is consistently &lt;1.0, regardless of the conditions under which point counts are conducted ( Sauer et al. 1994 ,  Huffman 1997 ,  Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2008 ,  McNeil et al. 2014 ) and provide a mechanistic explanation of how variables are associated with detection probability.  Summary results from studies of male Golden-winged Warbler detection probability.  Revisions to the assumed maximum detection distance (125 m in  Panjabi et al. 2005 ) would decrease the error in population estimates for Golden-winged Warblers ( Thogmartin 2010 ), but population size likely would still be underestimated because detection probability during our passive subcounts was &lt;1.0 at distances &lt;125 m. In fact, our mean detection probability during passive subcounts ranged from 0.60 when MCP centers were 4 m (the minimum distance) from a point-count location to 0.39 when MCP centers were 125 m from a point-count location.  Confer et al. (2008)  detected a male Golden-winged Warbler with an active nest within 50 m of a point-count location during only 12&percnt; of 3-min point counts. A single species-specific correction factor for converting relative counts into absolute population estimates would be convenient but seems unlikely to be agreed upon, even with further research, because of variability in detection probability among observers ( Sauer et al. 1994 ), distances, geographic locations, point-count protocols, vegetation community types ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ,  Confer et al. 2008 ,  McNeil et al. 2014 ), and weather ( Huffman 1997 ). Furthermore, there are multiple reliable methods that account for detection probability and do not require 100&percnt; detection&mdash;for example, distance sampling ( Thomas et al. 2010 ), mark&ndash;recapture ( White and Burnham 1999 ), time removal ( Farnsworth et al. 2002 ), and combinations of these methods ( Amundson et al. 2014 ) can be used to estimate population size if extra information is collected ( Farnsworth et al. 2005 ).  Detection probability during passive and playback subcounts and the likelihood of elaborate and territorial responses decreased as distance from a point-count location to a male's MCP center increased. Our distance variable does not explicitly address an observer's ability to detect a Golden-winged Warbler among distances, but rather the probability that a Golden-winged Warbler will be detected given the location of its territory in relation to a point-count location. Still, based on our passive and playback detection probability models and the distances at which we detected males (maximum &equals; 190 m), the maximum detection distance for Golden-winged Warblers probably is ~200 m, though detection probability at such distances is low (0.28 with passive subcounts and 0.20 with playback subcounts). Based on the detection probabilities at 200 m and the shapes of the curves in  Figure 1 A and  1 C, playback appears to have decreased detection probability for distant males. We suspect that aural interference from the playback speaker inhibited observers' ability to hear distant males. This conclusion is further supported by the similarity of overall detection probability estimates for passive and playback subcounts (both 0.45). Distant males may have heard the playback but did not show a behavioral response because vegetation unsuitable for territories (e.g., extensive grassland) or other territorial males prevented them from approaching or because they did not perceive playback at such a long distance to be a threat.  Detection probability for most songbirds decreases as the morning progresses ( Robbins 1981 ), presumably because of decreasing natural singing rates. Undisturbed Golden-winged Warblers on our pastures also sang less as the period during 0550&ndash;1005 hours EDT progressed, indicated by decreasing detection probability during passive subcounts ( Figure 1 B). Detection probability and behavioral responses during our playback subcounts, however, were not associated with time since sunrise, which suggests that playback can be an effective tool to compensate for temporal reductions in detection probability ( Lynch 1995 ). For effective compensation of temporal reductions in detection probability, it is important to follow a playback subcount with a passive subcount to detect males that were not detected during the playback subcount because of aural interference, as was presumably the cause of similar mean detection probabilities for both passive and playback subcounts in our study.  Golden-winged Warbler singing rates are known to decrease as the breeding season progresses, particularly after pairing ( Ficken and Ficken 1967 ,  Highsmith 1989 ), leading to decreases in detection probability ( Kubel and Yahner 2007 ). However, we found no significant decrease in detection probability during May 10&ndash;June 7 on our pastures using passive or playback subcounts. Our point counts probably ended before the time when singing rates declined significantly as nests on these pastures can be active throughout June ( Aldinger and Wood 2014 ). It is difficult to speculate about detection probability outside of our point-count season, but our results suggest that researchers may be able to assume constant detection probability if point counts begin ~2 wk after arrival of the first males and last ~4 wk. Conversely, elaborate and territorial responses using playback subcounts decreased significantly as the season progressed. Whether the decreases in behavioral responses were due to breeding phenology ( Catchpole 1977 ,  Yahner and Ross 1995 ) or habituation to playback ( Fisher 1954 ,  Harris and Haskell 2013 ) was unclear. Anecdotally, during GOWAP surveys in Randolph and Pocahontas counties in 2008 and 2009, males sampled outside of our pastures similarly appeared to be less responsive to playback (e.g., fewer approaches and aggressive type 2 songs) later in the season. Because of the difficulty in finding adequate samples sizes of Golden-winged Warblers for playback experiments, the present study and  Kubel and Yahner (2007)  used repeated measures designs and were unable to determine reasons for declining detection probability or behavioral responses. Nonetheless, the available evidence seems to suggest that playback is most effective early in the breeding season for eliciting responses from male Golden-winged Warblers, thereby increasing visual identification.  Male Golden-winged Warblers often sing type 2 songs in intrasexual territorial disputes ( Highsmith 1989 ,  Confer et al. 2011 ). As such, we expected type 2 playback subcounts to have greater detection probability than type 1 playback subcounts because males responding to the former might perceive our playback as an aggressive intruder. Not only did our playback detection probability and latency models support this presumption, but our behavioral response model also showed that territorial response was more likely with type 2 than with type 1 playback. If using type 2 song with point counts, it is important to consider potential responses by and misidentification of Blue-winged Warblers (and hybrids), which may not distinguish between type 2 songs of their own species and those of Golden-winged Warblers ( Gill and Murray 1972 ). On the other hand, we now suspect that interspecific discrimination of type 1 songs also may be poor because of increasing range overlap and genetic introgression ( Vallender et al. 2009 ), despite historical evidence that Golden-winged and Blue-winged warblers responded only weakly or rarely to each other's type 1 songs ( Ficken and Ficken 1969 ,  Gill and Murray 1972 ). Even in the case that multiple   Vermivora   spp. phenotypes all respond to type 2 playback, our results suggest that their response is more likely to be rapid (during the first 2 min of playback) and territorial (e.g., approach, slow undulating moth-flight, and circling the speaker) than when using type 1 playback, so visual confirmation of phenotype is likely. We caution readers, however, that our playback results are based on recordings from 2 males and that characteristics of their songs could have contributed to our results ( Kroodsma et al. 2001 ).  The effect of point-count length on detection probability has been studied extensively ( Ralph et al. 1995 ) but, to our knowledge, the effect of playback duration has not been evaluated. Although we did not vary playback duration explicitly, our playback latency model gives insight into the responses of males as playback duration increased up to 3 min. Our playback latency model suggested that the previously documented difference in detection probability between playback subcount types was the result of a greater number of detections occurring during the first 2 min of type 2 playback subcounts. By minute 3, both playback subcount types were equal. Thus, if we consider mean detection probabilities from passive subcounts (0.45), type 1 playback subcounts (0.39), and type 2 playback subcounts (0.52) and notice that type 1 playback subcounts are lower than passive subcounts in terms of detection probability, then by minute 3 our type 2 playback subcounts probably are not effectively increasing detection probability. Therefore, our results suggest that 2 min of type 2 playback (again, followed by passive listening) will result in the most efficient (detections per unit time) point-count protocol.  Our results are strong because they were derived empirically (i.e. from known detections and nondetections of males with known locations and identities) rather than theoretically (i.e. from distance-sampling, mark&ndash;recapture, or time-removal methods). We have provided important information on variables associated with detection probability, detection latency, and behavioral responses of Golden-winged Warblers that can be considered when designing monitoring protocols. Given the imperiled status of Golden-winged Warbler populations in the Appalachian Mountain region ( Roth et al. 2012 ) and the interest in managing breeding habitat (e.g., USNRCS 2012), a standardized and logistically feasible monitoring program is needed. Passive point counts preceded by 2 min of type 2 playback, starting 11 min before sunrise to 237 min after sunrise, and conducted 2&ndash;6 wk after males first arrive on territory may yield constant and maximum, although imperfect, detection probability. Overall, even with our study design biased toward increased detection probability, detection probability was imperfect at short distances, during peak singing times, and with the aid of playback.  Logistic and administrative support was provided by the U.S. Geological Survey West Virginia Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit and by the Division of Forestry and Natural Resources at West Virginia University. Housing was provided by the West Virginia Division of Natural Resources (WVDNR) Elkins Operation Center and the Littlefield family. The U.S. Forest Service (USFS) allowed access to the pastures. We thank J. L. Kreiser, A. K. Newman, C. W. Sedgwick, L. G. Stout, D. Ware, and M. E. Weston for their long hours of work in the field. Additional help in the field was provided by M. McDermott and M. B. Shumar. Members of the Golden-winged Warbler working group provided insight for the study and manuscript. J. L. Confer and J. E. Kubel provided comments on the manuscript. G. Merovich aided in data analyses.   Funding statement:  Funding for this project was provided by the WVDNR Wildlife Diversity Program, USFS Monongahela National Forest, National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Migratory Bird Program. None of our funders had any influence on the content of the submitted or published manuscript. None of our funders require approval of the final manuscript for publication. Use of tradenames or products does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. Government.   Ethics statement:  This study was completed under the auspices of West Virginia University IACUC protocols 07-0303 and 10-0201.  Characteristics of the two types of point-count surveys of Golden-winged Warblers used in this study. We used recordings of type 1 and type 2 songs taken from the protocol of the Golden-winged Warbler Atlas Project (for protocol information and access to recordings, see  Roth et al. 2012 : appendices F&ndash;G) because these songs appeared to reflect the local dialect and were widely used with point counts for Golden-winged Warblers (K. R. Aldinger personal observation). 