Predation and reduced grazing interact to reduce recruitment and population growth in Black BrantWeb-tagging ducklings in pipped eggsHome range and movements of arctic fox (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>) in western AlaskaEstimating populations of nesting brant using aerial videographyFoods of arctic foxes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>) during winter and spring in western AlaskaArctic fox removal improves nesting success of Black BrantAfrican grazing lawns&mdash;how fire, rainfall, and grazer numbers interact to affect grass community statesUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's information criterionChanges in the composition and standing crop of salt marsh communities in response to the removal of a grazerShared predators and indirect trophic interactions: Lemming cycles and arctic-nesting geeseDemographic characteristics of molting Black Brant near Teshekpuk Lake, AlaskaReproductive effort accelerates actuarial senescence in wild birds: An experimental studyGlaucous Gull predation of goslings on the Yukon Kuskokwim Delta, AlaskaRelative influence of human harvest, carnivores, and weather on adult female elk survival across western North AmericaModel averaging and muddled multimodel inferencesIndividual covariation in life-history traits: Seeing the trees despite the forestGame birds of the Hooper Bay region, AlaskaEnvironmental change and the cost of philopatry: An example in the Lesser Snow GooseRetrospective analysis of demographic responses to environmental change: A Lesser Snow Goose exampleHow do Brent Geese (<italic>Branta b. bernicla</italic>) cope with evil? Complex relationships between predators and preyNesting ecology and behavior of Pacific Brant in AlaskaMass- and density-dependent reproductive success and reproductive costs in a capital breederNest population size and potential production of geese and Spectacled Eiders on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska, 1985&ndash;2011. Unpublished report U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Anchorage, AK, USASurvival of juvenile Black Brant during brood rearingPopulation dynamics of large herbivores: Variable recruitment with constant adult survivalEffects of the timing of multiple grazings by geese on net above-ground primary production of swards of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Puccinellia phryganodes</named-content></italic>Estimating nest success: The Mayfield method and an alternativeEvaluating apparent competition in limiting the recovery of an endangered ungulateHierarchical organization of ecosystems at multiple spatial scales on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska, USAEstimating temporary emigration and breeding proportions using capture&ndash;recapture data with Pollock's robust designMethods for studying cause-specific senescence in the wildPopulation dynamics of large and small mammals: Graeme Caughley's grand visionBody mass of pre-fledging Emperor Geese <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Chen canagica</named-content></italic>: Large-scale effects of interspecific densities and food availabilityModelling survival and testing biological hypotheses using marked animals: A unified approach with case studiesSeasonal variation in growth of Greater Snow Goose goslings: The role of food supplyPredation on wader nests in EuropeEcology of a grazing ecosystem: The SerengetiAre there trade-offs between pre- and post-fledging survival in Black Brent geese?Trade-offs between offspring fitness and future reproduction of adult female Black BrentA study of goose and brant nesting on the Yukon-Kuskokwim DeltaStatistical inference from capture data on closed animal populationsFactors affecting the survival of Barnacle Geese on migration from the breeding groundsComparative changes in adult vs. juvenile survival affecting population trends of African ungulatesCompensation and additivity of anthropogenic mortality: Life-history effects and review of methodsForage variation in brood-rearing areas used by Pacific Black Brant geese on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, AlaskaFeedback dynamics of grazing lawns: Coupling vegetation change with animal growthUtilization of capture-mark-recapture for the study of recruitment and population growth rateFemale age and egg size in the Lesser Snow GooseAge and reproductive success in female Lesser Snow Geese: Experience, senescence and the cost of philopatryProlonging the Arctic pulse: Long-term exploitation of cached eggs by arctic foxes when lemmings are scarceProtein and amino acid composition of tundra vegetation in relation to nutritional requirements of geeseEffects of visiting Black Brant nests on egg and nest survivalAdaptations to and consequences of an herbivorous diet in grouse and waterfowlSurvival and breeding advantages of larger Black Brant goslings: Within and among cohort variationFidelity and breeding probability related to population density and individual quality in Black Brent geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans</italic>)Environmental influence on life-history traits: Growth, survival, and fecundity in Black Brant (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content></italic>)Large-scale variation in growth of Black Brant goslings related to food availabilityEarly environment and recruitment of Black Brant into the breeding populationCurrent status and recent dynamics of the Black Brant breeding populationTesting for handling bias in survival estimation for Black BrantDensity dependent effects on growth, body size and clutch size in Black BrantAge-specific breeding probability in Black Brent: Effects of population densityRecent trends in first-year survival for Black Brant breeding in southwestern AlaskaBlack Brant harvest, density dependence, and survival: A record of population dynamicsDietary selectivity in relation to availability and quality of food for goslings of Cackling GeeseNesting ecology of Black Brant in AlaskaSeasonal patterns of prey availability and the foraging behavior of arctic foxes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>) in a waterfowl nesting areaVariation and distribution of Glaucous Gulls in western AlaskaBreeding production of Dark-bellied Brent Geese <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content></italic> in relation to lemming cyclesRelationships between variations of the land-ocean-atmosphere system of northeastern Asia and northwestern North AmericaTemporal and geographic variation in survival of juvenile Black BrantAerial photographic survey of brant colonies on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, AlaskaDynamics of avian populations may be governed by a complex interaction between immediate effects of predation and longer-term trophic feedbacks between individuals and their foods. We used a long-term study of uniquely marked Black Brant geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans</italic>) to estimate recruitment into the breeding population. We related recruitment to nest success, which directly affects recruitment 2 to 3 years later. We also assessed similarly time-lagged relationships between recruitment and number of nests in the colony, a measure of local density, and pre-fledging and first-year survival, the latter of which is strongly influenced by growth conditions and food availability for young of the year. We assessed relationships between number of recruits and explanatory variables in 2 sets of models, which either included or excluded a linear trend across years in numbers of recruits. The best-performing models in each model set explained a substantial proportion of the variation in numbers of recruits 2 to 3 years later (85 and 78&percnt; in the 2 model sets, respectively). First-year survival was an important predictor of number of recruits in both sets of models, whereas nest success was important only in models lacking a trend across years. Number of nests in the colony had a relatively weak negative association with number of recruits. First-year survival reflects a lagged response to earlier nest-predation events. Reduced grazing during predation events can result in loss of grazing lawns and thus reduced growth rates of future cohorts of goslings, which are regulated by food abundance and density of broods. Our finding that recruitment is insufficient to maintain the breeding population results from both direct effect of predation on nests, primarily by Arctic foxes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>), and longer-term indirect effects of such predation on first-year survival of Black Brant.Las din&aacute;micas poblacionales de las aves pueden estar gobernadas por un interacci&oacute;n compleja entre los efectos inmediatos de la depredaci&oacute;n y los efectos de largo plazo de la retroalimentaci&oacute;n tr&oacute;fica entre los individuos y su alimento. Usamos un estudio de largo plazo de gansos <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans</italic> marcados individualmente para estimar el reclutamiento de la poblaci&oacute;n reproductiva. Relacionamos el reclutamiento con el &eacute;xito de los nidos, el cual afecta directamente el reclutamiento dos a tres a&ntilde;os despu&eacute;s. De forma similar, determinamos el desfase temporal en la relaci&oacute;n entre el reclutamiento y el n&uacute;mero de nidos en la colonia, una medida de densidad local y la supervivencia durante el pre-emplumamiento y el primer a&ntilde;o; esta &uacute;ltima se ve fuertemente influenciada por las condiciones durante el crecimiento y la disponibilidad de alimento para los polluelos del a&ntilde;o. Determinamos las relaciones entre el n&uacute;mero de aves reclutadas y las variables explicativas en dos modelos que inclu&iacute;an o exclu&iacute;an una tendencia lineal en el n&uacute;mero de reclutas a trav&eacute;s de los a&ntilde;os. Los mejores modelos explicaron una proporci&oacute;n sustancial de la variaci&oacute;n en el n&uacute;mero de aves reclutadas dos a tres a&ntilde;os despu&eacute;s (85&percnt; y 78&percnt; en los dos modelos, respectivamente). La supervivencia del primer a&ntilde;o fue un predictor importante del n&uacute;mero de reclutas en ambos modelos mientas que el &eacute;xito de los nidos s&oacute;lo fue importante en los modelos que no inclu&iacute;an la tendencia a trav&eacute;s de los a&ntilde;os. El n&uacute;mero de los nidos en la colonia tuvo una asociaci&oacute;n negativa relativamente d&eacute;bil con el n&uacute;mero de aves reclutadas. La supervivencia del primer a&ntilde;o refleja una respuesta retrasada a los eventos de depredaci&oacute;n anteriores. La reducci&oacute;n en el ramoneo durante los eventos de depredaci&oacute;n puede resultar en la p&eacute;rdida de las &aacute;reas de pastoreo. Tales p&eacute;rdidas reducen las tasas de crecimiento de las cohortes futuras de polluelos, que est&aacute;n reguladas por la abundancia del alimento y la densidad de las nidadas. Nuestro hallazgo de la insuficiencia del reclutamiento para mantener la poblaci&oacute;n reproductiva resulta tanto de los efectos directos de la depredaci&oacute;n en los nidos principalmente por zorros <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic> como de los efectos indirectos a largo plazo de la depredaci&oacute;n en la supervivencia del primer a&ntilde;o de <italic>B. b. nigricans</italic>.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans,</italic> cascada tr&oacute;fica, depredaci&oacute;n, din&aacute;micas poblaiconales, &eacute;xito de los nidos, ramoneo, reclutamiento, supervivencia, zorro &aacute;rticoPopulation dynamics in species with high adult survival rates are typically governed primarily by variation in recruitment because adult survival is largely conserved, even though finite rate of population increase, &lambda;, is usually most sensitive to adult survival (Stearns 1992, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-FestaBianchet1">Festa-Bianchet et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cooch2">Cooch et al. 2001</xref>). Exceptions may exist for species subjected to human harvest if harvest rates affect adult survival sufficiently to influence &lambda; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger14">Sedinger et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Brodie1">Brodie et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Peron1">P&eacute;ron 2013</xref>). Presumably, when nonhuman predation on adults is sufficiently high, it may influence population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-OwenSmith1">Owen-Smith and Mason 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Johnson2">Johnson et al. 2013</xref>).Variation in recruitment is the principal mechanism by which density-dependent feedbacks are manifest in populations of long-lived species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Gaillard1">Gaillard et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cooch2">Cooch et al. 2001</xref>). Density dependence commonly operates directly through availability of food for young (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cooch2">Cooch et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger11">Sedinger et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">2001</xref>). When density dependence is less important, however, predation can play an important role in population regulation. In birds, nest predation is the most conspicuous predation mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Macdonald1">MacDonald and Bolton 2008</xref>), and declines in numerous avian populations have been attributed to predation on nests and young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Newton1">Newton 1998</xref>).For herbivores (e.g., geese), effects of predation and density dependence are frequently negatively associated because predation reduces grazing of vegetation, with associated positive effects on food supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Krebs1">Krebs 2009</xref>). Such effects, however, can be complex; reduced grazing clearly has the potential to increase food availability in the short term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>). Numerous species of grazers maintain grazing lawns in which plants are more nutritious than in surrounding areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Bazely1">Bazely and Jefferies 1986</xref>), and reduced grazing pressure can result in loss of grazing lawns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-McNaughton1">McNaughton 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Archibald1">Archibald 2008</xref>). Because availability of highly nutritious plants may limit productive processes (e.g., growth; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger1">Sedinger 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger3">1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Barboza1">Barboza et al. 2009</xref>), the condition of grazing lawns may influence these productive processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai2">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012b</xref>). Thus, reduced grazing due to higher predation rates might reduce grazing lawns, resulting in lagged reductions in growth and recruitment.Several species of Arctic-nesting geese maintain such grazing lawns, which are vital for growth of their offspring during the short Arctic summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Hik1">Hik et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lake1">Lake et al. 2008</xref>). Growth rates of goslings are directly related to food abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cooch1">Cooch et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lepage1">Lepage et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>), and growth largely governs survival during the first year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Owen2">Owen and Black 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cooch1">Cooch et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger4">Sedinger and Chelgren 2007</xref>). Thus, areal extent of grazing lawns and biomass of vegetation on grazing lawns directly influence recruitment of goslings into the breeding population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Herzog1">Herzog 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger13">Sedinger and Nicolai 2011</xref>).Predation by Arctic foxes on goose nests reduces grazing activity in the current year because, following loss of their nests, adult geese undergo molt migrations to distant locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Owen1">Owen 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Bollinger1">Bollinger and Derksen 1996</xref>) and do not graze vegetation near colonies. Consequently, in years of high nest predation rates, areal extent of grazing lawns is reduced because sedges in grazing lawns &ldquo;revert&rdquo; to an ungrazed, taller, and less nutritious morph (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger15">Sedinger and Raveling 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>). Thus, predation reduces recruitment immediately through reduced numbers of offspring produced and in future years by reducing food required for gosling growth and survival. The lagged negative effects of predation on recruitment mean that relatively rare predation events can lead to lower recruitment rates inadequate to balance mortality, resulting in population declines for extended periods following such predation events.We used a long-term study of individually marked Black Brant geese on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta (YKD) of western Alaska, where colonies have declined since at least the early 1980s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger9">Sedinger et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Wilson1">Wilson 2012</xref>), to assess both direct and indirect roles of predation on recruitment into the breeding population. Specifically, we assessed the effects of colony size, nest success, pre-fledging survival, and first-year (post-fledging) survival to understand the immediate role of predation vs. its delayed effects operating through changes in grazing lawns. This study complements earlier work describing long-term patterns in adult and juvenile survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger14">Sedinger et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger13">Sedinger and Nicolai 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai2">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012b</xref>) and improves understanding of the relative roles of changes in survival vs. recruitment in the population decline of a long-lived herbivore during the past 4 decades.Black Brant nest primarily colonially from the YKD in southwestern Alaska along the Pacific coast of North America to the central Canadian Arctic and on Banks and Victoria islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lewis1">Lewis et al. 2014</xref>). Black Brant also nest along the Siberian coast from approximately the Bering Strait to the Lena River Delta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lewis1">Lewis et al. 2014</xref>). Historically, &gt;70&percnt; of the Black Brant breeding population nested on the YKD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger9">Sedinger et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lewis1">Lewis et al. 2014</xref>), where &sim;80&percnt; nested in 4 major colonies, each ranging from 4,000 to 8,000 nests, with remaining nests in smaller aggregations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger9">Sedinger et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Wilson1">Wilson 2012</xref>). Colonies occur within &sim;2 km of the Bering Sea coast in tidally influenced coastal ecosystems, dominated by grass and sedge communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger9">Sedinger et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Jorgenson1">Jorgenson 2000</xref>). Some nests (typically &lt;10&percnt;) have been flooded by high tides during the nesting period in May&ndash;June up to 3 times per decade (A. W. VanDellen personal communication); more extensive flooding, destroying about 40&percnt; of nests, has occurred twice since 1950 (1966 and 1972; C. Lensink personal communication). Immediately following hatch, Black Brant lead their broods to rearing areas within 40 km of their breeding colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Flint1">Flint et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lake1">Lake et al. 2008</xref>). Rearing areas consist of graminoid meadows with grazing lawns of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Carex subspathacea</named-content></italic> along borders of mudflats and pond margins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Jorgenson1">Jorgenson 2000</xref>). We conducted this study from 1987 to 2006 at the Tutakoke River colony (TRC; 61&deg;N, 165&deg;W) on the central Bering Sea coast of the YKD. Before 2000, the TRC represented about 20&percnt; of the entire Black Brant breeding population.The 2 most important predators on nests of Black Brant during our study were Arctic foxes and Glaucous Gulls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Larus hyperboreus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Strang1">Strang 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony4">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>). Glaucous Gulls nested within the Black Brant colony in small numbers (&lt;50 nests annually), and low-level predation on nests was relatively constant, although predation on goslings was substantial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Bowman1">Bowman et al. 2004</xref>). No quantitative data exist on numbers of Arctic foxes present on the YKD, although we can infer general patterns of abundance from historical accounts and patterns of nest predation. Predation by Arctic foxes on goose nests was not observed by investigators in the coastal zone of the YKD before 1976 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Conover1">Conover 1926</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Brandt1">Brandt 1943</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Olson1">Olson 1951</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Shepherd1">Shepherd 1963</xref>), although indigenous residents indicated Arctic foxes were present in the region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Olson1">Olson 1951</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Eisenhauer1">Eisenhauer (1977)</xref> first reported Arctic foxes at TRC in 1976, observing them 4 times in 427 hr from an elevated observation tower. Nest success averaged 80&percnt; at TRC during 15 field seasons between 1950 and 1982 and was as low as 60&percnt; during only 2 years, when tidal flooding destroyed substantial numbers of nests. Irruptions of Arctic foxes resulted in destruction of &gt;80&percnt; of nests at TRC in 1982, 1984, 1985, and again in 2001 and 2003 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony4">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>; J. S. Sedinger personal communication). Arctic foxes also destroyed substantial numbers, but &lt;50&percnt;, of nests in 1994, 1997, 2004, and 2008. Most egg predation by Glaucous Gulls at TRC resulted in partial loss of the clutch, not complete destruction of nests, and Glaucous Gulls never accounted for predation in &gt;6&percnt; (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 2&percnt;) of nests. Furthermore, proportion of predation attributable to Glaucous Gulls was negatively correlated with the proportion of nests that failed (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.012), indicating that gulls were not the principal predator during years of high nest predation (J. S. Sedinger personal communication).Small numbers of Arctic foxes are capable of destroying large numbers of nests because they cache, rather than immediately consume, eggs and thus are not satiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Stickney1">Stickney 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Samelius1">Samelius et al. 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Stickney1">Stickney (1991)</xref> estimated that a single Arctic fox was capable of removing 60 eggs (15 nests) per day, or 390 nests during a 26-day incubation period, of Black Brant. Thus, 10 Arctic foxes could destroy all of the nests in a Black Brant colony containing 3,900 nests. Nonbreeding Arctic foxes are especially effective predators of Black Brant eggs because they are not tied to den sites and are free to forage throughout the nesting colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony4">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony1">Anthony 1997</xref>). Arctic foxes on the YKD depend on high tundra vole (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Microtus oeconomus</named-content></italic>) numbers to breed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony3">Anthony et al. 2000</xref>), which results in low predation rates by Arctic foxes when tundra vole numbers are high, likely associated with the spatial separation of den sites from the breeding colony. Because tundra voles on the YKD do not cycle regularly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Fischer1">Fischer and Stehn 2011</xref>; J. S. Sedinger personal observation), Arctic foxes and associated predation on nests are not cyclic as they have been in the Palearctic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Summers1">Summers 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Ebbinge1">Ebbinge and Spaans 2002</xref>) and eastern Canadian Arctic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Bety1">B&ecirc;ty et al. 2002</xref>).We annually searched for Black Brant nests on 49 plots, 100 m in diameter, randomly placed throughout TRC. We began searching plots when &sim;10&percnt; of nests had been initiated. Each plot was searched every 4 days until egg laying was complete, then all nests were checked again immediately before hatch began and again after hatch was complete. A subsample of these nests was associated with individually marked adults (discussed later) and, once hatch began, these nests were visited on alternate days until they hatched. This protocol provided a sample of nests monitored on a regular schedule from egg laying until their fates were determined. We estimated apparent nest success from this sample of nests. We also searched the entire colony and attempted to locate all nests associated with at least one marked adult by flushing females from their nests and checking their legs for tarsal bands. All nonplot nests were visited on alternate days as hatch approached to check for pipping eggs, indicating hatch. We applied uniquely numbered webtags (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Alliston1">Alliston 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Flint1">Flint et al. 1995</xref>) to as many goslings as possible on their hatch day in all nests both on and off plots, associated with a marked adult both on and off plots.We captured both adults and goslings in mid-July during the adult wing molt by herding them into corral traps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger10">Sedinger et al. 1997</xref>). We determined sex by cloacal examination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Owen1">Owen 1980</xref>), and individuals received a steel U.S. Geological Survey band and a 2.5 cm tall plastic band, engraved with a unique 3-character code. We released all individuals together following processing. In some large banding drives, some individuals were moved directly from the capture pen to the holding pen during the banding operation to reduce the time the entire group was held. These individuals were moved to the release pen throughout processing and were not excluded based on any criteria, so we do not believe any bias was introduced by this practice. We recorded the number of individuals of each age class released without bands and all previously marked individuals recaptured during banding.where <italic>n<sub>ij</sub></italic> was the number of banded recruits of age <italic>i</italic> encountered nesting in year <italic>j</italic>; <italic>&rho;<sub>(j-k)</sub></italic> was the proportion of goslings captured <italic>k</italic> years earlier that had received bands; and <italic>p̂<sub>b(j-k)</sub></italic> was the probability of capturing a gosling <italic>k</italic> years before year <italic>j</italic> (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>), <italic>p̂<sub>nj</sub></italic> was the probability of encountering a breeding female conditioned on that female nesting (from analyses for <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai2">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012b</xref>), and 0.67 was the probability that a 2- or 3-year-old female nested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger5">Sedinger et al. 2008</xref>). The latter 2 parameters were based on robust design analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Kendall1">Kendall et al. 1997</xref>). We calculated per capita recruitment as the ratio of recruits to nests in a given year.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger (2012a)</xref> developed encounter histories for goslings webtagged in the nest based on encounters of the webtags themselves to minimize bias associated with individuals receiving a visible band during their first summer. Consequently, they did not use encounters based on observation of engraved tarsal bands. Because webtags required physical capture to encounter and first-year survival was generally low, we recorded encounters of relatively small numbers of webtags following each gosling's first summer. Therefore, all such encounters were pooled to create the third encounter occasion necessary to estimate survival from hatching to fledging or pre-fledging survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lebreton1">Lebreton et al. 1992</xref>). This analysis also produced annual estimates of the probability of capturing goslings in banding drives, which we used in the calculation of the number of new recruits.Estimates of age-specific probability of breeding for 2- and 3-year olds were from a robust design CMR analysis of encounters of breeding Black Brant during nesting and banding drives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger5">Sedinger et al. 2008</xref>). The robust design uses patterns of encounters among secondary occasions (nesting and banding drives, during which the population is assumed to be closed; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Kendall1">Kendall et al. 1997</xref>) within primary occasions, which for Black Brant was the entire breeding season. Robust design produces estimates of (1) the probability of being present, synonymous with breeding in this study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>), and (2) encounter probabilities conditioned on individuals being present during a primary occasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Kendall1">Kendall et al. 1997</xref>). We used both kinds of parameters in estimates of the number of new recruits.We used estimates of both pre-fledging and first-year (post-fledging) survival as explanatory variables in the analysis of numbers of new recruits to TRC. Estimates of first-year survival were based on Cormack-Jolly-Seber models of encounters of individual goslings captured and released during banding drives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lebreton1">Lebreton et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>). Nicolai and Sedinger (2102a) produced estimates of first-year survival for each brood-rearing area from which marked goslings were released (see details on both kinds of survival estimates in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>). We calculated weighted colony-wide means of pre-fledging survival and first-year survival estimates for each year, where the weights were the inverse of the variances of the survival estimates from each brood-rearing area, and we used these means in models predicting number of recruits. We provide annual mean (&plusmn;SE) estimates of pre-fledging and first-year survival in Appendix A.U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has annually estimated numbers of nests in 4 major Black Brant colonies on the YKD using aerial videography since 1992, except in 1996 due to logistical problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony2">Anthony et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Wilson1">Wilson 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Wilson1">Wilson (2012)</xref> provides detail about the methodology, which we describe briefly here. Numbers of nests were estimated by counting Black Brant nests in images generated by digital cameras along systematically placed transects within each colony. A sample of images was ground-truthed annually to estimate detection and error rates. Approximately 10&percnt; of each colony was sampled annually, except in 1996 when no survey was flown. We used the average of numbers of nests for 1995 and 1997 to produce an estimate of number of nests for 1996.The L-P estimator assumed that the population was closed between the 2 samples. This assumption may be relaxed, as long as both marked and unmarked individuals have the same probability of leaving the population between the first and second samples, in which case the population size (number of nests in our case) at the time of the first sample is estimated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Otis1">Otis et al. 1978</xref>).We also used estimates of apparent nest success (number of nests hatched/number of nests monitored on plots) as an explanatory variable for numbers of recruits. Apparent estimates of nest success can overestimate nest success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Johnson1">Johnson 1979</xref>). Bias results primarily from (1) underestimates of numbers of failed nests and (2) reduced exposure to failure in samples discovered during incubation. Black Brant nests were conspicuous, and we generated samples from plots where we found all nests during egg laying. Thus, bias should have been minimal and relatively constant. Because our goal in this study was to assess variation in recruitment and factors affecting recruitment, we believe some bias in our estimates of nest success is acceptable.We calculated the average of each explanatory variable (e.g., nest success) for 2 and 3 years before the year of recruitment because our estimate of recruitment included 2- and 3-year-olds nesting for the first time. We standardized the response variable and each explanatory variable by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation so all variables were on the same scale. We have observed declining long-term trends in numbers of recruits, nest success, and both pre-fledging and first-year survival of Black Brant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>). Although it is biologically plausible that trends in recruits and explanatory variables were causally related, we cannot rule out the possibility that the common trend among variables represented a spurious relationship with another variable we did not consider. We thus considered 2 sets of models. One set included the following explanatory variables in candidate models: number of nests in the TRC, nest success, pre-fledging survival, and first-year survival. We also included a quadratic term for number of nests to allow for nonlinear density effects of numbers of nests. The second model set included all of the explanatory variables from the first set plus a term allowing for a linear trend across years. Although this second model set potentially provided an overly conservative assessment of the effects of explanatory variables, it protected against the potential for spurious covariation among variables through time and allowed an assessment of the residual effects of the explanatory variables on annual variation in numbers of recruits after controlling for the effects of long-term trends.We used linear models with an identity link and assuming a Gaussian error distribution in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2013</xref>) to assess models of variation in annual number of recruits. We considered all potential additive combinations of explanatory variables (linear and quadratic terms for number of nests at TRC, nest success, pre-fledging survival, and first-year survival) and a subset of their pairwise interactions in candidate models. Number of nests provided a measure of local density, which can influence food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Herzog1">Herzog 2002</xref>). We included interactions between number of nests and nest success because the product of the 2 governed density of broods. We included an interaction between nest success and first-year survival because in years of high nest success, more broods were present on rearing areas, thereby reducing food availability, growth rates, and first-year survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Herzog1">Herzog 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger4">Sedinger and Chelgren 2007</xref>). We use Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size (AICc) to assess performance of models and Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) to assess the strength of evidence for the influence of individual variables on recruitment. We used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cade1">Cade's (2015)</xref> approach for producing model-averaged parameter estimates and conditional confidence intervals, which accounts for correlation among explanatory variables in linear models. We report model-averaged coefficients and 85&percnt; confidence intervals for parameter estimates, consistent with an information theoretic approach to model selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). We also used the cor and pcor.test (ppcor package) functions in R to estimate correlations and partial correlations, controlled for year, among variables, respectively.We monitored 6,196 nests (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 282 annually) for nest success. Apparent nest success ranged from 0.16 to 0.89 between 1987 and 2004 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Estimates of pre-fledging and first-year survival were based on release of 17,388 webtagged goslings and 21,941 goslings near fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>). Pre-fledging survival ranged from 0 in 2001 to 0.40 in 1999, whereas first-year survival ranged from 0 in 2001 to 0.85 in 1987 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>; Appendix A). Number of nests at TRC ranged from 885 in 1987 to 7,437 nests in 2000, with numbers generally increasing during the1990s but declining since 2000 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f02">Figure 2</xref>). We estimated that 4,283 2- and 3-year-old recruits (ranging from 27 in 2004 to 852 in 1990) entered the breeding population at TRC between 1987 and 2006. Number of recruits declined from 852 in 1990 to 27 in 2004 and has been &lt;10&percnt; of nests at TRC every year since 1993 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f03">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f04">4</xref>).Annual estimates of apparent nest success of Black Brant nests on the Tutakoke River colony, Alaska, 1987&minus;2004, used to estimate number of recruits from 1990 to 2006. Sample sizes are indicated above each estimate.Number of Black Brant nests on the Tutakoke River colony, Alaska, 1987&ndash;2006. Estimates for 1987&minus;1991 were based on Lincoln-Petersen estimates, and estimates after 1991 were based on aerial videography of random strips throughout the colony (see Methods). We used number of nests 1987&minus;2004 as an explanatory variable in models of recruitment and numbers of nests 1990&minus;2006 to compare against number of recruits. No estimate was available for 1996 due to logistical problems.Estimated number of 2- and 3-year-old female recruits into the breeding population of Black Brant geese nesting on the Tutakoke River colony, Alaska, 1990&minus;2006. Estimates were based on the observed number of female recruits, adjusted for the proportion of each cohort marked, proportion of individuals examined during the recruitment year, and the proportion of females breeding in a given year. See Methods for more detail.Ratio of 2-and 3-year-old female recruits to number of nests on the Tutakoke River Black Brant colony, 1990&minus;2006. No estimate of number of nests was available for 1996. See Methods.Covariation among biological explanatory variables and between these variables and year was substantial (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t01">Table 1</xref>a), especially for the relationships between nest success and both pre-fledging and first-year survival (<italic>r</italic> &gt; 0.73, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t01">Table 1</xref>A) and between pre-fledging and first-year survival (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.63, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Partialling out effects of year slightly weakened some correlations among explanatory variables while strengthening others (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t01">Table 1</xref>B).Pearson correlations among explanatory variables used in models of number of recruits to the Tutakoke River Black Brant colony, Alaska, 1987&minus;2004. All variables except Yr represented 2-year averages used to predict number of recruits 2 or 3 years into the future. Yr represented recruitment year. Recruits were estimated for 1990&ndash;2006 whereas explanatory variables were from the pairs of years 1987&ndash;1988 through 2003&ndash;2004. A includes correlations among explanatory variables, including year (Yr); B includes partial correlations among the other 4 variables after controlling for the effects of year.Variables: Yr &equals; year, Spre &equals; pre-fledging survival, S1 &equals; first-year survival, Nests &equals; number of nests on the Tutakoke River colony, and NS &equals; nest success.The best-supported model of recruitment from analyses that excluded a linear trend across years included first-year survival, pre-fledging survival, and nest success (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.78; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t02">Table 2</xref>). This model explained 78&percnt; of the variation in number of recruits 2 and 3 years later. The 3 best-supported models all included nest success and either first-year or pre-fledging survival. Residual plots for these models did not indicate nonlinearities in the relationships between recruits and explanatory variables, and Q-Q plots indicated only slight deviations from normality at the extremes. Sum of weights for models that included first-year survival, pre-fledging survival, and nest success were 0.93, 0.89, and 0.93, respectively. Number of nests, including a quadratic term for nests, was less well supported than pre-fledging or first-year survival and nest success (&Sigma;<italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &lt; 0.05 for nests and nests<sup>2</sup>). A model including only nests and nests<sup>2</sup>, however, accounted for 25&percnt; of the variation in recruits (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t02">Table 2</xref>), and the confidence intervals for the model-averaged regression slopes linking nests and nests<sup>2</sup> to recruits in this model did not overlap 0 (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.35, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.67 to &minus;0.023; <italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; 0.21, 85&percnt; CI &equals; 0.05&ndash;0.36, respectively). The number of recruits was positively associated with both nest success and first-year survival (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; 0.50, 85&percnt; CI &equals; 0.26&ndash;0.73; and <italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; 0.46, 85&percnt; CI &equals; 0.24&ndash;0.68, respectively), but negatively related to pre-fledging survival (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.60, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.82 to &minus;0.38).Performance of general linear models of numbers of recruits into the Black Brant breeding population at the Tutakoke River colony. Models in this table did not include a linear trend across years. We show models with &Delta;AICc &lt; 10, and both the intercept only model and the most complex model considered. <italic>k</italic> &equals; number of parameters, RSS &equals; residual sums of squares, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; Akaike weights.Variables: S1 &equals; first-year survival, Spre &equals; pre-fledging survival, NS &equals; nest success, Nests &equals; number of nests on the Tutakoke River colony, and Nests<sup>2</sup> &equals; quadratic term for Nests.Support for specific models was less clear in the suite of models that included a linear trend across years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t03">Table 3</xref>), likely due to the strong correlations between year and number of recruits (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.83, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and between year and some of the explanatory variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t01">Table 1</xref>A). The best-supported model in this candidate set included first-year and pre-fledging survival in addition to year; this model explained 85&percnt; of the variance, carried 45&percnt; of the model weight, and had a lower AICc (&Delta;AICc &equals; 6.60 ) than the best-supported model in the candidate set that excluded a linear trend. Residual plots for models in this set did not indicate nonlinearities in the relationships between recruits and explanatory variables, and Q-Q plots indicated only slight deviations from normality at the extremes. The trend in number of recruits across years, which was substantial (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.64, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.47 to &minus;0.06), tended to obscure effects of other explanatory variables. Nevertheless, 4 of the 6 best-supported models included first-year survival (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t03">Table 3</xref>), with which number of recruits was positively associated (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; 0.37, 85&percnt; CI &equals; 0.18&ndash;0.57). As in the case of models excluding the linear year trend, number of recruits was negatively associated with both pre-fledging survival and number of nests (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.28, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.47 to &minus;0.06; and <italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.28, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.47 to &minus;0.09, respectively). In contrast, number of recruits was only weakly associated with nests success (<italic>Β̂</italic> &equals; &minus;0.16, 85&percnt; CI &equals; &minus;0.41&ndash;0.09) when year was included in models.Performance of general linear models of numbers of recruits into the Black Brant breeding population at the Tutakoke River colony, Alaska. Models in this table included a linear trend across years. We show models with &Delta;AICc &lt; 10, and both the intercept-only model and the most complex model considered. <italic>k</italic> &equals; number of parameters, RSS &equals; residual sums of squares, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; Akaike weights.Variables: S1 &equals; first-year survival, Spre &equals; pre-fledging survival, NS &equals; nest success, Nests &equals; numbers of nests on the Tutakoke River colony, and Nests<sup>2</sup> &equals; quadratic term for Nests.Nest success and first-year survival were both positively associated with recruitment into the breeding population 2 to 3 years later when trends across years were not included in models. This result was not unexpected because these demographic rates contribute directly to the number of Black Brant in a cohort at 1 year of age. Number of nests was weakly negatively associated with number of recruits, which could be interpreted as an indication of weak negative density dependence in the recruitment process. The negative association between pre-fledging survival and recruitment, while unexpected, can be explained as follows. Pre-fledging survival and first-year survival are strongly positively associated with each other (discussed earlier; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger 2012a</xref>). The negative relationship between pre-fledging survival and recruitment can thus be viewed as the remaining effects of pre-fledging survival after accounting for the positive relationship between first-year survival and recruitment. The negative relationship between pre-fledging survival and recruitment could also result from negative density dependent effects of marginal increases in pre-fledging survival because when pre-fledging survival is higher, more goslings remain on brood-rearing areas longer, thus increasing competition for food.Patterns were generally similar when trend across years was included in models, except the effect of nest success on recruitment was diminished to nearly nonexistent, and the magnitude of the effects of other variables was reduced relative to models lacking annual trends across years. There is a clear potential biological linkage between the explanatory variables we considered and number of recruits; thus, we argue that controlling for the long-term trend in explanatory variables and number of recruits produces a conservative assessment of the relationships between the two. Controlling for a trend across years depends on the assumption that some suite of variables we did not consider simultaneously explains the decline in both number of recruits and explanatory variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-t01">Table 1</xref>) while weakening the relationship between these explanatory variables and number of recruits. Our data were not the result of a controlled experiment, so we cannot rule out the existence of such a suite of variables, but we believe such a hypothesis is less plausible than direct influences of the variables we considered on recruitment.Grazing lawns, which regulate growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Herzog1">Herzog 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Lake1">Lake et al. 2008</xref>) and therefore first-year survival of goslings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger4">Sedinger and Chelgren 2007</xref>), are maintained by grazing by the geese themselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>; R. W. Ruess personal communication). After 3 years of intense predation by Arctic foxes on nests at TRC in 1983&minus;1985 (nest success &lt;10&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony4">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>), areal extent of grazing lawn was still increasing on brood-rearing areas associated with TRC in 1998 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>). Mass of goslings at fledging tracked this increase in grazing lawn extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>), resulting in increased first-year survival and recruitment. Gosling mass during this period, however, remained well below the potential if more food had been available; Black Brant goslings from Alaska's Arctic coast, where food biomass was higher, were about 50&percnt; heavier at fledging during this period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger7">Sedinger et al. 2001</xref>) and experienced higher first-year survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Ward1">Ward et al. 2004</xref>). The evidence thus suggests that after 3 years of high predation rates on nests in the early 1980s, grazing lawns had still not been fully restored by 1998, more than a decade later.The complex relationships among predation, grazing, and extent of grazing lawns creates the potential for substantial time lags in the relationship between goose density and food abundance. In the short term (a single breeding season) following a predation event, density exceeds carrying capacity, and growth of goslings is reduced, resulting in lower first-year survival and lower recruitment. Annual grazing, however, slowly increases the extent of grazing lawn and the number of broods that can be supported for up to a decade following major predation events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person2">Person et al. 2003</xref>). Our understanding of this dynamic is currently not sufficient to predict the response to the more moderate reductions in nest success during the 1990s (1994, 1995, 1997), but we believe the destruction of most nests at TRC in 2001 and 2003 was sufficient to have again produced major losses of grazing lawn. Visual inspection of brood rearing areas near TRC during 2006&minus;2010 indicates substantial reductions in grazing lawn compared to the late-1990s (J. S. Sedinger personal observation).We have emphasized lagged negative effects of predation on grazing lawns and the resulting negative effects on growth and survival of goslings. Earlier work on the TRC Black Brant population suggests that slow growth can also reduce the probability that individuals breed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger6">Sedinger et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger8">2004</xref>). Thus, reduced numbers of recruits could also reflect a smaller proportion of fledged goslings that enter the breeding population even if they survive.Annual survival of adult female Black Brant has averaged 89&percnt; since the 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger14">Sedinger et al. 2007</xref>). Consequently, 11&percnt; of breeding females must be replaced annually to maintain a stable population. Because 2- and 3-year-old recruits represented 90&percnt; of total recruits into the breeding population, the population should have been increasing when numbers of these recruits exceeded 10&percnt; of total nests. Two- and 3-year old recruits have not exceeded 10&percnt; of nests since 1992 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f04">Figure 4</xref>). Numbers of nests at TRC have declined an average of 5&percnt; annually since the mid-1990s, which is approximately consistent with the deficit in numbers of recruits during this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-f03">Figure 3</xref>). We note that the long-term decline is unlikely the result of investigator impact because we ruled out such effects elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger2">Sedinger 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Sedinger10">Sedinger et al. 1997</xref>).Our results are consistent with the hypothesis that changes in abundance of Arctic foxes in the early 1980s increased the frequency of catastrophic nest failures, which combined with lagged effects of such events has reduced recruitment rates. We hypothesized elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Anthony4">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>) that increased Arctic fox numbers could be the result of anthropogenic food subsidies. Climate change, which is increasing temperatures in the Arctic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Walsh1">Walsh et al. 2013</xref>), could also contribute to increased Arctic fox abundance by altering the energy balance of Arctic foxes during winter. Improved understanding of mechanisms underlying the dynamics of Arctic foxes is important to understanding both predator&ndash;prey dynamics and dynamics of geese and their food plants.The deficit in number of recruits has resulted in a rapidly aging breeding population; mean age of breeding females in the nesting population is now &gt;10 years old (J. S. Sedinger personal observation). Senescence in reproductive success has been detected in Lesser Snow Geese at 8 years of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Rockwell1">Rockwell et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Robertson1">Robertson et al. 1994</xref>) and in annual survival at 13 years of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Koons1">Koons et al. 2014</xref>). Senescence in key life-history traits occurs at even younger ages in other long-lived species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Cam1">Cam et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Boonekamp1">Boonekamp et al. 2014</xref>). Preliminary analyses of age-specific breeding probability and survival suggest that both begin to senesce at 11 years of age in Black Brant (J. S. Sedinger personal communication), and adult annual survival is now 5&percnt; lower than before 2000 (A. G. Leach et al. personal communication), consistent with senescent decline in survival in an aging population. Lower adult survival will exacerbate the rate of population decline in the absence of increased recruitment.In summary, we suggest that relatively infrequent predation events are capable of reducing recruitment for long periods in a long-lived herbivore that depends on grazing lawns for recruitment of offspring into the breeding population. Such lagged effects of predation could potentially occur for other avian herbivore populations that rely on and maintain grazing lawns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-McNaughton1">McNaughton 1985</xref>) or for those that improve vegetation quality following herbivore foraging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Hik1">Hik et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Person1">Person et al. 1998</xref>). We describe a scenario with relatively sporadic high levels of predation; in scenarios where high levels of predation occur more frequently, the predation itself could be adequate to produce population decline.We thank the following for assisting with field work: B. Anker, M. Anteau, M. Axelson, J. Bacon, R. Baden, T. Barnett, E. Beers, T. Bentzen, L. Bernstein, M. Blom, K. Bollinger, D. Bos, C. Brown, J. Caikoski, E. Carr, J. Chakuchin, M. Chambers, N. Chelgren, D. Christian, R. Clancy, B. Comstock, R. Crain, J. Curtis, K. Degroot, T. Dixon, W. Don, B. Dugger, A. Earp, D. Eichholz, M. Eichholz, S. Farley, P. Flint, P. Freshman, J. Hall, T. Hande, M. Herzog, J. Hill, D. Hoffman, D. Johnson, T. Jones, Y. Kawaguchi, S. Keane, I. Kharitonov, S. Kharitonov, M. Knoche, P. Kugzruk, C. Lake, L. Lake, J. Lawlor, P. Lemons, P. Lemons II, M. Lindberg, B. Lorenz, D. Maso, G. Moydell, A. Nash, K. Nicholson, A. Nicolai, D. Nicolai, S. Nicolai, D. Nonne, T. Obritchkewitz, W. O'Connell, T. Olson, E. Osnas, J. Otto, H. Panyiak, T. Paragi, A. Perez-Arteaga, B. Person, D. Person, J. Phillipsborn, J. Prop, J. Pratt, C. Pylant, R. Rockwell, T. Rogers, N. Saake, J. Schamber, M. Schreiner, B. Sedinger, M. Shellicans, S. Sindelar, H. Singer, C. Slats, L. Snoddy, C. Stava, A. Stewart, P. Svete, T. Trapp, Y. Uchiro, G. Ulroan, L. Valadez, S. van Laer, C. VanStratt, E. Vaughn, C. Villa, L. Wahlberg, D. Welsh, B. Wentzell, K. Wolfe, and D. Youkie.Funding statement: Studies at the Tutakoke River colony were supported by the U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Migratory Bird Management Region 7; Ducks Unlimited; the Morro Bay Brant Group; Phil Jebbia (in memory of Marnie Shepherd); and the National Science Foundation (OPP 9214970, DEB 9815383, OPP 9985931, OPP 0196406, DEB 0743152, DEB 1252656, respectively); the Yukon Delta National Wildlife Refuge provided logistical support. None of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication. The findings and conclusions in this manuscript are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. Any use of trade, product, or firm names in this publication is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.Ethics statement: This research was conducted in compliance with the Guidelines to the Use of Wild Birds in Research. All research was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committees of the University of Alaska Fairbanks and the University of Nevada Reno. Most recent protocol number 00056.Author contributions: J.S.S. managed the project, analyzed data, and wrote the initial manuscript. C.A.N., A.W.V., A.G.L., H.M.W., and R.M.A. collected key data and edited the manuscript.Annual estimates of mean pre-fledging and first-year (post-fledging) survival (&phi; &plusmn; SE) based on estimates from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-433-Nicolai1">Nicolai and Sedinger (2012a)</xref>. Annual means were calculated as weighted means of brood-rearing area specific survival estimates, in which we weighted each estimate by the inverse of its variance.