Erratum: Taxonomy of &ldquo;Mouse-colored Tapaculos&rdquo; (II): An endangered new species from the montane Atlantic Forest of southern Bahia, Brazil (Passeriformes: Rhinocryptidae: <italic>Scytalopus</italic>)Taxonomy of &ldquo;Mouse-colored Tapaculos&rdquo; (II): An endangered new species from the montane Atlantic Forest of southern Bahia, Brazil (Passeriformes: Rhinocryptidae: <italic>Scytalopus</italic>)Taxonomy of &ldquo;Mouse-colored Tapaculos.&rdquo; I. On the application of the name <italic>Malacorhynchus speluncae</italic> M&eacute;n&eacute;tri&eacute;s, 1835 (Aves: Passeriformes: Rhinocryptidae)In a recent paper, we described a new bird species, <italic>Scytalopus gonzagai</italic>, and proposed the English name &ldquo;Bahian Mouse-colored Tapaculo&rdquo; for it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-951-Mauricio1">Maur&iacute;cio et al. 2014</xref>). However, this proposal conflicts with general principles of the formation of English names and, thus, we propose the name &ldquo;Boa Nova Tapaculo&rdquo; for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>.Em um trabalho recente descrevemos uma nova esp&eacute;cie de ave, <italic>Scytalopus gonzagai</italic>, para a qual recomendamos o nome comum em ingl&ecirc;s &ldquo;Bahian Mouse-colored Tapaculo&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-951-Mauricio1">Maur&iacute;cio et al. 2014</xref>). Entretanto, essa proposi&ccedil;&atilde;o conflita com as regras para a forma&ccedil;&atilde;o de nomes comuns em ingl&ecirc;s. Assim, propomos um novo nome comum em ingl&ecirc;s para <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>: &ldquo;Boa Nova Tapaculo&rdquo;.<italic>Palavras-chave:</italic> Boa Nova, Boa Nova Tapaculo, nome comum em ingl&ecirc;s, <italic>Scytalopus gonzagai</italic>In a recent paper, we described a new bird species, <italic>Scytalopus gonzagai</italic>, for which we proposed the English name &ldquo;Bahian Mouse-colored Tapaculo&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-951-Mauricio1">Maur&iacute;cio et al. 2014</xref>). However, this proposal conflicts with general principles of the formation of English names, in that there is already a species called &ldquo;Mouse-colored Tapaculo&rdquo; (<italic>S. speluncae</italic>; sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-951-Mauricio2">Maur&iacute;cio et al. 2010</xref>) without a modifier. Thus, to preserve our originally proposed English name for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>, we would have to introduce a modifier to the existing name, such as &ldquo;Southern&rdquo; (resulting in &ldquo;Southern Mouse-colored Tapaculo&rdquo;) or an equivalent term. However, it is beyond our intention to propose a modifier for the English name &ldquo;Mouse-colored Tapaculo,&rdquo; because it is a well-established name in the ornithological literature, both scientific and amateur (e.g., bird-watching guides). Therefore, we discarded this option, and the only alternative was to propose a novel English name for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>. The alternative of shortening the name to &ldquo;Bahian Tapaculo&rdquo; was discarded because this name has long been applied to <italic>Eleoscytalopus psychopompus</italic>, another tapaculo endemic to the Brazilian state of Bahia. Therefore, we propose &ldquo;Boa Nova Tapaculo&rdquo; as the English name for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>.The following aspects justify our proposal: (1) Boa Nova is the first place where the new species was found, collected, and recorded; (2) all additional known localities for the species are within ~120 km to the southeast of Boa Nova; (3) Boa Nova is an internationally well-known birding site; and (4) Boa Nova is an Important Bird Area (IBA), which motivated the creation of the Boa Nova National Park and the Boa Nova Wildlife Refuge, both in 2010. Thus, &ldquo;Boa Nova Tapaculo&rdquo; well represents all other known sites for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic>, and it also highlights important conservation initiatives of international relevance. The new English name formally proposed here for <italic>S. gonzagai</italic> has recently been adopted by the South American Classification Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-951-Remsen1">Remsen et al. 2015</xref>).We are grateful to J. V. Remsen, Jr., for informing us about the problem with the English name proposed in our original paper.