 Do nestling Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  ) respond to parental alarm calls?  Species specificity of Grey Warbler begging solicitation and alarm calls revealed by nestling responses to playbacks  Audacity  Lme4: Linear mixed-effects models using S4 classes. R package version 0.999375-42  Development of auditory sensitivity in Budgerigars (  Melopsittacus undulatus  )  Begging in nestling birds  Learning fine-tunes a specific response of nestlings to the parental alarm calls of their own species  Brown-headed Cowbird nestling vocalizations and risk of nest predation  Responses of breeding reed warblers   Acrocephalus scirpaceus   to mounts of sparrowhawk   Accipiter nisus  , cuckoo   Cuculus canorus   and jay   Garrulus glandarius    Calling at a cost: Elevated nestling calling attracts predators to active nests  Vocal begging by nestlings and vulnerability to nest predation in Meadow Pipits   Anthus pratensis  : To what extent do predation costs of begging exist?  Acoustic interactions in broods of nestling birds (  Tachycineta bicolor  )  Alarm calls and chick reactions in the Moustached Warbler,  Acrocephalus melanopogon   Nest defense in the American Goldfinch  Nest-defense behavior in the Red-winged Blackbird  Development of the auditory sensitivity and formation of the acoustically guided defensive behavior in nestlings of the Pied Flycatcher   Ficedula hypoleuca    Begging and the risk of predation in nestling birds  Parental calls and nestling behavior in Tree Swallows  Provisioning rules in Tree Swallows  Begging calls and parental feeding decisions in Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  )  Begging in the absence of parents by nestling Tree Swallows  False alarms and begging in nestling birds  A predation risk-and-avoidance model of nestling responses to parental vocalizations  Nestling responses to adult food and alarm calls: 1. Species-specific responses in two cowbird hosts  Calling in the face of danger: Predation risk and acoustic communication by parent birds and their offspring  Begging to differ: Scrubwren nestlings beg to alarm calls and vocalize when parents are absent  Nestling begging increases predation risk, regardless of spectral characteristics or avian mobbing  Parental alarm calls suppress nestling vocalization  Adaptive differences in response to two types of parental alarm call in altricial nestlings  Tree Swallow  Features of begging calls reveal general condition and need of food of Barn Swallow (  Hirundo rustica  ) nestlings  The development of visual discrimination patterns in the crouching reactions of nestling grackles  Reduction of nestlings' vocalizations in response to parental alarm calls in the Southern House Wren,  Troglodytes musculus   Parental alarm calls warn nestlings about different predatory threats  Predation by bears on woodpecker nests: Are nestling begging and habitat choice risky business?  Anti-predator defence by neighbors as a responsive amplifier of parental defence in Tree Swallows  Nestling birds use a conspicuous begging display, which includes loud begging calls, to solicit food from their parents. Although these calls are important in communicating offspring need, predators can use begging calls to locate nests. Parents may, however, counteract nestling vulnerability by giving alarm calls to silence calling nestlings when predators are nearby. This defense has been observed in grass- and reed-nesting species, whose nestlings beg to vibrational cues of a parent's arrival, even in the absence of the parents. It is considered less likely to occur, however, in cavity-nesting species, because the rigid substrate of the nest does not provide vibrational cues, and nestlings instead wait for a parental food call before begging. Cavity-nesting Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  ) use food calls to solicit begging, which suggests that parental alarm calls are not required to silence them. Older nestling Tree Swallows, however, beg in the absence of their parents, which suggests that responding to parental alarm calls with silence might be adaptive after all, at least at older ages. The goal of our study was to determine whether nestling Tree Swallows alter their begging behavior in response to parental alarm calls and, if so, whether this response varies with age. We found that older nestlings (15 days posthatch) reduced calling and crouched in the nest in response to playback of parental alarm calls, unlike younger nestlings (5 and 10 days posthatch). Our results suggest that parent Tree Swallows might reduce predation risk caused by calling nestlings, especially older nestlings, by giving alarm calls when predators are near their nests. Counter to our prediction, nestlings of cavity-nesting species may indeed respond to alarm calls, particularly if they beg in the absence of parents.  Les oisillons utilisent un stimulus de sollicitation bruyant, lequel comprend des cris puissants pour qu&eacute;mander de la nourriture &agrave; leurs parents. Malgr&eacute; que ces cris soient importants pour communiquer les besoins des oisillons, les pr&eacute;dateurs peuvent les utiliser pour localiser les nids. Les parents peuvent cependant contrer la vuln&eacute;rabilit&eacute; des oisillons en &eacute;mettant des cris d'alarme pour faire taire les oisillons lorsque des pr&eacute;dateurs sont &agrave; proximit&eacute;. Cette d&eacute;fense a &eacute;t&eacute; observ&eacute;e chez les esp&egrave;ces nichant dans les herbes et les roseaux, dont les oisillons qu&eacute;mandent de la nourriture en pr&eacute;sence de vibrations annon&ccedil;ant l'arriv&eacute;e du parent, m&ecirc;me en l'absence de leurs parents. Cependant, on pense que cela est moins susceptible de se produire chez les esp&egrave;ces cavicoles, car le substrat rigide du nid ne transmet pas de vibrations. Les oisillons attendent plut&ocirc;t les cris de nourrissage des parents avant de qu&eacute;mander.   Tachycineta bicolor  , une esp&egrave;ce cavicole, utilise les cris de nourrissage pour inciter les oisillons &agrave; qu&eacute;mander, ce qui sugg&egrave;re que les cris d'alarme des parents ne sont pas requis pour les rendre silencieux. Toutefois, les oisillons plus &acirc;g&eacute;s de   T. bicolor   qu&eacute;mandent en l'absence de leurs parents, ce qui sugg&egrave;re que de se taire en r&eacute;ponse aux cris d'alarme des parents pourrait &ecirc;tre un comportement adaptatif, du moins &agrave; un &acirc;ge plus avanc&eacute;. Le but de notre &eacute;tude &eacute;tait de d&eacute;terminer si les oisillons de   T. bicolor   modifient leur comportement de sollicitation en r&eacute;ponse aux cris d'alarme des parents et, le cas &eacute;ch&eacute;ant, si cette r&eacute;ponse varie avec l'&acirc;ge. Nous avons trouv&eacute; que les oisillons plus &acirc;g&eacute;s (15 jours apr&egrave;s l'&eacute;closion) ont r&eacute;duit l'&eacute;mission de cris et se recroquevillaient dans le nid en r&eacute;ponse &agrave; la diffusion d'enregistrements de cris d'alarme parentaux, contrairement aux oisillons plus jeunes (5 et 10 jours apr&egrave;s l'&eacute;closion). Nos r&eacute;sultats sugg&egrave;rent que les parents de   T. bicolor   pourraient r&eacute;duire le risque de pr&eacute;dation caus&eacute; par les oisillons qui crient, surtout les oiseaux plus &acirc;g&eacute;s, en &eacute;mettant des cris d'alarme lorsque les pr&eacute;dateurs se trouvent pr&egrave;s de leurs nids. Contrairement &agrave; notre pr&eacute;diction, les oisillons des esp&egrave;ces cavicoles peuvent effectivement r&eacute;pondre aux cris d'alarme, particuli&egrave;rement s'ils qu&eacute;mandent en l'absence des parents.   Mots-cl&eacute;s:  cris d'alarme, cris pour qu&eacute;mander de la nourriture, communication parent&ndash;prog&eacute;niture,   Tachycineta bicolor    Nestling passerine birds produce loud begging calls when soliciting care from their parents ( Budden and Wright 2001 ,  Wright and Leonard 2002 ). Begging calls contain information on nestling hunger levels and condition ( Leonard and Horn 2001b ,  Sacchi et al. 2002 ,  Horn and Leonard 2008 ), and parents use the information encoded in the calls to make decisions about which nestling to feed ( Leonard and Horn 2001a ). Thus, begging calls play an important role in communicating offspring need to parents.  Although begging calls provide a benefit to nestlings, they may also increase predation risk ( Magrath et al. 2010 ). Playback experiments with artificial nests have shown that nests that broadcast begging calls, especially at higher rates and amplitudes, experience greater predation than control nests ( Dearborn 1999 ,  McDonald et al. 2009 ). Experiments at natural nests have reinforced these conclusions. For example, nestling Yellow-bellied Sapsuckers (  Sphyrapicus varius  ) experienced greater predation rates when begging calls were loudest ( Tozer et al. 2009 ), and nests of White-browed Scrubwrens ( Sericornis frontalis ) were more likely to attract predators during playback of nestling vocalizations ( Haff and Magrath 2011 ).  If begging calls betray nest location and increase predation risk, parents may counteract this vulnerability by modulating the production of nestling begging calls when predators are near nests. Specifically, in the presence of predators, parents may use alarm calls to discourage nestlings from begging, thus reducing the chances that the predator will find the nest ( Madden et al. 2005 ,  Platzen and Magrath 2004 ).  Nestlings of a variety of species respond to parental alarm calls. The most common response is for nestlings to fall silent and stop begging when presented with parental alarm calls ( Knight and Temple 1986 ,  Duckworth 1991 ,  Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ,  Halupka 1998 ,  Davies et al. 2004 ,  Platzen and Magrath 2004 ,  Madden et al. 2005 ). Nestlings may also crouch, move from the center of the nest to the edge, or jump from the nest ( Knight and Temple 1986 ,  Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ,  Madden et al. 2005 ,  Suzuki 2011 ). The type and intensity of these responses can vary with age, becoming more prevalent as nestlings approach fledging ( Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ). Although these responses are widespread, they are not universal. Young Eastern Phoebes (  Sayornis phoebe  ), for instance, do not respond to alarm calls ( Madden et al. 2005 ). White-browed Scrubwrens (  Corvus brachyrhynchos  ), in some situations, not only fail to respond but may continue to beg during playback of alarm calls ( Maurer et al. 2003 ,  Platzen and Magrath 2004 ).  Differences in nestling responsiveness to parental alarm calls have been attributed to differences in nesting ecology ( Madden et al. 2005 ). Specifically, young of species nesting on flexible substrates, such as grass or reeds, may be more likely than those nesting in rigid substrates, such as cavities or the ground, to beg to vibrational cues associated with the arrival of a parent with food. If vibrational cues indicate the arrival of a parent, nestlings may beg to inappropriate stimuli, such as the wind moving the nest, in the absence of parents. It is in these species that alarm calling is expected to discourage begging ( Madden et al. 2005 ). Young of cavity-nesting species tend to beg when parents signal their arrival with a food call. Nestlings that are silent until prompted to beg may be less likely to beg in the absence of parents, and less likely to respond to alarm calls ( Madden et al. 2005 ).  Most studies of nestling responses to parental alarm calls have focused on species that nest on flexible substrates, with nestlings that beg in the absence of parental food calls. These studies have found that nestlings respond defensively to alarm calls, as predicted (see above). Relatively less is known about this response for species that nest on rigid substrates, with nestlings that beg primarily to parental food calls (but see  Korneeva et al. 2006  and references therein). Although cavity-nesting Tree Swallow (  Tachycineta bicolor  ) parents use food calls to solicit begging ( Robertson et al. 1992 ), nestlings are known to beg to inappropriate stimuli, and increasingly so as they age ( Leonard and Horn 2001b ,  Leonard et al. 2005 ). Therefore, parental alarm calls might indeed function to switch off begging in this species, despite its rigid nest site. Here, we determine whether nestling Tree Swallows alter their begging behavior in response to parental alarm calls and, if so, whether the response varies with age.  We conducted the study in the Gaspereau Valley of Nova Scotia, Canada, from May to July, 2011, using a population of box-nesting Tree Swallows (for details on the study sites, see  Leonard and Horn 1996 ).  To test whether nestling Tree Swallows alter begging behavior in response to parental alarm calls and whether the response varies with age, we presented nestlings from each of 26 broods (of 3&ndash;6 nestlings) with playback of parental alarm calls (alarm treatment) and background noise (control treatment) when nestlings were 5, 10, and 15 days posthatch. Playbacks consisted of 2 parental food calls, used to stimulate begging ( Leonard et al. 1997 ), each followed by 1 s of silence and then a sequence of either alarm calls (mean duration &equals; 4.7 s, range: 4.4&ndash;4.9 s;  Figure 1 A) as recorded in the field, or background noise of the same duration ( Figure 1 B) and from the same recording session as the alarm calls (for detailed information on playbacks, see below).  We recorded parental food calls and alarm calls when nestlings were 1&ndash;3 days old, between 0600 and 1000 hours. To record food calls, we suspended a Sennheiser wireless lapel microphone, attached to a Marantz PMD471 sound recorder, inside the nest box &sim;5 cm above the center of the nest cup, when parents were away from the nest. We recorded food calls during the next 5 parental feeding visits.  Alarm ( A ) and control ( B ) playback sequences; the spectrogram was produced in Raven with a Hanning window function at a sample rate of 1,040, with 3-dB filter bandwidth at 61 Hz, and with overlap set to 95&percnt;.  To elicit alarm calls, we placed a decoy of an American Crow (FFD Elite-series crow decoy, 45 cm long &times; 15 cm tall; Avery Greenhead Gear, Memphis, Tennessee, USA), a known nest predator ( Robertson et al. 1992 ), on a tripod 1 m to the left of the nest box, with the crow facing the box entrance, the base of the crow level with the base of the box. To record alarm calls, when parents were away from the nest, we taped a Sennheiser wireless lapel microphone, attached to a Marantz PMD471 sound recorder, underneath the box, oriented toward the crow decoy. When parents returned to the nest, we recorded alarm calls for 5 min or until neighboring birds joined in defense of the nest. We distinguished between parents and neighbors by their defensive behaviors. Parents actively defend nests by giving alarm calls and repeatedly diving at predators, while neighboring birds passively defend by circling above the predator and calling, but not diving ( Winkler 1994 ). The order in which food calls and alarm calls were recorded was alternated from nest to nest, and recordings at the same nest were separated by &ge;5 min.  Recordings were uploaded to a MacBook Pro computer, high-pass filtered at 2 kHz, and edited for playback using Audacity version 1.3.13-beta ( Audacity Team 2011 ). To determine whether alarm calls stop or reduce begging, we needed to stimulate begging and then present the treatment sound before the begging stopped naturally. We therefore designed the playback sequence so that if nestlings begged to the parental food calls, they would still be begging when they received the treatment sound. The approximate duration of a begging event following a parental food call at 5 days posthatch is 6 s (M. L. Leonard and A. G. Horn personal observation). Thus, to ensure that the playback of treatment sounds overlapped with the majority of a begging event, the duration of a playback sequence from the beginning of the second food call to the end of the treatment sound was also 6 s.  We selected the first 2 parental food calls of the recording session for the playback tape and an unmanipulated section of recorded alarm calls, beginning with the first parental alarm call on the recording, that produced the requisite 6-s interval (i.e. length of treatment sound &equals; 6 s &ndash; &lsqb;length of 2nd food call &plus; 1 s silence&rsqb;;  Figure 1 A). An unmanipulated section of background noise, of equal length and uninterrupted by Tree Swallow calls, was chosen for the control sequence ( Figure 1 B).  Approximately 24 h before each playback experiment, we opened the hinged side door of a nest box and inserted a Plexiglas plate into the opening. We then wrapped this side of the box with a black plastic bag that would cover the recording equipment the next day. On the day of the playback, we suspended a lapel microphone inside the nest box (as in recordings of parental food calls) and set up a tripod with a Canon Optura 300 digital video camcorder &sim;30 cm from the Plexiglas wall of the nest box. We wrapped a black plastic bag around the camera and the open side of the nest box so that the box interior remained dark during filming. We placed a speaker (Koss, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, USA) on a tripod, 1 m to the left and level with the base of the nest box, with the speaker facing the nest box's opening. The speaker was connected to an mp3 player from which alarm and control sequences were played.  Alarm and control sequences were played when parents were away from the nest and at the levels at which they were recorded (58&ndash;65 dB). Both the food calls and alarm calls played to nestlings were of their own parents. Alarm and control playbacks at each nest were separated by 5 min of silence, and the order in which they were presented was alternated between nests, but constant within nests across ages.  To determine whether alarm calls affected nestling calling, we imported audio recordings into Audacity. Using the time display in Audacity as a guide, we calculated the duration of calling by the brood (calling duration) by recording whether a nestling (or nestlings) was calling every 0.5 s, beginning with the treatment sound and continuing until the nestlings were silent for 10 s.  We also examined whether alarm calls affected a visual component of the begging display: postural begging intensity. Although this component is not likely to attract predators to the nest, stretching toward the nest opening could increase the chances of a nestling being taken once a predator was at the nest. Here, we imported the video recordings into Apple iMovie HD version 6.0.4. We considered postural begging to include gaping, stretching toward the parent, and waving wings. Beginning 10 s before the treatment sound started and continuing for 2 min, each time a nestling begged we recorded its maximum begging intensity, as well as every change in its intensity, on the following scale: 0 &equals; head down, beak closed, sitting on tarsi; 1 &equals; head down, gaping, sitting; 2 &equals; head up, gaping, sitting; 3 &equals; 2 &plus; neck stretched upward; 4 &equals; 3 &plus; body lifted off tarsi; 5 &equals; 4 &plus; wings waving. To test whether the treatment affected begging intensity, for each nestling that begged in response to the parental food calls, we calculated the change in begging intensity immediately before, and 1 s after, the treatment sound began (change in postural begging intensity). We also determined the duration of postural begging for each nestling that continued begging after the treatment sounds were played, measured from the start of the treatment sound until the nestling stopped begging (intensity score &equals; 0) or switched to a nonbegging behavior. Nestlings that switched from begging to nonbegging behaviors (see below) when the treatment sound began were excluded from the analysis of change in postural begging intensity.  We also recorded all nonbegging behaviors that occurred after the treatment sound began. In previous studies, passerine nestlings have responded to alarm calls by crouching (e.g.,  Knight and Temple 1988 ,  Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ), which includes lowering the body into the nest cup, shifting the bill from the nest rim to the nest middle, and withdrawing the head ( Schaller and Emlen 1961 ,  Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ). We recorded the presence or absence of crouching for each nestling after initiation of the treatment sound. If a nestling crouched, we also recorded the length of time between the beginning of the treatment sound and the onset of crouching (time to crouch).  The final sample size ( n  &equals; number of broods) for each age was reduced because of technical difficulties, poor weather, or nestlings failing to respond to the parental food calls. Sample sizes for the alarm treatment (A) and control treatment (C) were as follows: for audio data, day 5: (A)  n  &equals; 3 and (C)  n  &equals; 4; day 10: (A)  n  &equals; 12 and (C)  n  &equals; 14; day 15: (A)  n  &equals; 13 and (C)  n  &equals; 16; for video data, day 5: (A)  n  &equals; 7 and (C)  n  &equals; 5; day 10: (A)  n  &equals; 11 and (C)  n  &equals; 11; day 15: (A)  n  &equals; 11 and (C)  n  &equals; 9.  We conducted all analyses using R version 2.14.0 ( Bates et al. 2011 , R Development Team 2011). To analyze average calling duration, change in postural begging intensity, and postural begging duration, we used a generalized mixed model with restricted maximum likelihood estimation, with treatment (alarm or control) and age (5, 10, or 15 days) as fixed factors and nest as a random factor. To assess significance, we used a submodel routine in which the fixed effect of interest was removed from the model, and the new model was then compared to the original model using Wald's chi-square statistic. All broods at 15 days posthatch and 2 broods at 10 days posthatch stopped begging and switched to nonbegging behaviors when presented with the alarm treatment. They were therefore omitted from the analyses of changes in postural begging intensity. Time to crouch was compared with time to stop begging using a one-way ANOVA.  Calling duration did not vary significantly with treatment (&chi; 2  &equals; 0.91, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.34) or age (&chi; 2  &equals; 0.19, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.91) but did show a significant interaction between treatment and age (&chi; 2  &equals; 11.76, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.0028;  Figure 2 ), with calling duration decreasing in response to the alarm treatment and increasing in response to the control treatment (i.e. food calls with background noise) with age.  Mean (&plusmn; SE) calling duration for broods of nestling Tree Swallows after alarm (dark bars) or control (light bars) playbacks at days 5, 10, and 15 posthatch. Bars represent means of the observed data, and lines represent SE.  The change in postural begging intensity did not vary significantly with treatment (&chi; 2  &equals; 0.85, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.36), age (&chi; 2  &equals; 1.53, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.22), or their interaction (&chi; 2  &equals; 0.02, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.88). Postural begging duration also did not vary with treatment (&chi; 2  &equals; 1.33, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.25) but did vary significantly with age (&chi; 2  &equals; 15.64, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.0004), with postural displays decreasing in duration as nestlings aged. The interaction between treatment and age was not significant (&chi; 2  &equals; 1.70, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.43).  Crouching was observed only following alarm treatments, and if crouching occurred, all begging nestlings in the brood crouched, with the exception of a single nestling that did not crouch with its brood mates. By day 15, 100&percnt; of broods (11 of 11) crouched in response to alarm calls, as opposed to 18&percnt; (2 of 11) at day 10 and 0&percnt; (0 of 7) at day 5. The time taken by nestlings to crouch in the nest following the alarm treatment (mean &plusmn; SE &equals; 1.10 &plusmn; 0.21 s) was significantly less than the time taken to stop begging (i.e. return to a begging score of 0) in the control treatment (8.88 &plusmn; 1.82 s; one-way ANOVA,  F  1,9.24  &equals; 18.08,  P  &equals; 0.002), which suggests that a response to alarm calls is both specific and prompt.  We found that older nestling Tree Swallows responded to parental alarm calls by calling less and quickly crouching in the nest. This is consistent with the results of previous studies in which nestlings reduced calling and/or crouched in response to parental alarm calls (e.g.,  Kleindorfer et al. 1996 ,  Halupka 1998 ,  Davies et al. 2004 ,  Platzen and Magrath 2004 ,  Madden et al. 2005 ,  Serra and Fernandez 2011 ). Although the result is counter to the general prediction that nestlings of cavity-nesting species would be less likely to respond to alarm calls, it is consistent with the more fundamental hypothesis that nestlings that beg to inappropriate stimuli are also likely to respond to alarm calls ( Madden et al. 2005 ).  Begging calls can attract predators to the nest ( Leech and Leonard 1997 ), and predators are more attracted to nests where nestling calling is elevated ( Haff and Magrath 2011 ). Therefore, reducing calling in the presence of predators should reduce the probability of nest detection and, therefore, predation risk. Further study is required, however, to test this possibility. In addition, crouching, which included nestlings lowering their bodies in the nest and raising tail feathers above the head, may be an effective strategy for avoiding capture by predators once they have located the nest. Again, whether this combination of defenses prevents or reduces predation has yet to be tested.  We found that only the oldest nestlings responded to parental alarm calls. One explanation for the change in response with age is that younger nestlings have not yet developed the ability to perceive alarm calls ( Brittan-Powell and Dooling 2004 ,  Maurer et al. 2003 ,  Lock and Hauber 2012 ) and may be unable to detect the signal and respond appropriately. Another, not mutually exclusive, possibility is that vulnerability to predation increases with age ( Platzen and Magrath 2005 ) and, therefore, an appropriate response is only adaptive at later ages. Young Tree Swallows generally beg only in response to parental food calls, but older nestlings also beg to additional stimuli in the absence of parents ( Leonard and Horn 2001b ,  Leonard et al. 2005 ), which could increase the chance of a predator detecting the nest ( Haff and Magrath 2011 ). Older nestlings, then, may develop a defensive response to alarm calls to coincide with increased predation risk. It is also possible that a response to alarm calls is beneficial to fledglings rather than nestlings and occurs in older nestlings simply because they are close to leaving the nest.  Interestingly, we also found that, on average, younger nestling Tree Swallows increased their calling duration in response to alarm calls as compared to the control treatment. The response shown by the younger nestlings suggests that they may be unable to discriminate between different parental call types and may have been stimulated to beg by any adult call, irrespective of its function (also see  Maurer et al. 2003 ). Younger nestlings may not be sufficiently developed to perceive alarm calls or, alternatively, may be ignoring or not hearing the calls.  It is worth noting that we did not present nestlings with a call of a benign species, so it is possible that the response of the nestlings was simply a general response to an adult call rather than a specific response to an alarm call. We consider this unlikely, however, for several reasons. First, the response of the nestlings to the alarm calls was consistent with previous studies (see above). Additionally, nestlings across a variety of ages showed no antipredator behavior in response to neutral calls of other species in studies that used such controls ( Davies et al. 2004 ,  Madden et al. 2005 ,  Anderson et al. 2010 ). Finally, older nestlings in our study begged to parental food calls but became silent and crouched to alarm calls, indicating a specific response to the latter calls.  In conclusion, we found that older nestling Tree Swallows respond to parental alarm calls by decreasing their calling and crouching in the nest. A reduction in calling may decrease the likelihood that some predators will detect the nest, while crouching may reduce predation at an individual level. Predictions of nestling response to alarm calls may not be comprehensive if based solely on nesting ecology; a more appropriate predictor of nestling response to alarm calls may be the propensity to beg to inappropriate stimuli. Cavity-nesting species may indeed respond to alarm calls, particularly if nestlings beg in the absence of parents.  We thank H. MacGillivray for her assistance in the field, and the Coldwell, Hynes, and Minor families for use of their land. This study was supported by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Discovery Grant awarded to M.L.L. and by an Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship to E.M. The experiment conducted in this study followed both federal and institutional requirements for the use of animals in research and was approved by Dalhousie University's Committee on Laboratory Animals (protocol no. 11&ndash;029). 