Predator exclosures, predator removal, and habitat improvement increase nest success of Snowy Plovers in Oregon, USAInformation theory and an extension of the maximum likelihood principlePiping Plover habitat selection and nest success on natural, managed, and engineered sandbarsFactors influencing nest survival and renesting by Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes regionWestern Snowy Plovers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius alexandrinus</named-content> nivosus</italic> select nesting substrates that enhance egg crypsis and improve nest survivalSnowy Plover reproductive success in beach and river habitatsThe effectiveness of removing predators to protect bird populationsAn evaluation of different predator exclosures used to protect Atlantic Coast Piping Plover nestsBlack Skimmer nest survival in MississippiAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalAn assessment of factors affecting population growth of the Mountain PloverHigh duck nesting success in a predator-reduced environmentEffectiveness of predator exclosures for Pectoral Sandpiper nests in AlaskaConservation of Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) in North America: Science, successes, and challengesInfluence of striped skunk removal on upland duck nest success in North DakotaExpenditures and effort associated with recovery of breeding Atlantic Coast Piping PloversManaging predation on ground-nesting birds: The effectiveness of nest exclosuresExperimental removal of introduced hedgehogs improves wader nest success in the Western Isles, ScotlandAre nest exclosures an effective tool in plover conservation?Population viability of Piping Plovers: Effects of predator exclusionThe distribution and reproductive success of the Western Snowy Plover along the Oregon coast&mdash;2003Annual report of The Oregon Biodiversity Information Center, PortlandIntegrated predator damage management report for the Western Snowy Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius alexandrinus</named-content> nivosus</italic>) 2009 breeding seasonAssessing the effectiveness of predator exclosures for ploversDirecting nest site selection of Least Terns and Piping PloversNest predation and nest sites: New perspectives on old patternsPopulation studies of Piping Plovers at Lake of the Woods, Minnesota: 19 year history of a declining populationElectric fences reduce mammalian predation on Piping Plover nests and chicksPredator exclosures: A technique to reduce predation at Piping Plover nestsThe efficacy of feral cat, fox, and rabbit exclusion fence designs for threatened species protectionSnowy Plovers select open habitats for courtship scrapes and nestsPredator exclusion methods for managing endangered shorebirds: Are two barriers better than one?Predation on adult Piping Plovers at predator exclosure cagesEffect of mammalian predator management on Snowy Plover breeding successEffects of predator exclosures on nesting success of KilldeerDistribution and abundance of the Snowy Plover on its western North American breeding groundsSnowy Plover (<italic>Charadrius nivosus</italic>)Spacing out at Mono Lake: Breeding success, nest density, and predation in the Snowy PloverDuck nesting success in a fragmented prairie landscape: Is edge effect important?Selection on clutch size in birdsUse of predator exclosures to protect Piping Plover nestsUse of fencing to limit terrestrial predator movements into Least Tern coloniesNest success of Snowy Plovers (<italic>Charadrius nivosus</italic>) in the southern high plains of TexasSnowy Plover nest survival in Kansas and effective management to counter negative effects of precipitationNest success of Black-winged Stilt <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Himantopus himantopus</named-content></italic> and Kentish Plover <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius alexandrinus</named-content></italic> in rice fields, southwest SpainEndangered and threatened wildlife and plants: Proposed special rule pursuant to Section 4(d) of the Endangered Species Act for the Pacific Coast distinct population segment of the Western Snowy PloverThe impact of different predator exclosures on Piping Plover nest abandonmentMethods for determining the age of game bird eggsProgram MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsManagement to increase reproductive success is commonly used to aid recovery of threatened and endangered species. The Western Snowy Plover (<italic>Charadrius nivosus nivosus</italic>) breeds from coastal Washington, USA, to Baja California, Mexico, and in disjunct interior sites. The Pacific coast population is federally listed as Threatened; habitat loss and nest loss to a suite of terrestrial and avian predators are thought to be primary factors limiting population growth in this species. In coastal Oregon, USA, a consortium of state and federal management agencies deployed nest exclosures on active Snowy Plover nests, initiated a lethal predator management program, and conducted local-scale habitat management in an effort to boost local productivity. During 1990&ndash;2009, we monitored 1,951 Snowy Plover nests at 9 sites with varying treatments. We examined the effectiveness of 3 types of nest exclosures (large, small, and outfitted with electric wire), predator removal, and habitat management on nest survival. Habitat management to remove invasive grasses and provide more suitable nesting substrate more than doubled nest survival. Predator management or use of any of the 3 types of exclosures also affected nest survival. There appeared to be no additional benefit to using both approaches, but the biological relevance of these findings is unclear because of site differences in treatments applied. Importantly, these management techniques only affected nesting success; their effect on other contributions to population viability (e.g., fledging success) was not correlated with nesting success. This long-term study illustrates the short-term benefits and tradeoffs of using nest exclosures, predator management, and habitat restoration to improve nesting success. Although we gained broader insight into the relative efficacy of common management techniques to improve avian nesting success, we cannot yet determine how improved nest success contributes to population growth.El manejo tendiente a aumentar el &eacute;xito reproductivo se usa com&uacute;nmente para ayudar a la recuperaci&oacute;n de especies amenazadas o en peligro. <italic>Charadrius nivosus nivosus</italic> nidifica desde la costa de Washington hasta Baja California, M&eacute;xico, y en sitios disjuntos del interior. La poblaci&oacute;n de la costa pac&iacute;fico esta listada a nivel federal como amenazada; se piensa que la p&eacute;rdida de h&aacute;bitat y la p&eacute;rdida de nidos causada por depredadores terrestres y por aves son los factores principales que limitan el crecimiento poblacional en esta especie. En la costa de Oreg&oacute;n, un consorcio de manejo de agencias estatales y federales despleg&oacute; exclusiones en nidos activos de <italic>C. n. nivosus</italic>, inici&oacute; un programa de manejo letal de los depredadores y condujo un manejo de h&aacute;bitat a escala local en un esfuerzo por impulsar la productividad local. Desde 1990 hasta 2009 monitoreamos 1.951 nidos de <italic>C. n. nivosus</italic> en nueve sitios con varios tratamientos. Examinamos la efectividad de tres tipos de exclusiones de nidos (exclusiones grandes y peque&ntilde;as, y con cerco el&eacute;ctrico), de la remoci&oacute;n de depredadores y del manejo de h&aacute;bitat sobre la supervivencia de los nidos. El manejo de h&aacute;bitat para remover los pastos invasores y brindar un sustrato de anidaci&oacute;n m&aacute;s adecuado duplic&oacute; y m&aacute;s la supervivencia del nido. El manejo de los depredadores o el uso de cualquiera de los tres tipos de exclusiones tambi&eacute;n afectaron la supervivencia del nido. Parece haber un beneficio adicional de usar ambos enfoques, pero la relevancia biol&oacute;gica de estos hallazgos no est&aacute; clara debido a las diferencias entre sitios en los tratamientos aplicados. Un hecho importante es que estas t&eacute;cnicas de manejo solo afectaron el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n; su efecto sobre otras contribuciones a la viabilidad poblacional (e.g., &eacute;xito de emplumamiento) no estuvo correlacionado con el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n. Este estudio de largo plazo muestra los beneficios de corto plazo y los pros y contras de usar exclusiones de nidos, manejo de depredadores y restauraci&oacute;n de h&aacute;bitat para mejorar el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n. Aunque adquirimos una visi&oacute;n m&aacute;s amplia de la eficacia relativa de las t&eacute;cnicas de manejo comunes para mejorar el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n de las aves, no podemos a&uacute;n determinar como la mejora del &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n contribuye al crecimiento poblacional.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic>Charadrius nivosus</italic>, depredador, exclusi&oacute;n, exclusi&oacute;n de nidos, &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n, manejo de h&aacute;bitat, Oreg&oacute;n, supervivencia del nidoConservation efforts for threatened and endangered birds often seek to boost reproductive success as a means of increasing overall population growth. There are many published examples of nesting success in birds having been improved by management strategies designed to protect nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Duebbert1">Duebbert and Lokemoen 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Rimmer1">Rimmer and Deblinger 1990</xref>). A critical assumption of this philosophy is that better nesting success translates into better recruitment and population growth. However, few studies have critically examined the long-term benefits of improved nesting success to population growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Isaksson1">Isaksson et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Claassen1">Claassen et al. 2014</xref>). Moreover, many studies fail to provide appropriate cautionary comments about the unknown contribution of improved nesting success to population growth, which should be the primary focus of any management action.In most birds, predation is the primary cause of nest loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Martin1">Martin 1993</xref>). There are many ways to reduce nest predation, such as placement of nest exclosures directly on nests or the use of electric fencing around nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Rimmer1">Rimmer and Deblinger 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mayer1">Mayer and Ryan 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Vaske1">Vaske et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Jackson1">Jackson 2001</xref>). A second approach, often used in conjunction with exclosures, is the lethal management of specific predators known to prey upon nests, chicks, or adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Duebbert1">Duebbert and Lokemoen 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>). Alternatively, when lack of high-quality habitat appears to be limiting populations, management efforts may be focused on improving critical nesting habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-GrattoTrevor1">Gratto-Trevor and Abbott 2011</xref>). Despite their widespread use, the benefits and costs of each approach are seldom rigorously assessed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mabee1">Mabee and Estelle 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Johnson1">Johnson and Oring 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 2003</xref>).Predator management is a popular approach to increase nest survival in several species of ground-nesting plovers (subfamily Charadriinae) and is believed to aid population recovery in some species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Hecht1">Hecht and Melvin 2009</xref>). One approach is to use a nest exclosure, which consists of a structure placed around the nest to deter nest predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Nol1">Nol and Brooks 1982</xref>). Exclosures vary in size and material, and some include electrical fencing as an added deterrent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mayer1">Mayer and Ryan 1991</xref>). Exclosures are widely used to promote increased nest survival in shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mayer1">Mayer and Ryan 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Deblinger1">Deblinger et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Melvin1">Melvin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Vaske1">Vaske et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Estelle1">Estelle et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mabee1">Mabee and Estelle 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Larson1">Larson et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Murphy1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 2003b</xref></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>). In these studies, exclosures were used as a tool to manage nest losses to predators. The short-term effects of exclosures are well documented; in nearly all studies, they enhanced nest success. However, the long-term benefits of nest exclosures, and other forms of predator management, to population growth are less certain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Johnson1">Johnson and Oring 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Isaksson1">Isaksson et al. 2007</xref>). Plovers rely on crypsis and early detection of predators to avoid predation; adults stealthily move from nests when a predator is detected. It is possible that exiting an exclosure slows this departure enough that predators are better able to capture the adult (D. J. Lauten and K. A. Castelein personal observation). Exclusion of predators through the use of fences is also possible, though this limits the movement of precocial young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Mayer1">Mayer and Ryan 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Rimmer2">Rimmer and Deblinger 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Moseby1">Moseby and Read 2006</xref>). Lethal predator control has been used only sparingly with shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Parker1">Parker and Takekawa 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>; see summary in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-GrattoTrevor1">Gratto-Trevor and Abbott 2011</xref>). The long-term value of predator control is often debated because removal is often followed by a recolonization of the site by predators, which means that some control must be maintained in perpetuity or its benefits will be lost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>). Like predator control, habitat management has been used sparingly to increase reproductive success of shorebirds, though its long-term effects are difficult to measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Maxson1">Maxson and Haws 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Marcus1">Marcus et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Catlin1">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>). Each of the 3 approaches described above has seen some application to conserving plover populations in North America.The Western Snowy Plover (<italic>Charadrius nivosus nivosus</italic>) breeds along the Pacific coast from Washington, USA, to Baja California Sur, Mexico, and at alkaline lakes in the interior of the western United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Page1">Page et al. 1991</xref>). Loss of habitat, predation pressures, and disturbance have caused declines in the Pacific coast population of Snowy Plovers and led to its listing as Threatened in 1993 (U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 1993, 2006, 2007). Nesting habitat has been lost to coastal development and is also threatened by dune stabilization caused by the exotic European beachgrass (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammophila arenaria</named-content></italic>). Range-wide recovery efforts have increased breeding populations, but at many sites the fledging rate (a key recovery parameter) remains below the recovery plan's goal of 1 fledgling per adult male per year (U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2007), prompting continued intensive management of the species. In Oregon, USA, recovery efforts have focused on habitat restoration and maintenance at breeding sites, predator management through both lethal and nonlethal methods, and management of human-related disturbances to nesting plovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Lauten2">Lauten et al. 2003</xref>). This suite of management activities is intended to improve annual productivity, increase Oregon's breeding population, and eventually sustain productivity and population numbers at recovery levels (U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2007). Our objectives in the present study were to (1) estimate Snowy Plover nest success; and (2) assess the possible benefits of 3 types of nest exclosures, lethal predator management, and habitat restoration. The large sample of nests, the ability to compare nests between treatments (e.g., exclosed and unexclosed nests), and the long-term dataset make this study unique. Its results are critical to conservation of this threatened coastal shorebird and may be applicable to other beach-nesting species.We measured effects of management strategies on Snowy Plover nest success across 20 breeding seasons (1990&ndash;2009) in coastal Oregon. We studied breeding Snowy Plovers at 9 sites along the Oregon coast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f01">Figure 1</xref>). From north to south, the study sites were Sutton Beach, Siltcoos River estuary, the Dunes Overlook, Tahkenitch Creek estuary, Tenmile Creek estuary, Coos Bay North Spit, Bandon Beach, New River, and Floras Lake; they are described in greater detail in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Lauten1">Lauten et al. (2010)</xref>. These sites represent habitat typical of nesting Snowy Plovers in this region and are composed of open ocean beaches and sand spits, ocean overwash sites within sand dunes dominated by European beachgrass, open estuarine areas with sand flats, and several habitat restoration sites.Map showing the location of the 9 sites along the central and southern coast of Oregon, USA, where nesting Snowy Plovers were monitored, 1990&ndash;2009. County names are in italics, and the 9 sites are labeled with filled squares.We conducted weekly surveys at all sites from roughly early April through late September, with some variation due to weather and the presence of unusually early or late nests. Field methods followed the approach outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Lauten2">Lauten et al. (2003)</xref>. Briefly, we used searches for incubating adult Snowy Plovers and behavioral cues to locate nests, which we defined as a tangible bowl or scrape with eggs or evidence of eggs (e.g., eggshells). We floated eggs to predict hatch date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Westerskov1">Westerskov 1950</xref>, G. Page personal communication) and assumed a 29-day incubation period. Nests were monitored weekly, more often near the predicted hatch date, and a &ldquo;successful nest&rdquo; was defined as a nest where &ge;1 egg hatched. Most nesting adults were individually color banded to study site fidelity and annual survival, and each brood was individually color banded to monitor brood success. Adults were captured using a lily pad trap and noose mats placed around the nest; trapping was limited to a 20-min effort at each nest, to minimize disturbance.We used the nest survival model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Dinsmore2">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>) in Program MARK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>) to model Snowy Plover nest survival in coastal Oregon. We included in our models the following 7 sources of variation in nest survival.We evaluated the effects of 3 types of nest exclosures on the survival of Snowy Plover nests: (a) a large wire exclosure with an electric wire along the top (Hotwire), (b) a large wire exclosure without an electric wire (Large), and (c) a more recently designed smaller wire exclosure (Mini) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Castelein1">Castelein et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Lauten2">Lauten et al. 2003</xref>). All exclosures were constructed of wire mesh, with an opening that was approximately 5 &times; 5 cm or 5 &times; 10 cm (the latter was most common), which allowed an adult Snowy Plover to walk, but not fly, through it (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Avian and most mammalian predators of this species cannot get through the fencing. The fencing did not exclude small mammal predators, including deer mouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Peromyscus maniculatus</named-content></italic>)<italic>,</italic> short-tailed weasel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mustela erminea</named-content></italic>), long-tailed weasel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. frenata</named-content></italic>), and immature striped skunk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mephitis mephitis</named-content></italic>). Prior to 2001, nests were exclosed as they were discovered. After 2001, exclosures were not deployed until after the peak of raptor migration (approximately May 15) because of concerns that raptors might depredate adults as they exited the structure. Exclosures were used at Sutton Beach (1994&ndash;2006; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 39), Siltcoos River estuary (1994&ndash;2009; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 126), the Dunes Overlook (1999&ndash;2008; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 65), Tahkenitch Creek estuary (1994&ndash;2008; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 92), Tenmile Creek estuary (1992&ndash;2008; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 124), Coos Bay North Spit (1990&ndash;2006; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 208), Bandon Beach (1991&ndash;2009; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 89), New River (1991&ndash;2009; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 233), and Floras Lake (1991&ndash;2009; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 42). Collectively, across all sites and years, 1,018 (52&percnt;) Snowy Plover nests received an exclosure, while 933 nests were never exclosed.Snowy Plover exclosure (Mini design) placed over a 3-egg nest in coastal Oregon. Nests are frequently in the shelter of sparse vegetation or beach debris. Photo credit: Adam KotaichLethal management of the principal predators of Snowy Plovers began at some sites in 2002 and expanded to all sites in 2004. Management was done under the appropriate state and federal permits by U.S. Department of Agriculture Wildlife Services personnel. The target species of these efforts were Common Ravens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>), American Crows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus brachyrhynchos</named-content></italic>), and several species of mammals, including red fox (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vulpes vulpes</named-content></italic>), coyote (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Canis latrans</named-content></italic>), striped skunk, and raccoon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Procyon lotor</named-content></italic>), all of which are known predators of Snowy Plover nests in this region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Burrell1">Burrell 2010</xref>). Removal was primarily done by trapping, shooting, and use of the avicide DRC-1339 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Little1">Little 2009</xref>). Effort and the number of animals removed per year varied, but the latter was generally &gt;200 corvids and &lt;30 mammals per year across all sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Little1">Little 2009</xref>, M. Burrell personal communication). Because of the variation in annual effort, we used this as a categorical variable only in our analyses.Habitat restoration efforts began in 1994 as part of the recovery plan and occurred at all sites except Floras Lake. The goal of these efforts was to provide more natural habitat at existing Snowy Plover nesting sites. Habitat Restoration Areas (HRAs) varied in size from 2 to 60 ha; because of this variation and the limited number of sites, we modeled this only as a categorical variable. Treatments occurred during the winter and included bulldozing or hand-pulling exotic European beachgrass, adding oyster shell hash as a nesting substrate, and disking to set back plant succession. Once initiated, site maintenance typically occurs annually at all HRAs. A total of 1,182 nests (61&percnt;) were located in habitat restoration areas.The 9 sites used in our study differed in size, degree of human disturbance, risk of predation by birds and mammals, and other factors. Because we did not collect data to directly address these factors, we chose to include an omnibus site effect in our models to account for these differences.Annual differences in nest survival can result from many factors, such as weather or changes in the predator community. To account for this variation, we included year effects in our model set.Other studies of the Snowy Plover have demonstrated variation in nest survival within the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Colwell1">Colwell et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Saalfeld1">Saalfeld et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Sexson1">Sexson and Farley 2012</xref>), a pattern that also occurs in other plover species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Dinsmore2">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Toral1">Toral and Figuerola 2012</xref>). Seasonal variation in survival could result from a host of factors, including adult age, differences between first nests and renests, and many others. To account for this, we compared a model with no seasonal variation &lsqb;.&rsqb; to models in which within-season variation exhibited a linear &lsqb;T&rsqb; or quadratic &lsqb;TT&rsqb; pattern. The latter 2 models do not force a specific seasonal pattern (e.g., a peak in midseason), but instead allow the data to suggest a pattern, if one exists.Clutch size ranges from 1 to 6 eggs in the Snowy Plover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Page2">Page et al. 2009</xref>), and some have suggested that smaller clutches may indicate lower-quality females that are more vulnerable to predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Price1">Price and Liou 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-PasitschniakArts1">Pasitschniak-Arts et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore 2008</xref>).We used model selection by second-order Akaike's Information Criterion, corrected for small sample sizes, (AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Akaike1">Akaike 1973</xref>) and the general approach of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson (2002)</xref> to evaluate model effects for inference. We used a hierarchical modeling approach that examined temporal patterns of nest survival first (year effects and within-year patterns of nest survival), then site differences, and finally other covariates (e.g., clutch size and habitat restoration) and the effects of predator management.We monitored a total of 1,951 nests during the 20-yr study (1990&ndash;2009; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-t01">Table 1</xref>). The total number of nests monitored at each site ranged from 63 to 486 and spanned a 153-day nesting season (March 27 to August 26) across all years. Across years, mean nest initiation date was May 30 (SD &equals; 28 days) and mean clutch size was 2.68 eggs (SD &equals; 0.67; range: 1&ndash;5 eggs). Apparent nesting success was 47&percnt; (921 of 1,951 nests were successful). Losses were primarily due to a suite of predators that included corvids (Common Raven and American Crow) and large mammals (e.g., raccoon), ocean overwash, blowing sand, and unknown causes. Apparent nesting success was greater for exclosed (68&percnt;) than for unexclosed (25&percnt;) nests; this pattern was evident in every year of the study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-t02">Table 2</xref>). However, despite this increase in nesting success, fledging rates from exclosed and unexclosed nests did not differ (two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test with unequal variances, 1990&ndash;2009; <italic>t</italic><sub>20</sub> &equals; &minus;0.92, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.37). Nest abandonment rates were similar between exclosed (56/1018 &equals; 0.055) and unexclosed (63/933 &equals; 0.068) nests. The population size and number of fledglings produced generally increased during the study period. We documented 41 adult mortalities associated with the use of nest exclosures, although we have no data on adult mortalities at unexclosed nests for comparison.Summary of Snowy Plover nesting activity by site and year in coastal Oregon, USA, 1990&ndash;2009. Sites were Sutton Beach (SU), Siltcoos River estuary (SI), the Dunes Overlook (OV), Tahkenitch Creek estuary (TA), Tenmile Creek estuary (TM), Coos Bay North Spit (CBNS), Bandon Beach (BA), New River (NR), and Floras Lake (FL).Summary of Snowy Plover numbers and productivity in coastal Oregon, USA, 1990&ndash;2009. Numbers of adults present and adults breeding were determined from detailed surveys and represent a minimum estimate. Fledgling numbers were derived from detailed brood surveys and also represent the minimum known to have survived to fledge age (28 days posthatch). The apparent nesting success for all nests, broken down by those with and without nest exclosures, represent the percentage of the total nests where &ge;1 egg hatched.Our modeling results yielded a single model with overwhelming support (AIC<sub>c</sub> weight &equals; 0.90) and a second, less competitive model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-t03">Table 3</xref>). Thus, we chose to make inference from the single best model. Collectively, these models all had support from the model set (summed AIC<sub>c</sub> weight &equals; 1.0; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-t03">Table 3</xref>). The best model combined the additive effects of site, year, a quadratic seasonal effect within year, clutch size, habitat restoration, and an interaction between predator management and the presence of any exclosure (35 parameters). The less competitive model was identical, except that the effects of predator management and the presence of any exclosure were additive (34 parameters). In the best model, there was strong evidence for site and year differences. In addition, there were strong positive effects of clutch size (&beta;<sub>Clutch</sub> &equals; 0.79 on a logit scale; 95&percnt; confidence interval &lsqb;CI&rsqb;: 0.69 to 0.89), habitat restoration (&beta;<sub>HRA</sub> &equals; 0.23 on a logit scale; 95&percnt; CI: 0.05 to 0.41), and the presence of an exclosure of any type (&beta;<sub>Exclosure</sub> &equals; 2.00 on a logit scale; 95&percnt; CI: 1.76 to 2.25), and an interaction between predator management and any exclosure (&beta;<sub>PM&lowast;Exclosure</sub> &equals; &minus;0.44 on a logit scale, 95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.78 to &minus;0.10). Thus, Snowy Plover nest survival increased with clutch size, habitat restoration, and the presence of any exclosure; with predator management, exclosures had no effect. It was the presence of any exclosure, not a particular type of exclosure, that most benefited nest survival.Model selection results for patterns of nest survival of Snowy Plovers in Oregon, USA, 1990&ndash;2009. Model effects included study sites (Site), year, linear (T) and quadratic (TT) patterns within years, clutch size (Clutch), habitat restoration efforts (HRA), lethal predator management (PM), the effects of 3 specific types of nest exclosures &lsqb;Hotwire, Large, and Mini), and a model with a single effect for the presence of any exclosure (Exclosure).We used the best model to illustrate the effects of exclosures on Snowy Plover nest survival as a function of site, year, day of season, and the presence of any exclosure. For the Siltcoos River estuary in 1990, we predicted the daily nest survival probability for a 3-egg clutch with and without an exclosure, revealing the strong seasonal increase in survival of nests without exclosures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f03">Figure 3</xref>). We also predicted the probability that a Snowy Plover nest would hatch &ge;1 egg (nest success), by site and with and without an exclosure, for years that we considered to represent poor success (1991; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f04">Figure 4</xref>A), above-average success (2004; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f04">Figure 4</xref>B), or typical success (2009; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-f04">Figure 4</xref>C).Predicted daily survival rates for a Snowy Plover nest containing 3 eggs at the Siltcoos River estuary, Oregon, USA, 1990. The two lines illustrate the effects of seasonal variation in nest survival and the predicted survival difference for exclosed and unexclosed nests.Predicted probabilities of surviving the 29-day incubation period for Snowy Plover nests in coastal Oregon, USA. The graphs illustrate differences between sites, exclosed and unexclosed nests, and 3 yr of the study. Study years were (<bold>A</bold>) a poor year (1991), (<bold>B</bold>) a good year (2004), and (<bold>C</bold>) a typical year (2009).The number of Snowy Plovers nesting in coastal Oregon has increased since the early 1990s, at least partly because of intensive management efforts that included protecting nests, removing key predators, and targeted habitat restoration efforts. The recovery strategy initially used nest exclosures and then habitat restoration to improve nesting success. Lethal predator management was later implemented as a means of improving fledging success. Biologists believed that predator management would benefit nesting success, but its primary intent was to improve fledging success. As this population increases, it is pertinent to closely examine the benefits and potential tradeoffs of these management efforts. In addition, the long-term nature of our study and its use of multiple management strategies allows for a comparison of the consequences to nest survival within a single population.Predation of nests and chicks has been identified as an important cause of population decline in the Snowy Plover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Page3">Page et al. 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Colwell2">Colwell et al. 2005</xref>), and mitigating these losses has been the focus of management activities for this species. The use of exclosures on Snowy Plover nests in Oregon resulted in an overall increase in apparent nesting success (68&percnt; for exclosed nests vs. 25&percnt; for unprotected nests). Our modeling efforts showed a similar response, with protected nests having substantially greater daily survival than unprotected nests. The increase in apparent nesting success for protected nests is consistent with the results of earlier studies of plovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Rimmer1">Rimmer and Deblinger 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Melvin1">Melvin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Maxson1">Maxson and Haws 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>). In Oregon, Snowy Plovers tend to nest at sites where they have previously succeeded in hatching a nest, regardless of their success in fledging chicks (D. J. Lauten and K. A. Castelein personal observation). Exclosures clearly increase nesting success but may not improve fledging success (Neumann et al. 2004). Exclosures may allow nests to successfully hatch young, but this may be wasted energy if predation results in high levels of chick loss. There is additional concern that exclosures may increase nest abandonment rates, but our study was consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Vaske1">Vaske et al. (1994)</xref> in finding that abandonment rates did not differ between exclosed and unprotected nests.Few studies have examined the long-term impacts of nest exclosures on shorebird populations. There is strong support that exclosures improve nesting success, but they require costly maintenance and can increase mortality of incubating adults. Adult survival may be an important factor driving population growth rate in shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Larson1">Larson et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Dinsmore3">Dinsmore et al. 2010</xref>), so any adult mortality at exclosed nests could have negative effects on population growth.Lethal predator management can be an effective tool to increase reproductive success in birds. The primary nest predators must be carefully identified, and control efforts should target only those specific predators. Such targeted management efforts can result in increased survival, as shown with Snowy Plovers in California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>), Piping Plovers (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-GrattoTrevor1">Gratto-Trevor and Abbott 2011</xref>), and a suite of shorebird species in Scotland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Jackson1">Jackson 2001</xref>). However, control measures often must be maintained in perpetuity or the benefits of control will quickly disappear, as shown in studies of waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Duebbert1">Duebbert and Lokemoen 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Greenwood1">Greenwood 1986</xref>). A meta-analysis of 22 bird species found that predator removal had large, positive effects on both nesting success and postbreeding population size, but a nonsignificant effect on subsequent breeding population size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>). Our results also suggest that predator control must take exclosure use into consideration; predator management improved nest success at unexclosed nests but did not provide additional benefits to exclosed nests.Long-term costs associated with predator removal must be weighed against the cost of habitat restoration, which may provide better long-term benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Cote1">C&ocirc;t&eacute; and Sutherland 1997</xref>). Nests on habitat restoration areas were more successful than those outside of restoration areas. Eight of 9 sites on our study area have received habitat treatments to remove nonnative vegetation and add shell hash. These treatments increase the area of suitable habitat available to breeding plovers and improve nest crypsis, potentially reducing predator nest detection. Similar results have been seen on the Missouri River with Piping Plovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Catlin1">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-619-Muir1">Muir and Colwell (2010)</xref> reported that Snowy Plovers nested in sites with significantly less <italic>Ammophila</italic> than random sites, presumably because open sites allow plovers to detect approaching predators earlier.Collectively, these management efforts (nest exclosures, lethal predator management, and habitat management) have aided the recovery of the Snowy Plover in coastal Oregon. Since 1990, the number of breeding adults has nearly tripled, the number of fledglings has increased (but with increased year-to-year variation), nesting success has benefited from exclosures, and nesting success of unexclosed nests has increased with predator management. Population growth of the Snowy Plover in Oregon is a model success story for this federally listed species. Looking ahead, this population growth has implications for the future use of the management activities we examined, as well as for future allocation of limited resources for monitoring. Monitoring this population of Snowy Plovers is becoming increasingly difficult as the population grows. Habitat management has increased the areas available to Snowy Plovers along the Oregon coast but has also made nest searching more time-consuming&mdash;there is more habitat, and, by design, improved habitat makes nests more difficult to find. Some of the adult depredations associated with exclosures have occurred within a short period, causing us to avoid using exclosures at densely populated nesting sites, for fear of losing large numbers of adults. As the population has increased, it has become difficult to use exclosures safely, because nests are more densely packed at some sites, and at others field staff does not have the time to adequately monitor the exclosures. For these reasons, exclosure use has lessened in the past few years. For monitoring, one consequence of reduced deployment of exclosures is that we have fewer opportunities to identify adults associated with nests.The suite of management actions described here (nest exclosures, lethal predator management, and habitat restoration efforts) helped increase the size of Oregon's Snowy Plover population. We recommend that exclosure use be minimized to prevent unnecessary adult depredations and that they be erected only when there is evidence of persistent corvid or large mammal activity that threatens plover nesting success. We believe that habitat management and predator management continue to be important tools to maintain Snowy Plovers along the Oregon coast.Snowy Plover management in Oregon has been supported by Coos Bay District Bureau of Land Management (BLM), Siuslaw National Forest, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife, and Oregon Parks and Recreation Department. Funding for this analysis was provided by Coos Bay District BLM. We thank the many field staff who have worked on the Oregon Snowy Plover monitoring crew over the years. We appreciate the support of the Recovery Unit 1 working team and the cooperation of USDA Wildlife Services.