Nest sanitation in cooperatively breeding Carrion CrowsDivision of labour within cooperatively breeding groupsLazy group members are substitute helpers in Carrion CrowsKin selection in cooperative alliances of Carrion CrowsCooperatively breeding groups of Carrion Crow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>) in northern SpainDirect fitness benefits of group living in a complex cooperative society of Carrion Crows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>Effect of parentage and relatedness on the individual contribution to cooperative chick care in Carrion Crows <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>Costs of chick provisioning in cooperatively breeding crows: An experimental studyReproductive success increases with group size in cooperative Carrion Crows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>Cooperative breeding in Carrion Crows reduces the rate of brood parasitism by Great Spotted CuckoosHelpers at the nest compensate for reduced maternal investment in egg size in Carrion CrowsFalse feeding: The trade-off between chick hunger and caregivers needs in cooperative crowsDivision of labour in parental care in the Magellanic Woodpecker <italic>Campephilus magellanicus</italic>Of Great Tits and fleas: Sleep baby sleep&hellip;Evolution of helping behavior in cooperatively breeding birdsA DNA test to sex most birdsNest sanitation in passerine birds: Implications for egg rejection in hosts of brood parasitesRole of helpers in the sentinel behaviour of the Florida Scrub Jay (<italic>Aphelocoma c. coerulescens</italic>)Helping is costly to young birds in cooperatively breeding White-winged ChoughsChick parasitism by blowflies affects feeding rates in a Mediterranean population of Blue TitsEffects of ectoparasites of young on parents' behaviour in a Mediterranean population of Blue TitsObservations of fecal-sac disposal by Eastern BluebirdsA test of whether economy or nutrition determines fecal sac ingestion in nesting corvidsHelper contributions to antiparasite behavior in the cooperatively breeding Bell MinerFecal sac dispersal by Prothonotary Warblers: Weatherhead's hypothesis re-evaluatedFecal sac removal: Do the pattern and distance of dispersal affect the chance of nest predation?Ectoparasitism as a possible cost of social life: A comparative analysis using Australian passerines (Passeriformes)Reproductive biology of the Bell Miner (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manorina melanophrys</named-content></italic>, Meliphagidae) at Healesville, south-eastern VictoriaGroup-living and infestation by ectoparasites in passerinesFecal sac removal by tree swallows: The cost of cleanlinessAdaptive disposal of fecal sacs?A clean nest is important for successful breeding in most bird species, because parasites and bacterial infestations can reduce nestling survival. In cooperatively breeding species, caregivers may either share nest and chick sanitation activities or specialize in different tasks related to chick care, such as food provisioning, nest sanitation, and territory and nest defense. We used video-recorded observations at nests of cooperatively breeding Carrion Crows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>) to describe sanitation behaviors and analyze the factors that influenced individuals' contributions to each particular task. We then combined data on sanitation and chick provisioning to investigate whether labor was divided within the group and whether individuals specialized in any particular task. Finally, we asked whether nest sanitation was flexible and responded to current conditions&mdash;in particular, food availability in the territory. In a controlled experiment, we supplemented 11 territories with food during the breeding season, reducing the costs of caring for the young. We found that in the cooperative groups, breeding females carried out the vast majority of sanitation tasks (i.e. nest and chick cleaning and fluffing of the nest's inner layer), whereas other group members contributed relatively little to these activities, with the exception of fecal-sac removal, which was done by any adult present at the nest during excretion. We suggest that the greater contribution of females occured because a clean nest is beneficial not only for the brood, but also for breeding females, which perform all incubation and brooding and are therefore more exposed to nest parasites. Nest sanitation also proved to be condition dependent and decreased in experimentally food-supplemented territories, where birds may have been in healthier condition and therefore less likely to transmit parasites to the brood. We suggest that extending the study of division of labor to different tasks other than chick provisioning is important to widen our understanding of the evolution and maintenance of cooperative breeding.Un nido limpio es importante para el &eacute;xito de la reproducci&oacute;n en la mayor&iacute;a de especies de aves porque los par&aacute;sitos e infecciones bacterianas pueden reducir la supervivencia de los polluelos. En especies con cr&iacute;a cooperativa, los individuos que brindan cuidado a los polluelos podr&iacute;an compartir las actividades de limpieza del nido y de los polluelos, o especializarse en diferentes tareas relacionadas con el cuidado de los polluelos como la b&uacute;squeda de alimento, la limpieza del nido y la defensa del nido y el territorio. Aqu&iacute; mostramos que en los grupos de crianza cooperativa de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic> son las hembras las que llevan a cabo la gran mayor&iacute;a de las tareas de limpieza, como la limpieza del nido y los polluelos y el mantenimiento de la capa interna del nido, mientras que otros miembros del grupo contribuyen relativamente poco a estas actividades con la excepci&oacute;n de la remoci&oacute;n de sacos fecales, que se lleva a cabo por parte de cualquier adulto presente en el nido durante la excreci&oacute;n. Sugerimos que la mayor dedicaci&oacute;n por parte de las hembras ocurre debido a que un nido limpio no solamente beneficia a las cr&iacute;as sino tambi&eacute;n a las hembras reproductivas, las cuales incuban y cr&iacute;an a los polluelos y por lo tanto est&aacute;n m&aacute;s expuestas a los par&aacute;sitos del nido. La limpieza del nido fue dependiente de la condici&oacute;n de las aves y disminuy&oacute; en los territorios en los que se brind&oacute; alimento suplementario, donde las aves podr&iacute;an haber estado en una condici&oacute;n m&aacute;s saludable y por esto tuvieron menor probabilidad de transmitir par&aacute;sitos a las cr&iacute;as. Sugerimos que la extensi&oacute;n del estudio de la divisi&oacute;n de labores en tareas diferentes a la b&uacute;squeda de alimento para los polluelos es importante para ampliar nuestro entendimiento de la evoluci&oacute;n y mantenimiento de la cr&iacute;a cooperativa.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ayudantes del nido, divisi&oacute;n de labores, limpieza de los polluelos, limpieza del nido, par&aacute;sitos del nido.A clean nest is crucial for successful breeding in most birds because bacteria and parasites can kill embryos or nestlings, reduce their growth, or augment offspring demand for food, forcing parents to increase provisioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Poiani2">Poiani 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Christe1">Christe et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-HurtrezBousses1">Hurtrez-Bouss&egrave;s et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-HurtrezBousses2">2000</xref>). Most studies have been focused on fecal-sac removal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-McGowan1">McGowan 1995</xref>), showing that it hinders microbial infestation and makes the nest less conspicuous to predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Weatherhead1">Weatherhead 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Weatherhead2">1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Petit1">Petit and Petit 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Petit2">Petit et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Lang1">Lang et al. 2002</xref>). Birds, however, perform other nest sanitation behaviors, like inspecting and preening the chicks and prodding, pulling, fluffing, or shaking vigorously the nest structure to remove the parasites (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Guigueno1">Guigueno and Sealy 2012</xref>). These tasks are demanding in terms of time and energy and may reduce the time that parents can devote to other activities, like feeding, resting, or chick provisioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Christe1">Christe et al. 1996</xref>). For example, female Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) significantly reduced their sleeping time to fight the parasites when their nests where experimentally infested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Christe1">Christe et al. 1996</xref>).The risk of parasite transmission in nests of cooperatively breeding birds may be particularly high because of the presence of multiple caregivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Poulin1">Poulin 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Poiani1">Poiani 1992</xref>). Group members should therefore respond by increasing nest sanitation, which could be affordable because parental duties are shared among several individuals. Focusing on nest sanitation also helps us understand the dynamics of cooperation in birds. Most studies on cooperative (non-eusocial) breeding in vertebrates have focused on allofeeding, neglecting other important components of parental care (but for helpers' contributions to incubation and sentinel behavior, respectively, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Heinsohn1">Heinsohn and Cockburn 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Hailman1">Hailman et al. 1994</xref>). In most species, provisioning effort is unevenly distributed among helpers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Cockburn1">Cockburn 1998</xref>), which raises the question of whether contributions to other tasks may balance the parental workload. Indeed, a few studies have found a certain degree of &ldquo;specialization&rdquo; among social-group members in tasks other than allofeeding. In cooperatively breeding Bell Miners (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manorina melanophrys</named-content></italic>), 18&percnt; of helpers only performed mobbing, 20&percnt; only provisioned the chicks, and the rest carried out both tasks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Arnold1">Arnold et al. 2005</xref>). Regarding nest sanitation, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Pacheco1">Pacheco et al. (2008)</xref> found that breeding female Bell Miners provided the greatest effort against larvae of a parasitic fly that infested the nestlings. Our understanding of cooperation at the nest would therefore benefit from a more comprehensive view of the role of each member of the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione1">Baglione et al. 2010</xref>) that analyzes contribution to any activity related to rearing of young.We studied nest sanitation in a population of cooperatively breeding Carrion Crows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone</italic>) in northern Spain. We used video-recorded observations at the nest to describe sanitation behaviors and analyze the factors that influenced individuals' contributions to each particular task. We expected a positive effect of the number of caregivers on the sanitation rate, because parasite transmission in passerines increases with group size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Poulin1">Poulin 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Poiani1">Poiani 1992</xref>) and individuals in larger groups may allocate more time to nest or chick cleaning. Second, by combining data on sanitation and chick provisioning, we investigated whether labor was divided within the groups and whether individuals specialized in any particular task. Finally, we asked whether nest sanitation was flexible and responded to current conditions&mdash;in particular, food availability in the territory. In a controlled experiment, we supplemented 11 territories with food during the breeding season, reducing the costs of caring for the young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>). If individuals faced a trade-off between nest sanitation and other parental (chick provisioning) or self-maintenance activities (feeding), we expected sanitation to increase in supplemented territories. Conversely, if individuals adjusted sanitation to the risk of brood infection, we expected that supplemented caregivers&mdash;which are in healthier condition than unfed ones during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>) and, therefore, are potentially less likely to transmit parasites to the chicks&mdash;would decrease their effort. Alternatively, nest sanitation behavior may not respond to current environmental conditions and thus not vary with food availability.Since 1995, we have studied a population of Carrion Crows in a 45-km<sup>2</sup> rural area in northwestern Spain (42&deg;37&prime;N, 5&deg;26&prime;W). Carrion Crows build large nests (~40 cm external diameter) in the upper third of the tree in Pyrenean oaks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Quercus pyrenaica</named-content></italic>), black poplars (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus nigra</named-content></italic>), willows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Salix</named-content></italic> spp.), holm oaks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Quercus ilex</named-content></italic>), and pines (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus</named-content></italic> spp.). The nest structure consists of 3 layers: a base, made of strong branches; an intermediate layer formed by thinner branches, stems, and roots; and an inner part composed of animal hair (mostly from sheep and other domestic animals), moss, herbs, and sometimes soft anthropogenic materials.In this population, Carrion Crows breed cooperatively in 75&percnt; of the territories and form cohesive groups of &le;9 individuals that comprise a breeding pair, its philopatric offspring, and/or immigrants closely related to the breeder of the same sex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione3">Baglione et al. 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione2">2003</xref>). Breeding females alone incubate the clutch (2&ndash;7 eggs) and brood for 2 wk after hatching. Although females can delay natal dispersal and occasionally immigrate and help in other territories, sex ratio in the groups is typically male biased. Sexually mature immigrants may share reproduction with the dominant pair, whereas nondispersing offspring do not, thus avoiding incest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione4">Baglione et al. 2002b</xref>). Nonbreeders contribute to defending the territory, building the nest, and feeding the chicks and the incubating female. However, some group members refrain from helping in any task, 5 being the maximum number of caregivers found in a group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari1">Canestrari et al. 2005</xref>). Breeders feed the chicks at a higher rate than nonbreeding helpers and, among helpers, males contribute more than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari1">Canestrari et al. 2005</xref>). Allofeeding increases annual reproductive success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari3">Canestrari et al. 2008</xref>), but it is costly for caregivers, which lose weight proportionally to their effort (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>). In this long-lived species, both breeders and helpers invest in self-maintenance rather than increasing chick provisioning when food availability is experimentally augmented during the breeding season, which shows the importance of reducing the high costs of parental care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>).Adults were captured using 2 compartment walk-in traps and a snap trap (3 &times; 3 m) specifically designed for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione3">Baglione et al. 2002a</xref>), whereas nestlings were taken from the nest just before fledging. All birds were marked with a unique combination of plastic color rings and/or patagial wing tags (6.5 &times; 3.5 cm). We collected 50&ndash;200 &mu;L of blood from the brachial vein for DNA extraction and P2&ndash;P8 molecular sexing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Griffiths1">Griffiths et al. 1998</xref>).Data were collected in 2000, 2003, 2004, 2006, and 2007 in 31 territories. Observations were repeated in different years (&le;4 yr) in 9 territories where group composition had completely or partly changed. In total, we collected data from 46 groups yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> (repeated measures from the same territory were accounted for in the statistical analyses; see below). The sample comprised 69 breeders (36 males and 33 females) and 51 nonbreeders (34 males and 17 females), all individually recognizable; 10 groups yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> (9 territores) comprised 2 unbanded birds that could not be differentiated in the video-recordings and that were therefore excluded from the sample; 22 groups yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> comprised only 1 unbanded bird, which could therefore be recognized and used for analyses. All these birds were breeding females, as unequivocally inferred from the composition of the rest of the group and from brooding behavior. Substitution of a breeding female during a nesting attempt has never been observed in our study population, from the start of our long-term study in 1995. We have also never observed immigrant Carrion Crows joining a breeding group during the breeding season and helping raise the current brood. Therefore, we are confident that, despite the lack of marks, in every territory we always observed the same female throughout the sampling period. At the beginning of the breeding season, we monitored all territories to record group size and locate the nests (for details, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari3">Canestrari et al. 2008</xref>). We used camouflaged micro video cameras placed 2&ndash;2.5 m away from the nests to record individual provisioning rate and nest sanitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari1">Canestrari et al. 2005</xref>). Recording bouts (4&ndash;8 hr) were distributed randomly between 0600 and 2000 hours. Some recordings had to be discharged partly or completely when the quality was unsuitable for analysis, typically because the wind shook the video camera. We collected for an average (&plusmn; SE) of 22.8 &plusmn; 1.6 hr nest<sup>&minus;1</sup> (range: 6&ndash;56 hr). Brood age at the time of video-recording ranged from 2 to 36 days. In every nest visit, we measured the total time allocated to sanitation tasks (see below) by every recognizable individual, as well as the number of feedings delivered to the chicks (&ldquo;feeding&rdquo; is defined here as every act of delivering food to a chick's open gape and is a suitable proxy for the caregiving effort; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari1">Canestrari et al. 2005</xref>) and the number of chicks' fecal sacs disposed of (either eaten or carried away). Seven nests were parasitized by Great Spotted Cuckoos (<italic>Clamator glandarius</italic>), a brood parasite that specializes on corvids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari4">Canestrari et al. 2009</xref>). The presence of cuckoo chicks was taken into account in the analyses (see below).We identified 3 different sanitation behaviors: (1) chick cleaning (caregiver inspects the chicks and removes ectoparasites and dirt); (2) nest cleaning (caregiver eats or carries away food leftovers, feces, insects, broken or spoiled pieces of the nest structure, and dead chicks); and (3) nest fluffing (adult grabs the inner layer of the nest with its beak and pulls it quickly, vigorously, and repeatedly). All contributions to sanitation could be classified within these categories.At the beginning of the breeding seasons of 2003 and 2004, we randomly chose 12 territories and supplemented them every day with canned dog food (brand DIA, chicken and beef flavor), in which the proportions of meat and vegetables (78.8&percnt; and 21.2&percnt;, respectively) resembled the proportions of animal and vegetal components of the Carrion Crow's natural diet (between 82.6&percnt; animal:17.4&percnt; vegetal and 41.7&percnt; animal:58.3&percnt; vegetal; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>). The food was delivered in the middle of the territory (~200 m away from the nest), from the beginning of the breeding season (after the nest was completed but before egg laying) until the chicks fledged or the nest failed. All nonsupplemented territories served as the control. After accounting for nest failures, we eventually collected data on 11 supplemented territories and 35 control territories. In experimental territories, we confirmed with video-recordings at the feeding spot that all target birds had access to the supplemental food. Usually, all food was consumed or stored within 20 min after our departure. Food supplementation never coincided with video-recording, so that the behavioral data collected at the nest would not be biased by the fact that Carrion Crows were busy at the bait pile.We analyzed data with linear mixed models (LMMs) fitted with the &ldquo;lmer&rdquo; function from lme4 library in R statistical software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Crawley1">Crawley 2013</xref>). Individual identity, nested in territory identity, and year were fitted as random terms in all models to account for repeated measures of the same individuals and territories. Initially, we ran LMMs using maximum likelihood, including all potential explanatory variables. Subsequently, we used Akaike's Information Criteria (AIC) to reduce the model. We sequentially removed those variables that significantly increased the AIC value according to a log likelihood ratio test. The final optimal model was the one with the lowest AIC, regardless of the <italic>P</italic> values of the variables included. This model was rerun with restricted maximum likelihood, and final <italic>P</italic> values of fitted terms were obtained with a log likelihood ratio test. Final <italic>P</italic> values of dropped terms were obtained with the same test, by reintroducing them individually into the optimal model run with restricted maximum likelihood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Crawley1">Crawley 2013</xref>). All models were checked for homoscedasticity of variance and normality of residuals.First, we analyzed the factors affecting an individual's total duration of nest sanitation behavior per hour of observation, summing up the time spent in the 3 sanitation tasks (i.e. nest cleaning, chick cleaning, and nest fluffing). This analysis was repeated in a subsample of broods &gt;15 days old to check whether the results held when the breeding female was no longer brooding and therefore flew to and from the nest like any other group member. Afterward, we investigated each sanitation task separately. Additionally, we checked whether the experimental food supplementation influenced the duration of nest visits, because such an effect could hinder the interpretation of any change in sanitation (see below). All these response variables were log transformed for normality. Finally, we tested which factors influenced individual (square root transformed) fecal-sac-removal frequency (number of fecal sacs removed per hour). In all models, we fitted the following variables as fixed terms: sex, status (breeder or helper), provisioning effort (i.e. number of feedings delivered per hour), brood size, brood age, number of nest caregivers, presence&ndash;absence of Great Spotted Cuckoo chicks, experimental treatment (food supplemented&ndash;control), and the interactions sex&ast;status, sex&ast;experiment, and status&ast;experiment. Values for nonsignificant interactions are omitted from the results.Breeding females invested in sanitation more than any other group member, as shown by the significant interaction between sex and status on total nest sanitation time (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 22.99, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f01">Figure 1</xref>A and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t01">Table 1</xref>). The result held when we restricted the analysis to broods &gt;15 days old (i.e. when the breeding females no longer brooded; &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 11.25, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004). Females also tended to decrease their effort when food was experimentally provided (see interaction sex&ast;experiment: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.252, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.071; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f02">Figure 2</xref>A and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t01">Table 1</xref>). We also found a positive correlation between total sanitation time and both chick provisioning rate (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 38.46, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and brood size (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 6.21, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.013).Model estimates (means &plusmn; SE) of time spent on each type of sanitation by sex and breeding status. Males are represented by black bars and females by white bars. Samples sizes: 36 breeding males, 33 breeding females, 34 male helpers, and 17 female helpers.Model estimates (means &plusmn; SE) of time spent on each type of sanitation by sex and experimental condition. Males are represented by black bars and females by white bars. Samples sizes: 57 control males, 37 control females, 15 experimental males, and 16 experimental females.Nest visits by breeding females lasted longer than those of other group members, as shown by the significant interaction between sex and status (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 39.73, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t06">Table 6</xref>). As brood age and brood size increased, the duration of the visits significantly decreased (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 27.54, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 12.54, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.0004, respectively). The food supplementation experiment did not influence the average length of visits to the nest (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.82, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.365) of any individual.When we considered the 3 different sanitation tasks separately, we found that breeding females contributed more than the rest of the individuals to chick cleaning (sex&ast;status: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 9.09, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.011; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f01">Figure 1</xref>B and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t02">Table 2</xref>) and significantly decreased their effort when food was experimentally provided (interaction sex&ast;experiment: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 6.082, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.048; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f02">Figure 2</xref>B and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t02">Table 2</xref>). Chick cleaning was positively correlated with provisioning effort (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 9.055, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003) and with brood age (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 12.476, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.0004; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t02">Table 2</xref>).Nest cleaning was performed mainly by females, regardless of their status (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 18.286, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f01">Figure 1</xref>C and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t03">Table 3</xref>) and decreased with brood size (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 22.994, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). All caregivers, regardless of sex or status, reduced the time allocated to nest cleaning when food was experimentally provided (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 4.389, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.036; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f02">Figure 2</xref>C and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t03">Table 3</xref>). Again, group members that provisioned the chicks most also allocated more time to this activity (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 46.394, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001).Nest fluffing was done mainly by breeding females (sex&ast;status: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 29.357, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f01">Figure 1</xref>D and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t04">Table 4</xref>), which tended to decrease their effort in experimentally fed territories (interaction sex&ast;experiment: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 5.142, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.076; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f02">Figure 2</xref>D and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t04">Table 4</xref>). Nest fluffing also decreased significantly with brood age (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 6.305, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.012) and tended to increase with chick provisioning rate (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.465, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.063).Breeding males disposed of fecal sacs more than breeding females did, but the pattern was reversed among nonbreeders, as shown by the significant interaction sex&ast;status (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 51.591, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-f03">Figure 3</xref> and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t05">Table 5</xref>). Fecal-sac disposal rate also increased significantly with chick provisioning rate (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 111.31, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), brood age (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 18.658, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), and brood size (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 18.975, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), whereas it tended to decrease if the nest was parasitized (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.108, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.078). The number of caregivers never showed a significant effect on any sanitation task considered (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t01">Tables 1</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-t05">5</xref>).Model estimates (means &plusmn; SE) of fecal disposal rate by sex and breeding status. Males are represented by black bars and females by white bars. Samples sizes: 36 breeding males, 33 breeding females, 34 male helpers, and 17 female helpers.Chick cleaning increased with brood age, probably because the risk of ectoparasites or bacterial infestations increased as chicks grew feathers. Nest fluffing, on the contrary, decreased over the nestling period, surely impeded by the growing weight and size of the brood. Besides, caregivers sometimes removed the nest's inner layer when chicks were ~20 days old and were fully feathered, probably to favor chick thermoregulation when the weather warmed up and to get rid of dirt and parasites. Finally, total sanitation time and, particularly, nest cleaning decreased in larger broods. This is surprising, because the larger the number of chicks, the dirtier the nest should be. We suggest that the high food demand of large broods may constrain the time allocated by caregivers to other activities, like nest sanitation.The number of caregivers attending a nest had no significant effect on the individual effort allocated to any sanitation task, which suggests that the risk of infestation did not increase with the number of helpers at the nest. This is plausible, because adult Carrion Crows in bad conditions dramatically decrease or cease feeding the nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione1">Baglione et al. 2010</xref>), so that the sickest individuals are unlikely to get in direct touch with the brood.Among members of cooperative groups, chick cleaning and nest fluffing were done mainly by breeding females, whereas all female caregivers, regardless of breeding status, were more active than males in nest cleaning. Males, in general, contributed little to sanitation activities, with the exception of fecal-sac removal. This time-inexpensive task, however, was invariably carried out by any adult present at the nest at the moment of chick defecation, which typically occurred immediately after feeding; thus, the greater contribution by males was a consequence of their greater nest-visiting rate. Overall, in this society, sanitation activities were mainly a female duty, though males were not incapable of doing sanitation tasks&mdash;they performed a small proportion of all the activities described.A clear division of tasks among members did not occur in Carrion Crow groups, as indicated by the fact that individuals that were more active in chick provisioning also spent more time in sanitation activities. Conversely, in Noisy Miners (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Manorina melanocephala</named-content></italic>), helpers that provisioned the chicks at higher rates contributed less to mobbing and vice versa, with some individuals fully specialized in either activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Arnold1">Arnold et al. 2005</xref>). More data are needed to test whether, in cooperative Carrion Crows, other activities such as vigilance and territory or nest defense, which are not considered in this work, may compensate for a reduced investment in caring for chicks. However, preliminary observations suggest that defense tasks are carried out mainly by breeding group members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Baglione3">Baglione et al. 2002a</xref>), which are also the most active in chick provisioning and nest sanitation. This suggests that division of labor between breeders and helpers does not occur in Carrion Crow groups, and that breeding adults invest highly in all activities related to chick care.Our results show that breeding females contributed the greatest effort to nest sanitation. Breeding Carrion Crows, especially females, are very sensitive to the costs of reproduction and minimize them by finely adjusting their investment between the current brood and self-maintenance, reducing the current nestling-care effort whenever possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari6">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari5">2011</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that the important contribution to sanitation by breeding females may be beneficial not only for the chicks, but also for the adult. Individuals that perform egg incubation and chick brooding are more exposed than others to the risk of ectoparasites or bacterial infections from a dirty nest and are therefore expected to benefit more from increasing sanitation activities. Consistent with this idea, incubation and brooding are exclusive to breeding female Carrion Crows, which also show the greatest effort in cleaning activities. A similar pattern was found in cooperatively breeding Bell Miners, in which the greatest antiparasite effort was made by the breeding female (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Pacheco1">Pacheco et al. 2008</xref>); and in Magellanic Woodpeckers (<italic>Campephilus magellanicus</italic>), in which the male performed most of the brooding and nest sanitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Chazarreta1">Chazarreta et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, a recent review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Guigueno1">Guigueno and Sealy (2012)</xref> also confirmed that ectoparasite removal is mainly performed by the brooding individuals.It can be argued that breeding females invest more time in nest sanitation because they spend more time on nest incubating and brooding and thus have more opportunity to do so. However, breeding females have never been recorded performing sanitation tasks while brooding. Therefore, sanitation in breeding females involves a trade-off with other activities, as it does for any other group member. In addition, analysis of our data including only broods &gt;15 days old dismissed this explanation, showing that breeding females continued to perform most of the sanitation even after brooding was completed.The fact that nest sanitation proved to be a flexible behavior that varied according to external conditions, specifically food availability, also confirms that females make decisions about how much they invest in cleaning. Supplementally fed breeding females significantly reduced sanitation time compared with unfed ones, thus dismissing the hypothesis of a trade-off between nest sanitation and other activities, particularly feeding (see above). Food supplementation has been shown to improve the body condition of chick caregivers in Carrion Crows by significantly reducing their weight loss during the nesting phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-Canestrari2">Canestrari et al. 2007</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that females decreased sanitation in experimentally fed territories because the healthier conditions of all caregivers decreased the risk of parasite transmission to the brood. It should be noted here that fecal-sac consumption can have some energetic value to the parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-604-McGowan1">McGowan 1995</xref>), such that supplemented females may have cleaned less merely because they did not need extra energy. This hypothesis, however, is unlikely to explain our results, because supplementation did not change the rate at which sacs were removed (all sacs were removed immediately when an adult was present). Therefore, although the rate of sac consumption by adults might have changed (coprophagy was not measured in the present study), the observed variation in the rate of sanitation among fed and unfed females was driven by changes in other, more time-consuming behaviors (i.e. nest cleaning, chick cleaning, and nest fluffing) that are unlikely to provide any nutritional return.In summary, our study uncovered a greater contribution by females to nest sanitation, which is one important component of cooperative nestling care. Ongoing research on territory defense, vigilance, and sentinel behavior will widen our view on the dynamics of cooperation in the Carrion Crow, leading to a better understanding of the function of each member of the group. We believe that such a comprehensive approach, which extends beyond allofeeding behavior, will be crucial for explaining the evolution and maintenance of cooperative breeding in birds.We thank two anonymous reviewers for useful comments on the manuscript and H. Robles and J. Seoane for statistical advice.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This study was financially supported by the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation and the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitivity through projects CGL2008-01829BOS and CGL2011-27260 to V.B.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> All bird manipulations were authorized by Junta de Castilla y Le&oacute;n and caused no damage to the birds.Factors affecting total sanitation time spent by caregivers. Variables included in the minimal model are in bold.Factors affecting chick-cleaning time spent by caregivers. Variables included in the minimal model are in bold.Factors affecting nest-sanitation time spent by caregivers. Variables included in the minimal model are in bold.Factors affecting nest-fluffing time spent by caregivers. Variables included in the minimal model are in bold.Factors affecting fecal-sac-removal rate of caregivers. All variables were included in the minimal model.Factors affecting the average length of visits to the nest. Variables included in the minimal model are in bold.