Winter body condition in the Collared Flycatcher: Determinants and carryover effects on future breeding parametersEvolution of reversed sexual size dimorphism and role partitioning among predatory birds, with a size scaling of flight performanceAerodynamics and the evolution of long tails in birdsApparent inferiority of first-time breeders in the kittiwake: The role of heterogeneity among age classesFeather traits and ptilochronology as indicators of stress in Iberian Blackcaps <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia atricapilla</named-content></italic>Territory quality and feather growth in the White-backed Woodpecker <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendrocopos leucotos</named-content></italic>Winter segregation of migrant European Robins <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Erithacus rubecula</named-content></italic> in relation to sex, age and sizeRate of moult affects feather quality: A mechanism linking current reproductive effort to future survivalRepeatable length and mass but not growth rate of individual feathers between moults in a passerine birdFeather mass and winter moult extent are heritable but not associated with fitness-related traits in a long-distance migratory birdGenetic and environmental effects on a condition-dependent trait: Feather growth in Siberian JaysPtilochronology: Feather growth bars as indicators of nutritional statusSupplementary food improves the nutritional condition of wintering woodland birds: Evidence from ptilochronologyPtilochronology: Induced feather growth in Northern Cardinals varies with age, sex, ambient temperature, and day lengthHabitat-specific nutritional condition in Loggerhead Shrikes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lanius ludovicianus</named-content></italic>): Evidence from ptilochronologyWinter body condition in relation to age, sex and plumage ornamentation in a migratory songbirdHow fast can birds migrate?Using information theory as a substitute for stepwise regression in ecology and behaviorRapid temporal change in the expression and age-related information content of a sexually selected traitPlumage colour signals nutritional condition in the House FinchHigh individual repeatability and population differentiation in stable isotope ratios in winter-grown Collared Flycatcher <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic> feathersThe energetic cost of feather synthesis is proportional to basal metabolic rateStudies of less familiar birds. Collared FlycatcherCorrelates of wing morphology with foraging behaviour and migration distance in the genus <italic>Phylloscopus</italic>The role of behavioral dominance in structuring patterns of habitat occupancy in a migrant bird during the nonbreeding seasonLinking winter and summer events in a migratory bird by using stable-carbon isotopesCorticosterone levels as indicators of habitat quality: Effects of habitat segregation in a migratory bird during the non-breeding seasonMalaria infection and feather growth rate predict reproductive success in House MartinsNo effect of age of males on reproductive success of the Collared Flycatcher <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>Sexual selection in the Barn Swallow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>. VI. Aerodynamic adaptationsEnergy and nutrient use during moult by White-crowned Sparrows <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> gambelii</italic>Malnutrition during the postnuptial molt of White-crowned Sparrows: Feather growth and qualityThe cost of reproduction: A new link between current reproductive effort and future reproductive successTropical winter habitat limits reproductive success on the temperate breeding grounds in a migratory birdThe timing of birds' breeding seasonsBirds of a feather winter together: Migratory connectivity in the Reed Warbler <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Acrocephalus scirpaceus</named-content></italic>A ptilochronological study of carry-over effects of conditions during wintering on breeding performance in the Barn Swallow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>Ecological conditions during winter predict arrival date at the breeding quarters in a trans-Saharan migratory birdAdaptive evolution in the avian wingDisappearance of female Pied Flycatchers in relation to breeding stage and experimentally induced moltReduced feather growth rates of two common birds inhabiting Central Amazonian forest fragmentsFood availability and primary feather molt in European Starlings, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>Comparison of trace element and stable isotope approaches to the study of migratory connectivity: An example using two hirundine species breeding in Europe and wintering in AfricaThe growth bars on tail feathers in the male Styan's Grasshopper Warbler may indicate qualityFeather development under environmental stress: Lead exposure effects on growth patterns in Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>On the aerodynamics of birds' tailsFood segregation in three hole-nesting bird species during the breeding seasonEffects of caching supplemental food on induced feather regeneration in wintering Gray Jays <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>: A ptilochronology study.Territory size influences nutritional condition in nonbreeding Loggerhead Shrikes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lanius ludovicianus</named-content></italic>)&mdash;A ptilochronology approachFactors that determine the condition of migratory birds at their wintering sites are poorly known. Age, sex, and morphological characteristics of birds may have an influence on their winter condition by affecting their foraging and competitive abilities. Winter body condition could have long-term consequences on the reproductive success of migratory birds during the subsequent breeding season. Using 3 yr of data from Collared Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>), we examined the characteristics of winter-grown tail feathers, as indicators of winter body condition, in relation to sex, age, morphological traits, and future breeding variables. Tail feather mass was highly repeatable between years, but feather growth rate was not repeatable, which suggests that the latter trait mainly indicates environmental circumstances during molt, whereas feather mass may more strongly reflect genetic effects. Tail feathers of males and adults showed better quality than those of females and juveniles, possibly because of differences between age classes and sexes in individual quality and foraging skills or because of winter habitat segregation. Birds with longer wings produced better-quality tail feathers, which suggests that wing and tail feather characteristics are similarly affected, presumably by individual genetic quality. Smaller Collared Flycatchers grew their tail feathers faster during the winter molt, possibly because they had better foraging ability due to better flight maneuverability. Tail feather quality showed no relationship with laying date; however, females that had produced heavier tail feathers during winter laid larger clutches during the following breeding season, which suggests that tail feather mass potentially reflects intrinsic individual quality.Les facteurs d&eacute;terminant la condition des oiseaux migrateurs sur leurs sites d'hivernage sont peu connus. L'&acirc;ge, le sexe et les caract&eacute;ristiques morphologiques des oiseaux peuvent avoir une influence sur leur condition hivernale en affectant leurs capacit&eacute;s de se nourrir et comp&eacute;titives. La condition corporelle hivernale a pu avoir des cons&eacute;quences &agrave; long terme sur le succ&egrave;s de reproduction des oiseaux migrateurs au cours de la saison de reproduction subs&eacute;quente. &Agrave; partir de trois ann&eacute;es de donn&eacute;es sur <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>, nous avons examin&eacute; les caract&eacute;ristiques des rectrices d&eacute;velopp&eacute;es pendant l'hiver comme des indicateurs de la condition corporelle en hiver, en relation avec le sexe, l'&acirc;ge, les traits morphologiques et les variables de reproduction future. La masse des rectrices &eacute;tait hautement reproductible entre les ann&eacute;es mais le taux de croissance des plumes n'&eacute;tait pas reproductible, sugg&eacute;rant que ce dernier trait indique surtout les circonstances environnementales au cours de la mue, alors que la masse des plumes peut refl&eacute;ter davantage les effets g&eacute;n&eacute;tiques. Les rectrices des oiseaux m&acirc;les et adultes &eacute;taient de meilleure qualit&eacute; que celles des oiseaux femelles et juv&eacute;niles, probablement en raison des diff&eacute;rences dans la qualit&eacute; individuelle et les comp&eacute;tences de recherche de nourriture entre les classes d'&acirc;ge et les sexes, ou la s&eacute;gr&eacute;gation de l'habitat hivernal entre eux. Les oiseaux avec de plus longues ailes ont produit des rectrices de meilleure qualit&eacute;, ce qui sugg&egrave;re que les caract&eacute;ristiques des plumes des ailes et de la queue sont affect&eacute;es de fa&ccedil;on similaire, probablement par la qualit&eacute; g&eacute;n&eacute;tique individuelle. Les plus petits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">F. albicollis</named-content></italic> ont d&eacute;velopp&eacute; leurs rectrices plus rapidement au cours de la mue hivernale, possiblement parce qu'ils ont une meilleure capacit&eacute; de recherche de nourriture en raison d'une meilleure man&oelig;uvrabilit&eacute; de vol. La qualit&eacute; des rectrices n'a montr&eacute; aucune relation avec la date de ponte; cependant, les femelles qui ont produit des rectrices plus lourdes en hiver ont pondu des couv&eacute;es plus grosses au cours de la saison de reproduction suivante, ce qui sugg&egrave;re que la masse des rectrices refl&egrave;te potentiellement la qualit&eacute; individuelle intrins&egrave;que.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> condition corporelle, taille de couv&eacute;e, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>, passereau migrateur, qualit&eacute; du plumage, ptilochronologie, mue hivernaleFactors that determine the condition of migratory birds at their wintering sites are poorly known. The age, sex, and morphology of birds all may have an influence on their winter condition by affecting their foraging and competitive abilities. Winter body condition could be an important factor that determines arrival time, laying date, and reproductive success of migratory birds during the subsequent breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Norris1">Norris et al. 2004</xref>). For example, winter habitat quality influenced the condition and spring departure dates of American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>), which resulted in variable arrival times at the breeding areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>). For migratory birds, early arrival is generally advantageous because it gives access to the best breeding sites and mates, higher food availability, and additional time to replace lost clutches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Perrins1">Perrins 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Nilsson1">Nilsson and Svensson 1996</xref>).Plumage is replaced repeatedly over the lifetime of birds, necessitated by the mechanical abrasion of feathers. Because plumage is important in thermoregulation, protection, communication, and locomotion, time spent molting should be minimized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 1988</xref>). Avian molt is physiologically costly, not only in terms of energy, but also in the requirements for specific nutrients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy1">Murphy and King 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Lindstrom1">Lindstr&ouml;m et al. 1993</xref>), so molt parameters may vary with food quality and availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Swaddle1">Swaddle and Witter 1997</xref>). Therefore, it is expected that individuals of the same species that molt in habitats of different quality may show differences in plumage quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Carlson1">Carlson 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Carbonell1">Carbonell and Teller&iacute;a 1999</xref>). Replacement of feathers may be slower, and feathers may contain lower amounts of materials when feather development competes for a limited supply of energy and specific nutrients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb1">Grubb 1989</xref>).To estimate the body condition of birds during the period of molt, a technique called &ldquo;ptilochronology&rdquo; has been used successfully (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Stratford1">Stratford and Stouffer 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Talloen1">Talloen et al. 2008</xref>). Growth bars across the vane of the feathers reflect the daily cycles of melanocyte activity, with darker and lighter bands marking the growth during day and night, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb1">Grubb 1989</xref>). Therefore, the width of the bars indicates daily feather growth rate and, indirectly, the nutritional condition of an individual over the molt period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb1">Grubb 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb2">Grubb and Cimprich 1990</xref>). It has been demonstrated that growth bar width of feathers is influenced by food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hill1">Hill and Montgomerie 1994</xref>), territory size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Yosef1">Yosef and Grubb 1992</xref>), habitat quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb4">Grubb and Yosef 1994</xref>), parasite infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Saino1">Saino et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marzal1">Marzal et al. 2013</xref>), and environmental stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Talloen1">Talloen et al. 2008</xref>). Additionally, individuals of high intrinsic quality may grow their feathers more rapidly than lower-quality individuals, as suggested by the high within-individual repeatability of plumage characteristics between molts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera1">de la Hera et al. 2009</xref>) and the significant heritability of feather growth rate and mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Gienapp1">Gienapp and Meril&auml; 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera2">de la Hera et al. 2013</xref>).Feathers may also be shorter and lighter under nutritional stress conditions, when allocation of resources to plumage production may be limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy2">Murphy et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Carbonell1">Carbonell and Teller&iacute;a 1999</xref>). Feather stiffness and hardness may be positively correlated with feather mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Dawson1">Dawson et al. 2000</xref>), so feather mass could be an indirect measure of feather quality. One cost of having shorter and lighter feathers may be an impaired flight performance, which could affect foraging efficiency and increase predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Slagsvold1">Slagsvold and Dale 1996</xref>). Also, lower-quality feathers might influence migration speed, prolonging the duration of migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marchetti1">Marchetti et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hedenstrom1">Hedenstr&ouml;m and Alerstam 1998</xref>).We examined the following associations in a migratory passerine, the Collared Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>). First, we tested the repeatability of tail feather characteristics between consecutive years to see how much they may depend on stable individual quality versus changing environmental circumstances. Second, we investigated whether stable traits (age, sex, and tarsus length) and a characteristic that had been developed during the preceding summer molt (wing length) influenced winter condition, as reflected by tail feather quality. The relationships between sex, age, and feather growth rate have already been analyzed in our previous study on a smaller dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hargitai1">Hargitai et al. 2012</xref>). Finally, we studied the relationships between tail feather quality and the breeding variables (laying date and clutch size) of birds during the following spring to examine whether conditions during winter could have long-term life history consequences.The study was carried out in a nestbox-breeding population of Collared Flycatchers in an oak-dominated woodland in the Pilis Mountains (47&deg;43&prime;N, 19&deg;01&prime;E), Hungary, in 2008&ndash;2010. The Collared Flycatcher is a long-distance migratory, hole-nesting, insectivorous passerine that spends the winter in sub-Saharan Africa, as confirmed by ringing recoveries and visual observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Cramp1">Cramp and Perrins 1993</xref>). Flycatchers molt body feathers, tail feathers, and tertials in their winter quarters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Svensson1">Svensson 1992</xref>). Birds were captured in the nestbox during the nestling feeding period. They were weighed with a Pesola spring balance (&plusmn;0.1 g), the length of the tarsus was measured with a caliper (&plusmn;0.1 mm), and the length of the wing was measured with a ruler (&plusmn;1 mm). We determined the age (yearling or adult) of males from the color of remiges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Svensson1">Svensson 1992</xref>) or ringing data; the age of females was determined from ringing data.We plucked the left and right second-outermost rectrices of birds during the nestling feeding period in each year (May&ndash;June) and stored them in envelopes until analyses. In 2010, we collected only one feather, because measurements were strongly correlated between left and right feathers (length: <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.85, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 235; vane area: <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.63, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 228; growth rate: <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.54, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 130; feather mass: <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.81, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 334). We collected tail feathers from 172 (76 males and 96 females), 126 (68 males and 58 females), and 166 (95 males and 71 females) birds in 2008, 2009, and 2010, respectively. We measured the width of eight growth bars perpendicular to the vane of the second rectrices as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hargitai1">Hargitai et al. (2012)</xref>. We weighed the rectrices to the nearest 0.0001 g with a Mettler AE200 digital balance. Also, we scanned the feathers and measured the total length of each from the calamus end to the feather tip, and the area of the vane, with the Scion Image program (see Acknowledgments) in 2008 and 2009. Because we found that feather length and vane area were strongly correlated with feather mass (see below), we did not measure them in 2010. Where available, average values of the left and right feathers were used in the analyses.Data were analyzed with Pearson correlations and general linear models. In general linear models, a stepwise analysis based on backward deletion procedure was employed, removing nonsignificant (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) interactions and main effects from the model one by one, in decreasing order of <italic>P</italic> values. We did not report the <italic>F</italic> and <italic>P</italic> values of nonsignificant variables before elimination, because nonsignificance could be due to overparameterization of the model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hegyi1">Hegyi and Garamszegi 2011</xref>). Therefore, we reintegrated them to the final model one by one, and we present those <italic>F</italic> and <italic>P</italic> values here. We analyzed the relationships between various tail feather traits with Pearson correlations. The repeatabilities of feather traits between consecutive years were analyzed only for adult birds with Pearson correlations. We tested the effects of stable (age, sex, tarsus length) or summer-developed (wing length) traits on tail feather quality by including age (yearling or adult), sex, and year as factors, and tarsus length and wing length as covariates, in two different models with feather growth rate and feather mass as the dependent variables. We calculated standardized effect sizes for predictor variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-McNeil1">McNeil et al. 1996</xref>). Second-order interactions between factors and continuous variables were included in the models, but only significant interactions are reported.We examined the relationships between tail feather traits and future breeding variables by using laying date and clutch size (5&ndash;8 eggs) as dependent variables; age, sex, and year as fixed factors; and growth rate and feather mass as continuous predictor variables. Laying date was entered as the deviation from the median laying date in the particular year. In the model with clutch size as dependent variable, laying date was a covariate.Wing length was significantly affected by age (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and sex (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), laying date was affected by age (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05), and body mass differed among years (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.026) and sexes (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), so they were standardized for these factors (mean &equals; 0, SD &equals; 1), and the standardized variables were used as independent variables in the tests. Moreover, we used year-, sex-, and age-standardized feather growth rate and feather mass when they were included as independent variables in the models. In the analyses of variables of the breeding season (laying date and clutch size), we used only those nests where no experimental manipulation had been performed. Analyses were performed in Statistica version 5.5 (StatSoft, Tulsa, Oklahoma, USA), and figures were prepared in SPSS version 19 (SPSS, Chicago, Illinois, USA).We found positive correlations between tail feather growth rate, length, vane area, and mass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-t01">Table 1</xref>). We decided to use only feather growth rate and mass in further analyses, because feather length and vane area were strongly positively correlated with feather mass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-t01">Table 1</xref>).Correlation matrix of various tail feather traits of Collared Flycatchers (&ast;&ast;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; &ast;&ast;&ast;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).We analyzed the repeatability of feather traits of adult Collared Flycatchers between consecutive years. According to our results, tail feather mass was correlated strongly between years (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.79, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 32; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-f01">Figure 1</xref>). However, feather growth rate showed no repeatability between years (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.33, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.23, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15). Regarding wing feathers, we also found a high repeatability of wing length between years (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.79, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 69).Repeatability of tail feather mass of adult Collared Flycatchers between consecutive years. The dashed line indicates a reference 1:1 line.The tail feathers of male and adult Collared Flycatchers were heavier and grew faster than those of females and juveniles, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-t02">Table 2</xref>). We also investigated whether growth rate and mass of tail feathers varied significantly within the adult age category, but we found no significant variation in these variables between 2 and 5 yr of age (growth rate: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,118</sub> &equals; 0.95, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.42; mass: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,163</sub> &equals; 0.61, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.61). There was also a difference in wing length between the sexes and age classes: Males and adults had longer wings (sex: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,375</sub> &equals; 119.09, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; age: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,375</sub> &equals; 83.88, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, there was no difference in tarsus length between the sexes and age classes (sex: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,377</sub> &equals; 0.04, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.83; age: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,377</sub> &equals; 1.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.32). Our results showed that birds with longer wings and with smaller body size produced tail feathers that grew faster (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-t02">Table 2</xref>). We also found a positive correlation between wing length and the mass of winter-grown tail feathers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-t02">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Tail feather quality of Collared Flycatchers in relation to sex, age, year, and morphological traits. Wing length was standardized for age and sex (mean &equals; 0, SD &equals; 1).Relationship between wing length and tail feather mass of Collared Flycatchers. Wing length was standardized for age and sex, and tail feather mass was standardized for sex, age, and year (mean &equals; 0, SD &equals; 1).We found that female Collared Flycatchers that had grown heavier tail feathers during winter laid larger clutches during the subsequent breeding season (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,48</sub> &equals; 3.95, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05, standardized effect size &equals; 0.28; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-f03">Figure 3</xref>). When we included spring female body mass and tarsus length as covariates in the model, the effect of tail feather mass on future clutch size remained significant (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,43</sub> &equals; 5.20, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03, standardized effect size &equals; 0.33; mass: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,43</sub> &equals; 0.23, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.63; tarsus: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,43</sub> &equals; 1.97, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.17). However, feather growth rate showed no association with the clutch size of females (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,47</sub> &equals; 0.96, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.33). According to our results, laying date was not related to either tail feather trait (feather growth rate: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,168</sub> &equals; 0.10, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.75; feather mass: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,168</sub> &equals; 0.34, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.56).Relationship between tail feather mass and clutch size of female Collared Flycatchers. Tail feather mass and clutch size were standardized for year and age (mean &equals; 0, SD &equals; 1).The positive correlations we found between tail feather growth rate, length, vane area, and mass suggest that these traits are similarly affected by the quality of the individual or the molting environment. Likewise, in the Eurasian Blackcap (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia atricapilla</named-content></italic>) and the Gray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>), it has been demonstrated that individuals with a faster feather growth rate produced longer feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Waite1">Waite 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera1">de la Hera et al. 2009</xref>). By contrast, no significant correlation was found between feather growth rate and tail length in Styan's Grasshopper Warbler (<italic>Locustella pleskei</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. 2001</xref>) or the Siberian Jay (<italic>P. infaustus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Gienapp1">Gienapp and Meril&auml; 2010</xref>).Adult Collared Flycatchers produced similar feathers in two consecutive winter molts, as shown by the highly repeatable mass of their rectrices. However, feather growth rate showed no repeatability between years. In accordance with our results, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera1">de la Hera et al. (2009)</xref> also found high repeatability in the length and mass of Eurasian Blackcap tail feathers, and no significant repeatability in feather growth rate between molts. By contrast, in a study of Styan's Grasshopper Warbler, feather growth rate showed a significant positive correlation between years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. 2001</xref>). In the European Pied Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">F. hypoleuca</named-content></italic>), feather mass also showed high repeatability and heritability, which suggests that genetic variation accounts for a considerable proportion of phenotypic variation of this feather trait (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera2">de la Hera et al. 2013</xref>). This result implies that the mass of tail feathers depends more on individual genetic factors or early environmental effects than on the environmental quality of the molting habitat. By contrast, feather growth rate seems to be more affected by environmental factors at the time of feather production.Our results showed that male Collared Flycatchers possessed heavier tail feathers than females. Similarly, a study of Northern Cardinals (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cardinalis cardinalis</named-content></italic>) found that males grew longer rectrices than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb3">Grubb et al. 1991</xref>). Collared Flycatchers are sexually dimorphic in their coloration (Svensson 2002). Although wing and tail feathers of males were longer than those of females, tarsus length, which is related to skeletal body size, did not differ between the sexes. There could be a selective pressure for males to have longer, larger, and heavier feathers. Better feathers could help males increase flight performance in terms of speed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Savile1">Savile 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Balmford1">Balmford et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marchetti1">Marchetti et al. 1995</xref>), which could be important for earlier spring arrival at the breeding grounds and, thus, the occupation of better-quality nesting areas. Indeed, male Collared Flycatchers generally arrive earlier on the breeding sites than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Mitrus1">Mitrus 2004</xref>, R. Hargitai et al. personal observation). Furthermore, better flight ability could also be important in male&ndash;male competition for breeding sites and in escape from predator attacks because of their conspicuous plumage and courtship behavior.We found that male Collared Flycatchers had a faster rate of tail feather growth than females (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hargitai1">Hargitai et al. 2012</xref>). It is possible that sex-related physiological, metabolic, or endocrine differences caused the faster feather growth rate of male birds, and not their relatively better body condition. Alternatively, males may occupy better-quality territories because of their dominance over females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Piper1">Piper 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra1">Marra 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Catry1">Catry et al. 2004</xref>) and, consequently, develop their feathers faster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Gienapp1">Gienapp and Meril&auml; 2010</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Saino1">Saino et al. 2012</xref>). In support of this hypothesis, a study of Downy Woodpeckers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides pubescens</named-content></italic>) showed that females grew their feathers slower in woods without food supplementation; however, in food-supplemented sites, feather growth rate did not differ between the sexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb1">Grubb 1989</xref>). These results suggest that the faster feather growth rate of males may indicate their better nutritional status, probably due to their social dominance. Indeed, in a study of Swedish Collared Flycatchers, it has been suggested that males winter in less arid habitats than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hjernquist1">Hjernquist et al. 2009</xref>).We found that the tail feathers of juvenile birds were lighter and grew slower than those of adult birds (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hargitai1">Hargitai et al. 2012</xref>); however, there was no difference in feather quality among 2- to 5-yr-old birds. Wing length also differed between juvenile and adult Collared Flycatchers: Juveniles had shorter wings. Juvenile birds may winter in less suitable areas with poorer availability and quality of food; thus, the quality of their tail feathers may be lower. Supporting this hypothesis, it has been observed in some passerines that older males forced most juveniles into habitats of poorer quality during winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra3">Marra and Holberton 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Catry1">Catry et al. 2004</xref>). Alternatively, juveniles may be less experienced foragers or otherwise lower-quality individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Cam1">Cam and Monnat 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hegyi2">Hegyi et al. 2006</xref>), which may not allow them to develop high-quality feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Grubb3">Grubb et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Gienapp1">Gienapp and Meril&auml; 2010</xref>).We also analyzed whether summer-developed and stable morphological traits (wing and tarsus lengths) of birds had an effect on their winter condition, as indicated by winter-grown tail feather quality. We found that birds with longer wings produced tail feathers that grew faster and were heavier. The mechanism underlying such a link could be the effect of either environmental or genetic factors. A longer wing may allow the bird to fly faster and cover a longer distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marchetti1">Marchetti et al. 1995</xref>), seeking an optimal winter habitat with better food availability. Moreover, a bird with longer wings may have better foraging ability due to higher speed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Savile1">Savile 1957</xref>), and therefore it may molt faster and grow heavier tail feathers. It is also possible that both wing and tail feather quality reflect the same genetically determined individual quality rather than that of the molting environment. This latter hypothesis is also supported by the strong within-individual repeatability of tail feather mass and wing length between consecutive years. Alternatively, length of wing and mass of tail feathers may be genetically positively linked and may have evolved under natural selection in order to achieve an aerodynamically optimal body shape for flight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Thomas1">Thomas 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 1995</xref>). Nevertheless, this hypothesis does not exclude the possibility that individuals capable of producing both longer wing and heavier tail feathers have generally better quality, because it requires more resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Murphy1">Murphy and King 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Lindstrom1">Lindstr&ouml;m et al. 1993</xref>). This supposition is also supported by the observation that adult birds, which probably have higher intrinsic quality than juveniles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Cam1">Cam and Monnat 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hegyi2">Hegyi et al. 2006</xref>), had both longer wing and heavier tail feathers than juveniles.We also found that smaller Collared Flycatchers grew their tail feathers faster during the winter molt. A smaller bird may perform better in foraging because of its better flight maneuverability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Andersson1">Andersson and Norberg 1981</xref>), which is especially important in species such as Collared Flycatchers, which capture flying insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Lohrl1">L&ouml;hrl 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Torok1">T&ouml;r&ouml;k 1986</xref>).Birds spending the winter in a poor habitat could lose some of their body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>), which could have long-term consequences, leading to delayed departure dates in the spring and later arrival at the breeding area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Norris1">Norris et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Saino2">Saino et al. 2004</xref>). In addition, birds that produce better-quality feathers during the winter molt may have better flight performance and, thus, may arrive earlier at the breeding site and show higher reproductive success. In concert with this hypothesis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marzal1">Marzal et al. (2013)</xref> found that birds that had higher tail feather growth rates, reflecting better nutritional condition during the winter molt, arrived earlier and acquired a mate faster in the subsequent breeding season. However, in contrast to our expectations, we detected no relationship between tail feather characteristics of Collared Flycatchers and their laying date in the breeding season following feather molt, although we must note that we did not record the arrival time of birds. Similarly, no relationships have been observed between feather mass and spring arrival time and laying date in the Pied Flycatcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-delaHera2">de la Hera et al. 2013</xref>), which suggests that in flycatchers, winter condition does not predict the laying date of individuals.We found that the tail feather growth rate of Collared Flycatchers showed no relationship with future breeding performance. Similarly, in Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>) and Siberian Jays, feather growth rate showed no association with the reproductive performance of females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Gienapp1">Gienapp and Meril&auml; 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Saino1">Saino et al. 2012</xref>). In Styan's Grasshopper Warblers, females with wider tail feather growth bars tended to achieve higher reproductive success, probably as a result of breeding earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Takaki1">Takaki et al. 2001</xref>). Likewise, in Common House Martins (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Delichon urbica</named-content></italic>), birds with a higher tail feather growth rate started breeding earlier and, consequently, laid larger clutches and produced more fledglings, but no significant relationship between tail feather growth rate and the number of fledglings produced was detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Marzal1">Marzal et al. 2013</xref>). These results are in agreement with our findings in suggesting that winter-developed feather growth rate does not show a direct relationship with future reproductive performance, although in some species it may have an indirect effect on reproductive success by influencing the laying date of birds.Most studies have tested the relationship between feather growth rate and reproductive success, whereas studies on tail feather mass or length are lacking. Our results indicate that female Collared Flycatchers that had grown heavier tail feathers during winter laid larger clutches during the subsequent breeding season, although we must note that the association was barely significant. A possible explanation for such a link could be that heavier feathers may help females forage more efficiently during the egg-laying period and, thus, produce larger clutches. Alternatively, these birds may be generally higher-quality individuals, which can both develop high-quality feathers during winter molt and lay larger clutches during spring. Accordingly, tail feather mass could be a reliable indicator of the quality of female Collared Flycatchers.In summary, our results suggest that tail feather mass of Collared Flycatchers is highly repeatable, correlated with wing length, and related to future clutch size in females, thus potentially reflecting intrinsic individual quality. By contrast, feather growth rate could rather indicate the environmental circumstances during molt. The winter condition of birds seemed to be affected by several variables, including age, sex, year, wing length, and body size. However, we found no indication that body condition at their wintering sites in Africa has significant consequences on the laying date of Collared Flycatchers. Further research based on the analysis of trace elements or stable isotopes in feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Prochazka1">Proch&aacute;zka et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Hjernquist1">Hjernquist et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-257-Szep1">Sz&eacute;p et al. 2009</xref>) could be applied to outline groups of individuals that molted in the same areas during winter.We are grateful to Gy. Bl&aacute;zi, R. F&odblac;z&odblac;, L. Z. Garamszegi, D. Kiss, G. Mark&oacute;, and several students for assistance during fieldwork. We thank two anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments. This study was supported by the Hungarian Scientific Research Fund (OTKA, grants no. 68295, 75618, 100304, and 101611), the E&ouml;tv&ouml;s Lor&aacute;nd University, the Erd&odblac;k a K&ouml;zj&oacute;&eacute;rt Alap&iacute;tv&aacute;ny, the Pilis Park Forestry, and the Bolyai J&aacute;nos Research Fellowship to R.H. The Hungarian Ministry of Environment and Water provided permissions for this study (KTVF 30871-1/2008 and KTVF 43355-1/2008). Scion Image software is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scion-image.software.informer.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://scion-image.software.informer.com/</ext-link>.