The impact of radio-tags on Ruby-throated Hummingbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>)Image processing with ImageJEffect of radio tranmitters on return rates of Swainson's WarblersMeta-analysis of transmitter effects on avian behaviour and ecologyCaptivity effects on wide-ranging carnivoresWildlife telemetryPreening and associated comfort behavior in birdsConsequences of antenna design in telemetry studies of small passerinesHur kan vikt och vingl&auml;ngd anv&auml;ndas f&ouml;r att uppskatta m&auml;ngden lagrat fett hos flyttande f&aring;glar? en metodstudie hos h&ouml;stflyttande bl&aring;hakar <italic>Luscinia s. svecica</italic>Estimated effects of age and sex on the fat-free body mass of autumn migrating BluethroatsRadio-telemetry increases free-living energy costs in the endangered Takahe <italic>Porphyrio mantelli</italic>Telemetric observations of a robin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>)The North American Bird Banding Manual &lsqb;electronic version&rsqb;. Version 1.0Radiotelemetry studies: Are we radio-handicapping Northern Bobwhites?Tropical deforestation alters hummingbird movement patternsSpace use of bumblebees (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bombus</named-content></italic> spp.) revealed by radio-trackingThe diurnal migration of passerines along an Appalachian ridgeWinter and migratory weight and fat field study on some North American buntingsEffects of radiotransmitters on body mass, feed consumption, and energy expenditure of Northern BobwhitesA simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedureThe effects of radio weight and harnesses on time budgets and movements of Acorn WoodpeckersA Lego system for conditional inferenceImplementing a class of permutation tests: The coin packageAtmospheric structure and avian migrationRadiotelemetry of the respiration of a flying duckDetrimental impacts of radiotransmitters on juvenile Louisiana WaterthrushesA new transmitter for small animals and enhanced methods of home-range analysisA test for effects of radio-tagging on survival and movements of small birdsWind tunnel experiments to assess the effect of back-mounted radio transmitters on bird body dragDo not log-transform count dataEffects of radio tags on captive Northern Bobwhite (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colinus virginianus</named-content></italic>) body composition and survivalSeasonal differences in immunological condition of three species of thrushesLong-distance pollen flow assessment through evaluation of pollinator foraging range suggests transgene escape distancesThe effect of an external transmitter on the drag coefficient of a bird's body, and hence on migration range, and energy reserves after migrationEffects of harness transmitters on behavior and reproduction of wild MallardsEffects of radio transmitters on migrating Wood ThrushesA radio transmitter attachment for small passerine birdsThe birds of North and Middle AmericaWildlife radio telemetryFactors influencing the movement biology of migrant songbirds confronted with an ecological barrierAdditional observations on winter Bald Eagle populations: Including remarks on biotelemetry techniques and immature plumagesWing morphology and flight behavior of some North American hummingbird speciesEvaluation of three minature radio transmitter attachment methods for small passerinesFactors influencing survival of radiotagged and banded Northern Bobwhites in GeorgiaRadio-transmitters do not affect seasonal mass change or annual survival of wintering Bicknell's ThrushesRuby-throated Hummingbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>)Simple rules guide dragonfly migrationLarge-range movements of Neotropical orchid bees observed via radio telemetryFall migration of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds in the northeastern United StatesAge-related differences in the stopover of fall landbird migrants on the coast of AlabamaRadiotelemetry has advanced the field of wildlife biology, especially with the miniaturization of radio-tags. However, the major limitation when radio-tagging birds is the size of the animal to which a radio-tag can be attached. We tested how miniature radio-tags affected flight performance and behavior of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>), possibly the smallest bird species that has been fitted with radio-tags. Using eyelash adhesive, we fitted hatch-year individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 20 males, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15 females) with faux radio-tags of 3 sizes that varied in mass and antenna length (220 mg, 12.7 cm; 240 mg, 12.7 cm; and 220 mg, 6.35 cm), then filmed the birds in a field aviary to quantify activity budgets. We also estimated flight range using flight simulation models. When the 3 radio-tag packages were pooled for analysis, the presence of a radio-tag significantly decreased both flight time (&sim;8&percnt;) and modeled flight range (&sim;23&percnt;) in comparison to control birds. However, a multiple-comparison analysis between the different packages revealed that there was a significant difference in flight time when the larger radio-tag package (240 mg) was attached, and no significant difference in flight time when the lighter radio-tag packages (220 mg) were attached. Our results are similar to those of other studies that analyzed the flight time or flight range of birds wearing radio-tags. Therefore, currently available lightweight radio-tags (&le;220 mg) may be a new option to aid in the study of hummingbird biology. Future study should focus on the additional drag created by the radio-tag and the effects of the lightest radio-tag packages on free-ranging birds. These studies would provide additional information to determine the feasibility of the use of radio-tags to study hummingbird biology.La radio telemetr&iacute;a ha permitido lograr avances en el campo de la biolog&iacute;a de fauna silvestre, especialmente con el desarrollo de tama&ntilde;os en miniatura de radio etiquetas. Sin embargo, la mayor limitaci&oacute;n que se enfrenta al marcar aves con radio etiquetas es el tama&ntilde;o del animal al cual puede adjuntarse una radio etiqueta. Evaluamos como las radio etiquetas en miniatura afectaron el desempe&ntilde;o del vuelo y el comportamiento de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>, posiblemente la especie m&aacute;s peque&ntilde;a de ave a la que se le ha colocado una radio etiquetas. Usando pegamento de pesta&ntilde;as, le colocamos a individuos eclosionados en el a&ntilde;o (n &equals; 20 machos y 15 hembras) radio etiquetas falsas de tres tama&ntilde;os que variaron en peso y largo de la antena (220 mg/12.7 cm, 240 mg/12.7 cm, y 220 mg/6.35 cm), y luego filmamos las aves en un aviario de campo para cuantificar los presupuestos de actividad. Tambi&eacute;n estimamos el rango de vuelo usando modelos de simulaci&oacute;n de vuelo. Cuando los tres paquetes de radio etiquetas fueron agrupados para el an&aacute;lisis, la presencia de una radio etiqueta disminuy&oacute; significativamente el tiempo de vuelo (&sim;8&percnt;) y el rango de vuelo modelado (&sim;23&percnt;) comparado con las aves control. Sin embargo, un an&aacute;lisis de comparaci&oacute;n m&uacute;ltiple entre los diferentes paquetes revel&oacute; que hubo una diferencia significativa en el tiempo de vuelo con el paquete de radio etiqueta m&aacute;s grande (240 mg) y no hubo una diferencia significativa en el tiempo de vuelo con los paquetes de radio etiquetas m&aacute;s livianos (220 mg). Nuestros resultados son similares a los de otros estudios que analizaron el tiempo de vuelo o el rango de vuelo de aves cargando radio etiquetas. Por tal motivo, las etiquetas de vuelo disponibles actualmente de bajo peso (&le;220 mg) pueden ser una nueva opci&oacute;n para ayudar en el estudio de la biolog&iacute;a de los colibr&iacute;es. Los estudios futuros deber&iacute;an enfocarse sobre la resistencia adicional que generan las radio etiquetas y los efectos de los paquetes de radio etiquetas m&aacute;s livianos en las aves en libertad. Estos estudios brindar&iacute;an informaci&oacute;n adicional para determinar la factibilidad de usar radio etiquetas para estudiar la biolog&iacute;a de los colibr&iacute;es.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>, comportamiento, migraci&oacute;n, radio etiquetado, radio telemetr&iacute;a, radio transmisores, simulaciones de vueloRadiotelemetry has advanced our understanding of wildlife biology in lockstep with advances in technology. Radiotelemetry was first used to study birds in the early 1960s (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Lord1">Lord et al. 1962</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Southern1">Southern 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Graber1">Graber and Wunderle 1966</xref>) and is now widely used to remotely collect movement data of free-ranging birds. Advances in technology have allowed miniaturization of radio-tags, which has enabled researchers to radio-tag smaller and smaller animals, including hummingbirds (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>) and arthropods (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Wikelski1">Wikelski et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Wikelski2">2010</xref>). The usual limitation in the use of radio-tags in avian biology is the weight of the radio-tag in relation to total body mass, which is recommended to be less than 3&ndash;5&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Cochran1">Cochran 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Gustafson1">Gustafson et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Fair1">Fair et al. 2010</xref>). The added weight of a radio-tag may decrease the probability of nesting and increase energetic expenditure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Barron1">Barron et al. 2010</xref>), yet field studies have found that tags up to 5&percnt; of the bird's total body weight do not meaningfully affect survival or movements of small (&lt;20 g) birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>).Some research on passerines has shown that radio-tags negatively affect survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Dougill1">Dougill et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Mattsson1">Mattsson et al. 2006</xref>), whereas other studies on large, mostly flightless birds have suggested negative impacts based on increased energy expenditure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Osborne1">Osborne et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Godfrey1">Godfrey et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Guthery1">Guthery and Lusk 2004</xref>). However, most studies that investigated direct impacts of radio-tags on survival rates have found negligible effects, if any (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Powell1">Powell et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hernandez1">Hern&aacute;ndez et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Terhune1">Terhune et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Townsend1">Townsend et al. 2012</xref>). The detrimental effects of radio-tags described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Dougill1">Dougill et al. (2000)</xref> were due to tag design, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Mattsson1">Mattsson et al. (2006)</xref> found decreased survival when outfitting nestlings with radio-tags. Long-term survival of radio-tagged birds does not seem to be impeded by tags if the tags are well-designed and are attached after fledging. Additionally, temporary radio-tags, which eventually fall off, would likely affect survivorship the least (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Raim1">Raim 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Sykes1">Sykes et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer1">Naef-Daenzer 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Smolinsky1">Smolinsky et al. 2013</xref>).Even if there is no increased likelihood of mortality or reduced reproductive success while wearing a radio-tag, other influences might handicap organisms during particular times of their annual cycle. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Barron1">Barron et al.'s (2010)</xref> meta-analysis on the effects of radiotelemetry found no significant effect on flight ability, a radio-tag externally mounted to the back of a bird will necessarily increase body drag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Obrecht1">Obrecht et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al. 2012</xref>). The main variable in telemetry effect studies is the ratio of equipment weight to body, but the additional drag created by the radio-tag arguably has a larger impact on flying animals than the increase in weight. An increase in body drag has been estimated (all things being equal) to reduce long-distance flight ranges, such as during migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Obrecht1">Obrecht et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Powell1">Powell et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al. 2012</xref>). Additionally, the extra weight of a radio-tag may exacerbate energy expenditure during flight, an especially difficult problem for migrating birds that are already carrying increased fat loads. Nonetheless, most investigators make no attempt to determine any impacts of the device before implementing a radio-tracking study.The impact of radio-tags on flight performance, especially for drag, is usually not tested prior to application on free-flying birds. If flight performance is affected by the weight of a radio-tag, we would expect birds with the heaviest radio-tags to experience the largest effect. Drag, however, varies with transmitter and antenna size, not with mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al. 2012</xref>). Differing antenna lengths could have a disproportionate effect on the transmitter's center of gravity, imposing increased energetic costs per unit flight time on individuals outfitted with a longer antenna than on individuals outfitted with a shorter antenna. Individuals with the longer antenna will either compensate energetically for the increased flight costs or fly less.We analyzed the impact of radio-tags on the flight performance and behavior of the Ruby-throated Hummingbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Archilochus colubris</named-content></italic>), a long-distance migrant (likely both trans-Gulf and circum-Gulf) that travels between breeding and wintering destinations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Weidensaul1">Weidensaul et al. 2013</xref>). To our knowledge, it is the smallest bird species that has been outfitted with radio-tags. We used a pairwise study design on individuals in a controlled setting to examine 3 different radio-tag packages that varied in weight and antenna length during fall migration, a time when individuals are accumulating additional mass via fat stores in order to fuel migratory flights. Our two main objectives a priori were to (1) quantify the flight time of birds with and without a radio-tag and (2) estimate the flight range of birds with and without a radio-tag from a mechanical model of weight and drag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick 2008</xref>). A secondary objective, a posteriori, was to determine whether preening behavior differed between treatments.We captured Ruby-throated Hummingbirds in nylon mist nets at the Bon Secour National Wildlife Refuge, Fort Morgan, Alabama (30&deg;10&prime;N, 88&deg;00&prime;W), between sunrise and noon from September 3 to September 16, 2010. Netting effort was both active, baiting 10 nets with artificial feeders, and passive. We banded the birds with a USGS aluminum band, aged and sexed them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pyle1">Pyle 1997</xref>), estimated fat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Helms1">Helms and Drury 1960</xref>), measured wing chord and mass, and took a wing photo to determine wingspan and wing area for flight range estimates.We randomly selected a subsample (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 35) of hatch-year birds (mass &equals; 3.80 &plusmn; 0.73 g for males, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 20; mass &equals; 3.76 &plusmn; 0.46 g for females, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15; all results are reported as means &plusmn; SD). We individually placed birds selected for experimentation into a field aviary (2.43 &times; 1.31 &times; 1.94 m) with a perch and a feeder without a perch. We used a pairwise study design in which all individuals received, in random order, the control treatment (no radio-tag) and 1 of 3 experimental treatments (with faux radio-tag; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-f01">Figure 1</xref>). In each experimental treatment, the faux radio-tag varied by antenna length and/or mass. The first experimental group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 15) received a heavy radio-tag (240 mg; total body mass: females, 6.00&percnt;; males, 6.32&percnt;) with a long antenna (length &equals; 12.7 cm, diameter &equals; 0.229 mm). The second experimental group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 10) received a lightweight radio-tag (220 mg; total body mass: females, 5.50&percnt;; males, 5.79&percnt;) with a long antenna (length &equals; 12.7 cm, diameter &equals; 0.152 mm). The third experimental group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 10) received a lightweight radio-tag (220 mg; total body mass: females, 5.50&percnt;; males, 5.79&percnt;) with a short antenna (length &equals; 6.35 cm, diameter &equals; 0.152 mm). Radio-tag design and 2 faux transmitters were provided courtesy of JDJC Corp. (Fisher, Illinois, USA).Ruby-throated Hummingbird with a faux radio-tag attached. Photo credit: T. J. ZenzalWe attached radio-tags using a modified version of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Raim1">Raim's (1978)</xref> method. Radio-tags were first sewn to a piece of cloth the size of the radio-tag, and then a second piece of cloth similar in size to the one sewn to the radio-tag was glued to the back of the bird using Revlon brand &ldquo;Fantasy Lengths&rdquo; eyelash adhesive. The cloth sewn to the radio-tag was glued to the cloth on the bird (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Cloth, thread, and glue were not included in the radio-tag weight. We removed radio-tags by clipping feathers under the cloth. Treatment order was randomized between individuals to eliminate any effect of order on subsequent analysis. Each individual tested only 1 radio-tag. After being prepared for the appropriate treatment (with or without radio-tag), individuals were placed in the aviary, allowed to acclimate for 10 min before the treatment was recorded, and then videotaped (Panasonic PV-GS65) at 1/4,000 frames s<sup>&minus;1</sup> for 7 min to score behaviors and time spent in various activities. We then prepped the same individual for the next treatment (attachment or removal of radio-tag), allowed another 10 min for acclimation, and then videotaped for another 7 min. After a bird completed both treatments, we released it without a radio-tag.Flight time was quantified from the total 14 min (7 min for control treatment and 7 min for experimental treatment) of video recording. We defined &ldquo;flight&rdquo; as any period during which an individual was not perched; we did not distinguish hovering flight (including feeding) from forward flight. Body condition was determined for two reasons: (1) Birds were randomly selected during migration and differed in the amount of fat carried, and (2) this species exhibits reverse sexual size-dimorphism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Weidensaul1">Weidensaul et al. 2013</xref>). We calculated body condition (fat) based on mass and wing length of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds captured on the Bon Secour National Wildlife Refuge, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Ellegren1">Ellegren (1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Ellegren2">1992</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Owen1">Owen and Moore (2006)</xref>. For both sexes, we determined fat-free mass by regressing body mass on fat score for individuals in the same wing chord class (1-mm increments). The intercept of the regression provided an approximation of fat-free mass for a sex-specific wing chord class. After performing regressions on all wing chord classes of individuals included in the study, we executed a second linear regression by regressing the intercepts on each related wing chord class for each sex. The resulting equation from the second regression allowed an estimation of size-specific fat-free masses for each bird.Restricted maximum likelihood (REML) models were used to assess the influence of radio-tags on flight time data using JMP statistical software version 10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2013</xref>). We performed a preliminary analysis on a subset of individuals balanced by experimental order (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 14 for each group) to determine whether the order in which treatments were applied had an effect on flight time. Flight time (square root transformed) was the response variable in a repeated-measures mixed model with radio-tag type, experimental order, and presence&ndash;absence of radio-tag as fixed factors and individual as a random nested blocking factor. We removed experimental order from subsequent analysis (see below). We then analyzed flight time data using a repeated-measures mixed model with radio-tag type, sex, body condition (described above), and presence&ndash;absence of radio-tag as fixed factors and individual as a random nested blocking factor. To determine the impact of each radio-tag type, we reran the analysis for the 3 radio-tags separately and interpreted <italic>P</italic> values using the Holm-Bonferroni adjustment method for multiple comparisons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Holm1">Holm 1979</xref>). Body condition did not meet the assumptions of normality (Shapiro-Wilk test, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02), even after attempting all standard transformations. Therefore, we ran each analysis with and without body condition included as a covariate. To further explore the relationship between body condition and activity budget, we used a Spearman's rank correlation between flight time and body condition.We quantified the number of preening occurrences from the video analysis of each bird. &ldquo;Preening&rdquo; is defined as each time an individual's bill made contact with its feathers. We analyzed preening occurrences using a generalized linear mixed-effects model fit by maximum likelihood with a quasi-Poisson distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-OHara1">O'Hara and Kotze 2010</xref>) in the R statistical language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2013</xref>), package &ldquo;MASS&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Venables1">Venables and Ripley 2002</xref>). The fixed factors of this model included radio-tag type, experimental order, body condition, and presence&ndash;absence of radio-tag, with individual as a random nested blocking factor. We excluded sex in this model because we did not believe there was any biological significance of sex on preening. We did, however, include experimental order, because observations suggested that birds that received the experimental treatment first may have preened more after the back feathers were clipped to remove the transmitter. To further explore interactions, we performed 2 additional tests in the R statistical language: First, a Nemenyi post hoc test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hollander1">Hollander and Wolfe 1999</xref>) from package &ldquo;coin&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hothorn1">Hothorn et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hothorn2">2008</xref>) was performed on significant effects of the model; second, a Spearman's rank correlation was used to determine a relationship between preening occurrences and flight time.We used Flight version 1.24 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick 2008</xref>) to estimate flight range of birds with and without radio-tags. Simulations were based on wing area, fat-free mass, and body condition of each bird (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 31) with and without a radio-tag. We obtained fat-free mass and body condition using methods described above. However, 3 of the individuals fell below the average fat-free mass and thus, according to the conditions of the model, were not able to migrate. Therefore, 2 females and 1 male were eliminated from analysis because of lean body condition; additionally, a third female was removed because she had no associated wing photograph. We quantified wingspan and wing area as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick (2008)</xref>, although we photographed rather than hand-traced wings. We modified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick's (2008)</xref> wing-area quantification by using ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Abramoff1">Abramoff et al. 2004</xref>) to determine the exact wing area (partial wing area plus rootbox) from a digital tracing of an individual's semi-span instead of using a grid to quantify area as performed with hand tracings. We assumed trans-Gulf flight in still-air conditions and an altitude of 500 m (air density of 1.17 kg m<sup>&minus;3</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger and Moore 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Woodrey1">Woodrey and Moore 1997</xref>). When an individual was simulated with a radio-tag, a payload mass was determined for the appropriate radio-tag size (220 or 240 mg) with a drag factor of 1.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al. 2012</xref>). We determined differences between simulated flight ranges (square root transformed) for individuals with and without a radio-tag using a REML repeated-measures mixed model. Radio-tag type, sex, and presence&ndash;absence of radio-tag were set as fixed factors and individual as a random nested blocking factor. This statistical analysis was performed using JMP.We found mixed evidence of experimental order affecting flight time of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds, due to a significant interaction between experimental order and presence&ndash;absence of a radio-tag (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,55</sub> &equals; 21.12, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Individuals had decreased flight time during the second treatment, regardless of treatment order. There was, however, much individual variation, which clouds the interpretation of the results but illustrates that attachment of a radio-tag will not elicit the same response from every individual. Individuals that received the control treatment first had a decrease of 80.00 &plusmn; 167.59 s when the radio-tag was attached, whereas individuals with a radio-tag attached first had a decrease of 5.95 &plusmn; 148.26 s during the control treatment. A bird undergoing the control treatment second had feathers clipped, which possibly explains why there was decreased flight time during the control treatment. The decrease in the subsequent treatment is likely a result of preening and, possibly, of acclimation to captivity (see below). However, the main effect of experimental order did not affect flight time (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,55</sub> &equals; 0.32, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.58). On the basis of the main effect test, the large amount of interindividual variation, and the a priori effort to randomize treatment order, we concluded that experimental order did not meaningfully affect activity budgets and excluded it as a factor from the subsequent analysis.Flight time was &sim;8&percnt; less with a radio-tag attached (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 7.36, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 6.00, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02 with body condition as a factor). Flight time without a radio-tag (182.94 &plusmn; 121.72 s) was greater than when a radio-tag was attached (149.6 &plusmn; 104.39 s, averaged across all models). However, size of the radio-tag did not have a significant effect on flight time in either model (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,69</sub> &equals; 0.98, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.39 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,69</sub> &equals; 1.83, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.18 with body condition as a factor). Further analysis using multiple-comparison testing between radio-tag types using the Holm-Bonferroni adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Holm1">Holm 1979</xref>) revealed that the only radio-tag to have a significant decrease (&sim;11&percnt;) in flight time between the treatment and the control was the heavy tag (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,29</sub> &equals; 15.06, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,29</sub> &equals; 13.27, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004 with body condition as a factor; adjusted &alpha; &equals; 0.017), whereas flight time in both of the lightweight tag treatments did not differ from controls (long-antenna tag: &sim;8&percnt; decrease, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,19</sub> &equals; 1.76, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,19</sub> &equals; 2.32, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.18 with body condition as a factor; adjusted &alpha; &equals; 0.025; short-antenna tag: &sim;6.5&percnt; increase, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,19</sub> &equals; 0.05, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.83 without body condition as a factor; F<sub>1,19</sub> &equals; 0.06, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.82 with body condition as a factor). Mean flight time decreased predictably from the lightweight short-antenna tag, which had the longest flight time (210.70 &plusmn; 127.14 s); to the lightweight long-antenna tag (148.40 &plusmn; 74.93 s); to the heavyweight long-antenna tag, which had the shortest flight time (137.00 &plusmn; 107.92 s; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Although wing morphology of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds is sex-dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Stiles1">Stiles et al. 2005</xref>), neither model showed an effect of sex on flight activity (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 2.31, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals;1.24, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.28 with body condition as a factor) or an interaction between sex and the presence of a radio-tag (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 0.21, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.65 without body condition as a factor; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 1.49, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.24 with body condition as a factor). Finally, body condition did not affect flight time (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,69</sub> &equals; 1.35, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26), and a Spearman's rank correlation showed no relationship between flight time and body condition (with radio-tag: Spearman's rho &equals; &minus;0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.94, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35; without radio-tag: Spearman's rho &equals; &minus;0.18, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.30, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35).Mean flight time (s &plusmn; SD) of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds per 7-min treatment with radio-tags attached (240 mg: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15; 220 mg: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 10) and without radio-tags attached (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 35). Radio-tags are separated by mass (mg) and length of antenna (cm).As expected, initial analysis revealed that preening occurrences had a significant negative correlation with flight time (with radio-tag: Spearman's rho &equals; &minus;0.39, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35; without radio-tag: Spearman's rho &equals; &minus;0.38, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35), which is not surprising, given that preening and flying are mutually exclusive behaviors. Preening occurrences did not differ with presence or absence of a radio-tag (<italic>t</italic><sub>23</sub> &equals; 0.18, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.86, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35). However, experimental order had a significant effect on the number of preening occurrences (<italic>t</italic><sub>23</sub> &equals; 2.43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35). Birds that received the control treatment first (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 16) had a mean of 25.31 &plusmn; 42.53 preening occurrences, which increased to 37.63 &plusmn; 55.15 preening occurrences when the radio-tag was attached. Birds that first received the experimental treatment (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 19) increased preening occurrences from 27.84 &plusmn; 35.06 to 30.26 &plusmn; 40.71 after the radio-tag was removed. However, given the close means and the significant effect of preening on experimental order, a Nemenyi post hoc test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hollander1">Hollander and Wolfe 1999</xref>) was performed on the number of preening occurrences by order, which yielded a nonsignificant effect (<italic>Z</italic> &equals; 0.31, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.76, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35). Although the number of preening occurrences did not differ significantly while an individual had a radio-tag attached, the number of preening occurrences was greater when a radio-tag was attached (32.31 &plusmn; 35.38) than when no radio-tag was attached (28.00 &plusmn; 41.01), averaged across treatments. There was much individual variation between subjects, regardless of treatment. When a radio-tag was attached, preening occurrences ranged from 0 to 184 instances over 7 min; individuals without a radio-tag attached showed a similar range of 0 to 157 instances over the same time frame. This analysis further explains the significant effect on flight time of the interaction between presence&ndash;absence of a radio-tag and experimental order.Flight modeling provided an estimate of how a radio-tag affected flight range. The presence of a radio-tag significantly affected simulated flight ranges (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,62</sub> &equals; 135.26, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), reducing an individual's flight range by &sim;340 km, on average (without radio-tag: 1,512.26 &plusmn; 1,188.65 km; with radio-tag: 1,172.00 &plusmn; 916.86 km). There was no effect of sex on flight range (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,62</sub> &equals; 0.48, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49), nor was there an effect of radio-tag mass (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,62</sub> &equals; 1.08, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.36).Hummingbirds are challenging to study because their size and speed of movement make visual detection difficult. The ability to continually track and record the behavior of radio-tagged hummingbirds would measurably enhance our understanding of migratory movement, dispersal, resource use, home-range activity, and habitat use. For example, the first published application of a radio-tag on a hummingbird determined the movement patterns of Green Hermits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phaethornis guy</named-content></italic>) in Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>). To our knowledge, the Green Hermit is the smallest bird (5.8 &plusmn; 0.09 g; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>) that has been radio-tagged prior to the present study of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds. The miniaturization of transmitters has allowed others to track flying arthropods, much smaller than most hummingbirds, which has provided insight on questions that would be difficult to answer using other means (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Wikelski1">Wikelski et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Wikelski2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pasquet1">Pasquet et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hagen1">Hagen et al. 2011</xref>).Activity budgets of Ruby-throated Hummingbirds are influenced by the presence of a radio-tag, although only the heaviest radio-tag showed a significant decrease (&sim;11&percnt;) in flight time from the control treatment. The lightweight radio-tags had less influence on flight time, with the long-antenna tag decreasing flight time by &sim;8&percnt; and the short-antenna tag increasing flight time by &sim;6.5&percnt;. At 220 mg, or just more than 5&percnt; of the total body mass of a Ruby-throated Hummingbird, these radio-tags did not seem to pose a significant handicap on activity, which is similar to the results of other studies that used radio-tags at a comparable percent body weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>). However, it is difficult to extrapolate the small differences found in flight activity that might be an artifact of a 7-min experimental period in an aviary to actual migratory flight.Free-ranging animals may behave differently when in captivity (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Clubb1">Clubb and Mason 2003</xref>). The size of the aviary&mdash;or simply being placed in an aviary&mdash;may have limited the activity of the Ruby-throated Hummingbirds in our study once they determined there was no way out. Although time of day was not included as a factor in analysis, most birds were tested in the late morning or early afternoon, when they are typically inactive (T. J. Zenzal, Jr., personal observation) or migrating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hall1">Hall and Bell 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Willimont1">Willimont et al. 1988</xref>). The length of time allotted for birds to acclimate to the radio-tag may have been too short, affecting the outcome; most birds receiving any sort of marker (e.g., band, radio-tag) spend an unpredictable amount of time reacting to the tag (preening or attempting to remove the marker) before resuming normal behaviors.Preening increased in individuals that received the experimental treatment in contrast to the control treatment. Increases in comfort behavior (as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Delius1">Delius 1988</xref>; i.e. preening, wing flapping, head shaking) would necessarily increase the amount of time spent perching, while decreasing time spent in flight. Although some of the variation found during flight activity, particularly between the different experimental orders, is explained by preening that may have resulted from our attaching radio-tags directly to feathers or clipping back feathers to remove the radio-tags, we recommend caution when making interpretations from this analysis, given that handling of birds seemed to increase their likelihood of preening. Although we found no significant effect of a radio-tag on preening, other studies have shown that preening increased with the attachment of a transmitter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Sykes1">Sykes et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hooge1">Hooge 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pietz1">Pietz et al. 1993</xref>).The apparent effect of the radio-tag on activity may have been influenced by attachment method, given that the radio-tag was glued directly to back feathers instead of skin for easy removal after the experiment was complete. The most common adhesive attachment method requires feathers to be clipped in order to create a strong bond between the radio-tag backing and the skin of the bird or the feather shaft (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Raim1">Raim 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Sykes1">Sykes et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer1">Naef-Daenzer 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Hadley1">Hadley and Betts 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Smolinsky1">Smolinsky et al. 2013</xref>). The effects on small birds of this attachment method are negligible in comparison to other attachment methods that have been tested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Sykes1">Sykes et al. 1990</xref>). Furthermore, field studies showed no decrease in survivorship when this attachment method was used, compared with non-radio-tagged birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-NaefDaenzer2">Naef-Daenzer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>).The percent body mass and size of radio-tags, but not the antenna length, appeared to affect the activity budget; however, much variation existed between and within treatments. Our findings are consistent with the influence of the device's drag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Barron1">Barron et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al. 2012</xref>) rather than the weight of the radio-tag, in terms of energetic expenditure. The lightweight radio-tag with the short antenna had the highest amount of flight time, likely due to decreased drag of the antenna. However, large individual variation across all the variables explored make it difficult to suggest any hard-and-fast rules for radio-tagging hummingbirds, besides selecting a radio-tag that has the smallest weight and drag available. A valuable follow-up study to the one described would determine, with the use of a wind tunnel, the amount of drag that different radio-tag designs have on free-flying hummingbirds, similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Pennycuick2">Pennycuick et al.'s (2012)</xref> study of external device drag on Rosy Starlings (<italic>Pastor roseus</italic>).Predicted flight range was affected by the presence of a radio-tag but did not vary with the size of the radio-tag or the sex of the individual. Individuals able to fly farther, by virtue of larger fat loads, experienced larger decreases in distance when radio-tagged than individuals with shorter flight ranges. Although flight simulations showed a decrease in flight ranges, most studies on survival and return rates of radio-tagged long-distance migrants have not shown an effect of radio-tags on survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Powell1">Powell et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Cardinal1">Cardinal 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Townsend1">Townsend et al. 2012</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Samuel1">Samuel and Fuller 1996</xref>). In two of these studies, a subsample of birds tagged were recaptured a year later (in one case, 2 yr later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Powell1">Powell et al. 1998</xref>) with radios still attached (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Powell1">Powell et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Townsend1">Townsend et al. 2012</xref>).Hummingbird behavior is potentially affected by the presence of a radio-tag, so caution should be exercised when selecting individuals to tag, which will depend on season, sex, and condition. For example, a radio-tag is likely to impede nest construction in female hummingbirds (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-518-Weidensaul1">Weidensaul et al. 2013</xref>). That said, observations of free-flying Ruby-throated Hummingbirds during stopover revealed that individuals with radio-tags behave similarly to marked individuals without radio-tags in stopover duration, foraging, competitive interactions, and seasonally appropriate departure directions (T. J. Zenzal, Jr., personal observation). One of these free-flying radio-tagged birds was detected, wearing its tag, at an artificial feeder in Corpus Christi, Texas, USA (&sim;950 km from Fort Morgan, Alabama, USA) two weeks after being tagged (USGS Bird Banding Laboratory, personal communication).Research funding was provided by the Department of Biological Sciences at the University of Southern Mississippi (USM) and by a grant from the National Science Foundation (NSF) to F.R.M. (IOS 844703). T.J.Z. was also supported by a fellowship from the NSF GK&ndash;12 program &ldquo;Molecules to Muscles&rdquo; (award no. 0947944 through USM). We would especially like to thank the Bon Secour National Wildlife Refuge and Fort Morgan Historic Site for allowing us to work on their properties. We thank the 2010 Fort Morgan Field crew for help with data collection, C. J. Pennycuick for insightful conversations during the formulation of the manuscript, C. Qualls and J. Schaefer for statistical advice, and J. Cochran for conversations about designing radio-tags for hummingbirds and supplying faux radio-tags. We thank the Migratory Bird Research Group at USM for their support. Finally, we thank Z. N&eacute;meth and anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on the manuscript. This study was approved by the USM Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee and by the U.S. Geological Survey Bird Banding Laboratory. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.