Heterothermic flexibility allows energetic savings in a small tropical swift: The Silver-rumped Spinetail (<italic>Rhaphidura leucopygialis</italic>)Energy saving in huddling penguinsEnvironmental correlates of Freckled Nightjar (<italic>Caprimulgus tristigma</italic>) activity in a seasonal, subtropical habitatTorpidity in the White-throated Swift, Anna Hummingbird, and Poor-willIntra-individual variation in body temperature and pectoral muscle size in nestling Alpine Swifts <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus melba</named-content></italic> in response to an episode of inclement weatherHeterothermy in caprimulgid birds: A review of inter- and intraspecific variation in free-ranging populationsOptimal foraging: The marginal value theoremSeasonal variation in thermal energetics of the Australian Owlet-Nightjar (<italic>Aegotheles cristatus</italic>)Torpor in Australian birdsA phylogenomic study of birds reveals their evolutionary historyEffects of light and prey availability on nocturnal, lunar and seasonal activity of tropical nightjarsAvian energeticsThe temporal organization of daily torpor and hibernation: Circadian and circannual rhythmsOn temperature regulation and metabolism in the swift, <italic>Micropus a. apus</italic> L., during fastingTorpor and metabolism in hummingbirdsOn optimal use of a patchy environmentAvian facultative hypothermic responses: A reviewHeterothermy in Afrotropical birds and mammals: A reviewPhenotypic plasticity in the scaling of avian basal metabolic rateThe energetics of Australian swifts, frogmouths, and nightjarsNocturnal hypothermia in the White-throated Needletail (<italic>Hirundapus caudacutus</italic>)nlme: Linear and Nonlinear Mixed Effects Models. R package version 3.1&ndash;120Temperature changes in Chimney Swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chaetura pelagica</named-content></italic>) at lowered environmental temperaturesPhylogenetic analysis of avian energetics: Passerines and nonpasserines do not differTorpor in dark times: Patterns of heterothermy are associated with the lunar cycle in a nocturnal birdThe constraints of digestive rate: An alternative model of diet selectionTemperature effects on food supply and chick mortality in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Facultative heterothermy, or torpor, has been demonstrated in different clades of the Apodidae, proposed as a mechanism to reduce energetic demand in response to different physiological cues. In a small tropical Southeast Asian swiftlet species, the Silver-rumped Spinetail (<italic>Rhaphidura leucopygialis</italic>), we measured the facultative heterothermic response in a pair of experiments. In the first experiment, the mean body temperature of birds immediately after capture was ~38.9&deg;C. Individuals exposed to consistent ambient temperatures of 28.0&deg;C reduced mean body temperatures over time, and these reductions were greater in individuals kept in the dark than in those that were exposed to light during the trial. The second experiment consisted of respirometry trials measuring rates of carbon dioxide production along with internal body temperature in relation to decreasing ambient temperatures. Two different responses to the respirometry trials emerged: Some individuals modulated body temperature in relation to changes in ambient temperature, and other individuals maintained body temperature (~31.6&deg;C) independent of ambient temperature. Our results suggest considerable flexibility among individual heterothermic responses in <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic>. Our results are in agreement with other studies on swifts, suggesting that these alternative modes for energy conservation are likely context-dependent and based upon individual body condition, life stage, and annual cycle.La heterotermia facultativa o torpor ha sido demostrada en diferentes clados de Apodidae y se ha propuesto que es un mecanismo para reducir la demanda energ&eacute;tica en respuesta a diferentes pistas fisiol&oacute;gicas. En una especie de peque&ntilde;o vencejo tropical del sudeste asi&aacute;tico, <italic>Rhaphidura leucopygialis,</italic> medimos la respuesta de heterotermia facultativa en un par de experimentos. En el primer experimento, la temperatura corporal media de las aves inmediatamente despu&eacute;s de su captura fue 38.89 &deg;C. Los individuos expuestos a temperaturas ambientales constantes de ~28 &deg;C redujeron su temperatura media corporal con el tiempo y estas reducciones fueron m&aacute;s pronunciadas en individuos que se mantuvieron en la oscuridad que en aquellos que estuvieron expuestos a luz durante el experimento. El segundo experimento consisti&oacute; en ensayos de respirometr&iacute;a para medir las tasas de producci&oacute;n de di&oacute;xido de carbono junto con la temperatura corporal interna en relaci&oacute;n con la disminuci&oacute;n en temperatura ambiental. Surgieron dos respuestas diferentes en los experimentos de respirometr&iacute;a: algunos individuos modularon la temperatura corporal en relaci&oacute;n con los cambios en temperatura ambiental mientras que otros individuos mantuvieron la temperatura corporal (~31.6 &deg;C) independiente de la temperatura ambiental. Nuestros resultados sugieren que hay una flexibilidad considerable entre individuos de <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> en sus respuestas heterot&eacute;rmicas. Nuestros resultados concuerdan con otros estudios en vencejos, lo que sugiere que estos modos alternativos para la conservaci&oacute;n de energ&iacute;a probablemente dependen del contexto, basado en la condici&oacute;n corporal individual, el estad&iacute;o en el ciclo vida y el ciclo anual.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> Apodidae, energ&iacute;a, fisiolog&iacute;a, heterotermia, homeotermia, ritmo circadiano, torporA fundamental aspect of survival for any vertebrate is the acquisition and management of energy reserves. Energy is the currency for metabolic processes, and, as a consequence, selection favors traits that optimize efficiency, such as altering foraging behavior in response to food scarcity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-MacArthur1">MacArthur and Pianka 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Charnov1">Charnov 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Stephens1">Stephens and Krebs 1986</xref>) or selecting food items with higher energetic content or digestibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Verlinden1">Verlinden and Wiley 1989</xref>). Aerial insectivores such as swifts and swallows are typically considered to have the most temporally varying food supply, with changes in air temperature of only a few degrees causing the food supply to transition from feast to famine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2013</xref>). Thus, at certain times it is paramount for these taxa to be able to obtain the maximum amount of energy possible in the shortest possible time and/or to create energetic reserves, allowing animals to engage in behaviors unrelated to food acquisition, such as mate selection, social behaviors, and reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab1">McNab 2002</xref>). In addition, if energetic requirements for maintenance can be reduced during periods of inactivity, energetic resources can be used more efficiently.The thermoregulatory strategy with the greatest energetic cost for small organisms exposed to low ambient temperatures (T<sub>a</sub>) is homeothermy, or maintaining a consistently elevated body temperature (T<sub>b</sub>). Much of the energetic demand at low ambient temperatures is due to increased heat loss to the environment, which can be reduced by changes in conductance through behavioral adaptations such as huddling, selection of favorable microclimates, or changes in posture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Ancel1">Ancel et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Ashdown1">Ashdown and McKechnie 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Smit1">Smit et al. 2011</xref>). Physiological changes such as heterothermy have been of interest to energetics research; however, little is known about the physiological and environmental cues that prompt the regulation of a lowered body temperature.A growing body of evidence suggests that many birds from a diverse group of unrelated families may not maintain constant body temperature set points as originally assumed, and may instead demonstrate heterothermic flexibility in response to increased energetic costs of thermoregulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McKechnie1">McKechnie and Lovegrove 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McKechnie2">McKechnie and Mzilikazi 2011</xref>, Brigham et. al. 2012). Despite heterothermy being a characteristic of most, if not all, Caprimulgiformes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Hackett1">Hackett et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Brigham1">Brigham et al. 2012</xref>), studies that have investigated the physiological and environmental cues that prompt heterothermy are not common. The reliability of these internal and external cues that prompt heterothermy is relevant to the energetic budgets of animals, as these cues prompt individuals to abandon homeothermy when the thermoregulatory costs exceed the benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Geiser1">Geiser et al. 2006</xref>). Use of thermoregulatory cues is context dependent, as the costs and benefits of homeothermy vary among species, populations, sex, and age. Variations in thermoregulatory patterns within these groups thus likely function to optimize homeothermic benefits while minimizing costs of homeothermy.The Silver-rumped Spinetail (<italic>Rhaphidura leucopygialis</italic>) is a small swift (~12 g) within the tribe Chaeturini that roosts in large tree hollows in the emergent canopy. With its small size (and thus high surface-to-volume ratio), high metabolic rate, and temporally variable food supply, this species is likely to utilize heterothermy to conserve energy. In this study, we carried out a series of experiments using solitary birds to document the thermoregulatory responses of <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> to different temperatures. First, we determined whether <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> showed a heterothermic response when exposed to an ambient temperature lower than body temperature, in both a light and a dark environment. Second, we measured the energetic demands of thermoregulation when exposed to different ambient temperatures using flow-through respirometry. Finally, we compared our results in an evolutionary context with data from other Apodidae species, and explored some of the patterns seen within this family.We captured birds at Tawau Hills Park, Sabah, Malaysia, from March 3 to April 22, 2013, approximately 30 min after sunrise (06:45 local time). Individuals were captured using a 9 m mist net strung across a small stream that the birds were visiting to drink. A total of 22 birds were captured on the morning of April 4, 2013, of which 12 birds were measured for body temperature immediately after flight, with individuals placed in either the &lsquo;light' group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 11) or the &lsquo;dark' group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 11). For the respirometry trials, 6 birds were captured on nonconsecutive days. Within 1 min of removal from the mist net, body temperate was measured using an OMEGA HH801 handheld thermometer (OMEGA Engineering, Stamford, Connecticut, USA) with an N-type thermocouple inserted 10 mm into the cloaca, with temperature recorded upon its stabilization after ~10&ndash;15 s. Birds were used for only 1 of the 2 experiments: either in the light vs. dark trial, or in the respirometry trials.For the first experiment, individuals were weighed and detained separately in lightweight cotton bird bags before the start of the experiment. Individuals were placed into 1 of 2 groups and treatments were run concurrently: (1) exposure to ~28&deg;C for 120 min in the presence of light, or (2) exposure to ~28&deg;C for 120 min in darkness. At the conclusion of the 120 min trial, cloacal temperature was measured, and morphological measurements (mass, wing chord, and head&ndash;bill length) were taken.To determine metabolic rates, we used an open-flow, pull-mode respirometry setup coupled with a climate-controlled chamber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Lighton1">Lighton 2008</xref>). Respirometry trials started 2&ndash;3 hr after capture, typically at ~09:00 each morning. Individuals were placed in the chamber and allowed to acclimate to conditions for 60 min before the start of the trial. All individuals had body temperatures below 34&deg;C when metabolic rate measurements began after acclimation. Measurement of metabolic rate started at an ambient temperature of 30&deg;C held for 120 min (including 60 min of acclimation before measurement), then ambient temperature was lowered 5&deg;C per hour until a final ambient temperature of 10&deg;C was reached. For drift correction, we took baseline measurements lasting 10 min every hour and at the completion of each trial. The initial trial exposed an individual to temperatures below 5&deg;C; however, it appeared that the bird's condition suffered and we chose not to expose future individuals to what appeared to be a minimum survivable temperature. This first individual was excluded from analyses.A 3 m copper coil constructed of 6.35 mm tubing was placed in-line upstream of the respiration chamber and inside the temperature controlled environment to equilibrate the temperature between the incurrent airstream and the metabolic chamber. Air was drawn from outside while using an initial moisture scrubber containing Drierite (W. A. Hammond Drierite, Xenia, Ohio, USA), reducing the relative humidity of the intake air to ~60&percnt; (determined by handheld hygrometer). Respired gas was analyzed using a Sable Systems FoxBox field carbon dioxide analyzer (Sable Systems International, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA) in a pull setup following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Lighton1">Lighton (2008)</xref>, in which samples were scrubbed of water vapor before CO<sub>2</sub> measurements. All connection tubing was 6.35 mm Bev-a-line IV (Thermoplastic Processes, Georgetown, Delaware, USA).We used a one-way analysis of variance in base R version 3.1.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>) to compare body temperatures before and after the trials and to compare temperatures between light and dark experimental groups. For comparison of T<sub>b</sub> (body temperature) and RMR with T<sub>a</sub> (ambient temperature), we used general linear models with T<sub>b</sub> and RMR as nested effects within individual ID in package &lsquo;nlme' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Pinheiro1">Pinheiro et al. 2015</xref>). Numerical values are presented as mean &plusmn; SD for <italic>n</italic> individuals and <italic>N</italic> samples.For the dark vs. light trials, initial internal body temperature immediately after capture averaged 38.89&deg;C. Birds in both groups reduced their body temperatures when exposed to ~28&deg;C for 120 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The reduction in mean body temperature was greater for the birds held in the dark (mean &equals; 30.83&deg;C, difference &equals; 8.06&deg;C) than for those exposed to light (mean &equals; 36.66&deg;C, difference &equals; 2.23&deg;C), and this difference in temperature reduction was significant (ANOVA, <italic>F</italic><sub>2,33</sub> &equals; 347.3, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Post-hoc pairwise comparisons (Tukey's HSD) showed that all groups were significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Histogram of body temperatures of Silver-rumped Spinetails after different experimental treatments. Cloacal temperatures were taken immediately after capture (within 60 s) and individuals were placed into either a (1) light, or (2) dark treatment group for 120 min at ~28&deg;C. Means for each group are represented by vertical dotted-dashed lines. The dark treatment group mean body temperature decreased by 8.06&deg;C, whereas the light treatment group mean temperature only decreased 2.23&deg;C from the initial &lsquo;active' body temperature mean of 38.89&deg;C. Both treatment effects (dark and light) were significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) when compared with the &lsquo;active' body temperature mean and each other (Tukey's HSD).For the respirometry trials, experimental temperatures were not above the predicted thermoneutral zone (30&ndash;35&deg;C) of similarly sized Apodidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso 1995</xref>), but individual responses fell into 1 of 2 groups. Due to the acclimation period, at the start of the respirometry trials all individuals had temperatures that were below the &lsquo;active' mean temperature at the time of capture of 38.9&deg;C. Individuals that maintained a mean body temperature of ~31.6 &plusmn; 1.0&deg;C during the trial independent of decreasing ambient temperature (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f02">Figure 2</xref>) displayed a negative relationship (RMR &equals; &minus;0.1938(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 8.5075, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,8</sub> &equals; 5.89, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) between ambient temperature (T<sub>a</sub>) and metabolic rate. In contrast, the individuals that exhibited a heterothermic response (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f02">Figure 2</xref>) maintained a consistent body temperature when ambient temperatures were above 20&deg;C and demonstrated a weak negative relationship (RMR &equals; &minus;0.2790(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 10.1588, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,3</sub> &equals; 2.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04) between ambient temperature and metabolic rate. However, when ambient temperatures dropped below 20&deg;C the relationship between T<sub>a</sub> and metabolic rate appeared to become positive (RMR &equals; 0.1003(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 2.7130, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,1</sub> &equals; 0.68, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.62), although the explanatory power of the model was nonsignificant.Resting metabolic rates (RMR) of Silver-rumped Spinetails relative to ambient temperature (T<sub>a</sub>). (<bold>A</bold>) Illustration of the increasing metabolic rate in several individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 3, solid symbols) in which RMR increased proportionally as T<sub>a</sub> decreased, compared with other individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2, hollow symbols) in which, at T<sub>a</sub> below ~19&deg;C, RMR decreased with decreasing T<sub>a</sub>. (<bold>B</bold>) Illustration of the relationship between T<sub>a</sub> and T<sub>b</sub> (body temperature), where the relationship between T<sub>a</sub> and T<sub>b</sub> suggests active thermoregulation at all experimental temperatures in some individuals (solid symbols), whereas in others the relationship suggests that T<sub>b</sub> decreases as T<sub>a</sub> falls below ~19&deg;C (hollow symbols), i.e. a positive correlation between T<sub>a</sub> and T<sub>b</sub> below ~19&deg;C. Each symbol is associated with data collected from an individual.The relationship between body temperature and ambient temperature for the homeothermic group was nonsignificant (RMR &equals; 0.0042(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 31.5078, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,8</sub> &equals; 0.39, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.70), suggesting active thermoregulation as there was little change in body temperature in relation to ambient temperature. A similar pattern suggesting active thermoregulation occurred in the heterothermic group at temperatures above 20&deg;C (RMR &equals; 0.0025(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 29.5369, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,3</sub> &equals; 0.05, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.96), although this changed below 20&deg;C (RMR &equals; 0.4878(T<sub>a</sub>) &plus; 20.8799, <italic>t</italic><sub>0.05,1</sub> &equals; 174.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004) to a relationship in which body temperature was positively correlated with ambient temperature. Thus, for some individuals within our study, thermoregulation below 20&deg;C was either no longer possible or energetically favorable and T<sub>b</sub> decreased in concert with T<sub>a</sub>.Our results demonstrate flexibility in the body temperature set point among individuals of <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> in response to different environmental conditions. In our first experiment, individuals exposed to either a light or a dark treatment at ~28&deg;C showed significant decreases in body temperature relative to initial temperatures measured after active flight. When exposed to ~28&deg;C, light-treatment birds regulated their body temperatures near 37&deg;C, whereas those held in dark conditions dropped their temperatures to ~31&deg;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f01">Figure 1</xref>). These results are similar to those from other studies within Apodidae. For example, White-throated Needletails (<italic>Hirundapus caudacutus</italic>) have a similar heterothermic range as had the birds in this study, with normothermic temperatures averaging 38&deg;C and a torpid temperature of 28&deg;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Pettigrew1">Pettigrew and Wilson 1985</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso (1995)</xref> also found that individual body temperatures in swiftlets (<italic>Collocalia</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aerodramus</named-content></italic> spp.) were variable, both within the thermoneutral zone (TNZ) as well as in response to descending ambient temperatures.In the second experiment, we found that the lowest normothermic metabolic rate of <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> was comparable to the basal metabolic rate (BMR) measured in other Apodidae (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-t01">Table 1</xref>). As our interests were heterothermic responses to low ambient temperatures (T<sub>a</sub>), we did not measure responses at the upper TNZ limit. The initial T<sub>a</sub> was ~30&deg;C, near the lower critical temperature of similarly sized swift species such as <italic>A. vanikorensis</italic> (30&ndash;34&deg;C) and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. esculenta</named-content></italic> (32&ndash;34&deg;C; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso 1995</xref>). The lowest recorded metabolic rate of <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> within the expected TNZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso 1995</xref>) was 2.31 mL O<sub>2</sub> hr<sup>&minus;1</sup> g<sup>&minus;1</sup>. This metabolic rate is 80&percnt; of the predicted BMR for all birds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f03">Figure 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Reynolds1">Reynolds and Lee 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McKechnie3">McKechnie et al. 2006</xref>), 116&percnt; greater than that predicted for Caprimulgiformes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Doucette1">Doucette and Geiser 2008</xref>), and 53&percnt; of that predicted for Trochilidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Kruger1">Kr&uuml;ger et al. 1982</xref>). The similarity between the BMR of Apodiformes (BMR &equals; 3.84B<sub>m</sub><sup>&minus;0.264</sup>) and Caprimulgiformes (BMR &equals; 6.38B<sub>m</sub><sup>&minus;0.431</sup>) is unexpected; low metabolic rates of Caprimulgiformes have been attributed to low activity during foraging, small muscle-to-body-mass ratio, and nocturnal nature, none of which describe Apodiformes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Doucette1">Doucette and Geiser 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Brigham1">Brigham et al. 2012</xref>).Thermoregulation studies within the Apodidae: Swifts.Scaling of metabolic rate in Apodiformes. From a comparison of different body mass and basal metabolic rate (BMR) equations published on all bird families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Reynolds1">Reynolds and Lee 1996</xref>), Trochilidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Kruger1">Kr&uuml;ger et al. 1982</xref>), Caprimulgiformes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Doucette1">Doucette and Geiser 2008</xref>), and captive vs. wild birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McKechnie3">McKechnie et al. 2006</xref>), the predicted line for Apodiformes (BMR &equals; 3.84 B<sub>m</sub><sup>&minus;0.264</sup>) is most similar to the wild-caught birds (BMR &equals; 3.83 B<sub>m</sub><sup>&minus;0.256</sup>) and Caprimulgiformes (BMR &equals; 6.38 B<sub>m</sub><sup>&minus;0.431</sup>). However, metabolic data on swifts covers only a small portion of the range of body masses, biasing these results toward the smaller taxa. The asterisk (&ast;) indicates the lowest observed metabolic rate of a homeothermic individual in this study.Averaged across all individuals in this study, metabolic rate increased 219&percnt; as ambient temperatures decreased 10&deg;C (from a T<sub>a</sub> of 30&deg;C to 20&deg;C). At temperatures below 18&ndash;19&deg;C, 2 individuals began to lower their body temperatures and their metabolic rates began to decrease with temperature, indicating heterothermy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-f02">Figure 2</xref>). However, this pattern was not consistent across all individuals in our study, as 3 individuals continued to maintain a consistent body temperature of ~31&deg;C, independent of decreased ambient temperature and with the expected increase in metabolic rate. Each individual of <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> in this study had a lower body temperature after the acclimation period and during the respirometry trials when compared with the measured body temperature after active flight. The mechanisms or cues that prompted these 2 different thermoregulatory modes remain unclear, but it appears that considerable flexibility may be possible among individuals of this species depending on the costs and benefits of homeothermy and individual fitness.In the Apodidae, several thermoregulatory cues have been studied experimentally: ambient temperature, light intensity, circadian rhythms, and somatic energy reserves. Our results suggest that the decrease in active body temperature from ~39&deg;C to ~31&deg;C in <italic>R. leucopygialis</italic> is likely cued by inactivity, and that light levels may play a role in how much or how rapidly individuals change body temperature set-points. Similarly, White-throated Needletails become heterothermic every night during the nonbreeding season, triggered by darkness or circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Pettigrew1">Pettigrew and Wilson 1985</xref>). Common Swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus apus</named-content></italic>) have a comparable range of body temperatures, with temperatures during activity of ~37&ndash;39&deg;C and minimum nightly temperatures of 25&ndash;29&deg;C, and typically alter their body temperatures in a circadian fashion coinciding with foraging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Koskimies1">Koskimies 1948</xref>).Light levels and photoperiod have been demonstrated to regulate circadian rhythms in birds and small mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Kortner1">K&ouml;rtner and Geiser 2000</xref>). Selection should favor traits that optimize efficiency in acquiring energetic resources, such as decreased foraging in response to reduced food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-MacArthur1">MacArthur and Pianka 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Charnov1">Charnov 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Stephens1">Stephens and Krebs 1986</xref>). This suggests that daily circadian rhythms prompted by light levels may be a cue for heterothermy in members of the Apodidae, because foraging prospects at night are minimal for these visual aerial insectivores.Common Swifts lower their body temperatures in response to low ambient temperatures and food limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Koskimies1">Koskimies 1948</xref>). The author found that both adult and young swifts can survive considerable amounts of time without food (~9 days) by using torpor to reduce metabolic demand. White-throated Swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aeronautes saxatalis</named-content></italic>) also appear to undergo torpor without low (&lt;20&deg;C) ambient temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-Bartholomew1">Bartholomew et al. 1957</xref>). In <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. saxatalis</named-content></italic>, heterothermy occurred in 3 experimental treatment groups: (1) unfed at 4&ndash;5&deg;C, (2) unfed at 20&ndash;22&deg;C, and (3) fed at 20&ndash;22&deg;C; however, food-restricted individuals became heterothermic before those fed ad libitum. Significant weight loss occurred in all treatment groups before they entered torpor, and the authors concluded that diminishing energetic reserves may have been a physiological cue to heterothermy.In contrast to findings for the Apodini and Chaeturini, a heterothermic response could not be initiated in swiftlets in the tribe Collocaliini, despite considerable among-individual variation in body temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-697-McNab2">McNab and Bonaccorso 1995</xref>). Both species studied, the Glossy Swiftlet (<italic>Collocalia esculenta</italic>) and the Uniform Swiftlet (<italic>Aerodramus vanikorenesis</italic>), when exposed to cool temperatures (&lt;30&deg;C), increased their metabolic rates with decreasing ambient temperatures, suggesting to the authors that both species were actively attempting to maintain homeothermy. In their low ambient temperature trials, the body temperatures of both species remained at ~38&deg;C. Despite these results, the authors concluded that they expected that these species would become heterothermic, and suggested that the appropriate physiological or environmental cues may not have been provided in their experiment.Our research and review of the literature suggest that a combination of behavioral and physiological cues prompt heterothermy in the Apodidae. In many species it appears that daily circadian rhythms&mdash;likely related to foraging success&mdash;play a role in the thermoregulatory behavior of individuals. In addition, depletion of energy reserves appears to be another cue promoting heterothermy. In spite of this information, we know little about how these patterns of energy management play a role in the general ecology of this group of birds. More research is needed to document the metabolic costs and thermoregulatory patterns of these birds within different annual and life-cycle stages. The increased metabolic costs of reproduction are likely to both highlight and constrain the energy budgets and thermoregulatory strategies of these most aerial of birds.This work was undertaken in parallel and in collaboration with a student-led Cornell Expedition in Field Ornithology funded by the Ivy Expedition Fund. J.R.S. would like to thank C. W. Twining for helpful comments on a previous version that greatly improved the quality of the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> We are grateful to the anonymous donor who provided the funds that made this collaborative expedition possible, and Cornell University for funds that supported other aspects of the research reported here. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript, and none of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This work was conducted under Cornell IACUC Protocol &num;2001-0051 to D.W.W.