Stable occupancy by breeding hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo</named-content></italic> spp.) over 25 years on a privately managed bunchgrass prairie in northeastern Oregon, USAQuantifying the grazing impacts associated with different herbivores on rangelandsUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionAn aerial sightability model for estimating Ferruginous Hawk population sizeSixty-seven years of landscape changes in the last, large remnant of the Pacific Northwest bunchgrass prairieSwainson's Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></italic>)Nest sites and habitats of sympatric hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo</named-content></italic> spp.) in WashingtonFerruginous Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>)Estimating occupancy to monitor Northern Goshawk in the central Rocky MountainsAbundance of diurnal raptors on open space grasslands in an urbanized landscapeLand use history at multiple scales: Implications for conservation planningDetection probability of cliff-nesting raptors during helicopter and fixed-wing aircraft surveys in western AlaskaNorth American grassland birds: An unfolding conservation crisis?Cumulative effects of wild ungulate and livestock herbivory on riparian willowsDemography and habitat availability in territorial occupancy of two competing speciesChanges in forage quantity and quality with continued late-summer cattle grazing a riparian pasture in eastern Oregon of United StatesTransient dynamics of invasive competition: Barred Owls, Spotted Owls, habitat, and the demons of competition pastEffects of ungulate herbivory on aspen, cottonwood, and willow development under forest fuels treatment regimesPredicting landscape patterns of aspen dieback: Mechanisms and knowledge gapsRed-shouldered Hawk occupancy surveys in central Minnesota, USALand use and the conservation status of raptors in BotswanaConfronting a biome crisis: Global disparities of habitat loss and protectionResponses of pond-breeding amphibians to wildfire: Short-term patterns in occupancy and colonizationPopulation structure and genetic diversity in Swainson's Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></italic>): Implications for conservationStatus and decline of Swainson's Hawks in Oregon: The role of habitat and interspecific competitionPartial loss of Red-tailed Hawk territories to Swainson's Hawks: Relations to habitatMate and nest site fidelity in a resident population of Bald EaglesEffects of rotational grazing on rodents and raptors in a coastal grasslandBird community responses to cattle stocking rates in a Pacific Northwest bunchgrass prairieNest success and cause-specific nest failure of grassland passerines breeding in prairie grazed by livestockLivestock impacts on riparian ecosystems and streamside management implications. A reviewThe potential of occupancy modelling as a tool for monitoring wild primate populationsEffects of native and non-native grassland plant communities on breeding passerine birds: Implications for restoration of northwest bunchgrass prairieAvifaunal responses to fire in southwestern montane forests along a burn severity gradientFactors influencing stream occupancy and detection probability parameters of stream-associated amphibians in commercial forests of Oregon and Washington, USADesigning occupancy studies: General advice and allocating survey effortPesticide acute toxicity is a better correlate of U.S. grassland bird declines than agricultural intensificationEfficient species-level monitoring at the landscape scaleDecline of raptors over a three-year period in Laikipia, central KenyaTerrestrial ecoregions of the world: A new map of life on earthModeling of site occupancy dynamics for Northern Spotted Owls, with emphasis on the effects of Barred OwlsRed-tailed Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo jamaicensis</named-content></italic>)Aspen, climate, and sudden decline in western USAResource partitioning among three <italic>Buteo</italic> species in the Centennial Valley, MontanaLifetime nesting area fidelity in male Cooper's Hawks in WisconsinOn judging the significance of differences by examining the overlap between confidence intervalsHabitat associations and population trends of two hawks in an urbanizing grassland region in ColoradoDemography of Ferruginous Hawks breeding in western CanadaMigration and mortality of Alberta Ferruginous HawksCoexistence of three species of hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo</named-content></italic> spp.) in the prairie-parkland ecotoneOccupancy as a measure of territory qualityNorthern Goshawk ecology: An assessment of current knowledge and information needs for conservation and managementLandscape correlates of reproductive success for an urban&ndash;suburban Red-tailed Hawk populationHabitat samplingAplomado Falcons and grazing: Invoking history to plan restorationChanges in population and agricultural land in conterminous United States counties, 1790 to 1997Program MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsUnderstanding ungulate herbivory&mdash;Episodic disturbance effects on vegetation dynamics: Knowledge gaps and management needsRemaining large grasslands may not be sufficient to prevent grassland bird declinesAspen decline, aspen chemistry, and elk herbivory: Are they linked?Potential for large prairie remnants to provide habitat for grassland-obligate wildlife may be compromised by nonsustainable range-management practices. In 1979&ndash;1980, high nesting densities of 3 species of hawks in the genus <italic>Buteo</italic>&mdash;Ferruginous Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>), Red-tailed Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content></italic>), and Swainson's Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic>)&mdash;were documented on the Zumwalt Prairie and surrounding agricultural areas (34,361 ha) in northeastern Oregon, USA. This area has been managed primarily as livestock summer range since it was homesteaded. Unlike in other prairie remnants, land management on the Zumwalt Prairie was consistent over the past several decades; thus, we predicted that territory occupancy of these 3 species would be stable. We also predicted that territory occupancy would be positively related to local availability of nesting structures within territories. We evaluated these hypotheses using a historical dataset, current survey and habitat data, and occupancy models. In support of our predictions, territory occupancy of all 3 species has not changed over the study period of &sim;25 yr, which suggests that local range-management practices are not negatively affecting these taxa. Probability of Ferruginous Hawk occupancy increased with increasing area of aspen, an important nest structure for this species in grasslands. Probability of Swainson's Hawk occupancy increased with increasing area of large shrubs, and probability of Red-tailed Hawk occupancy was weakly associated with area of conifers. In the study area, large shrubs and conifers are commonly used as nesting structures by Swainson's Hawks and Red-tailed Hawks, respectively. Availability of these woody species is changing (increases in conifers and large shrubs, and decline in aspen) throughout the west, and these changes may result in declines in Ferruginous Hawk occupancy and increases in Swainson's Hawk and Red-tailed Hawk occupancy in the future.El potencial para que los grandes remanentes de praderas provean h&aacute;bitat para las especies especialistas de pastizales podr&iacute;a verse comprometido por pr&aacute;cticas de manejo no sostenibles. Entre 1979 y 1980, se documentaron altas densidades de nidos de tres especies de <italic>Buteo</italic> (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. regalis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic>) en la pradera Zumwalt y &aacute;reas agr&iacute;colas circundantes (34,361 ha) en el nordeste de Oregon, EEUU. Esta &aacute;rea ha sido administrada principalmente como zona de pastoreo de ganado en el verano desde que fue convertida en un &aacute;rea de granjas. A diferencia de otros remanentes de praderas, el manejo de la pradera Zumwalt fue consistente a trav&eacute;s de las d&eacute;cadas pasadas, por lo cual predijimos que la ocupaci&oacute;n del territorio de estas tres especies tambi&eacute;n habr&iacute;a sido estable. Adem&aacute;s predijimos que la ocupaci&oacute;n de los territorios estar&iacute;a relacionada positivamente con la disponibilidad local de las estructuras de anidaci&oacute;n en los territorios. Evaluamos estas hip&oacute;tesis usando una base de datos hist&oacute;rica, censos y datos de h&aacute;bitat contempor&aacute;neos, y modelos de ocupaci&oacute;n. De acuerdo con nuestras predicciones, la ocupaci&oacute;n de los territorios de las tres especies no ha cambiado en el periodo de 25 a&ntilde;os, lo que sugiere que las pr&aacute;cticas locales de manejo no tienen un impacto negativo sobre estas especies. La probabilidad de ocupaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. regalis</named-content></italic> aument&oacute; con el incremento en el &aacute;rea de &aacute;lamos, una estructura importante para la anidaci&oacute;n de esta especie en los pastizales. La probabilidad de ocupaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic> se increment&oacute; con el aumento del &aacute;rea de arbustos grandes y la probabilidad de ocupaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content></italic> estuvo d&eacute;bilmente asociada con el &aacute;rea de con&iacute;feras. En el &aacute;rea de estudio, los arbustos grandes y las con&iacute;feras son usados com&uacute;nmente como estructuras de anidaci&oacute;n por <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content></italic>, respectivamente. La disponibilidad de estas especies le&ntilde;osas est&aacute; cambiando (las con&iacute;feras y los arbustos grandes est&aacute;n aumentando y los &aacute;lamos est&aacute;n disminuyendo) a trav&eacute;s del occidente de los Estados Unidos y estos cambios podr&iacute;an conducir a disminuciones de la ocupaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. regalis</named-content></italic> y a aumentos en la ocupaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content></italic> en el futuro.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ave rapaz, aves de pastizal, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic>, datos hist&oacute;ricos, h&aacute;bitat de anidaci&oacute;n, modelos de ocupaci&oacute;nGrassland birds are threatened globally as a result of numerous factors, including habitat modification and conversion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Brennan1">Brennan and Kuvlesky 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Hoekstra1">Hoekstra et al. 2005</xref>). Most conversion of grasslands to agricultural fields occurred by the 1940s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Waisanen1">Waisanen and Bliss 2002</xref>); thus, recent declines are attributed to other activities that alter the habitat suitability of remaining grasslands for grassland birds. These activities include modern row-crop agricultural practices that involve increased mechanization (e.g., closer row spacing) and more intensive management practices, such as extensive irrigation and increased use of pesticides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Mineau1">Mineau and Whiteside 2013</xref>). More intensive ranching practices such as increased stocking rates of livestock, increased fire frequency from frequent prescribed burns, and increased frequency of haying also alter grassland habitat unfavorably for grassland birds. For example, declining populations of 3 grassland passerines in the Flint Hills of Oklahoma and Kansas, the last large remnant of U.S. tallgrass prairie, may be driven by high frequency of prescribed fire and high stocking rates of livestock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-With1">With et al. 2008</xref>). Raptor use of small (2.2 ha), experimental paddocks in mesic coastal grasslands in northwestern California was higher on ungrazed areas than on grazed areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Johnson1">Johnson and Horn 2008</xref>), which suggests that rangeland management practices influence raptor foraging activity. Unsustainable livestock grazing has also been hypothesized as a major factor in the decline of many raptors globally (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Herremans1">Herremans and Herremans-Tonnoeyr 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Truett1">Truett 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Ogada1">Ogada and Keesing 2010</xref>).We had the unique opportunity to examine effects of livestock grazing on breeding hawks in the genus <italic>Buteo</italic> (hereafter &ldquo;buteos&rdquo;) on the Zumwalt Prairie (hereafter &ldquo;Zumwalt&rdquo;; see below), a large grassland remnant in North America where livestock grazing has long been the predominant land use. Similar to the Flint Hills, the Zumwalt is largely privately owned and primarily managed for spring&ndash;summer livestock (mostly cattle) grazing. However, average livestock stocking rates on Zumwalt are compatible with grassland passerine conservation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Johnson2">Johnson et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Johnson3">2012</xref>). Fire frequencies on Zumwalt are lower now than they have been historically; low- to moderate-severity fires burned this area every 10&ndash;20 yr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Black1">Black et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bartuszevige1">Bartuszevige et al. 2012</xref>). Currently, most fires are suppressed, unlike in the Flint Hills, where a quarter to a third of the region is burned annually.We evaluated temporal trends in nesting territory occupancy of Ferruginous Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>), Swainson's Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic>), and Red-tailed Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. jamaicensis</named-content></italic>) on Zumwalt. We resurveyed Zumwalt and reanalyzed data from surveys in 1979 and 1980, which showed high nesting densities of these species (Cottrell &lsqb;now Houle&rsqb; 1981). Rangewide, Ferruginous Hawks and Swainson's Hawks have declined to levels that have led to conservation concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Collins1">Collins and Reynolds 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-U.S.FishandWildlifeService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2008</xref>). Declines have been attributed to habitat conversion and degradation, but persecution and secondary pesticide poisoning may play a role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schmutz2">Schmutz and Fyfe 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bechard3">Bechard and Schmutz 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Hull1">Hull et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schmutz1">Schmutz et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bechard1">Bechard et al. 2010</xref>). The third species, Red-tailed Hawk, is common in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Preston1">Preston and Beane 2009</xref>) and is known to increase in human-modified environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Berry1">Berry et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schmidt1">Schmidt and Bock 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Stout1">Stout et al. 2006</xref>). Nest-structure availability may also limit densities of buteos in prairies, as evidenced by intraspecific and interspecific agonistic interactions close to nest structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Janes1">Janes 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Janes2">1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Restani1">Restani 1991</xref>). However, the utility of this literature to rangewide conservation planning is limited because none of the demographic analyses to date incorporated a probability-based random sampling approach or corrected population estimates for detection probabilities &lt;1.0, which results in biased estimates and precludes inference beyond specific sample units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Williams1">Williams et al. 2002</xref>).Trends in territory occupancy are a good index of population performance in breeding raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Sergio1">Sergio and Newton 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Olson2">Olson et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Henneman1">Henneman et al. 2007</xref>) and other wildlife (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Hossack1">Hossack and Corn 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Keane1">Keane et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Noon1">Noon et al. 2012</xref>). In the present study, we used a probability-based sampling approach that allowed us to estimate variation in both site occupancy and detection rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>) and make inferences beyond our sample units to the entire Zumwalt Prairie and comparable habitats. On the basis of this body of literature and the historical data, we developed a priori predictions about the habitat factors that might influence buteo territory occupancy, which we tested using a model selection framework.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Houle1">Houle (2007)</xref> hypothesized that high densities at Zumwalt could be attributed to the management practices of the private landowners, which retained high abundances of prey and nest structures. If so, we would expect high occupancy to continue at Zumwalt, given that management practices were consistent over the 25 yr since Cottrell's study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bartuszevige1">Bartuszevige et al. 2012</xref>; for more details, see below) and because raptors have high site fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Jenkins1">Jenkins and Jackman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Rosenfield1">Rosenfield and Bielefeldt 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Squires1">Squires and Kennedy 2006</xref>).We also predicted that nest-structure availability would influence the probability of territory occupancy, on the basis of described nesting substrates used by buteos in other sympatric populations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schmutz3">Schmutz et al. 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bechard2">Bechard et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Restani1">Restani 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Janes2">Janes 1994</xref>). We predicted that (1) area of aspen (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus tremuloides</named-content></italic>) and number of rock outcrops would be positively related to Ferruginous and Red-tailed hawk territory occupancy; (2) area of conifers, mostly ponderosa pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus ponderosa</named-content></italic>) and Douglas-fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pseudotsuga menziesii</named-content></italic>), would be positively related to Red-tailed Hawk territory occupancy; (3) area of conifers would be negatively related to Ferruginous and Swainson's hawk territory occupancy; and (4) area of large shrubs (big enough to support a buteo nest) would be positively related to Swainson's Hawk territory occupancy.Zumwalt is located in northeastern Wallowa County, Oregon, USA (117&deg;3&prime;N, 45&deg;31&prime;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). It is the last large (&sim;64,000 ha) remnant of Pacific Northwest bunchgrass prairie, which was formerly widely distributed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Black1">Black et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Olson1">Olson et al. 2001</xref>). The Zumwalt, unlike many prairies in the United States, is still largely intact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Kennedy1">Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>); very little of the Zumwalt has been cultivated (&sim;8.6&percnt; in 1938; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bartuszevige1">Bartuszevige et al. 2012</xref>). It is dominated by bunchgrasses and perennial forbs. Patches of shrub and forest vegetation occur in areas with deeper soils, cooler microclimates, or higher soil moisture such as valleys, swales, slopes with northerly aspects, and riparian areas. Almost all of the Zumwalt is in private ownership. The primary land use since European-American settlement has been seasonal cattle grazing (April&ndash;October). Currently, very few people reside on the study area. Thus, human influence on the prairie is evidenced primarily by old fields and homesites that have been abandoned for more than a century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Belew1">Belew 2000</xref>). In addition, there are fences and impoundments typical of open rangeland.Location of the Zumwalt Prairie study area in northeastern Oregon, USA. The historical study area boundary (Cottrell Study Area, 1979&ndash;1980; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell 1981</xref>) and current study area boundary (OSU Study Area) are depicted. Squares are plots sampled in 2004&ndash;2006. &ldquo;Discarded&rdquo; plots were sampled in 2004&ndash;2005, and these plots were replaced with the &ldquo;added&rdquo; plots in 2006. Suitable habitat was further stratified into areas of &ldquo;high&rdquo; (white) or &ldquo;low&rdquo; (medium gray) suitability on the basis of historical nest distributions. Plots surveyed in 2004&ndash;2006 were randomly distributed in these areas. For additional details, see text.The original study area used in 1979&ndash;1980 was 36,361 ha (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell 1981</xref>). In 2004, we modified the study area boundary originally defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell (1981)</xref> to eliminate habitats that were not relatively intact native prairie. We excluded cultivated areas in the southern portion of the study area (&sim;8,100 ha). The study area was also expanded to include additional intact grasslands (3,034 ha) not surveyed by Cottrell. Additionally, we adjusted Cottrell's northeastern and western boundaries to coincide with the prairie boundary defined by The Nature Conservancy (personal communication). Our study area (defined in 2004) was 31,136 ha (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Landowner permission for property access was secured from 28 of 32 landowners, representing 98&percnt; of the study area.We estimated trends in territory occupancy (presence or absence of breeding buteos at a plot; for occupancy criteria, see below) for this revised study area in 2004&ndash;2006. To estimate study area occupancy, we selected a plot size of 800 &times; 800 m as representative of a buteo nesting territory, on the basis of nearest-neighbor distances from Cottrell's data, and applied this plot size to the entire study area (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 551 total).We stratified the study area to reduce potential for sampling large numbers of unoccupied plots. Ninety-two percent of historical nests were found in 3 landforms: side slope, cove ravine (concave bottom of a draw), and steep slope. Using ArcGIS version 9 (ESRI, Redlands, California, USA), we combined polygons of the 3 landforms and labeled them &ldquo;suitable habitat.&rdquo; Large areas that lacked any 1 of these 3 landforms, primarily the flat high ridgetops, were labeled &ldquo;unsuitable habitat.&rdquo; This resulted in essentially 2 sections of suitable habitat for sampling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We further stratified the 2 sections of suitable habitat by historical nest densities. Using a map of historical nest locations and following natural landforms that formed boundaries (e.g., ravines and other landscape features), we drew a line between areas of high and low nest densities, thus subdividing suitable habitat into 2 areas of &ldquo;high&rdquo; suitability and 1 area of &ldquo;low&rdquo; suitability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>).One hundred plots (18.1&percnt; of the study area) were randomly distributed in the suitable habitat, weighted by available area in the high- and low-suitability areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We replaced plots on properties where we did not have access with randomly chosen accessible plots. In 2006, 2 plots were replaced because of conflicts with elk calving grounds and close proximity to a private home (&ldquo;added&rdquo; and &ldquo;discarded&rdquo; plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). A similar approach to stratified random sampling was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Beck1">Beck et al. (2011)</xref> to monitor Northern Goshawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter gentilis</named-content></italic>) territory occupancy in the central Rocky Mountains.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell (1981)</xref> searched the entire area for nests; thus, we assumed that she conducted a complete census of buteo nests in the study area. If Cottrell recorded nesting activity in a plot, that plot was deemed occupied; otherwise it was unoccupied. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell (1981)</xref> visited plots 1&ndash;5 times; we used plots visited at least twice to estimate detection probabilities for 1979 and 1980 (see below). We sampled all plots 1&ndash;3 times yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> between April 10 and July 8, 2004&ndash;2006. In 2004, we sampled each plot 2 times (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 187 plot visits) using a removal design (whereby surveying halts at a plot once the species is detected; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-MacKenzie2">MacKenzie and Royle 2005</xref>). To improve detection probabilities, we added a third visit in 2005 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 261 plot visits). Because it is plausible for a plot to be occupied by more than 1 species, we modified the removal design as follows: If a plot was deemed occupied by 1 <italic>Buteo</italic> species and no other <italic>Buteo</italic> species were observed in the plot, that plot was not revisited. However, if another <italic>Buteo</italic> species was observed in that plot (but occupancy was not established for that species; see below), the plot was revisited to determine whether it was occupied by more than 1 species. This approach allowed for calculation of detection probabilities for each species, necessary for developing an occupancy model. A similar design was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Kroll1">Kroll et al. (2008)</xref> to estimate occupancy of stream-associated amphibians in the Pacific Northwest.Because they are migratory, Swainson's Hawks initiate breeding later than the other 2 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bechard1">Bechard et al. 2010</xref>). To increase the probability of detecting Swainson's Hawks (which were rarely detected during the first visit), we switched to a standard design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-MacKenzie2">MacKenzie and Royle 2005</xref>) in 2006, whereby all plots were visited 3 times even if they were determined to be occupied in a previous visit (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 300 plot visits).The same 2 observers completed most plot visits (91&percnt; in 2004, 100&percnt; in 2005, and 89&percnt; in 2006); 3 other observers made the remaining visits. In all years, plots visited more than once were sampled by 2 different observers to reduce observer bias, and the sequence of observer visits was alternated when possible.During each plot visit, we searched for raptors and nest structures, noting behaviors and interactions associated with mated-pair or territorial behavior. Because many of the plots were remote and required hiking access, raptors could be recorded in a plot when the observer was not yet in that plot. For adjacent plots, a raptor observed flying between 2 plots would be recorded in both plots. Plot visits varied in length (mean &equals; 1.5 hr; range: 0.75&ndash;8.0 hr), depending on the number of potential nest structures in the plot. Once data recording began, observers walked the entire plot, recording all nest structures and all buteos observed in the plot. A plot was deemed occupied if we observed a mated pair (based on synchronous pair flight, nonaggressive interactions with each other, or mutually aggressive behavior directed at an intruder) or a nest with eggs, nestlings, or fledglings.We digitized landscape features of the sample plots from 2001 digital orthophoto quadrangles using ArcGIS. We determined area of conifers, shrubs, and aspen and number of rock outcrops. We ground truthed aerial photo data between May and July 2005. &ldquo;Rock outcrops&rdquo; were defined as rocky features extending from the ground, &gt;1 m tall. In 2006, we documented woody vegetation as conifer (mostly ponderosa pine and Douglas-fir); aspen; or large shrubs (i.e. big enough to support a buteo nest), mostly black hawthorn (<italic>Crataegus douglasi</italic>), willows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Salix</named-content></italic> spp.), and cottonwoods (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus</named-content></italic> spp.) (hereafter &ldquo;shrubs&rdquo;). We also recorded the length of fences (m), which provide perches for hunting hawks, and the numbers of ponds or impoundments, which influence prey availability and livestock use.We used single-season occupancy models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>) to estimate occupancy rates (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>), while also accounting for imperfect detection rates (<italic>p̂</italic>). We used model selection procedures as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson (2002)</xref> to rank and compare models using Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>). We considered models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> values &le;2 to have strong support, an appropriate criterion for a small set of single-covariate models (for a discussion of alternative AIC<sub>c</sub> criteria for multiple-covariate models, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). We also evaluated Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) as relative measures of support for each model based on their ranking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). In addition, we used estimates of regression coefficients (&beta;) and their 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CIs) to provide strength of evidence and support for specific effects in competitive models.We used Program MARK version 4.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>) for model selection and to estimate model parameters. We present means and 95&percnt; CIs for all estimates. Lack of overlap of confidence intervals with means of other estimates was interpreted as evidence of statistical difference between estimates, whereas asymmetrical overlap of means (confidence intervals overlap one mean but not the other) was interpreted as suggestive evidence of a statistical difference between groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schenker1">Schenker and Gentleman 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Ramsey1">Ramsey and Schafer 2002</xref>:674&ndash;675).To test our first prediction about trends in occupancy, we estimated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> for each year (1979&ndash;1980 and 2004&ndash;2006), based only on presence of active nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Cottrell1">Cottrell &lsqb;1981&rsqb;</xref> did not record presence of mated pairs). Sparse data, lack of covariates for data collected in 1979&ndash;1980, and confounding of time and observer effects (observers were systematically assigned to surveys) resulted in very simple models incorporating time-dependent (p̂(t)) or constant ((p̂(.)) detection rates within seasons, and a single estimate of territory occupancy across all plots for each year (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>(.)). The model structure best supported by the data was (p̂(.)<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>(.) where parameters were estimable.In the second modeling step, using data from 2006, we developed a series of a priori single-factor models based on our predictions about the 6 potential habitat factors that might influence <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> for each hawk species: amount of conifer or aspen forest (CONIFER or ASPEN; ha), amount of shrub (SHRUB; ha), number of large rocks (ROCKS) or ponds (PONDS), and linear amount of fencing (FENCE; m). We chose to develop an a priori model set that included each habitat covariate in a univariate model because, although we had a large sample of plots in all years, the number of plots where raptors were detected was quite small for many species in some years. We also chose to use only 2006 data for this analysis, because it was the largest dataset with the most surveys per plot (3 complete surveys with all occupancy criteria). For reasons similar to those previously given for the trend analysis, we did not examine the influence of covariates on <italic>p̂</italic>. Therefore, the general model form of our models was p̂(.)<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> (covariate).We used the aforementioned model selection procedures to evaluate which of the 7 models (6 single habitat covariate models &plus; the null model p̂(.)) for each species were best supported by the data. The direction of the effect (positive or negative) of covariates included in the top models was obtained from a review of the 95&percnt; CIs of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> values. If the 95&percnt; CI overlapped zero, we concluded that there was weak support for an association between the covariate and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.Detection probabilities were &lt;1.0 for every species and every year except for Swainson's Hawk in 1980 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t01">Table 1</xref>). There is some support for <italic>p̂</italic> being higher during the historical surveys than in the current surveys for both Swainson's Hawks (asymmetrical overlap of 95&percnt; CIs for 1979 and 2006) and Ferruginous Hawks (asymmetrical overlap of 95&percnt; CIs for 1979 and 2006 and for 1980 and 2006) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t01">Table 1</xref>). However, detection probabilities were similar for Red-tailed Hawks during all years, which suggests that differences among years may be related to the sparseness of the dataset for the 2 rarer species.Estimates of detection probability (<italic>p̂</italic>) for 3 species of <italic>Buteo</italic> nesting on the Zumwalt Prairie in northeastern Oregon, USA, for 1979, 1980, 2004, 2005, and 2006.Occupancy could not be estimated for Ferruginous Hawks and Swainson's Hawks in 2004, one of the years with just 2 sampling occasions. However, all estimates of occupancy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f02">Figure 2</xref>) support our prediction that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> was stable over the study period. All 95&percnt; CIs of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> for the Ferruginous Hawk and Red-tailed Hawk overlap. For Swainson's Hawk, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> was significantly lower for 1980 than for all other years, but this does not indicate increases in occupancy, because <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> for 1979 and 2005&ndash;2006 were similar.Year-specific occupancy estimates (&psi;&circ;) with 95&percnt; confidence intervals for Ferruginous Hawks (<bold>A</bold>), Red-tailed Hawks (<bold>B</bold>), and Swainson's Hawks (<bold>C</bold>) during the breeding season on the Zumwalt Prairie in northeastern Oregon, USA. Because of sparse data, &psi;&circ; for Ferruginous and Swainson's hawks could not be estimated for 2004.The most abundant species was the Red-tailed Hawk, which occupied 12.4&percnt; (2004) to 20.7&percnt; (1979) of the Zumwalt during 1979&ndash;2006. Occupancy rates of the other 2 <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo</named-content></italic> spp. were similar: Ferruginous Hawks occupied 3.8&percnt; (1979) to 11.1&percnt; (2006) and Swainson's Hawks occupied 1.1&percnt; (1980) to 11.0&percnt; (1979) of the Zumwalt during this period.Although aspen was not abundant in the study area (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t02">Table 2</xref>), model selection results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>) indicated that area of aspen was positively related to Ferruginous Hawk <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 17.69 &plusmn; 8.84; 95&percnt; CI: 0.36&ndash;35.02; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f03">Figure 3</xref>), as predicted. There were no competing models, which contradicts our prediction that other types of nest strata influence <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in Ferruginous Hawks. There was also no evidence that fences or ponds influenced <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in Ferruginous Hawks.Values of habitat covariates collected in occupancy plots (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref> for plot locations) during 2005 in the Zumwalt Prairie in northeastern Oregon, USA.Model selection results for all models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 4. These models estimate the effect of a priori habitat variables on occupancy (&psi;&circ;) of Ferruginous, Red-tailed, and Swainson's hawks nesting on the Zumwalt Prairie in northeastern Oregon, USA, during 2006. Model covariates include acreage of coniferous or aspen forest (CONIFER or ASPEN; ha), acreage of large shrubs (SHRUB; ha), number of large rocks (ROCKS), and linear amount of fencing (FENCE; m) in each plot. Model weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), model deviance, and number of parameters (<italic>k</italic>) are also given for all models. &ldquo;Sign&rdquo; refers to the regression coefficient corresponding to the habitat variable: positive (&plus;) or negative (&ndash;) if 95&percnt; confidence intervals for the coefficient do not overlap zero, and zero otherwise.Predicted estimates of occupancy (&psi;&circ;) with 95&percnt; confidence intervals from our top models for Ferruginous Hawks, Red-tailed Hawks, and Swainson' Hawks during the breeding season on the Zumwalt Prairie in northeastern Oregon, USA (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref> for top models). These were based on the 2006 data and were plotted across the range of covariate values observed in our 800 x 800 m plots.Conifers were the most abundant woody species on the study area (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t02">Table 2</xref>). Model selection results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>) indicated that area of conifers was positively related to Red-tailed Hawk <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, as predicted. However, the 95&percnt; CI of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> value for amount of conifer overlapped zero, indicating weak support for the effect of this covariate (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.20 &plusmn; 0.13; 95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.06 to 0.46; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f03">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>). There were no competing models, which does not support our prediction that other types of nest strata influence <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in Red-tailed Hawks. There was also no evidence that fences or ponds influenced <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> of Red-tailed Hawks (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>).Shrubs were used by Swainson's Hawks as nest structures in the study area. Model selection results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>) indicated that area of shrubs was positively associated with Swainson's Hawk <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, as predicted (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 1.07 &plusmn; 0.41; 95&percnt; CI: 0.27&ndash;1.87; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f03">Figure 3</xref>). There were no competing models, which does not support our prediction that other types of nest strata influence <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in Swainson's Hawks (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-t03">Table 3</xref>).Combining a historical dataset with more recent surveys that incorporated stratified random sampling allowed us the unique opportunity to assess patterns in territory occupancy of Ferruginous, Red-tailed, and Swainson's hawks on one of the last large bunchgrass prairie remnants in North America. Our results support the results of other investigations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Johnson2">Johnson et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Johnson3">2012</xref>) that grassland birds of conservation concern do not necessarily decline over time in working landscapes in the western United States. Zumwalt is providing habitat for the Ferruginous Hawk and Swainson's Hawk, species that are declining in other parts of their ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Collins1">Collins and Reynolds 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-U.S.FishandWildlifeService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2008</xref>). The ability of this working landscape to support these species is likely due to the fact that Zumwalt has not been extensively modified by the anthropogenic activities that typically threaten grasslands (e.g., conversion to cropland, fragmentation from exurban development, and increasing extent and frequency of fire; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bartuszevige1">Bartuszevige et al. 2012</xref>). In addition, there is no evidence that the Red-tailed Hawk is expanding its occupancy in the study area, which commonly occurs as a result of anthropogenic change in other areas (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Berry1">Berry et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Schmidt1">Schmidt and Bock 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Stout1">Stout et al. 2006</xref>). However, our occupancy estimates for this species have large confidence intervals, so it is possible that our analysis did not detect increases or decreases that may have occurred in the past 25 yr. In addition, our study provides only &ldquo;snapshots&rdquo; in time; without a more complete time series, we have no understanding of the range of variation in occupancy rates that characterize raptors on the Zumwalt prairie over time. That said, this is one of the few studies to estimate raptor territory occupancy rates while taking into account detection rates &lt;1.0 and providing estimates of sampling variance. The few studies that have estimated detection of breeding buteos are not directly comparable because they used different survey techniques. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Henneman1">Henneman et al. (2007)</xref> estimated that detection of Red-shouldered Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. lineatus</named-content></italic>) from call-broadcast surveys in central Minnesota ranged from 0.28 to 0.54. Using aerial surveys, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Ayers1">Ayers and Anderson (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Booms1">Booms et al. (2010)</xref> estimated that detection ranged from 0.24 to 0.37 for Ferruginous Hawks nesting in south-central Wyoming and from 0.10 to 0.42 for cliff-nesting Rough-legged Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. lagopus</named-content></italic>) in western Alaska, respectively.Although agricultural management practices on Zumwalt have not changed during the past &sim;30 yr, landscape changes have occurred as a result of these practices. The most dramatic change in this landscape is the shift in the abundance of woody species, the primary nesting substrates for the 3 species of <italic>Buteo</italic> in this area (84.5&percnt; of all known nest structures, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 84; P. L. Kennedy et al. personal observation). Aspen has declined by 18&percnt; (from 7.2 ha in 1976 to 5.9 ha in 2005) in Zumwalt, and there is little or no regeneration of the current decadent clones. Ponderosa pine and shrubs have increased by 455&percnt; (from 10.8 ha in 1976 to 60.0 ha in 2005) and 72&percnt; (from 21.8 ha in 1976 to 37.5 ha in 2005), respectively. This declining trend in aspen is common throughout the western United States. Multiple land-use factors (e.g., fire suppression and livestock herbivory) and ecological factors (e.g., native ungulate herbivory and climate change) influence these trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Brookshire1">Brookshire et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Frey1">Frey et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Rehfeldt1">Rehfeldt et al. 2009</xref>).In our study area, decline in aspen can partially be attributed to high levels of native and domestic ungulate grazing and differences in the palatability of the woody species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bartuszevige1">Bartuszevige et al. 2012</xref>). The invading species, conifers and hawthorns, are less palatable to ungulates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Kauffman1">Kauffman and Krueger 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Darambazar1">Darambazar et al. 2013</xref>), whereas aspen is a particularly desired foraging substrate for elk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Wooley1">Wooley et al. 2008</xref>) and is also eaten by cattle. Therefore, there are few unprotected aspen stands where new stems are able to grow tall enough to escape increased pressure from browsing due to high abundance of ungulates (see two unpublished reports by R. V. Taylor and coauthors: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/1bplH41" xlink:type="simple">http://bit.ly/1bplH41</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/1gglzGt" xlink:type="simple">http://bit.ly/1gglzGt</ext-link>). Herbivory by domestic and native ungulates is a well-documented chronic disturbance that can affect vegetation dynamics globally (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Wisdom1">Wisdom et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Albon1">Albon et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Endress1">Endress et al. 2012</xref>). Given that aspen is a strong predictor of Ferruginous Hawk occupancy, it is possible that continued decreases in the availability of this nest structure will result in future declines of this species on Zumwalt unless they switch to other nest structures, which they have used on the study area (e.g., ponderosa pine and rock outcrops) and are known to use in other parts of their range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Bechard3">Bechard and Schmutz 1995</xref>). Conversely, increases in shrub and pine could result in higher occupancy of Swainson's Hawks and Red-tailed Hawks, respectively.The Red-tailed Hawk has replaced the forest-dwelling Red-shouldered Hawk in partially cleared hardwood bottomland forests in the eastern United States. It has also become more common through the northern Great Plains during the past 100 yr, likely as a result of increased tree growth in formerly treeless grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Preston1">Preston and Beane 2009</xref>). Thus, if tree encroachment continues in this grassland, we predict that Red-tailed Hawks will replace Ferruginous and Swainson's hawks in Zumwalt in the future.In addition to the availability of nest structures, prey availability and interspecific competition for nest sites may also influence territory occupancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Squires1">Squires and Kennedy 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Tapia1">Tapia et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Dugger1">Dugger et al. 2011</xref>). The fact that different nest structures were associated with the occupancy rates of each species suggests that these 3 species may partition resources to avoid competition for a limited resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Restani1">Restani 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Carrete1">Carrete et al. 2005</xref>). However, we did not test any hypotheses related to these factors in the present study. Future studies on this topic should examine the influence of prey and congeners on occupancy.Combining historical data collected using traditional techniques with a dataset collected using current survey methods allowed us to use modern analytical approaches (for a similar approach, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Kotliar1">Kotliar et al. 2007</xref>). This enabled us to assess trends in model parameters based on datasets collected 25 yr apart. Caution must be exercised when using historical data, however. We were forced to make assumptions about the original sampling regime (e.g., a census of the entire study area) to fit the current analysis, which may have influenced parameter estimates for 1979&ndash;1980. Also, our stratified random sample of the prairie included many areas that were not sampled in the original study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-f01">Figure 1</xref>). This resulted in a large number of zeros in our dataset, which influenced our ability to model all parameters and covariates simultaneously or with much structure. It also eliminated the possibility of using multiseason occupancy models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>) to evaluate effects of temporal changes in territory turnover. We might have been able to reduce the number of zeros by incorporating an additional stratification factor: whether an area had been searched previously. However, this additional stratification would also have reduced our ability to infer results for the entire prairie. The data sparseness was particularly problematic in 2004, when we had only 2 sampling occasions. In that year, we could not estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-435-e01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> accurately for the 2 rare species. Thus, future studies of territory occupancy for these species should incorporate a minimum of 3 sampling occasions and/or increase the number of plots sampled.Finally, our results support the findings of other raptor studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Henneman1">Henneman et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-435-Booms1">Booms et al. 2010</xref>) that breeding raptors are not 100&percnt; detectable. In the present study, Swainson's Hawks had the lowest detection probabilities, which are likely a result of their small sample sizes, late arrival on the study area, smaller nest size, nest placement (commonly embedded in dense hawthorn shrubbery), and secretive, nondefensive behavior toward nest-site intruders. The detection rate of 1.0 for Swainson's Hawks during 1980 is likely inflated as a result of superimposing detection probabilities on a small set of initial observations that were collected using a different methodology.We are grateful for financial support to conduct this research from the National Resources Conservation Service, Wildlife Habitat Management Institute. Additional support was provided by The Nature Conservancy's Northeast Oregon Office and the Eastern Oregon Agriculture and Natural Resource Program of Oregon State University. We are deeply indebted to C. Henny and C. Warren, who inspired and guided Cottrell's original study. Our sincere gratitude goes to the 28 landowners on the Zumwalt who made this study possible by generously providing access to their property, and to T. Smith, R. Childers, and C. Warnock for assisting us with landowner contacts. D. MacKenzie assisted with study design and answered numerous questions about multiseason occupancy models. We also thank the Oregon Department of Fish and Wildlife (V. Coggins and M. Hansen) for technical assistance with data-recording techniques and for providing information on aspen and hawk sightings. C. Whiting, P. Arentsen, and A. Lueders helped conduct hawk surveys, and K. Allen assisted with the GIS analyses. C. Coiner assisted with GIS, graphics support, copyediting, and general field support. The comments of J. Fontaine, R. Taylor, A. J. Kroll, and several anonymous reviewers greatly improved the manuscript. The use of trade names or products does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. Government.