Fifty-sixth Supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union: <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Townsend's and Newell's Shearwater (<italic>Puffinus auricularis</italic>)A new bird for North AmericaSome thoughts on the identification of Gunnison's Red-backed Hawk (<italic>Buteo polyosoma</italic>) and why it's not a natural vagrantEcology and the evolution of some Hawaiian birdsThe Hawaiian honeycreepers (Aves, Drepaniidae)Forty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>The natural history of French Frigate Shoals, northwestern Hawaiian IslandsMolecular evidence of the taxonomic status of western Mexican populations of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phaethornis longirostris</named-content></italic> (Aves: Trochilidae)Forty-third supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Going to extremes: Contrasting rates of diversification in a recent radiation of New World passerine birdsNew insights into New World biogeography: An integrated view from the phylogeny of blackbirds, cardinals, sparrows, tanagers, warblers, and alliesBehavioural and molecular evidence for specific status of light and dark morphs of the Herald Petrel <italic>Pterodroma heraldica</italic>Range expansion and hybridization in Round Island petrels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pterodroma</named-content></italic> spp.); evidence from microsatellite genotypesPhylogenetics and diversification of tanagers (Passeriformes: Thraupidae), the largest radiation of Neotropical songbirdsFirst North American records of Bicolored Wren (<italic>Campylorhynchus griseus</italic>) and Dusky Pigeon (<italic>Patagioenas goodsoni</italic>)Fifty-fourth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Report of the California Bird Records Committee: 2002 recordsReflections on a 1975 ornithological expedition to the lost world of the Alaka&lsquo;i and other notes on the natural history, systematics, and status of Kaua&lsquo;i birdsDescription de quinze esp&egrave;ces nouvelles de Trochilid&eacute;esLineage diversification and morphological evolution in a large-scale continental radiation: The Neotropical ovenbirds and woodcreepers (Aves: Furnariidae)Divergence in morphology, calls, song, mechanical sounds, and genetics supports species status for the Inaguan hummingbird (Trochilidae: <italic>Calliphlox &ldquo;evelynae&rdquo; lyrura</italic>)Evolution on a volcanic conveyor belt: Using phylogeographic reconstructions and K-Ar-based ages of the Hawaiian Islands to estimate molecular evolutionary ratesMolecular systematics of the caracaras and allies (Falconidae: Polyborinae) inferred from mitochondrial and nuclear sequence dataFamily Stercorariidae (Skuas)Herald Petrel new to the West IndiesPhylogeny of the Falconidae inferred from molecular and morphological dataPhylogeny of the Falconidae (Aves): A comparison of the efficacy of morphological, mitochondrial, and nuclear dataTaxonomy and song of Mexican Hermit <italic>Phaethornis mexicanus</italic>Identification of Manx-type shearwaters in the eastern PacificThe osteology and phylogeny of the Hawaiian Finch radiation (Fringillidae: Drepanidini), including extinct taxaDescriptions of thirty-two new species of birds from the Hawaiian Islands. Part II. PasseriformesGenetic evidence for the origin and relationships of Hawaiian honeycreepers (Aves: Fringillidae)A revised nomenclature and classification for family-group taxa of parrots (Psittaciformes)A comprehensive multilocus assessment of sparrow (Family Passerellidae) relationshipsFirst record of hybridization in the Hawaiian Honeycreepers: 'I'iwi (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vestiaria coccinea</named-content></italic>) &times; 'Apapane (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Himatione sanguinea</named-content></italic>)Notes on certain birds from New Granada, with descriptions of new speciesMultilocus resolution of phylogeny and timescale in the extant adaptive radiation of Hawaiian honeycreepersPhylogenetic placement of the critically endangered Townsend's Shearwater (<italic>Puffinus auricularis auricularis</italic>): Evidence for its conspecific status with Newell's Shearwater (<italic>Puffinus a. newelli</italic>) and a mismatch between genetic and phenotypic differentiationCorrections to the original citations and type localities of some birds described by John Gould and recorded from New ZealandMolecular phylogenetics and the diversification of hummingbirdsA molecular phylogenetic hypothesis for the manakins (Aves: Pipridae)Lista oficial de las aves de Costa Rica. Actualizaci&oacute;n 2014. Comit&eacute; Cient&iacute;fico, Asociaci&oacute;n Ornitol&oacute;gica de Costa RicaMolecular phylogeny of the manakins (Aves: Passeriformes: Pipridae), with a new classification and the description of a new genusHistory, structure, evolution, behavior, distribution, and ecology of the extinct Hawaiian genus <italic>Ciridops</italic> (Fringillidae, Carduelini, Drepanidini)Prodromus of the fossil avifauna of the Hawaiian IslandsNomenclature of the Hawaiian akialoas and nukupuus (Aves: Drepanidini)25th Report of the ABA Checklist Committee 2013&ndash;1014Status and distribution of Egyptian Geese (<italic>Alopochen aegyptiaca</italic>) in southeast FloridaSpecies limits in akepas (Drepanidinae: <italic>Loxops</italic>)Family Drepanididae (Hawaiian honeycreepers)A consensus taxonomy for the Hawaiian honeycreepersThe interplay of species concepts, taxonomy, and conservation: Lessons from the Hawaiian avifauna'Akiap&ograve;l&agrave;'au (<italic>Hemignathus munroi</italic>) and Nukupu'u (<italic>Hemignathus lucidus</italic>)Nomenclature of the Laysan Honeycreeper <italic>Himatione</italic> &lsqb;<italic>sanguinea</italic>&rsqb; <italic>fraithii</italic>Patterns and processes of diversification in a widespread and ecologically diverse avian group, the buteonine hawks (Aves, Accipitridae)Convergent evolution of &ldquo;creepers&rdquo; in the Hawaiian honeycreeper radiationPhylogenetic analyses of the genera <italic>Pipra</italic>, <italic>Lepidothrix</italic> and <italic>Dixiphia</italic> (Pipridae, Passeriformes) using partial cytochrome <italic>b</italic> and 16S mtDNA genesDiagnoses of new forms of Micropodidae and TrochilidaeThe birds of North and Middle AmericaPopulation size and factors affecting at-sea distributions of four endangered procellariids in the tropical PacificMitochondrial-DNA variation and evolutionary relationships in the amakihi complexEvolutionary relationships of the Hawaiian honeycreepers (Aves: Drepanidinae)Phylogeny and phylogenetic classification of the tyrant flycatchers, cotingas, manakins, and their allies (Aves: Tyrannides)First record of Newell's Shearwater from the mainland of North AmericaZino's Petrel movements at sea&mdash;a preliminary analysis of datalogger resultsThis is the 15th supplement since publication of the 7th edition of the <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">American Ornithologists' Union &lsqb;AOU&rsqb; 1998</xref>). It summarizes decisions made between May 15, 2014, and April 15, 2015, by the AOU's Committee on Classification and Nomenclature&mdash;North and Middle America. The Committee has continued to operate in the manner outlined in the 42nd Supplement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion3">AOU 2000</xref>).Changes in this supplement include the following: (1) seven species (<italic>Alopochen aegyptiaca</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria irrorata</named-content></italic>, <italic>Pterodroma madeira</italic>, <italic>Syrigma sibilatrix</italic>, <italic>Patagioenas goodsoni</italic>, <italic>Campylorhynchus griseus</italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</named-content></italic>) are added to the main list on the basis of new distributional information, including two species transferred from the Appendix; (2) 11 species (<italic>Pterodroma heraldica</italic>, <italic>Puffinus newelli</italic>, <italic>Phaethornis mexicanus</italic>, <italic>Calliphlox lyrura</italic>, <italic>Himatione fraithii</italic>, <italic>Hemignathus hanapepe</italic>, <italic>H. affinis</italic>, <italic>Akialoa stejnegeri</italic>, <italic>A. lanaiensis</italic>, <italic>Loxops wolstenholmei</italic>, and <italic>L. ochraceus</italic>) are added to the main list due to splits from species already on the list; (3) one species name is changed (to <italic>Cranioleuca dissita</italic>) because of a split from an extralimital species; (4) the distributional statement of one species (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Stercorarius skua</named-content></italic>) is changed because of a split from an extralimital species; (5) the distributional statements and English names of four species (<italic>Pterodroma arminjoniana</italic>, <italic>Hemignathus lucidus</italic>, <italic>Akialoa ellisiana</italic>, and <italic>Loxops coccineus</italic>) and the distributional statements of four others (<italic>Puffinus auricularis</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phaethornis longirostris</named-content></italic>, <italic>Calliphlox evelynae</italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Himatione sanguinea</named-content></italic>) are changed as a result of taxonomic changes; (6) the scientific names of two species (<italic>Leptotila cassinii</italic> and <italic>Amazilia saucerottei</italic>) are corrected on the basis of evidence in their original descriptions; (7) the scientific names of two species (<italic>Hemignathus wilsoni</italic> and <italic>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</italic>) are changed following changes in generic assignment that affected the priority of their species names; (8) seven genera (<italic>Rupornis</italic>, <italic>Geranoaetus</italic>, <italic>Cryptopipo</italic>, <italic>Akialoa</italic>, <italic>Chlorodrepanis</italic>, <italic>Viridonia</italic>, and <italic>Spizelloides</italic>) are added as a result of splits from other genera, resulting in changes to 10 scientific names (<italic>Rupornis magnirostris</italic>, <italic>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</italic>, <italic>Cryptopipo holochlora</italic>, <italic>Akialoa obscura</italic>, <italic>A. ellisiana</italic>, <italic>Chlorodrepanis virens</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. flava</named-content></italic>, <italic>C. stejnegeri</italic>, <italic>Viridonia sagittirostris</italic>, and <italic>Spizelloides arborea</italic>); (9) one genus (<italic>Vestiaria</italic>) is lost by merger (into <italic>Drepanis</italic>) and the scientific name of one species (<italic>D. coccinea</italic>) is thereby changed; (10) the citation for one species (<italic>Pterodroma solandri</italic>) is corrected; and (11) two species (<italic>Anthropoides virgo</italic> and <italic>Grus monacha</italic>) are added to the Appendix. In addition, the English name of one species is transferred to another scientific name in the aftermath of a taxonomic change: Thus, Herald Petrel is now the English name for <italic>Pterodroma heraldica</italic> rather than for <italic>P. arminjoniana</italic>.One new subfamily of Falconiformes is added and two subfamilies are deleted, one new family and three new subfamilies of Psittaciformes are added and two subfamilies are deleted, and one new subfamily is added to the Pipridae. New linear sequences are adopted for genera in the family Thraupidae and in the Hawaiian honeycreepers (Carduelinae, in part), and for species in the <italic>Buteo</italic> group (Accipitridae, in part) and in the genera <italic>Ramphocelus</italic> and <italic>Sporophila</italic>, all due to new phylogenetic data. The family placements of 22 genera (<italic>Volatinia</italic>, <italic>Sporophila</italic>, <italic>Melopyrrha</italic>, <italic>Tiaris</italic>, <italic>Loxipasser</italic>, <italic>Loxigilla</italic>, <italic>Euneornis</italic>, <italic>Melanospiza</italic>, <italic>Pinaroloxias</italic>, <italic>Haplospiza</italic>, <italic>Acanthidops</italic>, <italic>Diglossa</italic>, <italic>Sicalis</italic>, <italic>Emberizoides</italic>, <italic>Saltator</italic>, <italic>Coereba</italic>, <italic>Nesospingus</italic>, <italic>Phaenicophilus</italic>, <italic>Calyptophilus</italic>, <italic>Rhodinocichla</italic>, <italic>Mitrospingus</italic>, and <italic>Spindalis</italic>) are changed on the basis of new information on their phylogenetic relationships.Literature that provides the basis for the Committee's decisions is cited at the end of this supplement, and citations not already in the Literature Cited of the 7th edition (with supplements) become additions to it. A list of the bird species known from the AOU <italic>Check-list</italic> area can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://checklist.aou.org/taxa" xlink:type="simple">http://checklist.aou.org/taxa</ext-link>.The following changes to the 7th edition (page numbers refer thereto) and its supplements result from the Committee's actions:pp. xvii&ndash;liv. Change the number in the title of the list of species to 2,116. Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:<italic><bold>Alopochen aegyptiaca</bold></italic> Egyptian Goose. (I)<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria irrorata</named-content></bold></italic> Waved Albatross. (A)<italic><bold>Pterodroma madeira</bold></italic> Zino's Petrel. (A)<italic><bold>Pterodroma heraldica</bold></italic> Herald Petrel. (A)<italic><bold>Pterodroma arminjoniana</bold></italic> Trindade Petrel.<italic><bold>Puffinus newelli</bold></italic> Newell's Shearwater.<italic><bold>Syrigma sibilatrix</bold></italic> Whistling Heron. (A)<italic><bold>Rupornis magnirostris</bold></italic> Roadside Hawk.<italic><bold>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</bold></italic> White-tailed Hawk.<italic><bold>Patagioenas goodsoni</bold></italic> Dusky Pigeon. (A)<italic><bold>Leptotila cassinii</bold></italic> Gray-chested Dove.<italic><bold>Phaethornis mexicanus</bold></italic> Mexican Hermit.<italic><bold>Calliphlox lyrura</bold></italic> Inagua Woodstar.<italic><bold>Amazilia saucerottei</bold></italic> Steely-vented Hummingbird.<bold>Herpetotherinae</bold><bold>PSITTACULIDAE</bold><bold>Psittaculinae</bold><bold>Agapornithinae</bold><bold>Loriinae</bold><italic><bold>Cranioleuca dissita</bold></italic> Coiba Spinetail.<bold>Piprinae</bold><italic><bold>Cryptopipo holochlora</bold></italic> Green Manakin.<italic><bold>Campylorhynchus griseus</bold></italic> Bicolored Wren.<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</named-content></bold></italic> Common Redstart. (A)<italic><bold>Spizelloides arborea</bold></italic> American Tree Sparrow.<italic><bold>Drepanis coccinea</bold></italic> Iiwi. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Himatione fraithii</bold></italic> Laysan Honeycreeper. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus hanapepe</bold></italic> Kauai Nukupuu. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Hemignathus lucidus</bold></italic> Oahu Nukupuu. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus affinis</bold></italic> Maui Nukupuu. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus wilsoni</bold></italic> Akiapolaau. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Akialoa obscura</bold></italic> Lesser Akialoa. (H)<italic><bold>Akialoa stejnegeri</bold></italic> Kauai Akialoa. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Akialoa ellisiana</bold></italic> Oahu Akialoa. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Akialoa lanaiensis</bold></italic> Maui-nui Akialoa. (H)<italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis virens</bold></italic> Hawaii Amakihi. (H)<italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis flava</bold></italic> Oahu Amakihi. (H)<italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</bold></italic> Kauai Amakihi. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Viridonia sagittirostris</bold></italic> Greater Amakihi. (H)<italic><bold>Loxops wolstenholmei</bold></italic> Oahu Akepa. (H)<italic><bold>Loxops ochraceus</bold></italic> Maui Akepa. (H)<italic><bold>Loxops coccineus</bold></italic> Hawaii Akepa. (H)Delete the following names:<italic><bold>Pterodroma arminjoniana</bold></italic> Herald Petrel. (A)<italic><bold>Buteo magnirostris</bold></italic> Roadside Hawk.<italic><bold>Buteo albicaudatus</bold></italic> White-tailed Hawk.<italic><bold>Leptotila cassini</bold></italic> Gray-chested Dove.<italic><bold>Amazilia saucerrottei</bold></italic> Steely-vented Hummingbird.<bold>Micrasturinae</bold><bold>Caracarinae</bold><bold>Platycercinae</bold><bold>Psittacinae</bold><italic><bold>Cranioleuca vulpina</bold></italic> Rusty-backed Spinetail.<italic><bold>Xenopipo holochlora</bold></italic> Green Manakin.<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella arborea</named-content></bold></italic> American Tree Sparrow.<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus virens</named-content></bold></italic> Hawaii Amakihi. (H)<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus flavus</named-content></bold></italic> Oahu Amakihi. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus kauaiensis</bold></italic> Kauai Amakihi. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Hemignathus sagittirostris</bold></italic> Greater Amakihi. (H)&dagger;<italic><bold>Hemignathus obscurus</bold></italic> Lesser Akialoa. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus ellisianus</bold></italic> Greater Akialoa. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus lucidus</bold></italic> Nukupuu. (H)<italic><bold>Hemignathus munroi</bold></italic> Akiapolaau. (H)<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vestiaria coccinea</named-content></bold></italic> Iiwi. (H)<italic><bold>Loxops coccineus</bold></italic> Akepa. (H)Change the sequence of species from <italic><bold>Morphnarchus</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Buteo</bold></italic> to:<italic><bold>Morphnarchus princeps</bold></italic><italic><bold>Rupornis magnirostris</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parabuteo unicinctus</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Pseudastur albicollis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Leucopternis semiplumbeus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo plagiatus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo nitidus</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo lineatus</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo ridgwayi</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo platypterus</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo solitarius</bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo brachyurus</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold>Buteo albonotatus</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo jamaicensis</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo lagopus</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></bold></italic>Move <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Herpetotheres cachinnans</named-content></bold></italic> to follow subfamily <bold>Herpetotherinae.</bold>Move <italic><bold>Psittacula krameri</bold></italic> to follow subfamily <bold>Psittaculinae</bold>, move <italic><bold>Agapornis roseicollis</bold></italic> to follow subfamily <bold>Agapornithinae</bold>, and move <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melopsittacus undulatus</named-content></bold></italic> to follow subfamily <bold>Loriinae</bold>.Change the sequence of genera in the <bold>PIPRIDAE</bold> to:<italic><bold>Chiroxiphia</bold></italic><italic><bold>Corapipo</bold></italic><italic><bold>Cryptopipo</bold></italic><italic><bold>Lepidothrix</bold></italic><italic><bold>Manacus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Dixiphia</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ceratopipra</bold></italic>Transfer <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Coereba flaveola</named-content></bold></italic>, the six species of <italic><bold>Saltator</bold></italic>, <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Volatinia jacarina</named-content></bold></italic>, the nine species of <italic><bold>Sporophila</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Melopyrrha nigra</bold></italic>, the three species of <italic><bold>Tiaris</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Loxipasser anoxanthus</bold></italic>, the four species of <italic><bold>Loxigilla</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Euneornis campestris</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Melanospiza richardsoni</bold></italic>, <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinaroloxias inornata</named-content></bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Haplospiza rustica</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Acanthidops bairdi</bold></italic>, the two species of <italic><bold>Diglossa</bold></italic>, the two species of <italic><bold>Sicalis</bold></italic>, and <italic><bold>Emberizoides herbicola</bold></italic>, arranged according to the linear sequence below, to the family <bold>THRAUPIDAE</bold>.Transfer <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nesospingus speculiferus</named-content></bold></italic>, the two species of <italic><bold>Phaenicophilus</bold></italic>, the two species of <italic><bold>Calyptophilus</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Rhodinocichla rosea</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Mitrospingus cassinii</bold></italic>, and the four species of <italic><bold>Spindalis</bold></italic>, in this sequence, to <bold>Genera</bold> <italic><bold>INCERTAE SEDIS</bold></italic> following <italic><bold>Saltator striatipectus</bold></italic>.Change the sequence of genera in the <bold>THRAUPIDAE</bold> to:<italic><bold>Bangsia</bold></italic><italic><bold>Paroaria</bold></italic><italic><bold>Thraupis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Tangara</bold></italic><italic><bold>Conirostrum</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sicalis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Haplospiza</bold></italic><italic><bold>Acanthidops</bold></italic><italic><bold>Diglossa</bold></italic><italic><bold>Chlorophanes</bold></italic><italic><bold>Chrysothlypis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Heterospingus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Hemithraupis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Volatinia</bold></italic><italic><bold>Eucometis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Tachyphonus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Lanio</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ramphocelus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Tersina</bold></italic><italic><bold>Cyanerpes</bold></italic><italic><bold>Dacnis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Coereba</bold></italic><italic><bold>Tiaris</bold></italic><italic><bold>Euneornis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Loxigilla</bold></italic><italic><bold>Melopyrrha</bold></italic><italic><bold>Loxipasser</bold></italic><italic><bold>Melanospiza</bold></italic><italic><bold>Pinaroloxias</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila</bold></italic><italic><bold>Emberizoides</bold></italic><italic><bold>Saltator</bold></italic>Change the sequence of species in <italic><bold>Ramphocelus</bold></italic> to:<italic><bold>Ramphocelus sanguinolentus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ramphocelus flammigerus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ramphocelus passerinii</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ramphocelus costaricensis</bold></italic><italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ramphocelus dimidiatus</named-content></bold></italic>Change the sequence of species in <italic><bold>Sporophila</bold></italic> to:<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila funerea</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila crassirostris</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila nuttingi</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila corvina</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila schistacea</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila torqueola</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila nigricollis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Sporophila minuta</bold></italic>Change the sequence of genera from <italic><bold>Telespiza</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Melamprosops</bold></italic> to:<italic><bold>Melamprosops</bold></italic><italic><bold>Oreomystis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Paroreomyza</bold></italic><italic><bold>Loxioides</bold></italic><italic><bold>Telespiza</bold></italic><italic><bold>Chloridops</bold></italic><italic><bold>Rhodacanthis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Ciridops</bold></italic><italic><bold>Palmeria</bold></italic><italic><bold>Himatione</bold></italic><italic><bold>Drepanis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Psittirostra</bold></italic><italic><bold>Dysmorodrepanis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Pseudonestor</bold></italic><italic><bold>Hemignathus</bold></italic><italic><bold>Akialoa</bold></italic><italic><bold>Magumma</bold></italic><italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis</bold></italic><italic><bold>Viridonia</bold></italic><italic><bold>Loxops</bold></italic>p. 12. After the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria nigripes</named-content></italic>, insert the following new species account:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Diomedea irrorata</named-content></italic> Salvin, 1883, Proc. Zool. Soc. London, p. 430. (Callao Bay, Peru.)Pelagic Waters; breeds on islands.<italic>Breeds</italic> on Hood Island (Gal&aacute;pagos Islands) and on Isla de la Plata off Ecuador.<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea near the coasts of Ecuador and Peru.Accidental in Costa Rica (Cabo Blanco, Puntarenas, 9 January 2014; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-ObandoCalderon1">Obando-Calder&oacute;n et al. 2014</xref>). Sight reports from Panama, west of Pi&ntilde;as Bay, Dari&eacute;n, 26 February 1941 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgely1">Ridgely 1976</xref>), and southwest of the Pearl Islands, 27 September 1964 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgely2">Ridgely and Gwynne 1989</xref>).Also known as Galapagos Albatross.p. 13. The citation for <italic>Pterodroma solandri</italic>, which was transferred from the Appendix to the main list in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Chesser1">Chesser et al. (2013)</xref>, is corrected following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-McAllan1">McAllan (2004)</xref> to:<italic>Procellaria Solandri</italic> Gould, 1844, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist. 13:363. (Bass's Straits &equals; Bass Strait.)p. 13. <italic>Pterodroma heraldica</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic>P. arminjoniana</italic>. In the species account for <italic>P. arminjoniana</italic>, change the English name to Trindade Petrel, and change the distributional statement and Notes to:<italic>Breeds</italic> on islands in the South Atlantic (Trindade, Martin Vas Rocks) and Indian Ocean (Round Island off Mauritius).<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea generally in the South Atlantic near the breeding grounds and into the subtropical North Atlantic, regularly off North Carolina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell2">Howell 2012</xref>).Casual or accidental from New York (near Ithaca; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Allen1">Allen 1934</xref>) south to Virginia (including inland records), in Puerto Rico (Cayo Lobito, Culebra National Wildlife Refuge; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Gochfield1">Gochfeld et al. 1988</xref>), northeast of the Lesser Antilles (lat. 21&deg;51&prime;N, long. 43&deg;35&prime;W), and in England.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>P. heraldica</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. atrata</named-content></italic> Mathews, 1912 &lsqb;Henderson Petrel&rsqb;, but the three are treated as separate species on the basis of assortative mating on islands where they breed in sympatry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Brooke1">Brooke and Rowe 1996</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Brown1">Brown et al. &lsqb;2010&rsqb;</xref> for hybridization in secondary contact on Round Island).After the species account for <italic>P. arminjoniana</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Oestrelata heraldica</italic> Salvin, 1888, Ibis, p. 357. (Chesterfield Islands, western Pacific.)Pelagic Waters; nests on islands on bare rock under overhanging ledges or plants.<italic>Breeds</italic> on islands in the tropical South Pacific.<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea in the South Pacific near the breeding grounds.Accidental in the Hawaiian Islands (French Frigate Shoals, 14 March 1968; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amerson1">Amerson 1971</xref>:125), with additional sight reports near Clipperton Island and north to the Revillagigedo Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell6">Howell and Webb 1995</xref>).See Notes under <italic>Pterodroma arminjoniana</italic>.p. 16. After the species account for <italic>Pterodroma feae</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Pterodroma mollis madeira</italic> Mathews, 1934, Bull. Brit. Ornithol. Club 54:179. (Madeira.)Pelagic Waters; nests in burrows at highest elevations on Madeira.<italic>Breeds</italic> on Madeira, where critically endangered.<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea in waters around Madeira, also recorded around the Azores. Geolocator data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Zino1">Zino et al. (2011)</xref> showed birds ranging widely in the northeastern Atlantic during the breeding season; during the nonbreeding season they were mostly found off western Africa, along the Mid-Atlantic Ridge to St. Helena, and off Brazil.Accidental off North Carolina (Hatteras, 16 September 1995; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell2">Howell 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Flood1">Flood and Fisher 2013</xref>).See Notes under <italic>Pterodroma feae</italic>.p. 21. <italic>Puffinus newelli</italic> is considered a species separate from <italic>P. auricularis</italic>. In the species account for <italic>P. auricularis</italic>, replace the distributional statement and existing Notes with the following:<italic>Breeds</italic> in the Revillagigedo Islands (Socorro and, at least formerly, Clarion and San Benedicto), off western Mexico.<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea from Baja California south to Clipperton Island, west to long. ~121&deg;W, and along the coast of Mexico south to Oaxaca; sight reports from California and from Oaxaca southward require confirmation.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>P. newelli</italic>, but treated as a separate species on the basis of differences in plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell5">Howell et al. 1994</xref>), morphology and breeding chronology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ainley1">Ainley et al. 1997</xref>), and feeding ecology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Spear1">Spear et al. 1995</xref>) comparable to or greater than the differences among other valid species of small shearwater (and despite apparent similarity in mitochondrial DNA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-MartinezGomez1">Mart&iacute;nez-G&oacute;mez et al. 2015</xref>).After the species account for <italic>Puffinus auricularis</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Puffinus newelli</italic> Henshaw, 1900, Auk 17:246. (Waihee Valley, Ulani &equals; Maui.)Pelagic Waters; nests in burrows on oceanic islands.<italic>Breeds</italic> in the Hawaiian Islands on Kauai (possibly also on other main islands).<italic>Ranges</italic> at sea primarily near the Hawaiian Islands.Accidental in the Marianas, American Samoa, and California (Del Mar, San Diego County, 1 August 2007; specimen; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Unitt1">Unitt et al. 2009</xref>).The relationship of <italic>newelli</italic> to the extralimital <italic>P. myrtae</italic> Bourne, 1959 &lsqb;Rapa Shearwater&rsqb; is unresolved, and we tentatively consider them separate species pending additional data. See Notes under <italic>P. auricularis</italic>.p. 41. After the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mesophoyx intermedia</named-content></italic>, insert the following heading and new account:<italic>Syrigma</italic> Ridgway, 1878, Bull. U.S. Geol. Geogr. Surv. Territories, 4, pp. 224, 247. Type, by original designation, <italic>Ardea sibilatrix</italic> Temminck.<italic>Ardea sibilatrix</italic> Temminck, 1824, Planches Color., livr. 46, pl. 271. (Brazil and Paraguay.)Low Seasonally Wet Grasslands, Freshwater Marshes, Pastures/Agricultural Lands.Orinoco basin and llanos of Colombia and Venezuela and disjunctly from northern Bolivia east to southeastern Brazil and south to Buenos Aires Province, Argentina.Accidental or casual in Panama (near Portobelo, Col&oacute;n, 27 February 2010, photos; near Chepo, eastern Panam&aacute; province, 11 July 2013 and probably the same bird intermittently to 11 October 2014, photos, North American Birds 67:256&ndash;258; near Gorgona, western Panam&aacute; province, 15 July 2014, intermittently to at least 13 January 2015, photos; and near El Rinc&oacute;n, Herrera, 20 July 2014, photos).p. 61. After the species account for <italic>Neochen jubata</italic>, insert the following heading and new account:<italic>Alopochen</italic> Stejneger, 1885, in Kingsley, Standard Nat. Hist., 4, p. 141. Type, by subsequent designation (Oberholser, 1918, Journ. Washington Acad. Sci. 8:572), <italic>Anas aegyptiaca</italic> Linnaeus.<italic><bold>Alopochen aegyptiaca</bold></italic> (Linnaeus). Egyptian Goose.&emsp;<italic>Anas aegyptiaca</italic> Linnaeus, 1766, Syst. Nat., ed. 12, 1:197. (Egypt.)In subtropical Africa, inland freshwater rivers and near lakes and pools; in Florida and Europe, where introduced, managed habitats with aquatic features (parks, golf courses, etc.).<italic>Resident</italic> in Africa south of the Sahara, and north along the Nile to about Aswan Dam, Egypt. Some northward movement during the wet season. Formerly, until early 18th century, found north to the Danube Valley in southern Hungary and Romania.Casual north to Israel, Cyprus, Malta, and the Red Sea coast of Arabia.Introduced in Martin County, Florida, in 1993&ndash;1994, and now established in southeast Florida (~1,200 birds as of 2012&ndash;2013; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pranty2">Pranty and Ponzo 2014</xref>). A small population is present in Orange County, California, and scattered individuals have been noted elsewhere in North America. Also introduced and established in parts of western Europe, notably Great Britain and The Netherlands.pp. 96&ndash;103. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amaral1">Raposo do Amaral et al. 2009</xref>) has shown that the generic limits and linear sequence of species currently placed in the genera <italic>Morphnarchus</italic>, <italic>Parabuteo</italic>, <italic>Pseudastur</italic>, <italic>Leucopternis</italic>, and <italic>Buteo</italic> do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:After the account for <italic>Morphnarchus princeps</italic>, insert the following heading:<italic>Rupornis</italic> Kaup, 1844, Class. S&auml;ugethiere V&ouml;gel, p. 120. Type, by monotypy, <italic>Falco magnirostris</italic> Gmelin.&emsp;Change <italic><bold>Buteo magnirostris</bold></italic> (Gmelin) to <italic><bold>Rupornis magnirostris</bold></italic> (Gmelin), place the account for this species under the heading and citation for <italic>Rupornis</italic>, and substitute the following for the Notes at the end of the species account:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Buteo</italic>, but genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amaral1">Raposo do Amaral et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that <italic>R. magnirostris</italic> is sister to all other species in the <italic>Buteo</italic> group other than <italic>Morphnarchus princeps</italic>, and not closely related to true <italic>Buteo</italic>.After the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parabuteo unicinctus</named-content></italic>, insert the following heading:<italic>Geranoaetus</italic> Kaup, 1844, Class. S&auml;ugethiere V&ouml;gel, p. 122. Type, by monotypy, <italic>Falco aguja</italic> Temminck &equals; <italic>Spizaetus melanoleucus</italic> Vieillot.&emsp;Change <italic><bold>Buteo albicaudatus</bold></italic> Vieillot to <italic><bold>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</bold></italic> (Vieillot), place the account for this species under the heading and citation for <italic>Geranoaetus</italic>, and insert the following Notes at the end of the species account:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Buteo</italic>, but genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amaral1">Raposo do Amaral et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that this species forms a clade with extralimital species <italic>Geranoaetus melanoleucus</italic> (Vieillot, 1819) &lsqb;Black-chested Buzzard-Eagle&rsqb; and Appendix species <italic>G</italic>. (formerly <italic>Buteo</italic>) <italic>polyosoma</italic> (Quoy and Gaimard, 1824) &lsqb;Variable Hawk&rsqb;.Rearrange the sequence of species from <italic>Morphnarchus princeps</italic> to <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo lagopus</named-content></italic> to:<italic>Morphnarchus princeps</italic><italic>Rupornis magnirostris</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parabuteo unicinctus</named-content></italic><italic>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</italic><italic>Pseudastur albicollis</italic><italic>Leucopternis semiplumbeus</italic><italic>Buteo plagiatus</italic><italic>Buteo nitidus</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo lineatus</named-content></italic><italic>Buteo ridgwayi</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo platypterus</named-content></italic><italic>Buteo solitarius</italic><italic>Buteo brachyurus</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></italic><italic>Buteo albonotatus</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo jamaicensis</named-content></italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo lagopus</named-content></italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>Add the following Notes under the heading Genus <bold><italic>BUTEOGALLUS</italic></bold> Lesson (p. 97): Linear sequence of genera from <italic>Buteogallus</italic> through <italic>Buteo</italic> follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amaral1">Raposo et al. (2009)</xref>.pp. 107&ndash;111. Phylogenetic analysis of syringeal morphological characters and mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Griffiths1">Griffiths 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Griffiths2">Griffiths et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Fuchs1">Fuchs et al. 2012</xref>) indicate that our current subfamily classification of the Falconiformes does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Delete the headings Subfamily MICRASTURINAE: Forest-Falcons, Subfamily CARACARINAE: Caracaras, Tribe Herpetotherini: Laughing Falcons, and Tribe Falconini: True Falcons.Delete the existing Notes under the heading Family <bold>FALCONIDAE</bold> and insert the following:Subfamily arrangement follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Griffiths1">Griffiths (1999)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Griffiths2">Griffiths et al. (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Fuchs1">Fuchs et al. (2012)</xref>.After the heading and Notes for Family <bold>FALCONIDAE</bold>: Caracaras and Falcons, insert the following new heading:Subfamily HERPETOTHERINAE: Laughing Falcon and Forest-FalconsMove the heading and citation for Genus <italic><bold>HERPETOTHERES</bold></italic> Vieillot and the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Herpetotheres cachinnans</named-content></italic> to follow this heading.Change the heading Subfamily FALCONINAE: Falcons to Subfamily FALCONINAE: Caracaras and Falcons, and move this heading to follow the species account for <italic>Micrastur semitorquatus</italic>.p. 181. <italic>Stercorarius antarcticus</italic> is considered a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. skua</named-content></italic>. Replace the distributional statement and Notes in the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. skua</named-content></italic> with the following:<italic>Breeds</italic> in Iceland, the Faeroe, Shetland and Orkney islands, locally on the northern Scotland mainland, Svelbard, Norway, and Kola Peninsula, Russia.<italic>Winters</italic> at sea in the eastern North Atlantic, from lat. 60&deg;N south to the Tropic of Cancer, regularly on the Newfoundland Banks and off the coast from Nova Scotia to North Carolina, and rarely to the Canary Islands, the Mediterranean Sea, and off northeastern South America (Guyana, French Guiana, and Brazil).Accidental in Belize (Ambergris Cay), Guyana, Novaya Zemlya, and continental Europe.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. antarcticus</named-content></italic> (including <italic>S. lonnbergi</italic>), but treated as a separate species on the basis of phenotypic differences commensurate with or greater than those found in reproductively isolated sympatric congeners in the Southern Hemisphere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Furness1">Furness 1996</xref>).p. 221. After the species account for <italic>Patagioenas nigrirostris</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Patagioenas goodsoni</bold></italic> (Hartert). Dusky Pigeon.<italic>Columba goodsoni</italic> Hartert, 1902, Bull. Brit. Ornithol. Club 12:42. (San Javier, Pambilar, and Carondelet, n.w. Ecuador &equals; Pambila, Ecuador.)Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest, Montane Evergreen Forest (0&ndash;1,000 m).<italic>Resident</italic> in western Colombia and western Ecuador.Accidental or casual in eastern Panama near the Colombian border (near Hito Palo de las Letras, Dari&eacute;n, 28 December 2012; photos and video; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-CamposCedeno1">Campos-Cede&ntilde;o and Vallely 2014</xref>). Additional sight reports from this area in upper Tuila Valley, Dari&eacute;n, 7 March 1981 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgely2">Ridgely and Gwynne 1989</xref>), and on trail to Cerro Pirre above Cana, Dari&eacute;n, 17 April 1992 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Angehr1">Angehr et al. 2006</xref>).See comments under <italic>P. nigrirostris</italic>.p. 229. The name <italic>Leptotila cassini</italic> is corrected to <italic>Leptotila cassinii</italic>, in accordance with the spelling of the name in the original description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Lawrence1">Lawrence 1867</xref>), <italic>contra</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgway2">Ridgway (1916)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Peters1">Peters (1937)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Sibley1">Sibley and Monroe (1990)</xref>.pp. 232&ndash;245. Molecular, paleontological, and morphological evidence (summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Joseph1">Joseph et al. 2012</xref>) indicate that our current family and subfamily classification of the Psittaciformes does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Delete the existing Notes under the heading Order <bold>PSITTACIFORMES</bold>: Parrots, transfer the existing Notes for Family PSITTACIDAE: Lories, Parakeets, Macaws, and Parrots to Order <bold>PSITTACIFORMES</bold>: Parrots, and add the following to the end of these newly added Notes: Family and subfamily arrangement follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Joseph1">Joseph et al. (2012)</xref>.Change the heading Family <bold>PSITTACIDAE</bold>: Lories, Parakeets, Macaws, and Parrots to:Move the heading Subfamily ARINAE: New World Parakeets, Macaws, and Parrots and its included genera and species to follow this family heading.Delete the headings Subfamily PLATYCERCINAE: Australian Parrots and Rosellas and Subfamily PSITTACINAE: Typical Parrots.After the species account for <italic>Amazona imperialis</italic>, insert the following new headings:Family <bold>PSITTACULIDAE</bold>: Lories, Lovebirds, and Indomalayan and Papua-Australian ParrotsSubfamily PSITTACULINAE: Indomalayan and Papua-Australian ParrotsMove the heading and citation for Genus <italic><bold>PSITTACULA</bold></italic> Cuvier and the species account for <italic><bold>Psittacula krameri</bold></italic> to follow this heading.After the species account for <italic>Psittacula krameri</italic>, insert the following new heading:Subfamily AGAPORNITHINAE: Lovebirds and Hanging-ParrotsMove the heading and citation for Genus <italic><bold>AGAPORNIS</bold></italic> Selby and the species account for <italic><bold>Agapornis roseicollis</bold></italic> to follow this heading.After the species account for <italic>Agapornis roseicollis</italic>, insert the following new heading:Subfamily LORIINAE: Lories and AlliesMove the heading and citation for Genus <italic><bold>MELOPSITTACUS</bold></italic> Selby and the species account for <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melopsittacus undulatus</named-content></bold></italic> to follow this heading.p. 283. <italic>Phaethornis mexicanus</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. longirostris</named-content></italic>. In the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. longirostris</named-content></italic>, change the distributional statement and Notes to:<italic>Resident</italic> &lsqb;<italic>longirostris</italic> group&rsqb; on the Gulf-Caribbean slope from Veracruz, Tabasco, northern Oaxaca, and northern Chiapas south through Central America to Nicaragua, on both slopes of Costa Rica and Panama, and in northern Colombia and northwestern Venezuela; and &lsqb;<italic>baroni</italic> group&rsqb; in South America west of the Andes in western Ecuador and northwestern Peru.Groups: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. longirostris</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. baroni</italic> Hartert, 1897 &lsqb;Hartert's Hermit&rsqb;. Formerly considered conspecific with extralimital <italic>P. superciliosus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1766) &lsqb;Long-tailed Hermit&rsqb;, but separated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Banks1">Banks et al. 2002</xref>) largely on morphological grounds. See Notes under <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. mexicanus</named-content></italic>.Before the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. longirostris</named-content></italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Phaethornis mexicanus</bold></italic> Hartert. Mexican Hermit.<italic>Pha&euml;thornis mexicanus</italic> Hartert, 1897, Ibis, p. 425. (Dos Arroyos, near Chilpancingo, Guerrero.)Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest, Montane Evergreen Forest (100&ndash;1,900 m; Tropical and Subtropical zones).<italic>Resident</italic> &lsqb;<italic>griseoventer</italic> group&rsqb; in western Mexico from west-central Nayarit (near Tepic and San Blas) south to Jalisco (Sierra de Autl&aacute;n, Mineral San Sebastian) and Colima (Cerro Grande); and &lsqb;<italic>mexicanus</italic> group&rsqb; in Guerrero and western Oaxaca.Groups: <italic>P. griseoventer</italic> Phillips, 1962 &lsqb;Jalisco Hermit&rsqb; and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. mexicanus</named-content></italic>. Formerly considered conspecific with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. longirostris</named-content></italic>, but treated as a separate species on the basis of differences in vocalizations, behavior, genetics, and morphology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-ArbelaezCortes1">Arbel&aacute;ez-Cort&eacute;s and Navarro-Sig&uuml;enza 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell3">Howell 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-McGuire1">McGuire et al. 2014</xref>).p. 299. The name <italic>Amazilia saucerrottei</italic> is corrected to <italic>Amazilia saucerottei</italic>. The name in the original description (<italic>saucerrottei</italic>) was a misspelling of Saucerotte, the person for whom the species was named (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Delattre1">Delattre and Bourcier 1846</xref>). This inadvertent error must be corrected under the rules of the <italic>Code of Zoological Nomenclature</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-InternationalCommissiononZoologicalNomenclature1">International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature 1999</xref>, Article 32.5.1).p. 307. <italic>Calliphlox lyrura</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic>C. evelynae</italic>. In the species account for <italic>C. evelynae</italic>, change the habitat and distributional statements and Notes to:Pine Forest, Second-growth Scrub, Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest Edge, and Arid Lowland Scrub.<italic>Resident</italic> throughout the Bahamas and Turks and Caicos, except Great and Little Inagua.Casual in southern Florida (Lantana, Homestead, Miami area).Sometimes placed in <italic>Philodice</italic> or <italic>Nesophlox</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgway1">Ridgway 1910</xref>) or merged into <italic>Calothorax</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell1">Howell 2002</xref>). Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>C. lyrura</italic>, but treated as a separate species (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgway1">Ridgway 1910</xref>) on the basis of differences in calls, songs, mechanical sounds, morphology, and genetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Feo1">Feo et al. 2015</xref>). English names for this species and for <italic>C. lyrura</italic> follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgway1">Ridgway (1910)</xref> as a temporary measure, pending a family-wide revision of English group names based on a complete phylogeny of the Trochilidae.After the species account for <italic>C. evelynae</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Calliphlox lyrura</bold></italic> (Gould). Inagua Woodstar.<italic>Doricha lyrura</italic> Gould, 1869, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist. 4:108&ndash;112. (Matthew Town, Great Inagua, Bahamas.)Second-growth Scrub, Riparian Thickets, and Arid Lowland Scrub.<italic>Resident</italic> on islands of Great and Little Inagua (Bahamas).Also called Lyre-tailed Hummingbird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Cory1">Cory 1880</xref>), Inaguan Hummingbird, or Inagua Lyretail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Feo1">Feo et al. 2015</xref>). See Notes under <italic>C. evelynae</italic>.p. 349. <italic>Cranioleuca dissita</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic>C. vulpina</italic>. Remove the species account for <italic>C. vulpina</italic> and replace it with the following new account:<italic><bold>Cranioleuca dissita</bold></italic> Wetmore. Coiba Spinetail.<italic>Cranioleuca vulpina dissita</italic> Wetmore, 1957, Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 134:55. (Isla Coiba, Panama.)Tropical Deciduous Forest.<italic>Resident</italic> on Isla Coiba, Panama.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>C. vulpina</italic> (Pelzeln, 1856) &lsqb;Rusty-backed Spinetail&rsqb;, but treated as separate on the basis of differences in vocalizations, genetics, and behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ridgely2">Ridgely and Gwynne 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2011</xref>).pp. 423&ndash;426. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ohlson1">Ohlson et al. 2013</xref>) has shown that the classification, generic limits, and linear sequence of genera in the family Pipridae do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Delete the existing Notes under the heading Family <bold>PIPRIDAE</bold>: Manakins and insert the following:Linear sequence of genera and species follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Rego1">R&ecirc;go et al. (2007)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tello1">Tello et al. (2009)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-McKay1">McKay et al. (2010)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ohlson1">Ohlson et al. (2013)</xref>.After the heading Family <bold>PIPRIDAE</bold>: Manakins, insert the following new heading:Subfamily PIPRINAE: Typical ManakinsAfter the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chiroxiphia linearis</named-content></italic>, replace the heading Genus <italic><bold>XENOPIPO</bold></italic> Cabanis and its citation and Notes with the following:Genus <italic><bold>CRYPTOPIPO</bold></italic> Ohlson et al.<italic>Cryptopipo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ohlson1">Ohlson, Fjelds&aring; and Ericson, 2013</xref>, Mol. Phylogenet. Evol. 69:802. Type, by original designation, <italic>Chloropipo holochlora</italic> Sclater.Change <italic><bold>Xenopipo holochlora</bold></italic> (Sclater) to <italic><bold>Cryptopipo holochlora</bold></italic> (Sclater), place the account for this species under the heading and citation for <italic>Cryptopipo</italic>, and replace the existing Notes with the following:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Xenopipo</italic>, but genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Ohlson1">Ohlson et al. 2013</xref>) indicate that <italic>C. holochlora</italic> is sister to the genus <italic>Lepidothrix</italic> and not closely related to true <italic>Xenopipo</italic>.Rearrange the genera in the family Pipridae in the following new sequence:<italic>Chiroxiphia</italic><italic>Corapipo</italic><italic>Cryptopipo</italic><italic>Lepidothrix</italic><italic>Manacus</italic><italic>Dixiphia</italic><italic>Ceratopipra</italic>p. 473. After the species account for <italic>Campylorhynchus chiapensis</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Campylorhynchus griseus</bold></italic> (Swainson). Bicolored Wren.<italic>Furnarius griseus</italic> Swainson, 1837, Anim. Menag., p. 325. (savannas of Guiana.)Lowland and Montane Arid Scrub, Tropical Deciduous Forest, Gallery Forest, and Tropical Lowland Forest Edge (0&ndash;2,100 m; Tropical and Subtropical zones).Northern Colombia and northern Venezuela locally south and east to extreme northern Brazil (Roraima) and southwestern Guyana.Casual breeder in eastern Panama (at least two individuals, including nesting birds, at Paya, Dari&eacute;n, 23&ndash;25 December 2012; photos; North American Birds 67:349&ndash;356; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-CamposCedeno1">Campos-Cede&ntilde;o and Vallely 2014</xref>). Vocal report from eastern Panama (Boca de Cupe, Dari&eacute;n, 28 December 2012; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-CamposCedeno1">Campos-Cede&ntilde;o and Vallely 2014</xref>).See Notes under <italic>C. chiapensis</italic>.p. 498. After the species account for <italic>Ficedula albicilla</italic>, insert the following heading and new account:<italic>Phoenicurus</italic> T. Forster, 1817. Synop. Cat. Br. Birds, p. 16. Type by monotypy and tautonymy &equals; <italic>Sylvia phoenicurus</italic> Latham et auct. &equals; <italic>Motacilla phoenicurus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758.<italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</named-content></bold></italic> (Linnaeus). Common Redstart.<italic>Motacilla Phoenicurus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758, Syst. Nat. ed. 10, 1, p. 187 (&ldquo;in Europa&rdquo; &equals; Sweden).Open woodland, parkland. Also scrublands in migration and winter.<italic>Breeds</italic> from the United Kingdom, western Europe, and northern Morocco, east to Iran and across Asia to northwest China and eastern Siberia (east to Lake Baikal).<italic>Winters</italic> from the southwest Arabian Peninsula and across central Africa south of the Sahara; in east Africa south to the north shore of Lake Victoria.Rare migrant to Iceland. Casual to Madeira, offshore Japan and the Kuril Islands.Accidental in Alaska (an immature male at St. Paul Island, Pribilofs, 8&ndash;9 October 2013; photos; North American Birds 68:167, 2014; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pranty1">Pranty et al. 2014</xref>).pp. 569&ndash;599. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) has shown that the composition and linear sequence of genera and species in the family Thraupidae do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Under the heading Family <bold>THRAUPIDAE</bold>: Tanagers, insert the following:Linear sequence of genera follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. (2014)</xref>.Remove the genus <italic>Coereba</italic>, its citation, and the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Coereba flaveola</named-content></italic> from genus <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic>, and position them in the Thraupidae in the linear sequence as indicated below. Delete the heading <bold>Genus</bold> <italic><bold>INCERTAE SEDIS</bold></italic>. After the citation for the genus, insert the following:Formerly placed in the monotypic family Coerebidae, but analysis of sequences of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that its correct placement is in the Thraupidae.Remove the genus <italic>Saltator</italic>, its citation, and its included species from genus <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic>, and place them in the Thraupidae in the linear sequence as indicated below. Delete the heading <bold>Genus</bold> <italic><bold>INCERTAE SEDIS</bold></italic>. Replace the first two sentences of the Notes for <italic>Saltator</italic> with the following: Formerly placed in the Cardinalidae, but analysis of sequences of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that its correct placement is in the Thraupidae.Delete the Notes under the heading Family <bold>EMBERIZIDAE</bold>: Emberizids.Remove the genus headings, citations, and included species for <italic>Volatinia</italic>, <italic>Sporophila</italic>, <italic>Melopyrrha</italic>, <italic>Tiaris</italic>, <italic>Loxipasser</italic>, <italic>Loxigilla</italic>, <italic>Euneornis</italic>, <italic>Melanospiza</italic>, <italic>Pinaroloxias</italic>, <italic>Haplospiza</italic>, <italic>Acanthidops</italic>, <italic>Diglossa</italic>, <italic>Sicalis</italic>, and <italic>Emberizoides</italic> from the Emberizidae and place them in the Thraupidae in the linear sequence as indicated below.Under the headings Genus <italic><bold>VOLATINIA</bold></italic> Reichenbach, Genus <italic><bold>MELOPYRRHA</bold></italic> Bonaparte, Genus <italic><bold>TIARIS</bold></italic> Swainson, Genus <italic><bold>LOXIPASSER</bold></italic> Bryant, Genus <italic><bold>LOXIGILLA</bold></italic> Lesson, Genus <italic><bold>MELANOSPIZA</bold></italic> Ridgway, Genus <italic><bold>PINAROLOXIAS</bold></italic> Sharpe, Genus <italic><bold>SICALIS</bold></italic> Boie, and Genus <italic><bold>EMBERIZOIDES</bold></italic> Temminck, insert the following:Formerly placed in the Emberizidae, but analysis of sequences of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that its correct placement is in the Thraupidae.Under the headings Genus <italic><bold>EUNEORNIS</bold></italic> Fitzinger, Genus <italic><bold>HAPLOSPIZA</bold></italic> Cabanis, and Genus <italic><bold>ACANTHIDOPS</bold></italic> Ridgway, replace the existing Notes with the following: Formerly placed in the Emberizidae, but analysis of sequences of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that its correct placement is in the Thraupidae.Under the headings Genus <italic><bold>SPOROPHILA</bold></italic> Cabanis and Genus <italic><bold>DIGLOSSA</bold></italic> Wagler, add the following to the beginning of the Notes: Formerly placed in the Emberizidae, but analysis of sequences of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that its correct placement is in the Thraupidae.Following the species account for <italic>Saltator striatipectus</italic>, insert the following new heading and Notes:<bold>Genera</bold> <italic><bold>INCERTAE SEDIS</bold></italic><italic>Nesospingus</italic>, <italic>Phaenicophilus</italic>, <italic>Calyptophilus</italic>, <italic>Rhodinocichla</italic>, <italic>Mitrospingus</italic>, and <italic>Spindalis</italic>, formerly placed in the Thraupidae, are part of the nine-primaried oscine radiation but do not belong to the Thraupidae or to any other traditionally recognized family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker2">2015</xref>). These taxa are placed as genera <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic> as a temporary measure, pending consideration of the classification of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Barker1">Barker et al. (2013)</xref>, who proposed that each genus be accorded family status (Nesospingidae, Phaenicophilidae, etc.).Move the genus headings and species accounts for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nesospingus speculiferus</named-content></italic>, the two species of <italic>Phaenicophilus</italic>, the two species of <italic>Calyptophilus</italic>, <italic>Rhodinocichla rosea</italic>, <italic>Mitrospingus cassinii</italic>, and the four species of <italic>Spindalis</italic>, in this linear sequence, from Thraupidae and insert them under this new heading.Under the headings Genus <italic><bold>NESOSPINGUS</bold></italic> Sclater, Genus <italic><bold>PHAENICOPHILUS</bold></italic> Strickland, Genus <italic><bold>CALYPTOPHILUS</bold></italic> Cory, and Genus <italic><bold>MITROSPINGUS</bold></italic> Ridgway insert:Formerly placed in the Thraupidae; see Notes under Genera <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic> above.Replace the existing Notes under the headings Genus <italic><bold>RHODINOCICHLA</bold></italic> Hartlaub and Genus <italic><bold>SPINDALIS</bold></italic> Jardine and Selby with: Formerly placed in the Thraupidae; see Notes under Genera <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic> above.Rearrange the sequence of genera in the Thraupidae to:<italic>Bangsia</italic><italic>Paroaria</italic><italic>Thraupis</italic><italic>Tangara</italic><italic>Conirostrum</italic><italic>Sicalis</italic><italic>Haplospiza</italic><italic>Acanthidops</italic><italic>Diglossa</italic><italic>Chlorophanes</italic><italic>Chrysothlypis</italic><italic>Heterospingus</italic><italic>Hemithraupis</italic><italic>Volatinia</italic><italic>Eucometis</italic><italic>Tachyphonus</italic><italic>Lanio</italic><italic>Ramphocelus</italic><italic>Tersina</italic><italic>Cyanerpes</italic><italic>Dacnis</italic><italic>Coereba</italic><italic>Tiaris</italic><italic>Euneornis</italic><italic>Loxigilla</italic><italic>Melopyrrha</italic><italic>Loxipasser</italic><italic>Melanospiza</italic><italic>Pinaroloxias</italic><italic>Sporophila</italic><italic>Emberizoides</italic><italic>Saltator</italic>Under the heading Genus <italic><bold>RAMPHOCELUS</bold></italic> Desmarest, insert the following:Linear sequence of species follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Burns1">Burns et al. (2014)</xref>.Rearrange the sequence of species in <italic>Ramphocelus</italic> to:<italic>Ramphocelus sanguinolentus</italic><italic>Ramphocelus flammigerus</italic><italic>Ramphocelus passerinii</italic><italic>Ramphocelus costaricensis</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ramphocelus dimidiatus</named-content></italic>Rearrange the sequence of species in <italic>Sporophila</italic> to:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></italic><italic>Sporophila funerea</italic><italic>Sporophila crassirostris</italic><italic>Sporophila nuttingi</italic><italic>Sporophila corvina</italic><italic>Sporophila schistacea</italic><italic>Sporophila torqueola</italic><italic>Sporophila nigricollis</italic><italic>Sporophila minuta</italic>p. 610. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2014</xref>) has shown that the genus <italic>Spizella</italic> is polyphyletic. Their findings result in the following changes:Move the heading Genus <italic><bold>SPIZELLA</bold></italic> Bonaparte and its citation to precede the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella passerina</named-content></italic>.After the species account for <italic>Torreornis inexpectata</italic>, insert the following heading and citation:<italic>Spizelloides</italic> Klicka and Slager, 2014, Zootaxa 3821:399. Type, by monotypy, <italic>Fringilla arborea</italic> Wilson.Change <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella arborea</named-content></bold></italic> (Wilson) to <italic><bold>Spizelloides arborea</bold></italic> (Wilson).Insert the following at the beginning of the Notes for <italic>Spizelloides arborea</italic>: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Spizella</italic>, but analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2014</xref>) indicates that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. arborea</named-content></italic> is not closely related to true <italic>Spizella</italic>.pp. 671&ndash;679. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Lerner1">Lerner et al. 2011</xref>) and a synthesis of molecular, morphological, and behavioral data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt5">Pratt 2014</xref>) have shown that the generic limits and linear sequence of genera in the Hawaiian honeycreepers do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Change <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vestiaria coccinea</named-content></bold></italic> (Forster) to <italic><bold>Drepanis coccinea</bold></italic> (Forster), delete the genus heading and Notes for <italic>Vestiaria</italic>, move the citation for <italic>Vestiaria</italic> into the synonymy of <italic>Drepanis</italic>, insert the species account for <italic>Drepanis coccinea</italic> to follow the heading and citation for <italic>Drepanis</italic>, and insert the following Notes at the end of the species account for <italic>Drepanis coccinea</italic>:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Vestiaria</italic>; see comments under <italic>Drepanis</italic>.Replace the existing Notes under the heading Genus <italic><bold>DREPANIS</bold></italic> Temminck with the following:<italic>Vestiaria</italic> and <italic>Drepanis</italic>, previously considered separate genera, are merged on the basis of morphological similarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt1">Pratt 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Olson1">Olson 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Knowlton1">Knowlton et al. 2014</xref>).Delete the Notes under Genus <italic><bold>HEMIGNATHUS</bold></italic> Lichtenstein and move the species accounts for <italic>Hemignathus lucidus</italic> and <italic>Hemignathus munroi</italic> to follow this heading and its citations.Change <italic><bold>Hemignathus munroi</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Hemignathus wilsoni</bold></italic> and substitute the following for the existing Notes:Formerly known as <italic>Hemignathus munroi</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt1">Pratt, 1979</xref>, due to priority of the name <italic>Heterorhynchus wilsoni</italic> Rothschild, 1893, when both taxa were included in <italic>Hemignathus</italic>.After the species account for <italic>Hemignathus wilsoni</italic>, insert the following heading:Genus <italic><bold>AKIALOA</bold></italic> Olson and JamesRemove the citation for this genus from the synonymy of <italic>Hemignathus</italic>, place it to follow this new heading, and insert the following:Formerly considered part of <italic>Hemignathus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>), but genetic and morphological data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tarr1">Tarr and Fleischer 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tarr2">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Fleischer1">Fleischer et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-James1">James 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Reding1">Reding et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Lerner1">Lerner et al. 2011</xref>) indicate that the expanded version of <italic>Hemignathus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt1">Pratt 1979</xref>) is not a monophyletic group.Change <italic><bold>Hemignathus obscurus</bold></italic> and <italic><bold>Hemignathus ellisianus</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Akialoa obscura</bold></italic> and <italic><bold>Akialoa ellisiana</bold></italic>, respectively, and place the accounts for these species under the heading and Notes for <italic>Akialoa</italic>.Replace the existing distributional statement and Notes for <italic>Akialoa obscura</italic> with the following:EXTINCT. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Hawaii (last collected in 1903, last sight report 1940) in the Hawaiian Islands.<italic>A. obscura</italic> and <italic>A. ellisiana sensu lato</italic> are sometimes treated as conspecific (e.g., Greenway <italic>in</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Paynter1">Paynter 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Olson2">Olson and James 1982</xref>), in which case <italic>A. obscura</italic> &lsqb;Akialoa&rsqb; is the appropriate name. See comments under <italic>A. stejnegeri</italic>.After the species account for <italic>Akialoa ellisiana</italic>, insert the following heading:<italic>Chlorodrepanis</italic> Wilson and Evans (ex Perkins MS), 1899, Aves Hawaiienses, p. xxi. Type, by subsequent designation (Richmond, 1902, Proc. U.S. Nat. Mus., 24, p. 673), <italic>Himatione stejnegeri</italic> Wilson.Change <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus virens</named-content></bold></italic>, <italic><bold><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus flavus</named-content></bold></italic>, and <italic><bold>Hemignathus kauaiensis</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis virens</bold></italic>, <italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis flava</bold></italic>, and <italic><bold>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</bold></italic>, respectively, and move the accounts for these species to follow the citation for <italic>Chlorodrepanis</italic>.Replace the existing Notes for <italic>Chlorodrepanis virens</italic> with the following:This species and the following two species, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. flava</named-content></italic> and <italic>C. stejnegeri</italic>, were formerly placed in the genus <italic>Hemignathus</italic>. They have also sometimes been placed, along with <italic>Viridonia sagittirostris</italic>, in <italic>Viridonia</italic> (e.g., Greenway <italic>in</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Paynter1">Paynter 1968</xref>) or in <italic>Loxops</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amadon1">Amadon 1947</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Amadon2">1950</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-James2">James and Olson 1991</xref>). The following two species have been considered conspecific with <italic>virens</italic> (e.g., Greenway <italic>in</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Paynter1">Paynter 1968</xref>), but are here considered separate species based on studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Johnson1">Johnson et al. (1989)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tarr1">Tarr and Fleischer (1993)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Johnson1">Johnson et al. (1989)</xref> showed that the group on Molokai, Maui, and Lanai (<italic>C. wilsoni</italic> Rothschild, 1893 &lsqb;Maui Amakihi&rsqb;) is genetically closest to <italic>virens</italic>.Replace the existing Notes for <italic>Chlorodrepanis flava</italic> with the following:See Notes under <italic>Chlorodrepanis virens<bold>.</bold></italic>Replace the existing Notes for <italic>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</italic> with the following:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Hemignathus</italic>. When included in <italic>Hemignathus</italic>, the species name <italic>stejnegeri</italic> is preoccupied by <italic>Hemignathus stejnegeri</italic> Wilson, 1889 &lsqb;Kauai Akialoa&rsqb;, and <italic>kauaiensis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt2">Pratt, 1989</xref> is used. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Conant1">Conant et al. (1998)</xref> for reasons for treating <italic>C. stejnegeri</italic> as a species.After the species account for <italic>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</italic>, insert the following heading:Genus <italic><bold>VIRIDONIA</bold></italic> RothschildRemove the citation for this genus from the synonymy of <italic>Hemignathus</italic>, place it to follow this new heading, change <italic><bold>Hemignathus sagittirostris</bold></italic> (Rothschild) to <italic><bold>Viridonia sagittirostris</bold></italic> Rothschild, move the account for this species to follow the citation, and change the Notes for this species to the following:Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Hemignathus</italic>, but genetic and morphological data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tarr1">Tarr and Fleischer 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Tarr2">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Fleischer1">Fleischer et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-James1">James 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Reding1">Reding et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Lerner1">Lerner et al. 2011</xref>) indicate that the expanded version of <italic>Hemignathus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt1">Pratt 1979</xref>) is not a monophyletic group.Rearrange the sequence of genera from <italic>Telespiza</italic> to <italic>Melamprosops</italic> to:<italic>Melamprosops</italic><italic>Oreomystis</italic><italic>Paroreomyza</italic><italic>Loxioides</italic><italic>Telespiza</italic><italic>Chloridops</italic><italic>Rhodacanthis</italic><italic>Ciridops</italic><italic>Palmeria</italic><italic>Himatione</italic><italic>Drepanis</italic><italic>Psittirostra</italic><italic>Dysmorodrepanis</italic><italic>Pseudonestor</italic><italic>Hemignathus</italic><italic>Akialoa</italic><italic>Magumma</italic><italic>Chlorodrepanis</italic><italic>Viridonia</italic><italic>Loxops</italic>Delete the existing Notes under Genus <bold><italic>LOXIOIDES</italic></bold> Oustalet, Genus <bold><italic>TELESPIZA</italic></bold> Wilson, Genus <bold><italic>CHLORIDOPS</italic></bold> Wilson, Genus <bold><italic>RHODACANTHIS</italic></bold> Rothschild, Genus <bold><italic>PSITTIROSTRA</italic></bold> Temminck, and Genus <bold><italic>DYSMORODREPANIS</italic></bold> Perkins, and replace the existing Notes under Genus <bold><italic>MELAMPROSOPS</italic></bold> Casey and Jacobi with the following:<bold>Notes.</bold>&mdash;<italic>Melamprosops</italic> and the following 19 genera constitute the Hawaiian honeycreepers, formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) considered to constitute the subfamily Drepanidinae. Linear sequence of these genera follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Lerner1">Lerner et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt5">Pratt (2014)</xref>.p. 675. <italic>Akialoa stejnegeri</italic> and <italic>A. lanaiensis</italic> are treated as species separate from <italic>A. ellisiana</italic>. In the species account for <italic>A. ellisiana</italic>, add a dagger (&dagger;) before the scientific name, change the English name to Oahu Akialoa, and change the distributional statement and Notes to:EXTINCT. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Oahu (last collected in 1837, last sight report 1939).See Notes under <italic>A. stejnegeri</italic>.Before the species account for <italic>A. ellisiana</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Hemignathus Stejnegeri</italic> Wilson, 1889, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist., ser. 6, 4, p. 400. (Kauai.)Humid montane forest.Probably extinct. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Kauai (Alakai plateau; last collected in 1960, last sight report 1965).Formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">AOU 1998</xref>) considered conspecific with <italic>A. ellisiana</italic> and <italic>A. lanaiensis</italic> (and previously also with <italic>obscura</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>), but these are treated as separate species on the basis of sympatry between some taxa in <italic>Akialoa</italic> and a lack of knowledge of relationships among these taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Olson3">Olson and James 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt5">Pratt 2014</xref>).After the species account for <italic>A. ellisiana</italic>, insert the following new account:&dagger;<italic><bold>Akialoa lanaiensis</bold></italic> (Rothschild). Maui-nui Akialoa.<italic>Hemignathus lanaiensis</italic> Rothschild, 1893, Bull. Brit. Ornithol. Club 1:24. (Lanai.)Humid montane forest.EXTINCT. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Lanai (last collected in 1892, last sight report 1894).See Notes under <italic>A. stejnegeri</italic>.p. 675. <italic>Hemignathus hanapepe</italic> and <italic>Hemignathus affinis</italic> are treated as species separate from <italic>H. lucidus</italic>. In the species account for <italic>H. lucidus</italic>, add a dagger (&dagger;) before the scientific name, change the English name to Oahu Nukupuu, and change the distributional statement and Notes to:EXTINCT. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Oahu (last collected in 1837, possible sight reports until 1860).See Notes under <italic>H. hanapepe</italic>.Before the species account for <italic>H. lucidus</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Hemignathus hanapepe</bold></italic> Wilson. Kauai Nukupuu.<italic>Hemignathus hanapepe</italic> Wilson, 1889, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist., ser. 6, 4, p. 401. (Kauai.)Humid montane forest, especially ohia and koa.Probably extinct. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Kauai (last collected in 1899, sight reports until 1990s in the Alakai plateau region).Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>H. lucidus</italic> and <italic>H. affinis</italic>, but treated as separate species on the basis of plumage differences commensurate with those observed among several other species groups of Hawaiian honeycreepers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt7">Pratt et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt6">Pratt and Pratt 2001</xref>).After the species account for <italic>H. lucidus</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Hemignathus affinis</bold></italic> Rothschild. Maui Nukupuu.Humid montane forest, especially ohia and koa.Possibly extinct, or <italic>resident</italic> locally in precarious numbers in the mountains of eastern Maui (windward slopes of Haleakala; last collected in 1896, last sight report 1996).See Notes under <italic>H. hanapepe</italic>.p. 677. <italic>Loxops wolstenholmei</italic> and <italic>Loxops ochraceus</italic> are treated as species separate from <italic>L. coccineus</italic>. In the species account for <italic>L. coccineus</italic>, change the English name to Hawaii Akepa, and change the habitat and distributional statements and Notes to:Humid montane forest, primarily ohia-koa and ohia.<italic>Resident</italic> in the mountains of Hawaii (rare and local).See Notes under <italic>L. wolstenholmei</italic>.Before the species account for <italic>L. coccineus</italic>, insert the following two new accounts, in this sequence:<italic><bold>Loxops wolstenholmei</bold></italic> Rothschild. Oahu Akepa.<italic>Loxops wolstenholmei</italic> Rothschild, 1893, Ibis, p. 570. (Oahu.)Humid montane forest, primarily ohia-koa and ohia.Probably extinct. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of Oahu (last collected in 1893, last sight report 1976).Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>Loxops coccineus</italic> and <italic>Loxops ochraceus</italic>, but treated as separate species on the basis of plumage and behavioral differences greater than those among the three species of amakihi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt4">Pratt 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt5">2014</xref>).<italic><bold>Loxops ochraceus</bold></italic> Rothschild. Maui Akepa.<italic>Loxops ochracea</italic> Rothschild, 1893, Ibis, p. 112. (Maui.)Humid montane forest, primarily ohia-koa and ohia.Probably extinct. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> in the mountains of eastern Maui (last collected ca. 1900, last sight report 1980).See Notes under <italic>L. wolstenholmei</italic>.p. 678. <italic>Himatione fraithii</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. sanguinea</named-content></italic>. In the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. sanguinea</named-content></italic>, change the habitat and distributional statements and Notes to:Humid montane forests, primarily ohia&ndash;koa, but occasionally in mixed native&ndash;exotic forest.<italic>Resident</italic> in the mountains in the Hawaiian Islands (all main islands from Kauai eastward).Accidental on Niihau.See Notes under <italic>H. fraithii</italic>.Before the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. sanguinea</named-content></italic>, insert the following new account:&dagger;<italic><bold>Himatione fraithii</bold></italic> Rothschild. Laysan Honeycreeper.<italic>Himatione fraithii</italic> Rothschild, 1892, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist., ser. 6, 10, p. 109. (Laysan.)Brushy areas and bunchgrass.EXTINCT. Formerly <italic>resident</italic> on Laysan Island (extinct since 1923).Formerly considered conspecific with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. sanguinea</named-content></italic>, but treated as a separate species on the basis of differences in song and song phenology, feeding behavior, nest placement and structure, habitat, and morphology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt6">Pratt and Pratt 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pratt3">Pratt 2005</xref>). Sometimes known by the species name <italic>freethi</italic>; however, this is an unjustified emendation of the original spelling <italic>fraithii</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pyle1">Pyle 2011</xref>).p. 685. Delete the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria irrorata</named-content></italic> from the Appendix.p. 691. In the Appendix, change <italic><bold>Buteo polyosoma</bold></italic> to <italic><bold>Geranoaetus polyosoma</bold></italic> and change the English name of this species from Red-backed Hawk to Variable Hawk. In the account for this species, change <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. swainsoni</named-content></italic> to <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></italic> and change the last sentence to the following: The origin of the bird remains highly questionable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Allen2">Allen 1988</xref>).p. 691. In the Appendix, following the species account for <italic>Porphyrio porphyrio</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Anthropoides virgo</bold></italic> <bold>(</bold>Linnaeus). Demoiselle Crane.<italic>Ardea Virgo</italic>, Linnaeus, 1758, Syst. Nat., ed. 10, 1, p. 141. (&ldquo;In Oriente&rdquo; &equals; India.)An individual was photographed wintering with Sandhill Cranes near Lodi and Staten Island, San Joaquin County, California, from 30 September 2001 to 18 February 2002; probably the same individual was photographed later near Smithers, British Columbia, on 2 May 2002, and again probably the same bird at Gustavus, southeast Alaska, 13&ndash;14 May 2002 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Hamilton1">Hamilton et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Howell4">Howell et al. 2014</xref>). The species was placed on the Supplemental List, indicating uncertain origin, by the California Bird Records Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Cole1">Cole and McCaskie 2004</xref>). It is not rare in captivity in North America, and previous escapes are known. On the other hand, the species is highly migratory and has occurred as a stray throughout western Europe, north to the Orkney Islands and Scandinavia, and in northern Russia, far from its normal central and southern Asian and African range.p. 691. In the Appendix, following the species account for <italic>Anthropoides virgo</italic>, insert the following new account:<italic><bold>Grus monacha</bold></italic> Temminck. Hooded Crane.<italic>Grus monacha</italic> Temminck, 1835, Pl. col., livr. 94, pl. 555. (Hokkaido and Korea.)Sight reports (at least some documented with photographs) of this eastern Asian species from Idaho (April 2010), Nebraska (April 2011), Tennessee (December 2011&ndash;January 2012), and Indiana (February 2012), perhaps all of the same bird, were detailed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pranty1">Pranty et al. (2014)</xref>. Although accepted by three states' rare bird committees (not yet reviewed by the Idaho committee), the origin of these records was questioned by the American Birding Association's Checklist Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-748-Pranty1">Pranty et al. 2014</xref>). The issue of origin (wild versus escape) is best considered unresolved at this time.p. 693. Delete the account for <italic>Patagioenas goodsoni</italic> from the Appendix.pp. 705 ff. Make the following changes to the list of French names of North American birds:Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:<italic>Alopochen aegyptiaca</italic> Ouette d'&Eacute;gypte<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria irrorata</named-content></italic> Albatros des Galapagos<italic>Pterodroma madeira</italic> P&eacute;trel de Mad&egrave;re<italic>Pterodroma heraldica</italic> P&eacute;trel du Herald<italic>Pterodroma arminjoniana</italic> P&eacute;trel de Trindade<italic>Puffinus newelli</italic> Puffin de Newell<italic>Syrigma sibilatrix</italic> H&eacute;ron fl&ucirc;te-du-soleil<italic>Charadrius collaris</italic> Pluvier de d'Azara<italic>Rupornis magnirostris</italic> Buse &agrave; gros bec<italic>Geranoaetus albicaudatus</italic> Buse &agrave; queue blanche<italic>Patagioenas goodsoni</italic> Pigeon de Goodson<italic>Leptotila cassinii</italic> Colombe de Cassin<italic>Ninox japonica</italic> Ninoxe bor&eacute;ale<italic>Phaethornis mexicanus</italic> Ermite de Hartert<italic>Calliphlox lyrura</italic> Colibri d'Inagua<italic>Doricha eliza</italic> Colibri d'Eliza<italic>Mellisuga helenae</italic> Colibri d'Elena<italic>Amazilia saucerottei</italic> Ariane de SophiePSITTACULIDAE<italic>Cranioleuca dissita</italic> Synallaxe de Coiba<italic>Cryptopipo holochlora</italic> Manakin vert<italic>Campylorhynchus griseus</italic> Troglodyte bicolore<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</named-content></italic> Rougequeue &agrave; front blanc<italic>Chlorophanes spiza</italic> Tangara &eacute;meraude<italic>Spizelloides arborea</italic> Bruant hudsonien<italic>Oreomystis bairdi</italic> Akikiki de Kauai<italic>Paroreomyza maculata</italic> Alauhaio d'Oahu<italic>Paroreomyza flammea</italic> Alauhaio de Molokai<italic>Paroreomyza montana</italic> Alauhaio de Maui<italic>Himatione fraithii</italic> Picchion de Laysan<italic>Drepanis coccinea</italic> Iiwi rouge<italic>Pseudonestor xanthophrys</italic> Pseudonestor de Maui<italic>Hemignathus hanapepe</italic> Nukupuu de Kauai<italic>Hemignathus lucidus</italic> Nukupuu d'Oahu<italic>Hemignathus affinis</italic> Nukupuu de Maui<italic>Hemignathus wilsoni</italic> Akiapolaau d'Hawa&iuml;<italic>Akialoa obscura</italic> Akialoa d'Hawa&iuml;<italic>Akialoa stejnegeri</italic> Akialoa de Kauai<italic>Akialoa ellisiana</italic> Akialoa d'Oahu<italic>Akialoa lanaiensis</italic> Akialoa de Lanai<italic>Chlorodrepanis virens</italic> Amakihi familier<italic>Chlorodrepanis flava</italic> Amakihi d'Oahu<italic>Chlorodrepanis stejnegeri</italic> Amakihi de Stejneger<italic>Viridonia sagittirostris</italic> Grand Amakihi<italic>Loxops wolstenholmei</italic> Loxopse d'Oahu<italic>Loxops ochraceus</italic> Loxopse de Maui<italic>Loxops coccineus</italic> Loxopse d'Hawa&iuml;in APPENDIX (Part 1)<italic>Anthropoides virgo</italic> Grue demoiselle<italic>Grus monacha</italic> Grue moine<italic>Geranoaetus polyosoma</italic> Buse tricoloreDelete the following names:<italic>Pterodroma arminjoniana</italic> P&eacute;trel de la Trinit&eacute; du Sud<italic>Charadrius collaris</italic> Pluvier d'Azara<italic>Buteo magnirostris</italic> Buse &agrave; gros bec<italic>Buteo albicaudatus</italic> Buse &agrave; queue blanche<italic>Leptotila cassini</italic> Colombe de Cassin<italic>Ninox japonica</italic> Ninoxe du Japon<italic>Doricha eliza</italic> Colibri &eacute;lise<italic>Mellisuga helenae</italic> Colibri d'Helen<italic>Amazilia saucerrottei</italic> Ariane de Sophie<italic>Cranioleuca vulpina</italic> Synallaxe renard<italic>Xenopipo holochlora</italic> Manakin vert<italic>Chlorophanes spiza</italic> Guit-guit &eacute;meraude<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella arborea</named-content></italic> Bruant hudsonien<italic>Pseudonestor xanthophrys</italic> Psittirostre de Maui<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus virens</named-content></italic> Amakihi familier<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hemignathus flavus</named-content></italic> Amakihi d'Oahu<italic>Hemignathus kauaiensis</italic> Amakihi de Kauai<italic>Hemignathus sagittirostris</italic> Grand Amakihi<italic>Hemignathus obscurus</italic> H&eacute;mignathe akialoa<italic>Hemignathus ellisianus</italic> H&eacute;mignathe &agrave; long bec<italic>Hemignathus lucidus</italic> H&eacute;mignathe nukupuu<italic>Hemignathus munroi</italic> H&eacute;mignathe akiapolaau<italic>Oreomystis bairdi</italic> Grimpeur de Kauai<italic>Paroreomyza maculata</italic> Grimpeur d'Oahu<italic>Paroreomyza flammea</italic> Grimpeur de Molokai<italic>Paroreomyza montana</italic> Grimpeur de Maui<italic>Loxops coccineus</italic> Loxopse des Hawa&iuml;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vestiaria coccinea</named-content></italic> Iiwi rougein APPENDIX (Part 1)<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoebastria irrorata</named-content></italic> Albatros des Galapagos<italic>Buteo polyosoma</italic> Buse tricolore<italic>Patagioenas goodsoni</italic> Pigeon de GoodsonChange the sequence of species from <italic>Morphnarchus</italic> to <italic>Buteo</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Move <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Herpetotheres cachinnans</named-content></italic>, <italic>Psittacula krameri</italic>, <italic>Agapornis roseicollis</italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melopsittacus undulatus</named-content></italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Transfer <italic>Coereba</italic>, <italic>Saltator</italic>, <italic>Volatinia</italic>, <italic>Sporophila</italic>, <italic>Melopyrrha</italic>, <italic>Tiaris</italic>, <italic>Loxipasser</italic>, <italic>Loxigilla</italic>, <italic>Euneornis</italic>, <italic>Melanospiza</italic>, <italic>Pinaroloxias</italic>, <italic>Haplospiza</italic>, <italic>Acanthidops</italic>, <italic>Diglossa</italic>, <italic>Sicalis</italic>, <italic>Emberizoides</italic>, and their included species to the family THRAUPIDAE, and arrange as indicated by the text of this supplement.Transfer <italic>Nesospingus</italic>, <italic>Phaenicophilus</italic>, <italic>Calyptophilus</italic>, <italic>Rhodinocichla</italic>, <italic>Mitrospingus</italic>, <italic>Spindalis</italic>, and their included species, in this sequence, to &lsqb;INCERTAE SEDIS&rsqb; following <italic>Saltator striatipectus</italic>.Change the sequence of genera in the PIPRIDAE and THRAUPIDAE as indicated by the text of this supplement.Change the sequence of species in <italic>Ramphocelus</italic> and <italic>Sporophila</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Change the sequence of genera from <italic>Telespiza</italic> to <italic>Melamprosops</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Proposals considered but not accepted by the committee included separation of Northern Harrier <italic>Circus hudsonius</italic> from Hen Harrier <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. cyaneus</named-content></italic>, separation of <italic>Toxostoma arenicola</italic> from LeConte's Thrasher <italic>T. lecontei</italic>, separation of <italic>Passerina pallidior</italic> from Painted Bunting <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. ciris</named-content></italic>, separation of Northern Cardinal <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cardinalis cardinalis</named-content></italic> into six species, transfer of <italic>Loxops mana</italic> to <italic>Manucerthia</italic>, change of the English name of American Pipit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus rubescens</named-content></italic> to Buff-bellied Pipit, and the universal adoption of American spellings of words in bird names for which British and American spellings differ.Normand David serves as the committee's advisor for classical languages in relation to scientific names, and Michel Gosselin is the authority for French names. We thank G. R. Angehr, G. Armistead, P. C. Banko, G. Bieber, N. Brinkley, M. Churchill, C. J. Clark, R. E. David, J. Ellis, T. J. Feo, L. A. Freed, D. D. Gibson, C. S. Griffiths, P. Harrison, H. F. James, A. Jaramillo, P. Kovalik, T. Leukering, N. A. Mason, J. M. Musser, G. Obando-Calder&oacute;n, S. L. Olson, B. Patteson, H. D. Pratt, T. K. Pratt, P. Pyle, M. P. Retter, T. S. Schulenberg, D. L. Slager, R. C. Tweit, A. Wilson, and R. Wright for assistance, suggestions, and comments.