No evidence of food limitation during the breeding season of a freshwater marsh-nesting ternForaging behavior of the American White Pelican (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>) in western NevadaIntraclutch variation in egg size of American CootsVariation in laying date, clutch size, egg size, and egg composition of Yellow-headed Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Xanthocephalus xanthocephalus</named-content></italic>): A supplemental feeding experimentEffects of supplemental food on egg production in American CootsEgg composition of American Coots in relation to habitat, year, laying date, clutch size, and supplemental feedingSeabird ecology and the marine environmentA comparison of yolk growth rates in seabird eggsSize selective predation and food habits of two California ternsLuxury in freshwater and stress at sea? The foraging of the Common Tern <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>Tests of three hypotheses of hatching asynchrony in the Common TernOrientation in &ldquo;featureless&rdquo; environments: The extreme case of pelagic birdsPrimary productivity, decomposition and consumer activity in freshwater wetlandsSeasonal and annual variation in brood attendance, prey type delivered to chicks, and foraging patterns of male Common Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>)Experimental demonstration of the insurance value of extra eggs in an obligately siblicidal seabirdFood limitation explains most clutch size variation in the Nazca BoobyThe Forster's Tern in Minnesota: Status, distribution, and reproductive successForaging areas and feeding habitat selection of American White Pelicans (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>) nesting at Pathfinder Reservoir, WyomingFeeding ecology of Forster's Terns on Lake Osakis, MinnesotaA simple and universal method for molecular sexing of non-ratite birdsComponents of productivity in Black-legged Kittiwakes <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rissa tridactyla</named-content></italic>: Response to supplemental feedingWhy does the Herring Gull lay three eggs?Breeding biology, life histories, and life history&ndash;environment interactions in seabirdsThe effect of food abundance on the reproductive patterns of cootsPractical methods of estimating volume and fresh weight of bird eggsDoes food availability affect energy expenditure rates of nesting seabirds? A supplemental-feeding experiment with Black-legged Kittiwakes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rissa tridactyla</named-content></italic>)Cumulative impacts to wetlandsForster's Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic>Food as a limit on breeding birds: A life-history perspectiveChanges in the status, distribution, and abundance of American White Pelicans (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>) in Wisconsin, 1850&ndash;2013Forster's Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic>)Mate provisioning, nutritional requirements for egg production, and primary reproductive effort of female Common Terns <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>Food addition and twinning experiments in the Cape Gannet: Effects on breeding success and chick growth and behaviorDependence of fledging success on egg-size, parental performance and egg composition among Common and Roseate terns, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic> and <italic>S. dougallii</italic>Responses of known-aged Common Terns to experimental shortening of the wingsAsynchronous hatching in Common and Roseate terns, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic> and <italic>S. dougallii</italic>Variations in growth of Roseate Tern chicksVariations in growth of Roseate Tern chicks: II. Early growth as an index of parental qualityReproductive parameters in relation to food supply in the Whiskered Tern (<italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>)Asynchronous hatching and chick mortality in the Herring Gull <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus argentatus</named-content></italic>New perspectives for estimating body condition from mass/length data: The scaled mass index as an alternative methodSome considerations on the reproductive energetics of pelagic seabirdsEvidence for prey limitation of Common and Roseate tern reproductionTrends in Elegant Tern and northern anchovy populations in CaliforniaClimate and weather effects on seabirdsForaging behavior and food of seabirdsSeabird foraging ranges as a preliminary tool for identifying candidate Marine Protected AreasSeabird demography and its relationship with the marine environmentChick provisioning by the Yellow-nosed Albatross <italic>Diomedea chlororhynchos</italic>: Response of foraging effort to experimentally increased costs and demandsEffects of parental quality and effort on the reproduction of Common TernsSustained increase in food supplies reduces broodmate aggression in Black-legged KittiwakesFood availability is considered an important limiting factor in the breeding performance of marine birds, which exhibit restraint in reproductive life-history characteristics (e.g., delayed maturation, small clutch size, slow growth). Less well understood, however, is the extent to which taxonomic analogue species that breed in freshwater habitats are similarly regulated by food availability. Marsh-nesting Forster's Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic>) were studied from 2004 to 2008 at Horicon Marsh, a freshwater colony site in Wisconsin, USA, where reproductive success has been chronically poor. The adequacy of the food base to support a breeding colony of terns was evaluated (1) indirectly, through measures of breeding performance correlated with food availability during the egg-laying and incubation stages; and (2) directly, through a supplemental feeding experiment, conducted in 2004 and 2006, to determine whether nestling growth was limited by food availability. Clutch size, egg size, and adult body condition did not differ significantly among years, despite considerable annual fluctuation in environmental conditions and the rapid and extensive colonization of the wetland complex during the study period by a potential food competitor, American White Pelican (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>). Growth rates of chicks were &sim;10&percnt; higher, on average, in 2006 than in 2004, but no difference was found in mean daily growth rates between food-supplemented and control chicks, nor did chick growth differ according to hatching order in the brood or hatching date. These results suggest that food availability is not a limiting factor during the breeding season for Forster's Terns at Horicon Marsh, the only actively managed breeding site remaining for this species in Wisconsin.Se piensa que la disponibilidad de alimentos es un factor importante que limita el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo de las aves marinas, que exhiben una restricci&oacute;n en las caracter&iacute;sticas reproductivas de la historia de vida (e.g., maduraci&oacute;n demorada, tama&ntilde;o de nidada peque&ntilde;o, crecimiento lento). Sin embargo, resulta menos claro en qu&eacute; medida especies taxon&oacute;micamente an&aacute;logas que se reproducen en h&aacute;bitats de agua dulce est&aacute;n igualmente reguladas por la disponibilidad de alimentos. La especie <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic> fue estudiada de 2004 a 2008 en el Pantano Horicon, una colonia de agua dulce en Wisconsin, USA, donde el &eacute;xito reproductivo ha sido cr&oacute;nicamente bajo. El objetivo principal fue evaluar la pertinencia de la base alimentaria para sustentar a la colonia reproductiva de gaviotines, tanto indirectamente a trav&eacute;s de medidas de desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo correlacionadas con la disponibilidad de alimentos durante las etapas de puesta de huevos e incubaci&oacute;n, y directamente a trav&eacute;s de un experimento de suplementaci&oacute;n de alimentos, realizado en 2004 y 2006, para determinar si el crecimiento de los pichones estuvo limitado por la disponibilidad de alimentos. A pesar de fluctuaciones anuales considerables en las condiciones ambientales y la r&aacute;pida y extensa colonizaci&oacute;n del humedal durante el per&iacute;odo de estudio por parte de un competidor potencial por el alimento (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>), el tama&ntilde;o de la nidada, el tama&ntilde;o del huevo y la condici&oacute;n corporal del adulto no difirieron significativamente entre a&ntilde;os. Las tasas de crecimiento de los pichones fueron &sim;10&percnt; m&aacute;s altas en promedio en 2006 que en 2004, pero no se encontr&oacute; una diferencia en las tasas de crecimiento diario promedio entre los pichones suplementados con alimento y los control, y tampoco difiri&oacute; el crecimiento de los pichones de acuerdo al orden de eclosi&oacute;n en la camada o a la fecha de eclosi&oacute;n. Estos resultados sugieren que la disponibilidad de alimentos no es un factor limitante durante la estaci&oacute;n reproductiva para <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. forsteri</named-content></italic> en el Pantano Horicon, el &uacute;nico sitio reproductivo manejado activamente para esta especie en Wisconsin.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> alimentaci&oacute;n suplementaria, crecimiento del pich&oacute;n, desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo, disponibilidad de alimentos, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic>A primary evolutionary constraint in the life history of marine birds is the necessity of breeding on land but feeding at sea. This constraint is thought to be reflected in several demographic patterns typical of marine birds, including deferred maturation, low fecundity, irregular breeding schedules, slow growth, and extended development times for chicks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Hamer1">Hamer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Weimerskirch1">Weimerskirch 2001</xref>). Early hypotheses for these reproductive differences between marine and terrestrial (e.g., passerine) birds emphasized food availability and the difficulty experienced by marine birds in obtaining sufficient food to maintain themselves and rear offspring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Lack1">Lack 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Ashmole1">Ashmole 1971</xref>). Subsequent research, however, has indicated that the explanation is not so simple: Although the ocean may appear &ldquo;featureless&rdquo; to a human observer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Bonadonna1">Bonadonna et al. 2003</xref>), prey resources actually can be predictable, both spatially and temporally, and seabirds have evolved the foraging specializations necessary to exploit these conditions in a variety of ways (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Shealer1">Shealer 2001</xref>).Empirical tests of such a &ldquo;food limitation&rdquo; hypothesis have included correlative studies that compared measures of breeding performance with environmental stochasticity (e.g., El Ni&ntilde;o&ndash;Southern Oscillation events; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Schreiber1">Schreiber 2001</xref>) or with independent measures of prey abundance or availability (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Safina1">Safina et al. 1988</xref>). More direct approaches include clutch-size manipulations or &ldquo;twinning&rdquo; experiments, whereby additional eggs or chicks are added to nests and measures of breeding performance are compared between manipulated and control groups (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Navarro1">Navarro 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Clifford1">Clifford and Anderson 2001a</xref>), and &ldquo;handicap&rdquo; experiments in which parent birds are manipulated by adding weights or by feather clipping to increase their energy expenditure during the rearing period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Weimerskirch2">Weimerskirch et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet2">Nisbet et al. 2004</xref>). Still other methods involve provisioning adults or nestlings with extra food and comparing measures of breeding success to unsupplemented controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Clifford2">Clifford and Anderson 2001b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Gill1">Gill and Hatch 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Jodice1">Jodice et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-White1">White et al. 2010</xref>). Some studies have supported a food-limitation hypothesis, but sufficient equivocal evidence exists to indicate that the reproductive restraint exhibited by seabirds cannot be explained entirely by food limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Hamer1">Hamer et al. 2001</xref>).Much less attention has been paid to the influence of food availability on breeding performance in related freshwater-breeding taxa such as loons and grebes, pelicans, coots, herons, and some gulls and terns. Similar to marine birds, these species also breed on land but obtain food from the water, although the scale of the foraging area usually is much smaller than for seabirds, whose foraging ranges may extend tens to hundreds of kilometers from the breeding colony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Thaxter1">Thaxter et al. 2012</xref>). Freshwater wetlands vary considerably in size, composition, and primary productivity across the landscape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Brinson1">Brinson et al. 1981</xref>) and, accordingly, can be considered unpredictable habitats, depending on anthropogenic factors (e.g., nutrient and pesticide pulses from agriculture, invasive species introductions) and natural phenomena (e.g., flooding, drought). The ability of birds to discriminate among wetlands of variable quality, therefore, should be under strong selective pressure and influence decisions about where to breed. In the United States, however, wetland loss and degradation have been severe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Johnston1">Johnston 1994</xref>), with freshwater wetlands declining by &gt;250,000 ha between 1986 and 1997 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Dahl1">Dahl 2000</xref>). Such losses may affect wetland-dependent birds by limiting the remaining available breeding sites and by potentially forcing prospecting individuals to breed in suboptimal habitats.Forster's Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna forsteri</named-content></italic>) is primarily a marsh-nester whose breeding distribution is restricted entirely to North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-McNicholl1">McNicholl et al. 2001</xref>). It nests both in coastal salt marshes and in estuaries, as well as in freshwater marshes and lakes in the continental interior. In Wisconsin, Forster's Tern was placed on the state endangered species list in 1979, primarily on the basis of poor productivity and the instability of its few known breeding sites in the state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Mossman1">Mossman 1988</xref>), which currently have been reduced to 5 colonies and &sim;500 pairs total (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Kreitinger1">Kreitinger et al. 2013</xref>). Causes of poor breeding performance remain unknown, but lack of suitable habitat, predation, or weather-related losses may be important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Mossman1">Mossman 1988</xref>). In some years, food availability also may limit reproductive success, although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Fraser1">Fraser (1997)</xref> found no evidence of this in her 2-yr study of the feeding ecology of Forster's Terns at a freshwater colony site in Minnesota, where adults were able to provide increasingly larger prey fish to their chicks as they grew larger.I conducted a 5-yr study (2004&ndash;2008) of Forster's Terns breeding at Horicon Marsh, Wisconsin, the only remaining breeding site for this species in the state with the capacity for water-control management. The overarching objective of this project was to identify factors that limit reproductive success in this population, which from 2003 to 2005 experienced complete, or nearly complete, breeding failure each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Shealer2">Shealer 2005</xref>, D. A. Shealer personal observation). Here, the adequacy of the prey base to support breeding Forster's Terns is assessed both (1) indirectly, through measures of breeding performance correlated with food availability during the egg-laying and incubation stages; and (2) directly, through a supplemental feeding experiment, conducted in 2 of the 5 yr, that was designed to assess food availability during the chick-rearing period and identify factors contributing to variation in chick growth. Over the course of the study period, Horicon Marsh experienced 2 severe flooding events and the rapid and extensive colonization of the wetland complex by American White Pelicans (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pelecanus erythrorhynchos</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;pelicans&rdquo;), a potential food competitor. I therefore expected to detect evidence of food limitation in some years due to one or more of these factors. Specifically, I predicted that years of poor food availability would be reflected by lower average clutch or egg sizes and slower growth rates of nestlings.This study was conducted at Horicon Marsh, Dodge County, Wisconsin, USA (43&deg;30&ndash;37&prime;N, 088&deg;37&ndash;40&prime;W). Horicon Marsh (&sim;13,000 ha) is a managed wetland complex dominated by cattails (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Typha</named-content></italic> spp.), with scattered patches of other emergent aquatic vegetation consisting of bulrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Scirpus</named-content></italic> spp.), bur-reed (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sparganium eurycarpum</named-content></italic>), and purple loosestrife (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lythrum salicaria</named-content></italic>). The northern two-thirds of the marsh is part of the Horicon National Wildlife Refuge, and the southern one-third is administered by the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources. The main source of water for this wetland complex is the Rock River, which enters the marsh from the northwest. Water levels in the northern impoundments are controlled by a series of levees and gated culverts and are managed to provide suitable breeding and feeding habitat for a variety of aquatic wildlife. Water control is limited in the Main Pool, which renders it susceptible to periodic flooding, establishment of cattail monocultures in the shallow areas, and invasion by carp (mostly <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyprinus carpio</named-content></italic>).The study was conducted from May through July over 5 consecutive years (2004&ndash;2008). During this period, the estimated number of breeding pairs of Forster's Terns ranged from a low of 42 pairs (2005) to a high of 110 pairs (2008). In each year, the species nested in one of the northern impoundments of the marsh (Teal Pool) and in scattered subcolonies throughout the Main Pool. Other nesting species, and potential competitors for nesting substrate, included American Coots (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Fulica americana</named-content></italic>), Black Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chlidonias niger</named-content></italic>), and Pied-billed Grebes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Podilymbus podiceps</named-content></italic>). The pelican, a piscivorous species and potential food competitor, first colonized the marsh beginning in 1999; the population peaked in 2006 at an estimated 777 nesting pairs and 1,450 fledglings produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Matteson1">Matteson et al. 2014</xref>). By 2008, only 8 pairs attempted to nest and no fledglings were produced; pelicans abandoned the marsh in 2009, following 2 consecutive years of high water levels and flooding that eliminated most of the available nesting habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Matteson1">Matteson et al. 2014</xref>).Beginning on or about May 20 of each year, Forster's Tern nesting colonies were located by conducting systematic surveys from roadside dikes, or with canoes or an airboat in the larger impoundments. Where adult activity indicated the presence of nests, the entire area was searched by canoe or on foot (i.e. by wading through the marsh). For each nest found in each year, its latitude and longitude were recorded with a GPS receiver (precision &plusmn;3 m); eggs were numbered with a nontoxic waterproof marker and weighed on an electronic scale (&plusmn;0.1 g); and linear measurements (length and maximum breadth) were recorded with calipers (&plusmn;0.5 mm). Precise laying dates were known only for a small fraction of eggs, because most clutches were complete when found. Therefore, fresh masses of Forster's Tern eggs were estimated by the formula <italic>LB</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>k</italic><sub>m</sub>, where <italic>L</italic> is the egg's length (cm), <italic>B</italic> is the egg's maximum breadth (cm), and <italic>k</italic><sub>m</sub> is a species-specific mass constant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Hoyt1">Hoyt 1979</xref>). A sample of 50 eggs weighed on the known or suspected date of laying gave a mean <italic>k</italic><sub>m</sub> of 0.524 (95&percnt; confidence interval: 0.520&ndash;0.527), with no significant difference between first-laid eggs and those laid second or third in the clutch (<italic>t</italic><sub>48</sub> &equals; 1.74, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.09); the mean <italic>k</italic><sub>m</sub> value was used in the equation to estimate the fresh masses of all eggs in each year.Nests were visited daily around the predicted time of hatching (&sim;23 days of incubation) and every 3&ndash;5 days thereafter in Teal Pool during the incubation period to monitor nest survival and survey the colony for new nests. The Main Pool was searched thoroughly by airboat &ge;3 times yr<sup>&minus;1</sup>, once each in May, June, and July, to cover the early, middle, and late nesting periods, respectively. Visits to nests in the Main Pool were less frequent because of logistic constraints and averaged &sim;1 visit wk<sup>&minus;1</sup>. Consequently, most of the intensive research involved nests in Teal Pool, for ease of access, but data from nests in the Main Pool are included where appropriate for comparison.During the incubation period, adult Forster's Terns were captured opportunistically with walk-in or drop-in traps placed over their eggs. Adults were banded, and their mass and the lengths of head &plus; bill, culmen, wing, tarsus, and tail were recorded. A blood sample (&sim;30 &mu;L) was collected from the tarsal vein of each adult for molecular sex determination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Fridolfsson1">Fridolfsson and Ellegren 1999</xref>).Indirect quantitative assessments of food availability were made each year by comparisons of clutch sizes (number of eggs laid per nesting attempt; chi-square test of association) and of egg sizes (estimated fresh mass; analysis of variance &lsqb;ANOVA&rsqb;). To control for the lack of independence among eggs within a clutch, 1 egg from each 3-egg clutch was selected randomly for inclusion in the sample for comparison.Following the procedures outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Peig1">Peig and Green (2009)</xref>, a scaled mass index (SMI) was derived from measurements of adult Forster's Terns trapped during incubation. The SMI was intended to serve as an index of body condition for each adult at the time of capture. Of the linear body measurements recorded, head &plus; bill length was most strongly correlated with body mass (Pearson's <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.39, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 52) and therefore was used as the single linear measure to compute SMI, according to Equation 2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Peig1">Peig and Green (2009)</xref>. The slope of the standardized major axis regression (&beta;SMA) used for Forster's Terns was 2.13, with <italic>L</italic><sub>0</sub> &equals; 84.7 mm and <italic>L</italic><sub>0</sub> &equals; 79.5 mm for males and females, respectively. The SMI was compared among adults each year with analysis of covariance (ANCOVA), using trap date as a covariate to control for a possible seasonal decline in this measure.In 2004 and 2006, chicks from 8 nests in Teal Pool were assigned to receive supplemental food (SF) and chicks from 8 other nests were designated as controls (C). To minimize potential confounding effects, nests in the candidate pool consisted of 3-egg clutches and all were begun (i.e. first egg laid) within 5 days of each other; otherwise, selection and assignment of nests to the treatment or control group were made randomly. Chicks from SF nests were periodically hand fed supplements of fish obtained from minnow traps placed in the marsh, frozen until needed, and then thawed, blotted dry, and weighed in the field. Prey sampling in the vicinity of the Forster's Tern colony and casual observations of fish delivered by adults to chicks indicated that the main diet of Forster's Terns at Horicon consisted of fingerling carp (mostly <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyprinus carpio</named-content></italic>) and other small cyprinids (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Umbra limi</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pimephales promelas</named-content></italic>), so these species were used in the supplemental feeding experiment. An attempt was made to provision each SF chick with enough fish to equal 10&percnt; of its body mass on the day of feeding. Chicks, usually those &le;2 days old, sometimes refused to eat, whereas other chicks ate as much as 20&percnt; of their body mass at a particular feeding; this was not a concern, however, because only the total amount of fish each chick received during the course of the experiment was used as a variable. Chicks from C nests were handled similarly and as frequently as the SF chicks, but they did not receive any food other than what their parents provided. Because of the additional time required to weigh fish and feed chicks at SF nests, visits to these nests were timed and adjusted accordingly at C nests.Because chicks readily depart the nest and swim away from an approaching threat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-McNicholl1">McNicholl et al. 2001</xref>), all study nests were enclosed before the first chick hatched. Enclosures were constructed by encircling each nest with plastic mesh fencing, which was anchored to the marsh bottom with PVC poles, and were large enough in circumference to contain the entire nest substrate, with a fringe of open water to permit drinking, bathing, and defecation. Study nests were visited daily during the late incubation period to document hatching date for each chick, and both SF and C chicks were banded and first weighed on the day of hatching. Study nests were visited every 3&ndash;5 days thereafter to monitor nest survival, and chicks were weighed immediately upon arrival at the nest (i.e. before SF chicks were fed). Because of the time constraints associated with maneuvering through the marsh, nearly 4 hr were required to visit all study nests. To minimize time-of-day variation in body mass of chicks, nests were visited in the same order each time, and each chick was weighed and measured within 1 hr of the previous visit.In 2004, three SF nests were either destroyed by or abandoned because of lodge renovation by muskrats (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ondatra zibethicus</named-content></italic>) after severe storms and flooding. The study sample in that year thus consisted of 15 chicks from 5 nests in the SF group and 21 chicks from 8 nests in the C group. In 2006, predation reduced the sample size throughout the season, such that the final analysis sample consisted of 10 SF chicks from 4 nests and 16 C chicks from 6 nests. When the youngest chick in the brood had reached 13 days of age, enclosures around study nests were removed to permit chicks to move freely about the marsh and to reduce the risk of whole-brood predation. Consequently, no information about actual fledging success was obtained, because chicks rarely were encountered once enclosures were removed.Like related species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet4">Nisbet et al. 1995</xref>), Forster's Tern chicks exhibit a logistic growth curve, with a linear phase when growth is at its maximum rate. For Forster's Terns, the linear phase occurs between days 1 and 13 posthatching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Linear growth rate (LGR) represents the time of maximum energy demand and is likely to be highly sensitive to variation in food availability. I calculated LGR as the slope of the least-squares regression line for chick masses recorded on &ge;3 different days between days 1 and 13. I compared LGR using analysis of covariance between experimental treatments (SF and C), with year (2004 or 2006) and hatch order (first, second, or third) as additional categorical predictor variables, and with hatch date and fresh egg mass as covariates. Clutch size was not included as a variable because only clutches and broods of 3 were used in the experiment. Because of small sample size, a full-factorial model could not be run without compromising statistical power. Consequently, only 1 interaction term, hatch order &times; experimental treatment, was included, under the assumption that, in a food-limited environment, supplemental feeding would have a disproportionate effect on the third-hatched chick in the brood, in relation to the other 2 chicks (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Parsons1">Parsons 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Graves1">Graves et al. 1984</xref>).Composite growth curve for body mass of known-age Forster's Tern chicks at Horicon Marsh, 2004&ndash;2008. Points are mean mass at each day of age; capped bars represent &plusmn; SD. The best-fit linear growth model extends from day 1 to day 13 (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.955), which was used to calculate LGR for chicks in the growth study. Sample sizes range from 11 to 27 chicks through day 14, then decline to <italic>n</italic> &equals; 1 on day 19.Means are reported &plusmn; SD unless otherwise noted. Statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS version 14.0 for Windows (SPSS, Chicago, Illinois, USA). All statistical tests assume two-tailed probabilities. Statistical significance was accepted at <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.05.Modal clutch size for Forster's Terns nesting at Horicon Marsh from 2004 to 2008 was 3 eggs yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f02">Figure 2</xref>). The distribution of clutch sizes during the study period did not differ significantly among years (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 4.8, df &equals; 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.31, comparing clutch sizes of 1&ndash;2 vs. clutch sizes 3&ndash;4), despite a noticeable decline in 3-egg clutches in 2005. One-egg and 4-egg clutches were rare in all 5 yr.Clutch size distribution for Forster's Terns nesting at Horicon Marsh, 2004&ndash;2008. Numbers of nests: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 59 (2004), <italic>n</italic> &equals; 32 (2005), <italic>n</italic> &equals; 24 (2006), <italic>n</italic> &equals; 42 (2007), and <italic>n</italic> &equals; 94 (2008).Summary data on egg sizes (as indexed by estimates of fresh mass) for the Teal Pool colony (2004&ndash;2008) are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-t01">Table 1</xref>. ANCOVA indicated no effect of laying date on egg size (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.008 &plusmn; 0.011 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;, <italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;0.70, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49) and no significant differences in mean egg sizes among years (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.72, df &equals; 4 and 41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.58). Comparisons between Teal Pool and 2 other colony sites in 2004 also revealed no difference in egg size (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.27, df &equals; 2 and 61, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.76) and no evidence of an influence of laying date on egg size (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.011 &plusmn; 0.210 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;, <italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;0.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.60). Mean egg sizes between the Teal Pool and Main Pool colonies at Horicon Marsh in 2007 and 2008 likewise were not significantly different (both <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.20).Egg-size (g, indexed as fresh egg mass) comparisons among colony sites and years (means &plusmn; SD, with sample sizes in parentheses) for each colony site and year for which data were obtained (nd &equals; no data).Scaled mass indices for adult Forster's Terns trapped during incubation are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f03">Figure 3</xref>. ANCOVA indicated that trap date was not a significant predictor of adult body condition (&beta; &equals; 0.046 &plusmn; 0.095 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;, <italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.49, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.63) and that body condition did not differ significantly among years (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.45, df &equals; 4 and 46, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.23).Scaled body-mass indices of adult Forster's Terns, 2004&ndash;2008. Shown are medians (horizontal lines) with boxes indicating 25th and 75th percentiles and whiskers indicating minimum and maximum values. Sample sizes range from <italic>n</italic> &equals; 8 (2006 and 2007) to <italic>n</italic> &equals; 17 (2004).The total amount of fish each SF chick received ranged from 14.1 to 47.9 g (mean &equals; 29.4 &plusmn; 10.1). All SF chicks received supplemental food on at least 4, and on as many as 8, different days. The LGR of individual chicks ranged from 2.6 to 9.2 g day<sup>&minus;1</sup> (mean &equals; 7.4 &plusmn; 1.2). The relationship between the total amount of fish that SF chicks received and LGR was positive but not statistically significant (Pearson's <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.46, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 25).The initial full-factorial ANOVA model indicated that neither the year effect (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.15, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.29) nor any of the interaction terms (all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) contributed significantly to variation in LGR among the chicks in the study sample. The model was rerun without the year effect and the year-associated interaction terms to increase statistical power. The reduced model (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.78, df &equals; 5 and 55, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.57), however, indicated that neither the experimental treatment, hatching order, nor their interaction was a significant predictor of nestling growth (all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.25; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f04">Figure 4</xref>). A nested ANOVA treating brood identity (chicks nested within broods) as a random factor indicated that variation in LGR among chicks was strongly dependent on the brood in which they were reared (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-t02">Table 2</xref>), again with hatching order and experimental treatment contributing very little to variation in growth performance of chicks. Mean LGR among broods ranged from a low of 4.6 to a high of 9.1 g day<sup>&minus;1</sup>.Mean (&plusmn; SD) linear growth rates (LGR) of Forster's Tern chicks according to hatching order in the brood and whether they were (shaded bars) or were not (unshaded bars) provisioned with supplemental food.Results of nested ANOVA (nests within treatments) testing for variation in linear growth rate as a function of treatment, brood identity, and hatching order.The ANCOVA model indicated that neither the main effects of hatching order or whether a chick received supplemental food contributed significantly to variation in chick growth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-t03">Table 3</xref>). Likewise, the hatching order &times; experimental treatment interaction was not significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f04">Figure 4</xref>). A marginally significant year effect (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.052) provided some evidence that overall chick growth was slightly (&sim;10&percnt;) better in 2006 (mean &equals; 7.76 &plusmn; 0.25 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;) than in 2004 (mean &equals; 7.04 &plusmn; 0.22 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;). Of the 2 covariates, only egg mass indicated a significant relationship with LGR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-t03">Table 3</xref>), but the slope estimate was negative, indicating that chicks that hatched from lighter eggs grew faster during the linear phase of growth and vice versa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-f05">Figure 5</xref>).Results of ANCOVA model for linear growth rate of Forster's Tern chicks at Horicon Marsh (independent variables; model <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.182, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.25, df &equals; 8 and 45, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.29).Relationship between linear growth rates (LGR) of chicks and estimated fresh mass of eggs from which they hatched.In 2004, all 15 SF chicks reached 13 days of age, compared with 20 of 21 C chicks. In 2006, all 10 SF chicks reached 13 days of age, compared with 12 of 16 C chicks. Survival to day 13 was statistically equivalent between SF and C chicks in each year (Fisher's exact test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.10 for each year comparison). Of the C chicks that were lost, only 1 appeared to have starved; the remainder went missing from enclosures between nest visits.For terns that breed and forage in marine environments, variation in prey abundance or availability has been shown to correlate positively with measures of breeding performance, including the number of breeding individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Schaffner1">Schaffner 1986</xref>), clutch size, and nestling growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Safina1">Safina et al. 1988</xref>). By contrast, terns in freshwater habitats appear to enjoy more stable and predictable foraging patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Burness1">Burness et al. 1994</xref>) and foraging trips of shorter duration, resulting in lower energy expenditure and leaving more time for nest attendance and brood defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Becker1">Becker et al. 1997</xref>). Assuming that reproductive energetics and reproductive output in birds are regulated, to a large extent, by food supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Lack1">Lack 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Martin1">Martin 1987</xref>), variation in average measures of reproductive output within a population among years should reflect variation in local food availability. The lack of any statistical differences among years for measures of clutch size, egg size, or adult body condition therefore suggests that food availability for Forster's Terns breeding at Horicon Marsh was consistent during the early part of the breeding season each year. The similarity in clutch and egg sizes at Horicon to those reported from other colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-McNicholl1">McNicholl et al. 2001</xref>) indicate also that the prey base was adequate for Forster's Terns to realize their maximum reproductive potential.Presumably, the cost of egg production is high for female larids, which lay large eggs, in relation to their body size, over a brief period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Astheimer1">Astheimer and Grau 1990</xref>). Forster's Terns typically produce clutches of 3 eggs that weigh, collectively, &sim;40&percnt; of their body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-McNicholl1">McNicholl et al. 2001</xref>). Female terns mostly use dietary intake, rather than stored reserves, to produce eggs, and their greatest nutritional needs, at least in the congeneric Common Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>), tend to peak 1 or 2 days before the first egg is laid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Moore1">Moore et al. 2000</xref>). Consequently, a food shortage during the period of egg production should be reflected in either the sizes or number of eggs that a female can produce, as was found in a 2-yr study of Common Terns, which produced larger clutches, but not larger eggs, during the year of greater food abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Safina1">Safina et al. 1988</xref>). Such a tradeoff was also reported in marsh-breeding Whiskered Terns (<italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>) in western France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Paillisson1">Paillisson et al. 2007</xref>), whereby females laid larger clutches but smaller eggs during a year of high food availability. Conversely, cold temperatures in the following year apparently reduced the invertebrate prey base, resulting in lower average clutch sizes but eggs of larger average volume. No such tradeoff was evident in Forster's Terns at Horicon Marsh, despite considerable interannual fluctuation in environmental conditions. The diet of Forster's Terns, however, consists mostly of fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Baltz1">Baltz et al. 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Fraser1">Fraser 1997</xref>), which presumably are less sensitive than aquatic invertebrates to temperature changes.Growth rates of chicks also should reflect food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Safina1">Safina et al. 1988</xref>), particularly during the linear phase of the growth curve when chicks are growing most rapidly and energy demands are highest. Variation in chick growth could be a function of environmental influences, variation in parental quality, or both. The supplemental feeding experiment was designed to tease apart these extrinsic and intrinsic factors. Differences in average growth between years, between SF and C chicks, or among chicks within broods would suggest a food-limited environment; none of these effects was found convincingly, although average growth rates were slightly lower in 2004 than in 2006. Of particular interest was the lack of a significant hatching-order effect. Because of hatching asynchrony among the Laridae, last-hatched chicks tend to begin life at a competitive disadvantage in relation to their older siblings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Parsons1">Parsons 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Graves1">Graves et al. 1984</xref>). This phenomenon has been well documented in terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna</named-content></italic> spp.) breeding in marine environments, whereby the last-hatched chick in a brood typically exhibits inferior growth and a much lower survival probability than its siblings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet3">Nisbet and Cohen 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet1">Nisbet 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet4">Nisbet et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet5">1998</xref>). Third-hatched Forster's Tern chicks grew as fast as their older siblings, however, regardless of whether they were provided with supplemental food, and survival rates were high for all chicks in the study. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Bollinger1">Bollinger et al. (1990)</xref> reported a similar finding for Common Terns breeding at a freshwater site: Survival of all 3 chicks in the brood was not unusual, and growth rates of third-hatched chicks were equivalent to those of brood mates in 1 of the 2 yr of the study.In the supplemental feeding experiment, brood identity was the only predictor of variation in chick growth rates. This finding suggests that, even under adequate environmental conditions and sufficient food resources, breeding performance is largely a function of the intrinsic quality of the parents, in terms of their ability or willingness to locate, catch, and deliver prey to their chicks. Although parental quality in terns and other seabirds is usually inferred by the outcomes measured, such as body size, timing of breeding, or egg size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet5">Nisbet et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Wendeln1">Wendeln and Becker 1999</xref>), only egg size contributed significantly to variation in chick growth rates, and, unexpectedly, the relationship was inverse. This finding suggests that, despite the initial disadvantage to chicks that hatch from smaller eggs (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Nisbet1">Nisbet 1978</xref>), parent terns are able to compensate by increasing their provisioning rates to those chicks, although not all parents necessarily do so. Unfortunately, no information was recorded on parental feeding rates, so further study is needed to determine whether parent Forster's Terns are capable of such fine-scale discrimination, or whether feeding rates can be mediated, to some extent, by the frequency or intensity of begging by chicks.Although productivity in freshwater wetlands is highly variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Brinson1">Brinson et al. 1981</xref>), experimental tests of food limitation in marsh-nesting birds have produced mostly negative results. Supplemental feeding experiments conducted on herbivorous or insectivorous marsh birds have shown little or no effects on measures of breeding performance, including laying date, clutch size, egg size, and egg composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Arnold1">Arnold 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Arnold2">1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Arnold3">1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Arnold4">Arnold et al. 1991</xref>), although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Hill1">Hill (1988)</xref> found that female American Coots nesting in territories with experimentally enriched food supplies laid heavier eggs than those nesting in control territories. The present study extends the scope of investigation to include a primarily piscivorous species, with similar results indicating little or no effect of food availability on egg production or nestling growth performance.Particularly noteworthy is the colonization of Horicon Marsh by pelicans that began in 1999 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Matteson1">Matteson et al. 2014</xref>). Assuming that adult and near-fledgling pelicans require &sim;1.2 kg fish day<sup>&minus;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Anderson1">Anderson 1991</xref>), pelicans directly removed &gt;2,600 kg of potential food for terns daily from Horicon Marsh in 2006, when 777 breeding pairs produced 1,450 fledglings, but only &sim;10 kg day<sup>&minus;1</sup> in 2008, when only 8 pairs nested and no fledglings were produced. This &ldquo;natural experiment&rdquo; suggests either that there is little overlap between terns and pelicans in the species or sizes of prey fish taken&mdash;unlikely, because both species take small (&lt;10 cm) prey fish from the epilimnion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Findholt1">Findholt and Anderson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Fraser1">Fraser 1997</xref>)&mdash;or that the prey base is superabundant at this site and the impact on fish stocks by pelicans was negligible. The absence of a measurable impact on the breeding performance of Forster's Terns over the 5-yr study period, and particularly in 2006, supports the latter conclusion.Because of its breeding distribution in both interior freshwater systems and in salt marshes along coastal areas, Forster's Tern seems an ideal model species for comparative ecological investigations of predator&ndash;prey dynamics and environmental influences on breeding performance. Evidence presented in this paper suggests that freshwater-nesting birds are not limited by food availability, despite population declines and poor breeding success in many of the colonies under study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Cuthbert1">Cuthbert and Louis 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-McNicholl1">McNicholl et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-378-Shealer3">Shealer 2008</xref>). The situation could be very different, however, for coastal populations that rely on a marine-based food source. Comparative studies between the interior and coastal populations are lacking but would be a fruitful area of research to elucidate how different populations of a single species adapt to, or at least tolerate, very different environmental regimes.I thank the many student field assistants who participated in this project over the years, in particular J. M. Buzzell, M. Freil, T. Gaul, D. Harezlak, J. A. Heiar, A. Janke, N. Machovec, and S. Stanchuk. I appreciate the lodging and logistical support provided by staff at the Horicon National Wildlife Refuge, with special thanks to D. Kitchen, J. Krapfl, W. Woyczik, and M. Madel. Birds were banded under Federal Master Bird-banding Permit no. 22827 and Wisconsin Bureau of Endangered Resources endangered species permit. I appreciate the insightful comments of two anonymous reviewers that substantially improved the content and clarity of the manuscript. This research was funded by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Region 3 (agreement no. 301816J108).