 Stopover ecology of American Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis dominica  ) in Midwestern agricultural fields    Community composition and migration chronology of shorebirds using the saline lakes of the Southern Great Plains, USA  Spring migration of shorebirds on the Yakutat Forelands, Alaska  Rates of mass gain and energy deposition in Red Knot on their final spring staging site is both time- and condition-dependent  Species factsheet:   Pluvialis dominica    Site selection by migratory shorebirds in Delaware Bay, and its relationship to beach characteristics and abundance of horseshoe crab ( Limulus polyphemius ) eggs  The package adehabitat for the R software: A tool for the analysis of space and habitat use by animals  Travelling to breed  Spring migration of Lesser Golden-Plover in Benton County, Indiana  unmarked: an R package for fitting hierarchical models of wildlife occurrence and abundance  Factors affecting earthworms in pastures  Optimal fat loads and long-distance flights by migrating Knots   Calidris canutus  , Sanderlings  C. alba  and Turnstones   Arenaria interpres    Optimum fuel loads in migratory birds: Distinguishing between time and energy minimization  The adaptation of molt pattern in migratory Dunlins   Calidris alpina    Biology of the Eared Grebe and Wilson's Phalarope in the nonbreeding season: A study of adaptations to saline lakes  American Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis dominica  )  Fat cyclicity, predicted migratory flight ranges, and features of wintering behavior in Pacific Golden-Plovers  Buff-breasted Sandpiper density and numbers during migratory stopover in the Rainwater Basin, Nebraska  Catching waders with a &ldquo;Wilsternet&rdquo;  Modeling survival and testing biological hypotheses using marked animals: A unified approach with case studies  Turnover rates of fall-migrating Pectoral Sandpipers in the lower Mississippi Alluvial Valley  Can intensively farmed arable land be favourable for birds during migration? The case of the Eurasian Golden Plover   Pluvialis apricaria    Earthworms and rate of breakdown of soybean and maize residues in soil  Estimating site occupancy, colonization, and local extinction when a species is detected imperfectly  Population estimates of North American shorebirds, 2006  Parameter estimation in encounter sampling surveys  Mechanisms and control of molt  Residuals in generalized linear-models  Prairie conservation in North America  Migrating birds stop over longer than usually thought: An improved capture-recapture analysis  Moult, mass and migration of Grey Plovers   Pluvialis squatarola   wintering in South Africa  Migration stopovers and the conservation of Arctic-breeding Calidridine sandpipers  Toward conservation of midcontinental shorebird migrations  Are there optimal densities for prairie birds?  eBird: A citizen-based bird observation network in the biological sciences  A horizon scanning assessment of current and potential future threats to migratory shorebirds  Distance software: design and analysis of distance sampling surveys for estimating population size  The fly-and-social foraging hypothesis for diurnal migration: Why American Crows migrate during the day  Evaluation of automated radio telemetry for quantifying movements and home ranges of snakes  Program MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animals  Feeding and social behavior of some migrant shorebirds in southern Manitoba  Allyl isothiocyanate: An alternative chemical expellant for sampling earthworms  Moult, mass, and flight range of waders ready to take off for long-distance migrations  Stopover locations represent critical habitat in the life cycle of migratory birds and the alteration of this habitat can profoundly influence a population. American Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis dominica  ) migrate though the Midwestern United States each spring, where most natural habitat has been converted to row crop agriculture. We investigated the stopover ecology of the golden-plover in the agricultural matrix of east-central Illinois and west-central Indiana between 2008 and 2012. We found that golden-plovers remained in the region for &sim;45 days and individuals spent on average 24 days in the area before departing to the northwest. During a period of peak migration, golden-plovers preferred fields with standing water and, to a lesser extent, soybean fields. Over the 45-day stopover duration, golden-plovers moved extensively (shown by a dynamic occupancy model and area used estimation), with some evidence for tilled fields becoming unoccupied at greater rates than untilled fields. The tendency to use fields with standing water and the movement of individuals from tilled fields suggests that food accessibility, rather than food abundance, is likely a critical factor associated with the prolonged stay, movement, and field type selection of golden-plovers. Food accessibility is important to the golden-plover because they undergo molt into breeding plumage in the region and must refuel for the next leg of their migration. The Midwest is a key stopover location for American Golden-Plovers and promoting foraging conditions by manipulating the drainage of agricultural fields, via the temporary blockage of drain tiles, should be a management focus.  Los sitios de parada migratoria representan h&aacute;bitats cr&iacute;ticos en el ciclo de vida de las aves migratorias y la alteraci&oacute;n de estos h&aacute;bitats podr&iacute;a influir profundamente en una poblaci&oacute;n.   Pluvialis dominica   migra cada primavera a trav&eacute;s del medio oeste de los Estados Unidos, donde la mayor&iacute;a de los h&aacute;bitats naturales han sido convertidos en &aacute;reas agr&iacute;colas para cultivos en surco. Investigamos la ecolog&iacute;a de las paradas migratorias de   Pluvialis dominica   en la matriz agr&iacute;cola del centro-oriente de Illinois y el centro-oeste de Indiana entre 2008 y 2012. Encontramos que   P. dominica   est&aacute; presente en la regi&oacute;n aproximadamente por 45 d&iacute;as y que los individuos pararon en promedio por 24 d&iacute;as antes de partir al noroeste. Durante el periodo pico de migraci&oacute;n,   P. dominica   prefiri&oacute; los campos de cultivo con aguas estancadas y, en menor medida, los campos de soya. Durante los 45 d&iacute;as, los individuos se movieron considerablemente (evidenciado a partir de un modelo din&aacute;mico de ocupaci&oacute;n y de la estimaci&oacute;n del &aacute;rea usada) y existe alguna evidencia de que los campos cultivados se desocupan a tasas mayores que los no cultivados. Creemos que la tendencia de usar los campos con aguas estancadas y el movimiento de los individuos desde los campos cultivados sugieren que la accesibilidad al alimento, y no su abundancia, es probablemente un factor cr&iacute;tico asociado con la estad&iacute;a prolongada, el movimiento y la selecci&oacute;n del tipo de campo en   P. dominica  . Dicha accesibilidad al alimento es importante para   P. dominica   debido a que los individuos mudan a su plumaje reproductivo en esa regi&oacute;n y deben reabastecerse para la siguiente etapa de su migraci&oacute;n. El medio oeste de los Estados Unidos es una localidad clave de parada migratoria para   P. dominica   y el manejo de los campos agr&iacute;colas deber&iacute;a enfocarse en la manipulaci&oacute;n del drenaje de los mismos por medio del bloqueo temporal de los canales de desag&uuml;e para promover las buenas condiciones de alimentaci&oacute;n para esta especie.   Palabras clave:  agricultura, ave playera, ecolog&iacute;a de escalas migratorias, migraci&oacute;n, muda  Stopover locations are a critical component of a migratory bird's annual cycle and the loss or alteration of stopover habitat can negatively impact a species' population ( Skagen 2006 ). Choosing high quality stopover sites could greatly enhance the condition of migrating individuals, because the majority of time spent during migration is at stopover locations ( Hedenstrom and Alerstam 1997 ). Ideally, stopover sites provide safe (i.e. refuge from predators) access to ample food so that individuals can refuel for continued migration ( Zwarts et al. 1990 ,  Atkinson et al. 2007 ) and possibly undergo molt ( Holmgren et al. 1993 ,  Lindstr&ouml;m et al. 2010 ). Locations with these conditions are neither widespread nor well known. However, where they occur, thousands of migrating individuals may congregate ( Botton et al. 1994 ,  Andres and Browne 1998 ,  Andrei et al. 2006 ), which can represent a large percentage of the global population for some species ( Jehl 1988 ,  Jorgensen et al. 2008 ). Given their importance in a migratory species' annual cycle, it is imperative that stopover sites are identified and the aspects that make them valuable determined.  The flyway through the Midwestern United States is an important pathway for many long-distance migratory shorebirds ( Colwell 2010 ). Historically, the region contained large expanses of grasslands with wet meadows and marshes ( Prince 1997 ) that millions of migrating shorebirds depended on during migration ( Skagen et al. 1999 , Skagen and Yackel Adams 2010). However, much of the natural landscape has been lost as most of the native prairie has been converted to agriculture ( Samson and Knopf 1994 ). For instance, in Illinois, less than 1&percnt; of the original 21 million acres of prairie still exists ( Herkert et al. 1993 ), with most of the land converted to row crop agriculture, specifically corn and soybeans ( Walk et al. 2010 ). The loss of the native wetlands and prairies throughout the Midwest may be a contributing factor in the population declines of many migrating shorebirds ( Skagen 2006 ).  The American Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis dominica  , hereafter golden-plover) is a long-distance migratory shorebird that undertakes one of the longest migrations in the world, traveling from its wintering grounds in southern South America to its breeding grounds in the tundra of northern North America ( Johnson and Connors 2010 ). The yearly migration follows an elliptical pattern, with a September to November southward migration along an offshore Atlantic Ocean route followed by a midcontinental northward return from February to April ( Johnson and Connors 2010 ). Individuals typically arrive on their breeding grounds in northwestern Canada to northern Alaska in mid-May to mid-June ( Johnson and Connors 2010 ). During the northward migration, large congregations of golden-plovers have been reported in the Midwest ( Braile 1999 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010 ), with eBird observations from this region beginning in late March and continuing until the start of May ( Sullivan et al. 2009 ). In the Midwest, the species is most often found in agricultural fields ( Braile 1999 ), a habitat that is highly disturbed and not the traditional stopover habitat for the species.  How the conversion of stopover habitat has affected golden-plovers is unclear. The golden-plover must now rely on agricultural fields during its northbound migration ( Braile 1999 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010 ) because little natural habitat exists. The loss of natural habitat may have been a contributing factor in the dramatic decline of the historic population of the species ( Clay et al. 2010 ), although there is no direct evidence for this. The current population status of the golden-plover is also somewhat tenuous: The species is listed as a &ldquo;Species of High Concern&rdquo; in Canada, a species in greatest need of conservation in Illinois, a species of conservation concern in Indiana, and is approaching the population decline thresholds of the IUCN Red List ( Birdlife International 2008 ). While a multitude of factors can influence shorebird populations ( Colwell 2010 ,  Sutherland et al. 2012 ) the migration period is particularly critical ( Skagen and Knopf 1993 ,  Drent et al. 2006 ), and alteration of stopover habitat can have deleterious consequences ( Skagen 2006 ). However, very little is known about the utilization of the modern agricultural landscape by golden-plovers, and improved knowledge of stopover areas is a priority for future research ( Potter et al. 2007 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010 ).  We investigated the stopover ecology of golden-plovers to address several basic questions associated with the time they spend in east-central Illinois and west-central Indiana. Specifically, we estimated stopover duration of individuals and the window of time for which the species is present in our study area. We also investigated the migratory behavior of arriving and departing individuals, determining whether the species migrates primarily by day or at night, whether migration departures and arrivals are synchronous, and the average departure direction of migrating individuals. We examined the mass of individuals (a measure of body condition) and whether individuals were molting during their stopover in the agricultural fields of Illinois. Finally, we studied the habitats (i.e. agricultural fields) used by golden-plovers during stopover to determine whether specific fields were preferred based on agricultural crop and tillage practices and investigated whether food availability differed among field types. With these data we synthesize the factors that may be most limiting for golden-plovers stopping over in agricultural fields of the Midwest and suggest some management strategies for improving stopover habitat.  We investigated golden-plover stopover ecology between 2008 and 2012. From 2008 to 2010 we investigated habitat selection at 6 townships (93 km 2  in area) located in east-central Illinois and west-central Indiana, USA. Between 2009 and 2012 we supplemented the surveys with a targeted radio-telemetry approach that investigated movement, stopover duration, departure times, and departure direction of golden-plovers in 2 specific regions of east-central Illinois. One survey region was located east of Arcola, Illinois (Douglas County, 39&deg;41&prime;N, 88&deg;18&prime;W) and the other survey region was located south of Allerton, Illinois (Vermillion County, 39&deg;54&prime;N, 87&deg;56&prime;W), each survey region encompassing approximately 75 km 2 . Agricultural fields in our study area are typically 0.8 km &times; 0.8 km fields planted with corn or soybeans. Little natural vegetation remains, with row crops being planted to within a meter of roads and with little delineation between fields.  We captured golden-plovers from 2009 to 2012 using handheld nets and a Wilsternet ( Koopman and Hulscher 1979 ). We placed 1.2-g transmitters on 24 golden-plovers over the 4 years of our study (3 in 2009, 5 in 2010, 5 in 2011, and 11 in 2012). We used automated radio-telemetry, specifically an Automated Recording Unit (ARU; JDJC Corporation, Fisher, Illinois, USA), from 2010 to 2012, following the methods of  Ward and Raim (2011 ) and Ward et al. (2013). The ARU collected data from 6 antennas distributed 60&deg; apart and allowed us to gather daily information regarding detection and to estimate when and in what direction an individual migrated. We used this information to calculate the stopover duration of golden-plovers in the region. We categorized migratory departures from the study areas as being initiated during daylight (nautical twilight sunrise&ndash;sunset, &sim;05:10&ndash;20:40) or at night (&sim;20:40&ndash;05:10). The ARU was positioned &sim;35 km to the northwest of the study areas in 2010 and 2011 and within the Allerton study area in 2012. We also attempted to locate all birds every day or every other day using a vehicle-mounted antenna and traditional telemetry. We estimated the area used by golden-plovers during the stopover period in our region using the manual tracking data and the &lsquo;adehabitat' package in R ( Calenge 2006 ). Least-squares cross-validation was used to estimate the smoothing parameters.  We estimated stopover duration by blending 2 estimation approaches in a novel way. First, we estimated stopover duration postcapture using a mark&ndash;recapture framework described by  Schaub et al. (2001 ), which provided an estimate of stopover duration postcapture based on observed capture histories while accounting for imperfect detection. We were unable to calculate stopover duration precapture using the methods described by  Schaub et al. (2001 ) because our use of transmitters changed the detection probability pre- and post-capture. Second, we estimated stopover duration prior to known departure using encounter sampling ( Otis et al. 1993 ), which provided an estimate of stopover duration assuming the time of departure was known. However, encounter sampling alone was not a sufficient means of estimating stopover duration because detection of golden-plovers was less than 1, which violates the known-fate requirement. Therefore, we reasoned that total stopover duration could be estimated from the addition of stopover duration predeparture ( Otis et al. 1993 ) and stopover duration postcapture ( Schaub et al. 2001 ) minus the observed (or na&iuml;ve) time of residence.  We collected information on the habitat used by golden-plovers during their stopover at 2 different temporal scales. Between 2008 and 2010 we conducted habitat surveys during peak migration to investigate agricultural field type preference during this critical period. We supplemented this information by assessing field type preference over the entire stopover duration in 2012.  We surveyed for golden-plovers at the end of April over the 3-year period between 2008 and 2010. Specifically, we conducted our surveys on April 19 and 20, 2008, April 25, 2009, and April 24, 2010, which represented one survey per field per year. We surveyed near the end of April because golden-plovers are typically most abundant around this time period when migrating through our study area, based on reported observations by local birders ( Sullivan et al. 2009 ). We conducted our surveys in 6 townships in east-central Illinois and west-central Indiana. We utilized the township unit to standardize our surveys and chose 30 random locations within each township, located at the midpoints of each east&ndash;west section road. Consequently, the centers of our sampling locations were at least 1.6 km apart. At each sampling location, we conducted a 5-min visual search of the 4 fields in the intermediate directions (NW, NE, SW, SE) and recorded the presence of golden-plovers.  We collected information on the type of agricultural field (corn, soybean, or other) and type of tillage practice employed (intensive tillage: largely bare ground; conservation tillage: &gt;30&percnt; soil surface covered with crop residue; and stubble: basal parts remaining) on each field surveyed. The high-intensity agriculture of the landscape led to 6 unique field classifications (corn stubble, corn conservation, corn tilled, soy stubble, soy tilled, and other). We also classified the moisture level of each field as dry, wet, or standing water present (&gt;1 m 2  pool of water).  In 2012 we conducted a season-long assessment of the agricultural fields used by golden-plovers in the Arcola and Allerton survey regions. We utilized the north&ndash;south, east&ndash;west layout of the county roads to thoroughly survey both focal areas. We drove at a rate of &lt;35 km hr &minus;1 , scanning the surrounding fields for congregations of golden-plovers. We noted the agricultural crop (soybeans, corn, other) and the tillage practice employed (tilled, untilled) in each quarter section (0.8 km &times; 0.8 km&mdash;the most common field size) as well as the presence or absence of golden-plovers. In total, we surveyed 160 fields in the Arcola region and 161 in the Allerton region (we excluded areas with high amounts &lsqb;&gt;50&percnt;&rsqb; of development, as these areas never contained golden-plovers and were too infrequent to warrant inclusion in our analyses). Each survey was concluded by resurveying an east&ndash;west or north&ndash;south road that had been previously surveyed 2&ndash;3 hr prior, which allowed us to resample approximately 20&percnt; of all fields. We conducted 8 surveys, separated by 5&ndash;6 days on average, in each location between the end of March and the beginning of May. This time period coincided with the arrival and subsequent departure of golden-plovers in the area.  We monitored the plumage of golden-plovers during our habitat surveys in 2012 to determine whether golden-plovers used their stopover time in central Illinois to molt into breeding plumage. We recorded the proportion of each congregation that was in 3 classes of plumage: winter plumage (&lt;10&percnt; breeding plumage), transitional plumage (10&ndash;90&percnt; breeding plumage), and breeding plumage (&gt;90&percnt; breeding plumage).  We determined whether agricultural fields differed in earthworm abundance and biomass. We sampled earthworms because golden-plovers are known to eat them ( Bent 1929 ,  Wishart et al. 1981 ,  Braile 1999 , K. W. Stodola personal observation) and preliminary surveys suggested that there were few other forage items available. We used a chemical method of earthworm extraction that has been shown to outperform hand sorting ( Zaborski 2003 ). We sampled 36 different fields in 2011 and 2012, gathering 1&ndash;6 samples per field. Each sample consisted of a 0.5 m 2  patch of soil to which we added 10 L of extraction solution. The extraction solution consisted of allyl isothiocyanate diluted to a concentration of 100 mg L &minus;1  with isopropanol and water ( Zaborski 2003 ). Finally, we weighed 10 individuals (3 in 2009, 3 in 2011, and 3 in 2012) using a spring-loaded Pesola scale.  We calculated the amount of time for which golden-plovers were present after capture by modeling apparent survival ( Lebreton et al. 1992 ), which is a good approximation of permanent emigration if mortality is assumed to be zero (we detected no mortality). We estimated stopover duration postcapture using the Live Recaptures extensions in Program MARK ( White and Burnham 1999 ). We fit 6 different models describing daily survival. Daily survival was modeled as constant within and among years, as a function of year, and as a function of date within year. Detection was modeled as either constant among years or as a function of year. We estimated stopover duration predeparture using the methods of  Otis et al. (1993 ) and program DISTANCE ( Thomas et al. 2010 ). Specifically, we calculated strip width (i.e. stopover duration;  Lehnen and Krementz 2005 ) by fitting the probability density function using 3 different models: uniform key with a cosine adjustment; uniform key with a simple polynomial adjustment; and half-normal key with a cosine adjustment. We compared candidate models of postcapture and predeparture stopover duration using second-order Akaike's information criterion adjusted for small sample size (AIC c ;  Burnham and Anderson 2002 ) and provide model-averaged estimates where appropriate. Finally, we used 100,000 Monte-Carlo simulations to calculate confidence intervals around our estimate of stopover duration, because each estimate (predeparture, observed, postcapture) was derived from different distributions.  We investigated the frequency with which fields were used by golden-plovers and how they varied based on our categorical predictors prior to analyzing habitat selection during peak migration. We failed to observe any golden-plovers in the field classification &ldquo;other&rdquo; ( n  &equals; 120) and deleted this group of fields from the analysis. We used logistic regression to investigate the influence that agricultural crop, tillage practice, and soil moisture had on golden-plover observations in a field. We focused on presence or absence of golden-plover congregations because less than 6&percnt; of fields were occupied. Inclusion of abundance therefore provided little additional information concerning field use by golden-plovers. A Hosmer-Lemeshow ( Hosmer and Lemeshow 1989 ) goodness-of-fit test on a model that included year, township, soil type, soil moisture, and field character failed to indicate any lack of fit of the data ( P  &equals; 0.19). However, a plot of the deviance residuals ( Pierce and Schafer 1986 ) indicated dependence among points nested within townships. Consequently, we incorporated both township and location nested within township as random effects, while agricultural crop, tillage practice, and soil moisture were treated as fixed effects. The dispersion parameter (Pearson chi-square/degrees of freedom) from this model failed to indicate any overdispersion of the data ( &ccirc;  &lt; 1).  We evaluated the relative fit of 8 models that included agricultural crop, tillage practice, soil moisture, combinations of these predictors, and the interaction between agricultural crop and tillage practice. We compared competing models using second-order Akaike's information criterion adjusted for small sample size (AIC c ;  Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). We report log-odds ratios for the parameter estimates from the best-fitting model to facilitate comparisons.  We assessed season-long habitat preferences in 2012 using a dynamic occupancy model ( MacKenzie et al. 2003 ). We first modeled how detection of golden-plovers was related to agricultural crop and tillage practice while keeping occupancy constant. We then modeled how colonization (arrival) and extinction (departure) were related to survey region, agricultural crop, and tillage practice while using the best-fitting detection model. We kept initial occupancy constant since we began our surveys at the beginning of the year when fields were unoccupied. We fit models using the function  colext  in the &lsquo;unmarked' package in R ( Fiske and Chandler 2011 ) and compared model performance using AIC c .  Finally, we investigated the pattern of molt over the course of the stopover duration using logistic regression on the percentage of a congregation classified as primarily in winter plumage and classified as primarily in breeding plumage. We analyzed the proportion of golden-plovers that departed during the day in relation to total daylight hours using a chi-square test. We evaluated earthworm abundance using a zero-inflated Poisson model with agricultural field (crop type and tillage practice) and survey region as fixed effects and field as a random effect. Earthworm biomass was log-transformed prior to analysis and we used a generalized linear model with a normal distribution and identity link, including survey regions as fixed effects and field as a random effect.  American Golden-Plovers were present in agricultural fields in east-central Illinois for &sim;45 days, with detections beginning at the end of March and lasting until mid-May ( Figure 1 ). Median capture date was April 19, which was the approximate midpoint of when golden-plovers were present in our region ( Figure 1 ). Minimum stopover duration (days from radio-transmitter attachment to last detection) averaged 11.4 &plusmn; 1.6 SE days. The longest observed stopover was 29 days and the shortest was 2 days. The best-fitting model describing stopover duration postcapture included detection as a function of year and time to departure as constant within and among years ( Table 1 ). Mean detection estimates ranged from 0.95 in 2009 when only 3 golden-plovers were tracked to 0.50 in 2012 when we tracked 11 golden-plovers; mean estimates in 2010 and 2011 were 0.60 and 0.64 respectively. The estimate from the best-fitting model suggested that golden-plovers remained in the region for 14.2 days (95&percnt; CI &equals; 9.0&ndash;22.5 days) after being captured. Stopover duration prior to departure using program DISTANCE and encounter sampling suggested a stopover duration of 20.4 days (95&percnt; CI &equals; 14.6&ndash;28.4 days). Total stopover duration estimated by combining the 2 approaches was 23.7 days (95&percnt; CI &equals; 17.5&ndash;33.1 days).  We observed golden-plovers on &sim;5&percnt; of fields (93 of 1,966) over the 3 years of the study, irrespective of township or location within township. We observed the highest percentage of fields occupied by golden-plovers in 2010 (5.6&percnt;) and the lowest percentage in 2009 (3.6&percnt;). We had a high count of 2,992 individuals in one township in 2010. The best-fitting model explaining golden-plover observations, which received 70&percnt; of the weight of evidence ( Table 2 ), included crop type and soil moisture. Although there was a high amount of model uncertainty, the importance of tillage practice appeared to be much lower than that of crop type (models with only those predictors had &Delta;AIC c  &equals; 16). In addition, the additive models that included tillage practice with crop type improved model performance approximately as much as random data. Consequently, we believe there is strong evidence that crop type and soil moisture are the most important predictors of golden-plover observations.  Golden-plovers were more likely to be observed in fields with standing water in comparison with fields that were &ldquo;wet&rdquo; or &ldquo;dry.&rdquo; Specifically, golden-plovers were 11 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 3&ndash;30) and 22 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 7&ndash;71) times more likely to be found in fields with standing water than in wet and dry fields respectively. Golden-plovers were also 5.2 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 2.7&ndash;9.9) times more likely to be observed in soybean than in corn fields.  We found little evidence that detection of golden-plovers differed by agricultural crop (AIC c  &equals; 728.1) or tillage practice (AIC c  &equals; 733.6) in comparison with the constant detection model (AIC c  &equals; 726.5). Detection of golden-plovers was 0.50 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 0.33&ndash;0.66). The best-fitting occupancy model included colonization as a function of survey region and extinction as a function of tillage practice ( Table 3 ). Initial site occupancy was low. We estimated that 5&percnt; (95&percnt; CI &equals; 2&ndash;10&percnt;) of fields were occupied, irrespective of survey region. During stopover, fields near Allerton, Illinois, were on average 5.6 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 2.8&ndash;11.7) times more likely to have golden-plovers use them if they were previously unused in comparison with fields near Arcola, Illinois. However, the probability of an unused field becoming used was still relatively low for both areas: &sim;2&percnt; (95&percnt; CI &equals; 0&ndash;3&percnt;) near Arcola and &sim;9&percnt; (95&percnt; CI &equals; 5&ndash;13&percnt;) near Allerton. The probability of a used field becoming unoccupied between surveys was most dependent on field tillage practice ( Table 3 ). Although the evidence was somewhat equivocal and our estimation imprecise, a tilled field with golden-plovers was 7.3 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 0.8&ndash;67.0) times more likely to become unoccupied than an untilled field. Most fields with golden-plovers would not have golden-plovers on a subsequent survey with 71&percnt; (95&percnt; CI &equals; 47&ndash;87&percnt;) of untilled fields and 88&percnt; (95&percnt; CI &equals; 45&ndash;98&percnt;) of tilled fields becoming unoccupied between surveys.  The high turnover among occupied sites indicated substantial movement by golden-plovers. This movement was illustrated by the area used estimates for the 4 individuals for which we had sufficient information, which ranged from 1,706 ha to 56,034 ha, with a median area of 9,962 ha ( Figure 2 ).  Departure from the study area was synchronous within a year. Five of the 11 radio-tagged birds left on April 25, 2012, with another 3 individuals leaving within 4 days of that date. In 2011, 4 of the 5 birds with transmitters left within 4 days of May 13, while in 2010, 4 of the 5 birds with transmitters left within 2 days of May 8. We determined that 12 birds departed and migrated in a northwesterly direction (300&deg; &plusmn; 2.3&deg; SE), one departed almost due north (355&deg;), and the other individual left the study area heading to the northeast (40&deg;). Nearly every individual (13 of 14) initiated migration during daylight hours ( &chi; 2  &equals; 4.89,  P  &equals; 0.03).  Our study area appears to be an important area for molt: The percentage of birds in breeding plumage changed from 0&percnt; early in the season to nearly 100&percnt; later in the season ( Figure 3 ). On several occasions we noted that an individual that had been caught and radio-tagged in basic plumage was seen molting into alternate plumage and in some cases was observed in full alternate plumage before it departed.  We found no difference in earthworm abundance or biomass related to year (abundance: &chi; 2  &equals; 0.10,  P  &equals; 0.76; biomass: &chi; 2  &equals; 1.50,  P  &equals; 0.22), region (abundance: &chi; 2  &equals; 2.42,  P  &equals; 0.12; biomass: &chi; 2  &equals; 2.89,  P  &equals; 0.09) or crop type (abundance: &chi; 2  &equals; 0.63,  P  &equals; 0.73; biomass: &chi; 2  &equals; 1.59,  P  &equals; 0.45). Earthworm abundance was highly variable both within a field and among fields ( Figure 4 ). There was also a large amount of variability in the mass of golden-plovers among years. Average mass (range) was 158 g (147&ndash;173 g) in 2009, 170 g (151&ndash;190 g) in 2010, and 226 g (200&ndash;238 g) in 2012.  American Golden-Plovers make an extended stopover in the Midwestern agricultural fields of our study area. We used a novel approach to estimate stopover duration by combining 2 analytical methods ( Otis et al. 1993 ,  Schaub et al. 2001 ). We took this approach because our data did not meet the assumptions of each method independently, and we believe that more quantitative development of such approaches would be useful. Using this combined analysis, we found that golden-plovers stayed in our region for approximately 24 days. The extended time that golden-plovers spend in Midwestern agricultural fields highlights the importance of the area, since golden-plovers engage in one of the longest migrations in the world and spend a considerable portion of the year doing so. The species spends less than 60 days on the breeding grounds in the tundra ( Johnson and Connors 2010 ), so it was surprising that individuals spent such an extended period in the row crop agricultural fields of east-central Illinois. Row crops are not traditionally considered good wildlife habitat, yet they are the dominant land cover across the modern Midwestern landscape. Thus, golden-plovers may be using row crop fields out of necessity and not because of quality. The enormous area that golden-plovers traverse during their stopover period may illustrate their constant search for high-quality sites within this nontraditional habitat.  Golden-plovers exhibited an overwhelming tendency to use fields with standing water in comparison with dry and wet fields during the period of peak migration. Fields with standing water are highly ephemeral in our region because they quickly drain due to the ubiquitous use of drain tile (perforated plastic tubes buried in fields to facilitate the removal of excess water from a field), yet golden-plovers actively sought them out. Fields with standing water are likely used by golden-plovers because soil moisture influences the availability of earthworms at the soil surface ( Gerard 1967 ). Earthworms are a preferred food source for migrating golden-plovers ( Wishart et al. 1981 ,  Braile 1999 ). Our sampling suggested little difference among agricultural fields with regard to earthworm abundance, which is not unexpected given the homogeneity of the landscape and frequent crop rotations. However, we were sampling earthworms below the soil surface ( Zaborski 2003 ), which may not be accessible to golden-plovers. Therefore, golden-plovers may seek out fields with standing water where earthworms are more available and closer to the soil surface.  Golden-plovers also preferred fields that had been planted in soybeans the previous year during the period of peak migration. Golden-plovers forage at greater rates in tilled soybean fields in comparison with other habitats ( Braile 1999 ) and other researchers have also noted that golden-plovers prefer soybean fields ( Erickson 1992 ,  Braile 1999 ). Although our sampling failed to indicate any difference among fields in terms of earthworm abundance, fields that have been permanently planted in soybeans have greater abundance and biomass of earthworms compared with fields that are permanently planted in corn ( Mackay and Kladivko 1985 ). However, because nearly all agricultural fields in our area rotate soybean and corn on a yearly basis, crop rotation likely diminishes any effect of crop type on earthworm abundance. Thus, we may have observed golden-plovers in soybean fields because soybean fields are often tilled earlier in the year to allow spring planting of corn. Tilling makes earthworms immediately accessible to golden-plovers as moist soil is brought to the surface. Anecdotally, we would observe golden-plovers flying between freshly plowed fields where the soil had recently been turned. Local farmers would also relate similar stories of large congregations of birds flying in behind their plows. Birds would forage in these fields for a day or two and then move on.  Our dynamic occupancy analysis and home range estimates demonstrate how much golden-plovers are moving around the landscape and the importance of various habitat types. Very few fields are used by golden-plovers at any one time, with most fields becoming unused at later time periods. As we alluded to previously, the ephemeral nature of fields with standing water probably drives this pattern. Although 2012 was an extremely dry year and no fields had standing water, fields that had just been tilled had wet soil. These fields would quickly dry out (within 1&ndash;2 days), which probably contributed to our observation that tillage practices influenced the temporal utilization of a field by golden-plovers. Furthermore, we only observed golden-plovers in a small proportion of untilled fields, yet these fields may represent an important habitat component. Every morning we observed thousands of golden-plovers leaving from a few select fields with standing corn stubble and at night they were observed returning, indicating a disproportionate and important use of this habitat type during the night. Fields with standing corn stubble provide one of the few places with remaining vegetation cover, which may offer the best protection from nocturnal predators, although more research is necessary.  Migrating golden-plovers utilized our study area in large numbers, even though they were constantly moving in search of high-quality sites and food. We observed nearly 4,000 individuals during one survey in one township, although the true number is likely higher. A minimum of 4,000 individuals represents nearly 2&percnt; of the estimated global population ( Morrison et al. 2006 ) stopping over in a relatively small region of east-central Illinois, signifying the importance of the region. The ability to gain mass during stopover is a sign of high-quality habitat ( Zwarts et al. 1990 ,  Gudmundsson et al. 1991 ) and is exhibited in other closely related species occupying high-quality areas ( Johnson et al. 1989 ,  Serra et al. 1999 ). Of the birds we caught during our study, most were at least as heavy as has been observed on the breeding grounds ( Johnson and Connors 2010 ), indicating that birds were not emaciated. However, no data exist for condition of golden-plovers during migration so we have little with which to compare.  High fuel intake is necessary for migrating individuals because this is one of the most energetically demanding times during their annual cycle. We observed golden-plovers undergoing a near-complete molt of their body feathers from basic to alternate plumage during their stopover period in east-central Illinois. Molt is an energetically demanding process for birds ( Payne 1972 ), and golden-plovers must both molt and refuel for the next leg of their migration. Golden-plovers predominantly left during the day and, based on the direction of departing golden-plovers (&sim;300&deg;), we estimated that individuals would travel another 3,500 km to reach their breeding grounds. Using a tracking vehicle, we followed one migrating golden-plover from east-central Illinois to central Iowa before we lost the bird; these data suggest that this individual migrated at a rate of 56 km hr &minus;1  on average. If birds averaged 56 km hr &minus;1 , it would require an additional 62 hr of flight to reach the breeding grounds. Arrival at the breeding grounds by late May would require many individuals to migrate 3,500 km in &sim;2 weeks. Even if these individuals stopped to refuel and rest, they would not be able to spend the same amount of time as they did in our study area. Therefore, the time they spend in our region appears to be critical.  The agricultural fields of the Midwestern United States present an interesting opportunity for the conservation of migrating American Golden-Plovers. As a whole the region is likely to be composed of lower-quality habitats than were historically present; however, the area remains an important stopover area. The closely related Eurasian Golden-Plover also exhibits a similar predisposition towards using intensively farmed lands and the species performs quite well in this habitat ( Lindstr&ouml;m et al. 2010 ). Although row crop agriculture may not be optimal habitat for migrating plovers, because they move extensively while stopping over in our region, targeted conservation actions could be successful in improving agricultural habitat for plovers.  Agriculture throughout the Midwest has been made possible by artificial surface and subsurface draining of fields ( Pavelis 1987 ). The use of drain tiles for subsurface draining is exceptionally prevalent in Illinois and Indiana, where nearly 7 million hectares of cropland are artificially drained ( Sugg 2007 ). However, draining only needs to take place prior to the planting of fields, which typically occurs in early May for corn and late May for soybeans in Illinois and Indiana (U.S. Department of Agriculture 2010). Most golden-plovers will have left this region before corn, and especially soybeans, would need to be planted. Consequently, temporarily blocking drain tiles to promote the flooding of fields during the late winter and early spring could provide valuable foraging locations, while minimizing costs to agriculture. The propensity of golden-plovers to utilize flooded fields suggests that these areas could provide stable foraging locations and reduce the energetic costs of searching for food, thereby increasing the quality of stopover habitat in Illinois and Indiana.  We thank Dave Enstrom, Misty Barron, Arlo Raim, Ben Neece, Amber Wingert, Jake Hennig, Matt McKim-Louder, Megan Bales, Kelly VanBeek, Addison Demanes, John Bender, and the University of Illinois Wildlife Society for assistance in the field. We are grateful to the Illinois Department of Natural Resources, Illinois Ornithological Society, and U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Division of Migratory Birds for funding this project. We are also appreciative of the many landowners who allowed us to capture and monitor birds on their property.  Phenology of American Golden-Plover presence in central Illinois, USA, as demonstrated by the largest count of American Golden-Plovers detected during each week of the 2012 stopover period. The start of week 1 corresponds to March 30.  Area used estimates for 4 American Golden-Plovers with radio transmitters during spring migration in 2009, 2010, and 2011 in central Illinois, USA. Different polygons represent different individuals with sufficient information to estimate area used, and demonstrate that American Golden-Plovers use extremely large areas during their stopover, ranging from 1,706 ha to 56,034 ha. The dark box in the inset map of Illinois indicates the approximate location of our study region.  Proportion of individual American Golden-Plovers (mean and 95&percnt; confidence interval) in winter (&lt;10&percnt; breeding plumage) and breeding (&gt;90&percnt; breeding plumage) plumage in Douglas and Vermillion County, Illinois, USA, between March 27 and May 11, 2012.  Earthworms, which are a prominent food item in the diet of migrating American Golden-Plovers through the Midwest, detected per field grouped by agricultural crop. We found no earthworms in untilled corn. Sampling effort varied among fields (1&ndash;6 samples per field). Error bars represent 1 standard error.  Comparison of candidate models describing stopover duration postcapture (i.e. daily survival rate;  Schaub et al. 2001 ) of American Golden-Plovers in Illinois, USA, in 2012. Stopover duration postcapture (&phiv;) was modeled as either constant (.), or as a function of year or date. Detection ( p ) was modeled as either constant (.) or as a function of year. Models were ranked based on Akaike's information criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC c ) and weights of evidence ( w i  ).  K  is the number of model parameters and &Delta;AIC c  is the difference in AIC c  from the top model.  Comparison of logistic regression models relating American Golden-Plover observations at 6 townships in central Illinois and Indiana, USA, to the field characteristics of agricultural crop (CROP), tillage practice (TILL), and soil moisture (MOISTURE). Surveys were conducted at the end of April in 2008, 2009, and 2010. Year was included as a fixed effect in all models, and township and specific location within each township were included as random effects. Models were ranked based on Akaike's information criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC c ) and weights of evidence ( w i  ).  K  is the number of model parameters and &Delta;AIC c  is the difference in AIC c  from the top model.  Comparison of dynamic occupancy models relating American Golden-Plover observations to survey region (SITE), agricultural crop (CROP), and tillage practice (TILL). Constant detection was the best-fitting detection model and therefore detection was held constant. Models were ranked based on Akaike's information criterion (AIC) and weights of evidence ( w i  ).  K  is the number of model parameters, &Delta;AIC is the difference in AIC from the top model, &psi; is initial occupancy, &epsiv; is extinction probability, &gamma; is colonization probability, and  p  is detection probability. 