 Thank You to the Reviewers of the 2014  Condor , Volume 116   pstouffer@lsu.edu    The Condor's  116 th  year saw significant changes to the journal. We moved to online publishing, combined journal management and production with  The Auk: Ornithological Advances , and, most importantly, redefined the journal's name and mission as  The Condor: Ornithological Applications . Despite all of these changes, the journal's scientific foundation remains with the peer review process. Peer reviewers receive little reward, but their timely and diligent work allows us to make the journal as strong as it can be. In the name of all of us who have been involved in launching  The Condor: Ornithological Applications , I thank all of you who contributed reviews during the period that Volume 116 was in preparation (reviews completed between September 1, 2013, and August 31, 2014). Individuals identified with asterisks are especially dedicated; they reviewed two, three, or even four manuscripts.   The Condor: Ornithological Applications  also gratefully acknowledges the work and commitment of our two fine Editors, our busy Associate Editors, and the superb editorial team at the Central Ornithology Publication Office (COPO). The new look and content of 2014 attest to their dedicated collective efforts.  Ken Abraham  Marissa Ahlering  Cameron Aldridge  Courtney Amundson  Angela Anders&ast;  Beatriz Arroyo  Jonathan Atwood  Blake Barbaree  Thomas Benson  Marcello Bertellotti  Christine Bishop  Jeffrey Black  John Blake  Erik Blomberg  Alexander Bond&ast;  Carlos Bosque  Reed Bowman&ast;  Clait Braun  Jay Carlisle  Daniel Catlin  Antonio Celis-Murillo  David Cerasale  Richard Chandler  Roy Churchwell  Carla Cicero  Mariano Codesido  Nigel Collar  Bret Collier&ast;  John Connelly  Jacob Cooper  Francesca Cuthbert  Jeremy Dertien  Randall DeYoung  Stephen Dinsmore&ast;  Barny Dunning  Robert Dusek  Chris Elphick  Matthew Etterson&ast;  Andrew Farnsworth&ast;  Ryan Fisher  Curtis Flather  Leonard Freed  Sidney Gauthreaux, Jr.  T. George  Jennifer Gervais&ast;  Frank Gill  Thomas Gottschalk  Cheri Gratto-Trevor  Adam Green&ast;  M. Green  Juan Guayasamin  Ralph Gutierrez  Michael Guttery  Linnea Hall  Colleen Handel  Steven Hanser  Patrick Hart  Garth Herring  Jason Hill  Kyle Horton  David Howerter  Luis Hurtado  Richard Hutto&ast;  Douglas Johnson  Andrew Jones  Leo Joseph  Romain Julliard  Yula Kapatenakos  Jeffrey Kelly  Kevin Kenow  Paul Kerlinger  Matthew Kirchhoff  John Klicka  Jonas Knape  Jessie Knowlton  William Kristan  Ron Larkin  Quresh Latif&ast;  Aleksi Lehikoinen  Xingong Li  Sara Lipshutz  Alberto Macias Duarte  Ivan Maggini  James Maley  Raivo Mand  Stuart Marsden  Kyle McCarthy  David Mehlman  Daniel Mennill  Tricia Miller  David Miller  Ara Monadjem  William Monahan  Michael Morrison  Joan Morrison  Antoine Nappi  Zoltan Nemeth  Christopher Nicolai  Joseph Nocera&ast;  Erica Nol&ast;  Timothy O'Connell&ast;  Darcy Ogada  Ken Otter  Susan Pagano  Monica Papes  Guillaume Peron  Bradley Pickens  Luke Powell  Larkin Powell&ast;  Christin Pruett&ast;  Robert Rempel  Richard Reynolds  S. James Reynolds  Gregory Robertson  Erin Roche  Kenneth Rosenberg  Jay Rotella  J. Andrew Royle  Mark Rumble  Victoria Saab  Sarah Saalfeld  Emi Saito  Alejandro Salinas-Melgoza  Brett Sandercock  Hanno Sandvik  Michael Schroeder  James Sedinger  Nathan Senner  W. Gregory Shriver  Dave Shutler&ast;  Theodore Simons  Peter Singleton  Robert Smith  Paul Smith  Peter Solymos  Christopher Somers  Sarah Sonsthagen  Garth Spellman  Jessica Stanton  Karen Steenhof  Kirk Stodola  Eric Stolen  Craig Stricker  Phil Taylor  Sabrina Taylor&ast;  Morgan Tingley  Philip Unitt  Amanda Van Dellen  Eric VanderWerf  Vincent Viblanc  Peter Vickery  Kerri Vierling  Margaret Voss  Nils Warnock&ast;  Rekha Warrier  Brian Washburn  Stephen Webb  Walter Wehtje  Nathaniel Wheelright  Scott Wilson  David Wilson  Virginia Winder  Kristopher Winiarski  Stefan Woltmann  Petra Wood  Yuri Zharikov  Victor Zwiener 