Offspring sex ratio varies according to nest location within a colony of Great CormorantsSurvival of the kittiwake in relation to sex, year, breeding experience and position in the colonyFemale body condition and brood sex ratio in Yellow-legged Gull <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus cachinnans</named-content></italic>Reproductive success in the cormorant <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax carbo</named-content> carbo</italic> in relation to colony nest position and timing of nestingEffects of nest density, location and timing of breeding success of Caspian TernsEffects of coloniality on gull predation on Common Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>) chicksSex ratio adjustments in Common Terns: Influence of mate condition and maternal experienceInfluence of sibling competition on nestling sex ratios of sexually dimorphic birdsDiet, maternal condition, and offspring sex ratio in the Zebra FinchEta-squared and partial eta-squared in fixed factor ANOVA designDifferences in the quality of birds nesting in the center and on the edges of a colonyBreeding-success relative to nest location and density in Ring-billed Gull coloniesSex ratio adjustment in relation to paternal attractiveness in a wild bird populationSex ratio in Lesser Black-backed Gull in relation to environmental pollutantsA simple and universal method for molecular sexing of non-ratite birdsColonial breeding reduces nest predation in the Common Gull (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus canus</named-content></italic>)A DNA test to sex most birdsSex-biased environmental sensitivity: Natural and experimental evidence from a bird species with larger femalesExtra-pair paternity results from female preference for high-quality males in the Blue TitSexual dimorphism in the cormorant <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax carbo</named-content> sinensis</italic>: Possible implications for differences in structural sizePotential mechanisms for sex ratio adjustment in mammals and birdsNest placement choice in cormorants (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax auritus</named-content></italic>) from the Madeleine Islands, Qu&eacute;becSex determination of Great Cormorants (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax carbo</named-content> sinensis</italic>) using morphometric measurementsFood availability and offspring sex in a monogamous seabird: Insights from an experimental approachEvolution of within-colony distribution patterns of birds in response to habitat structureIs it always beneficial to breed in the center? Trade-offs in nest site selection within the colony of a tree-nesting waterbirdDistribution of pair quality in a tree-nesting waterbird colony: Central&ndash;periphery model vs. satellite modelSpatial variation in clutch size and egg size within the colony of Whiskered Terns (<italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>)Nest location affects chick growth rates in Whiskered Terns <italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>An experimental study on the causes of sex-biased mortality in the Black-headed Gull&mdash;The possible role of testosteroneExperimental demonstration that offspring sex ratio varies with maternal conditionParental condition, brood sex ratio and differential brood survival: An experimental study in gulls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus fuscus</named-content></italic>)Coloniality of Brown Booby (<italic>Sula leucogaster</italic>) in Gorgona National Natural Park, Eastern Tropical PacificTiming and spacing of broods in the Black-headed Gull <italic>Larus rididbundus</italic>Experimental evidence that corticosterone affects offspring sex ratios in quailExtrinsic modification of vertebrate sex ratios by climatic variationMothers under stress? Hatching sex ratio in relation to maternal baseline corticosterone in the Common Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>)Geostatistical tool for modelling and interpreting ecological spatial dependenceMeiotic drive and sex determination: Molecular and cytological mechanisms of sex ratio adjustment in birdsMaternal investment during egg laying and offspring sex: An experimental study of Zebra FinchesSex allocation in Yellow-legged Gulls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus michahellis</named-content></italic>) depends on nutritional constraints on production of large last eggsStressed mothers lay eggs with high corticosterone levels which produce low-quality offspringNesting density is an important factor affecting chick growth and survival in the Herring GullPredators as stressors? Physiological and reproductive consequences of predation risk in tropical Stonechats (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Saxicola torquata</named-content> axillaris</italic>)Sex difference in criteria determining fidelity towards breeding sites in the Great CormorantUltraviolet colour variation influences Blue Tit sex ratiosBreeding performance of the Imperial Shag (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax atriceps</named-content></italic>) in relation to year, laying date and nest locationMate quality affects offspring sex ratio in Blue TitsFemale-biased mortality in nestlings of a bird with size dimorphismNatural selection of parental ability to vary the sex ratio of offspringHow general is the central-periphery distribution among seabird colonies? Nest spatial pattern in the European ShagSex ratio in relation to timing of breeding, and laying sequence in a dimorphic seabirdAge and breeding success in relation to nest position in a White Stork <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ciconia ciconia</named-content></italic> colonyMeasuring the effects of pairing success, extra-pair copulations and mate quality on the opportunity for sexual selectionSex differences in parental investment and chick growth in Wandering AlbatrossesPopulation sex ratio variation in a monogamous long-lived bird, the Wandering AlbatrossOffspring sex ratios in Tree Swallows: Females in better condition produce more sonsEffects of extra-pair and within-pair reproductive success on the opportunity for selection in birdsExtra-pair fertilizations increase the opportunity for sexual selection in the monogamous House Martin <italic>Delichon urbica</italic>Late-breeding Great Cormorants <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax carbo</named-content> sinensis</italic> produce fewer young of the more vulnerable sexPredation by Kelp Gulls <italic>Larus dominicanus</italic> at a mixed-species colony of Royal Terns <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna maxima</named-content></italic> and Cayenne Terns <italic>Sterna eurygnatha</italic> in PatagoniaOffspring sex ratio in birds is adjusted according to the relative fitness payoff of producing sons and daughters, which is known to depend on parental quality. Therefore, spatial patterns in offspring sex ratio should be consistent with the distribution of pair quality within avian colonies. In many colonial birds, central parts of colonies provide greater safety against predators and thus are occupied by high-quality pairs, who relegate conspecifics of poorer quality to the peripheral zones of colonies. For this reason, we expected that offspring sex ratio was likely to follow similar central&ndash;periphery gradients. This hypothesis was tested in a colony of tree-nesting Great Cormorants (<italic>Phalacorcorax carbo sinensis</italic>) in central Poland, where 204 nestlings from 53 broods were molecularly sexed. We found a clear central&ndash;periphery pattern in offspring sex ratio within the studied colony. There was a considerable bias toward male offspring in the broods of centrally nesting pairs, while edge pairs invested more in female progeny. We also found that broods with a higher proportion of male offspring were associated with higher nesting densities. A nonrandom distribution of offspring sex ratio within the studied colony of Great Cormorants indicates that special care should be taken by researchers to randomize sampling of broods when studying sex allocation in colonial species.La proporci&oacute;n de sexos de la progenie en aves se ajusta de acuerdo a la ganancia relativa de aptitud al producir machos o hembras, lo cual depende de la calidad de los padres. Por ende, los patrones espaciales en la proporci&oacute;n de sexos de la progenie deber&iacute;an coincidir con la distribuci&oacute;n de la calidad de los padres en las colonias de aves. En muchas aves coloniales, las partes centrales de la colonia proveen mayor seguridad contra depredadores. Por ello, estas partes son ocupadas por parejas de alta calidad, lo que relega a los individuos coespec&iacute;ficos de menor calidad a las zonas perif&eacute;ricas de la colonia. Por esta raz&oacute;n, esperamos que la proporci&oacute;n de sexos de la progenie probablemente siga un patr&oacute;n similar de gradiente centro-periferia. Esta hip&oacute;tesis fue puesta a prueba en una colonia de <italic>Phalacorcorax carbo sinensis</italic> en el centro de Polonia, donde se determin&oacute; molecularmente el sexo de 204 polluelos de 53 nidadas. Encontramos un patr&oacute;n claro centro-periferia en la proporci&oacute;n de sexos de la progenie en la colonia estudiada. Hubo un sesgo considerable hacia polluelos macho en las nidadas de las parejas que se ubicaban en el centro de la colonia, mientras que las parejas de la periferia invirtieron m&aacute;s en polluelos hembra. Tambi&eacute;n encontramos que las nidadas con una mayor proporci&oacute;n de polluelos macho se asociaron con mayores densidades de nidos. La distribuci&oacute;n no aleatoria de la proporci&oacute;n de sexos en la progenie de la colonia de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. carbo</named-content> sinensis</italic> indica que los investigadores deben tener especial cuidado al aleatorizar el muestreo de las nidadas en estudios sobre la porporci&oacute;n de sexos en especies coloniales.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> autocorrelaci&oacute;n espacial, colonialidad, gen CHD, <italic>Phalacorcorax carbo sinensis</italic>, proporci&oacute;n de sexosSince the fitness benefits of rearing sons and daughters may vary considerably, there could be a strong selective pressure acting on offspring sex ratio in populations of vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Trivers1">Trivers and Willard 1973</xref>). Two major mechanisms are likely to be responsible for departures from an equal sex ratio under random segregation of chromosomes. A skewed sex ratio may be attributed to differential mortality of nestlings in the early stage of development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Krackow1">Krackow 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Muller1">M&uuml;ller et al. 2005</xref>), which could result from selective provisioning by parents or, alternatively, from different vulnerability of sexes to unfavorable rearing conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Nager2">Nager et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Kalmbach1">Kalmbach et al. 2005</xref>). However, there is also increasing empirical evidence that females may, at least to some extent, control chromosomal segregation in relation to the environmental and social circumstances experienced at laying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Post1">Post et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Sheldon1">Sheldon et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Torres1">Torres and Drummond 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Rutkowska1">Rutkowska and Badyaev 2008</xref>). It is widely recognized that the condition of females during egg formation may play a significant role in the sex determination of offspring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Whittingham1">Whittingham and Dunn 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Rutkowska2">Rutkowska and Cicho&nacute; 2002</xref>).On the other hand, fitness benefits that parents gain through rearing offspring of either sex are also likely to vary with their condition. In many avian species, males have greater variance in reproductive success than females, mainly due to the possibility of siring numerous extra-pair offspring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Webster1">Webster et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Whittingham3">Whittingham and Lifjeld 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Whittingham2">Whittingham and Dunn 2005</xref>). However, the likelihood of siring extra-pair young increases with male quality, as females tend to seek genetic benefits for their offspring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Kempenaers1">Kempenaers et al. 1992</xref>). In consequence, only high-quality males are likely to produce more offspring than females of any given quality. Assuming that the quality of the male offspring is partially heritable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Ellegren1">Ellegren et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Svensson1">Svensson and Nilsson 1996</xref>), we could expect that females in good condition or those paired with males of high quality would benefit more from producing male offspring, while mothers in poor condition or those paired with a poor-quality male should produce female-biased broods. In fact, male-biased offspring sex ratios of high-quality individuals have been reported for various avian species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Bradbury1">Bradbury and Blakey 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Whittingham1">Whittingham and Dunn 2000</xref>), including colonial waterbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Nager1">Nager et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez and Velando 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Weimerskirch2">Weimerskirch et al. 2005</xref>).A tendency for high-quality individuals to invest more in sons implies that the spatial distribution of offspring sex ratios should match the distribution of pairs of different quality within avian colonies. Nesting sites in colonies of birds usually differ considerably in attractiveness, which provokes intense competition and leads to the appearance of specific spatial patterns of pair distribution. In many colonial species, central&ndash;periphery patterns prevail, where pairs of high quality assemble in the central parts of colonies, while poor-quality conspecifics are relegated to the peripheries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Coulson1">Coulson 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Aebischer1">Aebischer and Coulson 1990</xref>). Higher attractiveness of central nesting sites is usually attributed to better safety of adults and their offspring, as colony centers are less accessible to predators. Also, group defense and vigilance is more effective in the colony center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Gotmark1">G&ouml;tmark and Andersson 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Yorio1">Yorio and Quintana 1997</xref>).Given the spatial distribution of pair quality within colonies and quality-dependent offspring sex allocation of parents, it could be expected that offspring sex ratios are distributed centroperipherally in avian colonies. Despite this theoretical prediction, we are aware of no data on spatial gradients in offspring sex composition within breeding aggregations of birds. The aim of this study was to examine the spatial distribution of offspring sex ratios within a colony of a tree-nesting waterbird, the Great Cormorant (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax carbo</named-content> sinensis</italic>). The Great Cormorant is a size-dimorphic species, with males being on average 10&percnt; larger and up to 20&percnt; heavier than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Koffijberg1">Koffijberg and van Eerden 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Liordos1">Liordos and Goutner 2008</xref>), so high-quality cormorant pairs are expected to produce more sons. Since the central&ndash;periphery distribution of pair quality in colonies has already been reported for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Andrews1">Andrews and Day 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias3">Minias et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias2">Minias and Kaczmarek 2013</xref>), we predicted that the offspring sex ratio in central parts of cormorant colonies should be male-biased, while peripheral pairs should invest more in female offspring.Our study was conducted in 2010&ndash;2011 at Jeziorsko Reservoir (51&deg;73&prime;N, 18&deg;63&prime;E), central Poland. The studied colony of Great Cormorants was located in the vicinity of Proboszczowice village (51&deg;43.39&prime;N, 18&deg;38.61&prime;E) on the western shore of the reservoir. The colony was established in 2005, when breeding of ca. 40 cormorant pairs was recorded. Since then, the number of breeding cormorants has grown rapidly and reached 240 pairs in 2007, but declined to the level of ca. 120&ndash;150 pairs in 2010&ndash;2011. The cormorants nested in an area covered with riparian willow woodland dominated by White Willow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Salix alba</named-content></italic>) and Grey Willow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Salix cinerea</named-content></italic>).In both breeding seasons, the colony was visited from mid-March, when the first pairs initiated laying. Laying dates and clutch sizes were determined for 50 randomly chosen nests each year. From this subsample, at the time of hatching, 30 nests per year were randomly chosen for the purpose of sex-ratio analysis. To minimize the problem of pseudoreplication, we avoided choosing the same nest sites in both seasons, which, owing to the high site fidelity of Great Cormorants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Schjorring1">Schj&oslash;rring et al. 2000</xref>), was expected to preclude repeated measurements of offspring sex ratio of the same individuals. The chosen broods were randomly distributed within the colony, as there were no differences in the coordinates of the nests included in the study and all the other nests in the colony (Wilks: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,121</sub> &equals; 0.18, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.84 for 2010; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,149</sub> &equals; 1.35, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26 for 2011). Seven broods in which two or more eggs were lost or did not hatch were excluded from the analyses. In the remaining 53 nests, all eggs (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 31 nests), or all except one egg (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 22 nests; mean clutch size &equals; 4.36 &plusmn; 0.12 &lsqb;SE&rsqb; eggs), hatched successfully. In total, 204 (90.3&percnt;) out of 226 eggs hatched, so the studied offspring sex composition was close to the primary sex ratio. The results of our spatial analyses were considered unlikely to be affected by the presence of unhatched eggs for two reasons: (1) nests containing an unhatched egg were distributed evenly among the central and peripheral zones of the colony (<italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.97, df &equals; 51, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.34) and among different nest densities (<italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.46, df &equals; 51, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.65); and (2) any potential effect of sex-specific embryo mortality should be similar in all parts of the colony. A large majority of the sexed broods contained 3&ndash;4 chicks (83.0&percnt;), while the remaining 17.0&percnt; of broods consisted of 5 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 8) or 6 (<italic>n</italic> &equals;1) chicks.Blood samples (ca. 10 &mu;l) for molecular sexing were collected from the ulnar veins of all hatchlings (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 204 chicks from 53 broods), suspended in 96&percnt; ethanol, and stored until analysis. Nuclear DNA from blood samples was extracted with the Blood Mini kit (A&amp;A Biotechnology, Gdynia, Poland) according to the kit protocol. Amplification of the CHD region was performed with the primer pair 2550F and 2718R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Fridolfsson1">Fridolfsson and Ellegren 1999</xref>), according to the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Griffiths1">Griffiths et al. (1998)</xref>. The PCR products were stained and separated on 2&percnt; agarose gel until the differences in the product size (ca. 200 bp) were clearly visible. Offspring sex ratio was expressed as the percentage of males in a brood.All the nests within the colony were mapped with a handheld Global Positioning System (GPS) unit (Garmin GpsMap 60Cx, Olathe, Kansas, USA) and collected coordinates were used to calculate distances between them. On the basis of a nest-distance matrix, we calculated two nest location characteristics: distance to the center of the colony (m) and nest density (number of nests within a radius of 25 m). The center of the colony was calculated as the mean coordinates of all the nests within the colony. The maximum distance to the colony center was 131 m. In the analysis of nest density, a radius of 25 m was chosen to ensure sufficient variation in this trait, as shorter radii were associated with lower variation. The mean nest density in the colony was 14.53 &plusmn; 0.48 (SE) nests in the radius of 25 m (range: 1&ndash;35 nests per 25 m radius). There were no differences in the mean nest location characteristics of all the nests in the colony between the two study years (distance to the colony center: <italic>t</italic> &equals; 1.22, df &equals; 271, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22; nest density: <italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.35, df &equals; 271, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.73). There was a significant negative correlation between nest density and distance to the colony center, indicating that central parts of the colony were associated with higher nest densities (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.54, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 272, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).We used a geostatistical approach to analyze spatial patterns in offspring sex ratios across the colony. Geostatistical tools, such as variograms, describe the degree of spatial dependence of data by relating the values of investigated parameters recorded for each nesting pair to the values recorded for neighboring pairs located within varying distances, i.e. within the lags of different radii (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Rossi1">Rossi et al. 1992</xref>). We evaluated how our data on the offspring sex ratio fit two basic theoretical models of distribution: central&ndash;periphery and random. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Velando1">Velando and Freire (2001)</xref>, the central&ndash;periphery model assumes that variation in any parameter (measured by semivariance) should be low at short distances (lags) and increase with increasing lag, as the parameter values are greater in the central parts of a colony than at the edges. In consequence, neighboring pairs are expected to show similar parameter values, which is associated with a positive spatial autocorrelation at short lags and a negative autocorrelation at large lags. By contrast, the random distribution is characterized by constant level of semivariance at all lags and a lack of autocorrelation.Apart from testing autocorrelations, we also analyzed the effects of both nest location characteristics (distance to the colony center, nest density) on the offspring sex ratio with general linear models. Since central parts of the colony were associated with high nest densities, we performed separate analyses for each variable in order to avoid multicolinearity of dependent variables. Since the mean offspring sex ratio is known to change over the course of the season in the studied population of Great Cormorants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-WojczulanisJakubas1">Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2013</xref>), we controlled for the effect of date in both analyses. We also accounted for the effect of year and included a year&ndash;location interaction to check whether the effect of nest location on offspring sex ratio differed between the breeding seasons. The stepwise procedures of backward removal were used to select for significant independent variables. Offspring sex ratio was subjected to arcsin transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Zar1">Zar 1996</xref>) and nest location characteristics were standardized to equal unit variances (z-scores) prior to the analysis. The character and strength of significant explanatory variables were evaluated with &beta; coefficients of regression lines. The percent of variance in the dependent variable explained by particular independent factors was evaluated with partial eta-squared (&eta;<sup>2</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Cohen1">Cohen 1973</xref>). All statistical analyses were performed using Statistica 10.0 (Statsoft, Tulsa, Oklahoma, USA). All values are presented as means &plusmn; SE.There was a strong effect of distance to the colony center on offspring sex ratio, as broods raised in the central parts of the colony were male-biased (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> &equals; 4.54, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04, &beta; &equals; &minus;0.012 &plusmn; 0.006, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). A similar relationship was found for nest density, with pairs located in areas of high density raising a higher proportion of males in their broods (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> &equals; 5.25, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03, &beta; &equals; 0.13 &plusmn; 0.06; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-f01">Figure 1</xref>B). The effects of distance to the colony center and nest density explained 8.2&percnt; and 9.3&percnt; of variation in the offspring sex ratio, respectively. Both relationships remained significant after controlling for the effect of hatching date (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Relationships between mean offspring sex ratio and nest location characteristics were similar in both years of study, as indicated by nonsignificant year&ndash;location interactions (distance to the colony center: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,49</sub> &equals; 1.55, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22; nest density: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,49</sub> &equals; 2.93, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.09). There was no difference in the mean offspring sex ratio between years (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.1).Relationships between offspring sex ratio of Great Cormorants and two within-colony nest location characteristics: distance to the colony center (<bold>A</bold>) and nest density (<bold>B</bold>). For the purpose of presentation, both spatial variables were grouped into three categories based on the tertile division of 53 broods included in the analysis. Means &plusmn; SE are presented.In 2010, we found a nearly significant positive autocorrelation in offspring sex ratio over the lag of 25 m (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.17, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 124, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.055). This indicated that, across the colony, neighboring pairs tended to raise broods of a similar sex ratio, which was consistent with the central&ndash;periphery pattern of distribution. Significant negative autocorrelation (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.21, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 370, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) over the most distant lag (75&ndash;125 m) also confirmed the assumptions of the central&ndash;periphery model. Consistently, the constructed omnidirectional variogram indicated that semivariance in offspring sex ratio increased with increasing distance between nests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-f02">Figure 2</xref>). By contrast, we found no significant spatial autocorrelation in offspring sex ratio in 2011 (all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05).Standardized variogram for the offspring sex ratio of Great Cormorants. Semivariances (<italic>&ycirc;</italic>(<italic>h</italic>)) are shown in three chosen lags (distances of different radii), with high values (&gt;1) indicating a negative spatial autocorrelation and low values (&lt;1) a positive spatial autocorrelation. The dashed line indicates standardized total variance. Numbers of pair comparisons are given in each case above the symbol.We demonstrated a strong central&ndash;periphery pattern in offspring sex ratio within the studied colony of Great Cormorants. Offspring sex ratio of pairs nesting in the center was male-biased and the proportion of males in broods decreased toward the edges of the colony. We also found that broods with a higher proportion of male offspring were associated with higher nesting densities. Such within-colony distribution of offspring sex ratio is consistent with the central&ndash;periphery gradient of pair quality that was previously documented for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias3">Minias et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias2">Minias and Kaczmarek 2013</xref>). Assumptions of the central&ndash;peripheral distribution were also confirmed with autocorrelation analysis, which indicated similar offspring sex ratios of neighboring pairs across the colony, although this relationship prevailed only in one of two breeding seasons.Central&ndash;periphery patterns of distribution within avian colonies arise mainly in relatively homogeneous habitats, where there is little variation in the physical quality of nest sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias1">Minias 2014</xref>). Therefore, central&ndash;periphery patterns dominate in ground-nesting birds, such as larids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Patterson1">Patterson 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Dexheimer1">Dexheimer and Southern 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Antolos1">Antolos et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Becker1">Becker 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Savoca1">Savoca et al. 2011</xref>), but they are also recorded in colonial species nesting in trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Leger1">L&eacute;ger and McNeil 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Vergara1">Vergara and Aguirre 2006</xref>) or on floating vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias4">Minias et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias5">2012b</xref>), where variation in the physical quality of nesting sites is only moderate. In such habitats, attractiveness of particular sites is largely determined by within-colony nest-site location and central nesting places are highly preferred, as they provide greater safety against predators. There is strong empirical evidence that predation pressure in central parts of such colonies is lower than in the peripheral zones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Gotmark1">G&ouml;tmark and Andersson 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Yorio1">Yorio and Quintana 1997</xref>). On the other hand, when habitats provide great variation in the physical quality of nest sites, birds of high quality may choose good-quality sites irrespective of their location within a colony. Under such circumstances, central&ndash;periphery patterns may be disrupted, resulting in the random distribution of high-quality pairs within a colony. Random distributions prevail in species nesting in different types of rocky habitats, on cliffs, and in ground burrows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Velando1">Velando and Freire 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-OspinaAlvarez1">Ospina-Alvarez 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Svagelj1">Svagelj and Quintana 2011</xref>), where the physical characteristics of each nesting site may provide a different level of protection against predators and adverse weather conditions.It seems very likely that the central&ndash;periphery pattern in offspring sex ratio, which we observed in the studied colony of tree-nesting Great Cormorants, is related to the higher quality of centrally nesting pairs. Although direct information on the spatial distribution of pair quality in the colonies of Great Cormorants are lacking, there is lots of circumstantial evidence for the occurrence of central&ndash;periphery gradients in this species. Centrally nesting cormorant pairs have been reported to initiate laying earlier in the season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Andrews1">Andrews and Day 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias3">Minias et al. 2012a</xref>), as well as to raise offspring in better physiological condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias2">Minias and Kaczmarek 2013</xref>). Assuming that centrally breeding pairs are of higher quality, the observed spatial distribution of offspring sex ratio in the study colony is consistent with the assumptions of sex allocation theory. High-quality individuals are expected to invest more in offspring of the larger sex, which are more costly to rear, but also more vulnerable to unfavorable rearing conditions. Since male Great Cormorants are on average 10&percnt; larger than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Liordos1">Liordos and Goutner 2008</xref>), we might expect that smaller female chicks should be more resistant to poor feeding conditions, as they require fewer food resources to maintain growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Weimerskirch1">Weimerskirch et al. 2000</xref>). In consequence, pairs of poor quality should produce more daughters, since they could have inadequate abilities to rear larger numbers of sons. A tendency of late-breeding pairs, which are presumably of lower quality, to invest more in female offspring has been confirmed in various cormorant species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Velando2">Velando et al. 2002</xref>), including the Great Cormorant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-WojczulanisJakubas1">Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2013</xref>).However, it cannot be excluded that parents may adaptively bias offspring sex ratio in response to predation risk, more readily investing in the more expensive sex while nesting in the areas of the colony where chicks are less vulnerable to predators. In fact, there is direct empirical evidence for lower predation-related losses of broods in the central parts of cormorant colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Minias2">Minias and Kaczmarek 2013</xref>), where offspring sex ratio is skewed toward males. Females subjected to higher predation pressure (peripheral zones with lower nesting densities) may have chronically elevated levels of corticosterone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Scheuerlein1">Scheuerlein et al. 2001</xref>) and thus may lay eggs with higher yolk concentrations of this hormone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Saino2">Saino et al. 2005</xref>), which is known to bias offspring sex ratio toward females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Pike1">Pike and Petrie 2006</xref>). Such a hypothesis would also be consistent with a density-dependent distribution of sex ratios within the studied colony. It is possible that dense aggregations of breeding birds are likely to provide efficient protection against predators, irrespective of their location within the colony (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Savoca1">Savoca et al. 2011</xref>), and consequently high breeding densities may reduce stress associated with predation risk. However, in the studied Great Cormorant colony, high nesting densities were recorded in the central parts of the entire aggregation, so disentangling the effects of nest density vs. centrality on offspring sex ratio would be possible only under special experimental design.Since central&ndash;periphery patterns in pair-quality distribution prevail in many colonial species of birds, we might expect similar spatial gradients in offspring sex ratio to be a common phenomenon in avian colonies. We also predict that such patterns are especially likely to occur in species that nest in homogeneous habitats. However, many more empirical studies are required to confirm these hypotheses. We suggest that our results, demonstrating a nonrandom distribution of offspring sex ratio within the Great Cormorant colony, may have some methodological implications for further research on sex allocation in colonial species. Most importantly, we recommend that researchers take special care to randomize sampling of broods within colonies when analyzing offspring sex ratios. Failure to do so could result in considerable biases in estimating population sex ratios and in testing specific hypotheses on sex allocation. This methodological consideration seems especially important when taking into account that colonial waterbirds are frequently chosen as focal species for studying sex ratios under natural conditions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Nager2">Nager et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Erikstad1">Erikstad et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Saino1">Saino et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Merkling1">Merkling et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Benito1">Benito et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-388-Riechert1">Riechert et al. 2013</xref>).Fieldwork was performed under permissions of the Bioethical Commission and the Regional Environmental Protection Directorate in &Lstrok;od&zacute;. The study was supported by grants from the University of Gda&nacute;sk (BW/L120-5-0422-0) and from the Ministry of Science and Higher Education (N N303 319940), as well as by the scholarships of the European Social Fund and the Polish National Budget in the D-RIM project of the Human Capital Programme. P. Minias was financially supported by the Scientific Foundation of the University of &Lstrok;&oacute;d&zacute;. We are very grateful to Tomasz Janiszewski, Bartosz Lesner, Anna Piasecka, and Rados&lstrok;aw W&lstrok;odarczyk for their help with the fieldwork. We wish to thank two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on the earlier draft of the manuscript.