Northern Flickers increase provisioning rates to raise more but poorer quality offspring when given experimentally enlarged broodsSite- and sex-level differences in adult feeding behaviour and its consequences to offspring quality in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) following brood-size manipulationlme4: Linear mixed-effects models using S4 classes. R package version 0.999999-0Brood size and the cost of provisioning nestlings: Interpreting Lack's hypothesisMating systemsBrood size manipulations in the kestrel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Falco tinnunculus</named-content></italic>): Effects on offspring and parent survivalThe prudent parent: Energetic adjustments in avian breedingEffects of sex and age on survival of Northern Flickers: A six-year field studyEnvironmental and within-nest factors influencing nestling feeding patterns of Mediterranean Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>)Brood age and size influence sex-specific parental provisioning patterns in a sex-role reversed speciesDeterminants of parental care and offspring survival during the post-fledging period: Males care more in a species with partially reversed sex rolesLack of diet segregation during breeding by male and female Northern Flickers foraging on antsBody-mass dependent fledging order in the Great TitBrood size in Canada Geese: A manipulation experimentPrey choice and nestling hunger: An experiment with Pied Flycatchers, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>Selection on fledging mass in the Collared Flycatcher and the Great TitFood availability and offspring demand influence sex-specific patterns and repeatability of parental provisioningNestling mass and juvenile survival in the Blackbird <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus merula</named-content></italic>The manipulation of food resources reveals sex-specific trade-offs between parental self-feeding and offspring careModel selection and multimodel inference based on (Q)AIC(c). R package, version 1.35Parental care and parentage in monogamous great spotted woodpeckers (<italic>Picoides major</italic>) and middle spotted woodpeckers (<italic>Picoides medius</italic>)The evolution of paternity and parental care in birdsWhy don't birds lay more eggs?Differential response by males and females to brood manipulations in the Pied Flycatcher: Energy expenditure and nestling dietOptimal allocation of parental investmentParental condition, brood sex ratio and differential young survival: An experimental study in gulls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus fuscus</named-content></italic>)The consequences of brood size for breeding Blue Tits II. Nestling weight, offspring survival and optimal brood sizeFeeding frequencies of nestling Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus caeruleus</named-content></italic>): Costs, benefits and a model of optimal feeding frequencyMonogamy with exceptions: Social and genetic mating system in a bird species with high investment in paternal careSex and environmental sensitivity in Blue Tit nestlingsDo brood sex ratio, nestling development and sex affect fledging timing and order? An experimental study on Great TitsTesting ecological theory using the information-theoretic approach: Examples and cautionary resultsResponse of adult Leach's Storm-Petrels to increased food demand at the nestSex-related parental care strategies in the Lesser Spotted Woodpecker <italic>Picoides minor</italic>: Of flexible mothers and dependable fathersRegulation of parental effort in a long-lived seabird: An experimental manipulation of the cost of reproduction in the Antarctic Petrel, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassoica antarctica</named-content></italic>Feeding effort of male Tawny Owls St<italic>rix aluco</italic> follows a fixed schedule: A field experiment in the early nestling periodDevelopmental plasticityParental provisioning and offspring fitness: Size mattersRhinoceros Auklet developmental responses to food limitation: An experimental studyUltimate adjustment of clutch size to parental feeding capacity in a passerine birdA brief guide to model selection, multimodel inference and model averaging in behavioural ecology using Akaike's information criterionFemale-biased mortality in nestlings of a bird with size dimorphismParental investment and sexual selectionLack's clutch size hypothesis: An examination of the evidence using meta-analysisSex-specific nestling body mass in relation to brood sex composition in the Eurasian Sparrowhawk <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter nisus</named-content></italic>An experimental study of parental behavior in Red-winged BlackbirdsAsymmetric costs favor female desertion in the facultatively polyandrous Northern Flicker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>): A removal experimentDivision of labor during incubation in a woodpecker <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic> with reversed sex roles and facultative polyandryThe social and genetic mating system in flickers linked to partially reversed sex rolesNorthern Flicker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>)Clutch size relative to tree cavity size in Northern FlickersParental care and social mating system in the Lesser Spotted Woodpecker <italic>Dendrocopos minor</italic>Biparental care: Short-term manipulation of partner contribution and brood size in the starling, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>Incubation and fledging durations of woodpeckersSubmitted March 6, 2014; Accepted May 23, 2014; Published August 6, 2014Brood enlargement experiments have been conducted in several species of birds to investigate how parents of both sexes adjust their investment in the current breeding attempt. We studied parental feeding effort in the Northern Flicker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>), a species with partially reversed sex roles where males invest more in parental care than females and in which there is facultative polyandry and no extra-pair young. By experimentally manipulating brood sizes to be either larger or smaller by about 40&percnt;, we tested the flexibility of provisioning responses by each sex and whether the upper limit to provisioning corresponded to the maximum clutch size in the population. Both male and female parents increased feeding rates to enlarged broods, but per-nestling provisioning declined so that they fledged lighter nestlings with shorter wings. Mortality in reduced broods was lower than in control broods, but there was no difference in the incidence of mortality between control and enlarged broods. Parents with enlarged broods raised lighter fledglings than control parents with the same brood size suggesting clutch size is individually optimized. We conclude that, although flickers were able to raise extra offspring, brood size may be individually optimized if the smaller mass and wing length of offspring lead to lower recruitment.Des exp&eacute;riences d'agrandissement des couv&eacute;es ont &eacute;t&eacute; r&eacute;alis&eacute;es chez plusieurs esp&egrave;ces d'oiseaux pour &eacute;tudier comment les parents des deux sexes ajustent leur investissement dans la tentative de reproduction. Nous avons &eacute;tudi&eacute; l'effort parental de nourrissage chez <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>, une esp&egrave;ce ayant des r&ocirc;les sexuels partiellement invers&eacute;s, o&ugrave; les m&acirc;les investissent plus dans les soins parentaux que les femelles et chez lesquels il existe une polyandrie facultative sans jeunes issus de copulations hors couple. En manipulant exp&eacute;rimentalement les tailles des couv&eacute;es pour les rendre plus grosses ou plus petites d'environ 40&percnt;, nous avons test&eacute; la flexibilit&eacute; des r&eacute;ponses d'approvisionnement des deux sexes et si la limite sup&eacute;rieure de l'approvisionnement correspondait &agrave; la taille de couv&eacute;e maximale dans la population. Les deux parents ont augment&eacute; les taux d'alimentation aux couv&eacute;es agrandies mais l'approvisionnement par poussin a chut&eacute;, de sorte qu'ils ont produit des poussins plus l&eacute;gers avec des ailes plus courtes. La mortalit&eacute; dans les couv&eacute;es r&eacute;duites &eacute;tait plus faible que dans les couv&eacute;es t&eacute;moins, mais il n'existait aucune diff&eacute;rence de l'incidence de la mortalit&eacute; entre les couv&eacute;es t&eacute;moins et agrandies. Les parents avec des couv&eacute;es agrandies ont &eacute;lev&eacute; des poussins plus l&eacute;gers que les parents t&eacute;moins avec la m&ecirc;me taille de couv&eacute;e, sugg&eacute;rant que la taille de couv&eacute;e est optimis&eacute;e individuellement. Nous concluons que, malgr&eacute; que <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. auratus</named-content></italic> &eacute;tait capable d'&eacute;lever des jeunes suppl&eacute;mentaires, la taille des couv&eacute;es pourrait &ecirc;tre optimis&eacute;e individuellement si la masse et la longueur des ailes plus petites des rejetons entra&icirc;nent un plus faible recrutement.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> taille de couv&eacute;e, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>, histoire naturelle, qualit&eacute; de la prog&eacute;niture, approvisionnement, soins parentaux, picOffspring provisioning is energetically costly for birds raising altricial young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Drent1">Drent and Daan 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-CluttonBrock1">Clutton-Brock 1991</xref>). A life history tradeoff between provisioning effort and parental survival means that natural selection should favor an optimal effort to the current brood such that lifetime reproductive success is maximized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-CluttonBrock1">Clutton-Brock 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Stearns1">Stearns 1992</xref>). For single-brooded birds, clutch size may be the most important factor used by parents to adjust their investment in the current breeding attempt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Slagsvold1">Slagsvold and Lifjeld 1988</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Lack1">Lack's (1954)</xref> classic hypothesis suggested that clutch size in nidicolous species evolved to correspond with the maximum number of young that parents could rear. However, because some subsequent field tests found that parents given enlarged broods sometimes reared more young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Drent1">Drent and Daan 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Lessells1">Lessells 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-VanderWerf1">Vander Werf 1992</xref>), Lack's hypothesis was refined to acknowledge the tradeoffs between current and future reproductive effort (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Nur2">Nur 1984b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Conrad1">Conrad and Robertson 1993</xref>) and between offspring quality and quantity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Nur1">Nur 1984a</xref>). For example, although parents sometimes reared more young, the per-nestling provisioning decreased resulting in fledglings with a lower body mass and lower survival prospects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Dijkstra1">Dijkstra et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Schwagmeyer1">Schwagmeyer and Mock 2008</xref>). Thus, food may not always be a proximate factor limiting provisioning levels; rather, parents may lay fewer eggs than they could rear to optimize lifetime reproductive success.Not all brood enlargement experiments have resulted in increased provisioning effort. Parents with a fixed provisioning strategy do not change their foraging effort when nestling demand is experimentally altered, presumably because they are subsequently unwilling to increase effort past a predetermined threshold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Morris1">Morris 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs 1987</xref>). A fixed provisioning strategy appears to be more common in long-lived birds such as seabirds and raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Sather1">S&aelig;ther et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Sasvari1">Sasv&aacute;ri and Hegyi 2010</xref>) in which increased effort may jeopardize adult survival and severely reduce lifetime reproductive success. However, the extent to which flexible or fixed responses to increased brood demands are adaptive is hard to measure, and the responses of parents across and within species are variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Drent1">Drent and Daan 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Davies1">Davies 1991</xref>).Within species, body condition, sex, and age of parents may influence responsiveness to brood demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Ardia1">Ardia 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-GarciaNavas1">Garc&iacute;a-Navas and Sanz 2012</xref>). Most brood size manipulations have not measured the distinct contributions of male and female partners despite their potentially different life histories and different prioritization of the current brood. Although results from previous studies are mixed, most female passerines provide more overall care than males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-CluttonBrock1">Clutton-Brock 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Moller1">M&oslash;ller and Cuervo 2000</xref>) and are often more responsive to brood size if they have the available energy reserves to respond to increased demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Markman1">Markman et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Low1">Low et al. 2012</xref>). Males, on the other hand, may increase provisioning to cover shortfalls when females are already feeding at their maximum levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Whittingham1">Whittingham 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Moreno1">Moreno et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Low1">Low et al. 2012</xref>).In this study, we examine whether the provisioning rate of male and female Northern Flickers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>; order Piciformes; hereafter &ldquo;flickers&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f01">Figure 1</xref>) is flexible in relation to brood size. In natural (unmanipulated) broods of woodpeckers, feeding rates were positively correlated with brood size in flickers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>) and in Lesser Spotted Woodpeckers (<italic>Picoides minor;</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Rossmanith1">Rossmanith et al. 2009</xref>). To our knowledge, no one has previously investigated the responsiveness of biparental birds with partially reversed sex roles to experimental changes in brood size. Woodpeckers are an interesting group to investigate sex-specific parental investment because they are one of only two families of altricial birds with partially reversed sex roles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Ligon1">Ligon 1999</xref>). In particular, the males of most woodpecker species seem to contribute more than females by being the primary excavator at the nest and by being the sole provider of nocturnal incubation and brooding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiktander1">Wiktander et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe2">Wiebe 2008</xref>). Along with the high investment by males, extra-pair young are very rare among woodpeckers studied to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Michalek1">Michalek and Winkler 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Pechacek1">Pechacek et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe3">Wiebe and Kempenaers 2009</xref>). Thus, we predicted that male flickers would be more responsive to nestling demands compared with many other species and would provision more than females because they may value the current breeding attempt more. Further, if parents increased their provisioning rate to larger broods, we wanted to see at what brood size provisioning rates reached a maximum and how the per-nestling provisioning rates in different-sized broods affected the quality of offspring. Finally, we tested if clutch sizes were individually optimized by comparing fledging mass and success of enlarged broods to unmanipulated (control) broods from a long-term dataset. If clutch sizes are individually optimized, we expected the number of fledglings or nestling mass from enlarged and reduced broods to be lower than the unmanipulated (control) broods within the population.Male Northern Flicker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colaptes auratus</named-content></italic>). Photo credit: Ron LeValley (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.levalleyphoto.com" xlink:type="simple">www.levalleyphoto.com</ext-link>)We studied breeding Northern Flickers near Riske Creek, British Columbia, Canada (51&deg;52&prime;N, 122&deg;21&prime;W) during 2012 and 2013, on an area of approximately 100 km<sup>2</sup> of grassland interspersed with clumps of trembling aspen (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus tremuloides</named-content></italic>) and surrounded by mixed coniferous forests. The breeding effort of &sim;100&ndash;160 breeding flicker pairs has been monitored here since 1998. Flickers weigh &sim;150 g, and have a relatively &ldquo;r-selected&rdquo; or &ldquo;fast&rdquo; life history strategy with large and variable clutch sizes (mean 8 eggs, range of 3&ndash;13 in the absence of brood parasitism; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe4">Wiebe and Moore 2008</xref>) and relatively low annual apparent survival rates of adults of &sim;42&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Fisher1">Fisher and Wiebe 2006</xref>). Incubation lasts &sim;12 days and the nestling period 25&ndash;27 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe4">Wiebe and Moore 2008</xref>). The sexes provision nestlings at a similar rate, but males make slightly more feeding visits than females during the mid-nestling period when nestling energy demands are at their peak (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>).We found nests by using tape-recorded territorial playbacks and visually checking tree cavities. At active nests, we cut a small replaceable door in the tree trunk below the cavity entrance for access to nestlings and parents. Parents were trapped while incubating at the nest by plugging the cavity hole, placing a net over the hole, then removing the plug and flushing the bird into it. We weighed the adults and took 6 morphometric measurements (wing length, 9<sup>th</sup> primary, and rectrix length were measured to the nearest mm; bill length, bill depth, and tarsus to the nearest 0.01 mm) with a ruler or digital calipers. For each sex, the 6 measures were entered into a principal components analysis (PCA) and all 6 measures weighted positively on the first axis (PCA1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe5">Wiebe and Swift 2001</xref>), which was used as an overall measure of body size. The residuals of a regression of weight on body size (PCA1) was used as an index of body condition. At the time of trapping, we aged adults up to 4 years according to molt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Pyle1">Pyle et al. 1997</xref>). By visiting nests every 4&ndash;6 days, we determined clutch sizes and hatching dates.During 2012 and 2013, we experimentally manipulated brood sizes 2&ndash;4 days after hatching by transferring &sim;40&percnt; (1&ndash;4 nestlings) from reduced broods to enlarged broods. All reduced&ndash;enlarged nest pairs were matched with respect to hatching date (&plusmn; 1 day). We chose the number of nestlings to transfer such that we could maintain brood sizes within the natural range observed for the species (3&ndash;12 nestlings at the time of this study). Control broods were not manipulated but had similar hatch dates as the reduced&ndash;enlarged pairs and were visited with the same frequency. The timing of breeding, i.e. hatch date (ANOVA: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,108</sub> &equals; 0.20, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.82), original clutch size (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,104</sub> &equals; 2.00, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14), and original brood size (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,104</sub> &equals; 1.85, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.16) did not differ between treatments. Sample sizes at the start of the experiment of reduced, control, and enlarged nests, respectively in 2012 were 10, 11, and 10, and in 2013 were 12, 8, and 12. However, we used only nests of monogamous pairs (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 58 at the beginning of the experiment and <italic>n</italic> &equals; 41 at fledging) and deleted data if one parent subequently died or disappeared.Nestlings were weighed using a Pesola spring balance to &plusmn; 0.01 g at 3 stages of development: Stage 1 (5&ndash;7 days old), Stage 2 (10&ndash;13 days), and Stage 3 (18&ndash;21 days). Flattened wing chord measurements were taken with a ruler at Stage 3, to the nearest 1 mm, and included both the skeletal wing length and the primary feather length. During the three stages, we used Sony Handycam video cameras (Sony, Tokyo, Japan) placed 4&ndash;6 m from the nest tree to record parental provisioning rates for 3&ndash;4 hr on days when it was not raining. Preliminary analyses showed that estimates of feeding rates did not change with filming periods longer than 3 hr, so this was a sufficient period for estimation. We used the dimorphic plumage of flickers to identify which parent was feeding the young. Flickers regurgitate ants and ant larvae directly into nestlings' mouths and each visit to the nest was assumed to correspond to a feeding event unless a second visit occurred within 5 min from the last. Other videos taken from inside flicker cavities show that such visits are associated with nest sanitation and fecal sac removals and not additional feeding (K. Wiebe unpublished data) and so they were not included in estimates of provisioning rates.An initial ANCOVA on provisioning rate as the dependent variable and incorporating effects of sex, brood size, nestling stage, and year found no effect of time of day (ANCOVA: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,275</sub> &equals; 1.29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26) or hatch date (ANCOVA: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,275</sub> &equals; 0.91, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.34) and a model with these 2 variables included did not fit the data significantly better (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.46). Thus, these 2 variables were excluded from subsequent models. Provisioning rates were normally distributed and the data fit assumptions of homogeneity of variance, so we used linear mixed-effect models (LME) to investigate the fixed effects of brood size, nestling stage, parent body condition, parent age, and the interaction between stage and brood size on provisioning rates from nests where both parents were known to be present. Random effects were year and nest to account for the repeated measures at the nest. However, because we were interested in sex-specific responses and due to interaction between nest stage and brood size (males: <italic>F</italic> &equals; 7.42, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; females: <italic>F</italic> &equals; 4.68, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.009), we ran separate models for the provisioning of each parent at each stage (Stage 1: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 53, Stage 2: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 51, Stage 3: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 40) with only year included as a random effect (fitted as a random intercept).We evaluated the support for a full model versus models with fewer parameters (including an intercept-only model) by using Akaike's information criterion corrected for sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>) and AIC<sub>c</sub> weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>). We show models with &Delta;<sub>i</sub> values of &le; 6 (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Richards1">Richards 2005</xref>), but consider models with &Delta;<sub>i</sub> value of &le; 2 AIC<sub>c</sub> to be as plausible as the top-ranked model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). AIC<sub>c</sub> weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) sum to 1 across the model set and indicate the relative likelihood of a model being the best at describing the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We further determined the explanatory power of a fixed factor by summing the weights of all models that included the specific factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Symonds1">Symonds &amp; Moussalli 2011</xref>). Because of model uncertainty in the top models, we generated natural model-averaged parameter estimates &plusmn; unconditional standard error (SE) and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CI) and tested whether they overlapped with zero. Finally, to test whether provisioning rates increased linearly with brood size or reached a threshold, we pooled provisioning by males and females and compared the fit of a linear versus quadratic regression model at each of the three stages with ANOVA <italic>F</italic>-tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Zuur1">Zuur et al. 2010</xref>).We used LME models and model selection techniques (AIC<sub>c</sub>) to investigate the factors that best predicted nestling mass at each of the three nestling stages. Brood size was the only main effect for Stages 1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 58 nests) and 2 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53 nests), but in Stage 3 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 40 nests) when we could sex nestlings by plumage, we also included sex and an interaction between sex and brood size. Nest of rearing was included as a random effect to account for multiple nestlings within each brood (fitted as a random intercept). Wing chord, as a dependent variable, was assessed at Stage 3 using an LME model with the same fixed and random effects used for nestling mass. Because not all nestlings were measured at exactly the same age and we wanted to pool nestlings in the LME models, we standardized body mass (at Stages 1 and 2) and wing length based on average values for a particular age from the growth curves of control nestlings in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. (2013a)</xref>. We did not standardize mass at Stage 3 because mass plateaus during this stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>). Because of model selection uncertainty, we focused on parameter estimates (&plusmn; unconditional SE) and unconditional 95&percnt; CI for the fixed parameters in the selection of a &ldquo;best&rdquo; wing chord LME model.Logistic regression was used to determine the odds ratio of at least one nestling dying according to brood size. To test whether clutch sizes may be individually optimized, we compared the chance of nestling mortality and fledging success in manipulated broods to that of control broods of the same size within the natural population collected over 14 yr. Similarly, we compared fledging mass between manipulated and control broods of the same size within the natural population (collected over a span of 7 yr). The mass at fledging of these control nestlings did not differ between years (ANCOVA: <italic>F</italic><sub>9,1462</sub> &equals; 2.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12) and neither did the fledging success (<italic>F</italic><sub>9,819</sub> &equals; 1.85, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.11) so the years were similar in environmental conditions.All analyses were conducted in R version 2.15.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-RCoreDevelopmentTeam1">R Core Development Team 2012</xref>). LME models were run using the lme4 package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Bates1">Bates et al. 2012</xref>) and AIC<sub>c</sub> values, weights, and natural model-averaging of parameter estimates were run using the AICcmodavg package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Mazerolle1">Mazerolle 2013</xref>). Unless otherwise indicated, data are reported as means &plusmn; SE, with statistical significance set at &alpha; &le; 0.05.Averaged over brood sizes, treatments, and years, the mean provisioning rate by males (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 40) was 1.50 &plusmn; 0.08, 1.72 &plusmn; 0.06, and 1.39 &plusmn; 0.17 trips per hr and for females (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 40) was 1.41 &plusmn; 0.07, 1.69 &plusmn; 0.07, and 1.21 &plusmn; 0.17 trips per hr for Stages 1&ndash;3, respectively. The maximum rate of 5&ndash;6 trips/hr occured in the largest broods of 10&ndash;11 nestlings at the oldest nestling stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f02">Figure 2</xref>). A post hoc test of the total number of provisioning visits to the nest (males and females pooled) varied according to nestling stage (ANOVA: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,142</sub> &equals; 4.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01), with an increase between Stages 1 and 2 (Tukey HSD: <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03), but not between Stages 2 and 3 (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.98). Feeding rates between partners did not differ at any stage of the nestling period (paired <italic>t</italic>-test: Stage 1: <italic>t</italic><sub>52</sub> &equals; 0.99, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.32; Stage 2: <italic>t</italic><sub>50</sub> &equals; 0.43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.67; Stage 3: <italic>t</italic><sub>39</sub> &equals; 0.32, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.75).Total provisioning by parent Northern Flickers (sexes combined) in relation to brood size for 3 nestling stages: (<bold>A</bold>) age 5&ndash;7 days, (<bold>B</bold>) age 10&ndash;13, and (<bold>C</bold>) age 18&ndash;21. The best-fit model was linear at Stage 1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53 nests) and quadratic at Stages 2 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 51 nests) and 3 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 41 nests). Symbols represent the experimental treatments.Except for males at Stage 2, brood size always appeared in the top model for provisioning rates and led to a summed <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> of &ge; 0.98 (except for males at Stage 2: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.26 and females Stage 1: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.59; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-t01">Table 1</xref>). Parameter estimates (&plusmn; unconditional SE) indicated that males and females increased provisioning with brood size at all stages (Supplemental Material <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="131-04-09-s01.doc" xlink:type="simple">Table S1A</inline-supplementary-material>). Body condition also sometimes appeared in the top model with brood size, but the unconditional CI overlapped zero indicating non-significance. The best model for provisioning rate in relation to brood size was a linear increase at Stage 1, a decelerating quadratic curve at Stage 2, and an increasing curve at Stage 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Despite the increase in provisioning rates with brood size, per-nestling provisioning rates decreased with brood size (ANOVA: Stage 1: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> &equals; 28.27, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Stage 2: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,49</sub> &equals; 71.21, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Stage 3: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,39</sub> &equals; 7.09, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The decline in per-nestling provisioning rates was fairly linear across the range of brood sizes except at Stage 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f03">Figure 3</xref>). At Stages 1 and 2, nestlings in the smallest broods received about twice as many feedings per hour as those in the largest broods.A ranking of linear mixed-effect models on provisioning rates (trips per hour) by Northern Flickers, showing models within 6 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the top model. Separate models were done for each sex of the parents during 3 nestling stages (Stage 1: ages 5&ndash;7, Stage 2: ages 10&ndash;13, and Stage 3: ages 19&ndash;21 days). Year was included as a random effect, <italic>k</italic> is the number of parameters, and sample sizes are listed by each model candidate set.Per-nestling provisioning (trips per hour per nestling) by parent Northern Flickers in relation to brood size for 3 nestling stages: (<bold>A</bold>) age 5&ndash;7 days, (<bold>B</bold>) age 10&ndash;13, and (<bold>C</bold>) age 18&ndash;21). The best-fit models were linear for Stages 1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53 nests) and 2 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 51 nests), and quadratic for Stage 3 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 41 nests). Symbols represent the experimental treatments.Within each stage, nestling mass decreased with brood size (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-t02">Table 2</xref>, Supplemental Material <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="131-04-09-s01.doc" xlink:type="simple">Table S1B</inline-supplementary-material>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The interaction between brood size and nestling sex was the best model at Stage 3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-t02">Table 2</xref>; <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.75); mass of male nestlings declined more dramatically with increasing brood size compared to that of females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The wing chord of male nestlings at Stage 3 (116 &plusmn; 0.7 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 126) did not differ significantly from females (116 &plusmn; 0.6 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 139; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-t02">Table 2</xref>). Standardized to age, wing chord length decreased with increasing brood size (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-t02">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f05">Figure 5</xref>). According to parameter estimates and unconditioned CI, only brood size and not sex explained variation in wing length at fledging (Supplemental Material <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="131-04-09-s01.doc" xlink:type="simple">Table S1B</inline-supplementary-material>).A ranking of linear mixed-effect models on the body mass and wing chord length of Northern Flicker nestlings, showing models within 6 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the top model. The 3 nestling stages are Stage 1: ages 5&ndash;7, Stage 2: ages 10&ndash;13, and Stage 3: ages 18&ndash;21 days. Sex of the nestling and the interaction between sex and brood size was only considered at Stage 3. Nest was included as a random effect; <italic>k</italic> is the number of parameters. Sample sizes are 378 nestlings in 58 nests for Stage 1, 336 nestlings in 53 nests for Stage 2, and 265 nestlings in 40 nests for Stage 3.Body mass of Northern Flicker nestlings in relation to brood size at (<bold>A</bold>) Stage 1: age 5&ndash;7 days, (<bold>B</bold>) Stage 2: age 10&ndash;13 days, and (<bold>C</bold>) Stage 3: age 18&ndash;21 days. Sex-specific nestling mass is shown at Stage 3 with male (filled circles) and females (open circles). Sample sizes of nestlings are listed above the standard error bars.Wing chord of Northern Flicker nestlings in relation to brood size at Stage 3 (age 18&ndash;21 days). Sample sizes of nestlings are listed above the standard error bars.Ten of 16 enlarged nests (63&percnt;) experienced nestling mortality as did 8 of 12 control nests (66&percnt;) and 2 of 13 reduced nests (15&percnt;). Of the 41 broods in the experiment that made it through Stage 3, a single nestling died in 10 cases, 2 nestlings died in 6 cases, and &ge; 3 nestlings died in 4 broods. The likelihood that at least one nestling died did not differ between control and enlarged nests (&chi;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub> &equals; 0.22, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.64), however the likelihood of mortality tended to be lower in reduced compared to control nests (&chi;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub> &equals; 3.6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.06) and was significantly lower in reduced compared to enlarged broods (&chi;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub> &equals; 5.33, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02). The likelihood of mortality increased with brood size (logistic regression: odds ratio &equals; 1.58, 95&percnt; CI: 1.18&ndash;2.28, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.005). To see how mortality changed in relation to the degree of manipulation away from the original brood size, we classified nests according to the number of nestlings added or removed. The likelihood that at least one nestling died declined as nestlings were removed (&chi;<sup>2</sup><sub>4</sub> &equals; 13.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.009), but did not increase in enlarged broods as more nestlings were added.Although the number of nestlings that died increased with brood size, the number of nestlings that fledged also increased with brood size (ANOVA: brood size effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,39</sub> &equals; 120.6, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; treatment effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,38</sub> &equals; 33.23, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f06">Figure 6</xref>). To determine whether clutch size may be individually optimized, we compared the productivity (number of fledglings) of manipulated broods to control broods of the same size from the natural population. There was no difference in fledging success between enlarged broods and the control broods from the natural population (2-way ANOVA: treatment group effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,491</sub> &equals; 0.33, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.56; brood size effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,491</sub> &equals; 12.89, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, interaction effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,491</sub> &equals; 0.75, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.52; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f06">Figure 6</xref>). Similarly, the number of fledglings from experimentally reduced broods did not differ from the control broods in the natural population (2-way ANOVA: treatment group effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,510</sub>&equals; 0.60, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.44; brood size effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,510</sub> &equals; 252.38, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, interaction effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,510</sub> &equals; 0.14, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.93; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f06">Figure 6</xref>). In the comparison of nestling mass between enlarged broods and control broods from the natural population, there was a significant interaction between brood size and treatment group (2-way ANOVA: treatment group effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,1138</sub> &equals; 0.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.47, brood size effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,1138</sub> &equals; 13.14, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, interaction effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,1138</sub> &equals; 4.20, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Inspection of the data showed that for broods &ge; 8, nestlings were of lower mass in the enlarged broods compared to those in the control broods from the natural population. Nestlings in reduced broods were significantly heavier than nestlings in the natural population (2-way ANOVA: treatment group effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,768</sub> &equals; 14.41, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; brood size effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,768</sub> &equals; 6.91, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, interaction effect: <italic>F</italic><sub>3,768</sub> &equals; 0.29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.84).Mean number of fledglings according to brood size in the natural population (filled circles) and in broods with experimentally reduced (open squares) and enlarged (open triangles) broods. Nests with 11 and 12 nestlings are pooled. Sample sizes are the number of broods listed above standard error bars.Brood size manipulations in flickers revealed 2 main findings. First, both male and female parents followed a flexible rather than fixed provisioning strategy in relation to brood demands, and second, parents could rear more offspring than their original brood size. Provisioning rates and brood size were positively correlated in our control broods and in unmanipulated flicker broods in the population (this study; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>) but our current experiment confirms that parents can assess demands from the brood and adjust their effort &ldquo;in real time&rdquo; as brood size both decreases and increases. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow1">Gow (2014)</xref> reviewed brood size experiments and found that only 50&percnt; of 6 studies on long-lived birds (&gt; 80&percnt; adult survival rate) with a &ldquo;slow&rdquo; life history (mainly seabirds and raptors) reported an increase in provisioning rates to enlarged broods and none decreased provisioning to reduced broods. This was in contrast to the 90&percnt; of 29 studies on short-lived species (mainly passerines) in which parents increased provisioning rates to enlarged broods and 100&percnt; of 18 studies where at least one sex decreased provisioning to reduced broods. Flickers thus appear to fit the flexible provisioning strategy typical of many other short-lived species.In our study, both male and female flicker parents responded in a similar way to brood size. One reason that male flickers may be responsive to increased brood demands is that they are as confident of their parentage of a clutch as females. Parasitic eggs in the population may reduce the confidence of both maternity and paternity equally, but there are no extra-pair fertilizations to further reduce confidence of paternity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe3">Wiebe and Kempenaers 2009</xref>). In general, species of birds with a high assurance of paternity should be the most willing to increase investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Trivers1">Trivers 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Moller1">M&oslash;ller and Cuervo 2000</xref>). In another species of woodpecker, however, the provisioning strategy to natural broods was sex-specific; female, but not male, Lesser Spotted Woodpeckers (<italic>Picoides minor</italic>) provisioned in relation to brood size perhaps because females had lower survival rates and valued the current brood more than males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Rossmanith1">Rossmanith et al. 2009</xref>). In contrast, survival rates do not differ between male and female flickers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Fisher1">Fisher and Wiebe 2006</xref>), and indeed females may be less invested in the current brood than males because they have alternate reproductive opportunities through polyandry and conspecific brood parasitism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe3">Wiebe and Kempenaers 2009</xref>).The similar responses by the sexes also suggest that they face similar energetic constraints during the nestling period and are equally capable and/or willing to adjust effort to changes in nestling demand. In our study, the provisioning rates of the parents were nearly equal and it appears that the sexes work equally hard during the nestling period. However, female flickers often terminate care earlier than males in the post-fledging period and so their overall energetic investment in the brood may be lower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow3">Gow and Wiebe 2014</xref>). Among passerines, females often feed at higher rates than males, and thus are often working near their maximum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Low1">Low et al. 2012</xref>). During poor conditions (e.g., low food abundances or poor weather) this means that female passerines may be more energetically constrained than males and unable to respond (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Whittingham1">Whittingham 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Moreno1">Moreno et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Low1">Low et al. 2012</xref>), but this was not true for female flickers.Male and female flickers with enlarged broods increased average provisioning rates by &sim;1.2 and &sim;1.3 times, respectively, relative to controls. This is lower than the increase of &sim;1.6 times and &sim;1.8 times for the sexes seen in a mate removal experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe1">Wiebe 2005</xref>), but in the current study we only increased demands by &sim;40&percnt; compared with a 100&percnt; increase which would have resulted from a missing partner.Brood size was by far the strongest predictor of provisioning rate, whereas sex, age, and body condition of the parent had little effect. Feeding rates generally increased with brood size at each stage and reached a maximum at the latest nestling stage in the largest broods of 10&ndash;11 nestlings. If this high visit rate represents a theoretical maximum work rate for parents, they were not working at maximum capacity during the mid-nestling stage (seen in the quadratic concave down model; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f02">Figure 2</xref>A) despite this being the time of peak energy demands of nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>). Woodpeckers in general have unusually long nestling periods relative to other birds their size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-YomTov1">Yom-Tov and Ar 1993</xref>), and perhaps flicker parents restrain their effort during the mid-nestling period to ensure that they have enough reserves for continued care during the late nestling period (Stage 3) and the post-fledging period.Although parents increased the rate of feeding to experimentally enlarged broods, the per-nestling feeding rate generally declined with brood size in a similar way as in natural, non-manipulated broods of flickers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>). However, the decrease was more dramatic with the manipulated broods in the current study. The decline in per-nestling provisioning indicates that parents are not willing or able to fully compensate for additional nestlings in large broods, in agreement with some previous studies on other species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Drent1">Drent and Daan 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wright1">Wright and Cuthill 1990</xref>). An exception to the declining per-capita feeding rate occured in the very largest broods at the oldest nestling stage which had relatively high feeding rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-f03">Figure 3</xref>C). Possibly, parents under severe brood demands were bringing more frequent, but smaller, food loads to nestlings as documented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Lifjeld1">Lifjeld (1988)</xref> for Pied Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>). We were not able to measure food loads directly, but the low fledgling mass of nestlings in large broods would be consistent with smaller loads.Brood size influenced the body mass of nestlings at each stage of development, likely as a result of the lower per-capita feeding rates in larger broods. Although parents reduced total feeding rates to smaller broods, these nestlings had higher survival and fledging mass than in control or enlarged broods. On the other hand, the probability of mortality did not differ between enlarged and control broods, but the impact of less food was felt mainly in terms of reduced nestling body mass. The body mass of male nestlings was more negatively affected by brood size than that of females, perhaps because male nestlings (the larger sex) were more energetically costly to produce and thus more sensitive to food shortages. The body mass of the larger sex was also more suseptible to food shortages in several other studies (Eurasian Sparrowhawk <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter nisus</named-content></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Vedder1">Vedder et al. 2005</xref>; Lesser Black-backed Gull <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus fuscus</named-content></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Nager1">Nager et al. 2000</xref>; Blue-footed Booby <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sula nebouxii</named-content></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Torres1">Torres and Drummond 1997</xref>). However, in some species, the larger sex may be at a competitive advantage within the brood if it is dominant and more able to monopolize food from parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Raberg1">R&aring;berg et al. 2005</xref>). Our data do not support the idea that male flicker nestlings could outcompete females for access to parental deliveries, because of the greater decline in mass for males.Male and female flicker nestlings had similar wing lengths, which decreased with brood size. Thus, despite the slight sexual dimorphism in body mass, the sexes seemed to prioritize wing and feather growth to the same degree. In many nestling birds, structural size (i.e. wing chord) is less influenced by food shortages than body mass due to the preferential allocation of energy to skeletal elements during growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Schew1">Schew and Ricklefs 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Sears1">Sears and Hatch 2008</xref>). The fact that wing growth was slower in the enlarged flicker broods points to rather severe energy limitations experienced by those nestlings, and not just the males. We were unable to quantify exact fledging dates in our study because of the risk of forced fledging, but in other studies, delays in fledging caused by slow development relative to siblings may lead to starvation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Lemel1">Lemel 1989</xref>) or a lengthening of the nestling period, which may increase predation risk and decrease flying skills after fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Radersma1">Radersma et al. 2011</xref>). The general decline of both body mass and wing chord length with brood size suggests a quality-versus-quantity tradeoff in both manipulated and natural broods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow2">Gow et al. 2013a</xref>, this study) of flickers. Unfortunately, local recruitment into our population is low (natal dispersal is high), and so we could not measure the direct effect of mass or size at fledging on recruitment. However, reduced recruitment among fledglings of lower body mass and size is a common pattern across species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Magrath1">Magrath 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Linden1">Lind&eacute;n et al. 1992</xref>).If clutches (and by extension brood sizes) are individually optimized, unmanipulated brood sizes should be the most productive in the population. Relative to the original brood size, the chance of mortality declined in reduced broods, but parents of reduced broods did not rear significantly more fledglings compared with control broods of the same size in the population. Furthermore, especially heavy fledglings have reduced survival in the post-fledging period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow3">Gow and Wiebe 2014</xref>), suggesting that the number of fledglings cannot be increased by having a smaller clutch than the one originally laid. On the other hand, parents of enlarged broods could rear the same number of nestlings as control broods of the same size in the natural population, but for broods larger than 7 the nestlings were lighter than those of unmanipulated parents in the population. This is consistent with individually optimized brood size because parents forced to rear unexpectedly large broods could not match the performance of parents with naturally large broods. At the population level, the proportion of the brood that fledged seemed to decline after a brood size of 8, the mean clutch size in the population. Although we did not quantify food supply, the availability of ants (the main prey of flickers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Gow4">Gow et al. 2013b</xref>) or time constraints for foraging may limit the capacity of most parents in the population to fledge more than 8 nestlings.In summary, the flexible feeding response by both flicker parents fits the pattern of &ldquo;r-selected&rdquo; species, with both sexes investing heavily in the current brood and discounting future survival prospects. The ability to forage and deliver food did not seem to be the limiting proximate factor constraining the original brood size laid by flickers, but parents had limited ability to provide for unexpectedly large broods. If anything, we may have overestimated the ability of parents to care for enlarged broods because we did not force the parents to lay and incubate extra eggs (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Monaghan1">Monaghan and Nager 1997</xref>). We also did not create unnaturally large broods, but it would be interesting to do so to determine whether the limit to productivity is about 13 nestlings, the maximum recorded clutch size for the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-571-Wiebe4">Wiebe and Moore 2008</xref>). It seems likely that the smaller mass and size of fledglings in enlarged broods would be associated with lower recruitment, but this needs further investigation. If true, it would be consistent with individual optimization of brood size in the Northern Flicker.We thank E. A. Gow and B. Griffiths for their help in the field and V. Wishingrad, E. A. Gow, and R. G. Clark for their insightful comments and support. This research was funded by a NSERC Discovery Grant (KLW) and by a University of Saskatchewan Graduate Scholarship to ABM. This study was conducted with Animal Care Permit number 20010113 from the University of Saskatchewan and corresponds with the current laws of Canada.