Avian interactions with renewable energy infrastructure: An updateWind generation records and turbine productivityVariation in bat and bird fatalities at wind energy facilities: Assessing the effects of rotor size and tower heightWire marking results in a small but significant reduction in avian mortality at power lines: A BACI designed studyBehavioural and environmental correlates of soaring-bird mortality at on-shore wind turbinesImpacts of chronic anthropogenic noise from energy-sector activity on abundance of songbirds in the boreal forestBoreal bird abundance estimates within different energy sector disturbances vary with point count radiusThe impacts of roads and other infrastructure on mammal and bird populations: A meta-analysisEffect of wind turbine proximity on nesting success in shrub-nesting birdsMultiple factors affect a population of Agassiz's desert tortoise (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Gopherus agassizii</named-content></italic>) in the northwestern Mojave DesertImpact of power lines on bird mortality in a subalpine areaExperimental evidence for the effects of chronic anthropogenic noise on abundance of Greater Sage-Grouse at leksManaging a subsidized predator population: Reducing Common Raven predation on desert tortoisesMap of bird sensitivities to wind farms in Scotland: A tool to aid planning and conservationMortality at wind-farms is positively related to large-scale distribution and aggregation in Griffon VulturesNest predation of Greater Sage-Grouse in relation to microhabitat factors and predatorsPredators of Greater Sage-Grouse nests identified by video monitoringLandscape alterations influence differential habitat use of nesting buteos and ravens within sagebrush ecosystem: Implications for transmission line developmentReduced breeding success in White-tailed Eagles at Sm&oslash;la windfarm, western Norway, is caused by mortality and displacementGriffon Vulture mortality at wind farms in southern Spain: Distribution of fatalities and active mitigation measuresCollision fatality of raptors in wind farms does not depend on raptor abundanceBird use of solar photovoltaic installations at US airports: Implications for aviation safetyMinimal effects of wind turbines on the distribution of wintering farmland birdsAssessment of bat and avian mortality at a pilot wind turbine at Coega, Port Elizabeth, Eastern Cape, South AfricaAssessing the impacts of wind farms on birdsCollision effects of wind-power generators and other obstacles on birdsChihuahuan Raven (<italic>Corvus cryptoleucus</italic>)Predictive model of avian electrocution risk on overhead power linesPower pole density informs spatial prioritization for mitigating avian electrocutionTesting nest deterrents for Chihuahuan Ravens on H-Frame transmission structuresA comprehensive analysis of small-passerine fatalities from collision with turbines at wind energy facilitiesImpact of wind turbines on birds in Zeebrugge (Belgium)As the raven flies: Using genetic data to infer the history of invasive Common Raven (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>) populations in the Mojave DesertBehavioral responses by two songbirds to natural-gas-well compressor noiseResponse of raptors to a windfarmEffects of artificial night lighting on migrating birdsThe role of tower height and guy wires on avian collisions with communication towersHome range and landscape use of coyotes in a metropolitan landscape: Conflict or coexistence?Changes in coyote movements due to military activityEnergy development affects populations of sagebrush songbirds in WyomingNest survival of Red-winged Blackbirds in agricultural areas developed for wind energySolar energy development and aquatic ecosystems in the Southwestern United States: Potential impacts, mitigation, and research needsNo evidence of displacement due to wind turbines in breeding grassland songbirdsWind turbines do not negatively affect nest success in the Dickcissel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Spiza americana</named-content></italic>)Environmental impacts of utility-scale solar energyLand-use efficiency of big solarEffects of wind farms on Montagu's Harrier (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Circus pygargus</named-content></italic>) in southern SpainReducing the maladaptive attractiveness of solar panels to polarotactic insectsPolarized light pollution: A new kind of ecological photopollutionEvidence of negative effects of anthropogenic structures on wildlife: A review of grouse survival and behaviourSelection of anthropogenic features and vegetation characteristics by nesting Common Ravens in the sagebrush ecosystemWhich birds adjust the frequency of vocalizations in urban noise?Avian collisions at two wind farms in Tasmania, Australia: Taxonomic and ecological characteristics of colliders versus non-collidersFlight call rates of migrating thrushes: Effects of wind conditions, humidity and time of day at an illuminated offshore platformSynurbanization of the magpie in the PalearcticCollision mortality of local and migrant birds at a large-scale wind-power development on Buffalo Ridge, MinnesotaIncreased flight altitudes among migrating Golden Eagles suggest turbine avoidance at a Rocky Mountain wind installationGrassland songbirds exhibit variable responses to the proximity and density of natural gas wellsNight migrant fatalities and obstruction lighting at wind turbines in North AmericaEstimation of bird fatalities at wind farms with complex topography and vegetation in Hokkaido, JapanInteractions between avian predators and Greater Sage-Grouse before and after construction of an overhead electric transmission line in northern NevadaEffects of wind turbines and other physical elements on field utilization by Pink-footed Geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Anser brachyrhynchus</named-content></italic>): A landscape perspectiveResponses of understory rain forest birds to road edges in central AmazoniaShort-term impacts of wind energy development on Greater Sage-Grouse fitnessNonlethal effects in the ecology of predator&ndash;prey interactionsUltraviolet vision in birds: The importance of transparent eye mediaMitigating avian collision with power lines: A proof of concept for installation of line markers via unmanned aerial vehicleEffect of wind energy development on breeding duck densities in the Prairie Pothole regionAvian interactions with energy infrastructure in the context of other anthropogenic threatsBird&ndash;building collisions in the United States: Estimates of annual mortality and species vulnerabilityEstimates of bird collision mortality at wind facilities in the contiguous United StatesDirect mortality of birds from anthropogenic causesGolden Eagle mortality at a wind-energy facility near Palm Springs, CaliforniaWildlife conservation and solar energy development in the desert Southwest, United StatesOil and natural gas development has mixed effects on the density and reproductive success of grassland songbirdsCollision avoidance by migrating raptors encountering a new electric power transmission lineAnimal behavioral adaptation to changing landscapes: Spring-staging geese habituate to wind farmsReproductive success of Horned Lark and McCown's Longspur in relation to wind energy infrastructureUnderstanding bird collisions at wind farms: An updated review on the causes and possible mitigation strategiesUnderstanding bird collisions with man-made objects: A sensory ecology approachThrough birds' eyes: Insights into avian sensory ecologyBird collisions with power lines: Failing to see the way ahead?Visual fields, foraging and collision vulnerability in <italic>Gyps</italic> vulturesCorvid response to human settlements and campgrounds: Causes, consequences, and challenges for conservationAn experimental investigation into the effects of traffic noise on distributions of birds: Avoiding the phantom roadAvian mortality at a solar energy power plantEffects of wind energy development on nesting ecology of Greater Prairie-Chickens in fragmented grasslandsDifferential mortality of birds killed at wind farms in northern PortugalInfluence of wind turbines on presence of Willet, Marbled Godwit, Wilson's Phalarope and Black Tern on wetlands in the Prairie Pothole region of North Dakota and South DakotaEffects of noise pollution on birds: A brief review of our knowledgeBald and Golden eagle mortalities at wind energy facilities in the contiguous United StatesThreshold distances to nearby cities and roads influence the bird community of a mosaic landscapeRole of renewable energy sources in environmental protection: A reviewGreater impacts of wind farms on bird populations during construction than subsequent operation: Results of a multi-site and multi-species analysisThe distribution of breeding birds around upland wind farmsWintering Sandhill Crane exposure to wind energy development in the central and southern Great Plains, USAIdentification of bird collision hotspots along transmission power lines in Alberta: An expert-based geographic information system (GIS) approachDisturbance by traffic of breeding birds: Evaluation of the effect and considerations in planning and managing road corridorsThe impact of roads on birds: Does song frequency play a role in determining susceptibility to noise pollution?Scavenging of migratory bird carcasses in the Sonoran DesertNesting success of Scissor-tailed Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Tyrannus forficatus</named-content></italic>) at a wind farm in northern TexasAvian behavior and mortality at power lines in coastal South CarolinaEcological and evolutionary trapsEffects of wind-energy facilities on breeding grassland bird distributionsModelling power-line collision risk for the Blue Crane <italic>Anthropoides paradiseus</italic> in South AfricaBirdsong and anthropogenic noise: Implications and applications for conservationBird mortality in the Altamont Wind Resource Area, CaliforniaNovel scavenger removal trials increase wind turbine&ndash;caused avian fatality estimatesInfluence of behavior on bird mortality in wind energy developmentsBurrowing Owl mortality in the Altamont Pass Wind Resource AreaIndirect effects of an existing wind energy facility on lekking behavior of Greater Prairie-ChickensMarking power lines to reduce avian collisions near the Audubon National Wildlife Refuge, North DakotaWhooping Crane collisions with power lines: An issue paperAn analysis of displacement from wind turbines in a wintering grassland bird communitySex-biased mortality of Common Terns in wind farm collisionsUltraviolet vision and avoidance of power lines in birds and mammalsBird-community shifts in relation to wind farms: A case study comparing a wind farm, croplands, and secondary forests in southern MexicoResponses of male Greater Prairie-Chickens to wind energy developmentEffects of wind energy development on survival of female Greater Prairie-ChickensImpact of wind power plants on Black Grouse, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Lyrurus tetrix</named-content></italic> in Alpine regionsCanadian estimates of bird mortality due to collisions and direct habitat loss associated with wind turbine developmentsWind farm noise suppresses territorial defense behavior in a songbirdConflicts between birds and on-shore wind farmsCurrent address: Department of Biological Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USAEnergy infrastructure is widespread worldwide. Renewable energy technologies, which are expanding their footprint on the landscape and their contribution to energy availability, represent a different kind of infrastructure from extractive energy technologies. Although renewable energy sources may offer a &lsquo;greener alternative' to traditional extractive energy sources, mounting evidence suggests that renewable energy infrastructure, and the transmission lines needed to convey energy from renewable energy facilities to users, may impact birds. Peer-reviewed literature historically has focused on the direct effects of electrocution and, to a lesser extent, collisions with overhead power systems, and on avian collisions at wind energy facilities, with less consideration of indirect effects or other energy sectors. Here, we review studies that have examined direct and indirect effects on birds at utility-scale onshore wind- and solar-energy facilities, including their associated transmission lines. Although both direct and indirect effects appear site-, species-, and infrastructure-specific, generalities across energy sectors are apparent. For example, large-bodied species with high wing loading and relatively low maneuverability appear to be especially susceptible to direct effects of tall structures, and the risk of collision is likely greater when structures are placed perpendicular to flight paths or in areas of high use. Given that all infrastructure types result in direct loss or fragmentation of habitat and may affect the distribution of predators, indirect effects mediated by these mechanisms may be pervasive across energy facilities. When considered together, the direct and indirect effects of renewable energy facilities, and the transmission lines serving these facilities, are likely cumulative. Ultimately, cross-facility and cross-taxon meta-analyses will be necessary to fully understand the cumulative impacts of energy infrastructure on birds. Siting these facilities in a way that minimizes avian impacts will require an expanded understanding of how birds perceive facilities and the mechanisms underlying direct and indirect effects.La infraestructura energ&eacute;tica est&aacute; ampliamente distribuida en todo el mundo. Las tecnolog&iacute;as de energ&iacute;a renovable est&aacute;n expandiendo su huella en el paisaje y su contribuci&oacute;n a la disponibilidad de energ&iacute;a, y representan un tipo diferente de infraestructura a la de las tecnolog&iacute;as extractivas de energ&iacute;a. Aunque las fuentes de energ&iacute;a renovable ofrecen una &ldquo;alternativa m&aacute;s verde&rdquo; en comparaci&oacute;n con las fuentes tradicionales de extracci&oacute;n de energ&iacute;a, existe bastante evidencia que sugiere que la infraestructura de energ&iacute;a renovable y las l&iacute;neas de transmisi&oacute;n necesarias para transportar la energ&iacute;a hacia los usuarios podr&iacute;an afectar a las aves. La literatura cient&iacute;fica tradicionalmente se ha enfocado en los efectos directos de la electrocuci&oacute;n y, en menor medida, en las colisiones con los sistemas a&eacute;reos de energ&iacute;a y con las estructuras de energ&iacute;a e&oacute;lica. En cambio, ha habido escasa consideraci&oacute;n de sus efectos indirectos y de otros sectores energ&eacute;ticos. En este trabajo revisamos estudios que investigaron los efectos directos e indirectos sobre las aves a la escala de instalaciones terrestres de energ&iacute;a e&oacute;lica y solar, incluyendo sus l&iacute;neas de transmisi&oacute;n. Aunque los efectos directos e indirectos parecen ser espec&iacute;ficos para cada sitio, especie y tipo de energ&iacute;a, existen generalidades evidentes entre diferentes sectores energ&eacute;ticos. Por ejemplo, las especies de mayor tama&ntilde;o, con alta carga alar y maniobrabilidad relativamente baja parecen ser especialmente susceptibles a los efectos directos de las estructuras altas, y el riesgo de colisi&oacute;n probablemente es mayor cuando las estructuras se ubican perpendiculares al sentido del vuelo o en &aacute;reas con alto uso. Dado que todos los tipos de infraestructura resultan en la p&eacute;rdida directa del h&aacute;bitat o en su fragmentaci&oacute;n y podr&iacute;an afectar la distribuci&oacute;n de los depredadores, los efectos indirectos mediados por estos mecanismos pueden ser comunes entre diferentes instalaciones energ&eacute;ticas. Cuando se consideran en conjunto, los efectos directos e indirectos en las instalaciones de energ&iacute;a renovable y en las l&iacute;neas de transmisi&oacute;n asociadas probablemente son acumulativos. Finalmente, ser&aacute; necesario hacer meta an&aacute;lisis a trav&eacute;s de varios tipos de instalaciones y taxones para entender completamente los impactos acumulativos de la infraestructura energ&eacute;tica sobre las aves. La localizaci&oacute;n de estas instalaciones de forma que minimice el impacto sobre las aves requerir&aacute; un mayor entendimiento acerca de c&oacute;mo las aves perciben las instalaciones y de los mecanismos que subyacen a los efectos directos e indirectos.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> aves, efectos directos, efectos indirectos, e&oacute;lico, l&iacute;neas de energ&iacute;a, mitigaci&oacute;n, solarConcerns regarding the depletion of fossil fuels, global climate change, and energy security have triggered rapid growth in the use of renewable energy technologies. For example, in the United States (U.S.), wind energy capacity increased by &sim;140&percnt; from 25,000 megawatts (MW) in 2008 to &gt;61,000 MW in 2013 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-AmericanWindEnergyAssociation1">American Wind Energy Association 2014</xref>). Collectively, &sim;13&percnt; of U.S. electricity generated in 2014 was derived from renewable energy sources (e.g., biomass &lsqb;1.7&percnt;&rsqb;, geothermal &lsqb;0.4&percnt;&rsqb;, hydroelectric &lsqb;6.0&percnt;&rsqb;, solar &lsqb;0.4&percnt;&rsqb;, and wind &lsqb;4.4&percnt;&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-USEnergyInformationAdministration1">U.S. Energy Information Administration 2015a</xref>). Continued growth of the wind energy sector is predicted to meet the U.S.'s wind energy target of 20&percnt; of all energy used by 2030 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-U.S.DepartmentofEnergy1">U.S. Department of Energy 2008</xref>). Although government targets are centered on wind energy, the expansion of other renewable energy sectors also is expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-USEnergyInformationAdministration2">U.S. Energy Information Administration 2015b</xref>). In particular, projections suggest that the solar energy sector could meet 14&percnt; of electricity demands in the contiguous U.S. by 2030 and 27&percnt; by 2050 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-U.S.DepartmentofEnergy2">U.S. Department of Energy 2012</xref>).Renewable energy as a &lsquo;greener alternative' to the combustion of fossil fuels offers important environmental benefits over traditional energy sources, such as reductions in greenhouse gas emissions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Panwar1">Panwar et al. 2011</xref>). Yet, increasing evidence of direct and indirect effects has raised concerns regarding the potential impacts of renewable energy infrastructure on birds. Avian collisions with wind turbines (i.e. direct effects) are well documented and have received the most attention to date (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood1">Smallwood and Thelander 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss3">Loss et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Morinha1">Morinha et al. 2014</xref>). In comparison, studies of the direct effects of other types of renewable energy infrastructure on birds have been limited (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McCrary1">McCrary et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lovich2">Lovich and Ennen 2011</xref>). Further, relatively few studies have considered the potential for indirect effects on avian behavior, spatial ecology, or demographics resulting from increased disturbance, changes in trophic interactions, or changes in habitat availability and connectivity (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Drewitt1">Drewitt and Langston 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Zwart2">Zwart et al. 2016a</xref>). Renewable energy infrastructure often is accompanied by the construction of new transmission lines to connect renewable energy facilities to the existing power line network. Thus, the direct and indirect effects of multiple infrastructure types at renewable energy facilities need to be considered to identify the cumulative effects of a national (and global) transition from extractive to renewable energy production.Of the studies that have assessed interactions between renewable energy infrastructure and birds, many have primarily targeted specific management crises, often focusing on species of conservation concern (e.g., Greater Sage-Grouse &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-LeBeau1">LeBeau et al. 2014</xref>; Greater Prairie-Chicken &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Tympanuchus cupido</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smith1">Smith et al. 2016</xref>) in areas targeted for development (e.g., the Great Plains of North America; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Harrison1">Harrison 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Whalen1">Whalen 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Winder1">Winder et al. 2015</xref>). Thus, studies have been necessarily limited and inconsistent in the focal species addressed, experimental design, and study site. As a consequence, developing general siting guidelines and mitigation strategies for new facilities remains challenging. Given the projected increase in renewable energy infrastructure throughout the U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-U.S.DepartmentofEnergy1">U.S. Department of Energy 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-USEnergyInformationAdministration2">U.S. Energy Information Administration 2015b</xref>), it is critical that we develop a more comprehensive understanding of the effects of renewable energy infrastructure on birds so that informed siting guidelines can be developed and implemented.Here, we review recent studies of the direct and indirect effects on birds from utility-scale onshore wind- and solar-energy facilities and their accompanying transmission lines. We focused on these energy sectors because of their projected increase in the U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-U.S.DepartmentofEnergy1">U.S. Department of Energy 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-USEnergyInformationAdministration2">U.S. Energy Information Administration 2015b</xref>). Our goals were to: (1) provide an up-to-date and consolidated summary of direct and indirect impacts of utility-scale onshore wind- and solar-energy infrastructure and associated power lines on birds based on peer-reviewed literature; (2) use our findings to inform siting guidelines; and (3) highlight important knowledge gaps and areas for future research.To summarize the impacts of utility-scale renewable energy infrastructure, we conducted a literature review to identify studies that empirically tested the effects of energy infrastructure on birds (i.e. not commentaries or predictive studies). We did so by using combinations of the following search terms in Web of Science (formerly ISI Web of Knowledge; Thomson Reuters, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA): avian, bird, collision, conservation, electrocution, photovoltaic cell, renewable energy infrastructure, solar energy, transmission power line, wind energy, wind farm, and wind resource area.The direct effects of wind energy development on birds have received considerable attention (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood1">Smallwood and Thelander 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss3">Loss et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Erickson1">Erickson et al. 2014</xref>). Collisions between birds and onshore wind turbines result in impact trauma, which can result directly in death or render birds more susceptible to predation. Collisions have been documented for a wide range of taxa, including ducks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2002</xref>), grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Zeiler1">Zeiler and Gr&uuml;nschachner-Berger 2009</xref>), raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas2">De Lucas et al. 2008</xref>), and songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Morinha1">Morinha et al. 2014</xref>). Of specific concern are fatalities of species of conservation concern (e.g., Western Burrowing Owl &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Athene cunicularia</named-content> hypugaea</italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood4">Smallwood et al. 2007</xref>) and species with small populations, delayed maturity, long lifespans, and low reproductive rates, for which even a few mortalities can have population-level effects (e.g., Golden Eagle &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Aquila chrysaetos</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lovich1">Lovich 2015</xref>; White-tailed Eagle &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Haliaeetus albicilla</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dahl1">Dahl et al. 2012</xref>). While the number of birds affected is uncertain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Pagel1">Pagel et al. 2013</xref>), estimates adjusted for searcher detection and scavenger removal suggest that between 140,000 and 328,000 birds are killed annually by collisions with turbines at wind energy facilities in the contiguous U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss3">Loss et al. 2013</xref>). For songbirds in particular, fatalities at wind energy facilities in the U.S. and Canada are estimated to be between 134,000 and 230,000 annually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Erickson1">Erickson et al. 2014</xref>). Avian collisions with turbines also have been documented outside the U.S. (e.g., Australia: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hull1">Hull et al. 2013</xref>; Canada: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Zimmerling1">Zimmerling et al. 2013</xref>; Japan: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kitano1">Kitano and Shiraki 2013</xref>; South Africa: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Doty1">Doty and Martin 2013</xref>; Western Europe: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Everaert1">Everaert and Stienen 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas1">De Lucas et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Morinha1">Morinha et al. 2014</xref>), suggesting that the direct effects of wind energy facilities are of concern globally.Intuitively, mortality rates at wind energy facilities should be related to avian abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Carrete1">Carrete et al. 2012</xref>), but a more complex suite of site-specific factors may be important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas2">De Lucas et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Marques1">Marques et al. 2014</xref>). For example, habitats or prey that promote foraging at wind energy facilities are likely to increase collision rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Barrios1">Barrios and Rodr&iacute;guez 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood4">Smallwood et al. 2007</xref>). Collisions may also increase when turbines are sited on landscape features, including cliffs and steep slopes, that are regularly used by hunting or migrating birds (e.g., Black Kite &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Milvus migrans</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kitano1">Kitano and Shiraki 2013</xref>). Weather may further increase collision risk when visibility around turbines is reduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger et al. 2010</xref>). For species that exploit thermals, the risk of collision may increase during weather that forces birds to gain lift from topographical features near wind turbines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Barrios1">Barrios and Rodr&iacute;guez 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas2">De Lucas et al. 2008</xref>). Collisions during migration may be particularly important because they have the potential to indirectly affect breeding populations far beyond the wind energy facility. Because most conservation efforts in North America are focused on breeding habitat, migration mortality can be a cryptic and often unrecognized effect of wind turbines.Collision rates can additionally be affected by the design features of wind turbines. For example, collision rates between Western Burrowing Owls and wind turbines were highest at vertical axis towers, lower at tubular towers, and lowest at lattice towers, corresponding with a decline in the ability to see through the infrastructure type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood4">Smallwood et al. 2007</xref>). Conversely, mortality rates of Eurasian Kestrels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Falco tinnunculus</named-content></italic>) and Eurasian Griffons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Gyps fulvus</named-content></italic>) were equivalent between tubular and lattice towers at a wind energy facility in the Straits of Gibraltar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Barrios1">Barrios and Rodr&iacute;guez 2004</xref>). As turbine height increases, species that rely on lift for flight may become more susceptible to collisions (e.g., Eurasian Griffons; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas2">De Lucas et al. 2008</xref>), as may species that typically fly at higher altitudes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss3">Loss et al. 2013</xref>). Turbine rotor diameter may also increase mortality rates through increasing the area within which birds are at risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss3">Loss et al. 2013</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Barclay1">Barclay et al. 2007</xref>). For species attracted to artificial light sources (e.g., nocturnal migrants; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gauthreaux1">Gauthreaux and Belser 2006</xref>), the use of steady-burning lights at facilities may increase mortality rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger et al. 2010</xref>). However, the use of flashing red lights at wind energy facilities, as recommended by the Federal Aviation Association, does not appear to influence collision rates between infrastructure and nocturnal migrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger et al. 2010</xref>). Fatalities may also increase when turbines are positioned perpendicularly to regular flight paths of birds; 90&ndash;95&percnt; of tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Sterna</named-content></italic> spp.) fatalities at a wind energy facility in Belgium resulted from collisions with turbines positioned in a line perpendicular to their flight path between the breeding colony and feeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Everaert1">Everaert and Stienen 2007</xref>). Similarly, wind energy facilities sited along migration pathways may result in more migrant birds being killed than resident birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2002</xref>).Direct mortality also varies by species. Species that forage on the ground are less likely to collide with turbines compared with species that use aerial foraging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hull1">Hull et al. 2013</xref>). Similarly, aerial foragers that forage within rotor-swept areas and that appear to focus more on prey than on turbine blades are more susceptible to direct mortality than those that exercise caution around turbines (e.g., American Kestrel &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Falco sparverius</named-content></italic>&rsqb; vs. Northern Harrier &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Circus cyaneus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood3">Smallwood et al. 2009</xref>). Also at risk are species that frequently engage with conspecifics during aerial territorial conflicts (e.g., Golden Eagle; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood1">Smallwood and Thelander 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood3">Smallwood et al. 2009</xref>). Collision risk may be further elevated for species with visual fields that may prohibit them from detecting structures (e.g., wind turbines) directly ahead of them (e.g., vultures in the genus <italic>Gyps</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Martin1">Martin 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Martin4">Martin et al. 2012</xref>), or for large species with weak-powered flight and high wing loading that rely on thermals for lift and thus have relatively low maneuverability in flight (e.g., Eurasian Griffon; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeLucas2">De Lucas et al. 2008</xref>). Vulnerability to turbine collisions may also vary within species for which sex-specific behaviors result in one sex spending more time within rotor-swept areas. For example, heightened foraging activity of male terns during egg-laying and incubation at a wind energy facility in Belgium resulted in male-biased mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stienen1">Stienen et al. 2008</xref>). Similarly, song flights performed by male Sky Larks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Alauda arvensis</named-content></italic>) during the breeding season at a wind energy facility in Portugal increased collision risk, resulting in male-biased mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Morinha1">Morinha et al. 2014</xref>).To date, most studies of indirect effects have focused on the displacement of birds from wind energy facilities. Displacement, typically measured via telemetry or point counts, has been documented for a wide range of taxa including geese (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Larsen1">Larsen and Madsen 2000</xref>), ducks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loesch1">Loesch et al. 2013</xref>), raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins2">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Garvin1">Garvin et al. 2011</xref>), grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins1">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2012</xref>), shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins2">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins1">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Niemuth1">Niemuth et al. 2013</xref>), and songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins2">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2013</xref>). While the mechanisms driving displacement are poorly understood, loss or degradation of habitat may be important, especially for habitat specialists (e.g., Le Conte's Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Ammodramus leconteii</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2013</xref>), and may be compounded for species that are sensitive to turbine noise, construction noise, or tall structures (e.g., geese: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Larsen1">Larsen and Madsen 2000</xref>; raptors: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Garvin1">Garvin et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Johnston1">Johnston et al. 2014</xref>). The latter may be especially relevant in open areas (e.g., grasslands), where species may be sensitive to tall structures, including wind turbines and power poles (e.g., prairie grouse; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hovick1">Hovick et al. 2014</xref>). While some species appear sensitive to wind energy development, evidence for the displacement of other species is either minimal or site-specific (e.g., Sky Lark: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Devereux1">Devereux et al. 2008</xref>; Savannah Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Passerculus sandwichensis</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2013</xref>; Montagu's Harrier &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Circus pygargus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-HernandezPliego1">Hern&aacute;ndez-Pliego et al. 2015</xref>; Eastern Meadowlark &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Sturnella magna</named-content></italic>&rsqb;: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hale1">Hale et al. 2014</xref>), and some species may even be attracted to wind energy facilities (e.g., Killdeer &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Charadrius vociferus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Buhl 2016</xref>). Moreover, sensitivity to wind energy development may not always be reflected through changes in spatial ecology, but instead through other behaviors (e.g., lekking; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smith1">Smith et al. 2016</xref>). Birds that avoid wind energy facilities during and immediately following construction may fail to show avoidance behavior thereafter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Madsen1">Madsen and Boertmann 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins1">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2012</xref>), perhaps minimizing long-term effects in those species. Alternatively, some species may exhibit a delayed response to wind energy facilities, tolerating disturbance immediately following construction, but avoiding the site thereafter (e.g., Grasshopper Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Ammodramus savannarum</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Buhl 2016</xref>).Wind energy facilities may also indirectly affect breeding performance. For example, distance to a turbine negatively affected nest survival of Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-LeBeau1">LeBeau et al. 2014</xref>), but had little effect on nest survival of Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gillespie1">Gillespie and Dinsmore 2014</xref>), Greater Prairie-Chickens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McNew1">McNew et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Harrison1">Harrison 2015</xref>), and McCown's Longspurs (<italic>Rhynchophanes mccownii</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Mahoney1">Mahoney and Chalfoun 2016</xref>). In contrast, Scissor-tailed Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Tyrannus forficatus</named-content></italic>) nesting in sites close to a 75-turbine wind energy facility in Texas had higher nest survival compared with their counterparts nesting in sites farther away (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rubenstahl1">Rubenstahl et al. 2012</xref>). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hatchett1">Hatchett et al. (2013)</xref> documented higher nest success for Dickcissels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Spiza americana</named-content></italic>) nesting near, compared with far from, a wind energy facility in Texas. However, the authors stressed that habitat configuration across the study site, not proximity to turbines, may have underpinned their results.Wind energy development may also influence adult survival, but, again, effects are likely to be site- and species-specific. For example, annual survival of female Greater Prairie-Chickens increased postconstruction compared with preconstruction of a wind energy facility in Kansas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Winder2">Winder et al. 2014</xref>). In contrast, distance to a turbine did not affect the survival of female Greater Prairie-Chickens breeding along a 25-km gradient at a wind energy facility in Nebraska (J. A. Smith personal observation). Similarly, the survival of female Greater Sage-Grouse breeding in the vicinity of a wind energy facility in Wyoming was unaffected by distance to a turbine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-LeBeau1">LeBeau et al. 2014</xref>).Despite continuing efforts to assess the indirect effects of wind energy development on birds, the underlying mechanisms are seldom evaluated. For species targeted by brood parasites, a reduction in parasitism rates at wind energy facilities may increase nest success; Blue-gray Gnatcatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Polioptila caerulea</named-content></italic>) nesting close to a wind energy facility in Texas had a lower probability of nest parasitism by Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>) and, subsequently, higher nest success than birds farther away. While it remains unclear why parasitism rates were lower at the wind energy facility, disturbance at the site may have impeded the ability of Brown-headed Cowbirds to detect nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bennett1">Bennett et al. 2014</xref>).Changes in predator abundance may be key to understanding the indirect effects of wind energy development on measures of breeding success and adult survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rubenstahl1">Rubenstahl et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-LeBeau1">LeBeau et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Winder2">Winder et al. 2014</xref>). For example, avoidance of wind energy facilities by raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins2">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Garvin1">Garvin et al. 2011</xref>), or by mammalian predators due to increased disturbance associated with human activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gese1">Gese et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gehrt1">Gehrt et al. 2009</xref>), may reduce predation risk at sites close to wind energy facilities, consequently increasing survival. Alternatively, the presence of carcasses under wind turbines due to collision-induced mortalities may attract mammalian predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smallwood2">Smallwood et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rogers1">Rogers et al. 2014</xref>), whose presence will, in turn, decrease survival. Despite these expectations, to our knowledge only one study has evaluated predation risk as a possible mechanism underlying survival by simultaneously assessing occupancy of predators and survival of Greater Prairie-Chickens. Site occupancy of avian predators in the vicinity of a wind energy facility in Nebraska was significantly lower within, compared with 2 km beyond, the wind energy facility (J. A. Smith personal observation). In contrast, mammalian predator site occupancy was unaffected. Although no effect was found on the survival of Greater Prairie-Chickens, the study provides evidence of an ecological mechanism that could have important implications for a wide range of species at risk from wind energy development.The mechanisms underlying displacement or changes in the spatial ecology of birds at wind energy facilities are often discussed, but rarely evaluated. Given that prey species may avoid areas of high predation risk (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lima1">Lima 1998</xref>), changes in predator abundance at wind energy facilities (e.g., abundance of raptors; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins2">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2009</xref>) may be important for elucidating displacement behavior. Similarly, the presence of tall structures (i.e. wind turbines, power poles) at wind energy facilities that provide perches for avian predators may increase perceived predation risk, resulting in avoidance of those sites by potential prey species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2013</xref>). Alternatively, species associated with disturbed ground or gravel substrates may be attracted to wind energy facilities through increased opportunities for foraging or nesting (e.g., Killdeer; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Buhl 2016</xref>), as has been observed at disturbance sites with relatively small footprints associated with other energy sectors (e.g., oil and natural gas developments; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gilbert1">Gilbert and Chalfoun 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Ludlow1">Ludlow et al. 2015</xref>). Wind turbines may also create barriers, causing birds to alter their flight patterns to avoid those areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Drewitt1">Drewitt and Langston 2006</xref>).Increasing evidence suggests that birds may be sensitive to anthropogenic noise, and that noise from traffic, roads, aircraft, and energy infrastructure could disrupt acoustic communication through masking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Ortega1">Ortega 2012</xref>). In response to anthropogenic noise, birds may alter the characteristics of their vocalizations to compensate for masking (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hu1">Hu and Cardoso 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Francis1">Francis et al. 2012</xref>), or they may show behavioral avoidance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bayne1">Bayne et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Blickley1">Blickley et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McClure1">McClure et al. 2013</xref>). Recent research suggests that low-frequency noise produced by wind turbines may disrupt acoustic communication, causing birds to modify their vocalization characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Whalen1">Whalen 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Zwart1">Zwart et al. 2016b</xref>). These results suggest that noise associated with wind energy development may disturb birds and could act as a mechanism driving indirect effects (e.g., lekking behavior; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Smith1">Smith et al. 2016</xref>). However, the likelihood of noise as an intermediary mechanism is likely to be species-specific, depending on the extent of masking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rheindt1">Rheindt 2003</xref>).Because solar energy development can occur in areas of high endemism (e.g., the deserts of the southwestern U.S.), the potential impacts on bird populations are substantial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lovich2">Lovich and Ennen 2011</xref>). Yet, to our knowledge, only 1 peer-reviewed study of direct impacts exists: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McCrary1">McCrary et al. (1986)</xref> concluded that the risk of collision with infrastructure at a solar energy facility in the Mojave Desert, California, was low after documenting 70 mortalities of 26 bird species over a 40-week period. The facility consisted of mirrors (heliostats) that concentrated solar energy onto a centrally located tower where liquid was converted to steam to generate electricity (hereafter &lsquo;solar tower'). More recent preliminary evaluations across 3 different solar energy facilities in southern California suggest that direct impacts are greater than previously thought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>), and that installation design also affects risk. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. (2014)</xref> considered 3 quite different installations: solar towers; photovoltaic cells that convert solar energy directly into electricity; and parabolic troughs consisting of mirrors that reflect solar energy onto a receiver tube within the trough which transports heated fluid to generate electricity. Opportunistic collection of carcasses at the 3 facilities suggested that mortality rates were higher at solar towers compared with parabolic troughs or photovoltaic cells. However, given the lack of information regarding fatalities at solar energy facilities, conclusive estimates of mortalities associated with solar energy facilities cannot be established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss4">Loss et al. 2015</xref>).Two main causes of death have been identified across solar energy facilities: impact trauma and exposure to concentrated solar energy (heat) at solar tower facilities (hereafter, &lsquo;solar flux'; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>). In common with other anthropogenic structures, all types of solar energy facilities may result in deaths of birds through impact trauma; solar flux trauma is unique to solar tower facilities. By damaging feathers (sometimes severely) when birds fly through areas of concentrated heat near the tower, solar flux can hinder a bird's ability to fly, induce shock, and damage soft tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>). By impairing flight, solar flux trauma may increase the risk of direct collision with infrastructure or the ground, or may reduce a bird's ability to forage or evade predators.Carcasses from a wide range of taxa have been identified at solar energy facilities (e.g., ducks, wading birds, raptors, rails, shorebirds, and songbirds; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McCrary1">McCrary et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>). The mortality of an individual of the federally endangered subspecies of Ridgway's Rail (<italic>Rallus obsoletus yumanensis</italic>) suggests that solar energy facilities may have important consequences for species of conservation concern. While it appears that many species may be at risk, relatively high numbers of waterbird carcasses at photovoltaic cell facilities suggest that waterbirds may be particularly at risk where infrastructure (i.e. photovoltaic cells) reflects polarized light, giving the impression of water (Horv&aacute;th et al. 2009, 2010). The water retention ponds needed at solar tower facilities may exacerbate risk by attracting birds to solar energy facilities, especially in arid landscapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McCrary1">McCrary et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>). Insects that are apparently attracted to solar tower facilities may underlie the large number of aerial insectivores affected by solar flux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hovath1">Hov&aacute;th et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>), emphasizing the complex ecological processes that may contribute to risks to birds. While the mechanisms underlying mortality events are sometimes unclear, evidence indicating that solar energy facilities could be ecological traps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Schlaepfer1">Schlaepfer et al. 2002</xref>) has begun to accrue.To our knowledge, only 1 peer-reviewed study has evaluated the indirect effects of solar energy development on birds. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeVault1">DeVault et al. (2014)</xref> demonstrated that solar photovoltaic facilities could potentially alter bird communities: In 5 locations across the U.S., species diversity was lower at photovoltaic array sites than in adjacent grasslands (37 vs. 46 species, respectively). In contrast, bird densities at the same photovoltaic array sites were more than twice those of adjacent grasslands. Observations during the study suggested that shade and the provision of perches increased bird use of the photovoltaic array sites. However, the results were species specific, with some small songbird species (e.g., American Robin &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) more abundant at photovoltaic facilities compared with adjacent grasslands used for habitat comparisons, but corvids and raptors less abundant. Similarly, raptor abundance was higher preconstruction compared with postconstruction of a utility-scale solar energy facility in south-central California, suggesting avoidance of the facility. In comparison, ravens and icterids increased in abundance during construction, possibly as a result of increased foraging opportunities at disturbed sites (J. Smith personal communication).Similarly to the effects of wind energy development and other onshore energy development (e.g., oil and natural gas development; Kalyn Bogard and Davis 2014, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bayne2">Bayne et al. 2016</xref>), the potential indirect effects of solar energy facilities on birds are likely site-specific. For example, given that the footprint and configuration of solar energy facilities vary with the technology used (e.g., photovoltaic facilities are typically larger than solar tower sites; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hernandez2">Hernandez et al. 2014a</xref>), indirect effects mediated through habitat loss or barrier effects are likely dependent on site-specific infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hernandez1">Hernandez et al. 2014b</xref>). Solar energy facilities may also disrupt local hydrology through groundwater extraction or channelization, which could reduce both food and habitat availability for birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Grippo1">Grippo et al. 2015</xref>). Such effects are likely amplified at sites where footprints are large and at facilities that consume large volumes of groundwater (e.g., parabolic troughs and solar towers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hernandez1">Hernandez et al. 2014b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Grippo1">Grippo et al. 2015</xref>). The potential for contaminant runoff to indirectly affect birds also may be elevated at sites with large footprints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Grippo1">Grippo et al. 2015</xref>). Variation in other disturbances (e.g., vehicular traffic, construction noise, and operations) among sites could also contribute to site-specific variation in indirect effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lovich2">Lovich and Ennen 2011</xref>); we encourage further exploration of these factors.Renewable energy facilities often require the construction of new transmission lines to deliver the energy produced at the facility to the existing power line network. These permanent connections may include many kilometers of lines supported by towers 30&ndash;35 m tall, and can traverse habitats beyond the line of sight from either the renewable energy facility or from a center of energy consumption. This is particularly true after ideal siting locations close to existing lines have been developed; subsequently constructed renewable energy facilities can be increasingly distant from the existing transmission line network, requiring increasingly longer connections. Transmission lines are associated with collision mortalities of flying birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rogers1">Rogers et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lobermeier1">Lobermeier et al. 2015</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Luzenski1">Luzenski et al. 2016</xref>), but renewable energy connections can be overlooked when investigating direct and indirect effects of renewable energy facilities.Avian interactions with transmission lines appear to affect populations primarily through direct mortality, although indirect effects of habitat fragmentation have been hypothesized. Direct collision mortality is an ongoing concern in many areas of the U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Yee1">Yee 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Sporer1">Sporer et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Luzenski1">Luzenski et al. 2016</xref>). Collisions are most often associated with aquatic habitats, where species with high wing loading, high flight speeds, and poor maneuverability are common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaw1">Shaw et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Quinn1">Quinn et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Barrientos1">Barrientos et al. 2012</xref>). Large, heavy-bodied species such as swans, pelicans, herons, and cranes are generally thought to be more susceptible to transmission line collisions than smaller, more maneuverable species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-APLICAvianPowerLineInteractionCommittee2">APLIC 2012</xref>). Nocturnal migrants have not been well studied, but also may be susceptible, particularly within migration corridors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Rogers1">Rogers et al. 2014</xref>), and especially in light of their susceptibility to collision with other types of tall anthropogenic structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Drewitt2">Drewitt and Langston 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Gehring1">Gehring et al. 2011</xref>). Relatively small duck and grouse species are also vulnerable to collision because of their high flight speed, low altitude, and flocking flight, in which the view of upcoming obstacles is obscured by leading birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-APLICAvianPowerLineInteractionCommittee1">APLIC 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bevanger1">Bevanger and Br&oslash;seth 2004</xref>). Transmission lines bisecting daily movement corridors, such as those located between roosting and foraging sites, have been most associated with avian collisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bevanger1">Bevanger and Br&oslash;seth 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Stehn1">Stehn and Wassenich 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-APLICAvianPowerLineInteractionCommittee2">APLIC 2012</xref>), with risk exacerbated during low light, fog, and other inclement weather conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Savereno1">Savereno et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-APLICAvianPowerLineInteractionCommittee2">APLIC 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Huppop1">H&uuml;ppop and Hilgerloh 2012</xref>). Transmission lines are typically constructed with relatively thin overhead shield wires at the top, and thicker energized conductors below. Birds appear to see energized conductors and adjust flight altitudes upward to avoid them, subsequently colliding with smaller, less visible overhead shield wires (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Murphy1">Murphy et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-VentanaWildlifeSociety1">Ventana Wildlife Society 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Martin3">Martin and Shaw 2010</xref>). Collision risk may be further exacerbated for species with narrower fields of view (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Martin3">Martin and Shaw 2010</xref>), but this remains an important research gap because to date it has been thoroughly studied only in Kori Bustards (<italic>Ardeotis kori</italic>), Blue Cranes (<italic>Grus paradisea</italic>), and White Storks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Ciconia ciconia</named-content></italic>), which are large, collision-prone species. Collision risk may be mitigated in migrating raptors, which tend to fly diurnally during good weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Ligouri1">Ligouri 2005</xref>) and appear to detect and avoid transmission lines, even those located in major migration corridors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Luzenski1">Luzenski et al. 2016</xref>).The indirect effects of transmission lines are not well studied. Of the existing studies that have addressed indirect effects, most have considered grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lammers1">Lammers et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Coates2">Coates et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Coates1">Coates and Delehanty 2010</xref>) or desert tortoises (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Gopherus agassizii</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Boarman1">Boarman 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Berry1">Berry et al. 2013</xref>), species of conservation concern potentially preyed upon by corvids and raptors using utility structures as hunting perches. As power lines have proliferated, at least some corvid species appear to have expanded their breeding ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Jerzak1">Jerzak 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Marzluff1">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dwyer1">Dwyer et al. 2013a</xref>) or increased their breeding densities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Coates3">Coates et al. 2014</xref>) through utilizing power poles for nesting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Fleischer1">Fleischer et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Howe1">Howe et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dwyer4">Dwyer et al. 2015</xref>), possibly leading to indirect effects on their prey. Recent research suggests that avoidance by reindeer (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Rangifer tarandus</named-content></italic>) may be linked to their ability to detect ultraviolet (UV) light emitted by transmission lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Tyler1">Tyler et al. 2014</xref>). At least some birds also see in the UV spectrum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lind1">Lind et al. 2014</xref>), but the potential implications of this for indirect effects have not been thoroughly investigated.Our review summarizes existing studies of direct and indirect effects of energy infrastructure associated with 2 expanding energy sectors (onshore wind and solar), and indicates ongoing concern about the transmission lines connecting these facilities to existing electric transmission lines. This overview demonstrates that both the magnitude and the mechanisms of direct and indirect effects of renewable energy infrastructure and the associated power lines on birds are site- and species-specific (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-VillegasPatraca1">Villegas-Patraca et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-DeVault1">DeVault et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bayne2">Bayne et al. 2016</xref>). However, while we have provided comprehensive coverage of existing peer-reviewed literature, we stress that existing gray literature, much of which is held by private energy companies, would likely shed additional light on the direct and indirect effects of renewable energy infrastructures. Thus, increased public availability of privately funded data is urgently needed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss1">Loss 2016</xref>).Despite highlighting the prevalence of both site- and species-specific effects, some generalities can be drawn from our review. Large-bodied species with weakly powered flight, high wing loading, and relatively low maneuverability appear to be especially susceptible to the direct effects of tall structures at energy facilities (e.g., wind turbines and power poles). This is of concern, given that the sensitivity of such species at the population level is likely high because of delayed maturity and low reproductive rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dahl1">Dahl et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Lovich1">Lovich 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss1">Loss 2016</xref>). The effects of placement appear to be important across all energy infrastructure types considered in this review; infrastructure that bisects regular daily or migratory flight paths (e.g., turbine lines, transmission lines) may disproportionately affect birds compared with structures sited outside regular flight paths. The placement of infrastructure in habitat with few natural tall perches (deserts, grasslands, sagebrush steppe) may be more disruptive to the overall ecology of an area than the placement of infrastructure in habitat previously characterized by natural tall structures (forests), but further research is needed to explore these expectations. Given that all infrastructure results in direct habitat loss, indirect effects that act through the loss or fragmentation of habitat are likely to occur across all energy sectors. Similarly, given the potential for energy infrastructure and power lines to affect the distribution of predators, predation may be an important mechanism underlying indirect effects across energy facilities.When considered together, the direct and indirect effects at renewable energy facilities and the transmission lines serving those facilities are likely cumulative and could be synergistic, especially when facilities are poorly sited (e.g., in areas of high bird abundance, in regular flight paths, or where facilities could act as ecological traps). However, the magnitude of direct effects is likely far less for energy facilities compared with other anthropogenic mortality sources in the U.S. (e.g., cats, buildings, communication towers, and automobiles; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss4">Loss et al. 2015</xref>), and the indirect effects of wind energy facilities may be less than those of traditional energy infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hovick1">Hovick et al. 2014</xref>). Nevertheless, the potential for additional effects of other infrastructure at energy facilities could further increase direct and indirect effects within an energy facility's footprint (e.g., roads: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-BenitezLopez1">Ben&iacute;tez-L&oacute;pez et al. 2010</xref>; maintenance buildings: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Loss2">Loss et al. 2014</xref>).A critical end-goal for research in this field is to integrate research findings into mitigation strategies and to inform siting guidelines. Given the site- and species-specific nature of the effects of the energy infrastructure reviewed here, siting guidelines should be carefully developed in the context of vulnerable species within a particular geographic area. However, some key generalities have emerged that should be considered during siting decisions. We suggest the following: (1) Avoiding areas of high bird use (e.g., regularly used flight paths, migration corridors, and aggregation areas); (2) Avoiding areas inhabited by sensitive species or those of conservation concern; (3) Avoiding topographical features that promote foraging or that are used by migrating birds for uplift (e.g., the tops of slopes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kitano1">Kitano and Shiraki 2013</xref>); (4) Avoiding areas of high biodiversity, endemism, and ecological sensitivity; (5) Developing conservation buffers for vulnerable species based on thresholds determined through empirical research; (6) Carefully selecting or modifying infrastructure to minimize collision risk or indirect effects (e.g., by the use of flashing red lights and ground devices, or by employing efficient technology that uses less space; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kerlinger1">Kerlinger et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Martin2">Martin 2012</xref>); and (7) Curtailing turbine operation under certain conditions (e.g., fog in the presence of sensitive species).We also encourage the use of predictive models to gauge likely impacts at sites (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaw1">Shaw et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dwyer2">Dwyer et al. 2013b</xref>), and encourage the development and use of spatially explicit sensitivity maps that incorporate the distribution of bird populations, key flight paths, habitats, and risk factors (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Bright1">Bright et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Dwyer3">Dwyer et al. 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Pearse1">Pearse et al. 2016</xref>).The expected trajectory of the renewable energy sector (both in size and in technological advances) will expand the geographic area and, thus, habitats impacted by development. Much research to date has focused on wind energy development in grassland habitats in the Great Plains (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-LeBeau1">LeBeau et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Harrison1">Harrison 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Winder1">Winder et al. 2015</xref>) and, to a lesser extent, solar energy development in the deserts of the southwestern U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-McCrary1">McCrary et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Kagan1">Kagan et al. 2014</xref>). However, interactions between renewable energy infrastructure and birds are likely different among habitats (e.g., grasslands vs. woodlands), and thus continued habitat-specific research is needed. Because the effects of energy infrastructure on birds may vary with stage of operation (e.g., during construction, immediately following construction, and &gt;1 yr postconstruction; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Madsen1">Madsen and Boertmann 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-PearceHiggins1">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Buhl 2016</xref>), such studies should be conducted over an extended period (e.g., 5, 10, or 15 yr). Studies that enable researchers to separate the effects of different infrastructure at facilities (e.g., roads, buildings, and wind turbines) are also encouraged. Given that wind energy infrastructure is also associated with bat collisions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Doty1">Doty and Martin 2013</xref>), future research should seek to integrate avian and bat monitoring to identify cumulative effects.Understanding the mechanisms that underlie the indirect effects of energy infrastructure on birds is essential if we are to establish conservation strategies that minimize potential impacts. While efforts have been made to address these concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Whalen1">Whalen 2015</xref>, J. A. Smith personal observation), the mechanistic drivers of effects are likely to vary with infrastructure type and across sites. Therefore, we encourage researchers to adopt mechanistic approaches in future studies of indirect effects by designing studies to reveal important mechanisms. Mechanisms could include, but are not limited to, changes in predation risk, food availability, and habitat availability, and avoidance of physical structures, lights, and UV light. Given that anthropogenic noise may disturb birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Slabbekoorn1">Slabbekoorn and Ripmeester 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Blickley1">Blickley et al. 2012</xref>), we suggest that studies of energy development and avian interactions consider the role that infrastructure noise plays in driving indirect effects. Studies of solar facilities should explore the mechanisms resulting in avian concentrations at photovoltaic arrays (e.g., polarized light; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Hovath2">Hov&aacute;th et al. 2009</xref>).Given that siting guidelines are often concerned with threshold distances (i.e. the distances from energy facilities at which effects on target species become negligible), we stress the relevance of using a gradient approach in studies of avian and energy infrastructure interactions. For example, by evaluating impacts on target populations at various distances from energy facilities, threshold distances can be identified and used to develop biologically meaningful conservation buffers. Such approaches have proven valuable in studies of disturbance associated with roads, urban areas, and oil and gas development (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Reijnen1">Reijnen et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Laurance1">Laurance 2004</xref>, Palomino et al. 2007), and should be integrated into studies of renewable energy infrastructure (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Winder2">Winder et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Harrison1">Harrison 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Whalen1">Whalen 2015</xref>). By centering buffers on sensitive habitat patches or populations, areas where development should be avoided can be delineated. However, we note that the effects of energy infrastructure may not always be detected via a gradient approach. Instead, the intensity of development (e.g., density of wind turbines) may be more informative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-411-Mahoney1">Mahoney and Chalfoun 2016</xref>). When possible, we also encourage implementation of a Before-After-Control-Impact (BACI) study design that allows comparison of preconstruction, postconstruction, and control data, or, better still, an Impact-Gradient-Design (IGD) study design that incorporates the properties of both a gradient approach and a BACI study design. When preconstruction data is not available, control sites away from the focal energy facility should be considered. Researchers should also consider the specific biology (e.g., spatial ecology, life-history strategy) of the focal species, or focal populations, to sample suitable control sites.We thank R. E. Harness, J. Smith, and A. Chalfoun for conversations which guided the direction of this work. We are also grateful to D. H. Johnson for reviews of an earlier draft of this manuscript, which improved it substantially.Funding statement: J.A.S. was supported through U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Wildlife Restoration dollars administered by the Nebraska Game and Parks Commission. J.F.D. was supported by EDM International. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript, nor required approval of the manuscript prior to submission or publication.Author contributions: The idea for this review was conceived by both J.A.S. and J.F.D. following a symposium that they jointly developed and moderated at the 2014 joint meeting of the American Ornithologists' Union (AOU), Cooper Ornithological Society (COS), and Society of Canadian Ornithologists (SCO) at Estes Park, Colorado, USA. Both J.A.S. and J.F.D. wrote this review.