Summer vs. winter: Examining the temporal distribution of avian biodiversity to inform conservationSeasonal variation of foraging niches in a guild of passerine birds in a cork-oak woodlandThe boreal forest region: North America's bird nurseryNational shorebird conservation assessment: Shorebird conservation status, conservation units, population estimates, population targets, and species prioritizationImpacts of sudden winter habitat loss on the body condition and survival of Redshank <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tringa totanus</named-content></italic>Temporal changes in the foraging behaviour of insectivorous birds in a sclerophyll forest in TasmaniaHabitat use under latent predation risk. A case study with wintering forest birdsWinter bird distribution in abiotic and habitat structural gradients: A case study with mediterranean montane oakwoodsThermal, food and vegetation effects on winter bird species richness of Mediterranean oakwoodsModern methods of estimating biodiversity from presence-absence surveysEstimating species richness and accumulation by modeling species occurrence and detectabilityRecent advances in understanding migration systems of New World land birdsThe valley riparian forests of California: Their importance to bird populationsAbundance patterns of landbirds in restored and remnant riparian forests on the Sacramento River, California, U.S.AInference from iterative simulation using multiple sequencesTemporal and taxonomic variability in response of fauna to riparian restorationHabitat-specific demography of breeding Black-throated Blue Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendroica caerulescens</named-content></italic>): Implications for population dynamicsThe effect of energy and seasonality on avian species richness and community compositionHabitat selection by nonbreeding, migratory land birdsDetecting diversity: Emerging methods to estimate species diversityGlobal distribution and conservation of evolutionary distinctness in birdsHabitat use does not reflect habitat quality for Henslow's Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus henslowii</named-content></italic>) wintering in fire-managed longleaf pine savannasConservation of riparian ecosystems in the United StatesScale perspectives on avian diversity in western riparian ecosystemsUse of data on avian demographics and site persistence during overwintering to assess quality of restored riparian habitatSeasonal dynamics of guild structure in a bird assemblage of the central Monte DesertEstimating site occupancy, colonization, and local extinction when a species is detected imperfectlyBiodiversity hotspots for conservation prioritiesSeasonal interactions, habitat quality, and population dynamics in migratory birdsThe effects of human-induced changes on the avifauna of western riparian habitatsFeathering the scene: The effects of ecological restoration on birds and the role birds play in evaluating restoration outcomesJAGS: A program for analysis of Bayesian graphical models using Gibbs samplingVertebrate use of a restored riparian site: A case study on the central coast of CaliforniaHandbook of Field Methods for Monitoring LandbirdsRelationships of population size and recruitment of pintails to habitat conditions and harvestThe riparian bird conservation plan: A strategy for reversing the decline of riparian associated birds in CaliforniaUsing breeding land birds in the assessment of western riparian systemsBoreal migrants in winter bird communitiesEcological conditions during winter affect sexual selection and breeding in a migratory birdEnvironmental determinants of seasonal changes in bird diversity of Mediterranean oakwoodsWinter habitat quality, population limitation, and conservation of Neotropical-Nearctic migrant birdsProjected large-scale range reductions of northern-boreal land bird species due to climate changeSeasonal change in guild structure: Oak woodland insectivorous birdsGlobal role for sustaining bird populationsModelling community dynamics based on species-level abundance models from detection/nondetection dataPatterns of avian population density, habitat use, and flocking behavior in urban and rural habitats during winterComparison of bird community indices for riparian restoration planning and monitoringCurrent address: Point Blue Conservation Science, Petaluma, California, USAWinter habitat quality plays a key role in avian population regulation, and conservation of winter habitat is a priority for waterfowl, shorebirds, and Neotropical migrant landbirds. Yet, there has been little discussion of the importance of conserving temperate wintering habitat for landbirds, including the billions of Neotemperate migratory landbirds that winter in the United States. The value and impact of conservation initiatives in the U.S. could be maximized by accommodating the habitat requirements of bird communities throughout the full annual cycle, particularly in the southern and western U.S. where winter species richness is concentrated. To estimate the degree to which winter bird communities should be a conservation priority, we examined the temporal distribution of avian diversity using riparian habitat in the lower Cosumnes River and lower Putah Creek watersheds in California's Central Valley. We used hierarchical multispecies occupancy models to estimate seasonal species richness and phylogenetic diversity in each watershed. We found that total species richness was equally as high in winter as in summer, and that phylogenetic diversity was higher in winter, with a considerable proportion of the winter avian diversity attributable to boreal-breeding Neotemperate migrants. Our results provide evidence that maintaining and restoring high-quality riparian habitat for winter bird communities in California is an important conservation opportunity. Broader recognition of the diversity of temperate winter bird communities and additional research into the factors affecting body condition and survival would facilitate effective conservation of high-quality winter habitat, benefiting Neotemperate migrants and year-round residents during a season that can have important impacts on their population dynamics.La calidad de los h&aacute;bitats de invierno juega un rol clave en la regulaci&oacute;n de las poblaciones de aves, y la conservaci&oacute;n de los h&aacute;bitats de invierno es una prioridad para las aves acu&aacute;ticas, las aves playeras y las aves terrestres migratorias neotropicales. A pesar de esto, ha habido poca discusi&oacute;n sobre la importancia de conservar los h&aacute;bitats templados de invernada para las aves terrestres, incluyendo los miles de millones de aves terrestres migratorias neotempladas que invernan en los Estados Unidos. El valor y el impacto de las iniciativas de conservaci&oacute;n en los EEUU podr&iacute;an maximizarse si se acomodaran los requerimientos de h&aacute;bitat de las comunidades de aves a lo largo del ciclo anual completo, particularmente en las comunidades del sur y del oeste de EEUU donde se concentra la riqueza de especies de invierno. Para estimar el grado de prioridad de conservaci&oacute;n de las comunidades de aves de invierno, examinamos la distribuci&oacute;n temporal de la diversidad de aves usando los h&aacute;bitats ribere&ntilde;os en las cuencas bajas del R&iacute;o Cosumnes y del Arroyo Putah en el Valle Central de California. Usamos modelos de ocupaci&oacute;n jer&aacute;rquicos multiespec&iacute;ficos para estimar la riqueza estacional de especies y la diversidad filogen&eacute;tica en cada cuenca. Encontramos que la riqueza total de especies fue igual de alta en invierno que en verano, y que la riqueza filogen&eacute;tica fue m&aacute;s alta en invierno, con una proporci&oacute;n considerable de la diversidad de aves de invierno atribuible a los migrantes neotemplados que cr&iacute;an en el norte. Nuestros resultados ponen en evidencia que mantener y restaurar h&aacute;bitat ribere&ntilde;o de alta calidad para las comunidades de aves de invierno en California representa una oportunidad importante de conservaci&oacute;n. Un mayor reconocimiento de la diversidad de las comunidades de aves de invierno de las &aacute;reas templadas e investigaci&oacute;n adicional de los factores que afectan la condici&oacute;n corporal y la supervivencia facilitar&iacute;an la conservaci&oacute;n efectiva de los h&aacute;bitats de invierno de alta calidad, beneficiando a los migrantes neotemplados y a los residentes durante la estaci&oacute;n invernal, con potenciales impactos importantes en la din&aacute;mica poblacional de estas especies.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> California, conservaci&oacute;n de la biodiversidad, diversidad filogen&eacute;tica, invierno, migrante neotemplado, ribere&ntilde;o, riqueza de especiesWinter habitat quality plays a key role in regulating avian populations, affecting body condition, survival rates, migration timing, and reproductive success across taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Raveling1">Raveling and Heitmeyer 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Holmes1">Holmes et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sherry1">Sherry and Holmes 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Saino1">Saino et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Burton1">Burton et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Norris1">Norris and Marra 2007</xref>). Consequently, North American bird conservation plans recognize the importance of conserving and managing temperate wintering habitat for waterfowl and shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Brown1">Brown et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-NorthAmericanWaterfowlManagementPlanNAWMP1">NAWMP 2012</xref>) and tropical wintering habitat for Neotropical migratory landbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Berlanga1">Berlanga et al. 2010</xref>). There has been surprisingly little discussion of the importance of conserving and managing temperate wintering habitat for landbirds, however, including Neotemperate migratory landbirds, which breed in the boreal region and winter in the U.S. and/or southern Canada.Although the boreal forest has been called a &ldquo;Neotropical migrant factory&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Rich2">Rich et al. 2004</xref>), more boreal-breeding species winter in temperate latitudes, especially in the U.S. and southern Canada (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Blancher1">Blancher and Wells 2005</xref>). These Neotemperate migrants represent billions of individual birds that can make up a large proportion of winter bird communities in the U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Robertson1">Robertson et al. 2011</xref>). Although they breed in one of the largest and most intact habitats in the world, many of these species are in decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Berlanga1">Berlanga et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wells2">Wells et al. 2014</xref>). For example, Breeding Bird Surveys in the Boreal Hardwood Transition ecoregion indicate significant negative trends for 49&percnt; of migratory species between 1966 and 2012 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2014</xref>). Thus, winter habitat quality and quantity are likely important factors in these declines. Further, accelerating rates of development and climate change in the boreal region increase the likelihood of future declines and are an area of growing conservation concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Virkkala1">Virkkala et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wells2">Wells et al. 2014</xref>). Maintaining and restoring high-quality winter habitat for Neotemperate migratory landbirds is therefore an important research and conservation need.Research over the full annual cycle of migratory birds has proven a valuable approach for identifying seasonal limiting factors and prioritizing conservation efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Faaborg1">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>). Similarly, research over the full annual cycle of an individual ecosystem or management area could prove valuable in identifying seasonal habitat needs, prioritizing conservation efforts, and maximizing the impact of a local or regional conservation plan. This approach may be especially important in regions where winter species richness is concentrated, including the southern and western U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Rich2">Rich et al. 2004</xref>). For example, the conservation and restoration of riparian habitat is a high priority in California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Knopf1">Knopf et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Rich1">Rich 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-RiparianHabitatJointVentureRHJV1">RHJV 2004</xref>), in part because of its importance to wildlife (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Gaines1">Gaines 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Knopf1">Knopf et al. 1988</xref>) and the high densities of breeding birds found there (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Knopf2">Knopf and Samson 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Ohmart1">Ohmart 1994</xref>). Evaluating restoration success by monitoring the response of the breeding bird community is widely recommended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Rich1">Rich 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Gardali1">Gardali et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-OrtegaAlvarez1">Ortega-&Aacute;lvarez and Lindig-Cisneros 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Young1">Young et al. 2013</xref>), yet the responses of winter bird communities to riparian restoration are rarely studied (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Queheillalt1">Queheillalt and Morrison 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Golet1">Golet et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Latta1">Latta et al. 2012</xref>). Thus, it is unclear to what extent current conservation practices and restoration designs are meeting the needs of winter bird communities, or to what degree the value of these restoration projects could be increased by making the needs of winter bird communities a priority.We propose that seasonal conservation priorities can be identified by examining the temporal distribution of biodiversity at a site over the full annual cycle. This approach is analogous to setting spatial conservation priorities by identifying areas that support high levels of biodiversity (i.e. biodiversity hotspots; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Myers1">Myers et al. 2000</xref>). To identify seasons during which riparian ecosystems support high levels of biodiversity, we used hierarchical multi-species occupancy models to compare the species richness and phylogenetic diversity of the summer and winter bird communities in 2 watersheds in California's Central Valley. While we expected both measures of diversity to be higher in summer, we also expected to observe considerable levels of both species and phylogenetic diversity in winter, indicating that the value of riparian habitat conservation projects in California could be increased by incorporating the needs of winter bird communities into their designs.We conducted strip transect surveys for birds in the lower Cosumnes River and lower Putah Creek watersheds, located in California's Central Valley (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Putah Creek is a heavily impacted riparian system, with 2 dams, a deeply-incised creek channel, and a narrow riparian forest, while the Cosumnes River is the only major free-flowing river remaining in California; it has a much broader riparian forest and is considered to be a relatively intact riparian ecosystem. Surveys were distributed over 14 sites along Putah Creek beginning in 2004 and 10 sites along the Cosumnes River beginning in 2006, continuing through 2012. No surveys were conducted in the Cosumnes River watershed during the breeding season of 2006 due to extreme flooding. During each 45-minute survey, trained observers walked a 500 m transect paralleling the waterway, tallying the number of individuals of each species detected within 30 m of the transect line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Ralph1">Ralph et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Bibby1">Bibby et al. 2000</xref>). Surveys were not conducted under adverse weather conditions (i.e. rain or high winds). Barring flooding and access constraints, generally one survey was conducted per site in each of the winter (1 January&ndash;29 February) and summer seasons (1 April&ndash;30 June) in each year. To minimize effects of time of day, summer surveys were completed by 0930 hours; however, time of day restrictions were relaxed for winter surveys due to reduced bird activity during cold mornings. For this analysis, we excluded surveys conducted in April to minimize the number of transient individuals detected on spring migration and to make the 2 survey seasons of comparable length.Putah Creek and Cosumnes River study areas in the Central Valley of California, showing the 24 study sites.We assigned each species to 1 of 3 groups: primarily summer visitors, winter visitors, or year-round residents. We also determined the extent to which each winter visitor species was known to breed in the boreal forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wells1">Wells and Blancher 2011</xref>) and compiled continent-wide population trends from Breeding Bird Survey data, 1966&ndash;2012 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2014</xref>). Finally, as a measure of phylogenetic diversity, we compiled evolutionary distinctness (ED) scores for each species as reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Jetz1">Jetz et al. (2014)</xref>, which represent how isolated a species is on its phylogenetic tree. Species with few close relatives have higher ED scores and may be considered more valuable in that they represent a larger share of avian evolutionary history. Examining variation in phylogenetic diversity provides an alternative method to species richness for identifying biodiversity hotspots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2014</xref>).Making use of repeated surveys at each site, occupancy models can be used to estimate the probability of a species' presence at a site while accounting for variation in detection probabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Dorazio1">Dorazio et al. 2011</xref>). In hierarchical multispecies occupancy models, all species are combined into a single model in which detection and occupancy probabilities for each species are assumed to come from a common distribution. Further, they can be used to generate unbiased estimates of species richness for each site or groups of sites, including hypothetical species that have not yet been detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Dorazio1">Dorazio et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>). We fit a hierarchical multispecies occupancy model that allowed occupancy to differ by season and watershed. Because we were primarily interested in the differences across seasons, we treated the 24 sites in each season as 48 independent sites, allowing the true occupancy status of each species in each site-season to be estimated separately. We also assumed there was no change in the true occupancy status of each species in each site-season across years, and we treated repeated transects in the same site-season across years as our replicate visits.We used a model structure recently described in detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. (2014)</xref>. The observed presence or absence of each species <italic>i</italic> in site <italic>j</italic> on survey replicate <italic>k</italic> (<italic>y<sub>ijk</sub></italic>) was modeled as resulting from the true occupancy status of each species in each site (<italic>Z<sub>ij</sub></italic>) with imperfect detection (<italic>p<sub>i</sub></italic>): <italic>y<sub>ijk</sub></italic> ~ <italic>Bernoulli</italic>(<italic>p<sub>i</sub>Z<sub>ij</sub></italic>), where <italic>Z<sub>ij</sub></italic> &equals; 1 or 0 if species <italic>i</italic> in site <italic>j</italic> is truly present or absent, respectively. True occupancy (<italic>Z<sub>ij</sub></italic>) was modeled as resulting from the probability of occupancy by each species in each site-season (&psi;<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>) and the existence of the species in the region (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>): Z<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> ~ <italic>Bernoulli</italic>(&psi;<italic><sub>ij</sub>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), where <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 1 for all observed species. To account for unobserved species, we augmented the observed data with 100 hypothetical species with all zero encounter histories, which were modeled as existing in the community with probability &Omega;: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> ~ <italic>Bernoulli</italic>(&Omega;). The model can estimate how many of these species are present but never detected on any surveys, analogous to the asymptote of a species-accumulation curve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Yamaura1">Yamaura et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>). An arbitrarily large number of hypothetical species must be chosen to ensure that it exceeds the posterior estimate of the number of unobserved species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Dorazio2">Dorazio et al. 2006</xref>).We also specified in the model several metrics of species richness and phylogenetic diversity derived directly from the species-specific estimates of true occupancy at each site-season (<italic>Z<sub>ij</sub></italic>) in each iteration of the model, allowing incorporation of estimation error. For species richness (subscript s), these metrics included local species richness (&alpha;<sub>s</sub>), defined as the total number of observed and hypothetical species present at each site, and mean local species richness (&alpha;̄<sub>s</sub>), defined as the mean number of observed and hypothetical species present across sites in each season, overall and within each watershed. Regional species richness (&gamma;<sub>s</sub>) was defined as the total number of observed and hypothetical species present overall and within each watershed, and the turnover in species richness (&beta;<sub>s</sub>) was defined as the ratio of &gamma; diversity to mean &alpha; diversity overall and within each watershed (&beta;<sub>s</sub> &equals; &gamma;<sub>s</sub> / &alpha;̄<sub>s</sub>). Similarly, we calculated each of these metrics for phylogenetic diversity (subscript p: &alpha;<sub>p</sub>, &gamma;<sub>p</sub>, and &beta;<sub>p</sub>) for each season and watershed based on the total ED of all observed species. We did not include unobserved species in the metrics of phylogenetic diversity because there was no clear way to estimate the ED of unobserved species.We used JAGS 3.4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Plummer1">Plummer 2003</xref>) and the R package R2jags 0.04-01 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Su1">Su and Yajima 2014</xref>) to fit the model using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC). We used uninformative priors for the means and variances of the community-level distributions of each <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> in the model. To ensure convergence, even for species with very few detections, we ran 3 chains of 120,000 iterations, discarding the first 100,000 iterations and thinning the remainder by 20, resulting in 3,000 iterations used for inference. We assessed convergence using the Gelman-Rubin diagnostic (R̂), and for all parameters R̂ &lt; 1.1, indicating convergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Gelman1">Gelman and Rubin 1992</xref>). We considered there to be a significant difference between seasonal community parameters if the 95&percnt; credible interval for the difference in the parameters did not overlap zero. All values reported in the Results section are posterior means followed by 95&percnt; credible intervals.The final dataset included 315 surveys, with 41 summer and 66 winter surveys in the lower Cosumnes River watershed and 93 summer and 115 winter surveys in the lower Putah Creek watershed, on which we detected 138 total species (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>). Local species richness (&alpha;<sub>s</sub>) was significantly higher in summer for 6 of the 10 Cosumnes River sites and 2 of the 14 Putah Creek sites; no sites had higher species richness in winter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Mean species richness across sites (&alpha;̄<sub>s</sub>) was significantly higher in summer (83.8, 74.4&ndash;95.1) than winter (74.5, 66.2&ndash;84.4) overall and within each watershed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f03">Figure 3</xref>), with a mean of 8.8 (1.7&ndash;16.4) more species per site. However, we found no significant difference between total species richness (&gamma;<sub>s</sub>) in summer (124.1, 115&ndash;138) and winter (129.6, 117&ndash;146) overall, or within either watershed. Consequently, the ratio of total to local species richness (&beta;<sub>s</sub>) was significantly higher in winter (1.74, 1.59&ndash;1.90) than summer (1.48, 1.37&ndash;1.62), both overall and within each watershed.Mean and 95&percnt; credible intervals for seasonal differences in (<bold>A</bold>) species richness and (<bold>B</bold>) phylogenetic diversity at individual sites in the lower Cosumnes River and lower Putah Creek watersheds. A positive difference indicates higher richness or diversity in summer.Species richness of summer (filled) and winter (open) communities, overall and within each watershed. Mean and 95&percnt; credible intervals for each metric are shown. (<bold>A</bold>) Mean species richness across sites (&alpha;̄<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). (<bold>B</bold>) Total species richness across sites (&gamma;<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). (<bold>C</bold>) Ratio of total to site species richness (&beta;<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). &ast;95&percnt; credible intervals for the difference between seasons do not overlap zero.Despite significant seasonal differences in species richness at the site level, we found no significant seasonal differences in local phylogenetic diversity (&alpha;<sub>p</sub>) at any individual site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f02">Figure 2</xref>). There were also no significant differences between mean phylogenetic diversity across sites (&alpha;̄<sub>p</sub>) in summer (506.0, 455.9&ndash;562.7) and winter (495.5, 447.8&ndash;549.2), either overall or within each watershed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f04">Figure 4</xref>). However, total phylogenetic diversity (&gamma;<sub>p</sub>) across all sites was significantly higher in winter (855.2, 821.9&ndash;891.6) than summer (759.7, 724.8&ndash;825.5), and the ratio of total to local phylogenetic diversity (&beta;<sub>p</sub>) was significantly higher in winter (1.73, 1.55&ndash;1.91) than in summer (1.50, 1.37&ndash;1.68) overall. Differences in total phylogenetic diversity within each watershed were not significant.Phylogenetic diversity of summer (filled) and winter (open) communities, overall and in each watershed, based on the total evolutionary distinctness of each species present. Mean and 95&percnt; credible intervals for each metric are shown. (<bold>A</bold>) Mean phylogenetic diversity across sites (&alpha;̄<italic><sub>p</sub></italic>). (<bold>B</bold>) Total phylogenetic diversity across sites (&gamma;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic>). (<bold>C</bold>) Ratio of total to site phylogenetic diversity (&beta;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic>). &ast;95&percnt; credible intervals for the difference between seasons do not overlap zero.Individual species contributed differently to seasonal changes in species richness and phylogenetic diversity. Of the 138 species detected, 32 were identified <italic>a priori</italic> as summer visitors, 34 as winter visitors, and 72 as year-round residents (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>). Of the summer and winter visitor groups, 3 species were rare (Cassin's Vireo, Black-throated Gray Warbler, and Pine Siskin; all scientific names provided in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>), with high uncertainties in their occupancy estimates (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t02">Table 2</xref>). Of the remainder, the seasonal occupancy probabilities confirmed our summer and winter visitor groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f05">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f06">6</xref>), most of which had <italic>b<sub>i</sub></italic> estimates with credible intervals that did not overlap zero, indicating significant differences in seasonal occupancy probabilities. Several winter visitors had moderate (&gt;0.2) summer occupancy estimates (e.g., Hermit Thrush, Yellow-rumped Warbler, and Golden-crowned Sparrow; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f05">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f06">6</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t02">Table 2</xref>), reflecting their late departures from the area and thus their contribution to summer richness and diversity estimates.Summer and winter occupancy probabilities in the lower Putah Creek watershed for groups of (<bold>A</bold>) summer visitors, (<bold>B</bold>) winter visitors, and (<bold>C</bold>) year-round residents. Filled circles mark species with significant differences in seasonal occupancy probabilities; open circles are not significantly different. Year-round resident species showing little difference (&lt;10&percnt;) between summer and winter occupancy probabilities are marked with gray triangles. Rare species with 3 or fewer detections in either season, and thus high uncertainty in occupancy probabilities, are marked with gray crosses. Select species are identified with their 4-letter codes (see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>).Summer and winter occupancy probabilities in the lower Cosumnes River watershed for groups of (<bold>A</bold>) summer visitors, (<bold>B</bold>) winter visitors, and (<bold>C</bold>) year-round residents. Filled circles mark species with significant differences in seasonal occupancy probabilities; open circles are not significantly different. Year-round resident species showing little difference (&lt;10&percnt;) between summer and winter occupancy probabilities are marked with gray triangles. Rare species with 3 or fewer detections in either season, and thus high uncertainty in occupancy probabilities, are marked with gray crosses. Select species are identified with their 4-letter codes (see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>).Of the 72 year-round residents, 14 were rarely detected, but of the remaining 58 species, nearly half (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 27) had a &lt;10&percnt; difference in seasonal occupancy probabilities in both watersheds (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t02">Table 2</xref>), indicating little seasonal variation in their use of riparian habitat. Of the remainder, <italic>b<sub>i</sub></italic> estimates with credible intervals that did not overlap zero indicated several year-round residents with significant differences in their seasonal occupancy probabilities: 3 that significantly increased in summer (Black-crowned Night-Heron, Brown-headed Cowbird, and American Goldfinch) and 3 that significantly increased in winter (Canada Goose, Anna's Hummingbird, and Northern Mockingbird) in both watersheds, indicating seasonal changes in their local abundance and/or use of riparian habitat. Two additional species (Black Phoebe and Western Scrub-Jay) significantly increased in winter only in the lower Cosumnes River watershed.Detection probabilities varied widely among species (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>), but there were no significant differences in mean detection probabilities across all observed species between summer (0.137, 0.117&ndash;0.159) and winter (0.133, 0.115&ndash;0.154), or for year-round residents between summer (0.166, 0.140&ndash;0.194) and winter (0.159, 0.140&ndash;0.181). These relatively low mean detection probabilities reflect the relatively large number of difficult to detect and/or sparsely distributed species that may be missed on any individual survey. Detection probabilities were significantly higher in summer for 9 year-round resident species and significantly higher in winter for 1 (Northern Flicker; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>). Because detection probabilities were overall similar between seasons, a similar estimated number of species were missed in summer (12.2, 4&ndash;24) and winter (14.9, 6&ndash;28). Consequently, excluding these hypothetical species had no effect on the results for seasonal differences in &alpha; or &gamma; species richness, and only the seasonal difference in &beta; species richness within the lower Putah Creek watershed became nonsignificant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f07">Figure 7</xref>).Species richness of summer (filled) and winter (open) communities, excluding hypothetical, unobserved species, overall and for each watershed. Mean and 95&percnt; credible interval for each metric are shown. (<bold>A</bold>) Mean species richness across sites (&alpha;̄<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). (<bold>B</bold>) Total species richness across sites (&gamma;<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). (<bold>C</bold>) Ratio of total to site species richness (&beta;<italic><sub>s</sub></italic>). &ast;95&percnt; credible intervals for the difference between seasons do not overlap zero.Of the 34 winter visitors to these 2 watersheds, 33 were species that regularly breed in the boreal forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wells1">Wells and Blancher 2011</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t03">Table 3</xref>). As a group they represented an average of 24.4&percnt; (21.6&ndash;26.9&percnt;) of the total winter species richness (&gamma;<sub>s</sub>) and 26.4&percnt; (25.3&ndash;27.5&percnt;) of the total winter phylogenetic diversity (&gamma;<sub>p</sub>). Of these 33 species, at least 10 have significantly declined on continent-wide Breeding Bird Surveys since 1966 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2014</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t03">Table 3</xref>), including 5 species with estimated occupancy probabilities &gt;80&percnt; in one or both of these watersheds (Dark-eyed Junco, White-crowned Sparrow, Purple Finch, Common Merganser, and Varied Thrush; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t02">Table 2</xref>).The riparian habitat in the 2 watersheds we studied in California's Central Valley supported diverse winter bird communities, as we expected. Contrary to our expectation, however, winter species richness (&gamma;<sub>s</sub>) was just as high as summer species richness in both watersheds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f03">Figure 3</xref>B), and when the 2 watersheds were pooled, winter phylogenetic diversity (&gamma;<sub>p</sub>) was significantly higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f04">Figure 4</xref>B). Thus, riparian habitat supported just as many species and a greater proportion of avian genetic diversity in winter as in summer. The presence of high winter richness and diversity does not necessarily indicate robust and thriving populations, however, and a considerable proportion of the winter species richness and phylogenetic diversity was contributed by boreal-breeding Neotemperate migrants, nearly one-third of which are significantly declining continent-wide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2014</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t03">Table 3</xref>). Because winter habitat quality plays a key role in avian population regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Holmes1">Holmes et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sherry1">Sherry and Holmes 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Saino1">Saino et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Norris1">Norris and Marra 2007</xref>) and may be a factor in these declines, our results provide evidence that maintaining and restoring high-quality riparian habitat for Neotemperate migrants and year-round residents in California is an important conservation responsibility.Wintering birds are often regarded as habitat generalists with relaxed habitat requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Yaukey1">Yaukey 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Queheillalt1">Queheillalt and Morrison 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Golet1">Golet et al. 2011</xref>). While they may not be restricted to a particular habitat type, birds may actively select winter habitat based on food availability, structure, microclimate, or predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Hutto1">Hutto 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Carrascal2">Carrascal and Diaz 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Carrascal1">Carrascal et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Carrascal3">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Seoane1">Seoane et al. 2013</xref>). Thus, if riparian vegetation represents relatively high-quality winter habitat in California's Central Valley with a reliable food supply and preferred vegetation structure, then many species may be locally riparian-dependent during the winter. Many of our year-round residents had little difference (&lt;10&percnt;) between their summer and winter occupancy probabilities, and 3 species had significantly higher occupancy probabilities in winter in both watersheds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f05">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f06">6</xref>), indicating continued or increased reliance on riparian habitat through the winter. Among Neotemperate migrants, future comparisons of occupancy probabilities between riparian and other habitat types would provide important information about the degree to which species are dependent on riparian habitat during the winter.Our results also indicate that the value of riparian habitat conservation initiatives could be maximized by accommodating the needs of both breeding and wintering communities. In addition to species turnover within the avian community itself, resource availability, predation risk, habitat structure, and microclimate may all change between the summer and winter seasons. In response, species may use different habitat types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Hutto1">Hutto 1985</xref>), expand or specialize their foraging niches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wagner1">Wagner 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Cale1">Cale 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Almeida1">Almeida and Granadeiro 2000</xref>), or switch dietary guilds altogether (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-LopezdeCasenave1">Lopez de Casenave et al. 2008</xref>). Because the habitat requirements of the wintering bird community are likely to be distinct from those of the breeding bird community, we recommend extra consideration of the needs of the temperate wintering bird community and their responses to restoration and management practices. Here, we found that birds were less evenly distributed in winter, with significantly greater heterogeneity in species composition (&beta;<sub>s</sub>) and phylogenetic diversity (&beta;<sub>p</sub>) across sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f03">Figures 3</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-f04">4</xref>C), which may reflect aggregation in the highest quality sites and reveal patchiness in required resources and variation in habitat suitability for winter birds that is not apparent among breeding birds. Given limited conservation resources, these winter biodiversity &ldquo;hotspots&rdquo; could be targeted for protection, or, alternatively, features missing from the &ldquo;coldspots&rdquo; could be identified and restored. Additional research linking specific vegetation structure and composition, food availability, microclimate, and/or predation risk to winter bird distributions, abundance, body condition, or survival rates (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Carrascal2">Carrascal and D&iacute;az 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Carrascal1">Carrascal et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Latta1">Latta et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Seoane1">Seoane et al. 2013</xref>) will contribute to the design of effective restoration strategies and management plans to benefit wintering birds.Our examination of the temporal distribution of avian biodiversity in 2 California Central Valley watersheds revealed that riparian habitat supports diverse bird communities throughout the year, a pattern that may also hold true in other habitat types and other regions of North America, particularly in the southern and western U.S. where winter species richness is concentrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Hurlbert1">Hurlbert and Haskell 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Rich2">Rich et al. 2004</xref>). We recommend this approach for setting seasonal conservation priorities, estimating not only seasonal differences in site-level species richness (&alpha;<sub>s</sub>), but also seasonal differences in heterogeneity among sites (&beta;<sub>s</sub>) and in total species richness (&gamma;<sub>s</sub>). We recommend the use of occupancy models that allow variation in detection probability among species and seasons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>). Although here we did not find seasonal differences in mean detection probabilities, detection probabilities did vary among species (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-t01">Table 1</xref>), and failing to account for variation in detection probability can bias estimates of occupancy and diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>). Finally, because species richness is not the sole measure of biodiversity, we recommend considering seasonal differences in other measures of diversity, such as diversity metrics that account for relative abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Iknayan1">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>) or evolutionary distinctness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2014</xref>). Broader recognition of the diversity and importance of winter bird communities and research into their habitat requirements will facilitate effective conservation of high-quality winter habitat for Neotemperate migrants and year-round residents during a season that can have important impacts on their population dynamics.We wish to thank Richard Marovich, David Okita, and the members of the Lower Putah Creek Coordinating Committee for their ongoing assistance and support; The Nature Conservancy and the Cosumnes River Preserve Conservation Partners for access to study sites on the Preserve; and the many landowners along Putah Creek without whom this study would not have been possible. We also wish to acknowledge John Trochet, Irene Engilis, and the many hard-working and talented field assistants at the Museum of Wildlife and Fish Biology who were instrumental in gathering field data over the span of this study. Three anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments on an earlier draft.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> We thank our partners and funding agencies, including Solano County Water Agency, Putah Creek Council, CALFED Bay-Delta Program, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, California Department of Water Resources, California Department of Fish and Wildlife, UC Davis Department of Wildlife, Fish &amp; Conservation Biology (Selma Herr Fund for Ornithology), and the cities of Davis and Winters, CA. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript nor required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.Seasonal detection probability estimates (medians with 95&percnt; credible intervals), grouped by species that are primarily summer visitors, winter visitors, or year-round residents. Also shown are scientific names, species codes and evolutionary distinctness scores (ED; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2014</xref>).Seasonal occupancy estimates for each watershed, grouped by species that are primarily summer visitors, winter visitors, or year-round residents.Boreal breeding status of winter visitors to Putah Creek and Cosumnes River. Shown are the estimated percent of the North American population breeding in the boreal forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Wells1">Wells and Blancher 2011</xref>) and continent-wide Breeding Bird Survey trends, 1966-2012 (with 95&percnt; credible intervals; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-560-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2014</xref>).