Interpreting negative results with taxonomic and conservation implications: Another look at the distinctness of coastal California GnatcatchersSpeciation on oceanic islands: Rapid adaptive divergence vs. cryptic speciation in a Guadalupe Island songbird (Aves: <italic>Junco</italic>)Speciation and geographic variation in Black-tailed GnatcatchersSubspecies limits and geographic patterns of morphological variation in California Gnatcatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>)Cladists in wonderlandRapid SNP discovery and genetic mapping using sequenced RAD markersGenomic and morphological analysis of a semi-permeable avian hybrid zone suggests asymmetrical introgression of a sexual signalFunds enough, and time: mtDNA, nuDNA and the discovery of divergenceGenome-wide genetic marker discovery and genotyping using next-generation sequencingLooking forwards or looking backwards in avian phylogeography? A comment on Zink and Barrowclough 2008Speciation in birds: Genes, geography, and sexual selectionArlequin suite ver 3.5: A new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and WindowsAnalysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes: Application to human mitochondrial DNA restriction dataHybridization of bird speciesA critical inspection of the gnatcatchers of the CaliforniasProspects for nuclear gene phylogeographyPhylogeographic patterns in widespread corvid birdsGenomic variation in a widespread Neotropical bird (<italic>Xenops minutus</italic>) reveals divergence, population expansion, and gene flowGenetic variation and seasonal migratory connectivity in Wilson's Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Wilsonia pusilla</named-content></italic>): Species-level differences in nuclear DNA between western and eastern populationsPhylogeographical approaches to assessing demographic connectivity between breeding and overwintering regions in a Nearctic&ndash;Neotropical warbler (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Wilsonia pusilla</named-content></italic>)The criterion of reciprocal monophyly and classification of nested diversity at the species levelProspects for the use of next-generation sequencing methods in ornithologyRelationship between funding source and conclusion among nutrition-related scientific articlesDnaSP v5: A software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism dataPavo: an R package for the analysis, visualization and organization of spectral dataUse of juvenal plumage in diagnosing species limits: An example using buntings in the genus <italic>Plectrophenax</italic>A hierarchy of species concepts: The denouement in the saga of the species problemDoes niche divergence accompany allopatric divergence in <italic>Aphelocoma</italic> jays as predicted under ecological speciation?: Insights from tests with niche modelsSpecies concepts in ornithologyTaxonomic status of the California Gnatcatchers of northwestern Baja CaliforniaThe geographic scale of diversification on islands: Genetic and morphological divergence at a very small spatial scale in the Mascarene Grey White-eye (Aves: <italic>Zosterops borbonicus</italic>)Thirty-seventh supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Checklist of North American Birds</italic>Genotyping-by-sequencing in ecological and conservation genomicsPredicting nuclear gene coalescence from mitochondrial data: The three-times ruleThe genomic consequences of adaptive divergence and reproductive isolation between species of manakinsNull expectations in subspecies diagnosisAre subspecies useful in evolutionary and conservation biology?The genomic landscape underlying phenotypic integrity in the face of gene flow in crowsHabitat shifts of endangered species under altered climate conditions: Importance of biotic interactionsThe evolution of F1 postzygotic incompatibilities in birdsAlaska Song Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melospiza melodia</named-content></italic>) demonstrate that genetic marker and method of analysis matter in subspecies assessmentsPattern, process, and rigor meet classificationGenetic introgression: An integral but neglected component of speciation in birdsGIS-based niche modeling for mapping species' habitatMapping migration in a songbird using high-resolution genetic markersDevelopers seek end to federal protections for California GnatcatcherType I errors linked to faulty statistical analyses of endangered subspecies classificationsPetition of the Center for Environmental Science, Accuracy and Reliability; Coalition of Labor, Agriculture, and Business; Property Owners Association of Riverside County; National Association of Home Builders; and The California Building Industry Association to remove the coastal California Gnatcatcher from the list of threatened species under the Endangered Species ActEndangered and threatened wildlife and plants; determination of threatened status for the coastal California Gnatcatcher. March 30, 1993. Final ruleEndangered and Threatened Wildlife and Plants; 90-Day Finding on a Petition to Delist the coastal California Gnatcatcher as Threatened. October 26, 2011Concerning some <italic>Polioptilae</italic> of the west coast of Middle AmericaTetrachromacy, oil droplets and bird plumage coloursGenome-wide RAD sequence data provide unprecedented resolution of species boundaries and relationships in the Lake Victoria cichlid adaptive radiationEnvironmental niche equivalency versus conservatism: Quantitative approaches to niche evolutionSubspecies represent geographically partitioned variation, a gold mine of evolutionary biology, and a challenge for conservationVainly beating the air: Species-concept debates need not impede progress in science or conservationThe genic view of the process of speciationThe role of subspecies in obscuring avian biological diversity and misleading conservation policyGenetics, taxonomy, and conservation of the threatened California GnatcatcherMitochondrial DNA under siege in avian phylogeographyMolecular systematics and biogeography of aridland gnatcatchers (genus <italic>Polioptila</italic>) and evidence supporting species status of the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>)Phylogeography of the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>) using multilocus DNA sequences and ecological niche modeling: Implications for conservationRigor and species conceptsThe debate over species concepts and its implications for ornithologyA recent study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> raises questions about how to interpret negative results in studies when the distinctness of a species of conservation concern is in question. Zink et al. found no evidence for genetic or ecological distinctness of the coastal California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content> californica</italic>). We discuss why the genetic markers they chose were not well suited to the question of distinctness and how they overinterpreted negative results in their genetic and ecological analyses. We reanalyze their genetic data and find evidence that several genetic loci show significant differentiation in the coastal California Gnatcatchers. We provide recommendations for best practices in determining distinctness in phenotype, genetics, and ecology for California Gnatcatchers and other populations of conservation concern.Un estudio reciente de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> pregunta sobre c&oacute;mo interpretar los resultados negativos en estudios donde la diferenciaci&oacute;n de la especie de inter&eacute;s para la conservaci&oacute;n est&aacute; cuestionada. Zink y sus colegas no encontraron evidencia sobre diferenciaciones gen&eacute;ticas o ecol&oacute;gicas de los individuos costeros de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content> californica</italic>. Planteamos aqu&iacute; por qu&eacute; los marcadores gen&eacute;ticos que ellos eligieron no fueron apropiados para evaluar la pregunta sobre la diferenciaci&oacute;n de la especie y c&oacute;mo exageraron la interpretaci&oacute;n de los resultados negativos en sus an&aacute;lisis gen&eacute;ticos y ecol&oacute;gicos. Reanalizamos sus datos gen&eacute;ticos y encontramos evidencia de que varios loci gen&eacute;ticos mostraron diferencias significativas para los individuos costeros de <italic>P. c. californica</italic>. Brindamos recomendaciones de buenas pr&aacute;cticas para determinar la diferenciaci&oacute;n en el fenotipo, en el genotipo y en la ecolog&iacute;a de <italic>P. c. californica</italic> y otras poblaciones de inter&eacute;s para la conservaci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ADN mitocondrial, ADN nuclear, aves, filogeograf&iacute;a, gen&eacute;tica de la conservaci&oacute;n, modelos de nichoIf land developers and conservationists are to work together, they require objective scientific evidence upon which to base their actions. In situations involving threatened or endangered species, the question of whether a population is distinct in phenotype, genetics, or habitat is often key, and all parties must determine how studies that report negative results should be interpreted. What conclusions should be drawn when scientists <italic>fail</italic> to find evidence for distinctness? Not finding something does not mean it is not there. And the likelihood of an absence being a true absence increases with search effort. These ideas form the basis of statistical hypothesis testing, a core underlying principle of the scientific process.A recent study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> raises questions about how to interpret negative results and what constitutes reasonable search effort in a case with high conservation stakes. Zink and colleagues found no evidence for genetic or ecological distinctness of populations of the California Gnatcatcher in the coastal sage scrub of southern California (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content> californica</italic> or coastal California Gnatcatcher). This finding, combined with similar results from a previous genetic study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink2">Zink et al. 2000</xref>), contrasted with a century of prior work documenting the occurrence of a distinct population of gnatcatchers in southern California based on evidence of physical differences (summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea 1994</xref>). On the basis of the negative results in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>, land developers petitioned the U.S. Department of the Interior and U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) to remove the California Gnatcatcher from listing under the U.S. Endangered Species Act (ESA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Thornton1">Thornton and Schiff 2014</xref>), which could potentially open 197,000 acres of currently protected habitat to human development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Sahagun1">Sahagun 2014</xref>).Prior to the current debate, we have had no involvement in the issue of the coastal California Gnatcatcher. This Commentary reflects our critique of the basic science in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013</xref>), and its application to taxonomy and conservation. Specifically, we discuss why their choice of genetic markers was not well suited to the question of distinctness. We also address how negative results were overinterpreted in their genetic and ecological analyses. We reanalyze their genetic data and find evidence that several genetic loci actually show significant differentiation in the federally listed coastal California Gnatcatchers. Finally, we provide recommendations for best practices in determining distinctness in phenotype, genetics, and ecology in coastal California Gnatcatchers and in other cases with important taxonomic and conservation implications.The California Gnatcatcher was first recognized as a distinct species based on differences from other gnatcatchers in song and morphology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood1">Atwood 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Monroe1">Monroe et al. 1989</xref>). Phylogenetic data supported this decision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink4">Zink and Blackwell 1998</xref>), placing the California Gnatcatcher as the sister species of the Black-tailed Gnatcatcher (<italic>P. melanura</italic>), with which it occurs sympatrically. Despite the relatively recent decision to elevate the California Gnatcatcher to species level, it is important to recognize that subspecies variation within the group, including the occurrence of a distinct form in southern California, had already been well described over the past century (summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea 1994</xref>).In the first genetic study of these subspecies, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink2">Zink et al. (2000)</xref> showed that coastal California Gnatcatchers did not possess a unique set of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) haplotypes compared to southern populations in Baja California and, therefore, did not meet the criteria set for &ldquo;reciprocal monophyly.&rdquo; When each of two populations has a unique set of alleles, and alleles from each set share a more recent common ancestor with one another than with alleles from the other set, biologists term this scenario &ldquo;reciprocal monophyly&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Kizirian1">Kizirian and Donnelly 2004</xref>). We will discuss below why reciprocal monophyly is an overconservative threshold for assessing distinctness, but for now we simply note <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al.'s (2013)</xref> reasoning in selecting markers for their study.The rationale behind looking at more than a single marker is that mtDNA, being a single inherited unit, can be affected by pressures like natural selection, or even by chance events, and therefore sometimes does not accurately reflect the population's history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Edwards2">Edwards et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Edwards1">Edwards and Bensch 2009</xref>). To address this potential problem, it is advisable to supplement mtDNA with markers from the nuclear genome. Collecting nuclear data was, in fact, a major recommendation of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-U.S.FishandWildlifeService2">USFWS (2011)</xref> in response to a previous petition to delist the coastal California Gnatcatchers, which followed the publication of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink2">Zink et al. (2000)</xref>.For their nuclear markers, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> looked at 7 nuclear DNA introns, 1 nuclear exon, and 2 mtDNA regions (i.e. 1 more mtDNA region than their previous study, but still considered 1 linked locus). The problem with this marker choice is that nuclear introns do not mutate as quickly as mtDNA; consequently, unit for unit, they contain less signal of the population history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Hare1">Hare 2001</xref>). Nuclear introns also achieve reciprocal monophyly more slowly than mtDNA because of their larger population size&mdash;4 chromosomal copies compared with the haploid mtDNA genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Palumbi1">Palumbi et al. 2001</xref>). In short, given that coastal California Gnatcatchers were already known to lack reciprocal monophyly in mtDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink2">Zink et al. 2000</xref>), one would not expect to find reciprocal monophyly in the handful of additional nuclear markers chosen by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>. This is not to say that all types of nuclear markers are always a poor choice for assessing distinctness, even with recent divergence. In these cases, however, the nuclear markers should have high mutation rates, as was requested in the case of the gnatcatchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-U.S.FishandWildlifeService2">USFWS 2011</xref>), or should be assayed in high numbers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Wagner1">Wagner et al. 2013</xref>).What makes their marker choice all the more perplexing is that Zink and colleagues have been vocal critics of doing precisely what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> did&mdash;namely, using nuclear DNA loci to assess population distinctness and reciprocal monophyly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink3">Zink and Barrowclough 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Barrowclough1">Barrowclough and Zink 2009</xref>). Given their own negative views about the use of nuclear DNA in phylogeography, it is ironic that Zink and colleagues have chosen to rely on such data to prove their point. At the end of this commentary, we will discuss best practices for marker choice in studies like this.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> never tested whether the coastal California Gnatcatchers were genetically distinct. Instead they based their conclusions largely on qualitative patterns in pie charts, like those that appear in their <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-f01">figure 1</xref>. They also referred to their table 1, which describes nucleotide diversity within and between populations but does not test for differentiation. They reported a nonsignificant <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> value for the ND2 gene, but it appears they conducted a global test across all populations, instead of specifically testing whether coastal California Gnatcatchers were distinct from southern populations.Groupings of California Gnatcatcher populations for the two AMOVA tests conducted in this study. Sampling localities are from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>. Test 1 is based on the original Endangered Species Act listing at 30&deg; latitude. Test 2 is based on the division between <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content> californica</italic> and <italic>P. c. atwoodi</italic> described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea (1994)</xref>.Their figure 3, which they reported as an analysis of genetic structure across geographic distance, is not an appropriate test because pairwise points are not independent from one another and, therefore, should not be analyzed for significance with regression. Given pairwise comparisons across all populations (not just nearest neighbors), it is far from clear what the expected pattern would be in the case of geographically structured genetic variation. Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> did not explain which of the 13 original populations were pooled or removed to arrive at the 9 populations used to generate the 36 pairwise points on the plot.Here, we analyze genetic data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> and show that, despite the chosen genes being few and relatively poor for addressing differentiation, statistical tests actually support divergence of the coastal California Gnatcatchers. We downloaded <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al.'s (2013)</xref> data from GenBank (KC863990&ndash;KC864745) and conducted a standard and widely accepted test of population differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Excoffier2">Excoffier et al. 1992</xref>), analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA), between populations for each locus. We conducted tests by dividing the populations in two separate ways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-f01">Figure 1</xref>). For test 1, we separated the recognized subspecies <italic>californica</italic> (Los Angeles south to San Telmo) from more southern populations (Misi&oacute;n San Fernando south to Cabo San Lucas), based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood's (1991)</xref> quantitative morphological subspecies boundaries and the USFWS initial listing boundary of 30&deg;N latitude. For test 2, we restricted our analysis to those samples assigned to the northern subspecies <italic>californica</italic> (Los Angeles to San Diego) and an adjacent, more southern subspecies <italic>atwoodi</italic> (Ensenada to San Telmo), basing the dividing line on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea's (1994)</xref> subspecies boundaries. We did not reanalyze the BFIB-5 locus because these data likely combine alleles from two different (i.e. paralagous) genes, and thus they are not appropriate for phylogeographic analysis (Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-f02">Figure 2</xref>). We assigned sequences from the remaining loci to the populations described above, using DnaSP version 5.10.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Librado1">Librado and Rozas 2009</xref>), and exported these as Arlequin project files. We then tested for significant differentiation using an AMOVA in Arlequin version 3.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Excoffier1">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>).Results from test 1 show that according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood's (1991)</xref> boundaries, the <italic>californica</italic> subspecies of California Gnatcatchers is significantly differentiated from southern populations at 2 of the 7 nuclear loci: ACON (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.062, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.014) and TGFB-2 (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.077, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.0049). Results from test 2 show that 2 of 7 nuclear loci (1 the same as above and 1 different) are significantly differentiated between the northern subspecies <italic>californica</italic> and <italic>atwoodi</italic>: ACON (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.087, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.046) and MC1R (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.195, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001); the mtDNA locus ND2 is also significantly differentiated (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.336, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.016). Another nuclear locus, CEPUS, was nearly significant (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.060, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.051). This is not terribly surprising upon reinspection of the pie charts in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-f01">figure 1</xref> of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>, which shows that northern populations have private alleles at the TGFB-2 and MC1R loci. This is also true of the ACON and ND2 loci, although these data are not shown in figure format in their paper.In summary, according to our analysis of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al.'s (2013)</xref> original data, the threatened <italic>californica</italic> subspecies of California Gnatcatchers is genetically differentiated from Baja populations at 29&percnt; (2 of 7) of the nuclear loci examined. Additionally, <italic>californica</italic> is differentiated from <italic>atwoodi</italic> at 29&percnt; (2 of 7) of the nuclear loci as well as mtDNA, which suggests that <italic>californica</italic> has a smaller geographic range and could be restricted to the United States. Importantly, 3 of the 7 nuclear loci examined show differentiation between <italic>californica</italic> and other populations in at least 1 of 2 different sets of comparisons.We do not claim that these analyses are the final word on differentiation of coastal California Gnatcatchers, as they are based on only a small fraction of the genome. Additionally, AMOVA tests, because they compare population means and variances, do not speak to diagnosability of individuals. However, given that neutral nuclear DNA loci are lagging indicators of differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink3">Zink and Barrowclough 2008</xref>), the population-level differences from the AMOVA results lend credence to a genetic basis for, or parallel to, the phenotypic diagnosability of individuals described in previous work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea 1994</xref>). Further, the AMOVA results show that the underlying genetic data contained in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> can produce positive results, at odds with their conclusions, when analyzed with a standard method.The ESA listing of the coastal California Gnatcatcher was originally based both on its status as a subspecies and on evidence for its distinctness (USFWS 1993). It seems reasonable that taxonomic recognition and distinctness should always go hand in hand, but unfortunately the empirical question of distinctness and the debate over what to call distinct units (sometimes called debate over &ldquo;species concepts&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink7">Zink and McKitrick 1995</xref>) are not as decoupled as they might be. Likely for this reason, the ESA also provides for protection of &ldquo;distinct population segments&rdquo; (DPSs), which currently lack taxonomic recognition and are instead designated on the basis of empirical evidence for discreteness, significance, and population status.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> was the latest in a series of works on genetics, taxonomy, and species concepts by the first author. Summarizing these works, Zink has advocated that all populations showing reciprocal monophyly should be recognized as species, whereas all potential taxa not meeting this criterion should go without taxonomic recognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-McKitrick1">McKitrick and Zink 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink1">Zink 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink6">Zink and Johnson 2006</xref>). In other words, by defining species through reciprocal monophyly, but requiring the same criterion for subspecies recognition, Zink effectively believes that the subspecies and DPSs covered by the ESA should not be given names (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>). Zink's views on subspecies are not widely accepted by his peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Remsen1">Remsen 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Winker2">Winker et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>) and reflect a rather extreme adherence to the phylogenetic species concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mayden1">Mayden 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Avise1">Avise 2000</xref>). In fact, many studies support the utility of the subspecies rank, while admitting that subspecies described long ago should be reevaluated with modern methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Phillimore1">Phillimore and Owens 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Price1">Price 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Pruett1">Pruett and Winker 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Winker1">Winker 2010</xref>).The expectation of reciprocal monophyly for taxonomic or legal recognition simply cannot be reconciled with what we know today about how biodiversity is generated. As the field of phylogeography has moved to using next-generation sequencing, we have seen populations distinctive in phenotype, but indistinguishable in mtDNA, become well resolved with thousands of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). One recent example is the case of Wilson's Warbler (<italic>Cardellina pusilla</italic>). Until recently, genetic markers, including mtDNA, could only discriminate broad differences between the 1 subspecies in eastern and the 2 subspecies in western North America, but not between the 2 western subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Kimura1">Kimura et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Irwin1">Irwin et al. 2011</xref>). Using a panel of 96 SNPs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Ruegg1">Ruegg et al. (2014)</xref> resolved Wilson's Warblers into genetic clusters that conform closely to the subspecies boundaries. They also found more fine-scale differentiation within subspecies that coincides with biogeographic regions. A potential criticism is that, with enough markers, every sampling location (and every individual, for that matter) will eventually show its own distinctive genetic pattern. This does not appear to be the case with the Wilson's Warblers study, in which some geographically distant localities (like those in western Alaska) showed genetic cohesiveness even when the analytical program was asked to continue dividing up the localities into ever finer units (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Ruegg1">Ruegg et al. 2014</xref>: supplementary fig. 1).New sequencing methods have also revealed how divergence and speciation can proceed despite gene exchange, leading to situations where reciprocal monophyly is not expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Rheindt1">Rheindt and Edwards 2011</xref>). The genome, it turns out, is a porous boundary, especially in birds, which have fewer postzygotic reproductive barriers than other vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Grant1">Grant and Grant 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Price2">Price and Bouvier 2002</xref>). When hybridization occurs, some genes flow freely between diverging lineages while other genes resist movement, resulting in monophyly at some genomic regions but not at others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Wu1">Wu 2001</xref>). This is nicely illustrated in the case of the Hooded Crow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus cornix</named-content></italic>) and Carrion Crow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. corone</named-content></italic>). These two species with distinct plumage patterns are not differentiated from one another in mtDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Haring1">Haring et al. 2007</xref>). A recent study of whole genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Poelstra1">Poelstra et al. 2014</xref>) revealed that, in fact, most of the genome demonstrates allele sharing between species, partly due to hybridization. Meanwhile, the phenotypic differences appear to be encoded in a small portion of the genome that resists movement between species; and it is these regions alone that show reciprocal monophyly.Another problem with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> is the authors' interpretation of their ecological analysis, specifically the niche tests developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Warren1">Warren et al. (2008)</xref>. The way these tests work is that, first, the predicted niches are compared using a randomization procedure to see whether they are statistically different. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Warren1">Warren et al. (2008)</xref> called this a &ldquo;niche identity&rdquo; test, which provides statistical confidence to what had previously been the subjective endeavor of visualizing niche predictions on a map and eyeballing whether they were different. Using this test, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> found <italic>strongly significant differentiation</italic> between the niches of coastal California Gnatcatchers and other populations. Their figure 7 shows this highly significant niche difference with an arrow far outside the null distribution.There are confounding factors with this kind of test, however&mdash;principal among them that temperature and rainfall show continuous trends with latitude and are thus strongly correlated with geographic distance. No matter what species you might be looking at, or even if you just picked random points on a map, you would find that points at higher latitudes experience cooler and more seasonal temperatures than points at lower latitudes. This is not particularly interesting. To address this, and to provide a more robust test of niche differentiation, researchers developed additional tests that attempt to control for this &ldquo;background effect&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-McCormack1">McCormack et al. 2010</xref>).When implementing these &ldquo;background tests,&rdquo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> found that coastal California Gnatcatchers were not more differentiated in temperature and rainfall than their geographic position would predict, but neither were they more similar. In other words, they failed to reject the null hypothesis that niches and background areas were equally divergent. From this result they concluded that the coastal California Gnatcatcher is a habitat generalist. This is unsupported by their results. The proper interpretation is that by failing to reject the null hypothesis of the &ldquo;background test,&rdquo; it cannot be disentangled whether the strong niche differences from the &ldquo;identity test&rdquo; represent differences important to the California Gnatcatchers or arise simply from clinal trends in climate variables. No one, however, should doubt whether the coastal California Gnatcatchers live in a different climate than populations to the south; figure 7 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> shows that they most certainly do.We are in a time of new technologies and advances in genetic and ecological analyses. Because of time and money constraints, not every study can avail itself of the latest methods. But those studies that purport to demonstrate results with important societal consequences have a scientific obligation to use either the best available methods or to couch their conclusions in the appropriate level of uncertainty. Our critique of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> is not just that the authors did not always use the latest methods, but that the conclusions they drew from negative results were too sweeping and too assertive, given the already known and acknowledged limitations of both their data and the applied analyses.So what is the best way to test for distinctness of coastal California Gnatcatchers? Below, we provide recommendations for best practices in this case and in future cases in which the distinctness of potentially threatened or endangered populations is in question.Discrete phenotypic differences were the original basis for listing the coastal California Gnatcatchers under the ESA (USFWS 1993). &ldquo;Discrete&rdquo; means that differences must not vary smoothly from one population to another, but instead must show a discontinuity (i.e. step cline) in their character values. Over the years, many studies on the California Gnatcatcher have delimited changes in phenotypic characters consistent with discrete variation, affirming the distinctness of <italic>P. c. californica</italic> from subspecies to the south (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Grinnell1">Grinnell 1926</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-VanRossem1">Van Rossem 1931</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Phillips1">Phillips 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood 1991</xref>). There is evidence for phenotypic discontinuities at even finer scales. Using phenotypic traits, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea (1994)</xref> described a new subspecies from within the <italic>californica</italic> subspecies. This subspecies, <italic>P. c. atwoodi</italic>, shows discrete differences in the brightness of the white on the breast feathers, among other traits, and on this phenotypic basis it is recognized by authoritative taxonomic references (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Dickinson1">Dickinson et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-delHoyo1">del Hoyo et al. 2006</xref>).The study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Skalski1">Skalski et al. (2008)</xref>, cited by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>, claimed to invalidate the discreteness of the variation found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood (1991)</xref>, but in reality they analyzed little of the original data. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Skalski1">Skalski et al. (2008)</xref> also made some questionable claims. For example, they claimed that by showing two trends, one relating breast-plumage brightness to latitude and another relating breast-plumage brightness to specimen age, these results &ldquo;indicate that the specimens from the more northerly latitudes were collected earlier than the specimens from more southerly latitudes&rdquo; (their <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-f02">fig. 2</xref>). That is certainly one hypothesis. Another possibility is that breast brightness varies with latitude <italic>in addition to age</italic>. These hypotheses can be disentangled by restricting analysis to specimens of similar collection year, which is exactly what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea (1994)</xref> did in their determination that variation was discrete among northern subspecies, including <italic>P. c. californica</italic>.The fact remains that, despite all the previous work, the California Gnatcatcher has never been the subject of a comprehensive phenotypic analysis, using modern methods and all available specimens and controlling for potential sources of error like specimen age. In some ways, the methodology for collecting phenotypic data has not changed dramatically in the past 50 years. Researchers still commonly use analog calipers to measure morphological features like the length of the bill or wing. Two recent developments, however, have improved our ability to assess differences in birds, neither of which has yet been applied rigorously to the question of the California Gnatcatchers.First, plumage reflectance analysis, using a modern spectrophotometer that can measure light over the full range of avian vision, can detect subtle physical distinctions among populations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Maley1">Maley and Winker 2007</xref>) and test whether the birds themselves are able to notice these differences perceptually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Vorobyev1">Vorobyev et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Maia1">Maia et al. 2013</xref>). Second, multivariate statistics like principal component analysis can often reveal phenotypic variation that would otherwise be overlooked in univariate tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mila1">Mil&aacute; et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Aleixandre1">Aleixandre et al. 2013</xref>). Although the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood (1991)</xref> used precursors of these methods, equipment and analyses have undergone considerable development in the past 20 years. A comprehensive analysis that joins morphological and plumage reflectance data in a multivariate analysis, and which tests for the discreteness of variation against a null hypothesis of smooth clinal change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>), is the minimum effort required to confirm or refute the phenotypic distinctness of the coastal California Gnatcatchers.Methods for genetic analyses have gone through a revolution in the past 10 years with the advent of next-generation sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Lerner1">Lerner and Fleischer 2010</xref>). To assess differentiation in the California Gnatcatchers (and other, similar cases), densely sampled SNPs are ideal, like those employed in the Wilson's Warbler study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Ruegg1">Ruegg et al. (2014)</xref> or in other studies that used even higher numbers of SNPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Harvey1">Harvey and Brumfield 2014</xref>). The technique used to generate these SNPs falls under a broad category of methods called &ldquo;genotyping by sequencing&rdquo; (GBS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Baird1">Baird et al. 2008</xref>), which can provide thousands of SNPs with the power to resolve difficult taxonomic conundrums (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Wagner1">Wagner et al. 2013</xref>), to compare genomic and phenotypic signatures of divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre et al. 2014</xref>), and to uncover loci potentially linked to targets of selection, like those governing plumage color (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Parchman1">Parchman et al. 2013</xref>). The generation and analysis of GBS data is well developed and affordable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Davey1">Davey et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Narum1">Narum et al. 2013</xref>) and should only become more so with time.Prior niche modeling on the coastal California Gnatcatchers investigated the extent of their habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Rotenberry1">Rotenberry et al. 2006</xref>) and the potential effects of climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Preston1">Preston et al. 2008</xref>) but did not compare these habitats with those of populations in Baja California. To test whether these habitats differ, &ldquo;old-fashioned methods&rdquo; using measuring tape and sampling grids might trump high-tech solutions. There are few enough sampling points that a field survey of plant species and vegetative characteristics would not be too onerous and would stand the best chance of detecting the qualitatively described habitat differences in the coastal California Gnatcatchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Atwood2">Atwood 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Mellink1">Mellink and Rea 1994</xref>).Niche modeling would help complement these &ldquo;ground-truthed&rdquo; data and would provide a more continuous assessment of habitat, compared with the necessarily patchy coverage of any method drawing only from sampling points. Niche modeling should use environmental variables that describe both climate (e.g., rainfall and temperature data used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. &lsqb;2013&rsqb;</xref>) and the vegetation itself, like those available from remote-sensing satellites (e.g., vegetative cover, greenness, and height, which were not used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. &lsqb;2013&rsqb;</xref>). Remote-sensing data, because they describe aspects of the niche likely to vary over smaller spatial scales than climatic data, may show more promise for finding evolutionarily important differences among gnatcatcher habitats.Finally, data collection and analysis should be carried out either free of any financial conflict of interest or, at minimum, with such conflicts stated openly. A conflict of interest occurs in any situation in which the impartiality of a study <italic>might</italic> be undermined by a competing interest, often a funding source. The work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> was funded by developers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Sahagun1">Sahagun 2014</xref>), which we believe represents a conflict of interest that should have been acknowledged in their paper. The paper does not disclose that the R. Thornton thanked in the Acknowledgments for &ldquo;securing funding&rdquo; is a lawyer who has represented developers. Thornton is representing the National Association of Home Builders in the petition to delist the gnatcatcher. The presence of a financial conflict of interest does not necessarily invalidate a study or imply malfeasance. Yet many journals have decided that financial conflicts of interest should be stated openly because of the demonstrated effect of &ldquo;sponsorship bias&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Lesser1">Lesser et al. 2007</xref>). The risk of sponsorship bias is even greater with negative results, which rely more heavily on the researcher's assumptions and interpretation. Especially when it comes to threatened or endangered species, explicit funding statements provide important context for researchers, the media, and the public in assessing a study's rationale, methods, and interpretation.The manuscript benefited enormously from the advice and critical input of K. Winker, K. Garrett, M. Patten, P. Unitt, A. Zellmer, B. Mil&aacute;, and an anonymous reviewer. E. Ridley organized and sorted the GenBank data. This project was funded by an endowment to Occidental College by the late Robert T. Moore and Margaret C. Moore.Partial screen grab of an alignment of the B-FIB locus from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-380-Zink5">Zink et al. (2013)</xref>. Variable bases are marked with colored bars. Sequences are in order by population and individual, meaning that the 2 alleles for each individual are adjacent. Paralagous genes are likely because the locus has little overall variability but contains 2 highly divergent gene lineages (differing by 7 substitutions). Additionally, many individuals have 1 allele copy from each of the divergent gene lineages (as seen in the alternating pattern moving down the list of individuals).