Factors affecting seasonal movements of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse: A reconceptualized nest survival modelInformation theory and an extension of the maximum likelihood principleThe role of predator removal, density-dependence, and environmental factors on Mallard duckling survival in North DakotaDemography of female Greater Prairie-Chickens in unfragmented grasslands in KansasMovements and survival of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse in southeastern IdahoSurvival and breeding strategies of grouseEffects of sampling regime on the mean and variance of home range size estimatesAdjustment to climate change is constrained by arrival date in a long-distance migrant birdBreakup and sibling dispersal of two sage grouse broodsAnimal ecology meets GPS-based radiotelemetry: A perfect storm of opportunities and challengesEffects of climatic variation and reproductive trade-offs vary by measure of reproductive effort in Greater Sage-GrouseWinter habitat use by juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse on Parker Mountain, Utah: Implications for sagebrush managementGreater Sage-Grouse juvenile survival in UtahImpact of reproductive effort on survival of Rio Grande Wild Turkey <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Meleagris gallopavo</named-content> intermedia</italic> hens in TexasEffects of predation and hunting on adult Sage Grouse <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic> in IdahoSeasonal movements of Sage Grouse in southeastern IdahoCharacteristics and dynamics of Greater Sage-Grouse populationsMovements and radionuclide concentrations of Sage Grouse in southeastern IdahoEcology and management of sage-grouse and sage-grouse habitatAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalLate summer&ndash;spring movement of juvenile Sage GrouseA method for obtaining Sage Grouse age and sex ratios from wingsHungry grouse in a warming world: Emerging risks from plant chemical defenses and climate changeGreater Sage-Grouse population dynamics and probability of persistenceMethods for trapping Sage Grouse in ColoradoThe effects of a large-scale wind farm on breeding season survival of female Mallards and Blue-winged Teal in the Prairie Pothole RegionEffects of landscape-scale environmental variation on Greater Sage-Grouse chick survivalGreater Sage-Grouse sex ratios in Utah: Implications for reporting population trendsSources of variation in survival of breeding female Wood DucksDistinguishing technology from biology: A critical review of the use of GPS telemetry data in ecologyAnalyzing animal movements using Brownian bridgesInventory and analysis of rangeland resources of the state land block on Parker Mountain, UtahError on choroplethic maps: Definition, measurement, reductionViability and conservation of an exploited Sage Grouse populationQuantity versus quality: Programmed collection and analysis of radio-tracking dataAnalysis of animal space use and movementsFood habits of juvenile Sage GrouseTrends in snowfall versus rainfall in the western United StatesSatellite telemetry in avian research and management: Sample size considerationsThe influence of climate on the timing and rate of spring bird migrationA general discrete-time modeling framework for animal movement using multistate random walksAnalysis of radiotelemetry dataOptimizing radio retention and minimizing radio impacts in a field study of upland sandpipersBlue Grouse production, movements, and populations in the Bridger Mountains, MontanaAutocorrelation of location estimates and the analysis of radiotracking dataComparative demography of increasing and stable populations of Blue Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendragapus obscurus</named-content></italic>)Modeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SASDistribution of sage-grouse in North AmericaManaging multiple vital rates to maximize Greater Sage-Grouse population growthTranslocation to a fragmented landscape: Survival, movement, and site fidelity of Northern BobwhitesEffects of necklace radio transmitters on survival and breeding success of Red Grouse <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagopus lagopus</named-content> scoticus</italic>Proposed rule: Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; 12-month finding for petitions to list the Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) as threatened or endangeredDuration of snow cover and its influence on life-history variation in yellow-bellied marmotsSummer movements and habitat use by Sage Grouse broods in central MontanaProgram MARK: Survival rate estimation from both live and dead encountersCurrent address: Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Fairbanks, Alaska, USAEstimating the climatic and habitat factors that affect animal movement patterns (e.g., migration, dispersal, site fidelity) is informative for management and conservation. Juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) have been identified as having a significant influence on population growth, but relatively little is known about factors that influence survival, movement, and the potential interrelation between the two. Movement out of fall habitat has been suggested to influence the survival of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse. We reconceptualized the nest survival model (equating movement out of a focal area with failure of a nest) to extend its use to movement data on juveniles in south-central Utah. We found that juveniles' seasonal movements were affected by a linear trend in time (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.655, 95&percnt; confidence interval &lsqb;CI&rsqb;: &minus;1.049 to &minus;0.26) and by precipitation (&beta; &equals; &minus;3.718, 95&percnt; CI: &minus;6.687 to &minus;0.749), with an interaction between the parameters (&beta; &equals; 0.360, 95&percnt; CI: 0.002&ndash;0.718). In the absence of precipitation, the probability of movement increased weekly through time (within a year). Weekly precipitation increased the probability of movement in earlier weeks, but the effect of precipitation attenuated in later weeks (i.e. interaction parameter). The precipitation was likely non-accumulating snowfall, given the observed below-freezing temperatures. Our results suggest that changes in precipitation (mainly snowfall) that result from climate change could influence the timing and duration of seasonal movements (i.e. population-level time to complete movement) in migratory populations of Greater Sage-Grouse. Furthermore, our results demonstrate the utility of the nest survival model for evaluating the factors that affect animal movements with &ldquo;ragged&rdquo; data.Estimar los factores clim&aacute;ticos y del h&aacute;bitat que afectan los patrones animales de movimiento (e.g. migraci&oacute;n, dispersi&oacute;n, fidelidad al sitio) brinda informaci&oacute;n para el manejo y la conservaci&oacute;n de especies. Se ha determinado que las aves j&oacute;venes de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic> tienen una influencia significativa en el crecimiento poblacional, pero se sabe relativamente poco sobre los factores que afectan su supervivencia, movimientos e interacciones entre estas dos variables. Se ha sugerido que los movimientos fuera del h&aacute;bitat de oto&ntilde;o afectan la supervivencia de las aves j&oacute;venes de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>. En este trabajo volvemos a conceptualizar el modelo de supervivencia de los nidos equiparando el movimiento hacia afuera de un &aacute;rea focal con el fracaso de los nidos para extender su uso a los datos de movimiento de aves j&oacute;venes de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> en el centro-sur de Utah. Encontramos que el movimiento estacional de los j&oacute;venes en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> fue afectado por una tendencia lineal en el tiempo (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.655, 95&percnt; IC &equals; &minus;1.049 a &minus;0.26) y la precipitaci&oacute;n (&beta; &equals; &minus;3.718, 95&percnt; IC &equals; &minus;6.687 a &minus;0.749), y que exist&iacute;a una interacci&oacute;n entre los par&aacute;metros (&beta; &equals; 0.360, 95&percnt; IC &equals; 0.002&ndash;0.718). En ausencia de precipitaci&oacute;n, la probabilidad semanal de movimiento se increment&oacute; con el tiempo (en un a&ntilde;o). La precipitaci&oacute;n semanal increment&oacute; la probabilidad de movimiento en las primeras semanas, pero el efecto de la precipitaci&oacute;n se atenu&oacute; semanas m&aacute;s tarde (i.e. par&aacute;metro de interacci&oacute;n). Probablemente la precipitaci&oacute;n correspond&iacute;a a nieve que no se acumulaba debido a las temperaturas bajo el punto de congelamiento. Nuestros resultados sugieren que los cambios en precipitaci&oacute;n, principalmente de nieve, que resulten del cambio clim&aacute;tico podr&iacute;an afectar la sincronizaci&oacute;n y duraci&oacute;n (i.e. el tiempo a nivel poblacional para completar el movimiento) de los movimientos estacionales de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> en las poblaciones migratorias. Adem&aacute;s demostramos la utilidad del modelo de supervivencia de los nidos para evaluar los factores que afectan los movimientos de animales con datos imperfectos.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>, dispersi&oacute;n, juvenil, migraci&oacute;n, modelo de supervivencia de los nidos, movimiento estacional, programa MARKAnimal movements are inherently linked to population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Kernohan1">Kernohan et al. 2001</xref>), such that the energetic and survival costs associated with movement and acquisition of resources may affect individual fitness. Consequently, understanding the factors that affect the movement of individuals is useful when establishing management guidelines to conserve species. Environmental cues elicit responses by individuals or specific cohorts (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-VanVuren1">Vuren and Armitage 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Both1">Both and Visser 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Marra1">Marra et al. 2005</xref>), ostensibly to provide a survival or reproductive advantage. Oscillation in the timing of these environmental triggers, however, may influence survival and reproduction, particularly with respect to human-mediated regulation of a species (e.g., harvest). There is thus a need to elucidate behavioral responses to environmental conditions in order to inform management and conservation efforts.Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) populations have experienced long-term population declines and habitat degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Schroeder1">Schroeder et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly3">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Garton1">Garton et al. 2011</xref>), thereby becoming a species of conservation concern throughout western North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-CanadianSageGrouseRecoveryTeam1">Canadian Sage Grouse Recovery Team 2001</xref>, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2010). Climate appears to significantly influence numerous aspects of the species' biology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Guttery1">Guttery et al. 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill2">Caudill et al. 2014a</xref>). Although juveniles may be critical to population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Johnson1">Johnson and Braun 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>), the demographics (e.g., survival, predation, movement) of juveniles are poorly understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Crawford1">Crawford et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>; e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Beck1">Beck et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>). Greater Sage-Grouse populations can be classified as either migratory or nonmigratory, and fall movement of migratory populations is similar for adults and juveniles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 1988</xref>). In migratory populations, climatic variability may influence juvenile survival by affecting the timing of seasonal movements and spacing of individuals in fall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>). However, the factors that affect the timing and duration of seasonal movement are poorly documented. In juveniles, brood breakup occurs prior to fall movements to wintering areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Klebenow1">Klebenow and Gray 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Browers1">Browers and Flake 1985</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly3">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>). Studies have documented fall movements of Greater Sage-Grouse in relation to descriptive measures by relating climate to movement; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dunn1">Dunn and Braun (1986)</xref> concluded that movement was tied to snowfall, which influenced availability of sagebrush. However, in several grouse species, snowfall-stimulated fall movements occur before food availability becomes limited by snow depth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Bergerud1">Bergerud and Gratson 1988</xref>). Furthermore, studies have reported conflicting results regarding the temporal nature of migratory movements from late-summer areas to wintering areas for Greater Sage-Grouse, where movements were rapid in some instances and prolonged in others (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Wallestad1">Wallestad 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly4">Connelly and Markham 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dunn1">Dunn and Braun 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 1988</xref>). Knowledge of the timing and spatial arrangement of movement is requisite to optimizing many conservation actions. For example, management of seasonal-use areas requires accurate information on the explicit timing of movement and the variability in use both within and across seasons (e.g., function of climatic conditions).Despite the development and use of numerous methods to evaluate animal movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Horne1">Horne et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Terhune1">Terhune et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-McClintock1">McClintock et al. 2012</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Millspaugh1">Millspaugh et al. 2012</xref>), many methods are focused on intensively sampling a few individuals (e.g., &ldquo;random walk&rdquo; approaches), which may have pitfalls (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-White2">White and Garrott 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Kenward1">Kenward 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Kenward2">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Otis1">Otis and White 1999</xref>). In many instances, there is a trade-off between sample size and transmitter technology: Fewer global positioning system (GPS) units can be deployed, given their cost, compared with very-high-frequency (VHF) transmitters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Hebblewhite1">Hebblewhite and Haydon 2010</xref>). A primary advantage of more advanced transmitter technology (e.g., GPS) is the ability to record more locations per individual on a predefined schedule; nevertheless, marked individuals are the sampling unit and, consequently, larger sample size&mdash;at the expense of sampling rate per individual&mdash;could be preferable (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Borger1">B&ouml;rger et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Lindberg1">Lindberg and Walker 2007</xref>). Conversely, VHF transmitters could facilitate larger sample sizes at the cost of number and schedule of relocations when logistical constraints (e.g., field conditions, number of personnel, competing project objectives) lead to more irregular data (or &ldquo;ragged data&rdquo;). Despite the inherent need, many approaches to analysis of movement data do not lend themselves to ragged data (i.e. unequal monitoring intervals among animals and time; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>). The nest survival model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>) in Program MARK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>), however, has been extended to accept ragged radiotelemetry data for evaluation of survival; it allows the inclusion of group and individual covariates, as well as complex time structures and time-varying covariates (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Hartke1">Hartke et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Mong1">Mong and Sandercock 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Collier1">Collier et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Amundson1">Amundson and Arnold 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Augustine1">Augustine and Sandercock 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Gue1">Gue et al. 2013</xref>). Thus, we reconceptualized the widely used nest survival model to evaluate the influence of various environmental factors on the timing of seasonal movements of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse.We studied a migratory population (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 1988</xref>) of Greater Sage-Grouse on Parker Mountain in south-central Utah, at the southern extent of the species' range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Schroeder1">Schroeder et al. 2004</xref>). Winter habitats of juveniles on Parker Mountain are geographically distinct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill1">Caudill 2011</xref>). The mountain ranges in elevation from 2,200 to 3,000 m; it receives 65&ndash;80 frost-free days and 40&ndash;50 cm of precipitation annually, most of which occurs during winter as snow (60&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Jaynes1">Jaynes 1982</xref>). The vegetation was primarily black sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Artemisia nova</named-content></italic>) on ridges and mountain big sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. tridentata</named-content> vaseyana</italic>) in the swales. Quaking aspen (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus tremuloides</named-content></italic>), pinyon pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus edulis</named-content></italic>), and juniper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Juniperus</named-content></italic> spp.) occurred on the study area. Parker Mountain is predominantly publicly owned (98.6&percnt;; 947 km<sup>2</sup>).We captured juveniles using night spotlighting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Giesen1">Giesen et al. 1982</xref>) from August 1 to September 30 annually (2008&ndash;2009). We defined juveniles as young-of-the-year that were &gt;80 days old. Accordingly, individuals were captured after brood breakup (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Klebenow1">Klebenow and Gray 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Browers1">Browers and Flake 1985</xref>) and can be considered independent. We used characteristics of the first secondary flight feather to distinguish adults from juveniles and ascertained sex on the basis of primary length and molt patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Beck2">Beck et al. 1975</xref> &lsqb;adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Eng1">Eng 1955</xref>&rsqb;). We later confirmed sex through DNA analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Guttery2">Guttery et al. 2013b</xref>), and field classification was 100&percnt; accurate (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>). In cases where molt had not progressed enough to implement the methods outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Beck2">Beck et al. (1975)</xref>, we relied on DNA analysis for sex classification (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 32). We recorded the molt progression of primary feathers for all captured individuals to index juvenile age. Age was standardized by dividing molt progression by ordinal date of capture. Juveniles were fitted with suture-on backpack or necklace-style VHF transmitters (American Wildlife Enterprises, Monticello, Florida, USA). Each transmitter weighed 15 g and did not exceed 3&percnt; of the individual's body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Thirgood1">Thirgood et al. 1995</xref>). Transmitters were battery powered and equipped with mortality switches (activated after 12 hr of inactivity). Survival status was confirmed remotely using the pulse signal emitted by the transmitters. Radio frequencies were monitored from the ground daily from August 15 to December 15, but signals were not always detected. Because survival was the primary objective of field methods, locations were acquired 1&ndash;4 times mo<sup>&minus;1</sup>, a location interval similar to those used in previous studies in this species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 1988</xref>). Transmitter type appeared to affect the survival of juveniles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>) but not movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill3">Caudill et al. 2013</xref>), so we included both types in our analysis. The study protocols were approved by the Utah State University Institutional Animal Use and Care Committee (IACUCC no. 942R).Both temperature and precipitation have been hypothesized to affect Greater Sage-Grouse biology (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill3">Caudill et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Guttery1">Guttery et al. 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill2">Caudill et al. 2014a</xref>, b), and fall movements appear to be influenced by snowfall, which presumably limits the availability of sagebrush (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dunn1">Dunn and Braun 1986</xref>). However, for many grouse species, including Greater Sage-Grouse, movement occurs before snow depth limits food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Bergerud1">Bergerud and Gratson 1988</xref>). Clearly, temperature and precipitation work in tandem to influence snow conditions, and accordingly we compiled climatic variables averaged by calendar week for snow depth, minimum temperature mean (MTmean), and precipitation (snow and rain). In addition, we included weekly minimum temperature (MTM) and weekly total snow accumulation. Climatic data were downloaded from the U.S. Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service SNOTEL website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wcc.nrcs.usda.gov/snow/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.wcc.nrcs.usda.gov/snow/</ext-link>). All SNOTEL covariate data were averaged across the 2 stations in proximity that were representative of our study site, Black Flat&ndash;U.M. Creek (site no. 348; 2,884 m elevation) and Donkey Reservoir (site no. 452; 2,986 m elevation); these two SNOTEL sites are 23.66 and 9.41 km from our study area, respectively. We developed an a priori candidate model set by combining year, linear trend in time (by week within a year, T), and climatic variables in additive and interactive forms (total number of candidate models &equals; 29). Climatic variables that were correlated with time (e.g., MTM, MTmean, snow depth) were not included in models with a linear trend in time effect. Correlation between parameters, Pearson's coefficient, was assessed using the &ldquo;cor&rdquo; function in R version 3.0.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2013</xref>). We tested for the effect of juvenile age and sex in a post hoc analysis, treating both parameters as potential nuisance parameters. Sex and age were added to the best-performing (AIC<sub>c</sub>) climatic model as additive terms, and a likelihood ratio test (LRT) was performed to test parameter effects.We defined late summer&ndash;early fall habitats (i.e. premovement habitats) by elevation. We reclassified a digital elevation model (DEM, 10 m resolution; obtained from the Natural Resources Conservation Service geospatial data gateway) to 12 jenks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Jenks1">Jenks and Caspall 1971</xref> &lsqb;see also &ldquo;natural breaks&rdquo;&rsqb;). Twelve jenks represented 50 m resolution if dispersed evenly, which we consider a biologically meaningful scale for assessing movements of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse. Visual inspection of data yielded all definitive premovement locations (August) occurring in the 3 highest-elevation jenks (i.e. &plus;2,747 m elevation).We used the nest survival model in Program MARK to estimate seasonal movements out of the late summer&ndash;early fall habitats (i.e. 3 highest-elevation jenks). The nest survival model was reconceptualized such that survival equaled not moving out of fall seasonal habitat (i.e. exhibiting site fidelity; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t01">Table 1</xref>), so we estimated one-way movements (i.e. out of focal area). Individuals that died prior to moving were right censored at the last known live (apparent survival) date. Individuals were considered &ldquo;moved&rdquo; (i.e. &ldquo;dead&rdquo; in the modeling framework) when they were located outside the late summer&ndash;early fall habitats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t01">Table 1</xref>). Because we considered movement equal to &ldquo;death&rdquo; in our framework, individuals could not move out of and then back into the premovement habitat. However, we documented only 1 occurrence of this behavior, where the individual was considered to have broken site fidelity and thus was considered &ldquo;moved&rdquo; when it first left the focal area. However, the individual moved back into the focal area for only 1 wk.Example encounter histories and interpretations of a reconceptualization of the nest survival model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>) to evaluate single-direction movements.The nest survival model was initialized for our analysis such that intervals in the modeling framework equaled calendar weeks. A priori candidate models were ranked using Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Akaike1">Akaike 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Burnham2">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). Models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2 were considered equally supported by the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 1998</xref>). We used the delta method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Seber1">Seber 1982</xref>:7&ndash;9) to derive standard error estimates when weekly movement rates were combined into longer intervals. To calculate confidence intervals for estimates derived using the delta method, estimates were transformed to the logit scale then back-transformed to the probability scale to ensure that estimates were appropriately bounded at 0 and 1.We captured 91 juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse and collected 267 live locations from August 15 to December 3 of both years. Forty-four individuals were known to have moved (average number of locations per individual &equals; 4.5) prior to actual death (i.e. apparent mortality) and were observed in wintering areas. Forty-seven individuals died (apparent mortality) prior to movement and were consequently right censored when last observed alive (i.e. apparent survival). Right censoring at apparent mortality date allowed us to glean inference and sample size from individuals that died prior to movement. Mortality locations were removed from analysis because predators may have moved carcasses, which could lead to misclassification of location within the context of seasonal movement.There was a single most-supported model, seasonal movement ~ precipitation&ast;time; no other models were considered competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t02">Table 2</xref>). The top model contained a linear trend though time (T) with a negative slope (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t03">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The top model also contained an additive effect of precipitation and an interaction between precipitation and time, which had negative and positive slopes, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t03">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Probability of not moving decreased through time in the absence of precipitation, and precipitation increased the probability of movement early in the season (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). However, given the interaction between time and precipitation, the effect of precipitation changed over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). As a result of the interaction, late precipitation could negatively affect the probability of movement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). However, very few individuals remained in premovement areas late in time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f02">Figure 2</xref>), so the effect of late precipitation could be an artifact of the interaction. Combined period-specific probabilities of movement demonstrate that fall movement occurred over the course of several weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Our post hoc LRT analysis revealed that neither sex (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 1.04, df &equals; 1, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.31) nor juvenile age (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.682, df &equals; 1, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.41) appeared to affect movement.Models evaluated in Program MARK to estimate fall seasonal movement of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse on Parker Mountain, Utah, USA, 2008&ndash;2009. Models are listed with their differences in AIC<sub>c</sub> (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>), AIC<sub>c</sub> weight (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), model likelihood (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>/<italic>w</italic><sub>best model</sub>), number of parameters (<italic>k</italic>), and deviance.Beta estimates (logit scale) for the best-supported model (seasonal movement ~ precipitation &times; linear trend in time) of fall movements of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse on Parker Mountain, Utah, USA, 2008&ndash;2009.Predicted probability of seasonal movement in juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse on Parker Mountain, Utah, USA, 2008&ndash;2009, based on the best-supported model (movement ~ precipitation &times; linear trend in time). Early in the season, precipitation drives movement (a); the influence of precipitation on movement dissipates through time (b); and movement likelihood increases with time (c).Derived cumulative probability (<italic>p</italic>) of site fidelity in relation to precipitation for juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse during the population's fall seasonal movements on Parker Mountain, Utah, USA, 2008&ndash;2009.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dunn1">Dunn and Braun (1986)</xref> reported that movements of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse were associated with snowfall where snow limited the availability of sagebrush. We found little evidence that either snow depth or snow accumulation influenced the probability of seasonal movement on Parker Mountain, though snow accumulation provided limited explanatory value in multimodel inference (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t02">Table 2</xref>). Our results indicate that precipitation was the main climatic driver of seasonal movements among juveniles during fall; but, given the observed temperatures, many of the precipitation events were likely snow that was not accumulating. Consequently, our results appear to support the notion that snowfall cues fall movements, but not necessarily because food has become limited (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Bergerud1">Bergerud and Gratson 1988</xref>). Similar to the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. (1988)</xref>, movements from late summer&ndash;early fall habitats occurred over a period of several weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f02">Figure 2</xref>), which is further evidenced by the overwhelming support for the linear time trend (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t02">Table 2</xref>). Early-season precipitation increased the probability of movement, whereas the interaction between precipitation and time suggested attenuation of the effect of precipitation through time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Greater Sage-Grouse harvest paradigms are linked to movements from fall to winter habitats, and our results provide insight where little information previously existed (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly4">Connelly and Markham 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Dunn1">Dunn and Braun 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 1988</xref>). Variation in altitudinal migration or seasonal movements likely affect harvest rates in blue grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendragapus</named-content></italic> spp.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Mussehl1">Mussehl 1960</xref>) and Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>), where hunters and predators may be keying on flocks of successful hen and juvenile Blue Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Bendell1">Bendell and Elliott 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Redfield1">Redfield 1975</xref>) and Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Wik1">Wik 2002</xref>) in late fall. Our results demonstrate that movements from late fall habitat can be variable and, consequently, that the effect of harvest may vary with the timing of harvest in relation to seasonal movements. Moreover, our results and statistical approach could be used to build predictive fall movement models that allow managers to time the harvest in relation to fall movements and better regulate harvest composition (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Mussehl1">Mussehl 1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Bendell1">Bendell and Elliott 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Redfield1">Redfield 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill2">Caudill et al. 2014a</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. (2014b)</xref> suggested that the survival of juvenile Greater Sage-Grouse was tied to the timing and magnitude of climatic events through fall movements and hypothesized that the effect could be a result of transition from fall (high mortality) to winter (high survival) strategies. Our results corroborate this notion, in that our derived cumulative estimate of movement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-f02">Figure 2</xref>) accelerates within days (3 in 2008; 2 in 2009) of the lowest juvenile survival rates of Greater Sage-Grouse reported in a concurrent study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill4">Caudill et al. 2014b</xref>). Delayed onset of winter environmental conditions associated with climate change (e.g., snowfall; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Knowles1">Knowles et al. 2006</xref>) may pose a threat to Greater Sage-Grouse conservation if seasonal movement patterns are altered such that movement to wintering areas is delayed. Our results corroborate previous findings that climate change may negatively affect Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Guttery1">Guttery et al. 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Caudill2">Caudill et al. 2014a</xref>) and grouse in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Forbey1">Forbey et al. 2013</xref>), underscoring the importance of evaluating spatial and temporal factors that influence seasonal movements.Estimating individual behavior (e.g., migration, dispersal, site fidelity) in relation to extrinsic factors (e.g., climate, habitat fragmentation) is useful for understanding the impacts of, and biological response to, changing habitat conditions and therefore aids in optimizing conservation actions. However, in some instances, evaluating the factors that affect movement will likely necessitate the use of data from studies in which movement was of interest in the initial design but was not the primary objective of the field methods. Moreover, estimating long-term trends in the effects of extrinsic factors (e.g., climatic variation, habitat fragmentation) on movement will likely require concatenation of several datasets with varying primary objectives, data discrepancies, and technologies employed (e.g., VHF vs. GPS transmitters). For instance, there is a trade-off between sample size and transmitter technology in many studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Hebblewhite1">Hebblewhite and Haydon 2010</xref>), and although technological costs will undoubtedly decrease (i.e. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Cagnacci1">Cagnacci et al. 2010</xref>) and lessen the trade-off, long-term movement analysis will require flexible approaches accommodating multiple data types where sampling discrepancies arise as a result of the technology employed. In these instances, having model flexibility to incorporate ragged data while retaining a robust statistical framework will be necessary to attain valid biological inference. The flexibility of the nest survival model allowed us to evaluate seasonal movements of Greater Sage-Grouse out of a focal area (site fidelity) and incorporate critical parameters of interest (e.g., time varying covariates) while accounting for ragged telemetry data. Accordingly, we were able to elucidate seasonal movements of Greater Sage-Grouse to better understand how climatic conditions influence demographics in, and management for, a species of conservation concern. Although we used geographic states to assess movement, one could incorporate distance (e.g., from last location, capture location) into this approach to parameterize fidelity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-t01">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, our approach could be extended to include other movement parameters, including onset and duration of migration, seasonal site fidelity of individuals to natal sites or groups, and onset and duration of breeding behaviors. We assumed that sampled individuals were independent, and thus a core assumption would be violated in cases with dependence among samples. However, our approach could be modified to include random effects (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>) to account for intra-group correlation. Finally, while we assumed that movements of interest were in a single direction, another method should be considered when multidirectional movements are of interest (e.g., multistate models; <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-1-139-Terhune1">Terhune et al. 2010</xref>).We thank G. Caudill, J. Tarwater, and A. Wiley for invaluable support in the field; A. Taft and J. Lamb for sharing their extensive knowledge of the local areas; M. R. Guttery for help with trapping; and D. Adler, D. Murdoch, and others for the creation of the rgl library in R, which vastly aids the depiction of models with interactive effects. Comments from J. Rodgers, G. Caudill, M. R. Guttery, and three anonymous reviewers significantly improved the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Utah State University Quinney Fellowship, College of Natural Resources, Jessie and S.J. Quinney Foundations, Quinney Professorship for Wildlife Conflict Management, Jack H. Berryman Institute for Wildlife Damage, UDWR, and Utah State University Extension provided financial and logistical project support.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> The study protocols were approved by the Utah State University Institutional Animal Use and Care Committee (IACUCC no. 942R).<bold>Author contributions:</bold> D.C., T.T., and T.M. conceived the idea and design. D.C., T.T., and B.B. collected the data. D.C., T.T., and T.M. wrote the paper. D.C. and T.T. designed the methods. D.C., T.T., and B.B. analyzed the data. T.M. contributed substantial materials and funding.