Structure of avian assemblages in grasslands associated with cattle ranching and soybean agriculture in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion of Brazil and UruguayConservation of grassland birds in North America: Understanding ecological processes in different regionsAvian assemblages in altered and natural grasslands in the Northern Campos of UruguayEcology and conservation of grassland birds in southeastern South America: A reviewLand-use and land cover dynamics in South American temperate grasslandsCap&iacute;tulo AvesProperties of land mosaics: Implications for nature conservation in agricultural environmentsCambios en la fauna pampeanaImpactos de la actividad agropecuaria sobre la biodiversidad en la Ecorregi&oacute;n PampeanaImpactos de la transformaci&oacute;n agropecuaria sobre la biodiversidad en la provincia de Buenos AiresIUCN Red List for BirdsPasture area and landscape heterogeneity are key determinants of bird diversity in intensively managed farmlandChanges in the abundance of farmland birds in relation to the timing of agricultural intensification in England and WalesAsociaciones entre diferentes patrones de uso de la tierra y ensambles de aves en agroecosistemas de la regi&oacute;n pampeana, ArgentinaAgricultural land-use, avian nesting and rarity in the Pampas of central ArgentinaLandbird assemblages in different agricultural landscapes: A case study in the Pampas of central ArgentinaEstimating terrestrial biodiversity through extrapolationAvian response to landscape change in fragmented southern Great Plains grasslandsCobertura vegetal atual do Rio Grande do SulLivestock as ecosystem engineers for grassland bird habitat in the western great plains of North AmericaConserva&ccedil;&atilde;o das aves e da biodiversidade no bioma Pampa aliada a sistemas de produ&ccedil;&atilde;o animalPatterns of bird abundance along the agricultural gradient of the Pampean regionGrassland bird densities in seral stages of mixed-grass prairieEcological dynamics and agricultural landscapesEffects of habitat fragmentation on grassland bird communities in a private farmland in Pampa biomeThe effects of habitat fragmentation on Midwestern grassland bird communitiesEffects of landscape complexity on farmland birds in the Baltic StatesAvian assemblages in eucalypt forests, plantations and pastures in northern NSW, AustraliaPost-fire vegetation change and bird use of a salt marsh in coastal ArgentinaIUCN Red List of Threatened Species, version 2013.2Area requirements of grassland birds: A regional perspectiveSpecies richness of migratory birds is influenced by global climate changeConservaci&oacute;n de praderas en el conosur: Valoraci&oacute;n de las &aacute;reas protegidas existentesReviving common standards in point-count surveys for broad inference across studiesEffects of agriculture expansion and intensification on the vertebrate and invertebrate diversity in the Pampas of Argentinavegan: Community Ecology Package. R package version 2.0&ndash;5Soybean growth and developmentReconciling food production and biodiversity conservation: Land sharing and land sparing comparedManaging and monitoring birds using point counts: Standards and applicationsCountryside biogeography of moths in a fragmented landscape: Biodiversity in native and agricultural habitatsDoes no-till soybean farming provide any benefits for birds?Effects of habitat area on the distribution of grassland birds in MaineRolling Pampas agroecosystem: Which landscape attributes are relevant for determining bird distributions?Patterns of area sensitivity in grassland-nesting birdsThese authors contributed equally to the paper.Conversion of grasslands into crops is a major factor leading to the decline of grassland birds. Cattle ranching represents another disturbance to natural grasslands, but may be less detrimental to grassland birds. We studied the diversity, density, and composition of bird species in Brazilian and Uruguayan grasslands under two different land use types: cattle ranching on seminatural grasslands, and soybean fields with interspersed patches of grassland. Cattle sites had higher species richness (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 75 species) than soybean sites (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 57 species). Most birds showed higher densities in cattle sites, but some common and habitat-generalist species were more abundant in soybean sites. Species composition did not differ significantly with land use. The generalist Eared Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida auriculata</named-content></italic>), however, was strongly associated with soybean sites. Among species of conservation interest, either regionally or globally, all had higher densities in cattle sites, highlighting the importance of maintaining these ranching areas. The persistence of grassland birds in soybean fields may be related to the presence of seminatural grassland patches within soybean crops.A convers&atilde;o dos campos naturais em cultivos agr&iacute;colas &eacute; um dos principais fatores que causam decl&iacute;nio de aves campestres. &Aacute;reas de pecu&aacute;ria tamb&eacute;m apresentam dist&uacute;rbio, no entanto s&atilde;o aparentemente menos impactantes quando comparadas &agrave; agricultura. Nesse estudo avaliamos poss&iacute;veis diferen&ccedil;as na diversidade, densidade e composi&ccedil;&atilde;o de aves entre &aacute;reas sob dois diferentes usos do solo (pecu&aacute;ria em campos semi-naturais e planta&ccedil;&atilde;o de soja com manchas de campo). Utilizamos o m&eacute;todo de pontos de contagem para amostrar as aves. As &aacute;reas de pecu&aacute;ria apresentaram maior riqueza de esp&eacute;cies (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 75) do que as &aacute;reas de soja (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 57). A maior parte das esp&eacute;cies apresentou maior densidade nas &aacute;reas de pecu&aacute;ria. Quanto &agrave; composi&ccedil;&atilde;o das esp&eacute;cies, n&atilde;o houve uma separa&ccedil;&atilde;o evidente entre os dois tipos de uso, no entanto, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida auriculata</named-content></italic>, uma esp&eacute;cie generalista, apareceu fortemente associada aos cultivos de soja. Registramos cinco esp&eacute;cies regional ou globalmente amea&ccedil;adas ou quase amea&ccedil;adas, todas com maior densidade em &aacute;reas de pecu&aacute;ria, destacando a import&acirc;ncia da preserva&ccedil;&atilde;o destes campos. O desenvolvimento de pr&aacute;ticas e pol&iacute;ticas de manejo que tornem a produ&ccedil;&atilde;o agr&iacute;cola e pecu&aacute;ria menos prejudiciais &agrave; biodiversidade s&atilde;o essenciais, uma vez que a manuten&ccedil;&atilde;o das aves campestres em campos com soja est&aacute; relacionada &agrave; exist&ecirc;ncia de manchas de campos semi-naturais entre os cultivos.<italic>Palavras-chave:</italic> riqueza de esp&eacute;cies, densidade de aves, composi&ccedil;&atilde;o, manchas de campo, conserva&ccedil;&atilde;oAgricultural intensification is considered one of the major causes of population declines of grassland birds worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Chamberlain1">Chamberlain et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Askins1">Askins et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz3">Azpiroz et al. 2012b</xref>). Agricultural areas support less diverse bird communities than native grasslands, and tend to support generalist species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Herzon1">Herzon and O'Hara 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Codesido3">Codesido et al. 2013</xref>). Species respond differently to habitat changes, according to characteristics such as life history and plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Filloy1">Filloy and Bellocq 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Lemoine1">Lemoine et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Codesido2">Codesido et al. 2012</xref>).Agriculture brings a number of changes that affect virtually all aspects and processes of ecosystems, reducing the area of original habitats and transforming landscapes, which can result in few isolated fragments of natural habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Gilpin1">Gilpin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Baldi1">Baldi and Paruelo 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bilenca1">Bilenca et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bilenca3">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Medan1">Medan et al. 2011</xref>). Conversion of grasslands into crops negatively affects biodiversity, through mechanization and use of herbicides and fertilizers, but livestock production on grasslands also has negative effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Filloy1">Filloy and Bellocq 2007</xref>). However, management practices that increase vegetation heterogeneity in structure or composition tend to be positive for grassland birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Derner1">Derner et al. 2009</xref>). Similarly, the amount of fallow area on a site and the presence of other seminatural habitats can also be positive for grassland birds.The significant number of threatened grassland birds (50 species in Brazil and 24 in Uruguay) and the low representation of temperate grasslands in protected areas (2.2&percnt; in Brazil and 1.7&percnt; in Uruguay) underline the necessity of developing strategies to combine agricultural activities with conservation to maintain the biodiversity of the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion (MMA 2007, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Develey1">Develey et al. 2008</xref>). Land use in this ecoregion has been changing, with grasslands replaced by crops, particularly soy (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Glycine max</named-content></italic>) and corn (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zea mays</named-content></italic>), during the Austral spring and summer, and exotic pastures (oats &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Avena sativa</named-content></italic>&rsqb; and ryegrass &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lolium multiflorum</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) during the Austral fall and winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Gressler1">Gressler 2008</xref>). Planted pastures increased by 32&percnt; between 1980 and 1990 in Uruguay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Martino1">Martino 2004</xref>). Moreover, almost 16&percnt; of the original vegetation of Rio Grande do Sul State, Brazil, was replaced from 1976 to 2002, mostly through the introduction of exotic species for forage (i.e. ryegrass, lovegrass &lsqb;<italic>Eragrostis plana</italic>&rsqb;, and other species), agricultural activity, mainly soybean and rice, and forestry (i.e. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Eucalyptus</named-content></italic> spp. and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus</named-content></italic> spp.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Martino1">Martino 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-MMAMinisteriodoMeioAmbiente1">MMA 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Develey1">Develey et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Cordeiro1">Cordeiro and Hasenack 2009</xref>). In addition, areas of seminatural grassland without any sort of production, or that are managed under low densities of livestock, are almost nonexistent in the region. In this ecoregion, grassland patches remaining within soybean fields are typically unsuitable for agriculture because of topography, soil type, or moisture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Isacch1">Isacch et al. 2004</xref>). Most soybean fields in the region include patches of seminatural grassland, varying in size, quantity, and shape.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz1">Azpiroz and Blake (2009)</xref> considered the value of barley (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hordeum vulgare</named-content></italic>) and sunflower (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Helianthus annuus</named-content></italic>) fields, pasturelands, and native grasslands for grassland birds. Their results highlighted the importance of natural grasslands for specialist species. Here, we extend their study by including grasslands in Brazil and by including soybean fields containing grassland patches. Soybean agriculture is especially important to consider, as soybeans are currently the main crop causing habitat loss in the temperate grasslands of southern Brazil and Uruguay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Oyhantcabal1">Oyhant&ccedil;abal and Narbondo 2011</xref>).Our goal was to determine differences in bird species richness, density, and community composition in areas under two types of land use: (1) cattle ranching on seminatural grasslands (hereafter referred to as cattle sites), and (2) soybean fields with scattered patches of grassland (soybean sites). We hypothesized that both species richness and species density would be greater in cattle sites. To emphasize birds of conservation concern, we also analyzed the responses of birds classified as near-threatened and threatened, regionally and globally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz2">Azpiroz et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-IUCN1">IUCN 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-DOEDiarioOficialdoEstadodoRioGrandedoSul1">DOE 2014</xref>).We worked in eight 300-ha sites in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion divided into two land use types, cattle sites (C) and soybean sites (S; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Cattle sites (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4) were dominated by seminatural grassland (cattle stocking rate ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>: C1 &equals; 0.96; C2 &equals; 0.57; C3 &equals; 0.89; C4 &equals; 0.75) and were located in Brazil&mdash;in Dom Pedrito county (C1: 30&deg;58&prime;58&prime;&prime;S, 54&deg;20&prime;12&prime;&prime;W) in the state of Rio Grande do Sul&mdash;and in Uruguay: Rivera (C2: 30&deg;58&prime;19&prime;&prime;S, 55&deg;26&prime;40&prime;&prime;W), Vichadero (C3: 31&deg;40&prime;04&prime;&prime;S, 54&deg;31&prime;30&prime;&prime;W), and Melo (C4: 32&deg;21&prime;03&prime;&prime;S, 53&deg;58&prime;54&prime;&prime;W). Soybean sites (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4) had 8&ndash;17&percnt; coverage of seminatural grasslands, but were dominated by soybean fields during the Austral summer, and either wheat (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Triticum vulgare</named-content></italic>; in Uruguay) or ryegrass (in Brazil) during the Austral winter. The locations of soybean sites and percentage of grassland were as follows: Dom Pedrito county (S1: 31&deg;04&prime;25&prime;&prime;S, 54&deg;20&prime;33&prime;&prime;W; 90&percnt; soy and 10&percnt; grassland) and Santana do Livramento county (S2: 30&deg;56&prime;39&prime;&prime;S, 55&deg;24&prime;45&prime;&prime;W; 92&percnt; soy and 8&percnt; grassland), both in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil; and Vichadero (S3: 31&deg;40&prime;23&prime;&prime;S, 54&deg;33&prime;09&prime;&prime;W; 83&percnt; soy and 17&percnt; grassland) and Melo (S4: 32&deg;13&prime;29&prime;&prime;S, 54&deg;34&prime;01&prime;&prime;W; 89&percnt; soy and 11&percnt; grassland) in Uruguay.Bird species surveys in 2010&ndash;2012 in 8 sites in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion in Brazil and Uruguay: 4 cattle sites (cattle ranching on seminatural grasslands; circles) and 4 soybean sites (soybean fields with scattered patches of grassland; squares).We chose our study sites based on similar climatic characteristics, type of soil (deep soils), and topography, which ranged from 100 to 400 m asl with undulating features (called <italic>coxilhas</italic>) among flat areas, so that any differences in species composition would not be related to differences in these characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Hasenack1">Hasenack et al. 2010</xref>). We assumed that dominant plant species in grassland patches within soybean fields were the same as those found on cattle sites. Soybean sites had also been used for cattle ranching until the recent introduction of soybeans; the sites we surveyed were in the second and third year of crop plantations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Oyhantcabal1">Oyhant&ccedil;abal and Narbondo 2011</xref>). Cattle sites were mainly composed by the following species: <italic>Andropogon selloanus</italic>, <italic>Axonopus affinis</italic>, <italic>Dichantelium sabulorum</italic>, <italic>Eragrostis neesii</italic>, <italic>Mnesithea selloana</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pennisetum clandestinum</named-content></italic>, <italic>Sporobolus indicus</italic>, <italic>Stipa setigera</italic>, <italic>Aspilia montevidensis</italic>, <italic>Chaptalia piloselloides</italic>, <italic>Chevreulia sarmentosa</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Conyza bonariensis</named-content></italic>, <italic>Facelis retusa</italic>, <italic>Gamochaeta americana</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Baccharis</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Paspalum</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Piptochaetium</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setaria</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hypochaeris</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lucilia</named-content></italic> spp., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Senecio</named-content></italic> spp., and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Soliva</named-content></italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Dotta1">Dotta 2013</xref>, V. Gomes personal communication). All soybean fields had the same type of management, with no-till of genetically modified seeds and use of glyphosate. The sowing period was in October&ndash;November, with a few later-maturing varieties being planted in December, and harvesting began in late March to April (T. W. da Silva and G. Dotta personal observation). Our surveys were carried out across all the main growth stages (i.e. recently sown, emergent, in full flower, in full pod, in full seed, and at full maturity; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Pedersen1">Pedersen et al. 2007</xref>).We surveyed each of the 8 sites during the Austral spring&ndash;summer, once in 2010&ndash;2011 and once in 2011&ndash;2012. We distributed 20 points systematically in each site, at least 100 m from the field edge to avoid edge effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Ricketts1">Ricketts et al. 2001</xref>); points were circular plots of unlimited radius, separated from each other by 300 m. Birds counted in soybean sites could be either in soybeans per se or in the patches of seminatural grasslands within the soybean fields. All 20 points were sampled in each of the 2 survey periods. We surveyed birds with 5-min point counts, excluding flyovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Ralph1">Ralph et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bibby1">Bibby et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Matsuoka1">Matsuoka et al. 2014</xref>). Surveys started at 06:00 and lasted &sim;4 hr. We only carried out surveys on days without wind and/or rain. Distances from the observer to birds were measured with a rangefinder. T. W. da Silva and G. Dotta carried out all surveys. We followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Remsen1">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref> for taxonomy.We used ANOVA to test for treatment effects on species richness recorded in all point counts combined in each plot after testing for homoscedasticity with a Levene's test, for all species found and for grassland species only. We estimated species richness for each treatment for all plots combined based on the Chao 1 estimator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Colwell2">Colwell and Coddington 1994</xref>), with 100 randomizations, using EstimateS 8.2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Colwell1">Colwell 2009</xref>). We also used Chao 1 to estimate numbers of grassland species for each treatment. All statistical analyses were performed using R 2.15.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>) package &lsquo;car' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Fox1">Fox and Weisberg 2011</xref>).We estimated the density of individual species in each treatment using the MCDS (Multiple Covariates Distance Sampling) engine in Distance 6.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Thomas1">Thomas et al. 2009</xref>). Aquatic birds, raptors, and swallows were excluded from the density analyses. Species with &gt;30 observations were analyzed individually (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Fritcher1">Fritcher et al. 2004</xref>). For these species we poststratified analysis by sample, in order to obtain species density in each site. Other species were assigned into 5 groups using characteristics of habitat and conspicuousness, in order to achieve the minimum number of observations required to produce a reliable detection function with Distance (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Buckland1">Buckland et al. 2001</xref>:302, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz1">Azpiroz and Blake 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Phalan1">Phalan et al. 2011</xref>). For species analyzed as a group, we used the group detection probability function and poststratified the model by species to obtain each species' density in each site. We truncated the 10&percnt; of the data with the longest distances within each species individually and within each group to avoid double-counting of the same individual, as recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Buckland1">Buckland et al. (2001)</xref>. We compared the following models for each species and group: half-normal and hazard-rate key functions with cosine, simple polynomial, and hermite polynomial series expansion adjustments. We chose the final model based on the Kolmogorov-Smirnov probability test for goodness-of-fit and on Cram&eacute;r&ndash;von Mises uniform and cosine probability tests for plausibility, and then compared model AIC (Akaike's Information Criterion) values to select the model with the lowest value. Density estimates are presented with 95&percnt; confidence intervals; species with nonoverlapping intervals are considered to have different densities between land use types.Using Nonmetric Multidimensional Scaling (NMDS) with the Bray-Curtis index, we plotted the 8 sites in a multidimensional space defined by the total number of individuals of each bird species to graphically represent associations among sites. For this analysis we used package &lsquo;vegan' in R 2.15.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Oksanen1">Oksanen et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>). Aquatic birds, raptors, and swallows were again excluded from these analyses.We recorded 2,998 individuals from 32 families and 87 species (Appendix): 1,453 individuals from 75 species in the seminatural grassland cattle sites, and 1,564 individuals from 57 species in the soybean sites. Among these species, 38 species that were detected in the cattle sites and 30 species detected in the soybean sites are considered representative of southeastern South American grasslands (&lsquo;grassland species' hereafter; indicated in the Appendix based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz3">Azpiroz et al. 2012b</xref>). Based on raw point count records from each plot, cattle sites had higher species richness than soybean sites for all species (ANOVA, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 14.3, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003) and for just grassland species (ANOVA, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 17.9, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.07). Chao 1 curves for all sites combined within each treatment did not reach a plateau for all species or for just grassland species, especially for cattle sites, indicating that more species would be found with more effort (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Despite some overlap in 95&percnt; CI, the cattle sites showed higher estimated species richness for all species (cattle: Chao 1 estimate &equals; 93 species, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 80&ndash;140; soybean: Chao 1 estimate &equals; 69 species, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 60&ndash;105) and for just grassland species (cattle: Chao 1 estimate &equals; 51 species, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 40&ndash;132; soybean: Chao 1 estimate &equals; 32 species, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 30&ndash;43).Sample-based bird species accumulation curves in 8 sites in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion in Brazil and Uruguay in 2010&ndash;2012 from Chao 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Colwell2">Colwell and Coddington 1994</xref>) estimates (mean &plusmn; 95&percnt; CI) for each treatment (cattle sites &equals; solid line, soybean sites &equals; dashed line) for all sites combined within each treatment: (<bold>A</bold>) All species, (<bold>B</bold>) Grassland species only.Among the 56 species for which we analyzed density, most showed higher densities in cattle sites, but only 6 species had nonoverlapping 95&percnt; confidence intervals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-t01">Table 1</xref>): Eared Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida auriculata</named-content></italic>), Rufous Hornero (<italic>Furnarius rufus</italic>), Firewood-gatherer (<italic>Anumbius annumbi</italic>), Great Kiskadee (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pitangus sulphuratus</named-content></italic>), Grassland Yellow-Finch (<italic>Sicalis luteola</italic>), and Rufous-collared Sparrow (<italic>Zonotrichia capensis</italic>). Eared Doves had higher densities in soybean sites, and the other 5 species had higher densities in cattle sites.Density of birds in 2010&ndash;2012 in 8 sites in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion in Brazil and Uruguay based on Distance sampling (individuals ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>; D), and 95&percnt; confidence intervals, at sites with cattle ranching on seminatural grasslands (cattle sites; C) and soybean with grassland patches (soybean sites; S). Nonoverlapping confidence intervals between treatments are in bold.The NMDS did not show a clear separation between the two land use types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Although cattle sites were more tightly clustered than soybean sites, two soybean sites fell within that cluster. The Eared Dove was strongly associated with the other two soybean sites, which were highly distinct on NMDS axis 2.Nonmetric Multidimensional Scaling (NMDS) based on the abundance of bird species of 8 sites in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion in Brazil and Uruguay in 2010&ndash;2012 in the two types of land use: 4 cattle sites (circles, C1&ndash;C4) and 4 soybean fields with grassland patches (squares, S1&ndash;S4), using the Bray-Curtis similarity index. Species abbreviations are in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-t01">Table 1</xref>.Among the species classified in any of the categories of threat or as near-threatened, either regionally or globally, we recorded 5 species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-t02">Table 2</xref>): Greater Rhea (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rhea americana</named-content></italic>), Burrowing Owl (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content></italic>), Black-and-white Monjita (<italic>Xolmis dominicanus</italic>), Sedge Wren (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cistothorus platensis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-f04">Figure 4</xref>), and Saffron-cowled Blackbird (<italic>Xanthopsar flavus</italic>). The first 3 species were recorded in both soybean and cattle sites. The Sedge Wren and Saffron-cowled Blackbird were recorded only in cattle sites.Number of records and replicates of species of conservation concern in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion in Brazil and Uruguay in 2010&ndash;2012 in cattle sites (C) and soybean sites (S) where threatened species were observed.Sedge Wren (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cistothorus platensis</named-content></italic>). Photo credit: G. Dotta.Our results showed that the two land use types did not differ in bird species composition or individual species densities for most species. Nevertheless, cattle sites had higher species richness than soybean sites, and also supported more species considered representative of southeastern South American grasslands. Moreover, some threatened species were found only in cattle sites, highlighting the greater value of this land use for bird conservation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Codesido1">Codesido et al. (2008)</xref> found the same pattern for species richness when comparing seminatural grasslands under cattle ranching and crop fields (several crops) in Argentina. The high number of species (57) that we found in soybean fields, including some grassland specialists, is possibly associated with the grassland patches within the soy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Coppedge1">Coppedge et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bennett1">Bennett et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Cerezo1">Cerezo et al. 2011</xref>). These patches might increase the heterogeneity of vegetation at the landscape level, supplying areas for foraging that favor the occurrence and abundance of grassland specialists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Herkert1">Herkert 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Vickery1">Vickery et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Winter1">Winter and Faaborg 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Johnson1">Johnson and Igl 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Cerezo1">Cerezo et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, the Black-and-white Monjita and Saffron-cowled Blackbird, which are species of conservation concern, have been reported in crop fields, including soy, albeit not frequently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz3">Azpiroz et al. 2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-BirdLifeInternational1">BirdLife International 2014</xref>, C. S. Fontana personal observation).To our knowledge there are no published studies of birds in soybean monoculture in South American grasslands, and it would be useful to examine birds' responses without the presence of interspersed patches of natural habitat. Further, it will be important to understand how grassland patches within row crops change over time in suitability for birds. A relatively high number of bird species can be recorded in crop fields, provided the management processes, from planting to harvest, generate some differences in vegetation structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz1">Azpiroz and Blake 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-VanBeek1">VanBeek et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Weyland1">Weyland et al. 2014</xref>). Nevertheless, many bird species are likely to disappear as crops replace natural habitats and as land use switches from a species-rich grassland ecosystem to a simpler system, such as soybean monoculture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Blum1">Blum et al. 2008</xref>).Agricultural intensification leads to homogeneous landscapes. As such, monocultures affect birds through reducing areas for nesting, food supply, and cover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Filloy1">Filloy and Bellocq 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Codesido1">Codesido et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bilenca2">Bilenca et al. 2009</xref>). Our results on species composition are comparable to those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Filloy1">Filloy and Bellocq (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Codesido1">Codesido et al. (2008)</xref>, suggesting that replacing seminatural grasslands with crops is more harmful to grassland birds than cattle ranching activities, at least at the vegetation and stocking densities that we sampled. In the grasslands of southern Brazil and Uruguay the matrix is still predominantly composed of seminatural habitat (i.e. grasslands), and although we have not examined the effects of the matrix on bird species composition, the matrix is likely to exert some influence. Moreover, bird communities are likely to be more homogeneous in crop fields than in more complex habitats such as natural grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Hsu1">Hsu et al. 2010</xref>).Among the species of conservation interest, the Greater Rhea was the only one with a larger number of records in soybean fields, highlighting the importance of maintaining other habitats for species of conservation concern. Both Saffron-cowled Blackbird and Black-and-white Monjita populations have been declining, mainly due to natural habitat destruction and alteration of land use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Bencke1">Bencke et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz2">Azpiroz et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-IUCN1">IUCN 2013</xref>). The fact that the Black-and-white Monjita was recorded in soybean fields might represent a legacy effect of the recent conversion of the site, or might reflect actual persistence in soybean fields with interspersed grassland remnants, with these remnants perhaps providing foraging opportunities amongst the soybeans. It is important to note that a pair and a young individual of the species were observed more than once in a seminatural grassland area adjoining a soybean field. On the other hand, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-53-Azpiroz1">Azpiroz and Blake (2009)</xref> recorded the Black-and-white Monjita only in crop areas (barley and sunflower fields) in a study carried out in Paysand&uacute; and Salto, Uruguay, and Gressler (2008) observed the species adjacent to corn crops. Perhaps additional study will reveal how this species uses mixed agricultural landscapes.Agricultural production and conservation of biodiversity compete for land in the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion. Conservation practices and agricultural production in this region should be considered together, and discussed among farmers, conservationists, and government agencies. Future studies should focus on monitoring species densities through time and carrying out research on the breeding biology, distribution, and population viability of grassland birds. Our research did not evaluate possible within-season heterogeneity in bird use of soybean fields as the fields developed from sowing through to harvesting, but this could reveal more detailed patterns of bird use, especially whether birds are able to complete breeding cycles. Soybean fields are a recent addition to the region, and remnant patches of seminatural grassland might provide birds with opportunities for feeding and breeding. Our results can be considered a first step in a range of research that is still needed to understand the factors that allow persistence of grassland birds in crops with grassland patches.We are indebted to the landowners for allowing us to carry out the study on their farms, particularly Jos&eacute; Carlos Severo for all the logistical support he provided upon receiving us on his farm. We thank three anonymous reviewers for constructive comments and suggestions on the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement.</bold> CAPES (Coordena&ccedil;&atilde;o de Aperfei&ccedil;oamento de Pessoal de N&iacute;vel Superior) supplied scholarships to T.W.S. (M.Sc.) and G.D. (Ph.D.). A Rufford Small Grant to G.D. provided financial support for carrying out the fieldwork. No funders had input into the manuscript, nor required manuscript approval prior to submission or publication.Number of individuals of species sampled in 2010&ndash;2012 in the two types of land use of the Uruguayan savanna ecoregion, including aquatic birds, raptors, and swallows. C &equals; cattle sites (cattle ranching on seminatural grasslands) and S &equals; soybean sites (soybean fields with scattered patches of grassland).