Oil and natural gas development has mixed effects on the density and reproductive success of grassland songbirdsCorticosterone and foraging behavior in a diving seabird: The Ad&eacute;lie Penguin, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pygoscelis adeliae</named-content></italic>Effects of population density and supplemental food on reproduction in Song SparrowsUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriteriaConservation of grassland birds in North America: Understanding ecological processes in different regionsImpacts of chronic anthropogenic noise from energy-sector activity on abundance of songbirds in the boreal forestNest orientation and hatching success in the Tree Pipit <italic>Anthus trivialis</italic>The Canadian Association of Oil Well Drilling Contractors well countsLong-term ecosystem effects of an introduced grass in the northern Great PlainsProximity to a high traffic road: Glucocorticoid and life history consequences for nestling White-crowned SparrowsAbundance of three grassland songbirds in an area of natural gas infill drilling in Alberta, CanadaNesting ecology of mixed-grass prairie songbirds in southern SaskatchewanArea sensitivity in grassland passerines: Effects of patch size, patch shape, and vegetation on bird abundance and occurrence in southern SaskatchewanGrassland songbird occurrence in native and crested wheatgrass pastures of southern SaskatchewanWestern Meadowlark (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnella neglecta</named-content></italic>)Minimal effects of wind turbines on the distribution of wintering farmland birdsGreater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) select habitat based on avian predators, landscape composition, and anthropogenic featuresFrom Wiens to Robel: A review of grassland bird habitat selectionPost-fledging dispersal, habitat use, and survival of Sprague's Pipits: Are planted grasslands a good substitute for native?Monitoring the conservation of grassland habitats, Prairie Ecozone, CanadaRoads as conduits for exotic plant invasions in a semiarid landscapeEnergy development affects populations of sagebrush songbirds in WyomingAvian response to warm-season grass use in pasture and hayfield managementChronic industrial noise affects pairing success and age structure of Ovenbirds <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Seiurus aurocapilla</named-content></italic>No evidence of displacement due to wind turbines in breeding grassland songbirdsNegative impact of traffic noise on avian reproductive successEffects of disturbance associated with natural gas extraction on the occurrence of three grassland songbirdsMulti-scale impacts of crested wheatgrass invasion in mixed-grass prairieThe Mayfield method of estimating nesting success: A model, estimators and simulation resultsEffects of old world bluestem (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bothriochloa ischaemum</named-content></italic>) on food availability and avian community composition within the mixed-grass prairieChestnut-collared Longspur (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calcarius ornatus</named-content></italic>)Passerine response to roads associated with natural gas extraction in a sagebrush steppe habitatGrassland songbirds exhibit variable responses to the proximity and density of natural gas wellsThe nest predator community of grassland birds responds to agroecosystem habitat at multiple scalesResponses of raven and Red-tailed Hawk populations to linear right-of-waysReproductive success of Chestnut-Collared Longspurs in native and exotic grasslandNon-invasive corticosterone treatment changes foraging intensity in Red-eyed Vireos <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vireo olivaceus</named-content></italic>Using candlers to determine the incubation stage of passerine eggsNesting ecology of grassland songbirds: Effects of predation, parasitism, and weatherPotential gas development impacts on sage grouse nest initiation and movementAre microhabitat preferences of coexisting species under selection and adaptive?Nest-monitoring plots: Methods for locating nests and monitoring successThe North American Central Plains as an isolating agent in bird speciationUse of roadsides by diurnal raptors in agricultural landscapesHierarchical cues in brood parasite nest selectionLegacy effects of habitat degradation by Lesser Snow Geese on nesting Savannah SparrowsImpact of road traffic on breeding bird populationsUse of native plants on federal lands: Policy and practiceSprague's Pipit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus spragueii</named-content></italic>)Relationships between visual obstruction measurements and weight of grassland vegetationAre agrofuels a conservation threat or opportunity for grassland birds in the United States?Nest site characteristics in the Song Sparrow and parasitism by Brown-headed CowbirdsA unified approach to analyzing nest successAn analysis of displacement from wind turbines in a wintering grassland bird communityGrassland songbird abundance along roads and trails in southern SaskatchewanCensus efficiency and number of visits to a study plot when estimating bird densities by the territory mapping methodHow do cowbirds find and select nests to parasitize?Forecasting agriculturally driven global environmental changeGreater Sage-Grouse population response to energy development and habitat lossFemale response to reduced male parental care in birds: An experiment in Tree SwallowsOil and natural gas development has increased dramatically in native grasslands over the past 25 years. Some grassland songbirds are less abundant in areas with oil and gas development, but the effects vary among species and geographically within a species' range. The reproductive consequences of nesting in areas with oil and gas development are unknown. We assessed how the density and reproductive success of five species of grassland songbird in Alberta, Canada, varied with distance to oil and gas wells, gravel roads, and trails, and cover of crested wheatgrass (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agropyron cristatum</named-content></italic>), an aggressive alien plant that often becomes established following anthropogenic disturbance. Crested wheatgrass cover had the greatest impact on the grassland songbird community. Sprague's Pipit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus spragueii</named-content></italic>) nest survival decreased as the amount of crested wheatgrass increased. As crested wheatgrass cover increased from 0&percnt; to 60&percnt;, density of Savannah Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerculus sandwichensis</named-content></italic>) declined by 50&percnt;, but they fledged 25&percnt; more young from successful nests. Density of Savannah Sparrows was twice as high near wells, and fledging success was 40&percnt; higher compared with 700 m away. Distance to gravel roads did not influence the density or reproductive success of any species. Sprague's Pipits and Baird's Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus bairdii</named-content></italic>) avoided nesting within 100 m of trails, and both species fledged fewer young from successful nests near trails. In contrast, Vesper Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pooecetes gramineus</named-content></italic>) nested close to trails and fledged more young from successful nests near trails. Western Meadowlarks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnella neglecta</named-content>)</italic> were not strongly affected by any variable. Brown-headed Cowbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>) abundance was three times higher in study plots with wells, although we detected no associated increase in brood parasitism. Our results indicate that the introduction and spread of crested wheatgrass and the creation of access trails to well pads have negative reproductive consequences for primary endemic species such as Sprague's Pipit and Baird's Sparrow, although these results do not extend to other grassland birds. The spread of crested wheatgrass and the disturbance of access trails could be reduced by directional drilling of multiple wells from a single well pad.El desarrollo de petr&oacute;leo y gas ha incrementado enormemente en las praderas de pastos nativos en los &uacute;ltimos 25 a&ntilde;os. Algunas aves canoras de praderas son menos abundantes en &aacute;reas con desarrollo de petr&oacute;leo y gas, pero los efectos var&iacute;an entre especies y entre regiones para una especie. Se desconocen las consecuencias reproductivas de anidar en &aacute;reas con desarrollo de petr&oacute;leo y gas. Evaluamos como la densidad y el &eacute;xito reproductivo de cinco especies de aves canoras var&iacute;an con la distancia a pozos de petr&oacute;leo y gas, rutas enripiadas, senderos y con la cobertura del pasto <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agropyron cristatum</named-content></italic>. La cobertura de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic> tuvo el mayor impacto en la comunidad de aves canoras de pradera. La supervivencia del nido de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus spragueii</named-content></italic> disminuy&oacute; a medida que la cantidad de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic> aument&oacute;, mientras que <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerculus sandwichensis</named-content></italic> emplum&oacute; un 25&percnt; m&aacute;s de j&oacute;venes provenientes de nidos exitosos a medida que la cobertura de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic> aument&oacute; de 0 a 60&percnt;. Sin embargo, la densidad de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. sandwichensis</named-content></italic> fue el doble de alta en &aacute;reas sin <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic> en comparaci&oacute;n con una cobertura de 60&percnt;. El &eacute;xito de emplumamiento de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. sandwichensis</named-content></italic> fue 40&percnt; m&aacute;s alto cerca de los pozos y la densidad de estas aves fue el doble de alta cerca de los pozos que a una distancia de 700 m. La distancia a las rutas enripiadas no influenci&oacute; la densidad o el &eacute;xito reproductivo de ninguna especie. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. spragueii</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus bairdii</named-content></italic> evitaron anidar a menos de 100 m de los senderos y ambas especies emplumaron menos j&oacute;venes provenientes de nidos exitosos cerca de los senderos. En contraste, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pooecetes gramineus</named-content></italic> anid&oacute; cerca de los senderos y emplum&oacute; m&aacute;s j&oacute;venes provenientes de nidos exitosos cerca de los senderos. Nuestros resultados indican que la introducci&oacute;n y propagaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic> y la creaci&oacute;n de senderos de acceso a las plataformas de perforaci&oacute;n tienen consecuencias reproductivas negativas para especies end&eacute;micas primarias como <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. spragueii</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. bairdii</named-content></italic>. El futuro desarrollo de petr&oacute;leo y gas deber&iacute;a minimizar la creaci&oacute;n de senderos por medio de perforaci&oacute;n dirigida de m&uacute;ltiples pozos desde una &uacute;nica plataforma de perforaci&oacute;n y deber&iacute;a minimizar la propagaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. cristatum</named-content></italic>.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agropyron cristatum</named-content></italic>; depredaci&oacute;n del nido; desarrollo de energ&iacute;a; efectos de la distancia; modelos mixtos; parasitismo de nidada; pradera de pastos mixtos; supervivencia del nidoHuman activities have altered natural landscapes worldwide. As human populations expand, resource exploitation is likely to continue to stress natural systems, resulting in additional habitat destruction and loss of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Tilman1">Tilman et al. 2001</xref>). The grassland biome is the most drastically altered biome in North America, and has experienced continent-wide loss and degradation due to agricultural activities, fire suppression, and industrial and urban development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Askins1">Askins et al. 2007</xref>). It is estimated that &lt;25&percnt; of original native grassland remains in Canada, with the largest contiguous tracts occurring in southern Alberta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Gauthier1">Gauthier and Wiken 2003</xref>). The widespread loss and degradation of native grasslands have likely been major contributors to population declines of grassland species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Askins1">Askins et al. 2007</xref>).Native grasslands provide important breeding habitat for many grassland species, but the quantity and quality of remaining habitat may be threatened by oil and gas development. The number of oil and gas wells in Alberta increased from 5,811 to 13,555 between 1998 and 2008 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-CAODC1">CAODC 2010</xref>), and there is continued economic incentive to increase the number of wells. Wells are typically accompanied by compressor stations, roads, and other linear features (e.g., pipelines and power lines) that lead to habitat loss, increased amounts of edge, increased or altered predator and brood parasite communities, and anthropogenic disturbance to nesting behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lyon1">Lyon and Anderson 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Ingelfinger1">Ingelfinger and Anderson 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Klug1">Klug et al. 2009</xref>). Furthermore, such development can increase invasion by exotic plant species, through intentional planting or through establishment and spread due to soil disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Gelbard1">Gelbard and Belnap 2003</xref>). Although current practices focus on using native seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-AlbertaEnvironment1">Alberta Environment 2010</xref>), historically, industrial reclamation practices involved the use of exotic grasses to revegetate impacted sites. These grasses were chosen because they are highly adaptive, inexpensive, and readily available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Richards1">Richards et al. 1998</xref>). As a result, old well sites now serve as point sources for invasion of native grassland by exotic grasses, such as crested wheatgrass (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agropyron cristatum</named-content></italic>). Crested wheatgrass is an aggressive invader of native prairie and often outcompetes native species, resulting in a monoculture that dominates the vegetation community and the seed bank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Christian1">Christian and Wilson 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Henderson1">Henderson and Naeth 2005</xref>). This homogenization of habitats with crested wheatgrass reduces habitat suitability for some grassland songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Davis3">Davis and Duncan 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lloyd1">Lloyd and Martin 2005</xref>). Fewer birds may occupy areas with oil and gas development that have been planted with, or invaded by, crested wheatgrass.Oil and gas development has reduced bird abundance in grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Dale1">Dale et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Bogard1">Kalyn Bogard and Davis 2014</xref>), boreal forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Habib1">Habib et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Bayne1">Bayne et al. 2008</xref>), and sagebrush-steppe habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Walker1">Walker et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Gilbert1">Gilbert and Chalfoun 2011</xref>). Roads and trails are commonly associated with oil and gas development because wells need to be visited for maintenance. The presence of roads also reduces bird abundance in adjacent habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Sutter1">Sutter et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Ingelfinger1">Ingelfinger and Anderson 2004</xref>), and may reduce reproductive success for those individuals that do occupy these areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Halfwerk1">Halfwerk et al. 2011</xref>). Bird abundance may be reduced near oil and natural gas wells because of traffic associated with their maintenance, alterations to habitat resulting from construction and maintenance, or noise generated by the structures themselves. The purpose of our study was to assess how density and reproductive success varied with (1) distance to wells, roads, and trails, and (2) the amount of crested wheatgrass (the primary invasive plant species in the area). Previous research on the effects of energy development on avian species abundance has been conducted in native grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Dale1">Dale et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hamilton1">Hamilton et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Bogard1">Kalyn Bogard and Davis 2014</xref>), but currently there are no published data on the extent to which oil and gas development affects grassland songbird reproductive success. We postulated that primary endemic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Mengel1">Mengel 1970</xref>) typically associated with native grassland (e.g., Sprague's Pipit &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus spragueii</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, Baird's Sparrow &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus bairdii</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) would experience reduced density and reproductive success near oil and gas infrastructure and in areas with increased cover of crested wheatgrass. In contrast, we hypothesized that species that are more broadly distributed and more general in their habitat requirements (secondary endemic species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Mengel1">Mengel 1970</xref>), such as Vesper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pooecetes gramineus</named-content></italic>) and Savannah sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerculus sandwichensis</named-content></italic>), would not be affected, or would be more abundant, or experience greater reproductive success in areas with oil and gas development.We conducted our study in the Antelope Creek Habitat Development Area (ACHDA; 50&deg;33&prime;N, 111&deg;53&prime;W) in southeastern Alberta, Canada. The ACHDA is characterized by large tracts of native, dry, mixed-grass prairie. The predominant vegetation consists of needle-and-thread (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Stipa comata</named-content></italic>) and blue grama grass (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bouteloua gracilis</named-content></italic>), sage (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Artemisia</named-content></italic> spp.), club moss (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Selaginella densa</named-content></italic>), and various native forbs. Crested wheatgrass and sweet clover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melilotus officinalis</named-content></italic>) radiate out from roads, wells, and other energy development infrastructure.In 2010, we established 12 plots distributed across the ACHDA. We determined plot placement prior to the start of the nesting season, and attempted to maximize coverage of the ACHDA while ensuring plots were not directly adjacent to one another. Plot locations were chosen based on the availability of upland grassland vegetation, the location of energy development infrastructure, and percent cover of crested wheatgrass. Plot placement in 2010 was limited due to large amounts of standing water. In 2011, conditions were drier and we added 4 plots to increase the sample size of nests. Plots were 35&ndash;448 m apart (mean &plusmn; SD &equals; 227 &plusmn; 134 m) and ranged from 14 to 21 ha (18 &plusmn; 2 ha). Over the course of each summer, locations of all oil and gas wells, roads, trails, and patches of crested wheatgrass were determined by ground truthing. We calculated the percent cover of all roads, trails, well sites, and patches of crested wheatgrass in a geographic information system (ArcMap 9.3; ESRI, Redlands, CA, USA), and then summed this value to determine the amount of overall disturbance for each plot. Plots were classified along a disturbance gradient, which ranged from 0&percnt; to 60&percnt; of the plot area (mean &plusmn; SD &equals; 16&percnt; &plusmn; 19&percnt;). Ten of our 16 study plots contained a well site. The aspects of oil and gas development that we measured included distance to oil (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 10) and gas (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 35) wells (grouped as &lsquo;wells'), gravel roads and trails, and percent cover of crested wheatgrass. Trails consisted of two tracks through the grass which were mowed each year to reduce the risk of fire. Roads in the ACHDA provided access to the paddocks in the pastures and were not strictly associated with oil and gas development, although the majority of the traffic was by oil and gas company vehicles. In contrast, trails in the ACHDA existed solely to provide employees of the oil and gas industry with access to wells.We quantified bird density using spot-mapping surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Svensson1">Svensson 1979</xref>). Each plot was visited 6 times in 2010 and 10 times in 2011. The number of male and female Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>) observed in each plot was also recorded during spot-mapping surveys to allow determination of mean cowbird abundance. We conducted spot-mapping surveys from 05:00 to 09:00 Mountain Standard Time (MST) on clear days with wind velocities &lt;20 km hr<sup>&minus;1</sup>. Spot-mapping surveys were performed May 24&ndash;July 3 in 2010 and May 23&ndash;July 23 in 2011.We quantified vegetation structure using 50 &times; 50 cm quadrats. Quadrats were placed at random distances in each of the four cardinal directions at every second grid point in each plot, resulting in 77 &plusmn; 10 quadrats per plot (range &equals; 68&ndash;108 quadrats, depending on plot shape). In each quadrat, we visually estimated percent cover of live native grass, dead native grass, forbs, crested wheatgrass, bare ground, and lichen and club moss to the nearest 5&percnt;. At the center of each quadrat, we measured both mean vegetation height and litter (unattached, unconsolidated plant material) depth using a 30 cm ruler, and we indexed vegetation density using a Robel pole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Robel1">Robel et al. 1970</xref>). We took 4 visual obstruction readings (VOR) per quadrat (1 in each of the cardinal directions), and averaged these values to obtain a single value for each quadrat. We measured vegetation in each plot once each year, from June 6 to July 9, 2010, and from June 21 to July 9, 2011. To obtain plot-level distance variables, we measured the distance of the nearest well, road, and trail from the center of each plot.We located nests by systematically dragging a weighted 25 m rope between 2 people across each study plot to flush incubating birds from their nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Davis1">Davis 2003</xref>). We conducted nest searches 06:00&ndash;14:00 MST from early May to late July in each year, and also located nests fortuitously while conducting other activities. We searched each plot for nests 5 times, and took precautions to minimize human-induced nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Martin2">Martin and Geupel 1993</xref>). We checked nests every 3&ndash;4 days until completion of the nesting attempt, and candled eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lokemoen1">Lokemoen and Koford 1996</xref>) to determine clutch initiation and hatching dates to increase the precision of our nest survival rate estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Shaffer1">Shaffer 2004</xref>). We aged chicks based on images of known-age young for nests found after hatching. We considered a nest attempt successful if at least one host young fledged, and used cues such as age of nestlings at last nest visit, presence of droppings and feather scales in the nest, and young observed in the area to identify successful nests.We performed all analyses using SAS Enterprise Guide 4.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2010</xref>). We used the GLIMMIX procedure to model the density of singing males as a function of vegetation structure and oil and gas disturbance. We modeled the number of territories using a Poisson distribution, and used the log of plot area as an offset and study plot as a random effect to account for use of the same sites in both years. We first considered models with both the additive and interactive effects of year to determine whether we could combine the data on density from the 2 years. We combined data if models containing no year effect or an additive effect of year performed better than those with an interactive effect of year. Explanatory variables included vegetation features identified as important predictors of grassland songbird habitat use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Fisher1">Fisher and Davis 2010</xref>), as well as disturbance features associated with oil and gas development. Grassland bird habitat and nest-site selection are influenced by both vertical and horizontal vegetation cover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Fisher1">Fisher and Davis 2010</xref>). Therefore, to avoid overparameterizing models, we divided our vegetation variables into two model categories based on vegetation structure: horizontal (percent cover of bare ground, lichen and club moss, forbs, live grass, and dead grass) and vertical (mean vegetation height and VOR) structure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t01">Table 1</xref>). Litter depth was included as a separate model. None of the vegetation variables were highly correlated (<italic>r</italic> &lt; 0.70). We used Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>) to rank models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>), and considered the model with the lowest AIC<sub>c</sub> value to be the best of those considered. We first identified the best horizontal and vertical vegetation model by ranking all subset models in each model set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t01">Table 1</xref>), and then used variables from these models along with litter depth to generate a global vegetation model. We compared all subset models along with a null model to identify our best vegetation model for each species. We analyzed development variables (distance to roads, trails, and wells, and percent cover of crested wheatgrass) as a separate model set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t01">Table 1</xref>), and included a null model, a global model, and all subsets of the development variables, for a total of 16 models. We compared the top development and vegetation models with a null model and the vegetation and development models combined to determine whether variation in bird density was due mainly to vegetation characteristics or to oil and gas development. We calculated 85&percnt; confidence intervals to identify uninformative parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>) and to assess the strength of effect for each parameter. We modeled the mean number of Brown-headed Cowbirds per plot as a function of proximity to wells, trails, and roads, percent cover of crested wheatgrass, and presence of a well in a plot using mixed linear models (PROC MIXED; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2010</xref>) with plot as a random effect to account for using the same plots each year.List of the models representing horizontal vegetation structure, vertical vegetation structure, and oil and gas development used in the density analyses for five species of grassland songbird in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. The variables in the horizontal vegetation structure model set include percent cover of live grass (live), dead grass (dead), forbs (forb), bare ground (bare), and lichen (lichen). The variables in the vertical vegetation model set include vegetation height (veg&lowbar;ht) and visual obstruction (robel). The oil and gas development variables include distance to gravel roads (roads), trails (trails), and oil and gas wells (wells), and percent cover of crested wheatgrass (pcwg).We used Fisher's exact test (&alpha; &equals; 0.05) to determine whether nest placement relative to energy development infrastructure differed from random. We tallied the number of nests for each species in each 100 m distance category up to 600 m for wells and roads and up to 500 m for trails. We chose the 500 m and 600 m distance cutoffs because at least 75&percnt; of nests of all species were located within these distances. We used ArcGIS (ESRI, Redlands, CA, USA) to place 100 random points within each plot, and summed the number of random points within each 100 m distance category. For both nests and random points we calculated the proportion of nests or random points within each distance interval by dividing the number of nests within each interval by the sum of all nests or random points. We used the proportion of nests and random points within each distance interval as &lsquo;observed' and &lsquo;expected', respectively, in further analyses.We calculated daily nest survival rate as a function of distance to the various disturbance features using the logistic exposure method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Shaffer1">Shaffer 2004</xref>). We considered five a priori models, including a null model (constant survival), distance to wells, roads, and trails, and percent cover of crested wheatgrass, for each species. We determined whether the relationship between daily nest survival rate and distance to the various disturbance features depended upon the year of the study using the same procedure outlined in our density analysis. We used generalized linear models (PROC GENMOD; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Burton1">Burton 2006</xref>) with a Poisson distribution and a log link to determine the extent to which the number of young fledged per nest and per successful nest varied with proximity to gravel roads, trails, and wells. We used logistic regression models (PROC LOGISTIC; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2010</xref>) to determine the extent to which the probability of cowbird parasitism (parasitized vs. nonparasitized nests) varied with distance to roads and trails and the presence of a well. To maximize available sample size, we combined parasitized nests of all songbird species for analysis (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 24). Unless indicated otherwise, all results are presented as mean &plusmn; standard error (SE). Only results for which 85&percnt; confidence intervals did not overlap or include zero are presented and discussed.We found 332 passerine nests during the 2 years of our study. However, only species for which at least 20 nests were found were included in our analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hensler1">Hensler and Nichols 1981</xref>). This resulted in 325 nests of 5 grassland songbird species: Sprague's Pipit (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 21), Vesper Sparrow (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53), Savannah Sparrow (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 190), Baird's Sparrow (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 35), and Western Meadowlark (<italic>Sternella neglecta</italic>; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 26). For all species, the relationship between disturbance and density did not vary as a function of year; therefore, we combined the data for both years in all analyses. Clutch size, daily survival rate, and fledging success in the AHCDA were similar to rates reported elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Ludlow1">Ludlow et al. 2014</xref>).The top model explaining variation in Savannah Sparrow density included litter depth, percent cover of crested wheatgrass, and distance to roads, wells, and trails (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t02">Table 2</xref>). Density was most strongly influenced by well proximity and percent cover of crested wheatgrass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t03">Table 3</xref>). Savannah Sparrow density was lower near wells and decreased with increasing cover of crested wheatgrass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Baird's Sparrow density was most influenced by Robel VOR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t02">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t03">Table 3</xref>) and decreased as VOR increased. Variation in Vesper Sparrow density was best explained by percent cover of bare ground (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t02">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t03">Table 3</xref>), with density increasing with greater amounts of bare ground cover. The top model explaining Western Meadowlark density included distance to gravel roads (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t02">Table 2</xref>), but confidence limits included zero (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t03">Table 3</xref>). Sprague's Pipit density was best explained by litter depth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t02">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t03">Table 3</xref>), and was lower in areas with increased depth of litter. Mean cowbird abundance was best explained by the presence of a well in the study plot, and was almost three times higher in plots containing an oil or gas well (2.5 &plusmn; 0.3 birds 18 ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>) than in plots where wells were absent (0.9 &plusmn; 0.3 birds 18 ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>).Model selection results for generalized linear mixed models of territory density for five species of grassland songbird in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. Log(<italic>L</italic>) is the value of the maximized log-likelihood function, <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters in the model, AIC<sub>c</sub> is Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the scaled value of AIC<sub>c</sub>, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the Akaike weight. Well, road, and trail represent the distance from the center of the plot to any oil and gas well, gravel road, and trail, respectively. Pcwg represents the percent cover of crested wheatgrass, litter is percent cover of unconsolidated plant material, bare ground is the percent cover of bare ground, and robel represents visual obstruction readings measured with a Robel pole.Parameter estimates of the best generalized linear mixed models for territory density of five species of grassland songbird in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t01">Table 1</xref> for definitions of model parameters.Density of Savannah Sparrows (mean and 85&percnt; CI) in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011, as a function of (<bold>A</bold>) the amount of crested wheatgrass, and (<bold>B</bold>) distance to oil and gas wells.Nest locations relative to wells did not differ from random for Sprague's Pipit, or for Vesper, Savannah, and Baird's sparrows. The proportion of Western Meadowlark nests within 100 m of wells was higher than expected by chance alone (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), although meadowlarks tended to avoid nesting within 100 m of gravel roads (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05). Baird's Sparrows also tended to avoid nesting within 100 m of roads (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03). Nest locations relative to roads did not differ from random for Savannah and Vesper sparrows and Sprague's Pipits. The proportion of Vesper Sparrow nests within 100 m of trails was higher than expected based on chance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), whereas Baird's Sparrows (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03) and Sprague's Pipits (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) tended to avoid nesting within 100 m of trails. The distribution of Savannah Sparrow and Western Meadowlark nests relative to trails did not differ from random.We found no effect of proximity to wells, roads, or trails on nest survival, as 85&percnt; confidence limits included zero in all cases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t04">Table 4</xref>). Nest survival varied with percent cover of crested wheatgrass only for Sprague's Pipits (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t04">Table 4</xref>), with daily nest survival rate decreasing with increased cover of crested wheatgrass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t04">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-f02">Figure 2</xref>). We failed to find any relationship between the frequency of brood parasitism and distance to gravel roads (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.000 &plusmn; 0.001) or trails (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.001 &plusmn; 0.001), well presence (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.647 &plusmn; 0.517), and percent cover of crested wheatgrass (&beta; &plusmn; SE &equals; &minus;0.009 &plusmn; 0.015).Effects of distance to gravel roads, trails, and oil and gas wells, along with percent cover of crested wheatgrass (&percnt; CWG), on the daily nest survival rates of five species of grassland songbird in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. Data presented are mean estimates followed by upper and lower 85&percnt; confidence limits.Daily survival rate (mean and 85&percnt; CI) of Sprague's Pipit nests as a function of percent cover of crested wheatgrass in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011.Savannah Sparrows fledged more young per nest closer to wells than farther away (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-f03">Figure 3</xref>A). The number of young fledged per nest did not vary with proximity to wells for the other four species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t05">Table 5</xref>). The number of young fledged per nest did not vary with percent cover of crested wheatgrass or distance to gravel roads or trails for any species, as confidence limits included zero in all cases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t05">Table 5</xref>).The mean number of young fledged from (<bold>A</bold>) Savannah Sparrow nests as a function of oil and gas well proximity, (<bold>B</bold>) successful Baird's Sparrow nests as a function of proximity to trails, and (<bold>C</bold>) successful Savannah Sparrow nests as a function of percent cover of crested wheatgrass in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. Dashed lines show 95&percnt; CI.Parameter estimates for the number of young fledged from all nests and successful nests as a function of distance to gravel roads, trails, and oil and gas wells, and percent cover of crested wheatgrass (&percnt; CWG) for five species of grassland songbird in southeastern Alberta, Canada, 2010&ndash;2011. Data presented are mean estimate (EST), standard error (SE), and upper and lower 85&percnt; confidence limits (UCL and LCL, respectively).The number of young fledged from successful nests was lower near trails than farther away for Baird's Sparrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-f03">Figure 3</xref>B) and Sprague's Pipits, but was higher closer to trails for Vesper Sparrows (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t05">Table 5</xref>). The number of Savannah Sparrow young fledged per successful nest increased as the percent cover of crested wheatgrass increased from 0&percnt; to 60&percnt; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-f03">Figure 3</xref>C). The number of young fledged per successful nest did not vary with distance to wells or gravel roads for any of the five species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-t05">Table 5</xref>).The effect of oil and gas development on grassland songbird density and reproductive success varied by species, despite these species establishing territories in the same plots and nesting in similar habitats. Furthermore, many of the species share similar life history traits, such as diet, parental care, and foraging and nesting behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Ehrlich1">Ehrlich et al. 1988</xref>). Differences in responses among species may reflect differences in sensitivity to habitat alteration or intensity of disturbance. If nest placement is adaptive, birds would be expected to place their nests in areas that maximize reproductive success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Martin1">Martin 1998</xref>). Indeed, some species in the ACHDA tended to locate their nests in areas where they were more successful. For example, Sprague's Pipits and Baird's Sparrows tended to avoid nesting within 100 m of trails, and both of these species fledged fewer young from successful nests near trails. In contrast, Vesper Sparrows nested closer to trails than expected by chance and fledged more young from successful nests near trails.Of the variables that we investigated that were related to oil and gas development, the amount of crested wheatgrass had the most wide-ranging effects on the density and reproductive success of grassland songbirds. Savannah Sparrow density was nearly two times lower in areas with 60&percnt; cover of crested wheatgrass compared with areas without this exotic grass. Grasslands dominated by exotic grasses are typically poor-quality habitat for songbirds compared with native prairie (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lloyd1">Lloyd and Martin 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Fisher2">Fisher and Davis 2011</xref>). However, increased fledging success of Savannah Sparrows in areas with higher amounts of crested wheatgrass suggests that a density-dependent relationship may exist, whereby a lower density of breeding pairs in a patch of crested wheatgrass may provide increased opportunities to acquire food resources. Population density has been shown to influence fledging success and other reproductive parameters in Song Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melospiza melodia</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Arcese1">Arcese and Smith 1988</xref>). In contrast, Sprague's Pipit nest survival was lower in areas with increased cover of crested wheatgrass. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lloyd1">Lloyd and Martin (2005)</xref> found that Chestnut-collared Longspurs (<italic>Calcarius ornatus</italic>) had reduced reproductive success in crested wheatgrass compared with native grassland. Grasslands composed of exotic vegetation typically have lower plant diversity and reduced arthropod biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hickman1">Hickman et al. 2006</xref>) than native grasslands. Sprague's Pipit nest survival may be lower in areas with large amounts of crested wheatgrass if these areas are deficient in the bird's preferred prey. Like the Chestnut-collared Longspur, Sprague's Pipit is a primary endemic grassland specialist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hill1">Hill and Gould 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Robbins1">Robbins and Dale 1999</xref>), and is more sensitive to habitat alteration or degradation than the Savannah Sparrow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Sutter1">Sutter et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Davis2">Davis 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hamilton1">Hamilton et al. 2011</xref>).Although proximity to roads did not influence the density or nest success of any species, Baird's Sparrows and Western Meadowlarks avoided placing nests within 100 m of gravel roads. Such avoidance may be a result of unsuitable vegetation structure along roadsides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Gelbard1">Gelbard and Belnap 2003</xref>), increased predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Knight1">Knight and Kawashima 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Meunier1">Meunier et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Dinkins1">Dinkins et al. 2014</xref>), or disturbance by vehicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Reijnen1">Reijnen and Foppen 2006</xref>).Proximity to wells had several positive effects on grassland songbird density and reproductive success in the ACHDA. The proportion of Western Meadowlark nests located within 100 m of wells was higher than expected by chance. Western Meadowlarks may locate nests near wells due to these structures providing perch sites for territorial males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Davis4">Davis and Lanyon 2008</xref>). Savannah Sparrows had higher fledging success closer to wells, and this may be related to increased rates of parental provisioning. In many socially monogamous species, nestling provisioning by both parents is necessary to successfully raise young, and any adjustments to the level of provisioning by either parent may alter the total number of young fledged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Whittingham1">Whittingham et al. 1994</xref>). Provisioning rates and nest attentiveness of male Savannah Sparrows may be higher near wells due to elevated levels of corticosterone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Crino1">Crino et al. 2011</xref>), a stress-induced hormone known to influence avian foraging behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lohmus1">L&otilde;hmus et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Angelier1">Angelier et al. 2008</xref>). Higher fledging success near wells may also be the result of increased density of Savannah Sparrows in these areas. However, the fledging success of Savannah Sparrows in southern Saskatchewan, Canada, was not influenced by proximity to natural gas wells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Gaudet1">Gaudet 2013</xref>). Regional variation in Savannah Sparrow fledging success in response to well proximity highlights the influence of site-level variation on species' responses to development, and suggests that extrapolation of results from a single site across a species' range may be tenuous. This may be especially true for a species like the Savannah Sparrow, which shows variation in habitat preferences across its broad range (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Peterson1">Peterson et al. 2014</xref>). More studies across a range of sites are needed to gain a better perspective of the influence of oil and gas wells on grassland songbird reproductive success. It would also be useful to make comparisons among various energy-related activities in grasslands, particularly including indirect effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Devereaux1">Devereaux et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Robertson1">Robertson et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Hale1">Hale et al. 2014</xref>).Variation in Brown-headed Cowbird abundance was best explained by the presence of a well. The mean abundance of cowbirds in plots containing an oil or gas well was almost three times that in plots where wells were absent. Oil and gas wells provide perch sites for cowbirds to use for displaying and locating host nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Thompson1">Thompson and Gottfried 1976</xref>), and therefore may increase the frequency of cowbird parasitism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Patten1">Patten et al. 2011</xref>). However, the frequency of brood parasitism by cowbirds in the ACHDA was not higher in plots containing wells. The lack of a relationship between brood parasitism frequency and well presence may be due to the presence of, or proximity to, other similar perches (e.g., fences, power lines, shrubs) across the landscape; alternatively, the small sample of parasitized nests may have precluded us from finding an effect.Overall, our results indicated that the effect of oil and natural gas development on grassland songbird density and reproductive success varied with species and type of disturbance. Furthermore, our results supported our initial prediction that primary endemic species would suffer adverse effects of oil and gas development while generalist species would either be positively or not affected. The percent cover of crested wheatgrass had the widest-ranging effects of the disturbance variables that we investigated. Although all species of grassland songbird that we studied had nests located in crested wheatgrass, Sprague's Pipits experienced reduced nest survival in these areas compared with native grassland. Our results are consistent with those of other studies, which have found reduced reproductive rates for grassland songbirds nesting in crested wheatgrass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Lloyd1">Lloyd and Martin 2005</xref>) and other exotic grasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Guiliano1">Guiliano and Daves 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-64-Fisher2">Fisher and Davis 2011</xref>). The Savannah Sparrow was the sole species whose reproductive success was positively influenced by crested wheatgrass cover, although its density declined with increased cover of this exotic grass. Our results indicate that the creation of access trails to well pads and the introduction and spread of crested wheatgrass can have negative reproductive consequences for primary endemic species such as Sprague's Pipits and Baird's Sparrows. We encourage future oil and gas developments to minimize trail creation through directional drilling of multiple wells from one lease site, and to continue to minimize the spread of crested wheatgrass in native grasslands.We are grateful to the numerous field assistants who contributed to this project, and to N. Wilson and S. Burnard for their hospitality and logistical assistance. We appreciate the comments made by two anonymous reviewers, which greatly improved the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement.</bold> Funding was provided by the Antelope Creek Habitat Development Area, Alberta Conservation Association, MITACS&ndash;Accelerate Saskatchewan, Petroleum Technology Alliance Canada, Saskatchewan Ministry of Environment &ndash; Fish and Wildlife Development Fund, Environment Canada &ndash; Canadian Wildlife Service, and the University of Regina. None of our funders had any input into the manuscript, nor did they require approval of the manuscript prior to submission or publication.