Thank You to the Reviewers of the 2014 <italic>Condor</italic>, Volume 116<email xlink:type="simple">pstouffer@lsu.edu</email><italic>The Condor's</italic> 116<sup>th</sup> year saw significant changes to the journal. We moved to online publishing, combined journal management and production with <italic>The Auk: Ornithological Advances</italic>, and, most importantly, redefined the journal's name and mission as <italic>The Condor: Ornithological Applications</italic>. Despite all of these changes, the journal's scientific foundation remains with the peer review process. Peer reviewers receive little reward, but their timely and diligent work allows us to make the journal as strong as it can be. In the name of all of us who have been involved in launching <italic>The Condor: Ornithological Applications</italic>, I thank all of you who contributed reviews during the period that Volume 116 was in preparation (reviews completed between September 1, 2013, and August 31, 2014). Individuals identified with asterisks are especially dedicated; they reviewed two, three, or even four manuscripts.<italic>The Condor: Ornithological Applications</italic> also gratefully acknowledges the work and commitment of our two fine Editors, our busy Associate Editors, and the superb editorial team at the Central Ornithology Publication Office (COPO). The new look and content of 2014 attest to their dedicated collective efforts.Ken AbrahamMarissa AhleringCameron AldridgeCourtney AmundsonAngela Anders&ast;Beatriz ArroyoJonathan AtwoodBlake BarbareeThomas BensonMarcello BertellottiChristine BishopJeffrey BlackJohn BlakeErik BlombergAlexander Bond&ast;Carlos BosqueReed Bowman&ast;Clait BraunJay CarlisleDaniel CatlinAntonio Celis-MurilloDavid CerasaleRichard ChandlerRoy ChurchwellCarla CiceroMariano CodesidoNigel CollarBret Collier&ast;John ConnellyJacob CooperFrancesca CuthbertJeremy DertienRandall DeYoungStephen Dinsmore&ast;Barny DunningRobert DusekChris ElphickMatthew Etterson&ast;Andrew Farnsworth&ast;Ryan FisherCurtis FlatherLeonard FreedSidney Gauthreaux, Jr.T. GeorgeJennifer Gervais&ast;Frank GillThomas GottschalkCheri Gratto-TrevorAdam Green&ast;M. GreenJuan GuayasaminRalph GutierrezMichael GutteryLinnea HallColleen HandelSteven HanserPatrick HartGarth HerringJason HillKyle HortonDavid HowerterLuis HurtadoRichard Hutto&ast;Douglas JohnsonAndrew JonesLeo JosephRomain JulliardYula KapatenakosJeffrey KellyKevin KenowPaul KerlingerMatthew KirchhoffJohn KlickaJonas KnapeJessie KnowltonWilliam KristanRon LarkinQuresh Latif&ast;Aleksi LehikoinenXingong LiSara LipshutzAlberto Macias DuarteIvan MagginiJames MaleyRaivo MandStuart MarsdenKyle McCarthyDavid MehlmanDaniel MennillTricia MillerDavid MillerAra MonadjemWilliam MonahanMichael MorrisonJoan MorrisonAntoine NappiZoltan NemethChristopher NicolaiJoseph Nocera&ast;Erica Nol&ast;Timothy O'Connell&ast;Darcy OgadaKen OtterSusan PaganoMonica PapesGuillaume PeronBradley PickensLuke PowellLarkin Powell&ast;Christin Pruett&ast;Robert RempelRichard ReynoldsS. James ReynoldsGregory RobertsonErin RocheKenneth RosenbergJay RotellaJ. Andrew RoyleMark RumbleVictoria SaabSarah SaalfeldEmi SaitoAlejandro Salinas-MelgozaBrett SandercockHanno SandvikMichael SchroederJames SedingerNathan SennerW. Gregory ShriverDave Shutler&ast;Theodore SimonsPeter SingletonRobert SmithPaul SmithPeter SolymosChristopher SomersSarah SonsthagenGarth SpellmanJessica StantonKaren SteenhofKirk StodolaEric StolenCraig StrickerPhil TaylorSabrina Taylor&ast;Morgan TingleyPhilip UnittAmanda Van DellenEric VanderWerfVincent ViblancPeter VickeryKerri VierlingMargaret VossNils Warnock&ast;Rekha WarrierBrian WashburnStephen WebbWalter WehtjeNathaniel WheelrightScott WilsonDavid WilsonVirginia WinderKristopher WiniarskiStefan WoltmannPetra WoodYuri ZharikovVictor Zwiener