Vocal distinctiveness of the Red Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>) on the island of Newfoundland, CanadaMorphological diversification of Common Crossbill <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> populations within Iberia and the BalearicsOn the evolution and ecology of island populations of crossbillsAdaptation to single resources and the evolution of crossbill (<italic>Loxia</italic>) diversityDivergent selection drives the adaptive radiation of crossbillsDiversifying coevolution between crossbills and conifersA new species of the Red Crossbill (Fringillidae: <italic>Loxia</italic>) from IdahoA new subspecies of crossbill from NewfoundlandA flight of Newfoundland crossbillsPraat: Doing Phonetics by Computer (Version 5.3)Local divergence between Mediterranean crossbills occurring in two different species of pineGeographic variation in Newfoundland birdsThe Sound Approach to Birding: A Guide to Understanding Bird SoundThe &ldquo;old northeastern&rdquo; subspecies of Red CrossbillPopulation differentiation and restricted gene flow in Spanish crossbills: Not isolation-by-distance but isolation-by-ecologyBirds in boreal Canada: Communities, densities, and adaptationsVocal types in crossbill populations (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia</named-content></italic> spp.) of southwest EuropeRed squirrels, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tamiasciurus hudsonicus</named-content></italic>, in the Salmonier River Valley, NewfoundlandThe analysis of animal communicationA monographic study of the Red CrossbillResolution of cryptic species in Appalachian Red CrossbillsEvolutionary differentiation in morphology, vocalizations, and allozymes among nomadic sibling species in the North American Red Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>) complexCall matching and positive assortative mating in Red CrossbillsRelation of sample size to the stability of component patternsA new and cryptic call type of the Red CrossbillDiscriminant analysis of principal components: A new method for the analysis of genetically structured populationsThe sympatric breeding of Common and Scottish Crossbills <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> and <italic>L. scotica</italic> and the evolution of crossbillsCorrelation between beak and food in the crossbill, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> LinnaeusCrossbill call types in Finland, 1998&ndash;2009Bird calls: A cornucopia for communicationOrigins of irruptive migrations by Common Crossbills <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> into northwestern Europe revealed by stable isotope analysisA new quantitative technique for categorizing whistles using simulated signals and whistles from captive bottlenose dolphins (Delphinidae, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tursiops truncatus</named-content></italic>)The races of the Red Crossbill, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>, in ArizonaVocal imitation and individual recognition of finch callsAPE: Analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R languagePatterns of genetic variation in the adaptive radiation of New World crossbills (Aves: <italic>Loxia</italic>)Red squirrel introduction to NewfoundlandPopulations and type specimens of a nomadic bird: Comments on the North American crossbills <italic>Loxia pusilla</italic> Gloger 1834 and <italic>Crucirostra minor</italic> Brehm 1845nlme: Linear and Nonlinear Mixed Effects ModelsAcoustic discrimination of sympatric morphs in Darwin's finches: A behavioural mechanism for assortative mating?Ecological speciation in Darwin's finches: Parsing the effects of magic traitsPhylogeographical evidence of gene flow among Common Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>, Aves, Fringillidae) populations at the continental levelIntroduction to vocalizations of crossbills in north-western EuropeSexual selection accelerates signal evolution during speciation in birdsMagic traits in speciation: &lsquo;Magic' but not rare?Limited adult vocal learning maintains call dialects but permits pair-distinctive calls in Red CrossbillsSocial experience modifies behavioural responsiveness to a preferred vocal signal in Red Crossbills, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>Early learning of discrete call variants in Red Crossbills: Implications for reliable signalingBird song, ecology and speciationA coevolutionary arms race causes ecological speciation in crossbillsAssortative flocking in crossbills and implications for ecological speciationThe role of marker traits in the assortative mating within Red Crossbills, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> complexAssortative mating and patterns of inheritance indicate that the three crossbill taxa in Scotland are speciesThe distribution and habitats of crossbills <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia</named-content></italic> spp. in Britain, with special reference to the Scottish Crossbill <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia scotica</named-content></italic>Nonlinear phenomena in the vocalizations of North Atlantic right whales (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Eubalaena glacialis</named-content></italic>) and killer whales (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orcinus orca</named-content></italic>)Evolutionary divergence in acoustic signals: Causes and consequencesType 5 Red Crossbills (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>) in New York: First confirmation east of the Rocky MountainsNew evidence in support of a distinctive Red Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>) type in NewfoundlandOn the relationship between, and measurement of, amplitude and frequency in birdsongTen vocal types of Red Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>) are recognized in North America. Little is known about this species' vocalizations on the island of Newfoundland, where the subspecies <italic>L. c. percna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bent1">Bent 1912</xref>) was described on the basis of study skins collected in a single year from one area; subsequently a distinctive vocal type was proposed on the basis of one sound recording. We made field recordings (&sim;1000 min) of Red Crossbill vocalizations in Newfoundland to describe vocalizations and compare them with vocal types recognized elsewhere in North America. One class of call (&ldquo;flight call&rdquo;; class I call hereafter) was distinctive, and discriminant analysis distinguished 98&percnt; of Newfoundland class I calls from mainland North American and European samples. Class I calls of 5 (out of 83) Newfoundland birds resembled recognized vocal types from mainland North America. Other call classes (&ldquo;excitement/alarm&rdquo; and &ldquo;chitter&rdquo;) of Newfoundland birds also differed from mainland North American samples. We conclude that several vocal types of Red Crossbill, one of which may represent <italic>L. c. percna</italic>, occur in Newfoundland. Samples from other areas are needed to determine whether the distinctive vocal type in insular Newfoundland (a) represents <italic>L. c. percna</italic> and (b) is restricted to Newfoundland or also occurs in other areas such as Cape Breton Island.Se reconocen diez tipos vocales de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> en Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Poco se sabe sobre las vocalizaciones de esta especie en la isla de Newfoundland, donde la subespecies <italic>L. c. percna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bent1">Bent 1912</xref>) fue descubierta en base al estudio de pieles colectadas en un &aacute;rea en un &uacute;nico a&ntilde;o; subsecuentemente se propuso un tipo vocal distintivo en base a un registro de sonidos. Realizamos grabaciones en el campo (&sim;1000 min) de vocalizaciones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic> en Newfoundland para describir las vocalizaciones y compararlas con los tipos vocales reconocidos en el resto de Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Un tipo de llamada (&ldquo;llamada de vuelo&rdquo;; llamada clase I) fue distintiva, y los an&aacute;lisis discriminantes distinguieron al 98&percnt; de las llamadas clase I de Newfoundland de las muestras del &aacute;rea continental de Am&eacute;rica del Norte y Europa. Las llamadas clase I de 5 aves (de un total de 83) de Newfoundland se parecieron a tipos vocales reconocidos del &aacute;rea continental de Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Las otras clases de llamada (&ldquo;excitaci&oacute;n/alarma&rdquo; y &ldquo;chitter&rdquo;) de las aves de Newfoundland tambi&eacute;n difirieron de las muestras del &aacute;rea continental de Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Concluimos que varios tipos vocales de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">L. curvirostra</named-content></italic>, uno de los cuales puede representar a <italic>L. c. percna</italic>, se encuentran en Newfoundland. Se necesitan muestras de otras &aacute;reas para determinar si el tipo vocal distintivo de la isla de Newfoundland (a) representa a <italic>L. c. percna</italic> y (b) est&aacute; restringido a Newfoundland o tambi&eacute;n se encuentra en otras &aacute;reas como la isla de Cabo Breton.<italic>Palabras clave</italic>: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>, Newfoundland, taxonom&iacute;a, tipo vocal, vocalizaci&oacute;nMorphological and ecological variation in the Red Crossbill in North America has long interested and confused systematists, and various subspecies schemes have been proposed over the years based on museum specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Griscom1">Griscom 1937</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Monson1">Monson and Phillips 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Dickerman1">Dickerman 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Payne2">Payne 1987</xref>). The situation has been greatly clarified through vocal analysis. In the first analysis of both morphology and vocalizations, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth1">Groth (1988)</xref> revealed two types of Red Crossbill in Virginia and North Carolina that differ vocally from one another (we follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth &lsqb;1993a&rsqb;</xref> in using the term <italic>vocal type</italic> &lsqb;or <italic>type</italic>&rsqb; to refer to vocally distinct Red Crossbill forms). Subsequently he revealed a continent-wide pattern of vocal differentiation in which different vocal types could be recognized and used as a basis for describing parallel differentiation in body measurements and plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>). Those findings triggered much research on Red Crossbill differentiation throughout the species' Holarctic range. Other vocal types of North American Red Crossbill have since been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman5">Benkman et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>), and multiple vocal types have also been recognized in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers2">Summers et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Alonso1">Alonso et al. 2006</xref>, Constantine and The Sound Approach 2006, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Borras1">Borr&aacute;s et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Forschler1">F&ouml;rschler and Kalko 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Lindholm1">Lindholm 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Edelaar1">Edelaar et al. 2012</xref>).Vocal types of Red Crossbill recognized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth (1993a)</xref> differ in ecology (e.g., habitat, conifer-species feeding preference) and ecologically important morphological traits (e.g., body and bill size, palate anatomy; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman2">Benkman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman5">Benkman et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>). Phenotypic divergence is thought to be recent (principally within the last 12,000 years) because vocal types exhibit weak genetic differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Parchman1">Parchman et al. 2006</xref>). Nomadism in the Red Crossbill, an adaptation to ephemeral and irregularly distributed cone crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman2">Benkman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Marquiss1">Marquiss et al. 2012</xref>), presumably contributes to weak genetic differentiation.Vocalizations can be important in enabling intraspecific ecological divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Slabbekoorn1">Slabbekoorn and Smith 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Price1">Price 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Wilkins1">Wilkins et al. 2013</xref>); an example is the &ldquo;flight call&rdquo; of the Red Crossbill (we refer to this kind of call as class I; see below). Young birds learn these calls from their parents and the calls are structurally stable across generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Sewall4">Sewall 2011</xref>). Class I calls serve for cohesion of families and flocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Snowberg1">Snowberg and Benkman 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Smith2">Smith et al. 2012</xref>). Association of ecomorphologically similar birds is important because their traits (e.g., bill size) are correlated with cone-type preference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Lack1">Lack 1944</xref>) and feeding performance is optimized when crossbills specialize on cones of different conifer species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman2">Benkman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman4">2010</xref>). Furthermore, bill size is heritable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers1">Summers et al. 2007</xref>) and hybrids between ecologically differentiated forms likely are selected against (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman2">Benkman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman3">2003</xref>). In summary, vocalizations enable and promote differentiation because they contribute to reproductive isolation among different ecomorphological groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Podos1">Podos 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Servedio1">Servedio et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Podos2">Podos et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Seddon1">Seddon et al. 2013</xref>). Red Crossbills exhibit mate preferences and mate assortatively on the basis of acoustic cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Snowberg1">Snowberg and Benkman 2007</xref>), which helps to explain how phenotypic differences can be maintained across multiple vocal types in sympatry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Knox1">Knox 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth3">Groth 1993b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Smith1">Smith and Benkman 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers1">Summers et al. 2007</xref>).It has long been assumed that the island of Newfoundland (&ldquo;Newfoundland&rdquo; hereafter) is home to a single well-marked subspecies of Red Crossbill, <italic>L. c. percna</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bent1">Bent (1912)</xref> described this subspecies on the basis of 11 specimens that were collected in southwestern Newfoundland in 1912. He noted differences in body and bill size from other North American subspecies recognized at the time, and remarked especially on the much darker plumage of <italic>L. c. percna</italic>. Other workers have supported the distinctiveness of <italic>L. c. percna</italic>, and it has generally been assumed that this taxon is restricted to Newfoundland (&ldquo;in the breeding season at least&rdquo; &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bent1">Bent 1912</xref>:1&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Griscom1">Griscom 1937</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Burleigh1">Burleigh and Peters 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Payne2">Payne 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-COSEWIC1">COSEWIC 2004</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bent2">Bent 1920</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Dickerman1">Dickerman 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth (1993a)</xref> proposed a unique vocal type for Newfoundland (&ldquo;type 8&rdquo;) based on a sound recording from a single individual.Red Crossbills were considered to be common in Newfoundland through the first three-quarters of the twentieth century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Peters1">Peters and Burleigh 1951</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Erskine1">Erskine 1977</xref>). However, Christmas Bird Count data suggest that Red Crossbill numbers on the island declined precipitously in the 1970s, possibly due to habitat reduction and seed competition with, or nest predation by, the Red Squirrel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tamiasciurus hudsonicus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman1">Benkman 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-COSEWIC1">COSEWIC 2004</xref>). Squirrels were introduced to the Northern Peninsula in 1963 and 1964, and subsequently spread throughout the island through natural and deliberate human-aided dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Northcott1">Northcott 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Payne1">Payne 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Goudie1">Goudie 1978</xref>). Because of the population decline and assumption that the subspecies <italic>L. c. percna</italic> represents a biological entity and is restricted to Newfoundland, the subspecies is currently listed as Endangered at both Provincial (Newfoundland and Labrador) and Federal (Canada) levels. We studied vocalizations to determine how many and which vocal types of Red Crossbill are present in Newfoundland.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Young2">Young et al. (2012)</xref> reported a form of class I call from the Red Crossbill in Newfoundland that may not occur elsewhere in North America and on that basis reasoned that <italic>L. c. percna</italic> persists in Newfoundland. Here we confirm and extend that report through acoustic and statistical analyses of Newfoundland sound recordings, and compare Newfoundland calls with samples from continental North America and Europe.We use the term <italic>call class</italic> to refer to a set of structurally similar calls; together these sets constitute a species' vocal repertoire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Marler1">Marler 2004</xref>). Names used for Red Crossbill call classes sometimes have been onomatopoetic (e.g., <italic>chip</italic> or <italic>dyip</italic>) or given in vague, functional or interpretive terms (e.g., &ldquo;social&rdquo; or &ldquo;threat&rdquo; calls). Other names suggest specific contexts of use (e.g., &ldquo;flight&rdquo; and &ldquo;traveling&rdquo; calls). We avoid the use of such names because (a) onomatopoetic names differ across observer languages and cultures, (b) functional or interpretive names usually suggest single functions that have not been rigorously established, and (c) most context-based names imply only single contexts of use. An example of the latter is the call class analyzed in this paper, widely referred to as &ldquo;flight call.&rdquo; This type of call class is given by Red Crossbills in varied circumstances, only some of which include flight: in perched flocks prior to or in flight; in flocks that are taking flight after being flushed by a large bird; by males flying to the nest to provision the incubating female and then flying away from the nest to join a foraging flock; during interactions between mates; while foraging or perching in trees; or during pauses between song bouts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth1">Groth 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Smith2">Smith et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Hynes1">Hynes 2013</xref>). In this paper we refer to the &ldquo;flight call&rdquo; (&ldquo;contact call&rdquo; of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Sewall1">Sewall 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Sewall2">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Sewall3">Sewall and Hahn 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Smith2">Smith et al. 2012</xref>) simply as class I. We also describe call classes II and III (&ldquo;excitement&rdquo; and &ldquo;chitter&rdquo; calls, respectively, of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>) below; they are analyzed in more detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Hynes1">Hynes (2013)</xref>.We recorded class I calls from 83 adults across 10 sites in Newfoundland, from February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t01">Table 1</xref>). Seven sites were in urban areas: Clarenville and Glovertown in central Newfoundland; and Conception Bay South, Goulds, South River, Upper Gullies, and Whitbourne on the Avalon Peninsula in eastern Newfoundland. Many recordings at these sites were made near bird feeders on private property or in nearby forest. Forest habitat was mainly mature boreal forest; black spruce (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picea mariana</named-content></italic>) and balsam fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Abies balsamea</named-content></italic>) were the dominant conifers. White spruce (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picea glauca</named-content></italic>) and American larch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larix laricina</named-content></italic>) were also common, and crossbills were observed feeding in both of these species. In Clarenville, Glovertown, and Whitbourne, cultivated pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus</named-content></italic> spp.) was present and crossbills also foraged there. The three remaining sites were in or near wilderness areas: La Manche (Avalon Peninsula; dominated by black spruce and balsam fir), West Brook Ecological Reserve, and Howley. At the latter two sites, we recorded crossbills in forests dominated by red pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus resinosa</named-content></italic>).Summary of metadata for Red Crossbills seen or recorded in Newfoundland, February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011.We recorded calls with a Fostex FR-LE2 field recorder, a Telinga Pro Series microphone and a 570 mm Telinga parabola. Vocalizations were sampled at 44.1 Hz and digitized at 16 bits. To augment our Newfoundland sample and extend geographic and species coverage, we obtained &gt;25 hr of archived recordings from other sources: Avian Vocalizations Center, Michigan State University (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://avocet.zoology.msu.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://avocet.zoology.msu.edu/</ext-link>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bergmann1">Bergmann et al. (2008)</xref>; Borror Laboratory of Bioacoustics, Ohio State University; Constantine and The Sound Approach (2006); Macaulay Library, Cornell University; Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, University of California, Berkeley; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb (2000)</xref>; and xeno-canto (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xeno-canto.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.xeno-canto.org/</ext-link>).We classified call classes from our Newfoundland sample jointly on the basis of context (e.g., whether the bird was in flight or foraging), audile qualities (e.g., soft versus loud) and appearance as spectrograms, as is usual in descriptive studies. For archived recordings, vocal types and call classes were identified and labeled based on published records (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>) or corresponding track metadata. To verify the classifications of vocal types, we also compared class I calls across Newfoundland, mainland North America, and Europe with discriminant analysis (see below). We selected and measured a subset of 245 class I calls from 31 individuals from the archived recordings made outside Newfoundland. Our original Newfoundland field recordings comprised 890 calls from 83 individual birds. Recordings will be deposited in the Macaulay Library, Cornell University.We analyzed samples with Praat version 5.3.04 software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Boersma1">Boersma and Weenink 2011</xref>). We measured acoustic variables directly from fundamental frequencies using Praat's autocorrelation algorithm. This technique improves measurement accuracy by obviating the need to measure variables manually on spectrograms, which vary due to signal amplitude and analysis settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Zollinger1">Zollinger et al. 2012</xref>). We measured fundamental frequency (f<sub>0</sub>; this was the dominant frequency component of class I&ndash;III calls) with pitch tracking and measurement tools in Praat's SoundEditor window (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We measured 9 variables on each call: <italic>Frequency at start</italic>, <italic>Frequency at end</italic>, <italic>Minimal frequency</italic>, <italic>Maximal frequency</italic>, <italic>Frequency at maximal intensity</italic>, <italic>Mean frequency</italic>, <italic>Duration</italic>, <italic>Maximal intensity</italic>, and <italic>Intensity at maximal frequency</italic>.Examples of acoustic variables used in the study for Red Crossbill call classes I&ndash;III. (<bold>A</bold>) The fundamental frequency (f<sub>0</sub>) of a class I call is shown. Variables were taken from frequency contours (in blue) that were computed with Praat 5.3.04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Boersma1">Boersma and Weenink 2011</xref>). The time interval between successive samples (shown as blue points) along the contour was set at 0.0005 s. Frequency change points (FCPs) were quantified by counting the number of directional frequency changes along the call's frequency contour (see Methods). The variable <italic>Mean frequency</italic> was computed as the sum of frequency points divided by the total number of sample points. (<bold>B</bold>) Graphical illustration of how <italic>Maximal intensity</italic> (I1) and <italic>Frequency at maximal intensity</italic> (F5) were measured via spectral slice analysis in Praat. F1: <italic>Frequency at start</italic>; F2: <italic>Frequency at end</italic>; F3: <italic>Minimal frequency</italic>; F4: <italic>Maximal frequency</italic>; F6: <italic>Mean frequency</italic>; D1: <italic>Duration</italic>; and I2: <italic>Intensity at maximal frequency</italic>.We extracted time-normalized frequency contours to further explore call variation. Time normalization was performed by sampling the extracted contours for a fixed number (64) of frequency points at equal time intervals within each call (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-McCowan1">McCowan 1995</xref>). To quantify frequency modulation (FM), we counted the number of directional frequency changes &gt;50 Hz in magnitude (frequency change points, FCPs) along the frequency contour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f01">Figure 1</xref>A).To determine temporal patterning of calls from Newfoundland birds, we manually measured 556 inter-call intervals on spectrograms from 36 individuals.To test for microgeographic trends in class I calls, we used nested random-effects models to estimate variance components attributable to variation among Newfoundland recording sites (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 10), individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 83), and calls of individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 890). Individuals were not banded in this study but crossbills at all sites appeared to consist of single cohesive groups; individual and site were assumed to be nested random effects. Variance components were estimated with the &ldquo;varcomp&rdquo; function from a fitted &ldquo;lme&rdquo; object using the packages &ldquo;ape&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Paradis1">Paradis et al. 2004</xref>) and &ldquo;nlme&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Pinheiro1">Pinheiro et al. 2011</xref>) in R (version 2.14.0; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2011</xref>). Variables were not independent so we used scores from principal components analysis (PCA; package MASS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Venables1">Venables and Ripley 2002</xref>) as dependent variables. Principal components (PCs) with eigenvalues &gt;1 (Kaiser-Guttman criterion; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Jackson1">Jackson 1991</xref>) were used in the nested random effects models and provided new uncorrelated variables that contained most of the variation in the original dataset.We compared class I calls across Newfoundland, mainland North America, and Europe with discriminant analysis (DA; package MASS). PCs from a PCA on calls were used as synthetic uncorrelated variables for the DA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Jombart1">Jombart et al. 2010</xref>), using the selection criteria described above. Individual means of call variables were used to test whether individuals could be correctly classified to vocal type. A leave-one-out cross-validation (LOOCV, within DA) technique was used for constructing and validating the classification model. LOOCV is an iterative process that creates jackknifed estimates, where a sample of <italic>n</italic>&minus;1 attempts to predict the class of the remaining sample.The basic structure of class I calls from Newfoundland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>A) was similar to that of calls in Europe and elsewhere in North America (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">2</xref>C). Newfoundland calls were brief (&sim;50 ms) tones with a dominant frequency of &sim;2&ndash;5 kHz (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t02">Table 2</xref>); were typically uttered in series (median inter-call interval &sim;164 msec); often had 3&ndash;4 harmonics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f03">Figure 3</xref>A); and sometimes exhibited biphonation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Tyson1">Tyson et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figures 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f03">3</xref>A). Amplitude commonly peaked &sim;midway through the call (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f03">Figure 3</xref>A) but varied across calls, presumably in part because of orientation of the calling bird to the microphone. Class I calls varied little within individuals and only one bird showed substantial variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f03">Figure 3</xref>B). At least three adult male&ndash;female pairs produced pair-specific calls (i.e. call matching &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Mundinger1">Mundinger 1970</xref>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>A).(<bold>A</bold>) Class I calls of 78 individual adult Red Crossbills (one spectrogram per individual; fundamental frequencies are shown; harmonics, where present, are not displayed because they were at frequencies &gt;6 kHz) recorded in Newfoundland February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011, have a common structural plan but vary considerably in frequency modulation. The sample is similar to some European samples (<bold>B</bold>; 3 individuals shown) but was acoustically distinct from 9 other North American vocal types (<bold>C</bold>: T1&ndash;T7, T9 and T10). Spectrograms in (<bold>A</bold>) may represent calls of <italic>L. c. percna</italic>. Examples of three presumed male&ndash;female (&ldquo;m&ndash;f&rdquo;) pairs are labeled; some examples differ across individuals at the beginning or end of the call and may represent grading (marked with arrows). Triangles mark examples of non-linear phenomena.Descriptive statistics (grand mean &plusmn; SD, range in parentheses) for variables measured on 1,135 Red Crossbill calls recorded in Newfoundland, February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011. The calls may represent <italic>L. c. percna</italic>.(<bold>A</bold>) Waveforms and spectrograms of class I calls from four individual Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland (from left to right: Goulds, August 2, 2011; West Brook Ecological Reserve, June 30, 2011; South River, June 1, 2011; Howley, May 2, 2011). Triangles (waveforms) and arrows (spectrograms) mark intensity peaks and biphonations, respectively; vertical bars separate individuals. (<bold>B</bold>) One bird recorded in Clarenville (June 27, 2011) expressed call variation across successive calls (natural call sequence is shown; harmonics are not displayed because they were &gt;6 kHz in frequency). (<bold>C</bold>) Frequency contours were similar across birds (recorded in Newfoundland, February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011) with the same number of frequency-change points (FCPs) within class I calls. Time-normalized frequency contours for FCP classes are based on grand means of individual birds (<italic>n</italic> adults is indicated). Red lines connect mean FCP values; black vertical bars represent &plusmn; 1 SD.The presence of marked FCPs in class I calls set most Newfoundland birds apart from mainland North American and European samples. Of 890 Newfoundland calls, 556 (62&percnt;) had 4&ndash;5 FCPs, which appeared M-shaped as spectrograms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f03">Figure 3</xref>C; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Young2">Young et al. 2012</xref>). Calls with fewer or more FCPs often showed graded variation, e.g., parts at the beginning or end of calls were added or omitted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>A); a few of these individuals probably represented other vocal types (see below).A PCA on the individual means of Newfoundland birds identified the first 3 PCs with eigenvalues &gt;1, accounting for 73&percnt; of the variance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t03">Table 3</xref>). Salient variables (i.e. those with loadings &gt;0.40; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Guadagnoli1">Guadagnoli and Velicer 1988</xref>) for the first PC were <italic>Maximal frequency</italic>, <italic>Frequency at maximal intensity</italic>, and <italic>Mean frequency</italic>; salient variables for the second PC were <italic>Frequency at start</italic> and <italic>Duration</italic>.Results of principal components (PCs) analysis based on individual means (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 83) of class I call variables for Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland, mainland North America, and Europe.Most of the variance (52&ndash;71&percnt;) in nested random-effects models on the 3 PCs was explained by variation among individuals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t04">Table 4</xref>). Variation among calls accounted for the second-largest amount (23&ndash;29&percnt;) and variation among sites explained the least (6&ndash;19&percnt;).Individual differences accounted for most variation (52&ndash;71&percnt;) in class I calls of Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland, February 4, 2010&ndash;August 2, 2011. Variance components attributable to recording sites, individuals, and within individuals are shown using the first 3 PCs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t03">Table 3</xref>). Variance components were estimated using nested random effects models (calls within adults within recording site; see text).We identified 5 Newfoundland birds whose calls resembled those of vocal types 2, 4, and 10 from mainland North America (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f04">Figure 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Young1">Young 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>). Hence, 78 of 83 individuals (94&percnt;) in our Newfoundland sample may represent <italic>L. c. percna</italic>. For the pooled sample from all locations, DA based on individual means of acoustic variables correctly classified 89&percnt; of individuals to vocal type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Most (98&percnt;) Newfoundland birds were correctly classified but 5 of 6 European individuals were classified as Newfoundland birds. Vocal types from mainland North America were discriminated well by DA: 86&percnt; of individuals were classified correctly.Multiple kinds of class I calls of Red Crossbill occur in Newfoundland (NF &equals; Newfoundland samples) suggesting the presence of several Red Crossbill vocal types on the island. Examples of similar calls from other individuals from mainland North American localities are included for comparison: vocal type 2 (T2), top two panels; vocal type 4 (T4), third panel from the top; vocal type 10 (T10), bottom panel (for variation in vocal types see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>). Broken vertical bars separate calls from different individuals. Fundamental frequencies are shown; harmonics are not displayed because they were &gt;6 kHz in frequency.Class I calls of Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland differ acoustically from calls recorded elsewhere in North America. This scatterplot shows the first 2 functions of a discriminant analysis on individual means of acoustic variables taken from class I calls from Newfoundland, mainland North America, and Europe. Vocal types are shown in different colors; dots represent individual birds; ellipses represent 95&percnt; confidence intervals for vocal types. Spectrograms show some similarities between calls from Newfoundland and Europe (right side; individuals NF-1 to NF-4 and E-1 to E-4, respectively). Fundamental frequencies are shown; harmonics are not displayed because they were &gt;5 kHz in frequency.We recorded these calls at 9 of 10 recording sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">Figure 6</xref>A). These calls seemed to be elicited by the sudden appearance of different heterospecific animals including Osprey (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pandion haliaetus</named-content></italic>), Blue Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta cristata</named-content></italic>), American Crow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus brachyrhynchos</named-content></italic>), European Starling (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>), and dog (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Canis familiaris</named-content></italic>). In one case, Red Crossbills appeared to use the call as a mobbing signal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>), apparently in response to a low-flying Herring Gull (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Larus argentatus</named-content></italic>). Calls of this class also were also given by one male just before and following an attempt to copulate with a female; were only recorded from perched birds, sometimes by individuals near bird feeders; and were sometimes inserted into song. Class II calls were stereotyped and varied little across individuals or contexts of use. The calls were relatively low in frequency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t02">Table 2</xref>) and showed a distinctive frequency pattern: calls began with an accelerating decline in frequency to a minimum, followed by a decelerating rise in frequency to the end of the call; harmonic stacking typically was present at the frequency minimum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">Figure 6</xref>A). The median inter-call interval was &sim;179 ms. Newfoundland calls differed greatly from mainland North American samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">Figure 6</xref>B) and resembled calls of the Scottish Crossbill (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">L. scotica</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">Figure 6</xref>C) in the pattern of accelerating/decelerating frequency changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">Figure 6</xref>C; patterns of harmonic richness differed however). Calls of this class are widely referred to as &ldquo;excitement&rdquo; or &ldquo;alarm&rdquo; calls (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers2">Summers et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Benkman5">Benkman et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>; &ldquo;toop&rdquo; of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-NethersoleThompson1">Nethersole-Thompson 1975</xref>).(<bold>A</bold>) Class II calls of 10 adult Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland, May 23, 2010&ndash;August 1, 2011 (spectrograms from different individuals are separated by vertical bars). These individuals resembled some European samples (<bold>C</bold>; 3 individuals depicted) but were acoustically distinct from other North American vocal types (<bold>B</bold>; T1&ndash;T5, T10). Like class I calls depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>A, we suggest that class II calls in (<bold>A</bold>) suggest the presence of <italic>L. c. percna</italic> in Newfoundland.These calls were recorded from at least 30 individuals across 9 recording sites. Some individuals gave these calls in rapid series while pivoting or lifting into flight. They often were accompanied by &ldquo;soft whirring of wings&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>:65) as birds fed and moved within conifers or repositioned themselves at bird feeders; they were never given by birds in full flight. Class III calls had weak or no harmonics and most had simple patterns of FM, such as rises and falls in frequency with one to several FCPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f07">Figure 7</xref>), and they were generally briefer and softer than calls of classes I and II (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-t02">Table 2</xref>). Class III calls were uttered singly or in series of up to 6; the median inter-call interval was &sim;154 ms. Most workers refer to these as &ldquo;chitter&rdquo; calls (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>).Examples of class III calls from 30 adult Red Crossbills recorded in Newfoundland, May 24, 2010&ndash;August 1, 2011 (spectrograms from different individuals separated by vertical bars). Fundamental frequencies are shown; harmonics are not displayed because they were &gt;7 kHz in frequency.We determined that a distinct kind of call is the most common form of class I call (&ldquo;flight call&rdquo;) of Red Crossbills on the island of Newfoundland. These calls signify the presence of a vocal type that is different from those in mainland North America and may represent the morphologically recognized subspecies <italic>L. c. percna</italic>.Class I and II calls of Red Crossbills have been used as markers for different vocal types (or even different species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Robb1">Robb 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers2">Summers et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Forschler1">F&ouml;rschler and Kalko 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin 2010</xref>). Class I and II calls in our Newfoundland sample of Red Crossbill differ from other described vocal types in having a marked quasi-rhythmic FM (quantified by the number of FCPs) and a distinct declining&ndash;rising pattern of FM, respectively. Further, quantitative features of the class I and II samples from Newfoundland birds differ little across contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Hynes1">Hynes 2013</xref>). Therefore we suggest that most Newfoundland birds represent a different vocal type than occurs elsewhere in North America. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Groth2">Groth (1993a)</xref>, vocal type 8 may be the appropriate name to apply, but his 1981 sample from Newfoundland may represent a class II call. If the calls do not represent <italic>L. c. percna</italic>, they must represent a previously undescribed Atlantic Canadian vocal type of Red Crossbill, although recent body measurements of Newfoundland birds fall within the known range for <italic>L. c. percna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Young2">Young et al. 2012</xref>). Several birds also uttered song motifs that differ from those of Red Crossbills in mainland North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Hynes1">Hynes 2013</xref>).Our sample of Newfoundland Red Crossbill vocalizations may represent only a part of a widely distributed vocal type of Red Crossbill in Canada's Atlantic provinces (e.g., Cape Breton Island), and hence <italic>L. c. percna</italic> (assuming that this taxon represents a biological entity) may not be endemic to the island of Newfoundland. To explore this possibility, further sound recordings are needed from western and southwestern Newfoundland, eastern Canada, and the Maritime Provinces, and should be coupled with assessment of morphological characters.Our Newfoundland sample included some individuals whose class I calls resembled known mainland vocal types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f04">Figure 4</xref>), suggesting that other North American vocal types occur on the island. A few other calls from the Newfoundland sample also appeared similar to vocal type 2 (see the first 3 individuals of the seventh row in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figure 2</xref>A), but uttered class II calls that were acoustically similar to other Newfoundland samples. Class II calls may be more sensitive indicators of differentiation than class I calls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Summers2">Summers et al. 2002</xref>), and deserve attention in future studies.Crossbills appear to exhibit assortative flocking with shared vocalizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Smith2">Smith et al. 2012</xref>). Therefore, variation among flocks (approximated by recording sites) should exceed among-individual variation if our Newfoundland samples contain more than one vocal type. Our analyses disclosed only minor variation among recording sites and most variation among individuals, suggesting that one vocal type dominated Newfoundland samples. Vocalizations of some Newfoundland birds were extremely similar even over hundreds of kilometers. Many class I calls that we recorded are similar to those that have been recorded from Newfoundland Red Crossbills dating back to 2005 (this study; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Young2">Young et al. 2012</xref>).Calls from European and Newfoundland birds generally differ from one another (e.g., vocal types A&ndash;D, F, and X as described by Constantine and The Sound Approach 2006), although some class I and II calls of Common Crossbills (from mainland Europe) and crossbills from Scotland resemble some Newfoundland samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-f06">6</xref>). Other acoustic similarities occur between Old World and New World crossbills (e.g., North American vocal type 1 and Parrot Crossbill, <italic>Loxia pytyopsittacus</italic>). The systematic significance of such similarities cannot be appraised in isolation from genetic information, in our opinion. Genetic analysis suggests that Newfoundland Red Crossbills differ from European but not from other North American birds (based on analysis of part of the mtDNA control region from study skin samples; E. A. Perry, personal communication). These findings are consistent with limited genetic differentiation among North American vocal types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Parchman1">Parchman et al. 2006</xref>) and monophyly within the Old World and New World groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Questiau1">Questiau et al. 1999</xref>), and suggests that vocal similarities between Newfoundland and European Red Crossbills are not of systematic significance. The similarities may represent convergence as a byproduct of morphological adaptation (e.g., bill size) or as an adaptive response to similar habitat acoustics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Slabbekoorn1">Slabbekoorn and Smith 2002</xref>).Class III calls have not been well studied in the Red Crossbill; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Irwin1">Irwin (2010)</xref> suggested that they might be useful in systematics. Class III calls in our Newfoundland recordings varied greatly, which suggests they may not be useful in systematic studies in all cases. Such high variation may represent grading, which is common in short-range signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Green1">Green and Marler 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-421-Bradbury1">Bradbury and Vehrencamp 2011</xref>). Further studies would be informative about the communicative significance and systematic value of this call class in the Red Crossbill.We thank B. Rodrigues, G. Stroud, and D. Fifield for allowing us to use their original tape recordings. We also acknowledge the many recordists who have contributed Red Crossbill recordings to publicly accessible archives such as those listed in Methods. We thank the Macaulay Library (Cornell Lab of Ornithology) for access to their collection and associated metadata. We also thank C. Cicero and R. Bowie at the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology for providing access to Groth's recordings. We are grateful to L. Rees for his advice, discussion, and field assistance. We also thank many people who reported Red Crossbill sightings to us during our study, including C. Barrett, D. Burton, K. Butler, R. Cashin, L. Crisby-Whittle, R. Cox, P. Drover, J. Gosse, K. Knowles, T. Leonard, B. Mactavish, B. Rodrigues, P. Thomas, A. Tock, J. Wells, and D. Whittaker. K. Tulk and other staff at Terra Nova National Park provided most funding and logistical support. Other support was from the Natural Sciences and Engineering and Research Council of Canada (Discovery Grant to E.H.M.). Finally we thank C. Benkman, D. Innes, I. Jones, W. Montevecchi, R. Summers, and C. Walsh for reviewing manuscript drafts.