 Effect of parasite-to-host egg ratio on egg rejection by a Brown-headed Cowbird host  Getting rid of the cuckoo   Cuculus canorus   egg: Why do hosts delay rejection?  Evidence for egg discrimination preceding failed rejection attempts in a small cuckoo host  Simultaneous viewing of own and parasitic eggs is not required for egg rejection by a cuckoo host  Do clay eggs attract predators to artificial nests?  Host intra-clutch variation, cuckoo egg matching and egg rejection by Great Reed Warblers  A recoverable cost of brood parasitism during the nestling stage of the American Robin (  Turdus migratorius  ): Implications for the evolution of egg rejection behaviors in a host of the Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  )  High repeatability of egg rejection in response to experimental brood parasitism in the American Robin (  Turdus migratorius  )  Spectral tuning and perceptual differences do not explain the rejection of brood parasitic eggs by American Robins (  Turdus migratorius  )  An experimental study of co-evolution between the cuckoo,   Cuculus canorus  , and its hosts. I. Host egg discrimination  Hatching asynchrony, nestling competition, and the cost of interspecific brood parasitism  Experimental shift in hosts' acceptance threshold of inaccurate-mimic brood parasite eggs  Desertion of nests parasitized by cowbirds: Have Clay-coloured Sparrows evolved an anti-parasite defence?  Notes on the nesting habits of the American Robin (  Turdus migratorius   L.)  The determination of clutch size in birds. A review  Variation in host response to brood parasitism reflects evolutionary differences and not phenotypic plasticity  A meta-analysis of the impact of parasitism by the Brown-headed Cowbird on its hosts  Rejection of cuckoo eggs in relation to host age: A possible evolutionary equilibrium  Constraints on egg discrimination and cuckoo&ndash;host co-evolution  Discordancy or template-based recognition? Dissecting the cognitive basis of the rejection of foreign eggs in hosts of avian brood parasites  Increased host tolerance of multiple cuckoo eggs leads to higher fledging success of the brood parasite  Foreign egg retention by avian hosts in repeated brood parasitism: Why do rejecters accept?  Cowbirds, conservation, and coevolution: Potential misconceptions and directions for future research  Phenotypic plasticity in Common Grackles (  Quiscalus quiscula  ) in response to repeated brood parasitism  Intraclutch variation in egg appearance constrains rejection of Brown-headed Cowbird eggs in Common Grackles  Mechanism of egg recognition in the Great-tailed Grackle  Correlates of egg rejection in hosts of the Brown-headed Cowbird  Moorhens have an internal representation of their own eggs  Video recording reveals the method of ejection of Brown-headed Cowbird eggs and no cost in American Robins and Gray Catbirds  Verhalten von singvogeln bei aenderung des geleges  Mechanisms of avian egg recognition: Possible learned and innate factors  An experimental and teleonomic investigation of avian brood parasitism  Mechanisms of avian egg-recognition: Do birds know their own eggs?  Cowbird parasitism and egg recognition of the Northern Oriole  Mechanisms of avian egg recognition: Additional evidence for learned components  Mechanisms of avian egg recognition: Which egg parameters elicit responses by rejecter species?  A model system for coevolution: Avian brood parasitism  American Robin (  Turdus migratorius  )  Do first-time breeding females imprint on their own eggs?  Rejection of artificial cuckoo (  Cuculus canorus  ) eggs in relation to variation in egg appearance among Reed Warblers (  Acrocephalus scirpaceus  )  Parasitic cowbirds may defeat host defense by causing rejecters to misimprint on cowbird eggs  Influence of shape on egg discrimination in American Robins and Gray Catbirds  Multiple parasitism of the Red-winged Blackbird: Further experimental evidence of evolutionary lag in a common host of the Brown-headed Cowbird  Breeding behavior and nesting of the Eastern Robin  American Robins (  Turdus migratorius  ) typically eject parasitic Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ) eggs from their nests. In order to successfully remove parasitic eggs, robins must first differentiate between their eggs and foreign eggs, and then remove the foreign egg(s). Our primary objectives were to determine (1) whether the robins reject cowbird eggs because they are in the minority (&ldquo;discordancy hypothesis&rdquo;) or because robins have learned the appearance of their own eggs regardless of whether they form the majority of eggs in the nest (&ldquo;true egg recognition hypothesis&rdquo;); and (2) whether the robin's ability to recognize its eggs and reject parasitic eggs was affected by the parasite-to-host egg ratio. We added artificial cowbird eggs to robin nests to create 3 treatments: (1) a majority of robin eggs, (2) an equal number of robin and cowbird eggs, and (3) a majority of cowbird eggs. Parasite-to-host egg ratios were between 1:3 and 3:1. Robins ejected all cowbird eggs at 88&percnt; of nests (51 of 58). The frequency of ejection did not differ between the 3 treatments, indicating that robins typically recognized their eggs regardless of whether they were the majority egg type, providing strong support for the true egg recognition hypothesis. However, the risk of ejection for the artificial cowbird eggs was greater as the ratio of cowbird to host eggs increased, which suggests that robins respond adaptively to the increased fitness costs of multiple parasitism. Finally, the risk of ejection of our artificial cowbird eggs was greater later in the nesting season. Because many individuals were exposed to their eggs for the first time early in the season, this result suggests that robins learn to recognize their eggs during their initial nesting attempt.    Turdus migratorius   t&iacute;picamente expulsa huevos par&aacute;sitos de   Molothrus ater   de sus nidos. Para remover exitosamente los huevos par&aacute;sitos, los individuos de   T. migratorius   deben primero diferenciar sus huevos de los huevos extranjeros, y luego remover el o los huevos extranjeros. En este estudio, tuvimos dos objetivos principales: determinar (1) si   T. migratorius   expulsa los huevos de   M. ater   debido a que son una minor&iacute;a (&lsquo;hip&oacute;tesis de discordancia') o debido a que   T. migratorius   ha aprendido la apariencia de sus propios huevos independientemente de si representan o no la mayor&iacute;a de los huevos del nido (&lsquo;hip&oacute;tesis de reconocimiento del huevo verdadero'); y (2) si la habilidad de   T. migratorius   de reconocer sus propios huevos y de expulsar los huevos par&aacute;sitos estuvo afectada por la proporci&oacute;n de huevos par&aacute;sito-hospedador. Adicionamos huevos artificiales de   M. ater   a los nidos de   T. migratorius   para crear tres tratamientos: (1) una mayor&iacute;a de huevos de   T. migratorius  , (2) un n&uacute;mero igual de huevos de   T. migratorius   y   M. ater  , y (3) una mayor&iacute;a de huevos de   M. ater  , y proporciones de huevos par&aacute;sito-hospedador de 1:3 a 3:1. Los individuos de   T. migratorius   expulsaron todos los huevos de   M. ater   en 88&percnt; de los nidos (51 de 58). La frecuencia de expulsi&oacute;n no vari&oacute; entre los tres tratamientos, indicando que   T. migratorius   t&iacute;picamente reconoci&oacute; sus huevos independientemente de si ellos fueron el tipo de huevo mayoritario, brindando un fuerte apoyo a la &lsquo;hip&oacute;tesis de reconocimiento del huevo verdadero'. Sin embrago, el riesgo de expulsi&oacute;n de los huevos artificiales de   M. ater   fue mayor a medida que la proporci&oacute;n de huevos de   M. ater   en relaci&oacute;n a los del hospedador aument&oacute;, sugiriendo que los individuos de   T. migratorius   responden de modo adaptativo al aumento de los costos en la adecuaci&oacute;n biol&oacute;gica del parasitismo m&uacute;ltiple. Finalmente, el riesgo de expulsi&oacute;n de nuestros huevos artificiales de   M. ater   fue mayor m&aacute;s tarde en la estaci&oacute;n de nidificaci&oacute;n. Debido a que muchos individuos estuvieron expuestos a sus huevos por primera vez a comienzos de la estaci&oacute;n, este resultado sugiere que   T. migratorius   aprende a reconocer sus huevos durante su intento de nidificaci&oacute;n inicial.   Palabras clave:  expulsi&oacute;n de huevos,   Molothrus ater  , parasitismo de nidada, parasitismo m&uacute;ltiple,   Turdus migratorius    The Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ; hereafter &ldquo;cowbird&rdquo;) is a ubiquitous brood parasite in North America, laying its eggs in the nests of &gt;240 host species ( Lowther 2012 ). Brood parasitism typically reduces host fitness ( Lorenzana and Sealy 1999 ,  Hauber 2003 ,  Peer et al. 2013 ), and many host species have evolved specialized defenses to minimize the costs of parasitism ( Rothstein 1990 ). One of the most efficacious host defenses is the rejection of cowbird eggs ( Rothstein 1975a ,  Peer and Sealy 2004 ). However, species that reject brood-parasite eggs must distinguish the foreign egg from their own and may do so by means of 3 mechanisms, the first 2 of which are cognitive mechanisms. The first of these mechanisms is rejection via discordancy. These hosts do not recognize their eggs or the parasite egg per se, but simply reject the egg type that is in the minority ( Rensch 1925 ,  Rothstein 1974 ,  1975b ,  Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2010 ). The disadvantage of using this mechanism to reject foreign eggs is that when a host is multiply parasitized, its own eggs may be discordant and will be ejected from the nest.  The second mechanism is called &ldquo;true egg recognition,&rdquo; whereby hosts rely on a mental template that enables them to learn the appearance of their own eggs and reject eggs that are sufficiently different, regardless of whether they are the majority egg type in the nest ( Rothstein 1974 ,  1978 ,  Peer and Sealy 2001 ,  Hauber et al. 2006 ,  Strausberger and Rothstein 2009 ). The amount of time required for a host to learn the appearance of its eggs may vary, depending on the degree of intraclutch variation it demonstrates, and this variation may also increase the host's tolerance of foreign eggs ( Lotem et al. 1995 ,  Peer et al. 2010 ). Occasionally, hosts misimprint on parasite eggs that are laid early in the nest cycle and reject their own eggs ( Rothstein 1974 ). This may be a strategy employed by cowbirds to exploit this learning mechanism and to increase the chances that their eggs will be accepted ( Strausberger and Rothstein 2009 ).  A third mechanism for egg recognition is minimization of intraclutch egg variation. Hosts that have been subjected to brood parasitism should evolve clutches with minimal intraclutch variation in appearance, facilitating recognition of the parasitic egg (Davies and Brooke 1989,  Stokke et al. 1999 ; but see  Cherry et al. 2007 ,  Abernathy and Peer 2014 ). Multiple parasitism with nonmimetic eggs should also lead to increased rejection of foreign eggs because of the increased intraclutch variation this creates ( Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2009 ).  Only 10&percnt; of North American hosts reject cowbird eggs, and among these rejecters is the American Robin (  Turdus migratorius  ; hereafter &ldquo;robin&rdquo;), which rejects close to 100&percnt; of cowbird eggs ( Peer and Sealy 2004 ,  Peer and Rothstein 2010 ,  Croston and Hauber 2014b ,  Kuehn et al. 2014 ). Robins typically eject cowbird eggs by grasping them with their bills, but they also occasionally peck them despite the risk of damage to their own eggs ( Rasmussen et al. 2009 ). To eject a parasitic egg from its nest, a robin must first recognize which egg(s) should be ejected. Robin eggs are immaculate blue and are larger than cowbird eggs (see below), whereas cowbird eggs have a white background with brown and gray spots. Although robin and cowbird eggs are readily discernible to humans, robin eggs appear more similar to cowbird eggs when viewed from the perspective of the avian eye ( Croston and Hauber 2014c ).  Rothstein (1982)  suggested that robins distinguish their own eggs from cowbird eggs by focusing on the 3 parameters of size, background color, and spotting pattern, in addition to shape ( Underwood and Sealy 2006 ), but reject eggs only if they differ from robin eggs in at least 2 of these parameters. In this manner, they avoid rejecting their own odd eggs that may differ in one of these characteristics ( Rothstein 1982 ).  In the present study, we first examined the egg recognition behavior of robins by subjecting them to 3 treatments in which the clutches contained either a majority of robin eggs, a majority of cowbird eggs, or equal numbers of both. The true egg recognition, discordancy, and clutch uniformity hypotheses generate different predictions when hosts are confronted with single versus multiple parasite eggs ( Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2009 ). If robins display true egg recognition, they should eject all cowbird eggs placed in their nest, regardless of which egg type is in the majority. On the other hand, if rejection is based on discordancy, robins should simply eject the minority egg type ( Rothstein 1978 ). Rejection based on clutch uniformity is not likely to be the mechanism used by robins, because, like most members of the family Turdidae, they lay immaculate blue eggs with minimal intraclutch variation. If minimal intraclutch variation evolved in response to cowbird parasitism, rejection should be a trait common to the majority of the Turdidae, yet relatively few thrushes reject foreign eggs ( Peer and Sealy 2004 ).  Second, we examined the effect of the ratio of cowbird to robin eggs on the ejection behavior of robins. Higher numbers of cowbird eggs in robin nests are likely to decrease their fitness. Thus, robins should be more likely to eject cowbird eggs from nests (or eject them more rapidly) with higher parasite-to-host egg ratios.  Finally, we examined the development of egg recognition by robins over the course of the breeding season. The earliest-breeding individuals may have nested in a previous season, are familiar with their egg appearance and variation (e.g.,  Peer et al. 2010 ), and should be more likely to reject foreign eggs ( Lotem et al. 1992 ). Alternatively, later-nesting birds may have nested earlier in the current season and remember their eggs from the previous clutch ( Petrie et al. 2009 ,  Strausberger and Rothstein 2009 ). We predicted that experienced birds would always express rejection behavior, but that naive birds tending their first nest would be less likely to reject cowbird eggs from their nest, or may require more time to reject. If there is a difference in the expression of egg rejection between naive and experienced birds, there should be a seasonal increase in rejection reflecting the higher proportion of naive birds nesting at the beginning of the season.  Artificial eggs mimicking those of cowbirds and robins were formed from modeling clay (Sculpey Original; Polyform, Elk Grove Village, Illinois, USA) and baked ( Bayne and Hobson 1999 ). Artificial cowbird eggs averaged 22.2 &plusmn; 0.3 &times; 16.9 &plusmn; 0.5 mm (subsample  n  &equals; 20; all measurements are presented as means &plusmn; SD); real cowbird eggs average 21.5 &times; 16.2 mm ( Bent 1958 ). Artificial robin eggs averaged 29.5 &plusmn; 0.5 &times; 21.7 &plusmn; 0.7 mm (subsample  n  &equals; 7); real ones measure 28.1 &times; 20.0 mm ( Bent 1949 ). Eggs were painted with acrylic all-purpose water-based paint (DecoArt, Stanford, Kentucky, USA) and sprayed with a clear acrylic gloss (Krylon Indoor/Outdoor; Sherwin-Williams, Cleveland, Ohio, USA). This acrylic paint and gloss increased the detectability of pecks inflicted by the robins.  Nests were found throughout Charleston and Mattoon, Illinois (Coles County), USA, during May and June of 2010 ( n  &equals; 44) and April of 2011 ( n  &equals; 27). Areas were visited only once per year to avoid testing the same birds again. Also, because robins tend to return to the same nesting location each year ( Young 1955 ), different locations within the study area were used in each year. Every nest was assigned a Julian date, when an experiment was initiated. This allowed us to combine both years of data to assess the development of rejection behavior in first-time nesters. Correctly differentiating yearling from adult American Robins is difficult ( Howell 1942 ), and we did not capture adults. Therefore, the number of days into the nesting season was used as an alternative method of assessing the experience level of birds.  The first nest found at the start of the study was randomly assigned a treatment of &ldquo;majority robin,&rdquo; &ldquo;equal,&rdquo; or &ldquo;majority cowbird.&rdquo; After manipulations, majority robin nests had more robin eggs than cowbird eggs, nests in the equal treatment group had an equal number of cowbird and robin eggs, and majority cowbird nests had more cowbird than robin eggs. All subsequent nests were assigned a treatment sequentially. To allow robins the opportunity to learn to recognize their own eggs, only nests that contained at least 2 eggs were used in our manipulations. Manipulations were conducted during the laying and incubation stages of the nest cycle; therefore, individuals whose nests were manipulated during incubation may have had more time to learn the appearance of their eggs than those whose nests were manipulated during the laying stage.  When manipulating clutches, the assigned treatment and number of eggs found in the nest determined the exact manipulation. To mimic natural parasitism as closely as possible, the total number of eggs in the nest was never increased by more than 1. Because the number of eggs initially found in a nest was variable, the number of robin eggs removed and the number of cowbird eggs added varied accordingly; more than 1 robin egg was removed in some cases to achieve the desired ratio. For example, if a nest assigned a &ldquo;majority cowbird&rdquo; treatment was found with 3 robin eggs, 3 cowbird eggs would replace 2 of the robin eggs. After manipulation, the total number of eggs would have been increased from 3 to 4, and the resulting ratio would be 3 cowbird eggs to 1 robin egg. If that same nest was given the &ldquo;equal&rdquo; treatment, 1 robin egg would be removed and 2 cowbird eggs would be added, resulting in 2 robin and 2 cowbird eggs after manipulation. This protocol created parasite-to-host egg ratios that varied from 1:3 to 3:1. As a control, single robin eggs were replaced with artificial robin eggs in 8 nests. After manipulation, nests were checked at ~24-hr intervals for 5 days. Nests that contained cowbird eggs on the fifth day were considered to have accepted the parasitism, and those from which the cowbird egg had been removed were considered rejections ( Rothstein 1975a ). Desertions were not considered rejections because nests are deserted for numerous reasons and it is often difficult to ascertain the proximate cause ( Rothstein 1975a ,  Hill and Sealy 1994 ,  Peer and Rothstein 2010 ). Robins typically eject foreign eggs ( Croston and Hauber 2014b ), but low levels of desertion have been reported in experimentally parasitized nests, and it is unclear whether these are responses to parasitism or to some other disturbance ( Rothstein 1975a ,  Kuehn et al. 2014 ).  A motion-detecting color video camera (Sony Super HAD, 580-line color bullet camera, 3.6-mm lens) was used to observe the initial response to cowbird parasitism at 2 robin nests in 2011. One artificial cowbird egg was added to each nest, and the camera was attached to a nearby branch or trunk ~30 cm above the nest. The camera was left to record for ~5 hr.  We conducted 2 separate survival analyses using either treatment egg ratio or Julian day as the independent variable. In this context, survival analyses combine the likelihood that an ejection occurred and the latency to that ejection, together represented by a hazard ratio ( Bayne and Hobson 1999 ). The hazard ratio is an estimate of the risk of ejection in response to a predictor variable. This risk estimate will hereafter be referred to as &ldquo;risk of ejection.&rdquo;  Robins exhibited 1 of 4 responses to the eggs placed in their nest: (1) All parasitic eggs were removed, (2) all parasitic eggs were pecked but not removed, (3) some parasitic eggs were pecked but not removed, or (4) no eggs were pecked or removed. These 4 responses were placed into 3 categories: full ejections (no. 1 above), partial ejections (nos. 2 and 3), and acceptance (no. 4). Robins that removed cowbird eggs from their nests were termed &ldquo;full ejections.&rdquo; Alternatively, if eggs were not removed but peck marks were observed, the nest was categorized as a partial ejection. Although both partial and full ejections were included in the survival analysis, only the nests that fully ejected cowbird eggs were analyzed using a Kruskal-Wallis analysis to assess the effect of treatment ratio (number of cowbird eggs per robin egg), overall treatment (majority cowbird, equal, or majority robin), and the number of eggs present at the start of the manipulation on the number of days to ejection. The number of days to ejection was used to assess the ability of robins to recognize foreign eggs and the ability to remove foreign eggs from their nest. This was based on the assumption that the latency to eject is correlated with the birds' ability to recognize and remove foreign eggs (e.g.,  Antonov et al. 2008 ). If ratio affects this ability, there will be varying response times, influenced by differential ability to recognize and eject cowbird eggs.  A total of 71 robin nests were tested, 58 of which were included in the analyses. Thirteen nests were excluded because of depredation ( n  &equals; 3), desertion ( n  &equals; 4;  Table 1 ), or hatching of robin eggs within the 5-day observation period ( n  &equals; 6). No nests were naturally parasitized. Cowbird eggs were fully ejected at 88&percnt; of our nests, and the likelihood of ejection did not differ among our 3 treatments (majority robin, equal, or majority cowbird; Fisher's exact test,  P  &equals; 0.67;  Figure 1 A). In 5 of the 7 nests from which cowbird eggs were not fully ejected, peck marks were observed on at least 1 cowbird egg in the nest ( Table 2 ). However, 2 nests subjected to the equal treatment did not show any damage to the cowbird eggs by the fifth day. The 5 nests that showed evidence of pecking were in either the &ldquo;majority robin&rdquo; or &ldquo;majority cowbird&rdquo; treatments.  Description of events when American Robin nests were deserted following egg manipulations.  ( A ) Likelihood of complete ejection of all artificial cowbird eggs by American Robins for the 3 treatments and ( B ) latency to ejection for all nests with complete ejection of all cowbird eggs for the 3 treatments (&plus; SE); &ldquo;majority robin&rdquo; signifies nests that had more host eggs than parasite eggs, &ldquo;equal&rdquo; signifies nests that had equal numbers of host and parasite eggs, and &ldquo;majority cowbird&rdquo; signifies nests that had more parasite eggs than host eggs. Sample sizes (number of nests) are in parentheses. Nests were checked at 1-day intervals.  Description of events at American Robin nests from which cowbird eggs were partially ejected ( n  &equals; 5) and nests where the cowbird eggs were accepted ( n  &equals; 2).  Across all treatments, 67&percnt; of ejections occurred within the first 24 hr of manipulation ( Figure 2 ). For nests that fully ejected all cowbird eggs, there was no difference in the days to ejection, either among treatment groups (&chi; 2  &equals; 3.87, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.14;  Figure 1 B) or among parasite-to-host egg ratios (&chi; 2  &equals; 4.87, df &equals; 6,  P  &equals; 0.56;  Table 3 ). The number of robin eggs present in the nest at the time of manipulation also had no effect on the latency to ejection (&chi; 2  &equals; 4.31, df &equals; 2,  P  &equals; 0.12). However, when the likelihood of ejection occurring and the latency to ejection were combined as the risk incurred by a cowbird egg using a survival analysis, this risk increased as the nesting season progressed (using the Julian day of manipulation; &chi; 2  &equals; 4.96, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.03), where birds tending nests later in the season were more likely to eject and to eject faster. Also, risk increased with the cowbird-to-robin egg ratio in the nest (&chi; 2  &equals; 6.21, df &equals; 1,  P  &equals; 0.01), indicating that ejection risk was greater for nests with higher proportions of cowbird eggs.  Latency to ejection of artificial cowbird eggs placed in American Robin nests ( n  &equals; 51) in which all parasitic eggs were ejected.  Summary of American Robins' latency to eject artificial cowbird eggs by parasite-to-host egg ratio and treatment group.  Two nests contained damaged robin eggs after the artificial cowbird eggs were ejected. One nest had a parasite-to-host egg ratio of 1:3 and had 2 robin eggs damaged, and the second had a ratio of 1:2 and had 1 robin egg damaged. One of the deserted nests also had a host egg damaged ( Table 1 ).  Video recordings of 2 nests showed variation in response to the cowbird egg. At the first nest (May 12, 2011), an adult robin returned within 2 min 30 s of the manipulation and immediately began pecking at the artificial egg. This continued for 45 s, at which time the robin flew away and then returned in 6 s to grasp the egg in its bill and fly away with it. The second nest was tested and recorded in the same manner ~24 hr later. At this nest, an adult returned to the nest in 3 min and began pecking at the cowbird egg less vigorously. Instead of removing it, the bird pecked several times and then began incubating the eggs. This process happened 6 times throughout the recording period and every time the bird returned to the nest. At one point, both adults perched on the edge of the nest and pecked alternately, and 1 opened its bill in an apparent attempt to grasp the egg. Ultimately, however, they did not remove the artificial cowbird egg but continued with incubation. The cowbird egg was still in the nest after ~5 hr when the video camera was removed. Finally, all 8 artificial robin eggs remained in the control nests, with no evidence of pecking for 5 days.  Our results support the true egg recognition hypothesis that robins recognize their eggs and reject those that are sufficiently different, regardless of whether their eggs are in the minority ( Rothstein 1975b ,  1977 ,  Peer and Sealy 2001 ,  B&aacute;n et al. 2013 ). Robins ejected or pecked at least 1 of the cowbird eggs in all but 2 nests (96&percnt;), and the likelihood of rejection of cowbird eggs was not lower in the majority cowbird egg treatment, as predicted by the discordancy hypothesis ( Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2009 ). This is also evidence against the clutch uniformity hypothesis, which predicts the highest rejection frequencies in nests with equal numbers of host and parasitic eggs ( Mosk&aacute;t et al. 2009 ).  Evidence of egg recognition was also apparent at the 2 nests that were video recorded. One adult ejected a cowbird egg at the first nest, whereas the other pair pecked at the cowbird egg repeatedly, indicating recognition of the cowbird egg as foreign. The bird at the first nest pecked the artificial cowbird egg prior to grasp-ejecting it, and this may be a form of exploratory pecking whereby birds inspect the foreign egg. The lack of pecking on some, but not all, artificial cowbird eggs at 4 nests might also be due to the artificiality of the eggs. If pecking at the first egg did not result in it breaking, the robin may have been discouraged from attempting to destroy the other artificial parasitic eggs. Alternatively, all but 1 of these nests was multiply parasitized, and these could have been young birds not completely familiar with their egg appearance. Indeed, all of the nests with partial ejections were from early in the season in April.  Although recognition was exhibited by most birds, not all birds that recognized their eggs ejected cowbird eggs (also see  Antonov et al. 2009 ). In the video of the second nest, both adult robins pecked the cowbird egg but did not remove it from their nests. This suggests that ejection behavior may develop progressively beyond the initial recognition of foreign eggs. It is also possible that some robins are puncture-ejectors and others may be grasp-ejecters similar to rejecters including the Gray Catbird (  Dumetella carolinensis  ;  Rasmussen et al. 2009 ). Lastly, robin eggs were damaged in 2 nests from which cowbird eggs were rejected, and also in 1 nest that was deserted. Thus, it is possible that robins occasionally damage their eggs during the rejection attempts (i.e. rejection errors).  Our results are the first to show an increased risk of rejection by a cowbird host as the ratio of cowbird to host eggs increased. This adaptive response is expected because more cowbird eggs will lead to a greater reduction in host fitness, even in a large host like the robin (see  Croston and Hauber 2014a ). This result is in contrast to a similar study on the Red-winged Blackbird (  Agelaius phoeniceus  ), an accepter species. Red-winged Blackbirds showed no adaptive modulation of response to multiple parasitism, which is likely explained by an evolutionary lag in this host ( Ward et al. 1996 ). In addition, our results differ from those of  B&aacute;n et al. (2013)  and  Mosk&aacute;t et al. (2014) , who found that egg ejection by Great Reed Warblers (  Acrocephalus arundinaceus  ) was more likely when their clutches were parasitized by a single foreign egg, compared with parasitism by multiple eggs.  Our results are also the first to demonstrate that a cowbird host is more likely to reject eggs later in the nesting season, which suggests that first-time nesters imprint and learn the appearance of their eggs during their initial breeding attempt. Although older birds often breed earliest in a season (e.g.,  Klomp 1970 ,  Lotem et al. 1992 ), we also expected the highest proportion of first-time nesters during this period. These first-time nesters may not have fully developed ejection behavior and are less likely to eject cowbird eggs (also see  Lotem et al. 1992 ,  1995 ). Later in the breeding season, birds nesting for the first time at the beginning of the breeding season were now nesting for a second or third time, as robins typically do ( Sallabanks and James 1999 ). With increased nesting experience, ejection rates would be expected to increase over the nesting season. Accordingly, we recorded only complete ejections of all parasitic eggs later in the season, presumably after birds had fully learned to recognize their own eggs and developed the ability to eject foreign eggs.  Although imprinting may begin on the first egg, hosts may require a longer period or additional eggs to fully learn the range of variation in their eggs ( Peer et al. 2010 ). A developmental period might exist during the first nesting attempt whereby naive birds imprint on their own eggs and develop ejection behavior, and young birds might not fully express ejection behavior if parasitized during this period ( Strausberger and Rothstein 2009 ). This is similar to the finding of  Lotem et al. (1995)  that cuckoo hosts were more likely to accept parasitism in first clutches than in second clutches in the same nesting season. It also seems noteworthy that all of our &ldquo;partial rejections&rdquo; (like our 2 acceptances) were also relatively early in the nesting season. Alternatively, it is possible that birds reacquaint themselves with the appearance of their eggs anew in each breeding season ( Soler et al. 2013 ), which could also explain the seasonal effect. Finally, because we found robin nests only early in the nesting season in 2011, our result may be due to yearly variation in rejection frequency independent of nesting experience, although we consider this explanation is unlikely.  Of the 3 possible mechanisms that hosts use when rejecting foreign eggs, our study supports the true egg recognition hypothesis for robins (also see  Rothstein 1975b ). Robins were also more responsive to cowbird eggs as the ratio of parasite to host eggs increased, which is indicative of an adaptive response to the increased cost to robin fitness. Egg rejection was not always an immediate response to foreign eggs in our study, but it may require a developmental period during the first nesting attempt to be fully expressed. A large majority of robins tested recognized the foreign eggs in their nest, but not all had developed the grasp-ejection behavior normally exhibited by this species.  We thank S. J. Mullin, B. Rolfsen, P. V. Switzer, and two anonymous reviewers for providing helpful comments on the manuscript. We also thank S. J. Meiners for help with data analysis, and M. Strange and T. R. Bollinger for field assistance. Finally, we thank the City of Charleston, Illinois, USA, for their cooperation with our fieldwork and Eastern Illinois University for funding. 