Patterns of migratory connectivity in Vaux's Swifts at a northern migratory roost: A multi-isotope approachEffect of geolocators on migration and subsequent breeding performance of a long-distance passerine migrantStable isotope ratios indicate that body condition in migrating passerines is influenced by winter habitatChanging gull diet in a changing world: A 150-year stable isotope (&delta;<sup>13</sup>C, &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) record from feathers collected in the Pacific Northwest of North AmericaKirtland's Warbler (<italic>Setophaga kirtlandii</italic>)Global application of stable hydrogen and oxygen isotopes to wildlife forensicsIsotope landscapes for terrestrial migration researchAdvances in tracking small migratory birds: A technical review of light-level geolocationVaux's Swift (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chaetura vauxi</named-content></italic>)Global vegetation change through the Miocene/Pliocene boundaryAdvances in linking wintering migrant birds to their breeding-ground origins using combined analyses of genetic and stable isotope markersNbClust: An R package for determining the relevant number of clusters in a data setGlobal patterns of foliar nitrogen isotopes and their relationships with climate, mycorrhizal fungi, foliar nutrient concentrations, and nitrogen availabilityDistribution mapping of world grassland typesThe response of bird populations to habitat lossPutting people in the map: Anthropogenic biomes of the worldSeason patterns in hydrogen isotopes of claws from breeding wood-warblers (Parulidae): Utility for estimating migratory originsThe influence of microhabitat, moisture and diet on stable-hydrogen isotope variation in a Neotropical avian food webIntraspecific variation in the wing shape of the long-distance migrant Reed Warbler <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Acrocephalus scirpaceus</named-content></italic>: Effects of age and distance of migrationFrom food to offspring down: Tissue-specific discrimination and turn-over of stable isotopes in herbivorous waterbirds and other avian foraging guildsAvian claw morphometry and growth determine the temporal pattern of archived stable isotopesHigh-resolution global maps of 21st-century forest cover changeStable isotopes and the determination of avian migratory connectivity and seasonal interactionsIsotopic ornithology: A perspectiveMigratory connectivity in the Rusty Blackbird: Isotopic evidence from feathers of historical and contemporary specimensA continent-wide migratory divide in North American breeding Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>)Stable isotopes (&delta;D) delineate the origins and migratory connectivity of harvested animals: The case of European woodpigeonsA feather hydrogen isoscape for MexicoConnecting breeding and wintering grounds of Neotropical migrant songbirds using stable hydrogen isotopes: A call for an isotopic atlas of migratory connectivityLinking hydrogen (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H) isotopes in feathers and precipitation: Sources of variance and consequences for assignment to isoscapesA method for investigating population declines of migratory birds using stable isotopes: Origins of harvested Lesser Scaup in North AmericaEfficacy of stable isotope ratios in assigning endangered migrants to breeding and wintering sitesSources of variation in isotopic composition in plantsWinter site fidelity of Prairie Warblers in the Dominican RepublicSome methods for classication and analysis of multivariate observationsThe role of behavioral dominance in structuring patterns of habitat occupancy in a migrant bird during the nonbreeding seasonLinking winter and summer events in a migratory bird by using stable-carbon isotopesMigratory connectivityEstimating origins of short-distance migrant songbirds in North America: Contrasting inferences from hydrogen isotope measurements of feathers, claws, and bloodPatterns of differential migration in White-throated Sparrows evaluated with isotopic measurements of feathersAn examination of procedures for determining the number of clusters in a data setA study of standardization of variables in cluster analysisHabitat segregation by sex in the Hooded Warbler: Experiments on proximate causation and discussion of its evolutionNitrogen isotope studies in forest ecosystemsDeclines of aerial insectivores in North America follow a geographic gradientHistorical pesticide applications coincided with an altered diet of aerially foraging insectivorous Chimney SwiftsCarry-over effects and habitat quality in migratory populationsTropical winter habitat limits reproductive success on the temperate breeding grounds in a migratory birdSexual habitat segregation by American Redstarts wintering in Jamaica: Importance of resource seasonalityPopulation Estimates Database, version 2013Enriching the isotopic toolbox for migratory connectivity analysis: A new approach for migratory species breeding in remote or unexplored areasUsing stable isotopes to estimate trophic position: Models, methods, and assumptionsThe nature of the dietary protein impacts the tissue-to-diet <sup>15</sup>N discrimination factors in laboratory ratsVariation in deuterium (&delta;D) signatures of Yellow Warbler <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendroica petechia</named-content></italic> feathers grown on breeding and wintering groundsWhen density dependence is not instantaneous: Theoretical developments and management implicationsNon-breeding season events influence sexual selection in a long-distance migratory birdPlumage brightness predicts non-breeding season territory quality in a long-distance migratory songbird, the American Redstart <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>Carry-over effects of winter climate on spring arrival date and reproductive success in an endangered migratory bird, Kirtland's Warbler (<italic>Setophaga kirtlandii</italic>)Mapping migration in a songbird using high-resolution genetic markersNovel statistical methods for integrating genetic and stable isotope data to infer individual-level migratory connectivityNitrogen isotopic ecology in southern Africa: Implications for environmental and dietary tracingThe importance of stopover habitat for developing effective conservation strategies for migratory animalsImpacts of a global climate cycle on the population dynamics of a migratory songbirdStable hydrogen and oxygen isotopes in aquatic food webs are tracers of diet and provenanceContinental-scale distributions of vegetation stable carbon isotope ratiosSex-biased winter distribution and timing of migration of Hermit Thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus guttatus</named-content></italic>) in eastern North AmericaNatal dispersal driven by environmental conditions interacting across the annual cycle of a migratory songbirdTracking long-distance songbird migration by using geolocatorsHierarchical clustering via joint between&ndash;within distances: Extending Ward's minimum variance methodCombining stable-isotope (&delta;D) and band recovery data to improve probabilistic assignment of migratory birds to originIdentifying the wintering grounds of hybrid flycatchers using a multi-isotope (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) assignment approachStable isotope ratios of hydrogen separate mammals of aquatic and terrestrial food websEcological and dietary correlates of stable hydrogen isotope ratios in fur and body water of syntopic tropical batsHierarchical grouping to optimize an objective functionStable-carbon and hydrogen isotope ratios reveal breeding origins of Red-winged BlackbirdsThe importance of understanding migratory connectivity and seasonal interactionsLinks between worlds: Unraveling migratory connectivityRange-wide effects of breeding- and nonbreeding-season climate on the abundance of a Neotropical migrant songbirdDetermining geographic patterns of migration and dispersal using stable isotopes in keratinsKirtland's Warblers in anthropogenically disturbed early-successional habitats on Eleuthera, the BahamasThe strength of migratory connectivity between breeding, stopover, and wintering areas can have important implications for population dynamics, evolutionary processes, and conservation. For example, patterns of migratory connectivity may influence the vulnerability of species and populations to stochastic events. For many migratory songbirds, however, we are only beginning to understand patterns of migratory connectivity. We investigated the potential strength of migratory connectivity within a population of Vaux's Swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chaetura vauxi</named-content></italic>). Like many aerial insectivores, this species is currently experiencing population declines. In 2012, a mass mortality event at a spring migratory roost on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada, resulted in the deaths of &gt;1,000 individuals (~2&percnt; of the British Columbia population). In these individuals, we examined variation in 3 stable isotopes (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) from claw samples to determine whether spring migrants showed inherent isotopic similarity in the habitats they used on their Mexican and Central American wintering grounds. Our results indicated the presence of 2 or 3 broad isotopic clusters, which suggests that Vaux's Swifts that migrated through Vancouver Island most likely originated from 2 or 3 overwintering locales or habitat types. We found no evidence of sex- or morphology-based segregation, which suggests that these groups likely share a similar overwintering ecology and, thus, may be equally vulnerable to stochastic events or habitat loss on the wintering grounds. Our results highlight the need for more studies on the nonbreeding-season ecology and migratory connectivity of this species.La fuerza de la conectividad migratoria entre &aacute;reas de cr&iacute;a, parada e invernada puede tener implicancias importantes para la din&aacute;mica poblacional, los procesos evolutivos y la conservaci&oacute;n. Por ejemplo, los patrones de conectividad migratoria pueden influenciar la vulnerabilidad de las especies y de las poblaciones a eventos estoc&aacute;sticos. Para muchas aves canoras migratorias, sin embargo, reci&eacute;n estamos comenzando a comprender los patrones de conectividad migratoria. Aqu&iacute; investigamos la fuerza potencial de la conectividad migratoria dentro de una poblaci&oacute;n de <italic>Chaetura vauxii</italic>. Esta especie, como muchas insect&iacute;voras a&eacute;reas, est&aacute; experimentando actualmente disminuciones poblacionales y un evento de mortalidad masivo en un dormidero migratorio de primavera en la Isla Vancouver, Columbia Brit&aacute;nica, Canad&aacute;, resultando en la muerte de m&aacute;s de 1,000 individuos, lo que representa cerca del 2&percnt; de la poblaci&oacute;n de Columbia Brit&aacute;nica. A partir de estos individuos, examinamos la variaci&oacute;n en tres is&oacute;topos estables (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C y &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) de muestras de las garras para determinar si los migrantes de primavera mostraban una similitud isot&oacute;pica inherente de los h&aacute;bitats que usan en los sitios de invernada en M&eacute;xico y Am&eacute;rica Central. Nuestros resultados indicaron la presencia de dos a tres agrupaciones isot&oacute;picas amplias, sugiriendo que los individuos de <italic>C. vauxii</italic> que migran a trav&eacute;s de la Isla Vancouver probablemente provienen de dos o tres localidades o tipos de h&aacute;bitat de invernada. No encontramos evidencia de segregaci&oacute;n basada en el sexo o en la morfolog&iacute;a, sugiriendo que estos grupos diferentes probablemente comparten una ecolog&iacute;a de invernada similar y por lo tanto pueden ser igualmente vulnerables a los eventos estoc&aacute;sticos o a la p&eacute;rdida de h&aacute;bitat en los sitios de invernada. Nuestros resultados remarcan la necesidad de m&aacute;s estudios sobre la ecolog&iacute;a de la estaci&oacute;n no reproductiva y la conectividad migratoria de esta especie.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> an&aacute;lisis de agrupaci&oacute;n, <italic>Chaetura vauxii</italic>, conectividad migratoria, conservaci&oacute;n, dormidero, is&oacute;topos establesMigratory birds move annually between breeding, wintering, and stopover sites that can be separated by hundreds or thousands of kilometers. Hence, they face an array of both natural and human-mediated environmental challenges. For their effective conservation, it is essential to take an annual-cycle approach that addresses factors that influence populations throughout the year and across broad geographic scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Webster2">Webster et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Webster1">Webster and Marra 2005</xref>). Stressors that occur during one phase of the annual cycle can have carryover effects to subsequent phases of the annual cycle, affecting both individual- and population-level dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Sillett1">Sillett et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink1">Reudink et al. 2009a</xref>). Population-level carryover effects can be caused by density-dependent population regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fretwell1">Fretwell 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Ratikainen1">Ratikainen et al. 2008</xref>), large-scale climatic cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Sillett1">Sillett et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2011</xref>), and habitat loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Norris1">Norris 2005</xref>). Examples of carryover effects that influence individual fitness include wintering-habitat-mediated differences in reproductive success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink1">Reudink et al. 2009a</xref>) and natal dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Studds1">Studds et al. 2008</xref>). Understanding patterns of migratory connectivity, defined as the extent to which individuals from the same wintering site migrate to the same breeding site and vice versa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra3">Marra et al. 2010</xref>), may be important for understanding species- or population-specific responses to anthropogenic disturbances (e.g., land-use change, agricultural development), as well as large-scale selective pressures such as climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Webster2">Webster et al. 2002</xref>).Migratory populations may be especially vulnerable to stochastic events when they display high migratory connectivity, particularly if population size is also small. For example, Kirtland's Warblers (<italic>Setophaga kirtlandii</italic>) exhibit extremely strong connectivity between breeding populations in Michigan, USA, and wintering populations in the Bahamas, Turks, and Caicos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bocetti1">Bocetti et al. 2014</xref>). As a consequence, the species experiences pronounced carryover effects, whereby drier winters delay arrival and nest initiation on the breeding grounds, ultimately resulting in fewer offspring fledged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Rockwell1">Rockwell et al. 2012</xref>). Intensive management of the species on the breeding grounds has led to population increases, but continued long-term recovery likely depends on active management in the Bahamas as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Wunderle1">Wunderle et al. 2010</xref>), especially given that climate change is predicted to increase drought severity in the Caribbean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Rockwell1">Rockwell et al. 2012</xref>).For small migratory birds, making geographic connections for individuals and populations between different phases of their annual cycle can be exceedingly difficult. In recent years, information gleaned from traditional bird ringing has been greatly enhanced with the use of intrinsic markers such as genetic (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Ruegg1">Ruegg et al. 2014</xref>) and stable-isotope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson2">Hobson 2011</xref>) techniques, as well as combinations of these techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Chabot1">Chabot et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Rundel1">Rundel et al. 2013</xref>). Stable isotopes of hydrogen (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H), in particular, have been instrumental in migratory-connectivity research, owing to geographically predictable patterns of isotopic variation that are reflected in animal tissue and thus provide &ldquo;markers of origin&rdquo; that indicate where the tissue was grown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson8">Hobson et al. 2012a</xref>). Such intrinsic markers have the advantage that birds need only be captured once, and they may be especially useful as a first step to understanding patterns of migratory connectivity in poorly studied species or in remote areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson7">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Pekarsky1">Pekarsky et al. 2015</xref>). The advent of new extrinsic marker technologies such as geolocators and GPS loggers has led to higher-resolution information on the migratory behavior of certain species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Stutchbury1">Stutchbury et al. 2009</xref>). However, use of these extrinsic markers is complicated by the need to recover data loggers and remains impractical, and often prohibitively expensive, for large-scale studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Arlt1">Arlt et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bridge1">Bridge et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson7">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>). In addition, extrinsic markers cannot be used to infer historical patterns of migratory connectivity. By contrast, intrinsic markers can be extremely useful in forensic studies, including dietary reconstruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Nocera1">Nocera et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Blight1">Blight et al. 2015</xref>) and inference of migratory connectivity from historical specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson3">Hobson et al. 2010</xref>). Given the paucity of information on population- or region-specific migratory connectivity for many species of conservation concern, there is a pressing need to apply intrinsic and/or extrinsic marker approaches to evaluate factors that limit populations throughout their annual cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson7">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>).Like many other aerial insectivores, breeding populations of Vaux's Swift (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chaetura vauxi</named-content></italic>) have undergone significant declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Nebel1">Nebel et al. 2010</xref>). Recent estimates from the North American Breeding Bird Survey suggest a population decline of &minus;2.2&percnt; yr<sup>&minus;1</sup> in Canada since the 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-EnvironmentCanada1">Environment Canada 2014</xref>). Vaux's Swifts breed throughout western North America but exhibit an unusual roosting strategy during migratory journeys between their western North American breeding grounds and their southern Mexican and Central American wintering grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>). During migration, groups of Vaux's Swifts roost communally in tree cavities or, more commonly, in abandoned industrial chimneys, where they can remain for several days to weeks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>). Migratory roosts may contain hundreds to thousands of individuals. During winter, Vaux's Swifts also appear to occupy large roost sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>). However, little is known about migratory connectivity in Vaux's Swift, and it is unknown whether (1) individuals from particular wintering areas migrate north together and stop at the same roost sites (strong migratory connectivity) or (2) migratory roost sites comprise individuals arriving from multiple locations across their winter range (weaker migratory connectivity). The degree of connectivity can have important implications for conservation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Sheehy1">Sheehy et al. 2011</xref>), and if large concentrations of individuals winter together and move together throughout migration, they may be particularly vulnerable to stochastic events. Here, we use intrinsic markers to study putative migratory connectivity in migrating Vaux's Swifts. We sampled claws (grown during the overwintering period) from a large group of communally roosting Vaux's Swifts that accidentally suffocated at a spring migratory roost site on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada. We used cluster analyses based on multiple stable-isotope markers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) to examine support for the existence of a single versus multiple wintering origins within this population.On May 9, 2012, a mass mortality event occurred at a migratory roost in Cumberland, British Columbia, used annually by Vaux's Swifts during spring migration. Approximately 1,350 Vaux's Swifts died from suffocation after being trapped in the roost. That single event represented a loss of 1.5&ndash;2.7&percnt; of the published population-size estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Summers1">Summers and Gebauer 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-PartnersinFlightScienceCommittee1">Partners in Flight Science Committee 2013</xref>) for Vaux's Swifts in British Columbia. From these mortalities, we randomly subsampled 98 individuals for analysis. On each individual, we measured wing length, tail length, and tail pin length, and we sexed each individual via laparoscopy. We then sampled 2 mm (0.30&ndash;0.40 mg) of tissue from the tip of the central claw, ensuring that we avoided the quick, of each foot from each individual for isotope analysis. Although claws grow continuously and, because of their conical growth pattern, incorporate materials grown at slightly different times, analysis of the claw tip should accurately reflect the isotopic environment over an extended period (weeks to months) preceding sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Mazerolle1">Mazerolle and Hobson 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hahn1">Hahn et al. 2012</xref>). For instance, on the basis of changes in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H after arrival on the breeding grounds, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2008)</xref> estimated that isotopic values in claws of parulids may reflect the nonbreeding area for 3&ndash;7 wk after the birds arrive on the breeding grounds. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hahn1">Hahn et al. (2014)</xref> also provided empirical evidence demonstrating that in Palearctic&ndash;African migratory passerines, the distal claw tip should reflect isotopic environments over a few months prior to sampling, with typical claw-growth rates of 0.03&ndash;0.05 mm day<sup>&minus;1</sup>. Though data on the migration timing of Vaux's Swifts are sparse, major flight passages occur during mid-April to late May in California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Small1">Small 1994</xref>), with birds arriving in Oregon from late April to late May (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>, and references therein). Thus, claws sampled from birds that died during spring migration on May 9 should reflect wintering conditions, as has been demonstrated in passerines captured both on migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bearhop1">Bearhop et al. 2004</xref>) and upon arrival on the breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink1">Reudink et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink2">2009b</xref>).There are many different methods available for determining the optimal number of clusters in a dataset. For this reason, we made use of the package &ldquo;NbClust&rdquo; in program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2013</xref>), which provides the user with results from 30 indices aimed at determining the number of clusters into which the data should be split (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Charrad1">Charrad et al. 2014</xref>). Clustering validity indices combine information such as intracluster and intercluster variation, geometric or statistical properties of the data, and dissimilarity or similarity measurements. For a detailed description of all 30 indices, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Charrad1">Charrad et al. (2014)</xref>. Two widely used clustering algorithms are available in the NbClust package: <italic>k</italic>-means and hierarchical agglomerative clustering. In <italic>k</italic>-means clustering, observations are assigned to initial cluster centers, which are then iteratively updated until the cluster centers no longer change and the within-cluster sum of squares is minimized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-MacQueen1">MacQueen 1967</xref>). In hierarchical agglomerative clustering, each observation begins in its own cluster, and pairs of clusters are joined on the basis of a distance measure and an agglomeration criterion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Szekely1">Sz&eacute;kely and Rizzo 2005</xref>). Because of the differences in these clustering approaches and a lack of a priori reasons to hypothesize a set number of clusters in our data, we used both clustering algorithms. We used a Euclidean distance (square distance between 2 vectors; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Seber1">Seber 1984</xref>) in both clustering algorithms and examined the relative support for division of the data into 2&ndash;10 clusters based on the 3 isotopic markers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N). For hierarchical agglomerative clustering, we used the Ward agglomeration method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Ward1">Ward 1963</xref>), which minimizes the total within-cluster variance. We also repeated the above procedures after removing 6 multivariate outliers, assessed using the robust Mahalanobis distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Varmuza1">Varmuza and Filzmoser 2009</xref>).After the optimal number of clusters was identified by each clustering approach, we examined the partitioning of observations (individual birds) into clusters. We performed multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) to verify significant differences among the selected clusters in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N ratios. We then used a Pearson's chi-square test to examine whether the proportion of claws from male and female birds differed among clusters, and we used a <italic>t</italic>-test or analysis of variance (ANOVA) to examine whether wing length and tail length varied among clusters.Finally, we used a model-based hierarchical clustering procedure within the package &ldquo;mclust&rdquo; in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fraley1">Fraley et al. 2012</xref>) to determine whether the optimal number(s) of clusters selected by the above procedures was preferred over no clustering at all. Package &ldquo;mclust&rdquo; uses an expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm to estimate the finite mixture models that correspond to different numbers of clusters, and uses the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) to select the best number of clusters. Importantly, a single cluster can also be considered. We evaluated the support for 1&ndash;10 clusters.The &delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N isotope ratios were standardized prior to analysis by subtracting by their mean and dividing by their standard deviation. Standardization is recommended in cluster analysis when variables are on different scales, to minimize the effects of outliers and so that cluster formation is not overly influenced by variables with greater absolute variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Milligan2">Milligan and Cooper 1988</xref>). Although isotope ratios represent the ratio of heavy to light isotopes in a sample divided by the ratio of a standard and are always expressed in the same units (&permil;), differences in the natural abundances and fractionation of heavy and light isotopes among elements lead to differences in the magnitude of the range of typical &delta; values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fry1">Fry 2006</xref>). Thus, standardization was useful in giving equal weight to variation among the 3 isotope ratios. All analyses were performed in R version 3.1.1, and results are shown as means &plusmn; SD.Stable isotopic values (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N) were available from claws of 98 individuals. All 3 elements showed considerable variation in all 3 isotopes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t01">Table 1</xref>). Mean isotope ratios were &minus;37.9 &plusmn; 12.4&permil; for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &minus;21.6 &plusmn; 0.6&permil; for &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and 7.3 &plusmn; 0.9&permil; for &delta;<sup>15</sup>N. Correlations among isotope ratios were <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.09 (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.37) for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H and &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.14 (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.17) for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N, and <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.53 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) for &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N. Of those 98 individuals with isotope data, we were unable to determine sex for 1 individual. There was a nearly even number of males and females in our sample (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 47 females, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 50 males). Males and females did not differ in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H (<italic>t</italic><sub>95</sub> &equals; &minus;0.02, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.98), &delta;<sup>13</sup>C (<italic>t</italic><sub>95</sub> &equals; &minus;0.98, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.33), or &delta;<sup>15</sup>N (<italic>t</italic><sub>95</sub> &equals; &minus;0.18, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.86). Mean wing length was 113.5 &plusmn; 2.8 mm and did not differ between males and females (males: 113.4 &plusmn; 2.7, females: 113.7 &plusmn; 2.8; <italic>t</italic><sub>95</sub> &equals; &minus;0.46, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.65). Wing length was not correlated with &delta;<sup>2</sup>H (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.06, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.59), &delta;<sup>13</sup>C (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12), or &delta;<sup>15</sup>N (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12). Mean tail length was 36.2 &plusmn; 2.3 mm and did not differ between males and females (males: 35.8 &plusmn; 1.8, females: 36.5 &plusmn; 2.7; <italic>t</italic><sub>95</sub> &equals; &minus;1.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.13). Tail length was not correlated with &delta;<sup>2</sup>H (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.00, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.99) or &delta;<sup>13</sup>C (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.07, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49), but it was negatively correlated with &delta;<sup>15</sup>N (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.23, <italic>P</italic> &equals; &minus;0.02).Sex, age, morphometrics (mm), and stable isotope values (&permil;) for 98 Vaux's Swift claws from a roost site on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada.When using the full dataset, 11 of 30 clustering validity indices (37&percnt;) proposed 2 as the optimal number of clusters in the <italic>k</italic>-means clustering procedure. The next highest-ranked numbers of clusters were 3 and 4, which received support from 6 (20&percnt;) and 5 (17&percnt;) clustering indices, respectively. Three was deemed the optimal number of clusters by the majority (10, or 33&percnt;) of indices in the hierarchical agglomerative procedure, but a large proportion of indices (9, or 30&percnt;) also supported 2 clusters. The only alternative clustering that received support was a 10-cluster solution with support from 5 (17&percnt;) indices. Results of the <italic>k</italic>-means clustering procedure were similar when outliers were removed, with 2 deemed the optimal number of clusters by the majority (9, or 30&percnt;) of indices. For the hierarchical agglomerative procedure, 2 was identified as the optimal number (8, or 27&percnt; of indices) and 3 received the second-most support (5, or 17&percnt; of indices). Overall, these results suggest that the isotope data grouped most naturally into 2 or 3 clusters, and thus we used the full dataset for the remainder of the analyses. Although the selection of the optimal number of clusters was not unanimous among indices, similar results are obtained from simulated datasets even when distinct, non-overlapping clusters are used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Milligan1">Milligan and Cooper 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Charrad1">Charrad et al. 2014</xref>). Furthermore, according to the BIC, the model-based clustering procedure suggested that the optimal number of clusters was 2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t02">Table 2</xref>).Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) from model-based hierarchical clustering procedure using the package &ldquo;mclust&rdquo; in R. BIC values are shown for 1&ndash;10 clusters for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H, &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N isotopes from Vaux's Swift claws.We examined the classification of individual claws into 2 or 3 clusters using the results from <italic>k</italic>-means clustering or hierarchical agglomerative clustering, respectively. The clusters were significantly different from one another for all 3 isotope ratios simultaneously when partitioned into 2 (MANOVA, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 52.5, df &equals; 3 and 93, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) or 3 clusters (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 36.4, df &equals; 3 and 93, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The 2-cluster solution resulted from a split between individuals with higher &delta;<sup>15</sup>N and &delta;<sup>13</sup>C ratios and those with lower &delta;<sup>15</sup>N and &delta;<sup>13</sup>C ratios, with little influence of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H on clustering (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t03">Table 3</xref>). The 3-cluster solution suggested an additional division of the individuals with low &delta;<sup>15</sup>N and &delta;<sup>13</sup>C ratios into those with higher or lower &delta;<sup>2</sup>H ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-f02">2</xref>). There was no association between sex and cluster membership when the claws were grouped in 2 (<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-117-4-670-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-117-4-670-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 1) or 3 (<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-117-4-670-ilm02"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-117-4-670-ilm02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.42) clusters. There was no association between wing length and cluster membership for 2 (<italic>t</italic><sub>96</sub> &equals; 0.62, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.54) or 3 (ANOVA, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.70, df &equals; 2 and 95, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.50) clusters. Similarly, there was no association between tail length and cluster membership for 2 (<italic>t</italic><sub>96</sub> &equals; &minus;0.48, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.64) or 3 (ANOVA, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.60, df &equals; 2 and 95, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.21) clusters.Mean (&plusmn; SD) stable isotope ratios of Vaux's Swift claws partitioned into 2 or 3 clusters based on <italic>k</italic>-means or hierarchical agglomerative clustering, respectively. Cluster numbers (1&ndash;3) corresponds to those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-f02">2</xref>.Variation in claw stable isotopes of hydrogen (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H: <bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>), carbon (&delta;<sup>13</sup>C: <bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>), and nitrogen (&delta;<sup>15</sup>N: <bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) in Vaux's Swifts from a roost site on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada. Claws were clustered into 2 (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) or 3 (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) clusters. The median, interquartile range (IQR), and outliers (&gt;1.5 &times; IQR) are shown.Clustering of stable isotope ratios of Vaux's Swift claws from a roost site on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada, into (<bold>A</bold>) 2 clusters or (<bold>B</bold>) 3 clusters based on <italic>k</italic>-means or hierarchical agglomerative clustering, respectively.Patterns of migratory connectivity in long-distance migratory birds can have important implications for population dynamics, evolutionary processes, and effective conservation strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Webster1">Webster and Marra 2005</xref>). Using multiple stable isotopes (&delta;<sup>13</sup>C, &delta;<sup>15</sup>N, and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H) from claw samples of Vaux's Swifts at a spring migratory roost, our goal was not to assign individuals to a particular overwintering locality or localities, which would have been exceedingly difficult given the poor resolution in isoscapes of Mexico and Central America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bowen1">Bowen et al. 2005</xref>) and our lack of known-origin tissues from these areas. Rather, we asked whether Vaux's Swifts at a single migratory roost likely came from a single winter location, which would indicate stronger migratory connectivity, or multiple winter locations, which would indicate weaker migratory connectivity. We found evidence in support of 2 or possibly 3 broad isotopic clusters on the overwintering grounds from the single migratory roost on Vancouver Island. While alternative explanations for our observations are possible (see below), we tentatively interpret our findings as likely demonstrating differences in overwintering locations used by Vaux's Swifts in our sample.Understanding patterns of migratory connectivity in small, long-distance migratory birds has been exceedingly challenging, but the use of stable isotope analysis over the past 2 decades has revolutionized our ability to establish patterns of connectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson1">Hobson 2005</xref>). Generally, this approach relies on the assignment of tissues to spatially explicit isoscapes generated from precipitation isoscapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bowen2">Bowen and West 2008</xref>) or known-origin individuals sampled across their range (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson6">Hobson et al. 2009b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson9">2012b</xref>). Recently, these methods have been enhanced through the use of Bayesian statistical methods and GIS-based models of precipitation isoscapes, as well as additional information such as band recoveries, to improve assignments by creating probabilistic regions of origin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson5">Hobson et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson10">2009c</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-VanWilgenburg1">Van Wilgenburg and Hobson 2011</xref>). However, most studies have been focused on assigning breeding origins to winter-captured individuals, rather than vice versa, because breeding-ground isoscapes, particularly in North America, are better delineated than wintering-ground isoscapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bowen1">Bowen et al. 2005</xref>). This poses a problem for assigning winter origins to individuals sampled within breeding or migratory populations, as in our study. Furthermore, the particular tissue chosen for sampling must reflect the area of origin that is of interest to the researcher. This too poses difficulties for assigning winter origins because many North American bird species, including Vaux's Swifts, molt their feathers on or near the breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Pyle1">Pyle 1997</xref>; but see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Kelly1">Kelly et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Quinlan1">Quinlan and Green 2011</xref>). Thus, we chose to sample claws because they reflect conditions several weeks prior to sampling, a time during which the birds should have been present on the wintering grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bearhop1">Bearhop et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink1">Reudink et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink2">2009b</xref>).Despite the relatively high variation in all 3 isotopic signatures (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H range: 66&permil;; &delta;<sup>15</sup>N range: 5.8&permil;; &delta;<sup>13</sup>C range: 3.5&permil;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t01">Table 1</xref>), our analysis provides support for Vaux's Swift claws fitting into 2 or 3 isotopically distinct clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-f02">Figure 2</xref>), with strongest support for 2 clusters when outliers were removed. When partitioned into 2 clusters, the claws separated into those with higher &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N and those with lower &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N. Variation in &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N is most likely related to broad-scale habitat differences, given that food-web &delta;<sup>13</sup>C signatures are strongly related to the distribution of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Lajtha1">Lajtha and Marshall 1994</xref>), and food-web &delta;<sup>15</sup>N signatures are associated with soil exposure and climate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Nadelhoffer1">Nadelhoffer and Fry 1994</xref>). Although we cannot exclude the possibility that birds were separated, in part, on the basis of dietary shifts and niche specialization, broad-scale differences in &delta;<sup>13</sup>C, &delta;<sup>15</sup>N, and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H appear to be consistent with Vaux's Swift using habitats that follow climatic&ndash;moisture gradients. Regardless of the clustering algorithm, birds associated with cluster 2 were enriched in <sup>13</sup>C by ~0.9&permil; over individuals from cluster 1. Simultaneously, birds associated with cluster 2 were also enriched in <sup>15</sup>N by ~1.6 &permil; compared with birds from cluster 1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t03">Table 3</xref>). Assuming that &delta;<sup>13</sup>C follows gradients similar to those reported elsewhere (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>), these data appear to suggest that birds in cluster 2 originated from hotter and drier habitats than birds in cluster 1.The agglomerative clustering approach suggested that birds could be further partitioned into a third cluster on the basis of splitting claws that had both low &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N values, based on those with higher (cluster 3) and lower (cluster 1) &delta;<sup>2</sup>H values (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-t03">Table 3</xref>). Latitudinal and altitudinal gradients in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H are well established and among the strongest of isotopic gradients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson1">Hobson 2005</xref>), and our results thus suggest that individuals that had low &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N were likely further segregated along a latitudinal or, possibly, an altitudinal gradient. Although a species-specific &delta;<sup>2</sup>H claw-tissue isoscape is lacking for the Vaux's Swift overwintering range, a &delta;<sup>2</sup>H feather isoscape developed for House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>) in Mexico showed more positive &delta;<sup>2</sup>H signatures in the northeast of the country and more negative signatures in the south and in high-altitude regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson6">Hobson et al. 2009b</xref>). Overall, our results indicate that individuals from the migratory population of Vaux's Swifts on Vancouver Island may have originated from a small number of different latitudes and/or habitats.Breeding populations that are more strongly connected to specific wintering areas, particularly those experiencing degradation, may be most vulnerable to population declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Dolman1">Dolman and Sutherland 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Webster1">Webster and Marra 2005</xref>), although a recent study found that the strength of connectivity in breeding populations of Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>) in North America was unrelated to their population trend (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez and Hobson 2014</xref>). Our data suggest that further research to estimate the strength of connectivity across breeding populations of Vaux's Swifts is now warranted and might help explain patterns of decline if extrinsic markers could be deployed along a gradient of declining versus increasing populations (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fraser3">Fraser et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson4">Hobson et al. 2015</xref>).We also asked whether individuals in our sample showed evidence of segregation based on sex or morphology during the overwintering period, as has been observed in several other passerines, such as Hooded Warblers (<italic>Setophaga citrina</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Morton1">Morton 1990</xref>), Prairie Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. discolor</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Latta1">Latta and Faaborg 2001</xref>), and American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. ruticilla</named-content></italic>), which segregate on the basis of habitat; and White-throated Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia albicollis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Mazerolle2">Mazerolle and Hobson 2007</xref>) and Hermit Thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus guttatus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Stouffer1">Stouffer and Dwyer 2003</xref>), which segregate on the basis of latitude. For example, American Redstarts exhibit marked age- and sex-biased habitat segregation, with older males disproportionately inhabiting high-quality mangrove forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Parrish1">Parrish and Sherry 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra1">Marra 2000</xref>)&mdash;a characteristic also easily discerned via stable isotope analysis of muscle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>), blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Norris2">Norris et al. 2004</xref>), and claw samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink1">Reudink et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Reudink2">2009b</xref>). Furthermore, larger females were more likely to inhabit high-quality mangrove territories because of dominance-mediated habitat segregation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Marra1">Marra 2000</xref>). Latitudinal segregation, on the other hand, may be related to trade-offs between body size or wing size/shape and migration distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-GarciaPeiro1">Garc&iacute;a Peir&oacute; 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Mazerolle2">Mazerolle and Hobson 2007</xref>). Our results suggest no evidence for sex- or morphology-based segregation, at least when considering wing and tail length, and indeed there was no evidence of differences in wing size between males and females, which suggests that male and female Vaux's Swifts likely share a similar overwintering ecology and, thus, may be equally vulnerable to stochastic events or habitat loss.The utility of triple-isotope isoscapes for assigning origins to South American and African wintering birds has recently been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hobson9">Hobson et al. 2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez and Hobson 2014</xref>), and our results indicate that the approach has potential for identifying Mexican and Central American wintering clusters as well. Taken together, our results highlight the need for additional research on the overwintering ecology and behavior of this poorly studied long-distance migrant and the need for calibrating tissue-specific isoscapes to better assign Nearctic&ndash;Neotropical migratory birds to wintering localities. Our data suggest that birds migrating through Vancouver Island likely overwinter in 2 or 3 isotopically similar regions or habitat types, and these predictions should now be validated. Wintering-ground sampling would facilitate nominal assignment (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Wunder1">Wunder 2012</xref>) to 2 or 3 spatially delineated geographic regions or, alternatively, might facilitate spatially explicit, multivariate assignment approaches (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-GarciaPerez1">Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez and Hobson 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Veen1">Veen et al. 2014</xref>).Recent work has highlighted the potential for keratinous tissues to vary isotopically with diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fraser2">Fraser et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Soto1">Soto et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Voigt2">Voigt et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Voigt1">2015</xref>) and microhabitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Fraser2">Fraser et al. 2011</xref>). Thus, although we interpret our results primarily in the context of migratory connectivity, we cannot preclude the possibility that multivariate differences in the isotopic composition of claws could stem from variation in microhabitat, behavior, or dietary preferences among individuals. Given the high motility of Vaux's Swifts while foraging on the wing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>), it is plausible that our results could also stem from variation in the degree of foraging over aquatic versus terrestrial habitats, or over forested versus grassland or agricultural habitats. Like other aerial insectivores, Vaux's Swifts forage broadly over forest canopy, meadows, and open water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Bull1">Bull and Collins 2007</xref>), and their diets likely reflect the composition of aerial plankton from major insect emergences from both the aquatic and terrestrial environments. Within their wintering grounds, these major habitat types should be relatively isotopically distinct, owing to major isotopic differences in &delta;<sup>13</sup>C and &delta;<sup>15</sup>N between forest canopy, which primarily uses a C<sub>3</sub> phytosynthetic pathway, and grasslands&ndash;pastures, which are dominated by C<sub>4</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Still1">Still and Powell 2010</xref>). It is important to note that the distribution of forest versus grassland, pasture, and agricultural lands displays a great deal of geographic structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Ellis1">Ellis and Ramankutty 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Dixon1">Dixon et al. 2014</xref>) and, thus, it is probable that isotopic differences due to differences in habitat selection would also covary with any spatial segregation. Regardless of whether the patterns we observed are attributable solely to differences in migratory connectivity or to variation in local habitat selection, our results point to relatively limited variation in overwintering niches of Vaux's Swifts. Thus, a better understanding of the overwintering ecology of Vaux's Swifts is necessary to inform conservation. Wintering-ground work on habitat use and diets of Vaux's Swifts or multi-isotope assays on claws from birds fitted with miniaturized GPS tags (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hallworth1">Hallworth and Marra 2015</xref>) would shed light on the mechanistic explanations for our observations.Like most migratory aerial insectivores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Nebel1">Nebel et al. 2010</xref>), Vaux's Swifts are in decline. Given the unique roosting ecology of Vaux's Swifts, they are particularly susceptible to stochastic events as exemplified by this 1 mass mortality, which may represent a loss of about 1.5&ndash;2.7&percnt; of the British Columbia population of Vaux's Swifts in a single evening. This exceptional vulnerability, coupled with increasing habitat loss and alteration in the tropics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-670-Hansen1">Hansen et al. 2013</xref>), indicates a crucial need for further research to determine patterns of migratory connectivity and identify critical winter and migratory roost sites for future conservation planning.We thank S. Joly for assistance in data collection.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Funding was provided by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Discovery Grant, a Thompson Rivers University Internal Research Fund Award to M.W.R., and a National Science Foundation grant to P.P.M.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Birds were collected under a Canadian salvage permit (BC-SA-0049-12).