Synergistic effects of spring temperatures and land cover on nest survival of urban birdsDeclining egg viability explains higher hatching failure in a suburban population of the threatened Florida Scrub-Jay <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aphelocoma coerulescens</named-content></italic>The shelf life of bird eggs: Testing egg viability using a tropical climate gradientClimate change and unequal phenological changes across four trophic levels: Constraints or adaptations?Habitat and weather are weak correlates of nestling condition and growth rates of four U.K. farmland passerinesHabitat structure mediates predation risk for sedentary prey: Experimental tests of alternative hypothesesClimate change or land use dynamics: Do we know what climate change indicators indicate?Evolution of passerine incubation behavior: Influence of food, temperature, and nest predationTemperature can interact with landscape factors to affect songbird productivityClimate change hotspots in the United StatesAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalDrought and cooler temperatures are associated with higher nest survival in Mountain PloversLand-use and climate change effects on population size and extinction risk of Andean plantsUrbanization and the predation paradox: The role of trophic dynamics in structuring vertebrate communitiesWeather and prairie grouse: Dealing with effects beyond our controlInfluence of temperatures during the nestling period on post-fledging survival of Great Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> in a Mediterranean habitatHeat storage in urban areas: Local-scale observations and evaluation of a simple modelWarm is better: Incubation temperature influences apparent survival and recruitment of Wood Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>)Habitat suitability and nest survival of White-headed Woodpeckers in unburned forests of OregonClimate Change 2013: The Physical Science BasisHabitat near nest boxes correlated with fate of Eastern Bluebird fledglings in an urban landscapeRegional relationships between surface temperature, vegetation, and human settlement in a rapidly urbanizing ecosystemEvaluation of the &ldquo;safe nesting zone&rdquo; hypothesis across an urban gradient: A multi-scale studyBetween a rock and a hard place: The impacts of climate change and housing development on breeding birds in CaliforniaA multiscale analysis of nest predation on Least Bell's Vireos (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vireo bellii</named-content> pusillus</italic>)An &lsquo;ecological trap' for Yellow Warbler nest microhabitat selectionNovel communities from climate changeInteractions between climate and habitat loss effects on biodiversity: A systematic review and meta-analysisConsequences of habitat utilization by nest predators and breeding songbirds across multiple scales in an urbanizing landscapeClimate change increases the likelihood of catastrophic avian mortality events during extreme heat wavesUrban areas as refuges from predators and flight distance of preyVariation in a sparrow's reproductive success with rainfall: Food and predator-mediated processesDevelopment of incubation temperature and behavior in thrushes nesting at high altitudeOxidative damage in different tissues of neonatal chicks exposed to low environmental temperatureNest-site selection and nest survival of Lewis's Woodpecker in aspen riparian woodlandsWeather-related mass-mortality events in migrantsThe urban energy-balanceNestling growth and thermoregulatory development in subalpine Dusky FlycatchersUrban ecological systems: Scientific foundations and a decade of progressCauses of mortality in a nestling population of free-living hihi (stitchbird&mdash;<italic>Notiomystis cincta</italic>)Anthropogenic resource subsidies decouple predator&ndash;prey relationshipsQuantifying avian nest survival along an urbanization gradient using citizen- and scientist-generated dataDistinguishing stressors acting on land bird communities in an urbanizing environmentMicrohabitat nest cover effect on nest survival of the Red-crested CardinalGlobal forecasts of urban expansion to 2030 and direct impacts on biodiversity and carbon poolsAttenuated nesting season of the Acadian Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax virescens</named-content></italic>) in urban forestsWeather effects on avian breeding performance and implications of climate changeEffects of recreational trails on Northern Cardinals (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cardinalis cardinalis</named-content></italic>) in forested urban parksNest survival of birds in an urban environment in New ZealandThe importance of land cover change across urban&ndash;rural typologies for climate modelingProjected large-scale range reductions of northern-boreal land bird species due to climate changeWarmer springs lead to mistimed reproduction in Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>)Egg laying, egg temperature, attentiveness, and incubation in the Western BluebirdThermal tolerance of avian embryos: A reviewProgram MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsInfluence of spring temperatures and individual traits on reproductive timing and success in a migratory woodpeckerTemperature effects on food supply and chick mortality in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Importance of climatic and environmental change in the demography of a multi-brooded passerine, the Woodlark <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lullula arborea</named-content></italic>Climate change has the potential to influence avian population dynamics through nest-fate sensitivity to temperatures during the breeding season. Nest fate also varies across spatially heterogeneous habitat, and changing land uses may independently introduce stressors on reproductive outcome. Identifying the individual and synergistic effects of climate change and land-use change is necessary for understanding the impact of global change on native species. We studied the nest fate of 3 sympatric species breeding in urban habitat in an arid region of the western United States. We monitored nests (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 371) of American Robin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>), Mourning Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida macroura</named-content></italic>), and Black-headed Grosbeak (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pheucticus melanocephalus</named-content></italic>) over 4 yr on an urban-to-rural gradient and analyzed nest fate in relation to temperatures at the time of egg laying and after eggs hatched. Habitat measurements included nest height and the amounts of canopy cover and impervious surfaces at 3 spatial scales of 20-m, 100-m, and 500-m radii from the nest. Our data most strongly supported models that included temperature deviation after hatching, nest stage, fine-scale canopy cover, and pedestrian traffic. Nest survival increased at slight temperature increases during the nestling stage, which suggests that in a climate-change context, moderate warming in spring temperatures may be beneficial for some breeding birds. Nests were more likely to survive at locations with more canopy cover in a 20-m radius and at sites with more pedestrian traffic, which suggests that increasing cover of native riparian tree canopy at fine scales may enhance habitat quality in multiuse urban reserves. Our results demonstrate that effects of climate change on avian populations must be considered synergistically with land-use and land-cover characteristics of the urban landscape, including tree canopy cover and level of human disturbance.El cambio clim&aacute;tico tiene el potencial de influenciar las din&aacute;micas de las poblaciones de aves debido a la sensibilidad del nido a las temperaturas durante la estaci&oacute;n reproductiva. El destino del nido tambi&eacute;n var&iacute;a con la heterogeneidad espacial del h&aacute;bitat, y los cambios en el uso del suelo pueden introducir independientemente factores de estr&eacute;s en el resultado reproductivo. La identificaci&oacute;n de los efectos individuales y sin&eacute;rgicos del cambio clim&aacute;tico y del cambio de uso del suelo es necesaria para entender el impacto del cambio global en las especies nativas. Estudiamos el destino del nido de tres especies simp&aacute;tricas reproduci&eacute;ndose en h&aacute;bitat urbano en una regi&oacute;n &aacute;rida del oeste de Estados Unidos. Monitoreamos nidos (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 371) de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida macroura</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pheucticus melanocephalus</named-content></italic> durante cuatro a&ntilde;os en un gradiente urbano-rural y analizamos el destino del nido con relaci&oacute;n a las temperaturas al momento de la puesta del huevo y luego de la eclosi&oacute;n. Las mediciones de h&aacute;bitat incluyeron la altura del nido y la cantidad de cobertura del dosel y de superficies impermeables a tres escalas espaciales de 20 m, 100 m y 500 m de radio desde el nido. Nuestros datos apoyaron con mayor firmeza a los modelos que incluyeron el desv&iacute;o de la temperatura luego de la eclosi&oacute;n, la etapa del nido, la cobertura del dosel a escala fina y el tr&aacute;fico pedestre. La supervivencia del nido aument&oacute; con leves aumentos de la temperatura durante la etapa de volant&oacute;n, sugiriendo que en un contexto de cambio clim&aacute;tico, el calentamiento moderado en las temperaturas de primavera puede ser beneficioso para algunas aves reproductoras. Los nidos tuvieron mayor probabilidad de sobrevivir en los sitios con m&aacute;s cobertura del dosel en un radio de 20 m y en sitios con m&aacute;s tr&aacute;fico pedestre, sugiriendo que el aumento de cobertura del dosel de los &aacute;rboles ribere&ntilde;os nativos a escala fina puede mejorar la calidad del h&aacute;bitat en las reservas urbanas de uso m&uacute;ltiple. Este estudio demuestra que los efectos del cambio clim&aacute;tico en las poblaciones de aves deben ser considerados de modo sin&eacute;rgico con las caracter&iacute;sticas de uso del suelo y de cobertura del suelo de los paisajes urbanos, incluyendo la cobertura de los &aacute;rboles del dosel y el nivel de disturbio humano.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> din&aacute;mica de poblaciones, ecolog&iacute;a urbana, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pheucticus melanocephalus</named-content></italic>, supervivencia del nido, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>, variaci&oacute;n de la temperatura, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida macroura</named-content></italic>The impacts of global climate change on avian populations are widely recognized (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Moller2">M&oslash;ller et al. 2010</xref>), yet the underlying mechanisms are not well established. Several studies have demonstrated that the effects of changing temperature or precipitation can be indirect. Examples include the contraction or expansion of current bioclimatic envelopes that can limit habitat availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Virkkala1">Virkkala et al. 2008</xref>) or help establish novel communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Lurgi1">Lurgi et al. 2012</xref>); phenological shifts in the timing of breeding in relation to peak prey availability (the &ldquo;mismatch hypothesis&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Visser1">Visser et al. 1998</xref>); and the amount of overlap in the activity of breeding birds and their predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Both1">Both et al. 2009</xref>).Climate change may also influence vital rates through direct abiotic effects. Extreme stochastic events such as heat waves are becoming more common and may increase mortality rates of adult birds in some regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-McKechnie1">McKechnie and Wolf 2010</xref>). Climates in many temperate regions are also forecast to experience increases in average background temperatures and temperature variability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Stocker1">IPCC 2013</xref>), with perhaps less obvious consequences. One such consequence may be a negative influence on reproductive success. Egg viability is sensitive to temperatures above and below those needed to initiate embryonic development&mdash;physiological zero temperature (PZT)&mdash;and warmer ambient temperatures during incubation may decrease hatching success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Aldredge1">Aldredge et al. 2012</xref>). Nestlings and chicks with low thermoregulatory ability are also vulnerable to heat stress from warmer temperatures. For example, relative increases in fall harvest rates of juvenile Sharp-tailed Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tympanuchus phasianellus</named-content></italic>) were negatively correlated with the number of days above chick heat-stress tolerance during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-FlandersWanner1">Flanders-Wanner et al. 2004</xref>).Alternatively, warming temperatures during the nesting period could alleviate temperature-related nest failure associated with cold and wet weather. Hypothermia is a serious hazard for underdeveloped young, and oxidative stress in precocial chicks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gallus gallus</named-content></italic>) maintained at low temperatures (20&deg;C) for 12 hr caused damage to heart and brain tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Mujahid1">Mujahid and Furuse 2009</xref>). Hypothermia is also an issue for altricial chicks, as well as for their food supply. Daily brood survival of Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) was negatively associated with &ldquo;cold snaps&rdquo; during which temperatures did not exceed a critical threshold for insect flight activity over consecutive days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2013</xref>).The sensitivity of stages within the nesting cycle to temperature variation needs elucidation as well. Wood Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>) eggs experimentally maintained at 0.9&ndash;2.3&deg;C cooler temperatures during incubation produced females that were less likely to fledge, survive their first winter, and reproduce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Hepp1">Hepp and Kennamer 2012</xref>). By contrast, the daily minimum temperatures for the first 15 days after hatching in Great Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) nests explained most of the variation in postfledging survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Greno1">Greno et al. 2008</xref>). The relative sensitivity of nest survival to spring temperatures is poorly understood, especially for passerines that breed in temperate regions, and could explain population declines in addition to other climate-change-induced factors.Any temperature-related influences on nest survival are likely to be mediated by habitat. Different land covers have different biophysical effects on climate through a change in albedo, surface roughness, heat capacity, or water retention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Vargo1">Vargo et al. 2013</xref>). Concurrent with climate change, the ranges of many bird populations are undergoing rapid land-use changes and land-cover modification, with implications for local temperatures. The fastest-growing global land use is urban development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Seto1">Seto et al. 2012</xref>), which typically modifies the thermal environment, including milder winters and warmer summers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Oke1">Oke 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Grimmond1">Grimmond and Oke 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Pickett1">Pickett et al. 2011</xref>). Clearing land for urban development and introducing other anthropogenic stressors may be more important for nest survival than local temperature variation or long-term climate change, as has been observed for less anthropogenically influenced ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Clavero1">Clavero et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Cox1">Cox et al. 2013</xref>). Decreased vegetation density surrounding the nest, as often found in urban habitat, may decrease detection by predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Chalfoun1">Chalfoun and Martin 2009</xref>). Nest height was a significant factor for nest survival of Northern Cardinals (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cardinalis cardinalis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-SmithCastro1">Smith-Castro and Rodewald 2010</xref>), Silvereyes (<italic>Zosterops lateralis</italic>), and Eurasian Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus merula</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-vanHeezik1">van Heezik et al. 2008</xref>) breeding in urban habitat, where substrates of suitable height may be underrepresented. Species population trends and distribution patterns are more likely to be influenced by the synergistic effects of land-use change and climate change, as opposed to either global change factor in isolation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Feeley1">Feeley and Silman 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Jongsomjit1">Jongsomjit et al. 2013</xref>), and understanding those effects is necessary for mitigating the impact of global change on native species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-MantykaPringle1">Mantyka-Pringle et al. 2012</xref>).We studied the influence of variation in urban habitat and spring temperatures on nest survival of 3 sympatric songbird species in northern Nevada, USA. Our primary objectives were to determine (1) the variation in nest survival explained by slight temperature deviation compared with temperatures above and below physiological tolerances of eggs and nestlings, (2) the nesting stage most sensitive to temperatures, and (3) the relative importance of nest habitat to temperatures during nesting. We hypothesized that excessive heat or cold would influence nest survival more than slight deviations from baseline temperatures. We also hypothesized that nest survival would be more sensitive to temperatures after eggs hatched than during the egg-laying stage. Finally, we considered that in a disturbed urban ecosystem, temperature-related nest failure may be masked by land cover and anthropogenic sources of nest failure, such as human activity.Our study system was a series of municipal parks on a 15.25-km transect along the Truckee River, through the cities of Reno and Sparks in northern Nevada (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The city boundaries have expanded rapidly in the past 40 yr, establishing residential areas, suburbs, and industrial parks in a complex patchwork of land uses. Areas of natural vegetation, primarily sagebrush communities, and farmland remain where the boundaries of developed land parcels abruptly end. We selected the only available 7 public parks with a minimum of 3 ha (maximum &equals; 18 ha) that all contained at least some native riparian vegetation, were adjacent to the river, and represented the composite of land covers available in the urban matrix and reserves.Location of study area (star) in the western United States. Enlarged area of Reno and Sparks, Nevada, with study sites (black) connected by the Truckee River (black line). Location of the Reno/Cannon International Weather Station (Co-op ID: 266779) is marked by a plus sign. Enlarged images of 2 study sites demonstrate the within-site variation in land cover and among-site variation along the urban-to-rural gradient.The study area is on the border of the Great Basin and eastern Sierra Nevada, where there is strong interannual, seasonal, and intraseasonal temperature variation. Arid lands in the Southwest and Intermountain West regions of North America, including the Great Basin, are forecast to become warmer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Diffenbaugh1">Diffenbaugh et al. 2008</xref>). Average winter temperatures are 7&deg;C, and summers reach highs of 33&deg;C. The region is arid (mean annual precipitation &sim;190 mm), and most precipitation falls as snow during winter. Temperatures during the breeding season in spring and summer can vary greatly over a short period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Daily maximum temperatures (Tmax) in the study area during the breeding season, 2009&ndash;2012. The 20-yr Tmax average is shown with 95&percnt; confidence interval in a gray band. Upper shaded area marks a temperature threshold of 27&deg;C, the upper boundary of physiological zero. Lower shaded area marks the temperature threshold for 15&deg;C, below which nestlings are likely to be negatively affected by cold.We studied 3 synanthropic species&mdash;American Robin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;robin&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f03">Figure 3</xref>), Black-headed Grosbeak (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pheucticus melanocephalus</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;grosbeak&rdquo;), and Mourning Dove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida macroura</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;dove&rdquo;)&mdash;that differ in the length of their nesting season and their nest-habitat preferences. Doves and robins initiate nesting in early spring, when temperatures are often cold and unpredictable, and continue to nest through summer. Doves and robins are habitat generalists and construct nests in a wide range of substrates. Grosbeaks arrive in the study area at the very end of April and begin breeding in mid-May, when temperatures are usually warmer. Grosbeaks typically nest in denser vegetation close to the river, and they are less likely to be found in areas with high levels of human activity.Juvenile American Robin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus migratorius</named-content></italic>) on park bench. Photo credit: M. BeckerWe began nest searching in late March or early April and located nests by using behavioral cues of the adults or by visually scanning vegetation. We excluded 16 nests located higher than 8 m above ground because limited visibility made it difficult to accurately assess nest age and fate. The nests monitored below 8 m most likely represented the majority of nests constructed by our study species in the study area because they were constructed at mid- to low-level heights (3.9 &plusmn; 1.6 m) in relation to the height of nest trees (11.9 &plusmn; 7.0 m). A mirror pole was used to examine nest contents unless parents were observed feeding chicks or fledges. Nests were visited every 3 to 5 days until the nest failed or nestlings fledged. Visits between study sites were systematically rotated to ensure consistent search effort.Females of our study species typically lay 1 egg day<sup>&minus;1</sup>; therefore, the day the first egg was laid could be estimated with a high level of accuracy for nests observed in the middle of the laying sequence. For all other nests, we estimated clutch initiation by counting back from hatch day or by aging nestlings. Nestlings of uncertain hatch date were aged using reference photographs taken of nests for which the hatch day was observed. A single observer aged all nests.Nest fate was determined from the nest contents at consecutive visits to the nest. Nests checked and found empty &gt;4 days before the expected fledge date, with no signs of fledglings, were recorded as failed. Evidence of fledglings from auditory or visual observations, such as adults bringing food to fledglings near the nest tree, was used to confirm a successful nest. Alternative sources of nest failure, such as abandonment or depredation, could not be distinguished for most nests. Predators may consume eggs or chicks after parents abandon a nest and before the next visit by an observer, making it difficult to know the primary source of nest failure for observations at multiday intervals. Because temperatures can affect nestling physiology and parental behavior in ways that influence rates of both abandonment and nest depredation, it was not possible to distinguish sources of nest failure from the protocol we used.Daily temperatures in the study area are recorded continuously by a National Weather Station at the Reno Tahoe International Airport, located in proximity to the study sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We used 5 measures of temperature variability. The first 3 were intended to detect small changes from background levels of ambient temperatures. We calculated an average daily temperature for every ordinal day in the breeding season from a data set of the past 20 yr. This baseline average was used to standardize temperature deviation during the nesting cycle of a nest (Tdev) in the 4-yr study period by subtracting the baseline temperature from the same days in the year the nest was observed. Tdev avoids confounding day of the season with temperatures, because actual temperatures generally increase as the breeding season progresses. We then calculated average Tdev for a moving window in the 5 days after clutch initiation (Cdev) and 5 days after hatching (Hdev) to isolate the relative importance of those 2 stages. A 5-day window was used because complete incubation and full nest-attentiveness start after the final egg is laid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Wang1">Wang and Weathers 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Morton1">Morton and Pereyra 2010</xref>) and because nestling songbirds are least capable of thermoregulation in the first few days after hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Pereyra1">Pereyra and Morton 2001</xref>). In the 5-day moving window of temperatures, the daily deviation between the current year and the baseline temperature was averaged across 5 days.The other 2 temperature metrics were intended to capture heat events beyond the physiological tolerances of eggs or nestlings. Physiological zero temperatures range from 24&deg;C to 27&deg;C, and we used a conservative estimate of the upper limit to calculate the number of days that maximum daily temperatures were above 27&deg;C during the 5 days after clutch initiation for each nest (pzt). The temperature threshold for nestling survival is less specific, but reportedly, 11&ndash;20&deg;C may be required for mortality or tissue damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Mujahid1">Mujahid and Furuse 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Rippon1">Rippon et al. 2011</xref>). We used an intermediate threshold value of 15&deg;C that may correspond to negative consequences for nestlings in our study. The number of days with maximum temperature (Tmax) below 15&deg;C in the first 5 days after eggs hatched was also calculated for each nest that survived to hatching (u15). Daily Tmax was used to calculate the exposure of eggs and nestlings to suboptimal temperatures because it represents the capacity for temperatures to exceed our defined thresholds at any time in a day.Nest-site habitat has the potential to mediate predation risk and, therefore, nest fate. Nest-habitat variables considered in the analysis were nest height (nest ht), percentage of canopy cover within a 20-m radius (canopy20), and percentages of impervious surface and all vegetation within a 100-m radius (imperv100, veg100) and within a 500-m radius (imperv500, veg500). We selected spatial scales for their ecological relevance: 20 m for within territory, 100 m for approximate territory level, and 500 m for site level. Although other studies have included a larger extent for landscape-level influences on nests scattered in the matrix (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Ryder1">Ryder et al. 2010</xref>) or buffers around entire study sites (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Shustack1">Shustack and Rodewald 2010</xref>), we stopped at 500 m to avoid excessive overlap between adjacent buffers that would violate assumptions of spatial independence.We measured nest height (to nearest meter) with a clinometer. Areas of land-cover types within specified radii were calculated in ArcGIS (ArcMap 10; ESRI Software, Redlands, California, USA) using layers provided by the City of Reno (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-AMECEnvironmentandInfrastructure1">AMEC Environment and Infrastructure 2012</xref>). Land-cover types were classified using a geographic object-based image analysis based on 1-m-resolution orthophotographs captured in summer 2010 by the National Agriculture Imagery Program that yielded an overall accuracy of 94&percnt;. Canopy cover included only trees with a minimum crown diameter of 1 m. Impervious surfaces were any sealed surface, including buildings, sidewalks, and parking lots.Temperature and land-cover variation could mediate human disturbance through changes in activity at the study sites. Pedestrians have the potential to disturb birds in our study area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Schlesinger1">Schlesinger et al. 2008</xref>). We estimated levels of pedestrians (peds) along transects through each park in the 2011 breeding season to establish relative differences in human activity between sites. The study parks met specific recreational needs in their respective neighborhoods that did not change from year to year, and pedestrian traffic estimated in 2011 represented relative pedestrian traffic between study parks over the 4-yr study period. Line transects used for pedestrian surveys followed a foot or bicycle path through the entire length of each site and generally ran parallel to the river. Pedestrian traffic was recorded within a fixed distance of 100 m on either side of the transect footpath. We were able to observe everyone traveling on designated paths in relatively open habitat with a detection probability of &sim;100&percnt;. Pedestrians were recorded in units of people per kilometer per hour. Transects were started between 0630 and 1000 hours, and sites were assigned to 1 of 3 groups based on geographic proximity. The sampling order within a group was rotated at every visit to avoid a temporal bias. Within a round, all groups were sampled over 3 days and repeated 8 times over the season every 5&ndash;8 days for a constant observer effort between sites. We sampled on weekday mornings and in the absence of precipitation to avoid potential biases from temporal and weather-mediated variation in recreational use of the study sites.Nest survival was analyzed in Program MARK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>) for a series of maximum-likelihood-based models built with different combinations of individual covariates. Given that nests were clustered in time (years) and space (sites), we first examined site-, year-, and species-level effects by structuring the input file to group nests by those 3 factors. Species was the only grouping factor that introduced significant variation on nest survival, so we pooled data across years and sites. Correlations between covariates in the same model can be problematic. We found a significant correlation only between pedestrian traffic (peds) and vegetation at the 500-m scale (veg500; <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.92, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003), so we did not include those 2 terms in the same model.Tdev was a time-varying covariate: Every day of the nest cycle in the design matrix corresponded to a unique daily value for each nest in the input file. To separate the sensitivity of different nest stages to temperature, temperatures during egg laying (Cdev, pzt) contributed to modeled variance in daily nest survival only during the incubation period. Temperatures in the first 5 days after hatching (Hdev, u15) were designed to influence only nestling survival and excluded nests that failed during incubation (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 128). Two additional time-varying covariates were built into models using the design matrix. First, the day of clutch initiation for a nest in relation to the start of that year's breeding season (season) was allowed to increase for every consecutive day in the nesting cycle to represent the progression of dates over time. Second, all days over the entire nest cycle were assigned to a nest stage of egg laying, incubation, or nestlings (stage) for a time-varying trend. Habitat at a nest was unchanged for the duration of a nest cycle, and those variables were held constant over time.We standardized all covariates prior to employing the logit link for the analysis in MARK to account for different scales between the habitat and temperature variables. After <italic>z</italic>-transformation, the mean value for any covariate is zero. We substituted zero for the missing values of time-dependent temperature covariates (Tdev, Hdev, Cdev, pzt, u15) for the 15&percnt; of the nests that we were unable to age. Assigning the average covariate value to missing values does not change the mean but may slightly shrink the variance. Nests with uncertain age were first observed after egg laying was complete and failed prior to hatching.The relative fit of all models in the candidate set was assessed with an information-theoretic approach using the second-order Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>). Initial models included only species and a single covariate. In addition to modeling a single term for individual covariates in the simpler models, we also built models with a quadratic term for the covariate to allow for a nonlinear relationship with nest survival. Models were also constructed for an interaction term between an individual covariate and species, since the study species might respond differently to temperature and habitat. The only covariate that had more support for the species-interaction model than the additive model counterpart was nest stage. We then selected the better-performing single covariates representing time (season, stage), temperature (Tdev, Cdev, Hdev, pzt, u15), or habitat (nest ht, canopy20, imperv100, plant100, imperv500, plant500, peds) to construct more complex models with combinations of the most important covariates. Higher-performing models were given support by smaller &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> and larger AIC<sub>c</sub> weights. Important variables were included in the same number of candidate models to provide an unbiased AIC<sub>c</sub> weight.Cumulative daily survival, or nest survival probability, for each species was calculated by raising the estimated daily survival rate (DSR) from the top model to the number of exposure days in the entire nesting cycle. For estimates of a single nest stage, only the number of exposure days in that stage was used for the calculation. We used all the exposure days in the nesting cycle for nest survival probabilities associated with habitat variables (e.g., canopy cover) that did not change over the course of the nesting cycle. To determine the changes in nest survival probability at incremental levels of a given covariate (e.g., nestling stage or 10&percnt; canopy cover), user-defined values were entered to provide an estimate for the specified level of interest while holding all other covariates constant. Such reconstituted estimates for a covariate were then back-transformed from the logit scale for the reported beta estimate. Standard error values for the reconstituted survival probabilities were back-transformed from the logit scale by bootstrapping. All statistics other than nest survival estimates and cumulative survival probabilities are reported as means &plusmn; SD.Daily temperatures averaged over the 4-yr study period increased from 6.9&deg;C (&plusmn; 3.9&deg;C) in March to 19.6&deg;C (&plusmn; 4.5&deg;C) in June. Within the study period, 2009 and 2012 were warmer springs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Average daily temperatures between the first and second quartiles of clutch initiation were colder for doves and robins (11.7&deg;C and 11.8&deg;C) than for grosbeaks (15.0&deg;C), which is not surprising given that the first quartile of grosbeak nests was started 21 and 37 days later than those of robins and doves, respectively. The standard deviation in temperatures at any given day in the breeding season during the 20-yr baseline data set was &sim;4&deg;C of the mean. During our 4-yr study period, daily temperature deviation was within 4&deg;C of the 20-yr average for 75&percnt; of the nests during egg laying and for 65&percnt; of nests from hatch to fledging.Doves and robins built significantly higher nests (4.2 &plusmn; 1.6 m and 4.0 &plusmn; 1.6 m) than grosbeaks (2.9 &plusmn; 1.5 m; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,370</sub> &equals; 11.941, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Canopy cover within 20 m of a nest was also significantly greater for dove nests (31.1 &plusmn; 16.8&percnt;) and robin nests (28.1 &plusmn; 18.1&percnt;) than for grosbeak nests (22.2 &plusmn; 16.5&percnt;; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,370</sub> &equals; 5.050, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.007). Across all species, canopy and understory vegetation accounted for 53.0 &plusmn; 13.4&percnt; and impervious surfaces for 19.8 &plusmn; 7.4&percnt; of the land cover within 100 m of nests. At a 500-m radius from nests, the amount of canopy and vegetation (39.5 &plusmn; 8.7&percnt;) was more similar to the land cover by impervious surfaces (37.6 &plusmn; 11.5&percnt;). The estimated number of pedestrians walking through a site every hour ranged from none to 136 (31.4 &plusmn; 30.3) at the busiest downtown park.We monitored 159 robin nests, 163 dove nests, and 49 grosbeak nests from 2009 to 2012. The probability of nest survival for the entire nesting cycle was highest for grosbeaks at 68&percnt; (DSR &equals; 0.988 &plusmn; 0.004) and somewhat lower for doves and robins, with a respective probability of 53&percnt; (DSR &equals; 0.979 &plusmn; 0.010) and 44&percnt; (DSR &equals; 0.973 &plusmn; 0.013). Several variables were important for variation in daily nest survival. Both dove and grosbeak nests were more likely to fail during the nestling stage (doves: &beta; &equals; &minus;0.932 &plusmn; 0.259 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;; grosbeaks: &beta; &equals; &minus;1.049 &plusmn; 0.408 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;). Temperature during the first 5 days after eggs hatched (Hdev) was the most important temperature variable considered when fit with a quadratic term and included with species and nest stage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-t01">Table 1</xref>). Estimates of nestling survival probabilities from hatching to fledging were lowest at temperatures &minus;2&deg;C from baseline temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f04">Figure 4</xref>A). Across all species, nestling survival increased by 12&percnt; for every &plus;1&deg;C above baseline temperatures and also increased at temperatures below &minus;2&deg;C. Replacing temperature deviation in the nestling stage (Hdev) with temperature deviation for all days in the nesting period (Tdev) or during egg laying (Cdev) did not improve the model (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 10.89, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.004; &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 9.35, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.009). Models with the 2 variables for more excessively hot or cold temperatures, daily maximum temperatures above 27&deg;C (pzt) or below 15&deg;C (u15), were not supported by the data (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 22.92, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0; &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 22.36, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0). Nest survival did not vary significantly with season (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 21.45, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0).A summary of maximum-likelihood-based nest survival models for 3 species along an urban-to-rural gradient in Reno and Sparks, Nevada, USA. Variance in nest survival between year, site, and species were modeled with their respective terms. Models include covariates and are compared to the null model of constant survival S(.). Individual covariates included are the temperature deviation from a 20-yr average at hatching (Hdev) with a quadratic term (Hdev<sup>2</sup>), amount of canopy cover in a 20-m radius (canopy20), and rates of pedestrians at a study site (peds). An interaction term for species and nest stage (stage&ast;species) was also included to represent 3 stages of nesting that differ in daily survival rates. The highest AIC<sub>c</sub> value of all candidate models considered was 1,444.39.Fitted curve of nestling-survival probability estimates (&plusmn; SE) during the exposure days from hatch to fledging for (<bold>A</bold>) temperature deviations from a 20-yr baseline, (<bold>B</bold>) canopy cover within a 20-m radius of the nest, and (<bold>C</bold>) pedestrian traffic at the nest site. Fitted curve is for 3 species (American Robin, Mourning Dove, and Black-headed Grosbeak) breeding in urban habitat over a 4-yr study period.For the habitat variables considered, canopy cover in a 20-m radius was a significant factor in nest survival (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-t01">Table 1</xref>). The cumulative probability of nest survival increased by 3&percnt; for every increase of 10&percnt; canopy cover (&beta; &equals; 0.159 &plusmn; 0.076 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f04">Figure 4</xref>B). Apparent nest survival was highest at sites surrounded by more canopy, for all species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Sites with heavier pedestrian traffic (peds) had a positive influence on nest survival, and 10 more people per hour translated into a 2&percnt; increase in cumulative nest survival probability (&beta; &equals; 0.164 &plusmn; 0.085 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f04">Figure 4</xref>C). More robin and dove nests fledged at sites with more pedestrians, but pedestrian levels were similar between failed and fledged grosbeak nests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-f05">Figure 5</xref>B). Nest survival was not significantly related to nest height (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 21.05, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0) for the range of heights we observed.Differences in the amount of (<bold>A</bold>) canopy cover within a 20-m radius and (<bold>B</bold>) rates of pedestrian traffic (&plusmn; SE) at the nests of 3 species (American Robin, Mourning Dove, and Black-headed Grosbeak) that fledged young or failed to fledge young in urban habitat over a 4-yr study period.A few degrees of temperature deviation made a significant difference in nest survival, even in highly modified urban habitat. Nest survival increased at temperatures above and below baseline temperatures that did not exceed our defined optimal thermal range for egg and nestling development. Estimates of nest survival increased more at warmer relative temperatures, possibly reflecting a greater benefit to nest survival at warmer absolute temperatures, with only a small benefit to nesting at colder temperatures.The sensitivity of nest survival for robins, doves, and grosbeaks to slight changes in ambient air temperatures, which were well within the range of background levels, is consistent with the results of previous studies. Nests of the cavity-nesting White-headed Woodpecker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides albolarvatus</named-content></italic>) in central Oregon were more likely to fledge young at higher daily maximum temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Hollenbeck1">Hollenbeck et al. 2011</xref>), as were Lewis's Woodpeckers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanerpes lewis</named-content></italic>) in riparian woodlands of Idaho (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>). Two ground-nesting species, Lark Bunting (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calamospiza melanocorys</named-content></italic>) and Woodlark (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lullula arborea</named-content></italic>), also had higher nest survival at warmer average temperatures over the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Wright1">Wright et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Skagen1">Skagen and Yackel Adams 2012</xref>), possibly due to additive effects with precipitation events in cold and wet conditions. Only Mountain Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius montanus</named-content></italic>) breeding in eastern Colorado have been reported to increase nest survival at cooler temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Dreitz1">Dreitz et al. 2012</xref>). Weather during the nesting cycle may also have only a weak or negligible effect on productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Bradbury1">Bradbury et al. 2003</xref>), which suggests that the magnitude and direction of sensitivity may be related to species traits or habitat. Additionally, nest sites that are close to each other may experience differences in microclimate at the same area-wide temperatures, as could be the case in our study for the higher nests (above 8 m) whose fate we did not monitor.We were not able to observe the effects of extreme temperatures (e.g., heat wave, late spring blizzards) on nest survival, and such weather events may be detrimental to nest survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Newton1">Newton 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-McKechnie1">McKechnie and Wolf 2010</xref>). Temperatures believed to be in excess of the physiological tolerances of embryo development or nestling thermoregulatory ability may not have influenced nest survival in our study because extreme temperatures are difficult to define in an ecophysiological context. The temperature range we considered to be within comfortable limits for eggs or nestlings, 15&ndash;27&deg;C, may not necessarily be biologically meaningful. Eggs need to reach a critical temperature threshold of 24&ndash;27&deg;C to initiate embryonic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Webb1">Webb 1987</xref>); this threshold is usually reached in altricial songbirds once the female begins complete incubation after the penultimate egg is laid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Wang1">Wang and Weathers 2009</xref>). Incubation maintains egg temperature within the narrow range of 34&ndash;36&deg;C required for proper development. A few days of warm weather during egg laying may prematurely initiate embryonic development and expose eggs to daily minimum temperatures below the optimal range, resulting in egg inviability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Beissinger1">Beissinger et al. 2005</xref>). However, ambient air temperatures differ from egg temperatures because egg cooling rate is partly dependent on female nest attentiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Wang1">Wang and Weathers 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Morton1">Morton and Pereyra 2010</xref>). As such, there is no universal ambient temperature at which eggs are at risk of developmental arrest. Similarly, critical ambient-temperature thresholds for passerine nestling survival are not well established.In addition to direct abiotic effects on eggs and nestlings, temperature variation could have influenced nest survival indirectly through changes in predation risk. Some predators, such as snakes, may be more active at warmer temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Morrison1">Morrison and Bolger 2002</xref>), and higher energy requirements for thermoregulation in colder weather could stimulate increased foraging activity by some nest predators. In either case, daily nest survival would be expected to decrease at colder and warmer temperatures, the opposite of the results for our study species. Colder temperatures may also decrease the availabilty of invertebrate prey to nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2013</xref>), but of the 3 study species, grosbeaks are the only dietary specialists strongly associated with foliar insect prey.Short-term variation in temperatures during a single nest cycle may expose nest stages to different temperatures that could influence nest fate. As expected, nest survival was most sensitive to temperature deviation in the nestling period immediately after hatching, when young nestlings are less capable of thermoregulation. Nestlings may be more vulnerable than developing embryos to temperature variability because adults with nestlings may face a more intense trade-off between brooding young and leaving the nest to bring them food. Eggs are self nourishing, and incubating adults may be capable of buffering eggs from suboptimal temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Conway1">Conway and Martin 2000</xref>). Temperatures during egg laying could also be closer in time to the preferred short-term temperatures used as cues by females to initiate clutches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Wiebe1">Wiebe and Gerstmar 2010</xref>). Another explanation for the greater sensitivity of nestlings to temperatures is an indirect effect from changes in predation risk. Nestlings' behavioral adjustments in response to different temperatures, such as begging intensity, could have increased nest detection by predators during the nestling stage.Nest survival was correlated to urban habitat through variation in canopy cover and pedestrian traffic. Nests in isolated trees and narrow stands of trees in our study parks were also surrounded by other types of land cover, including lawn, structures, paved paths, and parking areas. Canopy cover within 20 m of the nest was positively associated with a higher nest-survival probability for all 3 study species that are low- to mid-level canopy nesters. Percent forest cover was also positively associated with increased DSRs of Indigo Buntings (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerina cyanea</named-content></italic>) and Acadian Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax virescens</named-content></italic>) in Midwestern forests at a much broader scale of a 10-km radius from the nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Cox1">Cox et al. 2013</xref>). The importance of land cover within 20 m of the nest in our study, and not at broader spatial scales at the territory and site levels, differed from the results of previous studies in urban landscapes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Ryder1">Ryder et al. (2010)</xref> found that impervious surfaces and canopy cover at a scale of 1,000 m were more important than at finer scales, down to 100 m for nest survival of several species breeding within the matrix of Washington, D.C., USA. In a study of riparian habitat adjacent to urban areas, land use within 400 m of the nest was the most important factor in nest survival of Least Bell's Vireo (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vireo bellii</named-content> pusillus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Kus1">Kus et al. 2008</xref>). However, when only 1 scale was considered for another riparian species, microhabitat within 5 m of the nest of Yellow Warblers (<italic>Setophaga petechia</italic>) influenced nest survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Latif1">Latif et al. 2011</xref>).Inconsistencies in study designs may contribute to mixed results on the influence of urban habitat on nest survival. Our study nests were located in parks that may have been less susceptible to disturbance than nests located in the surrounding matrix of heterogeneous urban land-cover types. Continuous nest monitoring at locations on an urban-to-rural gradient in North America occurs in urban reserves similar to ours (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Marzluff1">Marzluff et al. 2007</xref>), in larger forested plots (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Rodewald1">Rodewald et al. 2011</xref>), and within backyards contained in the matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Ryder1">Ryder et al. 2010</xref>). Inferred generalizations about the response of reproductive output to urban development need to consider the context in which the study sites are described.Several mechanisms might explain the benefits of canopy cover in our study, including the moderation of nest-site temperatures. Canopy cover, understory vegetation, and lawn generally cool air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Jenerette1">Jenerette et al. 2007</xref>), and some species may benefit from cooler nest temperatures to buffer hot temperatures late in the season. Vegetation above a nest will provide shade in the day and reduce heat loss from radiation at night. Canopy cover can also increase nest survival by mitigating predation risk. Nests in denser woody vegetation require more of a predator's search effort to find than a nest in an isolated tree or shrub (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Chalfoun1">Chalfoun and Martin 2009</xref>). In open woodland of Argentina, Red-crested Cardinal (<italic>Paroaria coronata</italic>) nests that had more vegetation within 50 cm above the nest were less likely to fail as a result of predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Segura1">Segura et al. 2012</xref>). Similarly, fledgling Eastern Bluebirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia sialis</named-content></italic>) in urban habitat survived their first 10 days out of nest boxes with more canopy cover within 30 m than nests where fledglings succumbed to predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Jackson1">Jackson et al. 2013</xref>). Increased vegetation or tree density may have deterred the corvids, raptors, or mammalian predators in our study area that hunt using visual or olfactory cues.The other important habitat factor was pedestrian traffic. Nest failure has been observed to increase in towns with more pedestrians at multiple sites across Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Jokimaki1">Jokim&auml;ki et al. 2005</xref>), an opposite result from that of our study, which sampled pedestrian activity at much finer spatial scales. Our results are not inconsistent with other studies that, in general, have found that predator abundance increases in urban areas even as predation rates decrease, posing a predation paradox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Rodewald1">Rodewald et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Fischer1">Fischer et al. 2012</xref>). Urban areas may provide a safe refuge for bird species able to tolerate human disturbance because of a disproportionately negative effect of pedestrians on predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Moller1">M&oslash;ller 2012</xref>). At the spatial level of study parks, we found a negative correlation between pedestrian traffic and vegetation cover, indicating potentially fewer refugia for mammalian mesopredators at the highly trafficked parks close to the urban core. The absence of suitable habitat and negative interactions with people may lead to predator interference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-18-Moller1">M&oslash;ller 2012</xref>) in the most urban sites.Both habitat and temperature contributed to the predictability of nest success in our study, and it was unexpected that air temperatures were as important for nest survival as the metrics of the urban environment that we sampled. Low-impact recreation by pedestrians did not appear to be negatively associated with nest survival for any of the species studied, and appeared to have a positive effect for the more synanthropic species. Although warming spring temperatures may be beneficial for some breeding birds up to a point, as suggested by our results, the effects of climate change will depend on land-use and land-cover characteristics of the urban landscape, including vegetation structure and level of human disturbance. Modeling interaction effects between land-use and climate change in future studies will be especially important for understanding vital rate and population responses of urban birds to global change.L. Saito, J. Sedinger, M. Forister, and S. Bassett reviewed drafts of the manuscript. D. Nonne assisted with survival analyses. S. Churchillo and J. Trammell provided GIS land cover layers. We thank two anonymous reviewers for their comments. Funding came from UNR EECB small grants and summer research stipends. Access to field sites was granted by City of Reno, Washoe County, and The Nature Conservancy. All field protocol for live birds was approved by UNR IACUC.