Vocal begging and locomotor activity are modulated independently in Bank Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) nestlingsStudies on the breeding biology of the sand martin <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic> (L.) (Aves) in artificial nest sitesParent-offspring recognition in bank swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>): II. Development and acoustic basisParent-offspring recognition in bank swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>): I. Natural historyNest life of the Bank SwallowCatch-up growth strategies differ between body structures: Interactions between age and structure-specific growth in wild nestling Alpine SwiftsSibling competition and the risk of falling out of the nestBirth order, individual sex and sex of competitors determine the outcome of conflict among siblings over parental careHatching asynchrony, sibling competition and siblicide in nestling birds: Studies of swiftlets and bee-eatersEffect of food shortage on the physiology and competitive abilities of sand martin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) nestlingsEffect of refeeding on growth, development and behavior of undernourished bank swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) nestlingsRelationship between avian growth rate and immune response depends on food availabilityExercise capacity of House Wren nestlings: Begging chicks are not working as hard as they canEnergetic costs of begging behaviourChick begging strategies in relation to brood hierarchies and hatching asynchronyBiparental care and offspring begging strategies: Hungry nestling blue tits move towards the fatherHow siblings adjust sib-sib communication and begging signals to each otherAdaptive significance of synchronized breeding in a colonial bird: a new hypothesisMuting individual nestlings reduces parental foraging for the broodParental feeding behaviour and sibling competition in the pied flycatcher <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>Weight differences, brood reduction, and sibling competition among nestling stonechats <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Saxicola torquata</named-content></italic> (Aves: Turdidae)Advantages and disadvantages of Bank Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) colonialityEfficacy and the design of begging signalsFood allocation among nestling starlings: Sibling competition and the scope of parental choiceThe evolution of complex begging displaysSignals of need in parent-offspring communication and their exploitation by the common cuckooNavigation in a cup: Chick positioning in great tit, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>, nestsBegging and food distribution in crimson rosella (<italic>Platycercus elegans</italic>) broods: Why don't hungry chicks beg more?Growth of late-hatched, competitively disadvantaged nestling house wrens relative to their older, larger nestmatesThe role of posturing and calling in the begging display of nestling birdsHatching asynchrony in European bee-eaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Merops apiaster</named-content></italic>Effects of experimental increase of corticosterone levels on begging behavior, immunity and parental provisioning rate in house sparrowsDifferences in begging behaviour between barn swallow, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>, nestlingsAmerican robin nestlings compete by jockeying for positionThe role of development, parental behavior, and nestmate competition in fledging of nestling Tree SwallowsHonest begging: Expanding from Signal of NeedIs there empirical evidence for the cost of begging?Brood size, sibling competition, and the cost of begging in great tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>)Sibling competition affects individual growth strategies in marsh tit, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus palustris</named-content></italic>, nestlingsThe breeding cycle in the bank swallowState-dependent begging with asymmetries and costs: A genetic algorithm approachRole of begging and sibling competition in foraging strategies of nestlingsBehavioral domination of food delivery by tree swallow nestlingsFood limitation in asynchronous bluethroat broods: Effects on food distribution, nestling begging, and parental provisioning rulesGrowth of nestling sand martinsNestlings of birds breeding in closed nests compete for food by both vocal begging and competing for a position near the nest entrance (locomotor activity). The latter strategy can be particularly effective in nests with long entrance tunnels, where nestlings can intercept feedings from incoming parents. However, little is known about whether the intensity of locomotor activity is related to food availability in the same way as the intensity of vocal begging. We hand-fed Bank Swallow nestlings (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) in the laboratory under four feeding regimes: without restriction (AL), or facing different levels of food restriction (in order of increasing degree: FR1, FR2, FR3). Compared with group AL, the intensity of vocal begging was elevated in group FR1 and did not increase further in the FR3 group, whereas only the FR3 nestlings showed higher locomotor activity (quantified as the frequency of crawling to the nest tunnel). The FR3 group was also the only group where reduced food intake slowed wing development. We conclude that vocal begging and locomotor activity were modulated independently by the level of food intake. We hypothesize that in young Bank Swallow nestlings locomotor activity is a more effective but also more expensive means of soliciting food than vocal begging and therefore is used only by the neediest of nestlings (e.g., those with impeded wing development). Our results illustrate the interplay between different components of complex begging displays serving to convey information about individual needs and competition with nestmates.Los pichones de las aves que se reproducen en nidos cerrados compiten por alimento mediante llamados de alimentaci&oacute;n y por una posici&oacute;n cerca de la entrada del nido (actividad locomotora). Esta &uacute;ltima estrategia puede ser particularmente efectiva en los nidos con t&uacute;neles largos como entrada, donde los pichones pueden interceptar el alimento que traen sus padres. Sin embargo, se sabe poco en cuanto a si la intensidad de la actividad locomotora se relaciona con la disponibilidad de alimento en el mismo modo que la intensidad de llamados de alimentaci&oacute;n. Alimentamos manualmente a pichones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic> en el laboratorio bajo cuatro reg&iacute;menes de alimentaci&oacute;n: sin restricci&oacute;n (AL) o enfrentando diferentes niveles de restricci&oacute;n alimenticia (en orden de menor a mayor: FR1, FR2, FR3). En comparaci&oacute;n con el grupo AL, la intensidad de los llamados de alimentaci&oacute;n se elev&oacute; en el grupo FR1, pero no increment&oacute; m&aacute;s en el grupo FR3, mientras que solo los pichones FR3 mostraron mayor actividad locomotora (cuantificada como la frecuencia de sus acercamientos al t&uacute;nel del nido). El grupo FR3 tambi&eacute;n fue el &uacute;nico en el que la reducci&oacute;n en la toma de alimento demor&oacute; el desarrollo de las alas. Concluimos que los llamados de alimentaci&oacute;n y la actividad locomotora fueron modulados independientemente por la cantidad de alimento ingerido. Formulamos la hip&oacute;tesis de que la actividad locomotora de los polluelos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. riparia</named-content></italic> es una forma m&aacute;s efectiva pero m&aacute;s costosa de solicitar alimento que los llamados vocales, por lo cual solo es empleada por los pichones m&aacute;s necesitados (e.g., aquellos con impedimentos en el desarrollo de sus alas). Nuestros resultados ilustran la interacci&oacute;n entre diferentes componentes de los despliegues complejos de ruego por alimento, que sirven para transmitir informaci&oacute;n sobre las necesidades individuales y la competencia con los compa&ntilde;eros de nido.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ruegos de alimentaci&oacute;n, comportamiento, pichones, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>Nestlings of altricial birds use vocal begging, gaping, neck stretching, gape color, etc., to inform parents about their needs and to compete with siblings for food (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Mock2">Mock and Parker 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Wright1">Wright and Leonard 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Mock1">Mock et al. 2011</xref>). However, nestlings can also use locomotor activity in competition for a favorable position within the nest cup, to get close to incoming parents (usually near the nest entrance; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-GreigSmith1">Greig-Smith 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Gottlander1">Gottlander 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-McRae1">McRae et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kacelnik1">Kacelnik et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Neuenschwander1">Neuenschwander et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Smiseth1">Smiseth et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kolliker1">K&ouml;lliker and Richner 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Dickens1">Dickens et al. 2008</xref>). The relative role of vocal begging and locomotor activity can vary. It is hypothesized that the rate of parental food provisioning depends mainly on vocal begging, whereas locomotor activity may be important in food allocation within the brood, because more-mobile nestlings can gain better access to parents than their nestmates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-RodriguezGirones1">Rodriguez-Girones et al. 2001</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Glassey1">Glassey and Forbes 2002</xref>). Thus, locomotor activity (and other forms of physical competition) serves to effectively intercept incoming parents, rather than to convey information about individual needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Mock1">Mock et al. 2011</xref>). The nestling's position in the nest is more important in securing feeding than vocal begging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Gottlander1">Gottlander 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Cotton1">Cotton et al. 1999</xref>), and may affect the intensity of vocal begging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Leonard1">Leonard et al. 2003</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Dreiss1">Dreiss et al. 2010</xref>). Some observations show that vocal begging and locomotor activity may be modulated independently by the chick (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Dickens1">Dickens et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Loiseau1">Loiseau et al. 2008</xref>). Such independent modulation can presumably enable better adjustment of the nestlings' behavior to their individual needs and competitive situation.Competition for nest position can be particularly effective in securing feeding in species breeding in burrows with entrance tunnels. In such nests, the direction of the parents' arrival with food is constrained by the position of the nest tunnel; field observations show that a position near the tunnel entrance or within the nest tunnel itself secures a higher feeding rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Asbirk1">Asbirk 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Lessells1">Lessells and Avery 1989</xref>). The Bank Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) is a particularly interesting species for studies of nestlings' vocal begging, locomotor activity, and sibling competition. This colonial species breeds in deep burrows, which reduces predation on nestlings (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Hoogland1">Hoogland and Sherman 1976</xref> for more discussion on the link between coloniality and predator pressure in Bank Swallow). Moreover, the constant presence of highly vocal adults near the breeding colony makes nestlings' vocal begging unlikely to affect predatory pressure (since predators can detect a colony by adult vocalization even when nestlings are quiet). Thus, predation exerts presumably little effect on the evolution of nestlings' behavior. On the other hand, as in other aerial insectivores, Bank Swallows face frequent and unpredictable periods of food shortage caused by inclement weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Emlen1">Emlen and Demong 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Asbirk1">Asbirk 1976</xref>), during which sibling competition for food could be particularly high.Under natural conditions, young Bank Swallows frequently enter the nest tunnel where they are fed by parents, and their locomotor activity may be a key factor in food distribution within the brood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beyer1">Beyer 1938</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Petersen1">Petersen 1955</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Asbirk1">Asbirk 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beecher2">Beecher et al. 1981b</xref>). In our earlier studies carried out under laboratory conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek2">2004</xref>) we found that food-restricted Bank Swallow nestlings enter the artificial nest tunnel more frequently than <italic>ad libitum</italic> fed individuals, but this behavior ceases soon after the beginning of refeeding. In the present study we further analyzed the effect of food intake on vocal begging and locomotor activity in young Bank Swallow nestlings hand-reared in artificial burrows. By &ldquo;locomotor activity&rdquo; we specifically mean the movements of nestlings within the nest tunnel, and we disregard as such the movements that are directly related to vocalization (like gaping or changes in posture within the nest cup). We hand-fed four groups of nestlings in the laboratory: fed without restriction, and facing three levels of underfeeding. This experimental design allowed us to examine how both vocal begging and locomotor activity change under the gradient of food intake. We assumed that locomotor activity may be a more effective (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Gottlander1">Gottlander 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Cotton1">Cotton et al. 1999</xref>) but also a more energetically costly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Chappell1">Chappell and Bachman 1998</xref>, also increased cooling rate) and risky (risk of falling out of the nest: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beyer1">Beyer 1938</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Bize2">Bize and Roulin 2006</xref>; increased exposure to predators) strategy than vocal begging. We therefore predicted that both locomotor activity and vocal begging should be more intense in underfed nestlings, but the thresholds of food restriction triggering these behavioral responses should differ. In particular, we expected that locomotor activity (crawling to the nest tunnel) should be used only by nestlings with lowest food intake that are willing to risk more in order to obtain feedings. Our experiment can broaden understanding of the evolution and role of complex begging displays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kilner1">Kilner 2002</xref>), particularly the interactions between signaling (vocal begging) and non-signaling (locomotor activity) components of begging display.Behavioral observations described in the present paper were carried out on Bank Swallow nestlings as a part of the larger experimental study of the effect of food availability on the tradeoff between immunocompetence and body mass growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>). Methods used in collecting and rearing of nestlings subjected to the present experiment are described in detail elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>). In brief, 36 six-day-old Bank Swallow nestlings were collected from 26 natural nests near Bia&lstrok;ystok (northeast Poland). Nests were inspected daily with a veterinary endoscope to detect hatching and evaluate nestling age. To eliminate the confounding effects of relatedness and hatching order, we did not use the last-hatched young, collected no more than two nestlings from each nest, and always assigned them randomly to different feeding regimes. Nestlings were brought to the laboratory and reared in artificial nests made of transparent plastic. Each nest cavity consisted of a cylindrical chamber (12 cm in diameter and 15 cm high) with the bottom modeled to mimic the nest cup, and an attached nest tunnel (a tube 30 cm long and 5 cm in diameter) with the end covered with netting. The nest cavities were covered with cardboard, leaving the tunnel entrance as the only place through which light entered. This mimicked light conditions in natural Bank Swallow nests. Nestlings were individually marked on the tarsus with a nonpermanent, xylene-free, nontoxic pen. The experiment was carried out in a climate chamber at 32&deg;C, 90&percnt; relative air humidity, and 16h/8h light/dark lighting regime.We created nine artificial broods of four nestlings each (typical natural brood size is 4&ndash;5 nestlings, P. Brz&eogon;k personal observation), and assigned them to four different feeding regimes for 3 days (days 6&ndash;9 of nestlings' life). Each artificial brood was kept in a separate artificial nest cavity. Initial body mass did not differ between experimental groups or artificial broods (nested ANOVA: <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.9 for both effects; mean &plusmn;SE was 7.16 &plusmn; 0.16 g in AL, 7.24 &plusmn; 0.21 g in FR1, 7.16 &plusmn; 0.26 g in FR2, and 7.16 &plusmn; 0.22 g in FR3 nestlings). Feeding regimes differed only with respect to food intake:12 nestlings (three whole artificial broods) were hand-fed every 45 min between 0600 and 2200 (22 feeding sessions daily). At each feeding bout nestlings were fed until they stopped begging in response to shadowing and touching (hereafter referred to as <italic>ad libitum</italic>, AL);the remaining 24 nestlings were divided into three groups (each of eight nestlings in two whole artificial broods) that were hand-fed every 45 min between 0800 and 2000 (17 feeding sessions daily) with a limited food amount during each feeding session. The feeding protocol was validated in our previous experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>) and enabled us to achieve a between-group gradient of reduction of body mass increments (these groups are referred to as FR1, FR2, FR3, with the latter fed the least amount of food). Feeding sessions in these groups were fewer than in the AL group (17 vs. 22), but the nestlings were weighed and controlled in the morning and in the evening, so the total handling time and frequency were similar in all regimes.Regimes AL, FR1, and FR3 are the same as used in the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski (2007)</xref> experiment, where they were referred to, respectively, as AL, I, and FR.Nestlings were fed alternately, with crickets and a special formula designed for the nestlings of insectivorous birds (J. Desselberger personal communication; detailed information presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>). Daily food intake was measured for each nestling as a difference of food mass individually recorded before and after each daily feeding period. Food intake per whole experiment averaged (mean &plusmn;SE) 183 &plusmn; 3.4 kJ in AL, 121 &plusmn; 2.4 kJ in FR1, 90 &plusmn; 1.5 kJ in FR2, and 74 &plusmn; 1.7 kJ in FR3 nestlings, and resulted in conspicuous between-group differences in body mass increments during the course of our experiment (AL 6.9 g, FR1 4.3 g, FR2 2.4 g, FR3 1.6 g, LSD test: <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.005 for all comparisons, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>). We intended to mimic the range of food conditions faced by nestlings in natural nests. Body mass of AL nestlings at the completion of our experiment matched that observed in wild birds of the same age of nine days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Turner1">Turner and Bryant 1979</xref>). Regimens FR1, FR2, and FR3 were intended to mimic feeding conditions under adverse weather, resulting in slowed growth (nestlings in natural broods can lose body mass during periods of low ambient temperature as brief as 2 days; P. Brz&eogon;k and M. Konarzewski personal observation).Upon completion of the third day of the experiment, we measured length of tarsus (nearest 0.1 mm with calipers) and wing (nearest 1 mm with a wing rule) of all nestlings. Our wing measurement included a combined length of both wing chord and developing primaries and thus quantified general development of flight apparatus. Nestlings were subsequently returned to their native nests, with the exception of two individuals that were returned earlier (see Statistical Analyses). Before the return to natal nests the individuals from groups FR1, FR2, and FR3 were refed <italic>ad libitum</italic> for 3&ndash;4 h.All experimental procedures were approved by the ethics committee (Lokalna Komisja Etyczna, permit no. LKE 68/OP/2001). Nestlings used in the present experiment were collected under permission of the Polish Ministry of Environment (Ministerstwo &Sacute;rodowiska, permit no. DLOPiK.og-4201-03-95/2001/2002).Locomotor activity of nestlings was quantified by recording the position of each nestling at the moment the artificial nest cavity was uncovered before each feeding session. A nestling was defined as being in the nest tunnel when its bill tip was at least 1 cm deep in the tunnel. However, in the majority of cases nestlings were found deep in the nest tunnel, frequently near its entrance. All nestlings were then removed from the artificial nest cavity, fed, and returned to the center of the nest cup. We quantified the nestlings' locomotor activity in two ways: (1) by calculating the frequency of entrances as the ratio of the number of feedings when a particular nestling was found in the nest tunnel to the total number of feedings; (2) by determining the average distance crawled by a nestling during the time between two feedings (calculated as the summed distance crawled by a nestling during all entrances divided by the total number of feedings). This average distance probably underestimates locomotor activity of FR3 nestlings because the covered distance was limited by the length of the artificial nest tunnel. However, the frequency of entrances was presumably not affected by this factor.Measurements of vocal begging effort would have disrupted the regular feeding schedule and thus affected the nestlings' locomotor activity. Thus, we decided to quantify the nestlings' vocal begging effort only once, after 2.5 days of experimentation. All nestlings were fed <italic>ad libitum</italic> and then fasted for 2 hours to reduce the effect of recent feeding on vocal begging effort. Each nestling was then individually placed in a separate artificial nest and, when it became calm, provoked to beg by shadowing and touching. Each nestling's vocalization was recorded digitally on a laptop computer with a Shure 16A microphone at 44.1 kHz and 16 bits, and subsequently analyzed using Cool Edit 2000 (Syntrillium Software Corporation, Phoenix, Arizona, USA). The whole trial was carried out once for each individual in an area where it could not hear other nestlings begging. For technical reasons we failed to collect credible recordings of vocal begging of the FR2 nestlings, and therefore they were excluded from subsequent analyses of vocal begging.At the age of 8&ndash;9 days, Bank Swallow nestlings produce relatively simple calls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beecher1">Beecher et al. 1981a</xref>). Therefore, we restricted our analysis to measurements of the length of begging bout duration and the number of calls (syllables) produced per bout. Nestlings produced begging calls in distinct series, and begging bout duration was estimated as the time between the beginning of the first and the end of the last call in a given bout.Similarly to our earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek2">2004</xref>), we only used data from the last two days of our experiment to quantify locomotor activity and omitted data from the first day when nestlings were developing behavioral responses to feeding treatments. In all analyses, we excluded two nestlings from AL group because they exhibited abnormally low food intake and low body mass increments (at the level of FR group; these nestlings were returned to their natal nests before the end of experimentation; they were also excluded from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref> study). Data for variables quantifying locomotor activity were transformed (arcsin for frequency of nest tunnel entrances, ln for average distance crawled by nestling during the time between two feedings) before analyses to improve homogeneity of variation. For the sake of accuracy we present non-transformed data for these variables in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref> and transformed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>, although all analyses were carried out on transformed data.Interactions between nestmates may affect a nestling's behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Caprioli1">Bonisoli-Alquati et al. 2011</xref>). Therefore, observations for individual nestlings in the same artificial brood were not independent and the effective sample size in our experiment was equal to the number of artificial broods. To control for non-independence of our observations, we analyzed them in two ways that used artificial brood, rather than individual nestling, as a single data point: (1) by means of nested ANOVA, with the feeding regime as a main factor and the artificial brood as a random factor nested within the feeding regime. We applied the MIXED procedure of SAS software that uses mean square error and degrees of freedom of a random factor when testing the significance of the main factor (see table 9.4 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Quinn1">Quinn and Keough 2002</xref>). When a significant effect of experimental group was found, we compared each food-restricted group to the AL group by means of the Dunnett's test; (2) by means of multiple regression using mean and the square of mean food intake (calculated for the whole experimental period) of each artificial brood as independent variables, and mean values of parameters quantifying nestlings' locomotor activity and vocal begging in each artificial brood as dependent variables. We thus tested the non-linearity of the effect of food intake on studied parameters.The effect of the artificial brood was not significant for tarsus and wing length, and thus they were analyzed only by means of ANCOVA with the effect of initial body mass as covariate. All analyses were carried out using SAS software (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA.; version 9.1.3), with two-tailed tests. The standard level of significance, &alpha; &equals; 0.05, was used.Frequency of nest tunnel entrances was significantly affected by feeding regime (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 6.09, df &equals; 3 and 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.040; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). Only the FR3 nestlings with the lowest food intake entered the nest tunnel more frequently than the AL nestlings (Dunnett's test; <italic>t</italic> &equals; 4.09, df &equals; 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.023). There was no difference in frequency of nest tunnel entrances between the AL nestlings and groups FR1 and FR2 (<italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.53, df &equals; 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.92, and <italic>t</italic> &equals; 1.33, df &equals; 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49, respectively). The effect of feeding regime on the average distance crawled by nestlings between two feedings was non-significant (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 5.13, df &equals; 3 and 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.055) but the trend shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref>B suggests that the pattern of between&ndash;feeding-regime variation was similar to that of the frequency of nest tunnel entrances.Multiple regression analysis revealed that the relationship between food intake and locomotor activity was not linear. The effects of both mean food intake and square of the mean food intake were significant for frequency of nest tunnel entrances (<italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> &equals; 0.80, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 11.69, df &equals; 2 and 6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.008, quadratic term: <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.024, linear term: <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.015; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>A) and for the average distance crawled by nestlings between two feedings (<italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> &equals; 0.74, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 8.74, df &equals; 2 and 6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.017, quadratic term: <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.028, linear term: <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.019; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>B).Feeding regimes exerted a significant effect on both begging bout duration (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 8.18, df &equals; 2 and 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.039; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref>C) and the number of syllables produced per bout (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 8.99, df &equals; 2 and 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.033; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref>D). The AL nestlings begged for a shorter time and produced fewer syllables per bout than nestlings in the FR1 group (Dunnett's test; <italic>t</italic> &equals; 3.81, df &equals; 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.033, and <italic>t</italic> &equals; 4.19, df &equals; 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.024, respectively). On the other hand, the difference between the AL and FR3 nestlings was non-significant for begging duration (<italic>t</italic> &equals; 2.92, df &equals; 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.074) and for the number of syllables produced per bout (<italic>t</italic> &equals; 2.44, df &equals; 4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12).Regression analysis carried out on the mean values for artificial broods did not find a significant effect of food intake on parameters quantifying vocal begging effort of nestlings (begging bout duration: <italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> &equals; 0.53, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 5.53, df &equals; 1 and 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.065, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>C; number of syllables produced per bout: <italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> &equals; 0.37, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 2.94, df &equals; 1 and 5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>D).Feeding regimes exerted a significant effect on both tarsus length (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 9.77, df &equals; 3 and 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; initial body mass was significant as covariate: <italic>F</italic> &equals; 26.92, df &equals; 1 and 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f03">Figure 3</xref>A), and wing length (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 15.58, df &equals; 3 and 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; initial body mass was significant as covariate: <italic>F</italic> &equals; 42.46, df &equals; 1 and 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f03">Figure 3</xref>B) at the completion of our experiment. Tarsus length of the AL nestlings differed significantly from that of the FR2 and FR3 nestlings (Dunnett's test; <italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;4.31, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, and <italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;4.70, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively), but not from the FR1 nestlings (<italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;1.84, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.19). The final wing length did not differ between the AL and FR1 (<italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;0.53, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.9) or the AL and FR2 (<italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;2.23, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.088) groups, but was significantly different between the AL and FR3 nestlings (<italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;6.33, df &equals; 29, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Our experiment offered a unique opportunity to analyze behavioral responses in nestlings of a burrow-breeding, otherwise difficult-to-study species. An increase in the intensity of nestling movements during food shortage or in enlarged broods has been described in many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Gottlander1">Gottlander 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-McRae1">McRae et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kacelnik1">Kacelnik et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Neuenschwander1">Neuenschwander et al. 2003</xref>). However, we showed for the first time that this increase is not proportional to food intake (in our experiment it appeared only in the FR3 group with the lowest food intake), and that it is related to food intake differently from the intensity of vocal begging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">2</xref>). Under laboratory conditions, we could not demonstrate that locomotor activity improves nestlings' feeding prospects. However, young Bank Swallows in natural nests frequently enter the nest tunnel where they are fed by their parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beyer1">Beyer 1938</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Petersen1">Petersen 1955</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Asbirk1">Asbirk 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beecher2">Beecher et al. 1981b</xref>), and such behavior was already reported in 9-day-old Bank Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Petersen1">Petersen 1955</xref>), i.e. at the same age as on the last day of our experiment.Young Bank Swallows from the FR1 group vocalized more intensively than the individuals fed <italic>ad libitum</italic> but, unexpectedly, the intensity of vocalization of the AL and FR3 nestlings did not differ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">Figure 1</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">1</xref>D; see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">Figure 2</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f02">2</xref>D). The latter may reflect a genuine decrease in the intensity of vocal begging in the FR3 group or may be due to the insufficient power of our testing. In any case, our results clearly suggest that the FR3 nestlings did not beg more than the FR1 nestlings, in spite of highly significant differences in food intake between these groups. This pattern agrees with theoretical predictions that vocal begging should be relatively independent of nestlings' needs in species with safe nests and high risk of starvation (like aerial insectivores, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Price1">Price et al. 2002</xref>). Likewise, low food intake or poor condition of the nestlings does not always increase the intensity of vocal begging (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Lotem1">Lotem 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Krebs1">Krebs 2001</xref>). Our results hinge on the assumption that begging bout duration and the number of calls adequately characterize begging effort. Bank Swallows at &lt;10 days of age produce relatively simple calls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beecher1">Beecher et al. 1981a</xref>), which offer little possibility for fine modulation of acoustic parameters. Also, we found that nestlings subjected to different feeding treatments did not differ in the average length of a single call (including those AL nestlings that responded during vocal begging trial; data not shown). Therefore, we conclude that only FR3 nestlings with the lowest food intake were willing to enter the nest tunnel more frequently than birds from group AL, whereas the intensity of vocal begging was elevated in moderately undernourished group FR1 but did not increase further in group FR3.In our experiment, we did not directly quantify the costs and benefits of vocal begging and locomotor activity. Thus, we cannot unambiguously identify the proximate mechanisms responsible for the observed patterns of behavior. However, based on the results of other studies, we hypothesize that in Bank Swallows and other burrow-breeding species, locomotor activity is more costly and risky, but also a more effective strategy than vocal begging. The latter is hypothesized to be energetically cheap (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Chappell2">Chappell and Bachman 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-MorenoRueda1">Moreno-Rueda 2007</xref>). Likewise, nests of Bank Swallows are relatively safe, and thus nestlings' vocalizations are unlikely to increase predator pressure. On the other hand, although we are not aware of any direct estimate of energetic costs of nestlings' crawling, they may be not negligible. In nestling House Wrens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Troglodytes aedon</named-content></italic>), intense movements result in similar or higher oxygen consumption than vocal begging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Chappell1">Chappell and Bachman 1998</xref>). In the Blue-throated Bee-eater (<italic>Merops viridis</italic>), another burrow-breeding aerial insectivore, the intense sibling competition in asynchronous broods leads to higher energy expenditure, interpreted as the cost of increased locomotor activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Bryant1">Bryant and Tatner 1990</xref>). Moreover, even if direct energetic costs of locomotor activity are low, nestlings that enter the nest tunnel can suffer higher cooling rates because of the lack of brooding from nestmates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>). Nestlings entering the nest tunnel also risk falling out of the nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Beyer1">Beyer 1938</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Bize2">Bize and Roulin 2006</xref>) and may be more exposed to the attack of predators than in the nest chamber.On the other hand, even if locomotor activity or jostling for a favorable position in the nest is presumably more costly/risky than vocalization, it can be more effective in securing feeding than vocal begging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Gottlander1">Gottlander 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Cotton1">Cotton et al. 1999</xref>). This may be particularly true in Bank Swallows, because a nestling can physically block the nest tunnel and restrict parental opportunity for feeding its nestmates (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Slagsvold1">Slagsvold and Rohwer 2000</xref>). Moreover, in cavity nesters vocal signals can become obstructed by walls of the nest chamber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Horn1">Horn and Leonard 2002</xref>) and therefore can be less effective at conveying information about individual nestlings. However, some level of vocal activity may still be necessary even for nestlings that use locomotor activity. First, parents usually adjust provisioning rate to the average level of begging in the brood (strikingly, even a lone chick of the Common Cuckoo <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cuculus canorus</named-content></italic> tries to mimic begging of the whole brood of host nestlings; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kilner2">Kilner et al. 1999</xref>). Thus, the silence of nestlings may reduce the rate of food delivery to the nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Glassey1">Glassey and Forbes 2002</xref>). Vocalization in Bank Swallow nestlings may also be necessary to trigger feeding from an incoming parent that otherwise could simply ignore a silent nestling in the nest tunnel.Although food restriction affected body mass increments and/or tarsus development in the FR1 and FR2 groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f03">Figure 3</xref>A; see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f01">figure 1</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>), wing development was impeded only in group FR3, with the lowest food intake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-f03">Figure 3</xref>B). Development of wings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Nilsson1">Nilsson and G&aring;rdmark 2001</xref>) and primaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Lago1">Lago et al. 2000</xref>) has high priority in undernourished nestlings, because they are critical for successful fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Michaud1">Michaud and Leonard 2000</xref>) and require longer compensation during refeeding than body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>). Therefore, the potential long-term effect of low food intake was likely to be much higher in the FR3 than in FR1 and FR2 groups. We hypothesize that it may be the reason why only the FR3 nestlings decided to embark on crawling into the nest tunnel to improve their feeding prospects. Therefore, locomotor activity could be seen as a &ldquo;last resort&rdquo; strategy, used only by very needy individuals. However, relative costs and benefits of this behavior can change with age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kilner1">Kilner 2002</xref>). For example, costs of locomotor activity can be lower in older nestlings (because of better thermoregulation or locomotor coordination) and they may be more willing to enter the nest tunnel even when they are less hungry. Moreover, we admit that different benefits and costs (mainly energetic) of locomotor activity and vocal begging may not be the only factors that affect nestlings' decisions of when to use these strategies. For example, in young Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) the intensity of vocal begging depends on the nestlings' position within the nest cup (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Leonard1">Leonard et al. 2003</xref>), suggesting interaction between vocal begging and locomotor activity.In conclusion, we showed that in underfed, 7&ndash;9-day-old Bank Swallow nestlings vocal begging and locomotor activity are related to the level of food intake in a different way. Moderately underfed individuals only increase their vocal begging, but not their locomotor activity. However, when the magnitude of undernourishment drops below some threshold level and affects development of important body components such as the wings, nestlings begin entering the nest tunnel, while maintaining the intensity of vocal begging at the level similar to moderately underfed individuals. Thus, vocal begging and locomotor activity are triggered by different levels of food intake, and we hypothesize that observed patterns can reflect different costs and potential benefits of these behaviors. These results show that different components of a complex begging display can be modulated independently. Therefore, our study may help in understanding the role and evolution of complex begging displays in young birds (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-215-Kilner1">Kilner 2002</xref>).We are very grateful for help of Ma&lstrok;gorzata Lewoc, Bogus&lstrok;aw Lewonczuk, Ma&lstrok;gorzata Olkowska, and Joanna Przydacz with nestlings' feeding. Kevin D. Kohl helped to edit the paper. This work was supported by the State Committee for Scientific Research of the Republic of Poland (6 P04F 098 21 to P.B.).Frequency of entrances by Bank Swallow nestlings into nest tunnel (<bold>A</bold>), average distance crawled by nestling between two feedings (<bold>B</bold>), begging bout duration (<bold>C</bold>), and number of syllables produced per bout (<bold>D</bold>) for four experimental feeding regimes. Each point depicts an individual nestling. Symbol shapes indicate feeding regime: squares (FR3), rhombuses (FR2), triangles (FR1), circles (AL); non-transformed data are shown. For technical reasons we failed to collect credible recordings of vocal begging of the FR2 nestlings and thus this group is missing in (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>).Frequency of entrances by Bank Swallow nestlings into nest tunnel (<bold>A</bold>), average distance crawled by nestling between two feedings (<bold>B</bold>), begging bout duration (<bold>C</bold>), and number of syllables produced per bout (<bold>D</bold>) in nine (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) or seven (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) artificial broods plotted against food intake (in kJ). Each point depicts mean value for one artificial brood. For technical reasons we failed to collect credible recordings of vocal begging of the FR2 nestlings and thus this group is missing in (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>). Symbol shapes indicate feeding regime: squares (FR3), rhombuses (FR2), triangles (FR1), circles (AL). Lines and respective equations indicate multiple ((<bold>A</bold>): y &equals; 0.000104&ast;x<sup>2</sup> &minus; 0.0318&ast;x &plus; 2.439, (<bold>B</bold>): y &equals; 0.000316&ast;x<sup>2</sup> &minus; 0.0944&ast;x &plus; 6.934) and linear ((<bold>C</bold>): y &equals; &minus;0.0278&ast;x &plus; 7.194, (<bold>D</bold>): y &equals; &minus;0.0986&ast;x &plus; 27.12) regressions fitted to data. Slopes of regression lines on (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>) are not significant (see Results) but we show them to indicate the trends. On (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>), transformed data are shown; on (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>), non-transformed data are shown.Tarsus length (<bold>A</bold>) and wing length (<bold>B</bold>) at the completion of the experiment in Bank Swallow nestlings under four experimental feeding regimes. Values are residuals corrected for initial body mass. Each point depicts an individual nestling. Symbol shapes indicate feeding regime: squares (FR3), rhombuses (FR2), triangles (FR1), circles (AL).