Tradeoffs between predation risk and fruit resources shape habitat use of landbirds during autumn migrationCorrelation between raptor and songbird numbers at a migratory stopover siteOptimal bird migration: The relative importance of time, energy, and safetyThe effect of diet composition on migratory fuelling in Garden Warblers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia borin</named-content></italic>Nutritional mechanisms and temporal control of migratory energy accumulation in birdslme4: Linear mixed-effects moels using Eigen and S4Wintering Yellow-rumped Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendroica coronata</named-content></italic>) track manipulated abundance of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Myrica cerifera</named-content></italic> fruitsHazardous duty pay and the foraging cost of predationThe ecology of fear: Optimal foraging, game theory, and trophic interactionsEnergetic constraints and predation pressure during stopoverFat affects predator-avoidance behavior in Gray Catbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dumetella carolinensis</named-content></italic>) during migratory stopoverPasserine migrants respond to variation in predation risk during stopoverTradeoffs between foraging and predation risk determine habitat useScale-dependent habitat use by fall migratory birds: Vegetation structure, floristics, and geographyMigratory fuelling in Blackcaps (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia atricapilla</named-content></italic>) under perceived risk of predationForaging and predator avoidance: A test of a patch choice model with juvenile bluegill sunfishTradeoffs between predation risk and forage differ between migrant strategies in a migratory ungulateFlight performance in relation to fuel load in birdsOptimum fuel loads in migratory birds: Distinguishing between time and energy minimizationGeneral results concerning the tradeoff between gaining energy and avoiding predationHabitat selection by nonbreeding, migratory land birdsOn the importance of en route periods to the conservation of migratory landbirdsquantreg: Quantile regressionHunger-dependency of hiding behaviour after a predator attack in dominant and subordinate Willow TitsOptimal foraging, predation risk and territory defenseImpaired predator evasion in fat Blackcaps (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia atricapilla</named-content></italic>)Vigilance during the initiation of daily feeding in Dark-eyed JuncosBehavioral decisions made under the risk of predation: A review and prospectusFinch flock size and risk of hawk predation at a migratory stopover siteThe role of predation risk in stopover habitat selection in migrating Bramblings, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Fringilla montifringilla</named-content></italic>Optimal fat loads in migrating birds: A test of the time-minimization hypothesisDiet and preparation for spring migration in captive Hermit Thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus guttatus</named-content></italic>)Landscape-scale habitat availability, and not local geography, predicts migratory landbird stopover across the Gulf of MaineChanging priorities: The effect of pre-migratory fattening on the tradeoff between foraging and vigilanceResumption of feeding under risk of predation: Effect of migratory conditionMechanisms of <italic>en route</italic> habitat selection: How do migrants make habitat decisions during stopover?Stopover and fat deposition by North American wood-warblers (Parulinae) following spring migration over the Gulf of MexicoHabitat requirements during migration: Important link in conservationThe influence of weather, geography, and habitat on migrating raptors on Cape May PeninsulaMatching ephemeral resources on autumnal stopover and the potential for mismatchPatterns of frugivory and energetic condition in Nearctic landbirds during autumn migrationBehavioral, energetic, and conservation implications of foraging plasticity during migrationLiving off the wax of the land: Bayberries and Yellow-rumped WarblersFeeding&ndash;danger trade-offs underlie stopover site selection by migrants. Avian Conservation and EcologyExperimental evidence that migrants adjust usage at a stopover site to trade off food and dangerActivities of a migrant Merlin during an island stopoverHabitat use and behavior of mixed species landbird flocks during fall migrationStopover habitat use by spring migrant landbirds: The roles of habitat structure, leaf development, and food availabilityScale-dependent habitat selection in migratory frugivorous passerinesBehavior of fish predators and their prey: Habitat choice between open water and dense vegetationOptimal bird migration and predation risk: A field experiment with Northern Wheatears <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Oenanthe oenanthe</named-content></italic>Effects of fat and lean body mass on migatory landbird stopover durationPrey uncertainty and the balancing of antipredator and feeding needsMigrant songbird species distribution and habitat use during stopover on two islands in the Gulf of MaineUse of successional habitat and fruit resources by songbirds during autumn migration in central New JerseyCompensatory mechanisms for ameliorating the fundamental tradeoff between predator avoidance and foragingDoes the risk of encountering lions influence African herbivore behaviour at waterholes?Vegetative and fruit resources as determinants of habitat use by mature-forest birds during the postbreeding periodHabitat associations and community of birds in shrubsteppe environmentsEffects of weather on autumn hawk movements at Fort Morgan, AlabamaMultiple effects of weather on the starvation and predation risk tradeoff in choice of feeding location in RedshanksEffects of predator landscapes on the evolutionary ecology of routing, timing and molt by long-distance migrantsWestern Sandpipers have altered migration tactics as Peregrine Falcon populations have recoveredWhile foraging, animals often trade off between food and safety, reducing feeding in response to increased predation risk. This response, however, may not be a viable option for animals that are energetically compromised. Many single-species studies have shown that hungry animals select habitats within which foraging opportunities are greater even if predation pressures are higher, but it is unclear whether these patterns can be extrapolated to entire communities. Here, we examined the stopover habitat use of 28 frugivorous landbird species along the coast of Maine, USA, during an energetically demanding period of the annual cycle, fall migration. Across 6 stopover sites, we determined whether or not a tradeoff existed between using safe habitat patches (patches with high woody plant stem density) and patches with high food resources (patches with high fruit abundance). Controlling for raptor abundance at a site, landbird migrants were captured at higher rates in sites where no tradeoff existed, suggesting that birds avoided staying in sites where there was a predation risk&ndash;foraging tradeoff. At all sites, regardless of the presence or absence of a tradeoff, longer-distance migrants used patches with high food availability more frequently than shorter-distance migrants; patch use by shorter-distance migrants was explained by habitat cover alone. Our findings suggest that, for the Gulf of Maine, birds reduce predation risk at the scale of a stopover site, and differences in habitat selection at finer patch scales are mediated by migration strategy.Mientras se alimentan, los animales frecuentemente balancean la alimentaci&oacute;n y la seguridad, reduciendo el consumo de alimentos como respuesta a un mayor riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n. Esta respuesta, sin embargo, puede no ser una opci&oacute;n viable para los animales que est&aacute;n energ&eacute;ticamente comprometidos. Muchos estudios de especies individuales han mostrado que los animales hambrientos seleccionan los h&aacute;bitats donde las oportunidades de forrajeo son mayores, incluso si las presiones de depredaci&oacute;n son m&aacute;s altas, pero no est&aacute; claro cu&aacute;n generalizable son estos patrones a las comunidades completas. Aqu&iacute; examinamos el uso del h&aacute;bitat de parada por parte de 28 especies de aves terrestres frug&iacute;voras a lo largo de la costa de Maine, EEUU, durante un per&iacute;odo energ&eacute;ticamente demandante del ciclo anual, la migraci&oacute;n de oto&ntilde;o. A lo largo de seis sitios de parada determinamos si exist&iacute;a o no un balance entre los parches de h&aacute;bitat seguros (parches con una alta densidad de tallos) y los parches con muchos recursos alimenticios (parches con una alta abundancia de frutos). Luego de controlar por la abundancia de rapaces en cada sitio, las aves migratorias terrestres presentaron mayores tasas de captura en los sitios sin un balance, sugiriendo que las aves evitan permanecer en los sitios donde existe un balance entre el riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n y el forrajeo. En todos los sitios, independientemente de la presencia de un balance, los migrantes de distancia m&aacute;s larga usaron m&aacute;s frecuentemente los parches con alta disponibilidad de alimentos, mientras que el uso de los parches por parte de los migrantes de menor distancia fue explicado solamente por la cobertura de h&aacute;bitat. Nuestros resultados sugieren que para el Golfo de Maine, las aves alivianan el riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n a la escala de sitio de parada, y las diferencias en la selecci&oacute;n de h&aacute;bitat a escalas m&aacute;s finas de parche est&aacute;n determinadas por la estrategia de migraci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> aves terrestres, depredaci&oacute;n, forrajeo, fruta, migraci&oacute;n, riesgo, sitio de parada, uso de h&aacute;bitat, vegetaci&oacute;nFood acquisition and predator avoidance are fundamental components of the survival strategy of most animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Furness 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Houston1">Houston et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cowlishaw1">Cowlishaw 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Brown1">Brown and Kotler 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hebblewhite1">Hebblewhite and Merrill 2009</xref>). To maximize fitness, animals often trade off between foraging and either increased vigilance for predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Brown2">Brown et al. 1999</xref>), flocking behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lindstrom1">Lindstr&ouml;m 1989</xref>), time spent in a patch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Ydenberg2">Ydenberg et al. 2004</xref>), or crypsis (reduced rates of movement or protective cover; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Thaler1">Thaler et al. 2012</xref>). In situations in which animals are energetically constrained, however, the costs of reducing the time spent foraging to decrease predation risk may be prohibitively high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Krebs1">Krebs 1980</xref>).Predation risk can be a strong modifier of animal habitat selection (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lima1">Lima 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Gotceitas1">Gotceitas 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lindstrom2">Lindstr&ouml;m 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Yasue1">Yasu&eacute; et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hebblewhite1">Hebblewhite and Merrill 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Thaler1">Thaler et al. 2012</xref>). As a rule, animals choose feeding habitats that allow them to meet their energetic requirements while minimizing predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Yasue1">Yasu&eacute; et al. 2003</xref>), and avoid areas with high predation risk even if these areas would maximize foraging efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Gotceitas1">Gotceitas 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Pomeroy2">Pomeroy et al. 2006</xref>). In times of higher-than-average energetic demand, however, added predation risk may be outweighed by the costs of decreased foraging efficiency in safer habitats.Migration may be such a period, during which the tradeoff between foraging and predation risk shifts predictably. Migration is energetically expensive, and suitable habitats for rest and refueling are critical for successful migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hutto1">Hutto 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore4">Moore et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Rodewald2">Rodewald and Brittingham 2007</xref>). The large scale of migration further increases risks to survival, because individuals find themselves in unfamiliar environments with unknown predation pressures while trying to balance predator evasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore1">Moore 1994</xref>) and food acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore2">Moore and Aborn 2000</xref>) under higher-than-average energetic demand. Predation risk varies both spatially and temporally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Sih1">Sih 1992</xref>), so migrating animals must renegotiate the tradeoff between predation risk and energetic demand across a multitude of sites en route. Further, major landscape features (e.g., coastlines and water resources) are known to concentrate both migratory animals and their predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Aborn1">Aborn 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Valeix1">Valeix et al. 2009</xref>). Therefore, the benefits of optimal behaviors are likely greatest at these choke points, as they concentrate landbirds (often before over-water flights) and their aerial predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Aborn1">Aborn 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Schmaljohann1">Schmaljohann and Dierschke 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-DeSorbo1">DeSorbo et al. 2012</xref>). Predator risk is thus increased at the same time as energetic demand.Together, these added challenges during migration are likely to shift the optimal solution to the foraging vs. predator avoidance tradeoff. For example, studies of both passerine songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore1">Moore 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cimprich3">Cimprich et al. 2005</xref>) and charadriiform shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Furness 1984</xref>) have demonstrated that individuals in migratory condition decrease crypsis and vigilance relative to individuals that are not migrating.Further, the high energetic demands of migration affect an individual's energy stores, which control behavioral responses to the predation risk&ndash;foraging tradeoff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cimprich1">Cimprich and Moore 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Pomeroy1">Pomeroy et al. 2008</xref>). Fat stores can alter flight performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hedenstrom1">Hedenstr&ouml;m 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cimprich2">Cimprich and Moore 2006</xref>) and motivation to forage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Krebs1">Krebs 1980</xref>), such that fatter birds increase vigilance while leaner birds take more risks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lima2">Lima and Dill 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Koivula1">Koivula et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cimprich2">Cimprich and Moore 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lindstrom3">Lindstr&ouml;m and Alerstam (1992)</xref>, however, state that each individual may have a &ldquo;set point,&rdquo; or optimal fuel load, at which point its motivation to forage decreases, which may disrupt any correlation between fuel load and antipredator behavior.In this study, we assessed stopover habitat use by 28 species of passeriform and piciform birds (hereafter, &ldquo;landbirds&rdquo;) under the increased risk and energetic demand of migration along the coast. While single-species studies are invaluable for determining specific behavioral and physiological reactions to predation, it is difficult to translate that information into multispecies migration habitat conservation and management efforts. To understand the community-level response to tradeoffs between predation risk and foraging demand, we examined the habitat use of the entire migratory landbird community during fall migration along the coast of Maine, USA, at 2 types of stopover sites: (1) sites where the local habitat composition forces birds to make a tradeoff between predator avoidance and food availability, and (2) sites where such a tradeoff is not necessary. In sites of the first type, the habitat patches with the highest food availability have relatively little protective cover. In the second site type, birds do not face a tradeoff between predation avoidance and foraging, because the patches with the highest food availability are also the patches with the highest structural cover within the site. We used weekly relationships between fruit and cover to allow the presence (or absence) of a tradeoff between fruit availability and cover at a particular site to vary throughout the season as fruit availability changed.Our study design explicitly tested how well fruit availability predicted habitat patch use within a stopover site each week as a function of: (1) the structural cover present within the same patch, (2) whether the stopover site as a whole possessed or lacked characteristics forcing a tradeoff between cover and fruit availability, and (3) the site-level abundance of avian predators. Further, because we examined all 28 commonly caught species in our migrant community, we were able to assess whether migration distance, which likely influences energetic demand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Bairlein2">Bairlein and Gwinner 1994</xref>), affected the interactions among these 3 patch- and site-level covariates.Specifically, we predicted that birds presented with a tradeoff between fruit availability and cover would accept more risk (use patches with relatively less cover) than those not facing such a tradeoff, given the high energetic demand of migration. Further, we expected that low raptor abundance would increase the impact of fruit availability on patch use within sites requiring a tradeoff, relative to sites not requiring a tradeoff. Finally, we predicted that these 2 differences between tradeoff and nontradeoff sites would be greater for species with longer migration distances, as they are presented with the greatest energetic constraints.We sampled fall-migrating landbirds and their stopover habitat in the DownEast and MidCoast regions of Maine during 2011&ndash;2012 at 6 monitoring stations, including 2 coastal headland and 4 island sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We considered each monitoring station as a largely independent stopover site. Each station was no closer than 10 km to the nearest station (mean nearest station distance &plusmn; SE &equals; 23 &plusmn; 10 km; mean pairwise distance among all stations &equals; 46 &plusmn; 9 km). Within each of our monitoring sites we sampled habitat use through bird captures, using passive mist nets placed in a variety of different habitat types (see below).Locations of 6 landbird migration monitoring sites within the DownEast and MidCoast regions of Maine, USA.We defined a 4-m buffer area around each mist net as a habitat patch within the stopover site. Within each site, nets were placed 4&ndash;398 m apart (&mu; &plusmn; SE &equals; 119 &plusmn; 3 m). Four-meter-wide belt transects were established parallel to each net. While capture within a patch does not require that an individual be using a patch for foraging or crypsis (e.g., passage use during movement between patches), capture rates should increase as individuals spend longer within a patch, and there is no reason to suspect that any other type of use would correlate with either structural cover or fruit availability. Capture rates should thus serve as an adequate index of patch use.We sampled 3 islands with sizes of 0.75 km<sup>2</sup> (Great Duck Island, 2011), 1.30 km<sup>2</sup> (Metinic Island, 2011), and 280 km<sup>2</sup> (Mount Desert Island). We sampled 2 locations on Mount Desert Island, one at the southern-most coastal headland (Seawall, 2011&ndash;2012) and one 16 km to the north in the interior of the island (McFarland Hill, 2011). The 3 islands varied in their distance from the nearest mainland (Mount Desert Island &equals; 1 km, Metinic Island &equals; 8 km, and Great Duck Island &equals; 23 km). We also sampled the headlands of 2 peninsulas: Schoodic Peninsula (2012) and Petit Manan Point (2011&ndash;2012). The entire sampled region stretched 114 km, from Metinic Island in the southeast to Petit Manan Point in the northeast. All 6 migration stations possessed 4 broad vegetation types: forest dominated by <italic>Picea</italic> species (with <italic>Alnus, Larix</italic>, <italic>Betula</italic>, <italic>Acer</italic>, and <italic>Populus</italic> species); shrubland dominated by <italic>Alnus, Aronia, Sorbus</italic>, and <italic>Ilex</italic> species; mowed or grazed grassland; and a mixture of edge habitats among these broader types. The monitoring stations were all located on protected conservation lands and operated in collaboration with researchers at Acadia National Park, the Maine Coastal Islands National Wildlife Refuge, The Nature Conservancy, and the University of Maine.We surveyed migrant landbirds during fall migration in 2011 (August 16 to October 28) and 2012 (August 18 to October 18) using passive mist-netting. Nets were opened 30 min before sunrise and closed 6 hr after opening, weather conditions permitting. The specific nets and the total number of nets opened on any given day varied with weather conditions, most commonly with the presence of strong winds or rain. The number of nets at each site ranged from 14 to 20. The range of site area (summed 4-m buffer areas around all nets) was 2,143&ndash;2,912 m<sup>2</sup>. We fit all captured birds with a uniquely numbered aluminum band.Foraging habitat use was defined as the number of birds caught per week for each species, patch, and year. Birds recaptured within the same season were excluded from the dataset. Due to the difficulty of separating resident and migratory individuals, we removed all species found year-round at our sites from analyses. We also removed all species whose diet during migration did not include fruit, because we used fruit availability as our index of food resources. Species' diets were determined using previous categorizations created from 3 sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Parrish1">Parrish 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Suomala1">Suomala et al. 2010</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.allaboutbirds.org" xlink:type="simple">www.allaboutbirds.org</ext-link>). We further excluded species when we captured fewer than 50 birds across all sites and years, because rare species introduced many zero weekly capture counts, causing overdispersion of the data. To account for the hierarchical nature of habitat selection by migratory birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hutto1">Hutto 1985</xref>), we kept all zero counts at nets when species were caught in that net sometime during the migration season (i.e. birds were available to use the patch, but the patch was not selected during a given time period). However, we dropped all zero counts at nets when a given species was either never captured in that site during a given year (i.e. birds never selected the site and were therefore unavailable to select a patch secondarily) or never captured in that net during any time period within the year (i.e. birds may have selected the site, but it was impossible to distinguish between the lack of patch selection due to a preference for another patch and the lack of patch selection due to its unsuitability for the species' niche more broadly).Together with species, age, sex, and morphological measurements, the amount of subcutaneous fat in the furculum and abdomen was recorded. Fat was scored on a scale of 0 to 5: 0 &equals; none; 0.5 &equals; trace; 1 &equals; lining furculum; 2 &equals; filling furculum; 3 &equals; mounded in furculum and beginning to cover abdomen; 4 &equals; mounded on breast and sides of abdomen; 5 &equals; covering breast and abdomen (no or very little skin visible). Although individual fat load has been shown to affect antipredator behavior and foraging in other migration studies, we did not include a metric for individual energy reserves in our analysis. Preliminary data exploration indicated that there was not a biologically significant difference in the mean fat scores across tradeoff vs. nontradeoff sites (&mu; &plusmn; SD: tradeoff group &equals; 1.46 &plusmn; 1.75; nontradeoff group &equals; 1.06 &plusmn; 1.37). Therefore, any reported differences between patch use at tradeoff and nontradeoff sites could not be attributed to a difference in the mean energy reserves of the population selecting patches.Landbird species differ in their energetic constraints and consequently in their habitat needs during migration stopover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore4">Moore et al. 1995</xref>). These differences in energetic needs may drive differential habitat use by species. We included each species' migration distance as a potential predictor of habitat use to capture this variation in energetic demand. Migration distance was calculated by obtaining each species' most northerly and most southerly nonbreeding range limits based on Cornell Lab of Ornithology range maps (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.allaboutbirds.org" xlink:type="simple">www.allaboutbirds.org</ext-link>), determining the latitudinal midpoint of each species' nonbreeding range, and calculating the latitudinal distance from the capture region to this midpoint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-McCabe1">McCabe and Olsen 2015</xref>). This method provided an estimate (as a continuous variable) of the median distance left to travel for each species.Predation pressure was measured in the field by recording all birds of prey seen utilizing (not merely flying over) the migration banding stations during the hours of banding operation. As our raptor abundance variable we used a weekly raptor total for each banding site divided by the total number of hours that nets were open at each site to control for varying effort. The most common avian predator species observed at our sites were Merlin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Falco columbarius</named-content></italic>), Sharp-shinned Hawk (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter striatus</named-content></italic>), and Peregrine Falcon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">F. peregrinus</named-content></italic>), predators that do not hunt in dense cover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Raim1">Raim et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Niles1">Niles et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Fransson1">Fransson and Weber 1997</xref>).Within each habitat patch, two 4-m-wide belt transects running parallel to the net were established. These transects were placed outside the areas directly affected by the maintenance of the net lanes.Woody stem density was measured down the center of each 4-m belt transect by counting stems in 1-m intervals at 2 heights (0.5 m and 1.5 m). We then summed the stem counts across both transects along each net for each height and averaged the sums from the 2 heights to provide us with a single continuous stem density count per patch.We used ripe fruit abundance as a measure of food availability. While the use of patches with high fruit abundance does not necessitate that birds are foraging on fruit, there are few obvious alternative behavioral mechanisms that could produce a positive relationship between patch use and fruit availability among frugivorous birds that are not related to foraging behavior (or indirectly to flocking behavior of birds foraging on fruit), especially once habitat structure is controlled for (using the multivariate approaches described below).We recorded ripe fruit abundance weekly along the 2 belt transects for each mist net. We assessed fruit abundance for several shrub species, including black chokeberry (<italic>Photinia melanocarpa</italic>), wild raisin (<italic>Viburnum nudum</italic>), pin cherry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Prunus pensylvanica</named-content></italic>), lowbush and highbush blueberry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vaccinium angustifolium</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vaccinium corymbosum</named-content></italic>), black huckleberry (<italic>Gaylussacia baccata</italic>) and 2 <italic>Rubus</italic> species. We excluded bayberry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Myrica pensylvanica</named-content></italic>) because only 1 species, the Yellow-rumped Warbler (<italic>Setophaga coronata</italic>), is able to digest its waxy fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Place1">Place and Stiles 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Borgmann1">Borgmann et al. 2004</xref>). Black chokeberry, wild raisin, and pin cherry comprised the majority of fruiting species at all sites. The numbers of individual fruits were estimated for each species using a modified scale with 8 abundance categories, first developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Smith1">Smith and McWilliams (2009)</xref>. Abundance categories were defined as: 1 &equals; &le;10 ripe fruits, 2 &equals; 11&ndash;25 ripe fruits, 3 &equals; 26&ndash;100 ripe fruits, 4 &equals; 101&ndash;250 ripe fruits, 5 &equals; 251&ndash;1,000 ripe fruits, 6 &equals; 1,001&ndash;3,000 ripe fruits, 7 &equals; 3,001&ndash;10,000 ripe fruits, and 8 &equals; &ge;10,000 ripe fruits. To obtain our continuous fruit availability variable we summed the categorical midpoints of estimated ripe fruit abundance across both transects for each week.For each week, we modeled ripe fruit availability as a function of stem density across all habitat patches for each site using quantile regression (&tau; &equals; 0.80), using the R package &lsquo;quantreg' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Koenker1">Koenker 2013</xref>). We used quantile regression to describe the relationship between the 80<sup>th</sup> percentile of fruit availability for a given stem density. This allowed us to identify sites with patches that had both high cover and abundant fruit vs. sites that lacked such patches during a given week. Site-weeks (hereafter, &ldquo;sites&rdquo;) for which there was a negative relationship between fruit availability and stem density were labeled as tradeoff sites, and sites with a positive relationship were categorized as nontradeoff sites. Although banding stations had similar broad habitats, fruiting plant species diversity, abundance, and fruiting phenology differed within and among sites. By modeling weekly relationships between fruit and cover, we thus allowed patches to exhibit tradeoffs between fruit availability and cover variably through time with patch fruiting phenology.Based on a priori hypotheses about the differences in foraging habitat use between tradeoff and nontradeoff sites, we constructed a set of candidate models. We then used model selection to determine which combination of predictors best explained patch use and whether use differed for sites that did or did not require a tradeoff between food and cover. To test our hypotheses we constructed a series of generalized linear mixed effects models, with weekly species counts modeled as a negative binomial distribution with a log-link function and an offset of weekly net hours (to account for effort). We used a negative binomial distribution to account for overdispersion and zero-inflation in our capture data. We repeatedly measured captures of 28 species at 144 patches weekly over 2 yr; therefore, species and patch identity were included as random effects. We fit the generalized linear negative binomial mixed models with the R package &lsquo;lme4&prime; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Bates1">Bates et al. 2014</xref>). All models included year and week as fixed effects to account for the differences between years and to control for variation in the phenology of the migratory community. Weekly fruit availability measurements were heavily skewed, thus we square-root-transformed the variable. The relationship between bird abundance and week was nonlinear; therefore, we added a quadratic term for week in all models. As our hypotheses were concerned only with relative foraging patch use for the migratory community in sites that did or did not require a tradeoff between food and cover, we did not disentangle differences in captures due to true abundance vs. detection probability. We should note, however, that our methods assume that detection probability is similar within a given site, year, and species for all nets within a site.The candidate model set consisted of 8 models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t01">Table 1</xref>). All models aside from the null model included year (2011 or 2012), week (linear and quadratic terms), fruit availability, tradeoff (yes or no), raptor abundance, stem density, and migration distance as single variables. Additive models of these single variables described each variable's overall effect on patch use. For example, fruit availability as a single variable only explained whether more or fewer birds were captured at patches with varying fruit availability. To test our hypotheses that the relationship between bird use and fruit availability varied with risk and migration strategy, we used a series of 2- and 3-way interactions.Model selection results for all models explaining migrating landbird stopover use of patches on the coast of Maine, USA, 2011&ndash;2012. Models were ranked based on the difference from the top model in AIC value (&Delta;AIC). Also presented are the log-likelihood (&minus;2In<italic>L</italic>), number of parameters (<italic>K</italic>), and model weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>). All models include the variables &ldquo;year&rdquo; and &ldquo;week.&rdquo; &ldquo;Fruit Avail.&rdquo; is an index of ripe fruit abundance within a habitat patch; &ldquo;Tradeoff&rdquo; indicates whether or not there is a negative relationship between stem density and fruit abundance among patches within a site during a given week; &ldquo;Stem Den.&rdquo; is an index of vegetative cover within a patch; &ldquo;Migration Dist.&rdquo; is the median latitudinal distance left to travel from the study region to the midpoint of the wintering grounds for each species; and &ldquo;Raptor Abund.&rdquo; is an index of predation risk to landbirds at each site during a given week.Specifically, the model set contained: (1) 3 models, each with one 2-way interaction between fruit availability and either stem density, migration distance, or raptor abundance; (2) three 3-way interaction models formed by interacting tradeoff with each of the 2-way interactions above (plus their associated 2-way interactions and main effects); (3) one model containing only the single variables (fruit availability, migration distance, tradeoff status, stem density, and raptor abundance); and (4) a null model, containing only year and week as fixed effects. The three 2-way interactions tested whether the relationship between fruit availability and patch use varied by risk (indicated by raptor abundance and the inverse of stem density) and energetic strategy (indicated by migration distance). The 3-way interactions then tested whether any of these relationships differed between sites that did or did not require a tradeoff between food and cover.We standardized all of our continuous candidate variables by subtracting the mean and dividing them by the standard deviation. By standardizing the variables we could directly compare the parameter estimates among our candidate variables to describe the strength of the difference between tradeoff and nontradeoff sites.We used Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) to rank models based on their ability to explain variance in the data, and used Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) to estimate the relative likelihood of each model given the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We considered models with differences in AIC values (&Delta;AIC) &lt;2.0 to be equivalent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We assessed model fit (including the random variables) by calculating the conditional <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>. We used the &ldquo;Wald&rdquo; method to calculate 95&percnt; confidence intervals around the parameter estimates from the top model.During the 2011 and 2012 fall migration seasons, we captured 9,649 migrant birds belonging to 28 species of 7 families. We operated nets for 27,544 hr over 144 net-years. The number of sampling days for each site during a given year ranged from 33 to 55 days (&mu; &plusmn; SE &equals; 43 &plusmn; 3 days). Yearly net effort for individual banding stations ranged from 2,122 to 4,363 net-hours. The weekly predation pressure averaged 0.033 (SD &equals; 0.004, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 24 site-weeks, range &equals; 0&ndash;50 raptors per site-week) and 0.005 (SD &equals; 0.036, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 35 site-weeks, range &equals; 0&ndash;11 raptors per site-week) raptors per net-hour for 2011 and 2012, respectively.A tradeoff between cover and fruit availability was present during 15 site-weeks, and a tradeoff was absent during 46 site-weeks. Fruit availability and stem density differed between years and by tradeoff group. Stem density varied between years because the sites operated varied between the 2 years. Fruit availability was higher in 2011 (&mu; &plusmn; SE &equals; 21.76 &plusmn; 1.56 fruit per effort) than in 2012 (6.74 &plusmn; 0.72), and higher among tradeoff sites (22.17 &plusmn; 2.44) vs. nontradeoff sites (13.27 &plusmn; 1.02). Stem density was slightly lower among patches measured in 2011 (7.29 &plusmn; 0.22 stems) than in 2012 (7.97 &plusmn; 0.22), and lower in the tradeoff sites (6.19 &plusmn; 0.30) vs. the nontradeoff sites (8.05 &plusmn; 0.18).Our top-ranked model predicting variation in patch use contained a 2-way interaction between fruit availability and migration distance (and the associated main effects), controlling for the single variables of raptor abundance, tradeoff status, stem density, year, and week (model weight &equals; 0.82; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t01">Table 1</xref>). Our final model fit the data reasonably well (conditional <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.40) and was not overdispersed, with a ratio of the sum of squared Pearson's residuals to residual degrees of freedom of 1.08.Within the top-ranked model we found important effects of week, year, tradeoff status, raptor abundance, stem density, and the interaction between fruit availability and migration distance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t02">Table 2</xref>). The variable having the largest effect on predicted capture rates was week; captures increased toward the beginning of the season at all sites and decreased at the end (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t02">Table 2</xref>). Model-predicted capture rates were higher in nontradeoff sites (&mu; &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.018 &plusmn; 0.000) than in tradeoff sites (0.011 &plusmn; 0.000) during 2011 and 2012 (nontradeoff: 0.011 &plusmn; 0.000, tradeoff: 0.009 &plusmn; 0.000), and in sites with high raptor abundance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t02">Table 2</xref>). Controlling for all other factors, birds preferred patches with higher stem densities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t02">Table 2</xref>). Fruit availability had little effect on the capture rates of shorter-distance migrants; however, as migration distance increased, species were captured more and more preferentially in patches with high fruit availability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t02">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Parameter estimates with 95&percnt; confidence intervals for all variables within the top model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-t01">Table 1</xref>) predicting capture rates of migrating landbirds at migratory stopover sites within the Gulf of Maine, USA, 2011&ndash;2012. Bold font highlights parameters for which the 95&percnt; confidence intervals do not bound zero.Effect of fruit availability (square-root transformed) on predicted capture rates (&plusmn; 95&percnt; CI) of 4 different migratory landbird guilds (defined by quartiles of the latitudinal distance from our study region to the midpoint of the nonbreeding season range) at 6 stopover sites on the coast of Maine, USA, 2011&ndash;2012.Animals have repeatedly been shown to modify their foraging choices to reflect both foraging success and predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Lima2">Lima and Dill 1990</xref>). In situations in which individuals are food-deprived or engaged in energetically costly events, however, they may make more &ldquo;risky&rdquo; foraging decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Furness 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Pomeroy1">Pomeroy et al. 2008</xref>). In a community of species actively engaged in migration, we predicted that capture rates would be higher in patches with higher fruit abundance among sites where individuals had to choose between patches with high food availability or high cover. Further, we predicted that in sites that did not require a tradeoff, capture rates would be positively correlated with both fruit abundance and cover. Instead, we found that birds preferentially used patches with high cover regardless of the presence (or absence) of a tradeoff within the site, once we controlled for predator abundance. Further, fruit availability was only predictive of patch use among the longest-distance migrants, again regardless of the presence or absence of a tradeoff between food availability and cover. Overall bird abundance, however, was highest in sites without a tradeoff.Migrants approaching stopover are constantly assessing their surroundings and making decisions at finer and finer spatial scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hutto1">Hutto 1985</xref>). Our results are consistent with this hierarchical stopover decision-making process, and suggest that site selection may be more important than patch selection for explaining habitat use at timescales of a week or greater. We hypothesize that migrants rapidly assess the relative safety and productivity of a site, departing sites more rapidly if there is a tradeoff between foraging and safety. Assuming similar landing densities among our sites, longer stopover times at higher quality sites would explain the patterns that we report here.Patch use among longer-distance migrants was explained by fruit availability across all sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-f02">Figure 2</xref>), which is concordant with our assumption that these birds have higher energetic demands (i.e. are likely to accept more risk during foraging). This pattern could also be explained by a bias in more specialized frugivory (during migration) among the longest-distance migrants. Given the advantages of a more frugivorous diet during stopover that have been reported for a number of landbird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Parrish1">Parrish 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Parrish2">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Bairlein1">Bairlein 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Long1">Long and Stouffer 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Newton1">Newton 2008</xref>), long-distance migrants may select habitats that are higher in fruit resources, regardless of their diet during nonmigratory periods, in order to gain weight more efficiently during stopover. Such behavior minimizes the time spent on stopover, in turn shortening total migratory passage time, and is one of the hallmarks of a &ldquo;time minimizer&rdquo; migration strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Alerstam1">Alerstam and Lindstr&ouml;m 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hedenstrom2">Hedenstr&ouml;m and Alerstam 1997</xref>). Short-distance migrants are generally assumed to be less constrained by time and to depart stopover sites with lower mass loads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hedenstrom2">Hedenstr&ouml;m and Alerstam 1997</xref>). Doing so allows them to be more cautious on stopover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Furness 1984</xref>) and also increases their escape velocity and maneuverability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Kullberg1">Kullberg et al. 1996</xref>), both of which lessen predation risk at a cost to migration time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Alerstam1">Alerstam and Lindstr&ouml;m 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Seewagen1">Seewagen and Guglielmo 2010</xref>). Here we support this overall paradigm, showing that shorter-distance migrants prioritized patches with high cover (low predation risk) at all sites, whereas longer-distance migrants compromised between cover and food availability when presented with a tradeoff.It is important to note that our measure of fruit availability was a weekly calculation, and that the timing and composition of fruiting plants at a stopover site may vary at even finer timescales. However, using similar data collected in the same sites as this study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Olsen1">Olsen et al. (2015)</xref> found that food resource phenology, along with other ephemeral resources (deciduous leaf drop and soil moisture), predicted patch use throughout the migration season better than static habitat structure (i.e. vegetation cover and height). Ripe fruit abundance was positively associated with the capture rates of Parulidae, Emberizidae, and Vireonidae, but was unrelated to capture rates of Tyrannidae. Results from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Olsen1">Olsen et al. (2015)</xref> and this study confirm the importance of within-season variation in resource availability for predicting migrating songbird habitat use.Vegetation structure is an essential factor shaping birds' habitat choices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Wiens1">Wiens and Rotenberry 1981</xref>), as it can provide information regarding shelter from predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Sapir1">Sapir et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Deppe1">Deppe and Rotenberry 2008</xref>). To assess habitat use of the migrant community, we used woody stem density as a proxy for protection from predation risk, where high stem density was assumed to equate to lower predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Savino1">Savino and Stein 1989</xref>). It is possible that individuals utilize other characteristics to select cover, such as percent vegetation cover or height, when seeking protection. Vegetation cover, height, and density, however, are often highly correlated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Vitz1">Vitz and Rodewald 2007</xref>), although this remains untested at our study sites. Previous fall migration studies have found correlations between stem density and bird abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Rodewald1">Rodewald and Brittingham 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Suthers1">Suthers et al. 2000</xref>), although whether these correlations can be attributed to perceived protection or an association with food resources is unknown. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Cimprich3">Cimprich et al. (2005)</xref> found that both American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>) and Blue-gray Gnatcatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila caerulea</named-content></italic>) moved deeper into shrubs when presented with a predation risk, demonstrating that migrants are indeed relying on vegetation as protection and perceive increased cover as increased protection. Additional behavioral studies are needed to determine the precise behavioral mechanisms responsible for the patch associations presented here.Across all sites, capture rates were higher in sites with greater raptor abundance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Aborn1">Aborn (1994)</xref> also found a positive correlation between raptor and landbird abundances during spring migration along the Gulf of Mexico coastline. Correlations in abundance may be due to migratory behaviors that are similar across both avian groups, to predator movements tracking prey resources, or both. Beneficial weather patterns for migrating raptors are also advantageous for migrating landbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore3">Moore and Kerlinger 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Aborn1">Aborn 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Woltmann1">Woltmann and Cimprich 2003</xref>); neither group prefers to fly into a headwind or heavy precipitation. Also, landbird abundance along the Gulf of Maine is directly proportional to the amount of vegetated land available for stopover at the scale of a few kilometers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-McCabe1">McCabe and Olsen 2015</xref>). It is reasonable to assume that similar behavioral processes are at work among raptor species. Since landbirds are an important food source for migrating raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Aborn1">Aborn 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Ydenberg1">Ydenberg et al. 2007</xref>), raptor movements also might track the abundance of their prey. For these reasons we hypothesize that increased landbird captures at high-abundance raptor sites are not related to landbird movements in response to raptor abundance. If, however, landbirds are unable to avoid sites with high raptor abundance due to these mechanisms, avoiding sites with a tradeoff between cover and food might be the adaptive solution to a constraint imposed by predation.Migration is a critical event in the life cycle of most North American landbirds. With increases in both predation risk and energetic demand relative to stationary periods of the annual cycle, migration is inherently costly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore4">Moore et al. 1995</xref>). Balancing predator avoidance with foraging is critical because of direct mortality risk and the costs of arriving late to either nonbreeding or breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Moore1">Moore 1994</xref>). We suggest that migrating landbirds universally prioritize habitat patches with high cover, but avoid sites where this cover is not correlated with the presence of food resources. Further, increased energetic demand (as indicated by migration distance) is associated with increased use of patches with abundant food resources, regardless of cover. Our community-scale results thus corroborate past single-species behavioral research demonstrating that migrants prioritize foraging when energetic demand is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Furness 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Yasue1">Yasu&eacute; et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hebblewhite1">Hebblewhite and Merrill 2009</xref>).Important stopover habitat for the entire migratory community may be difficult to define (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Hutto2">Hutto 2000</xref>). However, in this study we found that, when given the opportunity, migrants preferred habitats with both high vegetative protection and abundant fruit resources. Both resources are typically found in edge-dominated, early successional habitats, which are not considered high-quality breeding habitat for many of the species that we studied here (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Rodewald2">Rodewald and Brittingham 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Vitz1">Vitz and Rodewald 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-903-Suomala1">Suomala et al. 2010</xref>). Thus, landbird conservation efforts should consider not only prime breeding habitat, but also habitat where migrants can find protection from aerial predators while efficiently and safely refueling. Additionally, habitats with fruit resources that occur during the migration seasons may be particularly important. More study is needed to quantify the costs to bird condition and survival in sites that lack these resources.We are grateful to The Nature Conservancy, College of the Atlantic, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service's Maine Coastal Islands National Wildlife Refuge, and Acadia National Park for allowing us access to their lands. Thank you to A. Leppold, S. Williams, and the many wonderful technicians who assisted with field data collection.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> We thank all funding agencies: the National Park Service's Northeastern Temperate Network, Acadia National Park, the University of Maine, the Maine Agriculture and Forest Experimental Station, and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service's Maine Coastal Islands National Wildlife Refuge. None of our funders had any influence on the content of the submitted or published manuscript. None of our funders required approval of the final manuscript to be published.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> The ethical treatment of animals was approved by the University of Maine Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee under permits A2010-08-02 and A2013-08-01. Bird banding was licensed under Maine state wildlife scientific collection permit &num;270 and U.S. federal banding permit &num;23613 and &num;22055.