 Distribution and movements of Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders in the nonbreeding period  lme4: Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using Eigen and S4. R package version 1.1&ndash;7  Direct and indirect estimates of Gyrfalcon nest site fidelity and breeding and natal dispersal using non-invasive genetic sampling  Habitat use by wintering Steller's Eider in northern Norway  The diet of Steller's Eiders wintering in Varangerfjord, northern Norway  The package &ldquo;adehabitat&rdquo; for the R software: A tool for the analysis of space and habitat use by animals  The abundance and distribution of euphausiids and zero-age pollock on the inner shelf of the southeast Bering Sea near the Inner Front in 1997&ndash;1999  Distribution of recoveries of Steller's Eiders banded on the lower Alaska Peninsula, Alaska  Moderating Argos location errors in animal tracking data  Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; threatened status for the Alaska breeding population of the Steller's Eider  Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; proposed designation of critical habitat for the Steller's Eider  Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; final determination of critical habitat for the Alaska-breeding population of the Steller's Eider  Breeding of Steller's Eiders,   Polysticta stelleri  , on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska  Annual survival and site fidelity of Steller's Eiders molting along the Alaska Peninsula  Spring habitat use and feeding behaviour of Steller's Eider   Polysticta stelleri   in Varangerfjord, northern Norway  Reproductive effort and survival of wild Blue-winged Teal,   Anas discors  , with backpack harness and implant transmitters  Aerial surveys of eiders and other waterbirds on the eastern Arctic coast of Russia  Winter philopatry of Harlequin Ducks in Prince William Sound, Alaska  Returns from Steller's Eiders banded in Izembek Bay, Alaska  Disappearance of the Steller's Eider from the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska  Implanting intra-abdominal radiotransmitters with external whip antennas in ducks  The spring behavior of wild Steller's Eiders  Effect of implanted satellite transmitters on the nesting behavior of murres  Surgical and immediate postrelease mortality of Harlequin Ducks (  Histrionicus histrionicus  ) implanted with abdominal radio transmitters with percutaneous antennae  The birds of Bering Sea and the Arctic Ocean. In Cruise of the Revenue-Steamer Corwin in Alaska and the Northwest Arctic Ocean in 1881, Notes and Memoranda&mdash;Medical and Anthropological  Steller's Eiders   Polysticta stelleri   wintering in Europe: Numbers, distribution and origin  International importance of the eastern Chukchi Sea as a staging area for migrating King Eiders  Timing and distance of King Eider migration and winter movements  Observations of wing-feather moult and summer feeding ecology of Steller's Eiders at Nelson Lagoon, Alaska  Populations, feeding ecology, and molt of Steller's Eider  Multiple spring migration strategies in a population of Pacific Common Eiders  Breeding and moulting locations and migration patterns of the Atlantic population of Steller's Eiders   Polysticta stelleri   as determined from satellite telemetry  Steller's Eider   Polysticta stelleri   at the Lithuanian Baltic coast in 1969 to 1991  Reconstruction of historic sea ice conditions in a sub-Arctic lagoon  Evidence for wing molt and breeding site fidelity in King Eiders  Movements of the King Eider during the non-breeding period revealed by satellite telemetry  Periodic non-breeding of Steller's Eiders near Barrow, Alaska, with speculations on possible causes  Historical and present breeding distribution of Steller's Eiders in Alaska  Movements and foraging effort of Steller's Eiders and Harlequin Ducks wintering near Dutch Harbor, Alaska  Diel vertical migration and interaction of zooplankton and juvenile walleye pollock (  Theragra chalcogramma  ) at a frontal region near the Pribilof Islands, Bering Sea  Steller's Eider (  Polysticta stelleri  )  Measuring devices on wild animals: What constitutes acceptable practice?  Current address: ABR Inc., Environmental Research &amp; Services, Fairbanks, Alaska, USA  Steller's Eiders (  Polysticta stelleri  ) that breed in Alaska, USA, are listed as threatened under the U.S. Endangered Species Act (ESA), yet the degree to which these individuals segregate during the nonbreeding period from conspecifics that nest in Russia is unknown. Likewise, very little is known about the timing of use and distribution of autumn migration routes, stopover sites, and molting and wintering areas by the Alaska-breeding population. To address this information need, we implanted 14 Steller's Eiders with satellite transmitters in 2000 and 2001 at their primary Alaskan breeding grounds near Barrow. We found no evidence for segregation of the Alaska-breeding population in midwinter because locations were well-distributed along the Alaska Peninsula, congruent with prevailing knowledge about the wintering distribution of Steller's Eiders that breed in Russia. During the wing molt, from late August to early October, 7 of 13 individuals used Kuskokwim Shoals, corroborating the importance of this area and its designation as critical habitat under the ESA. Steller's Eiders are generally described as preferring shallow waters &lt;10 m deep, but our winter tracking data clearly documented occupancy of deeper offshore waters. Steller's Eiders frequently used up to 30-m deep water almost exclusively at night during winter. We speculate that nighttime occupancy of deeper water habitats may be for resting and/or for consumption of zooplankton species, such as euphausiids, that are abundant and well known for their nocturnal vertical migrations in the water column.  Los individuos de   Polysticta stelleri   que se reproducen en Alaska est&aacute;n listados como amenazados por la Ley de Especies en Peligro (LEP) de EEUU. Sin embargo, se desconoce el grado de segregaci&oacute;n de estos individuos de los individuos que anidan en Rusia durante el per&iacute;odo no reproductivo. Del mismo modo, se sabe muy poco del momento y la distribuci&oacute;n de las rutas migratorias de oto&ntilde;o, de los sitios de parada y de las &aacute;reas de muda e invernada de la poblaci&oacute;n reproductiva de Alaska. Para obtener esta informaci&oacute;n, colocamos transmisores satelitales a 14 individuos de   P. stelleri   en 2000 y 2001 en sus sitios primarios de reproducci&oacute;n en Alaska cerca de Barrow. No encontramos evidencia de segregaci&oacute;n de la poblaci&oacute;n reproductiva de Alaska a mediados del invierno, debido a que las localizaciones de los individuos marcados estuvieron ampliamente distribuidas a lo largo de la Pen&iacute;nsula de Alaska, lo que es congruente con el conocimiento previo sobre la distribuci&oacute;n invernal de los individuos de   P. stelleri   que se reproducen en Rusia. Durante la muda alar, desde fines de agosto hasta inicios de octubre, siete de 13 individuos usaron el &aacute;rea de Kuskokwim Shoals, corroborando la importancia de esta &aacute;rea y su designaci&oacute;n como un h&aacute;bitat cr&iacute;tico bajo la LEP.   P. stelleri   es descripta generalmente como una especie que prefiere aguas someras de &lt;10 m de profundidad, pero nuestros registros de seguimiento de invierno muestran claramente la ocupaci&oacute;n de aguas m&aacute;s profundas.   P. stelleri   us&oacute; con frecuencia aguas de hasta 30 m de profundidad durante el invierno casi exclusivamente por la noche. Especulamos que la ocupaci&oacute;n nocturna de aguas m&aacute;s profundas puede ser para descansar y/o para el consumo de especies del zooplancton, como los euf&aacute;sidos, que son abundantes y muy conocidos por las migraciones verticales nocturnas que realizan en la columna de agua.   Palabras clave:  Alaska, amenazada, distribuci&oacute;n, h&aacute;bitat marino, Ley de Especies en Peligro, movimientos,   Polysticta stelleri  , telemetr&iacute;a satelital  The breeding range of the Steller's Eider (  Polysticta stelleri  ) lies mainly in Arctic Russia, and while those birds nesting west of ~102&deg;E winter in the Atlantic, most Russia-breeding birds winter in the Pacific basin ( Nyg&aring;rd et al. 1995 ,  Solovieva et al. 1998 ,  Petersen et al. 2006 ). The size of the Pacific-wintering population is poorly known, but a single 1994 aerial survey of the Russian breeding grounds between the Kolyma and Lena river deltas yielded an estimate of 160,000 ( Hodges and Eldridge 2001 ). Much of the Russia-breeding population migrates to molting and wintering areas in southwestern and south-coastal Alaska, USA, with the greatest concentrations occurring on the Alaska Peninsula ( Jones 1965 ,  Petersen 1981 ). Annual spring aerial surveys along the Alaska Peninsula estimated 59,638 Steller's Eiders in 2012, punctuating an estimated annual decline of 2.4&percnt; during 1992&ndash;2012 ( Larned 2012 ). The Pacific population also includes a small number of birds that breed in Alaska, administratively defined by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) as the &ldquo;Alaska-breeding population&rdquo; and listed as threatened under the U.S. Endangered Species Act (hereafter, ESA) in 1997 ( Federal Register 1997 ). The decision to list the species was based on apparent reductions in Alaska's breeding population and range, especially on the Yukon&ndash;Kuskokwim Delta ( Kertell 1991 ,  Flint and Herzog 1999 ).  The only place in Alaska where breeding has been regularly documented during the past 25 years is near the North Slope Arctic coastal community of Barrow ( Figure 1 ;  Quakenbush et al. 2002 ), and the best available population estimate of North Slope&ndash;breeding Steller's Eiders is 576 birds (95&percnt; CI: 292&ndash;859;  Stehn and Platte 2009 ); however, obtaining a reliable breeding population estimate is difficult for this species. The species' periodic nonbreeding behavior, as reported for both the Barrow ( Quakenbush and Suydam 1999 ,  Quakenbush et al. 2002 ) and Lena River Delta populations ( Solovieva et al. 1998 ), hampers accurate characterization of population size. At Barrow, nesting was observed in 15 of 23 years during 1991&ndash;2013, and intervals with few or no eiders observed nesting ranged from 1 to 5 years ( Safine 2013 , D. Safine personal communication). Steller's Eiders typically arrive in Barrow in late May or early June, both in years with prevalent nesting (hereafter called high-nesting years) and in years when few or no nests are observed (hereafter called low-nesting years). In low-nesting years, pairs and small flocks may be observed for up to several weeks (although in reduced numbers relative to high-nesting years), but most birds apparently depart Barrow without occupying territories or initiating nesting. It is not known if females that depart Barrow in early summer attempt to nest elsewhere, in either Alaska or Russia.  Fall migration stopover sites and molting areas used by 7 male and 6 female Steller's Eiders captured at Barrow, Alaska, in 2000 and 2001. Stopover site symbol size is proportional to the total number of use-days (among all birds), and the numeral indicates the number of individual birds that used the site. Molt area names appear in text boxes with the number of birds using the area in parentheses. Colored lines follow idealized routes for each individual to illustrate connectivity between sites and destinations.  The general postbreeding distribution of Steller's Eiders in coastal Alaska is reasonably well known ( Federal Register 2000 ,  Baldassarre 2014 ). During the period of wing molt from late August to early October, dense flocks occur in shallow estuaries and lagoons on the northern side of the Alaska Peninsula, particularly at Izembek and Nelson lagoons. Molting birds have also been noted as far north as St. Lawrence Island, Nunivak Island, and along the coast of Bristol Bay. From November to April, wintering flocks are found in shallow, nearshore marine waters along both sides of the Alaska Peninsula, and in lesser numbers on the eastern Aleutian Islands, the Kodiak Archipelago, and lower Cook Inlet. Band recoveries corroborate that Russia-breeding birds predominate at the molting areas on the lower Alaska Peninsula, although some Alaska-breeders are represented ( Jones 1965 ,  Dau et al. 2000 ). An analysis of 285 band recoveries from Arctic Russia and Alaska ( Dau et al. 2000 ) was uninformative regarding the degree to which the Alaska-breeding population was segregated during wing molt, and provided no information on the winter (postmolt) distribution of the Alaska-breeding population.  The Recovery Plan ( USFWS 2002 ) prepared following the ESA listing outlines tasks currently considered necessary to recover Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders, one of which is to elucidate distribution during the nonbreeding season. Although the USFWS conducted annual aerial surveys during the latter part of the nonbreeding season from 1992 through 2012 in southwestern Alaska ( Larned 2012 ), it was unknown if the Alaska-breeding population concentrated in distinct areas in the nonbreeding season or dispersed throughout the species' broad marine range. To help managers decide when and where to implement the most effective and efficient conservation efforts and to inform impacts assessments, we implanted 14 Steller's Eiders with satellite transmitters at Barrow in 2000 and 2001. Our specific objectives were to: (1) document movements and distribution during the wing molt and winter periods; (2) describe the timing and routes of migration; and (3) describe the behavior of birds in low-nesting years after their departure from Barrow.  We captured Steller's Eiders in the vicinity of the community of Barrow, Alaska (71.29&deg;N, 156.79&deg;W). The Barrow region, in the northwestern portion of the Arctic Coastal Plain, remains the primary nesting area for Steller's Eiders in Alaska ( Quakenbush et al. 2002 ). The coastal tundra at Barrow has low relief and is dominated by a pattern of shallow lakes, drained lake basins, small ponds, and ice-wedge polygons ( Brown et al. 1980 ). All capture activity occurred within 1 km of the Barrow road system. Trapping effort, especially in 2001, was focused on the area in and around Footprint Lake, a vegetated and seasonally flooded drained lake basin that tends to provide early access to open water for eiders and other waterfowl.  To capture eiders, we first identified ponds used by foraging eiders during the prebreeding season. We then hung mist nests just above the water at these ponds and placed decoys a few meters downwind. Up to 4 observers watched the ponds at all times, and eiders were usually captured by slowly herding them toward the nets. In this manner, we captured 3 males on separate small ponds during June 16&ndash;19, 2000, and 5 putative pairs at Footprint Lake during June 9&ndash;15, 2001. Pair status was inferred on the basis of behavioral association, i.e. when a male and female remained &lt;5 m apart during the herding phase and were captured simultaneously. We caught 1 female at her nest on July 11, 2000, by slowly lowering a mist net over her as she incubated her eggs.  We implanted transmitters following a technique modified from  Korschgen et al. (1996)  and described by  Mulcahy and Esler (1999) . Surgery lasted 29&ndash;50 min, from intubation until the bird recovered sufficiently to hold its head up. The elapsed time between capture and release ranged from 6.0 to 7.7 hr, with 2 exceptions: One female did not fly when released and was returned to the clinic to recover for an additional 6 hr (total elapsed time &equals; 16 hr), and the female captured on her nest was held for a total of 21 hr for observation and treatment because postoperative recovery was slow. All birds captured, including the 2 held for extra time, appeared alert and strong at the time of release. Birds captured together were released together, and, aside from the exceptions previously noted, elapsed time between the conclusion of surgery and release ranged from 3 to 6 hr.  We used PTT-100 transmitters (Microwave Telemetry, Columbia, Maryland, USA) that weighed 38&ndash;40 g and averaged 4.7&percnt; (range: 4.0&ndash;5.1&percnt;) of a bird's body mass at the time of capture. All transmitters were programmed to transmit with a 60 sec pulse rate and a duty cycle that alternated between 6 hr on and 72 hr off to conserve battery power. Total length of the duty cycle was 78 hr (not a multiple of 24), so all hours of the day were sampled every 10 days. The expected battery life was approximately 1 yr. The transmitters were equipped with sensors that monitored internal body temperature and battery voltage.  Bird movements were tracked by Service Argos (Argos CLS America, Lanham, Maryland, USA) using Doppler least-squares processing to estimate locations with both standard and auxiliary location classes (Argos User's Manual,  http://www.argos-system.org/web/en/76-user-s-manual.php ). Standard location classes (LC &equals; 3, 2, and 1) have an estimated 1-sigma error radius of 250, 500, and 1,500 m, respectively, while accuracy of the auxiliary location classes (LC &equals; 0, A, B, and Z) is highly variable and unquantified by Service Argos (Argos System FAQ,  http://www.argos-system.org/web/en/78-faq.php ). We used the Douglas Argos-Filter Algorithm ( Douglas et al. 2012 ) to remove implausible auxiliary locations; we did not filter standard quality locations. We retained auxiliary locations only if they were confirmed by a temporally consecutive location within 10 km. Filtered locations obtained during periods of sustained directional movement were allowed to reenter the dataset if they maintained reasonable directionality and their apparent rates of movement were &lt;80 km hr &minus;1 . From the retained locations, we constructed a final dataset by selecting 1 location per transmitter duty cycle based on the best location class quality.  The fate of each bird was determined by examining the temperature and battery voltage sensor data prior to signal loss. If temperature dropped but battery voltage did not, the bird was assumed to have died. A drop in battery voltage but not in temperature was interpreted as transmitter battery failure. Fate remained unknown when signal loss was not preceded by a drop in either temperature or battery voltage.  The annual cycle was subdivided into 6 periods ( Table 1 ), classified for each individual on the basis of its behavior and movement patterns ( Petersen et al. 2006 ,  Phillips et al. 2006 ,  Oppel et al. 2008 ). Onset of the premigratory period was assumed to begin immediately upon release after surgery; otherwise, the date of entry into a new period was defined as the midpoint of the time interval between the last known date of the previous period and the first known date of the new period. The year 2000 was a high-nesting year at Barrow, whereas no Steller's Eider nests were found in 2001 ( Safine 2013 ). Based on this generality, rather than specific knowledge of an individual's status, all birds tagged in 2000 were classified as breeding and all birds from 2001 as nonbreeding. We also estimated the number of &ldquo;use-days&rdquo; that an eider occupied a given area as the sum of the number of days between the arrival and departure dates, which were estimated as the mid-dates between the first (or last) date of occupancy and date of the preceding (or subsequent) location.  Definitions used to partition the Steller's Eider annual cycle into 6 behavioral periods.  Molt and winter use areas were estimated by a fixed-kernel technique with a least-squares cross-validation smoothing method ( Silverman 1986 ). We used the 95&percnt; probability contour derived with the program R package &lsquo;adehabitatHR' ( Calenge 2006 ) to estimate the size of use areas, and we allowed the kernel smoothing factor ( h ) to vary for each bird at each use area (mean  h  &equals; 992 &plusmn; 443 m). Use areas were derived from standard Argos location classes only, and only for birds that survived with a functional transmitter for the entire period. We used great circle paths to measure distances between molt and winter use areas.  Water depths (mean lower low water) associated with eider locations were extracted from National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) digital charts (Maptech Digital ChartKit 2005 Edition, Richardsons' Maptech, New Bedford, Massachusetts, USA). We classified eider locations as &ldquo;deep water&rdquo; when depth exceeded 5 fathoms (~10 m), or &ldquo;shallow water&rdquo; otherwise. We tested a diurnal (day or night) effect on eider use of deep or shallow water at winter areas with a binomial linear mixed model in which area and bird-within-area were treated as random effects. We defined &ldquo;day&rdquo; as 10:00&ndash;16:59 AST and &ldquo;night&rdquo; as 17:00&ndash;09:59 AST, and for analysis we used the glmer function in the  R Development Core Team (2013)  lme4 library ( Bates et al. 2014 ). Proportions of day and night locations predicted to be in deep water were calculated with the predict.merMod function in the lme4 library, while variance in the predictions was calculated from 1,000 bootstrapped iterations derived with the R function bootMer (lme4 library). We used SAS 9.3 software (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina, USA) to compare timing of migration by sex with a Kolmogorov-Smirnov two-sample test (npar1way procedure), variability in timing of migration by sex with Levene's test of equal variance (glm procedure), and linear relationship between size and duration of use areas with Pearson's product-moment correlation (corr procedure). We present descriptive statistics as a range, followed parenthetically by mean &plusmn; SD.  We obtained 7,667 locations from the free-ranging eiders prior to transmitter failure or animal mortality (49&percnt; standard and 51&percnt; auxiliary location quality). Filtering removed 17&percnt; of the auxiliary locations. After selecting the highest quality location per transmitter duty cycle, 1,193 locations (89&percnt; standard, 11&percnt; auxiliary; 57&percnt; male, 43&percnt; female) remained for analysis of movements and use areas.  Temperature sensor data confirmed the mortality of 5 birds (2 females, 3 males) during the study. No mortality occurred immediately following surgery. Deaths occurred at irregular intervals, from August through March, 48&ndash;272 (187 &plusmn; 91) days after release. Loss of signal due to battery failure ( n  &equals; 8) occurred from 191 to 365 (322 &plusmn; 61) days after release. Abrupt signal loss 150 days postsurgery meant that the fate of 1 female could not be conclusively determined. As a consequence of mortalities and battery failures, sample size declined through time and no individual was followed for a second summer.  Five of 8 males (0.62) in this study were known to have survived during the tracking period, and female survival depended on whether we assumed that the female whose fate was ambiguous (because the transmitter abruptly stopped working) had died (0.50, 3/6) or lived (0.67, 4/6). While survival rates among our marked birds were lower than the annual survival rates reported by  Flint et al. (2000)  for male (0.77) and female (0.90) Steller's Eiders, our small sample size precluded meaningful statistical comparison. Nevertheless, recognizing that most of our 9 &ldquo;surviving&rdquo; birds were monitored for less than 1 full year (150&ndash;365 &lsqb;303 &plusmn; 81&rsqb; days), and that weather conditions on the winter range during the years of our study were not unusually harsh ( Petrich et al. 2014 ), a negative transmitter effect on survival is possible.  The breeding female captured and released at her nest site (July 12, 2000) did not resume incubation, but remained in the vicinity. Except for 1 excursion 11 km to the southeast, all her locations before August 6 were within 2 km of the abandoned nest, after which she occupied nearshore marine waters in Elson Lagoon ~30 km from her original nest site. Her August 21 departure from the Barrow area was the latest for any bird in this study.  Presumed breeding males ( n  &equals; 3) released June 15&ndash;19, 2000, remained briefly in freshwater wetlands near Barrow, and then departed July 3&ndash;7. Two individuals remained within 3 km of their release sites, and the third moved ~20 km south to the Walakpa Bay area on Alaska's Chukchi Sea coast, before initiating molt migration.  Presumed nonbreeding birds in 2001 exhibited a variety of movement patterns following release. There was no evidence of site residency over a period of sufficient length to suggest that any of these individuals attempted to nest elsewhere. Most eiders remained within 25 km of Barrow until initiating molt migration, although 4 individuals made excursions to the southwest of up to 150 km before departing from the Barrow area for the season. Mean 2001 departure date was July 6 for males and August 2 for females ( Table 2 ); however, the distribution of departure dates between the sexes was not statistically different ( D  max  &equals; 0.80,  P  &equals; 0.08) owing to 1 female (ID 9920) that departed to Chukotka, Russia, in June while all other females remained in the vicinity of Barrow until August. Differences in departure dates and destinations between individuals of the nonbreeding pairs captured together in 2001 indicated that their subsequent behaviors could be analyzed as independent samples.  Steller's Eiders captured at Barrow, Alaska, June 2000 and 2001, and duration of their molt migrations. Eider IDs marked with the same superscript denote birds captured simultaneously and considered pairs on the basis of behavioral association. Definitive pair affiliations could not be ascertained postcapture for the 2 pairs that were simultaneously caught on June 13, 2001.  Data on molt migration were obtained from 13 birds. Estimated duration of the migration period ranged from 1 to 53 (30 &plusmn; 17) days ( Table 2 ) and did not differ statistically between nonbreeding males and females ( D  max  &equals; 0.60,  P  &equals; 0.36), but duration was more variable among females ( F  1,8  &equals; 5.6,  P  &equals; 0.05).  Fifty-six percent ( n  &equals; 205) of all molt migration stopover use-days ( n  &equals; 365) were along the north coast of Chukotka, and another 20&percnt; ( n  &equals; 73) occurred in the Bering Strait region, which includes the east coast of Chukotka and the Seward Peninsula, Alaska ( Figure 1 ). Sites along the Chukchi Sea coast of Alaska accounted for 19&percnt; of use-days, with sites on the Yukon&ndash;Kuskokwim River Delta of lesser importance (5&percnt; of use-days). Five of 7 males, but only 1 of 6 females, used the north coast of Chukotka during fall migration. Residence at Chukotka stopover sites ranged from 7 to 43 (29 &plusmn; 12) days. The entrance to Koliuchin Bay, near the islands of Serykh Gusey, Russia, was used by 5 males for a total of 132 use-days. Three females and 2 males used migration stopover sites in the Bering Strait region (at Uelen Lagoon and Cape Nanyagmo in Chukotka, Russia, and near Wales, Alaska), with residence times ranging from 3 to 16 (9 &plusmn; 6) days. Sites along the Chukchi Sea coast of Alaska were used briefly (&le;3 days) by birds en route to the coast of Chukotka, and for longer periods (12&ndash;23 days) by males that did not continue to Russia.  The vast majority (&gt;95&percnt;) of locations at stopover sites were in nearshore marine waters within 5 km of the coastline. A notable exception was one eider's brief stopover (repeated locations during a single duty cycle) on Aropuk Lake, one of a series of interconnected inland lakes ~60 km east of Hazen Bay on the Yukon&ndash;Kuskokwim Delta. Although stopover locations were mostly in nearshore waters, 2 offshore migration tracks were documented. On June 24, a female en route to Chukotka was tracked on a westerly course to a point ~450 km offshore of Barrow. On August 9, a male was tracked on a southeasterly course over the Bering Sea (from 125 km north of Savoonga, Alaska, to 76 km east of Northeast Cape). Two other offshore migration tracks were recorded in spring (see below). All offshore in-flight tracking events ranged from 3 to 8 hr in duration. Maximum tracking speeds during these 4 events approached 50 km hr &minus;1 ; thus, this was our best estimate of a minimum, sustained, in-flight ground speed for Steller's Eiders, given that an animal's true rate of movement is typically underestimated by assuming that great-circle routes are strictly followed between tracking locations.  Five distinct areas were used during the period of wing molt, all in the southeastern Bering Sea, from Nunivak Island to the Alaska Peninsula ( Figure 1 ). The most frequently used area was near Cape Avinof on the southwestern coast of the Yukon&ndash;Kuskokwim Delta, in waters adjacent to Kigektek, Pingurbek, and Kwiguk islands (hereafter, &ldquo;Kuskokwim Shoals&rdquo;). The Kuskokwim Shoals area was used by 7 of the 13 individuals.  Arrival dates at molting areas ranged from August 6 to September 10 ( Table 3 ). The distribution of arrival dates between nonbreeding females and males did not differ statistically ( D  max  &equals; 0.80,  P  &equals; 0.08), but was more variable among females ( F  1,8  &equals; 14.2,  P  &equals; 0.006). Estimated residence time at molting areas ( n  &equals; 11) ranged from 46 to 85 (68 &plusmn; 15) days. Departure dates ranged from September 22 to November 19 (October 26 &plusmn; 18 days). Molt use area size (95&percnt; utilization distribution &lsqb;UD&rsqb;) ranged from 12 to 186 (75 &plusmn; 55) km 2 , did not differ between the sexes ( D  max  &equals; 0.33,  P  &equals; 0.82), but was weakly correlated with duration of use ( r  &equals; 0.58,  P  &equals; 0.06,  n  &equals; 11).  Location, size, and timing of use of molt use areas occupied by Steller's Eiders in southwestern Alaska, fall 2000 and 2001.  Eleven birds provided postmolting movement data. All but 1 bird (ID 9921, near Nelson Lagoon) migrated from molting areas to other areas used during the winter period. Birds that molted north of the Alaska Peninsula ( n  &equals; 7) migrated 448&ndash;537 (508 &plusmn; 30) km from molting to wintering areas, while birds that molted on the Alaska Peninsula ( n  &equals; 4) moved only 11&ndash;330 (138 &plusmn; 156) km to wintering areas ( Figure 2 ). Six individuals moved from their molting area to a persistent winter use area within 2 consecutive transmitter duty cycles (i.e. in &le;6 days), but the other eiders relocated up to 5 times, sometimes remaining for up to 3 weeks at a single stopover site. Fall migration duration ranged from 0 to 43 (15 &plusmn; 19) days.  Fall movements from molting areas to winter use areas by 6 male and 5 female Steller's Eiders fitted with satellite transmitters near Barrow, Alaska, in June 2000 and 2001. Numerals indicate the number of individual birds that occupied the winter use area. Colored lines follow idealized routes for each individual to illustrate connectivity between molting and winter areas. Arrowheads denote arrival at primary and secondary winter use areas (see  Table 4 ).  Location, size, and timing of use of winter use areas occupied by Steller's Eiders in southwestern Alaska, winter 2000&ndash;2001 and 2001&ndash;2002. Primary use areas are denoted with bold font. Estimated duration, area, and maximum distance offshore are reported only for individuals that survived with functional transmitters for the entire period.  Eleven birds provided data on wintering areas ( Table 4 ). All winter use areas were located in nearshore waters adjacent to the Alaska Peninsula and associated islands ( Figure 2 ). Most birds spent the winter at 1 or 2 areas, designated as &ldquo;primary&rdquo; and &ldquo;secondary&rdquo; winter use areas depending on the length of residence ( Table 4 ). For birds that used 2 winter areas ( n  &equals; 5), the change in location occurred rapidly (&le;3 days). Timing varied, with 1 bird occupying a secondary use area from November to early February and another from late January to late February (between 2 periods of residence at a primary use area). Three birds with primary use areas on the southern side of the Alaska Peninsula (Sanak Islands, Wide Bay) initiated movement to secondary areas on the northern side of the Alaska Peninsula (Izembek Lagoon, Cinder River Estuary, Port Heiden) from late February to mid-March.  Six birds provided data for the entire winter period ( Table 4 ). Among these individuals, residence time in primary use areas ranged from 88 to 204 (121 &plusmn; 44) days. Residence time in secondary use areas ranged from 33 to 76 (51 &plusmn; 19) days. The size of primary use areas ranged from 14 to 424 (163 &plusmn; 148) km 2 . Use area size was not correlated with residence time for either primary use areas ( r  &equals; 0.37,  P  &equals; 0.47,  n  &equals; 6) or secondary use areas ( r  &equals; 0.07,  P  &equals; 0.91,  n  &equals; 5). All winter use areas were adjacent to the coastline, with maximum distance offshore ranging from 2.3 km (Sanak Islands) to 19.5 km (Port Heiden).  Use of deep water (&gt;10 m) was widespread among individuals and tended to occur after November ( Figure 3 A). Occupancy of deep water after November was significantly influenced by time of day ( z  &equals; &minus;5.1,  P  &lt; 0.001, df &equals; 308), with 36&percnt; (&plusmn; 12&percnt;) of nighttime and 5&percnt; (&plusmn; 4&percnt;) of daytime locations predicted to be in waters &gt;10 m deep ( Figure 3 B).  ( A ) Pooled time series of Steller's Eider locations at winter use areas along the Alaska Peninsula in winter 2000&ndash;2001 and 2001&ndash;2002 that were in deep (&gt;10 m) or shallow (&le;10 m) water. All birds began to use deeper offshore waters after November when ( B ) locations in deep water were obtained primarily during nighttime hours.  Departure dates from winter use areas on the Alaska Peninsula ranged from April 16 to May 8 (4 males, 2 females). Two spring migration tracks were obtained for birds (ID 9908 and 9912) that departed from Izembek Lagoon and flew north across Bristol Bay, passing 25&ndash;50 km to the west of Cape Newenham. All spring migrants used the Kuskokwim Shoals area for an extended period of time, with arrival as early as April 18 and departures between May 17 and June 9. Residence times at Kuskokwim Shoals ranged from 21 to at least 38 days (1 transmitter failed after 38 days, but the bird may have remained longer). Only 4 individuals (1 female, 3 males) continued to provide location data after departing Kuskokwim Shoals. The female's (ID 9918) final location (June 5, 2002) was near Peard Bay, Alaska Chukchi Sea coast, at a locale where she had resided for most of July in the previous summer. One male (ID 9912) was last located on the south coast of St. Lawrence Island on June 12, 2001. Another male (ID 9926) traversed the south coast of Chukotka (consecutive locations at Cape Bering and Kresta Bay) and was last located in the Kolyma River Delta, 1,600 km west of Barrow, on June 4, 2002. The third male (ID 9923) remained at Kuskokwim Shoals until at least May 26, followed by a hiatus in locations, and a final location at the Kolyma River Delta on June 13, 2002.  We found no evidence that the Alaska-breeding population of Steller's Eiders segregates from the Russia-breeding population in winter, because locations of the Alaska-tagged birds were broadly distributed along the Alaska Peninsula where the Pacific population as a whole is known to winter ( Larned 2012 ).  During the wing molt period, 7 of 13 tagged eiders (54&percnt;) used Kuskokwim Shoals, which was identified as a molting area as early as 1975 (C. Dau personal communication). Counts of 5,000&ndash;6,000 Steller's Eiders were estimated through aerial reconnaissance in September of 1996, 2000, and 2001; and over 11,000 were observed at Kuskokwim Shoals in 2005 ( Larned and Tiplady 1996 , B. McCaffery personal communication). These estimates represent 6&ndash;13&percnt; of the average southwestern Alaska spring population of 84,000 ( Larned 2005 ), suggesting disproportionately high use of Kuskokwim Shoals amongst our sample. If Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders preferentially and extensively use Kuskokwim Shoals for molting, they could be particularly susceptible to threats in this area.  The Kuskokwim Shoals area is also a spring staging area frequently used by Steller's Eiders, based on data from systematic aerial surveys of the southwestern Alaska coast conducted in April and early May in many years between 1992 and 2012 (e.g.,  Larned 2005 ,  2012 ). Our telemetry results reinforce the importance of the Kuskokwim Shoals area by documenting not only a high frequency of use, but also an extended period of use (3&ndash;5 weeks). Most eiders remained at Kuskokwim Shoals throughout May despite ice-free coastal waters becoming available farther north (National Ice Center,  http://www.natice.noaa.gov ), suggesting that their extended use of the Shoals was not because of ice conditions precluding continued migration. The spring staging pattern of our small sample of tagged Steller's Eiders is notably different from that of King (  Somateria spectabilis  ) and Common eiders (  S. mollissima  ), which use the eastern Chukchi Sea as a major spring staging area ( Oppel et al. 2009 ,  Petersen 2009 ).  Late-summer aggregations of Steller's Eiders in Chukotka were observed over 100 yr ago by  Nelson (1883) , who described vast flocks near Cape Vankarem in early August, 1881. Recent observations confirm that the northern coast of Chukotka from the Anguyema River to Koliuchin Bay remains a region of large (4,000&ndash;19,000 birds) summer aggregations ( Syroechkovski et al. 2003 ,  Kochnev et al. 2005 ). All observations indicate that males greatly outnumber females at these sites, consistent with our tracking data in which twice as many males as females (6:3) used coastal sites in Chukotka during summer.  Although tagged Steller's Eiders were broadly distributed along the Alaska Peninsula during midwinter (November&ndash;March), individual birds each used only 1 or 2 relatively small areas. Even the larger individual winter use areas were &lt;40 km wide, and the smallest was &lt;5 km wide, consistent with localized winter use areas observed for other small sea ducks ( Iverson et al. 2004 ,  Reed and Flint 2007 ). Steller's Eiders are generally described as preferring shallow waters (e.g.,  McKinney 1965 ,  Petersen 1980 ,  Metzner 1993 ,  Bustnes and Systad 2001 ), with foraging reported at depths as low as 6 m, and in some circumstances down to 10 m ( Petraitis 1991 ). Our results partially agree with that pattern, but we also found that a substantial proportion of locations were in water &gt;10 m deep at most winter use areas ( Table 4 ). Furthermore, the deep-water (&gt;10 m) habitats were almost exclusively used during nighttime hours ( Figure 3 B).  Steller's Eiders in Varangerfjord, Norway, spent less time feeding and more time sleeping at night ( Fox and Mitchell 1997 ); similarly, our locations of eiders in deep water may have been associated with resting activities. Alternatively, the eiders may have been exploiting prey resources at night that were not found in shallower waters. Steller's Eiders rely on mobile crustaceans to a greater extent than other sea ducks ( Bustnes et al. 2000 ), and many zooplankton species exhibit diel vertical migrations, ascending to the surface at night. In the nearshore waters of the eastern Bering Sea, the euphausiid   Thysanoessa raschii   is a prominent example ( Schatsberger et al. 2000 ,  Coyle and Pinchuk 2002 ). Because use of deep-water habitats in our study did not commence until December ( Figure 3 A), there may be a seasonal component to prey availability or a shift in foraging strategies with diminishing daylight. Regardless of the behavioral basis for the observed nighttime use of deep-water habitats, the presumption that Steller's Eiders almost exclusively occupy waters &lt;10 m deep (e.g.,  Federal Register 2001 ) should be reevaluated. Recognizing that Steller's Eiders use deeper-water offshore habitats during December through April could possibly improve the efficacy of environmental impact analyses, as well as the accuracy of population estimates obtained from aerial surveys.  Most of our tagged eiders (10 of 14 individuals) were captured in 2001, a low-nesting year near Barrow. After release, females implanted with transmitters did not appear to attempt to nest in an alternative area. If the behavior of the birds with transmitters was representative, our data support the notion that low-nesting years at Barrow represent an actual lost reproductive opportunity rather than nomadic behavior during the prenesting period. Capture and transmitter implantation may, however, have affected the subsequent behaviors of our tagged birds ( Wilson and McMahon 2006 ). We documented one instance of nest abandonment by an implanted female in 2000, similar to studies of other species that have documented alterations in nesting behavior following implantation of transmitters ( Garrettson and Rohwer 1998 ,  Meyers et al. 1998 ). Several visual observations of birds that had been implanted with transmitters traveling with conspecific flocks at distances up to 20 km from the capture site, however, suggested that the movements of implanted birds during the premigratory period were representative of birds unaffected by the treatment. Our data are insufficient to determine whether long-distance movement behaviors were influenced by the transmitters, but the extent of seasonal movements by the tagged birds was consistent with the population's known distribution.  Our study indicates marked individual variation in the timing and location of movements throughout the annual cycle. If our sample is representative of the Alaska-breeding population as a whole, the risk of population-level impacts from localized pollution or disturbances during the nonbreeding season is diminished due to the birds' dispersed distribution. Concentrated use of Kuskokwim Shoals during molt and spring migration is an exception to this generality, however. Coupled with survey results that document use of this area by a large proportion of the Pacific population in spring, it is clear that conservation of Kuskokwim Shoals is important to the Alaska-breeding population of Steller's Eiders and should receive special attention in environmental impact analyses and for species recovery efforts in general.  Steller's Eiders captured at Barrow used molting and wintering areas in southwestern Alaska that were also used by Russia-breeding birds. Many eiders tagged near Barrow visited the Chukotka coast during molt migration, with stays lasting up to 6 weeks. Males in particular spent extended periods at Russian staging areas. Thus, conservation of Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders depends in part on environmental and wildlife management practices in Russia.  All 3 males that provided locations after departing Kuskokwim Shoals in spring of 2002 migrated to Russia, providing evidence that (1) the area may be important to a much broader fraction of the Pacific population than just those nesting in Alaska, and (2) males may shift their summer destination in successive years, as is known in other eiders ( Phillips and Powell 2006 ,  Petersen 2009 ). Interchange of breeding areas may not apply to females, however, since female breeding site fidelity is common in eiders ( Phillips and Powell 2006 ,  Petersen 2009 ), including the 1 female in this study (ID 9918) that was tracked long enough to document her apparent return to the breeding area in Alaska. Additional studies are needed to acquire a better understanding of breeding site fidelity of Steller's Eiders, including noninvasive DNA approaches ( Rudnick et al. 2009 ,  Booms et al. 2011 ) that have the potential to yield larger sample sizes at lower cost and with less risk to study subjects than telemetry.  The question of whether there is an ecologically and behaviorally distinct Alaska-breeding population has important management implications, because the ESA-listed entity of Steller's Eiders is the Alaska-breeding population. The potential conservation benefits of management actions intended to improve nest success and adult survival at Barrow, as well as reintroduction into areas other than Barrow, is related to the propensity of Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders for breeding site fidelity or natal philopatry. Long-term banding efforts of nesting females near Barrow, and recent collections of genetic material, have provided evidence of some level of breeding site fidelity (D. Safine personal communication). This study provides no new information on breeding site fidelity of females, as none of the transmitters functioned longer than 1 yr. Disproportionate use of Kuskokwim Shoals for molting, however, implies a level of behavioral distinctiveness in Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders that may have an indirect bearing on the question of natal philopatry. High rates of fidelity to molting sites are reported by  Flint et al. (2000) , but the basis for the initial choice of molting site is not known. In the absence of some degree of natal philopatry, it is difficult to envision a mechanism for establishing and perpetuating the selective use of Kuskokwim Shoals among Alaska-breeding Steller's Eiders.  We thank the following persons who aided in trapping eiders: N. Adams, B. Akootchook, J. Connor, M. Corrigan, C. Edwards, L. Guyer, J. Judkins, B. Lake, G. Leavitt, A. Matz, B. Meiklejohn, N. Pamperin, L. Phillips, M. Reakoff, D. Rudis, and N. Stellrecht. Veterinarian C. Scott kindly supervised the implantation surgeries with the assistance of veterinarians H. Neville and K. Wellington. C. Hanns facilitated the use of the North Slope Borough Veterinary Clinic. R. Suydam, North Slope Borough Department of Wildlife Management, supported the project in numerous ways. J. Bromaghin graciously contributed statistical analysis and technical review. S. Oppel, A. Powell, D. Safine, J. Schmutz, and T. Swem provided valuable comments that improved an early draft of the manuscript.   Funding statement:  Funding for purchase of transmitters and satellite data was provided by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS), U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, and U.S. Air Force. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript, nor did they require approval of the manuscript before submission or publication. The findings and conclusions in this paper are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the USFWS. This paper was reviewed and approved by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) under their Fundamental Science Practices policy ( http://www.usgs.gov/fsp ). Use of trade names is for descriptive purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by the U.S. government.   Ethics statement:  Efforts were taken to minimize impacts on Steller's Eiders through the application process for a permit pursuant to section 10(a)(1)(A) of the ESA (permit TE043136), and USFWS Alaska Region standards for animal care were ensured through the supervision of experienced wildlife veterinarians. 