Individual quality and double-brooding in a highly synchronous songbird populationTree Swallows trade off immune function and reproductive effort differently across their rangelme4: Linear mixed-effects models using Eigen and S4. R package version 1.1-7Timing of current reproduction directly affects future reproductive output in European CootsReproductive costs in the House Martin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Delichon urbica</named-content></italic>)Factors affecting the probability of double-brooding by Southern House WrensIndividual variation in parental workload and breeding productivity in female European Starlings: Is the effort worth it?Incidents and determinants of double-brooding in WrentitsIndividual variation in reproductive costs of reproduction: High-quality females always do betterFactors influencing double brooding in Eurasian Hoopoes <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Upupa epops</named-content></italic>Multiple brooding and productivity of a Neotropical migrant, the Black-throated Blue Warbler (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendroica caerulescens</named-content></italic>), in an unfragmented temperate forestDecline in the frequency and benefits of multiple brooding in Great Tits as a consequence of changing environmentIndividual quality explains association between plumage colouration, arrival dates and mate acquisition in Yellow Warblers (<italic>Setophaga petechia</italic>)The significance of clutch-sizeThe adaptive value of stress-induced phenotypes: Effects of maternally derived corticosterone on sex-biased investment, cost of reproduction, and maternal fitnessAvian life history evolution in relation to nest sites, nest predation, and foodZero tolerance ecology: Improving ecological inference by modeling the source of zero observationsComponents of variance underlying fitness in a natural population of the Great Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>Reproductive effort and return rates in the Mountain White-crowned SparrowFactors influencing fecundity in migratory songbirds: Is nest predation the most important?Food limits annual fecundity of a migratory songbird: An experimental studyTo double-brood or not? Individual variation in the reproductive effort in Black-throated Blue Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dendroica caerulescens</named-content></italic>)Experimental dissociation of individual quality, food and timing of breeding effects on double-brooding in a migratory songbirdConstraints on double-brooding in a Neotropical migrant, the Hooded WarblerBrood size manipulation affects frequency of second clutches in the Blue Titnlme: Linear and nonlinear mixed effects models. R package version 3.1-113Males achieve greater reproductive success through multiple broods than through extrapair mating in House WrensCosts of reproduction: An evaluation of empirical evidenceIs there an optimal clutch size in Snow Geese?Results of experimental and natural food reductions for breeding Black-throated Blue WarblersManipulating rearing conditions reveals developmental sensitivity in the smaller sex of a passerine bird, the European Starling <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>Avian life history variation and contribution of demographic traits to the population growth rateLimitation of reproductive success by food availability and breeding time in Pied FlycatchersSelection for synchronous breeding in the European StarlingSeasonal variation in the incidence of double-broods: The date hypothesis fits better than the quality hypothesisFood, reproductive success and multiple breeding in the Great Tit, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>Sex-specific development of avian flight performance under experimentally altered rearing conditionsConstraints on, and determinants of, the annual number of breeding attempts in the multi-brooded Black Redstart <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus ochruros</named-content></italic>Heterogeneity in individual quality overrides costs of reproduction in female reindeerMid-winter temperatures, not spring temperatures, predict breeding phenology in the European Starling <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>What is individual quality? An evolutionary perspectiveDiagnostic checking in regression relationshipsRegression models for count data in RMultiple brooding, the production of more than one set of offspring per breeding season, is a life-history trait that potentially doubles or triples fecundity, but the factors responsible for variation in the occurrence of multiple brooding within species remain poorly understood. We investigated the potential causes and consequences of double-brooding in the highly synchronously breeding European Starling (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>), for which we predicted that clutch initiation date would have little effect on double-brooding propensity compared with individual quality. Double-brooding effectively doubled annual fecundity in European Starlings (based on the annual number of chicks fledged), but on average only 38&percnt; of individual females had a second brood. Furthermore, 39&percnt; of females that initiated a second clutch experienced total failure of their second brood, and thus accrued no advantage in fecundity from their decision to double-brood. As we predicted, variation in the propensity for, and success of, double-brooding was independent of laying date, but also of other putative measures of individual quality (clutch size, egg mass, relative female age, and nestling provisioning rate). However, we found no evidence of a cost of double-brooding; females that double-brooded had significantly higher return rates and similar breeding productivity in the year after double-brooding compared with single-brooding females. Thus, a small proportion (~20&percnt;) of &lsquo;high-quality' female European Starlings effectively double their potential breeding productivity through double-brooding without apparently paying a cost or experiencing any simple tradeoffs.Las nidadas m&uacute;ltiples, que representan la producci&oacute;n de m&aacute;s de un juego de cr&iacute;as por estaci&oacute;n reproductiva, son un rasgo de la historia de vida que potencialmente duplica o triplica la fecundidad, pero poco se sabe de los factores responsables de la variaci&oacute;n <italic>intra-espec&iacute;fica</italic> en la presencia de nidadas m&uacute;ltiples. Investigamos las causas y consecuencias potenciales de la nidada doble en individuos reproductivos altamente sincr&oacute;nicos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>, donde predijimos que la &lsquo;fecha' (inicio de la nidada) tendr&iacute;a un efecto moderado en la propensi&oacute;n a la nidada doble comparada con la &lsquo;calidad' individual. La nidada doble efectivamente duplic&oacute; la fecundidad anual en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. vulgaris</named-content></italic> (basado en el n&uacute;mero anual de polluelos criados), pero en promedio solo 38&percnt; de las hembras presentaron nidada doble. M&aacute;s a&uacute;n, 39&percnt; de las hembras que iniciaron una segunda nidada fracasaron totalmente en su segundo intento, por lo que no acumularon una ventaja en su fecundidad a partir de su decisi&oacute;n de realizar una nidada doble. Como predijimos, la variaci&oacute;n en la propensi&oacute;n a, y el &eacute;xito de, la nidada doble fue independiente de la fecha de puesta, pero tambi&eacute;n de otras medidas putativas de la &lsquo;calidad' individual (tama&ntilde;o de la nidada, masa del huevo, edad relativa y tasa de aprovisionamiento). Sin embargo, no encontramos evidencia de un costo de la nidada doble; las hembras con nidada doble presentaron una tasa de retorno significativamente m&aacute;s alta y una productividad reproductiva similar en el a&ntilde;o posterior a la nidada doble en comparaci&oacute;n con las hembras con nidada simple. Por ende, una peque&ntilde;a proporci&oacute;n (~20&percnt;) de las hembras de &lsquo;alta calidad' de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. vulgaris</named-content></italic> efectivamente duplicaron su productividad reproductiva potencial a trav&eacute;s de la nidada doble sin aparentemente pagar un costo o sufrir soluciones de compromiso simples.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> calidad individual, fecha de puesta, fenolog&iacute;a reproductiva, nidada m&uacute;ltipleBirds have evolved a variety of strategies for maximizing fecundity, despite the constraints of clutch size per brood, and one such mechanism is to produce multiple broods of offspring in a single breeding season, which can potentially double or triple fecundity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Lack1">Lack 1947</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Rockwell1">Rockwell et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Martin1">Martin 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-McCleery1">McCleery et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Weggler1">Weggler 2006</xref>). Some populations of species in at least 64 avian families are known to pursue multiple broods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Bennett1">Bennett and Owens 2002</xref>), and in some species the number of broods has been used to predict reproductive success with better accuracy than the success of one brood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Sather1">S&aelig;ther and Bakke 2000</xref>). Nevertheless, although double-brooding can have seemingly obvious and significant consequences for individual fecundity, second brood success is often not quantified in avian breeding studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Holmes1">Holmes et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Ogden1">Ogden and Stutchbury 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Nagy1">Nagy and Holmes 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Weggler1">Weggler 2006</xref>). In addition, the fitness consequences of double-brooding in adults (survival, future fecundity) as a result of increased reproductive effort are relatively poorly studied (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and Desante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Morton1">Morton et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Nagy3">Nagy and Holmes 2005b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>). Previous studies have suggested that double-brooding can be associated with lower survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Bryant1">Bryant 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Brinkhof1">Brinkhof et al. 2002</xref>) or no survival cost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and Desante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Morton1">Morton et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Nagy3">Nagy and Holmes 2005b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>), but few studies have considered the effects on future fecundity, likely due to a combination of low return rates and the difficulty of repeatedly finding nests belonging to the same individuals.Numerous studies have suggested that the timing of breeding&ndash;laying date of the first clutch&mdash;is the most important factor determining the propensity for double-brooding: The incidence of second clutches generally declines the later the first clutch is initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and DeSante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Verboven2">Verboven et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Brinkhof1">Brinkhof et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Parejo1">Parejo and Danchin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-OBrien1">O'Brien and Dawson 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Hoffmann1">Hoffmann et al. 2015</xref>). A higher frequency of double-brooding among early-laying females could occur simply because these females then have more time to rear a second brood, or because their initially early laying date makes them less affected by seasonal declines in the quality of the rearing environment (e.g., the feeding of earlier second broods can still be relatively synchronous with the seasonal peak in food supply (date hypothesis); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Verboven1">Verboven and Verhulst 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>). Alternatively, early-laying females might be high-quality individuals (quality hypothesis), such that females differ in their intrinsic ability to produce and raise a second brood. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Hoffmann1">Hoffmann et al. (2015)</xref> suggested that high-quality, early-laying females might be better able to sustain the energetic investment costs of producing both first and second clutches. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-OBrien1">O'Brien and Dawson (2013)</xref> showed that the highest-quality female Mountain Bluebirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia currucoides</named-content></italic>), which were naturally early breeders, were better able to compensate for the effects of experimentally delayed breeding, whereas lower-quality females were much less likely to double-brood when their first attempt was delayed.Here, we investigate the potential causes and consequences of double-brooding in free-living European Starlings (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>) in the context of the individual quality vs. date hypotheses. In our study population, females facultatively double-brood (~40&percnt; of females produce a second clutch; see Results), even though egg-laying is highly synchronous for first broods: Mean egg-laying date varies by &plusmn;4 days among years, and 80&percnt; of nests are initiated within a 5-day period within years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Williams1">Williams et al. 2015</xref>). We therefore predicted that laying date would not be a strong driver of the propensity to double-brood in this population, so that we could identify phenotypic components of individual quality (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Wilson1">Wilson and Nussey 2010</xref>) that were associated with a double-brooding strategy. Our specific objectives were: (1) to quantify how much more successful double-brooding females are compared with females that produce only a single brood in terms of total breeding productivity, and where this increased productivity comes from, i.e. how important is additive productivity from the second brood vs. higher first brood productivity; (2) to determine whether the propensity for, and/or success of, double-brooding is associated with putative measures of individual quality (laying date, egg and clutch size, relative female age, chick provisioning rate, size-corrected body mass); (3) to test whether the success of second broods is explained by within-season nest-site fidelity or nest switching between first and second broods; and (4) to determine whether there is a &lsquo;cost' of double-brooding in European Starlings in terms of a reduced local return rate of individual females between years or breeding productivity the following year.We used 10 yr of breeding data (2004&ndash;2014) from our long-term European Starling study at Davistead Farm, Langley, British Columbia, Canada (49.17&deg;N, 122.83&deg;W), which comprises ~150 nest boxes mounted on posts around pastures and on farm buildings. All nest boxes are surrounded by, and potentially equidistant from, similar high-quality foraging areas (pasture). Nest predation is low, and many boxes to which birds do not return are occupied in subsequent years. In each year, we followed the same basic field protocol: Nest boxes were checked daily from April 1 to determine laying date and clutch size, all newly laid eggs were measured (&plusmn;0.001 g), and nests were monitored until either failure or fledging to quantify productivity. In several years we conducted experiments that involved catching females upon clutch completion and removing their eggs to stimulate the laying of replacement clutches (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Love1">Love and Williams 2008</xref>). Therefore, we restricted our analysis to clutches initiated during the first peak of egg-laying in each year, defined as a 12-day period from the earliest first nest initiation date (based on a mean 5-egg clutch, 2 further days for determination of clutch completion, and a minimum renesting interval after egg removal of 5 days), so that we excluded any potential replacement clutches in experimental years in which first clutches were removed. Only known control birds were used from experimental years, and experimental birds were excluded from analysis in the subsequent year of treatment to minimize potential carry-over effects. No egg removal (and experimentally delayed laying) occurred in 2012&ndash;2014, so we restricted some analyses to these years, where indicated, to understand population-level annual trends (see Results).During the period when starlings had their first broods, we were successful in banding 398/419 (95&percnt;) of all females with nests that survived until hatching across years. We missed banding the remaining individuals largely due to early nest failure or abandonment, hence our restriction of first broods to the peak laying period to exclude replacement nests of birds of unknown status (unbanded birds). Females that failed to fledge offspring from their first clutch laid replacement clutches in only 19 instances, 12 of which were successful in fledging young (~8&percnt; of all single-brooders or 16&percnt; of failed single-brooders). We included productivity resulting from replacement clutches in the total annual productivity analysis, but not in the calculation of first brood productivity. None of the individuals that laid a replacement clutch attempted to double-brood. We checked all nest boxes regularly during the second brood window, beginning ~31 days (10 days of incubation, 21 days to fledging) after clutch completion of the earliest first clutch, and trapped and identified 160/198 (81&percnt;) of females with nests that survived to hatch across years. Only known individuals (numbered Federal metal bands) that laid clutches during both the first and second brood windows were classified as &lsquo;double-brooders'; unbanded birds (single- or double-brooding) were not included in any analyses.Local return rate and relative age (age &equals; 1 in the first year in which birds were encountered and banded as adults) were determined by the recapture of banded individuals in subsequent years. Our detection probability was high, as only 5/125 individuals (4&percnt;) skipped years in our records. Due to the multiple years included in this dataset, laying date was calculated as a residual based on the annual mean laying date. In order to assess parental provisioning (nest visitation) rates, we conducted 30-min surveys from 09:00 to 14:00 on days 6, 7, and 8 posthatching, either 3 times (75&percnt; of nests) or twice (25&percnt; of nests). Therefore, we obtained either 1.0 hr or 1.5 hr of data per nest, and we standardized the timing of observations. Days 6&ndash;8 were chosen as they represent the period of most rapid chick growth, and we used the mean nest visitation rate over 3 days. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Fowler1">Fowler and Williams (2015)</xref> conducted a detailed analysis of these data and showed that nest visitation rate was highly correlated among successive days (hence the decision to use the mean), that is nest visitation rate was repeatable. Nest visitation rate was also repeatable within years between first and second broods, confirming that it does capture individual variation in provisioning. We used this standardized approach in our previous studies, and it does have the power to detect treatment effects in provisioning rate in experimental studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Rowland1">Rowland et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Verspoor1">Verspoor et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Love1">Love and Williams 2008</xref>). For some analyses, individuals that pursued second broods but failed to fledge offspring from the second nest were grouped as failed double-brooders. Individuals that fledged &ge;1 offspring from the second clutch were grouped as successful. Because many single-brooding individuals fledged zero young (failed single-brooders; see Results), we excluded these birds where indicated to avoid favorable bias toward double-brooders. Values in the tables and Results are presented as means &plusmn; standard deviations.All analyses were completed in RStudio 0.98.1028 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2013</xref>) using the pscl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Zeileis2">Zeileis et al. 2008</xref>), lme4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Bates1">Bates et al. 2014</xref>), lmtest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Zeileis1">Zeileis and Hothorn 2002</xref>), nlme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Pinheiro1">Pinheiro et al. 2013</xref>), and stats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2013</xref>) packages. Linear mixed-effects models were used to compare the breeding productivity, individual quality metrics, nest visitation rate, and subsequent year's laying date of single- and double-brooders and failed and successful double-brooders, with band number (individual) as a random factor. Clutch size was only incorporated into models where noted. Analysis of return rates was done using generalized linear mixed-effects models with a binomial distribution, controlling for individual (band number) and year as random factors. Significance was determined by comparing the fit of the models with and without the terms of interest using likelihood ratio tests (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Jones1">Jones et al. 2014</xref>). Subsequent-year productivity was analyzed using a zero-adjusted Poisson (ZAP) or hurdle model, similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Jones1">Jones et al. (2014)</xref>, due to the high distribution of zeros and few repeat measures (no random effect of individual). These models are suitable for data with a high proportion of true zero values (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Martin2">Martin et al 2005</xref>) because they treat zeros simultaneously as a count metric and as a negative binomial, which cannot be simply modeled with a normal, binomial, or Poisson distribution. The significance of the terms of interest was determined by comparing the fit of the models with and without the terms of interest using likelihood ratio tests.In 2012&ndash;2014 (years in which we did not do any manipulation of laying date), 43&percnt; of 65 (2012), 36&percnt; of 89 (2013), and 44&percnt; of 43 (2014) individual females double-brooded, but for these double-brooding females, 42&percnt; of 27 (2012), 29&percnt; of 28 (2013), and 42&percnt; of 19 (2014) birds experienced total brood failure of their second brood (hereafter, failed double-brooders, compared with successful double-brooders who fledged young from both broods). Neither the proportion of single- to double-brooders nor successful to failed double-brooders varied among years (number of broods: <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 1.17, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.56; success of the second brood: <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm06"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm06.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 1.79, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.41). When the single-brooders that failed to rear any chicks from the first brood (hereafter, failed single-brooders, compared with successful single-brooders who did fledge chicks from the first brood) were excluded, the frequency of double-brooding did not vary among years: 49&percnt; of 46 (2012), 52&percnt; of 46 (2013), and 60&percnt; of 27 (2014; <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm07"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm07.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.94, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.63).Mean annual productivity estimated as brood size at fledging from all breeding attempts was almost twice as high for double-brooding females as for all single-brooding females (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,61</sub> &equals; 108.02, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Furthermore, brood size at fledging for first broods alone was significantly higher for double-brooding females than for all single-brooding females (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,56</sub> &equals; 18.80, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001, controlling for clutch size; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>). Productivity resulting from replacement clutches (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 12) was included in the total annual productivity analysis, but not in the calculation of first brood productivity. When we restricted our analysis to successful single-brooders, breeding productivity from first broods was similar for single- and double-brooding females (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,47</sub> &equals; 2.25 <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>); however, overall, double-brooders still produced more total annual offspring than successful single-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,47</sub> &equals; 24.31, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, controlling for clutch size; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>). Among double-brooders who were successful in fledging offspring from the second brood, brood size at fledging from the second clutch was reduced compared with the first clutch (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>52</sub> &equals; 3.82, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Mean values and 95&percnt; confidence limits of productivity and breeding cost metrics. The 1<sup>st</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value corresponds to the comparison between all single-brooders and all double-brooders, the 2<sup>nd</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value to the comparison between successful single-brooders and all double-brooders, and the 3<sup>rd</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value to the comparison between successful and failed double-brooders of European Starlings in our study site in British Columbia, Canada, 2004&ndash;2014. Productivity is the number of chicks fledged, and local return rate is the percentage of females that returned to the study site in subsequent breeding seasons. Subsequent year laying date is the laying date of the first egg in the following year, relative to the mean laying date for that year, with negative values being days earlier than the mean and positive values being days after the mean.Total annual productivity (i.e. sum of offspring fledged from 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> nesting attempts) for the successful single-brooders and all double-brooders of European Starlings in our study site in British Columbia, Canada, 2004&ndash;2014. Frequency reflects the percentage of successful single-brooders and all double-brooders, respectively.Productivity of first broods for all single-brooding females had a bimodal distribution, with 73/157 (46&percnt;) females failing to fledge any offspring. Similarly, for double-brooding females, brood size at fledging for second broods had a bimodal distribution, with 34/87 (39&percnt;) double-brooding females failing to fledge any offspring from their second brood. Females that fledged no offspring from their second brood (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 34) were just as successful in their first brood attempts as individuals who did fledge chicks from their second brood (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,16</sub> &equals; 0.03, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.87; controlling for clutch size; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Productivity data for all double-brooders' 2<sup>nd</sup> broods, 1<sup>st</sup> brood productivity of successful double-brooders (&gt;0 chicks fledged from second brood), and 1<sup>st</sup> brood productivity of failed double-brooders (0 chicks fledged from second brood) of European Starlings in our study site in British Columbia, Canada, 2004&ndash;2014.The mean relative laying date of first clutches was not significantly different between single- and double-brooding females, either including all single-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,73</sub> &equals; 1.17, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.28) or excluding the failed single-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,55</sub> &equals; 0.43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.51). Furthermore, single-brooders did not differ from double-brooders in the clutch size of their first breeding attempt (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,63</sub> &equals; 0.26, <italic>P &equals;</italic> 0.61), mean egg size (controlling for clutch size, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,65</sub> &equals; 1.72, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.19), or relative age (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,62</sub> &equals; 3.44, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t02">Table 2</xref>; excluding failed single-brooders, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.09). Size-corrected body mass for 3 yr (2012&ndash;2014; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 88) also showed no difference between all single-brooders and double-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,84</sub> &equals; 2.62, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.19) or between successful single-brooders and double-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,15</sub> &equals; 1.89, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.19).Averages &plusmn; standard deviations and significance of individual quality metrics between all single-brooders (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 157) vs. double-brooders (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 95; 1<sup>st</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value), successful single-brooders (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 84) vs. double-brooders (2<sup>nd</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value), and successful (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 53) vs. failed double-brooders (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 34; 3<sup>rd</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value) of European Starlings in our study site in British Columbia, Canada, 2004&ndash;2014. Clutch size refers to the 1<sup>st</sup> brood only. Female provisioning rate is the number of visits to the nest per chick every 30 min. Relative laying date is measured in days relative to the mean laying date for each year; egg size is measured in grams; and relative female age is measured in years, with the first year of capture equal to 1.Among double-brooding females, comparing failed double-brooders (fledged no chicks from the second brood) with successful double-brooders (fledged &ge;1 chick from both broods), there was no difference in relative laying date of the first clutch (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,22</sub> &equals; 2.36, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14), clutch size of the first clutch (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,18</sub> &equals; 1.35, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26), mean egg size (controlling for clutch size, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,13</sub> &equals; 1.36, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22), or relative age (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,18</sub> &equals; 0.55, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.47; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t02">Table 2</xref>). Overall, 48&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 54) of successful double-brooding females retained the same nest box between breeding attempts, compared with 62&percnt; of failed double-brooding females (<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm08"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm08.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 1.06, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.30). Laying date of the second brood was related to nest-box fidelity, with birds that retained the same box laying earlier (&minus;0.26 &plusmn; 4.77 days relative to the mean laying date for the year) than birds that switched their box (1.49 &plusmn; 3.23 days; Welch's two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>81</sub> &equals; &minus;2.03, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, among successful double-brooding females, the mean number of offspring fledged from the second brood did not differ between birds that switched boxes (2.82 &plusmn; 1.28 chicks) and birds that retained boxes from the first to the second breeding attempt (2.93 &plusmn; 1.26 chicks; Welch's two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>51</sub> &equals; 0.29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.77).The provisioning rate (nest visits per chick per 30 min) of first broods did not differ between double-brooding and single-brooding females (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,27</sub> &equals; 3.06, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.09; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t02">Table 2</xref>). Similarly, neither male visitation rate nor total visitation rate (sum of male and female visits) per chick differed at nests of single- and double-brooders (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.35 in both cases). When these analyses were conducted per nest visit, rather than per chick, there was also no relationship (female: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 1.19, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.30; male: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 0.49, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.50; total: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.91, controlling for brood size and individual as random factors). There was no difference in mean female provisioning rate of the first brood between successful and failed double-brooders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,11</sub> &equals; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.92; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t02">Table 2</xref>), nor for male or total nest visitation rates (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.80 in both cases). No significant difference was found when these groups were analyzed per nest rather than per chick (female: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 0.19, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.68; male: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 0.02, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.90; total: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 0.09, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.77, controlling for brood size and individual as random factors).Double-brooding females had higher local return rates (71&percnt;) than all single-brooding females (56&percnt;) and successful single-brooders (57&percnt;; <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm09"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm09.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 5.17, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02, and <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm10"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm10.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 3.07, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.08, with relative age as a covariate, and individual and year as random effects; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-f03">Figure 3</xref>). However, the local return rate of double-brooders was independent of the success of the second brood (failed double-brooders &equals; 81&percnt;, vs. successful double-brooders &equals; 67&percnt;; <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm11"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm11.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.22, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.69, with relative age as a covariate, and individual and year as random effects; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-f03">Figure 3</xref>).Total percent local return rates to the study site among all single-brooders and all double-brooders, successful single-brooders, and successful double-brooders of European Starlings in our study site in British Columbia, Canada, 2004&ndash;2014.Laying date in the subsequent year was independent of whether the female was single- or double-brooding in the previous year (all single-brooders: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,24</sub> &equals; 0.30, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.59; excluding failed single-brooders: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,16</sub> &equals; 0.43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.43), and was also independent of whether the previous year's second brood was a success or a failure (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,1</sub> &equals; 6.56, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.25). Total annual productivity of birds in the following year did not relate to whether the female was single- or double-brooding in the preceding year (hurdle model, count portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm12"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm12.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 2.00, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.16; 0/1 portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm13"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm13.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.52; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>), even with failed single-brooders excluded (hurdle model, count portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm02"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 1.19, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.28; 0/1 portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm03"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm03.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.46, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.50; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>). Because the average number of breeding seasons for a bird in our site is 1.42 &plusmn; 1.31 years, this represented lifetime reproductive success for 64&percnt; of our birds. Similarly, successful and failed double-brooders did not differ in their subsequent year's total breeding productivity (hurdle model, count portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm04"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm04.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.59, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.44; 0/1 portion, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm05"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-133-2-251-ilm05.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &lt; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.96; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>).We investigated the potential causes and consequences of double-brooding in European Starlings, for which we predicted that laying date would have little effect on the propensity to double-brood compared with individual quality due to the high degree of breeding synchrony in the population. Double-brooding effectively doubled annual fecundity in European Starlings (based on the number of chicks fledged), and, given that 25&percnt; of our birds only breed on site once, this is a powerful representation of lifetime fecundity. However, on average, only 38&percnt; of individual females were double-brooding. Furthermore, 39&percnt; of females that initiated a second clutch experienced total failure of their second brood, and thus accrued no fecundity advantage from their decision to double-brood. So, on average, only 23&percnt; of females in our study population obtained higher breeding productivity through double-brooding. As we predicted, this variation in the propensity for, and success of, double-brooding was independent of laying date, but was also independent of clutch size, egg mass, and relative female age (putative measures of individual quality). However, double-brooding females did achieve higher breeding productivity from their first broods compared with all single-brooding females. Additionally, double-brooding females had higher local return rates and similar breeding productivity in the year after double-brooding compared with single-brooding females (even when failed single-brooders were excluded), i.e. there was no evidence of a cost of double-brooding.Most studies have reported annual variation in the frequency of double-brooding, with an increase in the incidence of double-brooding in years with earlier laying dates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and DeSante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Verboven2">Verboven et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Brinkhof1">Brinkhof et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Parejo1">Parejo and Danchin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-OBrien1">O'Brien and Dawson 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Hoffmann1">Hoffmann et al. 2015</xref>). In some species this variation can be quite marked; for example, in Black Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicurus ochruros</named-content></italic>), the proportion of females initiating more than 1 clutch per season varied from 84&percnt; to 42&percnt; across 10 yr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Weggler1">Weggler 2006</xref>). In contrast, we found no annual variation in the proportion of double-brooding among 3 yr, which is likely due to the small interannual variation in laying dates in European Starlings (&plusmn;4 days; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Williams1">Williams et al. 2015</xref>). Similarly, neither the frequency of double-brooding nor the success of second broods was related to relative laying date, which is also consistent with the high level of breeding synchrony within years in European Starlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Feare1">Feare 1984</xref>), even though other life-history traits are related to laying date in this species (e.g., clutch size; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Williams1">Williams et al. 2015</xref>; and recruitment; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Smith1">Smith 2004</xref>). In other species, for which an effect of laying date on double-brooding has been reported, the range of first-egg dates is relatively large; e.g., in the well-studied Eurasian Great Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>), the range of first-egg dates within years averages 27 days (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 59 years; M. Visser personal communication), compared with only 12 days in our study population. Therefore, as we predicted, egg-laying date within the typical breeding window for first breeding attempts was not a major determinant of double-brooding in European Starlings.In our study population, females that pursued second broods fledged almost twice as many chicks as single-brooding females, consistent with other studies which have shown that multiple brooding significantly increases total reproductive output (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Holmes1">Holmes et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Poirier1">Poirior et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Weggler1">Weggler 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Carro1">Carro et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Hoffmann1">Hoffmann et al. 2015</xref>). However, our data showed that part of this increased productivity was due to a higher brood size at fledging in these female's first broods, not simply due to the additive effect of second brood productivity. One cause of this difference in first brood productivity was that single-brooding females had a total brood failure rate of nearly 46&percnt;. Renesting after first brood failure does occasionally occur in our study site. However, for &gt;157 records of single-brooders, we have only 19 records of birds relaying after failure of the first brood (12&percnt;). Only 12 of these 19 nests (~8&percnt;) were successful in fledging offspring, and none of these females attempted a second brood. This is likely due to the limited time window for breeding in our system; typically, all second brood chicks fledge by July 1. This supports the idea that either (1) these are low-quality females or (2) that date is a main driver of breeding success, at least for low-quality birds (although females that have a second brood can clearly still be successful later in the season). Almost all of the breeding failures that we have observed were due to nest abandonment and/or starvation of the chicks; nest predation is rare and in some years does not occur at all. It is likely that adults either make a decision to abandon the nest in order to invest in personal maintenance, or perhaps are depredated themselves. We suspect, but cannot confirm, that most breeding failure is caused by predation of adults away from the nest. Some adults probably choose to abandon the nest to invest in self-maintenance rather than continued reproduction. This would be consistent with failed single-brooders being potentially lower-quality individuals than successful single- or double-brooders because they are unable to maintain the investment of resources necessary for successful reproduction. However, our putative measures of individual quality (laying date, egg mass, and clutch size), relative age, and parental care (nest visitation rate) were not related to the propensity to double-brood (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and DeSante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Holmes1">Holmes et al. 1992</xref>), which suggests that individual quality was related to other components of parental quality (e.g., genetic or physiological traits associated with parental care and rearing of offspring) or, simply, that higher quality parents produce higher quality offspring, which then have better nestling or fledgling survival.Interestingly, the pattern of high total brood failure rate (46&percnt;) initially found among single-brooders reemerged in second broods, with 39&percnt; of females that initiated a second clutch failing to rear any second brood chicks. However, these double-brooding females that failed to rear their second clutch showed similarly high first brood productivity when compared with successful double-brooders. Thus, regardless of the success of the second brood, all of the double-brooding females were of equally high quality based on the success of their first broods. Instead, perhaps a date-dependent decrease in environmental quality during the second brooding window makes second broods a risky investment (for doubling reproductive effort) with a high failure rate, despite the proven ability of parents to successfully rear offspring from first broods. Consistent with this idea, even successful double-brooding females had lower brood size at fledging from their second breeding attempt compared with their first breeding attempt. There is existing evidence to suggest that the seasonal window for second broods may be more challenging due to difficult environmental conditions or lower food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Rodenhouse1">Rodenhouse and Holmes 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Silkamaki1">Silkamaki 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Nagy2">Nagy and Holmes 2005a</xref>). Regardless of the low probability of success, a double-brooding strategy clearly has a high potential payoff in doubling fecundity within the year if individuals can manage potential costs to survival and/or future fecundity.Although there is clearly additional reproductive effort involved in doubling egg production, incubation, and chick provisioning for a second brood, we were not able to identify a cost for double-brooders. Double-brooding had no negative effect on the timing of breeding or breeding productivity in the year following double-brooding (future fecundity), and double-brooding females actually had higher local return rates (survival). In other words, double-brooding females did not show the predicted tradeoff between current reproductive effort and our indices of survival and future reproduction as predicted by life-history theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Reznick1">Reznick 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Stearns1">Stearns 1992</xref>). Several other studies have also shown this lack of a tradeoff between double-brooding and various indices of survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Geupel1">Geupel and DeSante 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Morton1">Morton et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Nagy3">Nagy and Holmes 2005b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>), although double-brooding birds had lower survival in the Northern House-Martin (<italic>Delichon urbicum</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Bryant1">Bryant 1979</xref>) and Eurasian Coot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Fulica atra</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Brinkhof1">Brinkhof et al. 2002</xref>). In our population of European Starlings, regardless of the success of the first brood, single-brooders had a significantly lower return rate than double-brooders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Because we have not attached long-term tracking equipment to our birds, we do not know what proportion of individuals fail to return due to mortality vs. a search for new breeding grounds. It is possible that successful single-brooders that decide not to pursue a second brood may require additional self-maintenance to support their return the following year. Thus, these single-brooders deliberately choose not to invest in a second brood that is unlikely to pay off. On the other hand, double-brooders do increase their reproductive effort by rearing a second clutch, but may do so <italic>because</italic> they can manage the consequences of the additional effort without compromising their return rate and subsequent year's reproductive success. This ability may be due to a combination of unmeasured components of quality, such as genetic or physiological traits, or pairing with high-quality mates. So, in conclusion, a small proportion (~20&percnt;) of high-quality female European Starlings effectively doubles their potential breeding productivity through double-brooding without apparently paying any costs in the variables that we measured or experiencing simple tradeoffs in our indices of survival and future fecundity in the way that life-history theory predicts (as has been reported elsewhere; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Ardia1">Ardia 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Weladji1">Weladji et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-251-Hamel1">Hamel et al. 2009</xref>).We would like to thank the many field assistants who helped to collect data over the 10 yr of this project, with special thanks to Sophie Bourgeon, Melinda Fowler, Raime Fronstin, and Oliver Love. David J. Green provided valuable comments on the writing of and statistical analysis for this paper.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This work was funded by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Council of Canada Discovery and Accelerator Grant to T.D.W. (Grant numbers 155395-2012-RGPIN and RGPAS/429387-2012). The funders did not have any input into the content of the manuscript nor require approval before submission.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This work was conducted under license from the Simon Fraser University Animal Care Committee (permit&num; 1018B-96) and an Environment Canada banding permit (permit &num; 10646 to T.D.W.).<bold>Author contributions:</bold> T.D.W. supervised the research; A.C. collected the data; A.C. and T.D.W. wrote the paper (or substantially edited the paper); and A.C. analyzed the data.