 Geographic variation in morphometrics, molt, and migration suggests ongoing subspeciation in Pacific Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis fulva  )  Wing pointedness associated with migratory distance in common-garden and comparative studies of stonechats (  Saxicola torquata  )  Biometrics and moult of Lesser Golden Plovers   Pluvialis dominica  fulva  in Victoria  Taxonomy, distribution, and evolution of Golden Plovers (  Pluvialis dominica   and   Pluvialis fulva  )  Birds of the Soviet Union, vol. 3  Variation in the wing morphology of Western Sandpipers (  Calidris mauri  ) in relation to sex, age class, and annual cycle  The Pacific Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis fulva  ): Discovery of the species and other historical notes  Radio-tagged Pacific Golden-Plovers: The Hawaii&ndash;Alaska link, spring destinations, and breeding season survival  American Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis dominica  )  Pacific Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis fulva  )  New insight concerning transoceanic migratory pathways of Pacific Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis fulva  ): The Japan stopover and other linkages as revealed by geolocators  Tracking the migrations of Pacific Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis fulva  ) between Hawaii and Alaska: New insight on flight performance, breeding ground destinations, and nesting from birds carrying light level geolocators  Plumage-molt-age relationships in &ldquo;over-summering&rdquo; and migratory Lesser Golden-Plovers  Morphometric features of Pacific and American golden-plovers with comments on field identification  Migration by radio-tagged Pacific Golden-Plovers from Hawaii to Alaska, and their subsequent survival  Migration and bioenergetics of flight in the Pacific Golden Plover  Golden Plovers   Pluvialis apricaria   do not show sexual dimorphy in external and internal linear dimensions  Occurrence of Pacific Golden Plovers in The Netherlands: Historical perspectives from the &ldquo;wilsternetters.&rdquo;  In tundra plovers the frequency of inner flight feather replacement varies with length of long-distance flights  Ecomorphology of Wheatears (genus  Oenanthe )  The bird fauna of Niue Island, Southwest Pacific, with special notes on the White-tailed Tropic Bird and Golden Plover  Do migrant birds have more pointed wings? A comparative study  Is geographical variation in the size of Australian shorebirds consistent with hypotheses on differential migration?  Age-related variation in wing shape of migratory and sendentary blackcaps   Sylvia atricapilla    Wing length changes of the knot with age and time since moult  Real Statistics Using Excel  Breeding Pacific Golden-Plovers (  Pluvialis fulva  ) cover 140 longitudinal degrees of Arctic tundra. Having examined 557 museum skins from across this huge distributional range, we conclude that Pacific Golden-Plovers breeding in Alaska are structurally larger than those breeding in Siberia, especially in wing length. Birds from Alaska also have more pointed wings and almost always postpone the initiation of primary molt until they reach their winter quarters, whereas many Siberian birds start primary molt in the breeding areas. These differences could have been favored by the longer transoceanic flights followed by the Alaskan populations to nonbreeding destinations in the Pacific Islands. We propose that the Alaskan and Siberian breeding birds be distinguished as distinct flyway populations to be used in conservation assessments by the international conservation community.        The breeding and nonbreeding ranges of the Pacific Golden-Plover ( Figure 1 ) are enormous ( Figure 2 ). The breeding range extends from the Yamal Peninsula to western Alaska across the Arctic into the Subarctic, thus covering much of the Siberian tundra. This continuous breeding range ( Figure 2 ) is interrupted only by the Bering Strait between Alaska and Chukotka (~82 km wide), the De Long Strait separating Wrangel Island from the Siberian mainland (~140 km), and the Gulf of Ob between the Gydan and Yamal peninsulas (~50 km) ( Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ,  Lappo et al. 2012 ). The wintering range includes almost all Pacific islands, along with coastal areas in Southeast Asia, Indonesia, Australia, and New Zealand (e.g.,  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ). This &ldquo;winter&rdquo; range no longer includes northwestern Europe, where evidence for regular winter occurrences until the 1940s was assembled on the basis of oral history ( Jukema and Piersma 2002 ).  A male Pacific Golden-Plover in its breeding area (Taymyr), displaying the wings-high posture in concluding the territorial song flight. Photo credit: Bas van den Boogaard  Pacific Golden-Plover breeding area (based on  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ,  Lappo et al. 2012 ), centers of the breeding and staging or wintering regions for grouping the skins, approximate major flyways (based on  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ,  Johnson et al. 2011 ,  2012 ), Pacific wintering sites mentioned in the text, and capture sites of live birds. For each region, total numbers of adult and juvenile skins are given.  The Pacific Golden-Plovers nesting in Alaska are known to differ from their western conspecifics in several ways: (1) They make very long, nonstop oceanic flights to the Pacific isles ( Figure 2 ), whereas flights of Siberian birds are apparently transcontinental (thus allowing stops) and without extensive barriers ( Dement'ev and Gladkov 1951 ,  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson et al. 2001 ,  2011 ,  2012 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ,  Lappo et al. 2012 ); (2) they molt flight feathers in their winter quarters ( Kinsky and Yaldwyn 1981 ,  Connors 1983 ,  Johnson and Johnson 1983 ,  Barter 1988 ), whereas Siberian birds start wing molt in the breeding area ( Tulp et al. 1997 ,  2000 ,  Tulp and Schekkerman 2001 ,  Jukema et al. 2013 , P. Tomkovich personal communication); and (3) their first molt of secondaries in the second year of life is partial and all subsequent secondary molts are complete, whereas Taymyr birds molt half of their secondaries in all years ( Jukema et al. 2013 ). Here, on the basis of newly collected data from both the breeding and nonbreeding ranges, we present a new review of the morphometrics of the Pacific Golden-Plover and interpret the patterns with reference to known differences in their annual cycle. We propose that there is evidence for incipient subspeciation and define 2 distinct flyway populations.  Specimens ( n  &equals; 557) from many museums were examined: Amsterdam (11), Auckland (9), Chicago (50), Christchurch (17), Honolulu (60), Leiden (124), Melbourne (12), Moscow (195), New York (6), Sydney (40), Tring (1), and Wellington (34) (see Acknowledgments). In many cases, the skins were shipped to the Netherlands and studied in the Natuurmuseum Frysl&acirc;n, Leeuwarden. To avoid variability, all measurements were made by J.J. These were length of bill (to 0.1 mm), tarsus length (straight to 0.1 mm), wing length (mm; primaries maximally flattened and straightened), and distances (mm) between primary tips P10&ndash;P9, P10&ndash;P8, P10&ndash;P7, and P10&ndash;P6. The latter measurements were made to determine wing pointedness (e.g.,  M&ouml;nkk&ouml;nen 1995 ,  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Kaboli et al. 2007 ,  Baldwin et al. 2010 ). Molt stage for each of the 10 primaries was scored on a 5-point scale (0 &equals; unmolted old feather, 5 &equals; fully developed new feather;  Ginn and Melville 1983 ). From May (to include all arriving birds in the breeding area) until the following molt period, all primaries were considered old (score 0). We classified each bird as follows: &ldquo;primary molt not yet started&rdquo; (all primaries old); &ldquo;beginning primary molt&rdquo; (1 or a few primaries at score 1); &ldquo;proceeding primary molt&rdquo; (1 or more primaries at score 2); &ldquo;suspended primary molt&rdquo; (temporary interruption: 1 or more primaries scored at 5 and all others at 0, or a single primary scored at 4 between the rows of scores 5 and 0;  Prater et al. 1977 ); &ldquo;resumed primary molt&rdquo; (1 or a few primaries at score 1 between a series scored 5 and a series scored 0; and &ldquo;completed primary molt&rdquo; (all primaries at 5, or the final feather in a row of score 5 was scored 4).  We divided the sample skins into 15 groups (each comprising &ge;10 adults &lsqb;&gt;1 yr old&rsqb;) representative of the following geographic regions ( Figure 2 ): (1) Taymyr (including Yamal and Gydan), (2) Yakutia, (3) Chukotka (including Wrangel Island), (4) Kamchatka, (5) Alaska, (6) southern Siberia (Baikal region and farther westward), (7) southeastern Siberia (Sahkalin Island and the southeastern Siberian coastal area), (8) western Indonesia (Sumatra and farther northwestward), (9) central Indonesia (including Christmas Island and all skins from &ldquo;Indonesia&rdquo; without any further detail), (10) New Guinea (including the Moluccas Islands and northeastern Australia), (11) Hawaii, (12) Pacific Islands (Fiji and Niue), (13) Lord Howe Island, (14) southeastern Australia, and (15) New Zealand. Groups 1&ndash;5 comprise breeding regions; groups 6&ndash;15 comprise staging and wintering regions.  In addition to museum specimens, J.J. measured wing length (mm; primaries maximally flattened and straightened) and recorded sex and age (&le;1 yr old or &gt;1 yr old) in live Pacific Golden-Plovers captured in the field ( Figure 2 ): 21 nesting birds, captured in 1996 at Medusa Bay, Taymyr (73&deg;N, 81&deg;E); 294 captured in 2005 at a staging ground in northeastern Mongolia (49&deg;N, 116&deg;E; see  Wijmenga et al. 2011 ); and 34 nesting birds trapped in 2008 and 2010 on the Seward Peninsula, western Alaska (near Nome: 65&deg;N, 166&deg;W).  We compared adults (&gt;1 yr old) only with adults, juveniles (&le;1 yr old) only with juveniles, skins only with skins, and live birds only with live birds. Because previous studies did not find sexual size dimorphism among Eurasian Golden-Plovers (  P. apricaria  ;  Jukema and Piersma 1992 ) and Pacific Golden-Plovers ( Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Johnson 2004 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ), we did not treat the sexes separately in our analyses.  To compare the skins from the 15 geographic regions, averages and indices were calculated separately for adults and juveniles (see  Figure 3 ; all raw data and the frequencies, averages, and standard deviations per region are listed in the  Supplemental Material Appendix ). The measurements are bill length (B), tarsus length (T), wing length (W), an index  P  for wing pointedness (see below), an index  M  for primary molt completion (see below), and time&ndash;date (D; see below).  Averages and SD per region of bill length (B: mm), tarsus length (T: mm), wing length (W: mm), corrected wing length (C: mm &equals; breeding area), wing pointedness (P), primary molt completion (M), and dates (D: May &equals; 5, January &equals; 13, etc.) for skins of adult Pacific Golden-Plovers (&gt;1 yr old, in bold) and averages for skins of juveniles (&le;1 yr old, not in bold). For definitions, see text. Averages were calculated only when data from &ge;5 skins were available.  Index  M  on primary molt completion was obtained by adding the molt scores of the 10 primaries (minimum &equals; 0, maximum &equals; 50). Time&ndash;date (D) when the skins were collected had to reflect calendar month and whether the bird stayed an extra season in the wintering area. It was scored by the month's number for birds collected in the breeding areas (May &equals; 5, June &equals; 6, etc.), for those collected in the staging and wintering areas (August &equals; 8 to December &equals; 12, January &equals; 13, etc.), and for those that stayed there during the summer (May &equals; 17 to September &equals; 21).  For all comparisons of skins between the 5 breeding areas, and between all 15 areas that were distinguished, we first applied single-factor analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by Games-Howell tests between separate groups, because sample sizes differed considerably ( Zaiontz 2014 ). We used  t -tests to compare wing lengths of live birds from Taymyr, Mongolia, and Alaska.  The geographic distribution ( Figure 3 ) of bill lengths in museum specimens of adults was nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  4,118  &equals; 5.48,  P  &lt; 0.001). Bills from Taymyr and Yakutia birds were significantly shorter than bills from Chukotka and Kamchatka birds (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Bills of Alaskan breeding birds did not differ significantly from those of any other area. Also, tarsus-length distribution in skins of adults was nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  4,115  &equals; 4.73,  P  &equals; 0.001), tarsus lengths from Taymyr and Yakutia being significantly smaller than those from Alaska (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Tarsus lengths from Chukotka and Kamchatka did not differ significantly from the tarsi in other areas. Wing-length distribution in skins of adults was highly nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  4,117  &equals; 23.32,  P  &lt; 0.001), wings from Taymyr, Yakutia, Chukotka, and Kamchatka being significantly shorter than those from Alaska (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Overall, 81&percnt; of the wings from Siberia (skins) were &lt;170 mm, whereas 87&percnt; of those from Alaska were &ge;170 mm.   Table 1  gives the averages of the 5 wing-pointedness measures. The distributions of almost all were nonrandom (single-factor ANOVAs). Only differences in index  P  were compared by subsequent Games-Howell tests ( P  &lt; 0.05). Wings from Alaska were significantly more pointed than those from Taymyr. None of the other pairwise comparisons appeared to be significant. Distribution of primary molt scores in skins of adults was nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  4,119  &equals; 2.56,  P  &equals; 0.042), but none of the pairwise comparisons showed significant differences (Games-Howell tests, all  P  &gt; 0.05). However, Siberian birds (all 4 areas combined) showed more advanced primary molt than the birds from Alaska ( t -test,  t  &equals; 2.01, df &equals; 122,  P  &equals; 0.046).  Wing-pointedness measures (and index  P ; see text) taken from skins of adult Pacific Golden-Plovers from the different breeding regions.  The data on wing length of birds captured alive on western and eastern breeding grounds were in agreement with the skin measurements. Average wing length in live adults from Taymyr was 168.8 mm (SD &equals; 4.7,  n  &equals; 21); from Alaska, 175.4 mm (SD &equals; 4.4,  n  &equals; 34); and from Mongolia, 169.7 mm (SD &equals; 4.1,  n  &equals; 272). The difference between Taymyr and Alaska was highly significant ( t -test,  t  &equals; 4.96, df &equals; 53,  P  &lt; 0.001). The difference between Mongolia and Alaska was also highly significant ( t -test,  t  &equals; 5.82, df &equals; 304,  P  &lt; 0.001), but that between Mongolia and Taymyr was not ( t -test,  t  &equals; 0.89, df &equals; 291,  P  &equals; 0.38). Wings from Mongolia were expected to become ~0.5&percnt; shorter by wear upon arrival in the breeding area; with this correction, their wing lengths are identical to those from Taymyr but diverge even more from those of Alaska birds. Overall, 76&percnt; of the wings from Taymyr (live birds) were &lt;173 mm, whereas 76&percnt; of those from Alaska were &ge;173 mm; 83&percnt; of the wings from Mongolia were &lt;173 mm (after correction).  Distribution of bill length in museum specimens of adults was nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,247  &equals; 7.33,  P  &lt; 0.001); the longest bills were from Hawaii (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Tarsus-length distribution in skins of adults was nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,209  &equals; 5.67,  P  &lt; 0.001). Tarsus lengths were largest from the Pacific Islands and shortest from southern Siberia ( Table 2 ; Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Corrected wing-length distribution in skins of adults was highly nonrandom (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,235  &equals; 15.71,  P  &lt; 0.001). Wing lengths from Hawaii, Pacific Islands, Lord Howe Island, and New Zealand were significantly larger than those from other areas; wing lengths from southern and southeastern Siberia and western and central Indonesia were significantly smaller than those from other areas (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05;  Table 3 ).  Results of Games-Howell tests ( P  &lt; 0.05) between wintering and staging areas on tarsus-length distribution in adult Pacific Golden-Plovers (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,209  &equals; 5.67,  P  &lt; 0.001). Abbreviations: SS &equals; southern Siberia, SES &equals; southeastern Siberia, WI &equals; western Indonesia, CI &equals; central Indonesia, NG &equals; New Guinea, HA &equals; Hawaii, PI &equals; Pacific Islands, LH &equals; Lord Howe Island, SA &equals; southeastern Australia, and NZ &equals; New Zealand. Symbols: &ast; same area; &plus; value for column region significantly larger than for row region; &minus; value for column region significantly smaller than for row region.  Results of Games-Howell tests ( P  &lt; 0.05) between wintering and staging areas on corrected wing-length distribution in adult Pacific Golden-Plovers (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,235  &equals; 15.71,  P  &lt; 0.001). For abbreviations and symbols, see  Table 2 .  Distributions of wing-pointedness measures in skins of adults were, in most cases, nonrandom (single-factor ANOVAs, P10&ndash;P9:  F  8,155  &equals; 1.63,  P  &equals; 0.12; P10&ndash;P8:  F  8,155  &equals; 3.36,  P  &equals; 0.001; P10&ndash;P7:  F  8,154  &equals; 5.73,  P  &lt; 0.001; P10&ndash;P6:  F  8,151  &equals; 10.24,  P  &lt; 0.001; index  P :  F  8,151  &equals; 2.99,  P  &equals; 0.004). Index  P  was largest in birds from New Zealand and southeastern Australia, and smallest in birds from southeastern Siberia and New Guinea, but the differences between the wintering areas were not significant in pairwise comparisons (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). Distributions of primary molt scores in adults were highly dissimilar (single-factor ANOVA,  F  9,256  &equals; 13.03,  P  &lt; 0.001). Birds from southeastern Siberia had significantly lower scores than those from several other areas, whereas birds from New Zealand, southeastern Australia, Lord Howe Island, and Hawaii had significantly higher scores (Games-Howell tests,  P  &lt; 0.05). The same trends were found in the proportions of adult birds that had not yet started, had begun, were proceeding with, had suspended, had resumed, or had completed primary molt.  We found strong heterogeneity across the breeding and wintering ranges of Pacific Golden-Plovers, as have other studies on their geographic morphological variation ( Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Johnson and Johnson 2004 ). The question we would like to pose here is whether the trends from west to east are continuous or discontinuous and, if the latter, where any such discontinuity is geographically situated. Because all our measurements were made by only one experienced observer, the present study is better suited to solve these questions than earlier studies that were based on measurements by many observers and whose results thus included an extra source of variation.  Uncorrected wing length in skins from the Pacific Islands (Fiji and Niue) was in the same range as that in skins from Siberia and Indonesia&mdash;and not, as expected on the basis of known migration patterns ( Johnson et al. 2012 ), the same as in skins from Alaska. This anomaly is attributable to the fact that all the skins from Fiji and Niue were collected during a small number of expeditions between June and September in 1971&ndash;1974 ( Kinsky and Yaldwyn 1981 ); no skins from the winter months were available. The sample included mostly young &ldquo;over-summering&rdquo; individuals (1&ndash;2 yr old,  n  &equals; 26) with short wings (x̄ &equals; 165.7 mm; corrected: 174.6 mm) and a few, probably older, individuals ( n  &equals; 5) with longer wings (x̄ &equals; 173.6 mm; corrected: 175.3 mm) that had just returned from their breeding area. Apparently, as noted by  Johnson and Johnson (1983) , Pacific Golden-Plovers that stay on the equatorial Pacific Islands during the summer show excessive primary wear, probably due to heavy sun radiation.  Pacific Golden-Plovers that were measured by  Johnston and McFarlane (1967)  at Wake Island (see  Figure 2 ) also had shorter wings (wing chord &equals; 163 mm) than those from Alaska. Wing chord measurements are shorter (~5 mm) than those on flattened wings such as we used. However, this difference is too small for them even to approach our Alaskan data (x̄ &equals; 175.4 mm in live birds). In addition, the birds from Wake Island were all captured in autumn, winter, or early spring. Thus, over-summering could not be the reason in this case. Most probably, Wake Island is a wintering area for Siberian populations. A closer inspection of the data from New Guinea also confirms conformity with the Siberian populations. Australia seems to be visited by Pacific Golden-Plovers both from Siberia (in northwestern Australia) and from Alaska (in southeastern Australia).  Nebel et al. (2013)  reported that wing lengths in the former group (x̄ &equals; 168.7 mm,  n  &equals; 12) were smaller than those in the latter (x̄ &equals; 173.5 mm,  n  &equals; 36). C. Minton, H. Sitters, and M. Remisiewicz (personal communication), using a larger sample, confirmed that wing lengths of Pacific Golden-Plovers captured in northwestern Australia (x̄ &equals; 165.3 mm,  n  &equals; 21) were consistent with the Siberian populations, whereas those from southeastern Australia (x̄ &equals; 172.0 mm,  P  &equals; 0.024,  n  &equals; 151) were consistent with the populations from Alaska. The differences in both cases were significant ( t -test,  t  &equals; 2.42, df &equals; 23,  P  &equals; 0.024). In addition, primary molt schedules (C. Minton et al. personal communication) in individuals captured in northwestern Australia ( n  &equals; 16) appeared to run ahead of those captured in southeastern Australia ( n  &equals; 153), in line with the differences between other wintering Pacific Golden-Plovers from Siberia and Alaska.  The long wings that were distinctive for the breeding populations from Alaska were found in various wintering areas, including Hawaii, Pacific Islands (after correction), southeastern Australia (including Lord Howe Island), and New Zealand. This is consistent with recent findings that show these birds to belong to the same populations. By fitting Pacific Golden-Plovers with VHF transmitters and geolocators ( Johnson et al. 1997 ,  2001 ,  2011 ,  2012 ), it has been established that breeding birds from Alaska winter on Hawaii and other Pacific islands. Birds wintering on Hawaii could be traced as early-breeding birds in southern Alaska, whereas those wintering on most other Pacific islands were later-breeding birds in northwestern Alaska (O. W. Johnson personal communication). On the basis of wing-length measurements in live Pacific Golden-Plovers captured in Australia ( Barter 1988 ), the connection between Alaska and southeastern Australia could be made. Geolocator studies ( Johnson et al. 2012 ) confirmed that at least some birds from northwestern Alaska winter in Australia (Fraser Island; see  Figure 2 ). Similar connectivity with New Zealand seems likely but has not been demonstrated. Geolocator studies ( Johnson et al. 2012 ) have clearly shown that breeding Pacific Golden-Plovers from northern Alaska winter on American Samoa, Fiji, Gilbert Islands, and Marshall Islands (see  Figure 2 ). These studies also showed that wintering Pacific Golden-Plovers on American Samoa breed in northern Alaska. By contrast, wintering Pacific Golden-Plovers from Saipan (Mariana Islands; see  Figure 2 ) probably breed mainly in eastern Siberia ( Johnson et al. 2012 ), as do those on Wake Island (see above). Three individuals from Kwajalein (Marshall Islands) have even been detected flying to eastern Chukotka, and 6 others went to northern Alaska (O. W. Johnson personal communication).  Thus, our data on wing length, combined with data from other studies, strongly suggest that Pacific Golden-Plovers from Alaska have their wintering areas in Hawaii, most of the Pacific Islands, eastern Australia, and New Zealand. Some islands in the western Pacific (New Guinea, Mariana Islands, and Wake Island), however, are visited by birds from Siberia during the winter. As had been assumed, western and central Indonesia and central and eastern Asia accommodate Siberian birds too.  On the basis of the molt patterns of the secondary flight feathers,  Jukema et al. (2013)  concluded that Pacific Golden-Plovers from Alaska differ fundamentally from those that were studied on Taymyr. From the age of 2 yr, birds from Alaska molt all their secondaries every year, whereas birds from Taymyr molt only half of them. In addition, almost all birds from Alaska start their large flight-feather molt in the wintering area ( Kinsky and Yaldwyn 1981 ,  Connors 1983 ,  Johnson and Johnson 1983 ,  Barter 1988 ,  Johnson et al. 2011 ,  2012 ), whereas many individuals from Siberia (best documented for Taymyr) start the large flight-feather molt in the breeding area ( Tulp et al. 1997 ,  2000 ,  Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ,  Tulp and Schekkerman 2001 , P. Tomkovich personal communication). It has been proposed that this is functionally associated with their migration patterns: Birds from Alaska make very long, nonstop flights to their wintering areas on Hawaii and the Pacific Islands ( Johnson et al. 2001 ,  2011 ,  2012 ,  Johnson and Connors 2010a ,  2010b ,  Jukema et al. 2013 ), whereas birds from Siberia are supposed to migrate more slowly to the wintering areas in southeastern Asia. The present study confirms that many Siberian Pacific Golden-Plovers start primary molt in their breeding areas, whereas those from Alaska rarely do so, although the latter tend to breed earlier (see below).  Our data on skins (and supported by the comparisons with live birds) show that the birds from Alaska and from Siberia are even more distinct. Despite their geographically widespread origin, the group of Siberian birds is relatively homogeneous. Birds from Alaska have longer and (to a lesser extent) more pointed wings, and longer legs. In various species of birds, differences in length and pointedness of wings have also been associated with migration pattern ( P&eacute;rez-Tris and Teller&iacute;a 2001 ,  Fern&aacute;ndez and Lank 2007 ,  Kaboli et al. 2007 ,  Jukema et al. 2013 ), long and pointed wings being most common among species or populations making the longest flights.  We thus propose that there are good reasons to distinguish the Alaskan breeding population from the Siberian population, and we suggest that the differences between these 2 types are maintained by reproductive isolation. The Bering Strait itself (&ge;82 km open water) cannot act as an effective barrier between 2 types that are capable of making long flights. However, climatic differences between the 2 sides of the Bering Strait enable Pacific Golden-Plovers from Alaska to start their breeding cycle 3&ndash;4 wk earlier than those from northeastern Siberia ( Byrkjedal and Thompson 1998 ). Because of this, synchronization of breeding might be difficult between members of the 2 types.  As in an earlier comparison between the different tundra plover species ( Jukema et al. 2013 ), wing length, molt patterns, and probably wing pointedness may be considered adaptations to long, nonstop flights during migration. Pacific Golden-Plovers from the Alaskan populations (probably including birds from eastern Chukotka) have to make such flights, possess long and pointed wings, and have a complete molt of the flight feathers, whereas most of those from Siberia do not have to make such exhausting flights, possess shorter wings, and have a less complete flight feather molt.  The differences between Alaskan and Siberian Pacific Golden-Plovers reflect a clear discontinuity, probably maintained by reproductive isolation. We therefore propose that the international conservation community, in conservation assessments (e.g.,  Delany and Scott 2006 ), treat the Alaskan and Siberian breeding birds as distinct flyway populations. We also propose distinguishing them as subspecies that differ in wing measurements. The type specimen for   Pluvialis fulva   (collected on Tahiti in 1773 by J. R. Forster during Captain Cook's second voyage, described by J. F. Gmelin) has been lost ( Johnson 1993 ), so we cannot compare its wing measurements with those of the skins we studied. However, Tahiti should be regarded as a wintering site for Alaskan Pacific Golden-Plovers only. Therefore, the Alaskan populations are compatible with the holotype (the subspecies name should be   Pluvialis fulva  fulva ), and the Siberian populations represent a new subspecies. We suggest the name   Pluvialis fulva  johnsoni  in honor of two long-term students of the species, Oscar W. and Patricia Johnson.  We are grateful to the Natuurmuseum Frysl&acirc;n, Leeuwarden, The Netherlands, for offering work space, help, storage, and mediation. In particular, support by curator P. Koomen was crucial in facilitating the lending of skins from the Natural History Museum, Tring, UK; Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, IL, USA; American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY, USA; Museum of Natural History, Brigham Young University&ndash;Hawaii, Laie, HI, USA; Australian Museum, Sydney, Australia; and Museum Victoria, Melbourne, Australia. For permission to examine skins, we thank conservators H. van Grouw and R. Dekker (Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden, The Netherlands; including the Amsterdam collection), P. Tomkovich (Zoological Museum, Moscow, Russia), P. Schofield (Canterbury Museum, Christchurch, New Zealand), S. Bartle and G. Stone (Papa Museum, Wellington, New Zealand), and B. Gill and C. Jones (Auckland Museum, Auckland, New Zealand). J. Reneerkens gave support in Moscow, and Jan Jukema gave support in New Zealand. Fieldwork in Taymyr was done together with I. Tulp and L. Bruinzeel. In Mongolia, J. Reneerkens and J. Wijmenga collaborated, Professor S. Gombobaatar (National University of Mongolia, Ulaanbaatar) helped organize the expedition, Professor M. Tsogbadrakk (Dean of the Faculty of Biology) advised, and S. Tsereadmid and B. Gantulga assisted in the field. Professor O. W. Johnson (Montana State University, Bozeman, MT, USA) invited J.J. for the fieldwork in Alaska that was done in cooperation with P. Johnson and P. and N. Brusseau. C. Minton, H. Sitters, and M. Remisiewicz provided unpublished data collected by the Australasian Wader Studies Group and Victorian Wader Study Group on Pacific Golden-Plovers wintering in Australia. We are very grateful to all these people. We also thank R. Gill, O. W. Johnson, P. Tomkovich, and anonymous reviewers for their critical reading, valuable suggestions, and constructive comments on the manuscript. P. Tomkovich kindly supplied the Russian abstract.   Ethics statement:  Live birds were captured, measured, and banded under permits from the Russian Bird Ringing Center and the director (V. Badukin) of the Great Arctic Reserve (Taymyr); from the Mongolian Government and the National University of Mongolia; and from the U.S. Geological Survey Bird Banding Laboratory (Alaska).   Supplemental Material Appendix . All raw data and the frequencies, averages, and standard deviations per region from our comparisons of Pacific Golden-Plover skins from the 15 geographic regions in the study. Averages and indices were calculated separately for adults (Ad) and juveniles (Juv). Available at doi: 10.1642/AUK-14-303.1.s1  