Compensatory growth in nestling Zebra Finches impacts body composition but not adaptive immune functionIncreased susceptibility to oxidative damage as a cost of accelerated somatic growth in Zebra FinchesOntogeny of constitutive immunity: Maternal vs. endogenous influencesEffect of the genetic selection of turkeys for increased body weight and egg production on immune and physiological responsesNestling diet, secondary sexual traits and fitness in the Zebra FinchCatch-up growth strategies differ between body structures: Interactions between age and structure-specific growth in wild nestling Alpine SwiftsEvidence for a major gene for rapid postweaning growth in miceImmunocompetence and its costs during development: An experimental study in Blue Tit nestlingsEffect of food shortage on the physiology and competitive abilities of Sand Martin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) nestlingsEffect of refeeding on growth, development, and behavior of undernourished Bank Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>) nestlingsRelationship between avian growth rate and immune response depends on food availabilityLow plasticity in digestive physiology constrains feeding ecology in diet specialist, Zebra Finch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>)Effect of brood size manipulation on offspring physiology: An experiment with passerine birdsSkeletal-muscle growth, enzyme-activities, and the development of thermogenesis&mdash;A comparison between altricial and precocial birdsEarly nutrition and phenotypic development: &ldquo;Catch-up&rdquo; growth leads to elevated metabolic rate in adulthoodCosts of compensation: Effect of early life conditions and reproduction on flight performance in Zebra FinchesEnergy allocation and postnatal growth in captive Elegant Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna elegans</named-content></italic>) chicks: Responses to high- versus low-energy dietsLong-term effects of brood size manipulation on morphological development and sex-specific mortality of offspringBreeding biology of White-fronted Bee-eaters at Nakuru: The influence of helpers on breeder fitnessCompensatory growth impairs adult cognitive performanceParental care in wild and captive Zebra Finches: Measuring food delivery to quantify parental effortTransgenerational priming of immunity: Maternal exposure to a bacterial antigen enhances offspring humoral immunityPhysiological mechanisms mediating costs of immune responses: What can we learn from studies of birds?Quantitative analysis of compensatory and catch-up growth in diverse taxaDevelopmental plasticity in a passerine bird: An experiment with Collared Flycatchers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>Stable isotopes reveal strategic allocation of resources during juvenile development in a cryptic and threatened seabird, the Marbled Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus marmoratus</named-content></italic>)Growth and development of House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>) in response to chronic food restriction throughout the nestling periodOntogeny of adaptive antibody response to a model antigen in captive altricial Zebra FinchesOntogenetic patterns of constitutive immune parameters in altricial House SparrowsAre maternal antibodies really that important? Patterns in the immunologic development of altricial passerine House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>)Effect of short-term feed restriction, realimentation and overfeeding on growth of Song Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus philomelos</named-content></italic>) nestlingsCompensatory growth affects exploratory behaviour in Zebra Finches, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>The use of avian epiphyseal chondrocytes for in vitro studies of skeletal metabolismLinking immune defenses and life history at the levels of the individual and the speciesEffect of ephemeral food restriction on growth of House SparrowsThe role of muscle development in the transition to endothermy in nestling Bank Swallows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>Increase in the constitutive innate humoral immune system in Leach's Storm-Petrel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Oceanodroma leucorhoa</named-content></italic>) chicks is negatively correlated with growth rateCompensation for a bad start: Grow now, pay later?Morphological plasticity reduces the effect of poor developmental conditions on fledging age in Mourning DovesParent-offspring interactions in Zebra FinchesEcological immunology: Life history trade-offs and immune defense in birdsMaternal antibodies in a wild altricial bird: Effects on offspring immunity, growth and survivalA flexible growth function for empirical useLife-history consequences of growth rate depression: An experimental study on Carrion Crows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corone</named-content> corone L</italic>.)Relative growth, body constituents, and energy content of nestling Barn Swallows and Red-winged BlackbirdsPatterns of growth in birdsPatterns of growth in birds. V. A comparative study of development in the Starling, Common Tern, and Japanese QuailWater content, thermogenesis, and growth rate of skeletal muscles in the European StarlingInverse relationship between functional maturity and exponential growth rate of avian skeletal muscle: A constraint on evolutionary responseDevelopmental plasticityEffects of early nutrition on growth rate and adult size in Song Sparrows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melospiza melodia</named-content></italic>Growth rate and function of skeletal muscles in Japanese Quail selected for four-week body massVariability of embryo development rate, fry growth, and disease susceptibility in hatchery stocks of chum salmonTrade-off between immunocompetence and growth in magpies: An experimental studyPatterns of development: The altricial&ndash;precocial spectrumResource allocation in fledglings of the Rhinoceros Auklet under different feeding conditions: An experiment manipulating meal size and frequencyTrade-off between growth and immune function: A meta-analysis of selection experimentsCompensatory strategies have evolved in birds to minimize the effects of poor rearing conditions on future survival and fitness. Undernourished nestlings may accelerate growth and/or development relative to age, termed compensatory growth, to achieve normal asymptotic size at the same time as well-fed chicks. While compensatory growth allows birds to fledge at a suitable size and time, it may have persistent detrimental effects on the development of complex body systems. Our study examined compensatory growth following short-term food restriction of caged groups of Zebra Finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>; adult breeding pair and their brood) during the nestling period, and tested for postrestriction effects on tissue maturity (indexed by body tissue water content) and adaptive immune function. Food restriction reduced nestling body mass, tarsus, and culmen growth. Rapid compensatory growth in body mass, but not in tarsus and culmen lengths, was observed upon return to ad libitum feeding of the food-restricted group. Nestlings that were raised in food-restricted treatment cages showed no significant difference in adaptive antibody response to a model antigen compared with those raised in control cages with ad libitum feeding. Reductions in tissue maturity were observed in nestlings that experienced food restriction, indicating a decoupling of chronological age and physiological age. These data provide evidence of capacity for rapid, compensatory body mass growth in nestling Zebra Finches, and suggest that the energetic costs of body growth and development are relatively larger than the costs of development of the humoral immune system.Las estrategias de compensaci&oacute;n de las aves han evolucionado para minimizar los efectos de las malas condiciones de cr&iacute;a en la supervivencia futura y en la adecuaci&oacute;n biol&oacute;gica. Los pichones pueden acelerar el crecimiento y/o el desarrollo relativo a la edad, llamado crecimiento compensatorio, para alcanzar un tama&ntilde;o asint&oacute;tico normal al mismo tiempo que las aves bien alimentadas. Mientras que el crecimiento compensatorio permite a las aves dejar el nido con un tama&ntilde;o y en un tiempo adecuados, puede tener efectos persistentes negativos en el desarrollo de los sistemas corporales complejos. Este estudio examina el crecimiento compensatorio luego de breves restricciones de alimento a grupos enjaulaos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic> (parejas reproductivas de adultos y sus nidadas) durante el per&iacute;odo de nidificaci&oacute;n, y eval&uacute;a los efectos posteriores a la restricci&oacute;n en la madurez del tejido (indexado por el contenido de agua del tejido corporal) y en la funci&oacute;n inmunol&oacute;gica adaptativa. Las restricciones de alimento redujeron la masa corporal de los pichones y el crecimiento del tarso y del culmen. Se observ&oacute; un crecimiento compensatorio r&aacute;pido en la masa corporal, pero no en el largo del tarso y del culmen, como resultado de la alimentaci&oacute;n <italic>ad libitum</italic> del grupo enjaulado. Los pichones criados en las jaulas con tratamientos de restricci&oacute;n de alimentos no mostraron diferencias significativas en la respuesta adaptativa de anticuerpos a un ant&iacute;geno modelo, comparados con aquellos criados en jaulas control con alimentaci&oacute;n <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Se observaron reducciones en la madurez de los tejidos en pichones que tuvieron un tratamiento con restricci&oacute;n de alimentos, indicando un desacople de la edad cronol&oacute;gica y la edad fisiol&oacute;gica. Estos datos brindan evidencia de una capacidad de crecimiento y compensaci&oacute;n de masa corporal r&aacute;pida en los pichones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. guttata</named-content></italic> y sugiere que los costos energ&eacute;ticos del crecimiento corporal y del desarrollo son relativamente mayores que los costos de desarrollo del sistema inmunol&oacute;gico humoral.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> anticuerpos, hemocianina, madurez del tejido, plasticidad de desarrollo, recuperaci&oacute;n del crecimiento, restricciones de alimento, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>Periods of food restriction can be a common occurrence for growing altricial birds, which hatch in a relatively undeveloped state and rely on parental delivery of food during the nestling period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Starck1">Starck and Ricklefs 1998</xref>). Compensatory strategies have evolved to minimize the effects of poor rearing conditions on future survival and fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Schew1">Schew and Ricklefs 1998</xref>). Birds experiencing slowed growth and/or development resulting from resource limitation may extend the growth and developmental periods to achieve asymptotic size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Schew1">Schew and Ricklefs 1998</xref>). Alternatively, once food becomes freely available, birds may accelerate growth and/or development relative to age, termed compensatory growth, to achieve normal asymptotic size at the same time as well-fed birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Schew1">Schew and Ricklefs 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hector1">Hector and Nakagawa 2012</xref>).While compensatory growth allows birds to fledge at a suitable size and time, it may have persistent detrimental effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Monaghan 2001</xref>). Early resource limitation during the nestling period of Zebra Finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>) was associated with reduced postfledging survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-DeKogel1">DeKogel 1997</xref>) and reduced lifespan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Birkhead1">Birkhead et al. 1999</xref>), despite birds attaining similar sizes to well-fed controls as adults. Zebra Finch females that demonstrated rapid growth following a switch from a low-quality to a high-quality rearing diet as nestlings later demonstrated decreased flight performance as reproductive adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo2">Criscuolo et al. 2011</xref>). Reduced flight performance may reflect reduced muscle tissue differentiation resulting from catch-up growth during the nestling phase, as has been observed in Japanese Quail (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Coturnix japonica</named-content></italic>) that were artificially selected for rapid growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Shea1">Shea et al. 1995</xref>). In Zebra Finches, compensatory growth has been shown to result in reduced cognitive function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Fisher1">Fisher et al. 2006</xref>), increased susceptibility to oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>), and elevated adult resting metabolic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo1">Criscuolo et al. 2008</xref>). These phenotypic effects may be manifestations of oxidative stress or altered development of complex tissue and organ systems due to accelerated body growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo1">Criscuolo et al. 2008</xref>).Compensatory growth may alter another complex system, the immune system, and tradeoffs may occur if resources are allocated to rapid growth at the expense of immune system development following food restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Norris1">Norris and Evans 2000</xref>). Artificial selection for rapid growth has been linked to decreased immune function and increased pathogen susceptibility in a variety of taxa, including mice, salmon, turkeys, and chickens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bradford1">Bradford and Famula 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Smoker1">Smoker 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bayyari1">Bayyari et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-vanderMost1">van der Most et al. 2011</xref>). However, the effects of early food restriction and compensatory growth on adaptive immune function in Zebra Finches and other nondomesticated passerines has not been extensively studied. Development of adaptive humoral components in birds is purportedly costly, as it requires generation and proliferation of B-cell lineages with diverse, functional antibody specificities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Lee1">Lee 2006</xref>). Because altricial birds develop capacity for adaptive antibody response during the early weeks after hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Grindstaff1">Grindstaff et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Pihlaja1">Pihlaja et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-King1">King et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack2">Killpack and Karasov 2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack3">Killpack et al. 2013</xref>), food restriction and compensatory growth of nestlings may reduce the ability to mount diverse functional antibody responses later in life.We examined compensatory growth and tested for its effects on body composition and adaptive immune function development in captive, altricial Zebra Finches. Previous studies of compensatory growth in Zebra Finches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo1">Criscuolo et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo2">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Fisher1">Fisher et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Krause1">Krause and Naguib 2011</xref>) examined the effects of inadequate feeding conditions (e.g., enlarged brood sizes, low-quality diets) lasting the majority or entirety of the nestling period, and measured subsequent growth responses over a 15-day or longer refeeding period postfledging. Because Zebra Finches have determinate growth, and rapidly reach adult size during the first two weeks of the 21-day nestling period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Brzek4">Brz&eogon;k et al. 2010</xref>), we examined the capacity for rapid compensatory growth following an ecologically relevant food-restriction period during this time (6&ndash;9 days posthatch). We then used two criteria to evaluate compensatory growth upon return to ad libitum feeding of the experimental group: accelerated growth rate in the previously food-restricted nestlings compared with controls in the first 72 hr of refeeding (9&ndash;12 days posthatch), and whether food-restricted nestlings reached the same asymptotic size at the same time as controls. We chose two criteria because there is no uniform or consensus protocol in the literature for demonstrating compensatory growth (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Lepczyk1">Lepczyk and Karasov 2000</xref>), and because both of these criteria corresponded well operationally to the concept. Based on studies of animals artificially selected for rapid growth, we predicted that tissue maturation and adaptive antibody response would be reduced in nestlings demonstrating compensatory growth. This is the first study of a rapidly growing altricial bird to test both for compensatory growth entirely during the nestling period and for an associated effect on immunity when nestlings are still developing adult-level capacity for adaptive antibody production.Zebra Finches in a breeding colony at the University of Wisconsin&ndash;Madison, Wisconsin, USA, were maintained under standardized conditions of 14 hr:10 hr light:dark photoperiod (lights on at 0600 hr), 21&ndash;24&deg;C temperature, and 40&ndash;50&percnt; relative humidity. Breeding pairs of adult Zebra Finches were placed in individual breeding cages and provided with nesting material, a nest box, cuttlefish bone (calcium source), grit, and water ad libitum. Breeding pairs were also provided ad libitum with seed mix (by mass, 70&percnt; commercial seeds and 30&percnt; food supplement; Mazuri Small Bird Breeder, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.mazuri.com" xlink:type="simple">www.mazuri.com</ext-link>). Pairs were additionally provided with enrichment foods of green vegetables and an egg-food mixture (hard-boiled eggs with shells, dried egg food &lsqb;Volkman Featherglow; Volkman Seed Company, Ceres, CA&rsqb;, and liquid vitamin and mineral supplements &lsqb;Vetafarm Products, Australia&rsqb;) three times per week. Upon hatching of the first chick, enrichment feeding ceased. There was no food restriction during the egg-laying period.In Zebra Finches, nestlings hatch asynchronously, and are fed by regurgitation of food by both male and female parent birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Muller1">Muller and Smith 1978</xref>). We imposed food restriction by manipulating the quantity of seed mix available to adult pairs to feed to their broods. This method allowed for resource allocation during restriction and realimentation to occur in the ecologically relevant context of parental feeding behavior. Broods were culled to have a maximum of three nestlings, although some pairs successfully hatched only one or two nestlings. Limiting brood size to three nestlings increases the probability that all nestlings in a brood are evenly fed each feeding bout, and reduces nestling mortality not associated with feeding treatment (deKogel 1997, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Gilby1">Gilby et al. 2011</xref>). There was no significant difference in brood size between control (2.54 &plusmn; 0.2 nestlings) and food-restricted cage groups (2.17 &plusmn; 0.2 nestlings; <italic>t</italic><sub>22</sub> &equals; 1.34, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.19).Cage groups were randomly assigned to either control or food-restricted experimental treatment upon hatching of the first chick. Control groups were fed ad libitum for the duration of the experiment (ad libitum feeding: experiment day &minus;6 to 16). Because Zebra Finches hatch asynchronously, the timing of food restriction in the experimental treatment groups was determined using the average age of nestlings in each experimental brood. Experimental treatment groups were fed seed mix ad libitum from hatch until an average brood age of 6 days posthatch (ad libitum feeding: experiment day &minus;6 to 0). Food restriction in experimental treatment groups began when the average brood age was 6 days posthatch. At this time, experimental treatment groups were restricted to 70&percnt; of ad libitum seed mix for a 72 hr duration (food restriction: experiment day 0 to 3). The imposed food restriction level of 70&percnt; of ad libitum quantity was calculated based on the percentage of seed mix that was edible food (i.e. not seed hulls) and the average daily food consumption in the three days prior to experiment day 0. Following the 72 hr restriction, experimental treatment groups were returned to ad libitum feeding until the end of the experiment (ad libitum feeding: experiment day 3 to 16).There was no significant difference in average nestling age at experiment day 0 between control (5.9 &plusmn; 0.1 days) and food-restricted (6.0 &plusmn; 0.1 days) broods (<italic>t</italic><sub>57</sub> &equals; 1.34, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.8). If adult pairs had multiple broods, experimental treatment assignments were alternated. The control treatment was applied to a total of 33 nestlings in 13 broods from 9 parental pairs, and the food-restriction treatment was applied to a total of 26 nestlings in 12 broods from 9 parental pairs.Cage groups were visited every day between 1400 and 1600 hr CST. Although we did not directly quantify parental feeding effort, we quantified the daily food intake of the cage groups and the body measures of nestlings and adults to track allocation of food resources. Body mass of nestlings and adults (&plusmn;0.01 g) and tarsus and culmen lengths of nestlings (&plusmn;0.10 mm using digital calipers) were measured during daily visits from experiment day &minus;6 to 16. After these body measurements had been taken, all seeds were collected from each cage, fecal matter was removed, and daily food consumption for the cage was calculated (seed mass provided the previous day minus orts, i.e. remaining seed mass).For a subset of nestlings, we tested the effect of food restriction on immune function after refeeding (control: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 17, food-restricted: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 13). Antibody production, a component of adaptive immunity, was induced by modifying a previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack2">Killpack and Karasov 2012b</xref>). Briefly, on experiment day 13 (average brood age: 19 days posthatch), nestlings were injected intramuscularly in the pectoralis muscle with a 50 &mu;l primary injection of 25 &mu;l of keyhole limpet hemocyanin (KLH) antigen (Calbiochem, San Diego, California, USA) diluted in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) at a dose of 1.0 &mu;g antigen per g body mass emulsified with 25 &mu;l Titermax adjuvant (Titermax USA, Norcross, Georgia, USA). A blood sample was taken 7 days after primary injection (experiment day 20; average brood age: 26 days posthatch) by puncturing the brachial vein with a 28-gauge needle and collecting the blood into heparinized microcapillary tubes. Following collection of the primary blood sample, nestlings were boosted with the same dose of KLH emulsified with Titermax adjuvant, and a postboost blood sample was taken 7 days later (experiment day 27; average brood age: 33 days posthatch). Blood samples were centrifuged and plasma was stored at &minus;80&deg;C until enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) analysis of KLH-specific antibodies was performed. After the postboost blood sample was taken, all nestlings were euthanized with CO<sub>2</sub> and carcasses were frozen for later use. All experimental procedures were designed to minimize sample size and distress of the birds (see Ethics statement in the Acknowledgments).The intestines of all nestling carcasses were removed for use in a separate study. The wet carcass mass (without intestines) was measured and carcasses were individually wrapped in preweighed, labeled filter paper. Carcass packets were dried to constant mass in a 65&deg;C drying oven, dry masses were recorded, and water mass (g wet tissue &minus; g dry tissue) was calculated. The skulls were then cracked to allow ether to penetrate the skull cavity, and lipids were extracted from the carcass packets using diethyl ether in a modified Soxhlet side-arm extractor. Lean dry mass, lipid mass extracted (g dry tissue &minus; g lean dry tissue), and indices of tissue water content (g water/g lean dry tissue) and tissue lipid content (g lipid extracted/g lean dry tissue) were recorded.Adaptive immune function was measured using a previously described ELISA for detection of KLH-specific immunoglobulin Y (IgY) antibodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack2">Killpack and Karasov 2012b</xref>), with the following modifications: After addition of ABTS (2,2&prime;-azino-bis(3-ethylbanzo-thiazoline-6-sulfonic acid)) substrate, plates were incubated in the dark at room temperature for 15 min, and 100 &mu;l of 1&percnt; sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) solution was added to all wells before optical densities were read.Results are given as means &plusmn; SE (<italic>n</italic> &equals; number of individuals). All tests were carried out using R statistical package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2008</xref>), except for nonlinear curve-fitting to growth models, which was performed in SYSTAT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Wilkinson1">Wilkinson 2000</xref>). Parametric tests were used when data were normal or could be transformed to an approximately normal distribution. For all tests, the significance level was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and 0.05 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.10 was considered to indicate a trend.We fit linear mixed models of food consumption using maximum likelihood criteria, with day, treatment, and their interaction as fixed effects. Pair ID and brood ID were included as random effects to control for repeated measures and for nonindependence of our samples (i.e. feeding treatment imposed on cage families) to avoid pseudoreplication. Single-term deletion chi-square-based tests were used to determine the significance of individual interaction and fixed effect predictors (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack3">Killpack et al. 2013</xref>). Post hoc analyses were performed for models with significant interactions using simultaneous tests for general linear hypotheses and defined contrasts of treatment differences in food consumption on a given experiment day. Two-sample <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to compare treatment differences in changes in body measures over the 72-hr experimental period (experiment day 0 to 3) for broods of nestlings or pairs of adults.Two criteria were used to evaluate compensatory growth in food-restricted Zebra Finch nestlings: whether there were accelerated growth rates following restriction, and whether the same asymptotic size was achieved at the same time as control-fed nestlings. Using these two criteria for compensatory growth evaluation required that attainment of control body size in food-restricted nestlings be achieved through faster-than-normal growth rates. This contrasts with &lsquo;catch-up' growth achieved through normal growth rates and an extended developmental period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hector1">Hector and Nakagawa 2012</xref>).Growth rates (g day<sup>&minus;1</sup> or mm day<sup>&minus;1</sup>) were calculated for 72 hr prior to food restriction (Pre), 72 hr during food restriction (Restriction), and 72 hr following food restriction (Post). We fit linear mixed models for each 72 hr period using maximum likelihood criteria, with treatment as a fixed effect and pair ID and brood ID as random effects to control for repeated measures and nonindependence of our samples (i.e. relatedness of siblings in a nest). Single-term deletion chi-square-based tests were then used to determine whether there were significant treatment differences in growth rate for that period. We also examined treatment effects on growth rates while including size at the start of each period as a covariate in the mixed models.To test for asymptotic size and the time when it was reached, we performed nonlinear curve-fitting of empirical control data using the Richards equation to fit body mass data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Richards1">Richards 1959</xref>; shape parameter value: 2.5) and the logistic growth equation fit to tarsus and culmen data. Both equations have been used to describe growth in passeriform species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Lepczyk1">Lepczyk and Karasov 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Ricklefs2">Ricklefs 1968</xref>) and we chose equations based on least-squares criteria. We calculated the average asymptotic size (g or mm) and 95&percnt; confidence interval from the nonlinear curve models of all control nestlings. We then used empirical data to determine the day that control and food-restricted nestlings reached the modeled asymptotic size, and used a two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test to compare the mean day that asymptotic size was reached between treatment groups.For the analysis of treatment differences in nestling body composition, we fit linear mixed models and used single-term deletion chi-square-based tests as described above. Wilcoxon rank sum nonparametric tests were used to examine treatment differences in KLH-specific antibody responses after the primary and booster injections. Paired <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to compare KLH antibody responses after the primary vs. booster injection within each treatment group.Food consumption significantly differed between treatment groups only during the imposed 72-hr food-restriction period (day &times; treatment interaction: &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 102, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for daily contrasts of food consumption on experiment days 1, 2, 3). During the 72-hr food-restriction period, seed consumption in the experimental groups (6.25 &plusmn; 0.28 g day<sup>&minus;1</sup>) averaged 46&percnt; less than control group consumption (11.55 &plusmn; 0.39 g day<sup>&minus;1</sup>). Both sexes of the parent Zebra Finches fed their nestlings, and there was a significant difference in body mass change over the 72-hr experimental period between adult pairs in control and food-restricted cages. While adults feeding nestlings in ad libitum control cages showed only a 1&percnt; reduction in body mass during the 72-hr experimental period (&minus;0.14 &plusmn; 0.33 g from experiment day 0 to 3), there was an 8&percnt; reduction in body mass of adults in experimentally food-restricted cages during this 72-hr period (&minus;0.91 &plusmn; 0.68 g from experiment day 0 to 3; <italic>t</italic><sub>14</sub> &equals; 3.46, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004).Decreased food intake in food-restricted cages over the 72-hr experimental period was associated with significant reductions in growth of nestling broods compared with broods in control cages. Broods in control ad libitum feeding cages exhibited a 43&percnt; increase in body mass over the 72-hr experimental period (3.47 &plusmn; 0.28 g from experiment day 0 to 3), but broods in food-restricted cages showed only an 18&percnt; increase in body mass during this time (0.96 &plusmn; 0.22 g from experiment day 0 to 3; <italic>t</italic><sub>22</sub> &equals; 7.34, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). Broods in control ad libitum cages exhibited a 30&percnt; increase in tarsus length over the 72-hr experimental period (3.47 &plusmn; 0.38 mm from experiment day 0 to 3), whereas broods in food-restricted cages showed only a 21&percnt; increase in tarsus length during this time (1.93 &plusmn; 0.46 mm from experiment day 0 to 3; <italic>t</italic><sub>22</sub> &equals; 2.70, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.013; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). Broods in control ad libitum cages exhibited a 25&percnt; increase in culmen length over the 72-hr experimental period (1.20 &plusmn; 0.20 mm from experiment day 0 to 3), while broods in food-restricted cages showed only a 15&percnt; increase in culmen length during this time (0.63 &plusmn; 0.15 mm from experiment day 0 to 3; <italic>t</italic><sub>22</sub> &equals; 2.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f03">Figure 3</xref>A).(<bold>A</bold>) Body masses of control (filled triangles) and food-restricted (unfilled circles) Zebra Finch nestlings. Food restriction (denoted by white box on <italic>x</italic>-axis) occurred from experiment day 1 (average brood age &equals; 6 days posthatch) through experiment day 3. Data are means &plusmn; SE. (<bold>B</bold>) Body mass growth rates of Zebra Finch nestlings during the 72 hr prerestriction (Pre; experiment days &minus;2, &minus;1, 0), food restriction (Restriction; experiment days 1, 2, 3), and postrestriction (Post; experiment days 4, 5, 6) periods. Asterisks indicate experiment days when growth rates were significantly different between control (filled bars) and food-restricted (unfilled bars) groups (&ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, &ast;&ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).(<bold>A</bold>) Tarsus lengths of control (filled triangles) and food-restricted (unfilled circles) Zebra Finch nestlings. Food restriction (denoted by white box on <italic>x</italic>-axis) occurred from experiment day 1 (average brood age &equals; 6 days posthatch) through experiment day 3. Data are means &plusmn; SE. (<bold>B</bold>) Tarsus growth rates of Zebra Finch nestlings during the 72 hr prerestriction (Pre; experiment days &minus;2, &minus;1, 0), food restriction (Restriction; experiment days 1, 2, 3), and postrestriction (Post; experiment days 4, 5, 6) periods. Asterisks indicate experiment days when growth rates were significantly different between control (filled bars) and food-restricted (unfilled bars) groups (&ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).(<bold>A</bold>) Culmen lengths of control (filled triangles) and food-restricted (unfilled circles) Zebra Finch nestlings. Food restriction (denoted by white box on <italic>x</italic>-axis) occurred from experiment day 1 (average brood age &equals; 6 days posthatch) through experiment day 3. Data are means &plusmn; SE. (<bold>B</bold>) Culmen growth rates of Zebra Finch nestlings during the 72 hr prerestriction (Pre; experiment days &minus;2, &minus;1, 0), food restriction (Restriction; experiment days 1, 2, 3), and postrestriction (Post; experiment days 4, 5, 6) periods. Asterisks indicate experiment days when growth rates were significantly different between control (filled bars) and food-restricted (unfilled bars) groups (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.05).Given that the food restriction treatment did significantly impact nestlings, we examined evidence for compensatory growth following food restriction using two criteria: evidence of accelerated growth rates following restriction, and whether the same asymptotic size was achieved at the same time as control-fed nestlings. Both criteria for compensatory growth in body mass were met by food-restricted nestlings. Body mass growth rates did not significantly differ between treatments prerestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.001, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.98), were significantly lower in food-restricted birds during restriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 33, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and were significantly higher in food-restricted birds postrestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 9.68, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f01">Figure 1</xref>B). Mean modeled asymptotic body mass, calculated using Richards' (1959) equation fit to individual control nestling growth curves, was 12.09 g (95&percnt; confidence interval: 11.80 g, 12.39 g). The experiment day when asymptotic size was reached did not significantly differ between control (9.8 &plusmn; 0.75 days) and food-restricted nestlings (11.8 &plusmn; 1.2 days; <italic>t</italic><sub>30</sub> &equals; &minus;1.40, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15), and experimental nestlings reached the modeled asymptotic body mass prior to fledging age (21 days posthatch, or experiment day 15; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f01">Figure 1</xref>A).In contrast to body mass growth, the dual criteria for compensatory tarsus growth were not met in food-restricted nestlings. No accelerated tarsus growth was observed following food restriction. Tarsus growth rates did not significantly differ between treatments during prerestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.63, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.06), were significantly lower in food-restricted nestlings during restriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup>&equals; 8.99, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003), and did not significantly differ between treatments postrestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 2.19, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f02">Figure 2</xref>B). Although prerestriction tarsus growth was slightly lower in the food-restricted group, neither the interaction of prerestriction tarsus growth rate with treatment (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.10, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.75) nor the fixed effect of prerestriction tarsus growth rate (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.62, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.43) had a significant effect on postrestriction tarsus growth rate. Mean asymptotic tarsus size, calculated using the logistic equation fit to individual control bird growth curves, was 14.76 mm (95&percnt; confidence interval: 14.49 mm, 15.02 mm). The majority of control (19 of 26) and food-restricted (13 of 21) nestlings reached this asymptotic tarsus length prior to the end of our experimental period and prior to fledging. Among those nestlings, there was no significant difference in the day when asymptotic length was reached (control: 9.1 &plusmn; 0.72 days, vs. food-restricted: 9.5 &plusmn; 0.67 days; <italic>t</italic><sub>30</sub> &equals; &minus;0.37, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.73; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). Some of the nestlings that did not reach the modeled asymptotic tarsus length by the end of the experimental period were in the immune subset, and their tarsus sizes were compared at the time of euthanization. At experiment day 27 (average age: 33 days posthatch), there were no significant differences in tarsus length between the subsets of control (13.47 &plusmn; 0.12 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 6) and food-restricted nestlings (13.22 &plusmn; 0.21 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 6; <italic>t</italic><sub>8</sub> &equals; 1.17, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.27).No compensatory culmen growth was observed in Zebra Finch nestlings. Culmen growth rates did not significantly differ between treatment groups prerestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.91), were significantly lower in food-restricted nestlings during restriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 4.92, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03), and continued to be significantly lower in food-restricted nestlings postrestriction (&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 3.96, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f03">Figure 3</xref>B). Mean asymptotic culmen size, calculated using the logistic equation fit to individual control nestlings, was 8.93 mm (95&percnt; confidence interval: 8.30 mm, 9.56 mm). The majority of control (18 of 26) and food-restricted (18 of 21) nestlings did not reach this asymptotic culmen length prior to the end of our experimental period and prior to fledging. Some of the nestlings that did not reach the modeled asymptotic culmen length by the end of the experimental period were in the immune subset, and their culmen sizes were compared at the time of euthanization. When measured at experiment day 27, there were no significant differences in culmen length between the subsets of control (8.85 &plusmn; 0.12 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 12) and food-restricted nestlings (8.78 &plusmn; 0.09 mm, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 13; <italic>t</italic><sub>21</sub> &equals; 0.51, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.62).A subset of nestlings from the compensatory growth experiment (control <italic>n</italic> &equals; 17 and food-restricted <italic>n</italic> &equals; 13) were analyzed for adaptive immune function and body composition following refeeding. KLH-specific antibody responses of birds in both treatments increased between sampling following the primary injection (on experiment day 13) and the booster injection (on experiment day 20; <italic>t</italic><sub>28</sub> &equals; &minus;3.24, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.003; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f04">Figure 4</xref>), providing evidence of significant secondary IgY antibody response to the booster in both control and food-restricted groups. However, there was no significant difference between control and food-restricted birds in KLH-specific primary antibody response 7 days after the primary injection (<italic>z</italic> &equals; 98, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.81) or in secondary antibody response 7 days after the booster injection (<italic>z</italic> &equals; 109, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.97; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f04">Figure 4</xref>). There was no significant correlation between postbooster KLH response and growth rate during the three days postrestriction within the food-restricted group (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.45, <italic>t</italic><sub>11</sub> &equals; 1.68, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12) or the control group (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.18, <italic>t</italic><sub>15</sub> &equals; 0.69, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.50).Specific antibody responses of control (filled bars) and food-restricted (unfilled bars) Zebra Finch nestlings injected intramuscularly with keyhole limpet hemocyanin (KLH) antigen. Data are means &plusmn; SE. Asterisks indicate a significant difference between postvaccination and postboost antibody response levels (&ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). No significant treatment effect was observed between control and food-restricted groups.There were no significant differences in lean dry mass between control (2.89 &plusmn; 0.13 g) and food-restricted (2.82 &plusmn; 0.09 g) nestlings at the end of the experimental period(&chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.331, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.57). Lean body water content (g water per g lean dry mass) was significantly higher in food-restricted nestlings (2.59 &plusmn; 0.02) compared with controls (2.46 &plusmn; 0.02; &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 12.70, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Body lipid content (g lipid per g lean dry mass) did not significantly differ between food-restricted nestlings (0.42 &plusmn; 0.02) and controls (0.39 &plusmn; 0.02; &chi;<sup>2</sup> &equals; 1.17, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.28).Our food restriction protocol significantly reduced nestling growth, and we demonstrated rapid compensatory body mass growth in nestling Zebra Finches upon return to ad libitum feeding. We observed accelerated growth rates in food-restricted nestlings in the 72 hr following restriction, and the same asymptotic body mass was reached on the same experimental day as controls. Food-restricted nestlings did not significantly differ from controls in lean dry-body mass at the end of the experiment, providing additional evidence that the compensatory growth in body mass likely represented functional lean tissue mass gain rather than increased lipid stores. This capacity to accelerate body mass growth lends support to the theory that normal body growth under typical feeding conditions is regulated at an optimized, rather than maximized, rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Monaghan 2001</xref>). While compensatory growth in Zebra Finches has been previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Fisher1">Fisher et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo1">Criscuolo et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo2">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Krause1">Krause and Naguib 2011</xref>), ours is the first study, to our knowledge, to demonstrate accelerated compensatory growth in Zebra Finch nestlings within a few days following food restriction. Previous studies have presented mixed results regarding compensatory body mass growth after short-term food restriction in altricial nestlings. Laboratory studies using hand-feeding to impose short-term food restrictions on House Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Lepczyk1">Lepczyk and Karasov 2000</xref>), Song Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus philomelos</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Konarzewski1">Konarzewski et al. 1996</xref>), and Bank Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Riparia riparia</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Brzek1">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2001</xref>) nestlings did not find evidence of compensatory growth in body mass upon refeeding of the birds. In contrast, free-living altricial Alpine Swift (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus melba</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>) and Collared Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hegyi1">Hegyi and T&ouml;r&ouml;k 2007</xref>) nestlings experiencing short-term food restriction demonstrated accelerated rates of body mass growth upon return to improved feeding conditions. Models utilizing parents to feed nestlings, whether in the wild (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hegyi1">Hegyi and T&ouml;r&ouml;k 2007</xref>) or in the laboratory (our study), may therefore be better experimental models for comparative studies of capacity for nestling compensatory growth.In contrast to body mass growth, we observed near-parallel, rather than accelerated, tarsus growth rates in Zebra Finch nestlings during the immediate refeeding period. There was no significant increase in tarsus growth rate in food-restricted birds in the 72 hr following food restriction, although control and food-restricted birds reached the same asymptotic size at the same time. Thus, following food restriction, control tarsus size was achieved in the absence of accelerated growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hector1">Hector and Nakagawa 2012</xref>). Sternum size reductions in Alpine Swifts experiencing a one-week period of undernutrition were not recovered until 30 days following food restriction, demonstrating slow growth to asymptotic sternum size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>). In 7-day-old Collared Flycatchers, tarsus length reductions following a 3-day food restriction were not recovered by fledging age at 4 days postrestriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hegyi1">Hegyi and T&ouml;r&ouml;k 2007</xref>). Lack of accelerated skeletal growth may reflect the strong endocrine control of long-bone growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Leach1">Leach and Rosselot 1992</xref>), which may impose a critical rate and time window for structural growth. It is ecologically advantageous for structural size to be achieved prior to fledging, as decreased structural size can have negative implications for fledging time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Miller1">Miller 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Searcy1">Searcy et al. 2004</xref>), social rank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Richner1">Richner et al. 1989</xref>), and recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Emlen1">Emlen and Wrege 1991</xref>). Because restriction occurred early in the nestling period, food-restricted Zebra Finches appeared to reach control tarsus length prior to fledging without significantly accelerating their growth rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-f02">Figure 2</xref>). However, if food restriction had occurred later in the nestling period, control tarsus size may not have been reached prior to fledging. Future studies should examine the impact of the timing and magnitude of food restriction during the nestling period on patterns of subsequent growth of body mass and skeletal structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Bize1">Bize et al. 2006</xref>).Reduced culmen growth rates in food-restricted Zebra Finches persisted in the 72 hr after return to ad libitum feeding. Slow catch-up of reduced culmen length did occur during the weeks postfledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hector1">Hector and Nakagawa 2012</xref>); food-restricted birds in the immune subset did not have significantly shorter average culmen lengths compared with controls on experiment day 27 (average age 33 days posthatch). It is possible that accelerated compensatory body mass growth postrestriction came at the cost of a reduction in culmen growth rates. Apparent tradeoffs between body mass and culmen growth may be related to relatively slow growth to asymptotic size of the culmen and skull compared with other skeletal components. In a study of growth in Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>), the head was shown to have a relatively low postnatal growth constant compared with other body components such as the wings and digestive organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs 1967</xref>). In Marbled Murrelets (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus marmoratus</named-content></italic>), bill growth continued to increase significantly after nest departure, and bill length was positively influenced by the quality of the postfledging (at-sea) diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Janssen1">Janssen et al. 2011</xref>). Future studies of structure-specific tradeoffs in growth should include culmen and skull measurements and consider fitness effects of reduced culmen and skull growth.Given the evidence that many animals are capable of growing at faster rates than they generally display, it is possible that the benefits of always maximizing growth rate may be outweighed by other physiological and/or ecological costs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Monaghan 2001</xref>). Compensatory growth in Zebra Finches has been associated with reduced cognitive ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Fisher1">Fisher et al. 2006</xref>), reduced flight performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo2">Criscuolo et al. 2011</xref>), increased susceptibility to oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2007</xref>), and elevated adult resting metabolic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo1">Criscuolo et al. 2008</xref>). In our study we examined tissue maturity in Zebra Finches demonstrating compensatory growth. Tissue maturity is commonly indexed by lean tissue water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Marsh1">Marsh and Wickler 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Choi1">Choi et al. 1993</xref>), because reductions in muscle water content occur with age and coincide with increasing muscle function in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Ricklefs4">Ricklefs and Webb 1985</xref>). In previous studies of altricial and semialtricial birds, no significant increases in muscle water content were observed during food restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Burness1">Burness et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Dahdul1">Dahdul and Horn 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Killpack1">Killpack and Karasov 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Konarzewski1">Konarzewski et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Takenaka1">Takenaka et al. 2005</xref>). In contrast, following food restriction and compensatory growth, Zebra Finches in our study had significantly higher lean tissue water content, and thus decreased tissue maturity, compared with controls. Therefore, it appears that a tradeoff between growth and development occurred as result of accelerated growth during the nestling period, resulting in a decoupling of chronological age and physiological age in food-restricted birds. Acquisition of functional maturity through rapid cellular differentiation could limit the proportion of tissue capable of cell proliferation and growth, and this antagonism might constrain postnatal growth and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Ricklefs3">Ricklefs 1979</xref>). For example, exponential growth rate of muscles has been negatively correlated with indices of glycolytic activity, electric potential, and contractile protein content in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Ricklefs5">Ricklefs et al. 1994</xref>). Delayed tissue differentiation resulting from compensatory growth could have negative effects on maintenance metabolism and thermogenesis, as well as flight performance (which has been observed in Zebra Finches following compensatory growth; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Criscuolo2">Criscuolo et al. 2011</xref>) in adults. Food-restricted Zebra Finches in our study did not differ from controls in body lipid content; this finding is in agreement with another study of birds refed after food restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Brzek2">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2004</xref>). These patterns suggest that while developmental maturation of the tissues may be suspended or delayed as a result of compensatory growth, the ability to recover depleted fat stores resulting from food restriction is more flexible.An apparent tradeoff between investment in growth and investment in immune response has been observed in free-living nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Soler1">Soler et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Brommer1">Brommer 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Mauck1">Mauck et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Arriero1">Arriero et al. 2013</xref>) and in food-restricted nestlings in the laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Brzek3">Brz&eogon;k and Konarzewski 2007</xref>). To our knowledge, this is the first study to examine the effects of accelerated, compensatory growth on adaptive humoral immune development in Zebra Finches or rapidly growing altricial birds in general. Development of adaptive humoral components is purportedly costly because it requires generation and proliferation of B-cell lineages with diverse, functional antibody specificities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Lee1">Lee 2006</xref>). However, food restriction and accelerated growth did not alter development of the humoral immune system or the capacity for functional memory antibody response in our current study. Previously food-restricted Zebra Finches mounted functional secondary antibody responses to a booster KLH injection, and the magnitude of the response did not significantly differ from that of controls. Additionally, neither the previously food-restricted birds nor the control birds showed a significant correlation between postrestriction growth rate and the adaptive antibody response level, reinforcing the absence of a tradeoff between growth and development of adaptive immune capacity. Together, these data suggest that the energetic costs of growth are relatively larger than the costs of development of the humoral immune system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-vanderMost1">van der Most et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Hasselquist1">Hasselquist and Nilsson 2012</xref>), and that tradeoffs in adaptive antibody response may not be expected following rapid growth. To further examine tradeoffs in immune function and growth, future studies should examine the effects of varied timing and duration of food stress, as well as the immune impacts of food restriction alone and restriction followed by compensatory growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-396-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Monaghan 2001</xref>).In conclusion, experimentally decreased food availability in cage groups for 72 hr led to reduced body mass and structural growth in nestling Zebra Finches fed by parents. Using two criteria (accelerated growth rates in the first 72 hr of refeeding and attainment of the same asymptotic size at the same time as controls), we demonstrated compensatory growth in body mass, but not tarsus or culmen length, in previously food-restricted nestlings. Nestlings raised in the experimental feeding treatment had significantly reduced tissue maturity, but no significant alterations in adaptive antibody response, when compared with control nestlings.All experimental procedures were approved by the University of Wisconsin&ndash;Madison Animal Care and Use Committee (Permit No. 1421). We thank undergraduate research assistants for help with animal husbandry. We thank C. An&eacute; for statistics consulting, and T. Crenshaw and D. Schneider for assistance with lipid extraction. Thanks also to Karasov lab members and anonymous reviewers for their comments on earlier versions of this manuscript. This study was supported by grants from the National Science Foundation &lsqb;grant number IOS-0615678&rsqb; and USDA&ndash;Hatch to W. H. Karasov, and National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship and awards from the American Ornithologists' Union, Bunde Fund, and Noland Fund to T.L.K.