Genetics, morphology, and ecological niche modeling do not support the subspecies status of the endangered Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>)A review of the races of the Traill's FlycatcherThe seventy-five percent rule for subspeciesGeographic variation, predictiveness, and subspeciesGenetic structure, introgression, and a narrow hybrid zone between northern and California spotted owls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Strix occidentalis</named-content></italic>)Utah birds: Geographic distribution and systematicsU.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Authority under Section 4(c)(l) of the Endangered Species Act to Revise Lists of Endangered and Threatened Species to &ldquo;Reflect Recent Determinations,&rdquo;Hawth's analysis tools for ArcGISNotes on certain flycatchers of the genus <italic>Empidonax</italic>Comments on the taxonomy of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic> (Willow Flycatcher)Genetic variation in the endangered Southwestern Willow FlycatcherSorting out tigers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Panthera tigris</named-content></italic>): Mitochondrial sequences, nuclear inserts, systematics, and conservation geneticsA statistical explanation of MaxEnt for ecologistsArlequin suite ver 3.5: A new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and WindowsAvian subspecies: Summary and prospectusModeling the dynamic habitat and breeding population of Southwestern Willow FlycatcherMultilocus coalescence analyses support a mtDNA-based phylogeographic history for a widespread Palearctic passerine bird, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sitta europaea</named-content></italic>Divergence across Australia's Carpentarian barrier: Statistical phylogeography of the Red-backed Fairy Wren (<italic>Malurus melanocephalus</italic>)Prospects for the use of next-generation sequencing methods in ornithologyThe detection of disease clustering and a generalized regression approachFinancial costs of meeting global biodiversity conservation targets: Current spending and unmet needsDoes niche divergence accompany allopatric divergence in <italic>Aphelocoma</italic> jays as predicted under ecological speciation?: Insights from tests with niche modelsPhenotypic variation is clinal in the Yellow-throated WarblerA review of centers of differentiation for birds in the western Great Basin regionApplications of mitochondrial DNA analysis in conservation: A critical reviewNew light on the status of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic> (Audubon)Descriptions of new birds from Oregon, chiefly from the Warner Valley regionA new flycatcher from the western United StatesNull expectations in subspecies diagnosisDiagnosability versus mean differences of Sage Sparrow subspeciesGeographic variation in the plumage coloration of Willow Flycatchers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>Using molecular genetic markers to resolve a subspecies boundary: The northern boundary of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher in the four-corner statesWinter distribution of Willow Flycatcher subspeciesPredicting species' geographic distributions based on ecological niche modelingAre subspecies useful in evolutionary and conservation biology?Geographic variation in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>Maximum entropy modeling of species geographic distributionsPattern, process, and rigor meet classificationGeographic variation in size and shape of Savannah Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerculus sandwichensis</named-content></italic>)Geographic variation of the Curve-billed Thrasher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Toxostoma curvirostre</named-content></italic>) complexGeographic variation in the song of Willow Flycatchers: Differentiation between <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>Type I errors linked to faulty statistical analyses of endangered subspecies classificationsMEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0The biogeography of mitochondrial and nuclear discordance in animals<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>: An endangered subspeciesFinal rule determining endangered status for the Southwestern Willow FlycatcherEndangered and threatened wildlife and plants; 90-day finding on a petition to delist the coastal California Gnatcatcher as threatenedPolicy regarding the recognition of distinct vertebrate population segments under the Endangered Species ActEnvironmental niche equivalency versus conservatism: Quantitative approaches to niche evolutionENMTools: A toolbox for comparative studies of environmental niche modelsENMTools User Manual v1.3The subspecies concept and its taxonomic applicationPatterns and evolutionary significance of geographic variation in the Schistacea group of the Fox Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passerella iliaca</named-content></italic>)The role of subspecies in obscuring avian biological diversity and misleading conservation policyMitochondrial DNA under siege in avian phylogeographyPhylogeography of the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>) using multilocus DNA sequences and ecological niche modeling: Implications for conservationEvolutionary processes and patterns of geographic variation in birdsThe Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>) breeds throughout much of the United States, northwestern Mexico, and southeastern and southwestern Canada. A subspecies found in the southwestern United States and northwestern Mexico, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (Southwestern Willow Flycatcher), is listed as endangered under the U.S. Endangered Species Act (ESA). This subspecies was described in 1948, based on comparisons of a few external morphological characters from an unstated number of specimens and localities, although it was excluded from the last official list of subspecies by the American Ornithologists' Union. Like most avian subspecies, its validity has not been tested with modern morphological or genetic methods. Recent assessments of the subspecies have assumed it to be a distinct taxon, and some authors have limited their comparisons to <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> versus <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (the subspecies immediately to the north of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>), excluding comparison to western (<italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>) and eastern (<italic>E. t. traillii</italic>) subspecies. To test subspecies limits, I reanalyzed available quantitative data on plumage coloration, and genetic variation in mitochondrial DNA and nuclear loci, and found no support for the distinctiveness of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher. A test of niche divergence suggested that the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher does not have a significantly different climatic niche from its nearest geographic neighbor, <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. I suggest that the Willow Flycatchers of the Southwest represent peripheral populations of an otherwise widespread species that do not merit subspecific recognition, and are therefore inappropriately listed as endangered under the ESA.<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic> se reproduce a trav&eacute;s de la mayor&iacute;a de Am&eacute;rica del Norte al norte del noroeste de M&eacute;xico. Una subespecie hallada en el sudoeste de Estados Unidos y noroeste de M&eacute;xico, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, est&aacute; listada como en peligro de extinci&oacute;n bajo la Ley de Especies Amenazadas de Estados Unidos. Esta subespecie fue descripta por primera vez en 1948 en base a un n&uacute;mero no especificado de espec&iacute;menes y localidades. Como la mayor&iacute;a de las subespecies, su validez no ha sido evaluada usando m&eacute;todos modernos morfol&oacute;gicos o gen&eacute;ticos. En cambio, los estudios publicados han asumido que la subespecie representa un tax&oacute;n distintivo. El re-an&aacute;lisis de datos cuantitativos disponibles de la coloraci&oacute;n del plumaje y la variaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica en el ADN mitocondrial y el loci nuclear no apoyan el car&aacute;cter distintivo de <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. Un examen de divergencia de nicho sugiere que <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> no presenta un nicho clim&aacute;tico significativamente diferente de su vecino geogr&aacute;fico m&aacute;s cercano, <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. Por ende, los individuos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic> del sudoeste pertenecen a poblaciones perif&eacute;ricas de una especie ampliamente distribuida que no amerita un reconocimiento sub espec&iacute;fico, y por lo tanto se encuentra err&oacute;neamente listada como en peligro de extinci&oacute;n bajo la Ley de Especies Amenazadas.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> ADN mitocondrial; coloraci&oacute;n del plumaje; <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>; Ley de Especies Amenazadas; modelado de nicho; subespeciesThe U.S. Endangered Species Act (ESA) extends protection to species, subspecies, and the distinct population segment (DPS; vertebrates only). Application of the ESA requires that subspecies and DPSs represent evolutionarily significant populations or groups of populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Moritz1">Moritz 1994</xref>). The reason for this expectation is that nearly all species show geographic variation in at least 1 morphological, ecological, physiological, genetic, or behavioral characteristic, and it is possible to subdivide this variation taxonomically in numerous ways without yielding evolutionarily significant taxa. This situation is often suggested to reflect the subspecies category in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Wilson1">Wilson and Brown 1953</xref>); in ornithology, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Remsen1">Remsen (2005</xref>:407) noted that &ldquo;Widespread, long-standing dissatisfaction with subspecies-level designations in bird classification derives from the historical fact that most bird subspecies were described in an era when quantitative methods were unavailable to assess their validity as entities.&rdquo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Barrowclough1">Barrowclough (1982)</xref> noted that authors of comprehensive quantitative surveys of geographic variation often avoided trinomials whereas studies involving qualitative assessments of color or a few study-skin measurements from a few specimens that represented a few widespread sites often included subspecies descriptions. These observations led <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Barrowclough1">Barrowclough (1982</xref>:601) to remark that &ldquo;This strongly suggests to me that most subspecies are not to be taken too seriously.&rdquo;Others find intrinsic value in subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Haig1">Haig and Winker 2010</xref>), and attempts have been made to define subspecies more rigorously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Patten2">Patten and Unitt (2002</xref>:26) suggested that &ldquo;A subspecies is a collection of populations within a biological species that are diagnosably distinct from other such collections of populations.&rdquo; The question then is what is meant by &ldquo;diagnosably.&rdquo; Probably all populations differ in some respect from other populations. For example, an individual in one area might have an allele that is found nowhere else, or there might be an individual that is larger and darker-colored than any other individual in the species. Although both of these unique phenotypes might represent the &ldquo;raw material&rdquo; from which the population could adapt to a changing environment, few would consider this sufficient evidence to warrant a subspecies designation if the criterion is that they are diagnosably distinct. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Barrowclough1">Barrowclough (1982)</xref> suggested that subspecies should be held to the same standard as all taxa, in that a taxonomic name at whatever rank should be predictive of concordant patterns of character variation. The &ldquo;75&percnt; rule&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Amadon1">Amadon 1949</xref>) requires that &ldquo;75&percnt; of a population effectively must lie outside 99&percnt; of the range of other populations for a given defining character or set of characters&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Patten2">Patten and Unitt 2002</xref>:27). I suggest that subspecies or other taxa protected under the ESA should be nearly (&gt;95&percnt;) if not completely diagnosable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Cracraft1">Cracraft et al. 1998</xref>).The lack of a consistent definition of subspecies has resulted in currently described subspecies ranging from evolutionarily distinct taxa to arbitrary divisions of geographic clines in single characters. Thus, some subspecies are not appropriate for certain scientific or conservation uses. If the goal of an investigator is to identify geographic patterns of potentially adaptive variation, all subspecies might be a useful starting point. By contrast, if a subspecies is to be used in an analysis that requires historically significant units, such as listing under the ESA, it should be based on, or evaluated with, modern molecular, morphological, and ecological methods.Here, I reanalyze published genetic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>) and morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>) data to test the validity of the endangered Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>). I also analyze all available mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) sequences in GenBank that have not been pooled previously. In addition, I used methods in ecological niche modeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren2">2010</xref>) to determine whether the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher is ecologically distinct in its climatic niche. The goal was to analyze variation irrespective of a priori subspecies limits to determine whether there were geographic patterns in genetics, plumage coloration, or ecological niche dimensions that were consistent with described subspecies limits or any other heretofore undiscovered geographically significant divisions.The Willow Flycatcher has been divided by taxonomists into subspecies, with up to 7 having been recognized at some time in the past (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1951</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Behle1">Behle 1985</xref>). Most (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>) consider the species to include 4 subspecies: <italic>E. t. traillii</italic>, <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>, and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>). Review of the original subspecies descriptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Brewster1">Brewster 1895</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Oberholser1">Oberholser 1918</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Oberholser2">1932</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Oberholser3">1947</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1951</xref>) reveals that few specimens were examined from relatively few areas. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Oberholser1">Oberholser (1918)</xref> described <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> from a total of 13 male specimens taken from Oregon, California, Arizona, New Mexico, and Colorado, and a total of 10 females from Oregon, California, Arizona, and Utah. It is difficult to quantify the range of biological variation present within and among populations with such sample sizes; although this may not have been a goal of early taxonomists, it nonetheless obscured whether variation was clinal or discrete. The wide-ranging <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Oberholser2">Oberholser (1932)</xref> on the basis of specimens from Hart Mountain in the Warner Valley of south-central Oregon; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Miller1">Miller (1941)</xref> was unable to distinguish this subspecies from others, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Aldrich1">Aldrich (1951)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips (1948)</xref> believed it to be valid, although there is disagreement over its distribution. In the description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>) of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, no sample sizes were given and no statistical tests performed. Although <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> was described in 1948, it was excluded from the most recent American Ornithologists' Union (AOU) Checklist that included subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1957</xref>). However, taxonomic assessments of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic> have included <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> after its original description, and it is listed as an endangered subspecies under the ESA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-U.S.FishandWildlifeService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 1995</xref>).Several recent studies have compared subspecies of Willow Flycatchers. In a genetic study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> compared mtDNA sequences and amplified fragment length polymorphisms (AFLPs) from nuclear DNA. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Busch1">Busch et al. (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref> concentrated on AFLP variation within and among subspecies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> quantified variation in lightness, saturation, and hue of the crown and back. Sample sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f01">Figure 1</xref>) for the 2 larger recent studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">2010</xref>) excluded &sim;75&percnt; of the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and &sim;50&percnt; of the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. Furthermore, formal comparisons with the subspecies to the west (<italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>) and east (<italic>E. t. traillii</italic>) were not performed, making it unclear how the study could evaluate the genetic distinctiveness of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton4">Paxton et al. (2011)</xref> examined mtDNA sequences from migrant individuals, as well as specimens representing much of the breeding range of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic> (including all 4 widely recognized subspecies). However, these studies did not provide tests of subspecies limits. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010</xref>:131) stated that &ldquo;Because this study was intended to distinguish among established taxonomic units, we grouped breeding sites a priori into one of the four subspecies based on geographic ranges delineated via morphological studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Browning1">Browning 1993</xref>).&rdquo; However, the samples of <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> were &gt;1,000 km from the nearest sample of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> or <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, and the samples of western <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> were &gt;900 km from the nearest <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> locality. I contend that the assertion that the subspecies limits are &ldquo;established&rdquo; is debatable. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt (1987)</xref> stated that the most comprehensive study of geographic variation in Willow Flycatchers was by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Aldrich1">Aldrich (1951)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Aldrich1">Aldrich's (1951)</xref> general review of the subspecies gave no lists of specimens, no values for measurements (except for his description of a new subspecies, <italic>E. t. campestris</italic>, which has subsequently been ignored), and no quantitative character analyses. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt (1987)</xref> used statistical analyses of character variation, although he too only compared preexisting subspecies limits. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Browning1">Browning (1993)</xref> did not perform statistical tests. Therefore, recent studies assumed, rather than tested, whether the data supported described subspecies limits.Distribution of sample sites for genetics (triangle; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>) and coloration (cross, excluding the eastern United States; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>), with approximate boundaries of named subspecies.A fifth study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick 2001</xref>) compared vocalizations of Willow Flycatchers from the Southwest, representing localities from within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (again excluding comparison of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> with <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> or <italic>E. t. traillii</italic>). The results suggested that part of the song of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> differed from that of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. Given that <italic>Empidonax</italic> inherit their songs, it might indicate that genetic differentiation exists that was missed by mtDNA and AFLPs. However, Sedgwick's UPGMA phenogram that shows 2 distinct song groups was based on a reduced set of song characters that were chosen because they separated the 2 groups, whereas characters not showing the same (or a different) pattern were excluded. In addition, the 2 clusters did not group samples entirely by subspecies, and Sedwick (2001:366) concluded that his data suggested &ldquo;moderate introgression of <italic>extimus</italic> genes into the <italic>adastus</italic> gene pool.&rdquo; Lastly, a sampling gap corresponded to the geographic division in song features, reducing the potential to detect gradation in song characteristics between areas. Although the raw data are not available, future studies of vocalizations are warranted.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> surveyed mtDNA and AFLPs within and among <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. The highly variable AFLP data sets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Busch1">Busch et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton1">Paxton 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>) were less informative and did not conflict with conclusions drawn from the mtDNA data, and I did not reanalyze the AFLP data. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> documented the occurrence of 33 mtDNA haplotypes at the cytochrome <italic>b</italic> locus in 145 individuals across 25 breeding sites in Arizona (7 sites), New Mexico (4 sites), Colorado (7 sites), and Utah (7 sites). Assuming that table 2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> is correct, haplotype C2 in GenBank (AF297261) is incorrect because it has an &ldquo;A&rdquo; instead of a &ldquo;G&rdquo; at position 708. I reanalyzed the cytochrome <italic>b</italic> data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> using Arlequin version 3.5.1.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Excoffier1">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>) to compute <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, a measure of pairwise population differentiation that theoretically ranges from zero (absence of geographic structure) to 1 (fixation), and an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA), which estimates the proportion of genetic variance attributable to various geographic groupings of populations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton4">Paxton et al. (2011</xref>:611) sequenced &ldquo;316 individuals sampled at 91 sites on the breeding grounds&rdquo; that represented 62 haplotypes. A search of GenBank (December 13, 2013) found 93 haplotypes for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic>, but there is no corresponding information on their frequencies or geographic origins, although some are from wintering or migrant individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton4">Paxton et al. 2011</xref>). Although the geographic localities are not given with the GenBank submissions, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton4">Paxton et al. (2011)</xref> stated that the sequences represent breeding individuals from <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> (New York, Tennessee, Illinois, North Carolina, Virginia, North Dakota, South Dakota, Minnesota, and Maryland), and <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> (Washington, Oregon, and California), providing considerable coverage of the breeding range (excluding western Canada and the Maritime provinces). I used Mega6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Tamura1">Tamura et al. 2013</xref>) to construct a neighbor-joining tree (distance &equals; <italic>P</italic> value) with 1,000 bootstrapped replicates, of all 93 haplotypes available in GenBank. Despite uncertainty over the exact geographic origins of haplotypes, if there was significant geographic structure in the species range, it would be recovered by this analysis in the form of significantly supported nodes in the tree.The only available quantitative data (at the level of individuals) that allow testing subspecies limits are from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref>, who used a colorimeter to measure lightness, saturation, and hue on the back and crown of 374 live-captured individuals from 29 locations. &ldquo;Lightness&rdquo; is a measure of how light or dark the color is, whereas saturation and hue reveal color direction in 2-dimensional space. They found that coloration changed over time because of feather wear, and adjusted values for the date measurements were taken by &ldquo;multiplying the regression coefficient (b) by the date (day of year) starting from the earliest capture date (9 May, day of year&lowbar;129). These seasonally adjusted color values were used for all subsequent analyses.&rdquo; E. Paxton (personal communication) provided a copy of the adjusted color values (minus the sample from Rush Creek, California). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> divided their samples of breeding individuals into <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (5 locations, 69 individuals), <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> (3, 38), <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (7, 123), <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> (5, 39), and &ldquo;boundary&rdquo; (9, 77). The boundary category included sampling sites between &ldquo;core&rdquo; <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> previously classified 3 sites (CCCO, DELT, and FICR) as <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and 1 (MCSP) as <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. I analyzed the color data using principal component analysis, plotting individuals on orthogonal axes.The occurrence of Willow Flycatchers in riparian areas of the arid Southwest might be associated with significant ecological distinctiveness from flycatchers breeding elsewhere and representing different subspecies. Thus, in lieu of morphological or genetic distinctiveness of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, listing under the ESA could be based on ecological distinctiveness and significance at either the subspecies or DPS level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceandNationalMarineFisheriesService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and National Marine Fisheries Service 1996</xref>). I constructed correlative ecological niche models (ENMs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Peterson1">Peterson 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Elith1">Elith et al. 2011</xref>) using breeding records from the Breeding Bird Survey (accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs</ext-link>) and Ornis2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ornis2.ornisnet.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://ornis2.ornisnet.org/</ext-link>) that were input into Maxent version 3.2.2. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips2">Phillips et al. 2006</xref>). I divided locality points into those representing <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 204) and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 269), limiting the latter taxon to localities south of 49&deg;N so as to equalize the areas of the 2 subspecies compared and to avoid confounding variation due to distance with that among putative taxa. There is concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>) that male <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>, at least in California, sing during their migration through the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, confounding identification of breeding localities from vocalization records (such as the Breeding Bird Survey). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt (1987)</xref> suggested that only singing male <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> noted after June 20 should be considered breeders, but in the same paper he cited verified breeding dates in May (9, 16, 22, and 26) and early June (5, 12, and 13). Considering data on egg sets, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Unitt1">Unitt (1987</xref>:158) wrote that &ldquo;On the basis of 187 dated sets, <italic>extimus</italic> usually begins nesting about 1 June. The sets range in date from 24 May to 30 July; the mean date is 16 June.&rdquo; This suggests that male <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> must sing much earlier when establishing territories. To be conservative, I performed a second niche model in which only localities of singing males noted after June 16 were used (40 <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and 100 random localities drawn from 184 breeding records of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>). Climate data (19 layers) were obtained from the Worldclim bioclimatic database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Hijmans1">Hijmans et al. 2005</xref>).To determine whether these 2 subspecies differ in niche characteristics, I used the niche identity test and the background test for niche divergence in ENM Tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren2">2010</xref>). The niche identity test involved 100 iterations of randomized locality points for the 2 subspecies (maintaining the original number of points for each group), with an ENM constructed for each group in Maxent using the randomized points, followed by calculation of the degree of niche overlap. Schoener's <italic>D</italic> (for details, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren2">2010</xref>) was used as a measure of niche overlap; it ranges from 0 to 1, with 1 indicating complete overlap. If the observed niche overlap value is &lt;95&percnt; of the randomized niche overlap values (1-tailed test), then the climatic niches of the 2 species are considered significantly different.The niche identity test assumes that populations &ldquo;tolerate the exact same set of environmental conditions and have the same suite of environmental conditions available to them&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren3">Warren et al. 2011</xref>:17). Thus, it is possible to obtain a significant niche identity test if populations live in differing environments, but this does not mean, necessarily, that the species have diverged ecologically, only that they are able to survive in different climates because of ecological plasticity. Hence, the appropriate test for evaluating whether niches are significantly divergent is the background test, which allows one to assess &ldquo;whether two species are more or less similar than expected based on the differences in the environmental background in which they occur&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren3">Warren et al. 2011</xref>:19). The background test involves multiple iterations in which the niche overlap is calculated between 1 taxon's ENM and an ENM constructed from random points (obtained from Hawth's Tools &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Beyer1">Beyer 2004</xref>&rsqb; in ArcGIS9) within the range of the second taxon, where the number of random points is the same as the number of actual points for that taxon (subspecies in the present study). Tests are conducted in both directions. The observed niche overlap between 2 species' ENMs is compared with the distribution of overlap values from the runs in each direction to determine whether species' niches are significantly more or less divergent than expected (2-tailed test). Rejection of the null hypothesis (of niche identity) indicates that observed niche differences are a function of habitat selection and/or availability. If niches overlap more than expected, it is often interpreted as evidence for niche conservatism; if niches overlap less than expected, one can assume niche divergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-McCormack1">McCormack et al. 2010</xref>). Only in the case of niche divergence would one assume that <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> had evolved ecological distinctiveness.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> found no fixed mtDNA differences between <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. A large percentage of individuals (30&percnt;) possessed a common haplotype (&ldquo;C1&rdquo;), which was found in 16 localities, although small samples precluded definitive evidence of absence. A second haplotype, D1, was also found in 16 localities although in fewer individuals, and no special significance was attached to it by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref>. A significant isolation-by-distance (IBD) effect was found using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Mantel1">Mantel's (1967)</xref> test when considering all samples, which indicates that genetic differences increase with geographic distance between samples. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> did not observe a significant IBD effect within either subspecies, although the geographic distances were much smaller and, hence, do not obviously support their conclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>:9) that there is a &ldquo;rapid change in &lsqb;haplotype&rsqb; frequencies at the boundary&rdquo; between the subspecies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> also considered how grouping samples into subspecies by moving the boundary north or south affected the amount of genetic variation explained by an AMOVA. This exercise was intended to determine whether a new subspecies boundary would explain more of the genetic variance than the current one. Although there was an effect brought about by changing the boundary, it was not possible to identify a clear and objective boundary. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> constructed a UPGMA dendrogram (their fig. 2) to display the spatial pattern of genetic variation. They found 2 clusters, 1 including populations of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and the other a mixture of both subspecies, which does not support the subspecies as described. In addition, the algorithm used to construct UPGMA phenograms results in the &ldquo;root&rdquo; being placed at the midpoint of the largest pairwise genetic distance. If the sample of localities is biased geographically, the appearance of 2 clades could recover the pattern of sampling. Even if there were a root to the phenogram, there could be no support for <italic>E. t. extimis</italic>, given the topology.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> plotted a graph (their fig. 3) of the frequency of the C-group mtDNA haplotypes versus latitude that purports to show a relatively sharp transition between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. Contrary to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al.'s (2008)</xref> figure legend, their figure 3 is not a plot of C-group haplotypes versus latitude but, instead, haplotype frequencies versus a function of latitude and elevation. It is unusual to plot a subspecies boundary in this way, and elevation was not a part of the original subspecies descriptions (reviewed above), which are based solely on latitude and longitude.I was unable to determine a clear genetic boundary by varying the populations included in an AMOVA. I plotted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f02">Figure 2</xref>) the data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al.'s (2008)</xref> table 2; these data show a gradual transition between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and, therefore, do not support a sharp genetic transition in C-group haplotypes.Plot showing a smooth, clinal relationship between the latitude of the breeding site and the frequency of the C-group haplotypes for cytochrome <italic>b</italic> data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref> (their table 2).The neighbor-joining tree (not shown) for all 93 unique haplotypes was not consistent with distinct groupings, and the highest bootstrap basal nodal support was 29&percnt;. Therefore, although the samples were identified only to U.S. state of origin, there is no phylogenetic structure that could be associated with distinct geographic groupings or named subspecies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> conducted several analyses, such as a canonical discriminant analysis to &ldquo;represent the linear relationship of the plumage coloration by subspecies&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>:131). However, this model was built &ldquo;using only large sample sites within the core area of each subspecies,&rdquo; thereby excluding the boundary sites. Representative conclusions included &ldquo;While there is overlap in the color values of individual flycatchers from the different subspecies, mean value for the breeding sites tended to cluster together by subspecies&rdquo; and that the data indicated &ldquo;intergradation among the subspecies, consistent with a molecular genetic study,&rdquo; that being <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref>.To test the validity of subspecies, I did not group specimens into a priori subspecies, because that process is circular. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f03">Figure 3</xref>, I plot the relationship among individuals in <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, and individuals from boundary locations on PC1 and PC2. The subspecies are not separated; instead, there is a gradation of variation among them.Plot of the distribution of 363 individual Willow Flycatchers from 3 subspecies, and boundary localities for the first 2 principal components (PC) based on analysis of 6 color variables (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>). PC1 (horizontal axis) explains 39&percnt; of the variation, and PC2 (vertical axis) explains 27&percnt;. Note that the subspecies are not distinct and overlap greatly with each other and the boundary locations.The observed niche overlap (Schoener's <italic>D</italic> &equals; 0.17) was much less than the distribution of random values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f04">Figure 4</xref>A), which indicates that niche overlap between the subspecies is less than expected at random. However, comparison of the 2 subspecies did not yield a significant background test (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f04">Figure 4</xref>B), which suggests that the observed niche-identity difference is explained by geographic variation in the environmental conditions available to each subspecies within their respective ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Warren2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-McCormack1">McCormack et al. 2010</xref>). That is, the subspecies are using common environmental features as often as one would expect by chance&mdash;hence, the species likely has a broad ecological (climatic) tolerance, at least in the area studied, and does not show significant ecological divergence in climate niche dimensions. The same results (not shown) were obtained for the analyses of the samples restricted to a temporal window that was designed to exclude migrant birds (see above).(<bold>A</bold>) Results of a niche identity test for <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> versus <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (100 random repetitions), showing that the observed niche identity (Schoener's <italic>D</italic>; arrow) is much less than expected by chance (black bars) and that the 2 subspecies use different niche characteristics. (<bold>B</bold>) Results of a background test for niche divergence between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, showing that although the subspecies use different niche characteristics, they apparently do not exhibit significant niche divergence. If the subspecies had divergent niches, the observed Schoener's <italic>D</italic> would be less than the random distribution shown by the histogram.<italic>Empidonax t. extimus</italic> is not supported by published genetic (mtDNA or nuclear AFLPs) data as a distinct entity. This result can be illustrated by plotting <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values within and between subspecies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f05">Figure 5</xref>). The 2 distributions overlap because the subspecies boundary is situated arbitrarily on a cline in allele frequencies. The lack of genetic support was noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2008</xref>:16): &ldquo;&lsqb;T&rsqb;he evidence for a region of intergradation suggests there is little support biologically for the legal necessity of designating a boundary line. As a result, designating the location of a discrete line separating the 2 subspecies cannot be made unambiguously based on genetic data and thus becomes a value judgment dependent on the philosophy of policy makers.&rdquo; I would argue that if the best available data do not support 2 subspecies, the philosophy of policymakers is irrelevant. Furthermore, the exclusion of comparisons of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> with <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> and <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> is a serious omission, because the validity of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> cannot be established without testing whether it is distinctive from all geographically adjacent neighbors. My analysis of all mtDNA sequences in GenBank suggests that none of the subspecies is genetically distinct.Distribution of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values between populations within (black bars) and between (gray bars) subspecies in the Willow Flycatcher (data reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>). The 2 distributions overlap greatly, a result of a gradual transition of genetic variation and a lack of support for distinct subspecies.Some authors, as well as the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-U.S.FishandWildlifeService2">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (2011)</xref>, have concluded that mtDNA alone is insufficient to judge the validity of avian subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink4">Zink et al. 2013</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink3">Zink and Barrowclough (2008)</xref> pointed out that mtDNA has a greater chance than nuclear loci of detecting genetic differences between recently isolated populations and subspecies, owing to the more rapid coalescence time of mtDNA. Thus, in species without geographically structured mtDNA variation, there is a very low likelihood of differentiation at nuclear loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Lee1">Lee and Edwards 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Hung1">Hung et al. 2012</xref>). However, because some exceptions exist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Toews1">Toews and Brelsford 2012</xref>), it is important that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref> analyzed 197 polymorphic nuclear AFLP markers, although low by modern standards, and found no geographic structure that corresponded to subspecies limits.The genus <italic>Empidonax</italic> is known for a high number of sibling species, which are defined as closely related species that lack distinctive morphologies. Hence, one might suggest that analyses of morphology would be uninformative for assessing taxonomic limits below the species level (e.g., subspecies). However, each of the subspecies was described as having differing coloration. For example, <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> is described as having &ldquo;Entire head, neck and upper parts greenish and relatively uniform&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>:508). <italic>Empidonax t. adastus</italic> was described as &ldquo;Head (especially sides of neck) grayish, more contrasted with the back than in <italic>traillii</italic> or <italic>alascnesis</italic>; back duller and more grayish green&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>:510). <italic>Empidonax t. extimus</italic> was considered &ldquo;The palest race of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic>. Adults most closely resemble <italic>adastus</italic>, but are even paler above&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>:513). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips (1948</xref>:510) stated that specimens of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> were &ldquo;practically identical with those of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>.&rdquo; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillips1">Phillips (1948</xref>:514) also remarked that &ldquo;A male in peculiar, retarded plumage from the Gallinas River at Las Vegas, New Mexico, May 23, seems to be typical <italic>extimus</italic>.&rdquo; Presumably, Phillips meant that it was unusual to find a spring male that had not yet molted out of its previous plumage, but he does not describe diagnostic plumage characteristics of the subspecies at different plumage stages, so it is not clear how he ascertained that it was &ldquo;typical.&rdquo;The differences in coloration noted in the subspecies descriptions make relevant the quantitative data on head and back coloration of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref>. Analyses of these color data did not support the subspecies limits, because the coloration grades between them. I predict that a multivariate analysis of standard morphological characters from samples throughout the range (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink1">Zink 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Rising1">Rising 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-McKay1">McKay 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Skalski1">Skalski et al. 2008</xref>) would reinforce the results from the analysis of coloration. The importance of proper sampling is critical. As noted above, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> excluded boundary samples and tested for differences between core areas. The problem with these tests can be appreciated by inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f06">Figure 6</xref>, which is a plot of PC2 values versus latitude, showing a gradual geographic progression. If only samples from 32&ndash;36&deg;N and 45&ndash;49&deg;N were compared (putative core areas), there would likely be a statistically significant difference, whereas inclusion of intermediate samples reveals the biased nature of that inference.Plot of the average score for individuals from 28 sites on principal component 2 (PC2; from analysis of 6 adjusted color variables) versus latitude (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>), showing that if only the geographic extremes were compared, it would give the illusion of statistical significance&mdash;when, in fact, there is gradual variation between sites.It is also a concern that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> obtained data from living specimens that were released, eliminating the possibility of others verifying their measurements. Although analysis of museum specimens is preferable, there are insufficient specimens in collections, and it is not feasible to collect a large series of museum specimens of this endangered bird.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Hatten1">Hatten et al. (2010)</xref> provided a perspective on the habitat of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> but did not make quantitative tests of niche differentiation. I found that niche identities for populations from different areas differ more than expected by chance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f04">Figure 4</xref>A), which is understandable given the large degree of environmental variation that exists across the range. The insignificant background test (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-f04">Figure 4</xref>B) suggests that the species might have a broad ecological tolerance (e.g., plasticity) that allows it to exist across a broad range of environmental conditions without evolving special ecological adaptations, at least in the western portion of the range. Therefore, the available data do not support the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher as being ecologically distinct, although future studies might identify niche dimensions other than climate that could distinguish taxa.The subspecies of Willow Flycatcher, including the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic>E. t. extimus</italic>), were described using traditional methods that involved few specimens scattered from throughout the range, and few characters that were not analyzed quantitatively or multivariately. Although this was typical for the era when most subspecies were described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink5">Zink and Remsen 1986</xref>), use of subspecies for many modern applications requires assessment of their diagnosability. The present study found that molecular, morphological, and ecological data did not support the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher as a distinct subspecies (or DPS). It would seem that the most recent official checklist of subspecies of North American birds (AOU 1957) was prescient in excluding <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. Hence, the Willow Flycatchers of the Southwest represent peripheral populations of an otherwise widespread species that do not merit subspecific recognition and are therefore inappropriately listed as endangered under the ESA.The ESA was designed to protect distinct elements of biodiversity. The U.S. Congress directed the Fish and Wildlife Service to use the ESA &ldquo;sparingly&rdquo; when listing distinct population segments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Bernhardt1">Bernhardt 2008</xref>), and it would follow that listed taxa should be strongly differentiated in at least 1 genetically based character set. The importance of listing only distinct subspecies is revealed by the cost of endangered species conservation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-McCarthy1">McCarthy et al. (2012)</xref> estimated that $1 billion is needed annually to reduce the threat level of globally threatened bird species, obviously an unrealistic level of support. Perhaps, going forward, the null hypothesis for avian subspecies should be that they are not appropriate for listing without a modern assessment of their validity.In a sample of 234 North American songbird species, the average number of subspecies is 3.34 (R. M. Zink personal observation). Hence, a primary question: What attributes would qualify a subspecies for recognition as an evolutionarily significant unit, appropriate for listing under the ESA? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Barrowclough1">Barrowclough (1982)</xref> suggested that a subspecies name should be predictive of concordant patterns of variation in multiple characters. This criterion would eliminate many named subspecies, including the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink2">Zink (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Phillimore1">Phillimore and Owens (2006)</xref> found that, on average, temperate-breeding bird species possess &sim;2 evolutionarily significant units per species, based on patterns of genetic variation at neutral loci (e.g., mtDNA). In my opinion, if the Southwestern Willow flycatcher corresponded to such a unit, it would be qualified for listing, but the available data are not in support. In general, molecular data indicate that the number of listable avian taxa is twice the number of species but considerably less than the number of subspecies.I am concerned that a double standard may exist among conservation biologists involving the nature of data required for listing under the ESA. For example, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has relied on results of mtDNA studies in &gt;80 cases since 1989, although they (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-U.S.FishandWildlifeService2">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2011</xref>) did not accept mtDNA evidence that suggested that the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content> californica</italic>) was not distinct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Zink4">Zink et al. 2013</xref>). I suspect that if there were a pattern of reciprocal monophyly in the mtDNA of Southwestern Willow Flycatchers, many would consider it sufficient to establish the evolutionary-independence requisite for ESA listing. However, this was not the case, and some will claim that investigators have just not studied enough characters to disprove a hypothesis of no distinctiveness. Listing under the ESA requires the best available scientific and commercial data&mdash;which, in the case of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher, are not currently supportive of its status. It is important to recognize that sometimes it is necessary to make a listing or delisting decision and not wait for a new technique that might provide a different answer.It is fair to ponder what new data or analyses might be relevant. I noted above that a thorough study of vocalizations could be useful. I do not think there are enough specimens in museums to conduct a decisive morphological analysis, and although live specimens could be measured and released, it is my opinion that the data cannot be combined with museum specimens, and that all specimens, whether live or in museums, should be measured multiple times by the same observer to minimize and quantify measurement error (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-RojasSoto1">Rojas-Soto 2003</xref>). The other new horizon in geographic variation research involves the use of &ldquo;genomics,&rdquo; or surveys of large numbers of loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-1-76-Lerner1">Lerner and Fleischer 2010</xref>). It remains to be seen whether genomics will reveal patterns of geographic variation that will corroborate the limits of most avian subspecies, or instead will reveal myriad geographic patterns that defy a simple interpretation. It will also be of interest to observe whether genomic studies that fail to support subspecies limits are also considered inadequate in some way. That is, one might wonder what technique will supplant genomics or whether we have indeed achieved the holy grail of molecular methods.I thank E. Paxton for providing color data. J. Klicka, R. Ramey, and A. Jones provided useful comments on the manuscript. S. Lanyon suggested the null hypothesis for listing of subspecies. I thank four anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript. No outside funding was received for this study.