Habitat use and population status of Yellow-billed and Pacific loons in western Alaska, USAAdvances and applications of occupancy modelsModeling co-occurrence of Northern Spotted and Barred owls: Accounting for detection probability differencesGeneral methods for monitoring convergence of iterative simulationsStatus assessment and conservation plan for the Yellow-billed Loon (<italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>)A landscape-scale model of Yellow-billed Loon (<italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>) habitat preferences in northern AlaskaPopulation size and trend of Yellow-billed Loons in northern AlaskaEndangered and threatened wildlife and plants: 12-month finding on a petition to list the Yellow-billed Loon as threatened or endangeredStatus and trends of loon populations summering in Alaska, 1971&ndash;1993Risk of predation and weather events affect nest site selection by sympatric Pacific (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia pacifica</named-content></italic>) and Yellow-billed (<italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>) loons in arctic habitatsOccupancy of Yellow-billed and Pacific loons: Evidence for interspecific competition and habitat mediated co-occurrenceWinBUGS&mdash;A Bayesian modeling framework: Concepts, structure, and extensibilityWas it there? Dealing with imperfect detection for species presence/absence dataInvestigating species co-occurrence patterns when species are detected imperfectlyEstimating site occupancy rates when detection probabilities are less than oneModeling species occurrence dynamics with multiple states and imperfect detectionImproving inferences in population studies of rare species that are detected imperfectlyInvestigating the population dynamics of California Spotted Owls without marked individualsWestern Alaska Yellow-billed Loon survey&mdash;2005Dynamic multistate site occupancy models to evaluate hypotheses relevant to conservation of Golden Eagles in Denali National Park, AlaskaJoint estimation of habitat dynamics and species interactions: Disturbance reduces co-occurrence of non-native predators with an endangered toadImproving occupancy estimation when two types of observational error occur: Non-detection and species misidentificationAddressing challenges when studying mobile or episodic species: Hierarchical Bayes estimation of occupancy and useOccupancy estimation and modeling with multiple states and state uncertaintyInferences about landbird abundance from count data: Recent advances and future directionsYellow-billed LoonYellow-billed Loon, <italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>, breeding chronology and reproductive success in arctic AlaskaPlanning for success: Identifying effective and efficient survey designs for monitoringTwo-species occupancy models: A new parameterization applied to co-occurrence of secretive railsAccounting for incomplete detection: What are we estimating and how might it affect long-term passerine monitoring programs?Variation in foraging behavior and body mass in broods of Emperor Geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chen canagica</named-content></italic>): Evidence for interspecific density dependenceSize and retention of breeding territories of Yellow-billed Loons in Alaska and CanadaInvasion, competitive dominance, and resource use by exotic and native California grassland speciesR2WinBUGS: A package for running WinBUGS from RAlaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act, PUBLIC LAW 96-487-DEC. 2, 1980. 94 STAT. 2371The roles of competition and habitat in the dynamics of populations and species distributionsMulti-species occurrence models to evaluate the effects of conservation and management actionsEffective conservation of sympatric avian populations depends on unbiased estimates of population size, distribution, and habitat use. For populations of Yellow-billed Loons (<italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>) and Pacific Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. pacifica</named-content></italic>) co-occurring in Arctic wetland communities in Alaska, USA, such data are limited and difficult to obtain, hindering population assessments and decision making. The Yellow-billed Loon is also under consideration for additional protections under the Endangered Species Act due to small global population size, specific habitat requirements, and low fecundity, further increasing the need for information at the landscape scale. To help evaluate the population status and habitat use of both species, we used repeated aerial surveys and a dynamic multistate occupancy modeling approach to jointly estimate 1) probability of lake use and 2) probability of use for nesting for Yellow-billed and Pacific loon populations at the landscape scale on the Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern, Alaska, in 2011 and 2013. We also estimated state-specific transition probabilities and degree of interspecific competition to assess population stability and degree of species interactions. We found that probability of site reuse (&phi;<sub>Yellow-billed</sub> &equals; 0.73 &lsqb;0.44&ndash;0.94&rsqb;; &phi;<sub>Pacific</sub> &equals; 0.86 &lsqb;0.72&ndash;0.98&rsqb;) or reuse for nesting (&phi;<sub>Yellow-billed</sub> &equals; 0.72 &lsqb;0.46&ndash;0.97&rsqb;; &phi;<sub>Pacific</sub> &equals; 0.59 &lsqb;0.38&ndash;0.85&rsqb;) in 2013 was high, as was overall use of lakes &gt;7 ha by loons (&gt;80&percnt;). These results suggested that lake habitats may have been saturated, and that populations of both species were stable over the two-year interval between surveys. Our estimates indicated that nesting populations in western Alaska were much larger than previously thought for both Yellow-billed (&sim;2.5 times larger) and Pacific loons (&sim;1.5&ndash;2.0 times larger). Together our results indicate that Arctic wetlands in western Alaska are important for both species and that loon populations in this area warrant additional consideration for conservation.La conservaci&oacute;n efectiva de poblaciones simp&aacute;tricas de aves depende de estimaciones imparciales de tama&ntilde;o poblacional, distribuci&oacute;n, y uso de h&aacute;bitat. Para poblaciones de <italic>Gavia adamsii</italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. pacifica</named-content></italic> que co-ocurren en comunidades de humedal &aacute;rctico en Alaska, datos de este tipo son escasos y dif&iacute;ciles de obtener, lo cual dificulta las evaluaciones poblacionales y la toma de decisiones. <italic>Gavia adamsii</italic> tambien est&aacute; bajo consideraci&oacute;n para protecciones adicionales bajo la Ley de Especies en Peligro de Extinci&oacute;n de los Estados Unidos, debido a su peque&ntilde;a poblaci&oacute;n global, requisitos espec&iacute;ficos de h&aacute;bitat, y baja fecundidad, aumentando la necesidad de obtener informaci&oacute;n a la escala de paisaje. Para asistir en la evaluaci&oacute;n del estado poblacional y uso de h&aacute;bitat por las dos especies, utilizamos muestreos a&eacute;reos repetidos y modelaci&oacute;n din&aacute;mica de ocupancia con m&uacute;ltiples estados para estimar conjuntamente 1) la probabilidad de uso del lago y 2) la probabilidad de uso para nidificaci&oacute;n para poblaciones de <italic>G. adamsii</italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. pacifica</named-content></italic> a la escala de paisaje en la Pen&iacute;nsula Seward y el Cabo Krusenstern, Alaska, en los a&ntilde;os 2011 y 2013. Tambien estimamos probabilidades de transici&oacute;n espec&iacute;fica de cada estado y grado de competencia interespec&iacute;fica para evaluar la estabilidad poblacional y el grado de interacci&oacute;n interespec&iacute;fica. Encontramos que la probabilidad de reutilizaci&oacute;n de sitio (&phi;<sub>G. adamsii</sub> &equals; 0.73 &lsqb;0.44&ndash;0.94&rsqb;; &phi;<sub>G. pacifica</sub> &equals; 0.86 &lsqb;0.72&ndash;0.98&rsqb;) o reutilizaci&oacute;n para nidificaci&oacute;n (&phi;<sub>G. adamsii</sub> &equals; 0.72 &lsqb;0.46&ndash;0.97&rsqb;; &phi;<sub>G. pacifica</sub> &equals; 0.59 &lsqb;0.38&ndash;0.85&rsqb;) en el a&ntilde;o 2013 fue alta, al igual que el uso en general de lagos de &gt;7 ha por ambas especies (&gt;80&percnt;). Estos resultados sugieren que los h&aacute;bitats lacustres podr&iacute;an haber estado saturados y que las poblaciones de ambas especies fueron estables durante el intervalo de dos a&ntilde;os entre muestreos. Nuestras estimaciones indican que las poblaciones nidificadoras en Alaska occidental fueron mucho m&aacute;s grandes que se hab&iacute;a pensado anteriormente, tanto para <italic>G. adamsii</italic> (&sim;2.5 veces m&aacute;s grande) como para <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. pacifica</named-content></italic> (&sim;1.5&ndash;2.0 veces m&aacute;s grande). En conjunto, nuestros resultados indican que los humedales &aacute;rcticos del occidente de Alaska son importantes para ambas especies y que las poblaciones de <italic>G. adamsii</italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. pacifica</named-content></italic> en esta &aacute;rea merecen consideraci&oacute;n adicional para la conservaci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> muestreo a&eacute;reo, ocupancia din&aacute;mica multi-estatal, uso de h&aacute;bitat, conservaci&oacute;n de colimbos, especies raras, simp&aacute;tricoEffective conservation of sympatric avian populations, particularly those of conservation concern, requires reliable estimates of population parameters, habitat preferences, and space use (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Schmutz1">Schmutz and Laing 2002</xref>). Accurate, species-specific measures of abundance, reproductive success, and distribution all are of interest to managers and ecologists, but may be difficult to obtain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Williams1">Williams et al. 2002</xref>). Further, many field methods are too costly or difficult to employ effectively for species that are distributed over large areas, are difficult to detect, or both (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Thompson1">Thompson 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Reynolds1">Reynolds et al. 2011</xref>). The combination of these factors often limits the potential for a cohesive and rigorous assessment of populations of interest, diminishing the chances of successful conservation outcomes.Sympatric populations of Yellow-billed Loons (<italic>Gavia adamsii</italic>) and Pacific Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia pacifica</named-content></italic>) in Arctic Alaska provide a good example of the challenges that can be encountered when attempting to assess the status of widely distributed, low-density populations. The total number of Yellow-billed Loons in Alaska is perhaps a few thousand individuals, occurring primarily on the Arctic Coastal Plain (ACP) and the northwestern Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern in western Alaska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst3">Earnst et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>). In contrast, Pacific Loons are more widely distributed and may number &gt;100,000&ndash;150,000 individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Russell1">Russell 2002</xref>), although densities also tend to be low. Most of the information on these species comes from the ACP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-North1">North 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst2">Earnst et al. 2006</xref>), but other breeding areas in Alaska may also be important for long-term conservation. Recently, concerns about small population size, restricted breeding range, and habitat loss resulted in a decision by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service to designate the Yellow-billed Loon range-wide as warranted for listing under the Endangered Species Act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-FederalRegister1">Federal Register 2009</xref>). Although listing was precluded due to other higher priority actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-FederalRegister1">Federal Register 2009</xref>), species status will be reevaluated in the near future. The importance of loons to ecosystem integrity and conservation suggest that the ongoing conservation decision process in Alaska could benefit from a broader understanding of loon population dynamics and habitat use, particularly in areas outside the ACP.While many factors influence species distribution, an incomplete understanding of the relationships between species and the possible causes of differences in population size may complicate conservation actions. For example, recent work on the ACP has demonstrated that competitive interactions may affect the distribution of breeding loons, and the presence of nesting Yellow-billed Loons on a lake can decrease the probability of Pacific Loons nesting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>). Competition can also confound assessments of population status by influencing detection probability (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Richmond1">Richmond et al. 2010</xref>) and/or the distribution of one or both species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst2">Earnst et al. 2006</xref>). Even if a species is competitively dominant, it can remain rare due to other factors such as limited recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Seabloom1">Seabloom et al. 2003</xref>). Also, the presence of a competitor can result in higher site extinction probabilities when the other species is present and can lead to a weaker apparent relationship between habitat and occupancy rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Yackulic1">Yackulic et al. 2014</xref>). These possible effects of competition suggest that some measure of these interactions is necessary to help understand occupancy dynamics.One difficulty associated with sampling species that are sparsely distributed across large landscapes is attaining sufficient sample sizes for inference under typical budgetary constraints. Site-occupancy methods have been demonstrated to be an effective and logistically feasible sampling approach for broad geographic assessments of population dynamics for a variety of species, partly because individual identification is not required for inference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie3">MacKenzie et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">2006</xref>). These approaches have been extended to include multiple occupancy states, allowing insights into patterns of habitat occupancy and use, as well as reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Nichols1">Nichols et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie5">MacKenzie et al. 2009</xref>). Further extensions allow estimation of the probability of transitioning among states (e.g., from occupied to breeding) between years, and, if certain assumptions are met, estimates of the strength of competitive interactions between species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey1">2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie7">MacKenzie et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Miller1">Miller et al. 2012</xref>). Together, these estimates can offer a detailed understanding of habitat occupancy, breeding probability, and population equilibrium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Martin1">Martin et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie7">MacKenzie et al. 2012</xref>), providing coherent in-depth information on population dynamics.Loon populations have been monitored for several decades in Alaska, primarily through the use of aerial index surveys (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst3">Earnst et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mallek1">Mallek et al. 2006</xref>). These surveys have provided useful information on broad population trends, but more rigorous estimates of loon population dynamics and habitat use are needed to inform current and future conservation decisions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-FederalRegister1">Federal Register 2009</xref>). We conducted intensive aerial surveys of closed-basin lakes on the northwestern Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern in western Alaska in 2011 and 2013, recording all sightings of loons and loon nests. We used a repeated survey design to address incomplete detection and a dynamic multistate occupancy approach for analysis, with the goal of improving population assessments and future conservation decisions for Yellow-billed and Pacific loons. Our primary objectives were to: 1) estimate the probability of lake use and nesting for both Pacific and Yellow-billed loons, 2) quantify site reuse and transition probabilities among occupancy states between 2011 and 2013 for both species, to provide measures of habitat importance and population trajectory, and 3) evaluate a dynamic multistate occupancy modeling approach as a tool for loon population assessment at the landscape scale.Our study area included approximately 13,572 km<sup>2</sup> of potential loon habitat on the northwestern Seward Peninsula and the area in and around Cape Krusenstern National Monument in western Alaska (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f01">Figure 1</xref>). This area supports all five North American loon species, but we focused our analyses on Yellow-billed and Pacific loons. For this study, we lumped Arctic (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia arctica</named-content></italic>) and Pacific loons for analysis because of the difficulty of distinguishing the two species from the air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>). These two species have similar ecological requirements and are likely to interact with Yellow-billed Loons in a similar manner, and hereafter we use the term Pacific Loon to refer to both Arctic and Pacific loons.Location of the study area on the northwestern coast of the Seward Peninsula, Alaska, USA. Squares indicate sampled plots, hatched lines indicate the study area boundary, and shaded areas indicate U.S. National Park Service units for Bering Land Bridge National Preserve and Cape Krusenstern National Monument.We used a spatial survey design developed by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mallek1">Mallek et al. 2006</xref>), which consisted of 24 12 km &times; 12 km plots centered on randomly selected points throughout the study area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Plot centers were required to be within the study area boundaries, and all plot edges were separated by &gt;2 km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mallek1">Mallek et al. 2006</xref>). The minimum lake size of 7 ha was based on prior work on the ACP which suggested that approximately 98&percnt; of all Yellow-billed Loons detected occurred on lakes &gt;10 ha (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst2">Earnst et al. 2006</xref>). The study area contained 1,291 lakes &gt;7 ha in size and the 24 selected plots contained approximately 35&percnt; of these lakes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 447). In our sample, median lake area was 14.2 ha, mean area was 42 ha (SD &equals; 178.5), and the largest lake was 2,004 ha. The median perimeter length was 1.9 km, the mean was 2.5 km (SD &equals; 1.8), and the longest perimeter in our sample was 13.2 km. Surveys were conducted in late June in 2011 and 2013, at a time when most breeding loons were expected to have constructed nests, but before hatching occurred at nests initiated earlier in the season.We used a repeated sampling aerial survey approach to search all lakes &gt;7 ha in each plot twice within a one-week survey period in 2011 and 2013. While our 2-yr survey interval does not directly track the annual biological cycle of loons, biennial surveys were determined to be a reasonable compromise between more detailed annual information and sustainable project cost for the long-term loon monitoring program going forward. Surveys were conducted from a float-equipped tandem aircraft (e.g., Aviat Husky) flown at &sim;45&ndash;60 m above ground level at &sim;174 km hr<sup>&minus;1</sup>. We circled each lake perimeter and surface, multiple times if necessary, until the entire lake area had been searched for loons and nests. For each lake, we recorded whether a loon was detected, species, number of loons, and nest location if a nest was detected. Most plots were resurveyed within &sim;4&ndash;48 hr by a second team (consisting of a different pilot and observer) to provide an independent resurvey of the area.We assumed that each lake could exist in one of three states for each species: unused, used, and used for nesting. Unused lakes were defined as lakes with no loon occurring on the water or shoreline during the survey period. Lakes were considered to be used if one or more loons occurred on the water or shoreline during the survey period. Lakes were considered used for nesting if a loon nest was present in close association with an adult loon. Multiple nests of a single species occurred on the same lake very rarely, so we expected the estimated number of lakes used for nesting to approximate nest abundance. Because our repeated visits were conducted up to 2 days apart, population closure could not be assumed for use (without nesting) because some loons may not have been available for detection during both surveys due to movement. While this violation of the assumption of closure during repeated surveys would result in biased estimates of occupancy probability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>), our estimates represent the probability that a lake was &lsquo;used' by loons during the survey period each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mordecai1">Mordecai et al. 2011</xref>). We preferred this interpretation because it provided information on how each species occurred within the landscape during the survey, rather than an estimate of occupancy at a single point in time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Royle1">Royle and Dorazio 2008</xref>:104&ndash;105). By estimating use, we acknowledged that some loons likely moved among lakes for foraging or prospecting for nest sites. This broadened the scope of inference from the probability that a given lake was occupied at a single point in time to the probability that it was used over the survey period.We developed a dynamic, multistate occupancy model for Pacific and Yellow-billed loons, describing the probability of each sampled lake existing in one of the three states for each species as defined above: unused, used, or used for nesting (<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="10.1650_CONDOR-14-28.1.s1.txt" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary Material</inline-supplementary-material>). We employed aspects of multispecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie2">MacKenzie et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>) and multistate occupancy models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie5">MacKenzie et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Kery1">Kery and Schaub 2012</xref>) to investigate both species' occurrence dynamics and competitive interactions over two sampling years, 2011 and 2013. We used the parameterization of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Kery1">Kery and Schaub (2012)</xref> for a single-season multistate occupancy model, extended to accommodate multiple seasons and species. Similar approaches have been used to quantify variation in detection probabilities for co-occurring species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>), and for predator&ndash;prey and habitat interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Miller1">Miller et al. 2012</xref>). However, due to limited sample sizes, we were prohibited from applying these more complex models to more fully investigate patterns of co-occurrence. If competitive interactions influence both detection and occupancy state (Yellow-billed Loons are competitively dominant; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst1">Earnst 2004</xref>), our simplified approach could produce biased estimates. We expect any bias to be limited based on the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. (2014b)</xref> and our experience with aerial survey techniques for loons.We expected that detection of lake use would vary by year, but assumed that both species had similar probabilities of detection during aerial surveys due to their large body sizes, distinctive coloration, and similar behaviors. Exploratory analyses confirmed the validity of this assumption. Probability of detecting use has a different definition than probability of detecting occupancy because the latter is conditional on an individual being present and available for sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Nichols2">Nichols et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Schmidt1">Schmidt et al. 2013</xref>). In our case, detection probability for use also included the probability that an individual was present (i.e. on the lake during a visit) and available (i.e. above water) for sampling. We also expected that the probability of detecting use would be lower in 2013 because some of the pilots were inexperienced with loon surveys. Due to the low numbers of nests in general, we assumed that the probability of detecting a nest was constant among years and species to improve estimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie6">MacKenzie et al. 2005</xref>). We often used loon behavior and presence as an aid for detecting nests, so we expected that most of the variability in detection between years would be related to the detection of individuals (i.e. use). Exploratory analysis and the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. (2014b)</xref> suggested that the probability of detecting a nest was very similar among years, supporting our assumption.To extend the basic multistate model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Kery1">Kery and Schaub (2012)</xref> to accommodate multiple species and multiple seasons, we created separate detection and multistate occupancy submodels for each species. We assumed that there were no false positives in the data. That is, that the probability of detecting use on an unused lake or detecting use for nesting on a lake that was only used was equal to 0. The probability of detecting a used lake as unused was estimated as<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. The probabilities of detecting a lake as unused<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm08"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm08.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, used<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm09"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm09.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, or used for nesting<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm10"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm10.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, given that the true state was used for nesting, were constrained to sum to one. Detection parameters were shared between the two species (e.g.,<inline-formula id="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm11"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-116-3-483-ilm11.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> was not species-specific), but occupancy parameters were estimated separately.We used program R version 2.14.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>) to fit models with WinBUGS 1.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Lunn1">Lunn et al. 2000</xref>) using the R2WinBUGS package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Sturtz1">Sturtz et al. 2005</xref>). We used diffuse priors for all parameters. We ran two Markov Chains for 10,000 iterations, discarding the initial 2,500 from each as burn-in, thinned the values by three, and retained the remaining values for inference on the posterior distribution for each parameter. We visually inspected chains for convergence, in addition to verifying that the Gelman-Rubin diagnostic was &lt;1.1 for all monitored parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Brooks1">Brooks and Gelman 1998</xref>). Derived parameters (i.e. measures of the SIF and estimates of the probability of transitioning from one state to another) were directly calculated during each update of the sampler, which allowed us to produce posterior distributions for all parameters. Estimates are presented as means with 95&percnt; credible intervals (CrI; i.e. the 0.025<sup>th</sup> and 0.975<sup>th</sup> percentiles of the posterior).We conducted surveys from June 21&ndash;28, 2011, and June 22&ndash;29, 2013. We surveyed 24 plots in 2011, 17 of which were covered by both observer teams. In 2013 we surveyed 16 plots, 15 of which were covered by both teams. Pacific Loons were more likely to use lakes in our study area than Yellow-billed Loons, and the probability of lake use for nesting by Pacific Loons was also much higher than that of Yellow-billed Loons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Overall, we estimated that &sim;67&percnt; of surveyed lakes were utilized (i.e. either used or used for nesting) by Pacific Loons, while approximately 33&percnt; of lakes were utilized by Yellow-billed Loons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f02">Figure 2</xref>). We estimated that Yellow-billed Loons used 163 (95&percnt; CrI: 84&ndash;235) of the 1,291 lakes in 2011 and 207 (95&percnt; CrI: 125&ndash;287) in 2013, with an additional 225 (95&percnt; CrI: 154&ndash;312) and 205 (95&percnt; CrI: 143&ndash;279) used for nesting in 2011 and 2013, respectively. Pacific Loons were estimated to have used 444 (95&percnt; CrI: 310&ndash;556) lakes in 2011 and 500 (95&percnt; CrI: 369&ndash;618) in 2013, with an additional 433 (95&percnt; CrI: 329&ndash;572) and 367 (95&percnt; CrI: 267&ndash;487) having been used for nesting in each year, respectively. Very few lakes (&lt;3 annually) were observed to contain more than one nest of a given species, so the estimated number of lakes containing nests for each species approximated the nesting populations for lakes &gt;7 ha in the study area.Probability of a lake occurring (&Psi;<sup>&lsqb;<italic>k</italic>&rsqb;</sup>) in each of <italic>k</italic> occupancy states (unused, used, used for nesting) in 2011 (gray points) and 2013 (black points) for Pacific Loons (diamonds), Yellow-billed Loons (triangles), and both species simultaneously (circles) on the northwestern Seward Peninsula, Alaska, USA. Error bars represent 95&percnt; credible intervals.Yellow-billed Loon probability of reuse of individual lakes in 2013 was &gt;0.70 for both use and use for nesting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f03">Figure 3</xref>), suggesting that either site fidelity or the attractiveness of specific lakes was high over the two-year interval between surveys. Overall probability of reuse of individual lakes by Pacific Loons was also high (0.86), with some limited evidence that probability of reuse of lakes for nesting may have been lower (0.59) than that of Yellow-billed Loons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The probability of transitioning from lake used for nesting to unused lake by either species was very low (0.04), further indicating consistent use of specific habitats. Despite some transitions between states, the estimated state-specific occupancy probabilities did not change between 2011 and 2013 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f02">Figure 2</xref>), suggesting that both habitat use and nesting were stable for both species over the three-year study period. The probability of use and/or use for nesting of a lake by at least one of the species in each year was 0.83, indicating that most of the available lakes &gt;7 ha in size were used by at least one of the two species in each year during the breeding season.Estimated transition probabilities among occupancy states (unused &lsqb;1&rsqb;, used &lsqb;2&rsqb;, and used for nesting &lsqb;3&rsqb;) between 2011 and 2013 for Pacific Loons (diamonds) and Yellow-billed Loons (triangles) on the northwestern Seward Peninsula, Alaska, USA. Error bars represent 95&percnt; credible intervals.The point estimates for all SIFs were &lt;1, suggesting a reduction in use by Pacific Loons of lakes that were also used by Yellow-billed Loons or contained a Yellow-billed Loon nest, although the 95&percnt; credible intervals indicated uncertainty in the magnitude of the competitive exclusion under most state combinations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The presence of nesting Yellow-billed Loons appeared to reduce Pacific Loon use and nesting more than use by Yellow-billed Loons without nesting, and the probability of Pacific Loon nesting was reduced if a Yellow-billed Loon nest was present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The probability of detecting a loon on a used lake was higher in 2011 (0.74; 95&percnt; CrI: 0.65&ndash;0.82) than in 2013 (0.55; 95&percnt; CrI: 0.44&ndash;0.65), and the probability of detecting a nest in either year (0.35; 95&percnt; CrI: 0.27&ndash;0.43) was much lower than the probability of detecting a loon, as expected. Our results suggested that Yellow-billed Loons may use lakes with smaller perimeters than Pacific Loons (&beta;<italic><sub>perimYL</sub></italic> &equals; &minus;0.08, 95&percnt; CrI: &minus;0.57, 0.37; versus &beta;<italic><sub>perimPL</sub></italic> &equals; 0.22, 95&percnt; CrI: &minus;0.18, 0.69), but both estimates overlapped 0 considerably. Lake area did not appear to be related to probability of use for either species. The estimated precision of the random effects terms suggested that use varied among plots (&tau;<sub>YL</sub> = 1.3, &tau;<sub>PL</sub> = 2.8).Estimated species interaction factors for used lakes and lakes used for nesting in 2011 (gray points) and 2013 (black points) for Pacific Loons (P) and Yellow-billed Loons (Y) on the northwestern Seward Peninsula, Alaska, USA. Values &lt;1 (dotted line) indicate avoidance of Yellow-billed Loons by Pacific Loons. Error bars represent 95&percnt; credible intervals.We used dynamic multistate occupancy modeling techniques to estimate probabilities of habitat use, nesting, state-specific transitions over the two-year survey period, and competitive interactions for both Yellow-billed and Pacific loons at the landscape scale in western Alaska. Our results revealed that a majority of lakes in the study area were utilized by loons during late June. Low transition rates between 2011 and 2013 for both species indicated that specific lakes were consistently reused over multiple years. In addition, estimated nesting populations of both species in our study area were much larger than previously thought. While we found evidence for competitive exclusion of Pacific Loons by Yellow-billed Loons, the magnitude of exclusion may be lower than on the ACP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>), possibly reflecting differences in foraging habitats (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Schmutz2">Schmutz et al. 2014</xref>). The sampling and analytical approaches that we used provided new information about loon populations in western Alaska that will be useful for future conservation efforts. Overall, our results suggest that the Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern area may support significant populations of both species, warranting additional consideration for conservation.As we expected, the probabilities of Yellow-billed Loon lake use and use for nesting were much lower than those of Pacific Loons in our study area. Low transition probabilities among states suggested that nesting lakes are consistently reused (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-North2">North and Ryan 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst1">Earnst 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes1">Haynes et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">2014b</xref>). Our estimates of the probabilities of lake use for nesting are very similar to those produced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. (2014b)</xref> for a portion of the ACP, with some of the highest observed densities of both species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst3">Earnst et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>). After accounting for incomplete detection, we estimated that the overall nesting population of both species on the Seward Peninsula was much larger than that found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mallek1">Mallek et al. (2006)</xref>. Although we could not estimate the total number of individuals, the overall estimated number of used lakes was similar to the total population estimate by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mallek1">Mallek et al. (2006)</xref>, suggesting that previous work has likely underestimated population size. The bias inherent in index surveys for loons confirmed by our results and by those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. (2014b)</xref> suggests that statewide populations of both Yellow-billed and Pacific loons may be much larger than previously thought, particularly estimates of nesting pairs. Our high nesting-rate estimates, combined with similar levels of use without nesting, indicate that habitats on the northwestern Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern are likely to be much more important for the overall conservation of Yellow-billed Loons in Alaska than previously realized. The additional protections afforded to loon populations and breeding habitats on U.S. National Park Service lands in western Alaska (U.S. Congress 1980) may become more important for the conservation of the species in the future due to projected resource development on the ACP. Further, unlike Yellow-billed Loons in other areas, loons on the northwestern Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern frequently use saltwater habitats, presumably for feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Schmutz2">Schmutz et al. 2014</xref>). Recent growth in oil exploration and vessel traffic along the western coast of Alaska could expose a majority of the breeding population to any related impacts that may occur in these areas (e.g., oil spills).Our estimates of lake use, as opposed to occupancy, also provide additional information on habitat use that cannot be acquired from a single visit survey. Because our surveys were separated in time, we expected that loons might have moved among lakes for foraging or prospecting for future nest sites. Therefore, our estimates were interpreted as the probability that a species used a site during the survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Mordecai1">Mordecai et al. 2011</xref>). In the context of loon ecology and conservation, the proportion of sites occupied by loons during a single point in time may be of less interest than the proportion of sites used during the survey period. For example, if loons require multiple lakes for foraging, it is important to capture these movements among lakes when assessing habitat use. Potential movement and the collection of detection vs. nondetection data precluded direct interpretation of population size from estimates of use. On the other hand, nests are stationary and, because lakes containing &gt;1 nest per species were very rare, our estimates of nesting could be used to approximate nest abundance for those nests surviving during the survey period.For nesting loons, the relatively short time period between surveys approximately met the closure assumption because nest locations were fixed and would have been available for detection during the entire survey period. While some nests may have been initiated or failed during the &le;2-day resurvey interval, we expected these gains and losses to be minimal relative to survey timing and the length of the breeding season. Because our surveys were conducted late in the nesting period, some proportion of initiated nests likely failed prior to our surveys. Therefore, our estimates of the probability of a lake being used for nesting necessarily included some unknown component of nest initiation and survival probability prior to our surveys. Correspondingly, estimates of used lakes included those used by loons after a failed nesting attempt. In our study area, multiple nests of either species on the same lake were rare, so that estimates of the number of sites used for nesting approximated nest abundance (for lakes &gt;7 ha) as well as the number of breeding pairs attending nests in late June each year for each species.In addition to assessing basic habitat use, we found some evidence of reduced competitive exclusion by nesting loons in the Seward Peninsula&ndash;Cape Krusenstern population (annual point estimate of SIF &equals; 0.55 and 0.66 in 2011 and 2013, respectively) as compared with the ACP (SIF &equals; 0.31; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>). This apparent difference could indicate a reduction in competition for food resources in lakes used for nesting relative to the ACP due to the use of ocean resources by Yellow-billed Loons in our study area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Schmutz2">Schmutz et al. 2014</xref>). On the ACP, Yellow-billed Loons typically forage in lakes used for nesting, likely increasing the potential for competitive behavior. We found that the direction of the point estimates of the SIFs were in the expected direction, with the least amount of apparent exclusion for use (without nesting) by both species, and the strongest evidence for competitive exclusion when Yellow-billed Loon nests were present. However, only the nest:nest SIF estimate did not include 0, suggesting that use alone may not foster competitive exclusion. Additional years of data and the application of models directly incorporating co-occurrence and codetection (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Miller1">Miller et al. 2012</xref>) will likely be necessary to fully understand the effects of competition on the occupancy dynamics of these two species in our study area.In our study area we found little support for lake characteristics as explanatory variables for use, in contrast to work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes1">Haynes et al. (2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">2014b</xref>), although apparent covariate effects can be weakened by competitive interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Yackulic1">Yackulic et al. 2014</xref>) and small sample sizes. On the ACP, lake size and perimeter were found to be positive, significant predictors of Yellow-billed Loon presence, with larger lake sizes likely supplying dependable fish resources and lake complexity providing ideal brood-rearing sites and fish habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Earnst2">Earnst et al. 2006</xref>). A reduced range of lake sizes in our study area may have also affected our ability to detect general habitat relationships, and additional data may be required to fully assess potential habitat associations in the northwestern Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern study area.Our results agree with past work showing that dynamic occupancy approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie4">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Bailey2">Bailey et al. 2009</xref>) and their multistate extensions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Martin1">Martin et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Miller1">Miller et al. 2012</xref>) provide information that can help us to understand key population parameters, even if the parameters cannot be estimated directly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie6">MacKenzie et al. 2005</xref>). For example, size of the local nonbreeding loon population using lake habitats is likely the product of longer-term productivity and survival prior to breeding. If so, then temporal changes in lake use could indicate multiyear changes in one or both of these parameters, or perhaps declines in habitat suitability. Similarly, decreased survival rates of breeding pairs may result in increased transition probabilities for lakes being used for nesting. For Yellow-billed Loons in particular, a previous lack of population-level information hampered a detailed status assessment for conservation decision making.Our results also demonstrate the benefit of combining information about both rare and common species, especially when data for rare species are difficult to obtain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Royle1">Royle and Dorazio 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Zipkin1">Zipkin et al. 2010</xref>). Yellow-billed Loons were relatively uncommon, and detections of nests in particular were infrequent. If we had considered each species separately, there would have been much less data with which to estimate detection probability, leading to less precise estimates of probabilities of lake use and nesting. Loon behavior and survey methodology (i.e. aerial lake-circling) were consistent in our study, suggesting that the probabilities of detecting loons and nests were similar for both species (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Haynes2">Haynes et al. 2014b</xref>). Assuming that the detection process was the same for both species allowed joint estimation of detection probabilities, allowing more precise estimates of the occupancy state of each lake for each species. Although we are confident that Yellow-billed and Pacific loons were not misidentified from the air due to distinctive head and neck colorations and profiles, if misidentification had occurred, substantial bias could have resulted. This should be taken into consideration if misidentification error is expected to be an issue in other surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-483-Miller2">Miller et al. 2011</xref>).As managers consider conservation options for loons in general, and Yellow-billed Loons in particular, our results suggest that the Seward Peninsula and Cape Krusenstern populations should receive more attention than in the past, despite their smaller sizes relative to the ACP population. Future changes in transition probabilities could be used to assess long-term population changes or to identify local impacts of development on breeding loons in the area. Yellow-billed Loons may also be useful as an indicator in the case of an oil spill along the coast, due to their tendency to forage in salt water. Changes in use parameters for freshwater lake habitats after a major event like oiling could be used to help quantify the effects on populations. Slight modifications of the survey protocol to include all lake sizes and additional waterbird species would provide detailed community-level information and further sensitivity to environmental change at little additional cost.We thank T. Haynes, J. Lawler, M. Lindberg, C. McIntyre, D. Rizzolo, J. Schmutz, and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on a previous version of this manuscript. We also thank pilots and observers N. Guldager and T. Zeller of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and R. Cebulski, E. Sieh, and T. Whitesell of the U.S. National Park Service. Funding for this work was provided by the U.S. National Park Service's Inventory and Monitoring program through the Arctic Network. The use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. government.