Effects of weather variation on the timing and success of breeding in two cavity-nesting species in a subtropical montane forest in TaiwanUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionBreeding biology of passerines in a subtropical montane forest in northwestern ArgentinaTemperature and foraging success of Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> hunting for spidersUsing video monitoring to assess the accuracy of nest fate and nest productivity estimates by field observationDarwin's finches (<italic>Geospiza</italic>) on Isla Daphne Major, Galapagos: Breeding and feeding ecology in a climatically variable environmentAvian reproductive failure in response to an extreme climate eventThe effect of climate change on the correlation between avian life-history traitsLarge-scale geographical variation confirms that climate change causes birds to lay earlierVariation in laying date and clutch size: The Everglades environment and the endangered Cape Sable Seaside Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus maritimus</named-content> mirabilis</italic>)Effects of elevated temperature on multi-species interactions: The case of pedunculate oak, winter moth and titsImpacts of vegetation onset time on the net primary productivity in a mountainous island in Pacific AsiaSpring heavy rain events in Taiwan during warm episodes and the associated large-scale conditionsPredators of Greater Sage-Grouse nests identified by video monitoringHow Great Tits maintain synchronization of their hatch date with food supply in response to long-term variability in temperatureMixed-grass prairie passerines exhibit weak and variable responses to patch sizeControl of the annual cycle in birds: Endocrine constraints and plasticity in response to ecological variabilityAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalGenetic diversity increases regional variation in phenological dates in response to climate changeBreeding dates and reproductive performanceEffects of climate change on timing of breeding and reproductive successGenetics and extinctionSpring phenology delays in an insular subtropical songbird: Is response to climate change constrained by population size?Time-specific patterns of nest survival for ducks and passerines breeding in North DakotaTime-specific variation in passerine nest survival: New insights into old questionsClimate impacts on Mediterranean Blue Tit survival: An investigation across seasons and spatial scalesClimate change affects breeding of Reed Warblers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Acrocephalus scirpaceus</named-content></italic>Does food supplementation really enhance productivity of breeding birds?Timing of breeding in tropical birds: Mechanism and evolutionary implicationsA Neotropical forest bird can measure the slight changes in tropical photoperiodDecline in the frequency and benefits of multiple brooding in Great Tits as a consequence of a changing environmentLarge-scale circulation patterns associated with heavy spring rain events over Taiwan in strong ENSO and non-ENSO yearsMonitoring breeding bird populations in TaiwanA matter of timingNest predation increases with parental activity: Separating nest site and parental activity effectsRelative importance of environmental variables in determining the growth of nestling Tree Swallows <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>Temperature and egg-laying trendsRisks and rewards of nest defence by parent birdsProximate and ultimate aspects of phenotypic plasticity in timing of Great Tit breeding in a heterogeneous environmentNest-site selection and nest survival of Lewis's Woodpecker in aspen riparian woodlandsOffspring age and nest defence: Test of the feedback hypothesis in the Meadow PipitThe timing of birds' breeding seasonsEffects of extreme weather on reproductive success in a temperate-breeding songbirdTropical avian phenology in relation to abundance and exploitation of food resourcesApproximating variance of demographic parameters using the delta method: A reference for avian biologistsThe importance of rainfall to a cavity-nesting speciesActivity patterns of parent Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> feeding their young during rainfallModeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SASCorrecting nest-success estimates for observer effects: Maximum likelihood estimates of daily survival rates with reduced biasReproductive responses of birds to experimental food supplementation: A meta-analysisClimate variation and regional gradients in population dynamics of two hole-nesting passerinesSpring phenology does not affect timing of reproduction in the Great Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>)Food supplementation and timing of reproduction: Does the responsiveness to supplementary information vary with latitude?The effects of climate change on tropical birdsMaking meaningful estimates of nest survival with model-based methodsNestling growth and mortality of Pied Flycatchers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic> in relation to weather and breeding effortWeather effects on avian breeding performance and implications of climate changeAvian phenology: Climate change and constraints on breedingAnnual fecundity of a Neotropical bird during years of high and low rainfallParental energy expenditure during brood rearing in the Great Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) in relation to body mass, temperature, food availability and clutch sizeSynchronisation of pre-imaginal development and reproductive success in the winter moth, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Operophtera brumata</named-content></italic> LReversal of breeding season by lowland birds at higher altitudes in western CameroonSelection for the timing of Great Tit breeding in relation to caterpillar growth and temperatureVariable responses to large-scale climate change in European <italic>Parus</italic> populationsGlobal climate change leads to mistimed avian reproductionShifts in caterpillar biomass phenology due to climate change and its impact on the breeding biology of an insectivorous birdEcological responses to recent climate changeNest soaking in natural holes&mdash;A serious cause of breeding failure?Characteristics of predators and offspring influence nest defense by Arctic and Common ternsSeasonality of reproduction in a Neotropical rain forest birdPredicting the effects of climate change on avian life-history traitsSeasonal fluctuations in rainfall, food and abundance of tropical insectsSeasonal variation of the rainfall over TaiwanBiological processes at low latitudes are often associated with seasonal rainfall, while those at high altitudes are also influenced by low temperature and high humidity. Thus, the breeding phenology of montane species at low latitudes requires clarification. We monitored the timing of nesting for two species of secondary cavity-nesting passerine, the Green-backed Tit (<italic>Parus monticolus</italic>) and the Rufous-faced Warbler (<italic>Abroscopus albogularis</italic>), in a montane cloud forest in subtropical Taiwan between 2010 and 2014. To determine the effects of weather and extreme events on nesting success, we used program MARK to model daily nest survival rate as a function of weather variables. The results showed that March temperatures, but not spring (February&ndash;March) rainfall, affected the mean laying date of Green-backed Tits. Females shifted their laying dates to lay earlier in response to earlier warm spring weather. The Rufous-faced Warbler exhibited a similar but weaker relationship between March temperature and mean laying date. Spring temperature and rainfall did not affect the length of the laying season of either species. The reduction in the limiting effect of spring rainfall on biological processes may be attributable to the perhumid climate of the study area. Both species were negatively affected by heavy seasonal rainfall during the nesting period. Nest survival declined under extremely heavy rainfall (daily precipitation &gt;20 mm), but did not vary linearly or nonlinearly with daily precipitation levels. The daily survival rate of Green-backed Tits was further reduced by cold weather combined with heavy rain. Our results show that the breeding densities of both species declined across the 5-yr study period, indicating that the negative effects of adverse weather may contribute to further decreases in annual productivity, which would accelerate population declines at the current rate of climate change.Los procesos biol&oacute;gicos en las latitudes bajas est&aacute;n usualmente asociados con las precipitaciones estacionales, mientras que en las latitudes altas tambi&eacute;n est&aacute;n influenciados por la baja temperatura y la alta humedad. De este modo, la fenolog&iacute;a reproductiva de las especies montanas en las latitudes bajas requiere ser clarificada. Monitoreamos la &eacute;poca reproductiva de dos especies paserinas que anidan en cavidades secundarias, <italic>Parus monticolus</italic> y <italic>Abroscopus albogularis</italic>, en un bosque nublado montano del &aacute;rea subtropical de Taiw&aacute;n entre 2010 y 2014. Para determinar los efectos del tiempo y de los eventos extremos en el &eacute;xito reproductivo, empleamos el programa MARK para modelar la tasa de supervivencia diaria del nido como una funci&oacute;n de las variables del tiempo. Los resultados mostraron que las temperaturas de marzo, pero no las lluvias de primavera (febrero-marzo), afectaron la fecha promedio de puesta para <italic>P. monticolus</italic>. Las hembras desplazaron la puesta hacia fechas m&aacute;s tempranas en respuesta a la presencia m&aacute;s temprana de tiempo primaveral caluroso. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. albogularis</named-content></italic> mostr&oacute; una relaci&oacute;n similar pero menos marcada entre la temperatura de marzo y la fecha promedio de puesta. La temperatura y la precipitaci&oacute;n de primavera no afectaron la duraci&oacute;n de la estaci&oacute;n de puesta en ninguna de las especies. La reducci&oacute;n del efecto limitante de las precipitaciones de primavera en los procesos biol&oacute;gicos puede ser atribuida al clima perh&uacute;medo del &aacute;rea de estudio. Ambas especies fueron negativamente afectadas por las fuertes precipitaciones estacionales durante el per&iacute;odo reproductivo. La supervivencia del nido disminuy&oacute; con las precipitaciones extremas (precipitaci&oacute;n diaria &gt;20 mm), pero no vari&oacute; de modo lineal o no lineal con los niveles diarios de precipitaci&oacute;n. La tasa de supervivencia diaria de <italic>P. monticolus</italic> se redujo adicionalmente debido al tiempo fr&iacute;o combinado con fuertes precipitaciones. Nuestros resultados muestran que los destinos reproductivos de ambas especies disminuyeron a lo largo del per&iacute;odo de 5 a&ntilde;os, indicando que los efectos negativos del tiempo adverso pueden contribuir a una mayor disminuci&oacute;n en la productividad anual, lo que acelerar&iacute;a la disminuci&oacute;n poblacional a la tasa actual de cambio clim&aacute;tico.<italic>Palabras clave: Abroscopus albogularis</italic>, <italic>Parus monticolus</italic>, precipitaci&oacute;n estacional, supervivencia del nido, temperatura de primaveraClimate change is widely recognized as one of the most serious and widespread threats to biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-IPCCIntergovernmentalPanelonClimateChange1">IPCC 2007</xref>). To implement the appropriate management, conservation, or mitigation actions for a declining species, it is first important to elucidate how populations respond to variations in weather and to determine the demographic mechanisms that link weather variations with population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Walther1">Walther et al. 2002</xref>). Breeding biology is an important and frequently used tool in investigations of bird population dynamics. Many studies have demonstrated that climate change is affecting the onset of avian reproduction and nest survival, either directly through increases in extreme weather events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Bolger1">Bolger et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Pipoly1">Pipoly et al. 2013</xref>), or indirectly through changes in interspecies interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Visser2">Visser et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Visser3">2006</xref>). However, most evidence of this phenomenon has been obtained from studies conducted in temperate regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn2">Dunn and Winkler 2010</xref>), with publications about the impact of climate change on the breeding ecology of tropical and subtropical passerines remaining scarce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Gordo1">Gordo and Doi 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Sekercioglu1">&Scedil;ekercio&gbreve;lu et al. 2012</xref>). The causes and effects of climate change differ greatly across locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Sather1">S&aelig;ther et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Visser1">Visser et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Both2">Both et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Lyon1">Lyon et al. 2008</xref>). Moreover, some ecosystems and species appear to be particularly vulnerable to climate change. Montane species, for example, may be vulnerable because they are generally sedentary, often endemic species isolated on mountains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Sekercioglu1">&Scedil;ekercio&gbreve;lu et al. 2012</xref>). Therefore, it is important to determine the factors that govern the productivity of highly vulnerable, but poorly studied, species in the tropics and subtropics.Taiwan is a high-relief island that encompasses both tropical and subtropical climatic zones (22&deg;&ndash;26&deg;N), and experiences highly seasonal rainfall that is a result of the summer southwest monsoon and the winter northeast monsoon and is modified by the local topography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Yen1">Yen and Chen 2000</xref>). In contrast, the transition period between the two monsoon seasons (around February to March) is relatively dry. Rainfall during this period has been termed &ldquo;spring rainfall&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chen1">Chen et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. 2013</xref>, this study) and is subject to significant interannual variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chen1">Chen et al. 2003</xref>). Spring rainfall is important because it, and not summer monsoon rain, governs the vegetation phenology and net primary productivity for the entire island (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. 2013</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. (2013)</xref> suggested that wetter springs may trigger earlier onset of vegetation growth and a longer growing season, with higher annual net primary productivity, and vice versa. However, it remains unclear whether spring rainfall levels also affect the phenology and productivity of higher trophic levels through food-mediated processes. For most breeding birds, changes in day length (photoperiod) are the primary cue for gonadal maturation and the release of hormones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dawson1">Dawson 2008</xref>). However, environmental cues, such as rainfall and air temperature, provide supplementary cues that increase the precision of timing decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wikelski1">Wikelski et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dawson1">Dawson 2008</xref>). In some tropical and subtropical regions, seasonal rainfall is associated with increased food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wolda1">Wolda 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 1992</xref>) and consequently triggers the onset of breeding activity and increases avian productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Boag1">Boag and Grant 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wikelski1">Wikelski et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Boulton1">Boulton et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Styrsky1">Styrsky and Brawn 2011</xref>). In comparison, most birds inhabiting high-latitude regions with pronounced seasonal temperature fluctuations fine-tune their laying date based on increasing spring temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dawson1">Dawson 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn2">Dunn and Winkler 2010</xref>). Low temperatures in early spring delay the onset of breeding because female birds must allocate more energy to thermoregulation than to nesting activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Perrins1">Perrins 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Stevenson1">Stevenson and Bryant 2000</xref>). Thus, it is important to determine which cues (i.e. spring rainfall or temperature) montane birds use to fine-tune breeding behavior in subtropical Taiwan.In addition to influencing the onset of avian breeding, weather also influences breeding success. In most cases, nest survival decreases under conditions of low temperature and high rainfall. For example, heavy rainfall may cause flooding or soaking of nests, and thus nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wesolowski1">Weso&lstrok;owski et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Radford1">Radford and Du Plessis 2003</xref>). Furthermore, during inclement weather, parent birds are more likely to encounter adverse foraging conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Avery1">Avery and Krebs 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCarty1">McCarty and Winkler 1999</xref>), resulting in less food being delivered to nestlings, and, consequently, poor nestling growth and nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Siikamaki1">Siikam&auml;ki 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCarty1">McCarty and Winkler 1999</xref>). Although the effects of unfavorable weather on breeding performance are recognized, these effects have primarily been investigated with regard to interannual variation in total precipitation and annual fecundity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Siikamaki1">Siikam&auml;ki 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wesolowski1">Weso&lstrok;owski et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Radford1">Radford and Du Plessis 2003</xref>). In contrast, few studies have evaluated the effects of weather and extreme events per se at the individual level (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Skagen1">Skagen and Yackel Adams 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Pipoly1">Pipoly et al. 2013</xref>). In addition, inclement weather may have a more severe impact on birds inhabiting montane cloud forests, owing to the effects of lower temperatures and higher humidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Tye1">Tye 1992</xref>). Many montane species in Taiwan breed from late March to August, during which time the summer monsoon and severe tropical storms prevail. Therefore, it is important to examine the effects of weather and extreme events on their nest survival.This study aimed to estimate the effects of weather variation on the timing and success of nesting for 2 montane passerines, the Green-backed Tit (<italic>Parus monticolus</italic>) and the Rufous-faced Warbler (<italic>Abroscopus albogularis</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Both species are small insectivorous passerines (ca. 12 g and 6 g body mass, respectively), and are facultative multiple breeders that readily accept nest boxes. The Green-backed Tit is an endemic subspecies that is restricted to low- to mid-altitude (1,000&ndash;2,500 m) evergreen broadleaf forests and plantations in Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Severinghaus1">Severinghaus et al. 2012</xref>), and it has been listed as a protected species by the Council of Agriculture, Executive Yuan, Taiwan, since 1989. The Rufous-faced Warbler is widely distributed from southwestern to southeastern China, including Hainan Island, and is found at altitudes of 500 to 2,300 m in Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Severinghaus1">Severinghaus et al. 2012</xref>). Although the Rufous-faced Warbler is widely distributed, little information is available regarding its ecology. The Breeding Bird Survey database for Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ko2">Ko et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ko1">2015</xref>) indicates that the populations of both the Green-backed Tit and the Rufous-faced Warbler (as well as those of several other montane species) declined noticeably from 2009 to 2013, with population declines of 44&percnt; and 24&percnt;, respectively. During a 5-yr study on the reproduction of these 2 species, we had the opportunity to study the effects of weather variation on avian reproduction. We present the first characterization of the nesting ecology of the Green-backed Tit and Rufous-faced Warbler. Specifically, we used the 5-yr dataset to test whether the timing of laying and the length of the laying season were associated with spring rainfall and/or temperature, and whether nest survival was negatively affected by adverse weather during the nesting period. We predicted that sufficient spring rainfall in conjunction with warmer temperatures would favor avian reproduction, whereas heavy rainfall during the nesting period would adversely affect nest survival.Subtropical montane birds, such as (top) Rufous-faced Warbler (Abroscopus albogularis) and (bottom) Greenbacked Tit (Parus monticolus), used spring temperature to fine-tune breeding behavior, whereas the nest survival for these species declined under heavy seasonal rainfall during the nesting period. Photo credit: Yen-Ling ChangOur study was conducted in a subtropical montane cloud forest at Guanwu (24&deg;30&prime;N, 121&deg;06&prime;E, 1,900&ndash;2,200 m elevation) in Shei-Pa National Park, north-central Taiwan. The landscape is a patch mosaic of natural broadleaf forest and conifer plantations, with steep mountain slopes between 10&deg; and 40&deg;. The natural forest is dominated by caudate-leaved chinkapin (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Castanopsis cuspidata</named-content></italic> var. <italic>carlesii</italic>), Mori oak (<italic>Cyclobalanopsis morii</italic>), Formosan alder (<italic>Alnus formosana</italic>), bird-lime tree (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Trochodendron aralioides</named-content></italic>), and Hayata's cleyera (<italic>Cleyera japonica</italic>). The plantations were reforested ~30&ndash;40 yr ago after the clear-cutting of the natural forest, and are dominated by Japanese cedar (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cryptomeria japonica</named-content></italic>) interspersed with Taiwan cedar (<italic>Taiwania cryptomerioides</italic>) and Chinese fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cunninghamia lanceolata</named-content></italic>).The study area has a humid, subtropical climate with distinct annual cycles of temperature and rainfall. We used weather data obtained from automatic weather station C0D550 of the Central Weather Bureau (24&deg;31&prime;37&prime;&prime;N, 121&deg;06&prime;58&prime;&prime;E, 1,956 m elevation), which is located ~2.4 km from our study site and was installed in October 2007. The general weather pattern during the study period encompassed increasing temperatures from January to July. The daily mean temperature from April to August averaged across the 5-yr study period was 16.9 &plusmn; 2.3&deg;C, with a range of 9.3 to 23.3&deg;C. Spring rainfall (February&ndash;March) was related to the El Ni&ntilde;o&ndash;Southern Oscillation cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Jiang1">Jiang et al. 2003</xref>). The highest spring rainfall (431.5 mm) occurred in a strong El Ni&ntilde;o year (2010), whereas lower spring rainfall (198 and 134 mm) occurred in non&ndash;El Ni&ntilde;o years (2011 and 2013; average &plusmn; SD &equals; 297.6 &plusmn; 126.0 mm). Total precipitation during the nesting period (April&ndash;August) also exhibited significant interannual variation, and was highest in 2013 (2,806 mm) and lowest in 2011 (1,128 mm; average &plusmn; SD &equals; 1,550 &plusmn; 705 mm).Each nest box was designed for small passerines and had an entrance that was 3 cm in diameter and a bottom area of 10.5 &times; 12.5 cm<sup>2</sup>. The depth of each nest box was 11.3 cm (measured from the entrance hole to the box floor). We chose 3 natural forest patches and 3 plantation stands in which to erect nest boxes (each plot encompassed ca. 2 ha). During the 2010&ndash;2014 study period, 90 nest boxes were erected in the plantation stands (30 nest boxes per stand). In comparison, the total number of nest boxes in the natural forest patches varied among years, owing to disparate research topics and limited effort. In total, 74 boxes were erected in the natural forest patches between 2010 and 2014: 15, 30, 18, 1, and 10 boxes each consecutive year. The nest boxes were distributed in a grid pattern or irregularly along trails at intervals of ~15 m. All nest boxes were nailed to tree trunks at a height of 3 m.All nest boxes were checked and the contents (eggs and nestlings) recorded at least once a week during the nesting period from late March to August, 2010&ndash;2014. The mean interval between nest visits for the total effective sample of 178 nests was 4.81 &plusmn; 1.51 SD days. Four nests were excluded from analyses because they had failed upon first observation. Most nests were found during the egg-laying or early incubation period. We determined the date of clutch initiation by assuming that 1 egg was laid per day and back-counting when more than 1 egg was present in a nest box. Nestlings were weighed when first found, or as soon as possible thereafter, and aged by fitting the average nestling mass of the brood to the growth curve, which was constructed from nestlings of known age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Huang1">Huang 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Shiao1">Shiao 2006</xref>). We also estimated the annual breeding density by dividing the maximum number of simultaneously active nests during the nesting period by the study area.Given the difficulty of accurately determining nest fate and fledging date during regular visits, we monitored nest activity through video recordings for some nests during the mid-to-late nestling period (96&percnt; of Green-backed Tit nests and 59&percnt; of Rufous-faced Warbler nests). For each sample nest, the original, wooden nest box roof was replaced with a translucent acrylic board, in which a color charge-coupled-device camera was installed at 5&ndash;7 days after hatching. The camera was linked to a digital video recorder (DVR) or digital video (DV) placed 15&ndash;20 m from the nest box, and the device was connected to a 45&ndash;75 Ah car battery as the power source. The disturbance created by installing the video system did not cause the birds to abandon their nests immediately after the nestlings hatched. We monitored activity within each sample nest between 05:00 and 19:00 hr each day until nest failure or fledging, and recorded nest fate and the date that the nestling stage ended or was terminated. For the nests without video surveillance, we used field cues to determine nest fate, including nestling age at the previous visit, presence of fecal droppings in the nest, flattened nest material, and fledglings observed or heard near the nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ball1">Ball and Bayne 2012</xref>). Nest success was defined as at least 1 nestling fledging from the nest, whereas nest failure was defined as either (1) the eggs or nestlings disappearing from the nest before the expected fledging age, or (2) the nest contents still remaining but no longer attended by the parents. The observer effects of nest visits and video surveillance were included in the nest survival model.The Green-backed Tit and the Rufous-faced Warbler usually lay replacement clutches after a failed first attempt. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-vanNoordwijk1">van Noordwijk et al. (1995)</xref> and our empirical evidence, replacement clutches always start &gt;30 days after the egg-laying date of the first clutch in the same year. Therefore, when determining the timing of nesting, we used only the first nesting attempt from each pair and excluded clutches that started &gt;30 days after the first clutch. For each year, we calculated the earliest egg-laying date (earliest nest found during each nesting period) and the mean egg-laying date. In addition, we calculated the difference between the earliest egg-laying date and the day that the last egg was laid in the last nest of the season as a measure of the length of the laying season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Halupka1">Halupka et al. 2008</xref>).We used linear regression to examine whether the timing of laying and the length of the laying season were associated with spring weather. The mean egg-laying date and the length of the laying season for each year were used as response variables, whereas mean February temperature, mean March temperature, and February&ndash;March rainfall were used as explanatory variables. To examine whether earlier nests contained larger clutches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Cresswell1">Cresswell and McCleery 2003</xref>), we also used linear regression to evaluate relationships between mean egg-laying date and average clutch size of the first nesting attempt. In addition, we employed a one-way ANOVA to test for annual variation in mean egg-laying date, clutch size, brood size, and hatching rate, and we used Tukey's post hoc test to detect significantly different group means. Analyses were performed using JMP 5.0 statistical programming software (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina USA). All values are presented as mean &plusmn; SE, unless otherwise stated.We used an information-theoretic approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>) to evaluate a priori models for the effects of weather variables, and other spatial and temporal variables such as habitat type, nest age, and calendar year, on daily survival rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t01">Table 1</xref>). We grouped these variables by type to facilitate analyses, including habitat and year effects (suite 1), age-specific effects (suite 2), weather effects (suite 3), and observer effects (suite 4). A hierarchical modeling procedure with the 4 model suites was applied, and Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>) was used to select optimal models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). Any model that had a difference in AIC<sub>c</sub> value from the top model (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>) of less than 2 was carried over and included in the next model suite. The first set of models assessed the effects of habitat and year on daily survival rate. Habitat was a binary variable (1, 0), where 1 &equals; natural forest and 0 &equals; plantation stand. In contrast, year was a categorical variable that contained 4 parameters to represent 2011 to 2014, using 2010 as the reference value.Variables incorporated into candidate models and alternative hypotheses explaining variation in nest survival for the Green-backed Tit and Rufous-faced Warbler at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014.The second set of models evaluated whether daily survival rate varied linearly with nest age or nonlinearly with nest age via a quadratic or cubic polynomial function. We included linear, quadratic, and cubic effects of nest age separately in the models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t01">Table 1</xref>). The quadratic model contained both linear and quadratic terms, whereas the cubic model contained linear, quadratic, and cubic terms. We did not consider the effect of date during the nesting period because it was strongly correlated with daily mean temperature (Pearson correlation, <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.76, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 738).The third set of models assessed the effects of weather on daily survival rate. We considered different model structures to assess the relationship between nest survival and rainfall (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t01">Table 1</xref>): (1) daily survival rate linearly related to daily precipitation; (2) daily survival rate nonlinearly related to daily precipitation via a quadratic or cubic polynomial function; and (3) rain-threshold nest survival, in which the daily survival rate was affected only after daily precipitation reached a &ldquo;threshold&rdquo; amount (termed &ldquo;heavy rainfall&rdquo; in this study). Heavy rainfall was defined as daily precipitation that was higher than 20 mm, which was the 85<sup>th</sup> percentile of our daily precipitation data for April to August in 2010&ndash;2014. The threshold value was also similar to the 85<sup>th</sup> percentile for precipitation (21.5 mm) for the 1987&ndash;2007 dataset at a neighboring weather station that is now decommissioned (C0E410, 24&deg;30&prime;28&prime;&prime;N, 121&deg;06&prime;18&prime;&prime;E). This effect was allowed to vary per day and was coded as a binary variable (1, 0), where 1 and 0 indicated the presence and absence of heavy rainfall events, respectively. In addition, daily mean temperature was considered as a temperature predictor variable and was included in the weather models.Finally, because some studies have demonstrated that the act of nest observation itself may negatively bias daily survival rate estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Rotella2">Rotella et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>), we separately incorporated 2 variables for observer effects into the best-supported model to determine whether regular nest visits or equipping the video system had an impact on daily survival rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t01">Table 1</xref>). The effects of these 2 variables were allowed to vary for the days that nest contents were visited or were equipped with the video system. Both variables were coded as binary (1, 0), in which 1 and 0 represented the presence and absence of the observer effect, respectively. After preliminary analyses, all models within 2 &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> units of the top models were considered to be supported models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We evaluated parameter estimates and 95&percnt; confidence intervals from the supported models to identify uninformative parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). A parameter was considered as strongly affecting daily survival rate if the 95&percnt; CI did not include 0, and was considered to have no relationship with survival if the 95&percnt; CI overlapped 0.We used the nest-survival module in program MARK version 8.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>) to evaluate the relative support for each candidate model. Covariates and encounter history were coded following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. (2002)</xref>. We built all models with a logit link function and without standardizing covariates. We assumed that the nesting period of the Green-backed Tit extended from March 22 (the date the first egg in the earliest nest was laid) to August 10 (fledging date of the nestling in the last nest), totaling 142 days (encounter occasions), whereas that of the Rufous-faced Warbler extended from March 27 to August 16, totaling 143 days. We calculated the daily survival rate from the best-supported model by varying covariates of interest while holding the remaining covariates at their mean values. If more than one supported model existed, we used model-averaged estimates of coefficients to avoid model selection uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). In addition, we calculated the period survival rate, which was the product of the daily survival rate during the egg-laying, incubation, and nestling periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Thompson 2007</xref>). The length of each period was assumed to be as follows: 5 days for egg-laying for both species based on mean clutch size (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t02">Table 2</xref>); 14 days for incubation for the Green-backed Tit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Severinghaus1">Severinghaus et al. 2012</xref>) and 17 days for the Rufous-faced Warbler; and 21 days for the nestling period for the Green-backed Tit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Huang1">Huang 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Shiao1">Shiao 2006</xref>) and 16 days for the Rufous-faced Warbler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Huang1">Huang 1996</xref>). Therefore, the total nesting period was assumed to be 40 days and 38 days for the Green-backed Tit and the Rufous-faced Warbler, respectively. Variance estimates and 95&percnt; confidence limits for the daily and period survival rates of nests were calculated using the delta method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Powell1">Powell 2007</xref>).Reproductive parameters of the Green-backed Tit and Rufous-faced Warbler at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014.From 2010 to 2014, we monitored 74 Green-backed Tit nests and 108 Rufous-faced Warbler nests. The breeding densities of the 2 species declined steeply from 2010 to 2014 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t02">Table 2</xref>). For the Green-backed Tit, the earliest laying date ranged from March 22 (2014) to April 4 (2011), with the mean laying date varying significantly among years (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,36</sub> &equals; 13.40, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Laying dates of the Green-backed Tit were earlier in years with warmer March temperatures (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 17.52, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.85; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f03">Figure 3</xref>), but were not significantly affected by February temperatures (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 1.20, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.35, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.29) or the amount of rainfall in February and March (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 0.03, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.88, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.008). The laying season of the Green-backed Tit extended from late March to June, or even into early July (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t02">Table 2</xref>), and was not significantly affected by February temperatures (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 1.92, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.39), March temperatures (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 0.23, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.66, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.07), or February&ndash;March rainfall (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 0.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.52, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.15).Mean egg-laying date of the first nesting attempt for the Green-backed Tit (closed circles) and Rufous-faced Warbler (open circles) at Guanwu, Taiwan, varied during 2010&ndash;2014. Numbers adjacent to the circles denote the number of nests that were sampled.Mean egg-laying date of the first nesting attempt for the Green-backed Tit (closed circles) and Rufous-faced Warbler (open circles) in relation to mean temperature in March at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014. Solid and dashed lines represent the fitted relationships for the Green-backed Tit (slope of the regression &equals; &minus;8.56 &plusmn; 2.05) and the Rufous-faced Warbler (slope of the regression &equals; &minus;4.69 &plusmn; 3.76), respectively.The Rufous-faced Warbler started laying significantly later than the Green-backed Tit (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,88</sub> &equals; 80.43, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The earliest laying date of the Rufous-faced Warbler ranged from March 27 (2013) to April 14 (2011), with the mean laying date also differing significantly among years (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,44</sub> &equals; 5.31, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f02">Figure 2</xref>). The laying season of the Rufous-faced Warbler extended from late March to early July (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t02">Table 2</xref>). Neither the mean laying date nor the laying season of the Rufous-faced Warbler was significantly affected by February temperatures, March temperatures, or February&ndash;March rainfall (ANOVA, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.30, all <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.50; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f03">Figure 3</xref>).We found no significant relationship between the mean laying date and the average clutch size of the first nesting attempt across all 5 yr for either the Green-backed Tit (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 0.12, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.75) or the Rufous-faced Warbler (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,3</sub> &equals; 1.09, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.37). For both species, the mean clutch size did not vary among years (Green-backed Tit: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,63</sub> &equals; 1.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.21; Rufous-faced Warbler: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,93</sub> &equals; 1.81, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.13). For the Green-backed Tit, mean annual brood size differed significantly among years (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,49</sub> &equals; 4.98, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002), with significantly larger brood sizes in 2014 than in 2010, 2012, and 2013. The hatching success of the Green-backed Tit also varied among years (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,49</sub> &equals; 2.83, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03), although Tukey's test did not yield significant pairwise differences in hatching success. For the Rufous-faced Warbler, neither brood size nor hatching success varied significantly among years (brood size: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,70</sub> &equals; 1.91, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12; hatching success: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,70</sub> &equals; 2.18, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.08).We had sufficient data to analyze the survival of 73 Green-backed Tit nests (36 in the broadleaf forest and 37 in the conifer plantations; the effective sample size, which was calculated by summing the total number of days that nests were known to have survived and the total number of intervals in which nest failure occurred, was 1,823) and 105 Rufous-faced Warbler nests (49 in the broadleaf forest and 56 in the conifer plantations; effective sample size &equals; 2,595). For the Green-backed Tit, the daily survival rate of nests varied temporally as a function of year and nest age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t03">Table 3</xref>). Annual variation in survival rates was found, but the parameter estimates were highly imprecise (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t04">Table 4</xref>). The daily survival rate of nests was related to nest age via a cubic polynomial function that increased from the onset of laying to early incubation (1&ndash;10 days), followed by a steady decrease from the late-incubation to early-nestling period (11&ndash;26 days), and finally an increase after the mid-nestling period (27&ndash;40 days; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f04">Figure 4</xref>).Summary of model selection results for nest survival of the Green-backed Tit at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014. Models are ranked based on Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>), and the model with the lowest AIC<sub>c</sub> is considered to be the best model. <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters in the model; Dev is the deviance; &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference between the AIC<sub>c</sub> of each model and the AIC<sub>c</sub> of the best model; and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the relative support for each model within the model set.Beta estimates and 95&percnt; confidence intervals for parameters in the most supported model for nest survival of the Green-backed Tit at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014.Daily survival rates of the Green-backed Tit in relation to nest age (days) at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014. Predicted daily survival was estimated from the best model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t04">Table 4</xref>), and all covariates that were not plotted were held constant at their mean values to show the variation in the covariate of nest age. The solid line represents survival rate estimates, whereas the dashed lines represent the 95&percnt; confidence limits.Our results supported our hypothesis that the daily survival rate of Green-backed Tit nests would be associated with weather factors. Heavy rainfall events (but not linear or nonlinear effects of daily precipitation) had a negative effect on the daily survival rate of nests (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t03">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t04">4</xref>). Moreover, the most supported model of daily survival rate for the Green-backed Tit included the effect of daily mean temperature, and indicated that lower temperatures increased the risk of nest failure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t03">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Furthermore, the addition of an observer effect, but not a video surveillance effect, further improved model fit (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t03">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t04">4</xref>). This result indicated that viewing nest contents (observer effect) had a negative impact on daily nest survival rate, whereas video recording had no effect on nest survival. The logistic regression equation from the best model was used to predict period survival for Green-backed Tit nests. We incorporated nest age effects but held the effects of weather and year covariates constant by multiplying the coefficient of each covariate by its mean value. The effect of the binary variable VISIT was held constant at 0, or absence. The predicted probability of a Green-backed Tit nest surviving the entire 40-day nesting period in 2010&ndash;2014 was 0.76 &plusmn; 0.08.Daily survival rates of the Green-backed Tit in relation to daily mean temperature and the absence (black lines) or presence (gray lines) of heavy rainfall at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014. Predicted daily survival was estimated from the best model (Table 4), and all covariates that were not plotted were held constant at their mean values to show variation in the covariates of daily mean temperature and heavy rainfall events. The solid lines represent survival rate estimates, whereas the dashed lines represent the 95% confidence limits.For the Rufous-faced Warbler, the model that received the most support based on our data indicated that the daily survival rate of nests varied across years and was related to nest age via a cubic polynomial function (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t05">Table 5</xref>). However, the confidence intervals of the 2 parameter estimates encompassed 0, indicating model uncertainty (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t06">Table 6</xref>). The most supported model included the heavy rainfall covariate, indicating that nests that were subjected to heavy rainfall had a lower daily survival rate than those that were not. The VISIT effect also appeared in the most supported model, supporting our hypothesis that disturbance by nest-visiting procedures reduced nest survival for this species as well.Summary of model selection results for nest survival of the Rufous-faced Warbler at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014. Models are ranked based on Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>), and the model with the lowest AIC<sub>c</sub> is considered to be the best model. <italic>K</italic> is the number of parameters in the model; Dev is the deviance; &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference between the AIC<sub>c</sub> of each model and the AIC<sub>c</sub> of the best model; and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is relative support for each model within the model set.Beta estimates and 95&percnt; confidence intervals for parameters in the most supported models for nest survival of the Rufous-faced Warbler at Guanwu, Taiwan, 2010&ndash;2014.The model incorporating year, temperature, observer effects, and the cubic effect of nest age also received support (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t05">Tables 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-t06">6</xref>). Daily mean temperature had a positive influence on daily survival rate, but the parameter estimate was highly imprecise. In addition, the remaining competing model, containing the quadratic effect of daily precipitation, appeared to receive less support and the confidence interval of the parameter estimate encompassed 0 (&beta; estimate &plusmn; SE of the parameter PRECIPITATION &equals; &minus;0.037 &plusmn; 0.018; 95&percnt; confidence limits: &minus;0.073, &minus;0.002; &beta; estimate &plusmn; SE of PRECIPITATION<sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.0003 &plusmn; 0.0002; 95&percnt; confidence limits: &minus;0.0001, 0.0008).We averaged the 2 most supported models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2 to obtain estimates of all covariate effects and used the results to compute the period survival of Rufous-faced Warbler nests. We incorporated nest age effects and held the effects of weather and year covariates constant by multiplying the coefficient of each covariate by its mean value. The effect of the binary variable VISIT was held constant at 0, or absence. The probability of a Rufous-faced Warbler nest surviving the entire 38-day nesting period in 2010&ndash;2014 was 0.69 &plusmn; 0.07.Our results demonstrated that the breeding phenology of the Green-backed Tit, a subtropical montane species, was similar to that of many temperate species, with spring temperature rather than rainfall having the greatest influence. Female tits shifted their laying dates to earlier in the season in response to earlier warm spring weather, and vice versa. Although the effects of spring temperature on the timing of avian reproduction have been extensively studied for species from the temperate latitudes of Europe and North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn1">Dunn 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn2">Dunn and Winkler 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Schaper1">Schaper et al. 2011</xref>), to our knowledge this is the first study to confirm this effect for a subtropical montane species. Moreover, the slope of the laying date&ndash;air temperature regression line for Green-backed Tits was steeper than that recorded for many temperate species (see table 1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn1">Dunn 2004</xref> and table 10.1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn2">Dunn and Winkler 2010</xref>). Therefore, low-latitude species that have less pronounced seasonality in temperature and photoperiod exhibit relatively high sensitivity in exploiting changes in photic and nonphotic cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Hau2">Hau et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Hau1">2008</xref>), and even slight environmental changes may shift their laying dates. The plasticity observed in the timing of breeding may be explained as a constraint of environmental conditions prior to laying or as an adaptation by female birds to fine-tune their laying with the aim of rearing young at the optimal time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Nager1">Nager and van Noordwijk 1995</xref>). The former explanation is related to energetic constraints and food availability at the onset of the breeding period. In cold springs, female birds allocate energy toward thermoregulation at the expense of gonadal maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Perrins1">Perrins 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Stevenson1">Stevenson and Bryant 2000</xref>). Prebreeding food supplementation experiments solve this energy bottleneck for birds, and advance laying dates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Schoech1">Schoech and Hahn 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Harrison1">Harrison et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ruffino1">Ruffino et al. 2014</xref>). Another explanation is that spring temperature acts as a supplementary cue for females, who adjust their laying to coincide with seasonal peaks in food abundance when the energetic demands of offspring are presumably highest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Lack1">Lack 1954</xref>). As spring temperature increases, invertebrates develop faster and their populations increase exponentially (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Topp1">Topp and Kirsten 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Buse1">Buse et al. 1999</xref>); consequently, female birds advance their laying dates to keep pace with peak food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCleery1">McCleery and Perrins 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Cresswell1">Cresswell and McCleery 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Both1">Both and Visser 2005</xref>). However, more research is needed to determine the extent of annual variation in food availability and how it influences the timing of breeding in Green-backed Tits.The Rufous-faced Warbler showed a similar but weaker negative relationship between spring temperature and mean laying date compared with the Green-backed Tit. This difference may be a result of the Rufous-faced Warbler starting to breed slightly later than the Green-backed Tit, and thus being less responsive to annual temperature variation in early spring. The rates at which various species respond to environmental conditions are related to gonadal growth and maturation, which are primarily regulated by photoperiod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dawson1">Dawson 2008</xref>). Although photoperiod is fixed at the same latitude, there are interspecific differences in the threshold amount of light required to start gonadal growth and the rate of gonadal growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dawson1">Dawson 2008</xref>). These differences will further influence species' responses to weather variations. Alternatively, the relationship between spring temperature and mean laying date may differ between our 2 study species due to dietary differences. The nestling diet of the Green-backed Tit is mainly composed of caterpillars (70&ndash;90&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chuang1">Chuang 2006</xref>). In contrast, Rufous-faced Warbler parents provide nestlings with a high diversity of small invertebrates, with the diet being composed of 38&percnt; Hemiptera, 25&percnt; Diptera, 19&percnt; Coleoptera, 8&percnt; Orthoptera, 8&percnt; Araneae, and 2&percnt; Hymenoptera (M.-T. Shiao personal observation). Therefore, the laying dates of the 2 species may be differentially timed to match different peaks in food abundance later in the season when offspring demands are highest. Furthermore, as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Winkler1">Winkler et al. (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Dunn1">Dunn (2004)</xref>, species with higher dietary diversity, such as the Rufous-faced Warbler, will be less influenced by phenological shifts in their prey.In tropical and subtropical regions with high rainfall seasonality, seasonal rainfall acts as a proximate factor for avian reproduction through food-mediated processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wikelski1">Wikelski et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Boulton1">Boulton et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Styrsky1">Styrsky and Brawn 2011</xref>), even for subtropical montane species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Auer1">Auer et al. 2007</xref>). Although spring rainfall may affect vegetation phenology in subtropical Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. 2013</xref>), we failed to find any relationship between the timing of egg laying and spring rainfall for either montane species that we studied. This lack of correlation may be due to the fact that our study area experiences a perhumid climate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Wan1">Wan 2008</xref>), with February&ndash;March precipitation exceeding 40 mm in all study years. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. (2013)</xref> indicated that an apparent delay in the onset of vegetation growth occurred in regions with &lt;40 mm of spring rainfall. Therefore, the limiting role of spring rainfall on primary productivity and, consequently, secondary productivity (i.e. biomass of invertebrate prey), and ultimately overall avian reproduction, may be less important in our study area. The laying seasons of our 2 study species were predicted to extend following a wetter and warmer spring, assuming that the invertebrate prey on which the birds fed during the nesting period would also be available for a longer period of time because of a longer growing season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. 2013</xref>). However, in contrast to our prediction, we did not detect a significant relationship between the length of the laying season and spring rainfall or temperature for either species. We postulate that in areas that often receive &lt;40 mm of spring rainfall, such as central and southwestern Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Chang1">Chang et al. 2013</xref>), spring rainfall may have a stronger influence on biological processes than air temperature.Our study showed that both Green-backed Tits and Rufous-faced Warblers suffered, rather than benefited, from heavy seasonal rainfall during the nesting period. The nest survival analysis results indicated that nest survival declined for both species under extreme heavy rainfall, whereas light rain had no impact on nest survival. Moreover, the daily survival rate for Green-backed Tits was further reduced in cold weather combined with heavy rain. Although cavity-nesting birds nest in a cavity that often buffers, to some extent, the effects of environmental factors on eggs or nestlings, these nests may still suffer directly from severe floods caused by heavy rainfall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Radford1">Radford and Du Plessis 2003</xref>). In parallel, severe weather may increase the energy expenditure required for thermoregulation and maintenance of nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Tinbergen1">Tinbergen and Dietz 1994</xref>). Parents may respond to such inclement weather by increasing the amount of time spent brooding nestlings at the expense of foraging time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Radford2">Radford et al. 2001</xref>). Furthermore, the foraging efficiency of parents decreases with the lower activity of insect prey during wet and cold weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Avery1">Avery and Krebs 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCarty1">McCarty and Winkler 1999</xref>). Thus, these adverse weather effects also reduce nest survival indirectly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Siikamaki1">Siikam&auml;ki 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCarty1">McCarty and Winkler 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Skagen1">Skagen and Yackel Adams 2012</xref>). Long-term climatic data for Taiwan show that extreme precipitation events have increased over the past 5 decades, and that the annual number of typhoons affecting Taiwan has also increased over the past 2 decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Hsu1">Hsu et al. 2011</xref>). In a warming environment (multimodel average projections for the IPCC Special Report on Emissions Scenarios, A1B scenario; IPCC 2007), the summer mean precipitation in Taiwan, i.e. the 2080 to 2099 average, will increase by 15&percnt; to 45&percnt;, and heavy rainfall events are very likely to become more intense and to occur more frequently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Hsu1">Hsu et al. 2011</xref>). Thus, under the future warming scenarios, the negative effects of severe weather may contribute toward further decreasing the annual productivity of montane birds, and may accelerate population declines.Age-specific survival was indicated by the Green-backed Tit model. The daily survival rate increased during egg laying and early incubation, but then decreased from late incubation to early in the nestling stage. Rapid increases in nest survival during egg laying may be related to a higher limit of tolerance to disturbance because more reproductive effort has been invested (i.e. more eggs have been laid; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Grant2">Grant et al. 2005</xref>). Conversely, a decrease in the daily survival rate may result from the naked, neonate nestlings being more vulnerable to adverse weather because they exhibit reduced thermal capacity during the first week after hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-McCarty1">McCarty and Winkler 1999</xref>). In addition, a higher frequency of parental foraging trips after hatching may increase predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Martin1">Martin et al. 2000</xref>). During the mid-to-late nestling period, the daily survival rate may increase again because older, feathered nestlings are able to thermoregulate and are thus less vulnerable to adverse weather conditions. Moreover, parents often increase nest defense as nestlings reach the fledging stage because of the high investment in the nest by that stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Montgomerie1">Montgomerie and Weatherhead 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Whittam1">Whittam and Leonard 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Pavel1">Pavel and Bure&scaron; 2001</xref>). Similar nest survival patterns have been recorded for some open-cup-nesting altricial birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Grant2">Grant et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Davis1">Davis et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Grant1">Grant and Shaffer 2012</xref>), but not for cavity-nesting birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>).Our study indicated that regularly visiting nests for observation, rather than video monitoring, had a strong negative effect on the nest survival of both study species, supporting the findings of previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Rotella2">Rotella et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Rotella1">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>). Nest visiting may provide cues to predators, helping them to locate nests; it may also reduce nest attendance by parents, or even lead to nest abandonment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>). Therefore, it is important to consider observer effects in nest survival models to obtain more precise estimates of nest survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Rotella2">Rotella et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Newlon1">Newlon and Saab 2011</xref>, this study). In comparison, video monitoring is an effective tool for reducing the disturbance caused by nest visits and for improving the accuracy of nest fate determination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Coates1">Coates et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ball1">Ball and Bayne 2012</xref>).In conclusion, our study demonstrated that, similarly to effects on temperate birds, spring temperature triggered the breeding phenology of at least 2 species of subtropical montane birds, whereas heavy rainfall during the breeding period negatively affected nest survival. Thus, it is necessary to determine to the extent to which the mechanism of the avian response to spring temperature can be applied to subtropical montane species in general. In addition, the breeding densities of both study species declined over the 5-yr study period, which appears to be similar to overall population trends in Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ko2">Ko et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Ko1">2015</xref>). Population declines may reduce genetic diversity, resulting in insufficient plasticity to adjust to climatic fluctuations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Frankham1">Frankham 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Doi1">Doi et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Gordo1">Gordo and Doi 2012</xref>). Thus, it is important to clarify the main causes of current widespread population declines, and to use this information to predict population dynamics under future climate scenarios. Future studies should focus on elucidating how weather variation affects other life-history traits, such as adult survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Arendt1">Arendt 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Grosbois1">Grosbois et al. 2006</xref>) and juvenile recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Both1">Both and Visser 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-671-Husby1">Husby et al. 2009</xref>), which also determine population growth rates. Ultimately, existing climate change is expected to accelerate the population declines of montane bird species, such as the 2 species investigated here, making long-term detailed studies essential to develop potential mitigation measures.We thank Wan-Ju Huang, Hui-Ping Hsieh, Ying-Lan Chen, Kung-Kuo Chiang, Mu-Chun Yao, Po-Yin Chen, Shu-Yen Huang, Shih-Han Hsu, Yu-Chieh Pan, and the members of the Wildlife Laboratory of the Department of Life Science, National Taiwan Normal University, for assistance with fieldwork. We also thank the rangers of Shei-Pa National Park and the staff of Guanwu Police Squad of the Shei-Pa Police Brigade for their support and assistance. We are grateful to two reviewers for valuable comments on a previous draft of our manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Our research was partly supported by the Shei-Pa National Park Headquarters with a grant to M.-T.S. The funder did not have input into the content of the manuscript, nor did the funder require approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This project was conducted under permits from Shei-Pa National Park Headquarters.