Black Curassow habitat relationships in <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of the Guiana Shield: A multiscale approachA new model for the continuum conceptHunting pressure on cracids (Cracidae: Aves) in forest concessions in PeruUse and conservation of Cracidae (Aves: Galliformes) in the Peruvian AmazonAbundancia y area de accion del Pauji de Copete (<italic>Crax daubentoni</italic>) en los llanos centrales de VenezuelaThe importance of spatial autocorrelation, extent and resolution in predicting forest bird occurrenceAvian habitat evaluation: Should counting birds count?Evaluating the sustainability of hunting in the NeotropicsRelative use of secondary forests by cracids in central AmazoniaThe utility of hotspot identification for forest management: Cracids as bioindicatorsResource separation in a Napo-Amazonian gamebird communityModel averaging and muddled multimodel inferencesRegional ecosystem structure and function: Ecological insights from remote sensing of tropical forestsInference about density and temporary emigration in unmarked populationsConservation interests of applying spatial distribution modelling to large vagile Neotropical mammalsVariation in aboveground tree live biomass in a central Amazonian forest: Effects of soil and topographyL'end&eacute;misme en Guyane fran&ccedil;aiseTransamazonian crustal growth and reworking as revealed by the 1:500,000-scale geological map of French GuianaRapid evaluation of threats to biodiversity: Human footprint score and large vertebrate species responses in French GuianaImpacts of subsistence game hunting on Amazonian primatesMethods to account for spatial autocorrelation in the analysis of species distributional data: A reviewR&eacute;gime alimentaire de <italic>Tinamus major</italic> (Tinamidae), <italic>Crax alector</italic> (Cracidae) et <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Psophia crepitans</named-content></italic> (Psophiidae) en for&ecirc;t guyanaiseFruit characters in the diet of syntopic large frugivorous forest bird species in French GuianaHigher treefall rates on slopes and waterlogged soils result in lower stand biomass and productivity in a tropical rain forestValidating forest types based on geological and land-form features in central AmazoniaEvidence for density-dependent habitat occupancy at varying scales in an expanding bird populationHabitat&ndash;performance relationships: Finding the right metric at a given spatial scaleBroad scale pattern of forest landscape types in Guiana ShieldPredictive habitat distribution models in ecologyLandform and landscape mapping, French Guiana (South America)Geomorphological landscape features explain floristic patterns in French Guiana rainforestEstimating tropical tree diversity indices from forestry surveys: A method to integrate taxonomic uncertaintyThe habitat concept and a plea for standard terminologyInterspecific primate associations in Amazonian flooded and unflooded forestsCorrespondence analysis: A neglected multivariate methodD&eacute;partement de la Guyane (973) R&eacute;sum&eacute; statistiqueIUCN Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2013.2Efficiency, bias, and consistency of visual and aural surveys of curassows (Cracidae) in tropical forestsTemporal variation in the diet of Black Curassows (<italic>Crax alector</italic>, Cracidae)The comparison of usage and availability measurements for evaluating resource preferenceMeasuring habitat quality: A reviewThe application of electronic computers to factor analysisPopulation densities of curassows, guans, and chachalacas (Cracidae): Effects of body size, habitat, season, and huntingFrom space to species: Ecological applications for remote sensingModelling avian abundances from replicated counts using binomial mixture modelsLandscape heterogeneity at differing scales: Effects on spatial distribution of mule deerTree species diversity and forest structure in relation to microtopography in a tropical freshwater swamp forest in French GuianaThe influence of differing hunting practices on the relative abundance of mammals in two rainforest areas of the Western Ghats, IndiaIncorporating covariates into standard line transect analysesAICcmodavg: Model selection and multimodel inference based on (Q)AIC(c). R package version 2.0-3Diets of cracids: How much do we know?Remote sensing for conservation monitoring: Assessing protected areas, habitat extent, habitat condition, species diversity, and threatsThe Office National des For&ecirc;ts &ldquo;Expertise Littoral&rdquo; project databaseLiDAR measurements of canopy structure predict spatial distribution of a tropical mature forest primateRegional-scale heterogeneity in primate community structure at multiple undisturbed forest sites across southeastern PeruUse of space by a pair of Salvin's Curassows (<italic>Mitu salvini</italic>) in northwestern Columbian AmazonAllocation of hunting effort by Amazonian smallholders: Implications for conserving wildlife in mixed-use landscapesGeneral guidelines for standardizing line-transect surveys of tropical forest primatesDensity compensation in Neotropical primate communities: Evidence from 56 hunted and nonhunted Amazonian forests of varying productivityExtent of nontimber resource extraction in tropical forests: Accessibility to game vertebrates by hunters in the Amazon basinDetecting anthropogenic disturbance in tropical forestsDetection of macro-ecological patterns in South American hummingbirds is affected by spatial scaleThe use and interpretation of principal component analysis in applied researchLandscape patterns influence communities of medium- to large-bodied vertebrates in undisturbed <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of French GuianaTopographic variation and stand heterogeneity in a wet evergreen forest of IndiaShrub vegetation on tropical granitic inselbergs in French GuianaBiological consequences of ecosystem fragmentation: A reviewSpatial and temporal patterns of Amazon rainfall: Consequences for the planning of agricultural occupation and the protection of primary forestsFloristic patterns along a 43-km long transect in an Amazonian rain forestDensity as a misleading indicator of habitat qualityPalm distribution patterns in Amazonian rainforests: What is the role of topographic variation?Modeling water availability for trees in tropical forestsWildlife hunting practices and bushmeat dynamics of the Banyangi and Mbo people of southwestern CameroonTropical forests in a changing environmentPiaroa and the Cracidae: Game management under shifting cultivationThe Black Curassow (<italic>Crax alector</italic>) is a large game bird with Vulnerable conservation status found in north-central South America. We examined its distributional pattern across French Guiana using a large number of environmental descriptors at 3 scales of analysis: landscape, forest type, and microhabitat. We used a hierarchical model with temporary emigration and imperfect detection for data collected by standard distance sampling methods at 35 study sites. At the landscape scale, Black Curassow density decreased with hunting pressure and increased with steeper slopes in both hunted and unhunted areas. Topography appeared to be a good proxy for Black Curassow ecological requirements and probably reflected habitat quality. At the forest scale, population density was negatively correlated with the abundance of palms and Mimosoideae and positively correlated with the abundance of Lauraceae. Botanical families did not directly influence Black Curassow distribution, but rather determined spatial patterns by being markers of a particular forest type. At the microhabitat scale, Black Curassows used hilltops more frequently than other parts of the local topographical gradient. Our multiscale analysis shows that this species' distribution can be explained by biotic or abiotic conditions, regardless of the scale. For conservation, we recommend maintaining connectivity between Black Curassow populations separated by hunted areas. Our predicted densities could be used to adapt hunting quotas across French Guiana's forests. We show that combining field and remote sensing data helps to understand the ecological processes responsible for Black Curassow habitat relationships.El <italic>Crax alector</italic> es una especie cineg&eacute;tica de ave de gran tama&ntilde;o, con un estado de conservaci&oacute;n vulnerable. Se ha estudiado su patr&oacute;n de distribuci&oacute;n en la Guayana Francesa a partir de numerosas variables ambientales, a tres escalas de an&aacute;lisis: paisaje, tipo de bosque, y microhabitat. Se ha aplicado un modelo jer&aacute;rquico, con emigraci&oacute;n temporal y probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n imperfecta, sobre datos obtenidos aplicando un protocolo estandardizado de distance sampling en 35 localidades. A la escala del paisaje, se muestra que la densidad del <italic>Crax alector</italic> disminuy&oacute; bajo la presi&oacute;n de caza, y que aument&oacute; en zonas de fuerte pendiente, tanto en &aacute;reas con como sin actividad de caza. La topograf&iacute;a parece ser un buen descriptor de los requisitos ecol&oacute;gicos del <italic>Crax alector</italic>, y probablemente informa sobre la calidad del h&aacute;bitat. A la escala del bosque, la densidad del <italic>Crax alector</italic> est&aacute; negativamente correlacionada con la abundancia de palmeras y de plantas de la familia Mimosoideae, y positivamente correlacionada con la familia Lauraceae. Las familias de plantas no influyen directamente en la distribuci&oacute;n de la especie, pero influyen en el patr&oacute;n espacial como un indicador de un tipo de bosque particular. A la escala de microhabitat, el <italic>Crax alector</italic> prefiere las cumbres de las colinas que otras partes del gradiente topogr&aacute;fico. El an&aacute;lisis multiescala muestra que la distribuci&oacute;n de esta especie puede explicarse por factores bi&oacute;ticos o abi&oacute;ticos seg&uacute;n la escala de estudio. Como medidas de conservaci&oacute;n se propone mantener la conectividad entre poblaciones, ya que la &aacute;reas con caza dividen las poblaciones, as&iacute; como utilizar las densidades predichas por el modelo para establecer cuotas de caza en la Guayana Francesa. Se demuestra tambi&eacute;n que la combinaci&oacute;n de teledetecci&oacute;n con datos de campo facilita la comprensi&oacute;n los procesos ecol&oacute;gicos que explican los v&iacute;nculos del <italic>Crax alector</italic> y su h&aacute;bitat.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> an&aacute;lisis multiescala, bosque de tierra firme, caza, Cracidae, <italic>Crax alector</italic>, relaci&oacute;n especie-habitatSpecies&ndash;habitat relationships occur in geographic and ecological spaces where environmental heterogeneity is expressed at different spatial scales. At each scale, a given population, group, or individual is associated with specific environmental features. We define habitat as the resources and environmental conditions (abiotic and biotic) present in an area that determine the presence, survival, and reproduction of a population, which implies that habitat is species-specific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Hall1">Hall et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gaillard1">Gaillard et al. 2010</xref>). The hierarchical approach developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Johnson1">Johnson (1980)</xref> to characterize habitat selection can help to determine the conceptual framework of habitat models by examining species&ndash;habitat relationships from the scale of distribution (the broadest scale of species&ndash;habitat relationships) to specific requirements, e.g., nest, shelter, and food (the finest scale of species&ndash;habitat relationships). The challenge is to identify the scale of analysis (i.e. the spatial extent and spatial resolution of measurement; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Rahbek1">Rahbek and Graves 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kie1">Kie et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Betts1">Betts et al. 2006</xref>) that will maximize the likelihood of detecting a potential effect of an environmental feature on an animal. Today, remote sensing combined with statistical techniques and GIS has become an extremely useful approach to describe environmental characteristics over large spatial extents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kerr1">Kerr and Ostrovsky 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Peres4">Peres et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chambers1">Chambers et al. 2007</xref>) and is potentially a major methodological step forward for our knowledge of the broadest scales of species&ndash;habitat relationships. However, field observation remains the method that provides the most useful data to investigate the finest scales of species&ndash;habitat relationships.Across the Amazon forest basin, landscape heterogeneity (i.e. <italic>terra firme</italic> vs. floodplain forests) is of primary importance for determining primate and bird assemblages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Haugaasen1">Haugaasen and Peres 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Palminteri2">Palminteri et al. 2011</xref>). Most forested areas in the Guiana Shield do not flood and are classified as <italic>terra firme</italic>. However, recent studies have demonstrated that forest structure and plant community composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Tuomisto1">Tuomisto et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gond1">Gond et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Figueiredo1">Figueiredo et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>) are heterogeneous even in <italic>terra firme</italic> forests. Five landscape types have been identified in French Guiana based on geomorphological features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. 2013</xref>). Strong subregional patterns (mostly geomorphological) within these landscapes shape alpha and beta tree diversities and beta diversity of medium- to large-bodied vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet3">Guitet et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-RichardHansen1">Richard-Hansen et al. 2015</xref>). At smaller spatial extents, forest structure and dynamics are strongly influenced by topography and soil hydromorphy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Robert1">Robert and Moravie 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Koponen1">Koponen et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Ferry1">Ferry and Morneau 2010</xref>). Given that the apparent homogeneity of <italic>terra firme</italic> forests throughout the Guiana Shield masks their inherent heterogeneity when observed at a finer scale, we wondered how these multiscale spatial patterns might drive species&ndash;habitat relationships.The Black Curassow (<italic>Crax alector</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f01">Figure 1</xref>) is a large game bird found in north-central South America. Across its distributional range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f02">Figure 2</xref>), the Black Curassow is threatened by deforestation (e.g., across the Amazon basin), hunting, and trapping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-IUCN1">IUCN 2014</xref>). In the Guiana Shield, deforestation rates are very low and the inaccessibility of the southern and central forests limits human impacts on Black Curassows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy1">de Thoisy et al. 2010</xref>). However, human disturbances such as hunting and forest clearing in the wake of timber harvesting may cause local risks of extinction, and these risks may increase in the coming decades due to human population dynamics in these areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Wright1">Wright 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-INSEEInstitutnationaldelastatistiqueetdesetudeseconomiques1">INSEE 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-IUCN1">IUCN 2014</xref>). Black Curassows are typically associated with old-growth forests and are considered highly sensitive to disturbance. They are thus considered bioindicators of forest integrity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Brooks1">Brooks 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy1">de Thoisy et al. 2010</xref>). In French Guiana the Black Curassow occurs only in undisturbed forests, but elsewhere it sometimes occurs in secondary forests that have regrown after clear-cutting often followed by burning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Zent1">Zent 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Borges1">Borges 1999</xref>). In terms of habitat use within their home ranges, the availability of fallen fruit may be particularly important. Black Curassows may supplement their diet with nitrogen-rich leaves and invertebrates as sources of protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Jimenez2">Jimenez et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Parra1">Parra et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Erard2">Erard et al. 2007</xref>).Black Curassow (<italic>Crax alector</italic>), Nouragues Research Station (CNRS), Nouragues National Nature Reserve (co-managed by the GEPOG and the ONF), Regina, French Guiana, France. Photo credit: Antoine BaglanThe study area in French Guiana, northern South America, covering 35 survey sites for Black Curassows. Yellow circles &equals; sites described by remote sensing data only; blue circles &equals; sites described by remote sensing and field data; hunter on top of circle &equals; sites subject to hunting pressure. The study area is compared with the Black Curassow distributional range (hatched area) in the map to the top (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-IUCN1">IUCN 2014</xref>).Apart from studies of their diet, little research exists on relationships between Black Curassows and their habitat based on resources and environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kattan1">Kattan et al. 2016</xref>). We examined how environmental features shape Black Curassow distribution in French Guiana, in particular in the absence of hunting pressure. We used a multiscale approach inspired by the selection order of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Johnson1">Johnson (1980)</xref>: (1) relationships between Black Curassow populations and French Guiana's forest landscapes (large spatial extent of &sim;85,000 km<sup>2</sup> and coarse-resolution remote-sensing descriptors), referred to as the &lsquo;landscape scale'; (2) relationships between Black Curassow populations and French Guiana's forest types (same spatial extent, but with fine-resolution descriptors computed from field-based measurements), referred to as the &lsquo;forest scale'; and (3) relationships of individual Black Curassows with forest microhabitats (small spatial extent of &sim;50 km<sup>2</sup> and same fine-resolution descriptors), referred to as the &lsquo;microhabitat scale.' We used both remote sensing and field data to reveal landscape-scale effects (topographic and hydromorphic conditions and forest structure<bold>)</bold> and forest-scale effects (physical conditions, forest structure, and botanical composition).French Guiana (4&deg;N, 53&deg;W) covers &sim;85,000 km<sup>2</sup> in the eastern part of the Guiana Shield between Suriname and the Brazilian state of Amap&aacute;. Elevation ranges between 0 and 200 m a.s.l. (mean &equals; 140 m), with a few peaks above 800 m. The climate is equatorial. Annual rainfall ranges between 3,600 mm in the northeast and 2,000 mm in the south and west. Mean annual temperature is &sim;26&deg;C. The number of consecutive months with &lt;100 mm of precipitation (dry season) varies from 2 in the north to 3 in the south, with high interannual variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Sombroek1">Sombroek 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Wagner1">Wagner et al. 2011</xref>). The geological background is a 2.2&ndash;1.9-Gyr-old crystalline basement, which makes up the oldest and most homogeneous part of the Guiana Shield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Delor1">Delor et al. 2003</xref>). Savannas and mangroves occur, but exclusively in the coastal sedimentary plain. Evergreen rainforest covers more than 90&percnt; of the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-FAOFoodandAgricultureOrganizationoftheUnitedNations1">FAO 2010</xref>). In 2014, 88&percnt; of the population (250,400 people) lived in the coastal strip in human-modified areas (artificial, agricultural, and disturbed areas) covering &sim;1,000 km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-ONFOfficeNationaldesForets1">ONF 2011</xref>). Outside this area, the average population density is 0.04 people km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-INSEEInstitutnationaldelastatistiqueetdesetudeseconomiques1">INSEE 2014</xref>).This study is based on data from 35 study sites distributed across French Guiana (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Among these sites, 10 were close to villages or towns, and thus were easily accessible and regularly hunted. The other 25 sites were located either within territory under strict protection laws, or far enough (at least 6 km on foot) from human activities to be considered free from hunting pressure, including that from indigenous communities.We used standard distance sampling methods to count Black Curassow individuals along line transects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Peres1">Peres 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Jimenez1">Jimenez et al. 2003</xref>). One design was used for all sampling sites, and consisted of 2&ndash;4 individual 3-km transects radiating from a central point. Transects were walked at a speed of &lt;1 km hr<sup>&minus;1</sup> twice daily, once in the morning (07:00&ndash;11:00) and once in the afternoon (14:30&ndash;18:00) by one observer per transect (C. Richard-Hansen, T. Denis, and others). Observers alternated transects on consecutive days to avoid observer bias. Encounters with Black Curassows (groups or individuals) and their locations along the transect were recorded. The perpendicular distance from the transect to the animal (or group centroid) was measured with a laser range finder to the nearest meter. Surveys were conducted during the dry season (between July 1 and December 31), except for 1 survey in January and 1 in June. Only adult-sized animals were observed during the surveys, likely because hatching takes place after the end of the dry season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Delacour1">Delacour and Amadon 2004</xref>, C. Richard-Hansen personal observation) and because birds reach adult size &lt;1 yr after hatching (C. Richard-Hansen personal observation). Each site was surveyed once during an 8-day field session. Surveys were conducted between 2000 and 2013, with more than two-thirds (23 of 35) conducted from 2007 onward.Only one site, Parar&eacute;, was surveyed more than once. Sampling surveys were conducted at the Parar&eacute; site twice a year (once in the rainy season and once in the dry season) for a period of 6 yr (from 2007 to 2013), representing 11 sampling surveys and a total of 154 half-day replicates. The extended sampling effort (&sim;920 km along 2 transects comprising 60 units each) at this site helped to highlight Black Curassow habitat relationships at the microhabitat scale. The Parar&eacute; site data were analyzed separately.All study sites were located in <italic>terra firme</italic> forests where no long-term flooding occurs. The sites were selected to ensure the most accurate representation of different landscape types in <italic>terra firme</italic> forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>): coastal plain (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 3 sites); plateau (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 9 sites); mountain (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 15 sites); multiconvex, e.g., dome form (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4 sites); and multiconcave, e.g., basin form (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4 sites). Environmental descriptors taken from field data and remote sensing were used for the 3 different scales of analysis.At the landscape scale (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 35 sites), we used 11 coarse-resolution descriptors extracted from remote sensing data within a 4-km radius around the centroid of each site. We used a recent geomorphological landform map (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. 2013</xref>) generated from full-resolution Shuttle Radar Topography Mission (SRTM; 1 arc sec &sim;30 m) data to obtain mean topographical parameters (slope, elevational range, and elevation). The proportion of hydromorphic areas and dominant geomorphological types (mesoforms, at a resolution of &sim;10 km<sup>2</sup>) was extracted. At 1 km<sup>2</sup> resolution, forest types were taken from remote sensing landscape classes (RSLC) based on the analysis of a 1-yr daily dataset (from January 1 to December 31, 2000) from the VEGETATION sensor of the SPOT-4 satellite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gond1">Gond et al. 2011</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t03">Table 3</xref>A).Acquisition of field descriptors was based on the standardized sampling protocol of the HABITAT program, which aims to describe all <italic>terra firme</italic> forests by analyzing the faunal and floral composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-RichardHansen1">Richard-Hansen et al. 2015</xref>). Each sampling transect used for animal censuses was divided into 30 0.2-ha units (100 &times; 20 m) described in the field with fine-resolution descriptors as follows: (1) 9 physical condition descriptors (mean slope, mean maximum slope, mean elevational range, elevation, abundance of rocky outcrops, and 4 plant abundances &lsqb;Rapataceae, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Euterpe</named-content></italic> spp., Bromeliaceae, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Carex</named-content></italic> spp.&rsqb;) as indicators of hydromorphic soil conditions; (2) 15 forest structure descriptors (ordinal variables for understory density, canopy openings &lsqb;importance of canopy gaps&rsqb;, and liana density, and continuous variables for canopy height, understory palm density, total palm density, total tree density, tree &lsqb;20&ndash;30 cm DBH&rsqb; density, tree &lsqb;55&ndash;75 cm DBH&rsqb; density, total tree basal area, tree &lsqb;20&ndash;30 cm DBH&rsqb; basal area, tree &lsqb;55&ndash;75 cm DBH&rsqb; basal area, mean number of tree-fall gaps, mean size of tree-fall gaps, and total area of tree-fall gaps); and (3) botanical composition: Density of tree species (trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>) equal to or larger than 20 cm DBH<sub>130</sub> (diameter at breast height measured 130 cm above the forest floor) using rapid forestry surveys (completed by S. Guitet, O. Brunaux, G. Jaouen, and others) that proved to be sufficiently effective to distinguish 50 botanical families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet3">Guitet et al. 2014</xref>). All descriptors were collected over a period of 1 mo before conducting Black Curassow counts.The dataset resulting from the 6-yr survey at Parar&eacute; research station was used to examine Black Curassow habitat relationships at the microhabitat scale. We used the same field descriptors for the microhabitat scale as those used at the forest scale, except when the descriptor captured no variability (identical values) across transect units (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t03">Table 3</xref>C).Explanatory variables are often correlated, and strong collinearity may affect the ability to correctly estimate model parameters and interpret the results of models. Thus, we first ran a principal components analysis (PCA) on the entire set of variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Rao1">Rao 1964</xref>) at the landscape scale. Secondly, we used the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kaiser1">Kaiser (1960)</xref> rule, which recommends that only the axes with an eigenvalue at least equal to 1 are kept. Above this threshold, the amount of variance of the component is greater than that contributed by 1 variable. Finally, we kept the explanatory variable most correlated with each selected PCA axis using factorial plans and absolute and relative contributions.At the forest and microhabitat scales, we first ran a PCA on each of the 2 distinct sets of covariates, i.e. physical condition and forest structure descriptors. For each scale of analysis, we implemented the same methodological framework as above to select the explanatory covariates. We then applied a correspondence analysis (CA) to the 3<sup>rd</sup> dataset on tree abundance (botanical composition) to show the distributional patterns of families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Hill1">Hill 1974</xref>). The selection of the number of axes was guided by the break in the ranked eigenvalues plot. If no break was observed, we selected the 1<sup>st</sup> axes that contributed to 80&percnt; of the total inertia. Botanical families were chosen based on their absolute and relative contribution and their biological significance.Environmental features can cause major biases due to different sources of measurement error. Among the landscape types distinguishable from their landform types and forest structure, visibility for observers may be variable, which may affect the detection of animals. Furthermore, the Black Curassow is a large and mobile species with a home range size of at least 80 ha (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deCoster1">de Coster 2011</xref>), which is close to that of similar cracid species such as the Salvin's Curassow (<italic>Mitu salvini</italic>) and Yellow-knobbed Curassow (<italic>Crax daubentoni</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Parra1">Parra et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Bertsch1">Bertsch and Barreto 2008</xref>). Temporary emigration (individuals entering and leaving the sampled strip during the survey period) can also bias density estimates because the assumption of a closed population no longer holds. Consequently, we used the generalized distance sampling model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref>, which is an extension of the <italic>N</italic>-mixture models for repeated count data. Compared with other distance sampling methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Marques1">Marques and Buckland 2003</xref>), the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref> model determines the probability of detecting an animal given its presence (<italic>p</italic>) and the probability of its being present during the survey period (&phi;), thus allowing studies with an open population. This hierarchical model allows inferences to be drawn about the superpopulation size (<italic>M</italic>) (i.e. the total number of individuals likely to use the sampled strip during the survey period). The superpopulation size is an outcome of a discrete probability distribution (Poisson or negative binomial) with mean (&lambda;). Black Curassow abundance (<italic>N</italic>, computed as the product of the superpopulation size and &phi;) can be estimated while incorporating multiple covariates in order to: (1) explain variations in density due to environmental features; (2) minimize or eliminate biases due to temporary emigration (the probability that individuals may be out of the sampling area during the survey period &equals; 1 &minus; &phi;); and (3) minimize detection bias when objects are easier to see in some conditions than in others. Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) was used to compare models.At each scale of analysis, the abundance of Black Curassows was modeled as a random effect with a negative binomial (landscape and forest scales) or a Poisson (microhabitat scale) distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kery1">K&eacute;ry et al. 2005</xref>) using the number of Black Curassows observed per experimental unit and per replicate. All continuous covariates were scaled to avoid convergence problems. We assumed that temporary emigration was constant across experimental units. We applied the half-normal function to the pooled data from all sites at the forest and landscape scales and from all transect units at the microhabitat scale to estimate the detection probability parameters. At the landscape and forest scales, the 2&ndash;4 individual 3-km transects were considered as a single line transect (experimental unit). Ten and 13 replicates were carried out during the repeat survey at the landscape and forest scales, respectively. The sampling effort across sites varied from 58 to 174 km (mean 116.3 &plusmn; 18.9 SD km) at the landscape scale and from 75 to 226 km (151.2 &plusmn; 25.8 km) at the forest scale.At the microhabitat scale (estimates from the Parar&eacute; site), we considered each transect unit (20 &times; 100 m) of the 2 3-km transects as an experimental unit. Given the small number of Black Curassows observed (85 individuals) during the 6-yr survey, we cumulated the 154 half-day replicates by 14 half-days to obtain 11 new replicates in order to facilitate model convergence. The sampling effort per transect unit was 15.3 km. We used the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref> model to estimate the local distribution of Black Curassows according to the characteristics of microhabitats.We ran <italic>N</italic>-mixture models following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref> using Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) to rank models and to calculate Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>). Akaike weights may be interpreted as the probability that the model is the &lsquo;best' among all of the candidate models. The combined weight (relative importance) of each covariate can be compared by summing the Akaike weights of all models that contain each respective covariate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). A set of all candidate models corresponded to all of the combinations of additive models, and each covariate (and parameter) thus appeared an equal number of times within the candidate model set. At the 3 scales of analysis, the combined weight (relative variable importance) of an environmental covariate can thus be examined to explain Black Curassow habitat relationships. Akaike weights were also used to calculate model-averaged coefficients, such as the environmental covariate parameters and their standard errors. We calculated predictions by model-averaging the density estimates (using function modavgPred in R package AICcmodavg; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Mazerolle1">Mazerolle 2015</xref>) of all candidate models with a &Delta;AIC lower than 2 units. The model-averaged coefficients of each explanatory covariate were calculated as the sum of the product of the Akaike weights and the estimated coefficients of all the candidate models over the combined weight of the covariate. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Cade1">Cade (2015)</xref> stressed that averaging model parameters makes no sense because the scaling of units in the denominators of the regression coefficients changes when there is multicollinearity among predictors. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Cade1">Cade (2015)</xref> proposed solutions for multiple linear regression models and generalized linear models. We think that these methods should not apply for the model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref> because their methods have not been validated for this hierarchical model type. Thus, the values of model-averaged parameters are used here to illustrate covariate effects, but not to predict density. In addition, the effects of the most important covariates on Black Curassow density are shown by fixing the values of the other covariates when displaying results in graph form. We did not include the first-order interactions of covariates in the global model because of their large number.At the landscape scale, we added latitude and longitude to the explanatory remote sensing covariates when building the global model in order to account for a possible regional linear gradient effect. In this way, we tried to avoid a potential unimodal or multimodal pattern within the Black Curassow distributional range caused by climatic or other biophysical conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Morrison1">Morrison et al. 2006</xref>). Hunting pressure was also included through a presence&ndash;absence predictor, because hunting is known to have a strong influence on the density of game species such as the Black Curassow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Peres2">Peres and Dolman 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Bodmer1">Bodmer and Robinson 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy2">de Thoisy et al. 2009</xref>). A site was considered to be hunted when it was easily accessible from roads, trails, or rivers and when there were indications that the area was hunted (e.g., presence of hunters, shotgun cartridges, and other clues, and forest tracks). Given that <italic>terra firme</italic> forests differ in structure and physical characteristics (e.g., topographical differences), we used landscape types as detection covariates in the global model to correct any bias caused by potential differences in visibility among sites at the landscape scale.At the forest scale, we selected models using 2 stages because the number of sampled sites was still low compared with the number of potential predictor covariates, even though the 3 sets of covariates were reduced by PCA and CA. We first built 3 global submodels, each with a reduced set of field covariates: descriptors of physical conditions, with mean maximum slope, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Carex</named-content></italic> spp., and abundance of rocky outcrops; descriptors of forest structure, with tree density &lsqb;55&ndash;75 cm DBH&rsqb;, mean size of tree-fall gaps (ground-surface disturbance), and total tree, total palm, and understory densities; and botanical composition, with Arecaceae, Burseraceae, Lauraceae, Legumiunosae&ndash;Mimosoideae, and Sapotaceae abundances. Second, we built a final global model including covariates from the previous model selection stage when their combined weight was greater than 0.60. We included latitude and longitude as regional predictors for the same reasons given for the landscape scale. Mean maximum slope and understory density are probably important environmental features affecting observations of this terrestrial species, which is why we tested their effects as detection covariates in the global model. We assumed that the steepest reliefs and densest forests could reduce observer capacity to detect Black Curassows.At the microhabitat scale, we built the global model with the explanatory covariates retained by PCA and CA for each set of environmental descriptors: descriptors of physical conditions, with mean maximum slope; descriptors of forest structure, with tree &lsqb;55&ndash;75 cm DBH&rsqb; basal area, tree &lsqb;20&ndash;30 cm DBH&rsqb; density, canopy height, area of tree-fall gaps, and liana density; and botanical composition, with Caesalpinioideae subfamily (Leguminosae family). We included mean maximum slope and understory density as detection covariates in the global model.Remote sensing data made it possible to extrapolate predictions from the landscape model to all of French Guiana. We calculated the predicted density of Black Curassow individuals (i.e. the predicted number of adult-sized Black Curassows per km<sup>2</sup>). Predictions of Black Curassow density on the map are shown at the same resolution as the descriptors extracted from GIS (i.e. a 50.4-km<sup>2</sup> pixel) an area similar to the 4-km sampling radius around each study site. We estimated that hunting was likely to occur in a 2.5-km-wide buffer zone on each side of the main rivers and roads and around human settlements, excluding strictly protected areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy1">de Thoisy et al. 2010</xref>; see map to the bottom right in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f03">Figure 3</xref>).Predictive map of the distribution of adult-sized Black Curassow (individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) in French Guiana according to the landscape-scale model. Black Curassow densities were not estimated outside <italic>terra firme</italic> forests. Forests other than <italic>terra firme</italic> forests (e.g., white-sand forests, seasonally flooded forests such as mangroves, swamp forests) that were not considered in this study are shown in green. Human-modified areas (savannas and artificial, agricultural, and disturbed areas) are represented in white: 90&percnt; of the population lives in the coastal strip and western border (expertise fonci&egrave;re du littoral et des territoires isol&eacute;s de Guyane 2005&ndash;2008&ndash;2011, from Office National des For&ecirc;ts &lsqb;ONF&rsqb;, updated in 2014, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geoguyane.fr/catalogue/">http://www.geoguyane.fr/catalogue/</ext-link>). Areas of water (main rivers, the reservoir of the Petit Saut hydroelectric dam, and the Atlantic Ocean) are drawn in blue. The areas in gray on the map to the bottom right (2.5-km-wide buffer along the main rivers and roads and around human settlements) were considered to be hunted.All analyses were performed using R 3.0.3 with the ade4, unmarked, AICcmodavg, and ggplot2 packages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>).No single landscape-scale model stood out as the best among the top-ranked models (those with the lowest &Delta;AIC) because all 9 top models differed by &lt;2.0 AIC units (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t04">Table 4</xref>A). AIC weights were low, but the large number of candidate models must be taken into consideration. The combined weight of the landscape type covariate was 58&percnt;, which lends similar support to the hypotheses that landscape types affect or do not affect detection probabilities. However, the lowest effect on detection probability was found for coastal plain landscapes, while the effect was highest for all-slope topography landscapes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t01">Table 1</xref>A). A number of common abundance covariates clearly featured among the top-ranked models. Mean slope and hunting were the most important covariates, with combined weights (relative variable importance) of 96&percnt; and 99&percnt;, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t02">Table 2</xref>A). The number of adult-sized individuals increased as the mean slope became steeper in both hunted and unhunted sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f04">Figure 4</xref>). Although latitude was included in the 2 top-ranked models, the influence of this factor on Black Curassow distribution was uncertain, with a combined weight of 58&percnt;. We note, however, that Black Curassow density was correlated negatively with latitude (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t02">Table 2</xref>A). Estimated Black Curassow density ranged from 0.37 to 1.08 individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (median: 0.64; 90&percnt; range: 0.43&ndash;1.06) across the 10 hunted sites, and from 1.47 to 5.31 individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (median: 2.96; 90&percnt; range: 1.99&ndash;4.26; &phi; &equals; 0.15) across the 25 unhunted sites. When we checked for overlap in the confidence intervals for this species&ndash;habitat relationship, Black Curassow density differed significantly (based on upper and lower 95&percnt; confidence intervals) between hunted and unhunted sites where the mean slope was &gt;2&deg; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f04">Figure 4</xref>). Predicted density was calculated for the center of French Guiana (3.755&deg;N, 53.181&deg;W) and using the median values of the other covariates (simple smaller landforms &lsqb;SSL&rsqb; &equals; 31.5&percnt;, and high forest with regular canopy, mostly <italic>terra firme</italic> forest &lsqb;RSLC19&rsqb; &equals; 52.1&percnt;).Summary of detection covariates in Black Curassow habitat models at multiple scales in the <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of French Guiana. Detection probability is denoted by <italic>p</italic>. The combined weight (relative importance) of each explanatory covariate was calculated as the sum of the Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) across all of the models in which the parameter of interest appeared. The model-averaged coefficients (parameters and standard errors) of each covariate were calculated as the sum of the product of the Akaike weights and the estimated coefficients of all of the candidate models over the combined weight of the covariate. The model-averaged 95&percnt; confidence limits (95&percnt; CL) were calculated using model-averaged standard errors. For the landscape types (LandS), SLO &equals; all-slope topography landscapes, PLA &equals; more or less dissected plateaus, MCX &equals; typical multiconvex landscapes, PLN &equals; coastal plain landscapes, and MCV &equals; multiconcave and joint-valley landscapes (see landscape classification by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. &lsqb;2013&rsqb;</xref>). For the forest and microhabitat scales, MMS &equals; mean maximum slope, and USD &equals; understory density (see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t03">Table 3</xref>).Summary of abundance covariates in Black Curassow habitat models at multiple scales in the <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of French Guiana. Population abundance is denoted by &lambda;. The combined weight (relative importance) of each explanatory covariate was calculated as the sum of the Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) across all of the models in which the parameter of interest appeared. The model-averaged coefficients (parameters and standard errors) of each covariate were calculated as the sum of the product of the Akaike weights and the estimated coefficients of all of the candidate models over the combined weight of the covariate. The model-averaged 95&percnt; confidence limits (95&percnt; CL) were calculated using model-averaged standard errors. Covariate abbreviations: MS &equals; remote sensing mean slope; Hunt &equals; hunting pressure; (pres) &equals; presence of hunting pressure; Lat &equals; latitude; Lon &equals; longitude; RSLC19 &equals; high forest with regular canopy (mostly <italic>terra firme</italic> forest); SSL &equals; simple smaller landforms; USD &equals; understory density; TTD &equals; total tree density; Mimo &equals; Mimosoideae abundance; Are &equals; Arecaceae abundance; Lau &equals; Lauraceae abundance; MMS &equals; mean maximum slope; &lsqb;20&ndash;30&rsqb;BA &equals; tree (20&ndash;30 cm DBH) basal area; &lsqb;55&ndash;75&rsqb;TD &equals; tree (55&ndash;75 cm DBH) density; CanH &equals; Canopy height; LD &equals; liana density; TFG &equals; size of tree-fall gaps; and Caes &equals; Caesalpinioideae abundance.Landscape-scale predictions (thick lines) of the estimated density (<italic>N</italic>) of adult-sized Black Curassow (individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) in French Guiana in response to the presence (blue line) or absence (red line) of hunting and mean landform slope. Dashed lines represent upper and lower 95&percnt; confidence intervals. Density estimates were calculated for the center of French Guiana (3.755&deg;N, 53.181&deg;W) and using the median values of the other covariates (SSL &lsqb;simple smaller landforms&rsqb; &equals; 31.5&percnt;, and RSLC19 &lsqb;high forest with regular canopy, mostly <italic>terra firme</italic> forest&rsqb; &equals; 52.1&percnt;).The 5 top models (out of 128 candidate models) for the forest scale were very similar, and represented 56&percnt; of the cumulative weight of the set of all candidate models (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t04">Table 4</xref>B). Mean maximum slope (MMS) and understory density (USD) had negative and positive effects, respectively, on the probability of detection of Black Curassows (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t01">Table 1</xref>B), which was consistent with our expectations. The combined weight for <italic>p</italic>(MMS &plus; USD) was 94&percnt; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t01">Table 1</xref>B), which supports the hypothesis that these 2 covariates influence the detection of Black Curassow individuals. With regard to abundance covariates, the combined weights of the Arecaceae, Lauraceae, and Mimosoideae families were 94&percnt;, 80&percnt;, and 79&percnt;, respectively. The effects of Arecaceae and Mimosaceae on abundance were negative, while the effect of Lauraceae was positive (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t02">Table 2</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Out of the 51 botanical families, these 3 botanical families were the only ones that were likely to influence Black Curassow distribution. None of the physical descriptors (topography, hydromorphy, and so on) helped to explain Black Curassow distribution at the forest scale. Black Curassow densities ranged from 1.52 to 5.48 individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (median: 3.01; 90&percnt; range: 1.66&ndash;4.60; &phi; &equals; 0.13) across the subset of 20 unhunted sites in which these data were collected.Forest-scale predictions (thick lines) of the estimated superpopulation density (<italic>M</italic>) of adult-sized Black Curassow (individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) in French Guiana in response to botanical composition: (<bold>A</bold>) Arecaceae, (<bold>B</bold>) Mimosoideae, and (<bold>C</bold>) Lauraceae. Dashed lines represent upper and lower 95&percnt; confidence intervals. Density estimates were calculated for the center of French Guiana (3.755&deg;N, 53.181&deg;W) and using the median values of the other covariates: Understory density (index) &equals; 0.38, Arecaceae &equals; 10 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>, and/or Mimosoideae &equals; 14.5 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>, and/or Lauraceae &equals; 4.5 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>.The 8 top models, out of 256 candidate models for the microhabitat scale, all had a &Delta;AIC &lt;2 units. No candidate model stood out clearly among these top 8 models (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t04">Table 4</xref>C). At this scale, the combined weight of the mean maximum slope and understory density was only 13&percnt;, indicating that Black Curassow detection was unlikely to have been affected by these 2 environmental features (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t01">Table 1</xref>C). These covariates appeared for the first time in the 25<sup>th</sup>-ranked model, which had a &Delta;AIC of 3.99. However, our results showed that canopy height and mean maximum slope stood out among the covariates that influenced abundance, with combined weights of 93&percnt; and 74&percnt;, respectively. Black Curassow abundance increased with increasing canopy height and decreasing mean maximum slope (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t02">Table 2</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f06">Figure 6</xref>). Local density ranged from 0.11 to 0.57 individuals per transect unit (median: 0.26; 90&percnt; range: 0.15&ndash;0.49; &phi; &equals; 0.016).Microhabitat-scale predictions (thick lines) of the estimated superpopulation density (<italic>M</italic>) of adult-sized Black Curassow (individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) in French Guiana in response to (<bold>A</bold>) canopy height and (<bold>B</bold>) mean maximum slope. Dashed lines represent upper and lower 95&percnt; confidence intervals. Density estimates were calculated using the median values of the other covariates: Understory density (index) &equals; 2.0, mean tree (55&ndash;75 cm DBH) density &equals; 23.1 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>, mean tree (20&ndash;30 cm DBH) density &equals; 112.6 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>, Caesalpinioideae abundance &equals; 40.0 trees ha<sup>&minus;1</sup>, Liana density (index) &equals; 1, size of tree-fall gaps &equals; 0 m<sup>2</sup>, and mean maximum slope &equals; 12.5&deg; or canopy height &equals; 30 m.From the landscape model, we estimated Black Curassow density (adult-sized individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) for the whole of French Guiana (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The lowest predicted density of Black Curassows was on the coastal plain (low relief and inhabited areas), along the main rivers where there was potential hunting pressure, and in 2 southern parts of the territory corresponding to particular geomorphological landscapes (i.e. multiconcave reliefs; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. 2013</xref>). In contrast, predicted Black Curassow density was highest in mountainous forested areas (i.e. areas with steeper slopes), in the southwestern and central eastern parts of French Guiana.The population distribution of Black Curassows was strongly influenced by topography. Between sampling sites with little topographic variability and more mountainous sites, the predicted densities of Black Curassows varied by a factor of &sim;3 for hunted areas and &sim;4 for unhunted areas. We hypothesize that the relationship between the mean slope of landforms and the population density of Black Curassows is due to the fact that areas with higher mean slopes are those that best meet the ecological requirements of the species.Topography is an indirect but effective predictor (i.e. good proxy; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Austin1">Austin and Smith 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guisan1">Guisan and Zimmermann 2000</xref>) that integrates information about historical ecological trajectories leading to divergences in <italic>terra firme</italic> forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>). The mean slope of landforms was strongly negatively correlated with soil hydromorphy in our dataset (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.66, <italic>P</italic>-value &equals; 1.5 e&minus;9), and in French Guiana reflects a generally varied landscape relief. Together, relief, topography, and soil hydromorphy drive vegetation characteristics such as forest structure and the botanical composition of tropical forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Vormisto1">Vormisto et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deCastilho1">de Castilho et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Ferry1">Ferry and Morneau 2010</xref>).Sites with high curassow density were generally steeper (e.g., plateau and all-slope landscapes). High densities of Black Curassows may be due to decreases in the size of home ranges or to overlap between home ranges. The latter may be important for this species, with an overlap of 45&percnt; and 75&percnt; (95&percnt; kernel method) for 2 home ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deCoster1">de Coster 2011</xref>). Qualitatively and/or quantitatively, the steepest sites appear to offer better resources and/or environmental conditions for this species.Another hypothesis to explain the relationship between Black Curassows and mean slope is the influence of long-term human occupation. The main rivers and coastal strip of French Guiana have been inhabited for several thousand years. Hunting impacts may decrease from the inhabited areas and access paths to the steepest areas because the increase in relief may restrict hunters' penetration into the forest. However, in most cases, hunters do not move for more than half a day from their base camp (along rivers) or from access paths, during which time they may walk several kilometers of tropical forest trails, making long-term human disturbance an unlikely explanation for the relationship between Black Curassow population density and mean slope. Furthermore, while human occupation over time may have shaped the distribution of Black Curassows close to the coastal strip, it is unlikely to have done so in the central and southern parts of French Guiana where human population density is very low (0.04 people km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) and the human population (27,404 inhabitants) is concentrated in a dozen villages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-INSEEInstitutnationaldelastatistiqueetdesetudeseconomiques1">INSEE 2014</xref>).Our landscape model confirms the vulnerability of the Black Curassow to hunting pressure, a result already found for other Cracidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Begazo1">Begazo and Bodmer 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Brooks2">Brooks et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Barrio1">Barrio 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kattan1">Kattan et al. 2016</xref>). Hunting is the most important factor explaining the distribution of Black Curassows across French Guiana. Even when optimum resources and conditions are available (steep mean slopes), the population drops to a very low density in sites affected by hunting. Like other Cracidae across the Amazon basin, the Black Curassow is a popular game bird. Its meat is sought after, and its large body size and behavior make it easy to find and hunt when the population density is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Brooks2">Brooks et al. 2001</xref>). During a 15-yr hunting survey carried out in French Guiana, of 8,069 prey animals, Black Curassows represented &sim;5&percnt; of prey animals recorded and 40&percnt; of the bird biomass (C. Richard-Hansen personal observation). A preliminary study has already suggested that the Black Curassow is unsustainably hunted across French Guiana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Niel1">Niel et al. 2008</xref>). The high vulnerability of the species to hunting makes it a good candidate to be an indicator of hunting pressure on a broad scale, as highlighted by some authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Brooks1">Brooks 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy1">de Thoisy et al. 2010</xref>). However, our results show that the influence of slope on densities also has to be taken into account in the assessment of the potential impact of hunting: in steep areas, a low density of Black Curassows in hunting surveys would probably be an indication of highly unsustainable hunting, whereas in areas with no steep slopes, low densities would mainly be a result of poor habitat quality.The forest types associated with the largest Black Curassow populations were characterized by the lowest abundances of Arecaceae (palms) and Mimosoideae and the highest abundance of Lauraceae. A major latitudinal gradient and significant subregional patterns in tree composition have been highlighted in French Guianan forests, which can be explained by the geomorphological features that incorporate current and past environmental filters and historical biogeographical processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>).The latitudinal gradient is partly related to the increase in Mimosoideae abundance from north to south. Mimosoideae are also found in high abundance in both the peneplains of the south and on steeply sloping reliefs in forests. Lauraceae abundance is particularly high in the steepest areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. 2015</xref>). Lauraceae is one of the 6 most important plant families in cracid diets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Munoz1">Mu&ntilde;oz and Kattan 2007</xref>). However, diets are broad and plastic in Cracidae. Thus, diet is unlikely to explain variation in population density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Munoz1">Mu&ntilde;oz and Kattan 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kattan1">Kattan et al. 2016</xref>). Furthermore, in the case of the Parar&eacute; site, Lauraceae represents only a low proportion (&sim;5&percnt;) of the diet of Black Curassows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Erard2">Erard et al. 2007</xref>), but the population density estimate is high (4.55 individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) based on the forest model. Complementary information is needed to relate Lauraceae abundance to its dietary role in Black Curassow distribution. In our dataset, the palm taxa were made up of 52&percnt; <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Oenocarpus</named-content></italic> spp. and 33&percnt; <italic>Astrocaryum sciophilum</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet2">Guitet et al. (2015)</xref> did not note any patterns in palm distribution across French Guiana. We did not find any concrete interpretation for the effects of botanical families on Black Curassow densities.At this modeling scale, it is risky to link the effect of a botanical family with a particular type of animal behavior (foraging, nesting, shelter, etc.) because species&ndash;habitat relationships occur at the population level and there is therefore no direct tree abundance effect on the behavior of an individual or a group. We do not think that botanical families directly influence Black Curassow distribution, but rather suggest that they determine patterns of favorable or unfavorable habitat distribution associated with particular forest types. Our results at the forest scale were not always consistent with those at the landscape scale, even though our analyses were implemented at the same spatial extent. We focused on ecological processes occurring on a smaller scale than that of the landscape by using fine-resolution descriptors.In addition to identifying landscape and forest types favorable for Black Curassow populations, we also tried to identify Black Curassow habitat relationships at the microhabitat scale. Black Curassows were considerably more common in areas with the highest trees and the flattest topography (i.e. on hilltops). These microhabitats were visited 5 times more often than others. Our data showed that the average canopy height of bottomlands (28 m) was shorter than that of slopes (32.5 m) and hilltops (31.1 m). Considering that the Black Curassow diet comprises a high proportion of fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Erard1">Erard et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Erard2">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Munoz1">Mu&ntilde;oz and Kattan 2007</xref>), mainly from tall trees, hilltops may be important for foraging. Black Curassows also consume a significant proportion of fruits from shrubs and smaller trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Erard2">Erard et al. 2007</xref>) that can be found in other microhabitats. However, bottomlands such as riversides and <italic>Euterpe</italic>-dominated forests situated mainly along the southern transects and slopes along the northern transects were used less frequently than hilltops.The Black Curassow is a mobile species that uses the center of its stable home range more frequently than the edges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deCoster1">de Coster 2011</xref>). This biological characteristic may produce spatial autocorrelation, e.g., locations close to each other may display more similar values than those farther apart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Dormann1">Dormann et al. 2007</xref>). Black Curassow distribution in core home ranges may therefore be spatially dependent. Black Curassows may be found in unfavorable or &lsquo;neutral' areas simply because they are close to other favorable areas within the core home range.We did not include spatial autocorrelation in this study. The model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref> makes the use of most methods impossible by reducing spatial autocorrelation in model residuals. Not having found any satisfactory methods that would have allowed us to take spatial autocorrelation into account, coefficient estimates may consequently be biased (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Dormann1">Dormann et al. 2007</xref>). Given that our microhabitat-scale analysis was conducted at only one site (Parar&eacute;), we must be cautious in extrapolating Black Curassow habitat relationships to the rest of French Guiana. Available resources and environmental conditions differ, thereby affecting microhabitat choices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gaillard1">Gaillard et al. 2010</xref>). Moreover, species&ndash;habitat relationships are generally density dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gadenne1">Gadenne et al. 2014</xref>).Predictive mapping based on mean slope and hunting pressure revealed significant heterogeneity in the distribution of Black Curassow populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f03">Figure 3</xref>). It is generally believed that population abundance is a reliable way of measuring the habitat quality of a species on a broad scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Bock1">Bock and Jones 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Johnson2">Johnson 2007</xref>), but this is not necessarily the case at the local scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-VanHorne1">Van Horne 1983</xref>). The predictive map of Black Curassow distribution shows that low densities may occur even in remote areas because of poor habitat quality, which, combined with hunting pressure and considering other recent studies on threats to this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deThoisy1">de Thoisy et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Clement1">Cl&eacute;ment et al. 2014</xref>), should be taken into account in defining the conservation status of the Black Curassow.Predictive maps have a number of direct and indirect management applications as decision-support tools for the development of conservation policies. From our predictive map of Black Curassow distribution, we recommend, as the best course of action, maintaining connectivity between Black Curassow populations across French Guiana's forests by (1) partly restricting hunting along rivers, roads, and trails, particularly in the north, and (2) planning protected areas to optimize reserve functions and corridors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 1991</xref>) according to the habitat quality of this sensitive species. Mountainous areas where Black Curassows are most abundant are also those with a high rate of endemism and rare species, thus providing more diverse and singular environmental conditions (e.g., plateaus on lateritic crust, deep valleys, cliffs, and granitic outcrops; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-deGranville1">de Granville et al. &lsqb;1993&rsqb;</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Sarthou1">Sarthou et al. &lsqb;2003&rsqb;</xref> for vascular plants). Therefore, optimum Black Curassow habitat is potentially of high conservation value.However, with almost 30&percnt; of French Guiana already under high protection status, it is unlikely that many new protected areas will be created in the future. A second, and perhaps more realistic, course of action would be to introduce direct restrictions on the hunting of Black Curassows, either through species protection measures or by setting hunting quotas, as was recently done in French Guiana (see Order of the Prefect no. 583, Guiana Environment, Planning and Housing Directorate, April 12th, 2011, which sets hunting quotas for various species including the Black Curassow). The variation in density estimates for Black Curassows across the whole of French Guiana, which is related to habitat characteristics, should be taken into account when establishing hunting quotas. However, sustainable quotas for this species would need to be low as our results lead us to believe that, whatever the intensity of hunting pressure, Black Curassow density is always close to zero in hunted areas.How far human disturbance affects the distribution of the species is difficult to estimate spatially because it depends on many complex factors. The exact locations and sizes of areas affected by hunting strongly depend on ease of access, distance to a populated area, and hunting practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Peres3">Peres and Lake 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kumara1">Kumara and Singh 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Willcox1">Willcox and Nambu 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Parry1">Parry et al. 2009</xref>). The hunted area estimate (map to the bottom right in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f03">Figure 3</xref>) should be refined, especially in areas that are more remote from the coastal strip and from inhabited areas. Even when rivers are large enough to reach these areas, the distance from a village could reduce the area actually hunted, particularly in the sparsely populated south of French Guiana, because access to more remote areas is costly and time consuming. Another required refinement is to adjust for high mean slope values, found in the extreme southwest of French Guiana due to the number of rocky outcrops (inselbergs), and thus overestimation of Black Curassow densities. The species does not often use the tops of these granitic outcrops, but can be found in high forests at their feet. There is a threshold value at which the effect of mean slope on Black Curassow density decreases. Furthermore, because of the lack of data on the steepest sites, there is significant uncertainty as regards Black Curassow density where the mean slope is &gt;20&deg; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f04">Figure 4</xref>).Our predictive map closely resembles the map based on the geomorphological landscape classification of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. (2013</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-t05">Table 5</xref>, Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f07">Figure 7</xref>). This confirms a landscape approach as a promising management and conservation tool for French Guiana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-RichardHansen1">Richard-Hansen et al. 2015</xref>).We showed that abiotic conditions (topographic descriptors) determined the spatial distribution of the Black Curassow at the landscape and microhabitat scales, while biotic conditions (botanical composition and canopy height) were important at the forest and microhabitat scales. Our results for the different scales studied show that the distribution of this species may be explained by both biotic and abiotic conditions, but that neither type is more closely associated with one scale or another.Combining field and remote sensing data in a multiscale approach to species&ndash;habitat relationships helps our understanding of the underlying biological processes of these relationships and our interpretation of which habitat components are chosen by a species. Several studies have implemented this kind of strategy to identify how a species perceives and responds to resources or environmental gradients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kie1">Kie et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Betts1">Betts et al. 2006</xref>), underlining the importance of taking spatial extent and measurement resolution into account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guisan1">Guisan and Zimmermann 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Morrison1">Morrison et al. 2006</xref>). For our study, the mean slope measured by remote sensing over large areas was a relevant predictor of distribution, whereas the mean slope measured along linear transects during field sampling was not, which shows that ecological significance may differ depending on spatial resolution. Remote sensing data made it possible to extrapolate density predictions and to build density distribution maps. Data from remote sensing or other GIS layers reflect not only biophysical conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Kerr1">Kerr and Ostrovsky 2003</xref>), but also anthropic disturbances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Peres4">Peres et al. 2006</xref>). Greater availability of such data, together with new modeling techniques and GIS tools, should make it easier to map species distributions, not only over large spatial extents but also at smaller spatial scales, and to work at finer resolutions, e.g., to examine species&ndash;habitat relationships within the home range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Palminteri1">Palminteri et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Nagendra1">Nagendra et al. 2013</xref>).We are very grateful to all participants in the line transect surveys, including those from the ONCFS (Office National de la Chasse et de la Faune Sauvage) and PAG (Parc Amazonien de Guyane) institutions and some hard-working and passionate volunteers. Special thanks to St&eacute;phane Traissac, Marie-Pierre Etienne, H&eacute;ctor Rodr&iacute;guez-P&eacute;rez, and Herv&eacute; Lorm&eacute;e for their assistance, corrections, and constructive comments on how to improve the manuscript. The authors are grateful to 2 anonymous reviewers and the Associate Editor, Amy Davis, for helpful comments on previous versions of the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Funding was provided over many years by ONCFS and various external sources: the EU <italic>HABITAT</italic> and <italic>CHASSE</italic> programs, the French Ministry for Overseas Territories, the French Ministry of the Environment (ECOTROP program), the Parc Amazonien de Guyane (PAG), Office National des For&ecirc;ts, and the CNRS (Centre national de la recherche scientifique) Nouragues program. T.D. and B.H. were supported by a grant from the Investing for the Future program (Investissements d'Avenir) managed by the French National Research Agency (Agence nationale de la recherche, CEBA, ref. ANR-10-LABX-0025). None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript, nor required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> The animals were not treated badly nor captured. Data were collected respecting the lives and the habitats of the animals.<bold>Author contributions:</bold> T.D., B.H., G.J., S.G., O.B., and C.R.-H. conceived the idea, design, or experiment (supervised research, formulated question or hypothesis); T.D., G.J., S.G., O.B., and C.R.-H. performed the experiments (collected data, conducted the research); T.D., B. H., G.J., S.G., and C.R.-H. wrote the paper (or substantially edited the paper); T.D., B. H., S.G., and C.R.-H. developed or designed the methods; and T.D. analyzed the data.Summary of explanatory covariates in Black Curassow habitat models at multiple scales in the <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of French Guiana. VFL &equals; very flat landforms; SSL &equals; simple smaller landforms; LCL &equals; large complex landforms; HL &equals; high landforms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. 2013</xref>); RSLC18 &equals; low dense forest, including savanna on poorly drained soils; RSLC19 &equals; high forest with regular canopy (mostly <italic>terra firme</italic> forest); RSLC20 &equals; high forest with disrupted canopy; RSLC21 &equals; mixed high open forest; and RSLC22 &equals; open forest and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Euterpe</named-content></italic> spp. palm forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Gond1">Gond et al. 2011</xref>). Terms in square brackets represent the transformation type used to change the scale from transect units (fine-resolution field descriptors) to sites (larger scale of analysis).Summary of the modeling results for Black Curassow habitat relationships at multiple scales in the <italic>terra firme</italic> forests of French Guiana. For each model, &Delta;AIC is the difference between the model's Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) value and the minimum AIC of the set of all candidate models (landscape &equals; 128 candidate models, forest &equals; 128, microhabitat &equals; 256), and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the Akaike weight for a model, representing the probability that a given model is the best model in the set of candidate models. For each model description, Cum.w &equals; cumulative Akaike weight; <italic>K</italic> &equals; the number of estimated parameters; and &minus;2<italic>l</italic> &equals; the negative log-likelihood. Models are ranked in ascending order of &Delta;AIC, and only the top 9 models are shown for each scale. Detection probability is denoted by <italic>p</italic>, and &lambda; represents population abundance. LandS &equals; landscape types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. 2013</xref>), MS &equals; mean slope determined by remote sensing, Hunt &equals; presence or absence of hunting pressure, Lat &equals; latitude, Lon &equals; longitude, RSLC19 &equals; high forest with regular canopy (mostly <italic>terra firme</italic> forest), SSL &equals; simple smaller landforms, USD &equals; understory density, TTD &equals; total tree density, Mimo &equals; Mimosoideae abundance, Are &equals; Arecaceae abundance, Lau &equals; Lauraceae abundance, MMS &equals; mean maximum slope, &lsqb;20&ndash;35&rsqb;BA &equals; tree (20&ndash;35 cm DBH) basal area, &lsqb;55&ndash;75&rsqb;BA &equals; tree (55&ndash;75cm DBH) basal area, CanH &equals; canopy height, LD &equals; liana density, TFG &equals; size of tree-fall gaps, and Caes &equals; Caesalpinioideae abundance.Modeling Black Curassow distribution using landscapes as abundance covariates. We tested the predictive power of the landscape classification (LandS) of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. (2013)</xref> against that of remotely sensed mean slope (MS). We used the generalized distance sampling model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Chandler1">Chandler et al. (2011)</xref>, which is a hierarchical model that allows inference about the density of unmarked populations subject to temporary emigration and imperfect detection. We compared the LandS model, i.e. <italic>p</italic>(LandS) &lambda;(LandS &plus; Hunt &plus; Lat) with the MS top-ranked model, i.e. <italic>p</italic>(LandS) &lambda;(MS &plus; Hunt &plus; Lat) using Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC). The landscape classification proved to be appropriate to predict large-scale variations in Black Curassow densities with the highest values in mountainous landscapes (SLO). The coastal plain (PLN) landscape held the lowest densities. Although density prediction based on landscape classification (Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-f07">Figure 7</xref>) was obviously less accurate (AIC &equals; 2044.42) than direct mapping (Figure 3) from the landscape model (AIC &equals; 2034.42), this classification nevertheless captured the major patterns of variation in density. This is important because the work done here with Black Curassows will be difficult to pursue for all species of large animal in Guiana's forests. Whether or not the predictive power of this map is confirmed for other species or key groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-RichardHansen1">Richard-Hansen et al. 2015</xref>), the classification by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. (2013)</xref> is a good operational tool for the management of forests and game resources. For the landscape types (LandS), PLN &equals; coastal plain landscapes, MCX &equals; typical multiconvex landscapes, MCV &equals; multiconcave and joint-valley landscapes, PLA &equals; more or less dissected plateaus, and SLO &equals; all-slope topography landscapes. Hunt &equals; hunting pressure; (pres) &equals; presence of hunting pressure.Predictive map of the distribution of adult-sized Black Curassow (individuals km<sup>&minus;2</sup>) in French Guiana from the landscape classification by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-253-Guitet1">Guitet et al. (2013)</xref>: PLN &equals; coastal plain landscapes; MCX &equals; typical multiconvex landscapes; MCV &equals; multiconcave and joint-valley landscapes; PLA &equals; more or less dissected plateaus; and SLO &equals; all-slope topography landscapes. Black Curassow densities were not estimated outside <italic>terra firme</italic> forests. Forests other than <italic>terra firme</italic> forests (white-sand forests, seasonally flooded forests such as mangroves, swamp forests, etc.) that were not considered in this study are shown in green. Human-modified areas (savannas and artificial, agricultural, and disturbed areas) are represented in white: 90&percnt; of the population lives in the coastal strip and western border (expertise fonci&egrave;re du littoral et des territoires isol&eacute;s de Guyane 2005&ndash;2008&ndash;2011, from Office National des For&ecirc;ts &lsqb;ONF&rsqb;, updated in 2014, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geoguyane.fr/catalogue/">http://www.geoguyane.fr/catalogue/</ext-link>). Areas of water (main rivers, the reservoir of the Petit Saut hydroelectric dam, and the Atlantic Ocean) are drawn in blue. The areas in gray on the map to the bottom right (2.5-km-wide buffer along the main rivers and roads and around human settlements) were considered to be hunted.