Western Veeries use an eastern shortest-distance pathway: New insights to migration routes and phenology using light-level geolocatorsEcological causes and consequences of bird orientationOptimal bird migration revisitedGreat-circle migration of Arctic passerinesMigration along orthodromic sun compass routes by arctic birdsLong-distance migration: Evolution and determinantsOrientation along great circles by migrating birds using a sun compassVeery (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>)Lineage origin and expansion of a Neotropical migrant songbird after recent glaciation eventsThe effects of geolocator drag and weight on the flight ranges of small migrantsMigrant&ndash;habitat relationships during stopover along an ecological barrier: Extrinsic constraints and conservation implicationsDo mature forest birds prefer early-successional habitat during the post-fledging period?A meta-analysis of the effects of geolocator application on birdsLight-level geolocators reveal strong migratory connectivity and within-winter movements for a coastal California Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>) populationDramatic intraspecific differences in migratory routes, stopover sites and wintering areas, revealed using light-level geolocatorsHybrid songbirds employ intermediate routes in a migratory divideFuel reserves affect migratory orientation of thrushes and sparrows both before and after crossing an ecological barrier near their breeding groundsThe ade4 package: Implementing the duality diagram for ecologistsRecent advances in understanding migration systems of New World land birdsTracking migratory songbirds: Accuracy of light-level loggers (geolocators) in forest habitatsGeographic origins and timing of fall migration of the Veery in northern ColombiaDark-bellied Brent Geese <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta bernicla</named-content> bernicla</italic>, as recorded by satellite telemetry, do not minimize flight distance during spring migrationVariable detours in long-distance migration across ecological barriers and their relation to habitat availability at groundIntratropical migration of a Nearctic-Neotropical songbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>) in South America with implications for migration theoryVeery (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>) wintering locations, migratory connectivity, and a revision of its winter range using geolocator technologyGeosphere: Spherical Trigonometry. R package version 1.3-8Theory of geolocation by light levelsLinking breeding and wintering grounds of neotropical migrant songbirds using stable hydrogen isotopic analysis of feathersOn the importance of stopover sites to migrating birdsA comprehensive change detection method for updating the National Land Cover Database to circa 2011A new approach to linear filtering and prediction problemsThe role of atmospheric conditions in the seasonal dynamics of North American migration flywaysEvolutionary precursors of long-distance migration: Resource availability and movement patterns in neotropical landbirdsGeolocation by light: Accuracy and precision affected by environmental factorsThe detection of disease clustering and a generalized regression approachEstimating geolocator accuracy for a migratory songbird using live ground-truthing in tropical forestEvidence of food-based competition among passerine migrants during stopoverAn allometric function to fit leg-loop harnesses to terrestrial birdsCan conditions experienced during migration limit the population levels of birds?Evolution of long-distance migration in and historical biogeography of <italic>Catharus</italic> thrushes: A molecular phylogenetic approachState-space models of individual animal movementNew harness design for attachment of radio transmitters to small passerinesTrue winter range of the Veery (C<italic>atharus fuscescens</italic>): Lessons for determining winter ranges of species that winter in the tropicsPhenological matching across hemispheres in a long-distance migratory birdA state-space model to derive bluefin tuna movement and habitat from archival tagsThe evolution of bird migration&mdash;A synthesisEstablishing the breeding provenance of a temperate-wintering North American passerine, the Golden-crowned Sparrow, using light-level geolocationWinter habitat quality, population limitation, and conservation of Neotropical-Nearctic migrant birdsHorizontal movements of bigeye tuna (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thunnus obesus</named-content></italic>) near Hawaii determined by Kalman filter analysis of archival tagging datakftrack: An add-on package for the statistical environment R to estimate most probable track from archival tagged individualsVariation in survivorship of a migratory songbird throughout its annual cycleConnectivity of Wood Thrush breeding, wintering, and migration sites based on range-wide trackingSpecies abundance and migratory status affects large-scale fruit tracking in thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus</named-content></italic> spp.)Postbreeding movements and habitat use of adult wood thrushes in northern VirginiaDirect and inverse solutions of geodesics on the ellipsoid with application of nested equationsVegetative and fruit resources as determinants of habitat use by mature-forest birds during the postbreeding periodDo birds select habitat or food resources? Nearctic-Neotropic migrants in northeastern Costa RicaWe investigated movements of a western population of Veeries (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>) breeding in the Okanagan region of British Columbia, Canada, in 2013&ndash;2014 using light-level geolocators. We tracked 9 individuals and incorporated a state-space Kalman filter model approach to estimate movement parameters. During migration, Veeries traversed the Rocky Mountains, Great Plains, Gulf of Mexico, and Caribbean Sea with stopovers generally closer to the shorter orthodromic (great circle) route than a loxodromic (straight line) route between breeding and first wintering grounds, particularly on fall migration. Birds initially settled in the south-central portion of the Amazon basin in Brazil at sites that were 666 &plusmn; 299 km apart, suggesting low migratory connectivity. Intra-tropical movements were observed for 8 of 9 (88.9&percnt;) birds, with second wintering sites an average of 1,447 &plusmn; 472 km to the northwest (initial bearing <italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 316 &plusmn; 16&deg;). Veeries typically followed a pattern of loop migration at the Gulf of Mexico, with more birds using the Yucatan Peninsula to stop and reorient toward destinations on spring migration (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 7) vs. fall migration (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 2). Western Veeries follow a presumed ancestral (eastern) migration route, but this route is also the shortest (great circle) route between breeding and wintering grounds, even though this route was only ~100 km shorter than the straight line route. Eight Veeries (88.9&percnt;) underwent a post-breeding, pre-migratory movement up to 628 km (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 263 &plusmn; 152 km) away from breeding territories, possibly to molt. We encourage researchers utilizing light-level geolocators to apply similar state-space modeling approaches to reduce the influence of observers and erroneous location estimates on analysis and interpretation of geolocator data.Investigamos los movimientos de una poblaci&oacute;n occidental de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic> que se reproduce en la regi&oacute;n Okanagana de Columbia Brit&aacute;nica, Canad&aacute;, entre 2013 y 2014 usando geolocalizadores de nivel de luz. Rastreamos 9 individuos e incorporamos un nuevo modelo de filtro de Kalman del espacio del estado para estimar los par&aacute;metros del movimiento. Durante la migraci&oacute;n <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic> atraviesa las Monta&ntilde;as Rocosas, las Grandes Planicies, el golfo de M&eacute;xico y el mar Caribe, haciendo paradas generalmente m&aacute;s cercanas a la ruta ortodr&oacute;mica (c&iacute;rculo m&aacute;ximo) m&aacute;s corta que a la ruta loxodr&oacute;mica (en l&iacute;nea recta) entre las &aacute;reas de reproducci&oacute;n y las primeras &aacute;reas de invernada, particularmente en la migraci&oacute;n de oto&ntilde;o. Las aves inicialmente se instalaron en la porci&oacute;n centro-sur de la cuenca amaz&oacute;nica en Brasil en sitios separados por 666 &plusmn; 299 km, lo que sugiere baja conectividad migratoria. Existieron movimientos intra-tropicales en 8 de 9 aves (88.9&percnt;) con un segundo sitio de invernada en promedio 1444 &plusmn; 472 km hacia el noroccidente (direcci&oacute;n inicial de movimiento <italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 316 &plusmn; 16&deg;). T&iacute;picamente, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic> sigui&oacute; un patr&oacute;n de migraci&oacute;n en c&iacute;rculo en el golfo de M&eacute;xico. M&aacute;s aves usaron la pen&iacute;nsula de Yucat&aacute;n para parar y reorientarse hacia sus destinos durante la migraci&oacute;n de primavera (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 7) que durante la migraci&oacute;n de oto&ntilde;o (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2). La poblaci&oacute;n occidental de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic> sigui&oacute; una ruta migratoria presuntamente ancestral (oriental), pero esta ruta es tambi&eacute;n la m&aacute;s corta (c&iacute;rculo m&aacute;ximo) entre las &aacute;reas de reproducci&oacute;n e invernada aunque es s&oacute;lo ~100 km m&aacute;s corta que la ruta en l&iacute;nea recta. Ocho individuos (88.9&percnt;) hicieron movimientos posteriores a la reproducci&oacute;n y previos a la migraci&oacute;n de hasta 628 km (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 263 &plusmn; 152 km) de distancia de las &aacute;reas de reproducci&oacute;n, posiblemente para la muda. Animamos a los investigadores a que usen geolocalizadores de nivel de luz para aplicar modelos similares de espacio del estado, para reducir la influencia del observador y los estimados de localizaci&oacute;n err&oacute;neos en el an&aacute;lisis y la interpretaci&oacute;n de los datos de geolocalizadores.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> distancia de c&iacute;rculo m&aacute;ximo, filtro de Kalman, geolocalizaci&oacute;n, loxodromia, modelos de espacio del estado, ortodromia, ruta migratoria, parada migratoria.Migration routes and stopover behavior of migratory birds have been shaped by multiple biotic and abiotic factors, including risk of mortality, the need to conserve energy and/or time, and avoidance of geographical barriers and adverse weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Moore1">Moore and Yong 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam2">Alerstam 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>). In addition, for Nearctic-Neotropical migrants with broad continental distributions, the history of glaciation on the North American continent has influenced both distributional patterns of species and the use of ancestral movement patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Boulet1">Boulet and Gibbs 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Salewski1">Salewski and Bruderer 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>). For example, Veeries (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>) from western North America east of the continental divide have been assumed to migrate using an eastern pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>), possibly following ancestral routes that evolved as the breeding range expanded during glacial retreat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Outlaw1">Outlaw et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Salewski1">Salewski and Bruderer 2007</xref>). Birds breeding west of the continental divide may be more likely to utilize the shortest route (e.g., across the Great Plains and Gulf of Mexico) or one that takes advantage of overland travel through Central America to the South American wintering grounds, similar to that seen in far western Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>) populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>).Orientation during migration is accomplished through celestial, geomagnetic, experiential, landscape, and other cues and has evolved differentially in various clades of birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam1">Alerstam 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hahn1">Hahn et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>). The simplest mode of positioning during migration is maintaining a constant bearing (straight line or loxodromic route), which represents the shortest route only if migration occurs in a direct north&ndash;south path. The shortest distance between 2 points on a sphere with any longitudinal difference is the great circle (orthodromic) route. Orienting migration along a great circle route is complicated by having to continually shift compass bearing during flight and by the need to account for time-shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>). Most research indicates that many large-bodied birds (e.g., geese, raptors) do not fly along a great circle route (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Green1">Green et al. 2002</xref>), suggesting greater influence of other environmental factors for these species. Evidence for migration along great circles by small-bodied birds (e.g., passerines) is mostly limited to a few studies that used radar to estimate bearings of migrating birds in the Arctic (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam3">Alerstam et al. 2008</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hahn1">Hahn et al. 2014</xref>), where travel along a great circle path provides the greatest decrease in flight distance relative to a straight line route anywhere on the globe. For species that orient along a great circle during migration, strict adherence to this path is not expected because of the requirements to navigate over large inhospitable environments (e.g., water bodies, deserts) and to allow maintenance of physiological parameters (e.g., fuel stores) at geographically variable stopovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hahn1">Hahn et al. 2014</xref>).For all migrants, the complex nature of large-scale movements makes it difficult to predict actual routes taken and how these vary across a species' range. Presumably, the most direct, or great circle route, would be favored in the absence of all other considerations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam3">Alerstam et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>), but until recently it has been impossible to test such hypotheses due to the difficulty in tracking small-bodied individuals. The miniaturization of archival light-level geolocator technology (hereafter, geolocators) has advanced studies of small passerines and has opened new possibilities in researching their movements, sedentary locations, and phenology during the non-breeding period. Geolocation theory utilizes day-length and solar noon to estimate latitude and longitude, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hill1">Hill 1994</xref>), and is currently one of the most accurate techniques available for measuring small passerine movement throughout the annual cycle, even though accuracy errors can exceed 300 km latitude and 150 km longitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Fudickar1">Fudickar et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Lisovski1">Lisovski et al. 2012</xref>).For Veeries, banding data, museum specimens, and live captures have been used almost entirely to infer the timing and routes of migration and wintering ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Remsen1">Remsen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>). Recent research by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. (2011)</xref> using geolocators has shown that Veeries from an eastern (i.e. Delaware, USA) population typically migrate along the eastern seaboard through Florida to South America in the fall. Their research also led to the discovery that Veeries consistently undertake intra-tropical movements within South America, purportedly to escape flooding of lowland forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">2015</xref>). However, similar information on the migration routes, stopover sites, and wintering distribution for Veeries breeding in the western region of their breeding range is largely unknown.Here, we describe the results of our investigation of the post-breeding season movements of a far western breeding population of Veeries using geolocators. Our primary purpose was to contrast our results with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. (2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">2015</xref>) for eastern birds, identify potential migration paths and stopover locations of this population, and to assess whether the far western Veery population would favor a loxodromic, orthodromic, or other route (e.g., completely overland). We expected birds from our study population breeding west of the Rocky Mountain continental divide to use a western route, with birds migrating south along the west coast of the United States and Central America to avoid crossing the Gulf of Mexico, and to utilize forested habitats along this route. Additionally, we anticipated that if western Veeries did cross the Gulf of Mexico that they would fly to and from the Yucatan Peninsula as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. (2005)</xref>, and that birds from this population would also undertake intra-tropical migrations on the wintering grounds.Veeries were captured using mist nets and playback of a conspecific song or call on their breeding grounds in the Okanagan Valley of British Columbia, Canada (centroid 49.56&deg; latitude, &minus;119.77&deg; longitude), June 16&ndash;20, 2013, near the Canada&ndash;U.S. border. Each bird was weighed to &plusmn;0.1g, measured, sexed and aged to second year (SY) or after second-year (ASY) based on criteria in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Pyle1">Pyle (2008)</xref>, and fit with a uniquely numbered U.S. Geological Survey metal leg band. We then attached light-level geolocators (Migrate Technology v3.12.4; Coton, Cambridge, UK) to male birds (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 22) using leg-loop backpack harnesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Rappole1">Rappole and Tipton 1991</xref>) and 1 mm silicone string, sized according to the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-NaefDaenzer1">Naef-Daenzer (2007)</xref> formula. Geolocators and harnesses weighed 1.0 &plusmn; 0.1 g, and all geolocator batteries lasted the duration of the logging period. We re-visited capture locations May 29&ndash;June 7, 2014, and used the same playback/mist netting method to recapture birds. The terrain in this region is mountainous or hilly and consists mostly of conifer-dominated forests at higher elevations, with preferred Veery habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>) typically occurring in narrow strips of deciduous forest along mountain waterways and in the Okanagan Valley where agriculture (i.e. fruit orchards, wineries) is the principal land use.Geolocator data were initially processed with Migrate Technology's IntiProc v1.02 user interface to calibrate sun elevation angles and derive raw location data for individual birds. Sun elevation angles were calibrated from on-bird light-level data for a period of 10 days after the geolocator was attached, during which we assumed all birds stayed on or near breeding territories (i.e. similar habitat). Errors in the estimation of positions, particularly for latitude, are expected for light-level data due to environmental and behavioral factors (e.g., vegetation, topography, weather; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Fudickar1">Fudickar et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Lisovski1">Lisovski et al. 2012</xref>). We also recognize that sun elevation angles may differ due to differences in these factors during breeding and non-breeding periods; however, discrepancies in latitude estimates between breeding and wintering ground sun- elevation angles may be negligible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-McKinnon1">McKinnon et al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, we used the same sun elevation angle for all parts of the Veeries' annual cycle to estimate daily locations.To increase the precision of estimated migration routes and locations of sedentary periods (e.g., stopover, wintering), we used a state-space Kalman filter model that estimated errors, movement parameters, and most probable tracks from geolocator data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Kalman1">Kalman 1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sibert1">Sibert et al. 2003</xref>). State-space models have 2 components, a hidden mechanistic process model of individual movement and an observation model that estimates the probability of obtaining a particular observation dependent on the organism's actual position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Patterson1">Patterson et al. 2008</xref>). The state portion of the model comprises one or more &ldquo;known&rdquo; variables (e.g., spatial location, behavior), and the process portion predicts a future state of an individual given its present state (Markov condition; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sibert1">Sibert et al. 2003</xref> for derivation of Kalman filter equation). The Kalman filter recursively estimates the state of the system at time <italic>t</italic>, dependent on the previous state at time <italic>t</italic> &minus; 1. Length of day and night time is approximately equal for 2 weeks around the spring and fall equinoxes, making estimation of latitude unreliable. The state-space model we used in the analysis provides position estimates during the equinox; however, we found some locations to be unrealistic (e.g., in the ocean), and therefore we only used longitude data from September 8&ndash;October 5, 2013, and March 6&ndash;April 4, 2014, and geographical features (e.g., Gulf of Mexico) to estimate locations during this period. The accuracy of results from state-space modeling depends on the quality of data used, and we recognize that there will be limitations in interpretation of geolocator tracks; however, state-space modeling notably reduces potential observer bias associated with analyzing raw locations from geolocator data.We used the package kftrack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sibert2">Sibert and Nielsen 2002</xref>) in R v2.15.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2012</xref>) to provide state-space Kalman filter estimates of geolocation errors and &ldquo;most probable tracks&rdquo; from raw coordinates. The diffusion component (variability in movement) of the model was set to 285 km (approximate maximum flight distance of Veery during migration on land; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>), systematic error in the longitudinal and latitudinal positions were calculated from differences in raw position from the day after capture to July 15 for individual birds, variance structure was set to &ldquo;uniform,&rdquo; and all other parameters were left at their default values. We only included raw midday positions in the models to reduce error in location estimates because Veeries migrate at night (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>). Using the kftrack results, we calculated mean positions for sedentary periods including post-breeding locations, stopovers, and wintering sites and depicted 50&percnt; confidence ellipses associated with all points used to calculate mean position during these periods. Confidence ellipses therefore depict the estimated error for each point at a stopover rather than a standard deviation of the points combined. We defined movement (e.g., migration) as large changes (&ge;100 km) in estimated longitude or latitude where no subsequent locations were observed near the most recent sedentary position during the same part of the annual cycle (e.g., fall migration). Periods where no movement was detected for 2 or more days were considered sedentary locations.To test if birds favored a shorter route to and from the wintering grounds, we used the Wilcoxon matched-pairs test using distances of stopovers (post-breeding, pre- and post-Gulf crossovers, spring) to the great circle and straight line routes at the same latitude. All distances, except the aforementioned straight line distance, are reported as the Vincenty orthodromic (great circle) distance for ellipsoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Vincenty1">Vincenty 1975</xref>), calculated with the R package geosphere v1.3-8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hijmans1">Hijmans et al. 2014</xref>). Using linear regression models, we analyzed the effect of different independent variables on biologically relevant dependent variables. To assess migratory connectivity of Veeries from the western (Okanagan) population, we used the Mantel test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Mantel1">Mantel 1967</xref>) in the R package ade4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Dray1">Dray and Dufour 2007</xref>). Significance level for all statistical tests was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. Finally, estimated positions of Veery sedentary locations were overlaid on digital land cover maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Jin1">Jin et al. 2013</xref>) to provide an evaluation of potential stopover sites in the United States. Values reported are means &plusmn; standard deviation (SD).Of 22 birds fit with geolocators, we retrieved and downloaded data from 9 individuals and observed 1 bird with a geolocator that we were unable to capture. When a bird observed with a geolocator but not captured is included in our estimate, our recapture rate (45.5&percnt;) of Veeries is similar to a study in eastern North America (47.9&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2015</xref>). Calibrated sun elevation angle values from birds caught the following summer ranged from &minus;6.1&deg; to &minus;5.5&deg;. Systematic error in breeding location estimates averaged 28.3 &plusmn; 20.9 km latitude and 45.3 &plusmn; 29.1 km longitude for raw geolocation data but was reduced to 7.6 &plusmn; 13.0 km latitude and 3.1 &plusmn; 2.4 km longitude when the state-space Kalman filter model was used to analyze the data.Geolocator positions indicated a southern and/or eastern movement for 8 of the 9 birds after the breeding period (start date <italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; August 4 &plusmn; 10 days) for a mean of 25 &plusmn; 10 days (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The mean distance from breeding sites to these post-breeding sites was 263 &plusmn; 152 km (range 172&ndash;628 km). Additionally, a bird fit with a geolocator in June 2014 was recaptured 21 km southeast of the original capture site on July 17, 2014, providing evidence that these estimated changes in location are not due to errors in geolocation (e.g., changes in light levels due to changes in habitat) per se. Bearings from breeding grounds to the post-breeding sites (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 163.1 &plusmn; 22.4&deg;) were significantly different from the bearings to the wintering grounds of both the great circle (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>7</sub> &equals; 5.74, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and the straight line (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>7</sub> &equals; 3.36, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Based on a classified digital land cover map, most birds seemed to move into lower elevation shrub habitats in the Okanagan Valley in the United States or into forested regions south or east of the breeding grounds.Summary of fall and spring migration, stopover, and wintering locations and phenology of male Veeries (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 9) fit with archival light-level geolocators in the Okanagan Valley, BC, Canada, June 2013 and recovered in June 2014. SD &equals; standard deviation.Fall (black) and spring (red) migration routes, stopover locations and wintering sites for male Veeries (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 9) fit with archival light-level geolocators in the Okanagan Valley, BC, Canada, June 2013 and recovered in June 2014. Solid lines represent estimated routes from Kalman filter state-space models, dashed lines represent estimated routes during equinoxes from longitude data only, circles represent mean stopover locations, green squares represent estimated stopover locations from longitude data only, and ellipses denote 50&percnt; confidence ellipses around all estimated points during a given sedentary period. Geolocator numbers for individual birds are shown in the top right of each panel.Veeries in our study moved eastward or south then east across the Rocky Mountains and Great Plains on fall migration. The mean distance to cross the Great Plains for birds with reliable positions (i.e. not during the fall equinox; <italic>n &equals;</italic> 6) was 1,791 &plusmn; 437 km, taking 6.0 &plusmn; 2.7 days with an estimated travel rate of 256 &plusmn; 62 km day<sup>&minus;1</sup>. Time to cross the Great Plains was not significantly related to latitude of the post-breeding site location (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.18, df &equals; 6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.77). Only one bird made a clear stopover while crossing the Great Plains, with points centered on the Black Hills of South Dakota; however, the migration routes of 2 other birds also crossed over this area. All birds stopped near the Gulf of Mexico coast (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; &minus;87.55 &plusmn; 3.00&deg; longitude; Louisiana to western Florida) for 17.4 &plusmn; 6.1 days (range 10&ndash;28 days) prior to crossing. Migration routes across the Gulf of Mexico varied, with 2 birds flying to the Yucatan peninsula (Mexico) and the rest flying to Cuba across the Gulf of Mexico (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 6) or via Florida (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 1). Four birds had clear stopovers for 12.0 &plusmn; 4.1 days on the Yucatan Peninsula (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 1) or the Caribbean Islands (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 3) prior to commencing migration to South America. Duration at these stopovers was not significantly associated with duration at a post-Gulf crossing stopover (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;0.1, df &equals; 7, <italic>P &equals;</italic> 0.61) or arrival date into South America (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.15, df &equals; 7, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.45). Veeries arrived in South America on October 10 &plusmn; 7.5 days, with a mean post-Gulf crossing stopover duration of 8.4 &plusmn; 3.0 days (range 3&ndash;11 days). Mean longitude of stopovers in South America was &minus;73.48 &plusmn; 5.04&deg;, ranging from northwest Columbia to north-central Venezuela. Differences between distances of fall stopovers to the great circle and straight line routes from the breeding grounds to the first wintering area were significantly different for 2 of 3 stopovers: pre-Gulf crossing (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.005) and post-Gulf crossing (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), with locations closer to the great circle than the straight line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f03">3</xref>).Fall (<bold>A</bold>) and spring (<bold>B</bold>) migration routes and the maximum extent of orthodromic (great circle) and loxodromic (straight line) routes between breeding and first wintering sites for male Veeries (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 9) fit with archival light-level geolocators in the Okanagan Valley, BC, Canada, June 2013 and recovered in June 2014.Box and whisker plots showing distances of migration stopovers to the orthodromic (great circle) and loxodromic (straight line) routes between breeding and first wintering grounds for male Veeries (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 9) fit with archival light-level geolocators in the Okanagan Valley, BC, Canada, June 2013 and recovered in June 2014. Stopovers marked with &ast; represent significant differences in distances between the 2 routes using a Wilcoxon matched-pairs test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Arrival date onto the wintering grounds (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; November 5 &plusmn; 9.5 days) was not dependent on departure date from breeding grounds (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.68, df &equals; 7, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.45). First wintering areas were centered in the Amazon basin of south-central Brazil (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; &minus;8.73 &plusmn; 3.68&deg; latitude, &minus;56.92 &plusmn; 2.87&deg; longitude; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f01">Figure 1</xref>), with individual Veeries settling in different areas (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 666 &plusmn; 299 km apart; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Duration at the first wintering site was not significantly related to the first wintering location (Mantel test, <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub> &equals; &minus;0.02, <italic>n &equals;</italic> 9, <italic>P &equals;</italic> 0.47). The difference between the mean great circle and straight line distances between breeding and first wintering sites was 98.1 &plusmn; 8.6 km. Second wintering areas (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; &minus;0.15 &plusmn; 2.72&deg; latitude, &minus;65.64 &plusmn; 2.51&deg; longitude) were distinguishable from first wintering areas for 8 of 9 birds that moved in a north or northwest direction on a bearing (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 316.2 &plusmn; 15.5&deg;) similar to both the great circle (paired <italic>t-</italic>test, <italic>t</italic><sub>7</sub>&equals; &minus;1.49, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.18) and straight line (paired <italic>t-</italic>test, <italic>t</italic><sub>7</sub> &equals; &minus;0.1, df &equals; 7, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.93) bearings from the first winter site to the breeding grounds. Distances between first and second wintering sites ranged from 919 to 2,047 km (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 8; <italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; 1,447 &plusmn; 472 km), with low connectivity between first and second wintering area locations (Mantel test, <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub> &equals; 0.25, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.13). Second wintering sites were in northern Brazil (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 6), southern Colombia (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 1), and Venezuela (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 1), where Veeries arrived on March 25 &plusmn; 14.8 days for a duration 24.6 &plusmn; 14.9 days. Second wintering sites were closer to the great circle than the straight line route, but differences between these distances were not significant (<italic>P &equals;</italic> 0.2).Veeries initiated spring migration on April 17 &plusmn; 7.3 days (range April 1&ndash; 25), and birds departed South America on April 21 &plusmn; 3.6 days (range April 18&ndash;26). To cross the Gulf of Mexico on spring migration, Veeries used a route farther west than fall migration, with 7 birds flying across the Caribbean Sea to the Yucatan peninsula and 2 birds flying to Cuba and then across the Gulf of Mexico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f02">2</xref>). Post-Gulf crossing stopovers were located along the north Gulf Coast from Texas (&minus;96.74&deg; longitude) to the Mississippi Delta (&minus;88.84&deg; longitude), with a mean stopover duration of 10.1 &plusmn; 3.1 days. All birds arrived in the United States from South America by May 1 (<italic>x̄ </italic> &equals; April 29 &plusmn; 4 days). After commencing northward migration from this stopover, 8 birds had at least one apparent stopover with a mean duration of 5.0 &plusmn; 1.5 days. Except for one bird that travelled northwest from the first North American stopover, Veeries moved north and generally followed the eastern temperate forest and then crossed the Great Plains and approximately followed the great circle path (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Only the second North American stopover location was closer to the great circle (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 8, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) than to the straight line route on spring migration. Mean arrival date on the breeding grounds was May 21 &plusmn; 1.9 days and was not correlated with departure date from the wintering grounds (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.24, df &equals; 7, 1.87, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.21) or total length of stopovers (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;2.0, df &equals; 7, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15).Contrary to our initial expectations, far western breeding Veeries did not migrate directly south using an overland route to South America as seen in other <italic>Catharus</italic> species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>). Instead, they moved eastward and crossed the Great Plains to cross the Gulf of Mexico and Caribbean Sea in a manner similar to eastern Veery populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>). Their route during fall migration was closer to the shorter great circle path to the wintering grounds vs. the straight line distance. Our study also provided several other important discoveries on western Veery movement to pre-migration and other stopover sites and the phenology and use of 2 major wintering sites in South America. These insights have important ramifications for the conservation of this and likely several other species.Short-distance (typically &lt;20 km), pre-migratory movements have been recorded in several passerines and are typically associated with the need to exploit more productive habitats (e.g., fruiting plants) for pre-migratory fuelling and molt or to avoid predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-VegaRivera1">Vega Rivera et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Vitz1">Vitz and Rodewald 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Chandler1">Chandler et al. 2012</xref>). We provide the first evidence that adult male Veeries from the Okanagan Valley undertake relatively large (mean 263 km) post-breeding movements from their breeding territories prior to the onset of clear fall migration. The timing of this movement overlaps with the molting period (July&ndash;September; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Pyle1">Pyle 2008</xref>), indicating that these movements may be a molt migration. Suitable breeding habitat in our study area is limited mostly to narrow strips of deciduous and mixed-wood forests that occur along valleys of mountain streams in a landscape otherwise dominated by coniferous forests, agriculture, and urban development. Post-breeding movement may be common for Veery populations breeding in regions like the Okanagan Valley compared to eastern regions where preferred (molting) habitat may be more ubiquitous on the landscape. The occurrence of molt migration in Veeries requires further testing, potentially by combining geolocator data with stable isotopes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hobson1">Hobson and Wassenaar 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>).Multiple factors may impact the choice of migration route between breeding and wintering grounds, including ancestral paths, weather, barriers, physiological condition, predation risk, and regional phenology of plants and insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Deutschlander1">Deutschlander and Muheim 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam2">Alerstam 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>). Several studies have shown that some Arctic bird species optimize migration by utilizing the shortest (great circle) distance between breeding and wintering locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam6">Alerstam and Pettersson 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam3">Alerstam et al. 2008</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to demonstrate the orientation of migration along a great circle vs. a straight line route for a Nearctic-Neotropical migrant that migrated across the Rocky Mountains, Great Plains, and Gulf of Mexico. This was in contrast to our expectation that western populations would use a north&ndash;south pathway that allowed the use of potential stopover sites in forested areas of the western United States and Central America while avoiding crossing the Gulf of Mexico. While the great circle route was the most direct, it likely involved fewer stopover options due to crossing extensive agricultural land (i.e. the Great Plains) and the Gulf of Mexico and Caribbean Sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam5">Alerstam et al. 2003</xref>). Additionally, the difference in the distance between the great circle and straight line routes between breeding and wintering grounds for our Veeries was only ~100 km. The benefit of reducing travel distance by following a great circle route between North and South America was therefore not as clear for Veeries as for other species (e.g., Arctic passerines; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam3">Alerstam et al. 2008</xref>), suggesting that other factors may be more important in determining migration routes (e.g., ancestral routes, weather, avoidance of desert regions).Stopover sites are important refuelling habitats during migration, and their quality and quantity may ultimately influence breeding success and survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hutto1">Hutto 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Faaborg1">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>). We identified several general areas used as stopovers for western Veery during fall migration. Most birds crossed the Great Plains on fall migration without stopping, possibly taking advantage of tailwinds to expedite migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>), likely because there are few forested stopover options on this route. Our predicted mean travel rates of 289 km day<sup>&minus;1</sup> for Veeries traversing the Plains were consistent with estimated maximum travel rates of other studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>), indicating that this region possibly provides poor stopover habitat. Veeries were previously thought to migrate only to the Yucatan Peninsula after crossing the Gulf of Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bevier1">Bevier et al. 2005</xref>); however, only 2 of 9 birds on fall migration used the Yucatan Peninsula, with the rest migrating via a Caribbean route, a path also used by Veeries from eastern North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>), suggesting that this ancestral route may be more important than expected. This Caribbean pathway is also closer to the shorter great circle route between breeding and wintering grounds for the Okanagan Veery population.Male birds from our western population arrived at a first winter site within 3 days of those from an eastern population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2015</xref>), not accounting for year effects. This was unexpected because the western migration route was up to 1,600 km farther than the distance travelled by eastern Veeries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>), and most western birds arrived via a trans-Gulf migration, which we expected to result in longer pre- and post-Gulf crossing stopovers. Such synchronous arrival across the longitudinal range of Veeries may be linked to dynamics of food availability (e.g., fruits) on migration routes and wintering sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Renfrew1">Renfrew et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-LaSorte1">La Sorte et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Wolfe1">Wolfe et al. 2014</xref>) or to the need to defend winter territories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sherry1">Sherry and Holmes 1996</xref>). Birds from our western population initially wintered in the south-central Amazon basin in Brazil but had low migratory connectivity (i.e. individuals settled hundreds of kilometers apart), a result also observed for Veeries from eastern North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">2015</xref>).Until recently, little was known about the movement of Nearctic-Neotropical migrant birds on their wintering grounds. Intra-tropical migration has been documented for some tropical species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Faaborg1">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>) and is likely more common than previously thought for migrant thrush species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>), including the Veery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">2015</xref>). These migrations may be caused by seasonal flooding of lowland forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Faaborg1">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>) and or spatial and temporal changes in resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Levey1">Levey and Stiles 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Telleria1">Telleria et al. 2014</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. (2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">2015</xref>) found that eastern Veeries underwent synchronized intra-tropical movements in mid-February from a first wintering area in west central Brazil to other regions in South America, including south to eastern Bolivia. Second wintering locations are likely not part of their spring migration because these areas were not located along migration routes and because birds spent similar amounts of time at both sites. In contrast, most western Veeries settled first in central Brazil then migrated to more northern latitudes generally aligned with great circle and straight line migration routes to the breeding grounds. Western Veeries also stayed on average 36 days longer at the first winter site than eastern Veeries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2015</xref>), resulting in later arrival dates and shorter durations at the second winter site (~ &gt;22 days).Western Veeries used a loop migration pattern around the Gulf of Mexico, with 7 of 9 birds using a more western spring route via the Yucatan Peninsula to North America compared to the common fall migration route to wintering grounds via the Caribbean Islands. After crossing the Gulf of Mexico, birds concentrated stopovers along the Gulf Coast from Texas to Louisiana, an important area for many migrating bird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Moore1">Moore and Yong 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Elphick1">Elphick 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton2">Newton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Buler1">Buler and Moore 2011</xref>). Eight of 9 birds then travelled north toward the great circle route before crossing the Great Plains. The Black Hills and Bighorn Mountains in Wyoming and South Dakota and the Rocky Mountains of Colorado were used as stopovers by several western Veeries crossing the Plains during spring migration. Based on digital land cover maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Jin1">Jin et al. 2013</xref>), these sites are the first forested habitats on the trans-Plains route from eastern forests to the breeding grounds. One bird travelled generally in a northwest direction from Texas toward Great Salt Lake, Utah, and then north to the breeding grounds. Consistent with other studies of Veeries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher2">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>), birds arrived on the breeding grounds after ~30 days of migration, which is ~2 times faster than migration to the wintering grounds.The weight and drag of geolocators likely puts additional physiological stress on birds during migration, potentially affecting refuelling rates, stopover and wintering lengths and locations, migration phenology, and survival, and may be exacerbated for bird traversing vast inhospitable environments (e.g., Gulf of Mexico; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Bowlin1">Bowlin et al. 2010</xref>, Constantini and Moller 2013). These factors may lead to biased results for some variables, emphasizing the need for caution in the interpretation of results from geolocators. Here, the return rate of birds fit with geolocators was similar to studies where return rates of Veeries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2015</xref>) and Swainson's Thrushes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>) without geolocators were estimated. The duration of stopovers after crossing the Gulf of Mexico for birds in our study was also similar to those estimated for Veeries captured after traversing this water body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-GonzalezPrieto1">Gonzalez-Prieto et al. 2011</xref>), indicating that small (&le;1 g) geolocators likely do not have as detrimental effects on Veery compared with other (smaller) species.Position estimates from geolocators include errors, especially in the estimation of latitudes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Hill1">Hill 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Lisovski1">Lisovski et al. 2012</xref>). Moreover, the technique is hampered by an inability to estimate latitudes during the fall and spring equinoxes. We incorporated the use of state-space models, which reduced bias in latitude and longitude by 21 km and 42 km, respectively, and to assist with determination of positions during the equinoxes. State-space models have been used in movement studies of multiple (especially marine) organisms (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sibert1">Sibert et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Royer1">Royer et al. 2005</xref>) and have only recently been incorporated into geolocator studies involving birds (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Seavy1">Seavy et al. 2012</xref>). We encourage the further development and use of state-space models for avian tracking studies because they are particularly suited to diminishing the influence of researcher bias when screening problematic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Patterson1">Patterson et al. 2008</xref>).Our sample of Veeries was relatively small (<italic>n &equals;</italic> 9) and was limited to male birds only and 1 year of data from a single breeding area; however, multiple years of tracking of Veeries show remarkably consistent locations and phenology during the non-breeding season across years (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2015</xref>). In addition, all birds in our sample showed remarkably similar trajectories, and so we believe they are representative of this and other western Veery populations.Our study provides the first evidence that birds from a far western North American population favor a shorter distance great circle route vs. a straight line or overland route during migration. Travel via the great circle route theoretically provides the advantages of reduced energy requirements and predation risk through decreased travel distance and time, which may have carry-over effects to other parts of the annual cycle (e.g., earlier arrival times for territory establishment). There is increasing evidence that survivorship of Nearctic-Neotropical migrant passerines is greatly influenced by factors operating during the migration period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Sillett1">Sillett and Holmes 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Newton1">Newton 2006</xref>). The use of a shortest distance (great circle) route for small migrating passerines has been demonstrated for cases of long-distance, trans-ocean travel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam4">Alerstam et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Alerstam3">2008</xref>). How small birds migrate and orient during over-land travel is poorly known and likely involves several trade-offs that take into account multiple biotic and abiotic factors in space and time. We suggest that use of the great circle path may be more common for passerines than previously understood (e.g., see migration routes for Swainson's Thrush in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-540-Delmore2">Delmore and Irwin 2014</xref>), and recent advances in tracking technology will allow investigation of the dominant factors influencing these movements, including use of the great circle route.We thank S. L. Van Wilgenburg, C. Bishop, T. Forrester, and several field staff for assisting with data collection. Early discussions with S. L. Van Wilgenburg were helpful in integrating state-space models and great circle routes in our work. We are also grateful to C. Heckscher for providing an early draft of his manuscript on intra-tropical Veery movement.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Funding for this project was provided by Environment Canada with an operational grant to K.A.H. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript, and none of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This research was conducted under the Animal Care Committee protocol permit &num;EC-PN-11-030.