Modeling three-dimensional space use and overlap in birdsRanging patterns of two syntopic howler monkey species (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Alouatta guariba</named-content></italic> and <italic>A. caraya</italic>) in northeastern ArgentinaEstimating territory and home-range sizes: Do singing locations alone provide an accurate estimate of space use?Describing breeding territories of migratory passerines: Suggestions for sampling, choice of estimator, and delineation of core areasBurrowing behaviour of radio-labelled earthworm revealed by analysis of 3D-trajectories in artificial soil coresMulti-dimensional space use: The final frontierEffects of sampling regime on the mean and variance of home range size estimatesTwo bodies cannot occupy the same place at the same time, or the importance of space in the ecological nicheHigh spatial resolution three-dimensional mapping of vegetation spectral dynamics using computer visionEliminating autocorrelation reduces biological relevance of home range estimatesEffects of winter weather on horizontal and vertical use of isolated forest fragments by bark-foraging birdsAnalysis of radio telemetry data in studies of home rangeks: kernel density estimation and kernel discriminant analysis for multivariate data in RPlug-In bandwidth matrices for bivariate kernel density estimationConvergence rates for unconstrained bandwidth matrix selectors in multivariate kernel density estimationCross-validation bandwidth matrices for multivariate kernel density estimationCompetition refuges and coexistence: An example from Serengeti carnivoresImproved techniques for studying the temporal and spatial behavior of fish in a fixed locationKernel density estimators of home range: Smoothing and the autocorrelation red herringQuantifying home-range overlap: The importance of the utilization distributionIntersexual variation in the foraging ecology of sexually monochromatic Western Wood-PeweesBandwidth selection for fixed-kernel analysis of animal utilization distributionsForaging habitats of top predators, and Areas of Ecological Significance, on the Kerguelen PlateauIntratree vertical variation of fruit density and the nature of contest competition in frugivoresMicrohabitat separation among diurnal saxicolous lizards in Zimbabwe<named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Concluding remarks</named-content>. In Population Studies: Animal Ecology and DemographyModeling utilization distributions in space and timeThe problem of m rankingsEstimating the location of the focal center in red squirrel home rangesA critical review of home range studiesTemporal variation in flock size and habitat use of parrots in New CaledoniaLandscape structure and spatial scale affect space use by songbirds in naturally patchy and harvested boreal forestsPopulation ecology of some warblers of northeastern coniferous forestsThe role of behavioral dominance in structuring patterns of habitat occupancy in a migrant bird during the nonbreeding seasonTerritorial exclusion by a long-distance migrant warbler in Jamaica: A removal experiment with American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>)Characterizing independence of observations in movements of Columbian black-tailed deerElk and hunter space-use sharing in South DakotaComparability of three analytical techniques to assess joint space useTable of equivalent populations of North American small mammalsThe role of territory in bird lifeThe role of dominance in the social life of birdsSpatial relationships between Iberian Lynx and other carnivores in an area of south-western SpainVertical stratification of bat assemblages in flooded and unflooded Amazonian forestsVertical use of space by the marsupial <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Micoureus paraguayanus</named-content></italic> (Didelphimorphia, Didelphidae) in the Atlantic Forest of BrazilThree-dimensional use of space by a tropical rainforest rodent, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melomys cervinipes</named-content></italic>, and its implications for foraging and home-range sizeVertical stratification of Neotropical leaf-nosed bats (Chiroptera: Phyllostomidae) revealed by stable carbon isotopesThree-dimensional distribution of fish larvae in a cyclonic eddy in the Gulf of California during the summerSpectral niche segregation and community organization in a tropical cricket assemblageEffects of sample size on kernel home range estimatesAn evaluation of the accuracy of kernel density estimators for home range analysisAmerican Redstart (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>)Three-dimensional kernel utilization distributions improve estimates of space use in aquatic animalsSurveying wintering warbler populations in Jamaica: Point counts with and without broadcast vocalizationsShrimp stocking, salmon collapse, and eagle displacement: Cascading interactions in the food web of a large aquatic ecosystemOperationally defining home range: Temporal dependence exhibited by hispid cotton ratsResource partitioning and interspecific interactions among sympatric rain forest arboreal mammals of the Western Ghats, IndiaOn testing for independence of animal movementsComparison of several probabilistic home-range modelsHabitat heterogeneity and use of physical and acoustic space in anuran communities in southeastern BrazilSpatial ecology of migratory passerines on temperate and boreal forest breeding groundsA review of models of home range for animal movementCatadioptric stereo-vision system for the real-time monitoring of 3D behavior in aquatic animalsHow animals use space has fundamental behavioral and ecological implications. Utilization distributions are among the most common methods for quantifying space use and have advanced our knowledge of animal ecology in a variety of ways. However, until recently, they were limited to 2 spatial dimensions (2D), despite the fact that most taxa use their environments in all 3 dimensions (3D). We (1) created 3D utilization distributions via a multivariate kernel density estimator, (2) adapted 2 overlap indices for use with 3D data, (3) estimated the minimum sample sizes required for accurate estimation of territory size, and (4) assessed these methods using data from American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>) during their nonbreeding season in Jamaica. We found that, compared to 3D methods, 2D methods overestimated individual (pairwise) spatial overlap by 3&percnt; in scrub habitat and 4&percnt; in mangrove habitat. Similarly, 2D methods overestimated total (all neighbors combined) spatial overlap by 9&percnt; in scrub and 12&percnt; in mangrove habitat. This indicates that American Redstarts may partition territorial space in all 3 spatial dimensions. Moreover, using overlap indices, we found that American Redstarts may avoid areas of overlap, possibly to limit agonistic interactions with neighbors. Although 3D methods require larger sample sizes (80&ndash;110 locations) than 2D (40&ndash;70 locations), we argue that modeling animal space use in 3D is more realistic and will enhance understanding of niche differentiation, interspecific and intraspecific competition, habitat selection and use, and wildlife conservation.Entender c&oacute;mo los animales usan el espacio tiene implicancias comportamentales y ecol&oacute;gicas fundamentales. Las distribuciones de utilizaci&oacute;n son una de las maneras m&aacute;s comunes de cuantificar el uso del espacio y ha permitido el avance de nuestro entendimiento de la ecolog&iacute;a animal de varios modos. Sin embargo, hasta hace poco, estaban limitadas a dos dimensiones espaciales (2D), a pesar del hecho de que la mayor&iacute;a de los taxa usan sus ambientes en las tres dimensiones (3D). En este estudio (1) creamos distribuciones de utilizaci&oacute;n 3D por medio de un estimador de densidad kernel multivariado, (2) adaptamos dos &iacute;ndices de superposici&oacute;n para usarlos con datos 3D, (3) estimamos los tama&ntilde;os de muestreo m&iacute;nimos requeridos para una estimaci&oacute;n precisa del tama&ntilde;o del territorio, y (4) evaluamos estos m&eacute;todos usando datos de la estaci&oacute;n no reproductiva de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic> en Jamaica. Encontramos que, en comparaci&oacute;n con los m&eacute;todos 3D, los m&eacute;todos 2D sobreestimaron la superposici&oacute;n espacial individual (por pareja) en un 3&percnt; en el h&aacute;bitat de matorral y 4&percnt; en el h&aacute;bitat de manglar. De modo similar, los m&eacute;todos 2D sobreestimaron la superposici&oacute;n espacial total (todos los vecinos combinados) en un 9&percnt; en el matorral y 12&percnt; en el h&aacute;bitat de manglar. Esto indica que <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. ruticilla</named-content></italic> puede sectorizar el espacio territorial en las tres dimensiones espaciales. M&aacute;s a&uacute;n, usando &iacute;ndices de superposici&oacute;n, encontramos que <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. ruticilla</named-content></italic> puede evitar &aacute;reas de superposici&oacute;n, posiblemente para limitar interacciones agon&iacute;sticas con sus vecinos. Aunque los m&eacute;todos 3D requieren tama&ntilde;os de muestra m&aacute;s grandes (80&ndash;110 localizaciones) que los m&eacute;todos 2D (40&ndash;70 localizaciones), argumentamos que el modelado del uso del espacio por parte de los animales en 3D es m&aacute;s realista y ayudar&aacute; a comprender mejor la diferenciaci&oacute;n de nicho, la competencia inter-espec&iacute;fica e intra-espec&iacute;fica, la selecci&oacute;n y uso del h&aacute;bitat, y la conservaci&oacute;n de la vida silvestre.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <sc>3D,</sc> &aacute;mbito hogare&ntilde;o, &iacute;ndice de superposici&oacute;n de la distribuci&oacute;n de utilizaci&oacute;n, &iacute;ndice del volumen de intersecci&oacute;n, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>, superposici&oacute;n, territorio, uso del espacio conjuntoHow animals use space in their environment is a fundamental question in behavioral ecology because of its implications for demography, interspecific and intraspecific competition, habitat use and selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Belant1">Belant et al. 2012</xref>), niche partitioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Cunha1">Cunha and Vieira 2004</xref>), and predator&ndash;prey relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Millspaugh1">Millspaugh et al. 2000</xref>). Methods for quantifying space use range from the minimum convex polygon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Mohr1">Mohr 1947</xref>), which simply delineates the outer boundary of space used, to the utilization distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-VanWinkle1">Van Winkle 1975</xref>), which both defines the outer boundary and provides information about the internal structure of the space used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>). Kernel density estimators are the most commonly used method for creating utilization distributions, but, until recently, they have only been used to analyze 2-dimensional (2D) data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Belant1">Belant et al. 2012</xref>).Although animal space use has typically been quantified in the 2 horizontal dimensions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>), the vast majority of animal taxa (e.g., flying, arboreal, burrowing, and aquatic animals) use space in 3 dimensions. For example, interspecific and intraspecific vertical stratification of the environment has been documented in insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Schmidt1">Schmidt et al. 2012</xref>), fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-SanchezVelasco1">S&aacute;nchez-Velasco et al. 2013</xref>), amphibians (Vasconcelos and Rossa-Feres 2008), reptiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Howard1">Howard and Hailey 1999</xref>), arboreal mammals and bats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Sushma1">Sushma and Singh 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Houle1">Houle et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Pereira1">Pereira et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Rex1">Rex et al. 2011</xref>), and birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-MacArthur1">MacArthur 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Dolby1">Dolby and Grubb 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Legault1">Legault et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fogg1">Fogg et al. 2013</xref>). All of these studies quantified space use by comparing heights directly and ignored the other 2 dimensions, whereas others created 2D utilization distributions and then separately analyzed vertical data (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Rader1">Rader and Krockenberger 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Prevedello1">Prevedello et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Agostini1">Agostini et al. 2010</xref>). A few studies have modeled animal movements simultaneously in three dimensions (3D), but using species-specific methods that are not easily generalized (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Bastardie1">Bastardie et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Ehrenberg1">Ehrenberg and Steig 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Zhu1">Zhu and Weng 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Hindell1">Hindell et al. (2011)</xref> analyzed 3D space use in diving birds by creating 2D utilization distributions at multiple depth intervals, rather than incorporating the vertical dimension as part of the utilization distribution itself. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Keating1">Keating and Cherry (2009)</xref> developed a kernel-based model for analyzing animal movements in 3D space and time but presented it using data in only 2 spatial dimensions. More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Simpfendorfer1">Simpfendorfer et al. (2012)</xref> quantified space use of European eels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anguilla anguilla</named-content></italic>) using 3D utilization distributions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong1">Duong 2007</xref>), which can be applied to nearly any species. However, nothing is known about the minimum sample sizes required to accurately estimate 3D utilization distributions, and several useful indices for quantifying spatial overlap have not yet been adapted for use with 3D data.Spatial overlap is quantified most simply as the proportion of overlap of 1 animal's home range or territory with its neighbor's (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-White1">White and Garrott 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>). However, this method is biased when animals use areas of overlap less frequently than other areas, either because birds actively avoid these areas or because overlapped areas are on the periphery of their territories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seidel1">Seidel 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Millspaugh2">Millspaugh et al. 2004</xref>). As a result, several indices were developed that use information from utilization distributions to account for frequency of use within the overlapped space. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny (2005)</xref> explored the use of 2 such indices: the volume of intersection index (VI) and the utilization distribution overlap index (UDOI). Using both simulated and empirical data, they demonstrated that incorporating use improved estimates of spatial overlap.Our main objectives here are to create 3D utilization distributions for animals, specifically birds, and to adapt 2 commonly used overlap indices for use in 3D. We also provide the first estimates of the minimum sample size necessary for 3D analyses. Using spatial location data from wintering American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>) in Jamaica, we then quantify differences between 2D and 3D estimates of spatial overlap to assess 3D partitioning of space by territorial American Redstarts. Through the use of overlap indices, we also attempt to determine whether redstarts avoid areas of overlap with neighbors. Finally, we suggest broad ecological applications and call for further refinement of this exciting new technique.All data were collected on the southwest coast of Jamaica, at the Font Hill Nature Preserve in Saint Elizabeth Parish (18&deg;02&prime;N, 77&deg;57&prime;W). We collected data on wintering American Redstarts (hereafter &ldquo;redstarts&rdquo;), a Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migratory species that breeds across the eastern United States and Canada and winters in the Caribbean, eastern Mexico, and northern South America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Sherry1">Sherry and Holmes 1997</xref>). Most wintering redstarts are territorial throughout the wintering period and occupy multiple habitat types across Jamaica, including coastal mangrove and second-growth scrub forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Sliwa1">Sliwa and Sherry 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Marra2">Marra et al. 1993</xref>). The scrub habitat at Font Hill is a tropical dry deciduous forest (<italic>x̄</italic> canopy height &equals; 8.5 m) dominated by logwood (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Haematoxylon campechianum</named-content></italic>) and contains a thick understory composed of other trees, vines, and thorny plants. Mangrove habitat (<italic>x̄</italic> canopy height &equals; 9.1 m) is evergreen, has little or no understory, and is dominated by black mangrove (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Avicennia germinans</named-content></italic>).Data for the analyses of spatial overlap were collected from February 15 to March 15 in 2011 and 2012. Spatial overlap was measured using focal birds and as many of their neighbors as possible, in a different randomly selected &sim;1.5-ha area each year, in both scrub (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17 birds) and mangrove (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 32 birds) habitat. Data for the sample-size analysis were collected from February 15 to April 1 in 2013 using 9 randomly selected after-second-year males in mangrove habitat.Throughout each sampling period, a pair of observers visited focal territories at least every 2 days between 0530 and 1200 hours. Most birds (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 54) were located visually and identified via plastic colored leg bands, but 4 birds were included that were not banded, but whose unique feather patterns allowed for individual recognition. We used burst sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Dunn1">Dunn and Gipson 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Swihart1">Swihart and Slade 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>), which involved collecting locations of birds at short but regular time intervals (30 s) during 10-min bursts in 2011 and 2012 and 15-min bursts in 2013. No more than 20 (2011&ndash;2012) or 30 (2013) points were collected per day per bird. We chose to collect data in a manner that was biologically rather than statistically independent (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Lair1">Lair 1987</xref>). Several authors (e.g., de Solla 1999, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg1">Fieberg 2007</xref>) have suggested that it may not be possible to use statistically independent data to accurately quantify phenomena that are inherently spatially autocorrelated, such as space use. Moreover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Swihart1">Swihart and Slade (1997)</xref> found that utilization distribution methods are robust to spatial autocorrelation, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-deSolla1">de Solla et al. (1999)</xref> found that bias in estimating home range was actually reduced at increasing levels of autocorrelation. Also, achieving statistical independence may not always be feasible given reasonable time, cost, and manpower constraints (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-McNay1">McNay et al. (1994)</xref> found that to remain statistically independent, they would have had to collect Columbian black-tailed deer (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Odocoileus hemionus</named-content> columbianus</italic>) locations at a rate of only 8 yr<sup>&minus;1</sup>. To remain biologically independent, the chosen time interval between collecting locations should provide sufficient time for the focal animal to travel to any point in its territory. Based on observations in the field and the small territory size of wintering redstarts (<italic>x̄</italic> &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.18 &plusmn; 0.01 ha; N. W. Cooper personal observation), we chose a 30-s time interval, which is consistent with other studies (e.g., 60 s for 0.70-ha Cerulean Warbler territories; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>). Once located and identified, birds were observed foraging from a distance (&gt;5 m) by both observers. One observer noted the position of the bird every 30 s, while the other observer placed prenumbered staked flags into the ground directly below the focal bird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>). Placement of flags was delayed by up to several minutes if placing a flag was likely to disturb the bird or influence its movement. Height was estimated visually (&plusmn;1 m), by consensus of both observers. To calibrate height estimates, the heights of 1 to 3 trees territory<sup>&minus;1</sup> were measured directly and labeled with yellow flagging. A reference tree was visible from nearly all parts of each territory, and observers surveyed territories to calibrate height estimates prior to the beginning of each sampling burst. Redstarts foraged from the ground to near the top of the canopy, but overall foraging heights were relatively low (<italic>x̄</italic> foraging height &equals; 4.3 &plusmn; 0.04 m; range: 1&ndash;12 m), which aided in accurate estimation of height. At the end of each day, the Universal Transverse Mercator coordinates of each flagged location were collected using a global positioning system unit (&lt;1 m; Trimble Pathfinder ProXRT Receiver; Trimble, Sunnyvale, California, USA) and foraging heights were matched with the numbered flags. In 2011 and 2012, we collected &sim;70 locations bird<sup>&minus;1</sup>; in 2013, we collected &ge;180 locations to estimate minimum sample sizes.We used package &ldquo;ks&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong1">Duong 2007</xref>) in program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2014</xref>) to create 2D and 3D utilization distributions (for sample code, see Appendix). This package allows for the creation and visualization of utilization distributions via kernel density estimation in multivariate space (2&ndash;6 dimensions) using a normal or Gaussian kernel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-f02">Figure 1</xref>). This process involves creating a 2D grid or 3D gridded cube, which contains a user-defined number of pixels or voxels (i.e. 3D pixels), and then determining the density estimate inside each pixel or voxel. We used the 2D default setting (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 151) for grid size for all analyses. A smoothing parameter or bandwidth is necessary for each analysis and multiple automated methods for bandwidth selection exist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seaman2">Seaman and Powell 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Gitzen1">Gitzen et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong1">Duong 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>). Inappropriate bandwidths can result in either oversmoothing, which obscures areas of high use by the animal; or undersmoothing, which creates nonexistent areas of high use. We chose the 2-stage plug-in method developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong2">Duong and Hazelton (2003)</xref>, which has been shown to have similar convergence rates to other estimators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong3">Duong and Hazelton 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Gitzen1">Gitzen et al. 2006</xref>). Utilization distributions can be created and visualized at different isopleths, each of which contains areas of equal use by a focal bird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>). Each isopleth describes the chance of locating the focal bird within that area. We defined each bird's territory at the 95th isopleth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-White1">White and Garrott 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>).Overlapping 95&percnt; utilization distributions of 2 neighboring American Redstarts (red &equals; 79 locations, blue &equals; 70 locations) wintering in Jamaica, in 2 dimensions (left panel) and 3 dimensions (right panel).To quantify spatial overlap, we first calculated the area (2D) and volume (3D) for each redstart territory. The terms &ldquo;territory&rdquo; and &ldquo;home range&rdquo; are often used interchangeably, even though they describe different concepts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Leonard1">Leonard et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Anich1">Anich et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Whitaker1">Whitaker and Warkentin 2010</xref>). Redstarts regularly travel outside their defended territories but are difficult to detect because of the wide area they cover and their inconspicuous behavior while off territory. All redstart observations were based on sight detections during active foraging bouts, so we assumed that we measured territory size rather than home-range size. We calculated spatial overlap for pairs of neighboring birds as the area or volume of overlap, divided by each individual's territory area or volume, creating a proportion (hereafter &ldquo;individual spatial overlap&rdquo;). For 42 of 49 birds from 2011 and 2012, we were able to collect data on all (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 16) or the majority (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 26) of overlapping neighbors, which allowed us to estimate the total percentage of area and volume that was overlapped by neighbors (hereafter &ldquo;total spatial overlap&rdquo;). Estimates of total spatial overlap should therefore be treated as minimum estimates, but this does not affect our analyses that compare 2D and 3D methods, because the same birds were used in each case. We also calculated the nondirectional overlap indices, VI and UDOI, for each pair of birds as described below.The distributions of individual spatial overlap, total spatial overlap, VI, and UDOI did not meet the assumptions of normality, prompting use of paired-sample Wilcoxon signed-rank tests to compare estimates of overlap. Effect sizes (<italic>r</italic>) were calculated following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Field1">Field (2005)</xref>. We also used Kendall's coefficient of concordance (Kendall's <italic>W</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Kendall1">Kendall and Smith 1939</xref>) to determine whether using individual spatial overlap, VI, or UDOI ranked pairs of birds similarly. Because VI and UDOI are nondirectional (i.e. produce a single value for each pair of birds) and individual spatial overlap is directional, we averaged the 2 individual spatial overlap values for each pair of birds to create a single value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>) when directly comparing individual spatial overlap with VI and UDOI.We estimated the minimum sample size necessary for creating 2D and 3D utilization distributions by creating 100 random subsamples (without replacement) of 10 locations, 20 locations, etc., until reaching the final sample including all 180 locations. We then plotted these data to visually estimate at what number of locations the territory size stabilized. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly (2008)</xref> criticized visual estimation of this asymptote, so we also determined the point at which the 95&percnt; confidence interval (CI) of the territory size estimate fell within 10&percnt; of the final territory size estimated using all 180 points.All statistical analyses, except for the creation of the utilization distributions, were carried out using PASW version 18.0 (SPSS, Chicago, Illinois, USA). As spatial overlap data were not normally distributed, we report the median as a measure of central tendency and the interquartile range as a measure of dispersion.We collected spatial overlap data on 17 redstarts in scrub (<italic>x̄</italic> number of locations &equals; 68 &plusmn; 2.1, range: 60&ndash;88) and 32 redstarts in mangrove (<italic>x̄</italic> number of locations &equals; 69 &plusmn; 1.3, range: 60&ndash;80). Overall, we quantified spatial overlap for 20 pairs of redstarts in scrub and 49 pairs in mangrove. The total spatial overlap of redstart territories by all neighbors was generally high in both scrub (2D: 34 &plusmn; 30&percnt;, 3D: 26 &plusmn; 24&percnt;) and mangrove habitats (2D: 27 &plusmn; 39&percnt;, 3D: 15 &plusmn; 28&percnt;), with some birds having as much as 50&ndash;60&percnt; of their territory overlapped by neighboring redstarts. For both habitats, 2D and 3D methods of measuring spatial overlap were comparable for some individuals; but for others, 2D methods overestimated individual spatial overlap by as much as 20&percnt; and total spatial overlap by as much as 30&percnt; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-f02">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-f03">2</xref>). More specifically, in scrub habitat, 2D methods significantly overestimated individual spatial overlap and total spatial overlap by 3&percnt; and 9&percnt;, respectively. Similarly, in mangrove habitat, 2D methods significantly overestimated both individual spatial overlap (4&percnt;) and total spatial overlap (12&percnt;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-t01">Table 1</xref>). When comparing 2D and 3D versions of VI and UDOI, we found that in both habitats, 2D versions of VI and UDOI overestimated overlap compared to 3D methods (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-t01">Table 1</xref>).Comparison of 2D and 3D estimates of individual spatial overlap for American Redstarts in scrub (<bold>A</bold>) and mangrove (<bold>B</bold>) habitats, Jamaica. Points above the line show overestimation of overlap using 2D methods.Results of paired-sample Wilcoxon signed-rank tests comparing 2D and 3D measures of spatial overlap for American Redstarts wintering in Jamaica. &ldquo;Individual overlap&rdquo; refers to the spatial overlap between 2 neighboring American Redstarts; &ldquo;total overlap&rdquo; refers to overlap between 1 American Redstart and all its neighbors.To determine whether redstarts potentially avoided areas of overlap with neighbors, we also compared estimates of individual overlap with VI and UDOI. For both 2D and 3D data, values of VI and UDOI were lower than individual spatial overlap (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-t02">Table 2</xref>), which suggests that redstarts avoided areas of overlap. However, despite differences in the raw values, each of the 3 measures ranked pairs of birds almost identically in terms of spatial overlap for both scrub (2D: Kendall's <italic>W</italic> &equals; 1.00, df &equals; 2, <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.001, 3D: Kendall's <italic>W</italic> &equals; 1.00, df &equals; 2, <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.001) and mangrove habitat (2D: Kendall's <italic>W</italic> &equals; 0.98, df &equals; 2, <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.001, 3D: Kendall's <italic>W</italic> &equals; 0.96, df &equals; 2<italic>, P</italic> &le; 0.001).Median (&plusmn; interquartile range) values for 3 measures of 2D and 3D spatial overlap for American Redstarts wintering in Jamaican scrub and mangrove forests.Considering all 9 males for which we collected 180 points, we found that territory size generally approached an asymptote around 50&ndash;70 locations with 2D data, whereas it took 90&ndash;110 locations for 3D data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-f04">Figure 3</xref> and Appendix Figure 4). We found that the 95&percnt; CI of territory size fell within 10&percnt; of the final estimate of territory size at 40&ndash;50 points for 8 of 9 birds using 2D data, but took &sim;90 points for 1 individual. Using 3D data, 80&ndash;90 points were needed to reach this threshold for all but 1 individual, for which 100 points were needed.Territory size estimates at various sample sizes in 2D (closed circles) and 3D (open diamonds) for a representative American Redstart wintering in Jamaica. Each point represents the mean (&plusmn; SD) territory size for 100 random (without replacement) resamples at the given sample size. For the additional 8 males in the analysis, see Appendix Figure 4.Our results highlight the importance of taking into account all 3 spatial dimensions simultaneously when quantifying space use. Territories have been defined in many ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Nice1">Nice 1941</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Whitaker1">Whitaker and Warkentin 2010</xref>) but can be thought of most simply as &ldquo;any defended area&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Noble1">Noble 1939</xref>). Wintering redstarts exhibit strong defense of their territories, as evidenced by playback experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Sliwa1">Sliwa and Sherry 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Marra1">Marra 2000</xref>), but our results revealed that some tolerate a high degree of spatial overlap with neighbors, even though they do not necessarily overlap in time (see below). Regardless, using 2D methods resulted in significant overestimates of spatial overlap compared to 3D methods in both habitats (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Simpfendorfer1">Simpfendorfer et al. 2012</xref>). Similarly, 2D versions of VI and UDOI both overestimated the extent of spatial overlap compared to 3D versions. This suggests that although wintering redstarts tolerate a fairly high degree of spatial overlap with their conspecific neighbors, they seem to partition space in all 3 spatial dimensions, possibly to reduce agonistic interactions. However, because of the addition of another dimension in which space use can vary, some difference between 2D and 3D measures of overlap might be likely even if space use were totally random. Canopies in scrub and mangrove are fairly low (see above), and we would expect that in more vertically complex environments, differences between 2D and 3D methods would be greater. What remains unknown, however, is how redstarts overlap in 3D space with heterospecifics. Furthermore, we know little about how factors such as age, sex, habitat, resource levels, and both conspecific and heterospecific density might affect levels of overlap. Regardless, understanding 3D partitioning of space and proper quantification of spatial overlap is important for understanding the potential for both interspecific and intraspecific competition with neighbors.Estimates of spatial overlap from both VI and UDOI were lower than individual spatial overlap, regardless of the number of dimensions, which indicates that redstarts may avoid spending time in areas of overlap. Avoidance of overlapped areas presumably reduces agonistic interactions with neighbors and emphasizes the importance of taking the utilization distribution into account when assessing overlap between territories or home ranges (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seidel1">Seidel 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Millspaugh2">Millspaugh et al. 2004</xref>). However, all 3 measures of spatial overlap resulted in identical rankings of pairs of neighbors in terms of the extent of overlap. This suggests that although redstarts perhaps avoided areas of overlap, each of the 3 measures would have resulted in very similar interpretations if the goal were simply to rank individuals by the amount of overlap.Interpreting whether redstarts avoided areas of overlap is challenging because of known biases of these 2 indices. For example, VI and UDOI tend to be biased low when the true overlap is high; in some cases, they will be biased high if the true overlap is low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seidel1">Seidel 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Millspaugh2">Millspaugh et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>). Unfortunately, these biases are known to vary with both sample size and the shape of the utilization distributions, thus making interpretation within a study and comparison among studies difficult (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seidel1">Seidel 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>). In our case, estimates of overlap using VI seemed reasonable, in that they were only somewhat smaller than estimates using individual spatial overlap. Visual inspection of the areas of spatial overlap indicated that redstarts occupied these areas, at least to some extent. Estimates of overlap using UDOI were perhaps less reasonable, for they indicated that redstarts almost never occupied overlapped areas, even though plots of the overlapping utilization distributions showed that both birds spent some time in the overlapped area. Little is known about how either of these 2 indices functions at the relatively low levels of individual spatial overlap found in our study. Similarly low overlap may be expected for other territorial species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Millspaugh2">Millspaugh et al. 2004</xref>). Therefore, more study will be needed to assess more fully the utility of these overlap indices. However, both VI and UDOI can be used not only to measure the overlap between 2 different individuals, but also to quantify how the same individual's territory changes over time (e.g., between life history stages, or before and after an experimental manipulation). In fact, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny (2005)</xref> showed that VI may be better suited in this context than it is in measuring overlap between 2 different individuals. Regardless, both VI and UDOI may be most useful for estimating the similarity of 2 different estimates of the same animal's utilization distribution pending further study at the low levels of individual spatial overlap seen in our study.For 2D data, our sample-size analyses support what other researchers have reported for minimum sample size (40&ndash;70 points; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Worton1">Worton 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seaman2">Seaman and Powell 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seaman1">Seaman et al. 1999</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Belant1">Belant et al. (2012)</xref> postulated that 3D analyses would require a sample size an order of magnitude larger than that needed for 2D analyses; this was not supported by our results&mdash;the first such assessment for 3D data&mdash;which indicated that 80&ndash;110 points sufficed. However, minimum sample size may vary with species, age, sex, habitat, territory size, accuracy of location collection (e.g., satellite vs. radio-transmitters), and sampling regime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Borger1">B&ouml;rger et al. 2006</xref>). Therefore, our recommendation is that 80&ndash;110 points should be used at a minimum until data from other species permit better generalizations. It is important to note that our estimates indicate only the minimum sample size for estimating the outer boundary of the territory (i.e. 95th isopleths) and that different sample sizes may be needed to estimate other properties of the utilization distribution.The ability to quantify space use in 3D could advance the study of animal behavior and ecology in several ways. For example, the Hutchinsonian niche (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Hutchinson1">Hutchinson 1957</xref>) is a fundamental concept in ecology, and past niche descriptions have failed to simultaneously consider all 3 spatial dimensions, despite the fact that differentiation in space alone appears to be an important determinant of community structure and the resulting species richness across many taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Cunha1">Cunha and Vieira 2004</xref>, and references therein). By creating 3D utilization distributions, ecologists may be able to detect niche differentiation previously missed by 2D analyses, especially in vertically complex environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Cunha1">Cunha and Vieira 2004</xref>).Analysis of space use in 3D may also lead to better understanding of habitat use and selection. Integration of 3D utilization distributions with 3D habitat models created using LIDAR (light detection and ranging) or photogrammetric methods employed by an unmanned aerial system (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Dandois1">Dandois and Ellis 2013</xref>) could improve such analyses by allowing ecologists to more accurately determine how differences in habitat structure, and the associated resources (e.g., food, cover, and nesting sites), correlate with differences in space use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Belant1">Belant et al. 2012</xref>). Gaining a more realistic understanding of habitat selection and use in this manner could benefit not only ecologists, but also managers tasked with making conservation decisions. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Belant1">Belant et al. (2012)</xref> recently suggested that understanding how, when, and where particular species move in 3D could allow for reduction of bird and bat strikes with airplanes and more informed decisions on where to build wind farms to reduce bird, bat, and insect mortality. Clearly, 3D utilization distributions have the potential to benefit both basic science and wildlife management, but further refinement of this method to include other dimensions (e.g., time) may prove even more useful.Time, like height and depth, has rarely been considered when creating utilization distributions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>), and it has never been incorporated simultaneously as a fourth dimension. However, space use varies in time, and such variation may have implications for the study of territory size and shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Spencer2">Spencer et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Keating1">Keating and Cherry 2009</xref>), habitat selection and use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Keating1">Keating and Cherry 2009</xref>), trophic interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Spencer1">Spencer et al. 1991</xref>), and predator&ndash;prey relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Palomares1">Palomares et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Durant1">Durant 1998</xref>). Incorporating time into 3D measures of spatial overlap may also be important for measuring the type and amount of competition within or among species. For example, our results indicate a high degree of total spatial overlap for some wintering redstarts, but field observations suggest that redstart territories rarely overlap in both space and time. Thus, incorporating time could have allowed us to determine whether competition was exploitative or interference based. The software package &ldquo;ks&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong1">Duong 2007</xref>) allows for kernel density estimation in up to 6 dimensions, so incorporation of time as a fourth dimension should be possible (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Keating1">Keating and Cherry 2009</xref>). However desirable, collection of the necessary data is challenging. In our case, we would have needed multiple teams collecting data on neighboring birds simultaneously to determine whether pairs of birds used the overlapped space at the same time. Furthermore, given the addition of another dimension, increased sample sizes would have been necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Silverman1">Silverman 1986</xref>). For larger organisms that can carry satellite-based tracking devices, automated, simultaneous, and high-volume sampling is currently possible and could permit the incorporation of time. Similarly, acoustic systems have the ability to capture high-volume horizontal-position and depth data for aquatic organisms (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Simpfendorfer1">Simpfendorfer et al. 2012</xref>). Finally, efforts are underway to incorporate the collection of vertical height into automated radio-tracking technology (B. C. Dossman personal communication), thus providing the potential for incorporation of time into 3D analyses for smaller organisms as well.Before widespread adoption of 3D utilization distribution methods, further refinement is needed in several areas. First, it appears that lessons learned regarding bandwidth selection for bivariate data do not necessarily apply to multivariate data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong3">Duong and Hazelton 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Duong4">2005b</xref>). We do know that bandwidth selection can have large consequences on the resulting size, shape, and accuracy of the utilization distributions (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Laver1">Laver and Kelly 2008</xref>). Second, little is known about the minimum sample size required for creation of accurate 3D utilization distributions, because the present study is the first to investigate sample size. However, sample size can have a strong effect on home-range and territory size estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Worton1">Worton 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seaman2">Seaman and Powell 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Seaman1">Seaman et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Barg1">Barg et al. 2005</xref>); therefore, more studies using both simulated and empirical data are needed to establish guidelines. Third, the 2 overlap indices used in our study (VI and UDOI), along with several others (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>), have not been previously adapted for use with 3D data. As a result, more information is needed on their performance in relation to sample size, bandwidth selection, amount of spatial overlap, and utilization distribution size and shape. Clearly, more theoretical and practical work is needed before widespread use of 3D utilization distributions. Nonetheless, the ability to model animal movements, determine home-range and territory size, and quantify spatial overlap in 3D represents an exciting advance in methodology that should prove broadly useful in studies of animal behavior and ecology.We thank the Petroleum Corporation of Jamaica and the Font Hill staff for access to field sites. We also thank T. Duong for assistance with package &ldquo;ks,&rdquo; S. D. Hafner for troubleshooting code, and assistants for help with fieldwork. Finally, we thank J. Pointon at OmniSTAR for providing access to subscription satellite service. P.P.M. and T.W.S. supported all research with a grant (DEB0717243) from the National Science Foundation. The following is code for the program R to (1) create and plot 3D utilization distributions via a multivariate kernel density estimator (Duong et al. 2007) and (2) quantify 3D spatial overlap using VI and UDOI (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Fieberg2">Fieberg and Kochanny 2005</xref>). Portions of the code were adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-681-Simpfendorfer1">Simpfendorfer et al. (2012)</xref>. &num;Loads necessary libraries library("ks&rdquo;) library("MASS&rdquo;) library("KernSmooth&rdquo;) &num;Reads files for Animal A and Animal B into R workspace, where &ldquo;Animal a.csv&rdquo; is a file with X,Y,Z coordinates a&lt;-read.csv("Animal a.csv&rdquo;) b&lt;-read.csv("Animal b.csv&rdquo;) &num;Calls the plug-in bandwidth estimator for dataset &ldquo;a&rdquo; and &ldquo;b" BandA &lt;- Hpi(a) BandB &lt;- Hpi(b) &num;Joins the 2 datasets and then determines the minimum and maximum boundaries for each dimension. It is important &num;that overlapping territories are evaluated in the same physical space. Also adds small buffer so that no part of the &num;territories are cut off. ab&lt;-rbind(a,b) minX&lt;-min(ab$X)-25 minY&lt;-min(ab$Y)-25 minZ&lt;-0 maxX&lt;-max(ab$X)&plus;25 maxY&lt;-max(ab$Y)&plus;25 maxZ&lt;-max(ab$Z)&plus;5 &num;Runs the kernel density analysis fhata &lt;- kde(x&equals;a, H&equals;BandA, binned&equals;FALSE, xmin&equals;c(minX,minY,minZ), xmax&equals;c(maxX,maxY,maxZ),gridsize &equals; 151) fhatb &lt;- kde(x&equals;b, H&equals;BandB, binned&equals;FALSE, xmin&equals;c(minX,minY,minZ), xmax&equals;c(maxX,maxY,maxZ),gridsize &equals; 151) &num;Defines 95th isopleth CL95a &lt;- contourLevels(fhata, cont&equals;95, approx&equals;FALSE) CL95b &lt;- contourLevels(fhatb, cont&equals;95, approx&equals;FALSE) &num;Calculates the volume at the 95th isopleth Vol95a&lt;-contourSizes(fhata, cont&equals;95) Vol95b&lt;-contourSizes(fhatb, cont&equals;95) &num;Allows for use of other isopleths when calculating VI and UDOI (see eqn 5) fhata$estimate &lt;- ifelse(fhata$estimate&gt;&equals;CL95a,fhata$estimate/.95,0) fhatb$estimate &lt;- ifelse(fhatb$estimate&gt;&equals;CL95b,fhatb$estimate/.95,0) &num;Computes individual spatial overlap at 95th isopleth fhat.overlap &lt;- fhata fhat.overlap$estimate &lt;- fhata$estimate&gt;CL95a &amp; fhatb$estimate&gt;CL95b &num;Quantifies volume of overlapped space Overlap95&lt;-contourSizes(fhat.overlap, abs.cont&equals;.5) &num;Computes percentage of territory bird &ldquo;a&rdquo; that is overlapped by bird &ldquo;b&rdquo; and vice versa PercentOverlap95a&lt;-(Overlap95/Vol95a)&ast;100 PercentOverlap95b&lt;-(Overlap95/Vol95b)&ast;100 &num;Computes voxel size vol.cell &lt;- prod(sapply(fhata$eval.points, diff)&lsqb;1,&rsqb;) &num;Calculates 3D versions of VI (eqn 2) and UDOI (eqn 4) VI3D &lt;- sum(pmin(fhata$estimate,fhatb$estimate)&ast;vol.cell) UDOI3D&lt;-Overlap95&ast;sum(fhata$estimate&ast;fhatb$estimate&ast;vol.cell) &num;Plots 95th isopleth of neighboring animals on same graph plot(fhata,cont&equals;95,colors&equals;"red&rdquo;,drawpoints&equals;TRUE,xlab&equals;"&rdquo;, ylab&equals;"&rdquo;, zlab&equals;"&rdquo;,size&equals;2, ptcol&equals;"black&rdquo;) plot(fhatb,cont&equals;95,colors&equals;"blue&rdquo;,add&equals;TRUE,drawpoints&equals;TRUE,xlab&equals;"&rdquo;, ylab&equals;"&rdquo;, zlab&equals;"&rdquo;,size&equals;2,ptcol&equals;"grey&rdquo;) (A&ndash;H) Additional sample-size figures for 8 males not shown in text. Closed circles (2D) and open diamonds (3D) represent territory-size estimates at various sample sizes. Each point represents the mean (&plusmn; SD) territory size for 100 random (without replacement) resamples at the given sample size.