Feather-chewing lice and Tree Swallow biologyEffects of feather lice on flight behavior of male Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>)Generalized linear mixed models: A practical guide for ecology and evolutionExperimental demonstration of the energetic cost of parasitism in free-ranging hostsStress during feather development predicts fitness potentialVertical transmission of feather lice between adult blackbirds <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus merula</named-content></italic> and their nestlings: A lousy perspectiveBarn Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>)Ectoparasites reduce long-term survivorship of their avian hostsOccurrence of feather-degrading bacilli in the plumage of birdsHow birds combat ectoparasitesComparative effects of mites and lice on the reproductive success of Rock Doves (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Columba livia</named-content></italic>)Collection and quantification of arthropod parasites of birdsThe influence of age on the breeding biology of the Tree Swallow, <italic>Iridoprocne bicolor</italic>Clutch size, breeding success, and parental survival in the Tree Swallow (<italic>Iridoprocne bicolor</italic>)The sequence of plumages and molts of passerine birds of New YorkAge-dependent health status and song characteristics in the Barn SwallowAge and plumage color in female Tree SwallowsProtozoa, helminths, and arthropods of birdsThe phylogeny of the louse genus <italic>Brueelia</italic> does not reflect host phylogenyThe biology, ecology, and evolution of chewing liceNestling Tree Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) diets in an upland old field in western MichiganSexual selection, feather breakage and parasites: The importance of white spots in the tail of the Barn Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>)Population biology of swift (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus apus</named-content></italic>) ectoparasites in relation to host reproductive successSexual differences in parental effort during the nestling period in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Microbes in Tree Swallow semenLocal breeding experience and the reproductive performance of Tree SwallowsCommunities of cloacal bacteria in Tree Swallow familiesParasitism, immunity, and arrival date in a migratory bird, the Barn SwallowParasite biodiversity and host defenses: Chewing lice and immune response of their avian hostsUropygial gland size correlates with feather holes, body condition and wingbar size in the House Sparrow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>Is reproduction by Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) cost-free?Frequency and consequences of feather holes in Barn Swallows <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>Louse loads of Pied Flycatchers: Effects of host's sex, age, condition and relatednessThe disparity between observed and uniform distributions: A new look at parasite aggregationQuantitative Parasitology, version 3.0Quantitative Parasitology on the Web, version 1.0Patterns in the distribution of avian lice (Phthiraptera: Amblycera, Ischnocera)A long-term study of reproductive performance in Tree Swallows: The influence of age and senescence on outputTree SwallowQuantifying parasites in samples of hostsPatterns of macroparasite abundance and aggregation in wildlife populations: A quantitative reviewPatterns of macroparasite aggregation in wildlife host populationsTime and recruitment costs as currencies in manipulation studies on the costs of reproductionTree Swallow reproductive investment, stress, and parasitesMolt patterns in the Tree Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)High lineage diversity and host sharing of malarial parasites in a local avian assemblageEffect of vertically transmitted ectoparasites on the reproductive success of swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus apus</named-content></italic>)Anthropometric comparison of world-class sprinters and normal-populationsThe feather holes on the Barn Swallow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic> and other small passerines are probably caused by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brueelia</named-content></italic> spp. liceAdaptation in hole-nesting birdsThe costs of reproduction in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Clutch size, offspring quality, and female survival in Tree Swallows: An experimentHeterogeneities in macroparasite infections: Patterns and processesTree Swallow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Breeding dispersal and philopatry in the Tree SwallowSome banding suggestions at nest boxesCurrent address: Humane Society of the United States, Washington, D.C., USAFeather-chewing lice (Order Phthiraptera, Suborder Ischnocera) commonly infest birds and may affect their survival and reproduction. From 1993 to 2005, we examined several aspects of the biology of breeding Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) potentially associated with holes in wing and tail feathers caused by feather-chewing lice. Most individuals had &lt;10 feather holes, but 90&percnt; of second-year (SY) females, 68&percnt; of after-second-year (ASY) females, and 80&percnt; of males had &ge;1 feather hole. ASY females had significantly fewer feather holes than SY females and males. There was evidence of positive assortative mating for feather hole number between ASY females and their mates. SY females and their mates did not differ significantly in the number of feather holes, but ASY females had significantly fewer holes than their mates. Males with fewer feather holes were heavier and had longer right wings. Feather hole abundance was not significantly associated with reproductive performance. Feather hole abundance was not associated with whether females bred 1 time or &gt;1 time at our study site, but males with fewer holes were more likely to breed &gt;1 time. Mean feather hole abundance differed significantly among years for SY females and males that bred 3 and 4 times, respectively, but not for ASY females that bred 4 times. Collectively, these data suggest that feather-chewing lice, as estimated by the damage they cause to wing and tail flight feathers, have little effect on Tree Swallow fitness.Los piojos masticadores de plumas (Orden Phithiraptera, Suborden Ischnocera) com&uacute;nmente infestan a las aves y pueden afectar su supervivencia y reproducci&oacute;n. De 1993 a 2005, examinamos varios aspectos potencialmente asociados de la biolog&iacute;a de los individuos reproductivos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic> con agujeros en las plumas del ala y la cola causados por piojos masticadores de plumas. La mayor&iacute;a de las golondrinas presentaron menos de 10 agujeros en las plumas pero 90&percnt; de las hembras del segundo a&ntilde;o, 68&percnt; de las hembras de m&aacute;s de dos a&ntilde;os y 80&percnt; de los machos presentaron al menos un agujero en las plumas. Las hembras de m&aacute;s de dos a&ntilde;os presentaron significativamente menos agujaron en las plumas que las hembras de dos a&ntilde;os y los machos. Se encontr&oacute; evidencia de un apareamiento selectivo positivo de acuerdo al n&uacute;mero de agujeros en las plumas entre las hembras de m&aacute;s de dos a&ntilde;os y sus parejas. Las hembras del segundo a&ntilde;o y sus parejas no difirieron significativamente en el n&uacute;mero de agujeros en las plumas, pero las hembras de m&aacute;s de dos a&ntilde;os presentaron significativamente menos agujeros que sus parejas. Los machos con menos agujeros en las plumas fueron m&aacute;s pesados y presentaron alas derechas m&aacute;s largas. La abundancia de agujeros en las plumas no estuvo significativamente asociada con el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo. La abundancia de agujeros en las plumas no estuvo asociada con el hecho de que las hembras hayan tenido cr&iacute;as una vez o m&aacute;s de una vez en nuestra &aacute;rea de estudio, pero los machos con menos agujeros tuvieron mayor probabilidad de criar m&aacute;s de una vez. La abundancia media de agujeros en las plumas difiri&oacute; significativamente entre a&ntilde;os para las hembras del segundo a&ntilde;o y los machos que criaron tres y cuatro veces, respectivamente, pero no para las hembras de m&aacute;s de dos a&ntilde;os que criaron cuatro veces. En conjunto, estos datos sugieren que los piojos masticadores de plumas, seg&uacute;n lo estimado por el da&ntilde;o que causan a las plumas del vuelo del ala y la cola, tienen un efecto menor en la adecuaci&oacute;n biol&oacute;gica de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. bicolor</named-content></italic>.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> agujeros en las plumas, Ischnocera, piojos masticadores de plumas, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>An enduring problem in modern natural history studies is identifying the causes of selection. Parasites have attracted attention as possible causes of selection because they are ubiquitous and negatively affect the survival and reproductive success of their avian hosts (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brown1">Brown and Brown 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton2">Clayton and Moore 1997</xref>). Field ornithologists have focused most of their attention on the effects of ectoparasites on their hosts, probably because detecting their presence is relatively easy compared with detecting endoparasites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton2">Clayton and Moore 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>).Birds are commonly infested with feather-chewing lice (Order Phthiraptera, Suborder Ischnocera) that feed on the nonliving keratin of feather barbules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Janovy1">Janovy 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson2">Johnson and Clayton 2003</xref>). Feeding by ischnoceran lice produces pin-prick-sized holes in the primary and secondary feathers of the wings and in tail feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>). Because feather holes damage feathers, they have the potential to negatively affect fitness in several non&ndash;mutually exclusive ways. First, holes in flight feathers break up the continuity of the flight surfaces, thereby allowing air to move through the holes, reducing aerodynamic efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Norberg1">Norberg 1990</xref>; although the aerodynamic effects of feather holes need experimental examination). Second, feather holes may increase feather breakage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Kose1">Kose et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>), negatively affecting the aerodynamic properties of wing and tail feathers. Third, feather holes may result in increased metabolic rates by increasing the amount of time spent in energetically expensive flapping flight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>). These negative effects suggest that ischnoceran infestations may be important causes of selection in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>). Finally, feather holes, by exposing the medulla of feathers, may increase their susceptibility to damage from feather-degrading bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>).Our goal was to examine the possible role of feather-chewing lice as a cause of selection in Tree Swallows. We counted feather holes caused by lice, rather than counting lice, because we know that in European Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>), feather hole and louse abundance are strongly positively correlated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>) and feather hole abundance covaries with feather breakage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Kose1">Kose et al. 1999</xref>), flight performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>), immunity levels and arrival dates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2004</xref>), song characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Garamszegi1">Garamszegi et al. 2005</xref>), and mate choice preferences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Kose1">Kose et al. 1999</xref>), which all suggests that feather-chewing lice may also be a cause of selection in Tree Swallows. To evaluate the potential of feather-chewing louse infestations as causes of selection in breeding Tree Swallows, we examined relationships between feather holes and patterns of assortative mating, morphology, reproductive performance, and return rates.We studied the relationships between various aspects of the biology of breeding Tree Swallows and louse-chewed feather holes in individuals that bred during 1993&ndash;2005 in wooden nest boxes mounted on metal poles erected in grids in old fields on the campus of Grand Valley State University (GVSU), Ottawa County, Michigan (42&deg;57&prime;N, 85&deg;53&prime;W), USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson3">Johnson and Lombardo 2000</xref>).Breeding Tree Swallows were categorized for analyses as either (a) second-year (SY) female (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 150), (b) after-hatching-year (AHY) female (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 43), (c) after-second-year (ASY) female (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 305), or (d) male (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 432), based on their sex and plumage characteristics, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Dwight1">Dwight (1900)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Hussell1">Hussell (1983)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Winkler1">Winkler et al. (2011)</xref>. We focused our analyses on SY and ASY females and their mates because of the relatively small proportion of breeding AHY females (9.5&percnt; of all females).We began monitoring breeding activity on about May 1 of each year. Clutches were never initiated before that date. We recorded clutch initiation date, clutch size, and the number of fledglings produced from each nest to evaluate reproductive performance. Data from nests lost to predation were not included in analyses of reproductive performance.We captured birds at their nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Yunick1">Yunick 1990</xref>) throughout the breeding season and measured their mass, bill length, unflattened right wing-chord length, and depth of the right tail fork (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2011</xref>) and color-marked them to facilitate individual identification. We banded birds with federal bands to identify individuals that bred multiple times or had fledged from nests at GVSU. We captured &gt;95&percnt; of breeding Tree Swallows each year.We counted the numbers of holes in the primary and secondary feathers of both wings and tail feathers and used the sum of these counts in analyses. Our methods require several caveats. First, we did not identify the species of feather lice infesting our study birds. However, the feather holes found in Barn Swallows and several other small passerines are likely caused by lice of the genus <italic>Brueelia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>). <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brueelia</named-content></italic> spp. are found mostly on passerines and tend to be very host specific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2002</xref>). <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brueelia</named-content></italic> spp. disperse to new hosts on hippoboscid flies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson2">Johnson and Clayton 2003</xref>) and during physical contact between hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Rekasi1">R&eacute;k&aacute;si et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brooke1">Brooke 2010</xref>).Second, we did not quantify feather-chewing lice, so we did not directly test our assumption that feather hole number estimated louse abundance. However, tail feather hole and louse abundance were strongly positively correlated in Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>), which supports our assumption.Third, feather hole counts may overestimate the prevalence of ischnoceran lice because feather holes may also be caused by anomalies during feather growth that produce feather abrasions similar to the holes chewed by lice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti et al. 2002</xref>). Notwithstanding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti et al.'s (2002)</xref> suggestion, we think that our counts of feather holes produced accurate estimates of not only feather damage from activities of feather-chewing lice, but also their abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton4">Clayton and Walther 1997</xref>).We examined data for normality and used parametric or nonparametric statistical analyses, where appropriate, in IBM SPSS Statistics version 20.0 for Windows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-IBM1">IBM 2011</xref>) and SAS version 9.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-SAS1">SAS 2011</xref>). M.P.L. made all morphological measurements and counted louse holes to avoid interobserver variation.We used methods described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Rozsa1">R&oacute;zsa et al. (2000)</xref> and QPweb (Reiczigel et al. 2013) to analyze and report abundance, intensity, and prevalence of feather holes. Feather hole abundance is the number of feather holes found in all birds, including those with no feather holes. We report feather hole abundance as means &plusmn; SE. Feather hole intensity is the number of feather holes in birds with &ge;1 hole; birds with no feather holes are excluded from this calculation. Feather hole prevalence is the proportion of all birds with feather holes. We report feather hole intensity and prevalence as mean &plusmn; 95&percnt; confidence interval.We used QPweb to calculate the degree of aggregation (<italic>k</italic>) and index of discrepancy (<italic>D</italic>) of feather holes. As feather hole aggregation increases, <italic>k</italic> approaches 0; <italic>k</italic> &lt; 1 is typical of most macroparasitic infections because most hosts have few parasites whereas only a few hosts have many (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>). The index of discrepancy quantifies aggregation as the discrepancy between the observed distribution and a hypothetical one in which all hosts are equally infected; <italic>D</italic> ranges from 0 (i.e. no aggregation) to 1 (i.e. all parasites are located in 1 host) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Poulin1">Poulin 1993</xref>). To avoid pseudoreplication, our calculations of <italic>k</italic> and <italic>D</italic> used feather hole count data collected the first time we measured a breeding bird. Most of our analyses focused on feather hole abundance because it estimated feather damage likely to have negative effects on flying ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Norberg1">Norberg 1990</xref>) and, thus, survival.To investigate the relationships between feather hole abundance and the date that feather holes were counted, morphological measures, reproductive performance data, and return rates, we used generalized linear mixed models (GLMMs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Bolker1">Bolker et al. 2009</xref>) in PROC GLIMMIX in SAS. PROC GLIMMIX automatically scales the variance with the overdispersion parameter for GLMMs. The generalized chi-square statistic measures the residual sum of squares in the final model, and the ratio with its degrees of freedom is a measure of variability of the observation about the mean model. The ratio between the Pearson chi-square and the degrees of freedom provides information on the variability of the model; a ratio close to 1 indicates that the variability has been properly modeled and that there is no residual overdispersion. We report instances of overdispersion, which occurs when the residual deviance is greater than the residual degrees of freedom and tends to arise when 1 or more factors that were not measured during the study have an important effect on response variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Crawley1">Crawley 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Bolker1">Bolker et al. 2009</xref>). It may also occur if an incorrect error distribution is specified&mdash;that is, if the probability one is attempting to model is not constant within each cell but behaves like a random variable, resulting in an inflated residual deviance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Crawley1">Crawley 2002</xref>).On the basis of our preliminary analyses, during the GLMM analyses we assumed that feather hole abundance and clutch initiation dates fit a Poisson distribution and that each morphological and reproductive performance variable fit a Gaussian distribution. We used binomial distributions during GLMM analyses to examine whether there were relationships between (a) having 0 or &ge;1 feather holes and morphology and reproductive performance; and (b) having bred only 1 time or &ge;1 time at GVSU and feather hole abundance. We controlled for date in PROC GLIMMIX and specified the interaction between an individual (as indicated by its band number) and year as the random effect because (a) ASY females tend to have earlier dates of clutch initiation and larger clutch sizes, and to fledge more nestlings, than SY females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-DeSteven1">DeSteven 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Robertson1">Robertson and Rendell 2001</xref>); and (b) birds were most often captured when they were tending nestlings, such that individuals that bred earlier in the season were measured, and their feather holes counted, earlier in the season than those that bred later.We report GLMM fixed-effects estimates to indicate the directionality (positive or negative) and degree of the effect of the independent variable(s) on the response variable(s) when GLMM analyses detected statistically significant relationships. All statistical tests were 2-tailed. Differences between measures were considered statistically significant if <italic>P</italic> &le; 0.05.Mean feather hole abundance did not differ significantly among years for SY females (Kruskal-Wallis, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 17.95, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12) but did for ASY females (Kruskal-Wallis, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm02"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 44.67, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and males (Kruskal-Wallis, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm03"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm03.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 45.04, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). We did not control for year in subsequent analyses, however, because year contributed very little to the variation in mean feather hole abundance (SY females: <italic>y</italic> &equals; 399.23 &minus; 0.19<italic>x</italic>, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 150</sub> &equals; 5.75, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.62, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.002; ASY females: <italic>y</italic> &equals; 0.30<italic>x</italic> &minus; 600.16, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 550</sub> &equals; 5.05, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.009; males: <italic>y</italic> &equals; 542.02 &minus; 0.27<italic>x</italic>, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 650</sub> &equals; 2.24, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.003).When breeder category was accounted for, feather hole abundance increased significantly with date (GLMM, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 1,220</sub> &equals; 24.98, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, the model was overdispersed (generalized chi-square test, df &equals; 18.05), and date contributed a very small, but statistically significant, positive effect on feather hole abundance (GLMM, fixed-effects estimate, 0.0044 &plusmn; 0.0008 holes day<sup>&minus;1</sup>, <italic>t</italic><sub>1,220</sub> &equals; 5.00, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). When breeder categories were analyzed separately, feather hole abundance increased significantly with date only for ASY females (GLMM, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 464</sub> &equals; 9.30, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002). Again, the model was overdispersed (generalized chi-square test, df &equals; 12.95). Similarly, whether or not we found &ge;1 feather holes in a breeding individual increased significantly with date for ASY females (GLMM, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 464</sub> &equals; 5.82, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; fixed-effects estimate, 0.0183 &plusmn; 0.008 ASY female day<sup>&minus;1</sup> with holes, <italic>t</italic><sub>461</sub> &equals; 2.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.016) but not for SY females or males (both <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.28).Most breeding individuals had &lt;10 holes in their wing and tail feathers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Distributions of feather holes for SY females and males did not differ significantly from those expected by the negative binomial distribution (i.e. they were aggregated; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f01">Figure 1</xref>). By contrast, the observed data for ASY females did not fit a negative binomial distribution, rendering <italic>k</italic> noninterpretable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Reiczigal1">Reiczigal and R&oacute;zsa 2005</xref>). We did not compute <italic>k</italic> for all birds pooled together because <italic>k</italic> values differed among breeder categories. Computing <italic>k</italic> for all birds pooled together would have resulted in a poorly fitted model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>). Discrepancy values indicated a moderate level of aggregation of feather holes among individuals within each breeder category (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f01">Figure 1</xref>).Distribution of feather holes by category of breeding Tree Swallows at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. Measures of feather hole aggregation: <italic>k</italic> &equals; index of aggregation (as the aggregation of feather holes increases, <italic>k</italic> approaches 0); and <italic>D</italic> &equals; index of discrepancy, which quantifies aggregations as the discrepancy between the observed distribution and a hypothetical one in which all hosts are equally infected (<italic>D</italic> ranges from 0 &lsqb;i.e. no aggregation&rsqb; to 1 &lsqb;i.e. all parasites are in 1 host&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Poulin1">Poulin 1993</xref>).There were significant differences between breeder categories in feather hole prevalence (GLMM, binomial analysis; <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 1,220</sub> &equals; 8.87, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The breeder categories differed significantly in mean (Fisher's exact test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and median (Mood's median test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) prevalence; prevalence in SY females was greater than that in males and ASY females; males had greater prevalence than ASY females (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-t01">Table 1</xref>).Feather hole prevalence, intensity, and abundance in relation to breeder categories of Tree Swallows at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. Prevalence (mean with 95&percnt; confidence interval &lsqb;CI&rsqb; in parentheses) is the percentage of all birds with &ge;1 feather hole. Intensity (mean with 95&percnt; CI) is the number of feather holes in birds with &ge;1 hole; birds with no feather holes were excluded from calculations of intensity. Abundance (mean &plusmn; SE) is the mean number of feather holes found in all birds, including those with no feather holes. Abbreviations: SY &equals; second-year, ASY &equals; after-second-year.Mean (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and median (Mood's median test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) intensity differed significantly among breeder categories and between SY and ASY females (both <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-t01">Table 1</xref>). Likewise, mean intensity differed significantly between SY and ASY females pooled together and males (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02), but median intensity did not (Mood's median test, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.12) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-t01">Table 1</xref>).Feather hole abundance differed significantly among SY females, ASY females, and males (Kruskal-Wallis, <inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm04"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-3-551-ilm04.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 85.07, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001); it was greater in SY than in ASY females (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001); greater in males than in SY and ASY females pooled together (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.005); greater in SY females than in males (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.005); and greater in males than in ASY females (bootstrap 2-sample <italic>t</italic>-test, 1,000 replicates, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-t01">Table 1</xref>).When date was statistically accounted for, GLMM analyses did not detect significant associations between feather hole abundance and right tarsus (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.16), bill (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.16), or right tail fork (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.21) length within any breeder category. By contrast, feather hole abundance was negatively associated with mass (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 549</sub> &equals; 5.12, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; GLMM fixed-effects estimate, &minus;0.0066 &plusmn; 0.0029 holes g<sup>&minus;1</sup>, <italic>t</italic><sub>549</sub> &equals; &minus;2.26, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02) and right wing length in males (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 550</sub> &equals; 5.56, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; GLMM fixed-effects estimate, &minus;0.0175 &plusmn; 0.0074 holes mm<sup>&minus;1</sup>, <italic>t</italic><sub>550</sub> &equals; &minus;2.36, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02) but not in breeding SY or ASY females (both <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.58).Second-year females and their mates did not differ significantly in mean feather hole abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f02">Figure 2</xref>), and linear regression analyses did not detect evidence of assortative mating based on feather hole abundance (<italic>y</italic> &equals; 16.57 &minus; 0.03<italic>x</italic>, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 106</sub> &equals; 0.08, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.78, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.001). By contrast, ASY females had significantly fewer feather holes than their mates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f02">Figure 2</xref>), and linear regression analysis revealed evidence of positive assortative mating based on feather hole abundance (<italic>y</italic> &equals; 0.09<italic>x</italic> &plus; 5.65, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 448</sub> &equals; 5.75, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02). However, the feather hole abundance in males explained very little of the variation in feather hole abundance in their ASY female mates (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.01). Males mated to SY females had significantly greater mean feather hole abundance than males mated to ASY females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Comparisons of mean feather hole abundance between mates in Tree Swallows at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. Mates in second-year (SY) female pairs did not differ significantly in mean abundance of feather holes (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>107</sub> &equals; 1.83, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.07). In after-second-year (ASY) female pairs, males had significantly more feather holes than their mates (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>449</sub> &equals; &minus;2.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03). Males mated to SY females had significantly greater mean feather hole abundance than males mated to ASY females (Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> &equals; 19,381.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001).When date was accounted for, GLMM analyses did not detect significant associations between feather hole abundance and clutch initiation date (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.20), clutch size (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.44), or the number of fledglings produced (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.42) for any breeder category.When date was accounted for, feather hole abundance was significantly associated with whether males bred only 1 time or &gt;1 time at GVSU (GLMM, <italic>F</italic><sub>1, 551</sub> &equals; 9.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002), but not with whether SY or ASY females did so (both <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.65).Breeding males, but not SY or ASY females, with no feather holes during their first breeding season at GVSU were more likely than males with &ge;1 feather hole to breed &ge;1 time (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-t02">Table 2</xref>). However, within each breeder category, there were no significant differences in feather hole abundance during a bird's first breeding season between those individuals that bred only 1 time and those that returned to breed at least 1 more time at GVSU (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.31). However, mean feather hole abundance was significantly greater in the first than in the second breeding season for SY females and males, but significantly lower in the first than in the second season for ASY females at GVSU (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Among birds that bred &ge;4 times, there were no significant differences in feather hole abundance during an individual's first breeding season and subsequent breeding seasons for SY females, ASY females, and males (all <italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.18). Mean feather hole abundance differed significantly among years for 12 SY females that bred 3 times, 17 ASY females that bred 4 times, and 17 males that bred 4 times at GVSU (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f04">Figure 4</xref>). In addition, mean feather hole abundance significantly differed among years for 11 males that bred 5 times at GVSU (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 10</sub> &equals; 11.53, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.007).Presence or absence of feather holes in relation to whether a Tree Swallow bred only 1 time or &gt;1 time at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. Abbreviations: SY &equals; second-year, ASY &equals; after-second-year.Comparisons of mean feather hole abundance for each breeder category in first- and second-year breeding Tree Swallows at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. There were significant differences in mean feather hole abundance between first- and second-year breeding for second-year (SY) females (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>25</sub> &equals; 3.00, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.006), after-second-year (ASY) females (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>70</sub> &equals; &minus;2.30, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02), and males (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>115</sub> &equals; 3.42, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001).Comparisons of mean feather hole abundance for each breeder category in first-, second-, third-, and fourth-year breeding Tree Swallows at the GVSU study site, Michigan, USA, 1993&ndash;2005. Feather hole abundance differed significantly among years for 12 second-year (SY) females that bred 3 times (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 11</sub> &equals; 12.41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.005), 17 after-second-year (ASY) females that bred 4 times (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 16</sub> &equals; 11.69, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004), and 17 males that bred 4 times (<italic>F</italic><sub>1, 16</sub> &equals; 14.92, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001).The pattern of feather hole aggregation we observed in breeding Tree Swallows was typical of the macroparasite aggregations found in other vertebrate hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shaw1">Shaw and Dobson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shaw2">Shaw et al. 1998</xref>). Most individuals had &lt;10 feather holes; only a few had many. Indices of discrepancy for all categories indicated a moderate level of aggregation of feather holes among individuals in each breeder category.Depending on breeder category, feather hole prevalence ranged from 68&percnt; to 90&percnt;. These prevalence values are lower than those reported for Barn Swallows in separate studies in Hungary: &gt;99&percnt; of 673 adult females and males in eastern Hungary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>) and 88&ndash;97&percnt; of 781 adults and juveniles at 2 locations in central Hungary had feather holes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>). A lower prevalence, 52&percnt; of 25 adult Barn Swallows, was observed in Spain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shutler2">Shutler et al. (2004)</xref> found that 46&percnt; of 52 adult Tree Swallows sampled in Saskatchewan, Canada, had lice of the genera <italic>Brueelia</italic> and <italic>Myrsidea. Myrsidea</italic> (Suborder Ambylcera) feed by chewing on skin and so are not responsible for producing feather holes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson2">Johnson and Clayton 2003</xref>). <italic>Brueelia longa</italic> were much less prevalent on Cliff Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Petrochelidon pyrrhonota</named-content></italic>) than on either Barn or Tree Swallows; only 8&percnt; of 1,551 Cliff Swallows breeding in western Nebraska harbored <italic>B. longa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brown3">Brown et al. 1995</xref>). Variations in prevalence among different swallow species suggest that they vary in their susceptibility to infestations of feather-chewing lice, and different populations of the same species exhibit geographic variation in prevalence. Differences among populations in prevalence could also result from differences among observers in their louse-detection abilities. It is not surprising that colonially nesting Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brown2">Brown and Brown 1999</xref>), on average, had a higher prevalence of feather holes than Tree Swallows, because lice tend to be more prevalent and less aggregated on colonial than on territorial hosts because lice typically require body-to-body contact for transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Rekasi1">R&eacute;k&aacute;si et al. 1997</xref>). It is surprising that ischnoceran lice infested relatively few colonially nesting Cliff Swallows that often build their nests in contact with one another because other ectoparasites frequently infest Cliff Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brown1">Brown and Brown 1996</xref>).In the present study, feather hole prevalence and abundance varied significantly among categories of breeding Tree Swallows and were lowest in ASY females, followed by males and SY females. This pattern suggests that ASY female Tree Swallows may be more resistant than males and SY females to ischnoceran infestations.Because feather-chewing lice rely primarily on physical contact between hosts for dispersal opportunities, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brooke1">Brooke (2010)</xref> predicted that lice would preferentially aggregate on female, rather than male, Eurasian Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus merula</named-content></italic>) to increase their chances of dispersal to new hosts because females brood nestlings more than males do. He found that prevalence, but not intensity, of <italic>Brueelia merulensis</italic> was greater on females than on males but did not detect differences between male and females for 2 other species of feather lice, <italic>Philopterus turdi</italic> and <italic>Menacanthus eurysternus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brooke1">Brooke 2010</xref>). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Potti1">Potti and Merino (1995)</xref> found that the ischnoceran lice <italic>Docophorulus capillatus</italic> were more prevalent and abundant on female than on male Pied Flycatchers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>). By contrast, feather hole prevalence and mean abundance were significantly lower on female than on male Tree Swallows, even though opportunities for louse dispersal are greater from females to nestlings because females brood and feed nestlings more often than males do (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Lombardo1">Lombardo 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2011</xref>). Others have not found sex-related patterns of ectoparasite infestations, for example in Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>) and House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-MorenoRueda1">Moreno-Rueda 2010</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that sex-related patterns of ectoparasite infestation vary among passerine species.Similarities in feather hole abundance between mates may reflect positive assortative mating or, more simply, recent transmission of lice from a mate. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Potti1">Potti and Merino (1995)</xref> found a significant correlation between Pied Flycatcher mates in the number of <italic>D. capillatus</italic> lice on their crowns. By contrast, in the present study, although SY female Tree Swallows and their mates did not differ in mean feather hole abundance, there was no correlation between mates in abundance&mdash;a pattern inconsistent with assortative mating. The significant correlation between ASY females and their mates in feather hole abundance is consistent with both assortative mating and recent transmission of lice between mates. However, the observation that ASY females had significantly fewer feather holes than their mates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f02">Figure 2</xref>) is inconsistent with the &ldquo;recent transmission&rdquo; explanation, reinforcing the hypothesis that ASY females are more resistant to infestations of chewing lice than other categories of breeding Tree Swallows. Additionally, the mates of ASY females had significantly fewer feather holes than the mates of SY females. This pattern suggests that older males may be more resistant than younger males to ischnoceran infestations because the mates of SY females are more likely to be younger than the mates of ASY females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Robertson2">Robertson et al. 1992</xref>).The overall pattern of younger individuals having greater feather hole prevalence and abundance than older ones suggests 2 explanations that are not mutually exclusive. First, perhaps older birds become more resistant to feather-chewing lice because, with experience, they become better at mechanically removing lice from their feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton1">Clayton et al. 2010</xref>). Alternatively, older birds, as a result of their prior experience, may have more time available for removing ectoparasites because they take less time to perform other tasks such as nest building and foraging. Second, it is also possible that decreasing prevalence with age may result from the feathers of older individuals being less palatable or digestible to lice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson2">Johnson and Clayton 2003</xref>, D. Shutler personal communication). Finally, young individuals with large numbers of feather holes may be of lower overall quality and do not survive. However, our data suggest that feather hole abundance&mdash;and, thus, the ability to resist damage from feather-chewing lice&mdash;had little effect on the survival of breeding Tree Swallows.The patterns of aggregations of feather holes that we observed suggest that feather-chewing lice may not typically be important causes of selection in Tree Swallows, in that a small proportion of individuals had many feather holes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Consequently, if there is parasite-associated mortality, a small proportion of the host population would be lost, and a large segment of the parasite population would be lost simultaneously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Poulin1">Poulin 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>). Indeed, observations suggest that lice are weak causes of selection in wild birds under most circumstances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Rekasi1">R&eacute;k&aacute;si et al. 1997</xref>). For example, feather-chewing lice had little direct effect on their hosts during the breeding season in Rock Pigeons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Columba livia</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton3">Clayton and Tompkins 1995</xref>) and Common Swifts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Apus apus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Lee1">Lee and Clayton 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Tompkins1">Tompkins et al. 1996</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Booth1">Booth et al. 1993</xref>). For several additional reasons, we think that feather-chewing lice had little effect on the evolutionary fitness of Tree Swallows breeding at GVSU during our study period, and we therefore conclude that they may not typically be an important cause of selection in this species.First, although feather hole abundance increased with date for each breeder category, the effect of date was small. The overdispersion of the model describing the relationship between date and feather hole abundance suggests that unmeasured factors influenced the increase in feather holes with date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Crawley1">Crawley 2002</xref>). In addition, the abundance of feather holes found on SY females and males, but not ASY females, over the course of the breeding season was not influenced significantly by date. Moreover, the overdispersion of the model describing the relationship between date and feather hole abundance in ASY females suggests that unmeasured factors influenced the increase in feather holes in these Tree Swallows as the season progressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Crawley1">Crawley 2002</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that feather-chewing louse infestations on individuals do not change appreciably over the course of a breeding season. Although this hypothesis requires a direct test, the pattern suggests that Tree Swallows may become infested with feather-chewing lice before the breeding season commences and control louse infestations as the season progresses, thereby limiting feather damage. Alternatively, as feathers grow and harden after molting, they may become more difficult for lice to chew and, therefore, more resistant to damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Johnson2">Johnson and Clayton 2003</xref>). This hypothesis needs experimental testing. Because Tree Swallows molt their flight feathers before migrating south (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Dwight1">Dwight 1900</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Stutchbury1">Stutchbury and Rohwer 1990</xref>), the consequences of feather holes on long-distance flying ability during the southward migration are probably low. By contrast, feather hole number increased on recaptured Barn Swallows over the course of the season in Hungary, which suggests that those birds did not limit damage to their feathers caused by feather-chewing lice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>). In one study, there was little association between cell-mediated immune responses and richness of ischnoceran genera in Barn Swallows, which suggests that avian immune systems may not be able to control ischnoceran lice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Moller2">M&oslash;ller and R&oacute;zsa 2005</xref>). Swallows probably use their bills to mechanically remove lice from feather shafts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Clayton1">Clayton et al. 2010</xref>), although lice may avoid being removed by &ldquo;hiding&rdquo; between feather barbs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Vas1">Vas et al. 2008</xref>).Second, we found no significant associations between feather hole abundance and measures of Tree Swallow reproductive performance. By contrast, feather hole abundance was negatively correlated with arrival times on breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2004</xref>) and positively correlated with delayed onset of breeding in Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>). However, as in Tree Swallows, feather hole abundance in Barn Swallows was not significantly associated with clutch size or breeding success as measured by the number of fledglings produced. Moreover, feather hole abundance was not associated with nestling condition or patterns of male and female parental care in Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>). We did not examine relationships between feather hole abundance and nestling condition or patterns of parental care in Tree Swallows.Third, feather hole abundance had little effect on Tree Swallow return rates. It did not significantly affect whether SY or ASY females bred &gt;1 time at GVSU. By contrast, males with more feather holes were less likely to breed &gt;1 time. However, there were no significant differences in mean feather abundance during the first breeding season of individuals that bred 1 time or &gt;1 time. This suggests that feather holes had little effect on survivorship, because Tree Swallows show breeding-site fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Winkler2">Winkler et al. 2004</xref>). Similarly, there was not a relationship between louse prevalence and Pied Flycatcher survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Potti1">Potti and Merino 1995</xref>). By contrast, feather holes and ectoparasite loads have been associated with decreased survivorship in Cliff Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Brown3">Brown et al. 1995</xref>) and Barn Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. 2005</xref>).Mean feather hole abundance significantly differed among years for Tree Swallows that bred multiple times at GVSU. Both SY females and males had fewer feather holes after their first breeding season, which suggests that, over time, they became more resistant to feather damage caused by feather-chewing lice. However, this explanation makes it unclear why feather hole abundance increased in ASY females after their first breeding season. By contrast, Pied Flycatchers of both sexes had similar louse loads in successive years, which suggests no improvement in their ability to control louse infestations with experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Potti1">Potti and Merino 1995</xref>).Finally, there were few significant associations between feather hole abundance and morphology in breeding Tree Swallows, which suggests little interaction between the ability to resist feather damage from feather-chewing lice and body size. Male Tree Swallows with relatively few feather holes weighed more and had longer right wings than those with more feather holes. These observations suggest a possible link between the ability to resist damage from feather-chewing lice and typical measures of physical quality in birds. In Barn Swallows, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. (2002)</xref> found no significant relationships between feather hole abundance and wingspan or tail length, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Pap1">Pap et al. (2005)</xref> found that males with more feather holes had shorter tail feathers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Potti1">Potti and Merino (1995)</xref> found a negative correlation between louse load and body condition in Pied Flycatchers. Collectively, these results suggest variation in the association between feather-chewing louse infestations and body condition both within and among passerines.In summary, ischnoceran louse infestations, as estimated by the prevalence and abundance of feather holes, appeared to have little effect on the evolutionary fitness of Tree Swallows nesting at GVSU. In retrospect, this result is not surprising because other evidence suggests that events during the breeding season may not be important causes of selection in this species under most circumstances. First, reproduction, as estimated by the return rates of breeders, appears to be relatively &ldquo;cost-free&rdquo; in Tree Swallows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-DeSteven2">DeSteven 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wiggins1">Wiggins 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Wheelwright1">Wheelwright et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Murphy1">Murphy et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shutler1">Shutler et al. 2006</xref>), and local experience has little effect on subsequent reproductive performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Lombardo3">Lombardo and Thorpe 2010</xref>). There is no compelling evidence that feather mites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shutler2">Shutler et al. 2004</xref>), parasitic worms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Winkler1">Winkler et al. 2011</xref>), blood parasites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Shutler2">Shutler et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Szymanski1">Szymanski and Lovette 2005</xref>, M. P. Lombardo personal observation), or cloacal and semen microbes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Lombardo4">Lombardo et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Lombardo2">Lombardo and Thorpe 2000</xref>) negatively affect adult survivorship or reproductive success, although they must under some circumstances. These observations suggest that, on average, breeding Tree Swallows are in good physical condition.Finally, we propose that it should not be surprising that breeding Tree Swallows appear to be in good physical condition, because a Tree Swallow breeding &ldquo;colony&rdquo; is, in a sense, like an Olympic Village. Just as all of the inhabitants of an Olympic Village are of superior quality compared with the nonqualifying athletes they outcompeted during several rounds of preliminary competitive events, breeding Tree Swallows have also successfully made it through their &ldquo;preliminary events.&rdquo; Breeding Tree Swallows have survived migration between breeding areas and overwintering grounds and successfully competed in nest-site and mate acquisition; ceteris paribus, individuals of inferior quality failed at these &ldquo;events.&rdquo; Consequently, just as there are few significant physical differences among athletes competing in the same Olympic events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-Uth1">Uth 2005</xref>), there are likely to be few physical differences between breeding Tree Swallows. In the context of our study, perhaps those individuals most susceptible to feather damage from feather-chewing lice did not become breeders and therefore were not sampled. Consequently, the differences we detected in the effects of feather-chewing lice among our sample of breeding Tree Swallows were small. This perspective implies that natural selection may be more intense during the migration and overwintering phases of the Tree Swallow's life cycle than during the breeding season. We suggest that this may also be the case for other migratory, secondary cavity-nesting birds that migrate long distances between overwintering and breeding grounds and compete for limited nest sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-3-551-vonHaartman1">von Haartman 1957</xref>).We thank the dozens of field assistants who helped us collect data during the course of this study at Grand Valley State University (GVSU). D. Shutler provided very helpful comments on the manuscript. B. Tate and M. Woller-Skar provided helpful statistical advice.<bold>Funding statement</bold>: The Research and Development Committee and the Department of Biology at GVSU supported this study at various times.<bold>Ethics statement</bold>: The Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at GVSU approved this study.