Divergence history of the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orthotomus sericeus</named-content></italic>) of Sundaland: Implications for the biogeography of Palawan and the taxonomy of island species in generalGenomics of natural bird populations: A gene-based set of reference markers evenly spread across the avian genomeA gene-based genetic linkage map of the collared flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula albicollis</named-content></italic>) reveals extensive synteny and gene-order conservation during 100 million years of avian evolutionMedian-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogeniesNotes on Philippine birds collected by Governor W. Cameron ForbesModelled atmospheric temperatures and global sea levels of the past million yearsAn ancient origin for the enigmatic flat-headed frogs (Bombinatoridae: <italic>Barbourula</italic>) from the islands of Southeast AsiaContrasting patterns of polymorphism and divergence on the Z chromosome and autosomes in two <italic>Ficedula</italic> flycatcher speciesPre-glacial Bornean primate impoverishment and Wallace's lineEcology predicts levels of genetic differentiation in Neotropical birdsThe current refugial rainforests of Sundaland are unrepresentative of their biogeographic past and highly vulnerable to disturbanceTwo new Malaysian subspecies of birdsThe &lsquo;island rule' in birds: Medium body size and its ecological explanationBiogeographic kinetics: Estimation of relaxation times for avifaunas of Southwest Pacific islandsBiogeographic umbilici and the origin of the Philippine avifaunaBiogeography of Philippine birds. In The Birds of the Philippines: An Annotated Check-list. BOU Check-list Series No. 12Oil, geology and changing concepts in the Southwest Philippines (Palawan and the Sulu Sea)Integrating phylogenetic and taxonomic evidence illuminates complex biogeographic patterns along Huxley's modification of Wallace's LineArlequin suite ver 3.5: A new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and WindowsMolecular phylogeny and biogeography of honey-buzzards (genera <italic>Pernis</italic> and <italic>Henicopernis</italic>)Quaternary rainforest refugia in south-east Asia: Using termites (Isoptera) as indicatorsSpecies taxonomy of birds: Which null hypothesis?IOC World Bird List. Version 4.2Vicariance or dispersal? Historical biogeography of three Sunda shelf murine rodents (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Maxomys surifer</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Leopoldamys sabanus</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Maxomys whiteheadi</named-content></italic>)The plate tectonics of Cenozoic SE Asia and the distribution of land and seaCenozoic geological and plate tectonic evolution of SE Asia and the SW Pacific: Computer-based reconstructions and animationsSoutheast Asia's changing palaeogeographyZoogeographic evidence for middle and late Pleistocene land bridges to the Philippine IslandsBiogeography of mammals in SE Asia: Estimates of rates of colonization, extinction and speciationMultilocus methods for estimating population sizes, migration rates and divergence time, with applications to the divergence of <italic>Drosophila pseudooscura</italic> and <italic>D. persimilis</italic>Integration within the Felsenstein equation for improved Markov chain Monte Carlo methods in population geneticsSystematics and zoogeography of Philippine AmphibiaThe spatio-temporal colonization and diversification across the Indo-Pacific by a 'great speciator' (Aves, <italic>Erythropitta erythrogaster</italic>)Evolution in a tropical archipelago: Comparative phylogeography of Philippine fauna and flora reveals complex patterns of colonization and diversificationA well-tested set of primers to amplify regions spread across the avian genomeRevisiting Wallace's haunt: Coalescent simulations and comparative niche modeling reveal historical mechanisms that promoted avian population divergence in the Malay ArchipelagoMultilocus analysis of the evolutionary dynamics of rainforest bird populations in Southeast AsiaPhylogeny of magpie-robins and shamas (Aves: Turdidae: <italic>Copsychus</italic> and <italic>Trichixos</italic>): Implications for island biogeography in Southeast AsiaCryptic genetic diversity in &ldquo;widespread&rdquo; Southeast Asian bird species suggests that Philippine avian endemism is gravely underestimatedFamily Cisticolidae (Cisticolas and allies) &lsqb;<italic>Orthotomus</italic> accounts&rsqb;A new species of lowland tailorbird (Passeriformes: Cisticolidae: <italic>Orthotomus</italic>) from the Mekong floodplain of CambodiaSpecies concepts in ornithologyMammals of south-east Asian islands and their Late Pleistocene environmentsUse of an exotic tree plantation by Bornean lowland forest birdsExplosive Pleistocene diversification and hemispheric expansion of a &ldquo;great speciator.&rdquo;Feeding behavior, toe count, and the phylogenetic relationships among alcedinine kingfishers (Alcedininae)A phylogeny for the Cisticolidae (Aves : Passeriformes) based on nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequence data, and a re-interpretation of an unique nest-building specializationThe birds of the Natuna IslandsOrigin and diversification of Philippine bulbulsThe phylogenetic position of some Philippine &ldquo;babblers&rdquo; spans the muscicapoid and sylvioid bird radiationsNotes on some Philippine tailor-birdsCollections from the Philippine Islands. BirdsTaxonomy is important in conservation: A preliminary reassessment of Philippine species-level bird taxonomyjModelTest: Phylogenetic model averagingSingle-nucleotide polymorphism characterization in species with limited available sequence information: High nucleotide diversity revealed in the avian genomePatterns of genetic variation of the little spiderhunter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arachnothera longirostra</named-content></italic>) in Southeast AsiaSpecies limits in <italic>Pteruthius</italic> (Aves: Corvida) shrike-babblers: A comparison between the Biological and Phylogenetic Species ConceptsMagnitude of sea level lowstands of the last 500,000 yearsMrBayes 3.2: Efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model spaceMaps of Holocene sea level transgressions and submerged lakes on the Sunda shelfMorphological shifts in island-dwelling birds: The roles of generalist foraging and niche expansionPreservation of avian blood and tissue samples for DNA analysisPhylogeography of the magpie-robin species complex (Aves: Turdidae: <italic>Copsychus</italic>) reveals a Philippine species, an interesting isolating barrier, and unusual dispersal patterns in the Indian Ocean and Southeast AsiaOrnithology of Sabah: History, gazetteer, annotated checklist, and bibliographyMolecular phylogeny and insular biogeography of the lowland tailorbirds of Southeast Asia (Cisticolidae: <italic>Orthotomus</italic>)Did geckos ride the Palawan raft to the Philippines?Soils on exposed Sunda Shelf shaped biogeographic patterns in the equatorial forests of Southeast AsiaForaging behaviour of two tailorbirds in Singapore: Habitat, morphological, and temporal comparisonsQuantitative criteria for species delimitationMaps of Pleistocene sea levels in Southeast Asia: shorelines, river systems and time durationsForest contraction in north equatorial Southeast Asia during the Last Glacial PeriodOnland signatures of the Palawan microcontinental block and Philippine mobile belt collision and crustal growth process: A reviewAccretion and postaccretion tectonics of the Calamian Islands, North Palawan block, PhilippinesCurrent address: Smithsonian Institution, National Museum of Natural History, Washington, District of Columbia, USACurrent address: Department of Animal Biology, University of Illinois, Urbana, Illinois, USASubmitted April 13, 2014; Accepted June 6, 2014; Published August 27, 2014The Rufous-tailed Tailorbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orthotomus sericeus</named-content></italic>)&mdash;a Sunda endemic&mdash;is divided into 3 morphologically based subspecies: one in western Sundaland (Malay Peninsula, Sumatra, and associated islands), one from the Natuna Islands in the South China Sea, and one on Borneo, Palawan, and smaller islands of the Sunda continental shelf east of Borneo. Previous study, however, suggested that these subspecies do not conform to molecular genetic subdivisions of the species. We reexamined the morphology and performed molecular phylogeographic and multi-locus coalescent analysis of two subspecies of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird comprising populations on the Malay Peninsula, Sumatra, Borneo, and Palawan. We found (1) little morphological difference among the two subspecies, (2) no substantial genetic differences between the Borneo and western Sunda populations, but (3) marked genetic divergence between the Palawan and other populations. We conclude that the Bornean and western Sunda populations interbred extensively during Quaternary glacio-eustatic land connections, whereas the Bornean and Palawan populations did not. Unlike the other Greater Sunda Islands, Palawan has not been attached by a land bridge to the rest of Sundaland for at least one million years, and its relative isolation has prevented extensive intermixing between Palawan's and other Sunda populations. Thus, the Palawan population appears to be on its own evolutionary trajectory. The ability to demonstrate extensive interbreeding among some Sunda island populations, but not others, illustrates the practicality of testing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gill1">Gill's (2014)</xref> &ldquo;null hypothesis&rdquo; that morphologically distinct populations on different islands are different species unless a compelling argument can be made to the contrary. In this case, Rufous-tailed Tailorbird morphology provided little or misleading evidence of the extent of interbreeding, whereas modern genetic analysis provided a clear view.<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orthotomus sericeus</named-content></italic>&mdash;end&eacute;mica de Sonda&mdash;est&aacute; dividida en tres subespecies en base a la morfolog&iacute;a: una del oeste de Sondalandia (Pen&iacute;nsula Malay, Sumatra e islas asociadas), una de las Islas Natuna en el Mar del Sur de China y una en Borneo, Palawan e islas m&aacute;s peque&ntilde;as de la plataforma continental de Sonda al este de Borneo. Estudios previos, sin embargo, sugirieron que estas subespecies no coinciden con las subdivisiones gen&eacute;ticas moleculares de la especie. Reexaminamos la morfolog&iacute;a y realizamos an&aacute;lisis moleculares filogeogr&aacute;ficos y de coalescencia multi-locus de dos subespecies de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">O. sericeus</named-content></italic> abarcando poblaciones de la Pen&iacute;nsula Malay, Sumatra, Borneo y Palawan. Encontramos (1) poca diferencia morfol&oacute;gica entre las dos subespecies, (2) falta de diferencias gen&eacute;ticas substanciales entre las poblaciones de Borneo y del oeste de Sonda, pero (3) divergencia gen&eacute;tica marcada entre la poblaci&oacute;n de Palawan y otras poblaciones. Concluimos que las poblaciones de Borneo y del oeste de Sonda se entrecruzaron enormemente durante las conexiones terrestres glacio-eust&aacute;ticas del Cuaternario, mientras que las poblaciones de Borneo y de Palawan no lo hicieron. A diferencia de las otras Islas Mayores de Sonda, Palawan no ha estado unida por un puente terrestre al resto de Sondalandia por al menos un mill&oacute;n de a&ntilde;os, y su aislamiento relativo ha impedido una gran entremezcla entre las poblaciones de Palawan y otras poblaciones de Sonda. As&iacute;, la poblaci&oacute;n de Palawan parece estar en su propia trayectoria evolutiva. La posibilidad de demostrar un enorme entrecruzamiento entre algunas poblaciones de las islas de Sonda, pero no entre otras, ilustra la practicidad de evaluar la &ldquo;hip&oacute;tesis nula&rdquo; de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gill1">Gill (2014)</xref> de que poblaciones morfol&oacute;gicamente distintivas en islas diferentes son especies diferentes, a menos de que haya un argumento de peso en contra. En este caso, la morfolog&iacute;a de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">O. sericeus</named-content></italic> brind&oacute; evidencia limitada o confusa del grado de entrecruzamiento, mientras que los an&aacute;lisis gen&eacute;ticos modernos brindaron un panorama claro.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> an&aacute;lisis de coalescencia, an&aacute;lisis multi-locus, Borneo, ciclos glaciares, conceptos de especie, filogeograf&iacute;aPalawan is a large Philippine island (14,650 km<sup>2</sup>) connected to the northeastern end of Sundaland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f01">Figure 1</xref>), the biogeographic region of Southeast Asia that encompasses the Sunda continental shelf and its constituent land masses: the Malay Peninsula, Sumatra, Java, Bali, Borneo, Palawan, and many other islands of the Indo-Malayan Archipelago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Whitmore1">Whitmore 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Whitmore2">1987</xref>). During the Pliocene and Pleistocene, the Sunda shelf was exposed as land numerous times by glacial-eustatic sea level lowering, periodically uniting the Sunda islands with each other and the Asian mainland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sathiamurthy1">Sathiamurthy and Voris 2006</xref>). At these times, Palawan formed a peninsula northeast of Borneo pointing into the heart of the oceanic Philippine islands. Thus, biogeographers traditionally assumed Palawan was the main conduit for Asian vertebrates to reach the Philippines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Dickerson1">Dickerson et al. 1928</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Delacour1">Delacour and Mayr 1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Inger1">Inger 1954</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Darlington1">Darlington 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Diamond2">Diamond and Gilpin 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Heaney1">Heaney 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Dickinson1">Dickinson 1991</xref>). They also assumed that Asian invasions of the oceanic Philippines occurred relatively recently, i.e. during the late Quaternary, when glacial events were most frequent and dramatic. We now know, however, that invasions of the Philippines by many Asian forest animals occurred much earlier than the late Pleistocene, and the route through Palawan was less important than previously believed (e.g., for birds: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim3">Lim et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oliveros1">Oliveros and Moyle 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gamauf1">Gamauf and Haring 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Moyle2">Moyle et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Jones1">Jones and Kennedy 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Moyle1">Moyle et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon1">Sheldon et al. 2009</xref>). The Sunda shelf, when exposed as land, does not simply transform into a wide expanse of rainforest through which forest animals can easily travel, but rather it seems to become a matrix of diverse habitats and montane and river barriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-BrandonJones1">Brandon-Jones 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-GathorneHardy1">Gathorne-Hardy et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Meijaard1">Meijaard and van der Zon 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gorog1">Gorog et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Cannon1">Cannon et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Wurster1">Wurster et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Slik1">Slik et al. 2011</xref>). Movement though Palawan is further impeded by water barriers at both ends, making it act more as a filter or cul-de-sac than a transmigration facilitator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Esselstyn1">Esselstyn et al. 2010</xref>).Map of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird distribution and sampling sites (black squares). Dark gray indicates the approximate distribution of the species (Sundaic lowlands). It is absent from light gray areas (mountains) and blank areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-VanMarle1">Van Marle and Voous 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Madge1">Madge 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Wells1">Wells 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Phillipps1">Phillipps and Phillipps 2014</xref>).Part of the reason Palawan has been misunderstood as a biogeographic force is because only recently have we begun to understand the degree to which it is not a typical Sunda island. Whereas elements of Borneo, Sumatra, and even Java have been part of the Sunda continental core since the Cretaceous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hall2">Hall 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hall3">2009</xref>), Palawan is a newcomer to the area. It began as a continental fragment that broke off southern China &sim;30 Ma and drifted south to hit the Sunda shelf near northeastern Borneo &sim;20&ndash;10 Ma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hall1">Hall 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Zamoros1">Zamoros and Matsuoka 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Yumul1">Yumul et al. 2009</xref>). Although Palawan was originally thought to have been submerged during all or most of its southward journey, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Blackburn1">Blackburn et al. (2010)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Siler1">Siler et al. (2012)</xref> have argued that little evidence of complete submergence has been presented. Instead, on the basis of molecular genetic comparisons of frogs and lizards and a review of geology, they have suggested that parts of Palawan may actually have remained emergent during the entire journey. Moreover, the micro-continental plate on which Palawan sits would have drifted south with other micro-plates that later played a role in the accretion of some of the oceanic Philippine islands (e.g., Panay, Carabao, Mindoro, and the Romblons). Thus, Palawan may have acted as an &ldquo;ark,&rdquo; transporting vertebrates and other organisms to the oceanic Philippines, as well as to Sundaland and even Sulawesi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Blackburn1">Blackburn et al. 2010</xref>). When Palawan reached its current location, it was thrust upward and took on its present conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Durkee1">Durkee 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hall2">Hall 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Yumul1">Yumul et al. 2009</xref>). As a result of its voyage, Palawan experienced a much different history than the other Sunda islands. Also, recent evidence indicates that Palawan has not been &ldquo;firmly&rdquo; connected to Sundaland as a result of sea level lowering. Although sea level models originally suggested a land connection between greater Borneo and Palawan during the last glacial maximum (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Rohling1">Rohling et al. 1998</xref>), recent work indicates that during the most extreme glacial events of the last 700 Ka, sea levels did not fall below 125 m (&plusmn;12 m); before 700 Ka, sea level drops were even less extreme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bintanja1">Bintanja et al. 2005</xref>). Because Palawan is separated from Borneo by a 140 m channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Heaney2">Heaney 1986</xref>), it has probably been isolated by a narrow water barrier for much of the Quaternary, if not forever (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bintanja1">Bintanja et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Esselstyn1">Esselstyn et al. 2010</xref>). Even if the channel were completely closed, the coastal habitat spanning Borneo and Palawan (e.g., mangrove, swamp forest, coastal strand) may not have been hospitable to most species of the interior lowland rainforest.Palawan's relatively recent and tenuous connection to Sundaland helps explain the history of its forest avifauna. Most of its upland birds appear to have colonized from Sundaland within the last 5&ndash;8 Ma; fewer have colonized from the oceanic Philippines; none seems old enough to have ridden the island as an ark from mainland Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim3">Lim et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lohman1">Lohman et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oliveros1">Oliveros and Moyle 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Rahman1">Rahman et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oliveros2">Oliveros et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Irestedt1">Irestedt et al. 2013</xref>). Among its Sunda colonizers, there appear to be 2 classes of genetic divergence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref>): the first representing earlier colonists, each of which is morphologically and genetically distinct from its sister taxon in Sundaland; and the second comprising more recent colonists displaying little morphological or genetic difference from their Bornean sisters. The first group consists entirely of Palawan endemics, many of which have been recently accorded status as full species. Among these endemics are the sister species of some Sunda taxa that are completely or mainly restricted to mature forest in Borneo, e.g., Bornean Wren-Babbler (<italic>Ptilocichla leucogrammica</italic>), Short-tailed Babbler (<italic>Malacocincla malaccensis</italic>), and Grey-cheeked Bulbul (<italic>Alophoixus bres</italic>). Such species would be incapable of dispersing from Borneo to Palawan without a substantial rainforest corridor connecting the 2 islands (assuming ancestors of these species had the same habitat requirements as the modern birds). The second group of Palawan taxa, i.e. those displaying little divergence from their Bornean sisters, includes species that are expected to be good overwater dispersers: e.g., 2 kingfishers that occur in mangrove&mdash;Oriental Dwarf Kingfisher (<italic>Ceyx erithaca</italic>) and Blue-eared Kingfisher (<italic>Alcedo meninting</italic>)&mdash;and the highly vagile Black-headed Bulbul (<italic>Pycnonotus atriceps</italic>). One species that exhibits little morphological and only moderate genetic distinctiveness between its Palawan and Bornean populations is the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orthotomus sericeus</named-content></italic>). Unlike the kingfishers and Black-headed Bulbul, the tailorbird is a notably poor flier and, presumably, disperser. Thus, it would not be expected to move back and forth between Borneo and Palawan without a land bridge.Bornean and Palawan sister taxa and their uncorrected proportional mitochondrial divergence values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim3">Lim et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lohman1">Lohman et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oliveros1">Oliveros and Moyle 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Rahman1">Rahman et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>, R.G.M. and C.H.O. personal observation).The Rufous-tailed Tailorbird occurs on the Malay Peninsula, Sumatra, Belitung, Borneo, Palawan, Natunas, and various coastal islands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f01">Figure 1</xref>). In the Philippines it is found only on islands that lie on the Sunda continental shelf, i.e. the Palawan chain (Balabac, Palawan, Busuanga, Culion), the western Sulu Archipelago (Sibutu, Sitanki, Omapoy, Sipangkot, Tumindao), and Cagayan Sulu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Dickinson2">Dickinson et al. 1991</xref>). Originally, 4 subspecies of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird were described: the nominate <italic>O. s. sericeus</italic> of Borneo, <italic>O. s. nuntius</italic> of Cagayan Sulu Island and the Sulu Archipelago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bangs1">Bangs 1922</xref>), <italic>O. s. hesperius</italic> of Sumatra, Belitung, and the Malay peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Chasen1">Chasen and Kloss 1931</xref>), and <italic>O. s. rubicundulus</italic> of the Natuna Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oberholser1">Oberholser 1932</xref>). Individuals from Palawan were not examined in this initial taxonomic process. Later, the Palawan and other western Philippine populations were merged into <italic>O. s. sericeus</italic> because they were considered undifferentiated from Bornean birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Peters1">Peters 1939</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Parkes1">Parkes 1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Dickinson2">Dickinson et al. 1991</xref>). This arrangement left just 3 morphologically based subspecies: <italic>O. s. hesperius</italic>, <italic>O. s. sericeus</italic>, and <italic>O. s. rubicundulus</italic>. However, subsequent molecular comparisons suggest this arrangement may be wrong. Mitochondrial ND2 sequence comparisons have indicated that the Palawan population is &sim;1.9&percnt; divergent from the Bornean population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>) and that the Borneo and western Sunda populations have recently and extensively intermixed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim1">Lim et al. 2011</xref>).In this paper, we explore Rufous-tailed Tailorbird phylogeography further in an effort to improve our understanding of the species' population history and the historical relationship between Palawan and the rest of Sundaland. Our investigation proceeds in 2 steps. First, we reexamine previous findings based on morphological characteristics and ND2 sequence divergence by comparing a relatively large number of individuals from populations spanning Sundaland. This step shows that populations from western Sundaland (Sumatra and the Malay Peninsula), Borneo, and Palawan are very similar to one another morphologically, and confirms that the Palawan population is genetically distinct from the western Sunda and Borneo populations. Next, we examine the divergence history of the Palawan population relative to the combined western Sunda and Borneo populations using a multi-locus coalescent analysis of ND2 and nuclear gene sequences. Specifically, we use immigration with migration analysis (IMa) to estimate the time since divergence of the 2 populations, levels of gene flow between them since their divergence, and their effective population sizes. This analysis provides a fairly clear picture of the recent biogeographic history of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird populations. It also illustrates an effective approach to identifying species limits in an island setting and, as such, illustrates the practicality of testing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gill1">Gill's (2014)</xref> &ldquo;null hypothesis&rdquo; that morphologically distinguishable populations on different islands be considered different species unless a compelling argument can be made to the contrary.Because original descriptions of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird subspecies were vague and confused (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oberholser1">Oberholser 1932</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Peters1">Peters 1939</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Parkes1">Parkes 1960</xref>), we reassessed morphological variation among the populations whose DNA was compared in this study using specimens borrowed from the Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University, American Museum of Natural History, Delaware Museum of Natural History, Field Museum, Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science, National Museum of Natural History (U.S.A), Natural History Museum (U.K.), University of Kansas Museum of Natural History, and the Western Foundation. The taxa compared were <italic>O. s. sericeus</italic> from Borneo (30 individuals), <italic>O. s. hesperius</italic> from western Sundaland (peninsular Malaysia, Singapore, and Sumatra; 31 individuals), and <italic>O. s. sericeus</italic> from Palawan (31 individuals). We did not compare the Natuna and Cagayan Sulu populations because very few specimens exist from these sites; almost all are types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bangs1">Bangs 1922</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Chasen1">Chasen and Kloss 1931</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Oberholser1">Oberholser 1932</xref>), which are difficult to borrow and which museums are loath to subsample for DNA; and all are very old (collected in 1893, 1900, and 1921) and, thus, likely to be faded. Also, we reasoned that the populations of Natuna, which lies in the South China Sea between Borneo and the Malay Peninsula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f01">Figure 1</xref>), would have been well connected and likely to interbreed with western populations during most or all glacial events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Cannon1">Cannon et al. 2009</xref>). Cagayan Sulu is biogeographically more interesting than the Natunas, as it lies at the eastern limit of Sundaland. Unfortunately, only one specimen is available from this island, the type for the original <italic>O. nuntius</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bangs1">Bangs 1922</xref>). We hope to work with this specimen in the future.We examined plumage color and measured 7 characters (all measurements were taken by VLC from adult birds using standard calipers): culmen length, length from nostril to bill tip, bill width, and bill depth; wing length; tail length; and tarsus length. Measurement data were analyzed using principal components analysis (PCA) and discriminant function analysis (DFA) using program &ldquo;R&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2008</xref>) with the package MASS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Venables1">Venables and Ripley 2002</xref>). PCA was based on a singular value decomposition of the data matrix for numerical accuracy. To test for sex-specific differences, separate analyses were performed on male and female specimens.For molecular comparisons, we obtained mitochondrial ND2 (nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide dehydrogenase subunit 2) sequences of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird from 51 individuals from 3 areas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>): Palawan (3 individuals); Malaysian Borneo (44 individuals); and Sumatra and Singapore (4 individuals). Two outgroup species were used in the phylogenetic analyses: Grey-backed Tailorbird (<italic>O. derbianus</italic>) of the Philippines and Ashy Tailorbird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">O. ruficeps</named-content></italic>) from Borneo. These species are members of the clades closest to Rufous-tailed Tailorbird, but are still 9&ndash;11&percnt; divergent from it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>). ND2 sequences of 21 specimens, including outgroups, were produced in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Nguembock1">Nguembock et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim2">Lim and Sheldon 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>); their GenBank numbers are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>. Seven nuclear loci were sequenced in 19 individuals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>). Six of the nuclear loci were autosomal: 16214 (methylmalonic aciduria type A protein mitochondrial precursor), 20771 (p21-activated protein kinase-interacting protein), and 27189 (gamma-tubulin complex component 3) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Backstrom1">Backstr&ouml;m et al. (2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Backstrom2">2008b</xref>); GARS (glythyl-tRNA synthetase intron 11) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Kimball1">Kimball et al. (2009)</xref>; and GADPH (glyceraldehyde 3-PDH) and TGFB (fifth nuclear intron of transforming growth factor, &beta;2) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Primmer1">Primmer et al. (2002)</xref>. One was a Z-linked locus: BRM15 (a core ATPase of the SWI/SNF ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling complex) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Borge1">Borge et al. (2005)</xref>.<italic>Orthotomus</italic> species and DNA samples used in this study.DNA was extracted from ethanol-preserved pectoral muscle using DNeasy tissue kits (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) or from blood preserved in Queen's Lysis Buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Seutin1">Seutin et al. 1991</xref>) using a standard phenol&ndash;chloroform protocol. PCR was conducted using primers published in the citations above. PCR products were purified with 20&percnt; polyethylene glycol and cycle-sequenced in both directions using PCR primers and BigDye Terminator Cycle-Sequencing kits version 3.1 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA). Cycle-sequencing products were cleaned with Sephadex G-50 fine (GEHealthcare, Little Chalfont, Buckinghamshire, UK) before analysis on an ABI Prism 3100 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems). The sequences were assembled and edited in Sequencher version 4.7 (Gene Codes, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA). To determinate allelic phases of non-recombining blocks in nuclear sequences, we used TA-cloning and computational procedures described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim2">Lim and Sheldon (2011)</xref>. GenBank numbers of sequences produced in this study are KJ864966&ndash;KJ865225.The phylogeny of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird populations was estimated from aligned ND2 sequences using maximum-likelihood and Bayesian approaches, with models of molecular evolution first estimated with jmodeltest 0.1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Posada1">Posada 2008</xref>). We used MrBayes 3.2 to construct a majority rule consensus Bayesian tree using the following parameters: 2 simultaneous runs, number of MCMC generations &equals; 10 million (sampling every 1,000 trees), burn-in fraction &equals; 0.25, 4 search chains in each run, general time reversible model of nucleotide substitution (nst &equals; 6), and gamma-distributed rate variation across sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Ronquist1">Ronquist et al. 2012</xref>). We ascertained that runs in MrBayes had converged in view of the small average standard deviation of split frequencies (0.004) and by inspection of log-likelihood-value and parameter trend lines in the program Tracer v1.6. For maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis, 500 bootstrap replicates were estimated using a genetic algorithm implemented by the GARLI web service: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molecularevolution.org/software/phylogenetics/garli/garli_create_job" xlink:type="simple">http://www.molecularevolution.org/software/phylogenetics/garli/garli&lowbar;create&lowbar;job</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Zwickl1">Zwickl 2006</xref>). GARLI parameters were set as follows: non-partitioned analysis; general time reversible model of nucleotide substitution; estimated base frequencies and proportion of invariant sites; and gamma-shaped, across-site rate heterogeneity (4 categories).We evaluated Rufous-tailed Tailorbird population structure using an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) of the ND2 data in ARLEQUIN 3.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Excoffier1">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>). Following results from phylogenetic analysis (see Results) and based on our previous observation of genetic variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim1">Lim et al. 2011</xref>), we partitioned the data by grouping birds from western Sundaland and Borneo into one population (BWS) and birds from Palawan into another. We also constructed a median joining network from the ND2 data using the program Network v.4.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bandelt1">Bandelt et al. 1999</xref>) to visualize genetic diversity and geographical relationships.IMa analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hey1">Hey and Nielsen 2004</xref>) was conducted to determine time of divergence, effective population sizes, and gene flow between Palawan and BWS. In this analysis, we used phased sequences of all 7 nuclear genes and sequences of ND2. Approximate mutation rates of 4 nuclear genes (BRM15, GAPDH, GARS, and TGFB) and ND2 were applied so that IMa would produce results in demographic units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim2">Lim and Sheldon 2011</xref>). To determine prior limits and run convergence characteristics, we performed several short-length (5 million generation) and moderate-length (50 million generation) IMa runs. We then carried out a final analysis of 100 million generations with 10 heated chains (total run time &equals; 343 h; geometric heating scheme, g<sub>1</sub> &equals; 0.8, g<sub>2</sub> &equals; 0.9). We recorded results every 100 generations and discarded the first 10&percnt; as burn-in. We set one year as the generation time, as a best guess, but note that little is known about the breeding cycle of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-VanMarle1">Van Marle and Voous 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Smythies1">Smythies 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Wells1">Wells 2007</xref>). In addition to using IMa to produce estimates of demographic parameters and divergence, we also used it to assess the fit of simpler demographic models nested within the full six-parameter divergence model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Hey2">Hey and Nielsen 2007</xref>). In these nested models (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 16), simplifications included assuming populations have the same effective size and symmetrical gene flow. We assessed the fit of reduced models to the data by comparing them against their null models using likelihood ratio tests (LRT). The significance of the differences was then determined with appropriate chi-squared distributions and Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons.We observed no consistent differences in plumage among the 92 specimens compared, but note that the specimens from Western Sundaland were old and potentially faded. PCA of combined male and female measurements indicated the majority of variance (57&percnt;) was distributed among 2 components: PC1 (40&percnt;) and PC2 (17&percnt;). Wing and tail lengths accounted for most of this variation. In males alone, 50&percnt; of the variance was distributed between PC1 (32&percnt;) and PC2 (19&percnt;). In females, 55&percnt; was in PC1 (38&percnt;) and PC2 (16&percnt;). None of the PCA scatter plots indicated a clear difference among populations; the male plot shows the most difference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f02">Figure 2</xref>). DFA of all individuals was highly influenced by bill depth and total culmen length, as was the DFA of males. In females, it was most influenced by bill width and wing length. In jacknife analysis of all individuals, DFA properly classified 57&percnt; of the Borneo population, 65&percnt; of the Palawan population, and 58&percnt; of the western Sundaland population. Overall classification accuracy was 60&percnt;. For males alone, DFA properly classified 60&percnt; to Borneo, 69&percnt; to Palawan population, and 67&percnt; to western Sundaland, with overall accuracy of 65&percnt;. For females, DFA accuracy was 73&percnt; for Borneo, 60&percnt; for Palawan, and 70&percnt; for western Sundaland, with overall accuracy of 55&percnt;. In general, none of the morphological characters we examined could discriminate effectively among the 3 populations (western Sundaland, Borneo, and Palawan) or the 2 subspecies (<italic>sericeus</italic> and <italic>hesperius</italic>).PCA of 6 size characters of male Rufous-tailed Tailorbird. Open squares: Borneo; closed triangles: western Sundaland; and stars: Palawan.The ND2 data consisted of 1,038 sites. Among Rufous-tailed Tailorbirds, 982 sites were invariable, 40 polymorphic, 8 unique, and 32 parsimony informative. The average uncorrected ND2 divergence between the Palawan and BWS populations was 1.7&percnt;. There were 20 haplotypes, haplotype diversity was 0.933, and nucleotide diversity was 0.00528. The haplotype network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f03">Figure 3</xref>) showed a series of Bornean locations radiating from western Sundaland, and Palawan was differentiated by 19 steps from all other populations. AMOVA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t03">Table 3</xref>) indicated a high degree of genetic structure occurring among populations, 63&percnt; (Borneo, Palawan, and Western Sundaland), and less within, 37&percnt;. Phylogenetic analysis of ND2 sequences using maximum likelihood bootstrapping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f03">Figure 3</xref>) and Bayesian methods (not shown) yielded trees with largely unresolved among-population relationships, but again with the Palawan population well differentiated from the others.(<bold>Left</bold>) GARLI bootstrap consensus maximum-likelihood tree of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird population relationships from ND2 sequences. Numbers on the tree indicate bootstrap support/posterior probability of adjacent branches (numbers omitted when bootstrap support less than 70&percnt; or posterior probability less than 95&percnt;). Outgroups are not included in this figure; they are Ashy Tailorbird and Grey-backed Tailorbird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>). (<bold>Right</bold>) Median-joining network of ND2 haplotypes. Cross hatches on interconnecting lines indicate number of substitutions (19 on the line to Palawan); circle size denotes number of individuals sampled.Results of AMOVA among western Sunda, Borneo, and Palawan populations.IMa analysis yielded good mixing among successive MCMC chains (minimum swap rate &gt;35&percnt;), and convergence in results was observed among different IMa runs. For the longest IMa analysis (100 million generations, results reported here), different parameters were adequately sampled, with the minimum effective sample size being 311 (for time of divergence). Based on the full six-parameter IMa model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>), the effective size of the BWS population (1.3 &times; 10<sup>6</sup>) is about 7 times larger that of the Palawan population. Palawan and BWS diverged from a small ancestral population &sim;1.2 Mya, although the confidence interval for divergence time is very large. Nested IMa models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t05">Table 5</xref>) that assume the BWS population is the same size as Palawan's or the ancestral population (model numbers 6, 9, 14, 15) are significantly worse than their respective null models, which do not assume so. Gene flow in either direction was low (range: 0&ndash;0.0003 migrants per 1,000 generations per gene copy), and the relative magnitude of directionality is not distinguishable because of the large confidence intervals. However, nested models assuming no post-divergence gene flow (model numbers 4, 8, 10, 13, 16) are significantly worse than their respective null models, suggesting that there has been a small amount of gene flow between BWS and Palawan after the initial population divergence. In addition, the 2 nested models with unidirectional gene flow (2, 3) also cannot be rejected. Thus, the evidence is equivocal regarding which direction has the higher gene flow rate.Peak estimates and their 95&percnt; confidence intervals for current and ancestral population sizes (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>), divergence time, and gene flow (with time moving forward, not in the coalescent) from Sundaland (S) to Palawan (P) and from Palawan to Sundaland based on the full IMa model.Marginal likelihood and peak estimates of the full and various reduced (nested) IMa models. Likelihood ratio test (LLR) statistic, models being compared, and significance of the statistic with and without Bonferroni correction (BC) are also shown. Population 1 &equals; Palawan; population 2 &equals; Borneo and western Sundaland. Because IMa analyzes data in the coalescent, <italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub> indicates gene flow going from population 2 into population 1 when time is moving forward.Our morphological comparisons support traditional taxonomic opinion that Rufous-tailed Tailorbirds of Palawan &ldquo;do not differ appreciably&rdquo; from those of Borneo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Peters1">Peters 1939</xref>:110, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Parkes1">Parkes 1960</xref>). However, our multigene coalescent analysis indicates that the populations on Borneo and Palawan have been largely independent of one another for &sim;1.2 Ma and have experienced only a small amount of gene flow since then. Even when the sea level dropped by its greatest extent&mdash;about 125 m during the last glacial maximum (&sim;20,000 years ago)&mdash;and the channel between Palawan and the rest of Sundaland was at its narrowest, gene flow was low. This rather decisive break contrasts strongly with the situation in western Sundaland, where the Sumatran, Malayan, and Bornean populations have extensively interbred, presumably during a series of glacial events, including the last glacial maximum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim1">Lim et al. 2011</xref>). We may also assume, with some confidence, that the Natuna Islands' population of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird interbred with Bornean and other western populations during the late Quaternary because of the Natunas' intervening position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-f01">Figure 1</xref>) and the likely paleo-distributions of appropriate coastal habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Voris1">Voris 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Cannon1">Cannon et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Slik1">Slik et al. 2011</xref>). The situation for the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird populations of Cagayan Sulu and the Sulu Archipelago east of Borneo, however, remains unclear, as we have not compared (the rare) specimens from these islands and are uncertain about the extent and timing of the islands' connections to Borneo or (in the case of Cagayan Sulu) to Palawan.The precise scenario of division between Bornean and Palawan populations of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird is unknown. As a lineage, the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird has been extant for &sim;5&ndash;10 Ma, and there is evidence that it may be the sister group of the main clade of Philippine tailorbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon3">Sheldon et al. 2012</xref>). Thus, it may have reached Palawan millions of years ago and colonized Borneo &sim;1.2 Ma, or it may have dispersed to Palawan from Borneo for the first time &sim;1.2 Ma, or it may have moved back and forth freely between the 2 islands until &sim;1.2 Ma.One million years of almost complete isolation of Palawan's Rufous-tailed Tailorbird population has not been adequate to cause it to diverge morphologically to any great extent from its Sundaic sisters. This is true even though the ecological situation for tailorbirds on Palawan is different than on Borneo and in western Sundaland. On Palawan, Rufous-tailed Tailorbird is the only species of <italic>Orthotomus</italic>, but in the rest of Sundaland at least 2 other <italic>Orthotomus</italic> species occur in sympatry with the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird. Assuming competition among tailorbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Mitra1">Mitra and Sheldon 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Soh1">Soh 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Mahood1">Mahood et al. 2013</xref>), the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird of Palawan has enjoyed ecological release and would be expected to differ from other populations, especially in size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Clegg1">Clegg and Owens 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Scott1">Scott et al. 2003</xref>). The Palawan population may have diverged in behavior and song, but we have not investigated these characters.The genetic distance between the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird populations of Borneo and Palawan&mdash;1.7&percnt; in this study and 1.9&percnt; in previous studies&mdash;falls somewhat in the middle of the 2 divergence classes evident between Palawan and Bornean sister taxa in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> (i.e. substantial divergence versus little divergence). The 2 tailorbird populations are more distinct genetically than those of kingfishers (<italic>Ceyx erithaca</italic> and <italic>Alcedo meninting</italic>) and Black-headed Bulbul (<italic>Pycnonotus atriceps</italic>), but much less than the other sister pairs. This difference may be attributed to the tailorbird's reduced dispersal capabilities relative to the kingfishers and bulbul (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Burney1">Burney and Brumfield 2009</xref>). Birds in both these groups range widely in coastal areas in search of food and have wings with relatively high aspect ratios compared to the short, rounded wings of tailorbirds. On the other hand, Rufous-tailed Tailorbird would be expected to disperse across salt water more readily than &ldquo;typical&rdquo; Sunda forest species because of its regular occurrence in mangroves and other coastal habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-VanMarle1">Van Marle and Voous 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Sheldon2">Sheldon et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Wells1">Wells 2007</xref>), which likely predominated between Greater Borneo and Palawan during glacial events. Even so, it is not easy to explain why the weak-flying tailorbird should have a smaller pairwise population divergence value than some of the highly vagile, nectarivorous/frugivorous, coastal habitat generalist species in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref>. We would expect, for example, that the mangrove-dwelling whistlers and wide-ranging spiderhunters and secondary forest bulbuls (e.g., <italic>Pycnonotus simplex</italic>/<italic>cinereifrons</italic>) would be able to disperse more readily than tailorbirds between Borneo and Palawan during times of low sea level. Bird-community &ldquo;relaxation&rdquo; factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Diamond1">Diamond 1972</xref>), such as competition and extinction, clearly have played a role in determining the composition of the Palawan avifauna.A relatively large proportion of Philippine forest birds are classified as members of widespread Southeast Asian species when they are better treated as endemic Philippine species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Peterson1">Peterson 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lohman1">Lohman et al. 2010</xref>). This underestimation of Philippine species endemicity is largely a historical artifact, a hangover from taxonomic and biogeographic thinking of the mid-twentieth century. Although ornithologists have long recognized the distinctiveness of many Philippine forest-bird populations, they have purposely treated them as subspecies, not full species. This occurred because, in the years following World War II, when taxonomic revision of birds was booming, the study of Southeast Asian bird relationships was dominated by ornithologists at American museums, including Herbert G. Deignan, Jean Delacour, Ernst Mayr, Kenneth C. Parkes, Austin L. Rand, and S. Dillon Ripley, and all of these men were heavily influenced by the polytypic species approach of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Mayr1">Mayr (1942</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Mayr2">1963</xref>). It was quite natural for them to treat populations of similar-looking congeners that replace one another geographically as subspecies of widespread species. This tendency was exacerbated by the prevailing view of Philippine biogeography at the time, i.e. that Philippine populations were the result of late Pleistocene or Holocene expansions of widespread continental species. The presumed young age of Philippine taxa was all the more reason to join them as polytypic members of widespread species. Nowadays, however, we know that many Philippine forest populations are older than previously believed, and we have different and more precise standards of species description as a result of the promulgation of alternative species concepts that emphasize smaller groupings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-McKitrick1">McKitrick and Zink 1988</xref>), the development of more objective methods of morphological assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Rheindt1">Rheindt and Eaton 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Tobias1">Tobias et al. 2010</xref>), and the widespread use of molecular tools that allow measurement of divergence among taxa.As a result of these advances, we are now in a position to treat the taxonomy of Philippine populations more objectively. This ability is enhanced by the recent suggestion of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Gill1">Gill (2014)</xref> that physically separated, moderately divergent populations be treated as distinct species until compelling evidence of free interbreeding is produced, upon which the populations may be merged. In the Rufous-tailed Tailorbird, we have an almost perfect illustration of such &ldquo;compelling evidence,&rdquo; not only for interbreeding, but lack of interbreeding. Our genetic comparisons allow us to identify with confidence those populations that are interbreeding and those that are not. In this case, the Bornean and western Sunda populations are genetically intermixed and barely (if at all) differentiated morphologically. We can essentially prove these populations interbred during the last glacial maximum and were probably in contact until 10,000 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Lim1">Lim et al. 2011</xref>). Thus, they can be considered without question members of the same species. The Palawan population, however, is genetically distinct. Palawan has not been regularly attached to the rest of Sundaland by glacio-eustatic land or habitat bridges, and its population of tailorbirds has rarely interbred with the Bornean population. Thus, the Palawan population appears to be on its own evolutionary trajectory. However, it has not yet diverged morphologically, and we know of no non-DNA characteristics that distinguish it from the Bornean population, so there is no reason to call it a different species at this point. If diagnosable differences in song or behavior are discovered for the Palawan population, it should then be named a different species.Our personal preference is not to change the classification of Rufous-tailed Tailorbird populations, i.e. maintain the subspecies as they are. Although the western Sunda and Borneo populations do not appear to us to differ from one another morphologically, fresh specimens from Sumatra and the Malay Peninsula might exhibit plumage differences from Bornean birds. Naming the Palawan population as a distinct taxon, e.g., in recognition of its genetic distinctiveness or in the case of new character discovery, will have to wait until genetic comparisons are made between it and the Cagayan Sulu population, because the Palawan population is subsumed under the name given the Cagayan Sulu population (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Orthotomus sericeus</named-content> nuntius</italic>) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-629-Bangs1">Bangs (1922)</xref>.For permission to undertake research in Malaysia we thank the Prime Minister's Department; the Chief Ministers' Departments of Sabah and Sarawak; Sabah Parks, Wildlife, and Forestry Departments; and Sarawak Forestry Department, Forestry Corporation, and Biodiversity Institute. We also thank the staff of Sabah Parks (Dr. Jamili Nais, Dr. Maklarin Lakim, Alim Biun, Paul Yambun, and Benedict Butit), Sabah Museum (Jaffit Majuakim, Albert Lo, Freddie Julus, Patrick Francis, Mathius Angkaus), Sabah Wildlife Department (Augustine Tuuga, Peter Malim, Anna Wong), and UNIMAS (Isa Said, Mohamad Fizl Sidq Ramji, Mohamad Jalani Mortada, and numerous graduate students). For permission to work in Palawan, we thank the Philippine Department of Environment and Natural Resources and the Palawan Council for Sustainable Development. For use of morphological and genetic specimens, we thank the Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University, American Museum of Natural History, Delaware Museum of Natural History, Field Museum, Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science, National Museum of Natural History (USA), Natural History Museum (UK), University of Kansas Museum of Natural History, and Western Foundation of Vertebrate Zoology. This work was supported financially by NSF DEB-0228688 and DEB-1241059 to F.H.S., FRGS/06(03)/647/2007(12) to M.A.R., and by the Coypu Foundation, Louisiana State University, and Universiti Malaysia Sarawak.