 Fifty-Fifth Supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Genetic structure, conservation genetics and evidence of speciation by range expansion in Shy and White-capped albatrosses  Phylogeography of Shy and White-capped albatrosses inferred from mitochondrial DNA sequences: Implications for population history and taxonomy  Speciation on oceanic islands: Rapid adaptive divergence vs. cryptic speciation on a Guadalupe Island songbird (Aves:  Junco )  Multilocus analysis of a taxonomically densely sampled dataset reveal &lsqb; sic &rsqb; extensive non-monophyly in the avian family Locustellidae  Forty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Estrildinae finches (Aves, Passeriformes) from Africa, South Asia and Australia: A molecular phylogeographic study  Forty-ninth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union Check-list of North American Birds  Classification of a clade of New World doves (Columbidae: Zenaidini)  First record of a Shy Albatross in Alaska  Family Icteridae  A Brown Hawk-Owl ( Ninox scutulata ) from Kiska Island, Aleutian Islands, Alaska  The type locality of Craveri's Murrelet  Synthliboramphus craveri   Phylogenetic conservatism and antiquity of a tropical specialization: Army-ant-following in the typical antbirds (Thamnophilidae)  Phylogenetics and diversification of tanagers (Passeriformes: Thraupidae), the largest radiation of Neotropical songbirds  Biogeography and evolutionary history of the Neotropical genus  Saltator  (Aves: Thraupini)  Fiftieth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Fifty-first supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Fifty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Fifty-fourth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union  Check-list of North American Birds   Phylogeny and classification of  Automolus  foliage-gleaners and allies (Furnariidae)  Lineage diversification and morphological evolution in a large-scale continental radiation: The Neotropical ovenbirds and woodcreepers (Aves: Furnariidae)  Report of the California Bird Records Committee: 2001 records  Catalogue of birds of the Americas  Identification of immature Salvin's, Chatham and Buller's albatrosses  Oregon's first White-capped Albatross (  Diomedea cauta  cauta )  Checklist of the Birds of the Oriental Region  Build-up of the Himalayan avifauna through immigration: A biogeographical analysis of the  Phylloscopus  and  Seicercus  warblers  The Central American land bridge as an engine of diversification in New World doves  Species limits in the Brown Boobook  Ninox scutulata  complex  Phylogenetic relationships of the extinct Carolina Parakeet ( Conuropsis carolinensis ) inferred from DNA sequence data  A Siberian Chiffchaff (  Phylloscopus collybita  tristis ) at Gambell, Alaska  Molecular phylogenetics and diversification of the genus  Sporophila  (Aves: Passeriformes)  Mitochondrial and next-generation sequence data used to infer phylogenetic relationships and species limits in the Clapper/King rail complex  Molecular phylogenetics of the Neotropical seedeaters and seed-finches ( Sporophila ,  Oryzoborus ,  Dolospingus )  Report of the California Bird Records Committee: 2000 records  Speciation in the avian genus  Junco   Song divergence in hummingbird and junco populations on Guadalupe Island  Evolutionary relationships among extant albatrosses (Procellariiformes: Diomedeidae) established from complete cytochrome- b  gene sequences  Lista Oficial de las Aves de Costa Rica &ndash; Actualizaci&oacute;n  A revision of the subspecies of  Sporophila  (&ldquo; Oryzoborus &rdquo;)  angolensis  (Aves: Emberizidae)  The nature of the variability in the Variable Seedeater in Panama ( Sporophila americana : Emberizinae)  Non-monophyletic taxa and cryptic species&mdash;Evidence from a molecular phylogeny of leaf-warblers ( Phylloscopus , Aves)  Family Estrildidae  A comprehensive species-level molecular phylogeny of the New World blackbirds (Icteridae)  Patterns and processes of diversification in a widespread and ecologically diverse avian group, the buteonine hawks (Aves, Accipitridae)  DNA-sequence data require revision of the parrot genus  Aratinga  (Aves: Psittacidae)  A classification of the bird species of South America  Molecular systematics and patterns of diversification in  Pyrrhura  (Psittacidae), with special reference to the  picta-leucotis  complex  Molecular systematics in  Aratinga  parakeets: Species limits and historical biogeography in the  solstitialis  group, and the systematic position of  Nandayus nenday   The birds of North and Middle America  The birds of North and Middle America  Salvin's Albatross ( Thalassarche salvini ) on Midway Atoll  Old divergences in a boreal bird supports &lsqb; sic &rsqb; long-term survival through the Ice Ages  Notes on the classification of the pigeons  A record of the Tasmanian White-capped Albatross,   Diomedea cauta  cauta , in American North Pacific waters  Clade-limited colonization in brood parasitic finches (  Vidua   spp.)  When black plus white equals gray: The nature of variation in the variable seedeater complex (Emberizinae:  Sporophila )  The Birds of the Palearctic Fauna: Order Passeriformes  Family Sylviidae  Andean uplift promotes lowland speciation through vicariance and dispersal in  Dendrocincla  woodcreepers  First North American record of Brown Hawk-Owl ( Ninox scutulata ) on St. Paul Island, Alaska  This is the 14th supplement since publication of the 7th edition of the  Check-list of North American Birds  ( American Ornithologists' Union &lsqb;AOU&rsqb; 1998 ). It summarizes decisions made between May 15, 2013, and May 15, 2014, by the AOU's Committee on Classification and Nomenclature&mdash;North and Middle America. The Committee has continued to operate in the manner outlined in the 42nd Supplement ( AOU 2000 ).  Changes in this supplement include the following: (1) three species ( Ciconia maguari ,   Phylloscopus collybita  , and   Sporophila lineola  ) are added to the main list on the basis of new distributional information; (2) four species ( Thalassarche salvini ,  Rallus tenuirostris ,  Phylloscopus examinandus , and  Junco insularis ) are added to the main list as a result of splits from species already on the list; (3) two species ( Rallus obsoletus  and  R. crepitans ) are added to the main list and one species (  Rallus longirostris  ) is lost because of the split of that species; (4) three species names are changed (to  Ninox japonica ,  Gymnopithys bicolor , and  Sporophila corvina ) because of splits from extralimital species; (5) the distributional statement of one species ( Pyrrhura picta ) is changed because of splits of extralimital species; (6) the distributional statement and English name of one species  ( Thalassarche cauta  ) and the distributional statement of another (  Phylloscopus borealis  ) are changed as a result of taxonomic changes; (7) seven genera ( Leptotrygon ,  Zentrygon ,  Eupsittula ,  Psittacara ,  Cassiculus ,  Spermestes , and  Euodice ) are added as a result of splits from other genera, resulting in changes to 20 scientific names ( L. veraguensis ,  Z. carrikeri ,  Z. costaricensis ,  Z. lawrencii ,  Z. albifacies ,  Z. chiriquensis ,  Z. goldmani ,  Eupsittula nana ,  E. canicularis ,  E. pertinax ,  P. holochlorus ,  P. strenuus ,  P. finschi ,  P. euops ,  P. chloropterus ,  P. mitratus ,  Cassiculus melanicterus ,  S. cucullata ,  Euodice malabarica , and  E. cantans ); (8) one genus ( Clibanornis ) is added as a result of a transfer of a species ( C. rubiginosus ) to a formerly extralimital genus; (9) four genera ( Nandayus ,  Hyloctistes ,  Oryzoborus , and  Padda ) are lost by merger (into  Aratinga ,  Automolus ,  Sporophila , and  Lonchura , respectively) and the scientific names of seven species ( Aratinga nenday ,  Automolus subulatus ,  S. nuttingi ,  S. funerea ,  S. crassirostris ,  S. angolensis , and  L. oryzivora ) are thereby changed; (10) the type locality for one species ( Synthliboramphus craveri ) is corrected; (11) the English names of 10 species ( Buteogallus anthracinus ,  B. gundlachii ,  B. urubitinga ,  Phylloscopus proregulus ,  Chlorospingus flavopectus ,  C. tacarcunae ,   C. inornatus  ,  C. pileatus ,  C. flavigularis , and  C. canigularis ) are changed to reflect new information on their phylogenetic relationships; (12) the English name of one species ( Lonchura punctulata ) is changed to conform with global usage; and (13) one species ( Thalassarche eremita ) is added to the Appendix. In addition, the English names of three species are transferred to other scientific names in the aftermath of taxonomic changes: thus, Clapper Rail is now the English name for  Rallus crepitans  rather than   R. longirostris  , Bicolored Antbird is now the English name for  Gymnopithys bicolor  rather than  G. leucaspis , and Variable Seedeater is now the English name for  Sporophila corvina  rather than   S. americana  .  One family name (Locustellidae) is changed in accordance with the rules of priority for group names. New linear sequences are adopted for species in the genera  Dendrocincla ,  Saltator , and  Sporophila , and for species currently and formerly (see below) in the genera  Geotrygon ,  Aratinga ,  Hyloctistes ,  Automolus ,  Thripadectes ,  Lonchura , and  Padda , all due to new phylogenetic data.  Literature that provides the basis for the Committee's decisions is cited at the end of this supplement, and citations not already in the Literature Cited of the 7th edition (with supplements) become additions to it. A list of the bird species known from the AOU  Check-list  area can be found at  http://checklist.aou.org/taxa .  The following changes to the 7th edition (page numbers refer thereto) and its supplements result from the Committee's actions:  pp. xvii&ndash;liv. Change the number in the title of the list of species to 2,098. Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:     Thalassarche cauta    White-capped Albatross. (A)    Thalassarche salvini   Salvin's Albatross. (A)    Ciconia maguari   Maguari Stork. (A)    Buteogallus anthracinus   Common Black Hawk.    Buteogallus gundlachii   Cuban Black Hawk.    Buteogallus urubitinga   Great Black Hawk.    Rallus obsoletus   Ridgway's Rail.    Rallus tenuirostris   Aztec Rail.    Rallus crepitans   Clapper Rail.    Leptotrygon veraguensis   Olive-backed Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon carrikeri   Tuxtla Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon costaricensis   Buff-fronted Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon lawrencii   Purplish-backed Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon albifacies   White-faced Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon chiriquensis   Chiriqui Quail-Dove.    Zentrygon goldmani   Russet-crowned Quail-Dove.    Ninox japonica   Northern Boobook. (A)    Eupsittula nana   Olive-throated Parakeet.    Eupsittula canicularis   Orange-fronted Parakeet.    Eupsittula pertinax   Brown-throated Parakeet.    Aratinga nenday   Nanday Parakeet. (I)    Psittacara holochlorus   Green Parakeet.    Psittacara strenuus   Pacific Parakeet.    Psittacara finschi   Crimson-fronted Parakeet.    Psittacara euops   Cuban Parakeet.    Psittacara chloropterus   Hispaniolan Parakeet.    Psittacara mitratus   Mitred Parakeet. (I)    Gymnopithys bicolor   Bicolored Antbird.    Clibanornis rubiginosus   Ruddy Foliage-gleaner.    Automolus subulatus   Striped Woodhaunter.     Phylloscopus collybita    Common Chiffchaff. (A)    Phylloscopus proregulus   Pallas's Leaf Warbler. (A)    Phylloscopus examinandus   Kamchatka Leaf Warbler. (A)   LOCUSTELLIDAE     &ast;Chlorospingus flavopectus   Common Chlorospingus.    &ast;Chlorospingus tacarcunae   Tacarcuna Chlorospingus.    &ast;Chlorospingus inornatus   Pirre Chlorospingus.    &ast;Chlorospingus pileatus   Sooty-capped Chlorospingus.    &ast;Chlorospingus flavigularis   Yellow-throated Chlorospingus.    &ast;Chlorospingus canigularis   Ashy-throated Chlorospingus.    Cassiculus melanicterus   Yellow-winged Cacique.    &ast;Sporophila funerea   Thick-billed Seed-Finch.    &ast;Sporophila nuttingi   Nicaraguan Seed-Finch.    &ast;Sporophila crassirostris   Large-billed Seed-Finch.    &ast;Sporophila corvina   Variable Seedeater.    &ast; Sporophila lineola    Lined Seedeater. (A)    Junco insularis   Guadalupe Junco.    Spermestes cucullata   Bronze Mannikin. (I)    Euodice malabarica   Indian Silverbill. (I)    Euodice cantans   African Silverbill. (I)    Lonchura oryzivora   Java Sparrow. (I)    Lonchura punctulata   Scaly-breasted Munia. (I)  Delete the following names:     Thalassarche cauta    Shy Albatross. (A)    Buteogallus anthracinus   Common Black-Hawk.    Buteogallus gundlachii   Cuban Black-Hawk.    Buteogallus urubitinga   Great Black-Hawk.     Rallus longirostris    Clapper Rail.    Geotrygon veraguensis   Olive-backed Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon albifacies   White-faced Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon chiriquensis   Chiriqui Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon carrikeri   Tuxtla Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon lawrencii   Purplish-backed Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon costaricensis   Buff-fronted Quail-Dove.    Geotrygon goldmani   Russet-crowned Quail-Dove.    Ninox scutulata   Brown Hawk-Owl. (A)    Aratinga holochlora   Green Parakeet.    Aratinga strenua   Pacific Parakeet.    Aratinga finschi   Crimson-fronted Parakeet.    Aratinga mitrata   Mitred Parakeet. (I)    Aratinga chloroptera   Hispaniolan Parakeet.    Aratinga euops   Cuban Parakeet.    Aratinga nana   Olive-throated Parakeet.    Aratinga canicularis   Orange-fronted Parakeet.    Aratinga pertinax   Brown-throated Parakeet.    Nandayus nenday   Nanday Parakeet. (I)    Gymnopithys leucaspis   Bicolored Antbird.    Hyloctistes subulatus   Striped Woodhaunter.    Automolus rubiginosus   Ruddy Foliage-gleaner.    Phylloscopus proregulus   Pallas's Leaf-Warbler. (A)   MEGALURIDAE     Chlorospingus flavopectus   Common Bush-Tanager.    Chlorospingus tacarcunae   Tacarcuna Bush-Tanager.    Chlorospingus inornatus   Pirre Bush-Tanager.    Chlorospingus pileatus   Sooty-capped Bush-Tanager.    Chlorospingus flavigularis   Yellow-throated Bush-Tanager.    Chlorospingus canigularis   Ashy-throated Bush-Tanager.    Cacicus melanicterus   Yellow-winged Cacique.    Oryzoborus nuttingi   Nicaraguan Seed-Finch.    Oryzoborus funereus   Thick-billed Seed-Finch.    Oryzoborus crassirostris   Large-billed Seed-Finch.    Sporophila americana   Variable Seedeater.    Lonchura malabarica   Indian Silverbill. (I)    Lonchura cantans   African Silverbill. (I)    Lonchura cucullata   Bronze Mannikin. (I)    Lonchura punctulata   Nutmeg Mannikin. (I)    Padda oryzivora   Java Sparrow. (I)  Change the sequence of species from   Zenaida   to   Starnoenas   to:  &dagger;   Ectopistes migratorius       Columbina inca      Columbina passerina      Columbina minuta      Columbina talpacoti      Claravis pretiosa      Claravis mondetoura      Starnoenas cyanocephala      Geotrygon versicolor       Geotrygon montana       Geotrygon violacea      Geotrygon caniceps      Geotrygon leucometopia      Geotrygon chrysia      Geotrygon mystacea      Leptotrygon veraguensis      Leptotila verreauxi      Leptotila jamaicensis      Leptotila cassini      Leptotila plumbeiceps      Leptotila wellsi      Zentrygon carrikeri      Zentrygon costaricensis      Zentrygon lawrencii      Zentrygon albifacies      Zentrygon chiriquensis      Zentrygon goldmani       Zenaida asiatica        Zenaida aurita        Zenaida auriculata        Zenaida macroura       Zenaida graysoni    Change the sequence of species from   Aratinga   to   Ara   to:    Eupsittula nana      Eupsittula canicularis      Eupsittula pertinax      Aratinga nenday      Ara severus      Ara militaris      Ara ambiguus      Ara chloropterus       Ara macao       Ara tricolor      Ara ararauna      Psittacara holochlorus      Psittacara strenuus      Psittacara finschi      Psittacara euops      Psittacara chloropterus      Psittacara mitratus    Change the sequence of species in   Dendrocincla   to:    Dendrocincla homochroa      Dendrocincla anabatina      Dendrocincla fuliginosa    Change the sequence of species formerly in   Hyloctistes  ,   Automolus  , and   Thripadectes   to:    Clibanornis rubiginosus      Thripadectes rufobrunneus      Automolus ochrolaemus      Automolus subulatus    Change the sequence of species in   Saltator   to:    Saltator atriceps      Saltator maximus      Saltator grossus      Saltator albicollis      Saltator coerulescens      Saltator striatipectus    Change the sequence of species in   Sporophila   to:    Sporophila minuta      Sporophila funerea      Sporophila nuttingi      Sporophila crassirostris      Sporophila corvina      Sporophila torqueola      Sporophila nigricollis       Sporophila lineola       Sporophila schistacea    Change the sequence of species formerly in   Lonchura   and   Padda   to:    Spermestes cucullata      Euodice malabarica      Euodice cantans      Lonchura oryzivora      Lonchura punctulata      Lonchura malacca      Lonchura atricapilla    p. 10.  Thalassarche salvini  and  T. eremita  are treated as species separate from   T. cauta  , following  Remsen et al. (2014) . In the species account for   T. cauta  , change the English name to White-capped Albatross, and change the distributional statement and Notes to:   Breeds  on islands off southern Australia and New Zealand, and  ranges  widely in the southern Pacific and Indian oceans, less commonly in the South Atlantic.  Accidental off the coast of Washington (lat. 47&deg;55&prime;N. long. 125&deg;37&prime;W. ca. 39 miles west of the mouth of Quillayute River, 1 September 1951; specimen USNM;  Slipp 1952 ); also Oregon (October 1996; photos;  Hunter and Bailey 1997 ; and October 2001; photos), California (August-September 1999; photos), and Washington (January 2000; photos), these four records possibly of the same individual ( Howell 2012 ).  Formerly known as Shy Albatross and considered conspecific with  T. salvini  and  T. eremita , but treated as separate species on the basis of differences in plumage and genetic data ( Nunn et al. 1996 ,  Abbott and Double 2003a ,  2003b ) and reports of isolated pairs of one form nesting within the range of another ( Tickell 2000 ).  After the species account for   T. cauta  , insert the following new account:   Thalassogeron salvini  Rothschild, 1893, Bull. Brit. Ornith. Club 1:58. (New Zealand.)  Pelagic Waters; breeds on islands.   Breeds  on islands off New Zealand and on Crozet Islands, Indian Ocean, and  ranges  widely in the southern Pacific and Indian oceans, less commonly in the South Atlantic.  Accidental in Hawaii (Midway Atoll, 8 April 2003; photos;  Robertson et al. 2005 ) and off the coast of Alaska (18 km northwest of Kasatochi Island, Aleutians, 4 August 2003; photos;  Benter et al. 2005 ).  See comments under   T. cauta  .  In the Appendix, following the species account for   Thalassarche chrysostoma   (p. 685), insert the following new account:    Thalassarche cauta  eremita  Murphy, 1930, Amer. Mus. Novit. 419:4. (Pyramid Rock off Pitt Island, Chatham Islands.)  p. 50. Preceding the heading Tribe LEPTOPTILINI: Jabirus and Allies, add the following headings and species account:  Tribe CICONIINI: Typical Storks  Genus   CICONIA   Brisson   Ciconia  Brisson, 1760, Ornith. 1, p. 48; 5, p. 361. Type, by tautonymy,  Ciconia &equals; Ardea ciconia  Linnaeus.    Ciconia maguari   (Gmelin). Maguari Stork   Ardea Maguari  Gmelin, 1789, Syst. Nat. 1: 623; based on &ldquo;Maguari&rdquo; of Marcgrave, 1648, Hist. Rerum Nat. Brasiliae, p. 204. (northeastern Brazil.)  Freshwater Marshes, Southern Temperate Grasslands, Low Seasonally Wet Grasslands, Pastures/Agricultural Lands (0&ndash;900 m; Tropical Zone).  Northeastern Colombia and Venezuela east through Guianas to Brazil in Roraima, Amap&aacute;, and extreme northern Par&aacute;. Disjunctly from central and southeastern Brazil, northern and eastern Bolivia south to Paraguay, Uruguay, and central Argentina. Formerly regular nonbreeder in central Chile.  Casual through eastern Brazil and in southeastern Peru.  Accidental in Costa Rica (near Gulf of Nicoya, Chomes, Puntarenas province, 16 September 2013; photos;  Obando-Calder&oacute;n et al. 2013 ).  pp. 97&ndash;98. The hyphen is removed from the English names of Common Black Hawk  Buteogallus anthracinus , Cuban Black Hawk  B. gundlachii , and Great Black Hawk  B. urubitinga  because  B. anthracinus  and  B. urubitinga  are not sister taxa (Raposo do Amaral et al. 2009;  B. gundlachii  was not included in the study).  p. 131.  Rallus obsoletus  and  R. crepitans  are treated as species separate from the now extralimital   R. longirostris  . Remove the account for   R. longirostris   and insert the following new species accounts in this sequence:    Rallus elegans   var.  obsoletus  Ridgway, 1874, Am. Nat. 8:111. (San Francisco, California.)  Salt and brackish marshes, locally (mostly in the Imperial and lower Colorado River valleys) in freshwater marshes (Temperate and Subtropical zones).  &lsqb;same as for  obsoletus  group.&rsqb;  See comments under  R. crepitans .   Rallus crepitans  Gmelin, 1789, Syst. Nat. 1, pt. 2, p. 713. (&ldquo;in Noveboraco,&rdquo; restricted type locality, Long Island, New York.)  Salt and brackish marshes and mangrove swamps; during migration may be found in freshwater marshes (Tropical and Subtropical zones).  &lsqb;same as  longirostris  group except delete South American parts of distribution.&rsqb; Northernmost populations tend to be partially migratory.  Formerly ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ) considered conspecific with  R. obsoletus  and South American   R. longirostris   Boddaert, 1783 &lsqb;Mangrove Rail&rsqb; and sometimes with   R. elegans   and   R. tenuirostris   (e.g.,  Ripley 1977 ). The five members of this complex are treated as separate species on the basis of strong, although incomplete, reproductive isolation between parapatric populations of  R. crepitans  and   R. elegans   in their extensive contact zone, and morphological and genetic differences among other members of the complex commensurate with those between  R. crepitans  and   R. elegans   ( Maley and Brumfield 2013 ).  p. 132.  Rallus tenuirostris  is treated as a species separate from   R. elegans  . After the account for  R. obsoletus , insert the following new species account:    Rallus elegans   var.  tenuirostris  &ldquo;Lawrence&rdquo; Ridgway, 1874, Am. Nat. 8:111. (City of Mexico.)  Freshwater marshes (1,550&ndash;2,800 m; Subtropical and Temperate zones).  &lsqb;same as  tenuirostris  group&rsqb;.  Formerly considered conspecific with   R. elegans  , but they are not sister taxa ( Maley and Brumfield 2013 ). See comments under  R. crepitans . Also known as Mexican Rail.  Move the species account for   R. elegans   to follow the account for   R. tenuirostris  . Delete information on the  tenuirostris  group from the habitat and distributional statements in the account for   R. elegans  , and change the Notes to:  See comments under  R. crepitans  and   R. tenuirostris  .  p. 213. Based on  Bowen (2013) , change the type locality for  Synthliboramphus craveri  to the following: Golfo della California &lsqb;Mexico&rsqb; &equals; (probably) Isla Partida Norte, Gulf of California.  pp. 229&ndash;231. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences ( Johnson and Weckstein 2011 ,  Banks et al. 2013 ) have shown that the genus  Geotrygon  is polyphyletic and that the linear sequence of species currently placed in this genus does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. The type species  G. versicolor  forms a clade with six other species in our area, but  G. veraguensis  is sister to the genus  Leptotila , and six other species of  Geotrygon  are sister to the genus  Zenaida . These findings result in the following changes:  Move the heading Genus   STARNOENAS   Bonaparte and the species account for  Starnoenas cyanocephala  to a position following the species account for  Claravis mondetoura . Insert the following at the end of the species account for  Starnoenas cyanocephala :  The phylogenetic relationships of this species within the Columbidae are uncertain ( Shufeldt 1891 ,  Dickinson and Remsen 2013 ), but we leave it in its traditional placement near  Geotrygon  pending further data.  Add the following under the citation for genus  Geotrygon :  See comments under  Leptotrygon  and  Zentrygon .  Revise the composition of  Geotrygon  and rearrange the linear sequence of species remaining in this genus to:   Geotrygon versicolor     Geotrygon montana     Geotrygon violacea    Geotrygon caniceps    Geotrygon leucometopia    Geotrygon chrysia    Geotrygon mystacea   Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Geotrygon mystacea :   Leptotrygon   Banks, Weckstein, Remsen, and Johnson, 2013 , Zootaxa 3669:185. Type, by original designation,  Geotrygon veraguensis  Lawrence.  Formerly ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ) considered part of  Geotrygon , but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data ( Johnson and Weckstein 2011 ,  Banks et al. 2013 ), which indicate that  Leptotrygon  is sister to  Leptotila .  Change   Geotrygon veraguensis   Lawrence to   Leptotrygon veraguensis   (Lawrence) and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for  Leptotrygon . Add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Geotrygon . See comments under  Leptotrygon .  Move the genus heading for  Leptotila  to follow the species account for  Leptotrygon veraguensis , and place the species accounts for  L. verreauxi ,   L. jamaicensis  ,  L. cassini ,  L. plumbeiceps , and  L. wellsi  in this sequence under the heading for  Leptotila .  Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Leptotila wellsi :   Zentrygon   Banks, Weckstein, Remsen, and Johnson, 2013 , Zootaxa 3669:185. Type, by original designation,  Geotrygon costaricensis  Lawrence.  Formerly considered part of  Geotrygon  ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ), but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data ( Johnson and Weckstein 2011 ,  Banks et al. 2013 ), which indicate that  Zentrygon  is sister to  Zenaida .  Change the generic names of  Geotrygon carrikeri ,  G. costaricensis ,  G. lawrencii ,  G. albifacies ,  G. chiriquensis , and  G. goldmani  to  Zentrygon , add parentheses around the authority names for each species, make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, delete the Notes for  Z. goldmani , replace the Notes for  Z. lawrencii  with &ldquo;Closely related to  Z. costaricensis ; the two are reportedly sympatric in Costa Rica.&rdquo; and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for  Zentrygon . In the species accounts for all species, add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Geotrygon . See comments under  Zentrygon .  Move the genus heading for  Zenaida  to follow the species account for  Zentrygon goldmani , and place the species accounts for   Zenaida asiatica  ,   Z. aurita  ,   Z. auriculata  ,   Z. macroura  , and  Z. graysoni  in this sequence under the heading for  Zenaida .  p. 233. Three extralimital South American populations of  Pyrrhura picta  are separated as the species  P. amazonum ,  P. roseifrons , and  P. lucianii , following  Ribas et al. (2006)  and  Remsen et al. (2014) . Replace the distributional statement and Notes in the species account for   P. picta   with the following:   Resident  in western Panama (Azuero Peninsula), patchily in northern Colombia and northern Venezuela, and from southeastern Venezuela and the Guianas to Brazil north of the Amazon River, east of the Rio Negro.  DNA sequence data ( Ribas et al. 2006 ) indicate that the subspecies  eisenmanni  in Panama is sister to a clade containing Guianan Shield  picta  and north-central Venezuelan  emma , but not  P. leucotis  (Kuhl, 1820) &lsqb;Maroon-faced Parakeet&rsqb;; however, intervening northern South American populations were not sampled. These intervening populations are morphologically intermediate between nominate  picta  of northeastern Amazonia and  eisenmanni . Formerly included  P. amazonum  Hellmayr, 1906 &lsqb;Santarem Parakeet&rsqb;,  P. roseifrons  (Gray, 1859) &lsqb;Rose-fronted Parakeet&rsqb;, and  P. lucianii  (Deville, 1851) &lsqb;Bonaparte's Parakeet&rsqb; of southern and western Amazonia. These three species do not form a monophyletic group with  Pyrrhura picta  ( Ribas et al. 2006 ) and are treated as separate species, following  Remsen et al. (2014) .  pp. 234&ndash;236. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (summarized in  Remsen et al. 2013 ) have shown that the genus  Aratinga  is highly polyphyletic and that the linear sequence of species currently placed in this genus does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. The type species  A. solstitialis  forms a clade with five other species, of which the  AOU Check-list  includes one species, currently placed in the genus  Nandayus  (see below). Other species currently placed in  Aratinga  constitute three clades, two of which include species from our area. These findings result in the following changes:  Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Conuropsis carolinensis :   Eupsittula  Bonaparte, 1853, Compt. Rend. Ac. Sci. Paris 37: 807. Type, by monotypy,  Psittacus petzii  Leiblein &equals;  P. canicularis  Linnaeus.  Formerly (e.g.,  AOU 1983 ,  1998 ) included in  Aratinga  following  Peters (1937) , but now treated as separate (as in  Ridgway 1916 ) on the basis of genetic data (e.g.,  Kirchman et al. 2012 ; summarized in  Remsen et al. 2013 ), which indicate that  Eupsittula  is not closely related to true  Aratinga  and is likely the sister genus to  Rhynchopsitta .  Change the generic names of  Aratinga nana ,  A. canicularis , and  A. pertinax  to  Eupsittula , make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for  Eupsittula . Delete the last sentence in the Notes for  E. pertinax . In the species accounts for all species, add the following to the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Aratinga . See comments under  Eupsittula .  Insert the following at the end of the Notes for Genus   ARATINGA   Spix: See comments under  Eupsittula  and  Psittacara .  Change   Nandayus nenday   (Vieillot) (added to the  Check-list  in  Chesser et al. 2013 ) to   Aratinga nenday   (Vieillot), delete the genus heading for  Nandayus , move the citation for  Nandayus  into the synonymy of  Aratinga , insert the species account for  Aratinga nenday  to follow the heading and Notes for  Aratinga , and insert the following at the beginning of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Nandayus , but genetic data (e.g.,  Ribas and Miyaki 2004 ,  Kirchman et al. 2012 ; summarized in  Remsen et al. 2013 ) indicate that  Nandayus  is embedded within  Aratinga .  Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Ara ararauna :   Psittacara  Vigors, 1825, Zool. Journ. 2: 388. Type, by original designation,  Psittacus leucophthalmus  Statius M&uuml;ller, 1776.  Formerly included in  Aratinga  (e.g.,  AOU 1983 ,  1998 ) following  Peters (1937) , but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data (e.g.,  Kirchman et al. 2012 ; summarized in  Remsen et al. 2013 ), which indicate that  Psittacara  is not closely related to  Aratinga  but rather is sister to a group of three extralimital genera ( Leptosittaca  von Berlepsh &amp; Stolzmann 1894 , Diopsittaca  Ridgway 1912, and  Guaruba  Lesson 1830).  Change   Aratinga holochlora   (Sclater),   Aratinga strenua   (Ridgway),   Aratinga finschi   (Salvin),   Aratinga euops   (Wagler),   Aratinga chloroptera   (de Souanc&eacute;), and   Aratinga mitrata   (Tschudi) to   Psittacara holochlorus   (Sclater),   Psittacara strenuus   (Ridgway),   Psittacara finschi   (Salvin),   Psittacara euops   (Wagler),   Psittacara chloropterus   de Souanc&eacute;, and   Psittacara mitratus   (Tschudi), make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for  Psittacara . In the species accounts for all species, add the following Notes (for  P. mitratus ) or add to the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Aratinga . See comments under  Psittacara .  p. 266.  Ninox japonica  is treated as a species separate from  N. scutulata  (which was added to the  Check-list  in  Chesser et al. 2009 ). Remove the species account for  N. scutulata  and replace it with the following new account:   Strix hirsuta japonica  Temminck and Schlegel, 1845, in Siebold, Fauna Japonica, Aves, p. 28, pl. 9B. (Japan.)  A variety of woodland habitats.   Breeds  from southeastern Russian Far East, Korea, and northern and central (possibly southern) China south through Japan and Taiwan, and possibly in the northern Philippines.   Winters  in southern part of breeding range and throughout mainland Southeast Asia, the Philippines, and much of Indonesia.  Accidental in Alaska (St. Paul Island, Pribilof Islands, 27 August&ndash;3 September 2005; photos;  Yerger and Mohlmann 2008 ; and Kiska Island, Aleutian Islands, 1 August 2008; photos of carcass;  Bond and Jones 2010 ), and on Ashmore Reef, Australia.  Formerly considered conspecific with  Ninox scutulata  (Raffles) &lsqb;Brown Hawk-Owl&rsqb;, but treated as a separate species on the basis of vocal differences ( King 2002 ). Group name changed from Hawk-Owl to Boobook to conform to general usage for this species (e.g.,  Dickinson and Remsen 2013 ).  pp. 350&ndash;353. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences ( Derryberry et al. 2011 ,  Claramunt et al. 2013 ) has shown that the generic limits and linear sequence of species currently placed in the genera  Hyloctistes ,  Automolus , and  Thripadectes  do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:  Change   Hyloctistes subulatus   (Spix) to   Automolus subulatus   (Spix), delete the genus heading and Notes for  Hyloctistes , move the citation for  Hyloctistes  into the synonymy of  Automolus , insert the species account for  Automolus subulatus  to follow the account for  Automolus ochrolaemus , and insert the following at the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Hyloctistes , but genetic data ( Derryberry et al. 2011 ,  Claramunt et al. 2013 ) indicate that  Hyloctistes  is embedded within  Automolus .  After the account for  Syndactyla subalaris , insert the following heading:   Clibanornis  Sclater and Salvin, 1873, Nomen. Av. Neotrop., pp. 61, 155. Type, by original designation,  Anabates dendrocolaptoides  Pelzeln.  Change   Automolus rubiginosus   (Sclater) to   Clibanornis rubiginosus   (Sclater), place the account for this species under the heading for  Clibanornis , make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and insert the following at the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Automolus , but genetic data ( Derryberry et al. 2011 ,  Claramunt et al. 2013 ) indicate that  C. rubiginosus  is part of a clade that is sister to a clade consisting of  Thripadectes  and  Automolus .  Rearrange the linear sequence of genera and species that follow  Syndactyla subalaris  as follows:  Genus  Clibanornis    Clibanornis rubiginosus   Genus  Thripadectes    Thripadectes rufobrunneus   Genus  Automolus    Automolus ochrolaemus    Automolus subulatus   p. 355. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences ( Derryberry et al. 2011 ,  Weir and Price 2011 ) have shown that the linear sequence of species in the genus  Dendrocincla  does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships.  Under the heading Genus   DENDROCINCLA   Gray, insert the following:  Linear sequence of species follows  Derryberry et al. (2011)  and  Weir and Price (2011) .  Rearrange the sequence of species of  Dendrocincla  as follows:   Dendrocincla homochroa    Dendrocincla anabatina    Dendrocincla fuliginosa   p. 369.  Gymnopithys bicolor  is considered a species separate from  G. leucaspis , following  Remsen et al. (2014) . Remove the species account for  G. leucaspis  and replace it with the following account:   Pithys bicolor  Lawrence, 1863, Ann. Lyc. Nat. Hist. New York 8: 6. (Lion Hill Station, Panam&aacute; Railroad.)  Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest (0&ndash;1,500 m; Tropical Zone).  &lsqb;same as for  bicolor  group&rsqb;  Formerly considered conspecific with South American  Gymnopithys leucaspis  (Sclater) &lsqb;White-cheeked Antbird&rsqb;. Treated as a separate species because mitochondrial and nuclear DNA ( Brumfield et al. 2007 ) indicate that  G. leucaspis  and   G. bicolor   are not sisters, but that  G. leucaspis  is sister instead to the South American  G. rufigula  Boddaert 1783.  p. 489. Remove the heading Family  MEGALURIDAE : Grassbirds (added to the  Check-list  in  Chesser et al. 2010 ) and the Notes under this heading and replace them with the following heading and Notes:    Formerly ( Chesser et al. 2010 ) known as Family Megaluridae, but the name Locustellidae has priority when  Locustella  is included. See comments under Family Sylviidae.  In the Notes under Family  SYLVIIDAE : Sylviid Warblers, replace &ldquo;Megaluridae&rdquo; with &ldquo;Locustellidae.&rdquo;  p. 490. After the account for   Phylloscopus trochilus  , insert the following new species account:   Sylvia collybita  Vieillot, 1817, Nouv. Dict. Hist. Nat., nouv. &eacute;d., 11, p. 235. (&ldquo;r&eacute;gions septentrionales&rdquo; of France; restricted to Normandy by Mayaud, 1941, Oiseau, 11, no. sp&eacute;c., p. 87.)  Breeds in a variety of forested habitats and hedgerows with an understory. Winters in similar habitats, but also parks and gardens, and even marshes and mangroves.   Breeds  from northern Europe in the British Isles, Denmark, Sweden and central Finland, east across northern Russia to about the Kolyma River and south to Italy, Greece, Bulgaria, Turkey, northern Iran, and Lake Baikal, Altai, and northwestern Mongolia.   Winters  from southern part of breeding range in the Mediterranean region south to North Africa and Senegal and Sudan, the southern Caspian Mountains, the Arabian Peninsula and lower Himalayas east through Nepal, India (West Bengal and western Assam, south to Maharashtra), and Bangladesh.  Casual in Japan and Thailand.  Accidental in Alaska (Gambell, St. Lawrence Island, 6&ndash;7 June 2012; photos;  Lehman and Zimmer 2013 ).  The St. Lawrence Island bird was identified from photos as the easternmost subspecies  P. c. tristis  Blyth, which has been maintained by some as a separate species based on vocalizations (e.g.,  Rasmussen and Anderton 2005 ).  Phylloscopus ibericus  (Ticehurst, 1937) &lsqb;Iberian Chiffchaff&rsqb; and   P. canariensis   (Hartwig 1886) &lsqb;Canary Islands Chiffchaff&rsqb;, formerly treated ( Vaurie 1959 ) as a junior synonym of nominate  collybita  and as a subspecies of   P. collybita  , respectively, were treated as separate species by  Dickinson (2003) .  p. 490. The hyphen is removed from the English name of Pallas's Leaf Warbler  Phylloscopus proregulus  (added to the  Check-list  in  Banks et al. 2008 ) because the various species named &ldquo;Leaf Warbler&rdquo; do not form a monophyletic group ( Olsson et al. 2005 ,  Johansson et al. 2007 ).  p. 490.  Phylloscopus xanthodryas  and  P. examinandus  are considered species separate from   P. borealis  . Replace the distributional statement and Notes in the species account for   P. borealis   with the following:   Breeds  in western and central Alaska from the Noatak River and western and central Brooks Range south to southwestern Alaska, the base of the Alaska Peninsula, the Alaska Range, and Susitna River highlands; and in Eurasia from Sweden, northern Russia, and northern Siberia south to central Russia, Mongolia, and Amurland. Recorded in summer north to Barrow and on St. Lawrence Island. Records from St. Matthew Island and Prince Patrick Island (northern Northwest Territories) have not been positively identified as this species or as  P. examinandus .   Winters  from Andaman Islands, Southeast Asia, and southeastern China and Taiwan south to eastern Indonesia, Ashmore Reef, and the Philippines.   Migrates  through eastern Asia.  Casual in California (Monterey, San Luis Obispo, Stanislaus, San Francisco, and Kern counties).  See comments under  Phylloscopus examinandus .  After the species account for   P. borealis  , insert the following new species account:    Phylloscopus borealis  examinandus  Stresemann, 1913, Novit. Zool. 20:353. (Bali.)  Broadleaf forest, birch, swampy woods, and shrubby areas (rarely pine) below 1,000 m.   Breeds  in southern Kamchatka (north to at least 56&deg;N), Sakhalin, the Kuril Islands, and northeastern Hokkaido.   Wintering range  poorly known; specimens from Indonesia (Bali through Sumba;  Ticehurst 1938 ).   Migrates  through northeastern Russia, Japan, and northeastern China.  Casual in the Aleutians (Attu, Shemya, Amchitka) during spring and autumn migration.  Formerly included in   P. borealis   along with  P. xanthodryas  (Swinhoe 1863) &lsqb;Japanese Leaf Warbler&rsqb;, but treated as separate species on the basis of differences in song and mitochondrial DNA ( Saitoh et al. 2010 ,  Alstr&ouml;m et al. 2011 ).  Phylloscopus xanthodryas , which breeds in the mountains of Japan (except Hokkaido), has not been reported definitely from North America. The latter species and  P. examinandus  were formerly considered to constitute   P. borealis  xanthodryas  ( Vaurie 1959 ,  Watson et al. 1986 ); all known reports of   P. borealis  xanthodryas  from the AOU area pertain to  P. examinandus .  pp. 570&ndash;571. Change the English group name of  Chlorospingus flavopectus ,  C. tacarcunae ,   C. inornatus  ,  C. pileatus ,  C. flavigularis , and  C. canigularis  from Bush-Tanager to Chlorospingus, following  Remsen et al. (2014) . These species were transferred recently ( Chesser et al. 2011 ) from the Thraupidae to the Emberizidae; the removal of &ldquo;Bush-Tanager&rdquo; from the English names reflects this taxonomic change. In the Notes for  C. flavopectus , add the following sentence: Formerly known as Common Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for  C. tacarcunae , add the following sentence: Formerly known as Tacarcuna Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for   C. inornatus  , add the following sentence: Formerly known as Pirre Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for  C. pileatus , add the following sentence: Formerly known as Sooty-capped Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for  C. flavigularis , add the following sentence: Formerly known as Yellow-throated Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for  C. canigularis  add the following sentence: Formerly known as Ashy-throated Bush-Tanager.  p. 592. Preceding the account for  Sporophila schistacea , insert the following new species account:   Loxia lineola  Linnaeus, 1758, Syst. Nat., ed. 10, 1, p. 174. (Asia; error, emended to Surinam by Berlepsch and Hartert, 1902, Novit. Zool. 9:26; further emended to Bahia, Brazil, by Meyer de Schauensee, 1952, Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia 104:77.)  Second-growth Scrub, Riparian Thickets, Pastures/Agricultural Lands (0&ndash;1,200 m; Tropical Zone).  Resident in northeastern Brazil from Maranh&atilde;o, Tocantins, and Bahia eastward. Summer resident from Mato Grosso do Sul, Minas Gerais, and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, south to north-central Argentina, southeastern Bolivia, Paraguay, and Paran&aacute; and S&atilde;o Paulo, Brazil. In winter, widespread throughout South America east of the Andes north of its summer breeding range.  Accidental in Costa Rica (playa El Rey, Quepos, Puntarenas province, lat. 9&deg;22&prime;45.15&prime;&prime;N. long. 84&deg;03&prime;32.10&prime;&prime;W. 5&ndash;7 October 2013; photos;  Obando-Calder&oacute;n et al. 2013 ).  p. 592.  Sporophila corvina  is considered a species separate from   S. americana  , following  Stiles (1996)  and  Remsen et al. (2014) . Remove the species account for   S. americana   and replace it with the following account:   Spermophila corvina  Sclater, 1859, Proc. Zool. Soc. London, p. 379. (Playa Vicente, Oaxaca, Mexico.)  Second-growth Scrub, Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest Edge, Tropical Deciduous Forest, Secondary Forest (0&ndash;1,500 m; Tropical and Lower Subtropical zones).   Resident  &lsqb; corvina  group&rsqb; from northern Oaxaca, southern Veracruz, and Tabasco south on the Gulf&ndash;Caribbean slope of Central America to western Panama (Bocas del Toro); and &lsqb; ophthalmica  group&rsqb; from the Pacific slope of southwestern Costa Rica (north to the Gulf of Nicoya) south through Panama (both slopes, except for Bocas del Toro), western Colombia, and western Ecuador to northwestern Peru. The  ophthalmica  group was formerly ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ) known as the  aurita  group, but see comments below.  Groups:  S. corvina  (Sclater, 1860) &lsqb;Black Seedeater&rsqb; and  S. ophthalmica  (Sclater, 1860) &lsqb;Variable Seedeater&rsqb;. Formerly considered conspecific with South American  Sporophila americana  (Gmelin 1789) &lsqb;Wing-barred Seedeater&rsqb;, but treated as a separate species on the basis of similarities in plumage pattern, plumage sequences, distribution, and biometrics, and two localized zones of at least sporadic hybridization between  S. corvina  and extralimital  Sporophila intermedia  Cabanis, 1851 &lsqb;Gray Seedeater&rsqb;, which on this basis are considered to be sister species ( Stiles 1996 ). As noted by  Olson (1981b)  and  Stiles (1996) ,  Sporophila  &ldquo; aurita &rdquo; Bonaparte 1850 represents intergrades between  S. c. corvina  and  S. c. hicksii  Lawrence 1865. The type has disappeared, and it is impossible to assign this name to either of the parental populations.  pp. 593&ndash;594. Phylogenetic analyses of mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences indicate that the genus  Oryzoborus  is embedded within  Sporophila . Change   Oryzoborus nuttingi   Ridgway,   Oryzoborus funereus   Sclater, and   Oryzoborus crassirostris   (Gmelin) to   Sporophila nuttingi   (Ridgway),   Sporophila funerea   (Sclater), and   Sporophila crassirostris   (Gmelin), delete the genus heading and notes for  Oryzoborus , move the citation for  Oryzoborus  into the synonymy of  Sporophila , and make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes for each species. In the species accounts for all species, add the following Notes (for  S. crassirostris ) or add to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Oryzoborus ; see comments under  Sporophila .  Replace the existing Notes under the heading Genus  Sporophila  Cabanis (p. 591) with the following:  DNA sequence data indicate that  Oryzoborus , formerly considered a separate genus, is embedded within  Sporophila  ( Lijtmaer et al. 2004 ,  Mason and Burns 2013 ,  Burns et al. 2014 ), as previously predicted from morphological characters ( Olson 1981a ). Linear sequence of species follows  Mason and Burns (2013)  and  Burns et al. (2014) .  Rearrange the sequence of species of  Sporophila  as follows:   Sporophila minuta    Sporophila funerea    Sporophila nuttingi    Sporophila crassirostris    Sporophila corvina    Sporophila torqueola    Sporophila nigricollis     Sporophila lineola     Sporophila schistacea   p. 625.  Junco insularis  is considered a species separate from   J. hyemalis  . In the Notes under genus  Junco , delete the last sentence. After the species account for   J. hyemalis  , insert the following new account:   Junco insularis  Ridgway, 1876, Bull. Geol. Geog. Surv. Terr. 2, pt. 2, p. 188. (Isla Guadalupe, Baja California.)  Pine Forest, Pine&ndash;Oak Forest (0&ndash;1,300 m).   Resident  on Guadalupe Island, off Baja California.  Formerly considered conspecific with   Junco hyemalis  , but treated as a separate species on the basis of differences in song, morphology, and DNA sequence data (Mirsky 1976, Aleixandre et al. 2013).  In the species account for   J. hyemalis  , remove information on the  insularis  group from the habitat and distributional statements and change the Notes to the following:  Groups:   J. hyemalis   &lsqb;Slate-colored Junco&rsqb;,  J. oreganus  (J. K. Townsend, 1837) &lsqb;Oregon Junco&rsqb;,  J. aikeni  Ridgway, 1873 &lsqb;White-winged Junco&rsqb;, and  J. caniceps  (Woodhouse, 1853) &lsqb;Gray-headed Junco&rsqb;. The groups intergrade to varying degrees. Several other forms may merit recognition as groups:  Junco mearnsi  Ridgway, 1897 &lsqb;Pink-sided Junco&rsqb;, of the  oreganus  group, breeding from southeastern Alberta and southwestern Saskatchewan to eastern Idaho and northwestern Wyoming, and  J. dorsalis  Henry, 1858 &lsqb;Red-backed Junco&rsqb;, of the  caniceps  group, breeding from northern and central Arizona and central New Mexico to western Texas. For detailed information on groups, see  Miller (1941) . See comments under  J. vulcani  and  J. insularis .  pp. 631&ndash;632. Phylogenetic analysis of mitochondrial DNA sequences ( Chaves et al. 2013 ) has shown that the linear sequence of species in the genus  Saltator  does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships.  Under the heading Genus   SALTATOR   Vieillot, add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Linear sequence of species follows  Chaves et al. (2013) .  Rearrange the sequence of species of  Saltator  as follows:   Saltator atriceps    Saltator maximus    Saltator grossus    Saltator albicollis    Saltator coerulescens    Saltator striatipectus   p. 657. DNA sequence data ( Powell et al. 2014 ) indicate that  Cacicus melanicterus  is sister to a clade consisting of  Psarocolius  and the other species of  Cacicus . Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Amblycercus holosericeus :   Cassiculus  Swainson, 1827, Philos. Mag., new ser., 1: 436. Type, by original designation,  Cassiculus coronatus  Swainson &equals;  Icterus melanicterus  Bonaparte.   Ridgway (1902)  and  Hellmayr (1938)  treated this species in the monotypic genus  Cassiculus .  Blake (1968)  merged it into  Cacicus , and this was followed in most subsequent classifications (e.g.,  AOU 1983 ,  1998 ). DNA sequence data ( Powell et al. 2014 ), however, indicate that  Cassiculus  is sister to a clade consisting of  Psarocolius  and true  Cacicus .  Change   Cacicus melanicterus   (Bonaparte) to   Cassiculus melanicterus   (Bonaparte) and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for  Cassiculus . Replace the second sentence of the Notes with the following: Formerly placed in the genus  Cacicus . See comments under  Cassiculus .  Delete the citation of  Caciculus  from the synonymy of  Cacicus . Remove the existing Notes under the heading Genus   CACICUS   Lac&eacute;p&egrave;de.  pp. 682&ndash;683. DNA sequence data ( Sorenson et al. 2004 ,  Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009 ) indicate that the generic limits and linear sequence of species currently placed in the genera  Lonchura  and  Padda  do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:  Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Amandava amandava :   Spermestes  Swainson, 1837, Birds W. Africa 1, p. 201. Type, by monotypy,  Spermestes cucullata  Swainson.  Formerly considered part of  Lonchura  ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ), but now treated as separate because DNA sequence data ( Sorenson et al. 2004 ,  Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009 ) indicate that  Spermestes  is not included in true  Lonchura .  Delete the citation of  Spermestes  from the synonymy of  Lonchura . Change   Lonchura cucullata   (Swainson) to   Spermestes cucullata   Swainson and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for  Spermestes . Replace the last sentence of the Notes with: Formerly placed in the genus  Lonchura . See comments under  Spermestes .  Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for  Spermestes cucullata :   Euodice  Reichenbach, 1862&ndash;1863, Singv&ouml;gel, p. 46. Type, by subsequent designation (Sharpe, 1890, Cat. Birds Brit. Mus. 13, p. 368),  Loxia cantans  Gmelin.  Formerly considered part of  Lonchura  ( AOU 1983 ,  1998 ), but now treated as separate because DNA sequence data ( Sorenson et al. 2004 ,  Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009 ) indicate that  Euodice  is not included in true  Lonchura .  Delete the citation of  Euodice  from the synonomy of  Lonchura . Change   Lonchura malabarica   (Linnaeus) and   Lonchura cantans   (Gmelin) to   Euodice malabarica   (Linnaeus) and   Euodice cantans   (Gmelin), and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for  Euodice . Make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes. Add the following to the end of the Notes for each species: Formerly placed in the genus  Lonchura . See comments under  Euodice .   Change   Padda oryzivora   (Linnaeus) to   Lonchura oryzivora   (Linnaeus), delete the genus heading and Notes for  Padda , move the citation for  Padda  into the synonymy of  Lonchura , insert the species account for  Lonchura oryzivora  to precede the account for  Lonchura punctulata , and insert the following at the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus  Padda , but DNA sequence data ( Sorenson et al. 2004 ,  Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009 ) indicate that  Padda  is embedded within  Lonchura , as treated by  Payne (2010) .  p. 683. Change the English name for  Lonchura punctulata  to Scaly-breasted Munia (as in  Inskipp et al. 2001 ,  Robson 2005 ,  Payne 2010 , and  Rasmussen and Anderton 2012 ). Change the Notes to read: Formerly known as Nutmeg Mannikin (e.g., AOU 1983, 1998), but name modified to conform to general worldwide usage. Also known as Spotted Munia, Spice Finch, or Ricebird.  p. 698. Change   Oryzoborus angolensis   (Linnaeus) to   Sporophila angolensis   (Linnaeus). Phylogenetic analyses based on sequences of mitochondrial and nuclear DNA indicate that  Oryzoborus , formerly considered a separate genus, is embedded within  Sporophila  ( Mason and Burns 2013 ,  Burns et al. 2014 ).  pp. 705 ff. Make the following changes to the list of French names of North American birds:  Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:  Rearrange the species sequence in  Dendrocincla ,  Saltator , and  Sporophila  as indicated by the text of this supplement.  Rearrange the species sequence from  Zenaida  to  Starnoenas  as indicated by the text of this supplement.  Rearrange the species sequence from  Aratinga  to  Ara  as indicated by the text of this supplement.  Rearrange the sequence of species formerly in  Hyloctistes ,  Automolus , and  Thripadectes  as indicated by the text of this supplement.  Rearrange the sequence of species formerly in  Lonchura  and  Padda  as indicated by the text of this supplement.  Proposals considered but not accepted by the committee included transfer of several species of  Spinus  to  Sporagra  or  Astragalinus , merger of Thick-billed Parrot  Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha  and Maroon-fronted Parrot  R. terrisi  into a single species, separation of the Cuban Parrot ( Amazona leucocephala ) complex into two or more species, separation of Siberian Stonechat  Saxicola maurus  from Common Stonechat   S. torquatus  , separation of  Toxostoma palmeri  from Curve-billed Thrasher   T. curvirostre  , elimination of the subfamily Trogoninae, and transfer of Azure Gallinule  Porphyrio flavirostris  from the main list to the Appendix.  Normand David serves as the committee's advisor for classical languages in relation to scientific names, and Michel Gosselin is the authority for French names. We thank A. Borodayko, R. T. Brumfield, J. Cracraft, B. Freeman, K. L. Garrett, D. D. Gibson, S. N. G. Howell, M. J. Iliff, J. M. Maley, N. A. Mason, R. G. Moyle, G. Obando-Calder&oacute;n, J. Penhallurick, A. P. Peterson, M. L. P. Retter, B. T. Smith, M. D. Sorenson, C. Stahala, R. C. Tweit, A. Urant&oacute;wka, J. Withrow, and J. Zook for assistance, suggestions, and comments. 