On the &ldquo;real estate market&rdquo;: Individual quality and the foraging ecology of male Cory's ShearwatersSite and mate fidelity of Shags <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</named-content></italic> at two British coloniesSpatial variability of seabird distribution associated with environmental factors: A case study of marine important bird areas in the AzoresOceanographic influences on seabirds and cetaceans of the eastern tropical Pacific: A reviewWhose young win? Parental quality and recruitment in seabirdsSite and mate choice in seabirds: An evolutionary approachNest site selection and competitive interactions of Herring and Laughing Gulls in New JerseyThe regulation of seabird colony size: A hinterland modelDo Cory's Shearwaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic> synchronize laying among close neighborhoods? A reappraisal using data from artificial nest sitesIncubation routine, body mass regulation, and egg neglect in the blue petrel, <italic>Halbaena caerulea</italic>Nest Building and Bird BehaviourDifferences in the quality of birds breeding in the center and on the edges of a colonyThe prudent parent: Energetic adjustments in avian breedingCentral-place foraging in an arctic seabird provides evidence for Storer-Ashmole's HaloThe L&eacute;vy flight foraging hypothesis in a pelagic seabirdAshmole's halo and population regulation in seabirdsThe breeding biology of Cory's Shearwater <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic> on Berlenga Island, PortugalVariation in measurements of Cory's Shearwater between populations and sexing by discriminant analysisMysterious attendance cycles in Cory's Shearwater, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>: An exploration of patterns and hypothesesPatterns of activity and burrow attendance in Cory's Shearwater <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic> as revealed by a novel logging techniqueFlexible foraging strategy of Cory's Shearwater, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>, during the chick-rearing periodMass/length residuals: Measures of body condition or generators of spurious results?Offshore diplomacy, or how seabirds mitigate intra-specific competition: A case study based on GPS tracking of Cape Gannets from neighbouring coloniesSite use and fidelity in the Common Guillemot <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>Nest site characteristics, duration of use and breeding success in the guillemot <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>Regulation of protein breakdown and adrenocortical response to stress in birds during migratory flightPrelaying exodus of Cory's Shearwaters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic>) on Selvagem GrandeCompetition for breeding sites and site-dependent population regulation in a highly colonial seabird, the Common Guillemot <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>Population trends of Cory's Shearwaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic> breeding at Berlengas Islands, PortugalFirst complete census of Cory's Shearwaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic> breeding at Berlengas Islands (Portugal), including the small islets of the archipelagoEvidence of intra-specific competition for food in a pelagic seabirdDual-foraging of Cory's Shearwaters in the Azores: Feeding locations, behaviour at sea, and implications for food provisioning of chicksThe use of energy, fat, and protein reserves by breeding Great Black-backed GullsMovements, morphology, breeding, molt, diet, and feeding of seabirds in the AzoresLifetime reproductive success in seabirds: Interindividual differences and implications for conservationPairing in the Cory's Shearwater (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>) of Selvagem GrandeThe attendance cycles of the Cory's Shearwater <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic> on Selvagem GrandeInexperienced birds and breeding in the Cory's Shearwater (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>)Patch time allocation and patch sampling by foraging Great and Blue TitsForaging segregation between two closely related shearwaters breeding in sympatryNutritional and feeding ecology in Cory's Shearwater <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic> during breedingEnvironmental determinants of strategies in Cory's Shearwaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>On the theory of central place foragingInfluences of food availability and predation on survival of kittiwakesForaging plasticity in a pelagic seabird species along a marine productivity gradientOceanographic characteristics of areas used by Cory's Shearwaters during short and long foraging trips in the North AtlanticHow area restricted search of a pelagic seabird changes while performing a dual foraging strategyFlight dynamics of Cory's Shearwater foraging in a coastal environmentOvercoming difficult times: The behavioural resilience of a marine predator when facing environmental stochasticityEffects of environmental variability on different trophic levels of the North Atlantic food webNesting sites and nest types as important factors for the conservation of Humboldt penguins (<italic>Sphensicus humboldti</italic>)Age-related differences in nest defense in common terns: Relationship to other life-history parametersEffects of satellite transmitters on albatrosses and petrelsScale-dependent habitat use in a long-ranging central place predatorPopulation dynamics and breeding success of the Shag, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</named-content></italic>, on the Farne Islands, NorthumberlandCompetition for nest sites between Kelp Gulls (<italic>Larus dominicanus</italic>) and terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna maxima</named-content></italic> and <italic>S. eurygnatha</italic>) in PatagoniaFlight morphology and foraging behavior of male and female Cory's ShearwaersReproductive measures and chick provisioning of Cory's Shearwaters <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic> in the AzoresCharacteristics and competition for nest cavities in burrowing procellariiformesPetrels night and day: A Sound Approach GuideFactors affecting mortality of shearwaters stranded by light pollutionResponse of the haematocrit to body condition changes in Northern Bald Ibis <italic>Geronticus eremita</italic>Oceanographic and climatic factors influencing breeding and colony attendance patterns of Humboldt Penguins <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spheniscus humboldti</named-content></italic> in central ChileIdentification of upwelling areas on sea surface temperature images using fuzzy clusteringNest-site tenacity and mate fidelity in relation to breeding success in Cory's Shearwater (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>)Indirect, physiological assessment of reproductive state and breeding chronology in free-living birds: An example in the Marbled Murrelet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Brachyramphus marmoratus</named-content></italic>)Marked Sooty Shearwaters (<italic>Puffinus griseous</italic>) in the Northern HemisphereTastsinn und Gemeingef&uuml;hlThe role of body condition in breeding and foraging decision in albatrosses and petrelsAn extended reproductive period and high variability in food resource availability at sea make good quality nest sites particularly important for the survival of pelagic seabird chicks. Despite high philopatry during the early pre-laying period, males compete strongly for nests, making this period a unique opportunity to independently assess the influence of nest-site characteristics and individual quality on the foraging behavior of Cory's Shearwater (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic>) individuals. We found significant differences in the at-sea foraging behavior of males and females at temporal (trip duration) and spatial (foraging areas, trip distance, and trip sinuosity) scales, both of which are greater in females. Furthermore, we suggest that nests of higher quality are deeper and closer to the nest of a conspecific neighbor because both variables were associated with males foraging closer to the colony. Finally, we showed that during the early pre-laying period the influence exerted by nests on males' behavior at sea is independent from the individual's quality. Our study links nest-site features with the at-sea behavior of pelagic male seabirds during a period of nest competition and suggests that nest-site characteristics are important to explain foraging patterns of central-place foraging birds.Un nido de buena calidad es particularmente importante para la supervivencia de las cr&iacute;as de aves pel&aacute;gicas debido a su periodo reproductivo extenso y la alta variabilidad en la disponibilidad de sus recursos alimenticios en el mar. A pesar de que estas aves presentan filopatr&iacute;a, los machos compiten por nidos durante el periodo previo a la puesta del huevo. Esto nos brind&oacute; una oportunidad &uacute;nica de evaluar de manera independiente la influencia de las caracter&iacute;sticas del nido y de la calidad de individuo sobre el comportamiento en el mar en individuos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic>. Encontramos diferencias significativas entre el comportamiento de forrajeo de hembras y machos a escalas temporales (duraci&oacute;n de viajes) y espaciales (&aacute;rea de forrajeo, distancia de viaje y sinuosidad de viaje), siendo mayores en hembras en ambos casos. Asimismo sugerimos que los nidos de mejor calidad son m&aacute;s profundos y se encuentran m&aacute;s cerca a un nido de un vecino de la misma especie, ya que ambas variables est&aacute;n asociadas a machos que forrajean m&aacute;s cerca de la colonia. Finalmente, demostramos que en el per&iacute;odo previo a la puesta del huevo la influencia ejercida por los nidos sobre el comportamiento de los machos es independiente de la calidad del individuo evaluado. Nuestro estudio asocia las caracter&iacute;sticas de los nidos con el comportamiento de machos de aves marinas pel&aacute;gicas durante un periodo de competencia en los nidos y sugiere que las caracter&iacute;sticas del nido son importantes para explicar el comportamiento de forrajeo de aves que presentan un lugar central de forrajeo.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> comportamiento en el mar, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content></italic>, comportamiento de forrajeo, calidad del individuo, calidad del nido, per&iacute;odo previo a la puesta de huevosThe quality of the breeding territory positively influences the reproductive success of individuals, and dominant parents generally get access to territories with better quality resources. In central-place foraging animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Orians1">Orians and Pearson 1979</xref>) with a long breeding season, parents must select and defend appropriate nest sites to protect eggs and chicks, and optimize prey delivery to the chicks by minimizing travelling distances to foraging patches (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-NaefDaenzer1">Naef-Daenzer 2000</xref>). Thus, the need to acquire and defend high-quality nest sites may help explain the foraging patterns of central-place foraging species such as seabirds, in particular those of males, which are more often engaged in nest defense.The reproductive period in pelagic seabirds is extended, and there is high variability in their food resources at sea (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Oro1">Oro and Furness 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Simeone1">Simeone et al. 2002</xref>). Their reproductive cycle is characterized by the laying of a single highly nutritious egg per breeding attempt and the occurrence of a short exodus in females&mdash;and sometimes in males&mdash;from the breeding area immediately before egg laying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Warham1">Warham 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Warham2">1990</xref>). The pre-laying period in migratory shearwater species lasts several months; that of Cory's Shearwaters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calonectris diomedea</named-content> borealis</italic>) is approximately 90 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin2">Mougin et al. 2000</xref>), beginning with the arrival of both individuals at the colony (by late February and early March; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Monteiro1">Monteiro et al. 1996</xref>) and ending when the egg is laid (between late May and early June; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin2">Mougin et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos2">Ramos et al. 2003</xref>). Many studies have described the foraging ecology of Cory's Shearwaters during the breeding period (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Magalhaes1">Magalh&atilde;es et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro1">Navarro et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro3">Navarro and Gonz&aacute;lez-Sol&iacute;s 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva1">Paiva et al. 2010a</xref>), and the few that addressed the pre-laying exodus found marked distinctions in the location and extension of foraging grounds for both sexes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Warham2">Warham 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva5">Paiva et al. 2013a</xref>). Only a handful however, specifically addressed the at-sea behavior before the pre-laying exodus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro5">Granadeiro et al. 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin2">Mougin et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jouanin1">Jouanin et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro2">Navarro et al. 2007</xref>), hereafter called the early pre-laying period.During the early pre-laying period, males must acquire the nest site and guard and defend it from other males while females begin to gather energy for egg production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro4">Granadeiro et al. 1998b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jouanin1">Jouanin et al. 2001</xref>). Hence, the energetic investment of males (i.e. fat reserves) during the pre-laying period is much higher than that of females; males lose as much mass as females gain by the end of this period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mawhinney1">Mawhinney et al. 1999</xref>). Differences between male and female at-sea behavior have been suggested for this period, based primarily on the monitoring of attendance cycles at the colony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro5">Granadeiro et al. 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin2">Mougin et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jouanin1">Jouanin et al. 2001</xref>) and the use of low accuracy devices such as geolocators (Global Location Sensing; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro2">Navarro et al. 2007</xref>).A good nest is particularly important because it can potentially increase the fitness of breeders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Collias1">Collias and Collias 1984</xref>) by providing protection and a suitable microclimate, especially in burrowing petrels (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos3">Ramos et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Kokko1">Kokko et al. 2004</xref>). Philopatry occurs in most seabird species (review in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Bried1">Bried and Jouventin 2002</xref>), and competition for nests in burrowing species is common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Burger1">Burger and Shisler 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos3">Ramos et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Quintana1">Quintana and Yorio 1998</xref>), which leads to the prediction that good quality breeders occupy good quality nest sites (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Pearson1">Pearson et al. 2005</xref>). Good quality breeders should also be more efficient foragers and, hence, have a better body condition, as inferred by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Pinaud1">Pinaud and Weimerskirch (2005)</xref>. Moreover, seabirds such as albatrosses and petrels are known to behave as prudent parents during the reproductive period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Drent1">Drent and Dann 1980</xref>), opting to abandon reproduction (incubation and chick rearing) if they reach a mass threshold that could jeopardize their future reproductive success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Chaurand1">Chaurand and Weimerskirch 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Weimerskirch1">Weimerskirch 1999</xref>). Thus, the early pre-laying period presents a unique opportunity to separately assess the influence of nest-site characteristics and individual quality on the foraging behavior of individuals.In this study we equipped male and female Cory's Shearwaters with GPS loggers during the early pre-laying period to determine sexual differences in foraging areas and at-sea foraging behavior. Because males must guard and defend the nest from conspecifics, we predicted that male foraging trips should be shorter and closer to the colony than those of females. If so, we also predicted that nest-site characteristics should be more important than individual quality to explain male behavior at sea. Hence, we assessed whether male at-sea behavior was associated to specific nest-site features or if it was related to males' individual quality (breeding experience, body condition, and physiological intrinsic factors to the individual).We performed our study on Berlenga Island on the west coast of Portugal (39.413611N, &minus;9.508056E) from April 10 to May 10, 2010. Rich foraging grounds surround this area, possibly as a result of the Portuguese upwelling system (Souza et al. 2008, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva1">Paiva et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva6">2013b</xref>) and the combination of bathymetric features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ballance1">Ballance et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Amorim1">Amorim et al. 2009</xref>), oceanic currents, and wind circulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva2">Paiva et al. 2010b</xref>). About 310 breeding pairs of Cory's Shearwater nest on Berlenga Island (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Lecoq2">Lecoq et al. 2011</xref>), and in our study colony approximately 130 pairs nest in rock crevices, burrows, and semi-artificial nests (these only differ from natural nests in that the rocks forming the nests walls were piled up by people). Competition for nests in this colony has intensified as the breeding population tripled between the 1990s and 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Lecoq1">Lecoq et al. 2010</xref>). Birds were sexed using vocalizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Robb1">Robb et al. 2008</xref>), and when needed a discriminator function based on bill and head measurements was applied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro2">Granadeiro 1993</xref>).We employed CatTraq Travel Loggers (Perthold Engineering, Anderson, South Carolina, USA) as GPS loggers. This 44.5 &times; 28.5 &times; 13 mm device weighs 20 g and contains a SiRFStarIII chipset, a patch antenna, a 230mAh lithium-ion battery, and offers accuracy up to 10 m. We removed the plastic case and replaced it with a 7 cm long thermo-retractile, heat-sealed rubber sleeve, reducing the total weight to 17 g. The logger weight represented between 1.8&percnt; and 2.4&percnt; of the instrumented birds weight during the study period (average weight was 878 &plusmn; 60g and 732 &plusmn; 35g for males and females, respectively), which is below the 3&percnt; threshold beyond which behavioral disruptions may occur in flying seabirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Phillips1">Phillips et al. 2003</xref>). Furthermore, an earlier study conducted in the same location in 2007 and using the same deployment method to attach heavier devices (&sim;27 g) to the birds' backs showed that birds carrying devices had similar weight increments to those of control birds. Also, fledging success of chicks fed by these 2 groups of individuals was similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva3">Paiva et al. 2010c</xref>).We deployed GPS loggers 51&ndash;30 days before laying (April 10&ndash;May 10, 2010), covering the middle third of the pre-laying period, before females left for the pre-laying exodus (when most birds had arrived at the colony and competition for nests was strong). The logger deployment took 3 nights, and birds carried the devices for different periods of time, mostly dependent on the presence of the bird at the colony for recapture and battery duration. GPS loggers recorded data (instantaneous geographic position, altitude, ground speed, course, distance) every 5 minutes from 0500 to 2200 hours when birds are more likely to be foraging at sea; they are commonly found ashore and inside nests at night during the pre-laying period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro1">Granadeiro 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro3">Granadeiro et al. 2009</xref>). Birds were captured during the night at their nest sites, weighed, and individually identified by their ring numbers (all study birds were ringed in former scientific studies conducted on our study colony since 1986). For each bird, approximately 1.5 mL of blood from the brachial vein was collected to measure hematocrit. Blood-based sexing was not necessary because the vocalizations of each sex are easily distinguishable, and we have worked annually in this colony since 2005 (i.e. bird's sex has been confirmed several times).We attached GPS loggers (using Tesa 4651 tape) to the contour feathers along and between both scapulae to minimize dislodging from neck movements and to cover the uropigial gland (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva4">Paiva et al. 2010d</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva5">2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Focardi1">Focardi and Cecere 2013</xref>). The cross-sectional area of the tags represented &sim;10&percnt; of the cross-sectional area of each bird's back. As an extra security measure we glued the tips of each tape stripe used to attach the logger. The use of tape instead of glue or a harness makes this method much less harmful for telemetered seabirds because (1) by removing the tape carefully with the help of alcohol the bird only loses a few back feathers, and (2) if we fail to recapture the bird, the device will fall off by itself after one month or so.Total handling time did not exceed 10 minutes, and birds were released immediately after securing the logger. We deployed 40 GPS loggers on 18 male and 22 female Cory's Shearwaters ranging from experienced breeders to new breeders (reproductive success data were available for breeding individuals since 2005; V. H. Paiva personal communication). Only 30 GPS loggers were retrieved with data (14 males and 16 females).We characterized 87 nest sites, including the 14 nests from males retrieved successfully with functioning loggers, using the following variables: temperature (Tvar: nest temperature variation during the study period, in &deg;C); humidity (Hvar: relative humidity variation during the study period, in &percnt;); substrate (soil in the nest chamber, assessed visually, in &percnt;); nest depth (total depth of nest from nest entrance, in cm); nest entrance area (in cm<sup>2</sup>), and distance to the nearest neighbor (in cm). Tvar and Hvar were recorded using five LOG32 data loggers. For this purpose, a pilot nest characterization was made to group 107 nests that were significantly similar in both variables (Spearman <italic>r<sub>s</sub></italic> &gt; 0.7, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Twelve groups of nests were obtained, and data loggers were set to register data every 5 minutes; nests were then placed in different groups, rotating among groups every 48 hours from April 10 to May 10, 2010.We assessed 3 criteria that influence the quality of a breeder as individual quality proxies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Becker1">Becker 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin3">Mougin et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Moreno1">Moreno 2003</xref>): (1) breeding experience based on the estimated age of each individual, (2) body condition measured with a body mass index (BMI), and (3) an intrinsic factor to the individual measured as the percentage of red blood cells (hematocrit); the higher the hematocrit, the more fit the bird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-SanchezGuzman1">S&aacute;nchez-Guzm&aacute;n et al. 2004</xref>). The age estimate for each bird used in this study indicates the minimum age the bird should be in the year the study was performed (2010). We estimated age based on the year the bird was ringed (between 1986 and 2006; most birds in the colony were not ringed as chicks). Because scientists come to this colony almost every year (at least since 1986) and band all birds they encounter, we are confident that our age estimation method correctly assigns a minimum age for each individual. The age code assigned during banding followed the classification given by the Euring database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.euring.org" xlink:type="simple">www.euring.org</ext-link>). In accordance with this, our birds' ages ranged from at least 7 to at least 24 years. Our age estimation method was also supported by the positive significant correlation between the estimated age of adult males and chicks produced by each individual per breeding attempt since 2005 (Spearman <italic>r<sub>s</sub></italic> &gt; 0.68, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14).We used the standard residuals of an ordinary least squares (OLS) linear regression of mass (mean body mass) and length of tarsus as body size indicator (BSI) to obtain the body condition index (BCI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Green1">Green 2001</xref>, Rodriguez et al. 2012). Mean body mass was obtained from body mass recorded at the beginning of the study (when GPS loggers were attached to the bird) and at the end of the study (when GPS loggers were retrieved from the bird). The hematocrit was obtained after centrifuging the collected blood.For each instrumented bird, an individual foraging trip was considered as starting and ending at the colony. To standardize the sampling effort for each bird, the duration of each trip was divided by the number of days the logger was actively recording movements of the instrumented bird (up to the minute the battery ran down before logger recovery; one logger working day equaled 17 hours).Because all foraging trips should be self-provisioning during this period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Cramp1">Cramp and Simmons 1997</xref>), we analyzed the frequency distribution of the duration of each single trip. We found a marked bimodal pattern that allowed trip duration to be divided into short (&equals; 1 day) and long (&ge;2 days; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). Similarly, we considered birds to be flying when the GPS speed was &gt;9 km h<sup>&minus;1</sup> by noticing the same bimodal pattern in the distribution of frequencies of the recorded speeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>B; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Gremillet1">Gr&eacute;millet et al. 2004</xref>). Values below this threshold corresponded to birds resting, landing, or departing from the water surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva4">Paiva et al. 2010d</xref>).Frequency histograms for (<bold>A</bold>) trip duration and (<bold>B</bold>) flying speed, determining break points at 2 days and 9 km hr<sup>&minus;1</sup>, respectively. Percentages were maximized to (<bold>A</bold>) 10&percnt; and (<bold>B</bold>) 3&percnt; for better visualization.For each short and long trip we calculated 6 variables: minimum convex polygon (MCP, in km<sup>2</sup>); trip duration (TD, in days calculated to a temporal resolution of minutes); maximum trip distance from the colony (MD, in km), trip sinuosity index (TSI, ratio of the maximum trip distance to the cumulative distance of each trip); 95&percnt; probability kernel area (K95, in km), and flying time (FT, in &percnt;). MCP represents the minimum polygon uniting the more extreme locations of a given animal in the representation of the vital area or home range of that animal. Maximum trip distance and K95 were calculated in ArcView 3.2 under Alberts Equal Area Conic Projection using the Animal Movement v2.04 extension for each trip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Hooge1">Hooge and Eichenlaub 1997</xref>). We selected this projection to control for both distance and area measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Pinaud1">Pinaud and Weimerskirch 2005</xref>).We used a mixed-effects model fitted with restricted maximum likelihood (REML) to compare all foraging variables between sexes, separately for short and long trips, using data for each trip and including bird identity as a random factor. The overall mean TD (i.e. without separating into short and long trips) was also compared between sexes with a mixed-effects model in the same manner. We log-transformed all variables to attain normality of the model residuals; K95 was not normally distributed, even after log transformation, but mixed-effects models fitted with the REML method are robust to moderate deviations of normality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Zuur1">Zuur et al. 2009</xref>).We analyzed nest-site variables with 2 principal component analyses (PCA): (1) using data for all nest sites (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 87), and (2) using data for the nest sites of the 14 males equipped with loggers. All variables were log(x&plus;1) transformed, and the first 3 principal components (PC) were extracted using a varimax normalized rotation to obtain a clear pattern of the factor loadings and make the output more understandable (Statsoft 2013). We compared the results of these 2 PCAs to evaluate whether the nests of males with loggers were representative of the overall nest variability in the colony.Individual quality proxies of the 14 individuals equipped with loggers were log transformed (except BCI) and analyzed by a PCA. We used the first 2 PC that were extracted.We used Pearson correlation coefficients to relate at-sea male foraging variables log(x&plus;1) transformed with the PC scores representing nest-site variation and individual quality.We recorded 218 foraging trips (males &equals; 145, <italic>M</italic> &equals; 10.36 &plusmn; 3.15, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14; females &equals; 73, <italic>M</italic> &equals; 4.50 &plusmn; 2.19, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 16). The at-sea foraging behavior differed significantly between males and females, in particular for long trips, for which the foraging areas (MCP and K95), MD, and the TSI were significantly larger for females (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Our data suggest that when engaged in short trips, males stay away from the colony for a significantly shorter time period than females (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 4.30, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-t01">Table 1</xref>).Comparison of at-sea foraging behavior variables minimum convex polygon (MCP, km<sup>2</sup>), trip duration (TD, in days), maximum distance from the colony (MD, in km), trip sinuosity index (TSI), and flying time (FT, in &percnt;), for short and long trips between male and female Cory's Shearwaters during the pre-laying period. The <italic>F</italic>-statistic and <italic>P</italic>-values are from a generalized linear mixed model (GLMMs) fitted with restricted maximum likelihood (REML), using data from each trip and including bird identity as a random factor. <italic>N</italic> is the number of recorded trips and sample size is the number of birds that performed them. Mean &plusmn; SD of each variable calculated for each individual is presented. Significant values are in bold.Differences in size of foraging areas between male and female Cory's Shearwaters from Berlenga Island (marked with a quadrangle).The PCA performed on the individual age, BCI, and hematocrit extracted 2 axes that explained 55.6&percnt; and 38.9&percnt; of the variation. The first axis (PC1) was related to age and BCI, and the second (PC2) to hematocrit (factor loadings &equals; 0.92, 0.90, and 0.99, respectively). Yet, the correlations of both PC to all the behavioral variables were nonsignificant (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.16).The PCA reduced the original 6 nest-site variables to 3 PCs (PC1, PC2, and PC3) that accounted for 70&percnt; of the total variation in the data of all 87 nests (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-t02">Table 2</xref>). For the 14 nests belonging to males equipped with data loggers, the PCA extracted 2 PCs (PC1 and PC2) that accounted for 64&percnt; of the total variation in these data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-t02">Table 2</xref>). In both sets of data the variables significantly associated with the first 2 PCs were the same, although in inverse order (i.e. significant variables in PC1<sub>(<italic>n</italic></sub> <sub>&equals; 87)</sub> &equals; PC2<sub>(<italic>n</italic></sub> <sub>&equals; 14)</sub> and significant variables in PC2<sub>(<italic>n</italic></sub> <sub>&equals; 87)</sub> &equals; PC1<sub>(<italic>n</italic></sub> <sub>&equals; 14)</sub>). Because the variables were the same, we concluded that the variation in those 14 nests were representative of the overall nest-site variation in the colony. Hence, PC1 was positively associated with nest depth and distance to the closest neighbor, while PC2 was positively associated with the variation in temperature and humidity inside the nest.Component loadings of the 6 explanatory nest-site variables for all nests and for nests of males equipped with loggers. Data for all variables were log(x&plus;1) transformed. The strongest associations between variables and principal components (PC) are in bold.We found highly significant negative correlations between PC1 and MD (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.63; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.017; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14) and the K95 (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.02; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.018; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14), suggesting that nests located in higher nest-density areas and those that are deeper are conditioning males to forage closer to the colony; therefore, these males have shorter-than-average foraging trips. Home range (i.e. MCP) was also significantly and negatively correlated with PC1 (<italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.60; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14), supporting the previous results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-f03">Figure 3</xref>). A positive significant correlation between PC2 (variation in temperature and humidity inside the nest) and FT was found (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.57; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.035; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14), but the correlation with FT was due to the presence of an outlier (the correlation was nonsignificant after removing the outlier; <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05).Significant correlations between PC1 (nest depth and distance to closest neighbor) and (<bold>A</bold>) minimum convex polygon (MCP, in km<sup>2</sup>), <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.60, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; (<bold>B</bold>) maximum distance to colony and (MD, in km), <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.63, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; (<bold>C</bold>) K95, <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.62, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02, male at-sea short foraging excursions.This study indicates that the at-sea behavior of Cory's Shearwater during the early pre-laying period is strongly influenced by sex, which in males relates to the characteristics of their nest sites. As expected, TD was significantly shorter for males than females in both short and long foraging trips, indicating that males return significantly more often to guard their nests. Previous studies in Cory's Shearwater had shown that attendance cycles during the pre-laying period were higher in males than in females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro4">Granadeiro et al. 1998b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jouanin1">Jouanin et al. 2001</xref>), supporting the male nest-guarding hypothesis, but no study had previously shown how these differences in behavior were expressed at-sea for both sexes. In accordance with the attendance cycles reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro4">Granadeiro et al. (1998b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jouanin1">Jouanin et al. (2001)</xref>, TD were shorter, and size of foraging areas (MCP and K95) were smaller for males than for females, suggesting that males fed closer to the colony because staying away from the nest for longer periods could result in the nest being occupied by new individuals or close neighbors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Brooke1">Brooke 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin1">Mougin 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin3">Mougin et al. 2002</xref>). The closer male foraging is also supported by our findings that increasing proximity of nests sites significantly decreased the size of male foraging areas and MD from the colony.In comparison, females performed longer foraging trips and also spent longer periods searching for food in greater areas, as suggested by their higher TSI. Females are not restrained by nest guarding behavior, which enables them to be more flexible in their foraging strategies by targeting more productive areas within the North Atlantic region, particularly when marine productivity close to the breeding colony is low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva5">Paiva et al. 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paiva6">2013b</xref>). Moreover, staying close to the colony could also imply direct competition with males foraging in the same area (as inferred by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Cairns1">Cairns 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Lewis1">Lewis et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Gaston1">Gaston et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Elliott1">Elliott et al. 2009</xref>). Previous studies on Cory's Shearwater activity patterns at-sea during the incubation period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos1">Ramos et al. 2009</xref>) and stable isotopes signatures from their tissues during the pre-laying and breeding periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro2">Navarro et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro3">2009</xref>) did not show differences between sexes, but our study found a clear difference in the foraging patterns of males and females during long foraging trips in the pre-laying period.In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Navarro2">Navarro et al. (2007)</xref> found significant differences in the plasma concentration of triglycerides and uric acid between sexes related to egg formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Vanderkist1">Vanderkist et al. 2000</xref>) and use of protein as a metabolic resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Jenni1">Jenni et al. 2000</xref>), respectively, which indicates a differential use of resources by both sexes during the pre-laying period. The observed at-sea behaviors in our study provide strong evidence that at the beginning of the pre-laying period, males engage in nest defense while females are already gathering energy for egg production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Warham2">Warham 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Granadeiro4">Granadeiro et al. 1998b</xref>).We also found that nest-site characteristics (which should be indicators of nest quality) influence the behavior of Cory's Shearwater males. For instance, males whose nests were deeper and closer to neighbors foraged closer to the colony, suggesting that nests with those characteristics should be of higher quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos3">Ramos et al. 1997</xref>). In fact, deeper nests may permit a more stable environment in the incubation chamber, increase protection of the egg and chick, and should be easier to defend from conspecifics. Changes to nests with better qualities have been reported in species with high nest fidelity, such as Common Guillemot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Harris1">Harris et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Harris2">1997</xref>) and Common Shag (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Potts1">Potts et al. 1980</xref>). Furthermore, Common Guillemot individuals that lost a better quality nest would remain as &ldquo;floaters&rdquo; near their previous breeding site for many years without breeding rather than move into a lower quality nest to breed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Kokko1">Kokko et al. 2004</xref>).Cory's Shearwater are known to have philopatry and high nest fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin3">Mougin et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Thibault1">Thibault 1994</xref>), although not absolute, and increased breeding experience will increase mate and nest-site fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Mougin1">Mougin 2000</xref>). In many species with high nest fidelity, individuals will attempt to breed in a close radius from their previous nest site (e.g., 2 m in Common Guillemots &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Harris1">Harris et al. 1996</xref>&rsqb; and 16 m in Common Shags &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Aebischer1">Aebischer et al. 1995</xref>&rsqb;), increasing competition. Hence, defending a nest with more or closer conspecific neighbors would force previous nest-site owners to invest more resources (i.e. time) in defending them, thereby decreasing the size of their foraging areas and spending more time at the colony.Although it has been suggested that Cory's Shearwaters do not benefit from communal nest defense or physical protection from neighbors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Catry1">Catry et al. 2006</xref>), we suggest that choosing nests closer to conspecific neighbors could represent an advantage to previous nest owners when discerning a specific nest from those closest to it. In fact, high nest fidelity and philopatry could play an important role in increasing the ability to perceive the slight differences between 2 stimuli (i.e. location of a specific nest), thus helping previous breeders to more effectively discern high-quality nests (i.e. deeper nests) within areas of higher nest density. This discrimination capacity (explained by the Weber's Law; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Weber1">Weber 1846</xref>) could therefore increase over time, conferring &ldquo;older&rdquo; individuals with an advantage in the future against recruits and overall newer conspecific males. Moreover, the quality of the habitat and breeding output in higher density areas (i.e. closer to conspecifics) are likely to be higher than those in lower density areas (Coulson 1968), and birds breeding in those are likely to return more frequently from foraging trips to defend their nests.Because we did not find significant correlations between individuals' at-sea behaviors and their quality, we suggest that the at-sea foraging behavior in males is largely the result of competition for nests, highlighting the importance of nest-site quality in Cory's Shearwaters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos3">Ramos et al. 1997</xref>), and possibly other seabirds. Competition for nests in this species is crucial to its breeding success because there seems to be a shortage of nests throughout its distribution range, and about half of the breeding birds lose their eggs during the incubation stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Ramos2">Ramos et al. 2003</xref>). The role of nest-site characteristics in the breeding success of many seabird species has been widely reported, such as in Common Guillemots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Harris2">Harris et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Kokko1">Kokko et al. 2004</xref>), Humboldt Penguins (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spheniscus humboldti</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Paredes1">Paredes and Zavalaga 2001</xref>), Common Shags (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Potts1">Potts et al. 1980</xref>), and Manx Shearwater (<named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple"><italic>Puffinus puffinus</italic></named-content>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-3-265-Thompson1">Thompson 1987</xref>). Our study, however, is the first to link nest-site features with the at-sea behavior of individuals during time of nest competition.In summary, a clear difference in at-sea behavioral patterns expressed by male and female Cory's Shearwaters was observed in the early pre-laying period. Females foraged at a larger spatial scale than males, whose spatial and temporal foraging scale seemed to be constrained by the need to guard the nest against conspecifics during this period. Moreover, some of the observed at-sea behaviors in males, such as the size of the area explored for foraging and the traveling distance from the colony, seemed to be related to changes in the variables that could determine nest quality, such as nest depth and the closeness to conspecific neighbor nests. Our study suggests that the need to defend a good quality nest is an important factor in seabird foraging patterns; therefore, the ability of males to acquire and defend a high quality nest site during the pre-laying period may be important to breeding success in pelagic seabirds.We would like to thank the Instituto da Conserva&ccedil;&atilde;o da Natureza e da Biodiversidade (ICNB) for their support with logistics, especially the wardens of the Reserva Natural da Berlengas. GPS loggers were financed by the EU INTERREG project FAME: The Future of the Atlantic Environment. A.C.W. acknowledges the study grant given by the EMMC-EMAE consortium and the European Commission. V.H.P. acknowledges the post-doctoral grant given by Funda&ccedil;&atilde;o para a Ci&ecirc;ncia e Tecnologia (FCT; SFRH/BPD/63825/2009). The experimental approach was conducted with permission from the Portuguese Government (Institute for the Conservation and Biodiversity). All methods used in this study comply with the current laws of Portugal.