 Conservative and opportunistic settlement strategies in Arctic-breeding shorebirds  Arctic shorebirds in North America: A decade of monitoring  Shared predators and indirect trophic interactions: Lemming cycles and arctic-nesting geese  Impacts of global change on arctic-breeding bird populations and migration  The coastal tundra at Barrow  Arctic Shorebird Demographics Network breeding camp protocol, Version 5, April 2014  Nest predation in relation to snow-cover: A possible factor influencing the start of breeding in shorebirds  Distance to nearest neighbor as a measure of spatial relationships in populations  Return rates of prairie shorebirds: Sex and species differences  Phalarope philopatry  Monitoring Arctic-nesting shorebirds: An international vision for the future  Advanced techniques for modeling avian nest survival  The breeding biology of shorebirds on Bylot Island, Northwest Territories, Canada  Philopatry, nest-site tenacity, and mate fidelity of Semipalmated Plovers  The Red Knot (  Calidris canutus  rufa ) decline in the Western Hemisphere: Is there a lemming connection?  High renesting rates in Arctic-breeding Dunlin (  Calidris alpina  ): A clutch-removal experiment  Explaining bird migration  Nest survival in Dusky Canada Geese (  Branta canadensis  occidentalis ): Use of discrete-time models  Geographic variation in the breeding biology of the Semipalmated Sandpiper  Philopatry, site tenacity, and mate fidelity in the Semipalmated Sandpiper  The influence of snow conditions on the date of breeding of wading birds in north-east Greenland  Mating systems, philopatry and dispersal in birds and mammals  The natal and breeding dispersal of birds  Breeding biology of the Red-necked Pharalope   Phalaropus lobatus   in Finland  Temperature and the biomass of flying midges (Diptera: Chironomidae) in the high Arctic  Breeding ecology and annual cycle adaptations of the Red-backed Sandpiper (  Calidris alpina  ) in Northern Alaska  Differences in population density, territoriality, and food supply of Dunlin on arctic and subarctic tundra  Density, habitat, and the mating system of the Western Sandpiper (  Calidris mauri  )  Food overlap among coexisting sandpipers on northern Alaskan tundra  Ecological zoogeography of North European waders, or Why do so many waders breed in the North?  Effects of mate and site fidelity on nest survival of Western Sandpipers (  Calidris mauri  )  American Golden-Plovers on the Seward Peninsula, Alaska: A new longevity record for the species and other breeding ground observations  Features of breeding biology in Pacific and American Golden-Plovers nesting on the Seward Peninsula, Alaska  Male-biased breeding ground fidelity and longevity in American Golden-Plovers  Linking climate change to lemming cycles  The use of a breeding synchrony index  Return rates of male and female monogamous shorebirds to their breeding grounds  Synchrony in lemming and vole populations in the Canadian Arctic  Comparisons of breeding range structure for Dunlin   Calidris alpina   and Curlew Sandpiper  Calidris ferruginea : Conservative and nomadic tundra waders  Adaptive sleep loss in polygynous Pectoral Sandpipers  Assessing the development of shorebird eggs using the flotation method: Species-specific and generalized regression models  Point counts underestimate the importance of arctic foxes as avian nest predators: Evidence from remote video cameras in Arctic Alaskan oil fields  Using eggshell evidence to determine nest fate of shorebirds  Food as a limit on breeding birds: A life-history perspective  Suggestions for calculating nest success  Undependable breeding conditions in the Red Phalarope  How intensive is intensive enough? Limitations of intensive searching for estimating shorebird nest numbers  Timing of breeding, peak food availability, and effects of mismatch on chick growth in birds nesting in the High Arctic  Lower predation risk for migratory birds at high latitudes  Wader populations at Zackenberg, high-arctic Northeast Greenland, 1996&ndash;2005  Ornithological observations in Northeast Greenland between 74&deg;30&prime; and 76&deg;00&prime; N. lat., 1976  Differences in food abundance cause inter-annual variation in the breeding phenology of High Arctic waders  (2007b). Effects of climate variation on the breeding ecology of Arctic shorebirds  Predevelopment surveys of nesting birds at two sites in the Kuparuk Oilfield, Alaska, 1988&ndash;1992  Body transformations, condition, and survival in Red Knots   Calidris canutus   travelling to breed at Alert, Ellesmere Island, Canada  Survival of the fattest: Body stores on migration and survival in Red Knots   Calidris canutus  islandica   How often do Arctic shorebirds lay replacement clutches?  Sources of variation in clutch size, egg size and clutch completion dates of Semipalmated Plovers in Churchill, Manitoba  Sexual selection, arrival times, philopatry and site fidelity in the polyandrous Spotted Sandpiper  Breeding area fidelity, natal philopatry, and the social systems of sandpipers  A 16-year record of summer birds on Truelove Lowland, Devon Island, Northwest Territories, Canada  Habitat selection, diet, arthropod availability and growth of a moorland wader: The ecology of European Golden Plover   Pluvialis apricaria   chicks  Do global patterns of habitat use and migration strategies co-evolve with relative investments in immunocompetence due to spatial variation in parasite pressure?  High daily energy expenditure of incubating shorebirds on High Arctic tundra: A circumpolar study  Population cycles of lemmings near Barrow, Alaska: A historical review  Ecology and evolution of social organization in Arctic sandpipers  The Birds of North America Online, Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology, Ithaca, NY  Application of small automatic bows for catching birds  Philopatry, site fidelity, dispersal, and survival of Spotted Sandpipers  Mating system and nesting biology of the Red-necked Phalarope   Phalaropus lobatus  : What constrains polyandry?  The influence of mating systems on philopatry: A test with polyandrous Red-necked Phalaropes  Survival of Western Sandpiper broods on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska  Nesting density dynamics and site fidelity of waders on the middle and northern Yamal  The breeding biology of Red-necked Phalaropes   Phalaropus lobatus   at Nome, Alaska  Ecological correlates of mate fidelity in two Arctic-breeding sandpipers  Polyandry, replacement clutches, and site tenacity in the Red Phalarope (  Phalaropus fulicarius  ) at Barrow, Alaska  Breeding site fidelity and natal philopatry in the sex role-reversed Red and Red-necked Phalaropes  Mechanisms promoting higher growth rate in Arctic than in temperate shorebirds  Timing of shorebird migration in relation to prey depletion  Low abundance of King Eider nests during low lemming years in northeast Greenland  Probability of detection of nests and implications for survey design  Effects of nest habitat, food, and parental behavior on shorebird nest success  Inter-annual variation in the breeding chronology of arctic shorebirds: Effects of weather, snow melt and predators  Intraseasonal patterns in shorebird nest survival are related to nest age and defence behaviour  Breeding cycle and population dynamics in the Dunlin (  Calidris alpina  )  Breeding conditions and numbers of birds on Taimyr, 2009: Report of the Wader Monitoring Project on Taimyr  Factors related to breeding production of Brent Geese  Branta b. bernicla  and waders (Charadrii) on the Taimyr Peninsula  The breeding productivity of dark-bellied Brent Geese and Curlew Sandpipers in relation to changes in the numbers of arctic foxes and lemmings on the Taimyr Peninsula, Siberia  Site fidelity and territory establishment in breeding Pacific Golden Plovers and Grey Plovers at Taimyr, Siberia  Site fidelity in High Arctic breeding waders  Population dynamics of breeding shorebirds in Arctic Alaska  Has prey availability for Arctic birds advanced with climate change? Hindcasting the abundance of tundra arthropods using weather and seasonal variation  Breeding of waders (Charadrii) and Brent Geese   Branta bernicla  bernicla  at Pronchishcheva Lake, northeastern Taimyr, Russia, in a peak and a decreasing lemming year  Shifts in caterpillar biomass phenology due to climate change and its impact on the breeding biology of an insectivorous bird  Links between worlds: Unraveling migratory connectivity  Shorebirds seem to have evolved a number of strategies for adapting to and exploiting the unpredictable and inhospitable Arctic environment. Two such strategies put forth by Holmes and Pitelka suggest that species either conservatively or opportunistically select breeding locations based on local environmental conditions. &ldquo;Conservative&rdquo; species were characterized by strong site fidelity and territoriality, consistent population densities, relatively even spacing of individuals, and monogamous mating systems, while &ldquo;opportunistic&rdquo; species exhibited opposite traits and were polygamous. Here, we assessed whether 10 shorebird species consistently exhibited these settlement strategies over a 10-year period (2003&ndash;2012) near Barrow, Alaska, by comparing annual estimates of site fidelity, territoriality, and population density. Additionally, we determined the relative importance of past and current environmental and social conditions in predicting annual breeding densities of these same species. Data from 1,413 captured adults and 1,946 shorebird nests indicated that most species conformed to 1 of the 2 settlement strategies, while others exhibited traits of both strategies, and a few had settlement patterns inconsistent with that predicted for their mating system. We suggest that deviations from these strategies may occur depending on a species' location within its breeding range. For some species, however, described settlement patterns may be too simplistic. Species with the same settlement strategy seem to respond similarly to environmental cues but differently than species with the alternative strategy. However, we were unable to determine a common environmental cue for species with the same settlement strategy, although lemming abundance, overall nest survival rate, and presence of conspecifics or heterospecifics did seem to influence settlement decisions in some species. Results from this study indicate that understanding how species settle may have important consequences for implementing monitoring or conservation actions.  Las aves playeras parecen haber desarrollado una serie de estrategias para adaptarse y explotar el ambiente impredecible e inh&oacute;spito del &Aacute;rtico. Dos de estas estrategias, puestas a consideraci&oacute;n por  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) y  Pitelka et al. (1974) , sugieren que las especies seleccionan los sitios de cr&iacute;a ya sea de modo conservador u oportunista basadas en las condiciones ambientales locales. Las especies &ldquo;conservadoras&rdquo; estuvieron caracterizadas por una fuerte fidelidad al sitio y territorialidad, densidades poblacionales consistentes, esparcimiento relativamente homog&eacute;neo de individuos y sistema de apareamiento mon&oacute;gamo, mientras que las especies &ldquo;oportunistas&rdquo; mostraron rasgos opuestos y fueron pol&iacute;gamas. Aqu&iacute;, evaluamos si 10 especies de aves playeras exhibieron de modo consistente estas estrategias de asentamiento a lo largo de un per&iacute;odo de 10 a&ntilde;os (2003&ndash;2012) cerca de Barrow, Alaska comparando estimaciones anuales de fidelidad al sitio, territorialidad y densidad poblacional. Adicionalmente, determinamos la importancia relativa de las condiciones ambientales y sociales pasadas y presentes para predecir las densidades anuales reproductivas de estas mismas especies. Los datos provenientes de 1.413 adultos capturados y 1.946 nidos de aves playeras indicaron que la mayor&iacute;a de las especies se ajustaron a una de las dos estrategias de asentamiento, mientras que las otras exhibieron rasgos de ambas estrategias, y unas pocas presentaron patrones de asentamiento inconsistentes con lo predicho a partir de sus sistemas de apareamiento. Sugerimos que los desv&iacute;os de estas estrategias pueden darse dependiendo de la localizaci&oacute;n de la especie dentro de su rango de reproducci&oacute;n. Para algunas especies, sin embargo, los patrones de asentamiento descriptos pueden ser simplemente demasiado simplistas. Las especies con la misma estrategia de asentamiento parecen responder de modo similar a las se&ntilde;ales ambientales, pero de modo diferente a las especies con la estrategia alternativa. Sin embargo, no pudimos determinar una se&ntilde;al ambiental &uacute;nica para especies con la misma estrategia de asentamiento, aunque la abundancia de lemmings, la tasa global de supervivencia del nido y la presencia de individuos co- o hetero-espec&iacute;ficos parecen influenciar las decisiones de asentamiento de algunas especies. Los resultados de este estudio indican que entender c&oacute;mo las especies se asientan puede tener consecuencias importantes para implementar acciones de monitoreo o de conservaci&oacute;n.   Palabras clave:  Alaska, Barrow, densidad, estrategia de asentamiento, fidelidad al sitio, nidificaci&oacute;n, tasas de retorno.  The Arctic provides important habitat for numerous avian species, including millions of nesting and migrating shorebirds ( J&auml;rvinen and V&auml;is&auml;nen 1978 ,  Boyd and Madsen 1997 ,  Bart and Johnston 2012 ); &sim;20&percnt; of all shorebird species and 30&percnt; of individual shorebirds breed in the Arctic ( CHASM 2006 ). Long-distance migrations to Arctic regions are thought to benefit shorebirds through lower predation rates ( Gilg and Yoccoz 2010 ,  McKinnon et al. 2010 ), reduced risk of diseases and parasites ( Piersma 1997 ), increased food availability, and longer daylight hours that promote growth of offspring ( Schekkerman et al. 2003 ). However, shorebirds breeding in the Arctic must also cope with unfavorable weather that can be energetically taxing, short breeding seasons, unpredictable breeding environments, and hazards of annual long-distance migrations ( Piersma et al. 2003 ,  Morrison 2006 ,  Morrison et al. 2007 ). Because of these challenges, shorebirds seem to have evolved a number of strategies for adapting to and exploiting the Arctic environment.   Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974)  described 2 such adaptive strategies in relation to how shorebirds settle (i.e. how individuals locate annual nesting locations) within Arctic environments. The first strategy, termed the &ldquo;conservative&rdquo; strategy, was characterized by strong site fidelity and territoriality, consistent population densities at any given location, relatively even spacing of individuals across the landscape within appropriate habitats, and monogamous mating systems. It was hypothesized that by returning to the same breeding locations, conservative species have increased knowledge of the local resources, allowing at least a moderate number of offspring to be produced annually, regardless of local conditions ( Pitelka et al. 1974 ). Conversely, the second strategy, termed the &ldquo;opportunistic&rdquo; strategy, was characterized by opposite traits and a polygamous mating system. By selecting the most favorable annual breeding locations, opportunistic species were hypothesized to have a greater opportunity for more offspring to be produced in some years or locations ( Pitelka et al. 1974 ).  This hypothetical framework has been subsequently supported by a number of studies that relied on marked populations of individual species to document density, territoriality, or annual return rates (see  Oring and Lank 1984 ); however, few studies have documented potential evidence for both strategies in multiple shorebird species breeding at the same location ( Colwell and Oring 1989 ,  Tomkovich and Soloviev 1994 ,  Lappo 1996 ,  Ryabitsev and Alekseeva 1998 ,  Soloviev et al. 2010 ). We are also unaware of any long-term studies where researchers collected data on all traits used to define these 2 settlement strategies (i.e. breeding site fidelity, territoriality, nest density, and mating system) from a community of uniquely identified shorebird species. Such information is needed to validate the existence of these 2 settlement strategies and, if present, to determine if species consistently follow one strategy through time.  Assuming these 2 settlement strategies exist, understanding the local cues individuals use when deciding to settle is important for understanding the evolution and maintenance of these 2 strategies within a species.  Pitelka et al. (1974)  suggested the primary factor responsible for the evolution of these strategies was the amount and dependability of food because invertebrates, the primary food source for shorebirds, can fluctuate in both time and space in Arctic regions, depending on local weather conditions ( Tulp and Schekkerman 2008 ). By association,  Pitelka et al. (1974)  suggested that the timing and rate of snow melt may be the primary cue that individuals of opportunistic species use when making settlement decisions (conservative species should return regardless of conditions). Within the &sim;40 years since this hypothesis was put forth, however, little effort has been made to support or refute it. We suggest that other cues could also be important to individuals of opportunistic species when making settlement decisions, including density of predators and alternative prey, prior reproductive success of shorebirds in the immediate and surrounding areas, and the presence of conspecifics and heterospecifics (see predicted relationships of these variables in  Table 1  and  Figure 1 ).  Predicted effects of environmental, social, and genetic factors on Arctic-breeding shorebird nesting metrics and settlement patterns. Reference letters correspond to effects found in  Figure 1 .  Model of how local environmental, social, and genetic factors may influence annual population densities of shorebirds using conservative and opportunistic settlement strategies. Solid lines indicate an effect in the same year; dashed lines indicate an effect between years. Boxes encapsulate factors used by individuals to determine whether to settle; circles encapsulate demographic characteristics that affect number of adults available, as well as return and settlement rates; and hexagons encapsulate annual populations of shorebirds using different settlement strategies (size indicates predicted relative abundance of each group prior to and after settlement). Collectively the interaction of these terms determines the makeup of the local population and overall density of the shorebird population. Predicted effects can be found in  Table 1 , referenced by letter.  Unlike opportunistic species, conservative species, which exhibit high site fidelity, should be less affected by current local conditions and more affected by factors occurring in prior years (e.g., adult survival, hatching success, and fledgling survival;  Table 1 ,  Figure 1 ). These traits are indicative of the number of individuals that survive and are produced, and thus are capable of returning to a prior breeding site or their natal area. While  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974)  focused mainly on adult site fidelity as the mechanism for consistent annual population densities of conservative species, natal philopatry could also be important, especially in species with high juvenile return rates. For example, annual population densities of Semipalmated Sandpiper (  Calidris pusilla  ), Ruddy Turnstone (  Arenaria interpres  ), and Red Knot (  Calidris canutus  ) have been linked to chick survival in prior years ( Troy 1996 ,  Meltofte 2006 ); however, neither study documented true natal philopatry, but only associations between regional hatching success and population density. We are unaware of any study that has systematically assessed the importance of the many environmental and social factors identified in this study ( Table 1 ;  Figure 1 ) in predicting settlement patterns of multiple shorebird species, although a few studies have investigated 1 or 2 of these factors ( Troy 1996 ,  Meltofte 2006 ,  Soloviev et al. 2010 ).  Using intensive observations of shorebirds and a suite of environmental variables collected near Barrow, Alaska, between 2003 and 2012, we evaluated whether 10 shorebird species exhibited consistent conservative or opportunistic settlement strategies and evaluated the importance of past and current environmental and social conditions in predicting settlement patterns of these same species. Understanding whether these 2 settlement strategies are consistently exhibited by species and are related to environmental and social conditions is invaluable for making management and conservation decisions. For example, biologists may need to adjust monitoring programs to take into account large fluctuations in annual local population densities that are not a reflection of true changes in population size but rather are reflective of local environmental conditions. Similarly, any assessment of conservation actions will need to address predictable changes in population density, especially among opportunistic species.  Assigning species to conservative or opportunistic strategies is an essential first step in this process. In addition, understanding how individuals use environmental and social conditions to make settlement decisions would allow biologists to evaluate how changes in cues may impact species in the future. This evaluation is particularly important to understand as the impacts of climate change on lemmings, invertebrate emergence, and other potential environmental cues become known.  From 2003 to 2012, 7 plots, each 36 ha, were nonrandomly established for shorebird monitoring near Barrow, Alaska ( Figure 2 ). Plots were selected based on previous research activities in the area (e.g., plots 1 and 2 were used for shorebird research in the 1970s), accessibility from the road system, and suitable densities of shorebird nests. The final plots reflected the general diversity of habitat types and species of shorebirds found nesting in the Barrow vicinity. Plots 1&ndash;3 were monitored in all 10 years; plots 4 and 6 were monitored only in 2003 and 2004, respectively; and plots 5 and 7 were monitored from 2004 to 2012 (9 years) and 2005 to 2012 (8 years), respectively. We divided all plots into 144 quadrats (50 &times; 50 m) using wooden stakes placed every 50 m to facilitate data collection. Habitat within the study plots consisted mainly of tundra dominated by sedges, grasses, and moss interspersed with small ponds, creating a mosaic of low, wet marsh habitat and higher, well-drained upland habitat ( Brown et al. 1980 ).  Location of shorebird study plots near Barrow, Alaska, 2003&ndash;2012. Dashed line in plot 7 illustrates eastern plot edge of plot 6 before it was moved to the east to create plot 7.  From 2003 to 2012, we located nests each year using single-person area searches, 2-person rope drags, and opportunistically ( Troy 1996 ,  Naves et al. 2008 ). Area searches consisted of surveyors systematically searching plots and locating nests by following individual birds displaying nest attendance behaviors or, occasionally, by flushing an incubating bird. For all years but 2003, area searches were conducted 4 hours per day by one person, 6 days per week, between early June and early July each year (see  Naves et al. 2008  for search effort through 2006; similar effort was made between 2007 and 2012). In 2003, area searches covered a smaller area within each plot and had longer but less frequent plot visits. In all years, surveyors rotated among plots and recorded their movements daily on maps to facilitate equal coverage of the entire plot. Also, for all years except 2003, surveyors shared information on potential nest locations to maximize nest detections ( Smith et al. 2009 ). In late June&ndash;early July of each year, surveyors also dragged a 35 m rope 1 to 2 times over the plots to flush incubating birds from nests that had not been found. Finally, nests were found opportunistically as researchers trapped birds at nests on the plot. Once a nest was found, we recorded its location using handheld global positioning system (GPS) units (typically within &plusmn;3 m).  We visited nests found with &lt;4 eggs (modal clutch size for all species) daily until clutches were completed or until clutch size remained unchanged for 2 consecutive days. If clutch size remained unchanged from the day the nest was discovered or if a nest was discovered with 4 eggs, we floated eggs to determine incubation stage. We estimated nest initiation dates (i.e. date first egg laid) of nests found during laying by assuming one egg was laid per day, and for nests found during incubation by (1) subtracting a species' incubation period (based on the Birds of North America accounts;  Poole 2005 ) from hatching dates for successful nests or (2) using egg flotation to estimate embryo development ( Liebezeit et al. 2007 ) for unsuccessful nests. Based on nest initiation dates, we determined that 99&percnt; of discovered nests were active for some time between 12 June and 13 July across all years (hereafter called the primary nesting period).  Evidence of hatching and failure was based on criteria developed by the Arctic Shorebird Demographics Network ( Brown et al. 2014 ). Briefly, we checked nests every 3&ndash;5 days until 3&ndash;4 days prior to the estimated hatch date, at which time we checked nests every 2 days until eggs were starred, and daily thereafter. Hatch dates were estimated by adding standard incubation periods to the day the fourth egg was laid or based on egg flotation. We defined a nest as successful when at least one egg hatched ( Mayfield 1975 ). Evidence of hatching included visually locating chicks in or near the nest (&lt;50 m from nest within 2 days of hatching), the breeding pair acting defensive or &ldquo;broody,&rdquo; or presence of small egg shell fragments (1&ndash;5 mm) or egg caps indicative of hatching ( Mabee 1997 ). We considered nests failed when (1) eggs were absent prior to 4 days of estimated hatch date, (2) there were signs of predation (i.e. large egg shell fragments in or near the nest bowl and/or predator sign near nest), (3) there were signs of trampling (i.e. crushed eggs in nest and footprints near or on nest), (4) nests were destroyed by weather (i.e. nest flooded, covered in snow), or (5) eggs were abandoned (i.e. eggs present more than 7 days after estimated hatch date or when eggs were cold and parents did not adjust a repositioned egg within 24 hr). If circumstances at the nest did not match these definitions or evidence was contradictory, we classified the nest fate as unknown. We calculated nest survival rates for each species and year using species-specific incubation periods (based on the Birds of North America accounts;  Poole 2005 ) and previously developed nest survival models in Program MARK (R. B. Lanctot et al. personal communication). Using a similar technique, we also calculated annual nest survival rates for all species combined; however, these estimates were based on a weighted average incubation period for each year (based on the annual number of nests per species). We estimated variances of nest survival rates using the delta method ( Seber 1982 ).  From 2003 to 2012, we captured adult shorebirds on nests using a modified luchock trap (or bow-net;  Priklonsky 1960 ) and marked them with a U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) metal leg band, a unique combination of colored leg bands, and a single dark green flag with ends soldered to reduce band loss. Additionally, we captured chicks by hand in or near nests at hatching and marked them with a USGS metal band and a single color band. For Dunlin (  Calidris alpina  ) chicks, we also attached a dark green flag next to the single color band. Calculations of individual return rates were limited to physical captures of birds on nests and resightings of birds near nests; resightings were individuals observed flushing and returning to marked nests, usually at distances &lt;3 m from observer, with bands easily seen. This approach reduced resighting bias for species whose morphology (e.g., short legs) and behavior (e.g., use of dense vegetation) made bands difficult to see, allowing us to directly compare local site fidelity estimates among species. This metric only provides a minimum return rate, however, because individuals that returned but did not nest or whose nest failed prior to being found would have gone undetected. Because of this, return rates presented in this study are likely lower than those reported in other studies that use resightings away from nest sites to estimate return rates. Furthermore, we present return rates for both sexes in species with biparental care, and only for the incubating sex in species with uniparental care.  From 2008 to 2012, we used 10 pitfall traps to estimate invertebrate biomass within tundra ecosystems throughout the nesting season. In all years, pitfall traps were located near (&lt;200 m) plot 2 and were equally distributed among mesic and xeric tundra habitat types. In 2008 and 2009, we used &ldquo;cup&rdquo; pitfall traps made from &sim;0.5 L clear plastic drinking cups cut to &sim;9 cm in height with an 8 cm diameter. These traps were placed 20 m apart along one transect line (5 traps in mesic habitat and 5 in xeric habitat) at ground level so ambulatory invertebrates would be captured. In 2010&ndash;2012, we used modified &ldquo;Malaise&rdquo; pitfall traps made from &sim;38 &times; 5 &times; 7 cm plastic containers, topped with a 36 &times; 36 cm mesh screen ( Brown et al. 2014 ). These traps were placed 15 m apart along 2 transect lines (one transect in mesic habitat and one in xeric habitat) at ground level so ambulatory invertebrates would be captured. The mesh screen also captured aerial invertebrates that hit the screen and fell into the trap. In 2008&ndash;2009, we sampled traps every other day from late June to early August, while in 2010&ndash;2012 we sampled traps on average every 3 days from early-mid&ndash;June to late July.  In 2008&ndash;2009, we identified all invertebrates &gt;1 mm to family (only Tipulidae) or order and measured the length to the nearest 0.5 mm for individuals &lt;5 mm long and to the nearest 1 mm for individuals &gt;5 mm. In 2010&ndash;2012, individuals were identified to family or order, and length was measured to the nearest 0.25 mm for individuals &lt;2 mm and to the nearest 0.5 mm for individuals &gt;2 mm. We calculated biomass for each individual using published length to biomass equations based on taxa. For each sampling day, we then calculated the total biomass (i.e. sum of each individual biomass) divided by the number of traps and days between sampling to estimate total invertebrate biomass on each day traps were deployed (expressed in mg trap &minus;1  d &minus;1 ).  To account for differences in sampling methodology among years, we developed a correction factor so that data from cup traps used in 2008&ndash;2009 could be compared to data from the Malaise traps used in 2010&ndash;2012. To do this, we installed 5 cup and 5 Malaise traps next to each other on a mesic and xeric transect (20 traps total) in 2013 and collected invertebrates every 3 days from all traps between early June and late July. We then performed a linear regression using daily invertebrate biomass on each sampling day (i.e. total biomass divided by the number of traps and days between sampling) obtained from the 2 sampling methods. The resulting regression equation (y &equals; 0.967x &plus; 2.753;  n  &equals; 15;  r  2  &equals; 0.83) was then used to correct the 2008&ndash;2009 data so that they were directly comparable to later years.  Although we did not directly confirm the diet of shorebirds in this study, previously published studies have determined the importance of both adults and larvae from the families Aranea, Anthomyiidae, Carabidae, Chironomidae, Muscidae, Mycetophilidae, and Tipulidae in the diet of Arctic-breeding shorebirds ( Drury 1961 ,  Holmes and Pitelka 1968 ,  Pearce-Higgins and Yalden 2004 ). Because a large percentage of the biomass in our samples was composed of these taxa, we assumed our sampling accurately represented invertebrates used by nesting shorebirds in this region. Prior to analyses, however, we did remove bees and wasps (Apidae and Hymenoptera) because these taxa have not been described as important in the diet of shorebirds and can result in a large percentage of the biomass if many large-bodied individuals are collected.  From 2003 to 2012, we estimated the percentage of snow cover in 36 quadrats, each 50 &times; 50 m, within each study plot to the nearest 5&percnt; every 2&ndash;5 days until &le;10&percnt; snow cover remained. We estimated the mean percent snow cover over all plots on a given date using the mean snow cover across all quadrats on each plot and then linearly regressed these values through time to determine the date when 50&percnt; snow cover was present on the study area in each year.  From 2003 to 2012, we conducted weekly to biweekly 10-min point counts of avian predators at 3 locations within each survey plot from early June to late July. To minimize bias as a result of predator activity patterns, point counts were conducted at times distributed throughout the day (i.e. 0900 to 1900 AST). Point count locations were 200 m apart and &ge;100 m from the plot edge. During point counts, we documented all avian shorebird nest predators within 300 m of each point count location and used the total number of avian predators observed at all 3 point counts to estimate predator abundance for a given survey at a plot. Effort was made to avoid double counting individuals. We calculated the mean number of avian predators detected during the primary nesting period per plot each year and categorized years into high and low avian predator abundance using natural breaks; 2006, 2007, and 2008 were categorized as high predator years with 7&ndash;9 avian predators detected per survey, and the remaining years were categorized as low predator years with only 3&ndash;5 avian predators detected per survey.  Because predator point counts can underestimate the importance of mammalian predators ( Liebezeit and Zack 2008 ), we used data from an arctic fox (  Vulpes lagopus  ) removal program conducted to enhance Steller's Eider (  Polysticta stelleri  ) productivity (see  Gilsdorf and Rossi 2008 ,  Savory et al. 2009 ,  2010 ,  Bair et al. 2011 ) as an index of mammalian predator levels. Between 2005 and 2012, trappers removed adults and kits at dens and opportunistically shot and trapped adult foxes from mid-late&ndash;May to mid-July across &sim;220 km 2  that included the greater Barrow area and our study plots. Here, we assumed lower fox densities were present when fox removal effort was greater. Yearly efforts varied by duration and areal extent of trapping, number and type of traps deployed, and trap check frequency ( Stevens and Smith 2012 ). We grouped years based on fox removal effort, with 2009 categorized as low, 2005 and 2010 as mid, 2006&ndash;2008 as high, and 2011 and 2012 as very high. No fox removal was conducted in 2003 and 2004, preventing us from evaluating the effect of fox removal during these 2 years. Other mammalian predators, such as short-tailed (  Mustela erminea  ) and least weasels (  M. nivalis  ), were rarely observed and assumed to not influence shorebird settlement patterns.  We noted the presence (2003) and number (2004&ndash;2012) of brown (  Lemmus trimucronatus  ) and collared (  Dicrostonyx groenlandicus  ) lemmings each day; other microtines occur rarely at Barrow ( Pitelka and Batzli 2007 ), and waterfowl numbers are low and the species are noncolonial (D. Safine, personal communication). We standardized daily counts of lemmings among years by dividing the total number of lemmings (both species combined) detected during the primary nesting period in a year by the number of researcher days (i.e. the product of the number of days observations were obtained and the average number of researchers in the field). We categorized years into high, mid, and low categories using natural breaks, with 2008 categorized as a high lemming year with 21 lemmings seen per field crew days; 2006 and 2007 as mid lemming years with 3&ndash;4 lemmings seen per field crew days; and the remaining years as low lemming years with &lt;1 lemming seen per field crew days. Because lemmings were only noted as present or absent on a daily basis in 2003, we characterized this year as a low lemming year because the number of days in which &ge;1 lemming was observed (56&percnt;) fell within the range for years categorized as low lemming years (16&ndash;94&percnt;), but was much lower than years categorized as mid or high lemming years (100&percnt;).  Because search effort and methodology can greatly impact nest detection rates ( McCaffery and Ruthrauff 2004 ,  Smith et al. 2009 ), we restricted our estimates of nest density and internest distances to 2004&ndash;2012 when consistent nest searching effort took place. Data from 2003, however, were used to estimate nest initiation dates, adult and juvenile return rates, shorebird nest survival, and alternative prey levels. We pooled data across plots for all analyses. Unless noted otherwise, we used SAS ( SAS Institute 2008 ) for all statistical analyses and report estimates &plusmn;SE.  We determined whether the pattern of each species' site fidelity, territoriality, and population density matched that predicted by  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974) . Specifically, we predicted that species with conservative settlement strategies would (1) have greater adult site fidelity and natal philopatry, (2) be territorial and therefore exhibit greater nearest internest distances, and (3) have less variability in annual population densities, as indicated by nest densities, compared to species that settled opportunistically. We assumed each species followed the predominant mating system described in the Birds of North America accounts ( Poole 2005 ).   Site fidelity : As a measure of site fidelity, we estimated overall adult return rates by dividing the number of adults captured or observed at nest sites in &ge;1 year following capture by the total number of marked adults from 2003 to 2011. Additionally, we tallied the number of years individual adults of each species were captured or observed at nests after their initial capture year. Because individuals were banded throughout the study and thus could not be detected returning for the same number of years (e.g., individuals banded in 2003 could be detected returning for 9 years, whereas individuals banded in 2011 could be detected for only 1 year), we standardized this value by dividing the number of adults detected in each year category (e.g., 1 year, 2 years, etc.) by the number of adults that were banded at least that many years prior to 2012. We also estimated overall juvenile return rates using similar procedures as that used for adults.   Territoriality : As a measure of territoriality, we calculated the distance to the nearest conspecific nest on each plot within a year using GPS locations and ArcGIS 10.0 (ESRI, Redlands, CA). We included all nests in these analyses regardless of incubation status because all were laid within a short time (typically &gt;80&percnt; within 15 days). Due to the geographic separation of our study plots, we were unable to conduct more formal spatial analyses that take into account annual nest densities and compare observed and expected distributions under spatial randomness (e.g., Clark and Evan's test;  Clark and Evans 1954 ). We limited nearest neighbor distance measurements to situations where at least 2 nests of the same species were present in a plot in a given year, although note that larger internest distances may not accurately represent territoriality for species with low sample sizes because these estimates may be an artifact of just a few nests placed far apart. Internest distances were then combined across plots and years for each species and compared among species using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA).   Population density : As an estimate of population density, we calculated adjusted annual nest densities for each species to account for the number of nests likely missed due to nest failing prior to being found. We adjusted the number of nests using daily survival rates estimated in a previous analysis (R. B. Lanctot et al. personal communication) and the Horvitz-Thompson estimator ( Dinsmore et al. 2002 ). Briefly, we estimated the adjusted number of nests that were initiated on the same day as a found nest by dividing the frequency of each nest (always 1) by the probability that the nest survived until discovery (estimated from the daily survival rate). We then summed these adjusted values to get the number of nests likely present for each species and year. These estimates were then divided by the total survey area, resulting in the adjusted annual nest density for each species. We restricted the estimated number of nests initiated per known nesting event to &le;5 because larger numbers were likely an artifact of underestimating daily survival rates when sample sizes were low (e.g., tail ends of the nesting season;  Grand et al. 2006 ). Virtually all (99&percnt;) of our estimates fell below this cutoff value. Because sample sizes for White-rumped Sandpiper (  Calidris fuscicollis  ) and Buff-breasted Sandpiper (  Tryngites subruficollis  ) were low, we used the mean number of initiated nests estimated based on daily survival rates for the 8 other shorebird species to adjust the number of nests present for these species. We determined how variable population densities for each species were across years by first fitting a linear regression to the adjusted annual nest densities and using the variation in density from this line and the overall mean density to generate a coefficient of variation (CV). This approach allowed us to remove the effects of increasing population levels observed during the time of our study and investigate the remaining annual variability in nest densities among species. Because sample sizes of nests were variable among species, we also report the range of adjusted annual nest densities as a metric for evaluating annual nest density variation among species.  To evaluate the importance of past and current environmental and social conditions on shorebird settlement patterns, we focused on changes in annual nest densities because this measure incorporates information on internest distances, immigration, and site fidelity. To assess whether species were responding to local cues in the same way through time, we first compared adjusted annual nest densities among species using a correlation analysis. A positive correlation among species would suggest species were responding similarly to the same variable(s), although the mechanism for doing so may differ. We then evaluated potential cues ( Table 1 ;  Figure 1 ) individual shorebirds may use when making settlement decisions by evaluating how adjusted annual nest densities vary with changes in these past and current local conditions.   Food availability : To assess the influence of food availability on adjusted annual nest densities, we selected a 10-day period for each species and year that corresponded to the dates that had the most number of broods with chicks &lt;10 days old (i.e. 84&ndash;100&percnt; of nests within species&ndash;year groupings had chicks &lt;10 days old at some time during these selected periods). We chose to focus on food availability during brood-rearing because productivity is likely regulated primarily by chick survival, and invertebrate resources are most important to chicks during the first 10 days after hatch, the time period when they are most vulnerable to starvation and exposure ( McKinnon et al. 2012 ). We used actual hatch dates or estimated hatch dates (see &ldquo;hatching success&rdquo; section above) to generate the number of broods available on each date. We limited these data to individuals nesting on plot 2, which was in close proximity to the location where invertebrates were sampled. Only species with sufficient sample sizes (i.e. &ge;4 nests per year) were included in the analyses. Available food was then calculated for each species and year by summing the total invertebrate biomass on each day within this 10-day period. In one instance (Long-billed Dowitchers &lsqb;  Limnodromus scolopaceus  &rsqb; in 2011), invertebrate data collection ceased 8 days into the selected 10-day period, and we substituted daily biomass values obtained on the last day of collection for the last 2 days. We then compared the relationships between the adjusted annual nest densities for each shorebird species and their 10-day cumulative invertebrate biomass across all years (2008&ndash;2012) using a Spearman's rank correlation analysis. The importance of the relationship of food availability and nest density could not be compared with other environmental variables (see next item) because data were available for only 5 years.   Timing of snow melt, predator abundance, alternative prey abundance, and prior reproductive success of shorebirds in an area : For each species, we compared linear regression models within an information-theoretic framework ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ) to identify which metrics were most likely to predict adjusted annual shorebird nest densities. We developed a candidate set of models consisting of Julian date of 50&percnt; snow cover, predator abundance in the current year, lemming abundances in the current and prior year, species-specific nest survival rate in the year prior (only included for species that had an estimate in all years), and apparent nest survival rate of all species combined from the previous year. Because some species have shown increasing population levels through time, we also included year as a potential explanatory variable and modeled it using a hierarchical approach. Here, we first determined if year had a significant impact on nest density for a given species, as determined by a reduction in the Akaike's information criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ) compared to the intercept-only model. If a significant effect was found, we then included year as an additive effect in all subsequent models; otherwise, year was not added to subsequent models. Because the number of years was low in relation to the number of predictor variables, we were unable to test additive or interactive effects of environmental variables. We used AIC c  to compare candidate models (plausible models occurred when &Delta;AIC c  &lt; 2;  Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). In addition to this analysis, we visually assessed the impact of foxes on adjusted annual nest densities. Because we had only 8 years of data and arctic fox removal was categorized into 5 categories, we were unable to include this variable in the above analysis.   Conspecifics and heterospecifics : To assess whether individuals were using the presence of conspecifics in settlement decisions, we estimated the duration of the laying season for each species and then tested for differences among species using an ANOVA. We predicted that the laying period would be longer in species that settled based on the presence of conspecifics because individuals cuing in on others would by necessity initiate nests later, prolonging the breeding season. We estimated the duration of the nesting season in 3 ways: (1) the difference between nest initiation dates of the first and last laid nests (total length), (2) the difference between the third and first quartile of nest initiation dates (peak), and (3) the proportion of simultaneously fertile females (breeding synchrony;  Kempenaers 1993 ). For the last measure, we defined an 8-day fertile period for each female including 4 days prior to laying the first egg through the day when the last egg was laid (assuming a 4-egg clutch). In some instances, the maximum number of eggs found within a nest was &lt;4; however, because we were unable to determine the causes of reduced clutch sizes (e.g., partial predation or females laying reduced clutches), we assumed that 4 eggs were laid in all nests. For this analysis, we removed species with insufficient sample sizes (i.e. &gt;2 years with no nest detections and &lt;50 nests overall). To determine if species might be using the presence of heterospecifics in settlement decisions, we used an ANOVA to evaluate whether the timing of the laying season (i.e. first quartile and median nest initiation dates) varied among species. As above, analyses were restricted to those species with sufficient sample sizes. We predicted that species using the presence of heterospecifics in settlement decisions would consistently nest later than one or more species.  From 2003 to 2012, we located 1,946 shorebird nests on our study plots, representing 10 species and 3 mating systems ( Table 2 ). From these nests, we captured and banded 1,413 adults and 2,979 chicks. Based on this large number of banded birds, we documented the greatest (&gt;28&percnt;) overall adult return rates for Dunlin and Semipalmated Sandpipers, followed by intermediate rates (12&ndash;18&percnt;) for American Golden-Plover (  Pluvialis dominica  ), Red-necked Phalarope (  Phalaropus lobatus  ), and Red Phalarope (  P. fulicarius  ), and the lowest rates (&lt;1&percnt;) for Western Sandpiper (  Calidris mauri  ), White-rumped Sandpiper, Pectoral Sandpiper ( C. melantos ), Buff-breasted Sandpiper, and Long-billed Dowitcher ( Table 2 ). In addition to high overall adult return rates, adult Semipalmated Sandpipers and Dunlin were observed returning to nest on our study plots for up to 4 and 5 successive years, respectively; most of the remaining species were observed returning for only 1 or 2 successive years, although Buff-breasted Sandpipers, Western Sandpipers, and White-rumped Sandpipers were never observed in subsequent years ( Figure 3 ). Juvenile return rates were extremely low for all species, with only 1 Semipalmated Sandpiper chick ever documented returning to breed on our study plots ( Table 2 , but see table footnote c).  Metrics used to describe settlement strategies among shorebird species nesting near Barrow, Alaska, 2003&ndash;2012.  Number of years individual adult shorebirds returned to nest near Barrow, Alaska, 2004&ndash;2012. Return index values represent the number of individuals that returned for a given number of years divided by the number of individuals that were banded at least that many years (number of years returned does not imply bird returned in consecutive years). Data limited to species in which at least one individual returned in a subsequent year. Species are ordered based on overall settlement patterns, from conservative to opportunistic (see  Table 2 ).  Mean conspecific nearest internest distances varied significantly among species when data were combined across years ( F  &equals; 62.23, df &equals; 8 and 1,799,  P  &lt; 0.001), with American Golden-Plover, Semipalmated Sandpiper, Western Sandpiper, Dunlin, Buff-breasted Sandpiper, and Red-necked Phalarope placing nests farthest apart (&gt;144 m), and Pectoral Sandpiper, Long-billed Dowitcher, and Red Phalarope placing nests closest together (&lt;115 m;  Table 2 ). For almost all species analyzed (with the exception of American Golden-Plover, Semipalmated Sandpiper, and Red-necked Phalarope), annual internest distances were negatively correlated with annual nest densities ( r  &equals; &minus;0.96 to &minus;0.74;  P  values &lt;0.001&ndash;0.035), suggesting that when more birds were present, nests were placed closer together.  After controlling for increasing nest densities during the 10-year study, annual nest densities varied the least (CV &lt; 31) for Dunlin and Red-necked Phalarope; varied intermediately (CV &equals; 47&ndash;93) for American Golden-Plover, Semipalmated Sandpiper, Western Sandpiper, Pectoral Sandpiper, Long-billed Dowitcher, and Red Phalarope; and varied most (CV &gt; 126) for White-rumped Sandpiper and Buff-breasted Sandpiper ( Table 2 ;  Figure 4 ). Pectoral Sandpiper and Red Phalarope exhibited the greatest annual change in nest densities, varying by up to 48&ndash;74 nests km &minus;2  across years; all other species exhibited changes of &lt;34 nests km &minus;2  ( Table 2 ;  Figure 4 ).  Adjusted (solid circle and solid line) and apparent (open circle and dashed line) annual nest densities for shorebird species nesting on standardized plots near Barrow, Alaska, 2004&ndash;2012. Adjusted nest densities take into account the likelihood of a nest not being detected. Species are ordered based on overall settlement patterns, from conservative to opportunistic (see  Table 2 ).  Using the 3 characteristics (i.e. site fidelity, territoriality, and annual variability in population density) described by  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974)  to indicate whether species exhibited conservative or opportunistic settlement strategies, we found that the majority of species tended to conform to 1 of the 2 settlement strategies. Specifically, we found that the monogamous species, Dunlin and Semipalmated Sandpiper, exhibited conservative traits, having the greatest adult return rates, large internest distances indicating territoriality, and low variability in annual nest densities. Conversely, polygamous species, including the Buff-breasted Sandpiper, Red Phalarope, White-rumped Sandpiper, and Pectoral Sandpiper, exhibited opportunistic traits, having low adult return rates, small internest distances suggesting nonterritoriality, and large annual fluctuations in nest densities. Four exceptions to this pattern were noted, however. American Golden-Plover, Western Sandpiper, and Long-billed Dowitcher exhibited more opportunistic traits than expected given their monogamous mating system, and Red-necked Phalarope exhibited more conservative traits than expected given their polyandrous mating system.  We found that, in general, adjusted annual nest densities were positively correlated among species with similar settlement strategies, with few significant correlations between species with different strategies ( Table 3 ;  Figure 4 ). These results indicate that species with the same settlement strategy are responding similarly to the same local conditions but differently than species with the alternate strategy. However, we did not detect any significant correlations between White-rumped Sandpiper, Buff-breasted Sandpiper, Long-billed Dowitcher, or Red-necked Phalarope and any other species, suggesting these species may be responding uniquely to local conditions. Annual nest densities for Pectoral Sandpiper and Red Phalarope were also correlated with annual nest densities of all species combined, indicating that these species were generally responsible for annual fluctuations seen in the overall nest density ( Table 3 ).  Correlation coefficients between adjusted annual nest densities of shorebird species nesting near Barrow, Alaska, 2004&ndash;2012.  Adjusted annual nest density was negatively related to the cumulative invertebrate biomass during the 10-day period corresponding to when the majority of chicks were &lt;10 days old for Long-billed Dowitchers (Spearman's rank correlation coefficient &equals; &minus;1.0,  P  value &lt; 0.001) but unrelated for all other species (all other  P -values &gt; 0.05;  Figure 5 ).  Relationship between adjusted shorebird nest densities and cumulative invertebrate biomass during the 10-day period corresponding to when the majority of chicks were &lt;10 days old near Barrow, Alaska, 2008&ndash;2012. Species are ordered based on overall settlement patterns, from conservative to opportunistic (see  Table 2 ).  We detected positive relationships between adjusted annual nest densities and environmental conditions in 4 of the 10 species in our study ( Table 4 ;  Figures 4  and  6 ). Specifically, we found that Long-billed Dowitchers had greater nest densities in years when lemming abundance was high ( &beta;  &equals; 35.91 &plusmn; 6.82) compared to years with mid ( &beta;  &equals; 14.53 &plusmn; 4.82) and low lemming abundance ( &beta;  &equals; 10.36 &plusmn; 2.78;  Table 4 ;  Figures 4  and  6 ). In addition, lemming abundance in the year prior was positively associated with nest densities in 2 species (Western Sandpiper:  &beta;  high  &equals; 8.62 &plusmn; 2.42,  &beta;  mid  &equals; &minus;1.29 &plusmn; 1.75,  &beta;  low  &equals; &minus;0.50 &plusmn; 1.46; American Golden-Plover:  &beta;  high  &equals; 18.62 &plusmn; 2.68,  &beta;  mid  &equals; 5.76 &plusmn; 1.89,  &beta;  low  &equals; 4.76 &plusmn; 1.09;  Table 4 ;  Figures 4  and  6 ). Because we only had 1 year classified as a high lemming year (2008), however, the effect of this factor on current and subsequent year nest densities requires further study. Additionally, we detected a positive relationship between annual Red-necked Phalarope nest density and the overall nest survival rate in the prior year ( &beta;  &equals; 0.03 &plusmn; 0.01;  Table 4 ;  Figures 4  and  6 ). For all other species, we did not find a significant effect of any environmental variable; the intercept-only model had the lowest AIC c  value.  Linear regression models predicting adjusted annual nest densities of shorebird species nesting near Barrow, Alaska, 2004&ndash;2012. Values correspond to &Delta;AIC c , the difference between a model's AIC c  and the lowest AIC c  value, and in parentheses, the AIC  c   relative weight attributed to the model ( w i  ). Plausible models are indicated with an &ast; (i.e. &Delta;AIC c  &lt; 2).  Annual environmental conditions and nest survival of shorebirds near Barrow, Alaska, 2003&ndash;2012 including ( A ) mean (&plusmn;SE) number of avian predators observed per plot on point counts, ( B ) categorical rankings of fox removal effort, ( C ) number of lemmings observed during incidental surveys per field crew days, ( D ) date of 50&percnt; snow cover (Julian date 150 &equals; 30 May), and ( E ) Program MARK nest survival estimates (&plusmn;SE).  Based on a visual assessment of the impact of foxes on adjusted annual nest densities, no clear relationships were noted between fox removal effort and adjusted annual nest densities for most species. We noted, however, that 4 species (Dunlin, Semipalmated Sandpiper, American Golden-Plover, and Western Sandpiper) had greater nest densities in 2009, a year with low fox removal effort, while 2 species (Red Phalarope and Pectoral Sandpiper) had greater nest densities in 2011 and 2012, years with very high fox removal effort. The reverse relationships were not found for these species, however, making it difficult to evaluate the effect of this factor on current and subsequent year nest densities. Because we only had 8 years of data and 4 fox removal categories, our ability to detect a response was limited.  Two of our 3 measures of nest initiation duration (total length and breeding synchrony) were significantly different among species, with species exhibiting conservative traits tending to nest within a shorter time frame and with greater synchrony than species with opportunistic traits ( Table 5 ;  Figure 7 ). This pattern suggests the presence of conspecifics may be an important cue for the settlement of species with opportunistic traits; however, trends were not always consistent within settlement strategies. For example, Dunlin, a species exhibiting conservative traits, nested over a long time frame, while American Golden-Plover, a species exhibiting both conservative and opportunistic traits, nested with the least synchrony. The presence of heterospecifics as a cue for making settlement decisions seemed more important for species with opportunistic traits. Both measures of nest initiation timing (first quartile and median) were significantly different among species, with species with conservative traits tending to nest earlier than species with opportunistic traits ( Table 5 ;  Figure 7 ). But like above, these patterns were not always consistent within settlement strategies. For example, Red-necked Phalarope, a species with conservative traits, tended to nest later, overlapping with species with opportunistic traits, such as Red Phalarope that nested earlier than expected. Semipalmated Sandpiper and Dunlin nested the earliest ( Table 5 ;  Figure 7 ), suggesting these species were not cuing into the presence of heterospecifics. In contrast, all other species nested later, after other heterospecifics in most years, suggesting they may have been cuing into the presence of heterospecifics ( Table 5 ;  Figure 7 ).  Duration and timing of nest initiation (means across years and standard errors in parentheses) among shorebird species near Barrow, Alaska, 2003&ndash;2012.  F  and  P  values from one-way analysis of variance comparing across species are presented. Means with the same letter for a given nest initiation metric are not significantly different ( P  &gt; 0.05, least square means). Analysis limited to species with &ge;50 nests, and with nests present in &ge;8 years.  Shorebird annual nest initiation dates near Barrow, Alaska, 2004&ndash;2012. Julian date 150 &equals; 30 May. Boundaries of the box plots represent the 25 th  and 75 th  percentile, the line within the box represent the median, error bars above and below box represent the 10 th  and 90 th  percentiles, and open circles represent outliers. Stars correspond to median nest initiation dates for all heterospecifics combined. Species are ordered based on overall settlement patterns, from conservative to opportunistic (see  Table 2 ).  We found that shorebirds breeding near Barrow, Alaska, generally conformed to 1 of the 2 settlement strategies described by  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974) , with monogamous species characterized by a conservative strategy, having greater return rates, consistently spaced out nests, and less annual variability in nest densities. Conversely, polygamous species were characterized by an opportunistic settlement strategy, having lower return rates, clumped nests in high density years, and greater annual variability in nest densities. Contrary to our predictions, however, juvenile return rates were extremely low to nonexistent for all species, even for conservative species for which we predicted natal philopatry might drive greater return rates. These unusually low natal philopatry rates suggest that juvenile Arctic shorebirds breeding in high latitudes may receive additional benefits from settling in unfamiliar areas away from natal sites. Additionally, some species had settlement patterns inconsistent with their mating systems, and some species had traits of both settlement strategies. We suggest that deviation from these strategies may occur as a result of geographic variability in settlement strategies exhibited by a species or simply because the dichotomized settlement patterns are too simplistic.  Geographic variation may exist in settlement strategies of species if the predictability of environmental conditions varies across their breeding range. For example, shorebird species have been documented to have greater site fidelity and nest densities at southern latitudes ( Holmes 1969 ,  Gratto and Cooke 1987 ,  Colwell et al. 1988 ,  Schamel and Tracy 1991 ,  Tomkovich and Soloviev 1994 ,  Ryabitsev and Alekseeva 1998 ,  Sviridova 2000 ,  Klima and Johnson 2005 ). These authors suggest that these latitudinal differences may be due to an increased predictability of resources farther south. Because Barrow is located at the northern extent of many of these species' ranges, site fidelity may be lower compared to more southern regions, which may explain the unexpected tendency toward opportunistic traits seen in American Golden-Plover, whereas in other portions of the species' range, stable nest densities ( Moitoret et al. 1996 ) and greater return rates have been reported (33&ndash;72&percnt;;  Moitoret et al. 1996 ,  Johnson et al. 1997 ,  2001 ,  2007 ,  Klima and Johnson 2005 ). In addition, site fidelity may be lower outside a species' core breeding range ( Tomkovich and Soloviev 1994 ,  Ryabitsev and Alekseeva 1998 ). For example, the low site fidelity and low nest densities observed in Western Sandpipers at Barrow may be due to this site being on the fringe of its breeding range. Indeed, nesting seems sporadic and has been documented only in recent years. These results are likely not representative of the entire population, and several studies within core areas of this species' range have noted consistently high nest densities ( Holmes 1971 ) and high breeding site fidelity (40&ndash;65&percnt;;  Holmes 1971 ,  Sandercock et al. 2000 ,  Johnson and Walters 2008 ) more reflective of a conservative settlement strategy.  Several other species exhibited traits contrary to the settlement pattern predicted by  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974) . For example, Red-necked Phalarope had much greater site fidelity than the closely related Red Phalarope, despite both being (facultatively) polyandrous and presumed to be opportunistic settlers. Biologists in other geographic locations have also noted differences in site fidelity between these 2 species (Red-necked Phalarope, 11&ndash;51&percnt; return;  Reynolds and Cooke 1988 ,  Schamel and Tracy 1991 ,  Moitoret et al. 1996 ,  Sandercock 1997 ; and Red Phalarope: 3&ndash;16&percnt; return;  Schamel and Tracy 1977 ,  1991 ,  Moitoret et al. 1996 ). However, both species have been noted to have variable annual nest densities ( Mayfield 1978 ,  Reynolds 1987 ,  Moitoret et al. 1996 ,  Troy 1996 ) characteristic of an opportunistic settlement pattern. Long-billed Dowitcher also did not conform to the predictions of  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974) ; this species was characterized as having a more opportunistic settlement strategy due to the lack of site fidelity and clumped nesting, despite its monogamous mating system.  Moitoret et al. (1996)  also failed to document any site fidelity in this species. Perhaps the extremely late nesting by this species allows it to settle according to environmental and social cues similar to an opportunistic species, despite having a monogamous mating system. Why this species nests so late is difficult to ascertain but may be due to factors affecting the species away from breeding grounds. For example, this species may form pair bonds prior to arrival on the breeding grounds, allowing pairs more time to select where to breed based on current conditions rather than returning to prior nesting sites that might have poor breeding conditions, thus resulting in later nest initiation dates. Nonetheless, this species remains an enigma because it was the only species that exhibited opportunistic traits despite being monogamous.  Our results suggest that species with similar settlement strategies are using one or more common factors to settle in the Arctic, a supposition supported by the correlation of nest densities among species with similar settlement strategies. Because shorebird species nesting at Barrow, and generally throughout the Arctic, migrate along different flyways to reach different wintering areas throughout the world ( Poole 2005 ), the relevant explanatory factor(s) is likely something present on the breeding grounds ( Troy 1996 ,  Webster et al. 2002 ). However, none of the variables investigated in this study proved to be the common environmental factor that explained annual nest densities among conservative or opportunistic shorebirds. Specifically, we failed to find any evidence for the hypothesis made by  Holmes (1966 ,  1971 ) and  Pitelka et al. (1974)  that food availability plays a role in the settlement patterns of opportunistic species. Unfortunately, we do not know if or how shorebirds assess current and future food availability, and it is possible they use factors not tested in this study.  We did, however, find some support to suggest that other factors were related to nest densities in a few species. For example, we found some evidence supporting the hypothesis that predator abundance influences settlement decisions. While we found no direct effect of predator density on shorebird nest densities, we did find that high lemming abundance correlated with high nest densities of several species. According to the alternative prey hypothesis, shorebird nest survival rates should increase when alternative prey (i.e. lemming) abundance is greater because predators switch to prey upon the more numerous species ( Summers and Underhill 1987 ,  Underhill et al. 1993 ,  Summers et al. 1998 ,  Sittler et al. 2000 ,  B&ecirc;ty et al. 2002 ). Because most shorebird nest failures are a result of predation ( Smith et al. 2007 ,  Liebezeit and Zack 2008 , R. B. Lanctot et al. personal communication), we would expect all species to take advantage of reduced predation rates and occur in greater numbers; however, we documented only greater densities of Long-billed Dowitchers during mid to high lemming years. We did find greater nest densities of conservative species in 2009, a year following the single high lemming year. This 1-year lag in density increase follows the alternative prey hypothesis (see references above), which suggests high lemming years may result in greater recruitment and adult return rates and, thus, greater nest densities of conservative species in subsequent years. Unfortunately, 2009 was also a year with low fox removal effort and high nest failures; therefore, greater nest densities for some species in that year may have been due to greater renesting rates, artificially inflating our nest densities, rather than due to a lag in lemming effects. Because documenting the presence of replacement nests is difficult ( Naves et al. 2008 ,  Gates et al. 2013 ), we do not know the magnitude of this effect.  We failed to find a relationship between annual nest densities and prior reproductive success for most species, with the exception of Red-necked Phalarope, although this species had low nest numbers overall and, thus, increases were not substantial. Why we failed to detect a positive relationship in other species is unclear but could have been caused by cross-seasonal effects, such as high mortality during migration or on wintering grounds, that nullified a prior year's high reproductive success.  We also found evidence that some opportunistic species may use the presence of conspecifics in settlement decisions. The majority of species exhibiting opportunistic traits nested later and over a longer time frame relative to species exhibiting conservative traits, possibly because conservative species arrive earlier, and thus initiate nests earlier, as a result of greater site fidelity and the attendant increased familiarity with resources ( Greenwood 1980 ,  Greenwood and Harvey 1982 ). In contrast, opportunistic species may arrive later as a result of visiting multiple sites before deciding where to settle. The nature of this relationship remains unclear, however, because little is known about prebreeding movements. Additionally, the initiation and synchrony of nesting may be an artifact of where species migrate from, the availability of preferred habitats, and changes in the proportion of older and younger birds in a species in any given year; younger birds have been shown to settle later ( Hild&eacute;n and Vuolanto 1972 ,  Oring and Lank 1982 ,  1984 ). Thus, our results illustrate the potential for opportunistic species to use conspecifics or heterospecifics in settlement decisions; however, more research is needed to further examine these variables and evaluate alternative explanations.  The variation in site-fidelity, territoriality, and population density observed in this study indicates that contemporary monitoring programs used for Arctic-breeding shorebirds may result in biased local population estimates, particularly for opportunistic species. Because established protocols for monitoring Arctic-shorebirds depend primarily on surveying areas only once, the value of a site as well as the local population density may be overestimated or underestimated in any given year, depending on local conditions and annual settlement patterns. Given this, we advise future efforts that monitor Arctic-breeding shorebirds to conduct surveys over the same area for multiple years and incorporate annual variation in population density estimates when possible.  Conservation decisions made by resource managers are also likely to be affected by the settlement strategies employed by shorebirds in the Arctic. Because individuals of some species may breed in different areas each year depending on their suitability, designating sites for protection may be difficult and, at a minimum, need to be sufficiently large to provide suitable habitat in all years. Knowing that lemming abundance may be a potential cue for some species would seem to assist in selecting sites, but, unfortunately, this factor is regulated by weather patterns ( Hodkinson et al. 1996 ,  Krebs et al. 2002 ) that could change drastically under predicted future climate change; for example, fewer regular rodent peaks ( Kausrud et al. 2008 ) are predicted under projected climate change. Viewed at an individual bird level, the absence, moderation, or decoupling of such cues may decrease the ability of individuals to determine the best locations to settle and, consequently, decrease their nest survival and ultimately the overall population size ( Fraser et al. 2013 ).  To better incorporate settlement pattern information into conservation efforts, in-depth studies are needed on Arctic-breeding shorebirds throughout their range relating environmental data and nest densities to determine whether particular cues relate to settlement patterns. For some species (e.g., White-rumped Sandpiper, Baird's Sandpiper &lsqb;  Calidris bairdii  &rsqb;, Purple Sandpiper &lsqb;  C. maritima  &rsqb;, Long-billed Dowitcher), little to no information is available, and for others (e.g., American Golden-Plover, Buff-breasted Sandpiper, phalaropes), information is limited to only a few sites, precluding us from fully understanding settlement patterns for a given species. Fortunately, data on shorebirds and environmental factors are currently being collected throughout the Arctic as part of the Arctic Shorebird Demographics Network ( Brown et al. 2014 ). Additionally, information should be collected on other potential cues not presented here (e.g., migration strategies, migration distances, energy reserves, and habitat conditions) that Arctic-breeding shorebirds may use when making settlement decisions. Regardless of how much data become available on shorebirds and the environment in the Arctic, however, shorebirds are also likely influenced by environmental conditions outside the Arctic ( Webster et al. 2002 ), requiring a lifecycle approach for understanding settlement patterns.  We thank the many field assistants that helped on this project throughout the years, especially graduate students Brooke Hill, River Gates, Audrey Taylor, Andy Doll, Jenny Cunningham, and Kirsten Grond. We thank Robert Wisseman and Aquatic Biology Associates, Inc. (Corvallis, Oregon) for invertebrate analysis. Logistical support was provided by the Barrow Arctic Science Consortium and the Umiaq, LLC. The Ukpea&gdot;vik I&ntilde;upiat Corporation and the North Slope Borough kindly permitted us to conduct this research on their lands. The Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, Wildlife Services (Palmer, Alaska) provided unpublished information on their efforts to remove arctic foxes each year. Paul Smith, Bart Kempenaers, and 3 anonymous reviewers provided constructive criticisms of the manuscript that improved it greatly.   Funding statement:  Funding for this study was provided by the Arctic Landscape Conservation Cooperative, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Region 7 Migratory Bird Management Division), Bureau of Land Management (Fairbanks District Office), University of Alaska Fairbanks, University of Colorado Denver, Kansas State University, and the University of Missouri Columbia.   Ethics statement:  The findings and conclusions in this article are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily represent the views of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. 