Comparing models of Red Knot population dynamicsRed Knot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content></italic>)Rapid population decline in Red Knots: Fitness consequences of decreased refueling rates and late arrival in Delaware BayIndirect effects of lemming cycles on sandpiper dynamics: 50 years of counts from southern SwedenThe Red Knot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content> rufa</italic>) decline in the western hemisphere: Is there a lemming connection?Accuracy and variation in estimates of large numbers of birds by individual observers using an aerial survey simulatorA Bayesian approach to stock assessment and harvest decisions using the sampling/importance resampling algorithmDemographic consequences of migratory stopover: Linking Red Knot survival to horseshoe crab spawning abundanceDeveloping objectives with multiple stakeholders: Adaptive management of horseshoe crabs and Red Knots in the Delaware BayIncorporating parametric uncertainty into population viability analysis modelsMultispecies model for adaptive management of horseshoe crabs and Red Knots in Delaware BayAdaptive harvest management of North American waterfowl populations: A brief history and future prospectsTen heuristics for interdisciplinary modeling projectsEffects of horseshoe crab harvest in Delaware Bay on Red Knots: Are harvest restrictions working?Visibility bias in aerial surveys: A review of estimation proceduresDiet selection in Arctic lemmings (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lemmus sibiricus</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dicrostonyx groenlandicus</named-content></italic>): Demography, home range, and habitat useAn approximate Bayesian computation approach to parameter estimation in a stochastic stage-structured population modelEvaluating a multispecies adaptive management framework: Must uncertainty impede effective decision-making?A pragmatic approach to modeling for wildlife managementPredation may link the cycles of lemmings and birdsAn age-structured population model for horseshoe crabs in the Delaware Bay area to assess harvest and egg availability for shorebirdsPredictive population modeling contributes to our basic scientific understanding of population dynamics, but can also inform management decisions by evaluating alternative actions in virtual environments. Quantitative models mathematically reflect scientific hypotheses about how a system functions. In Delaware Bay, mid-Atlantic Coast, USA, to more effectively manage horseshoe crab (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Limulus polyphemus</named-content></italic>) harvests and protect Red Knot (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content> rufa</italic>) populations, models are used to compare harvest actions and predict the impacts on crab and knot populations. Management has been chiefly driven by the core hypothesis that horseshoe crab egg abundance governs the survival and reproduction of migrating Red Knots that stopover in the Bay during spring migration. However, recently, hypotheses proposing that knot dynamics are governed by cyclical lemming dynamics garnered some support in data analyses. In this paper, I present alternative models of Red Knot population dynamics to reflect alternative hypotheses. Using 2 models with different lemming population cycle lengths and 2 models with different horseshoe crab effects, I project the knot population into the future under environmental stochasticity and parametric uncertainty with each model. I then compare each model's predictions to 10 yr of population monitoring from Delaware Bay. Using Bayes' theorem and model weight updating, models can accrue weight or support for one or another hypothesis of population dynamics. With 4 models of Red Knot population dynamics and only 10 yr of data, no hypothesis clearly predicted population count data better than another. The collapsed lemming cycle model performed best, accruing ~35&percnt; of the model weight, followed closely by the horseshoe crab egg abundance model, which accrued ~30&percnt; of the weight. The models that predicted no decline or stable populations (i.e. the 4-yr lemming cycle model and the weak horseshoe crab effect model) were the most weakly supported.El modelado predictivo poblacional aporta al conocimiento cient&iacute;fico b&aacute;sico de la din&aacute;mica de las poblaciones pero tambi&eacute;n puede guiar las decisiones de manejo mediante la evaluaci&oacute;n de acciones alternativas en ambientes virtuales. Los modelos cuantitativos reflejan matem&aacute;ticamente las hip&oacute;tesis cient&iacute;ficas sobre c&oacute;mo funciona un sistema. En la Bah&iacute;a de Delaware, para manejar m&aacute;s eficientemente la cosecha del cangrejo <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Limulus polyphemus</named-content></italic> y proteger a las poblaciones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content> rufa</italic>, se usan los modelos para comparar las acciones de conservaci&oacute;n y predecir los impactos en las poblaciones de cangrejos y de <italic>C. c. rufa</italic>. El manejo ha sido impulsado principalmente por la hip&oacute;tesis central de que la abundancia de huevos del cangrejo determina la supervivencia y la reproducci&oacute;n de los individuos migratorios de <italic>C. c. rufa</italic> que se detienen en la bah&iacute;a durante la migraci&oacute;n de primavera. Sin embargo, han surgido hip&oacute;tesis recientes que proponen que la din&aacute;mica de los individuos de <italic>C. c. rufa</italic> est&aacute; determinada por la din&aacute;mica c&iacute;clica de los leming, las cuales han obtenido cierto apoyo a partir del an&aacute;lisis de los datos. En este trabajo, presento modelos alternativos de la din&aacute;mica poblacional de <italic>C. c. rufa</italic> para reflejar hip&oacute;tesis alternativas. Usando dos modelos con diferentes longitudes de los ciclos de los leming y dos modelos con diferentes efectos de los cangrejos, proyecto la poblaci&oacute;n hacia el futuro bajo escenarios de estocasticidad ambiental e incertidumbre param&eacute;trica con cada modelo. Luego comparo las predicciones de cada modelo con 10 a&ntilde;os de seguimiento poblacional en la Bah&iacute;a de Delaware. Usando el teorema de Bayes y actualizando el peso del modelo, los modelos pueden acumular peso o apoyo para una u otra hip&oacute;tesis. Con cuatro modelos sobre la din&aacute;mica poblacional de <italic>C. c. rufa</italic> y solo 10 a&ntilde;os de datos, ninguna hip&oacute;tesis predice claramente mejor que otra los datos de los conteos poblacionales. El modelo de colapso de la din&aacute;mica c&iacute;clica de los leming presenta en mejor desempe&ntilde;o, acumulando ~35&percnt; del peso del modelo, seguido de cerca por el modelo de la abundancia de los huevos del cangrejo que acumula ~30&percnt; del peso. Los modelos que predicen que no hay una disminuci&oacute;n o que las poblaciones son estables (i.e., un modelo del ciclo de 4 a&ntilde;os del leming, o el modelo de un efecto menor del cangrejo) fueron los que contaron con menor apoyo.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> actualizaci&oacute;n del peso del modelo bayesiano, <italic>Caldris canutus</italic>, ciclos de los leming, modelado poblacionalIn the fields of ecology and ecological management, system models reflect scientific hypotheses about how systems function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Starfield1">Starfield 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Williams1">Williams et al. 2002</xref>). Formalizing our hypotheses into system models can facilitate predictions about how the system will respond to environmental perturbations and management actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Starfield1">Starfield 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Nicolson1">Nicholson et al. 2002</xref>). Building predictive models can contribute to our basic scientific understanding of ecological dynamics, and can also inform management decisions by evaluating alternative actions in virtual environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Starfield1">Starfield 1997</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Baker2">Baker et al. (2004)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Sweka1">Sweka et al. (2007)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref> developed models to inform the management of a complex ecological system in Delaware Bay on the mid-Atlantic Coast of the United States involving a harvested horseshoe crab (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Limulus polyphemus</named-content></italic>) population and migratory Red Knots (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content> rufa</italic>; hereafter, Red Knot or knot). The models were used to predict Red Knot population viability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Baker2">Baker et al. 2004</xref>) and to compare harvest actions and predict the effects on crab and knot populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Sweka1">Sweka et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>). Harvest management decisions in Delaware Bay have been chiefly driven by the core hypothesis that horseshoe crab egg abundance governs Red Knot weight gain during migratory stopover, and that Red Knot annual survival and reproduction are dependent on weight gain during stopover in Delaware Bay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Niles1">Niles et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan4">McGowan et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">2011a</xref>). However, multistate mark&ndash;recapture and mark&ndash;resight analyses concluded that although horseshoe crab spawning abundance does affect knot weight gain in Delaware Bay, stopover departure weight only weakly affects annual survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan1">McGowan et al. 2011b</xref>). These results led to significant uncertainty in population dynamics, and the Delaware Bay Adaptive Management Plan incorporated multiple system models to account for this ecological uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan4">McGowan et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>).Adding further complication to management decision-making, recently, a hypothesis proposing that knot dynamics are governed by cyclical lemming (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lemmus sibiricus</named-content></italic> and/or <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dicrostonyx groenlandicus</named-content></italic>) dynamics has emerged and garnered some support in data analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> postulated that lemming population abundance historically exhibited cyclical peaks and troughs that may have corresponded with precipitation cycles in the Arctic, i.e. that heavy snow depths in the winter and early spring provided sufficient cover and protection for lemmings and elevated their survival and recruitment. Thus, in years with very high lemming abundance (i.e. following heavy winter and spring snowfall), predators in the Arctic (e.g., Arctic foxes &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vulpes lagopus</named-content></italic>&rsqb; and Snowy Owls &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bubo scandiacus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) that might normally eat shorebird eggs and chicks could easily meet their energetic requirements eating only lemmings, and therefore migratory birds and their nests may have much lower predation pressure. This hypothesis has not been confirmed, and the mechanism(s) driving lemming cycles as well as the prey-switching behavior of Arctic predators is still uncertain. However, the hypothesis has been supported for other species of shorebird in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Blomqvist1">Blomqvist et al. 2002</xref>) and for other Arctic-nesting bird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Sutherland1">Sutherland 1988</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> found that Red Knot population counts exhibited cyclical peaks and troughs every ~3&ndash;4 yr that were 2 yr out of step with lemming cycles (because Red Knots have delayed maturation, we would expect to see elevated recruitment to the breeding population 2 yr after a lemming boom in the Arctic; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. 2012</xref>). The study was not fully conclusive because the time series of available data was not long enough; however, it did find some evidence to support the hypothesis. The study also concluded that lemming cycles ceased or were at least dampened in magnitude beginning in the late 1990s, just prior to significant Red Knot population declines.We are left with competing hypotheses to explain Red Knot population dynamics, each with some empirical support. In an adaptive management framework, multiple models can be used concurrently to provide weighted predictions, collectively leading to optimal management actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Williams1">Williams et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Williams2">2007</xref>). Bayes' theorem is used to update model weights depending upon how the system responds to management compared with the individual model predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Williams1">Williams et al. 2002</xref>, Nichols 2007, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>). In this paper, I use a similar process to compare simulated data from competing models of Red Knot population dynamics with observed population count data from Delaware Bay. I used 2 versions of the model from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref>, 1 with a strong survival effect and 1 with a weak survival effect of horseshoe crab abundance on knots, because they have been applied to the existing adaptive management framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>). I further developed a model to reflect the hypothesis that recruitment is related to Arctic precipitation cycles because it has been proposed as an alternative model of Red Knot population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. 2012</xref>). I used simulated data from these models and compared simulated data with empirical count data from Delaware Bay, using Bayes' theorem to allow model weights to evolve over time depending on how accurately each model corresponded with the observed data. At the end of the time series of observed data, each model has had the opportunity to accrue weight, and if one or more models performs better than others, we can learn about Red Knot population dynamics. As weight accrues on a model over time, we can conclude that the data support the hypothesis that the model represents.In the projection model, adult annual survival rates (<italic>S<sup>A</sup></italic>) were drawn from a beta distribution, where the mean and standard error were set to 0.91 and 0.02, respectively, based on mark&ndash;resight survival analyses reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan1">McGowan et al. (2011b)</xref>. I incorporated parametric uncertainty for survival rates into the model by including sampling variance (variance &equals; 0.02) in the model as recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan3">McGowan et al. (2011c)</xref>. There are no empirical estimates of immature or first-year survival rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Niles2">Niles et al. 2008</xref>); in any given year of the simulations, immature survival rates were set at 85&percnt; of adult survival (i.e. <inline-formula id="i0010-5422-117-4-494-ilm02"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-117-4-494-ilm02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>), and first-year survival rates were set at 65&percnt; of adult survival (i.e. <inline-formula id="i0010-5422-117-4-494-ilm03"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0010-5422-117-4-494-ilm03.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>), following the approach used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref>.In the projection model, fecundity was dependent on a binomially distributed randomization function (<italic>Q</italic><sub>t</sub> &equals; <italic>binomial</italic>(f)) that returned a 0 or a 1 with a probability determined by <italic>f</italic>. The term <italic>f</italic> could be modified in the model code to manipulate the frequency with which the binomial function returned a 1, and I ran simulations where <italic>f</italic> &equals; 0.25, 0.18, 0.10, and 0.05 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f01">Figure 1</xref>). If the function <italic>Q</italic> was equal to 1, it was a lemming boom year, which meant that Red Knot fecundity was high, averaging 0.90 (&plusmn; 0.22 SD), and if <italic>Q</italic> was equal to 0, it was a low lemming density year and Red Knot fecundity was low, averaging 0.05 (&plusmn; 0.01 SD). These fecundity values were not based on empirical estimates of Red Knot productivity, but rather were chosen so that when <italic>f</italic> was equal to 0.25 (i.e. on average 1 out of every 4 yr was a lemming boom year), Red Knot population growth was stable to slightly increasing over time. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> hypothesized that Red Knot populations are regulated by lemming population cycles that historically exhibited 3&ndash;4-yr periodicity. Therefore, the model and the fecundity input values were designed to have a stable or slightly increasing knot population under a 4-yr lemming cycle. The low-productivity year was set at 0.05 to mimic the low productivity rate used in previous modeling efforts by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref>, in which birds that did not gain enough mass in Delaware Bay had very low reproductive success. I set this number greater than 0.0 to allow for the fact that some reproduction might occur in those years. There is very little empirical data on Red Knot productivity in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Niles2">Niles et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. 2011a</xref>), and the studies that have been published have very low sample sizes. All simulation models were developed and run in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2011</xref>).Abundance trajectories of Red Knots modeled with 4-, 6-, 10-, and 20-yr breeding cycles compared with observed count data from aerial surveys in Delaware Bay, mid-Atlantic coast, USA, during the spring migratory stopover from 1998 to 2008.As noted earlier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Baker2">Baker et al. (2004)</xref> developed and published Red Knot population models linking Red Knot population dynamics to horseshoe crab populations and management in Delaware Bay, which also were prebreeding projection models. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Baker2">Baker et al. (2004)</xref> postulated that there were severe survival consequences of birds not acquiring sufficient mass (&ge;180 g) during stopover in the Delaware Bay estuary on northward migration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan1">McGowan et al. (2011b)</xref>, through mark&ndash;recapture analyses, found that survival for birds above and below the 180 g mass threshold was similar, and postulated that horseshoe crabs could affect migrating knot populations by reducing or eliminating the fecundity of birds that failed to attain the 180 g mass threshold. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref> simulated both regulatory mechanisms to evaluate harvest strategies, but made no judgments as to which model more effectively reflected Red Knot population dynamics. Here, I used 2 parameterizations of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref> model, 1 with a strong survival effect and 1 with a weak survival effect of horseshoe crabs, to produce 2 sets of simulation data reflecting 2 different models of the system. In the strong survival effect model, survival of birds that exceeded 180 g during stopover in Delaware Bay was on average 0.92, and survival of birds that did not reach the 180 g mass threshold was 0.72. In the weak survival effect model, survival of birds that exceeded 180 g during stopover in Delaware Bay was on average 0.92, and survival of birds that did not reach the 180 g mass threshold was 0.89. The proportion of birds in the population that reached the mass threshold in both models was a function of horseshoe crab abundance taken from a horseshoe crab projection model. In these simulations I used the same parameter estimates and variance structure described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. (2011a)</xref>. I applied the known harvest rates to the crab population for the years 1997&ndash;2012 to virtually re-create the period spanning the available count data from Delaware Bay.I used population size and rate of change from the simulation models to compare simulated data with the statistical distribution for observed population change taken from Delaware Bay population count data. I assigned each model an initial model weight, and used Bayes' theorem to update model weights at each annual time step given the comparison of predicted model trajectories with observed data. This retrospective analysis is similar to model weight updating in adaptive management contexts (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Nichols1">Nichols et al. 2007</xref>), but here I used observed historical data to evaluate projection models. I used 4 competing models: (1) a 4-yr cyclical productivity model (on average, 1 out of every 4 yr was a good Red Knot breeding year); (2) a 10-yr cyclical productivity model (on average, 1 out of every 10 yr was a good Red Knot productivity year); (3) a strong survival effect of horseshoe crabs model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. 2011a</xref>); and (4) A weak survival effect of horseshoe crabs model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan5">McGowan et al. 2011a</xref>). I initially assigned equal weight to all models (i.e. <italic>w<sub>i</sub> &equals;</italic> 0.25). I ran each model 100 times, and calculated the rate of change for each year in each replication. For informing the Bayesian updating, I used 2 approaches: (1) I calculated the 3-yr running average rate of change and 3-yr standard deviation for each iteration under each model; and (2) I used single-year rates of change and the overall standard deviation for all 10 yr of data to create the distribution of rate of change each year. I used the 3-yr running average for 2 primary reasons: (1) to dampen the effect of year-to-year changes in observed data due to counting error during Delaware Bay aerial surveys on model weight updating; and (2) because the observed data were from aerial survey counts in Delaware Bay, with no reported variance estimates or standard deviations. Using the 3-yr average allowed me to calculate a standard deviation and therefore a statistical distribution for the observed abundance for use in Bayesian model weight updating. In the single-year rate of change analysis, I used the overall standard deviation from all 10 yr of data to create the statistical distribution for the Bayesian model weight updating. For each model, I had a set of 100 3-yr running average population growth rates and a set of 100 single-year population growth rates. The observed data represent one single population trajectory; therefore, using individual replicated modeled trajectories allowed for equivalent comparisons between simulated data and observed data.Evolving model weights, starting with equal weight and updated annually using Bayes' theorem, of 4 competing models in comparison with the observed 3-yr running average rate of Red Knot population change over 10 yr (1998&ndash;2008) in Delaware Bay, mid-Atlantic coast, USA. The 4 models are: 4-yr cyclical productivity of knots; 10-yr cyclical productivity of knots; a strong horseshoe crab effect on Red Knot survival; and a weak horseshoe crab effect on Red Knot survival.Evolving model weights, starting with equal weight and updated annually using Bayes' theorem, of 4 competing models in comparison with the observed single-year rate of Red Knot population change over 10 yr (1998&ndash;2008) in Delaware Bay, mid-Atlantic coast, USA. The 4 models are: 4-yr cyclical productivity of knots; 10-yr cyclical productivity of knots; a strong horseshoe crab effect on Red Knot survival; and a weak horseshoe crab effect on Red Knot survival.Prior model weight refers to the previous year's model weight, and posterior model weight refers to the successive year's model weight. In this equation, the posterior model weight is a function of the probability of observing the simulated data from model <italic>i</italic> given the statistical distribution of the empirical data, multiplied by the prior probability of simulation model <italic>i</italic> (i.e. the prior model weight).Median population trajectories indicated that with a boom productivity year occurring on average 1 out of every 4 yr (<italic>f</italic> &equals; 0.25), the population would increase 15&percnt; over 20 yr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f01">Figure 1</xref>). When the boom productivity frequency was extended to 1 out of every 6 yr (<italic>f</italic> &equals; 0.18), the median population trajectory declined 30&percnt; over 20 yr. When the boom productivity frequency was further extended to 1 out of every 10 yr (<italic>f</italic> &equals; 0.10), the median population trajectory declined by 51&percnt; over 20 yr, and the median trajectory declined by over 65&percnt; when the boom frequency was extended to 1 out of every 20 yr (<italic>f</italic> &equals; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f01">Figure 1</xref>).Comparing the 4 competing models of Red Knot population dynamics with the observed data from aerial counts in Delaware Bay, model weights did evolve over time. The results of the 3-yr running average analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>) and the single-year analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f03">Figure 3</xref>) were very similar, although the single-year analysis exhibited more variability in model weight from year to year. Compared with just the 10 yr of observed count data reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Niles2">Niles et al. (2008)</xref> and starting with equal weight for all 4 models, model 4, the weak horseshoe crab survival effect model, initially lost model weight and remained lower than the other 3 models for most or all of the duration of the time series (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f03">3</xref>). Model 1, the 4-yr cyclical productivity model, exhibited a similar pattern of model weight loss as model 4 in the single-year analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f03">Figure 3</xref>), and lost model weight, but not as steeply as model 4, in the 3-yr running average analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Model 2, the 10-yr cyclical productivity model, and model 3, the strong horseshoe crab survival effect model, initially gained weight in both model weight updating analyses and retained that weight over the duration of the analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f03">3</xref>). At the end of the time series, model 2 had the most support, with over 33.9&percnt; of the model weight among the 4 models in the 3-yr running average analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>) and 34.6&percnt; of the model weight in the single-year analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Combined, models 2 and 3 had &gt;60&percnt; of the model weight after 10 yr of model weight updating under each analysis. There was large variation in the model weights across simulation replicates. For example, using the 3-yr running average analysis, at year 10 the standard deviation for the model weight of model 1 was 0.246 and the standard deviation for the model weight of model 2 was 0.365.My analysis found some support for the knot cyclical productivity model with a 10-yr cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>). While not fully conclusive, this result is consistent with the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> hypothesis that some aspect of Arctic precipitation cycles, which were diminished in magnitude or even eliminated in the Red Knot's breeding range throughout the 2000s, drive Red Knot abundance and population growth. At the very least, we can conclude that a reproductive collapse model (i.e. a 10-yr interval between boom productivity events) can explain the observed decline in Red Knot abundance. Both models that accrued weight over time showed strong declines in Red Knot abundance, but the disrupted cyclical breeding model (model 2) gained slightly more weight under the 3-yr running average analysis because the individual trajectories occasionally exhibited interannual increases, as did the observed data in some years, whereas the horseshoe crab strong survival effect model trajectories did not. The simulation analyses demonstrated that extending the mean interval between productivity booms from just 4 to 6 yr could take a population from an increasing trajectory to one that declined by 30&percnt; over 20 yr. Extending the mean productivity boom to 20-yr intervals led to a &gt;60&percnt; population decline over 20 yr. Observed aerial counts over the period of 1998&ndash;2008 showed a nearly 70&percnt; decline in Red Knot peak counts in Delaware Bay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Niles2">Niles et al. 2008</xref>). While the observed counts declined further and faster than the median 10-yr or 20-yr productivity boom model trajectories, the count data were subject to observer error, and comparing specific abundances directly may not be appropriate given uncertainty in observed data (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Pollock1">Pollock and Kendall 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Frederick1">Frederick et al. 2003</xref>). Regardless, this model indicates that it is possible to reverse a positive population trend with even just a 2-yr extension of mean frequency of boom productivity (i.e. a 6-year cycle), and that a 6-yr extension (i.e. a 10-yr cycle) is capable of producing precipitous declines. The horseshoe crab strong survival effect model also produced a precipitous knot population decline, but the 10-yr productivity boom cycle model garnered more weight in the model weight updating analysis of the 3-yr running average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>).It should be noted that even though Red Knots and lemmings have extensive range overlap in the Canadian Arctic, the 2 species utilize very different habitats during the breeding season (P. Smith personal communication). Knots tend to nest in the dry, sparsely vegetated uplands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Baker1">Baker et al. 2013</xref>), and lemmings tend to inhabit coastal lowlands or areas with denser vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Rodgers1">Rodgers and Lewis 1986</xref>). Given this habitat differentiation, lemmings may not have an effect (via predators) on knots as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> speculated. It is possible for wide-ranging mobile predators to move from the uplands to the lowlands in years of extremely high lemming abundance. However, the model that I built here does not detail the ecological mechanism that drives Red Knot cyclical productivity booms, but rather applies a simple binomial probability trial that dictates annual productivity. In these simulations there could be any number of reasons for the cyclical productivity. Knots and lemmings and their predators may have completely independent dependencies on the same climatic precipitation cycles, but the species may not influence each other. The independent, yet temporally linked, climatic dependencies may appear to be linked in statistical analyses, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> demonstrated, simply because they depend on the same precipitation cycle for different reasons.Regardless, the Bayesian model weight updating analysis found some support for the 10-yr cyclical productivity model. The model gained and retained the most weight among the 4 competing models in the analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Focusing on the 3-yr running average analysis, which attempted to dampen the variability caused by observation error in aerial counts, the results indicated that, among the 4 models tested, the 10-yr cycle model, followed closely by the strong survival effect of horseshoe crabs model, outperformed the other models when evaluated in relation to observed abundance counts in Delaware Bay. The analysis could be greatly improved with additional years of monitoring data and further Bayesian model weight updating, and perhaps with additional models exploring different productivity boom frequencies. The model set could also be expanded to include models that combine horseshoe crab effects and extended interval cyclical productivity, since there is no reason to believe that these hypotheses are mutually exclusive. Further, it may be helpful to model the effects of Arctic conditions on adult survival because <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan1">McGowan et al. (2011b)</xref> found strong correlations between Arctic snow depth and annual Red Knot survival, potentially suggesting an additional link to lemming populations and prey switching by Arctic predators. Further empirical research, perhaps studying nesting and Red Knot breeding biology directly in the Arctic, may be warranted to fully understand Red Knot breeding ecology, its relation to precipitation cycles, its effect on population viability, and, perhaps most importantly, management strategies for conserving this migratory species. Questions remain as to what specific aspects of Arctic ecology drive Red Knot productivity and what about those ecosystems has changed since 1998, potentially leading to Red Knot population collapse.The results of this analysis could be used to update and improve the adaptive management plan for Delaware Bay horseshoe crab harvests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan4">McGowan et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan2">2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>). Adaptive management plans often include a double loop process that enables managers to reevaluate and update all parts of the adaptive management plan (e.g., objective functions, system models, and management actions) after several successive years of plan implementation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Williams2">Williams et al. 2007</xref>). It may be prudent to incorporate a long-period cyclical productivity model of Red Knot population dynamics into the Delaware Bay horseshoe crab harvest adaptive management plan. Currently, the management plan includes a &ldquo;no effect&rdquo; model, with no interaction between Red Knots and horseshoe crabs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McGowan4">McGowan et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>), and that model predicts a stable or increasing population of Red Knots regardless of crab harvest management. The two stable or increasing trend models received minimal support in this current analysis. A cyclical productivity model with an extended periodicity would behave similarly with respect to horseshoe crab harvest management effects on knots, but would also include some probability of significant population decline, which the existing no effect model does not predict (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Smith1">Smith et al. 2013</xref>).With this analysis, I was able to quantitatively formalize existing hypotheses regarding Red Knot population dynamics. Formalizing these hypotheses as competing models of population dynamics allowed for an explicit evaluation of model performance compared with observed data. A process like this can simultaneously inform conservation and management of species or ecosystems and give insight into the basic underlying functioning of the ecological system. Even though the cyclical productivity model was relatively simple, by using a binomial probability function to represent Arctic dynamics, instead of the full and complex lemming population model or an Arctic predator population model, the model development and analysis gave some insight into Red Knot ecology and conservation. This analysis is similar to a sampling&ndash;importance resampling analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-McAllister1">McAllister et al. 1994</xref>) or to approximate Bayesian computation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Scranton1">Scranton et al. 2014</xref>). Both use a Bayesian framework to compare competing system models, and the approach presented here represents an alternative to these analyses. This analysis provided some support for the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-494-Fraser1">Fraser et al. (2012)</xref> lemming hypothesis, or at least a reproductive collapse hypothesis; we can conclude that extended periods of widespread reproductive failure is a plausible hypothesis to explain Red Knot population decline.I thank Auburn University and the U.S. Geological Survey for logistical support of this research, and R. A. Robinson and anonymous reviewers for reviewing earlier versions of this manuscript and helping to improve the paper. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This work was not executed under any specific grant, but was completed as part of the author's job responsibilities.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> There were no ethical issues associated with this manuscript.