The importance of site to mate choice: Mate and site fidelity in Piping PloversCoefficient of variationSite and mate fidelity of Shags <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</named-content></italic> at two British coloniesJoint modeling of live-recapture, tag-resight, and tag-recovery dataPiping Plover habitat selection and nest success on natural, managed, and engineered sandbarsCan river management improve the Piping Plover's long-term survival on the Missouri River?Is mate fidelity related to site fidelity? A comparative analysis in CiconiiformsRe-mating between and within breeding seasons in the Greater Flamingo <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicopterus ruber</named-content> roseus</italic>Divorce in birds: A review of the hypothesesBarnacle geese preferentially pair with familiar associates from early lifeSurvival, site fidelity, and the population dynamics of Piping Plovers in SaskatchewanNesting density and reproductive success of Piping Plovers in response to storm- and human-created habitat changesMate change and reproductive success in the Lesser Snow GooseEarly arrival, initiation of nesting, and social status: An experimental study of breeding female Red-winged BlackbirdsMate retention in Caspian TernsSexual conflict and the polygamy thresholdOwners and satellites: The economics of territory defence in the Pied Wagtail, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Motacilla alba</named-content></italic>Divorce in the European BlackbirdCauses and effects of divorce in the Blue Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus caeruleus</named-content></italic>Between- and within-population variation in mate fidelity in the Great TitComparison of model building and selection strategiesCollinearity: A review of methods to deal with it and a simulation study evaluating their performanceBreeding success and mate retention in birds: A meta-analysisPiping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)Mate fidelity and divorce in monogamous birdsDivorce in the long-lived and monogamous oystercatcher, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Haematopus ostralegus</named-content></italic>: Incompatibility or choosing the better option?Benefits of early arrival at breeding grounds vary between malesPhilopatry, nest-site tenacity, and mate fidelity of Semipalmated PloversAge-related reproductive success in the Barnacle GooseAge and reproduction in birds&mdash;hypotheses and testsDifferential timing of spring migration in Wood Warblers (Parulinae)On territorial behavior and other factors influencing habitat distribution in birds. I. Theoretical developmentThe ecological significance of behavioral dominanceIdentification and breeding of yearling Piping PloversThe natal and breeding dispersal of birdsMate, site, and territory fidelity in Piping PloversMate fidelity and breeding site tenacity in a monogamous sandpiper, the Black TurnstoneField criteria for determining incubation stage in eggs of the Common TernEvidence for long-distance dispersal and successful interpopulation breeding of the endangered Piping PloverEffects of mate and site fidelity on nest survival of Western Sandpipers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris mauri</named-content></italic>)Competition for early arrival in migratory birdsTerritorial defence in the great tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>): Do residents always win?Age, arrival date and reproductive success of male American Redstarts <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>Larid site tenacity and group adherence in relation to habitatPredator exclosures: A technique to reduce predation at Piping Plover nestsMale tail length and female mate choice in the monogamous swallow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>Phenotype-dependent arrival time and its consequences in a migratory birdA test of three hypotheses for latitudinal segregation of the sexes in wintering birdsBreeding performance, mate fidelity, and nest site fidelity in a long-lived seabird: Behaving against the current?Monogamy in the SparrowhawkEffects of age and breeding experience on seasonal reproductive success in the Song SparrowSexual selection, arrival times, philopatry and site fidelity in the polyandrous Spotted SandpiperEffects of age, breeding experience, mate fidelity and site fidelity on breeding performance in a declining population of Cassin's AukletsA closer look at assumptionsSearch theory and mate choice. I. Models of single-sex discriminationRe-mating in birdsMate fidelity, senescence in breeding performance and reproductive trade-offs in the Barn SwallowFemale site familiarity increases fledging success in Piping Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)The time and energy budget of the male Dickcissel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spiza americana</named-content></italic>)Nest-site tenacity and mate retention of the Piping PloverA twenty year banding study of the Piping PloverThe cost of dispersal: Predation as a function of movement and site familiarity in Ruffed GrouseEach breeding season, seasonally monogamous birds can divorce or reunite with their previous year's mate, assuming both partners survive and return. We tested a suite of variables related to mate choice and site choice to determine which of 4 prominent mate fidelity hypotheses (better &lsqb;mate&rsqb; option, habitat mediated, musical chairs, and bet-hedging) best explained the interyear reunion rate and breeding dispersal of a seasonally monogamous shorebird, Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>), nesting on dynamic sandbars on the Missouri River, USA, 2005&ndash;2012. Of 252 pairs in which both members returned to the breeding grounds the following year, only 20&percnt; reunited. Pairs with an early-arriving male had the highest mate fidelity. Reunited pairs returned to previous nest sites (median breeding dispersal &equals; 39 m), and divorced and widowed birds tended to move farther (median &equals; 229 m and 193 m, respectively). Overall, site fidelity was higher in males than females. Previous reproductive success of a pair did not predict reunion, but all successful birds, with the exception of divorced females, exhibited high site fidelity, suggesting selection for site based on prior breeding success. Among divorced birds, females had higher-quality mates and higher nest success compared to their former partners, and they nested in areas of similar quality between years, whereas males settled in lower-quality areas following divorce. The benefits that females gained from divorce suggested that females initiated divorce to improve reproductive success, which supports the better option hypothesis. Although females seemed to initiate most divorces, males may have divorced as a safeguard against remaining unmated when there was uncertainty about the survival and return of a former mate, as proposed by the bet-hedging hypothesis.Cada temporada reproductiva, las aves estacionalmente mon&oacute;gamas pueden divorciarse o reunirse con su pareja del a&ntilde;o anterior, suponiendo que ambos compa&ntilde;eros sobreviven y vuelven al mismo lugar. Probamos un conjunto de variables relacionadas con la escogencia de pareja y de sitio para determinar cu&aacute;l de cuatro hip&oacute;tesis prominentes sobre fidelidad (mejor opci&oacute;n, mediada por el h&aacute;bitat, sillas musicales o apuesta diversificada) explica mejor la tasa de reuni&oacute;n interanual y la dispersi&oacute;n reproductiva de un ave playera estacionalmente mon&oacute;gama (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) anidante en los bancos de arena din&aacute;micos del r&iacute;o Missouri, EEUU, entre 2005 y 2012. De 252 parejas en las que ambos miembros regresaron a los territorios reproductivos al a&ntilde;o siguiente, s&oacute;lo el 20&percnt; se reuni&oacute;. Las parejas con machos que arribaron temprano presentaron mayor fidelidad. Las parejas reunidas volvieron a los sitios previos de anidaci&oacute;n (mediana de distancia de dispersi&oacute;n reproductiva &equals; 39m) y las aves divorciadas o que enviudaron tendieron a moverse m&aacute;s lejos (mediana &equals; 229 m y 193 m, respectivamente), aunque la fidelidad al sitio en general fue alta, especialmente en los machos. El &eacute;xito reproductivo previo de una pareja no predijo su reencuentro, pero todas las aves exitosas, con excepci&oacute;n de las hembras divorciadas, exhibieron alta fidelidad al sitio, lo que sugiere que los sitios son seleccionados con base en el &eacute;xito reproductivo previo. Entre las aves divorciadas, las hembras tuvieron parejas de mayor calidad y mayor &eacute;xito reproductivo comparado con sus antiguas parejas, y anidaron en &aacute;reas de calidad similar, mientras que los machos se establecieron en &aacute;reas de menor calidad luego del divorcio. Los beneficios que las hembras obtienen sugieren que &eacute;stas iniciaron el divorcio para incrementar su &eacute;xito reproductivo, lo que sustenta la hip&oacute;tesis de la mejor opci&oacute;n. Aunque las hembras parecieron iniciar la mayor&iacute;a de los divorcios, los machos habr&iacute;an podido divorciarse como una salvaguarda contra permanecer sin pareja cuando hay incertidumbre en la supervivencia y el retorno de una pareja anterior, como propone la hip&oacute;tesis de apuesta diversificada.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>, dispersi&oacute;n, divorcio, fidelidad al sitio, fidelidad de pareja, r&iacute;o MissouriMonogamous mating systems include those in which pairs maintain perennial bonds and those in which the pair bond is seasonal and dissolves after each breeding period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Rowley1">Rowley 1983</xref>). In seasonally monogamous partnerships, each breeding season presents 2 options for previously mated pairs returning to the same area: individuals may reunite with their previous partner or they may divorce and mate with a different partner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dhondt1">Dhondt and Adriaensen 1994</xref>). This decision may be influenced by factors related to qualities specific to a partner, a location, or an interaction of both.Gaining the cumulative benefits of a partner's age and breeding experience is one potential advantage of reunion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Rowley1">Rowley 1983</xref>). Across bird species, breeding success tends to increase with age until senescence. This increased breeding success may be due to differential survival of high-quality individuals, improvements in foraging and breeding skills with experience, or optimization of reproductive efforts. Younger, less experienced birds may be more likely to divorce because they have the greatest potential for reproductive improvement.Older birds tend to return to the breeding grounds earlier than younger birds. Early arrival can be linked to high mate quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Moller1">M&oslash;ller 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Moller2">1994</xref>) if the costs of expedited arrival (e.g., enduring inclement spring weather) are greater to individuals in lower condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Kokko1">Kokko 1999</xref>). Arrival sequence also corresponds with territory quality when holding a territory is based on prior ownership and effort invested in defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Forstmeier1">Forstmeier 2002</xref>). Additionally, early arrival creates the opportunity for early nest initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Lozano1">Lozano et al. 1996</xref>), which has been linked to increased nest success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cristol1">Cristol 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Johnson1">Johnson and Walters 2008</xref>).In a meta-analysis of breeding success and mate retention in birds, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dubois1">Dubois and C&eacute;zilly (2002)</xref> found an overall pattern of divorce following nest failure; however, there is wide variation in avian divorce rates, and several studies have shown no relationship between nest success and mate fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Aebischer1">Aebischer et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Flynn1">Flynn et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Saino1">Saino et al. 2002</xref>). Finally, areas with a low breeding density can have higher rates of mate fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Pyle1">Pyle et al. 2001</xref>), which may be due to a lack of alternative breeding options. The rate of divorce in seasonally monogamous birds varies among and within species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens1">Ens et al. 1996</xref>), and this variation has led to the development of multiple hypotheses to identify and describe the environmental and social factors contributing to divorce (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Choudhury1">Choudhury 1995</xref>). Four hypotheses that may account for divorce in seasonally monogamous birds are the better option hypothesis, the habitat mediated hypothesis, the musical chairs hypothesis, and the bet-hedging hypothesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t01">Table 1</xref>).Predictions and outcomes of divorce according to specific hypotheses explaining divorce in birds.The better option hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Davies1">Davies 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens2">Ens et al. 1993</xref>) proposes that divorce improves reproductive success of the divorcer through mating with a higher-quality partner than the bird's previous partner. Divorce results from one mate's desertion for a better partner, and its frequency may be highest when there is a greater availability of possible mates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Pyle1">Pyle et al. 2001</xref>) or when there is high variation in individual quality within a population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens2">Ens et al. 1993</xref>). Similarly, under the habitat mediated hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens2">Ens et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Desrochers1">Desrochers and Magrath 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Newton1">Newton and Wyllie 1996</xref>), divorce may be advantageous when there is an opportunity to improve reproductive success by nesting at a higher-quality site (independent of the new mate's quality). This can occur in situations where competition for high-quality habitat relegates lower-quality individuals to suboptimal areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Fretwell1">Fretwell and Lucas 1970</xref>). The habitat mediated hypothesis predicts a higher divorce rate when there is wide variation in habitat quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Newton1">Newton and Wyllie 1996</xref>), which potentially allows divorcing birds to move from low-quality to high-quality sites.The musical chairs hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dhondt1">Dhondt and Adriaensen 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dhondt2">Dhondt et al. 1996</xref>) suggests that divorce is related to site choice because each individual attempts to nest on the best territory available when it arrives at the breeding grounds. Unlike the better option and habitat mediated hypotheses, divorce is unrelated to previous breeding success. In male-territorial species, male birds typically arrive at the breeding grounds earlier than females to establish a territory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Gauthreaux1">Gauthreaux 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Myers1">Myers 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Francis1">Francis and Cooke 1986</xref>). Under the musical chairs hypothesis, a female selects a mate based on the quality of his territory, regardless of prior breeding experience with that male. Differential arrival dates of pair members, low site fidelity, and high variation in habitat quality create more opportunity for divorce to occur.The bet-hedging hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Handel1">Handel and Gill 2000</xref>) proposes that divorce is related to a pair's asynchronous arrival at the breeding grounds. An individual returns to its previous territory at the onset of the breeding season and, in the absence of its former mate, courts all nearby available birds to avoid delayed or missed breeding while waiting for a possibly deceased former mate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Handel1">Handel and Gill 2000</xref>). Divorce, then, occurs when a former pair's gap in arrival dates is long enough that the early arriver settles with a new mate and the late arriver, having been replaced, must relocate. In this situation the benefit of divorce to the individual initiating divorce is assurance of a breeding opportunity, not improvement in mate or territory quality; thus, divorce rate should be unaffected by previous reproductive success, mate quality, or site quality. Site fidelity should be high in the early-arriving sex, and the likelihood of divorce is expected to increase with later arrival dates and a longer gap in pair arrival dates.In this study, we evaluated the effects of age, arrival date, previous nest success, and the availability of potential mates on mate fidelity in a seasonally monogamous shorebird, the Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>), in the context of the above hypotheses. Because there is a strong association between mate and site fidelity in many bird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Desrochers1">Desrochers and Magrath 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cezilly1">C&eacute;zilly et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Naves1">Naves et al. 2006</xref>), we chose to test hypotheses that vary in their attribution of divorce to selection for mate, selection for site, or as a consequence of differential arrival dates and unrelated to mate or site quality. Additionally, to further understand the relationship between mate and site fidelity, we examined site fidelity in relation to sex, prior nest success, and mate fidelity.We studied Piping Plovers over 8 breeding seasons (April&ndash;August 2005&ndash;2012) on 115 km of the Missouri River from Lewis and Clark Lake, South Dakota (42&deg;51&prime;N, 97&deg;47&prime;W), to Ponca State Park, Nebraska (42&deg;36&prime;N, 96&deg;42&prime;W). Piping Plovers nested on bare to sparsely vegetated portions of river sandbars that ranged in size from &lt;0.1 to &gt;100 ha of suitable nesting habitat. Encroaching vegetation, varying water levels, sand deposition and erosion, and active management changed the amount of habitat available to Piping Plovers from season to season.Piping Plovers migrate annually and arrive at their breeding grounds in spring, when males establish territories and begin courtship. Pairs form within one day to several weeks after arrival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ElliottSmith1">Elliott-Smith and Haig 2004</xref>). They are seasonally monogamous, and a pair shares incubation of a (typically) 4-egg clutch for 27&ndash;31 days after the last egg is laid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Wilcox1">Wilcox 1959</xref>). The average annual true survival rate at our study site is &sim;78&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin3">Catlin et al. 2014</xref> in press), and the fidelity rate of surviving adults to the study area is &gt;90&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin1">Catlin 2009</xref>). Both values were established using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Barker1">Barker's (1997)</xref> capture-mark-recapture model for determining true survival and site fidelity.We surveyed sandbars for adult Piping Plovers and nests throughout the breeding season by walking transects through potential nesting areas. Adults were captured on their nests with drop-door traps or box traps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Wilcox1">Wilcox 1959</xref>), and we estimate that, except for the first year of the study, &ge;75&percnt; of our population was banded in any given year (D. H. Catlin personal observation). We measured wing-chord length (nearest 1 mm), culmen length (nearest 0.1 mm), and body mass (nearest 0.1 g) and marked birds with a unique combination of Darvic colored plastic leg bands and a Darvic flag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-GrattoTrevor1">Gratto-Trevor 2004</xref>). We attempted to identify both parents attending each nest by reading the band combination of adults captured or observed on nests. Over the course of the study period, we located 1,893 plover nests; of these, 35&percnt; had 2 known banded adults and 18&percnt; had one known banded adult.Nest locations were mapped using a handheld GPS unit (TrimbleGeo-XT, Trimble Navigation, Sunnyvale, CA) and were checked approximately every other day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin2">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>) until failure or hatching. The date the first egg was laid (nest initiation date) was established by floating eggs of complete clutches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Hays1">Hays and LeCroy 1971</xref>) or by backdating incomplete clutches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Wilcox1">Wilcox 1959</xref>). If a brood was found post-hatch, chicks were aged based on body size to backdate the nest initiation date. We determined the sex of adult birds by evaluating their plumage and bill characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-GrattoTrevor2">Gratto-Trevor et al. 2010</xref>), making behavioral observations (male territorial and courtship displays, copulation position), and linking them to a nest with a partner of known sex.We analyzed site fidelity of banded birds that nested with a banded bird in one year (<italic>t</italic>) and returned to the study area and nested the following year (<italic>t</italic> &plus; 1). We determined the distance between the year <italic>t</italic> nest and the year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 nest (hereafter &ldquo;breeding dispersal&rdquo;; based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Greenwood1">Greenwood and Harvey 1982</xref>) for each individual that reunited, divorced (both birds present in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 but one or both mated to a new bird), or whose year <italic>t</italic> mate did not return to the breeding grounds in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 (hereafter &ldquo;widowed&rdquo;). We used generalized linear and generalized linear mixed models to estimate the influence of mate fidelity (reunited, divorced, or widowed), sex, and year <italic>t</italic> nest success (success &equals; hatched &ge;1 egg) on the breeding dispersal distance of individual birds. Because the breeding dispersal decisions of individuals within a pair, on the same sandbar, or within the same year could be related, we compared models with all fixed effects and (1) no random effect, (2) a pair-specific random effect, (3) a sandbar-specific random effect, (4) a year-specific random effect, and (5&ndash;7) all 2-way interactions of pair, sandbar, and year random effect prior to further modeling. We included nest initiation date of an individual's year <italic>t</italic> nest in all models to control for the possibility that it was not the first nesting attempt. Distance measurements were log-transformed prior to analysis to meet the distributional assumptions of the model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ramsey1">Ramsey and Schafer 2002</xref>).After selection of the most parsimonious random effects structure, we compared 19 models consisting of all possible subsets of mate fidelity, sex, and nest success, including all 2- and 3-way interactions of these variables, and a null (intercept only) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Doherty1">Doherty et al. 2012</xref>). We used Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>) to compare models and to select the most parsimonious (lowest AIC<sub>c</sub> value) random effects structure. We used model-averaged parameter estimates and relative importance statistics (RI, sum of model weights of all models containing a particular variable) to interpret fixed effects. We used least squares means from the most parsimonious model to compare log distances among all categorical variables and their interactions (mate fidelity, sex, and nest success). We used a Tukey-Kramer correction to adjust <italic>P</italic> values for multiple comparisons. When presenting raw distance data we used the median distances, which are related to the mean log distances (Ramsey and Shafer 2002) and are easier to interpret.We considered habitat quality in a year to be related to the amount of foraging habitat available to a pair. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cohen2">Cohen et al. (2009)</xref> established that sites with access to moist foraging habitats were of higher quality than those with little of that habitat. In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cohen2">Cohen et al. (2009)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin1">Catlin (2009)</xref> showed that, at higher nesting densities, population growth slowed through decreased reproductive output (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin1">Catlin 2009</xref>), increased emigration, and decreased immigration into a site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin1">Catlin 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cohen2">Cohen et al. 2009</xref>). We therefore estimated an index of habitat quality as the ratio of the total hectares of wet habitat on a sandbar to the maximum number of active nests on that sandbar in a given year. To determine the influence of habitat quality on nest site selection, we compared the difference in habitat quality of nest sites from year <italic>t</italic> to year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 for divorced males and for divorced females. We accounted for general trends in the quality of habitat on the study site from year to year by comparing nest site quality of divorced birds to reunited birds. We also compared habitat quality for divorced females vs. divorced males to see if either sex nested in higher quality habitat following divorce. We calculated the coefficient of variation (CV) for habitat quality to assess the level of variation in quality. To better interpret the CV values, we found the potential maximum CV using the formula CV<sub>max</sub> &equals;<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Abdi1">Abdi 2010</xref>).We analyzed mate fidelity of banded birds that were paired in year <italic>t</italic> and both present in the following year, with at least one individual known to nest in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1. We used logistic regression to investigate 7 sources of variation in pair mate fidelity (1 &equals; reunite, 0 &equals; divorce): (1) arrival date (first resight of the year) of the male in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1; (2) arrival date of the female in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1; (3) difference between arrival dates of the male and female of a pair; (4) minimum age (number of years since banding &plus; 1 for birds banded as adults) of the male; (5) minimum age of the female; (6) nest success (1 &equals; hatched &ge;1 egg, 0 &equals; failed) in year <italic>t</italic>; and (7) availability of mates (maximum number of active nests on a sandbar in a given year) in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1. We used the number of nests on a sandbar rather than nesting density as a measure of available mates because using density to determine mate availability could be misleading. For example, a small sandbar with 2 pairs has a relatively high density of birds but a paucity of available mates. We controlled for the potential effects of a year <italic>t</italic> nest being a renest by including nest initiation date in every model under the assumption that mate fidelity for renests could be lower than that for first nests.We compared 81 models consisting of all possible subsets of the 7 variables, including a null (intercept only) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Doherty1">Doherty et al. 2012</xref>), with the exception of the difference in arrival date variable, which did not appear in the same model as male arrival date or female arrival date because it was derived from the sex-specific variables. To assess potential non-independence of samples from the same pair across multiple seasons, we compared a fixed effects global model (all variables in the model) to a mixed effects global model with a random effect for pair. We tested the fit of the best-fitting model with a Hosmer and Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Hosmer1">Hosmer and Lemeshow 2004</xref>).To determine the influence of mate quality in partner selection, we compared the year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 body conditions of each divorced individual's year <italic>t</italic> and year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 mate using a subset of birds that were captured and measured in a given year. We estimated individual body condition in a year as the residual value (in grams) from a linear regression of body mass against the first principal component of a principal components analysis on wing-chord length and culmen length. This created a comparison among the masses of similarly sized individuals. We used average values for wing-chord and culmen length if these values were measured more than once in a year. We assumed that birds with positive condition values (more massive than average given their body size) were of better quality, but it is possible that average mass by size is optimal. Although no direct connection between the condition and quality of Piping Plovers has been established, more massive birds likely are better at acquiring food and acquiring and maintaining better territories, such that body condition is an index of individual quality. We quantified the overall degree of variation in body condition using the CV. Because CV can be calculated for positive numbers only, a constant equal to the absolute value of the minimum residual was added to all body condition values to raise them to positive numbers prior to averaging while maintaining the same range.We examined the consequences of divorce by comparing the interyear nest success of individuals that divorced and by comparing the year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 nest success of divorced males vs. divorced females. Many of the nests in this study were exclosed from predators (had a wire cage placed around them; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Melvin1">Melvin et al. 1992</xref>), a management tool used to improve nest success, and these nests had an artificially elevated hatch rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin2">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>); therefore, a subset of uncaged nests was used for this part of the analysis.We used 2-sided <italic>t</italic>-tests and paired <italic>t</italic>-tests for comparisons between groups and employed Satterthwaite's method when groups had unequal variances. Significance was determined at the &alpha; &equals; 0.05 level. Means are reported as <italic>x̄</italic> &plusmn; SD unless otherwise indicated. For any model with multiple independent variables, we examined pairwise correlation coefficients between all variables to rule out potential negative effects from collinearity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dormann1">Dormann et al. 2013</xref>). We performed all analyses using the SAS statistical program, version 9.3 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA).We analyzed 556 movements from year <italic>t</italic> to year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 nest sites of 443 individual Piping Plovers (228 males and 215 females); 18&percnt; of birds reunited with their former partner, 57&percnt; divorced, and 25&percnt; were widowed. Breeding dispersal distance ranged from &lt;1 to 92,584 m (interquartile range &equals; 40&ndash;4,538 m); the median interannual distance between an individual's nests was 153 m. Controlling for sandbar &times; year as a random effect provided the best general fit to the data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t02">Table 2</xref>); therefore, further modeling included the sandbar &times; year random effect. The global model (including all fixed effects, 2-way interactions, and the single 3-way interaction) was the best-supported model for site fidelity, receiving 84&percnt; of the total model support (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> from null model &equals; 116.2); thus, we used this model for all estimates.Models comparing random effects on site fidelity (interyear breeding dispersal) of Piping Plovers nesting on Missouri River sandbars, 2005&ndash;2012. Models were ranked according to differences in Akaike's Information Criterion (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>).Site fidelity varied because of mate fidelity, sex, and year <italic>t</italic> nest success of individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Reuniting birds were highly site loyal and nested closer to their year <italic>t</italic> nest sites (median &equals; 39 m) than birds that divorced (median &equals; 229 m) or were widowed (median &equals; 193 m; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, row 1). Divorced birds never dispersed significantly farther than widowed birds, but in some cases they dispersed farther than reunited birds and widows did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). Females moved farther than males (median &equals; 367 m vs. 72 m; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>B, row 1), divorced females moved farther than divorced males (median &equals; 914 m vs. 83 m; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>B, row 4), and widowed females moved farther than widowed males (median &equals; 1203 m vs. 88 m; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>B, row 5). Year <italic>t</italic> nest success alone did not predict breeding dispersal distance (successful median &equals; 127 m vs. failed median &equals; 2,127 m; least squares means: <italic>t</italic><sub>470</sub> &equals; 1.4, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15), but it was involved in several significant 2- and the 3-way interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>).Relative breeding dispersal of Piping Plovers nesting on Missouri River sandbars, 2005&ndash;2012, compared among groups of (<bold>A</bold>) different mate fidelity (Reunited, Widowed, Divorced) or (<bold>B</bold>) sex, shown as least squares mean difference of log(distance) (dots) and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (bars). Widowed and divorced birds were compared to reunited birds with (<bold>A</bold>) sex and nest success held constant, and (<bold>B</bold>) females were compared to males with mate fidelity and nest success held constant. There were no significant differences in the effect of nest success between males and females, or between birds that reunited, divorced, or were widowed. Estimates were derived from a linear mixed model that controlled for nest initiation date and used sandbar &times; year as a random effect.Male and female Piping Plovers behaved differently in response to nest success. Successful males stayed near their year <italic>t</italic> nest location regardless of their mate choice in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 (median &equals; 57 m; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, row 5). Successful females remained relatively near their year <italic>t</italic> nest site when reunited or widowed and moved significantly farther when divorced than when reunited (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, row 8). Unsuccessful males moved relatively long distances only when divorced (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, row 6); unsuccessful females dispersed when divorced or widowed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, row 9).Interyear breeding dispersal distances (m) in relation to 3-way interactions among mate fidelity (Reunite, Divorce, or Widow), sex, and nest success (Fail or Hatch in year <italic>t</italic>) of Piping Plovers nesting on Missouri River sandbars, 2005&ndash;2012. Males and females of pairs that reunited in successive years have the same dispersal distances and are grouped.Over the duration of this study, Piping Plovers nested on sandbars with 0.008&ndash;17.1 ha of foraging habitat per pair (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 1.9 &plusmn; 2.9, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 113). The amount of foraging habitat varied widely (CV &equals; 1.53, CV<sub>max</sub> &equals; 10.6). Divorced females did not nest on higher-quality sites in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 than in year <italic>t</italic> (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>156</sub> &equals; &minus;0.6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.55), even when compared to reunited females (paired <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>204</sub> &equals; &minus;0.1, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.93). Likewise, there was no difference in the nest site quality of divorced vs. reuniting male Piping Plovers (paired <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>199</sub> &equals; &minus;0.6, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.54). Overall, males had lower quality nest sites in year <italic>t</italic> than in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>276</sub> &equals; &minus;2.0, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05), which was apparent in divorced males (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>151</sub> &equals; &minus;2.0, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05); however, there was no difference in the interyear change in habitat quality of divorced females compared to divorced males (paired <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>307</sub> &equals; 0.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.63).We monitored 252 plover pairs (139 males and 125 females) that nested together in year <italic>t</italic> where both members returned and at least one mated with a known bird in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1; 50 pairs (20&percnt;) reunited in successive seasons and 202 (80&percnt;) divorced. Controlling for pair as a random effect did not improve the fit of the logistic regression model predicting mate fidelity (AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 233.8 vs. 240.1); thus, further modeling was done without the random effect for pair. The baseline model provided a reasonable fit to the data (<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm02"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm02.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 10.0, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.26).The top model describing mate fidelity included male arrival date, female arrival date, male age, and year <italic>t</italic> nest success (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t04">Table 4</xref>). Male arrival date had the greatest influence on mate fidelity (RI &equals; 0.94) and was the only significant predictor of reunion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t05">Table 5</xref>). Mean male arrival date was earlier than mean female arrival date (males: April 26 &plusmn; 10 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 284; females: April 29 &plusmn; 13 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 272). Males that reunited arrived on average 5 days earlier than males that divorced (reunite: April 22 &plusmn; 7 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 50; divorce: April 27 &plusmn; 12 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 154). Likewise, reunited females arrived earlier than divorced females (reunite: April 26 &plusmn; 11 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 50; divorce: April 30 &plusmn; 13 days, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 161). The effect of female arrival date had a high RI (0.75) and approached significance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t05">Table 5</xref>). Despite the high RI values of male and female arrival date, the difference between year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 arrival dates of a year <italic>t</italic> pair received no support as a predictor of reunion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t05">Tables 5</xref> and 6). The mean difference in arrival date between pair members that reunited was the same as the mean difference in arrival date between pair members that divorced (reunited: 3 days &plusmn; 1.0 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 50; divorced: 3 days &plusmn; 1.0 &lsqb;SE&rsqb;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 202).Rankings of best supported (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le;4.0) logistic regression models used to estimate interyear mate fidelity of Piping Plover pairs nesting on Missouri River sandbars, 2005&ndash;2012. Models were ranked according to differences in Akaike's Information Criterion (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>) and Akaike weights (w<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>). The null model is shown for comparison.Model-averaged estimates and relative importance (RI, sum of Akaike weights of all models including a given variable) of factors affecting interyear mate fidelity in Piping Plover pairs nesting on Missouri River sandbars, 2005&ndash;2012. Estimates are from an all-possible subset logistic regression. Variables were ranked according to RI.Male age appeared in several of the top-ranked models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t04">Table 4</xref>) and had a moderately high RI value (0.68); the model-averaged parameter estimate and confidence limits (slight overlap with 0; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t05">Table 5</xref>) suggest that older males may have been more likely to reunite with previous mates than were younger males. Female age, availability of mates, and prior nest success were not significant predictors of reunion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-t05">Table 5</xref>).For all banded males on the study site, body condition ranged from &minus;10.2 to 15.5 g (residual value from the regression of body mass on the first principal component of wing-chord length and culmen length; <italic>x̄</italic> &equals; &minus;0.2 &plusmn; 3.6, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 596). There was a moderate amount of variation in male body condition (CV &equals; 0.36). For all banded females on the study site, body condition ranged from &minus;8.9 to 11.3 (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 0.0 &plusmn; 3.3, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 536), with a level of variation similar to males. In year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1, divorced males paired with females in lower body condition than their previous mate (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>65</sub> &equals; &minus;1.9, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05). Although divorced females did not pair with higher-quality mates in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 vs. year <italic>t</italic> (one-sample <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>90</sub> &equals; 0.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.64), divorced females did significantly improve their mate quality when compared to divorced males (paired <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic><sub>155</sub> &equals; &minus;1.7, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04).The effect of divorce on future reproductive success differed by sex. Females showed the most benefit, despite their nest success not changing between year <italic>t</italic> and <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 (<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm03"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm03.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 0.02, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.88, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 23). In comparison, divorced males had lower nest success in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 than in year <italic>t</italic> (<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm04"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm04.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 4.0, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 25). Divorced females did, however, have higher nest success than divorced males in year <italic>t</italic> &plus; 1 (<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm05"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-1-265-ilm05.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula> &equals; 6.3, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 48).We observed an 80&percnt; rate of interyear divorce that was largely driven by female Piping Plovers choosing a &ldquo;better option&rdquo; for a mate, but with some males potentially &ldquo;bet-hedging&rdquo; and initiating divorce themselves. Although not all of the predictions of the better option hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Davies1">Davies 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens2">Ens et al. 1993</xref>) were satisfied by the data, this hypothesis provided the most reasonable explanation of the main causes of female-initiated divorce observed in Piping Plovers. Under this hypothesis, one sex instigates and benefits from divorce, and the other sex suffers negative consequences. Although females did not improve their mate quality or reproductive success following divorce, we found that, relative to their former partners, they had significantly higher nest success and mated with significantly higher-quality partners. That males actually decreased their nest success and mate quality following divorce strongly suggests that they generally were victims of divorce. There was a moderate level of variation in male quality, which could create the opportunity for females to &ldquo;trade up&rdquo; if they were formerly paired with a lower-quality mate. There was no relationship between the number of available mates, measured as the maximum number of active nests on a given sandbar, and the probability of divorce. It is possible, however, that including unpaired individuals at a site or quantifying the degree to which individuals move among sandbars to scout for a mate or a site would improve this estimate.Our results showed some support for male-initiated divorce, as in the bet-hedging hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Handel1">Handel and Gill 2000</xref>). We did not observe a clear link between arrival asynchrony of a former pair and divorce, which is an expectation of the bet-hedging hypothesis, but when both members of a pair returned and only the male was known to renest (potential male-initiated divorce), these females arrived &sim;6.3 days later than their mates. Bet-hedging is a means for males to avoid the costs of delayed nesting or remaining unmated after waiting on a late-returning or non-returning former partner and is related to the chance of survival. The annual survival rate of Piping Plovers on our study site is &sim;78&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin3">Catlin et al. 2014</xref> in press), and &sim;92&percnt; of surviving adults return to the study site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin1">Catlin 2009</xref>). At these observed survival and fidelity rates, the chance of a male's former partner surviving and returning is &sim;72&percnt;. Females exercising choice in mate or site would further contribute to the high rate of divorce that we observed because males may have to hedge their bets not just against their former mate returning to the breeding grounds, but also against her opting to return to him. Whereas successful males always remained near their former nest site, successful females that divorced moved away from their previous nest site. Some of these females may have been victims of bet-hedging divorce who were usurped by earlier-arriving females. A similar situation has been observed in Semipalmated Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius semipalmatus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Flynn1">Flynn et al. 1999</xref>) and Spotted Sandpipers (<italic>Actitis macularia</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Oring1">Oring and Lank 1982</xref>).When a male returned to the breeding grounds early in the season, he was more likely to reunite with his former mate and thereby more likely to exhibit philopatry. In a male-territorial species, this is a male strategy to gain the benefits of a familiar nest location and, according to the bet-hedging hypothesis, potentially gain the benefits of reunion with his former mate by means of establishing a &ldquo;meeting place&rdquo; at which to reunite. Male Piping Plovers have relatively high site fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Wilcox1">Wilcox 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cohen1">Cohen and Gratto-Trevor 2011</xref>), which may be advantageous because of known foraging areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Davies2">Davies and Houston 1981</xref>) and predator locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Yoder1">Yoder et al. 2004</xref>) as well as established relationships with neighbors at a familiar site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Krebs1">Krebs 1982</xref>). Our results reinforce this idea because male Piping Plovers exhibited strong site fidelity in consecutive breeding seasons on the river, despite experiencing a significant reduction in nest site quality that mirrored the overall decline in plover habitat quality during the majority of the study period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin2">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin3">2014</xref> in press). Reuniting is expected to benefit male Piping Plovers because they can abbreviate courtship and mate selection, which are time- and energy-consumptive activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Schartz1">Schartz and Zimmerman 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Real1">Real 1990</xref>), have coordinated breeding and defense with a familiar partner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cooke1">Cooke et al. 1981</xref>), and can potentially initiate a nest earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Choudhury2">Choudhury and Black 1994</xref>). Site-loyal males that reunite with their mate may also benefit from a positive effect of female site familiarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 2012</xref>) and age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Nol1">Nol and Smith 1987</xref>) on reproductive success.Early-arriving females were marginally more likely to reunite than were later-arriving females. Like males, the best available habitat for early-arriving females may have been their previous nest site, leading them to be more site- and mate-loyal. However, because female Piping Plovers are not constrained by the responsibility of establishing a territory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>), it may not be as costly for them to change their nest site between years. Divorced female Piping Plovers may have been selecting for site quality, as evidenced by the trend of divorced females securing nest sites of similar quality across years, whereas males nested in lower-quality habitat subsequent to divorce, but there was no difference between the change in interyear habitat qualities of males and females. Because there was a moderate amount of variation in habitat quality, and one pair member initiated and benefitted from divorce, it may be possible that site selection plays a role in divorce, supporting the habitat mediated hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens2">Ens et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Desrochers1">Desrochers and Magrath 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Newton1">Newton and Wyllie 1996</xref>), but this is uncertain. Piping Plovers likely base their judgment of habitat quality on multiple criteria (e.g., predator presence, habitat availability, social cues) in addition to quality of foraging.Aside from the moderate amount of variation in habitat quality and difference in habitat quality between divorced males and divorced females, we found no other evidence supporting the musical chairs hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dhondt1">Dhondt and Adriaensen 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Dhondt2">Dhondt et al. 1996</xref>), where arrival sequence dictates territorial settlement. Because mate fidelity was so strongly associated with arrival date and reunited birds nested on habitat similar in quality to divorced birds, we could not determine if early arrival correlates with occupation of objectively higher-quality habitat. Again, however, we recognize that habitat selection may be much more complex than the amount of foraging habitat per pair.Our results indicate that mate fidelity of Piping Plovers on the Missouri River was related to early male arrival, high male nest site fidelity, and female selection for a higher-quality mate. Although we did not find a direct link between divorce and selection for site, ancillary evidence suggests that females were exercising choice for site when there was a potential for reproductive improvement. Widowed females that were successful in year <italic>t</italic> remained just as close to their former nest site as did reunited females; however, when they were previously unsuccessful at a site, widowed females moved farther than reunited females, suggesting they were choosing a new mate or site based on their past breeding success. If site selection occurred independently of previous nest success, these unsuccessful widowed birds would be unlikely to differ from successful widowed birds in their breeding dispersal distance. Additionally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Desrochers1">Desrochers and Magrath (1996)</xref> posited that divorce was female-initiated in the European Blackbird, given that females dispersed farther in response to divorce than did males. We observed this same relationship in Piping Plovers.Birds in this study exhibited behavior typical of a monogamous, male-territorial species, with males that compete for territories to which they remain site-loyal, and females select mates or sites that potentially improve their reproductive success. Piping Plovers at our site differ from many other Charadriiformes, however, because they nest on river sandbars, a highly unstable habitat for nesting birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-McNicholl1">McNicholl 1975</xref>). Erosion, vegetation encroachment, and flooding can alter habitat quality and availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Catlin2">Catlin et al. 2011</xref>). The relatively high rate of divorce that we observed may be attributable to the dynamic nature of sandbars, where variation in habitat quality from year to year allowed Piping Plovers to reevaluate their choice of territory and mate.The divorce rate in this study (80&percnt;) was higher than that of Piping Plovers in Manitoba (67&percnt;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 30; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>) and Minnesota (55&percnt;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 11; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Wiens1">Wiens and Cuthbert 1988</xref>) as well as other Charadriiforms with similar life history traits (0&ndash;54&percnt;; seasonal migrants in which &gt;80&percnt; of successful pairs raise only a single brood per season and the pair bond dissolves at the end of each breeding season; see Appendix 19.1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Ens1">Ens et al. 1996</xref>). High divorce rates have been observed in other species that inhabit ephemeral habitats, such as the Caspian Tern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hydroprogne caspia</named-content></italic>, 50&percnt;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 12; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cuthbert1">Cuthbert 1985</xref>) and Greater Flamingo (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phoenicopterus ruber</named-content> roseus</italic>, 98&percnt;, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 60; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Cezilly2">C&eacute;zilly and Johnson 1995</xref>), which may be due to a connection between site and mate fidelity.Adult Piping Plovers show relatively high site fidelity and low median dispersal distances, but in an ephemeral habitat such as a river sandbar or a barrier island, long-distance movements may not improve fitness because of a loss in site familiarity or because high-quality habitat may not be readily available or detectable elsewhere. Although long-distance dispersal sometimes occurs (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-265-Hillman1">Hillman et al. 2012</xref>) our results suggest that female Piping Plovers were making local site- and mate-quality choices, shifting to find improved breeding locations, whereas males remained site-loyal regardless of breeding success and habitat quality. Our results highlight the different and competing strategies between the sexes and offer further insight into the mechanisms driving mate fidelity in birds.A. Silvis provided insight and support. We thank 2 anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments on earlier drafts of this manuscript. We acknowledge the tireless efforts of numerous technicians and crew leaders in collecting the data for this work.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> We thank the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and the Virginia Tech Graduate School for funding this project.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Field methods were approved by the Virginia Tech Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC permit 11-027).