 Plasticity of incubation behaviors helps Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  ) maintain an optimal thermal environment for developing embryos  Temperature and life history: Experimental heating leads female Tree Swallows to modulate egg temperature and incubation behaviour  Nest box orientation affects internal temperature and nest site selection by Tree Swallows  Experimental cooling during incubation leads to reduced innate immunity and body condition in nestling Tree Swallows  Effects of ambient temperature on avian incubation behavior  Evolution of passerine incubation behavior: Influence of food, temperature, and nest predation  Avian incubation patterns reflect temporal changes in developing clutches  Body mass regulation during incubation in female Common Eiders   Somateria mollissima    The price of insulation: Costs and benefits of feather delivery to nests for male Tree Swallows   Tachycineta bicolor    Fitness cost of incubation in Great Tits (  Parus major  ) is related to clutch size  The effect of apparatus, extraction time, and solvent type on lipid extractions of Snow Geese  Reproductive energetics of Wood Ducks  Slight differences in incubation temperature affect early growth and stress endocrinology of Wood Duck (  Aix sponsa  ) ducklings  Incubation temperature affects multiple measures of immunocompetence in young Wood Ducks  Embryonic developmental patterns and energy expenditure are affected by incubation temperature in Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  )  Ecological, evolutionary, and conservation implications of incubation temperature-dependent phenotypes in birds  Incubation temperature affects the metabolic cost of thermoregulation in a young precocial bird  Effects of habitat use and movement patterns on incubation behavior of female Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  ) in southeast Alabama  Plasticity of parental care under the risk of predation: How much should parents reduce care?  Differential investment and costs during avian incubation determined by individual quality: An experimental study of the Common Eider (  Somateria mollissima  )  Cost of reproduction in a long-lived bird: Incubation effort reduces immune function and future reproduction  Age determination of female Wood Ducks during the breeding season  Optimal allocation of effort between reproductive phases: The trade-off between incubation costs and subsequent brood rearing capacity  An overview of the factors influencing the morphology and thermal properties of avian nests  Nest temperature, incubation period, and investment decisions of incubating Wood Ducks   Aix sponsa    Effects of age and experience on reproductive performance of Wood Ducks  Date of nest initiation mediates incubation costs of Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  )  Warm is better: Incubation temperature influences apparent survival and recruitment of Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  )  Incubation as a reproductive cost in female Wood Ducks  Maternal effects in Wood Ducks: Incubation temperature influences incubation period and neonate phenotype  Using artificial nests to test importance of nesting material and nest shelter for incubation energetics  Incubation temperature influences locomotor performance in young Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  )  Is clutch size limited by incubation ability in Northern Lapwings?  Effect of feathers as nest insulation on incubation behavior and reproductive performance of Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  )  Extended incubation recesses by alpine-breeding Horned Larks: A strategy for dealing with inclement weather?  Latitudinal variation in Blue Tit and Great Tit nest characteristics indicates environmental adjustment  Effects of mate removal on incubation behavior and reproductive success of female Wood Ducks  Patterns of nest attendance in female Wood Ducks  Geographic variation in avian incubation periods and parental influences on embryonic temperature  Intrinsic vs. extrinsic influences of life history expression: Metabolism and parentally induced temperature influences on embryo development rate  The effect of feather nest lining on reproduction in the swallow   Hirundo rustica    Thermal aspects of nest-site location for Vesper Sparrows and Horned Larks in British Columbia  Incubation temperature affects growth and energy metabolism in Blue Tit nestlings  Context-dependent costs of incubation in the Pied Flycatcher  Female Zebra Finches compromise clutch temperature in energetically demanding incubation conditions  Selection on heritable phenotypic plasticity in a wild bird population  Periodic cooling of bird eggs reduces embryonic growth efficiency  Experimental heating reveals nest temperature affects nestling condition in Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  )  Behavioural plasticity may compensate for climate change in a long-lived reptile with temperature-dependent sex determination  Resource allocation between reproductive phases: The importance of thermal conditions in determining the cost of incubation  Energetic consequences of clutch temperature and clutch size for a uniparental intermittent incubator: The starling  Costs of reproduction: An evaluation of the empirical evidence  Energetics of reproduction in birds  Geographic variation in nests of Yellow Warblers breeding in Churchill, Manitoba, and Elgin, Ontario  An overview of the evolutionary causes and consequences of behavioural plasticity  Energetics of incubation  An experimental study of incubation effort in high-Arctic Barnacle Geese  Thermal tolerance of avian embryos: A review  The effects of nest size and insulation on thermal properties of Tree Swallow nests  Optimal development of avian embryos occurs within a narrow range of incubation temperatures. Most parents that physically incubate their eggs through direct contact are challenged to balance their time on the nest with taking foraging recesses to satisfy their energetic requirements. To explore the costs and investment strategies of incubating female Wood Ducks (  Aix sponsa  ), we manipulated the microclimate of nests by reducing down insulation from the typical 4.0 g to 0.5 g. Cooling rates of clutches during morning recesses increased when down insulation was reduced, especially at low ambient temperatures. Females with reduced down responded to increased cooling rates by shortening morning recesses and increasing daily incubation constancy, and these behavioral changes were independent of their body mass at the start of incubation. Females in both treatment groups responded similarly to changes in ambient temperature and spent less time incubating as ambient temperatures increased. Clutch temperatures at the end of morning recesses were similar for females with reduced and normal insulation. Average clutch temperatures for the full incubation period did not differ between treatments, and, correspondingly, there were no differences in length of the incubation period, hatching success, or duckling phenotype. Our results show that female Wood Ducks were sensitive to changes in both clutch temperature and ambient temperature and that they modified their time on the nest to provide developing eggs with an optimal thermal environment without negatively affecting their body mass at the end of incubation. Further examination of the limits of behavioral plasticity in incubating birds will be essential, particularly in light of future challenges presented by climate change.  El desarrollo &oacute;ptimo de los embriones de aves ocurre dentro de un rango estrecho de temperaturas de incubaci&oacute;n. La mayor&iacute;a de los padres que incuban f&iacute;sicamente sus huevos por medio del contacto directo se enfrentan al desaf&iacute;o de balancear su tiempo en el nido con la toma de recesos para alimentarse y satisfacer sus requerimientos energ&eacute;ticos. Para explorar los costos y las estrategias de inversi&oacute;n de las hembras incubadoras de   Aix sponsa  , manipulamos el microclima de los nidos al reducir el aislamiento por plumones de los 4.0 g t&iacute;picos a s&oacute;lo 0.5 g. Las tasas de enfriamiento de las nidadas durante los recesos de la ma&ntilde;ana se incrementaron cuando se redujo el aislamiento por plumones, especialmente a bajas temperaturas ambientales. Las hembras con reducci&oacute;n del plum&oacute;n respondieron al incremento en las tasas de enfriamiento acortando los recesos de la ma&ntilde;ana e incrementando la constancia diaria de incubaci&oacute;n, y estos cambios de comportamiento fueron independientes de su masa corporal al inicio de la incubaci&oacute;n. Las hembras en ambos tratamientos respondieron similarmente a los cambios en la temperatura ambiental y pasaron menos tiempo incubando a medida que las temperaturas ambientales aumentaban. La temperatura de la nidada al final de los recesos de la ma&ntilde;ana fue similar para las hembras con aislamiento normal y reducido. Adem&aacute;s, la temperatura promedio de la nidada por el periodo completo de incubaci&oacute;n no fue diferente entre tratamientos, y no hubo diferencias en la longitud del periodo de incubaci&oacute;n, el &eacute;xito de eclosi&oacute;n, o el fenotipo de los polluelos. Demostramos que las hembras de   Aix sponsa   fueron sensibles a los cambios en la temperatura de la nidada y en la temperatura ambiental, y modificaron su tiempo en el nido para brindar a los huevos en desarrollo un ambiente t&eacute;rmico &oacute;ptimo sin afectar negativamente su masa corporal al final del periodo de incubaci&oacute;n. Un examen m&aacute;s profundo de los l&iacute;mites de la plasticidad del comportamiento en las aves que incuban ser&aacute; esencial, particularmente a la luz de los futuros desaf&iacute;os que impone el cambio clim&aacute;tico.   Palabras clave:  Aix sponsa  , Anatidae, comportamiento de incubaci&oacute;n, compromisos, costos reproductivos, temperatura de incubaci&oacute;n  Incubating birds must balance the competing demands of satisfying their own energetic requirements and maintaining proper thermal environments for developing embryos. Avian eggs begin to develop at 24&ndash;27&deg;C, but optimal development of embryos occurs between 35.5&deg;C and 38.5&deg;C ( Webb 1987 ). Reduced incubation temperature affects offspring phenotype and slows embryonic development, resulting in longer incubation periods and increased risk of nest predation ( Reid et al. 2002 ,  Hepp et al. 2006 ,  Olson et al. 2006 ). Incubation is metabolically expensive, and incubation recesses allow time for parents to forage and meet energetic costs ( Reid et al. 2002 ,  Tinbergen and Williams 2002 ). The evolution of incubation strategies has been shaped by various constraints, including food availability, temperature, and nest predation risk (e.g.,  Conway and Martin 2000b ). Within species, avian incubation rhythms are flexible and respond to factors such as female condition ( Criscuolo et al. 2002 ), predation risk ( Ghalambor et al. 2013 ), ambient temperature ( Conway and Martin 2000a ), egg temperature ( Reid et al. 2002 ), and incubation stage ( Cooper and Voss 2013 ). Number, length, and timing of recesses can influence incubation temperatures and the metabolic cost of incubation ( Deeming and Ferguson 1991 ,  Martin et al. 2007 ).  Reproductive costs often are best estimated using manipulative experiments ( Reznick 1985 ). Studies of incubation costs, for example, have manipulated clutch size, the length of the incubation period, or the thermal property of nests. Enlarging clutch size resulted in longer incubation periods in European Pied Flycatchers (  Ficedula hypoleuca  ;  Nord and Nilsson 2012 ) and Northern Lapwings (  Vanellus vanellus  ;  Larsen et al. 2003 ); reduced immune function, body mass, and future fecundity in incubating Common Eiders (  Somateria mollissima  ;  Hanssen et al. 2005 ); and decreased future survival and reproduction in Great Tits (  Parus major  ;  de Heij et al. 2006 ). Experimental lengthening of incubation periods caused an increased loss of body mass and reduced hatching success in Barnacle Geese (  Branta leucopsis  ;  Tombre and Erikstad 1996 ). The removal of nesting material or lining, specifically contour feathers from swallow (Family: Hirundinidae) nests, increased parental nest attendance and shortened length of daily recesses ( M&oslash;ller 1991 ), as well as slowed nestling growth ( Lombardo et al. 1995 ,  Dawson et al. 2011 ).  P&eacute;rez et al. (2008)  and  Ardia et al. (2009)  reduced energetic constraints of incubating Tree Swallows (  Tachycineta bicolor  ) by heating nest boxes, and females of heated nest boxes increased incubation constancy and egg temperature, ended incubation in better body condition, and raised nestlings that were larger and in better condition than for females of unheated nest boxes. Therefore, it is clear that incubation is an important reproductive cost in birds that can limit both current and future reproductive success and potentially influence the evolution of avian life histories ( Heaney and Monaghan 1996 ,  Reid et al. 2000 ,  2002 ,  Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ,  2012 ,  DuRant et al. 2013 ).  The Wood Duck (  Aix sponsa  ) is a relatively small-bodied, cavity-nesting duck species. Females alone incubate, take 2 recesses day &minus;1 , and spend &gt;80&percnt; of the day on the nest ( Manlove and Hepp 2000 ,  Folk and Hepp 2003 ). Conspecific brood parasitism is common in Wood Ducks, and parasitized clutches frequently exceed 20 eggs and result in lengthened incubation periods ( Hepp et al. 1990 ). During egg laying, females remove feather down from their belly and breast to line nests and cover eggs during incubation recesses. Incubation temperature ranges between 34.8&deg;C and 37.8&deg;C, and incubation period averages 32 days ( Hepp et al. 2006 ). Low incubation temperature has been shown to negatively affect offspring quality in Wood Ducks. Embryos of eggs that were artificially incubated at temperatures &lt;35.9&deg;C developed slowly, expended more energy, and hatched with reduced nutrient reserves compared with those incubated at higher temperatures ( Hepp et al. 2006 ,  DuRant et al. 2011 ). Further, these ducklings had higher baseline and stress-induced corticosterone levels ( DuRant et al. 2010 ), decreased growth and acquired immunity responses ( DuRant et al. 2012a ), and reduced locomotor performance ( Hopkins et al. 2011 ) and expended more energy for thermoregulation ( DuRant et al. 2012b ) than ducklings from eggs incubated at higher temperatures. Effects of low incubation temperature (&lt;35.9&deg;C) carried over to subsequent life history stages and negatively affected survival, recruitment to the breeding population, and reproductive success of female Wood Ducks ( Hepp and Kennamer 2012 ). Current evidence suggests that incubation is an important reproductive cost in Wood Ducks, but nesting date and female quality may help mediate these costs ( Hepp et al. 1990 ,  2005 ,  Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ).  In the present study, we further investigated incubation costs of Wood Ducks by altering the thermal properties of naturally incubated nests. We manipulated the amount of down insulation in nests and examined tradeoffs between female incubation behavior, incubation temperature, and length of the incubation period. We compared females with reduced levels of down (0.5 g) to females with normal levels of down (4.0 g). We predicted that nests with reduced insulation would cool faster during incubation recesses. Because we know that low incubation temperature in Wood Ducks lengthens the incubation period and influences offspring quality ( DuRant et al. 2013 ), we predicted that females with reduced insulation would seek to maintain optimal incubation temperature by taking shorter incubation recesses and spending more time on the nest. However, investment decisions of incubating females should be condition dependent. Therefore, we predicted that females starting incubation at relatively low body mass would be more likely to invest in self-maintenance than in maintaining optimal egg temperatures.  We conducted the study at the U.S. Department of Energy's Savannah River Site in west-central South Carolina, USA (33&deg;1&prime;N, 81&deg;3&prime;W), in January&ndash;July, 2011 and 2012. Wooden nest boxes specific for Wood Ducks had previously been attached to posts and placed over water at Par Pond ( n  &equals; 87) and other wetlands ( n  &equals; 24;  Bellrose and Holm 1994 ). During the present study, nest boxes were checked every 4 days for nesting activity. When nests were located, eggs were measured (length and breadth &lsqb;mm&rsqb;) and chronologically labeled with a permanent marker to record laying order within the clutch. Wood Ducks lay 1 egg day &minus;1  ( Drobney 1980 ), and the date of nest initiation was estimated by subtracting the number of eggs in the nest when it was first discovered from the date the nest was checked ( Hepp and Kennamer 1993 ). Brood parasitism is common in Wood Ducks, so when the number of eggs in initiated nests outnumbered the days between nest checks, the day after the previous check was assumed to be the day of nest initiation.  Incubating females were captured at the nest during the first and last week of incubation. At first capture, unmarked females were banded with U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service leg bands and aged as adult (after second year) or yearling (second year;  Harvey et al. 1989 ). All females were weighed to the nearest 5 g with a 1,000-g Pesola scale, and tarsus length (&plusmn;0.1 mm), wing length from wrist to edge of longest primary (&plusmn;1 mm), and culmen length (&plusmn;0.1 mm) were measured.  We installed temperature data loggers (HOBO U23, Pro version 2; Onset Computer, Bourne, Massachusetts, USA) in nests during egg laying to monitor incubation behaviors ( Manlove and Hepp 1998 ,  2000 ). Briefly, all nesting material was removed, and a platform containing a wooden egg with an embedded thermistor was placed in the nest box. The wooden egg was securely fastened to the platform so that the female could not reposition the egg, and the egg with the thermistor was placed in the center of the nest. Nesting material and eggs were returned to the nest, and the wooden egg was positioned so that the thermistor would come in direct contact with the incubating female's brood patch. These loggers recorded temperatures every 6.4 min ( n  &equals; 225 day &minus;1 ). Temperature data were downloaded and plotted for each 24-hr period. Data from these plots provided an accurate method of determining presence and absence of incubating females ( Manlove and Hepp 2000 ). We used these data to compute morning recess length (min), incubation constancy (percentage of day spent on the nest incubating), and average daily clutch temperature. Incubation was initiated on the first day that females spent portions of the day and night on the nest, and hatch date was the day prior to ducklings exiting the nest box ( Hepp et al. 2006 ). Incubation period was the number of days between onset of incubation and day of hatching. Any days during which we disturbed the hen's natural incubation rhythm, including days when captures were attempted, were not used in our analysis. In 2012, an iButton (i-Button, Maxim Integrated Products, San Jose, California, USA) was attached with epoxy to the blunt end of the wooden egg to calculate clutch cooling rates (&deg;C min &minus;1 ) during morning incubation recesses. This data logger was positioned in the nest at the same level as the rest of the eggs and recorded temperature every 6 min ( n  &equals; 240 day &minus;1 ).  We also installed iButtons inside nest boxes in a standardized location at the back of the box, 10 cm below the entrance hole, to measure ambient nest-box temperature (&plusmn;0.5&deg;C) every 30 min ( n  &equals; 48 day &minus;1 ). Mean daily ambient temperature and mean morning ambient temperatures were calculated for each box. Morning temperatures were calculated from 0500 to 1000 hours to coincide with the period of morning recess activity ( Bellrose and Holm 1994 ).  We considered full incubation to have started when females began spending portions of both the day and night on the nest. On the morning of the fifth day of full incubation, we manipulated the amount of down insulation in nests to either normal (4.0 g) or reduced (0.5 g) amounts. All insulation in the nest was removed and replaced with cleaned, premeasured down. The normal amount of down was similar to amounts measured previously in natural nests on Par Pond (3.8 &plusmn; 1.2 g;  n  &equals; 12). Manipulations of down were completed when females were away from the nest during early-morning recesses to minimize disturbance to incubating females. A pilot study in 2011 showed that females ( n  &equals; 10) with reduced down (0.5 g) compensated very little for the loss of down, adding just 0.03 &plusmn; 0.17 g. We also standardized the clutch to the first 12 viable eggs at this time. In subsequent visits to the nest, any new eggs were removed, because nests were sometimes parasitized after the start of incubation. We visited nests after ducklings had fledged to determine hatching success.  We chose to reduce down to 0.5 g because it successfully increased cooling rates across different ambient temperatures while still leaving enough down to allow for a thin layer to cover the eggs. Egg cooling rates for 4.0 g and 0.5 g of down were tested in environmental chambers (Environmental Growth Chambers, Chagrin Falls, OH, USA) with temperatures set at 7&deg;C, 15&deg;C, and 22&deg;C ( n  &equals; 6,  n  &equals; 10, and  n  &equals; 10, respectively). Clutches of 12 undeveloped Wood Duck eggs were warmed in incubators to an average temperature of 37.6&deg;C. To accurately measure egg temperatures, we drilled a small hole in 1 of the eggs, placed a thermistor in the albumen, and sealed the hole with silicone gel. Warmed clutches were placed immediately into nest boxes in the environmental chamber. Egg temperature was recorded every 1.2 min (Stowaway, Onset Computer, Bourne, MA, USA), and eggs were allowed to cool for 2 hr. Cooling rates from these clutches were linearly estimated and averaged for each treatment and temperature group.  During the last week of incubation in 2012, we randomly selected and removed 2 eggs (1 each from early &lsqb;days 2&ndash;5&rsqb; and late &lsqb;days 7&ndash;9&rsqb; in the laying sequence) from each experimental nest ( n  &equals; 24). These eggs were brought to the lab and placed in an incubator at 37.6&deg;C. When eggs pipped, they were transferred to a brooder to hatch. Hatched ducklings were weighed and sexed, and the tarsus and culmen were measured within 12 hr of hatching. Ducklings were euthanized using CO 2  inhalation and cervical dislocation. Ducklings were placed in individually labeled plastic bags and frozen for later processing.  Duckling body composition was determined using methods of  Hepp et al. (2006) . Ducklings were thawed and dried (65&deg;C) to constant mass. Dry ducklings were ground and neutral lipids were extracted from whole ducklings in a Soxhlet apparatus using petroleum ether ( Dobush et al. 1985 ). Lean samples were dried to constant mass, and lipid content was the difference in mass of the dry sample before and after lipid extraction. Total lipid mass was calculated by multiplying the proportion of lipid in the dry, ground sample by the dry mass of the whole duckling. Lean dry mass was calculated by multiplying the proportion of nonlipid material in the dry, ground sample after lipid extraction and dry duckling mass. Lean dry samples were burned in a muffle furnace at 550&deg;C for 10 hr to determine ash content. Ash-free lean dry mass (AFLDM) was calculated as the difference between ash content of burned sample and lean dry mass. The proportion of AFLDM in the sample multiplied by the dry mass of the duckling provided an estimate of the duckling's protein mass ( Ricklefs 1974 ).  All data summaries and statistical tests were completed using SAS 9.3 ( SAS Institute 2011 ). We tested effects of insulation treatment and ambient temperature on clutch cooling rates during morning recesses and clutch temperature at the end of morning recesses using mixed linear models (Proc MIXED) and restricted maximum-likelihood (REML) methods. We evaluated the covariance structure of models using Akaike's Information Criterion and chose autoregressive covariance for use in all mixed linear models. Insulation treatment and ambient nest-box temperature were fixed effects, nests were random effects, and repeated measures were used within nests. Interaction effects of insulation treatment and ambient temperature were removed from the model if effects were not significant ( P  &gt; 0.05).  Mixed linear models with repeated measures and an autoregressive covariance structure were fitted with REML and used to test effects of insulation treatment on morning recess length, incubation constancy, and daily clutch temperature. Models included fixed effects of insulation treatment, daily ambient nest-box temperature, day of incubation, early incubation female body mass, as well as the interaction of treatment with incubation day, female body mass, and ambient nest-box temperature. Individual females and repeated measures within nests were accounted for using random effects. We arcsine-transformed the square root of constancy before analysis.  We used one-way analyses of variance (Proc GLM) to test for differences in initiation date of incubation, incubation period length, early and late incubation body mass of females, percentage change in body mass, and hatching success (&percnt;). We arcsine-transformed the square root of hatching success and percent change in body mass before analysis. Effects of insulation treatment on wet and dry masses of ducklings and their body components (lipid, protein, and ash) were tested using mixed linear models. Models accounted for the fixed effects of insulation treatment and fresh egg mass, random effects of nests, and repeated measures of eggs within nests. For mixed linear models, we present least-squares means and use Tukey's test for separation of means; otherwise, means &plusmn; SE are presented.  Nests were randomly assigned to treatments in 2011 and 2012, and we manipulated the amount of insulation in Wood Duck nests (normal insulation, 4.0 g,  n  &equals; 17; reduced insulation, 0.5 g,  n  &equals; 17) on day 5.12 &plusmn; 0.16 of incubation. Date of incubation initiation did not differ between treatments ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 1.33,  P  &equals; 0.28) and averaged March 25 &plusmn; 2 days (range: March 7&ndash;April 30). Body mass of females at the onset of incubation was 567.5 &plusmn; 5.5 g (range: 495&ndash;635 g) and did not differ between treatments ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 0.52,  P  &equals; 0.49).  In 2012, we measured cooling rates of clutches ( n  &equals; 9 normal and  n  &equals; 10 reduced insulation) during 447 morning recesses. Insulation treatment ( F  1,&thinsp;17  &equals; 17.42,  P  &equals; 0.0007), ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;426  &equals; 339.57,  P  &lt; 0.0001), and the interaction of treatment and ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;426  &equals; 9.13,  P  &equals; 0.003) influenced clutch cooling rates. Clutch temperature declined more slowly with increasing ambient nest-box temperature for nests with normal insulation (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.0033 &plusmn; 0.0003&deg;C min &minus;1 ) than for nests with reduced insulation (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.0046 &plusmn; 0.0003&deg;C min &minus;1 ). Least-squares mean cooling rate was greater for clutches with reduced insulation (&minus;0.083 &plusmn; 0.004&deg;C min &minus;1 ) than for clutches with normal insulation (&minus;0.067 &plusmn; 0.004&deg;C min &minus;1 ;  t  &equals; 2.82, df &equals; 17,  P  &equals; 0.01). Our experiments with egg cooling rates in environmental chambers showed similar effects of insulation treatment and ambient temperature on cooling rate ( Figure 1 ). Eggs with reduced insulation cooled faster than eggs with normal amounts of insulation, and these differences increased as ambient temperature declined.  Mean (&plusmn; SE) cooling rates of Wood Duck eggs housed in environmental chambers at 7&deg;C, 15&deg;C, and 22&deg;C with normal (4.0 g) and reduced (0.5 g) feather down insulation.  Temperature of clutches at the end of morning recesses was not influenced by the interactions of insulation treatment with ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;425  &equals; 0.39,  P  &equals; 0.53) or female body mass at the onset of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;425  &equals; 0.26,  P  &equals; 0.61) , so the interaction terms were dropped from the model. Clutch temperature at the end of morning recesses increased with higher ambient temperatures ( F  1,&thinsp;426  &equals; 202.17,  P  &lt; 0.0001; &beta; &equals; 0.359 &plusmn; 0.025) but was not affected by insulation treatment ( F  1,&thinsp;17  &equals; 0.47,  P  &equals; 0.51) or by female body mass ( F  1,&thinsp;426  &equals; 0.68,  P  &equals; 0.41) . Least-squares mean temperature of clutches when females returned from morning recesses was 30.48 &plusmn; 0.55&deg;C for nests with normal insulation and 29.95 &plusmn; 0.52&deg;C for nests with reduced insulation. Clutch temperatures were 14.47 &plusmn; 0.47&deg;C warmer than ambient temperatures when females returned from morning recesses.  Daily incubation behaviors of females ( n  &equals; 17 normal and  n  &equals; 17 reduced insulation) were measured for a total of 686 days. Interactions of insulation treatment with ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 1.26,  P  &equals; 0.26), body mass of females at the onset of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;30  &equals; 0.55,  P  &equals; 0.47), and day of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 2.38,  P  &equals; 0.12) did not influence morning recess length, so they were removed from the model before testing main effects. Length of morning recesses declined as the day of incubation progressed ( F  1,&thinsp;650  &equals; 9.57,  P  &equals; 0.002; &beta; &equals; &minus;0.946 &plusmn; 0.306), but recess length was not affected by female body mass at the onset of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;31  &equals; 0.55,  P  &equals; 0.46) or ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;650  &equals; 2.69,  P  &equals; 0.10). Least-squares mean morning recess length was shorter for females with reduced insulation (93.92 &plusmn; 3.26 min) than for females with normal insulation (106.26 &plusmn; 3.39 min;  t  &equals; 2.61, df &equals; 31,  P  &equals; 0.014).  Daily incubation constancy averaged 83.0 &plusmn; 6.0&percnt; (range: 59.5&ndash;97.3&percnt;). Interactions of insulation treatment with ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 0.26,  P  &equals; 0.61), female body mass at the onset of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;30  &equals; 0.02,  P  &equals; 0.88), and day of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 2.70,  P  &equals; 0.10) did not affect incubation constancy. Incubation constancy declined with increasing ambient temperature (&beta; &equals; &minus;0.30 &plusmn; 0.05,  F  1,&thinsp;650  &equals; 34.83,  P  &lt; 0.001). Incubation constancy increased as the day of incubation progressed (&beta; &equals; 0.10 &plusmn; 0.05,  P  &equals; 0.047), but female body mass at the start of incubation had no effect on incubation constancy ( F  1,&thinsp;31  &equals; 1.17,  P  &equals; 0.29). Least-squares mean incubation constancy was greater for females with reduced insulation (84.48 &plusmn; 0.58&percnt;) than for females with normal insulation (81.89 &plusmn; 0.61&percnt;;  t  &equals; 3.07, df &equals; 31,  P  &equals; 0.004).  Daily clutch temperatures ( n  &equals; 17 normal and  n  &equals; 17 reduced insulation) were measured for 686 days. Interactions of insulation treatment with ambient nest-box temperature ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 1.62,  P  &equals; 0.20), female body mass at the onset of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;30  &equals; 3.17,  P  &equals; 0.09), and day of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;648  &equals; 0.86,  P  &equals; 0.35) did not affect clutch temperature, so interaction terms were removed from the model. There was a strong positive relationship between ambient nest-box temperature and daily clutch temperature (&beta; &equals; 0.054 &plusmn; 0.007&deg;C;  F  1,&thinsp;650  &equals; 59.40,  P  &lt; 0.001), and clutch temperature increased as the day of incubation advanced (&beta; &equals; 0.022 &plusmn; 0.010;  F  1,&thinsp;650  &equals; 4.75,  P  &equals; 0.03), but daily clutch temperature was not affected by early incubation body mass of females ( F  1,&thinsp;31  &equals; 0.01,  P  &equals; 0.92). Daily clutch temperature also did not vary with insulation treatment ( F  1,&thinsp;31  &equals; 0.95,  P  &equals; 0.34). Least-squares mean clutch temperature was 36.63 &plusmn; 0.14&deg;C for females with reduced insulation and 36.82 &plusmn; 0.14&deg;C for females with normal insulation.  We averaged daily clutch temperatures for each nest. Clutch temperature for the full incubation period ( n  &equals; 34) was 36.63 &plusmn; 0.12&deg;C (range: 34.10&ndash;38.07&deg;C) and did not vary with insulation treatment ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 0.26,  P  &equals; 0.62). Length of the incubation period ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 0.91,  P  &equals; 0.35), hatching success ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 0.24,  P  &equals; 0.63), percent loss of body mass ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 0.87,  P  &equals; 0.36), and female body mass at the end of incubation ( F  1,&thinsp;32  &equals; 2.18,  P  &equals; 0.15) also were not affected by insulation treatment ( Table 1 ). Using fresh egg mass as the covariate, wet mass ( F  1,&thinsp;23  &equals; 0.01,  P  &equals; 0.94), dry mass ( F  1,&thinsp;23  &equals; 0.00,  P  &equals; 0.98), and body components of ducklings (lipid:  F  1,&thinsp;21  &equals; 0.84,  P  &equals; 0.37; protein:  F  1,&thinsp;21  &equals; 1.36,  P  &equals; 0.26; and ash:  F  1,&thinsp;21  &equals; 0.56,  P  &equals; 0.46) were similar between insulation treatments ( Table 2 ).  Characteristics (means &plusmn; SE) of female Wood Ducks and nests with reduced (0.5 g) and normal (4.0 g) levels of down insulation. All comparisons between reduced- and normal-insulation nests were not significant ( P  &gt; 0.05).  Body mass and body composition (least-squares mean &plusmn; SE) of day-old Wood Duck ducklings hatched from nests with reduced (0.5 g) and normal (4.0 g) levels of down insulation. Fresh egg mass (mean &plusmn; SE) was used as the covariate. All least-squares means within rows are not significantly different ( P  &gt; 0.05).  We altered the microclimate of Wood Duck nests by manipulating the amount of down insulation. Clutches of eggs with reduced levels of down cooled faster than clutches with normal amounts of down, and differences in cooling rates were greater at low ambient temperatures. Females with reduced down insulation responded to increased cooling rates by shortening morning recesses and increasing overall incubation constancy. These behavioral changes were not influenced by female body mass. Plasticity of incubation behaviors helped females maintain an optimal thermal environment for developing embryos. Average clutch temperature (36.6&deg;C) for the full incubation period was similar between insulation treatments and was greater than incubation temperatures (&lt;35.9&deg;C) known to negatively affect a suite of phenotypic traits in Wood Duck neonates ( Hepp et al. 2006 ,  Hepp and Kennamer 2012 ,  DuRant et al. 2013 ). Behavioral plasticity allows organisms to respond and adapt to rapidly changing environments ( Snell-Rood 2013 ). Plasticity in various aspects of parental care and reproductive investment has been reported for many organisms, such as timing of nesting in Great Tits ( Nussey et al. 2005 ), changes in parental provisioning rates of nestling birds associated with predation risk ( Ghalambor et al. 2013 ), and nest-site selection in a turtle,   Chrysemys picta   ( Refsnider and Janzen 2012 ).  Birds use a variety of methods to help alter and maintain nest microclimate, which provides evidence for the importance of incubation temperature to the proper development of embryos ( Deeming 2002 ). Modifying incubation behaviors, as we have shown in Wood Ducks, is one method that affects incubation temperature and has been reported in many species (e.g.,  Martin et al. 2007 ). Nest size and structure can improve the thermal characteristics of nests ( Rohwer and Law 2010 ,  Mainwaring et al. 2012 ,  Heenan 2013 ), thereby helping to slow egg cooling rates ( Hilton et al. 2004 ,  Windsor et al. 2013 ). Selection of nest sites also can affect nest microclimate by influencing exposure to environmental conditions ( Nelson and Martin 1999 ,  Ardia et al. 2006 ). Further, parents at temperate latitudes can mediate the costs of incubation and help maintain optimal nest temperatures by simply nesting later in the season, when ambient temperatures are warmer ( Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ).  Recent studies have shown that Wood Duck eggs incubated at low temperatures developed more slowly and that embryos used more energy and hatched with fewer residual lipids ( Hepp et al. 2006 ,  DuRant et al. 2011 ,  Hepp and Kennamer 2012 ). These ducklings also had poor locomotor skills, reduced growth rates, reduced levels of immunocompetence, increased stress levels, and increased costs of thermoregulation compared with ducklings incubated at higher temperatures ( DuRant et al. 2010 ,  2011 ,  2012a ,  2012b ,  Hopkins et al. 2011 ). Further,  Hepp and Kennamer (2012)  showed that ducklings incubated at low temperatures were less likely to survive and reproduce than ducklings incubated at higher temperatures. Negative impacts of low incubation temperature also have been reported for other birds. For example, low incubation temperature negatively influenced the subsequent growth and metabolism of Blue Tits (  Cyanistes caeruleus  ;  Nord and Nilsson 2011 ) and the growth and innate immune function of Tree Swallows ( Ardia et al. 2010 ). However, effects of these phenotypic differences on fitness are still relatively unexplored.  It is clear that proper care of eggs is important for optimal reproductive success in birds, but incubation constancy and incubation temperature often vary within and between species ( Hepp et al. 2006 ,  Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ,  Martin et al. 2013 ). Incubation is costly for parents, and these costs increase with decreasing ambient temperature and increasing clutch size ( Reid et al. 2002 ,  Tinbergen and Williams 2002 ,  Nord et al. 2010 ). Parents that were energetically constrained often invested more in self-maintenance and spent less time on the nest ( Ardia et al. 2009 ,  MacDonald et al. 2013 ). However, tradeoffs can be mediated by parental quality ( Hanssen et al. 2003 ). In Wood Ducks, heavy females that were in good condition nested earlier, spent more time incubating, and lost more weight than females in poor condition that nested later in the season, when ambient temperatures were warmer ( Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ).  In the present study, female Wood Ducks did not appear to be energetically constrained. For example, they began incubation in better body condition than females from an earlier study of this population (567 vs. 543 g;  Hepp and Kennamer 2011 ) and lost &lt;3&percnt; of their body mass during incubation. As incubation costs increased with declining ambient temperature and greater clutch cooling rates, females spent more time on nests to keep eggs warm rather than investing in self-maintenance. These behavioral changes kept eggs at optimal developmental temperatures without negatively affecting female body condition. However, if environmental conditions had been more severe (i.e. colder temperatures or reduced habitat quality), we would have expected females, especially those starting incubation in relatively poor condition, to have reduced incubation effort and sacrificed clutch temperatures for self-maintenance. Modifying strategies and investing more in self-maintenance makes sense when females are energetically constrained, because finishing incubation at low body mass can reduce female survival ( Hepp et al. 1990 ).  We found that female Wood Ducks generally managed incubation costs successfully. Females were sensitive to changes in both ambient temperature and cooling rate of clutches and modified incubation behaviors to successfully maintain an optimal nest microclimate without affecting their body condition. The ability of females to make these changes and provide embryos with an optimal thermal environment ultimately depends on individual quality and prevailing environmental conditions. Incubation is an important reproductive cost, and successfully negotiating this cost can affect neonate quality as well as the survival and future reproduction of parents. In the future, how anticipated changes in climate and habitat quality influence tradeoffs between parents and offspring during this important period of reproduction in birds will be important areas of investigation.  Thanks are due to our field crew, J. McPherson, N. Allen, C. Weithman, and C. Gesmundo. We also thank T. Steury for statistical assistance, and the staff at the Savannah River Ecology Lab for support and hospitality. The Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Auburn University approved our research (PRN 2010-1691). Ducklings were collected under permits issued by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (MB 748024-0) and South Carolina (G-10-02). Research was supported by National Science Foundation grant IOB-0615361 to G.R.H., the Alabama Agricultural Experiment Station, and the Department of Energy under award DE-FC09-07SR22506 to the University of Georgia Research Foundation. 