Factors influencing nest survival and renesting by Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes regionCostly replacement: How do different stages of nest failure affect clutch replacement in the Red-backed Shrikes <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lanius collurio</named-content></italic>?Replacement clutches by Kentish PloversFactors affecting renesting in American CootsUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionFactors that affect renesting in Mallards (<italic>Anas platyrhnchos</italic>)Lme4: linear mixed-effects modeling using S4 classes. R package, version 2.15.3Renesting of Common Terns <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic> in the life history perspectiveTiming of current reproductive output in European CootsSurvival of Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) chicks in the Great Lakes regionBiology and behavior of breeding Piping PloversDivorce in birds: A review of the hypothesesDifferential maternal investment counteracts for late breeding in Magpies <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pica pica</named-content></italic>: An experimental studyEffects of spring body condition and age on reproduction in Mallards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>)Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)Renesting by Dusky Canada Geese on the Copper River Delta, AlaskaKittiwakes strategically reduce investment in replacement clutchesNest survival in Dusky Canada Geese (<italic>Branta Canadensis occidentalis</italic>): Use of discrete time modelsTime-specific variation in passerine nest survival: New insights into old questionsTime-specific patterns of nest survival for ducks and passerines breeding in North DakotaTotal plasma protein and renesting by Greater Sage-grouseFitness consequences of timing of breeding birds: Date effects in the course of a reproductive episodeMate, site, and territory fidelity in Piping PloversReproductive success of Piping Plovers at Big Quill Lake, SaskatchewanFitness-related consequences of relaying in an Arctic seabird: Survival of offspring to recruitment ageAre nest exclosures an effective tool in plover conservation?Variability in nest survival rates and implications to nesting studiesA multi-scale investigation of Piping Plover productivity on Great Plains alkali lakes, 1994&ndash;2000Working less to gain more: When breeding quality relates to foraging efficiencyBehavioral responses to higher predation risk in a subarctic population of the Semipalmated PloverThe role of behavioral dominance in structuring patterns of habitat occupancy in a migrant bird during the nonbreeding seasonNatal philopatry and recruitment of Willow Ptarmigan in north central and northwestern CanadaA quantitative framework to evaluate incidental take and endangered species population viabilityEstimating the nest-success rate and the number of nests initiated by radiomarked MallardsPredator exclosures: A technique to reduce predation at Piping Plover nestsPredation on adult Piping Plovers at predator exclosure cagesEffect of mammalian predator management on Snowy Plover breeding successSources of variation in clutch size, egg size and clutch completion dates of Semipalmated Plovers in Churchill, ManitobaAugmenting small populations of plovers: An assessment of cross-fostering and captive-rearingCaptive-rearing Piping Plovers: Developing techniques to augment wild populationsApparent nest abandonment as evidence of breeding-season mortality in Great Lakes Piping Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)Relative fitness of wild and captive-reared Piping Plovers: Does egg salvage contribute to recovery of the endangered Great Lakes population?Modeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SASSeasonal declines in the fecundity of Arctic-breeding sandpipers: Different tactics in two species with an invariant clutch sizeAge-specific survival and recruitment of piping plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) in the Great Lakes regionFemale site familiarity increases fledging success in Piping Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)Making meaningful estimates of nest survival with model-based methodsWeight-related renesting in Capercaillie <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tetrao urogallus</named-content></italic>Distribution of non-breeding Great Lakes Piping Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) along the Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico coastlines: Ten years of band sightingsBody mass changes in female Tawny Pipits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anthus campestris</named-content></italic> during the nesting stageInfluence of disturbance and predation on breeding success of the African Black Oystercatcher, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Haematopus moquini</named-content></italic>, on Robben Island, South AfricaSeasonal variation in local recruitment of Great Tits: The importance of being earlyThe timing of birds' breeding seasons: A review of experiments that manipulated timing of breedingA habitat-based population model for the Great Lakes population of the Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>)Parental care of replacement clutches in Common Terns (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sterna hirundo</named-content></italic>)Renesting is an important breeding strategy used by birds to compensate for nest failure. If birds renest, clutch removal for captive rearing can be used to augment endangered populations; however, not all individuals renest following nest loss, and later nesting attempts may have lower survival rates and clutch sizes. We investigated variation in nest initiation date, clutch size, daily nest survival, renesting propensity, and renesting intervals of federally endangered Great Lakes Piping Plovers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) from 1993 to 2010. We also compared productivity under hypothetical clutch removal for captive rearing vs. non-removal scenarios. Nest initiation date was earlier for older adults and was more strongly affected by female than male age. Clutch size and nest survival decreased with later nest initiation, and nest survival increased with male age and nest age until close to hatching. Overall, Piping Plovers replaced 49&percnt; of failed nests. Renesting propensity decreased with later date, increased with each successive nesting attempt, and varied according to cause of failure; probability of renesting was highest following flooding and lowest for inviable clutches. Renesting intervals increased with age of the previous nest and averaged 4.2 days longer for birds that changed mates. Results also indicated that, compared to leaving eggs in situ, clutch removal for captive rearing would produce 43&percnt; fewer 1-year-old recruits, partly because renesting does not fully offset clutch removal; therefore, efforts to increase fledging success in this endangered population should focus on proactively protecting nests in situ rather than relying on collection of eggs for captive rearing.La anidaci&oacute;n repetida es una importante estrategia reproductiva usada por las aves para compensar el fracaso de un nido. Si las aves vuelven a anidar, la remoci&oacute;n de las nidadas para su cr&iacute;a en cautiverio puede ser usada para aumentar las poblaciones amenazadas. Sin embargo, no todos los individuos vuelven a anidar luego de la p&eacute;rdida de sus nidos y los intentos posteriores de anidaci&oacute;n podr&iacute;an tener menores tasas de supervivencia y tama&ntilde;os de nidada. Investigamos la variaci&oacute;n en la fecha de inicio de anidaci&oacute;n, el tama&ntilde;o de la nidada, la supervivencia diaria de los nidos, la predisposici&oacute;n a volver a anidar y los intervalos entre nidadas de un ave amenazada a nivel federal, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>, entre 1993 y 2010. Tambi&eacute;n comparamos la productividad bajo la remoci&oacute;n hipot&eacute;tica de los nidos para su cr&iacute;a en cautiverio contra escenarios de no remoci&oacute;n. La fecha de inicio de la anidaci&oacute;n fue m&aacute;s temprana para adultos mayores y se vio m&aacute;s fuertemente afectada por la edad de las hembras que por la edad de los machos. El tama&ntilde;o y la supervivencia de la nidada disminuyeron cuando la anidaci&oacute;n comenz&oacute; m&aacute;s tarde, y la supervivencia se increment&oacute; con la edad de los machos y con la edad del nido hasta justo antes de la eclosi&oacute;n. En general, la poblaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. melodus</named-content></italic> reemplaz&oacute; el 49&percnt; de los nidos perdidos. La predisposici&oacute;n a volver a anidar disminuy&oacute; con fechas m&aacute;s tard&iacute;as, se increment&oacute; con cada intento sucesivo de anidaci&oacute;n y vari&oacute; de acuerdo a la causa de fracaso de los nidos; la probabilidad de volver a anidar fue mayor luego de inundaciones y menor en nidadas no viables. Los intervalos entre intentos de anidaci&oacute;n se incrementaron con la edad del nido anterior y en promedio fueron 4.2 d&iacute;as m&aacute;s largos en aves que cambiaron de pareja. Los resultados tambi&eacute;n indican que, en comparaci&oacute;n con dejar los huevos in situ, la remoci&oacute;n de la nidada para su cr&iacute;a en cautiverio producir&iacute;a 43&percnt; menos aves reclutas de un a&ntilde;o de edad, en parte debido a que la anidaci&oacute;n repetida no sobrepasa totalmente la remoci&oacute;n de la nidada. Por ende, los esfuerzos para incrementar el &eacute;xito de emplumamiento en esta poblaci&oacute;n amenazada deber&iacute;an enfocarse en la protecci&oacute;n proactiva de los nidos in situ en vez de basarse en la recolecta de los huevos para su cr&iacute;a en cautiverio.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content>,</italic> cr&iacute;a en cautiverio, especie amenazada, &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n, nidada de reemplazo, tama&ntilde;o de nidadaRenesting is an important reproductive strategy, especially among bird species with high rates of nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Sandercock1">Sandercock et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Hipfner1">Hipfner 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Lishman1">Lishman et al. 2010</xref>); however, the relative value of renesting is tempered by the fact that renesting attempts may be less successful or produce poorer quality young than earlier nesting attempts. For many species, clutch size and nest survival decline as the breeding season progresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Klett1">Klett and Johnson 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Tjorve1">Tj&oslash;rve and Underhill 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Verhulst1">Verhulst and Nilsson 2008</xref>), and replacement nests, which necessarily occur later in the year than initial nests, may have smaller clutches and lower survival rates than first nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Storaas1">Storaas et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Suarez1">Suarez et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Gregg1">Gregg et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Devries1">Devries et al. 2008</xref>). Likewise, pre- and post-fledging survival may be lower for young hatched later in the season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Gruebler1">Gr&uuml;ebler and Naef-Daenzer 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>) and for young hatched from renesting attempts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Martin1">Martin and Hannon 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-DeNeve1">De Neve et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Becker1">Becker and Zhang 2011</xref>).Potential reasons for seasonal declines in reproductive success include decreases in food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Verhulst1">Verhulst and Nilsson 2008</xref>), changes in predator dynamics or environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Grant1">Grant et al. 2005</xref>), variation in parental quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. 2012</xref>), or time constraints on migration or other post-breeding activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Verboven1">Verboven and Visser 1998</xref>). Also, lower survival of replacement nests may occur if physical condition of breeding adults declines with subsequent nesting attempts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Gasparini1">Gasparini et al. 2006</xref>).Even among species capable of renesting, not all individuals will renest after nest failure. Renesting propensity, the likelihood of renesting following nest failure, may vary according to timing of the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Amat1">Amat et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brinkhoff1">Brinkhoff et al. 2002</xref>), number of previous nesting attempts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>), age of the previous nest at the time of nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Fondell1">Fondell et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Antczak1">Antczak et al. 2009</xref>), or the age, experience, and physical condition of breeding adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>).Timing of a renesting attempt is influenced by date of previous nest failure and the amount of time it takes for a bird to initiate a replacement nest (i.e. the renesting interval). The renesting interval may vary according to season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Becker1">Becker and Zhang 2011</xref>), number of previous nesting attempts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>), age of the previous nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Fondell1">Fondell et al. 2006</xref>), or quality of breeding adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>). Also, renesting intervals may vary depending on type of nest failure (e.g., predation vs. abandonment) or whether breeding birds change mates or locations between subsequent nesting attempts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Amat1">Amat et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Lishman1">Lishman et al. 2010</xref>).The Piping Plover (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Charadrius melodus</named-content></italic>) is a small migratory shorebird with breeding populations in the Atlantic Coast, Great Plains, and Great Lakes region; the Great Lakes breeding population is federally endangered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-CommitteeontheStatusofEndangeredWildlifeinCanadaCOSEWIC1">COSEWIC 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Great Lakes Piping Plover numbers declined dramatically from the 1950s to 1990, prompting intensive conservation efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Low reproductive success is thought to have contributed to the species' decline, and conservation efforts in the U.S. have focused primarily on protecting Piping Plover breeding sites in the Great Lakes region, including the use of predator exclosures to safeguard nests and beach closures to minimize human disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>).A male Piping Plover brooding 5-day-old chicks. Male and female Piping Plovers share incubation and chick-tending duties, but females may desert broods before they fledge. Photo credit: Roger ErikssonBecause Piping Plovers nest on the ground, near water, and in exposed areas with little vegetative cover, their nests are especially vulnerable to predation, flooding, and disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wemmer1">Wemmer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Knetter1">Knetter et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Piping Plovers are known to renest following the loss of earlier nests and may renest several times during the breeding season if their nests continue to fail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Cairns1">Cairns 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>). A study of individually marked Piping Plovers in Manitoba found no difference in hatching success between first nests and renests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>), but causes and consequences of individual variation in renesting propensity were not investigated. In a study of unmarked Piping Plovers in Saskatchewan, seasonal declines in hatching success and clutch size were speculated to be an effect of renesting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Harris1">Harris et al. 2005</xref>); however, first nests could not confidently be separated from renests. The Great Lakes population has a high proportion (&gt;90&percnt;) of individually color-banded adults, presenting an opportunity to investigate sources of variation in renesting behavior by individual Piping Plovers.From a conservation perspective, it is important to assess how renesting contributes to overall reproductive success of Great Lakes Piping Plovers and to ensure the effectiveness of management strategies employed to augment this federally endangered population. One current strategy is egg salvage from recently abandoned nests for captive rearing and release of fledged chicks back into the wild (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Powell1">Powell and Cuthbert 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Powell2">Powell et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>). Proactive population augmentation has also been considered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>), which would entail active collection of eggs from first nests for captive rearing, assuming that wild birds will renest with little impact to overall reproductive success. Captive-reared individuals, however, have lower survival and reproductive success than wild-reared birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>). Furthermore, not all wild individuals will renest following clutch removal, and replacement clutches will be initiated later in the season and likely have lower reproductive success. Thus, any serious consideration of proactive clutch removal for captive rearing must properly measure the costs associated with renesting.The objectives of our study were to investigate causes and consequences of variation in (1) timing of nest initiation, (2) clutch size, (3) daily nest survival, (4) renesting propensity, and (5) length of the renesting interval. Specifically, we sought to understand and quantify the contribution that renesting behavior makes to overall reproductive success while also measuring the cost of delay, which is an inevitable consequence of renesting. This information has important management implications for Great Lakes Piping Plovers and other shorebird populations whose nests are affected by incidental take (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-McGowan1">McGowan and Ryan 2009</xref>). Our results can also be used to assess the costs and benefits of proactive vs. salvage egg collection programs for Great Lakes Piping Plovers.Since 1993, Piping Plovers have been banded with U.S. Geological Survey metal and Darvic colored bands and monitored annually in the Great Lakes region of North America. The study area included public and private sites on Lakes Michigan, Huron, and Superior used by breeding Piping Plovers during 1993&ndash;2010; the majority of sites were in Michigan, and a few were in eastern Wisconsin and southern Ontario, Canada (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f01">figure 1</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>). Sites consisted of wide, sparsely vegetated sand and gravel lakeshore beaches, the preferred breeding habitat of Piping Plovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wemmer1">Wemmer et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>).We analyzed Piping Plover nest data collected from 1993 to 2010 by a network of contributing partners as part of an ongoing recovery effort for the Great Lakes population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Shoreline surveys were conducted each year from late April to early August to locate nesting sites of Piping Plovers. Once located, nests were monitored until termination (i.e. until all eggs either hatched or were determined to have failed). Nests were usually visited every 1&ndash;2 days, although a few sites (&sim;7&percnt;) were visited less regularly with intervals between visits ranging from 3 to 9 days. For each nest, data were collected on clutch size, nesting attempt, nest fate (success or failure), date of hatch or failure, cause of nest failure, and adult identities. In cases of nest abandonment (i.e. nest unattended for &ge;4&ndash;5 hours), eggs were collected for captive rearing.Predator exclosures consisting of wire fencing and plastic mesh were erected immediately upon location of a nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Small, wire mesh box exclosures were used during egg laying and until full-sized exclosures could be erected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Melvin1">Melvin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>). Predator exclosures were used for nearly all nests; 100&percnt; of nests have been protected by this method since 2004 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. 2012</xref>). Additionally, rope fencing and signs were used to cordon off many of the nesting beaches to reduce human disturbance. Adult Piping Plovers were nest-trapped during mid-incubation and fitted with unique individual colored band combinations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2003</xref>).We investigated causes of variation in nest initiation date, clutch size, daily nest survival rate (DSR), renesting propensity, and length of the renesting interval. We examined only the nesting period (egg laying and incubation stages) up until hatching. For nest survival analyses, a nest was defined as successful if at least one egg hatched under natural conditions or if the nest was brought to full term (34 days) before eggs were salvaged for captive rearing. For renesting propensity analyses, a nest was considered to have failed if eggs only hatched in captivity and was only considered successful if at least one egg hatched under natural conditions.We defined renesting propensity as the proportion of individuals that renested following a failed previous nesting attempt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold1">Arnold 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Fondell1">Fondell et al. 2006</xref>). We calculated the renest interval as the number of days between failure of a previous nest and initiation of the replacement nest; for example, if a nest failed on June 3 and the first replacement egg was laid on June 10, then the renest interval was estimated as 7 days. Number of nesting attempts was tallied assuming that we found all initiated nests, but we likely missed some nests that were destroyed during early laying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-McPherson1">McPherson et al. 2003</xref>), so counts of previous nests represent minimum values.Nest initiation dates were estimated by backdating, assuming a 2-day laying interval between eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-ElliottSmith1">Elliott-Smith and Haig 2004</xref>; E. A. Roche personal observation) plus a 28-day incubation period after the last egg was laid (see Results). For nests found after the last egg was laid, but failed prior to hatching and thus had unknown initiation dates (6&percnt; of nests), we assumed the nests were the average age of discovery (7 days old) and backdated accordingly. Birds of unknown age were assigned a minimum age of 1 the first time they were captured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche1">Roche et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. 2012</xref>). We considered a nest to be abandoned if adults were observed again during the breeding season or in a subsequent year, and we considered an adult to have died if it disappeared early in the breeding season during incubation and was not seen again during that breeding season or any subsequent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche1">Roche et al. 2010</xref>).For renesting analyses, we excluded birds presumed to have died (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche1">Roche et al. 2010</xref>) and therefore incapable of renesting, but the surviving mate was included in the analyses. For renesting propensity analyses, we only included breeding attempts that failed during the nesting stage; we excluded 8 pairs that renested after complete or partial brood mortality, and we also excluded one female that renested after successfully fledging a first brood. For clutch size analyses, we excluded all nests that failed prior to clutch completion, and one-egg clutches that had likely experienced partial predation before they were discovered.Nesting attempts were divided into 3 categories: first attempts, second attempts, and &ge;third attempts. Because birds did not always reunite with their former mate for renesting, we analyzed male and female renesting attempts separately for renesting propensity and renesting interval analyses. We assumed that a renesting attempt was a continuation nest (i.e. replacement nests of birds that lost a nest during egg laying and renested soon after, with no interruption in laying) if nest loss occurred during egg laying and the replacement nest was initiated within 5 days of nest loss. In the nest survival analyses, inviable nests that were continuously tended by adults were treated as successful on the 34th day after they were initiated (i.e. average laying and incubation periods for a 4-egg clutch), at which point they were censored from further analysis; however, inviable nests were treated as failures for purposes of investigating renesting propensity.Nest survival analyses were conducted using the NLMIXED procedure with SAS software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>; SAS Institute, Cary, NC), which provides maximum likelihood estimates of DSR and allows interval censoring, daily covariate values, and a single random effect. We used a logit link function to constrain DSR to be between zero and one. Because penultimate visits to nests were not routinely recorded during nest monitoring efforts, we estimated dates of penultimate visits based on the nest monitoring frequency for each site. For ease of interpretation, we converted estimates of DSR into cumulative nest survival (the probability of a nest surviving the entire nesting period) by taking the product of predicted DSR for each day of an average 34-day exposure period, using appropriate covariate values for each day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Shaffer1">Shaffer and Thompson 2007</xref>); most important, this involved incrementing nest age by 1 day for each successive day.We investigated sources of variation in renesting propensity, renesting interval, clutch size, and nest initiation date using general linear models (Glm function) and generalized linear mixed models (package Lme4; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Bates1">Bates and Sarkar 2006</xref>) using R statistical software (version 2.15.1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>). For renesting propensity analyses, we used the binomial family (logit link). For nest initiation date, renesting interval, and clutch size analyses, we compared models using Gaussian and Poisson distributions and determined that Gaussian models fit better.For each of the 5 response variables (DSR, nest initiation date, clutch size, renesting propensity, and renesting interval), we investigated variation in response to relevant covariates such as date of nest initiation, date of nest failure, nest age, nesting attempt, year, cause of nest failure, male age, female age, sex of adult, clutch size, whether an adult changed location between consecutive nesting attempts, and whether an adult changed mates between consecutive nesting attempts. For each analysis we included only covariates for which we had formulated a priori hypotheses regarding how each covariate might explain variation in the specific breeding parameter of interest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t01">Table 1</xref>). For date, we considered day 1 &equals; April 20. We considered nest age &equals; 1 to be the day the first egg was laid and then incremented daily. We treated cause of nest failure as a categorical factor with 5 levels: predation, flooding, abandonment, adult mortality, or all eggs inviable.A priori hypotheses about variables affecting daily nest survival rate (DSR), nest initiation date, renesting propensity, renesting interval, and clutch size of Great Lakes Piping Plovers during 1993&ndash;2010.To avoid overfitting models, and because some covariates were correlated (e.g., nest initiation date and nesting attempt), we used a forward selection approach to model building, starting with the simplest model containing an intercept-only term and sequentially adding variables to each model. At each stage of the model selection process, we moved forward with the best-supported model. We evaluated models using an information&ndash;theoretic approach, ranking models according to their Akaike's Information Criteria values adjusted for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). If a model under consideration included a main effect (linear term) for a covariate, we also considered the quadratic term for that covariate. We identified the best-supported model in each candidate set based on minimal AIC<sub>c</sub> and the largest Akaike weight (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), which is the probability that each model is best, conditional on the data and model set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We considered a model to be competitive if it was &le;2 AIC<sub>c</sub> units of the best model, as long as it was not merely the best model plus one uninformative parameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold2">Arnold 2010</xref>).Because we assumed there was variation between years, and we wanted to account for this source of heterogeneity, we included year as an a priori random effect. Thus, for each response variable, our base model contained an intercept term and a random year effect. If random year effects were not supported (&sigma;<sup>2</sup><sub>year</sub> &equals; 0; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Zuur1">Zuur et al. 2009</xref>) in the best model from the resulting candidate set, we removed random year effects and repeated the entire model-selection procedure using fixed effects only. Unless otherwise indicated, means are reported <underline>&plusmn;</underline>1 standard deviation (SD).We compared Piping Plover productivity (number of 1-year-old recruits into the Great Lakes population) under 2 different management scenarios: (1) removal of eggs from first nests for captive rearing and (2) leaving eggs in situ. We assumed a sample size of 20 nesting pairs under each scenario. Under the captive rearing scenario, we assumed eggs were removed at nest age &equals; 10; we considered clutch removal to be nest loss.Total productivity (number of 1-year-old recruits from first nests and renests) was compared between the captive rearing and in situ management scenarios. We estimated productivity of first nests as: productivity &equals; sample size of clutches &ast; clutch size (this study) &ast; nest success (hatching success of captive-incubated eggs &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>&rsqb; or cumulative nest survival of wild clutches &lsqb;this study&rsqb;) &ast; fledging success (captive-reared fledging success &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>&rsqb; or wild fledging success &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>&rsqb;) &ast; hatch year (HY) survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 2014</xref>) &ast; reproductive value of 1-year-old recruits (0.75 for captive-reared, or 1 for wild 1-year-old recruits, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>). We estimated productivity of renests as: productivity &equals; sample size of nesting pairs that lost first nests &ast; renesting propensity (this study) &ast; clutch size of renests (this study) &ast; nest success of renests (this study) &ast; fledging success from renests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Cuthbert1">Cuthbert and Roche 2010</xref>) &ast; HY survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 2014</xref>). Estimates of renesting propensity, renest interval (and hence initiation date for replacement nests), clutch size, and renest survival were made using best-supported models from this study, based on predicted timing of renests.We obtained data from 772 nests over 18 years (1993&ndash;2010). The average age of nests at discovery was 7.0 (SD 6.7) days old. For 328 nests monitored from egg laying until hatching, the mean exposure period was 33.7 (SD 2.3) days from the day the first egg was laid, and 27.7 (SD 2.3) days from the day the last egg was laid.The mean initiation date for first nests was May 17 (SD 13 days; 90&percnt; range: April 30 to June 10; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 674). The best-supported model of nest initiation date included a random effect of year and quadratic effects of both female and male age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>). Older adults initiated nests earlier in the season than did younger adults, with the greatest advancements occurring between ages 1 and 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f02">Figure 2</xref>). The effect of age was stronger for females than males; a 9-year-old female nested &sim;14 days earlier than a 1-year-old female, but a 9-year-old male only nested &sim;9 days earlier than a 1-year-old male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Model selection results of the top 5 models of nest initiation date, clutch size, nest survival, renesting propensity, and renesting interval of Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes region during 1993&ndash;2010. Intercept models are also listed for reference.Parameter estimates, standard errors, and 95&percnt; confidence intervals from the best-supported models of nest initiation date, clutch size, nest survival, nest initiation date, renesting propensity, and renesting interval of Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes region during 1993&ndash;2010.Effects of male and female age on initiation date of first nests of Great Lakes Piping Plovers during 1993&ndash;2010. Dotted lines indicate 95&percnt; confidence intervals.Observed size of completed clutches was 3.9 (SD 0.4) eggs (range: 2&ndash;6 eggs; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 739), excluding 4 one-egg nests that likely experienced partial predation. The best-supported model of clutch size included a quadratic effect of nest initiation date (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>); this model received nearly all of the support among models in the candidate set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Clutch size increased slightly from 3.8 (SE 0.04) for nests initiated early (April 20) to 3.9 (SE 0.02) for nests initiated mid-season (May 25), but then declined to 3.4 (SE 0.07) for nests initiated late in the season (June 25; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">Table 3</xref>).For female plovers that lost nests during laying, 21 of 75 renesters (28&percnt;) produced continuation nests. On average, continuous layers produced 6.4 (SD 1.4) consecutive eggs (range: 4&ndash;8 eggs); only 9&percnt; of continuous layers stopped laying after 4 consecutive eggs. Because the occurrence of supranormal continuation clutches may have influenced model results regarding effects of female nesting attempt on variation in clutch size, we conducted a post hoc analysis with continuation nests removed from the dataset, but results were unchanged.Our sample included 772 nests (680 first nesting attempts and 92 nests that were second or later nesting attempts for at least one parent). Apparent nest success was 76&percnt; (recall that nearly all nests were protected by predator exclosures). Initiation date had the most influence on DSR, and all top models included the quadratic term of this covariate. The best-supported model of DSR also included a quadratic effect of nest age and a linear effect of male age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Parameter estimates from the best-supported model showed that DSR increased with nest age from nest initiation until late in incubation but declined as nests approached hatching age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f03">Figure 3</xref>). DSR increased with nest initiation date until mid-season (&sim;May 20) but then declined among late season nests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f04">Figure 4</xref>; DSR was converted to cumulative nest survival for ease of interpretation). Also, DSR increased with age of the male parent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">Table 3</xref>). Cumulative nest survival averaged 0.70 (SE 0.04) for a 1-year-old male, 0.74 (SE 0.02) for a 4-year-old male (mean age), and 0.81 (SE 0.05) for a 10-year-old male for nests initiated on May 15.Effect of nest age on daily survival rate (DSR) of Great Lakes Piping Plover nests. Dotted lines indicate 95&percnt; prediction intervals. Note that all nests were protected by predator exclosures.Effect of nest initiation date on cumulative survival of Great Lakes Piping Plover nests for an average 34-day exposure period. Dotted lines indicate 95&percnt; prediction intervals. Note that all nests were protected by predator exclosures.Piping Plovers replaced 138 of 280 failed nests, a 49&percnt; apparent renesting propensity; there was no difference in apparent renesting propensity between males and females. The greatest number of nesting attempts in a single season was 5; the same pair renested 4 times, laying a total of 15 eggs. Estimates of renesting propensity represent minimum values because some nests likely failed prior to detection.Nest losses were due to predation (34&percnt;), flooding (25&percnt;), death of a breeding adult (20&percnt;; surviving adult was included in the analysis), abandonment (17&percnt;; both adults still alive), and clutch inviability (4&percnt;). In 12 cases of inviable clutches, eggs were removed 7&ndash;16 days after the predicted hatching date, but none of these birds renested; however, models that included inviable nests as a separate cause of nest failure did not converge, so we removed inviable nests from the dataset and reanalyzed data for the remaining 268 nest failures with 4 rather than 5 causes of nest failure.Renesting propensity was most strongly affected by date; the inclusion of date covariates resulted in models with the lowest AIC<sub>c</sub> values. Nest failure date explained variation in renesting propensity better than nest initiation date and therefore was retained in subsequent models. The best-supported model of renesting propensity included a random effect of year, a quadratic effect of nest failure date, cause of nest failure, and nesting attempt (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Parameter estimates from the best-supported model showed that renesting propensity decreased according to the date of nest failure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">5</xref>B). Renesting propensity was also related to cause of failure, with flooding losses being most likely to be replaced, followed by predation, abandonment, and death of a mate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Additionally, renesting propensity increased for birds with a greater number of prior nesting attempts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>B).Effects of nest failure date on renesting propensity according to (<bold>A</bold>) cause of nest failure and (<bold>B</bold>) nesting attempt. In plot A, nesting attempt was held to the mean covariate value (1.22), and in plot B, cause of failure was held to the mean covariate value (0.25).The mean observed renesting interval was 5.9 (SD 4.5) days (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 138). The best-supported model of renesting interval included a random effect of year, a quadratic effect of nest age, and an effect of changing mates. This model received nearly all of the support among models in the candidate set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Estimated renesting intervals were &sim;4 days when nest failure occurred shortly after initiation but increased to &sim;8 days when nest failure occurred during mid-incubation. Also, renesting intervals were &sim;3 days longer for birds that renested with a new mate than for individuals that renested with the same mate; 80&percnt; of mate changes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 25) were due to death of a previous mate.We compared potential productivity (number of 1-year-olds recruited into the population) between 2 management scenarios: (1) removal of initial clutches for captive rearing, and (2) leaving clutches in situ. Under the captive rearing scenario, removal of 20 first nests at age 10 days resulted in the equivalent of 3.7 one-year-old recruits from captive-reared first nests and 4.0 one-year-old recruits from wild renests of those 20 pairs, totaling 7.6 one-year-old recruits (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t04">Table 4</xref>). Under the non-removal scenario, leaving all 20 first nests in situ resulted in 12.3 one-year-old recruits from first nests, and 1.0 one-year-old recruits from natural renests, totaling 13.3 one-year-old recruits. Thus, clutch removal resulted in 5.7 fewer one-year-old recruits into the population and only 57&percnt; productivity compared to leaving clutches in situ.Comparison of removing first nests for captive rearing vs. leaving first nests in situ, in terms of number of 1-year-old recruits into the Great Lakes Piping Plover population.Renesting is an important component of Piping Plover reproduction; nearly half of all individuals renested after failure of an earlier nest. In a natural scenario, nests would not be protected by individual predator exclosures and renesting would undoubtedly play an even more important role; however, we found that renests were less productive than initial nests, not because renests are less productive per se, but because they were initiated later in the season and consequently had lower average clutch size and nest survival (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f04">Figure 4</xref>) as well as lower chick survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>) and post-fledging survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders1">Saunders et al. 2014</xref>).Other studies of Piping Plovers have also found strong seasonal effects on reproductive success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Harris1">Harris et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>), and any factors that cause plovers to nest later, including renesting, are likely to lead to lower breeding productivity. Studies of other precocial species have found that after controlling for later nest initiation date, renests were as productive as initial nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Amat1">Amat et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>). In this study, nest survival was influenced by nest initiation date but not by later nesting attempt (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that Piping Plover reproductive success is better explained by seasonal effects rather than prior investments in clutch formation and incubation. We speculate that seasonal declines in reproductive success may have been a result of diminishing food resources for adults or chicks, changes in predator abundance or behavior, or increased frequency or intensity of late summer storm surges. Alternatively, seasonally declining reproductive success may have indicated lower parental investment in late season nests given reduced survival rates for late-hatched chicks and fledglings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>).Nesting attempt was an important factor in explaining renesting propensity of adults, although less so than seasonal effects related to date of failure of the previous nesting attempt (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>). Even though renesting propensity declined to zero toward the end of the breeding season, renesting propensity was higher for individuals that had a greater number of previous nesting attempts than for individuals with fewer previous nesting attempts (after controlling for nest failure date; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>B). This result was contrary to our a priori hypothesis that renesting propensity would decline with later nesting attempt due to costs of reproduction. Instead it suggests that individual quality is an important determinant of renesting propensity; proven renesters are more likely to renest repeatedly, owing to some unmeasured aspect of individual quality.We used age of breeding adults as an indication of adult breeding quality. A number of studies of other species have found that older birds nest earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Becker1">Becker and Zhang 2011</xref>), have higher nest survival rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Devries1">Devries et al. 2008</xref>), and have a greater likelihood of renesting after nest loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Wendeln1">Wendeln et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Fondell1">Fondell et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Arnold3">Arnold et al. 2010</xref>). In our study, nest survival increased with age of the breeding male (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>). Renesting propensity was not affected by male or female age; however, both nest survival and renesting propensity were strongly influenced by initiation date, and older males and females initiated nests earlier than younger individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f02">Figure 2</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. (2012)</xref> had similar results with respect to the influence of adult age on hatching date.We found that nest survival was more strongly influenced by male than female age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Male Piping Plovers arrive on the breeding grounds before females, and older birds generally arrive before younger individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Stucker1">Stucker et al. 2010</xref>). Males also have the primary role in territory establishment and defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Cairns1">Cairns 1982</xref>) and exhibit higher breeding site fidelity than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Haig1">Haig and Oring 1988</xref>). Higher nest survival of older males in this study may have been due to earlier arrival times and greater ability to establish and maintain high-quality breeding territories. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche1">Roche et al. (2010)</xref> found that breeding females had higher mortality rates than males, and older females had higher mortality rates than younger females. In this study, perhaps the benefits of female age and experience on nest survival were counteracted by a higher probability of death for older females. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Saunders2">Saunders et al. (2012)</xref> found that fledging success was more strongly influenced by age and experience of females than males. Females generally depart breeding grounds before males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Cairns1">Cairns 1982</xref>), and because older females nested earlier, they may have been less likely to abandon their broods before they fledged.Daily nest survival increased from nest initiation until mid-incubation but then followed a quadratic pattern of decline among older nests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The apparent decline in survival of older nests may be an artifact of fitting a quadratic model to data exhibiting a strong pattern during early nesting; however, other investigators have found similar patterns among waterfowl and speculated that lower survival of older nests may be related to changes in adult behavior close to hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Grand1">Grand et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Grant2">Grant and Shaffer 2012</xref>). Circumstantial evidence suggests that adult Piping Plovers also change their behavior, becoming increasingly attentive and restless close to hatching (S.P. Saunders personal observation).We initially considered whether increased activity by attendant parents and/or increased noise associated with hatching might have increased the probability of nest loss to predators near hatching. During the last week of incubation prior to hatching, however, the proportion of clutch loss from predation decreased from 39&percnt; (average during first 4 weeks of the nesting period) to 26&percnt;, but death of a breeding adult increased from 18&percnt; (average during first 4 weeks of the nesting period) to 30&percnt;. We speculate that increased activity close to hatching may have increased the probability of predation on attending adults, thus indirectly causing nest failure.Although age of the previous nest at the time of nest failure did not influence renesting propensity, it did influence length of the renesting interval (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Renesting intervals increased with age of the previous nest at the time of failure and were shortest for nests that failed during egg laying. Adults with nests that failed early in the incubation period had invested less time and energy in the previous nest, and females that lost clutches during egg laying potentially still had enlarged oviducts and developing follicles allowing prompt initiation of a continuation nest.Renesting intervals were also &sim;3 days longer for adults that needed to find a new mate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Table 2</xref>). Divorce (i.e. intra-year mate switching when both members of a pair were alive; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Choudhury1">Choudhury 1995</xref>) among Piping Plovers was rare, and 80&percnt; of intra-year mate changes were the result of the death of a previous mate.After controlling for date of failure and nesting attempt, death of a mate resulted in the second lowest renesting propensity after egg inviability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Birds did not renest if their clutches were inviable, even in cases where it was still early enough in the season for them to potentially do so; however, with the exception of one infertile male (inviable clutches in several different years) and one female who only survived a single breeding season, all birds with inviable clutches nested successfully in subsequent years. Renesting propensity was highest among birds with nests that failed due to flooding or clutch predation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). As with other shorebirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Sandercock1">Sandercock et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Lishman1">Lishman et al. 2010</xref>), renesting by Piping Plovers is likely an evolutionary adaptation to compensate for high rates of egg loss to predators and weather-related events rather than other causes of nest failure such as clutch inviability or mate loss. We speculate that the failure to renest following death of a mate may be due to constraints imposed by lack of available mates late in the season or may reflect individual restraint when faced with longer renesting intervals and subsequent seasonal limitations resulting from delayed renesting.Nearly all nests were protected by predator exclosures, which likely affected renesting propensity. Renesting rates in this study may have been lower than would have occurred naturally because nests likely survived longer before failing, and thus timing of nest losses occurred later in the season and after greater energy investments by incubating adults. Also, other studies have shown that use of exclosures may increase mortality risks for adult plovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Johnson1">Johnson and Oring 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Murphy1">Murphy et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Neuman1">Neuman et al. 2004</xref>). In this study, the likelihood of renesting was lower following death of a mate than for other types of nest loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Although there was no direct evidence of mortality due to exclosure use in this study, if exclosures contributed to adult disappearances, they may have thus indirectly affected renesting propensity of the surviving adult.Clutch size exhibited a quadratic pattern of decline; model-estimated clutch size increased from 3.8 to 3.9 from early to mid-season before declining to 3.4 at the end of the breeding season (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>). The slightly lower clutch size earlier in the season compared to mid-season may have been a result of low spring temperatures, a variable reported to affect clutch size in a closely related shorebird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Nol1">Nol et al. 1997</xref>). In general, clutch size of Great Lakes Piping Plovers declined with later nest initiation date, which is consistent with findings from studies of Piping Plovers elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Cairns1">Cairns 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Harris1">Harris et al. 2005</xref>). Although Piping Plovers have a modal clutch size of 4 eggs, we found that the frequency of 2- and 3-egg clutches increased toward the end of the breeding season. Continuation nesters were able to lay 5&ndash;8 eggs in normal succession, and the greatest number of eggs laid by a female in a single season was 15, suggesting that egg production capability of females was likely not the limiting factor for clutch size toward the end of the breeding season.Although our results indicate that nest survival and renesting by Great Lakes Piping Plovers are strongly influenced by seasonal variation, parental quality was somewhat important as well. Older males had higher nest survival (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>), and older males and females initiated nests earlier in the breeding season (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f02">Figure 2</xref>). A few Piping Plovers were able to produce replacement nests throughout the breeding season if their nests continued to fail; 5 nesting attempts was the maximum number recorded for a single bird in a single season. Although we did not find an effect of parent age per se on renesting propensity, perhaps other indicators of individual quality, such as foraging efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Lescroel1">Lescro&euml;l et al. 2010</xref>) or establishment of high-quality territories as a result of early arrival or competitive ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Marra1">Marra 2000</xref>) may better explain variation in renesting propensity among individuals.We compared 2 potential management strategies for Great Lakes Piping Plovers: (1) removing initial clutches for captive rearing and (2) leaving clutches in situ. Our results suggest that removal of clutches for captive rearing led to fewer 1-year-old Piping Plovers recruited into the Great Lakes population than leaving clutches in situ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t04">Table 4</xref>). Lower productivity under the clutch removal scenario was primarily a result of reduced survival of captive-reared chicks compared to wild chicks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Roche2">Roche et al. 2008</xref>), and renesting could only partially compensate for the removal of earlier nests.Overall, about half the Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes renested after failure of an earlier nest. Renesting propensity varied according to date and cause of previous nest failure however, and renesting was more likely to occur following early-season predation rather than a late-season weather event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Replacement nests are necessarily initiated later in the season and thus produce smaller clutches (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-t03">3</xref>) and have lower chances of nest survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-f04">Figure 4</xref>) and fledgling survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-3-394-Brudney1">Brudney et al. 2013</xref>). Based on our results, proactive removal of first nests for captive rearing is not recommended for this endangered population, although egg collection may be warranted in cases of probable nest failure (e.g., nest located within a flood zone). Our results suggest that as the breeding season progresses, conservation managers should be increasingly proactive with in situ nest protection efforts (e.g., enhanced predator control efforts) rather than relying on collection of eggs for captive rearing.We thank all who have been involved in annual plover banding efforts over the past 20 years, especially L. Wemmer, J. Stucker, L. Price, M. Westbrock, S. Schubel, A. Smith, C. Smith, and A. Van Zoeren. We also thank our extensive network of partners and the East Lansing Field Office, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, for enthusiasm for plover recovery as well as the University of Michigan Biological Station which has supported Piping Plover research efforts for many years. Additionally, we recognize B. Van Dam and T. Schneider for their continuous support of the captive rearing program and the Detroit Zoological Society and many other zoological institutions who participate in captive rearing of Great Lakes Piping Plovers annually. D. Catlin and an anonymous reviewer provided extensive and helpful comments on this manuscript, and suggestions by B. Meixell, J. Colburn, and J. Stucker improved earlier drafts of this effort. Funding for this study was provided by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the Michigan Department of Natural Resources. A. H. C. received additional support from the University of Minnesota Graduate School and the National Science Foundation, and F. J. C. was supported by funds from the Minnesota Agricultural Experiment Station. All research adhered to University of Minnesota Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee guidelines.