Erratum: The socioecology of Monk Parakeets: Insights into parrot social complexityHierarchical steepness and phylogenetic models I: Phylogenetic signals in MacacaSocial structure in a family group of Guanaco (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lama guanicoe</named-content></italic>, ungulate): Is female hierarchy based on &lsquo;prior attributes' or &lsquo;social dynamics'?Context-dependent linear dominance hierarchies in social groups of European badgers, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Meles meles</named-content></italic>The socioecology of Monk Parakeets: Insights into parrot social complexityTolerant food sharing and reciprocity is precluded by despotism among bonobos but not chimpanzeesSteepness: Testing steepness of dominance hierarchies. R package version 0.2-2Dominance, aggression and physiological stress in wild male Assamese macaques (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Macaca assamensis</named-content></italic>)Social relationships in free-ranging male <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Macaca arctoides</named-content></italic>Hierarchical dominance structure in reintroduced California Condors: Correlates, consequences, and dynamicsSex differences in the steepness of dominance hierarchies in captive bonobo groupsMothers matter! Maternal support, dominance status and mating success in male bonobos (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pan paniscus</named-content></italic>)Current address: National Institute for Mathematical and Biological Synthesis, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee, USAOur recent work on Monk Parakeets (<italic>Myiopsitta monachus</italic>) reported dominance steepness values that were inaccurate because of a bug in the analysis program. Updated steepness values are more moderate than initially reported, which places captive Monk Parakeet groups midway between egalitarianism and despotism.Nuestro trabajo reciente sobre <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Myiopsitta monachus</named-content></italic> present&oacute; valores incorrectos de pendiente de dominancia debido a un error en el programa de an&aacute;lisis. Los valores actualizados de pendiente son m&aacute;s moderados que los presentados originalmente, lo que ubica a los grupos cautivos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. monachus</named-content></italic> a medio camino entre igualitarismo y despotismo.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> jerarqu&iacute;a de dominancia, pendiente, SOCPROGThe dominance steepness results for captive Monk Parakeets (<italic>Myiopsitta monachus</italic>) we reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>) were inaccurate because of a bug in the program we used for dominance hierarchy analyses. SOCPROG version 2.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Whitehead1">Whitehead 2009</xref>) had an error in how steepness was calculated (H. Whitehead personal communication). We reanalyzed aggression for our captive Monk Parakeet groups using the R package &lsquo;steepness' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Leiva1">Leiva and de Vries 2014</xref>; 10,000 permutations). Dominance linearity was consistent with our originally published values. Steepness values are more moderate than previously reported (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-t01">Table 1</xref>; steepness values replace those in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>: table 4). The <italic>D<sub>ij</sub></italic> steepness values are no longer on the extremely egalitarian end of the egalitarian&ndash;despotic continuum as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>: figure 8). Rather, the updated values are now moderate for both captive groups, putting both groups in the middle of this continuum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Because captive conditions are likely to increase the chances of a steeper hierarchy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2007</xref>), dominance hierarchies for Monk Parakeets in the wild are still likely to be less steep, and more egalitarian, than those observed in captivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2014</xref>).Dominance steepness across species. Dominance steepness (<italic>D<sub>ij</sub></italic>) measures are reported for wild and captive adult groups, with species ordered by mean reported steepness values. Silhouettes indicate the type of animal. Superscripts indicate data sources: <sup>1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Balasubramaniam1">Balasubramaniam et al. 2012</xref>; <sup>2</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Jaeggi1">Jaeggi et al. 2010</xref>; <sup>3</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Stevens1">Stevens et al. 2007</xref>; <sup>4</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Surbeck1">Surbeck et al. 2011</xref> (<italic>D<sub>ij</sub></italic> method, corrected value &equals; 0.84; personal communication); <sup>5</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Ostner1">Ostner et al. 2008</xref> (<italic>Dij</italic> method, personal communication); <sup>6</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Richter1">Richter et al. 2009</xref>; <sup>7</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2014</xref> (revised steepness values); <sup>8</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hewitt1">Hewitt et al. 2009</xref>; <sup>9</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Sheppard1">Sheppard et al. 2013</xref>. Steepness values for adult <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lama guanicoe</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Correa1">Correa et al. 2013</xref>) that were reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-422-Hobson1">Hobson et al. (2014)</xref> were omitted from this revised version because that study reported using SOCPROG version 2.4 to calculate steepness.Corrected dominance steepness values for captive groups 1 and 2.Thanks to C. Neumann for his reanalysis of our data that alerted us to the presence of a bug in SOCPROG 2.4, and to H. Whitehead for confirming the bug. The newly released SOCPROG 2.5 has corrected this bug.