Biases in nest survival associated with choice of exposure period: A case study in North American upland game birdsNest survival of Piping Plovers at a dynamic reservoir indicates an ecological trap for a threatened populationMountain plover nest survival in relation to prairie dog and fire dynamics in shortgrass steppeSurvival, movements, and reproduction of translocated Greater Sage-Grouse in Strawberry Valley, UtahFactors influencing nesting success of King Eiders on northern Alaska's coastal plainWhite-tailed Ptarmigan (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagopus leucura</named-content></italic>)Northern Bobwhite (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colinus virginianus</named-content></italic>)Assessments of habitat preferences and quality depend on spatial scale and metrics of fitnessFactors influencing nest survival and renesting by Piping Plovers in the Great Lakes regionNest predation of Greater Sage-Grouse in relation to microhabitat factors and predatorsNesting density and reproductive success of Piping Plovers in response to storm- and human-created habitat changesReproduction and microhabitat selection in a sharply declining Northern Bobwhite populationCharacteristics and dynamics of Greater Sage-Grouse populationsLesser Scaup nest success and duckling survival on the Yukon Flats, AlaskaDemography, reproductive ecology, and variation in survival of Greater Sage-Grouse in northeastern CaliforniaWaterfowl nesting in fall-seeded and spring-seeded cropland in SaskatchewanModeling avian nest survival in Program MARKPredator exclosures, predator removal, and habitat improvement increase nest success of Snowy Plovers in Oregon, USAAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalLinking conservation actions to demography: Grass height explains variation in Greater Sage-Grouse nest survivalSpring temperature, clutch initiation date and duck nest success: A test of the mismatch hypothesisModeling fecundity in birds: Conceptual overview, current models, and considerations for future developmentsNest and brood survival of Lesser Prairie-Chickens in west central KansasObserver effects strongly influence estimates of daily nest survival probability but do not substantially increase rates of nest failure in Greater Sage-GrouseNest survival in Dusky Canada Geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta canadensis</named-content> occidentalis</italic>): Use of discrete-time modelsTime-specific patterns of nest survival for ducks and passerines breeding in North DakotaTime-specific variation in passerine nest survival: New insights into old questionsThe predicted influence of climate change on Lesser Prairie-Chicken reproductive parametersNesting ecology and nest survival of Lesser Prairie-Chickens on the Southern High Plains of TexasDemographics of breeding female Mallards in southern Ontario, CanadaGreater Sage-Grouse nesting habitat selection and success in WyomingThe influence of habitat on nest survival of snowy and Wilson's plovers in the lower Laguna Madre region of TexasWeather constrains the influence of fire and grazing on nesting Greater Prairie-ChickensDemographics of Northern Bobwhite on agricultural and intensively-managed bobwhite plantation landscapesEstimating nest success: The Mayfield method and an alternativeMethods of estimating nest success: An historical tourEffects of mate and site fidelity on nest survival of Western Sandpipers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris mauri</named-content></italic>)Effects of grassland biomass harvest on nesting pheasants and ducksNesting success and resource selection of Greater Sage-GrouseNest-site selection, interspecific associations, and nest success of King EidersWild Turkey nest survival and nest-site selection in the presence of growing-season prescribed fireIdentifying Greater Sage-Grouse source and sink habitats for conservation planning in an energy development landscapeEcological factors influencing nest survival of Greater Sage-Grouse in Mono County, CaliforniaShort-term impacts of wind energy development on Greater Sage-Grouse fitnessClutch size determination in shorebirds: Revisiting incubation limitation in the Pied Avocet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Recurvirostra avosetta</named-content></italic>)Age, arrival date and reproductive success of male American Redstarts <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>Regional variation in nesting success of Lesser Prairie-ChickensAvian life history evolution in relation to nest sites, nest predation, and foodNest predation increases with parental activity: Separating nest site and parental activity effectsGreater Prairie-Chicken nest success and habitat selection in southeastern NebraskaNesting success calculated from exposureSuggestions for calculating nest successDemography of Greater Prairie-Chickens: Regional variation in vital rates, sensitivity values, and population dynamicsEffects of wind energy development on nesting ecology of Greater Prairie-Chickens in fragmented grasslandsOptimizing nest survival and female survival: Consequences of nest site selection for Canada GeeseFactors affecting nest survival of Greater Sage-Grouse in northcentral MontanaHigh-tech or field techs: Radio-telemetry is a cost-effective method for reducing bias in songbird nest searchingEffects of large-scale predator reduction on nest success of upland nesting ducksSurvival and productivity of Eastern Wild Turkey females in contrasting landscapes in WisconsinNest success of Northern Bobwhite on managed and unmanaged landscapes in southeast IowaModeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SASNest success of Snowy Plovers (<italic>Charadrius nivosus</italic>) in the Southern High Plains of TexasDemographic sensitivity of population change in Northern BobwhiteGreater Sage Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>)A unified approach to analyzing nest successEffects of nest habitat, food, and parental behavior on shorebird nest successDaily nest survival rates of Gunnison Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus minimus</named-content></italic>): Assessing local- and landscape-scale driversManaging multiple vital rates to maximize Greater Sage-Grouse population growthImpact of encroaching woody vegetation on nest success of upland nesting waterfowlNesting ecology of White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content> deglandi</italic>) at Redberry Lake, SaskatchewanNest visits and capture events affect breeding success of Yellow-billed and Pacific loonsLow reproductive success of Mallards in a grassland-dominated landscape in the Sandhills of NebraskaNest survival of scaup and other ducks in the boreal forest of AlaskaPartial incubation in birds: Its occurrence, function, and quantificationLandscape features and weather influence nest survival of a ground-nesting bird of conservation concern, the Greater Sage-Grouse, in human-altered environmentsNest survival patterns in Willow Ptarmigan: Influence of time, nesting stage, and female characteristicsEstimated probability of daily nest survival is commonly used to derive cumulative nest survival for a specified nest-exposure period. For many species of birds, the presence of a parent is an important cue used by researchers to locate nests, but in some cases nest detection rates are reduced during egg laying, when parents spend a greater amount of time away from the nest. As a result, sample size becomes limited during the laying stage. Researchers must then choose between 2 alternative strategies for deriving cumulative nest survival, based on either (1) exposure length for only the incubation period or (2) exposure length for laying plus incubation. Both approaches carry implicit assumptions, the violation of which can result in bias. We reviewed recent literature and describe the extent to which these 2 strategies were used in studies of galliform birds (including grouse, quail, and Wild Turkey &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Meleagris gallopavo</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) in North America. We then evaluated the theoretical potential for bias under each approach across a range of daily nest survival probabilities and for 3 different life-history scenarios. The incubation-only strategy was most commonly applied, with 62&percnt; of publications reporting its use. We found that the incubation-only strategy was biased except under an assumption of zero nest failure during egg laying. Fewer studies reported using the laying-plus-incubation strategy, which was unbiased in situations where risk of failure was equivalent among laying and incubation stages. This strategy also minimized bias across the broadest range of situations, and accordingly we recommend its use where the daily survival rate during egg laying is unknown. We recommend that both the laying and incubation periods should be used to define the length of nest exposure when estimating cumulative nest survival, particularly for species with large clutches and long laying periods.Las estimaciones de la probabilidad de supervivencia diaria del nido son com&uacute;nmente usadas para derivar la supervivencia acumulada del nido para un per&iacute;odo espec&iacute;fico de exposici&oacute;n del nido. Para muchas especies de aves, la presencia de un progenitor es una importante se&ntilde;al usada por los investigadores para localizar los nidos, pero en algunos casos las tasas de detecci&oacute;n se reducen durante la puesta de los huevos, cuando los padres pasan una gran cantidad de tiempo lejos del nido. Como resultado, el tama&ntilde;o de la muestra se ve limitado durante el per&iacute;odo de puesta. Los investigadores deben por ende elegir entre dos estrategias alternativas para derivar la supervivencia acumulada del nido; una basada en la duraci&oacute;n de la exposici&oacute;n solo para el per&iacute;odo de incubaci&oacute;n, y una segunda basada en la duraci&oacute;n de la exposici&oacute;n para la puesta m&aacute;s la incubaci&oacute;n. Ambos enfoques conllevan supuestos impl&iacute;citos, y la violaci&oacute;n de &eacute;stos puede acarrear un sesgo. Revisamos la literatura reciente y describimos la frecuencia con que estas dos estrategias fueron usadas en los estudios de aves galliformes (urogallo, codorniz y pavo silvestre &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Meleagris gallopavo</named-content></italic>&rsqb;) en Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Luego evaluamos el potencial te&oacute;rico de sesgo bajo cada uno de los enfoques a trav&eacute;s de un rango de probabilidades de supervivencia diaria del nido y para tres escenarios diferentes de historias de vida. La estrategia que considera solo la incubaci&oacute;n fue m&aacute;s com&uacute;nmente aplicada, con 62&percnt; de las publicaciones mencionando este uso. Encontramos que la estrategia que considera solo la incubaci&oacute;n estuvo sesgada excepto bajo un supuesto de fracaso nulo del nido durante la puesta de huevos. Un menor n&uacute;mero de estudios mencionaron el uso de la estrategia que considera la puesta m&aacute;s la incubaci&oacute;n, que no estuvo sesgada en las situaciones en las que el riesgo de fracaso fue equivalente entre los per&iacute;odos de puesta e incubaci&oacute;n. Esta estrategia tambi&eacute;n minimiz&oacute; el sesgo a trav&eacute;s de un rango m&aacute;s amplio de situaciones, y por lo tanto recomendamos su uso donde no se conoce la tasa de supervivencia diaria durante la puesta de huevos. Recomendamos que tanto los per&iacute;odos de puesta como de incubaci&oacute;n deben ser usados para definir la duraci&oacute;n del periodo de exposici&oacute;n cuando se busca estimar la supervivencia acumulativa del nido, particularmente para las especies con nidadas grandes y con per&iacute;odos de puesta largos.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> codorniz, &eacute;xito del nido, Galliformes, pavo, perdiz nival, pollo de pradera, supervivencia diaria del nido, urogalloHereafter, we use NS in reference to values of nest survival probability that are derived from DNS across a cumulative nest-exposure period, and we use &ldquo;nest success&rdquo; as the true proportion of nests in a sampled population that are successful (i.e. the unknown population process). When NS is derived accurately, we assume that it is equivalent to nest success.Nest success is ultimately based on the viability of eggs and/or young in nests, and the nest-exposure period reflects the length of time that an average nest is at risk of failure. For birds with nidicolous young, the exposure period can be subdivided into at least 3 discrete stages: (1) the period before completion of the clutch (laying), (2) the period following clutch completion but prior to hatching (incubation), and (3) the period between hatching and when the young birds leave the nest (nestling) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Etterson1">Etterson et al. 2011</xref>). Partial incubation may occur during the laying stage, but this stage is still considered behaviorally distinct from full incubation, which occurs following completion of the clutch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Wang1">Wang and Beissinger 2011</xref>). For birds with nidifugous young, the nest-exposure period is defined by only laying and incubation stages because after hatching, young are vagile and are no longer associated with the nest. During each nest stage, period-specific DNS may vary for a number of reasons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore and Dinsmore 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Grant1">Grant and Shaffer 2012</xref>). For example, if nest sites vary in general quality (e.g., habitat structure), &ldquo;low-quality&rdquo; nests may be rapidly removed by predators, causing DNS to be lower during early stages compared with later stages, when a larger proportion of &ldquo;high-quality&rdquo; nests remain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Martin2">Martin et al. 2000</xref>). Changes in parental behaviors may also alter DNS among nest stages. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Martin2">Martin et al. (2000)</xref> found that among 10 species of open-nesting passerines, the degree of change in parental activity between the incubation and nestling periods was positively associated with concurrent changes in nest depredation risk.In the study of many birds, discovery of nests depends on observation of parents. For example, nests of ground-nesting birds are often found through systematic searches designed to flush incubating parents from nests (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Drever1">Drever and Clark 2007</xref>) or by observations of radio-tagged parents on nests (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Kolada1">Kolada et al. 2009</xref>). By contrast, canopy-nesting birds are commonly studied by observing parental territorial and nest-building behaviors to locate nest sites (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Lozano1">Lozano et al. 1996</xref>) or by also using radiotelemetry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Peterson1">Peterson et al. 2015</xref>). The same behavioral differences among nest stages that affect nest survival may also cause the likelihood of nest discovery to vary among nesting stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Mayfield2">Mayfield 1975</xref>). For ground-nesting birds in particular, nest discovery is far more likely following the onset of full incubation, when parents spend a much greater amount of time on nests. This issue is further complicated by the fact that many ground-nesting species are found in relatively low densities and are highly cryptic in their nesting habits, further reducing the availability of nests discovered during laying. In such cases, sample size may be insufficient to generate a robust estimate of DNS<sub>Lay</sub>. As a consequence, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e04">Equation 4</xref> cannot be used and researchers must choose how to appropriately derive NS despite this data deficiency. Two alternative strategies are commonly used in this scenario: (1) deriving NS by using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e02">Equation 2</xref> (or 3) but defining <italic>E</italic> on the basis of incubation period alone for the species being studied (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Hughes1">Hughes et al. 2005</xref>); or (2) extrapolating DNS<sub>Inc</sub> across the entire nest-exposure period, using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e01">Equation 1</xref> (i.e. <italic>E</italic> &equals; <italic>L</italic> &plus; <italic>I</italic>). Both alternatives involve implicit assumptions: the incubation-only strategy assumes that no nests fail during laying, whereas the laying-plus-incubation strategy assumes that DNS is homogeneous between the 2 nest stages. Violating assumptions in either case will result in values of NS that are biased in relation to nest success.Our objective for this work was to evaluate how NS obtained from DNS may be biased by the choice of exposure period in situations where data to estimate DNS during laying are limited. We used upland game birds (i.e. grouse, quail, and Wild Turkey &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Meleagris gallopavo</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; hereafter &ldquo;galliforms&rdquo;) as model organisms to evaluate these questions, because we have found approaches to be particularly variable for these taxa. Reproductive strategies in galliforms are diverse, but most species nest on the ground and produce nidifugous young that leave the nest within 24&ndash;48 hr of hatching. Clutch sizes are also generally large, which results in a long exposure period during laying compared with incubation. Many species of galliforms have experienced large-scale and long-term population declines, which makes accurate assessments of nest success that are comparable across studies important for conservation planning in these species. We evaluate the extent to which NS is biased under each strategy, and also which strategy produces the smaller bias under different circumstances.We conducted an informal review of nest ecology literature on North American galliforms to assess the extent to which researchers use the incubation-only or laying-plus-incubation strategies when deriving NS. We restricted our review to publications dated year 2004 and later, because this approximates the period during which use of DNS methods to evaluate nest success became increasingly common, in part because of advances in quantitative methodologies and published guidance on their application (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Dinsmore3">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Shaffer1">Shaffer 2004</xref>). We used Google Scholar (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scholar.google.com" xlink:type="simple">http://scholar.google.com</ext-link>) to search for the following terms: nest success, nest survival, daily nest survival, grouse, ptarmigan, prairie chicken, quail, bobwhite, turkey. We also explored citations contained within summary review publications for these taxa (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Sandercock1">Sandercock et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>) and used our own familiarity with galliform literature to locate relevant publications. Our goal for this exercise was not to produce an exhaustive review, but rather to generate a sample sufficient to characterize the relative extent to which the 2 strategies have been used in recent galliform research. Accordingly, we excluded publications from which we could not infer the strategy employed, and we also filtered results to include only publications in which DNS was modeled directly and derived NS was reported. We focused on peer-reviewed publications and excluded unpublished literature (e.g., graduate theses or technical reports).We used a scenario-based approach to evaluate potential bias in NS depending on exposure-period strategy. First, we generated a complete range of DNS values between 0.950 and 1.000, in increments of 0.001, for both the laying and incubation periods. We chose this range of values because they reflected a broad range of values for NS (more than 0.15&ndash;1.0), and we used a uniform parameter space (i.e. the same range of possible DNS values for both incubation and laying periods) because this would ultimately provide the greatest range of comparisons and would therefore encompass the majority of situations likely to occur in the field. We considered these to be &ldquo;true&rdquo; values for stage-specific DNS, and we used <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e04">Equation 4</xref> for each combination of DNS<sub>Inc</sub> and DNS<sub>Lay</sub> to calculate a value that we used as true nest success for that particular combination, given specified laying and incubation periods. Second, we calculated NS based strictly on the DNS<sub>Inc</sub> value for each combination, as though data were not available to estimate DNS<sub>Lay</sub>, which was thus an unknown value. For the incubation-only scenario, we calculated NS using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e01">Equation 1</xref> and defined <italic>E</italic> strictly on the basis of <italic>I</italic>. For the laying-plus-incubation scenario, we extended <italic>E</italic> to include the entire nest-exposure period (<italic>I</italic> &plus; <italic>L</italic>). In each case, the bias in the resulting NS could be computed as follows: bias equals NS minus nest success, where a positive bias reflects an overestimate of nest success and a negative bias reflects an underestimate. We repeated this process across all combinations of DNS<sub>Inc</sub> and DNS<sub>Lay</sub>, which allowed us to evaluate how bias changed in relation to increases or decreases in DNS for each nesting period. Throughout this exercise, we implicitly assumed that (1) DNS<sub>Inc</sub> reflects the true underlying survival probability during incubation for the sample population; and (2) bias in NS was driven strictly by choice of nest-exposure period, rather than by other potential biases inherent to estimation of DNS. To explore how bias was expected to change in relation to variation in clutch size and length of incubation, we repeated this process under 3 scenarios designed to reflect a range of life-history strategies exhibited by North American galliforms. These included (1) 5-day laying period, 25-day incubation period (e.g., White-tailed Ptarmigan &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagopus leucura</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Braun1">Braun et al. 1993</xref>); (2) 10-day laying period, 27-day incubation period (e.g., Greater Sage-Grouse &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Schroeder1">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>); and (3) 18-day laying period, 23-day incubation period (e.g., Northern Bobwhite &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colinus virginianus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Brennan1">Brennan et al. 2014</xref>). These 3 scenarios can be characterized as &ldquo;low,&rdquo; &ldquo;medium,&rdquo; and &ldquo;high,&rdquo; based on the relative investment each species makes in a single clutch of eggs. We evaluated bias in terms of its directional magnitude (i.e. positive or negative distance from 0.0) and absolute magnitude (i.e. absolute distance from 0.0) for each DNS combination. We also evaluated the distribution of biases within each egg-investment scenario and compared distributions among scenarios to make inferences about the general relationships between nest-exposure biases and variation in life-history strategies among species. Finally, for each combination of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub>, we determined which strategy produced the lower absolute bias. Here, we assume that given uncertainty associated with DNS<sub>Lay</sub>, the better strategy would be the one that minimized bias in a greater number of situations.We reviewed 26 publications and found that 16 (~62&percnt; of studies) derived NS using only the incubation period, whereas 9 derived NS using an exposure period based on laying-plus-incubation periods. A single publication reported NS based on both strategies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-t01">Table 1</xref>).Results of our literature review comparing choice of exposure-period strategy in publications reporting nest survival (NS) derived from daily nest survival (DNS) estimates for North American galliforms. Only peer-reviewed publications from 2004 to 2015 that explicitly report DNS, NS, and exposure period were used.In general, the incubation-only strategy produced values of NS that were positively biased, except in situations where DNS<sub>Lay</sub> approached a value of 1.0 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">Figure 1</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">1</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">1</xref>E). The magnitude of bias in NS for this strategy ranged from a low of 0.0 in all scenarios to highs of 0.22 (low investment), 0.40 (medium investment), and 0.60 (high investment). Bias was expected to be highest when DNS was low during laying and high during incubation, although even a modest deviation from the assumption of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> &equals; 1.0 produced nontrivial bias in NS in all scenarios and at almost all levels of DNS<sub>Inc</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The laying-plus-incubation strategy produced unbiased values in cases where DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> were equal, and yielded both positive and negative biases where DNS differed among the nesting stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">Figure 1</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">1</xref>D, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">1</xref>F). Again, the most extreme biases occurred when DNS during incubation was high and DNS during laying was low, and the maximum bias was reached at the same values reported above for of the incubation-only strategy. Negative biases associated with the laying-plus-incubation strategy were generally smaller in magnitude than the positive biases that were common to both strategies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The largest negative biases for each scenario were &minus;0.062, &minus;0.115, and &minus;0.186 for the low-, medium-, and high-investment scenarios, respectively. The distribution of biases for the laying-plus-incubation strategy overlapped 0.0 (no bias) to a much greater extent than the incubation-only scenario (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f02">Figure 2</xref>).Graphical depiction of bias in nest survival (NS) derived using daily nest survival (DNS) estimates from the incubation period, where exposure-period length was based only on the length of the incubation interval (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) or on both laying and incubation interval lengths (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, <bold>F</bold>). Each dot reflects a different combination of laying and incubation DNS, where size of dots represents absolute magnitude of bias and shading reflects directional magnitude of bias (0.0 &equals; unbiased). Each panel represents a different combination of exposure-period strategy and galliform life-history scenario based on clutch allocations: <bold>A</bold> &equals; incubation only, low investment; <bold>B</bold> &equals; laying plus incubation, low investment; <bold>C</bold> &equals; incubation only, medium investment; <bold>D</bold> &equals; laying plus incubation, medium investment; <bold>E</bold> &equals; incubation only, high investment; and <bold>F</bold> &equals; laying plus incubation, high investment. Life-history scenarios were designed to reflect a range of life-history strategies exhibited by North American galliforms. These include (1) 5-day laying period, 25-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagopus leucura</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Braun1">Braun et al. 1993</xref>); (2) 10-day laying period, 27-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Schroeder1">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>); and (3) 18-day laying period, 23-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colinus virginianus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Brennan1">Brennan et al. 2014</xref>).Comparison of the potential range of biases in cumulative nest survival (NS) derived from daily nest survival rates (DNS) specific to the incubation period, where exposure-period length was based on laying and incubation interval lengths (left panel) versus only the incubation interval length (right panel). Comparisons were made for 3 hypothetical species representative of variation in life-history strategies among North American galliforms. Life-history strategies were characterized on the basis of clutch investments, which determined the length of exposure during the laying and incubation stages for each scenario. When bias &equals; 0.0, NS is assumed to reflect true nest success.Patterns in the distribution and direction of bias across different combinations of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> were similar for the 3 life-history scenarios (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f02">Figure 2</xref>). However, the magnitude of potential bias increased substantially with increasing investment in clutch size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f02">Figure 2</xref>), where high-investment species had maximum biases more than double (Bias<sub>Max</sub> &equals; 0.60) those of low-investment species (Bias<sub>Max</sub> &equals; 0.23). The median bias for all combinations of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> under the laying-plus-incubation strategy was 0.0 and was similar among all scenarios. By contrast, under the incubation-only strategy, the median bias increased with increasing clutch investment (low &equals; 0.06, medium &equals; 0.10, high &equals; 0.16; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Differences among species scenarios were due primarily to increased length of the laying period in relation to length of the incubation period; as clutch size increased, so too did the exposure period during laying.Overall, compared with the incubation-only strategy, the laying-plus-incubation strategy minimized bias across a larger range of combinations of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub>, and this pattern was consistent for all 3 scenarios (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The incubation-only strategy tended to minimize bias only when DNS<sub>Lay</sub> was high and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> low, whereas the laying-plus-incubation strategy minimized bias across a broader range of combinations.Comparison between incubation-only and laying-plus-incubation strategies for estimating nest-exposure periods with respect to which strategy produces the minimum absolute bias at a given level of daily nest survival (DNS) during the laying and incubation periods. Shading indicates whether the incubation-only strategy minimizes bias (dark gray) compared with the laying-plus-incubation strategy (light gray). In some situations, both strategies are equal with respect to bias (black). Panels reflect life-history scenarios that were designed to reflect a range of clutch investments exhibited by North American galliforms: (<bold>A</bold>) 5-day laying period, 25-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagopus leucura</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Braun1">Braun et al. 1993</xref>); (<bold>B</bold>) 10-day laying period, 27-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Schroeder1">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>); and (<bold>C</bold>) 18-day laying period, 23-day incubation period (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Colinus virginianus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Brennan1">Brennan et al. 2014</xref>).Researchers study avian nesting ecology and derive NS with varying objectives. Nest success can be important for population performance (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>), and as a life-history trait it plays a central role in individual fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Chalfoun1">Chalfoun and Martin 2007</xref>). When evaluating the role of nest success in affecting either of these 2 phenomena, obtaining NS values that are unbiased and reflect nest success accurately is clearly important. In other situations, however, researchers may be more interested in evaluating sources of variation in nest success within their system than in quantifying nest success per se. In the latter case, the effects of explanatory covariates on DNS can be modeled directly (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-McNew2">McNew et al. 2014</xref>), and deriving NS may be only a secondary objective of a study. Even in such situations, however, the ability to minimize bias in reported NS is important, because published estimates are often used in reviews and meta-analyses to ask questions related to population regulation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Sandercock1">Sandercock et al. 2008</xref>) and evolutionary processes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Martin1">Martin 1995</xref>), or simply to evaluate general patterns in nest success through space and time for species of concern (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>).Bias related to exposure period could be minimized or eliminated entirely by collecting sufficient data to estimate both DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> independently, in which case NS can be derived using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e03">Equation 3</xref> or <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-e04">4</xref> in the absence of any simplifying assumptions. This might be accomplished, in theory, by increasing field effort, being creative about nest-searching methods, and recognizing that certain field methods are not suited to discovery of nests during laying. However, the problems involved in conducting field studies of cryptic organisms in low densities and with limited budgets are not easily solved. Even technological solutions to increase nest detection, such as radiotelemetry (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Peterson1">Peterson et al. 2015</xref>) or satellite telemetry (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Webb1">Webb et al. 2012</xref>), require the presence of parents to detect nests and are likely to miss nests during egg laying. Small sample sizes for nests discovered during laying are therefore likely to remain a reality for many researchers.Both the incubation-only and the laying-plus-incubation strategies make inherent assumptions about the risk of nest failure during laying; one assumes that no risk exists (laying only), whereas the other assumes that risk of failure exists and is uniform between the 2 stages (laying plus incubation). The degree to which these assumptions are violated ultimately determines which strategy is most appropriate in a particular system. Evidence for variation in DNS among nesting stages in galliforms is limited. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Wilson1">Wilson et al. (2007)</xref> found that DNS for Willow Ptarmigan (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">L. lagopus</named-content></italic>) decreased during early incubation in relation to laying; however, DNS during laying was still substantially lower than 1.0 (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2007</xref>: fig. 2). Additionally, the stage-specific difference in DNS was apparent only in 1 of 2 populations studied, which presumably indicates that in the second population, DNS was roughly constant between stages. More definitive examples of stage-specific survival are available for other ground-nesting birds, such as waterfowl. For example, in a study of King Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Somateria spectabilis</named-content></italic>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Kellett1">Kellett et al. (2003)</xref> reported lower estimates of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> compared with DNS<sub>Inc</sub> during 5 of 7 yr. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Grant1">Grant and Shaffer (2012)</xref> found small or no difference between DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> for Blue-winged Teal (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas discors</named-content></italic>) and Gadwall (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. strepera</named-content></italic>) but found that for Mallards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>), DNS was substantially lower during laying than during incubation. The lack of stage-specific DNS for galliforms is further complicated by the fact that many researchers avoid purposely flushing nesting females, which limits the ability to establish the age of nests at discovery (through candling or floating eggs) and may preclude modeling stage-specific DNS, even if data are otherwise sufficient to do so. Not flushing nesting females is likely motivated by concerns of observer effects on nest success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>), such as those demonstrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-UherKoch1">Uher-Koch et al. (2015)</xref> for Arctic-breeding loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia</named-content></italic> spp.). Many such concerns are related to abandonment of nests following flushing or capture of a parent on the nest. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Gibson1">Gibson et al. (2015)</xref> found that female Greater Sage-Grouse that abandoned nests after disturbance shared other characteristics (e.g., habitat composition) with females whose nests were depredated, which implies that abandoned nests were likely to otherwise fail in the absence of observer disturbance. Field researchers must balance the potential for negative bias due to observer effects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-UherKoch1">Uher-Koch et al. 2015</xref>) against bias associated with a lack of data to estimate DNS<sub>Lay</sub>. However, the former can be evaluated explicitly and corrected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Gibson1">Gibson et al. 2015</xref>), whereas the later cannot.Our results demonstrate that in the absence of information on stage-specific DNS, the laying-plus-incubation strategy produces a smaller absolute bias across a larger range of situations than the incubation-only strategy (i.e. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f03">Figure 3</xref>); this difference seems to be due, in part, to the more realistic assumptions of the laying-plus-incubation strategy. By contrast, the incubation-only strategy relies on an assumption of no nest failure during laying, which we believe to be rather unrealistic. In making our assessments, we have used a uniform parameter space, whereby we consider all values of DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub> equally. If substantial heterogeneity exists among nesting stages (e.g., if a proportionally high number of nests are lost early in the nesting period; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Thompson1">Thompson et al. 2012</xref>), a nonuniform parameter space, informed by the most likely range of values for DNS<sub>Lay</sub> and DNS<sub>Inc</sub>, may provide a better assessment of which strategy reduces bias in a greater number of situations. Such a case is likely to be situational, however, and in the absence of direct or presumed information for a particular system, we consider a uniform parameter space useful for making the general inferences we have presented. We have also focused on absolute bias as a metric for evaluating each strategy, though we recognize that as NS decreases to a small value, the proportional size of bias in relation to NS increases. In such cases, the laying-plus-incubation strategy will be superior because it produces relatively small bias at the lowest values of DNS, compared with the incubation-only strategy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-f01">Figure 1</xref>).Researchers may elect to explicitly report NS based on both strategies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Davis1">Davis et al. 2014</xref>). When both estimates are accompanied with a discussion of the limitations inherent to each, this approach will provide a range of possible values for NS, while acknowledging inherent uncertainty. Relevant DNS values (including time-specific estimates if applicable) should also be reported in order to maximize the utility of results for future research and meta-analysis. In cases where a single specific value for NS is needed (e.g., to calculate fecundity for a stage-specific population model), we recommend that the nest-exposure period be defined, and NS calculated, on the basis of the period lengths of both laying and incubation. This will be particularly important for species with large clutches and short incubation periods, such as Northern Bobwhite or Ruffed Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bonasa umbellus</named-content></italic>).We have focused this assessment on North American galliforms in part for simplicity, but also because of inconsistency among studies of this group of birds. However, the general patterns we have outlined likely apply to any number of taxa in which parental behavior varies among nesting stages and in which the availability of data during an early nest stage is limited by low detections of nests. To further explore the relevance of our results for other avian taxa, we conducted a post hoc review of literature for 2 other groups of ground-nesting birds, waterfowl (ducks and geese) and shorebirds, using criteria similar to those used for our review of galliforms (results summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-t02">Table 2</xref>). Of 13 waterfowl studies that we reviewed, all authors (100&percnt;) report using the laying-plus-incubation strategy, demonstrating consistency among recent studies of ducks and geese. For shorebirds, however, results were variable and more similar to our review of galliforms. Five of 9 studies (56&percnt;) reported NS based only on the incubation interval, whereas 4 studies (44&percnt;) employed the laying-plus-incubation strategy. Our comparisons among low, medium, and high clutch-allocation strategies in galliforms provides some insights that can be extended across taxonomic boundaries and may prove useful in other taxa for which approaches have traditionally been variable. For species in which the exposure period during a low-detection stage (laying, in the case of galliforms) is long in comparison to the high-detection stage(s), the potential for bias is greater than in scenarios when the low-detection stage is relatively short. As a general rule, we therefore suspect that the potential for exposure-period bias will be minimal for species with small clutches and/or where parents actively tend nests for long periods after the onset of incubation. For this reason, the consequences of ignoring the laying period in studies of shorebirds (almost universally 4 eggs clutch<sup>&minus;1</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-577-Lengyel1">Lengyel et al. 2009</xref>) are likely to be minor, at least in comparison to species with large clutches and/or short incubation periods, such as many species of waterfowl. It is relatively straightforward to replicate our scenario-based approach, and we encourage researchers to do so using species-specific parameters or other additional information (e.g., appropriate parameter space) when choosing between the 2 strategies in a particular system.Results of our literature review comparing choice of exposure-period strategy for publications reporting estimated nest survival (NS) derived from daily nest survival (DNS) estimates for waterfowl (ducks and geese) and shorebirds. Only peer-reviewed publications from 2004 to 2015 that explicitly report DNS and NS were used.We thank K. Winiarski for reviewing the manuscript. This work was supported by the University of Nevada Reno Agricultural Experiment Station, the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, the Nevada Department of Wildlife, the U.S. Bureau of Land Management, NV Energy Corp, and the University of Maine Agricultural and Forest Experiment Station. This is Maine Agricultural and Forest Experiment Station Publication no. 3430.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This work is based on research supported in part by McIntire-Stennis Grant ME0-021422 from the USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> No animal or human subjects were involved in the research.