 Effect of sampling effort on bias and precision of trends in migration counts  Temporal and spatial patterns of repeated migratory journeys by Ospreys  Within- and among-year effects of cold fronts on migrating raptors at Hawk Mountain, Pennsylvania, 1934&ndash;1991  Hierarchical models for smoothed population indices: The importance of considering variations in trends of count data among sites  Goals and strategies for estimating trends in landbird abundance  lme4: Linear mixed-effects models using S4 classes  Incorporating detectability into analyses of population trends based on hawk counts: A double-observer approach  Insufficient sampling to identify species affected by turbine collisions  Population trend status of Ontario's forest birds  Radar analysis of fall bird migration stopover sites in the northeastern U.S  Cross-scale environmental influences on migratory stopover behaviour  COSEWIC Assessment Process, Categories, and Guidelines  Long-term trends in the number of monarch butterflies (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae) counted on fall migration at Long Point, Ontario, Canada (1995&ndash;2014)  Modeling systematic change in stopover duration does not improve bias in trends estimated from migration counts  The Raptor Population Index, 2013 Analysis Methods and Trend Results  Quantifying regional variation in population trends using migration counts  Citizen science as an ecological research tool: Challenges and benefits  Identification of summer origins of songbirds migrating through southern Canada in autumn  Detecting population trends in migratory birds of prey  Migrations of humpback whales past Cape Vidal, South Africa, and an estimate of the population increase rate (1988&ndash;2002)  Changes in numbers of land birds counted on migration at Long Point Bird Observatory  The influence of weather on hawk movements in coastal Northern California  Predicting origins of passerines migrating through Canadian migration monitoring stations using stable-hydrogen isotope analyses of feathers: A new tool for bird conservation  Recommended methods for monitoring bird populations by counting and capture of migrants  Integrating information from geolocators, weather radar, and citizen science to uncover a key stopover area of an aerial insectivore  Routes of migrating soaring birds  Survey effort effects on power to detect trends in raptor migration counts  A hierarchical analysis of population change with application to Cerulean Warblers  Bird&ndash;building collisions in the United States: Estimates of annual mortality and species vulnerability  Understanding the value of imperfect science from national estimates of bird mortality from window collisions  Comparing models of Red Knot population dynamics  Timing and magnitude of Broad-winged Hawk migration at Montclair Hawk Lookout, New Jersey, and Hawk Mountain, Pennsylvania  Stable hydrogen isotopes identify leapfrog migration, degree of connectivity, and summer distribution of Golden Eagles in eastern North America  Regional distribution shifts help explain local changes in wintering raptor abundance: Implications for interpreting population trends  Migrating giant honey bees (  Apis dorsata  ) congregate annually at stopover site in Thailand  Analysis of the North American Breeding Bird Survey using hierarchical models  Departure of migrating European Robins,   Erithacus rubecula  , from a stopover site in relation to wind and rain  Landscape movements of migratory birds and bats reveal an expanded scale of stopover  Individuality in bird migration: Routes and timing  Natal origins of migratory monarch butterflies at wintering colonies in Mexico: New isotopic evidence  Hourly or daily counts of animals during migration are used to assess change in population status. However, due to financial and logistical constraints, it is sometimes not possible to sample the entire migration, resulting in an unknown impact on accuracy and precision of estimated trends. Using simulated migration counts of 3 raptor species, commonly detected Sharp-shinned Hawks (  Accipiter striatus  ), rarely detected Merlins (  Falco columbarius  ), and super-flocking Broad-winged Hawks (  Buteo platypterus  ), we used a hierarchical modeling framework to test whether sampling effort influenced accuracy and precision of trends. We subsampled simulated datasets in various ways: weekends only; a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of the migration; or the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration. Bias in trend estimates and probability of error (estimating a false but significant trend) varied little with sampling effort for the common and rare species, which suggests that for these species, sampling only a small subset of the migration will not increase the probability of drawing false inference from the data. However, when counts of the super-flocking species were highly variable among days, trends were strongly positively biased when the first 25&percnt; of the migration was sampled, and probability of error increased with sampling effort. For all species, probability of detecting a significant and accurate trend also improved with sampling effort, but only exceeded 80&percnt; for common and rare species when a majority of the migration was sampled. Increasing sampling effort is recommended to improve power of trend analyses for common and rare species, but for super-flocking species, randomly sampling a subset of observation days throughout the migration can minimize error, but at the expense of a ~22&ndash;25&percnt; reduction in power using 20-year datasets. For species with this pattern, other methods to improve power, such as combining data across sites, should be considered.  Les d&eacute;comptes horaires ou quotidiens des animaux en migration sont utilis&eacute;s pour &eacute;valuer les changements dans le statut des populations. Cependant, en raison de contraintes financi&egrave;res et logistiques, il n'est parfois pas possible d'&eacute;chantillonner la migration enti&egrave;re, ce qui r&eacute;sulte en un impact inconnu sur l'exactitude et la pr&eacute;cision des tendances estim&eacute;es. &Agrave; l'aide de d&eacute;comptes migratoires simul&eacute;s de trois esp&egrave;ces d'oiseaux de proie, soit une esp&egrave;ce commun&eacute;ment d&eacute;tect&eacute;e (  Accipiter striatus  ), une esp&egrave;ce rarement d&eacute;tect&eacute;e (  Falco columbarius  ) et une esp&egrave;ce se r&eacute;unissant en grands groupes (  Buteo platypterus  ), nous avons utilis&eacute; un cadre de mod&eacute;lisation hi&eacute;rarchique afin de tester si l'effort d'&eacute;chantillonnage influen&ccedil;ait l'exactitude et la pr&eacute;cision des tendances. Nous avons sous-&eacute;chantillonn&eacute; des ensembles de donn&eacute;es simul&eacute;s de diff&eacute;rentes fa&ccedil;ons : fins de semaine seulement; un &eacute;chantillon al&eacute;atoire de 40 &percnt;, 60 &percnt; ou 80 &percnt; de la migration; ou les premiers 25 &percnt;, 50 &percnt; ou 75 &percnt; de la migration. Le biais dans les estimations des tendances et la probabilit&eacute; d'erreur (estimation d'une fausse tendance significative) ont peu vari&eacute; avec l'effort d'&eacute;chantillonnage pour l'esp&egrave;ce commune et l'esp&egrave;ce rare, ce qui sugg&egrave;re que pour ces esp&egrave;ces, l'&eacute;chantillonnage d'un petit sous-ensemble de la migration n'augmente pas la probabilit&eacute; de faire de fausses inf&eacute;rences sur les donn&eacute;es. Toutefois, lorsque les d&eacute;comptes de l'esp&egrave;ce faisant de grands groupes &eacute;taient tr&egrave;s variables d'une journ&eacute;e &agrave; l'autre, les tendances &eacute;taient fortement biais&eacute;es de fa&ccedil;on positive lorsque les premiers 25&percnt; de la migration &eacute;taient &eacute;chantillonn&eacute;s, et la probabilit&eacute; d'erreur augmentait avec l'effort d'&eacute;chantillonnage. Pour toutes les esp&egrave;ces, la probabilit&eacute; de d&eacute;tecter une tendance significative et exacte augmentait aussi avec l'effort d'&eacute;chantillonnage mais exc&eacute;dait 80 &percnt; pour l'esp&egrave;ce commune et l'esp&egrave;ce rare seulement lorsque la majorit&eacute; de la migration &eacute;tait &eacute;chantillonn&eacute;e. Une augmentation de l'effort d'&eacute;chantillonnage est recommand&eacute;e pour am&eacute;liorer la puissance des analyses de tendance pour les esp&egrave;ces communes et rares; pour les esp&egrave;ces faisant de grands groupes, le fait d'&eacute;chantillonner al&eacute;atoirement un sous-ensemble de jours d'observation pendant la migration peut minimiser l'erreur au d&eacute;triment d'une r&eacute;duction de ~22-25 &percnt; de la puissance en utilisant des ensembles de donn&eacute;es sur 20 ans. Pour les esp&egrave;ces pr&eacute;sentant ce patron, d'autres m&eacute;thodes pour am&eacute;liorer la puissance, comme combiner des donn&eacute;es de divers sites, devraient &ecirc;tre consid&eacute;r&eacute;es.   Mots-cl&eacute;s:  suivi des migrations, tendance, plan d'&eacute;chantillonnage, science citoyenne, mod&egrave;les mixtes lin&eacute;aires g&eacute;n&eacute;ralis&eacute;s, exactitude, pr&eacute;cision, puissance  Accurate and precise estimates of long-term population change are imperative for providing reliable assessments of population status, particularly for the assessment of species at risk ( COSEWIC 2012 ). For species that are either secretive during breeding or breed and winter in remote areas, data from breeding and wintering surveys are often unavailable or provide insufficient sampling coverage to assess population trends ( Dunn 2005 ,  Blancher et al. 2009 ,  Sauer and Link 2011 ). Monitoring species as they migrate between wintering and breeding grounds can be used as an additional source of information on population trend for these species ( Downes et al. 2000 ,  Bildstein et al. 2008 ,  Blancher et al. 2009 ,  Findlay et al. 2011 ,  Crewe and McCracken 2015 ). Counts of migrating animals are typically collected as hourly or daily counts of the number of individuals migrating past a count site ( Farmer et al. 2007 ,  Findlay et al. 2011 ), as the number of individuals using a count site during migratory stopover ( Francis and Hussell 1998 ,  Robinson 2012 ,  McGowan 2015 ), or as the number of individuals collected injured or dead following collisions with man-made structures ( Loss et al. 2014 ,  Beston et al. 2015 ). Population trends extrapolated from counts of migrating individuals have shown general correspondence with breeding surveys ( Francis and Hussell 1998 ,  Farmer et al. 2007 ) and provide an important contribution to the identification of research and management priorities that can lead to the improved assessment and conservation of populations ( Machtans and Thogmartin 2014 ,  McGowan 2015 ).  At present, counts of migrating raptors and songbirds are collected daily at over 200 sites across North America during spring and/or fall migration by sites associated with the Hawk Migration Association of North America (HMANA,  http://www.hmana.org/ ) and the Canadian Migration Monitoring Network (CMMN;  Crewe et al. 2008 ). Many of these sites have limited resources and rely on citizen scientists for data collection. Data collection protocols are typically standardized at each site to minimize the impact of volunteer turnover and random environmental variation on population counts ( Hussell and Ralph 1998 ). However, a reliance on volunteer observers can sometimes result in sporadic or incomplete sampling coverage both within and among years, which may bias trends ( Dickinson et al. 2010 ). Further, if the full migration season is not sampled at a site, species migrating early or late might be missed.  Previous trend analyses using songbird and raptor migration counts typically dropped species that were not sampled during an arbitrary proportion (usually 75&percnt;) of the migration, i.e. days of the year when a species typically passes through a site ( Francis and Hussell 1998 ,  Farmer et al. 2007 ). The effect of incomplete sampling coverage during peak migration on power to detect trends in annual migration counts was previously explored ( Lewis and Gould 2000 ). However, the impact of sampling a smaller portion of the migration window and missing part or all of peak migration on our ability to detect trends in migration counts has not been previously examined.  Further, variation in observer skill ( Link and Sauer 2002 ) and the effect of environmental variation on migration volume ( Buler and Dawson 2014 ), migratory behavior ( Schaub et al. 2004 ,  Calvert et al. 2009 ), migratory route ( Hall et al. 1992 ,  Allen et al. 1996 ,  Leshem and Yom-Tov 1998 ,  Vardanis et al. 2011 ), and observer detection ( Berthiaume et al. 2009 ) can contribute an unknown magnitude of random error to migration counts. Combined with migration strategy (e.g., super-flocking vs. individual migration) and abundance (common vs. rare), the result is often overdispersed and/or zero-inflated count data where a large proportion of variation is unrelated to the underlying population trend. The influence of count distribution and random error on our ability to recover trends in migration counts with sufficient accuracy and precision to confidently inform conservation efforts has not been rigorously examined.  In this paper, we simulated hourly migration counts with known constant rate of change in annual count population size to test whether sampling effort and count distribution influenced our ability to recover known trend from these data. To illustrate, we simulated hourly migration counts that represented (1) a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk,   Accipiter striatus  , Red-tailed Hawk,   Buteo jamaicensis  :  Crewe et al. 2013 ; White-throated Sparrow,   Zonotrichia albicollis  :  Crewe et al. 2008 ), (2) a rarely detected species with a high proportion of zero-observation counts (e.g., Merlin,   Falco columbarius  , Peregrine Falcon,   Falco peregrinus  :  Crewe et al. 2013 ; Canada Warbler,  Cardellina canadensis :  Crewe et al. 2008 ), and (3) a species that is commonly detected in large aggregations or flocks (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk,   Buteo platypterus  , Swainson's Hawk,   Buteo swainsoni  :  Bildstein 2006 ,  Miller et al. 2002 ; monarch butterfly,   Danaus plexippus  :  Crewe and McCracken 2015 ), resulting in highly overdispersed counts. Each species was also simulated to have high or low levels of random error in annual and daily counts, to test whether count distribution and extent of random error influenced accuracy and precision of estimated trends. Simulated datasets for each species were then subset in several ways: weekends only; by taking a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of observation counts across the entire migration; and by sampling the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration. The latter was used to test whether excluding a complete section of the migration and part or all of peak migration influenced our ability to recover the simulated trend. Our simulations were modeled to represent counts of raptors migrating past a count site. However, our results are applicable to any sampling protocol that collects counts of migrating animals on an hourly or daily basis ( Crewe et al. 2008 ,  Crewe and McCracken 2015 ), and given comparable count distribution. We recommend how count sampling protocols might be used to optimize sampling effort and statistical power, while minimizing the probability of drawing false inference about population trends.  We accessed hourly migration counts online through HMANA ( http://www.hawkcount.org/ ) for a commonly detected species (Sharp-shinned Hawk; hereafter &ldquo;common&rdquo;), a rarely detected species (Merlin; hereafter &ldquo;rare&rdquo;) and a super-flocking species with highly over-dispersed counts (Broad-winged Hawk; hereafter &ldquo;super-flocking&rdquo;) collected at 8 eastern North American hawk watch sites: 1) Beamer Conservation Area (Ontario, Canada: 1995&ndash;2009); 2) Cape May (New Jersey, USA: 1974&ndash;2004); 3) Hawk Mountain (Pennsylvania, USA: 1966&ndash;2009); 4) Hawk Ridge (Minnesota, USA: 1974&ndash;2009); 5) Holiday Beach (Ontario, Canada: 1979&ndash;2009); 6) Militia Hill (Pennsylvania, USA: 1992&ndash;2009); 7) Montclair (New Jersey, USA: 1977&ndash;2009); and 8) Waggoner's Gap (Pennsylvania, USA: 1987&ndash;2009). These sites collect hourly counts of the number of individuals of each species flying overhead during daylight hours throughout spring and/or fall migration. Detailed count methodology for each site is described elsewhere ( http://www.hawkcount.org/ ). We included only days of the year that included the middle 95th percentile of observations for each species and site, with the purpose to omit excess zero observations at the tail ends of the migration. We then estimated mean and coefficient of variation (CV) of hourly, daily, and annual counts, and in the proportion of zero-observation hours and days, and used those values as a guide to simulate data with realistic low and high levels of variation in counts for each species ( Table 1 ). Summarizing counts across 8 monitoring sites provided a range in expected counts for each species, which can vary among sites due, for example, to among-site variation in the size of the source population, in the proportion of the source population that migrates past the site, and in the probability that individuals migrating past the site will be detected ( Dunn 2005 ).  Mean (coefficient of variation; CV) of annual, daily, and hourly counts and proportion of 0-observation days and hours for simulated data, compared with mean count and minimum and maximum CV of real data, for a common, rare, and super-flocking species: Sharp-shinned Hawk (SSHA), Merlin (MERL), and Broad-winged Hawk (BWHA), respectively. Real data were collected at 8 sites in eastern North America: 1) Beamer conservation area (Ontario, Canada: 1995&ndash;2009); 2) Hawk Mountain (Pennsylvania, USA: 1966&ndash;2009); 3) Holiday Beach (Ontario, Canada: 1979&ndash;2009); 4) Montclair (New Jersey, USA: 1977&ndash;2009); 5) Cape May (New Jersey, USA: 1974&ndash;2004); 6) Militia Hill (Pennsylvania, USA: 1992&ndash;2009); 7) Waggoner's Gap (Pennsylvania, USA: 1987&ndash;2009); and 8) Hawk Ridge (Minnesota, USA: 1974&ndash;2009). Results for simulated data were based on 1,000 simulations for each combination of species, level of random variation (low annual/low daily, etc.), and dataset length (10 vs. 20 years).  We simulated hourly counts of the number of individuals of each raptor species detected migrating overhead past a count site using R (R version 2.14.2;  R Core Team 2013 ; see Appendix 1 for simulation code and Appendix  Table 4  for simulation parameterization). Our simulation model included annual, daily, and hourly sub-models, and assumed that the count population at a migration monitoring site was a consistent and representative sample of the size of the monitored population.  Simulation parameter values (Appendix  Table 4 ) were chosen to maximize the concordance of real and simulated data in terms of mean and CV of hourly, daily, and annual counts, and of the proportion of zero-observation hours ( Table 1 ). We ensured the distribution of real and simulated counts were comparable using quantile&ndash;quantile plots (qqplot, R version 3.0.3; Appendix  Figure 6 ).  For each of our 3 species, we simulated 10- and 20-year time series with an annual rate of change of &minus;3.9&percnt; year &minus;1 , which is equivalent to a ~30&percnt; decline in 10 years or ~50&percnt; decline in 20 years. A decline of 30&percnt; in 10 years is often used as an assessment criterion for species at risk ( COSEWIC 2012 ). For each species and time series length, we simulated 1,000 datasets under each of 4 variance scenarios: (1) low annual and low &ldquo;daily and hourly&rdquo; variation in counts (hereafter &ldquo;daily&rdquo; variation), (2) low annual and high daily variation, (3) high annual and low daily variation, and (4) high annual and high daily variation. All datasets were then subset in 7 ways to test whether and how accuracy and precision of estimated trends varied with sampling effort: including only data collected on weekends (2 consecutive days out of every 7); including a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of observation days within the migration of each species; or including only the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration of each species.  Due to the large number of datasets simulated (1,000 datasets for each of 3 species, 4 variance scenarios, and 8 levels of sampling effort &equals; 96,000 datasets), data were generated and analyzed using the Shared Hierarchical Academic Computing Network (Sharcnet;  www.sharcnet.ca ), which allowed over 200 processors to run simultaneously. Trend in migration counts was estimated for each simulated dataset using a generalized linear mixed model fit using the latest version of lme4 available at the time (GLMM; lme4 package version 0.999375-42,  Bates et al. 2013 ; R version 2.14.2). While we recognize that more recent lme4 versions may change results slightly, we did not reanalyze the entire suite of simulated datasets because this would have required a significant amount of time (several weeks) using Sharcnet. Also, a reanalysis of a small subsample of simulated datasets with a more recent version of lme4 (version 1.1-7) suggests that differences between versions were minor (Appendix  Figure 7 ).  For each species, we tested whether the absolute bias (estimated &ndash; simulated trend) varied among simulated factor levels by fitting a generalized linear model with gamma distribution (inverse link; MASS package, R version 3.0.3;  Venables and Ripley 2002 ), where bias was the response variable, and length of dataset (10 or 20 years), variation level (high or low annual or daily variation), subset type (weekends only, etc.), and interactions between subset type and length of dataset and subset type and variation level were explanatory factors. A similar regression was also used to test whether standard error of the trend estimate (precision) varied with dataset length, variation level, and subset type, again assuming a gamma distribution of errors and inverse link. Model fit was assessed by examining plots of residuals.  For each species, we also examined how simulated factor levels influenced the probability of drawing false inference from the data by calculating 1) the proportion of simulated datasets where confidence limits of the estimated trend included the simulated trend, and the trend was statistically significant ( p  &lt; 0.1), i.e. a significant and accurate trend (hereafter &ldquo;power&rdquo;), and 2) the proportion of simulated datasets where the confidence limits of the estimated trend did not include the simulated trend, but the trend was statistically significant, i.e. a significant but inaccurate trend (hereafter &ldquo;error&rdquo;). We note that statistical power is typically defined as the probability of rejecting a false null hypothesis ( Lewis and Gould 2000 ), and does not take accuracy into account. Our definition of power is thus more conservative, because it excludes inaccurate trends that differ significantly from zero. Throughout the text we distinguish between these two definitions of power by stating &ldquo;statistical power&rdquo; when referring to the traditional interpretation. Following the recommendation of  Bart et al. (2004) , we used a  p -value of 0.1, which was shown to better balance the probabilities of type I (false positive) and type II (false negative) errors in the estimation of bird population trends.  A decline in bias with increasing sampling effort was observed for all 3 species, particularly when annual variation in counts was high for the common and rare species, and when daily variation was high for the super-flocking species ( Table 2 ). Probability of estimating a biased trend (i.e. larger standard deviation;  Figure 1 ) was also greater when annual variation was high for common and rare species, and when daily variation was high for the super-flocking species. However, mean bias was less than &plusmn;0.4&percnt; year &minus;1  for all 3 species, with the exception of super-flocking datasets subset to the first 25&percnt; of the migration when variation among daily counts was high, in which case bias exceeded 6&percnt; year &minus;1  using 10-year datasets and 1&percnt; year &minus;1  using 20-year datasets ( Table 2  and  Figure 1 ). In other words, for common and rare species, mean bias in estimated trend was comparable regardless of whether the entire migration was sampled, or data were collected as infrequently as weekends ( Figures 1 A,  1 B). For the super-flocking species, subsetting datasets with high daily variation to weekends or by drawing a random sample of observation days from across the migration did not have the same biasing effect on estimated trends as did sampling the first 25&percnt; of the migration ( Table 2  and  Figure 1 ).  Coefficients for the terms explaining variation in bias of estimated trend in hourly migration counts for datasets simulated to represent a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk), where bias of estimated trend was the response variable, and sampling effort, variation level, number of years, and interactions between sampling effort and variation level and sampling effort and years were explanatory factors.  Mean bias (simulated &ndash; estimated trend; &plusmn; standard deviation) of estimated trend in hourly migration counts for 10-year ( A ) and 20-year ( B ) simulated datasets representing a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk). Counts were simulated to have low (triangles) or high (squares) annual variation, and low (no fill) or high (black fill) daily variation (&ldquo;annual/daily&rdquo;), and were subset by sampling weekends only, sampling a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of the migration, or by sampling the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration ( n  &equals; 1,000 for each set of factor levels).  For all 3 species, increasing the length of the time series had the largest effect on bias, particularly when annual variation in counts was high for the common and rare species, and when daily variation in counts was high for the super-flocking species. However, again, effect sizes for differences in bias among variation levels did not exceed &plusmn;0.34&percnt; year &minus;1  ( Table 2  and  Figure 1 ). For the rare species, trend estimates became less positively biased but more negatively biased as the length of the time series increased from 10 to 20 years ( Table 2  and  Figure 1 ). Increasing the time series from 10 to 20 years also resulted in less-positively biased trends for the super-flocking species, and in particular, the reduction in bias resulted in negatively biased trends when daily variation in counts was high, though bias remained lower overall using the longer time series ( Table 2  and  Figure 1 ).  Precision of trend estimates increased, and standard errors became smaller, with length of the time series and with sampling effort for all 3 species ( Table 3 ), as is expected when the number of observations in a dataset increases. Increasing the time series from 10 to 20 years had the largest effect on precision for all 3 species, with precision increasing with number of years sampled ( Table 3  and  Figure 2 ). For common and rare species trends were also more precise when annual variation in counts was low, and with the exception of sampling the first 25&percnt; of the migration, standard errors were comparable among similar sized data subsets, regardless of whether data were a random sample or a continuous period of time (e.g., 80&percnt; random sample vs. 75&percnt; of the migration window;  Table 3 ). For the super-flocking species, trend estimates were more precise when daily variation in counts was low, and when data were collected as a random sample of observation days, as opposed to a continuous but incomplete sample of the migration, particularly when variation in daily counts was high ( Table 3  and  Figure 2 ).  Coefficients for the terms explaining variation in standard errors of trends in hourly migration counts, estimated using data simulated to represent a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species with zero-inflated counts (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk), where standard error of the trend estimate was the response variable, and sampling effort, variation level, and number of years were explanatory factors. In all cases,  p  &lt; 0.001.  Mean standard error (&plusmn; standard deviation) of estimated trend in hourly migration counts for 10-year ( A ) and 20-year ( B ) simulated datasets representing a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk). Counts were simulated to have low (triangles) or high (squares) annual variation, and low (no fill) or high (black fill) daily variation (&ldquo;annual/daily&rdquo;), and were subset by sampling weekends only, sampling a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of the migration, or by sampling the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration ( n  &equals; 1,000 for each set of factor levels).  Power increased with length of the time series and with an increase in sampling effort for all 3 species ( Figure 3 A,  3 B). Power was typically higher when annual and daily variation in counts were low. Overall, power to detect a 3.9&percnt; year &minus;1  decline over 20 years was 82&ndash;93&percnt; for a commonly detected species with an annual coefficient of variation &le;0.3 and when a random sample of 60&percnt; or more of the entire migration or the first 50&percnt; or more of the migration was sampled. For the rarely detected species, power of 81&ndash;85&percnt; was detected for 20-year datasets with an annual coefficient of variation of 0.4 when a random sample of at least 80&percnt; of the entire migration or the first 75&percnt; or more of the migration was sampled. For the super-flocking species, extreme variation in daily and/or annual counts resulted in particularly low power to detect a significant trend, and power did not exceed 40&percnt; regardless of length of time series and sampling intensity.  Power, or proportion of 1,000 simulated datasets where confidence limits of the estimated trend included the simulated trend, and the trend was statistically significant at  p  &le; 0.1, for 10-year ( A ) and 20-year ( B ) datasets simulated to represent a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk). Counts were simulated to have low (triangles) or high (squares) annual variation, and low (no fill) or high (black) daily variation (&ldquo;annual/daily&rdquo;), and were subset by sampling weekends, sampling a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of the migration, or by sampling the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration.  Error rate, and therefore the probability of drawing false inference from the data, declined with an increase in length of the time series from 10 to 20 years for all 3 species ( Figure 4 ). Using 20-year datasets, error was 5&percnt; or less for the common species, and 8&percnt; or less for the rare species, regardless of sampling effort. Error rates were lowest when annual variation was low for the common and rare species, and when daily variation was low for the super-flocking species. For super-flocking species with high daily variation, error increased from between 9&percnt; and 14&percnt; when sampling effort was low (weekends, first 25&percnt; of migration) to between 19&percnt; and 23&percnt; as sampling effort increased (80&percnt; random sample, 75&percnt; migration window, or entire migration sampled) using 20-year datasets ( Figure 4 ). Using 10-year datasets for this species, error was as high as 30&percnt; when the complete migration was sampled.  Rate of error, or proportion of 1,000 simulated datasets where confidence limits of the estimated trend did not include the simulated trend, but the trend was statistically significant at  p  &le; 0.1, for 10-year ( A ) and 20-year ( B ) datasets simulated to represent a commonly detected species (e.g., Sharp-shinned Hawk), a rarely detected species (e.g., Merlin), and a super-flocking species with highly overdispersed counts (e.g., Broad-winged Hawk). Counts were simulated to have low (triangles) or high (squares) annual variation, and low (no fill) or high (black) daily variation (&ldquo;annual/daily&rdquo;), and were subset by sampling weekends, sampling a random sample of 40&percnt;, 60&percnt;, or 80&percnt; of the migration, or by sampling the first 25&percnt;, 50&percnt;, or 75&percnt; of the migration.  With few exceptions, mean bias in estimated trend was within the suggested acceptable limit of 0.5&percnt; year &minus;1  suggested for landbird population monitoring ( Bart et al. 2004 ), regardless of sampling effort. With the exception of species counted migrating in large aggregations or flocks, bias and rate of error did not vary greatly with sampling effort, which suggests that sampling as infrequently as weekends or missing peak migration will not result in a higher probability of drawing false inference from the data than would sampling daily throughout the entire migration.  In contrast, the probability of detecting a significant but inaccurate trend increased with sampling effort for super-flocking species when variation in daily counts was high. In this case, trends were more likely to be biased, and combined with an increase in precision with sampling effort, trends were more likely to differ significantly from zero and to have confidence limits that excluded the simulated trend. Thus, when daily variation in counts is high, randomly sampling 40&percnt; of the migration can lower the probability of drawing false inference from the data with little influence on bias, but at the expense of a decline in power to 18&percnt; from 22&ndash;24&percnt; observed for full seasonal coverage using 20-year datasets. The reduction in power was less obvious using 10-year datasets; power declined from 9&ndash;10&percnt; for full seasonal coverage to 8&percnt; when trends were estimated using a random 40&percnt; sample of the migration.  Power, or our ability to accurately detect a decline of 3.9&percnt; year &minus;1  using counts of migrating individuals, did increase with sampling effort. While not directly comparable, power detected here was similar or better to the 80&percnt; statistical power to detect a 3&percnt; decline in annual raptor migration counts estimated using linear regression when coefficient of variation in annual counts was less than 0.22 ( Lewis and Gould 2000 ). Because our definition of power excludes inaccurate trends, and is therefore more conservative than the traditional definition of statistical power, this suggests that modeling random variation in hourly and daily migration counts through the specification of random effects in a mixed (hierarchical) modeling framework can increase the probability of detecting an accurate trend when compared with analyzing annual totals in a linear regression framework. This supports previous work that suggested hierarchical models result in more accurate and precise estimates of population trend than non-hierarchical (generalized linear or additive) models ( Amano et al. 2012 ,  Crewe 2015 ). Power is also expected to increase with rate of population change and with sample size, i.e. with length of time series and sampling effort, as observed here and elsewhere ( Crewe et al. 2015a , b ). We did not undertake a sensitivity analysis to determine the minimum rate of change required to confidently detect accurate and precise trends in migration counts for the various count distributions and levels of random variation in counts explored here. Such an analysis would make an important contribution to the assessment of the use of migration counts for population monitoring, and could be accomplished by modifying parameters in the migration count simulation presented here (Appendix 1).  For common and rarely detected migrants, estimating trends using daily totals as opposed to hourly counts or annual totals could further increase power ( Crewe 2015 ). Alternatively, given the high variability among hourly and daily counts often observed for migrants detected in large aggregations or flocks like the Broad-winged Hawk or monarch butterfly ( Crewe and McCracken 2015 ), aggregating counts into effort-corrected annual totals could improve model fit, and thus increase power and lower the probability of drawing false inference from the data ( Miller et al. 2002 ,  Crewe 2015 ). Incorporating weather or habitat covariates in trend analyses might also improve the precision of annual population indices ( Francis and Hussell 1998 ,  Farmer et al. 2007 ), and in the case that a long-term systematic change in environmental covariates has occurred, their inclusion could model any associated bias in trend (but see  Crewe et al. 2015a ). Further, the precision of trends derived from migration counts might be more heavily influenced by weather and other environmental covariates when trends are estimated using hourly as opposed to daily or annual totals, particularly when sampling effort is low ( Farmer et al. 2007 ), supporting either the use of covariates or the aggregation of counts to daily or annual totals. The influence of weather covariates on bias and precision of estimated trends should be examined for both hourly and daily migration count data.  Counts of migrating animals are assumed to be proportional to the size of the monitored population ( Dunn 2005 ). In other words, we assume that annual fluctuations in the count population reflect annual fluctuations in underlying population size. Thus, a temporal shift in breeding distribution ( Paprocki et al. 2014 ) or migration route ( Vardanis et al. 2011 ), for example, could lead to a temporal shift in the proportion of the monitored population that passes a site, and thus lead to inappropriate inference about population trends if such shifts are not taken into consideration ( Paprocki et al. 2014 ). Currently, the specific breeding origin of individuals detected at migration count sites is known only broadly. For raptors, songbirds, and monarch butterflies, broad breeding catchment areas were defined using stable hydrogen isotopes in feather samples ( Wassenaar and Hobson 1998 ,  Dunn et al. 2006 ,  Hobson et al. 2015 ,  Nelson et al. 2015 ). Combined with weather radar (migration volume and direction;  Laughlin et al. 2013 ) and large-scale telemetry studies (stopover behavior, migration orientation;  Taylor et al. 2011 ) breeding and wintering catchment areas of migrants, and migratory connectivity, could be refined ( Nelson et al. 2015 ). This would allow correlation of trends with underlying changes in habitat or land use on the inferred breeding or wintering grounds. Estimation of daily and annual variation in migration route or migration volume past a site might also be possible (e.g., using radar;  Buler and Dawson 2014 ), and could be used as a covariate to increase precision of trend analyses by accounting for some of the observed variation in counts. Enhancing the spatial coverage of the migration corridor by combining data across multiple sites that sample the larger population could also increase accuracy and precision of estimated trends by allowing site-specific variation in counts to be estimated independently of underlying change in the count population ( Amano et al. 2012 ,  Crewe et al. 2015b ).  Overall, our results suggest that when estimating long-term trends in counts of migrating animals, sampling daily throughout the entire migration is preferred to maximize power to detect an accurate trend, though probability of false inference is not compromised by sampling less frequently. In fact, for species with highly overdispersed daily counts, the probability of drawing false inference can be minimized by sampling less frequently than daily, with little influence on bias of trends if counts are collected randomly throughout the migration. Thus, while sampling daily should be encouraged, it need not be a prerequisite for the inclusion of a site in trend analyses. Rather, standardization of the timing and location of sampling within and among migration seasons should be the primary factor influencing whether migration count data are used to estimate trends at a particular site.  We thank all of the staff and volunteers that collect raptor migration data annually at Beamer Conservation Area, Hawk Mountain, Holiday Beach, Montclair, Cape May, Militia Hill, Waggoner's Gap, and Hawk Ridge watch sites. This work was made possible by the facilities of the Shared Hierarchical Academic Research Computing Network (SHARCNET:  www.sharcnet.ca ) and Compute/Calcul Canada. John Brzustowski and Ge Baolai provided technical assistance with SHARCNET. This report was prepared as part of the Raptor Population Index (RPI) partnership of Bird Studies Canada, Hawk Mountain Sanctuary, the Hawk Migration Association of North America, and HawkWatch International ( http://rpi-project.org/ ).   Funding statement:  Funding for this project was provided by an NSERC PGSB scholarship to T.L.C., a MITACS Accelerate Grant to T.L.C., P.D.T., Chris Guglielmo, and D.L (Bird Studies Canada), and an NSERC Discovery Grant to P.D.T.   Ethics statement:  Detailed count protocols for each site are described elsewhere ( http://www.hawkcount.org/ ). No birds were handled in the collection of the visual raptor migration counts used here, and counts were collected with the permission of relevant site authorities.   Author contributions:  T.L.C., D.L., and P.D.T. conceived the idea and design. T.L.C. conducted the research. T.L.C. wrote the paper. T.L.C., D.L., and P.D.T. developed the methods. T.L.C. analyzed the data. T.L.C., D.L., and P.D.T. contributed substantial materials, resources, or funding.    Definition of simulation parameters (values are shown for parameters that did not differ with species or levels of annual and daily variation; see Table S1 for values of parameters that did vary):  Y.1: starting population size (year &equals; 1).   nyears : number of years to simulate (10 or 20).   sday : start day, determines number of days in season.   sday.err : standard deviation of random normal error on start day.   shr  &equals; &minus;3; start hour, determines number of hours in day.   shr.err  &equals; 0.5; standard deviation of normal random error on start hour.   prob.move : binomial probability that birds move on a given day.   trend  &equals; &minus;0.03885; log-linear decline required to achieve approximately 30&percnt; decline in 10 years.   trend.err : standard deviation of random normal error added to trend on log scale.   day.err/hr.err : standard deviation of random normal error added to daily and hourly counts on log scale.   m.spread  &equals; 0/ m.spread.err  &equals; 0.8; mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the mean of the normal density curve describing distribution of daily counts.   m.peak/m.peak.err:  mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the standard deviation of the normal density curve describing distribution of daily counts.   k.day/k.hr  &equals; clumping parameter for negative binomial error added to daily and hourly counts.   m.spread.hr &equals; 0/m.spread.err.hr  &equals; 0.2; mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the mean of the normal density curve describing distribution of hourly counts.   m.peak.hr/m.peak.err  &equals; mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the standard deviation of the normal density curve describing distribution of hourly counts.   weath.pois  &equals; 1.2; lambda for Poisson error added to &lsquo;weather' vector.    Parameters modified to simulate hourly raptor migration counts with various levels of variation in annual, daily, and hourly counts, and in proportion of zero-observation days and hours, where nyears &equals; number of years in simulated dataset; Y.1 is the starting annual population size; trend.err, day.err, and hr.err &equals; standard deviation of random normal error added to trend, daily counts, and hourly counts, respectively, on log scale; sday &equals; start day (negative so days are centered on zero); sday.err &equals; standard deviation of random normal error on start day; m.peak and m.peak.err &equals; mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the standard deviation of the normal density curve describing distribution of daily counts; k.day and k.hr &equals; dispersion parameter for negative binomial distribution describing over-dispersion of daily and hourly counts; prob.move &equals; binomial probability that birds will move on a given day; and m.peak.hr and m.peak.err.hr &equals; mean and standard deviation of random normal error on the standard deviation of the normal density curve describing distribution of hourly counts.  Plots of a comparison of real and simulated daily total counts for the commonly detected Sharp-shinned Hawk (SSHA) to normal and gamma distributions. Real data (top row) were collected at Hawk Mountain Sanctuary in 2009, and simulated data (bottom row) were simulated to have high daily and annual variation in counts. Data are shown for a single, randomly chosen year. Note that while the simulation (Appendix S1) assumed that the availability of migrants followed a normal distribution, additional simulation parameters resulted in a distribution of counts that more closely resembled a gamma distribution, as is the case with real migration count data.  Series of quantile&ndash;quantile plots (qqplot, stats package; R Core Team 2011) comparing the distribution of real migration counts collected at Hawk Ridge Bird Observatory, Minnesota, United States (1974&ndash;2009), and 2 separate simulated migration count datasets (simulated datasets 1 and 100 of 1,000), with Pearson correlation (Corr) of q&ndash;q scores. Note that scales may differ between real and simulated data because data were simulated to represent the range of abundance distributions observed across 8 eastern North American hawk watch sites, and not this site in particular. A correlation coefficient for q&ndash;q scores near one suggests close correspondence between distributions, even if counts are on average higher in one dataset compared to the other.  Comparison of estimated year coefficients between old (lme4&lowbar;0.999375.42) and newer (lme4&lowbar;1.1-7) versions of lme4 in R for a subset of 10 simulated datasets for each of the 3 count distributions examined (common, rare, super-flocking), and for both the lowest and highest levels of annual and daily variation in migration counts (i.e. Low/Low, High/High). Results suggests little variation in year coefficient between lme4 versions. 