 Sustainability assessment of Plain Pigeons and White-crowned Pigeons illegally hunted in Puerto Rico  Land-cover and land-use change and its contribution to the large-scale organization of Puerto Rico's bird assemblages  Shorebird hunting in the Caribbean. Symposia report from the Western Hemisphere Group, fourth meeting  Important Bird Areas in the Caribbean  Landscape and regional impacts of hurricanes in Puerto Rico  General formulation for distance sampling  The status of Puerto Rico's forests, 2003  Estimating bird abundance: Making methods work  Design and analysis methods for fish survival experiments based on release&ndash;recapture  Further topics in distance sampling  The ecological life zones of Puerto Rico and the U.S. Virgin Islands  Allowable levels of take for the trade in Nearctic songbirds  Point transect sampling along linear features  Improving estimates of bird density using multiple-covariate distance sampling  BUGS in Bayesian stock assessments  Non-linear state space modeling of fisheries biomass dynamics by using Metropolis-Hastings within-Gibbs sampling  JAGS: A program for analysis of Bayesian graphical models using Gibbs sampling  Detectability and population density of Scaly-naped Pigeons before and after Hurricane Hugo in Puerto Rico and Vieques island  Spatial and temporal variation in the detectability and density of columbids in Puerto Rico and on Vieques Island  Nest density and success of columbids in Puerto Rico  Transect surveys of columbid nests on Puerto Rico, Vieques, and Culebra islands  Distance sampling survey and abundance estimation of the critically endangered Grenada Dove ( Leptotila wellsi )  Monitoring and modeling of population dynamics for the harvest management of Scaly-naped Pigeons in Puerto Rico  Estimation of density and population size and recommendations for monitoring trends of Bahama parrots on Great Abaco and Great Inagua  Reproduction of Plain Pigeons ( Columba inornata wetmorei ) in east-central Puerto Rico  Population monitoring of Plain Pigeons in Puerto Rico  Assessing allowable take of migratory birds  Some aspects of the dynamics of populations important to the management of commercial fisheries  Using R to run JAGS  Distance software: Design and analysis of distance sampling surveys for estimating population size  Migratory bird hunting; final frameworks for early-season migratory bird hunting regulations; final rule  Estimating sustainable mortality limits for shorebirds using the Western Atlantic Flyway  The White-crowned Pigeon in Puerto Rico: Status, distribution, and movements  Bird conservation in the United States Caribbean  The Puerto Rican Plain Pigeon ( Patagioenas inornata wetmorei ) and the White-crowned Pigeon ( P. leucocephala ) are hunted illegally in Puerto Rico, despite being protected. Data are lacking to estimate how many are hunted illegally each year. For this reason, we used abundance estimates derived from distance sampling surveys conducted in 1986&ndash;2014 to (1) fit a Bayesian state-space model, (2) estimate posterior distributions for population and harvest management parameters (e.g., growth rate, carrying capacity, and maximum sustainable harvest rate), and (3) predict abundance in 2025 as a function of potential illegal hunting in 2015&ndash;2024. For the Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon, respectively, the intrinsic rate of population growth was 0.351 (95&percnt; credible interval &equals; 0.086&ndash;0.737) and 0.352 (0.094&ndash;0.699), population carrying capacity was 55,840 (29,649&ndash;96,505) and 73,692 (47,225&ndash;98,434) individuals, maximum sustainable harvest rate was 0.176 (0.043&ndash;0.369 and 0.047&ndash;0.349), and predicted abundance was 20,536 (8,167&ndash;89,040) and 29,361 (1,779&ndash;100,937) individuals in 2025. Both pigeon populations increased from low numbers in the 1980&ndash;1990s, recovered quickly after hurricanes in 1989 and 1998, surpassed carrying capacity in 1995&ndash;2008, and decreased sharply at the same time that legal hunting of columbids increased in 2008&ndash;2014. Our monitoring and modeling results suggest that an increase in illegal hunting may be responsible for some of the abundance decline in 2008&ndash;2014, and that population sustainability may be affected by illegal hunting in 2015&ndash;2025. Therefore, data collection and the control of illegal hunting should be considered management priorities. Because we are updating model-based abundance predictions annually with monitoring data, we can inform management decisions, evaluate the results of conservation actions taken to maintain the pigeon populations fluctuating around carrying-capacity levels, and learn from the comparison of estimated and predicted abundances. Our monitoring and modeling scheme is applicable to other resident and migratory bird populations in the Caribbean.   Patagioenas inornata wetmorei  y  P. leucocephala  son cazadas ilegalmente, aunque est&aacute;n protegidas en Puerto Rico. No existen datos para estimar el n&uacute;mero de palomas que se cazan ilegalmente cada a&ntilde;o. Por esta raz&oacute;n, usamos estimados de abundancia de muestreos de distancia llevados a cabo en 1986&ndash;2014 para (1) ajustar un modelo Bayesiano de estado-espacio, (2) estimar las distribuciones posteriores de par&aacute;metros poblacionales y de manejo de cosecha (p.ej., tasa de crecimiento, capacidad de carga y tasa de cosecha m&aacute;xima sostenible), y (3) hacer predicciones sobre abundancia en 2025 como funci&oacute;n del potencial de caza ilegal en 2015&ndash;2024. Para el  P. i. wetmorei  y  P. leucocephala , respectivamente, la tasa intr&iacute;nseca de crecimiento poblacional fue 0.351 (intervalo de credibilidad de 95&percnt; &equals; 0.086&ndash;0.737) y 0.352 (0.094&ndash;0.699), la capacidad de carga poblacional fue 55,840 (29,649&ndash;96,505) y 73,692 (47,255&ndash;98,434) individuos, la tasa de cosecha m&aacute;xima sostenible fue 0.176 (0.043&ndash;0.369 y 0.047&ndash;0.349), y la predicci&oacute;n de abundancia fue 20,536 (8,167&ndash;89,040) y 29,361 (1,778&ndash;100,937) individuos en 2025. Ambas poblaciones de palomas crecieron de n&uacute;meros bajos en 1980&ndash;1990s, se recuperaron r&aacute;pidamente de los huracanes en 1989 y 1998, sobrepasaron su capacidad de carga en 1995&ndash;2008, y decrecieron marcadamente al mismo tiempo que la actividad de caza legal de los col&uacute;mbidos aument&oacute; en 2008&ndash;2014. Nuestros resultados de monitoreo y modelaje sugieren que un aumento en la caza ilegal puede ser responsable de al menos parte del decrecimiento poblacional en 2008&ndash;2014, y que la sostenibilidad de las poblaciones puede verse afectada por la caza ilegal en 2015&ndash;2024. Por lo tanto, la recopilaci&oacute;n de datos y el control de la caza ilegal deben ser considerados prioridades de manejo. Porque nuestras predicciones de abundancia en base al modelo son actualizadas con datos de monitoreo anualmente, podemos informar las decisiones de manejo, evaluar las acciones de conservaci&oacute;n que se lleven a cabo para mantener a las poblaciones de palomas fluctuando alrededor de sus niveles de capacidad de carga, y aprender de la comparaci&oacute;n de los estimados y las predicciones de abundancia. Nuestro esquema de monitoreo y modelaje es aplicable a otras poblaciones de aves residentes y migratorias en el Caribe.   Palabras clave:  Evaluaci&oacute;n poblacional, modelo Bayesiano de estado-espacio, monitoreo, muestreo de distancia,  Patagioenas inornata wetmorei ,  P. leucocephala   Bird populations are often harvested for subsistence, commercial, recreational, or control purposes and are often managed with incomplete information about annual changes in abundance or knowledge of sustainable harvest levels ( Runge et al. 2009 ,  Johnson et al. 2012 ,  Watts et al. 2015 ). Monitoring and modeling are essential for assessments of population sustainability given extant levels of hunting mortality (e.g., see  U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service &lsqb;USFWS&rsqb; 2015 ). In the Caribbean region, hunting can be a major factor in the conservation of resident and migratory birds ( BirdLife International 2008 ). However, assessments of population sustainability in relation to harvesting are lacking, even on islands where birds of conservation concern are hunted ( Andres 2011 ,  Watts et al. 2015 ).  In Puerto Rico, the legal hunting of game birds is regulated and monitored annually ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2014 ,  U.S. Department of the Interior &lsqb;USDOI&rsqb; 2015 ), but resource managers are concerned with the illegal hunting of nongame birds ( USFWS 1982 ,  Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources &lsqb;PRDNER&rsqb; 2005 ). Here, to address this concern, we provide an assessment of population sustainability given ongoing illegal hunting of the Puerto Rican Plain Pigeon ( Patagioenas inornata wetmorei ) and the White-crowned Pigeon ( P. leucocephala ). The Puerto Rican Plain Pigeon (&ldquo;Plain Pigeon&rdquo; hereafter) is a federally listed endangered subspecies ( USFWS 1982 ), and the White-crowned Pigeon is listed as a bird of conservation concern ( USFWS 2008 ).  The Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon are hunted illegally in Puerto Rico despite being protected by commonwealth and federal wildlife laws and regulations (e.g., see  USDOI 2015 ). Presently, both pigeon populations are at low numbers, and data are lacking to determine whether mortality from illegal hunting can be sustained ( Wiley 1979 ,  1985 ,  PRDNER 2005 ,  USFWS 2011 ). However, distance sampling surveys have been conducted annually to monitor changes in the abundance (density and population size) of game and nongame columbids in Puerto Rico since 1986 ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1995a ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003b ,  2014 ). Therefore, our objectives were to (1) fit a Bayesian state-space model using the abundance estimates derived from distance sampling surveys conducted in 1986&ndash;2014, (2) estimate posterior distributions for population and harvest management parameters (e.g., growth rate, carrying capacity, and maximum sustainable harvest rate), and (3) predict Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon abundance in 2025 as a function of potential illegal hunting in 2015&ndash;2024.  Puerto Rico is the easternmost (18&deg;35&prime;&ndash;17&deg;55&prime;N, 67&deg;15&prime;&ndash;65&deg;35&prime;W) and smallest of the Greater Antilles. The Puerto Rican mainland covers 864,360 ha, with a maximum elevation of 1,338 m ( Brandeis et al. 2007 ). There are 6 subtropical life zones, with the dry, moist, and wet zones covering 99&percnt; of the land area ( Ewel and Whitmore 1973 ). Two major hurricanes made landfall and caused severe vegetation damage in 1989 and 1998 ( Boose et al. 2004 ). Forest cover increased from 34&percnt; in 1985 to 57&percnt; in 2003 ( Brandeis et al. 2007 ).  We surveyed 1,375 points in the 3 major life zones of the island in 1986&ndash;2014 ( Figure 1 ). The survey region covered 749,000 ha, excluding urban centers and other heavily developed areas. On-road points were located systematically with random starts along paved and unpaved roads. Off-road points were located systematically with random starts at a minimum distance of 200 m from roads. Minimum distance was 400 m between off-road points and 800 m between on-road points. We used teams of 2 observers to increase the chance of meeting method assumptions ( Buckland et al. 2001 ,  2008 ). Both observers remained side by side at point centers for 6 min, focusing on detecting calling and noncalling pigeons within 180 m. One observer focused on recording the data, while the other focused on recording detection distances to single pigeons or the geometric center of pigeon clusters. A cluster was defined as &ge;2 pigeons detected within 10 m of each other, showing similar behavior (e.g., perching on adjacent tree branches).  Map of Puerto Rico, showing distance-sampling survey points used to estimate Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon abundance in April&ndash;June, 1986&ndash;2014.  The 6-min count was intended to increase pigeon availability for detection and the chance of detecting calling pigeons visually for distance measurement to the nearest meter with rangefinders. When pigeons were heard but not seen, distances were measured to the nearest location, and the following distance categories were used: 0&ndash;15, 16&ndash;30, 31&ndash;45, 46&ndash;60, 61&ndash;90, 91&ndash;120, 121&ndash;180, 181&ndash;240, 241&ndash;340, 341&ndash;440 m. We analyzed the distance data using category midpoints ( Buckland et al. 2001 ). We did not include flying pigeons in density estimates, unless initial locations were ascertained before movement. To minimize responsive movement, we did not implement a settling period before count initiation ( Buckland et al. 2008 ). To increase pigeon availability for detection, repeated surveys were conducted from sunrise to midmorning and from midafternoon to sunset. The points were visited 1&ndash;3 times in April&ndash;June. Survey effort accounted for the number of visits per point ( Buckland et al. 2001 ).  We evaluated the fit of uniform, half-normal, and hazard-rate detection models with quantile&ndash;quantile plots and goodness-of-fit tests ( Burnham et al. 2004 ). The half-normal and hazard-rate key functions with and without series expansions were used to explore the influence of the following covariates: year (1998&ndash;2002, 2008&ndash;2011, 2014), month (April, May, June), life zone (dry, moist, wet), detection mode (heard only, heard&ndash;seen), detection time (0&ndash;3 min, 4&ndash;6 min), time of day (minutes after sunrise, minutes before sunset), disturbance level from traffic and background noise (none&ndash;low, medium&ndash;high), vertical and horizontal vegetation cover within 60 m (0&ndash;50&percnt; &lsqb;none&ndash;low&rsqb;, 51&ndash;100&percnt; &lsqb;medium&ndash;high&rsqb;), point location (on road, off road), species (Plain Pigeon, White-crowned Pigeon), observer team (8 teams), and cluster size (as defined above). We used nonparametric bootstrapping to estimate density variation, and based model selection on minimization of Akaike's Information Criterion ( Buckland et al. 2001 ).  We estimated Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon detection and density independently each year in 1986&ndash;2014. Off-road points were not surveyed in 1993&ndash;1996, 2003&ndash;2007, 2012, and 2013; and covariate information was incomplete or not collected before 1998 ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1995a ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003b ). For this reason, we used multiple-covariate distance sampling for the analysis of covariate information collected at points along roads ( k  &equals; 725&ndash;1,025) and away from roads ( k  &equals; 300&ndash;350) in 1998&ndash;2002, 2008&ndash;2011, and 2014. Points along roads can result in biased detection and density estimation ( Marques et al. 2010 ). However, on-road points had land-cover and land-use classes that were proportional to their occurrences in costal and montane landscapes ( Acevedo and Restrepo 2008 ). Distance sampling combines design-based and model-based approaches for parameter estimation ( Borchers and Burnham 2004 ,  Marques et al. 2010 ). We were particularly interested in exploring the influence of point location on pigeon detection and density estimation. We used a 2-tailed  Z- test to determine whether detection and density estimates along and away from roads differed statistically ( P  &equals; 0.05;  Buckland et al. 2001 ). For data analysis, we used R 3.2.2 ( R Development Core Team 2015 ) and DISTANCE 6.0 release 2 ( Thomas et al. 2010 ). Distance sampling results are presented as means &plusmn; bootstrap SE.  We used a Bayesian framework to estimate the unobserved parameters and unknown population states, assuming conditional independence for each time step. We first specified uniform prior distributions with wide bounds for population growth rate ( r  ~ Uniform &lsqb;0.010, 0.200&rsqb;), carrying capacity ( K  ~ Uniform &lsqb;1,000, 100,000&rsqb;), and the mean of the initial population proportion on the log scale ( P  0  ~ Uniform &lsqb;&minus;10, 0&rsqb;). For the process error and initial population proportion standard deviations, we also specified uniform priors (&sigma; process  and      ~ Uniform &lsqb;0, 10&rsqb;;  Gelman and Hill 2007 ). Model simulations provided consistent results after conducting sensitivity analysis with other plausible priors and value ranges ( Meyer and Millar 1999 ,  Millar and Meyer 2000 ).  To calculate the posterior distribution, we used MCMC methods by running program JAGS 3.4.0 ( Plummer 2003 ) within the R2JAGS package ( Su and Yajima 2015 ). We conducted 250,000 iterations and used the first 50,000 iterations as a burn-in period. We generated 3 Markov chains with different initial parameter values, and used trace plots and node summary statistics to check for MCMC algorithm convergence (e.g., Brooks-Gelman-Rubin diagnostic statistic  R̂  &equals; 1.00;  Gelman et al. 2004 ). Before summarizing the posterior, we thinned the Markov chains by 25 to obtain samples of 8,000 points. For model-based abundance predictions ( N  2025 ), we assumed uniform illegal harvest rates ( h  ~ Uniform &lsqb;0.01, 0.25&rsqb;). We defined population sustainability in terms of the probability that predicted abundance in 2025 would exceed carrying capacity, given potential illegal harvest rates in 2015&ndash;2024 (i.e. Pr&lsqb; N  2025  &gt;  K  1986&ndash;2014 &thinsp;&verbar;&thinsp; h  2015&ndash;2024 &rsqb;). Simulation results are presented as means &plusmn; MCMC SD, and medians with 2.5&percnt; and 97.5 percentiles.  The uniform key function with 2 cosine series expansions provided the best fit to the distance data (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test:  D n   &equals; 0.02,  P  &equals; 0.84; chi-square test:      &equals; 2.15,  P  &equals; 0.54; lowest value of AIC &equals; 15,655,10;  Figure 2 A,  2 B). The hazard-rate key function was favored over the half-normal key function with or without series expansions; but the uniform detection model was favored over the hazard-rate detection models with or without covariates (range of values of &Delta;AIC: 33.73&ndash;48.66). The uniform and hazard-rate detection models generated similar density estimates (range of values of  D̂ : 0.042 &plusmn; 0.016 to 0.048 &plusmn; 0.031).  ( A ) Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon detection probability and ( B ) probability density function based on grouped radial distances recorded at surveyed points in Puerto Rico in April&ndash;June, 1998&ndash;2002, 2008&ndash;2011, and 2014 ( k  &equals; 1,075&ndash;1,375;  n  &equals; 1,365 species combined).  For both pigeon species combined, average and expected cluster sizes were 1.277 &plusmn; 0.011 and 1.207 &plusmn; 0.011 individuals, respectively. Cluster detection tended to be size-biased (Pearson's correlation coefficient:  r  1,363  &equals; &minus;0.05,  P  &equals; 0.05). Encounter rate ( n / k ) was 0.612 &plusmn; 0.025, detection probability within 120 m was 0.267 &plusmn; 0.012, and effective detection radius was 62.053 &plusmn; 1.427 m. Most of the density variation was related to factors associated with encounter rate (component percentage of  D̂  variance &equals; 54.8&percnt;) and detection probability (42.7&percnt;), with cluster size being relatively unimportant (2.5&percnt;). Detection and density estimates did not differ at on-road and off-road points ( P̂ d   &equals; 0.271 &plusmn; 0.012 vs. 0.257 &plusmn; 0.015 within 120 m,  Z  &equals; 0.73,  P  &equals; 0.47; and  D̂  &equals; 0.048 &plusmn; 0.006 vs. 0.043 &plusmn; 0.005 individuals ha &minus;1 ,  Z  &equals; 0.64,  P  &equals; 0.52).  The Plain Pigeon population increased from low numbers in the 1980&ndash;1990s, reaching a maximum of 76,398 &plusmn; 23,960 individuals in 1998, and decreased to 27,713 &plusmn; 14,231 individuals in 1999 ( Figure 3 ). The Plain Pigeon population increased to 43,422 &plusmn; 13,482 individuals in 2001; decreased to 5,992 &plusmn; 2,969 individuals in 2013; and remained low, with 14,445 &plusmn; 1,388 individuals in 2014 ( Figure 3 ). The White-crowned Pigeon population also increased from low numbers in the 1980&ndash;1990s, reaching a maximum of 83,139 &plusmn; 11,039 individuals in 2008 ( Figure 4 ). The White-crowned Pigeon population decreased to 14,980 &plusmn; 1,534 individuals in 2013 and remained low, with 24,764 &plusmn; 2,380 individuals in 2014 ( Figure 4 ). Both populations recovered quickly after hurricanes in 1989 and 1998, but decreased sharply at the same time that legal hunting of columbids increased in 2008&ndash;2014 ( Figures 3  and  4 ).  Plain Pigeon distance-sampling abundance estimates (crosses, with vertical lines indicating bootstrap SE) and Bayesian state-space model abundance estimates in thousands (dashed lines indicate median and 2.5&percnt; and 97.5&percnt; percentiles) in Puerto Rico, April&ndash;June, 1986&ndash;2025.  White-crowned Pigeon distance-sampling abundance estimates (crosses, with vertical lines indicating bootstrap SE) and Bayesian state-space model abundance estimates in thousands (dashed lines indicate the median and 2.5&percnt; and 97.5&percnt; percentiles) in Puerto Rico, April&ndash;June, 1986&ndash;2025.  Realizations of Markov chains and node summary statistics showed convergence of the MCMC algorithm (Brooks-Gelman-Rubin diagnostic statistic,  R̂  &equals; 1.00&minus;1.01). For the Plain Pigeon, the intrinsic rate of population growth was 0.351 (95&percnt; credible interval &lsqb;CI&rsqb;: 0.086&ndash;0.737), population carrying capacity was 55,840 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 29,649&ndash;96,505), maximum sustainable harvest rate was 0.176 (95&percnt; CI: 0.043&minus;0.369), maximum sustainable total harvest was 4,966 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 1,027&minus;10,823), initial population size was 13,411 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 3,346&minus;93,550), equilibrium population size was 27,920 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 14,825&minus;48,253), and process error was 0.139 (95&percnt; CI: 0.056&minus;0.342;  Table 1 ). For the White-crowned Pigeon, the intrinsic rate of population growth was 0.352 (95&percnt; CI: 0.094&minus;0.699), population carrying capacity was 73,692 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 47,225&minus;98,434), maximum sustainable harvest rate was 0.176 (95&percnt; CI: 0.047&minus;0.349), maximum sustainable total harvest was 6,651individuals (95&percnt; CI: 1,537&minus;12,867), initial population size was 13,047 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 2,477&minus;92,406), equilibrium population size was 36,846 individuals (95&percnt; CI: 23,612&minus;49,217), and process error was 0.113 (95&percnt; CI: 0.057&minus;0.243;  Table 1 ).  Posterior estimates of population and harvest management parameters and abundance predictions based on distance-sampling survey data and Bayesian state-space model of Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon population dynamics in Puerto Rico, 1986&ndash;2025.  Temporal variability was higher for the Plain Pigeon than for the White-crowned Pigeon (process error coefficient of variation &equals; 0.487 and 0.382, respectively). However, both pigeon populations fluctuated widely over time, and Bayesian estimates of parameters were uncertain, as reflected by the standard deviations and credible intervals ( Table 1 ;  Figures 3  and  4 ). With illegal harvest rates between 0.01 and 0.25 in 2015&ndash;2024, predicted abundance was 20,536 individuals (8,167&minus;89,040) for the Plain Pigeon and 29,361 individuals (1,778&minus;100,937) for the White-crowned Pigeon in 2025. The probability of the Plain Pigeon population exceeding the 2.5&percnt; percentile of carrying capacity was 0.731; the probability was 0.426 for exceeding the median and 0.050 for exceeding the 97.5&percnt; percentile of carrying capacity ( Table 1  and  Figure 3 ). The probability of the White-crowned Pigeon population exceeding the 2.5&percnt; percentile of carrying capacity was 0.510; the probability was 0.306 for exceeding the median and 0.208 for exceeding the 97.5&percnt; percentile of carrying capacity ( Table 1  and  Figure 4 ). The probability of predicted abundance being below the 2.5&percnt; percentile of carrying capacity was 0.208 and 0.490 for the Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon, respectively ( Table 1 ;  Figures 3  and  4 ).  We used distance sampling to monitor annual changes in Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon abundance, and a Bayesian state-space model to estimate the posterior distributions of population and harvest management parameters and to make abundance predictions as a function of potential illegal hunting in Puerto Rico. Through annual comparisons of distance-sampling abundance estimates and model-based abundance predictions, we can inform management decisions and evaluate the results of conservation actions that aim to maintain the pigeon populations fluctuating around carrying capacity levels ( USFWS 2002 ,  2011 ). Our monitoring and modeling efforts can also lead to a better understanding of the negative impacts of illegal hunting and other factors that influence population dynamics ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1996 ,  2001 ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003a ,  2014 ).  The reliability of our monitoring data depends largely on meeting method assumptions ( Buckland et al. 2001 ,  2008 ). Teams of 2 observers did not likely miss pigeons at point centers during 6-min counts. In most instances, calling pigeons were detected visually and distances were measured with little error, as evidenced by quantile&ndash;quantile plots and goodness-of-fit tests (e.g., see  Burnham et al. 2004 : figure 11.9). We did not include moving pigeons in density estimates unless distances were measured to initial locations, before responsive movements, which tended to be away from the observers and with loud wing-flapping sounds. Cluster size tended to be small and had a negligible effect on detection and density estimation. None of the covariates examined caused extreme heterogeneity in the detection function (e.g., see  Marques et al. 2007 : figure 5.7).  Moreover, the uniform and hazard-rate detection models generated similar density estimates, which suggests that model selection was of secondary importance for abundance inferences in the survey region ( Buckland et al. 2001 ). The survey scheme was extensive and provided representative coverage of pigeon abundance in the 3 major life zones of the island ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1995a ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003b ,  2014 ). Therefore, we suggest that the assumptions of distance sampling were met, and that relatively unbiased abundance estimates were obtained for monitoring and modeling the dynamics of the Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon populations in Puerto Rico.  The model was useful for describing Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon population dynamics, estimating the posterior distributions of population and harvest management parameters, and predicting changes in abundance resulting from potential illegal hunting. The posterior estimates of population growth rate and carrying capacity seem biologically reasonable, despite high uncertainty. For example, on the basis of life-history characteristics and nest-monitoring data ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1996 ,  2001 ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003a ), and using equation 18 in  Johnson et al. (2012) , we obtained a population growth rate of 0.35, assuming that annual fecundity rate was 1.50 young breeding pair &minus;1 , and that annual survival rate was 0.50 for juveniles and 0.60 for adults. Fecundity rates can be higher as a result of extended nesting (&ge;6 mo), multiple brooding (&ge;3 clutches), first-year reproduction, and diverse frugivorous diets. Ideally, we would like to develop more detailed models associated with hypotheses about how population growth rate and carrying capacity change in relation to foraging and nesting resources, but demographic and habitat data are lacking to represent this additional complexity.  We made a series of simplifying assumptions to model the dynamics of the pigeon populations (e.g., linear density dependence, negligible immigration and emigration, and additive hunting mortality). However, restricting the model to essential parameters was pragmatic and sufficed for description, estimation, and prediction, while explicitly accounting for variation associated with process and observation errors ( Meyer and Millar 1999 ,  Millar and Meyer 2000 ,  K&eacute;ry and Schaub 2012 ). Posterior distributions and abundance predictions were imprecise because variation from process and observation errors were included in the model. Pigeons can offset low survival rates through high fecundity rates ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1995b ,  1996 ,  2001 ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003a ), and this, in turn, can cause wide population fluctuations and high variation from process error (e.g., see  K&eacute;ry and Schaub 2012 : figure 5.7).  We monitored the pigeon populations during a period of natural reforestation in abandoned agricultural areas in the 1980s&ndash;1990s ( Brandeis et al. 2007 ). This period also included 2 major hurricanes in 1989 and 1998 ( Boose et al. 2004 ) and an increase in legal hunting of columbids in 2008&ndash;2014 ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2014 ). The Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon populations increased from low numbers and surpassed carrying capacity in 1995&ndash;2008, probably as a result of an increase in foraging and nesting resources in second-growth forests ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n 1996 ,  2001 ,  Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2003a ). Population recovery was quick after hurricanes, but abundance decreased sharply at the same time that legal hunting activity increased on the island. Although habitat loss due to urban development and other conservation threats cannot be ruled out, our monitoring and modeling results suggest that an increase in illegal hunting might be responsible for some of the abundance decline in 2008&minus;2014, and that population sustainability might be affected by illegal hunting in 2015&minus;2025. Therefore, data collection and the control of illegal hunting should be considered management priorities. Illegal hunting data can be collected through randomized mail questionnaires and more intensive telephone and personal interviews with hunters and the general public living near hunting areas (e.g., see  Levy and Lemeshow 1999 ). Illegal hunting activity can be partially controlled through hunter education efforts and by increasing surveillance activity and the number of areas closed to hunting on the island ( USFWS 1982 ,  USDOI 2015 ).  Because model-based abundance predictions are updated with monitoring data annually, we can continue learning from the comparison of estimated and predicted abundances, despite partial control of illegal hunting, imperfect observation of population state, incomplete understanding of population dynamics, and environmental variability due to weather conditions ( Williams et al. 2002 ). Finally, although we have focused here on the sustainability of Plain Pigeon and White-crowned Pigeon populations given potential illegal hunting in Puerto Rico, our monitoring and modeling scheme is applicable to population assessments of other resident and migratory birds in the Caribbean ( Rivera-Mil&aacute;n et al. 2005 ,  2015 ,  Watts et al. 2015 ).  Assistance with fieldwork was provided by wildlife biologists from projects W-11, W-16, and W-21, including D. Col&oacute;n, M. Delgado, D. Guzm&aacute;n, H. L&oacute;pez, A. Matos, and R. Ramos. Thanks to J. E. Haakonsson, P. Padding, K. Richkus, and two anonymous reviewers for comments and suggestions to improve the manuscript.   Funding statement:  We received support from the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Division of Migratory Bird Management, and the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources, Division of Terrestrial Resources, through Commonwealth and Federal Aid funds (USFWS, Region 4).   Ethics statement:  The findings and conclusions in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views, determinations, or policies of the USFWS and PRDNER. The use of trade, firm, or product names does not imply endorsement by these agencies.   Authors' contributions:  F.F.R.-M. conceived the idea, designed the study, collected data, conducted data analysis, and wrote the paper. S.B. conceived the idea, conducted data analysis, and wrote the paper. A.M. collected data and assisted with data analysis and writing the paper. 