 Drought-caused delay in nesting of Sonoran Desert birds and its facilitation of parasite- and predator-mediated variation in reproductive success  Dependence of desert rodents on winter annuals and precipitation  Factors affecting nesting success in riparian bird communities  Intense natural selection in a population of Darwin's finches (Geospizinae) in the Gal&aacute;pagos  Avian reproductive failure in response to an extreme climatic event  Adjustment to climate change is constrained by arrival date in a long-distance migrant bird  Delayed effect of monsoon rains influences laying date of a passerine bird living in an arid environment  Long-term trend toward earlier breeding in an American bird: A response to global warming?  Nest site selection and nest success in a Song Sparrow population: The significance of spatial variation  Effects of weather and population density on reproductive success and population dynamics in a Song Sparrow (  Melospiza melodia  ) population: A long-term study  The impact of climate change on birds  Climate change related to egg-laying trends  Climate change has affected the breeding date of Tree Swallows throughout North America  Spatial and temporal variation in climate change: A bird's eye view  The extraordinary El Ni&ntilde;o event of 1982&ndash;83: Effects on Darwin's finches on Isla Genovesa, Gal&aacute;pagos  Time-specific variation in passerine nest survival: New insights into old questions  A long-term study of vertebrate predator responses to an El Ni&ntilde;o (ENSO) disturbance in western South America  Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism of the Black-throated Sparrow in central Arizona  Brown-headed Cowbirds in California: Historical perspectives and management opportunities in riparian habitats  Curve-billed Thrasher reproductive success after a wet winter in the Sonoran Desert of Arizona  Nest monitoring plots: Methods for locating nests and monitoring success  The influence of drought and fires on Sonoran Desert birds  Variation in a sparrow's reproductive success with rainfall: Food and predator-mediated processes  The role of food, nest predation, and climate in timing of Wrentit reproductive activities  Field methods for monitoring landbirds  Model projections of an imminent transition to a more arid climate in southwestern North America  A unified approach to analyzing nest success  Making meaningful estimates of nest survival with model-based methods  Phoenix Metropolitan Area Weather Review 2009  eBird: A citizen-based bird observation network in the biological sciences  An international standard for a mapping method in bird census work recommended by the International Bird Census Committee  Projecting climate impacts on birds and reptiles of the southwestern United States  Seasonal and yearly fluctuations in Chihuahuan Desert lizard communities  As our understanding of climate change has increased, so has our awareness of the impacts of these changes on biotic systems. Climate models are nearly unanimous in their predictions for increased drought frequency in southwestern North America, and delays in nest initiation due to drought may influence nesting success and productivity for many Sonoran Desert bird species. In southeastern California and western Arizona in 2004&ndash;2009, we found negative correlations for 13 of 13 species between nest initiation date and rainfall accumulation during the preceding 4-month winter rainy season. Nesting was delayed more than 3 weeks for some species during extreme droughts in 2006 and 2007. During 2004&ndash;2009, we found a significant negative effect of nest initiation date on nest survival probability (&beta;̂ &equals; &minus;0.031 &plusmn; 0.005 SE,  P  &lt; 0.001) for the four species of greatest sample size. To investigate the role of nesting delay in nesting success and productivity, in 2010 we conducted a manipulative experiment with Black-tailed Gnatcatchers ( Polioptila melanura ; BTGN) and Verdins ( Auriparus flaviceps ; VERD). Following a wet winter, we delayed clutch initiation dates for treatment pairs to match first-egg dates that we observed during droughts in 2006 and 2007. Nest initiation date had a significant negative effect on nest survival of both species (BTGN: &beta;̂ &equals; &minus;1.18 &plusmn; 0.27 SE,  P  &lt; 0.001; VERD: &beta;̂ &equals; &minus;2.33 &plusmn; 0.51 SE,  P  &equals; 0.003). Treatment pairs were unable to overcome the lost period of high productivity in March and early April, and had lower productivity than control pairs over the entire breeding season. As nest predation and Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ) parasitism were the most common causes of nest failure, we conclude that the impacts of climate change&ndash;caused drought on annual reproductive output in the Sonoran Desert will be further compounded by parasitism and predation for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and by predation for Verdins.  A medida que aumenta nuestro entendimiento del cambio clim&aacute;tico, tambi&eacute;n lo hace nuestra conciencia de los impactos de estos cambios en los sistemas bi&oacute;ticos. Los modelos clim&aacute;ticos son casi un&aacute;nimes en sus predicciones sobre el aumento de la frecuencia de sequ&iacute;as en el sudoeste de Am&eacute;rica del Norte, y las demoras en la iniciaci&oacute;n del nido debido a la sequ&iacute;a pueden influenciar el &eacute;xito de nidificaci&oacute;n y la productividad de muchas especies de aves del Desierto de Sonora. En el sudeste de California, de 2004 a 2009 encontramos correlaciones negativas para las 13 especies estudiadas entre la fecha de inicio del nido y la acumulaci&oacute;n de las precipitaciones de los cuatro meses precedentes a la estaci&oacute;n de lluvias de invierno. La nidificaci&oacute;n se retras&oacute; por tres semanas para algunas especies durante las sequ&iacute;as extremas de 2006 y 2007. Durante el per&iacute;odo de 2004&ndash;2009, encontramos un efecto negativo significativo de la fecha de inicio del nido en la probabilidad de supervivencia del nido (&beta;̂ &equals; &minus;0.031 &plusmn; 0.005 EE,  P  &lt; 0.001) para las cuatro especies de mayor tama&ntilde;o de muestreo. Para investigar el rol de la demora de la nidificaci&oacute;n en el &eacute;xito de nidificaci&oacute;n y la productividad, en 2010 realizamos un experimento manipulativo con  Polioptila melanura  y  Auriparus flaviceps . Luego de un invierno h&uacute;medo, demoramos las fechas de inicio de la nidada para las parejas experimentales para que coincidan con las fechas del primer huevo que hab&iacute;amos observado durante las sequ&iacute;as previas en 2006 y 2007. La fecha de inicio del nido tuvo un efecto negativo significativo en la supervivencia del nido en ambas especies ( P. melanura : &beta;̂ &equals; &minus;1.18 &plusmn; 0.27 EE,  P  &lt; 0.001;  A. flaviceps : &beta;̂ &equals; &minus;2.33 &plusmn; 0.51 EE,  P  &equals; 0.003). Las parejas experimentales no pudieron superar la p&eacute;rdida del per&iacute;odo de alta productividad de marzo y principios de abril, y presentaron menor productividad a lo largo de toda la estaci&oacute;n reproductiva que las parejas control. La depredaci&oacute;n del nido y el parasitismo de   Molothrus ater   fueron las causas m&aacute;s comunes de fracaso del nido, por lo que concluimos que los impactos de la sequ&iacute;a causada por el cambio clim&aacute;tico en el resultado reproductivo anual en el Desierto de Sonora se ver&aacute;n aumentados a&uacute;n m&aacute;s por el parasitismo y la depredaci&oacute;n para  P. melanura  y por la depredaci&oacute;n para  A. flaviceps .   Palabras clave: Auriparus flaviceps , cambio clim&aacute;tico, demora de la nidificaci&oacute;n, fecha de puesta,   Molothrus ater  ,  Polioptila melanura , reproducci&oacute;n tard&iacute;a, supervivencia del nido de un ave paserina  In arid and semiarid environments, variation in precipitation creates dramatic, short-term responses in plant and animal production. These responses are easily visible and well documented ( Beatley 1969 ,  Boag and Grant 1981 ,  Grant and Grant 1987 ,  Bolger et al. 2005 ). As our knowledge of the connection between variation in extrinsic factors such as rainfall and changes in bird populations has increased, investigators have sought to identify the ecological processes that mediate population fluctuations. In some groups of animals, increases in primary production following above-average rainfall are correlated with increases in secondary and tertiary production due to rapid increases in food resources (birds:  Grant and Grant &lsqb;1987&rsqb; , mammals:  Beatley &lsqb;1969&rsqb; , birds and mammals:  Jaksic et al. &lsqb;1997&rsqb; ).  Jaksic et al. (1997)  found that increases in mammal numbers following heavy rains were followed by increases in numbers of their avian and mammalian predators, moving up through trophic levels in a &ldquo;bottom-up&rdquo; scenario.  Working on small North American passerines,  Morrison and Bolger (2002)  and  Chase et al. (2005)  found the effects of precipitation on reproductive output to be more complex. In these systems, nest predation rates were found to be lower in wet seasons, while breeding seasons were observed to be shorter or nonexistent in dry seasons. This convergence of possible influences led the authors to conclude that both food limitation and predation could mediate reproductive output in response to changes in precipitation.  Individual Sonoran Desert passerines can exhibit wide variation in the onset of their nesting seasons, with first-clutch initiation dates spanning differences of several weeks among years ( Anderson and Anderson 1973 ,  Johnson et al. 2002 ). Several studies suggest that delays in nest initiation follow periods of low rainfall, and that this variation in breeding initiation is related to precipitation levels ( Anderson and Anderson 1973 ,  Brown and Li 1996 ,  Johnson et al. 2002 ,  Morrison and Bolger 2002 ,  Chase et al. 2005 ,  Preston and Rotenberry 2006 ).  Prior to a manipulative experiment conducted in 2010, we observed delayed nesting by all of our Sonoran Desert study species in the midst of severe droughts in 2006 and 2007. Although delays reached several weeks for some species, all species but one attempted to nest during severe drought conditions. Given that nests may have lower survival rates later in the breeding season ( Best and Stauffer 1980 ,  Grant et al. 2005 ), we hypothesized that droughts might decrease reproductive output by exposing nesting individuals to higher rates of predation and Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ) parasitism which occur later in the season.  We tested this hypothesis with a nesting-delay experiment following the wet winter of 2010. Assuming that our study species would not be limited by food resources in the breeding season of this wet year, we predicted that we could produce declines in nesting success and reproductive output by delaying the nest initiation dates of randomly selected treatment pairs to match late nest initiation dates that we had recorded during prior drought seasons. We postulated that due to predation and Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism, the first nesting attempts of control (undelayed nesting) pairs would have significantly higher odds of success than would the first nesting attempts of treatment (delayed nesting) pairs, and that over the course of the entire breeding season, treatment pairs would be unable recover these early reproductive losses.  Our study sites were in two Sonoran Desert wash systems: Chemehuevi Wash and Alamo Wash, in California and Arizona, USA, respectively. Sonoran Desert wash systems are similar to riparian systems, but surface water is present only during the heaviest rains. These &ldquo;xeric riparian&rdquo; corridors of the region hold significantly greater woody plant diversity than the surrounding uplands, and they consequently support much higher avian abundance and diversity ( Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum 1999 ).  Chemehuevi Wash (34.45&deg;N, 114.32&deg;W) is located near the northern edge of the Sonoran Desert, in eastern San Bernardino County, California ( Figure 1 ). Alamo Wash (33.51&deg;N, 113.82&deg;W) lies 75 miles to the southeast, in southeastern La Paz County, Arizona. Our two Chemehuevi Wash study plots were located at 200 m and 320 m above sea level, and our 27 Alamo Wash study plots ranged from 400 m to 550 m above sea level.  Study sites in ( A ) southeastern California (Chemehuevi Wash, San Bernardino County, 2004&ndash;2008) and ( B ) western Arizona (Alamo Wash, La Paz County, 2009&ndash;2010). Chemehuevi plots numbered; plot 2 was broken into two subplots due to a small nonvegetated area between the two polygons. Alamo Basin plots on the primary wash labeled with ( L ); side wash plots labeled with ( s ).  Both the Chemehuevi and Alamo wash systems are similar, being dominated by leguminous phreatophytes of the blue palo verde&ndash;ironwood (  Parkinsonia florida  &ndash;  Olneya tesota  ) woodland alliance ( Sawyer and Keeler-Wolf 2009 ). Dominant trees include blue palo verde, ironwood, catclaw acacia (  Acacia greggii  ), yellow palo verde (  Parkinsonia microphylla  ), and honey and velvet mesquite (  Prosopis glandulosa   and   P. velutina  ).  Black-tailed Gnatcatchers ( Polioptila melanura ) and Verdins ( Auriparus flaviceps ) are small, resident passerines whose geographic ranges are largely contained by the Mojave, Sonoran, and Chihuahuan deserts ( Webster 1999 ,  Farquhar and Ritchie 2002 ). They are among the most common breeding species found at our study sites ( Sullivan et al. 2009 ). The two species can be found foraging together in mixed flocks; they appear to share overlapping diets of small insects and spiders, and their young are provisioned primarily with small caterpillars and spiders. Both species may occasionally consume fruits and seeds, although this is likely more common in Verdins, particularly in the nonbreeding season ( Webster 1999 ,  Farquhar and Ritchie 2002 ).  Both species share long breeding seasons, with nest-building commencing as early as mid-February in favorable conditions, and nestlings present well into August depending on the occurrence and severity of summer monsoonal rains ( Webster 1999 ,  Farquhar and Ritchie 2002 ). Verdins build a complex, spherical dome nest with a small entrance ( Webster 1999 ), while Black-tailed Gnatcatchers construct open-cup nests. Consequently, Black-tailed Gnatcatchers are more susceptible to Brown-headed Cowbird brood parasitism than are Verdins ( Farquhar and Ritchie 2002 ). Each species typically lays 3&ndash;5 eggs in a clutch (usually 4). Black-tailed Gnatcatchers incubate for 14&ndash;15 days, and nestlings generally fledge at 15 days old, but may fledge as early as 9 days old ( Farquhar and Ritchie 2002 ). Verdins incubate for 14&ndash;18 days, and nestlings often fledge by day 18 ( Webster 1999 ). In the Sonoran Desert these two bird species are highly dependent upon desert wash systems for foraging and particularly for nesting substrates.  The Sonoran Desert has two distinct precipitation periods: (1) winter rains (November through April) that are the result of cyclonic frontal systems following storm tracks from the Pacific Ocean, and (2) summer rains (July through September) that fall from convective thunderstorms. Winter rainfall may be heavy, but winter storms are generally characterized by relatively prolonged, gentle rains, with broad geographic patterns of accumulation. In contrast, summer &lsquo;monsoonal' rains are generally much more localized and severe than winter rains ( Western Regional Climate Center 2014 ). The two rainy seasons are separated by relatively dry periods in the spring (May&ndash;June) and autumn (October).  We summarized daily rainfall values for the Chemehuevi Wash in 2003&ndash;2008 and the Alamo Wash in 2008&ndash;2010 from archived weather station data (National Climatic Data Center,  http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/cdo-web/ ), utilizing mean accumulations recorded at the three most proximate weather stations to each study site. For the Chemehuevi Wash, these included the Lake Havasu City, Parker Reservoir, and Parker weather stations, and for the Alamo Wash included the Kofa Mine, Dateland Ranch, and Quartzsite stations. In the event of a missing value, we substituted that day's precipitation from the fourth-closest site (Needles for Chemehuevi and Bouse for Alamo). Winter season rainfall was defined as the 4-mo (prebreeding season) period from November 1 of the previous calendar year through March 1 of the breeding season year. This period captured the breeding season's preceding winter storm cycles and ended near the onset of nesting.  In order to provide background nesting information for our nesting delay experiment, we established two 40-ha nest monitoring plots on the Chemehuevi Wash in February 2004 ( Figure 1 ). From February through May each season (2004&ndash;2008), we used standardized spot-mapping protocols following guidelines suggested by the International Bird Census Committee ( Svensson et al. 1970 ) and  Ralph et al. (1993) . UTM-gridded maps ( ESRI 2011 ) with GPS receivers (Garmin, Olathe, Kansas, USA) were used to enhance mapping precision.  All nests that we found were monitored following protocols described in  Martin and Geupel (1993)  and  Martin et al. (1997) , with nest-check intervals generally being 4 days. We recorded nest contents, nestling age, and Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism on each visit. We determined outcomes for all nests, and only used nests with known fates in analyses. Nests were considered to have fledged young if we saw or heard fledglings at the nest site, observed repeated visits to fixed locations by adults carrying food, or observed whitewash on twigs around the nest combined with parent scolding. We typically spent up to 45 min ascertaining success or failure at each nest that was found to be empty. A nest was not considered to have failed unless we observed the parents without fledglings for over an hour.  In January 2009 we established four 3-km-long plots on Alamo Wash and 23 1-km-lengthwise plots on secondary tributaries throughout the Alamo Basin ( Figure 1 ). Plots were randomly ordered, with the objective of monitoring the nesting success and reproductive output of 30 Black-tailed Gnatcatcher pairs on the primary wash and 30 pairs on secondary washes. We spot-mapped territories and monitored nests from February 1 through May 31.  To investigate the relationship between drought conditions in 2006 and 2007 and late nesting dates, we delayed clutch initiation dates for Verdins and Black-tailed Gnatcatchers at the Alamo Wash during a wet year in 2010. We needed to delay the laying of treatment pairs for more than two weeks beyond the mean first-egg date of control pairs for the Black-tailed Gnatcatcher, and for more than three weeks beyond the mean first-egg date of control pairs for the Verdin, so that first-egg dates for treatment pairs mirrored first-egg dates observed during drought years. Once our plot order was established, we generated a random number table assigning control and treatment status for territory numbers for each species. We then assigned territory numbers (and hence randomized control and treatment status) in the chronological order in which we located nests. We followed the spot-mapping and nest-monitoring protocols described above, and began delaying Verdin nesting on March 6 and Black-tailed Gnatcatcher nesting on March 21. Control pairs were left to continue nesting without delay.  We delayed the nesting of treatment pairs during nest construction by opening a hole in the nest wall as building approached completion. We waited for pairs to leave the nest area so that we would not be seen, and each nest manipulation generally required &lt;5 s to perform. The nest wall was opened as minimally as possible, to (1) ensure that pairs could recycle all materials for their subsequent renesting attempt, and (2) ensure that material did not fall to the ground, potentially attracting predators.  Each treatment pair's subsequent and repeated renesting attempts were disturbed until 5&ndash;7 days prior to our target mean first-egg dates (April 9 for Verdins and April 15 for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers). We did not wish to cause failure of any established clutches; thus, we needed to find renesting attempts quickly, before egg-laying commenced. We achieved this by focusing nest searching efforts on the second or third day after delay, when treatment pairs were most likely to be found recycling material from their previous nest. This scheduling also helped to further confirm pairs' identities from previous nesting attempts, as we assumed that the same breeding birds retained their territories throughout the breeding season. We then monitored the success of treatment and control nests through the completion of the last active nest of the season (through the last week of July).  We used nest-check observations and backdating to calculate annual mean first-egg dates (i.e. the first egg of the first clutch of the season) for all species at the Chemehuevi Wash in 2004&ndash;2008, for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers at the Alamo Wash in 2009, and for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and Verdins at the Alamo Wash in 2010. Simple linear regressions were used to test quadratic and linear relationships between log-transformed winter season rainfall and first-egg dates ( Bolger et al. 2005 ). We then examined summed winter &plus; autumn rainfall and winter &plus; autumn &plus; summer rainfall to see whether greater time lags improved correlations.  Using the logistic-exposure method ( Shaffer 2004 ), we fit nine candidate models of nest survival as a function of species, winter precipitation, and Julian date of first egg for the four most common species (Loggerhead Shrike &lsqb;  Lanius ludovicianus  ; exposure period &equals; 37 days&rsqb;, Verdin &lsqb;38 days&rsqb;, Black-tailed Gnatcatcher &lsqb;31 days&rsqb;, and Phainopepla &lsqb; Phainopepla nitens ; 33 days&rsqb;) at Chemehuevi Wash from 2004 to 2008 and for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers at Alamo Wash in 2009. Our mixed-effects models were fit with year and plot as random effects, using package lme4 in program R version 2.15.1 ( R Development Core Team 2014 ), and models were ranked using Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size (AIC c ;  Burnham and Anderson 2002 ) using R package AICcmodavg version 1.35 ( Mazerolle 2013 ).  We investigated annual reproductive output by comparing eggs lost (per pair) to predation and/or parasitism for treatment vs. control pairs throughout the 2010 breeding season. The logistic-exposure method ( Shaffer 2004 ,  Shaffer and Thompson 2007 ) was used to model the effects of nest age (including quadratic and cubic age terms;  Grant et al. 2005 ) and nest initiation date on period survival. We also included a treatment and a treatment&ast;initiation date interaction effect to determine whether nest treatment had an effect on survival beyond that produced by the delay in nest initiation. Models were tested using all possible combinations of variables, including a constant survival model for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and Verdins separately. Models were ranked using AIC c  ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ), and coefficient estimates were averaged across models using R package MuMIn version 1.9.13 ( Barton 2013 ).  After we selected the models for Verdins and Black-tailed Gnatcatchers that best explained our data, we calculated model-averaged daily survival rates and their lower and upper 95&percnt; confidence interval bounds for each nest age to generate period survival estimates (Verdin period &equals; 38 days and Black-tailed Gnatcatcher period &equals; 31 days). We then plotted survival by nest initiation date ( Grant et al. 2005 ).  Historical mean winter season rainfall for the 3 weather stations nearest Chemehuevi Wash (1893 to 2010) and the 3 stations nearest Alamo Wash (1952 to 2010) was nearly identical ( x̄  CHEM  &equals; 54.78 mm,  x̄  ALAMO  &equals; 58.76 mm; Western Regional Climate Center,  http://www.wrcc.dri.edu/climate-summaries/ ). Annual winter season rainfall during our study in 2003&ndash;2010 varied dramatically ( Figure 2 ). The 2005 winter rainy season was one of the region's wettest on record, with accumulated rainfall nearly 500&percnt; of the historical mean. The 2006 and 2007 winters were 2 of the driest on record, each having only &sim;10&percnt; of the historical mean rainfall ( Figure 2 ).  Winter season precipitation (November 1 of previous autumn to March 1 of current breeding season) at the Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA, 2003&ndash;2008 (black bars) and the Alamo Basin, Arizona, USA, 2009&ndash;2010 (white bars). Historical mean winter season rainfall was 55 mm at the Chemehuevi Wash and 59 mm at the Alamo Basin, approximated for reference with the horizontal line.  The summer 2009 to winter 2010 period leading up to our 2010 nesting delay experiment was notable in its extremes. The 2009 summer monsoon season and autumn were abnormally dry, and 2009 was the seventh-driest year in recorded history for Phoenix, Arizona ( South West Weather 2009 ). This drought was interrupted by a rapid series of violent, wet, late-January storms that the National Weather Service gauged to be a 1 in 25-year event ( National Weather Service 2010 ).  Male Brown-headed Cowbirds arrived at our study sites within a 9-day window each year, from March 26 to April 1 ( Table 1 ). Cowbirds overwinter in the region, typically in agricultural areas and feedlots ( Corman and Wise-Gervais 2005 ). However, they were absent from our study plots during the winter and their arrival was conspicuous. Males arrived first, followed by females &sim;2&ndash;3 weeks later. We found no evidence that winter season rainfall influenced cowbird arrival date ( y  &equals; 87.63 &plus; 0.01 x ,  P  &equals; 0.36,  R  2  &equals; 0.21,  n  &equals; 6 years, simple linear regression), although the 2 years of earliest cowbird arrival were in the droughts of 2006 and 2007.  Male Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ) arrival dates at the Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA (2004&ndash;2008), and the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA (2009&ndash;2010).  We identified a negative correlation between winter season rainfall and first-egg date for 13 species for which we found &ge;4 nests ( Table 2 ). Addition of the preceding autumn and summer monsoon season precipitation to the rainfall dataset did not improve the predictability of this relationship. Black-tailed Gnatcatchers were the only species for which the addition of a quadratic term markedly improved model fit ( Figure 3 ).  Negative relationship between first-egg date and log (winter season rainfall) for 13 species nesting at Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA, 2004&ndash;2008, and Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, 2009. Species are ordered by increasing  P -values (simple linear regression).  Linear (dashed line) and quadratic (solid line) fit of negative relationship between Black-tailed Gnatcatcher first-egg date (circles) and winter season rainfall at the Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA, and the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, in 2004&ndash;2009. The linear model is  y  &equals; 131.9 &minus; 26.7 x ,  P  &equals; 0.002,  R  2  &equals; 0.93, and the polynomial model is  y  &equals; 159.2 &minus; 68.8 x  &plus; 13.8 x  2  , P  &equals; 0.001,  R  2  &equals; 0.99.  For seasons preceding our 2010 nest-delay experiment, the top-ranked models included a significant negative effect of nest initiation date on nest survival probability (&beta;̂ &equals; &minus;0.031 &plusmn; 0.005 SE,  P  &lt; 0.001;  Table 3 ,  Figure 4 ). The top model also included an interaction of species and nest initiation date, with the Loggerhead Shrike, Black-tailed Gnatcatcher, and Phainopepla showing a stronger decline in nest survival with later nesting date than the Verdin ( Figure 4 ). Winter precipitation had a significant positive effect on nest survival (&beta;̂ &equals; 0.412 &plusmn; 0.150 SE,  P  &equals; 0.005), although it was not included in the top-ranked models, indicating that nest initiation date explained a greater proportion of variation in nest survival.  Model selection results for nest survival probability as a function of species, nest initiation date, and winter season rainfall, ranked using Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC c ), for four species (Black-tailed Gnatcatcher, Phainopepla, Verdin, and Loggerhead Shrike) at Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA, 2004&ndash;2008, and for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers at Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, 2009. JFIRST &equals; Julian date of first egg, SPP &equals; species, PRECIP &equals; log(winter precipitation). Log-lik is the maximized log-likehihood,  K  is the number of model parameters, &Delta;AIC c  is the difference in AIC c  value from the top model,  w i   is the Akaike model weight, and ModLik is the likelihood of the model being the &ldquo;true&rdquo; model.  Nest survival probability (mean &lsqb;solid line&rsqb; and 95&percnt; confidence interval &lsqb;gray shading&rsqb;) as a function of nest initiation date (Julian date of first egg) for (A) Loggerhead Shrike, (B) Verdin, (C) Black-tailed Gnatcatcher, and (D) Phainopepla at Chemehuevi Wash, California, USA (2004&ndash;2008), and the Alamo Basin, Arizona, USA (2009). Julian date numbering commences on January 1 (&equals; JD 1), thus JD 60 &equals; March 1, JD 80 &equals; March 21, JD 100 &equals; April 10, JD 120 &equals; April 30, and JD 140 &equals; May 20.  Logistics limited us to a slightly smaller sample size than our target of 60 nests for each treatment. We monitored 60 control pairs of the Verdin but were able to delay the nesting of only 51 pairs. For the Black-tailed Gnatcatcher, we delayed the nesting of 39 pairs and had 36 control pairs. Mean 2010 first-egg dates for control pairs were later than expected for each species, given the above-average winter rainfall totals. Verdins began nest-building on February 14, and Black-tailed Gnatcatchers on March 14. Our mean delay period was 17 days for Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and 25 days for Verdins ( Table 4 ).  Black-tailed Gnatcatcher and Verdin first-clutch initiation dates with confidence intervals. Chemehuevi Wash (San Bernardino County, California, USA) dates are summarized for each species during years following average to above-average winter rainfall seasons (2004, 2005, and 2008) and during years following below-average winter rainfall seasons (2006 and 2007). Control and treatment dates refer to our 2010 nesting-delay experiment in which we delayed nest initiation by interrupting nest construction on the Alamo Wash (La Paz County, Arizona, USA). Sample units (pairs) are in parentheses.  Over the course of the entire breeding season, the delayed-nesting treatment pairs for both species were more likely to lose eggs to predation and/or Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism than control pairs ( Figure 5 ). The percentage of Black-tailed Gnatcatcher eggs lost (per pair) over the course of the season to predation and/or Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism was significantly different when comparing control and treatment pairs (mean difference &equals; 26&percnt;, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 12&percnt;&ndash;39&percnt;, one-sided  P  &lt; 0.001, df &equals; 74). This difference was less pronounced between Verdin control and treatment pairs (mean difference &equals; 15&percnt;, 95&percnt; CI &equals; 0&percnt;&ndash;30&percnt;, one-sided  P  &equals; 0.02, df &equals; 109). For both species, a delay in nesting resulted in lower productivity over the course of the entire breeding season.  Across-season mean percentage of eggs lost to predation or parasitism per pair (with 95&percnt; confidence intervals) for Black-tailed Gnatcatcher and Verdin control vs. treatment pairs at the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, in 2010. Control and treatment refer to our 2010 nesting-delay experiment in which we delayed nest initiation by interrupting nest construction on the Alamo Wash (La Paz County, Arizona, USA).  There were two competitive models (&Delta;AIC c  &lt; 2) for Black-tailed Gnatcatcher nest daily survival rate; both included cubic nest age, nest initiation date, and treatment, and one model also included a treatment&ast;nest initiation interaction ( Table 5 ,  Figure 6 ). The two best models for Verdin nest daily survival rate both included cubic nest age and nest initiation date, with one model also including treatment ( Table 5 ). Nest initiation date had a significant negative effect on nest survival for both species, while treatment and the treatment&ast;initiation date interaction had nonsignificant effects on the nest survival of both species ( Table 6 ).  Top 10 models for daily nest survival rate of Verdins and Black-tailed Gnatcatchers at the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, in 2010, ranked by Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC c ). AGE &equals; nest age, JFIRST &equals; nest initiation date, TREAT &equals; treatment (control or experimental delay, in which we delayed nest initiation by interrupting nest construction).  K  is the number of model parameters, Log-lik is the maximized log-likehihood, &Delta;AIC c  is the difference in AIC c  value from the top model,  w i   is the Akaike model weight, and ModLik is the likelihood of the model being the &ldquo;true&rdquo; model.  Nest period survival estimates (with 95&percnt; confidence intervals) in relation to nest initiation date (Julian date of first egg) for ( A ) Verdin pairs and ( B ) Black-tailed Gnatcatcher pairs for the 2010 breeding season at the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, 2010. Julian date numbering commences on January 1 (&equals; JD 1), thus JD 80 &equals; March 20, JD 100 &equals; April 10, JD 120 &equals; April 30, JD 140 &equals; May 20, JD 160 &equals; June 9, and JD 180 &equals; June 29.  Model-averaged standardized coefficient estimates for variables hypothesized to influence nest survival probability of Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and Verdins at the Alamo Wash, Arizona, USA, in 2010. AGE &equals; nest age, JFIRST &equals; nest initiation date, and TREAT &equals; treatment (control or experimental delay, in which we delayed nest initiation by interrupting nest construction). &ast; denotes significance at &alpha; &equals; 0.05.  Eighteen models used in the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change predicted drier conditions in southwestern North America with increased frequency of severe droughts ( Seager et al. 2007 ). An analysis of climate effects on seven southwestern bird species also predicted drier conditions for the region ( van Riper et al. 2014 ). These models predicted that higher aridity would result from decreased winter season precipitation. At Chemehuevi Wash, we found dramatic delays in nest initiation following dry winters in 2006 and 2007. Greater frequency of drought conditions in the future suggests that nest initiation dates will occur later into the nesting season with greater regularity.  We found that all 13 Sonoran Desert bird species for which we found &ge;4 nests experienced delayed nesting following winters of low rainfall. Delays extended more than 3 weeks for some species during the droughts of 2006 and 2007. The negative relationships between winter season precipitation and Julian first-egg date achieved  P -values of &le; 0.07 and explained over 70&percnt; of the variation in first-egg date for 11 of the 13 species. Of the 2 species with the weakest relationship, the Phainopepla failed to nest during the dry year of 2006. Had this species initiated nesting, the expected clutch date given the low winter season rainfall of 2006 would have strengthened this relationship ( R  2  &equals; 0.81,  P  &equals; 0.04,  n  &equals; 5 years). Lucy's Warblers ( Oreothlypis luciae ), which expressed the weakest relationship between winter rainfall and nest timing, are short-distance migrants and among the last of the breeding species to arrive at our study sites in the spring. Lucy's Warbler was the sole species that  van Riper et al. (2014)  predicted would increase in number during future climate change events.  The delay in nest initiation dates that we observed is contrary to multiple examples from higher latitudes in North America and Europe, where scientists have found long-term trends of earlier nest timing in response to changing climate ( Brown et al. 1999 ,  Crick and Sparks 1999 ,  Dunn and Winkler 1999 ,  Both and Visser 2001 ,  Crick 2004 ); however, nesting delay supports the findings of  Fontaine et al. (2009)  for migratory passerine birds in southwestern North America. In the higher-latitude examples, earlier nest initiation dates were tied to increasing temperatures. Increasing temperatures also may have some effect on nest initiation in the Sonoran Desert, but the effects of temperature differences seem to be obscured by the stronger reverse effect of low rainfall. Investigators have found drought-related delay of nest initiation dates in other arid and semiarid habitats of North America ( Anderson and Anderson 1973 ,  Brown and Li 1996 ,  Johnson et al. 2002 ,  Morrison and Bolger 2002 ,  Chase et al. 2005 ,  Preston and Rotenberry 2006 ), perhaps representing a widespread and consistent response of birds nesting in ecosystems with low and infrequent precipitation.  In 2010, we found that experimentally delaying nest initiation, designed to match nest initiation dates observed during drought years, had negative consequences for the nesting success and productivity of our study species. Nest survival was highest early in the breeding season, a period during which treatment pairs were excluded from nesting. Treatment pairs were unable to compensate for these missed nesting opportunities due to low nest survival rates over the remainder of the nesting season.  The low nest success of our treatment nests mirrored the low nest success and productivity that we observed on the Chemehuevi Wash following dry winters. Late-nesting treatment pairs were exposed to higher rates of predation and nest parasitism than were the early-nesting control pairs. Delayed-nesting treatment pairs missed optimal March conditions for high nesting success, and were unable to overcome lost productivity due to continued low nest survival rates during the remainder of the nesting season.  Although we were unable to measure arthropod density, we performed our experiment following a wet winter season. Researchers have previously found arthropod density to track rainfall and thus primary production in the Chihuahuan Desert ( Whitford and Creusere 1977 ) and in southwestern California ( Bolger et al. 2005 ), suggesting that there would have been high primary production and high arthropod density in our study plots in 2010. While low food availability during drought years may result in delayed nest initiation, both Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and Verdins still nest even during the severest droughts. Given the wet conditions in 2010 and the ability of our study species to nest in drought conditions, we do not believe that food availability decreased dramatically enough during our 2&ndash;3 weeks of experimental delay to limit our delayed-nesting treatment pairs. Yet by delaying the first-egg dates of treatment pairs by only 2&ndash;3 weeks, we produced low nest survival and productivity rates in treatment pairs that were similar to rates observed during droughts in 2006 and 2007.  Food-resource mediation (driven by variation in rainfall) of avian reproductive success has been documented by several investigators in arid habitats ( Boag and Grant 1981 ,  Grant and Grant 1987 ,  Bolger et al. 2005 ,  Preston and Rotenberry 2006 ).  Morrison and Bolger (2002)  and  Chase et al. (2005)  found that predation could also mediate annual changes in reproductive success in Song Sparrows (  Melospiza melodia  ) and Rufous-crowned Sparrows (  Aimophila ruficeps  ), while  Littlefield (2009)  speculated that Curve-billed Thrashers (  Toxostoma curvirostre  ) may escape predation from snakes by nesting earlier in the season during wet winters. To our knowledge, our study is the first documentation of nest parasite&ndash;mediated variation in reproductive success driven by variation in rainfall.  Working in coastal chaparral habitats,  Morrison and Bolger (2002)  determined that reproductive success was predator-mediated in wet years and food resource&ndash;mediated in dry years. Central to their conclusion was their observation that their study species largely failed to nest during a drought in 1999, an observation again made by  Bolger et al. (2005)  for Rufous-crowned Sparrows and for three additional study species during a severe drought in 2002. In the Sonoran Desert, we found that some species forego breeding during extreme drought, but that foregoing nesting is rare. Instead, we observed that Sonoran Desert species tended to delay nest initiation to a degree that was linearly related to the severity of winter rainfall shortages. Thus, while food-resource limitation may mediate reproductive success if species forego nesting completely, predation and parasitism may mediate reproductive success during drought if species simply delay nest initiation. In the Sonoran Desert, we found delayed nest initiation much more common than a complete cessation of nesting.  Delayed nesting exposes species to higher levels of predation and parasitism which exist later in the breeding season and which are not experienced by early-nesting individuals during wet breeding seasons. Our 2010 experiment demonstrated that this delay in nesting can result in significant decreases in nesting success and reproductive output even in the midst of a wet breeding season. It appeared that predator density increased on our study plots as the breeding season progressed. Female Brown-headed Cowbirds (which are both nest predators and nest parasites) were not present until mid-April. Anecdotally, we observed higher numbers of Greater Roadrunners (  Geococcyx californianus  ) and Cactus Wrens ( Campylorhynchus brunneicapillus ) later in the season due to the presence of young individuals, and we frequently observed what appeared to be family units of Cactus Wrens systematically hunting for Black-tailed Gnatcatcher and Verdin nests in May, June, and July. In addition,  Morrison and Bolger (2002)  and  Littlefield (2009)  provide convincing arguments that snakes are more active later in the season. Interestingly, although  Chase et al. (2005 ; following  Chase &lsqb;2002&rsqb; ) suggested that decreased vegetative nest cover during dry seasons may contribute to nest failure, we found that nest cover significantly increased for both Black-tailed Gnatcatchers and Verdins over the course of the season, such that potential nest concealment was highest when nest survival was lowest (McCreedy and van Riper, in press). This trend toward greater concealment was driven by a shift by both species to building nests in dense desert mistletoe (  Phoradendron californicum  ) clumps as the season progressed.  In a similar fashion, first broods of Black-tailed Gnatcatchers escaped cowbird parasitism. Brown-headed Cowbirds have occupied southwestern North America only in the last 100&ndash;200 years ( Laymon 1987 ,  Lowther 1993 ), and it appears that they have not yet adapted their breeding phenology to maximize their exposure to early-nesting desert species of the Mojave and Sonoran Deserts ( Johnson and van Riper 2004 ). Assuming that female cowbirds began parasitizing nests immediately upon arrival in our study plots, Black-tailed Gnatcatcher clutches completed by March 20 would have either fledged or nearly fledged before losses to cowbird activity began. As days lost to drought-delay accumulate, so too do the number of days the nest will be exposed to female cowbirds. This dynamic may play a significant role in the reproductive success of many other open-cup nesting species in southwestern North America, particularly the residents and short-distance migrants that appear to be most sensitive to drought-caused nesting delay ( Johnson and van Riper 2004 ).  It thus benefits avian species in the Southwest to nest earlier in the season, particularly in systems without severe late-winter storms. Yet, in drought conditions, many bird species appear unable to nest early. This suggests that food limitation may inhibit early nest initiation in arid habitats following winter drought, a topic that begs further research given climate projections into the coming decades. While some species in the arid Southwest forgo nesting completely during drought, many others simply delay nesting, a strategy that may produce diminished reproductive returns. Additional pressure from Brown-headed Cowbird parasitism may render this strategy untenable in the future for open-cup nesting species that are frequent nest-parasite hosts.  We wish to express our deep thanks to Dr. James Weigand and the Bureau of Land Management's California State Office for assistance with study design. Paul Taillie, Leonard Warren, and Stella Moss provided invaluable assistance locating and monitoring nests in 2010. In addition, Stuart Johnston, Jora Rehm-Lorber, Karl Bardon, Eileen Mueller, Kelly Iknayan, Michelle Gibson, Caroline Ailanthus, James Campbell, and Kyle Horton located and monitored nests over several seasons. Lindsay Smythe and the Kofa National Wildlife Refuge assisted with nest monitoring and housing in 2009 and 2010. Drs. Bob Steidl, Courtney Conway, William Mannan, and James Weigand assisted with experimental design and manuscript review. Terry Shaffer and Abigail Darrah assisted with logistic-exposure analysis. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. This is Point Blue Conservation Science contribution No. 1995.   Funding statement.  We wish to express our deep thanks to the Bureau of Land Management's California State Office for assistance with funding for the California portion of this work. We are grateful for funding provided by the California Off-Highway Motor Vehicle Recreation Division of California State Parks, the U.S. Geological Survey Ecosystem and Health Mission Areas, and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service via the Landscape Conservation Cooperative system. In particular, we thank Pattie Bright and David Lytle for their continued support of our research. No funders had input into the content of the manuscript, nor did any funders require their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.   Ethics statement.  Experimental protocol was approved prior to the 2010 season by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (Protocol &num;10-154). 