Fall stopover strategies of three species of thrush (<italic>Catharus</italic>) in northern South AmericaOptimal bird migration revisitedOptimality in avian migratory fuelling behaviour: A study of a trans-Saharan migrantComparison of autumn and spring migration strategies of Neotropical migratory landbirds in northeast BelizeEnergy reserves stored by migrating Gray-cheeked Thrushes <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus minimus</named-content></italic> at a spring stopover site in northern Colombia are sufficient for a long-distance flight to North AmericaFall migration of the Veery (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>) in northern Colombia: Determining the energetic importance of a stopover siteFruits in the diets of Neotropical migrant birds in Costa RicaBirds select fruits with more anthocyanins and phenolic compounds during autumn migrationCharacteristics of important stopover locations for migrating birds: Remote sensing with radar in the Great Lakes basinThe past and present of migratory connectivityBiotelemetry of New World thrushes during migration: Physiology, energetics and orientation in the wildTechnology on the move: Recent and forthcoming innovations for tracking migratory birdsPartly cloudy with a chance of migration: Weather, radars, and aeroecologyIndividual migratory tactics of New World <italic>Catharus</italic> thrushesLight-level geolocators reveal strong migratory connectivity and within-winter movements for a coastal California Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>) populationDramatic intraspecific differences in migratory routes, stopover sites and wintering areas, revealed using light-level geolocatorsMass change during migration stopover: A comparison of species groups and siteseBird: An online database of bird distribution and abundance &lsqb;web application&rsqb;Migrating birds stop over longer than usually thought: CommentLong-term decline of a winter-resident bird community in Puerto RicoConserving migratory land birds in the New World: Do we know enough?Tracking migratory songbirds: Accuracy of light-level loggers (geolocators) in forest habitatsBanding of migrant thrushes in Almirante, PanamaSeasonal variation in stopover site use: <italic>Catharus</italic> thrushes and vireos in northern ColombiaGeographic origins and timing of fall migration of the Veery in northern ColombiaVeery (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>), wintering locations, migratory connectivity, and a revision of its winter range using geolocator technologyAdaptations to migration in birds: Behavioural strategies, morphology and scaling effectsField estimates of body drag coefficient on the basis of dives in passerine birdsLinking hydrogen (&delta;2H) isotopes in feathers and precipitation: Sources of variance and consequences for assignment to isoscapesA multi-isotope (&delta;<sup>13</sup>C, &delta;<sup>15</sup>N, &delta;<sup>2</sup>H) feather isoscape to assign Afrotropical migrant birds to originsTrends in trappability and stop-over duration can confound interpretations of population trajectories from long-term migration ringing studiesLong-distance bird migration within South America revealed by light-level geolocatorsModel selection in ecology and evolutionA new multi-category classification of subcutaneous fat deposits of songbirdsIntegrating information from geolocators, weather radar, and citizen science to uncover a key stopover area of an aerial insectivoreModeling survival and testing biological hypotheses using marked animals: Case studies and recent advancesReturns and recoveries of banded North American birds in Panama and the tropicsGray-cheeked Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus minimus</named-content></italic>)Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>)The influence of climate on the timing and rate of spring bird migrationNew discoveries in landbird migration using geolocators, and a flight plan for the futureStop early to travel fast: Modelling risk-averse scheduling among nocturnally migrating birdsNon-destructive techniques to assess body composition of birds: A review and validation studyMultiple-day constancy as an alternative to pooling for estimating mark&ndash;recapture stopover length in Nearctic&ndash;Neotropical migrant landbirdsTropical winter habitat limits reproductive success on the temperate breeding grounds in a migratory birdPre-migratory &ldquo;fattening&rdquo; usually involves more than the deposition of fat aloneCapture&ndash;recapture survival models taking account of transientsTrue winter range of the Veery (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>): Lessons for determining winter ranges of species that winter in the tropicsPopulation declines in North American birds that migrate to the NeotropicsIntegrating concepts and technologies to advance the study of bird migrationA study of autumnal postmigrant weights and vernal fattening of North American migrants in the tropicsDivergence between subspecies groups of Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content> ustulatus</italic> and <italic>C. u. swainsoni</italic>)Not as the crow flies: A historical explanation for circuitous migration in Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>)Fuel deposition of three passerine bird species along the migration routeMigrating birds stop over longer than usually thought: An improved capture&ndash;recapture analysisVariation in survivorship of a migratory songbird throughout its annual cycleImpacts of a global climate cycle on population dynamics of a migratory songbirdFruit quality and consumption by songbirds during autumn migrationUse of successional habitat and fruit resources by songbirds during autumn migration in central New JerseyLandscape movements of migratory birds and bats reveal an expanded scale of stopoverStrategic diel regulation of body mass in European RobinsProgram MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsSpring stopovers of intercontinental migratory thrushes along the northern coast of the Gulf of MexicoNorthern South America is a geographic bottleneck that may be limiting the survival of Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migrants. However, very little is known about the migration ecology of transcontinental migrants wintering in South America. We studied the fall migratory strategies of three species of thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>) at 2 major migrant gateways into South America: the Dari&eacute;n and the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta (SNSM) of northern Colombia. Assuming that migration route shapes the stopover strategy of birds and that our sites receive birds from 2 different routes, we predicted that (1) migrants traveling over land through Central America (Dari&eacute;n) would make short and frequent stopovers followed by short flights and (2) migrants crossing the Caribbean (SNSM) would make few and long stopovers to acquire fuel for longer flights. To test these predictions, we estimated condition on arrival, stopover duration, fuel deposition rates, and potential flight ranges after stopover, using 3 yr of capture&ndash;recapture data. Each species adopted a different stopover strategy, with Swainson's Thrush arriving in South America through the Dari&eacute;n, making the shortest stopovers and achieving the shortest flight ranges (800 km); Gray-cheeked Thrush arriving primarily through the Dari&eacute;n, making short stopovers but achieving longer flight ranges (1,200 km); and Veery arriving in both the Dari&eacute;n and the SNSM, making the longest stopovers and achieving the longest flight ranges (1,900 km). Our results suggest that stopover strategies are shaped by both migratory route (over land vs. over water) and distance to final destination in South America. Unraveling the breeding origins and wintering destinations of individuals passing through northern Colombia would greatly improve our understanding of hemispheric migration systems and will be critical if we are to protect the most important stopover sites and habitats.El norte de Sur Am&eacute;rica es un cuello de botella geogr&aacute;fico que puede limitar la sobrevivencia de las aves migratorias Ne&aacute;rticas Neotropicales. Sin embargo, a&uacute;n conocemos poco sobre la ecolog&iacute;a migratoria de especies que pasan el invierno en Sur Am&eacute;rica. Estudiamos las estrategias migratorias oto&ntilde;ales de tres especies de <italic>Catharus</italic> (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. ustulatus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>) en dos sitios de entrada a Sur Am&eacute;rica: el Dari&eacute;n y la Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta (SNSM) en el norte de Colombia. Asumiendo que la ruta determina la estrategia migratoria, y que nuestros sitios reciben aves de dos rutas diferentes, predecimos que (1) aves volando sobre Centro Am&eacute;rica (Dari&eacute;n) har&aacute;n escalas cortas y frecuentes seguidas por vuelos cortos, y (2) aves volando sobre el Caribe (SNSM) har&aacute;n pocas escalas largas adquiriendo combustible para vuelos largos. Estimamos la condici&oacute;n f&iacute;sica al llegar, la duraci&oacute;n de la escala, la tasa de acumulaci&oacute;n de combustible y la distancia potencial de vuelo, usando tres a&ntilde;os de datos de captura y recaptura. Cada especie adopt&oacute; una estrategia diferente: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. ustulatus</named-content></italic> lleg&oacute; a Sur Am&eacute;rica por el Dari&eacute;n e hizo las paradas y vuelos m&aacute;s cortos (800 km), <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic> lleg&oacute; por el Dari&eacute;n e hizo escalas cortas pero logrando vuelos largos (1200 km), y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. fuscescens</named-content></italic> lleg&oacute; tanto por el Dari&eacute;n como por la SNSM e hizo las escalas y vuelos m&aacute;s largos (1900 km). Nuestros resultados sugieren que la estrategia migratoria depende tanto de la ruta (sobre continente o sobre mar) como de la distancia hasta el sitio de invierno en Sur Am&eacute;rica. Conocer los sitios de reproducci&oacute;n y los destinos de invierno de las aves que pasan por el norte de Colombia contribuir&aacute; a mejorar nuestro conocimiento sobre los sistemas migratorios y ser&aacute; cr&iacute;tico para la protecci&oacute;n de los sitios de parada y los h&aacute;bitats m&aacute;s importantes.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> tasa de acumulaci&oacute;n de combustible, escalas migratorias, migraci&oacute;n, Neotropicales, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus ustulatus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus fuscescens</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Catharus minimus</named-content></italic>Reversing population declines of many Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migratory birds will require conservation strategies that address their needs at all stages of their annual cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Robbins1">Robbins et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Sauer1">Sauer et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Faaborg2">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>). The majority of studies of migratory birds are still focused on the breeding grounds, however, even though there is growing evidence that limiting factors act during the nonbreeding period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Sillett2">Sillett et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Sillett1">Sillett and Holmes 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Norris1">Norris et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Faaborg2">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>). In particular, very little is known about the biology of migrants that winter in South America and, especially, about their migration ecology as they travel to and from their wintering grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Faaborg2">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Faaborg1">2013</xref>). A rapidly growing body of research, using remote tracking techniques, has started to unveil many aspects of the geographic origins, destinations, and routes of various species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bowlin1">Bowlin et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-GonzalezPrieto1">Gonz&aacute;lez-Prieto et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-McKinnon1">McKinnon et al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, it is now timely to complement this exciting information with detailed field research that documents the behavior of birds on the ground and in important stopover areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Robinson1">Robinson et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bridge1">Bridge et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Fudickar1">Fudickar et al. 2012</xref>). Northern Colombia is one of these important regions, recently identified as a gateway for migrants entering and leaving South America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>).Thrushes in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> have been widely used as a model system in the study of migratory bird behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bowlin1">Bowlin et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Cochran1">Cochran and Wikelski 2005</xref>). These birds provide a particularly useful model because, aside from performing some of the longest migrations of all Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic landbirds, they are relatively common, easy to capture due to their understory habits, and large enough to carry tracking devices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Mack1">Mack et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Lowther1">Lowther et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Remsen1">Remsen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Ruegg2">Ruegg and Smith 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bowlin1">Bowlin et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>). Furthermore, the existing body of information on these species allows us to construct hypotheses about their stopover ecology that can be tested in the field.Three <italic>Catharus</italic> species migrate through northern Colombia during the fall: Swainson's Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. ustulatus</named-content></italic>), Veery (C. <italic>fuscescens</italic>), and Gray-cheeked Thrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>). Despite having largely separate wintering areas, and potentially different migration routes from North America to South America, all 3 species pass through the narrow area of northern Colombia during the fall. This region is therefore a potential geographic bottleneck for these long-distance migrants, and understanding how they are using this area during stopover could be important for their conservation.Swainson's Thrushes of the eastern or olive-backed subspecies (<italic>C. u. swainsoni</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Ruegg1">Ruegg 2007</xref>) migrate primarily through the Caribbean lowlands of Central America in both spring and fall and are often abundant during fall migration from the Yucat&aacute;n through Costa Rica and Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Galindo1">Galindo et al. 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Mack1">Mack et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-eBird1">eBird 2014</xref>). They winter along the base of the eastern Andes, from western Venezuela through Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and Bolivia, and can reach northern Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Mack1">Mack et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>). Some birds probably make overwater crossings from Florida and the eastern U.S. Gulf Coast to the Yucat&aacute;n and northern South America, but the vast majority probably enter South America via Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Galindo1">Galindo et al. 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Loftin1">Loftin 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>).By contrast, most Veery arrive on the northern coast of Colombia after crossing the Caribbean from the southeastern United Sates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-GonzalezPrieto1">Gonz&aacute;lez-Prieto et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>). They are uncommon fall migrants in Central America but sometimes appear in large numbers along the Caribbean coast from Belize to Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Rogers1">Rogers and Odum 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Remsen1">Remsen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly2">Bayly and G&oacute;mez 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-eBird1">eBird 2014</xref>). The species winters in southern Amazonia and as far south as the Pantanal and southeastern Brazil and apparently makes long intrawinter movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Remsen1">Remsen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-eBird1">eBird 2014</xref>).Information about the fall migration of Gray-cheeked Thrush is scarcer. The few fall records from the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta, Venezuela, and the Guyanas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-eBird1">eBird 2014</xref>), and reports of relatively large numbers of birds during the fall in Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Galindo1">Galindo et al. 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Rogers1">Rogers and Odum 1966</xref>), suggest that this species has a prevailing Central American route into South America. Wintering grounds are believed to be primarily in the northwestern Amazon basin, extending to the base of the Colombian and Venezuelan Andes (Hilty and Brown 1987, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hilty1">Hilty 2003</xref>, N. J. Bayly and C. G&oacute;mez personal observation).Here, we test whether migratory bird species with different winter destinations and migration routes show differences in migration stopover strategy. We use 3 yr of field data from 2 sites in northern Colombia: the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta (SNSM) and the forests of the Dari&eacute;n close to the border between Colombia and Panama (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f01">Figure 1</xref>). By comparing arrival condition, stopover durations, fuel deposition rates, and potential flight range of <italic>Catharus</italic> from these 2 sites, we test the following predictions. (1) Given that Swainson's Thrush follows a predominantly continental route into South America with few large ecological barriers, we predict that it will be more abundant at the Dari&eacute;n site than at the SNSM and that its migratory strategy will consist of relatively short stopovers and short consecutive flights. (2) Given that Veery migrate primarily over the Caribbean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>), we predict that its strategy will consist of long flights interspersed by long stopovers during which birds refuel substantially. (3) For Gray-cheeked Thrush, historical records lead us to predict that the species has a predominantly Central American route and, therefore, is expected to be more common in the Dari&eacute;n and to make short and frequent stopovers resulting in short flight distances, as in Swainson's Thrush. (4) We further predict that individuals of all 3 species arriving through the Dari&eacute;n into South America (i.e. those potentially taking a Central American route) will adopt a stopover strategy similar to that predicted for Swainson's Thrush.Map showing the 2 study areas in northern Colombia (the Dari&eacute;n and the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta &lsqb;SNSM&rsqb;) where southward migration of 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> was monitored from 2009 to 2012.Two of the largest expanses of tropical forest in northern Colombia, separated by 450 km of largely agricultural land, are located in the isolated mountains of the SNSM near the Caribbean coast, and at the meeting point between Central America and South America commonly referred to as &ldquo;the Dari&eacute;n&rdquo; or &ldquo;the Dari&eacute;n gap&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-IDEAM1">IDEAM 2010</xref>).We worked in 2 areas of the SNSM. The first, Hacienda La Victoria, is situated in the northwest corner of the SNSM (11.1197750&deg;N, &minus;74.0819510&deg;W) and consisted of a matrix of shade coffee plantations with large remnants of premontane tropical forest 1,200 m above sea level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>). The second area, the Quebrada Valencia reserve, is located in the foothills of the northern slope of the SNSM (11.23624&deg;N, &minus;73.79921&deg;W) and consisted of lowland tropical rainforest 175 m above sea level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>). Although forests at 175 m and 1,200 m are different in structure and composition, we pooled the data from the 2 sites, because our main objective was to compare 2 geographically distinct areas (the SNSM and the Dari&eacute;n) and we considered the 2 SNSM sites to be representative of the wider SNSM region. Although our study species show differences in abundance along the elevation gradient of the SNSM during migration, with Gray-cheeked Thrush present in greater numbers in premontane forest and Veery in lowland forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>), defining fine-scale habitat quality for each species was not in the scope of our study.In the Dari&eacute;n, we worked in the Tacarcuna Nature Reserve (8.1561470&deg;N, &minus;77.2506470&deg;W) near the village of Sapzurro on the Caribbean coast, close to the border between Colombia and Panama (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Habitat at the Dari&eacute;n site consisted of tropical rainforest 100 m above sea level.We monitored the southward migration of birds from mid-September to mid-November during 2009, 2010, and 2011 in the SNSM and during 2011 and 2012 at the Dari&eacute;n site. At each site, we set up a constant-effort banding station consisting of 10 to 15 twelve-meter mist nets (we used 32-mm-mesh Japanese and North Ronaldsay nylon nets) covering an area of forest &ap;1 km<sup>2</sup>. Mist nets were positioned strategically to maximize capture rates, and positions were maintained virtually constant at the sites during each year and between years. Mist nets were opened daily from dawn (0545&ndash;0600 hours) for an average of 4.5 hr and were checked every 30 min. All birds captured were transported in individual cloth bags to a banding station where they were marked using numbered Porzana-made metal bands (band reporting website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aselva.co" xlink:type="simple">http://www.aselva.co</ext-link>). For all captured and recaptured birds, we recorded band number, date and time of capture, age according to plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Pyle1">Pyle 1997</xref>), visible subcutaneous fat score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Kaiser1">Kaiser 1993</xref>), pectoral muscle score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Redfern1">Redfern and Clark 2001</xref>), wing chord (&plusmn;1 mm), and body mass (&plusmn;0.1 g) using an electronic balance (Fast Weigh digital pocket scale, model M-500). <italic>Catharus</italic> cannot be reliably sexed using external characters during the nonbreeding period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Pyle1">Pyle 1997</xref>), so we did not include sex as a factor in our data. All birds were released immediately after processing.To determine the migration phenology of the 3 study species, we analyzed captures from the Dari&eacute;n in 2011 and 2012, and from the SNSM from 2009 to 2011. We present the mean capture total summed every 2 days across years to represent the phenology of migration. Mist-net effort was largely constant, and although weather conditions occasionally led to a reduced mist-net effort, we have not corrected for mist-net effort because the variation in effort is expected to have had limited impact on phenologies.To correct raw capture totals for variation in capture probability between sites, we estimated the expected number of captures by species, year, and site, using recapture probabilities estimated from mark&ndash;recapture models (see below; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hochachka1">Hochachka and Fiedler 2008</xref>). To do this, we ran POPAN models in MARK version 5.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>) using a logit link function to estimate survival (&Phi;) and recapture probability (<italic>p</italic>), a multinomial logit function to estimate the PENT probability (i.e. probability of an individual from the &ldquo;superpopulation&rdquo; entering our local population), and a log function for the corrected estimate of the size of the super population (<italic>N</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hochachka1">Hochachka and Fiedler 2008</xref>). In all cases, we assumed constant survival and recapture probability throughout our sampling period.Changes in the body mass of migrating birds largely reflect changes in the energy reserves available to individuals, and these reserves are primarily due to fat deposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Piersma1">Piersma 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-McWilliams1">McWilliams and Whitman 2013</xref>). For example, body mass and fat score have been shown to be positively and strongly correlated in both Veery and Gray-cheeked Thrush (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">2013</xref>). We modeled change in body mass as a function of the number of days since a bird was first captured, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. (2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">2013</xref>). Change in body mass for all recaptured individuals was calculated as the difference between mass at first capture and mass at any successive capture event. To correct for variation in size between individuals and species, we expressed mass change as a percentage of lean body mass (LBM, the estimated mass of a bird without visible fat reserves; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-McWilliams1">McWilliams and Whitman 2013</xref>). We estimated LBM using the regression equation for body mass against wing length for all captured individuals with fat score zero. We used the equations reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. (2012)</xref> for Veery (LBM &equals; 6.47 &plus; 0.212&ast;wing length, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 124) and in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. (2013)</xref> for Gray-Cheeked Thrush (LBM &equals; 3.60 &plus; 0.227&ast;wing length, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 43). For Swainson's Thrush, we estimated the equation using the subset of birds with fat score zero captured during fall migration in the Dari&eacute;n (LBM &equals; &minus;7.137 &plus; 0.339&ast;wing length, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 55).Modeling was carried out with the statistical package R, using general linear models with normal errors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2013</xref>) and forcing the intercept through zero, given that change in body mass at the point of first capture is zero. We tested a set of 6 models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t01">Table 1</xref>) with the following variables: interval of days between captures (I), date at first capture (D), starting body mass (CI), expressed as a condition index where CI &equals; (mass at first capture/wing length)&ast;100, and the difference in hour of capture between captures (H). We included H as an additive term in all models to correct for body-mass increase with time of day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Schaub1">Schaub and Jenni 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Thomas1">Thomas 2000</xref>). Age is known to affect body mass change in <italic>Catharus</italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>); however, because we did not have enough recaptures of adults to allow robust modeling of this parameter, we decided to exclude it as a variable in our analyses. Similarly, a lack of sufficient recaptures in some years made it unfeasible to model years separately, so data were pooled across years (2009&ndash;2012). For Gray-cheeked Thrush and Veery, we carried out an additional analysis to explore whether models of body mass change supported an effect of site (S) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t01">Table 1</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t04">Table 4</xref> in the Appendix).Model set designed to examine how body mass varies in 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> during stopovers in northern Colombia as a function of the number of days since first capture. Variables: I &equals; interval in days between captures, D &equals; date of first capture, CI &equals; initial body mass (CI &equals; &lsqb;mass/wing length&rsqb;&ast;100), S &equals; site (the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta or the Dari&eacute;n). Difference in hour of capture between captures (H) was included as an additive term in all models to correct for increases in body mass with time of day.Our model set aimed to determine whether linear, quadratic, or polynomial functions best described the variation of body mass with time and included plausible interactions of the individual variables with days since first capture. Model selection was carried out using Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC), comparing &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> values, where &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is the difference between each model and the model with the lowest AIC; and Akaike model weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), where <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> reflects the relative support that model <italic>i</italic> receives over other models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Johnson1">Johnson and Omland 2004</xref>). Where &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &lt; 2 and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &le; 10&percnt;, we carried out model averaging using a multimodel inference package in R (MuMIn) to get weighted averages for all the parameters in the top models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Johnson1">Johnson and Omland 2004</xref>).We estimated the fall stopover duration of <italic>Catharus</italic> in the Dari&eacute;n and the SNSM using mark&ndash;recapture analysis, except for Veery in the SNSM, for which we used the stopover durations presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. (2012)</xref>. For the other species, we estimated &ldquo;stopover after&rdquo; and &ldquo;total stopover&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Schaub2">Schaub et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Efford1">Efford 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Morris1">Morris et al. 2005</xref>) for years in which &gt;40 individuals were captured per species and site. For those species and years with smaller sample sizes, we present &ldquo;minimum stopover duration&rdquo; only, which was calculated as the average time interval between first and last capture. To estimate &ldquo;stopover after&rdquo; and &ldquo;total stopover,&rdquo; we analyzed capture histories in MARK using 2 models, 1 with constant survival and recapture probability (&Phi;(.) p(.)) and another evaluating the effect of transient individuals (those stopping for only 1 day) on survival probability (&Phi;(trans) p(.)). When models supported the presence of transients, we estimated the percentage of the population assumed to be transient using the equation <italic>T</italic> &equals; &lsqb;1 &minus; (&Phi;<sub>1</sub>/&Phi;<sub>2</sub>)&rsqb;&ast;100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Pradel1">Pradel et al. 1997</xref>). Age is potentially an important variable that can influence stopover duration, but we were unable to model its effect because samples sizes were insufficient. Our results therefore represent the average stopover duration for the population as a whole.We used AIC to infer model suitability and calculated <italic>&ccirc;</italic>, which is a measure of the overdispersion of the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Lebreton1">Lebreton et al. 1992</xref>), to assess model fit. All subsequent estimates were corrected for the resulting value of <italic>&ccirc;</italic>. In general, a model is considered to have relatively good fit if <italic>&ccirc;</italic> &le; 2. Where &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> were not supportive of a single model, we carried out model averaging. The resulting estimates of survival (&phi;) were used to estimate &ldquo;stopover after&rdquo; using the equation for life expectancy: LE &equals; &minus;1/ln(&phi;). &ldquo;Total stopover&rdquo; was calculated by estimating &phi; and the seniority probability (&gamma;) using this equation: total stopover &equals; &lsqb;&minus;1/ln(&phi;)&rsqb; &plus; &lsqb;&minus;1/ln(&gamma;)&rsqb;.Fuel load on arrival is a measure of how much stored energy a bird has available on arrival at a stopover site. It can also serve as a measure of the probability that a bird will make a multiday stopover, given that &ldquo;fatter&rdquo; birds are less likely to need to refuel than lean birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly1">Bayly 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hedenstrom1">Hedenstr&ouml;m 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-McLaren1">McLaren et al. 2013</xref>). We calculated fuel load on arrival by subtracting LBM from the mass of birds at first capture and expressing the difference as a percentage of LBM. This calculation assumes that most birds were first captured on or within 1 day of arrival at the stopover site. Violation of this assumption will result in overestimates of arrival fuel loads. We carried out chi-square and paired Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests with 95&percnt; confidence intervals to compare fuel loads between sites and species.Departure fuel load, expressed as a percentage of LBM, is an estimate of the energy reserves with which birds leave a site after stopover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>). We calculated departure fuel load by entering total stopover duration into the model of body mass change that received the greatest support from AIC. Our body-mass-change models predict daily mass gain minus overnight weight loss, which is the energy birds consume every night at the basal metabolic rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Dunn1">Dunn 2001</xref>). Because <italic>Catharus</italic> are expected to depart shortly after sunset on their last day of stopover, we include an additive term for overnight weight loss (<italic>O</italic>) to the equation for mass gain when calculating departure fuel load (<italic>O</italic> &equals; 2.6&percnt; LBM, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>).To estimate potential flight range after stopover, we entered values for departure fuel load, wingspan, and wing area into the program Flight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Pennycuick1">Pennycuick 2008</xref>). We calculated 2 flight ranges: (1) the range considering only the fuel gained at each site (e.g., the increase in range as a result of the stopover, LBM &plus; mass gain); and (2) total flight range, taking into consideration mean mass on arrival and adding the total fuel attained during stopover (arrival mass &plus; mass gain). The values used for wingspan (WS) and wing area (WA) were as follows: Veery, WS &equals; 0.285 m, WA &equals; 0.0156 m<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>); Gray-cheeked Thrush, WS &equals; 0.307 m, WA &equals; 0.0168 m<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>); and Swainson's Thrush, WS &equals; 0.297 m, WA &equals; 0.0142 m<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Yong1">Yong and Moore 1997</xref>). Starting altitude was set at 100 m, cruising altitude at 1,000 m, and muscle fraction at 0.17 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>). Body-drag coefficient was set at 0.1, which is the default value recommended for small passerines in the program Flight. For European passerines similar in size to <italic>Catharus</italic> species, body-drag coefficient values between 0.2 and 0.4 have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hedenstrom2">Hedenstr&ouml;m and Liechti 2001</xref>). It should therefore be borne in mind that flight ranges may be slightly overestimated if body-drag coefficients are &gt;0.1 in <italic>Catharus</italic>.Timing of migration varied between species and sites, but most birds passed in October (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f02">Figure 2</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f02">2</xref>B). Veery was the earliest species to pass through the Dari&eacute;n, primarily between September 30 and October 8, whereas in the SNSM its passage was concentrated from October 5 to 15. Swainson's Thrush and Gray-cheeked Thrush passed through the Dari&eacute;n simultaneously, with a first peak around October 8 and a second main passage period from October 14 to 30. In the SNSM, Swainson's Thrush passed earlier than in the Dari&eacute;n and in much lower numbers. Gray-cheeked Thrush passed through the SNSM in low and relatively constant numbers throughout October.Phenology of the southward migration of 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> through (<bold>A</bold>) the Dari&eacute;n in 2011 and 2012 and (<bold>B</bold>) the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta, Colombia, 2009&ndash;2011, based on new captures averaged over 2-day periods.On the basis of raw capture totals and taking into account mist-net effort, both Swainson's Thrush and Gray-cheeked Thrush were markedly more abundant in the Dari&eacute;n, whereas Veery showed similar abundances at both sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t02">Table 2</xref>). Capture totals corrected for encounter probability (EXP in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t02">Table 2</xref>) were slightly higher than raw totals but remained within the same order of magnitude and showed a similar overall pattern. The total number of captures by year also varied within species, particularly in Swainson's Thrush (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t02">Table 2</xref>); however, a large portion of this variation can be attributed to mist-net effort.Raw capture and recapture totals, and expected totals (EXP &plusmn; SE), corrected for capture probability using POPAN models in MARK, for 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> during fall migration at 2 sites in northern Colombia between 2009 and 2012. Totals are separated by age class (HY &equals; hatch year, AHY &equals; after hatch year, U &equals; unknown), and capture effort is expressed in net hours (1 net hour &equals; one 12-m net open for 1 hr). Abbreviations: SWTH &equals; Swainson's Thrush, VEER &equals; Veery, GCTH &equals; Gray-cheeked Thrush, SNSM &equals; Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta.Recapture rates varied between 1.5&percnt; and 20&percnt; at both sites, indicating the variation in the relative number of individuals of all species that made multiday stopovers at the study sites. Immature individuals were more abundant than adults at both sites during all years, but the ratio was not constant between years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t02">Table 2</xref>). The year with the highest ratio of immature to adult birds for all species was 2011 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t02">Table 2</xref>). Estimates of daily survival (&Phi;) and recapture probability (<italic>p</italic>) are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f03">Figure 3</xref>.Daily survival and recapture probabilities estimated from capture&ndash;recapture models (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t06">Table 6</xref> in the Appendix) for 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> on migration in northern Colombia (SNSM &equals; Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta). Estimates are presented separately for each year and study site. Error bars show the standard errors of the estimates.For all species, fuel loads on first capture showed considerable variation (from &minus;25&percnt; up to 60&percnt; LBM) at both sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f04">Figure 4</xref>). However, all species arrived with significantly lower fuel loads in the SNSM than they did in the Dari&eacute;n (Swainson's Thrush: <italic>t</italic><sub>132</sub> &equals; &minus;2.32, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; Veery: <italic>t</italic><sub>306</sub> &equals; 29.02, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Gray-cheeked Thrush: t<sub>94</sub> &equals; &minus;12.94, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). More than 50&percnt; of the first captures in the SNSM had fuel loads &le; &minus;5&percnt; LBM, whereas most individuals in the Dari&eacute;n had fuel loads &ge; 5&percnt; LBM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f04">Figure 4</xref>).Histograms of fuel loads at first capture (surrogate for arrival fuel load) of individuals of 3 species in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> captured during southward migration in northern Colombia. A value of zero means that birds were first captured at lean body mass (LBM), which is equivalent to having no visible fat reserves. Data are shown separately for each study site but are combined across years (Dari&eacute;n: 2011 and 2012; Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta: 2009 to 2011).Most recaptured individuals gained mass between captures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f05">Figure 5</xref>), and a polynomial model best described body mass change for all species and sites, with just 1 exception (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-f06">Figure 6</xref>). For both Veery and Gray-cheeked Thrush, polynomial models including the factor &ldquo;site&rdquo; received the highest support from AIC (Veery: AIC &equals; 472.28, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.960; Gray-cheeked Thrush: AIC &equals; 279.01, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.987); this is evidence for a higher rate of mass change in the SNSM than in the Dari&eacute;n in Veery but supports the opposite pattern for Gray-cheeked Thrush. Because of a lack of recaptures of Swainson's Thrush in the SNSM (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2), we could not test for site differences in this species.Change in body mass between successive captures of individuals of Swainson's Thrush (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>), Veery (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) and Gray-cheeked Thrush (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) during southward migration in the Dari&eacute;n (left) and the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta (right), Colombia. Variation in the shading of symbols reflects different years (2009&ndash;2012), and lines connect capture events of the same individual. The horizontal line is the mean lean body mass for each species. (<bold>D</bold>) was adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. (2012)</xref>.Change in body mass (expressed as percent lean body mass &lsqb;&percnt;LBM&rsqb;) in individuals of three species of thrush as a function of the number of days since first capture in the Dari&eacute;n and the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta (SNSM). Symbols represent birds from multiple years (2009&ndash;2012), and lines represent the predicted mass-change trajectory for each species based on model-averaged parameters from models that received the greatest support from AIC values. The model with most support from AIC is shown in the table under each graph with the respective AIC, &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> values. (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) Swainson's Thrush. (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) Veery, adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. (2012)</xref>. (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) Gray-cheeked Thrush. <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t05">Table 5</xref> in the Appendix shows the AIC, &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> values for all the models that were evaluated.&ldquo;Total stopover&rdquo; durations varied between 3 and 9 days for all species, with a tendency to be longer in the SNSM regardless of species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t03">Table 3</xref>). The shortest durations were those of Gray-cheeked Thrush in the Dari&eacute;n, whereas Veery in the SNSM made the longest stopovers. Models for Swainson's Thrush and Veery in the Dari&eacute;n supported the presence of transients in the population, whereas there was no evidence of transients of either species in the SNSM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t04">Tables 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t05">5</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t06">6</xref> in the Appendix). For Swainson's Thrush, the estimated percentage of transients in the Dari&eacute;n was 96&percnt; and 79&percnt; in 2011 and 2012, respectively, whereas for Veery it was 96&percnt; in both 2011 and 2012.Estimates of stopover duration (minimum, &ldquo;stopover after,&rdquo; and total), departure fuel load (LBM &equals; lean body mass), and potential flight range for 3 species of thrush in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic>. In parentheses are minimum and maximum stopover durations (95&percnt; confidence intervals), rounded to the nearest day. Blank spaces indicate species with insuficient sample sizes. The flight range gained on site reflects the distance that a bird could fly using the fuel accumulated during stopover only. &ldquo;Total distance&rdquo; takes into account both the mean fuel load that birds carried on arrival and the fuel load accumulated during stopover.The gain in fuel load during a stopover at either site generally varied between 10&percnt; and 20&percnt; of LBM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t03">Table 3</xref>). However, gains in Veery in the SNSM were larger, being closer to 30&percnt; of LBM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t03">Table 3</xref>). These gains increased flight range by about 500&ndash;700 km, but for Veery in the SNSM, flight range increased by &gt;1,400 km. Considering the reserves that birds had on arrival, total departure flight ranges were typically between 800 and 1,200 km (&gt;1,700 km for Veery in the SNSM), with birds in the Dari&eacute;n benefiting from the larger reserves carried on arrival (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-t03">Table 3</xref>).Our results suggest that these three <italic>Catharus</italic> species adopt markedly different stopover strategies at 2 sites in northern Colombia during their southward migration. In agreement with our predictions, Swainson's Thrush seem to take a primarily Central American route into South America, given that birds arrived mostly through the Dari&eacute;n and in relatively good body condition. Most individuals were either transient or made short stopovers that resulted in the shortest potential flight ranges of the 3 species (800 km). On the whole, this species seems to have a &ldquo;frequent-short-stopover-short-flight&rdquo; strategy. The results for Veery partially supported our prediction, in that birds that arrived through the Dari&eacute;n did so in better body condition than those from the SNSM (which suggests an overland route) and, hence, made shorter stopovers than the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>). However, Veery from both sites attained equivalent potential flight distances, which were the longest of the 3 species (2,000 km); this suggests that Veery has a &ldquo;few-stopover-long-flights&rdquo; strategy, regardless of the route taken. Gray-cheeked Thrush was much more abundant in the Dari&eacute;n, suggesting a primarily Central American route, as predicted. However, potential flight ranges after stopover were generally long (1,200 km), contradicting our prediction and supporting a few-stopover-long-flights strategy more similar to that of the Veery.Although we do not yet have quantitative data to describe the diet of <italic>Catharus</italic> during migration at our sites, our field observations and superficial examination of fecal samples from bird bags indicate that they eat large quantities of fruit during their fall stopover. This is not surprising, given that fruit has been shown to be metabolized more efficiently into fat by birds and has also been shown to contain a high antioxidant content, which makes it more appealing to fueling migrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Blake1">Blake and Loiselle 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Suthers1">Suthers et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Smith1">Smith et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bolser1">Bolser et al. 2013</xref>). We frequently saw birds eating fruit from native forest trees of the families Melastomataceae, Rubiaceae, and Moraceae, as well as eating the fruit of <italic>Carludovica palmata</italic>. More study is needed to properly quantify the diets of these migrants, but fruit resources from these forests are doubtlessly playing a crucial role in providing an important part of the fuel for migrating <italic>Catharus</italic> in northern Colombia.Our predictions about stopover strategies were based primarily on birds taking 1 of 2 routes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Alerstam1">Alerstam 2011</xref>), either an overland route through Central America or an oversea route across the Caribbean. However, our observed flight ranges for each species, regardless of site, condition on arrival, or stopover duration, suggest that the distance remaining to each species' wintering grounds may be the strongest determinant of stopover strategy, with Veery traveling the farthest from northern Colombian stopovers sites and Swainson's Thrush the shortest distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Ruegg2">Ruegg and Smith 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>). Distance to final destination could therefore be a critical factor shaping migratory strategies, and future research on the wintering grounds, linking populations to breeding and migration routes, will be essential to fully understand these hemispheric systems.Although we cannot be sure whether individual birds arrived at our sites via different routes, differences in body condition on arrival supported this assumption. In the SNSM, all <italic>Catharus</italic>, primarily Veery and Gray-cheeked Thrush, arrived in poor body condition and in need of extensive refueling. On the other hand, birds in the Dari&eacute;n, primarily Swainson's Thrush and Gray-cheeked Thrush, arrived in better body condition and generally continued their migration the following evening (as reflected by a high percentage of transients) or only stopped for short periods. In both cases, our results confirm the importance of these 2 areas for migrants heading to their wintering grounds in South America.Another explanation for the variation in body condition is that birds take similar routes into South America but originate from different populations in North America, thus arriving with different fuel loads at our sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>). Indeed, differences in the timing of passage between sites, within the same species, could be an indication that birds originated from different populations. Whether <italic>Catharus</italic> entering South America through the Dari&eacute;n or through the SNSM come by different routes (i.e. through Central America or by crossing the Caribbean) or are from different populations is still unknown and may be the key to understanding what determines the differences in arrival condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Heckscher1">Heckscher et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Delmore1">Delmore et al. 2012</xref>). Weather patterns&mdash;in particular, wind direction and storms&mdash;could also have an important effect on the condition of birds on arrival, and on the composition and abundance of species at each site in different years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Marra1">Marra et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bonter1">Bonter et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Chilson1">Chilson et al. 2012</xref>). For example, a large arrival of Swainson's Thrush in the SNSM in 2010 was associated with a change in the prevailing wind direction, which pushed birds east of their normal trajectory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>). Understanding how weather affects the abundance and composition of migrants at different stopover sites in the Neotropics is a topic for future research.Although our data show clear differences in stopover strategy between species and sites, our study has limitations that need to be accounted for when interpreting the results. For example, small sample sizes for some species, sites, and years, and different recapture rates of adult and immature birds, limited the power of our models to estimate rates of body mass change and stopover durations. This also meant that we could not test for age differences in stopover strategy, although we know that individual <italic>Catharus</italic> of different ages can behave differently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bowlin1">Bowlin et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-GonzalezPrieto1">Gonz&aacute;lez-Prieto et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">2013</xref>). Another limitation is that our localized capture areas and field-data-collection design did not allow us to account for birds that moved beyond the trapping areas but remained within the stopover region. Recent work has shown that <italic>Catharus</italic> can move large distances within stopover sites and regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Cormier1">Cormier et al. 2013</xref>), which means that stopover duration may be underestimated in designs such as ours.Despite these limitations, our study is one of the first to provide information about the differences in stopover site use by Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migrants within South America, while simultaneously highlighting the energetic importance of stopover sites in northern Colombia for <italic>Catharus</italic>. These data collected through field studies are essential to complement the information produced by remote tracking techniques, which still have some limitations despite a significant and continuous process of improvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Fudickar1">Fudickar et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hobson1">Hobson et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Hobson2">2012b</xref>). Only a combination of population-level field studies at a network of sites and a larger sample of remotely tracked individuals will reveal a complete picture of migration and stopover use throughout the Neotropical region. Our field studies in northern Colombia have also demonstrated the critical importance of this region to Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migrants during spring migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly3">Bayly et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>).To more fully put the results presented here into a hemispheric context, we must determine the geographic origin and wintering destination of individual birds stopping over in northern Colombia during the fall. We also need to understand how birds select the sites and habitats where they stop to refuel in South America and the implications that this selection may have on the success of their migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Bayly4">Bayly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Gomez1">G&oacute;mez et al. 2013</xref>). Similar studies should be carried out in other areas of northern South America and in Central America, targeting those sites that have been highlighted as potentially important through geolocator data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Jahn1">Jahn et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Laughlin1">Laughlin et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-McKinnon1">McKinnon et al. 2013</xref>). Most importantly, there is a need to analyze how all of these events connect to other stages in the annual cycle and how these connections affect individual fitness and survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Boulet1">Boulet and Norris 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-702-Faaborg2">Faaborg et al. 2010</xref>). Knowing where, when, and how species use stopover sites and whether they have preferential migratory routes will allow us to increase the efficacy of conservation efforts during one of the most critical stages in the annual cycle of migrants.We thank the Rufford Small Grants Foundation, the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, and Environment Canada for funding and supporting the fieldwork involved in this study. We are indebted to M. Rubio and F. Jimenez in Reserva Tacarcuna, M. and C. Weber in La Victoria, and I. Vieira and M. C. Rojas in Quebrada Valencia for letting us work in the three field sites. L. C&aacute;rdenas, V. G&oacute;mez, H. Arias, and J. Sanabria were part of our team in the field, and we thank them for their long hours of hard work. We thank A. J. Crawford, V. Flechas, L. M. Guti&eacute;rrez, A. M. Su&aacute;rez, D. Barrag&aacute;n, C. Cruz, A. Aldana, and three anonymous reviewers for comments and suggestions that helped improve all aspects of the manuscript.Model set and associated AIC, &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> values for models of body mass change as a function of site (S), days since first capture (I), date (D), initial body mass (CI), and hour of capture (H) for Veery and Gray-cheeked Thrush captured on &gt;1 occasion during southward migration in northern Colombia. The models that included site (in bold) received high support for both species.Model set and associated AIC, &Delta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> values for models of body mass change in 3 species of thrush in the genus <italic>Catharus</italic> on stopover at 2 sites in northern Colombia during southward migration. Variables include days since first capture (I), date (D), initial body mass (CI), and hour of capture (H). Models that received the best support from AIC are highlighted in bold for each species and site.Capture&ndash;recapture models evaluated in order to estimate stopover duration for 3 <italic>Catharus</italic> species on migration at 2 sites in northern Colombia. Models that received the greatest support from AIC are highlighted in bold.