Feather corticosterone levels independent of developmental immune challenges predict carotenoid-based, but not melanin-based, traits at adulthoodThe kinetics of hemopexin and &alpha;1-acid glycoprotein levels induced by injection of inflammatory agents in chickensMaternal corticosterone is transferred into the egg yolkParental investment and its sensitivity to corticosterone is linked to melanin-based coloration in Barn OwlsColoration signals the ability to cope with elevated stress hormones: Effects of corticosterone on growth of Barn Owls are associated with melanismAn experimental test of the dose-dependent effect of carotenoids and immune activation on sexual signals and antioxidant activityInteractions of corticosterone with feeding, activity and metabolism in passerine birdsStress and virulence: West Nile virus encephalitisWing whiteness as an indicator of age, immunocompetence, and testis size in the Eurasian Black-billed Magpie (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pica pica</named-content></italic>)Stress response during development predicts fitness in a wild, long lived vertebrateDo baseline glucocorticoids predict fitness?Corticosterone in feathers is a long-term, integrated measure of avian stress physiologyPhysiological stress mediates the honesty of social signalsSong as an honest signal of past developmental stress in the European Starling (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>)Effects of small increases in corticosterone levels on morphology, immune function, and feather developmentDevelopmental immune history affects adult immune function but not carotenoid-based ornamentation in Mallard ducksDifferential effects of early- and late-life access to carotenoids on adult immune function and ornamentation in Mallard ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>)How many color metrics do we need? Evaluating how different color-scoring procedures explain carotenoid pigment content in avian bare-part and plumage ornamentsOntogenetic immune challenges shape adult personality in Mallard ducksEndocrinology of the stress responsePhysiological regulatory networks: Ecological roles and evolutionary constraintsEffects of corticosteroids on oxidative damage and circulating carotenoids in captive adult kestrels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Falco tinnunculus</named-content></italic>)Carotenoid-based coloration, oxidative stress and corticosterone in common lizardsCorticosterone exposure during development has sustained but not lifelong effects on body size and total and free corticosterone responses in the Zebra FinchCorticosterone exposure during development improves performance on a novel foraging task in Zebra FinchesExogenous and endogenous corticosterone alter feather qualityEffects of stress on immune cell distribution: Dynamics and hormonal mechanismsMallard (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>)Pleiotropy in the melanocortin system, coloration and behavioural syndromesHormones, developmental plasticity and adaptationSlight differences in incubation temperature affect early growth and stress endocrinology of Wood Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>) ducklingsIncubation temperature affects multiple measures of immunocompetence in young Wood Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>)Synchronizing feather-based measures of corticosterone and carotenoid-dependent signals: What relationships do we expect?Experimental relationships between plasma- and feather-levels of corticosterone in a free-living birdFeather corticosterone of a nestling seabird reveals consequences of sex-specific parental investmentNestling corticosterone response to microclimate in an altricial birdImmune activation rapidly mirrored in a secondary sexual traitMelanin concentration gradients in modern and fossil feathersGlucocorticoid effects on natural and humoral immunity in MallardsImmune challenge mediates vocal communication in a passerine bird: An experimentSynergistic and antagonistic interaction between different branches of the immune system is related to melanin-based coloration in nestling Tawny OwlsMaternal investment of female Mallards is influenced by male carotenoid-based colorationEffects of carotenoid and vitamin E supplementation on oxidative stress and plumage coloration in House Finches (<italic>Haemorhous mexicanus</italic>)Habitat quality affects early physiology and subsequent neuromotor development of juvenile Black-capped ChickadeesMaternal antibodies reduce costs of an immune response during developmentStructural coloration signals condition, parental investment, and circulating hormone levels in Eastern bluebirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia sialis</named-content></italic>)Pigment-specific relationships between feather corticosterone concentrations and sexual colorationInfluences of sex, castration, and androgens on the eumelanin and pheomelanin contents of different feathers in wild MallardsCosts of an immune challenge and terminal investment in a long-lived birdA label of health: A previous immune challenge is reflected in the expression of a female plumage traitEffects of ectoparasites on seasonal variation in quality of nestling Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)Ultraviolet crown coloration in female Blue Tits predicts reproductive success and baseline corticosteroneDexamethasone inhibits corticosterone deposition in feathers of greenfinchesAntioxidant protection, carotenoids and the costs of immune challenge in greenfinchesExperimentally activated immune defence in female Pied Flycatchers results in reduced breeding successSignaling stress? An analysis of phaeomelanin-based plumage color and individual corticosterone levels at two temporal scales in North American Barn Swallows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content> erythrogaster</italic>Corticosterone: Effects on feather quality and deposition into feathersCarotenoid-based ornaments of female and male American Goldfinches (<italic>Spinus tristis</italic>) show sex-specific correlations with immune function and metabolic rateFeather coloration in museum specimens is related to feather corticosteroneBenefits and costs of increased levels of corticosterone in seabird chicksCorticosterone facilitates begging and affects resource allocation in the Black-legged KittiwakeMoult and basal metabolic costs in males of two subspecies of stonechats: The European <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Saxicola torquata</named-content> rubicula</italic> and the East African <italic>S. t. axillaris</italic>Does feather corticosterone reflect individual quality or external stress in Arctic-nesting migratory birds?Condition dependence of iridescent wing flash-marks in two species of dabbling ducksCarotenoid-based plumage coloration reflects feather corticosterone levels in male House Finches (<italic>Haemorhous mexicanus</italic>)Unrepeatable repeatabilities: A common mistakeThe energetic cost of feather synthesis is proportional to basal metabolic rateEarly development and fitness in birds and mammalsCondition-dependent effects of corticosterone on a carotenoid-based begging signal in House SparrowsEffects of experimental increase of corticosterone levels on begging behavior, immunity and parental provisioning rate in House SparrowsMaternal adversity and ecological stressors in natural populations: The role of stress axis programming in individuals, with implications for populations and communitiesPlasticity in the adrenocortical response of a free-living vertebrate: The role of pre- and post-natal developmental stressCorticosterone suppresses cutaneous immune function in temperate but not tropical House Sparrows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>Feather corticosterone levels and carotenoid-based coloration in Common Buzzard (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo buteo</named-content></italic>) nestlingsThe effect of capture-and-handling stress on carotenoid-based beak coloration in Zebra FinchesCarotenoid accumulation in the tissues of Zebra Finches: Predictors of integumentary pigmentation and implications for carotenoid allocation strategiesA quantitative comparison of the commonly used methods for extracting carotenoids from avian plasmaQuantifying iridescent coloration in animals: A method for improving repeatabilityCompensation for a bad start: Grow now, pay later?Melanin-based coloration covaries with fluctuating asymmetry, nutritional state and physiological stress response in Common SnipeEarly growth conditions, phenotypic development and environmental changePhysiological stress links parasites to carotenoid-based colour signalsFat stores in birds: An overlooked sink for carotenoid pigments?Song learning, early nutrition and sexual selection in songbirdsBrain development, song learning and mate choice in birds: A review and experimental test of the &ldquo;nutritional stress hypothesis.&rdquo;Female Mallard mating preferences for multiple male ornaments. II. Experimental variationImmune challenge affects basal metabolic activity in wintering Great TitsWithin seasons and among years: When are corticosterone levels repeatable?How stress influences the immune responseTrade-offs between immune investment and sexual signaling in male MallardsLinear social dominance hierarchy and corticosterone responses in male Mallards and pintailsWithin-brood social status and consequences for winter hierarchies amongst Mallard <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> ducklingsEffects of nutritional restrictions during post-hatching development on adrenocortical function in Western Scrub-Jays (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aphelocoma californica</named-content></italic>)Begging and provisioning of Thin-billed Prions, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pachyptila belcheri</named-content></italic>, are related to testosterone and corticosteroneSex-related effects of an immune challenge on growth and begging behavior of Barn Swallow nestlingsCorticosterone inhibits feather growth: Potential mechanism explaining seasonal down regulation of corticosterone during moltCorticosterone mediates the condition-dependent component of melanin-based colorationImmune and stress responses covary with melanin-based coloration in the Barn SwallowCorticosterone regulates multiple colour traits in <italic>Lacerta</italic> &lsqb;<italic>Zootoca</italic>&rsqb; <italic>vivipara</italic> malesHow do glucocorticoids influence stress responses? Integrating permissive, suppressive, stimulatory, and preparative actionsRegulation of the HPA axis is related to song complexity and measures of phenotypic quality in Song SparrowsShort-and long-term effects of developmental corticosterone exposure on avian physiology, behavioral phenotype, cognition, and fitness: A reviewEffects of thyroid status on arginine vasotocin receptor VT2R expression and adrenal function in osmotically stimulated domestic fowlReproductive effort and success of wild female Mallards: Does male quality matter?Nitric oxide production: An easily measurable condition index for vertebratesWhat does carotenoid-dependent coloration tell? Plasma carotenoid level signals immunocompetence and oxidative stress state in birds&mdash;A meta-analysisSimplifying the phytohaemagglutinin skin-testing technique in studies of avian immunocompetenceSong as an honest signal of developmental stress in the Zebra Finch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>)Postnatal stress in birds: A novel model of glucocorticoid programming of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axisIndicators of development as sexually selected traits: The developmental stress hypothesis in contextDelayed behavioral effects of postnatal exposure to corticosterone in the Zebra Finch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>)Post-natal exposure to corticosterone affects standard metabolic rate in the Zebra Finch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>)Glucocorticoids and insulin: Reciprocal signals for energy-balanceEnhanced male coloration after immune challenge increases reproductive potentialThe condition dependence of a secondary sexual trait is stronger under high parasite infection levelAn integrative view of the signaling phenotype: Dynamic links between signals, physiology, behavior and social contextOntogeny and individual variation in the adrenocortical response of Zebra Finch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>) nestlingsCurrent address: Department of Veterinary Pathology, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, CanadaConditions during development, including nutrition and immune challenges, can have long-lasting effects on subsequent physiological parameters. Many of these organizational effects are mediated by hormones, including corticosterone (CORT), a hormone involved in nutrient mobilization, immune response modulation, and responses to stressors. While the effects of exogenous CORT during development on later-life physiology have demonstrated the important role this hormone plays in developmental plasticity, relatively less attention has been paid to other factors capable of driving a CORT-mediated cascade of phenotypic effects. We tested the effect of nonpathogenic immune challenges during different stages of development and used levels of CORT in feathers (CORT<sub>f</sub>) to investigate whether CORT levels during development (when the feathers were grown) could predict variation in traits at adulthood. Mallards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>) exhibit a variety of traits as adults that could be influenced by CORT, including a carotenoid-pigmented beak used in mate choice and melanin-based patterning in the speculum of the wing that has no known signaling function. We found that nonpathogenic immune challenges during development had no detectable effects on duckling CORT<sub>f</sub>, which suggests that more robust immune challenges are required to create a sustained increase in circulating CORT levels. However, duckling CORT<sub>f</sub> predicted multiple traits at adulthood: higher levels of CORT<sub>f</sub> were associated with increases in circulating carotenoid levels, degree of carotenoid-based beak coloration, and mass gain. We failed to demonstrate a link between melanin-based speculum patterning and CORT at time of trait development, although speculum patterning was both affected by immune challenge treatment and correlated with adult immune function. These results support the &ldquo;quality hypothesis,&rdquo; which states that variation in CORT could be positively correlated with traits reflecting individual quality under certain conditions, and also suggest that the speculum in Mallards may be able to serve as an honest signal.Las condiciones durante el desarrollo, incluyendo la nutrici&oacute;n y los desaf&iacute;os inmunol&oacute;gicos, pueden tener efectos de larga duraci&oacute;n en par&aacute;metros fisiol&oacute;gicos subsecuentes. Muchos de estos efectos organizacionales est&aacute;n mediados por hormonas, incluyendo la corticosterona (CORT), una hormona involucrada en la movilizaci&oacute;n de nutrientes, la modulaci&oacute;n de la actividad inmune y la respuesta a agentes de estr&eacute;s. Mientras que los efectos de la exposici&oacute;n a la CORT ex&oacute;gena durante el desarrollo sobre la fisiolog&iacute;a de etapas de vida posteriores han demostrado el importante papel que cumple esta hormona en la plasticidad fenot&iacute;pica, se ha prestado relativamente poca atenci&oacute;n a otros factores capaces de producir una cascada de efectos mediados por la CORT. En este estudio evaluamos los efectos de desaf&iacute;os inmunol&oacute;gicos no patog&eacute;nicos durante diferentes etapas del desarrollo y usamos niveles de CORT en las plumas (CORT<sub>f</sub>) para investigar si los niveles de CORT durante el desarrollo (durante el crecimiento de las plumas) podr&iacute;an predecir variaci&oacute;n de rasgos en la adultez. Los adultos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> exhiben una variedad de rasgos que podr&iacute;an verse influenciados por la CORT, incluyendo un pico con pigmentos carotenoides usado en escogencia de pareja y un patr&oacute;n en el esp&eacute;culo del ala basado en melaninas de funci&oacute;n desconocida. Encontramos que los desaf&iacute;os inmunol&oacute;gicos no patog&eacute;nicos durante el desarrollo no tuvieron efectos detectables en la CORT<sub>f</sub> de los polluelos, lo que sugiere que se requieren desaf&iacute;os inmunes m&aacute;s robustos para crear un incremento sostenido en los niveles de CORT circulante. Sin embargo, la CORT<sub>f</sub> de los polluelos predijo m&uacute;ltiples rasgos en los adultos: mayores niveles de CORT<sub>f</sub> se asociaron con incrementos en los niveles de carotenoides, el grado de la coloraci&oacute;n del pico basada en carotenoides y la ganancia de peso. No pudimos demostrar una relaci&oacute;n entre el patr&oacute;n basado en melanina del esp&eacute;culo y la CORT durante el desarrollo del rasgo, aunque el patr&oacute;n del esp&eacute;culo s&iacute; fue afectado por el tratamiento de desaf&iacute;o inmunol&oacute;gico y se correlacion&oacute; con la funci&oacute;n inmune de los adultos. Estos resultados apoyan la hip&oacute;tesis de calidad, que establece que la variaci&oacute;n en CORT podr&iacute;a estar positivamente correlacionada con la calidad de los individuos bajo ciertas condiciones. Los resultados tambi&eacute;n sugieren que el esp&eacute;culo en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. platyrhynchos</named-content></italic> podr&iacute;a servir como una se&ntilde;al honesta.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> Coloraci&oacute;n estructural, coloraci&oacute;n mel&aacute;nica, condiciones durante la vida temprana, esp&eacute;culo, hormonas glucocorticoides, ornamentaci&oacute;n con carotenoides, plasticidad durante el desarrollo, se&ntilde;ales honestas.Conditions during early life can have profound effects on the developmental trajectory of animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Metcalfe1">Metcalfe and Monaghan 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Monaghan1">Monaghan 2008</xref>). This phenotypic variation is frequently produced via the actions of hormones, because hormones can alter cellular or physiological processes in response to environmental information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Nelson1">Nelson 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Dufty1">Dufty et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Monaghan1">Monaghan 2008</xref>). A diverse suite of environmental cues can be described as harmful or unpredictable perturbations (i.e. stressors), and the hormonal responses to these stressors are particularly important during development because they can exert strong organizational influences on physiology, behavior, and fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lindstrom2">Lindstr&ouml;m 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Blas1">Blas et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer3">Spencer and MacDougall-Shackleton 2011</xref>). Specifically, early-life activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, resulting in the subsequent release of glucocorticoid (GC) hormones, affects early-life energy management that can create trade-offs responsible for producing later-life phenotypic variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer4">Spencer and Verhulst 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Monaghan1">Monaghan 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer2">Spencer et al. 2009</xref>).The actions of GCs such as corticosterone (CORT), the primary avian GC, can be adaptive by modulating physiology and behavior to cope with stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sapolsky1">Sapolsky et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Charmandari1">Charmandari et al. 2005</xref>). For example, in nestling birds, food limitation increases levels of CORT, which triggers begging behavior that increases parental provisioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Kitaysky2">Kitaysky et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Quillfeldt1">Quillfeldt et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau2">Loiseau et al. 2008b</xref>). However, sustained elevated levels of CORT during development can affect metabolism, size, and cognitive ability in the short term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Kitaysky1">Kitaysky et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer4">Spencer and Verhulst 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer5">2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau1">Loiseau et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Crino2">Crino et al. 2014b</xref>) and can also drive variation in exploration and incubation behaviors, body size, and HPA axis activation weeks to months later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer1">Spencer et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer2">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Pravosudov1">Pravosudov and Kitaysky 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler1">Butler et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Almasi1">Almasi et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Love1">Love et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Crino1">Crino et al. 2014a</xref>). Thus, responses to stressors during early life, via actions of CORT, may be adaptive in confronting a current stressor, but may also affect multiple phenotypic traits throughout development and into adulthood.These persistent, pleiotropic effects of CORT have been recognized and put into broader frameworks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer3">Spencer and MacDougall-Shackleton 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Cohen1">Cohen et al. 2012</xref>), including investigations of CORT's role in the development of sexually selected traits. The &ldquo;developmental stress hypothesis&rdquo; formalized this thinking, demonstrating that physiological responses to conditions during development can affect both the ornamentation and quality of the individual at adulthood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Nowicki1">Nowicki et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer3">Spencer and MacDougall-Shackleton 2011</xref>). The majority of this work has focused on bird song (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Nowicki2">Nowicki et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Buchanan1">Buchanan et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer1">Spencer et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer3">Spencer and MacDougall-Shackleton 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Schmidt1">Schmidt et al. 2012</xref>), but several lines of evidence suggest that the pleiotropic effects of CORT may also be involved in the production of visual signaling systems because CORT can directly affect the expression of both melanin- and carotenoid-based traits, which are the two most common classes of pigment-based signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Hill1">Hill and McGraw 2006</xref>).Elevated CORT during development can inhibit melanogenesis in feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Roulin1">Roulin et al. 2008</xref>), and darker melanin-based plumage traits can signal resistance to stress (i.e. reduced CORT secretion) in nestlings and adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Almasi2">Almasi et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Almasi3">2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ducrest1">Ducrest et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Minias1">Minias et al. 2014</xref>). The effect of CORT on development of carotenoid-based traits is more context dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau1">Loiseau et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Cote1">Cote et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>), with evidence of both negative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau1">Loiseau et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-MartinezPadilla1">Mart&iacute;nez-Padilla et al. 2013</xref>) and positive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lendvai1">Lendvai et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-MartinezPadilla1">Mart&iacute;nez-Padilla et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>) associations between CORT and carotenoid-based signals. Importantly, both classes of pigments can be affected simultaneously. For example, administration of CORT affects both melanin- and carotenoid-based skin coloration in common lizards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zootoca vivipara</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-SanJose1">San-Jose and Fitze 2013</xref>). CORT can also influence the quality of feather structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Romero1">Romero et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-DesRochers1">DesRochers et al. 2009</xref>), affecting the expression of both carotenoid-pigmented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Kennedy1">Kennedy et al. 2013</xref>) and structurally colored plumage traits used for signaling adult quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Grindstaff2">Grindstaff et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Henderson1">Henderson et al. 2013</xref>).The honesty of such CORT-dependent visual signals may be related to variation in immune response. Immune function is frequently correlated with degree of coloration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Kelly1">Kelly et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Simons1">Simons et al. 2012</xref>), and CORT and other GCs can influence immune function and reduce resistance to disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fowles1">Fowles et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Dhabhar1">Dhabhar et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sapolsky1">Sapolsky et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Padgett1">Padgett and Glaser 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Martin1">Martin et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-BenNathan1">Ben-Nathan 2013</xref>). Moreover, even relatively small increases in CORT in nestlings can produce downstream effects on immune response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler1">Butler et al. 2010</xref>). This interdependency between CORT, immune function, and coloration is found in multiple contexts, with CORT mediating how parasites affect expression of carotenoid-based coloration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Bortolotti2">Bortolotti et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Mougeot1">Mougeot et al. 2010</xref>) and amount of eumelanin corresponding to immune response and activation of the HPA axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Saino1">Saino et al. 2013</xref>). Indeed, these observations have led some authors to suggest that the effects of CORT on immune response could also involve effects on coloration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau2">Loiseau et al. 2008b</xref>).Although the above evidence is suggestive, our understanding of potential pleiotropic effects of CORT is limited because the CORT&ndash;immune signaling nexus is complex. Studies have addressed 1 or 2 of these factors simultaneously (e.g., environmental conditions during embryonic development can program both CORT and immune responses in ducklings; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-DuRant1">DuRant et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-DuRant2">2012</xref>), but few have integrated the relationships among CORT, coloration, and immune response and considered both short- and long-term consequences. Here, we focus on immune challenges during development as a stressor because they can have consequences for immune response in adulthood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Jenkins1">Jenkins et al. 2013</xref>), and we suggest that such challenges are themselves stressors capable of activating the HPA axis. Previous work has investigated this idea in the context of infection, focusing on harmful stressors such as parasites and diseases (see above). However, factors that elicit an immune response but are otherwise not harmful offer an alternative perspective because they can provide insight into activation of the immune response without the physiological costs of coping with an ongoing infection. Immune challenges can have important consequences for the development and expression of phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Garamszegi1">Garamszegi et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Grindstaff1">Grindstaff 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Hanssen2">Hanssen et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Romano1">Romano et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler5">Butler et al. 2012</xref>), particularly traits used in signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Faivre1">Faivre et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-AlonsoAlvarez1">Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Peters1">Peters et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Velando1">Velando et al. 2014</xref>), and immune activation in the absence of infection can have physiological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ots1">Ots et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Horak2">H&otilde;rak et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>) and fitness costs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ilmonen1">Ilmonen et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Hanssen1">Hanssen 2006</xref>). Yet, despite the importance of physiological context to the development of signaling phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Vitousek1">Vitousek et al. 2014</xref>), CORT levels are rarely considered in studies linking immune challenges to expression of phenotypic traits, so the role of the HPA axis in mediating such effects remains poorly understood.We hypothesized that if noninfectious early-life immune challenges activate the HPA axis during development, (1) this could have simultaneous organizational effects on both immune function and coloration, due to the pleiotropic effects characteristic of CORT exposure; and (2) these effects occur both in the short term and during adulthood. We experimentally tested this hypothesis using captive male Mallard (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>) ducklings because they develop 3 colorful patches at different times in their development: Melanin-based (i.e. pattering and black banding) and structurally based (iridescent) traits form in speculum feathers grown during development, and a carotenoid-based trait (bill color) is expressed at maturity. Using the same ducklings from a previous experiment that addressed the effect of noninfectious early-life immune challenges on immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>), here we additionally consider the role of CORT and effects on plumage. Our study had 5 main predictions. (1) We expected levels of corticosterone in feathers (CORT<sub>f</sub>), which reflect plasma CORT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Horak1">H&otilde;rak et al. 2013</xref>) and environmental variation experienced during early life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst3">Fairhurst et al. 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst4">2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Grava1">Grava et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Harriman1">Harriman et al. 2014</xref>), to be elevated in Mallards that were given a series of immune challenges during development (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>). Because we varied the timing of immune challenges, we further predicted that individuals receiving the challenges earliest would have the highest levels of CORT<sub>f</sub> because the developmental consequences of a stressor (i.e. increased sensitivity and prolonged responses of the HPA axis; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer2">Spencer et al. 2009</xref>) would be most pronounced in the youngest birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lindstrom2">Lindstr&ouml;m 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Dufty1">Dufty et al. 2002</xref>). Assuming that higher CORT<sub>f</sub> reflects increased sensitivity to stress or cumulative energetic costs of responding to stressors, we expected higher CORT<sub>f</sub> to be associated with (2) reduced melanin-based and structurally based plumage traits formed during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ducrest1">Ducrest et al. 2008</xref>) and (3) reduced circulating carotenoid and carotenoid-based bill color as downstream developmental consequences (&ldquo;stress hypothesis&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>). Alternatively, if increased CORT<sub>f</sub> is more closely linked to individual quality than immune-challenge treatment (&ldquo;quality hypothesis&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Legagneux1">Legagneux et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Harms1">Harms et al. 2015</xref>), we expected positive relationships between CORT<sub>f</sub> and these phenotypic traits. (4) Because even small increases in CORT during early life can be detrimental to development of the immune system (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler1">Butler et al. 2010</xref>), we predicted that CORT<sub>f</sub> would negatively covary with measures of adult immune response (i.e. at the end of the experiment). Finally, we explored the consistency of development of plumage traits and adult immune response and expected (5) that they would positively covary, as an expression of individual quality.The specific husbandry, experimental design, and methodology of blood collection and immune-function quantification for these individuals have been described in detail elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>); here, we provide a brief summary. We acquired 1-day-old male ducklings (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 48) from Metzer Farms (Gonzales, California, USA) in December 2008; they were housed together, provided food ab libitum, and randomly assigned to 1 of 4 treatment groups based on the developmental stage at which injections were administered. Individuals in experimental groups received 1 injection of nonpathogenic sheep red blood cells (SRBC) each week for 3 consecutive weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Individuals in the Early group (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 11) received injections at 3, 4, and 5 wk old, which is the period of maximum growth. Middle-group individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 12) received injections at 8, 9, and 10 wk old, which is when growth is complete and speculum feathers finish developing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Drilling1">Drilling et al. 2002</xref>). Late-group individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 12) received injections at 13, 14, and 15 wk old, which is when individuals finish molting into nuptial plumage. Control-group individuals (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 11) did not receive injections at any point during development (to avoid inadvertently eliciting an immune response; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Adler1">Adler et al. 2001</xref>). Sample sizes reflect feathers available for analysis.Timeline of immune-challenge treatment and sample collection. Individuals received immune challenges weekly for 3 weeks during either the Early, Middle, or Late treatment periods or were not challenged at all (Control). Whole blood (for determining circulating carotenoid concentration) and mass were collected prior to the Early treatment period and at the conclusion of the Adult assessment period (A). At the beginning of the Adult assessment period (B), we quantified beak coloration and circulating IgG for all individuals and initiated the PHA-induced wing-web swelling assay (additional sample collected 24 hr later), nitric oxide quantification (additional sample collected 24 hr later), and KLH-specific antibody production (additional samples collected 6 and 10 days later for primary and secondary responses, respectively). Speculum feathers used for the assessment of melanin-based patterning and corticosterone grew during the Middle period and were collected at the end of the experiment (C).We collected ~300 &mu;L of whole blood using heparinized capillary tubes from all individuals at the beginning (week 1) and end (week 19) of the experiment by puncturing the alar vein. Whole blood was stored on ice for several hours and then centrifuged for 3 min at 10,000 rpm. We then pipetted plasma into separate microtubes for assessment of carotenoid content and stored the plasma at &minus;80&deg;C until analysis. At each time of blood collection, we also measured the body mass of each bird to the nearest gram to test whether immune challenges affected growth. To analyze plasma carotenoid content (prior to any adult immune metric assessment), we followed the hexane:methyl tert-butyl ether extraction method and high-performance liquid chromatography procedures of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-McGraw3">McGraw et al. (2008)</xref>.When ducks were 18 wk old, we administered a 24-hr PHA wing-web swelling test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Smits1">Smits et al. 1999</xref>), with wing-web thickness measured pre-challenge and 24 hr later, and also quantified nitric oxide response (a pro-oxidant that is part of the innate immune response; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sild1">Sild and H&otilde;rak 2009</xref>) from plasma collected at the time of both wing-web thickness measurements. Nitric oxide concentration was determined using the copper-reduction, Greiss-coloration method first described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sild1">Sild and H&otilde;rak (2009)</xref>. Concurrently (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f01">Figure 1</xref>), we also quantified circulating immunoglobulin (IgG) levels by performing an enzyme-linked immunosorbant assay (ELISA) in 96-well plates using an avian IgG-specific secondary antibody (A140-110A; Bethyl Laboratories, Montgomery, Texas, USA) that undergoes a colorimetric reaction. To further assess adult immune function, we quantified humoral immunity, or antibody production to a novel antigen, by quantifying individual humoral response to keyhole limpet hemocyanin, a nonpathogenic foreign protein. We then calculated antibody response to this specific antigen, using an ELISA similar to the circulating IgG ELISA described above, but after coating the wells with keyhole limpet hemocyanin. For specific details of these assays, please see Butler and McGraw (2012).Ornamental beak coloration in Mallards begins to develop by 10 wk of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Drilling1">Drilling et al. 2002</xref>) and is completed in all birds by 16 wk (M. W. Butler personal observation; J. Metzer personal communication). When we collected blood for adult immune assessments (see above), we measured carotenoid-based beak coloration of adults using an Ocean Optics (Dunedin, Florida, USA) USB2000 spectrophotometer with a PX-2 pulsed xenon light source to measure reflectance from &lambda; &equals; 300&ndash;700 nm. We measured a 1-cm band of the right dorsolateral surface of the beak between the nares and the beak tip and binned all measurements into 1-nm increments using CLRfiles (CLR version 1.05; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Montgomerie1">Montgomerie 2008</xref>). We then used CLRvars in CLR to calculate the brightness, saturation, and hue scores that are, respectively, correlated negatively, negatively, and positively with carotenoid content in the Mallard beak (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler5">Butler et al. 2012</xref>).Speculum feathers, grown at 8&ndash;10 wk of age, were collected at the end of the experiment for assessment of plumage traits. We cut the fifth secondary on the left wing and placed it in a white envelope until analysis. Samples were taped to black cardstock and analyzed as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Meadows1">Meadows et al. (2011)</xref> using a USB2000 spectrophotometer and PX-2 xenon light source (Ocean Optics, Dunedin, Florida, USA) that had an independently rotating sample stage, light-source fiber-optic cable, and light-collection fiber-optic cable. The angle between the 2 fiber-optic cables was 45&deg;, and the angle of the sample was rotated until the position at which the maximal amount of light was collected (i.e. the sample was at its brightest). The angle at which the sample was positioned was recorded, and then the angle was rotated by 5&deg; away from this maximal brightness to generate a second reflectance curve. We did this because the speculum feathers are iridescent, and changes in hue occur with a change in light geometry. We repeated this process twice more at different spots on the feather, yielding 3 measurements per feather at both maximal reflectance (max) and 5&deg; off of maximal reflectance (off). Spectral curves were converted to hue, brightness, and saturation values using CLR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Montgomerie1">Montgomerie 2008</xref>). Brightness, hue, and 2 metrics of saturation based on the relative reflectance in the blue (400&ndash;510 nm) and ultraviolet (300&ndash;400 nm) were all significantly repeatable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lessells1">Lessells and Boag 1987</xref>) within each feather (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; 0.73 &lt; <italic>r</italic> &lt; 0.81), so average values were used for all subsequent analyses.We analyzed speculum feather patterns (using Adobe Photoshop CS version 5.1) from photos taken with a Nikon D70 camera under standardized lighting conditions against a gray photo board. All photos were taken with the feather in 2 different orientations to account for any differences driven by the iridescent nature of the blue component of the feather. We quantified the area of the terminal white patch on the visible side of the feather (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f02">Figure 2</xref>) using the magnetic lasso tool, and measured its width along the rachis using the ruler tool. Similarly, we quantified the area and width of the black subterminal band on the other side of the feather (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Because we noticed interindividual differences in the size of the white area on either side of the rachis, we also quantified width of the white band on the side of the feather not visible when the bird is exhibiting normal feather positioning. Each photo was measured in triplicate by 3 individuals, with the exception of the metric capturing the white width on the nonvisible side of the feather; this metric was measured in duplicate by 1 individual. All measurements were significantly repeatable (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t01">Table 1</xref>).Diagram of Mallard secondary (speculum) feather, showing metrics of melanin-based pattern analyzed. Red dashed line indicates the area of the white patch on the visible side of the speculum; green dashed line shows the area of the black patch. Linear portions along the rachis indicate the widths of each of these patches. Double-arrowed line shows the width of the white area on the opposite (covered) side.Repeatability of multiple measurements of male Mallard feather-pattern metrics. The relatively poor repeatability of width of black band was likely driven by a poor resolution of where the black section ended and the iridescent blue section began in different orientations.Following assessment of coloration and patterning, we extracted and analyzed CORT from the same speculum feathers, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti et al. (2008)</xref>. The length of each feather (proximal calamus to distal tip of vane) was measured flat against the edge of a ruler after removal of the calamus. Feather samples were then placed in glass vials, cut into tiny pieces (~5 mm<sup>2</sup>), and 10 mL of methanol (HPLC grade; Fisher Scientific, Fair Lawn, New Jersey, USA) was added to each vial. Samples were placed in a sonicating water bath at room temperature for 30 min, followed by incubation overnight at 50&deg;C. Using a glass funnel fitted with polyester fiber and vacuum filtration, the methanol extract was separated from the feather pieces, and the collected methanol extract was then evaporated. Extract residues were reconstituted in 600 &mu;L of phosphate buffered saline (0.05 M, pH 7.6) and frozen at &minus;20&deg;C until analyzed by radioimmunoassay. All samples were extracted in a single batch. We assessed the recovery efficiency of the extraction by spiking 3 additional feather samples with ~5,000 cpm of <sup>3</sup>H-labeled CORT prior to overnight incubation and subsequent filtering (same as sample extracts). Average recovery was 85&percnt; (SD &equals; 0.4&percnt;) and, while we acknowledge that our approach of correcting by an average recovery does not account for interindividual variation in CORT<sub>f</sub> recovery, the very low variability in our recovery samples gives us confidence that interindividual variation in recovery was minimal. Samples were analyzed in duplicate in a single assay using a commercial antiserum (product C8784, lot 081M4788; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, USA). Serial dilutions of feather extracts produced displacement curves that were parallel to the CORT standard curve. We assessed assay variability using 6 replicates of an internal standard, and the intra-assay coefficient of variation (CV) was 10&percnt;. Average detection limit (&percnt;B/B<sub>0</sub>) was 17.26 pg/100 &mu;L of extract, and all samples were above this limit. CORT<sub>f</sub> measurements were corrected for total feather length, expressed as pg CORT/mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti et al. 2008</xref>).To address prediction 1, we compared average CORT<sub>f</sub> values among Early, Middle, Late, and Control treatment groups using a general linear model (GLM; SAS version 9.2). Because feathers were grown prior to administration of immune challenge in the Late group, we combined Late and Control groups in a second model, comparing CORT<sub>f</sub> values among 3 resulting treatment groups.To address predictions 2, 3, and 4, we used GLMs to model how the independent variables CORT<sub>f</sub>, treatment, and their interaction predicted variation in each of the plumage traits, measures of carotenoid-based traits and immune responses, and body mass and mass of testes as separate dependent variables. For analyses of plumage traits, we again used a Late/Control group because feathers were grown prior to administration of immune challenge, but 4 treatment groups (Early, Middle, Late, and Control) were used for all models of carotenoid, immune responses, mass, and testis size as these phenotypic characters were quantified at adulthood. Nonsignificant terms (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.10) were removed from final models, but CORT<sub>f</sub> was always retained. Significant treatment effects were investigated using post hoc comparisons and assessed against Tukey-Kramer adjusted <italic>P</italic> values. CORT<sub>f</sub> values were log transformed to meet assumptions of normality. Transformations applied to response variables are reported with model results. Unlike relationships with CORT, which could have direct (causal) consequences for development of immune responses, it seems very unlikely that plumage traits formed during development could themselves directly influence subsequent adult immune response. Therefore, to address prediction 5, we used Pearson correlations.CORT<sub>f</sub> did not differ among treatment groups, regardless of whether all groups were analyzed separately (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.99, df &equals; 3 and 42, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.41) or Late and Control groups were combined (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.72, df &equals; 2 and 43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49). No measure of speculum feather color (all <italic>F</italic> &lt; 1.04, df &equals; 1 and 44, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.3) or patterning (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t02">Table 2</xref>) was related to CORT<sub>f</sub>, and treatment did not affect any measure of feather color (all <italic>F</italic> &lt; 0.65, df &equals; 2 and 42, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.5). However, Mallards that received immune challenges during the middle of development grew speculum feathers with significantly shorter, and thus smaller, black subterminal bands than birds in other groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t02">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f03">Figure 3</xref>).Results of general linear models analyzing the relationships between the pattern of male Mallard secondary (speculum) feathers and corticosterone from the same feathers (CORT<sub>f</sub>). See text for definitions of treatments. Significant results are in bold.Average width of the black band on male Mallard speculum feathers in relation to when immune challenges were administered. Asterisk denotes significant difference at <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01.Similar to when CORT<sub>f</sub> was not an explanatory variable (Butler and McGraw 2012), treatment did not affect any measure of carotenoid beak color or levels of circulating carotenoids (all <italic>F</italic> &lt; 2.11, df &equals; 2 and 42, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.11). By contrast, CORT<sub>f</sub> was positively correlated with the level of circulating carotenoid at week 19 (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 6.44, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01) and with both the absolute (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 7.19, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01) and percent (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 6.27, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02) increase in circulating carotenoid from week 1 to week 19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f04">Figure 4</xref>A). Additionally, CORT<sub>f</sub> was negatively correlated with saturation of the beak color in the blue range at adulthood (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 4.27, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f04">Figure 4</xref>B). However, CORT<sub>f</sub> was not correlated with circulating carotenoid levels during week 1 (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.49, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.49). No interaction terms between treatment and CORT<sub>f</sub> were statistically significant for beak coloration (all <italic>F</italic> &lt; 2.27, df &equals; 2 and 40, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.12) or circulating carotenoid levels (all <italic>F</italic> &lt; 1.02, df &equals; 3 and 38, all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.39).Relationships between corticosterone from secondary (speculum) feathers (CORT<sub>f</sub>; log transformed) of male Mallards and (<bold>A</bold>) change in circulating carotenoids from week 1 to week 19 of development (square-root transformed) and (<bold>B</bold>) saturation of beak color in the blue range at adulthood (square-root transformed; lower values are associated with greater carotenoid-based color). See text for definition of treatments. Feathers were grown during weeks 8&ndash;10.Of the 5 measures of adult immune response we analyzed, only circulating IgG at week 18 showed any relationship with CORT<sub>f</sub>, but this negative trend did not reach statistical significance (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 3.16, df &equals; 1 and 41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.08). Treatment significantly affected adult mass, nitric oxide response, and wing-web swelling (all <italic>F</italic> &gt; 2.99, df &equals; 1 and 41, all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.04), in accordance with results published previously when CORT<sub>f</sub> was not an explanatory variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler2">Butler and McGraw 2012a</xref>). Percent mass gain during development (weeks 1&ndash;19) was also positively related to CORT<sub>f</sub> (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 4.10, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f05">Figure 5</xref>), but we found no relationship between CORT<sub>f</sub> and body mass at week 1 (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.52, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22), body mass at week 19 (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.28, df &equals; 1 and 41, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.6), or testis mass (<italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.41, df &equals; 1 and 44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.5).Percent gain in mass (g) from week 1 to week 19 (adulthood) in male Mallards was positively related to the corticosterone in their secondary (speculum) feathers (CORT<sub>f</sub>). See text for definition of treatments. Feathers were grown during weeks 8&ndash;10.Correlations between plumage phenotype and adult immune metrics revealed strong positive relationships between PHA-induced swelling of the wing-web and both the width and area of the white terminal patch (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t03">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-f06">Figure 6</xref>). However, no relationship was detected between PHA-induced swelling and the width of the white area on the opposite (covered) side of the feather (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t03">Table 3</xref>), nor was any other immune metric related to plumage traits (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-t03">Table 3</xref>).Pearson correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) and associated <italic>P</italic> values among measures of secondary (speculum) feather color and pattern and immune response of adult male Mallards (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 46, except where noted). Significant results are in bold.Relationship between the area of the terminal white patch on the visible side of secondary (speculum) feathers from male Mallards and wing-web swelling in response to the PHA test at week 18 (adulthood). Pearson correlation: <italic>R</italic> &equals; 0.44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.002. See text for definition of treatments. Feathers were grown during weeks 8&ndash;10.Overall, there was no clear evidence of pleiotropic effects of increased CORT on immune function and coloration in Mallard ducklings as we predicted, but we did find that CORT was related to multiple phenotypic traits. We detected variation in CORT<sub>f</sub>, which indicates that the HPA axis was functional by the time the Middle treatment was administered (and feathers were grown), but this variation was apparently unrelated to the nonpathogenic immune challenge of SRBCs. Either the immune challenges did not elicit an HPA response, indicating that an immunological threshold exists for HPA activation or, more likely, the HPA response was too weak and/or brief for our feather-based measure of CORT to detect it. Variation in CORT<sub>f</sub> is driven by strong, sustained changes in HPA activity, and both baseline levels and acute responses to stressors correlate with CORT<sub>f</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. 2013</xref>), but the relative contributions of these plasma levels of CORT&mdash;and the relative influence of frequency, duration, and intensity of stressors&mdash;to the feather signal are not well understood. Thus, it is possible that our stressor was too weak to be detected using CORT<sub>f</sub>. Regardless, because treatment did not affect CORT<sub>f</sub>, a lack of relationships between CORT<sub>f</sub> and speculum feather color or pattern, and a weak correlation with only 1 of the adult immune metrics, might be expected. If the HPA axis was not activated strongly, CORT levels would have been insufficient to cause effects on phenotype at the time of development (i.e. plumage traits) or to have had persistent developmental effects on adult immune response. Thus, our lack of relationships points to the ineffectiveness of the immune challenge to trigger a sustained elevated CORT release. This negative result is important because it suggests that repeated noninfectious immune challenges capable of shaping the development of the immune response may not be experienced by the endocrine system as strong stressors. Future studies would benefit by measuring plasma CORT measurements at the time of immune challenge to better understand how the HPA axis responds to such weak immune challenges. Moreover, assessment of the melanin content of the speculum patterning is important for understanding our results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Field1">Field et al. 2013</xref>). Although traits that are predominantly eumelanin-based may be associated with CORT physiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ducrest1">Ducrest et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-JenniEiermann1">Jenni-Eiermann et al. 2015</xref>), recent studies have failed to find links between CORT levels during feather growth and pheomelanin-based feather color (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Jenkins1">Jenkins et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Grunst1">Grunst et al. 2015</xref>). Thus, a relative abundance of pheomelanin in speculum patterning may help explain our lack of relationships but, to our knowledge, has not been assessed in speculum feathers (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Haase1">Haase et al. 1995</xref>).Despite an absence of links between CORT<sub>f</sub> and melanin-based feather color and patterning, CORT<sub>f</sub> was related to the developmental trajectory of the birds, and particularly to their use of carotenoids. Interestingly, this result was independent of treatment. Although we cannot assign causation to CORT, greater mass gains, within-individual increases in circulating carotenoid levels, and carotenoid-based ornament expression (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler4">Butler et al. 2011</xref>) are consistent with the quality hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>) and suggest that birds expressing higher baseline CORT levels benefited phenotypically. This relationship between CORT and both mass gains and carotenoid-based traits may not be surprising, given that the birds were well fed and, presumably, in good condition (see below), and such conditions are believed to be a key underpinning of CORT's positive energetic effects on growth and carotenoid expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>; and see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Bonier1">Bonier et al. 2009</xref>). Yet, despite all individuals' presumed good condition and the lack of a treatment effect, CORT<sub>f</sub> was still related to multiple traits that can reflect quality. That we found a relationship with beak color is particularly important because in male Mallards this trait signals immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler3">Butler and McGraw 2012b</xref>) and influences female investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Giraudeau1">Giraudeau et al. 2011</xref>). Frequently, ornament expression is linked to physiological measures of individual quality by assessing immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Simons1">Simons et al. 2012</xref>), oxidative status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Simons1">Simons et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Giraudeau2">Giraudeau et al. 2013</xref>), or body condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Vergara1">Vergara et al. 2012</xref>). Our data, in conjunction with the quality hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>) and supported by studies in Zebra Finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Taeniopygia guttata</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2011</xref>) and Common Kestrels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Falco tinnunculus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Costantini1">Costantini et al. 2008</xref>), suggest that in birds that are able to cope well with energetic demands (e.g., ad libitum access to food), higher sustained levels of circulating CORT (both baseline and stress induced) may be another index of quality that is being directly signaled by enhanced carotenoid-pigmented ornamentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lendvai1">Lendvai et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Bortolotti2">Bortolotti et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Mougeot1">Mougeot et al. 2010</xref>). However, because we found links between CORT<sub>f</sub> and one index of quality (i.e. carotenoid-based traits) but not others (e.g., adult body mass, adult immune function), further investigation is needed to determine which types of quality-based traits are likely to be related to CORT.Further supporting the link between CORT and carotenoid physiology, our data are based on metrics collected at 2 different time points (during development and at adulthood), and CORT deposited in feathers midway through development predicted carotenoid-based traits several months later. There are 2 likely explanations for this temporal pattern. First, HPA activity during development, as revealed by CORT<sub>f</sub>, could have had direct organizational effects on carotenoid physiology via common dietary and metabolic pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Negro1">Negro et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-McGraw2">McGraw and Toomey 2010</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>), meaning that levels of CORT during development had long-lasting effects (e.g., on assimilation or transport of carotenoids). Alternatively, baseline CORT levels may have been temporally consistent among individuals during development (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Wada1">Wada et al. 2009</xref>), such that early-life CORT levels were correlated with HPA activity at adulthood (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Ouyang1">Ouyang et al. 2011</xref>). If so, variation in carotenoid-based traits at adulthood may be driven by concurrent variation in baseline CORT levels and reflected by CORT during development (i.e. CORT<sub>f</sub>). While the effects of exogenous CORT exposure during development on later-life HPA activity have been relatively well studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Love2">Love and Williams 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Spencer2">Spencer et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Schoech1">Schoech et al. 2011</xref>), our data suggest that natural variation (i.e. not experimentally induced) in HPA activity at multiple stages may provide insight into mechanisms driving both body growth and carotenoid-based coloration in adult animals. Although both these hypotheses are reasonable, the lack of a treatment effect on CORT<sub>f</sub> implies that CORT did not cause the relationships with carotenoids. Instead, CORT<sub>f</sub> could have been a proxy for an additional, unmeasured, metabolic or physiological variable that covaried with CORT (e.g., thyroid hormone; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sharma1">Sharma and Chaturvedi 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Scanes1">Scanes 2014</xref>). Future research will be necessary to elucidate the mechanism responsible for the covariation between CORT<sub>f</sub> and phenotype that we observed.We predicted that even small increases in CORT would result in a reduced immune function later in life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler1">Butler et al. 2010</xref>). Partially in line with this, CORT<sub>f</sub> correlated negatively with circulating IgG levels at adulthood, but only weakly. Our prediction was based on experimental manipulations of CORT levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau1">Loiseau et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Loiseau2">2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Butler1">Butler et al. 2010</xref>), but given the lack of a treatment effect on CORT<sub>f</sub>, it is likely that our metric of HPA activity reflected natural (i.e. unmanipulated) variation in baseline CORT levels, albeit in captive birds. Because we detected a (weak) correlation between CORT<sub>f</sub> and only one immune metric, our data suggest that, in contrast to increases in CORT due to exogenous hormone administration or stressors, natural variation in CORT early in life may be minimally informative regarding later-life immune function. However, conditions experienced during captivity bear limited resemblance to those experienced in the wild, so this hypothesis requires testing in free-living birds.The positive relationship between CORT<sub>f</sub> and mass gain are in contrast to previous findings in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. 2013</xref>), but there are several distinctions between these studies. First, and most importantly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. (2013)</xref> used implants to experimentally elevate baseline CORT for days, whereas our immune treatment apparently did not have the same strong effects. Sustained elevated CORT levels can drive adverse phenotypic effects such as reduced mass and body size, and both these were manifest in the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. (2013)</xref>. By contrast, Mallards in our study with relatively high CORT apparently benefited in mass gain. Second, our study was conducted in captivity, where food was administered ad libitum and stressors were minimal, but the birds studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst2">Fairhurst et al. (2013)</xref> were wild and likely contended with an unpredictable food supply and additional stressors (e.g., weather). Third, whereas developing altricial passerine young are more susceptible to the detrimental effects of sustained, elevated CORT, precocial Mallard ducklings may have more adult-like physiology, should be more tolerant of the negative effects of CORT, and thus may be more able to take advantage of the positive energetic effects of CORT. Hence, the comparatively low levels of CORT, benign environment, and high nutritional condition experienced by developing Mallards in our study may have simultaneously influenced how CORT affected developmental mass gain and contributed to the positive CORT&ndash;carotenoid relationships we detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Astheimer1">Astheimer et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Strack1">Strack et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Negro1">Negro et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Fairhurst1">Fairhurst et al. 2014</xref>).Despite no known signaling function of the speculum in Mallards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Omland1">Omland 1996</xref>), the early-life immune challenges we administered during speculum feather growth reduced melanin-based feather patterning. The reason why this particular trait was affected, and the mechanism responsible, remains unclear. Although feather growth is costly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Lindstrom1">Lindstr&ouml;m et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Klaassen1">Klaassen 1995</xref>), and the additional demands of immune challenges during this period may have accumulated to a point that patterning was affected, birds in our study had ad libitum access to food, which suggests that they were not energy limited. Whether similar effects would be seen in wild Mallards, and the fitness implications of variation in this trait, requires additional research. We also detected a strong positive correlation between the size of the white patch on the visible, but not the hidden, side of speculum feathers and PHA-induced swelling at adulthood, evidence that this speculum trait may signal immune responsiveness. Female Mallards select males on the basis of traits other than speculum feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Omland1">Omland 1996</xref>; for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Sheppard1">Sheppard et al. 2013</xref>), indicating that the speculum is not used in mate choice. However, previous work with wild and semicaptive Mallards has suggested that the speculum is correlated with condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Legagneux2">Legagneux et al. 2010</xref>), and our work supports the possibility of the speculum acting as an honest signal. Collectively, these observed links among developmental immune challenges, melanin-based feather patterning, and adult immune response (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Gasparini1">Gasparini et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Blanco1">Blanco and Fargallo 2013</xref>) suggest that it may be worthwhile to reexamine whether Mallard speculum feathers have a signaling function in contexts other than mate choice (e.g., dominance interactions; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Poisbleau1">Poisbleau et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Poisbleau2">2009</xref>), although more work remains to elucidate the mechanisms by which the honesty of these signals would be maintained.In conclusion, we detected links between the HPA axis and phenotype, but these were apparently unrelated to the consequences of early-life immune challenges. This finding of a lack of pleiotropic effects of CORT on the development of plumage traits is supported by recent work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Grunst1">Grunst et al. 2015</xref>), though our study is among the first to additionally consider immune response. Correlations between CORT<sub>f</sub> and developmental trajectory, particularly carotenoids, indicate that these traits could be linked, but not necessarily caused, by the dietary and metabolic effects of CORT. This also highlights the importance of considering multiple physiological measures when studying the development of signaling traits. Given the low-intensity immune challenge used in our study, future work would benefit from manipulating CORT directly and/or using a stronger, extended immune challenge with an increased likelihood of simultaneously stimulating the HPA axis and influencing the development of the immune system. Although the HPA axis operates within a greater physiological regulatory network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-863-Cohen1">Cohen et al. 2012</xref>), the links among CORT secretion, development of the immune system, and formation of melanin- and carotenoid-based traits remain unclear. Nevertheless, our results highlight the temporal scale over which the HPA axis may operate, and reveal a novel relationship between development immune challenges and the formation of a melanin-based feather trait.We thank M. Astor and S. Gleich for image analysis assistance, B. Bero-Buell for iridescence quantification, K. J. McGraw for input during execution of the experiment, S. and B. Butler for donating the camera, T. Marchant for allowing us to use her endocrine lab, and B. Clark and two anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Funding was provided to M.W.B. by Lafayette College, and to G.D.F. by the University of Saskatchewan. This work was partially supported by a grant from the Howard Hughes Medical Institute to Lafayette College under the Precollege and Undergraduate Science Education Program.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This work was conducted on feathers previously collected from captive, domestic Mallards as part of a separate, completed project. Thus, this work does not itself require ethics approval. Possession of feathers for this experiment was permitted by Environment Canada/Canadian Wildlife Service.