 Influence of climate on annual survival of Barn Swallows (  Hirundo rustica  ) breeding in North America  Information theory as an extension of the maximum likelihood principle  Null hypothesis testing: Problems, prevalence, and an alternative  Population limitation in Palaearctic&ndash;African migrant passerines  Divergent patterns of impact of environmental conditions on life history traits in two populations of a long-distance migratory bird  Individual responses in spring arrival date to ecological conditions during winter and migration in a migratory bird  Classification, seasonality and persistence of low-frequency atmospheric circulation patterns  Drought and annual variation in bird populations  The past and present of migratory connectivity  Intense natural selection on body size and wing and tail asymmetry in Cliff Swallows during severe weather  Barn Swallow (  Hirundo rustica  )  Natural selection on tail and bill morphology in Barn Swallows   Hirundo rustica   during severe weather  Weather-mediated natural selection on arrival time in Cliff Swallows (  Petrochelidon pyrrhonota  )  Estimates of survival from the sighting of marked animals  Tree Swallow mortality from exposure during unseasonable weather  A multi-isotope (&delta; 2 H, &delta; 13 C, &delta; 15 N) approach to establishing migratory connectivity of Barn Swallow (  Hirundo rustica  )  Why are bird migration dates shifting? A review of weather and climate effects on avian migratory phenology  Foraging, scavenging, and other behavior of swallows on the ground  Decadal trends in the North Atlantic Oscillation: Regional temperatures and precipitation  Model selection in ecology and evolution  El Ni&ntilde;o-Southern Oscillation influences annual survival of a migratory songbird at a regional scale  Modeling survival and testing biological hypotheses using marked animals: A unified approach with case studies  Starvation of spring migrants in the Chiricahua Mountains, Arizona  Changes in spring arrival of Nearctic&ndash;Neotropical migrants attributed to multiscalar climate  Effects of large-scale climatic fluctuations on survival and production of young in a Neotropical migrant songbird, the Yellow Warbler   Dendroica petechia    Population dynamics of a declining swallow   Hirundo rustica   population  North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) effects of climate on the relative importance of first and second clutches in a migratory passerine bird  Behavioral and life history responses to extreme climatic conditions: Studies on a migratory songbird  Survival rate of adult Barn Swallows   Hirundo rustica   in relation to sexual selection and reproduction  Climate Indices: Monthly Atmospheric and Ocean Time Series  Declines of aerial insectivores in North America follow a geographic gradient  Weather-related mass-mortality events in migrants  Influences of the El Ni&ntilde;o/Southern Oscillation and the North Atlantic Oscillation on avian productivity in forests of the Pacific Northwest of North America  Global and regional scale precipitation patterns associated with the El Ni&ntilde;o/Southern Oscillation  Climate influences on avian population dynamics  Canadian precipitation patterns associated with the Southern Oscillation  The impact of El Ni&ntilde;o&ndash;Southern Oscillation on the temperature field over Canada  Summer versus winter limitation of populations: What are the issues and what is the evidence?  Impacts of a global climate cycle on population dynamics of a migratory songbird  The effect of ENSO on the intraseasonal variance of surface temperatures in winter  Habitat-specific effects of food abundance on the condition of Ovenbirds wintering in Jamaica  Sex and age-specific annual survival in a Neotropical migratory songbird, the Purple Martin (  Progne subis  )  Mesoscale disturbance and ecological response to decadal climatic variability in the American Southwest  Relationship between West African rainfall and the survival of Central European Sand Martins   Riparia riparia    Links between worlds: Unraveling migratory connectivity  Program MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animals  Advanced features of program MARK  Spring migrant mortality during unseasonable weather  Population dynamics of migratory birds are influenced by both local weather and larger-scale patterns in climate that can operate at various stages of their annual cycle. We investigated correlations between (1) annual climatic indices and weather during the breeding season and (2) the annual survival of Barn Swallows (  Hirundo rustica  ) breeding at 2 sites in North America. Mark&ndash;recapture data collected during a 10-yr period for each of the 2 colonies in eastern and western North America were analyzed to model annual survival probabilities. Annual survival rates of Barn Swallows breeding in Seattle, Washington, USA, were higher in years preceded by El Ni&ntilde;o Southern Oscillation (ENSO) winters and higher in years with more positive North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) values. ENSO was expected to primarily influence wintering conditions through rainfall amount, and NAO was expected to influence climate on the breeding grounds; thus, climatic conditions on both breeding and wintering grounds likely affected the survival of these Seattle-breeding birds. By contrast, annual survival of swallows breeding in southern Ontario, Canada, remained constant over time and were not affected by any of the climatic parameters studied, which suggests that NAO did not have a strong effect on climatic conditions there and/or that these birds winter in regions where ENSO is not strongly correlated with local weather conditions. Alternatively, there may be less geographic variation in wintering-ground locations for Barn Swallows breeding in Seattle, resulting in stronger ENSO effects on survival for the Seattle population. Our results demonstrate how correlations between climate patterns on wintering grounds and annual survival can provide information on migratory connectivity at continental scales and underline the importance of local weather conditions throughout the annual cycle on survivorship and population dynamics of aerial insectivorous birds.  Las din&aacute;micas poblacionales de las aves migratorias est&aacute;n influenciadas tanto por el tiempo local como por patrones clim&aacute;ticos de mayor escala que pueden operar en varios estadios de sus ciclos anuales. Investigamos las correlaciones entre &iacute;ndices clim&aacute;ticos anuales junto con el tiempo durante la estaci&oacute;n reproductiva y la supervivencia anual de individuos reproductivos de   Hirundo rustica   en dos sitios en Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Los datos de marcaje-recaptura colectados durante un per&iacute;odo de diez a&ntilde;os para cada una de las dos colonias en el este y oeste de Am&eacute;rica del Norte fueron analizados para modelar la probabilidad de supervivencia anual. Las tasas de supervivencia anual de individuos de   H. rustica   reproduci&eacute;ndose en Seattle, Washington, EEUU, fueron mayores en a&ntilde;os precedidos por inviernos con influencia de la Oscilaci&oacute;n del Sur El Ni&ntilde;o (ENSO por sus siglas en Ingl&eacute;s) y mayores en a&ntilde;os con valores m&aacute;s positivos de la Oscilaci&oacute;n Atl&aacute;ntica Norte (NAO por sus siglas en Ingl&eacute;s). Se esper&oacute; que ENSO influenciara principalmente las condiciones invernales a trav&eacute;s de la cantidad de precipitaciones y que NAO influenciara el clima en las &aacute;reas reproductivas, y de este modo que las condiciones clim&aacute;ticas tanto en los sitios reproductivos como de invernada afectaran la supervivencia de estas aves reproductivas de Seattle. En contraste, la supervivencia anual de individuos de   H. rustica   reproduci&eacute;ndose en el sur de Ontario, Canad&aacute;, permaneci&oacute; constante a lo largo del tiempo y no fue afectada por ninguno de los par&aacute;metros clim&aacute;ticos estudiados, sugiriendo que NAO no tuvo un efecto fuerte en las condiciones clim&aacute;ticas all&iacute; y/o que estas aves invernan en regiones donde ENSO no est&aacute; fuertemente correlacionado con las condiciones locales del tiempo. Alternativamente, puede haber menos variaci&oacute;n geogr&aacute;fica en las localidades de invernada de individuos de   H. rustica   reproduci&eacute;ndose en Seattle, resultando en efectos de ENSO m&aacute;s fuertes en la supervivencia de la poblaci&oacute;n de Seattle. Nuestros resultados demuestran como las correlaciones entre los patrones clim&aacute;ticos en los sitios de invernada y la supervivencia anual pueden brindar informaci&oacute;n de la conectividad migratoria a la escala continental y subraya la importancia de las condiciones locales del tiempo a lo largo del ciclo anual de supervivencia y las din&aacute;micas poblacionales de aves insect&iacute;voras a&eacute;reas.   Palabras clave:  datos de marca-recaptura,   Hirundo rustica  , insect&iacute;voros a&eacute;reos, migraci&oacute;n de larga distancia, Oscilaci&oacute;n Atl&aacute;ntica Norte, Oscilaci&oacute;n del Sur El Ni&ntilde;o, supervivencia  Local weather and large-scale patterns of climate during various stages of their annual cycle may strongly influence the population dynamics of migratory birds ( Sillett et al. 2000 ,  S&aelig;ther et al. 2006 ,  Newton 2008 ) through weather-dependent loss of individuals or a reduction in primary productivity and prey abundance ( M&oslash;ller 1989 ,  Baillie and Peach 1992 ,  Swetnam and Betancourt 1998 ). Unseasonably cold temperatures, heavy precipitation, and other severe local weather events can result in massive mortality episodes in migratory birds ( Blake et al. 1992 ,  Brown and Brown 1998 ,  1999b ,  2000 ,  Newton 2007 ). Additionally, for migratory aerial insectivores such as swallows, weather conditions are particularly important for survival and reproduction because of their almost complete dependence on flying insects ( Ligon 1968 ,  Whitmore et al. 1977 ,  Brown and Brown 1998 ,  1999b ,  2000 ; but see  Hobson and Sealy 1987 ).  The annual cycle of migratory birds can be divided among breeding, wintering, and stopover sites, and individuals from the same breeding population can disperse more or less extensively on the wintering grounds. Migratory connectivity defines the degree to which individuals breeding in the same areas migrate to the same wintering areas and vice versa ( Webster et al. 2002 ,  Boulet and Norris 2006 ). Understanding migratory connectivity is a critical part of evaluating the population dynamics of migratory birds because different populations may be subjected to considerably different conditions throughout their annual cycle ( Sherry and Holmes 1995 ). Long-term mark&ndash;recapture studies, which evaluate survival of individuals over time in relation to the effects of climatic variables over the annual cycle, can be used as a proxy to identify the approximate location and nature of the wintering grounds and the degree of migratory connectivity associated with breeding populations ( Sillett et al. 2000 ,  Balbont&iacute;n et al. 2009a ,  2009b ,  Stutchbury et al. 2009 ).  The El Ni&ntilde;o Southern Oscillation (ENSO) and the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) are climatic indices that describe periodic fluctuations in climate that can strongly influence local weather conditions on both the breeding and the wintering grounds of Neotropical migrants ( Philander 1990 ,  Nott et al. 2002 ,  LaManna et al. 2012 ). The effects of ENSO and NAO on local weather conditions differ significantly across geographic regions. The influence of ENSO on surface temperatures and precipitation is strong during the Northern Hemisphere winter and almost disappears by spring; thus, ENSO affects climatic conditions mainly on the wintering grounds of long-distance Neotropical migrants ( Shabbar and Khandekar 1996 ,  Shabbar et al. 1997 ,  National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration 2012 ). El Ni&ntilde;o conditions during winter and early spring tend to result in drier and warmer weather in southern Mexico and northern Central America, and in northwestern regions of Canada and the United States, while the southern United States and northern Mexico experience higher precipitation rates and colder temperatures ( Shabbar and Khandekar 1996 ,  Shabbar et al. 1997 ). On the wintering grounds of long-distance Neotropical migrants, regions in the north and northeastern South America show low precipitation during the El Ni&ntilde;o phase, while regions in southern and western South America experience higher precipitation rates ( Ropelewski and Halpert 1987 ). NAO influences ambient temperatures and precipitation during spring and summer in North America and can thus affect weather conditions on the breeding grounds of Neotropical migrants ( Gordo 2007 ). Overall, positive phases of NAO are associated with higher temperatures and precipitation, whereas negative phases have opposite effects ( Hurrell 1995 ).  Using data from 2 long-term mark&ndash;recapture studies, we investigated how annual adult survival of Barn Swallows (  Hirundo rustica  ) was related to NAO and ENSO and the intensity of cold-weather periods in spring on the breeding grounds. Our study focused on 2 regions in western (Seattle) and eastern (Ontario) North America. ENSO apparently has little effect on climatic conditions in Ontario, whereas Seattle tends to experience lower precipitation rates and warmer temperatures in early spring during the El Ni&ntilde;o phase of ENSO ( Shabbar and Khandekar 1996 ,  Shabbar et al. 1997 ). Given the differential effects of ENSO and NAO across breeding and wintering locations of Neotropical migrant birds, we used the ENSO index as a proxy for climatic conditions experienced by migrants mainly on the wintering grounds and the NAO index to reflect conditions primarily on the breeding grounds.  ENSO- and NAO-related weather conditions have been previously reported to have an effect on populations of migratory birds by indirectly affecting their survivorship and fecundity. The relative productivity of Barn Swallows in Europe was found to be affected significantly by NAO conditions, being higher in years with positive NAO values than in years with more negative NAO values ( M&oslash;ller 2002 ). In North America, NAO seems to have a stronger climatic effect on eastern regions. However,  Nott et al. (2002)  found a clear influence of NAO on avian productivity in the Pacific Northwest region of North America, where the Seattle population is located. Moreover, annual variation in ENSO has been previously related to fluctuations in adult survival of western populations of Swainson's Thrush in the USA (  Catharus ustulatus  ;  LaManna et al. 2012 ) and of Yellow Warblers ( Setophaga petechia ) in Manitoba ( Mazerolle et al. 2005 ), although ENSO also affects survival on the wintering grounds. For instance,  Sillett et al. (2000)  found that annual survival rates of Black-throated Blue Warblers (  S. caerulescens  ) on their wintering grounds in Jamaica were strongly associated with ENSO-related weather conditions on wintering habitats.  Barn Swallow numbers, especially in the northern parts of their range, have decreased drastically in recent decades ( Cadman et al. 2007 ,  McGowan and Corwin 2008 ,  Nebel et al. 2010 ). The reasons for this decline, among Barn Swallows and other aerial insectivores, remain unknown (NABCI  Canada 2012 ). Given that the severity and frequency of climatic fluctuations are predicted to change ( IPCC 2013 ), our aim was to evaluate linkages between climate (NAO and ENSO indices) and local weather (intensity of spring cold-weather periods) and annual survival of swallows in order to inform predictions of the potential effects of climate variability on Barn Swallows and, potentially, other aerial insectivores.  Mark&ndash;recapture data from adult Barn Swallows were collected during 2002&ndash;2011 for colonies in southern Ontario, Canada (80&deg;19&prime;W, 43&deg;37&prime;N), and during 1999&ndash;2011 for a colony located at the Woodland Park Zoo in Seattle, Washington, USA (122&deg;21&prime;W, 47&deg;40&prime;N). Individuals were captured using mist nets from June to August and were banded following the guidelines of the  North American Banding Council (2001) . Age and sex were determined on the basis of tail length and evidence of breeding status ( Pyle 1997 ).  A total of 9,448 Barn Swallows were captured, and data from 1,219 adults (i.e. after-hatch-year) individuals were included in the analysis. The average annual numbers of adults captured were 103.2 &plusmn; 90.7 for Ontario and 14.3 &plusmn; 3.7 for Seattle. Annual average recapture rates were 25.9&percnt; for Ontario and 35.0&percnt; for Seattle, which suggests that each single recaptured bird in a given year can have a significant effect on the fit of the model.  Mark&ndash;recapture data from birds breeding in Ontario and Seattle were used separately to estimate apparent adult survival between breeding seasons (&Phi;) and recapture ( p ) rates for both populations using live-recapture or Cormack-Jolly-Seber models ( Cormack 1964 ,  Lebreton et al. 1992 ). All analyses were performed using Program MARK ( White and Burnham 1999 ). Data from 2010 for the Seattle population were not included in the analysis because of an anomalously high predation rate during that year. We created a set of candidate models including covariates for climatic conditions, sex, and year, along with null models to identify variables related to annual survival of Barn Swallows.  Climatic conditions were quantified by the average monthly values of 2 climatic indices: the Bivariate ENSO Time series (BEST) and NAO from the previous year (i.e. from September of the previous year to August of the current year), covering the period between breeding seasons. We used the BEST index instead of the traditional Southern Oscillation Index (SOI) to provide a longer period for the ENSO index, because BEST combines both the information on atmospheric pressure (SOI) and a sea-surface&ndash;temperature time series ( Smith and Sardeshmukh 2000 ,  Nott 2011 ). We additionally created an index of intensity of cold-weather periods in the spring, defined as the total number of consecutive days with maximum daily temperatures &lt;11&deg;C, measured in a breeding season (COLD). The cutoff point (11&deg;C) followed studies by  Brown and Brown (1998 ,  1999b ) on responses of Cliff Swallows ( Petrochelidon pyrronota ) and Barn Swallows, respectively, to weather conditions on the breeding grounds (also see  Brown and Brown 2000 ).  Mean monthly values of BEST and NAO indices were obtained from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) ( National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Climate Prediction Center 2012 ). Temperature values for Seattle and Ontario were also obtained through NOAA from weather stations close to the breeding sites. The analysis was confined to the period from when the earliest Barn Swallows were reported to have arrived on breeding areas until June 30.  To examine the effects of sex and year on annual survival rates, an initial global model including sex group (g) and year (t) main effects and their interactions in both survival and recapture parameters was developed (&Phi; g&ast;t , p g&ast;t ). Reduced-parameter models of this global model were then created to evaluate the effects of these variables separately. Here, survival was affected only by age group (&Phi; g ), year (&Phi; t ) or &ldquo;remain constant over time&rdquo; (&Phi;.). A model that included the interaction of the 2 variables, allowing parallel variation over time of survival rates of males and females (&Phi; g&plus;t ), was also considered.  To investigate the influence of climatic conditions on annual survival rates, we created models that incorporated covariates of ENSO ( Philander 1990 ), NAO ( Barnston and Livezey 1987 ), and an index of duration of cold periods (COLD) ( Brown and Brown 1998 ,  1999b ). First, models that allowed simple variation in survival based on wintering-ground climatic conditions (&Phi; BEST ), breeding-ground climatic conditions (&Phi; NAO ), and cold periods on breeding grounds (&Phi; COLD ) were created. Male and female survival rates of Barn Swallows may differ according to their body condition and their capacity to cope with environmental factors ( M&oslash;ller and Sz&eacute;p 2002 ). Therefore, survival was modeled to vary in parallel with sex and climatic indices and cold periods separately (&Phi; g&plus;BEST , &Phi; g&plus;NAO , &Phi; g&plus;COLD ). Because annual survival rates could be affected by several climatic indices simultaneously, we also included models that constrained survival estimates to be a linear-logistic function of ENSO, NAO, and/or cold periods (&Phi; BEST&plus;NAO&plus;COLD , &Phi; BEST&plus;NAO , &Phi; NAO&plus;COLD , &Phi; BEST&plus;COLD ).  Apart from estimating annual survival probabilities, live-recapture models allow the estimate of recapture probabilities. For our set of candidate models, we assumed that recapture probabilities could be constant over time (p.) or could vary by year (p t ) or as a function of sex (p g ). Recapture probabilities were also modeled to vary in parallel over time between sexes (p g&plus;t ) and as full year and sex dependency (p g&ast;t ). The final candidate set comprised 95 models, including 19 parameter combinations for survival estimates and 5 parameter combinations for recapture estimates. All model notations follow  Lebreton et al. (1992) .  Prior to analysis, the fit of the global model was assessed using the parametric bootstrap procedure ( White et al. 2001 ). A total of 300 simulated bootstrap data sets that met the model assumptions of no overdispersion and independence were generated. The distribution of the deviance from the original data was then compared with that generated from the bootstrap data sets to determine the probability of encountering a deviance equal to or higher than that obtained from the original data. Additionally, a measure of the degree of overdispersion of the observed data ( &ccirc; ) was calculated, based on the mean of the deviance from both the observed and simulated results, and no overdispersion of the data was found ( White et al. 2001 ).  To select the most parsimonious model among all models from the candidate set, model selection methods based on Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) were used ( Akaike 1973 ,  Johnson and Omland 2004 ). Models in both candidate sets from Seattle and Ontario data were ranked on the basis of AIC corrected for small sample sizes (AIC c ). The model with the lowest AIC c  was selected as the most parsimonious model, although it was assumed that models with AIC c  values differing by &lt;2 had equally substantial level of support ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). Models within 2 units of the best model that differed only in 1 parameter (i.e. nested models) and had similar log-likelihood values were considered not supported ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ).  More than one of our models showed a &Delta;AIC c  value &lt;2. Therefore, a model-averaging procedure that accounts for model selection uncertainty when making inferences of annual survival rates was applied. This procedure uses all models in the candidate model set and the weight ( w i  ) of evidence for each model to calculate average survival estimates ( Anderson et al. 2000 ,  Burnham and Anderson 2002 ).  Because our results showed that ENSO affected annual survival estimates of Barn Swallows breeding in Ontario and Seattle differently, we decided to test whether ENSO conditions on breeding and/or wintering grounds had a stronger effect and whether SOI could also be used as a proxy of ENSO conditions instead of BEST. We therefore used the same mark&ndash;recapture database previously used and included in the set of models 2 different covariates to reflect ENSO during wintering months (SOI w ) and during breeding months (SOI b ).  SOI is a quantitative measurement of the ENSO phenomenon, defined as the difference in sea-level pressure between the tropical Pacific Ocean (Tahiti) and the Indian Ocean (Darwin) ( Philander 1990 ). In North America, negative SOI values correspond to the warm phase of the ENSO phenomenon called El Ni&ntilde;o, whereas positive SOI values indicate the La Ni&ntilde;a phase, whose effects are the opposite of those of the El Ni&ntilde;o phase. Mean monthly values of SOI were obtained from the NOAA website ( National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Climate Prediction Center 2012 ) as a measure of ENSO annual conditions. Barn Swallows usually arrive on their wintering grounds as early as September and tend to depart these areas by early March, and they occupy their breeding areas from April to August ( Brown and Brown 1999a ). Therefore, ENSO conditions on the wintering grounds (SOI w ) were quantified by the mean monthly SOI values from September to March (wintering months) and ENSO-related breeding conditions (SOI b ) by mean monthly SOI values from April to August (breeding months). Because no correlation between SOI w  and SOI b  was found for the years included in the analysis (Ontario:  R  2  &equals; 0.05; Washington:  R  2  &equals; 0.05), we assumed that these indices could be used separately to measure the effect on annual survival estimates of ENSO-related conditions on breeding and wintering grounds.  A methodology similar to that applied in the previous analysis using ENSO, NAO, and COLD covariates was followed, resulting in a final candidate set that comprised 70 models, including 14 parameter combinations for survival estimates and 5 parameter combinations for recapture estimates. We first developed an initial global model that comprised sex (g) and year (t) main effects and their interactions in both survival and recapture parameters (&Phi; g&ast;t , p g&ast;t ). We then created reduced-parameter models that included only the effect of sex (&Phi; g ) or year (&Phi; t ), as well as a model that included the interaction between these 2 variables (&Phi; g&plus;t ) and a model that assumed constant survival (&Phi;.). Then models with covariates that allowed simple variation in survival based on ENSO-related climatic conditions on wintering grounds (&Phi; SOIw ) and breeding grounds (&Phi; SOIb ) also were included in the set of models, as well as a model that constrained survival to be a linear function of both ENSO conditions on breeding and wintering grounds (&Phi; SOIw&plus;SOIb ) and models that allowed parallel variation in survival based on sex and ENSO conditions for both breeding and wintering months (&Phi; g&plus;SOIw , &Phi; g&plus;SOIb ). Recapture probabilities were modeled similarly to the previous analysis using SOI w  and SOI b  as covariates. The same approach previously used for model selection was used in this additional analysis.  Model selection and estimates of annual apparent survival based on year, sex, cold-weather periods, ENSO, and NAO clearly differed between Barn Swallows breeding in Ontario ( Table 1 ) and in Seattle ( Table 2 ). For the Seattle population, both NAO- and ENSO-related conditions affected survival, potentially because of a strong effect of NAO on weather during the breeding months and effects of ENSO operating on the wintering grounds. By contrast, survival of the breeding population in Ontario remained constant and was not affected by these climatic indices.  Summary of candidate models of annual survival (&Phi;) and recapture (p) probabilities for Barn Swallows breeding in Ontario from 2002 to 2011. Model notation: g &equals; sex group, BEST &equals; previous year's average Bivariate ENSO Time series, t &equals; year, NAO &equals; previous year's average Northern Atlantic Oscillation, and COLD &equals; number of consecutive cold days; no subscript &equals; constant over sex group and year. The best model is in bold. Only models with Akaike weights ( w i  ) &ge;0.01 are shown. Values of the null model are shown in the last row for reference.  Summary output of candidate models of annual survival (&Phi;) and recapture (p) probabilities for Barn Swallows breeding at Woodland Park Zoo, Seattle, from 1999 to 2011. Model notation: g &equals; sex group, BEST &equals; previous year's average Bivariate ENSO Time series, t &equals; year, NAO &equals; previous year's average Northern Atlantic Oscillation, and COLD &equals; number of consecutive cold days; no subscript &equals; constant over sex group and year. The best models are in bold. Only models with Akaike weights ( w i  ) &le;0.01 are shown. Values of the null model are shown in the last row for reference.  The best model for Ontario was the one in which survival was constant over the years ( Table 1 ). We performed model averaging to account for the weight of each model in the candidate set to estimate annual survival for Ontario ( Table 3 ). Survival estimates were then plotted against the climatic and weather parameters (NAO, ENSO, and COLD) separately and validated the constancy of survival ( Figure 1 A,  1 C,  1 E).  Survival estimates (&plusmn; SE) for Barn Swallows breeding in Ontario and Seattle, calculated by averaging the model weights of all models in the candidate set.  Apparent annual survival rates (&plusmn; SE) of adult Barn Swallows breeding at a site in southern Ontario from 2002 to 2011 in relation to ( A ) the previous year's average Northern Atlantic Oscillation (NAO), ( B ) the Southern Oscillation Index for the breeding months (SOI b ), ( C ) the previous year's average Bivariate ENSO Time series (BEST), ( D ) the Southern Oscillation Index for the wintering months (SOI w ), and ( E ) the number of consecutive cold days in the spring (COLD). The terms SOI b , BEST, and SOI w  correspond to different measurements of the El Ni&ntilde;o Southern Oscillation (ENSO) index.  In Seattle, 3 non-nested models that incorporated separate effects of year, NAO, and ENSO had strong support (&Delta;AIC c  &lt; 2;  Table 2 ). Because more than a single model with several variables included was found to have support, we performed model averaging to estimate annual survival probabilities ( Table 3 ). In contrast to Ontario, apparent survival rates of Barn Swallows breeding in Seattle varied over time and were correlated with the 3 climate and weather indices (NAO:  R  2  &equals; 0.52,  P  &equals; 0.011; BEST:  R  2  &equals; 0.49,  P  &equals; 0.017; COLD:  R  2  &equals; 0.45,  P  &equals; 0.023;  Figure 2 A,  2 C,  2 E). Survival estimates were higher in years with more positive NAO and ENSO (El Ni&ntilde;o years) values ( Figure 2 A,  2 C) and in those years with shorter periods of cold in the spring ( Figure 2 E). Additionally, we compared annual survival estimates between populations, and values were higher overall in Seattle than in Ontario ( Table 3 ).  Apparent annual survival rates (&plusmn; SE) of adult Barn Swallows breeding at Woodland Zoo, Seattle, from 1999 to 2011 in relation to ( A ) the previous year's average Northern Atlantic Oscillation (NAO), ( B ) the Southern Oscillation Index for the breeding months (SOI b ), ( C ) the previous year's average Bivariate ENSO Time series (BEST), ( D ) the Southern Oscillation Index for the wintering months (SOI w ), and ( E ) the number of consecutive cold days in the spring (COLD). The terms SOI b , BEST, and SOI w  correspond to different measurements of the El Ni&ntilde;o Southern Oscillation (ENSO) index.  Interestingly, none of the best models for Ontario and Seattle included the effect of sex on survival rates. The sum of model weights for the top-performing models for Ontario and Seattle was 40&percnt; and 40.5&percnt;, respectively, which suggests that the models selected had enough evidence in favor of being the best to fit the data ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). In terms of recapture probabilities, all models included in the set of best models for Ontario included the effect of sex and year on recapture ( Table 1 ). Recapture rates of these breeding birds depended on year and sex and were higher in females (mean &plusmn; SE &equals; 0.42 &plusmn; 0.07;  n  &equals; 9) than in males (0.34 &plusmn; 0.07;  n  &equals; 9). However, the substantial overlap of standard errors for both sexes in some cases suggests that these differences in recapture rates occur only in certain years ( Figure 3 A). By contrast, we found that recapture rates in Seattle were dependent only on year (0.72 &plusmn; 0.11;  n  &equals; 11;  Table 2  and  Figure 3 B).  Apparent recapture probabilities (means &plusmn; SE) over time of male and female adult Barn Swallows breeding in ( A ) Ontario and ( B ) Seattle.  The best model for the Ontario data had apparent survival constant over time (&Phi;, p g&plus;t ; &Delta;AIC c  &equals; 0.00;  w i   &equals; 0.208). The other 2 models in which survival varied with SOI b  (&Phi; SOIb , p g&plus;t ) and sex group (&Phi; g , p g&plus;t ) differed in AIC c  values &lt;2 (&Delta;AIC c  &equals; 0.86 and 1.55, respectively), also suggesting significant support. However, they differed from the best model only in having 1 extra parameter (nested models), and, therefore, the best candidate model was considered to be that with the lowest AIC c . Survival estimates, calculated using model averaging methods, were constant over time, and neither ENSO on breeding or wintering grounds had an effect on survival of birds breeding in Ontario ( Figure 1 B,  1 D).  Three candidate models differed in AIC c  values by &lt;2. A model that incorporated variation in survival in relation to ENSO conditions on the spring (&Phi; SOIb , p t ) showed the lowest AIC c  (&Delta;AIC c  &equals; 0.00;  w i   &equals; 0.254). Two other models in which apparent survival varied in parallel as a linear-logistic function of SOI b  and SOI w  (&Phi; SOIb&plus;SOIw , p t ) and a model that included only SOI b  as explanatory variable (&Phi; SOIb , p g&plus;t ) showed AIC c  values lower by &lt;2 from the top model (&Delta;AIC c  &equals; 1.80 and 1.99, respectively). We therefore used model averaging to make inferences of annual survival of Seattle birds and found that ENSO on both breeding and wintering grounds were clearly correlated with interannual survival probabilities (SOI b :  R  2  &equals; 0.96,  P  &equals; 0.000; SOI w :  R  2  &equals; 0.62,  P  &equals; 0.004;  Figure 2 B,  2 D).  Two different climatic indices were used in our study to reflect conditions across the annual cycle of Barn Swallows, and we found that both approaches produced similar results. NAO and SOI indices for the breeding months from the previous year (SOI b ) were used separately as proxies of climatic conditions experienced by swallows on the breeding grounds. BEST and SOI indices for the wintering months from the preceding year (SOI w ) were used to reflect climatic conditions on wintering grounds.  We found a clear effect of climate, operating on both breeding and wintering grounds, on the interannual survival of Barn Swallows breeding in Seattle, but we found no effect for birds breeding in Ontario. Apparent annual survival of swallows in Seattle was strongly and positively correlated with averaged values of ENSO and NAO from the previous year, being lower during La Ni&ntilde;a years and years with negative NAO values and higher during El Ni&ntilde;o years and years with positive NAO values. By contrast, survival rates for swallows in Ontario remained constant when compared with ENSO, NAO, and COLD values, which suggests no effect of the 3 indices studied for this breeding location.  On the breeding grounds, NAO has a stronger effect on temperature and precipitation in northeastern areas where negative values of NAO are related to cooler and wetter springs ( Hurrell 1995 ). However, recent studies have shown that weather conditions related to NAO could also have an effect on reproductive success and timing of migration of birds breeding in western North America ( Nott et al. 2002 ,  Macmynowski et al. 2007 ). Those studies confirmed that survival rates were negatively correlated with the NAO index, likely because of the stress of cold and wet weather directly or indirectly due to the lower insect availability associated with negative NAO values ( Nott et al. 2002 ). Contrary to other studies, we did not find effects of NAO on our northeast population, but our data do support the growing body of work showing effects of NAO on breeding birds in the west. Low insect abundance on the breeding grounds has been shown to reduce Barn Swallow survival ( Dence 1946 ,  Ligon 1968 ,  Whitmore et al. 1977 ,  Brown and Brown 1999b ). A clear example of the negative effect of reduced insect abundance on Barn Swallows was provided for those breeding in central Europe when populations were reduced by 20&ndash;50&percnt; because of an early period of cold during fall migration that dramatically reduced the amount of prey available ( M&oslash;ller 2011 ). Similar observations were reported for breeding Cliff Swallows in the northern Central Plains of the United States, where frequent periods of unseasonable weather in spring caused high mortality of individuals ( Brown and Brown 2000 ).  In addition to differential effects of ENSO and NAO operating on the breeding grounds, our results also indicate different wintering grounds for the Seattle and Ontario populations. On the wintering grounds in South America, changes in precipitation related to ENSO differ regionally ( Ropelewski and Halpert 1987 ). Our results are consistent with a scenario in which Barn Swallows breeding in Seattle winter in regions of northern South America where El Ni&ntilde;o years feature more rainfall during the boreal winter months ( Ropelewski and Halpert 1987 ). Increased precipitation on the wintering grounds is often positively correlated with insect biomass, so swallows wintering in these areas may experience lower mortality rates during those years ( Sz&eacute;p 1995 ,  Sillett et al. 2000 ,  Strong and Sherry 2000 ). By contrast, no correlation between survival and ENSO was found for swallows breeding in Ontario.  Sillett et al. (2000)  similarly showed a lack of correlation between survival and ENSO for Black-throated Blue Warblers breeding in New Hampshire, despite showing that annual survival rates of a wintering population in Jamaica were correlated with ENSO. In a study of Purple Martins (  Progne subis  ) breeding in northwestern Pennsylvania,  Stutchbury et al. (2009)  also found no evidence that ENSO influenced adult survival and hypothesized that this lack of correlation was due to low migratory connectivity between that site and any specific region of the wintering grounds. The effect of ENSO on weather conditions in South America varies geographically, and birds that breed in Ontario likely winter in areas in South America that are not as severely influenced by ENSO. Stable-isotope studies have found low migratory connectivity for Barn Swallows breeding in Ontario, which suggests that these birds may disperse extensively on the wintering grounds ( Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez and Hobson 2014 ). A broad wintering range may decouple population survival from the geographically variable effects of winter ENSO conditions. By contrast, swallows breeding in Seattle may occupy more restricted wintering regions where conditions are strongly coupled with ENSO.  Other mark&ndash;recapture studies have yielded greater total model weights than ours, which, we believe, is attributable to differences in biology rather than model support alone. For instance,  LaManna et al. (2012)  studied climatic factors affecting interannual survival of Swainson's Thrush and found a single climatic variable with a top-model sum of weights around 73&percnt;. One explanation for differences among studies is that in the case of Barn Swallows, individuals are subjected to many and varied climatic conditions due to their diverse wintering areas ( Brown and Brown 1999a ) and the tendency of individuals from the same population to disperse on the wintering grounds ( Garc&iacute;a-P&eacute;rez and Hobson 2014 ). Therefore, individuals from the same breeding population of swallows could be affected by a large and varied array of factors that could have different effects on annual survival. By contrast, Swainson's Thrush has a smaller winter range, so individuals are more likely to be subjected to similar factors on those areas, and a single variable could have a stronger effect on annual survival.  Seattle birds showed higher interannual survival rates than Ontario birds, and both breeding locations exhibited similar survival rates between sexes. Additionally, these similarities between sexes agree with the results of previous studies of survival rates in Bank Swallows (  Riparia riparia  ) breeding in Hungary ( Sz&eacute;p 1995 ) and Cliff Swallows in the northern Great Plains ( Brown and Brown 1996 ) and are consistent with the possibility that the sexes do not choose different wintering grounds.  Despite rapid declines in their populations, especially in northern regions of their range, there have been surprisingly few mark&ndash;recapture studies of Barn Swallows in North America. As we have demonstrated, such studies provide important opportunities to investigate the influence of climate, local weather, and other variables, such as age and year, on annual survivorship. Correlational analyses with large-scale climate phenomena such as ENSO and NAO also help reveal geographic variation in migratory connectivity. Further research should focus on expanding this knowledge to understand the different mechanisms operating on breeding and wintering grounds that determine population dynamics of Barn Swallows and other declining aerial insectivores.  We thank S. Wilson and N. Michel for valuable statistical insights. This work was funded by an operating grant from Environment Canada and the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada to K.A.H. and by a University of Saskatchewan Graduate Scholarship and Isabel Mar&iacute;a L&oacute;pez Mart&iacute;nez Memorial Scholarship to B.G.P. Three anonymous reviewers and the Associate Editor provided useful comments on the manuscript. 