 On the existence and potential functions of low-amplitude vocalizations in North American birds  Signalling while fighting: Further remarks on soft song  Song type matching is an honest early threat signal in a hierarchical animal communication system  Sing softly and carry a big stick: Signals of aggressive intent in the Song Sparrow  AOU Checklist of North and Middle American Birds, seventh edition  Soft song in Song Sparrows: Response of males and females to an enigmatic signal  The receiver-dependent cost of soft song: A signal of aggressive intent in songbirds  Soft song in Song Sparrows: Acoustic structure and implications for signal function  Reliable aggressive signalling in Swamp Sparrows  The function of song in Whitethroats   Sylvia communis    Male singing behaviour and female presence in the territory in Whitethroats   Sylvia communis    Simulated courtship interactions elicit neighbour intrusions in the Whitethroat,   Sylvia communis    Degradation of Whitethroat vocalisations: Implications for song flight and communication network activities  Bat serenades: Complex courtship songs of the sac-winged bat (  Saccopteryx bilineata  )  Life Histories of North American Cardinals, Grosbeaks, Buntings, Towhees, Finches, Sparrows, and Allies  Nest predation and the evolution of nestling begging calls  Female mate choice and songbird song repertoires  Loudness of birdsong is related to the body size, syntax and phonology of passerine species  Dark-eyed Junco song: Linking ontogeny and function with a potential role in reproductive isolation  Public, private or anonymous? Facilitating and countering eavesdropping. In Animal Communication Networks  Habitat-induced degradation of sound signals: Quantifying the effects of communication sounds and bird location on blur ratio, excess attenuation, and signal-to-noise ratio  Quiet song in song birds: An overlooked phenomenon  Tsip calls of Meadow and Rock pipits: Interspecific comparisons and playback experiments  Vocal communication at the nest between mates in wild Zebra Finches: A private vocal duet?  Testosterone and mate choice in the Dark-eyed Junco  Complex female vocal behaviour of Great and Blue tits inside the nesting cavity  A phylogenomic study of birds reveals their evolutionary history  Low-amplitude song predicts attack in a North American wood warbler  Efficacy and the design of begging signals  Whisper song in the Grey Thrush  Turdus cardis  immediately before and after feeding their young  Females whisper briefly during sex: Context- and sex-specific differences in sounds made by croaking gouramis  Singing activity and song pattern of the Redwing   Turdus iliacus   during the breeding season  Does twitter song amplitude signal male arousal in Redwings (  Turdus iliacus  )?  An avian eavesdropping network: Alarm signal reliability and heterospecific response  Female eavesdropping on male song contests in songbirds  Moths are not silent, but whisper ultrasonic courtship songs  Studies in the Life History of the Song Sparrow, II: The Behavior of the Song Sparrow and Other Passerines  Soft song and the readiness hypothesis: Comments on Ak&ccedil;ay et al. (2011)  Losses of female song with changes from tropical to temperate breeding in the New World blackbirds  Close calling regulates spacing between foraging competitors in the group-living Pied Babbler  Courtship song's role during female mate choice in the field cricket  Teleogryllus oceanicus   Low-amplitude songs produced by male Dark-eyed Juncos (  Junco hyemalis  ) differ when sung during intra- and inter-sexual interactions  Deciphering information encoded in birdsong: Male songbirds with fertile mates respond most strongly to complex, low-amplitude songs used in courtship  Nonpasserine bird produces soft calls and pays retaliation cost  Robust behavioral effects of song playback in the absence of testosterone or corticosterone release  Song as an aggressive signal in songbirds  Signal interception and the use of soft song in aggressive interactions  Bird song as a signal of aggressive intent  Individuality in the contact calls of cooperatively breeding Long-tailed Tits (  Aegithalos caudatus  )  Acoustic signals in cicada courtship behaviour (order Hemiptera, genus  Tibicina )  Soft song is a reliable signal of aggressive intent in Song Sparrows  Allometry of alarm calls: Black-capped Chickadees encode information about predator size  Short-range and long-range songs: Use of two acoustically distinct song classes by Dark-eyed Juncos  Meerkat close calls encode group-specific signatures, but receivers fail to discriminate  The importance of calling song and courtship song in female mate choice in the variable field cricket  Courtship song is more variable than calling song in the field cricket  Teleogryllus oceanicus   Current address: Department of Evolution and Ecology, University of California, Davis, California, USA  Current address: Department of Neurobiology and Behavior, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, USA  Research on acoustic communication has focused predominantly on high-amplitude, long-range vocalizations that are easily recognized from a distance by the human ear. However, attention has recently expanded to the more enigmatic low-amplitude (quiet) vocalizations produced during close-proximity interactions associated with a variety of social behaviors such as aggression, courtship, group movements, and predator avoidance. The existence of low-amplitude vocalizations has been identified in a number of individual avian and nonavian species (e.g., crickets, fish, and primates), but how common these signals are within larger taxonomic groups such as orders and classes remains poorly understood. Here, we used the Birds of North America Online archive to perform a survey of the existence and putative functions of low-amplitude vocalizations across 749 species accounts of breeding birds in North America. By searching with keywords such as soft, quiet, low-amplitude, and whispered, we found evidence that 433 species (&sim;58&percnt; of those sampled) produce at least one type of low-amplitude vocalization. Low-amplitude calls were more commonly reported than low-amplitude songs, but both types of vocalizations were thought to be used around twice as often in courtship interactions as in aggressive interactions. Furthermore, 40&percnt; of species that sang low-amplitude songs produced at least one song that was thought to be divergent in structure from any high-amplitude songs in the species' repertoire; however, these acoustic differences were predominantly based on each author's auditory perceptions rather than on quantitative data. Collectively, these patterns suggest that low-amplitude vocalizations are common at a broad taxonomic scale, and that low-amplitude songs may be a distinct class of vocal signal. In addition, the observation that low-amplitude vocalizations are produced in a variety of social contexts, including courtship, indicates that these vocalizations should receive greater attention in future studies of communication, sexual selection, and social behavior.  La investigaci&oacute;n sobre la comunicaci&oacute;n ac&uacute;stica se ha enfocado predominantemente en vocalizaciones de alta amplitud y largo alcance que son f&aacute;cilmente reconocidas por el o&iacute;do humano desde la distancia. Sin embargo, la atenci&oacute;n se ha expandido recientemente hacia las enigm&aacute;ticas vocalizaciones de baja amplitud (silenciosas) producidas durante interacciones cercanas y asociadas con una variedad de comportamientos sociales como agresi&oacute;n, cortejo, movimientos grupales y evasi&oacute;n de depredadores. La existencia de vocalizaciones de baja amplitud ha sido identificada en varias especies de aves y en otros organismos (e.g., grillos, peces, primates), pero a&uacute;n no se sabe qu&eacute; tan comunes son estas se&ntilde;ales en grupos taxon&oacute;micos m&aacute;s grandes como &oacute;rdenes y clases. En este trabajo usamos los archivos en l&iacute;nea Birds of North America Online para hacer un censo de la existencia y potenciales funciones de las vocalizaciones de baja amplitud a trav&eacute;s de 749 especies de aves que se reproducen en Norte Am&eacute;rica. Al buscar palabras clave como suave, silencioso, baja amplitud, y susurro, encontramos evidencia de 433 especies (&sim;58&percnt; de la muestra) que producen al menos un tipo de vocalizaci&oacute;n de baja amplitud. Los llamados de baja amplitud fueron m&aacute;s com&uacute;nmente reportados que los cantos de baja amplitud, pero ambos tipos de vocalizaciones fueron considerados parte de interacciones de cortejo con aproximadamente el doble la frecuencia que como parte de interacciones agresivas. Adicionalmente, el 40&percnt; de las especies que tienen cantos de baja amplitud produjeron al menos un canto que se consider&oacute; diferente en estructura comparado con cualquier canto de amplitud alta en el repertorio de cada especie. Sin embargo, estas diferencias ac&uacute;sticas se basaron casi exclusivamente en observaciones hechas a o&iacute;do por cada autor en vez de en datos cuantitativos. Colectivamente, estos patrones sugieren que las vocalizaciones de baja amplitud son comunes a trav&eacute;s de amplias escalas taxon&oacute;micas, y que los cantos de baja amplitud podr&iacute;an ser una clase distinta de se&ntilde;al vocal. Adem&aacute;s, la observaci&oacute;n de que las vocalizaciones de baja amplitud se producen en una variedad de contextos sociales, incluyendo el cortejo, indica que estas vocalizaciones deber&iacute;an recibir mayor atenci&oacute;n en futuros estudios de comunicaci&oacute;n, selecci&oacute;n sexual y comportamiento social.   Palabras clave:  canto de corto alcance, canto suave, comportamiento social, comunicaci&oacute;n, cortejo, llamados, selecci&oacute;n sexual, territorialidad  Acoustic signaling is a common mode of communication that has long served as a model in behavioral studies focusing on signaling theory, mate choice, and sexual selection ( McGregor 2005 ,  Searcy and Nowicki 2005 ,  Catchpole and Slater 2008 ,  Bradbury and Vehrencamp 2011 ). The dominant focus of decades of research on acoustic signaling has been high-amplitude (loud) signals that transmit over long distances and have the ability to serve multiple functions by reaching receivers of both sexes and many age classes ( Bradbury and Vehrencamp 2011 ). The study of high-amplitude signals has progressed in part because such songs are conspicuous to the human ear, which has facilitated their quantification and given rise to readily testable hypotheses regarding their presumed functions and evolutionary significance.  In addition to high-amplitude signals, many avian and nonavian species are known to produce a variety of low-amplitude signals, which are drastically understudied when compared with their high-amplitude counterparts ( Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Osiejuk 2011 ,  Reichard et al. 2011 ). Here, we broadly define low-amplitude signals as any acoustic signal produced at a low volume, such that the signal's effective transmission distance is limited to a close-proximity interaction between the sender and receiver. While high-amplitude signals primarily serve functions in territoriality, mate attraction and courtship, and predator avoidance situations ( Bradbury and Vehrencamp 2011 ), low-amplitude signals are produced in a variety of social contexts, such as pair or group movements and foraging ( Elfstr&ouml;m 1992 ,  Radford and Ridley 2008 ), close-proximity interactions between members of a pair bond ( Gorissen and Eens 2005 ,  Elie et al. 2010 ), feeding of young ( Horn and Leonard 2002 ,  Ishizuka 2009 ), aggressive interactions ( Searcy and Beecher 2009 ,  Ak&ccedil;ay et al. 2011 ), and directed courtship ( Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Reichard et al. 2013 ). Low-amplitude signals also appear to be taxonomically widespread, with evidence for low-amplitude signals existing in passerine ( Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Titus 1998 ,  Anderson et al. 2008 ) and nonpasserine species ( Radford and Ridley 2008 ,  R&eogon;k and Osiejuk 2011 ), as well as in other vertebrates ( Behr and von Helversen 2004 ,  Ladich 2007 ,  Townsend et al. 2010 ) and invertebrates ( Sueur and Aubin 2004 ,  Zuk et al. 2008 ,  Nakano et al. 2009 ).  Despite being recognized in many individual species across a broad taxonomic scale, our understanding of the general existence of low-amplitude signals within larger taxonomic groups such as orders and classes remains limited. Additionally, given that low-amplitude signals can serve functions in both territoriality and courtship interactions and likely affect fitness (e.g.,  Enstrom et al. 1997 ,  Wagner and Reiser 2000 ,  Rebar et al. 2009 ), it is imperative that we begin to explore how common these signals are, and how their functions and content complement or provide contrast to high-amplitude signals. Birds provide an excellent study system to begin investigating these questions, given the diversity of mating systems and life-history strategies present across avian taxa, and the abundance of published data on avian natural histories and acoustic communication (e.g.,  Poole and Gill 2005 ,  Catchpole and Slater 2008 ,  del Hoyo et al. 2011 ).  The existence of low-amplitude vocalizations in avian taxa, particularly in songbirds, has been documented for many decades (e.g.,  Nice 1943 ,  Bent and Austin 1968 ). Low-amplitude calls, which are generally less complex than songs (i.e. shorter in length and with fewer notes or elements), have been studied in a variety of contexts, including nestling begging ( Briskie et al. 1999 ,  Horn and Leonard 2002 ), predator-related alarm signaling ( Templeton et al. 2005 ,  Magrath et al. 2009 ), and contact signaling during group and pair interactions ( Gorissen and Eens 2005 ,  Sharp and Hatchwell 2005 ). However, observational and experimental analyses of the functions of low-amplitude songs, which are generally more complex than calls (i.e. longer in length and with more notes or elements) and are produced predominantly during the breeding season ( Catchpole and Slater 2008 ), have only recently gained momentum.  Much of the early research on low-amplitude songs focused on linking observations of their production to social (e.g., male&ndash;male or male&ndash;female interactions) or seasonal (e.g., pre&ndash; or post&ndash;egg laying) contexts in order to draw inferences about their functions ( Lampe and Espmark 1987 ,  Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Titus 1998 ,  Balsby 2000 ). Recently, the focus has shifted to testing whether low-amplitude singing can serve as an honest signal of behavioral intent ( Searcy et al. 2006 ,  Ballentine et al. 2008 ,  Hof and Hazlett 2010 ,  Templeton et al. 2012 ), and whether low-amplitude songs are salient signals that elicit responses from both male ( Balsby and Dabelsteen 2005 ,  Lampe et al. 2010 ,  Reichard et al. 2011 ,  Anderson et al. 2012 ,  Rosvall et al. 2012 ) and female receivers ( Anderson et al. 2007 ). The dominant focus of this research has emphasized the aggressive function of low-amplitude singing, and its surprising ability to predict a physical attack more reliably than other signaling strategies such as song-type matching or song overlapping ( Searcy and Beecher 2009 ,  R&eogon;k and Osiejuk 2011 ,  Ak&ccedil;ay et al. 2013 ). It is also well established that low-amplitude songs are produced during male&ndash;female interactions associated with courtship ( Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Balsby and Dabelsteen 2003 ,  Reichard et al. 2013 ), but our understanding of the relative importance of low-amplitude signals in courtship and mate choice has received considerably less attention in the literature.  In this study, we summarize the reported occurrence of both high- and low-amplitude songs and calls in North American birds using species accounts in the Birds of North America Online database ( Poole and Gill 2005 ). This database contains species accounts spanning 22 avian taxonomic orders, and thus provides an ideal starting place for a general investigation of the existence of low-amplitude vocalizations. Additionally, we summarize the available data relating to the putative functions of low-amplitude songs and calls, as well as the presumed sex of the singer when possible. In cases in which a species is thought to produce both a high-amplitude and a low-amplitude song, we rely on written descriptions of each song's acoustic structure and, less frequently, visual comparisons of spectrograms to determine whether the high- and low-amplitude songs are similar or divergent in acoustic structure. With respect to the putative function and acoustic structure data, which are largely based on subjective, nonquantitative reports, we establish two indices of data quality to provide insight into the interpretive power of each result.  We analyzed 749 individual species accounts in the Birds of North America Online database ( Poole and Gill 2005 ) for evidence of low-amplitude vocalizations (dates of analysis: February 26, 2014, to May 25, 2014). One or more experts on each species authored every species account, and the accounts are edited and updated, often by additional authors, as new research on each species becomes available.  Each species account in the database contained a section dedicated to the accumulated knowledge of every acoustic signal produced by that species, entitled &ldquo;Sounds.&rdquo; We focused on the &ldquo;Sounds&rdquo; section of each account, while using the &ldquo;Behavior&rdquo; section as a supplement only if the &ldquo;Sounds&rdquo; section referred to additional information found in the &ldquo;Behavior&rdquo; section. Due to variation in the level of detail presented in each species account, not all of the vocal attributes that we sampled were available or interpretable for every species in the database. In cases in which a variable (e.g., sex of singer) was unclear owing to an incomplete description, we excluded that species from the analysis of that variable.  Initially, we classified each vocalization as high-amplitude or low-amplitude based on the author's description of amplitude. Any vocalization described with keywords or phrases such as low-amplitude, soft, whispered, quiet, faint, muted, muffled, low-volume, strangled, or inaudible after a short distance (e.g., &gt;15 m) was identified as a low-amplitude vocalization, while all other vocalizations were classified as high-amplitude. We chose high-amplitude as the default classification because high-amplitude vocalizations are more conspicuous, and authors usually stated when a vocalization was produced at low amplitude but tended not to comment on amplitude when describing vocalizations commonly thought to be of high amplitude (e.g., songs of passerines). In rare cases in which a species' vocalization contained multiple components or phrases and one component was described as lower in amplitude, we conservatively considered those vocalizations as high-amplitude. We focused only on adult vocalizations (e.g., nestling begging calls and the subsongs of some juvenile passerines were excluded) and did not consider mechanical or nonvocal sounds.  We further classified each vocalization as a song or a call, again relying on the authors' designations, and noted the sex of the singer (male, female, or both) for all low-amplitude vocalizations. Differentiating between songs and calls is often an arbitrary process that varies depending on the species sampled and the scientist doing the sampling ( Catchpole and Slater 2008 ). Songbirds (Passeriformes), for example, may be more likely to have their vocalizations classified as songs than other species; however, we noted that of the 398 nonpasserine species sampled, 73 produced vocalizations that were classified as songs by the authors. Thus, it appears that many authors were not restrictive of their classifications based on taxonomy alone, but rather considered more general characteristics of each vocalization such as length, complexity, and function when determining their classifications of songs and calls.  When possible, each song or call was further classified according to its putative function. Songs were assigned to a function in courtship and/or territoriality, which are the two functional categories typical of breeding vocalizations. Calls were assigned to the same categories, as well as two additional categories: alarm or contact. These assignments were based on the authors' descriptions of the social contexts in which vocalizations were heard or the results of playback experiments. Any vocalization produced by a male or a female to a member of the opposite sex that preceded copulation or the formation of a pair bond was identified as having a function in courtship. Vocalizations were identified as having a function in territoriality if they were associated with aggressive encounters between individuals or if they were known to repel potential territorial intruders. Calls that were produced in response to predators were identified as functioning as alarm signals, and calls that were produced during pair or group interactions such as movements and foraging were identified as contact calls.  A complete test of the function of an acoustic signal is a multistep process that involves making observations of the various social contexts in which the signal is produced as well as measuring the responses of all potential receivers of that signal to ensure its saliency ( Searcy and Beecher 2009 ). The species accounts that we sampled varied greatly in the quality of their tests of song and call function, and many of the accounts relied largely on anecdotal evidence, which falls short of definitively testing a signal's function. To provide insight into the quality of the function data, we assigned a numerical score on a scale of 1&ndash;4 to each putative function according to the following guidelines: 1 &equals; author's personal observation or other unpublished personal communication with an outside expert; 2 &equals; published account that is solely observational and excludes any experimental manipulations; 3 &equals; published account that includes an experimental manipulation (e.g., playback experiment); and 4 &equals; multiple lines of published evidence including both observational and experimental data.  Many birds sing quiet versions of their high-amplitude songs. To determine whether or not a species' low-amplitude songs were similar to or divergent in structure from its high-amplitude songs, we relied on spectrograms in the species accounts for comparing visual representations of each species' songs and/or the written descriptions of song structure (e.g., note and syllable shape). Based on these data, it was possible to classify low-amplitude songs as either structurally similar or structurally divergent in comparison with any high-amplitude songs produced by each species. To investigate the quality of these data, which also varied substantially among the species accounts, we assigned a numerical score of 1&ndash;3 to each song according to the following guidelines: 1 &equals; structural differences determined by the author's ear; 2 &equals; visual comparison of spectrograms of high- and low-amplitude songs; and 3 &equals; published quantitative data supporting differences between songs. In cases in which a species sang a low-amplitude song but no high-amplitude song, that low-amplitude song was classified as structurally divergent.  For our final analysis, we first classified each species in the database according to the presence or absence of any high- or low-amplitude songs or calls. Any species that produced low-amplitude songs or calls were further classified according to the sex of singer and the putative functions of both low-amplitude songs and calls. Finally, species that produced low-amplitude songs were classified as having songs that were structurally similar to their high-amplitude songs or structurally divergent. Species were also divided into taxonomical orders based on the most recent Checklist of North American and Middle American Birds ( American Ornithologists' Union 2013 ). All  P -values represent the result of a two sample  Z -test for comparing two proportions.  All 22 avian orders present in the database contained species that are thought to produce low-amplitude vocalizations. Additionally, 15 of the 22 orders, including the 3 largest orders present in the database (Passeriformes &lsqb;perching birds&rsqb;, Charadriiformes &lsqb;shorebirds&rsqb;, and Anseriformes &lsqb;waterfowl&rsqb;), exhibited evidence for low-amplitude vocalizations in at least 50&percnt; of the species sampled ( Table 1 ). Of the 749 species sampled, 433 (57.8&percnt;) produced at least one type of low-amplitude vocalization, while 743 (99.2&percnt;) species produced at least one type of high-amplitude vocalization ( Table 1 ;  P  &lt; 0.001). For the 433 species that produced low-amplitude vocalizations, low-amplitude calls (374/433 &lsqb;86.4&percnt;&rsqb;) were more commonly reported than low-amplitude songs (144/433 &lsqb;33.3&percnt;&rsqb;,  P  &lt; 0.001;  Figure 1 ). High-amplitude calls (740/743 &lsqb;99.6&percnt;&rsqb;) were more common than high-amplitude songs (383/743 &lsqb;51.5&percnt;&rsqb;,  P  &lt; 0.001;  Figure 1 ). Low-amplitude songs were predominantly produced by members of the order Passeriformes (128/144 &lsqb;88.9&percnt;&rsqb;), while the production of low-amplitude calls was more evenly distributed across all of the orders sampled ( Table 1 ).  Summary data of the occurrence and putative functions of low-amplitude songs and calls reported in 749 individual species accounts from 22 taxonomic orders of North American breeding birds in the Birds of North American Online database ( Poole and Gill 2005 ). The sequence of the orders in this table was chosen to approximate phylogenetic relatedness (see  figures 2  and 4 in  Hackett et al. 2008 ). Cells in the table that contain &lsquo;&mdash;' indicate a value of zero.  Number of species of North American birds that are known to produce high-amplitude or low-amplitude songs and calls. Percentages above each bar represent the percentage of the total number of species sampled in this study that produced each signal type.  Occurrence of low-amplitude songs and calls of 749 North American bird species sampled from the Birds of North American Online database ( Poole and Gill 2005 ) in courtship, territorial, alarm, and contact contexts. Low-amplitude songs were only scored as courtship or territorial. Percentages were calculated using the total number of species accounts that contained sufficient data to identify a putative function. See  Table 1  for percentages of the total number of species that are thought to produce each signal type.  For the 144 species that sang low-amplitude songs, 100 species accounts reported the occurrence of both high- and low-amplitude songs, and also contained either verbal descriptions of the structure of both classes of song or spectrograms that we used to determine whether any low-amplitude songs were likely to be divergent in structure from any high-amplitude songs. Among those accounts, 40 species (40&percnt;) sang a structurally divergent low-amplitude song, and 60 species (60&percnt;) sang a similar song at both high and low amplitudes. We noted that 88&percnt; (88 total) of these structural differentiations were based solely on each author's auditory perceptions, 11&percnt; (11 total) relied on visual comparisons of spectrograms of both high- and low-amplitude songs, and 1&percnt; (1 total) was the result of published quantitative data from spectrograms. The one species that had published quantitative data differentiating its high- and low-amplitude songs was the Dark-eyed Junco (  Junco hyemalis  ). An additional 18 species (of 144 total, 12.5&percnt;), many of which were members of the Corvidae family (crows, jays, and magpies), produced a low-amplitude song without producing any high-amplitude songs.  The low-amplitude vocalizations of 330 species (of 433 total, 76.2&percnt;) have been linked to at least one putative function ( Figure 2 ). Among the 73 species (of 144 total, 50.7&percnt;) that sang low-amplitude songs for which there was information about function, 56 (76.7&percnt;) species' songs were thought to serve a function in courtship, while the songs of 31 species (42.5&percnt;) reportedly performed a function in territoriality ( P  &lt; 0.001;  Figure 2 ). These functions were largely based on published (quality score &equals; 2; 38/74, 52.1&percnt;) or unpublished (quality score &equals; 1; 35/74, 47.9&percnt;) observations of the social context in which these songs were produced (the denominator here is 74 rather than 73 because 1 species produced 2 different low-amplitude songs and each had a different data quality score). None of these functional assignments were based solely on an experimental manipulation (quality score &equals; 3), but one species, the European Starling (  Sturnus vulgaris  ), had a functional assignment that was based on both an experimental manipulation and observational data (quality score &equals; 4, 1.4&percnt;).  Among the 303 species (of 374 total, 81.0&percnt;) for which functions were determined for their low-amplitude calls, 130 (42.9&percnt;) produced calls that were thought to perform a function in courtship, while 44 (14.5&percnt;) had calls that served a function in territoriality ( Figure 2 ). Additionally, 38 (12.5&percnt;) produced low-amplitude calls that functioned as alarm signals, and 223 (73.6&percnt;) used low-amplitude calls as contact calls ( Figure 2 ). Most of these functional assignments were based on published (quality score &equals; 2; 171/315, 54.3&percnt;) or unpublished (quality score &equals; 1; 141/315, 44.8&percnt;) observations of the social context in which these calls were produced. Two species (0.6&percnt;; Great Horned Owl &lsqb;  Bubo virginianus  &rsqb; and Long-billed Thrasher &lsqb; Toxostoma longirostre &rsqb;) produced low-amplitude calls with functions that were determined by experimental manipulations (quality score &equals; 3), and one species (0.3&percnt;), the Hermit Thrush (  Catharus guttatus  ), had a call function that was supported by both observations and experimental data (quality score &equals; 4).  Low-amplitude vocalizations were produced by both sexes. There were more species reports in which males sang low-amplitude songs (135/139, 97.1&percnt;) than species reports in which females sang low-amplitude songs (49/139, 35.3&percnt;,  P  &lt; 0.001;  Figure 3 ). In contrast, both males (329/367, 89.7&percnt;) and females (320/367, 87.2&percnt;,  P  &equals; 0.30) commonly produced low-amplitude calls ( Figure 3 ). The low-amplitude songs produced by both sexes were thought to have a function during courtship (males: 56/72, 77.8&percnt;; females: 17/19, 89.5&percnt;) in more cases than during territoriality (males: 30/72, 41.7&percnt;,  P  &lt; 0.001; females: 8/19, 42.1&percnt;,  P  &equals; 0.002). With respect to low-amplitude calls, both sexes produced calls that most commonly functioned as contact signals (males: 188/264, 68.9&percnt;; females: 210/262, 78.7&percnt;). Less common were low-amplitude calls that functioned as alarm signals (males: 13/264, 4.8&percnt;; females: 35/262, 13.1&percnt;) or in territorial behavior (males: 22/264, 8.1&percnt;; females: 28/262, 10.5&percnt;). Both sexes produced low-amplitude calls during courtship, but females (87/262, 32.6&percnt;) produced these signals more commonly than males (46/264, 16.8&percnt;,  P  &lt; 0.001). Many of the low-amplitude courtship calls produced by females were precopulatory calls that are thought to signal a willingness to copulate.  Production of low-amplitude songs and calls by males and females of 749 North American bird species sampled from the Birds of North American Online database ( Poole and Gill 2005 ). Percentages were calculated using the total number of species accounts that contained sufficient data to identify the sex of the singer rather than the total number of species thought to produce each signal type.  More than half of the North American bird species sampled in this study produced low-amplitude vocalizations. In addition, the majority of the orders sampled, including the three most speciose, exhibited low-amplitude vocalizations in more than 50&percnt; of the species sampled within these orders. In comparison, nearly all of the species sampled produce high-amplitude vocalizations. Additionally, mirroring the trend of high-amplitude songs in North America ( Price et al. 2009 ), species in which males produced low-amplitude songs were more common than species in which females produced low-amplitude songs. In contrast, both sexes commonly produced low-amplitude calls.  Given that low-amplitude songs are inconspicuous and are transmitted over shorter distances than high-amplitude songs ( Dabelsteen et al. 1993 ,  Balsby et al. 2003 ), the probability is high that the data summarized here represent an underestimate of the actual number of avian species that produce low-amplitude vocalizations in North America. Additionally, our reliance on data collected by a wide array of scientists with diverse backgrounds may also have contributed to the underestimate. In spite of these limitations, our results clearly indicate that low-amplitude vocalizations are common at a broad taxonomic scale, and further emphasize the necessity of more detailed studies of the production, functionality, and fitness implications of low-amplitude signaling in the future. To that end, we also attempted to expand our analysis using the recently established Neotropical Birds Online database ( Schulenberg 2013 ), but we found evidence for only 84 species producing low-amplitude vocalizations out of 403 completed species accounts. Such a low prevalence of low-amplitude vocalizations is most likely due to incomplete sampling rather than a distinct difference between temperate and tropical species in low-amplitude signaling, and this result further emphasizes the broader need for more studies that focus on low-amplitude signals.  To produce a low-amplitude vocalization, birds may simply reduce the amplitude of an existing high-amplitude vocalization without varying the signal's structure, or they may produce a low-amplitude vocalization with an acoustic structure that is divergent from any other signals in the species' repertoire. In this study, more than one-third of the species that sang low-amplitude songs produced a low-amplitude song that was described as structurally divergent from any high-amplitude song produced by that species. However, it is important to note that the vast majority of these cases relied on each author's auditory perceptions rather than quantitative data, and, as such, these data need to be interpreted with some caution. In addition to the potential for observer biases, these observations are also likely to be representative of only a small number of exemplars of low-amplitude songs in each species, which further limits our ability to draw clear conclusions regarding any differences in acoustic structure. This clear lack of quantitative data comparing high- and low-amplitude songs (but see  Titus 1998 ,  Anderson et al. 2008 ) highlights a valuable area for future research. Future studies comparing the structural differences of high- and low-amplitude songs may provide insights into the physiological tradeoffs and constraints associated with vocalizing at different amplitudes ( Cardoso 2010 ), as well as novel hypotheses relating to the ontogeny of structurally divergent vocal signals either through genetic or cultural inheritance (Cardoso and Reichard in press).  The finding that some low-amplitude songs can be structurally divergent or even distinct is also important in that it suggests that certain low-amplitude vocalizations represent an entirely separate class of signal, with information content and functions that may complement or contrast with the other vocalizations in a species' repertoire. Thus, studies of song repertoires that seek to relate aspects of repertoire size or composition to an individual's fitness or phenotype may be overlooking a key component of the vocal repertoire if low-amplitude songs are ignored. In some contentious cases, such as studies investigating the link between female preferences and male repertoire size, the inclusion of low-amplitude songs that are sung during courtship interactions may provide a more complete test of the relationship between male repertoires and female preferences than what is currently recognized ( Searcy and Nowicki 2005 ,  Byers and Kroodsma 2009 ).  From a functional standpoint, our survey suggests that both low-amplitude songs and calls serve functions in courtship around twice as often as in territorial interactions, and low-amplitude calls function predominantly as contact signals and less frequently as alarm signals. With respect to low-amplitude songs, the majority of our functional assignments occurred in passerine species (67/73, 91.8&percnt;), which severely limits our interpretive power beyond that clade. Within the passerine species sampled, we noted that of the 18 species that produced low-amplitude songs, but no high-amplitude songs, 10 were members of the family Corvidae. This lack of a loud advertising song in corvids may be related to the social stability associated with year-round territories and long-term pair bonding present in many of these species, and the production of low-amplitude songs in male&ndash;female contexts could contribute to pair-bond stability and maintenance ( Poole and Gill 2005 ). However, more empirical data are needed to adequately test these hypotheses. The functional assignments for calls were more evenly distributed across the orders that were sampled; however, the results for both songs and calls should be interpreted with caution, given that nearly all of these functional assignments were based solely on published or unpublished observations of the social context in which these signals were produced, without any experimental manipulations. Additionally, some of these accounts have not been updated to reflect the recent surge of research on low-amplitude songs in a number of North American songbirds ( Anderson et al. 2007 ,  Ballentine et al. 2008 ,  Hof and Hazlett 2010 ).  Given these limitations, whether low-amplitude vocalizations are actually more prevalent in courtship than in aggressive interactions remains an open question. However, it is also worth considering that, unlike high-amplitude songs, which have the capacity to reach multiple types of receivers and serve multiple functions simultaneously, low-amplitude songs are more restricted in their transmission distance (e.g.,  Balsby et al. 2003 ) and are often directed toward a clear, close-proximity receiver. Consequently, the pool of potential receivers is much more limited for low-amplitude signals, which increases the interpretive power of observational data alone in identifying putative functions. Thus, the majority of the function data for low-amplitude vocalizations presented here that utilized observational data is likely to be more reliable than identical data collected for high-amplitude signals, which are typically the focus of tests of signal function. Furthermore, these observational data still clearly suggest that low-amplitude signals are being produced by a variety of species in social contexts that have clear fitness implications, such as courtship, aggression, and antipredator behavior.  Focusing on courtship, it is well established that many species of birds rely on high-amplitude songs to initially attract a mate, and that after a female approaches, signals from multiple modalities (i.e. visual, tactile, auditory, and olfactory), including low-amplitude songs, can be employed to further court and stimulate the female ( Catchpole and Slater 2008 ). The low-amplitude songs produced during directed courtship can be structurally distinct and more complex than the high-amplitude songs used in mate attraction ( Dabelsteen et al. 1998 ,  Balsby 2000 ,  Reichard et al. 2011 ). Based on a similar signaling system in crickets,  Zuk et al. (2008)  hypothesized that females may rely predominantly on high-amplitude, mate-attraction songs for information relating to species recognition, and low-amplitude, courtship songs for information about male quality. If accurate, this hypothesis would suggest that females should rely more heavily on low-amplitude songs when making their final mate choice decisions.  In support of this argument in birds, a  y -maze choice test of female mating preferences in Dark-eyed Juncos (  Junco hyemalis  ) showed a robust female preference for hormone-manipulated males that sang significantly more complex, low-amplitude songs, but did not differ from control males in high-amplitude song production or feather displays ( Enstrom et al. 1997 ). However, manipulated males in this study also differed in aspects of their visual courtship display, which may have contributed to the observed differences in female preference. Similarly, in two species of cricket, female  Gryllus lineaticeps  preferred males that had a high-quality, low-amplitude courtship song paired with a low-quality, high-amplitude calling song over males with the opposite pairing ( Wagner and Reiser 2000 ), and previously nonpreferred male  Teleogryllus oceanicus  became preferred when silenced and paired with playback of a high-quality, low-amplitude courtship song ( Rebar et al. 2009 ). These studies are part of a small but growing body of evidence suggesting that studies of mating preferences in birds and other species that focus only on high-amplitude signals are missing a critical signal in the courtship display.  One unifying question underlying all research on low-amplitude signals is, Why are these signals produced softly rather than loudly? A number of hypotheses have been put forth to explain the occurrence of low-amplitude signaling in birds, such as the &lsquo;eavesdropping avoidance hypothesis' and the &lsquo;readiness hypothesis' (see below; also reviewed and discussed in  Dabelsteen 2005 ,  Ak&ccedil;ay et al. 2011 ,  Osiejuk 2011 ,  Ak&ccedil;ay and Beecher 2012 ), but there have been very few experimental tests of the advantages of producing quiet signals across multiple behavioral contexts (but see  Balsby and Dabelsteen 2005 ,  Searcy and Nowicki 2006 ). Furthermore, difficulties of measuring amplitude in free-living animals have limited our ability to identify physiological tradeoffs between amplitude and other aspects of song structure (but see  Cardoso 2010 ) that could help to explain why certain songs, such as complex courtship songs, are produced only at low amplitude.  Setting aside the possibility of physiological constraints, the selective factors that are driving the evolution of low-amplitude signals are likely to differ across social contexts. For example, during courtship interactions the potential benefit of producing inconspicuous signals in order to avoid attracting the attention of eavesdropping male conspecific competitors seems clear (i.e. the &lsquo;eavesdroping avoidance hypothesis';  Dabelsteen 2005 ). However, during aggressive interactions, males may actually benefit from broadly advertising the result of a dominance interaction, particularly if female eavesdroppers are present ( Mennill et al. 2002 ). Thus, simple eavesdropping avoidance appears unable to explain low-amplitude signaling in all contexts, but males may still gain other advantages from signaling softly, such as increased vigilance (i.e. the &lsquo;readiness hypothesis';  Ak&ccedil;ay et al. 2011 ), which is likely to be important in elevated aggressive interactions. Without additional tests of these hypotheses across different species and signaling systems, our understanding of the factors selecting for low-amplitude signaling will remain limited.  As a whole, low-amplitude signals represent a frontier in research on animal communication, with basic questions about signal structure and more complex questions about the evolution of inconspicuous signals remaining to be thoroughly investigated. Low-amplitude signals have been recognized in many individual species across a wide array of animal taxa, and here we show that low-amplitude vocalizations are relatively common across all birds that breed in North America. The ubiquity of low-amplitude vocalizations and their apparent functions in both male&ndash;female and male&ndash;male interactions increases the likelihood that these signals are serving underappreciated, yet important roles in mediating behavioral interactions that affect fitness, which warrants more research. Future work on acoustic signaling in all contexts should consider the animal's entire vocal repertoire in analyses, rather than focusing exclusively on the signals that are conspicuous to the human ear and easy to record.  This study would not have been possible without access to the Birds of North America Online database, which was provided by the Cornell University, Indiana University, and University of California&ndash;Davis libraries. We thank Ellen Ketterson for comments on the manuscript and members of the Ketterson research group for many stimulating conversations on this topic. D. G. Reichard was funded by a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship. 