Comparative population structure of cavity-nesting sea ducksApparent survival, natal philopatry, and recruitment of Barrow's Goldeneyes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>) in the Cariboo-Chilcotin region of British Columbia, CanadaNest boxes facilitate local-scale conservation of Common Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala clangula</named-content></italic>) and Bufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>) in Alberta, CanadaCurrent and projected abundance of potential nest sites for cavity-nesting ducks in hardwoods of the north central United StatesCommon Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala clangula</named-content></italic>)Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>)A comparison of the characteristics and fate of Barrow's Goldeneye and Bufflehead nests in nest boxes and natural cavitiesArlequin suite ver 3.5: A new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and WindowsChanges in size and trends of North American sea duck populations associated with North Pacific oceanic regime shiftsBreeding season sympatry in Northern Pintails facilitates genetic exchange among allopatric wintering populations in Japan and CaliforniaMechanisms of population differentiation in seabirdsPhilopatry, nest-site fidelity, and reproductive performance in BuffleheadsBufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>)Phylogeography of the <italic>Calonectris</italic> shearwaters using molecular and morphometric dataEuropean flyway permeability and abmigration in teal <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas crecca</named-content></italic>, an analysis based on ringing recoveriesPostglacial colonisation patterns and the role of isolation and expansion in driving diversification in a passerine birdIdentification of conservation units in the European <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mergus merganser</named-content></italic> based on nuclear and mitochondrial DNA markersThe genetic legacy of the Quaternary ice agesEcology and management of postbreeding waterfowlUsing GIS to analyze animal movements in the marine environmentDiscord reigns among nuclear, mitochondrial and phenotypic estimates of divergence in nine lineages of trans-Beringian birdsA phylogeographic and population genetic analysis of a widespread, sedentary North American bird: The Hairy Woodpecker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Picoides villosus</named-content></italic>)Global lack of flyway structure in a cosmopolitan bird revealed by a genome wide survey of single nucleotide polymorphismsSite fidelity is an inconsistent determinant of population structure in the Hooded Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lophodytes cucullatus</named-content></italic>): Evidence from genetic, mark&ndash;recapture, and comparative dataMigratory patterns and population structure among breeding and wintering Red-breasted Mergansers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mergus serrator</named-content></italic>) and Common Mergansers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. merganser</named-content></italic>)Limited genetic differentiation among breeding, molting, and wintering groups of the threatened Steller's Eider: The role of historic and contemporary factorsLack of spatial genetic structure among nesting and wintering King EidersMechanisms of population heterogeneity among molting Common Mergansers on Kodiak Island, Alaska: Implications for genetic assessments of migratory connectivityBehavioural vs. molecular sources of conflict between nuclear and mitochondrial DNA: The role of male-biased dispersal in a Holarctic sea duckLate Pleistocene divergence between eastern and western populations of Wood Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>) inferred by the &lsquo;isolation with migration' coalescent methodNuclear loci and coalescent methods support ancient hybridization as cause of mitochondrial paraphyly between Gadwall and Falcated Duck (Anas spp.)Comparative phylogeography of five avian species: Implications for Pleistocene evolutionary history in the Qinghai-Tibetan plateauRelationship among breeding, molting, and wintering areas of male Barrow's Goldeneyes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>) in eastern North AmericaWinter philopatry in migratory waterfowlTiming of pairing in waterfowl II: Testing the hypotheses with Harlequin DucksThe moult migrationIntra- and inter-specific competition between Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>) and Bufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>)Relationships among breeding, molting and wintering areas of adult female Barrow's Goldeneyes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>) in eastern North AmericaSex-biased gene flow in Spectacled Eiders (Anatidae): Inferences from molecular markers with contrasting modes of inheritanceMultilocus phylogeography of Common Eiders (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Somateria mollissima</named-content></italic>) breeding in North America and ScandinaviaOrigin and availability of large cavities for Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>), a species at risk inhabiting the eastern Canadian boreal forestFaBox: An online toolbox for FASTA sequencesComparative biogeography of some aridland bird speciesA growing collection of mtDNA genetic information from waterfowl species across North America suggests that larger-bodied cavity-nesting species exhibit greater levels of population differentiation than smaller-bodied congeners. Although little is known about nest-cavity availability for these species, one hypothesis to explain differences in population structure is reduced dispersal tendency of larger-bodied cavity-nesting species due to limited abundance of large cavities. To investigate this hypothesis, we examined population structure of three cavity-nesting waterfowl species distributed across much of North America: Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>), Common Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>), and Bufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. albeola</named-content></italic>). We compared patterns of population structure using both variation in mtDNA control-region sequences and band-recovery data for the same species and geographic regions. Results were highly congruent between data types, showing structured population patterns for Barrow's and Common Goldeneye but not for Bufflehead. Consistent with our prediction, the smallest cavity-nesting species, the Bufflehead, exhibited the lowest level of population differentiation due to increased dispersal and gene flow. Results provide evidence for discrete Old and New World populations of Common Goldeneye and for differentiation of regional groups of both goldeneye species in Alaska, the Pacific Northwest, and the eastern coast of North America. Results presented here will aid management objectives that require an understanding of population delineation and migratory connectivity between breeding and wintering areas. Comparative studies such as this one highlight factors that may drive patterns of genetic diversity and population trends.Una colecci&oacute;n creciente de informaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica del ADN mitocondrial (ADNmt) de especies de aves acu&aacute;ticas a trav&eacute;s de Norteam&eacute;rica sugiere que entre las especies que anidan en cavidades, aquellas de tama&ntilde;o grande exhiben mayores niveles de diferenciaci&oacute;n poblacional que sus cong&eacute;neres de tama&ntilde;o m&aacute;s peque&ntilde;o. Aunque se conoce poco sobre la disponibilidad de cavidades para que estas especies aniden, una hip&oacute;tesis para explicar las diferencias en la estructura poblacional es la tendencia a la dispersi&oacute;n reducida de especies de tama&ntilde;o m&aacute;s grande que anidan en cavidades debido a la abundancia limitada de cavidades grandes. Para evaluar esta hip&oacute;tesis, examinamos la estructura poblacional de tres especies de patos anidantes en cavidades que se distribuyen a trav&eacute;s de Norteam&eacute;rica: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>, y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. albeola</named-content></italic>. Comparamos los patrones de estructura poblacional usando la variaci&oacute;n en secuencias de la Regi&oacute;n Control del ADNmt y los datos de recuperaci&oacute;n de anillos para las mismas especies y regiones geogr&aacute;ficas. Los resultados fueron &aacute;ltamente congruentes entre tipos de datos, demostrando patrones de poblaciones estructuradas en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. islandica</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>, pero no en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. albeola</named-content></italic>. De acuerdo con nuestras predicciones, la especie anidante de cavidades de menor tama&ntilde;o, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. albeola</named-content>,</italic> exhibi&oacute; el menor nivel de diferenciaci&oacute;n poblacional debido a su mayor dispersi&oacute;n y flujo gen&eacute;tico. Los resultados proveen evidencia de la existencia de poblaciones discretas del Viejo y del Nuevo Mundo en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>, y de diferenciaci&oacute;n de grupos regionales de <italic>B. isl&aacute;ndica</italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic> en Alaska, el Pac&iacute;fico noroccidental y la costa este de Norteam&eacute;rica. Los resultados aqu&iacute; presentados ser&aacute;n de ayuda para el manejo de poblaciones que requiera de un entendimiento de la delimitaci&oacute;n poblacional y la conectividad migratoria entre sitios de reproducci&oacute;n y sitios de invernada. Los estudios comparativos como este resaltan los factores que podr&iacute;an generar patrones de diversidad gen&eacute;tica y tendencias poblacionales.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>, recuperaci&oacute;n de anillos, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala clangula</named-content></italic>, anidantes en cavidades, conectividad migratoria, ADN mitocondrial, gen&eacute;tica de poblacionesComparative population genetic approaches to the examination of multiple and widespread species are useful in determining whether each taxon has been similarly influenced by historical isolating mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Avise1">Avise 2000</xref>). Two main conclusions can be made from recent comparative population genetic studies of avian species. First, sympatric taxa distributed across similar regions exhibit a range of phylogeographic patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Zink1">Zink et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Qu1">Qu et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Humphries1">Humphries and Winker 2011</xref>). Second, levels of population genetic structure are not correlated with taxonomic similarity (i.e. closely related taxa do not share similar phylogeographic patterns, genetic diversity values, and levels of gene flow between populations; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-GomezDiaz1">G&oacute;mez-D&iacute;az et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Friesen1">Friesen et al. 2007</xref>). Thus, comparisons among species can aid in the identification of isolating barriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2011</xref>) and their demographic impacts on populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Hewitt1">Hewitt 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Hansson1">Hansson et al. 2008</xref>). Additionally, genetic information can be used to infer aspects of species biology, such as flexibility of natural- and life-history traits, and thus the response to past and future changes in climate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Qu1">Qu et al. 2010</xref>).Sea ducks (tribe Mergini) are a group of 18 extant waterfowl species distributed across a variety of habitats, largely in the Northern Hemisphere, the Brazilian Merganser (<italic>Mergus octosetaceus</italic>) being the exception (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Johnsgard1">Johnsgard 1965</xref>). Of these 18 species, 7 are either obligate or semi-obligate cavity-nesting species, all 7 of which are secondary cavity-nesters, which means that they rely on naturally occurring cavities from tree decay or breakage or on excavator species that bore holes into trees. High levels of nest-site fidelity, a possible indicator of population structure, are well documented in nest-box studies of cavity-nesting sea ducks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Gauthier1">Gauthier 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Gauthier2">1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Eadie1">Eadie et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Eadie2">2000</xref>). However, patterns of fidelity may be driven by variables other than cavity availability, such as competition, food requirements, brood habitat, and body size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Boyd1">Boyd et al. 2009</xref>). For example, despite high levels of breeding-site fidelity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce1">Pearce et al. (2008)</xref> found little evidence of population genetic structure in the Hooded Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lophodytes cucullatus</named-content></italic>), which likely are not limited by nest-cavity availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Denton1">Denton et al. 2012</xref>). By contrast, another cavity-nesting sea duck, the Common Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. merganser</named-content></italic>), exhibits a high degree of population genetic structure across North America (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f01">Figure 1</xref>). These findings led <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. (2009a)</xref> to hypothesize that population structure among cavity-nesting ducks could be influenced by body size and cavity competition. Among cavity-nesting species of waterfowl, the Common Merganser has the largest body size, requiring larger cavities that may be rare in some forested landscapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Vaillancourt1">Vaillancourt et al. 2009</xref>). As a result, the Common Merganser may exhibit greater fidelity and population structure than smaller-bodied congeners (e.g., the Hooded Merganser). Thus, there may be a positive relationship between body size and level of population structure among cavity-nesting waterfowl due to a greater abundance of smaller cavities and rarity of large cavities.Estimates of genetic differentiation for 11 waterfowl species, as measured by <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> from large, geographic-scale studies in North America. Cavity-nesting species are shown in bold. For five species, both mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) and nuclear DNA (nuDNA) results are shown to illustrate the lower levels of population differentiation observed with nuDNA markers in waterfowl species. From left to right, species names represent results from Bufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>; this study), King Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Somateria spectabilis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce4">Pearce et al. 2004</xref>), Steller's Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polysticta stelleri</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce3">Pearce et al. 2005</xref>), Hooded Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lophodytes cucullatus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce1">Pearce et al. 2008</xref>), Spectacled Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. fischeri</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Scribner1">Scribner et al. 2001</xref>), Red-breasted Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mergus serrator</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. 2009a</xref>), Wood Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aix sponsa</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Peters2">Peters et al. 2005</xref>), Common Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. mollissima</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Sonsthagen1">Sonsthagen et al. 2011</xref>), Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. islandica</named-content></italic>; this study), Common Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>; this study), and Common Merganser (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">M. merganser</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce5">2009b</xref>). Studies with <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &gt; 0.2 represent cases of significant population structuring (category II from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Avise1">Avise 2000</xref>). For mtDNA, values are based on control-region sequences, except for King Eider and Steller's Eider, which are from cytochrome <italic>b</italic>.We further explored the hypothesis that relative body size may influence population structure in cavity-nesting sea ducks by examining three additional species: Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala islandica</named-content></italic>), Common Goldeneye (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. clangula</named-content></italic>), and Bufflehead (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. albeola</named-content></italic>). Our prediction was that small-bodied cavity-nesting birds would show lower levels of population structuring because of their ability to use a wider variety of cavities for nesting (i.e. both small- and large-diameter trees), whereas large-bodied birds would be restricted to nesting in relatively large-diameter trees with cavities. To test this, we determined the extent of population overlap, in terms of geographic overlap and gene flow, using leg-band recovery information and mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) sequence data collected across broad geographic regions (Alaska, western and eastern North America, Iceland, and Denmark). Although nuclear DNA (e.g., microsatellite loci) often are incorporated into population genetic studies for a more contemporary perspective on gene flow, levels of differentiation among waterfowl species for these molecular markers typically are very low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f01">Figure 1</xref>) because of male-mediated dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Peters1">Peters et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Kraus1">Kraus et al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, instead of nuclear DNA, we incorporated analyses of band-recovery data for an independent perspective on the structure of migratory flyways and populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Guillemain1">Guillemain et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Flint2">Flint et al. 2009</xref>). Because of the relative ease of capturing Common Goldeneye, Barrow's Goldeneye, and Bufflehead in artificial nest boxes and by other methods, thousands of individuals of these species have been banded across North America and Europe.We used band recoveries to delineate wintering areas used by birds of each species captured in different breeding areas and to determine the extent of overlap between winter distributions as an indicator of potential gene flow. Because pair-bond formation in waterfowl likely occurs on nonbreeding areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Rodway1">Rodway 2007</xref>), overlap or use of multiple wintering areas by a breeding population may influence dispersal and, thus, gene flow among populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Robertson1">Robertson and Cooke 1999</xref>). Therefore, we plotted band recoveries for each of the three <italic>Bucephala</italic> species within North America, focusing on broad regional scales that resembled our DNA sampling scheme (below). All band-recovery data were provided by the U.S. Geological Survey Bird Banding Laboratory (BBL; downloaded July 2011). In some cases, recoveries were grouped by geographic area for analysis (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>). We used only band-recovery data from normal, wild birds that were shot, retrieved, and reported (i.e. no &ldquo;found dead&rdquo; or &ldquo;injured&rdquo; types of recoveries). The final dataset contained a total of 1,827 band recoveries from across North America (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>). We plotted locations of leg-band recoveries made in winter (November&ndash;March) for ducks banded during summer (May&ndash;August). Because we were interested in the degree of population overlap between genetic and band-recovery data, we did not map recovery data separately for each age, sex, and recovery type (i.e. direct vs. indirect). Similarly, genetic data were not analyzed separately by age, sex, or resident&ndash;migrant status. This allowed us to maximize the detection of population overlap in both genetic and band-recovery datasets.Summary of DNA and band-recovery data from 1934 to 2009 used to examine population structure in Barrow's Goldeneye, Common Goldeneye, and Bufflehead within and outside North America (also see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Numbers represent sample sizes of DNA from each location and numbers of band-recovery reports from birds banded in the same areas. Additional sampling and mtDNA haplotype information is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t02">Table 2</xref> in the Appendix.Location of DNA sample locations for Barrow's Goldeneye, Common Goldeneye, and Bufflehead in (<bold>A</bold>) Alaska&ndash;Yukon and western North America and (<bold>B</bold>) eastern North America. Additional Barrow's and Common Goldeneye samples were obtained from Iceland and Denmark, respectively (not shown). (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of Barrow's Goldeneye summer banding locations (large open circles) and winter band recoveries, colored by banding area: Alaska&ndash;Yukon (white) and western North America (gray). Circles of both banding and recovery locations may represent more than one event. (<bold>D</bold>) 95&percnt; kernel home ranges for recoveries of birds banded in Alaska&ndash;Yukon (white polygon) and western North America (gray polygon).We used a kernel home-range analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Hooge1">Hooge et al. 2001</xref>) in ArcView to estimate the 95&percnt; utilization area for band recoveries from each regional group. Our use of winter band recoveries excludes northward molt migration or postbreeding dispersal that may take place after banding and before recovery during winter. Long-distance and northward molt and postbreeding migrations are common in waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Salomonsen1">Salomonsen 1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Hohman1">Hohman et al. 1992</xref>) and may substantially broaden the geographic distribution of certain breeding populations. However, band recoveries from molt-migration areas do not appear in the BBL database, likely because these migrations occur in late summer and well before the start of the sport hunting season (i.e. when most waterfowl bands are recovered).We obtained a total of 311 DNA samples from across North America and Europe (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t02">Table 2</xref> in the Appendix) for Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 115), Common Goldeneye (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 98), and Bufflehead (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 98) through captures of breeding birds, collection of nest-box material, tissues from scientific collections in summer, and tissues from birds harvested by sport hunters during fall and winter. Because few breeding samples were available for all species and geographic areas, winter samples (collected between October 1 and January 31) were obtained from tissues of male and female birds collected by hunters in North America (for all three species) and Denmark (Common Goldeneye only) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>). For Bufflehead, only 5 breeding samples were available from the Yukon Territory. The remaining 93 samples were collected during winter. Because of these sampling constraints, we limited our molecular computations to broad regional differences in mtDNA nucleotide diversity.We extracted DNA from all samples using methods described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce1">Pearce et al. (2008)</xref>. We amplified and sequenced an approximately 400-base-pair fragment of the control region (domain I) of mtDNA by using primers MMCRL F and MMCRL R, which were designed for the Common Merganser in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-HeftiGautschi1">Hefti-Gautschi et al. 2009</xref>) and following methods described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. (2009a)</xref>. We aligned all sequences with the program AlignIR version 2.0 (LI-COR, Lincoln, Nebraska) and organized multiple sequences into unique haplotypes using FaBox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Villesen1">Villesen 2007</xref>). The final sequence length used in analyses was 400 bases in Barrow's Goldeneye, 442 bases in Common Goldeneye, and 462 bases in Bufflehead. To assess levels of genetic differentiation among breeding locations, we calculated overall and population pairwise levels of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> from haplotype frequencies using Nei's average distance in the program Arlequin version 3.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Excoffier1">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>). We examined the homogeneity of mtDNA haplotype distributions within and among populations using an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) in Arlequin and inferred haplotype diversity for each species and sampling region using haplotype networks. All mtDNA haplotypes have been accessioned in GenBank (KF954779&ndash;KF954851).There were 462 winter recoveries of Barrow's Goldeneye banded during the summer between 1948 and 2009 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>), and the greatest percentage (51&percnt;) of recoveries of these bands occurred in November. Barrow's Goldeneye recoveries were banded as a mix of ages (48&percnt; juveniles, 52&percnt; adult) and sexes (28&percnt; male, 31&percnt; female, 41&percnt; unknown). A map of 95&percnt; kernel home ranges of all band recoveries showed no overlap between birds banded in Alaska and British Columbia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f02">Figure 2</xref>D), but some individual recovery locations were within 450 km of each other in southeast Alaska and coastal British Columbia. Most Alaska recoveries were concentrated around Kodiak Island and the northern portion of the Gulf of Alaska, whereas recoveries of banded birds banded in British Columbia were distributed near the original banding sites and in western Washington.There were 882 winter recoveries of Common Goldeneye banded during summer between 1940 and 2010 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">3</xref>B), with the greatest percentage (57&percnt;) of recoveries occurring in November. Most birds (73&percnt;) were banded as juveniles, and sexes were approximately equal (50&percnt; male, 47&percnt; female, 3&percnt; unknown). The lack of band-recovery data from birds marked in British Columbia prohibited comparison with those banded in Alaska. Consequently, it is unknown whether these two breeding populations winter in different geographic areas. A map of the 95&percnt; kernel home ranges of band recoveries of Common Goldeneye marked in Alaska showed no overlap with other recovery distributions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>C). However, some Common Goldeneye recoveries occurred within 350 km of each other (in southeast Alaska and coastal British Columbia), and 2 Common Goldeneye banded in Alaska were recovered well outside the Alaska kernel home range (1 in southwestern Manitoba and 1 in southern California). Birds banded in Alberta and Saskatchewan had similar recovery distributions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>C), with most bands (87&percnt;) encountered west of Saskatchewan banding areas (&minus;102.4&deg; longitude). Recoveries from nearly all eastern banding areas (Maine, Quebec, and New Brunswick) were distributed within the region of banding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">3</xref>D). A portion of the 95&percnt; kernel home range for Alberta overlapped that of Ontario banding areas in the Great Lakes and Chesapeake Bay regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">3</xref>D). Recoveries of Common Goldeneye banded in Minnesota and Ontario were predominantly distributed in the eastern United States and Canada (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>D). Only 9&percnt; of Minnesota bands were recovered west of &minus;96.0&deg; longitude, the position of the westernmost banding location. Home ranges for Minnesota- and Ontario-banded Common Goldeneye also overlapped in the Great Lakes and Chesapeake Bay regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">Figure 3</xref>D).(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of Common Goldeneye summer banding locations (large open circles) and winter band recoveries colored by banding area: Alaska (white), Alberta and Saskatchewan (black), and eastern North America (gray). (<bold>B</bold>) Distribution of Common Goldeneye summer banding locations (large open circles) and winter band recoveries by banding area: Minnesota (white) and Ontario (black). Circles of both banding and recovery locations may represent more than one event. (<bold>C</bold>) 95&percnt; kernel home ranges for winter band recoveries of birds banded in Alaska (stippled polygon), Alberta (horizontal striping), Saskatchewan (gray), and eastern North America (black). (<bold>D</bold>) 95&percnt; kernel home ranges for winter band recoveries of birds banded in Minnesota (black polygon) and Ontario (gray).There were 483 winter recoveries of Bufflehead banded during the summers of 1934&ndash;2009 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-t01">Table 1</xref>), and these occurred primarily (41&percnt;) in November. No summer banding data were available from the Atlantic Coast of North America. At the time of banding, birds were mostly (70&percnt;) adult and sexes were evenly distributed (42&percnt; male, 43&percnt; female, 15&percnt; unknown). Similar to those of Barrow's Goldeneye, winter recoveries of Bufflehead banded in British Columbia were distributed along the western North American coast. However, birds banded in Alaska also may winter within the geographic distribution of those banded in British Columbia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f04">Figure 4</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f04">4</xref>C). The broad spatial distribution of band recoveries for Bufflehead across North America (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f04">Figure 4</xref>B) resulted in 95&percnt; kernel home ranges that include a greater amount of offshore ocean areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f04">Figure 4</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f04">4</xref>D), which is likely an overestimation of coastal distribution.(<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of Bufflehead summer banding locations (large open circles) and winter band recoveries, colored by banding area: Alaska (white) and western North America (black). Map does not show one band recovery in Maine (from British Columbia) and one in Kamchatka, Russia (from Alaska). (<bold>B</bold>) Distribution of Bufflehead summer banding locations (large open circles) and winter band recoveries, colored by banding area in central North America: Alberta (black) and Saskatchewan (gray). Circles of both banding and recovery locations may represent more than one event. (<bold>C</bold>) 95&percnt; kernel home ranges for winter band recoveries of birds banded in Alaska (gray) and western North America (black). (<bold>D</bold>) 95&percnt; kernel home ranges for winter recoveries of birds banded in central North America: Alberta (dark gray polygon) and Saskatchewan (light gray).A similar number of mtDNA haplotypes were observed in Barrow's Goldeneye (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17) and Common Goldeneye (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 16) samples collected in North America and Iceland. Bufflehead exhibited a larger number of haplotypes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 28). An additional 12 Common Goldeneye haplotypes were observed in Danish samples. Haplotype diversity was variable across sampling regions for all species but was remarkably similar among North American and Icelandic samples of Barrow's and Common Goldeneye (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">5</xref>B). Each region had one or a few common haplotypes, with a few additional rarer haplotypes differentiated from the common lineage by a single nucleotide substitution. Samples of Barrow's Goldeneye from Iceland were all identical in haplotype. Winter samples of Common Goldeneye from Denmark exhibited much higher haplotype diversity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>B), as did Bufflehead samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>C).MtDNA haplotype networks for (<bold>A</bold>) Barrow's Goldeneye (black for Alaska, gray for British Columbia, white for Quebec, and diagonal for Iceland), (<bold>B</bold>) Common Goldeneye (black for Alaska&ndash;Yukon, gray for British Columbia, white for Ontario, light gray for Denmark), and (<bold>C</bold>) Bufflehead (black for Alaska&ndash;Yukon and Northwest Territories, gray for western North America, and white for eastern North America; see text). A single site substitution links each circle except where bars are present, which denote multiple substitutions between haplotypes. Circles are drawn proportionally to the observed number of each haplotype. The smallest open circles in each network represent inferred haplotypes that were not sampled. Numbers within larger circles correspond to the haplotype number.North American samples of Barrow's Goldeneye clustered into three groups of haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>A) that correspond closely to the geographic region of sampling (Alaska, British Columbia and Idaho, and Quebec). Overall genetic differentiation among sampling areas was high (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.576, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and all pairwise tests (not shown) were similarly high (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> range: 0.313&ndash;0.921), with the greatest value between the British Columbia and Iceland samples. The AMOVA revealed that 57.6&percnt; of the total genetic variation was distributed among populations.North American Common Goldeneye samples clustered into three groups of haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>B) corresponding to the geographic region of sample collection (Alaska and Yukon, British Columbia, and Ontario). Denmark was a separate group and differed by 12 bases from North American samples. The only evidence of haplotype sharing among sampling regions occurred between Ontario and the Yukon Territory (haplotype 3). All three Ontario samples with this haplotype were from immature birds collected in June and July, and the Yukon samples were from adult birds sampled in April. The overall difference among sampling areas was relatively high (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.825, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and all pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> statistics (not shown) were high and significant among North American comparisons (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> range: 0.398&ndash;0.664) and between North American and Danish sampling areas (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> range: 0.844&ndash;0.913). In the AMOVA, 82.6&percnt; of the total genetic variation was distributed among populations. The proportion of the total genetic variation explained by differences among populations was 52.8&percnt; when the Danish samples were excluded from the analysis.For Bufflehead, there were two common haplotypes (1 and 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>C) found in all North American sampling areas. Singleton haplotypes also were observed in each of the three broad sampling regions. The overall genetic difference among sampling areas was low (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; &minus;0.007, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.731), and all pairwise comparisons yielded similarly low and nonsignificant <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values, including between Alaska and Eastern North America (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; &minus;0.001, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.324). Thus, Bufflehead (the smallest species) exhibited the lowest level of mtDNA population differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f01">Figure 1</xref>).Consistent with our prediction, the smallest cavity-nesting species, the Bufflehead, exhibited the lowest level of population differentiation, whereas Barrow's and Common Goldeneye displayed intermediate levels of population genetic structure compared with those of the Common Merganser (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Although correlative, our results link species-specific genetic differentiation to nest-cavity requirements that may be driven by differences in body size. While others have suggested that site availability may be limiting for cavity-nesting species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Vaillancourt1">Vaillancourt et al. 2009</xref>), our data suggest that such limitation has, over time, had a greater influence on larger-bodied species. As such, our results suggest that it may be useful to examine the status and trends of nest cavities suitable for larger-bodied species of sea ducks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Denton1">Denton et al. 2012</xref>). Additionally, data presented here aid in the identification of populations for monitoring by delineating regional groups and revealing patterns of migratory connectivity between breeding and wintering areas.None of the study species displayed levels of differentiation observed in the Common Merganser (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-HeftiGautschi1">Hefti-Gautschi et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce5">2009b</xref>), the largest cavity-nesting sea duck. Thus, there may be a cost of breeding dispersal to large-bodied species (Common Merganser and both goldeneye) in terms of locating suitable cavities in unfamiliar habitats before the initiation of the nesting period. By contrast, smaller-bodied cavity-nesting waterfowl such as the Bufflehead and Hooded Merganser may exhibit more inconsistent patterns of natal and breeding fidelity because smaller cavities may be more abundant and dispersal may be a mechanism to limit intraspecific aggression observed among cavity-nesting waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Savard1">Savard 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Boyd1">Boyd et al. 2009</xref>). Other natural history attributes are likely involved in patterns of population structure among cavity-nesting waterfowl, but smaller body size may facilitate dispersal. Other observations corroborate our conclusions of higher dispersal and gene flow in Bufflehead than in their larger-bodied congeners. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Corrigan1">Corrigan et al. (2011)</xref> found a consistently lower artificial-cavity occupancy rate for Bufflehead in comparison to Common Goldeneye, suggesting that natural cavities were not limited for Bufflehead on the study areas examined. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Evans1">Evans et al. (2002)</xref> found that the average volume of natural nest cavities for Bufflehead was less than half that of natural cavities used by Barrow's Goldeneye and that natural cavities used by Bufflehead were located in smaller trees with smaller entrance openings. The ability to nest in smaller and, likely, younger trees would facilitate dispersal and colonization. Accordingly, we observed a star-like mtDNA haplotype network for Bufflehead (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>C), which is a common pattern in species that show evidence of population expansion or high rates of dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Avise1">Avise 2000</xref>).We found general agreement between two independent data sources (mtDNA variation and band-recovery information) regarding the continental-scale spatial patterns of population subdivision for Bufflehead, Barrow's Goldeneye, and Common Goldeneye. This comparison is more informative than comparing mtDNA with nuclear DNA because it provides direct quantification of migratory connectivity between breeding and wintering areas, and of winter distribution overlap among different breeding populations. Nuclear DNA is often used as an independent assessment of patterns of population differentiation and evolutionary history inferred from mtDNA. However, such comparative assessments (using nuclear and mtDNA) in waterfowl often are of limited value because male gene flow homogenizes allelic frequencies at nuclear loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Peters1">Peters et al. 2012</xref>). Indeed, past studies observed comparatively low levels of population differentiation at nuclear loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f01">Figure 1</xref>). However, broader-scale examinations have found the comparison between mtDNA and nuclear DNA more informative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Peters3">Peters et al. 2007</xref>). Differences in nuclear DNA for waterfowl species often equal those of mtDNA when compared across distances where male dispersal is rare, such as between continental landmasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Peters1">Peters et al. 2012</xref>). Thus, smaller-scale studies of population differentiation might examine other, nongenetic datasets with which to compare mtDNA variation, such as radiotelemetry and band-recovery data, particularly for species in which the patterns of dispersal vary between the sexes.The mtDNA haplotype networks for Barrow's and Common Goldeneye suggest either limited gene flow or incomplete lineage sorting between populations in Alaska and the Pacific Northwest. Although the kernel home-range analysis suggests separate wintering distributions for both goldeneye species banded in Alaska and the Pacific Northwest, individual recovery locations within southeastern Alaska are geographically close enough to allow population interchange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f02">Figures 2</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f03">3</xref>A). There was very limited band-recovery information for Barrow's Goldeneye from the eastern portion of North America (4 band recoveries), and these were not included in our analysis. However, satellite telemetry data from Barrow's Goldeneye show that eastern populations remain in that region for late summer wing molt and for winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Robert1">Robert et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Savard2">Savard and Robert 2013</xref>). Thus, interchange between eastern and western North American populations of Barrow's Goldeneye is likely nonexistent or extremely rare. Bufflehead banded in Alaska winter both within the state and across the Pacific Northwest, but those banded in British Columbia remain in that area during the winter. Bufflehead, unlike goldeneye species, show limited population connectivity between breeding and wintering areas across North America. Similarly, genetic data from Bufflehead show a pattern of no differentiation, with two common haplotypes found across all sampling locations.The mtDNA information from our study provides evidence that Barrow's and Common Goldeneye populations are genetically distinct across North America, but differences are shallow, with only one or two base-pair substitutions separating haplotypes. Similarly, only a single nucleotide substitution differentiates Barrow's Goldeneye in Iceland from those in North America. By contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. (2009a)</xref> observed a greater divergence among Common Merganser mtDNA haplotypes from Alaska, British Columbia, and the western and eastern coasts of North America. Thus, mtDNA patterns within Barrow's and Common Goldeneye studied here suggest either recent colonization and limited haplotype diversification or reduction of historical variation through population bottlenecks or selection. By contrast, Common Goldeneye from Europe exhibit a greater level of divergence from North American samples, with 11 nucleotide substitutions between haplotype groups. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Pearce2">Pearce et al. (2009a)</xref> observed Old World populations of Common Merganser to be highly differentiated from New World samples (19 nucleotide substitutions).We are aware that use of predominantly winter samples for Bufflehead may mask patterns of breeding-ground population genetic structure if wintering areas were composed of multiple breeding areas. However, we would then expect band-recovery data from Bufflehead to show patterns of differentiation between the west and east coasts of North America. Instead, band-recovery data provided no evidence of connectivity between particular breeding and wintering areas of Bufflehead. There also is no evidence of Alaska-specific mtDNA haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-f05">Figure 5</xref>C). The two common haplotypes in the network are star-shaped, evidence of recent population expansion. Another issue with our sampling scheme was that most samples from both goldeneye species from British Columbia and Iceland originated from single locales. If natal-site fidelity were high, this would contribute to low mtDNA diversity in one sampling area if females were related. However, nonbreeding goldeneye samples did not have substantially greater mtDNA diversity than breeding samples and haplotype diversity in other regions, such as Quebec. Samples from Iceland were representative of a small (&sim;2,000 individuals) resident population, and all were collected in the My&grave;vatn area, the primary breeding area of Barrow's Goldeneye in Iceland. Therefore, we do not believe that our sampling scheme led to spurious conclusions.North American populations of goldeneye and Bufflehead have been increasing since 1957 (based on the annual Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey conducted by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and Canadian Wildlife Service; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Smith1">Smith 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Flint1">Flint 2012</xref>). However, because Common and Barrow's Goldeneye cannot be reliably differentiated in this survey, counts of both species are aggregated into one general &ldquo;goldeneye&rdquo; category, thus precluding the estimation of species-specific population trends. Consequently, it may be advantageous to use ancillary data (e.g., mtDNA and band recoveries) for assessing population delineation, migratory connectivity, and gene flow among sea duck populations, as has been done in other waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Guillemain1">Guillemain et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-2-195-Flint2">Flint et al. 2009</xref>).We thank G. Gauthier, M. Robert, and J. Peters for their ideas during the early phases of this project. Samples used for DNA in this project were provided by D. Zwiefelhofer and T. Bowman (U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service); D. Esler (Simon Fraser University); G. Savard, R. McNeil, and B. Braune (National Wildlife Research Center, Canadian Wildlife Service); and K. Richkus (U.S. Geological Survey). K. Sage and J. Gust assisted with lab analyses, and J. Terenzi helped with the kernel home-range analysis. We thank the Canadian Wildlife Service, U.S. Geological Survey, and numerous waterfowl banders for use of their banding data from across North America. This research was supported by the North American Sea Duck Joint Venture, Environment Canada, and the U.S. Geological Survey. P. Flint and S. Sonsthagen and two anonymous reviewers provided constructive comments on an earlier draft of the manuscript. Any use of trade, product, or firm names in this publication is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.List of number, bird status, and haplotype observed in each geographic region of sampling for Barrow's Goldeneye, Common Goldeneye, and Bufflehead.