Genomic single-nucleotide polymorphisms confirm that Gunnison and Greater sage-grouse are genetically well differentiated and that the Bi-State population is distinctGenetic diversity at neutral and adaptive loci determines individual fitness in a long-lived territorial birdNew subspecies of birds from western North AmericaGeographic orientation of American TetraonidaeDistribution of American gallinaceous game birds. U.SForty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union Checklist of North American birdsMitochondrial gene trees and the evolutionary relationship of Mallard and Black DucksRapid SNP discovery and genetic mapping using sequenced RAD markersEvaluation of the eastern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content> urophasianus</italic>) and western (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content> phaios</italic>) subspecies of sage-grouse using mitochondrial control-region sequence dataGenetic evaluation of a demographic bottleneck in the Greater Prairie ChickenHigh resolution of human evolutionary trees with polymorphic microsatellitesPopulation structure and genetic diversity of Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) in fragmented landscapes at the northern edge of their range<italic>Stacks</italic>: Building and genotyping loci <italic>de novo</italic> from short-read sequencesA hierarchical integrated population model for Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) in the Bi-State Distinct Population Segment, California and NevadaMitochondrial-DNA and nuclear-gene differentiation in North American prairie grouse (genus <italic>Tympanuchus</italic>)Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: A simulation studyArlequin (version 3.0): An integrated software package for population genetics data analysisRegional variation in mtDNA of the Lesser Prairie-ChickenOn the correlation between heterozygosity and fitness in natural populationsAdaptive vs. neutral genetic diversity: Implications for landscape geneticsGeographic variation among sage-grouse in ColoradoRecent range expansion and divergence among North American prairie grouseEvidence supporting the recent origin and species status of the Timberline SparrowDelimiting species without monophyletic gene treesPoPoolation2: Identifying differentiation between populations using sequencing of pooled DNA samples (Pool-Seq)Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtoolsCd-hit: A fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequencesSNPs in ecology, evolution, and conservationWest Nile virus: Pending crisis for Greater Sage-GrouseInteractive influence of infectious disease on genetic diversity of natural populationsHeirarchical spatial genetic structure in a distinct population segment of Greater Sage-GrouseA population genetic comparison of large- and small-bodied sage grouse in Colorado using microsatellite and mitochondrial DNA markersPopulation genetics of Gunnison Sage-Grouse: Implications for managementRapid evolution in lekking grouse: Implications for taxonomic definitionsA multilocus genetic survey of Greater Sage-Grouse across their rangeGenAlEx 6.5: Genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research &ndash; An updateInference of population structure using multilocus genotype dataFitness differences among remnant populations of the endangered Sonoran topminnowGENEPOP (version 1.2): Population genetics software for exact tests and ecumenicismThe value of avian genomics to the conservation of wildlifeConservation genomics: Applying whole genome studies to species conservation effortsDistribution of sage-grouse in North AmericaLow neutral genetic diversity in isolated Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) populations in northwest WyomingEcological genomics and conservation: Where do we stand?Rapid courtship evolution in grouse (Tetraonidae): Contrasting patterns of acceleration between Eurasian and North American polygynous cladesA comparative behavioral study of three Greater Sage-Grouse populationsEndangered and threatened wildlife and plants: Threatened status for Gunnison Sage-Grouse, final ruleTracking the long-term decline and recovery of an isolated populationA new species of sage grouse (Phasianidae: <italic>Centrocercus</italic>) from southwestern Colorado, USAPhenotypic divergence of secondary sexual traits among sage grouse, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>, populationsSage-grouse are iconic, declining inhabitants of sagebrush habitats in western North America, and their management depends on an understanding of genetic variation across the landscape. Two distinct species of sage-grouse have been recognized, Greater (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) and Gunnison sage-grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>), based on morphology, behavior, and variation at neutral genetic markers. A parapatric group of Greater Sage-Grouse along the border of California and Nevada (&ldquo;Bi-State&rdquo;) is also genetically distinct at the same neutral genetic markers, yet not different in behavior or morphology. Because delineating taxonomic boundaries and defining conservation units is often difficult in recently diverged taxa and can be further complicated by highly skewed mating systems, we took advantage of new genomic methods that improve our ability to characterize genetic variation at a much finer resolution. We identified thousands of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) among Gunnison, Greater, and Bi-State sage-grouse and used them to comprehensively examine levels of genetic diversity and differentiation among these groups. The pairwise multilocus fixation index (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) was high (0.49) between Gunnison and Greater sage-grouse, and both principal coordinates analysis and model-based clustering grouped samples unequivocally by species. Standing genetic variation was lower within the Gunnison Sage-Grouse. The Bi-State population was also significantly differentiated from Greater Sage-Grouse, albeit more weakly (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.09), and genetic clustering results were consistent with reduced gene flow with Greater Sage-Grouse. No comparable genetic divisions were found within the Greater Sage-Grouse sample, which spanned the southern half of the range. Thus, we provide much stronger genetic evidence supporting the recognition of Gunnison Sage-Grouse as a distinct species with low genetic diversity. Further, our work confirms that the Bi-State population is differentiated from other Greater Sage-Grouse. The level of differentiation is much less than the divergence between Greater and Gunnison sage-grouse, supporting the idea that the Bi-State represents a unique population within the Greater Sage-Grouse. New genomic methods like the restriction-site-associated DNA (RAD-tag) method used here illustrate how increasing the number of markers and coverage of the genome can better characterize patterns of genetic variation, particularly among recently diverged taxa, providing vital information for conservation and management.Los urogallos son habitantes ic&oacute;nicos y en declive de los h&aacute;bitats de <italic>Artemisia</italic> en el occidente de Norte Am&eacute;rica y su manejo depende del entendimiento de su variaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica a trav&eacute;s del paisaje. Los urogallos est&aacute;n clasificados en dos especies, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>, con base en morfolog&iacute;a, comportamiento y gen&eacute;tica. Un grupo parap&aacute;trico de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> que habita el l&iacute;mite entre California y Nevada (poblaci&oacute;n biestatal) tambi&eacute;n es gen&eacute;ticamente distinto, aunque no es diferente en comportamiento o morfolog&iacute;a. Dado que los nuevos m&eacute;todos gen&oacute;micos pueden mejorar nuestra habilidad para caracterizar la variaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica, identificamos miles de polimorfismos de nucle&oacute;tidos sencillos (SNPs) entre <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> de la zona biestatal, y los usamos para examinar m&aacute;s detenidamente los niveles de diversidad gen&eacute;tica y la diferenciaci&oacute;n entre estos grupos. El valor de <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> fue alto (0.49) entre <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>, y los an&aacute;lisis de coordenadas principales y de agrupamiento basado en modelos agruparon la muestra por especies de manera inequ&iacute;voca. La variaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica fue menor dentro de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>. La poblaci&oacute;n biestatal tambi&eacute;n est&aacute; gen&eacute;ticamente diferenciada de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> aunque m&aacute;s d&eacute;bilmente (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 0.09), y los resultados de agrupamiento gen&eacute;tico fueron consistentes con flujo gen&eacute;tico reducido entre los grupos intraespec&iacute;ficos. No encontramos divisiones gen&eacute;ticas comparables dentro de la muestra de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>, que comprende la mitad sur de la distribuci&oacute;n. Por lo tanto, proveemos evidencia gen&eacute;tica mucho m&aacute;s fuerte que apoya el reconocimiento de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic> como una especie distinta con baja diversidad gen&eacute;tica. Adem&aacute;s, nuestro trabajo confirma que la poblaci&oacute;n biestatal est&aacute; diferenciada de otras poblaciones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>, lo que apoya la idea de que esa poblaci&oacute;n es &uacute;nica dentro de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>. Nuevos m&eacute;todos gen&oacute;micos como el de RAD-tags usado en este trabajo ilustran c&oacute;mo el incremento en el n&uacute;mero de caracteres y la cobertura del genoma pueden caracterizar mejor los patrones de variaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica, particularmente entre taxones recientemente separados. Esto es de vital importancia para la conservaci&oacute;n y el manejo de las especies.<italic>Palabras clave: <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus minimus</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>, especiaci&oacute;n, diversidad gen&eacute;tica, poblaci&oacute;n biestatal, RAD-tag, SNPsSage-grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus</named-content></italic> spp.) are the largest grouse found in North America. They are ground-dwelling, sagebrush-obligate species that are seen as icons of the Western United States. Historically, sage-grouse were considered to be a single species whose presettlement range included 14 U.S. states and 3 Canadian provinces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich2">Aldrich 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Johnsgard1">Johnsgard 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Schroeder2">Schroeder et al. 2004</xref>). In 1946, J. W. Aldrich described two subspecies, an Eastern Sage-Grouse (<italic>C. u. urophasianus</italic>) and a Western Sage-Grouse (<italic>C. u. phaios</italic>), based on slight color differences in 11 individuals collected from Washington, Oregon, and California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1946</xref>). Western Sage-Grouse presumably occurred in southern British Columbia, central Washington, east-central Oregon, and northeastern California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1946</xref>). Populations in other areas of the range were considered to be Eastern Sage-Grouse, although the validity of this taxonomic distinction was questioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Johnsgard1">Johnsgard 1983</xref>).Current (light gray) and presettlement (dark gray) distribution of sage-grouse (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Schroeder2">Schroeder et al. 2004</xref>), with approximate locations of samples used in this study. Samples in red are Greater Sage-Grouse, those in green are from the Bi-State population of Greater Sage-Grouse, and those in blue are Gunnison Sage-Grouse.In the 1990s, research in southwestern Colorado revealed strong morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Hupp1">Hupp and Braun 1991</xref>) and behavioral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Young2">Young et al. 1994</xref>) evidence that sage-grouse in southwestern Colorado and southeastern Utah were distinct from sage-grouse elsewhere in their range and might be a distinct species. Using mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) sequences and nuclear microsatellite loci, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. (1999)</xref> revealed genetic patterns consistent with a lack of gene flow between sage-grouse in southwestern Colorado&ndash;southeastern Utah and northern Colorado, which supported the idea that this group of sage-grouse was a different species. The amount of genetic divergence between these two groups was not large, however, and mtDNA haplotypes in the sage-grouse from southwestern Colorado were not reciprocally monophyletic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. 1999</xref>). Regardless, in 2000, the American Ornithologists' Union (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-AOU2">AOU 2000</xref>) recognized a new species named the Gunnison Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. minimus</named-content></italic>), described formally by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Young1">Young et al. (2000)</xref>. All other sage-grouse were subsequently renamed Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>).This reassessment of sage-grouse taxonomy spurred a reexamination of the subspecies classification of the Greater Sage-Grouse. The geographic delineation separating the eastern and western subspecies is ambiguous and has changed through time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich2">1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Aldrich3">Aldrich and Duvall 1955</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-AOU1">AOU 1957</xref>). Morphological comparisons by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Schroeder1">Schroeder (2008)</xref> revealed slight variations among individuals and some populations, yet the magnitudes of the differences were not sufficient to be recognized as distinct subspecies using current taxonomic standards, and the patterns of variation were not consistent with geographically described subspecies. Genetic data collected from individuals across the range were not differentiated at the subspecies boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Benedict1">Benedict et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>). In contrast, a population that spans the border between California and Nevada (Bi-State population; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f01">Figure 1</xref>) was found to be unique genetically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Benedict1">Benedict et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>).Within the Bi-State population, most individuals had mtDNA haplotypes that were novel (i.e. not found in other populations of Greater Sage-Grouse throughout the range; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Benedict1">Benedict et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance1">2014</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. (2005a)</xref> also revealed that the Bi-State population was significantly different from all other Greater Sage-Grouse populations at 7 nuclear microsatellite loci, suggesting that the Bi-State population had been isolated from neighboring populations for a considerable amount of time (thousands or perhaps tens of thousands of years; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Benedict1">Benedict et al. 2003</xref>). Recent genetic research on the Bi-State population, analyzing many more individuals and using more microsatellite markers, has confirmed the differentiation and uniqueness of the Bi-State population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance1">Oyler-McCance et al. 2014</xref>). Another significant finding, using standard neutral genetic markers, has been the fact that the Bi-State population is at least as divergent from other populations of Greater Sage-Grouse as Gunnison Sage-Grouse are from Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>).While Gunnison Sage-Grouse were recognized as a new species based on morphological, behavioral, and genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Young1">Young et al. 2000</xref>), comparisons of gross morphology and behavior between Bi-State and surrounding Greater Sage-Grouse populations have revealed little or no differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Taylor1">Taylor and Young 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Schroeder1">Schroeder 2008</xref>). This suggests that, while the Bi-State population may have been isolated for as long as Gunnison Sage-Grouse, they have not diverged morphologically or behaviorally in the same way that Gunnison Sage-Grouse have (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Young1">Young et al. 2000</xref>).Sage-grouse are lekking species with a highly skewed mating system. In lek-breeding species, sexual selection can act to influence morphological and behavioral traits at a rate much faster than can be tracked with neutral genetic markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Spaulding1">Spaulding 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance4">Oyler-McCance et al. 2010</xref>). Thus, for recently diverged species with strong sexual selection, large differences in morphological and behavioral traits associated with breeding may be apparent, yet such differences may not have had time to accumulate in unlinked neutral genetic markers. The patterns of genetic variation in Greater and Gunnison sage-grouse described above were all measured using standard population genetic methods involving a handful of rapidly mutating neutral markers. Small numbers of neutral markers may not only lack resolution in recently diverged taxa, but also may not reveal genes underlying morphological and behavioral traits that distinguish the Gunnison Sage-Grouse.New genomic methods, however, can increase the number of molecular markers by orders of magnitude (thousands to tens of thousands) through the identification of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). The high density of informative SNPs in most genomes can increase the resolution of population genetics studies and facilitate the detection of loci under selection. The objective of this study was to reexamine patterns of genetic variation among Gunnison Sage-Grouse, the Bi-State population of Greater Sage-Grouse, and Greater Sage-Grouse in the southern portion of their range using genomic SNPs discovered from reduced-representation genomic libraries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Baird1">Baird et al. 2008</xref>). Dramatically increasing the number of molecular markers and sampling across the genome should allow us to more accurately document differentiation and genetic diversity in these groups of sage-grouse.We chose DNA samples from 30 individual sage-grouse that had been used in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance1">2014</xref>). Gunnison Sage-Grouse and Bi-State population samples were chosen to cover the entire range of each of these groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Greater Sage-Grouse samples (other than those for the Bi-State population) were chosen to reflect the southern portion of the range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Samples were taken either from muscle tissue from hunter-killed sage-grouse or from blood samples from birds trapped for previous research. Extraction methods followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance3">Oyler-McCance et al. (2005b)</xref>.A 20 &mu;L double digestion reaction was set up using 1 &mu;g of whole genomic DNA (13 &mu;L of DNA in water at a concentration of 77 ng &mu;L<sup>&minus;1</sup>), 2 &mu;L of 10&times; T4 DNA ligase buffer (New England BioLabs, Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA) and 1 &mu;L each of the rare cutter SPEI (10,000 units ml<sup>&minus;1</sup>; New England BioLabs) and the common cutter Sau3AI (5,000 units ml<sup>&minus;1</sup>; New England BioLabs). The remainder was made up of 2.8 &mu;L of water and 0.2 &mu;L of 100&times; Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA; New England BioLabs). After digestion for 2 hr, restriction enzymes were heat-killed at 65&deg;C for 15 min and the reaction was cooled using a 37&deg;C hold. At 37&deg;C, 1 &mu;L of 10 &mu;M stocks of each P1 and individually barcoded P2 restriction-site-associated DNA (RAD-tag) adapters (Integrated DNA Technologies, Coralville, Iowa, USA; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-t01">Appendix Table 1</xref>) were spiked into the reaction and allowed to equilibrate to dehybridize any self&ndash;self hybridization of the adapters. Once in equilibrium, 1 &mu;L of T4 ligase (400,000 units ml<sup>&minus;1</sup>; New England BioLabs) was spiked in, and the temperature was reduced to 16&deg;C for 15 min to ligate the adapters to the double-digested DNA. The ligation reaction was cleaned using 0.6&times; AMPure beads (Beckman Coulter, Brea, California, USA) to assure the removal of any self-dimers that may have formed. PCR was performed on a Bio-Rad iCycler using IQ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad, Hercules, California, USA) to facilitate the quantification and pooling of PCR products without individual clean-up. The PCR consisted of 30 cycles of 95&deg;C for 30 s, 55&deg;C for 30 s, and 72&deg;C for 30 s. As with all RAD-tag protocols, the adapter attached to the common restriction enzyme (Sau3AI) was Y-yolked to reduce amplification of common&ndash;common fragments and enrich common&ndash;rare fragments. After PCR and pooling, 0.65&times; AMPure bead clean-up was performed on the pool to remove PCR dimers and small amplicons. Further size selection was done to 300&ndash;500 base pairs (bp) via Pippen Prep (Sage Science, Beverly, Massachusetts, USA). The pool of 30 libraries was sent to the University of Colorado Genomics and Microarray Facility (Denver, Colorado, USA) for sequencing on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, California, USA). The resulting sequences were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information's (NCBI) Short Read Archive under BioProject PRJNA211878.We used the FASTX-Toolkit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/" xlink:type="simple">http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/</ext-link>) to trim reads at a Phred-equivalent quality score of 15, and purged reads that were shorter than 84 bp after trimming. We then used <italic>Stacks</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Catchen1">Catchen et al. 2011</xref>) to collapse restriction-site-associated reads (RAD-tags) into loci, or &ldquo;stacks,&rdquo; using the combined reads from all populations and requiring at least 3 reads to designate an initial stack. We then made a catalog of shared loci among the 3 populations, allowing up to 3 mismatches. These stacks were further clustered using program cd-hit-est (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Li2">Li and Godzik 2006</xref>) at 85&percnt; identity and a word size of 7, to avoid competitively mapping reads to similar stacks. Reads from each individual sample were then mapped to stacks using Bowtie 2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Langmead1">Langmead and Salzberg 2012</xref>) in &ldquo;local&rdquo; mode, using a seed length of 20 and tolerating 1 mismatch in the seed and 3 total mismatches. Reads with mapping quality of 15 or greater were retained in the alignment output, which was converted to variant call format using SAMtools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Li1">Li et al. 2009</xref>). Stacks with more than 100 reads mapped from any 1 population read pool were removed as potential genomic repeats. Any locus with GC (guanine-cytosine) content greater than 2 standard deviations from the mean GC content of 38&percnt; was excluded.The total number of SNPs at this initial stage was 94,620; however, a large majority of these had a minor allele frequency (MAF) below 10&percnt;. As the total number of chromosome sets sampled was 60, the biological frequency threshold for SNPs was ~1.67&percnt;, although lower variant frequencies may have occurred in reads due to stochastic sampling and library-size variation. Furthermore, preliminary analysis showed no geographic structure of samples when the MAF in the pooled reads was 1&percnt; or less, and an alternative SNP prediction pipeline (CLC Genomics Workbench; CLCbio, Boston, Massachusetts, USA) showed little overlap with these low-frequency SNPs, suggesting that these were due largely to sequencing and/or alignment error. Based on these considerations and the fact that higher frequency polymorphisms are more efficient for assessing population genetic structure, we limited our analysis to SNPs with a MAF of 10&percnt; or greater in the total read pool.A small number of multiallelic sites were excluded for simplicity. A minimum SAMtools SNP quality score of 100 was required. Sites were further filtered to exclude loci within 3 bp of an indel (insertion-deletion polymorphism) and to retain loci with a combined coverage of 50&ndash;350&times;, using the &lsquo;vcfutils' script of SAMtools. The coverage values were chosen based on the distribution of read counts around the mean coverage of approximately 150&times; for all individuals, or ~5&times; per individual. The single most likely genotype was assigned for each locus&ndash;sample combination if the SAMtools-reported genotype quality was 10 or higher; otherwise, the genotype was considered undetermined. Finally, we removed SNPs that deviated from equal coverage in male and female samples by binomial test (<italic>P</italic> &ge; 0.05 without adjustment for multiple tests), resulting in a total of 11,630 presumed autosomal SNPs for population genetics analysis.Gene diversity at genotyped SNPs was calculated with Genepop version 4.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Raymond1">Raymond and Rousset 1995</xref>). Pairwise population fixation index (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) tests and analyses of molecular variance (AMOVA) were performed in Arlequin version 3.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Excoffier1">Excoffier et al. 2005</xref>). Principal components analysis (PCA) of genetic distance among individuals was performed with GenAlEx 6.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Peakall1">Peakall and Smouse 2012</xref>). The genetic distance between all pairs of individuals was calculated as 1 minus the average proportion of alleles shared, using the formula (IBS2 &plus; 0.5&ast;IBS1)/N, where IBS1 and IBS2 are the number of loci which share either 1 or 2 alleles identical by state (IBS), respectively, and N is the number of loci tested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Bowcock1">Bowcock et al. 1994</xref>). Genotype pairs with missing data were ignored.We used program <italic>Structure</italic> version 2.00 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Pritchard1">Pritchard et al. 2000</xref>) to perform model-based clustering without regard to original sampling locale. We first estimated the number of genetic clusters (<italic>K</italic>) by conducting 5 independent runs each for <italic>K</italic> &equals; 1&ndash;6 with 100,000 Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) repetitions. The runs initiated with a 10,000 burn-in period, and used an admixture model with correlated allele frequencies and no prior information on sampling locales (popinfo &equals; 0). The most likely value of <italic>K</italic> given the data was identified using both the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Pritchard1">Pritchard et al. (2000)</xref> and the &Delta;<italic>K</italic> method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Evanno1">Evanno et al. (2005)</xref>. To minimize the effects of incomplete data on parameter estimation, we used only the 10,385 loci with no more than 5 missing genotypes.We identified 11,630 SNPs among the 3 population pools that met our coverage, quality, and MAF cutoffs. A smaller fraction of the globally defined SNPs were polymorphic in Gunnison Sage-Grouse (57&percnt;) than in Greater Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State population samples (83&percnt; and 76&percnt;, respectively), and mean expected heterozygosity at polymorphic loci was also lower (0.181 vs. 0.307 and 0.284, respectively).Mean gene diversity (the 1-Qintra statistic of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Raymond1">Raymond and Rousset &lsqb;1995&rsqb;</xref>) at genotyped SNPs was lower in Gunnison Sage-Grouse (0.13) than in Greater Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State group, which had similar values (0.23 and 0.20, respectively). All pairwise multilocus <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> estimates were significantly different from zero, yet the levels of differentiation between Gunnison Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State group (0.54) and between Gunnison and Greater sage-grouse (0.49) were much higher than the level between the Bi-State group and Greater Sage-Grouse (0.09). The proportion of total genetic structure explained by population assignment was 41&percnt; according to AMOVA (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). While per-locus <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values are expected to have high variance among unlinked loci, the vast majority of high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values were between Gunnison Sage-Grouse and the other sampled populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f02">Figure 2</xref>). For example, the number of SNPs with <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &ge; 0.8 was 1,235 when comparing Greater Sage-Grouse and Gunnison Sage-Grouse, but only 10 when comparing Greater Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State population.Histograms of fixation index (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) for pairs of sage-grouse samples. Per-SNP (single-nucleotide polymorphism) <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> were calculated from read counts for 11,630 SNPs using PoPoolation2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Kofler1">Kofler et al. 2011</xref>) and plotted in increments of 0.05. Gunnison Sage-Grouse have many more SNPs with high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and almost all fixed differences.Principal Coordinates Analysis (PCA) of pairwise genetic distance among samples found that 77&percnt; of the variation could be explained by the first 2 principal coordinate axes alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The 3 sample groups were well separated along the plotted axes, but the Gunnison Sage-Grouse individuals were more tightly clustered together and were equidistant from Greater Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f03">Figure 3</xref>) along the first axis (67&percnt; of the total variation). The second axis completely discriminated Greater Sage-Grouse from the Bi-State group, yet explained a smaller fraction of the total variation (10&percnt;). Thus, the variation distinguishing the latter 2 sample groups was smaller in scale and largely orthogonal to that distinguishing both groups from Gunnison Sage-Grouse, whereas Gunnison Sage-Grouse appeared more genetically uniform relative to the total variation. Within the Bi-State group there were 2 clusters of individuals, which represented northern and southern groups.Principal Coordinates Analysis of the 3 groups of sage-grouse using 11,630 single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) loci. The first 2 principal coordinate axes explained 77&percnt; of the variation (67&percnt; for Coordinate 1 and 10&percnt; for Coordinate 2). Samples in the blue polygon represent Gunnison Sage-Grouse. Samples in the green polygon represent the Bi-State Greater Sage-Grouse. Samples in the red polygon represent the remaining Greater Sage-Grouse.Model-based clustering with program <italic>Structure</italic> further supported the genetic differentiation of Gunnison Sage-Grouse and Greater Sage-Grouse. The number of clusters that best fit the data was <italic>K</italic> &equals; 3, using the method suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Pritchard1">Pritchard et al. (2000)</xref>, which placed all 3 sample groups into separate clusters. However, the &Delta;<italic>K</italic> method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Evanno1">Evanno et al. (2005)</xref> indicated <italic>K</italic> &equals; 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f04">Figure 4</xref>), further differentiating the Bi-State population and Greater Sage-Grouse. With either value, or indeed in bar and triangle plots based on any <italic>K</italic> between 2 and 6 (not shown), there was no evidence of admixture between Gunnison Sage-Grouse and either Greater Sage-Grouse or the Bi-State samples.Results of program <italic>Structure</italic> analysis run among the 3 groups of sage-grouse (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 30) using 10,385 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) for 3 different numbers of genetic clusters (<italic>K</italic> &equals; 3&ndash;5). In all analyses, each distinct cluster is represented by a unique color. Each vertical bar represents an individual sage-grouse. The color on each vertical bar represents the individual's estimated membership in each unique genetic cluster.Our reexamination of genetic variation within the Greater and Gunnison sage-grouse complex demonstrates that the Gunnison Sage-Grouse is a well-differentiated species relative to the global variation found in its congeners, and has lower levels of standing genetic variation. Evidence of this includes the high pairwise multilocus <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> between Gunnison Sage-Grouse and the other 2 sample groups, exceeding 0.49 for both comparisons, and the observation that almost all fixed differences (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> &equals; 1) among populations were minor alleles private to Gunnison Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Program <italic>Structure</italic> runs that assumed <italic>K</italic> in the range of 2&ndash;6 all identified Gunnison Sage-Grouse as a distinct cluster with negligible admixture, and PCA identified a major axis explaining over half of the total variation that completely separated the 2 species. While the Bi-State population was also differentiated from the Greater Sage-Grouse samples in the PCA and program <italic>Structure</italic> runs, the allele frequency divergence was smaller in scale.The genetic structure identified in this study is quite different from results reported previously, suggesting that Gunnison Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State group are both different from other Greater Sage-Grouse and that these differences are similar in magnitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>). Importantly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. (2005a)</xref> used only a small number of neutral markers (7 nuclear microsatellites and 1 mitochondrial locus) to conduct their study, whereas this study used thousands of SNPs that presumably span the entire genome. Likewise, the goal of this study was to examine large-scale differences between species of sage-grouse and the distinct Bi-State population, not to document population genetic variation within groups. Several more fine-scale molecular studies have documented significant population genetic structure within Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Bush1">Bush et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Schulwitz1">Schulwitz et al. 2014</xref>), the Bi-State population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance1">Oyler-McCance et al. 2014</xref>), and Gunnison Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance3">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005b</xref>). Even so, clustering of individuals within the Gunnison Sage-Grouse and the Bi-State groups in this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-f03">Figure 3</xref>) are evident and are consistent with previous microsatellite data. In the Gunnison Sage-Grouse samples, the individual that deviated most from the group was an individual from Pi&ntilde;on Mesa, Colorado (GP6), which represented the most isolated population described in previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance3">Oyler-McCance et al. 2005b</xref>). Similarly, the Bi-State individuals clustered into 2 groups. The northern group represented individuals from Bodie Hills, Jackass Flat, Wheeler Burcham Flat, and Lyon County, Nevada, whereas the southern group consisted of individuals from Parker Meadows and Long Valley, California, and White Mountains, California&ndash;Nevada, which is consistent with a previous fine-scale genetic study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance1">Oyler-McCance et al. 2014</xref>).In addition to showing that Gunnison Sage-Grouse are well differentiated from Greater Sage-Grouse, we also revealed that Gunnison Sage-Grouse have lower genetic diversity than either the Bi-State group or Greater Sage-Grouse. Gunnison Sage-Grouse had many fewer polymorphic SNPs and their mean expected heterozygosity at polymorphic loci was lower. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Raymond1">Raymond and Rousset's (1995)</xref> 1-Qintra gene diversity statistic, which is the probability that two alleles at a diploid locus differ by state, was substantially lower for Gunnison Sage-Grouse than for Greater Sage-Grouse (0.13 and 0.23, respectively). That this lower diversity is not primarily due to the smaller geographic scale of sampling is strikingly illustrated by the fact that the Bi-State population has almost as much variation (0.20) as Greater Sage-Grouse, despite Bi-State samples being drawn from a small portion of the total range. Further, the estimated number of Gunnison Sage-Grouse was 4,075 in 2014 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-USFWSU.S.FishandWildlifeService1">USFWS 2014</xref>), which is slightly larger than the number of birds in the Bi-State distinct population segment (DPS), estimated to be 3,026 (95&percnt; CI &equals; 2,176&ndash;3,784) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Coates1">Coates et al. (2014)</xref>.Our SNP detection method, however, entailed a potential ascertainment bias, in that loci that strongly differentiated Gunnison from Greater sage-grouse were more likely to be discovered but less likely to be polymorphic within the former population if under divergent selection. To address this possibility, we performed the same SNP detection protocol for each population separately, except that we used a minimum coverage of 10&times; in each pool, rather than the range specified for the total dataset in the Methods. We also normalized library sizes by drawing reads randomly from Gunnison and Greater sage-grouse to equal the size of the smaller Bi-State population pool. The reanalysis identified 8,126 SNPs in Greater Sage-Grouse and 7,577 SNPs in the Bi-State group, but only 4,405 SNPs in Gunnison Sage-Grouse. On the other hand, the 3 groups of SNPs had almost identical expected heterozygosities (0.46). The highly similar mean values likely reflect the constraints on variant calling imposed by dramatically reducing the number of biological samples and reads, which prevented low MAF loci from reaching the quality-score cutoff. Even so, while we can conclude that the lower number of polymorphic SNPs in Gunnison Sage-Grouse do not reflect an ascertainment bias, we cannot eliminate the possibility of an effect on perceived genetic diversity at polymorphic sites.Our results confirm previous findings of lower genetic diversity at neutral genetic loci within Gunnison Sage-Grouse compared with Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance3">2005b</xref>). While most conservation biologists agree that genetic variation is relevant to the health and viability of populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OBrien1">O'Brien and Evermann 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Quattro1">Quattro and Vrijenhoek 1989</xref>), the use of neutral genetic markers as a correlative measure of fitness has been questioned, as correlations between such markers and fitness have been shown to be weak and inconsistent and to rely heavily on demography and natural history characteristics of the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Hansson1">Hansson and Westerberg 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Holderegger1">Holderegger et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Agudo1">Agudo et al. 2012</xref>). Our genomic SNP data reveal a pattern of reduced genetic variation throughout the genome of Gunnison Sage-Grouse. This finding is particularly important as Greater Prairie-Chickens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tympanuchus cupido</named-content></italic>), a closely related lekking grouse, have shown reduced fertility and hatching success due to a bottleneck caused by habitat loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Bouzat1">Bouzat et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Westemeier1">Westemeier et al. 1998</xref>). Gunnison Sage-Grouse have experienced similar isolation and reduction in population size resulting from the loss of habitat. Further, genetically depauperate populations face enhanced susceptibility to parasitic agents and infectious diseases such as West Nile Virus, which has been shown to be a significant threat for Greater Sage-Grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Naugle1">Naugle et al. 2004</xref>). It remains to be determined whether reduced genetic variation in Gunnison Sage-Grouse is an effect of demography or selection at speciation, or has anthropogenic causes.Rapidly advancing genomic technology not only allows us to more comprehensively examine patterns of genetic variation, but also provides us with the first steps to understanding the mechanisms that drive patterns of genetic variation, adaptation, and evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Morin1">Morin et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Ryder1">Ryder 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Romanov1">Romanov et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Segelbacher1">Segelbacher and H&ouml;glund 2009</xref>). In the past we examined patterns of genetic variation in sage-grouse using a handful of neutral molecular markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance2">Oyler-McCance et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance5">2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance3">2005b</xref>). While these studies provided important information regarding levels of gene flow and genetic diversity, they lacked the ability to directly address factors associated with differentiation that ultimately led to the split into two different species. A small number of neutral markers showed that the Bi-State Greater Sage-Grouse and Gunnison Sage-Grouse were both unique and had been isolated from Greater Sage-Grouse. The genomic approach used here reveals that the Gunnison Sage-Grouse is in fact much more different from Greater Sage-Grouse than is the Bi-State group of Greater Sage-Grouse. This finding is highly relevant as both species are of significant conservation concern and require accurate delineation of taxonomic and management units. Our study provides much stronger genetic evidence supporting the recognition of Gunnison Sage-Grouse as a distinct species and reaffirms the finding of low genetic diversity in this species. Further, while our work confirms that the Bi-State population is differentiated from other Greater Sage-Grouse, the level of differentiation is much less than the divergence between Greater and Gunnison sage-grouse, supporting the idea that the Bi-State represents a unique population within Greater Sage-Grouse. In addition, this research highlights the added value of using genomic markers that vastly improve resolution of genetic parameters of interest, such as estimates of genetic structure and diversity.Delineating taxonomic boundaries and defining conservation units is often difficult, particularly for recently diverged taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Avise1">Avise et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Knowles1">Knowles and Carstens 2007</xref>). Lekking grouse, in particular, are notoriously difficult in this regard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Ellsworth1">Ellsworth et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Johnson1">Johnson 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-Hagen1">Hagen et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-217-OylerMcCance4">Oyler-McCance et al. 2010</xref>). New genomic methods, such as the RAD-tag method used here, illustrate how increasing the sheer number of markers and the coverage of the genome can better characterize patterns of genetic variation, which is of vital importance for the conservation and management of species. These methods could be further extended to examine adaptive genetic variation, which is important to document and conserve, as well as to identify where in the genome levels of divergence are highest, which would provide clues to mechanisms of speciation.We thank M. E. Hunter for thoughtful comments on this manuscript. We thank P. S. Coates, M. L. Casazza, A. D. Apa, and C. E. Braun for collecting samples for previous studies that were subsequently used in this analysis. Any use of trade, product, or firm names in this publication is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.<bold>Funding statement.</bold> Funding for this project was provided by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). This paper has been peer-reviewed and approved for publication consistent with USGS Fundamental Science Practices (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.usgs.gov/circ/1367/" xlink:type="simple">http://pubs.usgs.gov/circ/1367/</ext-link>).<bold>Ethics statement.</bold> Samples were collected from birds that had been either killed by hunters or trapped under Colorado Division of Wildlife ACUC protocols.Adapters used in the restriction-site-associated DNA (RAD-tag) approach to discovering single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the sage-grouse genome.