Identifying carry-over effects of wintering area on reproductive parameters in White-winged Scoters: An isotopic approachArctic climate, spring nutrition, and recruitment in midcontinent Lesser Snow GeeseAge-specific in situ recruitment of female King Eiders estimated with mark-recaptureComponents of population growth rate for White-winged Scoters in Saskatchewan, CanadaMorphological, pharmacokinetic, and hematological studies of lead-exposed PigeonsUsing predator distributions, diet, and condition to evaluate seasonal foraging sites: Sea ducks and herring spawnUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's information criterionRelationships between hepatic trace element concentrations, reproductive status, and body condition of female Greater ScaupSurvey of levels of cadmium in oysters, mussels, clams, and scallops from the Pacific Northwest of CanadaBody condition, migration, and timing of reproduction in Snow Geese: A test of the condition-dependent model of optimal clutch sizePatterns of reproductive effort and success in birds: Path analyses of long-term data from European ducksNesting biology of the White-winged ScoterWhite-winged Scoter, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>, populations and nesting on Redberry Lake, SaskatchewanWhite-winged Scoter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>)Distribution of chemical concentrations in U.S. coastal and estuarine sedimentBioaccumulation, biological effects, and food chain transfer of contaminants in the Zebra Mussel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dreissena polymorpha</named-content></italic>)Is selenium affecting body condition and reproduction in boreal breeding Scaup, Scoters, and Ring-necked Ducks?Combining stable isotope and body composition analyses to assess nutrient-allocation strategies in breeding White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>)Heavy metals in tissues of waterfowl from the Chesapeake Bay, USAComparing the seasonal survival of resident and migratory Oystercatchers: Carry-over effects of habitat quality and weather conditionsChanges in size and trends of North American sea duck populations associated with North Pacific oceanic regime shiftsEarlier spring staging in Iceland amongst Greenland White-fronted Geese <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anser albifrons</named-content> flavirostris</italic> achieved without cost to refuelling ratesStable isotopes in terrestrial ecosystem researchExperimental exposure and distribution of lead in four species of raptors in southeastern SpainAge and the timing of breeding in a long-lived bird: A role for stress hormones?Time constraints in temperate-breeding species: Influence of growing season length on reproductive strategiesSeasonal variation in pre-fledging survival of Lesser Scaup <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aythya affinis</named-content></italic>: Hatch date effects depend on maternal body massCarry-over effects as drivers of fitness differences in animalsSelenium accumulation and elimination in MallardsRecoveries of Saskatchewan-banded White-winged Scoters, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>Predation danger can explain changes in timing of migration: The case of the Barnacle GooseCarry-over effects of spring hunt and climate on recruitment to the natal colony in a migratory speciesA capture technique for Marbled Murrelets in coastal inletsThe adaptive significance of creching behavior in the White-winged Scoter <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content> deglandi</italic>Patterns of variation in clutch sizes in a guild of temperate-nesting dabbling ducksForaging behaviors of Surf Scoters and White-winged Scoters during spawning of Pacific herringThe influence of climate on the timing and rate of spring bird migrationLinking winter and summer events in a migratory bird by using stable-carbon isotopesContaminants in Lesser Scaup eggs and blood from Yukon Flats National Wildlife Refuge, AlaskaSuggestions for calculating nest successInterannual flexibility in breeding phenology of a Neotropical migrant songbird in response to weather conditions at breeding and wintering areasLinking breeding and wintering areas of King Eiders: Making use of polar isotopic gradientsCarry-over effects and habitat quality in migratory populationsTropical winter habitat limits reproductive success on the temperate breeding grounds in a migratory birdNational distribution of chemical concentrations in mussels and oysters in the USA. Selenium in birdsDoes winter region affect spring arrival time and body mass of King Eiders in northern Alaska?Rapid increase and subsequent decline of zebra and quagga mussels in Long Point Bay, Lake Erie: Possible influence of waterfowl predationWinter feeding of birds increases productivity in the subsequent breeding seasonCarry-over effects of winter climate on spring arrival date and reproductive success in an endangered migratory bird, Kirtland's Warbler (<italic>Setophaga kirtlandii</italic>)Autumn diet of Greater Scaup, Lesser Scaup, and Long-tailed Ducks on eastern Lake Ontario prior to Zebra Mussel invasionSpring and early summer distribution of scoters and eiders in the St. Lawrence River estuaryCarry-over effects of winter location contribute to variation in timing of nest initiation and clutch size in Black Brant (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans</italic>)Fuel stores, fuel accumulation, and the decision to depart from a migration stopover siteSpecies status reportsUse of geolocators reveals previously unknown Chinese and Korean Scaly-sided Merganser wintering sitesContributions to automated trace analysisNutritional implications of molt in male Canvasbacks: Variation in nutrient reserves and digestive tract morphologyEffects of intrinsic and extrinsic factors on survival of White-winged Scoter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content> deglandi</italic>) ducklingsSelenium concentrations in Greater Scaup and <italic>dreissenid</italic> mussels during winter on western Lake OntarioBreeding strategy and organochlorine contamination of eggs in Lesser Scaup (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aythya affinis</named-content></italic>)Year to year correlations in blood metal levels among individuals of two species of North American sea ducksTrace element concentrations in blood of nesting King Eiders in the Canadian ArcticSurvival rates and blood metal concentrations in two species of free-ranging North American sea ducksConcentrations of cadmium, mercury and selenium in blood, liver and kidney of Common Eider ducks from the Canadian ArcticCadmium in birdsA simple field candler for waterfowl eggsProgram MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animalsCoupling contaminants with demography: Effects of lead and selenium in Pacific Common EidersCurrent address: University of Alaska Fairbanks, Institute of Arctic Biology, Fairbanks, Alaska 99775, USAEvents during one stage of the annual life cycle of migratory birds can have lasting (i.e. carry-over) effects that influence demographic parameters in subsequent seasons. We studied migratory connectivity and potential carry-over effects in a declining population of sea ducks. We measured stable isotope values of carbon (<italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C) and nitrogen (<italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N) in head feathers to assign breeding White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>; hereafter scoters) to either Atlantic or Pacific winter populations. The discriminant function for <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N correctly classified 93&percnt; of scoters sampled from these 2 winter areas. We then applied this classification scheme to head feathers of females breeding at Redberry Lake, Saskatchewan, and Cardinal Lake, Northwest Territories, to stratify each breeding population by winter provenance. We evaluated carry-over effects associated with winter location of females breeding in Saskatchewan by testing for differences in (1) nesting phenology, (2) clutch size, (3) mid-incubation body mass, (4) nest success, and (5) concentrations of trace elements contaminants of cadmium (Cd), mercury (Hg), selenium (Se), and lead (Pb) in blood, between strata of putative winter origin. Breeding females from the Atlantic coast had later dates of nest initiation, greater mid-incubation body mass, and also had higher concentrations of Cd (one year only), Pb, and Se, relative to birds from the Pacific. Neither nest initiation date nor mid-incubation body mass, however, were related to contaminant concentrations in blood. We found no differences in clutch size or nest success between putative winter strata. Our study detected carry-over effects in the Saskatchewan population that merit further attention.Los eventos durante una etapa del ciclo de vida anual de las aves migratorias pueden tener efectos duraderos (i.e. efectos de arrastre) que influencian los par&aacute;metros demogr&aacute;ficos de estaciones subsecuentes. Estudiamos la conectividad migratoria y los potenciales efectos de arrastre en una poblaci&oacute;n declinante de patos marinos. Medimos valores de is&oacute;topos estables de carbono, <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C, y nitr&oacute;geno, <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N, en las plumas de la cabeza para asignar a individuos reproductivos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic> a poblaciones ya sea del Atl&aacute;ntico o del Pac&iacute;fico. La funci&oacute;n discriminante para <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C y <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N clasific&oacute; correctamente 93&percnt; de los individuos muestreados de estas dos &aacute;reas de invernada. Luego aplicamos este esquema de clasificaci&oacute;n a las plumas de la cabeza de hembras anidando en el Lago Redberry, Saskatchewan, y en el Lago Cardinal, Territorios del Noroeste, para estratificar cada poblaci&oacute;n reproductiva con relaci&oacute;n a la procedencia de invierno. Evaluamos los efectos de arrastre asociados con la localizaci&oacute;n de invierno de las hembras anidando en Saskatchewan analizando diferencias en (i) fenolog&iacute;a de anidaci&oacute;n, (ii) tama&ntilde;o de la nidada, (iii) peso corporal a mediados de la incubaci&oacute;n, (iv) &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n, y (v) concentraciones de trazas de elementos contaminantes (cadmio, Cd, mercurio, Hg, selenio, Se, y plomo, Pb) en la sangre, entre estratos de origen putativo de invierno. Las hembras reproductivas de la costa atl&aacute;ntica tuvieron fechas m&aacute;s tard&iacute;as de iniciaci&oacute;n del nido, mayor peso corporal a mediados de la incubaci&oacute;n y tambi&eacute;n concentraciones m&aacute;s altas de Cd (solo un a&ntilde;o), Pb y Se, con relaci&oacute;n a las aves del Pac&iacute;fico. Sin embargo, ni la fecha de iniciaci&oacute;n del nido ni el peso corporal a mediados de la incubaci&oacute;n se relacionaron con las concentraciones de contaminantes en la sangre. No encontramos diferencias en el tama&ntilde;o de la nidada o en el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n entre estratos putativos de invierno. Nuestro estudio detect&oacute; efectos de arrastre en la poblaci&oacute;n de Saskatchewan que ameritan m&aacute;s atenci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> &aacute;reas de invernada, carbono-13, conectividad migratoria, contaminantes, is&oacute;topos estables, <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple"><italic>Melanitta fusca</italic></named-content>, nitr&oacute;geno-15, pato marinoBirds, particularly migrants, may use multiple habitats that can be distributed across broad spatial scales and encompass a diverse range of environmental conditions over the annual cycle. Increasing evidence has shown that processes during one stage or season of the annual cycle can influence the success of individuals in a subsequent season or life stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Marra2">Marra et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Norris2">Norris et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Robb1">Robb et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Duriez1">Duriez et al. 2012</xref>). These interactions, termed &ldquo;carry-over effects&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Harrison1">Harrison et al. 2011</xref>), can influence demographic rates and abundances of animal populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Juillet1">Juillet et al. 2012</xref>). For example, the quality of nonbreeding habitat can influence subsequent reproductive parameters; variable environmental conditions at wintering or staging areas can affect when individuals arrive at breeding areas, their physical condition, and when they breed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Norris1">Norris 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Schamber1">Schamber et al. 2012</xref>). Specifically, variation in nutritional condition of adult birds during spring migration can interplay with climate on remote breeding areas to influence the subsequent production of young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Alisauskas1">Alisauskas 2002</xref>). Similarly, delays in breeding phenology can reduce recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Alisauskas2">Alisauskas and Kellett 2014</xref>). Detecting carry-over effects and their influence in population dynamics could therefore be a prerequisite for informed conservation planning.Difficulties in tracking migratory animals over the annual cycle, however, can pose challenges for detecting and assessing carry-over effects. In addition to interspecific variation in their role, magnitude of carry-over effects may change between years. Adjustments to migration rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Marra1">Marra et al. 2005</xref>) or foraging behavior during migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Fox1">Fox et al. 2012</xref>) may allow organisms to maintain consistent reproductive effort despite variable wintering conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Mazerolle1">Mazerolle et al. 2011</xref>). In addition, the time and distance between wintering and breeding areas may dampen potential carry-over effects from winter on breeding migrants, leading to uncertainty about their relative influences (through survival or recruitment) on population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Oppel1">Oppel and Powell 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Flint1">Flint 2013</xref>).Migratory birds often arrive on breeding areas with contaminant burdens derived from nonbreeding areas, and these burdens can potentially affect reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Matz1">Matz and Rocque 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland1">Wayland et al. 2007</xref>). Contaminants that birds accumulate on the wintering grounds, however, may no longer be present by the time individuals arrive on the breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Warren1">Warren and Cutting 2011</xref>). Further, some studies have shown that contaminants encountered during migration do not affect reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-DeVink1">DeVink et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Badzinski1">Badzinski et al. 2009</xref>). Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland3">Wayland et al. (2008a)</xref> detected no effect of heavy metal burdens on apparent survival in either White-winged Scoter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) or King Eider (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Somateria spectabilis</named-content></italic>) females captured during nesting, their data did suggest a moderate, annually variable effect of blood mercury levels on capture probability, suggesting that breeding probability may have been negatively influenced. The potential for contaminants on wintering areas to mediate carry-over effects related to reproduction therefore merits further investigation, particularly in sea ducks that tend to have elevated blood concentrations of trace element contaminants.We studied variation in timing of nesting, clutch size, mid-incubation body mass, nest success, and blood concentrations of 4 trace element contaminants for a breeding population of White-winged Scoters (hereafter scoters) in Saskatchewan, Canada. Our objective was to test 2 hypotheses related to carry-over effects: (1) variation in winter provenance, inferred from stable isotope analysis, can influence breeding performance; and (2) carry-over effects on breeding grounds are a result of variation in contaminant burdens between birds from different wintering areas. Scoters are ideal for evaluating hypotheses related to carry-over effects because they have shown long-term declines in abundance over their breeding range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Alisauskas3">Alisauskas et al. 2004</xref>) and are known to winter in marine and brackish estuarine waters along both the Pacific and Atlantic coasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Houston1">Houston and Brown 1983</xref>), as well as on fresh water in the Great Lakes, where potential exposure to contaminants is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Godfrey1">Godfrey 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Ware1">Ware et al. 2011</xref>). Atlantic birds migrate farther than Pacific birds to our Saskatchewan study site, so we predicted that they would have delayed breeding due to either time constraints or reduced body condition, potentially leading to reduced nest success.To validate the isotope approach for assignment of breeding scoters to wintering areas and assess migratory connectivity in this species, we tested whether samples from geographically distinct winter populations could be discriminated using carbon (<italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C) and nitrogen (<italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N) isotope values of feathers. Successful discrimination allowed us to estimate proportional winter affiliations of females from a southern (Saskatchewan) and northern (Northwest Territories) nesting population.We collected contour feathers of adult scoters (males and females) from Atlantic and Pacific locations between 2001 and 2004 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t01">Table 1</xref>). We also delineated wintering ground origins for 2 populations of breeding scoters: Redberry Lake (studied during 2002&ndash;2004) in southwest Saskatchewan (52.66&deg;N, 107.17&deg;W; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Kehoe1">Kehoe 1989</xref>) and at Cardinal Lake (studied during 2002&ndash;2006) in the Northwest Territories, southeast of Inuvik (67.61&deg;N, 133.66&deg;W; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Gurney1">Gurney et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f01">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t02">Table 2</xref>).Current winter and breeding distribution of White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) in North America. Redberry Lake study area is marked with a star; Cardinal Lake is marked with a circle. Approximate locations of winter collections are shown as diamonds.To determine <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N values from feathers of wintering White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) during 2001&ndash;2004, we collected feathers from 181 individuals (males and females) at known wintering locations on Atlantic and Pacific coasts.To delineate wintering ground origins for 2 distinct breeding populations of White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>), we collected feathers from 706 birds (&equals; 490 individuals) between 2002 and 2006. Only females were sampled at Redberry Lake; at Cardinal Lake, both females and males were sampled.To determine <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N values in feathers from known wintering locations, scoters were captured during banding operations; feathers from hunter-killed scoters were also collected during the regular hunting season and from carcasses that washed up on beaches. To determine which feather tract provided the best isotopic segregation of wintering populations, 3 feather tracts (head, back, and flank) were sampled from each individual.Two or more observers systematically searched for nests at Redberry Lake by walking line transects between mid-June and late July 2002&ndash;2004. We counted eggs, determined incubation stage by candling eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Weller1">Weller 1956</xref>), and estimated initiation dates by back-dating, assuming a laying interval of 1.5 eggs per day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Brown1">Brown and Brown 1981</xref>). Nesting females were trapped using hand-held nets after mid-incubation (&sim;14 days incubation or later) and marked with a standard aluminum leg band. All captured females (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 242 captures, 172 individual females) had 3&ndash;4 feathers removed from each of 3 feather tracts (head, back, and flank) for isotope analysis. In 2002 and 2003, we also collected blood (4&ndash;6 cc) from a subset of the captured females for contaminant analyses (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 122 samples, 108 individual females). Concentrations of trace element contaminants in blood provide a suitable metric for both short-term as well as longer term exposure because blood concentrations of trace element compounds are correlated with concentrations in storage tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland4">Wayland et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Ohlendorf1">Ohlendorf and Heinz 2011</xref>).We trapped breeding pairs at Cardinal Lake during the pre-nesting period (mid-June to early July) using floating mist nets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Kaiser1">Kaiser et al. 1995</xref>) and collected feathers from both females and males (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 464 captures, 318 individuals), as described for Redberry Lake. Blood for contaminant analyses was not collected from Cardinal Lake birds. All research methods were approved by the Animal Care Committee, University of Saskatchewan, on behalf of the Canadian Council on Animal Care (Protocol 20000010).Two secondary isotopic reference materials (egg albumen and lyophilized bowhead whale baleen) were used as standards. Standards (in the same mass range as the test samples) were processed before and between every 5 feather samples within each analytical run (for albumen) and at the start, midpoint, and end of each run (for baleen). We used replicate standard measurements within a run to estimate analytical precision &plusmn;1 standard deviation (SD): mean <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C within runs &equals; &minus;22.4&permil; &plusmn; 0.0&percnt;, and mean <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N within runs &equals; 6.8&permil; &plusmn; 0.1&percnt; for egg albumen; mean <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C within runs &equals; &minus;18.5&permil; &plusmn; 0.1&percnt;, and mean <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N within runs &equals; 14.8&permil; &plusmn; 0.2&percnt; , for bowhead whale baleen. Measurement errors (&plusmn;1 SD) were estimated to be &plusmn; 0.1&permil; for <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and &plusmn; 0.3&permil; for <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N, based on measurements of laboratory standards across multiple runs.Following collection, blood samples from Redberry Lake females were transferred to nitric acid-washed vials, kept cool in the field, and frozen pending further processing. Mercury (Hg), Selenium (Se), and Lead (Pb) analyses were conducted at Atlantic Environment Canada's National Wildlife Research Centre according to methods described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Neugebauer1">Neugebauer et al. (2003)</xref>; Cadmium (Cd) was analyzed at the Institut National de Sant&eacute; Publique du Qu&eacute;bec according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Stoeppler1">Stoeppler and Brandt (1980)</xref>. Cd concentrations were expressed on a volumetric basis, whereas Hg, Se, and Pb concentrations were expressed on a wet weight basis. Blood samples used in these analyses were identical to those used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland1">Wayland et al. (2007)</xref>, who described analytical techniques in detail, including standard reference materials, percent recovery, detection limits, measurement precision, and accuracy.All statistical analyses were performed using SAS Version 9.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2009</xref>). We visually assessed bivariate plots of <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N from each feather tract to evaluate overlap between known Atlantic and Pacific winter populations. Feathers from 6 individuals (5 from Atlantic females and 1 from a Pacific female; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f02">Figure 2</xref>) showed extremely low <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C values relative to all others, suggesting a freshwater influence. These feathers may have been molted during fall migration while staging on freshwater ecosystems, and because no feathers from Redberry Lake birds had similar signatures, we excluded them from subsequent analyses.<italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N values of White-winged Scoter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) head feathers from known wintering locations provided the best discrimination between Atlantic and Pacific wintering areas. <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C values from 6 individuals (lower left of panel) were considered to be influenced by freshwater and excluded from subsequent analyses.Because isotope values were normally distributed, we used multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA, PROC GLM) to test for effects of winter area, sex, winter area&ast;sex interaction, and date of collection on <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N values, and to determine whether sex or date needed to be accounted for in our Discriminant Function Analysis (DFA). We then used DFA (PROC DISCRIM) to quantitatively assess which feather tract would most accurately discriminate between Atlantic and Pacific populations based on <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N. We tested for homogeneity of within-covariance matrices using a chi-square test of homogeneity (POOL &equals; TEST option). Because the variances were not different (&alpha; &equals; 0.05), they were pooled, and we conducted a linear DFA. Prior probabilities were set equal to sample sizes for each group, and separate DFAs were performed using <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N from all possible combinations of the 3 feather tracts, including each tract independently.The performance of each tract-specific DFA was evaluated based on the error rate from leave-one-out cross-validation, and subsequent DFA of isotopic differences between winter populations were based on feathers from the most informative tract. Feathers from breeding areas at both Redberry Lake and Cardinal Lake were assigned to either Atlantic or Pacific winter areas using linear DFA based on the discriminant function obtained from this analysis (Appendix A). To be conservative in further hypothesis testing, we considered scoters with &lt;0.90 posterior probability of assignment to either winter area to be of uncertain winter provenance and excluded them from further analyses.We used general linear mixed models (PROC MIXED) to test for effects of putative winter area on nest initiation date, clutch size, mid-incubation body mass, and blood Hg and Pb. Generalized linear mixed models (PROC GLIMMIX) were used to evaluate effects of winter area on blood Cd and Se, which had negative binomial distributions. Mixed models allowed us to account for covariance in the response variable from dependencies among repeated measures from the same bird (a random effect) while treating winter area and other covariates as fixed effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Littell1">Littell et al. 2006</xref>). Marginal log likelihood values were computed using either the restricted maximum likelihood method (PROC MIXED) or the Laplace approximation (PROC GLIMMIX; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2009</xref>). We used an information-theoretic approach to model selection, with models ranked according to second-order Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>).Candidate models for breeding phenology included fixed effects of year, winter location, and mid-incubation body mass. Predictor variables in models of clutch size were the same as for timing of breeding but also included clutch initiation date to account for seasonal declines in clutch size, a pattern observed consistently in single-brooded birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Krapu1">Krapu et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Gurney1">Gurney et al. 2011</xref>). To assess whether effects of clutch initiation date and winter origin on clutch size were confounded (because Atlantic birds tended to nest later), we also ran a clutch size model that included winter origin but not clutch initiation date. Our a priori model set for mid-incubation body mass included fixed effects of year and wintering origin. We estimated probability of nest survival in relation to winter origin with the nest survival model (logit-link function) in program MARK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-White1">White and Burnham 1999</xref>) and considered 6 candidate models for nest success, selecting the best-approximating model(s) using AIC<sub>c</sub>.In addition to a constant survival model, we assessed effects of year, winter location, nest initiation date, and nest location on nest survival. We also used a time invariant null model, using data for all found nests, to calculate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Mayfield1">Mayfield (1975)</xref> estimates of nest success for comparison with previously published results. Finally, to evaluate contaminant burdens as a potential mechanistic explanation for reproductive carry-over effects of wintering location, blood concentrations of Cd, Hg, Pb, and Se were included in model sets for timing of nesting and mid-incubation body mass. Candidate model sets for contaminants included year, winter location, and mid-incubation body mass as main fixed effects. We also estimated the influence of incubation stage on blood contaminant levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2007</xref>) by including nest initiation date in these model sets.In all cases, following selection of the top-ranked models, inference of fixed effects was based on the degree to which included variables reduced model deviance (i.e. &minus;2 log likelihood), as well as on the precision (85&percnt; confidence interval &lsqb;CI&rsqb;) of regression coefficients (&beta;). Although the 85&percnt; CI is narrower and less commonly used than a 95&percnt; CI, criteria for model selection and for estimating influence of parameters are more similar under this approach. If confidence intervals of estimated parameters included zero, effects associated with these parameters were considered to be uninformative; models containing such effects were not used for inference and were not included in final model sets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>).MANOVA for <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N values showed differences between winter areas (Wilks' &lambda; &equals; 0.73, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 33.09<sub>2,175</sub>, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but not between sexes (Wilks' &lambda; &equals; 0.98, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 1.96<sub>2,175</sub>, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15), no interaction between winter area and sex (Wilks' &lambda; &equals; 1.00, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.41<sub>2,175</sub>, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.66), and no effect of collection date (Wilks' &lambda; &equals; 0.99, <italic>F</italic> &equals; 0.90<sub>2,175</sub>, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.41). Therefore, we considered only 2 groups, Atlantic and Pacific, for discriminant analysis.Scoter feathers from known Pacific wintering sites had enriched <sup>13</sup>C and, to a lesser extent, enriched <sup>15</sup>N relative to those from known Atlantic sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Of the 3 feather tracts analyzed (head, back, flank), head feathers displayed the greatest difference in mean <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C values between Atlantic and Pacific coasts and therefore provided the most accurate discrimination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t03">Table 3</xref>). The most important value for correct classification was <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C; classification bias was reduced by only 3&percnt; with inclusion of <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N. Feather <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N of scoters from these known wintering populations provided reference data for assigning winter provenance to breeding scoters.Classification success (&percnt;) of linear discriminant function analysis based on <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C values from feathers of known-source Atlantic or Pacific coastal wintering populations of White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) indicates that this approach classifies winter origin with a high degree of precision. Feather tract(s) are listed in order of classification success for Atlantic populations. Sexes were pooled because MANOVA showed no sex effect.Certainty of correct assignment of Redberry Lake birds was somewhat greater during 2002, with 90&percnt; (65 of 72) of all individuals having &gt;0.90 probability of having wintered on either the Atlantic or Pacific coast, compared with 82&percnt; (80 of 97) of individuals with &gt;0.90 probability in 2003, and 78&percnt; (57 of 73) of individuals with &gt;0.90 probability in 2004. In both 2002 and 2003, 25&percnt; of females breeding at Redberry Lake were assigned to Atlantic and 75&percnt; to Pacific waters. In 2004, however, only 12&percnt; were assigned to Atlantic and 88&percnt; to Pacific waters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f03">Figure 3</xref>A). The classification of breeding females for Cardinal Lake was of similar precision in all years for which feathers were available; over 5 years (2002&ndash;2006), only 3&percnt; (7 of 321) individuals (males and females) were considered to be of unknown origin. In contrast to Redberry Lake scoters, those from Cardinal Lake were almost exclusively of Pacific winter origin, with only 3 classified as Atlantic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f03">Figure 3</xref>B).(<bold>A</bold>) White-winged Scoter (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>, females only) from Redberry Lake assigned to putative wintering areas based on <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N of head feathers were from both Atlantic (filled circles) and Pacific coasts (filled triangles). Feathers with &lt;90&percnt; classification probabilities were considered to be of uncertain wintering region (unfilled squares). (<bold>B</bold>) Most White-winged Scoters (females and males) from Cardinal Lake were inferred to have wintered along the Pacific coast.Of the reproductive parameters that we measured at Redberry Lake, only nest initiation date and mid-incubation body mass showed evidence of carry-over effects (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t04">Table 4</xref>). Nest initiation date was affected by wintering origin, with Atlantic birds tending to nest 3&ndash;4 days later than birds from the Pacific coast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f04">Figure 4</xref>; &beta;<sub>Winter</sub> &equals; 3.0, 85&percnt; CI: 1.4 to 4.6). The top-supported model also indicated annual variation in breeding phenology, with earlier nesting in 2003 relative to 2002 and 2004 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The best-approximating model for mid-incubation body mass also included an effect of wintering area, suggesting that during incubation Atlantic scoters were heavier than Pacific scoters (&beta;<sub>Winter</sub> &equals; 21.5, 85&percnt; CI: 3.3 to 39.7). For both nest initiation date and mid-incubation body mass, models that included contaminant values suggested that, in all cases, these reproductive parameters were unaffected by blood contaminant levels.Based on ranking of general linear mixed models (PROC MIXED), our data are consistent with an effect of wintering area on nest initiation day and mid-incubation body mass of female White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) breeding at Redberry Lake, Saskatchewan. Response variables are listed in the first column, and for each variable, the &check; indicates which predictor variables were included in the models as fixed effects. For all models, bird identity is included as a random effect, and in each case, models with no &check; are the null model. Models are ranked by differences in Akaike's Information Criterion, corrected for sample size (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>). Winter &equals; wintering area, as determined by discriminant function analysis; <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; Akaike weight.Timing of nesting by White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) at Redberry Lake, Saskatchewan, was earlier for birds that wintered on the Pacific coast and earlier in 2003 relative to other years.We did not detect an effect of wintering area for either clutch size or nest success at Redberry Lake. Mean clutch size was 9.0 &plusmn; 0.1 (SE), and the top-supported model for this response variable included a fixed effect of clutch initiation date and a random effect of bird. This model was supported by 100&percnt; of the weight of evidence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t04">Table 4</xref>), indicating that clutch size variability was unexplained by variables we considered. Mayfield nest success (&phi;) was also unaffected by winter location. The estimated daily survival rate of nests, however, showed considerable annual variation: &phi;<sub>2002</sub> &equals; 0.25, 85&percnt; CI: 0.19 to 0.31, &phi;<sub>2003</sub> &equals; 0.93, 85&percnt; CI: 0.84 to 1.01, and &phi;<sub>2004</sub>&equals; 0.73, 85&percnt; CI: 0.60 to 0.86.Our Redberry Lake sample of 108 unique females in 2002 and 2003 included those from which blood was sampled and for which posterior probability of assignment to either winter area was &gt;0.90. Levels of Cd in blood samples varied between winter area and year (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t05">Table 5</xref>), with an interaction between them (&beta;<sub>Year&ast;Winter</sub> &equals; &minus;0.70, 85&percnt; CI: &minus;1.08 to &minus;0.32); females from the Atlantic had higher Cd levels than birds that wintered in the Pacific in 2003 only (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). Levels of Pb were consistent across years and were higher for females from Atlantic compared to Pacific waters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f05">Figure 5</xref>B; &beta;<sub>Winter</sub> &equals; 0.026, 85&percnt; CI: 0.020 to 0.031). Levels of Hg did not vary between females that wintered in different areas, but values were higher in 2002 relative to 2003 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f05">Figure 5</xref>D; &beta;<sub>Year</sub> &equals; 0.091, 85&percnt; CI: 0.080 to 0.103). Similarly, blood Se was higher for birds from Atlantic winter areas (&beta;<sub>Winter</sub> &equals; 0.803, 85&percnt; CI: 0.650 to 0.957) but did not vary between years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-f05">Figure 5</xref>C). Of all metals, only Se was related to body mass, and this was a positive association (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t05">Table 5</xref>; &beta;<sub>BodyMass</sub> &equals; 0.002, 85&percnt; CI: 0.001 to 0.003).Based on ranking of general linear mixed models (PROC MIXED; lead, mercury) and generalized linear mixed models (PROC GLIMMIX; cadmium, selenium), our data are consistent with an effect of wintering area on levels of blood contaminants (cadmium, lead, selenium) in female White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) breeding at Redberry Lake, Saskatchewan. Response variables are listed in the first column, and for each variable the &check; indicates which predictor variables were included in the models as fixed effects, and the &ast; denotes an interaction. For all models, bird identity is included as a random effect; in each case, models with no &check; are the null model. Models are ranked by differences in Akaike's Information Criterion, corrected for sample size (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>). Winter &equals; wintering area, as determined by discriminant function analysis, Mass &equals; mid-incubation body mass, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; Akaike weight.In 2002 (unfilled squares) and 2003 (filled circles), concentrations of (<bold>A</bold>) cadmium (Cd), (<bold>B</bold>) lead (Pb), and (<bold>C</bold>) selenium (Se) in blood of White-winged Scoters (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melanitta fusca</named-content></italic>) breeding at Redberry Lake, Saskatchewan, were higher for birds that wintered in Atlantic regions, with the exception of (<bold>D</bold>) mercury (Hg, in both years) and Cd (in 2002). In all panels, values are least squares means (85&percnt; confidence interval).Head feathers provided the best discrimination between Atlantic and Pacific scoters, likely due to their relatively small size in relation to feathers from other tracts. Small size requires less material to replace feathers, and in turn, requires a shorter period of growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Thompson1">Thompson and Drobney 1996</xref>). Thus, the average isotopic input can be incorporated into the tissue over a shorter time, perhaps representing reduced variation in isotopic landscapes sampled by foraging birds over a shortened temporal sampling frame (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Mehl1">Mehl et al. 2005</xref>). Even so, classification success (&percnt;) was much higher for Pacific than for Atlantic wintering birds (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-t03">Table 3</xref>), possibly because of reduced heterogeneity in isoscapes used by Pacific scoters.Although use of stable isotope values resulted in reasonably good discrimination between winter areas, some overlap was evident because of similarities in <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C and <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>15</sup>N for winter diet items (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Swoboda1">Swoboda 2007</xref>). Head and body feathers are molted twice annually, with new plumage acquired during the prealternate molt, typically in July&ndash;September and then again during the prebasic molt in March&ndash;April, before migrating to breeding areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Brown3">Brown and Fredrickson 1997</xref>). Our samples were collected throughout the fall but were largely restricted to the regular hunting season (October&ndash;January) for Atlantic samples. Thus, these samples may have included feathers grown on the breeding area, or staging areas during fall migration (i.e. before birds reached terminal winter areas).Carbon sources influenced by freshwater inputs tend to be depleted in <sup>13</sup>C relative to carbon from marine sources; average <italic>&delta;</italic><sup>13</sup>C for freshwater ecosystems is about &minus;26&permil;, so values below &minus;20&permil; suggest that molt occurred when birds were consuming foods from fresh or estuarine water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Fry1">Fry and Sherr 1988</xref>). Depleted <sup>13</sup>C in head feathers of Atlantic birds may have resulted from increased foraging in brackish estuarine habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Savard1">Savard et al. 1999</xref>) relative to those from Pacific waters.Atlantic scoters also may have staged in freshwater habitats for prolonged periods during fall before continuing to coastal wintering areas. Females banded at Redberry Lake have been recovered on the Great Lakes in the fall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Houston1">Houston and Brown 1983</xref>), highlighting their use as freshwater staging areas and potential wintering habitat for these scoters. Increased use of the Great Lakes by both diving and sea ducks has been documented following invasion of these habitats by zebra mussels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dreissena polymorpha</named-content></italic>) in the late 1980s, and prolonged staging there has occurred in recent years as a result of longer ice-free periods during the winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Petrie1">Petrie and Knapton 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Schummer1">Schummer 2005</xref>).Using isotopic analyses, we have developed a molecular tool that will assist in conservation efforts for scoters by connecting breeding birds to known wintering areas. This study emphasizes the value of an isotopic approach for identifying connectivity between breeding and wintering locations, but we note that future research into migratory connectivity will also benefit from attached logging devices that use light-level archival technology (i.e. geolocators) to infer location (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Solovyeva1">Solovyeva et al. 2012</xref>), particularly in species with substantial body mass, such as scoters. Whereas banding data for the Redberry Lake population suggest that it is composed of nearly equal ratios of Atlantic and Pacific wintering scoters, our isotopic approach showed that Pacific females comprised at least 75&percnt; of breeding individuals. In addition, ours is the first published study to document wintering ground origins for a northern-breeding population of scoters, showing that these birds winter almost exclusively on the Pacific coast.Taken together, these results confirm the importance of Pacific wintering areas for scoters, an important first step in understanding environmental factors that may be limiting their populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-SeaDuckJointVenture1">Sea Duck Joint Venture 2003</xref>). We suggest that further studies of carry-over effects in this species would be valuable. From a conservation perspective, assessing annual variation in reproduction and survival relative to environmental changes on wintering and staging habitats would be particularly insightful. For example, scoters wintering and migrating along the Pacific coast seem to rely heavily on herring (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Clupea pallasi</named-content></italic>) spawn for restoring depleted nutrient reserves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Anderson1">Anderson et al. 2009</xref>). Declining herring stocks could thus result in carry-over effects related to reduced reproductive investment. This may be especially relevant at Cardinal Lake because scoters breeding at northern latitudes rely in part upon endogenous reserves for egg production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-DeVink2">DeVink et al. 2011</xref>).We found that scoters from Atlantic wintering areas nested later, were of higher body mass during mid-incubation, and tended to have higher blood levels of Cd, Pb, and Se than sympatrically nesting scoters from Pacific wintering areas; however, we found no direct negative associations between any trace elements in the blood and the reproductive parameters that we measured. Thus, Pacific scoters had an advantage in sympatric breeding phenology over Atlantic scoters, but this was not clearly a result of reduced blood contaminants. Other factors, including differences between winter populations with respect to diet, migration distance and duration, or use of staging areas likely have a greater influence on breeding parameters than do levels of trace element contaminants.It seems unlikely that Atlantic scoters that nested in Saskatchewan were nutritionally compromised because they had superior mid-incubation body mass compared to Pacific scoters. Delays in migration or breeding were therefore not likely the result of difficulties in accumulation of nutrient stores for migration and reproduction, as has been suggested elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Bety1">B&ecirc;ty et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Schaub1">Schaub et al. 2008</xref>). Instead, the inverse relationship between nesting phenology and mid-incubation body mass between winter populations may represent a trade-off. That is, even though the greater migration distance to Saskatchewan for Atlantic scoters (compared to those from Pacific winter areas) may have prolonged spring migration and resulted in nesting delays, it may also have permitted greater nutrient storage that resulted in higher body mass for these individuals. Additionally, differences in weather patterns between Atlantic and Pacific coasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Rockwell1">Rockwell et al. 2012</xref>), variation in the age structures of wintering populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Goutte1">Goutte et al. 2010</xref>), or differences in predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Jonker1">Jonker et al. 2010</xref>) could further influence or confound timing of migration and arrival on breeding grounds by scoters and other migratory species.Nesting by Atlantic scoters at Redberry Lake was delayed only by about 3 days, but relative to other species scoters are relatively late nesters with slow-maturing broods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Brown1">Brown and Brown 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Brown3">Brown and Fredrickson 1997</xref>), and there is strong evidence that survival of scoter ducklings declines with advancing hatch date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Traylor2">Traylor and Alisauskas 2006</xref>). Thus, for scoters and other species with similar life-histories, the demographic consequences of even minor delays in breeding could be substantial and certainly can influence recruitment probability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Alisauskas2">Alisauskas and Kellett 2014</xref>). Because timing of breeding is closely linked to reproductive success and recruitment in many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Blums1">Blums et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Gurney2">Gurney et al. 2012</xref>), the observed effect of wintering area on timing of breeding emphasizes that carry-over effects can potentially influence individual fitness and recruitment dynamics of migratory birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Harrison1">Harrison et al. 2011</xref>). Our findings suggest that carry-over effects of this nature may affect migratory populations to a greater extent than is currently recognized.Although breeding parameters were unrelated to concentrations of trace elements in the blood, our study did detect significant differences in 3 of 4 contaminants for birds from different wintering areas. Blood samples for this study were collected during mid-incubation (close to the end of June), when scoters had potentially been absent from wintering areas for up to 6 weeks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Brown2">Brown and Fredrickson 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Traylor1">Traylor 2003</xref>). Trace elements Cd, Pb, and Se all have relatively short half-lives in avian blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Anders1">Anders et al. 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Heinz1">Heinz et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland5">Wayland and Scheuhammer 2011</xref>); however, their concentrations in blood are usually well-correlated with concentrations in storage tissues, such as bone and kidney (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-GarciaFernandez1">Garc&iacute;a-Fern&aacute;ndez et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland4">Wayland et al. 2001</xref>), and can indicate differences in longer-term exposure (i.e. on nonbreeding areas; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Wayland2">Wayland et al. 2008b</xref>).In addition, the pattern we observed in blood contaminants is consistent with previously demonstrated coastal differences in environmental contamination (i.e. Atlantic &gt; Pacific; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Daskalakis1">Daskalakis and O'Connor 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-OConnor1">O'Connor 2002</xref>). Pacific-wintering scoters likely consume large quantities of herring spawn during spring migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Lewis1">Lewis et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Anderson1">Anderson et al. 2009</xref>), whereas those on Atlantic coasts may depend more on filter-feeding mussels, which bioaccumulate several trace elements, including Cd (Di Giulo and Scanlon 1984, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Bendell1">Bendell 2009</xref>). Spring staging on the Great Lakes by scoters after departing from the Atlantic coast may also contribute to elevated metals in blood. Exotic zebra mussels introduced to the Great Lakes bioaccumulate contaminants at higher concentrations than native bivalve species and may be replacing scoter invertebrate prey such as amphipods and gastropods, which do not filter feed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-DeKock1">De Kock and Bowmer 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Ross1">Ross et al. 2005</xref>).Current evidence thus suggests that observed differences in blood contaminants were likely the result of variable exposure to contaminants during winter or spring migration. Alternatively, exposure might be similar between wintering areas; however, if Atlantic wintering scoters deplete endogenous reserves during their longer migration route and Pacific scoters do not, metabolic changes might lead to greater mobilization of contaminants from storage tissues in birds from the Atlantic coast. Although the differences in contaminant burdens observed in our study might have been caused by events on sympatric nesting areas, this explanation seems unlikely because individuals of Atlantic and Pacific winter origin use the same habitats and have similar diets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Traylor1">Traylor 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-2-251-Swoboda1">Swoboda 2007</xref>). If Atlantic-origin scoters rely more on exogenous reserves for reproduction than Pacific-origin birds, however, it is conceivable that they may feed more locally during nesting and incubation, thereby being exposed to higher levels of local contaminants.In general, the interplay among contaminants, wintering areas, migration strategies, and local conditions on reproductive parameters were somewhat confounded in our study. Further research designed to attribute variation in breeding ecology to specific carry-over effects in this species might benefit from detailed studies of spring migration phenology for each winter population of scoters. In particular, the use of multi-season geolocators or satellite telemetry could be used to assess differences in migration phenology, stop-over site locations and duration, and overall distances travelled from different wintering areas to common nesting areas. Additional studies to evaluate the causes and possible consequences of elevated contaminants in Atlantic wintering scoters also seem warranted. Data describing concentrations of contaminants in wintering and staging birds from both Atlantic and Pacific locations would be particularly useful in distinguishing patterns of nonbreeding area exposure, and long-term capture&ndash;mark&ndash;recapture data would provide key information concerning biological implications of winter provenance and variable contaminant exposure. Assessing environmental levels of trace element contaminants at Redberry Lake would help clarify the role of local exposure, as would details concerning differences in breeding season nutrient allocation strategies between Atlantic and Pacific birds.By identifying clear differences in breeding chronology between sympatrically breeding scoters from different winter populations, our study highlights the importance of carry-over effects for migratory animals. Specifically, variation in breeding phenology constitutes an important carry-over effect with strong links to recruitment probability in many species of birds. Stratification of breeding populations by winter provenance will likely provide a much-improved understanding of variation in breeding biology in other bird species and will help clarify the extent to which carry-over effects influence bird populations.We thank Ducks Unlimited Canada, the Sea Duck Joint Venture, Environment Canada, the University of Saskatchewan, and the Gwich'in Renewable Resource Board for funding and logistic support, as well as the Gwich'in Tribal Council and the Gwichya Gwich'in Renewable Resource Council (Tsiigehtchic Renewable Resource Council) for permission to conduct work on their land. We are also grateful to Pat Kehoe, Michael Hill, Michael Anderson, and all the researchers, hunters, and outfitters who provided feather samples. Two anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments that greatly improved the manuscript.