 Nest-site selection and reproductive success of Common Yellowthroats in managed Iowa grasslands  When good animals love bad habitats: Ecological traps and the conservation of animal populations  Comparative breeding ecology of Cooper's Hawks in urban and exurban areas of southeastern Arizona  Effects of hay-cropping on eastern populations of the Bobolink  Effects of habitat characteristics on Gadwall nest predation and nest-site selection  A canopy-coverage method of vegetational analysis  Nest-site selection patterns and the influence of vegetation on nest survival of mixed-grass prairie passerines  Interactive effects of vegetation and predation on the success of natural and simulated nests of grassland birds  Adaptive plasticity in nest-site selection in response to changing predation risk  Red-winged Blackbirds and Brown-headed Cowbirds: Some aspects of a host&ndash;parasite relationship  Avian nest dispersion and fledging success in field&ndash;forest ecotones  Experimental analysis of nest predation in an old-field habitat  Perch promimity correlates with higher rates of brood parasitism of ground nesting Song Sparrows  Nest-site selection and the importance of nest concealment in the Black-Throated Blue Warbler  Nest concealment and predation in Hooded Warblers: Experimental removal of nest cover  Effects of habitat on Dickcissel abundance and nest success in Conservation Reserve Program fields in Kansas  Genetic variation for habitat preference: Evidence and explanations  Community selection by birds on the Helderberg Plateau of New York  Models for guiding management of prairie bird habitat in northwestern North Dakota  Processes organizing open-nesting bird assemblages: Competition or nest predation?  Are microhabitat preferences of coexisting species under selection and adaptive?  Nest predation and nest-site selection of a western population of the Hermit Thrush  Are nest predation and brood parasitism correlated in Yellow Warblers? A test of the cowbird predation hypothesis  Choices and consequences of habitat occupany and nest site selection in Sage Sparrows  Short-term bird response to harvesting switchgrass for biomass in Iowa  Winter bird use of Conservation Reserve Program fields harvested for biomass  . Potential effects on grassland birds of converting marginal cropland to switchgrass biomass production  Thermal aspects of nest-site location for Vesper Sparrows and Horned Larks in British Columbia  Relationship between visual obstruction measurements and weight of grassland vegetation  Ecological and evolutionary traps  A life history study of the yellow-throat  Birds are expected to select nest sites that maximize their reproductive success. In some settings, particularly in human-modified landscapes, birds may make maladaptive choices based on unreliable cues. We studied nest-site selection and the factors that influence reproductive success of Common Yellowthroats (  Geothlypis trichas  ) in managed switchgrass (  Panicum virgatum  ) grasslands in Iowa. We compared vegetation variables at 115 nest sites and corresponding random points. Conditional logistic regression was used to relate nest success, brood parasitism, and number of young fledged per successful nest to vegetation characteristics. Common Yellowthroats selected nest sites with denser and more senescent vegetation, and more forb cover compared with random points. Nest success, however, was negatively related to forb cover. Brood parasitism was not well-explained by any variables. Number of young fledged was positively related to the proportion of senescent vegetation. Selection of nest sites with denser vegetation and more senescent vegetation is consistent with variables reported in the literature and emphasizes the importance of nonharvested areas for Common Yellowthroats in switchgrass fields. Maladaptive preference for nest sites with more forbs could have negative consequences for Common Yellowthroat populations if the pattern we saw persists or applies to other settings.  Se espera que las aves seleccionen sus sitios de anidaci&oacute;n para maximizar su &eacute;xito reproductivo. En algunos lugares, sobre todo en paisajes modificados por el hombre, las aves pueden tomar decisiones maladaptativas, cuando se basan en se&ntilde;ales poco fiables. Estudiamos la selecci&oacute;n de sitios de anidaci&oacute;n y los factores que influyen en el &eacute;xito reproductivo de   Geothlypis trichas   en pastizales manejados de   Panicum virgatum   en Iowa. Comparamos variables de vegetaci&oacute;n en 115 sitios de anidaci&oacute;n y los correspondientes puntos aleatorios. Se utiliz&oacute; una regresi&oacute;n log&iacute;stica condicional para relacionar las caracter&iacute;sticas de vegetaci&oacute;n con el &eacute;xito de anidaci&oacute;n, parasitismo de la nidada, y n&uacute;mero de pichones que exitosamente abandonaron el nido.   Geothlypis trichas   selecciona sitios de anidaci&oacute;n con vegetaci&oacute;n mas densa y con vegetaci&oacute;n senescente, y con mayor cobertura herb&aacute;cea en comparaci&oacute;n a los puntos aleatorios. Sin embargo, el &eacute;xito de nidificaci&oacute;n se relacion&oacute; negativamente con la cobertura herb&aacute;cea. El parasitismo de nidada no se explic&oacute; por ninguna variable. El n&uacute;mero de pichones que dejaron el nido, estuvo positivamente relacionado con la proporci&oacute;n de vegetaci&oacute;n senescente. La selecci&oacute;n de sitios de anidaci&oacute;n con vegetaci&oacute;n m&aacute;s densa y m&aacute;s vegetaci&oacute;n senescente es consistente con las variables reportadas en la literatura y enfatiza la importancia de las zonas no cosechadas de campos de pasto varilla para   Geothlypis trichas  . Preferencias maladaptativas con mayor cobertura herb&aacute;cea para nidifcaci&oacute;n podr&iacute;an tener consecuencias negativas para las poblaciones de   Geothlypis trichas  , si el patr&oacute;n que vimos persiste u ocurre bajo otras condiciones.   Palabras clave:  parasitismo de la nidada,   Geothlypis trichas  , las Praderas, Selecci&oacute;n de Sitios de Anidaci&oacute;n,   Panicum virgatum    Habitat selection by animals is assumed to result from natural selection (e.g.,  Jaenike and Holt 1991 ). Patterns in nest-site selection by birds are expected to have evolved as a result of differential reproduction of individuals among different nesting sites ( Martin 1988 ). Therefore, when choosing nesting sites, birds should use cues that are positively associated with reproductive success, as revealed when birds nesting in preferred sites have higher nest success ( Martin 1988 ,  Martin 1998 ,  Forstmeier and Weiss 2004 ). Decoupling of nest success and nest-site selection could lead to population declines and potential extirpation from a habitat if birds do not select productive habitat ( Schlaepfer et al. 2002 ,  Battin 2004 ). Therefore, it is especially important to understand the relationships between habitat selection and reproductive success in birds of conservation concern, especially in landscapes modified by human activities, where formerly reliable cues may lead birds to make maladaptive choices.  Choice of breeding areas that result in lower reproductive success has been documented for several species in a variety of habitats, particularly following anthropogenic modification (e.g.,  Gates and Gysel 1978 ,  Crabtree et al. 1989 ,  Boal and Mannan 1999 ; reviewed in  Schlaepfer et al. 2002 ,  Battin 2004 ). Most studies that have reported selection for habitat with lower reproductive success than other habitats have focused on selection of habitat types (e.g.,  Crabtree et al. 1989 ) or habitat patches (e.g.,  Bollinger et al. 1990 ). Few studies have examined whether this relationship occurs at the territory placement level within a habitat patch or at the nest-site location within a territory. In one within-patch study,  Misenhelter and Rotenberry (2000 ) found that Sage Sparrows selected territories with lower reproductive success, but they found no relationship between nest-site characteristics within the territory and nest success.  Our objective was to determine whether there was a relationship between the selected nest-site characteristics and reproductive success of Common Yellowthroats (  Geothlypis trichas  ) in managed grasslands in Iowa. We expected that the vegetation variables selected by Common Yellowthroats during nest-site selection would be positively related to nest success and number of fledglings per successful nest and negatively related to brood parasitism. Our study provides information about the relationship between nest-site selection and reproductive success, including brood parasitism, for Common Yellowthroats in fields that differ in habitat structure because of agricultural practices.  We used 15 switchgrass (  Panicum virgatum  ) fields in Appanoose, Lucas, Monroe, and Wayne counties in southern Iowa. All fields were enrolled in the Conservation Reserve Program. Switchgrass is a warm-season grass native to North America, commonly used as a perennial cover in set-aside lands in Iowa. The land cover for the region consisted primarily of grasslands mixed with rowcrops (corn and soybeans) and woodland. Our study fields were part of another study that evaluated the effects of harvesting switchgrass in fall and winter on the avian community in switchgrass fields ( Murray and Best 2003 ,  2006 ; Murray et al. 2003). The fall and winter harvest eliminated any direct effects of the harvest on nest success of grassland birds in this habitat. Five fields were completely harvested, and five fields were harvested in alternating cut and uncut strips with 60&percnt; of the field being harvested. The remaining five fields were not harvested. Fields ranged in size from 3.8 to 13.0 ha ( x̄  &equals; 6.6 ha); a single 8-ha subplot was established in fields &gt;8 ha in size. Harvest brought about differences in vegetation structure early in the growing season among completely harvested, partially harvested, and nonharvested fields, with nonharvested fields having taller, denser vegetation because the residual vegetation in nonharvested areas of fields remained standing in the spring ( Murray and Best 2003 ).  We systematically searched each field for nests three times between 15 May and 15 July in 1999 and 2000. Four or five observers walked abreast (3 m apart), sweeping the vegetation with sticks and scanning for nests and flushed birds. All nests were found by searching the area surrounding where an adult bird was flushed from the vegetation. We also found nests incidentally during other research activities in the fields. Nests were marked with a surveyor flag 5 m north of the nest and checked every 2&ndash;4 days.  We measured vegetation characteristics at each nest within 3 days of the nest failing or fledging young. We recorded vegetation density, vegetation height, canopy cover, and litter depth at the nest location. Vegetation was also measured at random points as part of vegetation measurements for the entire field ( Murray and Best 2003 ). We divided fields into 50 &times; 100 m (0.5 ha) sections and measured vegetation density and vegetation height at a random point in each section once every 2 wk from mid-May to late July. We measured canopy cover and litter depth in mid-June and mid-July at the same points. In partially harvested fields, an equal number of points was measured in cut and uncut areas.  We used the same methods to measure vegetation at nest sites and random points. Vegetation density was measured as visual obstruction readings 4 m from a Robel pole at a height of 1 m in the four cardinal directions and then averaged ( Robel et al. 1970 ). Vegetation height was measured as the tallest piece of vegetation within 1 cm of the Robel pole. Canopy coverage was estimated as nonoverlapping percentages of switchgrass, forbs, other grasses, standing dead vegetation, woody vegetation, litter, and bare ground by using a 0.1-m 2  sampling frame ( Daubenmire 1959 ). Litter depth was measured to the nearest centimeter at the edge of the sampling frame closest to the Robel pole. We defined litter as plant material no longer supported by a stem; all other dead plant material was classified as standing dead vegetation.  Each nest was matched with the closest vegetation point in time and space, based on direction and distance from the corners of the 0.5-ha sections used for vegetation measurements. Exact distances between nest sites and random points were not measured; however, the maximum possible distance between a nest and random point given the sampling scheme was 112 m. We used a paired  t -test for each nest and the nearest random point to test for bias in the dates of vegetation measurements at random points in relation to nest sites for dates standardized as number of days since May 27 (the earliest date of any vegetation measurements for both years).  We investigated patterns of nest-site selection by comparing vegetation measurements between nest sites and random points using linear models in R (R Development Core Team, Vienna, Austria). Models included a random effect for each nest and random point that were paired to account for differences in vegetation among different fields and different areas of fields, allowing analysis to focus on nest-site selection at a small spatial scale. We selected vegetation variables thought to be related to Common Yellowthroat nest-site selection on the basis of previous studies, our observations, and vegetation characteristics appropriate for the habitat. The variables used were visual obstruction, litter depth, proportion of cover in standing senescent vegetation, proportion of cover that was switchgrass, and proportion of cover that was forbs. Visual obstruction and litter depth were log transformed, and all proportions were transformed using an arcsine transformation in our analyses to improve normality and homogeneity of variances; untransformed means and standard errors are reported for easier interpretation. Nest-site selection might differ among harvest treatments; therefore, models including interactions between harvest treatment and point type were examined. For each vegetation variable, three models were compared using Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ): (1) null model, (2) point type (nest or random), and (3) interaction between harvest treatment and point type. Conditional logistic regression was not used for nest-site selection analyses because quasi-complete separation for some vegetation variables caused model convergence errors and extreme log-odds ratios that impeded interpretation of results.  We used conditional logistic regression models to examine factors that influenced the probability of a Common Yellowthroat nest successfully fledging at least one host young and the probability of a nest being parasitized by a Brown-headed Cowbird (  Molothrus ater  ; hereafter &ldquo;cowbird&rdquo;), using the clogit function in R. Conditional logistic regression was used to allow for grouping of nests into strata based on fields to account for variability in nest success associated with field characteristics. Logistic exposure was not used to model nest success because data from individual nest check intervals were not available. A multiple linear regression analysis with the number of young fledged as the dependent variable and a random effect for field was used to assess the variables affecting the number of young fledged per successful nest ( n  &equals; 48) using lme in R. Nests determined to be abandoned between the finding of the nest and the first nest check or that contained cowbird eggs or young were not included in the nest success analysis, giving a final sample size of 97 nests. Parasitized nests were excluded from nest success analyses because the presence of nestling cowbirds could influence the probability of a nest being depredated ( McLaren and Sealy 2000 ). All nests except those abandoned as a result of observer effects were used in the brood parasitism analysis ( n  &equals; 115). We examined three sets of models for time variables, nest-site characteristics, and vegetation variables that might influence reproductive success.  Time-variable models included effects of year, age of nest when found, and date of incubation initiation and additive models of these effects, for a total of nine models for nest success and number of young fledged. The age of a nest when it was found was included because nests found later in the nesting cycle were expected to be more likely to fledge young. The age of the nest when found was not included in the brood parasitism analysis because the age of the nest when found should not influence the rate of parasitism. Age of the nest when found was measured as number of days since incubation began. The date that incubation began was included to examine seasonal effects on nest success. The date that incubation began was standardized as the number of days since May 5, which was the earliest date that incubation began for any nest. Nest age and date of incubation initiation were calculated by backdating nests on the basis of hatching date and/or approximate nestling age, using a 12-day incubation period. For nests depredated before hatching, we used the midpoint between the earliest and latest possible day that incubation began. For example, a nest found with eggs that was depredated before the next nest check could have begun incubation 12 days earlier and been expected to hatch on the day the nest was found, or incubation could have begun on the day the nest was found and been expected to hatch 12 days later; thus, an age of 6.5 days would be assigned to this nest.  Nest-site characteristics used in the models were nest height, proportion of the nest covered (hereafter &ldquo;nest cover&rdquo;), and distance to field edge. Nest height was measured as the distance from the ground to the rim of the nest in centimeters. The proportion of the nest covered was visually estimated by observers 1 m from the nest at a height of 1 m from the four cardinal directions and averaged among the four directions. The distance from the nest to the nearest field edge was visually estimated; a field edge was defined as a habitat that was not switchgrass, including linear habitats such as rows of trees.  The vegetation variables included in the nest success models were visual obstruction, litter depth, proportion of cover in standing senescent vegetation, proportion of cover that was switchgrass, and proportion of cover that was forbs. To allow for easier interpretation of odds ratios, these variables were not transformed for the conditional logistic regression analysis.  We compared models within each set of variables (i.e. time, nest, and vegetation) for each dependent variable, using AIC c . Variables in the best model for each set were used for a final set of additive models combining factors from each model set. The final model set was compared using AIC c , Akaike weights ( w i  ), and variable importance weights calculated for all models ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). We model-averaged the parameter estimates for models within 2 AIC c  units of the best model and report log-odds ratios and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CIs) based on model-averaged estimates ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ). Variables not included in a model were assigned an estimate of zero for that parameter and included in the model-averaged estimates for that parameter. To examine the relationship between a variable and the probability of a nest being successful or the probability that a nest was parasitized, we calculated the predicted probability based on the model-averaged parameters over the range of observed values for the variable of interest. All other variables were held constant at their means for continuous variables and midpoint for dichotomous variables (i.e. 1.5 for year as the midpoint of the first and second year). To account for uncertainty in parameter estimates, we also plotted the predicted probability using the 95&percnt; lower and upper confidence limits for each parameter across the range of values.  The mean date of vegetation measurements for nests was June 28. The date of vegetation measurements (standardized as number of days after May 27 to allow pooling of years) for nest sites and random points was not significantly different for measurements of vegetation density and height (nest &equals; 32.1, random &equals; 31.9,  t  130  &equals; 0.448,  P  &equals; 0.66) or for measurements of percent coverage and litter depth (nest &equals; 32.1, random &equals; 31.0,  t  130  &equals; 1.249,  P  &equals; 0.21). Vegetation measurements at both nest sites and random points were highly variable ( Table 1 ).  Nest versus random points were included in the top models to explain variation in the proportion of forb, visual obstruction, and proportion of senescent vegetation ( Table 2 ). The proportion forb, visual obstruction, and proportion senescent vegetation were greater at nest sites than at random points ( Table 1  and  Figure 1 ). The interaction between point type and harvest treatment was included in the best model explaining the proportion of senescent vegetation ( Table 2 ). Nonharvested and partially harvested fields had greater proportions of senescent vegetation than completely harvested fields; random points in completely harvested fields had no senescent vegetation ( Figure 1 ). The null model best explained variation in litter depth and switchgrass, with some empirical support for a difference between nests and random points ( Table 2 ).  Forty-one percent of nests successfully fledged at least one Common Yellowthroat young ( Murray and Best 2003 ). The age of a nest when it was found and year were included in the top model of nest success for time variables; the model including only nest age was the only other model within 2 AIC c  units ( Table 3 ). Nest cover was the only variable included in the top model of nest success for nest characteristics, but nest height and distance to edge were included in competing models ( Table 3 ). Proportion forb cover was the only variable in the top vegetation model of nest success and also was included in four of the five competing models; litter depth and the proportions of switchgrass and senescent vegetation were also included in models within 2 AIC c  units ( Table 3 ).  The variables included in the final set of nest success models were nest age, year, nest cover, and proportion forb. Only 3 of the 18 models examined received empirical support as competing models ( Table 3 ). Nest age and proportion forb were the only variables included in the best model, and both these variables were also included in the other competing models. Nest cover and year were included in the second- and third-best models, respectively. Nest success was higher for nests found later in the nesting cycle, ranging from 0.52 for nests found on the first day of incubation to 0.97 for nests found 20 days after the start of incubation ( Table 4  and  Figure 2 ), with the odds of a nest succeeding increasing by 19&percnt; each day. Nest success, however, was negatively related to the proportion of forb cover with an odds ratio of 0.04 between 100&percnt; forb coverage and zero forb coverage ( Table 4  and  Figure 2 ). Although the proportion of the nest covered and year were included in the average model of nest success, the 95&percnt; CIs for their coefficients included zero ( Table 4 ). The proportion forb and nest age also had high variable importance weights compared with year and the proportion of the nest covered ( Table 4 ).  Seventeen percent of nests were parasitized by cowbirds. Brood parasitism reduced the number of young fledged by 76&percnt;, from 1.92 (SD &equals; 1.95) young fledged for nests that were not parasitized to 0.47 (SD &equals; 0.86) for parasitized nests. The logistic regression model including date, year, and a date &times; year interaction was the top time model to explain the probability of brood parasitism; there was support for models with year and date alone and for the year-and-date additive model ( Table 5 ). The best nest-characteristic model of brood parasitism was the model including only proportion of the nest covered; models with nest height and distance to the nearest edge also had empirical support ( Table 5 ). Six models of vegetation characteristics had empirical support to explain brood parasitism ( Table 5 ). The best vegetation model included proportions of forb, senescent vegetation, and switchgrass. Other models that received support also included visual obstruction ( Table 5 ). The final set of models for parasitism thus included the full date &times; year interaction, proportion of nest cover, proportion forb, proportion of senescent vegetation, and proportion switchgrass, for a total of 32 models including the null model. Ten models from the final set of models had empirical support ( Table 5 ), with the most support for the model that included proportion of nest covered, proportion switchgrass, and the date &times; time interaction ( Table 5 ). The proportion switchgrass and the date variables were the most important variables explaining the probability of a nest being parasitized, but all 95&percnt; CIs for the coefficients of these variables (except year) spanned zero ( Table 4 ).  The mean number of young fledged per successful nest was 3.65 (SD &equals; 0.89; range: 1&ndash;5). The model with year as the only predictive variable was the only time model with empirical support ( Table 6 ). Nest cover was the best nest-characteristic model to describe the number of young fledged per successful nest ( Table 6 ). Four models of vegetation variables had empirical support to describe variation in the number of young fledged ( Table 6 ). The top model was the model with the amount of senescent vegetation only, and all the competing models also included senescent vegetation. The three other competing models also included the amount of switchgrass in the second- and fourth-best models and the amount of forb in the third- and fourth-best models. The final set of models was thus constructed with year, nest cover, and senescent vegetation as predictor variables. The model of number of young fledged with the most support was the model that included year, nest cover, and senescent vegetation. The model with only year and nest cover also had empirical support ( Table 6 ). The proportion senescent vegetation had strong support as an important variable and was positively related to the number of young fledged ( Table 4  and  Figure 3 ). Proportion of the nest covered and year did not have support as important explanatory variables, and the 95&percnt; CIs for these coefficients spanned zero ( Table 4 ).  Common Yellowthroats selected areas with higher forb abundance, but higher forb abundance was negatively related to nesting success. Selection for nest locations with lower nesting success has been demonstrated for other grassland bird species; however, these are primarily in habitats where low nest success is associated with human activity (e.g., haying;  Bollinger et al. 1990 ). Other studies of nest success of grassland birds did not report a relationship or found a positive relationship between nest success and forb abundance (e.g.,  Hughes et al. 1999 ,  Dion et al. 2000 ,  Davis 2005 ). A mechanism for decreased nest success at nest sites with more forb cover has not been tested; possible mechanisms to investigate include effects of forb cover on predator movement, availability of other prey sources that attract predators, and differences in parental behavior.  Selection of nesting sites with more forbs by Common Yellowthroats, however, may help increase lifetime reproductive success if it helps reduce brood parasitism rates. Proportion of forb around the nest had some support as an important variable to explain brood parasitism, suggesting a decrease in brood parasitism with more forbs. If nest sites with more forb cover are parasitized less often, the behavior of selecting for nest sites with more forb cover could be adaptive, despite lower nest success, given a 17&percnt; rate of parasitism and a 76&percnt; reduction in the number of young fledged from parasitized nests compared with nonparasitized nests.  The negative relationship that we found between brood parasitism and forb abundance contradicts the results of other studies.  Madden et al. (2000 ) demonstrated a positive relationship between cowbird abundance and forb cover in grasslands. In addition, several studies have shown that nests closer to perches have higher parasitism rates (e.g.,  Davis 1994 , Hauber and Russo 2000). In many grasslands, forbs are used as perches by cowbirds; in our study sites, forbs would not be sufficient perches for cowbirds to gain a vantage point to find host nests because of the height and density of grass.  The inconsistent relationships between forb abundance and nest success and brood parasitism in our results may be due to a correlation between forb abundance and an ecological variable not included in our analyses. For example, the abundance of other potential host species might influence nest success and parasitism rates. If Red-winged Blackbirds (  Agelaius phoeniceus  ), a common species in switchgrass fields, were more abundant in areas with more forbs, this could reduce parasitism of Common Yellowthroat nests because the blackbirds might provide both alternative opportunities for cowbirds to lay eggs and defense against cowbirds ( Freeman et al. 1990 ). The presence of other nesting birds might also explain decreased nest success in areas with more forbs if the presence of other nesting birds attracts more predators to the area.  Selection of nest sites with denser vegetation and more senescent vegetation is consistent with findings from other qualitative and quantitative studies of Common Yellowthroat nest placement ( Kendeigh 1945 ,  Stewart 1953 ). Selection for areas with more senescent vegetation appears to be an adaptive behavior, in that the number of young fledged was higher for nests in areas with more senescent vegetation. The presence of senescent vegetation may provide thermal benefits to eggs and nestlings;  Nelson and Martin (1999 ) have shown that vegetation near the nest can help moderate nest temperature. Areas with more senescent vegetation also provided more possible nesting sites, given that 65&percnt; of nests in our study were placed in the base of clumps of senescent switchgrass, other nests being placed in live grass, forbs, or woody vegetation.  A positive relationship between nest age and nest success was predicted because nests found later in the nesting cycle needed to survive fewer days to be considered successful. Increased nest cover also would be expected to increase nest success because it would help to conceal the nest from some potential predators ( Martin and Roper 1988 ). The lack of a relationship between nest concealment and nest success found in our study, however, has been reported in other studies ( Gottfried and Thompson 1978 ,  Holway 1991 ,  Howlett and Stutchbury 1996 ).  Howlett and Stutchbury (1996 ) suggested that a disconnect between nest concealment and predation likely is a result of nonspecialist predators that find nests during chance encounters.  We would expect nest-site selection behavior to be determined by long-term average relationships between nest-site characteristics and nest success during past generations. The relative novelty of switchgrass monocultures may contribute to the disconnect between nest-site selection and nest success; insufficient time may have passed for Common Yellowthroat behavior to evolve in response to a new habitat and environmental changes (e.g., change in the predator community;  Schlaepfer et al. 2002 ). We might expect Common Yellowthroat behavior to evolve to select areas of lesser forbs if the negative relationship between forb abundance and nest success continued over many generations. In addition, nest-predator communities and activity would be expected to vary temporally and spatially. Thus, selection for areas with more forbs may increase nest success over a longer period or larger area than we observed in our study.  It is important to point out that the findings in this study may not be generalizable to other areas because the ecological relationships of nest-site selection, nest parasitism, and brood parasitism will vary spatially. Furthermore, as with any study, variables not measured could also influence nest placement and reproductive success.  Future research evaluating the relationship between nest-site characteristics and nest success should include long-term studies that investigate yearly variation in nest success and nest placement. In addition, future studies should work to identify a mechanism that explains the relationship between forb abundance and nest success. Examination of other aspects of reproduction (i.e. nestling growth and fledgling survival) in relation to nest-site selection also would be necessary to determine the effects of nest-site selection on lifetime reproductive success of Common Yellowthroats.  Selection for nest sites with dense vegetation suggests that switchgrass fields provide breeding habitats and nesting cover for Common Yellowthroats. The higher proportion of senescent vegetation at nest sites than at random points, however, emphasizes the need to maintain unharvested areas with more senescent vegetation to provide nesting habitat for Common Yellowthroats and other birds ( Murray and Best 2003 ). Long-term selection for areas with higher forb abundance despite lower nesting success could potentially lead to population declines of Common Yellowthroats in these habitats.  We thank M. Braster, J. Sellers, and Chariton Valley Resource Conservation and Development, Inc., for help in locating study sites. We also are grateful to T. J. Benson and two anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript, and C. Ribic for statistical advice. Financial support was provided by a grant from the Petroleum Violation Escrow Funds through the Iowa Department of Natural Resources and an award (no. DE-FC36-96G0101148) from the U.S. Department of Energy Biomass Power for Rural Development Program. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the view of the U.S. Department of Energy or the Iowa Department of Natural Resources.  Means of proportion of forb cover, proportion of senescent vegetation cover, and visual obstruction for Common Yellowthroat nests and random points in switchgrass fields in southern Iowa, 1999 and 2000.  Probability of Common Yellowthroat nests fledging at least one young increased for nests found later in the nesting cycle and decreased with increasing forb coverage around the nest. Results from conditional logistic regression were used to create a model-averaged prediction of nest success when all variables were equal to the mean except the variable of interest. Dashed lines represent 95&percnt; confidence intervals based on the confidence limits for the coefficient of the selected variable, with other variables equal to their means.  Number of Common Yellowthroat young fledged per successful nest was positively related to the proportion of vegetation surrounding the nest that was senescent. Circle size represents numbers of nests for each combination of proportion senescent vegetation and number of young fledged; smallest circle &equals; 1 nest, largest circle &equals; 8 nests.  Mean vegetation measurements and standard deviations for Common Yellowthroat nests and random points in switchgrass fields in southern Iowa, 1999 and 2000.  Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ) and weight of importance ( w i  ) for models of differences in vegetation variables between nests and random points for Common Yellowthroats in switchgrass fields in Iowa, 1999 and 2000. Three models were compared for each vegetation variable: (1) nest versus random point, (2) nest versus random point with harvest interaction, and (3) null model (intercept only).  Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ) and model importance weight ( w i  ), among models within 2 AIC c  units, for models explaining Common Yellowthroat nest success in switchgrass fields in Iowa, 1999 and 2000. The variables in the top model for each model set (i.e. time, nest characteristics, and vegetation) were included in a set of final models.  Variable importance weights  w  &plus; ( j ), coefficients, 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CI), and odds ratios from model-averaged models to explain nest success, brood parasitism, and number of young fledged per successful nest in Common Yellowthroats in switchgrass fields in Iowa, 1999 and 2000. Conditional logistic regression models were used for nest-success and brood-parasitism analysis; linear regression analysis was used for number of young fledged per successful nest.  Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ) and model importance weight ( w i  ), among models within 2 AIC c  units, for models explaining brood parasitism by Brown-headed Cowbirds of Common Yellowthroat nests in switchgrass fields in Iowa, 1999 and 2000. The variables in the top model for each model set (i.e. time, nest characteristics, and vegetation) were included in a set of final models.  Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AIC c ) and model importance weight ( w i  ), among models within 2 AIC c  units, for models explaining number of young fledged per successful Common Yellowthroat nest in switchgrass fields in Iowa, 1999 and 2000. The variables in the top model for each model set (i.e. time, nest characteristics, and vegetation) were included in a set of final models. 