The enigmatic Black Tinamou: Do distribution, climate, and vocalizations reveal more than one species?A phylogeny of the tinamous (Aves: Palaeognathiformes) based on integumentary characters<italic>Tinamus osgoodi:</italic> IUCN Red List of Threatened SpeciesA Colombian race of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic>First photographs of Black Tinamou <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> in Ecuador with notes on subspecific identity and occurrenceFamily Tinamidae (Tinamous)A new species of <italic>Tinamus</italic> from PeruNew distributional bird data from the Cordillera Central of the Colombian Andes, with implications for the biogeography of northwestern South AmericaAvifauna of the Northern Cordillera Central of the Andes, Colombia<italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic>Rediscovery of Southern Horned Curassow <italic>Pauxi unicornis koepckeae</italic> in Cerros del Sira, PeruVery high resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areasTaxonomy and conservation: A tale of two tinamous species groupDistinctive song of highland form <italic>maculicollis</italic> of the Red-winged Tinamou (<italic>Rhynchotus rufescens</italic>): Evidence for species rankBirds of the Cerros del Tivara (300&ndash;900 m)Seewave: A free modular tool for sound analysis and synthesisNotes on birds from the Marcapata Valley, Cuzco, PeruThe Black Tinamou (<italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic>) is a rare species with 2 recognized subspecies distributed locally. This is one of the most poorly known tinamous; few sound recordings exist, and few behavioral or sighting records are found in the literature or in ornithological databases. We compiled all the information on its geographic distribution and climate to provide a greater understanding of its current distribution. We also compiled all available sound recordings of the species in order to perform bioacoustic analyses to evaluate differences between subspecies. The 2 subspecies seem to be isolated by an ample distance, and each inhabits an area with a distinct climate. We also found some differences between their vocalizations. Future work should consider reevaluating the taxonomic status of the 2 subspecies. Conservation status of the resulting taxa must be reassessed, although more information on their ecology and natural history is needed.<italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> es una especie rara y muy local con dos subespecies reconocidas. Es uno de los tinam&uacute;s menos conocidos: hay pocas observaciones de su comportamiento en la literatura, pocas grabaciones de su canto y muy pocos registros en las bases de datos ornitol&oacute;gicas. Recopilamos toda la informaci&oacute;n de su distribuci&oacute;n geogr&aacute;fica y clima para entender mejor su distribuci&oacute;n actual. Adicionalmente buscamos todas las grabaciones de sonido disponibles de la especie para determinar si existen diferencias entre las subespecies. Las dos subespecies parece est&aacute;n aisladas por una distancia considerable para un tinam&uacute; y habitan &aacute;reas con caracter&iacute;sticas clim&aacute;ticas distintas. Adicionalmente existen muchas diferencias entre sus vocalizaciones. Futuras investigaciones deben reevaluar el estatus taxon&oacute;mico de las dos subespecies. El estado de conservaci&oacute;n de los taxones resultantes debe ser reevaluado, y mas informaci&oacute;n de la historia natural y ecolog&iacute;a para las dos formas es necesaria.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> Am&eacute;rica del sur, limites de especie, Tinamidae, vocalizacionesThe Black Tinamou (<italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f01">Figure 1</xref>) is a very rare bird, known only from 2 small regions: the head of the Magdalena valley in southern Colombia, and east of Cusco in southern Peru (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Hilty1">Hilty and Brown 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cabot1">Cabot 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Schulenberg1">Schulenberg et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f02">Figure 2</xref>). In the past 2 decades, new localities and noteworthy records have been reported in the literature, such as Cerros del Tavara and Serranias Cofan in Ecuador, Antioquia in Colombia, and Reserva Megantoni in Peru (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Pitman1">Pitman et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Vriesendorp1">Vriesendorp et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cuervo1">Cuervo et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cuervo2">2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Brinkhuizen1">Brinkhuizen and C&oacute;rdova-Saeteros 2011</xref>). Although recent records indicate that its range is larger than previously thought, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-BirdLifeInternational1">BirdLife International (2014)</xref> has retained this species' Red List status as Vulnerable (VU), a classification typically associated with populations undergoing rapid decline in some parts of their distribution, mainly as a result of hunting pressure and/or ongoing habitat loss and degradation.Black Tinamou (<italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic>) in Alto Fragua National Park, Colombia. Photo credit: Pablo Jose NegretMap with all geographic records of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> compiled, used for climatic analyses.Tinamous are sedentary, ground-dwelling birds with poor flight abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cabot1">Cabot 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Bertelli1">Bertelli et al. 2002</xref>). They are cryptic, shy, and secretive birds, but their calls are very distinctive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cabot1">Cabot 1992</xref>). The vocalizations of tinamous are assumed to be innate; thus, any variation between populations may reflect genetic differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cabot1">Cabot 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma and Miller 1996</xref>), which offers the possibility of using such variation in proposing species limits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Maijer1">Maijer 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cadena1">Laverde-R. and Cadena 2014</xref>).We compiled all the localities reported for this species in the literature and in biodiversity databases to evaluate climatic and elevational differences between subspecies and to assess the current geographic distribution. We also compiled and described vocalizations of Black Tinamous, highlighting the differences between <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> and <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>.The Black Tinamou has 2 recognized subspecies and 1 unassigned population: <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Conover1">Conover 1949</xref>), which ranges from Peru to Bolivia; <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Blake1">Blake 1953</xref>), located in northern Ecuador and southern Colombia; and the isolated population of unknown taxonomic affinities found in 1998 in the northern Cordillera Central of the Colombian Andes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cuervo3">Cuervo and Toro 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cuervo1">Cuervo et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cuervo2">2008b</xref>). This species inhabits humid forest in tropical and subtropical zones (foothills) of the eastern Andes, where epiphytes, tree ferns, bromeliads, and mosses are abundant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cabot1">Cabot 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Brinkhuizen1">Brinkhuizen and C&oacute;rdova-Saeteros 2011</xref>)&mdash;features that characterize the tall primary forest in this part of the mountains.We collected geographic data from the literature, sound libraries, and biodiversity databases (eBird, GBIF, xeno-canto, and Macaulay Library of Natural Sounds; see Acknowledgments). We used the Latin and English name of the species for searching records in databases and libraries. Also, we asked researchers and birders who work in these areas for recent, unpublished records. We posted an e-mail to the Peruvian bird discussion list (INCASPIZA) to contact researchers from Peru; Juan Freile provided some information from Ecuador, and personal contacts helped us find researchers with some information from Colombia (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t03">Table 3</xref> in the Appendix).Using records found in the literature and in the biodiversity databases, we assessed variability in the species' elevational range. Some records gave a range of elevation instead of an exact value; in these cases, we used the mid-elevational point for the analysis. We extracted bioclimatic data used in WorldClim version 1.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Hijmans1">Hijmans et al. 2005</xref>; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t01">Table 1</xref>) from all the records and conducted a principal component analysis (PCA) to condense the information into fewer variables. Finally, we plotted and analyzed the first 2 components. We tested for differences between subspecies in elevational and climatic data using Student's <italic>t</italic>-test for unpaired observations.Principal components (PC1 and PC2) of bioclimatic variables (from WorldClim version 1.2) associated with localities of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi hershkovitzi</italic> and <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>. Values for the 2 most important variables in each component are in bold.Results of analyses of vocalizations of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi osgoodi</italic> and <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi. P</italic> values in bold emphasize the significant differences between subspecies.We compiled all available recordings of Black Tinamous from commercial CDs, xeno-canto, and the Macaulay Library of Natural Sounds (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t04">Table 4</xref> in the Appendix). Three previously unpublished vocalizations of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> were recorded by P.J.N. using a Zoom H4N Handy Portable Digital Recorder in the Indi-wasi National Park in southern Colombia. The birds were recorded, then they were identified by asking local people, and also vocalization identification was confirmed by P.J.N. in the field by observing the birds calling. We measured the number of notes, the length and bandwidth of vocalizations, the maximum and minimum frequencies, and the peak frequency and bandwidth of notes. Vocalizations were processed in Raven version 1.5 (Cornell Lab of Ornithology, Ithaca, New York, USA), using the following combination of settings: FFT window &equals; 512, window type &equals; Hann, and window overlap &equals; 50&percnt;. Maximum and minimum frequencies were measured using a threshold set at &minus;20 dB from the maximum amplitude of peak frequency. To explore differences in vocalizations between subspecies, we made sonograms in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2013</xref>), using the &ldquo;seewave&rdquo; package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Sueur1">Sueur et al. 2008</xref>). Because of the small sample size for <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>, we tested for differences between populations using the Mann-Whitney nonparametric <italic>U</italic>-test for 2 independent samples.In total, we obtained 25 geographic records for the Black Tinamou: 13 corresponding to <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>, 11 to <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>, and 1 to the Central Andean population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t03">Table 3</xref> in the Appendix). There is an evident gap in the records, with &sim;1,100 km between the northernmost record of <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> and the southernmost record of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>. The locality of the northern Central Andean population is on the western slope of the Andes, &sim;600 km north of the northernmost record of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>. Nevertheless, this record has not been confirmed: Over the past few years, the many birders and ornithologists who have visited this area have not reported any sightings or collected specimen or voice records of the species (A. Cuervo personal communication). Future expeditions and recordings of vocalizations are necessary to clarify (1) the presence of the species in the area; and (2) if present, the status and identity of this very local and isolated population. The record from Cerros del Sira in Huanaco, central Peru, mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Gastanaga1">Gasta&ntilde;aga et al. (2007)</xref>, was a misidentification: The bird in the photographs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Gastanaga1">Gasta&ntilde;aga et al. 2007</xref>: figure 2) turned out to be a Gray Tinamou (<italic>T. tao</italic>; D. Lane personal communication).The elevational limits of all the historical and recent records of the Black Tinamou over its whole geographic range are 300 and 2,100 m. We found a significant difference in elevational ranges between subespecies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f03">Figure 3</xref>; <italic>t</italic> &equals; 2.43, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.027): <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> was registered at lower altitudes (300 m in Cosha Cashu, Cusco, Peru), where 2 nests were found (G. Londo&ntilde;o personal communication); the lowest elevation where <italic>T. o hershkovitzi</italic> has been recorded is 800 m, in southern Colombia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t03">Table 3</xref> in the Appendix).Box plot of elevational ranges of <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> and <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>.The first 2 principal components explained 92.5&percnt; of variation in climatic information for <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> and <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The first component (PC1; 67.4&percnt;) loaded mainly precipitation variables (BIO19: precipitation of coldest quarter; BIO14: precipitation of driest quarter), and the second component (PC2; 25.1&percnt;) loaded temperature seasonality (BIO4). We found strong significant differences between subspecies in precipitation data (PC1; <italic>t</italic> &equals; 4.08, df &equals; 21.30, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and temperature seasonality data (PC2; <italic>t</italic> &equals; 4.7386, df &equals; 20.24, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). <italic>Tinamus o. osgoodi</italic> lives in areas where temperature is more seasonal, which is related to higher latitudes; and <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> prefers more humid areas, in the Amazon foothills between Ecuador and Colombia.Principal component analysis of bioclimatic data associated with localities of the Black Tinamou.We obtained 3 recordings with 6 vocalizations of <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> and 5 recordings with 8 vocalizations of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t04">Table 4</xref> in the Appendix). We found 3 different types of vocalizations in recordings of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic>. The first type (presumably the territorial song, which was the most common vocalization) is a song of 2 or 3 notes, from 2.66 to 5.11 s long, with a narrow frequency bandwidth of 400 Hz (range: 156&ndash;566 Hz; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). The second type is a longer vocalization of 5 notes, the first of which is a U-shaped, slightly modulated note; this call was given when 2 birds close together were disturbed by the presence of a researcher&mdash;the birds flew away and then started to call each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f05">Figure 5</xref>B). This vocalization was also recorded in Sumaco, Ecuador, and was repeated every &sim;2 min, but the context was not very clear (Du&scaron;an M. Brinkhuizen; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xeno-canto.org/forum/topic/8559" xlink:type="simple">http://www.xeno-canto.org/forum/topic/8559</ext-link>). The third type is the longest call (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 1), with 17 nonmodulated notes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f05">Figure 5</xref>C); this vocalization was not included in the analyses. In <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>, we found only 1 type of vocalization with a single note, which lasted 1.32 to 2.32 s, occupying a very narrow frequency bandwidth of 87 to 311 Hz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f05">Figure 5</xref>D, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f05">5</xref>E). Acoustic analyses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t05">Table 5</xref> in the Appendix) found differences between the 2 forms: <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> has longer vocalizations with more, but shorter, notes than <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>. In the spectral domain, maximum frequency was significantly different between populations: <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> produces vocalizations with higher maximum frequency than <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-t02">Table 2</xref>).Spectrograms of vocalizations from (<bold>A</bold>&ndash;<bold>C</bold>) <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> and (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic>.The distribution of the Black Tinamou shows that the 2 recognized subspecies may deserve species status, supported by 5 types of evidence. (1) There is a clear gap of 1,100 km between the edges of the distributions, and tinamous are not good dispersers. Nevertheless, a geographic barrier between populations does not seem to exist, because there is &ldquo;continuous&rdquo; habitat between subspecies ranges. (2) Bioclimatic information shows differences in temperature seasonality and precipitation. <italic>Tinamus o. hershkovitzi</italic> lives closer to the equator, where the climate is more tropical, but at higher altitude, whereas <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> lives in areas with more climatic variation throughout the year (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f04">Figure 4</xref>). (3) Elevational ranges differ between subspecies; <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> has not been recorded below 800 m and is very common between 1,400 and 1,500 m, whereas <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> has been recorded at lower elevations (300 m) but is more common between 1,000 and 1,350 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Pitman1">Pitman et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Vriesendorp1">Vriesendorp et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Brinkhuizen1">Brinkhuizen and C&oacute;rdova-Saeteros 2011</xref>). (4) Vocalizations are very different between subspecies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-f04">Figure 4</xref>); however, we still need more recordings from both populations to understand variation within and between subspecies. (5) We did not examine the specimens stored at the Chicago Field Museum, but differences in plumage between subspecies were evident, given that they were described as different forms. In general, the plumage of <italic>T. o. osgoodi</italic> is darker, with distinct speckling, vermiculation, or barring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Traylor1">Traylor 1952</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Blake1">Blake 1953</xref>); and the feathers of <italic>T. o. hershkovitzi</italic> are more or less edged with black, but without dark vermiculation or speckling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Blake1">Blake 1953</xref>).The north-central Andes record has not been confirmed. During recent years, birders and ornithologists have been watching and looking for rare birds around the area, without any sight, specimen, or voice recordings (A. Cuervo personal communication). Recordings of vocalizations and/or specimens are necessary to confirm the presence and the status of such a local, isolated population. Pictures are not reliable proofs in some cases; one misidentified record comes from a picture taken at Cerros del Sira in Huanaco, central Peru, but the bird in the picture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Gastanaga1">Gasta&ntilde;aga et al. 2007</xref>: figure 2) is actually the Gray Tinamou (D. Lane personal communication).The Black Tinamou is considered one of the rarest tinamous; this new information on the differences between subspecies should be taken into account, not only in future taxonomic work, but also in future conservation assessments and management plans for the species. Song differences in vocal nonlearners, including Tinamous, have been used for rapid assessment of taxonomic limits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Maijer1">Maijer 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-132-Cadena1">Laverde-R. and Cadena 2014</xref>), but we need more studies to better understand the relationship between species limits and song differences in this special family.We thank P. Stevenson for scientific advice and support in the field. We thank G. Budney, M. Medler, and T. Bishop of the Macaulay Library of Natural Sounds; P. Caycedo of the Colecci&oacute;n de Sonidos Ambientales, Instituto Alexander von Humboldt; and recordists D. Lane, D. Geale, and D. M. Brinkhuizen, who uploaded recordings in xeno-canto, making them available for our study. We thank A. Cuervo and D. Lane for sharing their knowledge of this species, and P. Pulgarin, C. Devenish, and K. Swing for comments on the manuscript. Biodiversity databases used in this study: eBird (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ebird.org" xlink:type="simple">http://ebird.org</ext-link>), GBIF (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gbif.org</ext-link>), xeno-canto (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xeno-canto.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.xeno-canto.org</ext-link>), and Macaulay Library of Natural Sounds (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://macaulaylibrary.org" xlink:type="simple">http://macaulaylibrary.org</ext-link>).Geographic records of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> subspecies.Geographic information on vocalizations of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> subspecies.Acoustic measurements of vocalizations of <italic>Tinamus osgoodi</italic> subspecies.