Fifty-Fifth Supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Genetic structure, conservation genetics and evidence of speciation by range expansion in Shy and White-capped albatrossesPhylogeography of Shy and White-capped albatrosses inferred from mitochondrial DNA sequences: Implications for population history and taxonomySpeciation on oceanic islands: Rapid adaptive divergence vs. cryptic speciation on a Guadalupe Island songbird (Aves: <italic>Junco</italic>)Multilocus analysis of a taxonomically densely sampled dataset reveal &lsqb;<italic>sic</italic>&rsqb; extensive non-monophyly in the avian family LocustellidaeForty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Estrildinae finches (Aves, Passeriformes) from Africa, South Asia and Australia: A molecular phylogeographic studyForty-ninth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union Check-list of North American BirdsClassification of a clade of New World doves (Columbidae: Zenaidini)First record of a Shy Albatross in AlaskaFamily IcteridaeA Brown Hawk-Owl (<italic>Ninox scutulata</italic>) from Kiska Island, Aleutian Islands, AlaskaThe type locality of Craveri's Murrelet <italic>Synthliboramphus craveri</italic>Phylogenetic conservatism and antiquity of a tropical specialization: Army-ant-following in the typical antbirds (Thamnophilidae)Phylogenetics and diversification of tanagers (Passeriformes: Thraupidae), the largest radiation of Neotropical songbirdsBiogeography and evolutionary history of the Neotropical genus <italic>Saltator</italic> (Aves: Thraupini)Fiftieth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Fifty-first supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Fifty-second supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Fifty-fourth supplement to the American Ornithologists' Union <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic>Phylogeny and classification of <italic>Automolus</italic> foliage-gleaners and allies (Furnariidae)Lineage diversification and morphological evolution in a large-scale continental radiation: The Neotropical ovenbirds and woodcreepers (Aves: Furnariidae)Report of the California Bird Records Committee: 2001 recordsCatalogue of birds of the AmericasIdentification of immature Salvin's, Chatham and Buller's albatrossesOregon's first White-capped Albatross (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Diomedea cauta</named-content> cauta</italic>)Checklist of the Birds of the Oriental RegionBuild-up of the Himalayan avifauna through immigration: A biogeographical analysis of the <italic>Phylloscopus</italic> and <italic>Seicercus</italic> warblersThe Central American land bridge as an engine of diversification in New World dovesSpecies limits in the Brown Boobook <italic>Ninox scutulata</italic> complexPhylogenetic relationships of the extinct Carolina Parakeet (<italic>Conuropsis carolinensis</italic>) inferred from DNA sequence dataA Siberian Chiffchaff (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus collybita</named-content> tristis</italic>) at Gambell, AlaskaMolecular phylogenetics and diversification of the genus <italic>Sporophila</italic> (Aves: Passeriformes)Mitochondrial and next-generation sequence data used to infer phylogenetic relationships and species limits in the Clapper/King rail complexMolecular phylogenetics of the Neotropical seedeaters and seed-finches (<italic>Sporophila</italic>, <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>, <italic>Dolospingus</italic>)Report of the California Bird Records Committee: 2000 recordsSpeciation in the avian genus <italic>Junco</italic>Song divergence in hummingbird and junco populations on Guadalupe IslandEvolutionary relationships among extant albatrosses (Procellariiformes: Diomedeidae) established from complete cytochrome-<italic>b</italic> gene sequencesLista Oficial de las Aves de Costa Rica &ndash; Actualizaci&oacute;nA revision of the subspecies of <italic>Sporophila</italic> (&ldquo;<italic>Oryzoborus</italic>&rdquo;) <italic>angolensis</italic> (Aves: Emberizidae)The nature of the variability in the Variable Seedeater in Panama (<italic>Sporophila americana</italic>: Emberizinae)Non-monophyletic taxa and cryptic species&mdash;Evidence from a molecular phylogeny of leaf-warblers (<italic>Phylloscopus</italic>, Aves)Family EstrildidaeA comprehensive species-level molecular phylogeny of the New World blackbirds (Icteridae)Patterns and processes of diversification in a widespread and ecologically diverse avian group, the buteonine hawks (Aves, Accipitridae)DNA-sequence data require revision of the parrot genus <italic>Aratinga</italic> (Aves: Psittacidae)A classification of the bird species of South AmericaMolecular systematics and patterns of diversification in <italic>Pyrrhura</italic> (Psittacidae), with special reference to the <italic>picta-leucotis</italic> complexMolecular systematics in <italic>Aratinga</italic> parakeets: Species limits and historical biogeography in the <italic>solstitialis</italic> group, and the systematic position of <italic>Nandayus nenday</italic>The birds of North and Middle AmericaThe birds of North and Middle AmericaSalvin's Albatross (<italic>Thalassarche salvini</italic>) on Midway AtollOld divergences in a boreal bird supports &lsqb;<italic>sic</italic>&rsqb; long-term survival through the Ice AgesNotes on the classification of the pigeonsA record of the Tasmanian White-capped Albatross, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Diomedea cauta</named-content> cauta</italic>, in American North Pacific watersClade-limited colonization in brood parasitic finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp.)When black plus white equals gray: The nature of variation in the variable seedeater complex (Emberizinae: <italic>Sporophila</italic>)The Birds of the Palearctic Fauna: Order PasseriformesFamily SylviidaeAndean uplift promotes lowland speciation through vicariance and dispersal in <italic>Dendrocincla</italic> woodcreepersFirst North American record of Brown Hawk-Owl (<italic>Ninox scutulata</italic>) on St. Paul Island, AlaskaThis is the 14th supplement since publication of the 7th edition of the <italic>Check-list of North American Birds</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">American Ornithologists' Union &lsqb;AOU&rsqb; 1998</xref>). It summarizes decisions made between May 15, 2013, and May 15, 2014, by the AOU's Committee on Classification and Nomenclature&mdash;North and Middle America. The Committee has continued to operate in the manner outlined in the 42nd Supplement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion3">AOU 2000</xref>).Changes in this supplement include the following: (1) three species (<italic>Ciconia maguari</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus collybita</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></italic>) are added to the main list on the basis of new distributional information; (2) four species (<italic>Thalassarche salvini</italic>, <italic>Rallus tenuirostris</italic>, <italic>Phylloscopus examinandus</italic>, and <italic>Junco insularis</italic>) are added to the main list as a result of splits from species already on the list; (3) two species (<italic>Rallus obsoletus</italic> and <italic>R. crepitans</italic>) are added to the main list and one species (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rallus longirostris</named-content></italic>) is lost because of the split of that species; (4) three species names are changed (to <italic>Ninox japonica</italic>, <italic>Gymnopithys bicolor</italic>, and <italic>Sporophila corvina</italic>) because of splits from extralimital species; (5) the distributional statement of one species (<italic>Pyrrhura picta</italic>) is changed because of splits of extralimital species; (6) the distributional statement and English name of one species <italic>(<named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassarche cauta</named-content></italic>) and the distributional statement of another (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus borealis</named-content></italic>) are changed as a result of taxonomic changes; (7) seven genera (<italic>Leptotrygon</italic>, <italic>Zentrygon</italic>, <italic>Eupsittula</italic>, <italic>Psittacara</italic>, <italic>Cassiculus</italic>, <italic>Spermestes</italic>, and <italic>Euodice</italic>) are added as a result of splits from other genera, resulting in changes to 20 scientific names (<italic>L. veraguensis</italic>, <italic>Z. carrikeri</italic>, <italic>Z. costaricensis</italic>, <italic>Z. lawrencii</italic>, <italic>Z. albifacies</italic>, <italic>Z. chiriquensis</italic>, <italic>Z. goldmani</italic>, <italic>Eupsittula nana</italic>, <italic>E. canicularis</italic>, <italic>E. pertinax</italic>, <italic>P. holochlorus</italic>, <italic>P. strenuus</italic>, <italic>P. finschi</italic>, <italic>P. euops</italic>, <italic>P. chloropterus</italic>, <italic>P. mitratus</italic>, <italic>Cassiculus melanicterus</italic>, <italic>S. cucullata</italic>, <italic>Euodice malabarica</italic>, and <italic>E. cantans</italic>); (8) one genus (<italic>Clibanornis</italic>) is added as a result of a transfer of a species (<italic>C. rubiginosus</italic>) to a formerly extralimital genus; (9) four genera (<italic>Nandayus</italic>, <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>, and <italic>Padda</italic>) are lost by merger (into <italic>Aratinga</italic>, <italic>Automolus</italic>, <italic>Sporophila</italic>, and <italic>Lonchura</italic>, respectively) and the scientific names of seven species (<italic>Aratinga nenday</italic>, <italic>Automolus subulatus</italic>, <italic>S. nuttingi</italic>, <italic>S. funerea</italic>, <italic>S. crassirostris</italic>, <italic>S. angolensis</italic>, and <italic>L. oryzivora</italic>) are thereby changed; (10) the type locality for one species (<italic>Synthliboramphus craveri</italic>) is corrected; (11) the English names of 10 species (<italic>Buteogallus anthracinus</italic>, <italic>B. gundlachii</italic>, <italic>B. urubitinga</italic>, <italic>Phylloscopus proregulus</italic>, <italic>Chlorospingus flavopectus</italic>, <italic>C. tacarcunae</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. inornatus</named-content></italic>, <italic>C. pileatus</italic>, <italic>C. flavigularis</italic>, and <italic>C. canigularis</italic>) are changed to reflect new information on their phylogenetic relationships; (12) the English name of one species (<italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic>) is changed to conform with global usage; and (13) one species (<italic>Thalassarche eremita</italic>) is added to the Appendix. In addition, the English names of three species are transferred to other scientific names in the aftermath of taxonomic changes: thus, Clapper Rail is now the English name for <italic>Rallus crepitans</italic> rather than <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. longirostris</named-content></italic>, Bicolored Antbird is now the English name for <italic>Gymnopithys bicolor</italic> rather than <italic>G. leucaspis</italic>, and Variable Seedeater is now the English name for <italic>Sporophila corvina</italic> rather than <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. americana</named-content></italic>.One family name (Locustellidae) is changed in accordance with the rules of priority for group names. New linear sequences are adopted for species in the genera <italic>Dendrocincla</italic>, <italic>Saltator</italic>, and <italic>Sporophila</italic>, and for species currently and formerly (see below) in the genera <italic>Geotrygon</italic>, <italic>Aratinga</italic>, <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, <italic>Automolus</italic>, <italic>Thripadectes</italic>, <italic>Lonchura</italic>, and <italic>Padda</italic>, all due to new phylogenetic data.Literature that provides the basis for the Committee's decisions is cited at the end of this supplement, and citations not already in the Literature Cited of the 7th edition (with supplements) become additions to it. A list of the bird species known from the AOU <italic>Check-list</italic> area can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://checklist.aou.org/taxa" xlink:type="simple">http://checklist.aou.org/taxa</ext-link>.The following changes to the 7th edition (page numbers refer thereto) and its supplements result from the Committee's actions:pp. xvii&ndash;liv. Change the number in the title of the list of species to 2,098. Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:<bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassarche cauta</named-content></italic></bold> White-capped Albatross. (A)<bold><italic>Thalassarche salvini</italic></bold> Salvin's Albatross. (A)<bold><italic>Ciconia maguari</italic></bold> Maguari Stork. (A)<bold><italic>Buteogallus anthracinus</italic></bold> Common Black Hawk.<bold><italic>Buteogallus gundlachii</italic></bold> Cuban Black Hawk.<bold><italic>Buteogallus urubitinga</italic></bold> Great Black Hawk.<bold><italic>Rallus obsoletus</italic></bold> Ridgway's Rail.<bold><italic>Rallus tenuirostris</italic></bold> Aztec Rail.<bold><italic>Rallus crepitans</italic></bold> Clapper Rail.<bold><italic>Leptotrygon veraguensis</italic></bold> Olive-backed Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon carrikeri</italic></bold> Tuxtla Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon costaricensis</italic></bold> Buff-fronted Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon lawrencii</italic></bold> Purplish-backed Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon albifacies</italic></bold> White-faced Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon chiriquensis</italic></bold> Chiriqui Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Zentrygon goldmani</italic></bold> Russet-crowned Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Ninox japonica</italic></bold> Northern Boobook. (A)<bold><italic>Eupsittula nana</italic></bold> Olive-throated Parakeet.<bold><italic>Eupsittula canicularis</italic></bold> Orange-fronted Parakeet.<bold><italic>Eupsittula pertinax</italic></bold> Brown-throated Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga nenday</italic></bold> Nanday Parakeet. (I)<bold><italic>Psittacara holochlorus</italic></bold> Green Parakeet.<bold><italic>Psittacara strenuus</italic></bold> Pacific Parakeet.<bold><italic>Psittacara finschi</italic></bold> Crimson-fronted Parakeet.<bold><italic>Psittacara euops</italic></bold> Cuban Parakeet.<bold><italic>Psittacara chloropterus</italic></bold> Hispaniolan Parakeet.<bold><italic>Psittacara mitratus</italic></bold> Mitred Parakeet. (I)<bold><italic>Gymnopithys bicolor</italic></bold> Bicolored Antbird.<bold><italic>Clibanornis rubiginosus</italic></bold> Ruddy Foliage-gleaner.<bold><italic>Automolus subulatus</italic></bold> Striped Woodhaunter.<bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus collybita</named-content></italic></bold> Common Chiffchaff. (A)<bold><italic>Phylloscopus proregulus</italic></bold> Pallas's Leaf Warbler. (A)<bold><italic>Phylloscopus examinandus</italic></bold> Kamchatka Leaf Warbler. (A)<bold>LOCUSTELLIDAE</bold><bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus flavopectus</italic></bold> Common Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus tacarcunae</italic></bold> Tacarcuna Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus inornatus</italic></bold> Pirre Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus pileatus</italic></bold> Sooty-capped Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus flavigularis</italic></bold> Yellow-throated Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>&ast;Chlorospingus canigularis</italic></bold> Ashy-throated Chlorospingus.<bold><italic>Cassiculus melanicterus</italic></bold> Yellow-winged Cacique.<bold><italic>&ast;Sporophila funerea</italic></bold> Thick-billed Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>&ast;Sporophila nuttingi</italic></bold> Nicaraguan Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>&ast;Sporophila crassirostris</italic></bold> Large-billed Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>&ast;Sporophila corvina</italic></bold> Variable Seedeater.<bold><italic>&ast;<named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></italic></bold> Lined Seedeater. (A)<bold><italic>Junco insularis</italic></bold> Guadalupe Junco.<bold><italic>Spermestes cucullata</italic></bold> Bronze Mannikin. (I)<bold><italic>Euodice malabarica</italic></bold> Indian Silverbill. (I)<bold><italic>Euodice cantans</italic></bold> African Silverbill. (I)<bold><italic>Lonchura oryzivora</italic></bold> Java Sparrow. (I)<bold><italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic></bold> Scaly-breasted Munia. (I)Delete the following names:<bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassarche cauta</named-content></italic></bold> Shy Albatross. (A)<bold><italic>Buteogallus anthracinus</italic></bold> Common Black-Hawk.<bold><italic>Buteogallus gundlachii</italic></bold> Cuban Black-Hawk.<bold><italic>Buteogallus urubitinga</italic></bold> Great Black-Hawk.<bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rallus longirostris</named-content></italic></bold> Clapper Rail.<bold><italic>Geotrygon veraguensis</italic></bold> Olive-backed Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon albifacies</italic></bold> White-faced Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon chiriquensis</italic></bold> Chiriqui Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon carrikeri</italic></bold> Tuxtla Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon lawrencii</italic></bold> Purplish-backed Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon costaricensis</italic></bold> Buff-fronted Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Geotrygon goldmani</italic></bold> Russet-crowned Quail-Dove.<bold><italic>Ninox scutulata</italic></bold> Brown Hawk-Owl. (A)<bold><italic>Aratinga holochlora</italic></bold> Green Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga strenua</italic></bold> Pacific Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga finschi</italic></bold> Crimson-fronted Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga mitrata</italic></bold> Mitred Parakeet. (I)<bold><italic>Aratinga chloroptera</italic></bold> Hispaniolan Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga euops</italic></bold> Cuban Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga nana</italic></bold> Olive-throated Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga canicularis</italic></bold> Orange-fronted Parakeet.<bold><italic>Aratinga pertinax</italic></bold> Brown-throated Parakeet.<bold><italic>Nandayus nenday</italic></bold> Nanday Parakeet. (I)<bold><italic>Gymnopithys leucaspis</italic></bold> Bicolored Antbird.<bold><italic>Hyloctistes subulatus</italic></bold> Striped Woodhaunter.<bold><italic>Automolus rubiginosus</italic></bold> Ruddy Foliage-gleaner.<bold><italic>Phylloscopus proregulus</italic></bold> Pallas's Leaf-Warbler. (A)<bold>MEGALURIDAE</bold><bold><italic>Chlorospingus flavopectus</italic></bold> Common Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Chlorospingus tacarcunae</italic></bold> Tacarcuna Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Chlorospingus inornatus</italic></bold> Pirre Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Chlorospingus pileatus</italic></bold> Sooty-capped Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Chlorospingus flavigularis</italic></bold> Yellow-throated Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Chlorospingus canigularis</italic></bold> Ashy-throated Bush-Tanager.<bold><italic>Cacicus melanicterus</italic></bold> Yellow-winged Cacique.<bold><italic>Oryzoborus nuttingi</italic></bold> Nicaraguan Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>Oryzoborus funereus</italic></bold> Thick-billed Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>Oryzoborus crassirostris</italic></bold> Large-billed Seed-Finch.<bold><italic>Sporophila americana</italic></bold> Variable Seedeater.<bold><italic>Lonchura malabarica</italic></bold> Indian Silverbill. (I)<bold><italic>Lonchura cantans</italic></bold> African Silverbill. (I)<bold><italic>Lonchura cucullata</italic></bold> Bronze Mannikin. (I)<bold><italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic></bold> Nutmeg Mannikin. (I)<bold><italic>Padda oryzivora</italic></bold> Java Sparrow. (I)Change the sequence of species from <bold><italic>Zenaida</italic></bold> to <bold><italic>Starnoenas</italic></bold> to:&dagger;<bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ectopistes migratorius</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic>Columbina inca</italic></bold><bold><italic>Columbina passerina</italic></bold><bold><italic>Columbina minuta</italic></bold><bold><italic>Columbina talpacoti</italic></bold><bold><italic>Claravis pretiosa</italic></bold><bold><italic>Claravis mondetoura</italic></bold><bold><italic>Starnoenas cyanocephala</italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon versicolor</italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Geotrygon montana</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon violacea</italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon caniceps</italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon leucometopia</italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon chrysia</italic></bold><bold><italic>Geotrygon mystacea</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotrygon veraguensis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotila verreauxi</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotila jamaicensis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotila cassini</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotila plumbeiceps</italic></bold><bold><italic>Leptotila wellsi</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon carrikeri</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon costaricensis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon lawrencii</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon albifacies</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon chiriquensis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Zentrygon goldmani</italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida asiatica</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida aurita</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida auriculata</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida macroura</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic>Zenaida graysoni</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species from <bold><italic>Aratinga</italic></bold> to <bold><italic>Ara</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Eupsittula nana</italic></bold><bold><italic>Eupsittula canicularis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Eupsittula pertinax</italic></bold><bold><italic>Aratinga nenday</italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara severus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara militaris</italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara ambiguus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara chloropterus</italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ara macao</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara tricolor</italic></bold><bold><italic>Ara ararauna</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara holochlorus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara strenuus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara finschi</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara euops</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara chloropterus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Psittacara mitratus</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species in <bold><italic>Dendrocincla</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Dendrocincla homochroa</italic></bold><bold><italic>Dendrocincla anabatina</italic></bold><bold><italic>Dendrocincla fuliginosa</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species formerly in <bold><italic>Hyloctistes</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>Automolus</italic></bold>, and <bold><italic>Thripadectes</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Clibanornis rubiginosus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Thripadectes rufobrunneus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Automolus ochrolaemus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Automolus subulatus</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species in <bold><italic>Saltator</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Saltator atriceps</italic></bold><bold><italic>Saltator maximus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Saltator grossus</italic></bold><bold><italic>Saltator albicollis</italic></bold><bold><italic>Saltator coerulescens</italic></bold><bold><italic>Saltator striatipectus</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species in <bold><italic>Sporophila</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Sporophila minuta</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila funerea</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila nuttingi</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila crassirostris</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila corvina</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila torqueola</italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila nigricollis</italic></bold><bold><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></italic></bold><bold><italic>Sporophila schistacea</italic></bold>Change the sequence of species formerly in <bold><italic>Lonchura</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>Padda</italic></bold> to:<bold><italic>Spermestes cucullata</italic></bold><bold><italic>Euodice malabarica</italic></bold><bold><italic>Euodice cantans</italic></bold><bold><italic>Lonchura oryzivora</italic></bold><bold><italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic></bold><bold><italic>Lonchura malacca</italic></bold><bold><italic>Lonchura atricapilla</italic></bold>p. 10. <italic>Thalassarche salvini</italic> and <italic>T. eremita</italic> are treated as species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. cauta</named-content></italic>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>. In the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. cauta</named-content></italic>, change the English name to White-capped Albatross, and change the distributional statement and Notes to:<italic>Breeds</italic> on islands off southern Australia and New Zealand, and <italic>ranges</italic> widely in the southern Pacific and Indian oceans, less commonly in the South Atlantic.Accidental off the coast of Washington (lat. 47&deg;55&prime;N. long. 125&deg;37&prime;W. ca. 39 miles west of the mouth of Quillayute River, 1 September 1951; specimen USNM; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Slipp1">Slipp 1952</xref>); also Oregon (October 1996; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Hunter1">Hunter and Bailey 1997</xref>; and October 2001; photos), California (August-September 1999; photos), and Washington (January 2000; photos), these four records possibly of the same individual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Howell2">Howell 2012</xref>).Formerly known as Shy Albatross and considered conspecific with <italic>T. salvini</italic> and <italic>T. eremita</italic>, but treated as separate species on the basis of differences in plumage and genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Nunn1">Nunn et al. 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Abbott1">Abbott and Double 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Abbott2">2003b</xref>) and reports of isolated pairs of one form nesting within the range of another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Tickell1">Tickell 2000</xref>).After the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. cauta</named-content></italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Thalassogeron salvini</italic> Rothschild, 1893, Bull. Brit. Ornith. Club 1:58. (New Zealand.)Pelagic Waters; breeds on islands.<italic>Breeds</italic> on islands off New Zealand and on Crozet Islands, Indian Ocean, and <italic>ranges</italic> widely in the southern Pacific and Indian oceans, less commonly in the South Atlantic.Accidental in Hawaii (Midway Atoll, 8 April 2003; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Robertson1">Robertson et al. 2005</xref>) and off the coast of Alaska (18 km northwest of Kasatochi Island, Aleutians, 4 August 2003; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Benter1">Benter et al. 2005</xref>).See comments under <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. cauta</named-content></italic>.In the Appendix, following the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassarche chrysostoma</named-content></italic> (p. 685), insert the following new account:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thalassarche cauta</named-content> eremita</italic> Murphy, 1930, Amer. Mus. Novit. 419:4. (Pyramid Rock off Pitt Island, Chatham Islands.)p. 50. Preceding the heading Tribe LEPTOPTILINI: Jabirus and Allies, add the following headings and species account:Tribe CICONIINI: Typical StorksGenus <bold><italic>CICONIA</italic></bold> Brisson<italic>Ciconia</italic> Brisson, 1760, Ornith. 1, p. 48; 5, p. 361. Type, by tautonymy, <italic>Ciconia &equals; Ardea ciconia</italic> Linnaeus.<bold><italic>Ciconia maguari</italic></bold> (Gmelin). Maguari Stork<italic>Ardea Maguari</italic> Gmelin, 1789, Syst. Nat. 1: 623; based on &ldquo;Maguari&rdquo; of Marcgrave, 1648, Hist. Rerum Nat. Brasiliae, p. 204. (northeastern Brazil.)Freshwater Marshes, Southern Temperate Grasslands, Low Seasonally Wet Grasslands, Pastures/Agricultural Lands (0&ndash;900 m; Tropical Zone).Northeastern Colombia and Venezuela east through Guianas to Brazil in Roraima, Amap&aacute;, and extreme northern Par&aacute;. Disjunctly from central and southeastern Brazil, northern and eastern Bolivia south to Paraguay, Uruguay, and central Argentina. Formerly regular nonbreeder in central Chile.Casual through eastern Brazil and in southeastern Peru.Accidental in Costa Rica (near Gulf of Nicoya, Chomes, Puntarenas province, 16 September 2013; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ObandoCalderon1">Obando-Calder&oacute;n et al. 2013</xref>).pp. 97&ndash;98. The hyphen is removed from the English names of Common Black Hawk <italic>Buteogallus anthracinus</italic>, Cuban Black Hawk <italic>B. gundlachii</italic>, and Great Black Hawk <italic>B. urubitinga</italic> because <italic>B. anthracinus</italic> and <italic>B. urubitinga</italic> are not sister taxa (Raposo do Amaral et al. 2009; <italic>B. gundlachii</italic> was not included in the study).p. 131. <italic>Rallus obsoletus</italic> and <italic>R. crepitans</italic> are treated as species separate from the now extralimital <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. longirostris</named-content></italic>. Remove the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. longirostris</named-content></italic> and insert the following new species accounts in this sequence:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rallus elegans</named-content></italic> var. <italic>obsoletus</italic> Ridgway, 1874, Am. Nat. 8:111. (San Francisco, California.)Salt and brackish marshes, locally (mostly in the Imperial and lower Colorado River valleys) in freshwater marshes (Temperate and Subtropical zones).&lsqb;same as for <italic>obsoletus</italic> group.&rsqb;See comments under <italic>R. crepitans</italic>.<italic>Rallus crepitans</italic> Gmelin, 1789, Syst. Nat. 1, pt. 2, p. 713. (&ldquo;in Noveboraco,&rdquo; restricted type locality, Long Island, New York.)Salt and brackish marshes and mangrove swamps; during migration may be found in freshwater marshes (Tropical and Subtropical zones).&lsqb;same as <italic>longirostris</italic> group except delete South American parts of distribution.&rsqb; Northernmost populations tend to be partially migratory.Formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) considered conspecific with <italic>R. obsoletus</italic> and South American <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. longirostris</named-content></italic> Boddaert, 1783 &lsqb;Mangrove Rail&rsqb; and sometimes with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. tenuirostris</named-content></italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ripley1">Ripley 1977</xref>). The five members of this complex are treated as separate species on the basis of strong, although incomplete, reproductive isolation between parapatric populations of <italic>R. crepitans</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic> in their extensive contact zone, and morphological and genetic differences among other members of the complex commensurate with those between <italic>R. crepitans</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Maley1">Maley and Brumfield 2013</xref>).p. 132. <italic>Rallus tenuirostris</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic>. After the account for <italic>R. obsoletus</italic>, insert the following new species account:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Rallus elegans</named-content></italic> var. <italic>tenuirostris</italic> &ldquo;Lawrence&rdquo; Ridgway, 1874, Am. Nat. 8:111. (City of Mexico.)Freshwater marshes (1,550&ndash;2,800 m; Subtropical and Temperate zones).&lsqb;same as <italic>tenuirostris</italic> group&rsqb;.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic>, but they are not sister taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Maley1">Maley and Brumfield 2013</xref>). See comments under <italic>R. crepitans</italic>. Also known as Mexican Rail.Move the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic> to follow the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. tenuirostris</named-content></italic>. Delete information on the <italic>tenuirostris</italic> group from the habitat and distributional statements in the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. elegans</named-content></italic>, and change the Notes to:See comments under <italic>R. crepitans</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">R. tenuirostris</named-content></italic>.p. 213. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Bowen1">Bowen (2013)</xref>, change the type locality for <italic>Synthliboramphus craveri</italic> to the following: Golfo della California &lsqb;Mexico&rsqb; &equals; (probably) Isla Partida Norte, Gulf of California.pp. 229&ndash;231. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Johnson1">Johnson and Weckstein 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks2">Banks et al. 2013</xref>) have shown that the genus <italic>Geotrygon</italic> is polyphyletic and that the linear sequence of species currently placed in this genus does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. The type species <italic>G. versicolor</italic> forms a clade with six other species in our area, but <italic>G. veraguensis</italic> is sister to the genus <italic>Leptotila</italic>, and six other species of <italic>Geotrygon</italic> are sister to the genus <italic>Zenaida</italic>. These findings result in the following changes:Move the heading Genus <bold><italic>STARNOENAS</italic></bold> Bonaparte and the species account for <italic>Starnoenas cyanocephala</italic> to a position following the species account for <italic>Claravis mondetoura</italic>. Insert the following at the end of the species account for <italic>Starnoenas cyanocephala</italic>:The phylogenetic relationships of this species within the Columbidae are uncertain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Shufeldt1">Shufeldt 1891</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Dickinson2">Dickinson and Remsen 2013</xref>), but we leave it in its traditional placement near <italic>Geotrygon</italic> pending further data.Add the following under the citation for genus <italic>Geotrygon</italic>:See comments under <italic>Leptotrygon</italic> and <italic>Zentrygon</italic>.Revise the composition of <italic>Geotrygon</italic> and rearrange the linear sequence of species remaining in this genus to:<italic>Geotrygon versicolor</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Geotrygon montana</named-content></italic><italic>Geotrygon violacea</italic><italic>Geotrygon caniceps</italic><italic>Geotrygon leucometopia</italic><italic>Geotrygon chrysia</italic><italic>Geotrygon mystacea</italic>Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Geotrygon mystacea</italic>:<italic>Leptotrygon</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks2">Banks, Weckstein, Remsen, and Johnson, 2013</xref>, Zootaxa 3669:185. Type, by original designation, <italic>Geotrygon veraguensis</italic> Lawrence.Formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) considered part of <italic>Geotrygon</italic>, but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Johnson1">Johnson and Weckstein 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks2">Banks et al. 2013</xref>), which indicate that <italic>Leptotrygon</italic> is sister to <italic>Leptotila</italic>.Change <bold><italic>Geotrygon veraguensis</italic></bold> Lawrence to <bold><italic>Leptotrygon veraguensis</italic></bold> (Lawrence) and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for <italic>Leptotrygon</italic>. Add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Geotrygon</italic>. See comments under <italic>Leptotrygon</italic>.Move the genus heading for <italic>Leptotila</italic> to follow the species account for <italic>Leptotrygon veraguensis</italic>, and place the species accounts for <italic>L. verreauxi</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">L. jamaicensis</named-content></italic>, <italic>L. cassini</italic>, <italic>L. plumbeiceps</italic>, and <italic>L. wellsi</italic> in this sequence under the heading for <italic>Leptotila</italic>.Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Leptotila wellsi</italic>:<italic>Zentrygon</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks2">Banks, Weckstein, Remsen, and Johnson, 2013</xref>, Zootaxa 3669:185. Type, by original designation, <italic>Geotrygon costaricensis</italic> Lawrence.Formerly considered part of <italic>Geotrygon</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>), but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Johnson1">Johnson and Weckstein 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks2">Banks et al. 2013</xref>), which indicate that <italic>Zentrygon</italic> is sister to <italic>Zenaida</italic>.Change the generic names of <italic>Geotrygon carrikeri</italic>, <italic>G. costaricensis</italic>, <italic>G. lawrencii</italic>, <italic>G. albifacies</italic>, <italic>G. chiriquensis</italic>, and <italic>G. goldmani</italic> to <italic>Zentrygon</italic>, add parentheses around the authority names for each species, make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, delete the Notes for <italic>Z. goldmani</italic>, replace the Notes for <italic>Z. lawrencii</italic> with &ldquo;Closely related to <italic>Z. costaricensis</italic>; the two are reportedly sympatric in Costa Rica.&rdquo; and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for <italic>Zentrygon</italic>. In the species accounts for all species, add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Geotrygon</italic>. See comments under <italic>Zentrygon</italic>.Move the genus heading for <italic>Zenaida</italic> to follow the species account for <italic>Zentrygon goldmani</italic>, and place the species accounts for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zenaida asiatica</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Z. aurita</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Z. auriculata</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Z. macroura</named-content></italic>, and <italic>Z. graysoni</italic> in this sequence under the heading for <italic>Zenaida</italic>.p. 233. Three extralimital South American populations of <italic>Pyrrhura picta</italic> are separated as the species <italic>P. amazonum</italic>, <italic>P. roseifrons</italic>, and <italic>P. lucianii</italic>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ribas1">Ribas et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>. Replace the distributional statement and Notes in the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. picta</named-content></italic> with the following:<italic>Resident</italic> in western Panama (Azuero Peninsula), patchily in northern Colombia and northern Venezuela, and from southeastern Venezuela and the Guianas to Brazil north of the Amazon River, east of the Rio Negro.DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ribas1">Ribas et al. 2006</xref>) indicate that the subspecies <italic>eisenmanni</italic> in Panama is sister to a clade containing Guianan Shield <italic>picta</italic> and north-central Venezuelan <italic>emma</italic>, but not <italic>P. leucotis</italic> (Kuhl, 1820) &lsqb;Maroon-faced Parakeet&rsqb;; however, intervening northern South American populations were not sampled. These intervening populations are morphologically intermediate between nominate <italic>picta</italic> of northeastern Amazonia and <italic>eisenmanni</italic>. Formerly included <italic>P. amazonum</italic> Hellmayr, 1906 &lsqb;Santarem Parakeet&rsqb;, <italic>P. roseifrons</italic> (Gray, 1859) &lsqb;Rose-fronted Parakeet&rsqb;, and <italic>P. lucianii</italic> (Deville, 1851) &lsqb;Bonaparte's Parakeet&rsqb; of southern and western Amazonia. These three species do not form a monophyletic group with <italic>Pyrrhura picta</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ribas1">Ribas et al. 2006</xref>) and are treated as separate species, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>.pp. 234&ndash;236. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen1">Remsen et al. 2013</xref>) have shown that the genus <italic>Aratinga</italic> is highly polyphyletic and that the linear sequence of species currently placed in this genus does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. The type species <italic>A. solstitialis</italic> forms a clade with five other species, of which the <italic>AOU Check-list</italic> includes one species, currently placed in the genus <italic>Nandayus</italic> (see below). Other species currently placed in <italic>Aratinga</italic> constitute three clades, two of which include species from our area. These findings result in the following changes:Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Conuropsis carolinensis</italic>:<italic>Eupsittula</italic> Bonaparte, 1853, Compt. Rend. Ac. Sci. Paris 37: 807. Type, by monotypy, <italic>Psittacus petzii</italic> Leiblein &equals; <italic>P. canicularis</italic> Linnaeus.Formerly (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) included in <italic>Aratinga</italic> following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Peters1">Peters (1937)</xref>, but now treated as separate (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ridgway2">Ridgway 1916</xref>) on the basis of genetic data (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Kirchman1">Kirchman et al. 2012</xref>; summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen1">Remsen et al. 2013</xref>), which indicate that <italic>Eupsittula</italic> is not closely related to true <italic>Aratinga</italic> and is likely the sister genus to <italic>Rhynchopsitta</italic>.Change the generic names of <italic>Aratinga nana</italic>, <italic>A. canicularis</italic>, and <italic>A. pertinax</italic> to <italic>Eupsittula</italic>, make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for <italic>Eupsittula</italic>. Delete the last sentence in the Notes for <italic>E. pertinax</italic>. In the species accounts for all species, add the following to the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Aratinga</italic>. See comments under <italic>Eupsittula</italic>.Insert the following at the end of the Notes for Genus <bold><italic>ARATINGA</italic></bold> Spix: See comments under <italic>Eupsittula</italic> and <italic>Psittacara</italic>.Change <bold><italic>Nandayus nenday</italic></bold> (Vieillot) (added to the <italic>Check-list</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chesser4">Chesser et al. 2013</xref>) to <bold><italic>Aratinga nenday</italic></bold> (Vieillot), delete the genus heading for <italic>Nandayus</italic>, move the citation for <italic>Nandayus</italic> into the synonymy of <italic>Aratinga</italic>, insert the species account for <italic>Aratinga nenday</italic> to follow the heading and Notes for <italic>Aratinga</italic>, and insert the following at the beginning of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Nandayus</italic>, but genetic data (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ribas2">Ribas and Miyaki 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Kirchman1">Kirchman et al. 2012</xref>; summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen1">Remsen et al. 2013</xref>) indicate that <italic>Nandayus</italic> is embedded within <italic>Aratinga</italic>.Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Ara ararauna</italic>:<italic>Psittacara</italic> Vigors, 1825, Zool. Journ. 2: 388. Type, by original designation, <italic>Psittacus leucophthalmus</italic> Statius M&uuml;ller, 1776.Formerly included in <italic>Aratinga</italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Peters1">Peters (1937)</xref>, but now treated as separate on the basis of genetic data (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Kirchman1">Kirchman et al. 2012</xref>; summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen1">Remsen et al. 2013</xref>), which indicate that <italic>Psittacara</italic> is not closely related to <italic>Aratinga</italic> but rather is sister to a group of three extralimital genera (<italic>Leptosittaca</italic> von Berlepsh &amp; Stolzmann 1894<italic>, Diopsittaca</italic> Ridgway 1912, and <italic>Guaruba</italic> Lesson 1830).Change <bold><italic>Aratinga holochlora</italic></bold> (Sclater), <bold><italic>Aratinga strenua</italic></bold> (Ridgway), <bold><italic>Aratinga finschi</italic></bold> (Salvin), <bold><italic>Aratinga euops</italic></bold> (Wagler), <bold><italic>Aratinga chloroptera</italic></bold> (de Souanc&eacute;), and <bold><italic>Aratinga mitrata</italic></bold> (Tschudi) to <bold><italic>Psittacara holochlorus</italic></bold> (Sclater), <bold><italic>Psittacara strenuus</italic></bold> (Ridgway), <bold><italic>Psittacara finschi</italic></bold> (Salvin), <bold><italic>Psittacara euops</italic></bold> (Wagler), <bold><italic>Psittacara chloropterus</italic></bold> de Souanc&eacute;, and <bold><italic>Psittacara mitratus</italic></bold> (Tschudi), make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for <italic>Psittacara</italic>. In the species accounts for all species, add the following Notes (for <italic>P. mitratus</italic>) or add to the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Aratinga</italic>. See comments under <italic>Psittacara</italic>.p. 266. <italic>Ninox japonica</italic> is treated as a species separate from <italic>N. scutulata</italic> (which was added to the <italic>Check-list</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chesser1">Chesser et al. 2009</xref>). Remove the species account for <italic>N. scutulata</italic> and replace it with the following new account:<italic>Strix hirsuta japonica</italic> Temminck and Schlegel, 1845, in Siebold, Fauna Japonica, Aves, p. 28, pl. 9B. (Japan.)A variety of woodland habitats.<italic>Breeds</italic> from southeastern Russian Far East, Korea, and northern and central (possibly southern) China south through Japan and Taiwan, and possibly in the northern Philippines.<italic>Winters</italic> in southern part of breeding range and throughout mainland Southeast Asia, the Philippines, and much of Indonesia.Accidental in Alaska (St. Paul Island, Pribilof Islands, 27 August&ndash;3 September 2005; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Yerger1">Yerger and Mohlmann 2008</xref>; and Kiska Island, Aleutian Islands, 1 August 2008; photos of carcass; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Bond1">Bond and Jones 2010</xref>), and on Ashmore Reef, Australia.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic>Ninox scutulata</italic> (Raffles) &lsqb;Brown Hawk-Owl&rsqb;, but treated as a separate species on the basis of vocal differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-King1">King 2002</xref>). Group name changed from Hawk-Owl to Boobook to conform to general usage for this species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Dickinson2">Dickinson and Remsen 2013</xref>).pp. 350&ndash;353. Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Claramunt1">Claramunt et al. 2013</xref>) has shown that the generic limits and linear sequence of species currently placed in the genera <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, <italic>Automolus</italic>, and <italic>Thripadectes</italic> do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Change <bold><italic>Hyloctistes subulatus</italic></bold> (Spix) to <bold><italic>Automolus subulatus</italic></bold> (Spix), delete the genus heading and Notes for <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, move the citation for <italic>Hyloctistes</italic> into the synonymy of <italic>Automolus</italic>, insert the species account for <italic>Automolus subulatus</italic> to follow the account for <italic>Automolus ochrolaemus</italic>, and insert the following at the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, but genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Claramunt1">Claramunt et al. 2013</xref>) indicate that <italic>Hyloctistes</italic> is embedded within <italic>Automolus</italic>.After the account for <italic>Syndactyla subalaris</italic>, insert the following heading:<italic>Clibanornis</italic> Sclater and Salvin, 1873, Nomen. Av. Neotrop., pp. 61, 155. Type, by original designation, <italic>Anabates dendrocolaptoides</italic> Pelzeln.Change <bold><italic>Automolus rubiginosus</italic></bold> (Sclater) to <bold><italic>Clibanornis rubiginosus</italic></bold> (Sclater), place the account for this species under the heading for <italic>Clibanornis</italic>, make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes, and insert the following at the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Automolus</italic>, but genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Claramunt1">Claramunt et al. 2013</xref>) indicate that <italic>C. rubiginosus</italic> is part of a clade that is sister to a clade consisting of <italic>Thripadectes</italic> and <italic>Automolus</italic>.Rearrange the linear sequence of genera and species that follow <italic>Syndactyla subalaris</italic> as follows:Genus <italic>Clibanornis</italic><italic>Clibanornis rubiginosus</italic>Genus <italic>Thripadectes</italic><italic>Thripadectes rufobrunneus</italic>Genus <italic>Automolus</italic><italic>Automolus ochrolaemus</italic><italic>Automolus subulatus</italic>p. 355. Phylogenetic analyses of nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Weir1">Weir and Price 2011</xref>) have shown that the linear sequence of species in the genus <italic>Dendrocincla</italic> does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships.Under the heading Genus <bold><italic>DENDROCINCLA</italic></bold> Gray, insert the following:Linear sequence of species follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Weir1">Weir and Price (2011)</xref>.Rearrange the sequence of species of <italic>Dendrocincla</italic> as follows:<italic>Dendrocincla homochroa</italic><italic>Dendrocincla anabatina</italic><italic>Dendrocincla fuliginosa</italic>p. 369. <italic>Gymnopithys bicolor</italic> is considered a species separate from <italic>G. leucaspis</italic>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>. Remove the species account for <italic>G. leucaspis</italic> and replace it with the following account:<italic>Pithys bicolor</italic> Lawrence, 1863, Ann. Lyc. Nat. Hist. New York 8: 6. (Lion Hill Station, Panam&aacute; Railroad.)Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest (0&ndash;1,500 m; Tropical Zone).&lsqb;same as for <italic>bicolor</italic> group&rsqb;Formerly considered conspecific with South American <italic>Gymnopithys leucaspis</italic> (Sclater) &lsqb;White-cheeked Antbird&rsqb;. Treated as a separate species because mitochondrial and nuclear DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Brumfield1">Brumfield et al. 2007</xref>) indicate that <italic>G. leucaspis</italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. bicolor</named-content></italic> are not sisters, but that <italic>G. leucaspis</italic> is sister instead to the South American <italic>G. rufigula</italic> Boddaert 1783.p. 489. Remove the heading Family <bold>MEGALURIDAE</bold>: Grassbirds (added to the <italic>Check-list</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chesser2">Chesser et al. 2010</xref>) and the Notes under this heading and replace them with the following heading and Notes:Formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chesser2">Chesser et al. 2010</xref>) known as Family Megaluridae, but the name Locustellidae has priority when <italic>Locustella</italic> is included. See comments under Family Sylviidae.In the Notes under Family <bold>SYLVIIDAE</bold>: Sylviid Warblers, replace &ldquo;Megaluridae&rdquo; with &ldquo;Locustellidae.&rdquo;p. 490. After the account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus trochilus</named-content></italic>, insert the following new species account:<italic>Sylvia collybita</italic> Vieillot, 1817, Nouv. Dict. Hist. Nat., nouv. &eacute;d., 11, p. 235. (&ldquo;r&eacute;gions septentrionales&rdquo; of France; restricted to Normandy by Mayaud, 1941, Oiseau, 11, no. sp&eacute;c., p. 87.)Breeds in a variety of forested habitats and hedgerows with an understory. Winters in similar habitats, but also parks and gardens, and even marshes and mangroves.<italic>Breeds</italic> from northern Europe in the British Isles, Denmark, Sweden and central Finland, east across northern Russia to about the Kolyma River and south to Italy, Greece, Bulgaria, Turkey, northern Iran, and Lake Baikal, Altai, and northwestern Mongolia.<italic>Winters</italic> from southern part of breeding range in the Mediterranean region south to North Africa and Senegal and Sudan, the southern Caspian Mountains, the Arabian Peninsula and lower Himalayas east through Nepal, India (West Bengal and western Assam, south to Maharashtra), and Bangladesh.Casual in Japan and Thailand.Accidental in Alaska (Gambell, St. Lawrence Island, 6&ndash;7 June 2012; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Lehman1">Lehman and Zimmer 2013</xref>).The St. Lawrence Island bird was identified from photos as the easternmost subspecies <italic>P. c. tristis</italic> Blyth, which has been maintained by some as a separate species based on vocalizations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Rasmussen1">Rasmussen and Anderton 2005</xref>). <italic>Phylloscopus ibericus</italic> (Ticehurst, 1937) &lsqb;Iberian Chiffchaff&rsqb; and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. canariensis</named-content></italic> (Hartwig 1886) &lsqb;Canary Islands Chiffchaff&rsqb;, formerly treated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Vaurie1">Vaurie 1959</xref>) as a junior synonym of nominate <italic>collybita</italic> and as a subspecies of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. collybita</named-content></italic>, respectively, were treated as separate species by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Dickinson1">Dickinson (2003)</xref>.p. 490. The hyphen is removed from the English name of Pallas's Leaf Warbler <italic>Phylloscopus proregulus</italic> (added to the <italic>Check-list</italic> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Banks1">Banks et al. 2008</xref>) because the various species named &ldquo;Leaf Warbler&rdquo; do not form a monophyletic group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Olsson1">Olsson et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Johansson1">Johansson et al. 2007</xref>).p. 490. <italic>Phylloscopus xanthodryas</italic> and <italic>P. examinandus</italic> are considered species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content></italic>. Replace the distributional statement and Notes in the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content></italic> with the following:<italic>Breeds</italic> in western and central Alaska from the Noatak River and western and central Brooks Range south to southwestern Alaska, the base of the Alaska Peninsula, the Alaska Range, and Susitna River highlands; and in Eurasia from Sweden, northern Russia, and northern Siberia south to central Russia, Mongolia, and Amurland. Recorded in summer north to Barrow and on St. Lawrence Island. Records from St. Matthew Island and Prince Patrick Island (northern Northwest Territories) have not been positively identified as this species or as <italic>P. examinandus</italic>.<italic>Winters</italic> from Andaman Islands, Southeast Asia, and southeastern China and Taiwan south to eastern Indonesia, Ashmore Reef, and the Philippines.<italic>Migrates</italic> through eastern Asia.Casual in California (Monterey, San Luis Obispo, Stanislaus, San Francisco, and Kern counties).See comments under <italic>Phylloscopus examinandus</italic>.After the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content></italic>, insert the following new species account:<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus borealis</named-content> examinandus</italic> Stresemann, 1913, Novit. Zool. 20:353. (Bali.)Broadleaf forest, birch, swampy woods, and shrubby areas (rarely pine) below 1,000 m.<italic>Breeds</italic> in southern Kamchatka (north to at least 56&deg;N), Sakhalin, the Kuril Islands, and northeastern Hokkaido.<italic>Wintering range</italic> poorly known; specimens from Indonesia (Bali through Sumba; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ticehurst1">Ticehurst 1938</xref>).<italic>Migrates</italic> through northeastern Russia, Japan, and northeastern China.Casual in the Aleutians (Attu, Shemya, Amchitka) during spring and autumn migration.Formerly included in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content></italic> along with <italic>P. xanthodryas</italic> (Swinhoe 1863) &lsqb;Japanese Leaf Warbler&rsqb;, but treated as separate species on the basis of differences in song and mitochondrial DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Saitoh1">Saitoh et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Alstrom1">Alstr&ouml;m et al. 2011</xref>). <italic>Phylloscopus xanthodryas</italic>, which breeds in the mountains of Japan (except Hokkaido), has not been reported definitely from North America. The latter species and <italic>P. examinandus</italic> were formerly considered to constitute <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content> xanthodryas</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Vaurie1">Vaurie 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Watson1">Watson et al. 1986</xref>); all known reports of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. borealis</named-content> xanthodryas</italic> from the AOU area pertain to <italic>P. examinandus</italic>.pp. 570&ndash;571. Change the English group name of <italic>Chlorospingus flavopectus</italic>, <italic>C. tacarcunae</italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. inornatus</named-content></italic>, <italic>C. pileatus</italic>, <italic>C. flavigularis</italic>, and <italic>C. canigularis</italic> from Bush-Tanager to Chlorospingus, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>. These species were transferred recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chesser3">Chesser et al. 2011</xref>) from the Thraupidae to the Emberizidae; the removal of &ldquo;Bush-Tanager&rdquo; from the English names reflects this taxonomic change. In the Notes for <italic>C. flavopectus</italic>, add the following sentence: Formerly known as Common Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for <italic>C. tacarcunae</italic>, add the following sentence: Formerly known as Tacarcuna Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. inornatus</named-content></italic>, add the following sentence: Formerly known as Pirre Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for <italic>C. pileatus</italic>, add the following sentence: Formerly known as Sooty-capped Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for <italic>C. flavigularis</italic>, add the following sentence: Formerly known as Yellow-throated Bush-Tanager. In the Notes for <italic>C. canigularis</italic> add the following sentence: Formerly known as Ashy-throated Bush-Tanager.p. 592. Preceding the account for <italic>Sporophila schistacea</italic>, insert the following new species account:<italic>Loxia lineola</italic> Linnaeus, 1758, Syst. Nat., ed. 10, 1, p. 174. (Asia; error, emended to Surinam by Berlepsch and Hartert, 1902, Novit. Zool. 9:26; further emended to Bahia, Brazil, by Meyer de Schauensee, 1952, Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia 104:77.)Second-growth Scrub, Riparian Thickets, Pastures/Agricultural Lands (0&ndash;1,200 m; Tropical Zone).Resident in northeastern Brazil from Maranh&atilde;o, Tocantins, and Bahia eastward. Summer resident from Mato Grosso do Sul, Minas Gerais, and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, south to north-central Argentina, southeastern Bolivia, Paraguay, and Paran&aacute; and S&atilde;o Paulo, Brazil. In winter, widespread throughout South America east of the Andes north of its summer breeding range.Accidental in Costa Rica (playa El Rey, Quepos, Puntarenas province, lat. 9&deg;22&prime;45.15&prime;&prime;N. long. 84&deg;03&prime;32.10&prime;&prime;W. 5&ndash;7 October 2013; photos; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ObandoCalderon1">Obando-Calder&oacute;n et al. 2013</xref>).p. 592. <italic>Sporophila corvina</italic> is considered a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. americana</named-content></italic>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Stiles1">Stiles (1996)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Remsen2">Remsen et al. (2014)</xref>. Remove the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. americana</named-content></italic> and replace it with the following account:<italic>Spermophila corvina</italic> Sclater, 1859, Proc. Zool. Soc. London, p. 379. (Playa Vicente, Oaxaca, Mexico.)Second-growth Scrub, Tropical Lowland Evergreen Forest Edge, Tropical Deciduous Forest, Secondary Forest (0&ndash;1,500 m; Tropical and Lower Subtropical zones).<italic>Resident</italic> &lsqb;<italic>corvina</italic> group&rsqb; from northern Oaxaca, southern Veracruz, and Tabasco south on the Gulf&ndash;Caribbean slope of Central America to western Panama (Bocas del Toro); and &lsqb;<italic>ophthalmica</italic> group&rsqb; from the Pacific slope of southwestern Costa Rica (north to the Gulf of Nicoya) south through Panama (both slopes, except for Bocas del Toro), western Colombia, and western Ecuador to northwestern Peru. The <italic>ophthalmica</italic> group was formerly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>) known as the <italic>aurita</italic> group, but see comments below.Groups: <italic>S. corvina</italic> (Sclater, 1860) &lsqb;Black Seedeater&rsqb; and <italic>S. ophthalmica</italic> (Sclater, 1860) &lsqb;Variable Seedeater&rsqb;. Formerly considered conspecific with South American <italic>Sporophila americana</italic> (Gmelin 1789) &lsqb;Wing-barred Seedeater&rsqb;, but treated as a separate species on the basis of similarities in plumage pattern, plumage sequences, distribution, and biometrics, and two localized zones of at least sporadic hybridization between <italic>S. corvina</italic> and extralimital <italic>Sporophila intermedia</italic> Cabanis, 1851 &lsqb;Gray Seedeater&rsqb;, which on this basis are considered to be sister species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Stiles1">Stiles 1996</xref>). As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Olson2">Olson (1981b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Stiles1">Stiles (1996)</xref>, <italic>Sporophila</italic> &ldquo;<italic>aurita</italic>&rdquo; Bonaparte 1850 represents intergrades between <italic>S. c. corvina</italic> and <italic>S. c. hicksii</italic> Lawrence 1865. The type has disappeared, and it is impossible to assign this name to either of the parental populations.pp. 593&ndash;594. Phylogenetic analyses of mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences indicate that the genus <italic>Oryzoborus</italic> is embedded within <italic>Sporophila</italic>. Change <bold><italic>Oryzoborus nuttingi</italic></bold> Ridgway, <bold><italic>Oryzoborus funereus</italic></bold> Sclater, and <bold><italic>Oryzoborus crassirostris</italic></bold> (Gmelin) to <bold><italic>Sporophila nuttingi</italic></bold> (Ridgway), <bold><italic>Sporophila funerea</italic></bold> (Sclater), and <bold><italic>Sporophila crassirostris</italic></bold> (Gmelin), delete the genus heading and notes for <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>, move the citation for <italic>Oryzoborus</italic> into the synonymy of <italic>Sporophila</italic>, and make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes for each species. In the species accounts for all species, add the following Notes (for <italic>S. crassirostris</italic>) or add to the end of the existing Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>; see comments under <italic>Sporophila</italic>.Replace the existing Notes under the heading Genus <italic>Sporophila</italic> Cabanis (p. 591) with the following:DNA sequence data indicate that <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>, formerly considered a separate genus, is embedded within <italic>Sporophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Lijtmaer1">Lijtmaer et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Mason1">Mason and Burns 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>), as previously predicted from morphological characters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Olson1">Olson 1981a</xref>). Linear sequence of species follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Mason1">Mason and Burns (2013)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Burns1">Burns et al. (2014)</xref>.Rearrange the sequence of species of <italic>Sporophila</italic> as follows:<italic>Sporophila minuta</italic><italic>Sporophila funerea</italic><italic>Sporophila nuttingi</italic><italic>Sporophila crassirostris</italic><italic>Sporophila corvina</italic><italic>Sporophila torqueola</italic><italic>Sporophila nigricollis</italic><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sporophila lineola</named-content></italic><italic>Sporophila schistacea</italic>p. 625. <italic>Junco insularis</italic> is considered a species separate from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">J. hyemalis</named-content></italic>. In the Notes under genus <italic>Junco</italic>, delete the last sentence. After the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">J. hyemalis</named-content></italic>, insert the following new account:<italic>Junco insularis</italic> Ridgway, 1876, Bull. Geol. Geog. Surv. Terr. 2, pt. 2, p. 188. (Isla Guadalupe, Baja California.)Pine Forest, Pine&ndash;Oak Forest (0&ndash;1,300 m).<italic>Resident</italic> on Guadalupe Island, off Baja California.Formerly considered conspecific with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Junco hyemalis</named-content></italic>, but treated as a separate species on the basis of differences in song, morphology, and DNA sequence data (Mirsky 1976, Aleixandre et al. 2013).In the species account for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">J. hyemalis</named-content></italic>, remove information on the <italic>insularis</italic> group from the habitat and distributional statements and change the Notes to the following:Groups: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">J. hyemalis</named-content></italic> &lsqb;Slate-colored Junco&rsqb;, <italic>J. oreganus</italic> (J. K. Townsend, 1837) &lsqb;Oregon Junco&rsqb;, <italic>J. aikeni</italic> Ridgway, 1873 &lsqb;White-winged Junco&rsqb;, and <italic>J. caniceps</italic> (Woodhouse, 1853) &lsqb;Gray-headed Junco&rsqb;. The groups intergrade to varying degrees. Several other forms may merit recognition as groups: <italic>Junco mearnsi</italic> Ridgway, 1897 &lsqb;Pink-sided Junco&rsqb;, of the <italic>oreganus</italic> group, breeding from southeastern Alberta and southwestern Saskatchewan to eastern Idaho and northwestern Wyoming, and <italic>J. dorsalis</italic> Henry, 1858 &lsqb;Red-backed Junco&rsqb;, of the <italic>caniceps</italic> group, breeding from northern and central Arizona and central New Mexico to western Texas. For detailed information on groups, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Miller1">Miller (1941)</xref>. See comments under <italic>J. vulcani</italic> and <italic>J. insularis</italic>.pp. 631&ndash;632. Phylogenetic analysis of mitochondrial DNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chaves1">Chaves et al. 2013</xref>) has shown that the linear sequence of species in the genus <italic>Saltator</italic> does not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships.Under the heading Genus <bold><italic>SALTATOR</italic></bold> Vieillot, add the following to the end of the existing Notes: Linear sequence of species follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Chaves1">Chaves et al. (2013)</xref>.Rearrange the sequence of species of <italic>Saltator</italic> as follows:<italic>Saltator atriceps</italic><italic>Saltator maximus</italic><italic>Saltator grossus</italic><italic>Saltator albicollis</italic><italic>Saltator coerulescens</italic><italic>Saltator striatipectus</italic>p. 657. DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Powell1">Powell et al. 2014</xref>) indicate that <italic>Cacicus melanicterus</italic> is sister to a clade consisting of <italic>Psarocolius</italic> and the other species of <italic>Cacicus</italic>. Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Amblycercus holosericeus</italic>:<italic>Cassiculus</italic> Swainson, 1827, Philos. Mag., new ser., 1: 436. Type, by original designation, <italic>Cassiculus coronatus</italic> Swainson &equals; <italic>Icterus melanicterus</italic> Bonaparte.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Ridgway1">Ridgway (1902)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Hellmayr1">Hellmayr (1938)</xref> treated this species in the monotypic genus <italic>Cassiculus</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Blake1">Blake (1968)</xref> merged it into <italic>Cacicus</italic>, and this was followed in most subsequent classifications (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>). DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Powell1">Powell et al. 2014</xref>), however, indicate that <italic>Cassiculus</italic> is sister to a clade consisting of <italic>Psarocolius</italic> and true <italic>Cacicus</italic>.Change <bold><italic>Cacicus melanicterus</italic></bold> (Bonaparte) to <bold><italic>Cassiculus melanicterus</italic></bold> (Bonaparte) and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for <italic>Cassiculus</italic>. Replace the second sentence of the Notes with the following: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Cacicus</italic>. See comments under <italic>Cassiculus</italic>.Delete the citation of <italic>Caciculus</italic> from the synonymy of <italic>Cacicus</italic>. Remove the existing Notes under the heading Genus <bold><italic>CACICUS</italic></bold> Lac&eacute;p&egrave;de.pp. 682&ndash;683. DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ArnaizVillena1">Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that the generic limits and linear sequence of species currently placed in the genera <italic>Lonchura</italic> and <italic>Padda</italic> do not accurately reflect their evolutionary relationships. Their findings result in the following changes:Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Amandava amandava</italic>:<italic>Spermestes</italic> Swainson, 1837, Birds W. Africa 1, p. 201. Type, by monotypy, <italic>Spermestes cucullata</italic> Swainson.Formerly considered part of <italic>Lonchura</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>), but now treated as separate because DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ArnaizVillena1">Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that <italic>Spermestes</italic> is not included in true <italic>Lonchura</italic>.Delete the citation of <italic>Spermestes</italic> from the synonymy of <italic>Lonchura</italic>. Change <bold><italic>Lonchura cucullata</italic></bold> (Swainson) to <bold><italic>Spermestes cucullata</italic></bold> Swainson and place the account for this species under the heading and Notes for <italic>Spermestes</italic>. Replace the last sentence of the Notes with: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Lonchura</italic>. See comments under <italic>Spermestes</italic>.Insert the following heading in a position following the species account for <italic>Spermestes cucullata</italic>:<italic>Euodice</italic> Reichenbach, 1862&ndash;1863, Singv&ouml;gel, p. 46. Type, by subsequent designation (Sharpe, 1890, Cat. Birds Brit. Mus. 13, p. 368), <italic>Loxia cantans</italic> Gmelin.Formerly considered part of <italic>Lonchura</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion1">AOU 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-AmericanOrnithologistsUnion2">1998</xref>), but now treated as separate because DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ArnaizVillena1">Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that <italic>Euodice</italic> is not included in true <italic>Lonchura</italic>.Delete the citation of <italic>Euodice</italic> from the synonomy of <italic>Lonchura</italic>. Change <bold><italic>Lonchura malabarica</italic></bold> (Linnaeus) and <bold><italic>Lonchura cantans</italic></bold> (Gmelin) to <bold><italic>Euodice malabarica</italic></bold> (Linnaeus) and <bold><italic>Euodice cantans</italic></bold> (Gmelin), and place the accounts for these species in this sequence under the heading and Notes for <italic>Euodice</italic>. Make the appropriate changes in generic names or abbreviations within the existing Notes. Add the following to the end of the Notes for each species: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Lonchura</italic>. See comments under <italic>Euodice</italic>. Change <bold><italic>Padda oryzivora</italic></bold> (Linnaeus) to <bold><italic>Lonchura oryzivora</italic></bold> (Linnaeus), delete the genus heading and Notes for <italic>Padda</italic>, move the citation for <italic>Padda</italic> into the synonymy of <italic>Lonchura</italic>, insert the species account for <italic>Lonchura oryzivora</italic> to precede the account for <italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic>, and insert the following at the end of the Notes: Formerly placed in the genus <italic>Padda</italic>, but DNA sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-ArnaizVillena1">Arnaiz-Villena et al. 2009</xref>) indicate that <italic>Padda</italic> is embedded within <italic>Lonchura</italic>, as treated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Payne1">Payne (2010)</xref>.p. 683. Change the English name for <italic>Lonchura punctulata</italic> to Scaly-breasted Munia (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Inskipp1">Inskipp et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Robson1">Robson 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Payne1">Payne 2010</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Rasmussen2">Rasmussen and Anderton 2012</xref>). Change the Notes to read: Formerly known as Nutmeg Mannikin (e.g., AOU 1983, 1998), but name modified to conform to general worldwide usage. Also known as Spotted Munia, Spice Finch, or Ricebird.p. 698. Change <bold><italic>Oryzoborus angolensis</italic></bold> (Linnaeus) to <bold><italic>Sporophila angolensis</italic></bold> (Linnaeus). Phylogenetic analyses based on sequences of mitochondrial and nuclear DNA indicate that <italic>Oryzoborus</italic>, formerly considered a separate genus, is embedded within <italic>Sporophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Mason1">Mason and Burns 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-CSi-Burns1">Burns et al. 2014</xref>).pp. 705 ff. Make the following changes to the list of French names of North American birds:Insert the following names in the proper position as indicated by the text of this supplement:Rearrange the species sequence in <italic>Dendrocincla</italic>, <italic>Saltator</italic>, and <italic>Sporophila</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Rearrange the species sequence from <italic>Zenaida</italic> to <italic>Starnoenas</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Rearrange the species sequence from <italic>Aratinga</italic> to <italic>Ara</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Rearrange the sequence of species formerly in <italic>Hyloctistes</italic>, <italic>Automolus</italic>, and <italic>Thripadectes</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Rearrange the sequence of species formerly in <italic>Lonchura</italic> and <italic>Padda</italic> as indicated by the text of this supplement.Proposals considered but not accepted by the committee included transfer of several species of <italic>Spinus</italic> to <italic>Sporagra</italic> or <italic>Astragalinus</italic>, merger of Thick-billed Parrot <italic>Rhynchopsitta pachyrhyncha</italic> and Maroon-fronted Parrot <italic>R. terrisi</italic> into a single species, separation of the Cuban Parrot (<italic>Amazona leucocephala</italic>) complex into two or more species, separation of Siberian Stonechat <italic>Saxicola maurus</italic> from Common Stonechat <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. torquatus</named-content></italic>, separation of <italic>Toxostoma palmeri</italic> from Curve-billed Thrasher <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">T. curvirostre</named-content></italic>, elimination of the subfamily Trogoninae, and transfer of Azure Gallinule <italic>Porphyrio flavirostris</italic> from the main list to the Appendix.Normand David serves as the committee's advisor for classical languages in relation to scientific names, and Michel Gosselin is the authority for French names. We thank A. Borodayko, R. T. Brumfield, J. Cracraft, B. Freeman, K. L. Garrett, D. D. Gibson, S. N. G. Howell, M. J. Iliff, J. M. Maley, N. A. Mason, R. G. Moyle, G. Obando-Calder&oacute;n, J. Penhallurick, A. P. Peterson, M. L. P. Retter, B. T. Smith, M. D. Sorenson, C. Stahala, R. C. Tweit, A. Urant&oacute;wka, J. Withrow, and J. Zook for assistance, suggestions, and comments.