 Thank You to the Reviewers of the 2015  Auk , Volume 132  Peer review, honest and careful, is the cornerstone of modern scientific publishing, and essential to the maintenance of high standards in a journal. The efforts of reviewers are critical and yet unpaid, and so in the name of all of us at  The Auk: Ornithological Advances , I take the opportunity to thank all of you who contributed reviews while Volume 132 was in preparation (reviews completed between July 2014 and June 2015). Individuals with an asterisk next to their name reviewed two or three manuscripts.   The Auk: Ornithological Advances  is also grateful for the work of our two dedicated Editors, our busy Associate Editors, and the In Memoriam, Book Reviews, and 100 Years Ago Editors, and the expert editorial team members of the Central Ornithology Publication Office (COPO) whose work made the another successful year of  The Auk  possible.  Stefan Abrahamczyk  Caglar Akcay  Robert Allen Aldredge&ast;  Courtney Amundson  Michael J. Anteau  Peter Arcese  Daniel Robert Ardia&ast;  Wayne J. Arendt&ast;  Ian J. Ausprey  Suzanne H. Austin  Julian Avery  Franz Bairlein  John Baldwin  Michael J. Baldwin  Susan Balenger  Christophe Barbraud  Frederick Keith Barker&ast;  Julia Barske  Daniel Barton  Shane Baylis  Robert C. Beason  Michelle Lee Beck  Steven Beissinger  Marc Belisle  Joanne Bennett  Morgan Benowitz-Fredericks&ast;  Thomas J. Benson  Brett Benz  Douglas F. Bertram  Adam Betuel  Clotide Biard  Tim Billo  John G. Blake  Jessica Blois  Peter T. Boag&ast;  Gil Bohrer  Veronica B&oacute;kony  Eric K. Bollinger  Rachel T. Bolus  Alexander Bond  David N. Bonter  Jelle Boonekamp  Carlos A. Bosque  Kimberly S. Bostwick  Rauri C. K. Bowie  James V. Briskie  Robb T. Brumfield  Joseph Burton Buchanan  Mariana Bulgarella  Edward H. Burtt, Jr.&ast;  Mike Butler  William Buttemer  Alaine F. Camfield&ast;  Ken Campbell  Daniela Campobello&ast;  Renee Carleton&ast;  Matthew D. Carling  Nikita Cartwright  Nikita Chernetsov  Emily Beth Cohen&ast;  John L. Confer  Peter G. Connors  Sergio Cordoba  Stephane Cornet  Josselin Cornuault  William Andrew Cox  Joel Cracraft  Roslyn Dakin  Selvino de Kort  Liesbeth de Neve  Vanessa De Pietri  Denis Charles Deeming&ast;  Elizabeth P. Derryberry  Andr&eacute; Desrochers  David DesRochers&ast;  Andre Dhondt  Robert H. Diehl  Colleen T. Downs  Adrienne Dubois  David C. Duffy  Camille Duval  Emily H. DuVal&ast;  Jessica Eberhard  Steve Emlen  R. Todd Engstrom  Matthew A. Etterson&ast;  David Ewert  John Faaborg  Juan Antonio Fargallo  Andrew Farnsworth  Alan Feduccia  William Feeney&ast;  Ricardo Fernandes  Valentina Ferretti  Daniel Jared Field  Robert C. Fleischer  Tyler Flockhart  Jennifer Rhea Foote  Scott Forbes  Mercedes S. Foster  Christian Foth  Mercival Francisco  Morton Frederiksen  Leonard Freed&ast;  Benjamin Gardner Freeman  Lenny Gannes  Tom Gardali  James Gilroy  Andrew G. Gosler  Elizabeth A. Gow&ast;  David John Green&ast;  Greg Grether  Andrea Sue Grunst  Melanie Guigueno&ast;  M. Guilfoyle  Sarah Laurence Guindre-Parker&ast;  Susan M. Haig  Frank Hailer  Margaret I. Hall  Anne Hecht  Christopher M. Heckscher  Carol Henger  Tomasz Hetma&nacute;ski  Keith A. Hobson  William L. Hohman  Marcel Honza  Jeffrey P. Hoover  Jocelyn Hudon  Melissa Hughes  Bransilav Igic&ast;  David Iles  Ei-Ichi Izawa  Helen James&ast;  Jill Jankowski  Erich Jarvis&ast;  Lukas Jenni  Bryan Jennings&ast;  Yuexin Jiang  Oscar W. Johnson  Jason Jones&ast;  Sara Ann Kaiser  Filiz Karadas  Takeshi Kawakami&ast;  Bart Kempenaers  Corinne Kendall  Dylan C. Kesler  Coby Klein&ast;  Walter Koenig  Carmi Korine  Niels Krabbe&ast;  Alan H. Krakauer&ast;  Robert Kraus  Milos Krist&ast;  Michael Kuehn&ast;  Daniel Lane  Tom Langen  Quresh Latif  Andrew Laughlin  Christophe Lebigre  Jin-Won Lee  Catherine A. Lindell&ast;  Dina Lipkind  Michael P. Lombardo  Isabel Lopez-Rull  Matthew Ian McKim Louder  Irby Lovette  Peter E. Lowther  Martin R. Luck  Sarah Luttrell&ast;  Bruce Lyon  Scott MacDougall-Shackleton&ast;  Andrew Mack  Mark C. Mainwaring  Peter Makovicky  James Maley  Mark L. Mallory&ast;  Albrecht Manegold  R. William Mannan  Joseph Manthey  Melissa Mark  Kathy Martin  Paul Martin&ast;  John McCormack  Jimmy McGuire  Marc McKee  Susan B. McRae  Todd J. McWhorter  Hanneke Meijer  Edward Miller  Anders P. Moller  Robert D. Montgomerie  Frank R. Moore  Ignacio Thomas Moore  Eugene S. Morton  Michael T. Murphy  Julie Mustard  Beat Naef-Daenzer  Laurent Nagle  Eric Nol  Jorge Noriega  George Olah  Carl Oliveros  Juan Francisco Ornelas&ast;  Luis Ortiz Catedral  Kean Alan Otter  Keith Pardieck&ast;  Juan Luis Parra  Gail L. Patricelli  Michael A. Patten&ast;  Kristina Paxton  Scott F. Pearson  Ricardo Pereira&ast;  Jonathan Hebbel Perez  Javier P&eacute;rez-Tris  Vitor Piacentini  Bradley A. Pickens  Walter H. Piper&ast;  Steven Portugal  Abby N. Powell  J. Jordan Price  Richard Prum&ast;  Cromwell Purchase  Peter Pyle&ast;  Dan Rabosky  Joel Ralston&ast;  Sedano Raul  Matt Rayner  Juan Carlos Reboreda  Dustin G. Reichard  Sophie Reichert  Paul Reillo  J. V. Remsen  Matthew W. Reudink  Amanda Ridley&ast;  Christina Riehl&ast;  Douglas Robinson  Scott K. Robinson  Jeremy T. Rockweit  Nicholas L. Rodenhouse  Vanya Gregor Rohwer  Victor Rosas-Guerrero  John Rotenberry  Alexandre Roulin  Alexander Royan  Dustin Rubenstein  Viviana Ruiz-Gutierrez&ast;  Scott Rush  Andy Russell  Peter Samas  John R. Sauer  Isabella B. R. Scheiber&ast;  Joshua H. Schmidt&ast;  Kimberly Schmidt  Ellen Schoener  Tom Schulenberg&ast;  Elizabeth Scordato  Juan Carlos Senar  Matthew D. Shawkey&ast;  David Shealer  Allison J. Shultz&ast;  Dave Shutler&ast;  Joseph Simonis  Theodore R. Simons  Brian Tilston Smith  N. Adam Smith&ast;  Robert Smith  Juan Jose Soler  Karen Spencer  Mark Thomas Stanback  Jessica Stapley&ast;  Caitlin Stern  Walter Sergio Svagelj&ast;  Caz M. Taylor  Graeme Taylor  Scott A. Taylor  Ethan J. Temeles&ast;  Frank R. Thompson III&ast;  Ralph Tiedemann  Anna Tigano  Christopher Tonra&ast;  Andrew J. Tyre  Ren&eacute; Erwin van Dijk  Eric Antony VanderWerf  Wouter Vansteelant  Maren Vitousek&ast;  Andrew C. Vitz  Carol M. Vleck  Margaret Voss&ast;  Jeffrey R. Walters  Ming Wang  Ian Warkentin  Christopher C. Warren  Jason Weir  Emily L. Weiser&ast;  Kenneth Welch&ast;  Caitlin Wells  David Westmoreland  Tim White&ast;  Bret Whitney  Karen Wiebe  Kevin Winker  Christopher C. Witt&ast;  Jared Wolfe  Tianjun Xu  Jenny York  Rebecca Young  Erica Zarate  Theodore Joseph Zenzal  Robert M. Zink&ast;  David J. Ziolkowski 