Bacteria-killing ability is negatively linked to epaulet size, but positively linked to baseline corticosterone, in male Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>)Competition between immune function and lipid transport for the protein apolipophorin III leads to stress-induced immunosuppression in cricketsSeasonal daily, daytime and night-time field metabolic rates in Arabian Babblers (<italic>Turdoides squamiceps</italic>)Interactions of corticosterone with feeding, activity and metabolism in passerine birdsSocial stability and territory acquisition in birdsRelationships of steroid hormones and polygyny to territorial status, breeding experience, and reproductive success in male Red-winged BlackbirdsDo baseline glucocorticoids predict fitness?The relationship between fitness and baseline glucocorticoids in a passerine birdThe stress of parenthood? Increased glucocorticoids in birds with experimentally enlarged broodsAssessing the cost of mounting an immune responseSong repertoire is not affected by stress in an adult male songbird, the Whitethroat <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia communis</named-content></italic>Physiological stress mediates the honesty of social signalsDiel rhythms of basal and stress-induced corticosterone in a wild, seasonal vertebrate, Gambel's White-crowned SparrowStress and the evolution of condition-dependent signalsFeedback action and tonic influence of corticosteroids on brain function: A concept arising from the heterogeneity of brain receptor systemsReproductive effort decreases antibody responsivenessEnhancing versus suppressive effects of stress on immune function: Implications for immunoprotection and immunopathologyAcute stress enhances while chronic stress suppresses cell-mediated immunity in vivo: A potential role for leukocyte traffickingStress: An inevitable component of animal translocationThe sequence of plumages and moults of the passerine birds of New YorkCompetition for territories in Red-winged Blackbirds: Is resource-holding potential realized?Ideal dominance distributions: A test using Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>)Cutaneous immune activity, but not innate immune responsiveness, covaries with mass and environment in nestling House Wrens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Troglodytes aedon</named-content></italic>)Plasma corticosterone response to acute and chronic voluntary exercise in female house miceSuppression of phytohemagglutinin skin response in thymectomized chickensInfectious diseases, reproductive effort and the cost of reproduction in birdsSeasonal sex-specific energy expenditure in breeding and non-breeding Palestine Sunbirds <italic>Nectarinia osea</italic>Heritable true fitness and bright birds: A role for parasites?Energetic constraints on expression of carotenoid-based plumage colorationPlumage colour signals nutritional condition in the House FinchReproductive and physiological costs of repeated immune challenges in female Wellington tree weta (Orthoptera: Anostostomatidae)The energetic cost of feather synthesis is proportional to basal metabolic rateTrade-offs in evolutionary immunology: Just what is the cost of immunity?Evolution of reproductive&ndash;immune interactionsStress and immunity in wild vertebrates: Timing is everythingPhytohemagglutinin-induced skin swelling in birds: Histological support for a classic immunoecological techniqueImmune function differences between continental and island forms: A symptom of an island syndrome?Capture stress and the bactericidal competence of blood and plasma in five species of tropical birdsDifferent colors reveal different information: How nutritional stress affects the expression of melanin- and structurally based ornamental plumageLinking a static signal to current condition: Song-repertoire size, corticosterone, and immunity in the Brown-headed CowbirdQuantifying and comparing constitutive immunity across avian speciesCross-fostering reveals sources of variation in innate immunity and hematocrit in nestling Tree Swallows <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>Reproductive effort reduces specific immune response and parasite resistanceSong learning, early nutrition and sexual selection in songbirdsAndrogens and the immunocompetence handicap hypothesis: Unraveling direct and indirect pathways of immunosuppression in Song SparrowsOn the adaptive significance of stress-induced immunosuppressionThe physiology/life-history nexusBody size and harem size in male Red-winged Blackbirds: Manipulating selection with sex-specific feedersPhysiological stress in ecology: Lessons from biomedical researchCollecting baseline corticosterone samples in the field: Is under 3 min good enough?Dynamic feedback between phenotype and physiology in sexually selected traitsSexual signal exaggeration affects physiological state in male Barn SwallowsNeuroendocrinology of the stress responseHow do glucocorticoids influence stress responses? Integrating permissive, suppressive, stimulatory, and preparative actionsThe reproductive success of secondary females relative to that of monogamous and primary females in Red-winged BlackbirdsFirst-year plumages of the Brown-headed Cowbirds and Red-winged BlackbirdUnderstanding stress-induced immunosuppression: Exploration of cytokine and chemokine gene profiles in chicken peripheral leukocytesSimplifying the phytohaemagglutinin skin-testing technique in studies of avian immunocompetenceThe PHA test reflects acquired T-cell mediated immunocompetence in birdsConstitutive innate immunity is a component of the pace-of-life syndrome in tropical birdsMale and female golden whistlers respond differently to static and dynamic signals of male intrudersFunctional analysis of the skin-swelling response to phytohaemagglutininFemale plumage colour influences seasonal oxidative damage and testosterone profiles in a songbirdParasite faunas, testosterone and secondary sexual traits in male Red-winged BlackbirdsEndocrine responses of White-crowned Sparrows to environmental stressSeasonal changes of the adrenocortical response to stress in birds of the Sonoran desertImmune defense and host life historyCurrent address: Illinois Natural History Survey, Champaign, Illinois, USASecondary sexual traits in males are thought to convey information about the quality of the male to rivals and potential mates. Semi-static signals such as sexually selected plumage are thought to convey information about how well a male fared through a critical period, such as development or molt, but it is unclear if they should relate to his current condition during the breeding season. We examined the relation between epaulet size and two measures of immune function, levels of baseline corticosterone (CORT), and body condition in adult male Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>). Epaulet size was significantly negatively related to the bacteria-killing ability (BKA) of the blood but was not related to the phytohemagglutinin swelling response. There was no significant relationship between CORT and epaulet size, but there was a significant positive relationship between CORT and BKA. In addition, BKA was significantly positively correlated with date, suggesting a possible tradeoff with breeding-related activity levels. However, body condition was not related to measures of immunity, CORT, or epaulet size. Our results indicate that male Red-winged Blackbirds with larger semi-static signals experience reduced BKA during the breeding season and that baseline levels of CORT can be positively associated with measures of immune function.Se cree que los caracteres sexuales secundarios en los machos transmiten informaci&oacute;n sobre la calidad del macho frente a sus rivales y posibles parejas. Se cree que las se&ntilde;ales semi-est&aacute;ticas, como el plumaje sexualmente seleccionado, transmiten informaci&oacute;n sobre cuan bien un macho ha atravezado per&iacute;odos cr&iacute;ticos, como el desarrollo o la muda, pero no est&aacute; claro si deber&iacute;an estar relacionadas con su condici&oacute;n actual durante la &eacute;poca reproductiva. Examinamos la relaci&oacute;n entre el tama&ntilde;o de la charretera y dos medidas de la funci&oacute;n inmunol&oacute;gica, los niveles basales de corticosterona (CORT), y la condici&oacute;n corporal de machos adultos de sargentos (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>). Se encontr&oacute; una relaci&oacute;n negativa significativa entre el tama&ntilde;o de la charretera con la capacidad bactericida (BKA) de la sangre, pero no estuvo relacionada con la respuesta inflamatoria de la fitohemaglutinina. No existi&oacute; una relaci&oacute;n significativa entre CORT y el tama&ntilde;o de la charretera, pero se encontr&oacute; una relaci&oacute;n positiva significativa entre CORT y BKA. Adem&aacute;s, se encontr&oacute; una correlaci&oacute;n positiva significativa entre BKA y la fecha, lo que sugiere una posible desventaja con los niveles relacionados a la actividad reproductiva. Sin embargo, la condici&oacute;n corporal no se relacion&oacute; con las medidas de inmunidad, CORT o el tama&ntilde;o de la charretera. Nuestros resultados indican que los sargentos machos con mayores se&ntilde;ales semi-est&aacute;ticas experimentan una reducci&oacute;n de la BKA durante la &eacute;poca reproductiva y que los niveles basales de CORT pueden estar positivamente asociados con las medidas de la funci&oacute;n inmunol&oacute;gica.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic>Agelaius phoeniceus</italic>, endocrinolog&iacute;a aviar, funci&oacute;n inmunol&oacute;gica, ecolog&iacute;a fisiol&oacute;gica, se&ntilde;ales semi-est&aacute;ticasSignals fall on a continuum from dynamic to static (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-vanDongen1">van Dongen and Mulder 2008</xref>); dynamic signals are those in which transmission of the signal can be modulated by the sender (e.g., song rate in birds), whereas static signals are those in which the size or intensity of the signal is fixed once it develops and cannot be modulated by the sender over its lifetime (e.g., song repertoire size in closed-ended learning species). Molt of breeding plumage in birds typically occurs once a year and is thus a <italic>semi-static</italic> signal of male quality to females and other males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Hamilton1">Hamilton and Zuk 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Andersson1">Andersson 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Hill1">Hill 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2002</xref>); the signal is mostly fixed once the feathers develop but is subject to change on an annual basis, depending on the physiology and condition of the individual (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Rubenstein1">Rubenstein and Hauber 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Safran1">Safran et al. 2008</xref>). The size and/or brightness of those feathers may provide information on how well the male fared during the energetically demanding period of molt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Lindstrom1">Lindstrom et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Hill2">Hill and Montgomerie 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-McGraw1">McGraw et al. 2002</xref>), comparable to the manner in which song repertoire size provides information on how well a male fared during the energetically demanding period of development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Nowicki1">Nowicki et al. 1998</xref>).The relationship between static or semi-static signals and current health is complicated by the lag between development of the signal and its use in intrasexual and intersexual communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Vitousek1">Vitousek et al. 2013</xref>). In addition, once the signal is generated, it typically does not fluctuate with hormone levels or current health. Our previous work on the relations between immune function, body condition, baseline corticosterone (CORT), and song repertoire size in adult male Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;cowbirds&rdquo;) indicated that breeding male cowbirds with larger repertoires experienced reduced bacteria-killing ability (BKA) of the blood plasma and had elevated baseline CORT levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Merrill1">Merrill et al. 2013</xref>). CORT and BKA were not associated, however, and we suggested that males with larger repertoires were more dominant, had increased energy expenditures, and traded off resources between breeding activities and BKA.Here, we examine epaulet size, immune function, body condition, and levels of baseline CORT in Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Agelaius phoeniceus</named-content></italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-f01">Figure 1</xref>) to better understand the relationship between semi-static signals and immune function. If epaulet size is positively linked with dominance (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Eckert1">Eckert and Weatherhead 1987a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy2">Searcy and Yasukawa 1996</xref>), and if dominant male Red-winged Blackbirds expend significantly more energy than subordinate males (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Eckert2">Eckert and Weatherhead 1987b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Beletsky2">Beletsky and Orians 1996</xref>), epaulet size should be negatively correlated with immune function during the breeding season as males trade off resources between parasite resistance (immunological or behavioral) and signaling behavior. The immune system is costly to develop and maintain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Raberg1">R&aring;berg et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Lochmiller1">Lochmiller and Deerenberg 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Zuk1">Zuk and Stoehr 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Bonneaud1">Bonneaud et al. 2003</xref>), and, because daily energy expenditure tends to be high during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Anava1">Anava et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Hambly1">Hambly et al. 2007</xref>), males may need to trade off resources between signaling and immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-OwenAshley1">Owen-Ashley et al. 2004</xref>). There is some evidence supporting this idea in Red-winged Blackbirds, in that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Weatherhead1">Weatherhead et al. (1993</xref>) and L. Merrill and T. E. Stewart (personal observation) found positive correlations between epaulet size and ectoparasite infections.Iteroparous organisms such as Red-winged Blackbirds need to trade off between investing in current reproduction and future reproduction (i.e. self-maintenance; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Stearns1">Stearns 1992</xref>). Immune function is a major component of self-maintenance, and there should be a reduction in at least some aspects of immune function as organisms allocate resources away from self-maintenance. There is good evidence that reproductive effort is traded off against immune function (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Gustafsson1">Gustafsson et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Deerenberg1">Deerenberg et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Nordling1">Nordling et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Kelly1">Kelly 2011</xref>), and many components of the immune system have receptors and/or binding sites for sex and/or reproductive hormones (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Lutton1">Lutton and Callard 2006</xref>). This linkage provides direct pathways for modulation of immune function via the same factors that affect reproductive condition. We used two measures of immune function in the present study to broaden our ability to detect a relationship between epaulet size and immune function. We assessed a component of constitutive innate immunity by measuring the BKA of the plasma against a novel strain of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Escherichia coli</named-content></italic> and an induced, pro-inflammatory response to an injection of a novel antigen, phytohemagglutinin (PHA). BKA is dependent on circulating antimicrobial proteins (complement; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Matson1">Matson et al. 2005</xref>, L. Merrill personal observation), whereas the PHA response is composed of cells of both innate and acquired immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Goto1">Goto et al. 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Martin2">Martin et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Tella1">Tella et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Vinkler1">Vinkler et al. 2010</xref>) and may be partly linked to the wound-healing process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Vinkler1">Vinkler et al. 2010</xref>).We also examined CORT because of the role it plays in modulating numerous physiological processes. Circulating CORT increases rapidly after exposure to noxious stimuli, triggering a suite of changes in the organism as part of the stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Romero1">Romero 2004</xref>), but CORT is also linked to activity levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Astheimer1">Astheimer et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Girard1">Girard and Garland 2002</xref>). CORT is immunosuppressive when chronically elevated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Sapolsky1">Sapolsky 1992</xref>), and if tied to T and/or breeding-related activity levels, which are themselves linked to signal expression, CORT may serve as an indirect handicap mechanism related to the expression of sexual signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Buchanan1">Buchanan 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Bortolotti1">Bortolotti et al. 2009</xref>). At baseline levels, however, CORT can act in a permissive manner on other physiological processes (i.e. permit or amplify the action of other processes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-DeKloet1">De Kloet and Reul 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Sapolsky2">Sapolsky et al. 2000</xref>) and has been positively associated with fitness components during some life-history stages in many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Bonier1">Bonier et al. 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Bonier2">2009b</xref>), including Red-winged Blackbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Beletsky3">Beletsky et al. 1989</xref>).We predicted that, in accord with the results we found between song repertoire size, immune function, and CORT in male cowbirds, epaulet size would be negatively related to immune function and positively associated with CORT levels, and that CORT would not be related to our measures of immune function.Red-winged Blackbirds (family Icteridae) are ubiquitous inhabitants of marshes, fields, and agricultural areas throughout North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Beletsky1">Beletsky 1992</xref>) and are highly polygynous in most of their range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Beletsky1">Beletsky 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy2">Searcy and Yasukawa 1996</xref>). Male Red-winged Blackbirds are 55&percnt; larger than females by mass, on average (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Rohwer1">Rohwer et al. 1996</xref>), and they have mean harem sizes of 1.8&ndash;6.2 females territory<sup>&minus;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy1">Searcy and Yasukawa 1995</xref>).We used only adult (&ge;2 years old) males because 1-year-old males almost never acquire mates (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy1">Searcy and Yasukawa 1995</xref>), and we aged birds as yearlings or adults by plumage and morphometric differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Dwight1">Dwight 1900</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Selander1">Selander and Giller 1960</xref>) at the times of capture.We captured Red-winged Blackbirds at four sites in Santa Barbara, California, USA (34&deg;25&prime;N, 119&deg;41&prime;W), in the breeding season of 2007 (April 13 to June 14). We used Potter traps baited with a wild-bird seed mix (millet, milo, cracked corn, and sunflower seeds) and Troyer V-Top decoy traps (1.4 &times; 1.5 &times; 1.7 m) baited with live birds, food, and water. Trapping occurred between 0600 and 1230 hours (PST) to control for variation in hormone levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Breuner1">Breuner et al. 1999</xref>) and immune activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Forsman1">Forsman et al. 2010</xref>). We collected blood from the brachial vein within 3 min of capture (in the Potter traps) or the arrival of people (decoy trap) to obtain baseline CORT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Wingfield1">Wingfield et al. 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Romero2">Romero and Reed 2005</xref>) and the BKA of the plasma. There were no differences in measures of immunity or CORT for birds captured using Potter versus decoy traps (BKA: Potter trap, mean &equals; 0.14 &plusmn; 0.04, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 12; decoy trap, mean &equals; 0.24 &plusmn; 0.08, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 3; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.36; PHA: Potter trap, mean &equals; 0.73 &plusmn; 0.08, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 16; decoy trap, mean &equals; 0.87 &plusmn; 0.15, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 5; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.45; CORT: Potter trap, mean &equals; 0.81 &plusmn; 0.08 ng mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 14; decoy trap, mean &equals; 0.62 &plusmn; 0.16 ng mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 3; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.32; means are presented &plusmn; SE throughout). We swabbed the skin around the brachial vein with 70&percnt; EtOH, allowed the alcohol to evaporate (&sim;10 s) and pierced the vein using a sterile 25-gauge needle. We collected blood using sterile, heparinized 75-mm capillary tubes, which were then plugged with clay at one end. Blood was placed on ice until we returned from the field, at which point it was spun down using a capillary tube centrifuge. We then removed the plasma, divided it between two 1.5-mL microcentrifuge tubes (one for the BKA assay and one for the CORT assay), and froze it at &minus;20&deg;C until it was assayed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Morrison1">Morrison et al. 2009</xref>). Following blood collection, we banded birds with U.S. Fish and Wildlife bands and collected morphometric data. For a measure of body condition, we used mass/tarsus<sup>3</sup> &times; 100 to provide some indication of the relative amount of muscle and fat reserves each male had. After capture, blood collection, banding, and measuring, birds were brought back to the aviary at the University of California, Santa Barbara. Upon arrival at the aviary, we photographed each male's right-wing epaulet using a 3.2-megapixel Nikon Coolpix 3100 digital camera. The wing was spread against a standardized background with a ruler immediately below the wing for reference, and the entire area of the badge was exposed for the photos. Immediately after being photographed, birds were placed in individual cages (46 &times; 27 &times; 27 cm) that were then placed inside individual sound-attenuating isolation chambers (internal dimensions 53 &times; 28 &times; 30 cm). Each chamber had an external fan for air circulation and a 30-cm, 110v fluorescent light set to a photocell so that the birds were maintained on the natural photoperiod. Each individual cage had food (Mazuri Small Birds Maintenance kibble mixed with millet seed) and water dispensers that were replenished daily. Birds were kept in isolation for 44&ndash;48 hr before we performed the PHA test.We used ImageJ software (see Acknowledgments) and a Wacom Intuos3 tablet to determine the epaulet size for each male. Using IMageJ's &ldquo;line trace&rdquo; tool, we measured 1 cm on the ruler included in each photograph, which allowed the program to calibrate how many pixels 1 cm comprises for each photo. We used the &ldquo;free trace&rdquo; tool to trace the outline of the epaulet and were then able to calculate the area inside the tracing.We used two techniques to assess immunocompetence: a bacteria-killing assay and the PHA challenge. The bacteria-killing assay against <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. coli</named-content></italic> (ATCC no. 8739) is easy to quantify and interpret: higher in vitro killing should translate to faster clearance of a bacterial infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Tieleman1">Tieleman et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Matson2">Matson et al. 2006</xref>).The second component of immune function that we assessed is a more integrated measure of an organism's induced pro-inflammatory response. PHA is a lectin from the red kidney bean (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phaseolus vulgaris</named-content></italic>) and is a novel antigen when injected subcutaneously into vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Elgert1">Elgert 1996</xref>). The response to PHA involves components of the innate and acquired arms of the immune system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Goto1">Goto et al. 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Martin2">Martin et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Tella1">Tella et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Vinkler1">Vinkler et al. 2010</xref>), causing a local inflammatory response at the site of injection. This challenge is thought to provide some indication of the strength of response that an organism can mount against an invading pathogen. We have used two measures of immune function in order to increase the power to detect tradeoffs between immunity and life-history strategies.Methods for the assay were derived from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Millet1">Millet et al. (2007</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Morrison1">Morrison et al. (2009</xref>). In brief, we added 5 &mu;L of plasma to a combination of CO<sub>2</sub>-independent media (Gibco and Invitrogen; Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA) &plus; 4mM L-glutamine (90 &mu;L), and the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. coli</named-content></italic> bacterial broth (10 &mu;L), incubated the solution for 20 min at 40&deg;C, then pipetted out 50 &mu;L in duplicate onto agar plates, which were then incubated overnight at 37&deg;C. The bacterial colonies were counted the following day and compared with control plates in which the bacterial broth and 95 &mu;L of PBS were incubated together without any plasma. Killing capacity was determined by subtracting the mean number of colonies for a bird's two plates from the mean number of control colonies and then dividing that by the control mean.Birds were placed in isolation chambers for &sim;48 hr following capture before we conducted the PHA challenge, to control for variation in handling time during capture as well as exposure to predators, rivals, and short-term inclement weather events. As mentioned above, stress can influence levels of immune function, and although captivity can cause an increase in glucocorticoids (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Dickens1">Dickens et al. 2010</xref>), this protocol allowed for greater control of unknown variables. To conduct the PHA challenge, we trimmed the feathers from the birds' left patagium, sterilized the site of injection with 70&percnt; isopropyl alcohol, measured the patagium thickness at the site of injection using a micrometer, and injected 0.05 mL of 1 mg PHA mL<sup>&minus;1</sup> phosphate buffered saline just below the skin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Smits1">Smits et al. 1999</xref>). We then returned the birds to their isolation chambers for another 48 hr, after which we remeasured the wing-web at the site of injection and released them. Swelling response was quantified as the wing-web thickness at 48 hr post-injection, minus the wing-web thickness pre-injection.We determined plasma levels of total CORT via radioimmunoassay, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Wingfield2">Wingfield et al. (1992</xref>). In brief, we added 20 &mu;L tritiated CORT to each sample and incubated overnight at 4&deg;C. We extracted each sample using dichloromethane for 2 hr before removing the organic layer, drying it using liquid nitrogen, and then resuspending the extract in PBS with gelatin. We assayed all samples in duplicate and corrected hormone values for any variation in initial plasma volumes and percentage of tritiated CORT recovered. Intra-assay coefficient of variation was 2.9&percnt;, and recoveries ranged from 55&percnt; to 84&percnt;.We examined the associations between epaulet size and BKA, date, baseline CORT, and body condition using general linear models (GLMs). We included tarsus length as a covariate in the models to control for differences in body size between males. For the model examining epaulet size and body condition, we used mass as the dependent variable and included tarsus length as a covariate. We used correlational analysis to examine the relations between BKA, CORT, and body condition, and linear regression to determine whether BKA, CORT, or body condition covaried with capture date. Male investment in breeding activities declines over the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy1">Searcy and Yasukawa 1995</xref>), and if males trade off between self-maintenance and current reproduction, there may be changes in BKA, CORT, and body condition over time. The CORT data were not normally distributed, so we log transformed the CORT data for all analyses.To examine the relationships between the PHA response and epaulet size, date, baseline CORT, and body condition, we ran separate GLMs for each independent variable, with absolute change in wing-web thickness as the dependent variable. We included initial wing-web thickness as a covariate in each model to control for variation in initial wing-web thickness between birds because we have documented a significant effect of initial wing-web thickness on the final swelling response in our studies of cowbirds (L. Merrill personal observation). We included tarsus length in the model examining PHA and epaulet size to control for body-size differences.The two measures of immune function depend on different components of the immune system, and we wanted to ascertain whether there was a tradeoff or a positive association between the two. We used a GLM with BKA and initial wing-web thickness as predictor variables and absolute change in wing-web thickness as the dependent variable.To check the fit of the models, residuals were tested for normality and homoscedasticity. Tests were two-tailed, with the significance level set at &alpha; &equals; 0.05. Sample sizes vary between tests as a result of sampling limitations (for example, insufficient blood collected for both BKA and CORT analyses). We used JMP version 9.0 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) for all analyses.We captured 21 adult male Red-winged Blackbirds and recorded epaulet size, PHA response, and morphometric data for each. Epaulet size ranged from 10.07 cm<sup>2</sup> to 14.92 cm<sup>2</sup> (mean &equals; 12.39 &plusmn; 1.32 cm<sup>2</sup>; median &equals; 12.15 cm<sup>2</sup>). We collected enough plasma to quantify CORT for 17 males, enough plasma to quantify BKA for 15 males, and enough plasma to quantify both CORT and BKA for 13 males.We found that BKA significantly positively covaried with date (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-f02">Figure 2</xref>; linear regression: <italic>t</italic><sub>1,14</sub> &equals; 4.28, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Given the documented importance of date on activity levels in male Red-winged Blackbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy1">Searcy and Yasukawa 1995</xref>) and the significant relation between date and BKA, we included date as a covariate in further analyses of BKA.In accord with our predictions, epaulet size was significantly negatively related to BKA in male Red-winged Blackbirds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-f03">Figure 3</xref>; GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,14</sub> &equals; 10.93, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). We checked for an effect of date on epaulet size but found none (GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> &equals; 0.08, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.78). Contrary to our predictions, we found a significant positive relationship between BKA and CORT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-f04">Figure 4</xref>; GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 5.82, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04), but no relationship between BKA and body condition (GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,14</sub> &equals; 0.59, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.46).There were no significant relations between PHA response and any of the other parameters (GLMs: epaulet size, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> &lt; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.96; BKA, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,14</sub> &equals; 0.78, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.40; CORT, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,16</sub> &equals; 0.10, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.76; body condition, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> &equals; 0.11, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.74; date, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> &equals; 0.08, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.78). CORT was not related to epaulet size (GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,16</sub> &equals; 1.27, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.28), date (linear regression: <italic>t</italic><sub>1,16</sub> &equals; 0.59, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.56), or body condition (correlation: <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.01, df &equals; 16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.74). Body condition was not related to epaulet size (GLM: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,19</sub> &equals; 2.44, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.14), nor did it covary with date (linear regression: <italic>t</italic><sub>1,20</sub> &equals; &minus;1.49, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.15).As predicted, we found a significant negative relationship between semi-static signal expression (epaulet size) and BKA, similar to the negative relationship between song repertoire size and BKA that we documented in adult male cowbirds. In contrast to our predictions, however, we found a significant positive relationship between baseline CORT levels and BKA, and that male Red-winged Blackbirds with larger epaulets did not have higher levels of CORT. We also documented a significant positive relationship between date and BKA in the male Red-winged Blackbirds, similar to the positive relationship that we found between date and PHA response in male cowbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Merrill1">Merrill et al. 2013</xref>).Males of both species exhibit a decline in activity levels over the course of the breeding season (Red-winged Blackbirds, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Searcy1">Searcy and Yasukawa 1995</xref>; cowbirds, L. Merrill personal observation), and the increase in measures of immune function in males of both species over the course of the breeding period suggests that males may allocate resources to self-maintenance as their investment in current reproduction declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Nordling1">Nordling et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs and Wikelski 2002</xref>). Static and semi-static signals can be tied to both immunocompetence and energy expenditure if a male's activity levels are influenced by the size of his signal, and if males need to trade off resources between activity levels and immune function. Results of other studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Eckert1">Eckert and Weatherhead 1987a</xref>) indicate that male Red-winged Blackbirds with larger signaling plumage traits are dominant to those with smaller signaling plumage traits, and there is evidence that dominant male Red-winged Blackbirds expend significantly more energy than subordinate individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Beletsky2">Beletsky and Orians 1996</xref>). We did not find a relationship between our measure of body condition and any measure of immunity, CORT, or epaulet size, however, which suggests either that this measure is not a good proxy for body condition in Red-winged Blackbirds or that other factors play larger roles in determining activity levels and immune function in breeding-season males.To understand more fully whether tradeoffs between signaling and immune function exist, and, if so, what factors shape the tradeoffs, it is important to consider the underlying physiological mechanisms in addition to the behavioral ones. Organisms may trade off between signaling and immune function for one or more of the following reasons: energy limitation (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Lochmiller1">Lochmiller and Deerenberg 2000</xref>), specific resource limitation (e.g., apolipophorin III in crickets; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Adamo1">Adamo et al. 2008</xref>), and avoidance of immunopathology (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Dhabhar1">Dhabhar 2009</xref>). Much of the work on sexual signals and immune function has focused on the role of hormones as modulators of these tradeoffs. CORT, in particular, has received considerable attention for its immunosuppressive properties when elevated for sustained periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Dhabhar2">Dhabhar and McEwen 1997</xref>), and circulating levels of the hormone have been negatively linked to sexual signals in some studies (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-OwenAshley1">Owen-Ashley et al. 2004</xref>). The functional role of variation in baseline levels of CORT is poorly understood, however, and CORT likely plays multiple roles in regulating allocation of resources. Our data indicate that baseline levels of CORT can be positively linked to immune function. To our knowledge, this is the first study to document a positive correlation between natural levels of baseline CORT and a measure of immune function in a wild bird. It is unclear whether the documented linkages between CORT and immune function are direct or indirect, but the emerging data suggest that the role of CORT in modulating immune function is complex. Research on the effects of acute stress on immune function has documented immunostimulation and/or immunoredistribution following short-term stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Dhabhar2">Dhabhar and McEwen 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Shini1">Shini et al. 2010</xref>), and it is becoming clear that CORT acts in a dosage- and time-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Martin1">Martin 2009</xref>). In addition, understanding the ecological context of the organism at the time of sampling (i.e. season, social setting, age, and sex) can have important ramifications for interpreting the role of circulating CORT levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Bonier3">Bonier et al. 2011</xref>).Here, we have demonstrated that a semi-static sexual signal can be linked to immune function and that during the breeding season, male Red-winged Blackbirds with larger sexual signals exhibit lower levels of immune function than males with smaller signals. These results are concordant with our findings that song repertoire size was negatively correlated with BKA in adult male cowbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Merrill1">Merrill et al. 2013</xref>). The energy required for displays could drive the tradeoff between immunity and activity levels, but whether it is energy limitation, a resource crunch, or avoidance of immunopathology is unclear. This tradeoff could still ensure honest signaling if males with larger signals expend more energy than males with smaller signals. Information on individual males' daily energy budgets, social ranking, behavioral interactions, and reproductive success would provide important insight into the link between static and semi-static signals and immune function in these birds. In neither the cowbird study nor the present study was baseline CORT negatively linked to measures of immune function, and baseline CORT was positively correlated with BKA in the present study.Static and semi-static signals are widespread in nature, but the information they convey is not well understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-3-Borowiec1">Borowiec et al. 2007</xref>). It is also clear that signals are not all comparable. The diversity in developmental origins, the variety of modes of expression, and the unknown relative importance of genetic and environmental factors for different static and semi-static signals make it difficult to draw unifying themes across these signal types. We believe, however, that activity levels related to static and semi-static signal expression may provide a common link between signals of different origins and measures of current condition.We thank K. Paulsen and D. Bush for help with the bacteria-killing assay. J. Krause, K. Lizars, M. Ramenofsky, and C. Craig-Veit provided assistance with the hormone assays. Thanks to S. Smolley, T. Stewart, P. Gomez-Gonzalez, A. Kuris, and two anonymous reviewers for feedback on the manuscript; D. Okamoto and T. Tunstall for help with statistical analyses; and K. Klasing for feedback on the immunology work. M. Allen, C. Batha, S. Borchert, V. Ellis, J. Hermosa, E. Kondo, Z. Philips, R. Sadler, T. Stewart, and D. Zaratzian were invaluable assistants. This work was supported by funding from the Ralph W. Schreiber Ornithology Research Award (Los Angeles Audubon Society); the Department of Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology, University of California (UC), Santa Barbara, through a Worster Award to L.M.; and the National Science Foundation (grant nos. 0446371 to S.I.R. and IOS-0750540 to J.C.W.). J.C.W. also acknowledges support from the Endowment in Physiology, UC, Davis. Birds were captured under L.M.'s U.S. Geological Survey bird-banding permit no. 23469 and California Department of Fish and Game scientific collecting permit no. SCP-8726. All procedures were approved for use by UC Santa Barbara's Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC protocol no. 185). ImageJ software is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html</ext-link>.Male Red-winged Blackbird engaging in a territorial display. Photo credit: Loren MerrillLinear regression for date of capture and bacteria-killing ability against <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. coli</named-content></italic> for adult male Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 15). Dashed lines indicate 95&percnt; confidence interval, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.Relation between epaulet size and bacteria-killing ability against <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. coli</named-content></italic> in adult male Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 15) using a general linear model with tarsus length and date included as covariates. Dashed lines indicate 95&percnt; confidence interval, and <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.Relation between log corticosterone (CORT) (ng mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>) and bacteria-killing ability against <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. coli</named-content></italic> in adult male Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 13) using a general linear model with date included as a covariate. Dashed lines indicate 95&percnt; confidence interval, and <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04.