Photoperiodic conditions affect the level of locomotory activity during autumn migration in the Long-tailed Tit (<italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>)Maintenance of family connections in migrating Long-tailed Tits (<italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>): The ringing data from Northwest RussiaPhotoperiodically regulated cycle of locomotory activity and fat reserves during migration seasons in the irruptive bird species, the Long-tailed Tit <italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>Autumn migration speed of juvenile Reed and Sedge warblers in relation to date and fat loadsDie quantitative Erfassung der Zugunruhe bei Tagziehern: Eine Pilotstudie an Ammern (<italic>Emberiza</italic>)The endogenous control of bird migration: A survey of experimental evidenceThe control of migration in European warblersSpatiotemporal programmes and genetics of orientationEvaluation of energetic parameters of birds in the fieldAre ecological differences of irruptive bird species from typical migrants real? (The example of the Long-tailed Tit <italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>)Body mass, moult and migration speed of the Goldcrest <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Regulus regulus</named-content></italic> in relation to the timing of migration at different sites of the migration routeDependence of postjuvenile moult on hatching date, condition and sex in the Great TitTiming of autumn migration of early and late-hatched Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> in NW RussiaAutumn migratory fuelling: A response to simulated magnetic displacements in juvenile Wheatears, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Oenanthe oenanthe</named-content></italic>North magnetic displacements trigger endogenous fuelling responses in a na&iuml;ve bird migrantFlexibility of timing of avian migration to climate change masked by environmental constraints en routeExperimental determination of the photoperiodic basis for geographical variation in avian seasonalityCircadian control of nocturnal songbird migrationSeasonal pre-migratory fattening and increased activity in a nomadic and irruptive migrant, the Red Crossbill <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Loxia curvirostra</named-content></italic>Under a neighbour's influence: Public information affects stress hormones and behaviour of a songbirdPhotoperiodic control of seasonality in birdsAutumnal premigratory and migratory periods in the Chaffinch (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Fringilla coelebs</named-content> coelebs</italic>) and some other temperate-zone passerine birdsSpeed of migration and migratory flight lengths of passerine birds ringed during autumn migration in SwedenPhotoperiodicity, circannual and reproductive cyclesTiming and speed of migration in North and West European populations of <italic>Sylvia</italic> warblersMagnetic cues trigger extensive refuellingStopover decision during migration: Physiological conditions predict nocturnal restlessness in wild passerinesFood availability but not melatonin affects nocturnal restlessness in a wild migrating passerineAktivit&auml;tsuntersuchungen an Tagziehern (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Carduelis carduelis</named-content></italic>)Locomotory activity of day-migrating finchesCircannual rhythms in the control of avian migrationPhotoperiod as a modifying and limiting factor in the expression of avian circannual rhythmsCircannual rhythms in bird migration: Control of temporal patterns and interactions with photoperiodCircadian and circannual programmes in avian migrationEndogenously controlled changes in migratory direction of the Garden Warbler, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia borin</named-content></italic>The migratory time program of the Garden Warbler: Is there compensation for interruptions?Adaptive specialization, conditional plasticity and phylogenetic history in the reproductive cue response systems of birdsMigratory orientation of Blackcaps (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia atricapilla</named-content></italic>): Population-specific shifts of direction during the autumnCarry-over effects of day length during spring migrationAnnual rhythms that underlie phenology: Biological time-keeping meets environmental changeGeomagnetic field affects spring migratory direction in a long distance migrantBehavioural and physiological reactions to environmental variation in bird migration: A reviewDie Sonnenorientierung der V&ouml;gel. Verhandlungen der Deutschen Zoologischen Gesellschaft, Zoologischer AnzeigerFuelling decisions in migratory birds: Geomagnetic cues override the seasonal effectMagnetic cues and time of season affect fuel deposition in migratory Thrush Nightingales (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Luscinia luscinia</named-content></italic>)Migratory restlessness in the Yellow-faced Honeyeater <italic>Lichenostomus chrysops</italic> (Meliphagidae), an Australian diurnal migrantObligate and facultative migration in birds: Ecological aspectsIntraspecific variation of moult: Adaptive significance and the ways of realizationOrientation of starlings after displacement to SpainEnvironmental conditions affect the behavior of captive migratory White-crowned SparrowsPhysiological and behavioral responses of migrants to environmental cuesTiming of bird migration in relation to weatherFuel deposition of three passerine bird species along the migration routeBody mass of six long-distance migrant passerine species along the autumn migration routeA comparative characteristic of two successive invasions of the Long-tailed Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aegithalos caudatus</named-content></italic>) in the fall of 1985 and 1986 on the Courish Spit of the Baltic SeaTiming and dynamics of autumn passage of the Long-tailed Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aegithalos caudatus</named-content></italic> on the Courish Spit (Eastern Baltic)Ecophysiological aspects of movements by migrants in the wintering quartersEvidence for a navigational map stretching across the continental U.S. in a migratory songbirdJuvenile songbirds compensate for displacement to oceanic islands during autumn migrationCan clock-and-compass explain the distribution of ringing recoveries of Pied Flycatcher?Avian migrants adjust migration in response to environmental conditions <italic>en route</italic>The shortening of day lengths is known to advance the late-summer and autumn events of the annual cycle preceding migration in late-hatched individuals in order to synchronize the individual cycles of birds that hatched on different dates. However, little is known about how day length influences behavior during autumn migration. Here, we tested the locomotory activity of first-year migrant Long-tailed Tits (<italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>) from northwestern Russia under two different photoperiodic conditions during the autumn migration period. The birds were taken into the experiment after they started their migration in the wild, and assigned to either the control (natural photoperiod) or the experimental group (photoperiod shifted 1 mo ahead to simulate shorter days). In the beginning of the experiment, locomotory activity was the same in both groups. After 3 weeks, however, individuals exposed to the light regime simulating a delay on the migration route (i.e. shorter days) showed higher levels of locomotory activity. This reveals that Long-tailed Tits are photosensitive in October with respect to their migratory behavior, and suggests that migrants may use photoperiod to adjust the speed of migration to their position en route.Se sabe que el acortamiento de la duraci&oacute;n del d&iacute;a acelera los eventos del ciclo anual de fines de verano y oto&ntilde;o que anteceden a la migraci&oacute;n de los individuos tard&iacute;amente eclosionados, de modo de sincronizar los ciclos individuales de las aves que eclosionaron en fechas diferentes. Sin embargo, poco se sabe sobre c&oacute;mo la duraci&oacute;n del d&iacute;a afecta el comportamiento durante la migraci&oacute;n de oto&ntilde;o. Aqu&iacute;, evaluamos la actividad locomotriz de juveniles migrantes del a&ntilde;o de <italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic> del noroeste de Rusia bajo dos condiciones diferentes del foto-per&iacute;odo durante el per&iacute;odo de migraci&oacute;n de oto&ntilde;o. Las aves fueron puestas en condiciones experimentales luego de haber comenzado su migraci&oacute;n en estado silvestre, y fueron asignadas ya sea al grupo control (foto-per&iacute;odo natural) o al experimental (foto-per&iacute;odo desplazado 1 mes hacia adelante para simular d&iacute;as m&aacute;s cortos). Al inicio del experimento, la actividad locomotriz fue la misma en ambos grupos. Luego de 3 semanas, sin embargo, los individuos expuestos al r&eacute;gimen de luz que simulaba una demora en la ruta migratoria (i.e. d&iacute;as m&aacute;s cortos) mostraron niveles m&aacute;s altos de actividad locomotriz. Esto evidencia que los individuos de <italic>A. c. caudatus</italic> son sensibles al foto-per&iacute;odo en octubre con relaci&oacute;n a su comportamiento migratorio y sugiere que los migrantes pueden usar el foto-per&iacute;odo para ajustar la velocidad de la migraci&oacute;n seg&uacute;n su posici&oacute;n en la ruta.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> actividad locomotriz, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aegithalos caudatus</named-content></italic>, foto-per&iacute;odo, inquietud migratoria, migraci&oacute;nMany features of migration in passerine birds have a genetic basis and are endogenously controlled (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner1">Gwinner 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold5">Berthold 1996</xref>). This may be particularly important for juveniles that have no prior experience with the migratory route, and it has been demonstrated that some juveniles have rather complicated innate programs for migration. For example, experiments suggest that inexperienced first-year Garden Warblers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia borin</named-content></italic>) and Blackcaps (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. atricapilla</named-content></italic>) migrate on a certain date in a certain direction for a certain period of time, then change direction and again move according to an endogenous program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner5">Gwinner and Wiltschko 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Helbig1">Helbig et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold4">Berthold 1990</xref>). As a result, birds find themselves in the species-specific wintering area. Such studies support the concept of a &ldquo;map and compass&rdquo; that was suggested more than half a century ago by G. Kramer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Kramer1">Kramer 1953</xref>).However, other studies have shown that the endogenous program itself does not lead birds to their wintering grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Jenni1">Jenni and Schaub 2003</xref>), but rather provides a temporal framework within which other factors determine the variability that is often observed in migratory behavior. Birds experience a broad spectrum of environmental conditions during their migration journeys (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Newton1">Newton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Newton2">2012</xref>). Field studies have suggested that environmental factors such as weather and atmospheric conditions, food availability, and social interactions can affect migratory behavior and introduce variation in flight onset, duration, and direction (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Richardson1">Richardson 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fusani1">Fusani et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fusani2">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Newton1">Newton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Tottrup1">T&oslash;ttrup et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Both1">Both 2010</xref>). The influence of these factors has also been shown experimentally (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fransson1">Fransson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Ramenofsky1">Ramenofsky et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Ramenofsky2">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Cornelius2">Cornelius et al. 2010</xref>).It has been demonstrated, however, that the endogenous time program for migratory activity does not compensate for interruptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner6">Gwinner et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>), which could arise as a consequence of unpredictable weather and feeding conditions. Neither does it allow birds to compensate for a displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Thorup3">Thorup et al. 2000</xref>), which may be caused by wind drift or orientation errors. Experiments on displacement have shown that not only adult birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Perdeck1">Perdeck 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Thorup1">Thorup et al. 2007</xref>), but also yearlings of some species (e.g. the Garden Warbler, Blackcap, and Willow Warbler &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phylloscopus trochilus</named-content></italic>&rsqb;), are able to compensate for longitudinal displacements during their first journey to wintering grounds by changing the direction of their movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Thorup2">Thorup et al. 2011</xref>). If migration distance is determined only by a time program, then considerable variation in the distance covered to the wintering grounds might be expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>). One might assume that birds use external cues to evaluate their position to compensate for interruptions (e.g., to increase the speed of migration) or to time key fueling places and moments (e.g., before a barrier crossing). Indeed, it has been found that at least some species (the Thrush Nightingale &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Luscinia luscinia</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, European Robin &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Erithacus rubecula</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, Northern Wheatear &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Oenanthe oenanthe</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, and Lesser Whitethroat &lsqb;<italic>Sylvia curruca</italic>&rsqb;) can use magnetic cues to define their latitudinal position on the migration route (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fransson2">Fransson et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Kullberg2">Kullberg et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Kullberg1">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bostrom1">Bostr&ouml;m et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bostrom2">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Henshaw1">Henshaw et al. 2010</xref>).Photoperiod acts as a synchronizer of circannual rhythms, which are known to affect the timing of individual migration (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold5">Berthold 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>). For example, late-born individuals, growing up under shorter day lengths than earlier-born conspecifics, complete molt and start autumn migration at an earlier age (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner1">Gwinner 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner2">1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold3">Berthold 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Noskov1">Noskov et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova3">Bojarinova et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova4">2002</xref>). Unlike autumn migration, spring migration, as well as winter molt, is advanced by longer day length (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Farner1">Farner and Gwinner 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Dawson1">Dawson et al. 2001</xref>). Very little is known, however, as to how day length influences birds that are already in a migratory state. In an experimental study of European Stonechats (<italic>Saxicola rubicola</italic>) exposed to different photoperiods during spring migration, it was shown that day length influenced the duration of migratory activity in spring and had carryover effects on the reproductive period, molt, and autumn migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Helm1">Helm and Gwinner 2005</xref>).Summer day length is known to influence the onset of autumn migration in many bird species, compensating for differences in hatching dates. However, it is not clear whether, during the autumn journey, day length acts as a synchronizer of migration of individuals and allows birds to adjust their speed of migration and position en route, or whether it allows birds to compensate for interruptions. Some evidence for the former comes from the analysis of banding recoveries: In a number of long- and short-distance migrants, late-migrating individuals moved faster than early-migrating ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Ellegren1">Ellegren 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fransson1">Fransson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bensch1">Bensch and Nielsen 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova2">Bojarinova et al. 2008</xref>).A positive relationship between the speed of migration and the date of banding has also been recorded for the Northern Long-tailed Tit (<italic>Aegithalos c. caudatus</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Shapoval1">Shapoval 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova1">Bojarinova and Babushkina 2010</xref>). Our recent studies demonstrate that the Northern Long-tailed Tit (hereafter, Long-tailed Tit) has an annual cycle of migratory restlessness that is exhibited in captivity and is influenced by photoperiod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). It is noteworthy that individuals that experienced a photoperiod simulating late hatching showed a significantly higher level of activity in autumn compared with their siblings that were kept on a photoperiod simulating early hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). However, it was not possible to separate an effect of light regime preceding the migration period from an effect of day length during the migration itself on the locomotory activity of birds. We tested the latter hypothesis on Long-tailed Tits captured during migration by exposing them to different day lengths immediately after catching. If the hypothesis is true that day length during migration itself influences locomotory activity, then shortening the day length during the migration period should cause an increase in locomotory activity.We studied the locomotory activity of 16 captive first-year Long-tailed Tits from mid-October to early January of the following year. The birds were trapped during the beginning of autumn passage on October 1 and 3, 2006, at the Ladoga Ornithological Station, northwestern Russia (60.41&deg;N, 32.57&deg;E), and represented 2 separately migrating flocks of 10 and 6 individuals, respectively. All of the Long-tailed Tits taken into the experiment were still molting some body feathers, which suggested that all of the individuals were near the start of their autumn migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova1">Bojarinova and Babushkina 2010</xref>). The age of trapped birds was checked by examination of the skull (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Svensson1">Svensson 1992</xref>): In first-year Long-tailed Tits, the skull is not completely ossified in early October. The birds from each of the 2 flocks were randomly distributed between 2 experimental groups. From October 6, when the photoperiod for both groups was the same (11 light:13 dark hours &lsqb;11L:13D&rsqb;), these 2 groups were kept under different photoperiodic conditions, both corresponding to 60&deg;N, but with a time shift for the second group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Group 1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 8) was kept under the natural photoperiod for 60&deg;N, decreasing from 11L:13D. By November 28, the day length was 7.5L:16.5D, and it was then kept constant at 7.5L:16.5D until early January. This day length is the minimum for a latitude of 55&deg;N. Group 2 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 8) was kept under photoperiodic conditions shifted 1 mo ahead, thus simulating a delay on the migration route. On October 6, the day length for this group was shortened from 11 hr (11L:13D) to 8 hr (8L:16D). It was then decreased to 7.5L:16.5D by October 28 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f01">Figure 1</xref>) and held constant until early January.Day length changes experienced by Long-tailed Tits from northwestern Russia held in captivity under two different photoperiodic conditions during the period of October 2006&ndash;January 2007. The two photoperiods were a natural photoperiod and a photoperiod shifted 1 mo ahead to simulate a delay on the migration route.According to banding recoveries, Long-tailed Tits migrate in flocks of constant composition. For instance, for the Ladoga Ornithological Station in northwestern Russia, 17 such cases are known, when from 2 to 7 birds (average 3.9 &plusmn; 0.4 SE) banded together were later recovered together in other places in Europe at an average distance of 806 km &plusmn; 60 km (SE) away (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina1">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2009</xref>). So, by taking birds simultaneously, in the same molting state, and from only 2 flocks, we minimized possible sources of variation in their activity at the outset.We did not, however, make a photoperiod correction to account for southward displacement of birds during migration. The speed of migration in the Long-tailed Tit according to banding results is rather low and variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova1">Bojarinova and Babushkina 2010</xref>), making such displacements very difficult to predict for this species. Thus, we think that our day length regimes corresponding to different dates at the same latitude were a reasonable first approximation.We used the same experimental equipment and procedure as in our previous study of the locomotory activity in Long-tailed Tits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). The birds were surveyed by a video recording system, consisting of video cameras connected to a computer with a VN4-Power interface board and the RVN-SDR program of VideoNet (Pentakon-Spb, Skyros, Saint Petersburg, Russia), and specially designed image processing software. One video camera was placed above each experimental cage. The interface board allowed a capture rate of 10 frames s<sup>&minus;1</sup> for each cage.The Long-tailed Tit is a social species and it is impossible to house experimental birds individually without significantly affecting their behavior (O. Babushkina personal observation). However, a previous study showed that 2 individuals could be successfully kept in 1 cage without affecting each other's locomotory activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). The 2 birds in each cage were individually marked with nontoxic solutions of brilliant green or rhodamine. Marks were put on the head and the breast of each bird. The recording system allowed independent data acquisition: The image processing software was able to recognize 2 moving objects online, distinguish them by color (green or red), and record their coordinates within the cage as a function of time.The Long-tailed Tit is a diurnal migrant, and the locomotory activity in this experiment was recorded only in daytime. At the &ldquo;Fringilla&rdquo; field site on the Courish Spit of the Baltic Sea, no Long-tailed Tits were captured at night during &sim;50 yr of trapping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Sokolov1">Sokolov et al. 2004</xref>). Similar observations have come from the Ladoga Ornithological Station, northwestern Russia, during 25 yr of trapping (J. Bojarinova personal observation). We have never recorded nighttime activity by this species in our previous experiments during the migration period (3 yr of study), even when Long-tailed Tits were kept in conditions of night lighting (up to 1 lux at nighttime, corresponding to full moonlight intensity). The birds went to sleep immediately after switching off the day light, roosting together in groups (or, in the case of only 2 birds, in pairs), and did not produce any calls or other signs of activity during the time of darkness.The experimental room that was fitted out with lighting and automatically controlled day length was divided into 2 parts by a nontransparent black curtain. Cages that were being recorded were installed on one side, while the second part housed the experimental group that was not being filmed. Video recording was performed between October 19, 2006, and January 12, 2007. During the simulated daytime the light intensity was &sim;300&ndash;350 lux. We did not organize any special night lighting for the experiment. Some weak, dispersed light came from the light-emitting diodes on the equipment, so the intensity of light during the nighttime in our experiment was &sim;0.002 lux. The 2 experimental groups were recorded in turn; the duration of continuous recording for each group was 2&ndash;3 days. The interval between recording periods for each group was 4&ndash;6 days. The total number of recording periods for each group was 12, and comprised 28 days for group 1 and 27 days for group 2. The activity of all birds from each group was recorded simultaneously during the recording intervals. All 8 birds (4 pairs) of each group were put into cages at the same time 1 day before the start of data collection and kept there until the end of the interval. Pairs of birds were kept stable during the whole experiment and were placed into the same cages every time. Since the Long-tailed Tit is known to be only a diurnal migrant, the video-recording system was in operation only in the daytime, and the time of recording was automatically controlled according to experimental light conditions.All the birds were provided with food (a homemade mix of mashed boiled eggs with grated carrots, mealworms &lsqb;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tenebrio molitor</named-content></italic>&rsqb;, and a mix for insectivorous birds &lsqb;Padovan Gr&acirc;nPat&eacute;e insectes; VALMAN s.l.r., Vicenza, Italy&rsqb;) and water ad libitum.Fat deposition determinations were made just after trapping (on October 1 and October 3 for the different flocks), on October 5 and 11, and then before and after each recording interval at approximately the same time in the afternoon. Fat reserves were estimated by scoring the amount of subcutaneous fat deposited within the furculum of the clavicle, under the wing, and in the abdominal region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Blyumental1">Blyumental and Dolnik 1962</xref>) by means of a system of 10 classes: 1 &equals; no visible fat, 2 &equals; a trace of fat, 3 &equals; base of tracheal pit obscured by fat but less than half full, 4 &equals; tracheal pit half full, 5 &equals; tracheal pit more than half full, 6 &equals; fat filling the tracheal pit but still a little bit below the level of the clavicle, 7 &equals; fat filling the tracheal pit but not bulging, 8 &equals; fat filling tracheal pit and bulging, 9 &equals; fat bulging and overlying pectoral muscle, and 10 &equals; extra fat bird, fat bulging in the area of the furculum of the clavicle, under the wing, and in the abdominal region. For each recording interval, we analyzed the average fat score within those dates.Only a few studies have been conducted on migratory restlessness in diurnal migrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Dolnik1">Dolnik and Blyumental 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold1">Berthold 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gluck1">Gl&uuml;ck 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Munro1">Munro and Munro 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Cornelius1">Cornelius and Hahn 2012</xref>). It is not always easy to separate restlessness from other activities in such species, and some authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gluck2">Gl&uuml;ck 1982</xref>) have tried to define it using indirect calculations.Our approach is based on the results of our previous long-term experiment, when we recorded the locomotory activity of Long-tailed Tits for about a year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). In that experiment, the locomotory activity of birds increased greatly along with changes in fat reserves in accordance with the migration seasons of the species. The level of activity relevant to autumn and spring migration was more than eight times higher than the initial activity level in August (before the migration period). These findings indicate that seasonal changes of activity exhibited by caged Long-tailed Tits reflect migratory restlessness (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref> for discussion), similarly to what was found earlier for many night-migrating species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner3">Gwinner 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold5">Berthold 1996</xref>).Using the actual distance covered by birds inside the cage instead of the traditional measure of the number of hops allows for a more accurate estimation of migratory behavior, because hops do not include movements made on the floor or sides of the cage. Such an approach is very important for recording the activity of diurnal migrants, which combine migratory activity with feeding activity during the migratory period. The camera was placed above the cage and vertical movements from perch to feeder contributed little to the total covered distance. Thus, the value of distance covered by a bird in our study reflects mostly the rise in migratory activity, since the distance to the feeder was rather short compared with the distance between perches and other possible paths of movement. Since the length of the day changed during the experimental period, the locomotory activity of caged Long-tailed Tits was expressed in terms of the distance covered per hour, averaged across all daylight hours. For each recording interval (2&ndash;3 days), we calculated the individual averages per day. From these values, an average value per group with its standard error was calculated for each recording interval.Statistical analysis was performed following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Sokal1">Sokal and Rohlf (1998)</xref>. First, we tested whether the activity of each of the 2 birds in 1 cage influenced the other's behavior (&ldquo;neighbor&rdquo; effect) using a correlation analysis. We also looked for correlations in activity per recording interval (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 12) across all possible pairs of birds in each group (independent of whether they were kept in the same or different cages, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 28). We found a significant correlation for only 1 cage out of 4 for each group (for cages of group 1: <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.50, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.09; <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.28, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.37; <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.20, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.54; <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.83, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.001; for cages of group 2: <italic>r</italic> &equals; &minus;0.45, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.13; <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.29, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.36; <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.38, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.22; <italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.66, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02). There were 8 cases of significant correlation (also negative and positive) between birds housed in different cages in group 1, and 4 such cases in group 2. These correlations in activity (for birds in the same and different cages) may have been due to the fact that the birds in each group were subjected to the same photoperiod, which might have affected their activity. To avoid this effect, we performed the same analysis for residues after subtracting mean activity across the group (birds subjected to the same photoperiod) for each date. We then found only 1 significant correlation for birds within the same cage and 13 significant correlations between birds from different cages. We concluded that placing 2 birds in 1 cage did not result in enhanced correlation of their activity, and therefore that all of the birds could enter the overall analyses individually. However, we also performed ANOVA for activity averaged over the 2 birds in each cage.The values of locomotory activity were found to be normally distributed (Shapiro-Wilks test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05). The variation in locomotory activity was studied using Student's <italic>t</italic>-test and repeated-measures ANOVA, including recording interval as a within-subject variable and group and flock as between-subject variables. Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic>-tests were used for comparing the relative increase in activity and for comparing fat reserves between birds from different flocks. Wilcoxon's signed-rank test (paired test) was used to compare fat loads during the experiment.All tests were performed with Statistica 7.1 (StatSoft, Tulsa, Oklahoma, USA). Means are reported with their standard errors.The Long-tailed Tits in each of the two groups showed similar levels of activity in the beginning of the experiment (October 19&ndash;23; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f02">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Average daily locomotory activity in Long-tailed Tits was affected by photoperiod (belonging to different groups) during the autumn migration period and by date (recording interval; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f03">Figure 3</xref>). The birds kept under the experimentally shifted photoperiod showed higher levels of activity compared with the individuals kept under a natural day length. No significant effect of the factor &ldquo;flock&rdquo; was found (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 0.94, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.35). Averaging the activity of the two birds in each cage did not change the result: Activity was significantly affected by photoperiod (i.e. group) (repeated-measures ANOVA: group, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,6</sub> &equals; 7.77, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.032; recording interval, <italic>F</italic><sub>11,66</sub> &equals; 2.28, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.02; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f03">Figure 3</xref>).Examples of activity diagrams obtained from 2 Long-tailed Tits from northwestern Russia from different groups held in captivity during the period of October 2006&ndash;January 2007: (<bold>A</bold>) group 1 (natural photoperiod); (<bold>B</bold>) group 2 (experimental photoperiod, shifted 1 mo ahead). See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f01">Figure 1</xref> for photoperiods for each group. Activity is presented as the distance covered by a bird in 15 min. The 12 intervals on the right represent the recording intervals for each group; the 2 experimental groups were recorded in turn, hence the offset dates for each group in each recording interval. Time on the <italic>x</italic> axis represents the 24-hr clock, where 00 &equals; 00:00, and 20 &equals; 20:00.Variation in average distance covered per hour by caged Long-tailed Tits from northwestern Russia recorded during all daylight hours under different light regimes during the period of October 2006&ndash;January 2007. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f01">Figure 1</xref> for photoperiods for each group. For each recording interval the figure shows the mean value for the distance covered &plusmn; SE. The results of repeated-measures ANOVA were: group, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 10.70, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.007; flock, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,12</sub> &equals; 0.94, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.35; recording interval, <italic>F</italic><sub>11,132</sub> &equals; 1.93, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04. The interactions between factors were not significant.The divergence in locomotory activity between the 2 groups occurred during the third week after exposure to different photoregimes (October 6). After 2 weeks (October 19&ndash;23), the levels of activity were the same in both groups (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic> &equals; 0.45, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.66; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f03">Figure 3</xref>). However, on the 23<sup>rd</sup> day of the experiment (October 30&ndash;31), the difference between groups was highly significant (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic> &equals; 2.87, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.012).A distinct increase in activity from the first (October 19&ndash;23) to the second (October 26&ndash;31) recording interval was recorded for all birds of group 2, whereas in group 1 an increase was observed in only 5 birds out of 8. Two birds out of the remaining 3 showed some increase in activity in the beginning of November (November 3&ndash;7, recording interval 3), and 1 in mid-November (November 10&ndash;15, recording interval 4). The relative rise in the activity levels of individual birds from October 19&ndash;23 to October 26&ndash;31 differed significantly between the 2 groups (for group1: <italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 0.08 &plusmn; 0.07, from &minus;0.24 to 0.42; for group 2: <italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 0.43 &plusmn; 0.11, from 0.07 to 0.97; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test, <italic>U</italic> &equals; 9, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.018).For group 1, average activity peaked in late November (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f03">Figure 3</xref>), before the photoperiod reached its minimum of 7.5L:16.5D, and then started to decrease gradually (from November 19&ndash;23 to January 6&ndash;11, regression analysis, linear model: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,5</sub> &equals; 7.02, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.046). For group 2, under simulation of a delay on the migration route, average activity increased significantly at the end of October, just after the decrease of day length to its winter minimum. However, the locomotory activity in this group did not decline before the end of the experiment in the beginning of January, except for a temporary decrease between November 19 and 23 (from October 26&ndash;31 to January 6&ndash;11, regression analysis, linear model: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,9</sub> &equals; 1.16, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.31). In both groups, activity remained high in December, when the wintering period for Long-tailed Tits starts in nature.No significant difference was found in fat reserves between the 2 flocks on the day of trapping (Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test, <italic>U</italic> &equals; 39.5, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.31). The pattern of changes and values of fat reserves was similar in the 2 groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f04">Figure 4</xref>), and was in good accordance with the data on fat loads in autumn reported in our previous study of the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). We recorded some increase in fat loads during the second part of October. However, the increase was significant only when comparing fat reserves from the trapping day and the end of October (October 26&ndash;31) (Wilcoxon's signed-rank test: group 1, <italic>T<sub>s</sub></italic> &equals; 1.97, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.049; group 2, <italic>T<sub>s</sub></italic> &equals; 2.03, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.041).Variation in fat reserves of two experimental groups of Long-tailed Tits from northwestern Russia held in captivity during the period of October 2006&ndash;January 2007, before the start of activity recording and during recording intervals. For each recording interval the figure shows the mean value &plusmn; SE. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-f01">Figure 1</xref> for photoperiods for each group.Adaptive modification of the endogenous time program by photoperiod is well known (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold5">Berthold 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Coppack1">Coppack 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Coppack2">Coppack and Bairlein 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Helm2">Helm et al. 2013</xref>). In late summer and autumn there are two main effects of experimental photoperiod manipulations in long- and short-distance migrants: the onset and duration of postjuvenile molt and the onset of autumn migration, both of which are advanced by short days (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner1">Gwinner 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner2">1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold3">Berthold 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Noskov1">Noskov et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova3">Bojarinova et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova4">2002</xref>).In our experiment, modification of day length during autumn migration affected the level of diurnal locomotory activity in the Long-tailed Tit: Shortening of the day length led to an increase in activity. It is important to note that the birds used in this experiment were known to be in a migratory state at the time of capture and at the beginning of the experiment. The results therefore demonstrate that Long-tailed Tits are photosensitive during migration. They may have been showing photorefractoriness with respect to reproductive competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Hahn1">Hahn and MacDougall-Shackleton 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Helm2">Helm et al. 2013</xref>), but they were photosensitive with respect to their migratory behavior.Although previous studies have suggested that day length influences the activity of birds in the migratory state during autumn, it has been difficult to distinguish a prolonged effect of the light regime preceding the migratory period from that of the day length during migration itself. For example, Garden Warblers kept under constant conditions during the period of autumn migration showed prolonged and flattened migratory restlessness in comparison with birds kept under a shorter constant day length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold2">Berthold 1984</xref>). However, this species has also been shown to respond to long photoperiods by terminating migratory restlessness at the end of the autumn migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner 1996</xref>). It was suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Gwinner4">Gwinner (1996)</xref> that a regulatory mechanism may change during the journey to the wintering grounds, so that long photoperiods induce termination of migration rather than acting to prolong it.Band recoveries for a number of long- and short-distance migrants have demonstrated that the speed of migration increases with the progress of the season: Late-migrating birds move faster than early-migrating ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Ellegren1">Ellegren 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Fransson1">Fransson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bensch1">Bensch and Nielsen 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova2">Bojarinova et al. 2008</xref>). Migrating faster, however, requires larger fuel loads and fewer stopovers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Schaub1">Schaub and Jenni 2000a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Schaub2">2000b</xref>). A positive relationship between the speed of migration and the date of banding, as well as an increase in body resources during migration, has been recorded for the Long-tailed Tit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Shapoval1">Shapoval 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bojarinova1">Bojarinova and Babushkina 2010</xref>). It has also been shown that Northern Wheatears increase their fuel reserves when exposed to a northern magnetic displacement compared with conspecifics kept in the local geomagnetic field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Bostrom2">Bostr&ouml;m et al. 2012</xref>). This supports the idea that the endogenous migration program of this species involves a seasonal fueling response that is latitudinal and is sensitive to magnetic cues.Length of the day depends on both calendar date and latitude, and day length decreases more quickly after the autumn equinox at higher latitudes. It cannot be ruled out that migratory birds use a combination of circannual clocks and photoperiod perceived during their autumn migration as a timing cue for migratory movements. Such cues may trigger, for example, an increase in locomotory activity in late migrants, or may allow for adjustments after unexpected delays on the migration route. The results of our experiment suggest that the photoperiod (and/or probably the rate of change) experienced by birds may affect their migratory activity during their journey, and may be used by migrants to adjust the speed of their migration to the date and to their position on the route.Our experiment showed that, for both groups, activity was still at a high level in December, after the end of the normal migration period, which is in accordance with results from our previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Babushkina2">Babushkina and Bojarinova 2011</xref>). A similar pattern was found for another diurnal migrant, the Yellow-faced Honeyeater (<italic>Lichenostomus chrysops</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Munro1">Munro and Munro 1998</xref>). Such prolonged autumn migratory activity in caged birds, also observed in a number of regular nocturnal migrants (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Terrill1">Terrill 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Berthold5">Berthold 1996</xref>), may be a result of keeping birds in conditions (e.g., geomagnetic field, photoperiod, or a combination of different factors) that prevent termination of migratory restlessness. In the case of the Long-tailed Tit, it is also possible that this pattern reflects movements within the wintering area. In group 2 (kept under a shifted photoperiod), the level of locomotory activity was higher than that of group 1 up to the end of the experiment in early January. The reason for such a prolonged effect of short photoperiod experienced by birds at the beginning of migration is still not clear. However, carryover effects of day-length conditions during migration have been found for another species: In captive European Stonechats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-370-Helm1">Helm and Gwinner 2005</xref>), spring photoperiods affected the dynamics and duration of migratory restlessness and the reproductive window.In conclusion, in this study we experimentally showed that a modification of day length during autumn migration affected the level of diurnal locomotory activity in caged Long-tailed Tits that were already in a migratory state. Shortening of the day length led to an increase in activity. These results demonstrate that Long-tailed Tits are photosensitive during migration and may use photoperiod as a cue to adjust migration speed en route.This work would have been impossible without the technical support provided by Kirill Kavokin and Petr Pak. Many thanks are due to Tatiana Rymkevich for stimulating discussions, to Dmitry Starikov for help with keeping birds, to Jamie Cornelius for helpful comments on earlier drafts of the paper, and to three anonymous reviewers for valuable comments.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This study was funded by Russian Foundation for Basic Research grant nos. 09-04-01087a and 13-04-01474a, and Saint-Petersburg State University research grant 1.37.149.2014. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript. None of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> In our experiments we adhered to the current legislation of the Russian Federation and the institutional guidelines of Saint-Petersburg State University.