An experimental test of host song mimicry as a species recognition cue among male brood parasitic indigobirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp.)Song discrimination suggests premating isolation among sympatric indigobird species and host racesThe characteristics and context of imprintingFunctional aspects of song learning in songbirdsControlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testingNonparametric methods in factorial designsSympatric host race formation and speciation in frugivorous flies of the genus <italic>Rhagoletis</italic> (Diptera, Tephritidae)Ecological approaches to species recognition in birds through studies of model and non-model speciesConspecific recognition by juvenile Brown-headed CowbirdsDNA fingerprint similarity between female and juvenile Brown-headed Cowbirds trapped togetherFirst contact: A role for adult-offspring social association in the species recognition system of brood parasitesSelf-referent phenotype matching in a brood parasite: The armpit effect in Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>)A password for species recognition in a brood-parasitic birdDiscrimination between host songs by brood parasitic Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>)Sexual and other long term aspects of imprinting in birds and other speciesExtension of mulitple range test to group means with unequal numbers of replicationSuggested experimental designs for song playbacksDer kumpan in der umwelt des v&ouml;gelsDer brutparasitismus der Viduinae als ethologisches problemContemporary cultural evolution of a conspecific recognition signal following serial translocationsBehavior, mimetic songs and song dialects, and relationships of the parasitic indigobirds (<italic>Vidua</italic>) of AfricaSong structure, behaviour, and sequence of song types in a population of Village Indigobirds, <italic>Vidua chalybeata</italic>Behavioral continuity and change in local song populations of Village Indigobirds <italic>Vidua chalybeata</italic>Field identification of the indigobirdsSpecies status and distribution of the parasitic indigobirds <italic>Vidua</italic> in east and southern AfricaSong learning in brood-parasitic indigobirds <italic>Vidua chalybeata</italic>: Song mimicry of the host speciesImprinting and the origin of parasite-host species associations in brood-parasitic indigobirds, <italic>Vidua chalybeata</italic>Genetic continuity of brood-parasitic indigobird speciesNonparametric analysis of ordinal data in designed factorial experimentsAn analysis of variance test for normality (complete samples)Innate versus learned recognition of conspecifics in Great Spotted Cuckoos <italic>Clamator glandarius</italic>Speciation by host switch in brood parasitic indigobirdsInstinct, with original observations on young animalsResponses of nesting Song Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melospiza melodia</named-content></italic>) and Red-winged Blackbirds (<italic>Agelaius phoneiceus</italic>) to models of parasitic cowbirds and nonthreatening towheesObligate brood parasites, which typically lack reliable interactions with conspecifics early in life, acquire species recognition cues by mechanisms other than imprinting on parents and siblings. The African indigobirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp.) are exceptional among brood parasites in that learning and mimicry of host vocalizations play an integral role in the social behavior of the parasites. Male indigobirds have impressive vocal repertoires featuring chatter calls, host mimicry, and complex non-mimicry songs. While chatter calls are similar, sympatric indigobirds are distinguished both by their mimicry of different hosts and by unique repertoires of non-mimicry songs. A previous playback experiment showed that male indigobirds respond differentially to natural singing (i.e. playbacks including host mimicry, chatter, and complex non-mimicry) of sympatric conspecifics and heterospecifics, but the relative role of host mimicry and complex non-mimicry in species recognition remains unknown. We addressed this question in a playback experiment that tested the response of focal males to 3 treatments: sympatric conspecific, allopatric conspecific (same host mimicry combined with unfamiliar complex non-mimicry songs), and sympatric heterospecific (different host mimicry and different, but familiar, complex non-mimicry). Three behavioral responses (number of hops, latency of response, and number of chatter calls) were similar in the 2 conspecific treatments but differed in comparison with the heterospecific treatment. Our study provides evidence that host mimicry is an important cue in species recognition among territorial male indigobirds and suggests that it may contribute to species cohesion when juveniles or adults disperse beyond the boundaries of their local dialect neighborhood. This study enhances our understanding of avian recognition systems by showing that cues obtained through heterospecific imprinting can be important for species recognition in brood parasitic birds.Les parasites de nich&eacute;e obligatoires, qui n'ont g&eacute;n&eacute;ralement pas de relations fiables avec leurs cong&eacute;n&egrave;res t&ocirc;t dans leur vie, acqui&egrave;rent les signaux de reconnaissance sp&eacute;cifique par des m&eacute;canismes autres que l'impr&eacute;gnation parentale et fraternelle. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp. sont exceptionnels parmi les parasites de nich&eacute;e par la fa&ccedil;on dont l'apprentissage et le mim&eacute;tisme des vocalisations de l'h&ocirc;te jouent un r&ocirc;le int&eacute;gral dans le comportement social des parasites. Les m&acirc;les de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp. poss&egrave;dent d'impressionnants r&eacute;pertoires vocaux comportant le caqu&egrave;tement, le mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te et des chants complexes sans mim&eacute;tisme. Alors que le caqu&egrave;tement est similaire, les individus sympatriques se distinguent par leur mim&eacute;tisme des diff&eacute;rents h&ocirc;tes et leur r&eacute;pertoire unique de chants sans mim&eacute;tisme. Une exp&eacute;rience ant&eacute;rieure de repasse de chants a montr&eacute; que les m&acirc;les r&eacute;pondent diff&eacute;remment au chant naturel (c.-&agrave;-d. des repasses de chants incluant le mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te, le caqu&egrave;tement et le non-mim&eacute;tisme complexe) de cong&eacute;n&egrave;res et individus h&eacute;t&eacute;rosp&eacute;cifiques sympatriques, mais le r&ocirc;le relatif du mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te et le non-mim&eacute;tisme complexe dans la reconnaissance sp&eacute;cifique demeure inconnu. Nous avons abord&eacute; cette question dans une exp&eacute;rience de repasse de chants qui testait la r&eacute;ponse des m&acirc;les &agrave; trois traitements : cong&eacute;n&egrave;re sympatrique, cong&eacute;n&egrave;re allopatrique (m&ecirc;me mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te combin&eacute; &agrave; des chants de non-mim&eacute;tisme complexe auxquels ils ne sont pas familiers) et h&eacute;t&eacute;rosp&eacute;cifique sympatrique (mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te diff&eacute;rent et non-mim&eacute;tisme complexe diff&eacute;rent mais familier). Trois r&eacute;ponses comportementales (nombre de sautillements, d&eacute;lai de la r&eacute;ponse et nombre de caqu&egrave;tements) &eacute;taient similaires dans les deux traitements de la m&ecirc;me esp&egrave;ce mais diff&eacute;rents en comparaison au traitement h&eacute;t&eacute;rosp&eacute;cifique. Notre &eacute;tude fournit des preuves que le mim&eacute;tisme de l'h&ocirc;te est un signal important dans la reconnaissance sp&eacute;cifique entre les m&acirc;les territoriaux de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp. et sugg&egrave;re que cela peut contribuer &agrave; la coh&eacute;sion sp&eacute;cifique lorsque les juv&eacute;niles ou les adultes se dispersent au-del&agrave; des fronti&egrave;res de leur voisinage de dialecte local. Cette &eacute;tude am&eacute;liore notre compr&eacute;hension des syst&egrave;mes de reconnaissance aviaire en montrant que les signaux obtenus par impr&eacute;gnation h&eacute;t&eacute;rosp&eacute;cifique peuvent &ecirc;tre importants pour la reconnaissance sp&eacute;cifique chez les oiseaux parasites de nich&eacute;e.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> parasitisme de nich&eacute;e, reconnaissance sp&eacute;cifique, repasse de chants, impr&eacute;gnation, mim&eacute;tisme, <italic>Vidua</italic>In most birds, highly predictable interactions with parents and siblings allow the reliable acquisition of species recognition cues and mate preferences based on associations formed during filial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Spalding1">Spalding 1873</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Lorenz1">Lorenz 1935</xref>) and sexual imprinting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Bateson1">Bateson 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Immelmann1">Immelmann 1972</xref>). In contrast, obligate brood parasites typically lack the opportunity to interact with conspecifics early in life and have likely evolved alternative mechanisms for the development of species recognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Goth1">G&ouml;th and Hauber 2004</xref>). Observations and experiments suggest several possibilities, including self-referencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Graham1">Graham and Middleton 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hauber2">Hauber et al. 2000</xref>), innate attraction to conspecific vocalizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hauber3">Hauber et al. 2001</xref>), post-fledging social interactions with conspecific adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hahn1">Hahn and Fleischer 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Soler1">Soler and Soler 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hauber1">Hauber 2002</xref>), and aggressive interactions with heterospecific adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Strausberger1">Strausberger and Horning 1998</xref>). These mechanisms, which encompass both innate and learned behaviors, are not mutually exclusive. For example, juvenile Brown-headed Cowbirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Molothrus ater</named-content></italic>) are drawn to the cowbird &ldquo;chatter&rdquo; call, which may serve as an innate &ldquo;password&rdquo; for species recognition, allowing juveniles to identify conspecific tutors for subsequent social learning of song and other species recognition cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hauber3">Hauber et al. 2001</xref>).A similar mechanism likely contributes to song learning in the parasitic whydahs and indigobirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vidua</named-content></italic> spp.), which are exceptional among brood parasitic birds in that early imprinting on heterospecific hosts shapes adult vocal behavior and mating preferences. Singing male indigobirds, for example, are well known for mimicking the songs and other vocalizations of their respective hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Nicolai1">Nicolai 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne6">Payne et al. 1998</xref>). Because each indigobird species generally parasitizes a single estrildid finch species, this results in nonoverlapping host mimicry repertoires among heterospecific indigobird males (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>). Female indigobirds also imprint on their hosts, as evidenced by their preference for mates that mimic their own host species and their parasitism of nests belonging to that same host species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne7">Payne et al. 2000</xref>). These behaviors result in the maintenance of host specificity within indigobird species and of premating reproductive isolation among species, while also providing a mechanism for rapid speciation by host shift (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Sefc1">Sefc et al. 2005</xref>).Beyond host mimicry, indigobird males also produce &ldquo;chatter&rdquo; calls, comprising a rapid sequence of broadband notes, and have impressive repertoires of complex non-mimicry songs that may contribute to species recognition. The chatter calls of individual males are variable in overall length and in the duration and spacing of individual notes, and different indigobird species are broadly overlapping in these traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>). Thus, chatter may serve as a general &ldquo;password&rdquo; for the recognition of male indigobirds, regardless of species. The vocal repertoires of individual males also include 10&ndash;20 &ldquo;complex non-mimicry&rdquo; songs that are shared among local conspecifics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>).The degree of overlap in non-mimicry songs between 2 individuals is negatively correlated with distance, resulting in song dialect &ldquo;neighborhoods&rdquo; that vary in size depending on habitat continuity and the dispersion of male territories across the landscape (J. M. DaCosta personal observation). Complex non-mimicry songs are subject to rapid cultural evolution as new songs are introduced through the cultural transmission of novel &ldquo;errors&rdquo; and/or innovations and the songs of successful males become more common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne3">Payne 1985</xref>). Note, however, that indigobirds associated with different hosts in a given local area do not share non-mimetic songs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>); males thus copy and/or learn non-mimetic songs only from other males associated with the same host. By delivering a mixture of all these repertoire elements (i.e. chatter, host mimicry, complex non-mimicry), singing male indigobirds likely signal their identity as an indigobird, their host species, and their membership in a local neighborhood.The territorial responses of male indigobirds have been experimentally tested in 2 previous studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson (2006)</xref> measured the response of males to playbacks of natural vocal sequences (i.e. 5-minute recordings including mimicry, chatter, and complex non-mimicry). Males responded strongly only to playbacks from conspecific males associated with the same host species. Playbacks from other local males, however, differed in both mimicry and non-mimicry songs, leaving open the question of how each contributes to eliciting an aggressive response. In an earlier study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne (1973)</xref> recorded the initial response of singing males to the playback of isolated song components. Most focal males flew toward the speaker in response to playback of complex non-mimicry songs, whereas playback of mimicry songs elicited minimal response. For both, responses were similar whether the playback was of the same or a different indigobird species. This lack of differential response is difficult to reconcile with the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson (2006)</xref> but may reflect differences in behavior between West African and southern African indigobirds, less extensive measurement of male responses by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne (1973)</xref>, and/or differences attributable to the playback of individual song components as compared to the complex, multicomponent signal delivered in natural singing (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Hauber4">Hauber et al. 2002</xref>). Thus, the relative role of mimicry and non-mimicry in indigobird species recognition remains uncertain.Resolving this uncertainty is important because dispersing juvenile or adult males may encounter conspecifics that sing the same mimicry songs but entirely different repertoires of complex non-mimicry. Whether these males recognize each other as conspecifics may affect territorial interactions, reproductive success, and, in turn, rates of gene flow, and thus the genetic cohesion of indigobird species across the landscape. To test the relative importance of mimetic and non-mimetic song components in indigobird species recognition, we used natural geographic variation in complex non-mimicry to design an experiment in which natural song sequences including the same mimetic songs combined with either familiar or unfamiliar non-mimetic songs were played back to focal males.We exploited natural geographic variation in the non-mimicry repertoires within indigobird species to design an experiment testing whether mimetic songs, non-mimetic songs, or both are important in indigobird species recognition during male&ndash;male competitive interactions. The experiment included 3 treatments with respect to the focal individual: sympatric conspecific (SC), allopatric conspecific (AC), and sympatric heterospecific (SH). Because male indigobirds typically respond strongly and immediately to the playback of their own songs and display little to no reaction to playback of isolated host mimicry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>) or playbacks of the host firefinches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lagonosticta</named-content></italic> spp.; J. M. DaCosta personal observation), we did not include a &ldquo;neutral&rdquo; non-<italic>Vidua</italic> control treatment (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Parker1">Parker et al. 2010</xref>). Each treatment involved the playback of natural sequences of indigobird males singing (i.e. a mixture of chatter, host mimicry, and complex non-mimicry). Chatter calls are broadly similar across species and therefore did not differ systematically across the 3 treatments.Most indigobird species parasitize a single host species, and individual males mimic the songs of only one host. The mimicry songs for a given indigobird species (or host race) are similar across much larger geographic areas than non-mimicry songs, suggesting much less geographic variation in the songs of hosts. Therefore, with respect to the focal male, the SH treatment included mimicry of a different host, while both the SC and AC treatments included mimicry of the focal male's host (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). Local conspecifics (SC treatment) share most of their complex non-mimicry songs, whereas both heterospecifics and allopatric conspecifics (SH and AC treatments, respectively) have completely nonoverlapping repertoires of complex non-mimicry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f01">Figure 1</xref>B). These 3 treatments thus allowed us to test whether host mimicry or complex non-mimicry is more important in species recognition in the context of male territorial defense. If host mimicry is a primary cue, then we expect similar responses to treatments with the same host mimicry (AC &equals; SC &gt; SH). Conversely, if complex non-mimicry is a primary cue, then we expect similar responses to the 2 treatments with different complex non-mimicry (AC &ne; SC &equals; SH).Representative sonograms illustrating the degree of similarity in (<bold>A</bold>) host mimicry and (<bold>B</bold>) complex non-mimicry between the repertoires of focal males and experimental playbacks. In this example, the focal male is a <italic>Vidua purpurascens</italic>, and each column shows songs recorded from a different individual male. Note that both sympatric and allopatric conspecifics share mimicry songs with the focal male, but only sympatric conspecifics share complex non-mimicry songs. Allopatric conspecifics have the same host mimicry as the focal male but completely nonoverlapping complex non-mimicry songs. Likewise, heterospecific males have completely different complex non-mimicry songs with respect to the focal male. Note that only a subset of each male's song repertoire is shown in this figure.Playback experiments were conducted in a habitat mosaic comprising small agricultural fields and sparse miombo woodlands west of Peramiho, United Republic of Tanzania (10.62&deg;S, 35.37&deg;E) from April 24 through May 11, 2009. These dates were within the breeding season for indigobirds in this region, during which time males vigorously defend territories and sing from a conspicuous &ldquo;call site&rdquo; at the top of a tree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>). Territories are defended against all other male indigobirds, and adjacent territories may be occupied by either conspecific or heterospecific males.Four indigobird species occur near Peramiho (<italic>V. chalybeata</italic>, <italic>V. codringtoni</italic>, <italic>V. funereal</italic>, and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic>), but only <italic>V. funerea</italic> and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> are found at relatively high densities. <italic>V. funerea</italic> parasitizes African Firefinches (<italic>Laganosticta rubricata</italic>), and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> parasitizes Jameson's Firefinches (<italic>L. rhodopareia</italic>). In this part of East Africa, <italic>V. funerea</italic> and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> adult males are not distinguishable based on morphometrics or coloration of the bill, legs, or plumage (J. M. DaCosta personal observation), but males are readily differentiated by song, which includes mimicry of the unique songs of their respective hosts. Host switching is rare (&lt;1&percnt; in adult males) in southern Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne5">Payne et al. 1992</xref>), and thus individuals were assigned to species based on their host mimicry (i.e. host association). Due to the difficulty of identifying and reliably locating females, we tested the territorial responses of male indigobirds only.Experimental playback tracks were prepared from field recordings collected during April&ndash;May 2008 and April 2009. Singing male indigobirds were recorded with a Marantz PMD660 digital recorder (Marantz, Kew Gardens, NY, USA) and a Sennheiser ME66 shotgun microphone (Sennheiser Electronic, Old Lyme, CT, USA) from a distance of &sim;5&ndash;10 m for &sim;20&ndash;25 minutes. The program Raven Pro v1.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Charif1">Charif et al. 2008</xref>) was used to create sonograms (Hann windows: size &equals; 256 samples; hop size &equals; 128 samples; grid spacing 188 Hz; 3 db bandwidth &equals; 270 Hz) for each recording, which were scanned to identify 5-minute segments with clear singing and minimal background noise from machines, people, or other organisms. Five-minute segments of high quality recordings that contained chatter, complex non-mimicry, and host mimicry were chosen for experimental playbacks.Playback tracks were further modified in Raven Pro by applying a filter to remove low and high frequency background noise (below 200 kHz and above 14000 kHz, respectively). Sympatric and allopatric playback tracks for both <italic>V. funerea</italic> and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> were prepared, and 9 unique playbacks were prepared for each population to avoid pseudoreplication generated by similar behavioral responses to a particular recording (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma 1989</xref>). Sympatric playbacks were made from birds recorded near Peramiho, where pairs of conspecific individuals share at least 50&percnt; and up to 100&percnt; of their complex non-mimicry songs, depending on distance between call sites (J. M. DaCosta personal observation).Allopatric playbacks of <italic>V. funerea</italic> were from birds recorded southeast of Iringa, Tanzania (7.77&deg;S, 35.70&deg;E; &sim;320 km north of Peramiho), and allopatric playbacks for <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> were from birds recorded north of Mikumi, Tanzania (7.38&deg;S, 36.97&deg;E; &sim;400 km north-northeast of Peramiho). Playback tracks contained an average of 80.3 vocalizations (range &equals; 56&ndash;109), composed mostly of complex non-mimicry (mean &equals; 68.6&percnt;), followed by host mimicry (mean &equals; 22.0&percnt;) and chatter (mean &equals; 8.4&percnt;), respectively. Note, however, that complex non-mimicry songs often contain host mimicry and/or introductory chatter syllables. Playback tracks for the 2 species did not differ in the total number of vocalizations or the number of each vocalization type (analysis of variance, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05).We subjected 18 males (9 each of <italic>V. funerea</italic> and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic>) to each of the 3 experimental treatments (total trials &equals; 54). Each focal male was present at his call site for at least 2 days prior to the first trial, which ensured that experimental males were occupying and defending a call site. As in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson (2006)</xref>, the order of each playback treatment was systematically shuffled among individuals to control for possible habituation across trials. All trials were conducted between 0800 and 1100 h, and successive trials for the same individual were separated by at least 3 days (mean &equals; 3.5, range &equals; 3&ndash;5).For each trial, a taxidermic mount and RadioShack 277-1008 speaker (RadioShack, Fort Worth, TX, USA) were placed &sim;10&ndash;20 m from the call site of the focal male in short vegetation with several branches suitable for perching in close proximity. Male territory holders regularly chase intruders that approach to within &sim;60 m of their call site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>), so the position of the speaker and mount was within the area defended by the focal individual. To control for visual stimuli associated with the taxidermic mount, a single male <italic>V. chalybeata centralis</italic> specimen collected near Iringa, Tanzania, was used in all trials. This subspecies does not occur at Peramiho and has a phenotype (red-orange legs, plumage with green sheen) that is different from the 2 focal species (pale legs, plumage with blue sheen). Presentation of the mount without playback did not elicit any noticeable behavioral responses (J. M. DaCosta personal observation), consistent with a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson 2006</xref>).The speaker was connected to an Apple iPod mp3 player (Apple, Cupertino, CA, USA) with &sim;7 m of audio cable. This long cable allowed observers to be a good distance from the speaker before starting the trial; observers increased their distance from the speaker an additional &sim;5&ndash;10 m after starting the playback track. Playbacks were started only when the focal male was present at the call site and engaging in normal singing activity (i.e. consistently singing all 3 song elements). The amplitude of playbacks was calibrated by ear to be comparable to that of natural singing. Each trial lasted 5 minutes, during which time 1 or 2 observers measured the following behavioral responses: time to the first vocalization or hop/flight toward the speaker (latency of response), number of flights toward the speaker (flights), number of hops toward the speaker (hops), time before moving within 1 m of the speaker/mount (latency close), time spent within 1 m of the speaker/mount (duration close), number of chatter calls (chatter), number of host mimicry songs/calls (mimicry), time spent engaging in normal courtship singing behavior (singing), and time spent absent (out of sight, generally &gt;20 m away) from the area (absent). All time measurements were recorded in units of seconds. Observations were recorded verbally during the trial using a digital audio recorder so that visual contact with the focal male could be maintained throughout the trial; these observations were then transcribed and quantified later during the same day.The raw dataset used for all analyses is provided in <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="10.1642_AUK-14-35.1.s1.txt" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material File S1</inline-supplementary-material>. Preliminary inspection of the data revealed many zeros in the matrix, and the distributions for all variables failed the Shapiro-Wilk normality test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Shapiro1">Shapiro and Wilk 1965</xref>) using the shapiro.test function in R v2.10.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-RCoreTeam1">R Core Team 2012</xref>), even after logarithmic transformations. Because these data are inappropriate for parametric methods such as analysis of variance and principal components analysis, we analyzed the data with non-parametric factorial tests based on rank transformations of the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Brunner1">Brunner and Puri 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Shah1">Shah and Madden 2004</xref>) in SAS v8.02 (SAS Institute, Inc.).Analyses were conducted using the PROC MIXED function following the guidelines provided in the appendix of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Shah1">Shah and Madden (2004)</xref>; the code used for these analyses is available in <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="10.1642_AUK-14-35.1.s2.sas" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary Material File S2</inline-supplementary-material>. Rather than testing the hypothesis of equal means among groups, the analysis tests for equal distributions of ordinal data among groups. The method does not require that the input data be normally distributed, and it computes an ANOVA-type statistic, which has an approximate <italic>F</italic> distribution. Data for each behavioral variable were rank transformed using the PROC RANK function and then tested with a separate, unstructured covariance matrix fit for each species. Focal species (<italic>V. funerea</italic> or <italic>V. purpurascens</italic>), treatment (AC, SC, or SH playback), and a species&ast;treatment interaction were included as fixed effects, and individual focal bird nested within species was added as a repeated effect.Preliminary tests that included trial order (first, second, or third for each focal bird) as a fixed effect showed that order of playback treatments did not significantly explain variation in behaviors, and so this effect was not included in final analyses. For tests that returned significant effects, the Tukey-Kramer post-hoc test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Tukey1">Tukey 1953</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Kramer1">Kramer 1956</xref>) was used to determine which comparisons were significant. We controlled for the false discovery rate associated with multiple hypothesis testing by transforming <italic>P</italic> values into <italic>Q</italic> values using the p.adjust function in R and the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Benjamini1">Benjamini and Hochberg (1995)</xref>.In all trials, the focal male immediately stopped singing when the playback started. Because this response was consistent across all trials, the time of the first vocalization or movement toward the speaker was recorded as the latency of response. Regardless of the treatment, the most common first response was a short flight to a lower branch of the call site tree. Although individuals varied in their behaviors toward playbacks, most trials included repeated flights toward and then past the mount/speaker, short flights and/or hops toward the speaker, and chatter calls. Focal males came within 1 m of the mount/speaker in 28 trials (52&percnt;) and subsequently investigated the mount with short hops and flights. In 7 trials (13&percnt;), the focal male attacked the mount by perching on and/or pecking it. In both conspecific and heterospecific treatments, focal males spent little or no time engaged in natural courtship singing and left their territories only on rare occasions when chasing away another intruding male.Non-parametric summary statistics and results from analyses based on rank transformations (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t01">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t02">2</xref>, respectively) indicate a significant treatment effect for 3 behavioral response variables, and in each case focal males responded differentially to the SH playback as compared to the AC and SC playbacks, which elicited the same response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Males responded significantly faster in SH trials than in AC and SC trials (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>2,&thinsp;23.5</sub> &equals; 10.48, <italic>Q</italic> value &equals; 0.02). The other significant treatment effects were (1) males hopped toward the speaker more often in AC and SC trials than in SH trials (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>2,&thinsp;23.8</sub> &equals; 7.00, <italic>Q</italic> value &equals; 0.03), and (2) males gave more chatter calls in SH trials than in AC and SC trials (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>2,&thinsp;14.9</sub> &equals; 8.14, <italic>Q</italic> value &equals; 0.03). For duration close, there was a significant species&ast;treatment effect; time spent close to the speaker/mount was higher in SC than in either AC or SH trials, but only for <italic>V. funerea</italic> focal males (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>2,&thinsp;13.5</sub> &equals; 9.62, <italic>Q</italic> value &equals; 0.03).Nonparametric summary statistics (median &lsqb;1st quartile, 3rd quartile&rsqb;) of behaviors measured during each playback treatment. Hops, latency to response, chatter, and duration close all had significant effects (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t02">Table 2</xref>).Summary of results for nonparametric analyses based on rank transformations for each behavioral variable. <italic>Q</italic> values &lt;0.05 are in bold. AC: allopatric conspecific; SC: sympatric conspecific; SH: sympatric heterospecific.Box plots of raw (white) and rank-transformed (grey) data for behavioral responses with significant treatment effects in nonparametric rank-based tests: (<bold>A</bold>) hops, (<bold>B</bold>) latency of response, and (<bold>C</bold>) chatter calls. Lowercase letters above box plots of rank-transformed data indicate categories with statically significant differences; AC: allopatric conspecific; SC: sympatric conspecific; SH: sympatric heterospecific.In addition to this species&ast;treatment effect, there was weak evidence that the 2 species exhibited differential responses for other behaviors. In each case, the uncorrected <italic>P</italic> value for the test was &lt;0.05, but after the false discovery rate correction the <italic>Q</italic> value was &ge;0.05. <italic>V. funerea</italic> males had lower latency close times (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,&thinsp;9.57</sub> &equals; 9.07, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.01, <italic>Q</italic> &equals; 0.05), more flights (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,&thinsp;16.7</sub> &equals; 5.38, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.03, <italic>Q</italic> &equals; 0.14), and spent less time absent (nonparametric rank-based test, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,&thinsp;14.7</sub> &equals; 4.89, <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.04, <italic>Q</italic> &equals; 0.15) compared to <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> males.We tested the relative roles of mimetic and non-mimetic songs in indigobird species recognition by measuring the response of males to playbacks of conspecific males that mimicked the same host and either shared (SC treatment) or did not share (AC treatment) complex non-mimicry songs. In all 3 significant treatment effects (i.e. hops, latency of response, and chatter), the response of focal males differed between heterospecific (SH) and conspecific (AC and SC) playbacks. These results support the hypothesis that host mimicry is an important cue for species recognition by male indigobirds engaged in territorial defense and add further evidence that imprinting on host vocalizations during development plays an important role in the social behavior of these birds. Although we did not find evidence that males use complex non-mimicry for species recognition, these songs may be important in other social interactions (e.g., advertising individual quality or social status) both within and between sexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne2">Payne 1979</xref>).Significant treatment effects were found for 3 of the 9 behaviors recorded: hops, chatter, and latency of response (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t02">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Males hopped toward the speaker significantly more often in both conspecific treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t01">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). While many birds repeatedly flew toward but then past the speaker, hops were shorter movements in which the focal male almost always moved in the direction of the playback. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson (2006)</xref> also found that focal males hopped toward the speaker more often during playbacks of males from the same population as compared with playbacks from a different species/host race.Perhaps counterintuitively, focal males gave significantly more chatter calls in response to playback of heterospecific males (SH) than in either of the conspecific treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f02">Figure 2</xref>C). Behavioral observations suggest that chatter calls are used during both aggression and general broadcasting of territory ownership (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne2">1979</xref>). Chatter is the most common call given upon returning to a call site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne2">Payne 1979</xref>); in this study, males responding to heterospecific playbacks may have used chatter to generally advertise territory ownership, particularly when returning to their call sites rather than as a means of directing aggression specifically toward the playback.Similarly, we found that latency to first response was shorter in the heterospecific (SH) than in conspecific treatments (AC and SC; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-f02">Figure 2</xref>B), which might also be interpreted as evidence of a more intense reaction toward heterospecifics. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson (2006)</xref> noted that heterospecific playbacks &ldquo;elicited either no response or a rapid, but short lived approach,&rdquo; such that latency to initial response may not be a reliable indicator of overall aggression. Regardless of how these 3 behaviors are interpreted, similar responses in the 2 conspecific treatments, which shared the same host mimicry, support the hypothesis that host mimicry is important in species recognition.In a previous indigobird playback experiment in Cameroon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Balakrishnan1">Balakrishnan and Sorenson 2006</xref>), differential behavior toward conspecific vs. heterospecific playbacks was much more pronounced than in this study. Focal males in Cameroon clearly had weaker reactions to heterospecific playbacks, whereas males in Tanzania often reacted strongly to both conspecific and heterospecific playbacks (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t01">Table 1</xref>). Greater evolutionary divergence among West African indigobird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Sorenson1">Sorenson et al. 2003</xref>) does not explain this difference because the degree of morphological and genetic divergence between the <italic>V. camerunensis</italic> host races tested in Cameroon is similar to that between <italic>V. funerea</italic> and <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> in Tanzania (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne4">Payne 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Sefc1">Sefc et al. 2005</xref>; J.M. DaCosta and M. D. Sorenson personal observation). Stronger responses toward heterospecific playbacks in Tanzania might reflect greater interspecific competition for mating opportunities if females in southern Africa are generally less discriminating. Alternatively, indigobirds in both regions might have similar patterns of seasonal variation in territorial behavior, but differences in the timing of the 2 studies with respect to the local breeding season generated a difference in the observed intensity of interspecific territoriality.Species differences for some behaviors suggest that <italic>V. funerea</italic> was generally more aggressive than <italic>V. purpurascens</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t01">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-t02">2</xref>). Although both species were actively defending territories and attracting mates during the experiment, it is possible that their respective hosts, and hence the indigobird parasites, were at different points in their breeding season. Asynchrony in breeding seasons is hypothesized to play a role in reducing gene flow among indigobird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne 1973</xref>) in a manner comparable to phytophagous insects that speciate via host shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Bush1">Bush 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Tilmon1">Tilmon 2008</xref>).In all behaviors that were significantly different among treatments, focal males responded differentially toward the heterospecific playback as compared with both conspecific playbacks (AC &equals; SC &ne; SH). Because the 2 conspecific playbacks featured different complex non-mimicry combined with the same host mimicry, these results provide evidence that host mimicry is an important cue for indigobird species recognition. This finding has potentially important implications for understanding indigobird population structure. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne1">Payne (1973)</xref> observed juveniles visiting the call sites of adult <italic>V. chalybeata</italic> and hypothesized that (1) these were <italic>V. chalybeata</italic> juveniles drawn to adults mimicking their foster species; (2) these adults serve as tutors for learning complex non-mimicry, thus preserving generational continuity of complex non-mimicry dialects within species; and (3) these behaviors are likely general to all indigobird species.Because conspecific adults mimic the same host, and host mimicry is important in species recognition, juveniles should be able to correctly identify conspecific tutors whether they disperse within or beyond the geographic range of their natal non-mimicry dialect. Adult indigobird males sometimes disperse outside of their dialect neighborhood and subsequently replace their complex non-mimicry songs with those of conspecifics in the new neighborhood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Payne3">Payne 1985</xref>); this open-ended song learning is an unusual trait in songbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Catchpole1">Catchpole and Slater 2008</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Beecher1">Beecher and Brenowitz 2005</xref>). Given that all indigobird species in the new location will be singing unfamiliar non-mimicry songs, these males likely use host mimicry to identify conspecific tutors for the acquisition of a new repertoire of non-mimicry songs. Thus, species recognition based on host mimicry may be an important mechanism allowing dispersing juvenile and adult indigobirds to acquire &ldquo;appropriate&rdquo; repertoires of complex non-mimicry songs and may help to increase the &ldquo;cohesion&rdquo; of indigobird species across space and time.A variety of mechanisms have been proposed for the acquisition of species recognition in obligate brood parasites, which generally lack reliable interactions with conspecifics during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-4-549-Goth1">G&ouml;th and Hauber 2004</xref>). This study provides evidence that imprinting on heterospecific hosts during development, and subsequently mimicking host vocalizations, is an important component of species recognition in male indigobirds. Because other <italic>Vidua</italic> (i.e. whydahs and paradise-whydahs) also mimic the vocalizations of their heterospecific hosts, this mechanism for the acquisition of species recognition may be widespread in the genus. Our study thus expands the suite of adult indigobird behaviors shaped by host imprinting during development and enhances our understanding of species recognition pathways in brood parasitic birds.David Moyer, Neil Baker, and Liz Baker provided indigobird locality information and valuable logistical support in Tanzania. Elia Mulungu provided field assistance during the experiment, and Cheryl Vanier provided consultation on statistical analyses. Three anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments on an earlier version of the manuscript. This work was supported by the National Science Foundation grant DEB 0640759 with the approval of the Tanzania Wildlife Research Institute and the Tanzania Commission for Science and Technology.