 Influence of primary reproductive investments on blood biochemistry, leukocyte profile, and body mass in a small Arctic seabird  The plasmatic index of body condition in Yellow-legged Gulls (  Larus cachinnans  ): A food-controlled experiment  Social and coevolutionary feedbacks between mating and parental investment  Egg formation in Cassin's Auklet  A comparison of yolk growth rates in seabird eggs  Habitat and year-to-year variation in hemoglobin concentration in nestling Blue Tits   Cyanistes caeruleus    The control of false discovery rate under dependency  Egg size, composition, and offspring quality in some  Alcidae  (Aves:  Charadriiformes )  Flight  Female reproductive energetics  Balancing food and predator pressure induces chronic stress in songbirds  Prevalence of different modes of parental care in birds  Sex rations in birds and mammals: Can hypotheses be disentangled?  Effects of handling time and repeated sampling on avian white blood cell counts  The use of leukocyte profiles to measure stress in vertebrates: A review for ecologists  Fitness cost of incubation in great tits (  Parus major  ) is related to clutch size  Pollution related effects on immune function and stress in a free-living population of pied flycatcher   Ficedula hypoleuca    The evolution of polyandry in shorebirds: An evaluation of hypotheses  Hormones and the physiological architecture of life-history evolution  Avian hematology: Identification and interpretation  Individual variation in field metabolic rate of Kittiwakes (  Rissa tridactyla  ) during the chick-rearing period  Field and laboratory metabolism and thermoregulation in Dovekies (  Alle alle  )  Energy costs of chick rearing in Black-legged Kittiwakes (  Rissa tridactyla  )  Determinants of reproductive costs in the long-lived Black-legged Kittiwake: A multiyear experiment  Ring structure of avian egg yolk  A DNA test to sex most birds  Infectious diseases, reproductive effort and the cost of reproduction in birds  Sex differences in Little Auk   Alle alle   parental care: Transition from biparental to paternal-only care  Egg composition in relation to female age and relaying: Constraints on egg production in Thick-billed Murres (  Uria lomvia  )  Fitness related consequences of relaying in an Arctic seabird: Survival offspring to recruitment age  The breeding population of Little Auk (  Alle alle  ) in colonies in Hornsund and northwestern Spitsbergen  Fatty acid signatures of female Br&uuml;nnich's guillemots   Uria lomvia   suggests reliance on local prey for replacement egg production  Estimating fitness: A comparison of body condition estimates  Predicting the sex of Dovekies by discriminant analysis  Rates and consequences of relaying in little auks   Alle alle   breeding in the High Arctic&mdash;An experimental study with egg removal  Sex differences in body condition and hematological parameters in Little Auk   Alle alle   during the incubation period  Capital and income breeding as alternative tactics of resource use in reproduction  Effects of gonadal hormones on the blood composition of white-crowned sparrows  Adaptation, exaptation, and constraint: A hormonal perspective  The ratio of amount of haemoglobin to total surface area of erythrocytes in birds in relation to body mass, age of nestlings and season of the year  Interannual changes in zooplankton on the West Spitsbergen Shelf in relation to hydrography and their consequences for the diet of planktivorous seabirds  Analyzing body size as a factor in ecology and evolution  The significance of clutch size  No evidence of extra-pair paternity in the little auk  Alle alle   Low oxygen-carrying capacity of blood may increase developmental instability of molt in migrating waders  Changes in body condition in breeding kittiwakes   Rissa tridactyla    Why don't birds lay more eggs?  The cost of egg production: Increased egg production reduces future fitness in gulls  The resting metabolic cost of egg laying and nestling feeding in great tits  Clutch size and malaria resistance  Collecting, processing, and storing avian blood: A review  Blood respiratory properties of swifts  New perspective for estimating body condition from mass/length data: The scaled mass index as an alternative method  The paradigm of body condition: A critical reappraisal of current methods based on mass and length  An empirical evaluation of several univariate methods that adjust for size variation in morphometric data  Corticosterone and insulin interact to regulate glucose and triglyceride levels during stress in a bird  Techniques for studying integrated immune function in birds  Is laying a large egg expensive? Female-biased cost of first reproduction in a petrel    Alle alle   little auk  Sexual size dimorphism in shorebirds, gulls and alcids: The influence of sexual and natural selection  Changes in body mass and body reserves of breeding Little Auks (  Alle alle   L.)  Budget of elements in little auk (  Alle alle  ) chicks  How an eggshell is made  Metabolic costs of egg production in the European starling (  Sturnus vulgaris  )  Blood rheology in the pigeon (  Columba livia  ), hen (  Gallus gallus domesticus  ), and Black-headed Gull (  Larus ridibundus  )  The costs of egg production and incubation in great tits (  Parus major  )  Hematological changes associated with egg production: Estrogen dependence and repeatability  Parental and first generation effects of exogenous 17&beta;-estradiol on reproductive performance of female zebra finches (  Taeniopygia guttata  )  Mechanisms underlying the costs of egg production  Laying-sequence-specific variation in yolk oestrogen levels, and relationship to plasma oestrogen in female zebra finches (  Taeniopygia guttata  )  What causes the decrease in haematocrit during egg production?  Sex-specific differences in body condition indices and seasonal mass loss in Tufted Puffins  Avoiding the &ldquo;costs&rdquo; of testosterone: Ecological bases of hormone&ndash;behavior interactions  Differences in food delivered to chicks by males and females of little auks (  Alle alle  ) on South Spitsbergen  When and why does my mother leave me? The question of brood desertion in the Dovekie (  Alle alle  )  Different tactics, one goal: Initial reproductive investments of males and females in a small Arctic seabird  Is the transition from biparental to male-only care in a monogamous seabird related to changes in body mass and stress level?  Extra-pair copulations are frequent but unsuccessful in a highly colonial seabird, the little auk,   Alle alle    Sex-specific parental care by incubating Little Auks (  Alle alle  )  No evidence of blood parasites in little auks (  Alle alle  ) breeding on Svalbard  Evolutionary endocrinology: The developing synthesis between endocrinology and evolutionary genetics  Evolutionarily stable reproductive strategies in sexual organisms: An integrated approach to life-history evolution and sex allocation  Growing evidence indicates that producing eggs may constitute a considerable cost of reproduction. If female parental care, which in many species exceeds male performance, is added to these initial costs, it may be concluded that females contribute more to reproduction than males. However, this additional burden on females should reduce their survival and skew the usually equal sex ratio, but this is generally not the case. A resolution of this apparent paradox requires studies estimating the parental investments of both sexes at different stages of breeding, with particular focus on the initial reproductive stage. In the present study, egg composition and its energetic value was estimated in the Dovekie (or Little Auk,   Alle alle  ), a seabird exhibiting bi-parental care except for the end of the chick-rearing period, when the female deserts the brood while the male continues the feeding and escorts the chick during fledging. Condition estimates (size-adjusted body mass and several hematological and biochemical parameters, including concentrations of hemoglobin, glucose, cholesterol, and triglycerides, as well as the leukocyte profile) were also examined in both sexes during the prelaying, laying/relaying, and chick-rearing periods. The egg composition and its energy content indicate that the energetic demands of egg production are not as high as previously assumed, and the non-resource&ndash;based costs in females seem to be similar to those experienced by males during the mating period (nest site and/or paternity guarding). However, it was also found that females had lower body mass than males throughout the whole breeding season, suggesting overall female-biased costs of reproduction despite very similar parental performance. This suggests that females are more susceptible to the negative effects of reproduction. If so, their earlier brood desertion may be a response to the additive costs of parental investments.  De plus en plus d'indices indiquent que la production des &oelig;ufs peut constituer un co&ucirc;t consid&eacute;rable de la reproduction. Si les soins parentaux prodigu&eacute;s par la femelle, lesquels surpassent la performance du m&acirc;le chez plusieurs esp&egrave;ces, sont ajout&eacute;s &agrave; ces co&ucirc;ts initiaux, on pourrait conclure que les femelles contribuent davantage &agrave; la reproduction que les m&acirc;les. Cependant, ce fardeau suppl&eacute;mentaire pour les femelles devrait r&eacute;duire leur survie et biaiser le rapport des sexes qui est habituellement &eacute;gal, mais ce n'est g&eacute;n&eacute;ralement pas le cas. La r&eacute;solution de ce paradoxe apparent requiert des &eacute;tudes qui estiment les investissements parentaux des deux sexes &agrave; diff&eacute;rents stades de la reproduction, avec une attention particuli&egrave;re sur le stade de reproduction initial. Dans la pr&eacute;sente &eacute;tude, la composition de l'&oelig;uf et sa valeur &eacute;nerg&eacute;tique ont &eacute;t&eacute; estim&eacute;es chez   Alle alle  , un oiseau marin pr&eacute;sentant des soins biparentaux sauf &agrave; la fin de la p&eacute;riode d'&eacute;levage du poussin, lorsque la femelle d&eacute;serte la nich&eacute;e alors que le m&acirc;le continue de nourrir et d'escorter le poussin pendant l'envol. Les estimations de la condition (masse corporelle ajust&eacute;e pour la taille et plusieurs param&egrave;tres h&eacute;matologiques et biochimiques, dont les concentrations en h&eacute;moglobine, en glucose, en cholest&eacute;rol et en triglyc&eacute;rides, ainsi que le profil des leukocytes) ont aussi &eacute;t&eacute; examin&eacute;es chez les deux sexes au cours des p&eacute;riodes de pr&eacute;-ponte, de ponte/relais et d'&eacute;levage du poussin. La composition de l'&oelig;uf et son contenu &eacute;nerg&eacute;tique indiquent que les demandes &eacute;nerg&eacute;tiques de la production de l'&oelig;uf ne sont pas aussi &eacute;lev&eacute;es que pr&eacute;vu et que les co&ucirc;ts non associ&eacute;s aux ressources chez les femelles semblent &ecirc;tre similaires &agrave; ceux des m&acirc;les au cours de la p&eacute;riode d'accouplement (d&eacute;fense du site de nidification ou de la paternit&eacute;). Toutefois, on a &eacute;galement trouv&eacute; que les femelles avaient une masse corporelle plus petite que les m&acirc;les tout au long de la saison de reproduction, sugg&eacute;rant des co&ucirc;ts de reproduction globaux biais&eacute;s en faveur des femelles malgr&eacute; une performance parentale similaire. Ceci sugg&egrave;re que les femelles sont plus sensibles aux effets n&eacute;gatifs de la reproduction. Si tel est le cas, leur d&eacute;sertion de la nich&eacute;e peut &ecirc;tre une r&eacute;ponse aux co&ucirc;ts additionnels des investissements parentaux.   Mots-cl&eacute;s:    Alle alle  , masse corporelle, cholest&eacute;rol, glucose, h&eacute;moglobine, rapport h&eacute;t&eacute;rophiles/lymphocytes, triglyc&eacute;rides  It has long been thought that the cost of avian reproduction is primarily related to chick rearing ( Lack 1947 ,  1968 ). However, more recent studies have suggested that producing eggs may also be an energetically expensive activity that requires additional nutrient acquisition and the mobilization of fat reserves ( Monaghan and Nager 1997 ,  Nilsson and Raberg 2001 ,  V&eacute;zina and Williams 2002 ,  Sanz-Anguilar et al. 2012 ). In several species, females that were made to lay additional eggs (through egg removal) had lower local return rates in the following year ( Nager and Monaghan 2000 ,  Visser and Lessells 2001 ). At present, the factors driving the costs of egg production are not clearly understood (reviewed in  Williams 2005 ), but empirical studies clearly indicate that this activity may constitute a burden that could affect the further reproductive performance of females.  If egg production is so costly, and given that in most bird species females provide at least half of the parental care (reviewed in  Cockburn 2006 ), one may conclude that females contribute to reproduction to a higher degree than males. However, such unequal contributions of the sexes would lead to differential survival of males and females and distortion of the usually equal operational sex ratio, which is, generally, not the case ( Cockburn et al. 2002 ). Moreover, unequal contributions of both sexes to reproduction contradict the theory of the evolutionary stable strategy of sexual reproduction ( Maynard-Smith 1982 ,  Zhang and Wang 1994 ). There are 2 possible explanations for this apparent paradox: (a) the cost of egg production is not as high as previously assumed or is compensated by the female during the egg formation process or at later stages of breeding; or (b) the initial costs of reproduction are similar for the 2 sexes, although expressed in a different way, i.e. egg production in females and nest site and/or paternity guarding in males.  A resolution of this paradox requires detailed studies that could estimate the parental investments of males and females at different stages of breeding, with particular attention paid to the initial reproductive stage. Although the parental investments of males and females have been the subject of many studies, these have usually focused on chick rearing (e.g.,  Golet et al. 2000 ,  Fyhn et al. 2001 ,  Golet et al. 2004 ), and occasionally on the incubation period (e.g.,  Visser and Lessells 2001 ,  de Heij et al. 2006 ). However, initial parental investments of the 2 sexes appear to be neglected in many studies on parental care (reviewed in  Sz&eacute;kely et al. 2000 ,  Alonzo 2010 ).  To gain insight into this issue, male and female body condition estimates were examined at the prelaying, laying/relaying, and chick-rearing stages in the Dovekie (or Little Auk,   Alle alle  ;  Figure 1 ). This is a small pelagic seabird, which breeds exclusively in the high Arctic ( Stempniewicz 2001 ). The Dovekie is socially and genetically monogamous ( Lifjeld et al. 2005 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2009a ), with negligible dimorphism (there are no differences in plumage appearance; males have a larger total head length than females but there is large overlap in measurements between the sexes;  Jakubas and Wojczulanis 2007 ). In this species, a female produces one egg annually. The cost of its production is unknown, but it is assumed to be high given the size of the egg (&sim;20&percnt; of the female body mass;  Stempniewicz 2001 ) and the fact that relaid eggs are usually smaller than the first one (by 2.7&percnt;;  Jakubas and Wojczulanis-Jakubas 2013 ). Male and female contributions to incubation and chick provisioning are similar ( Harding et al. 2004 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2009b ,  2012 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas and Jakubas 2012 ). Only at the end of the chick-rearing period (up to 4 days prior to fledging) does the female cease to feed the chick and depart the colony, while the male continues provisioning and escorts the fledgling during its first flight to the sea ( Stempniewicz 2001 ,  Harding et al. 2004 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas and Jakubas 2012 ). In fact, the earlier female brood desertion is a common trait of  Alcini  tribe including, apart from the Dovekie, Razorbill (  Alca torda  ), Thick-billed Murre (  Uria lomvia  ), and Common Murre (  U. aalge  ) ( Gaston and Jones 1998 ).  Adult Dovekies (  Alle alle  ). Photo credit: Katarzyna Wojczulanis-Jakubas  It has been proposed that this earlier female brood desertion in the Dovekie is related to her initial investments ( Harding et al. 2004 ). As a result of incurring the high costs related to the clutch production ( Erckmann 1983 ) and additional costs during the incubation and chick-rearing periods, a female would desert the brood when approaching a threshold of her own body reserves. However, studies examining male and female condition estimates during the incubation and chick-rearing period, including the late phase of breeding, did not provide support for the hypothesis of earlier female brood desertion due to poor body condition ( Jakubas et al. 2008 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2012 ). Without knowing the primary parental investments of both sexes, explaining the behavior of female Dovekies in consecutive phases of breeding is purely speculative.  The aim of this study was twofold. First, the crude composition, energetic value, and duration of yolk formation of the Dovekie egg were investigated to verify the assumption of high costs of egg production in the species. Second, condition estimates were compared between molecularly sexed males and females at the different stages of breeding: prelaying, laying, relaying (after removal of the first egg), and chick rearing to examine thoroughly the effect of primary parental investments on the birds' body condition.  The study was carried out in a large breeding colony of Dovekie on the Ariekammen slopes in Hornsund (SW Spitsbergen, Norway; 77&deg;00&prime;N, 15&deg;33&prime;E) in 2012. This area is considered one of the main breeding aggregations of the Dovekie on Svalbard ( Isaksen 1995 ).  To establish the costs that the Dovekie egg represents, eggs from the birds sampled for the examination of body condition estimates in the laying and relaying periods (see details below) were measured (length and breadth using calipers that are accurate to 0.1 mm). A total of 20 eggs were collected (within 24 hours after laying) from nests during the egg-removal treatment (see details below) and frozen at &minus;20&deg;C until laboratory analyses were performed (&sim;3 months). Additionally, unpublished data from eggs collected (within 24 hours of laying) from the same colony and analyzed in 1984 ( n  &equals; 21) and 1987 ( n  &equals; 14) by J. R. E. Taylor were also used in the present study.  To examine the effect of egg production on the female condition, individuals of both sexes were captured at 4 different stages of the breeding season: (a) during the prelaying period (14&ndash;15 days before the average time of egg laying obtained for the group of control nests); (b) 1&ndash;2 days after laying the egg; (c) 1&ndash;2 days after relaying, in the group of nests with egg removal; and (d) during the mid-chick rearing period (after 8&ndash;9 days of chick rearing, according to the median hatching time obtained for the group of control nests). The birds were captured in noose carpets spread in a specific colony area (&sim;200 m 2 ) during the prelaying (30 males and 21 females) and chick-rearing (14 males and 11 females) periods, or directly on the nests while incubating, 1&ndash;2 days after laying (21 breeding pairs) or 1&ndash;2 days after relaying (10 breeding pairs and 3 females). Following capture, birds were measured (head&ndash;bill length using a caliper with an accuracy of 0.1 mm), weighed (with a spring balance with an accuracy of 1 g), banded, and a small blood sample was collected (&sim;30&ndash;50 &mu;l according to a standard procedure;  Owen 2011 ) from the brachial vein. All birds were released without any harm after &sim;10 min of handling. The blood sample collected in a heparinized capillary was divided into subsamples in order to (a) analyze the concentration of hemoglobin (10 &mu;L) using a portable hemoglobin photometer (Hb 201&plus; System; HemoCue, &Aring;ngelholm, Sweden); (b) analyze the concentration of glucose, cholesterol, and triglycerides (5 &mu;L for each) using standard commercial strips and a portable photometer (CardioChek 1709; PTS, Indianapolis, Indiana, USA); (c) make an air-dried blood smear to examine the leukocyte profile (&sim;5 &mu;L); and (d) preserve material in 70&percnt; ethanol for further molecular sexing (the remaining blood sample was used for this purpose). In a small number of individuals, the amount of blood taken was not sufficient to perform the whole set of analyses; therefore, the sample size given varies across the studied body condition estimates. The values obtained for triglycerides and cholesterol concentrations were below the range specified by the CardioChek producer in 14&percnt; and 3&percnt; of samples, respectively. In such cases, the lowest measured value was assigned to the individual sampled.  To establish the date of egg laying, 380 potential nest burrows (mostly known to have contained a nest in the previous season) were inspected every day, starting from a week before the expected date of laying. Of the 380 control burrows, 264 turned out to be real nests, i.e. active later in the season. During each nest inspection, the adults found in the nests were banded to check the bird's identity in the egg laying phase. Nests with both partners banded were selected for adult blood sampling just after laying ( n  &equals; 21) and relaying ( n  &equals; 20). The rest of the nests with banded birds ( n  &equals; 79) were considered the control group from which the laying and hatching dates were calculated. To establish the hatching date, 32 nests from the control group were inspected every 2 days starting from a week before expected hatching, based on the assumption of a 28-day incubation period ( Stempniewicz 2001 ).  To induce the birds to relay, egg removal was performed in 20 nests. The treatment was performed very early in the season in order to increase the chance of relaying (see the results from an analogous treatment in  Jakubas and Wojczulanis-Jakubas 2013 ). Thus, the eggs were removed (and frozen for egg composition analysis, see details above) on the day of laying in the focal nests (first to fourth day of egg laying at the scale of the whole colony, when 25&percnt; of eggs had been laid in the 79 control nests). To minimize disturbance, the burrows with egg removal were rechecked for the first time 7 days after the treatment, and then every day until a replacement egg was found or until 29 days after the treatment in cases where the birds did not relay ( Jakubas and Wojczulanis-Jakubas 2013 ). The egg was relaid in 15 (75&percnt;) of nests, including 2 nests where birds were not recaptured.  Although the exact date of laying and hatching of each bird that was haphazardly captured in the colony during the prelaying and chick rearing periods was not known, the synchrony of egg laying and hatching in the control nests (79 eggs laid within 10 days and 32 hatched chicks within 5 days) allowed to assume a similar timing of breeding for all individuals (14&ndash;15 days prior to egg laying and 8&ndash;9 days of chick rearing, according to the median date of laying and hatching in the control nests, respectively).  The following estimates describing condition were used: body mass corrected for body size, concentration of hemoglobin (g L &minus;1 ), glucose (mg dL &minus;1 ), cholesterol (mg dL &minus;1 ), and triglycerides (mg dL &minus;1 ), heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, and the percentages of the 2 leukocyte types. Calculation of the size-adjusted body mass provides the cleanest way to separate the effects of condition from the effects of body size ( Reist 1985 ,  Jakob et al. 1996 ). It has been shown in many bird species including the Dovekie that body mass (appropriately corrected for body size) decreases under conditions of food deprivation and in response to elevated efforts related to parental performance (e.g.,  Taylor 1994 ,  Moe et al. 2002 ,  Williams et al. 2007 ). Multiple methods of correction of body mass for body size have been proposed. Of those, scaled mass index (SMI) recently proposed by  Peig and Green (2009)  seems to be the most efficient in the correction ( Peig and Green 2010 ). The SMI standardizes all individuals to the same body size, adjusting their body mass to the one they would have at their new body size in accordance with the scaling trend between body mass and body size ( Peig and Green 2009 ,  2010 ). Hemoglobin concentration is a measure of the oxygen-carrying capacity of blood ( Cambell 1995 ); it may serve as an approximate parameter of metabolic potential ( Kostelecka-Myrcha 1997 ,  Ba&nacute;bura et al. 2007 ,  Minias et al. 2013 ). There is some evidence that blood of more active species of birds has a higher hemoglobin content than that of less active species (e.g.,  Palomeque et al. 1980 ,  Viscor et al. 1984 ). Glucose levels are expected to be higher in chronically stressed birds, as such individuals should have a greater ability to mobilize energy for immediate muscle use at the expense of maintenance or reproduction ( Butler and Bishop 2000 ,  Clinchy et al. 2004 ). In contrast, the triglycerides level is expected to be lower in chronically stressed individuals ( Remage-Healey and Romero 2001 ). The concentration of cholesterol has been suggested to reliably indicate periods of food deprivation, as it decreases with diminution of body mass ( Alonso-Alvarez et al. 2002 ). The leukocyte profiles provide a convenient measure of integrated immune function ( Davis 2005 ,  Salvante 2006 ,  Davis et al. 2008 ), with lymphocytes and heterophils being responsible for pathogen-specific and non-specific immune responses, respectively ( Fudge 1989 ,  Campbell 1995 ); as a result, both increase during immunological challenges ( Eeva et al. 2005 ). The heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (H/L) is known to increase along with efforts associated with reproduction (mostly through a decrease in the number of lymphocytes), when birds facing the problem of limited energy resources reach a trade-off by partially suppressing their immune system ( Salvante 2006 ,  Davis et al. 2008 ).  Crude egg composition, energetic values, and the duration of yolk formation were analyzed using 3 sets of eggs. Based on the first set, which was composed of eggs collected in 2012 ( n  &equals; 19), crude egg composition and energetic values were established. The eggs were thawed and carefully divided into shell and the remaining content (yolk and albumen). Both components were weighed separately to an accuracy of 0.01 g (wet weight), then dried at 60&deg;C to constant mass and weighed again (dry weight) with the same level of accuracy. The energetic value of the homogenized egg content was measured using the C 7000 calorimetric system (IKA-Werke, Staufen, Germany). Two samples of dried egg content were examined and values were averaged (mean error &equals; 1.01&percnt;,  n  &equals; 19) for each egg. The energetic value was expressed as kJ g &minus;1  and calculated for the whole egg.  More detailed analysis of egg composition was performed in 1984 based on the second set of eggs which was collected in that season ( n  &equals; 21). The eggs were weighed just after collection (wet weight) and then carefully divided into shell, albumen, and yolk and weighed separately (0.1 g accuracy). All components were dried (at 60&deg;C to constant mass) and weighed separately again (dry weight). Lipids were extracted from the yolk in the Soxhlet apparatus with petroleum ether. This solvent efficiently eluted lipids, as the additional extraction of 4 yolks in acetone increased the mass of extracted lipids by only 2.8&percnt;.  Finally, based on eggs collected and analyzed in 1987 ( n  &equals; 14, taken from the nests within 24 hr after laying), the duration of the period of rapid yolk deposition was determined as described by  Grau (1976) . The eggs were frozen just after collection at &minus;20&deg;C overnight. Shells were removed and the frozen contents were fixed in 4&percnt; formalin at 65&deg;C for 16 hr. The yolks, after being freed from the albumen, were cut in half, and one half was immersed in 6&percnt; potassium dichromate for 16 hr at 65&deg;C. Rings of pale- and dark-staining yolk were counted. A pair of one light and one dark ring marked each 24-hr period of yolk deposition.  The blood smears were stained using the May&ndash;Gr&uuml;newald&ndash;Giemsa method ( Lillie 1977 ) with an Aerospray Hematology cytocentrifuge (Wescor, Logan, Utah, USA). Blood cells were examined by 400&ndash;1000&ndash;fold microscopy. The proportion of different types of leukocytes (lymphocytes, heterophils, monocytes, eosinophils, and basophils) was assessed based on the examination of 100 leukocytes under oil immersion. Due to the low numbers of monocytes, eosinophils, and basophils, these leukocytes were not considered in further analyses.  Sexing was performed utilizing DNA extracted from blood (A&amp;A Biotechnology, Gdynia, Poland). The primers P2 and P8 were used according to the protocol described by  Griffiths et al. (1998) , using a 50&deg;C annealing temperature for the PCR reaction. These primers amplify a 390-bp fragment on the W chromosome (in females only) and a 370-bp fragment on the Z chromosome (in both sexes) ( Griffiths et al. 1998 ). This size difference was clearly visible under UV light when the fragments were separated for 2 hr at 55 V on a 3&percnt; agarose gel containing ethidium bromide.  The assumptions of normality and homogeneity of variance were checked for all variables using the Shapiro&ndash;Wilk and Levene's tests, respectively. All variables met assumptions of parametric analyses, except for triglycerides concentrations and the percentage of heterophils and lymphocytes. Those 2 variables were arcsine square-root transformed to meet the assumptions of the parametric analyses ( Zar 1999 ). A  P  value of 0.05 was considered the threshold for significant differences, except for multiple comparisons, when the levels of alpha were decreased for significance following Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction (2001). The analyses were performed in SPSS 21 (IBM, Armonk, New York, USA) and STATISTICA 9.1 (StatSoft, Tulsa, Oklahoma, USA).  Separate general linear mixed model (GLMM) analyses were performed for each of the body condition estimates: body-scaled mass, concentrations of hemoglobin, glucose, cholesterol, and triglycerides, and relative number of heterophils and lymphocytes and the H/L ratio (dependent variables), with breeding phase and the sex of birds included as the fixed factors. As pair members were sampled during the laying and relaying period, nest identity was included in the models as the random factor. In all models, the interaction between the breeding phase and the sex of birds was included. Sums of squares of type III were used in all analyses. The Newman&ndash;Keuls test was used as post-hoc for the GLMM analyses.  Based on the egg measurements, egg volume (length &times; breadth 2 ) and egg shape index (length-to-breadth ratio) were calculated for the first and second eggs. The values were presented as mean &plusmn; SD. Both variables for the first and relaid eggs from the same females were investigated using Student's  t -test for dependent variables and Pearson correlation. The volume and shape of the first eggs were analyzed with each of the condition estimates of the focal females using the Pearson correlation. The relationship between the total volume of the 2 eggs and the condition estimates of relaying females was analyzed using the Pearson correlation coefficient.  Eggshells constituted 10&ndash;14&percnt; (1984&ndash;2012) and 25&ndash;27&percnt; (1984&ndash;2012) of the total wet and dry weight, respectively. Significant interannual differences were found for both wet and dry weight of the eggshell but not for the wet and dry weight of the egg content (yolk &plus; albumen) or the total weight ( Table 1 ).  Basic characteristics (mean &plusmn; SD) of Dovekie eggs collected in 1984 and 2012.  The yolk, with a wet weight of 9.80 &plusmn; 0.71 g ( n  &equals; 21) and a dry weight of 5.08 &plusmn; 0.41 g ( n  &equals; 21), constituted 31&percnt; of the total wet and 52&percnt; of the dry weight of the egg on average. The yolk consisted of lipids equal to 55&percnt; of the yolk dry weight (2.78 &plusmn; 0.22 g,  n  &equals; 19). The albumen, with a wet weight of 17.79 &plusmn; 1.67 g ( n  &equals; 21) and a dry weight of 2.29 &plusmn; 0.39 g ( n  &equals; 21), made up an average of 56&percnt; and 23&percnt; of the total wet and dry weight of the egg, respectively.  The energetic value of the average egg was 198.28 &plusmn; 20.20 kJ ( n  &equals; 20; 28.64 &plusmn; 0.55 kJ g &minus;1  of the dry weight). The yolk was formed during an average period of 5.3 &plusmn; 0.8 days (range: 4&ndash;6,  n  &equals; 14). The yolk-to-albumen ratio was on average 0.6:1 for wet weight and 2.3:1 for dry weight.  Body-scaled mass was not found to be significantly influenced by the phase of breeding but by the sex of birds (GLMM;  Table 2  and  Figure 2 ), with females being lighter than males ( Figure 2 ). There was no significant interaction between sex and phase of breeding ( Table 2 ).  The effects of sex and phase of breeding on the body-scaled mass, concentration of hemoglobin, glucose, triglycerides, and cholesterol in the Dovekie (GLMM, ANOVA). The asterisk indicates arcsine square-root&ndash;transformed variable.  Body-scaled mass: body mass corrected for body size (boxes are means and SD; whiskers are 95&percnt; CI) of Dovekie males (grey) and females (white) with respect to the phase of breeding (PRE: prelaying, LAY: 1&ndash;2 days after laying, REL: 1&ndash;2 days after egg relaying after egg removal, CHR : days 8&ndash;9 of chick-rearing period). The numbers above and below the bars denote the sample size in particular phases of breeding for males and females, respectively.  The phase of breeding was found to affect significantly hemoglobin and glucose concentrations (GLMM;  Table 2  and  Figure 3 ). Hemoglobin concentration was higher in the prelaying and chick-rearing periods compared with the laying and relaying periods (Newman&ndash;Keuls tests, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.02 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction). Glucose concentration during the chick-rearing period was higher than during all other phases (Newman&ndash;Keuls tests, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.02 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction, for all pairwise comparisons). Also, during the prelaying period, the glucose concentration was significantly higher compared with the laying and relaying periods (significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.02 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction). The phase of breeding was not found to affect the triglycerides concentration. Also, cholesterol concentration was similar during all of the studied phases. Neither hemoglobin, glucose, triglycerides, nor cholesterol concentrations differed between the sexes ( Table 2  and  Figure 3 ). The only significant interaction of phase and sex was found for cholesterol, with a higher value reported in males during the relaying compared with the chick-rearing period and to females during the same period (Newman&ndash;Keuls tests, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.01 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction;  Table 2  and  Figure 3 ).  Blood concentration of hemoglobin, glucose, triglycerides, and cholesterol (boxes are means and SD; whiskers are 95&percnt; CI) in Dovekie males (grey) and females (white) with respect to the phase of breeding (PRE: prelaying, LAY: 1&ndash;2 days after laying, REL: 1&ndash;2 days after egg relaying after egg removal, CHR: days 8&ndash;9 of chick-rearing period). The numbers above and below the bars denote the sample size in particular phases of breeding for males and females, respectively.  The phase of breeding was found to affect the H/L ratio as well as the percentages of heterophils and lymphocytes ( Table 3 ). Both the H/L ratio and heterophils number were significantly higher during the laying and relaying periods compared with the prelaying and chick-rearing periods (Newman&ndash;Keuls tests, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.02 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction;  Figure 4 ). In contrast, the relative lymphocyte number was lowest during the laying and relaying compared to the prelaying and chick-rearing periods (Newman&ndash;Keuls tests, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.02 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction;  Figure 4 ). No significant effect of sex was found for any of the studied variables. The only significant interaction of phase of breeding and sex was found for the H/L ratio ( Table 3 ), where the values for females were lower than those for males during the laying period (Newman&ndash;Keuls test, significant differences with  P  &lt; 0.01 after Benjamini&ndash;Yekutieli correction;  Figure 4 ).  The effects of sex and phase of breeding on percentages of heterophils (H) and lymphocytes (L), and H/L ratio in the Dovekie (GLMM, ANOVA). Asterisk indicates arcsine square-root&ndash;transformed variables.  Percentages of heterophils and lymphocytes and their (H/L) ratio (boxes are means and SD; whiskers are 95&percnt; CI) in Dovekie males (grey) and females (white) in respect to the phase of breeding (PRE: prelaying, LAY: 1&ndash;2 days after laying, REL: 1&ndash;2 days after egg relaying after the egg removal, CHR: days 8&ndash;9 day of chick-rearing period). The numbers above and below the bars denote the sample size in particular phases of breeding for males and females, respectively.  None of the condition estimates correlated significantly with the volume and shape of the egg in the females that laid the egg (Pearson correlations;  Table 4 ). Also, none of the condition estimates correlated with the total volume of the 2 eggs in the relaying females (Pearson correlations;  Table 4 ). The relaid eggs (mean volume: 55.65 &plusmn; 22.76 cm 3 ; mean shape: 1.41 &plusmn; 0.05) were significantly smaller than the first ones (mean volume: 56.88 &plusmn; 33.81 cm 3 , mean shape: 1.44 &plusmn; 0.04) laid by the same females (volume:  t -test for dependent variables,  t  21  &equals; 2.84,  P  &equals; 0.01; shape:  t  21  &equals; 3.84,  P  &equals; 0.01). However, there was a significant and positive correlation between the size of the first and second egg (volume:  r  &equals; 0.81,  t  22  &equals; 6.20,  P  &lt; 0.001; shape:  r  &equals; 0.71,  t  22  &equals; 4.46,  P  &lt; 0.001). Also, significant correlation was found between the caloric value of the first egg and triglycerides concentration (positive) and H/L ratio (negative) in the relaying females ( Table 4 ).  Relationship between particular female condition estimates and egg volume, shape, and energetic value after laying ( n  &equals; 20) and relaying ( n  &equals; 13) in the Dovekie (Pearson correlations). Significant correlations are in bold.  Dovekie eggs were found to have relatively large and high lipid-content yolk. That seems to be typical for precocial species ( Starck and Ricklefs 1998 ), and indeed very similar to the egg characteristic of the closely related auks (Razorbill, Thick-billed Murre, and Common Murre;  Birkhead and Nettleship 1984 ,  Hipfner and Nettleship 2001 ,  Hipfner et al. 2003 ). Producing such eggs requires a definite amount of energy. This comprises the energetic value of the egg per se (where yolk constitutes the highest value) and energetic expenses associated with the process of egg formation.  Owing to the food preferences of the Dovekie for energy-rich Arctic copepods, consisting of 36.8&percnt; lipids in dry mass ( Taylor and Konarzewski 1992 ) and occurring in great abundance in cold water masses in the vicinity of the breeding colonies (e.g.,  Kwasniewski et al. 2012 ), the female may quite easily collect sufficient energy resources to form the egg. Assuming 75&percnt; efficiency in the transformation of the consumed energy to the egg ( Carey 1996 ), Dovekie females need 219 kJ per yolk, which is the most costly part of the egg. Given the time required for yolk formation (5.3 days, reported in this study), each female needs 41.3 kJ day &minus;1  to form the yolk. This corresponds to 6.1 g of food (mean caloric value of the Dovekie food is 6.75 kJ g &minus;1 ;  Taylor and Konarzewski 1992 ), in other words, up to 2 average food loads brought by the females to the chick (3.5 g, with a range of 1.6&ndash;6.9;  Wojczulanis et al. 2006 ). Providing this level of energy resources does not seem to be a significant burden.  Egg-producing Dovekie females could rely on exogenous resources, thus employing the &ldquo;income&rdquo; breeding strategy ( sensu   J&ouml;nsson 1997 ). This would be in agreement with the observation that the females hardly visited the colony for 5 days prior to laying ( Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2014 ). Being outside the colony, females are likely to forage extensively for the purpose of fueling the egg-formation process. It is worth stressing that the time of the female &ldquo;exodus&rdquo; corresponds fairly well with the 5.3 days required for yolk formation that was revealed in the present study. Indeed, Dovekie females seem to be quite efficient in producing their egg, as the time required for yolk formation seems to be very short. Females of the Cassin's Auklet (  Ptychoramphus aleuticus  ) produce an egg similar in size to that of Dovekies, but need 3 days longer to produce the yolk ( Astheimer 1986 ). Duration of yolk formation in the Dovekie is shorter than in any of the 40 seabird species listed by  Astheimer and Grau (1990) , including 5 species that lay smaller eggs.  From a purely energetic point of view, given the energy content of the egg, its production constitutes 23&percnt; of the resting metabolism rate of adult Dovekie (RMR, estimated on 178 kJ day &minus;1 ;  Gabrielsen et al. 1991 ), while a 4-fold RMR increase is characteristic for chick-rearing adults ( Gabrielsen et al. 1991 ). Indeed, hemoglobin concentration was significantly lower during the laying and relaying periods than in the prelaying and chick-rearing periods. Given that hemoglobin level was expected to correlate with the maximum oxygen-transport rate and the potential metabolic rate ( Kostelecka-Myrcha 1997 ), the pattern of changes in that parameter suggests that egg production is not as energy consuming as activities performed during the prelaying and chick-rearing periods. Also, glucose concentrations varied throughout the breeding period, with lower levels reported during the egg-laying period compared with the prelaying and chick-rearing periods. This suggests relatively low stress levels of birds during the egg-laying period. Finally, neither triglycerides nor cholesterol indicated the females' poorer nutritional state during the egg-laying period compared with the other phases of breeding.  Nevertheless, body-scaled mass of females was significantly lower compared with males, although that was apparent for all examined breeding phases, i.e. not specific to the egg-laying period. That implies 2 issues. First, the cost of egg laying in terms of body mass loss are comparable to the costs of performing parental activities during chick rearing. Second, obtaining food for self-maintenance during both the egg-laying and chick-rearing periods was not so straightforward as it supposed to be (see above), at least for the females. Although males and females seem to provide parental care (incubation, chick brooding, and feeding) at very similar levels ( Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2009b ,  2012 ), the cost may be different for the 2 sexes. It has been shown for other species, for instance in the Black-legged Kittiwake (  Rissa tridactyla  ), that the same parental activity represents different costs for males and females ( Fyhn et al. 2001 ), and that may be manifested in differentiated body condition ( Moe et al. 2002 ). Moreover, it is possible that sex differences in Dovekie body mass might have been season-specific, as some other studies comparing body mass between males and females during particular phases of breeding did not show similar sex differences ( Jakubas et al. 2008 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2012 ,  2014 ). Thus, in some years the costs of all parental activities may be comparable between the sexes, but in less favorable circumstances, females may pay higher prices.  Some nutrients crucial to egg formation may be difficult to obtain for Dovekie females regardless of the season, constituting a constraint in egg production.  Jacobs et al. (2009)  found that certain fatty acids were depleted in the eggs relaid by Thick-billed Murre females while they were foraging on the local food resources. Also calcium, which is crucial for eggshell formation ( Taylor 1970 ), may limit egg production, as the food consumed by Dovekies contains very little of that element ( Taylor and Konarzewski 1992 ). There are some facts that seem to support this: (a) the relaid eggs were smaller than the initial ones ( Jakubas and Wojczulanis-Jakubas 2013 , this study), suggesting calcium limitation; (b) inter-seasonal differences in the mass of eggshells might be the result of interannual differences in calcium availability; and (c) the mass of the sternum in Dovekie females decreases by 9&percnt; after egg laying (J.R.E. Taylor, personal observation).  There are also other factors that may constitute a cost of egg formation, and their effect can occur over months or even years. There are non-resource&ndash;based costs that are associated with multiple physiological effects of reproductive hormones (reviewed in  Williams 2005 ). In such context, the lower level of hemoglobin concentration during the egg-laying period might be explained by hemodilution associated with osmoregulatory adjustments to elevated levels of lipoprotein yolk precursors ( Kern et al. 1972 ). Such an explanation was presented for some passerines, in which a decrease of red blood cell count was recorded at egg laying ( Kern et al. 1972 ,  Williams et al. 2004 ,  Wagner et al. 2008 ). Also, a decrease in the hemoglobin concentration might be due to a direct hormone-dependent (estradiol) inhibition of red blood cell production ( Kern et al. 1972 ,  Williams et al. 2004 ).  Another variable that could be explained in the light of non-resource&ndash;based costs of egg production is the number of lymphocytes that decreased significantly at the time of laying and prelaying, with a simultaneous increase in heterophils and an adequate elevation of the H/L ratio. The changes were consistent with the potential mechanisms of reallocation of resources from the immune system to egg production ( Gustafsson et al. 1994 ). It has been found in several species that egg-laying females (especially those which are forced to produce a larger than usual number of eggs) appeared to have a higher susceptibility to parasite infection due to the changes in the leukocyte profiles (e.g.,  Gustafsson et al. 1994 ,  Oppliger et al. 1996 ). Since all of these studies were conducted in parasite-abundant environments, there was a problem with discerning the cause and effect (i.e. whether the egg production effort caused changes in the immunocompetence and resulted in a higher parasite load, or infected individuals were in poorer condition and therefore likely to lay smaller clutches). The situation is much clearer in the Dovekie, for which there is no evidence of hemoparasite infection, possibly due to the lack of parasite vectors in the polar environment ( Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2010 ). Thus, the changes in the leukocyte profiles in females were likely to be related to the process of egg formation.  The cost of egg laying may also vary in different females, depending on their age and/or quality. The present results showed females that had laid a first egg of low-energy content had elevated stress levels after relaying, expressed in low triglyceride concentration and elevated H/L ratio. This suggests that egg formation is costly for females laying low-energy&ndash;content eggs, possibly young and/or low-quality individuals. On the other hand, it seems that for females producing high-energy&ndash;content first eggs, extra production of the replacement egg does not result in elevated stress level.  Interestingly, males experienced pronounced changes in hemoglobin and glucose concentrations as well as in the leukocyte profile throughout the breeding season, with a very similar pattern to that reported for females. The similarity of changes in male and female leukocyte profiles and hemoglobin concentrations during the prelaying and laying/relaying periods suggests that the changes have a hormonal basis. Both egg and sperm production are related to the great changes in hormone secretion in both sexes ( Kern et al. 1972 ,  Ketterson and Nolan 1999 ,  Wingfield et al. 2001 ,  Williams 2005 ). The steroid hormones and gonadotropins increase rapidly to a peak during courtship, territory defense, and egg laying ( Williams 1999 ,  Wingfield et al. 2001 ). Many, if not all, hormones involved in reproduction have widespread (pleiotropic) effects on a wide range of physiological systems ( Finch and Rose 1995 ,  Ketterson and Nolan 1999 ,  Williams et al. 2005 ,  Zera et al. 2007 ). Therefore, the 2 sexes, although being under the influence of different hormones, may experience their broad pleiotropic effect, incurring non-resource&ndash;based costs of reproduction ( Ketterson and Nolan 1999 ). Hence, all changes in biochemistry and hematological parameters explained by egg production in females might be interpreted in the context of specific activity, such as mate and territory defense in males.  Dovekie females cease chick feeding and depart the colony a few days (up to 4) before chick fledging, while males continue to provide food for the young ( Harding et al. 2004 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas and Jakubas 2012 ). It has been hypothesized that the females desert the brood earlier than males due to the high costs of egg formation ( Harding et al. 2004 ); however, the results of other studies have questioned this hypothesis ( Jakubas et al. 2008 ,  Wojczulanis-Jakubas et al. 2009b ,  2012 ). The present study shows that that egg production in the Dovekie is not so energetically demanding as it was previously assumed, and most of the necessary nutrients may be obtained from exogenous resources. Also, the non-resource&ndash;based costs of egg production seem to be similar to those that the males experience during the mating period due to male-specific activities (nest site and mate defense) and hormonal changes. In that context, it seems that costs of egg production per se are not the only reason for female brood abandonment. However, the present study also showed that Dovekie females had lower body mass compared with males throughout the whole breeding season, suggesting female-biased costs of reproduction, at least in the studied season. It indicates, therefore, that females are more prone to the lowering of body condition than males. If so, they may be predisposed for brood desertion more than males due to the additive effect of all parental investments, including egg production.  Summing up, the results of the present study strongly suggest that the common assumption of the high cost of egg production incurred by avian females is more complex and should be verified. It seems that when resources are not limited during the egg-laying period, the energetic costs of egg production may be negligible, and then non-resource costs only may affect the female's body condition. Therefore, resource and non-resource costs of egg production should be examined separately in future studies. Also, showing similarity of the sexes in the non-resource&ndash;based costs of the mating period, the present study suggests that the males' initial performance, typically neglected, should be seriously considered in future studies of avian parental investments.  Thanks go to Marek Konarzewski (1984 and 1987 seasons) and Mateusz Barcikowski (2013 season) for participation in the fieldwork, as well as to Proof-Reading Service (UK) for improvements in English usage. The study was supported financially by grants from the University of Gda&nacute;sk (538-L120-0814-12 to KWJ) and DEC-2011/01/N/NZ8/04569 to DK. All fieldwork was performed under permission of the Norwegian Animal Research Authority and the Governor of Svalbard. 