Nest size is not closely related to breeding success in Blue Tits: A long-term nest-box study in a Mediterranean oak habitatEffects of nest characteristics on breeding success of Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>Nest quality in relation to adult bird condition and its impact on reproduction in Great Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>Variation in Great Tit nest mass and composition and its breeding consequences: A comparative study in four Mediterranean habitatsA thirty-year study of phenotypic and genetic variation of Blue Tits in Mediterranean habitat mosaicsBrighter Great Tit parents build bigger nestsLocal temperature and not latitude determines the design of Blue Tit and Great Tit nestsFemale coloration indicates female reproductive capacity in Blue TitsTree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>) nesting on wetlands impacted by oil sands mining are highly parasitized by the bird blow fly <italic>Protocalliphora</italic> sppThe breeding biology of the great and blue titmiceGreen plants in starling nests: Effects on nestlingsBird&ndash;ectoparasite interactions, nest humidity, and ectoparasite community structureVariations in prevalence and intensity of blow fly infestations in an insular Mediterranean population of Blue TitsDoes the threat of European Pine Marten (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Martes martes</named-content></italic>) predation influence the height of nests built by Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>) and Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>)?The design of artificial nestboxes for the study of secondary hole-nesting birds: A review of methodological inconsistencies and potential biasesNest size and breeding success in first and replacement clutches: An experimental study in Blue Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>Great Tits build shallower nests than Blue TitsNest-building by Crested Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus cristatus</named-content></italic> males: An analysis of costs and benefitsPredators and the breeding bird: Behavioral and reproductive flexibility under the risk of predationNest architecture and reproductive performance in Tree Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tachycineta bicolor</named-content></italic>)The weight of female-built nests correlates with female but not male quality in the Blue Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>Latitudinal variation in Blue Tit and Great Tit nest characteristics indicates environmental adjustmentThe design and function of birds' nestsDependence of nest mass on nest hole depth in the Great Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>Breeding success of the Great Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> in relation to attributes of natural nest cavities in a primeval forestAromatic plants in nests of the Blue Tit <italic>Cyanistus caeruleus</italic> protect chicks from bacteriaClutch-size variation in Western Palaearctic secondary hole-nesting passerine birds in relation to nest box designVariation in clutch size in relation to nest size in birdsAvian nests and nest-building as signalsNest construction costs affect nestling growth: A field experiment in a cavity-nesting passerineNest construction rate and stress in female Pied Flycatchers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ficedula hypoleuca</named-content></italic>Energetic limitation in the egg-laying period of Great TitsBrutbiologische Konsequenzen des asynchronen Schl&uuml;pfens bei Kohlmeise (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) und Blaumeise (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus caeruleus</named-content></italic>)The role of nest sites in limiting the numbers of hole-nesting birds: A reviewThe evolution of nest-site selection among hole-nesting birds: The impact of nest predation and competitionFunctional significance of nest size variation in the Rufous Bush Robin <italic>Cercotrichas galactotes</italic>Breeding success in Blue Tits: Good territories or good parents?Nest design and the abundance of parasitic <italic>Protocalliphora</italic> blow flies in two hole-nesting passerinesOld nest material in nest boxes of Tree Swallows: Effects on nest-site choice and nest buildingExtended phenotypes as signalsThe insulation in nests of selected North American songbirdsExperiments on clutch size and nest size in passerine birdsOn the evolution of clutch size and nest size in passerine birdsIntra- and interspecific relationships between nest size and immunityNest building, sexual selection and parental investmentHouse Wrens alter nest architecture to compensate for cavity vulnerabilityCavity depth, not experience, determines nest height in Eastern BluebirdsNest size and aromatic plants in the nest as sexually selected female traits in Blue TitsNest weight and female health in the Blue Tit (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>)The relationship between nest-box size, occupation and breeding parameters of the Great Tit <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic> and some other hole-nesting speciesAnti-predator adaptations in nesting Marsh Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus palustris</named-content></italic>: The role of nest-site securityNest soaking in natural holes&mdash;a serious cause of breeding failure?The breeding performance of Blue Tits <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic> in relation to the attributes of natural holes in a primeval forestThe use of green plant material in bird nests to avoid ectoparasitesVarious components of breeding success are predicted to be related to avian nest size because (1) some individuals are physically able to build larger nests than other individuals or (2) larger nests provide more protection in the absence of predation than smaller nests. The results of an 18-yr correlative nest-box study in Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>) show that nest size is not closely related to components that reflect breeding performance, after controlling for other female characteristics (first-egg date, clutch size, and female age) assumed to influence breeding performance in long-term studies. Our results support those of most short-term field studies that have reported weak associations between nest size and breeding performance in cavity-nesting passerines. We suggest that the absence of an association between nest size and breeding performance can be explained by the fact that the vast majority of nest-box studies have used small nest chambers that imposed physical constraints on the full expression of the nest. We recommend using a larger range of nest-chamber sizes that better reflect the characteristics of natural holes exploited by secondary cavity-nesting species.Se predice que diferentes componentes del &eacute;xito reproductivo est&aacute;n relacionados con el tama&ntilde;o del nido de las aves debido a que (i) algunos individuos son f&iacute;sicamente capaces de construir nidos m&aacute;s grandes que otros individuos, o a que (ii) los nidos m&aacute;s grandes brindan m&aacute;s protecci&oacute;n en ausencia de depredaci&oacute;n que los nidos m&aacute;s peque&ntilde;os. Aqu&iacute; mostramos con un estudio de cajas nido de 18 a&ntilde;os correlativos en <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic> que el tama&ntilde;o del nido no est&aacute; cercanamente correlacionado a los componentes que reflejan el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo luego de controlar por otras caracter&iacute;sticas de las hembras (fecha del primer huevo, tama&ntilde;o de la nidada, edad de la hembra) que se asume que influencian el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo en estudios de largo plazo. Nuestro estudio apoya los resultados de la mayor&iacute;a de los estudios de campo de corto plazo que presentan asociaciones d&eacute;biles entre el tama&ntilde;o del nido y el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo en paserinos que anidan en cavidades. Sugerimos que la ausencia de una asociaci&oacute;n entre el tama&ntilde;o del nido y el desempe&ntilde;o reproductivo puede ser explicada por el hecho de que la gran mayor&iacute;a de los estudios con cajas nido usaron nidos con un tama&ntilde;o de la c&aacute;mara peque&ntilde;o, que impone l&iacute;mites f&iacute;sicos al aprovechamiento extensivo del nido. Recomendamos usar un rango m&aacute;s amplio de tama&ntilde;os de la c&aacute;mara del nido que refleje mejor las caracter&iacute;sticas de los huecos naturales usados por las especies que anidan en cavidades secundarias.<italic>Palabas clave:</italic> aves que anidan en cavidades, cajas nido, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>, &eacute;xito reproductivo, tama&ntilde;o del nidoAnimal nests are designed to provide protection against changes in the physical environment (e.g., weather; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Skowron1">Skowron and Kern 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Slagsvold1">Slagsvold 1989a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Slagsvold2">1989b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Nager1">Nager and van Noordwijk 1992</xref>, Hansell 2002, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Deeming1">Deeming et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring2">Mainwaring et al. 2012</xref>) or the biotic environment (e.g., predators, parasites; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Nilsson1">Nilsson 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wimberger1">Wimberger 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Slagsvold1">Slagsvold 1989a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Slagsvold2">1989b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Soler2">Soler et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wesolowski1">Weso&lstrok;owski 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lima1">Lima 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Schaedelin1">Schaedelin and Taborsky 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Stanback1">Stanback et al. 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring3">Mainwaring et al. 2014</xref>). If nest building is physically costly, some individuals should be physically able to build larger nests than other individuals (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lens1">Lens et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Palomino1">Palomino et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas2">Tom&aacute;s et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Soler1">Soler et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moreno3">Moreno et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Broggi1">Broggi and Senar 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moreno1">Moreno 2012</xref>). Therefore, nest size is often expected to be related to breeding performance or success.Secondary cavity-exploiting birds build nests within cavities they do not excavate themselves. Hence, they are often limited by the availability of tree cavities in secondary forest or other anthropogenically altered habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Newton1">Newton 1994</xref>). In the absence of tree cavities, avian secondary cavity-exploiters are willing to breed in artificial boxes that vary in design and that are attached to substrates such as buildings, artificial posts, or trees. Accessible boxes allow the routine monitoring and handling of nests, eggs, breeders, and offspring that facilitates the study of relationships between cavity characteristics, nest design, and breeding performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>). Positive relationships between nest size and breeding performance are expected to be weak in systems with natural or artificial holes where cavity nests are exposed to predation, accepting that large nests are more vulnerable to predation risks than small nests (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wesolowski1">Weso&lstrok;owski 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lima1">Lima 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wesolowski3">Weso&lstrok;owski and Rowi&nacute;ski 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Maziarz1">Maziarz et al. 2015</xref>). Field studies of the best-investigated nest-box breeding passerines in Europe have found, in the vast majority of cases, weak relationships between aspects of nest size and components reflecting breeding performance. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alabrudzinska1">Alabrudzi&nacute;ska et al. (2003)</xref> found that total nest mass was not strongly linked to the timing of breeding (laying date) or the hatchability of eggs in Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) in Poland. In the same study, fledging success was positively related to nest mass measured after the breeding season, but clutches were smaller in heavier nests and nest size measured before the incubation stage was not related to hatching or fledging success. In Great Tits in Spain, nest weight was not related to aspects reflecting breeding performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez1">&Aacute;lvarez and Barba 2008</xref>). However, when the various measures of nest design and breeding performance were combined in principal component analyses, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez1">&Aacute;lvarez and Barba (2008)</xref> reported a positive relationship between nest size and breeding success. By contrast, in 4 Mediterranean-type study plots, Great Tit nest mass was not related to measures of breeding performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez2">&Aacute;lvarez et al. 2013</xref>). In Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>), heavier or larger nests did not result in greater breeding success than lighter or smaller nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas2">Tom&aacute;s et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas1">2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). In Blue Tits in Spain, experimental manipulation of nest size and nest components (aromatic plants) did not affect laying date, clutch size, hatching date, hatching success, or brood size on day 6 posthatch and had no detectable influence on breeding success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas1">Tom&aacute;s et al. 2013</xref>). In Blue Tits in southern France, nest size was not significantly related to the number of hatchlings, the number of fledglings, hatching success, fledging success, or nestling mass, after controlling for factors frequently investigated in nest-box studies and known to influence breeding performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). However, several of the studies cited above reported significant, sometimes unexpected, relationships between size components of nests (e.g., cup dimension, fraction or mass of moss or sticks) and some aspects of reproductive performance. For instance, Great Tit clutches were smaller in nests with more moss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez2">&Aacute;lvarez et al. 2013</xref>), and aspects of parental investment changed after an experimental change in the size or composition of Blue Tit nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas1">Tom&aacute;s et al. 2013</xref>). The nest-box studies interested in reproductive consequences of nest size usually lasted ~2 yr (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lombardo1">Lombardo 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Rendell1">Rendell and Verbeek 1996</xref>). Nest size in relation to breeding success thus remains an underappreciated study topic in most long-term avian life-history studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring3">Mainwaring et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">2014b</xref>).Here, we reexplore the relationships between the size of nests and the measures of breeding success most frequently quantified in multiyear field investigations that used artificial nest boxes as tools. We present the results of an 18-yr study in Mediterranean Blue Tits in which nest contents have been protected as much as possible against nest predation. If larger nests were beneficial in the absence of predation or were a proximate result of phenotype-related characteristics of the nest builders, we would expect to find significant positive relationships between the size of the cavity nests and other aspects of breeding performance. Because our dataset is so large compared with those of previous studies, we provide especially strong tests.In a forest near Montpellier, France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Doutrelant1">Doutrelant et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>), we monitored wood-and-concrete Schwegler B1 boxes (Schorndorf, Germany) or concrete boxes with similar external chamber sizes (see appendix 1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>). These boxes have a relatively small internal floor area (~110 cm<sup>2</sup>) compared with other box types that are accepted by Blue Tits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>). Boxes were protected against intrusions of nest predators, most often by using wired cages surrounding the front-plate or the whole box or, in more recent years, by placing boxes in cages on metal posts.Boxes were usually visited once a week to check the progress of each breeding attempt, the initiation and progress of nest construction, the first egg-laying dates (Julian date), and the numbers of hidden or exposed eggs found in the nest, following basic protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Blondel1">Blondel et al. 2006</xref>). We measured nest thickness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-HurtrezBousses1">Hurtrez-Bouss&egrave;s et al. 1999</xref>) as the external distance between the internal box floor and the top of the nest rim, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Hansell1">Hansell (2000</xref>; his measure &ldquo;a&rdquo;, referred to as &ldquo;nest depth&rdquo;) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez1">&Aacute;lvarez and Barba (2008</xref>; their measure &ldquo;B&rdquo;). Nest volume was estimated as a proxy of nest size by multiplying the nest thickness by the inner surface area of the standardized box floor (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-HurtrezBousses1">Hurtrez-Bouss&egrave;s et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring1">Mainwaring et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts3">Lambrechts et al. 2014</xref>). Nest thickness and nest volume have been used as proxies of nest size in studies that compared investment in nest building across individuals that occupied the same box type (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-HurtrezBousses1">Hurtrez-Bouss&egrave;s et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts3">2014</xref>). Nests were not always measured during the same reproductive stage; in some years nests were measured only before the onset of egg laying, whereas in other years they were also measured during the period of egg laying or, occasionally, during the period of incubation. Reproductive stage was therefore divided into 3 study periods during which the nests were measured: (1) up to 1 wk before the initiation of egg laying, (2) during egg laying, and (3) after egg laying and prior to hatching (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts3">Lambrechts et al. 2014</xref>).In the vast majority of the cases, females were captured within the nest chamber with nest-box traps when the nestlings were &ge;8 days old. Occasionally, females were trapped with mist nets placed next to the occupied nest box. All captured females were ringed (with rings provided by the CRBPO in Paris). Body parts were measured following protocols established in a long-term monitoring program (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Blondel1">Blondel et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Doutrelant1">Doutrelant et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). Nestlings normally reach the body size of the adults from 13 days posthatch onward (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Gibb1">Gibb 1950</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Neub1">Neub 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Perrins1">Perrins 1979</xref>). In all years, nestling body mass was measured mostly at 14&ndash;16 days posthatch, rarely younger (11&ndash;13 days posthatch) or older (&gt;16 days posthatch) (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Doutrelant1">Doutrelant et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). On a given date, nestlings from the same brood could differ in age, so plumage development was scored and used as a reliable estimate of nestling age, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Gibb1">Gibb (1950)</xref>. In some years, eggs or whole clutches were removed for the purposes of other studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). Boxes with removed eggs or clutches were not considered in the analyses that related nest size to breeding success. Because of time or logistic constraints or difficulties in monitoring nests, not all the factors considered in the present study were quantified for all the nests measured. For instance, some nests were lost before the nestlings fledged (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t01">Table 1</xref>) and some female parents, for unknown reasons, could not be trapped.The number of first breeding attempts in Blue Tits per breeding season for which the thickness of nests was measured. Predation or desertion frequently happened before the parents could be trapped. For individual nests that were measured more than once, only one measure per breeding attempt per year is presented.We analyzed relationships between the thickness of nests and 3 measures of breeding performance from first clutches: brood size at hatching, brood size at fledging, and average nestling body mass per brood when the oldest nestlings in a brood stopped growing at &gt;13 days posthatch. We classified nests into breeding attempts with at least 1 fledgling versus breeding attempts that did not result in fledglings. Two types of breeding failure were defined: (1) depredated nests, from which eggs or nestlings disappeared well before the expected fledging date and/or where clear signs of predation were noticed; and (2) deserted nests, where unhatched clutches or dead broods without signs of predation were found.To investigate the relationships between nest size and measures of breeding performance in first clutches (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t01">Table 1</xref>), after controlling for other characteristics of the nest builders known to influence breeding performance in long-term field studies, we applied mixed models (proc mixed, Type 3, SAS 9.4, data not transformed) and considered the fixed effects of nest thickness as a proxy of nest size (cm), reproductive stage (nest thickness measured before vs. during vs. after egg laying), the Julian date when the first egg was laid (first-egg date), the size of the incubated clutch, and female age (yearling vs. older). First-egg date and clutch size were used as proxies of female quality or territory quality following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Przybylo1">Przybylo et al. (2001)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring1">Mainwaring et al. (2008)</xref>, or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Alvarez1">&Aacute;lvarez and Barba (2008)</xref>. We first took into account the nests with at least 1 fledgling and compared them with deserted and depredated nests, considering box identity (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 227) and year (1997&ndash;2014) as random factors. Female identity was not taken into account in this analysis because nests often failed before the parents could be trapped. We then analyzed only the nests with at least 1 fledgling, considering box identity (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 212), year (1997&ndash;2014, except 2009), and female identity (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 524) as random factors.During the 18-yr study period, 1,280 measures of nest thickness from first clutches were taken. In some breeding seasons, nests were measured more than once before the eggs hatched. Several females were also monitored during more than one breeding season. In this sample, the thickness of the nests varied between 1 and 11.5 cm; thus, nest volumes varied between approximately 110 and 1,300 cm<sup>3</sup> when nest thickness was multiplied by the internal bottom surface of the boxes.Despite our efforts to protect nests against predation, nests were occasionally deserted or depredated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t01">Table 1</xref>). Deserted or depredated nests were slightly thinner than nests with at least 1 fledgling (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t02">Table 2</xref>), but the differences in nest thickness were not significant (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.174; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t03">Table 3</xref>). Females that produced no fledglings tended to have larger clutches than females that produced at least 1 fledgling (<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.044; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t03">Table 3</xref>).Average (&plusmn; SD) thickness of Blue Tit nests that had different outcomes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; number of nest measures taken).The mixed procedure (Type 3 tests of fixed effects, data not transformed) using failure level (depredated vs. deserted vs. at least 1 fledgling), number of hatchlings, number of fledglings, or average full-grown nestling mass when the oldest nestling in a brood stopped growing (&gt;13 days posthatch) as the dependent variable, and nest thickness (as a proxy of nest size), reproductive stage (nests height measured before vs. during vs. after egg laying), onset of the first clutch (first-egg date in Julian dates), size of the incubated clutch (number of eggs), and female age (yearling vs. older) as fixed effects. Box identity, year, and/or female identity (ring number) were considered as random factors (for details, see text).In nests with at least 1 fledgling, the 3 measures of breeding performance were not related to nest thickness (all <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.20, <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t03">Table 3</xref>). As expected, females with larger clutches produced more hatchlings (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and more fledglings (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Nestlings were also heavier in smaller broods (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and in broods produced by older females (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001).In a nest-box breeding population of Mediterranean Blue Tits that was protected as much as possible against nest predation, we found no strong association between the size of the cavity nest and 4 components of breeding performance. Our study controlled for other female traits assumed to influence breeding performance in long-term field studies (first-egg date, clutch size, and female age; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>). Our findings therefore support the results of short-term nest-box studies that used substantially smaller data sets (see above; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Rendell1">Rendell and Verbeek 1996</xref>).Nest boxes are usually designed to protect bird occupants, which may explain why avian breeding success is often substantially lower in tree cavities accessible to nest predators than in artificial boxes protected against nest predation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wesolowski1">Weso&lstrok;owski 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Wesolowski2">Weso&lstrok;owski et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. 2014</xref>). Despite our efforts to protect the cavity nests against predation, some nests were either deserted or depredated and hence did not produce fledglings. In some years, a weasel (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Mustela nivalis</named-content></italic>) was noticed inside boxes that contained destroyed eggs or was seen close to boxes with traces of killed parents or nestlings (M. M. Lambrechts et al. personal observation). Occasionally, front-plates of boxes were found on the ground, combined with evident traces of predation. We observed that nest predation occurred most frequently in 4 study years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t01">Table 1</xref>) when the boxes were attached to the trunks of trees. Since 2011, boxes were protected by metal cages placed on metal posts, which substantially reduced the number of depredated nests in the study area. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. (2014)</xref> found that any nests in small chambers could suffer from predation when predators had access to the chamber contents via the entrance hole; however, they also explained that in larger chambers, the thicker (i.e. higher) nests suffered more from predation than the thinner ones. Perhaps reduction in nest size might be an efficient strategy against predation when front-plates cannot be removed by predators (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. 2014</xref>). In the present study, however, successful nests were somewhat thicker than depredated nests (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-t02">Table 2</xref>), which indicates that even the thickest nests were not depredated in our study area when nest boxes were protected.If nest size reflects the physical ability to build a nest without paying predator-related costs, we predicted greater breeding success in larger nests than in smaller nests, which was not supported by our results. For nests that produced at least 1 fledgling, we found that nest size was not closely related to breeding success when the breeding performance of different individuals was compared. However, the birds might have been able to adjust the size or design of the nest to perceived spatiotemporal variation in the environment to keep hatching success, fledging success, or the physical condition of nestlings at similar high levels. For instance, we do not exclude the possibility that nest components (e.g., moss or animal-based lining material) might be related to aspects of breeding performance when nest design would be adjusted to abiotic factors such as weather (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Hansell1">Hansell 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring2">Mainwaring et al. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mainwaring3">2014</xref>) or to biotic factors such as nest parasites (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Heeb1">Heeb et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Gentes1">Gentes et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mennerat1">Mennerat et al. 2009</xref>). In addition, most studies worked with 1 box type, exceptionally 2 or more (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">2014b</xref>). Nest size is adjusted to the size of the box chamber (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lombardo1">Lombardo 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Mazgajski1">Mazgajski and Rykowska 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Stanback2">Stanback et al. 2013b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">2014b</xref>; M. M. Lambrechts et al. personal observation), imposing physical constraints on the full expression of the nest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>). We observed that Great Tits and Blue Tits are able to double or triple the nest volume in larger box types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014b</xref>; M.&hairsp;M. Lambrechts et al. personal observation). Perhaps the relationships between nest size and aspects of breeding success might become stronger when the data from large and small boxes are compared (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-VanBalen1">van Balen 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">2014b</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lombardo1">Lombardo 1994</xref>) or in open-nesting species in which nest size is not physically constrained by the size of the nest chamber (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Soler2">Soler et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Hansell1">Hansell 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moreno1">Moreno 2012</xref>). Reproductive consequences of nest building have been investigated with field experiments that imposed nest designs that might have been counter-selected in the past (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Gwinner1">Gwinner et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Remes1">Reme&scaron; and Krist 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moreno3">Moreno et al. 2008</xref>). Future studies could investigate nest building and its biological consequences in relation to imposed changes in the architecture or properties of nest chambers that reflect the characteristics of natural holes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts1">Lambrechts et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Kalinski1">Kali&nacute;ski et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller1">M&oslash;ller et al. 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moller2">2014b</xref>). Multiyear experiments could also manipulate the size or composition of nests while controlling for nest-chamber characteristics (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Moreno2">Moreno et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Tomas1">Tom&aacute;s et al. 2013</xref>).We thank all the people who have helped maintain the study site since 1991. The town of Montarnaud kindly provided access to the study site.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> The long-term study was financially supported by the CNRS and OSU (OREME).<bold>Author contributions:</bold> M.M.L., A.G., and C.D. conceived the study (based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-198-Lambrechts2">Lambrechts et al. 2012</xref>) and supervised the research. P.P., C.D., A.G., and M.M.L. developed the methods. All the authors collected data and conducted the research. M.M.L., P.M., A.C., and A.G. analyzed the data. M.M.L. wrote the manuscript.