Scalar considerations in population trend estimates: Implications for recovery strategy planning for species of conservation concernImportance of spatial autocorrelation in modeling bird distributions at a continental scaleBayesian image restoration, with two applications in spatial statisticsModeling trends from North American Breeding Bird Survey data: A spatially explicit approachGeneral methods for monitoring convergence of iterative simulationsHenslow's Sparrow Conservation Action Plan Workshop Summary: March 7&ndash;8, 2007, Bloomington, MNGeographical patterns in openland cover and hayfield mowing in the Upper Great Lakes region: Implications for grassland bird conservationModel-based geostatisticsUsing decline in bird populations to identify needs for conservation actionBreeding Bird Survey ResultsBobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) population decline in agricultural landscapes in the Midwestern USAModeling spatial variation in disease risk: A geostatistical approachA hierarchical analysis of population change with application to Cerulean WarblersOf bugs and birds: Markov chain Monte Carlo for hierarchical modeling in wildlife researchWinBUGS&mdash;A Bayesian modelling framework: Concepts, structure, and extensibilitySite regions revisited: A climatic analysis of Hills' site regions for the province of Ontario using a parametric methodPosterior predictive <italic>p</italic>-valuesNew directions in management strategy evaluation through cross-fertilization between fisheries science and terrestrial conservationChristmas Bird Count Historical ResultsAgricultural landscapes: Can they support healthy bird populations as well as farm products?Statistical mapping of count survey dataAnalysis of the North American Breeding Bird Survey using hierarchical modelsEstimating Breeding Bird Survey trends and annual indices for Canada: How do the new hierarchical Bayesian estimates differ from previous estimates?Predicting regional abundance of rare grassland birds with a hierarchical spatial count modelA hierarchical spatial model of avian abundance with application to Cerulean WarblersBroad-scale population trends are often used to identify and list species of conservation concern and as baselines to surmise which recovery actions might arrest or reverse declines. It is therefore important that trends are quantified regionally, so that finer-scale assessments can be made about the plausible causes of declines and targeted conservation actions can be implemented. We estimated regional population trends for a grassland bird, the Bobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>), to compare with trends from provincial analyses used for risk assessment, to identify the regions contributing most substantially to population declines. We used 45 yr of count data from the North American Breeding Bird Survey, across 35 agricultural census divisions in southern Ontario, Canada, to develop spatially explicit hierarchical Bayesian models of regional population trends. Population trends were negative in 30 of 35 census divisions, 6 of which had 95&percnt; credibility intervals (CI) that did not include zero. In 34 of 35 census divisions, the CI included the provincial short-term recovery goal of a population trend of &minus;1&percnt;. Between 1998 and 2011, corresponding to the time series used for provincial risk assessment, the CI for 3 of 21 negative trends did not include 0 or &minus;1. Our results indicate that most regional trend estimates currently exceed the goal set out in the recovery strategy, insofar as they have been stable and not necessarily declining. This suggests a more optimistic picture of the state of Bobolink population trends than that obtained from analyses at broader spatial scales, which masked important regional variation. This result demonstrates the need for consideration of scale variance in trend estimation during risk assessment and management planning, and the application of spatially explicit trend estimation for small geographic areas to aid in this process.Les tendances des populations &agrave; grande &eacute;chelle sont souvent utilis&eacute;es pour identifier et lister les esp&egrave;ces dont la conservation est pr&eacute;occupante et comme point de r&eacute;f&eacute;rence pour d&eacute;duire quelles actions de r&eacute;tablissement peuvent arr&ecirc;ter ou renverser les d&eacute;clins. Il est donc important que les tendances soient quantifi&eacute;es au niveau r&eacute;gional afin que des &eacute;valuations &agrave; fine &eacute;chelle soient effectu&eacute;es sur les causes plausibles des d&eacute;clins et que des actions de conservation cibl&eacute;es soient mises en &oelig;uvre. Nous avons estim&eacute; les tendances des populations r&eacute;gionales d'un oiseau de prairie, <italic>Dolichonyx oryzivorous</italic>, pour les comparer &agrave; celles des analyses provinciales utilis&eacute;es dans les &eacute;valuations des risques afin d'identifier les r&eacute;gions qui contribuent le plus au d&eacute;clin des populations. Nous avons utilis&eacute; 45 ans de donn&eacute;es provenant du Relev&eacute; des oiseaux nicheurs de l'Am&eacute;rique du Nord, dans 35 divisions de recensement agricoles du sud de l'Ontario, au Canada, afin de d&eacute;velopper des mod&egrave;les bay&eacute;siens hi&eacute;rarchiques spatialement explicites des tendances des populations r&eacute;gionales. Les tendances des populations &eacute;taient n&eacute;gatives dans 30 des 35 divisions de recensement, six d'entre elles ayant des intervalles de cr&eacute;dibilit&eacute; de 95 &percnt; (IC) qui n'incluaient pas z&eacute;ro. Dans 34 des 35 divisions de recensement, les IC comprenaient l'objectif de r&eacute;tablissement provincial &agrave; court terme de moins un. Entre 1998 et 2011, qui correspond &agrave; la s&eacute;rie temporelle utilis&eacute;e pour l'&eacute;valuation des risques provinciale, les IC pour trois des 21 tendances n&eacute;gatives n'incluaient pas z&eacute;ro ou moins un. Les r&eacute;sultats indiquent que la plupart des estimations des tendances r&eacute;gionales d&eacute;passent actuellement l'objectif &eacute;tablit dans la strat&eacute;gie de r&eacute;tablissement, dans la mesure o&ugrave; elles ont &eacute;t&eacute; stables et pas n&eacute;cessairement en d&eacute;clin. Ceci sugg&egrave;re un portrait plus optimiste des tendances des populations de <italic>D. oryzivorous</italic> que celui obtenu &agrave; partir des analyses &agrave; plus large &eacute;chelle, lesquelles masquaient des variations r&eacute;gionales importantes. Ce r&eacute;sultat d&eacute;montre le besoin de consid&eacute;rer la variance d'&eacute;chelle dans l'estimation des tendances au cours d'une &eacute;valuation des risques et de la gestion pr&eacute;visionnelle, et d'appliquer une estimation des tendances spatialement explicite pour des petites zones g&eacute;ographiques afin d'aider dans ce processus.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> mod&eacute;lisation hi&eacute;rarchique, spatialement explicite, bay&eacute;sien, d&eacute;clin de la population, <italic>Dolichonyx oryzivorous</italic>, &eacute;laboration des politiques, gestion pr&eacute;visionnelle, cartographie des tendancesBroad-scale population trends are often used to identify and prioritize species that merit conservation attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Dunn1">Dunn 2002</xref>). For example, the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) considers a species critically endangered if it declines &ge;80&percnt; globally over a 10-yr period, or 3 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-IUCN1">IUCN 1994</xref>). Similar assessment criteria have been adopted by conservation organizations elsewhere and applied at various geographic extents, e.g., nationally in Canada by the Committee on the Status of Endangered Wildlife in Canada (COSEWIC), and provincially in Ontario by the Committee on the Status of Species at Risk in Ontario (COSSARO). These same trends in species occupancy and abundance, modeled with environmental and spatial covariates, can be used to improve knowledge about how species interact with their environments, and can provide insight into causal mechanisms responsible for population declines. However, misalignment between broad-scale trend estimates used for risk assessment and the finer scales at which management activities are initiated to protect and recover species of conservation concern may lead to ineffective or inefficient decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Dunn1">Dunn 2002</xref>). Resolving scalar discrepancies between trend estimates used for species designation and management implementation is a necessary prerequisite to testing hypotheses regarding causes of decline, identifying priority species and regions for allocating limited conservation resources, and assessing alternative management actions at scales amenable to conservation activities.In North America, a common approach for evaluating the status of breeding birds is through the assessment of changes in population abundance using long-term survey data, such as those collected by the Breeding Bird Survey (BBS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-EnvironmentCanada1">Environment Canada 2010</xref>), the Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-U.S.FishandWildlifeService2">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2014</xref>), and the Christmas Bird Count (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-NationalAudubonSociety1">National Audubon Society 2010</xref>). These trends are generally evaluated at the geographical extent of the nation, province, state, or Bird Conservation Region (BCR; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-NABCI1">NABCI 2000</xref>), and provide managers with broad-scale indices of population change from which risk assessments are made (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-U.S.FishandWildlifeService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2008</xref>). For example, the Henslow's Sparrow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Ammodramus henslowii</named-content></italic>) was listed as Threatened or Endangered in 13 states in the U.S. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Pruitt1">Pruitt 1996</xref>) and Endangered in the province of Ontario, Canada (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSSARO2">COSSARO 2011</xref>), based on trend estimates at these broad jurisdictional scales. Development of more regionally scaled management plans is a priority for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Cooper1">Cooper 2007</xref>), but trend estimates are generally unavailable at finer, regional scales. Because mechanisms affecting species population dynamics, such as habitat loss, fragmentation, and land-use intensification, can manifest at regional scales, resource managers require regionally specific information, first to address whether and by how much populations have changed, and subsequently to test alternative hypotheses about population change, assess the feasibility of achieving management targets, and make evidence-based conservation decisions to protect vulnerable species.Both the Canadian Wildlife Service (CWS) and the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) have adopted hierarchical Bayesian modeling to generate population trends and indices of annual abundance for North American breeding birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Smith1">Smith et al. 2014</xref>). Such frameworks provide a coherent and flexible approach for assessing the effects of sampling variation separately from temporal and spatial variation, while providing direct estimates of uncertainty about population parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Royle1">Royle and Dorazio 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Sauer1">Sauer and Link 2011</xref>). These models can further be used to analyze spatiotemporal variation in population size with respect to spatiotemporal characteristics of the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Thogmartin1">Thogmartin et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Royle1">Royle and Dorazio 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Sauer1">Sauer and Link 2011</xref>). Recently, these models have been adapted to allow spatially explicit summaries of trends for small geographic areas suitable for conservation planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Bled1">Bled et al. 2013</xref>) using small-area estimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Roa1">Roa 2003</xref>), a technique commonly used in fields such as epidemiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Lawson1">Lawson et al. 2003</xref>). Here, we demonstrate the application of this technique for a model grassland bird of conservation concern.Bobolinks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) are among the grassland birds that have experienced significant declines across much of their North American breeding range in recent decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Herkert1">Herkert 1997</xref>). In Canada, at the geographic scale of the province of Ontario, Bobolinks declined ~3&percnt; annually (65&percnt; overall) between 1968 and 2008 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSEWIC1">COSEWIC 2010</xref>), and were listed as Threatened, in particular due to a more rapid decline (7&percnt; annually; 52&percnt; overall) between 1998 and 2008 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSSARO1">COSSARO 2010</xref>). The designation of Bobolinks under the provincial Endangered Species Act of 2007 triggered the mandatory development of a recovery strategy, which recommended population targets for species listed under the Species at Risk in Ontario List (ESA 2007, Chapter 6, Section 11.(1)). The short-term recovery goal, determined in consultation with species experts and set out in the recovery strategy, is to slow the annual rate of population decline to an average less than or equal to &minus;1&percnt; annually, or less than or equal to &minus;10&percnt; over the first 10 yr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-McCracken1">McCracken et al. 2013</xref>).The objectives of our study were twofold. First, we compared regional Bobolink population trend estimates with those from broad-scale analyses, as used by COSEWIC and COSSARO for risk assessment, to identify the regions in the province contributing most substantially to provincial-level population declines. Second, we compared regional trends with the provincial recovery objective to identify priority areas for recovery strategy implementation.The study area covered a portion of Bird Conservation Region 13 (BCR13) in Ontario, Canada (43&deg;69&prime;N, 79&deg;45&prime;W; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Bobolinks are more abundant here than elsewhere nationally, and the population in this area comprises 10&ndash;12&percnt; of the global breeding population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSSARO1">COSSARO 2010</xref>). The study area covered all of the Mixedwood Plains Ecozone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Crins1">Crins et al. 2009</xref>). The climate here is mild and moist, with mean annual temperatures ranging from 2.8 to 9.4&deg;C, and 759&ndash;1,087 mm of precipitation per year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Mackey1">Mackey et al. 1996</xref>). There is a general gradient in climatic conditions (primarily decreasing temperatures and growing days) from southwest to northeast. The natural vegetation is mixed deciduous&ndash;evergreen forests and tolerant hardwood forests, including Carolinian forests in the south. However, 57&ndash;78&percnt; of the land base has been converted to agriculture, and 7&percnt; is urban.Relative abundance and distribution map for the Bobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) based on North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) data from 1987 to 2006 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Blancher1">Blancher 2009</xref>). The legend indicates the average number of birds per route per year calculated for each degree block, where white space &equals; no detection, and continuous gray with no black outlines (at north and south) &equals; no BBS data. The black rectangle encompasses the location of the study site in Ontario, Canada.The Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) consists of more than 3,000 39.4-km long roadside survey routes across Canada and the United States. Once annually, volunteers conduct point counts of all birds seen within a 0.4-km radius, or heard during a 3-min period, at intervals of approximately 0.8 km, for a total of 50 point counts per route (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Robbins1">Robbins et al. 1986</xref>). Auxiliary data include observers' identification numbers and weather during surveys. Data are available at the Breeding Bird Survey &ndash; Canadian Results webpage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ec.gc.ca" xlink:type="simple">www.ec.gc.ca</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-EnvironmentCanada1">Environment Canada 2010</xref>).Bobolinks are conspicuous while breeding in open farmland, and are easily sampled along roads, rendering the BBS data appropriate for analyzing geographic patterns in population trends for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Peterjohn1">Peterjohn 2003</xref>). To select a spatial resolution at which to address patterns in Bobolink population trends, we considered the applicability of results to further investigation of factors hypothesized to be driving Bobolink population trends, in order to aid with recovery strategy implementation. We therefore selected agricultural census divisions, because land-use statistics are summarized at this spatial extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-StatisticsCanada1">Statistics Canada 2011</xref>). However, a variety of geographic scales could be selected to accommodate species-specific research questions or to support regional conservation initiatives.A spatially explicit hierarchical modeling approach was used to accommodate known temporal and spatial correlations among survey routes, observers, and years. Spatial correlations among survey routes arise because of a tendency for areas that are closer geographically to be more similar than distant ones due to underlying environmental gradients or because of population-level processes, such as dispersal. Temporal correlations arise because counts on a given route are expected to be similar from one year to the next (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Thogmartin1">Thogmartin et al. 2006</xref>). A hierarchical approach also accounts for the effects of correlated observer error, as different perceptions and experiences of individuals influence counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Link1">Link and Sauer 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Thogmartin2">Thogmartin et al. 2004</xref>). The primary advantage of this technique is that it permits more precise trend estimates for areas with limited data, because the spatial dependencies between neighboring areas facilitate borrowing information from adjacent areas, effectively increasing the sample size on which trend estimates are based (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Bled1">Bled et al. 2013</xref>). This helps to improve the overall power of the model to predict trends by accounting for underlying geographic variation in the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Bahn1">Bahn et al. 2006</xref>).We estimated regional trends over the periods 1967&ndash;2011 and 1998&ndash;2011. The period 1967&ndash;2011 corresponded with time series of available land-use data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-StatisticsCanada1">Statistics Canada 2011</xref>), i.e. spatial covariates for subsequent analysis. The years 1998&ndash;2011 aligned with those cited in the federal (1968&ndash;2008; COSEWIC) and provincial risk assessments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSSARO1">COSSARO 2010</xref>). Annual Bobolink abundance on a survey route was indexed as the total number of birds counted over the 50 point counts. We excluded data from surveys that were completed under unacceptable conditions as outlined in the BBS Instructions Guide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-USGSPatuxentWildlifeResearchCenter1">USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center 1998</xref>), or if fewer than 10 yr of data were available throughout the entire period (1967&ndash;2011; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Corace1">Corace et al. 2009</xref>). These criteria resulted in point count data collected over 45 yr (<italic>t</italic>) by 200 observers (<italic>K</italic>) on 64 survey routes (<italic>i</italic>), distributed across 35 agricultural census divisions (<italic>c</italic>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-t01">Table 1</xref>).There is no closed-form expression for the parameter estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Royle2">Royle et al. 2002</xref>), so the model was fitted by iteration. Analyses were conducted using WinBUGS 1.4.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Lunn1">Lunn et al. 2000</xref>), a statistical package for conducting Bayesian inference with Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods (Gibbs sampling; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Link2">Link et al. 2002</xref>). Three chains with noninformative priors were run and, based on 50,000 samples from the posterior distribution of parameters subsequently, 10,000 iterations were discarded to obtain posterior samples of regional mean trends (&Delta;<italic><sub>c,a,b</sub></italic>) and conditional variance parameters of the CAR model (&sigma;<sup>2</sup><italic><sub>bt</sub></italic>); this determined the amount of spatial dependence between neighboring census divisions. Convergence was checked using the Gelman-Rubin diagnostic for assessing convergence in WinBUGS, which compared within-chain and between-chain variability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Brooks1">Brooks and Gelman 1998</xref>).A posterior predictive check was used to evaluate goodness-of-fit. We calculated a Bayesian <italic>P</italic>-value, which is defined as the probability of generating a test statistic from posterior predictions that is more extreme than that calculated from the observed data. A small Bayesian <italic>P</italic>-value (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.95) is indicative of poor model fit. Good model fit occurs when <italic>P</italic> approaches 0.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Gelman1">Gelman et al. 2003</xref>). Posterior predictive checks have been criticized because they require the double use of data. However, arguments have also been made in favor of posterior predictive checks, provided that their use is limited to studying model adequacy and not for making model comparison and inference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Meng1">Meng 1994</xref>).The posterior conditional variance (&sigma;<sup>2</sup><italic><sub>bt</sub></italic>) for the Gaussian CAR model was 1.57 (1.38&ndash;2.17 SD). This small conditional variance indicated strong residual dependence on neighboring census division values, which led to a smoother spatial structure in trend estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Lawson1">Lawson et al. 2003</xref>). The mean Bayesian <italic>P</italic>-value was 0.71, which indicated adequate model fit.Posterior samples of mean Bobolink population trends between 1967 and 2011 were predominantly negative; only 5 census divisions had slightly positive or neutral trends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). Six of 30 negative trend estimates had 95&percnt; credibility intervals (CI) that did not include 0&percnt; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f03">Figure 3</xref>A). These regions were clustered in southwestern Ontario (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>A, insert), and included agricultural census divisions Brant (3529), Perth (3531), Oxford (3532), Middlesex (3539), and Huron (3540), and an isolated area in south-central Ontario in the Kawartha Lakes region (3516). Of the census divisions that demonstrated evidence of population declines, only Perth had a trend estimate with a 95&percnt; CI that did not include &minus;1&percnt; (i.e. the short-term recovery goal).Posterior mean population trend estimates for the Bobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) from (<bold>A</bold>) 1967 to 2011, and (<bold>B</bold>) 1998 to 2011, mapped to agricultural census divisions in southern Ontario, Canada, using spatially explicit hierarchical models in a Bayesian statistical framework. Trends are expressed as percentages. Inserts bottom center: Maps of statistical significance, where areas in black indicate regions experiencing negative trends and 95&percnt; credibility intervals that do not overlap zero, areas in gray indicate positive trends and 95&percnt; credibility intervals that do not overlap zero, and white otherwise. Identification numbers on the census divisions are defined in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-t02">Table 2</xref>.Box plots of posterior mean trends (solid center line in box) for the Bobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) from (<bold>A</bold>) 1967 to 2011, and (<bold>B</bold>) 1998 to 2011, shown across 35 agricultural census divisions in Ontario, Canada (ordered from west to east and defined in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-t02">Table 2</xref>). The ends of the whiskers represent each 95&percnt; credibility interval. The horizontal solid black line indicates the zero trend line, and the dashed gray line indicates the recovery strategy short-term objective (&minus;1&percnt;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-McCracken1">McCracken et al. 2013</xref>).Posterior samples of mean Bobolink population trends between 1998 and 2011 were negative in 27 of 35 census divisions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>B), 3 of which (Leeds and Grenville &lsqb;3507&rsqb;, Kawartha Lakes &lsqb;3516&rsqb;, and Perth &lsqb;3531&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>B, insert) had 95&percnt; CI that did not include 0&percnt; or &minus;1&percnt; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f03">Figure 3</xref>B). Eight census divisions had slightly positive or neutral trends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>B).Our results demonstrate the capability of hierarchical Bayesian models to incorporate spatial data to obtain trend estimates for small geographic areas suited to focused management intervention. This modeling framework has important implications for conservation biologists, who often need robust estimates of population trends to assign risk and assess the feasibility of reaching population targets. Analyses performed at broader scales may mask regional variability in population trends and can inaccurately reflect the state of species population trends. In the case of Bobolinks, our models indicate that a majority of regional populations have not strongly declined, and, in some cases, have already met or exceeded the short-term recovery goal of slowing decline to &minus;1&percnt;. This is in contrast to provincial-level estimates, which depict strong declines over the same temporal intervals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-COSEWIC1">COSEWIC 2010</xref>); this is, in part, the result of trend homogenization over the spatial extent of Bobolinks in Ontario. Nevertheless, as regional trends were calculated using a subset of the provincial-scale BBS data, the power to detect significant changes in population size may have been reduced in these spatially segregated data. Similarly, credibility intervals flared on the regional trend estimates over the shorter timeframe that we analyzed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f03">Figure 3</xref>), further reducing the power to detect negative trends that may actually be present. Despite this, regions with CI that are clearly above or below the zero trend line may be of particular conservation interest.The regions that contributed most substantially to provincial-level declines were the agricultural census divisions of Perth and Kawartha Lakes, regardless of the time interval selected, and Leeds and Grenville for the 1998&ndash;2011 interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Factors often invoked to explain Bobolink population declines by Ontario stakeholders include habitat loss and hay harvest timing (D. Ethier and T. Nudds personal observation). Other threats include cattle trampling, pesticide exposure, habitat fragmentation, human activities associated with development, and nonbreeding ground effects. The regions identified here as having the strongest population declines coincide with portions of the province highly invested in cattle production (beef and dairy combined), and consequently have the largest amount of land devoted to hay and pastures relative to elsewhere in the province (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-StatisticsCanada1">Statistics Canada 2011</xref>). Changes to these industries have been realized in the past several decades. For example, the majority of new dairy barn construction is occurring in Perth and its surrounding counties, with a trend toward larger herds and fewer farms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Lang1">Lang 2011</xref>). Kawartha Lakes and Leeds and Greenville, on the other hand, have seen an overall decline in the number of dairy cattle on the landscape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-StatisticsCanada1">Statistics Canada 2011</xref>). In contrast, the areas experiencing neutral or increasing Bobolink population trends varied depending on the temporal interval selected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-f02">Figure 2</xref>), but consistently overlapped with Peterborough and Northumberland agricultural census divisions. These areas also have seen a general decline in the number of beef and dairy cattle, but a less obvious decline in the amount of land planted in hay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-StatisticsCanada1">Statistics Canada 2011</xref>). These anecdotal observations bring to light questions of whether and how changes to Ontario's cattle and other land-based industries influence Bobolink population dynamics, and how they vary temporally and spatially across the province. Although beyond the scope of this manuscript, future investigations relating land-based data (e.g., agriculture, forestry, and urban development) to regionally specific trend estimates could provide resource managers with a basis for examining factors responsible for Bobolink declines and for assessing alternative regionally specific management actions, which could ultimately be used to inform where and how to invest in conservation efforts to aid in reaching recovery targets.We caution that by identifying areas with the greatest levels of population declines, we are not implying that other areas are unimportant to Bobolinks. For example, investing in the areas with the greatest population declines may be undesirable if certain conservation measures in other areas will return greater rewards (i.e. increased fecundity, decreased mortality, or more habitat) for less investment. However, from the perspective of monitoring the effectiveness of recovery actions, it may prove useful to differentially invest in adaptive management strategies in the agricultural census divisions with the most pronounced declines, so that managers can more effectively assess the response of Bobolinks to alternative management actions. Such strategies might include payment schemes or tax incentives for farmers who adopt grassland bird&ndash;friendly land management practices, or land acquisition programs to increase the amount of habitat or decrease fragmentation. Regardless, management strategy selection ought to be contingent on regional factors identified as being important drivers of population declines.Including autocorrelation in our model not only ensured that statistical assumptions were better met, but also improved the predictive power of the model by including information from neighborhood locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Bahn1">Bahn et al. 2006</xref>). The selection of the neighborhood structure was therefore critical for spatially explicit parameter estimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Thogmartin2">Thogmartin et al. 2004</xref>). We assumed that the spatial model depended only on the neighborhood structure, and not on the distance between areas. Thus, the neighborhood structure used here may not have fully reflected underlying environmental autocorrelations. Alternative spatial models include regular grids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Bled1">Bled et al. 2013</xref>), geostatistical interpolation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Diggle1">Diggle et al. 1998</xref>), continuous surface models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Kelsall1">Kelsall and Wakefield 2002</xref>), and the replacement of spatial autocorrelation structure with appropriate environmental covariates at a scale relevant to underlying biological processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-Thogmartin2">Thogmartin et al. 2004</xref>). Although different spatial models are available, the irregular spatial scheme that we used here allowed us to estimate population trends for specific areas while also accommodating future model development, within which alternative hypotheses regarding causes of decline can be assessed using land-use data. This modeling technique is therefore valuable to a broad range of species, as there is often a need to amalgamate data from different sources to a common spatial extent in order to answer ecological questions at a scale that aligns with areas appropriate for management implementation.In general, our work highlights the influence that spatiotemporal variability may have on the apparent population dynamics of a species of conservation concern. Overlooking this variability could result in inappropriate risk designation or unrealistic management targets. By resolving scalar discrepancy in trend estimation, risk assessments and management targets can be more appropriately assigned to reflect the current state of local conditions. This will help to avoid wasted effort, unnecessary use of public funds, and the erosion of public confidence in policy decisions. The statistical framework used here generates spatially explicit estimates of population trends that can be used to test alternative mechanistic hypotheses about regional drivers of population change. Once statistical relationships have been established between environmental covariates and population trends, these models can further be used to conduct management strategy evaluations, which explore the predicted consequences of alternative conservation actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-545-MilnerGulland1">Milner-Gulland et al. 2010</xref>). Such models ought to prove important in the development of evidence-based management plans for Bobolinks in Ontario, and for species of conservation concern elsewhere.We acknowledge the countless volunteers involved in collecting Breeding Bird Survey data. Thanks to J. Sayers, V. La, and 2 anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on earlier drafts of this manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Funding for this work was provided in part by the Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources and Forestry's Species at Risk Stewardship Fund to T.D.N. and D.M.E., the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) grant PGSD3-420471-2010 to D.M.E., and the University of Guelph. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript. None of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) point count data collected for the Bobolink (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</named-content></italic>) in Ontario, Canada, over 45 years on 64 survey routes, distributed among 35 agricultural census divisions. Dots indicate the years and routes for which data were available for analysis.Agricultural census division identification numbers and their corresponding names and locations in Ontario, Canada.