Morphometrics of mid-Atlantic dabbling ducks for use in thermoregulation modelsThe effects of winter weather on the behavior and energy reserves of Black Ducks in MaineHeat transfer in biological systemsWinter survival of female American Black Ducks on the Atlantic coastThe significance of body mass to female dabbling ducks during late incubationThe relationship between body mass and survival of wintering CanvasbacksA new model to estimate daily energy expenditure for wintering waterfowlMississippi alluvial valleyDoes winter food limit populations of migratory birds?Estimating habitat carrying capacity for migrating and wintering waterfowl: Considerations, pitfalls and improvementsMetabolic rates and heart rate&ndash;metabolism relationships in the Black Duck (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>)Bioenergetics modeling is a popular tool used by waterfowl biologists to estimate carrying capacity based on food energy availability and daily energy expenditure (DEE). For wintering waterfowl, estimates of DEE may incorporate a cost of thermoregulation (CT) component, which accounts for metabolic heat production when ambient temperatures fall below a species-specific Lower Critical Temperature (LCT). Typically, DEE estimates have utilized either a fixed CT component or a simple CT model based solely on the magnitude of the difference between ambient temperature and LCT. Using a more complex CT model that accounts for differential heat loss from individual body regions due to temperature, wind speed, and contact with air or water may provide more detailed estimates of CT and, in turn, carrying capacity. However, such models required detailed morphometrics as model inputs in addition to environmental data. We present morphometrics for 8 dabbling duck species for use in thermoregulation models, as well as regression equations that may substitute for measurements of unmeasured species. We compared CT values produced via simple and complex CT models for American Black Ducks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas rubripes</named-content></italic>) wintering on the Delaware Bayshore, 2011&ndash;2013. We found that the complex CT model produced significantly higher CT estimates (5.38 &plusmn; SE 0.38 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> hr<sup>&minus;1</sup>) compared with the simple model (1.26 &plusmn; 0.04 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> hr<sup>&minus;1</sup>). Applying these CT values to bioenergetics models for American Black Ducks wintering in southern New Jersey suggested that this disparity in CT could produce substantial differences in estimated carrying capacity. Thus, we recommend that researchers consider incorporating detailed CT models into their estimates of DEE to reduce bias in carrying capacity estimates.El modelamiento bioenerg&eacute;tico es una herramienta popular entre los bi&oacute;logos que estudian aves acu&aacute;ticas para estimar la capacidad de carga basada en la disponibilidad de energ&iacute;a y en el gasto energ&eacute;tico diario (<italic>GED</italic>). Para los anseriformes invernantes los estimados del <italic>GED</italic> pueden incorporar un componente del costo de termorregulaci&oacute;n (<italic>CT</italic>), que tiene en cuenta la producci&oacute;n metab&oacute;lica de calor cuando las temperaturas ambientales caen por debajo de la temperatura cr&iacute;tica m&iacute;nima (<italic>TCM</italic>) de cada especie. Generalmente los estimados del <italic>GED</italic> han usado un componente fijo del <italic>CT</italic> o un modelo simple del <italic>CT</italic> basado solamente en la magnitud de la diferencia entre la temperatura ambiental y la <italic>TCM</italic>. El uso de un modelo m&aacute;s complejo del <italic>CT</italic> que considere las diferencias en la p&eacute;rdida de calor entre regiones del cuerpo debidas a la temperatura, velocidad del viento y al contacto con aire o agua podr&iacute;a llevar a estimados m&aacute;s detallados del <italic>CT</italic> y, a su vez, de la capacidad de carga. Sin embargo, tales modelos requieren datos detallados de morfometr&iacute;a como base, adem&aacute;s de la inclusi&oacute;n de datos ambientales. Presentamos datos de morfometr&iacute;a de 8 especies de patos de superficie para su uso en modelos de termorregulaci&oacute;n, as&iacute; como ecuaciones de regresi&oacute;n que pueden usarse para sustituir las medidas en especies no medidas. Comparamos los valores de <italic>CT</italic> producidos con modelos simples y complejos para la poblaci&oacute;n invernante de <italic>Anas rubriceps</italic> en la bah&iacute;a de Delaware entre 2011 y 2013. Encontramos que el modelo complejo de <italic>CT</italic> produjo estimados de <italic>CT</italic> significativamente mayores (5.38 &plusmn; DE 0.38 kJ/ave/hora) comparados con el modelo simple (1.26 &plusmn; 0.04 kJ/ave/hora). La aplicaci&oacute;n de estos valores de <italic>CT</italic> a los modelos bioenerg&eacute;ticos para la poblaci&oacute;n de <italic>A. rubriceps</italic> del sur de Nueva Jersey sugiri&oacute; que esta disparidad en el <italic>CT</italic> podr&iacute;a producir diferencias sustanciales en los estimados de capacidad de carga. Por esto, recomendamos que los investigadores consideren la incorporaci&oacute;n de modelos detallados del <italic>CT</italic> en sus estimados de <italic>GED</italic> para reducir el sesgo en los estimados de capacidad de carga.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> bioenerg&eacute;tica, tama&ntilde;o corporal, capacidad de carga, gasto de energ&iacute;a, anseriformesAccording to the winter food limitation hypothesis, migratory bird populations may be limited by food availability in the wintering period, when food resources are typically scarce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Sherry1">Sherry et al. 2005</xref>). Wildlife managers seeking to conserve wintering bird populations must therefore consider the available food energy present on the landscape, and strategies aiming to improve winter food resources may focus on increasing the amount of wintering habitat. Waterfowl biologists often use bioenergetics models to estimate carrying capacity (based on energy supply and demand) and to determine the amount and type of habitat required to meet North American Waterfowl Management Plan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-U.S.FishandWildlifeService1">U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 2012</xref>) population objectives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Williams1">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). In such models, energy demand is typically expressed as daily energy expenditure (DEE), a metric that represents the energy required to support an individual bird for one day. One method of quantifying DEE is to construct time&ndash;energy budgets by quantifying (1) the proportion of time a species engages in various behaviors, (2) a behavior-specific increase over its resting metabolic rate, and (3) heat loss due to cost of thermoregulation (hereafter CT; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Albright1">Albright et al. 1983</xref>).Efforts to model DEE largely utilize either fixed CT values or simple thermoregulation models that include a CT component if ambient temperature is below a given Lower Critical Temperature (LCT), at which point the animal incurs an additional energetic cost due to heat loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Cramer1">Cramer 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Jones1">Jones 2012</xref>). However, more detailed models that account for various environmental and physiological factors may improve DEE estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Williams1">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). In modeling DEE of wintering waterfowl, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref> applied a heat transfer model proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Birkebak1">Birkebak (1966)</xref> to their thermoregulatory calculations that accounted for (1) differential heat loss from various body regions by creating rough geometric approximations of the head, neck, and body; and (2) variation in CT from these regions due to the difference in specific heat of air and water, resulting in a higher rate of heat loss for body regions in contact with water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams 2005</xref>). This approach requires a series of morphometrics from the species of interest, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref> only reported these values for Buffleheads (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bucephala albeola</named-content></italic>) to employ their modeling efforts. CT values for additional waterfowl species would be useful for refining DEE estimates and bioenergetics models. Consequently, we summarize body measurement data from 8 dabbling duck species (genus <italic>Anas</italic>) to better estimate thermoregulation in future DEE models and carrying capacity estimates. Additionally, we use this information to assess whether predictive estimations based on body mass for other duck species can be used as a surrogate for taking multiple body measurements for other waterfowl species not yet measured. Our study will facilitate the use of more-complex CT models in management and conservation applications, which in turn improve estimates of DEE and carrying capacity, and lead to more accurate estimates of wintering habitat requirements.We collected morphometrics using a caliper ruler from live adult American Black Ducks (hereafter &ldquo;black ducks&rdquo;; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15), Mallards (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 2, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 2), Northern Pintails (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. acuta</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 2, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 1), Northern Shovelers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. clypeata</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 2, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 2), American Wigeon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. americana</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 2, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 2), Green-winged Teal (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. crecca</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 1, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 2), Blue-winged Teal (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. discors</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 1, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 1), and Gadwall (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. strepera</named-content></italic>; <italic>n</italic><sub>male</sub> &equals; 1, <italic>n</italic><sub>female</sub> &equals; 2) in March 2014 and January 2015 following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Birkebak1">Birkebak (1966)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref>. Measurements for black ducks were obtained from captive-bred, wild-strain individuals at the Patuxent Wildlife Research Center (Laurel, Maryland, USA; 39&deg;03&prime;N, 76&deg;49&prime;W). Morphometric data for all other species were collected from captive birds at Sylvan Heights Bird Park (Scotland Neck, North Carolina, USA; 36&deg;08&prime;N, 77&deg;24&prime;W). Measurements included length, width, height, and integument (feather) depth (mm) for the head, neck, and body regions. Integument depths were determined by averaging 6 measurements taken at equidistant locations around the thickest portion of each region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-f01">Figure 1</xref>). We summarized morphometric data by sex and species for use in CT calculations. We were unable to obtain sex-specific data for black ducks; thus, black duck measurements are presented for combined sexes only. Procuring body measurements for use in CT calculations may be prohibitive if captive individuals are not available, and researchers may be forced to subjectively assign values or choose a less-complex thermoregulatory model. Thus, to facilitate use of more-detailed models, we derived predictive equations for morphometric variables by regressing mean body measurements for each species against mean body mass (kg) estimates. Due to logistical limitations, we were unable to obtain body mass data from these individuals; thus, we obtained mean body mass estimates from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre (2014)</xref> for male and female dabbling ducks for use in this analysis.Morphometrics collected following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Birkebak1">Birkebak (1966)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref>. A &equals; head length, B &equals; head height, C &equals; head width, D &equals; body width, F &equals; body length, G &equals; body height, H &equals; neck length, I &equals; neck width, J &equals; neck height. Integument depth measurements are taken at 6 equidistant points around the pictured rings and averaged. Mallard images courtesy of Autodesk (San Rafael, California, USA).Mean &plusmn; standard error of morphometrics for dabbling duck species in the mid-Atlantic. Measurements were taken from captive adult male (M) and female (F) individuals in March 2014 and January 2015. Symbols (denoted in brackets) represent body measurements in thermoregulation equations proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Birkebak1">Birkebak (1966)</xref> and used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref> in daily energy expenditure calculations <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1650/CONDOR-15-63.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">(Supplemental Material Appendix A)</ext-link>.<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-t01">Table 1</xref> presents the mean &plusmn; standard error of morphometrics for males, females, and combined sexes of 8 dabbling duck species common to the mid-Atlantic, USA, region. Measurements collected from males were typically larger than those from females; however, small sample sizes precluded statistical comparisons. Regression analysis showed that mean body mass explained the greatest amount of variation in the body width (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.68), body length (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.66), body height (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.52), head height (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.52), and neck length (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.52) variables (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-f02">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-t02">Table 2</xref>). By contrast, body mass accounted for little variation in the head width, neck width, or various integument depth variables (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &le; 0.08). For wintering black ducks in Delaware, mean CT over the winter period was estimated to be 1.26 &plusmn; 0.04 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> hr<sup>&minus;1</sup> (30.24 &plusmn; SE 0.96 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup>) using the simple CT model, and 5.38 &plusmn; 0.38 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> hr<sup>&minus;1</sup> (129.12 &plusmn; 9.12 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup>) using the complex CT model. A paired <italic>t</italic>-test indicated that CT was significantly higher using the complex model (<italic>t</italic><sub>1725</sub> <italic>&equals;</italic> 11.4, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Scatterplots and linear regression of mean morphometrics (cm) vs. mean body mass (kg) for several body measurement variables used to calculate energetic cost of thermoregulation. Measurements were taken from captive male and female adults from 8 dabbling duck species in March 2014 and January 2015.Regression equations and associated coefficient of determination (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>) for various morphometrics obtained from 8 captive dabbling duck species in March 2014 and January 2015. The term &ldquo;<italic>m</italic>&rdquo; represents mean body mass (kg) per species.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Cramer1">Cramer (2009)</xref> estimated that DEE for black ducks wintering in southern New Jersey was 1,187.57 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup> using a fixed CT of 140.65 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup>; thus, DEE was 1,046.93 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup> not including CT. Using our model estimates, we calculated a DEE of 1,077.17 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup> using the simple CT model, and 1,176.05 kJ bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> day<sup>&minus;1</sup> using the complex CT model. Based on an energy availability of 6.57 &times; 10<sup>10</sup> kJ over the winter period (mean of estimates for southern New Jersey in October, January, and April, 2006&ndash;2008; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Cramer1">Cramer 2009</xref>), there were 6.10 &times; 10<sup>7</sup> DUD available using the simple CT model, but only 5.59 &times; 10<sup>7</sup> DUD using the complex model.Bioenergetics models rely on accurate estimates of DEE to produce meaningful estimates of carrying capacity. Including cost of thermoregulation in these models reduces bias in DEE estimates for waterfowl, which often experience temperatures below LCT wintering in the mid-Atlantic and northeast regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Williams1">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). Additionally, thermoregulatory costs may account for a large percentage (&gt;20&percnt; in some cases) of DEE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams 2005</xref>), suggesting that use of improved thermoregulation estimates obtained via more-detailed models could impact DEE estimates significantly. The summarized morphometric data we report expand upon those provided for Buffleheads in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-McKinney1">McKinney and McWilliams (2005)</xref> and will prove useful in further refining carrying capacity estimates for wintering dabbling ducks, which in turn informs management strategies for wintering habitats.Coefficients of determination (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>) produced by our regression analysis suggest that there is a weak to moderate (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &ap; 0.5) linear relationship between mean body mass and morphometrics in most cases, with integument depth measurements presenting exceptionally weak relationships (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-t02">Table 2</xref>). The majority of heat loss due to thermoregulation occurs in the body region, because it has the greatest surface area of any part of the animal. Since our regression equations performed best when predicting measurements from the body region, we believe that these models will provide useful morphometric estimates for use in DEE calculations. Additionally, our case study estimating CT for wintering black ducks using simple and complex CT models showed that using a more-detailed model may produce a significantly different CT estimate than simpler, more commonly used models&mdash;in this case, a drastically (&gt;400&percnt;) larger estimate, which can result in significant changes to DEE estimates. For example, applying the complex CT model to existing bioenergetics models for black ducks in southern New Jersey resulted in 5,100,000 fewer available DUD (an 8.36&percnt; decrease) over the winter period compared with using the simple CT model. Complex CT estimates therefore provide a more conservative approach in calculating available DUD.If simple CT models tend to overestimate available DUD, there may be significant ramifications for managers attempting to provide adequate wintering habitat, because in reality carrying capacity is likely lower (and perhaps drastically so) than the estimates produced by typical models. In this case, managers may allocate insufficient wintering habitat area to meet population goals. Additionally, because increased energy expenditure may lead to decreased body mass, it is possible that higher energy expenditure due to CT may impact survival in the wintering period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Haramis1">Haramis et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Conroy1">Conroy et al. 1989</xref>), and potentially in the breeding period if body mass changes persist between seasons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-644-Gloutney1">Gloutney and Clark 1991</xref>). Thus, because CT may often comprise a significant portion of DEE for wintering waterfowl, we recommend that researchers consider incorporating detailed thermoregulatory estimates into bioenergetics modeling efforts in order to produce the most informed possible estimates of carrying capacity.We thank the Patuxent Wildlife Research Center and Sylvan Heights Bird Park for providing access to their birds and for the opportunity to conduct this research, and J. McPherson and M. Livolsi for their assistance in data collection.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This study was funded by Ducks Unlimited, Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control's Division of Fish and Wildlife through the Federal Aid in Wildlife Restoration Act, Waterfowl Research Foundation, Camp Fire Conservation Fund, and the University of Delaware.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> Birds were handled in accordance with USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center ethics code ACUC &num;2011-11 and Sylvan Park internal guidelines.