Available data support protection of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher under the Endangered Species ActA review of the races of the Traill's FlycatcherThe seventy-five percent rule for subspeciesGenomic and morphological analysis of a semipermeable avian hybrid zone suggests asymmetrical introgression of a sexual signalGenetic variation in the endangered Southwestern Willow FlycatcherConsidering evolutionary processes in conservation biologyHZAR: Hybrid zone analysis using an R software packageSouthwestern Willow Flycatcher breeding site and territory summary, 2006Avian subspecies: Summary and prospectusA multiscaled model of Southwestern Willow Flycatcher breeding habitatModeling the dynamic habitat and breeding population of Southwestern Willow FlycatcherA critique of Wang Yong and Finch's field identifications of Willow Flycatchers subspecies in New MexicoThe role of ecologic diversification in sibling speciation of <italic>Empidonax</italic> flycatchers (Tyrannidae): Multigene evidence from mtDNASongs of the Alder Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax alnorum</named-content></italic>) and Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>) are innateInterpreting negative results with taxonomic and conservation implications: Another look at the distinctness of coastal California GnatcatchersSpecies concepts in ornithologyApplications of mitochondrial DNA analysis in conservation: A critical reviewNull expectations in subspecies diagnosisDiagnosability versus mean differences of Sage Sparrow subspeciesUsing molecular genetic markers to resolve a subspecies boundary: The northern boundary of the southwestern Willow Flycatcher in the Four Corner statesGeographic variation in the plumage coloration of Willow Flycatchers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>Geographic variation in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content></italic>Critique of the evolutionarily significant unit as a definition for &ldquo;distinct population segments&rdquo; under the US Endangered Species ActSubspecies as a meaningful taxonomic rank in avian classificationSpecies conservation and systematics: The dilemma of subspeciesGeographic variation in the song of Willow Flycatchers: Differentiation between <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>Isolating mechanisms between populations of Traill's Flycatcher<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>: An endangered subspeciesPolicy regarding the recognition of distinct vertebrate population segments under the Endangered Species ActEnvironmental niche equivalency versus conservatism: Quantitative approaches to niche evolutionENMTools: A toolbox for comparative studies of environmental niche modelsENMTools User Manual v1.3The subspecies concept and its taxonomic applicationThe genic view of the process of speciationThe effect of marker choice on estimated levels of introgression across an avian (Pipridae: <italic>Manacus</italic>) hybrid zoneThe role of subspecies in obscuring avian biological diversity and misleading conservation policyGenetics, morphology, and ecological niche modeling do not support the subspecies status of the endangered Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>)Phylogeography of the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>) using multilocus DNA sequences and ecological niche modeling: Implications for conservation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> argued there was no evidence for genetic, morphological, or ecological differentiation between the federally endangered Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>) and other Willow Flycatcher subspecies. Using the same data, we show there is a step-cline in both the frequency of a mtDNA haplotype and in plumage variation roughly concordant with the currently recognized boundary between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t adastus,</italic> the subspecies with which it shares the longest common boundary. The geographical pattern of plumage variation is also concordant with previous song analyses differentiating those 2 subspecies and identified birds in one low-latitude, high-elevation site in Arizona as the northern subspecies. We also demonstrate that the ecological niche modeling approach used by Zink yields the same result whether applied to the 2 flycatcher subspecies or to 2 unrelated species, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and Yellow Warbler (<italic>Setophaga petechia</italic>). As a result, any interpretation of those results as evidence for lack of ecological niche differentiation among Willow Flycatcher subspecies would also indicate no differentiation among recognized species and would therefore be an inappropriate standard for delineating subspecies. We agree that many analytical techniques now available to examine genetic, morphological, and ecological differentiation would improve our understanding of the distinctness (or lack thereof) of Willow Flycatcher subspecies, but we argue that currently available evidence supports protection of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher under the Endangered Species Act.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> argument&oacute; que no hab&iacute;a evidencia para la diferenciaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica, morfol&oacute;gica o ecol&oacute;gica entre el ave federalmente amenazada <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic> y otras subespecies de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic>. Usando los mismo datos, demostramos que existen clinas marcadas en la frecuencia de un haplotipo de ADN mitocondrial y en la variaci&oacute;n del plumaje que concuerdan en t&eacute;rminos generales con el l&iacute;mite actualmente reconocido entre <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> y <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, la subespecie con la que comparte el l&iacute;mite de distribuci&oacute;n com&uacute;n m&aacute;s largo. El patr&oacute;n geogr&aacute;fico de la variaci&oacute;n en plumaje tambi&eacute;n concuerda con an&aacute;lisis previos de cantos que diferencian estas dos subespecies e identifican aves en un sitio de baja latitud pero alta elevaci&oacute;n en Arizona como pertenecientes a la subespecie del norte. Tambi&eacute;n demostramos que la aproximaci&oacute;n de modelado de nicho ecol&oacute;gico usada por <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> arroja los mismos resultados si se aplica a ambas subespecies o a dos especies no relacionadas, <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> y <italic>Setophaga petechia</italic>. Como resultado, cualquier interpretaci&oacute;n de esos resultados como evidencia de una falta de diferenciaci&oacute;n de nicho ecol&oacute;gico entre subespecies de <italic>E. trailli</italic> tambi&eacute;n indicar&iacute;a que no hay diferenciaci&oacute;n entre subespecies reconocidas, y por ende ser&iacute;a un criterio inapropiado para delinear subespecies. Coincidimos en que muchas t&eacute;cnicas anal&iacute;ticas disponibles para examinar la diferenciaci&oacute;n gen&eacute;tica, morfol&oacute;gica y ecol&oacute;gica pueden mejorar nuestro entendimiento de las diferencias (o falta de ellas) entre subespecies de <italic>E. trailli</italic>, pero aducimos que la evidencia disponible actualmente sustenta la protecci&oacute;n de <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> bajo el Acta de Especies Amenazadas.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> Acta de Especies Amenazadas, ADN mitocondrial, canto, coloraci&oacute;n del plumaje, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content>,</italic> modelado de nicho, subespeciesA continuing challenge in conservation biology is defining what constitutes an endangered population. Although originally written to protect species, the Endangered Species Act (ESA) was amended in 1973 to include &ldquo;any subspecies of fish or wildlife or plants, and any distinct population segment of any species of vertebrate fish or wildlife which interbreeds when mature.&rdquo; This amendment stimulated considerable debate about how to define &ldquo;distinct population segments&rdquo; (DPSs) and brought the act into the long-standing debate among taxonomists of whether subspecies were valid taxonomic entities and, if so, how to define them. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Moritz1">Moritz (1994)</xref>, building on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Ryder1">Ryder's (1986)</xref> initial concept that conservation units protected under the ESA should represent evolutionary significant units (ESUs), argued reciprocal monophyly of mitochondrial genes could be a uniform standard by which ESUs could be recognized, while recognizing that management units below ESUs might also be important conservation targets. Others argued that adhering strictly to the requirement of reciprocal monophyly was overly restrictive and could ignore important differences among populations in adaptive genes or in phenotypic (both morphological and behavioral) characters (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Pennock1">Pennock and Dimmick 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Crandall1">Crandall et al. 2000</xref>). These debates paralleled those concerning the validity of subspecies, with some arguing that taxonomic ranks below the species level were impossible to define unambiguously and therefore of little utility (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Wilson1">Wilson and Brown 1953</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-McKitrick1">McKittrick and Zink 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink1">Zink 2004</xref>) whereas others argued that subspecies could reflect important population differentiation but needed to be defined based on quantitative, statistically defensible assessments (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Patten2">Patten and Unitt 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Haig1">Haig and Winker 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Remsen1">Remsen 2010</xref>). The authors arguing in favor of subspecies stressed that they needed to be quantifiably &ldquo;diagnosable,&rdquo; and several built on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Amadon1">Amadon's (1949)</xref> recommendation that subspecies meet the criterion that &ldquo;75&percnt; of a population effectively must lie outside 99&percnt; of the range of other populations for a given defining character or set of characters&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Patten2">Patten and Unitt 2002</xref>), although they differed on whether 75&percnt; or some higher value should be the standard.An important highlight in the 1973 amendment is that subspecies and DPSs are not reproductively isolated and, therefore, gene flow among adjoining populations will necessarily result in a complex boundary where genes and the phenotypic traits associated with them intergrade, making designations of subspecies and DPS boundaries difficult. Much like within hybrid zones between species, genes and phenotypic traits may move between adjoining subspecies at different rates and unequally in different directions, often yielding complex, indistinct boundaries between populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Yuri1">Yuri et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre et al. 2014</xref>). Within a subspecies boundary area, however, some traits should show a nonlinear break in frequency over geographic space (step clines) that would distinguish a subspecies boundary from the gradual, linear change in genetic and phenotypic frequencies (smooth clines) found in many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Patten1">Patten 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Remsen1">Remsen 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-McCormack1">McCormack and Maley 2015</xref>).In a recent commentary, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> argued that the current subspecies designation of the Southwestern Willow Flycatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Empidonax traillii</named-content> extimus</italic>) was not supported by genetics, morphology, or ecological niche modeling and, therefore, the subspecies did not merit protection under the ESA. Determining taxonomic affinities within <italic>Empidonax</italic> flycatchers is challenging because of the lack of, or subtlety in, differences in plumage and other morphological measurements among taxa. Song, which is inherited in these flycatchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma 1984</xref>), has been useful in distinguishing several sibling species that show little morphological differentiation. Genetic studies have clarified relationships among some taxa and have supported the hypothesis that species may separate spatially by selecting different habitats (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Johnson1">Johnson and Cicero 2002</xref>). Within <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic>, 4 subspecies are typically recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>): <italic>E. t. traillii</italic> ranging through the northern half of the eastern United States to a westward boundary abutting <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> in Colorado, Wyoming, and Montana; <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> ranging through the mountain and basin areas of the west to a boundary with <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> along the Sierra Nevada mountains; <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> extending along the Pacific coast from central California northward to southern Canada; and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> in the southwestern United States and northernmost Mexico. As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref>, these subspecies were initially described based on qualitative differences in plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1951</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>), and subsequent quantitative studies of plumage, song, and genetics have not sampled evenly across the range of the species, with most work instead focusing on the boundary between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Busch1">Busch et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>). We disagree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> contention that no evidence exists to support the distinctness of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. In this paper, we use available evidence and reanalysis of the same data used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> to critique the arguments he presented.Previous genetic studies of Willow Flycatchers based on amplified fragment length polymorphisms (AFLPs) and mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) found no fixed differences among putative Southwestern Willow Flycatcher populations and populations to the north (e.g., no reciprocal monophyly; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Busch1">Busch et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>). One mtDNA haplotype, however, was argued to show a nonlinear change in frequency with latitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">figure 3</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> asserted that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> had actually graphed expected frequencies of the C-group mtDNA haplotypes derived from a model based on the combined effects of latitude and elevation rather than the raw frequencies. In fact, it was <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> who graphed the modeled values based on latitude and elevation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f01">Figure 1</xref>A). We graphed the actual haplotype frequencies from table 2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f01">Figure 1</xref>B) and agree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> that there seemed to be a break in haplotype frequency between 36&deg; and 38&deg;N. We then used the package Hybrid Zone Analysis for R (HZAR; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Derryberry1">Derryberry et al. 2014</xref>) to determine the maximum likelihood cline and cline center based on sites sampled by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref>.<bold>(A)</bold> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f02">Figure 2</xref> from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> that was erroneously reported as C-haplotype frequencies vs. latitude but was in fact the estimated frequencies of that haplotype based on a model of latitude and elevation combined. <bold>(B)</bold> The true C-group haplotype frequencies vs. latitude. <bold>(C)</bold> The maximum likelihood cline and 95&percnt; credible cline region for C-haplotype frequencies along a roughly linear eastern subset of 8 sample locations from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> running from northwestern Colorado to southwestern New Mexico, estimated using HZAR. <bold>(D)</bold> A western subset of 11 sample locations running from northern Utah to central Arizona. Maximum likelihood centers are indicated by black arrows and 95&percnt; CI as the black bar atop the arrow in <bold>(C)</bold> and <bold>(D)</bold>.<bold>(A)</bold> Geographical distribution of mitochondrial DNA haplotypes in Willow Flycatchers as reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref>. Small circles represent individuals at sites where &lt;5 individuals were sampled; pie charts represent sites where 5&ndash;15 individuals were sampled, with size of pie chart reflecting sample size. Dashed line approximates the currently recognized subspecies boundary between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and subspecies to the north. Gray rectangles represent the 95&percnt; CI around the cline center as estimated by Package HZAR along each of 3 roughly linear north&ndash;south transects. <bold>(B)</bold> Gene tree of mtDNA cytochrome-b haplotypes modified from figure 2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref>. Each circle represents a unique haplotype, with lines connecting them indicating their inferred evolutionary relationship based on maximum parsimony. <bold>(C)</bold> The maximum likelihood cline and 95&percnt; credible cline region for C-haplotype frequencies vs. distance along a roughly linear series of 8 sample locations from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref> running from southern California (0 km) to northern Oregon (1490 km). The black bar indicates the 95&percnt; CI for cline center.Identity test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren2">Warren et al. 2010</xref>) comparing <bold>(A)</bold> <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (arrow), and <bold>(B)</bold> <italic>E. t. extimu</italic>s and Yellow Warbler (<italic>S. petechia</italic>) within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (arrow), compared to the distribution of Schoener's <italic>D</italic> niche differentiation values expected by chance (black bars in both). The closer to 1, the more similar 2 niches are. Niche overlap is significantly less than expected in each case. Background test of <bold>(C)</bold> <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> vs. random locations drawn from within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>, and <bold>(D)</bold> Yellow Warbler within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> compared to random locations within the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> to those expected by chance (black bars). The niche overlap is within that expected by chance based on availability of environmental niche space in each range, although in the case of the 2 flycatcher species only 4 of the 100 repetitions were lower than the observed value.HZAR fits molecular and morphological data to equilibrium geographic cline models using the Metropolis&ndash;Hastings Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm. One assumption of HZAR is that samples are collected along a linear transect perpendicular to the boundary between species. To meet this assumption, we used C-haplotype frequencies from a subset of sites sampled by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> that approximated 2 north&ndash;south lines, 1 containing 11 sites and the other 8 sites. One line ran from northern Utah along the Colorado River drainage to the San Pedro River in Arizona, while the other ran from northwestern Colorado and ended in southwestern New Mexico. We then analyzed each dataset separately as an independent test of where the cline center lay. The 2 maximum-likelihood clines generated by the 2 datasets were similar in shape, with the eastern transect estimating the cline center near 36&deg;N with a 95&percnt; confidence interval (CI) running from 34.3&deg; to 37.5&deg;N and the western transect estimating cline center near 36.5&deg;N with 95&percnt; CI running from 35.3&deg; to 37.8&deg;N (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f01">Figure 1</xref>C and D).To illustrate where these cline center estimates were relative to the geographic pattern of mtDNA variation and to the currently recognized subspecies boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2002</xref>) between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and subspecies to the north, we combined genetic data available in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton1">Paxton (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f02">Figure 2</xref>). We then estimated cline center for C-haplotype frequencies along another set of 8 sites running from southern California to northern Oregon using Package HZAR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f02">Figure 2</xref>C) and plotted its 95&percnt; CI cline center estimate on the same map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f02">Figure 2</xref>A). Together these data indicate a break in haplotype frequency roughly concordant with the boundary between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> as currently recognized by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS (2002)</xref> and also indicate a transition in haplotype frequencies consistent with a step cline rather than the smooth cline suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref>.Environmental niche modeling (ENM) links geographic occurrence data with GIS data layers and has become an important tool in conservation biology. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> used an ENM approach developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren1">Warren et al. (2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren3">2011</xref>) to test for niche differentiation between <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. The first step, the identity test, compares the niche similarity indices (<italic>I</italic> or Schoener's <italic>D</italic>) derived from the ENMs of the 2 putative populations and then generates a null distribution based on ENMs generated from randomized draws from the pooled locations. If the similarity indices of the 2 putative populations are significantly lower than expected from the null distribution, the 2 populations are considered to have distinct niches. Because allopatric populations may differ in the identity test simply because of differences in the relative availability of habitat types, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren1">Warren et al. (2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren3">2011</xref>) recommended a second test, the background test, to control for these potentially confounding factors. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> found strong support for niche differentiation between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> based on the identity test but no support based on the background test. He then argued that the Willow Flycatcher &ldquo;likely has a broad ecological (climatic) tolerance, at least in the area studied, and does not show significant ecological divergence in climate niche dimensions.&rdquo;Niche models are sensitive both to the accuracy of the georeferencing of occurrence points as well as to the scale at which climatic variables are measured. For the occurrence data in his models, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> used flycatcher presence data gleaned in part from the Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) and 19 climatic variables describing temperature and precipitation interpolated at the 1 km<sup>2</sup> scale from the WorldClim bioclimatic database. BBS surveys consist of 50 stop locations along a 24.5 mile (39.4 km) route surveyed annually. Although latitude and longitude are available for the beginning point of each route, they are not available for individual stops along that route. Thus, if start location coordinates were used in the niche-modeling exercise, the actual location at which a flycatcher was detected on a survey could differ by as much as 39.4 km from the location used in the model. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> does not indicate how he controlled for this variable. BBS surveys are also subject to observer error because routes are typically run by volunteers who vary in field identification skills. A route that has recorded a species repeatedly across years is likely to be a more accurate indication of whether birds used the area consistently and would reduce probability of observer error, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> did not indicate whether or how he controlled for this source of error.More important is that climate variables interpolated at the 1 km<sup>2</sup> scale are unlikely to reflect the climate experienced by Willow Flycatchers because the birds inhabit riparian zones that make up a relatively small proportion of the southwestern landscape. Evidence of niche differentiation using landscape-level data should include features that differentiate habitat and climate on much finer scales. For example, models currently available to predict whether habitat will be occupied by Southwestern Willow Flycatchers are based on parameters measured at much smaller scales (e.g., 30 &times; 30 m; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Hatten1">Hatten and Paradzick 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Hatten2">Hatten et al. 2010</xref>) than the 1 km<sup>2</sup> used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> approach. Likewise, they included niche parameters such as vegetative cover and distance to water that are more likely to reflect habitat suitability than the broad temperature and precipitation measures available in the WordClim database. Using additional, more specific parameters like those measured at finer spatial scales would be necessary to adequately test ecological niche differentiation between the 2 flycatcher subspecies.To demonstrate how niche models based on these coarse climatic variables could be misleading, we repeated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> exercise and calculated ENMs based on bird occurrences drawn both from data associated with museum skins catalogued in Vert.net and the BBS database, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> had done. For BBS data, however, we only used those occurrences that were within the first 10 stops from the starting point (therefore within at least 5 miles &lsqb;8 km&rsqb; of the latitude/longitude reported in the BBS database) and only when the species was detected in a minimum of 4 years. In all cases we used only occurrences recorded between June 15 and July 30 to maximize the probability that occurrence data reflected birds in breeding habitat. We limited our analysis to occurrences within the currently recognized range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> (Idaho and parts of Washington, Oregon, California, Nevada, Utah, Colorado, Wyoming, and Montana) and the currently recognized range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (Arizona and parts of New Mexico, Colorado, Utah, Nevada, and California). We excluded occurrences west of 120&deg;W to ensure that we did not sample <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>. After estimating <italic>D</italic> and <italic>I</italic> for both the identity and background test using ENM Tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren1">Warren et al. 2008</xref>) for the 2 flycatcher subspecies, we repeated the exercise comparing occurrences of Yellow Warbler (<italic>Setophaga petechia</italic>) from within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> to <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> occurrences used in the initial analysis. Yellow Warbler occurrences were drawn from the same 2 sources (Vert.net and BBS) with the same caveats as outlined above for flycatchers. Our hypothesis was that this test, based on relatively large-scale climatic variables and geographic locations that could contain significant error, would yield the same result for both comparisons and was therefore too coarse to be used as a reliable indicator of ecological differentiation among subspecies.The identity test of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren1">Warren et al. (2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren2">2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Warren3">2011</xref>) supported significant niche differentiation between <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">Figure 3</xref>A). In contrast to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref>, the background test indicated that the null hypothesis (that niche differences were due to differences in the background availability of niche parameters in the respective ranges of each subspecies) could be rejected at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 level because 96 of the 100 replicate values were larger than our estimate of Schoener's <italic>D</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">Figure 3</xref>C). We do not argue that this marginally significant result supports this approach to assessing differentiation, but simply note that by using this approach in this case, the test could be interpreted as evidence of significant niche differentiation between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. Our comparison of Yellow Warbler (138 occurrences) and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> showed that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> results for the subspecies comparison was not unexpected given the coarse climatic variables. Similar to the flycatcher subspecies comparison, the identity test indicated significant niche differentiation between Yellow Warbler and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">Figure 3</xref>B), and in this case, a failure of the background test to reject the null hypothesis that differentiation was due to differences in the background environment that each species inhabited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">Figure 3</xref>D).Following the reasoning of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref>, our results would indicate weak evidence of niche partitioning between flycatcher subspecies, but there is no evidence of niche partitioning between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and Yellow Warblers occurring in the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. The point of this exercise was not to improve on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> approach and provide a more rigorous test of niche differentiation, but rather to duplicate it, using the same type of data, and show the inherent weakness of the test. We argue that if the test is too weak to detect differences among species, it should not be used as a standard by which to measure distinctness of subspecies.The only indisputable result of this test is that the 2 flycatcher subspecies occur in areas with significantly different temperature and precipitation regimes over most of their range, as reflected in the significantly lower niche overlap values when occurrence locations for the 2 flycatcher subspecies are compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f03">Figure 3</xref>A). We also note, however, that even a negative result of the background test would not mean niche differentiation does not exist. This point was made previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-McCormack1">McCormack and Maley (2015)</xref> in their critique of a paper in which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink3">Zink et al. (2013)</xref> made similar arguments about ecological differentiation in the California Gnatcatcher (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Polioptila californica</named-content></italic>). As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-McCormack1">McCormack and Maley (2015)</xref>, &ldquo;the proper interpretation is that by failing to reject the null hypothesis of the &lsquo;background test,' it cannot be disentangled whether the strong niche differences from the &lsquo;identity test' represent differences important to the California Gnatcatchers or arise simply from clinal trends in climate variables&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-McCormack1">McCormack and Maley 2015</xref>). Equally important, niche differentiation tests based on a relatively small suite of climate variables measured at large spatial scales may lack the power to detect significant niche differences. We are not arguing against niche modeling as a useful tool for investigating ecological differentiation, but we emphasize that data for niche models should be collected at georeferenced locations, measured at appropriate spatial scales, and include other habitat characteristics beyond broad measures of temperature and precipitation.Song is innate in Willow Flycatchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Kroodsma1">Kroodsma 1984</xref>) and could act as a reproductive isolating mechanism. In many cases where morphology has failed to distinguish sibling species of <italic>Empidonax</italic>, song has done so, and song was the basis for separating Traill's Flycatcher into the Willow and Alder flycatcher species currently recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Stein1">Stein 1963</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick (2001)</xref> studied song characteristics of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> by sampling 16 geographic areas. He characterized the 4 northernmost sites (Oregon, northern Utah, and northern Colorado) as <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and 5 sites in the south (southern Nevada, southern Arizona, and New Mexico) as <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>. The remaining sites he characterized as of unknown affinity. Using cluster analysis and canonical discriminant analysis he found &ldquo;(1) low elevation, southerly desert populations (Arizona, New Mexico, and southern Utah) have a unique vocal identity corresponding to populations in the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>; (2) northerly song groups (Oregon, Colorado, and northern Utah) share a different song type corresponding to populations in the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>; and (3) a departure from vocal and morphological congruence occurs for a population of high-elevation Arizona birds that, although in the currently accepted range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic>, sings songs acoustically similar to more northern populations (<italic>E. t. adastus</italic>).&rdquo;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> dismissed this study because &ldquo;Sedgwick's UPGMA phenogram that shows 2 distinct song groups was based on a reduced set of song characters that were chosen because they separated the 2 groups, whereas characters not showing the same (or a different) pattern were excluded. In addition, the 2 clusters did not group samples entirely by subspecies.&rdquo; He also argued there was a sampling gap in the region where the 2 song types differed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick's (2001)</xref> graph of canonical discriminant analysis separated the sampling locations into 2, non-overlapping clusters along canonical axis 1 (CDF1; this axis explained 81&percnt; of the variance), with 1 cluster including all individuals from the 5 <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> sites and 2 individuals from a northern New Mexico unknown-affinity site. The other cluster included all <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> individuals and all other individuals from the unknown affinity sites. Thus, we fail to see how <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> contention that the analysis &ldquo;did not group samples entirely by subspecies&rdquo; can be supported.Unfortunately, not all populations were individually identified on the graph of canonical axis scores so we could not graph each location's CDF1 score against latitude to investigate the shape of the cline. Instead, we graphed the elevation of each sampling area vs. its latitude and then coded each site depending on whether it lay on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick's (2001)</xref> CDF1 axis at &lt;1 (representing the <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> cluster), or &gt;2 (representing the <italic>extimus</italic> cluster; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f04">Figure 4</xref>). This figure shows two 1&deg; latitude sampling gaps in the area of the proposed boundary but also shows clearly the pattern of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> song at northern latitude and high-elevation sites and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> song at low latitude, low-elevation sites. Had <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick (2001)</xref> presented means and standard errors for the song variables he measured, we could have calculated diagnosability scores for each of them independently as recommended by Patten and Unitt (2001). However, Sedgwick did state &ldquo;the difference in the duration of the FMs in the second part of the phrase III (P3bc3d) was especially important in distinguishing among groups; that for southerly groups ranged from 26.6&ndash;32.1 ms compared to a range of only 15.6&ndash;16.3 ms for the more northerly song groups.&rdquo; Given that these ranges do not overlap, this character would be considered 100&percnt; diagnosable, thereby meeting a critical criterion as a defensible character to distinguish subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Patten2">Patten and Unitt 2002</xref>).Elevation and latitude of 16 locations where Sedgwick (2002) measured song characteristics of Willow Flycatchers. Open circles represent populations that had a canonical axis 1 score &gt;2 (<italic>E. t. extimus</italic> songs), black circles represent populations with a canonical axis 1 score &lt;1 (<italic>E. t. adastus</italic> songs), and the gray circle represents a population that had some individuals with scores in both categories. Note that the high elevation, low latitude site (black circle at 33.8&deg; latitude) grouped with <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>.Variation in plumage coloration was traditionally used to recognize the 4 subspecies of Willow Flycatchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Phillips1">Phillips 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Aldrich1">Aldrich 1951</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Unitt1">Unitt 1987</xref>), but using those characteristics to reliably distinguish among subspecies can be difficult (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Hubbard1">Hubbard 1999</xref>) in a genus well-documented for the lack of morphological differentiation among species. The only quantitative study of plumage variation in the Willow Flycatcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>) used a colorimeter to measure lightness, saturation, and hue on 374 adult Willow Flycatchers from 29 locations. They reported significant differences among the 4 subspecies in mean values for plumage characteristics and considerable overlap among individuals.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref> illustrated that point with a figure showing both means and individuals plotted on 2 canonical discrimination axes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> noted that individuals from &ldquo;boundary populations&rdquo; (those population near the current subspecies boundary) were not included on that figure. He repeated the analysis using principle components analysis (PCA) and showed that including boundary populations increased the overlap of individual samples. He further showed that when the values from his PCA axis 2 were graphed against latitude, there was a linear relationship consistent with a smooth cline in plumage variation from north to south (figure 6 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink 2015</xref>). He did not graph PCA axis 1 values vs. latitude, although that axis explained more variation (39&percnt;) than did axis 2 (27&percnt;).Instead of combining all plumage variables into a PCA, we examined each of the 6 color variables (lightness, saturation, and hue measured on the crown and the same 3 measures on the back) independently under the hypothesis that some color characteristics would differ between subspecies whereas others would not. To do so, we first censored the plumage data to include only birds sampled between June 15 and July 30 to reduce any probability of including migrants, leaving 209 individuals at 19 sites within the range of <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> for subsequent analysis. We then graphed each color variable vs. latitude and visually inspected them for evidence of nonlinearity. We identified 1 of the 6 variables (crown hue) as potentially showing a nonlinear relationship. We then plotted crown hue value for each of the remaining 209 birds and used piece-wise regression (package &ldquo;segmented&rdquo; in R) to determine whether we could identify a breakpoint and whether resulting line segments differed in slope. We found a breakpoint at 40.4&deg;N, and the Davies test indicated that slopes of the 2 segments were significantly different (<italic>p</italic> &equals; 0.002; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Crown hue values from 3 birds from one low-latitude, high-elevation site (GREE) included in that analysis had plumage values more similar to northern latitude sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f05">Figure 5</xref>A). This site corresponded to the same low-latitude, high-elevation area where <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick (2001)</xref> found songs that grouped with <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> rather than <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f04">Figure 4</xref>). We then chose a subset of sampling locations that best approximated a north&ndash;south line and used package HZAR to determine the maximum likelihood cline and cline center based on relativized values of hue of the crown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f05">Figure 5</xref>B). This subset did not include the low-latitude, high-elevation site because it did not fall on the best approximated north&ndash;south line. The cline center was estimated at 39.8&deg;N, with maximum likelihood estimates around the cline center ranging from 37.6&deg;N to 41.9&deg;N. Although cline center estimates were considerably farther north based on crown hue, maximum likelihood estimates of cline center overlapped those for the C-haplotype clines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f01">Figure 1</xref>.<bold>(A)</bold> Crown hue of 209 Willow Flycatchers vs. latitude. The open circles represent samples measured at a high-elevation site in Arizona (GREE in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton3">Paxton et al. 2010</xref>) near the high-elevation, low-latitude site of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick (2001)</xref> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f04">Figure 4</xref>. <bold>(B)</bold> Maximum likelihood cline with 95&percnt; CI (gray area) for crown hue and cline center (black arrow) and range in maximum likelihood cline center values (horizontal line on cline center) of Willow Flycatchers based on a linear subset of locations in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton3">Paxton et al. (2010)</xref>. For comparison, the open arrow and bar represent the cline center and 95&percnt; credible area from the analysis of mtDNA C-haplotypes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-f01">Figure 1</xref>.In 1996, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) and the National Marine Fisheries Service (NMFS) attempted to clarify criteria for listing subspecies and DPSs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceandNationalMarineFisheriesServiceUSFWSandNMFS1">USFWS and NMFS 1996</xref>). According to this policy &ldquo;a population segment of a vertebrate species may be considered discrete if it is markedly separated from other populations of the same taxon as a consequence of physical, physiological, ecological, or behavioral factors. <italic>Quantitative measures of genetic or morphological discontinuity</italic> may provide evidence of this separation&rdquo; (italics added). The analyses presented here demonstrated that both genetic and morphological characteristics showed quantitative evidence of a step cline, a discontinuity, between currently recognized <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> populations to the south and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic> populations to the north, with the greatest change in frequencies roughly concordant with the currently designated subspecies boundary. We agree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> that previous studies have not sufficiently sampled the entire range of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. traillii</named-content></italic> to rigorously test for boundaries between all subspecies, but for the question of whether <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> is distinct from other subspecies, the most crucial comparisons are with <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and with <italic>E. t. brewsteri</italic>, with which it shares the longest border and likely the greatest gene flow.Across this boundary, we have shown that changes in 3 independent datasets, genetic (mtDNA), morphological (crown hue), and behavioral (song), are all roughly concordant with the currently recognized boundary between <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> and <italic>E. t. adastus</italic>. Although the breakpoint for the plumage character was considerably north of the current boundary and the cline centers estimated based on C-haplotypes south of it, it is not unusual for neutral genes and phenotypic traits to move at different rates and unequally in different directions across an area of hybridization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Yuri1">Yuri et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre et al. 2014</xref>). Importantly, the geographical pattern in a plumage trait was concordant with patterns of song variation, not only in general form but also in mirroring an exception to the general latitudinal pattern. Based on his song analysis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Sedgwick1">Sedgwick (2001)</xref> proposed that <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> occupied high-elevation, low-latitude sites, and the pattern of plumage variation was consistent with that hypothesis.An interaction among elevation, latitude, and subspecies distribution is also consistent with the hypothesis that <italic>Empidonax</italic> flycatchers subdivide niche space in part through differential habitat selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Johnson1">Johnson and Cicero 2002</xref>). The cooler, mesic habitats in high-elevation, low-latitude sites like the White Mountains of Arizona are more similar, both in habitat and climate, to areas at higher latitudes in Wyoming and Montana than they are to the geographically nearer, low-elevation, desert sites. Future niche modeling could test this hypothesis if data on habitat variables can be obtained at the appropriate spatial scale.The USFWS and NMFS policy statement clarifying criteria for listing subspecies and DPSs under the ESA states that once a population segment is considered discrete, its biological and ecological significance will then be considered based on 4 criteria, the first 2 of which are relevant here. Significance &ldquo;may include, but is not limited to: (1) persistence of the discrete population segment in an ecological setting unusual or unique to the taxon, (2) evidence that loss of the discrete population segment would result in a significant gap in the range of a taxon.&rdquo; We argue that the southwestern population of the Willow Flycatcher meets both of these criteria. The one clear result of both our and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink's (2015)</xref> ecological niche modeling exercises was that the large-scale climate matrix <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> occupy are significantly different. We argue that the low-elevation desert matrix inhabited by <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> represents a unique ecological setting. Likewise, the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> based on currently accepted boundaries makes up roughly 20&percnt; of the range of the species, and therefore loss of those populations would result in a major gap in species distribution.The lack of reproductive isolation between subspecies, and the gene flow that occurs as a result, makes delineating a boundary between subspecies difficult. Most genetic studies, including the datasets used here, rely on neutral alleles that may flow at varying rates and to varying distances across subspecies boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Wu1">Wu 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Yuri1">Yuri et al. 2009</xref>). Likewise, important phenotypic traits may show boundaries significantly different from neutral genetic markers or be present in the absence of genetic differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Baldassarre1">Baldassarre et al. 2014</xref>). Therefore, we agree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Paxton2">Paxton et al. (2008)</xref> that placement of any narrowly defined boundary between <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> would ultimately be somewhat arbitrary. Likewise, assigning individuals or populations that lie within the boundary to one or the other subspecies may often be difficult or impossible. If a line were drawn through a hybrid zone between species, one would not expect to be able to assign all individuals to one parental species or the other on either side of the line; many are simply hybrids. The same would be true for subspecies boundaries. Not unexpectedly, our analyses showed that the maximum likelihood estimates of cline centers covered roughly 2&deg; of latitude.Managing populations in these relatively large zones of overlap presents a challenge. Placement of a geographic boundary between <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> and <italic>E. t extimus</italic> is made more difficult because the population is patchily distributed in often small and temporally variable breeding sites. More than 50&percnt; of occupied Southwestern Willow Flycatcher breeding sites described in the 2007 range-wide survey consisted of 5 territories or fewer, and 142 sites that had recorded Willow Flycatchers at least one time since 1993 did not have active territories in 2007 (Durst et al. 2007). The complexity of the terrain in the American Southwest also presents challenges if subspecies are separated both by latitude and elevation. Large elevation changes over short distances lead to juxtaposition of areas that differ strikingly in climate and vegetation communities over small spatial scales, as found in the high-elevation Arizona sites set amid a larger desert landscape. Ultimately, our definitions of boundaries between parapatric subspecies must incorporate the fact that those boundaries are not discrete and therefore not best represented by a single line on a map. Managing parapatric endangered subspecies by designating core areas vs. boundary areas could be a solution, with the 2 areas potentially having different management goals and protection status under the ESA.We agree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-118-2-289-Zink2">Zink (2015)</xref> that many currently available techniques could be used to better test the genetic, behavioral, morphological, and ecological distinctness of Willow Flycatcher subspecies. Studies simultaneously examining song, plumage, and genetics at the same sites over the entire range of the species would undoubtedly improve our understanding of the patterns of variability among and within currently recognized subspecies. Likewise, ecological niche modeling conducted at appropriate spatial scales with carefully georeferenced locations could determine whether smaller-scale habitat selection by flycatchers reduces or enhances the significant differences in climate that distinguish the range of <italic>E. t. extimus</italic> from <italic>E. t. adastus</italic> at broader spatial scales. Until those analyses are undertaken, however, we do not agree that currently available data fail to support the subspecies status of the endangered Southwestern Willow Flycatcher or its protection under the Endangered Species Act.We thank C. A. Gehring, E. H. Paxton, and M. K. Sogge for reviewing earlier drafts of this manuscript. Three anonymous reviewers greatly improved this manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Authors wrote this paper while funded as faculty and graduate students of NAU but received no other funding to aid in the development or writing of this paper. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.<bold>Ethtics statement:</bold> We followed the Code of Ethics and Standards for Professional Conduct as outlined and adopted by The Wildlife Society.<bold>Author contributions:</bold> T.C.T. wrote the paper and developed the main arguments and figures, A.D.S., S.M.M., and K.E.I. aided in the genetic, HAZR, and ecological niche modeling analyses, respectively.