 Erratum 2: First global census of the Ad&eacute;lie Penguin  First global census of the Ad&eacute;lie penguin  Appendix B Table 2 in  Lynch and LaRue (2014)  incorrectly listed the total abundance of Ad&eacute;lie penguins for Subarea 48.4 as 56,932 (13,908&ndash;98,330) breeding pairs. The abundance should have been listed as 161,075 (107,044&ndash;226,000) breeding pairs.  La Tabla 2 del Ap&eacute;ndice B en Lynch y LaRue (2014) presenta incorrectamente la abundancia total de la sub-&aacute;rea 48.4 como 56,932 (13,908&ndash;98,330) parejas reproductivas. La abundancia debi&oacute; ser reportada como 161,075 (107,044&ndash;226,000) parejas reproductivas.   Palabras clave:  Ant&aacute;rtica, CCAMLR,  Pigoscelys adeliae , Islas Sandwich del Sur, Sub-&aacute;rea 48.4  In Appendix B Table 2 of our paper ( Lynch and LaRue 2014 ), the total abundance of Ad&eacute;lie penguins for Subarea 48.4 (South Sandwich Islands) should have been listed as 161,075 breeding pairs with 95 th  percentile CI of (107,044&ndash;226,000). Our original total for the region inadvertently excluded islands where satellite imagery, rather than direct on-the-ground surveys, were used to estimate abundance. The models developed to convert guano area to abundance require an estimate of terrain slope and we currently have no digital elevation model for the South Sandwich Islands; this led to their accidental exclusion from the regional totals. Our corrected estimate of Subarea 48.4 abundance assumes flat terrain (zero slope) for guano-covered areas, which we recognize is likely to be a poor model for many Ad&eacute;lie penguin colonies contained within the topographically complex South Sandwich Islands. While we are cautious in our interpretation of the estimates derived from satellite imagery in this area, we feel our corrected abundance estimate for Subarea 48.4 is far less biased than the originally published value that inadvertently excluded some islands in calculating the total Subarea 48.4 abundance. 