Feather-degrading bacteria from the plumage of Neotropical Spectacled Thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus nudigenis</named-content></italic>)Production, purification and characterization of an extracellular keratinase from <italic>Lysobacter</italic> NCIMB 9497Phylogenetic identification and in situ detection of individual microbial cells without cultivationProduction and properties of keratinolytic proteases from three novel Gram-negative feather-degrading bacteria isolated from Brazilian soilsEffects of feather lice on flight behavior of male Barn Swallows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content></italic>)Studies on lysogenesis. I. The mode of phage liberation by lysogenic <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Escherichia coli</named-content></italic>Characterization of a keratinolytic serine proteinase from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Streptomyces pactum</named-content></italic> DSM 40530Experimental demonstration of the energetic cost of parasitism in free-ranging hostsBacterial keratinases: Useful enzymes for bioprocessing agroindustrial wastes and beyondProduction of an extracellular keratinase <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chryseobacterium</named-content></italic> sp. growing on raw feathersOccurrence of feather-degrading bacilli in the plumage of birdsGloger's rule, feather-degrading bacteria, and color variation among Song SparrowsColorful parrot feathers resist bacterial degradationProduction and characterization of keratinase of a feather-degrading <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus licheniformis</named-content></italic> PWD-1Purification and characterization of an alkaline serine endopeptidase from a feather-degrading <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Xanthomonas maltophilia</named-content></italic> strainPurification and characterization of keratinase from <italic>B. circulans</italic>, <italic>B. licheniformis</italic>, and <italic>B. megaterium</italic>Bacterial degradation of black and white feathersThe evolution of bird plumage colouration: A role for feather-degrading bacteria?Feather-degrading bacteria: A new frontier in avian and host&ndash;parasite research?Evidence that plumage bacteria influence feather coloration and body condition of Eastern Bluebirds <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia sialis</named-content></italic>Resistance of melanized feathers to bacterial degradation: Is it really so black and white?An ecological perspective on bacterial diversityFeather-degrading <italic>Bacillus</italic> species from poultry wastePurification and characterization of a keratinase from a feather-degrading <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus licheniformis</named-content></italic> strainHigh diversity among feather-degrading bacteria from a dry meadow soilNovel keratinase from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus subtilis</named-content></italic> S14 exhibiting remarkable dehairing capabilitiesIncreased plumage darkness of female Shiny Cowbirds <italic>Molothrus bonariensis</italic> in the subtropics: An adaptation to bacterial degradation?Seasonally changing preen-wax composition: Red Knots' (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calidris canutus</named-content></italic>) flexible defense against feather-degrading bacteria?Keratinolytic bacteria isolated from feather wasteCharacterization of a new keratinolytic bacterium that completely degrades native feather keratinPurification and characterization of a keratinolytic matalloprotease from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cryseobacterium</named-content></italic> sp. kr6Plumage bacterial assemblages in a breeding wild passerine: Relationships with ecological factors and body conditionFeather keratin hydrolysis by a <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vibrio</named-content></italic> sp. strain kr2Microbial diversity of wild bird feathers revealed through culture-based and culture-independent techniquesChemical warfare? Effects of uropygial oil on feather-degrading bacteriaBacteria as an agent for change in structural plumage color: Correlational and experimental evidenceDo feather-degrading bacteria affect sexually selected plumage color?Registros de actividad reproductora y muda en algunas aves del norte de VenezuelaFeather degradation by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Kocuria rosea</named-content></italic> in submerged culturePrevalence and genetic diversity of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus licheniformis</named-content></italic> in avian plumageIsolation, identification, and characterization of a feather-degrading bacteriumEnumeration of some microbial groups in thermophilic poultry waste digesters and enrichment of a feather-degrading cultureMoult, flight performance and wingbeat kinematics during take-off in European Starlings <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sturnus vulgaris</named-content></italic>MaracayKeratin degradation: A cooperative action of two enzymes from <italic>Stenotrophomonas</italic> spFeather wastes digestion by new isolated strains <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus</named-content></italic> sp. in MoroccoWe studied the diversity and abundance of keratinolytic bacteria hosted by the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus nudigenis</named-content></italic>), and their capacities to break down feathers in vitro. From 40 individuals sampled in Venezuela during the rainy and dry seasons, we isolated 18 bacterial isolates able to grow on feather meal agar, a medium selective of bacteria capable of extracting energy and nitrogen from feather keratin. Fourteen of these isolates were not previously known to grow on feather keratin. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus cereus</named-content></italic> was the most prevalent, isolated from 85&percnt; of all individuals. Percentage of birds colonized by keratinolytic bacteria, prevalence of the most common bacteria, average number of bacteria species harbored per bird, and average abundance per bird of the most prevalent bacteria were not dependent on season. Capacity to degrade feathers in liquid culture varied extensively among bacterial isolates; four of them were able to noticeably damage feathers, but only <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> totally disintegrated them in 14 days. Degrading activity of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> was as intense as that of our positive control, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, well known for its feather-degrading properties. The rest of the bacteria, although showing perceptible growth on feathers, did not visually damage them under our experimental conditions. Contrary to previous studies on wild birds, most feather-degrading isolates (11) in our sample were Gram-negative, likely because our culture protocol was less restrictive than that of previous studies.Estudiamos la diversidad y abundancia de bacterias queratinol&iacute;ticas hospedadas por el plumaje de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus nudigenis</named-content></italic> y sus capacidades de degradar plumas in vitro. Aislamos a partir de 40 individuos, muestreados en Venezuela durante las estaciones lluviosa y seca, 18 aislamientos bacterianos capaces de crecer en agar pluma, un medio selectivo de bacterias capaces de extraer energ&iacute;a y nitr&oacute;geno de la queratina de las plumas. Previamente no se conoc&iacute;a que 14 de estos aislamientos crec&iacute;an con queratina de las plumas. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus cereus</named-content></italic> present&oacute; la prevalencia m&aacute;s alta; fue aislado del 85&percnt; de todos los individuos. El porcentaje de aves colonizadas por bacterias queratinol&iacute;ticas, la prevalencia de la bacteria m&aacute;s com&uacute;n, el n&uacute;mero promedio de especies de bacteria albergado por ave y la abundancia promedio por ave de la bacteria m&aacute;s prevalente no fueron dependientes de la estaci&oacute;n. La capacidad de degradar plumas en un cultivo l&iacute;quido vari&oacute; enormemente entre los aislados bacterianos; cuatro de ellos fueron capaces de da&ntilde;an notoriamente las plumas, pero s&oacute;lo <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> las desintegr&oacute; totalmente en 14 d&iacute;as. La actividad degradadora de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> fue tan intensa como la de nuestro control positivo, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, reconocido por sus propiedades degradadoras de plumas. El resto de las bacterias, aunque mostraron un crecimiento perceptible en las plumas, no las da&ntilde;aron de modo visible bajo nuestras condiciones experimentales. De modo contrario a estudios previos en aves silvestres, la mayor&iacute;a (11) de los aislamientos degradadores de plumas en nuestra muestra fueron Gram-negativo, probablemente debido a que nuestro protocolo de cultivo fue menos restrictivo que el de estudios previos.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> bacteria degradadora de plumas, bacteria queratinol&iacute;tica, queratina, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus nudigenis</named-content></italic>, VenezuelaPlumage wear and degradation can deter essential functions of birds such as thermoregulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Booth1">Booth et al. 1993</xref>), flight performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Barbosa1">Barbosa et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams3">Williams and Swaddle 2003</xref>), and visual communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey3">Shawkey et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey4">2009</xref>). One factor that may have an effect on plumage integrity is the action of microorganisms present in the feathers and skin of birds. Specifically, keratinolytic bacteria, those able to degrade the &beta;-keratin matrix of feathers, are capable of damaging plumage and may influence birds' defense mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gunderson1">Gunderson 2008</xref>).Two surveys have indicated that keratinolytic bacteria are diverse and widespread among North American birds. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>) found feather-degrading bacilli in 38.6&percnt; of 83 species and in six of seven species with large (<italic>n</italic> &gt; 80) sample sizes. The proportion of birds with feather-degrading bacilli varied with time of year and was highest in late fall, when 24&percnt; of all birds sampled were contaminated. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. (2005</xref>) isolated putative feather-degrading bacteria (FDB), mostly species of <italic>Bacillus</italic>, from 21&percnt; to 59&percnt; of the individuals of each of eight species examined. In both studies, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus licheniformis</named-content></italic>, a thriving soil bacterium, was the most prevalent member of the keratinolytic microbial community.Among bacteria, keratinases are produced by a number of phylogenetically diverse species often isolated from soil and poultry waste and mostly restricted to the Gram-positive genera <italic>Streptomyces</italic> and <italic>Bacillus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sangali1">Sangali and Brandelli 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>). However, recent findings indicate that the diversity of FDB is also associated with Gram-negative bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Bach1">Bach et al. 2011</xref>). Research on feather bacteria of wild birds has mainly focused on <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> because of its well-known capacity to disintegrate feathers in liquid culture and because of its widespread occurrence in the plumage of northern temperate birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Reneerkens1">Reneerkens et al. 2008</xref>). In these studies, selective incubating conditions, such as prolonged high temperature and a slightly salty and alkaline nutrient broth, favor the growth of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> while inhibiting growth of other bacteria, including most other bacilli and particularly Gram-negative bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>).Feather-degrading activity of bacteria isolated from the plumage of wild birds has been demonstrated experimentally in only a few studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>) found that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> from 32 species of North American birds degraded, in vitro, secondary feathers of white leghorn chickens. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. (2003</xref>) found a high production of keratinase, indicative of feather-degrading activity, in 10 of 13 bacterial isolates from House Finches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Carpodacus mexicanus</named-content></italic>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Saag1">Saag et al. (2011</xref>) cultivated 18 unidentified FDB phylotypes from wild Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>) in Estonia, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Mahler1">Mahler et al. (2010</xref>) demonstrated feather-degrading activity of several unidentified isolates from the plumage of Shiny Cowbirds (<italic>Molothrus bonariensis</italic>) from temperate and subtropical Argentina. In addition, keratinolytic activity has been demonstrated mostly among <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus</named-content></italic> spp. isolated from poultry waste (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams1">Williams et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>).In the present study, we (1) inventoried with culture-dependent protocols the naturally occurring FDB from the plumage of wild Spectacled Thrushes (Turdidae: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Turdus nudigenis</named-content></italic>) from northern Venezuela and (2) tested the potential of bacterial isolates to degrade feathers in liquid culture. Inventories of keratinolytic bacteria are an essential first step for gaining insight into the interactions between feather bacteria and birds and determining the proximate and ultimate consequences of such interactions. Nevertheless, the identities of the bacteria that inhabit the feathers of wild birds remain largely unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">Shawkey et al. 2005</xref>), and the present study is the first to look at keratinolytic bacteria in a Neotropical bird. Many previous studies have used culture-based surveys that selectively favor the growth of salt-tolerant, thermophilic bacteria such as <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Reneerkens1">Reneerkens et al. 2008</xref>). By contrast, we employed more inclusive protocols that allowed growth of other taxa, including mesophilic and Gram-negative bacteria. In addition, we examined the potential effect of season on the prevalence (the percentage of individuals contaminated) and density of keratinolytic bacteria on the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes. Seasonal effects may be important because the warm, moist environments that prevail in the tropical rainy season should favor microbial activity compared with dry periods (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>).We chose Spectacled Thrushes because they frequently forage on the ground and because they are abundant and easily trappable in mist nets at our study site. Featherborne bacteria, including FDB, have often been isolated from soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>), and birds in contact with the ground are more likely to be contaminated by soil bacteria, particularly by feather-degrading <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>). We anticipated that Spectacled Thrushes would host a diverse community of keratinolytic bacteria and that prevalence would be high because of the species' ground-foraging habits and because warm and humid conditions of tropical lowland habitats may facilitate growth and dispersion of such bacteria.In northern Venezuela, Spectacled Thrushes are common inhabitants of open forest and second growth, where they forage in the canopy and on the ground for fruit, arthropods, and earthworms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-MeyerdeSchauensee1">Meyer de Schauensee and Phelps 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Hilty1">Hilty 2003</xref>). We sampled bacteria from the plumage of 40 birds mist netted in 2008 in deciduous forest remnants near the campus of Universidad Central de Venezuela (10&deg;16&prime;15&prime;&prime;N; 67&deg;36&prime;27&prime;&prime;W; &sim;440 m asl) on the outskirts of the city of Maracay. In this region, yearly rainfall (901 mm) is highly seasonal, most of it (774.5 mm) falling in the 6-mo (May&ndash;October) rainy season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-WorldWeatherInformationService1">World Weather Information Service 2011</xref>). At our study site, Spectacled Thrushes breed from February, in the later part of the dry season, through July and molt between July and November (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Verea1">Verea et al. 2009</xref>). They frequently bathe during the rainy season and dust-bathe when dry (C. Verea and C. Bosque personal observation).To search for plumage bacteria and determine their seasonal occurrence, we sampled 40 unsexed adult birds, 20 toward the end of the dry season (March&ndash;April) and 20 during the rainy season (June&ndash;July). Handling mist-netted birds with sterile latex gloves, we collected from each individual the ninth primaries, the first secondaries, and the outer rectrices from both sides; in addition, we collected a few covert feathers from the head, back, breast, and belly. All feathers are olive-brownish except breast and belly coverts, which are lighter in color. Feathers from each individual were kept together in sealed sterile glass vials to prevent contamination and kept at &sim;4&deg;C for a few hours until processing. We did not sample birds that were molting or that had recently molted wing or tail feathers. All birds were released unharmed after sampling.Because we did not know what types of bacteria were present in the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes and because our purpose was to isolate cultivable keratinolytic bacteria from those present, we initially cultured bacteria from feather samples in a nutritionally rich generalized Luria-Bartani (LB) medium, from which we could isolate bacteria that degraded feathers. Bacteria from feathers collected from each individual were incubated in 5 mL of sterile LB medium in sterile sealed vials at 37&deg;C for 24 hr. This medium contained 10 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> bacto-tryptone, 5 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> yeast extract, and 5 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> NaCl 5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Bertani1">Bertani 1951</xref>). In all cultures the media became cloudy after 24 hr, indicating bacterial growth.To isolate FDB and estimate their concentrations in the liquid culture, the bacterial suspension was serially diluted 10&times; in saline (NaCl 0.85&percnt;), and 100 &mu;L of the 1:10,000 dilution was loaded into a micropipetter, discharged onto plates containing feather meal agar (FMA), and raked across the agar plate with a sterile spreader. Plates, in duplicate, from each individual bird, were incubated at 37&deg;C for 24 hr to detect keratinolytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams1">Williams et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sangali1">Sangali and Brandelli 2000</xref>). The FMA medium contained 0.4 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.3 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.3 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> NaCl, 15.0 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> feather meal, and 15.0 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> agar. Feathers from white leghorn chickens, obtained from a poultry processing plant, were washed extensively with water, dried, finely ground, and sterilized by autoclaving at 121&deg;C for 15 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Vidal1">Vidal et al. 2000</xref>). This medium is highly selective for keratinolytic bacteria because its only source of carbon and nitrogen is keratin; hence, only bacteria that are able to digest it can proliferate in it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams1">Williams et al. 1990</xref>). However, we did not consider capability to flourish in FMA as indicative of ability to degrade feathers.After 24&ndash;48 hr of incubation, we counted the number of colony-forming units (cfu) of each morphotype per plate to estimate densities of viable bacteria in the liquid cultures. We distinguished morphotypes on the basis of colony color, shape, size, and presence or absence of mucilaginous (viscid) aspect. Bacterial colonies of single species were obtained by repeatedly scratching the agar surface with a sterile loop onto plates of LB medium. In the case of mixed colonies, single-species isolates were purified by routine procedures, depending on the bacteria involved: Gram negatives mostly by culturing in MacConkey Agar, and bacillus-forming spores by heat shock. We confirmed the purity of isolated colonies through oil-immersion light microscopy and Gram stain. These procedures allowed us to ensure that we were working with individual-species isolates from each individual bird from both seasonal samplings. Isolates were stored at 4&deg;C in LB and FMA agar plates until needed.Prior to sample collection, we performed two preliminary tests to confirm the selective character of our FMA. In the first test, we inoculated an FMA plate with a strain of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> (Centro Venezolano de Colecciones de Microorganismos &lsqb;CVCM&rsqb; 586, reconstituted from freeze-dried ATCC 14580), a strain well known for its keratinolytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>), and two species for which we had no indication of such activity, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus pumilus</named-content></italic> (CVCM 1696) and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corynebacterium</named-content></italic> sp. (CVCM 1191). After incubation at 37&deg;C for 24 hr, we confirmed that only <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> grew. In the second preliminary test, we inoculated, with 100 &mu;L of the 1:10,000 broth dilution from an individual bird, three plates containing FMA and three plates containing nutrient rich LB medium to confirm that the number of morphotypes growing in LB would be greater than that in FMA. After incubation at 37&deg;C for 24 hr, we confirmed that in fact, the average (&plusmn; SD) number of morphotypes growing in FMA (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 2 &plusmn; 0) was smaller than that in LB medium (<italic>x̄</italic> &equals; 6.3 &plusmn; 1.2). Results of both preliminary tests confirmed the selectivity of our FMA medium a priori. In every experiment, we ran one control plate to test for contamination of media.Identification of pure colonies from each individual bird was based on colony morphology, microscopic examination of Gram-stained cells, and biochemical tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Holtz1">Holtz 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-MacFaddin1">MacFaddin 2000</xref>). For each bird, one bacterial isolate of each morphotype was selected at random, removed from cold storage, used to inoculate fresh LB agar plates, and incubated at 37&deg;C for 24 hr before processing. We used the automated ATB-Plus system (Bio-Merieux, Marcy L'Etoile, France) with API galleries (API Coryne, ID 32 GN, ID 32 E, API 20 NE, 50 CHB, and Rapid ID 32 E), depending on the bacteria involved, and following the instructions of the manufacturer. Gallery selection was based on the results of Gram stain and routine tests: catalase, oxidase, lactose, and carbohydrate fermentation, SIM (hydrogen-sulfide, indol, motility), citrate, and urease. The data were read automatically and interpreted with ATB-Plus, version 3.0, allowing for the identification of those isolates in its database. Each isolate was run in duplicate. When identity percentages of the ATB-Plus system indicated an uncertain identification, we carried out complementary tests, indicated by the ATB-Plus system, to confirm identification of the isolate. These tests are specific and included, depending on the taxon involved, nitrate, gelatin, ability to grow in 7.5&percnt; NaCl agar, and/or 50&deg;C, blood agar, MR/VP, of-glucose, bacitracine susceptibility, presence of parasporal crystals, and fresh motility when required, among others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gerhardt1">Gerhardt et al. 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Murray1">Murray et al. 2003</xref>). Given that defining a bacterial species is far from straightforward (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-HornerDevine1">Horner-Devine et al. 2004</xref>), in this work we consider bacterial isolates as &ldquo;operational taxonomic units&rdquo; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sokal1">Sokal and Sneath 1963</xref>), defined on the basis of shared biochemical and additional properties just outlined. However, for ease of reading, we refer to them by the binomial names assigned by ATB-Plus.We assessed feather-degrading properties of each isolate by examining macroscopically its damaging effect on secondary feathers of Spectacled Thrushes in a liquid medium; these feathers were collected from individuals other than those sampled for plumage bacteria. Our procedures basically followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>). Feathers were extensively washed in distilled water, and dried and sterilized by autoclaving (121&deg;C, 15 lb in<sup>&minus;2</sup>) for 20 min. We removed and discarded the distal 1 cm from the feather and placed the two adjacent 2-cm-long pieces, cut from the remains, in different test tubes containing 10 mL of basal medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams2">Williams and Shih 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Williams1">Williams et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Vidal1">Vidal et al. 2000</xref>). This medium contained 0.5 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 0.5 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> NaCl, 0.3 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.4 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> MgCl<sub>2</sub> 6H<sub>2</sub>O, and 0.1 g L<sup>&minus;1</sup> yeast extract. The tubes containing the basal medium and feathers were sterilized by autoclaving (121&deg;C, 15 lb in<sup>&minus;2</sup>) for 15 min. Bacterial isolates, whose degrading capacity we intended to assess, were removed from cold storage and used to inoculate fresh LB agar plates. After 24 hr at 37&deg;C, a loopful of bacteria was removed and added to sterile saline until a turbidity comparable to McFarland standard no. 0.5 (corresponding to about 1,5 10<sup>8</sup> cell mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>) was reached. For each isolate, we inoculated 100 &mu;L of the suspension (&ap;150,000 cells) into each of six replicate tubes. The tubes, containing basal medium, a piece of feather, and the bacterial inoculum, were incubated at 37&deg;C with agitation at 60 rpm (New Brunswick Scientific, model TC-7) for 21 days. Tubes were checked every 48 hr and a feather degradation index (FDI), based on visual inspection, was scored on a scale from 0 to 6 according to the following categories:0: No visible effect on feather; medium remains clear. No indication of bacterial growth.1: No visible effect on feather but medium becomes turbid, indicative of bacterial growth.2: A noticeable cloudy veil (or biofilm) over the feather surface; feather not broken.3: Feather rachis and barbs partially broken but feather remained in a single piece.4: Feather is fragmented into two to five large separate fragments floating in the medium.5: Only smaller fragments are floating in medium.6: Only pieces &le;0.5 mm<sup>2</sup> remain. At this point, we considered that the feather was completely degraded.We report the modal value of the FDI for each bacterial isolate at the end of the 21-day period, or the average number of days taken to reach FDI &equals; 6 when total degradation was achieved in &lt;21 days in all six replicates. To ensure that experimental isolates were not contaminated and remained viable at the end of the 21-day experimental period, we inoculated LB agar plates with the suspension from every experimental tube and cultured them for 24 hr at 37&deg;C. We then compared Gram stain and colony morphology (by oil-immersion light microscopy) with those of the original isolates. We confirmed that all replicates of every experimental bacterium, as well as negative control 2 (see below), remained viable at the end of the experimental period and that no contamination occurred.In addition to experimental tests, we ran two negative and one positive control. The first negative control consisted of one tube containing basal medium and a feather piece but no bacterial inoculum (negative control 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref>). The second negative control was one tube containing basal medium, a feather piece, and an inoculum of a nonkeratinolytic bacterium, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Enterobacter aerogenes</named-content></italic> (CVCM 596, reconstituted from freeze-dried ATCC 13048; negative control 2 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref>). Preliminary tests indicated that this bacterium was unable to grow on FMA. Our positive control consisted of basal medium, a feather piece, and an inoculum of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> (CVCM 586, reconstituted from freeze-dried ATCC 14580).From the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes, we cultured 18 bacterial isolates able to grow on selective FMA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>) whose only nitrogen, carbon, and energy sources were provided by poultry feathers. The average number of bacterial isolates per individual bird was 2.2 &plusmn; 0.45 (range: 1&ndash;3), regardless of season; most individuals (31; 77.5&percnt;) hosted two isolates, and all individuals harbored at least one species (100&percnt; prevalence). Most isolates (11) were enterobacteria, belonging to Enterobacteriaceae (7), Pseudomonaceae (3), and Moraxellaceae (1). <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus cereus</named-content></italic> was the most prevalent: It was isolated from 85&percnt; of all birds sampled (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>). Most isolates had low prevalence, seven were found only once, and 11 had a prevalence of 5&percnt; or less. Five isolates were isolated from birds trapped during both seasons; nine were present in the dry season only, and four in the rainy season only. Eleven isolates were Gram-negative and seven were Gram-positive (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>).The prevalence (proportion of birds) carrying the two most common bacteria (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Enterobacter cloacae</named-content></italic>) was not dependent on season (Fisher exact test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.18 in both cases; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 34 and 12, respectively; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>). The prevalence of other bacterial isolates (&lt;10&percnt; overall) was too low for statistical analysis. Likewise, there were no significant differences in the average number of isolates of keratinolytic bacteria harbored per bird during the dry (2.15 &plusmn; 0.49) versus the rainy season (2.20 &plusmn; 0.41; <italic>t</italic> &equals; &minus;0.4, df &equals; 38, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.72). Similarly, the average number of cfu per plate per colonized bird, considering only the two most prevalent species, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. cloacae</named-content></italic>, was not dependent on season (two-way analysis of variance, <italic>F</italic>-ratio &lt; 0.1, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.94). Hence, we pooled cfu density estimates from the dry and rainy seasons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>) and made no further attempt to examine seasonality. Relative densities of bacterial isolates were highly variable among colonized individual birds, as indicated by the large standard deviations within bacteria (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>). Likewise, there was ample variation in mean density among isolates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>). Among those bacteria with greater prevalence, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. cloacae</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Klebsiella pneumoniae</named-content></italic> had the highest average densities.Four bacterial isolates were able to noticeably degrade feathers of Spectacled Thrushes in vitro, but only <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> was able to fully disintegrate them in &lt;21 days (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-f01">Figure 1</xref>). <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Klebsiella oxytoca</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. cloacae</named-content></italic>, and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hafnia alvei</named-content></italic> also display perceptible keratinolytic properties; they were able to fragment feathers into large pieces (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Keratinolytic activity of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> was as severe as that of our positive control, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, well known for its feather-degrading properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>); both bacilli totally disintegrated feathers in 14 days. The remaining 14 isolates did not visibly fragment feathers (degradation index range: 1&ndash;2; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref>). Nevertheless, the degradation indices of all 18 bacteria were significantly greater than zero, the score of both negative controls after 21 days of exposure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Table 1</xref>; Mann-Whitney one-tailed test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 in all cases).Failure to fully or partially degrade feathers was not due to unviability of bacteria; all inocula from every experimental tube grew rapidly in rich LB medium at the end of the 21-day experimental period. Lack of feather degradation in both the negative controls confirmed that feather damage in experimental tubes was due to the action of bacteria and not to culture conditions.From the plumage of 40 Spectacled Thrushes, we cultured 18 bacterial isolates belonging to 13 genera capable of growing in FMA, a medium selective for keratinolytic bacteria. Comparable numbers of FDB were isolated in Alabama, USA, from the plumages of Eastern Bluebirds (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia sialis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">Shawkey et al. 2005</xref>) and House Finches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey4">2009</xref>) (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 15, 13, and 22, respectively). In Estonia, 18 FDB phylotypes were recorded on 290 wild Great Tits, averaging 2.3 phylotypes bird<sup>&minus;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Saag1">Saag et al. 2011</xref>). We know of no other inventory that comprehensively describes the diversity of FDB hosted by wild birds using culture-dependent protocols.Considering that selective cultivation protocols can reveal the presence of only a minor fraction of the bacterial species present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Amann1">Amann et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">Shawkey et al. 2005</xref>), a significant number of bacteria in our study must have gone undetected. Culture-independent methods should help reveal a considerably larger bacterial diversity than that accounted for by our methods.<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus cereus</named-content></italic>, the most ubiquitous and aggressive FDB in our sample, was previously known to have keratinolytic activity; it had been isolated from poultry waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Kim1">Kim et al. 2001</xref>), soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>), and wild birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">Shawkey et al. 2005</xref>). Except for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. megaterium</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-ElShora1">El-Shora et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>), <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-DeToni1">De Toni et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Yamamura1">Yamamura et al. 2002</xref>), <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Dermacoccus nishinomiyaensis</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>), and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic>, the rest (14) of the keratinolytic bacteria reported here were not known to grow on feather meal or to degrade feathers. Interestingly, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, the most widespread FDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>), was not found on the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes. Nevertheless, the widespread presence of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> was in agreement with the prediction of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>) that feather-degrading bacilli will be found in all species of birds that are adequately sampled.It is noteworthy that, contrary to previous studies, most isolates in our sample (11; 61.1&percnt;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">Table 2</xref>) were Gram-negative. The rest included Gram-positive coccus and bacilli of known keratinolytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>). In House Finches the percentage of Gram-negative bacteria able to grow on FMA ranged from only 9.1&percnt; (2 of 22 taxa; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey4">Shawkey et al. 2009</xref>) to 15.4&percnt; (2 of 13 taxa; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>: table 1). In a comprehensive summary of feather bacteria that have keratinolytic activity, 28.6&percnt; (6 of 21 species) were Gram-negative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gunderson1">Gunderson 2008</xref>:table 1).Most previous research of feather bacteria has focused on the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic> because, until recently, feather degradation by bacteria had been described mostly for isolates restricted to the genera <italic>Bacillus</italic> and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sangali1">Sangali and Brandelli 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>). Particular focus has been on <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> because of its well-known capacity to disintegrate feathers in liquid culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>). Hence, in many studies of wild birds, selective incubating conditions such as prolonged high temperature (50&ndash;60&deg;C) and a salty and alkaline nutrient broth (7.5&percnt; NaCl, pH 7.5) were designed to favor the growth of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Reneerkens1">Reneerkens et al. 2008</xref>). However, such conditions also inhibit growth of other bacteria, including most other bacilli and, especially, Gram-negative bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>). In the present study, we used culture conditions (37&deg;C, pH 7.2) that also favored the growth of a variety of bacilli and of Gram-negative bacteria. Recent evidence indicates that keratinolysis is not limited to Gram-positive bacteria. Several species of mesophilic Gram-negative bacteria tested from laboratory strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Allpress1">Allpress et al. 2002</xref>), isolated from poultry industrial waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sangali1">Sangali and Brandelli 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-DeToni1">De Toni et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli2">Brandelli and Riffel 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Riffel1">Riffel and Brandelli 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Riffel3">Riffel et al. 2007</xref>), wild birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey4">2009</xref>, present study), soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Bach1">Bach et al. 2011</xref>), and mammalian fur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Yamamura1">Yamamura et al. 2002</xref>), are currently known to have keratinolytic activity. It is unlikely that the absence of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> in our samples was due to unfavorable culture conditions, because the isolate that we used as positive control in our experiments readily grew on LB and FMA.These recent findings suggest that our knowledge of FDB diversity and physiology has been limited by the restrictions and bias of culture methods, and imply that there is an unknown diversity of FDB hosted in feathers. Future protocols in culture-dependent studies of wild birds should be more inclusive, to favor the growth of Gram-negative, mesophilic bacteria, and taxa other than bacilli. The identification of new feather-degrading isolates by culture-dependent techniques is necessary to develop culture-independent methods to examine community diversity of FDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>), as well as to compare results obtained using the two methodologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey1">Shawkey et al. 2005</xref>). In addition, the search for Gram-negative bacteria from wild birds may have interest for the processing of keratin-rich wastes, because keratinases of Gram-negative bacteria seem to be different from those isolated from Gram-positive bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Riffel2">Riffel et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Bach1">Bach et al. 2011</xref>).All 40 Spectacled Thrushes in our sample hosted at least one keratinolytic bacterial species, and the most prevalent one, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic>, was isolated from 85&percnt; of the birds. So great an overall prevalence of FDB or of <italic>Bacillus</italic> is uncommon among wild birds. In a sample of 1,588 birds belonging to 83 species of North American birds, the occurrence of keratinolytic bacilli ranged annually from 6.7&percnt; to 10.7&percnt;, depending on season and year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>). The greatest prevalence occurred in House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>), in which 23&percnt; of individuals had feather-degrading bacilli. Among 461 wild-captured northern temperate birds, putative FDB were isolated from 21&ndash;59&percnt; of individuals of each of eight species examined, and an estimated 27&percnt; of all individuals carried <italic>B. lichenformis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Whitaker1">Whitaker et al. 2005</xref>). In Song Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Melospiza melodia</named-content></italic>) of the western United States, feather-degrading bacilli occurred in 23&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 142) of individuals in humid habitats and in 18&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 77) of those in arid environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt2">Burtt and Ichida 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>) estimated that an average of 14 individuals would need to be sampled to find one individual with feather-degrading bacilli. These figures contrast with the ubiquitous prevalence of FDB in our Spectacled Thrush sample. Among temperate species, a similar prevalence of FDB (99&percnt; of individuals, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 68) was recorded in another turdid, the Eastern Bluebird, in southern Virginia, USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gunderson2">Gunderson et al. 2009</xref>).The prevalence of keratinolytic bacteria in our sample agrees with observations that ground-foraging birds such as Spectacled Thrushes have a greater prevalence of feather-degrading <italic>Bacillus</italic> because colonization of the birds' plumage is likely through contact with the soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida 1999</xref>); <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> has been isolated from soil samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lucas1">Lucas et al. 2003</xref>). In addition, high ambient temperatures at our study site throughout the year and high humidity throughout the lengthy rainy season should also favor the growth of bacteria and their successful colonization of plumage.Season was not important in explaining prevalence, abundance, or diversity of keratinolytic bacteria, although there is a marked seasonality at our study site; the rainy season is followed by a 4-mo dry season during which an average of only 30.3 mm of rain falls in just 9 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-WorldWeatherInformationService1">World Weather Information Service 2011</xref>). Our results contrast with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>), who found that the prevalence of feather-degrading bacilli in the plumage of eastern North American birds varied with the time of year, likely in relation to humidity and seasonal variations in feather maintenance behavior.The extent of feather damage in vitro by bacterial isolates was highly variable. At one extreme, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic> had degrading activity comparable to that of our positive control <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, seemingly the most aggressive feather-degrading bacillus known. Both bacilli were capable of fully disintegrating Spectacled Thrush feathers in 14 days in liquid culture. At the other extreme, 14 isolates, although showing perceptible growth on feathers, did not visually damage them. An ample range in the production of keratinase, assumed to reveal a bacterium's feather-degrading activity, was also found in vitro among 13 strains of keratinolytic bacteria isolated from House Finches. One of the isolates (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Kocuria rhizophila</named-content></italic>) produced a quantity of keratinase comparable to that of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic>, whereas the rest produced smaller or no detectable amounts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Shawkey2">Shawkey et al. 2003</xref>).It is important to note that keratinase production and feather-degrading activity in vitro are not properties of bacteria species only; both also depend on other factors, including bacterial strain, keratin substrate, sterilization method, and culture conditions. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt1">Burtt and Ichida (1999</xref>) isolated a strain of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. subtilis</named-content></italic> unable to degrade feathers, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Zerdani1">Zerdani et al. (2004</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Macedo1">Macedo et al. (2005</xref>) reported strains with high levels of keratinolytic activity. Similarly, although several strains of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> are capable of completely disintegrating feathers, not all strains have keratinolytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Allpress1">Allpress et al. 2002</xref>), and their proteolytic enzymes display a broad range of activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Lin1">Lin et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Cheng1">Cheng et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>). Presence and type of pigment in feathers also are known to affect the resistance of feather keratin to bacterial degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt2">Burtt and Ichida 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Grande1">Grande et al. 2004</xref>); melanized chicken (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Goldstein1">Goldstein et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gunderson3">Gunderson et al. 2008</xref>) and pigmented feathers of parrots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Burtt3">Burtt et al. 2011</xref>) are more resistant to hydrolysis by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. licheniformis</named-content></italic> than unmelanized feathers. Likewise, keratinase production and keratin-degrading ability in vitro are also dependent on culture conditions, such as pH, temperature, salinity, and presence of metals and additives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Bockle1">B&ouml;ckle et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Sangali1">Sangali and Brandelli 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Allpress1">Allpress et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli2">Brandelli and Riffel 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Riffel1">Riffel and Brandelli 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Brandelli1">Brandelli 2008</xref>). Hence, results from one species or strain of FDB under particular experimental protocols should not be generalized; findings of different studies may not be strictly comparable. Likewise, we cannot assert that bacterial impact in the plumage of free-living birds resembles in vitro bacterial activity.It is relevant to emphasize that in our experimental protocol, FDB were originally isolated by culturing in selective FMA, whose keratin was provided by white feathers of domestic chickens, whereas our feather-degrading experiments were performed on dark (brownish) secondary feathers of Spectacled Thrushes. It is also important to note that we sterilized feathers by autoclaving, which may make them more readily degradable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-Gunderson3">Gunderson et al. 2008</xref>). In brief, strict comparison of keratinolytic activity of FDB of wild birds is currently complicated by differences in experimental conditions among studies and by the diversity of methods used to estimate feather-degrading activity.It is not known whether the potential feather-damaging capacity of bacteria in vivo might also be a function of its density or, vice versa, that density might be a function of degrading capacity. Some of the isolates less effective at breaking down feathers in our study were numerically dominant in colonized individuals (e.g., <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">K. pneumoniae</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">E. cloacae</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t01">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-131-1-100-t02">2</xref>), having average densities 2&ndash;5 times higher than that of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">B. cereus</named-content></italic>. Hence, although this is speculative, their great abundance may enhance their effect on the plumage of wild Spectacled Thrushes.Ours is the first study on the keratinolytic bacterial community of a tropical bird. The results show that Spectacled Thrushes host a diverse, and prevalent, group of bacteria capable of growing in feathers in liquid culture. This result corroborates similar findings among temperate species of birds, although prevalence does not appear to be as great among the latter. Although we cannot assert that keratinolytic bacteria are (or are not) harmful to wild Spectacled Thrushes, the results of our feather-degrading in vitro assays indicate that they are potentially harmful. However, possible fitness consequences of feather damage remain to be investigated. We do not pretend to make a generalized statement about FDB of tropical birds; knowledge of the microbial diversity harbored by plumage and how bacteria interact with birds is just beginning in tropical as well as temperate species.We thank R. Gajardo, L. Lage, and I. Fajardo for their valuable help while carrying out microbiology tests. C.V. acknowledges FONACIT and Misi&oacute;n Ciencia for their worthy support of his doctoral studies. We also thank Oficina Nacional de Diversidad Biol&oacute;gica, M. P. P. Ambiente, for granting us permission to capture the birds used in this research. Capture of birds and feather collection were conducted under permit no. 3159 from Ministerio P. P. para el Ambiente to C.V. Birds were captured and handled by C.V. and A.S. in accordance with the AOU's &ldquo;Guidelines to the Use of Wild Birds in Research.&rdquo; We gratefully acknowledge the critical revision and constructive comments of two anonymous reviewers and of the editorial group.In vitro degradation of feathers of Spectacled Thrushes by keratinolytic bacteria isolated from their plumage: (<bold>A</bold>) <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bacillus cereus</named-content></italic>, (<bold>B</bold>) <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Klebsiella oxytoca</named-content></italic>, and (<bold>C</bold>) <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Escherichia hermannii</named-content></italic>, after 14, 21, and 21 days of incubation, respectively, in basal medium. (<bold>A</bold>) Corresponds to a maximum degradation index of 6: only fragments &lt;5 mm<sup>2</sup> float in the medium. (<bold>B</bold>) Corresponds to a degradation index of 4: The feather is fragmented into large fragments; the integrity of the feather is lost. (<bold>C</bold>) Degradation index 2, a veil, or cloudy biofilm indicative of bacterial growth, develops over the feather surface, but there is no apparent damage to it.In vitro feather-degrading activity of keratinolytic bacteria isolated from the plumage of Spectacled Thrushes.Keratinolytic bacteria isolated from the plumage of wild Spectacled Thrushes in northern Venezuela.