Determinants of parental care in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> oriantha</italic>)Parental effort in relation to structural plumage coloration in the Mountain Bluebird (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sialia currucoides</named-content></italic>)Senescence of maternal effects: Aging influences egg quality and rearing capacities of a long-lived birdReproductive compensation for offspring viability deficits by female Mallards, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Anas platyrhynchos</named-content></italic>Sexual selection for aesthetic traits in species with biparental careThe differential-allocation hypothesis: An experimental testBird hematocrits: Effects of high altitude and strength of flightNestling provisioning by male and female Yellow-breasted Chats: No relationships between morphology and parental carePaternal investment inversely related to degree of extra-pair paternity in the Reed BuntingSignals of status in wintering Mountain White-crowned Sparrows, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> gambelii</italic>Reproductive compensationThe hypothesis of reproductive compensation and its assumptions about mate preferences and offspring viabilityReproductive investment when mate quality varies: Differential allocation versus reproductive compensationNegotiation over offspring care?&mdash;A positive response to partner-provisioning rate in Great TitsThe good parent process of sexual selectionEndocrine influences on parental care during a short breeding season: Testosterone and male parental care in Lapland Longspurs (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Calcarius lapponicus</named-content></italic>)The relationship between maternal ornamentation and feeding rate is explained by intrinsic nestling qualityParental investment, sexual selection and sex ratiosAre Mountain White-crowned Sparrow badges reliable signals?Plumage brightness as an indicator of parental care in Northern CardinalsPaternal care declines with increased opportunity for extra-pair matings in Fairy MartinsMorphological and genetic predictors of parental care in the North American Barn Swallow <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Hirundo rustica</named-content> erythrogaster</italic>Female attractiveness affects paternal investment: Experimental evidence for male differential allocation in Blue TitsA three-genome phylogeny of malaria parasites (<italic>Plasmodium</italic> and closely related genera): Evolution of life-history traits and host switchesMale Rock Sparrows differentially allocate nest defence but not food provisioning to offspringMale parental care, differential parental investment by females and sexual selectionSafe betting: Males help dull females only when they raise high-quality offspringThe Mountain White-crowned Sparrow: Migration and reproduction at high altitudeDoes the badge of status influence parental care and investment in House Sparrows? An experimental testHaematological health state indices of reproducing Great Tits: Methodology and sources of natural variationTestosterone affects reproductive success by influencing extra-pair fertilizations in male Dark-eyed Juncos (Aves: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Junco hyemalis</named-content></italic>)Differential allocation and compensation: Who deserves the silver spoon?Corticosterone inhibits feather growth: Potential mechanism explaining seasonal down regulation of corticosterone during moltDynamic paternity allocation as a function of male plumage color in Barn SwallowsBrighter yellow Blue Tits make better parentsDifferential allocation: Tests, mechanisms and implicationsExtra-pair fertilizations in Mountain White-crowned SparrowsFood, feathers, and fluctuating assymmetriesEarly elevation of testosterone advances migratory preparation in a songbirdParental investment and sexual selectionParental feeding rates in the House Sparrow, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>: Are larger-badged males better fathers?The &ldquo;challenge hypothesis&rdquo;: Theoretical implications for patterns of testosterone secretion, mating systems, and breeding strategiesThese authors contributed equally to the paper.Extent of parental care, such as food provisioning to offspring, can vary widely between sexes in socially monogamous birds. The determinants of the sex-specific provisioning behaviors remain unclear as they could be associated with individual condition, as well as mate contribution and quality. In a population of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> oriantha</italic>), we tested the good parent hypothesis, the reproductive compensation hypothesis, and the differential allocation hypothesis among 29 nesting pairs during the breeding season. Using multivariable linear regression, we examined the relationship of offspring food provisioning rate, a measure of parental care, with each parent's own demographic (sex, age), morphological (tail length, wing chord, tarsus, mass, body fat, and cloacal protuberance), and physiological (hematocrit and infection status) characteristics, as well as crown-white, a reliable status signal in this species. In male birds, feeding rate was positively correlated with partner crown-white (0.31 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: 0.18, 0.44&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1&percnt; crown-white), and inversely associated with partner mass and body fat (mass: (&minus;0.42 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.80, &minus;0.05&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1 g; body fat: &minus;1.74 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;2.58, &minus;0.90&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1-unit increment in body-fat score). These findings suggest that mate quality is a predictor of food provisioning behavior in males but not females, thus providing some sex-specific support for the differential allocation hypothesis. On the other hand, we did not find conclusive evidence for the good parent or reproductive compensation hypotheses.El grado de cuidado parental, como la provisi&oacute;n de alimento a los polluelos, puede variar ampliamente entre sexos de aves socialmente mon&oacute;gamas. Los determinantes de los comportamientos de aprovisionamiento espec&iacute;ficos de cada sexo a&uacute;n no est&aacute;n claros, ya que pueden asociarse con la condici&oacute;n individual y con la contribuci&oacute;n y calidad de la pareja. En una poblaci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> oriantha</italic> pusimos a prueba las hip&oacute;tesis del buen padre, de compensaci&oacute;n reproductiva y de asignaci&oacute;n diferencial entre 29 parejas anidantes durante la temporada reproductiva. Usando regresi&oacute;n lineal m&uacute;ltiple examinamos la relaci&oacute;n de la tasa de aprovisionamiento de los polluelos (una medida de cuidado parental) con las caracter&iacute;sticas demogr&aacute;ficas (sexo, edad), morfol&oacute;gicas (longitud de cola, ala y tarso, masa, grasa corporal y protuberancia cloacal) y fisiol&oacute;gicas (hematocrito y estado de infecci&oacute;n) propias de cada padre, as&iacute; como con el blanco de la coronilla, una se&ntilde;al de estatus social en esta especie. En machos, la tasa de alimentaci&oacute;n se correlacion&oacute; positivamente con el blanco de la coronilla de su pareja (0.31 &lsqb;95&percnt; IC: 0.18, 0.44&rsqb; veces/hora por 1&percnt; de blanco de la coronilla), e inversamente con la masa y grasa corporal de su pareja (masa: (&minus;0.42 &lsqb;95&percnt; IC: &minus;0.80, &minus;0.05&rsqb; veces/hora por 1g; grasa corporal: &minus;1.74 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;2.58, &minus;0.90&rsqb; veces/hora por unidad de incremento en el puntaje de grasa corporal). Estos resultados sugieren que la calidad de la pareja es un predictor del comportamiento de aprovisionamiento de alimento en los machos pero no en las hembras, lo cual representa algo de sustento para la hip&oacute;tesis de asignaci&oacute;n diferencial. Por otro lado, no encontramos evidencia definitiva a favor de las hip&oacute;tesis del buen padre o de compensaci&oacute;n reproductiva.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> aprovisionamiento de alimento, cuidado parental, hip&oacute;tesis de asignaci&oacute;n diferencial, hip&oacute;tesis de compensaci&oacute;n reproductiva, hip&oacute;tesis del buen padre, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> oriantha</italic>Parental care is critical for offspring survival in species with altricial young. The factors that shape trends of parental investment have been a longstanding topic of interest among evolutionary biologists as trade-offs between survival versus current or future reproductive potential are crucial to an individual's fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Trivers1">Trivers 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-CluttonBrock1">Clutton-Brock 1991</xref>). For example, in brood-caring species, parents are faced with the dilemma of providing care according to their offspring's needs and their own needs, while also balancing their mate's contributions. These dynamics provide valuable insight into life history constraints and sexual selection pressures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Moller1">M&oslash;ller and Thornhill 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Kokko1">Kokko and Jennions 2008</xref>).There are currently 3 main hypotheses describing determinants of parental care: the good parent hypothesis, the reproductive compensation hypothesis, and the differential allocation hypothesis (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Maguire1">Maguire &amp; Safran 2010</xref>). According to the good parent hypothesis, quality of parental care is directly related to parental condition, which is in turn reflected in reliable signals of quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Hoelzer1">Hoelzer 1989</xref>). In other words, parents with adequate resources and health are able to sustain greater costs of parental care. Alternatively, the quality of parental investment in offspring may reflect mate quality. The reproductive compensation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Bluhm1">Bluhm and Gowaty 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Gowaty2">Gowaty et al. 2007</xref>) and the differential allocation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Burley1">Burley 1986</xref>) both propose that parental investment strategies are shaped by partner characteristics. According to the reproductive compensation hypothesis, parental effort may increase to offset low partner contribution characteristic of a suboptimal mate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Gowaty1">Gowaty 2008</xref>). On the other hand, the differential allocation hypothesis predicts that offspring food provisioning increases as partner quality increases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Burley1">Burley 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Burley2">1988</xref>). That is, when paired to a partner with high direct (i.e. resources) or indirect (i.e. genetic) qualities, individuals invest more in current offspring to maximize fitness through collective parental investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Sheldon1">Sheldon 2000</xref>).The three above-mentioned hypotheses have been tested in a range of species. Some studies provide support of the good parent hypothesis, which leverages quality of the individual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Linville1">Linville et al. 1998</xref>), while others point toward the differential allocation hypothesis or the reproductive compensation hypothesis&mdash;both of which predict that mate quality drives parental investment, albeit in different directions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Harris1">Harris and Uller 2009</xref>). Several studies have also reported no relationship between parental qualities and feeding rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Cooper1">Cooper and Ritchison 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Balenger1">Balenger et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Nakagawa1">Nakagawa et al. 2007</xref>). The inconsistencies in literature reflect an assortment of empirical methods and are difficult to interpret since parental strategies and fitness trade-offs vary by study organism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Ratikainen1">Ratikainen and Kokko 2009</xref>).In this study, we investigated male and female parental investment with respect to self and partner quality, as assessed by several morphological and physiological characteristics, and the crown-white signal in a population of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Zonotrichia leucophrys</named-content> oriantha</italic>), a socially monogamous species that exhibits biparental care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Morton1">Morton 2002</xref>). The crown-white signal is of particular interest because it is a badge of status relevant to breeding season social interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Laubach1">Laubach et al. 2013</xref>) and general dominance relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Fugle1">Fugle et al. 1984</xref>), and as such is likely related to resource acquisition ability. The aim of this study is to test the good parent, the reproductive compensation, and the differential allocation hypotheses across sexes, by integrating field parental investment information&mdash;in the form of nestling food provisioning rates&mdash;with comprehensive demographic data, morphometric measures, and other information about individual quality and condition. We tested each of these hypotheses with a set of explicit predictions comparable to those outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Maguire1">Maguire &amp; Safran (2010)</xref>. Under the good parent hypothesis we predicted higher feeding rates to be associated with an individual's own traits of quality. For the reproductive compensation hypothesis we expected birds with lower-quality mates to exhibit higher feeding rates. Finally, for the differential allocation hypothesis we predicted higher feeding rates by birds paired with high-quality partners.This study was conducted in a free-living population of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows from 2006 to 2009 at the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory in Gothic (Colorado, USA). On 4 preestablished study plots, we monitored Potter traps baited with white proso millet (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Panicum miliaceum</named-content></italic>) every morning (0600&ndash;1200 hours). Each captured bird received a unique combination of 3 colored plastic leg bands and a single numbered metal U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service band for individual identification and age determination. We measured crown-white and standard morphological traits of all captured birds including tail length, wing chord, tarsus length, and mass. Male and female adult Mountain White-crowned Sparrows have an anterior to posterior oriented white cranial plumage band bordered on each side by black plumage bands, and variation in crown plumage can be quantified, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Laubach1">Laubach et al. 2013</xref>). Crown-white is the ratio of the width of white crown plumage divided by the total crown width, which includes the white and black bands. White and total plumage widths were measured dorsolaterally between the eyes using a mechanical caliper and to the nearest 0.1 mm. Following standard avian morphometric measurement protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Morton1">Morton 2002</xref>), we measured tail length and wing chord using a small ruler and tarsus length was quantified to the nearest 0.1 mm with a caliper. We determined each bird's mass to the nearest 0.1 g using a spring scale. We also assigned each captured bird a body-fat score derived as the average of 2 body-fat ranks, ranging from 0 (no visible fat) to 5 (bulging fat deposits), measured on the abdomen and at the furcula. Measurements from birds caught multiple times within the same year were averaged before use in the final analyses. Sex was determined by measuring the length of the cloacal protuberance (males &ge; 4 mm, females &lt; 4 mm) and by looking for the presence of a brood patch, found only on nesting females.We conducted nest searches throughout the breeding season. Most nests were discovered as a result of flushing the brooding female, by observing parental defense behaviors around a nest, or by observing parents returning to the nest. Upon locating a nest, we determined the stage of the nest (number of eggs or nestlings) and collected information on the physical characteristics of the nesting site (latitude and longitude, height above the ground, and vegetative substrate). We visited each nest on alternating days to monitor hatch dates, fledge dates, and depredation rates. When nestlings were 7&ndash;8 days old, nests were video-recorded (using a Sony MiniDV DCR-HC48; Sony Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) for 2&ndash;4 hrs. Mountain White-crowned Sparrow offspring are expected to fledge around day 9 after hatching, so standardizing video recording a day before fledging was intended to capture the maximum parental nest feeding effort. Nest recording took place early- to mid-morning, and after nest parents had been introduced to camera and tripod the day before to facilitate acclimation. Recorder and tripod were placed ~2 m from the nest and were hidden under a camouflage net. We created a small viewing window by opening and securing vegetation with small clamps; removing vegetation was avoided to least disturb the nest. Parental identities were confirmed using the color combinations of leg bands and distinguishing plumage characteristics from the video recordings. Our variable of interest was parental food provisioning rate, which was calculated as the number of times each parent fed the nestlings per hour of observation. All video recordings were scored in the lab by one observer.We collected a small blood sample (&lt;300 &mu;L) from captured birds; recaptured birds were sampled no more than once every 2 weeks. Blood was drawn from the brachial vein using a fine-tipped syringe (26G) and collected into heparinized microcapillary tubes. All samples were immediately put on ice and processed the same day. We prepared blood smears of approximately one cell-layer thickness on glass microscope slides. Smears were air-dried and then stained using a differential stain (Fisher Hema 3 Stat Pack; Fisher Scientific, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA). We conducted differential counts on each smear at 1000&times; magnification using a compound microscope until 10,000 red blood cells (RBC) were evaluated for the presence of hemoparasites belonging to the genera <italic>Leucocytozoon</italic> (<italic>L. fringillinarum</italic> and <italic>L. majoris</italic>), <italic>Parahaemoproteus (H. coatneyi)</italic>, and <italic>Plasmodium</italic> (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. relictum</named-content></italic> and <italic>P. vaughani</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Valkiunas1">Valki&umacr;nas 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Martinsen1">Martinsen et al. 2008</xref>). While macro- and micro-gametocyte stages can be identified specifically, meront stages and trophozoid stages cannot be identified to species level. These asexual cells were therefore counted in a separate category (trophozoids) but their numbers were pooled with gametocyte numbers to obtain an aggregate parasitemia count for each bird. <italic>Trypanosoma avium</italic> was occasionally observed in a few blood samples, but was excluded from these analyses due to its exceedingly low occurrence and parasitemia numbers.Microcapillary tubes containing fresh blood were centrifuged to precipitate red blood cells and plasma (maximum speed 11,500 rpm for 5 minutes, using a Micro-MB Centrifuge; International Equipment Company, Needham Heights, Massachusetts, USA). Hematocrit levels were measured as the ratio of packed red blood cells to the total sample volume using a standard hematocrit card reader. Hematocrit levels were averaged if multiple samples were obtained from the same individual bird.Using multivariable linear regression, we explored support for the good parent hypothesis by examining the associations of a parent's feeding rate with their own demographic (sex, age), morphological (mass, tarsus length, wing chord, tail length, body fat, and cloacal protuberance), and physiological (hematocrit and infection status) characteristics, as well as with the crown-white signal. Because crown-white was previously demonstrated to be a reliable status badge in this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Laubach1">Laubach et al. 2013</xref>), we assessed it as the main indicator of quality, but we also considered the morphological and physiological characteristics as these traits are likely indicative of underlying quality.In the adjusted analyses, we additionally included number of nestlings as a covariate since it could be related to parental quality, as well as a predictor of feed rate. We assessed the statistical significance of these associations between feed rate and the effect of the main covariate of interest, &beta;<sub>1</sub>, using the Wald &chi;<sup>2</sup> test.We also explored whether feeding rate differed according to partner traits to assess for evidence of the reproductive compensation hypothesis and the differential allocation hypothesis. Using multivariable linear regression, we examined the relation of provisioning rate with respect to mate characteristics in separate models. In these models, we again included number of nestlings as a covariate. To minimize the possibility of false discoveries, we used Bonferroni's correction to determine which associations retained statistical significance after accounting for multiple comparisons and denoted them accordingly in our tables and figures. We carried out all analyses using SAS version 9.3 and multivariable regression was modeled in PROC GENMOD (SAS Inc., Cary, North Carolina, USA).We collected offspring food provisioning data on 29 nesting pairs of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows. Of the total 58 birds in this study, we captured 43 individuals from which we drew blood and obtained morphological data. Descriptive statistics on characteristics of the study population are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-t01">Table 1</xref>. Mean number of nestlings for the 29 nests was 3 (range: 1&ndash;5). The average feeding rate for both sexes (mean &plusmn; SD) per nest was 4.9 &plusmn; 3.3 times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>. Male birds fed offspring 4.1 &plusmn; 2.5 times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>, which was significantly (<italic>p</italic> &equals; 0.04) lower than that of females (5.7 &plusmn; 3.8 times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>); the degree of correlation in feeding rate between the sexes was low (Spearman's &rho; &equals; 0.02). Feeding rate was positively associated with the number of nestlings in male (0.96 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: 0.18, 1.74&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>) but not female parents (Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-t02">Table 2</xref>). To account for the influence of the number of nestlings on provisioning, models included number of nestlings in adjusted analyses, which will be the results we refer to from this point forward.Characteristics of Mountain White-crowned Sparrow for our study population.<sup>a</sup>To test the good parent hypothesis, we first looked at associations of the demographic, morphological, and physiological characteristics of each individual with feeding rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-f01">Figure 1</xref>A and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-t02">Table 2</xref>). Among females, but not males, age was inversely related to feeding rate (&minus;3.70 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;6.79, &minus;0.61&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1 year age). In both sexes, feeding rate was associated with tail length, although the trend was in opposite directions. Male feeding rate was 0.33 (95&percnt; CI: 0.14, 0.51) times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> lower per 1 mm tail length, while female feeding rate was 0.79 (95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.03, 1.60) times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> higher. We also observed a weak inverse relationship between male feeding rate and crown-white (&minus;0.10 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.20, 0.01&rsqb; per 1&percnt; crown-white). After applying Bonferroni's correction for 20 comparisons, the only association that remained statistically significant was the positive relation between tail length and feeding rate among male birds.Parental feed rate after accounting for number of nestlings with respect to (<bold>A</bold>) individual characteristics (the &ldquo;good parent hypothesis&rdquo;) and (<bold>B</bold>) partner's characteristics (the &ldquo;differential allocation hypothesis&rdquo;). Asterisk denotes statistical significance after accounting for multiple comparisons using Bonferroni's correction (20 comparisons for each hypothesis; <italic>P</italic> &lt; &alpha; &equals; 0.05/20 &equals; 0.0025). CP &equals; cloacal protuberance; CW &equals; crown-white.Next we compared parental feeding rates with respect to partner characteristics to evaluate support for the reproductive compensation hypothesis and the differential allocation hypothesis. Among male birds, feeding rate was positively associated with partner crown-white, but inversely related to partner mass and body-fat score (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-f01">Figure 1</xref>B and Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-t03">Table 3</xref>). Each 1&percnt; of the female partner's crown-white was associated with 0.31 (95&percnt; CI: 0.18, 0.44) times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> higher feeding rate, while higher partner mass and body-fat score corresponded with lower male feeding rate (partner mass: &minus;0.42 (95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.80, &minus;0.05) times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>; partner body-fat score: &minus;1.74 (95&percnt; CI: &minus;2.58, &minus;0.90) times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>). Because both mass and body fat could be a consequence of age, we further accounted for partner age and observed no change in the estimate for male feeding rate with respect to partner mass (&minus;0.42 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;0.80, &minus;0.03&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>) or partner body-fat score (&minus;1.78 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;2.68, &minus;0.89&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup>). After applying Bonferroni's correction, the inverse relation of partner fat score and the positive association with partner crown-white with male feeding rate retained statistical significance.Among female birds, feeding rate was negatively correlated with partner's cloacal protuberance (&minus;1.69 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: &minus;2.80, &minus;0.58&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1 mm) and positively related to partner's hematocrit levels (0.53 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: 0.00, 1.06&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1&percnt;). Accounting for partner age did not alter the direction of the estimates, though it did slightly strengthen these associations (partner cloacal protuberance: &minus;1.94 &lsqb;&minus;3.23, &minus;0.64&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1 mm; partner hematocrit: 0.68 &lsqb;95&percnt; CI: 0.03, 1.34&rsqb; times hour<sup>&minus;1</sup> per 1 &percnt;). The relations of partner cloacal protuberance and hematocrit levels with female feeding rate did not reach statistical significance after correcting for multiple comparisons.Patterns of parental care may vary between males and females due to differences in sexual selection pressure and life history trade-offs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Moller1">M&oslash;ller and Thornhill 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Kokko1">Kokko and Jennions 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Harris1">Harris and Uller 2009</xref>). To elucidate determinants of parental investment strategies, we examined rate of offspring food provisioning in 29 pairs of nesting Mountain White-crowned Sparrows with respect to each bird's own characteristics, as well as its partner's traits, during the mating season. We tested 3 hypotheses: the good parent hypothesis, which predicts that higher quality parents invest more in offspring; the reproductive compensation hypothesis, which posits that individuals may increase parental efforts to offset low partner quality and provisional contribution; and the differential allocation hypothesis, which proposes that parental investment increases with partner quality (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Maguire1">Maguire and Safran 2010</xref>). In support of differential allocation, we found that male birds paired with higher-quality females, as indicated by greater proportion crown-white, demonstrated higher rates of food provisioning. We did not find support for the good parent or reproductive compensation hypotheses.In the first portion of our analysis, we assessed how parental feeding rate related to each bird's own traits. Among males, percent crown-white, a reliable indicator of social status in this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Laubach1">Laubach et al. 2013</xref>), along with tail length, a possible indicator of nutritional status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Swaddle1">Swaddle and Witter 1994</xref>) and endocrine profile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Romero1">Romero et al. 2005</xref>), were each inversely associated with feeding rate. While such findings indicate that higher-quality males are less invested in offspring care, a study in House Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Passer domesticus</named-content></italic>) found a positive association between male status badge and feeding rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Voltura1">Voltura et al. 2002</xref>). The conflicting literature could be due to species-specific differences in the information encoded by different types of signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Senar1">Senar et al. 2002</xref>), i.e. what signals quality of parental care may differ from signals of resource holding potential or genetic quality in different species.In females, we observed lower feeding rates among older individuals, which could reflect senescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-BeamonteBarrientos1">Beamonte-Barrientos et al. 2010</xref>), as decaying condition inhibits ability to provision. Unlike male birds, feeding rate was not associated with number of nestlings. Taken in consideration with the inverse association of female age with feeding rate, this finding may indicate that the female birds are feeding at maximum capacity, and that limits may be determined by physical or health-related constraints. We also noted a marginally significant positive relation between tail length and feeding rate, which is the opposite of what was observed in males. This finding could lend some support to the good parent hypothesis, if tail length is indeed reflective of quality. A potential explanation for this sex-specific discrepancy is that higher-quality males improve fitness through extra-pair copulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Safran1">Safran et al. 2005</xref>), a trade-off with offspring investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Magrath1">Magrath and Elgar 1997</xref>), whereas higher-quality females devote to caring for offspring. This notion is supported by evidence of extensive extra-pair copulation in this (B. McDougall-Shackleton personal communication) and other populations of Mountain White-crowned Sparrows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Sherman1">Sherman and Morton 1988</xref>).When we examined parental investment with respect to mate quality, we found some support for the differential allocation hypothesis. Male food provisioning rate was positively associated with partner crown-white, an indicator of social status in both sexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Fugle1">Fugle et al. 1984</xref>), although it should be cautioned that crown-white badge reliability has only been confirmed in male birds during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Laubach1">Laubach et al. 2013</xref>). Our finding that male birds demonstrated higher feeding rates when paired with a higher-quality partner mirrors recent findings regarding paternal feeding rate in Blue Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanistes caeruleus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Mahr1">Mahr et al. 2012</xref>) and nest defense behaviors in Rock Sparrows (<italic>Petronia petronia</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Matessi1">Matessi et al. 2009</xref>), suggesting that males adjust their efforts according to partner quality. The opposite trend was found in Blue-footed Boobies (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sula nebouxii</named-content></italic>), although the investigators speculated that the appearance of low-quality traits in female birds may have been a consequence of greater investment in producing higher-quality eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Morales1">Morales et al. 2011</xref>). It is possible that female quality from the male perspective is assessed both by signals communicating potential to invest in current offspring as well as indications of earlier investment.We also found an inverse relation of partner's mass and body-fat scores with male feeding rate. By itself, this finding could support either the differential allocation or the reproductive compensation hypothesis depending on what is reflected by lower mass and body-fat score in female birds. On the one hand, lower mass and body fat could reflect poor condition. On the other hand, it could also be indicative of greater energy investment in offspring. Since previous work in this species indicates that both mass and body fat are directly influenced by energetic demands of parental effort in this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Morton1">Morton 2002</xref>), we suspect that these characteristics indicate higher quality by virtue of greater female investment, and that male birds increase their efforts to match those of their partner.Among females, feeding rate was not associated with their partner's crown-white badge or morphology, but it was positively related to the male's hematocrit levels, and inversely related to his cloacal protuberance. Since hematocrit increases with physical activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Carpenter1">Carpenter 1975</xref>), the direct association of female feeding rate with partner hematocrit supports the differential allocation hypothesis as it may reflect parallel efforts of female birds to match their mate's provisioning behaviors, a physically demanding task (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Ots1">Ots et al. 1998</xref>). On the other hand, cloacal protuberance is responsive to testosterone levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Tonra1">Tonra et al. 2011</xref>), an indicator of lower parental investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Hunt1">Hunt et al. 1999</xref>) and increased mating behavior in some species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Wingfield1">Wingfield et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Raouf1">Raouf et al. 1997</xref>), thus females paired with these males may lower their parenting efforts accordingly. Taken together, we speculate that females might respond in a direct manner to male effort&mdash;feeding more when paired to males who are more active or invest more in offspring, and less when their partners exhibit signs of mating behavior. These results are in line with findings in Great Tits (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Parus major</named-content></italic>), where experimental manipulation of one parent's feeding rate led to an increase in its partner's feeding rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Hinde1">Hinde 2006</xref>). Insomuch as collective parental effort may be synergistic, we noted that male and female feeding rates were not correlated in this population. A potential explanation for this is that feeding behaviors are likely not the only measures of parental investment. For example, nest guarding and incubation behaviors are also possible indicators of parental care that we did not measure in this study. In fact, the lack of correlation between partner feeding rates may indicate that this is but one of several important and interacting forms of parental investment. Future studies exploring multiple forms of parental investment are warranted in this species.Of note, we observed a direct relationship between feeding rate and number of nestlings among males only. There are a few explanations for this association. First, a larger brood represents higher energetic costs and reproductive investment from the female bird, thereby serving as an indicator of mate quality to the male bird. This could lead to differential allocation on his part through increased offspring provisioning efforts. Second, more nestlings may elicit higher rates of food provisioning simply in response to begging behavior; perhaps these responses are more easily elicited from the male bird. For example, more nestlings may represent higher apparent paternity, leading male birds to increase provisioning efforts since he might perceive greater reproductive fitness opportunities. It should be noted, however, that we accounted for brood size in all models, so the observed associations were robust to nestling quantity.Regulating individual parental investment in response to partner traits maximizes fitness by incurring the highest costs when mate quality is high and therefore reproductive potential is high, and conversely, reducing investment when fitness prospect is low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Sheldon1">Sheldon 2000</xref>). In our study population, rate of offspring food provisioning was higher among males paired with higher-quality partners, as assessed by crown-white, with similar but weaker trends observed among female birds, thus providing some support for the differential allocation hypothesis.While these findings shed light on potential evolutionary drivers of parental investment in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows, our study suffers some limitations, including an observational design, which precludes ability to infer causation, lack of information on signal preference and mate-selection constraint, and lack of data on other mechanisms of parental investment that contribute to offspring survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Gowaty2">Gowaty et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Gowaty1">Gowaty 2008</xref>). Furthermore, we did not account for offspring begging behaviors, which could influence parental feed rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Kiss1">Kiss et al. 2012</xref>). Future studies should quantify offspring behaviors, as well as mating efforts as they represent alternative strategies of reproductive investment. For example, in populations where extra-pair copulation rates are high, we might expect lower male feeding rates due to uncertainty in paternity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Dixon1">Dixon et al. 1994</xref>) and/or greater effort put toward mating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-4-893-Magrath1">Magrath and Elgar 1997</xref>); paternity analyses would provide insight into such discrepancies. Additionally, experimental manipulations that alter partners' signals of attractiveness and quality would allow causal inference about the differential allocation and reproductive compensation hypotheses, which are likely to change across shifting socio-ecological contexts.We would like to thank Dr. Peter Bednekoff, for his review of earlier drafts of this manuscript and the insightful feedback that he provided. In addition we thank Mike Akresh, Peter Tang, Greg Sampson, Rafael Rivera, and the entire Foufopoulos lab for their assistance with data collection.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> Financial support was provided by the University of Michigan Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program (to ML) and logistic support was provided by the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory to the sparrow working group.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> This project was approved by the University of Michigan Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (Protocol Nr. 09489).Parental feed rate with respect to parental characteristics (&ldquo;good parent hypothesis&rdquo;) in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows.Feed rate with respect to partner's characteristics (&ldquo;differential allocation hypothesis&rdquo;) in Mountain White-crowned Sparrows.