New insights into New World biogeography: An integrated view from the phylogeny of blackbirds, cardinals, sparrows, tanagers, warblers, and alliesPhylogeny and classification of the Old World Emberizini (Aves, Passeriformes)Avifaunal interchange across the Panamanian isthmus: Insights from <italic>Campylorhynchus</italic> wrensPhylogeny and diversification of modern passerinesA phylogenetic hypothesis for passerine birds: Taxonomic and biogeographic implications of an analysis of nuclear DNA sequence dataGoing to extremes: Contrasting rates of diversification in a recent radiation of New World passerine birdsNew insights into New World biogeography: An integrated view from the phylogeny of blackbirds, cardinals, sparrows, tanagers, warblers, and alliesPhylogeny and diversification of the largest avian radiationProcess in the evolution of bird migration and pattern in avian ecogeographyThe evolution of supertreesThe delayed rise of present-day mammalsBayesian estimation of speciation and extinction probabilities from (in)complete phylogeniesTesting for temporal variation in diversification rates when sampling is incomplete and nonrandomStrong mitochondrial DNA support for a Cretaceous origin of modern avian lineagesComparison of species tree methods for reconstructing the phylogeny of Bearded Manakins (Aves: Pipridae, Manacus) from multilocus sequence dataMolecular systematics of tanagers (Thraupinae): Evolution and biogeography of a diverse radiation of Neotropical birdsPhylogenetic relationships and morphological diversity in Darwin's finches and their relativesMolecular phylogenetics and biogeography of Neotropical tanagers in the genus <italic>Tangara</italic>Molecular phylogenetics of a clade of lowland tanagers: Implications for avian participation in the Great American InterchangePhylogenetics and diversification of tanagers (Passeriformes: Thraupidae), the largest radiation of Neotropical songbirdsTesting the molecular and evolutionary causes of a &lsquo;leapfrog' pattern of geographical variation in colorationEvolutionary differentiation in the Neotropical montane region: Molecular phylogenetics and phylogeography of <italic>Buarremon</italic> brush-finches (Aves, Emberizidae)The eBird/Clements checklist of birds of the world: Version 6.9The geologic evolution of the Central American IsthmusThe Great American Biotic Interchange revisitedThe evolution of avian migration systems between temperate and tropical regions of the New WorldPasseriformesSpecies trees from highly incongruent gene trees in riceSlowdowns in diversification rates from real phylogenies may not be realThe Great American Interchange in birds: A phylogenetic perspective with the genus <italic>Trogon</italic>Reweaving the tapestry: a supertree of birds(2007). The supermatrix approach to systematicsBayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7High-resolution species trees without concatenationDiversification of Neoaves: Integration of molecular sequence data and fossilsEvolution, biogeography, and patterns of diversification in passerine birdsPhylogeny of Passerida (Aves: Passeriformes) based on nuclear and mitochondrial sequence dataRe-evaluation of species limits in the genus <italic>Atlapetes</italic> based on mtDNA sequence dataHidden likelihood support in genomic data: Can forty-five wrongs make a right?The ecology and evolution of avian migration systemsPhylogenetic inference of reciprocal effects between geographic range evolution and diversificationOn divide-and-conquer strategies for parsimony analysis of large data sets: Rec-I-DCM3 versus TNTThe global diversity of birds in space and timeA phylogenetic supertree of oscine passerine birds (Aves: Passeri)Lower Miocene stratigraphy along the Panama Canal and its bearing on the Central American PeninsulaA comprehensive multilocus assessment of sparrow (Aves: Passerellidae) relationshipsA maximum pseudo-likelihood approach for estimating species trees under the coalescent modelEstimating species phylogenies using coalescence times among sequencesSimultaneous effects of phylogenetic niche conservatism and competition on avian community structureA comprehensive multilocus phylogeny for the wood-warblers and a revised classification of the Parulidae (Aves)Mammalian evolution and the Great American InterchangePhylogeny, biogeography, and recurrent evolution of divergent bill types in the nectar-stealing flowerpiercers (Thraupini: Diglossa and Diglossopis)History of the North American bird faunaInferences concerning the Tertiary American bird faunasThe age of the crown group of passerine birds and its evolutionary significance&mdash;molecular calibrations versus the fossil recordAWTY (are we there yet?): A system for graphical exploration of MCMC convergence in Bayesian phylogeneticsEvolution of long-distance migration in and historical biogeography of <italic>Catharus</italic> thrushes: A molecular phylogenetic approachBayesTraitsAPE: Analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R languagePhyloGenerator: An automated phylogeny generation tool for ecologistsA comprehensive species-level molecular phylogeny of the New World blackbirds (Icteridae)Testing macro-evolutionary models using incomplete molecular phylogeniesTracerA likelihood framework for inferring the evolution of geographic range on phylogenetic treesPlant dispersal across the tropical Atlantic by wind and sea currentsColonization of the Lesser Antilles by land birdsApplying a regional community concept to forest birds of eastern North AmericaTaxon cycles in the Lesser Antillean avifaunaNonequilibrium diversity dynamics of the Lesser Antillean avifaunaThe causes of evolutionary radiations in archipelagoes: Passerine birds in the Lesser AntillesTaxon cycles in the West Indian avifaunaMolecular phylogeny of the genus <italic>Buteo</italic> (Aves: Accipitridae) based on mitochondrial marker sequencesDispersal&ndash;vicariance analysis: A new approach to the quantification of historical biogeographyRec-I-DCM3: A fast algorithmic technique for reconstructing large phylogenetic treesThe origin of finches on Tristan da Cunha and Gough Island, central South Atlantic oceanThe evolution of bird migration&mdash;a synthesisPatterns of animal dispersal, vicariance and diversification in the HolarcticSouthern Hemisphere biogeography inferred by event-based models: Plant versus animal patternsAre the Northern Andes a species pump for Neotropical birds? Phylogenetics and biogeography of a clade of Neotropical tanagers (Aves: Thraupini)The profound influence of the Late Pliocene Panamanian uplift on the exchange, diversification, and distribution of New World birdsMega-phylogeny approach for comparative biology: An alternative to supertree and supermatrix approachesCattle Egret (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Bubulcus ibis</named-content></italic>)Fossil and recent avifaunas and the Interamerican InterchangePhylogenies and community ecologyLate Cenozoic mammal dispersals between the AmericasThe Great American Biotic Interchange in birdsLoss and re-evolution of complex life cycles in marsupial frogs: Does ancestral trait reconstruction mislead?Understanding the biogeographic origins and temporal sequencing of groups within a region or of lineages within an ecosystem can yield important insights into evolutionary dynamics and ecological processes. Fifty years ago, Ernst Mayr generated comprehensive&mdash;if limited&mdash;inferences about the origins of the New World avifaunas, including the importance of pre-Isthmian dispersal between North and South America. Since then, methodological advances have improved our ability to address many of the same questions, but the phylogenies upon which such analyses should be based have been incompletely sampled or fragmentary. Here, we report a near-species-level phylogeny of the diverse (~832 species) New World clade Emberizoidea&mdash;the group that includes the familiar sparrows, cardinals, blackbirds, wood-warblers, tanagers, and their close relatives&mdash;to our knowledge the largest essentially complete (&ge;95&percnt;) phylogenetic hypothesis for any group of organisms. Biogeographic analyses based on this tree suggest initial dispersal into the New World via Beringia, with rapid subsequent diversification, including early dispersal of 1 lineage (the tanagers, Thraupidae) into South America. We found substantial dispersal between North and South America prior to closure of the Isthmus of Panama, but with a notable increase afterward, with a directional bias from north to south. With much greater detail and historical rigor, these analyses largely confirm Mayr's speculations based on taxonomy, resolving outstanding ambiguity regarding the continental origins of some groups such as the Emberizidae and Icteridae. The phylogeny reported here will be a resource of broad utility for addressing additional evolutionary and ecological questions with this diverse group.Entender los or&iacute;genes biogeogr&aacute;ficos y la secuencia temporal de los grupos adentro de una regi&oacute;n o de los linajes adentro de un ecosistema puede brindar visiones importantes sobre la din&aacute;mica evolutiva y los procesos ecol&oacute;gicos. Hace 50 a&ntilde;os, Ernst Mayr generaba inferencias integrales&mdash;aunque limitadas&mdash;sobre los or&iacute;genes de las avifaunas del Nuevo Mundo, incluyendo la importancia de la dispersi&oacute;n previa a la formaci&oacute;n del Istmo entre Am&eacute;rica del Norte y de Sur. Desde entonces, los avances metodol&oacute;gicos han mejorado nuestra habilidad para atender muchas de las mismas preguntas, pero las filogenias sobre las cuales deben basarse estos an&aacute;lisis han sido muestreadas de modo incompleto o fragmentario. Aqu&iacute;, presentamos una filogenia realizada casi a nivel de especie del clado diverso (~832 especies) Emberizoidea del Nuevo Mundo&mdash;el grupo que incluye los t&iacute;picos gorriones, cardenales, tordos, reinitas del bosque, tangaras y sus parientes cercanos, a nuestro entender la m&aacute;s grande hip&oacute;tesis filogen&eacute;tica pr&aacute;cticamente completa (&ge;95&percnt;) para cualquier grupo de organismos. Los an&aacute;lisis biogeogr&aacute;ficos basados en este &aacute;rbol sugieren una dispersi&oacute;n inicial en el Nuevo Mundo a trav&eacute;s de Bering, con una r&aacute;pida diversificaci&oacute;n posterior, incluyendo la dispersi&oacute;n temprana de un linaje (los tangaras, Thraupidae) en Sud Am&eacute;rica. Encontramos una gran dispersi&oacute;n entre Am&eacute;rica del Norte y del Sur anterior al cierre del Istmo de Panam&aacute;, pero con un notable aumento despu&eacute;s, con un sesgo direccional de norte a sur. Con mucho m&aacute;s detalle y rigor hist&oacute;rico, estos an&aacute;lisis confirman ampliamente las especulaciones de Mayr basadas en taxonom&iacute;a, resolviendo una ambig&uuml;edad excepcional sobre el origen continental de algunos grupos como los Emberizidae e Icteridae. La filogenia presentada aqu&iacute; ser&aacute; un recurso de amplia utilidad para abordar para este diverso grupo preguntas evolutivas y ecol&oacute;gicas adicionales.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> &aacute;rea ancestral; dispersi&oacute;n; diversificaci&oacute;n; Gran Intercambio Americano de BiotaSince the need for a knowledge of the Tertiary composition of the &lsqb;North and South American&rsqb; avifaunas is considerable, some method must be found to reconstruct distributions in past geological periods&hellip;. Such a method &hellip; consists in an evaluation of the present pattern of distribution &hellip; and in a study of the distribution of near relatives. Direct proof is impossible by this method, but it allows for inferences with varying degrees of probability. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">Mayr, 1964</xref>:281)In two now classic papers on the biogeography of the New World avifauna, Ernst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr1">Mayr (1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">1964</xref>) clearly laid out the challenges and opportunities associated with reconstructing the evolutionary history of birds in this climatically dynamic, ecologically diverse region. In particular, Mayr believed that understanding the geographic origins of avian groups would shed light on current spatial diversity patterns, rules (if any) of community assembly and composition, and differential success of lineages, among other phenomena. Unfortunately, given the poor bird fossil record and the lack of rigorous quantitative methods for phylogeny reconstruction at the time, Mayr was limited in his analyses to tabulating regional endemism of families, genera, and species. On the basis of these data, Mayr classified the majority of New World birds by their continent of origin and reconstructed dispersal events and the establishment of secondary centers of endemism. Although the data available at the time were rudimentary, Mayr was able to argue that (1) there was likely an endemic North American tropical avifauna prior to land connections with South America; (2) the South American avifauna was much more successful in limiting influx from North America than its mammalian fauna had been, possibly due to an ongoing history of interchange prior to closure of the Isthmus of Panama; and (3) habitats in North America vary significantly in the prominence of autochthonous as opposed to more recent Eurasian immigrant species (e.g., grassland assemblages are dominated by species that originated in North America, and temperate forest residents&mdash;but not migrants&mdash;are dominated by immigrants). Although of great general interest and historical importance, these insights were limited by methodological barriers that have been greatly reduced during the past half century.Contemporary ecologists and evolutionary biologists now address these same areas of inquiry, using explicitly comparative phylogenetic methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Webb1">Webb et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ree1">Ree et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Goldberg1">Goldberg et al. 2011</xref>), especially when faced with a poor fossil record for the group of interest. Although they are powerful, historical methods are limited by the sampling of taxa included in the phylogeny and may be biased when sampling is incomplete or nonrandom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Pybus1">Pybus and Harvey 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Wiens1">Wiens et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Bokma1">Bokma 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cusimano1">Cusimano and Renner 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Brock1">Brock et al. 2011</xref>), which is especially likely when investigating continent-scale questions such as those posed by Mayr. Therefore, much research has focused on the generation of comprehensive trees for taxa of interest using synthetic methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-BinindaEmonds1">Bininda-Emonds 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Davis1">de Queiroz and Gatesy 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith2">Smith et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Pearse1">Pearse and Purvis 2013</xref>), even when data are absent for significant fractions of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-BinindaEmonds3">Bininda-Emonds et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2012</xref>). Although incomplete phylogenetic hypotheses may prove adequate for many process-related questions in which extremely broad-scale taxonomic coverage is more important than completeness, phylogenetic uncertainty limits our ability to address some lines of inquiry&mdash;especially those of a historical nature, in which the branching structure at particular nodes in the phylogeny provides core inferences about past events. Unfortunately, completely sampled phylogenies of particularly large clades remain rare. Here, we report a near-complete species-level phylogeny of a diverse, widespread New World bird lineage, the Emberizoidea. This songbird group&mdash;also known as the New World nine-primaried oscines&mdash;comprises the widely studied and ubiquitous blackbirds (Icteridae), cardinals (Cardinalidae), sparrows (Passerellidae), tanagers (Thraupidae), and wood-warblers (Parulidae). To our knowledge, this is the largest, essentially completely sampled, wholly data-based phylogenetic hypothesis for any group of organisms studied to date.The Emberizoidea, comprising some ~832 species (or 7.8&percnt; of all birds), represents the second most diverse lineage of New World birds after the South American suboscine radiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">Barker et al. 2004</xref>). Due primarily to the importance of the northern Andes for the radiation of sparrows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-GarciaMoreno1">Garc&iacute;a-Moreno and Fjelds&aring; 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cadena2">Cadena et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cadena1">2011</xref>) and tanagers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns3">Burns and Naoki 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mauck1">Mauck and Burns 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Sedano1">Sedano and Burns 2010</xref>), this clade is most diverse in northern South America, but it is widespread throughout the entire mainland New World, as well as in the Greater and Lesser Antilles. The high dispersal potential of this lineage is further evident in its colonization of the Old World (the buntings, Emberizidae) as well as more distant islands, including the Gal&aacute;pagos (Darwin's finches) and the Tristan da Cunha group in the South Atlantic (<italic>Nesospiza</italic> and <italic>Rowettia</italic>). This group is as ecologically diverse as it is widespread, with a consequently impressive array of feeding adaptations, ranging from thin decurved bills in nectarivores to massive seed-crushing bills in granivores. This morphological diversity has contributed to a long and controversial history of higher-level classification, with many genera misclassified at the family level or long classified as <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">incertae sedis</named-content></italic>. Now that molecular phylogenetic analyses have largely resolved such controversial relationships among higher taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker3">Barker et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ericson3">Ericson and Johansson 2003</xref>), as well as revealing species-level relationships within most of the major emberizoid lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Lovette2">Lovette et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns5">Burns et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Powell1">Powell et al. 2014</xref>), it is possible to conduct a synthetic analysis of the biogeographic history of this entire radiation. We report such a phylogenetic synthesis of the Emberizoidea here and use it to generate a quantitative, probabilistic analysis of emberizoid biogeographic origins and dispersal history, as requested by Mayr 50 years ago. Because the degree of participation of avian lineages in the Great American Biotic Interchange has been a focus of inquiry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Vuilleumier1">Vuilleumier 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker1">Barker 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-DaCosta1">DaCosta and Klicka 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns4">Burns and Racicot 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith1">Smith and Klicka 2010</xref>), especially in comparison with the rich fossil record of interchange in nonvolant mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Marshall1">Marshall et al. 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Webb2">Webb 1985</xref>), we pay particular attention to the timing and directionality of dispersal events between North and South America.We pursued a hierarchical sampling scheme for phylogeny reconstruction within the Emberizoidea. This approach focused on collection of mitochondrial DNA (the protein-coding genes CYTB and ND2, or only 1 of the 2 from species without available frozen tissue) from all species, supplemented by 4 nuclear genes (the protein-coding gene RAG1 and 3 introns, ACO1-I9, FGB-I5, MB-I2) sampled from generic exemplars as well as from deeply diverging lineages within genera as determined by mitochondrial DNA. One of the important outcomes of genus-level phylogenetic analysis of emberizoids was that gene trees are in fundamental conflict regarding basal relationships within the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>). Mitochondrial DNA data place the Old World buntings (Emberizidae <italic>sensu stricto</italic>) as sister to the New World sparrows (Passerellidae), whereas nuclear genes place Emberizidae outside of a monophyletic New World radiation. Species tree analysis of the data agrees with the former relationship, whereas concatenation favors the latter. These 2 alternative perspectives are not possible to integrate directly in a species-level phylogeny of the group because of the hierarchical sampling used here, not to mention the size of the phylogeny, which makes species tree inference from a single alignment computationally unfeasible. For these reasons, our hypotheses of emberizoid phylogeny were generated using a planned supertree approach. Specifically, we generated phylogenetic hypotheses for major subclades of Emberizoidea (i.e. the families Cardinalidae, Emberizidae, Icteridae, Parulidae, Passerellidae, and Thraupidae), then grafted these subclades onto the backbone topologies of generic relationships that were inferred using both species tree and concatenated analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-110.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Figures S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-110.1.s2" xlink:type="simple">S2</ext-link>). Because we are interested in both absolute and relative timing of evolutionary events within Emberizoidea, and because we want the opportunity to take phylogenetic uncertainty into account in downstream analyses, we have focused on Bayesian relaxed clock analyses, as implemented in BEAST version 1.7.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Drummond1">Drummond et al. 2012</xref>). Below, we describe both the subclade analyses and the procedure we used to integrate subclade and backbone trees into a posterior distribution of supertrees, which we call a &ldquo;pseudoposterior.&rdquo;Relative- or absolute-time-calibrated tree posteriors have already been generated for comprehensive species-level samples of the Parulidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Lovette2">Lovette et al. 2010</xref>), Icteridae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Powell1">Powell et al. 2014</xref>), Thraupidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns5">Burns et al. 2014</xref>), and Passerellidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Klicka1">Klicka et al. 2014</xref>), and these are not described further here. Currently, no relative-time tree posteriors are available for the Calcariidae, Emberizidae, or Cardinalidae. For these groups, we constructed the most complete data matrices possible, including mitochondrial DNA data from all species for which it was available, as well as nuclear data from the loci listed above for major lineages within each (supplemented with data from another nuclear locus, ODC, for the Emberizidae; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Alstrom1">Alstr&ouml;m et al. 2008</xref>). This yielded matrices with 6/6 Calcariidae, 36/41 Emberizidae, and 43/45 Cardinalidae sampled (for taxa and accessions, see <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-110.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Table S1</ext-link>). These matrices were analyzed individually in BEAST under an uncorrelated lognormally distributed clock model (with an exponential prior, &lambda; &equals; 3) with independent branch lengths for each locus, a GTR&plus;I&plus;G<sub>4</sub> model of sequence evolution for each protein-coding gene, and an HKY&plus;G<sub>4</sub> model for each intron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>). Chains were run for 2 replicates of 1 &times; 10<sup>7</sup> generations each. Parameter convergence, burn-in, and sampling adequacy were assessed using Tracer version 1.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Rambaut1">Rambaut and Drummond 2004</xref>), and convergence of nodal posterior probabilities was assessed with AWTY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Nylander1">Nylander et al. 2008</xref>).The posterior distributions of time-calibrated backbone trees (from concatenated and species tree analyses of a genus-level sample of emberizoids, described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>), along with uncalibrated posterior distributions of trees for each subclade (see above), were imported into R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>) using the &ldquo;ape&rdquo; package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Paradis1">Paradis et al. 2004</xref>). Outgroups for subclades were pruned as necessary. A pseudoposterior (a distribution of constructed supertrees) was generated using the following procedure: (1) Randomly select (with replacement) a backbone tree from its posterior; (2) randomly select (with replacement) 1 tree for each subclade; (3) for each subclade, graft the selected tree onto the backbone tree, such that the basal split of the subclade tree is coincident with the basal split for the corresponding clade in the backbone tree, scaling the subclade tree so that the grafted tree remains ultrametric; and (4) go to step 1 and repeat until a predetermined number of ultrametric trees have been generated. This procedure was automated by a script in R (available at the Dryad Digital Repository; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker5">Barker et al. 2014</xref>). For the present study, we assembled pseudoposterior distributions of 4,000 trees each for both the concatenated and species tree backbone analyses. These pseudoposteriors were summarized as maximum clade credibility (MCC) trees and associated posterior probabilities using BEAST's TreeAnnotator application. Where negative branch lengths occurred in the MCC trees, they were reflected and downstream branch lengths rescaled to maintain ultrametricity using a script in R.We reconstructed the biogeographic history of emberizoids at a roughly continental scale, dividing the current range of the group into the Old World (emberizid buntings are widely distributed across Eurasia and Africa), North America, South America (the 2 continents demarcated by the Canal Zone in Central Panama, roughly corresponding to the area of final seaway closure between them; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Coates1">Coates and Obando 1996</xref>), the Caribbean (excluding continental Trinidad and Tobago), and a separate category for other offshore islands including the Gal&aacute;pagos, Cocos Island, and the Tristan da Cunha group in the South Atlantic. Because many emberizoids are either short- or long-distance migrants, and there is controversy regarding which part of their range represents the ancestral resident area for such species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Gauthreaux1">Gauthreaux 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cox1">Cox 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Bell1">Bell 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Salewski1">Salewski and Bruderer 2007</xref>), we examined species distributional coding using both the breeding and wintering distributions. At this broad-scale level of analysis, vicariance is unlikely to be a significant factor in the evolution of emberizoids, given that all the demarcated areas were isolated by water barriers for most of the group's history (ending with closure of the Isthmus of Panama some 3 mya). For this reason, we analyzed the distributional data with multistate character methods in a likelihood framework using BayesTraits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Pagel1">Pagel and Meade 2006</xref>), rather than using explicitly biogeographic methods such as the dispersal&ndash;extinction&ndash;cladogenesis method (implemented in Lagrange; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ree1">Ree et al. 2005</xref>) or dispersal&ndash;vicariance analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ronquist1">Ronquist 1997</xref>); however, for the same reasons, we would expect results obtained with such methods to be essentially identical to those reported here. For each of the MCC trees obtained, we used BayesTraits to optimize the distributional data and obtain relative probabilities for each area at all nodes in the tree, using a partially constrained asymmetrical model of state transitions. In order to achieve stable parameter estimates in the face of a very small number of transitions involving offshore islands (not including the Antilles), we set the rate of dispersal from those islands to the mainland to zero. Consequently, our study cannot be considered a test of the direction of dispersal involving offshore islands (i.e. Gal&aacute;pagos and Tristan de Cunha group): Focused analyses of the history of these groups is necessary (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns2">Burns et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ryan1">Ryan et al. 2013</xref>).In order to test the significance of observed dispersal asymmetry between North and South America during the Great American Biotic Interchange, a model constraining symmetry was also optimized, and model likelihoods were compared using the likelihood ratio. We identified isthmus-crossing lineages on the basis of relative-likelihood calculations described above. Dispersal events inferred for a branch could have occurred at any point along the branch; consequently, we treated inferred dispersal of each lineage as a uniform distribution across its corresponding time interval, then integrated these distributions across the entire history of the clade (for a similar treatment, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cody1">Cody et al. 2010</xref>). Because many inferred dispersal events involved species that were ancestrally either North or South American but that currently occur in both areas (i.e. range expansions), this treatment will necessarily spread inferred dispersal densities into the past, though most of these cases likely involve fairly recent range expansions or sequential dispersal and divergence (i.e. unrecognized speciation events within widespread species). Additional intraspecific sampling within this group is necessary to overcome this issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith1">Smith and Klicka 2010</xref>), and the results presented here should be conservative with regard to the hypothesis of a burst of post-Isthmian dispersal. Because clade diversity necessarily increases over time, we also divided this distribution by the integral of standing diversity across the clade's history to obtain a per lineage dispersal rate for comparison with the estimated dates of Isthmian closure. We assessed the symmetry of exchange by examining inferred transition rates and the frequency of individual reconstructed transitions from the discrete model analysis and by performing likelihood ratio tests of symmetry.We obtained synthetic phylogenetic hypotheses (essentially planned supertrees) for 791 of an estimated ~832 emberizoid species, for 95&percnt; sampling. These summary trees and tree pseudoposterior distributions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f01">Figure 1</xref>; also see <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-110.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Figures S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1642/AUK-14-110.1.s2" xlink:type="simple">S2</ext-link>, deposited along with the code used in generation of the pseudoposterior in the Dryad Digital Repository; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker5">Barker et al. 2014</xref>) represent the best, most comprehensive estimate of phylogenetic relationships in this highly diverse clade, summarizing and adding to previously published higher-level and subclade analyses. These estimates are well resolved, with &ge;73&percnt; of all nodes reconstructed with 95&percnt; &ldquo;posterior probability&rdquo; (remembering that these values are composites of individual subclade concatenated analysis numbers and backbone species tree or concatenation tree numbers). As previously discussed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>), there are some substantial disagreements regarding basal relationships among major emberizoid clades (families in our treatment); more extensive gene sampling at that level is required to resolve these relationships. For most purposes, however, we expect that this uncertainty will have little effect on analyses using these trees, as we demonstrate below through the results of our biogeographic analyses of the group.Time-scaled phylogeny of Emberizoidea, based on maximum clade credibility from trees assembled on the species tree backbone (see text). Taxonomy follows the Clements sequence (version 6.9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Clements1">Clements et al. 2014</xref>), and major family groups are highlighted on the right. Dashed lines mark 5, 10, and 15 Ma before the present.Continued.Continued.Continued.Continued.Continued.Maximum likelihood analysis of emberizoid distributional data as a discrete character strongly favors a North American origin for this currently widespread New World group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="AUK-14-110.1.s1" xlink:type="simple">Supplemental Material Figures S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="AUK-14-110.1.s2" xlink:type="simple">S2</ext-link>). This result pertains regardless of which backbone tree is used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t01">Table 1</xref>) and whether we analyze current breeding or wintering distributions (not shown). This result is also consistent across samples (<italic>N</italic> &equals; 100) from both the species tree and concatenated tree posteriors, with all replicates yielding &ge;0.95 probability for North America at the root. On the species tree backbone, constraining the ancestral state for this clade to be South American reduces the ln-likelihood value for the model by 4.6 units (5.3 for the concatenation tree), corresponding to a relative likelihood of &lt;1&percnt;. In addition to the clade as a whole, 4 of the 5 most species-rich families of Emberizoidea were reconstructed as North American (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>).Likely ancestral areas for Emberizoidea (root node) and major subclades. Shown is the proportion of marginal likelihood attributable to individual areas in a maximum likelihood analysis of discrete distributional data on 2 alternative emberizoid phylogenies.Distributional reconstruction for the Emberizoidea, based on maximum likelihood discrete character analysis on the absolute-time-calibrated maximum clade credibility tree (using the species tree backbone). Pie graphs at each node indicate the relative likelihood of each state (NA &equals; North America, SA &equals; South America, C &equals; Caribbean, and OW &equals; Old World); width of fill in terminal triangles (lineages with &gt;1 species sampled) or squares (lineages with only a single species sampled) indicates the percentage of species in each group currently found in each region; and species diversity of each clade is indicated.Analysis of the timing of transcontinental dispersal events supports a post-Isthmian-closure increase in both absolute and relative rates of dispersal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f08">Figure 3</xref>). The total number of lineages involved in dispersal between North and South America increases continuously throughout emberizoid history, but markedly so after final closure of the Isthmus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f08">Figure 3</xref>B). However, this increase has to be considered in the context of the entire clade's history: Any randomly evolving discrete character would increase in the number of inferred transitions toward the present as the total amount of time sampled by the phylogeny increases. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f08">Figure 3</xref>C shows the density of crossing lineages corrected for standing diversity. Two patterns are of particular note. First, the relative rate of crossing is basically constant through most of the history of the clade, excepting a very high early rate due to the early invasion of South America by the cardinal&ndash;tanager clade (0.62 crossing lineage<sup>&minus;1</sup>; not shown on the figure because of scaling) at a time when we infer very few extant emberizoid lineages (though this is certainly an underestimate, the magnitude of which depends on extinction rates in this group). Second, we note a more modest but appreciable post-closure increase in dispersal rates. As expected on the basis of previous results in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith1">Smith and Klicka 2010</xref>) and mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Marshall1">Marshall et al. 1982</xref>), we found strong evidence for asymmetry in dispersal between continental areas. Although rates in both directions were significant, we inferred rates from North to South America &gt;3 times higher than the reverse (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t02">Table 2</xref>), similar to the pattern for mammals as a whole but in striking contrast to previous results from broader surveys of birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith1">Smith and Klicka 2010</xref>). Similarly, excluding the origin of widespread distributions, we found nearly twice as many inferred dispersal events from North to South America than the reverse (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t03">Table 3</xref>). Constraining the model of discrete character evolution to symmetry between North and South American dispersals reduced the likelihood by 8.4 natural log units, strongly supporting the asymmetric model (&minus;2 ln &Lambda; ~<inline-formula id="i0004-8038-132-2-333-ilm01"><inline-graphic xlink:href="i0004-8038-132-2-333-ilm01.gif" mimetype="image" xlink:type="simple"></inline-graphic></inline-formula>; <italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.004).Analysis of isthmus-crossing events within Emberizoidea. (<bold>A</bold>) Intervals of branches with reconstructed isthmus-crossings (based on likelihood reconstructions on the species tree backbone maximum clade credibility tree; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f01">Figure 1</xref>, Figure S1) with black indicating true dispersals and gray range expansions. (<bold>B</bold>) Absolute density of isthmus-crossing lineages (smoothed by Tukey's running median approach; Tukey 1977), integrating unit-area uniform distributions defined by branches in A. (<bold>C</bold>) Relative density of isthmus-crossing lineages (smoothed as in B), dividing the density in B by the standing diversity of emberizoid lineages at each point. The approximate window for closure of the isthmus (4.0&ndash;2.5 mya; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Coates1">Coates and Obando 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Kirby1">Kirby et al. 2008</xref>) is shown in gray.Transition (inferred dispersal) rates among areas (Ma<sup>&minus;1</sup>), as inferred by partially constrained (transitions from non-Caribbean islands set to zero) maximum likelihood analysis of distributional data on the species tree estimate of emberizoid phylogeny.Frequency of reconstructed distribution changes from discrete character analysis of emberizoid ranges based on maximum likelihood reconstruction on the species tree backbone estimate (N &equals; North America, S &equals; South America, C &equals; Caribbean, I &equals; Other Islands, and O &equals; Old World). Changes are divided by location in the tree: external or terminal branches with a single descendant versus internal branches. <italic>X</italic>&rarr;<italic>X</italic> transitions imply intra-region divergences and are reported to reflect regional diversity.Ideas on methods for construction of large phylogenetic trees have been largely focused on the debate between &ldquo;supertree&rdquo; and &ldquo;supermatrix&rdquo; approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-BinindaEmonds1">Bininda-Emonds 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-BinindaEmonds2">2004b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Davis1">de Queiroz and Gatesy 2007</xref>). On one hand, supertrees&mdash;generated by quantitative analysis and integration of independent phylogenetic trees without reference to the original data&mdash;may be computationally less demanding and can incorporate different incompatible data types (e.g., distance and character data). On the other hand, supermatrix analyses&mdash;integration of all available character data into a maximally informative matrix for subsequent phylogenetic analysis&mdash;afford the opportunity for data to interact in new ways that may reveal novel hypotheses or emergent support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Gatesy1">Gatesy and Baker 2005</xref>). Philosophically, many systematists tend to favor the supermatrix approach, but are hindered by significant computational constraints that limit our ability to appropriately analyze large multigene matrices. In particular, species tree methods are the most appropriate tool for analyzing large multigene matrices, but fully parametric approaches are computationally intensive, which can limit the numbers of both genes and taxa analyzed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cranston1">Cranston et al. 2009</xref>). Although less rigorous non- or pseudo-likelihood approaches are available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Liu2">Liu et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Liu1">2010</xref>), our previous analyses of emberizoid molecular data suggest that such methods can fail to adequately reflect the information content of the available data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>). Given these problems, we favored a hierarchical approach that integrates species tree and concatenated analyses of limited sampling to construct a well-supported higher-level backbone for the phylogeny, with taxonomically extensive concatenated analyses of specific subclades. Ideally, subclade analyses would also use species tree methods, but the large size of some subclades (e.g., tanagers) makes this unfeasible for the group treated here. Our approach is essentially a &ldquo;planned supertree&rdquo; strategy&mdash;a close parallel to divide-and-conquer strategies increasingly used in phylogenetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Roshan1">Roshan et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Goloboff1">Goloboff and Pol 2007</xref>)&mdash;that reflects what we consider to be the best possible analyses at each hierachical level of this large phylogeny. Given the ubiquity of gene tree incongruence at multiple hierarchical levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Edwards1">Edwards et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Brumfield1">Brumfield et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cranston1">Cranston et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>), we anticipate that this strategy will continue to be of use in the near term because of limitations on both the number of genes and the number of taxa that are computationally feasible using species tree methods.At least 3 previous studies have presented fairly comprehensive phylogenetic hypotheses for this group based on alternative strategies for tree construction. In particular, 2 supertree studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Jonsson1">J&oslash;nsson and Fjelds&aring; 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Davis1">Davis and Page 2014</xref>) and 1 hybrid supermatrix&ndash;supertree study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Jetz1">Jetz et al. 2012</xref>) have included 373, 525, and 684 emberizoids (45&percnt;, 63&percnt;, and 82&percnt;), respectively. Although these studies generally do a reasonable job of reflecting their constituent trees and/or underlying molecular data, they each have serious drawbacks as representations of emberizoid evolution. First, the 2 supertree studies omit critical, deeply diverging emberizoid taxa such as <italic>Nesospingus</italic>, <italic>Spindalis</italic>, <italic>Teretistris</italic>, <italic>Calyptophilus</italic>, <italic>Mitrospingus</italic>, <italic>Lamprospiza</italic>, and <italic>Rhodinocichla</italic>. Second, the same studies reflect some relationships now known to be spurious in the light of additional data or analyses (e.g., <italic>Nesopsar</italic> as a basal member of the blackbirds, failing to find some <italic>Thraupis</italic> tanagers nested within <italic>Tangara</italic>). Third, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Davis1">Davis and Page (2014)</xref> supertree, which was constructed algorithmically rather than &ldquo;hand assembled&rdquo; in light of expert knowledge like the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Jonsson1">J&oslash;nsson and Fjelds&aring; (2006)</xref> tree, exhibits a number of clear artifacts, such as placement of <italic>Rhodinocichla</italic> well within the tanagers and recovery of a clade of 1 <italic>Sturnella</italic> and 4 <italic>Icterus</italic> species far outside of Icteridae. In contrast to the other 2 studies, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Jetz1">Jetz et al. (2012)</xref> supertree of emberizoid relationships is based directly on analyses of available GenBank data (at least prior to grafting of missing taxa). One consequence of this is that their study includes the critical taxa missing from the supertrees. Even so, the study includes relationships that can only be explained as resulting from faulty assumptions used in tree assembly. In particular, the Jetz et al. tree presents finches of the genus <italic>Chlorophonia</italic> as members of the tanager clade, a result that can only reflect the assumption that these are tanagers, given that both mitochondrial and nuclear DNA strongly support their placement outside of emberizoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Burns1">Burns 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>), and that the Jetz tree correctly places the closely related <italic>Euphonia</italic> with the finches. Similarly, their tree weakly places South Atlantic <italic>Nesospiza</italic> and <italic>Rowettia</italic> within tanagers as distant relatives of <italic>Phaenicophilus</italic>: Mitochondrial DNA (the only locus sampled for these taxa by Jetz et al.) strongly suppports these taxa as close relatives of southern cone <italic>Melanodera</italic> and Andean <italic>Phrygilus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ryan1">Ryan et al. 2013</xref>, present study). Other differences between our trees, such as their failure to recover Mitrospingidae as a deep lineage closely related to but outside of Thraupidae, and the lack of monophyly of Thraupidae as we recover it here, may reflect differences in gene and taxon sampling. Still others, such as the placement of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Geospiza fortis</named-content></italic> far outside of <italic>Geospiza</italic>, are probably due to alignment artifacts or GenBank annotation errors. These and other issues with previous studies, along with our tree's more comprehensive taxon sampling and its improved support at multiple hierarchical levels, suggest that our hypothesis of emberizoid relationships is the best available to date.Oscine passerines appear to have arisen in Sahul (the continental mass including Australia, Tasmania, New Guinea, and portions of Wallacea; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker3">Barker et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">2004</xref>), possibly as early as the Paleocene (66&ndash;56 mya), although the age of passerines has been debated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">Barker et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ericson1">Ericson et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Brown1">Brown et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cracraft1">Cracraft and Barker 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr3">Mayr 2013</xref>). Subsequently, 1 diverse lineage of this group (the Passerida) is thought to have dispersed into Eurasia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">Barker et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker2">Barker 2011</xref>) or Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ericson2">Ericson et al. 2003</xref>), with later dispersal into the New World. In terms of species numbers, the Emberizoidea represent the most successful New World lineage of Passerida, exceeded in diversity in the region only by the endemic radiation of suboscines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">Barker et al. 2004</xref>). Given an estimated stem age of ~20 Ma for the Emberizoidea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker6">Barker et al. 2004</xref>), its presence in the New World is likely the result of dispersal over a Beringian land bridge (as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr1">Mayr 1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">1964</xref>), given that North Atlantic and Antarctic land connections were sundered by water barriers by 39 and 26 mya, respectively (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Sanmartin1">Sanmart&iacute;n et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Sanmartin2">Sanmart&iacute;n and Ronquist 2004</xref>). However, given the clear ability of many Recent birds to colonize new areas after dispersing long distances across water, this hypothesis has required testing in a phylogenetic framework.Our reconstruction of ancestral areas strongly supports a North American origin for the group and, hence, a Beringian dispersal route to the New World (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>), in agreement with previous judgments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr1">Mayr 1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">1964</xref>). Subsequent to dispersal across Beringia, this group of songbirds has accumulated ~791 species in the New World (plus 41 in the Old World, resulting from back-dispersal of Emberizidae at ~11.8 mya), for a total of ~7.8&percnt; of all extant avian species diversity. Our evidence for trans-Beringian dispersal and northern ancestry of this lineage suggests that a long-distance, transoceanic dispersal event to South America did not lead to colonization of the New World by emberizoids, as has been suggested for a variety of other taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Simpson1">Simpson 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Renner1">Renner 2004</xref>). Therefore, despite the potential for rare, long-distance dispersal events to shape patterns of avian distribution (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Telfair1">Telfair 1994</xref>), our results suggest that gradual range expansion, mediated initially by a Beringian land bridge, was the likely route of New World colonization by this group.The earliest history of this group was dominated by diversification within North America, as evidenced by 4 of the 5 major clades within the group appearing to be ancestrally North American (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t01">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>). These reconstructions are largely consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr1">Mayr's (1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">1964</xref>) assessment of these groups, although our analysis resolves his ambiguous &ldquo;Pan-American&rdquo; families Emberizidae (classified as North American in 1946) and Icteridae (classified as &ldquo;probably originally South American&rdquo; in 1946) as unequivocally North American. Although North America was clearly an important early center of emberizoid diversification, at least 3 relatively ancient dispersal events led to the founding of endemic South American and Caribbean lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>). One dispersing lineage would have been the common ancestor of Mitrospingidae, Cardinalidae, and Thraupidae, although it is possible that Mitrospingidae and Thraupidae independently reached South America. Subsequently, the Thraupidae have gone on to become a diverse component of many South American avifaunas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Stotz1">Stotz et al. 1996</xref>) and have not diversified substantially in North America. The history of Caribbean emberizoid diversity is less clear because of significant uncertainty in phylogenetic relationships of these lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>) but involved at least 2 ancient dispersal events (at ~11.7 and ~12.6 mya) into the region (the Teretistridae and the clade including Nesospingidae, Spindalidae, Calyptophilidae, and Phaenicophilidae; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f07">Figure 2</xref>). Dispersal among these regions increased in frequency as the total diversity of emberizoid clades increased, as well as with changes in connectivity (e.g., formation of the Isthmus of Panama; see below).As expected given the relative size of the landmasses involved, interchange between North and South America dominates the history of emberizoid dispersal within the New World (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t02">Table 2</xref>). Importantly, dispersal rates between these 2 landmasses do not appear to be temporally uniform. Aside from the early dispersal of thraupids and their allies into South America, much of emberizoid history is characterized by relatively constant dispersal rates. Subsequent to the closure of the Isthmus of Panama, however, there was a marked increase in per lineage dispersal between the continents (~30&percnt; on average, but up to twofold in the most recent 300,000 yr; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-f08">Figure 3</xref>). As noted above, it is likely that the analyses presented here underestimate the recent peak in dispersals, given that dispersal probabilities are effectively smoothed out by long branches. Even so, it seems clear that dispersal between North and South America has increased over the past 2 Ma or so, likely as a result of closure of the Isthmus.Notably, the second-highest overall inferred dispersal rate was from North America to the Caribbean. This is driven primarily by relatively recent dispersals of parulid and icterid lineages into the Caribbean, but also by the much more ancient origins of endemic family-level lineages (e.g., Teretistridae and Calyptophilidae; see above). These reconstructions suggest an early and ongoing importance of the Caribbean to diversification in this group. As expected, given faunal turnover as a function of island area and susceptibility to catastrophic weather events (e.g., hurricanes), all of the ancient family-level diversity in this group is found on the larger islands within the Greater Antilles, whereas generic- and species-level diversity of more recent origin is found in both the Greater and Lesser Antilles (e.g., <italic>Ptiloxena</italic>, <italic>Melopyrrha</italic>, <italic>Loxigilla</italic>, <italic>Catharopeza</italic>, and <italic>Setophaga plumbea</italic>). Clearly, both immigration and intrabasin diversification have played a role in assembly of the Caribbean avifauna, given that there are 54 species in this clade with some portion of their distribution in the Caribbean, and only 27 reconstructed dispersals or range expansions into the region (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-t03">Table 3</xref>). It is clear that assembly involved multiple processes, including one-off immigration events such as <italic>Dendroica vitellina</italic> (possibly a migratory &ldquo;drop-off&rdquo;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Outlaw1">Outlaw et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Riesing1">Riesing et al. 2003</xref>), the origin of widespread colonizing lineages such as <italic>Coereba</italic>, formation of allopatric clusters (either by local differentiation of a widespread ancestor or by island hopping) of closely related lineages within the Caribbean basin (e.g., <italic>Loxigilla</italic> and allies), and intra-island diversification as seen in the 4 Hispaniolan species of Phaenicophilidae. Thus, repeated cycles of colonization, isolation, specialization, and extinction have shaped modern emberizoid diversity in the Caribbean basin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs6">Ricklefs and Cox 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs3">Ricklefs and Bermingham 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs4">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs5">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs1">Ricklefs 2010</xref>).We have reported here a broad-scale analysis of origins and trends in interhemispheric dispersal of a widespread passerine radiation. We note that more detailed inference of geographic history is complicated by a feature of emberizoid biology that has often confounded avian historical biogeographic analyses: Many emberizoid species are long-distance seasonal migrants between North American breeding grounds and Neotropical wintering grounds. There has been considerable debate as to whether the breeding or nonbreeding distributions of migratory species represent the true ancestral ranges of migratory lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Gauthreaux1">Gauthreaux 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cox1">Cox 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Bell1">Bell 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Salewski1">Salewski and Bruderer 2007</xref>). In particular, it has been suggested that North American breeding ranges of many Nearctic&ndash;Neotropic migratory bird species may have evolved from ancestral areas closer to present-day nonbreeding ranges during the evolution of migration (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Cox1">Cox 1985</xref>), which would cast doubt on the ultimate North American ancestry of such lineages. Here, we find that both the breeding and nonbreeding distributions of the group are reconstructed as North American, supporting our conclusion that the ancestral emberizoid colonized the New World via Beringia as opposed to long-distance overwater dispersal to South America. However, it remains unclear how migratory ranges evolved among emberizoids subsequent to colonization of the New World, and how the emergence of these disjunct breeding and wintering ranges influenced interhemispheric dispersal patterns in this group. A biogeographic analysis that more explicitly evaluates the reciprocal evolution of breeding and wintering range throughout lineage history is required to resolve this issue as well as determine the geographic origins of long-distance migratory species.More than 50 years ago, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr1">Mayr (1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Mayr2">1964</xref>) envisioned&mdash;and attempted&mdash;a comprehensive analysis of the evolutionary origins of New World avifaunas and the ecosystems in which they are found. In the decades since, we have made significant methodological advances that have substantially increased the level of analytical detail as well as the rigor of inference possible. We are only now beginning to take up these questions with new data and methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Lovette1">Lovette and Hochachka 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Barker4">Barker et al. 2013</xref>), but the initial results, including those reported here, are encouraging. In agreement with Mayr, we reconstructed a North American origin for the Emberizoidea and most of its major clades, supporting a Beringian dispersal route for the group, as well as the existence of an endemic North American tropical avifauna. We also found that the tanagers form part of the endemic South American avifauna, derived from an early dispersal from the north. Although study of a single clade does not allow us to assess the overall asymmetry of faunal exchange, we found evidence of ongoing interchange between North and South America&mdash;both pre- and post-Isthmian&mdash;with much higher rates after closure. We also found a bias toward northern invasion of the south, consistent with a northern origin: Given the prominence of emberizoids in the New World avifauna, this suggests that Mayr may have underestimated the asymmetry of exchange. A more comprehensive assessment of the avifauna (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Weir1">Weir et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Smith1">Smith and Klicka 2010</xref>), using comprehensively sampled phylogenies for all relevant groups, will be necessary to assess this. Although beyond the scope of this paper, other questions addressed by Mayr offer clear avenues for future research. In particular, the phylogenetic structuring of New World avian communities is a question only now being addressed quantitatively with phylogenetic methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Lovette1">Lovette and Hochachka 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-2-333-Ricklefs2">Ricklefs 2011</xref>). The phylogenetic hypothesis presented here will be a critical resource for addressing these and a wide array of other evolutionary and ecological questions.We thank the scientific collectors, collection managers, staff, and curators at the following institutions for providing the tissues without which this study would have been impossible: American Museum of Natural History; Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia; University of Minnesota, Bell Museum of Natural History; Colecci&oacute;n Ornitol&oacute;gica Phelps; Cornell University Museum of Vertebrates; Universidad del Valle, Colombia; Field Museum of Natural History; Instituto de Investigaci&oacute;n de recursos Biol&oacute;gicos Alexander von Humboldt; Instituto de Ciencias Naturales, Universidad Nacional de Colombia; University of Kansas Natural History Museum; Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County; Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science Collection of Genetic Resources; Museo Argentino de Ciencias Naturales &ldquo;Bernardino Rivadavia&rdquo;; University of Nevada Las Vegas, Barrick Museum of Natural History; Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, University of California, Berkeley; San Diego State University Museum of Biodiversity, Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute; University of Michigan Museum of Zoology; National Museum of Natural History (Smithsonian Institution); University of Washington, Burke Museum; and Zoological Museum, University of Copenhagen. This research was supported by the National Science Foundation (DEB-0316092 to S.M.L. and F.K.B.; IBN-0217817, DEB-0315416, and DEB-1354006 to K.J.B.; DEB-0315469 to J.K.; and DEB-0315218 to I.J.L.). Some analyses were performed with resources of the Minnesota Supercomputing Institute. We thank B. Winger and two anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript.