 White tail spots and tail-flicking behavior enhance foraging performance in the Hooded Warbler  Frequency distribution and environmental correlates of plumage polymorphism in the Grey Fantail   Rhipidura fuliginosa    Unexplained recurrent features of the plumage of birds  An analysis of physical, physiological, and optical aspects of avian coloration with emphasis on wood-warblers  Hooded Warbler ( Setophaga citrina )  Do male plumage and song characteristics influence female off-territory forays and paternity in the Hooded Warbler?  Constraints on double brooding in a Neotropical migrant, the Hooded Warbler  The comparative ethology of the wood warblers: A review  Foraging behavior of Neotropical tyrant flycatchers  Escape behavior of Neotropical homopterans in response to a flush-pursuit predator  White tail markings are an indicator of quality and affect mate preference in Rock Sparrows  A field study of the mockingbird's wing-flashing behavior and its association with foraging  Some aspects of adaptation and evolution in Australian fan-tailed flycatchers  A test of the foraging function of wing-flashing in Northern Mockingbirds  Mate choice based on static versus dynamic secondary sexual traits in the Dark-eyed Junco  Foraging patterns of forest birds: Male&ndash;female differences  Determinants of between-season site, territory, and mate fidelity in Hooded Warblers (  Wilsonia citrina  )  A rare predator exploits prey escape behavior: The role of tail-fanning and plumage contrast in foraging of the Painted Redstart ( Myioborus pictus )  Sensory exploitation of prey: Manipulation of the initial direction of prey escapes by a conspicuous &lsquo;rare enemy'  Habitat-specific sensory-exploitative signals in birds: Propensity of dipteran prey to cause evolution of plumage variation in flush-pursuit insectivores  Exploitation of an ancient escape circuit by an avian predator: Prey sensitivity to model predator display in the field  Exploitation of an ancient escape circuit by an avian predator: Relationships between taxon-specific prey escape circuits and the sensitivity to visual cues from the predator  Sexual selection for white tail spots in the Barn Swallow in relation to habitat choice by feather lice  Foraging behavior of American Redstarts in breeding and wintering habitats: Implications for relative food availability  A comprehensive multilocus phylogeny for the wood-warblers and a revised classification of the Parulidae (Aves)  Habitat segregation between the sexes of wintering Hooded Warblers (  Wilsonia citrina  )  Diet quality affects an attractive white plumage pattern in Dark-eyed Juncos (  Junco hyemalis  )  A quantitative study of foraging of male and female spruce-woods warblers  Habitat segregation by sex in the Hooded Warbler: Experiments on proximate causation and discussion of its evolution  Do male Hooded Warblers exclude females from nonbreeding territories in tropical forest?  Scare tactics in a Neotropical warbler: White tail feathers enhance flush pursuit foraging performance in the Slate-throated Redstart ( Myioborus miniatus )  Evolutionary significance of geographic variation in a plumage-based foraging adaptation: An experimental test in the Slate-throated Redstart ( Myioborus miniatus )  Predator-elicited visual signal: Why the Turquoise-browed Motmot wag-displays its racketed tail  Intersexual and temporal variation in foraging ecology of Prothonotary Warblers during the breeding season  A classification scheme for foraging behavior of birds in terrestrial habitats  Plumage coloration predicts paternity and polygyny in the American Redstart  Foraging behavior of forest birds: The relationships among search tactics, diet, and habitat structure  Effects of plant species and foliage structure on the foraging behavior of forest birds  The niche exploitation pattern of the Blue-grey Gnatcatcher  Predator vocalizations alter parental return time at nests of the Hooded Warbler  American Redstart (  Setophaga ruticilla  )  Why some rails have white tails: The evolution of white undertail plumage and anti-predator signaling  Competition for winter territories in a Neotropical migrant: The role of age, sex and color  It isn't always sexy when both are bright and shiny: Considering alternatives to sexual selection in elaborate monomorphic species  Many species of insectivorous birds have contrasting plumage patches that are often displayed during foraging. Although such displays are widely hypothesized to flush potential prey and enhance foraging performance, experimental evidence that they function in this way was previously available only from redstarts (  Myioborus   spp.). I provide additional evidence from an experimental study of the Hooded Warbler ( Setophaga citrina ) in northwestern Pennsylvania, USA. Hooded Warblers regularly flick their tails while foraging, revealing large white spots on the outer tail feathers. I tested the function of the white tail spots with plumage manipulation experiments. At nests containing 5-day-old nestlings, the attending adults were captured and assigned to one of two treatment groups. For experimental birds, I temporarily darkened the white tail spots with a brown marking pen; for sham-darkened controls, I applied a comparable amount of ink to the dark inner rectrices. Experimental birds with darkened tails showed significantly reduced foraging performance compared with controls, and the decline in foraging performance was driven almost entirely by a decreased frequency of aerial prey attack. High-definition video recording at nests showed that plumage manipulation also altered the types of prey females delivered to nestlings; females with darkened tails delivered significantly fewer winged insects, and proportionally more insect larvae, than controls. However, the types of prey delivered by males were unaffected by plumage manipulation. Tail-flicking behavior codevelops with independent foraging in juveniles and is a significant positive predictor of juvenile foraging performance, even when the effects of juvenile age and activity are controlled statistically. Collectively, these results provide strong support for the hypothesis that white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior of Hooded Warblers function to flush visually oriented winged prey and enhance foraging performance. They also raise questions about sexual dimorphism in the tail pattern and its relationship to possible sex differences in foraging strategies.  Muchas especies de aves insect&iacute;voras tienen parches de plumaje contrastantes que son usualmente desplegados durante el forrajeo. Aunque generalmente se sugiere como hip&oacute;tesis que estos despliegues espantan a las presas potenciales y mejoran el desempe&ntilde;o de forrajeo, la evidencia experimental de que funcionan de esta manera s&oacute;lo est&aacute; disponible para las especies de  Myioborus . Aqu&iacute; brindamos evidencia adicional a partir de un estudio experimental de  Setophaga citrina  en el noroeste de Pensilvania, USA. Los individuos de  S. citrina  hacen &ldquo;parpadear&rdquo; sus colas con regularidad mientras forrajean, mostrando grandes manchas blancas en las plumas externas de la cola. Evalu&eacute; la funci&oacute;n de las manchas blancas de la cola con experimentos de manipulaci&oacute;n del plumaje. En nidos que conten&iacute;an pichones de m&aacute;s de 5 d&iacute;as de edad, los adultos asistentes fueron capturados y se les asign&oacute; uno de dos tratamientos. A las aves experimentales, les oscurec&iacute; temporalmente las manchas blancas de la cola con un marcador marr&oacute;n; a un segundo grupo control oscurecido, apliqu&eacute; una cantidad comparable de tinta a las rectrices oscuras internas. Las aves experimentales con las colas oscurecidas mostraron una reducci&oacute;n significativa en el desempe&ntilde;o de forrajeo con relaci&oacute;n a los controles, y la disminuci&oacute;n en el desempe&ntilde;o de forrajeo estuvo dado casi completamente por una disminuci&oacute;n en la frecuencia de ataques a presas a&eacute;reas. Los registros de video de alta definici&oacute;n en los nidos muestran que la manipulaci&oacute;n del plumaje tambi&eacute;n altera el tipo de presas que las hembras entregan a los pichones; las hembras con las colas oscurecidas entregaron significativamente menos insectos alados y proporcionalmente m&aacute;s larvas de insectos que los controles. Sin embargo, los tipos de presas entregadas por los machos no se vieron afectados por la manipulaci&oacute;n del plumaje. El comportamiento de parpadeo de la cola se desarrolla conjuntamente con la independencia de forrajeo de los juveniles y es un predictor positivo significativo del desempe&ntilde;o de forrajeo de los juveniles, aun cuando los efectos de la edad y de la actividad del juvenil son estad&iacute;sticamente controlados. En conjunto, estos resultados apoyan con fuerza la hip&oacute;tesis de que las manchas blancas de la cola y el comportamiento de parpadeo de la cola de  S. citrina  funcionan para espantar a presas aladas influenciadas por se&ntilde;ales visuales y mejoran el desempe&ntilde;o de forrajeo. Ellos tambi&eacute;n plantean preguntas sobre dimorfismo sexual en el patr&oacute;n de la cola y su relaci&oacute;n con posibles diferencias sexuales en las estrategias de forrajeo.   Palabras clave:  comportamiento de forrajeo, comportamiento de parpadeo de la cola, despliegues de forrajeo, manchas de la cola,  Setophaga citrina   Many species of insectivorous birds have striking plumage patches on their wings, tails, or rumps that are often displayed conspicuously during foraging. The contrasting plumage and animated displays are thought to startle and flush potential prey that can then be pursued and captured, often in flight. Species that employ this foraging strategy, termed &ldquo;flush-pursuit foraging&rdquo; ( Remsen and Robinson 1990 ), include redstarts ( Myioborus ;  Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  Mumme 2002 ), the American Redstart (  Setophaga ruticilla  ;  Sherry and Holmes 1997 ), gnatcatchers ( Polioptila ;  Root 1967 ), the Australasian fantails ( Rhipidura ;  Harrison 1976 ,  Atkinson and Briskie 2007 ), flycatchers ( Myiobius ;  Fitzpatrick 1980 ), and the Northern Mockingbird (  Mimus polyglottos  ;  Hailman 1960 ,  Hayslette 2003 ).  The role of contrasting plumage patterns in flush-pursuit foraging has been most thoroughly investigated in  Myioborus  (Parulidae) of the New World tropics and subtropics.  Myioborus  use animated spread-tail displays of their contrasting black-and-white tail feathers to startle potential insect prey, which are then pursued and captured in flight. Plumage manipulation experiments and analysis of insect responses to model redstarts have demonstrated that  Myioborus  foraging displays trigger escape behavior in potential insect prey and enhance flush-pursuit foraging performance, in both the Painted Redstart ( Myioborus pictus ) in Arizona ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  2001 ) and the Slate-throated Redstart ( M. miniatus ) in Costa Rica ( Mumme 2002 ,  Mumme et al. 2006 ). Displays of striking tail patterns exploit the sensory and neuromuscular pathways that control insect escape behavior, pathways that are sensitive to high visual contrast between an approaching object and its background ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski and Strausfeld 2000 ,  2001 ). Flying insects with well-developed visual systems, such as adult Diptera, Homoptera, and Lepidoptera, appear to be particularly sensitive to  Myioborus  displays, whereas nonflying insects with poorly developed visual systems are not ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski and Strausfeld 2000 ,  2001 ,  Galatowitsch and Mumme 2004 ,  Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski et al. 2006 ,  Mumme et al. 2006 ).  In addition to  Myioborus , other parulid warblers have contrasting tail patches that may play a role in foraging. The American Redstart is a flush-pursuit forager that is convergently very similar to the  Myioborus  redstarts. On both its breeding and wintering grounds, American Redstarts use animated spread-tail foraging displays that are thought to flush potential prey ( Robinson and Holmes 1982 ,  1984 ,  Lovette and Holmes 1995 ,  Sherry and Holmes 1997 ). Because conspicuous tail spots and tail-spreading displays are strongly associated with high rates of flycatching in the Parulidae ( Ficken and Ficken 1962 ,  Burtt 1986 ), it is likely that other warbler species also use their tails to flush winged prey.  One parulid warbler whose tail spots are especially likely to play a role in foraging is the Hooded Warbler ( Setophaga citrina ). Like the American Redstart, the Hooded Warbler is a basal member of a large clade of 34  Setophaga  species ( Lovette et al. 2010 ), all of which have conspicuous tail spots ( Curson et al. 1994 ). Hooded Warblers have large white patches on the inner vanes of the three outer rectrices (rectrices 4&ndash;6), and &sim;20&percnt; of birds also have a smaller white patch on the inner vanes of rectrix 3 ( Figure 1 ). The extent of white in the tail is mildly sexually dimorphic, with males having slightly more white than females ( Curson et al. 1994 ,  Chiver et al. 2011 ). During foraging, males and females continuously flick open their tails, revealing the conspicuous white tail spots that contrast with the olive green of the rest of the tail. Previous authors have noted the many morphological and behavioral similarities between Hooded Warblers and  Myioborus  ( Curson et al. 1994 ) and have suggested that the tail-flicking behavior of Hooded Warblers may play a role in foraging ( Chiver et al. 2011 ). Although Hooded Warblers are not considered flush-pursuit foragers, they regularly engage in aerial foraging maneuvers, including sallying (flycatching) and hover-gleaning ( Remsen and Robinson 1990 ,  Chiver et al. 2011 ).  Here, I examine the role of white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior in the foraging strategy of the Hooded Warbler. Using field experiments in which the tail spots of nesting adults were temporarily darkened, as well as data on the development of foraging behavior in juveniles, I tested the hypothesis that white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior help flush visually oriented potential prey and enhance foraging performance. I specifically tested four predictions of the prey-flushing hypothesis. (1) Birds with experimentally darkened tails will show reduced foraging performance compared with sham-darkened controls, and the decline in foraging performance will be driven largely by a decreased frequency of aerial prey attack. (2) Birds with experimentally darkened tails will provision nestlings at a rate lower than that of sham-darkened controls. (3) Experimental darkening of the tail will alter the types of prey delivered to nestlings, resulting in a relatively low proportion of visually oriented flying prey and a relatively high proportion of nonflying prey. (4) Tail-flicking behavior in juveniles will codevelop with independent foraging and be an important predictor of juvenile foraging performance.  The study was conducted during four consecutive nesting seasons (May&ndash;August, 2010&ndash;2013) at Hemlock Hill Field Station in Crawford County, northwest Pennsylvania. Hemlock Hill has been the site of many previous studies of Hooded Warblers (e.g.,  Evans Ogden and Stutchbury 1996 ,  Howlett and Stutchbury 2003 ,  Chiver et al. 2008 ,  Schaef and Mumme 2012 ) and supports a population of 40&ndash;50 territorial nesting pairs. More than 400 nests were found and monitored during the 4 yr of the study, and 175 breeding adults were captured in mist nets and color-banded.  This experiment was conducted during June 6&ndash;July 15, 2010, and focused on the nests of 14 breeding pairs with two to four 5-day-old nestlings. I controlled for brood size by randomly assigning the first nest of a particular brood size to either the experimental or control treatment group, and then alternating treatments for additional nests of that size for the remainder of the nesting season. Control ( n  &equals; 7) and experimental ( n  &equals; 7) nests did not differ significantly in either mean hatch date (15 June &plusmn; 4 days vs. 17 June &plusmn; 6 days,  t  &equals; 0.34,  P  &equals; 0.74) or brood size (2.9 &plusmn; 0.3 vs. 3.1 &plusmn; 0.3 nestlings,  t  &equals; 0.59,  P  &equals; 0.56).  When nestlings were 5 days old, I captured the breeding adults with mist nets placed near nests. For birds at experimental nests, I used a broad-tipped brown Staedtler Lumocolor 350 permanent marker to darken the white inner vanes of the outer rectrices of both the female and the male. For sham-darkened birds at control nests, I used the same marking pen to apply a comparable amount of ink to the dark inner vanes of the inner rectrices.  After giving birds 24 hr to recover from the effects of capture and handling, I collected foraging data on adults from experimental and control nests during the midmorning through early afternoon (0900&ndash;1430 hours). Once a foraging individual had been located and identified, I followed it and recorded its behavior on a hand-held recorder. Behaviors recorded included hops, tail-flicks, flights, and three types of prey-attack maneuvers: perch-gleans (or &ldquo;gleans&rdquo;;  Remsen and Robinson 1990 ), in which a perched bird pecked at potential prey on adjacent vegetation; hover-gleans (or &ldquo;sally-hovers&rdquo;;  Remsen and Robinson 1990 ), in which a hovering bird pecked at potential prey on vegetation; and sallying ( Remsen and Robinson 1990 ), in which flying birds attacked aerial prey. Because prey items were often small and difficult to see, I was seldom able to determine whether a given prey attack was successful or unsuccessful. I therefore used attack maneuvers rather than successful prey captures in analyses of foraging performance. Because birds foraging in dense vegetation were frequently lost from view, foraging samples were derived from many brief observation bouts (usually 10&ndash;30 s each) that were collected over a period of 2&ndash;4 hr. Control ( n  &equals; 14) and experimental ( n  &equals; 14) birds did not differ significantly in either duration of the total foraging sample (6.1 &plusmn; 0.6 min vs. 5.4 &plusmn; 0.6 min,  t  &equals; 0.84,  P  &equals; 0.41) or mean time of data collection (1204 hours &plusmn; 1 hr vs. 1055 hours &plusmn; 1 hr,  t  &equals; 0.95,  P  &equals; 0.36).  Although I used a &ldquo;permanent&rdquo; marker for the plumage manipulations, the brown ink typically lasted only a few days, and after 5&ndash;7 days it was difficult to tell that a bird had been treated at all. Plumage manipulation also had no lasting effect on feather structure; I recaptured one female 6 wk after her tail had been darkened, and both the color and structure of her outer tail feathers appeared to be identical to those of untreated birds.  Plumage manipulation experiments in 2011&ndash;2012 were similar to those performed in 2010. However, instead of measuring treatment effects on foraging performance, I used a tripod-mounted high-definition video camera (Panasonic HDC-TM80K) at nests of 25 breeding pairs to document provisioning rate and the types of prey delivered to nestlings by experimental and control birds. Adults were captured at nests with two to four 5-day-old nestlings and given 24 hr to recover from the effects of capture and handling before video recording began. Mean duration of the video sample at each nest was 146 &plusmn; 9 min. During video analysis, I recorded the number of provisioning visits made by each adult and categorized prey items as follows: (1) unwinged larval insects, (2) adult Diptera (flies), (3) adult Lepidoptera (moths and butterflies), (4) unidentified winged insects, (5) arachnids (primarily spiders and harvestmen), and (6) unidentified prey items. Results from categories (2)&ndash;(4) were summed to provide a composite measure of winged prey, both as a total delivery rate and as a proportion of all identifiable prey items (excluding category (6)).  Experimental design in 2011 was identical to that of 2010, and data were collected from 14 nests (7 control and 7 experimental). Control and experimental nests did not differ significantly in either date (June 21 &plusmn; 6 days vs. June 23 &plusmn; 5 days,  t  &equals; 0.13,  P  &equals; 0.90) or time (1005 hours &plusmn; 20 hr vs. 0935 hours &plusmn; 25 hr,  t  &equals; 1.03,  P  &equals; 0.32) of the video sample. In 2012, to better control for among-territory variation, I used a slightly different experimental design in which one member of the pair was assigned to the experimental treatment while its mate served as the sham-darkened control. Sex of the bird to be darkened was randomly determined for the first nest treated, and then alternated for the rest of the nesting season. Data were collected from 11 nests, 6 with darkened males and sham-darkened females and 5 vice versa. Thus, over the course of the 2 yr, video recordings were obtained from a total of 25 breeding pairs.  From July 15 to August 29, 2013, I collected data on the development of foraging behavior in known-age color-banded juveniles using the same data-collection methods described above for adults. Young Hooded Warblers usually fledge when they are 9 days old and reach independence &sim;4 wk later ( Chiver et al. 2011 ). A total of 65 separate foraging samples were obtained throughout daylight hours (0730&ndash;1620 hours) from 37 juveniles (11&ndash;40 days old). Mean duration of the foraging samples was 4.0 &plusmn; 0.3 min. For comparative purposes, I also collected foraging data from 13 adults (8 females and 5 males) during the same period. These samples, along with data from the 14 control birds in the 2010 foraging performance experiment, were used to compare foraging behavior and performance of adults and developing juveniles.  All statistical analyses were conducted using JMP version 10.0 for Mac OS X ( SAS Institute 2012 ). Data collected from the 2010 foraging performance experiment were analyzed using mixed-model analyses of variance (ANOVAs) in which experimental treatment and sex of the treated bird were included as fixed factors and nest was included as a random effect. Because preliminary modeling revealed no significant effects of either date or time of day, and because the experimental design largely controlled for these variables, neither was included as a factor in the final models. Mixed models were calculated using the recommended REML (restricted maximum likelihood) method with unbounded variance components. Residuals of all models were examined to ensure normality (Shapiro-Wilk test) and homoscedasticity, and log or square-root transformation of the dependent variable was employed when necessary.  Similar mixed-model ANOVAs were used to analyze video data from the 2011&ndash;2012 experiment on provisioning of nestlings; because preliminary modeling revealed no significant effects of year, date, or time of video sample, these variables were not included as factors in the final models. Data on the development of tail-flicking and foraging behavior in juveniles were analyzed by multiple regression. Values reported in the text and figures are means &plusmn; SE.  Adult Hooded Warblers with experimentally darkened tails had significantly fewer prey attacks per minute ( Figure 2 A) than sham-darkened control birds ( Table 1 ). Differences in foraging performance were driven largely by differences in rates of hover-gleaning (experimental birds: 0.9 &plusmn; 0.1 hover-gleans min &minus;1 ; controls: 1.5 &plusmn; 0.1 hover-gleans min &minus;1 ;  F  1,12  &equals; 13.5,  P  &equals; 0.0032). Experimental treatment had a marginally significant effect on sally rate (experimental birds: 0.16 &plusmn; 0.05 sallies min &minus;1 ; controls: 0.54 &plusmn; 0.13 sallies min &minus;1 ;  F  1,12  &equals; 4.6,  P  &equals; 0.053), but essentially no effect on perch-glean rates, which were nearly identical for experimental and control birds (0.23 &plusmn; 0.07 and 0.24 &plusmn; 0.06 perch-gleans min &minus;1 , respectively;  F  1,12  &equals; 0.1 &lsqb;square-root-transformed&rsqb;,  P  &equals; 0.80).  Despite the significant effects on foraging performance, darkening of the tail had no significant effect on foraging effort; experimental birds hopped and tail-flicked at rates that were comparable to those of sham-darkened controls ( Table 1  and  Figure 2 B,  2 C).  For the 2011&ndash;2012 video data, experimental treatment had no significant effect on provisioning of nestlings, as measured by feedings per nestling per hour (mixed-model ANOVA,  F  1,43.6  &equals; 1.3 &lsqb;log transformed&rsqb;,  P  &equals; 0.26). However, the treatment &times; sex interaction approached statistical significance ( F  1,38.2  &equals; 3.1,  P  &equals; 0.089). The provisioning rate of experimental females with darkened tails was &sim;70&percnt; that of control females (1.2 &plusmn; 0.1 and 1.7 &plusmn; 0.2 feedings nestling &minus;1  hr &minus;1 , respectively;  F  1,41.3  &equals; 4.2,  P  &equals; 0.048). By contrast, provisioning rates of experimental and control males were nearly identical (1.7 &plusmn; 0.2 and 1.6 &plusmn; 0.2 feedings nestling &minus;1  hr &minus;1 , respectively;  F  1,41.3  &equals; 0.2,  P  &equals; 0.70).  Of 539 total prey items delivered to nestlings, 93 (17.3&percnt;) could not be identified to a specific prey category. However, the hourly rate at which unidentified prey were delivered to nestlings was not significantly influenced by experimental treatment, sex, or the treatment &times; sex interaction (all  P  &gt; 0.15, square-root-transformed data). Thus, unidentifiable prey items were more-or-less equitably distributed among all treatment and sex categories and unlikely to bias analyses based on identifiable prey. Of the 446 items that could be categorized, the great majority were either insect larvae (42.8&percnt;, primarily Lepidoptera) or adult Diptera (32.5&percnt;, primarily crane flies, family Tipulidae). The remaining prey items were unidentified winged insects (13.7&percnt;), adult Lepidoptera (9.0&percnt;), and arachnids (2.0&percnt;).  Mixed-model ANOVAs indicated a significant treatment &times; sex interaction for both winged prey delivered per hour ( F  1,38.0  &equals; 11.8 &lsqb;log transformed&rsqb;,  P  &equals; 0.0014) and proportion of total prey that were winged ( F  1,33.8  &equals; 9.9,  P  &equals; 0.0034). Experimental females with darkened tails delivered many fewer winged insects to nestlings than sham-darkened control females ( Figure 3 ). For males, however, darkening of the tail spots had no effect on delivery of winged prey ( Figure 3 ). A significant treatment &times; sex interaction was also found for the proportion of prey that were insect larvae ( F  1,32.2  &equals; 10.2,  P  &equals; 0.0032). Only 26.6 &plusmn; 6.9&percnt; of the prey delivered by control females were larvae, compared with 59.2 &plusmn; 6.8&percnt; of the prey delivered by experimentally darkened females. By contrast, larval insects constituted almost identical proportions of the food items delivered by control and experimental males (44.3 &plusmn; 7.5&percnt; and 44.7 &plusmn; 6.0&percnt;, respectively).  Fledglings &lt;18 days old were largely immobile, never flicked their developing tails, and did not forage on their own. By day 18, however, juveniles began to become active foragers, and tail-flick rate, hop rate, and prey-attack rate increased steadily throughout the period of dependence ( Figure 4 ). After day 35, when juveniles were approaching independence, tail-flick rate, hop rate, and prey-attack rate were generally comparable to the rates for adult birds ( Figure 4 ). Juveniles usually left their natal territories around days 40&ndash;45, and the oldest juveniles I observed being fed by their parents were 40 days old.  To disentangle the effects of age, hop rate, and tail-flick rate on juvenile foraging performance, I conducted a multiple-regression analysis of the effects of these variables on prey-attack rate. Because juveniles &lt;27 days old seldom foraged independently ( Figure 4 ), this analysis excluded observation bouts from younger fledglings and samples &lt;100 s in duration. Total sample size was 29 independent foraging samples. In this analysis (adjusted  r  2  &equals; 0.62), both hop rate ( t  &equals; 4.6,  P  &equals; 0.0001) and tail-flick rate ( t  &equals; 3.0,  P  &equals; 0.0064) were significant positive predictors of prey-attack rate. Juvenile age was also positively related to prey-attack rate, but not significantly so ( t  &equals; 1.8,  P  &equals; 0.081). Neither date ( t  &equals; &minus;1.04,  P  &equals; 0.31) nor time of day ( t  &equals; &minus;0.98,  P  &equals; 0.33) was a significant predictor of juvenile foraging performance when these factors were added to the regression model.  The results provide three compelling lines of evidence that the white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior of Hooded Warblers enhance foraging performance and capture of aerial prey. First, experimental birds with darkened tails showed significantly reduced overall prey-attack rates ( Figure 2 A and  Table 1 ) compared with sham-darkened controls, and the influence of plumage treatment on foraging performance was driven entirely by effects on rates of aerial attack maneuvers (i.e. hover-gleaning and sallying), not by effects on perch-glean foraging. Second, experimental darkening of white tail spots significantly altered the types of prey that females delivered to nestlings; experimental females with darkened tails delivered significantly fewer flying insects, and proportionally more nonflying insect larvae, than sham-darkened control females ( Figure 3 ). Third, tail-flicking behavior codevelops with independent foraging in juveniles ( Figure 4 ) and is a significant predictor of prey-attack rate in juveniles, even when the effects of juvenile age and activity level are statistically controlled.  Taken together, these results provide strong evidence that white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior constitute an important foraging adaptation for Hooded Warblers. They add to the growing body of literature indicating that striking plumage &ldquo;ornaments&rdquo; and displays may arise outside the context of intraspecific social or sexual signaling ( Brooke 2010 ,  Tarvin and Murphy 2012 ), and that conspicuous plumage patterns can provide direct utilitarian benefits in foraging ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  Mumme 2002 ) or antipredator behavior ( Murphy 2006 ,  Stang and McRae 2009 ).  The precise mechanism by which white tail spots and tail-flicking behavior promote foraging performance in Hooded Warblers is not entirely clear. Unlike  Myioborus  species, Hooded Warblers do not show true flush-pursuit foraging ( Remsen and Robinson 1990 ), in which potential prey are flushed and then pursued and captured following intricate aerial maneuvers ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  Mumme 2002 ). Nonetheless, it is likely that tail-flicking displays by Hooded Warblers startle and flush winged insects, particularly dipterans and other insects known to be sensitive to such displays ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski 1999 ,  Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski and Strausfeld 2000 ,  Galatowitsch and Mumme 2004 ,  Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski et al. 2006 ,  Mumme et al. 2006 ). Once flushed and visible to a foraging bird, these insects can then be captured by aerial attack maneuvers, including hover-gleaning and sallying.  The results of my study also raise two additional questions. First, why did darkening of the white tail spots alter the types of prey delivered to nestlings by females but not by males? One possible answer is that female and male Hooded Warblers may have different foraging strategies, as has been demonstrated in other warblers ( Morse 1968 ,  Holmes 1986 ,  Petit et al. 1990 ), and that nesting females may be more affected by plumage manipulation than males. This possibility is supported by evidence that females tend to be more active foragers than males; in my sample of foraging behavior of adults in unmanipulated plumage, females did not hop more frequently (12.1 &plusmn; 1.0 vs. 10.7 &plusmn; 1.1 hops min &minus;1 ,  t -test,  P  &equals; 0.35) but had a significantly higher tail-flick rate than males (26.9 &plusmn; 1.8 vs. 21.3 &plusmn; 2.0 tail flicks min &minus;1 ,  t -test,  P  &equals; 0.05). In addition, control females delivered to their nestlings slightly more winged prey (2.8 &plusmn; 0.4 vs. 2.1 &plusmn; 0.4 prey hr &minus;1 ,  F  1,14.2  &equals; 2.0,  P  &equals; 0.18) and significantly fewer insect larvae (1.0 &plusmn; 0.2 vs. 1.6 &plusmn; 0.3 prey hr &minus;1 ,  F  1,10.1  &equals; 5.8,  P  &equals; 0.037) than control males. Because breeding males often position themselves in the lower canopy to enhance song transmission, whereas females spend more time in the understory ( Chiver et al. 2011 ), it is possible that males typically encounter more insect larvae and fewer winged insects than females. These potential sex differences in foraging strategies merit further investigation.  A second question that arises from my study is why the significant reduction of foraging performance in experimental birds ( Figure 2 A) did not lead to a significant decrease in provisioning of nestlings. One possibility is that birds with darkened tails may have been able to compensate for reduced effectiveness in flushing and attacking winged prey by either increasing foraging time or shifting to exploit other types of prey. Indeed, the rate at which insect larvae were delivered to nestlings was actually slightly higher for experimental birds than for controls (1.4 &plusmn; 0.2 vs. 1.0 &plusmn; 0.3 larvae min &minus;1  for females, and 1.8 &plusmn; 0.3 vs. 1.6 &plusmn; 0.2 larvae min &minus;1  for males), which suggests that such a shift in foraging strategy may well have occurred.  Although the results presented here strongly support the hypothesis that white tail spots enhance foraging performance, they are silent on the question of whether tail spots in Hooded Warblers may also have other important functions, including a role in social or sexual signaling. In particular, the sexual dimorphism in tail pattern, with males having slightly more extensive white than females ( Curson et al. 1994 ,  Chiver et al. 2011 ), suggests a potential role for sexual selection in the evolution of white tail spots, as in Dark-eyed Juncos (  Junco hyemalis  ;  Hill et al. 1999 ,  McGlothlin et al. 2007 ) and other birds in which tail ornaments have been identified as targets of sexual selection ( Kose et al. 1999 ,  Reudink et al. 2009 ,  Griggio et al. 2011 ). Nonetheless, it is important to note that plausible alternative hypotheses that do not rely on sexual selection could also explain the evolution of a sexually dimorphic tail pattern in Hooded Warblers.  One such alternative is based on the sexual habitat segregation shown by Hooded Warblers on their Central American wintering grounds: Males winter primarily in closed-canopy forest, whereas females typically inhabit open scrub habitat ( Lynch et al. 1985 ,  Morton et al. 1987 ,  Morton 1990 ,  Stutchbury 1994 ). It is therefore possible that selection for optimal foraging performance on the wintering ground has produced larger tail spots in males because tails with extensive white are typically more effective at flushing potential prey in dark forested habitats ( Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski et al. 2006 ). A second alternative hypothesis is based on the apparent sexual differences in foraging strategies on the breeding grounds (discussed above), and the possibility that white tail spots may have slightly different roles in the foraging behavior of males and females. Additional work is needed to discriminate among these alternatives and determine whether the sexual dimorphism in tail pattern of Hooded Warblers is a result of sexual selection on the breeding grounds, sexual habitat segregation on the wintering grounds, or sexual differences in foraging strategies during nesting.  This paper is dedicated to the memory of Russell Greenberg for his many original contributions to ornithology and the study of Neotropical migrants. I am grateful to G. Morton and B. Stutchbury for allowing me to work at Hemlock Hill Field Station. Eight Allegheny College undergraduates provided invaluable assistance in the field: K. DiPerna, S. Fort, D. Jacobs, J. Kuehn, K. Macie, R. Petroff, K. Schaef, and M. Vlah. M. MacPherson and S. Morton contributed additional assistance. P. Jab&lstrok;o&nacute;ski, G. Morton, and two anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments on the manuscript. The research described here was reviewed and approved by the Allegheny College Institutional Animal Care and Research Committee (April 26, 2010) and authorized by permits from the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Scientific Collecting Permit MB773715-0) and the Pennsylvania Game Commission (Special Use Permit 25&ndash;2010).  Typical tail pattern of an adult male Hooded Warbler, showing the large white patches on the inner webs of the three outer rectrices.  Effects of 2010 plumage manipulation experiment on foraging behavior of adult Hooded Warblers: prey attacks per minute (A), hops per minute (B), and tail flicks per minute (C). Results of statistical tests are shown in  Table 1 . Total sample size is 28 individuals, 7 for each of the sex and treatment categories.  Effects of 2011&ndash;2012 plumage manipulation experiment on delivery of winged prey to nestlings: delivery of winged prey per hour (A) and proportion of all identifiable prey that were winged (B). Numbers above SE bars indicate sample size for each sex and treatment category. Mixed-model ANOVA indicated a significant treatment &times; sex interaction for both winged prey per hour and proportion of prey that were winged.  Development of foraging behavior in juvenile Hooded Warblers in relation to age in days since hatching (day 0): tail flicks per minute (A), hops per minute (B), and prey attacks per minute (C). Young typically fledge at day 9 and reach nutritional independence around day 40. Data for adult Hooded Warblers (denoted &ldquo;Ad&rdquo;) are shown for comparison. Numbers above SE bars indicate sample size for each age category.  Results of mixed-model ANOVAs for 2010 plumage manipulation experiment on foraging behavior ( Figure 2 ). Nest was included as a random effect in all analyses. 