Spatial patterns in hydrogen isotope ratios in feathers of Burrowing Owls from western North AmericaFactors affecting the presence of nesting Burrowing Owls in an agricultural landscapeTreatment methods for the determination of delta H-2 and delta O-18 of hair keratin by continuous-flow isotope-ratio mass spectrometryInterpolating the isotopic composition of modern meteoric precipitationThe use of isotope tracers for identifying populations of migratory birdsComparative demography of Burrowing Owls in agricultural and urban landscapes in southeastern WashingtonStatistics for spatial dataStable isotopes in precipitationHydrogen isotope measurement of bird feather keratin, one laboratory's response to evolving methodologiesStable isotope composition of waters in southeastern California&mdash;1. Modern precipitationCorrelates of deuterium (&delta;D) enrichment in the feathers of adult American Kestrel of known originApplying isotopic methods to tracking animal movementsMigratory connectivity in Bicknell's Thrush: Locating missing populations with hydrogen isotopesLinking hydrogen (&delta;2H) isotopes in feathers and precipitation: Sources of variance and consequences for assignment to isoscapesLinking breeding and wintering grounds of Neotropical migrant songbirds using stable hydrogen isotopic analysis of feathersUsing isotopic variance to detect long-distance dispersal and philopatry in birds: An example with Ovenbirds and American RedstartsBreeding dispersal of a Burrowing Owl from Arizona to SaskatchewanConservation of the Burrowing Owl in western North America: Issues, challenges, and recommendationsDistribution of oxygen-18 and deuterium in river waters across the United StatesStatus assessment and conservation plan for the Western Burrowing Owl in the United StatesBurrowing Owl (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content></italic>) population genetics: A comparison of North American forms and migratory habitsHydrogen isotopic variation in migratory bird tissues of known origin: Implications for geographic assignmentEstimating the latitudinal origins of migratory birds using hydrogen and sulfur stable isotopes in feathers: Influence of marine prey baseA geographic-information-system approach to estimating the origin of migratory raptors in North America using stable hydrogen isotope ratios in feathersWinBUGS&mdash;A Bayesian modelling framework: Concepts, structure, and extensibilityDeuterium stable isotope ratios as tracers of water resource use: An experimental test with Rock DovesVariation in hydrogen stable-isotope ratios between adult and nestling Cooper's HawksMigratory decisions in birds: Extent of genetic versus environmental controlEffect of cleaning regime on stable-isotope ratios of feathers in Japanese Quail (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Coturnix japonica</named-content></italic>)Spatial and temporal migration patterns of Wilson's Warbler (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Wilsonia pusilla</named-content></italic>) in the southwest as revealed by stable isotopesFeather deuterium measurements reveal origins of migratory Western Loggerhead Shrikes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lanius ludovicianus</named-content> excubitorides</italic>) wintering in MexicoBurrowing Owl (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content></italic>)Age identification of nestling Burrowing OwlsInvestigation of preparation techniques for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H analysis of keratin materials and a proposed analytical protocolVulnerabilidad a la intrusi&oacute;n marina de acu&iacute;feros costeros en el Pacifico norte mexicano; un caso, el acu&iacute;fero costa de Hermosillo, Sonora, M&eacute;xicoStable isotopes (&delta;D) reveal east&ndash;west differences in scheduling of molt and migration in Northern Rough-winged Swallows (<italic>Stelgidopteryx serripennis</italic>)The ecology of Burrowing Owls in the agroecosystems of the Imperial Valley, CaliforniaNovel statistical methods for integrating genetic and stable isotope data to infer individual-level migratory connectivityDetermination of the concentration and stable isotopic composition of nonexchangeable hydrogen in organic matterIntrafeather and intraindividual variation in the stable-hydrogen isotope (&delta;D) content of raptor feathersDeuterium measurements of raptor feathers: Does a lack of reproducibility compromise geographic assignment?R2WinBUGS: A package for running WinBUGS from RUse of stable isotope methodology to determine natal origins of Mallards at a fine scale within the upper MidwestAn introduction to light stable isotopes for use in terrestrial animal migration studiesImproved method for determining the stable-hydrogen isotopic composition (&delta;D) of complex organic materials of environmental interestComparative equilibration and online technique for determination of non-exchangeable hydrogen of keratins for use in animal migration studiesThe Second International Burrowing Owl Symposium: Background and contextReferencing strategies and techniques in stable isotope ratio analysisUsing isoscapes to model probability surfaces for determining geographic originsAnalysis and design for isotope-based studies of migratory animalsPhilopatry of winter moult area in migratory Great Reed Warblers <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Acrocephalus arundinaceus</named-content></italic> demonstrated by stable isotope profilesDeuterium (<sup>2</sup>H) has been used to track movements of land birds, under the assumption that &delta;<sup>2</sup>H in precipitation (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>) and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H in bird feathers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>) are correlated across broad geographic gradients. The nature of this correlation has been evaluated only in a small percentage of the birds that breed in North America. We sampled Western Burrowing Owl (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content> hypugaea</italic>) feathers of known origin (nestling feathers) at 36 locations throughout North America (from southern Canada to central Mexico). We used a modification of the &ldquo;comparative equilibrium&rdquo; technique of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Wassenaar3">Wassenaar and Hobson (2003)</xref> to measure the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H of nonexchangeable hydrogen in feather samples. We characterized the strength of the relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and amount-weighted mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> in a raptor that breeds in arid grasslands and deserts throughout western North America. We used a Bayesian hierarchical approach to model the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship, accounting for levels of intrinsic and extrinsic variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>. We found a linear relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;13.48 &plus; 0.78 &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>; 95&percnt; credible interval (slope): 0.55&ndash;1.01) and used this relationship to construct a feather deuterium isoscape map. We observed relatively high levels of variation in mean &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> across locations (SD &equals; 11.01&permil;), due in part to variation in the contribution of precipitation to local food webs, and substantial variation among individuals within locations (SD &equals; 6.68&permil;). Our data demonstrate that &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> of juvenile Burrowing Owls can be used to infer local amount-weighted mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> from the location of origin. Deuterium remains a valuable tool for tracking continental-scale raptor movements, with the caveat that researchers must identify and model for potential discontinuities in the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship in their inferences. However, isotopic discontinuities, coupled with a high relative abundance of individuals in those areas, can seriously hinder the usefulness of deuterium for identifying the origin of individual birds.El deuterio (<sup>2</sup>H) se ha utilizado para rastrear los movimientos de las aves terrestres con el supuesto de que &delta;<sup>2</sup>H en la precipitaci&oacute;n (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>) y &delta;<sup>2</sup>H en las plumas de aves (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>) se correlacionan a trav&eacute;s de gradientes geogr&aacute;ficos amplios. La naturaleza de esta correlaci&oacute;n s&oacute;lo se ha evaluado en una peque&ntilde;a proporci&oacute;n de aves que se reproducen en Norteam&eacute;rica. Tomamos muestras de plumas del buho llanero occidental de origen conocido (plumas de pollos) en 36 localidades a trav&eacute;s de Norteam&eacute;rica (desde el sur de Canad&aacute; hasta el centro de M&eacute;xico). Utilizamos una modificaci&oacute;n de la t&eacute;cnica de Equilibrio Comparativo de Wassenaar y Hobson (2003) para medir &delta;<sup>2</sup>H de hidr&oacute;geno no intercambiable en muestras de plumas. Caracterizamos la intensidad de la relaci&oacute;n entre &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> y &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> medio anual ponderado por cantidad de una rapaz que se reproduce en pastizales &aacute;ridos y desiertos de todo el oeste de Am&eacute;rica del Norte. Utilizamos un enfoque jer&aacute;rquico bayesiano para modelar la relaci&oacute;n &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>, considerando niveles de variaci&oacute;n intr&iacute;nseca y extr&iacute;nseca en &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>. Encontramos una relaci&oacute;n lineal entre &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> y &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;13.48 &plus; 0.78 &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>, ICR 95&percnt; (pendiente) &equals; 0.55&ndash;1.01) y utilizamos esta relaci&oacute;n para construir un mapa isot&oacute;pico de deuterio en plumas. Observamos niveles relativamente altos de variaci&oacute;n en los valores medios de &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> a trav&eacute;s de localidades (DE &equals; 11.01&permil;), debido en parte a la variaci&oacute;n en la contribuci&oacute;n de la precipitaci&oacute;n a las redes alimenticias locales, y a una variaci&oacute;n sustancial entre los individuos dentro de las localidades (DE &equals; 6.68&permil;). Nuestros datos demuestran que &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> de b&uacute;hos llaneros puede utilizarse para inferir &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> media anual ponderada por cantidad de la ubicaci&oacute;n de origen. El deuterio sigue siendo una valiosa herramienta para rastrear los movimientos de aves rapaces a escala continental, con la advertencia de que los investigadores deben identificar y modelar las posibles discontinuidades en la relaci&oacute;n &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> en sus inferencias. Sin embargo, las discontinuidades isot&oacute;picas junto con una alta abundancia relativa de los individuos en esas &aacute;reas pueden obstaculizar seriamente la utilidad del deuterio para rastrear el origen de las aves individuales.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content></italic>, deuterio, is&oacute;topos estables, paisaje de isol&iacute;neas, plumasThe use of stable isotopes to investigate animal movements has expanded tremendously since the seminal work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Chamberlain1">Chamberlain et al. (1997)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson4">Hobson and Wassenaar (1997)</xref>, who used deuterium (<sup>2</sup>H) to infer the summer origin of migratory songbirds on their wintering grounds. Since then, stable isotopes in feathers have been used to track avian breeding dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson5">Hobson et al. 2004b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Yohannes1">Yohannes et al. 2008</xref>) and migratory connectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson2">Hobson et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Perez1">Perez and Hobson 2007</xref>). Birds capture the local stable isotope values through the ingestion of local materials (water, plants, prey) and then incorporate these isotope values into their tissues, including feathers. Consequently, if the concentration of an isotope changes along some geographic gradient (e.g., latitude), we can infer the location where an individual bird grew a feather by determining the isotope concentration in that feather. In this regard, the latitudinal gradient in mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H in precipitation (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Dansgaard1">Dansgaard 1964</xref>) has provided a valuable tool that has increased our understanding of avian migration and dispersal. Precipitation is more enriched with deuterium in southern latitudes than in northern latitudes. Given the strong correlation between growing-season &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H in bird feathers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson4">Hobson and Wassenaar 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson3">Hobson et al. 2012</xref>), birds of unknown origin with deuterium-depleted and -enriched feathers are inferred to have northern and southern origins, respectively.The validity of the use of deuterium to track bird movements relies on the implicit assumption that <italic>local</italic> precipitation is the primary source of water for tissue formation in birds. This assumption is perhaps most questionable for birds that use agricultural areas in arid lands of western North America (and other arid regions) that are irrigated by deep aquifers or rivers that transport waters from distant regions, where local precipitation may contribute little to the production of plant matter. Moreover, raptors in arid areas could present some unique problems for using hydrogen isotopes to infer origin, given (1) the possibility of body-water enrichment through heat stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-McKechnie1">McKechnie et al. 2004</xref>) and (2) the recent debate about the utility of stable isotopes to identify the origin of individual raptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Smith2">Smith et al. 2009</xref>). Hence, the validity of using &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> to infer movements of raptors in arid western North America requires explicit testing.We used feathers from nestling Western Burrowing Owls (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Athene cunicularia</named-content> hypugaea</italic>) to test the assumption that &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> reflects &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> at that latitude (i.e. that &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> is tightly correlated with &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>). The Burrowing Owl provides a prototype species to test this assumption because its breeding distribution includes the most arid regions in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Holroyd2">Holroyd et al. 2001</xref>). Groundwater and river water support agricultural ecosystems in many portions of the species' breeding range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-MaciasDuarte1">Macias-Duarte 2011</xref>), and uptake of these water sources into the food web may dampen the correlation between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>. Moreover, Burrowing Owls tolerate a variety of environmental conditions (including areas with and without intensive agricultural development; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Conway1">Conway et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Bartok1">Bartok and Conway 2010</xref>), and populations vary widely in dispersal and migratory distances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 2011</xref>). Hence, the inferences that can be made from stable isotope ratios of animal tissues in this species may be particularly sensitive to discontinuities in the relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and will provide insight into their utility for studying other raptors that breed and forage in agricultural areas within arid regions.Burrowing Owls are suitable for the study of both natal and breeding dispersal via stable isotope analysis, because the species undergoes preformative and prebasic molts on the natal and breeding grounds (respectively) before fall migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Pyle1">Pyle 1997</xref>). The species' breeding distribution extends from southern Alberta and Saskatchewan in Canada throughout the western United States to northern Sinaloa, the central Baja California Peninsula, and the Mexican Highlands in Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Wellicome1">Wellicome and Holroyd 2001</xref>). Burrowing Owls inhabit arid grasslands and open deserts and breed from mid-March to late August across their breeding range. They are migratory in the northern part of the breeding range, with varying proportions of resident and migratory individuals in populations throughout the rest of the breeding range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Conway1">Conway et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 2011</xref>); migratory behavior appears to be a plastic trait in the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Ogonowski1">Ogonowski and Conway 2009</xref>). Migratory Burrowing Owls winter across the southwestern United States and throughout Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 2011</xref>). However, the migratory connectivity of many breeding populations (especially those in Mexico) to their wintering grounds is unknown. Burrowing Owls often return to the same breeding site in subsequent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Klute1">Klute et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Rosenberg1">Rosenberg and Haley 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Conway1">Conway et al. 2006</xref>) but may disperse following a nest failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 2011</xref>). However, the detection of a female that bred in both Arizona and Saskatchewan in the same breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Holroyd1">Holroyd et al. 2011</xref>), and the small amount of genetic structure among populations throughout North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-MaciasDuarte1">Macias-Duarte 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Korfanta1">Korfanta et al. 2005</xref>), suggests that breeding and natal dispersal may be common throughout the breeding range.We collected feathers from 603 juvenile Burrowing Owls during the breeding seasons of 2004&ndash;2009 at 36 study locations throughout the species' breeding range in Canada, Mexico, and the United States (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-t01">Table 1</xref>). We pulled breast, back, and head feathers from fledglings and nestlings that were older than 10 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Priest1">Priest 1997</xref>). Individual samples sent to the isotope lab included any of these 3 types of feathers; therefore, single or multiple measurements of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> represent a sample from any feather within the individual sample.Posterior distributions of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>, deviations from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship (&theta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>), and individual variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (&sigma;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>), for 36 Burrowing Owl sampling locations in North America, with 95&percnt; credible intervals (CrI).We initially used a chloroform:methanol solution for cleaning feathers (used on 30.5&percnt; of our samples) to remove oils. We subsequently adopted a two-step cleaning procedure that included both a detergent solution and chloroform:methanol solution, because this was superior to the one-step procedure in reducing measurement error in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> from Japanese Quail (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Coturnix japonica</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Paritte1">Paritte and Kelly 2009</xref>). We processed all our samples in the Environmental Isotope Laboratory at the University of Arizona. We used a Thermo-Finnegan TC/EA (operating at 1,400&deg;C) connected to a Finnegan Delta Plus or a Delta-V mass spectrometer through a CONFLO III Interface to measure &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>. The mass spectrometer's analytical precision for &delta;<sup>2</sup>H, based on the repeated analysis of a benzoic acid lab standard, was 1.8&permil; (parts per mil; 1 SD). The bulk &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values of all feather samples were measured in relation to standards tied to the VSMOW-SLAP scale, using an internal benzoic acid standard at &minus;88&permil; &plusmn; 1 (recalibrated periodically due to the exchangeable hydrogen site in benzoic acid) and a C<sub>36</sub> <italic>n</italic>-alkane standard, &minus;246.7&permil;, from Indiana University (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mypage.iu.edu/~aschimme/hc.html" xlink:type="simple">http://mypage.iu.edu/~aschimme/hc.html</ext-link>). Standardization was based on IAEA standards NBS 30, NBS 22, and IAEA CH-7.We used a modification of the &ldquo;comparative equilibrium&rdquo; technique of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Wassenaar3">Wassenaar and Hobson (2003)</xref> to measure the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H of nonexchangeable hydrogen in feather samples (here designated &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Fan1">Fan and Dettman, in press</xref>). All samples were equilibrated for &ge;4 days in open silver capsules with the ambient water vapor in the lab, along with keratin control standards, which were used to calculate the changing &delta;<sup>2</sup>H value of exchangeable hydrogen in each set of samples. After equilibration, samples were typically dried overnight under vacuum with a desiccant and at room temperature to remove any adsorbed water. Sample capsules were then quickly closed (&lt;10 min exposure to lab air) and loaded into the helium atmosphere of the Costech zero-blank autosampler. Tests of the rate of back-reaction (or water adsorption) of dried samples exposed to lab air showed minimal measurable change after 30 min (2&permil;), in agreement with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Qi1">Qi and Coplen (2011)</xref>.Our primary keratin control standard, SWAN1, came from a single molt of flight feathers collected from a Whooper Swan (<italic>Cygnus cygnus</italic>) living in an aviary in Matsue, Shimane prefecture, Japan. A single dropped Tundra Swan (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. columbianus</named-content></italic>) flight feather was collected from the Yonago waterbird sanctuary, Lake Nakaumi, Tottori prefecture, Japan, and designated SWAN2. Worn edges and the top 5 cm of the feathers were trimmed. A single sheep's fleece was purchased from a farm in Idaho, USA, at &sim;800 m elevation for our standard WOOL. The feathers and wool were cleaned with detergent and solvents. Four swan feathers of small internal variation and identical isotopic values were grouped as the standard SWAN1. The single SWAN2 feather also showed small internal variation after trimming. Control standards were homogenized by cutting strands and vanes with scissors into small fragments; the fragments were very small after 1 or 2 hr of cutting, and 4 to 6 fragments could be used to make up 1 sample for analysis. Using multiple fragments of feather or hair should improve standard homogeneity. The internal variation of the control standards was &lt;3&permil; (1 SD; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 20).Using the principle of identical treatment for unknowns and standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Werner1">Werner and Brand 2001</xref>), the Environmental Isotope Laboratory calibrated keratin control standards at room temperature, equilibrating standards with 3 water vapors with very different &delta;<sup>2</sup>H values, similar to the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Qi1">Qi and Coplen (2011)</xref>. Control standards were placed in sealed chambers with 3 waters (liquid) ranging from &minus;139 to &plus;48&permil; to equilibrate for &ge;4 days. Standards were then dried, closed, and analyzed as described above. The slope of the line relating the total &delta;<sup>2</sup>H of the control standard to the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H value of the water vapor to which it was equilibrated is the product of (1) the proportion of exchangeable hydrogen in the sample and (2) the isotopic fractionation between water vapor and the exchangeable hydrogen in the sample (see the discussion of equation 4 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Bowen1">Bowen et al. &lsqb;2005&rsqb;</xref> and equation 4 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Wassenaar2">Wassenaar and Hobson &lsqb;2000&rsqb;</xref>). Unfortunately, the hydrogen isotope fractionation is not well known. The Environmental Isotope Laboratory used a value of 1.120, slightly higher than 1.095, the measured water&ndash;exchangeable hydrogen isotope fractionation in cellulose at 114&deg;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Schimmelmann1">Schimmelmann 1991</xref>). Once the percentage exchangeable hydrogen was calculated for the standards, we used a simple mass balance equation to calculate &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>:&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>total</sub> &equals; <italic>f</italic><sub>ex</sub>(&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>exchangeable</sub>) &plus; (1 &minus; <italic>f</italic><sub>ex</sub>)(&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>), where <italic>f</italic><sub>ex</sub> is the decimal fraction of exchangeable hydrogen. This leads to the following &delta;<sup>2</sup>H values for nonexchangeable hydrogen and percentage exchangeable hydrogen in the control standards: WOOL &equals; &minus;135.5&permil; VSMOW, 11.3&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 20); SWAN1 &equals; &minus;89.5&permil;, 9.0&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 20); and SWAN2 &equals; &minus;168&permil;, 8.9&percnt; (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 5).SWAN1 was the primary control standard, and 3 SWAN1 samples were run in every batch of samples. We used the mass-balance calculation above and the measured &delta;<sup>2</sup>H value for SWAN1 and its calibrated &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> to calculate the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H of the exchangeable hydrogen in each batch of samples. All feather samples were assumed to have 9.0&percnt; exchangeable hydrogen at laboratory temperature, and 11.3&percnt; was used for wool, derived from the calibration. The same mass-balance equation was then used to calculate the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> of the samples. Although many labs use a second keratin control standard to stretch or compress the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H scale for samples, a second keratin control standard was not necessary following the above method. Treating WOOL and SWAN2 as unknowns resulted in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>nonexchangeable</sub> values averaging &minus;135.7&permil; and &minus;170.3&permil;, respectively, close to the calibrated values. Hence, the exchangeable hydrogen in feather keratin in each sample batch was assumed to be very similar in both amount and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H value after equilibration with lab air.Although this method is internally consistent (and thus allows comparisons among our samples), it does not yet allow values of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> to be compared directly to those produced with other methods. Comparisons to data across labs will require a comparison of standards among labs. If the &ldquo;true&rdquo; &delta;<sup>2</sup>H values of the control standards are subsequently determined to diverge significantly from the values reported here, all of the values produced for the present study can be recalculated (but our internal comparisons will remain valid). In addition, the standard values can be adjusted to assist in comparison of these data with those from other labs.We observed a clear linear relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> at sampling locations throughout western North America (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The posterior intercept and slope of this linear relationship were &beta;̄<sub>0</sub> &equals; &minus;13.48&permil; (95&percnt; credible interval &lsqb;CrI&rsqb;: &minus;29.87 to 3.10) and &beta;̄<sub>1</sub> &equals; 0.78 (95&percnt; CrI: 0.55 to 1.01), respectively. This relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> produced a feather deuterium isoscape with a clear latitudinal gradient in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>), suggesting a 20&permil; reduction in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> for each 10&deg; change in latitude. However, we also detected substantial variation from the expected &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> at sampling locations, due to local climatic and hydrological conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Standard deviation from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship across sampling locations was &sigma; ̄<sub>&theta;</sub> &equals; 14.19 (95&percnt; CrI: 11.14 to 18.29&permil;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Deviations were greatest in the lower Colorado River region (predicted mean &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> was &minus;57.8&permil; from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>) at both the Mexicali Valley, Mexico (&theta;̄ &equals; &minus;37.81&permil;; 95&percnt; CrI: &minus;44.58 to &minus;31.05&permil;), and Imperial Valley, United States (&theta;̄ &equals; &minus;32.04&permil;; 95&percnt; CrI: &minus;40.04 to &minus;24.06&permil;), where discontinuity in the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship was apparent (white boxes in the lower right of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figure 1</xref>). This deviation roughly corresponds to the enrichment in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> from the northern to the southern United States (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>). If Imperial and Mexicali valleys are excluded from the analysis, standard deviation from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> relationship across sampling locations decreased 22&percnt;, to &sigma; ̄<sub>&theta;</sub> &equals; 11.01&permil;. In addition, we also found relatively high levels of within-location variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>. Average among-individual standard deviation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> within sampling locations was &sigma;̄̄<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> &equals; 6.68&permil;, with the highest level of variation (&sigma; ̄<sub>i</sub> &equals; 13.55&permil;) in coastal central Sonora, Mexico (Hermosillo sampling location; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figure 1</xref>). Consequently, the standard deviation of individuals' &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> linear relationship was &sigma; ̄ &equals; 16.09&permil; (95&percnt; CrI: 13.41 to 19.74&permil;) and &sigma; ̄ &equals; 13.34&permil; (95&percnt; CrI: 11.24 to 16.24&permil;) when we included or excluded the 2 lower Colorado River sampling locations, respectively.Relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> in Burrowing Owl nestling feathers and amount-weighted mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> as inferred by a Bayesian hierarchical model. Dashed lines denote the 95&percnt; credible interval of the linear regression line. Box plots represent the distribution of individuals' posterior mean &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> at 36 sampling locations. Box height denotes the interquartile range (IQR) in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> at each study location. Upper and lower whiskers denote the minimum and maximum &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values not smaller and not larger than 1.5&times; the IQR from the box, respectively, and black circles are &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values beyond these limits. Mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> values at each location were obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Bowen2">Bowen and Revenaugh (2003)</xref>. The 2 overlapping white boxes in the lower right indicate Mexicali Valley and Imperial Valley sampling locations in northwestern Sonora and southeastern California, respectively.Geographic variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> in Burrowing Owls throughout North America. Circles represent the deviation (&theta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>) from the predicted &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (based on &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>) at each study location. The area of each circle is proportional to the magnitude of the deviation (&verbar;&theta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>&verbar;). Blue and red circles denote positive (&theta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &gt; 0) and negative (&theta;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &lt; 0) deviations, respectively.Large discontinuities in the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> linear relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>), combined with large geographic variation in the species' abundance and high within-location variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>, had an evident effect on the assignment probabilities of prescribed &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values across a latitudinal gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f03">Figure 3</xref>). Enriched &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values (&minus;50&permil;), characteristic of the coastal agricultural areas of the Gulf of California, Mexico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>), had a relatively high assignment probability to this region, but much of the assignment probability was shared with the distant eastern edge of the Burrowing Owl's breeding range near the Oklahoma Panhandle in the United States, as well as in Sonora and the Mexican Highlands in Mexico. The &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values (&minus;70&permil;) characteristic of locations across the southwestern United States (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>) were assigned with the highest probability around the Oklahoma Panhandle, as well as northeastern Colorado, southern Arizona, and coastal California in the United States, and northwestern Mexico. The most evident local effect on assignment probabilities was in the lower Colorado River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">2</xref>). Most birds with depleted &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> values (&minus;110&permil; and &minus;90&permil;), characteristic of birds originating from the upper Great Plains, were assigned to the Imperial and Mexicali valleys.Assignment probability of feathers with (<bold>A</bold>) &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;110, (<bold>B</bold>) &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;90, (<bold>C</bold>) &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;70, and (<bold>D</bold>) &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;50&permil; by cells (1&deg; longitude &times; 1&deg; latitude) throughout the Burrowing Owl's breeding range. Red intensity (10 tones from white to red) is proportional to the relative assignment probability across cells.Finally, our hierarchical model also estimated standard deviation of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f(<italic>ij</italic>)</sub> in replicate samples from feather(s) from the same nestling as &epsi; ̄ &equals; 3.91&permil; (95&percnt; CrI: 3.68 to 4.15&permil;) and a standard deviation among batches of &sigma; ̄<sub>&eta;</sub> &equals; 5.37&permil; (95&percnt; CrI: 4.46 to 6.41&permil;). We found no effect of cleaning method on &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (95&percnt; CrI of &tau;<sub>1</sub> &minus; &tau;<sub>2</sub> &equals; &minus;3.64 to 5.42&permil;), and therefore we eliminated cleaning method from the model.The current use of deuterium from feathers to track movements of birds of unknown origin relies on both the existence of a simple functional relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and the use of the well-known relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and latitude. Our study is the first to confirm that the first assumption is valid across a wide latitudinal gradient (from 19.5&deg; to 52&deg;N latitude) for a raptor inhabiting arid ecosystems of western North America. Nevertheless, local climatic and hydrological characteristics and individual variation in foraging behavior may produce large variation from the expected contribution of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> to &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> that could complicate the use of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> to infer Burrowing Owl migration and dispersal movements across North America. In this regard, our Bayesian hierarchical model provided a suitable framework for parameter estimation to characterize the relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> in Burrowing Owls in the presence of these distinct levels of variation, including measurement error. Most studies that model feather isoscapes from &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> data and precipitation isoscapes use linear regression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Wunder1">Wunder 2010</xref>), where a single &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> value is the sampling unit and variance is modeled as constant along the linear-regression &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> line. Measurement errors in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> are ubiquitous in all isotope studies, and use of &gt;1 measurement of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> per feather is required to account for this source of variation. In addition, a homogeneous within-location variance in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> is, as we demonstrated, not a realistic assumption given the heterogeneous environmental conditions at a continental scale. Our analytical approach isolates all these sources of variation to characterize the true functional relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and, hence, produces a more reliable feather deuterium isoscape (implicitly accounting for altitude) for tracking birds of unknown origin. Our estimated value for the slope of this linear relationship (&beta;̄<sub>1</sub> &equals; 0.78) is comparable to those reported in a variety of other bird taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Lott1">Lott et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Lott2">Lott and Smith 2006</xref>), on the basis of amount-weighted growing-season average &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Hobson1">Hobson 2008</xref>). However, we did not include feathers from adult birds in the present study and, hence, our results may be applicable only to juveniles.Our results suggest that deuterium from feathers can be used to identify the origin of birds at a broad scale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f03">Figure 3</xref>), in spite of the relatively large deviation in individuals' &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> from the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> predicted by local &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> across the species' breeding range (&sigma; ̄ &equals; 13.34&permil;) in comparison to the latitudinal gradient in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (20&permil; per 10&deg; latitude; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f02">Figure 2</xref>). For example, an individual with deuterium-enriched feathers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;50&permil;) could be assigned, with high probability, to both northern Sinaloa and southeastern Colorado. For depleted-deuterium feathers (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> &equals; &minus;90 and &minus;110&permil;), our assignment probability maps confer some probability to areas through the upper half of the Burrowing Owl breeding range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f03">Figure 3</xref>). However, the large discontinuity in both the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> and the &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;latitude relationships introduced by the 2 sampling locations within the lower Colorado River region and the extremely high relative abundance of Burrowing Owls in those 2 sampling locations limits our ability to make isotopic inferences (based on &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> only) regarding dispersal events from the northern edge of the species' breeding range and vice versa. For instance, properly assigning a Burrowing Owl in Saskatchewan (Canada) that originated from the lower Colorado River Valley of Arizona (United States) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Holroyd1">Holroyd et al. 2011</xref>) to its proper origin would be almost impossible on the basis of its &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> value alone. Agricultural areas in the Imperial Valley, United States, receive only 89 mm of deuterium-enriched precipitation (mean annual &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> &equals; &minus;55&permil; in Yuma; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Friedman1">Friedman et al. 1992</xref>) but are heavily irrigated with depleted-deuterium water from the Colorado River (&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>w</sub> &lt; &minus;100&permil;; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Kendall1">Kendall and Coplen 2001</xref>), which retains the depleted-deuterium values of precipitation in the Colorado River headwaters in southwestern Wyoming and western Colorado in the United States while flowing southward through arid catchment basins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Kendall2">Kendall and McDonnell 1999</xref>). This &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub>&ndash;&delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> discontinuity in the lower Colorado River, if not appropriately accounted for, may cause inappropriate inferences of breeding dispersal and migration for this, and perhaps other, species. This discontinuity might be adequately accounted for by the incorporation of additional isotopes or genetic markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Rundel1">Rundel et al. 2013</xref>). For the Burrowing Owl, however, the use of genetic markers may not be an option, given that breeding populations across North America have low genetic differentiation in microsatellite and mitochondrial DNA markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Korfanta1">Korfanta et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-MaciasDuarte1">Macias-Duarte 2011</xref>).Local hydrological processes not only affect the relationship between &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> and &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub>, but also the within-location variability. In the present study, within-location variability in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> was most obvious in nestlings from central Sonora, Mexico (Hermosillo; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-f01">Figure 1</xref>), an agricultural valley sustained exclusively by deep groundwater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-DireccionGeneraldeDistritosdeRiego1">Direccion General de Distritos de Riego 1973</xref>). Because we collected feathers at 3 different (20 km apart) nesting locations at this study site, this within-location variability in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> probably reflects the diverse isotopic composition of aquifers and small-scale spatial variation in saltwater intrusion among those locations from the Gulf of California, Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-CastilloGurrola1">Rangel Medina et al. 2002</xref>). Furthermore, individual variation in foraging behavior and small-scale spatial variation in local prey availability may also increase the within-location variability in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (Burrowing Owls eat a wide spectrum of prey, including insects, rodents, birds, amphibians, and snakes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Poulin1">Poulin et al. 2011</xref>). In this regard, our estimate of average within-location variation in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> (&sigma; ̄ &equals; 13.34&permil; if we excluded the 2 sites in the lower Colorado River region) is comparable to the within-location standard deviation of &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> in other inland raptors, such as that in body feathers of nestling Cooper's Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter cooperii</named-content></italic>; SD &equals; 11.64&permil;, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Meehan1">Meehan et al. 2003</xref>) but larger than that of small inland passerines, such as juvenile American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>; SD &equals; 7&permil;, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Langin1">Langin et al. 2007</xref>) and rectrices of adult Wilson's Warblers (<italic>Cardellina pusilla</italic>; SD range: 3.3&ndash;9.1&permil;, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-132-1-25-Paxton1">Paxton et al. 2007</xref>). Regions in North America with large within-location variability in &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> should be viewed as locations that warrant further study to determine the source(s) of water that contribute to growth of local plant tissue (and, hence, are incorporated into bird feathers and other animal tissues).In summary, &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> in nestling feathers of Burrowing Owls (feathers of known origin) reflects local &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>p</sub> from most locations throughout the species' range. However, &delta;<sup>2</sup>H<sub>f</sub> reflects water sources other than (or in addition to) local precipitation in some locations (e.g., the irrigation water from deuterium-depleted Colorado River waters). Hence, future attempts to infer large-scale deuterium isoscape maps to track bird movements should seek to incorporate all isotopic deviations from broad-scale latitudinal gradients. For example, the building of accurate isoscape maps requires data from a large number of sampling locations and should include the lower basins of all major river systems and all areas with substantial acreage of irrigated crops within the target species' distribution. Doing so will reduce the likelihood of substantial prediction errors for birds of unknown origin. Finally, the problem of inverse prediction also requires an accurate and fine-scale characterization of the relative species abundance across the species' breeding range (i.e. <italic>f</italic> (<bold>x</bold>)). The use of deuterium to track birds will likely be most reliable when isotopic anomalies and peaks of high abundance do not converge through the species' breeding range.D. Dettman of the University of Arizona's Environmental Stable Isotopes Laboratory performed isotope analyses and provided expertise in lab methods. Many collaborators provided feather samples: New Mexico State University, dozens of U.S. Department of Defense installations, Colegio de Posgraduados, Universidad Aut&oacute;noma de Nuevo Le&oacute;n, and Canadian Wildlife Service. All activities were performed in compliance with Canadian, Mexican, and U.S. regulations, including the auspices of University of Arizona IACUC protocols nos. 01-089 and 04-296. Funding was provided by the Legacy Program of the U.S. Department of Defense, iPlant Collaborative, Russell E. Train Education for Nature Program of the World Wildlife Fund, U.S. National Park Service, American Ornithologists' Union, University of Arizona, Sonoran Joint Venture of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Rocky Mountain Bird Observatory, Silliman Memorial Research Award, T&amp;E Inc., Wallace Research Foundation, Tinker Foundation, William A. Calder III Memorial Scholarship, and International Wildlife Foundation. A. Mac&iacute;as-Duarte was a recipient of a doctoral fellowship from the National Council of Science and Technology of Mexico (CONACyT). Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. J. Montoya and two anonymous reviewers provided comments that greatly improved the manuscript.