Factors influencing nest survival and productivity of Red-throated Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>) in AlaskaCommunity reorganization in the Gulf of Alaska following ocean climate regime shiftFoods of Arctic foxes (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Alopex lagopus</named-content></italic>) during winter and spring in western AlaskaArctic fox removal improves nest success of Black BrantTechniques for identifying predators of goose nestsProximate composition, energetic value, and relative abundance of prey fish from the inshore eastern Bering Sea: Implications for piscivorous predatorsRed-throated Loon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>)Factors influencing nesting success of King Eiders on northern Alaska's Coastal PlainObservations on Arctic and Red-throated loons at Storkersen Point, AlaskaShared predators and indirect trophic interactions: Lemming cycles and arctic-nesting geeseBody condition, migration, and timing of reproduction in Snow Geese: A test of the condition-dependent model of optimal clutch sizeResponse of marine deltaic surfaces to major earthquake uplifts in southcentral AlaskaFledging success of Red-throated Divers in OrkneyBreeding biology of the Red-throated DiverBreeding Red-throated Divers in ShetlandRole of rabies in recent demographic changes in red fox (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vulpes vulpes</named-content></italic>) populations in EuropeEffect of nest-site location on reproductive success of Red-throated Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>)How do Arctic Skuas <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Stercorarius parasiticus</named-content></italic> search for diver eggs?Winter survival of adult female Harlequin Ducks in relation to history of oil contamination by the <italic>Exxon Valdez</italic> oil spillA device for simultaneously measuring nest attendance and nest temperature in waterfowlEffects of mammalian predator removal on production of upland-nesting ducks in North DakotaArctic foxTrophic interactions in a high arctic Snow Goose colonyClimate change and cyclic predator-prey population dynamics in the high ArcticBreeding performance of the Red-throated Diver <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic> in ShetlandCommon Loon, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>, nest attendance patterns recorded by remote video cameraNest survival in Dusky Canada Geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta canadensis</named-content> occidentalis</italic>): Use of discrete-time modelsPopulation growth and demography of Common Loons in the Northern United StatesStatus and trends of loon populations summering in Alaska, 1971&ndash;1993Density-dependent nest predation&mdash;An experiment with simulated Mallard nests in contrasting landscapesPrey density and the behavioral flexibility of a marine predator: The Common Murre (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Uria aalge</named-content></italic>)Empirical evidence for North Pacific regime shifts in 1977 and 1989Diagnosing a shorebird local population decline with a stage-structured population modelDemographics of breeding female Mallards in southern Ontario, CanadaA study of the nesting and family life of the Red-throated LoonHierarchical organization of ecosystems at multiple spatial scales on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska, USAA conceptual model for the impact of climate change on fox rabies in Alaska, 1980&ndash;2010Variability in nest survival rates and implications to nesting studiesBird demographic responses to predator removal programsResponse of Gigeon Guillemots to variable abundance of high-lipid and low-lipid preyBreeding success of Red-throated Diver (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>) in southern FinlandValidating growth and development of a seabird as an indicator of food availability: Captive-reared Caspian Tern chicks fed ad libitum and restricted dietsAlaska-Yukon waterfowl breeding population survey, May 13 to June 7, 2011A Pacific interdecadal climate oscillation with impacts on salmon productionCommon Loon nest defense against an American minkPredator functional response and prey survival: Direct and indirect interactions affecting a marked prey populationA 50&ndash;70 year climatic oscillation over the North Pacific and North AmericaAdult survival of the Black-throated Diver <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia arctica</named-content></italic>Hypotheses concerning the decline and poor recovery of Pacific herring in Prince William Sound, AlaskaSeabirds as indicators of marine food supplies: Cairns revisitedFeeding schedule and daily food consumption in Red-throated Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>) over the prefledging periodEgg flotation estimates nest age for Pacific and Red-throated loonsTesting the junk-food hypothesis on marine birds: Effects of prey type on growth and developmentModeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SASNest success of Snowy Plovers (<italic>Charadrius nivosus</italic>) in the southern high plains of TexasAvian community ecology at two sites on Espenberg Peninsula in Kotzebue Sound, AlaskaSurvival of adult Red-throated Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>) may be linked to marine conditionsSurvival of Greater White-Fronted Geese: Effects of year, season, sex, and body conditionEffects of gull predation and weather on survival of Emperor Goose goslingsEffects of survival and reproduction on the population dynamics of Emperor GeeseA critical review of the aerial and ground surveys of breeding waterfowl in North AmericaImpacts of fishing on low-trophic level species on marine ecosystemsIntraseasonal patterns in shorebird nest survival are related to nest age and defence behaviourSeabird responses to fluctuating prey availability in the eastern Bering SeaWhen should Mayfield model data be discarded?Duck nest survival in the Missouri Coteau of North Dakota: Landscape effects at multiple spatial scalesManaging multiple vital rates to maximize Greater Sage-Grouse population growthOil pollution and climate have wide-scale impacts on seabird demographicsLow energy values of fish as a probable cause of a major seabird breeding failure in the North SeaPopulation ecology of breeding Pacific Common Eiders on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta. AlaskaNest survival in Willow Ptarmigan: Influence of time, nesting stage, and female characteristicsSubmitted February 13, 2014; Accepted August 3, 2014; Published October 15, 2014Red-throated Loon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>) numbers in Alaska have fluctuated dramatically over the past 3 decades; however, the demographic processes contributing to these population dynamics are poorly understood. To examine spatial and temporal variation in productivity, we estimated breeding parameters at 5 sites in Alaska: at Cape Espenberg and the Copper River Delta we estimated nest survival, and at 3 sites within the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta we estimated nest survival and productivity. Nest survival varied broadly among sites and years; annual estimates (lower, upper 95&percnt; confidence interval) ranged from 0.09 (0.03, 0.29) at Cape Espenberg in 2001 to 0.93 (0.76, 0.99) at the Copper River Delta in 2002. Annual variation among sites was not concordant, suggesting that site-scale factors had a strong influence on nest survival. Models of nest survival indicated that visits to monitor nests had a negative effect on nest daily survival probability, which if not accounted for biased nest survival strongly downward. The sensitivity of breeding Red-throated Loons to nest monitoring suggests other sources of disturbance that cause incubating birds to flush from their nests may also reduce nest survival. Nest daily survival probability at the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta was negatively associated with an annual index of fox occurrence. Survival through the incubation and chick-rearing periods on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta ranged from 0.09 (0.001, 0.493) to 0.50 (0.04, 0.77). Daily survival probability during the chick-rearing period was lower for chicks that had a sibling in 2 of 3 years, consistent with the hypothesis that food availability was limited. Estimates of annual productivity on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta ranged from 0.17 to 1.0 chicks per pair. Productivity was not sufficient to maintain population stability in 2 of 3 years, indicating that nest depredation by foxes and poor foraging conditions during chick rearing can have important effects on productivity.El tama&ntilde;o poblacional de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic> en Alaska ha cambiado dram&aacute;ticamente en las &uacute;ltimas tres d&eacute;cadas, sin embargo los procesos demogr&aacute;ficos que han contribuido a esos cambios no son bien conocidos. Para explorar la variaci&oacute;n espacial y temporal del &eacute;xito reproductivo, estimamos los par&aacute;metros reproductivos en cinco lugares en Alaska: en Cape Espenberg y en el Copper River Delta, estimamos la probabilidad de supervivencia de los nidos y en tres lugares del Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, estimamos la probabilidad de supervivencia de los nidos y el &eacute;xito reproductivo. Las tasas de supervivencia de los nidos variaron ampliamente entre los sitios y a&ntilde;os: Estimativos anuales que oscilaron de 0.09 (IC del 95&percnt;:0.03&ndash;0.29) en Cape Espenberg en 2001 a 0.93 (IC del 95&percnt;: 0.76&ndash;0.99) en el Copper River Delta en 2002 y valores intermedios en los sitios del Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta. La variaci&oacute;n anual entre los sitios no fue consistente, lo cual sugiere que factores locales tuvieron mayor influencia sobre la supervivencia de los nidos que los factores a nivel regional. Los modelos de supervivencia de nidos indicaron que las visitas a los nidos tuvieron un efecto negativo sobre la probabilidad diaria de supervivencia lo cual, de no ser tenido en cuenta, sesgar&iacute;a fuertemente la supervivencia de los nidos de manera negativa. La sensibilidad de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic> al monitoreo de nidos sugiere que otras fuentes de perturbaci&oacute;n que causan que las aves incubadoras vuelen de los nidos tambi&eacute;n puede reducir la supervivencia de estos. La probabilidad diaria de supervivencia de los nidos en el Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta estuvo asociada negativamente con el &iacute;ndice anual de la ocurrencia de zorros. La supervivencia a trav&eacute;s de los periodos de incubaci&oacute;n y cr&iacute;a de los pichones en el Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta vari&oacute; entre 0.09 (IC del 95&percnt;: 0.001&ndash;0.493) y 0.50 (IC del 95&percnt;: 0.04&ndash;0.77). En dos de los tres a&ntilde;os del estudio, las tasas de supervivencia diarias eran menores para los pichones con hermanos, lo cual es consistente con la hip&oacute;tesis que la provisi&oacute;n de alimento fue limitada. Estimamos que el &eacute;xito reproductivo anual en el Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta fue 0.17&ndash;1.0 pichones por pareja. La producci&oacute;n no era suficiente para mantener una poblaci&oacute;n estable en 2 de los 3 a&ntilde;os, lo cual indica que la depredaci&oacute;n de nidos por los zorros y la falta de alimento durante el periodo de cr&iacute;a de los pichones afecta la producci&oacute;n de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia stellata</named-content></italic>.Effective species management requires knowledge of population vital rates, such as productivity and survivorship. Estimates of vital rates help managers identify the life stages that most strongly contribute to population change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Hitchcock1">Hitchcock and Gratto-Trevor 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Schmutz4">Schmutz et al. 1997</xref>) and are most amenable to management action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Hoekman1">Hoekman et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Taylor1">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>). Understanding factors associated with variation in vital rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Schmutz2">Schmutz and Ely 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Schmutz3">Schmutz et al. 2001</xref>) can help assess the impacts of environmental change and anthropogenic disturbance on wildlife populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Esler1">Esler et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Votier1">Votier et al. 2005</xref>).The Red-throated Loon (<italic>Gavia stellata</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f01">Figure 1</xref>) breeds throughout Alaska, primarily on coastal tundra habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Barr1">Barr et al. 2000</xref>). The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS) has monitored the abundance of Red-throated Loons on Alaskan breeding grounds south of the Arctic Coastal Plain as part of the Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey conducted annually since 1971 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Smith1">Smith 1995</xref>). Population estimates for Red-throated Loons based on this survey have fluctuated dramatically over the past 3 decades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Mallek1">Mallek and Groves 2011</xref>), including a &gt;50&percnt; decline from 1977 to 1993 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>). Due in part to this decline, the USFWS listed the Red-throated Loon as a species of conservation concern, a designation indicative of species that, without conservation action, are likely to become candidates for Endangered Species Act listing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-U.S.FishandWildlifeServiceUSFWS1">USFWS 2008</xref>). Although patterns of Red-throated Loon abundance in Alaska are well described, we have a poor understanding of the population processes that underlie these patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-McCaffery1">McCaffery 2000</xref>). Additionally, given the high level of interest in onshore and offshore resource development in Alaska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-BureauofLandManagement1">Bureau of Land Management 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-MineralsManagementService1">Minerals Management Service 2006</xref>), future management decisions will require relevant population data to evaluate potential impacts on species of conservation concern.A Red-throated Loon and its newly hatched chick on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska. Photo credit: Gerrit VynU.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey data on Red-throated Loon abundance in Alaska on breeding habitat south of the Arctic Coastal Plain.The Red-throated Loon is exceptional among the Gaviidae in a number of its life history traits, including its small body size, use of small ponds for breeding, and its reliance on marine prey during breeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Reimchen1">Reimchen and Douglas 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Eberl1">Eberl and Picman 1993</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball2">Ball et al. (2007)</xref> hypothesized a connection between the availability of marine prey and Red-throated Loon breeding success. According to this hypothesis, changes in abundance have occurred through bottom-up effects on productivity. Population models for Common Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic>) and Arctic Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. arctica</named-content></italic>) indicate that the level of annual productivity required to maintain a stable population ranges from 0.4 to 0.5 fledged young per pair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Nilsson1">Nilsson 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Evers1">Evers 2004</xref>). Productivity estimates for Red-throated Loons in Alaska are lacking, but outside of Alaska estimates range broadly from 0.36 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>) to 1.51 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Lokki1">Lokki and Kalevi 1984</xref>) fledged young per pair per year. Distance from breeding lakes to marine foraging sites has been shown to influence breeding success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Eberl1">Eberl and Picman 1993</xref>), highlighting the importance of accessible marine foraging habitat; however, other sources of variation in productivity are poorly understood.We monitored the fates of Red-throated Loon nests at sites distributed over a broad portion of their breeding range in Alaska to examine factors associated with variation in the daily survival probability (DSP) of nests and to estimate nest survival. We hypothesized that the occurrence of foxes (primarily arctic foxes, <italic>Volpes lagopus</italic>) at breeding sites would explain important variation in nest DSP and examined this relationship at sites on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta using an index of fox occurrence. For a subset of sites and years, we also examined factors associated with variation in the DSP of an egg through both the incubation and chick-rearing periods until fledging (i.e. progeny survival). Given results of a previous study showing low chick growth rates and low availability of energy-rich forage fish species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball2">Ball et al. 2007</xref>), we examined the association between brood size and DSP during the chick-rearing period. We predicted that the presence of a sibling would be associated with reduced DSP during chick rearing if food availability was limited. We used estimates of progeny survival to calculate annual productivity (fledged chicks per breeding pair) and evaluated these estimates in the context of known population trends on Alaskan breeding grounds.We monitored Red-throated Loon nests at 5 sites on the coast of Alaska: Cape Espenberg (66&deg;34&prime;N, W 163&deg;44&prime;W) in northwestern Alaska on the coast of the Chukchi Sea; the Kashunuk River (60&deg;20&prime;N, 165&deg;35&prime;W), Kigigak Island (61&deg;50&prime;N, 165&deg;50&prime;W) and the Manokinak River (61&deg;12&prime;N, 165&deg;06&prime;W) within the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta in western Alaska on the coast of the Bering Sea; and the Copper River Delta (60&deg;25&prime;N, 145&deg;27&prime;W) in south-central Alaska on the coast of the Gulf of Alaska (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f03">Figure 3</xref>). All sites were located in areas with high densities of Red-throated Loons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>) and were within the area surveyed annually by the USFWS Breeding Waterfowl and Habitat Survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Smith1">Smith 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Mallek1">Mallek and Groves 2011</xref>).Locations of study sites with years of study, nest and brood sample sizes indicated. Shaded polygons encompass areas where breeding attempts were monitored.Habitat at all sites consists primarily of low elevation tundra with abundant lakes and wetlands, and all sites are located within or near river deltas; all nests were within 5 km of marine or brackish water habitat. Detailed habitat descriptions of these sites can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Schamel1">Schamel et al. (1979)</xref> for Cape Espenberg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Jorgenson1">Jorgenson (2000)</xref> for the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Boggs1">Boggs and Shephard (1999)</xref> for the Copper River Delta. Although habitat was generally similar at all sites, the northernmost (Cape Espenberg) and southernmost (Copper River Delta) sites are separated by 6&deg; latitude. Number of years of nest monitoring differed by site, and at some sites monitoring continued through the brood-rearing period until chicks had fledged or were near fledging age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f03">Figure 3</xref>).We searched for nests systematically at each site and upon discovery recorded the number of eggs present in each nest we encountered. We mapped nest locations on aerial photographs and recorded coordinates using handheld Global Positioning Systems; we did not use physical nest markers to mark nest locations. Red-throated Loons typically lay a 2-egg clutch with a 24&ndash;36 hr laying interval and begin incubation with the first-laid egg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Barr1">Barr et al. 2000</xref>). We calculated nest age (number of days an egg has been incubated) for nests visited during laying or at hatch, or used egg flotation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Rizzolo1">Rizzolo and Schmutz 2007</xref>) to estimate nest age by assuming a 26-day incubation period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Barr1">Barr et al. 2000</xref>). We excluded nests with no age estimate from the analysis (&lt;5&percnt; of nests found).To monitor nest fate (nest hatched, nest failed), we returned periodically to inspect nest contents. We classified nests as having survived the interval preceding a nest visit if (1) we observed an adult incubating the nest, (2) eggs were present in an unattended nest, or (3) if an egg had hatched. Hatch was indicated by the presence of either pipped eggs or chicks. Red-throated Loon chicks leave the nest shortly after hatch but rely exclusively on provisioning by parents for food until fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Reimchen1">Reimchen and Douglas 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Eberl1">Eberl and Picman 1993</xref>). Chicks remain in or near their natal lake for at least 42 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Barr1">Barr et al. 2000</xref>); thus, we assumed that if a nest had successfully hatched, we would be able to locate a chick in the natal lake or in an adjacent lake. If we did not observe any chicks at a breeding lake after the predicted hatch data for a nest, we thoroughly searched the shoreline of the breeding lake and all adjacent lakes for living chicks or chick remains. We classified a nest as failed if (1) the entire clutch was destroyed, (2) the clutch was missing prior to its predicted hatch date, or (3) no chick was present after the predicted hatch date. We monitored fates of chicks at a subset of sites and years by periodically visiting brood lakes until fledging and counting the chicks present in the lake. If chicks were present on their brood lake through 42 days we classified them as fledged; otherwise we classified them as failed.In the analysis, we included only nests that were active at the time of discovery. Failed nests checked after their predicted hatch date may have failed either during late incubation or as a chick after hatch. In these instances, we censored data back to the last interval of known fate. Right censoring data has the effect of reducing the precision of daily survival probability estimates during late incubation but eliminates the bias inherent in attempting to infer nest fate without direct evidence of the timing of failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Stanley1">Stanley 2004</xref>). For nests we observed depredated during checks to monitor nest fate (22 of 671 nests monitored), we added a final interval of 1 day to the encounter history for that nest to capture that nest failure.We used generalized linear models fit to the data using the NLMIXED procedure in Program SAS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-SASInstitute1">SAS Institute 2002</xref>). Models related the binomially distributed response variable (nest active, nest failed) to covariates using a logit link to obtain maximum likelihood estimates of parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Stephens1">Stephens et al. 2005</xref>). Because nest survival was estimated as a daily probability, we calculated sample size as the sum of all days survived and intervals between revisits during which nest failure occurred (i.e. exposure intervals; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Stephens1">Stephens et al. 2005</xref>). We confirmed that variance inflation factors (&ccirc;) calculated for our most parameterized models were &le;1.0, which provides a conservative assessment that the models fit the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-McCullagh1">McCullagh and Nelder 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>).We analyzed data separately for (1) Cape Espenberg, (2) the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, and (3) the Copper River Delta. We constructed a set of candidate nest DSP models separately for each analysis. We used Akaike's Information Criteria adjusted for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>) to calculate model weights for each model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). AIC<sub>c</sub> model weights quantify the strength of support for each model relative to the other models considered given the data. Model weights are bound between 0 and 1, and those closer to 1.0 indicate stronger support. We used AIC<sub>c</sub> model weights to average beta parameter estimates and their variances across all models weighted by the AIC<sub>c</sub> weight of each model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>).To examine temporal variation in nest DSP within years, we included nest age (age), and calendar day of the breeding season (day) as explanatory variables in models as linear and quadratic polynomial trends. We adjusted day across years and areas so that the median nest initiation date was day 0 for each site&ndash;year combination. We included an indicator variable for days of observer visits to nests to monitor nest fate (OBSERVER) in models to examine the assumption that observer visits did not affect nest DSP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Rotella1">Rotella et al. 2004</xref>). Under this approach, if nest visits influenced nest DSP, the effect of nest observation would be accounted for in the estimates of other parameters through the model structure.We calculated nest survival estimates as the product of nest DSP over the 26 days of incubation. We calculated bootstrap percentile confidence intervals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Efron1">Efron and Tibshirani 1993</xref>) by resampling the data 1000 times with replacement and using the 2.5<sup>th</sup> and 97.5<sup>th</sup> percentiles of the distribution of nest survival estimates calculated from resampled datasets as the lower and upper 95&percnt; confidence limits, respectively, around nest survival. We generated nest survival estimates and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CI) from all models in the candidate model set and averaged them across models weighted by AIC<sub>c</sub> model weights.Models accounting for variation in nest DSP on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta included covariates for spatial variation among the 3 study sites (SITE), annual variation (YEAR), within-season temporal variation (age and day), and the effect of nest observation (OBSERVER). We constrained all models in the candidate set to include YEAR and OBSERVER. To formulate the candidate model set, we constructed within-season temporal variables as both linear and quadratic additive trends in all possible combinations with SITE. We included interactions between SITE and YEAR in additional models created from those that included SITE and YEAR main effects. Finally, we included a model with only YEAR and a model with only an intercept to arrive at the final set of 28 candidate models.Foxes (primarily arctic foxes but also red foxes, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vulpes vulpes</named-content></italic>) are important predators of bird nests on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony2">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony1">2000</xref>) and have been shown to be negatively associated with Red-throated Loon productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bergman1">Bergman and Derksen 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Dickson1">Dickson 1992</xref>). To examine the association between fox predation and nest DSP, we created an index variable for fox occurrence (fox) from observations of fox scat on plots (plot size &equals; 0.32 km<sup>2</sup>) randomly placed within the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta in each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Fischer1">Fischer and Stehn 2013</xref>). We included plots located within 20 km of the boundary of each site in each year. We created year-specific study site boundaries in a Geographic Information System by defining the perimeter created by connecting the outer-most nest locations and excluding nests that were located &gt;2 km from the next nearest nest and those that increased the overall boundary area by &gt;15&percnt;. For each site and year combination, we calculated the fox index as the proportion of all plots examined that contained fox scat. This index variable quantifies the spatial frequency of occurrence of fox scat around and within each study site during each year of study. We assumed that higher fox index values indicate a higher presence of foxes around a given site. An average (&plusmn;1 SD) of 39 (&plusmn;22) plots was searched at each site in each year (range: 17&ndash;68 plots).To evaluate the effect of fox, we substituted fox for SITE and YEAR in top-ranked models (i.e. models with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2.0) in the initial model set. We fit models including fox in place of SITE and YEAR to the data together with the initial set of models to allow model weights to reflect the full set of models we considered and to model average estimates of the fox parameter across all models. If the data supported an association between the fox index and nest DSP, replacing SITE and YEAR with fox would either maintain or improve model fit. Further, the estimate for the fox parameter (i.e. the slope of the linear relationship between nest DSP and fox occurrence on the logit scale) would have a 95&percnt; CI that did not include zero.We evaluated nest DSP at Cape Espenberg and the Copper River Delta in relation to YEAR, age, day, and OBSERVER. We constrained all models in the candidate set to include YEAR and OBSERVER and constructed the model set by formulating all possible combinations of additive linear and quadratic age and day effects. We included an intercept-only null model for a total of 10 models for each site. We did not include other explanatory variables in our models, but these sites span a broad geographic range across Red-throated Loon breeding distribution in Alaska and thus provide information on broad-scale spatial variation in nest DSP.We estimated annual productivity using nest and brood monitoring data from a subset of sites&ndash;years during which we monitored the fate of chicks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f03">Figure 3</xref>). To calculate productivity (chicks fledged per breeding pair per year), we first estimated the survival probability of an egg through the entire breeding period, including both incubation and chick-rearing periods, which we call progeny survival. Estimating survival across both the incubation and chick-rearing periods offered several benefits over estimating survival separately for each stage. First, estimating progeny survival permitted including mortality that occurred during intervals that spanned hatch. Further, estimating survival at the scale of a single egg, rather than at the scale of a nest or brood, is a more sensitive measure of breeding success because the fate of the second egg in a clutch, if it survives to fledge, represents a doubling of the reproductive success of a breeding pair.Thus, we assigned all failure during hatch to the late incubation period when intervals spanning hatch began, rather than right-censoring encounter histories, which would have created an upward bias in progeny survival estimates. We estimated progeny survival for the Kashunuk River in 2000 and the Manokinak River in 2000, 2002, and 2003; no data on chick survival at either site were available from 2001 due to high nest failure. We calculated progeny survival as the product of progeny DSP during 26 days of incubation and 42 days of chick rearing.We constructed progeny survival models by first including parameters supported in the analysis of nest DSP at the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta: YEAR, SITE, egg age, and OBSERVER. To this base model, we added an indicator variable specifying exposure intervals that occurred during chick rearing (CHICK). We considered SITE and YEAR as interactions with CHICK to permit estimating effects specific to the chick-rearing period. We added chick age (an age covariate associated with chick-rearing intervals) and day as linear and quadratic trends.Brood reduction in Red-throated Loons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bergman1">Bergman and Derksen 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Eberl1">Eberl and Picman 1993</xref>) may be associated with food limitation and the consequent starvation of the second-hatched junior chick. Because of asynchronous hatching of eggs within a brood, the first-hatched senior chick is typically larger and can outcompete the junior chick for food. In years when food is not limited, the size difference between chicks within a brood does not persist (D. Rizzolo personal observation). In this study, not all chicks were marked, and senior and junior chicks within a brood were not consistently identifiable. If junior chicks have lower survival than senior chicks, the average daily survival probability for chicks with a sibling would be lower than that of singleton chicks (chicks that either hatched from clutches with 1 egg due to partial clutch depredation or whose sibling died during chick-rearing) due to the mortality of the junior chick. To examine the data for a difference in DSP between chicks with a sibling present and singleton chicks, we created an indicator variable (BROOD) that took a value of 1 for exposure intervals of chicks that had a sibling present during an interval and 0 otherwise. We included the BROOD explanatory variable in models as an interaction with year because brood size likely would be associated with chick survival only during years of poor food availability.Survival of eggs within the same clutch and chicks within the same brood were not independent. To account for this dependence we included a unique identifier for each nest as a random effect with a mean of 0 and variance estimated from the data. We calculated progeny survival for each site&ndash;year combination using model-averaged parameters; however, we used only the model with the highest model weight as the inferential model for estimating progeny survival with bootstrap percentile distribution 95&percnt; confidence limits. We acknowledge that uncertainty around progeny survival was underestimated because model selection uncertainty was not considered. We calculated annual estimates of progeny survival from both model-averaged beta parameters and the inferential model for comparison. We used progeny survival estimates to calculate productivity (fledged chicks per breeding pair per year) as the product of progeny survival and clutch size, assuming that all clutches initially included 2 eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Barr1">Barr et al. 2000</xref>). We present all estimates as mean (lower, upper 95&percnt; confidence limit), unless otherwise noted.The fates of 348 nests were monitored for 3,544 exposure intervals at the 3 Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta sites over 7 years, although not all sites were monitored in all years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f04">Figure 4</xref>). Average interval length between nest revisits was 8.5 days (range: 1&ndash;24 days), and the average number of revisits per nest was 1.5 (range: 1&ndash;4 revisits). Explanatory variables common among models with the highest model weights included age and SITE (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t01">Table 1</xref>). Age was positively associated with nest DSP (&beta;<sub>age</sub> &equals; 0.073, &lsqb;0.004, 0.141&rsqb;), which increased by 2&percnt; over the 26-day incubation period (0.976 &lsqb;0.925, 0.993&rsqb; at age 1 day; 0.995 &lsqb;0.978, 0.999&rsqb; at age 26 days). Nest DSP was negatively associated with observer visits to nests (&beta;<sub>OBSERVER</sub> &equals; &minus;2.73 &lsqb;&minus;4.45, &minus;1.01&rsqb;), which, if not accounted for, biased average nest survival downward 51&percnt; from 0.74 (model-averaged estimate from models including OBSERVER) to 0.36 (model-averaged estimate from the same model set with OBSERVER removed from models). Parameter estimates indicated no support for an association between nest DSP and day (&beta;<sub>day</sub> &equals; &minus;0.004 &lsqb;&minus;0.032, 0.022&rsqb;, &beta;<sub>day</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;0.0001 &lsqb;&minus;0.0005, 0.0002&rsqb;), or quadratic age (&beta;<sub>age</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;0.0003 &lsqb;&minus;0.002, 0.001&rsqb;).Red-throated Loon nest survival probability at 5 study sites in Alaska, 1998&ndash;2004. Error bars represent 95&percnt; CIs.Models of nest daily survival probability of Red-throated Loons in the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska, 1998&ndash;2004. Models with AIC<sub>c</sub> weights (<italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub>) &gt; 0.01 are shown and ranked by ascending &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> values. Models from the SITE&ndash;YEAR model set were refit to the data with SITE and YEAR replaced with an annual index of fox occurrence to construct the Fox Index model set. The minimum AIC<sub>c</sub> values were 557.82 for the SITE&ndash;YEAR model set and 522.95 for the Fox Index model set. &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; difference in AIC<sub>c</sub> relative to the smallest AIC<sub>c</sub> value, <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &equals; AIC<sub>c</sub> model weight, K &equals; number of parameters in the model, Deviance &equals; measure of absolute fit of the model to the data.Estimates of annual nest survival for sites on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta ranged from 0.38 (0.02, 0.72) at the Manokinak River in 2001 to 0.91 (0.67, 0.99) at the Kashunuk River in 2000 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f04">Figure 4</xref>). The year of highest nest survival at all sites was 2000; however, uncertainty around annual nest survival estimates in most years was high. The index of annual fox occurrence at each site better explained variation in nest DSP than SITE and YEAR. Models in which we substituted the fox index for SITE and YEAR received strong support from the data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t01">Table 1</xref>). The parameter estimate for fox averaged across all models fit to the data (&beta;<sub>fox</sub> &equals; &minus;0.064 &lsqb;&minus;0.088, &minus;0.039&rsqb;) was associated with a 65&percnt; decrease in nest survival calculated at the maximal observed value of fox (nest survival &equals; 0.20 &lsqb;&lt; 0.01, 0.71&rsqb;) as compared to the minimal observed value of fox (nest survival &equals; 0.83 &lsqb;0.36, 0.97&rsqb;).Over 3 years, 217 nests were monitored at Cape Espenberg for a sample of 1,446 exposure intervals. Average interval length for this study area was 6.9 days (range: 1&ndash;24 days), and nests were revisited on an average of 2.1 occasions (range: 1&ndash;8 revisits). Explanatory variables included in nest DSP models with high model weights included age, age<sup>2</sup>, day, and day<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t02">Table 2</xref>). Nest DSP at Cape Espenberg was associated with day as a quadratic trend (&beta;<sub>day</sub> &equals; &minus;0.14 &lsqb;&minus;0.23, &minus;0.05&rsqb;, &beta;<sub>day</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.007 &lsqb;0.001, 0.006&rsqb;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t02">Table 2</xref>). Nest DSP declined as a quadratic function of day and was highest for earliest initiated nests (0.98, June 13), declined slightly to the median initiation date (0.96, June 18), and continued to decline into the late nesting season (0.89, July 7). Nest observation was associated with reduced nest DSP (&beta;<sub>OBSERVER</sub> &equals; &minus;1.39 &lsqb;&minus;2.62, &minus;0.15&rsqb;). The effect of OBSERVER biased nest survival downward by 23&percnt;, from 0.30 when accounted for in the model to 0.23 if not included as a covariate in the model. Age was not associated with nest DSP (&beta;<sub>age</sub> &equals; &minus;0.003 &lsqb;&minus;0.07, 0.06&rsqb;, &beta;<sub>age</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.0007 &lsqb;&minus;0.001, 0.002&rsqb;).Models of nest daily survival probability of Red-throated Loons in Cape Espenberg, Alaska, 2000&ndash;2002, Models with AIC<sub>c</sub> weights (<italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub>) &gt; 0.01 are shown and ranked by ascending &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> values. The minimum AIC<sub>c</sub> value was 425.83. &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; difference in AIC<sub>c</sub> relative to the smallest AIC<sub>c</sub> value, <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &equals; AIC<sub>c</sub> model weight, K &equals; number of parameters in the model, Deviance &equals; measure of absolute fit of the model to the data.Because day was associated with nest DSP at Cape Espenberg, we calculated nest survival estimates for each year from model-averaged parameter estimates for each day of the nesting season; we averaged day-specific estimates of nest survival over calendar days weighted by the proportion of nests initiated on each day. We averaged day-specific nest survival estimates across models weighted by AIC<sub>c</sub> model weights. Nest survival at Cape Espenberg was lower than at other sites in all 3 years and &lt;0.15 in 2 of 3 years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f04">Figure 4</xref>).Over 5 years, 106 nests were monitored for 1,557 exposure intervals at the Copper River Delta. Nests were revisited an average of 1.8 occasions (range: 1&ndash;5 revisits), and the average duration between revisits was 7.6 days (range: 1&ndash;24 days). Model selection results showed a high degree of uncertainty in which factors were associated with nest DSP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t03">Table 3</xref>). Nest DSP at the Copper River Delta was not associated with age (&beta;<sub>age</sub> &equals; 0.002 &lsqb;&minus;0.038, 0.042&rsqb;, &beta;<sub>age</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;3.0 &times; 10<sup>&minus;5</sup> &lsqb;&minus;1.0 &times; 10<sup>&minus;3</sup>, 9.2 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4&rsqb;</sup>), or day (&beta;<sub>day</sub> &equals; &minus;0.008 &lsqb;&minus;0.043, 0.027&rsqb;, &beta;<sub>day</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; 1.3 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup> &lsqb;5.8 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup>, 3.1 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup>&rsqb;). The model-averaged parameter estimate for OBSERVER was negative but with a 95&percnt; CI that included zero (&beta;<sub>OBSERVER</sub> &equals; &minus;1.34 &lsqb;&minus;4.09, 1.41&rsqb;); if real, the effect of nest observation at the Copper River Delta biased average nest survival downward 8&percnt; from 0.77 to 0.71. Nest survival at the Copper River Delta was generally higher than other sites, &gt;0.60 in all years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f04">Figure 4</xref>).Models of nest daily survival probability of Red-throated Loons in the Copper River Delta, Alaska, 2000&ndash;2004. All models fit to the data are shown and ranked by ascending &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> values. The minimum AIC<sub>c</sub> value was 182.08. &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; difference in AIC<sub>c</sub> relative to the smallest AIC<sub>c</sub> value, <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &equals; AIC<sub>c</sub> model weight, K &equals; number of parameters in the model, Deviance &equals; measure of absolute fit of the model to the data.We used 235 eggs from 147 Red-throated Loon nests to estimate progeny DSR at the Manokinak River and Kashunkuk River sites on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta. Average number of revisits to monitor egg and chick fate was 3.3 (range: 1&ndash;19 revisits), and average interval length was 8.5 days (range: 1&ndash;27 days). The total sample of exposure intervals was 3,683.Consistent with our analysis of nest DSP, progeny DSP during incubation was negatively associated with nest observation (&beta;<sub>OBSERVER</sub> &equals; &minus;2.1 &lsqb;&minus;3.8, &minus;0.3&rsqb;). The average effect of egg age estimated by the progeny DSP models was negative (&beta;<sub>egg age</sub> &equals; &minus;0.08 &lsqb;&minus;0.15, &minus;0.01&rsqb;), in contrast to the positive effect estimated by the nest DSP models, most likely due to mortalities that occurred during hatch and were assigned to late incubation. Progeny models with high model weights included chick age, chick day, and BROOD effects on progeny DSP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-t04">Table 4</xref>). At the Manokinak River site, where nest monitoring occurred through the chick-rearing period in 3 years, progeny DSP with a sibling present was similar to that of singletons in 2000 (&beta;<sub>BROOD</sub> &equals; 0.49 &lsqb;&minus;0.29, 1.28&rsqb;) but lower than singletons in 2002 (&beta;<sub>CHICK&times;2002</sub> &plus; &beta;<sub>BROOD</sub> &equals; &minus;0.91 &lsqb;&minus;2.25, 0.41&rsqb;) and 2003 (&beta;<sub>CHICK&times;2003</sub> &plus; &beta;<sub>BROOD</sub> &equals; &minus;1.79 &lsqb;&minus;3.34, &minus;0.23&rsqb;). Parameter estimates provide some evidence that progeny DSP during chick rearing increased with chick age (&beta;<sub>chick age</sub> &equals; 0.07 &lsqb;&minus;0.01, 0.14&rsqb;). We found no support for the effect of observer visits to monitor chicks on progeny DSP (&beta;<sub>CHICK&times;OBSERVER</sub> &equals; 1.26 &lsqb;&minus;1.67, 4.19&rsqb;) or for the effects of quadratic age, day, or SITE during chick rearing (&beta;<sub>chick age</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; 1.1 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup> &lsqb;&minus;9.1 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup>, 6.9 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup>&rsqb;; &beta;<sub>CHICK&times;day</sub> &equals; 0.02 &lsqb;&minus;0.04, 0.09&rsqb;; &beta; <sub>CHICK&times;day</sub><sup>2</sup> &equals; &minus;6.9 &times; 10<sup>&minus;4</sup> &lsqb;&minus;1.4 &times; 10<sup>&minus;3</sup>, 6.9 &times; 10<sup>&minus;5</sup>&rsqb;; &beta;<sub>CHICK&times;KASHUNUK</sub> &equals; &minus;0.16 &lsqb;&minus;0.68, 0.40&rsqb;). Progeny survival estimates from the model with the highest model weight were similar to those calculated from model-averaged parameter values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f05">Figure 5</xref>).Models of progeny daily survival probability during the complete breeding period (incubation and chick-rearing periods) for Red-throated Loons in the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta during 2000, 2002&ndash;2003. All models included the same parameterization for the incubation period (not shown in table): YEAR &plus; SITE &plus; age egg &plus; OBSERVER. Models with AIC<sub>c</sub> weights (<italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub>) &gt; 0.01 are shown and ranked by ascending &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> values. The minimum AIC<sub>c</sub> value was 704.7. &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; difference in AIC<italic><sub>c</sub></italic> relative to the smallest AIC<sub>c</sub> value, <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &equals; AIC<sub>c</sub> model weight, K &equals; number of parameters in the model, Deviance &equals; measure of absolute model fit to the data.Progeny survival probability for Red-throated Loons in the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta. Estimates are from the model with the highest model weight in the candidate set (squares) and model averaging across all models (circles). Horizontal lines represent the 95&percnt; confidence limits from the most-supported model.The probability that an egg survived to become a fledged chick ranged from 0.09 (&lt;0.01, 0.49) at the Manokinak River in 2003 to 0.50 (0.04, 0.77) at the Kashunkuk River in 2000 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f05">Figure 5</xref>). Productivity estimates at the Kashunuk River were 1.0 chicks per pair in 2000, and at the Manokinak River were 0.53, 0.20, and 0.17 chicks per pair in 2000, 2002, and 2003, respectively.We provide the first rigorous estimates of nest survival and productivity for Red-throated Loons in Alaska. We found substantial spatial and temporal variation in nest survival and productivity. Among sites, nest survival estimates ranged from consistently high at the Copper River Delta to consistently low at Cape Espenberg. Annual variation among Cape Espenberg, the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, and the Copper River Delta was not concordant, suggesting that site-scale factors had a greater influence on nest survival than any consistent regional-scale factors. These study areas span 6&deg; latitude and have distinct phenologies and predator and prey populations, which likely exert strong local effects on nest survival.At sites within the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta, spatial and temporal variation in nest DSP was additive with similar patterns of annual variation among sites. This spatial and temporal variation was most parsimoniously explained by an index of fox occurrence. Our fox index values have not been verified with estimates of fox abundance, and so we do not know how reliably index values correlate with true fox abundance. However, the random sampling design and consistent field methods of surveys used to calculate the fox index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Fischer1">Fischer and Stehn 2013</xref>) make us confident that fox index values correlate reliably with the presence of foxes around sites, and that higher index values indicate either higher fox abundance or longer fox residence. The support of the fox index covariate and its negative parameter estimate indicate that a higher occurrence of fox scat at study sites was associated with lower nest DSP. We believe the negative relationship between the fox index and nest DSP simply captures the direct mortality of eggs caused by fox depredation of nests.Foxes are known to depredate the nests of Red-throated Loons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bergman1">Bergman and Derksen 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Dickson1">Dickson 1992</xref>) and have been identified as an important nest predator on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony2">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony1">2000</xref>). Biparental incubation in loons is associated with high incubation constancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Goodale1">Goodale et al. 2005</xref>); thus, eggs are rarely unattended. Although Common Loons may defend their nests against mammalian predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-McCarthy1">McCarthy and Destefano 2011</xref>), the smaller body size of Red-throated Loons likely makes this species particularly vulnerable to mammalian nest predators such as foxes. Removal of foxes improved the nest success of Black Brant geese (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta bernicla</named-content> nigricans</italic>) on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony2">Anthony et al. 1991</xref>). Although fox removal can be an effective tool for improving nest success of ground-nesting species of birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Lavers1">Lavers et al. 2010</xref>), it would be difficult to apply to large, roadless areas in Alaska where breeding Red-throated Loons occur in relatively low densities.Harvest of foxes in Alaska is not an important source of mortality because of low fur prices (Garrott and Eberhardt 1987). Natural factors that regulate fox populations, including the availability of small mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bety1">B&ecirc;ty et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gauthier1">Gauthier et al. 2004</xref>) and the occurrence of rabies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Chautan1">Chautan et al. 2000</xref>), likely have the strongest influence on fox population abundance in the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta. Climate change effects on these factors are predicted to reduce temporal variance and increase average abundance of arctic fox populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Kim1">Kim et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Glig1">Glig et al. 2009</xref>), which in turn may lead to higher average depredation rates on tundra-nesting birds.At the Copper River Delta, Bald Eagles (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Haliaeetus leucocephalus</named-content></italic>) are an important nest predator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anthony3">Anthony et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Grand1">Grand et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Miller1">Miller et al. 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Miller1">Miller et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Grand1">Grand et al. (2006)</xref> showed that the rate of Bald Eagle predation on Canada Goose (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Branta canadensis</named-content></italic>) nests on the Copper River Delta was mediated by the availability of anadramous fish (eulachon, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thaleichthys pacificus</named-content></italic>), which served as alternative prey for eagles. Nest survival of both Canada Geese and Red-throated Loons at the Copper River Delta during 2001&ndash;2003 was highest in 2002, when the presence of eulachon was most protracted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Miller1">Miller et al. 2006</xref>). We hypothesize that Bald Eagles and the presence of alternative prey mediate nest survival of Red-throated Loons in a manner similar to that demonstrated for Canada Geese (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Grand1">Grand et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Miller1">Miller et al. 2006</xref>). Red-throated Loons may also gain direct benefits from eulachon consumed as prey, such as increased adult body condition and higher incubation constancy, which also may contribute to high nest survival at this site.Nest DSP decreased in association with calendar day at Cape Espenberg. The effect of calendar day was not present at the other sites in Alaska, but a similar pattern was found in the Shetland Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">Bundy 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>). Seasonal variation in nest success may be related to site-scale factors, such as changes in the abundance of predators and alternative prey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Wilson2">Wilson et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gunnarsson1">Gunnarsson and Elmberg 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Smith3">Smith and Wilson 2010</xref>), adult condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bety2">B&ecirc;ty et al. 2003</xref>), and seasonal changes in weather (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Saalfeld1">Saalfeld et al. 2011</xref>). Similarly, site-scale factors likely underlie nest age effects on nest DSP, which were inconsistent among sites. Nest age effects in other ground-nesting bird species have been attributed to differences in nest vulnerability related to nest concealment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Klett1">Klett and Johnson 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Garrettson1">Garrettson and Rowher 2001</xref>), differences in predator communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Wilson2">Wilson et al. 2007</xref>), and behavioral changes of incubating adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Smith3">Smith and Wilson 2010</xref>). Although we do not know the ultimate mechanisms underlying nest age and calendar day effects on Red-throated Loon nest DSP, it is important that these effects be accounted for to obtain unbiased estimates of nest survival.Observer visits to monitor nest fate had a strong negative influence on Red-throated Loon nest DSP. Negative observer effects on nest DSP have been found in other ground-nesting species in tundra habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bentzen1">Bentzen et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Wilson1">Wilson et al. 2012</xref>). The nesting habitat and behavior of Red-throated Loons make them especially vulnerable to nest depredation caused by human disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">Bundy 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Booth1">Booth 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Enquist1">Enquist 1983</xref>). Unlike other loon species, Red-throated Loons nest on small lakes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bergman1">Bergman and Derksen 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Dickson1">Dickson 1992</xref>), and in response to observer disturbance, breeding adults often take flight and leave the nest lake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Johnson1">Johnson and Johnson 1935</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">Bundy 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Booth1">Booth 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Enquist1">Enquist 1983</xref>). A small sample of temperature loggers deployed in Red-throated Loon nests at our study sites to measure incubation constancy indicated that, when flushed by observers, breeding adults remained off the nest for an average of 2 hours (D. Rizzolo personal observation). Given the observer effects we documented, we recommend researchers use less invasive nest monitoring methods for Red-throated Loons during incubation; for example, the use of temperature loggers to record incubation constancy allows one to infer when a nest had failed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Flint1">Flint and MacCluskie 1992</xref>). The sensitivity of incubating Red-throated Loons to observer visits suggests that other sources of disturbance that cause incubating birds to flush may similarly reduce nest survival and should be considered by resource managers when assessing the potential impacts of development.Red-throated Loons showed high levels of chick production during 2000 at the Kashunuk River and Manokinak River sites on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta; in contrast, chick production was low at the Manokinak River during 2002 and 2003. These estimates fall within the range of estimates of chick production from other areas of the species' breeding distribution: 0.31 chicks per pair in the Shetland Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy1">Bundy 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>) to 1.51 chicks per pair in Finland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Lokki1">Lokki and Kalevi 1984</xref>); however, direct comparison of our results with other estimates is uninformative given differences in estimation methods. Only one previous study used methods that accounted for nest failure prior to nest discovery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>), and some are based on monitoring chicks only and do not include breeding failure during incubation, which often represents the period of highest breeding failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">Bundy 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Gomersall1">Gomersall 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Dickson1">Dickson 1992</xref>). Further, the potential effects of nest observation on breeding success have been noted previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Bundy2">Bundy 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Dickson1">Dickson 1992</xref>) but not explicitly accounted for in estimates of productivity. Our estimates of productivity based on progeny survival include mortality during incubation and account for sources of bias during both incubation and chick-rearing periods of breeding.Birds with nonprecocial young must provision a sufficient quantity and quality of food to support the energy requirement of their growing chicks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Romano1">Romano et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Lyons1">Lyons and Roby 2011</xref>). For marine birds, this connection, although intuitive, is difficult to quantify given the expense and effort required to measure fish abundance and species composition in marine habitats at relevant spatial scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Harding1">Harding et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Piatt1">Piatt et al. 2007</xref>). We found that Red-throated Loon chicks with a sibling present had lower progeny DSP at the Manokinak River in 2002 and 2003, which is consistent with the hypothesis that food limited chick survival in those years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball2">Ball et al. 2007</xref>). Presence of a sibling may also lower daily survival probability due to increased visibility of the brood to predators, higher vulnerability of the junior chick to predation, or reduced adult attendance caused by increased provisioning demand. However, the inference of poor foraging conditions during 2002 and 2003 at the Manokinak River site is also supported by low chick growth rates and chick diets composed of low-to-moderate energy density fish species in those years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball 2004</xref>).Given the reliance of breeding Red-throated Loons on marine prey, the species is ecologically similar to species of piscivorous seabirds whose breeding success is correlated with prey quality and availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Springer1">Springer et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Litzow1">Litzow et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Wanless1">Wanless et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Piatt1">Piatt et al. 2007</xref>). Abundance and community composition of ecologically important species of fish can vary dramatically with ocean climate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Hare1">Hare and Mantua 2000</xref>), with consequent effects on breeding bird populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Anderson1">Anderson and Piatt 1999</xref>). The potential for anthropogenic effects on forage fish populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Smith2">Smith et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Pearson1">Pearson et al. 2012</xref>) emphasizes that decisions regarding opening Arctic waters to commercial fishing and development of offshore petroleum resources are relevant to marine piscivores, like the Red-throated Loon.The Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta supports 39&percnt; of the total number of Red-throated Loons counted during annual spring surveys in Alaska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>). Densities of Red-throated Loons counted during spring surveys were highest on the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta and the Seward Peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Groves1">Groves et al. 1996</xref>), areas that showed either low productivity (i.e. the Manokinak River) or low nest survival (i.e. Cape Espenberg). High rates of nest predation during periods of high fox occurrence in combination with the limited availability of high-lipid prey during chick rearing may combine to depress Red-throated Loon productivity. The life history traits of the Gaviidae lie toward the slow end of the fast&ndash;slow life history continuum (i.e. long lifespan, long juvenile nonbreeding life stage, low fecundity; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Nilsson1">Nilsson 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Evers1">Evers 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Grear1">Grear et al. 2009</xref>). Periods of poor productivity would therefore have to be prolonged over multiple years to induce a decline in the breeding population independent of changes in adult survival because of the low turnover rate of breeding adults. Changes in the availability of marine prey associated with the Pacific Decadal Oscillation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Mantua1">Mantua et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Minobe1">Minobe 1997</xref>) provide a potential mechanism for bottom-up effects on Red-throated Loon populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball2">Ball et al. 2007</xref>) because changes in the marine ecosystem occur at decadal timescales. Further, if Red-throated Loon populations are regulated by decadal-scale oscillations in the marine environment, population declines persisting for longer than such oscillations should raise the most concern for conservation and suggest management actions.The relationship between Red-throated Loon productivity and population abundance in Alaska is unclear. We lack the sample size of years to examine the correlation between our estimates of productivity and USFWS population estimates based on the Waterfowl Breeding Population and Habitat Survey. The present study occurred at the end of the period of numerical decline described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Groves1">Groves et al. (1996)</xref>; abundance rebounded after 2002 to near historic levels but has again begun to decline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-f02">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Mallek1">Mallek and Groves 2011</xref>). Our results demonstrate that, as expected given their life history strategy, Red-throated Loon nest survival and productivity are, on average, low and highly variable, and that some of this variation is associated with predation by foxes. Further, lower chick survival in the presence of a sibling is consistent with the hypothesis of limited food availability at the Manokinak River site in 2002 and 2003 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball1">Ball 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Ball2">Ball et al. 2007</xref>). These results suggest that changes on the breeding grounds that increase fox occurrence, increase disturbance of incubating adults, or that reduce the availability of marine forage fishes will likely reduce Red-throated Loon productivity.A more thorough understanding of population dynamics in this species requires additional information on other demographic parameters, particularly adult survival. If adult survival scales to adult body mass within the Gaviidae, adult survival may be lower in Red-throated Loons than in larger-bodied congeners (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-574-Schmutz1">Schmutz 2014</xref>) and lead to population dynamics that are inherently less stable and more sensitive to changes in productivity than other loon species. Hindcasting population trends in Alaska using population models would help to understand the relative effects of fecundity and survival as well as the timescales necessary to induce population declines.Funding for this project was provided by U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Migratory Bird Management. We are grateful for logistic support from Yukon Delta NWR and field assistance from T. Arensberg, J. Beagley, J. Ball, E. Bohman, C. Eldermire, P. Fontaine, J. Kiesau, B. Lake, D. Miller, C. Moran, D. Safine, M. Shepherd, E. Wald, M. Wege, M. Weiss; and to. H. Wilson. R. Churchwell, B. Lake, J. Pearce, P. Smith, and an anonymous reviewer provided helpful comments on previous versions of this manuscript. A. Gall and J. Zamudio translated the Spanish abstract. Any use of trade names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.