Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) select habitat based on avian predators, landscape composition, and anthropogenic featuresLinking occurrence and fitness to persistence: Habitat-based approach for endangered Greater Sage-GrouseDetectability adjusted count models of songbird abundanceUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionHabitat partitioning in endangered Cantabrian Capercaillie <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tetrao urogallus</named-content> cantabricus</italic>Characteristics of climate and landscape disturbance influence the dynamics of Greater Sage-Grouse populationsWhen a native predator becomes a pest: A case studyCommon Raven (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>)Coyote and bobcat responses to integrated ranch management practices in south TexasSage grouse declines in western North America: What are the problems?Common Raven activity in relation to land use in western Wyoming: Implications for Greater Sage-Grouse reproductive successSage-grouse habitat selection during winter in AlbertaHabitat structure mediates predation risk for sedentary prey: Experimental tests of alternative hypothesesNest predation of Greater Sage-Grouse in relation to microhabitat factors and predatorsCharacteristics and dynamics of Greater Sage-Grouse populationsGreater Sage-Grouse select nest sites to avoid visual but not olfactory predatorsEcology and management of sage-grouse and sage-grouse habitatNon-lethal effects of predation in birdsGreater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) select nest-sites and brood-sites away from avian predatorsGreater Sage-Grouse nesting habitat: The importance of managing at multiple scalesIdentifying and prioritizing Greater Sage-Grouse nesting and brood-rearing habitat for conservation in human-modified landscapesThe potential for interactions between predation and habitat change to cause population declines of farmland birdsThe influence of fine-scale habitat features on regional variation in population performance of alpine White-tailed PtarmiganNesting-area fidelity of Sage Grouse in southeastern IdahoNorthern Harrier (<italic>Circus cyaneaus</italic>) attacks on Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) in southern AlbertaHabitat use by meso-predators in a corridor environmentParental investment strategies in two species of nuthatch vary with stage-specific predation risk and reproductive effortMethods for trapping Sage Grouse in ColoradoEnergy development affects populations of sagebrush songbirds in WyomingSurvival of Greater Sage-Grouse chicks and broods in the northern Great BasinEffects of landscape-scale environmental variation on Greater Sage-Grouse chick survivalGreater Sage-Grouse: General use and roost site occurrence with pellet counts as a measure of relative abundanceDirect identification of northern sage-grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>) nest predators using remote sensing camerasSpatial distribution of Greater Sage-Grouse nests in relatively contiguous sagebrush habitatsYearling Greater Sage-Grouse response to energy development in WyomingSelection of anthropogenic features and vegetation characteristics by nesting Common Ravens in the sagebrush ecosystemViability and conservation of an exploited sage-grouse populationThe role of fire in structuring sagebrush habitats and bird communitiesEffectiveness of avian predator perch deterrents on electric transmission linesNonlethal effects in the ecology of predator&ndash;prey interactionsFood habits and nest characteristics of breeding raptors in southwestern WyomingRelating grouse nest success and corvid density to habitat: A multi-scale approachPredation on dependent off-spring: A review of the consequences for mean expression and phenotypic plasticity in avian life history traitsThe use of discrete-choice models for evaluating resource selectionDiscrete-choice modeling in wildlife studies exemplified by Northern Spotted Owl nighttime habitat selectionSage-grouse and indirect interactions: Potential implication of coyote control on sage-grouse populationsEnergy development and Greater Sage-GrouseInfluence of fire and juniper encroachment on birds in high elevation sagebrush steppeRaptor and corvid response to power distribution line perch deterrents in UtahManaging and Monitoring Birds using Point Counts: Standards and ApplicationsA terrain ruggedness index that quantifies topographic heterogeneityPredation and the management of prairie grouseDistribution of sage grouse in North AmericaSage Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>)Effectiveness of raptor perch deterrents on an electrical transmission line in southwestern WyomingManaging multiple vital rates to maximize Greater Sage-Grouse population growthRaptor predation and population limitation in Red GrouseDistance software: Design and analysis of distance sampling surveys for estimating population sizeFear factor: Prey habitat selection and its consequences in a predation risk landscapePredation on real and artificial nests in shrubsteppe landscapes fragmented by agricultureMeta-analysis of foraging and predation risk trade-offs in terrestrial systemsAn improved spotlighting technique for capturing Sage GrouseGreater Sage-Grouse population response to energy development and habitat lossPrey species minimize the risk of predation directly by avoiding predators and indirectly by avoiding risky habitat. Habitat loss and fragmentation have been prevalent in Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;sage-grouse&rdquo;) habitat, which has necessitated a better understanding of mechanisms driving habitat use. Using multinomial logistic regression, we compared landscape attributes and anthropogenic features (indirect mechanisms) and densities of avian predators (direct mechanisms) among 792 sage-grouse locations (340 nests, 331 early brood, and 121 late brood) and 660 random locations in Wyoming, USA, in 2008&ndash;2011. Anthropogenic features included oil and gas structures, communication towers, power lines, roads, and rural houses; and landscape attributes included a normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI), topographic ruggedness, the proportion of big sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Artemisia</named-content></italic> spp.), and proximity and proportion variables for forested and riparian habitats. Sage-grouse locations were best described with models that included multiple habitat variables and densities of small, medium, and large avian predators. Thus, both indirect and direct mechanisms of predator avoidance were employed by sage-grouse to select habitat and presumably lower their exposure to predation and nest predation. At all reproductive stages, sage-grouse selected flatter locations with a greater proportion of big sagebrush, a higher NDVI, and lower densities of oil and gas structures. Nest locations had a lower density of major roads and were farther away from riparian habitat; early-brood locations had a lower density of power lines and were closer to rural houses; and late-brood locations were closer to riparian habitat. The magnitudes of direct and indirect avoidance by sage-grouse hens were dependent on a sage-grouse's reproductive stage. Differential habitat use of female sage-grouse relative to predation risk and food availability was a means for sage-grouse hens to lower their risk of predation and nest predation, while using habitat to meet their energetic requirements and those of their chicks.Las especies de presa minimizan el riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n evitando directamente a los depredadores e indirectamente evitado los h&aacute;bitats riesgosos. La p&eacute;rdida de h&aacute;bitat y la fragmentaci&oacute;n han sido determinantes en el h&aacute;bitat de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>, lo que ha hecho necesaria una mejor comprensi&oacute;n de los mecanismos que determinan el uso del h&aacute;bitat. Usando regresi&oacute;n log&iacute;stica multinomial, comparamos los atributos del paisaje y las caracter&iacute;sticas antropog&eacute;nicas (mecanismos indirectos) y la densidad de aves depredadoras (mecanismos directos) entre 792 localizaciones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> (340 nidos, 331 cr&iacute;as recientes y 121 cr&iacute;as tard&iacute;as) y 660 localizaciones al azar en Wyoming, entre 2008 y 2011. Las caracter&iacute;sticas antropog&eacute;nicas incluyeron estructuras de petr&oacute;leo y gas, torres de comunicaci&oacute;n, tendidos el&eacute;ctricos, caminos y casas rurales; y los atributos del paisaje incluyeron el &iacute;ndice normalizado de diferencia de vegetaci&oacute;n (NDVI), rugosidad topogr&aacute;fica, proporci&oacute;n de especies de <italic>Artemisia</italic> y proximidad y proporci&oacute;n de h&aacute;bitats boscosos y ribere&ntilde;os. Las localizaciones de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> fueron mejor descritas con modelos que incluyeron m&uacute;ltiples variables de h&aacute;bitat y densidad de aves predadoras peque&ntilde;as, medianas y grandes. As&iacute;, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> us&oacute; mecanismos indirectos y directos de evasi&oacute;n de los depredadores para seleccionar los h&aacute;bitats y bajar presumiblemente su exposici&oacute;n a la depredaci&oacute;n y a la depredaci&oacute;n de los nidos. En todos los estadios reproductivos, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> seleccion&oacute; localizaciones m&aacute;s planas con una mayor proporci&oacute;n de especies de <italic>Artemisia</italic>, NDVI m&aacute;s elevado y densidades m&aacute;s bajas de estructuras de petr&oacute;leo y gas. Las localizaciones de los nidos tuvieron menor densidad de caminos principales y estuvieron m&aacute;s alejadas de los h&aacute;bitats ribere&ntilde;os; las localizaciones de las nidadas tuvieron menor densidad de tendidos el&eacute;ctricos y estuvieron m&aacute;s cercanas a casa rurales; y las localizaciones de las nidadas tard&iacute;as estuvieron m&aacute;s cerca a los h&aacute;bitats ribere&ntilde;os. Las magnitudes de la evasi&oacute;n directa e indirecta por parte de los individuos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> dependieron del estadio reproductivo de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic>. Los diferentes usos de h&aacute;bitat de las hembras de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> con relaci&oacute;n al riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n y a la disponibilidad de alimentos fue aprovechada por los individuos de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. urophasianus</named-content></italic> para bajar su riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n y la depredaci&oacute;n de los nidos, durante el uso del h&aacute;bitat para alcanzar los requerimientos energ&eacute;ticos de los adultos y los pichones.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> aves depredadores, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>, c&oacute;rvido, evasi&oacute;n del depredador, rapaz, riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n, selecci&oacute;n de sitio de la nidada, selecci&oacute;n de sitio del nido, uso de h&aacute;bitatPredator avoidance behaviors influence habitat selection indirectly by reducing the use of risky habitats (habitats correlated with higher risk of predation) or directly by avoiding predators once they are seen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Lima1">Lima 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Verdolin1">Verdolin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Cresswell1">Cresswell 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref>). Both indirect and direct mechanisms of predator avoidance are connected with an animal's perceived risk of predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Cresswell1">Cresswell 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Martin1">Martin and Briskie 2009</xref>). For example, the risk of predation taken by male Red-breasted Nuthatches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sitta canadensis</named-content></italic>) and White-breasted Nuthatches (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">S. carolinensis</named-content></italic>) to feed females on nests was lower in the presence of House Wrens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Troglodytes aedon</named-content></italic>) and Sharp-shinned Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Accipiter striatus</named-content></italic>), which indicates direct avoidance of predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Ghalambor1">Ghalambor and Martin 2000</xref>). Greater Sage-Grouse (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Centrocercus urophasianus</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;sage-grouse&rdquo;) use habitat with lower densities of avian predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref> suggested that the potential mechanism for this pattern was direct predator avoidance, but the pattern could also be explained in part as avoidance of habitat correlated with higher avian predator densities (e.g., oil and gas structures, power lines, forested habitat, etc.).Anthropogenic features can be used as perches or nest structures by avian predators or can be associated with food subsides. American Kestrels (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Falco sparverius</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;kestrel&rdquo;), Common Ravens (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;raven&rdquo;), Golden Eagles (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Aquila chrysaetos</named-content></italic>), Ferruginous Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo regalis</named-content></italic>), Red-tailed Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo jamaicensis</named-content></italic>), and Swainson's Hawks (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo swainsoni</named-content></italic>) use power lines for perching or nesting and areas around power lines for foraging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Lammers1">Lammers and Collopy 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Prather1">Prather and Messmer 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Slater1">Slater and Smith 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Coates2">Coates et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Howe1">Howe et al. 2014</xref>). Road-killed animals also attract mammalian and avian predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Bradley1">Bradley and Fagre 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Boarman1">Boarman 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Boarman3">Boarman et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Frey1">Frey and Conover 2006</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated that sagebrush-obligate birds, including Brewer's Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella breweri</named-content></italic>), Sagebrush Sparrows (<italic>Artemisiospiza nevadensis</italic>), Vesper Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pooecetes gramineus</named-content></italic>), and sage-grouse are negatively associated with oil and gas infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge1">Aldridge 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Walker1">Walker et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty1">Doherty 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Carpenter1">Carpenter et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran4">Holloran et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Gilbert1">Gilbert and Chalfoun 2011</xref>). In addition, sage-grouse avoid power lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Hanser1">Hanser et al. 2011</xref>) and roads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran1">Holloran 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge2">Aldridge and Boyce 2007</xref>). Thus, sagebrush birds, including sage-grouse, may avoid man-made features to indirectly reduce predation risk.In addition to avoiding tall man-made structures (structures &gt;2 m tall) and roads, prey species including sage-grouse may indirectly avoid avian predators by avoiding other landscape attributes that represent riskier habitat, such as riparian areas, coniferous forests, and rough terrain. In northeastern Wyoming, USA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty2">Doherty et al. (2010)</xref> found that sage-grouse selected nesting habitat with lower terrain roughness and percent cover of conifer, grassland, and riparian habitat; they also found that sage-grouse selected areas with a greater density of sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Artemisia</named-content></italic> spp.) at the scale of 100 to 350 m compared with random locations within sagebrush. Greater density of sagebrush at relatively large spatial extents may reduce the foraging efficiency of visual predators. Reduced predation has the potential to increase not just sage-grouse adult survival but also nest success. For example, Brewer's Sparrows nesting in areas with greater shrub cover and a greater density of vacant potential nest sites had better nest success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Chalfoun1">Chalfoun and Martin 2009</xref>).A better understanding of habitat quality and mechanisms driving habitat use is a key component of conservation of sage-grouse, a species of conservation concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Braun1">Braun 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder2">Schroeder et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>). Little research has explicitly compared the relative importance of indirect vs. direct predator avoidance mechanisms in relation to the use of habitat by prey species, which could have implications for management recommendations. Sage-grouse may avoid avian predators indirectly by avoiding landscape attributes or anthropogenic features that might attract avian predators or directly by observing them; however, it is more likely that sage-grouse use both indirect and direct means of avoiding predators. We used sage-grouse as a model prey species to test the importance of both indirect and direct predator avoidance. From 2008 to 2011, we recorded avian predator densities and calculated distances from landscape attributes and anthropogenic features to radio-tagged sage-grouse hens to determine the importance of direct and indirect predator avoidance by sage-grouse hens. For precocial species such as sage-grouse, predator avoidance may differ among reproductive stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Ghalambor1">Ghalambor and Martin 2000</xref>). Thus, we also evaluated habitat use of sage-grouse females during two reproductive stages, nesting and brood-rearing. We hypothesized that sage-grouse primarily would avoid nesting and raising their chicks in areas with high densities of avian predators and secondarily would avoid landscape attributes and anthropogenic features that posed a greater risk of predation. We also hypothesized that sage-grouse hens would respond to multiple predator species by always avoiding avian predators, which are a threat to adult hen survival during all reproductive stages, but by avoiding predators that are threats to just nests and chicks only during those reproductive stages. Finally, we predicted that hens would use more productive, but riskier, riparian habitat only when chicks were less vulnerable to predation.Our study was conducted at 12 sites in southwestern and south-central Wyoming, USA. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran3">Holloran and Anderson (2005)</xref> found that 93&percnt; of 415 observed nests were within 8.5 km of leks at which females were captured in central and southwestern Wyoming. Thus, our eight sites in southwestern Wyoming (Lincoln, Sweetwater, and Uinta counties) were 16 km in diameter, approximately centered around leks where hens were captured. The four sites in south-central Wyoming (Carbon and Sweetwater counties) were 24 km in diameter, because sage-grouse were captured at several nearby leks over a larger area. Sites were chosen to provide a representation of overall sage-grouse nesting habitat in southern Wyoming, with a variety of land uses and topographic features. Elevation ranged from 1,950 m to 2,600 m. Most of the area within our sites was federally owned and administered by the Bureau of Land Management, with a small percentage of private lands. Domestic sheep and cattle grazing were the dominant land uses in our sites. All sites had anthropogenic development, which consisted mostly of unimproved four-wheel drive roads. Conventional natural gas, coalbed methane natural gas, and/or conventional oil extraction activities were present in six (50&percnt;) of our sites; mean well density among all sites was 0.12 &plusmn; 0.22 SD wells km<sup>&minus;2</sup> (minimum&ndash;maximum &equals; 0.00&ndash;0.64 wells km<sup>&minus;2</sup>).The landscape at all sites was dominated by sagebrush; Wyoming big sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Artemisia tridentata</named-content> wyomingensis</italic>) and mountain big sagebrush (<italic>A. t. vaseyana</italic>) were the most common. Black sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. nova</named-content></italic>) and little sagebrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. arbuscula</named-content></italic>) were found on exposed ridges. Other common shrub species included alderleaf mountain mahogany (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cercocarpus montanus</named-content></italic>), antelope bitterbrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Purshia tridentata</named-content></italic>), chokecherry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Prunus virginiana</named-content></italic>), common snowberry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Symphoricarpos albus</named-content></italic>), greasewood (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Sarcobatus vermiculatus</named-content></italic>), rabbitbrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Chrysothamnus</named-content></italic> spp.), Saskatoon serviceberry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Amelanchier alnifolia</named-content></italic>), and spiny hopsage (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Grayia spinosa</named-content></italic>). Isolated stands of juniper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Juniperus</named-content></italic> spp.) and quaking aspen (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Populus tremuloides</named-content></italic>) were found at the higher elevations on north-facing hillsides.We monitored sage-grouse hens during nesting and brood-rearing from 2008 to 2011. Hens were captured, radio-tagged, and released in April of each year. We captured hens at night using all-terrain vehicles (ATVs), spotlights, and hoop-nets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Giesen1">Giesen et al. 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Wakkinen1">Wakkinen et al. 1992</xref>). Sage-grouse hens were fitted with 17.5-g or 22-g (&lt;1.5&percnt; body mass) necklace radio-collars (RI-2D, Holohil Systems, Carp, Ontario, Canada; or A4060, Advanced Telemetry Systems, Isanti, Minnesota, USA).We located hens weekly with Communications Specialists receivers (R-1000, Communications Specialists, Orange, California, USA) and three-way Yagi antennas. Potential nests were identified with binoculars from &sim;15 m away by visually locating a radio-tagged hen under a shrub. Nests were verified by triangulating the hen under the same shrub from &gt;50 m away or thoroughly searching the area of the potential nest when the hen was absent. We continued monitoring nests weekly until the nest hatched or failed.We located the broods of radio-tagged hens weekly with binoculars from &sim;15 m distance. Brood hens were identified either by visually detecting chicks or by observing hen behavior that indicated the presence of a brood (e.g., hesitation to flush, feigning injury, clucking). If there was evidence of at least one chick with a sage-grouse hen, we classified the hen as early brood (chicks &lt;4 weeks of age) or late brood (chicks 4&ndash;8 weeks of age). Monitoring of broods continued for as long as possible, which was usually until the chicks were 3&ndash;8 weeks posthatch, the hen lost her brood, the hen died, or the hen could no longer be located.To quantify avian predators, we used standard distance sampling techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Ralph1">Ralph et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Buckland1">Buckland et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomas1">Thomas et al. 2010</xref>), which entailed counting all avian predators observed during point counts and recording their distance from the observer. Point counts were conducted at random and sage-grouse (nest, early brood, and late brood) locations. Random locations were selected from habitat dominated by sagebrush within 8 km of the leks where sage-grouse were captured. This was intended to quantify avian predator density in habitat available for use by sage-grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref>). Within each year, random locations were &gt;2,000 m apart. Point counts at sage-grouse nests were established when hens had begun incubating; thus, we assumed that we detected raptors and corvids that were present when nests were initiated. For a detailed description of point count methods see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins1">Dinkins (2013)</xref>. All avian predator variables were calculated from the raw count data within effective detection radii (EDR) estimated with DISTANCE version 6.0 release 2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomas1">Thomas et al. 2010</xref>), as specified in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref>. Thus, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Buteo</named-content></italic> spp. hawk, Golden Eagle, Northern Harrier (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Circus cyaneus</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;harrier&rdquo;), kestrel, Black-billed Magpie (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pica hudsonia</named-content></italic>; hereafter &ldquo;magpie&rdquo;), and raven densities were individually calculated within 450 m, 1,000 m, 350 m, 400 m, 300 m, and 600 m, respectively, of each point count location (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref> for further details). We did not include other falcons or owls because they were rarely detected during point counts. Raw densities were standardized by the number of visits to each point count location and were log-transformed.We used ArcMap 10.0 (Esri, Redlands, California, USA) to calculate point count proximity (Euclidean distance) to anthropogenic features that could be used as perch or nest sites by avian predators or could provide food subsidies. We quantified the distance from each point count location to the nearest oil and gas structure (energy well, compressor station, transfer station, refinery, or other energy-extraction-related building), major road, any road type, communication tower, house, or power line. Densities of anthropogenic structures were calculated at four spatial extents (0.27-km, 0.54-km, 1.00-km, and 3.00-km radii) for oil and gas structures (number km<sup>&minus;2</sup>), major roads (km km<sup>&minus;2</sup>), all road types (km km<sup>&minus;2</sup>), houses (number km<sup>&minus;2</sup>), and power lines (km km<sup>&minus;2</sup>). The four spatial extents were derived from previous research on sage-grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran3">Holloran and Anderson 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge2">Aldridge and Boyce 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Carpenter1">Carpenter et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty2">Doherty et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge3">Aldridge et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Hanser1">Hanser et al. 2011</xref>). Ongoing energy development was occurring in half of our sites, which required us to assess the dates that energy-related structures and roads were added or removed from the landscape.In distance calculations, we included only oil and gas structures and roads that existed when each point count was conducted. We obtained information on oil and gas structures, including the date that construction started on the structure and the date when wells were plugged and abandoned (the date that the structure was removed), from the Wyoming Oil and Gas Conservation Commission (WOGCC; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wogcc.state.wy.us" xlink:type="simple">http://wogcc.state.wy.us</ext-link>). We verified the spatial location and existence of older structures with color aerial satellite imagery from summer 2006 and August 2009 obtained from the National Agriculture Imagery Program (NAIP; U.S. Department of Agriculture 2010). Aerial imagery from NAIP is produced by the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) on a 3-yr rotation; thus, we used WOGCC data and on-the-ground GPS units to map energy development that occurred after August 2009.We used 2009 NAIP imagery to digitize the location of major roads, all roads, communication towers, and houses within a 5-km buffer around sites; roads constructed between August 2009 and September 2011 were mapped on the ground with GPS units. Major roads included paved roads, improved gravel roads, and railroads; all roads included major roads and all unimproved four-wheel drive roads. All transmission and distribution power lines within a 5-km buffer around sites were mapped on the ground with GPS units; telephone lines not associated with a power line were included in power-line mapping.Sage-grouse were likely to respond to many different types of anthropogenic structure in a similar manner (e.g., select locations farther away from all tall structures). Thus, we created two anthropogenic structure variables that represented the nearest: (1) distance to an oil and gas structure, communication tower, or house (WCH); and (2) distance to an oil and gas structure, communication tower, house, or power line (ANTH). This was in addition to distances from point count locations to individual types of anthropogenic structures.Similarly to anthropogenic feature calculations, we used ArcMap 10.0 to calculate the distance from every point count location to landscape attributes including forested (deciduous or coniferous stands) and riparian habitats. Tree stands and riparian habitat were identified with Northwest ReGAP landcover data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gap.uidaho.edu/index.php/nw-gap/land-cover" xlink:type="simple">http://gap.uidaho.edu/index.php/nw-gap/land-cover</ext-link>) from 2011, and verified with NAIP imagery from 2009. At our sites, riparian habitat from ReGAP consisted of mesic areas with patchy shrubs. In addition to distance variables, we calculated a normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI) and the proportion of forested, riparian, and big sagebrush habitats around all point count locations. We extracted NDVI values that were generated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge3">Aldridge et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Hanser1">Hanser et al. (2011)</xref> for the Wyoming Basins Ecoregion, which were created from 250 m MODIS (Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer) satellite imagery (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/</ext-link>) between May and August of 2004. These NDVI values represent relative NDVI among point count locations during the sage-grouse nesting and brood-rearing season. Topography with greater surface roughness had the potential to create topographic structures (e.g., hilltops, knolls, and cliff edges) that could provide vantage points for avian predators. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Riley1">Riley et al. (1999)</xref> created a topographic ruggedness index (TRI) to describe the roughness of landscapes, quantified as the difference in elevation among adjacent pixels of a digital elevation map averaged over a user-defined area. For every point count location, we used ArcMap 10.0 to extract TRI values generated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge3">Aldridge et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Hanser1">Hanser et al. (2011)</xref>. Proportion of habitat (big sagebrush, forested, and riparian), NDVI, and TRI variables were constructed at four spatial extents (0.23-km<sup>2</sup>, 0.92-km<sup>2</sup>, 3.14-km<sup>2</sup>, and 28.26-km<sup>2</sup>) by using a moving window analysis within 0.27-km, 0.54-km, 1.00-km, and 3.00-km radii, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge3">Aldridge et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Hanser1">Hanser et al. 2011</xref>).We fit multinomial logistic regression models with maximum likelihood using function multinom in package nnet version 7.3&ndash;4 in R (R 2.14.2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>) to evaluate habitat selection of nesting and brood-rearing sage-grouse hens. In addition to our full analysis, we conducted the same analysis with the exclusion of anthropogenic features on a subset of random and sage-grouse locations that were at least 3 km away from oil and gas structures, communication towers, power lines, rural houses, and major roads. This analysis was intended to verify whether sage-grouse response to avian predators was consistent regardless of influences from anthropogenic structures. Multinomial logistic regression models have been used to model habitat selection of wildlife species with &gt;2 response categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-McCracken1">McCracken et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-McDonald1">McDonald et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Banuelos1">Ba&ntilde;uelos et al. 2008</xref>). We categorized point count locations into four response categories: (1) random, (2) sage-grouse nest, (3) early brood, and (4) late brood. Random point counts were kept in a single category across the summer, because we did not detect differences in avian densities between the first and second half of summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins1">Dinkins 2013</xref>); thus, modeling with multinomial logistic regression was more efficient as we could compare all response categories simultaneously rather than having to conduct a series of binomial regressions. Multinomial logistic regression uses one category as the reference for comparisons with all other categories; thus, each analysis can directly compare all categories among themselves by iteratively changing the reference category in the same model. To compare sage-grouse habitat selection with available sagebrush habitat (random locations), we made comparisons of sage-grouse locations with random locations by coding random locations as the reference category. We then alternated nest and early-brood location as the reference category to directly compare among sage-grouse locations.Modeling of sage-grouse habitat selection was conducted using an information-theoretic approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Anderson1">Anderson 2008</xref>). We compared models with Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>) and Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>) using function aictab in package AICcmodavg version 1.25 in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Mazerolle1">Mazerolle 2012</xref>). We employed sequential AIC<sub>c</sub> modeling of covariate sets (anthropogenic, landscape, and avian predator), which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Arnold1">Arnold (2010)</xref> suggested as an appropriate approach for identifying and ranking the most parsimonious models. Noninformative covariates (85&percnt; confidence intervals &lsqb;CIs&rsqb; of parameter estimates overlapped 0) were eliminated within each covariate set before comparing top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected models among covariate sets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). We classified models within 2 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the null model as being noncompetitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>); thus, any model within 2 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the null was omitted from further analyses.The best spatial extent and functional form of variables describing the effects of landscape attributes and anthropogenic features on habitat selection by sage-grouse were determined through AIC<sub>c</sub> prior to sequential modeling of covariate sets (Step 1). We did not include WCH or ANTH with any anthropogenic structure variable that was used to create WCH or ANTH. For all distance decay functions, we chose the best decay distance (0.25 km, 0.50 km, and 1.00 km) for each distance variable by comparing AIC<sub>c</sub> values. We compared models with individual density, proportion, and TRI variables measured at 0.27-km, 0.54-km, 1.00-km, and 3.00-km radii using AIC<sub>c</sub> to choose the best spatial extent for each of those variable groups to be used in the anthropogenic and landscape covariate sets. Density and proportion variables were compared to the analogous proximity variables with AIC<sub>c</sub>, and the best functional form of each variable was used in all further modeling (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref>).Variables selected in Step 1 of our modeling process and used in analysis of habitat selection by sage-grouse hens at nest (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 340), early-brood (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 331), and late-brood (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 121) locations at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. Subscripts indicate best spatial extent or distance decay (km), and descriptions indicate best functional form (see Results).In Step 2, anthropogenic and landscape covariate sets were evaluated sequentially to identify the variables to be included in the best models for each of those covariate sets (i.e. models within 2 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the top model within each covariate set). As the final modeling step (Step 3), we compared all top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected models from anthropogenic and landscape covariate sets and the best avian predator model from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref> among each other and as additive models. The avian predator model included three avian predator variables (small, medium, and large avian predators), and three of the four years of data were from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref>. The three avian predator variables were constructed by aggregating raw avian predator densities calculated within species-specific EDRs based on the size of the avian predator, which resulted in small (magpie and kestrel), medium (<italic>Buteo</italic> hawk, harrier, and raven), and large (Golden Eagle) avian predator variables. This avian predator model was shown by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref> to describe potential sage-grouse avoidance of avian predators better than models based on: individual species; distinguishing among different avian predator foraging styles; or avian predator threat to sage-grouse hens, nests, or broods. We based our inference on models within 2 AIC<sub>c</sub> of the top selected model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We prevented multicollinearity by not including in any model any two variables that covaried (<italic>r</italic> &gt;0.65) as determined with a Pearson's correlation matrix; thus, we eliminated one covarying variable from further analysis by retaining the variable that made the most biological sense.Although we could not test for spatial autocorrelation in multinomial logistic regressions, avian predator densities derived from distance-sampling techniques were robust to lack of independence of observation locations because distance sampling was set up to be a snapshot in time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomas1">Thomas et al. 2010</xref>). Our avian predator sampling was designed to count the greatest proportion of the actual number of avian predators within a site each week while not counting the same avian predator more than once per week, as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Ralph1">Ralph et al. (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomas1">Thomas et al. (2010)</xref>. Conducting all point counts within a site in one day reduced the possibility of double-counting individual avian predators during that week's visit. Counting the same individual avian predator during different weeks, regardless of the particular point count location, was properly scaled by accounting for survey effort. We replicated point counts in multiple weeks to increase detection of avian predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomas1">Thomas et al. 2010</xref>). When evaluating avian predator densities between sage-grouse and random locations, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref> accounted for spatial autocorrelation in generalized linear mixed models; however, accounting for spatial autocorrelation did not significantly change the coefficient values of their avian predator models. Furthermore, multinomial logistic regression only requires that successive habitat selection choices be independent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Agresti1">Agresti 2007</xref>).We conducted 4,441 point count surveys at 1,452 locations during 2008&ndash;2011, including 340 sage-grouse nest, 331 sage-grouse early-brood, 121 sage-grouse late-brood, and 660 random locations. These locations were compiled from 289 hens with a mean of 1.2 nests per hen, 2.9 early-brood locations per hen, and 3.0 late-brood locations per hen. Brood locations were compiled from 124 separate sage-grouse broods from 114 sage-grouse hens. We counted 196 <italic>Buteo</italic> hawks, 295 Golden Eagles, 77 harriers, 105 kestrels, 143 magpies, and 688 ravens within species-specific EDRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref>), which equated to 248 small, 961 medium, and 295 large avian predators. These counts do not necessarily indicate unique individuals, but rather detections used to quantify density around localized areas. Brood, nest, and random locations aggregated across all years were on average 598.0 m (38.8 m SE), 908.6 m (9.6 m SE), and 1,189 m (25.5 m SE) apart, respectively. Avian predator variables did not covary with any other variables (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.02, variance inflation factor &lsqb;VIF&rsqb; &le; 2.2), indicating no multicollinearity between avian predator variables and anthropogenic or landscape feature variables.During Step 1, our modeling generally suggested that anthropogenic features were influencing sage-grouse habitat selection at a larger spatial extent (3-km radius) than were landscape attributes (&lt;1-km radius; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref>). The best spatial extent for density variables was within 3 km of a point count location. Densities of oil and gas structures (OGSden<sub>3.0</sub>), power lines (POWden<sub>3.0</sub>), and major roads (MRDden<sub>3.0</sub>) fit the data better than raw distance or distance decay functions. The best spatial extents for the proportion of big sagebrush (SAGEpro<sub>1.0</sub>), TRI (TRI<sub>0.54</sub>), and NDVI (NDVI<sub>0.27</sub>) were within 1.00 km, 0.54 km, and 0.27 km, respectively. Distance to rural houses (HOM<sub>1.0</sub>) and riparian habitat (RIP<sub>1.0</sub>) as 1-km distance decay functions fit the data better than Euclidean distance or densities. The effects of HOM<sub>1.0</sub> and RIP<sub>1.0</sub> on sage-grouse selection of nesting and brood locations became negligible beyond approximately 4 km (i.e. 1 km distance decay approaches zero at approximately 4 km away from an object of interest).During Step 2 of sequential modeling, we found that sage-grouse selection of nest and brood locations was partially based on landscape attributes and anthropogenic features (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>). The top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected anthropogenic feature model (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.98) included OGSden<sub>3.0</sub>, POWden<sub>3.0</sub>, MRDden<sub>3.0</sub>, and HOM<sub>1.0</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>). The top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected landscape feature model (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.80) included SAGEpro<sub>1.0</sub>, RIP<sub>1.0</sub>, NDVI<sub>0.27</sub>, and TRI<sub>0.54</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>). During Step 3 of sequential modeling, our analyses indicated that sage-grouse hen selection of nest and brood locations was best described by small, medium, and large avian predator densities (avian predator model) in conjunction with many landscape attributes and anthropogenic features (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 1.00; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t03">Table 3</xref>). This indicates that sage-grouse respond to multiple factors related to habitat quality, including factors related to perceived predation risk (landscape attributes and anthropogenic features) and direct predation risk (avian predator densities).Multinomial logistic regression models comparing landscape-attribute and anthropogenic-feature variables as covariate sets among locations used by sage-grouse (nest: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 340, early-brood: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 331, and late-brood: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 121 locations) and random locations (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 660) at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. <italic>K</italic> is the number of model parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> for variable descriptions.Multinomial logistic regression models comparing anthropogenic and landscape covariate sets (top models from <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Table 2</xref>) and the avian predator model (including small, medium, and large avian predator densities) among locations used by sage-grouse (nest, early-brood, and late-brood locations) and random locations at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. <italic>K</italic> is the number of model parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight.Greater densities of small, medium, and large avian predators were negatively correlated with sage-grouse nest, early-brood, and late-brood locations compared with random locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). Early-brood and late-brood sage-grouse locations had lower avian predator densities than nesting sage-grouse locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t05">Table 5</xref>). Within each reproductive stage, sage-grouse locations had similar negative coefficient values for small and medium avian predators, but exhibited greater negative coefficient values for large avian predators (Golden Eagles) compared with small and medium avian predators (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t05">5</xref>).Parameter estimates with 95&percnt; confidence intervals (LCL and UCL) from top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected multinomial logistic regression models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t03">3</xref>). This analysis compares either nest, early-brood, or late-brood locations used by sage-grouse with random (reference category) locations at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> for variable descriptions.Parameter estimates with 95&percnt; confidence intervals (LCL and UCL) from top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected multinomial logistic regression models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t02">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t03">3</xref>). The reference category was alternated from random to nest or early-brood location to facilitate direct comparison of locations used by sage-grouse at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> for variable descriptions.In general, sage-grouse responded to most anthropogenic features by avoiding them, regardless of the sage-grouse's reproductive stage; however, many of these effects had parameter estimates with 95&percnt; CI that overlapped zero for all reproductive stages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t05">5</xref>). In contrast to the avoidance of other anthropogenic structures, our analyses indicated that early-brood and late-brood sage-grouse were closer to rural houses (HOM<sub>1.0</sub> parameter estimate was positive) compared with random locations and nest locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Tables 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t05">5</xref>). We found that nesting, early-brood, and late-brood sage-grouse were in areas with lower OGSden<sub>3.0</sub> compared with random locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). However, the effect of OGSden<sub>3.0</sub> on sage-grouse habitat use during nesting had a parameter estimate with 95&percnt; CI that overlapped zero (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). Sage-grouse use of habitat was negatively associated with MRDden<sub>3.0</sub> during all reproductive stages, with 95&percnt; CI of parameter estimates overlapping zero for brood locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). Early-brood and late-brood sage-grouse locations had lower POWden<sub>3.0</sub> compared with random locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>).For landscape attribute variables, we found that sage-grouse differed in their response to proximity to riparian habitat (RIP<sub>1.0</sub>) depending on their reproductive stage. Compared with random locations, sage-grouse selected nest locations farther away from riparian habitat (RIP<sub>1.0</sub> parameter estimate was negative), but early-brood sage-grouse neither selected nor avoided habitat based on proximity to riparian habitat, and late-brood sage-grouse selected locations closer to riparian habitat (RIP<sub>1.0</sub> parameter estimate was positive; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). However, both early-brood and late-brood locations were closer to riparian habitat compared with nest locations (RIP<sub>1.0</sub> parameter estimate was positive), and late-brood locations were closer to riparian habitat than early-brood locations (RIP<sub>1.0</sub> parameter estimate was positive; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t05">Table 5</xref>). SAGEpro<sub>1.0</sub> was positively associated with sage-grouse locations during nesting and early brood rearing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). NDVI<sub>0.27</sub> was positively associated with sage-grouse locations at all reproductive stages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>). Sage-grouse during all reproductive stages were located in areas with flatter topography (TRI<sub>0.54</sub> parameter estimates were negative) compared with random locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>).Our analysis that excluded locations within 3 km of anthropogenic structures comprised 2,406 point count surveys at 803 locations during 2008&ndash;2011. This equated to 153 sage-grouse nest locations (45&percnt; of total nest data), 207 sage-grouse early-brood locations (63&percnt; of total early-brood data), 93 sage-grouse late-brood locations (77&percnt; of total late-brood data), and 350 random locations (53&percnt; of total random data). Similar to the full analysis, avian predator variables did not covary with any other variable (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.05, VIF &le; 2.3), indicating no multicollinearity between avian predator variables and anthropogenic or landscape feature variables. The subset analysis illustrated that the pattern of habitat use by sage-grouse was nearly the same as that in our full analysis in relation to avian predator densities and sage-grouse response to landscape attributes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t06">Tables 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t07">7</xref>). Unlike in the full dataset, late-brood sage-grouse did not select for SAGEpro<sub>1.0</sub> or RIP<sub>1.0</sub>; even so, the coefficients had the same positive values as in the full analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t07">Table 7</xref>).Multinomial logistic regression models comparing landscape-attribute variables and then comparing the top model from the landscape covariate set with the avian predator model (small, medium, and large avian predator densities) among locations used by sage-grouse (nest: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 153, early-brood: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 207, and late-brood: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 93 locations) and random locations (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 350) at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011. Sage-grouse and random locations were greater than 3 km from anthropogenic features. <italic>K</italic> is the number of model parameters, &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> is the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criterion adjusted for small sample size, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> for variable descriptions.Parameter estimates with 95&percnt; confidence intervals (LCL and UCL) from top AIC<sub>c</sub>-selected multinomial logistic regression models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t06">Tables 6</xref>). This analysis compares either nest, early-brood, or late-brood locations used by sage-grouse at 12 sites in southern Wyoming, USA, 2008&ndash;2011, with random (reference category) locations. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t01">Table 1</xref> for variable descriptions.Sage-grouse hens used both indirect and direct mechanisms of predator avoidance to select habitat, which may have partially lowered their exposure to predation and nest predation. We did not quantify the effects of olfactory (mammalian) predators on sage-grouse selection of habitat. However, sage-grouse have not been found to hide their nests from olfactory predators at a microhabitat scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Conover1">Conover et al. 2010</xref>). In general, sage-grouse were located in less risky habitat that was farther away from potential perches and had lower densities of small, medium, and large avian predators. This result is largely concordant with the finding of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref>, who included some of the same bird location data but did not include landscape attribute or anthropogenic feature variables. The pattern of lower avian predator densities at sage-grouse locations was consistent between our full analysis and our analysis of locations &gt;3 km away from anthropogenic structures (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t03">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">4</xref> compared with <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t06">Tables 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t07">7</xref>), which provided additional evidence that sage-grouse used direct predator avoidance. We found that sage-grouse locations were best described with models that included multiple habitat variables and avian predator densities. This implies that information on avian predator use of sagebrush habitat, even sagebrush habitat little influenced by anthropogenic structures, could improve understanding of how sage-grouse are distributed in sagebrush habitat.Sage-grouse exhibit high individual (among seasons) and generational site fidelity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Fisher1">Fisher et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran3">Holloran and Anderson 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thompson1">Thompson 2012</xref>), which likely limits their ability to move in response to changing distributions of avian predators. Site fidelity has been suggested to delay nonuse patterns of sage-grouse in response to developing oil and gas fields, with older birds displaying strong fidelity despite low productivity and yearling birds (first nesting season) avoiding new anthropogenic structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran4">Holloran et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Naugle1">Naugle et al. 2011</xref>). Older sage-grouse hens with failed nests in a previous nesting season had lower nest site fidelity compared with hens with successful nests (i.e. eggs hatched), but the average distances between their sequential nests were 512 m and 283 m, respectively, hardly landscape-level movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran3">Holloran and Anderson 2005</xref>). Distances between sequential nests from our study also indicated lower nest-site fidelity for hens with previously failed nests compared with hens with successful nests, especially when stratified by sites with low vs. high raven density (average distance to previously failed nests: 0.66 km &lsqb;0.26 km SE&rsqb; and 1.16 km &lsqb;0.20 km SE&rsqb;, respectively; average distance to previously hatched nests: 0.53 km &lsqb;0.20 km SE&rsqb; and 0.36 km &lsqb;0.08 km SE&rsqb;, respectively; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins1">Dinkins 2013</xref>). The greatest average distance between subsequent nests was for birds with previously failed nests in areas with comparatively higher raven density. Yearling birds seem to adjust spatial location at relatively large spatial extents, whereas older birds changed spatial location at smaller scales.Rather than indirect and direct predator avoidance explaining our results, sage-grouse habitat use patterns could also be explained by areas of relatively greater predation over time leading to low sage-grouse productivity (i.e. sage-grouse disappear from a localized area, resembling nonuse by sage-grouse). It is plausible that our random locations were areas with greater avian predator densities associated with historically lower productivity for sage-grouse. Temporal stability in location of nesting structures for avian predators in sagebrush habitat could generate areas with greater predation risk for sage-grouse. However, stability also correlates with relatively constant spatial habitat use by avian predators, which might allow sage-grouse to directly avoid them. Even small distance adjustments in sequential nest locations have the potential to move a sage-grouse outside of a corvid's or a raptor's home range or use hotspots. Lower nest-site fidelity of sage-grouse illustrates the capacity of sage-grouse to at least partially adjust their use of habitat by moving away from threats after nest failure. Our results indicate that sage-grouse habitat use patterns were likely a remnant of multiple factors. Predator avoidance (indirect and direct mechanisms) and localized disappearance of sage-grouse were unlikely to be mutually exclusive processes shaping habitat use patterns of sage-grouse.Avian predators including <italic>Buteo</italic> hawks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-MacLaren1">MacLaren et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder3">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder1">Schroeder and Baydack 2001</xref>), Golden Eagles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-MacLaren1">MacLaren et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Danvir1">Danvir 2002</xref>), harriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder3">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thirgood1">Thirgood et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Fletcher1">Fletcher et al. 2003</xref>), kestrels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder3">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>), magpies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran2">Holloran and Anderson 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-VanderHaegen1">Vander Haegen et al. 2002</xref>), and ravens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Manzer1">Manzer and Hannon 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Bui1">Bui et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Coates1">Coates and Delehanty 2010</xref>) negatively affect nest success or potentially prey on sage-grouse adults and chicks. One of the responses of prey species to the presence of these predators is direct avoidance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Lima1">Lima 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Evans1">Evans 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Cresswell1">Cresswell 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. 2012</xref>). Similarly to the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dinkins2">Dinkins et al. (2012)</xref>, our analyses indicated that sage-grouse avoided avian predators during all reproductive stages&mdash;nesting, early brood, and late brood&mdash;but at different magnitudes. Our results also suggest that sage-grouse hens have the ability to distinguish among threats to their own survival, their nests, and their offspring.Sage-grouse are a relatively long-lived bird (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Connelly1">Connelly et al. 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Johnson1">Johnson and Braun (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Taylor1">Taylor et al. (2012)</xref> found that adult survival was the most influential demographic parameter on sage-grouse population growth, followed by chick survival and then nest success. Golden Eagles have been identified as the primary predator of adult sage-grouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder3">Schroeder et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Schroeder1">Schroeder and Baydack 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Mezquida1">Mezquida et al. 2006</xref>). Sage-grouse hens avoided Golden Eagles (large avian predators) at greater magnitudes than smaller avian predators within each reproductive stage (i.e. more strongly negative parameter estimates for large avian predators than for small and medium avian predators when comparing sage-grouse locations to random locations; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-t04">Table 4</xref>), suggesting that sage-grouse hens were predominantly concerned with their own survival. Our results also indicated that the magnitudes of avian predator avoidance for predators of all sizes were greater at early-brood and late-brood locations than at nest locations, suggesting that broods moved in a way that reduced predation risk to both adults and chicks.In addition to direct avoidance of avian predators, sage-grouse selected habitat in response to landscape attributes and anthropogenic features. Direct and indirect avoidance of avian predators were not necessarily linked (correlated) from the perspective of a sage-grouse, because indirect cues (perches and areas with food subsidies for predators) were not correlated with the density of any avian predator species (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.02). Similarly to previous research, our analyses confirmed that sage-grouse select locations farther away from landscape attributes that could be used as perches or provide subsidized food resources for predators, including oil and gas structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge1">Aldridge 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran1">Holloran 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Walker1">Walker et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty1">Doherty 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran4">Holloran et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Kirol1">Kirol 2012</xref>) at all reproductive stages, power lines at brood locations, and major roads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Holloran1">Holloran 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge2">Aldridge and Boyce 2007</xref>) and riparian habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty2">Doherty et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dzialak1">Dzialak et al. 2011</xref>) at nest locations. Sage-grouse also chose flatter locations, similarly to findings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Doherty2">Doherty et al. (2010)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dzialak1">Dzialak et al. (2011)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Kirol1">Kirol (2012)</xref>. A greater proportion of big sagebrush and higher NDVI values were positively associated with sage-grouse locations. Greater proportion of sagebrush habitat has been positively correlated with abundance of sagebrush-obligate and associated birds including Brewer's Sparrows, Green-tailed Towhees (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pipilo chlorurus</named-content></italic>), sage-grouse, Sagebrush Sparrows, and Sage Thrashers (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Oreoscoptes montanus</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Knick1">Knick et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Noson1">Noson et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge3">Aldridge et al. 2011</xref>). Sage-grouse population growth and recruitment have also been associated with a greater NDVI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Blomberg1">Blomberg et al. 2012</xref>); however, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Guttery1">Guttery et al. (2013)</xref> did not find a connection between NDVI values and sage-grouse chick survival.Habitat use involves tradeoffs among risks of weather exposure and predation and benefits of food acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Verdolin1">Verdolin 2006</xref>). Similarly to the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dzialak1">Dzialak et al. (2011)</xref>, our results confirmed that sage-grouse have opposing associations with riparian habitat depending on reproductive stage. Sage-grouse were farther away from riparian habitat compared with random locations while nesting, but were closer to it compared with random locations during late brood rearing. Nesting may have occurred away from riparian areas because concealment cover and lower predator abundance was more important than food availability for nesting sage-grouse hens. However, chicks have increasing energetic needs as they grow, and sage-grouse hens typically move broods to riparian areas after early brood rearing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Crawford1">Crawford et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Gregg1">Gregg and Crawford 2009</xref>). Sage-grouse hens also move broods to align with changes in food availability as the breeding season progresses. Riparian habitats provide forbs and invertebrates that meet the energetic demands of growing sage-grouse chicks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Connelly2">Connelly et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge2">Aldridge and Boyce 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Dzialak1">Dzialak et al. 2011</xref>), but riparian habitats have a higher risk of brood failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Aldridge2">Aldridge and Boyce 2007</xref>). Sage-grouse appear to minimize the negative effects of increased predation risk associated with riparian areas directly by avoiding avian predators and indirectly by avoiding riparian habitat during relatively more vulnerable reproductive stages (nest and early brood). Sage-grouse early-brood and late-brood locations were closer to rural houses than random and nest locations, which may be explained by the distribution of rural houses in more productive sagebrush habitat. This is speculative and deserves more research. If rural houses are in better habitat for brood foraging, sage-grouse movements to these areas may show similar patterns as movements to riparian habitat.A prey species' ability to predict and avoid risky habitat increases survival and reproductive success, but the ability to directly avoid predators is more beneficial than avoiding indirect cues of predation risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Thomson1">Thomson et al. 2006</xref>). Both mechanisms presumably achieve reduced predation rates; however, there may be other population-limiting effects as a result of indirect and direct predator avoidance, such as reduced foraging ability of prey species in areas of lower habitat quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Lima1">Lima 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Evans1">Evans 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-116-4-629-Cresswell1">Cresswell 2008</xref>). High densities of avian predators and close proximity to landscape attributes and anthropogenic features&mdash;specifically riparian habitat, rugged topography, oil and gas infrastructure, power lines, and major roads&mdash;are likely to result in reduced adult survival and higher predation of sage-grouse eggs and chicks. Sage-grouse use of habitat was negatively associated with avian predator densities, with quality sage-grouse habitat presumably having lower densities of small, medium, and large avian predators. Increased avian predator abundance may induce changes in sage-grouse behavior associated with habitat usage. Thus, human manipulation of habitat that promotes increased densities of avian predators may limit sage-grouse populations, because even habitat that has high-quality cover and forage may become functionally unavailable to sage-grouse as avian predator densities increase.Research funding was provided by the Anadarko Petroleum Corporation, Jack H. Berryman Institute, Lincoln County Predator Management Board, Predatory Animal District of Sweetwater County, School of Energy Resources at the University of Wyoming, South Central and Southwest Wyoming Sage-grouse Local Working Groups, Utah Agricultural Experiment Station (Utah State University, publication number 8718), Uinta County Predator Management Board, Wyoming Animal Damage Management Board, and Wyoming Game and Fish Department. We greatly appreciate the logistical support provided by N. Tratnik, T. Christiansen, M. Zornes, N. Hymas, T. Clayson, M. Holloran, D. Oles, L. Oles, F. Blomquist, C. Morton, L. McCarthy, C. Powell, R. Etzelmiller, M. Murry, and many others. We thank our many field technicians, who are too numerous to name. We would also like to give a special thanks to the cooperation of the many landowners throughout southwestern and south-central Wyoming for allowing access to private lands.