Thank You to the Reviewers of the 2015 <italic>Auk</italic>, Volume 132Peer review, honest and careful, is the cornerstone of modern scientific publishing, and essential to the maintenance of high standards in a journal. The efforts of reviewers are critical and yet unpaid, and so in the name of all of us at <italic>The Auk: Ornithological Advances</italic>, I take the opportunity to thank all of you who contributed reviews while Volume 132 was in preparation (reviews completed between July 2014 and June 2015). Individuals with an asterisk next to their name reviewed two or three manuscripts.<italic>The Auk: Ornithological Advances</italic> is also grateful for the work of our two dedicated Editors, our busy Associate Editors, and the In Memoriam, Book Reviews, and 100 Years Ago Editors, and the expert editorial team members of the Central Ornithology Publication Office (COPO) whose work made the another successful year of <italic>The Auk</italic> possible.Stefan AbrahamczykCaglar AkcayRobert Allen Aldredge&ast;Courtney AmundsonMichael J. AnteauPeter ArceseDaniel Robert Ardia&ast;Wayne J. Arendt&ast;Ian J. AuspreySuzanne H. AustinJulian AveryFranz BairleinJohn BaldwinMichael J. BaldwinSusan BalengerChristophe BarbraudFrederick Keith Barker&ast;Julia BarskeDaniel BartonShane BaylisRobert C. BeasonMichelle Lee BeckSteven BeissingerMarc BelisleJoanne BennettMorgan Benowitz-Fredericks&ast;Thomas J. BensonBrett BenzDouglas F. BertramAdam BetuelClotide BiardTim BilloJohn G. BlakeJessica BloisPeter T. Boag&ast;Gil BohrerVeronica B&oacute;konyEric K. BollingerRachel T. BolusAlexander BondDavid N. BonterJelle BoonekampCarlos A. BosqueKimberly S. BostwickRauri C. K. BowieJames V. BriskieRobb T. BrumfieldJoseph Burton BuchananMariana BulgarellaEdward H. Burtt, Jr.&ast;Mike ButlerWilliam ButtemerAlaine F. Camfield&ast;Ken CampbellDaniela Campobello&ast;Renee Carleton&ast;Matthew D. CarlingNikita CartwrightNikita ChernetsovEmily Beth Cohen&ast;John L. ConferPeter G. ConnorsSergio CordobaStephane CornetJosselin CornuaultWilliam Andrew CoxJoel CracraftRoslyn DakinSelvino de KortLiesbeth de NeveVanessa De PietriDenis Charles Deeming&ast;Elizabeth P. DerryberryAndr&eacute; DesrochersDavid DesRochers&ast;Andre DhondtRobert H. DiehlColleen T. DownsAdrienne DuboisDavid C. DuffyCamille DuvalEmily H. DuVal&ast;Jessica EberhardSteve EmlenR. Todd EngstromMatthew A. Etterson&ast;David EwertJohn FaaborgJuan Antonio FargalloAndrew FarnsworthAlan FeducciaWilliam Feeney&ast;Ricardo FernandesValentina FerrettiDaniel Jared FieldRobert C. FleischerTyler FlockhartJennifer Rhea FooteScott ForbesMercedes S. FosterChristian FothMercival FranciscoMorton FrederiksenLeonard Freed&ast;Benjamin Gardner FreemanLenny GannesTom GardaliJames GilroyAndrew G. GoslerElizabeth A. Gow&ast;David John Green&ast;Greg GretherAndrea Sue GrunstMelanie Guigueno&ast;M. GuilfoyleSarah Laurence Guindre-Parker&ast;Susan M. HaigFrank HailerMargaret I. HallAnne HechtChristopher M. HeckscherCarol HengerTomasz Hetma&nacute;skiKeith A. HobsonWilliam L. HohmanMarcel HonzaJeffrey P. HooverJocelyn HudonMelissa HughesBransilav Igic&ast;David IlesEi-Ichi IzawaHelen James&ast;Jill JankowskiErich Jarvis&ast;Lukas JenniBryan Jennings&ast;Yuexin JiangOscar W. JohnsonJason Jones&ast;Sara Ann KaiserFiliz KaradasTakeshi Kawakami&ast;Bart KempenaersCorinne KendallDylan C. KeslerCoby Klein&ast;Walter KoenigCarmi KorineNiels Krabbe&ast;Alan H. Krakauer&ast;Robert KrausMilos Krist&ast;Michael Kuehn&ast;Daniel LaneTom LangenQuresh LatifAndrew LaughlinChristophe LebigreJin-Won LeeCatherine A. Lindell&ast;Dina LipkindMichael P. LombardoIsabel Lopez-RullMatthew Ian McKim LouderIrby LovettePeter E. LowtherMartin R. LuckSarah Luttrell&ast;Bruce LyonScott MacDougall-Shackleton&ast;Andrew MackMark C. MainwaringPeter MakovickyJames MaleyMark L. Mallory&ast;Albrecht ManegoldR. William MannanJoseph MantheyMelissa MarkKathy MartinPaul Martin&ast;John McCormackJimmy McGuireMarc McKeeSusan B. McRaeTodd J. McWhorterHanneke MeijerEdward MillerAnders P. MollerRobert D. MontgomerieFrank R. MooreIgnacio Thomas MooreEugene S. MortonMichael T. MurphyJulie MustardBeat Naef-DaenzerLaurent NagleEric NolJorge NoriegaGeorge OlahCarl OliverosJuan Francisco Ornelas&ast;Luis Ortiz CatedralKean Alan OtterKeith Pardieck&ast;Juan Luis ParraGail L. PatricelliMichael A. Patten&ast;Kristina PaxtonScott F. PearsonRicardo Pereira&ast;Jonathan Hebbel PerezJavier P&eacute;rez-TrisVitor PiacentiniBradley A. PickensWalter H. Piper&ast;Steven PortugalAbby N. PowellJ. Jordan PriceRichard Prum&ast;Cromwell PurchasePeter Pyle&ast;Dan RaboskyJoel Ralston&ast;Sedano RaulMatt RaynerJuan Carlos ReboredaDustin G. ReichardSophie ReichertPaul ReilloJ. V. RemsenMatthew W. ReudinkAmanda Ridley&ast;Christina Riehl&ast;Douglas RobinsonScott K. RobinsonJeremy T. RockweitNicholas L. RodenhouseVanya Gregor RohwerVictor Rosas-GuerreroJohn RotenberryAlexandre RoulinAlexander RoyanDustin RubensteinViviana Ruiz-Gutierrez&ast;Scott RushAndy RussellPeter SamasJohn R. SauerIsabella B. R. Scheiber&ast;Joshua H. Schmidt&ast;Kimberly SchmidtEllen SchoenerTom Schulenberg&ast;Elizabeth ScordatoJuan Carlos SenarMatthew D. Shawkey&ast;David ShealerAllison J. Shultz&ast;Dave Shutler&ast;Joseph SimonisTheodore R. SimonsBrian Tilston SmithN. Adam Smith&ast;Robert SmithJuan Jose SolerKaren SpencerMark Thomas StanbackJessica Stapley&ast;Caitlin SternWalter Sergio Svagelj&ast;Caz M. TaylorGraeme TaylorScott A. TaylorEthan J. Temeles&ast;Frank R. Thompson III&ast;Ralph TiedemannAnna TiganoChristopher Tonra&ast;Andrew J. TyreRen&eacute; Erwin van DijkEric Antony VanderWerfWouter VansteelantMaren Vitousek&ast;Andrew C. VitzCarol M. VleckMargaret Voss&ast;Jeffrey R. WaltersMing WangIan WarkentinChristopher C. WarrenJason WeirEmily L. Weiser&ast;Kenneth Welch&ast;Caitlin WellsDavid WestmorelandTim White&ast;Bret WhitneyKaren WiebeKevin WinkerChristopher C. Witt&ast;Jared WolfeTianjun XuJenny YorkRebecca YoungErica ZarateTheodore Joseph ZenzalRobert M. Zink&ast;David J. Ziolkowski