Recreation changes the use of a wild landscape by corvidsA new look at the statistical model identificationRecreational disturbance and wildlife populationsCorvid density and nest predation in relation to forest fragmentation: A landscape perspectiveUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionEffects of urbanization on avian community organizationSynchronous eruptions of boreal seed-eating birdsHuman disturbance and nesting success of Common Eiders: Interaction between visitors and gullsRodents as nest predators: Influences on predatory behavior and consequences to nesting birdsResponse of passerine birds to forest edge in coast redwood forest fragmentsCommon Raven activity in relation to land use in western Wyoming: Implications for Greater Sage-Grouse reproductive successEffects of ecotourists on bird behavior at Loxahatchee National Wildlife Refuge, FloridaCommon Raven occurrence in relation to transmission line corridors transiting human-altered sagebrush steppeDistribution and causation of species endangerment in the United StatesIrruptions of the Clark's Nutcracker in CaliforniaThe 1961 irruption of the Clark's Nutcracker in CaliforniaDistribution of specialist and generalist species along spatial gradients of habitat disturbance and fragmentationRelative importance of habitat quality, structure, and spatial pattern to birds in urbanizing environmentsNoise pollution changes avian communities and species interactionsThe forest communities of Mount Rainier National ParkBird tolerance to human intrusion in Wyoming montane forestsDoes repeated human intrusion alter use of wildland sites by red squirrels? Multiyear experimental evidenceRepeated human intrusion and the potential for nest predation by Gray JaysEffects of exurban development on biodiversity: Patterns, mechanisms, and research needsEvidence of edge species attraction to nature trails within deciduous forestBird disturbance: Improving the quality and utility of disturbance researchDevelopment of a 2001 national landcover database for the United StatesThe impact of nature-based tourism on bird communities: A case study in Pallas-Yll&auml;stunturi National ParkThe central role of Clark's Nutcracker in the dispersal and establishment of whitebark pineA nest predator's view of a managed forest: Gray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>) movement patterns in response to forest edgesNut caching by Blue Jays (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta cristata</named-content></italic> L.): Implications for tree demographyWhitebark Pine decline: Infection, mortality, and population trendsHousing developments in rural New England: Effects on forest birdsFactors that influence wildlife responses to recreationistsWildlife responses to recreationistsResponses of raven and Red-tailed Hawk populations to linear right-of-waysCommon Ravens and number and type of linear rights-of-waySpatial autocorrelation: Trouble or new paradigm?Seasonal differences in space use by Clark's Nutcrackers in the Cascade rangeCorvid survey techniques and the relationship between corvid relative abundance and nest predationNest predation in forest birds: Influence of predator type and predator's habitat qualityNest predation and nest sites: New perspectives on old patternsRelating resources to a probabilistic measure of space use: Forest fragments and Steller's JaysCorvid response to human settlements and campgrounds: Causes, consequences, and challenges for conservationUnderstanding the effects of forest management on avian speciesThe effects of forest fragmentation on avian nest predationCorvids feeding on carrionInvasive pathogen threatens bird&ndash;pine mutualism: Implications for sustaining a high-elevation ecosystemInfluence of recreational trails on breeding bird communitiesWildlife responses to pedestrians and dogsModeling patch occupancy by forest rodents: Incorporating detectability and spatial autocorrelation with hierarchically structured dataResponses of American crow populations to campgrounds in remote native forest landscapesImpacts of picnic areas on bird assemblages and nest predation activity within Australian eucalypt forestsEffects of forest fragmentation on populations of the Marbled MurreletDoes repeated human intrusion cause cumulative declines in avian richness and abundance?Landbird counting techniques: Current practices and an alternativeEffect of investigator disturbance on the breeding success of the Black-legged KittiwakeSpace use by Common Ravens in Marbled Murrelet nesting habitat in northern CaliforniaNest predation and avian species diversity in northwestern forest understoryWhitebark pine and white pine blister rust in the Rocky Mountains of Canada and northern MontanaAssessing the effects of human activities on wildlifeTourism, mountain huts and distribution of corvids in the Bavarian Alps, GermanyGray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>)Dispersal of whitebark pine seeds by Clark's Nutcracker: A mutualism hypothesisClark's Nutcracker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nucifraga columbiana</named-content></italic>)Blister rust and western forest biodiversity: Ecology, values, and outlook for white pinesTourist impact on Clark's Nutcracker foraging activities in Rocky Mountain National ParkCoadaptations of the Clark's Nutcracker and the pinon pine for efficient seed harvest and dispersalAbundance, nest sites, and nesting success of Steller's Jays along a gradient of urbanization in western WashingtonIs nest predation by Steller's Jays (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta stelleri</named-content></italic>) incidental or the result of a specialized search strategy?Differences in space use by Common Ravens in relation to sex, breeding status, and kinshipAs urban areas have grown in population, use of nearby natural areas for outdoor recreation has also increased, potentially influencing bird distribution in landscapes managed for conservation. Members of the family Corvidae (crows, ravens, jays, and magpies) have strong interactions with humans and may be directly affected by recreation in wild landscapes. In Mount Rainier National Park, we evaluated the effects of vegetation, visitor use, and the availability of human-subsidized food on the use of landscape features by 4 corvid species: Steller's Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta stelleri</named-content></italic>), Gray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>), Common Raven (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>), and Clark's Nutcracker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nucifraga columbiana</named-content></italic>). We conducted &gt;1,400 point counts across areas that varied in habitat and in the degree of human recreational impact. We calculated predicted occupancy values while allowing for variation in detection probability. In addition to species-specific suites of vegetation and landscape variables, we found that patterns of human recreation, such as visitor use, food subsidy, and amount of road edge, were also significant in explaining corvid distribution. The number of visitors present during point counts was positively associated with Steller's Jay and Clark's Nutcracker use. Common Ravens used areas with fewer people but with a high density of road edge. Gray Jays, Common Ravens, and Clark's Nutcrackers were each more likely to use sites with anthropogenic food subsidy than sites without subsidies. These changes in landscape use may affect the performance of ecosystem services by corvids and could serve as useful and easily measured bioindicators of the impacts of recreation.A medida que la poblaci&oacute;n de las &aacute;reas urbanas crece, el uso recreativo de las &aacute;reas naturales vecinas tambi&eacute;n crece, influyendo potencialmente la distribuci&oacute;n de las aves en los paisajes manejados para la conservaci&oacute;n. Los miembros de la Familia Corvidae tienen interacciones intensas con los humanos y pueden ser afectados directamente por las actividades recreativas en los paisajes silvestres. En el Parque Nacional Mount Rainier, evaluamos los efectos de la vegetaci&oacute;n, el uso de los visitantes y la disponibilidad de alimentos subsidiados por los humanos sobre el uso de los rasgos del paisaje por parte de 4 especies de c&oacute;rvidos: <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta stelleri</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nucifraga columbiana</named-content></italic>. Realizamos m&aacute;s de 1,400 conteos por punto en &aacute;reas con distintos h&aacute;bitats y nivel de impacto humano recreativo y calculamos los valores predictivos de ocupaci&oacute;n con distintos niveles de probabilidad de detecci&oacute;n. Adem&aacute;s de series de vegetaci&oacute;n y variables de paisaje espec&iacute;ficos para cada especie, encontramos que los patrones de recreaci&oacute;n humana, como el uso de los visitantes, el alimento subsidiado y la cantidad de borde de caminos, tambi&eacute;n afectaron significativamente la distribuci&oacute;n de los c&oacute;rvidos. El n&uacute;mero de visitantes presentes durante los conteos por punto estuvo asociado positivamente con el uso por parte de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. stelleri</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">N. columbiana</named-content></italic>. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. corax</named-content></italic> us&oacute; &aacute;reas con menos cantidad de gente pero con una alta densidad de bordes de camino. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">P. canadensis</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">C. corax</named-content></italic> y <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">N. columbiana</named-content></italic> presentaron una mayor probabilidad de uso de sitios con alimentos humanos subsidiados que sitios sin subsidios. Estos cambios en el uso del paisaje pueden afectar el desempe&ntilde;o de los servicios ecosist&eacute;micos por parte de los c&oacute;rvidos y pueden servir como bio-indicadores &uacute;tiles y f&aacute;cilmente medibles de los impactos de la recreaci&oacute;n.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> c&oacute;rvidos, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta stelleri</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nucifraga columbiana</named-content></italic>, Parque Nacional Mount Rainier, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>, PRESENCE, recreaci&oacute;n.Recreation, ecotourism, and other nonconsumptive human activities affect native wildlife communities and the ecosystems to which they belong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Edington1">Edington and Edington 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight3">Knight and Gutzwiller 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Liddle1">Liddle 1997</xref>). Human recreation in natural areas (e.g., by outdoor photographers, rock climbers, hikers, and horseback riders) exposes wildlife to direct human disturbance, while the creation of recreational infrastructure (e.g., access roads, bike paths, campgrounds, and picnic areas) affects the composition and pattern of native landscapes. Although many native species of wildlife are negatively affected by human recreation in natural areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Anderson2">Anderson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight2">Knight and Cole 1995b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Czech1">Czech and Krausman 1997</xref>), the magnitude and direction of these impacts may vary by species, animal condition, season, amount of visitation, type of recreation, and visitor behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Kuss1">Kuss et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Liddle1">Liddle 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Steidl1">Steidl and Powell 2006</xref>). Although localized responses of wildlife, both positive and negative, to recreation are well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Burger1">Burger and Gochfeld 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Gutzwiller1">Gutzwiller et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Gutzwiller3">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>), population-level responses over broad spatial scales to patterns of human recreation have not been evaluated.Avian communities may be especially sensitive to nonconsumptive wildland recreation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Anderson2">Anderson 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight2">Knight and Cole 1995b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Miller1">Miller et al. 1998</xref>). The repeated presence of humans in the environment (e.g., hikers along a trail) may affect avian richness and abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Riffell1">Riffell et al. 1996</xref>). Recreation may decrease bird species diversity and skew density in favor of a few species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Beissinger1">Beissinger and Osborne 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hansen1">Hansen et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Devictor1">Devictor et al. 2008</xref>) by affecting avian fecundity and survivorship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Miller2">Miller et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Bolduc1">Bolduc and Guillemette 2003</xref>). Nesting birds in recreational areas may suffer increased nest desertion, decreased hatching success, reduced parental attendance at the nest, increased foraging effort, or increased nest parasitism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hickman1">Hickman 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Burger1">Burger and Gochfeld 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Miller1">Miller et al. 1998</xref>). Additionally, there may be an increase in egg and chick predation (the primary cause of nest failure in songbirds; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Martin2">Martin 1993</xref>) due to the attraction of mammalian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Bradley1">Bradley and Marzluff 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Martin1">Martin and Joron 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Gutzwiller2">Gutzwiller and Riffell 2008</xref>) and avian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Gutzwiller3">Gutzwiller et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Piper1">Piper and Catterall 2006</xref>) predators. Alternatively, human disturbance of some landscapes may directly deter predators or confound predatory behavior and result in inflated nest success for more tolerant avian species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Sandvik1">Sandvik and Barrett 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Francis1">Francis et al. 2009</xref>).The vulnerability of particular species to impacts of recreation such as nest desertion or increased predation is likely to depend on various life history traits as well as their resource requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight1">Knight and Cole 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hill1">Hill et al. 1997</xref>). Bird species that are likely to be negatively affected by an increase in nonconsumptive recreation include those that require specialized resources, ground nesters, rare species, and those that require large contiguous home ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight1">Knight and Cole 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Neatherlin1">Neatherlin and Marzluff 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>). By contrast, human recreation in natural areas may benefit generalist species, such as corvids (birds of the Family Corvidae, including jays, crows, ravens, magpies, and nutcrackers), which are able to adapt to living with humans and are associated with diverse landscapes. Avian predators, including corvids, may benefit from increased visibility and juxtaposition of diverse resources (e.g., edge habitats; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Martin1">Martin and Joron 2003</xref>). Corvids are intelligent generalist-omnivores that are well adapted to human presence, often flourishing in urban areas and in areas of more moderate human presence such as recreation areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff1">Marzluff and Angell 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Huhta1">Huhta and Sulkava 2014</xref>). In recreation areas with anthropogenic food, corvids may maintain smaller home ranges, and populations may increase in both number and density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Gutzwiller3">Gutzwiller et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Storch1">Storch and Leidenberger 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>).Changing corvid communities may also affect important ecosystem functions, including carrion decomposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight4">Knight and Kawashima 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Mason1">Mason and MacDonald 1995</xref>), seed dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-VanderWall1">Vander Wall and Balda 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Tomback4">Tomback and Taylor 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Johnson1">Johnson et al. 1997</xref>), and nest predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Andren1">Andr&eacute;n 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff5">Marzluff and Restani 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Ibarzabal1">Ibarzabal and Desrochers 2004</xref>). Increasing the spatial perspective on the response of corvids to human recreation may increase our understanding of recreation's effect on ecosystem processes and afford managers the information they need to achieve a balance between the provision of recreational opportunities and the resulting positive and negative influences on the native species, landscapes, and the performance of ecosystem functions.Although corvids are already known to be highly associated with humans and with man-made habitat features on the landscape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Neatherlin1">Neatherlin and Marzluff 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff1">Marzluff and Angell 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Huhta1">Huhta and Sulkava 2014</xref>), no research has explicitly investigated the effects of food subsidy on the distribution patterns of corvids and their use of landscape habitat features in wildland ecosystems. We evaluated the impact of anthropogenic food subsidy and other aspects of human recreation on the distribution patterns and landscape-scale habitat use of 4 corvid species in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA: Steller's Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cyanocitta stelleri</named-content></italic>), Gray Jay (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Perisoreus canadensis</named-content></italic>), Common Raven (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus corax</named-content></italic>), and Clark's Nutcracker (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Nucifraga columbiana</named-content></italic>).We expected corvid presence to increase near areas of high visitor use (e.g., visitor centers, picnic areas, and drive-up campgrounds) and with food subsidy. Although we expected the provision of anthropogenic food subsidy to be important in explaining landscape-scale distribution patterns of all 4 corvid species, we suspected that this relationship might be most apparent for species whose typical habitat requirements commonly occur in areas of relatively low human impact (e.g., high elevations). The habitat preferences of Steller's Jays naturally coincide with areas of relatively high human impact in the park (i.e. low-elevation forests with lots of edge; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Vigallon1">Vigallon and Marzluff 2005a</xref>), and we predicted that patterns of Steller's Jay use might best be explained by a model including both natural and human-influenced landscape features, such as edge, campgrounds, or park zones restricted to day use. Gray Jays tend to use higher-elevation contiguous forests away from most human-affected landscape features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Luginbuhl1">Luginbuhl et al. 2001</xref>), and we predicted that a model including natural landscape features and food availability would best explain this species' distribution patterns. By contrast, we predicted that recreational landscape features (particularly roads; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight5">Knight et al. 1995</xref>) and anthropogenic food availability would be most important in explaining patterns of Common Raven distribution. We suspected that vegetation characteristics, most notably the presence of whitebark pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus albicaulis</named-content></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hutchins1">Hutchins and Lanner 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Tomback1">Tomback 1982</xref>), would explain the distribution patterns of Clark's Nutcrackers. However, food subsidy may draw this species farther from pine stands to forage, perhaps to lower elevations or to areas of more contiguous vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Tomback4">Tomback and Taylor 1987</xref>).We surveyed corvids throughout Mount Rainier National Park (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-f01">Figure 1</xref>), a 95,354-ha reserve on a 4,392-m volcanic peak located on the west side of the Cascade Range, ~100 km southeast of Seattle in southwestern Washington. The park is 97&percnt; designated wilderness (Public Law 100&ndash;668). It has long, cool, wet winters and relatively warm, dry summers. Vegetation and habitat features vary widely throughout the park, due to the combined effects of the steep elevation gradient and precipitation levels that change with elevation and the east&ndash;west rain-shadow effect. Elevations below 1,000 m are characterized by mature forests dominated by Douglas-fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pseudotsuga menziesii</named-content></italic>), western redcedar (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Thuja plicata</named-content></italic>), and western hemlock (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tsuga heterophylla</named-content></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Franklin1">Franklin et al. 1988</xref>). Mixed forests of western white pine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Pinus monticola</named-content></italic>), western hemlock, and Pacific silver fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Abies amabilis</named-content></italic>) are found at midlevel elevations between 1,000 and 1,500 m. Relatively open mixed forests and subalpine meadows characterize elevations from 1,500 to 2,000 m, where dominant tree species include subalpine fir (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Abies lasiocarpa</named-content></italic>), mountain hemlock (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Tsuga mertensiana</named-content></italic>), Alaska cedar (<italic>Callitropsis nootkatensis</italic>), and whitebark pine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hamann1">Hamann 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Henderson1">Henderson 1974</xref>). Subalpine meadow vegetation may include heather species (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Cassiope</named-content></italic> sp. or <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Phyllodoce</named-content></italic> sp.), huckleberry (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Vaccinium</named-content></italic> sp.), subalpine lupine (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Lupinus arcticus</named-content></italic> ssp. <italic>subalpinus</italic>), false hellebore (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Veratrum viride</named-content></italic>), sedges, alpine aster (<italic>Aster alpinus</italic>), paintbrush (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Castilleja</named-content></italic> sp.), western anemone (<italic>Anemone occidentalis</italic>), or fescues (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Festuca</named-content></italic> sp.). Above 2,000 m is an alpine zone covered mostly by heather communities, snow, glaciers, rock outcrops, and talus fields (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Hamann1">Hamann 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Edwards1">Edwards 1980</xref>). In total, ~58&percnt; of the park is forested, ~23&percnt; is subalpine, and the remainder is alpine.Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, with locations of our corvid surveys. Open circles are sites that were surveyed only in 2009. White circles with black centers were surveyed only in 2010. Black circles with white centers are sites that were surveyed during both years. Roads are indicated by double lines and trails by dashed lines. Shading represents 5 landcover types, from white to darkest gray: open water&ndash;glacier, forest, meadow&ndash;shrub, barren rock, and stands of whitebark pine.The wide variety of plant communities found within Mount Rainier National Park provides numerous recreational opportunities, from picnicking to alpine climbing. During the study period, the park had &gt;2 million visitors each year (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nps.gov/mora" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nps.gov/mora</ext-link>). The park maintains 4 visitor centers, 3 wilderness information centers, 4 drive-up campgrounds, 41 hike-in campgrounds, and &gt;400 km of trail.Incorporating a variety of vegetation types, recreational impacts, and park management uses, we surveyed 168 sites for corvid presence throughout Mount Rainier National Park during the summer seasons (mid-June through late September) of 2009 and 2010. On Mount Rainier, heavy snow covered most of our survey sites during the rest of the year, and summer was the only season when many of our sites were accessible. We surveyed a total of 168 sites, including 113 sites sampled in 2009, 114 sampled in 2010, and 59 sampled in both survey seasons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-f01">Figure 1</xref>). During each year, we visited survey sites between 2 and 10 times, totaling 639 visits in 2009 and 774 visits in 2010. Although the number of visits to each site ranged from 2 to 18 across both seasons, the analysis program PRESENCE (we used version 2.4) allows unequal survey effort (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>; see Acknowledgments). Occupancy and detectability modeling in PRESENCE is robust to missing observations, and an equal sampling effort across all sites is not required (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). Most sites (84&percnt;) received &ge;6 visits (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 141). Although we made efforts to visit sites in each of 3 periods within the season&mdash;early (mid-June through mid-July), middle (mid-July through mid-August), and late (mid-August through late September)&mdash;whenever possible, visits were highly constrained by snow conditions (higher elevations in the park are often snow-covered through late July). Given the specific conditions for each site, however, we attempted to make visits at varying times throughout the accessible, snow-free portion of the season to minimize within-season differences in detectability.We chose survey locations that reflected a variety of human impacts and recreational intensities. Site selection was logistically constrained by snow level and by physical accessibility. It is possible that our results will have limited applicability to high-elevation sites, which may be used increasingly as temperatures rise and snowfall declines in response to climate change. For sites accessible by vehicle, we compiled lists of sites with and without food subsidy (defined by the presence or absence of at least 1 campsite, trash can, or picnic table) after analyzing park maps and consulting with park personnel, and we randomly chose a selection from each list. For hike-in-only sites, we randomly selected hikes from a list comprising all 1- or 2-day hikes, excluding those that were snow-covered during much of the field season or required the use of specialty equipment (e.g., crampons or ice axes). We then placed survey sites along each of the trails and at each backcountry campground encountered along the hike. In total, we included 35 sites accessible by car and 133 that were hike-in-only; 31 sites had anthropogenic food subsidies, and 137 did not have food available. Approximately half of vehicle-accessible sites had food subsidy available (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 17). Most hike-in sites did not have human-subsidized food available (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 119), but food subsidy was available at hike-in campgrounds (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 14).We intended to survey sites in areas of high human use and areas that provided human food subsidy to capture corvid presence in human-altered landscapes. Therefore, at campgrounds, administrative areas, and visitor centers, survey sites were located at the approximate center of the human use area. Likewise, along roads, we conducted point counts in pullouts or parking areas. We conducted surveys along low-human-use trail corridors to measure corvid presence and abundance in areas minimally affected by human recreational intrusion on otherwise natural landscapes. Additionally, linearity of the visual field can bias detectability during surveys, and the forested trail corridors were characterized by linear vegetation. Thus, to remove the influence of the trail corridor on visual corvid detections, we surveyed forested trail sites at a random distance (10&ndash;50 m) and right-angle direction off the trail. Observers remained within sight of the trail corridor, however, so that counts of visitors were not influenced. We separated all survey sites by &ge;500 m and assumed that sites were independent (i.e. corvids detected at a site were not detected at any other site).During each visit to a survey site, we conducted one 20-min point count, during which we recorded all corvids detected visually or audibly, following standard point-count techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Ralph1">Ralph et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Ralph2">1995</xref>). We conducted surveys on days with only light wind (&lt;19 kph) and no more than light precipitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-NationalOceanicandAtmosphericAdministration1">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration 1995</xref>), between sunrise and early afternoon (the time of day when corvids are most active; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Luginbuhl1">Luginbuhl et al. 2001</xref>). Across 2 field seasons, 3 observers conducted all corvid surveys and each observer surveyed the majority of the sites at least once.Variable field conditions during wildlife surveys can create differences in detectability between both survey sites and point counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Rosenstock1">Rosenstock et al. 2002</xref>, and references therein). Bird, and specifically corvid, detection may vary by wind, ambient noise, precipitation, time after sunrise, and light intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Anderson1">Anderson and Ohmart 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Luginbuhl1">Luginbuhl et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Donnelly1">Donnelly and Marzluff 2006</xref>). Therefore, during each point count, we noted the observer and recorded the percentage of cloud cover, the level of noise and wind, the presence of precipitation, and the start time (used to calculate the time after sunrise); at each survey site, we also measured canopy cover using a moosehorn and noted the structure of the surrounding forest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>).Point-count, site, and landscape-scale variables included in analyses of detection and habitat use by 4 corvid species in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010.To help assess the relationship between corvid distribution and habitat use, we measured numerous recreation and landscape variables during each of our surveys. We counted the number of visitors observed within 100 m of the survey site during each point count (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>); we did not count vehicles. We measured the elevation of each survey site and classified each site by zone type, a classification of the type of visitor use (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>) based on designations outlined in Mount Rainier National Park's 2001 General Management Plan. Using ArcGIS version 9.3.0 (ESRI, Redlands, California, USA), we measured the distance from each survey site to the nearest campground and the nearest stand of whitebark pine (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). We used the distance to whitebark pine only in the analyses of Clark's Nutcracker observations. We used the NPScape 2001 landcover dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Homer1">Homer et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-NationalParkService1">National Park Service 2010</xref>), which classified landcover in Mount Rainier National Park by 30-m cells, to represent the landcover patterns surrounding each survey site within buffer areas of 2-km and 5-km radii. Corvid home-range sizes may vary across habitats and between wild and developed areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>), and these buffer areas encompass the average home-range sizes of the targeted corvid species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Lorenz1">Lorenz and Sullivan 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Strickland1">Strickland and Ouellet 2011</xref>). Using FRAGSTATS version 3.3 (see Acknowledgments) and the landcover dataset, we calculated landscape metrics within each buffer area for each survey site, including contrast-weighted edge density, patch richness, percent forest, length of road edge, Shannon's diversity index, and contagion. We chose these metrics because they reflect the amount of edge and degree of fragmentation on the landscape, both known to be important characteristics in predicting corvid presence and abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff4">Marzluff et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff2">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Vigallon2">Vigallon and Marzluff 2005b</xref>). For contrast-weighted edge density, edges between forest and developed land received a weight of 1.0, edges between forest and meadow&ndash;shrub received a weight of 0.5, and all other landcover edges received a zero weight. Shannon's diversity index, contagion, and percent forest were highly correlated when considering both radii (2 km: <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.91, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; 5 km: <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.93, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001); thus, we included only contrast-weighted edge density, patch richness, percent forest, and length of road edge in our final analyses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). We used length of road edge only in the analyses of Common Raven observations.We used PRESENCE to model occupancy, while allowing for varying detectability, and to predict site-specific occupancy values for each corvid species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). Because some birds may disperse between sites, there is a potential lack of closure across our surveys; therefore, we interpret our model results as reflecting corvid use rather than occupancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). We scaled values of some variables to avoid numerical convergence issues with the logit link function in PRESENCE. We converted percent forest and cloud cover to proportions and expressed elevation and distance measurements in kilometers, with the exception of length of road edge, which we scaled to hundreds of kilometers. We divided values for average number of visitors and patch richness by 10. To evaluate variables for multicollinearity, we calculated variance inflation factors using the HH package in R version 3.1.1 (R Core Development Team, Vienna, Austria; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Heiberger1">Heiberger 2015</xref>). We found limited evidence of multicollinearity (no variance inflation factors were &gt;10; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Belsley1">Belsley et al. 1980</xref>) and did not exclude any variables from further analyses.For all PRESENCE analyses, we used Akaike's Information Criterion, corrected for small sample size (AIC<sub>c</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Akaike1">Akaike 1974</xref>), to rank models and identify the most parsimonious model that best explained the data collected for each species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Arnold1">Arnold 2010</xref>). We considered a model to be competitive if its &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> with respect to the top model was &lt;2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Burnham2">2002</xref>). We calculated model weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>) and evidence ratios, comparing the most parsimonious model with others in each dataset. We used odds ratios (ORs) to examine the effect of beta parameters in competitive models. We calculated ORs using the equation OR &equals; <italic>e</italic><sup>&beta;</sup>, and 95&percnt; confidence intervals (CIs) using the equation CI &equals; <italic>e</italic><sup>&beta; &plusmn; 2&ast;SE&beta;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). For continuous variables, ORs &gt;1 indicate a positive association between corvid use and covariate value, and ORs &lt;1 indicate a negative association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). When a categorical covariate has an OR between zero and 1, birds are less likely to use areas representative of that covariate compared to the covariate indicated by the intercept parameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>). Categorical covariates with an OR &gt;1 are positively associated with corvid use compared to the intercept state.Before investigating patterns of corvid landscape use, we determined a detection model for each species. Using AIC<sub>c</sub> and a null occupancy model, we compared models incorporating all possible combinations of 8 detection variables: observer, cloud cover, wind, noise, canopy cover, forest structure, precipitation, and time after sunrise (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). We chose the single best detection model to proceed with occupancy modeling for each species.In our investigation of corvid use, we first tested for the significance of survey year in explaining the distribution of corvids at 59 sites surveyed in both seasons. We compared 2 models: a null model with no explanatory use variables and a model considering only year. For each species, the null model was the most parsimonious (Steller's Jay: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.82; Gray Jay: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.84; Common Raven: <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> &equals; 0.82; Clark's Nutcracker: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.80). Thus, in all subsequent analyses, we did not consider the effect of year on corvid landscape use.We analyzed whether landscape metrics at the 2-km or the 5-km extent best explained patterns of corvid use. For each of the 4 species, we compared 3 models: a null model with no explanatory variables; a model that considered contrast-weighted edge density, percent forest, and patch richness within 2 km; and a model that considered the metrics within 5 km (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). We then used the spatial extent (2 or 5 km) indicated by the most parsimonious model in further analyses of each species.We reduced the number of variables by considering 3 model sets designed to test explicit hypotheses (natural landscape features, aspects of recreation, and food availability) and then evaluated the evidence for variables within each model set using forward model selection. We included all variables identified in competitive models of each set in a single comprehensive analysis of corvid use (for similar methods, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Coates1">Coates et al. 2014</xref>).We tested the hypothesis that the use of each species responds to vegetation and natural landscape features by comparing the null model to those including canopy cover, forest structure, and elevation as well as contrast-weighted edge density, percent forest, and patch richness within the appropriate spatial extent for each species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). For Clark's Nutcracker analyses, we additionally considered the distance to the nearest whitebark pine stand.We tested the hypothesis that corvid use increases in proximity to recreational activity by comparing the null model to models combining 3 explanatory variables: average number of visitors, the park administrative zone type (backcountry camp, backcountry trail, or day use), and the distance to the nearest campground (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). For Common Raven analyses, we also considered the length of road edge within the appropriate spatial extent.We tested the hypothesis that corvid use increases in proximity to anthropogenic food by comparing the null model to a model considering food availability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>). We considered food to be available at sites where picnic tables and/or trash cans were present.To describe the environments inhabited by each corvid, we used forward model selection to relate use to landscape, recreation, and food-availability variables previously identified as important (see above). For species for which anthropogenic food availability was important in explaining overall distribution patterns, we additionally compared models that included interactions between food and each landscape variable important to that species.Although we assumed that our sites were independent, spatial autocorrelation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Legendre1">Legendre 1993</xref>) was a potential limitation of our survey design because some of our sites were separated by only 500 m while some of our habitat variables considered areas up to 5 km surrounding each site. To assess the degree of spatial autocorrelation, we calculated residuals for each site as the observed presence value (presence &equals; 1, absence &equals; 0; presence indicates that the species was detected during &ge;1 visit to the site over the 2 study years) minus the probability of detecting the species at least once as predicted by the top occupancy model for each species (for detailed residual equations, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Moore1">Moore and Swihart 2005</xref>). For each species, we then used correlograms to calculate Moran's <italic>I</italic> (in R version 2.15.1; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) for residuals across a number of distance categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Cliff1">Cliff and Ord 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Moore1">Moore and Swihart 2005</xref>); we chose distance categories of 1,000 m because this was twice the minimum separation distance between sites.We detected Steller's Jays, Gray Jays, and Common Ravens at approximately half of the total 168 survey sites (Steller's Jay: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 81; Gray Jay: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 89; Common Raven: <italic>n</italic> &equals; 89). We observed Steller's Jays (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 413) most often and had 395 and 273 observations of Gray Jays and Common Ravens, respectively. We observed 176 Clark's Nutcrackers at only 28 different survey sites. We had no detections of American Crow (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Corvus brachyrhynchos</named-content></italic>), the only other corvid native to the region.We found no evidence of consistent spatial autocorrelation in the residual values for any of the 4 study species, based on Moran's <italic>I</italic> (see Appendix <xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-f02">Figure 2</xref>). Therefore, we present results for all species without further consideration of spatial autocorrelation.Several variables proved important for corvid detection in general (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t04">Table 2</xref>), and these occurred in top models as well as in competitive models (see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>). Forest structure and canopy cover were important for detection of all species except Common Raven. Noise was an important variable for all species except Clark's Nutcracker. Cloud cover and precipitation were not included in the most parsimonious detection model for any species. The odds of detecting a Steller's Jay was greater in complex (OR &equals; 2.48; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t04">Table 2</xref>) or very complex forests (OR &equals; 1.49) compared to simply structured forests, and detection was most likely during counts with at least some noise (OR &ge; 1.01) compared to very quiet counts. Steller's Jay detection was 105&percnt; more likely in forests with moderate canopy cover (OR &equals; 2.05) and 57&percnt; more likely with high canopy cover (OR &equals; 1.57) compared to forests with no canopy cover. The odds of detecting Gray Jays in complex (OR &equals; 5.45E&minus;10) or very complex forests (OR &equals; 9.74E&minus;10) were much less than in simply structured forests, and the likelihood of detection increased in forests with at least some canopy cover (OR &ge; 9.87E&plus;08) compared to open sites with little or no canopy cover. Detection of Gray Jays was most likely during relatively quiet counts compared to counts with at least moderate noise (OR &le; 0.76). The odds of Common Raven detection improved in breezy (OR &equals; 1.73) or windy conditions (OR &equals; 1.60) compared to still conditions and declined with time after sunrise (OR &equals; 0.03). The odds of Common Raven detection also changed between observers; observer 2 was 90&percnt; more likely to detect Common Ravens (OR &equals; 1.90) than observer 3. For Clark's Nutcrackers, detection odds were much greater in complex (OR &equals; 2.76E&plus;09) and very complexly structured forests (OR &equals; 7.20E&plus;10) than in simple forests. Detection of Clark's Nutcrackers was much less likely, however, in forests with greater amounts of canopy cover (OR &lt; 2.43E&minus;11) than in areas with little or no canopy cover. Contrary to the pattern observed in Common Ravens, the odds of Clark's Nutcracker detection improved with time after sunrise (OR &equals; 17.99).Landscape attributes associated with detection of 4 corvid species in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Only the results from the top model are shown, although there were several competitive models for each species (Steller's Jay: 6 competitive models; Gray Jay: 3 models; Common Raven: 3 models; Clark's Nutcrackers: 4 models). Full specifications of all competitive models for each species are provided in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. The parameter estimates (&beta; values) are untransformed logit values of variables, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the weight of the top model, and OR is the odds ratio of the parameter estimate. The confidence intervals (CI) are the 95&percnt; confidence limits of the odds ratio.Vegetation and landscape features, recreation, and food availability associated with habitat use of 4 corvid species in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Full specifications of all competitive models for each species are provided in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Tables 7</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">9</xref>.Top models describing corvid habitat use across all survey points, considering important landscape features, aspects of recreation, and food availability. Variables considered for each species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>) were identified using a process outlined in the text and detailed in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Tables 7</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">9</xref>. Only the results from the top model are shown, although there were several competitive models for each species (Steller's Jay: 5 competitive models; Gray Jay: 8 models; Common Raven: 2 models; Clark's Nutcrackers: 3 models). Full specifications of all competitive models for each species are provided in Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t02">Table 10</xref>. Parameter estimates (&beta; values) are untransformed logit values of variables, <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the weight of the top model, and OR is the odds ratio of the parameter estimate. Confidence limits (CL) are the 95&percnt; confidence limits of the odds ratio. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t04">Table 2</xref>.For each study species, 1 spatial extent was clearly best for explaining patterns of corvid use (see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t08">Table 6</xref>). For both jays, landscape metrics with a buffer extent of 5 km comprised the most parsimonious model (Steller's Jay: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 1.00; Gray Jay: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 0.87). For Common Ravens and Clark's Nutcrackers, a model considering a 2-km extent was most parsimonious (Common Raven: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 1.00; Clark's Nutcracker: <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> &equals; 1.00).Within each model set, each corvid responded to distinct natural and anthropogenic aspects of the montane environment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>; for details on all competitive models, see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Tables 7</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">9</xref>). However, as with detection, we found several features in each category to be important across several species.We first related corvid use to natural landscape features, independent of recreation or food availability, and found that at least 1 corvid responded to each landscape feature we considered (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Table 7</xref>). Steller's Jays, Common Ravens, and Clark's Nutcrackers were more likely to use areas with frequent nearby edges (Steller's Jay: OR &equals; 2.09E&plus;08; Common Raven: OR &equals; 6.62E&plus;35; Clark's Nutcracker: OR &equals; 3.29), and the odds of the jays and Clark's Nutcrackers using an area improved with greater patch richness (Steller's Jay: OR &equals; 6.72E&plus;06; Gray Jay: OR &equals; 2.49E&plus;10; Clark's Nutcracker: OR &equals; 5.26E&plus;08). Jays and Common Ravens were most likely to use areas with high nearby percent forest cover (Steller's Jay: OR &equals; 3.60; Gray Jay: OR &equals; 10.59; Common Raven: OR &equals; 1.91E&plus;06), although, within these forests, the odds of Steller's Jay use decreased with elevation (OR &equals; 0.15) and in areas with moderate (OR &equals; 0.53) and high canopy cover (OR &equals; 0.25). Common Ravens were less likely to use areas with complex (OR &equals; 1.68E&minus;04) or very complex forests (OR &equals; 0.04) compared to simply structured forests, whereas the odds of Gray Jay and Clark's Nutcracker use was greatest at complexly structured sites (Gray Jay: OR &equals; 22.00; Clark's Nutcracker: OR &equals; 19.30) compared to simple forest structures. Both Gray Jays and Clark's Nutcrackers were more likely to use high elevations compared to low (Gray Jay: OR &equals; 144.03; Clark's Nutcracker: OR &equals; 0.05E&plus;04). Finally, and as expected, the odds of Clark's Nutcrackers using an area decreased with distance from whitebark pine (OR &equals; 0.52).The presence of both jays and of Common Ravens depended on all 3 recreation variables when natural landscape features and food availability were not considered (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t10">Table 8</xref>). The odds of Steller's Jay use was greatest in day-use (OR &equals; 12.06) and trail zones (OR &equals; 5.58) compared to backcountry zones, and their use increased with distance from campgrounds (OR &equals; 1.28) and with greater numbers of visitors (OR &equals; 3.59). The odds of Gray Jay use were greatest in trail zones (OR &equals; 1.11) and least in day-use areas (OR &equals; 0.18) compared to backcountry zones, and Gray Jays were 118&percnt; more likely to use areas with greater amounts of visitors (OR &equals; 2.18). Common Ravens were most likely to use areas with abundant nearby roads (OR &equals; 1.10E&plus;19), but their odds of use decreased with the number of average visitors (OR &equals; 0.05). Both Gray Jay and Common Raven use decreased with distance to the nearest campground (Gray Jay: OR &equals; 0.83; Common Raven: OR &equals; 0.55). Clark's Nutcrackers were less likely to use the day-use (OR &equals; 0.16) or trail zones (OR &equals; 0.52) compared to backcountry zones, and the odds of Clark's Nutcracker use increased with average visitor presence (OR &equals; 2.92).When assessed independently, food availability was within the competitive model sets of each species compared against the null model and improved upon the null model for both Common Ravens and Clark's Nutcrackers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>; Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">Table 9</xref>). All species were more likely to use areas where food subsidies were available (Steller's Jay: OR &equals; 1.75; Gray Jay: OR &equals; 1.62; Common Raven: OR &equals; 21.33; Clark's Nutcrackers: OR &equals; 3.35) compared to areas where subsidies were absent.The joint importance of natural landscape features and environmental aspects related to human recreation (as identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t05">Table 3</xref>) explained significant variation in the use of Mount Rainier National Park by all corvids. In general, corvids most often used sites of high visitor use, including campgrounds, roads, and edgy areas at low elevations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t06">Table 4</xref>; for details on all competitive models, see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t02">Table 10</xref>). Gray Jays, Common Ravens, and Clark's Nutcrackers also used areas where food subsidy was available, even after we controlled for natural habitat associations.The odds of a Steller's Jay using a location decreased with elevation (OR &equals; 0.06) and increased with the amount of nearby edge (OR &equals; 2.45E&plus;06), patch richness of the surrounding landscape (OR &equals; 6.88E&plus;08), and average visitor presence (OR &equals; 55.70; <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t06">Table 4</xref>). Steller's Jays were also less likely to use areas with at least some canopy cover (OR &le; 0.71) compared to areas of little or no canopy cover. By contrast, Gray Jays utilized high-elevation areas (OR &equals; 1.54E&plus;04), and the odds of use increased with the availability of anthropogenic food (OR &equals; 4.53). Gray Jay use also increased with distance to the nearest campground (OR &equals; 2.32). Common Raven use was associated with fragmented forests, and the odds of Common Raven use increased with greater nearby edge density (OR &equals; 4.88E&plus;25), road length (OR &equals; 1.03E&plus;18), and percent forest cover (OR &equals; 6.14E&plus;06). Common Ravens were also more likely to use areas with anthropogenic food subsidies (OR &equals; 119.10), but, conversely, the odds of use decreased with average visitor presence (OR &equals; 0.02). Clark's Nutcrackers also used fragmented forests with high nearby edge density (OR &equals; 3.35E&plus;12), and they were more likely to use complexly structured forests (OR &equals; 5.81) than simply structured forests. The odds of use by Clark's Nutcrackers decreased with distance from stands of whitebark pine (OR &equals; 0.13) but increased with both visitor presence (OR &equals; 5.10) and the availability of anthropogenic food (OR &equals; 72.97). Clark's Nutcrackers were the only corvid species for which food was included in all competitive models.Based on the inclusion of anthropogenic food in the comprehensive model for Gray Jays, Common Ravens, and Clark's Nutcrackers, we investigated the importance of the interaction between food and vegetation variables. Models considering these interactions were not competitive, however, and food availability and natural landscape features did not interact to affect the use patterns of any species (we also evaluated the differences in raw variables at occupied sites with and without food, using a frequentist approach; see Appendix <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t03">Table 11</xref>).Recreational activity and infrastructure were important to the distribution of all 4 corvid species that regularly occur in Mount Rainier National Park. Particularly, Gray Jays, Common Ravens, and Clark's Nutcrackers use areas where anthropogenic food resources are available. Consequences of wilderness recreation and ecotourism, including increased human presence and food availability, are among the leading causes of species endangerment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Czech1">Czech and Krausman 1997</xref>). For adaptable and relatively common species like corvids, recreation in wilderness areas may affect their distribution, which in turn may affect important ecosystem functions.Variation in the relationship between recreation and corvid distribution likely stems from species-specific life history traits and behaviors. Flexible foraging strategies may enable some species to utilize areas of high visitor use and change their use of other landscape features in areas of food subsidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight4">Knight and Kawashima 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight5">Knight et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>). Additionally, species that naturally use vegetative features similar to those created by human development (e.g., use of edges by Steller's Jays; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Sieving1">Sieving and Willson 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Brand1">Brand and George 2001</xref>) may be more likely to use developed areas with high visitor use in wildland preserves such as Mount Rainier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Kluza1">Kluza et al. 2000</xref>). Alternatively, forest interior species such as Gray Jays utilize contiguous habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Raphael1">Raphael et al. 2002</xref>), which may help account for the lack of association on Mount Rainier between Gray Jays and landscape features heavily affected by recreation, despite their reputation as &ldquo;camp robbers.&rdquo;Home-range size may also affect the variables associated with each species' use of landscape features. Although we expected the presence of corvids with smaller home ranges to be correlated with landscape features at the smaller, 2-km scale, we found the opposite. Common Raven, the species with the largest home range, responded to the smaller landscape scale. This result matched previous observations in the Redwood National and State Parks, California, USA, where Common Raven home ranges were never &gt;2 km from a road or other feature of recreational infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Scarpignato1">Scarpignato and George 2013</xref>). Likewise, although the jays have relatively small home ranges, these species responded to the broader landscape scale. We are unsure how to explain this result, although it is possible that we captured a population-level effect for the smaller species, but trends more representative of individual birds for the larger corvids.Although we did not look directly at patterns of corvid density in the present study, we did observe Clark's Nutcrackers traveling in large flocks (&gt;10 birds) during 2 surveys of areas without food subsidies. We did not observe this behavior in areas where anthropogenic food was available. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-VanderWall1">Vander Wall and Balda (1977)</xref> also observed Clark's Nutcrackers flocking as the birds harvested seeds in the San Francisco Peaks during the nonbreeding season. If Clark's Nutcrackers flock during seed harvesting to increase the efficiency of seed collection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-VanderWall1">Vander Wall and Balda 1977</xref>), this could explain our observations at sites that both meet traditional Clark's Nutcracker summer habitat requirements (open, high-elevation forests near stands of whitebark pine; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Tomback2">Tomback 1998</xref>) as well as provide anthropogenic food subsidy, where foraging by Clark's Nutcrackers may be less focused on pine seeds. However, we made relatively fewer observations of Clark's Nutcrackers than of the other corvid species; further study with more observations, as well as direct analyses of density patterns, will likely elucidate a clearer relationship. Additionally, Clark's Nutcrackers collect and cache pine seeds mostly in the late summer and fall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-VanderWall1">Vander Wall and Balda 1977</xref>), and, thus, future Clark's Nutcracker surveys should consider season as a potentially important variable in explaining Clark's Nutcracker distribution.Here, we report the results of occupancy analyses alone in explaining patterns of corvid distribution in Mount Rainier National Park. However, anecdotal observations (see above) and previous work on Common Raven (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Bui1">Bui et al. 2010</xref>) suggest that research should consider the specific behavioral traits of targeted species (food specialization, territoriality, juvenile flocking, etc.) when designing surveys to measure either occupancy or density (or both). The distribution and abundance of territorial species, such as Steller's Jays, is likely to be fairly consistent, and either occupancy or density alone may adequately describe the species' use of landscape features. For flocking (e.g., Clark's Nutcrackers) or wide-ranging (e.g., Common Raven) species, however, occupancy and density may reveal different patterns in landscape use. This was not the case in our study area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Seckel1">Seckel 2011</xref>). Density and occupancy estimates were closely correlated for Steller's Jays, Gray Jays, and Clark's Nutcrackers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Seckel1">Seckel 2011</xref>). Although Common Ravens on Mount Rainier displayed only a weak correlation between occupancy and density estimates, variables important to Common Raven abundance were similar to those identified here: Density increased at sites near road edges, with high levels of visitor use, and with food subsidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Seckel1">Seckel 2011</xref>).Although we observed corvids using human-influenced landscape features as well as areas with anthropogenic food resources, we did not observe any changes in their use of natural landscape features in response to food availability. This suggests that the level of food provisioning in Mount Rainier National Park remains low enough to sustain natural habitat associations for this group of species. However, the use of areas with recreational development may affect the performance of ecosystem services by corvids.In Mount Rainier National Park, Steller's Jays are generalist predators that use areas of fragmented forest landscapes with nearby edges and high visitor presence. Although we did not find that food subsidy specifically was important to Steller's Jays, this species uses areas likely to have the most visitor traffic and, thus, likely to have abundant supplemental food resources. Our observations are generally consistent with previous studies in a similar habitat in Olympic National Park, Washington, USA, where Steller's Jays used forest edges, especially along campgrounds and other areas of human development and where Common Ravens foraged at greater densities at campgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff2">Marzluff et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>). Similarly, campgrounds in the Redwood National and State Parks affected space use by Steller's Jays during the breeding season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Goldenberg1">Goldenberg 2013</xref>). Although the home ranges of Steller's Jays at campground and non-campground sites were equivalent in size, home ranges overlapped more at campgrounds, which suggests that they are able to live and breed at higher densities in these areas. Although we do not present direct evidence of changes in predation levels near human-use areas, Steller's Jays shift their landscape use in response to recreational infrastructure and anthropogenic food provisioning, which suggests that localized increases in predation near human-use areas may occur.Common Ravens use edgy areas with nearby roads on Mount Rainier and in other wilderness areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff2">Marzluff et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Scarpignato1">Scarpignato and George 2013</xref>). Previous studies found that Common Ravens are drawn to roads, in particular, for the easy foraging opportunities for carrion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight4">Knight and Kawashima 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Knight5">Knight et al. 1995</xref>). Thus, roads provide an indirect anthropogenic food subsidy to Common Ravens and other carrion eaters (i.e. vultures). Similar patterns were observed in Olympic National Park, where Common Ravens also used forest edges, particularly along campgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff2">Marzluff et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>), and in the Redwood park system, where Common Ravens used edgy roaded areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Scarpignato1">Scarpignato and George 2013</xref>). In fact, Common Raven home ranges in California never extended beyond 2 km away from a road (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Scarpignato1">Scarpignato and George 2013</xref>), though this was not the case on the Olympic Peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Marzluff3">Marzluff and Neatherlin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Webb1">Webb et al. 2012</xref>). Notably, although Common Raven home ranges rarely overlapped, they did so most at areas with anthropogenic food resources. Roads and other human-supplied food resources may draw Common Ravens away from contiguous forest patches and reduce carrion removal in less disturbed areas.On Mount Rainier, Gray Jays (generalists that, like Common Ravens, may forage on carrion) use areas with food subsidy in high-elevation forests away from most recreational infrastructure. By contrast, Siberian Jays (<italic>Perisoreus infaustus</italic>, a close European relative of the Gray Jay) were more abundant near urban areas and campsites than in surrounding forests in Pallas-Yll&auml;stunturi National Park in Finland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Huhta1">Huhta and Sulkava 2014</xref>). Although we found that food subsidies were important for Gray Jays, there is no evidence that this species is shifting its use of landscape features in favor of greater food resources at lower elevations in areas with greater visitor impact. Instead, food availability may allow for localized increases in Gray Jay presence (e.g., near backcountry campgrounds), potentially increasing predation levels in these areas or reducing the jays' use of carrion farther from these sources of anthropogenic food subsidies.Clark's Nutcrackers coevolved with large-seeded pines, including the whitebark pine in the Pacific Northwest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Lanner1">Lanner 1996</xref>), and it is not surprising that, in Mount Rainier National Park, Clark's Nutcrackers use areas near stands of whitebark pine. We also found, however, that Clark's Nutcrackers are associated with the presence of anthropogenic food subsidies, and we anecdotally observed Clark's Nutcrackers foraging on anthropogenic food refuse during point counts at some high-visitor-use sites. When in areas generally near whitebark pine stands, Clark's Nutcracker distribution may shift slightly to encompass areas with food subsidies, perhaps indicating a general need for Clark's Nutcrackers to forage more widely when anthropogenic foods are not available. This may increase the dispersal of the pine, but it may also increase the energetic demands on Clark's Nutcrackers. Although we found no evidence that food subsidies negatively affect the use of whitebark pine by Clark's Nutcrackers in Mount Rainier National Park, food subsidy may still be an important energy source for Clark's Nutcrackers in years with low seed crops. Because Clark's Nutcrackers, like many granivorous birds, respond to cone crop failures and seed shortages with emigration or irruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Davis1">Davis and Williams 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Davis2">1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Bock1">Bock and Lepthien 1976</xref>), food subsidy from visitors to Mount Rainier could help prevent localized population extinctions and lower the risk of mutualism disruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-McKinney1">McKinney et al. 2009</xref>). This may be especially relevant because persistent threats to whitebark pine trees and cone production, particularly white pine blister rust, are widespread in western North America and throughout the range of whitebark pine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Kendall1">Kendall and Keane 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Smith1">Smith et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Tomback3">Tomback and Achuff 2010</xref>).Land managers of reserved public natural areas are challenged with both providing the public with recreational opportunities and preserving native landscapes for ecosystem function and service, a compromise legally mandated in the United States by the Wilderness Act of 1964 (Public Law 88&ndash;577). By monitoring patterns in the occupancy of synanthropic species, particularly corvids, managers can access a suite of useful bioindicators that are easy to measure, are responsive to human influence, and may reflect changes in important ecosystem functions. Changes in corvid distribution through time, or differences in corvid use in areas near and far from human impact, can be measured against a set threshold. For example, on Mount Rainier, Steller's Jays presently use lower-elevation edgy sites. An increase in Steller's Jay presence at backcountry campgrounds or along trails, typically in less fragmented higher-elevation habitats, could indicate an increase in visitor use or food provisioning in these areas and the crossing of a &ldquo;visitor-impact threshold.&rdquo; In many cases, management may wish to take action to avoid exceeding set thresholds, including increased fines for direct food provisioning, implementation of wildlife-proof garbage cans, improved policing of backcountry &ldquo;leave no trace&rdquo; rules, and an increased effort to improve and increase both public awareness and visitors' sense of responsibility (e.g., outlining risks to wildlife and visitors in park newspapers or through presentations and visitor programs; Mount Rainier National Park has an excellent &ldquo;Keep Wildlife Wild Day&rdquo;). Alternatively, in some specific circumstances, food provisioning may help maintain otherwise threatened corvid populations. If local whitebark pine populations decline, targeted food subsidies may help maintain resident populations of Clark's Nutcrackers.This research was greatly aided by National Park Service employees and staff, particularly R. Rochefort and M. Reid. We are grateful to J. Laake for advice and guidance in data analyses and to M. Wilson and J. Stirbys for help with fieldwork. We thank the reviewers for all their suggestions and help in improving the manuscript. Program PRESENCE is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/presence.shtml" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/software/presence.shtml</ext-link>. Program FRAGSTATS is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.umass.edu/landeco/research/fragstats/fragstats.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.umass.edu/landeco/research/fragstats/fragstats.html</ext-link>.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> This research was funded by the National Park Service. The National Park Service did not have any input into the content of this manuscript and did not require their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> All appropriate ethics and other approvals were obtained for the research.Moran's <italic>I</italic> correlograms of residuals from top models of corvid occupancy in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. We calculated residuals for each site as the observed presence value (presence &equals; 1, absence &equals; 0) minus the probability of detecting the species at least once as predicted by the top occupancy model (for detailed residual equations, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Moore1">Moore and Swihart 2005</xref>). For each species, we then calculated Moran's <italic>I</italic> in the program R for residuals across a number of distance categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Cliff1">Cliff and Ord 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-Moore1">Moore and Swihart 2005</xref>). We chose distance categories of 1,000 m because this was twice the minimum separation distance between sites. Only 1 distance category for each species (filled circles) exhibited evidence of significant spatial autocorrelation (using a 2-sided test and an alpha level of 0.05).Landscape attributes associated with corvid detection across all survey points for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of 8 variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>) for corvid detection by comparing logit link models considering all potential variable combinations. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) detection models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Influence of the extent of landscape variables on corvid habitat use across all survey points for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of contrast-weighted edge density, patch richness, and percent forest cover within radii of 2 km and 5 km on corvid occupancy by comparing occupancy models considering all 3 variables at each extent. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) use models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Vegetative and natural landscape attributes associated with corvid habitat use across all survey points for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>) on corvid habitat use by comparing logit link models using forward model selection. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) use models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Local and landscape features shaped by human presence and recreation patterns and associated with corvid habitat use across all survey points for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t01">Table 1</xref>) on corvid habitat use by comparing logit link models using forward model selection. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) use models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Influence of food availability on corvid habitat use across all survey points for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of food availability on corvid habitat use by comparing a null model with one considering food availability. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) use models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Variables influencing corvid habitat use across all survey points, considering predetermined suites (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Tables 7</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">9</xref>) of landscape features, aspects of recreation, and food availability for (A) Steller's Jay, (B) Gray Jay, (C) Common Raven, and (D) Clark's Nutcracker in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. Using PRESENCE, we evaluated the importance of predetermined variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t09">Tables 7</xref>&ndash;<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t11">9</xref>) on corvid habitat use by comparing logit link models using forward model selection. The coefficients are untransformed logit values of variables in competitive (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &lt; 2) use models. Standard errors are shown in brackets following coefficients. For each species, all models additionally considered the top detection model identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-2-262-t07">Table 5</xref>. <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the model weight, and ER is the evidence ratio.Effect of food subsidy (occupied sites with food &minus; occupied sites without food) on corvid presence on the landscape in Mount Rainier National Park, Washington, USA, 2009&ndash;2010. For continuous variables, effect is equal to the difference between the average raw variable value at occupied sites in areas with and without food subsidy. For categorical variables, effect is the difference between the percentage of occupied sites in areas with and without food subsidy. We tested for significant differences between occupied sites with and without food for each species using Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests and an alpha level of 0.05. Occupied sites are those where the species was observed during &ge;1 visit. Negative values indicate that the use of the landscape feature decreased in areas of food subsidy.