 Observer effects strongly influence estimates of daily nest survival probability but do not substantially increase rates of nest failure in Greater Sage-Grouse  Individual quality and age affect responses to an energetic constraint in a cavity-nesting bird  Uninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information Criterion  Individual and environmental effects on egg allocations of female Greater Sage-Grouse  Seasonal reproductive costs contribute to reduced survival of female Greater Sage-Grouse  Individual quality, survival variation and patterns of phenotypic selection on body condition and timing of nesting in birds  Reproductive effects of nest-marking studies in an American White Pelican colony  Nesting density, habitat structure and human disturbance as factors in Black Guillemot reproduction  Reproductive ecology of the Island Scrub-Jay  Factors influencing nesting success of eiders in Penobscot Bay, Maine  Nest predation of Greater Sage-Grouse in relation to microhabitat factors and predators  Characteristics and dynamics of Greater Sage-Grouse populations  Age and sex of sage grouse from wings  Advanced techniques for modeling avian nest survival  Methods for trapping sage grouse in Colorado  The effects of investigator disturbance on nesting birds  Do field observers attract nest predators and influence nesting success of Common Eiders?  Effect of flagging on predation of artificial duck nests  Evaluation of survival and cause-specific mortality rates using telemetry data  Greater Sage-Grouse nesting habitat selection and success in Wyoming  The impact of researcher disturbance on nest predation rates: A meta-analysis  Investigator activities reduce nest predation in blackbirds   Turdus merula    Predation of gulls in murre colonies  Effects of research activity on Piping Plover nest predation  Nesting success calculated from exposure  Effects of human disturbance on success of artificial duck nests  Effect of research activity on the success of American Robin nests  Crow predation on marked nests  The influence of human disturbance on Tufted Puffin breeding success  Modeling nest-survival data: A comparison of recently developed methods that can be implemented in MARK and SAS  Correcting nesting-success estimates for observer effects: Maximum-likelihood estimates of daily survival rates with reduced bias  Effects of visiting Black Brant nests on egg and nest survival  Improving understanding and assessment of Greater Sage-Grouse populations  Use of radio-telemetry for investigator effects on nesting Mallards,   Anas platyrhynchos    Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants  Nest monitoring does not increase nest predation in open-nesting songbirds: Inference from continuous nest-survival data  Effects of olfactory cues on artificial-nest experiments  Program MARK: Survival estimation from populations of marked animals  What is individual quality? An evolutionary perspective  Individual quality explains variation in reproductive success better than territory quality in a long-lived territorial raptor  Researchers have long recognized that the process of observing nests may influence nest success by increasing depredation risk or causing females to abandon nests. The effects of observer-related nest abandonment may also reduce estimates of daily nest survival when time to nest fate is reduced and the average nest exposure period within the sample becomes shorter. We used an 8-yr record of observer visitations of nesting female Greater Sage-Grouse (  Centrocercus urophasianus  ) in central Nevada, USA, to assess whether observers influenced either the probability of daily nest survival or the overall probability of nest success. Because nest success is influenced by factors other than visitation, we also accounted for the overall quality of a nest (i.e. probability of success in the absence of observer effects) based on potential confounding factors. Nest visitation (no flushing) had no effect on daily nest survival, regardless of nest quality or female age. Flushing a female from a nest substantially lowered the probability of the nest surviving the following day (maximum ~0.22). When considered in the context of the entire nest exposure period, however, flushing a female once produced only a marginal reduction in overall nest success (~0.015). Additionally, females that were younger, or that were associated with low-quality nests, were more likely to abandon the nest after flushing, compared with older females or those associated with higher-quality nests. Observer-related abandonment, however, introduced a negative bias (~0.07) into estimates of overall nest survival by reducing the average timing of nest fate and thereby lowering daily nest survival. Our results suggest that the act of flushing female Greater Sage-Grouse may bias estimates of nest survival low, but this is due to an effect on estimates of daily nest survival, rather than an actual influence on the probability of nest fate.  Los investigadores reconocen desde hace tiempo que el proceso de observaci&oacute;n de los nidos puede influenciar su &eacute;xito final debido al aumento del riesgo de depredaci&oacute;n o si las hembras abandonan el nido luego del disturbio producido por el observador. Los efectos del abandono del nido a causa de los observadores pueden tambi&eacute;n reducir las estimaciones de supervivencia diaria del nido cuando se reduce el tiempo al destino del nido y se hace m&aacute;s corto el per&iacute;odo medio de exposici&oacute;n del nido dentro de la muestra. Empleamos un registro de ocho a&ntilde;os de visitas de observadores a hembras anidando de   Centrocercus urophasianus   en el centro de Nevada para evaluar si los observadores influenciaron ya sea la probabilidad de supervivencia diaria del nido o la probabilidad general de &eacute;xito del nido. Debido a que el &eacute;xito del nido est&aacute; influenciado por una serie de factores adem&aacute;s de la visita, tambi&eacute;n consideramos la calidad general del nido (probabilidad de &eacute;xito en ausencia de los efectos del observador) como parte de estos posibles factores adicionales. La visita del nido (sin espantar) no tuvo un efecto en la supervivencia diaria del nido, independientemente de la calidad del nido y de la edad de la hembra. Espantar una hembra del nido disminuy&oacute; sustancialmente la probabilidad de supervivencia del nido el d&iacute;a siguiente (m&aacute;ximo de ~0.22). Sin embargo, cuando se considera en el contexto de todo el per&iacute;odo de exposici&oacute;n del nido, espantar una hembra una &uacute;nica vez produjo solo una reducci&oacute;n &iacute;nfima en el &eacute;xito global del nido (~0.015). Adicionalmente, las hembras j&oacute;venes y que presentaron nidos de baja calidad, tuvieron mayor probabilidad de abandonar el nido luego de ser espantadas en comparaci&oacute;n con las hembras m&aacute;s viejas o aquellas asociadas a nidos de mayor calidad. Los abandonos relacionados a los observadores, sin embargo, produjeron un sesgo negativo (~0.07) en las estimaciones de la supervivencia general del nido mediante la reducci&oacute;n del tiempo promedio de destino del nido y trajeron como resultado la disminuci&oacute;n de la supervivencia diaria del nido. Nuestros resultados sugieren que el hecho de espantar a las hembras de   C. urophasianus   puede sesgar las estimaciones de supervivencia del nido hacia abajo. Sin embargo, esto es debido a un efecto sobre las estimaciones de la supervivencia diaria del nido, m&aacute;s que a una influencia real en la probabilidad de destino del nido.   Palabras clave:  calidad individual, efectos del observador, sesgo del per&iacute;odo de exposici&oacute;n  Researchers have long acknowledged the potential influence of observers on the breeding success of study organisms ( Choate 1967 ,  G&ouml;tmark and &Aring;hlund 1984 ,  Boellstorff et al. 1988 ). In birds, observer effects could be manifested through increased nest abandonment ( Pierce and Simons 1986 ,  Boellstorff et al. 1988 ); increased nest depredation while nests are temporarily unguarded ( Choate 1967 ,  Cairns 1980 ,  Sedinger 1990 ); increased nest depredation related to predators following cues left by observers, such as scent ( Whelan et al. 1994 ) or visual markers ( Picozzi 1975 ,  Hein and Hein 1996 ); or increased total exposure period of eggs due to altering of female incubation patterns ( Pierce and Simons 1986 ). Observer effects on nest survival are likely variable across taxa ( Ib&aacute;&ntilde;ez-&Aacute;lamo et al. 2012 ) and could be related to spatial distribution (e.g., colonial or noncolonial nesting;  Johnson 1938 ,  G&ouml;tmark 1992 ) and density of nests ( Cairns 1980 ), behavioral responses of nest predators to observers ( Choate 1967 ,  MacIvor et al. 1990 ), or nest-predator community structure (e.g., avian vs. mammal;  Ib&aacute;&ntilde;ez-&Aacute;lamo et al. 2012 ). Additionally, observer effects may influence individuals differently, depending on the level of parental investment ( Caldwell et al. 2013 ) or environmental conditions ( Olson and Rohwer 1998 ), and in some cases may even positively influence nest success ( Ortega et al. 1997 ,  Weidinger 2008 ,  Ib&aacute;&ntilde;ez-&Aacute;lamo and Soler 2010 ). Variation in fitness potential among individuals (i.e. individual heterogeneity) is a central tenet of natural selection and can influence nest and overall breeding success ( Clutton-Brock 1988 ,  Zabala and Zuberogoitia 2014 ). It is likely that individuals perceive and react to observer effects differently and that individuals of higher inherent quality may be less sensitive to observer effects than less fit individuals.  As sample size approaches the size of a local population, it becomes increasingly likely that observer effects could alter population-level dynamics, which may be of particular concern for small populations or imperiled species. It is more often the case, however, that the primary concern with observer effects is related to biases in reported estimates of nest survival ( Rotella et al. 2000 ). Daily nest survival (DNS) approaches to estimate nest success were originally developed as an alternative to estimates of apparent nest success, which are biased high because successful nests are active for longer intervals and are therefore inherently more likely to be discovered than nests that fail ( Mayfield 1961 ). Using the  Mayfield (1961)  approach, DNS is used to estimate the overall probability of nest success based on the product of all daily survival rates within the nest exposure period. For consistency, we refer to this cumulative probability as &ldquo;nest survival,&rdquo; whereas we refer to discrete nest fate (e.g., whether a nest was successful or not) as &ldquo;nest success.&rdquo;  The original methods for estimating DNS were based on the ratio of the number of unsuccessful nests to the total number of exposure days ( Mayfield 1961 ). Modern applications expand this principle to a maximum likelihood framework wherein DNS is estimated as a binomial probability that is based on encounter histories generated from information on the known number of exposure days ( Dinsmore et al. 2002 ). In some cases females abandon their nests following observation, which may be particularly common when females are flushed from nests ( Thorn et al. 2005 ). In this situation, the ultimate fate of the nest occurs earlier than it would have in the absence of observation, and the total number of exposure days is reduced, regardless of whether the nest would ultimately have failed. This unidirectional shift in the timing of nest failure may result in an underestimate of DNS if the total number of exposure days is sufficiently reduced within the sample ( Rotella et al. 2000 ). In addition to biasing estimates of DNS, this issue may also cause overestimation of the impact of observer effects on nest success, because some number of abandoned nests were likely to fail even in the absence of abandonment. In these cases, flushing a female only changes the mechanism leading to nest failure (e.g., abandonment vs. predation) but does not change the fate of the nest. In many cases researchers have attempted to avoid the issue of nest abandonment by censoring abandoned nests from analysis. However, if low-quality individuals are more prone to nest abandonment, this approach may introduce a positive bias in estimated DNS if nests that are inherently more likely to fail are removed at a greater rate than those inherently more likely to be successful.  Greater Sage-Grouse (  Centrocercus urophasianus  ; hereafter &ldquo;sage-grouse&rdquo;) is a ground-nesting species endemic to sagebrush-steppe ecosystems of western North America ( Figure 1 ). Sage-grouse are thought to be sensitive to observer effects because they readily abandon nests ( Patterson 1952 ,  Connelly et al. 2011 ), and predators may be attracted to nests that have been visited ( Holloran et al. 2005 ,  Coates and Delehanty 2010 ). Nest success is the most widely studied and published demographic rate in the literature on this species ( Sedinger 2007 ), but despite the concerns over observer effects, no studies have evaluated observer effects on nest success. The sage-grouse is a species of conservation concern and is currently a candidate for protection under the U.S. Endangered Species Act (U.S. Department of Interior 2010). Therefore, it is important to establish what effect, if any, researchers have on sage-grouse nest success at both the individual and population levels.  An unoccupied Greater Sage-Grouse nest in a patch of dead Wyoming big sage-brush (  Artemisia tridentata  wyomingensis ) in central Nevada, USA.  We investigated the potential for observer effects on sage-grouse nest success using an 8-yr dataset collected from nesting female sage-grouse in central Nevada, USA. Our research goals were twofold. First, we sought to assess whether nest visitation influenced sage-grouse nest success, both when the female was observed but not flushed and when the female was flushed from the nest. Second, we investigated whether observer-related nest abandonment, which occurs most commonly after a female is flushed from a nest, produced a bias in estimates of nest survival that exceeded true observer effects. We hypothesized that heterogeneity in female quality might influence probabilities of abandonment related to research activities. Therefore, we assessed the relationship between nest visitation and nest survival for 2 metrics of female heterogeneity: female age and nest quality. We defined &ldquo;nest quality&rdquo; as a nest's estimated probability of nest success based on the environmental features associated with it (e.g., shrub cover) that are otherwise known to influence nest survival in this study system (D. Gibson et al. personal observation). Because observer-related nest abandonment represents nest failure that must occur prior to the point at which the nest would otherwise have been terminated, we hypothesized that this reduction in exposure period would introduce a nontrivial bias into estimates of nest survival. We investigated this issue by simulating post-abandonment encounter histories for each abandoned nest using the predicted DNS rates based on the nest's overall quality. We then compared estimates of nest survival between the simulated and observed datasets, the magnitude of difference indicating the degree to which the reduced exposure period affected DNS and biased estimates of nest survival.  We captured female sage-grouse in Eureka County, Nevada (for description of study area, see  Blomberg et al. 2013 ,  2014 ), by spotlighting ( Giesen et al. 1982 ) on or near 13 leks during the breeding season (March&ndash;May) from 2003 to 2012, and in seasonal-use areas during the fall from 2005 to 2011. These leks comprised ~33&percnt; of the known leks within Eureka Country and were selected as part of a study assessing the influence of transmission lines on sage-grouse demographic processes. Upon capture, females were classified as subadults (&lt;1 yr old) or adults (&gt;1 yr old) by feather wear on the 9th and 10th primaries ( Crunden 1963 ). Females were equipped with either a 22-g or a 12-g radio necklace (A4060 and A3950; Advanced Telemetry Systems, Isanti, Minnesota, USA) and a size-14 National Band and Tag metal band ( Walsh 2002 ). During the nesting season (April to mid-June) from 2005 to 2012, radio-tagged hens were located using a handheld receiver and YAGI antenna and were visually observed to determine nesting status approximately twice weekly. Observers approached hens and potential nests cautiously to minimize the probability of nest abandonment due to the hen flushing. After nest discovery, a viewpoint was created 10&ndash;20 m away from the nest using sticks, rocks, or other natural objects that were present near the nest site to mark the viewpoint. Active nests were visited approximately twice each week until determination of nest fate. A nest visitation consisted of a haphazard (i.e. not a direct, straight-line) approach to the viewpoint by 1 observer. Upon arrival at the viewpoint, nest occupation was determined either by VHF triangulation or by an observer using binoculars to visually locate the female on a nest. If a female was incubating the nest, the observer left in the direction opposite of the nest. If the nest was unoccupied, the observer determined nest fate as either depredated (i.e. empty nest bowl or crushed egg shells), successful (capped egg shells with detached egg membrane), or abandoned (eggs present and intact, but cold) or else determined that the female was on an incubation recess (eggs present and intact, but warm). Our monitoring methods were not able to identify whether incubation recesses were female-determined foraging bouts or unobserved flushing events, but they comprised a small percentage of total nest observations (&lt;0.25&percnt;). Additionally, we attempted to flush females from nests once during the nesting period to record clutch size and to float eggs to estimate nest initiation date and expected hatch date (see  Blomberg et al. 2014 ). When hens were accidentally flushed from their nests upon first discovery, we recorded clutch size and floated eggs, and we did not purposefully flush females again later in incubation. We did not require observers to employ any practices to mask or alter residual human scent when visiting nests (e.g., wear rubber boots, shower with unscented soap). The dates of all nest visitations and hen flushes, either purposeful or accidental, were recorded and used to model observer effects ( Rotella et al. 2000 ,  2004 ).  We modeled the effects of nest visitation and female flushing using 2 time-varying binary covariates, which represented whether a nest was visited and whether the female was flushed by an observer on any given day (0 &equals; not visited/not flushed, 1 &equals; visited/flushed;  Rotella et al. 2000 ,  2004 ). The observer-effect covariates were designed to evaluate whether a nest's survival until day (   t   &plus;1)  was altered if the nest was visited or the hen was flushed on day (   t   ) . To assess whether potential observer effects differed among females on the basis of their overall nesting quality, we also created a covariate that represented each nest's predicted probability of survival in the absence of research-related abandonment (hereafter &ldquo;nest quality&rdquo;). We developed this nest-quality covariate based on parameter coefficients from the most competitive model structure (hereafter &ldquo;predictor model&rdquo;) from a concurrent nest survival analysis in which we considered the influence of a wide variety of individual and environmental variables on nest success. Nest-site characteristics were derived from vegetation surveys that were conducted 1&ndash;3 days after hatch date for successful nests, or expected hatch date for unsuccessful nests. Vegetation surveys were conducted by technicians who were not blind to the nest's fate. The predictor model included the following effects (and the direction of the effect, &plus; or &minus;): (1) amount of non-sagebrush shrub cover within 100 m 2  (&plus;); (2) amount of forb cover within 100 m 2  (&plus;); (3) average shrub height within 100 m 2  (&plus;); (4) the amount of surrounding habitat (2 km) classified as pinyon&ndash;juniper woodlands (&plus;); and (5) the population the female was associated with (i.e. Roberts Creek Mountain &lsqb;&plus;&rsqb; or Cortez Mountain&lsqb;&minus;&rsqb;). The nest-quality covariate therefore represented an amalgamation of the environmental characteristics that best explained variation in nest success in this system. This continuous covariate was predictive of nest success (i.e. high-quality nests had a greater value than low-quality nests; Kendall's  c  &equals; 0.63). Although this covariate was based on characteristics of both the female and the nest site, we refer to it as &ldquo;nest quality&rdquo; for simplicity. We also note that the predictor model was constructed from a dataset in which all abandoned nests were censored for analysis, and therefore the parameter coefficients used to calculate the nest-quality covariate were not biased by nests that failed as a result of observer-induced abandonment. Lastly, we considered an effect of hen age, which was defined by a hen's minimum known age during each year of the study ( Blomberg et al. 2013 ). Because we could only classify females as subadults or adults at capture, individuals were assigned an age of 1 or 2 yr during the first year they were monitored, and then we increased their assigned age for each year they remained alive and monitored.  We used the &ldquo;nest survival&rdquo; module in Program MARK ( White and Burnham 1999 ) to estimate DNS probabilities. Individual encounter histories were based on nest age, such that for each nest history, the first occasion represented the day the first egg was laid, and occasion 10 was the 10th day the nest was active, regardless of the date of the year that these occasions corresponded to. Results from previous analyses did not find support for an influence of intra-annual variation in nest initiation on nest survival (D. Gibson et al. personal observation); therefore, we did not consider nest initiation date in this analysis. We found support, however, for an influence of nest age on DNS, which suggests that DNS varied between the laying, early-incubation, and late-incubation periods. Sage-grouse are often not found on nests until after the onset of incubation; therefore, only a limited number of visitation and flushing events occurred before day 10. We combined the laying period (days 1&ndash;10, on average) with the early incubation&ndash;late laying period (days 11&ndash;15, on average) and classified this 15-day period as the early stage. We considered the remainder of the incubation period (days 16&ndash;44) to represent the late stage. We considered models that allowed the effect of observation (i.e. being flushed or being visited) to be constant across nest age or to vary independently (i.e. unique slope coefficients) between nest-age periods. We then considered models that included interactions among observer effects and nest stage, observer effects and nest quality, and observer effects and minimum hen age, to assess whether female reactions to observers were heterogeneous and whether the effects of heterogeneity differed among nest stages. We used an information-theoretic approach ( Burnham and Anderson 2002 ) to evaluate support for models that contained different combinations of our explanatory covariates; we considered covariate effects meaningful if 85&percnt; confidence intervals of &beta; coefficients did not overlap zero ( Arnold 2010 ) and if inclusion of a covariate improved the model fit, compared with a similar model that lacked the inclusion of a covariate. All covariates in this analysis were  z -standardized (mean &equals; 0.0, SD &equals; 1.0;  White and Burnham 1999 ).  Post hoc, we used generalized linear models (GLMs) to assess whether the nest-quality covariate value for nests classified as abandoned differed from that for nests classified as either successful or depredated. Our objective was to evaluate whether nests that were abandoned by females were more similar to nests that were ultimately depredated than to those that were ultimately successful. Because abandoned nests were not used to derive our nest-quality covariate, the comparisons we made between abandoned nests and either successful or depredated nests were not confounded with the parameter coefficients we used to estimate nest quality. Direct comparisons, however, between depredated and successful nests would not be appropriate or informative, because these comparisons would be confounded with the regression-based analysis that we originally used to estimate nest quality. We also used a GLM to assess whether mean minimum hen age differed among abandoned, successful, and depredated nests. All GLM analyses were performed in R ( R Development Core Team 2012 ) with nest fate as paired binomial dependent variables (i.e. hatched&ndash;abandoned or depredated&ndash;abandoned) and nest quality and female age as independent variables.  To evaluate whether observer-induced abandonment created a potential bias in estimates of DNS, we simulated post-abandonment encounter histories for each abandoned nest based on the nest's predicted DNS in the absence of abandonment. We assumed that all nest abandonments that followed an observer-related flushing event were observer related. Encounter histories for each abandoned nest began on the occasion the nest was originally found; however, instead of terminating on the date of abandonment, post-abandonment DNS rates were simulated using a series of Bernoulli trials to predict nest fate (i.e. active or failed) on each day post-abandonment, based on a nest-specific DNS probability distribution that we derived from the nest-quality model described above. Abandoned nests that successfully survived to the 37th occasion were considered successful. To conform to the format necessary for nest survival estimation and our general field methods, nests that failed a trial were considered unsuccessful, the occasion prior to failure was assigned as the &ldquo;date last alive,&rdquo; and the occasion 3 days postfailure was considered the &ldquo;date last checked.&rdquo; Encounter histories for nests that terminated &ldquo;naturally&rdquo; (i.e. depredation or hatched) were not modified. We simulated 100 iterations of this dataset and considered 2 models from each simulated iteration: a constant or intercept-only model (.) of DNS and a model that allowed DNS to vary among years (year). We derived an overall estimate of DNS and its associated variance by taking the average and standard deviation from the estimated DNS for each model across all simulated iterations. We compared this average estimate from the simulated dataset to our original analysis to quantify the degree to which DNS was affected by nest abandonment and the resulting reduction in nest exposure period.  We monitored 396 nests from 2005 to 2012, of which 126 hatched (31.8&percnt;), 208 were depredated (52.5&percnt;), and 62 were abandoned (15.7&percnt;). The average nest was flushed on 1.01 occasions (range: 0&ndash;4) and visited on 4.43 occasions (range: 1&ndash;17). We found that DNS varied between the early and late nesting stages (&beta; Stage  &equals; &minus;0.34; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.57 to &minus;0.10). Model-averaged estimates of DNS were 0.942 (95&percnt; CI: 0.925&ndash;0.956) during the early stage (occasions 1&ndash;15), and 0.957 (95&percnt; CI: 0.949&ndash;0.964) during the late stage (occasions 16&ndash;44). This was equivalent to an overall nest survival probability of 0.156 (95&percnt; CI: 0.144&ndash;0.167) based on an average nest exposure period of 37 days for a 7-egg clutch.  We found that flushing a female from a nest during the early stage decreased daily survival probability and increased the risk of nest failure (&beta; FlushEarly  &equals; &minus;0.13; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.25 to 0.00;  Table 1 ); however, flushing a female from a nest during the late stage did not substantially influence DNS (&beta; FlushLate  &equals; 0.03; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.25 to 0.31). Additionally, we found support for an interaction (&beta; FlushEarly&ast;Quality  &equals; 0.13; 85&percnt; CI: 0.00&ndash;0.26) between flushing a female from a nest during the early stage and nest quality (&beta; Quality  &equals; 0.25; 85&percnt; CI: 0.15&ndash;0.36;  Figure 2 ), which suggested that nests predicted to otherwise have lower inherent survival probability were more likely to fail after flushing than nests with otherwise high inherent survival probability ( Figure 2 ). These relationships were not supported if abandoned nests were censored from the analysis (censored: &beta; FlushEarly  &equals; 0.10; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.17 to 0.39; &beta; FlushEarly&ast;Quality  &equals; 0.10; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.08 to 0.27;  Table 2 ). We also found support for an interaction (&beta; FlushEarly&ast;MinAge  &equals; 0.11; 85&percnt; CI: 0.02&ndash;0.21) between flushing a female during the early stage (&beta; FlushEarly  &equals; &minus;0.16; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.27 to &minus;0.06) and minimum hen age (&beta; MinAge  &equals; &minus;0.03; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.12 to 0.06), which suggested that younger females were more likely to abandon after a flushing event than older females ( Figure 3 ). There was no support, however, for an overall effect of female age on nest survival. Despite the magnitude of the difference in DNS between occasions that involved flushing and those that did not ( Figure 2 ), the overall impact of 1 day of reduced nest survival substantially influenced the overall probability of nest success only for low-quality nests ( Figure 4 ). For example, if a female associated with a low-quality nest was flushed once within the first 15 days of the nesting period, the overall probability of nest survival was reduced by ~0.015, which was equivalent to an absolute decrease of 25&percnt; in nest survival in relation to nests of that quality, whereas females associated with a nest of average or above-average quality were not any more likely to fail immediately after a flushing event.  Performance of all nest survival models used to assess the influence of observer effects on Greater Sage-Grouse nest survival in Eureka County, Nevada, USA, 2005&ndash;2012.  Estimated probability of daily nest survival (DNS) during the day following a female being flushed from a nest (solid gray line) compared with a female not being flushed (solid black line) for Greater Sage-Grouse in Eureka, Nevada, USA, as a function of predicted DNS in the absence of observed effects (referred to as &ldquo;nest quality&rdquo; in text). Predicted nest survival was based on vegetation characteristics near nest sites (i.e. non-sagebrush shrub and forb cover, average shrub height, and amount of pinyon&ndash;juniper woodlands) as well as population-level differences between females associated with the Cortez and Roberts mountain ranges (D. Gibson et al. personal observation). Box plot represents the distribution of predicted nest survival estimates from 2005 to 2012. Dashed lines are 95&percnt; confidence intervals.  Performance of all nest survival models used to assess the influence of observer effects on Greater Sage-Grouse nest survival in Eureka County, Nevada, USA, 2005&ndash;2012, with nest abandonment and observer effects censored.  Probability of daily nest survival during the day following a female being flushed from a nest (solid gray line) compared with a female not being flushed (solid black line) for Greater Sage-Grouse in Eureka, Nevada, USA. Box plot represents the distribution of minimum ages of hens recorded from 2005 to 2012. Dashed lines are 95&percnt; confidence intervals.  Deviation from the expected probability of overall nest survival (to 37 days) was related to the number of occasions (1&ndash;4) that a female was flushed from the nest. Females that were predicted to have above-average probabilities of overall nest survival (&gt;0.156) were not fully represented in this figure because flushing events were suggested to improve daily nest survival.  We did not find support for an effect of visiting a nest (but not flushing the female) during either the early stage (&beta; VisitEarly  &equals; 0.09; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.15 to 0.33) or the late stage (&beta; VisitLate  &equals; 0.14; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.05 to 0.32). Additionally, we did not find support for an interaction (&beta; Visit&ast;Quality  &equals; 0.02; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.11 to 0.15) between nest quality and nest visitation (&beta; Visit  &equals; 0.13; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.02 to 0.27), nor did we find support for an interaction (&beta; Visit&ast;MinAge  &equals; 0.07; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.09 to 0.22) between hen minimum age (&beta; MinAge  &equals; &minus;0.001; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.10 to 0.09) and nest visitation (&beta; Visit  &equals; 0.12; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.03 to 0.27).  We found that nest quality (i.e. predicted survival probability of nests based on habitat conditions and female characteristics) was higher for nests that ultimately hatched young than for nests that were abandoned by females after flushing (&beta; QualityHatch  &equals; 0.37; 85&percnt; CI: 0.15&ndash;0.59). However, estimates of nest quality for abandoned nests were not significantly different from those for depredated nests (&beta; QualityDepredated  &equals; &minus;0.11; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.31 to 0.10;  Figure 5 A). We found no evidence that minimum hen ages were significantly different among abandoned nests versus hatched (&beta; AgeHatch  &equals; 0.16; 85&percnt; CI: &minus;0.07 to 0.38); however, the minimum hen age for depredated nests was greater than that for abandoned nests (&beta; AgeDepredated  &equals; 0.23; 85&percnt; CI: 0.02&ndash;0.44;  Figure 5 B).  Distribution of ( A ) predicted nest survival values and ( B ) minimum hen ages (in years) for abandoned (light gray), depredated (dark grey), and hatched (white) Greater Sage-Grouse nests in Eureka, Nevada, USA. Estimates of significant differences (nonoverlapping 85&percnt; confidence intervals) were considered only between abandoned nests and depredated or hatched nests (i.e. not between depredated and hatched nests). Means not sharing the same lowercase letter were significantly different. Filled boxes represent 25&ndash;75&percnt;, with whiskers representing 5&ndash;95&percnt; of the data, and solid dots representing outlier data. Predicted daily nest survival values were estimated from the most competitive nest survival model.  Although we did not find that observer effects appreciably influenced a nest's probability of success, we did find that observer-induced nest abandonment negatively biased estimates of overall nest survival. The average DNS across all simulated encounter histories was 0.960 (95&percnt; CI: 0.958&ndash;0.962), which was equivalent to overall nest survival of 0.224 (95&percnt; CI: 0.206&ndash;0.242). These simulated estimates were 1.43&times; greater (relative difference ~0.068) than our estimated overall nest survival of 0.156 ( Figure 6 ), an estimate that included abandoned nests that terminated earlier than they might have in the absence of observer effects. Based on our simulated encounter histories, each abandoned nest was likely to have been active for an additional 13.7 &plusmn; 1.1 (SE) days longer, on average, if the female had not abandoned the nest. Although we have not found evidence of annual variation in nest survival within our study system (D. Gibson et al. personal observation), the magnitude of the difference between simulated and observed estimates varied substantially among years (0.03&ndash;0.13;  Figure 7 ). Additionally, these results suggested that, within our study system, censorship of abandoned nests resulted in an overestimate of overall nest survival by ~0.044 (in related work in this study system, estimated overall nest survival with abandoned nests censored was 0.268; D. Gibson et al. personal observation).  Comparisons between estimated overall nest survival from analyses that did not modify encounter histories for nests that were abandoned (&ldquo;observed&rdquo;); censored all encounter histories for nests that that were abandoned (&ldquo;censored&rdquo;); or corrected for nest abandonment by simulating their daily nest survival post-abandonment (&ldquo;simulated&rdquo;). Box plot represents estimated overall nest survival for 100 iterations of simulated encounter histories.  Annual comparisons between estimated overall nest survival from an analysis that did not modify encounter histories for nest abandonment (&ldquo;observed&rdquo;; open circles) and from an analysis that corrected for nest abandonment by simulating daily nest survival post-abandonment (&ldquo;simulated&rdquo;; box plots). Box plot represents estimated overall nest survival for 100 iterations of simulated encounter histories. Error bars associated with the observed data represent 95&percnt; confidence intervals.  We found that frequent visits to sage-grouse nests did not lower nest survival, but that flushing females from nests reduced DNS the day after flushing. One criticism of intensive nest monitoring (e.g., flushing of females or frequent nest visits) is that such protocols expose nests to higher risk of predation and may cause females to abandon nests ( Connelly et al. 2011 ). Our results suggest that in the sage-grouse, the larger influence of abandonment is on the timing of nest failure, rather than on nest success itself. Nests abandoned by females were similar in overall characteristics to nests that failed as a result of predation, and they differed significantly in characteristics from nests that were ultimately successful. These results suggest that females prone to nest abandonment were unlikely to successfully hatch their clutches even in the absence of flushing. We did not, however, find an influence of observer disturbance on DNS if abandoned nests were censored from the analysis. Together this suggests that the greater potential bias associated with nest observation is likely related to a reduction in estimated DNS associated with a truncated exposure period when females abandoned nests after being flushed. That is to say, abandonment lowers estimates of nest survival but does not appreciably affect the ultimate nest fate. This bias is analogous to concerns expressed by  White and Garrott (1990) , who elegantly demonstrated (pp. 231&ndash;232) that changes in exposure period following a mass-mortality event produced biased survival estimates from a modified Mayfield DNS estimator, despite no variation in total mortality ( Heisey and Fuller 1985 ). Unlike  White and Garrott's (1990)  example, which could be resolved primarily by relaxing constraints of constant DNS, accounting for biases associated with nest abandonment required a more robust approach because of temporal (i.e. timing of nest visits) and individual (i.e. female or nest quality) heterogeneity.  We found that variation in how individuals responded (i.e. abandon or continue) to being flushed from a nest was related to quantifiable metrics of quality or age ( Figures 2  and  3 ). Although individual quality has repeatedly been associated with components of fitness (e.g.,  Blums et al. 2005 ,  Ardia and Clotfelter 2007 ) and although the magnitude of observer effects has varied in relation to temporal dynamics (e.g., nest age;  Caldwell et al. 2013 ) or environmental conditions (e.g., predator community;  Olson and Rohwer 1998 ), our results are the first, to our knowledge, to link female quality with observer-related nest abandonment. Furthermore, the fact that a portion of females abandon a nest, as opposed to all or none, is evidence that individuals respond to similar cues differently. Given that populations consist of organisms that occupy positions across a continuum of quality ( Wilson and Nussey 2010 ), we argue that the most parsimonious explanation for why a female abandons a nest is related to the inherent reproductive value of the nest attempt. This suggests that both young females with a greater amount of future nesting attempts and females associated with nests that have lower probabilities of hatching should be more prone to abandoning a compromised nest than older females or females with higher-quality nests, respectively.  Our approach to account for this negative shift in total nest exposure period offers researchers an objective method for making system-specific adjustments to estimates of DNS. The approach accounts for both the relative number of nest abandonments and the magnitude of observer effects. Additionally, this approach should produce estimates of nest survival that are less biased than those of current standard procedures, including censoring of abandoned nests. We argue that censoring nests that were abandoned as a result of observer effects would be appropriate only if nest abandonment were extremely rare or if the distribution of predicted DNS for abandoned nests were similar to the distribution of predicted DNS for the rest of the sample. In our study system, this was not the case, and censoring abandoned nests introduced substantial positive bias into our estimate of nest survival. We acknowledge that our approach assumes that the data available are sufficiently robust to develop an explanatory model of nest survival based on environmental variables. To that end, data must include a sufficient sample of nonabandoned nests, such that DNS of both depredated and successful nests can be adequately modeled using explanatory covariates.  Our results suggest that although our nest-monitoring protocols sometimes led to nest abandonment, these protocols did not substantially influence overall nest success in our study system. Nest abandonment, however, negatively biased estimates of nest survival. We developed a relatively straightforward approach to correct estimates of nest survival biased by observer-induced nest abandonment. That being said, we would like to clarify that we do not suggest that researchers should take a cavalier approach to nest monitoring. We instead contend that researchers should make system-specific decisions that weigh the benefit of additional information that is obtained using various nest-monitoring protocols against the magnitude of any negative effects that may result from more invasive monitoring. The approach we have presented here can be replicated without the need to collect additional data other than that required for a normal nest survival study, and so we recommend that studies of nesting ecology employ a formal assessment of observer effects whenever such effects are of concern.  We thank the many field technicians and volunteers for assistance with sage-grouse capture and monitoring. We thank J. Rotella for conceptual guidance, as well as two anonymous reviewers who provided insightful comments. This work was supported jointly by the University of Nevada Agricultural Experiment Station, the Nevada Department of Wildlife, the U.S. Bureau of Land Management, the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, and NV Energy Corp. Capture and handling of sage-grouse were approved by the University of Nevada Reno Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (protocol nos. A02/03&ndash;22, A05/06&ndash;22, A07/08&ndash;22, A09/10&ndash;22). 