Erratum: Identical metabolic rate and thermal conductance in Rock Sandpiper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content></italic>) subspecies with contrasting nonbreeding life historiesIdentical metabolic rate and thermal conductance in Rock Sandpiper (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content></italic>) subspecies with contrasting nonbreeding life historiesTable 3 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-316-Ruthrauff1">Ruthrauff et al. (2013)</xref> incorrectly identified the reference levels for the parameters Sex and Subspecies. The correct reference level for sex is female, and for subspecies is <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content> tschuktschorum</italic>.La Tabla 3 en <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-316-Ruthrauff1">Ruthrauff et al. (2013)</xref> identifica incorrectamente los niveles de referencia para los par&aacute;metros de Sexo y Subespecie. El nivel de referencia correcto por Sexo es hembra, y para Subespecie es <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content> tschuktschorum</italic>.<italic>Palabras clave:</italic> <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content></italic>, conductancia termal, efectos de la temperatura, TMBIn Table 3 of our paper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0004-8038-133-2-316-Ruthrauff1">Ruthrauff et al. 2013</xref>), we incorrectly identified the reference levels for the model-averaged parameter estimates for Sex and Subspecies. In footnote <italic>a</italic> of Table 3, we inadvertently listed males as the reference level, and in footnote <italic>b</italic> we inadvertently listed <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Calidris ptilocnemis</named-content> ptilocnemis</italic> as the reference level. Females and the subspecies <italic>C. p. tschuktschorum</italic> are the correct reference levels for Sex and Subspecies, respectively. Although these terms were incorrectly noted in the table, our results and interpretation were derived from the appropriate reference levels.