Physical, human disturbance, and regional social factors influencing Common Loon occupancy and reproductive successAvian habitat management meets conspecific attraction: If you build it, will they come?Research needs and recommendations for the use of conspecific-attraction methods in the conservation of migratory songbirdsWhen to use social cues: Conspecific attraction at newly created grasslandsSocial information trumps vegetation structure in breeding-site selection by a migrant songbirdLake features, water quality and the summer distribution of Common Loons in New HampshireMethylmercury exposure associated with reduced productivity in Common LoonsConspecific attraction is a missing component in wildlife habitat modelingPublic information: From nosy neighbors to cultural evolutionReproductive advantages for Common Loons using raftsWaterfowl nesting in fall-seeded and spring-seeded cropland in SaskatchewanAdvanced techniques for modeling avian nest survivalCommon Loon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>)Emergent properties of conspecific attraction in fragmented landscapesSpecies interactions and population density mediate the use of social cues for habitat selectionSocial cues facilitate habitat selection: American Redstarts establish breeding territories in response to songTerritory occupancy by Common Loons in response to disturbance, habitat, and intraspecific relationshipsConspecifics influence the settlement decisions of male Brewer's Sparrows at the northern edge of their rangeMayfield logistic regression: A practical approach for analysis of nest survivalHabitat selection studies in avian ecology: A critical reviewEffects of human activities and lake characteristics on the behavior and breeding success of Common LoonsModeling habitat associations for the Common Loon (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>) at multiple scales in northeastern North AmericaHabitat as a potential factor limiting the recovery of a population of nocturnal seabirdsEffects of spatial disturbance on Common Loon nest site selection and territory successEffects of lake characteristics and human disturbance on the presence of piscivorous birds in northern Wisconsin, USAIncorporating social information to improve the precision of models of avian habitat useAggregations from using inadvertent social information: A form of ideal habitat selectionLocal movements of color-marked Common LoonsTerritory acquisition in loons: The importance of take-overProspecting in a solitary breeder: Chick production elicits territorial intrusions in Common LoonsNestsite selection by male loons leads to sex-biased site familiaritySources, sinks, and habitat selection: A landscape perspective on population dynamicsA unified approach to analyzing nest successResponse of the Common Loon to recreational pressure in the Boundary Waters Canoe Area, northeastern MinnesotaNest visits and capture events affect breeding success of Yellow-billed and Pacific loonsGroup foraging, public information, and patch estimationThe use of social cues in habitat selection by wetland birdsCommon Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>) appear to use physical habitat, human disturbance, and social cues when selecting territories; however, recent loon habitat models suggest that the importance of each of these cues may vary depending on population density. We conducted loon detection surveys on lakes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 42) in the Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, during 2007&ndash;2008, and developed territory occupancy and nest success models. We found that occupancy was positively associated with lake area and the presence of islands, whereas road density (human disturbance) and the number of loon pairs within 10 km (social cue) were not important predictors of occupancy. Similarly, loon nest success was positively associated with lake area and the presence of islands. Both models performed well when applied to an independent dataset of 85 lakes (AUC &equals; 0.743 and 0.724, respectively), indicating that these models could be used for identifying suitable habitat during conservation efforts. Our results suggest that managers should first focus efforts on maintaining or creating nesting islands on lakes, and then assess regional loon occupancy rates once physical habitat conditions are met. Comparing our results with recent loon habitat models, we suggest that social cue covariates are most important at low population densities, whereas physical habitat covariates are dominant predictors of occupancy at higher population densities of loons. Loon response to human disturbance appears to be location-specific, depending on the level of human development around lakes and local conservation efforts, particularly the provision of artificial nest platforms.<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic> semble utiliser l'habitat physique, le d&eacute;rangement humain et les indices sociaux dans la s&eacute;lection des territoires; cependant, des mod&egrave;les r&eacute;cents de l'habitat de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic> sugg&eacute;rant l'importance de chacun de ces indices peuvent varier en fonction de la densit&eacute; de population. Nous avons r&eacute;alis&eacute; des relev&eacute;s de d&eacute;tection de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic> sur des lacs (n &equals; 42) dans la p&eacute;ninsule inf&eacute;rieure du Michigan au cours de 2007-2008 et nous avons d&eacute;velopp&eacute; des mod&egrave;les d'occupation du territoire et de succ&egrave;s de nidification. Nous avons trouv&eacute; que l'occupation &eacute;tait positivement associ&eacute;e &agrave; la superficie du lac et &agrave; la pr&eacute;sence d'&icirc;les, alors que la densit&eacute; des routes (d&eacute;rangement humain) et le nombre de couples de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic> dans un rayon de 10 km (indice social) n'&eacute;taient pas des pr&eacute;dicteurs importants. De m&ecirc;me, le succ&egrave;s de nidification &eacute;tait positivement associ&eacute; &agrave; la superficie des lacs et &agrave; la pr&eacute;sence d'&icirc;les. Les deux mod&egrave;les ont bien perform&eacute; avec un jeu de donn&eacute;es ind&eacute;pendantes de 85 lacs (AUC &equals; 0,743 et 0,724, respectivement), ce qui indique que ces mod&egrave;les pourraient &ecirc;tre utilis&eacute;s pour identifier l'habitat dans les efforts de conservation. Nos r&eacute;sultats sugg&egrave;rent que les gestionnaires devraient d'abord concentrer leurs efforts sur le maintien ou la cr&eacute;ation d'&icirc;lots de nidification sur les lacs, pour ensuite &eacute;valuer les taux d'occupation de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic> &agrave; l'&eacute;chelle r&eacute;gionale une fois que les conditions physiques de l'habitat sont rencontr&eacute;es. En comparant nos r&eacute;sultats aux mod&egrave;les r&eacute;cents de l'habitat de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic>, nous sugg&eacute;rons que les covariables des indices sociaux sont les plus importantes lorsque les densit&eacute;s de populations sont faibles, alors que les covariables de l'habitat physique sont des pr&eacute;dicteurs dominants lorsque les densit&eacute;s de populations sont plus &eacute;lev&eacute;es. La r&eacute;ponse de <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">G. immer</named-content></italic> au d&eacute;rangement humain semble &ecirc;tre sp&eacute;cifique au site selon le niveau de d&eacute;veloppement humain sur les lacs et les efforts de conservation locaux, particuli&egrave;rement l'utilisation de plateformes de nidification artificielles.<italic>Mots-cl&eacute;s:</italic> <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>, mod&egrave;le d'habitat, d&eacute;rangement humain, Michigan, occupation, habitat physique, indice social, territoireA variety of proximate cues are used by individuals when selecting habitat or a territory, including physical and structural habitat features, the availability and distribution of resources, human disturbance, and social factors (e.g., conspecific attraction; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Cody1">Cody 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Jones1">Jones 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Ahlering2">Ahlering et al. 2010</xref>). Habitat models can incorporate covariates associated with the full range of habitat selection parameters, yet the relative importance of each of these cues may vary over space and time. Traditionally, habitat models have not incorporated social cues; however, conservation and management may be better served by using habitat models that incorporate multiple habitat selection cues, including conspecific attraction and competition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Campomizzi1">Campomizzi et al. 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Nocera1">Nocera and Forbes (2010)</xref> found that the inclusion of social behavioral cues improved their models for 2 of 3 bird species. One might also posit that there are threshold effects when factors such as population density alter the importance of social cues compared with other habitat selection cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Ahlering1">Ahlering and Faaborg 2006</xref>). However, it is unknown whether different models may be more appropriate at different population densities or at regional, patch occupancy rates for a species that is being conserved or managed. Field studies suggest that varying population densities of conspecifics and heterospecifics may alter the importance of social cues. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hahn1">Hahn and Silverman (2006)</xref> found that conspecific attraction was most influential at lower population densities of American Redstarts (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Setophaga ruticilla</named-content></italic>). Additionally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Harrison1">Harrison et al. (2009)</xref> found that social attraction was a primary driver of habitat selection for Brewer's Sparrows (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Spizella breweri</named-content> breweri</italic>) at the periphery of their range, where population densities were lower than at the center of their geographical range.Common Loons (<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Gavia immer</named-content></italic>; hereafter referred to as loons) select nesting lakes based on local physical, abiotic characteristics such as lake size, lake depth, water clarity, and presence of islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-McIntyre1">McIntyre 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers3">Evers et al. 2010</xref>). At a broader landscape scale, the density of feeding lakes nearby can also be important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper1">Piper et al. 1997</xref>). Human disturbance factors such as shoreline development, recreational lake use, and mercury pollution can affect loon nesting success on lakes selected for breeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Burgess1">Burgess and Meyer 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers3">Evers et al. 2010</xref>). Loons demonstrate high territorial fidelity, with &gt;71&percnt; annual return rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper1">Piper et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers1">Evers 2001</xref>), and average territory tenures of 4.6 and 5.7 yr for females and males, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper4">Piper et al. 2008</xref>). Pair bonds last an average of 5 yr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers1">Evers 2001</xref>); however, changes in pair bonds can occur during territorial takeovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper2">Piper et al. 2000</xref>). Loons disperse relatively short distances from their breeding or natal lake. Adult birds displaced from their breeding lake due to territorial intrusions disperse an average of 4 km to neighboring lakes, whereas young loons disperse &le;15&ndash;22 km from their natal lake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers1">Evers 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Meyer1">Meyer 2006</xref>). Loons are highly territorial during the breeding season, yet an average of 2&ndash;3 territorial intrusions occur per day by prospecting loons who do not hold territories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper2">Piper et al. 2000</xref>). Loons exhibit conspecific attraction and habitat copying to assess the habitat quality of lakes and to target possible lakes for usurpation. In particular, observing the presence of chicks during intrusion appears to be an important social information cue for assessing habitat quality, and a greater rate of eviction of territorial loons has been noted for loon pairs that produced chicks in a previous year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper2">Piper et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper3">2006</xref>).Previous habitat models for Common Loons have been largely based on the physical habitat characteristics of nesting lakes and human disturbance parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Blair1">Blair 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Newbrey1">Newbrey et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Meyer1">Meyer 2006</xref>). More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref> incorporated physical habitat, human disturbance, and social factors as potential cues used by loons for the selection of territories. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> modeled the presence of breeding loons in 3 ecoregions of New Hampshire, USA, and determined that the best models were those incorporating a mixture of physical, disturbance, and social cues, and at least 1 model solely comprised of physical habitat cues. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref> found that loon occupancy of breeding lakes in Montana, USA, was strongly tied to intraspecific interactions (i.e. social cues), and bore little to no relation to human disturbance or physical habitat cues. The disparity in the importance of these covariates determined in these 2 recent studies may be due to greater conspecific attraction at lower population densities of loons. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> found a relatively high loon occupancy rate of 45&ndash;75&percnt; in their study area, compared with the average 27&percnt; lake occupancy observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref>.Our objective was to model loon occupancy and nest success in Michigan, USA, as a function of physical habitat, human disturbance, and social cues. We were specifically interested in the relationships among these cues at varying population densities, measured as loon occupancy rate within the regional landscape surrounding our study lakes. We predicted that social cues would be the most important predictors of loon occupancy at moderate occupancy rates within the landscape, whereas social cues would decrease in importance at high occupancy rates. Determining the relative importance of each type of habitat cue in loon habitat models, particularly in relation to regional loon population size, would be valuable for informing the conservation of loons in Michigan and elsewhere.Our primary study area included Charlevoix, Cheboygan, and Emmet counties, located in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, and encompassed a total of 8,179 km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-f01">Figure 1</xref>). The region was characterized by rolling hills, large inland lakes, numerous rivers, mixed deciduous forests, and Great Lakes shoreline. Our secondary study area was Mecosta County, located in the central Lower Peninsula of Michigan, and encompassed a total of 1,479 km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-f01">Figure 1</xref>). This secondary area was used as a validation dataset for our loon occupancy and nest success models. Compared with the primary study area, Mecosta County was landlocked, with no Great Lakes shoreline. The landscape contained over 100 lakes and rivers, including the Muskegon River, a tributary to Lake Michigan. Both study areas were representative of high-quality loon habitat, with extensive lake systems available for both feeding and nesting. Loon surveys conducted during 1993&ndash;2008 by the Michigan Loon Preservation Association, Michigan Loonwatch volunteers suggested a stable population in both areas, with an index of 0.06 (&plusmn; 0.01 SE) loon pairs detected per ha of lake surveyed.Common Loon detection surveys were conducted in a 3-county primary study area in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. A validation dataset of loon occupancy was used for Mecosta County in the central Lower Peninsula of Michigan, 2008.We conducted loon surveys on inland lakes during mid-April through mid-September in 2007 and 2008 to observe the presence of loon territorial pairs and confirm loon nesting success. We selected all lakes &ge;2 ha in size (range of lake size &equals; 2.5&ndash;6,766.0 ha) for surveys because these lakes provided enough distance for loons to take off (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kaplan1">Kaplan et al. &lsqb;2002&rsqb;</xref>, cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Tischler1">Tischler &lsqb;2011&rsqb;</xref>). We surveyed during daylight hours to confirm the presence of a loon pair through visual observation using binoculars (12 &times; 50 magnification for smaller lakes, 20 &times; 60 magnification for larger lakes). We visited each lake on 3 separate occasions to confirm absences and to estimate detection rates. Surveys occurred in the morning and early afternoon and were ~2&ndash;3 hr long, depending on lake size. Small lakes where loon individuals could be observed from 1 point-count survey site were surveyed on foot. Larger lakes required the use of a kayak, canoe, or motorboat. We surveyed the entire shoreline of each lake, including islands, to confirm loon nesting activity. Loon nesting activity was confirmed, and nest success was estimated, through observations of adult loons incubating on nests, hatched loon chicks, and observations of loon juveniles prior to fledging, with the latter indicating reproductive success. Our estimate of nest success was based on multiple lake visits during mid-April through mid-September to correspond with the timing of loon nesting and fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers3">Evers et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Tischler1">Tischler 2011</xref>). While ideally we would have evaluated daily nest survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Dinsmore1">Dinsmore et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hazler1">Hazler 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Shaffer1">Shaffer 2004</xref>), our method provided a coarse measure of reproductive success, as an estimate of the probability of a lake supporting successful loon hatching and fledging relative to habitat factors. We also did not want our sampling to influence loon nest success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-UherKoch1">Uher-Koch et al. 2015</xref>). Our measure may have overestimated nest success if any nests failed during early April and went unrecorded; however, loons typically begin nesting in May&ndash;June in Michigan, with fall migration occurring predominantly during September and October (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers3">Evers et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Tischler1">Tischler 2011</xref>). During surveys, we also recorded the presence of any natural islands and artificial loon nesting platforms. Our validation dataset from our secondary study area consisted of 85 lakes surveyed for loons in 2008 by a Michigan Loonwatch volunteer loon ranger. These data were collected using an identical protocol to the one that we used in our primary study area, with lake visits occurring &ge;3 times over the breeding season.We identified habitat covariates that were indicative of physical habitat, human disturbance, and social cues important to loons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t01">Table 1</xref>). We obtained Michigan lake and hydrologic polygon data in the form of 1-m resolution 2008 digital orthophoto quadrangles (DOQs) from the Michigan Geographic Spatial Data Library (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mcgi.state.mi.us/mgdl/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mcgi.state.mi.us/mgdl/</ext-link>). We used ArcGIS 10.1 (Environmental Systems Research Institute, Redlands, California, USA) to measure lake attributes, including lake area (ha) and maximum lake depth (m). We also used DOQs, our loon surveys, and Michigan Loonwatch records to determine the presence vs. absence of islands, including artificial nesting platforms placed on lakes by Michigan Loonwatch volunteers. We did not differentiate between natural and artificial platform islands; however, artificial nest platforms were only placed on lakes that had been occupied by loons within the past 5 yr, and this included only 3 of 42 lakes surveyed. We estimated shoreline complexity as the lake perimeter divided by the square-root of lake area. For human disturbance, we examined two parameters. We created a 150-m buffer around each lake polygon in ArcGIS and overlaid that buffer on DOQs. We then estimated shoreline human development as the number of houses in the buffer divided by buffer area, and road density as the length of road sections within the buffer area. One social cue, the minimum number of territorial loon pairs, was estimated within a 10-km buffer surrounding each lake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. 2012</xref>). Michigan Loonwatch data were used to estimate the presence of loon pairs located outside our primary study area. We built buffers from the centroids of locations where loon pairs were detected in order to gain a relative index of the number of loon pairs at a regional scale around lakes.Types of habitat cue, covariates, and predicted relationships with Common Loon occupancy and nest success for models developed from loon detection surveys conducted on lakes in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008.We performed Pearson correlation analysis in Program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>) to determine multicollinearity among potential model input covariates. Variables that were correlated (i.e. <italic>r</italic> &ge; 0.50) were examined further, but never in the same model. We found that lake area was positively correlated with maximum lake depth (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.51), shoreline complexity (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.50), and shoreline human development (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.53). Road density was positively correlated with shoreline human development (<italic>r</italic> &equals; 0.68), so we retained only road density as a human disturbance covariate. We retained lake area, maximum lake depth, shoreline complexity, presence of islands, road density within a 150-m buffer, and minimum number of territorial loon pairs within 10 km for loon occupancy and nest success modeling. We also examined interactions, including: lake area &ast; minimum number of loon pairs, lake area &ast; road density, and road density &ast; minimum number of loon pairs.We used a single-species, multiseason approach to model occupancy (&Psi;) and detection probability (<italic>p</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-MacKenzie1">MacKenzie et al. 2006</xref>) using Program PRESENCE 6.9 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hines1">Hines 2006</xref>). Since our study was of only 2 yr duration, we estimated colonization (&gamma;) and extinction (&epsiv;) rates but treated them as constant in occupancy models. We used an iterative process to examine a limited set of biologically plausible models, each with a maximum of 3 habitat covariates in order to maintain degrees of freedom within the bounds of <italic>n/K</italic>, following an information-theoretic approach and using Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC<sub>c</sub>) to rank models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Burnham1">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We did not consider a model to be competitive if it was simply a subset of another model that we examined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Devries1">Devries et al. 2008</xref>). We report all models that we considered and their calculated Akaike weights (<italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic>), but used &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2 to differentiate the top models. We also estimated 95&percnt; confidence intervals in order to better interpret parameter coefficients and to identify uninformative covariates. We modeled loon nest success using a general linear model (GLM) with a binomial distribution in Program R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-RDevelopmentCoreTeam1">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>). Our nest success modeling approach used the same process as outlined for occupancy modeling.We validated the predictive power of our occupancy and nest success models using an independent dataset of 85 lakes surveyed in our secondary (Mecosta County) study site. We applied our top models to this dataset to calculate predicted probabilities of loon occupancy and nest success and compared these with actual observed values. We summarized results into Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curves from which we calculated the Area Under the Curve (AUC) to evaluate the predictive power of models. Values of AUC range from 0.5 to 1.0, with higher values indicating greater predictive power. An AUC &equals; 0.5 indicates that a model is no better than random in its predictive power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Agresti1">Agresti 2013</xref>).We surveyed 42 lakes for loons in the primary study area and detected territorial pairs on 26 lakes (na&iuml;ve occupancy &equals; 62&percnt;) during the 2 yr of our study. We observed successful nesting on 16 of these 26 occupied lakes. We observed colonization events on 2 lakes and abandonment on 2 lakes, while 24 of 42 lakes maintained territorial pairs over the 2 yr. Our estimated detection probability in Program PRESENCE was 0.822 (&plusmn; 0.032 SE). Our estimates of colonization and extinction rates were &gamma; &equals; 0.118 (&plusmn; 0.084 SE) and &epsiv; &equals; 0.072 (&plusmn; 0.053 SE), respectively. We observed islands on 3 of 16 unoccupied and 18 of 26 occupied lakes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t02">Table 2</xref>). In our secondary study area, we observed territorial pairs on 47 of 85 lakes (na&iuml;ve occupancy &equals; 55&percnt;), and successful nesting on 14 of 47 lakes over 1 yr.Habitat covariate mean (SE) values, including minimum and maximum values in brackets, estimated for lakes (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 42) surveyed and modeled for Common Loon occupancy in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. Road density was strongly correlated with shoreline human development, so we retained only road density as a human disturbance covariate from <xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t01">Table 1</xref>.We examined 12 competing occupancy models. Two models had &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2 (84&percnt; of model weight), both of which consisted of physical habitat covariates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t03">Table 3</xref>). Our top model suggested that loon occupancy was positively associated with lake area and the presence of islands (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t04">Table 4</xref>). A second competing model indicated that loon occupancy was positively associated with the presence of islands and deeper lakes; however, the slope coefficient for lake depth was nearly 0 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t04">Table 4</xref>). The presence of islands appeared to be the most influential covariate based on slope coefficient 95&percnt; confidence intervals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t04">Table 4</xref>). Models with interaction terms ranked a distant 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> in the model set, with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &gt; 4 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t03">Table 3</xref>). A model with human disturbance and social, but no physical habitat, variables ranked 9<sup>th</sup> in our model set, with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &gt; 12 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t03">Table 3</xref>), whereas a model with only a social cue was not considered since it was a subset of another model. We applied the lake area and presence of islands model to an independent dataset and it performed well (AUC &equals; 0.743).Competing models for predicting Common Loon occupancy (&Psi;) in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. Abbreviations for covariates: Area &equals; lake area; Depth &equals; maximum lake depth; ISL &equals; presence of island; Complex &equals; lake shoreline complexity; RD &equals; road density within 150 m of shoreline; LP &equals; minimum number of loon territorial pairs within 10 km. Models are ranked based on the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>). <italic>K</italic> is the number of model parameters, &minus;2ln<italic>L</italic> is the maximized log-likelihood, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the Akaike weight.Summary of parameters in top competing models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t03">Table 3</xref>) for predicting Common Loon occupancy (&Psi;) in our primary study area (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 42 lakes) located in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. Abbreviations for covariates: Area &equals; lake area; ISL &equals; presence of island; and Depth &equals; maximum lake depth.We examined 11 competing nest success models, but found only 1 model with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &le; 2. This top model had a model weight of 79&percnt; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t05">Table 5</xref>), and suggested that loon nest success was positively associated with lake area and the presence of islands (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t06">Table 6</xref>). The 2<sup>nd</sup>-ranked model (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 4.24) indicated greater loon nest success with increasing lake complexity. The best model with a social cue ranked 4<sup>th</sup> overall, with &Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub> &equals; 7.61. While the human disturbance covariate occurred as an interaction term in the 3<sup>rd</sup>- and 6<sup>th</sup>-ranked models, as a univariate variable it was in only the 2 lowest-ranked models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t05">Table 5</xref>). Our top model performed well when applied to an independent dataset (AUC &equals; 0.724).Competing models for predicting Common Loon nest success in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. Abbreviations for covariates: Area &equals; lake area; Depth &equals; maximum lake depth; ISL &equals; presence of island; Complex &equals; lake shoreline complexity; RD &equals; road density within 150 m of shoreline; LP &equals; minimum number of loon territorial pairs within 10 km. Models are ranked based on the difference from the top model in Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample sizes (&Delta;AIC<sub>c</sub>). <italic>K</italic> is the number of model parameters, &minus;2ln<italic>L</italic> is the maximized log-likelihood, and <italic>w<sub>i</sub></italic> is the Akaike weight.Summary of parameters in the top model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-t05">Table 5</xref>) for predicting Common Loon nest success in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan, USA, 2007&ndash;2008. Abbreviations for covariates: Area &equals; lake area, and ISL &equals; presence of island.Our top loon occupancy and nest success models suggested that physical habitat features, namely lake area and the presence of islands, were the dominant predictors of these parameters. Conversely, no top models included human disturbance and/or social cue covariates. Our results support the majority of past loon studies, and suggest that abiotic and/or physical lake features are the dominant predictors of preferred loon habitat. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Dahmer1">Dahmer (1986)</xref> found that the presence of an island and lake circumference were the most important variables for selection of a lake by breeding loons in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Jung1">Jung (1991)</xref> reported that 91&percnt; of observed nesting loons were found on lakes with islands in the northern Lower and eastern Upper Peninsula of Michigan. Larger lakes may offer loons more suitable and protected locations for nest sites and nurseries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers1">Evers 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers3">Evers et al. 2010</xref>), and may reduce exposure to human disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Evers2">Evers 2007</xref>). The presence of islands may influence occupancy because loons prefer islands for nesting, rather than exposed shorelines where nest success is generally lower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Titus1">Titus and VanDruff 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-McIntyre1">McIntyre 1988</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> reported that loon presence was closely tied to island presence and water clarity for all lakes in New Hampshire. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Meyer1">Meyer (2006)</xref> also found that territorial loons selected lakes that were larger and more complex in shape, contained good nesting habitat, had clear water, and were deep. Human disturbance, measured as shoreline building density and boating activity, was not determined to be an important variable associated with loon presence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Meyer1">Meyer 2006</xref>). Conversely, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref> determined that social cues were the best covariates in their loon occupancy models, whereas physical habitat features were of minor importance and human disturbance factors were unimportant.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-KuhnHines1">Kuhn-Hines (2008)</xref> found that greater loon nest productivity was associated with larger lakes, the presence of islands, lower total phosphorus, and lower shoreline development and road density. Human disturbance, measured as road density, was not important in determining nest success in our study area. Loons in areas of relatively high human prevalence appear to tolerate human disturbance, but human disturbance near nest sites can lower loon productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-UherKoch1">Uher-Koch et al. 2015</xref>). The importance of microhabitat selection decisions within lake systems was not addressed in our nest success model, but is important when considering the importance of human disturbance, such as boating activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-McCarthy1">McCarthy and Destefano 2011</xref>). Human disturbance does not yet appear to be an issue for loon occupancy and nest success in northern Lower Peninsula lakes. However, similar to conditions in the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Meyer1">Meyer (2006)</xref>, none of our loon-occupied lakes had a housing density of &gt;25 houses per km. Additional human development above this threshold might result in human disturbance being an important habitat selection covariate.Some habitat models may be improved by the inclusion of a variety of covariate types and scales, including social cues such as conspecific attraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Campomizzi1">Campomizzi et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Nocera1">Nocera and Forbes 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Major1">Major et al. (2012)</xref> found that a recovering population of Ancient Murrelets (<italic>Synthliboramphus antiquus</italic>) exhibited clustered colonies amongst extensive unused habitat areas, with the presence of conspecifics apparently outweighing physical cues in habitat selection decisions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Betts1">Betts et al. (2008)</xref> indicated that social information overrode the use of physical structural cues for the selection of breeding sites. However, age and experience may modify a reliance on purely social cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Betts1">Betts et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. 2012</xref>). Social cues also may differ in importance throughout the season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Andrews1">Andrews et al. 2015</xref>), with young loons possibly relying on social information prior to dispersal. Older individuals may rely more heavily on past experience to assess habitat quality, whereas younger individuals may be more reliant on social information and the settlement patterns of older individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Nocera2">Nocera et al. 2009</xref>). We didn't assess age structure in our study population, and this may be a useful area for future research.Recent loon habitat studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref> examined physical habitat, human disturbance, and social cues in determining occupancy at the lake level. These studies portrayed a range of disturbance levels and loon population densities. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> didn't use occupancy modeling, they did develop multiscale models for loon lake occupancy rates of 45&percnt; up to 75&percnt;. The occupancy models of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref> were developed for low loon occupancy rates (&lt;30&percnt; of lakes occupied). Our results were more similar to those from the White Mountain study area of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref>, which had higher (75&percnt;) loon lake occupancy and lower human disturbance levels. Loons exhibit an ideal preemptive distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Pulliam1">Pulliam and Danielson 1991</xref>), and individual pairs can hold a territory for multiple years on a lake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper4">Piper et al. 2008</xref>). Loons seeking a territory exhibit habitat copying behavior, whereby they frequently intrude into occupied territories and use the presence of loon chicks as an assessment of habitat quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper2">Piper et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Piper3">2006</xref>). Thus, loons rely on public information (i.e. the presence of chicks; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Valone1">Valone 1989</xref>) and social cues (i.e. the presence of a territorial pair on a lake; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Danchin1">Danchin et al. 2004</xref>) for assessing potential habitat. Particularly at low, and possibly at moderate, occupancy rates in the landscape, a strategy of using public information and social cues to inform settlement decisions likely increases individual fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Fletcher1">Fletcher 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Fletcher2">2007</xref>). However, at high occupancy rates, the landscape becomes saturated in terms of available lake territories, and social cues may not be reliable for distinguishing habitat quality. At high occupancy rates, young loons may continue to use public information to assess lake territories that they may attempt to usurp in the future, but may practice scramble competition for the remaining unoccupied lake territories, using physical habitat cues to assess these available habitats.Our top models performed well when applied to an independent dataset, indicating that they have predictive power and thus have a conservation application for identifying loon habitat and/or for improving lake physical habitat features (e.g., placing artificial nest platforms on large lakes without natural islands). Our results suggest that physical habitat cues are most important for predicting loon occupancy and nest success, whereas human disturbance and social cues are not important. However, based on our results and those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Kuhn1">Kuhn et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. (2012)</xref>, we suggest that the relative importance of each of these cues may vary with loon population size and the occupancy rate of loons of lakes across a landscape. At lower occupancy rates and/or when attempting to restore loon populations into former range areas, social cues appear to be the most important. Thus, maintaining loons on high-quality lakes will be important for attracting loons to settle in territories on available lakes nearby (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Ward1">Ward et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Hammond1">Hammond et al. 2012</xref>). Physical habitat cues, particularly the presence of an island, were more important at higher occupancy rates. Artificial nest platforms can improve nesting success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="i0010-5422-117-4-589-Desorbo1">Desorbo et al. 2007</xref>). Although we observed artificial nest platforms at only 3 of 42 lakes in our primary study area, these lakes had higher rates of human disturbance compared with other loon-occupied lakes in our study area. We suggest that these artificial nest platforms were responsible for loon occupancy and nest success on these lakes because the nest platforms were placed into more secluded bays and were clearly identified with buoys and signs to reduce human intrusions. Our results suggest that managers should first focus efforts on maintaining or creating nesting islands on lakes, and then assess regional loon occupancy rates once physical habitat conditions are met. Managers could also experimentally add islands to suitable lakes with low nesting success in an attempt to augment reproductive success. Further, we suggest that loon monitoring programs such as Michigan Loonwatch should maintain multiple surveys of lakes in order to estimate detection probabilities and further enhance the modeling of occupancy.We are grateful to the Michigan Loon Preservation Association and Michigan Loonwatch for their support, particularly J. Williams, D. Doepker, J. Lange, and P. Comfort. We thank 2 anonymous reviewers for constructive comments that improved this manuscript.<bold>Funding statement:</bold> We thank the Little Traverse Bay Bands of Odawa Indians Natural Resource Department, Bureau of Indian Affairs &ndash; Circle of Flight, and Central Michigan University for funding. None of our funders had any influence on the content of the submitted manuscript, nor did they require approval of the final manuscript to be published.<bold>Ethics statement:</bold> No IACUC protocol was required because this was an observation-based and modeling study.