 64    as the present reviewer is competent to judge.  An enormous amount of work has led to the production of a highly valu-  able compendium which certainly will serve many 'users needs'.    D. MULDER  (Wageningen)    Soil Science Simplified. M.I. Harpstead and F.D. Hole, illustrated by M. Bratz.  Iowa University Press, Ames, Iowa, 1980, 122 pp. US$7.75    Not only have the authors, both well-known teachers of soil science, suc-  ceeded in simplifying soil science in their book, but the illustrator, Miss  Bratz, has also contributed essentially with her 129 pictures to achieving  the aim of the book: a summary of basic information about soil science as  a guide to the study of soils by both the layperson and the natural scientist.  In twelve chapters the authors cover nearly the whole field: The soil around  us; Soft physical properties; Clays; Humus; Cation exchange; Water and tem-  perature; Soil classification; Plant nutrition; Engineering uses of soil; Soil  organisms; Soil classification; Soil landscapes, ending with a glossary with  some 200 entries and an index.  Being an old hand myself, and at present trying to edit a new Dutch book  on the same subject (25 authors and some 1000 pp.) I cannot help wondering:  is soil science as simple as this?  The book is well-suited for high~chool earth-science curricula and for  university students in many fields of natural science.  Some critical remarks: Soils are mappable, there are only few remarks  about soft maps on p. 86; in the last section (soft landscape appreciation)  even a few remarks about land evaluation are lacking.    H. DE BAKKER  (Wageningen)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               