 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 375--391                                                     375  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Aagaard, Per; and Helgeson, Harold C. Thermodynamic and kinetic constraints on reaction rates  among minerals and aqueous solutions; 1, Theoretical considerations: American Journal of Science, Vol.  282, No. 3, p. 237-285, illus., 1982.  Aeevido, Gilberto. Soil Survey of Arecibo area, northern Puerto Rico: 169 p., illus. (incl. 16 tables; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored sois maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. P.R., Coll. Agric. Sci.).  Afanas'eva, T. V.; and Tereshina, T. V. Mobile forms of iron in soils of the middle Ob floodplain:  Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 7-12, 3 tables, 1981.  Alekseev, A.A. Diffusion of zinc in soils: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p.  58-60, 2 tables, 1981.  Alexander, E. B. Volume estimates of coarse fragments in soils; a combination of visual and weighing  procedures: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 1, p. 62-63, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Altschaeffl, A. G.; Robinson, Lee; Narkiewicz, Steven A.; et al. Design considerations for collapsible  soils; discussions and closure: Journal of the Geotechnical Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. GT4,  p. 674-678, illus., 1982.  Andersland, O. B.; Edil, Tuncer B.; and Dhowian, Abdulmohsin W. At-rest lateral pressure of peat soils;  discussion and closure: Journal of the Geotechnical Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. GTJ, p. 513-  514, 1982.  Anderson, David C.; Harper, Kimball T.; and Holmgren, Ralph C. Factors influencing development  of cryptogamic soil crusts in Utah deserts: Journal of Range Management, Vol. 35, No. 2, p. 180-185,  illus. (incl. 6 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Anderson, George W.; Hilley, Terry E.; Martin, Paul G., Jr.; et al. Soil survey of Colfax County, New  Mexico:  187 p., illus. (incl. 15 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with N.M. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Anderson, Malcolm G.; and Kneale, Pauline E. The influence of low-angled topography on hillslope  soil-water convergence and stream discharge: Journal of Hydrology, Vol. 57, No. 1-2, p. 65-80, illus.  (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), 1982.  Anonymous. Exkursion in den Harz und das nordliche Harzvorland [Field trip in the Harz Mountains  and northern Harz Foreland]: Kulturring, Vol. 58, No. 1, p. 4-5, 1981.  Anonymous. Characteristics, genesis and classification of strongly weathered soils of Puerto Rico:  Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 1-2, 194 p., illus., 1982.  Appiah, M. R.; and Thomas, R.L. Inositol phosphate and organic phosphorus contents and phosphatase  activity of some Canadian and Ghanaian soils: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 31-  38 (incl. French sum.), 2 anal., 1 table, 1982.  Arya, Lalit M.; and Paris, Jack F. A physicoempirical model to predict the soil moisture characteristic  from particle-size distribution and bulk density data: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual  meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1023-  1030, illus., 1981.  Aubertin, R.; and Robert, C. Regions de Lamarck et de Troilus [The Lamarck and Troilus areas]: in  Travaux sur le terrain, 1981 (Quebec, Ministere de l'Energie et des Ressources, Direction Generale de  l'Exploration  Geologique et  Minerale), Travaux  sur le Terrain  -  Direction  de la  Geologic  (Quebec) = Field Work - Direction de la Geologic (Quebec), No. DPV-846, p. 48-49, 1981.    376    Auxt, Tara Lou. Effectiveness of four soil amendments in controlling toxic levels of aluminum and  manganese in orchard subsoils: 147 p., Doctoral, 1981, West Virginia Univ., Morgantown, WV. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.  Aylmore, L. A. G.; and Murali, V. A convective-dispersive-adsorptive flow model for solute transport  in soils; II, Evaluation of single and two-component adsorption models for phosphate movement in soils:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 287-298, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Baladi, J. Y.; Ayers, D. L.; and Schoenhals, R.J. Transient heat and mass transfer in soils: International  Journal of Heat and Mass Transfer, Vol. 24, No. 3, p. 449-458 (incl. French, German, Russian sum.),  1981.  Banwart, W. L.; I-Iassett, J. J.; Wood, S. G.; et aL Sorption of nitrogen-heterocyclic compounds by soils  and sediments: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 1, p. 42-47, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Barber, Larry B., II; and Steele, Kenneth F. Variability of mercury concentrations of Midcontinent  soils, USA; baseline data for a coal-fired power plant: in Proceedings of University of Missouri's 15th  annual conference on trace substances in environmental health (Hemphill, Delbert D., editor), Trace  Substances in Environmental Health, No. 15, p. 317-322, 1 table, sketch maps, 1981.  Barker, Raymond J. Soil survey; Idaho County area, Idaho, western part: 266 p., illus. (incl. 22 tables;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Bur. Indian Affairs; Univ. Idaho, Coll. Agric.).  Barren, P, F.; and Wilson, M.A. Humic soil and coal structure study with magic-angle spinning 13C  CP-NMR: Nature (London), Vol. 289, No. 5795, p. 275-276, 1981.  Barrow, N. J.; Bowden, J. W.; Posner, A. M.; et aL Describing the adsorption of copper, zinc and lead  on a variable charge mineral surface: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 309-321,  illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Bartlett, Richmond J. Nonmicrobial nitrite-to-nitrate transformation in soils: in Soil Science Society  of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal,  Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1054-1058, illus., 1981.  Beeson, Kenneth C.  Soil as an environmental factor in aging:  in Aging and the geochemical  environment (U. S., National Research Council, Panel on Aging and the Geochemical Environment),  p. 104-113, 3 tables, Natl. Acad. Press, Washington, DC, United States, 1981.  Beinroth, F.H. Somehighly weathered soils of Puerto Rico;1, Morphology, formation and classification:  in Characteristics, genesis and classification of strongly weathered soils of Puerto Rico (Anonymous),  Oeoderma, Vol. 27, No. 1-2, p. 1-73, illus. (incl. 11 anal., 8 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Benham, Ken E. Soil survey of St. Louis County and St. Louis City, Missouri: 137 p., illus. (incl. 16  tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (PubL in coop. with Me. Agric. Exper. Stn.).  Benitez O., Andres; Smachez S., Rlff~l; a~l Vital P., Roberto. Inventory of eroded areas in the State  of Guanajuato, Mexico, by automatic analysis of Landsat images: Procee~iings of the International  Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. III, p. 1353-1362, illus. (incl. sketch maps),  1981.  Birkeland, Peter W. Subdivision of Holocene glacial deposits, Ben Ohau Range, New Zealand, using  relative-dating methods: Geological Society of America Bulletin, Vol. 93, No. 5, p. 433-449, illus. (incl.  2 tables, sketch maps), 1982.  Blackburn, G. Particle-size analyses of Widgelli parna in South-east Australia: Australian Journal of  Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 355-360, 17 anal., 2 tables, 1981.  Bladh, Kenneth W. The formation of goethite, jarositc, and alunite during the weathering of sulfide-  bearing felsic rocks: Economic C~ology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, Vol.  77, No. 1, p. 176-184, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  Bleshinskiy, S. V.; Umarova, S. N.; Babenko, V. G.; et al. Fiziko-khimichsskiye osnovy kislotno-  osnovnogo vskryitiya polevoshpatovykh mineralov i vysokokremnistykh pored [Physico-chemicat  principles of acid-base decomposition of feldspars and high-silica rocks]: Izvestiya Akademiy Nauk  Kirglzskoy SSR=Kabarlary Kyrgyz SSR Ilimder Akademiyasynyn, Vol. 1981, No. 4, p. 34-39, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.    377    Bodere, Jean-Claude. Le role des influences structurales sur le trace d'une cote rocheuse volcanique;  l'exemple des strandflats du sud-est de l'Islande [Structural control in the outline of a coast made up of  volcanic rocks; the pattern of strand flats on southeastern Iceland]: Geographie Physique et Quaternaire,  Vol. 35, No. 2 (Morphologie littorale et marine), p. 231-240 (incl. English, German sum.), illus. (incl. geol.  sketch maps), 1981.  Boerner, Ralph E. J. An inexpensive, tension-free lysimeter for use in porous soils: Bulletin of the  Torrey Botanical Club, Vol. 109, No. 1, p. 80-83, illus., 1982.  Bonell, M.; Gilmour, D. A.; and Sinclair, D.F. Soil hydraulic properties and their effect on surface and  subsurface water transfer in a tropical rainforest catchment: Hydrological Sciences Bulletin, Vol. 26, No.  1, p. 1-18 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Bonn, Ferdinand; Bernier, Monique; and Broehu, Richard. Visual and digital analysis of H.C.M.M. data  over eastern Canada: Proceedings of the International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment,  No. 15, Vol. III, p. 1449-1463, illus. (incl. 1 tables), 1981.  Bowen, L. H.; and Weed, S.B. Moessbauer spectroscopic analysis of iron oxides in soil: in Moessbauer  spectroscopy and its chemical applications (Stevens, John G., editor; et al.), Advances in Chemistry  Series, No. 194, p. 247-261, illus. (incl. 13 tables), 1981.  179th meeting of the American Chemical Society;  Divisions of Nuclear Chemistry and Technology.  Brissaud, F.; Heurteaux, P.; Podlejski, J.; et al. Transferts dispersifs et propagation de pesticides dans  un sol de riziere inondee [Dispersive transfer and pesticide propagation in a submerged rice field]:  Journal of Hydrology, Vol. 57, No. 3-4, p. 233-245 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Brown, Jean-Louis; and Martel, Yvon. Interet des chablis dans l'etude des paleosols [Importance of  windfalls in the study of Paleosols]:  in Quatrieme Colloque sur le Quaternaire du Quebecin Fourth  symposium on the Quaternary of Quebec (Anonymous), Geographie Physique et Quaternaire, Vol. 35,  No. 1, p. 87-92 (incl. English, German sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1981.  Brown, R. B.; Cutshall, N. H.; and Kling, G.F. Agricultural erosion indicated by 137Cs redistribution;  I, Levels and distribution of 137Cs activity in soils:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual  meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1184-  1190, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch maps), 1981.  Brown, R. B.; Kling, G. F.; and Cutshall, N. H. Agricultural erosion indicated by 137Cs redistribution;  II, Estimates of erosion rates: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1191-1197, 4 tables, sketch map,  1981.  Brunskill, G. J.; and Wilkinson, P. Runoff of uranium-series elements from Arctic and temperate zone  watersheds [abstr.]:  in AGU/ASLO meeting abstracts (Anonymous), Eos, Transactions, American  Geophysical Union, Vol. 63, No. 3, p. 56, 1982.  Buekhouse, John C.; and Gaither, Ronald E.  Potential sediment production within vegetative  communities in Oregon's Blue Mountains: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 2, p.  120-122, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Butera, M. Kristine; and Seyfarth, Benjamin Rayborn. A determination of marsh detrital export from  Landsat MSS data; a function of transport distance and water body characterization:  in Machine  processing of remotely sensed data, with special emphasis on range, forest, and wetlands assessment  (Hoffer, Roger M., chairperson; et al.), Proceedings, Annual Symposium - Machine Processing of  Remotely Sensed Data, No. 7, p. 240-253, illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch maps), 1981.  Button, Andrew; and Tyler, Noel.  The character and economic significance of Precambrian  paleoweathering and erosion surfaces in Southern Africa:  in Economic geology; Seventy-fifth  anniversary volume; 1905-1980 (Skinner, Brian J., editor), p. 686-709, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sect., block  diags., sketch maps), Econ. Geol. Publ. Co., United States, 1981.  Bynum, Otto W. Soil survey of San Saba County, Texas:  163 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Byrne, R. H.; and Young, R. W. Trace metal complexation in high ligand variety media [abstr.]: in  AGU/ASLO meeting abstracts (Anonymous), Eos, Transactions, American Geophysical Union, Vol. 63,  No. 3, p. 49, 1982.    378    Carroll, T. R. Airborne soil moisture measurement using natural terrestrial gamma radiation: Soil  Science, Vol. 132, No. 5, p. 358-366, illus., 1981.  Cashln, W.; and Anderson, D.M. Planetary soil water analyzer (PSWA) prototype: NASA Technical  Memorandum, No. 84211, p. 364-366, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Cassel, D. K.; and Nelson, L. A, Selection of variables to be used in statistical analysis of field-measured  soil water content: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1007-1012, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Chang, F. H.; and Broadbent, F.E. Influence of trace metals on carbon dioxide evolution from a Yolo  soil: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 6, p. 416-421, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Chartres, C. ,L; and Cost'in, A. B. Buried soil cracks in alluvium near Braidwood, N.S.W.: Australian  Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 255-263, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1981.  Chandhri, R. S.; and Khan, H. M. M. Textural parameters of desert sediments; That Desert (India):  Sedimentary Geology, Vol. 28, No. 1, p. 43-62, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Chesworth, Ward. Late Cenozoic geology and the second oldest profession:  in Applied Quaternary  geology; a symposium in honor of Aleksis Dreimanis (Hicock, Stephen R., editor), Geoscience Canada,  Vol. 9, No. 1, p. 54-61, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), 1982.  Chu, Shu-Yuan; and Sl~ito, Garrison. The thermodynamics of ternary cation exchange systems and  the subregular model:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1084-1089, 2 tables, 1981.  Clauser, N. Strontium and argon isotopes in naturally weathered biotites, muscovites and feldspars:  Chemical Geology, Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 325-334, illus. (incl. 2 tables, anal.), 1981.  Colbeek, S. C. Configuration of ice in frozen media: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 116-123, illus.,  1982.  Collet, C.  Comparaison de methodes de classification appliquees a des donnees de teledetection  [Comparison of methods of classification applied to remote sensing data]: Espace Geographiqu Vol.  10, No. 1, p. 25-32 (incl. English, German sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Colman, Steven M. Clay mineralogy of weathering rinds and possible implications concerning the  sources of clay minerals in soils: Geology (Boulder), Vol. 10, No. 7, p. 370-375, illus. (incl. 2 tables,  sketch map), 1982.  Colwell, John E. Landsat feature enhancement, or, Can we separate vegetation from soil?: Proceedings  of the International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. II, p. 599-621, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Courts, P. J. F. Coastal archaeology in Victoria; Part 2, Adaptation technology and volcanism:  Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria, Vol. 93, No. 1-2, p. 15-22, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 198 i.  Cowardin, Lewis M. Wetlands and deepwater habitats; a new classification: Journal of Soil and Water  Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 2, p. 83-85, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Craw, D. Oxidation and microprobe-induced potassium mobility in iron-bearing phyllosilicates from the  Otago schists, New Zealand: Lithos, Vol. 14, No. 1, p. 49-57, illus. (incl. 18 anal., 4 tables), 1981.  Cruse, R. M.; C, assel, D. K.; StiR, R. E.; et al. Effect of particle surface roughness on mechanical  impedance of coarse-textured soil materials: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1210-1214, illus.  (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Dane, J. H.; and Mathis, F.H. An adaptive finite difference scheme for the one-dimensional water flow  equation:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1048-1054, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Daniel, Charles, III. Hydrology, geology and soils of pocosins; a comparison of natural and altered  systems: in Pocosin wetlands; an integrated analysis of coastal plain freshwater bogs in North Carolina  (Richardson, Curtis J., editor; et aL), p. 69-108, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sect., sketch maps), Hutchinson Ross  Publ. Co., Stroudsburg, PA, United States, 1981.    379    Davies, Brian E.; Ginnever, Rhoda C.; and Lear, Jean M. Cadmium and lead contaminated soils in some  British metal mining areas: in Proceedings of University of Missouri's 15th annual conference on trace  substances in environmental health (Hemphill, Delbert D., editor), Trace Substances in Environmental  Health, No. 15, p. 323-332, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Dawson, H. J.; Hrutfiord, B. F.; Zasoski, R. J.; et al. The molecular weight and origin of yellow organic  acids: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 3, p. 191-199, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  De Kimpe, C. R.; Bernier-Cardou, M.; and Jolieoeur, P. Compaction and settling of Quebec soils in  relation to their soil-water properties: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 165-175 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  de Kimpe, C. R.; and Laverdiere, M.R. Dissolution of organometallic complexes and silica from the  clay fraction of Podzolic soils: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 5, p.  387-400, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  de Vries, Jan. Prediction of non-Darcian flow in porous media; closure: Journal of the Irrigation and  Drainage Division, Vol. 108, No. IR1, p. 83-85, 1982.  Dillaha, T. A., II1; Beasley, D. B.; and Huggins, L F. Using the ANSWERS model to estimate sediment  yields on construction sites: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 2, p. 117-120, illus.  (incl. l table), 1982.  Doering, E. J.; and Sandoval, F.M. Chemistry of seep drainage in southwestern North Dakota: Soil  Science, Vol. 132, No. 2, p. 142-149, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Douglas, I. Soil conservation measures in river basin planning:  in River basin planning; theory and  practice (Saha, Suranjit K., editor; et al.), p. 49-73, illus. (incl. 1 table), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester.  United Kingdom, 1981. (A Wiley-Interscience Publ.).  International colloquium.  Drawe, D. Lynn; Kattner, Kenneth R.; MeFarland, Weldon H.; et al. Vegetation and soil properties  of five habitat types on North Padre Island: The Texas Journal of Science, Vol. 33, No. 2-4, p. 145-157.  illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Driseoll, Richard S. Remote sensing; its role in meeting information needs: in Machine processing of  remotely sensed data, with special emphasis on range, forest, and wetlands assessment (Hoffer, Roger  M., chairperson; et al.), Proceedings, Annual Symposium - Machine Processing of Remotely Sensed  Data, No. 7, p. 2-6, 1981.  Dudas, M. J.; and Pawluk, S.  Reevaluation of the occurrence of interstratified clays and other  phyllosilicates in southern Alberta soils: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 61-69 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Eekenrode, Joseph J. Soil survey of Lackawanna and Wyoming counties, Pennsylvania: 166 p., illus.  (incl. 16 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv..  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep.  Environ. Resour., State Conserv. Comm.).  Edmonds, T. E. The differential pulse polarographic determination of extractable molybdenum in soil:  Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 1, p. 1-6, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Elaehi, Charles. Spaceborne radar observation of the Earth surface: Proceedings of the International  Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. 1, p. 21-31, illus., 1981.  Elliott, H. A.; and Sparks, D. L.  Electrokinetic behavior of a paleudult profile in relation to  mineralogical composition: Soil Science, Vol, 132, No. 6, p. 402-409, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Elriek, D. E.; and Robin, M.J. Estimating the sorptivity of soils: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 2, p. 127-  133, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Enfield, Carl G.; Phan, T.; Waiters, David M.; et al. Kinetic model for phosphate transport and  transformation in Calcareous soils; I, Kinetics of transformation: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th  annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p.  1059-1064, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Enfield, Carl G.; Phan, T.; and Waiters, David M.  Kinetic model for phosphate transport and  transformation in Calcareous soils; II, Laboratory and field transport: in Soil Science Society of America,  45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  6, p. 1064-1070, illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch map), 1981.    880    England, J.; Bradley, R. S.; and Stuckenrath, R.  Multiple glaciations and marine transgressions,  western Kennedy Channel, Northwest Territories, Canada: Boreas, Vol. 10, No. 1, p. 71-89, illus. (incl.  sketch map), 1981.  Everett, Charles Jay. Effects of biological weathering on mine soil genesis and fertility:  134 p.,  Doctoral, 1981, Virginia Polyteeh. Inst. and State Univ., Btacksburg, VA. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Fagbami, Ayodele. SLAR imagery interpretation of eastern Niger Delta for soil survey purposes:  in  Technical papers of the American Society of Photogrammetry (Anonymous), Technical Papers of the  American Society of Photogrammetry, Fall Technical Meeting, Vol. 1981, p. 191-202, illus. (incl. sketch  maps), 1981.  Fehr, James P. Soil survey of Russell County, Kentucky: 93 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Ky. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour. Environ. Prot.).  Feng-ehih Lin; and Clemency, C. V. The kinetics of dissolution of muscovites at 25"C and 1 atm CO2  partial pressure: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, Vol. 45, No. 4, p. 571-576, illus. (incl. 3 tables),  1981.  Floran, R. J.; Abraham, M. M.; Boatner, L. A.; et aL Geologic stability of monazite and its bearing on  the immobilization of actinide wastes:  in Proceedings of the Third international symposium on the  scientific basis for nuclear waste management (Moore, John G., editor), Vol. 3, p. 507-514, 2 tables,  Plenum Press, New York, NY, United States, 1981.  Flores-Berrones, Raul; and Whitman, Robert V. Seismic response of end-bearing piles: Journal of the  Geotechnical Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. GT4, p. 554-569, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Folkoff, Michael E.; Meentemeyer, Vernon; and Box, Elgene O. Climatic control of soil acidity:  Physical Geography, Vol. 2, No. 2, p. 116-124, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Fouts, William L.; and Wisner, Robin J. Soil survey of Buchanan County, Iowa: 161 p., illus. (incl.  18 tables; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Stn.; Iowa State  Univ., Coop. Ext. Serv.; Iowa, Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Fox, Robert L. Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico; 3, Chemical properties: in Characteristics,  genesis and classification of strongly weathered soils of Puerto Rico (Anonymous), Geoderma, Vol. 27,  No. 1-2, p. 139-176, 11 anal., 15 tables, 1982.  Gavin, Brian. Soil and stream sediment base and precious metal geochemical exploration, Bearpaw  Mountains, Montana: 135 p., Master's, 1981, Univ. of Missouri, Rolla, Me.  Gazetas, George. Stresses and displacements in cross-anisotropic soils: Journal of the Geotechnical  Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. GT4, p. 532-553, illus., 1982.  Gee, G. W.; and Dodson, M. E. Soil water content by microwave drying; a routine procedure: in Soil  Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1234-1237, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Gilmour, J. T.; and Marx, D.B. Soluble salt concentration in runoff waters from soils previously cropped  to rice: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1 t 98-1201, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Godfrey, Paul J. (investigator). Oceanic overwash and its ecological implications on the outer banks  of North Carolina(Calo-N-1 and2): in Overwash processes (Leatherman, Stephen P.,editor),Vol. 58,  p. 321-333, illus., Hutchinson Ross Publ. Co., Stroudsburg, PA, United States, 1981.  Golden, Michael L.; Gabriel, Wayne J.; and Stevens, Jack W. Soil survey, Val Verde County, Texas:  138 p., illus. (incL 16 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Val  Verde Cry. Comm. Court.).  GoUghtly, J. Paul. Nickelifcrous laterite deposits:  in Economic geology; Seventy-fifth anniversary  volume; 1905-1980 (Skinner, Brian J., editor), p. 710-735, illus. (incl. 9 tables, sketch map), Econ. Geol.  Publ. Co., United States, 1981.    381    Gooding, J. L. Mineralogical aspects of terrestrial weathering effects in chondrites from Allen Hills,  Antarctica: in Section 2, Planets, asteroids and satellites (Lunar and Planetary Institute), Proceedings  of the Lunar and Planetary Science Conference, No. 12, Part B, p. 1105-1122, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  (Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, Supplement 16).  Goyer, M.; and Langlais, L. Region de la Faille du Grand Pabos [The Grand Pabos Fault area]:  in  Travaux sur le terrain, 1981 (Quebec, Ministere de l'Energie et des Ressources, Direction Generale de  l'Exploration Geologique et Minerale), Travaux sur le Terrain - Direction de la Geologic  (Quebec) = Field Work - Direction de la Geologic (Quebec), No. DPV-846, p. 45-47, 1981.  Gradusov, B. P.; Urusevskaya, I. S.; and Shoba, S. A. Micromorphological and clay-mineralogical  characteristics of Gray forest soils of the central part of the Russian Plain:  Moscow University Soil  Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 13-22, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Green, George L. Soil survey of Wasco County, Oregon, northern part: 125 p., illus. (incl. 23 tables;  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Oreg. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Grigg, J. L.; and Morrison, J. D. An automatic colorimetric determination of aluminium in soil extracts  using catechol violet: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 5, p. 351-361,  illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Grolier, M. J.; and Schultejann, P.A. The environment of South-central Tunisia as observed on Landsat  scene 206/036: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 82-0130, 43 p., illus.  (incl. 1 table, sketch maps; map), 1982. available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West.  Distrib. Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Grout, Marilyn Ann.  Rockwall erosion in the northern Sangre de Cristo Mountains, Colorado;  contributing factors, sequence, and rate: 165 p., illus., Master's, 1981, Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, CO.  Guileher, Andre. Cryoplanation littorale et cordons glaciels de basse mer dans la region de Rimouski,  cote sud de l'estuaire du Saint-Laurent, Quebec [Coastal cryoplanation and low-tide ice-formed ridges  in the Rimouski area, south shore of the Saint Lawrence Estuary, Quebec]: Geographic Physique et  Quaternaire, Vol. 35, No. 2 (Morphologie littorale et marine), p. 155-169 (incl. English, German sum.), illus.  (incl. sect., sketch maps), 1981.  Gunjigake, Noriaki; and Wada, Koji.  Effects of phosphorus concentration and pH on phosphate  retention by active aluminum and iron of Ando soils: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 5, p. 347-352, illus.  (incl. 18 anal., 4 tables), 1981.  Hacker, Leroy W.; and Carleton, Joseph Owen. Soil survey of Taos County and parts of Rio Arriba  and Mora counties, New Mexico: 220 p., illus. (incl. 16 tables; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with N.M. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Hailada, Wayne A.; Mertz, Frederick C.; Tinney, Larry R.; et al. Flexible processing of remote sensing  data through integration of image processing and geobased information systems: Proceedings of the  International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. III, p. 1099-1111, illus. (incl.  1 table), 1981.  Hart, George E.; and Loomls, Steven A. Erosion from mountain snowpack melt: Journal of Soil and  Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. l, p. 55-57, 1 table, 1982.  Hatcher, Patrick G.; Sehnitzer, Morris; Dennis, Larry W.; et al. Aromaticity of humic substances in  soils: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1089-1094, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Hawley, Mark E.; and MeCuen, Richard H. Water yield estimation in western United States: Journal  of the Irrigation and Drainage Division, Vol. 108, No. IR1, p. 25-34, 6 tables, sketch map, 1982.  Hawley, Mark E.; MeCuen, Richard H.; and Jackson, Thomas J. Volume-accuracy relationship in soil  moisture sampling: Journal of the Irrigation and Drainage Division, Vol. 108, No. IR 1, p. l-11, 3 tables,  1982.  Hendry, M. James. Hydraulic conductivity of a glacial till in Alberta: Ground Water, Vol. 20, No. 2,  p. 162-169, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch maps), 1982.  Hewitt, J.S.;andDexter, A.R. Measurement and comparison ofsoil structures: Applied Mathematical  Modelling, Vol. 5, No. 1, p. 2-12, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.    382    Hill, Deborah C.; Olson, Betty H.; and Rigby, Martin G. Accumulation of cadmium and zinc in soil  and vegetation from long-term application of wast~water: in Proceedings of University of Missouri's  15th annual conference on trace substances in environmental health (Hemphill, Delbert D., editor), Trace  Substances in Environmental Health, No. 15, p. 372-382, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Holdren, George R., Jr.; and Adams, John E. Parabolic dissolution kinetics of silicate minerals; an  artifact of nonequilibrium precipitation processes?: Geology (Boulder), Vol. 10, No. 4, p. 186-190, illus.,  1982.  Holdsworth, P. M.; and Roberts, G. A flow-proportional sampler for plot and lysimeter studies: Journal  of Hydrology, Vol. 57, No. 3-4, p. 389-393, illus., 1982.  Hopps, Howard C. How might geochemical factors affect senescence and age; associated pathology?:  in Aging and the geochemical environment (U. S., National Research Council, Panel on Aging and the  Geochemical Environment), p. 118-126, 1 table, Natl. Acad. Press, Washington, DC, United States,  1981.  Hoyt, Gregory Dana. Nitrogen cycling in a southeastern coastal plain agricultural ecosystem: 180 p.,  Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Georgia, Athens, GA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Hromadka, T. V., II; Guymon, G. L.; and Berg, R. L. Some approaches to modeling phase change in  freezing soils: Cold Regions Science and Technology, Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 137-145, illus., 1981.  Hu Ming hui; Edmond, J. M.; and Stallard, R. F. Major-ion chemistry of the large rivers of China  [abstr.]:  in AGU/ASLO meeting abstracts (Anonymous), Eos, Transactions, American Geophysical  Union, Vol. 63, No. 3, p. 48, 1982.  Hue, Nguyen Van. Effects of phosphorus levels and clays on the nitrification process: 116 p., Doctoral,  1981, Auburn Univ., Auburn, AL. availablefrora: Univ. Microfilms.  Hughes, Harold E. Greene and Lawrence counties, Missouri: 160 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Mo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Huq, Mohdudul. Investigation of rice crop suitability for productivity in terms of soil-geomorphic  conditions in Bangladesh [abstr.]:  in April program abstracts of the 91st annual meeting of the Ohio  Academy of Science; Women in science (Elfner, Lynn Edward, editor), The Ohio Journal of Science,  Vol. 82, No. 2, p. 50, 1982.  James, Robert O.; and Barrow, N.J. Copper reactions with inorganic components of soils including  uptake by oxide and silicate minerals: in Copper in soils and plants; proceedings of the Golden Jubilee  international symposium (Loneragan, J. F., editor; et a/.), p. 47-68, illus. (incl. 1 table), Acad. Press,  Sydney, Australia, 1981.  Jeannet, M. Les rongeurs du gisement acheuleen d'Orgnac 3 (Ardeche): essai de paleoecologie et de  chronostratigraphie [The rodents of the Acheulean Orgnac deposit (Ardeche); paleoecology and  chronostratigraphy]: Soc. Linn. Lyon, Bull., Vol. 50, No. 2, p. 49-71, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Jones, C. A.; Ratllff, L. F.; and Dyke, P.T. Estimation of potentially mineralizable soil nitrogen from  chemical and taxonomic criteria: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 2,  p. 75-86, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Jones, R. C.; Hudnall, W. H.; and Sakai, W. S. Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico; 2,  Mineralogy:  in Characteristics, genesis and classification of strongly weathered soils of Puerto Rico  (Anonymous), Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 1-2, p. 75-137, illus. (incl. 11 anal., 34 tables), 1982.  Katti, R. K.; Sardar, M. G.; Pavate, T. V.; et al. Utilisation of remote sensing in resources identification  and land use in India; an integrated approach: Proceedings of the International Symposium on Remote  Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. III, p. 1487-1497, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Keppens, E.; and Pasteels, P. Comment on the paper "A test of the reliability of the Rb-Sr dates for  selected glauconite morphologies of the Upper Cretaceous (Navesink Formation) of New Jersey", by R.  L. Montag and D. E. Seidemann: Earth and Planetary Science Letters, Vol. 58, No. 3, p. 439-441, 1982.  Keren, R.; and Kauschansky, P. Coating of calcium carbonate on gypsum particle surfaces:  in Soil  Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1242-1244, illus., 1981.    383    Kerr, Richard A. African lakes as alternative oceans: Science, Vol. 215, No. 4539, p. 1491, 1982.  Kilkelly, M. K.; Harbert, H. P.; and Berg, W.A. Revegetation studies on Tosco II and USBM retorted  oil shales: Oil Shale Symposium Proceedings, No. 14, p. 410-421, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1981.  King, d. J.; and Franzmeier, D. P.  Estimation of saturated hydraulic conductivity from soil  morphological and genetic information:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1153-1156, illus.  (incl. 1 table), 1981.  King, J. d.; and Franzmeier, D. P. Morphology, hydrology, and management of Clermont soils:  in  Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science fall meeting (Winslow, D. R., editor), Proceedings of  the Indiana Academy of Science, Vol. 90, p. 416-422, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  King, P. M.  Comparison of methods for measuring severity of water repellence of sandy soils and  assessment of some factors that affect its measurement: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19,  No. 4, p. 275-285, illus. (incl. 4 anal., 5 tables), 1981.  Koussis, Antonis D. Subdomain integration model of ground-water flow; discussion: Journal of the  Irrigation and Drainage Division, Vol. 108, No. IR1, p. 87-88, 1982.  Kubota, Joe; Naphan, E. A.; and Oberly, G. H. Fluoride in thermal spring water and in plants of Nevada  and its relationship to fluorosis in animals: Journal of Range Management, Vol. 35, No. 2, p. 188-192,  illus. (incl. 10 anal., 7 tables, sketch maps), 1982.  Kutilek, M.; Foroud, N.; and Broughton, R. S.  Flood hydrograph simulation model:  Journal of  Hydrology, Vol. 56, No. 3-4, p. 381-385, 1982.  Kutsenko, E. V.  Use of polycomplexes for anchoring wandering sands and controlling deflation of  coarse-textured soils: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 54-57, 3 tables, 1981.  Lamb, John L.  Erosion on abandoned strip-mined land, offsite sediment accumulation, and post-  reclamation stream response, Meigs County, Ohio [abstr.]: in April program abstracts of the 91st annual  meeting of the Ohio Academy of Science; Women in science (Elfner, Lynn Edward, editor), The Ohio  Journal of Science, Vol. 82, No. 2, p. 27-28, 1982.  Laroussi, C.; Touzi, T.; and De Backer, L. W. Hydraulic conductivity of saturated porous media in  relation to their geometrical characteristics: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 6, p. 387-393, illus. (incl. 4  tables), 1981.  Larue, J. P. Contribution a l'etude des formations superficielles recouvrant les nappes alluviales de la  Loire et de ses affluents [The surficial formations covering alluvial aquifers of the Loire and its affluents]:  Bulletin du Laboratoire Rhodanien de Geomorphologie, No. 9, p. 17-37 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl.  sketch map, sect.), 1981.  Leblane, Mare; and Billaud, Pierre. Cobalt arsenide orebodies related to an upper Proterozoic ophiolite;  Bou Azzer (Morocco): Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, Vol.  77, No. 1, p. 162-175, illus. (incl. 314 anal., 2 tables, geol. sketch map), 1982.  Levy, Rachel. Ionic activity product of calcium carbonate precipitated from soil solutions of different  degrees of supersaturation:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1070-1073, illus. (incl. 24 anal.,  2 tables), 1981.  Libardi, P. L.; Reiehardt, K.; Jose, C.; et al. An approximate method of estimating soil water diffusivity  for different soil bulk densities: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 1, p. 177-181, illus. (incl. 1  table), 1982.  Lin, Chenfang. Modeling and simulation of phosphate reaction and transport in acid sandy soils: 196  p., Doctoral, 1981, Rutgers State Univ., New Brunswick, NJ. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Lindberg, Steven E.; Harriss, Robert C.; and Turner, Ralph R. Atmospheric deposition of metals to  forest vegetation: Science, Vol. 215, No. 4540, p. 1609-1611, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Linkes, V. Geografia pod Vysokych Tatier a ich predpolia [Geography of soils of the Upper Tatra  Mountains region and its promontory]: Geograficky Casopis, Vol. 33, No. 1, p. 32-49 (incl. Russian,  English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1981.  Logan, T. d.; Urban, D. R.; Adams, J. R.; et al. Erosion control potential with conservation tillage in  the Lake Erie Basin; estimates using the universal soil loss equation and the land resource information  system (LRIS): Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 1, p. 50-55, 8 tables, sketch map,  1982.    384    Loneragan, J. F.; Robson, A. D.; and Gralmm, R. D. (editors). Copper in soils and plants; proceedings  of the Golden Jubilee international symposium: May 7-9, 1981, Australia. 380 p., illus. (incl. tables),  Acad. Press, Sydney, Australia, 1981.  Long, F. L. A new solid-state device for reading tensiometers: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 131-  132, illus., 1982.  Low, Philip F. The swelling of clay; II1, Dissociation of exchangeable cations: in Soil Science Society  of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal,  Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1074-1078, illus. (incl. 34 anal., 1 table), 1981.  Lyalin, S. P.; and Sokolova, T. A. Composition of the clay fraction in nonpodzolized and weakly  podzolized sand soils of the southern Taiga subzone: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36,  No. 2, p. 23-31, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Lyon, John Grimson. The influence of Lake Michigan water levels on wetland soils and distribution of  plants in the Straits of Mackinac, Michigan: 139 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI,  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  MacDonald, Harold C.; WaRe, William P.; and Demarcke, Janet S. Seasat radar geomorphic  applications in coastal and wetland environments, southeastern U.S.:  in Technical papers of the  American Society of Photogrammetry (Anonymous), Technical Papers of the American Society of  Photogrammetry, Fall Technical Meeting, Vol. 1981, p. 181-190, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1981.  Macias Vazquez, F. Formation of gibbsite in soils and saprolites of temperature-humid zones: Clay  Minerals, Vol. 16, No. I, p. 43-52 (incl. French, German sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Magaritz, iordeckai; and Amiel, Abraham J. Influence of intensive cultivation and irrigation on soil  properties in the Jordan Valley, Israel; recrystallization of carbonate minerals: in Soil Science Society  of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal,  VoL 45, No. 6, p. 1201-1205, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  iakeeva, V. I.; Samoilova, E. M.; and Yarilova, E. A. Characteristics of the structure of typical  Chernozems of the Oka-Don Plain: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 1-6,  2 tables, 1981.  Malone, E.J. Geology, geochemistry and setting of the Woodiawn Deposit: in Geophysical case study  of the Woodlawn Orebody, New South Wales, Australia (Whiteley, Robert J., editor), p. 49-75, illus.  (incl. 1 table, 1 plate, sects., geol. sketch map; geol. maps; geochem, maps 1:70,000), Pergamon Press,  Oxford, United Kingdom, 1981.  Mandul, S. K.; Ran, S. B.; and Sant, B. R. Decomposition of ores by manganese dioxide; analysis of  copper ores and concentrates: Talanta (Oxford), Vol. 28, No. 2, p. 121-122, illus. (incl. 2 tames), 1981.  Matney, E. A.; and Ruhe, R. V. Clay mineral study of soils from the Savannah River Plant, South  Carolina [ahstr.]: in Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science fall meeting (Winslow, D. R.,  editor), Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, Vol. 90, p. 406, 1981.  Matsumoto, G.; Torli, T.; and Hanya, T, High abundance of tong-chain normal alkanoic acids in  Antarctic soil: Nature (London), Vol. 290, No. 5808, p. 688-690, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), I981.  Maxwell, Harold B.; Shade, Steven P.; Roummville, Hayden D.; et al. Soil survey of Union County,  New Mexico: 83 p., illus. (incl. 10 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:443,520), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with N.M. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  McBride, Murray B. Forms and distribution of copper in solid and solution phases of soil: in Copper  in soils and plants; proceedings of the Golden Jubilee international symposium (Loneragan, J. F., editor;  et al.), p. 25-45, 1 table, Acad. Press, Sydney, Australia, 1981.  McCarter, Paul, Jr. Soil survey of Clay County, Indiana: 152 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (PubL in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  McConnell, J. Geochemical follow-up studies in Labrador:  in Current Research (O'Driscoll, C. F.,  editor; et aL), Report - Government of Newfoundland and Labrador, Department of Mines and ]Energy,  Mineral Development Division, VoL 82-1, p. 172-t74, 1 anal., sketch maps, 1982.    385    MeCormaek, D. E.; and Wilding, L. P. Soil properties influencing penetration resistance of Canfield  and Geeburg soils: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1148-1152, illus. (incl. 2 tables), t981.  MeCready, R. G. L; and Krouse, H. R. Sulfur isotope fractionation during the oxidation of elemental  sulfur by thiobacilli in a solonetzic soil: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 105-110  (incl. French sum.), illus., 1982.  MeKeague, J. A.; and Guertin, R.K. Fabrics of some Canadian soils in relation to particle size and other  factors: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 87-102, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1982.  Mead, J. A. A comparison of the Langmuir, Freundlich and Temkin equations to describe phosphate  adsorption properties of soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 333-342, illus. (incl.  38 anal., 3 tables), 1981.  Miles, Randall Jay. Development of soils on terraces associated with the Brazos River in Young and  Throckmorton counties, Texas: 263 p., Doctoral, 1981, Texas A&amp;M Univ., College Station, TX. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.  Milton, Nancy; and Madura, D.P. Map showing vegetation distribution in the central part of the East  Tintic Mountains, Utah: U. S. Geol. Surv., Misc. Field Stud. Map, No. MF-1195, 1 sheet, map 1:24,000,  1981 [1982].  Mizota, Chitoshi; Carraseo, Maria Adriana; and Wada, Koji. Clay mineralogy and some chemical  properties of Ap horizons of Ando soils used for paddy rice in Japan: Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 225-  237, illus. (incl. 13 anal., 4 tables), 1982.  Mohnke, M.; and Hoefling, R. Concentration des gaz rares dans des melanges gazeux pour mesurer les  faibles concentrations [Abundance of noble gases in gaseous mixtures applied to measurement of weak  concentrations]: Pretraduction du Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres, No. 922, 6 p., illus.  (incl. table), 1981.  Mont, H. R.  Soil survey of Champaign County, Illinois:  178 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Ill. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Montag, R. L.; and Seldemann, D. E. A test of the reliability of the Rb-Sr dates for selected glauconite  morphologies of the Upper Cretaceous (Navesink Formation) of New Jersey; reply to the comment by  E. Keppens and P. Pasteels: Earth and Planetary Science Letters, Vol. 58, No. 3, p. 442, 1982.  Morse, Jerome G.; Rana, Mahmood H.; and Morse, Lauren. Radon mapping as indicators of subsurface  oil and gas: Oil and Gas Journal, Vol. 80, No. 19, p. 227-246, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Mossaad, Mostafa El-Sayed. A stochastic model for soil erosion: 189 p., Doctoral, 1981, Ohio State  Univ., Columbus, OH. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Mott, R. J.; and Jaekson, L. E., Jr. An 18,000 year palynological record from the southern Alberta  segment of the classical Wisconsinan "ice-free corridor": Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal  Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, Vol. 19, No. 3, p. 504-513 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. chart, sketch  map), 1982.  Muicahy, M.J. Soil resources and land use in south-western Australia: Journal of the Royal Society  of Western Australia, Vol. 64, Part 3, p. 69-77, sketch maps, 1981.  Munro, D. S. On determining volumetric soil moisture variations in peat by the gravimetric method:  Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 103-110, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Myers, R. J. K.; Campbell, C. A.; and Weier, K. L. Quantitative relationship between net nitrogen  mineralization and moisture content of soils: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 111-  124 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 2 anal., 3 tables), 1982.  Neff, Earl L  Chemical quality and sediment content of runoff water from southeastern Montana  rangeland: Journal of Range Management, Vol. 35, No. 1, p. 130-132, 1982.  Niekell, Allan K.; and Torten, Stanley M. Parent material, landscape, soil interrelationships in Jefferson  County, Indiana [abstr.]: in Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science fall meeting (Winslow, D.  R., editor), Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, Vol. 90, p. 406-407, 1981.    386    Nixon, John R. Soil survey of Mills County, Iowa: 163 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:15,840;  colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States,  1982. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. Sm. Coop. Ext. Serv., Iowa State Univ.; Iowa,  Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Norton, Lloyd Darrell. Loess distribution and pedogenesis of loess-derived soils in East-central Ohio:  245 p., Doctoral, 1981, Ohio State Univ., Columbus, OH. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Nozette, Stewart; and Lewis, John S. Venus; chemical weathering of igneous rocks and buffering of  atmospheric composition: Science, Vol. 216, No. 4542, p. 181-183, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Ogg, Clayton W.; Johnson, James D.; and Clayton, Kenneth C. A policy option for targeting soil  conservation expenditures: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 2, p. 68-72, illus. (incl.  sketch maps), 1982.  Okusami, Temitope Abayomi. Land and pedogenetic characterization of selected wetlands in West  Africa with emphasis for rice production: 373 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Minnesota; Minneapolis, MN.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Olson, Gerald W. Soils and the environment; a guide to soil surveys and their applications: 178 p., illus.  (incl. tables), Chapman and Hall, New York, NY, United States, 1981. (A Dowden &amp; Culver book).  Omorinbola, E. O.  Verification of some geohydrological implications of deep weathering in the  basement complex of Nigeria: Journal of Hydrology, Vol. 56, No. 3-4, p. 347-368, illus. (incl. 6 tables,  geol. sketch map), 1982.  Onodera, Y. Adsorption of heavy metallic ions on clay and other mineral constituants of soil: Nippon  Kogyo Kaishi, Vol. 97, No. 1115, p. 33-40 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Pakshina, S. M.; Esafova, E. N.; Sapozlmikov, P. M.; et al. Effect of hydrophobic interlayers on  evaporation of water and transport of salts in southern Chernozems: Moscow University Soil Science  Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 40-44, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Parker, A.J. Introduction; the chemistry of copper: in Copper in soils and plants; proceedings of the  Golden Jubilee international symposium (Loneragan, J. F., editor; et al.), p. 1-22, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  Acad. Press, Sydney, Australia, 1981.  Parlange, J. Y.; Braddock, R. D.; Simpson, R. W.; et al. Optimization principle for air and water  movement: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 1, p. 4-9, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Parsons, R. W.; and Prentice, L C.  Statistical approaches to R-values and the pollen-vegetation  relationship: Review of Palaeobotany and Palynology, Vol. 32, No. 2-3, p. 127-152, illus. (incl. 5 tables),  1981.  Pavlov, A.V. Thermophysical studies of natural and disturbed landscape complexes in the north of the  U.S.S.R.: Cold Regions Science and Technology, Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 129-135, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1981.  Pawluk, S.; and Dndas, M.J. Pedological investigation of a gray luvisol developed from eolian sand:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 49-60 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch  map), 1982.  Pelletier, Roger T.  Multiresource inventory methods pilot test:  Proceedings of the International  Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol. I, p. 339-355, illus. (incl. sketch map),  1981.  Pesehke, G.; and Kutilek, M. Infiltration model in simulated hydrographs: Journal of Hydrology, Vol.  56, No. 3-4, p. 369-379, illus., 1982.  Piccolo, A.; and Stevenson, F. J. Infrared spectra of Cu2+, Pb2+, and CaR+ complexes of soil humic  substances: Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 195-208, illus., 1982.  Pietrzak, R. F.; Czyseinski, K. S.; and Weiss, A. J. Sorption measurements performed under site-  specific conditions; Maxey Fiats, Kentucky, and West Valley, New York, disposal sites: Nuclear and  Chemical Waste Management, Vol. 2, No. 4, p. 279-285, 4 tables, 1981.  Pingond, Kim. A lumped-parameter model for infiltration: Journal of Hydrology, Vot. 57, No. 1-2, p.  175-185, illus., 1982.  Poweil, John W.; Bowden, Gall L.; Latiolais, Donny L.; et al. Soil survey of Pointe Coupee and West  Baton Rouge parishes, Louisiana: 90 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps  1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop.  with La. Agric. Exp. Stn.; La. Soil Water Conserv. Comm.).    387    Preston, Michael B.; and Szabo, John P. Hydrology and geomorphology of Chippewa Creek Basin,  Cuyahoga County, Ohio [abstr.]:  in April program abstracts of the 91st annual meeting of the Ohio  Academy of Science; Women in science (Elfner, Lynn Edward, editor), The Ohio Journal of Science,  Vol. 82, No. 2, p. 28, 1982.  Prospero, J. M.; Glaccum, R. A.; and Nees, R.T. Atmospheric transport of soil dust from Africa to  South America: Nature (London), Vol. 289, No. 5798, p. 570-572, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Prost, R.; and Huard, E. Organisation de l'eau dans les milieux poreux ou concentres en solides [The  organization of water in porous or solidly concentrated media]: 61 p., illus. (incl. table), 1981. (Rep. No.  DGRST77 7 1554) availablefrom:CNRS-AR 8602, France.  Raad, Lufti. A mechanistic model for strength and fatique ofcement-treated soils: ASTMGeotechnical  Testing Journal, Vol. 4, No. 3, p. 104-110, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Rabenhorst, M. C,; and Fuss, J.E. Soil and geologic mapping over mafic and ultramafic parent materials  in Maryland: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1156-1160, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Rafahi, H. Proprietes physico-chimiques et mineralogiques des sols des forets de chenes de l'ouest de  l'Iran [The physico-chemical and mineralogical properties of the soils of the oak forests of western Iran]:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 39-48 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 1 anal., sketch  map), 1982.  Ragab, R.; Feyen, J.; and Hillel, D. Comparison of experimental and simulated infiltration profiles in  sand: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 1, p. 61-64, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Richardson, Curtis J. E.; Evans, Rhonda; and Cart, David. Pocosins; an ecosystem in transition:  in  Pocosin wetlands; an integrated analysis of coastal plain freshwater bogs in North Carolina (Richardson,  Curtis J., editor; et al.), p. 3-19, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch maps), Hutchinson Ross Publ. Co.,  Stroudsburg, PA, United States, 1981.  Richardson, J. L.; and Bigler, R.J. Comparison of Walkley-Black and dry combustion organic carbon  determinations in calcareous water-logged North Dakota soils: Communications in Soil Science and  Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 3, p. 175-183, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Ringwood, A. E.; Oversby, V. M.; Kesson, S. E.; et aL Immobilization of high-level nuclear reactor  wastes in SYNROC; a current appraisal: Nuclear and Chemical Waste Management, Vol. 2, No. 4, p.  287-305, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Rodrigues, Francisco Soland de Oliveira. Evaluation of some chemical methods for predicting the  availability oforganic soilnitrogen: 102 p., 62 anal., Doctoral, 1981, Mississippi State Univ., Mississippi  State, MS. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Ross, D. S.; and Bartlett, R.J. Evidence for nonmicrobial oxidation of manganese in soil: Soil Science,  Vol. 132, No. 2, p. 153-160, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Ross, G. J.; Wang, C.; Ozkan, A. I.; et aL Weathering of chlorite and mica in a New Brunswick Podzol  developed on till derived from chlorite-mica schist: Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 255-267, illus. (incl.  6 anal., 5 tables), 1982.  Rowe, R.K. The determination of rock mass modulus variation with depth for weathered or jointed rock:  Canadian Geotechnical Journal=Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 29-43 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Rubio-Montoya, David.  Determination of the erodibility factor of soils and lignite spoils:  91 p.,  Doctoral, 1981, Texas A&amp;M Univ., College Station, TX. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Sadowski, Frank G. Alternative approaches for utilizing Landsat data to address forest and range  applications [abstr.]:  in Machine processing of remotely sensed data, with special emphasis on range,  forest, and wetlands assessment (Holler, Roger M., chairperson; et al.), Proceedings, Annual Symposium  - Machine Processing of Remotely Sensed Data, No. 7, p. 19, 1981.  Sastri, G. G. K.; attd Sastry, C. S. Chemical characteristics and evolution of the laterite profile in  Hazaridadar bauxite plateau, Madhya Pradesb, India: Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society  of Economic Geologists, Vol. 77, No. 1, p. 154-161, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1982.    388    Santter, Howard. Soil survey of Otoe County, Nebraska:  146 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Nebr., Conserv. Sere. Die.).  Schalseha, E. B.; Ahumada, I.; and Pratt, P. F. Effects of time and leaching on phosphate-induced  increase in cation exchange capacity in volcanic ash soils: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th  annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p.  1237-1238, 2 tables, 1981.  Sehwertmann, U.; Murad, E.; and Sehulze, D. G. Is there Hotocene reddening (hematite formation)  in soils of axeric temperate areas?: Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 209-223, illus. (incl. 12 anal., 3 tables,  sketch map), 1982.  Sears, Stephen O.; and Langmuir, Don~d- Sorption and mineral equilibria controls on moisture  chemistry in a C-horizon soil: Journal of Hydrology, Vol. 56, No. 3-4, p. 287-308, illus. (incl. 146 anal.,  3 tables), 1982.  Shamberger, R. J. Selenium in the environment: The Science of the Total Environment, Vet. 17, No.  1, p. 59-74, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Shah Xiao.quan; Jin Long-zhu; and Ni Zhe-ming. Determination of selenium in soil digests by graphite  furnace atomic absorption spectrometry after extraction with 1,2-diamino-4 nitrobenzene: Atomic  Spectroscopy, Vet. 3, No. 2, p. 41-44 (incl. French, German sum.), illus. (incl. 4 anal.), 1982.  Sharma, P. P.; Gantzer, C. J.; and BlJdke, G.R. Hydraulic gradients across simulated rain-formed soil  surface seals: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1031-1034, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Sharpley, A.; Simmons, D.; and E[wileton, G. Effect of storage time on the soluble phosphorus  concentration of unfiltered runoff samples: Proceedings of the Oklahoma Academy of Science, Vol. 61,  p. 67-71, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Sheppard, J. C.; Westberg, H.; Hopper, J. F.; et al. Inventory of global methane sources and their  production rates: JGR. Journal of Geophysical Research. C. Oceans and Atmospheres, Vol. 87, p. 1305-  1312, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Sheridan, M. F.; and Moore, C.B. Carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur variation in the Bishop Tuff, California:  Lithos, Vol. 14, No. 1, p. 23-27, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Sheta, Mohamed; and Novsk, Miles. Vertical vibration of pile groups: Journal of the Geotechnical  Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. GT4, p. 570-590, illus., 1982.  Shih, S. F.; Vmader~fft, D. C.; Myhr D. L.; et aL The effect of land forming on subsidence in the  Florida Everglades' organic soil: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B.  A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1206-1209, illus. (incl. 3 tables),  1981.  Shoji, Sadao; Fujiwara, Ymuhi; Yambia, Ichiro; et aL Chemistry and clay mineralogy of ando soils,  Brown forest soils, and podzolic soils formed from Recent Towada ashes, northeastern Japan: Soil  Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 69-86, illus. (incl. 46 anal., 6 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Shoji, Sadao; Yamada, Ielflro; and Kuruhima, Keel. Mobilities and related factors of chemical  elements in the topsoils of Andosols in Tohoktl, Japan; 2, Chemical and mineralogical compositions of  size fractions and factors influencing the mobilities of major chemical elements: Soil Science, Vol. 132,  No. 5, p. 330-346, illus. (incl. 10 anal., 8 tables), 1981.  Shukla, J.; trod Mlmtz, Y. Infiuce of land-surface evapotranspiration on the Earth's climate: Science,  Vol. 215, No. 4539, p. 1498-1501, sketch maps, 1982.  Slbul, R. A.; S~va, V. P.; mul Po~hty~fl~ov, A.I. Change in soil resistivity and the parcel structure  of a biogeocenos Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 50.53, 2 tables, 1981.  Siqei, B. Z.; sad Siqel, S.M. Mercury content of Equisetum plants around Mount St. Helens one  year after the major eruption: Science, Vol. 216, No. 4543, p. 292-293, illus. (incl. 15 anal., 2 tables),  1982.  SiagL M.; Si~i]~, N.; ~MI R~, P. S. Adsorption and desorption of selenite and sclenate selenium on  different soils: Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 2, p. 134-141, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.    389    Sizgorie, M. Alteration of nickel sulfide ores and its effect on their flotation: in Process mineralogy;  extractive metallurgy, mineral exploration, energy resources (Hausen, Donald M., editor; et al.), p. 225-  232, illus. (incl. 1 table), Am. Inst. Min. and Metall., New York, NY, United States, 1981. llOthAIME  annual meeting, TMS-AIME Process Mineralogy Committee.  Smith, Robert V. Soil survey of Beaver and Lawrence counties, Pennsylvania: 192 p., illus. (incl. 17  tables; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep.  Environ. Resour., State Conserv. Comm.).  Sondheim, M. W.; and Lavkulieh, L. M.  Comparison of some podzolic horizons using chemical  properties and the multivariate density equation: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p.  91-96 (incl. French sum.), 4 tables, 1982.  Spalding, B. P.; and Hoffman, W. A., Jr. Soil radiochromatography using 22Na, 85Sr, and 58Co: ORNL-  TM (Oak Ridge National Laboratory), No. 8138 (Environ. ScL Div. Publ. No. 1892), 36 p., illus. (incl. 3  anal.), 1982. available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.  Spalding, Brian P, Precipitation of radiostrontium in soil:  in Proceedings of the Third international  symposium on the scientific basis for nuclear waste management (Moore, John G., editor), Vol. 3, p. 243-  250, illus. (incl. 1 table), Plenum Press, New York, NY, United States, 1981.  Sparks, D. L.; and Jardine, P. M. Thermodynamics of potassium exchange in soil using a kinetics  approach:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1094-1099, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Sparks, D. L.; and Liebhardt, W. C. Temperature effects on potassium exchange and selectivity in  Delaware soils: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 1, p. 10-17, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Sposito, Garrison; Holtzelaw, Kenneth M.; Johnston, CliffT.; et al. Thermodynamics of sodium-copper  exchange on Wyoming bentonite at 298"K:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1079-1084, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Ssali, H.; and Nuwamanya, J.K. Soil acidity components of tropical acid soils; their roles in determining  lime requirement values and the effect of lime upon them: Communications in Soil Science and Plant  Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 3, p. 203-214, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Starr, J. L.; Parlange, J. Y.; and Braddock, R.D. Dispersion in soil columns; the precursor effect: Soil  Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 111-115, illus., 1982.  Stednick, John D, Hydrochemical balance of an alpine watershed in Southeast Alaska: Arctic and  Alpine Research, Vol. 13, No. 4, p. 431-438, 4 tables, sketch maps, 1981.  Stedniek, John D.; Tripp, Larry N.; and McDonald, Robert J. Slash burning effects on soil and water  chemistry in southeastern Alaska: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, Vol. 37, No. 2, p. 126-128,  3 tables, sketch map, 1982.  Stephens, Floyd G. Soil survey of Tulare County, California, central part: 165 p., illus. (incl. 16 tables;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Stephens, Peter R.; and Cihlar, Josef. The potential of remote sensing to monitor soil erosion on  cropland: Proceedings of the International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 15, Vol.  II, p. 985-995, illus. (incl. 8 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Stephenson, Stephen L. Exposure-induced differences in the vegetation, soils, and microclimate of  north- and south-facing slopes in southwestern Virginia: Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 33, No. 1  (Spring), p. 36-50, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Stevenson, F. J.; and Fitch, Alanah. Reactions with organic matter:  in Copper in soils and plants;  proceedings of the Golden Jubilee international symposium (Loneragan, J. F., editor; eta/.), p. 69-95,  illus. (incl. 5 tables), Acad. Press, Sydney, Australia, 1981.  Stewart, B. A. (president). Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting: Nov. 29-Dec. 4,  1981, United States. Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1007-1246, illus. (incl.  87 tables, sketch maps), 1981.    390    Stieff, L. R. Studies of an improved polonium-120 analytical procedure and the distribution and  transport of uranium and its alpha emitting daughters using nuclear emulsions; final report: 120 p., illus.  (incl. 16 tables), 1981. (Rep. No. GJBX-111(82)) available from: U. S. Dep. Energy, Grand Junction Off.,  Grand Junction, CO, United States.  Stone, Earl L. Persistence of potassium in forest systems; further studies with the rubidium/potassium  technique: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1215-1218, 7 tables, 1981.  Stoner, E. R.; and Baumgardner, M.F. Characteristic variations in reflectance of surface soils: in Soil  Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1161-1165, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Straub, William A.; mad Lynch, Daniel R. Models of landfill leaching; moisture flow and inorganic  strength: Journal of the Environmental Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. EE2, p. 231-250, illus..  1982.  Straub, William A.; and Lynch, Daniel R. Models of landfill leaching; inorganic strength: Journal of  the Environmental Engineering Division, Vol. 108, No. EE2, p. 251-268, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Sundmacker, Harvey. Controlling sediment by watershed management techniques: in Proceedings of  a round table on reclaiming and managing lakes in Illinois (Keasler, Linda, editor), Special Report - Water  Resources Center, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, No. 12, p. 77-80, 1981.  Sykes, J. F.; Soyupatk, S.; and Farquhar, G.J. Modeling of leachate organic migration and attenuation  in groundwaters below sanitary landfills: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 1, p. 135-145, 2 tables,  1982.  Tam, S.W. Causes of environmental deterioration in eastern Barbados since colonization: Agriculture  and Environment, Vol. 5, No. 4, p. 285-308, 1981.  Tiller, Kevin G,; and Merry, Richard H. Copper pollution of agricultural soils: in Copper in soils and  plants; proceedings of the Golden Jubilee international symposium (Loneragan, J. F., editor; et al.), p  119-137, 3 tables, Acad. Press, Sydney, Australia, 1981.  Trenhaile, A. S.; and Rudlkas, P.A. Freeze-thaw and shore platform development in Gaspe, Quebec:  Geographic Physique et Quaternairc, Vol. 35, No. 2 (Morphologie littorale et marine), p. 171-181 (incl  French, German sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch), 1981.  Troeh, Frederick R.; Jabro, Jalal D.; and Kirk.hem, Don. Gaseous diffusion equations for porous  materials: Geoderma, Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 239-253, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Ukraintseva, V. V. Vegetation of warm late Pleistocene intervals and the extinction of some large  herbivorous mammals: Polar Geography and Geology, Vol. 5, No. 4, p. 189-203, illus. (incl. 1 table,  sketch map), 1981.  Utgard, Russell O.; and McKenzic, Garry D.  Monitoring erosion on a clearcut watershed near  Lancaster, Ohio [abstr.]: in April program abstracts of the 91st annual meeting of the Ohio Academy  of Science; Women in science (Elfner, Lynn Edward, editor), The Ohio Journal of Science, Vot. 82, No.  2, p. 27, 1982.  Vadyunina, A. F.; Sokolova, T. A.; Oleshko, K. P.; et aL Alteration of the clay material of "chocolate"  clay under the effect of an electric current: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2,  p. 45-49, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Vieira, S. R.; Nielsen, D. R.; and BilBar, J. W. Spatial variability of field-measured infiltration rate:  in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1040-1048, illus., 1981.  Walker, Robert D. A major water quality problem in Illinois; soil movement from the watershed and  channel: in Proceedings of a round table on reclaiming and managing lakes in illinois (Keasler, Linda,  editor), Special Report - Water Resources Center, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, No. 12,  p. 1-3, 1981.  Wang, C.; and McKeague, J.A. Illuviated clay in sandy podzolic soils of New Brunswick: Canadian  Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 62, No. 1, p. 79-89 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 anal., 2 tables), 1982.    391    Wang, M. K.; Greenhut, V. A.; and Hsu, Pa Ho. Electron microscopic study of hematite growth habits:  Soil Science, Vol. 132, No. 2, p. 182-187, illus., 1981.  Watson, K. K.; and Jones, M. J.  Estimation of hydrodynamic dispersion in a fine sand using an  approximate analytical solution: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 265-273, illus.,  1981.  Watson, Keith K.; and Jones, M.J. Hydrodynamic dispersion during absorption in a fine sand; 1, The  constant concentration case: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 1, p. 91-100, illus., 1982.  Weyer, K. U.; and Horwood-Brown, W. C. Program HVRLV 1; interactive determination of horizontal  permeabilities within uniform soils from field tests using Hvorslev's formulae: Ground Water, Vol. 20,  No. 3, p. 289-297, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  White, B. R.; and Greeley, Ronald. Soil transport by winds on Venus: NASA Technical Memorandum,  No. 84211, p. 201-202, 1981.  White, James M.; and Mathewes, Roll W. Holocene vegetation and climatic change in the Peace River  District, Canada: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences=Journal Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, Vol.  19, No. 3, p. 555-570 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. charts, sketch map), 1982.  Wood, R. M. Decay in the Karakorum: New Sci., Vol. 89, No. 1246, p. 820-823, illus., 1981.  Yakimenko, V. I. Physics and amelioration of soils: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36,  No. 2, p. 32-39, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Yanosky, T.M. Effects of flooding upon woody vegetation along parts of the Potomac River flood plain:  Geological Survey Professional Paper, No. 1206, 21 p., illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch maps), 1982.  Young, Jack F. Soil survey of Teton County, Wyoming, Grand Teton National Park area: 173 p., illus.  (incl. 13 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Wyo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Zaehmann, D. W.; DuChateau, P. C.; and Kiute, A. The calibration of the Richards flow equation for  a draining column by parameter identification: in Soil Science Society of America, 45th annual meeting  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 6, p. 1012-1015, 4  tables, 1981.  Zborishehuk, Yu.N. FactorsandprocessofsoilformationintheTwenteregion(Netherlands): Moscow  University Soil Science Bulletin, Vol. 36, No. 2, p. 67-69, 1981.                                                                                                                        