V    PREFACE    This special issue of Geoderma is the result of the work of members  of the "International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed  Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)". The papers are from the second workshop  of IWGSUSM, organized in 1981 by J. Ducloux at the University of Poitiers,  France; the symposium on "Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials"  organized in 1981 by M.L. Thompson in Atlanta, Georgia, U.S.A. during  the annual meeting of the Soil Science Socmty of America, and work done  in 1982. The papers mainly concern in situ electron microscopic studies  of materials in thin sections of softs and of unimpregnated soft constituents  in peds. Ion microscopy is discussed in one paper.  The plan to start IWGSUSM originated in 1975, but it was 1979 before  E.B.A. Bisdom could write the first circular letter. By this time sufficient  new submicroscopic techniques had been tested to allow detailed studies  of soil conshtuents in thin sections. One of the problems, then and now,  is however, that the costs of using electron microscopes, ion microscopes,  laser microprobe mass analyzers, etc. are rather high and that the inter-  pretation of data can be intricate. Consequently, an international organiza-  tion was founded to assess the significance of projects and to start cooper-  ative efforts. Such cooperation between specialized laboratories should  facilitate the study of intricate problems. Various specialists joined IWGSUSM,  i.e. soil mmromorphologlsts, soil physicists, soil chemists, engineers in soil  mechanics, geologtsts, geographers, biologists, etc. The first results of three  cooperative research projects, i.e. on soil pollution, the characterization of  orgamc matter in Vertisols, and the effects of the application of sewage  sludge and pig slurry on surface crusts of cultivated soils are discussed.  The first workshop of IWGSUSM was organized by E.B.A. Bisdom in  1980 at the Netherlands Soft Survey Institute, Wagenmgen, The Netherlands.  A book Submzcroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks contains papers  presented at this workshop plus introductory articles on techmques and  instruments used in submicroscopy, and review articles which discuss in  situ submicroscopic work done in soil science. The present special issue  of Geoderma, which will also appear as a book in the series "Developments  in Soil Science", gives various technical papers and practical applications  of submlcroscopy in soil science. Some papers discuss purely submicro-  scopic subjects, whereas submicroscopy is used in other papers as one  of a number of techniques.  Most submicroscopic studies start by using the light microscope to in-  vestigate soil constituents in thin sections and unhardened soil peds. Such  work is usually done by soil micromorphologlsts and specialists in, for  example, soil mechanics. Soil physicists are attracted by this type of in  sltu work because by using the combination of light microscopy and sub-  mmroscopy it can be seen where transported soil particles have been de-  posited in the soil profile -- especially under controlled experimental con-    0016--7061/83/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V    v1    ditlons -- and data on very free and larger pores (voids) can be collected  by using an image analyzer to study the porosity m mmrographs obtained  by light microscopy and electron microscopy. The soil chemist, who usually  works with wet chemistry and disturbed bulk samples, is attracted by  the m situ mmrochemical results obtamed from dry samples by various  submmroscopm  techmques.  Amorphous,  poorly crystalline and clayey  materials in thin sections will usually be of interest for the microanalysis  of chemical elements  Submicroscopy is a young fmld of soil science which can help different  speciahzatlons by giving various types of in situ information. IWGSUSM  was an independent organization until the end of 1982 and will form part  of the "Subcommission on Soil Micromorphology" of the "International  Socmty of Soil Science" in 1983. Colleagues who are interested in the  submicroscopic work of IWGSUSM can contact the secretary E.B.A. Bisdom,  or the orgamzers of sister organizations outside Western Europe, 1.e., S.  Zauyah (Asia), C.B. Wells (Austraha and New Zeeland), M.L. Thompson  (Canada and USA), T. Tursma (Eastern Europe} and J.J. de Oliveira (Latin  America).  Assistance in the preparation of this volume was given by the Techmcal  Staff of the Netherlands Soil Survey Institute.    E.B.A. Bisdom and J. Ducloux    VOLUME 30 NOS. 1--4  SPECIAL ISSUE  SUBMICROSCOPIC STUDIES OF SOILS    VII    edited by  E B.A BISDOM and J. DUCLOUX    Editorial Committee'  A. BOEKESTEIN, P. CURMI, C. JEANSON, C. FOX, S. LEDIN, P.J. LOVELAND,  P. SMART, G. STOOPS, M L. THOMPSON, and C.B. WELLS    CONTENTS    Preface  ....  List of abbreviations  ........      ........................  V    ........................  IX    Cooperative Research Projects  Submicroscopy and chemistry of heavy-metal-contaminated precipitates  from column experiments simulating conditions m a soil beneath a landfill  E B A. Blsdom, A. Boekestein (Wageningen, The Netherlands), P. Curmi  (Rennes, France), P. Lagas (Leidschendam, The Netherlands), A.C. Letsch  (Petten, The Netherlands), J.P.G Loch (Leidschendam, The Netherlands),  R. Nauta (Eindhoven, The Netherlands) and C B. Wells (Glen Osmond,  S.A., Australia)  ......................................  1  Characterization of in situ organic matter constituents in vertisols from  Argentina, using submicroscopic and cytochemical methods -- First report  S Stephan (Bonn, F.R. Germany), J. Berrier (Versailles, France),  A.A. De Petre (Tezanos Pinto, E.R., Argentina), C. Jeanson (Brunoy,  France), M.J. Kooistra (Wageningen, The Netherlands), H.W Scharpenseel  and H Schlffmann (Hamburg, F R. Germany)  ............  21  Changes in surface structure (crusting) after application of sewage sludge and  pig slurry to culhvated agricultural soils in northern Italy  M. Paghai (Pisa, Italy), E.B.A Bisdom (Wageningen, The Netherlands) and  S. Ledin (Uppsala, Sweden)  .......................  35    Submicroscopic Techniques  Etched thin sections for coupled optical and electron microscopy and micro-  analysis  L.D. Norton, J.M Bigham, G.F. Hall, and N.E. Smeck (Columbus,  Ohio, U.S.A.)  ......................................  55  Microradiography as a submicroscopic tool  L.R. Drees and L.P. Wilding (College Station, Texas, U.S.A.)  .........  65  STEM-EDXRA and SEM-EDXRA investigation of iron-coated organic  matter m thin sections with transmitted, secondary and backscattered  electrons  E B.A. Bisdom (Wageningen, The Netherlands), R. Nauta and B. Volbert  (Emdhoven, The Netherlands)  ......................  77  Variations in backscattered electron(BSE) images with a Scanning Electron  Microscope(SEM) as applied to mineral grains and excrements in a podzol,  to precipitates on a water-tube filter and to bauxite  E.B.A. Bisdom, F Thiel (Wageningen, The Netherlands), B. Volbert and  J. Jackman (Eindhoven, The Netherlands)  ......................  93  Quantitative analysis of trace and major elements in thin sechons of soils  with the secondary ion microscope(Cameca)  E.B.A Bisdom, S. Henstra (Wageningen, The Netherlands), H.W. Werner,  P.R. Boudewijn, W.F. Knippenberg, H.A.M. de Grefte (Elndhoven, The  Netherlands), J.M Gourgout and H.N. Migeon (Courbevoie, France)  .......  117    VIII    Applied Submicroscopy  Effect of potassium on soil structure in relation to hydrauhc conductivity  Y. Chen, A. Banin and A. Borochovitch (Rehovot, Israel). _                       ] 35  Lightmicroscope and submicroscope observations of salts in marine  alluvmm (India)  M.J Komstra (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  .....  149  An optical, scanning electron microscopic and mlcroanalytical study of  cementation in some podzols  W J McHardy and L Robertson (Aberdeen, Great Britain)  .....  161  Calcium-dominated organans in Humic Podzols from the Hudson and James  Bay Lowlands of Ontario, Canada  R Protz (Guelph, Ontario, Canada)  ...........  171  SEM and light mmroscopm observations of minerals m bog-ores of the  Belgian Camplne  G. Stoops (Gent, Belgium)  ................  179  Submicroscopm characterisatlon of phosphatic and sesquioxldm nodules of  some soils of the "Chaco Deprimido" (Argentina):  preliminary results  H.J.M Morris (Castelar, Argentina)  .................  187  Characteristms and sigmficance of composite particles derived from a  Colombian andosol profile  P A. Riezebos and W.J Lustenhouwer (Amsterdam, The Netherlands)         . _  195  SEM-EDXRA investigation of tubular features and iron nodules in lateritic  smls from Malaysia  S Zauyah (Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia) and E.B.A Bisdom (Wageningen,  The Netherlands)  ...............  219  Fabric sequences as related to genetic processes in two Alberta soils  S. Pawluk (Edmonton, Alta., Canada)  .............  233  Scanning electron microscopy of engineering soils  K Collins (Glasgow, Strathclyde, Great Britain)  ..............  243  SEM-EDXRA studies of precipitates which clogged a water-tube filter  E.B_A Blsdom and A. Jongerius (Wagenmgen, The Netherlands)                  253    Applied Submicroscopy and Image Analysis  Quantimet 720 analysis of porosities m backscattered electron scanning  images made with different photo-techniques  D. Schoonderbeek, F Thiel, and E B.A. Bisdom (Wageningen, The Netherlands).  271  The characterization of microporosity in a ploughpan by submicroscopm and  Quantlmet techniques  A Jager, O Boersma and E B.A. Bisdom (Wagenmgen, The Netherlands)  ......  277  The development of soil porosity in experimental sandy soils with clay  admixtures as examined by Quantimet 720 from BESI and by other  techniques  J Chrdtien (Dijon, France) and E.B A Bisdom (Wageningen, The    .....  285  Netherlands)  ...........................  The characterization of the shape of mineral grains in thin sections of soils  by Quantimet and BESI  E B.A. Bisdom and D Schoonderbeek (Wageningen, The Netherlands)        . .  303  Porosity measurements and form analysis of mineral grains in thin sections  from oil--gas reservoir rocks using Quantimet 720 and BESI  E.B A. Bisdom (Wageningen, The Netherlands), H.A van Adrmhem  Boogaert (Haarlem, The Netherlands), G. Heintzberger, D. Schoonderbeek  and F. Thiel (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  ...........  323  Subject Index  ........................  339                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   