350    Ecology of a Subarctic Mire. M. Sonesson (Editor). Ecol. Bull. 30. Swedish  Natural Science Research Council, Stockholm, 1980, 315 pp., SwCr.  125.00.    This book deals with the various aspects of structure and processes of a  subarctic more ecosystem at Stordalen near Abisko, northern Sweden  381'N 195'E). The mire exists under the extreme conditions represented  by tundra on permafrost. Study of this mire, as part of the 1964--1974  International Biological Programme, was conducted under international  guide-lines and was directed toward a better understanding of the circum-  polar tundra relative to the needs of man. The volume written in English  represents a compendium of collaborative reports by various individuals and  organizations in Sweden.  Each chapter contains a documentation of data and a discussion of the  factors involved in the particular study being considered. The book begins  with an introductory chapter on objectives, and progresses consecutively  through reports on (1) physical properties of the soil-water system, (2)  climatic factors, (3) supply and transport of nutrient minerals, (4) plant  distribution, (5) plant communities, (6) area-harvesting and biomass changes,  (7, 8) diurnal dry weight variation and dry-matter allocation of selected  plants, (9) microecology of Sphagnum photosynthesis, (10) ecologic factors  of Sphagnum growth, (11) nitrogen cycling, (12) carbon dioxide and methane  fluxes, (13) thawing and freezing, and (14) energy flow. The volume contains  an Appendix of previous publications relating to the study, and also a Subject  Index.  Independent investigations and isolated publications of parts of a complex  problem can, in this reviewer's opinion, lead to serious misunderstandings  of the total system. This book, on the other hand, represents a fine documen-  tation of many of the complex and interrelated variables that pertain to a  particular ecosystem. The interdisciplinary value of the volume could have  been enhanced by the inclusion of a final chapter, in which an attempt was  made to integrate the major conclusions of the various studies into a more  comprehensive overview of the total system. The book can be read not only  for specific content depending upon one's research interests, but it is also an  excellent example of the scope of investigation and the team approach  necessary for a better understanding of the complex biological and physical  interrelationships that exist in nature.    Ch.J. SMILEY  (Moscow, Idaho)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               