 Geoderma, 32 (1984) 203--226                                                         203  Elsevier Science Pubhshers B.V , Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    TEXTURAL DIFFERENTIATION IN CHRONOSEQUENCES FROM  EASTERN AUSTRALIA, II. EVIDENCE FROM PARTICLE-SIZE  DISTRIBUTIONS    D J CHITTLEBOROUGH*~, P H WALKER and J.M OADES  *Department of Agriculture, Box 1671 GPO Adelaide, S A 5001 (A ustraha)  Dw,sion of Sozls, CSIRO, P.O Box 639, Canberra Czty, A C T. 2601 (Australia)  Department of Soll Science, Waite Agrwultural Research Institute, Unwerslty of  Adelaide, Glen Osmond, S A_ 5064 (Australia)  (Received June 29, 1982, revised version accepted May 6, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Chittleborough, D J , Walker, P.H. and Oades, J M , 1984 Textural differentiation in  chronosequences from eastern Australia, II. Evidence from particle-size dlstnbutmns  Geoderma, 32 203--226    Data from particle-size analyses were used to determine the relative importance of the  four mechanisms proposed to explain the development of strong textural contrast m the  end members of four chronosequences  The mechanisms proposed were sedimentary  layering, m-sltu chemical weathering, clay illuvlation and physical breakdown  Depth functions of fine clay total clay ratios and detailed particle-size distmbutlons at   intervals from 0.6 um to 2000 um indicated that there had been a marked increase in  fine clay in the B horizons of the older soils of each sequence, a result consistent with,  but not proving, a clay llluvlatlon hypothesis Cumulative particle-size distmbution radices  showed that most profiles had texturally uniform parent materials Changes m the ratio  free silt  total silt with depth were slight for all but one profile, indicating no significant  contribution to the clay fraction by m-sltu chemical weathering of the silt fraction.  From changes in the depth functions of gravel with time, it was concluded that physi-  cal breakdown had occurred but that It had not been responsible for the development of  the textural B horizon The rate of disintegration was particularly high early in pedogene-  sis, preceding the development of texture-contrast. Breakdown contributed fines to the  whole solum and was not generally any more intense m one horizon than another. Grain  counts of rock fragments m the medium sand range lent support to this conclusion.  Changes in the particle-size distribution of quartz from 0.2 am to 2000 um indmated  that the contribution to the clay fraction from physical dlsintegratmn was only slight_    INTRODUCTION    The particle-size distribution down a soil profile can provide evidence  which helps to distinguish between four hypotheses to explain the origin of  the clay B horizon vlz. sedimentary layering, formation of clay by m situ    ,1 Present address' Department of Soil Scmnce, Waite Agrmultural Research Institute,  Umversity of Adelaide, Glen Osmond, S.A 5064 (Australia)    0016-7061/84/$03 00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B V.    204    chemical weathering, downward translocation of clay and physical weather-  ing (Chittleborough and Oades, 1979)  Ruhe (1956) used the presence of stone lines and Foss and Rust (1968)  used particle-size distributions of silt and sand fractions to identify stratified  sediments in soils. Methods for the statistical identifmatlon of such discon-  tinuities in the depth function have been developed by Oertel and Giles  (1966) and more fully by Raad and Protz (1971). Langohr and Van Vhet  (1979) have proposed a comparative particle-size distribution (CPSD) index  to estimate the magnitude of discontinuities (or similarities) in parent ma-  terials.  Little use has been made of partmle-slze properties of soils to assess the  extent of chemical weathering, despite the fact that the process is hkely to  have a marked effect on the particle-size distribution. It is often referred,  from an mcrease m clay content, that there has been an increase in chemmal  weathering but there is mvariably no evidence provided. Torrent and Nettle-  ton (1979) proposed a textural index for assessing chemical weathering in  soils based on the change with depth of the ratio of fine silt to total silt.  An increase m the proportion of fine clay (&lt;~0.2 um) to coarse clay has  been taken as an indication that clay has been illuviated. There appear to be  two reasons for this inference. One is that a high ratio of fine to coarse clay  is observed in horizons with higher total clay and which also show other  signs that clay has moved, e.g. the presence of void argillans (Smith and  Buol, 1968). Second, experimental evidence shows that fine clay moves  more readily than coarse clay (Dixit, 1978). It should be pomted out that  an increase in the ratio is not definitive evidence for clay illuviation. Other  mechanisms may also be revolved, e.g. lateral transport of clay into the hori-  zon and chemical weathering (Byers et al., 1938; Nikiforoff and Drosdoff,  1943).  There is a paucity of data for the role of physical breakdown of sand and  silt in soil profile development; the vast majority of pedogenetic studies have  been concerned with the nature and extent of chemical and biological weath-  ering mechanisms. The physical breakdown of rock fragments and individ-  ual minerals has been attributed to frost action (Zeuner, 1949; Arnaud and  Whiteside, 1963; Bronger and Kalk, 1976; Nornberg, 1980). In temperate  regions not subject to frosts, or only infrequently so, however, there will be  no freezing and thawing. Smeck et al. (1981) found that shale disintegration  contributed clay to the B2 horizon but that chemical weathering of coarse  clay and silt to fine clay was the dominant pedogenetic process.  Brewer and Walker (1969) noted a decrease in the presence of rock frag-  ments with age in a sequence of soils at Kempsey. Possibly bloturbation and  the action of shrinking and swelling may have aided disintegration of rock  fragments and mineral grains initially weakened during transport and depo-  sition. Moss (1973) and Moss and Green (1975) noted marked weakening  of quartz grains, in the form of microfractures, from alluvial deposits and    205    concluded that repeated static loading and collective movement in water  weakened the particles considerably. Ritchie et al. (1974) observed that  volume changes and fabric re-arrangement associated with the genesis of an  argillic horizon largely obliterated traces of rock structure in glacial till.  The purpose of this paper is to defme the mechamsm(s) involved in tex-  tural differentiation using particle-size distributions. The soils used m this  study form part of four chronosequences, the physical and chemmal proper-  ties of which have been described in Part I (Chlttleborough et al., 1984a) and  the elemental chemistry in Part III (Chittleborough et al., 1984b) of this  senes of papers.    METHODS    Determination of the ratio free clay:total clay    Distilled water (1.2 ml) and 0.4 ml 10% Calgon were pipetted into a 5 ml  plastic vial containing 1.6 g air&lt;iry soil material. Following shaking in a Spex  Mixer Mill for 1 mm, the suspension was washed into a 100 ml centrifuge  tube, made up to 80 ml with distilled water and centrifuged for the appropri-  ate time to permit setthng of particles &lt; 2 pm or &lt; 0.2 tim. 5 ml aliquots  were plpetted into a weighed container, oven dried and weighed. Two repli-  cates of each sample were treated in this way. Calibration of the centrifuge  was carned out by the method of Whitby (1955).    Detailed particle-size analysls    Particle-size was measured from 0.6 pm to 2000 ttm at intervals by cen-  trlfugatlon in the range 0.6 to 2 tLm (Steele and Bradheld, 1934; Walker and  Hutka, 1979), by settling under gravity in the range 2--31 t~m (Day, 1965)  and by dry sieving for partmles of 31--2000 t~m diameter. Analyses were car-  rled out on 5--50 g subsamples of the samples after mr-drying. Following  physmal dlsaggregat,on with an ultrasonic probe and treatment with H202 to  remove organic matter, samples were placed on an end-over-end shaker for  12 h. i M NaOH and 10% sodium trlpolyphosphate were used as dispersing  agents (Hutton, 1955).    Calculatzon of the cumulatwe particle-size distribution (CPSD) index    The CPSD index was calculated for six sand fractions; 63--88, 88--125,  125--250, 250--500, 500--1000 and 1000--2000 t~m. The method revolved  the superpositlon of two partmle-size distribution histograms and the mea-  surement of the degree of correspondence between the two. Langohr et al.  (1976) define the CPSD index as "the sum of the mmimum values of the  weight-percentages of particle-size fractions in two samples".    206    Weathering index    The weathering index of Torrent and Nettleton (1979) is calculated m  three steps: calculation of fine silt:totai silt ratios at different depths down  the profile, plotting the ratios down to a depth at which weathering is negli-  gible and finding the slope of the regression line for the plot. Only the first  step was carried out.    Determination of quartz content and calculation of the particle-size distribu-  tion of quartz    Coarse clay (0.2--2 ~m), free silt (2--5 ~m), coarse silt (5--20 ~m) and free  sand (20--53 ~m) were separated by sedimentation from a selection of sam-  ples representing the A, B and C horizons of the terrace sequences. The  coarse fractions, 53--125 ~m and 125--2000 #m, were obtained by wet  sieving. Fractions ~&gt; 5 pm were hand-ground using a mortar and pestle with  acetone. Samples were mounted in an end-loading sample holder with a  teflon backing (Schultz, 1978). The intensity of the quartz line at 3.34 A  was determined on an X-ray diffractometer set at 40 kV and 60 mA and  with 4receiving slits and a cobalt tube. Each plate was run twice, for a time  of 50 s each, and mean count calculated. The quartz content of the fine clay  was not measured because early experiments established that there was little  quartz in this fraction. The percentage of quartz was determined by calcula-  tion, knowing the elemental chemistry (Chittleborough et al., 1984b) and  mass absorption coefficmnts of each element (Norrish and Taylor, 1962).  The particle-size distribution of quartz in the range 2--2000 ~m was calcu-  lated from these data.    Measurement of proportions of rock fragments    Fractions (50--250 ~m) were separated from the same horizons as for the  quartz particle-size measurements after gentle end-over~nd shaking with  sodium tripolyphosphate as a dispersant. Subsamples were mounted on glass  slides and ground and polished to a thickness of 30 ~m. Rock fragments and  individual grains were counted by traversing the slide with the aid of a point-  counting stage. Grains intersecting the horizontal grid line in the eye-piece  were counted.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Fine clay:total clay ratios    There is a similar change in the depth functions with time for all four se-  quences (Figs. 1, 2, 3, 4).  There are differences with depth in the youngest units of each sequence.    207    Deplh  (crn)    20    40    60    80    ~00    120    ICme clGy   Iolol cloy  Ot      02      03      04  i                i        i  i  /         6,  /      ',  J  \  \  \  \  \  //    '  /  /    ,  "\  ,,'K,      /  /\  /     \    O5  i    \  \  \  /  /  !  /  /  /  "\  \  \  i  i  L  I  /  /  /  /    06    Fig. 1. Depth functions of fine clay'total clay for soils of the Gooromon Ponds sequence.    This is particularly evident in $1 which is probably of recent origm. Consid-  erable erosion has taken place in the Shingle House Creek area since settle-  ment 100 years ago and this may account for pedorehcts of an old soil whmh  were noted m the microfabric of S1 (see Part I of this series). The low ter-  race units, e.g. G3, $2, N2, have relatively umform ratios with depth but the  ratios become progressively more skewed with increasing age such that there  are marked reductions in the ratio in the A and marked increases m the B  horizon.  The ratio of fine clay to total clay was found to be higher in the profile,  the greater the age of the profile. This is partmularly so for the end members    208    0  0    O2  i    Fine clay  tolcll cloy  03      04      05  i                i    06     OR      tO  I       I        I    Depfh  (cm}    20    40    60    8C    I00    Sz    L  \    /  /  1    Si    Fig. 2. Depth functions of fine clay:total clay for soils of the Shingle House Creek se-  quence    of each sequence (cf. G4, G5; $2, $3; N3, N4; H3, H5). This observation is  consistent with a clay iUuviation hypothesis insofar as loss of clay from the  A horizon would be expected to cause a decrease in thickness of that hori-  zon. H4 is an exception to this general trend. One reason may be that there  has been loss of material from the A horizon by erosion. The presence of  sand dunes in the Richmond area is evidence for this.  The changes of the clay ratios with depth in the oldest profiles are consis-  tent with an hypothesis of clay illuviation on the basis that one would ex-  pect fine clay to be moved preferentially. The evidence is not conclusive,  however, because it could be a~gued that fine clay may be generated by  weathering of coarser grains in the B horizon and rot in the A (differential  weathering) or that there has been weathering throughout the profile with  loss by solution of fine clay products from the A horizon.    Depth  (cm)    20    40    60    80  i  I00    120    Fine cloy  totol cloy  OI      02      03      04  N2 ]     N, ~\  \  i  i  /,  /         I'  t  /  I    05     N,I  \    I  /  /  /  f    06    \    /  /  /  /  /    Fig. 3 Depth functions of fine clay:total clay for soils of the Nowra Creek sequence.    209    Detaded particle-size analysis    Particle-size distributions of the A and B horizons of the soils in each se-  quence show a similarity in both the form of the plots and the manner m  which those change with the ages of the soils. Results axe therefore presented  only for the Hawkesbury sequence. Particle-size distributions for the A hori-  zons chaxacteristically have steep sections in the sand size range and much  flatter gradients in the silt and clay ranges, indicating the predominance of    210    Depth  (cm)    20    40    60    O0    I00    120    140    Fine cloy  total clay  02             04                          i    H2  \   t/1i    /  t    06    )  /"    H4    08  i    Fig. 4. Depth funchons of fine clay :total clay for soils of the Hawkesbury River sequence.    sand (Fig. 5). With time there is a decrease m the gradient in the clay range  demonstrating a loss of this fraction.  The plots of B horizons have three segments (Fig. 6). There is a steep gra-  dient in the fine clay range (0.06--0.2 #m), a flattening in the coarse clay and  silt range (0.2--20 pro) and then a steep gradient in the sand range. The fine  clay segment steepens significantly with time showing that there is a signifi-  cant increase in fine and very fine clay at the expense of the coarse silt and  fine sand fraction. The plot for H5 is distinctly bimodal. The large percent-    211    iO0  BO  1:  2  u 40  2O  o     o1125 i i  006        025    i11  /i .  ;  s  itI }l  r'  I  i  i   r  jl  i  i i  ;';1  ;.  #11~r  ! i  /   J  I i   /  //    /"  i        i  o"  ....  ?     ,~,~   ~,  ....  o   ~oo ,o,oo  250  312   63  [    Porhcle size (,urn)    Fig. 5. Partmle-size distributions of A horizons of the Hawkesbury River sequenceH1  40--58 crn; H3 0--18 cm; H4 0--11 era; H5 0--10 cm.    age of fine gravel m H5 is due to the presence of ironstone nodules, probably  formed m sltu.    CPSD index    The CPSD index was calculated from the detailed particle-size data after  excluding the gravel and adjusting the accumulatwe percentages to the range  0--2000 pm (Tables I (Gooromon Ponds), II (Shingle House Creek), III  (Nowra), IV (Hawkesbury)). Langohr and Van Vliet (1979) consider that  values m excess of 94 indicate extremely high similarity because sampling  and analytical errors are of such magnitude that 94--100 could be considered  identical, whereas 85--94 indicates high similarity. Values of 70--85 were  considered similar in this study.  If these criteria are used, there appears to be good evidence for parent  material homogeneity m most profiles. There are several exceptions which  can be grouped into two categories. In the first are the surface layers of G3    212    tOO  /   /  /,/   /"  ~0                                                      iII   ii/  / J    11       ,  '     /  f,  o                                    H5                 H ////  0.o ;i /  o           i  y               2 0     //           /  /         /  z        /  0     01125 10125   [    I    I    5[9        I~16I  ....  I3   125  1250       I000  ,  i    L  ,         I         ,  006       02    05   I    2         71a     20    44   ~IIB   200   500      20"00  PQrtIcle size (~Jm)  Fig. 6. Particle-size dJatributioRs of B horizons of the Hawkesbury River sequence H1  40--58 cm; H3 40--?0 cm; H4 43--?0 cm; H5 80--100 cm.    and H2 (respectively, the 0--12 cm and the 15--30 cm layers). These layers  are lithologically very different. In the second category are the older pro-  files of Gooromon Ponds (G4), Shingle House Creek ($3) and Nowra (N4)  where the lowest layers appear to have different sand-size distributions from  the upper horizons. These may be lithological discontinuities.  An assumption is made in the calculation of the CPSD index that the in-  tegrity of the sand fraction is maintained following deposition. Subsequent  pedogenesis may, however, alter the particle~ize distribution in a number of  ways. For example, mobilization of iron and its segregation into Ipravel-size  nodules and concretions may isolate sand size grains. In situ physical break-  up of sand grains (particularly quartz), fractured during transport and depo-  sition, will cause an increase in the proportion of the finer sand fraction.  Whereas a constant ratio is unlikely to have arisen by chance, and is there-  fore good evidence for textural uniformity of the parent material, lack of  agreement may be due to several causes not necessarily related to lithologl-    213  TABLE I  Cumulative particle-size distribution index of sand fractions for selected horizons of the  soils of the Gooromon Ponds sequence    Profile   Horizons    Depth       Number  CPSD index  G1                               2     3  A1              0--6       1         96.1     84.7  IIC            18--32     2                   84.5  IIIC          42--56     3  G3                                             2        3  All           0--12     1         85.6    67.2  A12           24--32     2                   70.4  B21          41--55     3  IIC2       78--88   4  IIC3         102--115    5    4     5  63.2    68.1  70.1   79.8  88.7    67 5  70.7    G4                                             2        3       4       5  All            0--6       1          82.4     65.3     56.4    84.9  A22           21--31      2                   53.7     47.3     68.2  B2            57--69      3                            87 0    75.7  C         81--96   4                        71 5  C         96--112  5    G5                                                2        3        4        5        6  A1              0--8       1          93.3    94.2    92.1     82.5     78.7  A2                           8--18           2                                      98.9          90 4         75.9          72.1  B21                       30--32            3                                                         90.9         76.8         73.0  B22           42--52     4                                      84.3    77.7  B31                       65--73           5                                                                                               92.3  C2       120---140  6    cal differences. In these cases, other evidence is required to isolate the  cause (s).    Weathering index    There was little difference in the fine silt:total silt ratio with depth for  any profile with the possible exception of N3 (Table V). On the basis of this  criterion there has been an insignificant contribution to the clay fraction by  chemical weathering of silt-size particles.    Particle-s~ze distribution of gravel    Depth functions of gravel and fine silt + clay indicate little relationship  between the two. If there had been a significant contribution to the finer  fractions, especially in the B horizons, from disintegration of rock fragments  and minerals of gravel size, there should be general decreases in gravel con-  tents in those horizons. Particularly should this be so in the older members    214  TABLE II  Cumulative particle-size distribution index of sand fractions for selected horizons of the  soils of the Shingle House Creek sequence    Profile   Horizons    Depth       Number  CPSD index  S1                                                 2        3  A1            0--6        1          86.7     74.7  20-30    2            61.4  50-70      3  $2                                              2       3       4       5  All                      0-8                 1                   87.1          82.9          75.7          76.3  A13                   20-30              2                                      92.6         84.4         83.4  B1                       42--52              3                                                         92.3         88.9  IIC1                   70-90              4                                                                            95.9  IIC2      90-110   5    $3                               2     3     4     5  A1                         0--7                 1                    93.8         89.6         92.4         71.1  B21                    17--28              2                                      91.8         89.9         77.4  B22                    28--38              3                                                         91.1          78.3  B3                    38--48            4                                                                   71.0  C1          68--88      5  C2       88--108   6    6  59.8  63.8  67.5  62 2  77.5    % Grovel    0  0  20    40    Depfh  {cm)  60    80    I00    z20    140    I0     20     30     40  -(  (35  J //G3    .  i      /"  _V"  /:    50               0          I0         20         50  ,        1    S3   "S2    f    Fig. 7. Gravel content of soils of the Oooromon Ponds sequence.  Fig. 8. Gravel content of soils of the Shingle House Creek sequence.    40  |    5O  i    215    TABLE III  Cumulative partmle-size distribution index of sand fractions for selected horizons of the  Nowra Creek sequence    Prohle    Horizons    Depth       Number  CPSD index  (cm)    N1                                 2     3  C1                          5--18           1                  89 7         85 8  C2            32--45     2                  93 9  IIC           45--55     3    N2                                                2        3        4  All                       0-7              1                  93 5         92 1         93.7  A12                       7--20           2                                    95.7         90.7  B             30--41     3                          92_7  C             50--60     4    N3                                             2       3       4       5  A1                          0--10           1                  92.5         88 7         81.9         85.4  B1            10-25     2                  95.2    89.4    92.9  B21                     25--35           3                                                     93 0         94 2  B22          35--50     4                                   94.4  B3            50---70     5    N4                                             2       3       4       5       6    7  A1                          0-5             1                  95  6         96.6         941         810         64.2   60.6  A2                          5--17           2                                    95.8         92.5         78  3         61 4   57  8  B1                        17--30           3                                                      918         82.5         64.6   61.0  B2                        30-40           4                                                                       78.1         61_5   57.9  B3                        40-60           5                                                                                         81  6   7f  1  C1                        80--100        6                                                                                                     91.2  C1       120--140  7    of each sequence where clay contents are higher. This is not the case. The  older soils, G4, G5, N4, H4 and H5 have higher gravel contents than the  younger members in their respective sequences (Figs. 7, 8, 9, 10). This gravel  appears to have a pedogenetlc origm because the gravels are mostly nodules  and concretions of sesquioxide. Evidence for mobilization and segregation of  oxides of iron can be seen in thin sections of these soils.  In spite of the foregoing statement there appears to have been breakdown  of gravel. In all sequences, except for Hawkesbury where there is little or no  gravel in the first three members of the sequence, there is a marked decrease  in the gravel from the youngest to the next member in the sequence, i.e.  there is a decrease from G1 to G3, S1 to S2, N1 to N2. But profiles G3, $2  and N2 show no horizon of clay enrichment despite the substantial loss of  gravel. Texturally, they are relatively uniform. Comparison of $2 and $3, N2  and N3, shows that there is little change in gravel but there are strong tex-  ural B horizons. It appears that gravel may have broken down, m sltu,  throughout the whole profile of the next-youngest soils producing clay    216    % Gcevel  O          I0         20         30         40         50               0          I0         20         30        40  "~~'       '              '                  I              '  /                             :,  80  lI                                                                        ),  i  f~                              /'  ilt                                                                   i ',./                             /  12o  'L                                                                   /  ,                                                             /  /  140                                                                                               ./    Fig. 9. Gravel content of soils of the Nowra Creek sequence.  Fig. 10. Gravel content of soils of Hawkesbury River sequence.    50    /    which was subsequently translocated to form the textural B horizons of the  older soils. Thus, while physical disintegration has occurred, it is not respon-  sible 'per se' for the textural B horizon.    Quartz contents of the different horizons and particle-size d~tribution of  quartz    In most of the older profiles of the terrace soils, there is an increase in the  quartz contents of the A and B horizons relative to the parent material of  that profile (Table VI). Exceptions to this are $2, which shows little change,  G4 which shows a decrease, and G5 in which there was an increase in all frac-  tions except fine and coarse sand which showed slight decreases in the B  compared to the C horizon.  These results cannot be explained by physical weathering. On the basis of  such an hypothesis, the increase of quartz in the freer fzactions must be  matched by a corresponding decrease in the coarse fractions. This is only ob-  served in G5 and even there the decreases in quartz of the fine sand are slight  compared to the big increases in the coarse clay and fine silt. The results are  best explained by a preferential loss, from all fractions, of minerals other    TABLE IV  Cumulative partmle-slze  soils of the Hawkesbury    217    distribution index of sand fractions for selected horizons of the  River sequence    Prohle    Horizons    Depth       Number  CPSD ,ndex  (cm)    H1    IIC1       40--58   1  IIC2          58--90     2  IIC3          90--120    3    2     3  93.0   94.2  93.2    H2    2     3     4     5  IIA                        15--30           1                    73.7          74 0          67  2          55.1  IIB1                      45--67            2                                      98.6         91.2         81  5  IIB21                   67--88            3                                                         91.4         81.1  IIB31        110--130    4                                      87.9  IIC1      150--170   5    H3    2     3     4     5  A1                           0--18           1                    98.9         99.1          92.0         94.5  A3            18--32     2                   98.7     91.7     95.3  B1            32--48     3                          92 2    95.1  B21           48--70     4                                      91.7  BC        90--120  5  C        150--170  6    6  950  95.1  95.2  88.8  945    H4    2     3     4     5  A1                            0--11            1                    89.7          92.5          80.9          84 4  B21           11--23     2                   83.3    76.4    77.4  B23                       43--70            3                                                         83.9          87.4  C            100--130    4                                      96.5  C            130--160    5    H5    2     3     4     5  A1              0--10     1         92.1     92.5     86 2    97.6  A22           20--35      2                   92 9     91.8     91.8  B21                       35--60           3                                                         88.0         94.4  B22                       80--100         4                                                                            86.4  BC       130--160  5    than quartz. This loss could be due to flluvtation of free colloid (&lt; 0.2 pm)  into the B horizon, chemical breakdown of grains to colloids of size &lt; 0.2  #m or a combination of both. On this hypothesis, the fine fractions, especial-  ly the coarse clay and fine silt, should show a greater increase, relative to the  C horizon, than the coarser fractions because chemical weathering would be  more pronounced in the former. This is so. Moreover, with age, the differ-  ence between quartz contents of A and B horizons compared to the C  should increase. This was observed (cf. H3, H4 and H5, Table VI). The de-  crease m quartz of G4 may be due to the breakdown of gravel which is high-  er in minerals other than quartz compared to the fine earth.    218    TABLE V  Ratios of fine silt : total silt (2--5 urn/2--20 urn) of selected horizons for soils of four  terrace sequences    Gooromon  Ponds :    G1          G3           G4           G5    depth (cm) ratio   depth (cm)  ratio  depth (cm)  ratio  depth (cm)  raho    0--6              0.42            0--12           0.58         0--6                 0.53            0--8              0.43  18--32     0.42    24--32     0.55   21--21       0.52      8--18     0.43  42--56     0.49    41--55     0.54   57--69       0.48    30--42     0.48  78--88           0  54      81--96              0.42         42--52           0.52  102---115         0.52      9@--112           0.51         65--73           0.54  120--140  O.49    Shingle House Creek  S1                 $2    $3    depth (cm) ratio  depth (cm)  ratio  depth (cm)  raho    0--10     0.50     0--8      0.61    0--7        0.41  20--30           0.36         20---30           0.66      17--28              0.45  50--70           0.45         42--52           0.64      28--38              0.45  70--90           0.64       38--48              0.49  90--110         0.65       68--88              0.47  88--108   0.45    Nowra Creek :  N1    N2           N3           N4    depth (cm) ratio  depth (cm)  ratio  depth (cm)  ratio    depth (cm)  raho    5--18     0.45      0--7       0.40      0-10     0.49      0--5       0.37  32--45     0.44      7--20     0.44    10---25     0.48      5--17     0.37  45--55           0.50         30--41            0.46         25--35           0.42         17--30           0.36  50--60     0.42    35--50     0.39    30--40     0.34  50--60           0.34         40--60           0.38  80---100  0.36  120--140  0.44    Hawkesbury River:  H1           H3  depth (cm) ratio  depth (cm)    H4    ratio  depth (cm)  ratio    H5    depth (cm)  ratio    40--58   0.35   0--18  58--90     O. 38    18--32  90--120        0.38         32--48  48--70  90--120  150--170    0.49      0--11     0.31  0.51    11--23     0.35  0.51    43--70     0.41  0.52       100--130         0.42  0.54   130--160    0.43  0.57    0--10     0.34  20--35   0.37  35--60   0.44  80--100  0.55  130--160    0.48    219    TABLE VI  Quartz content of separates from selected horizons of the soils of the terrace sequences    Profile  Hon-   Depth  Coarse       Fine        Coarse       Free         Medium  zon     (cm)    clay          salt         salt           sand         sand  (0 2--2~-n)  (2--5~n)  (5--20~an)  (20--53pm) (53--125~an)    Coa~e  sand  (125--  2000~m)    Gooromon Ponds  G1            A1               12             20                        53                    65                       83                       73  G3      All        6       18            51           62            78            74  B21      46      20           56          64           81            78  G4      A12       9      29            57          64           87           77  B1               47             25                        57                    72                       85                       74  C         85      32           66          76           90           82  G5            A2              13             53                        86                    88                       92                       93  B22            47             33                        80                    84                       86                       87  B31             69             21                        66                    75                       98                        83    76  68  82  67  64  77  83  76  79    Shingle House Creek  $1      A        25      13            39          70           93          100  $2      A12      14      10           23          58           89           92  B1        47       11             27           63            91            93  IIC       80       i0            26          64            92            --  $3       A2        14       11             39          91            99           I00  B3       43       8            20          77           98           92  C1       78      11            25          71            93           95    98  89  68  72  100  79    Nowra Creek  N1            C1               12             28                        50                    58                       70                       81  N2            A12            14             27                       41                    57                       74                       89  B                  36             29                       46                    60                       71                        85  N3            B1               18             37                        46                    69                       75                       88  B22            42             33                        63                    65                       78                       88  N4            A1                 2             45                       54                    60                       84                       89  B2        35       39            81           79            90            92  C1      130      --            68          67           83           82    65  73  79  69  86  86  83  75    Hawkesbury River  H1      IIC       49      --             28           53            69            91  H2            IIA              23             19                        43                    62                       78                       91  IIB21         78             16                       43                    69                       84                       91  H3            A3              25             34                       67                    87                       96                       89  B21       59       34            73          86            99            98  C               160            --                         55                    73                       91                        93  H4      A1         6       18             52          73            91           I00  B22            33             22                                                71                        90                       98  C        115       12            35          56            74            81  H5            A22            28            --                         93                    88                     100                     100  B21      48      --             26           44            74            94  BC      145       26            19          21            62            81    98  88  101  100  100  89  90  94  88  100  96  96    220  G5                                                       ]40  o    G4    G3    /-  /    /j- B2  J    ~.0    20    %quortz    40    20    G l                                                  c     140  I         513        I                               '            0  z     5        20          125               2000    Porhcle size (jura)    Fig. 11. Particle-size distributions of quartz within the major horizons of the Gooromon  Ponds sequence.    There may still be a breakdown of quartz and quartz-bearing minerals  from coarser fractions to provide an increase of fine material in the coarse  clay and silt. The resultant decrease in the quartz content of the coarse frac-  tions may, however, be masked by a simultaneous, but higher, loss of the  weatherable minerals. Thus, there could still be a net increase in the quartz  content of the sand fractions even though disintegration of quartz-bearing  minerals was taking place. One way of testing this is to plot the particle~ize  distribution of quartz. If changes in quartz percentages as observed in Table  VI were only occurring as the result of changes in the weatherable minerals,  there should be no change in the particle-size distribution of quartz through-  out the profile.    221    The particle-size distributions of quartz were calculated and are shown in  Figs. 11, 12, 13 and 14. Differences between A and B horizons of a profile  are considered in relation to the C horizon of that profile. In the Gooromon  Ponds sequence, G4 shows a slight decrease m the coarse fraction of the B  horizon. This loss shows up as an increase m the fine sand and silt. There is  httle contribution to the coarse clay. The effect is more pronounced m the  older G5 profile. There is little change in quartz distributions of Shingle  House Creek soils indicating that physical disintegration of quartz is mslg-  mficant. In the Hawkesbury sequence there is a relatively umform distribu-  tion in H3 but in H4 there is a gain m fine sand and silt at the expense of the  coarse and medium sand in both A and B horizons. In H5, and also N4, the  trend is reversed and there is an increase in the proportion of quartz m the  coarse sand and a decrease in the fine and coarse silt and coarse clay. This is  probably caused by a breakdown of free-grained quartz by chemical weath-  ering.    $3  /,  __/  "'C    60    40    20    0  %quartz    C     0    Sl                                        _.~_~._.~20cm  140:~C)  J           0                  5                         20             52            125                                                2000  Porhcle SIZe (Lira)    Fig. 12. Particle-size distributtons of quartz within the major horizons of the Shingle  House Creek sequence    222    =4 (2-2ooo,~m)   ,"/A~',            _......~ A,    .. --//    ,D_/----- _._..._---    40  3,0  20  iO  0  40  20  I0  0    4O                %quortz  30  N3  20                                   ~..~1     ,o  'B2       0    40  30  20  IO    40  --                        Particle size (Am)  I     I       20    53   1152000'      0    Fig. 13. Partmle-size distributions of quartz within the major horizons othe Nowra  Creek sequence.    Breakdown of rock fragments    Rock fragments were identified as any grain which appeared to be made  up of two or more distinct grains. Some grains were highly fractured and it  was difficult to determine whether it was one fractured grain or a number of  grains of the same mineralogy. Most were designated rock fragments which  means that there may be an over-estimation of the proportion of rock frag-  ments (Table VII).    /  H5 (2-2000#m)                    /..//f       4o  B_c_~                                                                         O    /'B2  /~ A2  BC  H5    H4              ~B2  A1    l  a0  20  0  % quartz  ]' 2(3  0    223     14o  H~           .          "                     2O  .A3      ~  ....  c                                                  O    40  H2                  7~~'~  J~~Particle s,ze (#m)                        11  r~     I          I      I      I                   i        o  2                  5                        20              53            125                                              2000    Fig. 14. Particle~ize distributions of quartz within the major horizons of the Hawkesbury  River sequence.    In all sequences there is a decrease m the proportion of rock fragments  with age, an observation consistent with the changes in gravel percentages.  Apart from a decrease in the A horizon of G5, each profile has a relatively  uniform percentage of rock fragments. In the Shingle House Creek sequence  the increase in $2 compared to S1 is due to many grains being cemented by  iron. This may be an inherited feature but it is more hkely to be in-situ    224  TABLE VII  Proportion of rock fragments in sand fractions of soils from four terrace sequences    Profile  Horizon  Depth   Rock      Profile  Horizon  Depth  Rock  (cm)    fragments                     (cm)    fragments  (%)                        (%)    Gooromon Ponds  G1    A1     12    76  G3    All     6    83  B21    46    92  G4      A12       9      75  B1        47       73  C         85       72  G5    A2     13    49  B22       47       65  B31    69    65  Shinglehouse Creek  $1      A        25      39  $2      A12      14      82  B1        47       66  IIC       80      --  $3    A2     14    21  B3     43    36  C1       78      26    Nowra Creek  N1    C1      12   37  N2      A12        14     66  B       36   64  N3    B1      18   21  B22     42   32  N4    A1      2   16  B2      35   23  C1        130     31    Hawkesbury River  H1    IIC     49   55  H2    IIA     23   55  IIB21    78   44  H3      A1           6     27  A3      25   27  B21        59     19  C      160   19  H4    A1       6    8  B22     33    9  C      115   22  H5      A22       28      2  B21     48   18  BC        145     25    mobilisation and segregation of iron. The increase with depth of the rock  fragments in the profiles N4, H4 and H5 is also ascribedto this process. The  increase from the A horizon to the C horizon is greater in H5 than m H4, a  result consistent with the micromorphology which indicates a greater degree  of sesquioxide mobflisation in the oldest Hawkesbury profile.  It appears that breakdown of sand-size rock fragments has occurred but  the extent to which it has influenced other fractions, particularly the clay,  cannot be ascertained. A very mild procedure was used to isolate the 50--  250 ~tm fraction. If a more vigorous mechanical dispersion had been used,  similar to that used for determination of the particle~size distributions, many  weakly aggregated grains and fractured minerals might have been broken    225    down. Nevertheless, except for the oldest profiles, there are no marked  changes in proportions wxthin any one profile, mdmating that breakdown  has been relatively uniform within a profile.    CONCLUSION    From the sLrnilarity in the particle-size distribuhon of the sand fraction  within most profiles it was concluded that the parent material was initially  uniform in each. The few exceptions to this may be due to in-situ break-  down of coarse grams and/or formation of nodules.  Chemmal weathering does not appear to be responsible for the develop-  ment of B horizons high in clay because the depth functions of fine silt:total  silt ratios in all but one profile do not decrease with depth.  There is, however, a marked loss of fine clay from A horizons and a sub-  stantial increase in the B horizons within older soils of each sequence, indl-  catmg that clay illuviation has been an important mechanism m the develop-  ment of textural contrast.  Physical breakdown of fine-grained coarse fragments of sand and gravel  size has contributed silt and clay to the whole solum but the process has  played only a minor role in textural differentmtlon.    REFERENCES    Arnaud, St R.J. and Whiteside, E.P,, 1963. Physical breakdown m relation to soil devel-  opment J. Soil ScL, 14:267--281  Brewer, R. and Walker, P.H., 1969. Weathering and soil development m a sequence of  river terraces. Aust. J. Soil Res., 7 : 295--305.  Bronger, yon A. and Kalk, E., 1976. Zur Feldspatverwltterung und ihrer Bedeutung ftir  die Tonmineralbildung Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Bodenkd., 1 37--55.  Byers, H.G , Kellogg, C.E., Anderson, M.S. and Thorp, J, 1938. Formahon of soil. In-  U.S. Dept. Agric., Soils and Men. U.S. Dept. Agric.  Chittleborough, D J. and Oades, J.M., 1979. The development of a Red-brown earth, I.  A reinterpretation of published data. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17: 371--381.  Chittleborough, D.J., Walker, P.H. and Oades, J.M., 1984a. Textural differentiation m  chronosequences from eastern Austraha, I. Description, chemmal properties and m~cro-  morphology of soils. Geoderma, 32 : 181--202.  Chittleborough, D.J, Oades, J.M and Walker, P.H., 1984b. Textural differentiation in the  chronosequences from eastern Austraha, III. Ewdence from elemental chemistry. Geo-  derma, 32  227--248.  Day, P.R., 1965. Partmle fractionation and partmle-slze analysis. In: C.A Black, D D.  Evans, J.L. White, L.E. Esminger and F.E. Clark (Editors), Methods of Soil Analysis,  Part I. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wlsc., pp. 545--567.  Dixit, S P., 1978. Measurement of the mobihty of soil colloids. J. Soil Scl., 29: 557--566.  Foss, J.E. and Rust, R.H., 1968. Sml genesis study of a lithologm discontinuity in glacial  drift in Western Wisconsin. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32 393--398  Hutton, J.T., 1955. A method of particle-size analysis of soils CSIRO Aust. Dry. Soils,  Div. Rep. No. 11/55.    226    Langohr, R. and Van Vliet, R., 1979. Clay migration in well to moderately well drained  acid brown soils of the Belgian Ardennes: morphology and clay content determina-  tion. Pedologie, 29: 367--385.  Langohr, R., Scoppa, C.O. and van Wambeke, A., 1976. The use of a comparative par-  ticle-size distribution index for the numerical classification of soil parent materials: ap-  plication to soils of the Argentinian pampa. Geoderma, 15: 305--312.  Moss, A.J., 1973. Fatigue effects in quartz sand grains. Sediment. Geol., 10: 239--247.  Moss, A.J; and Green, P., 1975. Sand and silt grains: predetermination of their formation  and properties by microfractures in quartz. J. Geol. Soc. Aust., 22:485--495  Nikiforoff, C.C. and Drosdoff, M., 1943. Genesis of a claypan soil. Soft Sci, 55. 459--  482.  Nornberg, P., 1980. Mineralogy of a podzol formed in sandy materials in northern Den-  mark. Geoderma, 24: 25--43.  Norrish, K. and Taylor, R.M., 1962. Quantitative analysis by X-ray diffraction. Clay  Miner., Bull., 5: 98--109.  Oertel, A.C. and Giles, J.B., 1966. Development of a Red-brown earth profile. Aust. J  Soil Res., 5:133--147  Raad, A.T. and Protz, R., 1971. A new method for the identification of stratification in  soils of the Blue Springs Basin, Ontario. Geoderma, 6: 23--41.  Ritchie, A., Wilding, L.P., Hall, G.F. and Stanke, C.R., 1974. Genetic imphcations of B  horizons in Aqualfs of north-eastern Ohio. Soft Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38:351--358.  Ruhe, R.V., 1956. Geomorphic studies and the nature of soils. Soil Sci., 82: 441--445.  Schultz, L.G., 1978. Sample packer for randomly oriented powders in X-ray diffraction  analysis. J. Sediment. Petrol., 48: 627.  Smeck, N.E., Ritchie, A., Wilding, L.P. and Drees, L.R., 1981 Clay accumulation m sola  of poorly drained soils of western Ohio. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 45: 95--102.  Smith, B.R. and Buol, S.W., 1968. Genesis and relative weathering intensity studies in  three semi-arid soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32' 261--265.  Steele, J.G. and Bradfield, R., 1934. The significance of size distribution in the clay frac-  tion. Bull. Am. Soil Surv. Assoc., 15: 88--93.  Torrent, J. and Nettleton, W.D., 1979. A simple textural index for assessing chemical  weathering in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 373--377.  Walker, P.H. and Hutka, J., 1979. Size characteristics of soils and sediments with special  reference to clay fractions. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17 : 383--404.  Whitby, K.T., 1955. A rapid general purpose centrifuge sedimentation method for mea-  surement of size distribution of small particles -- apparatus and method. J. Air Pollut.  Con. Assoc., 5: 120--126.  Zeuner, F.E., 1949. Frost soils in Mount Kenya and the relation of frost soils of aeolian  deposits. J. Soil Sci., 1: 20--30.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractData from particle-size analyses were used to determine the relative importance of the four mechanisms proposed to explain the development of strong textural contrast in the end members of four chronosequences. The mechanisms proposed were sedimentary layering, in-situ chemical weathering, clay illuviation and physical breakdown.Depth functions of fine clay: total clay ratios and detailed particle-size distributions at  intervals from 0.6 m to 2000 m indicated that there had been a marked increase in fine clay in the B horizons of the older soils of each sequence, a result consistent with, but not proving, a clay illuviation hypothesis. Cumulative particle-size distribution indices showed that most profiles had texturally uniform parent materials. Changes in the ratio fine silt : total silt with depth were slight for all but one profile, indicating no significant contribution to the clay fraction by in-situ chemical weathering of the silt fraction.From changes in the depth functions of gravel with time, it was concluded that physical breakdown had occurred but that it had not been responsible for the development of the textural B horizon. The rate of disintegration was particularly high early in pedogenesis, preceding the development of texture-contrast. Breakdown contributed fines to the whole solum and was not generally any more intense in one horizon than another. Grain counts of rock fragments in the medium sand range lent support to this conclusion.Changes in the particle-size distribution of quartz from 0.2 m to 2000 m indicated that the contribution to the clay fraction from physical disintegration was only slight. 