 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 281--292                                                     281  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PREDICTING TRANSPORT OF THREE CATIONS IN SOIL COLUMNS  UNDER CONDITIONS OF STEADY.STATE FLOW, INDIA    R.S. SIYAG, R. PAL, S.R. POONIA and T.C. BARUAH  Department of Soils, Haryana Agricultural University, Hisar-125004 (India)  (Received March 6, 1984; accepted after revision September 6, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Siyag, R.S., Pal, R., Poonia, S.R. and Baruah, T.C., 1984. Predicting transport of three  cations in soil columns under conditions of steady-state flow, India. Geoderma, 34:  281--292.    The breakthrough curves (BTCs) of signal cation(s) i.e., Naand/or Mg2for Ca2  Na*--Mg2 Ca2-Naand Ca~-Mg2systems were obtained at different pulse volumes  and pore-velocities using calcium saturated columns of sandy loam and clay loam samples.  The BTCs showed that (1) the appearance of the signal cation was independent of the  pulse volume, (2) the maximum reduced concentration and retention volume increased  with the increase in pulse volume at a given pore velocity, (3) the maximum reduced  concentration of the cation at a given pulse volume was greater at high than at low  pore velocity, and (4) there was a delayed appearance in the effluent of the divalent  cation as compared to the monovalent cation.  The BTCs of Naand Mg2for a Ca2-Na+--Mg2+ system, those of Nafor a Ca2+-  Nasystem and those of Mg2. for a Ca2+---Mg2system were also predicted using the  analytical solution of the relevant equation for one-dimensional convective-dispersive  transport of a solute under given initial and boundary conditions. Predicted BTCs of  Naagreed well with those observed for the sandy loam sample for Ca~-Na+--Mg~and  Ca~+--Nasystems and in the clay loam sample only for the Ca2*--Na+--Mg2system at  a small pulse volume. For other treatments of the clay loam sample, the agreement  between predicted and observed BTCs was rather poor. There were considerable devia-  tions between predicted and experimental BTCs of Mg~for both soil samples.    INTRODUCTION    Leaching and accumulation of a cation in a soil system is chiefly depend-  ent upon its own concentration,  the nature and concentration of com-  plementary cations, the pore velocity of soil solution and cation exchange  (Biggar and Nielsen, 1963). Lai and Jurinak {1972) incorporated some of  these parameters in their study of the dynamics of cations. They conducted  their experiments on columns with uniformly packed samples of Yolo  loam in the laboratory.  Little or no attempt has been made in this direction on soils from arid    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    282    and semi-arid regions. This paper reports the effect of interstitial flow  velocity, pulse volume, concentration of the signal and complementary  cations on two texturally different soil samples from the semi-arid tract  of Haryana State (India) on transport of Na+, Ca2+ and Mg2 The study  also attempts to demonstrate the applicability of a theoretical model under  conditions of steady-state flow of cations in the soil samples.    EXPERIMENTAL    Surface (0--15 cm) samples of sandy loam and clay loam were collected  from soils of the Experimental Farm of Haryana Agricultural University,  Hisar, and the Government Agricultural Farm, Hansi, respectively. Some  of the physico-chemical characteristics of the soil samples are given in  Table I. The soil samples were ground and passed through a 2-mm sieve.  Plexiglass columns of 5.05 i.d. (internal diameter), and 40 and 90 cm in  length were filled as uniformly as possible with sandy loam (bulk density  1.4 -+ 0.02 g cm-3) and clay loam (bulk density 1.32 0.02 g cm-3) samples  to a depth of 20 cm (Table II). Uniformity of packing was ensured in so  far as possible by adding about 50 g of soil sample at a time followed by  a predetermined number of tappings with a wooden roller fitted with nails  at the bottom. Each soil column was positioned vertically in a wooden  stand with its bottom resting in a plastic funnel.  The columns were first leached with 0.25 N Ca (CH3COO)~ with hy-  draulic heads of 5 and 50 cm to maintain two flow velocities. After steady  state with respect to both flow rate and effluent composition was reached,  different combinations of pulse volumes (Table III) of cations containing  0.125 N NaC1 + 0.125 N MgCI~ for a Ca2-Na-Mg:system; 0.125 N  CaC12 + 0.125 N NaC1 for a Ca2-Nasystem and 0.125 N MgCl: + 0.125    TABLE I    Some physico-chemical properties of soil samples  Properties                            Hisar           Hansi    Soils (subgroup level of taxonomy,  Ahuja et al., 1978)    Typic          Episalic  Camborthid    Natrustalf    Particle size distribution (%):  Sand (2--0.02 ram)                  65  Silt (0.02---0.002 mm)            16  Clay (&lt;0.002 mm)                 19    42  22  36    Cation exchange capacity :  (meq./100 g)                         9.3            14.6  pH 1:2                          8.2           8.6  CaCO3 (%)                                 0.3                0.8    TABLE II  Column properties for sandy loam and clay loam samples    283    Property                                  Sandy    Clay  loam      loam    Bulk density (p, g cm-3)                       1.42      1.32  Cation exchange capacity (CEC, meq./g)      0.093     0.146  Column length (L, cm)                      20.00     20.00  Pore volume (PV, cm3 per column)        185       195  Pore fraction (0, cm3 cm-~)                   0.46      0.48    TABLE III  Experimental properties for column studies of sandy loam and clay loam soil samples    Pore          Dispersion    Input    Pulse   Peclet No.  velocity       coefficient    pulse     intake    VL  (V, cm h~)   (D, cm: h-~)  volume   time     4D  (cm3)    (T, h)    Sandy loam :  S1Vs    0.96  S:Vs    0.96  S~Vf    3.75  S2Vf    3.75  M~ Vs    0.98  M:Vs    0.98  MIVf    3.78  M2Vf   3.78  SIM, Ys  1.00  S:M:Vs 1.01  S~M, Vf  3.79  S:M2Vf 3.80    Clay loam :  S1Vs    0.25  S2Vs    0.25  S, Vf    0.92  S2Vf   0.92  MI Vs    0.25  M2Ys   0.25  M1Vf    0.94  M~Vf   0.94  S,MI Vs  0.25  S2M2Vs  0.25  S~MI Vf  0.94  S~M2Vf  0.95    0.322                   105                9.25       14.91  0.322                   202              18.50       14.91  1.070         102        2.56   17.53  1.070         204        5.06   17.53  0.316                   103                 9.15       15.51  0.316         205       18.40   15.51  1.050         102        2.50   18.00  1.050                   205                 5.00       18.00  0.313                   106                 9.41       15.97  0.313         203       18.01   16.13  1.040         102        2.50   18.22  1.040                   205                 4.98       18.26    0.064                   102              50.00       19.53  0.064                   203              98.00       19.53  0.254         100       11.50   18.11  0.254         200       23.25   18.11  0.064                   100              50.00       19.53  0.064                   200              98.00       19.53  0.254         100       11.45   18.50  0.254                   200              23.25       18.50  0.064                   102              50.00       19.22  0.064                   198              98.41       19.22  0.250         102       11.46   18.80  0.250         203      23.08   19.00    284    N CaC12 for a Ca2+--Mg:system were introduced. These pulses were eluted  by 0.25 N CaC12. The elution continued until the incoming and outgoing  solutions had the same composition. The effluent was collected successively  in instalments of 10 ml each in 25 ml measuring cylinders placed at the  bottom of each column. The effluent so collected was analysed for Na  Ca2and Mg2 The curves (BTCs) with respect to the signal cations, viz.,  Naand Mg2+ were drawn by plotting the reduced concentrations of the  signal cation in the effluent versus number of pore volumes.  The partial differential equation describing one-dimensional cation trans-  port is as follows:  ~C     32C     3C  R  = D-- Y                                    (1)  ~t     ~x2     3x  where V is the interstitial flow velocity (cm h-l); D, the dispersion coeffi-  cient (cm2 h-l); t, the time (h); x, the distance (era) along the direction  of flow; C, the concentration of the signal cation (eq 1-1); and R, the retar-  dation factor [= (1 + pQf/OCo), with p as the bulk density of the soil sample  (g era-3); Q, the cation exchange capacity (meq. g-l); 0, the volumetric  moisture content (cm3 cm-3); Co, the input cation concentration (eq. 1-1);  and f, the slope of the linear part of the normalized exchange isotherm  of the signal cation].  The solution of eq. 1 used for computation in the present study was  the same as that given by Lindstrom et al. (1967) and applied by Lai and  Jurinak (1972) and Lai et al. (1978).  The dispersion coefficient (D) was calculated using the chloride break-  through curve (Kirkham and Powers, 1972). The error function (erf) was  evaluated using the following relationship.  erfx = 1 - 1/(1 + 0.141128 x + 0.088641 x2 + 0.027433 x3 -  0.000394 x4 + 0.00329 xS)s  The pertinent soil sample and column parameters are given in Tables II  and III.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Sandy loam sample    The predicted and the observed BTCs of NaS) and Mg2+(M) for a Ca2  Na-Mg2system corresponding to two input pulse volumes, viz., small  (1 = 100 ml) and large (2 = 200 ml), and two flow velocities, viz., slow  (Vs) and fast (Vf) for the sandy loam sample (the treatments are listed as  SIM1Vs, S1M1Vf, S2M:Vf and S2M2Vs) are shown in Fig. 1.  A comparison between the observed BTCs of Naand Mg2for the two  input pulse volumes at two flow velocities showed that at a given flow    285    velocity Naand Mg2began to appear in the effluent at ~1 pore volume  (PV) and ~2 PV, respectively. The initial appearance of Naand Mg2was  not affected by the input pulse volumes. In other words, the pore volume  of the effluent at which signal cations i.e., Naor Mg2appeared did not  change with the total input pulse volume, though for Mg2it was almost  double that for Na The front parts of the BTCs for Naand Mg2+, re-  presenting the input pulse volumes, overlapped each other. The peaks of  the BTCs for both Naand Mg2 however, were relatively sharper for  small input pulse volumes than for large input pulse volumes. The delayed  appearance of Mg2in the effluent was attributed to the higher preference  of soil exchange sites for Mg2than for Na(Poonia et al., 1980). The  maximum reduced concentrations (C/Co) and the retention volumes, i.e.,  the pore volumes corresponding to the maximum reduced concentrations  of the signal cations in the effluent, increased with the increase in input  pulse volume. In the treatment S2M2Vs, the maximum reduced concentra-  tions of Naand Mg2were 0.42 and 0.38, respectively. The corresponding  reduced concentrations of these cations for S~M1Vs, S2M:Vf and SIM1Vf treat-  ments were 0.40 and 0.35, 0.45 and 0.40, and 0.42 and 0.38, respectively.  The retention volumes in terms of pore volume (PV) for Naand Mg2were  1.80 and 3.00, 1.60 and 2.37, 1.87 and 3.05, and 1.72 and 2.45 forS2M2Vs,    0.5  0-4    o  o  0.3  }    0.2  o  z  U    o o  NO  " A Mg EXPERIMENTAL    -- PREDICTED  S1 M1 VS  t,/,A    S2M2Vs  /    A&amp;,      0.5  Z  o    0.~  O    0.3  :3  a  uJ  0.2  er  0.1  0  0.5    S1M1Vf  A AA^  1.0    S2M2Vf  J  1.5  2.0  2.5   3.0  3.5 0.5  1.0    ,&amp;A J  1-5      20    2.5     3.0     3.5     4.0    4.5    PORE VOLUME    Fig. 1. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Naand Mg~in a Ca2+--Na+--Mg~system  as affected by input pulse volume and pore velocity in a sandy loam soil sample.    286    S~M, Vs, S2M2Vf and S~M1Vf treatments, respectively. With the fixed quantity  of the adsorbent, an increase in the input pulse volume would obviously  result in the increase in maximum reduced concentration because of an  increase in the quantity of the signal cation. This would also result in an  increase of the retention volumes because the larger input pulse volume  will continue to supply the signal cation in the effluent for a longer time  and/or for larger pore volumes. This is why BTCs for Na+ and Mg2for the  larger input pulse volumes were more flattened.  At a given input volume the maximum reduced concentrations of signal  cations i.e., Naand Mg2increased with the increase in pore velocity.  For small input pulse volume, i.e. 100 ml, the maximum reduced concen-  trations of Na+ and Mg2were, respectively, 0.42 and 0.38 for fast flow  velocity (Vf), whereas for slow flow velocity (Vs) the maximum reduced  concentrations of Naand Mg2+ were, respectively, 0.40 and 0.35. Sim-  ilarly, for large input pulse volumes, i.e. ~200 ml, the maximum reduced  concentrations of Naand Mg2were, respectively, 0.45 and 0.40 for Vf,  and 0.42 and 0.38 for Vs.  The findings of this study are consistent with those of Lai and Jurinak  (1972) except that they observed a gradual decrease in the retention vol-  ume with the decrease in flow velocity.  At a given pulse volume, the appearance of both Naand Mg2in the  effluent was slightly delayed with an increase in flow velocity. For ex-  ample, Mg2+ appeared at 2.05 PV when the flow velocity was fast (Vf) as  against 1.98 PV when the flow velocity was slow (Vs). These data pertain  to the larger input pulse volumes.  The peaks of Naand Mg2+ BTCs were relatively sharper at fast flow  than at slow flow velocities. The slower interstitial flow velocity resulted  in relatively more diffusion and thus broadened the effluent peaks for  Na+ and Mg2+. Biggar and Nielsen (1963) had earlier observed delays in  the appearance of signal cations with increases in flow velocity which they  attributed to the process of diffusion.  A comparison of the predicted and the observed BTCs (Fig. 1) shows  that in case of Nathere is a good agreement between them, so far as its  (Na appearance, retention volume and maximum reduced concentration  are concerned. But in case of Mg2 the predicted appearance, retention  volume and maximum reduced concentration were less than observed.  The predicted and the observed BTCs of Na+ for Ca2-Nasystem cor-  responding to small (1 = 105 ml) and large (2 = 202 ml) input pulse volumes  and two flow velocities, viz., slow (S = 0.96 cm h-1) and fast (f = 3.75 cm  h-1) (listing the treatment as S~Vs, S~Vf, S2Vs and S2Vf) are shown in Fig. 2.  The appearance of Nain the effluent, its maximum reduced concentration,  retention volume and sharpness of peaks were affected by input pulse  volume and interstitial flow velocity in the same way as in Ca2+--Na+-  Mg2system.    287    The reduced concentration of Nain the input solution was kept as 0.5  so that it remained within the linear range of the normalized exchange  isotherm. The value of the slope of the linear part as used in calculating  the retardation factor was 0.142.    0.5    0,4    0.3    0.2    o  o  071  2  L)  0  3  o  0.4  w  (.9  ~  0.3    o  o EXPERIMI  -- PREDICTEI  S1 VS  i    NTAL  $2 VS  J    s,v,               s2v,          o  0.2  0.1       /                                 o  0.5         1.0          115           2.0        2-5   0-5         1-0           1.5         2-0         2.5        3-0  PORE VOLUME  Fig. 2. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Nain a Ca2*--Na+ system as affected by  input pulse volume and pore velocity in a sandy loam soil sample.  The predicted and the observed BTCs of Mg:+ for the Ca:+--Mg:system  corresponding to small (1 = 103 ml) and large (2 = 205 ml) input pulse  volumes, and slow (s = 0.98 cm h-1) and fast (f = 3.78 cm h-1) flow veloc-  ities (listing the treatments as M~Vs, M, Vf, M:Vs and M:Vf) are shown in  Fig. 3. The pore volume at which Mg:appeared in the effluent remained  almost unchanged despite changes in the added pulse volumes. The max-  imum reduced concentration of Mg2 however, increased with an increase  in input pulse volume. At a given input pulse volume, the increase in veloc-  ity augmented the maximum reduced concentration of Mg: The value of  maximum reduced concentrations of Mg:for M1Vf, M1Vs, M2Vf and M2Vs  were 0.39, 0.34, 0.45 and 0.41, respectively.  The predicted and the observed BTCs of Mg2at fast velocities were    288    relatively closer to each other than those corresponding to slow velocities.  At slow velocities the predicted BTCs shifted to the right of the observed  data points. Further, at low pore volumes of an added pulse, the predicted  maximum reduced concentration of Mg2+ was smaller than the observed  one at both velocities (M~Vs and M1Vf).    0.5    0.4    0.3    0.2  U  0  z   0.5  c3  ~0.~.  E3  LU  n,. 0.3    0.2    M1 VS    0.1    a EXPER(MEN  -- PREDICTED    A&amp;  A    [AL  MZ~S  2  ^    M1 Vf    0 --  1.0                                                       a.0    &amp;&amp;  &amp;&amp;  h  &amp;  1.5    2.0   Z. 5   3"0    M2 Vf       &amp; ,,,  i  3.5        1.0       1.5        Z.O       2.5       3.0       3.5  PORE VOLUME    Fig. 3. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Mg2in a Ca2-Mg2system as affected by  input pulse volume and pore velocity in a sandy loam soil sample.    Clay loam sample    The predicted and observed BTCs of Naand Mg:for the Ca2+--Na  Mg2system corresponding to two input pulse volumes and two interstitial  flow velocities are given in Fig. 4. A comparison of observed BTCs of Na and Mg2showed that Nastarted appearing in the effluent at 1.08 pore  volumes, irrespective of flow velocity and pulse volumes. The appearance  of Mg2 however was affected by flow velocity. The pore volumes at  which Mg2appeared in the effluent were 1.98 and 2.16 at slow and fast  pore velocities, respectively. The effect of pulse volume on PV of the Mg2 appearance in the effluent was, however, negligible. The front parts of BTCs  of Naand Mg2overlapped each other. The BTCs were more sharp for  small than for large input pulse volume. The maximum reduced concen-    289    tration and retention volume for the cation in question increased with  the increase in pulse volume.  A comparison of the predicted and the observed BTCs of Na(Fig. 4)  shows that in treatments S1M1Vsand SIMIVf, there is fair agreement between  them, so far its appearance, retention volume and maximum reduced con-  centration are concerned. But in treatments S2M2Vs and S2M2Vf the pre-  dicted values of PV at which Naappeared in the effluent as well as its  retention volume were smaller than those observed. For Mg2 the predicted  values of the parameters mentioned above were less than those observed  in all the treatments.    0.5    o 0.,~  ~0.3  L)  g   ,  "-0.1  0  ~   C    o  o  NQ  " " Mg EXPERIMENTAL  -- PREDICTED    S1 M1 vS    o     A *' .,,    S2M2Vs  o          '~t~      Z  O  (D  a 0"5~  bJ  (.9  w  cc 0.3    0.2    0.1    0  0,5    S1 M1 Vf           A6A  O         A  A  0              A  ^A,    SzM2Vf  /%    1.0     1-5    2-0    2,5     3,0     3.5    4.0     0.5    1.0      1.5     2.0    2.5     3.0     3,5     ".0   4.5  PORE VOLUME  Fig. 4. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Na+ and Mg~+ in a Ca2+--Na+--Mg2system  as affected by input pulse volume and pore velocity in a clay loam soil sample.  The predicted and the observed BTCs of Nafor the Ca:*--Nasystem  corresponding to two input pulse volumes and two interstitial flow veloc-  ities are shown in Fig. 5. The effect of input pulse volume and interstitial  flow velocity on the initial appearance of Nain the effluent, its maximum  reduced concentration, retention volume and sharpness of peaks for the  Ca2+--Na+ system was almost similar to that for the Ca:+--Na+--Mg2system.  The difference in the magnitude of various parameters for sandy loam  and clay loam samples may be attributed to the small differences in the  treatments superimposed, viz., input volume and interstitial flow veloc-  ity, and relative specificity of exchange sites for Nain the presence and  absence of Mg2+ in the two exchange systems.    290    0.5     SlVs  0.4  0.3    The reduced concentration of Nain the input solution was kept at  0.5 and the value of the slope of the linear part of the normalized exchange  isotherm of Nawas taken as 0.13. The predicted BTCs of Nalagged be-  hind the observed data points. The predicted maximum reduced concen-  tration at low pore volume of the pulse added to corresponding to fast veloc-  ity (S1Vf) was lower than that observed. The significant shift of curve S2Vs  from the experimental values cannot be explained satisfactorily. Lai and  Jurinak (1972) also reported such results with pore velocity of 0.539 cm  h-1 and input volume of 150.4 ml, which corresponded to 0.5 pore volume.  o o o  EXPERIMENTAL  PREDICTED  S2 Vs    u  z  O 0.5     S1 Vf                         S2Vf   0.4     ~:               (J                   : o  ,~ 0.3  0.2  {1.5 1.0  ~.5 2.0 2.5 310 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0  2.5  3.0 3'.S   PORE VOLUME  Fig. 5. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Na+ in a Ca2+--Na+ system as affected by  input pulse volume and pore velocity in a clay loam soil sample.  The predicted and observed BTCs of Mg2+ for the Ca:+--Mg:+ system  are shown in Fig. 6. The initial appearance of Mg:+ in the effluent was  unaffected by input pulse volume but was affected by interstitial flow  velocity. The maximum reduced concentration of Mg:+ increased with  the increase in input pulse volume. Interstitial flow velocity had no effect  on retention volume.  The slope of the normalized exchange isotherm of Mg:+ was taken as  0.8 for the calculation of a retardation factor. There was reasonable agree-  ment between the predicted and the observed BTCs at high pulse volumes  corresponding to both slow and fast velocities (M2Vs and M2Vf). But at  low pulse volume corresponding to both velocities (M1Vs and M~Vf) the  predicted BTCs of Mg:+ were more flattened than the observed ones.    291    In conclusion it may be stated that the movement of Naremained  unaffected by the addition of Mg2to the Ca2*--Nasystem. This is at-  tributed to the fact that Mg2and Ca~behave almost identically in soil  cation exchange (Richards, 1954; Poonia and Pal, 1979). The theoretical  model proposed by Lindstrom et al. (1967) predicted NaBTCs well, both  for single and multicomponent systems. The predicted and the observed  BTCs of Mg2differed considerably from each other, which could not be ex-    plained.    0-5    0.4    0.3    M1 VS    0.2   0.1  (J  o  d  ~ 0.5  0  ~" 0.4  0  W  ~" 0.3    O:    EXPERIMENTAL  PREDI rED  M2Vs  &amp; A&amp;  &amp;    M1 Vf    o.5                        1.5                        ,:5    AA  &amp;   b  2'0   2"5   3"0    3.5   4.0    M2Vf              &amp; A&amp;  fQ  2.0       2-5       3.0       3.5       4.0    PORE VOLUME  Fig. 6. Experimental and predicted BTCs of Mg2+ in a Ca:+--Mg~+ system as affected  by input pulse volume and pore velocity in a clay loam soil sample.    REFERENCES    Ahuja, R.L., Garalapuri, V.N., Manchanda, M.L. and Khanna, S.S., 1978. Physiography  and soil associations of Haryana. J. Indian Soc. Soil Sci., 26: 261--267.  Biggar, J.W. and Nielsen, D.R., 1963. Miscible displacement, V. Exchange processes.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 27: 623--627.  Kirkham, D. and Powers, W.L., 1972. Advanced Soil Physics. Wiley, New York, N.Y.,  408 pp.  Lai, Sung-Ho and Jurinak, J.J., 1972. The transport of cations in soil columns at dif-  ferent pore velocities. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 26: 730--733.    292    Lai, Sung-Ho, Jurinak, J.J. and Wagenet, R.J., 1978. Multicomponent cation adsorption  during convective--dispersive flow through soils: Experimental study. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. J., 42: 240--243.  Lindstrom, F.T., Haque, R., Fread, V.H. and Baersma, L., 1967. Theory on the move-  ment of some herbicides in soils. Linear diffusion and convection of chemicals in soils.  Environ. Sci. Tech., 1: 561--565.  Poonia, S.R. and Pal, R., 1979. Sodification of soils in relation to sodium activity ratios  and Ca:Mg in soil solutions. J. Indian Soc. Soil Sci., 27: 116--122.  Poonia, S.R., Mehta, S.C. and Pal, R., 1980. Calcium-sodium, magnesium-sodium ex-  change equilibria in relation to organic matter in soil. Int. Syrup. Salt Affected Soils,  Karnal, pp. 134--141.  Richards, L.A. (Editor), 1954. Diagnosis and Improvement of Saline and Alkali Soils.  USDA Handbook 60, Washington, D.C., 160 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractThe breakthrough curves (BTCs) of signal cation(s) i.e., Na+ and/or Mg2+ for Ca2+Na+Mg2+, Ca2+Na2+ and Ca2+Mg2+ systems were obtained at different pulse volumes and pore-velocities using calcium saturated columns of sandy loam and clay loam samples. The BTCs showed that (1) the appearance of the signal cation was independent of the pulse volume, (2) the maximum reduced concentration and retention volume increased with the increase in pulse volume at a given pore velocity, (3) the maximum reduced concentration of the cation at a given pulse volume was greater at high than at low pore velocity, and (4) there was a delayed appearance in the effluent of the divalent cation as compared to the monovalent cation.The BTCs of Na2+ and Mg2+ for a Ca2+Na+Mg2+ system, those of Na+ for a Ca2+Na+ system and those of Mg2+for a Ca2+Mg2+ system were also predicted using the analytical solution of the relevant equation for one-dimensional convective-dispersive transport of a solute under given initial and boundary conditions. Predicted BTCs of Na+ agreed well with those observed for the sandy loam sample for Ca2+Na+Mg2+ and Ca2+Na+ systems and in the clay loam sample only for the Ca2+Na+Mg2+ system at a small pulse volume. For other treatments of the clay loam sample, the agreement between predicted and observed BTCs was rather poor. There were considerable deviations between predicted and experimental BTCs of Mg2+ for both soil samples. 