 Gcoderma, 30 (1983} 161--170                                                     161  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    AN OPTICAL, SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPIC AND  MICROANALYTICAL STUDY OF CEMENTATION IN SOME PODZOLS    W J. McHARDY and L. ROBERTSON  The Macaulay Instztute for Soil Research, Craigiebuckler, Aberdeen (Great Britain)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    McHardy, W.J. and Robertson, L., 1983. An optical, scanning electron microscopic and  mlcroanalytical study of cementation in some podzols. Geoderma, 30: 161--170.    The nature of a strongly cemented horizon occurring m a soil prohle at Lochend Farm  on the shores of Loch Leven has been investigated by optical and scanning electron mi-  croscopy and electron probe microanalysls, and comparisons have been made with more  weakly cemented Bh horizons of two other podzol profiles developed on sands and  gravels. Under the optical microscope the monomorphic organic coatings present on  skeleton grams m the cemented hormons of all three profiles appear similar. Of the ele-  ments detectable by microanalysis, AI is dominant in all the coatings whereas a low Fe  and relatively high Ca content is characteristic only of the Lochend material.    INTRODUCTION    Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and electron probe microanalysis  have been used in several studies on soil morphology. Lynn and Grossman  (1970) and McHardy and Birnie (1975), among others, have examined spe-  ClhC parts of the soil fabric. Gillesple and Protz (1972) used micromorphol-  ogy and electron probe microanalysls in the study of two residual soils and,  more recently, Qureshl et al. (1978) have studied the distribution of phos-  phorus within the soil fabric using electron probe microanalysis. In several  papers, (e.g., Eswaran, 1971; Eswaran and Raghu Mohan, 1973) SEM obser-  vations have been directly correlated with observations made by optical  microscopy. Indeed in SEM studies of soils, it is important to make such cor-  relations and comparisons, since scanning electron micrographs of softs tend  to have limited significance on their own.  The main problem with SEM studies of undisturbed soil materials is that  individual clay-size grains and their inter-relationships can only be resolved  at very high magnifications, at which only a few square microns can be exam-  ined and photographed at any one time: in order to get an overall picture of  the specimen many fields of view have to be examined and these may differ  widely in appearance. Also the large depth of field, characteristic of the SEM,    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevmr Science Publishers B V.    162    is not always an advantage since It can further complicate mterpretation.  Stereo-pairs can greatly assist with interpretation and are very desirable but,  unless the relevant sophisticated SEM equipment is available, they can only  be studied in retrospect. It would be useful to regard SEM of soils as an ex-  tension of conventional optical mlcromorphology but, although there is  good overlap in the magnification ranges, the widely dlffenng preparation  techniques required, present problems.  Optical microscopy of soil materials has reached an advanced stage. A wealth  of mlcromorphological data derived from examination of soil thin sections  using the polarising microscope has been accumulated and much of it can be  interpreted with varying degree of certainty in terms of soil forming pro-  cesses. In some of the more detailed soil classification systems mlcromorpho-  logical criteria are essential in defining dlagnostm horizons. The question  arises as to how the soil thin section, so meticulously prepared and examined,  can be utilized for SEM studies. Since the thin section consists of a flat  polished surface, three-dimensional morphological detail is not readily ob-  tained unless a combination of BE and SE techniques described by Blsdom  et al. (1983) or the low temperature ashing techmque described by Price  and Jenkins (1980) is used; where an X-ray analysis accessory, either energy-  dispersive spectroscopy (EDS) or wavelength dispersive spectroscopy (WDS)  is available, however, it is possible to obtain analytical data on optmally ob-  served features.  The potentml of this approach has been explored by an investigation of  the nature of the cementing material present m Bh horizons of three Scottish  podzols.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The three soil profiles used m this study are from Lochend Farm, Fife  (NGR NO 183/005), Culbm Forest, Morayshlre (NGR NJ 026/638) and  Wlndyhills, Aberdeenshire (NGR NJ 799/399). According to the U.S. De-  partment of Agriculture Soil Survey Staff (1975) all three profiles are  Spodosols and can be assigned to either the Humod or Aquod sub-order.  The Lochend Farm site differs from the other two in that it is located  within 1.5 km of the present shore-line of Loch Leven, a stretch of water that  has been artificially drained within historical times with subsequent lowering  of the water level. The profile is developed on water-laid sands and gravels  demved mainly from Upper Old Red Sandstone sediments and lavas. Five  horizons can be differentiated m the profile. The upper horizon, Ap, is a very  dark brown 10YR 2/2 fine sandy loam with coarse to medmm subangular  blocky structure, whmh changes sharply at 21 cm into AE, a dark reddish  brown (5YR 3/2 and 2.5/2) weakly cemented loamy sand. At 26 cm there is  a diffuse and irregular boundary with the Bh horizon, a black (5YR 2.5/1)  gritty sandy material, which is strongly cemented and almost impossible to  dig with a spade, and at 42 cm a very sharp change occurs into C1, a greyish    163    brown to dark greyish brown (1OYR 4/2-3/2) silty sand with dark reddish  brown streaks (5YR 3/2) containing old root material. There is a further  sharp change at 60--70 cm into C2, a dark reddish brown (5YR 3/3) gritty  sand with no apparent structure.  The profile from Culbin Forest has been described in detail elsewhere  (Soil Survey of Scotland, 1962). This profile is a buried humus podzol de-  veloped in blown sand over raised beach gravels. Humus-iron cementation is  a feature of the Bh horizon.  The profile from Windyhills is a podzol developed on Pliocene gravels.  Within the loose lower part of this profile there occur rather erratically and  at varying depths sandy layers cemented by translocated humic material.  Undisturbed soil samples were collected from the cemented horizons of  the three profiles using boxes 75 55 45 mm in size. The samples were  freeze-dried, vacuum-impregnated with polyester resin (BK 17449) and thin  sections were prepared for examination by a polarising microscope. Photo-  micrographic records were made of relevant areas in the thin sections after  which they were cut out, mounted on SEM stubs and coated with 20 nm of  carbon. At an early stage it was noted that during SEM examination the glass  disc on which the thin section was mounted made a significant contribution  to the Si X-ray signal. This was overcome by using Canada balsam rather than  polyester resin as a mounting medium, since after optical examination the  Canada balsam could be dissolved with Inhibisol (a commercial cleaning  fluid based on trichloroethylene), the thin section removed from the glass  support slide and cleaned ultrasonically prior to SEM study.  The SEM and mlcroanalysis work was carried out using a Cambridge  Scientific Instruments $4 stereoscan equipped with a wavelength dispersive  X-ray spectrometer and a Link Systems energy-dispersive X-ray analyzer.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Lochend profile    The most characteristm features observed in thin sections prepared from  the strongly cemented horizon were well developed isotropic monomorphic  grain coatings (De Coninck et al., 1973} as in Fig. 1, a and b and pellety  polymorphic aggregates as in Fig. lc. Fig. ld is a scanning electron micrograph  of the same field of vmw as shown in Fig. lc. The numbers 1--4 on Fig. ld  lndmate small areas which have been analyzed qualitatively using the energy  dispersive X-ray analysis system, and the spectra for 1, 2 and 4 are given in  Fig. le. Area 1 is m the embedding resin and the spectrum from this area  shows only a small Si-peak. Most of the primary mineral grains are quartz: an  X-ray spectrum (not shown m Fig. le) from area 3 has only a large Si-peak.  The particle labelled 2 is not quartz, however, as it contains, in addition to  Si, A1 and K a little Na, Mg, Ti and Fe. Both its chemical composition and  appearance under the optical microscope are consistent with it being a piece    164    "'l  a- r-  AI I Si  1"  ar_e~a~    Fig 1 Lochend profde. (a) Plane-polarized light mmrograph showrng strongly developed  isotropic rnonomorphm grain coatings. (b) Area m centre of (a) at higher magnification.  (c) Plane-polarized light rnicrograph showing peUety aggregates of cernentmg rnatenal (d)  Scanning electron rnicrograph of roughly the same field of view as (c) In the SEM the  specimen Is viewed at an angle of 45which causes foreshortening of the image. Thus it is  not possible to match the SEM image exactly with the light rn~crograph (e) X-ray spectra  from positions I, 2 and 4 marked on Fig ld.    165    Fig. 2. Lochend profile. Scanning electron mmrographs (a, c and e) and corresponding A1  distribution images (b, d and f) of (a) the area of pellety material depicted in Fig. lc,  (c) a single coated grain and (e) a region of continuous coatings at low magnification.    166    of lava. It is this particle that appears dark grey (arrowed) in the optmal  micrograph (Fig. lc). The spectrum from the brown pellety material, area 4,  shows that Al is the predominant constituent with Si, Ca and a httle Fe.  There are also small distinct peaks representing P, S, C1 and K. A scanning  electron micrograph of, roughly, the central area of Fig. ld (Fig. 2a) and the  corresponding A1 distributmn linage (Fig. 2b) show the pellety aggregates to  be rich in Al. The coating material surrounding the sand grain m the centre  of Fig. 2c is very clearly defined by the A1 distribution image (Fig. 2d) and  the continuous nature of the coatings at lower magmficatmn (Fig. 2e) is ob-  vious from the A1 distribution image (Fig. 2f) of the same field. The pellety  aggregates appear to have almost the same A1 content as the coatmgs. With  the WDS system used for the distribution images of Fig. 2, a high beam cur-  rent is necessary to get a measurable quantity of X-rays and th~s considerably  degrades the secondary electron image (Boekestem et al., 1981). The high  peak-to-background ratm of the WDS system, on the other hand, does give  much superior elemental dlstributmn images.  From optmal microscopy these cementing materials are descmbed as iso-  tropic monomorphic/polymorphm organic matter. X-ray microanalysls shows  that the A1 content is very high. A significantly high Ca but relatively low S1  and Fe content is characteristic. The P, S and Cl content ~s presumably as-  sociated with the organm part of the aluminmm orgamc complex.    Culbin profile    Optmal examination of soil thin sections prepared from the cemented ma-  terxal shows grain coatings similar in appearance to those from the cemented  Lochend material. Because the coatings tended to be thm and the grains were  mostly quartz, it was difficult to detect with the microprobe anythmg ex-  cept Si even at the edge of the grmns. However, it was possible to study the  coating material adhering to the walls of holes vacated by sand grains during  the ultrasonic cleaning of the section (Fig. 3, a and c). In Fig. 3a the approx-  imate area of analysis giving the X-ray spectrum m Fig. 3b is rmged, This  spectrum shows a very high AI:Si ratio, an intermediate Fe peak and small  peaks for P, S, C1, K and Ca. In Fig. 3c a piece of coating material (ringed)  Is more clearly visible on the reward sloping wall of another hole. The X-ray  spectrum (Fig. 3d) from this area is similar to that in Fig. 3b.    Wmdyhills profile    Optical nucroscopy of thin sections of the cemented horizon from this  profile again showed similar grain coatings (Fig. 4a). The scanning electron  micrograph (Fig. 4b) shows a hole (arrowed) in the section previously occu-  pied by a sand grain. A scanning electron micrograph of part of the pore wall  at higher magnification (Fig. 4c) and the accompanying AI, Si and Fe distri-  bution images (Fig. 4, d--f} show that the coating material clearly contains    b    167    J    Fig. 3. Culbin profile. (a) Plane-polaxized light mmrograph of a thin section from the  cemented Bh horizon. (b) X-ray spectrum from area ringed in Fig. 3a. (c) Plane-polarized  light micrograph showing pore vacated by a sand-grain. (d) X-ray spectrum from wall of  pore with coating material, ringed in Fig. 3c.    S1 and some Fe as well as A1. Allowing for the fact that the spectrum from  area 1 (Fig. 4c) is that for the embedding resin and is included merely for  comparison, X-ray spectra (Fig. 4g) show a variation of composition within  the coating. For example at area 2 on Fig. 4c the Al peak is slightly smaller  than the Si peak whereas at area 3 it is twice the size and the general pattern  of the spectrum is more akin to that of the Lochend pellety material. This  implies that in the coating there is a mixture of clay mineral and an alum/-  nium organic complex.    168    "~AIi                     ~'~       '~"~I~'~" ~. ~'~,,,~C~.  area 2      A....._..  Ill,  ......  -  ....  A!    Fig. 4. Windyhills profile (a) Plane-polarized light micrograph of a thin section of the  cemented Bh horizon. (b) Scanning electron mmrograph showing a pore vacated by a sand  gram (c) Magnified scanning electron micrograph of the wall of the pore m centre of Fig.  4b w]th corresponding A1, Sl and Fe X-ray distribution ]mages (d, e and f) (g) X-ray spectra  from areas 1, 2 and 3 marked on Fig 4c    169    DISCUSSION    The strong cementation in the Lochend profile has been compared with  weaker cementation in the Bh horizon of two other podzols. Optical micro-  scopy shows monomorphic orgamc coatings which appear similar for all three  profiles although they are best developed and thickest in the Lochend ma-  terial. X-ray microanalysis of the coatings shows some similarities, but also,  perhaps more significantly, some differences. Of the elements detectable by  X-ray analysis Al is dominant in all the coatings but a low Fe and relatively  high Ca content is characteristic only of the Lochend material. P, S and C1  axe consistently detectable m the Lochend coatings, less so in the others and  these elements may have some correlation with the nature and amount of  the organic part of the complex.  This approach to the study of coatings is not unique. Bisdom and Jongerms  (1978) have used a combined SEM-microanalysis technique in a study of the  nature of cutans in which they concluded that where organic matter is present  it may conceal a heterogeneous distribution of other compounds. Robm and  De Coninck (1978) have described similar coatmgs in the cemented B hori-  zons of podzols developed on sandy parent material in the Pans Basra, and  Van Ranst et al. (1980) have demonstrated the association of organic matter  with aluminmm in cemented spodic B horizons.  More work on this subject is necessary. In particular, the organic matter  occurring in other homzons of the profiles ought to be analysed for compari-  son and X-ray analysis should, if possible, be made quantitative for the  amount of aluminium present in the coatings.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    The authors wish to thank Mr. E.L. Birse for bringing the site at Lochend  Farm to their attention.    REFERENCES    Bisdom, E.B.A. and Jongerius, A., 1978 SEM-EXDRA and/or IMMA analysis of cutans,  an indurated horizon and clayified roots in th,n sections of some Dutch soils. In. M.  Delgado (Editor), Soil Micromorphology. Proceedings of the 5th International Working  Meeting on Soil Micromorphology, Granada, 1977. Universlty of Granada, Spare, pp  741--756.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Thiel, F., Volbert, B. and Jackman, J., 1983. Variatlons in backscattered  electron (BSE) images w,th a Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) as applied to min-  eral grains and excrements in a podzol, to precipitates on a water-tube f,lter and to  bauxite. Geoderma, 30: 93--116.  Boekestein, A., Henstra, S. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981. Submicroscopm techniques for m  situ mmrochemical analysis of soils, 1. Non-destructive techniques. In: E.B.A. Bisdom  (Edltor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Interna-  tional Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM),  1980, Pudoc, Wageningen, pp. 29--44.    170    De Coninck, F., Righi, D., Maucorps, J. and Robin, A.M., 1973. Origin and mmromorpho-  logical nomenclature of organic matter in sandy spodosols. In: G.K. Rutherford  (Edltor), Soil Microscopy. Proceedings of the 4th Internatlonal Working Meeting on  Soil Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973  The Llmestone Press, Kingston, Ont, pp  263--280.  Eswaran, H , 1971 Electron scanning studies of the fabric of fracture surfaces Soil_ Scl  Soc. Am J.,35'787--790.  Eswaran, H and Raghu Mohan, N.G , 1973 The microfabrm of petropllnthlte Soil Scl  Soc. Am. J., 37 79--82.  Gillespie, J.E and Protz, R., 1972. The mmromorphology and electron microprobe anal-  ysis of two residual soils, one developed on granite, the other on marble, in Peterborough  county, Ontario. Can. J. Soil Scl , 52:79--89  Lynn, W.C. and Grossman, R.B., 1970. Observations of certain sod fabrics with the  scanning electron microscope Soil. Sci. Soc. Am. J, 34 645--648_  McHardy, W J. and Birme, A.C., 1975 Scanning electron microscope studies of a surface  water gley J Soil. Sci., 26 426--431.  Price, F. and Jenkins, D A , 1980. Removal of resin from standard soft thin-sections by  low temperature ashing as a means of following transmitted optical by scanning elec-  tron microscopy Clay Minerals, 15 309---315  Qureshi, R.A., Jenkins, D.A. and Davies, R I., 1978. Electron probe mlcroanalytlcal  studies of phosphorus distribution within soil fabric. Soil Scl. Soc. Am. J., 42:698--703  Robin, A.M and De Comnck, F., 1978. Mlcromorphological aspects of some podzols in  the Paris Basin. In. M. Delgado (Editor), Soil Micromorphology Proceedings of the  5th International Working Meeting on Soil Mlcromorphology, Granada, 1977 Univer-  sity of Granada, Spain, pp. 1019---1050_  Soil Survey of Scotland, 1962_ Handbook of a Soil Survey Field Meeting, Inverness  Macaulay Inst. Soil Res., Aberdeen.  U.S. Department of Agriculture Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soft Taxonomy -- a Basic  System of Soil Classificatmn for Making and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Gov Print  Off., Washington, D.C.  Van Ranst, E., Rlghl, D., De Comnck, F , Robin, A M and Jamagne, M., 1980 Morphology,  composition and genesis of arglllans and organans m soils. J Microsc., 120 353--361                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractThe nature of a strongly cemented horizon occurring in a soil profile at Lochend Farm on the shores of Loch Leven has been investigated by optical and scanning electron microscopy and electron probe microanalysis, and comparisons have been made with more weakly cemented Bh horizons of two other podzol profiles developed on sands and gravels. Under the optical microscope the monomorphic organic coatings present on skeleton grains in the cemented horizons of all three profiles appear similar. Of the elements detectable by microanalysis, Al is dominant in all the coatings whereas a low Fe and relatively high Ca content is characteristic only of the Lochend material. 