 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 221--227                                                        221  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE EFFECT OF WEATHERING IN THE SILT FRACTIONS ON THE  APPARENT STABILITY OF CHLORITE IN SCOTTISH SOIL CLAYS    D.C. BAIN and D.M.L. DUTHIE  Department of Mineral Soils, The Macaulay Institute for Soil Research, Craigiebuckler,  Aberdeen AB9 2QJ (Great Britain)  (Received March 27, 1984; accepted after revision September 8, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Bain, D.C. and Duthie, D.M.L., 1984. The effect of weathering in the silt fractions on the  apparent stability of chlorite in Scottish soil clays. Geoderma, 34: 221--227.    Previous work on chloritic soils in Scotland indicated that, irrespective of soil type or  drainage class, the chlorite that was dominant in the clay fractions weathered only slight-  ly, showing  little variation in amount with depth. These soils have been investigated  further by determination of the chlorite content in the silt fractions by a quantitative X-  ray diffraction technique. In a Dystric Cambisol and a Placic Podzol, the fine silt fractions  (1.4--20 urn) contain much more chlorite than the coarse silt (20--75 urn) and in both  fractions the amount of chlorite decreases towards the surface, markedly so in the Placic  Podzol. It is suggested that chlorite is being dissolved out from the clay fractions but as  chlorite is being broken down and transferred to finer particle size fractions, this dissolu-  tion effect is being masked by the replacement of the clay fraction chlorite from the fine  silt. Analysis of the total soils (&lt; 2 mm) confirmed the net loss of chlorite from these pro-  files.    INTRODUCTION    In a study of fifteen chloritic soils of various drainage classes developed on  different parent materials, it was found that, with one exception, the clay  mineralogy varied only slightly with profile depth (Bain, 1977a). Iron-rich  chlorite, dominant at the base of the profile, persisted throughout the upper  horizons irrespective of drainage class, soil texture, organic matter content  or pH {commonly 5.2--4.9 in freely drained profiles and sometimes as low as  4.2). The only variation was that the iron in the chlorite in the freely drained  soils became oxidized in all horizons, altering the thermal characteristics of  the mineral (Bain, 1972), whereas in the gley soils, the oxidation occurred  only in the surface horizons. Thus, the study of the clay fractions suggested  that chlorite weathered only very slightly, perhaps by vermiculitization  around the edges of flakes.  In one Placic Podzol (the Eredine profile) from the same area of Argyll-  shire as eight of the other profiles, however, chlorite, although dominant in    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    222    the clay fraction from the C horizon, clearly decreases in amount towards  the soil surface and is absent from the A2 horizon in which the main mineral  is interstratified mica--vermiculite (Bain, 1977b). The distribution of heavy  minerals in the fine sand fraction verified that this profile had developed on  a uniform parent material, and the absence of any trioctahedral phase in the  A2 horizon together with the marked loss of iron and magnesium from the  clay fractions indicated that the chlorite had been destroyed, the only de-  tectable product being goethite. This podzol differs from the other profiles  examined in that it contains patches of translocated humus in the B2 hori-  zon, and it was postulated that organic compounds in solution percolating  downwards from the surface of the soil during podzolization are reacting  with and dissolving the chlorite.  With this one exception, chlorite in the clay fractions of Scottish soils ap-  pears to be fairly stable and this is contrary to what has been found else-  where in Great Britain (Stephen, 1952; Perrin, 1971; Adams et al., 1971)  and in similar soil types in other countries (Droste et al., 1962; Camez, 1962;  Johnson, 1964; Gilkes and Little, 1972; Schwertmann, 1976). In Norway  and Canada in particular, it is well documented that chlorite is highly un-  stable (i.a., Gjems, 1967; Brydon et al., 1968) particularly in Spodosols  (Ross, 1980).  The purpose of this paper is to investigate this discrepancy between the  weatherability of clay-size chlorite in Scottish soils and in similar soils else-  where by extending the study to the silt fractions and quantifying the  amount of chlorite present using an X-ray diffraction technique in order to  determine whether the chlorite content of the clay fractions may be affected  by weathering within the silt fractions.    EXPERIMENTAL    Soils    The five freely&lt;trained soils developed on glacial till derived from chlorite-  schists in the Loch Awe region are the profiles most suitable to examine as  they contain large amounts of chlorite and being freely-drained, are more  likely to show variations in amount with profile depth. Two criteria had to  be satisfied for this study: (1) development of the profile on a uniform  parent material; (2) absence of other phases which produce an X-ray diffrac-  tion peak at 7 A (kaolinite, serpentine, vermiculite) which would interfere  with the 002 reflection of chlorite at 7.1 A to be used in the quantitative  method. Two profiles proved suitable, the Sonachan Dystric Cambisol and  the Ardbrecknish Placic Podzol (FAO, 1974).  The clay mineralogy of the Sonachan profile is dominated by chlorite  with minor amounts of randomly interstratified vermiculite-chlorite, amphi-  bole and feldspar, and trace amounts of mica and goethite (X-ray diffraction  traces, differential thermal analysis curves and analytical data were published    223    by Bain, 1977a). The Ardbrecknish soil also contains dominant chlorite in  the clay fractions with minor amounts of interstratified  vermiculite--  chlorite and hornblende, and trace amounts of goethite in addition to unusu-  ally high contents of TiO2 (9--14%) in the form of cryptocrystalline anatase  (Bain, 1976). The pH varies from 4.5 in the C horizon to 4.9 in the B: to  4.5 in the A2.    Methods    The quantitative X-ray diffraction method used was that developed by  Chung (1974) by which no calibration curve is necessary as all the absorp-  tion and matrix effects are removed or flushed out of the intensity concen-  tration equation:  (  where Xi = weight percentage of component i, Xf-- weight percentage of  flushing agent, ki = reference intensity ratio, Ii = intensity of X-ray reflection  of component i, and If = intensity of X-ray reflection of flushing agent.  The ki factor has to be pre-determined by using a standard mineral (in this  case chlorite) similar in its X-ray diffraction characteristics to the mineral  being determined.  To apply this method to the soils in question, the 002 reflection of chlor-  ite at 14.50 (using iron-filtered CoK~ radiation) was used and boehmite  was chosen as the flushing agent as its 020 reflection at 16.80 occurs con-    BOEHMITE    J  20  B  1    CHLORITE    I  B     10  I    J    5  3  I   I e    Fig. 1. X-ray diffraction trace (CoKa radiation) showing chlorite and boehmite peaks and  background positions (marked B) used for intensity measurements. The peaks at 12.1 and  16.120 are due to hornblende and feldspar, respectively.    224    veniently near the 002 chlorite peak and is not at an angle at which any  other component might diffract. Intensities were measured by taking dupli-  cate counts for 10 s on both peaks and also at background positions on  either side (Fig. 1) and net peak counts were used in the calculations.  Specimens were prepared for analysis by grinding the samples in alcohol  for 10 min in a McCrone mill to ensure that particle size was less than 15  pm, and then a known weight of boehmite was thoroughly homogenized  with a known weight of sample. Two mixtures were prepared of each sample  and oriented slides made in triplicate from each.  To test the precision of the technique, nine samples were analysed from  the B3 horizon (&lt;2 mm) of the Dystric Cambisol. The mean was 12.96%  chlorite, standard deviation 1.23 and coefficient of variation 9.5%.    RESULTS    For both Sonachan and Ardbrecknish profiles, three sets of analyses were  obtained: (1) fine silt, 1.4--20 pm; (2) coarse silt, 20--75 pm; (3) total soils,  -~2 mm. These definitions of silt fractions do not conform with any of the  internationally accepted classifications but have been used so that the results  may be compared with previous results (Bain, 1977a).  The results for the Sonachan profile are depicted graphically in Fig. 2  where it can be seen that the chlorite content in the fine silt varies from 65%  in the C horizon to a maximum of 72% in the B: horizon and then to a mini-  mum of 55% in the A horizons. There is much less chlorite in the coarse silt,  the maximum being 19% in the B3 and the minimum being 9% in the A~  horizon. The trends in the chlorite content vary somewhat, but it is clear    DYSTRIC   CAMBISOL    AI  A2  B3  C    TOTAL SOIL   20 - 75 j.m  1.4 - 20j~  10     20    310    40    .SO    60    70  % CHLORITE    Fig. 2. Amount of chlorite plotted against horizons in the Dystric Cambisol.    225    that there is a decrease between B and A horizons. The amount of chlorite  in the total soil showed a parallel trend to that in the coarse silt, decreasing  from a maximum of 13% in the B3 to 5% in the A horizons.  In the Ardbrecknish profile the leaching has been much more intense and  the trends in chlorite content are much clearer (Fig. 3). Again the fine silt is  considerably more chloritic than the coarse silt, the content in the finer  fraction decreasing from 85% in the C horizon to 74% in the B2 and then  sharply to 21% in the A2. The decrease is more gradual in the coarser frac-  tion, falling from 14% in the C to 10% in the B2 and 4% in the A2. The chlor-  ite content of the total soil also shows a gradual decrease towards the soil  surface, from 5% in the C horizon to 4% in the B2 and 1% in the A2.    PLACIC  PODZOL    z  o  N  o  "r    A2    B2                   1.4- 2OJ.l'nII  20 -  75jam  v  i m  i      i      i      i      i      i      l  v  0             10          20          30          40          50          60           70          80  1o CHLORITE    Fig. 3. Amount of chlorite plotted against horizons in the Placic Podzol.    DISCUSSION    Although the chlorite contents obtained by the quantitative method em-  ployed may not be absolutely correct, the trends in the chlorite content be-  tween horizons for any one size fraction will be meaningful, as any errors  will be of comparable magnitude; furthermore, the method has been shown  to yield reproducible analyses (coefficient of variation is 9.5%).  In both soils, chlorite was dominant in the clay fractions and showed little  sign of variation in amount with profile depth. In the Dystric Cambisol the  trends in the chlorite content in the silt fractions indicate a slight decrease  towards the soil surface, but in the Podzol the trends very definitely indi-  cate a sharp fall in the chlorite content in the fine silt in the upper horizons  (particularly between the B2 and A2 horizons) and a steady decrease in the  coarse silt. In addition, the decrease in the chlorite content of the total soil  must indicate that chlorite is weathering out of the soil as a whole. In both  profiles the quantity of chlorite in the fine silt is considerably higher than in  the coarse silt. The process operating in the Eredine Podzol (Bain, 1977b),    226    where the chlorite is absent in the A horizon, probably occurs in all the soils  studied previously, or at least in the freely drained profiles, but the effect of  chlorite being dissolved out from the clay fractions is being masked as the  mineral is being replaced by chlorite from the fine silt fractions. Thus the  impression gained in the earlier study confined to the clay fractions only  (Bain, 1977a), that chlorite weathers slightly, appears to be erroneous.  In all the profiles examined from the Loch Awe region, chlorite is very  minor in the fine sand fraction, minor in the coarse silt, abundant in the fine  silt, and dominant in the clay fraction. This distribution, by which the  amount of chlorite increases with decreasing particle size, suggests that  chlorite is being broken down and transferred to finer particle size fractions  so that the coarse silt supplies the fine silt which in turn supplies the clay  fraction from which the chlorite is being dissolved out. With time, chlorite  will most probably disappear first from the fine sand fraction, then in turn  from the coarse silt, fine silt and eventually from the clay fraction.  Most of the soils in this area are developed on glacial till derived exclusive-  ly from chlorite-schists. The Eredine Podzol is developed on glacial till de-  rived from a mixture of chlorite-schists, grits and phyllites (Bain, 1977b)  and consequently the total amount of chlorite in the parent material would  have been less than in the other profiles. As a result, the effect of weathering  out of chlorite has become evident in this profile earlier than in the other  soils. Clearly the chlorite is rapidly being removed from the fine silt in the  A2 horizon of the Ardbrecknish Podzol, probably due to decomposition by  organic acids as in the Eredine Podzol and a New Brunswick Podzol de-  scribed recently by Ross et al. {1982), also developed on chloritic schists.  Eventually the A2 horizon of the Ardbrecknish Podzol will not contain any  chlorite and then, presumably, it will be similar mineralogically to the Cana-  dian Podzols.    CONCLUSIONS    Examining only the clay fraction when studying the weathering of a par-  ticular soil clay mineral can be misleading. Extension of the study of chlorite  weathering in a suite of highly chloritic Scottish soils to the silt fractions by  a quantitative X-ray diffraction method, indicates that, contrary to the find-  ings from the clay fraction study, chlorite is unstable in these soils and is  being dissolved out. This effect is masked in the clay fractions by the re-  placement of that chlorite by chlorite from the silt fractions. The overall  loss of chlorite from the soils was confirmed by the analysis of the total soils  which indicated that the amount of chlorite in the profile decreases towards  the soil surface.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    The authors thank Dr M.J. Wilson for advice based on his experience in  applying the quantitative X-ray method to soil materials.    227    REFERENCES    Adams, W.A., Evans, L.J. and Abduila, H.H., 1971. Quantitative pedological studies on  soils derived from Silurian mudstones, III. Laboratory and "in situ" weathering of  chlorite. J. Soil Sci., 22: 158--165.  Bain, D.C., 1972. Oxidation of chlorites in soil clays and effect on DTA curves. Nature  Phys. Sci., 238: 142--143.  Bain, D.C., 1976. A titanium-rich soil clay. J. Soil Sci., 27: 68--70.  Bain, D.C., 1977a. The weathering of chloritic minerals in some Scottish soils. J. Soil Sci.,  28: 144--164.  Bain, D.C., 1977b. The weathering of ferruginous chlorite in a podzol from Argyllshire,  Scotland. Geoderma, 17 : 193--208.  Brydon, J.E., Kodama, H. and Ross, G.J., 1968. Mineralogy and weathering of the clays  in orthic podzols and other podzolic soils in Canada. Trans. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 9th,  Adelaide, 3: 41--53.  Camez, T., 1962. Etudes sur l'6voluton des min6raux argileux dans les sols des r6gions  temp~rSes. Th~se Sci., Strasbourg, M6m. Serv. Carte g~ol., Als. Lorr., 20: 1--90.  Chung, F.H., 1974. Quantitative interpetation of X-ray diffraction patterns of mixtures,  I. Matrix-flushing method for quantitative multicomponent analysis. J. Appl. Cryst., 7 :  519--525.  Droste, J.B., Bhattacharya, N. and Sunderman, J.A., 1962. Clay mineral alteration in  some Indiana soils. Clays Clay Miner., 9: 329--342.  FAO, 1974. FAO--Unesco Soil Map of the World, Vol. I, Legend. Unesco, Paris, 50 pp.  Gilkes, R.J. and Little, I.P., 1972. Weathering of chlorite and some associations of trace  elements in Permian phyllites in southeastern Queensland. Geoderma, 7 : 233--247.  Gjems, O., 1967. Studies on clay minerals and clay mineral formation in soil profiles in  Scandinavia. Medd. Nor. Skogforsoksves., 21: 303--415.  Johnson, L.J., 1964. Chlorite--vermiculite intergrade as a weathering product of chlorite  in a soil. Am. Miner., 49: 556--572.  Perrin, R.M.S., 1971. The Clay Mineralogy of British Sediments. Mineralogical Society,  London.  Ross, G.J., 1980. The mineralogy of spodosols. In: B.K.G. Theng (Editor). Soils with  Variable Charge. N.Z. Soc. Soil Sci., pp. 127--143.  Ross, G.J., Wang, C., Ozkan, A.I. and Rees, H.W., 1982. Weathering of chlorite and mica  in a New Brunswick podzol developed on till derived from chlorite--mica schist. Geo-  derma, 27: 255--267.  Schwertmann, U., 1976. Die Verwitterung mafischer Chlorite. Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Boden-  kd., 139: 27--36.  Stephen, I., 1952. A study of rock weathering with reference to the soils of the Malvern  Hills, II. Weathering of appinite and "ivy-scar rock". J. Soil Sci., 3: 219--237.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractPrevious work on chloritic soils in Scotland indicated that, irrespective of soil type or drainage class, the chlorite that was dominant in the clay fractions weathered only slightly, showing little variation in amount with depth. These soils have been investigated further by determination of the chlorite content in the silt fractions by a quantitative X-ray diffraction technique. In a Dystric Cambisol and a Placic Podzol, the fine silt fractions (1.4–20 μm) contain much more chlorite than the coarse silt (20–75 μm) and in both fractions the amount of chlorite decreases towards the surface, markedly so in the Placic Podzol. It is suggested that chlorite is being dissolved out from the clay fractions but as chlorite is being broken down and transferred to finer particle size fractions, this dissolution effect is being masked by the replacement of the clay fraction chlorite from the fine silt. Analysis of the total soils (&lt;22 mm) confirmed the net loss of chlorite from these profiles. 