 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 257--273                                                   257  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    MINERAL FACIES DEVELOPED BY WEATHERING OF A META-GABBRO,  LOIRE-ATLANTIQUE (FRANCE)    P. ILDEFONSE  Laboratoire de P$dologie -- E.R.A. no. 220 du C.N.R.S., FacultO des Sciences de  l 'Universit~ de Poitiers, 40, avenue du Recteur Pineau, 86022 Poitiers CEDEX (France)  (Received June 11, 1979; accepted December 19, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Ildefonse, P., 1980. Mineral facies developed by weathering of a meta-gabbro, Loire-  Atlantique (France). Geoderma, 24: 257--273.    A study of the weathering products developed from a plagioclase amphibolite (meta-  gabbro) was carried out using a petrographic microscope, mineral separation, X-ray  diffraction, electron microprobe and wet chemical analysis methods. The weathering  profile was considered as having two parts: one where the structure of the source rock  had persisted and the other where an essentially argillaceous material was present in a  chaotic arrangement. It was apparent that rock structures governed the types of chemical  systems active in forming clay minerals. These systems:can be grouped into four types:  (1) Grain boundary reactions. These are the earliest manifestations of weathering.  Amphibole--plagioclase boundaries give rise to iron beidellite from the feldspars.  (2) Primary plasma zones: internal breakdown of the metamorphic minerals results  in heterogeneous plasma. In the lower layers (relict rock structure), plagioclases are less  affected than amphiboles. The latter form a nontronite-talc-iron-rich gel assemblage.  In the upper layers (argillized), both plagioclase and amphibole are altered to a vermi-  culitic mineral witha composition governed by that of the host mineral: aluminous  dioctahedral for plagioclases, and ferromagnesian trioctahedral for calcic amphiboles.  These vermiculites are altered to ferri-beidellites in the adjacent plasma.  (3) Secondary plasma zones: in the general plasma structure of the argillized zone,  a large-grain (often &gt; 100 um in length) trioctahedral vermiculite of highly variable  composition is formed.  (4) Fissure zones: walls of the fissures are sometimes covered with clay cutans  which are progressively thicker as porosity increases. Whatever the size or position of  these cutans, they are always composed of an iron beidellite--iron gel assemblage.  Mineral facies in these different zones are represented in Mg--A1--Fe coordinates.    INTRODUCTION    The objectives of the study were two-fold. The first purpose was to find  the exact locations within a weathering profile at which new minerals were  formed. The second was to determine the chemical and mineralogical  characters of the weathering products. It ~vas hoped that such information  would provide a better understanding of' mineral transformations during    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$ 02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    258    weathering, on the one hand, and the extent to which the local chemistry  of mineral grains and soil horizons governed the nature of the new  minerals crystallized, on the other.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Wea th ering profile    The weathering profile selected for study was at the edge of the Margerie  quarry, 2 km southwest of Gorges, Loire-Atlantique, France. Depth to bed-  rock was approximately 4 m, as shown in Fig. 1. The weathering profile, ex-  clusive of a thin overburden, consisted of two distinct sectors or zones, viz.:  (1) A lower zone (layers 3--8) in which the rock shows evidence of gra-    ir-~rt    overburden: soil  ctured argillized layers  tic structure    rock structure layers  ~ct altered rock.    Fig. 1. Weathering profile.    259    dual weathering in ~hat it becomes progressively more friable upward even  though the original rock structure persists. For identification, this is called  the zone of relict rock structure.  (2) An upper zone (layers 9--12) in which rock structure has been obli-  terated and in which there is an abundance of clay and plasma, as for  example 36% of the solids in layer 12 are in the &lt; 2-~m fraction. For identi-  fication, this zone is called argillized layers.   Samples were collected for laboratory analyses from all layers identified  by numerals on the right side of Fig. 1.  The overburden of Tertiary sediments, in which a Eutrochrept had  been formed, was not sampled because that material is not related to the  bedrock.  The bedrock is an amphibolitized gabbro forming part of the "Massif  du Pallet". Specimens of the rock were hand-picked from beneath the  weathering profile at the mine-head or upper part of the quarry. The rock  was composed generally of the following minerals: amphiboles (some  cummingtonite but mostly actinolites) 50%; plagioclase (An 52) 47%;  ilmenite 2%; accessory minerals such as brown hornblende, biotite and  apatite 1%. Negligible quantities of phyllosilicates were also identified.    Me thods    Thin sections of the rock and of the altered materials were made after they  had been impregnated with a very slow-setting epoxy resin. The thin sections  were examined with a petrographic microscope and with an electron probe,  using a CAMECA probe and TRACOR solid-state detector plus standard ZAF  correction procedures for measured radiation intensities. This method allows  the use of a low-energy electron beam (1 nano-ampere current) so that loss  through volatilization is kept to a minimum.  Some samples were crushed and analysed by several techniques. Amphibole  and plagioclase from layers 3--12 were separated by electromagnetic means  and given successive ultrasonic treatments (1--3 min). These treatments put  the plasma material into suspension first, followed by minerals found in  cracks or attached to the unaltered surfaces of large mineral grains. Minerals  present were then identified by X-ray diffraction. Clay fractions (&lt; 2 ~m)  obtained from layers 3--12 were placed into suspensions by standard treat-  ment (Robert and Tessier, 1974). These were then analysed by X-ray dif-  fraction, using a CGR apparatus providing reflections from CuK~-(060)  radiation to permit differentiation of di- and tri-octahedral minerals. DTA  and thermogravimetric analyses were also applied to the Clay fractions for  more precise determinations of smectites (Trauth and Lucas, 1967; Chantret  et al., 1971).  To obtain more information Dn the composition of the samples, bulk  chemical analyses were made of all samples and citrate-dithionite extractions  of five samples (&lt; 2-~m fractions extracted from plagioclase of layers 6 and    260    12, &lt; 2-~m fractions extracted from amphiboles of layers 9, 10 and 12).  For bulk chemical analyses, samples were fused with strontium metaborate  and then dissolved in HNO3. All elements were determined by atomic ab-  sorption. For the citrate-dithionite extraction, the procedure of De Coninck  and Herbillon (1969) was used. Fe was determined by atomic absorption.    PHASE IDENTIFICATION    As used in this paper, "phase" refers to the new mineral species that appear  in the same site under the same physico-chemical conditions.  The optical studies indicated four principal sites for new mineral forma-  tion (Ildefonse et al., 1978), as follows: contacts between mineral grains,  primary plasma internal to mineral grains, secondary plasma external to  mineral grains in the argillized layers and argillaceous accretions on edges of  pores and fissures.    Reactions at mineral contacts    The fine-grained (~ 10 pm) phase was extracted for examination from con-  tacts between amphibole and plagioclase grains in layers with relict rock struc-  ture. That phase was slightly pleochroic {colorless to pale yellow) in ordinary  light but had colors of a third order under crossed nicols, as shown in Fig. 2  (photo 1). Moreover, the minute reaction zones seemed to grow by invading  small fractures in plagioclase grains. The zones were restricted to surfaces of  amphibole grains, and were never found within them.  X-ray diffraction of clays extraced from the reaction zones of these  plagioclases indicates that they are dioctahedral smectites [(060) reflection  at 1.49 A ], specifically beidellite-type minerals (Si ~ A1, Mering, 1975; Table  I). DTA, thermogravimetric and bulk chemical analyses indicate them to be  aluminoferric. Charges are largely found in the tetrahedral layers and are  quite high (Table II). A citrate-dithionite treatment shows some amorphous  Fe in these fractions. For example, in the sample from layer 6, 3.59% Fe2 03  was extracted; the corrected formula is given in Table II.  Microprobe analyses indicated considerable heterogeneity in composition.    Fig. 2. Sites of secondary minerals formation in a weathered meta-gabbro.  Photo 1. Phyllites at grain contacts (layer 3). Natural light. Phyllites (r) enter into  labradorite (L); still unaltered amphibole (a) is used as support for this new crystallization.  Photo 2. Internal weathering of labradorite (layer 9). No polarized light. Little phyllites  (A) occur at the surfaces of weathered labrador fragments. Cryptocristalline material (~)  appears at the edges of grains or in microfissures. Note also intramineral cutan.  Photo 3. Internal weathering of amphiboles in relict rock structure (layer 3). No polax-  ized light. Amphiboles (a) almost entirely converted to pseudomorphs of pleochroic mate-  rial (P) (pale yellow to gold yellow). From place to place, an uncolored zone (2) consti-  tutes cryptocristalline minerals. An f represents a vein of little uncolored and birefringent  minerals (perhaps talc). Note also titanium oxide accumulation, very refringent and opaque  in photography.    TABLE I  X-ray data for minerals occurring at grain contacts (layer 3) (spacing in ~ngstroms of (001)  reflection)    bO    Interlayer cation    25    110  200  300  400  550  E. glycol.  14.24   13.79   11.29   10.74   10.34   10.03   16.97  12.87   12.79   heated to 110 and glycolated    16.98  Heated to 300C overnight and glycolated           17.04    Mg  K  Li    TABLE II  Structural formulae of beidellites occurring at grain contacts and extracted from the labradorites of the relict rock structure    Layers     Tetrahedral      Octahedral sheet                            Interlayer sheet           Octa-      Layer  sheet                                                                                   hedral     charge  occupancy    Si       Al       A1       Ti       Fe3     Mn      Mg      Ca      Na      K    Interlayer  charge    3          3.24    0.76    0.83    0.01    0.80    0.01    0.44    0.27    0.24    0.10    2.09       0.94  4          3.32    0.68    1.04    0.01    0.68    0.01    0.32    0.25    0.22    0.09    2.06       0.82  5           3.37     0.63     0.79     0.01     0.82     0.01     0.37     0.31     0.24     0.05     2.00        1.00  6           3.30    0.70    0.99     0.01     0.68     0.01     0.34    0.28     0.26     0.08     2.03        0.95  6 (after  citrate  dithionite) 3.41    0.59    1.12    0.01    0.50    0.01    0.36    0.29    0.27    0.09    2.00       0.95    0.88  0.81  0.91  0.90  0.94    263    The beidellites seem to be less rich in Mg and Fe the further they are from  the amphibole grain (Ildefonse, 1978). Hence, bulk chemical analyses pro-  vide only the average compositions of these smectites.    Internal alteration of plagioclase    Plagioclase grains are but slightly affected by weathering in the lower  layers and are strongly altered in the argillized layers. Specific optical proper-  ties are lost, e.g., twinning planes are no longer distinguishable. Microfissures  are obvious, dividing the crystals, and optical extinction becomes irregular  in something of a checkerboard pattern. Their alteration produces a primary  plasma which is heterogeneous {Fig. 2, photo 2). In the microfractures and  at the grain edges there is a ferric beidellite which is easily detached by ultra-  sonic treatment. A small amount of vermiculite is admixed with the beidel-  lite (Fig. 3). In the corrosion centers inside and on the plagioclase grain sur-  faces, there are vermiculites of a 5 pm grain-size (dioctahedral: (060) re-  flection at 1.49--1.50 A). Not restricted to the upper part, vermiculite is  much more abundant in the argillized layers. The slowness in collapse upon  heating indicates a similarity with material described by Jackson (1963),  Tardy and Gac (1968), and Meunier (1977), considered to contain hydroxy-  aluminous interlayers. No direct evidence of gibbsite formation was found  in the present study. Further, a ferric gel was indicated by the presence of  a strong exotherm at 330 in DTA determinations. A sodi-potassic zeolite  was found in layer 8 (Ildefonse, 1977), but not above or below it.  The chemical analyses of the &lt; 2-pm fractions from layers 9, 10, 11 and  12 indicate the presence of large amounts of beidellite in which tetrahedral  substitutions can be assumed. A citrate-dithionite treatment shows some    TABLE III    Calculated formulae based on eleven oxygens for &lt; 2-am material extracted from labra-  dorites (argillized zone); due to the heterogeneity of fractions, these calculations can only  be considered as indicative of relative proportions of the various ions present and do not  represent the formula of a given mineral    Layers  Tetrahedral      Octahedral sheet                        Interlayer sheet  sheet    Si       A1      Al      Ti      Fe3.    Mn  Mg      Ca      Na      K    9      3.39  10      3.39  11      3.40  12      3.37  12 (after  citrate di-  thionite) 3.46    0.61          0.97          0.04          0.72          --       0.38         0.15          0.15          0.10  0.61          1.01          0.04          0.65           --       0.35          0.17          0.21          0.15  0.60    1.05    0.05    0.64     --   0.35    0.15    0.20    0.09  0.63          1.12          0.03          0.68          --       0.26          0.13          0.16          0.09  0.54    1.22    0.03    0.55     --   0.27    0.13    0.17    0.10    264    Phases &lt; 2 pm easy to extract  by ultrasonic treatments  10.08  ~144      M  550  I ~g                                              Phases difficult to extract  1             .17.72                                                 by ultrasonic treatments  10.10           E. glycol.                        A ~3tt  Hlfe:::n- /   /,  14.33  Mg 550  y~~/KllOE" glyc" MgE'glyc" ~'~%~/ I kJI  J~~/K II0  Mg 25 C~'j  ~c                               T        1,o    t,, t,  Fig.'3. X-ray diffraction traces of secondary phases separated by successive ultrasonic  treatments from weathered labradorites in argillized-zone (layer 10). Anticathode Cu(Ke ).  amorphous Fe in these fractions. For example, in the sample from layer 12,  2.67% Fe2 Oa was extracted, the recalculated formula is given in Table III.  Compositions of the &gt; 2-pm material associated with the plagioclase indi-  cate the presence of an aluminous dioctahedral vermiculite (Ildefonse, 1978).  Results obtained in this study indicate that internal alteration of plagio-  clase grains occurs in two steps:  ('1) Corrosion centers on the grain surfaces give rise to vermiculite (already  in layer 3 but mostly in argillized layers) and zeolite (layer 8), the composi-  tions of which are strongly influenced by the host mineral.    265    (2) In argillized layers, these phases are altered to beidellites in primary  plasma. These smectites contain some Mg and more Fe which undoubtedly  come from the amphiboles.  Thus, the first clay-mineral phase produced (vermiculite of larger grain  size) is compositionally close to the host mineral, whereas its successor,  beidellite, indicates a chemical contribution from neighbouring grains of  another species.    Internal alteration of amphiboles    In the lower layers with relict rock structure, the amphiboles (cumingtonite  and actinolite} are greatly altered and at times completely replaced by pseudo-  morphs (Fig. 2, photo 3). X-ray diffraction indicates the presence of beidel-  litic nontronite [(060} reflection at 1.49 A ] and a type of talc. Differential  thermal analysis again indicates the presence of gel material in a 330  exotherm (Mackenzie and Berggren, 1970).  In the argillized layers, the structures of the altered grains of the lower  layers are completely obliterated leaving only a little (150--200 ~m) debris  of the host grains. No cummingtonite is present. The beidellitic nontronite  and talc minerals appear to contribute to the formation of a new phase, i.e.,  large-grain (50--200 pm) vermiculite. This phase was described by Ildefonse  et al. (1979). The actinolite is altered to a heterogeneous plasma (Fig. 4,  photo 4).  In highly microfissured zones of the primary plasma developed from  actinolites in layers 9, 10, 11 and 12, there are cryptocristalline materials  colored by iron oxide. Within the grains, there are small pleochroi'c (clear  to yellow orange) phyllites (&lt; 30 pm) with parallel extinction which seem  to be pseudomorphs of the amphiboles.  Ultrasonic treatment of these amphibole grains (actinolite) initially libera-  tes cryptocrystalline phases which are essentially beideUite with minor  amounts of vermiculite present. The phyllites which adhere tightly to the  grains are liberated by further ultrasonic treatment. They are trioctahedral  vermiculites [(060) reflection at 1.52--1.53 A ] (Fig. 5). Again DTA indi-  cates the presence of a gel plus smectites with ferric chemistry and Si--Al  substitutions (endotherm near 500C). Bulk chemical analysis of the &lt; 2-pm  fractions extracted from actinolites in layers 9, 10, 11 and 12 shows the  high content of Fe2 03 characteristic of ferric beidellite. An example of  citrate-dithionite treatment in a sample from layer 12 (4.23% Fe2 03 ex-  tracted) is given in Table IV. Analysis of the fraction closely held by the  actinolite indicates the influence of the host mineral on the composition of  the vermiculite (Ildefonse, 1978).  Alteration of amphiboles (cummingtonite and actinolite) leads to the forma-  tion of twa mineral facies depending upon position in the profile (relict rock  structure or argillized layers):  (1) The lower layers where cummingtonite and actinolite are altered to  a nontronite-talc-gel assemblage.    Phases &lt; 2 #m easy to extract  by ultrasonic treatments  K I IO  K 25    17.17  A       Mg  E. glycol.    Mg 25    267    Phases difficult to extract  by ultrasonic treatments  ~77  550OC~~I/  300  iolo  ?Ig  I  Mg E.  ~  ~                                  glycol .~  114 Ii7      A                      Mg 25 ~      110   14 li7 A  Fig. 5. X-ray diffraction traces of secondary minerals separated by ultrasonic treatments  from weathered actinolites in the argillized zone (layer 10). Anticathode Cu(Ka).    Fig. 4. Sites of secondary minerals formation.  Photo 4. Internal weathering of actinolite in argillized zone. Natural light. (Layer 9). In  this argillized zone, two sites of secondary minerals occurring can be seen: 1. pleochroic  phyllites pseudomorphose; they are imbricated in their structure; 2. in very microfissured  zones, cryptocrystalline material occurs in relation with porosity.  Photo 5. Large-grain vermiculites in argillized rock (layer 9). Natural light. These great  phyllites are pleochroic (uncolored to orange yellow). Meanwhile, few layers are coloured in  pale green (-+) and very refringent granulations of leucoxede can be seen.  Photo 6. Destabilization of vermiculites at the top of the outcrop (layer 12). Natural light.  Phyllites become very flexuous. Layers bundles diverge and in the space created crypto-  crystalline material appears (--*). Very 0xided aspects of these phyllites contrast with  those of inferior layers. Note also very fine and extensive secondary plasma.    268    TABLE IV    Calculated formulae based on eleven oxygens for &lt; 2-urn material extracted from actino-  lites (argillized zone); the calculations are only indicative and do not represent the formula  of a given material    Layers  Tetrahedral      Octahedral sheet                         Interlayer sheet  sheet    Si       AI      A1      Ti      Fe3  Mn    Mg      Ca      Na      K    9      3.31    0.69    0.84    0.07   0.88   0.01   0.45    0.15    0.02    0.06  10      3.21    0.79    0.63    0.11    0.90   0.01   0.62    0.22    0.04    0.05  11      3.24    0.76    0.73    0.08    0.84   0.01   0.61    0.19    0.03    0.03  12      3.27    0.73    0.96    0.04    0.85   0.01   0.36    0.13    0.04    0.09  12 (after  citrate di-  thionite) 3.38    0.62    1.13    0.04    0.63   0.01  0.37    0.13    0.04    0.09    (2) The argillized layers where actinolite (no cummingtonite is present)  is altered to trioctahedral vermiculites in a first stage. These are then altered  in the plasma to a ferric beidellite (an aluminous mineral) which indicates  a contribution from plagioclase to the_new minerals.    New phases in the secondary plasma    In the argiUized layers, the rock structure is lost, creating a mixture of  amphibole mineral grains and their decomposition products. In this situation,  the large grains of phyllite (50--200 pm) which crystallize are often associated  with amphibole debris. The prismatic grains polarize in the third order and  show colorless to yellow orange pleochroism (Fig. 4 photo 5). X-ray diffrac-  tion and powder studies show that this phase consists of a trioctahedral  vermiculite of 0.6--0.8 charge (Suquet, 1978). Electron microprobe analyses  (Ildefonse et al., 1979) indicate that the mineral differs in composition from  grain to grain. The octahedral site is often underfilled and the tetrahedral  site is at times filled by some iron atoms. The iron content is rather constant  whereas Mg seems to increase at the expense of A1 in the structure.  In the uppermost layers (11, 12) these vermiculites differ in their optical  aspects (Fig. 4, photo 6). They are deformed, split, present patches of oxides,  become smectitic and are apparently associated with ferric gel (Ildefonse,  1978). It appears that the vermiculite produced under weathering conditions  in the zone where the different types of new clay minerals are mixed in its  turn becomes unstable as weathering conditions change towards the surface.    Fissure systems    Percolation water creates fissures in rocks at the surface of the earth. Small  fissures already appear in the lower part of weathering profile. They then    269    become wider and ramify in more altered layers. Walls of the pores are some-  times covered with clay cutans which are progressively thicker as porosity  increases. Whatever the size or position of these cutans, they are always com-  posed of an assemblage of ferric beidellite-ferric gels. Microprobe analysis  confirms the alumino-ferric character of the material (Table V). The Mg  content is high; it may be present in interlayer sheets near Ca and K. A silica--  alumina ratio near 2 indicates significant substitutions in tetrahedral positions  characteristic of minerals of the beidellite type.    TABLE V  Calculated formulae based on eleven oxygens for cutans from layer 9 (microprobe  analyses); octahedral sheet is completed to 2 atoms; remaining Mg is put in interlayer  sheet    Tetrahedral      Octahedral sheet                   Interlayer sheet           Si/A1  sheet    Si       Al      A1      Ti      Fe3   Mg     Mg      Ca      K    3.36    0.64    1.07    0.03    0.67    0.23    0.31    0.08    0.04    1.96  3.37    0.63    1.03    0.02    0.75    0.20    0.30    0.07    0.04    2.03  3.30         0.70          0.90         0.02         0.84         0.24         0.35         0.09         0.02          2.05    DISCUSSION    It is possible to define four different geochemical systems during the  alteration of a metagabbro. These are: (1) mineral contacts; (2) primary plasma  within individual mineral grains; (3) secondary plasma which does not respect  former grain volumes but seems to include materials from several mineral  grains; (4) fissure zones.  If mineral compositions are projected on the coordinates A1--Mg--Fe3 (total iron expressed as Fe2 03 ), the mineral parageneses of alteration can  be followed and different weathering systems distinguished. Si is considered  to be in excess or its presence will not provoke the crystallization of a  separate phyllosilicate phase nor will a lack of silica suppress a phase. The  principal source of A1 in the original mineral assemblage is plagioclase and  the amphiboles are the major source of Mg and Fe. Neither Ca nor Na are  taken into account. Titanium seems to be slightly mobile, recrystallizing  rapidly to anatase and leucoxene.  The poles for A1, Mg and Fe in the chart represent the phases plagioclaseL-  talc--oxides, respectively, which cover the chemiographic space in which  old and ne.w phases occur (Fig. 6A).  The initial assemblage of amphibole--plagioclase--ilmenite is shown in  Fig. 6B.    270    Mg  - Fe,,'~"1/////~ "-.~  A I""                   Fe  AI                            -;"e  ~                           Mg  ,  o/:2  . \ .    Fig. 6. Chemiographic representation of mineralogical transformations of primary and  secondary minerals in the A1--Mg--Fe system.  A. Position of primary and secondary minerals in the A1--Fe--Mg system. B. Starting  assemblage. C. Grain contact assemblage. D. Internal destabilization in layers with relict  rock structure. E. ArgiUized zone: neogenesis in secondary plasma. F. Argillized zone:  internal destabilization of labradorite and actinolite. G. Fissure system.  A = amphiboles from parent rock (actinolite and cummingtonite);L = labradorite from  parent rock; T = talc (theorical composition); O = iron oxides and hydroxides (total  iron expressed in Fe2 03 ): ilmenite in fresh rock and gel in weathering profile; Z =  zeolites (heulandite and chabazite); r.Be = ferric beidellite at grain contacts (plotted with  results of Table II); N -- nontronite (plotted with analyses of &lt; 2-urn fractions extracted  from amphibole in layers where rock structure is conserved); Vd = dioctahedral vermi-  culite plotted with results of chemical analyses of difficult to extract phases by ultrasonic  treatments in weathered labradorite; Vt = trioetahedral vermiculites (plotted with results  in Ildefonse, 1978, 1979); large-size vermiculites and vermiculite in actinolite; L.Be =  ferric beidellite extracted from labradorite in argillized zone (plotted with results of Table  III); A.Be = ferric beidellite extracted from actinolite in argillized zone (plotted with results  of Table IV).    Layers with relict rock structure    In these ~ayers, two types of assemblages occur in the same sample.  Grain contacts. Fig. 6C indicates the product of reactions between plagio-  clase and amphibole which give rise to beidellite and iron oxides. The assem-  blage suggests a net loss of AI+Mg. Smectites appear to grow within plagio-  clase grains, thus using available A1 and Ca whereas iron and magnesium are    271    furnished by short-distance migration from adjacent amphibole grains.  Internal alteration. Fig. 6D shows the two assemblages due to internal recrys-  tallization of initial minerals. The plagioclase, that is relatively little affected,  is altered to an assemblage of a dioctahedral vermiculitic mineral plus zeolite.  These phases are present in minor quantities. In contrast, the amphibole is  greatly altered to nontronite, talc and ferric gels. The two microsystems  present facies separated in chemiographic space in the chart. The bulk com-  position of each system may not be greatly modified as far as Mg--A1--Fe  components are concerned. Nonetheless, the loss of calcium from the rock  is significant (Ildefonse, 1978). The cummingtonites alter more rapidly than  the actinolites.    Argillized layers    In the upper layers (9--12) there has been a significant increase in vermi-  culitic and smectitic minerals as compared to deeper layers (3--8). The  assemblage labradorite (unaltered) + beidellite (neoformed) + nontronite +  talc + amphibole (unaltered actinolite) reacts to form a new vermiculite  which is trioctahedral. This is the major phase formed in the secondary  plasma (Fig. 6E).  The remaining plagioclase and amphibole alter internally to a heterogene-  ous primary plasma. Labradorite gives dioctahedral vermiculite + ferric  beidellite + ferric gel which indicates transportation of some ferromagnesian  components into the microsystem from the exterior (Fig. 6F). Actinolites  are altered to an assemblage of trioctahedral vermiculite + ferric beidellite  + gel (Fig. 6F).  The new assemblages are again distinct due to the separate chemical sys-  tems which form them. The chemistry of the primary phases strongly  affects the nature of the neoformed phases as has been noted previously by  Tardy (1969) and Proust and Velde (1978). In plagioclase, vermiculite is  dioctahedral and aluminous, whereas in actinolite it is trioctahedral and  ferromagnesian. In contrast, the ferric beidellites which replace vermiculites  in both host minerals have closely related chemistry: i.e. there has been  plasmic homogeneization. Large grain size vermiculites, crystallized in  secondary plasma, which appears to incorporate and beidellites from the  primary plasma, have a chemistry which is not dependent on primary  minerals (plagioclase and amphibole).    Fissure systems    In this chemical environment, only the beidellite-oxide gel assemblage  occurs. This suggests that all older assemblages (dioctahedral vermiculite +  zeolite, dioctahedral vermiculite + ferric beidellites + gel in plagioclase,  nontronite + talc + gel, trioctahedral vermiculite + ferric beidellite + gel  in amphibole and large-sized trioctahedral Vermiculite in secondary plasma)    272    have become unstable in upper layers of the weathering profile and that  only beidellite-gel oxide remains to be transported by circulating water.  This assemblage is found at all levels in the fissures of the profile, suggesting  that fissure systems present the same chemical environment throughout.    CONCLUSION    This study permits comparisons of mechanisms in alteration of a meta-  gabbro with those for other basic rocks (Ildefonse et al., 1978) and for  granites (Meunier, 1977). It is apparent that the structure of the rock con-  trols the dimensions of the systems in which the reactive chemical com-  ponents are found. Thus, the different mineral assemblages produced are  functions of the specific situations in the rock (grain contact, grain center,  fissure) as well as the layer in the weathering profile (deep, surface, etc.).  The sequence of alteration phenomena can be summarized as follows:    1st stage:              2nd stage:             3rd stage:  relict rock structure    argillized layers        fissures    plagioclase             zeolite + gel            dioct, verm.  dioct, verm.  beidellite at grain                              ferric beidellite  contacts                                       + gel (Fe3    amphibole             nontronite + talc       trioct, verm.  + gel                   large-grain trioct, verm.    These three stages of alteration give rise to different mineral facies which  are then altered and transformed into the next stage. The fact that the clay  minerals are transformed into or altered to provide materials for other clay  minerals indicates that materials in weathering cycles are highly reactive and  respond quickly to new chemical contraints.    REFERENCES    Chantret, F., Desprairies, A., Douillet, P., Jacob, C., Steinberg, M. and Trauth, N., 1971.  R~vision critique de l'utilisation des m~thodes thermiques en s~dimentologie. Cas des  smectites (montmorillonites). Bull. Groupe Fr. Argiles, 23(2): 141--172.  De Coninck, F. and Herbillon, A., 1969. Evolution min~ralogique et chimique des fractions  argileuses dans des alfisols et des spodosols de la Campine (Belgique). Pedologie, 19(2):  159--272.  Ildefonse, P., 1977. Formation de z~olites dans l'alt~ration d'une roche gabbroi~lue du  massif du Pallet (Loire-Atlantique). C.R. Acad. Sci.., 284: 1373--1376.  Ildefonse, P., Proust, D., Meunier, A. and Velde, B., 1978. RSle des ph~nom~nes de  d~stabilisation--Tecristallisation'successifs dans l'alt~ration des roches cristallines au  sein des micromilieux chimiques. In: L'alt~ration des roches cristallines en milieu  superficiel, Commun. S~minaire A.F.E.S., Versailles (in press).    273    Ildefonse, P., 1978. M6canismes de l'Alt6ration d'une Roche gabbroi~lue du Massif du  Pallet (Loire-Atlantique). Th~se 3~me cycle, Univ. Poitiers, 142 pp.  Ildefonse, P., Copin, E. and Velde, B., 1979. A soil vermiculite formed from a meta-gabbro,  Loire-Atlantique, France. Clay Miner., 14(3): 201--210.  Jackson, M.L., 1963. Interlayering of expansible layer silicates in soils by chemical  weathering. Clays Clay Miner., 11: 20--46.  Mackenzie, R.C. and Berggren, G., 1970. In: R.C. Mackenzie (Editor), Differential  Thermal Analysis, 1. Acad. Press, London, pp. 277--279.  Meting, J., 1975. Smectites. In: J.E. Gieseling (Editor), Soil Components, 2. Inorganic  Components. Springer, Berlin. pp. 97--119.  Meunier, A., 1977. Les M6canismes de l'Alt~ration des Granites et le R61e des Micro-  syst~mes. Etude des Ar~nes du Massif granitique de Parthenay (Deux-S~vres). ThAse  Doct. Etat, Univ. Poitiers, 248 pp.  Proust, D. and Velde, B., 1978. Beidellite crystallization from plagioclase and amphibole  precursors: local and long-range equilibrium during weathering. Clay Miner., 13: 199--209.  Robert, M. and Tessier, D., 1974. M6thode de preparation des argiles et des sols pour les  6tudes min6ralogiques. Ann. Agron., 25(6): 859--882.  Suquet, H., 1978. Propridt6s des Gonflement et Structure de la Saponite. Comparaison  avec la Vermiculite. Th~se Univ. Paris VI, 280 pp.  Tardy, Y., 1969. G6ochimie des alterations. Etude des ar~nes et des eaux de quelques  massifs cristallins d'Europe et d'Afrique. (Th~se Fac. Sci. Strasbourg) M6m. Serv. Carte  G6ol. Alsace Lorraine, 31:199 pp.  Tardy, Y. and Gac, J.Y., 1968. Les min6raux argileux de quelques sols et atones des  Vosges cristallines. Prdsence de vermiculite-A1. Hypoth~se de la n~oformation des vermi-  culites et montmorillonites. Bull. Serv. Carte G~ol. Alsace Lorraine, 21(4): 285--304.  Trauth, N. and Lucas, J., 1967. Apport des m~thodes thermiques dans l'6tude des min6-  raux argileux. Bull. Groupe Ft. Argiles, 19(2): 11--24.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractA study of the weathering products developed from a plagioclase amphibolite (metagabbro) was carried out using a petrographic microscope, mineral separation, X-ray diffraction, electron microprobe and wet chemical analysis methods. The weathering profile was considered as having two parts: one where the structure of the source rock had persisted and the other where an essentially argillaceous material was present in a chaotic arrangement. It was apparent that rock structures governed the types of chemical systems active in forming clay minerals. These systems can be grouped into four types: 1.(1) Grain boundary reactions. These are the earliest manifestations of weathering. Amphibole—plagioclase boundaries give rise to iron beidellite from the feldspars.2.(2) Primary plasma zones: internal breakdown of the metamorphic minerals results in heterogeneous plasma. In the lower layers (relict rock structure), plagioclases are less affected than amphiboles. The latter form a nontronite-talc-iron-rich gel assemblage. In the upper layers (argillized), both plagioclase and amphibole are altered to a vermiculitic mineral with a composition governed by that of the host mineral: aluminous dioctahedral for plagioclases, and ferromagnesian trioctahedral for calcic amphiboles. These vermiculites are altered to ferri-beidellites in the adjacent plasma.3.(3) Secondary plasma zones: in the general plasma structure of the argillized zone, a large-grain (often &gt; 100 μm in length) trioctahedral vermiculite of highly variable composition is formed.4.(4) Fissure zones: walls of the fissures are sometimes covered with clay cutans which are progressively thicker as porosity increases. Whatever the size or position of these cutans, they are always composed of an iron beidellite—iron gel assemblage. MgAlFe coordinates. 