 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 337--354  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    337    ADSORPTION--DESORPTION AND/OR PRECIPITATION--  DISSOLUTION PROCESSES OF ZINC IN SOILS    GERHARD BRUMMER1, KEVIN G. TILLER:, ULRICH HERMS' and  PAUL M. CLAYTON2  'Institut fur Pflanzenern~ihrung und Bodenkunde der UniversitSt Kiel, 2300 Kiel (F.R.G.)  :Division of Soils, CSIRO, Glen Osmond 5064, S.A. (Australia)  (Received November 23, 1982; revised version accepted May 6, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Br~immer, G., Tiller, K.G., Herms, U. and Clayton, P.M., 1983. Adsorption--desorption  and/or precipitation--dissolution processes of zinc in soils. Geoderma, 31: 337--354.    The concentrations of trace and toxic metals in soil solutions are explained by several  authors either in terms of adsorption--desorption or precipitation--dissolution reactions  in soils. Data have been given for zinc to test the applicability of both concepts. The re-  sults show that the concentrations of zinc in equilibrium solutions with soil clay fractions  and whole soil samples at pH values below 7 are determined exclusively by adsorption--  desorption reactions for various pH's, contents of bound zinc and compositions of soils.  At neutral to alkaline pH values precipitation--dissolution reactions of zinc may take  place. There is some evidence that formation of zinc silicates may control the zinc con-  centration in solution provided natural complexing agents are absent, the affinity of the  soil for zinc is low and the content of reaching zinc is high (&gt; ~ 100 ppm). Even at pH  values above 7, the formation of other zinc compounds is unlikely in most soils because  additions of large amounts of zinc are required to ensure saturation of the adsorption  sites of different soil components before the zinc concentration in the soil solution can  increase sufficiently to bring about the precipitation of definite compounds. Model ex-  periments in CaCO~-buffered systems showed that the adsorption capacity for specifically  adsorbed zinc (in umole/g) by the following components increased in the order CaCO3  (0.44), bentonite (44), humic acid (842), amorphous Fe- and Al-oxides (1190, 1310) and  8-MnO: (1540) and demonstrated the importance of Mn-, Fe-, and Al-oxides and humic  substances for the binding of zinc in soils containing carbonates, and thus indicate the  special role of these components in limiting precipitation reactions.    INTRODUCTION AND CONCEPTUAL CONSIDERATIONS    The composition of the solution phase is one of the most important prop-  erties of soils. Many processes in soil and landscape development are con-  nected with the movement of dissolved substances. Plants take up nutrients  from the soil solution. The concentration of dissolved nutrients is a charac-  teristic value of the nutrient status of the soils. But the processes which  determine the concentration of the different elements in the soil solution are  not yet fully understood. Changes in soil water content, departures from  equilibrium or steady state to non-equilibrium conditions and changes in the    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    338    activity of microorganisms which influence redox conditions, contents of  soluble chelating agents and the composition of soil atmosphere, require  simultaneous consideration. These processes moderate the reactions of ad-  sorption--desorption, precipitation--dissolution and complex and ion-pair  formation in relation to the pH and thus influence the composition of both  the solid material and the composition of the soil solution. Even if we ignore  the complexity of possible reactions in natural soil systems and restrict con-  siderations to equilibrium conditions of simplified model systems, the ques-  tion often still arises as to whether adsorption--desorption or precipitation-  dissolution processes or both determine the solution concentrations of the  different elements.  Precipitation--dissolution processes depend on the solubility of definite  compounds in relation to chemical reactions taking place in soils. By ap-  plying the law of mass-action, solubility isotherms can be calculated for the  assumed reactions, e.g. in relation to pH or other variables, if the needed  thermodynamic data are available. With this concept, causal interpretations  of the chemical reactions taking place in soils, and quantitative predictions  of solution concentrations are possible. Therefore, many authors in soil  science have favoured the solubility product principle to explain measured  concentrations of elements in the soil solution.  In 1979 Lindsay summarized the published data of this field. He described  the solution concentrations of major and minor elements by the solubilities  of definite compounds of these elements and by solubility isotherms. The  solution concentration of zinc in soils is explained by the solubility of an  unknown zinc compound called "soil--Zn" in relation to pH. Kittrick (1976)  related the Zn concentration in solution in aerobic soils to the solubility of  ZnS. Under specific conditions the formation of Zn--carbonate (Udo et al.,  1970), Zn--phosphate (Kalbasi et al., 1978a) and Zn--silicate (Tiller and  Pickering, 1974; Leggett, 1978) may be important. There are, however, ex-  perimental, analytical and theoretical problems connected with the determi-  nation and calculation of solubility isotherms. For example, it may be diffi-  cult to attain real equilibrium conditions. Also, the determination of differ-  ent ionic species may create problems, especially for trace elements at very  low concentrations in solution. Further, solid phases may have an indefinite  or variable composition for which thermodynamic data do not exist and,  especially for trace elements, cannot be determined because of very low  contents of solids. Therefore, it is still an open question as to which elements  and under which soil conditions, solubility isotherms allow realistic expla-  nations of the solution concentrations. In fact, many papers about trace ele-  ments in soils show that solution concentrations of these elements cannot be  explained by solubility isotherms (Fassbender and Seekamp, 1976; Vlek and  Lindsay, 1977; Herms and Briimmer, 1980} but are connected with adsorp-  tion--desorption processes and can be described by adsorption or desorption  isotherms (Reisenauer et al., 1962; Tiller and Hodgson, 1962; Tiller et al.,  1969; Mayer, 1978; Gerth and Briimmer, 1979).    339    In contrast to solubility isotherms, adsorption and desorption isotherms  give little or no information about the kinds of reactions taking place and  the soil components involved. Numerous investigations of adsorption--de-  sorption processes of zinc have been carried out (Grimme, 1968; Udo et al.,  1970; Tiller et al., 1972; Shuman, 1975; Forbes et al., 1976; Kalbasi et al.,  1978b; McBride and Blasiak, 1979; Gerth and Brfmmer, 1979). From the  literature it is obvious that the relationship between soluble and adsorbed  zinc is strongly pH-dependent. Some authors assume a constant molar ratio  of one or two protons with the adsorbed Zn2 Others published adsorption  curves with 2 or 3 ranges of slopes in relation to pH. At alkaline pH and high  equilibrium Zn concentrations, precipitation--dissolution processes predomi-  nate over adsorption--desorption processes and various Zn compounds may  be formed (see references above).  Because of the conceptual difference between precipitation--dissolution  and adsorption--desorption processes it may be worthwhile to evaluate both  concepts and look for criteria to support one view or the other. The element  zinc is taken in this study as an example of the trace elements for which  these concepts are most difficult to apply.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Experiments with soil samples    In order to measure the concentration of zinc in aqueous equilibrium  solutions of soils in relation to pH, samples were taken from A-horizons of  eight cultivated soils and two subsurface samples representing a range of soil  types from northern Germany. The samples were air-dried and ground to  pass a 2 mm stainless steel screen. Identifications of horizons sampled and of  soils represented by the horizons plus the composition of the samples are  given in Table I.  The total zinc (Znt) concentration in seven samples ranged between 23  and 50 ppm, whereas three samples had much higher concentrations because  of industrial contamination. Sub-samples of the seven samples with lower  zinc contents were treated with an additional 100 ppm Zn, added as ZnCl2.  The added Zn was equilibrated with these sub-samples by alternating drying  and wetting during eight weeks.  After this pretreatment, 50 g of duplicate samples of each soil were mixed  with 2.5 g ground hay, 0.5 g glucose, 150 ml of distilled water and a few  drops of a soil suspension with active microorganisms. By addition of HC1 or  NaOH the pH was adjusted to values of 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 over a period of  about two weeks and was then kept constant for two more weeks. To avoid  reduction the samples were aerated and stirred by an automatic control sys-  tem three times an hour. At the end of the equilibration time the suspen-  sions were filtered through a Schleicher and SchfiU filter No. 589-2. The zinc  concentrations of the solutions were determined by anodic stripping voltam-  metry and atomic absorption spectrophotometry.    f~    TABLE I  Composition of soil samples    Soil    Suborder*'     Soil type*'  No.                   and horizon    1    Aquept  2  3    Ochrept  4    Udalf  5  6    Orthod  7    Aquod  8    Aquent  9    Aquept  10    Aquept    Kalk-  marsch  Braunerde  Parabraunerde  Braunerde-Pods.  Gley-Podsol  Salzmamh  Kleimarsh  Auenboden    Ap  Go  Ap  Ap  SB~t  Ap  Ap  Ah  Ap  Ap    Depth  (cm)    0--25  39--60  0--20  0--27  65--85  0--24  0--32  0--i0  0--20  0--20    Particles   Corg    CaC03    pH        Fed     Znt  &lt;2~m    (%)    (%)     (CaCl~)  (%)    (mg/kg)  (%)    20.2  18.9  10.3  18.1  23.7  6.9  2.1  47.5  28.9  14.2    1.3      0.8       7.2       0.31       46.5  0.6      3.5       7.7       0.37       61.5  1.8      --        5.5       0.51       40.2  1.4       --        6.6       0.64       50.4  0.2             --                 6.8                0.68               48.9  4.0             --                 5.3               0.62               31.1  2.2      --        5.0       0.13       22.9  3.8            7.3               7.8                1.09            282  2.4     0.2       6.9        --       768  2.0            1.4                7.1                  --            3740    ,, Soil Survey Staff (1975).  ,2 Miickenhausen (1982).    341    Experiments with soil clay fractions    The adsorption of Zn by soil clay fractions was also measured in relation  to pH. For this purpose the clay fractions of a range of soil samples of dif-  ferent composition were separated after saturation with sodium without  further chemical pre-treatment, according to the method described by Tiller  et al. (1979). As an example of the results obtained, Zn adsorption data of  the clay fraction of an A-horizon (Udalf) are given in this paper. The clay  fraction contained 10% organic matter and 90% mineral matter, including  2.6% dithionite--citrate--soluble Fe and 750 ppm Mn. The clay minerals  mainly consisted of illite and Al-chlorite. The CEC was 69 mequiv./100 g.  Zinc in solution and adsorbed on clay particles was determined by following  the methods of Tiller et al. (1979). Equilibrium was attained by shaking sus-  pensions of 20 mg clay in 10 ml 0.01 M Ca (NO3)2 solutions of different Zn  concentrations {10-6--10-4mole/l) tagged with carrier-free 6SZn, for one  week at 20+- I. The pH had been adjusted previously to values between 3.5  and 7 and was measured again in the clear solutions after centrifuging the  equilibrated suspensions. Aliquots of the solutions were taken for gamma-  spectrometric measurement of Zn.    Experiments with model systems    In order to estimate the significance of adsorption and precipitation reac-  tions of zinc under weakly alkaline conditions, experiments were carried out  in simple CaCO3-buffered model systems. The model substances used were  reagent-grade CaCO3 and two-component mixtures of CaCO3 with either of  the following, 10 and 25% bentonite (Upton, Wyoming), 10% humic acid  (Merck), 10% amorphous aluminium oxide, 10% amorphous iron oxide (sur-  face area 333 m2/g) or 1% birnessite (6-MnO2, surface area 39 m2/g). The  amorphous state of the oxides was confirmed by X-ray diffraction. The bir-  nessite was synthesized according to the method of McKenzie {1971). Four-  gram quantities of these mixtures were mixed with 20 ml portions of solu-  tions with different Zn concentrations (2.10 -~ to 10-2 mole/l) which had  been tagged with carrier-free 6SZn. The suspensions were stirred by passing  air through the reaction vessels and equilibrated for 7 days at 20+- 1. After  centrifugation, aliquots of the clear supernatant were taken for radioisotopic  measurement of Zn and determination of Ca by flame emission photometry.  The average Ca concentration of the solutions was 0.02 mole/1. The content  of Zn adsorbed was calculated by the difference between initial and final Zn  concentrations of the solution.    342    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Criteria for solubility and adsorption reactions of zinc    Zinc adsorption data for the clay fraction of a Udalf A-horizon are shown  in Fig. 1. The zinc concentrations in equilibrium solutions are plotted in re-  lation to pH for three different contents of total Zn added to the clay frac-  tions. If activities were plotted instead the experimental curves would be dis-  placed a little towards the abscissa. Complexing from any soluble organic  ligands released is presumed negligible at &lt; pH 7. Solubility isotherms are also  represented in Fig. 1 for Zn(OH)2, ZnCO3, Zna(PO~)2"4H20, Zn2SiO4,  soil--Zn (Lindsay, 1979), and ZnFe204. The isotherms are calculated accord-  ing to data published by Lindsay (1979). For the reaction, soil--Zn + 2H=  Zn~q + H20, he proposes a log Kof 5.80. The slopes of the solubility iso-  therms for soil--Zn as well as for Zn(OH)2, ZnCO3, Zn:SiO4, and ZnFe:O4  are -2.  In contrast to the straight lines of the solubility isotherms, the relation  between the zinc concentration from the adsorption experiment and the pH  is described by curves with various slopes at different pH ranges (Fig. 1).  Similar results were found by McBride and Blasiak (1979) for reactions of  Zn  log mcle/ I  -3"           ~ ~   ~v4   o~',0    ~      .~  ,   \    ~ ,%\    \  z~,    ",  \     ~ ":'o  \     \  pp~    ~   \     ,, ',, \     \  -/.   32s0 ~~.. ', ',  \    \  \\  -5    32s~\    ~  "..\    \  _6 33._._....,, \ y,\..  3  4   5  6  7  8 pH  Fig. 1. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solution of the clay fraction of a Udalf A-  horizon in relation to pH and total zinc added ; solubility isotherms of different zinc com-  pounds according to Lindsay (1979). (ZnCO,: log CO~(g) =-2.5; Zn,(PO~)=. 4H20: log  H~PO4- and log HPO ~ = -5; Zn=SiO~ in equilibrium with SiO2 (am) ; soil--Zn according to  Lindsay (1979); ZnFe=O4 in equilibrium with ferrihydrite or "soil-Fe"; Lindsay, 1979.)    343    Zn with an acid soil. At strongly acid reaction the slope is considerably less  than 1 but increases to 2 as suspension pH approaches 7. For a given pH, the  slope also varies with the content of total zinc added to the clay fraction.  Furthermore, the slopes of the curves are strongly influenced by the com-  position of the soil samples. For example, the slopes are lower at acidic to  neutral soil reactions when adsorption processes are dominated by organic  rather than mineral surfaces (Gerth and Briimmer, 1979).  The features of these curves of concentration versus pH, namely of slopes  that vary with pH, amount of zinc added and the kind of soil, are charac-  teristic of adsorption reactions. These contrast with precipitation--dissolu-  tion reactions of Zn compounds for which a single relationship at given pH  should theoretically result, a relationship independent of the amount of re-  actant or of the different mineral surfaces present. The presence of several  minerals, though not affecting theoretical solubility curves of accompany-  ing Zn compounds, may complicate the description of adsorption because  of the possibility of overlapping reactions associated with different soil  components. At higher pH values in Fig. 1 {above 6.5), the curves are near-  ly parallel to solubility isotherms but the corresponding isotherms depend  on the amount of Zn added. Thus, the curve described by the lowest level  of Zn approaches the 'soil--Zn' isotherm, whereas the others approximate  more closely the zinc silicate and zinc'phosphate isotherms, respectively.  Therefore a few data for metal concentrations or activities and over a narrow  range of pH are neither reliable evidence of the existence of a metal com-  pound which determines the solubility of the respective metal nor a safe  criterion for adsorption or desorption reactions, because the data may fit a  solubility isotherm as well as an adsorption isotherm, presented as described  in Fig. 1.    Relation between zinc concentration and pH in equilibrium solutions of soil  samples    To determine whether the zinc concentration in soil solutions is deter-  mined by adsorption--desorption or precipitating--dissolution reactions, the  equilibrium solutions of different soil samples with various contents of total  zinc were adjusted to pH values from 3 to 8 and zinc concentrations mea-  sured. In Fig. 2 the zinc concentrations of equilibrium solutions of whole  soil samples from the A-horizon of a Udalf (No. 4 in Table I) and solubility  isotherms of zinc compounds are plotted as functions of pH. The lower  curve shows the results for samples with their natural zinc contents of 50  ppm, whereas the upper curve describes the relation between zinc concen-  trations and pH for samples equilibrated for 8 weeks with an additional 100  ppm zinc. Both curves are, with respect to general shape, variations in slope  and dependence of total zinc content in the range of pH 3 to 7, more simi-  lar to the adsorption data in Fig. 1 than the solubility isotherms. Even when  some allowance is made for the possibility of variation of degree of com-    344    Zn  log r~ole/I  Z'I'  -4-            ~ ~~  50  -~-  ,   \  5  ~      6  7  8 pH'  Fig. 2. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solution of soil samples [rom the A horizon  of a Udalf with and without addition of 100 ,g Zn/g and solubility isotherms of different  zinc compounds (see Fig. 1).  plexing with pH, e.g. with hydroxyl ions and soluble organic ligands, there is  clearly no evidence of control of solubility by any known compounds of Zn.  The difficulty of measuring low concentrations of Zn~+ in solution and in  assessing the influence of complexing organic ligands at higher pH values  does, however, provide limits to the interpretation of soil solution data.  From the data of Fig. 3 it is also evident that the zinc concentrations of  equilibrium solutions of 9 surface soil samples are related to the contents  of total zinc in the range of pH 3 to at least 6 (see later). Although total zinc  includes lattice Zn of silicates, occluded Zn of metal oxides and other non-  reactive zinc pools, the connection between the solution concentration and  the total content of zinc is clear. This suggests that the solution concentra-  tion of zinc over the acid to near-neutral pH ranges is mainly determined by  adsorption--desorption reactions and not by the solubility of definite zinc  compounds. This conclusion is consistent with the results of McBride and  Blasiak (1979).  Precipitation--dissolution reactions of Zn are more likely at pH values  above 7 (Udo et al., 1970; Kalbasi et al., 1978a; Shukla and Mittal, 1980).  Accordingly, the scattered data at pH 7 in Fig. 3 may also be due to precipi-  tation--dissolution reactions. In Fig. 2 at pH 8 there is no significant differ-  ence between the zinc concentrations at both levels of total zinc, thus ap-  parently fulfilling one basic condition for precipitation--dissolution reac-    345    Znt  log mote/kg    pH7     6       5  L  3     -2            ~                                    x    0  -3.    /  -g       -g       -5 zn  oi It  Fig. 3. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solutions of soil samples from 9 A horizons  of different soil types in relation to the content of total zinc and suspension pH. (Sample  nos. 7, 8, 9, and 10 without added Zn and Nos. 1, 3, 4, 6 and 7 with added Zn; different  symbols indicate different pH curves.)    tions. The increase of the zinc concentration between pH 7 and 8, however,  is largely connected with increasing contents of soluble organic substances  with strong complexing ability (McBride and Blasiak, 1979; Herms and  Briimmer, 1980) as discussed earlier. The actual concentration of Zn2for  each curve at pH 8 may be different. In order to investigate the conditions  for adsorption--desorption and precipitation--dissolution reactions of zinc at  slightly alkaline conditions, experiments were carried out with several model  soil components in CaCO3-buffered systems.    Behaviour of zinc in CaC03- buffered model systems    Calcite (reagent grade CaCO3), bentonite (Upton, Wyoming), humic acid  (Merck), amorphous iron and aluminium oxide, and birnessite (5-MnO2) were  taken as model soil components. The model systems of pure CaCO3 and mix-  tures of CaCO3 with the other components were in equilibrium with atmo-  spheric carbon dioxide (pCO2(g) = 3.49; t = 20-+1). The average pH of  these CaCO3-buffered suspensions was 7.6 and the Ca concentration of the  equilibrium solutions about 0.02 mole/1. Fig. 4 shows the relation between  the zinc concentration of the equilibrium solution of pure CaCO3 and the  content of CaCO3-bound zinc (lower curve}. This relation can be described  by an adsorption isotherm up to a concentration of about 102 pmole/1. With  further additions of Zn, the concentration in solution is nearly constant and  independent of the content of CaCO3-bound zinc and presumably a form of  zinc carbonate is precipitated. The near-vertical solubility line shown in  Fig. 4 is close to that predicted for smithsonite (ZnCO3) under these condi-    346    Zn  pmole/g  101             pCO: ~: = 3.z.9                  ~/~"~ t  oo  10-3-          ,         ,         ,         ~         ,  10-~     10-2     104     100     101   ~u'nole Zn/I  Fig. 4. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solutions of pure calcite and a mixture of  calcite with 5 -MnO2 (1%) in relation to the amount of adsorbed or precipitated zinc. The  vertical line gives the calculated solubility of ZnCO5 for the conditions of the experiment.    tions of pH, pCO2(g) and temperature. The reason for the small decrease in  the solubility of the zinc carbonate with increasing content of precipitated  zinc is not clear but may be connected with some initial super-saturation  or the kind of precipitation, either on calcite surfaces or as separate zinc  carbonate particles of different size. Under the given experimental condi-  tions in a system of pure CaCO3, the precipitation of zinc carbonate begins  at about 0.5/~mole Zn/g CaCO3 (~ 30 ppm Zn). If CaCO3 is mixed with 1%  MnO2, then nearly one hundred times the concentration of Zn in the solid  phase is necessary for the formation of zinc carbonate (Fig. 4, upper curve).  Up to about 10 /Jmole Zn/g, the relation between soluble and MnO2+  CaCO3bound zinc is described by adsorption. With 10% amorphous iron  oxide or humic acid in the CaCO3-system the solubility of ZnCO3 is not  reached and the whole range up to 50 ~mole Zn/g mixture is due to ad-  sorption (Fig. 5). Amorphous aluminium oxide gave results similar to those  of amorphous iron oxide. Additions of bentonite (10 and 25%) also con-  siderably increased the adsorption range. These results indicate that in the  presence of soil components with strongly adsorbing surfaces, relatively  large concentrations of zinc are required, the amounts depending on the  composition of the soft, to reach the zinc concentration necessary for the  formation of ZnCO3. As the zinc content of most CaCO3- containing soils  is below 1--2/Jmole Zn/g (65--130 ppm Zn) these experiments would also  predict that ZnCO3 is not common under natural conditions.  In a similar way  the possibility of zinc phosphate and silicate forma-    347    Zn  IJrnole/g    101    100    10-1    10-2    Zn2SLO~.  SL02 (orn }    pC02,,~ : 3.49  pH = ?.6  90% CoC%"     F  10%Fe(OH)3 /e" ,~"  //    /  / "f   ii ii/  /    /  .41   ~'.  /     /    Z%IP0~. )2  log HPO2L~  -5          pC(  /t~    / "90%COCO  L V    ~"     10 ~/o hurmc acid  .  .  J    //  4V"   ,O  //  /"  ZnCQ    4H~0        ZnC0  = 3.49    10"3.          ,         ,                   ,  10.3     10-2     10-1      100      101   ~Jmote Zn/I  Fig. 5. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solutions of pure calcite and mixtures of  calcite (90%) with either humic acid (10%) or amorphous iron oxide in relation to the  amount of adsorbed or precipitated zinc. The vertical lines give calculated solubilities of  ZnCO3, Zn3PO,)2 4H2OandZn:SiO~ forpH7.6.    tion can be assessed with respect to the modifying influence of adsorption  and the solubility lines of both compounds are also given in Fig. 5. Although  zinc phosphate and zinc silicate have a lower solubility than zinc carbonate,  very high contents of total bound zinc are still necessary to permit a suffi-  ciently high concentration of Zn in solution for the formation of these com-  pounds. For example, in the presence of 10% amorphous iron oxide and 90%  CaCO3 at least 21 umole Zn/g mixture (~ 1400 ppm Zn) are necessary be-  fore the concentration of Zn is sufficient to exceed the solubility of  Zn3(PO4)2" 4H20 (Fig. 5) when HPO~- = 10 -s.  From the solubility point of  view the formation of zinc silicate is certainly more likely (Tiller and  Pickering, 1974; Leggett, 1978}. In the experiment with mixtures of iron  oxide and CaCO3, at least 1 ~umole of adsorbed Zn/g solid (65 ppm) is re-  quired to get a Zn concentration in solution appropriate to the formation of  Zn silicate. In two soil samples from subsurface horizons with low contents  of organic carbon (Nos. 2 and 5, Table I), and 100 ppm of added Zn, the Zn  concentration/pH curves are nearly identical with the Zn:SiO4 solubility iso-  therm in the range of pH 7 to 8 (Fig. 6). Thus Zn2SiO4 or other silicates, e.g.  ZnSiO3 could influence the Zn solubility in alkaline soils with sufficiently  high levels of bound Zn (:&gt; ~ 100 ppm Zn), but absolute evidence for the  existence of these compounds will remain difficult to achieve because of un-  certainties about the appropriate solubility constants and the problems in  measuring ionic species in soil solution. Hence it remains to be proved that    348    the adsorption capacity and affinity of soil components for Zn, even at aJ-  kaline pH values and elevated levels of bound Zn, can always prevent preci-  pitation reactions.    Adsorption characteristics of zinc for different soil components at slightly  alkaline pH.    The adsorption capacity and binding strength of different soil compo-  nents for zinc in CaCO3-buffered systems (pH 7.6) can be compared by cal-  culating adsorption characteristics from the data of the adsorption experi-  ments (Figs. 4, 5). The constants of the calculated Langmuir and Freundlich  adsorption isotherms are given in Table II. As the Langmuir adsorption max-  imum, b, depends upon the concentration range used, all calculations were  restricted to the constant upper zinc concentration of 102 pmole/1. The re-  spective values of adsorbed zinc are taken or extrapolated from the curves of    TABLE II    Constants of Langmuir and Freundlich equations for zinc adsorption by mixtures of dif-  ferent substances with CaCOj for concentrations up to 10= ,mole/I    Substances    N  Constants from      Constants from  Langmuir equation*  Freundlich equation**    k,        b             r         ks        1         r  umole/g    CaCO3 (100%)          13 0.94     0.44     0.998  0.11   0.43   0.976  Bentonite (10%)  CaCO= (90%)              9 0.68      4.7       0.998   0.62    0.58    0.975  Bentonite (25%)  CaCO= (75%)            10 0.39     11.4      0.995   1.49   0.64    0.981  Humic acid (10%)  CaCO= (90%)            12 0.05     84.6      0.904  2.50   0.81    0.996  Amorph. Fe-oxide (10%)  CaCO= (90%)            12 0.09    119.0      0.954  5.66   0.78   0.994  Amorph. Al-oxide (10%)  CaCO= (90%)           12 0.07   131.2      0.952  4.69   0.79   0.997  6-MnO,  (1%)  CaCO= (99%)           12 1.21     15.9      0.999  2.68   0.62   0.969  *x  =  k~. b*c                  ,In                     ;  **xm =/" C  m     l+kz.c      m    x/m = adsorbed amount in .mole/g;c - concentration in #mole/l; k~ = constant, which is a  relative measure of the binding strength of the adsorption sites; b = adsorption maximum in  .mole/g; k,,n = constants.    349    best fit (see Figs. 4, 5). The concentration of 102 tlmole/1 is chosen because  zinc carbonate precipitates at about this concentration. The amount of zinc  adsorbed at this concentration therefore indicates the adsorption maximum  of soil components in a CaCO3-buffered system.  The values of the correlation coefficient, r, in Table II show that the Lang-  muir isotherm gives a little better fit for the adsorption data of pure CaCO3  and mixtures of bentonite and MnO2 with CaCO3, whereas the Freundlich iso-  therm is somewhat better for mixtures of humic acid and amorphous iron  and aluminium oxide with CaCO3. There is some evidence that the log--log  curves, especially of the humic acid---CaCO3 mixture (Fig. 5, middle curve)  can be treated as 2-line segments thus implying two different reactions of  higher and lower affinities between zinc and humic acid. Several authors  have also found for soil samples that two different adsorption ranges of zinc  and other heavy metals exist (Shuman, 1975; Kuo and Mikkelsen, 1979;  Gerth and Brfimmer, 1979), which may be related to the influence of ad-  sorbates of different affinities, e.g. organic matter and iron and aluminium  oxides in soils.  The zinc adsorption maximum, b, for pure CaCO~ is very low (Table II).  Thus CaCO3 itself contributes little to the adsorption of zinc in the mix-  tures with other soil components. The constant k, of the Langmuir iso-  therm, which is related to the binding strength of zinc adsorption, shows the  highest values for the CaCO3 mixture with MnO2 and for pure CaCO3, medi-  um values for the mixtures of CaCO3 with bentonite and low values for the  mixtures with iron and aluminium oxide and with humic acid.  The actual Langmuir maxima of the individual substances used in mix-  tures with CaCOs have been calculated from the values of the appropriate  Langmuir adsorption maxima by subtraction of CaCO3-bound zinc (0.44  pmole Zn per gram CaCO3, Table II) from to~al zinc adsorbed by the mix-  tures. The derived values are given in Table III. The amounts of zinc adsorb-  ed by the substances at zinc concentrations of 10-1 to 102 ttmole/l are also  calculated by subtraction of CaCO3-bound zinc from total bound zinc of the  mixtures at the respective concentrations (Table III). For the latter purpose,  the amounts adsorbed at the different concentrations were taken from the  adsorption curves of best fit (Figs. 4 and 5). The adsorption capacities of the  different substances, calculated from the Langmuir adsorption maximum  and from the adsorbed amount at 102 pmole Zn/1, agree quite well (Table  III). The adsorption capacities of bentonite, derived from experiments with  10 and 25% bentonite, agree very well and thus indicate the reliability of the  experimental procedure. The adsorption capacities on an equal mass basis of  the different substances increase in the order CaCO3&lt;&lt;bentonite&lt;&lt;humic  acid&lt; Fe-oxide --- Al-oxide&lt;5-MnO2. This order is mainly determined by the  chemical and mineralogical composition of the components. Differences in  surface area are of minor importance as can be seen by comparing the values  of the amorphous iron oxide (333 m2/g) and the 5 -MnO2 (39 m2/g).  Birnessite has the highest zinc adsorption capacity of all substances tested    350  TABLE III  Amount of zinc (~mole/g) adsorbed by different substances at zinc concentrations of 10:  to 10TM umole/l in CaCO:~-buffered systems    Substance         umole zinc per gram at:  Langm.      10~       10'        10      10-'  max.        (umole zinc per !)    CaCO3                 0.44         0.45      0.32     0.16      0.06  Bentonite*'          43.2         42.2      22.3     10.6       3.6  Bentonite.2          44.4         43.3      21.5      9.3       2.7  Humic acid         842         790      147      27.9       5.0  Amorphous  Fe-oxide          1190        1120      296      75.7      15.6  Amorphous  Al-oxide          1310        1180      304      58.1       8.3  6-MnO,            1540        1540     1170     581       176    *' Calculated from the data of the experiment with 10% bentonite, and ,2 25% bentonite.    and also the highest kl-value (Table II) which is a relative measure of the  binding strength of the zinc adsorption. The zinc adsorption capacities of  amorphous iron and aluminium oxides and humic acid are relatively high,  especially in relation to the bentonite. The corresponding order for amounts  of Zn adsorbed also does not change with decreasing concentration of zinc  from 102 to 10 -~ /amole/1, although the relative affinity of zinc for MnO2 is  greatly enhanced at lower concentrations of Zn in solution (Table III). A  comparison of the zinc adsorption capacities of the different substances at  pH 7.6 with the cation exchange capacities (CEC) of these substances at the  same pH is given in Table IV. The zinc adsorption capacities of bentonite  and humic acid comprise only 0.1 and 0.5 times, respectively, the CEC's  of these substances, but 6.7 to 26.7 times that of the oxides. The high  values for the oxides indicate the extent of zinc bonding at specific sites  associated with the hydroxyl surfaces of the oxides which are not available  for normal cation exchange. Under the given experimental conditions the  zinc species in solution are mainly Zn (OH)*, Zn(OH)2 ZnHCO3*, ZnCO~ and complexes with organic ligands in the experiments with humic acid,  which hardly can compete with Ca2ions for the nonspecific negative sites  of the exchanger. This especially applies to clay mineral surfaces, where  specific adsorption of zinc and other heavy metals is mainly restricted to  broken bonds located at the edges of the crystals (Peigneur et al., 1975).  These data permit a quantitative evaluation of the importance of the  manganese, iron, and aluminium oxides for the adsorption of zinc at slight-  ly alkaline pH values. The selective accumulation of zinc and other heavy    TABLE IV  CEC and zinc adsorption capacity of different substances in CaCO3 -buffered systems    351    Substances     CEC at pH 7.6                   Zn-ads    meq uiv./100g*'    M2          max..2 in     b  umole/g     umole/g     a  (a)        (b)    CaCO3            --                      --               0.44       --  Bentonite        90                  450           44         0.10  Humic acid     340                 1700         842         0.50  Amorphous  Fe-oxide         32                  160        1190         7.4  Amorphous  Al-oxide          10                    50         1310         26.2  6 -MnO2          46                  230        1540         6,7    *' CEC measurements: Ba2*-saturation at pH 7.6 and exchange of Ba2* by Mg2  ,2 Calculated from Langmuir equations; see Tables II and III.    metals by manganese oxides under natural conditions was discussed by  Jenne {1968) and was clearly demonstrated by electron microprobe studies  of McKenzie (1975) and Norrish (1975). Other workers also showed the  accumulation of trace metals by iron and aluminium oxides (Shuman,  1975; Kalbasi et al., 1978b; Kalbasi and Racz, 1978; McBride and Blasiak,  1979).    GENERAL DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    In our experiments we have studied reactions of zinc under a range of  conditions using different materials including clay fractions from soils,  whole soil samples from A and B horizons, and CaCO3-buffered model sys-  tems. At pH values up to about 7, zinc solubility of whole-soft samples and  soil clay fractions as indicated by zinc concentrations in the equilibrium  solution was strongly dependent on the pH and the total zinc contents. In  this pH range, adsorption--desorption processes determine the Zn concentra-  tion in solution. Here the term adsorption has to include any condensation  reactions, involving small amounts of trace metal phases interacting strongly  with the soil surfaces, which can also be described by adsorption isotherms.  At pH values up to about 7, no evidence of precipitation--dissolution reac-  tions which can be described by constant solubility products could be found,  even for high contents of zinc.  It is well accepted that precipitation of zinc is most likely in alkaline soils,  and our data (Fig. 6) for B-horizon samples were consistent with the possi-    352  Zn  log mole/I                 g,~  \p  \~  ~   ~,   ~  ",,   \  - 5-              ",  \1  - ",  '",,\  ,  t\      ,,,',,,\,  J   g  6  5  fi pH  Fig. 6. Zinc concentrations in the equilibrium solutions of samples from subsurface hori-  zons of a Udalf (e) and an Aquept (A) in relation to pH; solubility isotherms of different  zinc compounds (see Fig. 1).    bility of precipitation in the pH range 7--8. The associated samples from A-  horizons, with higher organic matter contents but similar contents of bound  zinc, showed no tendency to conform with the solubility of any zinc com-  pound (Fig. 2, upper curve). The reason is two-fold, the increased concen-  tration of complexed zinc due to increasing content of soluble organic li-  gands (Herms, 1982) and thus decreased concentration of Zn2combined  with enhanced adsorption by solid organic surfaces.  Our experiments using model systems (Figs. 4 and 5) have demonstrated  the key role played by adsorption as a determinant of the potential for pre-  cipitation. Surfaces with sufficient adsorption capacity may lower the equi-  librium concentrations of zinc species sufficiently so that the required con-  centration for precipitation is not reached. Although the initial concentra-  tion may suffice for precipitation, the kinetics of adsorption processes, com-  bined with any tendency for supersaturation by potential compounds, may  determine that compounds never form. Accordingly, the presence of adsor-  bates characterized by high affinities for the ions concerned and with suffi-  cient adsorption capacity will become the dominant factor. The measured  values of zinc adsorption capacities of CaCO3, bin-, Fe-, and Al-oxides,  humic acid, and bentonite, as models of soil components in CaCO3~uffered  systems, confirm the importance of metal oxides for the adsorption of trace  metals and thus their importance as a deterrent for trace metal precipitation.    353    Our experiments indicate that very high concentrations of zinc can be ac-  comodated by adsorption before precipitation occurs. This was assessed by  the presence or absence of upward inflections in the 'adsorption' curves. The  alternative method of assessing the presence of trace-metal compounds, that  is, of evaluating solubility measurements in relation to published stability  constants of various idealized zinc compounds has limitations discussed ear-  lier. In fact, under those soil conditions of high pH, high zinc content, etc.,  for which use of solubility criteria seems more appropriate, identification  and interpretation problems associated with phases of uncertain composition  and crystallinity considerably restrict the reliability of this approach.  Generally it can be stated that the lower the content of a trace element in  the soil and the more sites available for high affinity adsorption, the more  likely it is that adsorption--desorption processes will determine the concen-  tration of the element in soil solution. Attempts to apply the solubility prod-  uct principle in these situations may generate misleading concepts that seri-  ously hinder the prediction of trace element behaviour. Stringent tests are  required, involving broader ranges of trace metal concentrations in solid and  solution phases, of pH, and of other interacting ions, in order to permit more  confident interpretations of solubility isotherms of trace elements in soil sys-  tems.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors are indebted to Drs. A.W. Fordham and R.M. Taylor for help-  ful advice during the experimental work in Adelaide and to Miss S. Kneesch  for able laboratory assistance in Kiel. The Division of Soils CSIRO (Austra-  lia) and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft financially supported this re-  search project.    REFERENCES    Fassbender, H.W. and Seekamp, G., 1976. Fraktionen und L~slichkeit der Schwermetalle  Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, Ni and Pb im Boden. Geoderma, 16: 55--69.  Forbes, E.A., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1976. The specific adsorption of divalent Cd,  Co, Cu, Pb, and Zn on goethite. J. Soil Sci., 27: 154--166.  Gerth, J. and Briimmer, G., 1979. Quantit~ts-Intensit~ts-Beziehungen yon Cadmium, Zink  und Nickel in BSden unterschiedlichen Stoffbestandes. Mitt. Dtsch. Bodenkd. Ges.,  29 : 555--566.  Grimme, H., 1968. Die Adsorption yon Mn, Co, Cu and Zn durch Goethit aus verdiinnten  L6sungen. Z. Pflanzenern~hr. Bodenkd., 121: 58---65.  Herms, U., 1982. Untersuchungen zur Schwermetallbslichkeit in kontaminierten Bbden  und kompostierten Siedlungsabf~illen in Abldhgigkeit yon Bodenreaktion, Redoxbe-  dingungen und Stoffbestand. Dissertation. Agrarwiss. Fak. Univ. Kiel, 269 pp.  Herms, U. and Br~mmer, G., 1980. Einfluss der Bodenreaktion auf L~slichkeit und  tolerierbare Gesamtgehalte an Nickel, Kupfer, Zink, Cadmium und Blei in Bbden und  kompostierten Siedlungsabf~llen. Ldw. Forsch., 33: 408--423.  Jenne, E.A., 1968. Controls on Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn concentrations in soils and  water: the significant role of hydrous Mn and Fe oxides. In: Trace Inorganics in Water.  Adv. Chem. Set., No. 73.    354    Kalbasi, M. and Racz, G.J., 1978. Association of zinc with oxides of iron and aluminium  in some Manitoba soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 58: 61--68.  Kalbasi, M., Racz, G.J. and Loewen-Rudgers, L.A., 1978a. Reaction products and solu  bility of applied zinc compounds in some Manitoba soils. Soil Sci., 125: 55--64.  Kalbasi, M., Racz, G.J. and Loewen-Rudgers, L.H., 1978b. Mechanism of zinc adsorption  by iron and aluminium oxides. Soil Sci., 125: 146--150.  Kittrick, J.A., 1976. Control of Zn2. in the soil solution by sphalerite. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  J., 40: 314--317.  Kuo, S. and Mikkelsen, D.S., 1979. Zinc adsorption by two alkaline soils. Soil Sci., ] 28:  274--279.  Leggett, G.E., 1978. Interaction of monomeric silicic acid with copper and zinc and  chemical changes of the precipitates with ageing. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 262--268.  Lindsay, W.L.. 1979. Chemical Equilibria in Soils. John Wiley and Sons, New York, N.Y..  449 pp.  Mayer, R., 1978. Adsorptionsisothermen als Regelgr6ssen beim Transport von Schwer-  metallen in B~den. Z. Pflanzenern~hr. Bodenkd., 141: 11--28.  McBride, M.B. and Blasiak, J.J., 1979. Zinc and copper solubility as a function ofpH in  an acid soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43'. 866--870.  McKenzie, R.M., 1971. The synthesis of birnessite, cryptomelane, and some other oxides  and hydroxides of manganese. Mineral. Mag., 38: 493--502.  McKenzie, R.M., 1975. An electron microprobe study of the relationships between heavy  metals and manganese and iron in soils and ocean floor nodules. Aust. J. Soil Res., 13:  177--188.  Miickenhausen, E., 1982. Entstehung, Eigenschaften und Systematik der 85den der  Bundesrepublik Deutschland. DLG-Verlag, Frankfurt am Main, 300 pp.  Norrish, K., 1975. Geochemistry and mineralogy of trace elements. In: Trace Elements in  Soil--Plant--Animal Systems. Academic Press, Inc., New York, N.Y., pp. 55--81.  Norvell, W.A. and Lindsay, W.L., 1969. Reactions of EDTA complexes of Fe, Zn, Mn and  Cu with soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 86--91.  Peigneur, P., Maes, A. and Cremers, A., 1975. Heterogeneity of charge density distribu-  tion in montmorillonite as inferred from cobalt adsorption. Clays Clay Miner., 23:  71--75.  l~eisenauer, H.M., Tabikh, A.A. and Stout, P.R., 1962. Molybdenum reactions with soils  and the hydrous oxides of iron, aluminium, and titanium. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 26:  23--27.  Shukla, V.E. and Mittal, S.B., 1980. Characterization of the zinc retained in some soils of  India using pH gradient elution. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44 : 29--33.  Shuman, L.M., 1975. The effect of soil properties on zinc adsorption by soils. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 454--457.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook 436,754 pp.  Tiller, K.G. and Hodgson, J.F., 1962. The specific sorption of cobalt and zinc by layer  silicates. Clays Clay Miner., 9: 393--403.  Tiller, K.G. and Picketing, J.G., 1974. The synthesis of zinc silicates at 20 and atmo-  spheric pressure. Clays Clay Miner., 22: 409--416.  Tiller, K.G., Honey~tt, J.L. and H, Ih~worth, E.G., 1969. The i~topically exchangeable  forms of native and applied cobalt in soils. Aust. J. Soil R~., 7 : 43--56.  Tiller, K.G., Honey~tt, J.L.  and De Vries, M.P.C., 1972. Soil zinc and its uptake by  plants, II. Soil chemistry in relation to prediction of availability. Aust. J. Soil Res.,  10: 165--182.  Tiller, K.G., Nayyar, V.K. and Clayton, P.M., 1979. Specific and non-specific sorption of  cadmium by soil clays as influenced by zinc and calcium. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17:  17--28.  Udo, E.J., Bohn, H.L. and Tucker, T.C., 1970. Zinc adsorption by calcareous soils. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 405--407.  Vlek, P.L.G. and Lindsay, W.L., 1977. Thermodynamic stability and solubility of molyb-  denum minerals in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41 : 42--46.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractThe concentrations of trace and toxic metals in soil solutions are explained by several authors either in terms of adsorption—desorption or precipitation—dissolution reactions in soils. Data have been given for zinc to test the applicability of both concepts. The results show that the concentrations of zinc in equilibrium solutions with soil clay fractions and whole soil samples at pH values below 7 are determined exclusively by adsorption—desorption reactions for various pH's, contents of bound zinc and compositions of soils. At neutral to alkaline pH values precipitation—dissolution reactions of zinc may take place. There is some evidence that formation of zinc silicates may control the zinc concentration in solution provided natural complexing agents are absent, the affinity of the soil for zinc is low and the content of reaching zinc is high (&gt; ∼ 100 ppm). Even at pH values above 7, the formation of other zinc compounds is unlikely in most soils because additions of large amounts of zinc are required to ensure saturation of the adsorption sites of different soil components before the zinc concentration in the soil solution can increase sufficiently to bring about the precipitation of definite compounds. Model experiments in CaCO3-buffered systems showed that the adsorption capacity for specifically adsorbed zinc (in μmole/g) by the following components increased in the order CaCO3 (0.44), bentonite (44), humic acid (842), amorphous Fe- and Al-oxides (1190, 1310) and δ -MnO2 (1540) and demonstrated the importance of Mn-, Fe-, and Al-oxides and humic substances for the binding of zinc in soils containing carbonates, and thus indicate the special role of these components in limiting precipitation reactions. 