 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 43--68                                                      43  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    EXPERIMENTAL STUDY OF SOIL MICROFABRICS INDUCED BY  ISOTROPIC STRESSES OF WETTING AND DRYING    J.B. DALRYMPLE and C.Y. JIM*~  Department of Soil Science, University of Reading, Reading (Great Britain)  (Received June 15, 1983; accepted after revision June 11, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Dalrymple, J.B. and Jim, C.Y., 1984. Experimental study of soil microfabrics induced  by isotropic stresses of wetting and drying. Geoderma, 34: 43--68.    This experimental study examines the relationship between texture and microfabric  under isotropic stresses generated by wetting and drying. This can be achieved by  observing and measuring the reorganization of microfabrics (plasmic fabrics and related  distribution pattern, RDP). Microfabrics are produced in the laboratory by mixing  montmorillonite with various proportions of sand and silt, and subjecting them to wetting  and drying without confinement. Thin sections axe cut to study their microfabrics.  Results show broad and systematic variations in fabric with changes in texture. Fine  matrix (silt plus clay in physical continuity) is developed in samples with low sand:silt  ratio, and regardless of this ratio at high clay levels. Coarse porphyric and fine porphyric  RDP are formed at low and high clay contents, respectively. Plasmic fabrics are repre-  sented mainly by insepic and weakly developed mosepic and masepic fabrics in the matrix  in the form of small plasma separations with random orientation, and weak skelsepic  plasma as embedded grain argillans. On the other hand, coarse matrix (sand grains in  physical continuity) dominates the sandy samples which are associated with relatively  thick and strongly birefringent free grain argillans giving wall-developed skelsepic fabric.  The RDP follows two major paths: beginning with orthogranic (very low clay content)  along the iunctic sequence at low clay:silt ratio and along the chlamydic sequence at high  ratio. The regularities in fabric development are interpreted in the light of the dynamic  properties and behaviour of the active clay fraction in a clay--water system. The  pedogenetic implications of the results are explored, and the term "erdic" fabric defined.    INTRODUCTION    Among the suite of fundamental soil processes subsumed under erdefica-  tion (Conacher and Dalrymple, 1977), wetting and drying is perhaps the  most important. It is its influence under an overall isotropic stress regime on  the micromorphological organization of soil materials with different texture  that constitutes the theme of the present study.    *~ Present address: Department of Geography and Geology, University of Hong Kong,  Pokfulam Road, Hong Kong.    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    44  =  Eswaran and Banos (1976) have provided a conceptual treatment to the  general thesis that relates fabric to texture and, although the subsequent  empirical investigations by Brewer (1979) and McKeague and Guertin (1982)  show that a broad relationship does exist, many aberrant cases were found to  occur. Thus, in order to avoid the uncertainty and conjecture involved in the  conventional empirical approach where both processes and historical recon-  struction of micromorphological reorganization are inferred from responses  (Brewer, 1972a, b), an experimental approach is adopted. This follows the  few, but notable examples in the work of Kubiena (1938), Day and  Holmgren (1952), Brewer and Haldane (1957), Bartelli and OdeU (1960),  Buol and Hole (1961), Wells (1965), Dijkerman et al. (1967), Dalrymple  (1972) and Wilke and Schwertmann (1978). Even so, many of the recent  advances on the colloidal properties and behaviour of clay minerals with a  clay--water system have yet to be translated into working hypotheses to  explain the organization of fabric units in soils. Thus, as there is little sound  knowledge as to what fabric features result from or are modified by what  pedogenetic processes, rigorous testing is necessary. In this case experimental  evidence is obtained on the relationship between the characteristics of soil  microfabrics -- related distribution pattern (RDP) and plasmic fabric (Brewer,  1964) -- and the behaviour of the constituents making up the elementary  fabric units. It is intended to test the hypothesis that the activity and  malleability, and hence the mobility, of the clay fraction operating in a low  moisture clay--water system is the prime agent in the moulding of fabric  units in the soil environment. If so, the reorganization of soil microfabrics  induced by isotropic stresses of wetting and drying could lead to the  establishment and definition of an "erdic" fabric.    EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES    Wyoming bentonite (BDH) was dispersed in deionized water and the  &lt;2gm e.s.d, fraction separated by gravity sedimentation. Calcium and  sodium clays were prepared by flocculating the clay in suspension with  appropriate chloride solutions, followed by three washings with molar  chloride solutions by centrifugation and decantation. The resulting homo-  ionic clays were washed repeatedly until free from chloride. In addition the  sodium clay was washed thrice with deionized water and thereafter with  industrial methylated spirit (IMS), in order to suppress spontaneous disper-  sion as the electrolyte concentration of the pore fluid was progressively  reduced. The replacement of interstitial pore fluid with alcohol -- being a  low-surface-tension liquid -- permitted the clay to be dried as a fine powder  rather than as hard lumps in the case of drying from water (El Rayah and  Rowell, 1973). Ca/Na mixed-ion clay was prepared by mixing dry Ca- and  Na-clay at a weight ratio of 7:3. Sand- (20--200 pm e.s.d.) and silt- (2--20 gm  e.s.d.) sized quartz particles were separated from silica flour by gravity  sedimentation. Each clay species at six levels (5%, 10%, 20%, 40%, 60%,    45    80%) were crossed with seven levels of skeletal grains (sand:silt ratios of sand  only (s), 4:1, 2:1, 1:1, 1:2, 1:4, silt only (z)}. The well-mixed samples were  placed into receptacles which were aluminium rings 1 cm internal diameter  and 1 cm tall, with one end closed by a piece of nylon cloth fixed in position  by rubber bands. The samples were equilibrated to pF zero over saturated  plastic foam with deionized water for two weeks. Additional samples at a  sand:silt ratio of 1:1 were equilibrated with appropriate chloride solutions  at 10-4, 10-3, 10-2 and 10-1 molar concentrations to check the effects of  electrolytes. The samples were then air-dried, impregnated with Spurt resin  and thin-sectioned according to the method of Jim (1981).  Related distribution patterns and plasmic fabrics were described according  to Brewer (1964, 1974, 1979). Unless stated otherwise, f-members refer to  sand-sized grains and f-matrices refer to silt- and clay-sized grains. Coarse  porphyric fabric refers to the case with f-members surrounded by an f-matrix  made up of mainly silt-sized materials; and fine porphyric of mainly clay-  sized materials. Coarse and fine matrices are used in the sense of Bodman  and Constantin (1965), that is with the f-member and the f-matrix in  physical continuity, respectively. Phyric RDP is used after Eswaran et al.  (1972).  Every sample was duplicated, and point-counting provided replicated  quantitative data on the relative proportions of micromorphological compo-  nents (Chayes, 1956; Anderson and Binnie, 1961; Eswaran, 1968).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Ca-mon tmorillonite    The results of the experimentally produced related distribution patterns  and plasmic fabrics using Ca-montmorillonite are given in Fig. 1.  (a) 5% clay. With 5% clay and where the skeletal grains are dominated by  one particle-size class (either of sand at s, 4:1, 1:4 or of silt z) a phyric RDP  is formed. Coarse porphyric RDP is not formed in the z and 1:4 samples,  despite their compound packing and absence of large pores (&gt;30 um).  This is because of the overall uniform range of grain size and virtual absence  of plasma resulting in an RDP consisting essentially of a simple packing of  silt grains. In contrast, the presence of a roughly equal amount of sand and  silt (2:1, 1:1 and 1:2) results in coarse porphyric fabrics with sand as  f-members embedded by a dense and continuous f-matrix made up of silt  grains. At 2:1, there is insufficient fine material (silt and clay) to fill all the  simple packing voids of the sand, which is in a continuous matrix.  The near-absence of clay coatings, except at s, suggests that some of the  clay is being distributed evenly in the low s:z samples and probably in the  form of coatings that are too thin to be discernible at the scale of observa-  tion (100). The majority of the clay domains occur as minute interstitial  fillings that are discrete, usually equant in shape, and often isotropic or    46    undulic. The low content of clay and their segregation into small isolated  pockets between the predominant skeletal grains preclude the formation of  sepic plasmic fabric.  At low s:z ratios, the void volume (at about 20% for all samples) are    CLAY    ~?o  +  +   +   +  +    9\?\~    ~?oI\   /Z:  SAND    o IS~    + \o?\ I\r~S~ ?\? o I \" + cYOI\ + \~?S~ + c?~     + O~?s~  +0c~      + c~       + c?   +~9oIg~ +c?oI~         oIS~           '~ IS~  + OO~?G~+ oct?o15~  +c?    + "~    SILT    Fig. 1. Related distribution patterns (RDP) on plasmic fabrics of Ca-montmorillonitic  samples. (For legend, see Table I.)    TABLE I    Abbreviated names of related distribution patterns and plasmic fabrics  Related distribution                  Plasmic fabric    Orthogranic            Og            Skelsepic          Sk  Phyric                 Ph            Vosepic           Vo  Chlamydic             Ch            Insepic            In  Plectic                 P1            Mosepic           Mo  Coarse porphyric      cPo           Masepic           Ma  Fine porphyric         fPo           Lattisepic         La  Iunctic                Iu            Omnisepic         Om  Argillamatric      Am  Argillasepic       Aa  Silasepic          Si    47    Fig. 2. Sample with 10% Ca-clay and a sand:silt ratio of 1:4, showing phyric RDP and  silasepic plasmic fabric; the f-matrix is made up predominantly of silt grains which  preclude the formation of sepic plasmic fabric. Note some weak orientation of silt around  sand grains. (Cross-polarized light, x 85.)    mainly made up of small voids (&lt; 30 ~m diameter) due to the simple pack-  ing of silt. The development of large voids at 4:1 and s reflect transition  from fine to coarse matrix. Thus, with 5% clay, the lack of plasma  separations suggests that the mobility of the clay induced by isotropic stress  of wetting and drying has had little effect on the microfabric produced.  (b) 10% clay. At 10% clay, the presence of more plasma materials gives  the f-matrix, with textures of from 1:1 to z, a dense and somewhat  porphyric appearance. Granic features, however, still remain and a phyric  porphyric intergrade is formed (Fig. 2). At 2:1, the fabric changes to mainly  coarse porphyric, with the sand grains firmly embedded in an f-matrix itself  made up of an intimate mixture of silt and clay. Further increase in sand  content to 4:1 creates an iunctic porphyric intergrade RDP. Here the  f-matrix of silt and clay forms relatively wide intergranular bridges, leaving  most of the sand surfaces away from the bridges uncoated. Although the z:c  ratio approaches 1:1, the small amount of clay in the f-matrix in relation to  skeletal grains results in the uneven spreading of the clay onto the sand  grains. At s, a large proportion of the f-matrix is clay, and this is thinly  spread onto the majority of sand surfaces to form coatings with only a few  surfaces remaining uncoated. Thus, this dominantly orthogranic chlamydic  intergrade is a mixed complex fabric with a subdominant orthogranic RDP.    48    It is thought that the relative absence of silt in the f-matrix results in the  mobilization of the clay on wetting and in its plastering onto the surfaces of  the sand grains. This orientation of groups of clay domains parallel to the  grain surfaces results from the drying down of the liquid/air interface as the  receding water menisci retreat away from the centre of pores towards the  sand grains.  From 4:1 to z, the plasmic fabric is mainly silasepic, again because the  orientation of clay domains is hampered by the boundary effect of fine silt.  Most of the clays occur as isotropic and undulic units which are small and  discrete, and form isolated fillings in the small voids between silt grains in  the silt and clay fine-matrix. The small quantity of visible clay represents  groups of clay domains that happen to be orientated in the right direction in  relation to the optical axis of the microscope to show birefringence. At s,  the absence of interference from silt allows preferred orientation of clay  domains around some sand grain surfaces and a modest development of  skelsepic fabric.  Despite the increase in clay content, the volume of both small and large  voids shows a slight increase at all s:z ratios. The formation of clay coatings  around grains slightly expands the bulk volume of the grain matrix and  hence creates more intergranular space. Thus, less clay is available to fill the  enhanced volume of intergranular voids. There is a slight increase in weak  vosepic plasma which is in fact due to grain coatings in simple packing voids.  At high s:z ratios, where the influence from silt is relatively small, the clay  at this 10% level on wetting and drying is actively involved in shaping the  microfabric.  (c) 20% clay. At 20% clay, coarse porphyric fabrics are formed from 1:1  to z. The f-matrix -- with more silt than clay -- is compact and the quantity  is sufficient to engulf the sand grains completely. Also, there is occasionally  some orientation of elongated silt grains around sand grains, indicating the  significance of the isotropic compressive stress of drying (Towner, 1961)  in organizing the microfabric. At 2:1, the f-matrix -- with nearly equal  quantities of silt and clay -- coats most sand-grain surfaces. Additionally,  short and wide braces are formed that are in physical continuity with the  coatings across intergranular spaces. Not much void space is left, and the  fabric formed is plectic porphyric (Fig. 3). The f-matrix is dynamic and  mobile enough upon wetting and drying to spread and organize itself around  the sand grains, but at 4:1 there is insufficient f-matrix material to form  wide braces. Instead, narrower bridges are formed that both link the sand  grains and tend to widen at their contacts to form iunctic porphyric fabric  (Fig. 4). At s, the clay forms continuous coatings around the sand grains  and the amount of clay is more than enough to coat all the grains. The  surplus forms short and narrow bridges between the grains, forming a mixed  complex iunctic-chlamydic fabric (Fig. 5).  From 1:2 to z, the plasmic fabric remains dominantly silasepic, though  there is a minor development of skelsepic features. At 1:1, there is some    49    Fig. 3. Sample with 20% Ca-clay and a sand:silt ratio of 2:1, showing plectic porphyric  RDP and inskelsepic plasmic fabric; the mobility of the f-matrix is enhanced by the  increasing amounts of clay and, as a result, intergranular braces are formed. The sample  also marks the transition between fine and coarse matrices. (Cross-polarized light, X 110.)    Fig. 4. Sample with 20% Ca-clay and a sand:silt ratio of 4:1, showing iunctic plectic  RDP and inskelsepic plasmic fabric; intergranular bridges are formed; and the coarse  matrix is established which leaves much interstitial areas empty. (Cross-polarized light,  10.)    50    Fig. 5. Sample with 20% Ca-clay and sand as the only skeletal grains, showing mixed com-  plex iunctic-chlamydic RDP and skelsepic plasmic fabric; virtually all the clay (f-matrix)  is associated with the surfaces of the sand grains to form relatively thick and continuous  free grain argillans; some clay forms narrow bridges between sand grains. (Cross-polarized  light, 110.)  incipient formation of plasma separations, which lead to a weak insepic  fabric, and this is accompanied by a stronger but very thin (&lt;2.5 pm)  expression of skelsepic plasma. Thus, with 20% clay, wetting and drying and  their associated stresses result in the organization of clay domains. With  increasing amounts of sand, the plasmic fabric changes to inskelsepic at 2:1  and 4:1, as skelsepic features take precedence over insepic. With this increase  in the c:z ratio, the extra clay is associated with the sand-grain surfaces (Figs.  3 and 4). Eventually at s, the plasmic fabric becomes overwhelmingly  skelsepic as all the surfaces of the sand grains are covered by birefringent  clay, some being over 2.5 ~m thick (Fig. 5).  The volume of voids is lower than that at 10% clay, and the proportion  that is vosepic increases from 2:1 to s. The higher 20%-clay content has  expanded the coarse matrix even further by coating the grains, while at the  same time there is an extra supply of clay available for the filling of inter-  stitial spaces. This now more than offsets the increase in void ratio due to  matrix expansion. The predominance of fine matrix at a s:z ratio of less  than 1:1 and of coarse matrix at more than 1:1 suggests that the void ratio  is at a minimum at 1:1 and increases in both directions towards z or s. This  is verified by the results obtained from point-counting.  (d) 40% clay.  At 40% clay, the f-matrix has a smooth appearance and    51    engulfs the sand grains to form a fine porphyric fabric. This is texturally  from 1:2 to z, whilst the decrease in the proportion of sand delays the estab-  lishment of a coarse matrix until 4:1. Instead of acting disruptively on clay  orientation, many of the silt grains now behave like sand grains as inert  islands in the f-matrix. At 4:1, the c:z ratio reaches 3.3, and with the belated  formation of a coarse matrix, the f-matrix organizes itself around the sand  grains~ covering their surfaces completely. In addition the extra amount of  clay forms wide braces connecting the sand grains and so forming a fine  matrix. Much of the intergranular space is filled, and the fabric formed is  mixed complex plectic-porphyric. At s, the f-matrix is made up exclusively  of clay. Here, because of the large simple packing voids of sand grains, the  coarse matrix is more open. The clay covers all the grain surfaces and links  them together in the form of braces, though leaving much void space vacant.  The fabric formed has plectic features which are more dominant than  porphyric, hence porphyric plectic.  The plasmic fabric changes drastically with the s:z ratio. Insepic is domi-  nant at z and 1:4, due to the presence of more silt than clay in the f-matrix.  Characteristically this interferes with clay orientation and domain align-  ment, both in the matrix and on grain surfaces. Mosepic begins to emerge  at 1:2, and is accompanied by increasing skelsepic features with changes in  the c:z ratio in favour of clay. At 1:1, skelmosepic is in evidence, and this is  replaced by moskelsepic at 2:1 as skelsepic features begin to dominate with  the increase in sand and concomitant decrease in silt content. This decrease  in silt reduces the disruptive effect on clay orientation, whereas the increase  in sand provides more sites for the development of skelsepic plasma, the  thickness of which tends to increase with the size of grains. Thus the gradual  increase in the expression of clay orientation at the clay/grain interface  occurring with the increase in the c:z ratio is accompanied by an increase  in the significance of oriented clay in the matrix from z to 2:1 {from insepic  to mosepic), followed by a decrease from 2:1 towards s {from mosepic back  to insepic). At 4:1, the changeover from fine to coarse matrix breaks the  continuity of the f-matrix, which then becomes isolated pockets in the  interstices of the sand grains, and allows domination of clay orientation  around sand grains, giving rise to inskelsepic fabric. At s, inskelsepic fabric is  also formed.  Normal shrinkage in the context of the bulk sample (Stirk, 1954; Yong  and Warkentin, 1975) in a coarse matrix sample is restricted, and shrinkage  limit is reached at a relatively high moisture content as soon as the coarse  particles are in contact. The entry of air into the voids at a moisture content  lower than the shrinkage limit implies that the effective isotropic stress due  to moisture suction is drastically reduced (Towner, 1961). On the other  hand, in samples with fine matrices (s:z &lt;2:1), shrinkage limits are at a  much lower moisture content, allowing stronger compressive stress of  suction to be exerted for a longer duration. This may explain the formation  of insepic rather than mosepic fabric in the f-matrix of the coarse matrix  samples.    52    The development of skelsepic plasma in a coarse matrix under the  isotropic stress of drying is also different from that in a fine matrix. In a  coarse matrix, relatively large and continuous air/water interfaces are devel-  oped in the niches of the intergranular voids when the sample is dried below  the shrinkage limit. With further removal of water, any clay present in the  voids is confined between two surfaces, namely the receding air/water inter-  face furnished by surface tension of water, and the stationary and rigid sand-  grain surface. The recession of the air/water interface therefore results in  compression with a dominant direction of strain perpendicular to the surface  of the sand grain. Both the degree of orientation and the thickness of  skelsepic plasma generated by this unidirectional stress are relatively en-  hanced. On the other hand, in a fine matrix, the unidirectional stress is  replaced by an overall compressive stress of the shrinking sample. Strain  occurring around and in the vicinity of the sand grains is concentrated in  the plasma because sand grains cannot be deformed. A clay which swells  more will have a greater total strain upon shrinkage and hence more signif-  icant development of skelsepic fabric. Also, swelling increases interparticle  distance which reduces both physical and physico-chemical resistance against  particle rearrangement. The presence of sand grains in a shrinking mass of  clay offers a larger passive volume and hence a greater disruption of the  otherwise uniform spatial distribution of strain than the presence of silt  grains, which allows greater concentration of strain on its surface and thicker  embedded grain argillans.  At 40% clay, the volume of voids decreases from z towards 2:1, and this  marks the minimum void ratio characteristic of the transition between fine  and coarse matrices. In the fine matrix, all the voids are small due to the  packing of fine materials, and this contrasts with the dominant large voids  of the coarse matrix.  (e) 60% and 80% clay. At 60%, all seven s:z samples have more clay than  silt in the f-matrix which surrounds sand grains completely and forms a fine  porphyric fabric. Silt grains are also embedded by clay and can also be  regarded as f-members. The low content of grains ensures that no voids  (observable} are left unfilled by the f-matrix and that no coarse matrix can  be developed. Fine matrix also dominates at 80% clay and results in the same  monotonous fine porphyric fabric. The only variation across s:z samples is  the size of the inert embedded grains.  The plasmic fabrics are similarly homogeneously skelmasepic from s to  1:4 at both 60% and 80% clay levels. The dominance of masepic over  skelsepic is caused by the large proportion of plasma in relation to grains,  rather than by a reduction in the ability of the plasma to form embedded  grain argillans. In fact, all the sand grains have coatings of clay with skelsepic  fabric (neostrain), and the thickness of birefringent coatings is greater than  that of their counterparts at lower clay contents. About half of the coatings  have a maximum thickness over 2.5 pm. Also, because the coatings are  better developed on sand than on silt grains, the degree of skelsepic expres-  sion increases with the proportion of sand in the samples.    53    The strong development of skelsepic plasma reflects the large shrink/swell  potential of the samples and the resulting concentration of more strain on  a grain of a given size in comparison with the conditions at lower clay  contents. The stronger development of masepic fabrics also suggests a greater  total strain.  At z, mamosepic fabrics are formed at both 60% and 80% clay levels.  Failure to develop a significant skelsepic fabric is due to the small size of silt  grains which concentrates less strain and to the boundary effect of fine silt.  As a result, mosepic and masepic fabrics formed by isotropic compression  of a shrinking plasma dominate.  Most of the plasma separations constituting the masepic fabric are less  than 20 pm long and more than half are narrow (&lt; 2.5 pm). Such relatively  weak expression of masepic fabric is expected from a non-shearing develop-  ment  of plasma separation by isotropic compression mainly during  shrinkage. Furthermore, the masepic fabric tends to become less developed  at 80% than at 60% clay. It is thought that the presence of a certain number  of skeletal grains in addition to a sufficient amount of clay is required for  the development of masepic fabric by isotropic compression. The mechani-  cally inert grains in the dynamic and somewhat mobile clay matrix upset the  otherwise homogeneous stress distribution and result in localized uneven  strain in areas between grains. At an optimum grain content, which differs  according to the state of stress, masepic fabric by isotropic compression will  be best developed.  At 60% clay, the visible volume of voids in samples from 1:2 to z is  reduced to a very low percentage ranging from 4% to 10%. The 15%--30%  void volume at s and 4:1 consists of predominantly small voids (longest axis  &lt; 30 pm), and this illustrates the domination of the fine matrix. At 80%  clay, the volume of visible voids drops to a mere 1%--3%, and these are all  small and non-vosepic.    Ca/Na-montmorillonite    Only four levels of clay at 20%, 40%, 60% and 80% are investigated,  and the results of their experimentally produced RDP and plasmic fabrics  are illustrated in Fig. 6. As expected, at the lower clay contents of 5% and  10%, the fabric is controlled by skeletal gains to the virtual exclusion of  the clay. In comparison with the less active Ca-montmorillonite samples, the  greater swelling potential, water retention capacity and high plasticity index  of Ca/Na-clay (with sodium on the exchange complex equivalent to an  exchangeable sodium percentage of 30%) is expected to result in more intense  reorganization of their microfabrics.  (a) 20% clay.  At 20% clay, a coarse porphyric fabric is developed from  1:1 up to z. This is the same as for the Ca-montmorillonite samples but, at  2:1, iunctic porphyric instead of plectic porphyric is formed. More swelling  must have occurred in the Ca/Na-clay and this pushes the sand grains further    54    CLAY    +-+ + ++ -~    ,~?oIs~      ~?olN~oN~    o1~\~    Is~           ~c9oIs~  ?" 15~"    +?'C'~ t s~".-e " \~? I s%'~-+c~\~                +c?    +~9 IS'~              +      +        +        +      +          S  /            +       +         +         +       +            \    SAND                                                                SILT    Fig. 6. Related distribution pattern (RDP) and plasmic fabrics of Ca/Na-montmorillonite  samples.    apart from each other. Upon shrinkage and the retreating air/water inter-  face, the limited amount of relatively mobile (c:z = 0.75) f-matrix material  is concentrated to form narrow bridges between adjacent grains. At 4:1,  the fabric is plectic chlamydic rather than iunctic plectic. The full develop-  ment of coarse matrix here allows the more mobile Ca/Na-clay to spread and  disseminate itself evenly on sand-grain surfaces rather than being confined  to grain contacts. The much higher amount of water that can be imbibed,  and the stronger interparticle repulsion, enhance the plasticity and mobility  of the Ca/Na-clay. Greater swelling allows larger total strain and more  freedom for particle reorganization upon shrinkage. At s, the absence of silt  has probably permitted maximum mobility to occur. This results in a more  complete and uniform plastering of plasma onto sand grains and coalescence  of coatings in the form of braces at many of the intergranular connections.  Thus, the fabric is best described as mixed chlamydic-plectic with the  smooth concavities of their braces suggesting genesis by receding curved  water menisci.  The plasmic fabrics from 1:1 up to z, like RDP, are the same as for    55    Ca-clay. At 2:1, however, the plasmic fabric is skel-insepic whilst, at 4:1  and s, strong skelsepic fabrics are developed. Here the formation of grain  argillans is strongly influenced by the presence of free air/water interfaces.  In the Ca/Na-montmorillonite clay samples, the volume of voids is much  higher than for Ca-clay, suggesting greater expansion of the coarse matrix by  clay coatings and by bridges at critical intergranular contacts. The incipient  development of a coarse matrix, as suggested by the appearance of large  voids at 2:1, suggests that the sample may have a fine matrix when wet  because of clay swelling and a coarse matrix upon drying. As yet, however,  there is no convincing technique for observing microfabrics in thin sections  when wet.  (b) 40% clay. At 40% clay, the same RDP is developed at all z:s ratios as  for Ca-clay. Plasmic fabrics also follow the same general trend but, as would  be expected with Ca/Na-clay, with a stronger development of clay orienta-  tion both in the matrix and on matrix/grain interfaces. Likewise, as in the  case of the 20% Ca/Na-clay samples, matrix expansion at 40% clay results in  a higher volume of voids.    CLAY    /    +     \  \  +        +        +              X    SAND                                                                                               SILT  Fig. 7. Related distribution pattern (RDP) and plasmic fabrics of Na-montmorillonite  samples.    56    (c) 60% and 80% clay. At both 60% and 80% clay, the same RDP plasmic  fabrics and volume of voids as for Ca-clay occur at all s:z ratios. The one  exception is for z at both clay levels where greater orientation in their  matrices results in momasepic rather than mamosepic fabrics being formed.    Na-montmorillonite    As for Ca/Na-montmorillonite, only four clay levels are examined, results  of which are given in Fig. 7.  (a) 20% clay. As for the other cationic types at 20% clay, coarse porphy-  ric fabrics are formed from 1:2 to z (Fig. 8). At 2:1 and 1:1, however,  iunctic porphyric rather than coarse porphyric fabric is formed. This reflects  the stronger mobility and swelling potential of the Na-clay, despite the low  c:z ratio of the f-matrix at 0.5 only {Fig. 9). At 4:1, chlamydic iunctic fabric  rather than the plectic chlamydic of the Ca/Na-clay is developed (Fig. 10),  suggesting a further expansion of the coarse matrix and the formation of  narrow bridges between grains. At s, the fabric, chlamydic plectic (Fig. 11),  is the same as for the Ca/Na-clay. At all textural levels, plasmic fabrics are  similar to those of the Ca/Na-clay, but with slightly stronger development of  birefringent plasma in the matrix. Particle rearrangement and pore collapse  upon shrinkage is thought to underlie the lower volume of voids in these  samples as compared with those of the Ca/Na-clay.    Fig. 8. Sample with 20% Na-clay and silt as the only skeletal grains, showing coarse  porphyrie RDP and silasepic plasmic fabric; the disruptive influence of silt on clay  orientation dominates despite the higher activity of the Na-clay. (Cross-polarized light,  x II0.)    57    Fig. 9. Sample with 20% Na-clay and a sand:silt ratio of 2:1, showing iunctic porphyric  RDP and weak inmosepic plasmic fabric; plasma orientation on sand grains is weakly  developed due to the hampering effect of silt in the f-matrix. (Cross-polarized light,  x 110.)    Fig. 10. Sample with 20% Na-clay and a sand:silt ratio of 4:1, showing chlamydic iunetie  RDP and inskelsepic plasmic fabric; ske|sepic features can develop despite the low clay  content (20%) which mirrors the high activity of Na-clay. (Cross-polarized light, 110.)    58    Fig. 11. Sample with 20% Na-clay and sand as the only skeletal grains with many voids,  showing chlamydic plectic RDP and skelsepic plasmic fabric; despite the low content of  clay (20%) the free grain argillans are strongly developed with continuous internal fabric,  sharp boundaries and are highly birefringent. (Cross-polarized light, 110.)    Fig. 12. Sample with 40% Na-clay with sand as the only skeletal grains, showing  porphyric plectic RDP and skelsepic plasmic fabric; very strong development of partially  embedded grain argillans and birefringent (orientated) intergranular braces are both indi-  cators of the high activity of the Na-clay. (Cross-polarized light, X 110.)    59    (b) 40%, 60% and 80% clay. At 40%, 60% and 80%, the same RDPs and  plasmic fabrics are formed as for both Ca/Na- and Ca-montmorillonite (Fig.  12). Orientated clay, however, both in the matrix and on grain surfaces is  better developed, and the microfabrics contain a slightly greater volume of  voids.    GENERAL DISCUSSION ON RELATED DISTRIBUTION PATTERNS    From the result of the experiments, relationships between RDP and  texture can be generalized into textural regions as shown in Fig. 13. Within  the given range of texture in each region is shown the most likely RDP -- the  modal fabric -- that would develop under the influence of the universal  process of wetting and drying and those, by analogy, to be expected in  soil microfabrics. There is, however, one proviso and that is that the strain  is isotropic. This results when there is no shear stress or too little to cause  any shearing. Intergrade fabrics would be expected to occur at transitional  areas adjacent to the demarcation lines. Where there are relatively large and    CLAY    fPo    Ch    Iu    Og    cPo    SAND                                                                SILT    Fig. 13. Generalized relationship between texture and related distribution pattern (RDP)  of samples subjected to isotropic stresses of wetting and drying. Arrows indicate the  likely movement of boundaries with increase in the activity of the clay fraction.    60    separable discrete areas with different textures, heterogeneous particle-size  distribution would create separated complexes, and mixed complexes where  there is intimate mixing of areas with different textures that cannot be  discretely separated (Brewer and Pawluk, 1975).  Orthogranic and phyric fabrics occupy the two 100% sand and silt apices,  respectively. The rest of the textural triangle is taken up mainly by  porphyric fabrics: coarse porphyric with a low clay content where both silt  and clay make up the f-matrix, and fine porphyric with a high clay content  where the f-matrix is dominated by clay with the role of silt becoming  that of f-members like sand. Around 100% clay, the fabric is predominantly  made up of plasma which can better be described as argillamatric (Eswaran,  1972), rather than fine porphyric. The role of plasma in RDP formation in  these fabric regions is largely passive.  A continuous fine matrix, which is the prerequisite for porphyric fabric,  is developed from 0% up to about 45% sand, above which it is supplanted by  coarse matrix. At low sand:silt ratio, the transition occurs at a higher sand  content ranging from 45% to 65% due to a dominantly silty f-matrix. This  implies that a lesser amount by weight of f-matrix material is required to  keep the sand grains apart. With little clay in the f-matrix, the loose packing  of the silt grains is the cause of its enhanced specific volume. Without  active plasma, the shrink/swell potential of the sample is extremely limited,  and the corollary is that only limited particle rearrangement towards closer  packing can occur. Also the binding effect of clay on grains which may  otherwise hold the silt grains closer together, is lacking. Hence, a relatively  small number of silt grains can keep a relatively large amount of sand from  establishing contact and can maintain a fine porphyric fabric at sand con-  tents &gt; 50%.  Coupled with a relatively low silt and clay content, the formation of  coarse matrix at high sand content allows the clay to play an active role  in moulding RDP. The majority of fabric variations, therefore, occur in  this part of the textural triangle where interfacial phenomena are significant.  Low clay content ensures that the intergranular voids are not completely  filled, whereas low silt content results in less disruption to clay organization.  In comparative terms, swelling and shrinkage and the associated particle  rearrangement are maximized in the niches of the relatively large voids.  Drying entails the recession of a relatively large and continuous air/water  interface away from the centre of the voids towards the sand-grain surfaces,  and in the process compresses the f-matrix materials onto the sand-grain  surfaces. The mobility of the f-matrix governs the extent and the forms of  the distribution on the sand grains. More silt than clay in the f-matrix  reduces its mobility and leads to a higher concentration around areas where  the intergranular distances are the least. More clay than silt, on the contrary,  enhances mobility and permits a more even spreading of the f-matrix onto  the sand grains. The former (high sand:silt ratio) creates dominantly bridges  linking sand grains: fabrics belonging to the iunctic sequence; the latter    61    (low sand:silt ratio) creates dominantly coatings around sand grains: fabrics  belonging to the chlamydic sequence.  In the iunctic sequence, an increase in the amount of f-matrix widens the  bridges and reduces the volume of voids such that the fabric grades towards  porphyric iunctic, then iunctic porphyric, until eventually the fine matrix is  established. As the f-matrix has more silt than clay, the coarse porphyric  fabric marks one end of the iunctic sequence. In the case of the chlamydic  sequence, an increase in the amount of f-matrix thickens the clay coatings on  sand grains, which merge, while still keeping the intergranular distance short  to form plectic fabric. Further increase builds up the volume of the f-matrix  at the expense of the voids such that the fabric grades into plectic porphyric  until the f-matrix is established. More clay than silt in the f-matrix then  creates a fine porphyric fabric.  The overall results of the present experiments agree to a large extent  with the detailed empirical observations on the broad relationships between  texture and fabrics in Australian (Brewer, 1979) and Canadian (McKeague  and Guertin, 1982) soils. The transition from coarse to fine matrix reported  by Brewer occurs at a much higher sand content (about 77%), suggesting that  the f-matrix has a more open structure and a larger specific volume than that  of the experimental materials reported here. The presence of inorganic as  well as organic binding agents that aggregate soils and stabilize them against  structural breakdown and pore collapse is a probable cause for the more  porous f-matrix.  An increase in the activity of the clay fraction can be expected to cause  changes in the RDP--texture relationship. In the present experiments, the  presence of sodium on the exchange complex enhances the activity of the  montmorillonite. Many of the changes occur at the boundaries between  coarse and fine matrices. The arrows in Fig. 13 summarize the directions of  displacement with increase in the activity of the clay. The transition from  coarse to fine porphyric fabrics can be interpreted as resulting from an  expansion of the coarse matrix due to the formation of thicker clay films  around sand grains, and consequently more f-matrix material is required to  establish a fine matrix. The transition is greater at higher clay content  because of the reduced development of clay coatings at low clay content.  The transition of the chlamydic towards the iunctic fabrics can be inter-  preted as resulting from the higher mobility of the f-matrix even at a relative-  ly low clay:silt ratio.    GENERAL DISCUSSION ON PLASMIC FABRIC    The generalized relationship between plasmic fabric and texture under the  influence of isotropic stresses of wetting and drying is summarized in  Fig. 14. Four regions can be recognized: (1) at very low clay content (&lt;10%)  plasmic fabric could not be assessed (not assessable), and at high silt content  silasepic (Si) fabric; (2) sepic fabric dominated by clay orientation around    62    CLAY    SkMa    Sk    Mo/Ma    IN    Si    Not Assessible    SAND                                                                SILT  Fig. 14. Generalized relationship between texture and plasmic fabric of samples subjected  to isotropic stresses of wetting and drying. Arrows indicate the likely movement of  boundaries with increase in the activity of the clay fraction.    sand grains (Sk); (3) sepic fabric dominated by clay orientation in the matrix  (In and Mo/Ma); (4) sepic fabric transitional between the last two (SkMa).  Contrary to RDP, much of the variation in plasmic fabric occurs on the  right-hand side in samples with low s:z ratios.  At low clay contents, silty samples understandably develop silasepic fabric  because of the dominating disruptive influence on clay orientation by silt.  Clay domains are scattered in the interstices or form very thin and hardly  perceptible coatings on silt grains. Plasma separations, which require at least  a partly continuous and dominantly clayey matrix to form, are therefore  absent. The percentage clay limit of silasepic fabric is higher at high silt  content and decreases with the increase in s:z ratio due to the gradual  decline in silt interference.  Samples with high sand content are dominated by skelsepic fabric from  about 10% to 50% clay. The coarse nature of these matrices results in the  reorganization of plasma on sand-grain surface and is better developed in  regions corresponding to chlamydic fabrics and less in iunctic fabrics. A  number of fine porphyric fabrics develop a dominant skelsepic fabric which    63    consists of embedded grain argillans rather than free grain argillans. The clay  content in this region is sufficient to form prominent skelsepic features but  not enough for prominent clay orientation in the matrix.  An increase in clay content in samples with low s:z ratios results in a  transition from silasepic to insepic fabric, with some incipient development  of small and randomly scattered plasma separations due to the increase in  c:z ratio. The changeover occurs at around 25% clay for samples with s:z  less than 1:2, and at around 18% clay for samples with s:z ranging from 1:2  to 2:1, indicating the effect of silt on clay orientation. In contrast, over a  similar range of clay content, the sandy samples maintain skelsepic fabrics.  Further increase in clay content in the silty region (fight-hand side of  Fig. 14) results in a transition to mosepic and weak masepic fabrics. Again,  the changeover is retarded till a higher clay content in samples with low s:z  ratios. The development of stronger sepic plasmic fabrics in the matrix  reflects the emergence of clay as the dominant particle-size fraction. The  expression of masepic features is always subordinate to those of mosepic in  this fabric region, especially in samples with a lower clay content.  At clay contents of more than 50% where the RDP is overwhelmingly fine  porphyric, samples from s to 1:4 give way to a dominantly masepic fabric  with subordinate skelsepic features. In samples with silt as the only skeletal  grains, a marked development of skelsepic fabric is not possible and the  fabric grades into masepic with auxiliary mosepic components. The same is  true at around 100% clay, corresponding to argillamatric RDP (Eswaran,  1972) where the paucity of skeletal grain precludes any skelsepic features.  On the whole, masepic fabrics are only weakly expressed. The limited  capacity of the isotropic stress of wetting and drying to rearrange clay  domains into elongated plasma separation is obvious. During wetting, the  originally randomly oriented clay domains swell by imbibing interlamellar  water and push against each other, the overall effect of which is the forma-  tion of an open microstructure that maintains the relative positions of the  domains. The main source of the increase in void ratio comes from the  expansion of interdomainal voids (Quirk, 1978). These movements are  unlikely to cause significant preferred orientation of clay domains. On the  other hand, the compressive stress generated by virtue of moisture suction  upon drying can lead to pore collapse and some domain-alignment on a  limited scale, thus forming small plasma separations characteristic of insepic,  mosepic, and at best weak masepic fabrics. Thus, any well-developed masepic  fabric in soils is likely to be formed by processes in addition to wetting and  drying. The findings of Greene-Kelly and Mackney (1970) support this  conclusion. Thus, wetting and drying that extends into the high suctions can  cause some limited particle organization by aligning clay domains into  positions of minimum potential energy. But this rearrangement creates only  small plasma separations with preferred orientation within them but very  poorly amongst them. Also, the equilibrium positions in general are attained  and stabilized fairly quickly in one cycle of wetting and drying (Croney and    64    Coleman, 1954; Greene-Kelly and Mackney, 1970). Shearing of soils under  strong anisotropic stress is therefore required if large plasma separations  with strong preferred orientations are to be developed.  The increase in the activity of the clay fraction with a greater amount of  exchangeable sodium causes some minor shifts of the generalized boundaries  which are concentrated in samples with low s:z ratios in the matrix at low to  medium clay contents. Sandy and clayey samples are less affected. The  overall trend of plasma fabric change is one of expansion from stronger sepic  towards  weaker  sepic--skelmasepic  (SkMa)  towards  mosepic/masepic  (Mo/Ma), and from weak sepic towards asepic--insepic (In) towards silasepic  (Si). The skelmasepic (SkMa) and skelsepic (Sk) fabrics also occur more  frequently.    PEDOLOGICAL IMPLICATIONS    Eswaran and Banos (1976) proposed normal RDP for samples packed  simply according to their texture without any influence from the processes  of pedogenic reorganization. The present results deviate significantly from  their normal RDP, suggesting that wetting and drying by itself can be sub-  stantial agents for fabric development in soils. Thus, it is proposed to  describe fabrics that result from the interplay of texture and wetting and  drying under an overall isotropic stress regime as "erdic" (after the term  "erdefication", Conacher and Dalrymple, 1977). Thus "erdic fabric" is a  group name for the suite of fundamental RDPs and plasmic fabrics sum-  marized in Figs. 13 and 14.  Whereas the present investigation is confined to the lowest level of organi-  zation of soil materials between plasma and grains, White (1966, 1967)  recognizes the importance of texture in conjunction with soil moisture  changes in the formation of various field structural types. Swelling and  shrinkage of soils with a clay matrix are more likely to result in structural  peds macroscopically because the fabric units of the f-matrix have a physical  continuity which allows a large portion of volume changes to be trans-  mitted. If the clay has a large shrink/swell potential, the fine porphyric  fabric could generate considerable stress upon swelling to cause shearing  along planes oblique to the directions of principal stresses. These may  exceed the rupture limit at certain intervals and result in the formation of  interpedal voids of blocky or sphenoid structures. If the texture creates  coarse porphyric fabric, which has silt as the principal component of the  f-matrix and therefore has much lower shrink/swell potential and is less  prone to shearing, orthogonal tensile fractures created during shrinkage  may become the interpedal voids of columnar or prismatic structures (White,  1966, 1967). When the clay content or the activity of the clay fraction is too  low, structural formation can be hampered due to the lack of volume  change, thus resulting in massive or apedal soils.    65    Some soils with coarse matrix (iunctic and chlamydic sequences) have  inherently lower shrink/swell potential in comparison with soils with the  same clay content and the same activity but more silt and less sand in their  porphyric fabrics. Here, some of the swelling of the clay that is largely  trapped within the interstices of sand grains can be accommodated within  the intergranular voids instead of being spread, and normal shrinkage is  arrested as soon as the f-members have established contacts. Shrinkage limit  is likely to be fairly high because the voids between f-members are not  collapsible. The inability to build up swelling pressure required for oblique  shear planes (Knight, 1980; Spoor and Godwin, 1980) and the lack of large  shrinkage required for orthogonal fractures necessary for the development of  peds imply that structure development in soils with coarse matrix can at best  be weak. Where such developments exist, softs are more likely to be of a low-  stress shrinkage-induced type, such as columnar or prismatic, rather than the  high-stress swelling-induced types, such as blocky or sphenoid that are char-  acteristic of soils with high shrink/swell potential and particularly evident in  Vertisols.  The formation of oriented clay films around f-members in coarse matrix  fabrics may enhance swelling in so far as any volume change at intergranular  contacts may be readily transmitted. The small volume of clay that is  involved and the dissipation of swelling-emanated stresses by plastic  deformation of the clay coatings (the intergranular voids provide room for  relatively unobstructed deformation) limit its effectiveness. Intergranular  bridges in iunctic fabrics generally exert less influence on shrink/swell  potential due to the presence of more inert silt than clay.  The arrangement of particles into RDP characteristic of a given texture  at the lowest level of organization in response to moisture fluctuations is  likely to be permanent and irreversible (Croney and Coleman, 1954). Like-  wise, fabric anisotropy has been related to aggregate stability (Brewer and  Blackmore, 1956; Cagauan and Uehara, 1965; Camp and Gill, 1969; Blake  and Gilman, 1970). This is aided by bonding agents but, except for physico-  chemical bonding amongst skeletal grains and clay domains, these have not  been assessed in this experimental study of microfabrics. Thus, as noted  earlier, a differing degree of restriction on the freedom of fabric unit  reorganization under an overall isotropic stress regime on wetting and drying  occurs in some of the experimentally produced erdic fabrics as compared  with those described from soil B-horizons.  As pointed out by McKeague and Guertin (1982), fabric identification  and classification is a rather subjective and inconsistent exercise. The large  measure of agreement between microfabrics produced experimentally  with empirical observations from soft B-horizons, however, suggests that  experimental fabrics produced under controlled and reproducible conditions  as described here offers the opportunity to set up benchmark fabrics to serve  as standards.    66    CONCLUSIONS    Results of this experimental study show that under the influence of  wetting and drying, systematic and repetitive variations in related distribu-  tion pattern (RDP) and plasmic fabric are formed in relation to textural-  change -erdic-fabric. At low clay content {0%--10%), all microfabrics are the  result of packing of skeletal grains. At medium clay content (20--40%),  the dynamic clay--water interaction generates reorganization. Here, the  sand:silt ratio begins to exert its influence and determines the fine to coarse  matrix transition and the degree of clay orientation. A low ratio disturbs  clay orientation and favours the formation of a fine matrix. A high ratio  favours clay orientation and the formation of a coarse matrix. In addition,  the clay:silt ratio determines the mobility of the f-matrix, which is more  mobile at a high ratio. At high clay content (&gt;60%), a fine matrix is formed  regardless of the sand:silt ratio, and clay mobility is hardly affected by the  clay:silt ratio. Thus, most fabric changes occur at medium clay contents  where a variety of packing (fine to coarse matrix) and a range of f-matrix  mobility (which itself is a function of the clay:silt ratio) are possible. The  domination of skeletal grains and clay at low and high clay contents, re-  spectively, produce a much lower variety of fabrics. Important variations  in RDP occur at medium clay content with coarse matrix, where a high  clay:silt ratio allows spreading of the f-matrix evenly on sand grains to form  fabrics of the chlamydic sequence and a low ratio restricts the f-matrix  movement, allowing only the formation of bridges between grains character-  istic of the iunctic sequence. A receding air--water interface in the coarse  matrix leads to the development of strong free grain argillans, whereas in the  fine matrix the disruption of the strain homogeneity by mechanically inert  grains is the cause of embedded grain argillans. The weak masepic fabric  tends to be less developed and expressed with increase in clay content and  is ascribed to the lack of strain disturbance provided by the grains. Increased  activity of the clay fraction brings about some limited changes in micro-  fabric. The only type of sepic plasmic fabric that can be developed strongly  under isotropic stresses of wetting and drying, is skelsepic. Strong develop-  ment of plasma separations in the matrix of erdic fabrics must be either  inherited or caused by anisotropic stresses. It is hoped that this study will  lead to further experimental investigations of the relationship between  specific soil-forming processes and fabrics.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    C.Y. Jim wishes to express his gratitude to the Commonwealth Scholar-  ship Commission for the provision of financial support which allowed him  to undertake postgraduate research at the University of Reading.    67    REFERENCES    Anderson, D.M. and Binnie, R.R., 1961. Modal analysis of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  25: 499--503.  Bartelli, L.J. and Odell, R.T., 1960. Laboratory studies and genesis of a clay-enriched  horizon in the lowest part of the solum of some brunizem and gray-brown podzolic  soils in Illinois. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 24: 390--395.  Blake, G.R. and Gilman, R.D., 1970. Thixotropic changes with ageing of synthetic soil  aggregates. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 561--564.  Bodman, G.B. and Constantin, G.K., 1965. Influence of particle-size distribution in soil  compaction. Hilgardia, 36: 567--591.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 470 pp.  Brewer, R., 1972a. The basis of interpretation of soil micromorphological data. Geo-  derma, 8: 81--94.  Brewer, R., 1972b. Microfabrics and soil history. In: R. Protz (Editor), Microfabric of  Soils and Sedimentary Deposits. Symposium, Guelph, Ont., pp. 162--201.  Brewer, R., 1974. Some considerations concerning micromorphological terminology.  In: G.K. Rutherford (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Limestone Press, Kingston, pp. 28--48.  Brewer R., 1979. Relationships between particle size, fabric and other factors in some  Australian soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17: 29--41.  Brewer R. and Blackmore, A.V., 1956. Effect of entrapped air and optically oriented  clay on aggregate breakdown and soil consistence. Aust. J. Appl. Sci., 7: 59--96.  Brewer, R. and Haldane, A.D., 1957. Preliminary experiments in the development of clay  orientation in soils. Soil Sci., 84: 301--309.  Brewer, R. and Pawluk, S., 1975. Investigations of some soils developed in hummocks of  Canadian Sub-arctic and Southern-arctic regions, I. Morphology and micromorphology.  Ca. J. Soil Sci., 55: 301--319.  Buol, S.W. and Hole, F.D., 1961. Clay skin genesis in Wisconsin soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 25: 377--379.  Cagauan, B. and Uehara, G., 1965. Soil anisotropy and its relation to aggregate stability.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29: 198--200.  Camp, C.R. and Gill, W.R., 1969. The effect of drying on soil strength parameters. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 641--644.  Chayes, F., 1956. Petrographic Modal Analysis, an Elementary Statistical Appraisal.  Wiley, New York, 113 pp.  Conacher, A.J. and Dalrymple, J.B., 1977. The nine unit landsurface model: an approach  to pedogeomorphic research. Geoderma, 18: 1--154.  Croney, D. and Coleman, J.D., 1954. Soil structure in relation to soil suction (pF).  J. Soil Sci., 5: 75--84.  Dalrymple, J.B., 1972. Experimental micropedological investigation of iron-oxide--  clay-complexes and their interpretation with respect to the soil fabrics of paleosols.  Proc. 3rd Int. Work-Meet. Soil Micromorphol., Wroclaw, 1969, pp. 583--594.  Day, P.R. and Holmgren, G.G., 1952. Microscopic changes in soil structure during com-  pression. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 16: 73--77.  Dijkerman, J.C., Cline, M.G. and Olson, GIW., 1967. Properties and genesis of textural  subsoil lamellae. Soil Sci., 104: 7--16.  E1 Rayah, H.M.E. and Rowell, D.L., 1973. The influence of iron and aluminium  hydroxides on the swelling of Na-montmorillonite and the permeability of a Na-soil.  J. Soil Sci., 24: 137--144.  Eswaran, H., 1968. Point-count analysis as applied to soil micromorphology. Pedologie,  18: 238--252.    68    Eswaran, H., 1972. Micromorphological indicators of pedogenesis in some tropical soils  derived from basalt from Nicaragua. Geoderma, 7: 15--31.  Eswaran, H. and Banos, C., 1976. Related distribution patterns in soils and their signif-  icance. Anal. Edafal. Agrobiol., 35: 33--45.  Eswaran, H., De Conick, F. and Conry, M.J., 1972. A comparative micromorphological  study of light and medium texture podzols. Proc. 3rd Int. Work. Meet. Soil Micro-  morphol., 1969, Wroclaw, pp. 269--286.  Greene-Kelly, R. and Mackney, D., 1970. Preferred orientation of clay soils: the effect  of drying and wetting. In: D.A. Osmond, and P. Bullock (Editors), Micromorpholog-  ical Techniques and Applications. Soil Surv. Engl. Wales, Tech. Monogr., 2: 43--52.  Jim, C.Y., 1981. Theoretical and experimental studies of some processes resulting in the  micromorphological reorganization in soils. Unpubl. Ph.D. thesis, Univ. Reading,  696 pp.  Jongerius, A., 1970. Some morphological aspects of regrouping phenomena in Dutch  soils. Geoderma, 4: 311--331.  Knight, M.J., 1980. Structural analysis and mechanical origins of gilgai at Boorook,  Victoria, Australia. Geoderma, 23: 245--283.  Kubiena, W.L., 1938. Micropedology. Collegiate Press, Ames, Iowa, 243 pp.  McKeague, J.A. and Guertin, R.K., 1982. Fabrics of some Canadian soils in relation to  particle size and other factors. Soil Sci., 133: 87--102.  Quirk, J.P., 1978. Some physico-chemical aspects of soil structural stability -- a review.  In: W.W. Emerson, R.D. Bond and A.R. Dexter (Editors), Modification of Soil Struc-  ture. Wiley, New York, N.Y., pp. 3--16.  Spoor, G. and Godwin, R.J., 1980. Soil deformation and shear strength characteristics of  some clay soils at different moisture contents. J. Soil Sci., 30: 483--498.  Stirk, G.B., 1954. Some aspects of soil shrinkage and the effect of cracking upon water  entry into the soil. Aust. J. Agric. Res., 5: 279--290.  Towner, G.D., 1961. Influence of soil--water suction on some mechanical properties of  soils. J. Soil Sci., 12: 180--187.  Wells, C.B., 1965. The formation of calcium carbonate concentrations. In: E.G. Halls-  worth and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimental Pedology. Proc. llth Easter School  in Agric. Sci., Univ. Nottingham, 1964, pp. 165--175.  Wilke, B.M. and Schwertmann, U., 1978. Micromorphology of synthetic soil aggregates.  Proc.  5th Int. Work-Meet. Soil Micromorphol., Granada, 1977, pp. 1387--1403.  White, E.M., 1966. Subsoil structure genesis: theoretical considerations. Soil Sci., 101:  135--141.  White, E.M., 1967. Soil age and texture factors in subsoil structure genesis. Soil Sci., 103:  288--298.  Yong, R.N. and Warkentin, B.P., 1975. Soil Properties and Behaviour. Elsevier, Amster-  dam, 449 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractThis experimental study examines the relationship between texture and microfabric under isotropic stresses generated by wetting and drying. This can be achieved by observing and measuring the reorganization of microfabrics (plasmic fabrics and related distribution pattern, RDP). Microfabrics are produced in the laboratory by mixing montmorillonite with various proportions of sand and silt, and subjecting them to wetting and drying without confinement. Thin sections are cut to study their microfabrics. Results show broad and systematic variations in fabric with changes in texture. Fine matrix (silt plus clay in physical continuity) is developed in samples with low sand:silt ratio, and regardless of this ratio at high clay levels. Coarse porphyric and fine porphyric RDP are formed at low and high clay contents, respectively. Plasmic fabrics are represented mainly by insepic and weakly developed mosepic and masepic fabrics in the matrix in the form of small plasma separations with random orientation, and weak skelsepic plasma as embedded grain argillans. On the other hand, coarse matrix (sand grains in physical continuity) dominates the sandy samples which are associated with relatively thick and strongly birefringent free grain argillans giving well-developed skelsepic fabric. The RDP follows two major paths: beginning with orthogranic (very low clay content) along the iunctic sequence at low clay:silt ratio and along the chlamydic sequence at high ratio. The regularities in fabric development are interpreted in the light of the dynamic properties and behaviour of the active clay fraction in a clay-water system. The pedogenetic implications of the results are explored, and the term erdic fabric defined. 