Geoderma, 32 (1984) 335--337                                                     335  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    A MOTORIZED GRINDER FOR MAKING SOIL THIN SECTIONS*    ALISON J. LOW, ERIC J. LOW and LOWELL A. DOUGLAS  Department of Soils and Crops, Cook College, New Jersey Agricultural Experiment  Station, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ 08903 (U.S.A.)  (Received April 5, 1983; revised version accepted November 2, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Low, A.J., Low, E.J. and Douglas, L.A., 1984. A motorized grinder for making soil thin  sections. Geoderma, 32: 335--337.    A small hand-held device is described which enables an operator to grind soil thin sec-  tions very rapidly as compared to conventional hand grinding. The apparatus is relatively  inexpensive and easy to construct as it comprises only a simple motorized grinder and grit  impregnated discs 2.5 cm in diameter.    INTRODUCTION    The most tedious and laborious, but seldom discussed, stage in the prep-  aration of soil thin sections is the final hand grinding, used to take the thin  sections down to a uniform thickness of approximately 30 um (FitzPatrick,  1980). As yet, there is no relatively inexpensive, automated system available  to carry out this operation. A method using a motorized grinding cylinder  is described here, and although this is not a fully automated system, it is  more rapid than conventional hand grinding. The time saved in section prep-  aration soon offsets the small cost of the device.    DESCRIPTION OF THE MOTORIZED GRINDING CYLINDER    The device comprises three parts: a small hand-held electric drill, a grinding  head and a mounting shaft. These are shown partially assembled in Fig. 1,  together with an arched, plastic shield mounted on a wooden block. As with  hand grinding, a lubricant is continually added to the surface of the slide  by the operator and the shield is used for protection against the spray caused  by the action of the grinding head on the specimen.    *New Jersey Agricultural Experiment Station Publication No. D-15408-1-83, supported  by State funds.  Present address of the first and second authors, 79 Desswood Place, Aberdeen, Scotland  (U.K.).    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    336    Fig. 1. Partially assembled grinding device with protective field.  The drill used was from a standard commercial tool kit.1 designed for  grinding, etching and polishing; but any small, hand-held, motorized shaft  which can operate at relatively slow speeds is suitable. The drive shaft of  our unit was designed to rotate at 30,000 rpm. This speed was further re-  duced to 2000 rpm using a variable rheostat. During grinding, the speed is  further reduced by friction.  The grinding heads were discs prepared by mixing the impregnating plastic  used in block preparation (in our case, a polyester resin, Bioplastic*2), a re-  latively large amount of catalyst (methyl ethyl ketone peroxide.2) and one  of the commonly used grinding powders (320, 400, or 600 grit, aluminum  oxide or silicon carbide), so that the plastic was loaded with grit. All air must  be removed from this mix so that the surface of the grinding disc is smooth.  In order to remove the air, the mixture was then placed in a 100-ml plastic  centrifuge tube (inside diameter, 2.5 cm) and spun for one hour at 1000  rpm. The precise technique will require some experimentation on the part  of individual operators, because the viscosity of the mix will differ with the  kind of plastic used and the amount of catalyst added. A balance must be  obtained where the air has been removed from the mix and the grit has not  all settled in the bottom of the centrifuge tube. The plastic is allowed to  harden overnight. The hardened cylinder of impregnated grit is then removed  1Sears model No. 572.25151, available from Sears Department stores.  ~Available from Wards Natural Science, Rochester, N.Y., 14603, U.S.A.    337    from the tube and cut into several discs of the desired length. In this study  discs about 1.5 cm thick were used.  A hole was drilled through the exact centre of the disc in order to accom-  modate the bolt which was used as the attaching shaft. Two nuts were used  to hold the disc on the shaft. It is important that the bolt fits tightly into  the hole and that the hole is in the exact centre of the disc, or the grinding  head will rotate eccentrically.  By use of this device, a 6 9 cm thin section with a starting thickness of  100 pm and containing 90% sand-sized quartz (2--0.05 mm e.s.d.) can be re-  duced by 5 pm in approximately 5 minutes, with a 400 grit disc. A sample  containing a higher proportion of fines will grind down much more rapidly.  Unless the slide is very thick, only 400 and 600 grit discs are required.  Each operator should work with his own set of discs, Because each opera-  tor holds the grinding device at a different angle, the discs are worn into a  cone shape specific to each individual. When a worn grinding head is held at a  different angle to that of the original operator, only part of the cone sur-  face is in contact with the thin section. This leads to very uneven grinding.  The principal departures from earlier methods made possible by the use  of this device are: (1) the preparation of grinding discs impregnated with  grit; (2) the use of the side rather than the flat end of the disc for grinding;  and (3) the use of a hand-held drill to spin the disc. This device considerably  reduces the amount of time required for final hand grinding in the prepara-  tion of thin sections.    REFERENCE  FitzPatrick, E.A., 1980. The Micromorphology of Soils. Dept. of Soil Science, Univ. of  Aberdeen, 186 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractA small hand-held device is described which enables an operator to grind soil thin sections very rapidly as compared to conventional hand grinding. The apparatus is relatively inexpensive and easy to construct as it comprises only a simple motorized grinder and grit impregnated discs 2.5 cm in diameter.