 Geoderma, 26 (1981) 311-322  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam - Printer: in the Netherlands 311    EFFECTS  pH AND ALLTMINILICATE COMPOSITION ON K-Mg EXCHANGE SELECTIVITY OF AMORPHOUS ALUMINOSILICATES    K.W. PERROTT    Ruakura Soil and Plant Research Station, Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, Private Bag, Hamilton (New Zealand)    (Received January, 1981; accepted July 5, 1981;    ABSTRACT    Perrott, K.W., 1981. Effects of pH and aluminosilicate composition on K-Mg exchange  selectivity of amorphous aluminosilicates. Geoderma, 26: 312-322.     The K-Mg ration exchange selectivity of some allophanic soil clays, imogolite and a range of synthetic hydrous oxides and amorphous aluminosilicates was studied using solutions 0.45N with respect to KCl and MgClz. The preference of the aluminosilicates for Mg2+ increased with pH, which is in qualitative agreement with the predictions based on double-layer theory. Large quantitative discrepancies indicated, however, specific interaction of potassium with aluminosilicates of low and intermediate Al/(AI + Si) molar ratio. The potassium selectivity of these materials probably arises from swelling-pressure effects and steric restriction on the entry of the larger hydrated Mg2* into channels in the alumosilicate aggregates. Hydrous oxides of iron and aluminium were found to specifically adsorb magnesiuyv at alkaline pH values and evidence indicates that specific adsorption by these materials also occurred in soil clays and in Fe(N03)3-created synthetic aluminosilates.    INTRODUCTION     Many investigations have been made of ration exchange equilibria in soils and soil clays. Only a few of these, however, have dealt with amorphous clays or with soils containing these clays. Hunsaker and Pratt (1971) found a preference by allophane for Cal' in Ca-Mg exchange equilibria and other studies have shown a preference by soils containing allophane for divalent rations over monovalent canons (Gessa,1970; Galindo and Bingham, 1977; Arshad et x1.,1972).   The surface charge properties of amorphous aluminosilicates are strongly dependent on solution concentration and pH (Wada and Harward,1974) and aluminosilicate composition (Perrott,1977a). Cation exchange equilibria of soils containing amorphous aluminosilicates are also affected by pH (During, 1973b; Schalscha et x1.,1975) and the variable composition of allophane could be a cause of the variation in cwtion~-exchange selectivity ob served with allophanic soils (During, 1973x).    0016-70611/0000-0000/$02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company  312     This paper reports the results of an investigation into the effect of pH and aluminosilicate composition on the cation exchange selectivity of some soil clays containing allophane and synthetic amorphous aluminosilicates and hydrous oxides using the K+ -Mg" cation pair.    EXPERIMENTAL     The synthetic aluminosilicates were prepared by the simultaneous hydrolysis of aluminium isopropoxide and methyl silicate (Rajah and Perrott, 1975). Hydrous alumina and silica were prepared by the separate hydrolysis of the respective reagents and goethite was prepared as described by Forties et al. (1974).   Allophanic soil clays (&lt;2 um) were obtained by gravitational sedimentation after ultrasonic dispersion of samples from the subsoil of Wai sandy loam ('Vitric ~ ndept) and an allophanic bed in the Hamilton .Ash Formation at Te Akatea (i'errott, 7.977a). Imogolite (&lt;1 gym) was similarly extracted (using a suspension pH of 4) from gel films separated from the Kurayoshi pumice bed (Yoshinagai and Yamaguchi, 1970). After flocculation of these three clays with NaCI, half of the material obtained in each case was dialyzed against distilled water until free from chloride and freeze-dried (Perrott, 1.7b). The remaining material was treated with citrate-dhionitebicarbonate and 2% NaL,2C03 to remove free oxides (Jackson, 1956). After washing, the treated clays were dialyzed and freeze-dried.   The synthetic and natural samples were characterized as described by Perrott (1977a). Specific surface areas were also determined by water adsorption using the BET equation (Orehiston,1953; Quirk, 1955).   Cation exchange selectivity was measured by a method similar to that of Dolcater et al. (1968). .Approximately 0.2 g of each sample was washed three times with 1N NaCI followed by three washings with a mixed solution, 0.05N with respect to ICI and MgC12. Suspensions in this mixed solution were adjusted to the desired pH value which was maintained for 1 h, by addition of HCl or KOH controlled by an automatic titrator (RadiometerCopenhagen) used in the pH-stat mode. A salt bridge containing the 0.05N KCl-MgC12 solution was used with the calomel reference electrode to prevent contamination with excess KCI. The samples were then transferred to 15 ml conical centrifuge tubes and washed seven more times with the 0.05N KCl-MgCl2 solution and the pH adjustment repeated. The amounts of HCl or KOH required for this final pH adjustment were very small and did not significantly change the K+ and Mg2+ concentrations in the final equilibration solutions. After centrifuging, the exchangeable adsorbed K+ and Mg" and the entrained solution were displaced by five 10 ml washes with 0.2M Ca(N03).2 and the centrifuge tubes and their contents then dried at 105 to constant weight. The oven-dried sample weights were calculated by substracting the dry weights of the tube and the entrained Ca(N03)Z.   The displaced K+ and Mg2+ were determined by flame emission and atomic  TABLE I    Characteristics of synthetic aluminosilicates and hydrous oxides    Sample w SiOz A1z03 Fe 20, Al Specific surface area Mineralogy   (%)*s (%)*2 (%)*x AI+Si (mZg ')      molar N2 H2p      ratio adsorption adsorption  SA-70 61.0 21.5 0 0.29 190 296 Amorphous  SA-60 47.6 32.8 0 0.45 272 343 Amorphous  SA-50 38.5 41.0 0 0.56 278 322 Amorphous  SA-40 31.2 47.8 0 0.64 357 459 Amorphous  SA-15 11.7 66.0 0 0.87 264 262 Amorphous + trace of          pseudoboehmite  Hydrous A1243 0 72.9 0 1.00 231 214 Bayerite +          pseudoboehmite  Hydrous Si02 85.6 0 0 0 - -  Amorphous  Goethite 0 0 83.3 - -  54 Goethite    'The number following SA- indicates the approximate Si02 content (100 SiOz%)   (S2%+A1203%) *2Mass percent (g/100 g). Chemical analyses and surface areas expressed on oven-dry (105C) basis.    w w  W N    TABLE II    Characteristics of sail clays _    Clay SiOz A1z03 Fe203 A1 Specific Mineralogy   (%)*' (%)*' (%)*~ A1+Si surface area      molar (m2g-.I        )      rato Hz0 adsorption    Te Akatea 33.4 35.4 5.2 0.56 546 Allophane + trace of        imogolite  Waihi 33.7 30.2 9.6 0.51 249 Allophane + small        amount of        imogolite  Imogolite 24.1 38.2 3.1 0.65 469 Imogolite  Iron oxide free clays  Ta Akatea 35.5 35.7 0.4 0.54 493  Waihi 42.4 30.6 1.9 0.46 212  Imogolite 27.6 40.9 0.4 0.64 478    * 1Mass percent (g 100/g) Chemical analyses and surface areas expressed on over-dry (105C) basis.  315    absorption spectrometry, respectively, and values for the adsorbed K+ and  'VIg2+ exchanged obtained by subtraction of the amounts in the entrained  l~Cl-0, solution. The equivalent fraction of exchangeable Mg2+ adsorbed  was calculated from:    (%) _ Mg adsorbed  100 equiv. Mg2+ exchanged    equiv. Mg 2+ exchanged + equiv. K+ exchanged    RESULTS     The results of the analysis and characterization of the synthetic samples and the soil clays are given in Tables I and II.    Effect o f pH     As can be seen in Figs. 1 and 2 the preference for Mg2+ of the untreated samples increased with pH. Hydrous alumina and goethite dice not adsorb K+ at any pH value but did adsorb Mg2+ at pli 5.5 and above, the amount adsorbed increasing with pH (Table III).    100   80,o' b__~__  o- -~,.,or~r    60 ~ SA-70 - 5~~ A-6 _  0     40- Hydrous Si02  Q-  20    0 ~i  o i i o ~~ n n n n  ~ o e   4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 7 8  N  `100   60  40- SA-5e SA-40  SA-15  20    4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 78      pH  --o- 1   2  __.a.__ 3    Fig. 1. Effect of pH on the equivalent fraction of exchangeable Mgz+ adsorbed by hydrous silica and synthetic amorphous aluminosilicates. Mg adsorbed (%) = 100 equiv. Mg" exchanged    equiv. Mg2* exchanged + equiv. K* exchanged    1= untreated samples; 2 = Fe(NO,)3-treated samples; 3 = Eriksson equation.  316    TABLE III    Adsorption of rations (mequiv/100 g) by hydrous alumina and goethe    pH Hydrous A1103 Goethite   Mg 2+ K+ Mgz+  5.5 + 0.3 -0.3 + 2.5 -0.8  7.0 + 5.0 -1.5 + 9.4 -0.7  8.0 +25.4 -0.8 +16.9 -1.0    100  80     60  1,3 40  20    0    rI  i    rr'  r    ~r  r r    Imogolite    Waihi    :~ J    _e AKatea    4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 7 8 4 5 6 78    1  - 2  _,o___ 3    pH    Fig. 2. Effect of pH on the equivalent of exchangeable Mgz* adsorbed by soil clays. 1 = untreated soil clays; 2 = Clays treated with citrate-dithionite-bicarbonate and 2% Na2C03 reagents; 3 = Eriksson equation.    Effect of aluminosilicate composition   A comparison of the results presented in Fig. 1 indicates that the synthetic almninosilicates of high Al/(Al + Si) ratio show a greater preference for Mg2+ than those of low Al/(Al + Si) ratio. The plots in Fig. 3 confirm this at pH values of 7 and 8. At the lower pH values the more aluminous samples do not have any cation exchange capacity (Perrott,1977a).    100     80 ~ 60 4.0  20  0    pH 8    pH 5U.5,,  EP    O    77~b I    0 2 4 6 .8 0 2 .4 6 .8 0 24 .6 .8 1.0    -o   2  ___p___ 3    Composition (A'/(AI +Si 3!    Fig. 3, Effect of aluminosilicate composition on the equivalent fraction of exchangeable Mg" adsorbed. 1 = untreated samples; 2 = Fe(N03)3-treated samples; 3 = Eriksson equation. Black squares: Waihi clay. White squares: Te Akatea clay.  317     The natural soil allophanes Te Akatea and Waihi showed a greater preference for Mg" than synthetic aluminosicates with the same Al/(Al + Si) ratio (Fig. 3). Although treatment to remove iron oxides decreased the preference for Mg" relative to the untreated clays at high pH values and increased it at low pH values, in the case of imogolite the deferrated sample had a lower preference for Mg" than the untreated sample at all pH values (Fig. 2).   Addition of hydrous iron oxide to the synthetic aluminosilicates by treatment with 1M Fe(N03)3 followed by washing, dialysis and freeze-drying increased the preference for Mg" for all the samples (Figs. 1 and 3). The Fe203contents of these samples are given in Table IV.    TABLE IV    Iron contents of Fe(N03)3-treated aluminosilicates    Sample Fe20.   (%)m  SA-70 2.8  SA-60 17.1  SA-50 30.5  SA-40 26.9  SA-15 29.9    *'Mass percent (g/100 g). Figures expressed on oven-dry (105C ) basis.    DISCUSSION     All the materials studies have pH-dependent surface charges. The cation exchange capacity, and hence the surface-negative charge density, increases with pH (Perrott,1977a). Eriksson (1952) derived an equation relating the replaceability of monovalent cations in monovalent-divalent cation exchange on clay minerals to the surface charge density of the exchanger. The equation  a simplified form as given by Bolt (1955) is:    r sink-' r    rr +4Yc\/CZ    in which T is the surface charge density of the exchanger in mequiv/cmz; i' 1/I` is the fraction of the surface charge that is neutralised by the sum of the excess of the monovalent cations and the deficit of the monovalent anions close to the surface; r = C,/,1-C.2(mol/1)'/Z where C, and C2 are the bulk bulk concentrations of the monovalent and divalent cations, respectively; = 1.06 X 10-IS cm/mmol at 25; and V,, is usually taken as 1, based on double-layer theory, this equation predicts an increase in the replaceability  318    of the monovalent rations as the surface charge density is increased.   Several workers have found good agreement between their experimental results and the predictions of the Erikssor equation, providing the surface charge densities for each soil or clay were multiplied by a correction factor, ranging from 1.0 to 2.1 (Bolt, 1955; Bower, 1959; Pratt et al., 1962). The necessity for a correction factor has been attributed to the size of the hydrated ion (Bolt, 1955; Bower, 1959) as well as the inclusion in the measured surface area of surfaces not contributing to the ration exchange capacity and also to specific effects (Pratt et a1.,1962). Galindo and Bingham (1977) obtained results for K+-Ca2+ and K+-Mgz+ exchange on three Chilean Andepts containing allophane which were in qualitative agreement with the predictions of the Eriksson equation.   The plots of the equivalent fraction of exchangeable Mgz+ adsorbed vs pH in Figs. 1 and 2 show the qualitative trend of increasing Mg2+ adsorption with pH predicted by the Eriksson equation. The quantitative discrepancies (compare solid and dashed plots in Figs. 1, 2 and 3) are far larger, however, than those found by Pratt et al. (1962), except in the case of SA-15 where a correctio=i factor of 2.2 was found necessary. These results indicate that most samples have a far greater selectivity for potassium than would be expected from effects dine to valence and ionic size, indicating a specific interaction between K+ and the aluminosilicates. Fig. 3 shows that the specific effects are greatest in the more siliceous aluminosicates and decrease with an increase in the AlAl + Si) ratio.   Van Reeuwijk aiid de Villiers (1968), who studied the effect of aluminosilicate composition on the fixation of potassium against exchange by Mg'+ and other rations, found greater fixation of potassium in the more siliceous samples. Their results indicated a steric influence on potassium fixation which they attributed to the mechanical sieve action of channels in the gel structure. The likely existence in soil allophanes of such channels or interstitial pores capable of exerting a steric influence on the adsorption of rations was shown by Thong (1972) for NH4 and a range of n-alkylammonium rations. Kozak and Huang (1971) who studied K-Ca ration exchange selectivity proposed a similar effect to explain the increased K selectivity when clay minerals were treated to produce hydroxy-aluminium interlayers. They suggested that hydroxy-aluminium polymers in the interlayer had a "retarding effect" on the entry of the hydrated Cal' ions compared with the smaller hydrated K+ ions.   The existence in the aluminosilicates used in this work of channels likely to have a steric influence on K-Mg ration exchange selectivity can be inferred from the values of specific surface area given in Table I. Although the values determined by N2 and HZO adsorption are very close for S A-15 and hydrous alumina, there are very large differences with the other synthetic aluminosilicates. The surface areas of allophanic clays determined by absorption of polar liquids are usually much greater than those determined by low temperature nitrogen adsorption and Aomine and 4tsuka (196 s) suggested  319    that N2 adsorption values represent "external" surfaces whereas H20 adsorption measures "internal" surfaces, inaccessible to nitrogen molecules, as well as the external surfaces. Such internal surfaces could be in channels or terspaces of aluminosilicate aggregates and some of these could be inaccessible to the larger hydrated cations as well as to N2 molecules. The surface area values indicate that these channels occur in those synthetic aluminosilicates which exhibit a greater selectivity for K+ than expected from their surface charge density.   Where Van Reeuwijk and de Villiers (1968) measured K+ retained against exchange with other cations , the selectivity observed in this work involved K+ which could still be replace by Ca 21 (K+ remaining in the sample after washing with Ca(N03)2was not determined in most cases). Because of the smaller size of the hydrated Ca2+ compared with the hydrated Mg2+ cation, some of the K+ in sites inaccessible to Mg` may have been measured, but Ca 2+ could not have replaced all such K+. Van Reeuwijk and de Villiers (1968) found for a range of aluminosilicate compositions and pH values that in most cases less than 5% of K+ adsorbed by hydrogels was retained against extraction with l.l1l CaC12. The retention of non-exchangeable K+ and Mg2+ in the present work was determined on the samples used for cation exchange selectivity measurements at pH 8. These samples were analysed for K and Mg after Ca(N03)2 extraction using a LiB02 fusion method (Boar and Ingram, 1970). The proportions of K+ and Mg2+ in a non-exchangeable form depended on the aluminosilicate composition. Although up to 15% of the retained K+ was non-exchangeable in the samples of low Al/(Al + Si) ratio, this proportion was only 5% in the samples of more intermediate composition. The proportion of retained Mg2+ in a non-exchangeable form was 6% or less except for the samples with a high Al/(Al + Si) ratio where it reached 20%.   Because of the gel-like nature of the amorphous aluminosilicates, the observed selectivity could also arise from swelling-pressure effects similar to those observed with ion exchange resins (Helfferich,1962, p. 160). Swellingpressure effects would be expected in those samples containing "internal" surfaces or channels and would lead to a preference for the cation with a smaller hydrated equivalent volume which is in line with the observed results.   Hydrous alumina and goethite adsorbed only Mg2+ at the pH values used in this work. This adsorption occurs at pH values below the point of zero charge for both the hydrous alumina X9.3, Rajan et al., 1974) and the goethe (7.6, Forbes et a1.,1974), indicating specific adsorption. Kinniburgh et al. (1976) also found strong specific adsorption of Mg` and other divalent cations by iron and aluminium hydrous oxide gels. The adsorption increased with pH and was riot observed below pH 6.0. Similar results were obtained by Huang and Stumm (1973) with hydrous y-A1203. It is possible that some specific adsorption of Mg2+ occurs at aluminium-hydroxy sites in the amorphous  aluminosilicates, particularly in the more aluminous samples. ,  Magnesium may also be retained by the formation of mixed Mg-Al  320    hydroxide. Hunsaker and Pratt (1970) found this to occur at alkaline pH values when hydrous aluminium oxide or allophane was present. Unless the mixed Mg-Al hydroxide redissolves during the Ca(N03)2extraction,, however, Mg" retained by this mechanism would not be measured by the method used.   The increase in the Mg" selectivity of the synthetic aluminosilicates on treatment with Fe(N03)3 could be due to specific adsorption of Mg" by iron-hydroxy material. This would not operate at low pH values, however, and additional mechanism such as altered steric and swelling pressure effects, and/or the blocking of specific adsorption sites for K+ by the iron-hydroxy material in the Fe(N03)3-treated samples must be postulated. Similarly, although the decrease in the Mg" selectivity at higr pH values of the soil clays after citrate-dithionite-bicarbonate and 2% sodium carbonate treatments is consistent with the removal of hydrous oxides of iron and aluminium, the different effects observed at low pH values may be due to the alteration of steric and swelling-pressure effects as a result of chemical attack on the allophane. In the case of ogolite there would be less chemical attack on the mineral structure itself because of its more ordered character. This treatment may, however, release sites for specific adsorption of K+ by removal of surface hydrous ox' pies. Where is also the possibility that some of the material dissolved during the citrate-dithionite-bicarbonate and 2% Na2C03 treatments is reprecipitated on washing (Arshad et al., 1972). This could explain the results obtained with the Te Akatea and Waihi soil clays if the reprecipitated material blocked some of K+-selective adsorption sites in the allophanic clay.    CONCLUSIONS     The synthetic amorphous aluminosilicates of low and medium AlAl + Si) ratio show a much greater selectivity for potassium than would be expected from valence and ionic size effects predicted by double-layer theory. Other work suggests that this selectivity may be due to steric effects in which channels in the aluminosilicate structure restrict the entry of the larger hydrated Mgt+. The observed selectivity can also be explained by swellgpressure effects. Specific adsorption of magnesium by hydrous oxides occurs at alkaline pH values. Aluminium-hydroxy material  the more aluminous aluminosilicates may also specifically adsorb magnesium. Specific adsorption of magnesium on hydrous oxides of iron and aluminium will also occur in soils at these pH values. These hydrous oxides probably also affect the cation exchange selectivity at lower pH values by blocking potassium selective sites andr influencing the steric and swelling-pressure effects involved in the exchange.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS     Thanks are due to the staff of the Spectrochemical Laboratory, Ruakura  321    Soil and Plant Research Station, Ruakura Agricultural Research Centre for  assistance with chemical analyses and to Dr N. Yoshinaga, Department of  Agricultural Chemistry, Ehirne University, Japan for the kind gift of a sample  of imogolite gel films from the Rurayoshi pumice bed.    REFERENCES    Aomine, S. and Otsuka, H., 1968. Surface of soil allophanic clays. Trans. 9th Conger. Int. Soil Sci. Soc., Vol. I, pp. 731-737.  Arshad, M.A., Huang, P.M. and St. Arnaud, R.J., 19 7 2. Effects of some chemical treatments on K/Ca canon exchange selectivity of layer silicates. Can. J. Soil Sci., 52: 151-161.  Boar, P.L. and Ingram, L.K., 1970. The comprehensive analysis of coal ash and silicate rocks by atomic-absorption spectrophotometry by a fusion technique. Analyst, 95: 124-130.  Bolt, G.H., 1955. Ion adsorption by clays. Soil Sci., 79: 267-276.  Bower, C.A., 1959. Cation exchange equilibria in soils affected by sodium salts. Soil Sci., 88: 32-35.  Dolcater, D.L., Lotse, E.G., Syers, J.K. and Jackson, M.L., 1968. Cation exchange selectivity of some clay-sized minerals and soil materials. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 795-798.  During, C., 1973a. The effective relative affinity for magnesium and potassium of some soils from North Island, New Zealand. N.Z. J. Agric. Res., 16: 1-8.  During, C., 1973b. Cation exchange capacity at field pH and its relation to the affinity of soils for individual cations. N.Z. J. Agric. Res., 16: 415-422.  Eriksson, E., 1952. Cation exchange equilibria on clay minerals. Soil Sci., 74: 103-113.  Forbes, E.A., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1974. The specific adsorption of inorganic Hg(II) species and Co(III) complex ions on goethite. J. Colloid Interface Sci., 49: 403-409.  Galindo, G.G. and Bingham, F.T., 1977. Homovalent and heterovalent cation exchange equilibria in soils with variable surface charge. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 883-886.  Gessa, C., 1970. Lo scambio Ca-K sui materials allofanici. Agrochimica, 14: 188-197.  Helfferich, F., 1962. Ion Exchange. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y.  Huang, C.P. and Stumam, W., 1973. Specific adsorption of cations on hydrous y-A1z03. J. Colloid Interface Sci., 43: 409-420.  Hunsaker, V.E. arid Pratt, P.F., 1970. The formation of mixed magnesium-aluminium hydroxides in soil materials. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 813-816.  Hunsaker, V.E. and Pratt, P.F., 1971. Calcium-magnesium exchange equilibria in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 151-152.  Jackson, M.L., 1956. Soil Chemical Analysis - advanced course. (Third printing 1967.) Published by the author, Department of Soil Science, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis.  Kinniburgh, D.G., Jackson, M.L. and Syers, J.K., 1976. Adsorption of alkaline earth, transition, and heavy metal cations by hydrous oxide gels of iron and aluminium. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 796-799.  Kozak, L.M. and Huang, P.M., 19? 1. Adsorption of hydroxy-AI by certain phyllosilicates and its relation to K/Ca cation exchange selectivity. Clays Clay Miner., 19: 95-102.  Orchiston, H.D., 1953. Adsorption of water vapour, I. Soil at 25. Soil Sci., 76: 453-465.  Perrott, K.W., 1977a. Surface charge characteristics of amorphous aluminosilicates. Clays Clay Miner., 25: 417-421.  Perrott, K.W., 1.977b. Freeze-drying of soil clays. Geoderma, 17: 219-224.  322    Pratt, P.F., Whitidg, L.I3. and Grover, B.L., 1962. Effect of pH on the sodium-calcium exchange equilibria in soil. Soil Sc 3oc. Am. Proc., 26: 227-230.  Quirk, J.P., 1955. Significance of surface areas calculated from water vapour sorption isotherms by use of the B.E.T. equation. Soil Sci., 80: 423-430.  Rajah, S.S.S. and Perrott, K.W., 1975. Phosphate adsorption by synthetic amorphous aluminosilicates. J. Soil Sci., 26: 257-266.  Rajah, S.S.S., Perrott, K.W. and Saunders, W.M.H., 1974. Identification of phosphatereacte sites of hv,irous alumina from proton consumption during phosphate adsorption at co:-istant pH values. J. Soil Sci., 25: 438-447.  Schalscha, E.B., Pratt, P.F. and de Andrade, L., 1975. Potassium-calcium exchange equilibria in volcanic ash soils. Soil $ci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 1069-1072.  Theng, B.K.G., 1972. Adsorption of ammonium and some n-alkylammonm cations by soil allophane. Nature, 238: 150-151.  Van Reeuwijk, L.P. and de Villiers, J.M., 1968. Potassium fixation by amorphous aluminosilicate gels. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 238-240.  VUada, K. and Harvard, M.E., 1974. Amorphous clay constituents of soils. Adv. Agron., 26: 211-260.  Yoshinaga, N. and Yamaguchi, M., 1970. Occurrence of imogolite as gel film in the pumice and scoria beds of Western and Central Honshu and Hokkaido. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 16: 215-223.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractThe KMg cation exchange selectivity of some allophanic soil clays, imogolite and a range of synthetic hydrous oxides and amorphous aluminosilicates was studied using solutions 0.05N with respect to KCl and MgCl2. The preference of the aluminosilicates for Mg2+ increased with pH, which is in qualitative agreement with the predictions based on double-layer theory. Large quantitative discrepancies indicated, however, specific interaction of potassium with aluminosilicates of low and intermediate Al/(Al + Si) molar ratio. The potassium selectivity of these materials probably arises from swelling-pressure effects and steric restriction on the entry of the larger hydrated Mg2+ into channels in the aluminosilicate aggregates. Hydrous oxides of iron and aluminium were found to specifically adsorb magnesium at alkaline pH values and evidence indicates that specific adsorption by these materials also occurred in soil clays and in Fe(NO3)3-treated synthetic aluminosilicates. 