 Geoderrna, 34 (1984) 37--42                                                         37  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CHARACTERIZING THE SOIL MOISTURE REGIME OF A TYPIC  HAPLOHUMOD    L.W. DEKKER, J.HaM. W()STEN and J. BOUMA  Soil Survey Institute (Stiboka), Box 98, 6700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Received December 6, 1983; revised version accepted June 19, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Dekker, L.W., WSsten, J.H.M. and Bouma, J., 1984. Characterizing the soil moisture  regime of a Typic Haplohumod. Geoderma, 34: 37--42.    The saturated hydraulic conductivities (Ksat) of 22 spodic horizons with and without  a thin iron pan, were measured in situ with a new technique, using large, carved-out  columns, encased in gypsum. Measured infiltration rates and pressure heads above and  below the spodic horizons allowed calculation of Ksat, which averaged 8 cm d-1. Flow  rates averaged 32 cm d-1, however, due to a hydraulic head gradient across the spodic  horizon of 4 cm cm-1. Occurrence of a thin iron pan in the spodic horizon did not affect  its Ksat-value. The measured high flow rates exclude the occurrence of perched water-  tables. Lateral flow of water, forming surface ponds in local depressions, was due to sur-  face runoff, rather than to lateral movement of perched water: surface ponding of water  occurred also in soils in which the spodic horizon had been mixed by tillage.    INTRODUCTION    Spodic horizons in sands are believed to have low permeabilities (e.g.,  Stahr, 1973; De Bakker, 1979). This low permeability could cause seasonally  perched water-tables and lateral flow of water on top of the spodic horizon  to adjacent lower areas. Such a mechanism has in fact been proposed to ex-  plain the occurrence of surface ponding of water in landscape depressions in  areas with softs having clearly developed spodic horizons. Perched water  tables"are also associated with relatively high water contents in the surface  layer of~soil, which result in a relatively low trafficability.  Removal or disruption of the spodic horizon would therefore have several  potential'benefits. Surface ponding of water in landscape depressions would  be reduced and trafficability would be improved in soils of the higher eleva-   tions due to better vertical drainage. These benefits are, of course, based on  the assumption that the permeability of the spodic horizon is sufficiently  low to allow formation of a perched water-table. Measurements to support  this assumption are, however, not available.  This study is concerned with a test of this assumption by developing a  proper method for measuring the saturated hydraulic conductivities (Ksat) of    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    38    spodic horizons and by applying them under field conditions. In addition,  processes of lateral flow and vertical drainage were characterized by field  measurement in a Typic Haplohumod, comparing soils with undisturbed  spodic horizons and soils in which the spodic horizon had been broken by  deep tillage.    MATERIALS AND METHODS  Soils    A description of a representative soil profile follows (De Bakker, 1979).  Analytical data are presented in Table I.    TABLEI    Analytical data for a Typic Haplohumod    Horl-   Depth    Fe203    pH--  Or~anlc  zon    (cm)     (%)      KCI   matter  (%)    Particle-size distribution of mineral f~act/on  (% of fine earth)    &lt;2  2--50  50--105 105--150  &gt; 150  &gt; 300#m    AI       0--  5  0.18      3.6   I0.I      2      4.5     10.5      20          63  A2      I0-- 15  0.02      3.8     1.7      0.5    3.5     11.5      20          64.5  B2h    18-- 20  0.13      3.9     9.2      0      5.5     10        19          65.5  B22    25-- 30  0.65      4.4     3.3      1.5   2.5     11.5      20          64.5  B3      50-- 75  0.32      4.6     0.6      0      1        I0        20          69  C       90--100  0.32      4.6     0,5      0      1.5     10        19          69.5    9.5    01    3--  0 cm  A1    0--  5 cm  A2    5-- 18 cm    B2h  18-- 23 cm    B22 23-- 40 cm    B3   40-- 80 cm    Black (10YR 3/2) organic matter, mainly composed of  recognizable plant remains.  Black (10YR 3/2) fine sand; single grain; abrupt, smooth  boundary.  Grey (10YR 5/1) fine sand, strongly bleached; single  grain; loose; abrupt, smooth, locally irregular boundary  when "pockets" of A2 go down to 40 cm depth.  Black (7.5YR 2/1) fine sand; dispersed organic matter  has filled nearly all pores (after ignition this illuvial  horizon turns white); massive; firm, hard; on the bound-  ary between the black and the brown B a thin (1--2  mm) iron pan occurs, very abrupt, smooth boundary.  This thin iron pan does not qualify as a placic horizon  (Soil Survey Staff, 1975), as discussed by De Bakker  (1979).  Dark reddish brown (5YR 2/3) fine sand, coated with  humus and iron (turns red on ignition). Many wavy  lamellae with thicker humus coatings; when removed  the soil crushes very easily to single grain; loose; diffuse,  smooth boundary to the:  very gradual transition, humus coatings becoming thin-    39    C    80--120 cm  plus    ner with depth, thus exposing the yellowish colour of  the iron coatings.  Light yellowish brown (10YR 6/4) sand; single grain;  loose.    The B2h horizon qualifies as a spodic horizon.    Measurement of the saturated hydraulic conductivity (Ksat)    The measurement of Ksat in a cemented soil horizon such as a B2h (spodic  horizon) is difficult. Undisturbed cores cannot be sampled because the hori-  zon will be fractured. Pushing infiltrometers or augers into the horizon has  the same effect. Because of these problems, a method, which was applied  successfully in clay soils with large peds (Bouma et al., 1979), was modified  to be used in this context. The method overcomes particular limitations im-  posed by soil conditions (Bouma, 1983) and comprises the following four  stages.  (1) A large cylindrical soil column (Fig. 1) with a diameter of 30 cm and a  height of at least 30 cm is carved out in situ. The upper surface of the  column occurs at approximately 10 cm above the B2h horizon. Thus, part  of the A2 horizon is included in the column. This arrangement is necessary to  allow placement of a closed cylinder infiltrometer on top of the column in  uncemented sand. Carving of the column through the B2h and B2ir horizons  should be done with great care, avoiding fracturing of the soil mass. Use of a  small, sharp knife is most effective for chipping away small fragments. The  column should extend well into the underlying, loose B3 horizon. This im-  plies a column height of 30--40 cm.    iiii iiiii!iiiiiiiiiiiiiiii iii iiii!iii{!iiiiii  ii iiiiiiiii!ii iiiii!iiiiiiiiii!iiii! iii           1    W = water  a = air vent  b = burette with mariotte device  T = transducer with two tensiometers  G = gypsum collar    Fig. 1. Cross-section of the experimental set-up, used to measure Ksat of spodic horizons.    40    (2) A closed-top cylinder infiltrometer is carefully fitted on top of the  column, ensuring close contact between the inner wall of the infiltrometer  and the soil. The infiltrometer is levelled. One small tensiometer is placed  below the B2h and B2ir horizon and another above the B2h horizon.  (3) A thick gypsum slurry is poured around the column into an encase-  ment which allows a wall thickness of at least 5 cm. The encasement is re-  moved after hardening of the gypsum. The gypsum slurry can also be applied  around the column by hand. Tensiometer tubings will then protrude from  the gypsum wall. Another possibility is to place the tensiometers in the soil  after applying the gypsum. Then, holes have to be drilled through the wall  well into the soil column.  (4) A burette with mariotte-device is placed next to the encased column.  The infiltrometer is filled with water and a shallow, constant hydraulic head  of a few millimetres is maintained on top of the column. The infiltration  rate into the column and pressure heads below and above the B2h horizon  are measured.  Saturated hydraulic conductivities were also measured in undisturbed  A1/A2, B3 and C horizons and in disturbed soil horizons which formed after  deep-plowing of the B2h. These measurements were made in large plastic  cylinders with a height and inner diameter of 20 cm. The cylinders were  filled by first carving out a column of soil in situ with a slightly larger dia-  meter than the cylinder. Next, the cylinder was gently pushed onto the  column until it was entirely filled. Measurements of Ksat were made by  monitoring steady outflow under shallow ponding conditions at a gradient  of the hydraulic head of 1 cm cm-1. The calculation of Ksat for the B2h and  B2ir horizons is more complicated because the in situ columns consisted of  different horizons with quite contrasting conductivities.  To calculate Ksat, four values were needed: (1) the steady infiltration rate  into the soil column (q cm d-l); (2) the positive pressure head on top of the  B2h (h cm); (3) the negative pressure head below the B2h (or B2ir) (-h cm);  and (4) the thickness of the horizon {z cm).  Ksat is calculated as follows: Ksat = q dz/dH, where: dH = difference in  hydraulic head across the horizon with thickness z being considered (cm).  Measurements were made at five different locations.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Hydraulic conductivities    Hydraulic conductivity measurements are summarized in Table II. Ksat-  values of soil horizons occurring below the cemented B2 horizons were very  high, exceeding 1000 cm d-1. A wide range of Ksat-values was found for the  surface horizons (01 + A1 + A2) in undisturbed soils. The lower values were  associated with sites in minor depressions in the landscape, where surface  runoff was accumulating. This process is associated with sedimentation of    41    TABLE II  Measured saturated hydraulic conductivity (Ksat) values for major horizons in a Typic  Haphohumod. Ksat-values for the B2h and B2ir horizons were calculated from infiltration  rates and measured gradients of the hydraulic head    Depth        Horizon            Ksat  (em)                              (cm d-1)    Undisturbed  0-- 20      01+A1+A2  20-- 45       B2h + B2ir  15-- 4O    B2h  40-- 85       (B22) + B3 + C1    Disturbed  0-- 20  20-- 50  50-- 80  80--100    1, 4, 5, 6, 13, 32, 48, 51, 57, 68, 140, 288  1, 3,  3, 4,  5,  5,  5,  9,  10,  11,  11,  14,  18  3, 5, 5, 7, 8, 9, 11, 18, 18  1000,  1100,  1400,  1400,  1700,  2300,  3400    200,250,260,270  200,280,650,780,960  840,980,1060,1200,1200  1400,3200    fine organic debris, causing plugging of soil pores and lower Ksat-values.  Deep plowing resulted in a strong increase of Ksat at levels where B hori-  zons did occur previously.  The average pressure head above the B2h horizon was +8cm and the aver-  age pressure head below the B2 horizon was - 7 cm. Consequently, the average  gradient of the hydraulic head across the 5 cm thick B2h horizon was 4 cm  cm-1. Steady infiltration rates into in situ columns, containing B2h and B2ir  horizons, were thus approximately four times as high as the calculated Ksat-  values of these horizpns.  No significant difference was found between Ksat of columns containing  B2ir horizons below the B2h, as compared with columns containing only a  B2h horizon. Presence of a B2ir does, therefore, not imply occurrence of re-  duced Ksat-values.  Hydraulic conductivity of 5 cm d-1 is regarded under Dutch conditions  as a critical value, separating potentially ponding conditions from conditions  where ponding is unlikely. The cited rate is derived from an average winter-  rain intensity of 2 mm h-1. Using this reference value, ten out of twenty-two  measurements of Ksat in B2 horizons indicate some potential for the occur-  rence of perched water-tables. These B2 horizons on top of permeable sands  with deep water-tables, however, induce a flow system in which water is  sucked into the underlying soil horizons at a rate which is, on average, four  times higher than the calculated Ksat-value. Obviously, these rates are much  higher than the critical value cited. Occurrence of ponded water, forming  perched water-tables on top of the B2 horizon, is therefore unlikely. Perched  water-tables have indeed not been observed in the field.    42    Surface ponding of water    Lateral flow of water on top of the spodic horizon is unlikely to occur be-  cause of the measured vertical fluxes through this horizon. The observed sur-  face ponding of water in shallow depressions of the landscape must there-  fore be caused by another mechanism. Surface runoff occurs during heavy  rains in summer, even though Ksat of surface soil is relatively high (Table II).  Runoff is evidenced by large plant fragments having been transported and  sedimented in characteristic patterns downslope and further by the occur-  rence of a thin and dark-coloured sedimentary crust on the soil surface in  local depressions. This crust is composed of fine-grained organic and mineral  constituents, which plug the soil pores in the sand, causing a strong drop of  Ksat to levels of 1 cm d-1 and lower. Such levels are sufficiently low to cause  ponding of water. The runoff process, followed by sedimentation, occurs  quite rapidly. Surface ponding of water was already observed in land that  had been deep-plowed in the previous year.    REFERENCES    Bouma, J., 1983. Use of soil survey data to select measurement techniques for hydraulic  conductivity. Agric. Water Manage., 6 (2/3): 177--190.  Bouma, J., Dekker, L.W. and Haans, J.C.F.M., 1979. Drainability of some Dutch clay  soils: a case study of soil survey interpretation. Geoderma, 22: 193--203.  De Bakker, H., 1979. Major Soils and Soil Regions in The Netherlands. Pudoc, Wageningen/  Junk, Den Haag, 203 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy; a basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook 436.  Stahr, K., 1973. Der Einflusz eines Fe-B~indchen-Mikrohorizonts (thin iron pan) auf  den Wasser- und Lufthaushalt yon Mittelgebirgsb~den. Pseudogley and Gley. Trans-  actions of Commissions V and VI of the Int. Soc. Soil Sci., pp. 521--528.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               AbstractThe saturated hydraulic conductivities (Ksat) of 22 spodic horizons with and without a thin iron pan, were measured in situ with a new technique, using large, carved-out columns, encased in gypsum. Measured infiltration rates and pressure heads above and below the spodic horizons allowed calculation of Ksat, which averaged 8 cm d−1. Flow rates averaged 32 cm d−1, however, due to a hydraulic head gradient across the spodic horizon of 4 cm cm−1. Occurrence of a thin iron pan in the spodic horizon did not affect its Ksat-value. The measured high flow rates exclude the occurrence of perched watertables. Lateral flow of water, forming surface ponds in local depressions, was due to surface runoff, rather than to lateral movement of perched water: surface ponding of water occurred also in soils in which the spodic horizon had been mixed by tillage. 