Geoderma, 30 (1983) 243--252                                                     243  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed In The Netherlands    SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY OF ENGINEERING SOILS    K. COLLINS  Department of Ciwl Engineering, Unwerszty of Strathclyde, George Street, Glasgow,  Strathclyde (Great Brztain)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Collins, K., 1983. Scanning electron microscopy of engineering sods. Geoderma, 30"  243--252    Specimen preparation for the scanning electron microscopy of engineering soils is  vitally important. The usefulness of critical point drying is assessed on the basis of macro-  scopic and microscopic data obtained from the critical point drying and the air drying  of several natural undisturbed soft clays.  It is emphasised that scanning electron microscopy can play a valuable reconnaissance  role, thus providing an indication of the broad character of the soil microfabric, over a  wide range of magnification, which aids in the selection of the appropriate programme  and methods of quantification.  It is also demonstrated that scanning electron microscopy observations are extremely  useful m the interpretation of, and for providing the very necessary background to, quan-  titative data such as that yielded by optical thin section and mercury porosimetry studies    INTRODUCTION    The scanning electron microscope (SEM) is an extremely useful tool for  studying the microfabric of engineering soils. Several examples are given here  in order to give a brief indication of some of the roles which the SEM can  successfully fulfil, particularly with regard to combined micromorphological  studms.  Consideration, however, is firstly given to some of the advantages and dis-  advantages of the critical point drying technique applied to wet clays.    CRITICAL POINT DRYING    Prismatic specimens (10 mm10 mm 30 mm) of four natural undis-  turbed soft sediments were dried by the critical point drying technique and  also for comparative purposes by the slow air drying (20 ambient) meth-  od. Shrinkage measurements were made (Table I) and the fabrics of the dried  specimens studied using the SEM.  Critmal point drying, involved firstly the replacement of the pore water    0016-7061/83/$03 00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B V.    244  TABLE I  Shrinkage measurements on crltmal point and air drmd clays    Soil    Approximate volumetric shrinkage ( % )    Air dried         Critical point drmd    Direct            Graded  replacement      replacement    Cemented estuarme silty clay,  Ottawa, Canada                   36               2                6  San Francisco Bay marine mud,  USA                    41           2           8  Cemented lacustrine varved clay,  New Liskeard, Canada              30                6                 1  Lacustrine clay, New Orleans,  U S.A.                              marked           none             not tested  apparent    with methanol (both graded and direct replacement methods were used) fol-  lowed by the replacement of methanol with liquid carbon dioxide, which  was then taken to its critmal point which occurs at 31 and 73 atmospheres  pressure.  As shown in Table I, volumetric shrinkage was greatly reduced by crltmal  point drying (1--8%) compared to that reduced by air drying (30--40%).  Visual Inspection of the dried specimens, however, showed that some of the  critical point drmd specimens of each soil were cracked both longitudinally  and laterally. Specimens of the uncemented critical point dried clays from  San Francisco and New Orleans were particularly fragile and this presented  problems in fracturing, mounting and peehng of specimens for the SEM.  SEM observations on the dried specimens indicated that crltmal point  drying had preserved open random clay particle arrangements (Fig. la --  stereopair), whereas m the case of mr drying much denser, though still large-  ly lsotropic configurations, were in evidence wherein lndlwdual clay particles  were not always easily discerned (Fig. lb -- stereopalr). It was also clear,  however, that unlike air drying the methanol impregnation procedures had  induced extensive microcrackmg in many cases (Fig. 1, c and d). Further-  more, in the case of uncemented critical point dried clays, excessive silt grain  removal had occurred during the dry fracturing and fracture surface peeling  processes, as evidenced by the apparently extremely porous texture shown in  Fig. lc.  The two stage critical point drying techmque therefore, caused minimal  shrinkage of soft clays studied and succeeded, it would seem, m preserving    Fig. 1. SEM micrographs of New Orleans clay' (a) clay arrangements, crltmal point drmd  -- stereopair, (b) clay arrangements, air-dried -- stereopalr; (e) clay matrix, critical point  dried', (d) clay matrix, air-dried    245        100~m~                ~    I00~    246    0  "0  0  ~u  e~  0  0  0  0  ei    247    open clay particle configurations. On the other hand, it induced extensive  macro- and micro-cracking, which is, of course, a serious limitation. The  simple air-drying method, while inducing considerable densification, by no  means altered totally the overall microfabric character of the natural sedi-  ments. Indeed observations of the air&lt;tried specimens served very well to  complement those made on the critical point dried specimens.    A RECONNAISSANCE ROLE FOR THE SEM    The SEM in the normal emissive mode can be of immense value in asses-  sing, relatively quickly, the broad character of an engineering soil micro-  fabric over a vast range of magnification from 20 to X 50,000.  As recommended by Stoops (1974) the first step is to study SEM  mounted specimens prior to coating, under the stereomicroscope, to locate  features of interest.  The construction of SEM micrograph montages (Fig. 2) is then camed  out, initially at low magmfications of X 20 to 80 with zero tilt (this links  well with the stereoscope observations}, and subsequently at those higher  levels of magnification which seem appropriate. In this way, any fabric  heterogeneity or multi-level fabric characteristics can be fully appreciated.  Stereopairs (Fig. 3) are also extremely useful, not only as a guard against  misinterpretation, but also for gaining a clear impression of the mutual and  spatial arrangement of particular fabric features at all levels of magnification.  Using the above approach it is often possible to identify the microfabric  features which need to be quantified. For example, Figs. 2 and 3 are SEM  observations from an ongoing engineering study of an undisturbed heavily    Fig. 3. SEM stereopair of clay peds shown in Fig. 2.    248    compressed marine clay, which have revealed a pedal fabric. They have also  suggested the possibility of preferred orientation of interpedal pores m  places, and a variation m the degree and direction of preferred orientation of  the clay matrices wxthln the mdividual peds. It has been decided, therefore,  on the basis of these SEM observatmns, that optical thin section studies  should be carried out to study and, if possible to quantify these aspects. In  this way the overall microfabric anlsotropy could be assessed and related to  engineering behavlour    AN INTERPRETATIVE ROLE FOR THE SEM    SEM observations provide a clearer understanding of the data yielded by  quantitative techniques such as optical thin section (birefringence) and mer-  cury porosimetry.    Optical thin section microscopy    Krishnamurthy (1975) studied the fabrm of an lllite clay compressed from  a slurry and sheared. Using crossed nicols he measured an omentatlon ratio in  each case, defined as the ratio of the intensity of illumination at the extinc-  tion phase, to the intensity of illumination at the  umination phase, and  ratios of umty and zero represent random and perfect clay orientation, res-  pectively (Morgenstern and Tchalenko, 1967). Fig. 4a indicates a medium  degree of preferred orientation overall for the undisturbed lllite with areas  of near perfect orientation as well as highly random zones. SEM observations  by the author on the same clay confirmed the existence of near perfect  orientation (Fig. 4b) and revealed the turbostratic nature of the random  fabric zones (Fig. 4c). The term turbostratic describes the turbulent array of  parallel orientated clay platelets (Aylmore and Quirk, 1960). The disruptive  influence of clay aggregates (slurry features) which were present in the orig-  inal slurry and which have survived the compression process, can be clearly  seen (Fig. 4b). Fig. 5a indicates that upon shearing, randomness increases  over the entire section. This observation was confirmed by the SEM which  indicated an increase in the occurrence of turbostratic zones and which also  gave a clear insight into the nature of the shear zone which can be seen to be  extenmve (Fig. 5b) but extremely narrow (2 um across) and branched in  places (Fig. 5c).    Mercury porosimetry    Safiullah (1981) measured the pore size distributions of samples of a silty  clay from Glasgow, U.K., compacted to various water contents by the stan-    Fig. 4. Fabric of fllite compressed one-dimensionally under 300 kN/m2' (a) optical mea-  surements; (b) SEM micrographs showing clay aggregation and preferred orientation; (c)  SEM micrograph showing turbostratic clay.    249    0-2  Relotive  Frequency    AVERAGE RATIO  OVER    SECTION   OF     0   47    05         1  Orlentation Rotlo    ,--.,   lo~t    250    Relative  Frequency    025    AVERAGE RATIO  OVER  SECTION  OF  0 58    I-  I      1  O5    Orientation    1  Ratio    Fig. 5. Fabric of compressed illite sheared under drained plane strain conditions" (a) opti  cal measurements; (b) and (c) SEM micrographs of shear zone.    251    Cumulative  Mercury  Intrusion  cm3/gm    0-2    0.1    \~Wet ~ Proctor Optimum   --'--..Dry  of  Proctor  ~  imum  I       I~~'~'k I  0"01          1-0           100  Pore Diometer IJm     ~      101Jmj                      ',-',      10tlm,    Fig. 6. Fabric of compacted silty clays" (a) mercury porosimetry plots, Glasgow silty clay;  (b) SEM stereopair of Luanda silty clay, dry of optimum; (c) SEM stereopair of Luanda  silty clay, wet of optimum.    252    dard Proctor method The cumulative mercury Intrusion curves (Fig. 6a) in-  dicated that the fabrics of the dry and wet side of optimum samples were  different with the former showing a blmodal pore dlstmbutlon. SEM obser-  vations showed clearly that this was associated with an aggregated clay fabric'  and that the small and large modes related to mtra-aggregate and inter-  aggregate porosity, respectively. This aggregate type fabric can be observed  in Fig. 6b which is a stereopmr showing the fabric of a silty clay from  Luanda, Angola, compacted on the dry side of optimum. By compamson the  fabric of the wet side of optimum compacted sample is seen to comprise a  uniform clay matrix (Fig. 6c --stereopmr).    CONCLUDING  REMARKS    Critical point drying reduces shnnkage to a minimum but can often in-  duce cracking and specimen fragility. It is suggested here that any drying  technique may introduce artefacts and that therefore as a matter of routine,  a number of drying methods should be employed in parallel. For example,  critical point drymg and mr drying can usefully complement one another in  the study of soft clays.  SEM observations over a full range of magnification from 20 to 50,000,  employmg montage and stereophotography, can provide a useful basis for a  more detailed and possibly quantitative structural analysis using some of the  other study techniques available. The SEM can then be employed m parallel  with such techniques in order to provide the often very necessary back-  ground information which aids in the interpretation of quantitative data  from such studies.    REFERENCES    Aylmore, L A.G. and Quirk, J.P, 1960. Domain or turbostratm structure in clays. Nature,  187: 1046--1048.  Krishnamurthy, D.N., 1975. Strength Anisotropy and Fabric Changes During Deforma-  tion and Failure of Orientated Clays. Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, University of Strath-  clyde, 301 pp.  Morgenstern, N.R. and Tchalenko, J.S., 1967. Microstructural observations on shear  zones from slips in natural clays. Proc. Geotech. Conf., Oslo. Vol. 1, pp. 147--152.  Safiullah, A.M.M., 1981. Aspects of Engineering Behaviour of Compacted Clays Related  to their Pore Size Distribution and Fabric Unpublished Ph D. Thesis, University of  Strathclyde, 101 pp.  Stoops, G., 1974. Optical and electron microscopy. A comparison of their principles and  their use in micropedology. In: G.K. Rutherford (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proceed-  ings of the 4th International Working-Meeting on Soil Micromorphology, Kingston,  1973. Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp. 101--118.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           AbstractSpecimen preparation for the scanning electron microscopy of engineering soils is vitally important. The usefulness of critical point drying is assessed on the basis of macroscopic and microscopic data obtained from the critical point drying and the air drying of several natural undisturbed soft clays.It is emphasised that scanning electron microscopy can play a valuable reconnaissance role, thus providing an indication of the broad character of the soil microfabric, over a wide range of magnification, which aids in the selection of the appropriate programme and methods of quantification.It is also demonstrated that scanning electron microscopy observations are extremely useful in the interpretation of, and for providing the very necessary background to, quantitative data such as that yielded by optical thin section and mercury porosimetry studies.