 Geoderma, 33 (1984) 181--189                                                  181  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    EFFECTS OF SLOPE LENGTH ON EROSION OF SOME ALFISOLS IN  WESTERN NIGERIA    R. LAL  International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan (Nigeria)  (Received March 22, 1983; accepted after revision January 27, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Lal, R., 1983. Effects of slope length on erosion of some Alfisols in western Nigeria.  Geoderma, 33: 181--189.    Erosion was monitored for erosive rainstorms received during 1977 and 1978 from  an Alfisol at Ibadan in western Nigeria on bare plowed soil using field runoff plots on  natural slopes of 1, 5, 10 and 15% and with 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths. Equations  of the type A = aLb were computed relating soil erosion (A) to slope length (L).  Erosion was affected more by slope gradient than by slope length and was in the  order of 1, 17.6, 31.3 and 22.8 for 1977 and 1, 25.5, 53.0 and 62.4 for 1978 for 1,  5, 10 and 15% slope gradients, respectively. For gentle slope gradients of 1 and 5%,  slope length had little effect on erosion. During 1978, erosion for 10% slopes was in  the order of 1, 1.05, and 1.08 for 5, 10 and 15 m slope lengths, respectively. For 15%  slope, however, the soil erosion was in the order of 1, 1.11, 1.51 and 1.60 for 5, 10,  15 and 20 m slope lengths. The mean sediment concentration (averaged over all slope  gradients), was 1, 1.27, 1.50, 1.99 for 1977 and 1, 1.61, 2.71, 2.73 for 1978 for 5,  10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths, respectively.    INTRODUCTION    Although the effects of slope length and its gradient on soil erosion  have been studied in the USA and other temperate regions, similar research  information is not available for soils in the tropics. Even in the USA, the  data base for developing the LS factor for the Universal Soil Loss Equation  (USLE} is rather narrow (Wischmeier et al., 1958). The objective of this  report is to describe the effects of short slope lengths on erosion over a  range of slope gradients measured on field runoff plots on softs in western  Nigeria. Slope lengths between 5 and 20 m were chosen to simulate field  lengths of small land holders who cultivate narrow strips of land of hold-  ings between 0.25 to 1.0 ha.  In the temperate parts of the United States, Kramer and Meyer (1969)  compared runoff velocity on slope lengths of 40, 70 and 100 ft. and ob-  served that longer slopes had higher runoff velocities and, therefore, more    0016-7061/84/$03.00   1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    182    erosion than did shorter slopes. Free and Bay (1969) studied the tillage  and slope effects on runoff and erosion and observed that although run-  off decreased on long compared with short slopes the reverse was the case  with erosion. Laflen et al. (1978) observed that erosion increased linearly  with increase in slope length. The more erosion on long compared with  short slope lengths is partly attributed to increase in rill erosion on long  ones (Foster et al., 1977). Long slopes have, therefore, higher length ex-  ponents than short slopes. Mutchler and Greer (1980) reported that the  magnitude of the slope length exponent depends on the slope gradient.  For low slope gradients of 0.5% and less, the value of the exponent was  about 0.15.  Previous studies indicated that findings on soils in temperate zones are  not necessarily applicable to Oxic Paleustalfs in the tropics because of  differences in effective rooting depths, in water retention and transmis-  sion properties, structural stability, in ease of developing surface crusts,  and in rates of mineralization of soil organic matter. Paleustalfs in tropical  Africa have shallow effective rooting depths, have low available water  retention capacities, are structurally unstable, develop surface crusts, and  the infiltration rates decline rapidly during cultivation. In spite of these  differences, results on soils from temperate zones are often used to install  erosion control measures (e.g. terraces and diversion channels) in tropical  Africa. These measures are often unsuccessful partly because the slope  length exponent for soil loss estimation is different for softs of different  physical and hydrological characteristics.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils of the experimental site are clayey skeletal, kaolinitic, isohyper-  thermic, Oxic Paleustalfs. They are medium to light textured near the  surface with sandy clay to clay B2t horizons and have layers of angular  and sub-angular quartz gravel immediately below the surface. Detailed  physical and chemical properties of these soils are described elsewhere  (Lal, 1981).  The runoff collection system for the plots established on natural slopes  have been described in previous reports (Lal, 1983). The plots were 4 m  wide. Sediment concentration in water runoff was determined for all rain-  storm events during 1977 and 1978 by filtering two 1-1itre representa-  tive samples from runoff for each plot for every erosive rain. In addition,  dry weights of sediments deposited at the bottom of the settling tank  and concentrating trough were also determined for each treatment for  every rain.  All plots were kept free of weeds and other vegetative cover. Soil erodi-  bility was computed according to the procedure of the Universal Soil Loss  Equation by dividing the cumulative erosion in short tons per acre per year  by the annual erosivity index R in ft./tons per acre. Appropriate correc-    183    tions were also made for the choice of a suitable LS factor as shown in  Table I of an earlier report (Lal, 1983).  Regression equations were developed relating slope steepness and slope  length as independent variables and soil erosion in water runoff as the  dependent variable. These empirical relations were developed for the fol-  lowing dependent variables.    TABLE I    Effects of slope steepness and length on soil erosion (t ha-~ year-1 )    Slope             Slope length (m)                   Mean  (%)    5       10      15      20    (a) 1977 data:  1                   2.8      1.3     8.3      1.1      3.4  5                  92.2    58.0    67.2    21.5    59.7  10                  82.1   101.9   134.9   107.0   106.5  15                  52.6    72.8    84.6   100.4    77.6  Mean               57.4    58.5    73.8    57.5    (b) 1978 data:  1                   4.5      2.8     6.5      2.2     4.0  5                 143.4    94.5   117.4    52.0   101.8  10                219.1   229.6   235.8   163.5   212.0  15                 190.7   212.4   288.5   306.0   249.5  Mean              139.4   134.8   162.1   130.9    (i) Soil loss (t ha-1) for every rainstorm event.  (ii) Soil loss (t ha-1 year-'), as accumulative sum for the whole year.  (iii) Soil loss per unit runoff (t ha-~ mm-1 year-') for every rainstorm  event.  (iv) Soil loss per unit runoff (t ha-~ mm-' year-') as accumulative sum  for the whole year.  (v) Soil loss per unit rainfall (tha-~ mm-~ year-') for every rainstorm  event.  (vi) Soil loss per unit rainfall (t ha-' mm-' year-') as accumulative sum  for the whole year.  Statistical analyses were also made to compute multiple regression equa-  tions relating soil loss with slope length and slope gradient.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Rainfall erosivity (R ) indices and soil erosion    Frequency distribution of 7.5-rain intensity storms shown in Fig. 1  indicates that 6.4 and 17.1% of rainstorms had peak intensities exceeding    184    100 mm h-~ in 1977 and 1978, respectively. In 1978, about 10% of the  rainstorms had peak intensities exceeding 150 mm h-1.  The correlation coefficient based on single rainstorm events indicated  that soil erosion per unit area was better correlated with different ero-  sivity indices than was the soil loss : runoff ratio. For the 1978 data, the  maximum value of the correlation coefficient of 0.61 was obtained for  EI3o and Aim indices. There were no differences in the correlation coeffi-  cients among the three indices EI3o, Aim, and KE&gt;I. Only 37% of the  variability in erosion of the individual rainstorms, however, could be at-  tributed to its erosivity as computed by different indices. Furthermore,  the correlation coefficient of soil erosion with I30 during 1977 was as good  as with either of the three commonly used erosivity indices. A high cor-  relation between soil erosion and I30 was also observed for the 1978 data.    5  PF.~(  RAINFALL iNTENSITY  (men / hr.)  Fig. 1. Frequency distribution of rainfall intensity for 1977 and 1978.    185    Soil erodibility (K)    The effects of slope characteristics on soil erodibility shown in Fig. 2  for 1978 indicate a general trend toward decrease in erodibility with in-  crease in slope length. Erodibility was in the order of 1, 0.51, 0.52, 0.18  for 1977 and 1, 0.52, 0.46, 0.30 for 1978 for 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope  lengths, respectively. Furthermore, erodibility was generally more for  soils of medium slopes (5 and 10%) than of gentle or steep slopes, e.g.,  0.025, 0.218, 0.176 and 0.078 t acre-' R-' for 1, 5, 10 and 15% slopes,  respectively. The maximum erodibility for 1977 and 1978 was observed  for a 5-m plot on 5% slope; 0.498 and 0.503 short ton acre-' year-' R-'  index, respectively. The softs of 15% slope plots have less erodibility than    1.0 08-  06.    04    0.2    Ol"     OOB-     0 06-  c~  0 04-  002  J    001-  0008-    0006,    0.004,,    0.002'    0001    1978     I% IlOpll plot  x   x 5% m Cot  \                      ~ i=0"./: ~ ~o,    SLOPE   LENGTH   (m)  Fig. 2. Effect of slope length on erodibility factor (K) for 1978.    186    those of 5 and 10% slopes because of their coarse texture and more per-  meable surface layers.    Effect of slope length and gradient on erosion    Soil erosion increased with the increase in steepness of slope and was  in the order of 1, 17.6, 31.3, 22.8 for 1977 and 1, 25.5, 53.0, 62.4 for  1978 for 1, 5, 10 and 15% slopes, respectively (Table I). Slope lengths  between 5 and 20 m had less effect on soil erosion per unit area than did the  slope gradient. Furthermore, there were either no consistent trends in  soil erosion per unit area or erosion decreased with increase in slope length.  There did exist, however, an interaction between slope length and slope  gradient with erosion. For 10 and 15% slopes, an increase in slope length  from 5 to 15 m increased soil erosion per unit area. During 1978, soil ero-  sion for the slopes with a 10% gradient was in the order of 1, 1.05, 1.08  for 5, 10 and 15 m slope lengths, respectively. For 15% slopes, however,  the soil erosion was in the order of 1, 1.11, 1.51, 1.60 for 5, 10, 15 and  20 m slope lengths. For gentle slopes of 1 and 5%, there was only a slight  or no effect of slope length between 5 and 20 m on soil erosion per unit  area. On long slopes of gentle gradient, there is a possibility of deposition  of large sized particles, resulting in less erosion from long than short slope  lengths (Long, 1964; Young, 1980).    Slope characteristics and sediment density in water runoff    The sediment concentration i.e. erosion : runoff ratio (t ha-1 mm-1)  increased linearly with the increase in slope length (Table II). The data    TABLE II    Effects of slope steepness and length on soil erosion : runoff ratio (t ha- ~ mrn-~ )    Slope             Slope length (m)                   Mean  (%)    5     10    15    20    (a) 1977 data:  1                  0.030   0.011   0.036   0.015   0.023  5                  0.343   0.292   0.299   0.147   0.270  10                 0.264   0.543   0.808   0.440   0.514  15                  0.254   0.287   0.197   1.170   0.477  Mean              0.223   0.283   0.335   0.443    {b) 1978 data:  1                  0.024   0.011   0.035   0.023   0.023  5                  0.248   0.327   0.507   0.314   0.349  10                 0.431   0.759   1.242   1.020   0.863  15                0.473   0.799   1.403   1.857   1.133  Mean              0.294   0.474   0.797   0.804    187    on runoff have been published elsewhere (Lal, 1983). For example, the  soil erosion:runoff ratio was 1, 1.27, 1.50, 1.99 for 1977 and 1, 1.61,  2.71, 2.73 for 1978 for 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths, respectively.  On the other hand, the erosion:runoff ratio increased logarithmically  with the increase in slope gradient. For example, the mean erosion : runoff  ratio was 1, 11.74, 23.34, 20.73 for 1977 and 1, 15.17, 37.52 and 49.26  for 1978 for 1, 5, 10 and 15% slopes, respectively.    Regression equations relating soil erosion with slope characteristics    Regression equations shown in Table III are of the type A = aLb. The  length exponent for the annual accumulative soil loss:runoff ratio was  positive and increased with the increase in slope gradient from 0.052 for  a 1% slope to 1.079 for a 15% slope. The correlation coefficients were  generally high, above 0.9. Perhaps only for 10 and 15% slope gradients  is the length exponent for the regression model relating soil erosion  to slope length consistent with similar findings reported by other workers  elsewhere (Zingg, 1940; Musgrave, 1947; Wischmeier et al., 1958). Vari-  ability in soil physical properties among soils of different slopes also con-  founds the results and, therefore, makes it difficult to express the data  in a simple 1 : 1 functional relationship. The length exponent for the an-  nual accumulative soil loss for 10 and 15% slope gradients ranged from  0.01 to 0.68 for 1977 and from 0.12 to 0.38 for 1978 data.  Multiple regression equations relating soil loss, soil loss:runoff, or soil  loss : rainfall ratio with slope length are shown in Table IV for 1978 data.    TABLE III    Regression equations relating soil loss with slope length for 1978    Slope  Soil loss (t ha-1)                Soil loss/rainfall    Soil loss/runoff  (%)                                (tha-~ mm-I)      (t ha-' mm-~)    equation    equation    equation    (a) Based on individual rainfall events:  1    A = 0.900 L'                A = 0.005 L8  5    A = 7.442 L-'6~               A = 0.296 L-43'  10    A = 6.829 LTM 7                A = 0.203 L"  15    A = 2.531L362               A = 0.086 L387    (b) Total soil loss for the water year:  1    A = 5.675 L-~'8  5    A = 305.125 L-'6~  10    A = 279.996 L1~  15    A = 96.974 L3ss    A = 0.005 L-~49  A = 0.269 L-467  A = 0.246 L~'~  A = 0.085 L3~s    A -- 0.287 L-8~8  A --- 0.166 L-~9'  A = 0.201 L683  A = 0.201 L73~    A = 0.021 L:  A = 0.195 L~s7  A = 0.220 LsT A = 0.076 L''9    188  TABLE IV  Multiple regression equations relating soil loss with slope length and slope steepness  for 1978    Dependent variable    Regression equation    Correlation  coefficient  (R)    (a) Based on individual rainfall event:  Soil loss (t ha-~)                A = 1.574+0.235S-0.138L+0.019 LS    0.33  Soil loss/rainfall (t ha-~ mm-~)   A = 0.067-0.008S-0.005L+0.0008 LS   0.38  Soil loss/runoff (t ha-~ mm-~ )    A = 0.133+0.010S-0.018L+0.007 LS    0.33    (b) Total soft loss for the water year:  Soil loss (t ha-1)                 A = 44.921+10.633S-2.947L+0.656 LS  0.93  Soil loss/rainfall (t ha-' rnm-' )   A = 0.037+0.009S-0.003L+0.006 LS    0.93  Soil loss/runoff (t ha-~ ram-')    A = 0.071-0.004S-0.007L+0.007 LS    0.95    The correlation coefficients are rather low for the data on the basis of  individual rainstorm events. The data are, therefore, better fitted according  to the relation of the type A = aLb than multiple regression.    GENERAL DISCUSSION    Similar to water runoff, soil erosion in relation to slope length for slopes  exceeding 5% is also better described by an exponential equation of the  type (A = aLb) rather than by simple or multiple linear regression models.  The exponential function fits equally well for data of individual rainstorms  and for the accumulation during the whole year.  These results have some practical and agronomic implications in terms  of slope length management for erosion control. For gentle slopes of less  than 5%, erosion is either independent or is negatively related with slope  lengths between 5 and 20 m. Elsewhere in the tropics, Georges (1977)  observed from his experiments on cane fields in Trinidad that larger plot  lengths (6 and 8 m) produced significantly less erosion than shorter plot  lengths (1, 2 and 4 m). Even for slopes exceeding 5%, an increase in soil  erosion due to increase in slope length is small in comparison with that  due to an increase in slope gradient. Furthermore, long slopes have an  additional advantage of savings in water because the runoff loss is more  from short than long slopes (Lal, 1983). The data presented, therefore,  do not support terrace intervals of less than 20 m for gentle slopes. The  decision regarding installation of terraces for erosion control on steep  slopes should be based on the expenses involved. If terraces are expensive  to install and maintain, the choice of appropriate soil management practices  and of suitable land use may be attractive alternative measures to combat  erosion.    189    CONCLUSIONS    The results presented support the following conclusions for Paleustalfs  in the tropics.  (1) Erosion is either independent of or is negatively related with slope  lengths between 5 and 20 m for gentle slope gradients of less than 5%.  (2) For slope gradients exceeding 5%, the regression model of the type  A = aLb better describes slope length/soil loss relationships than linear  or polynomial regression equations. Depending on slope gradient, the slope  length exponent ranges from 0.117 to 0.385.  (3) The soil erodibility factor (K) decreases with increases in slope length.  Erodibility is generally high for soils of medium (5 and 10%) slope gra-  dients.  (4) Sediment concentration in water runoff increases linearly with in-  crease in slope length and logarithmically with the increase in slope gra-  dient.    REFERENCES    Foster, G.R. and Wischmeier, W.H., 1974. Evaluating irregular slopes for soil loss pre-  diction. Trans. ASAE, 17: 305--309.  Foster, G.R., Meyer, L.L. and Onstad, C.A., 1977. A runoff erosivity factor and variable  slope length exponents for soil loss estimates. Trans. ASAE, 20: 683--687.  Free, G.R. and Bay, C.E., 1969. Tillage and slope effects on runoff and erosion. Trans.  ASAE, 12: 209--211; 125.  Georges, J.E.W., 1977. Soil erosion in cane fields in hilly lands in Trinidad. Proc. 16th  Congr. Int. Soc. Sugercane Technologiests. Int. Sugar J., 81: 147--157.  Krammer, L.A. and Meyer, L.D., 1969. Small amount of surface mulch reduces soil  erosion and runoff velocity. Trans. ASAE, 12: 638--641; 645.  Laflen, J.M., Baker, J.L., Hartwig, R.O., Buehelle, W.F. and Johnson, H.P., 1978. Soil  and water loss from conservation tillage system. Trans ASAE, 21: 88-1--886.  Lal, R., 1981. Soil erosion problems on Alfisols in western Nigeria, VI. Effects of ero-  sion on experimental plots. Geoderma, 25: 215--230.  Lal, R., 1983. Effect of slope length on runoff from Alfisols in western Nigeria. Geo-  derma, 31: 185--193.  Long, D.C., 1964. The Size and Density of Aggregates in Eroded Material. M.Sc. Thesis,  Iowa State Univ., Ames, Iowa.  Mutchler, C.K. and Greer, J.D., 1980. Effect of slope length on erosion from low slopes.  Trans. ASAE, 23: 866--869.  Musgrave, G.W., 1947. The quantitative evaluation of factors in water erosion, a first  approximation. J. Soil Water Conserv., 2: 133--138.  Wischmeier, W.H., Smith, D.D. and Uhland, R.E., 1958. Evaluation of factors in the  Soil Loss Equation. Agric. Eng., 39: 458.  Young, R.A., 1980. Characteristics of eroded sediments. Trans. ASAE, 23: 1139--  1142; 1146.  Zingg, R.W., 1940. Degree and length of land slope as it affects soil loss in runoff. Agric.  Eng., 21: 59--64.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractErosion was monitored for erosive rainstorms received during 1977 and 1978 from an Alfisol at Ibadan in western Nigeria on bare plowed soil using field runoff plots on natural slopes of 1, 5, 10 and 15% and with 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths. Equations of the type A = αLb were computed relating soil erosion (A) to slope length (L).Erosion was affected more by slope gradient than by slope length and was in the order of 1, 17.6, 31.3 and 22.8 for 1977 and 1, 25.5, 53.0 and 62.4 for 1978 for 5, 10 and 15% slope gradients, respectively. For gentle slope gradients of 1 and 5%, slope length had little effect on erosion. During 1978, erosion for 10% slopes was in the order of 1, 1.05, and 1.08 for 5, 10 and 15 m slope lengths, respectively. For 15% slope, however, the soil erosion was in the order of 1, 1.11, 1.51 and 1.60 for 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths. The mean sediment concentration (averaged over all slope gradients), was 1, 1.27, 1.50, 1.99 for 1977 and 1, 1.61, 2.71, 2.73 for 1978 for 5, 10, 15 and 20 m slope lengths, respectively. 