 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 45--69                                                         45  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PROPERTIES AND CLASSIFICATION OF SOME DESERT SOILS IN  COARSE-TEXTURED GLACIAL DRIFT IN THE ARCTIC AND ANTARCTIC    J.G. BOCKHEIM  Department of Soil Science, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, 53706 (U.S.A.)  (Received May 16, 1979; accepted November 12, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Bockheim, J.G., 1980. Properties and classification of some desert soils in coarse-textured  glacial drift in the Arctic and Antarctic. Geoderma, 24: 45--69.    Polar Desert soils in the Arctic (66and 74 latitude) are contrasted with Cold Desert  soils in the Antarctic (77). The soils are derived from sandy-skeletal glacial drift and have  not been influenced by cryoturbation. Pedogenic horizons are limited to a desert pavement  (designated D) and to a weak B horizon in the oldest soils of both groups. Solum thickness  increases with age in the two soil groups; however, because of a slightly greater amount of  soil moisture, the increase in solum thickness is greater for Polar Desert soils. Soils of both  groups often contain "dry" permafrost. The Polar Desert soils at 74 and most of the  Cold Desert soils are neutral to mildly alkaline and the Polar Desert soils at 66~N are  strongly to medium acid. Although soluble salts increase with age in soils of both groups,  the increase is more marked in the more arid Cold Desert soils. Results from this study  and a survey of the literature show that sodium is the prevalent cation in water extracts  of Cold Desert soils and in Polar Desert soils above ca. 80. Chloride is the major anion  in Cold Desert soils in the McMurdo Sound vicinity and in noncalcareous Polar Desert  soils. Ion ratios indicate that salts in these soils are contributed by marine aerosols. The  soils examined contain less than 5% clay-size (&lt; 2 urn) material. Mica, vermiculite and  kaolinite are the predominant phyllosilicate minerals in the clay fractions of Polar Desert  soils, and mica, vermiculite and montmorillonite are most abundant in Cold Desert soils.  A scheme contrasting clay-mineral alteration in soils of the two groups is provided. In the  Canadian system, the Cold Desert soils are Static Cryosols, and the Polar Desert soils are  either.Static Cryosols or Dystric Brunisols. In the U.S. system, the soils are Pergelic  Cryorthents. Suggestions are given to modify the U.S. system so as to better distinguish  polar soils.    INTRODUCTION    Polar Desert softs in the Arctic and Cold Desert softs in Antarctica formed in  a cold, arid climate, have a sparse vegetation, and have poorly expressed pro-  fries which are often alkaline and saline, low in organic matter, and underlain  by permafrost. Tedrow (1968) pointed out the morphological affinities of  Polar Desert and Cold Desert softs.  The objective of this study is to contrast the morphological, chemical, and  physical properties and the clay mineralogy of Cold Desert and Polar Desert    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    46    soils which are derived from sandy-skeletal glacial drift and which have been  relatively unaffected by congeliturbation. It should be pointed out that areas  of clayey and loamy soils occur in the high Arctic (Tarnocai, 1978) but that  examples of the more abundant coarse-textured soils were selected for this  comparative study.    BACKGROUND    Tedrow (1977) provided a comprehensive review of polar soils. He proposed  three pedologic zones in the Arctic: the tundra zone, the subpolar desert  zone, and the polar desert zone (Fig. 1). The southern boundary of the tundra  17~    60   90   120   90 30           0               30 150           180           150   60   90   120   47    zone is delineated by a latitudinal treeline, The southern limit of the polar  desert zone corresponds to the July isotherm of 4. The polar desert zone  corresponds geographically to the high Arctic and botanically to the rock  desert (Tedrow, 1977). In the Western Hemisphere, the polar desert zone  (ca. 74--83) includes the Queen Elizabeth Islands and northern Greenland.  The subpolar desert zone was recognized by Tedrow (1977) as transitional  to the tundra zone and the polar desert zone and also as corresponding to  the mid-arctic or the stony sedge-moss-lichen tundra. This zone (ca. 65--74)  includes most of Baffin Island, Melville and Boothia peninsulas; and  Somerset, Prince of Wales, Victoria and Banks islands.    Fig.2. Polar Desert soil (profile 73-8), Cornwallis Island, N.W.T., Canada (74).    Fig.1. Zonation of soils in the Arctic and in Antarctica (after Tedrow, 1977 ) and loca-  tion of study areas. T = tundra pedologic zone; SPD = subpolar desert zone; PD = polar  desert zone; CD --- cold desert zone; 1 = southwestern Cumberland Peninsula, Baffin  Island, N.W.T., Canada; 2 = Cornwallis Island, N.W.T. ; 3 = "dry valley" region, south  Victoria Land, Antarctica.    48    The predominant soil of the polar and the subpolar desert zones is the  Polar Desert soil (Tedrow, 1966, 1977). The Polar Desert soil is well-drained,  has a sparse vegetational cover, a desert pavement, and poorly expressed hori-  zons (Fig.2). The soil is commonly neutral to alkaline, saline and low (less  than 1%) in organic matter. In the subpolar desert zone (Fig. 3), the Polar  Desert soil has a greater amount of organic matter, a less strongly developed  desert pavement, lower pH values and more moisture in the subsoil (Tedrow,  1977). Permafrost in Polar Desert soils may be "dry" or ice-cemented.  Soil zonation is not as readily apparent in Antarctica. Tedrow and Ugolini  (1966) described soils of Antarctica as belonging to the cold desert zone.  In addition, Tedrow (1977) proposed the existence of a less arid polar desert  zone between 60 and 65 latitude, which includes the tip of the Antarctic  Peninsula and the South Shetland Islands (Fig. 1). The major upland soil in  icefree areas of the cold desert zone is an Ahumic soil, so named because it  lacks a humus layer (Tedrow and Ugolini, 1966). However, the Ahumic soil  is not necessarily abiotic. The Ahumic soil of the Cold Desert (referred to  here as simply the Cold Desert soil) has a strongly developed desert pavement,  poor horizonation, negligible organic matter, a mildly acid to alkaline reac-  tion, high salinity and "dry" permafrost within the upper 1 m (Fig. 4).  Tedrow (1968) arranged well-drained polar soils in a hypothetical bio-  climatic gradient from the tundra to the subpolar desert to the polar desert  to the cold desert. Along this gradient calcification, alkalization and salini.  zation were depicted as increasing in intensity and the organic matter contri-  bution as decreasing.    Fig.3. Polar Desert soil (profile 74-40), Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada (665'N).    49    Fig.4. Ahumic Cold Desert soil (profile 77-52), Taylor Valley, south Victoria Land,  Antarctica (773'S).    Although a number of polar pedologists have used the zonal classification  of Tedrow (1977), other soil classification systems have been utilized in the  polar regions, including the U.S. System (Rieger, 1974), the Canadian system  (Tamocai, 1978), the Soviet system (Rozov and Ivanova, 1967), and the zonal  system of Campbell and Claridge (1969). The zonal system of Tedrow (1977)  will be used here, because of its common usage in the polar softs literature  and because, unlike the other systems, it distinguishes soils of the high Arctic  from those of Antarctica.    STUDY AREA    Polar Desert soils were examined in the subpolar desert zone on south-  western Cumberland Peninsula, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada (66) and in  the polar desert zone on Cornwallis Island in the Queen Elizabeth Islands,  N.W.T. (74) (Fig.l). Cold Desert softs were examined in the "dry valleys"  of the Trans-Antarctic Mountains in south Victoria Land, Antarctica (77).  Climatic data for the three regions are summarized in Table I. Mean annual  precipitation, mean annual temperature, and mean temperature of the coldest  month are similar for McMurdo Station, Antarctica, and Resolute, Cornwallis  Island, N.W.T. The major differences in climate between the two areas are as  follows: the mean temperature of the warmest month is above freezing (4.5)  for Resolute and below freezing (--3) for McMurdo; in contrast to the  high Arctic, rainfall has never been recorded in the McMurdo Sound vicinity;    O    TABLE I  Climatic data for the three study areas    Station                Latitude    Pedologic  zone    Mean  annual  precipi-  tation  (cm)    Mean  annual  temper-  ature  ()    Mean  temper-  ature  coldest  month  ()    Mean  temper-  ature  warmest  month  ()    Average  summer  relative  humidity  (%)    Average  wind  velocity  (m/sec)    McMurdo Station,      771'S    cold       18.8  Antarctica                         desert  Pangnirtung, Baffin    669'N   subpolar   33.5  Island, N.W.T.                     desert  Resolute, Cornwallis   7443'N   polar       13.5  Island, N.W.T.                     desert    --17  --9  --16    --28  --27  --32    --2.8  7.8  4.6    57  87    6.5  4.9  5.2    TABLE II  Location and description of soil sampling sites    Profile  Location           Composition of  parent material    Vegetation    Landform    Slope  gradient  (    Estimated  soil age (yr BP)    Polar Desert    74-18   Baffin Island        granite, gneiss          stony sedge-moss-lichen   lateral moraine  73-7    Cornwallis Island   shale                  stony moss-lichen         ground moraine (?)  73-8    Cornwallis Island    dolomitic limestone    stony lichen              ground moraine (?)  73-9    Cornwallis Island    quartzose sand         none                      ground moraine (?)  74-41   Baffin Island        granite, gneiss          stony lichen              end moraine  74-40   Baffin Island        granite, gneiss          stony lichen              end moraine  74-43   Baffin Island        granite, gneiss          stony sedge-moss-lichen   lateral moraine    Cold Desert  77-36   Wright Valley,      gneiss, schist           none  Antarctica  77-46   Wright Valley,      granodiorite, diorite   none  Antarctica  76-21   Taylor Valley,      granite                 none  Antarctica  77-14   Wright Valley,      granodiorite           none  Antarctica  75-15   Taylor Valley,      diorite                 none  Antarctica  77-52   Taylor Valley,      granodiorite, diorite    none  Antarctica          gneiss    lateral moraine  end moraine  lateral moraine  end moraine  lateral moraine  lateral moraine    4  2  2  0  2  1    16  7  2  11  5    1,000  8,350  8,350  8,350  5,000--10,000  10,000--60,000  60,000--100,000    3,100  18,000  120,000  135,000  220,000  300,000    52    the average relative humidity is higher in the high Arctic; and the average wind  velocity is greater in Antarctica. These differences are significant, because, in  contrast to Polar Desert soils, Cold Desert soils rarely feature liquid water. Of  the three regions, the subpolar desert has the greatest mean annual precipitation,  mean annual temperature, and mean temperature of the warmest month  (Table I).  A description of the sampling sites is provided in Table II. The soils are  derived from coarse-textured (sandy-skeletal) glacial drift, with the exception  of profile 73-7 which is loamy-skeletal. The soils were located on moraine  crests; all but two profiles were situated on slopes of 7or less. The glacial  drift at the soil sampling sites on Baffin Island and in Antarctica is similar in  composition and is comprised of felsic igneous and metamorphic rocks. On  Cornwallis Island, the soils are derived from what appeared to be glacial  drift and are comprised of either shale (profile 73-7), dolomitic limestone  (73-8), or quartzose sand (73-9). Polar Desert soils on Cornwallis Island are  8,350 yr in age. On Baffin Island, Polar Desert soils range in age from about  1,000 to 100,000 yr BP (Bockheim, 1979a). Cold Desert soils examined in  Antarctica range from 3,100 to about 300,000 yr BP (Bockheim, 1977, 1979b).    METHODS    Soils were described in detail using criteria established by the U.S. Soil  Survey Staff (1951, 1975) and modified for polar soils (Bockheim, 1979b).  Sampling was conducted during the period August 1973--December 1977.  More than 800 samples were collected from over 200 profiles. The data pre-  sented here were selected as representative of Polar Desert and Cold Desert  soils. Although some of the data were published previously, many of them are  given here for the first time.  Particle-size distribution was determined by the modified Bouyoucos  hydrometer method (Day, 1965). Electrical conductivity, pH, and water-  soluble ions (Na Ca2 Mg2 K CI-, SO~-) were measured on 1:5 soil:water  extracts using standard methods for water analysis (American Public Health  Association et al., 1975). Concentrations of sodium and potassium were  measured by flame photometry and those of calcium and magnesium by  atomic-absorption spectroscopy. Sulphate was measured by the turbidometric  method (nephelometry) and chloride by the potentiometric method (chlorido-  meter). With the exception of profiles 73-7 and 73-8, free carbonates were  negligible and are not reported. Free-iron oxides were extracted with a citrate--  dithionite solution buffered with sodium bicarbonate (Mehra and Jackson,  1960). Iron was detected on an atomic-absorption spectrophotometer.  Samples of the clay (&lt; 2 ~m) fraction were treated and mounted on microscope  slides for X-ray diffraction analysis using standard methods summarized by  Whittig (1965).    53    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Soil morphology    Polar Desert soils older than 10,000 yr BP and Cold Desert soils older than  100,000 yr BP have a desert pavement and B horizons that fail to meet re-  quirements of a cambic horizon (Table III). Younger soils show no evidence  of horizonation. The desert pavement increases in development with soil age  and degree of exposure to katabatic winds. Not only are clasts in well-developed  desert pavements more closely knit, but they may also show desert varnish,  exfoliation, pitting, and ventifaction. Because there is no uniformly accepted  soil horizon symbol in the literature for expressing the desert pavement, the  symbol D is used here. This symbol was previously used for consolidated  parent rock below the C horizon (U.S. Soil Survey Staff, 1951). Although  it is no longer used with that meaning, the symbol may appear in the older  literature.  Thickness of solum increases with age in both soil groups; the rate of in-  crease is greatest in Polar Desert soils (Fig. 5). The linear regression equation  for the Polar Desert soil is Y = 8.08 + 0.00106 X, where Y = solum thickness  (cm) and X = time (yr 104). The correlation coefficient (r) is 0.97. The  equation for the Cold Desert soil is Y = --1.03 + 0.91 X (r = 0.97). Whereas  softs on Baffin Island which are 5,000--10,000 yr BP in age have sola 25 cm  in thickness, no profile development was observed in 18,000 year old soils of  Antarctica.  The product of the code of hue and chroma, color development equiva-  lences (CDE) are a measure of the magnitude of color development in soils  (Buntley and Westin, 1965). Color development equivalences of Cold Desert  soils and Polar Desert soils on Cornwallis Island are similar (Table III). How-  ever, Polar Desert soils on Baffin Island have a higher CDE than Polar Desert  soils of the high Arctic or Cold Desert soils of an equivalent age.  Soil texture is controlled by lithology of the parent material and weather-  ing. In general, the fine-earth fraction of Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils  examined in this study is dominated by sand (Table III). Coarse fragments  (&gt; 2 mm) commonly comprise from 25 to 75% of pedons in these soils. Cold  Desert soils in Antarctica and Polar Desert soils on Cornwallis Island are struc-  tureless and single-grained. However, due to the presence of very fine (&lt; I mm)  roots and a greater amount of organic matter, Polar Desert soils in the sub-  polar desert zone of Baffin Island have a weak-to-moderate, fine granular  structure.  Salt efflorescences were present on the surfaces of fine-textured soils on  Cornwallis Island after several days of clear, windy weather but were not seen  on southwestern Cumberland Peninsula, Baffin Island. Salt encrustations occur  beneath coarse fragments in Cold Desert soils with ages greater than 18,000 yr  BP (Bockheim, 1979b). Salt flecks 2--5 mm in diameter occur in the matrix  of soils older than 135,000 yr BP. Although soils older than 300,000 yr BP    TABLE III    e.gn    Morphology of Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils derived from coarse-textured glacial drift  Profile  Horizon   Depth  Munsell       Hue X      Soil              Structure                 Roots  (cm)    color         chroma    textural class    Polar Desert soils  74-18   A1          0--10  10YR 5/2      6         silt loam         massive-weak, fine gran.   plentiful v. fine, med.  IIC        10--26  10YR 4.5/2    6         loamy sand      weak, fine granular       plentiful v. fine  73-7    C1          1--21  7.5YR 4/2     8         gravelly loam    mod., fine crumb         few v. fine  C2         21--42  10YR 4/3      9         v.gr. sandy loam rood., v.fine crumb       v.few v.fine  C3ic       42+     10YR 4/2      6         v.gr.sandy loam  massive                   none  73-8    C1          1--23  2.5Y 5/2       4         gravelly sand     single grain               none  C2         23--40  10YR 6/3      9          gravelly sand     single grain                none  C3         40--53  5Y 7/3          3          sand              single grain                none  C4ie       53+     5Y 7/3         3         --                massive                   none  73-9    C1         1~-- 21  10YR 8/2      6         sand             single grain               none  C2         21--24  10YR 5/2      6         sand             single grain               none  C3         24--49  10YR 7/2      6          sand              single grain                none  C4ic       49+     --             --          sand             massive                   none  74-41   A1          0--2   7.5YR 4/4    16         gravelly sand     weak, fine gran.           few v.fine  B21         2--28  10YR 5/3.5   15         gr.loamy sand    rood., fine gran.           none  B22        28--31  10YR 5/5     15         gr. loamy sand   rood., fine gran.           none  Cn         31--76  10YR 5/4     12         gravelly sand     massive-rood., fine gran.   none  74-40   A1          0--12  5YR 3/4      20         gravelly sand     weak, fine granular       few v.fine  B21        12--40  10YR 4/3      9         gr. loamy sand   massive-weak, fine gran.   none  B22        40--73  10YR 5/4     12         cobbly sand      weak, fine granular        none  C          73--97  2.5Y 5/4       8         cobbly sand      massive-weak, fine gran.   none  74-43   A1          0~7   5YR 3/3      15         v. gravelly sand  single grain               many v.fine  B1          7--23  7.5YR 4/4    16         gravelly sand     weak, fine granular        few v.fine  B21        23--29  10YR 4/3      9         gravelly sand     massive-rood., fine gran.   few v.fine  B22        29--54  10YR 4/4     12         cobblyloamysandmassive-mod., fine gran.   v.few v.fine  B3         54--107 10YR 4/3      9         cobblyloamysandmassive-mod., fine gran.   none    TABLE III (continued)  Profile  Horizon    Depth   Munsell       Hue      Soil               Structure                  Roots  (cm)    color         chroma    textural class    Cold Desert soils  77-36   C1           0--8    10YR 7/3      9          v. gravelly sand  C2ic        8--16  10YR 7/3      9         v. gravelly sand  77-46   C1          0--33  10YR 6/3      9         v. gravelly sand  IIC2       33--72  10YR 7/2      6         cobbly sand  IIC3ic     72+        --         --         eobbly sand  76-21   B2          0--8   2.5Y 7/4       8         gravelly sand  C1          8--21  2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  C2         21--84  2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  77-14   D           0--1   variegated     --         v. gravelly sand  B2sa        1--13  2.5Y 7/4       8         gravelly sand  Clsa       13--42  2.5Y 7/4       8         v. gravelly sand  C2         42--70  2.5Y 7/4       8         gravelly sand  C3         70--100 2.5Y 7/4       8         gravelly sand  75-15   B2          1--11  10YR 6/4     12         gravelly sand  C1         11--50  2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  C2         50--85  2.5Y 6.5/2     4         gravelly sand  C3          85--100 10YR 6/4     12          gravelly sand  77-52   D            0--1/2   variegated     --          v. gravelly sand  B21         V2--10 2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  B22        10--20  2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  C1          20--40  2.5Y 6/4       8          sand  C2         40--70  2.5Y 6/4       8         gravelly sand  C3         70--115 2.5Y 7/4       8         gravelly sand    massive-single grain  massive-single grain  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single grain  single gram  single gram  single gram  massive-single grain  single grmn  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram  single gram    none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none  none    Oa  C.n    56    IOC  uE 80                              /~o  ~-                               Polar desert     4C  E  2  ~  2o  Cold desert ~'9o  0            fl           ,                       i  103                    104                  105  Time, years  Fig.5. Relationship between solum thickness and age in Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils  derived from granitic glacial drift.    are not discussed here, weakly cemented salt-indurated layers occur in soils  older than 1.2 m.yr and strongly cemented salt-indurated layers occur in those  older than 3.9 m. yr (Campbell and Claridge, 1975). Salt patches and pans  have not been reported in the Arctic, possibly because it is less arid.  The ice-cemented frost table (designated ic) is present at depths of 40--50  cm in well-drained Polar Desert soils of Cornwallis Island but was not found  in the upper 1 m of Polar Desert softs on southern Baffin Island, possibly due  to the milder climate and to the fact that the softs examined there generally  are older (Table III). Depth to the ice-cemented frost table is related to soil  age and proximity to glaciers in Antarctica. The ice-cemented frost table may  recede downward in the regolith through time in dry, inland localities of  Antarctica due to sublimation, resulting in "dry" permafrost. "Dry" perma-  frost is ground which remains below the 0-isotherm for two or more years  in succession but contains insufficient moisture to cause cementation by ice.  Whereas the 18,000 year old soil (profile 77-46) had an ice-cemented frost  table at 72 cm, older soils were not cemented by ice in the upper 1 m despite  soil temperatures as low as --20 in early November 1977.  Softs showing evidence of active cryogenic processes were not sampled in  the present study. In the polar desert zone, these soils are referred to as soils  of the hummocky ground (Tedrow, 1970) or Turbic Cryosols (Zoltai and  Tarnocal, 1974). Polar soils often contain features resulting from relict cryo-  genic processes. The former presence of ice-cemented permafrost in some  Cold Desert soils is suggested by fossil sand wedge casts in the upper 50 cm  and mineral coatings on coarse fragments in the subsoil. On Baffin Island,  Polar Desert soils contain horizons enriched in fine particles and coatings of  silt and very fine sand on coarse fragments. The silt caps may represent verti-  cal sorting due to a downward moving freezing front when ice-cemented  permafrost was within what now is part of the solum (Bockheim, 1979a).    57    Soil chemistry    Cold Desert softs in Antarctica and the Polar Desert soils studied on Corn-  waUis Island are neutral to mildly alkaline (Table IV). Polar Desert soils on  southern Baffin Island have pH values as low as 4.9, possibly because of  leaching. Because Antarctica is more arid than the high Arctic, electrical  conductivity values are greater in Cold Desert soils than in Polar Desert soils.  Whereas a 135,000 year old soil (profile 77-14) in Antarctica had an electri-  cal conductivity of 6.8, a soil of similar age (profile 74-43) on southern Baffin  Island had an electrical conductivity of 0.03 mmho/cm (Table IV). Fig. 6  shows the rate of increase in electrical conductivity with soil age to be con-  siderably greater in Cold Desert soils than in Polar Desert soils. The linear  regression equation for the Cold Desert soils is Y = 0.515 + 48 X, where Y =  electrical conductivity of the salt-enriched horizon (mmho/cm) and X = time  (yr 10-6 ). The correlation coefficient (r) is 0.999. The equation for the  Polar Desert soils is Y = 0.015 + 0.098 X (r = 0.937). Under carefully con-  trolled conditions, these equations are useful for the relative dating of soils  (Bockheim, 1979b).  The predominant cation in 1:5 soil: water extracts of soils older than  18,000 yr BP in Antarctica is sodium. Examination of data presented in  Table IV and data by Tedrow and Thompson (1969) and Tedrow (1970)  shows that no single cation is predominant in Polar Desert soils. However,  the proportion or milliequivalent-percent of sodium appears to increase with    E  u  o  ] 2  &gt;  ~g  D  ~3  E  o  u  u  E  LII    10    01    ///.////~Cold desert    Po,   I                   o  001                   J                   L~  103            104            105    Time, years    Fig.6. Relationship between el~ectrical conductivity in 1:5 soil: water extracts of the salt-  enriched zone and age in Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils derived from granitic glacial  drift.    00    TABLE IV  Chemical analyses of a 1:5 soil:water extract and dithionite-extractable iron for Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils    Profile  Horizon    Depth     EC              pH   Water-soluble ions (meq 1-~)  (cm)       (mmho em-1)    Polar Desert  74-18  A1  IIC  73-7    C1  C2  73-8    C1    73-9    74-40    C2  C3  C1  C2  C3  C4ic  A1  B21  B22  C    Na        Ca2       Mg2       K+          C1-      SO~-    soils    0--10     0.046             4.9   0.035  10--26     0.017             5.5   0.028  1--21     0.12              7.8   0.054  21--42        --               --   0.048  1--23     0.051             7.1   0.0013  23--40     0.050            7.0   0.0009  40--53     0.047            8.2   0.0017  1/2--21     0.016             6.9   0.0011  21--24     0.047             8.0   0.0020  24--49     0.039             7.6   0.0009  49+        0.073             8.3     --  0--12     0.019             5.1   0.021  12--40     0.016             5.7   0.023  40--73     0.017             6.0   0.023  73--97     0.021             6.2   0.035    Fed  (%)    0.100             0.064             0.073             0.036  0.062      0.025      0.021      0.018  0.014             0.0064           0.0028                --  0.011             0.0065           0.0036               --  0.0075          0.0035           0.0018                --  0.0063          0.0043          0.0020                --  0.0088     0.0043     0.0032       --  0.0050           0.0016          0.0012                --  0.0010          0.0023          0.0019                --  0.0010          0.0014          0.0012                --  0.049             0.026             0.018             0.063  0.052             0.031             0.015             0.027  0.060             0.038             0.016             0.054  0.067             0.043             0.015             0.054    0.153  0.100  0.017  0.040  0.020  0.040    0.21  0.13  0.45  0.084  0.036  O.04O  0.012  0.016  0  0  0.24  0.26  0.22  0.17    Cold Desert soils  77-36   C1          0--8      0.62  C2ic        8--16     0.60  77-46   C1          0--33     1.4  IIC2       33--72     0.45  76-21   B2          0--8      3.0  C1       8--21   6.5  C2      21--84   1.6  77-14   D          0--1      0.50  B2sa        1--13     4.5  Clsa       13--42     6.8  C2         42--70     1.8  C3         70--100    0.81  75-15   B2           1--11     2.4  C1          11--50     5.6  C2      50--85   1.9  C3          85--100    0.76  77-52   D             0--'~       1.8  B21      1/2--10   3.5  B22        10--20     5.4  C1          20--40     2.1  C2          40--70     1.7  C3          70--115    1.2    8.2   2.8  7.7   2.5  6.8   8.5  6.7   3.1  7.2 13.5  7.4 73.9  7.6   5.39  7.0   3.0  6.8 31.0  6.8 62.8  7.2 10.8  7.1   4.1  8.0  9.24  8.0 40.8  8.4 13.2  8.7   5.07  8.2 10.4  8.2  13.7  8.4 37.2  8.3   5.00  8.4   4.45  8.2   3.62    2.31  2.28  2.8  0.62  13.5  6.54  5.14  1.1  11.1  6.3  1.6  1.0  12.4  20.4  2.81  1.11  2.90  7.72  6.86  4.54  8.81  3.38    1.34  1.43  2.4  0.46  14.1  11.1  7.53  0.61  6.2  4.9  3.2  2.2  7.78  7.09  4.87  1.25  5.97  18.3  16.3  11.8  7.70  3.95    0.203  0.203  0.36  0.18  0.708  1.43  0.491  0.19  1.0  1.1  0.60  0.34  0.92  1.04  0.68  0.33  0.33  0.93  1.47  0.66  0.46  0.41    4.40  4.31  9.7  2.7  28.5  85.5  12.5  2.5  33.5  62.4  12.1  5.0  14.3  45.2  14.9  5.04  16.3  32.2  53.3  18.4  14.0  9.70    0.793  0.766  2.5  0.68  10.2  3.96  3.44  1.2  10.2  5.0  0.5  0  10.0  19.0  2.29  1.27  0.86  2.31  1.98  0.12  0.08  0.09    0.12  0.20  0.071  0.089  0.11  0.10  0.11  0.053  0.058  0.037  0.039  0.041  0.i0  0.085  0.082  0.11  0.042  0.11  0.10  0.11  0.12  0.12    1  D    60    latitude in the Arctic. Calcium and magnesium are predominant in Polar  Desert soils on Baffin Island. Magnesium and sodium are major constituents  of water extracts of Polar Desert soils on Cornwallis Island. Tedrow (1970)  reported an abundance of calcium followed by sodium in salt crusts from north-  west Greenland, 78 latitude. Day (1964) reported sodium as the dominant  cation in water extracts in two of three soils on northern Ellesmere Island  (819'N). The prevalence of sodium in Antarctic soils is a further indication  of the extreme aridity of the region. In Antarctica, chloride is the dominant  anion in soils located within about 75 km of the open sea. Chloride also is the  most abundant anion in Polar Desert soils reported here and in those analyzed  by Tedrow (1970) in northwest Greenland. Because CaCO3 was detected only  in two profiles (73-7 and 73-8), it is not reported here. However, calcification  is a dominant process in Polar Desert soils derived from calcareous materials  (Everett, 1968; Tedrow, 1970).  Ionic ratios of water extracts of Polar Desert soils of Baffin Island (Bock-  heim, 1979a) and of Cold Desert softs in southern Victoria Land (Bockheim,  1979b) suggest that the Na Mg2 and C1- have originated from marine aero-  sols. Based on ionic ratios, Ca2and Kare of rock weathering origin; SO~-  is due to marine aerosols and rock weathering. Everett (1968) considered Na and SO~- in soils of Ellef Ringnes Island to have resulted from rock weather-  ing because the island is ice-locked. However, Wilson and House (1965) demon-  strated that snow at the South Pole, which is 1,600 km from the ocean in  summer and twice that distance in winter, contained salts contributed by  marine aerosols. Claridge and Campbell (1977) showed the probable path-  ways followed by salts in Cold Desert soils.  Salt efflorescences of soils on Prince Patrick Island are mainly mirabilite,  Na2SO4 10H20 (Tedrow, 1966). Mirabilite is also the dominant salt in ef-  florescences, flecks, patches, and pans of softs in Taylor Valley (Bockheim,  1977) and in Wright Valley, Antarctica (Bockheim, 1979b). The origin of  the mirabilite in the two regions is not known. However, mirabilite is known  to precipitate first from freezing sea water (Thompson and Nelson, 1956).  It is possible that occluded mirabilite is blown across the sea ice, accumulating  in softs of coastal areas of the Arctic Ocean and the Ross Sea, Antarctica.  Dithionite-extractable iron (Fed) is more abundant in Polar Desert soils  of Baffin Island than in Cold Desert soils of Antarctica of an equivalent age  (cf. profiles 74-40 and 77-46; table IV). In both regions Fed increases with  soft age. The rate of increase is greater in Polar Desert soils, due to a greater  amount of soil moisture. A detailed study of a quartz diorite rock in south  Victoria Land, Antarctica, showed few changes in chemical composition fol-  lowing weathering, except for oxidation of iron in biotite and pyrrhotite  (Kelly and Zumberge, ] 961).    Particle-size distribution    Although all of the soils contain less than 5% clay, Polar Desert soils have  more clay than Cold Desert softs of equivalent age and initial material (cf.,    61    profiles 77-46 and 74-41; Table V). The greater amount of clay in Polar Desert  softs may be due to increased chemical weathering enhanced by the slightly  greater amount of soil moisture. Polar Desert soils also have greater quantities    TABLE V    Particle-size distribution and clay mineralogy of Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils    Profile  Horizon   Depth     Sand            Silt        Clay  (cm)      (2--0.05 mm)    (0.05--    (&lt;0.002 mm)  0.002 ram)    Clay minerals1    Polar Desert soils  74-18  A1        0--10     51           49       0          M,k  IIC       10--26     85           15       0           M,k,v  73-7    C1          1--21      50              49         1             M,K,c  C2        21--42      48             48        4            M,K,c  C3ic       42+         48              48         4             M,K,c  73-8    C1          1--23      92               7         1             I,k  C2         23--40      87              10         3             I,M,k  C3         40--53      90               8         2             I,M  73-9    C1         1/=--21      91               9         0             I,k  C2        21--24      86             10        4            K,m,i,c  C3         24--49      92               7         1             K,I  C4         49+         93               6         0             I  74-41   A1          0--2       95               5         0             I  B21        2--28      77             23        0            I,v,k  B22        28--31      79              16         5             K,I  C          31--76      89              11         1             I,k  74-40   A1          0--12      98               2         0             I,v  B21        12--40      83              17         0             I,v,k  B22        40--73      93               7         0             I,k  C          73--97      95               5         0             I,k  74-43   A1         0--7       99              1         0            I  B1          7--23      99              1         0            I,v  B21       23--29      88             11         1            V,k  B22        29--54      83              16         1             V,k  B3         54--107     79              20         1             M,v,k    Cold Desert soils  77-46   C1          0--33     100              0        0            C,m  IIC2       33--72     100               0         0             C,M  77-14   D           0--1      100               0         0             M,C,i  B2sa        1--13      98               2         0             M,C  Clsa       13--42      97               2         1             M,c  C2         42--70      99               1         0             M,c,i  C3        70--100    99              1         0            M,I,c  75-15   B2          1--11      90               6         4             m,mo,v,c  C1        11--50      91              7         2            m,mo,v,c,i  C2        50--85      94              4         2            m,mo,v,c,i  C3        85--100    98              1         1            m,mo,v,c    ' Mineral designations: Kk = kaolinite; Mm = mica; Mo,mo = montmorillonite; Vv = vermi-  culite; Ii = interstratified; Cc = iron-chlorite; upper case indicates strong and lower case  intermediate and weak X-ray diffraction intensities.    62    of silt than Cold Desert soils. The silt in Polar Desert softs of Baffin and  Cornwallis Islands may have been deposited by winds eroding floodplains of  braided Arctic streams. Broad floodplains providing a source of silt do not  exist in Antarctica.    Clay mineralogy    The dominant minerals in the clay-size (&lt; 2 ~m) fraction of Polar Desert  soils derived from felsic, mafic, and calcareous parent materials are mica, inter-  stratified phyllosilicates and kaolinite, with lesser amounts of chlorite and  vermiculite (Table V). Cold Desert softs originating from felsic parent mate-  rials contain mica and chlorite and lesser amounts of montmorillonite, vermi-  culite and interstratified phyllosilicate minerals.  A survey of the literature indicates that mica, vermiculite and kaolinite  are prevalent in Polar Desert softs (Everett, 1968; Tedrow et al., 1968;  Tedrow, 1970; Isherwood, 1975; Bockheim, 1979a; Evans and Cameron,  1979). Cold Desert softs contain an abundance of mica, vermiculite and mont-  morillonite (Claridge, 1965; Behling, 1971; Linkletter, 1971; Ugolini and  Jackson, 1977; Bockheim, 1979b).  The mica and chlorite in Polar Desert softs of Baffin Island and in Cold  Desert softs of Antarctica appear to have been inherited from the granitic  parent material. The vermiculite may represent a weathering product of mica,  and the montmorillonite is most likely weathered from vermiculite (Ugolini and  Jackson, 1977). Montmorillonite forms in soils with a high pH and in the  absence of leaching, conditions which exist in many Cold Desert soils. In Polar  Desert softs of Baffin Island, the ratio of the 001 X-ray diffraction peak  height of kaolinite (7.2 A ) to that of mica (9.9 A ) increased from less than 1  in 1,000 year old soils to 6 in 100,000 year old soils (Bockheim, 1979a).  Bockheim proposed that the kaolinite may have been produced by weathering  of feldspar or of mica, or it may have been crystallized from A1 and Si  solutions or gels at ambient thaw-period soil temperatures. Kaolinite minerals  occur predominantly in soils which are low in Ca and Mg and which have  undergone some leaching. These conditions are more likely to occur in softs  of the subpolar desert zone than in softs of the polar or cold desert zones.  The kaolinite in Polar Desert softs of Cornwallis Island may be inherited from  the sedimentary rocks contained in the drift.  Clay-size mineral alteration in Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils may be  depicted as in Fig. 7.  The degree of clay-mineral alteration in polar soils has been debated for  twenty years. In the polar desert zone, Tedrow et al. (1968) and Everett  (1968) were unable to detect consistent weathering differences in the clay  fraction of Polar Desert softs as a function of soil depth. In contrast to these  findings, Isherwood (1975), Bockheim (1979a), and Evans and Cameron  (1979) reported a reduction in mica and an increase in vermiculite with soil  age in Polar Desert softs on southern Baffin Island. Glazovskaya (1958),    Muscovite  mica  Hydrated mica  Vermiculite  , MontmorilLonite  Chlorltized (Fe) montmoPillonite  COLD DESERT    Feldspar    Kaolinite  POLAR DESERT    Fig.7. Clay-size mineral alteration.    63    Claridge (1965), Ugolini and Jackson (1977), and others presented evidence  favoring transformation of clay minerals in Cold Desert soils. In contrast,  Everett (1971) reported few changes in clay mineralogy of Cold Desert soils  ranging in age from about 4,400 to possibly 3.9 m. yr BP. Bockheim (1979b)  found no differences in clay-mineral suites of Cold Desert soils on moraines  deposited by the Wright Lower Glacier, which may range in age from about  3,100 to about 850,000 yr BP. In a chronosequence of softs in Taylor Valley,  Antarctica, Pastor and Bockheim (1980) found a broadening of the 001 re-  flection of mica due to hydration. Although the softs ranged from 200,000 to  possibly 3 m yr in age, no other clay mineral transformations were recorded.    Some problems in classifying polar soils    In addition to using the zonal system of Tedrow (1977), an attempt was  made to classify the softs considered in this study according to the Canadian  and U.S. taxonomic systems. Cold Desert softs of Antarctica which contain  an ice-cemented frost table within 75 cm of the surface (profiles 77-36, 77-46;  Table III) often feature marked evidence of cryoturbation; these soils are  Turbic Cryosols in the Canadian system (Canadian Soil Survey Committee,  1978). The other Cold Desert softs and the Polar Desert soils of Cornwallis  Island are Static Cryosols, because they have some form of permafrost with-  in 1 m of the surface but they show little or no evidence of cryoturbation.  Polar Desert soils on Baffin Island do not have an ice-cemented frost table  within 1 m of the surface. Soil temperature measurements at a depth of 1 m  were not taken. However, Evans and Cameron (1979) obtained a reading  greater than 0 at 1 m in a Polar Desert soil on southeastern Baffin Island.    64    If this reading is correct, Polar Desert soils on southern Baffin Island may be  Dystric Brunisols rather than Static Cryosols. Therefore, without monitoring  the soil temperature at 1 m for two or more years in succession, it becomes  impossible, using the Canadian system, to classify soils at the southern limit  of the subpolar desert zone which contain permafrost.  Another criticism of the Canadian system is related to the concept of the  Cryosol. Tedrow (1977, p. 115,118) advocated distinguishing patterned  ground formation from soil formation. He viewed cryoturbation as a mechani-  cal influence and not as a soft-forming process. Cryoturbation leads to the  degradation of soil horizons rather than their formation.  In the U.S. soil taxonomic system (U.S. Soil Survey Staff, 1975), most of  the soils analyzed in the present study contain greater than 35% coarse material  and are Pergelic Cryorthents. Profile 77-36 has an ice-core at 8 cm and is  not a soil according to the U.S. system.  There is nearly universal agreement among polar soil scientists that the arid  climate is a predominant soil-forming factor in high latitudes. Tedrow (1966)  recognized the importance of calcification, salinization and alkalization in  Polar Desert soils, as did Claridge (1965) in Cold Desert soils. Claridge and  Campbell (1968) found Cold Desert softs to be somewhat comparable to  those occurring in temperate deserts.  Some Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils could be recognized as special  arid members of the Entisols and others as weakly developed members of  the Aridisols. Polar Desert and Cold Desert softs without B horizons could be  recognized at the subgroup level as an extragrade, i.e., Aridic Pergelic Cryor-  thent. This would differentiate Polar Desert soils from Alpine soils (also Pergelic  Cryorthents), such as those occurring in the Rocky Mountains, U.S.A., with  udic soil moisture regimes. Polar Desert and Cold Desert softs with B horizons  could be placed in the Aridisols. However, Aridisols must have either an  aridic or a torric soil moisture regime. An aridic soil moisture regime does not  include soils with a pergelic soil temperature regime (U.S. Soil Survey Staff,  1975, p.55). Therefore, the aridic soil moisture regime would have to be  modified to include soils with pergelic soil temperature regimes.  The most logical great group for Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils with  B horizons would be the Camborthids, which are Aridisols with cambic  horizons. Presence of a cambic horizon is precluded from polar soils derived  from coarse-textured parent materials such as those in this study. The defini-  tion of the cambic horizon would have to be changed so as to include: (1) softs  with textures coarser than loamy fine sand, and (2) soils without the develop-  ment of structure but with a dry consistence which is weakly to strongly  coherent, i.e., not noncoherent. In temperate regions, as well as high-latitude  regions, this would distinguish stable sandy soils from those derived from  loose, shifting sands (Psamments). Emphasis on properties of the cambic  horizon wotfld thereby be given to: (1) the residual concentration of ses-  quioxides, silicate clays, or both; (2) the higher chroma or redder hue than  an underlying horizon in the same sequum; (3) the alteration of the original    TABLE VI  Classification of Polar Desert and Cold Desert soils    65    Soil taxa                             Profiles*    Non-soil  Aridic Pergelic Cryorthent;  ice-cemented permafrost  Aridic Pergelic Cryorthent;  dry permafrost  Pergelic Camborthid; dry  permafrost  Salic Pergelic Camborthid;  dry permafrost    77-36 (CD)  74-18 (PD), 73-7 (PD), 73-8 (PD),  73-9 (PD), 77-46 (CD)  76-21 (CD)    74-41 (PD), 74-40 (PD), 74-43 (PD),  75-15 (CD), 77-52 (CD)  77-14 (CD)    *PD = Polar Desert; CD = Cold Desert.    rock structure. This definition follows points 2, 3, and 4 for B horizons,  as given in the U.S. soil taxonomy (U.S. Soil Survey Staff, 1975, p.460). If the  soil temperature regime is cryic or pergelic, the base of the cambic horizon  does not have to be at least 25 cm below the surface (U.S. Soil Survey Staff,  1975, p.33).  Desert softs of the Arctic and Antarctic could be distinguished at the sub-  group level on the basis of salt content. A salic horizon must be at least 15 cm  thick and must contain a secondary enrichment of salts more soluble in cold  water than gypsum. It must contain at least 2% salts, and the product of its  thickness (cm) and its salt content (% by mass) must be 60 or more. Therefore,  a soil with an electrical conductivity (1:5 soil:water extract} of greater than  6.25 mmho/cm over a depth of 30 cm would contain a salic horizon. Of the  soils listed in Table IV, profile 77-14 contains a salic horizon. Salic could be  added as an adjective for an extragrade, e.g., Salic Pergelic Camborthid.  Finally, it would be desirable to distinguish softs containing ice-cemented  permafrost from those with "dry" permafrost at the family level, e.g., Pergelic  Cryorthent, coarse-skeletal, mixed, ice-cemented permafrost.  Using the forementioned scheme, the soils for which data are provided in  Tables II through V would be classified as shown in Table VI.  The soils on the list increase In development and age (see also Table II)  from top to bottom. This classification scheme reflects the arid nature of the  climate in high-latitude polar regions, indicates the presence of salic horizons  and differentiates soils with ice-cemented permafrost from those with "dry"  permafrost. The modifications would require minor changes in the U.S. soil  taxonomic system, and at the same time, would differentiate among well-drained  soils at high latitudes.    CONCLUSIONS    The availability of liquid water is important in polar soils relative to the  movement and accumulation of soluble salts, chemical weathering of clay    66    colloids, and cryoturbation. In the high Arctic (ca. 74), the mean monthly  temperature of the warmest month is above 0. At equivalent latitudes in  Antarctica, the temperature rarely exceeds 0 except for a few days. Where-  as rainfall is common in the polar desert zone, particularly during the summer,  rainfall has never been recorded in the cold desert zone of Antarctica. Snow  falling on soils of Antarctica only rarely melts in inland areas and generally  is removed by katabatic winds or by sublimation. Antarctic soils commonly  contain less than 2% field moisture (Ugolini, 1964). Cruikshank (1971) re-  corded field moisture contents ranging between 10 and 18% in Polar Desert  softs on Cornwallis Island.  Although published soft-moisture data are not available for Polar Desert  soils in the subpolar desert zone, the climatic data in Table I suggest that  these softs are more moist than Cold Desert soils of the same parent material.  A greater amount of moisture in Polar Desert soils in the subpolar desert zone  would enable them to become more deeply weathered than Cold Desert soils  of an equivalent age. This is reflected in the greater amount of dithionite-ex-  tractable iron and clay in Polar Desert soils, particularly in the subpolar  desert zone, as compared to Cold Desert soils.  Soluble salts are more abundant in Cold Desert softs than in Polar Desert  soils of an equivalent age. Salt patches and salt-cemented pans have not been  reported in soils of the high Arctic. The rate of accumulation of soluble salts  is about 500 times as great in Cold Desert soils as in Polar Desert soils (Fig.6).  Despite the greater concentration of salts in Cold Desert soils, they appear to  have originated from the same source as those in Polar Desert soils. Sodium  and CI- are the dominant ions in water extracts, and mirabilite (Na2SO4- 10H20)  is the dominant salt of surface encrustations of Cold Desert and of Polar  Desert soils at latitudes above ca. 78. Based on ionic ratios, the salts appear  to have originated from marine aerosols.  Leaching is not readily apparent in Cold Desert softs and in Polar Desert  softs of Cornwallis Island. Salts contributed by marine aerosols may be car-  ried downward in the soil profiles by water released from small amounts of  melting snow and may accumulate over long periods of time. Some of the  moisture may be contributed by melting during the downward recession of the  ice-cemented frost table through time. Ugolini and Anderson (1973) showed  that Naand C1- migrate upward in frozen Cold Desert soils via unfrozen  films of water on clay colloid surfaces. In older soils these processes lead to the  formation of a salic horizon or a salt-cemented pan. Because of a greater amount  of precipitation, lower pH values, and lower concentrations of soluble salts,  leaching is more evident in Polar Desert soils of the subpolar desert zone than  in the other softs considered. However, Polar Desert softs of the subpolar  desert zone are nevertheless aridic in that they are probably dry in all parts of  the solum more than half of the time and are never moist in some or all parts  for as long as 90 consecutive days. The low (5.5--6.0) pH values of several  Cold Desert softs is due to the salt effect rather than to leaching.  Wind is an important soft-forming agent in Antarctica in redistributing    67    snow, in abrading rocks, and in producing a desert pavement. The desert  pavement in Cold Desert softs is more strongly developed than that in Polar  Desert soils of an equivalent age.  Polar Desert and Cold Desert softs contain an abundance of vermiculite  and mica. Whereas Polar Desert soils also have kaolinite, Cold Desert soils  often contain montmorillonite. The presence of montmorillonite in Cold  Desert softs may be due to the greater aridity in Antarctica than in the high  Arctic. Despite the cold temperatures and lack of liquid water, clay-mineral  alterations occur in the two soft groups. Micas may become hydrated and  expanding layer species may be produced. The silt content of the soils analy-  zed in the present study is generally greater in Polar Desert soils than in  Cold Desert softs. The silt probably originates as loess from floodplains of  braided Arctic streams. Broad floodplains providing a source of silt do not  exist in Antarctica.  A soil as arid and salt-enriched as the mature Cold Desert soil does not  seem to exist in the Northern Hemisphere. As Tedrow (1977) pointed out,  the Southern Hemisphere analog of the Polar Desert soil may occur in  Antarctica at latitudes of 60--65. The search for Polar Desert softs in  Antarctica should be made on well-drained landscapes older than 120,000  yr BP, possibly in Enderby Land or along ihe Antarctic Peninsula.  In order to differentiate among polar softs, the following modifications  of the U.S. soft taxonomic system are suggested:  (1) The aridic nature of weakly developed (i.e., without B horizons) Cold  Desert and Polar Desert softs be recognized at the subgroup level by the  extragrade adjective "aridic".  (2) The aridic soil moisture regime be changed so as to include dry and  cold soils, i.e., softs with a pergelic soil temperature regime.  (3) The cambic horizon be redefined so as to include structureless, but  coherent, soils coarser than loamy fine sand.  (4) Polar softs with a salic horizon be recognized as extragrades at the sub-  group level with the adjective "salic".  (5) Softs containing ice-cemented permafrost be distinguished from those  with "dry" permafrost at the family level.  These changes would be minor but would adequately separate the more  arid Cold Desert softs from less arid Cold Desert and Polar Desert soils and  would show the desert nature of the soils. Finally, the changes would reflect  differences in degree of development of the soils.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Baffin Island research was funded by contract 74-112 to J.T. Andrews, Uni-  versity of Colorado, by Parks Canada, Department of Indian Affairs. Antarctic  research was funded by contract DPP 74-20991 to G.H. Denton, University  of Maine, by the Division of Polar Programs, National Science Foundation.  T.M. Ballard, University of British Columbia, provided chemical data for the  softs on Cornwallis Island. J.E. Leide read the manuscript.    68    REFERENCES    American Public Health Association, American Water Works Association and Water Pol-  lution Control Federation, 1975. Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and  Wastewater, 14th ed., 1193 pp.  Behling, R.E., 1971. Pedological Development on Moraines of the Meserve Glacier, Antarc-  tica. Ph.D. Diss., Ohio State Univ., Columbus, 216 pp.  Bockheim, J.G., 1977. Soil development in the Taylor Valley and McMurdo Sound area.  Antarct. J., U.S., 12: 105--108.  Bockheim, J.G., 1979a. Properties and relative age of soils of southwestern Cumberland  Peninsula, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada. Arct. Alp. Res., 11: 289--306.  Bockheim, J.G., 1979b. Relative age and origin of soils in eastern Wright Valley, Antarctica.  Soil Sci., 128: 142--152.  Buntley, G.J. and Westin, F.C., 1965. A comparative study of developmental color in a  Chestnut-Chernozem-Brunizem soil climosequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29: 579--  582.  Campbell, I.B. and Claridge, G.G.C., 1969. A classification of frigic soils -- the zonal soils  of the Antarctic continent. Soil Sci., 107: 75--85.  Campbell, I.B. and Claridge, G.G.C., 1975. Morphology and age relationships of Antarctic  soils. In: R.P. Suggate and M.M. Cresswell (Editors), Quaternary Studies. The Royal  Society of New Zealand, Wellington, pp. 83--88.  Canadian Soil Survey Committee, Subcommittee on Soil Classification, 1978. The Canadian  System of Soil Classification. Can. Dep. Agric. Publ., 1646:164 pp.  Claridge, G.G.C., 1965. The clay mineralogy and chemistry of some soils from the Ross  Dependency, Antarctica. N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 8: 186--220.  Claridge, G.G.C. and Campbell, I.B., 1968. Some features of Antarctic soils and their  relation to other desert soils. Trans. 9th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 4: 541--549.  Claridge, G.G.C. and Campbell, I.B., 1977. The soils in Antarctic soils, their distribution  and relationship to soil processes. Soil Sci., 123: 377--384.  Cruikshank, J.G., 1971. Soils and terrain units around Resolute, Cornwallis Island. Arctic,  24: 195--209.  Day, J.H., 1964. Characteristics of soils of the Hazen Camp area, northern Ellesmere  Island, N.W.T. Operation Hazen, Defense Res. Board (Ottawa), Hazen, 24:15 pp.  Day, P.R., 1965. Particle fractionation and particle-size analysis. In: C.A. Black et al.  (Editors), Methods of Soil Analysis. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, WI, pp. 545--567.  Evans, L.J. and Cameron, B.H., 1979. A chronosequence of soils developed from granitic  morainal material, Baffin Island, N.W.T. Can. J. Soil ScL, 59: 203--210.  Everett, K.R., 1968. Soil development in the Mould Bay and Isachsen areas, Queen Eliza-  beth Islands, Northwest Territories, Canada. Inst. Polar Studies, Ohio State Univ.,  Columbus, 75 pp.  Everett, K.R., 1971. Soils of the Meserve Glacier area, Wright Valley, south Victoria Land,  Antarctica. Soil Sci., 112: 425--438.  Glazovskaya, M.A., 1958. Weathering and primary soil formation in Antarctica. Inst.  Geol. Geogr. Sci., Moscow Univ., Sci. Pap., 1: 63--76. (Transl. from the Russian by  M. Czapowskyj ).  Isherwood, D.J., 1975. Soil Geochemistry and Rock Weathering in an Arctic Environment.  Ph.D. Diss., Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, 173 pp.  Kelly, W.C. and Zumberge, J.H., 1961. Weathering of a quartz diorite at Marble Point,  MeMurdo Sound, Antarctica. J. Geol., 69: 433--446.  Linkletter, G.O., Jr., 1971. Weathering and Soil Formation in Antarctic Dry Valleys. Ph.  D. Diss., Univ. of Washington, Seattle, 122 pp.  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a  dithionite-citrate buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7: 317--327.    69    Pastor, J. and Bockheim, J.G., 1980. Soil development on moraines of Taylor Glacier,  Lower Taylor Valley, Antarctica. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44 (in press).  Rieger, S., 1974. Arctic soils. In: J.D. Ives and R.G. Barry (Editors), Arctic and Alpine  Environments. Methuen, London, pp. 749--769.  Rozov, N.N. and Ivanova, E.N., 1967. Classification of the soils of the USSR. Soy. Soil  Sci., 2: 147--156; 3: 288--300.  Tarnocai, C., 1978. Distribution of soils in northern Canada and parameters affecting  their utilization. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., llth, 3: 281--304.  Tedrow, J.C.F., 1966. Polar Desert soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 30: 381--387.  Tedrow, J.C.F., 1968. Pedogenic gradients in the polar regions. J. Soil Sci., 19: 197--204.  Tedrow, J.C.F., 1970. Soil investigations in Inglefield Land, Greenland. Medd. Groenl.,  188(3): 93 pp.  Tedrow, J.C.F., 1977. Soils of the Polar Regions. Rutgers Univ. Press, New Brunswick,  N.J., 638 pp.  Tedrow, J.C.F. and Thompson, C.C., 1969. Chemical composition of polar soils. Biul.  Peryglac., 18: 169--181.  Tedrow, J.C.F. and Ugolini, F.C., 1966. Antarctic soils. In: J.C.F. Tedrow (Editor), An-  tarctic Soils and Soil-forming Processes (Antarctic Res. Ser., 8). Am. Geophys. Union,  pp, 161--177.  Tedrow, J.C.F., Bruggemann, P.F. and Walton, G.F., 1968. Soils of Prince Patrick Island.  Arct. Inst. N. Am. Res. Pap., 44:82 pp.  Thompson, T.G. and Nelson, K.H., 1956. Concentration of brines and deposition of salts  from sea water under frigid conditions. Am. J. Sci., 254: 227--238.  Ugolini, F.C., 1964. Pedological investigations in the lower Wright Valley, Antarctica. Proc  Int. Conf. Permafrost, Natl. Acad. Sci., Natl. Res. Counc., pp. 55--61.  Ugolini, F.C. and Anderson, D.M., 1973. Ionic migration and weathering in frozen Antarc-  tic soils. Soil Sci., 115: 461--470.  Ugolini, F.C. and Jackson, M.L., 1977. Weathering and mineral synthesis in Antarctic soils.  Third Symp. Antarct. Geol. Geophys., Aug. 22--27, 1977, Madison, WI.  U.S. Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil survey manual. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 18:503 pp.  U.S. Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil taxonomy: a basic system of soil classification for  making and interpreting soil surveys. In: U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Agric.  Handbook, 436:754 pp.  Whittig, L.D., 1965. X-ray 4iffraction techniques for mineral identification and mineralogi-  cal composition. In: C.A. Black et al. (Editors), Methods of Soil Analysis. Am. Soc.  Agron., Madison, WI, pp. 671--698.  Wilson, A.T. and House, D.A., 1965. Chemical composition of south polar snow. J. Geo-  phys. Res., 70: 5515--5517.  Zoltai, S.C. and Tarnocai, C., 1974. Soils and vegetation of hummocky terrain. Environ.  Social Comm., Task Force North. Oil Dev., Rep., 74-5:86 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractPolar Desert soils in the Arctic (66 and 74N latitude) are contrasted with Cold Desert soils in the Antarctic (77S). The soils are derived from sandy-skeletal glacial drift and have not been influenced by cryoturbation. Pedogenic horizons are limited to a desert pavement (designated D) and to a weak B horizon in the oldest soils of both groups. Solum thickness increases with age in the two soil groups; however, because of a slightly greater amount of soil moisture, the increase in solum thickness is greater for Polar Desert soils. Soils of both groups often contain dry permafrost. The Polar Desert soils at 74N and most of the Cold Desert soils are neutral to mildly alkaline and the Polar Desert soils at 66N are strongly to medium acid. Although soluble salts increase with age in soils of both groups, the increase is more marked in the more arid Cold Desert soils. Results from this study and a survey of the literature show that sodium is the prevalent cation in water extracts of Cold Desert soils and in Polar Desert soils above ca. 80N. Chloride is the major anion in Cold Desert soils in the McMurdo Sound vicinity and in noncalcareous Polar Desert soils. Ion ratios indicate that salts in these soils are contributed by marine aerosols. The soils examined contain less than 5% clay-size (&lt; 2 m) material. Mica, vermiculite and kaolinite are the predominant phyllosilicate minerals in the clay fractions of Polar Desert soils, and mica, vermiculite and montmorillonite are most abundant in Cold Desert soils. A scheme contrasting clay-mineral alteration in soils of the two groups is provided. In the Canadian system, the Cold Desert soils are Static Cryosols, and the Polar Desert soils are either. Static Cryosols or Dystric Brunisols. In the U.S. system, the soils are Pergelic Cryorthents. Suggestions are given to modify the U.S. system so as to better distinguish polar soils. 