 Geoderma, 28 (1982) 63--64                                                  63  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Compendium of Soil Fungi. K.H. Domsch, W. Gams and T-H. Anderson.  Academic Press, London, 1980, 2 volumes: 1,860 pp.; 2:406 pp.;  resp. 57.00 (US $137.00) and $ 23.00 (US $ 55.00).    An alphabetic order of fungi does not occur very commonly in books on  mycology. This characteristic together with the limitation of the number of  monographs to a selection of soil fungi makes this book very useful not only  for soil-mycologists but also for the group of non-taxonomists belonging to  various disciplines including phytopathology, physiology, medicine and  ecology. The book has appeared in two volumes: the first volume containing  monographs on 400 species of fungi, the second volume being essentially  literature references (6593 items) together with an index of fungal names  occurring in the first volume and a classification of and keys to the genera  treated (18 pp.).  According to the authors the 'users needs' have to a great extent been the  guiding principle for the selection of material for this book: "Most species  likely to be encountered in soil fungal analyses are included". It is a more  comprehensive version of the first book by the same authors called Fungi  in Agricultural Soils (1972) presenting now condensed data on a far greater  number of carefully selected soft fungi.  Each description of a fungus consists of three sections: taxonomy, ecology  and physiology (a.o., nutrient requirements).  The keys to species are dichotomous except for Fusarium. For this genus  there is a synoptic key. This key works rapidly and safely for the species  tested sofar in the laboratory for phytopathology in Wageningen. An excep-  tion may be F. ventricosum. For Fusarium species of which a teleomorph  is known the description of the speciesis arranged under the genus of the  ascigerous state. This holds also for other pleomorphic species.  Many useful cultural characteristics on other bases than morphology have  been added; e.g., on odour: 'odour often suggesting toiletsoap' (Cylindro-  carpon destructans ).  The numerous data on ecology and physiology are remarkably exhaustive  and concisely presented. This feature contributes highly to the value of this  compendium. The book contains very few printing errors (the semidpozol'  on p. 14 is probably a kind of podzol). The exchange of pages 146 and 149  is a regrettable accident. The editor should be blamed for not adding an  erratum to every copy.  There is no doubt that the authors have done a major effort to write a  book which will be the latest authority on soil fungi for a long time to come.  Many excellent line drawings, photographs and scanning electron micro-  graphs illustrate the work.  The english language as used in the book sounds perfectly allright as far    64    as the present reviewer is competent to judge.  An enormous amount of work has led to the production of a highly valu-  able compendium which certainly will serve many 'users needs'.    D. MULDER  (Wageningen)    Soil Science Simplified. M.I. Harpstead and F.D. Hole, illustrated by M. Bratz.  Iowa University Press, Ames, Iowa, 1980, 122 pp. US$7.75    Not only have the authors, both well-known teachers of soil science, suc-  ceeded in simplifying soil science in their book, but the illustrator, Miss  Bratz, has also contributed essentially with her 129 pictures to achieving  the aim of the book: a summary of basic information about soil science as  a guide to the study of soils by both the layperson and the natural scientist.  In twelve chapters the authors cover nearly the whole field: The soil around  us; Soft physical properties; Clays; Humus; Cation exchange; Water and tem-  perature; Soil classification; Plant nutrition; Engineering uses of soil; Soil  organisms; Soil classification; Soil landscapes, ending with a glossary with  some 200 entries and an index.  Being an old hand myself, and at present trying to edit a new Dutch book  on the same subject (25 authors and some 1000 pp.) I cannot help wondering:  is soil science as simple as this?  The book is well-suited for high~chool earth-science curricula and for  university students in many fields of natural science.  Some critical remarks: Soils are mappable, there are only few remarks  about soft maps on p. 86; in the last section (soft landscape appreciation)  even a few remarks about land evaluation are lacking.    H. DE BAKKER  (Wageningen)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            