 359    CONTENTS VOLUME 32, 1984    Total lead concentrations in Scottish soils  G.A. Reaves and M.L. Berrow (Aberdeen, Great Britian)  ....................  1  The importance of variable charge due to amorphous siliceous clay constituents in some  soils from Kenya  W.G. Wielemaker (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  ........................  9  Properties, weathering and classification of some soils formed in peralkaline volcanic  ash in Kenya  W.G. Wielemaker (Wageningen, The Netherlands) and T. Wakatsuki  (Matsue, Japan)  ..............................................  21  The origin and early genesis of clay bands in youthful sandy soils along Lake Michigan,  U.S.A.  R.C. Berg (Champaign, II., U.S.A.)  .................................  45  The effects of electrolyte concentrations on calcium~sodium exchange equilibria in  two soil samples of India  S.R. Poonia, S.C. Mehta and Raj Pal (Hissar, India)  ......................  63  Book Review  Proceedings of the Bangkok Symposium on Acid Sulphate Soils, by H. Dost and  N. van Breemen (Editors) -- D.S. Fanning  ............................  71    Current Titles in Soil Science  .......................................  75  Effect of organic matter on CEC due to permanent and variable charges in selected  temperate region soils  K.H. Tan and P.S. Dowling (Athens, Ga., U.S.A.)  .......................  89  Clay mineralogy of a soil sequence in slope deposits derived from Hauptdolomit  (dolomite) in the Bavarian Alps  B.M. Wilke (Bayreuth, Bundesrepublik Deutschland), V.-K. Mishra and  K.E. Rehfuess (Milnchen, Bundesrepublik Deutschland)  ..................  103  Extractable lead concentrations in Scottish soils  G.A. Reaves and M.L. Berrow (Aberdeen, Great Britain)  ..................  117  A climosequence of soils on Late Quaternary volcanic ash in highland Papua New Guinea  C.J. Chartres and C.F. Pain (Kensington, N.S.W., Australia)  ................  131  Book Review  Advanced Techniques for Clay Mineral Analysis, by J.J. Fripiat (Editor) --  J.D. Russell  ...............................................  157    Other Publications Received  ......................................  159  Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  161  Textural differentiation in chronosequences from eastern Australia  D.J. Chittleborough (Adelaide, S.A., Australia), P.H. Walker (Canberra City,  A.C.T., Australia) and J.M. Oades (Glen Osmond, S.A., Australia)  I. Descriptions, chemical properties and micromorphologies of soils  ..........  181  II. Evidence from particle-size distributions  ..........................  203  III. Evidence from elemental chemistry  .............................  227  Announcement  ...............................................  249  Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  251  Characteristics of soil profiles affected by smelting of nickel and copper at Coniston,  Ontario, Canada  P.W. Hazlett, G.K. Rutherford and G.W. van Loon (Kingston, Ont., Canada)  ....  273  Oxidation-reduction regimes in some Oxisols of tropical China  C.P. Ding, Z.G. Liu and T.R. Yu (Nanjing, People's Republic of China)  ........  287    360    Development and use of soil productivity ratings in the United States  J.H. Huddleston (Corvallis, Ore., U.S.A.)  ............................  297  Phosphate adsorption by dark alkaline vertisols in Greece  A.E. Nychas and C.S. Kosmas (Athens, Greece)  ........................  319  Concentric zonation of gleyed soils under individual tree canopies in south-  western British Columbia, Canada  C.B. Crampton (Burnaby, B.C., Canada)  ............................  329  A motorized grinder for making soil thin sections  A.J. Low, E.J. Low and L.A. Douglas (New Brunswick, N.J., U.S.A.)  ..........  335  Iron mobilization by heathland plant extracts  C.G. Fisher and Oi-Lai Yam (London, Great Britain)  ....................  339  Current Titles in Soil Science  .....................................  347                                                                                                   