 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 21--34                                                         21  Elsevier Science Publishers B V., Amsterdam -- Printed m The Netherlands    CHARACTERIZATION OF IN SITU ORGANIC MATTER  CONSTITUENTS IN VERTISOLS FROM ARGENTINA, USING  SUBMICROSCOPIC AND CYTOCHEMICAL METHODS -- FIRST  REPORT    S. STEPHANL, J. BERRIER~, A A. DE PETRE3, C. JEANSON4, M J KOOISTRAs,  H.W SCHARPENSEEL' and H SCHIFFMANN6   lnstztut fur Bodenkunde der Unzversit~t Nussallee 13, 5300 Bonn (F.R.G.)  2 C.N.R.A., D~parternent de Sczence du Sol, Etoile de Choisy, Route de Samt-Cyr,  78000 Versadles (France)  3 Facultad de Clencias Agropecuartas, Unwersidad Nacional de Entre R[os, Tezanos  Pinto, E R. (Argentina)  4 C N R.S, MusOum National d 'Histozre Naturelle, 4 Avenue du Petit Chateau, 91800  Brunoy (France)   Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6 700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)   Ordinariat fur Bodenkunde der Universitat, Von-Melle-Park 10, 2000 Hamburg (F.R.G.)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Stephan, S , Berrmr, J, De Petre, A.A, Jeanson, C., Kooistra, M.J., Scharpenseel, H W.  and Schiffmann, H., 1983. Characterization of in situ organic matter constituents in  vertisols from Argentina, using submicroscopm and cytochemical methods -- First  report Geoderma, 30  21--34    The investigation of residence, alteration and circulation of soil organic matter is an  ideal problem for integrated research including mmroscopy and submicroscopic methods.  The subject of the present study is an argillic Pelludert of Argentina The organic matter  in this sod shows an unexpectedly steep gradient of ~4C age. Below 25 cm the frequency  of microscopic organic features decreases rapidly. Only few types are present at greater  depth. Features produced by faunal activity, as well as brown to black areas of different  composition have been investigated with SEM-EDXRA. The main subjects of laser-  induced mass spectra were dark grains of few microns diameter whmh abound in the fine  mass. Some spectra are presented and discussed. Further investigations are planned in  order to demonstrate how submicroscopy, associated to the physico-chemmal methods,  can contribute to the knowledge and to the comprehension of the genesis of Vertisols.    INTRODUCTION    The investigation of soft organic matter (O.M.) by bulk analysis is reaching  the limits of usefulness. Further work may be expected to use in situ deter-  minations as well as the isolation of individual organic constituents (plant,    0016-7061/83/$03 00   1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    22    animal, fungal, bacterial and derived products) which show interestmg  chemical composition and turnover behavlour. Our intention is not to re-  place bulk analysis but to supplement it in order to increase our knowledge  of soil organic matter and improve our interpretation of soil processes. The  investigation of residence times, alteratzon and circulation of O.M. is an ideal  problem for integrated research using microscopic and submicroscopic  methods.  The subject of our work is a Vertlsol of the Yerua series (PNUD, FAO,  INTA, 1967), an Arglllic Pelludert with a gllgai relief of 5 m crest to crest  distance, situated In the Entre Rios province of Argentina at 5825'W 31 26'S on a shght slope, 30 m above sea level. The soil has been formed from  a Quaternary clay-rich marl; the annual precipitation is approximately  1000 mm and the mean annual temperature is about 19. The dominating  factor, however, is the high clay content, with a preponderance of smectlte,  some ilhte and traces of kaolinite. Fig. I presents some conventional data ob-  tained from samples of the gllgal trough. We emphasise the high swelhng  capacity shown by a COLE value of up to 0.16.    p, OM[c;, COLE C%~03 COLOUS  %,                 o     roOtS|  {2}       (3)   (~)  61Z612    0 102/YR1  I0 YR  634     II  016    0     2/1  0  6541  12  016   10    YR  3  3/!  722210 01Z  6  10 VR  3/2  721~   9   016     7    7.5YR  ~/2  7./05 9    7 7,5 YR  5/~    tTE~KTURE SLrCKEN-INTER-  CoCO3Fe-Mn  SLOES  SECTING IOOuLECON-  CAETIOI  p,P  /   0  0  2  P, Pr   3     3  I 0   2  Pr, W  3   3   1  2  PeW  3   3   3  2  Pr.W  2    0   3  2  ~oC pr.  W.P  !   0  3  2    Fig. 1  Analytic data of the Yerua pedon_ (1) grain size distribution, a = 0--2 .m, b =  2--20 um, c = 20--50 urn, d = 50 urn--2 mm; (2) organic matter; (3) carbonate noted as  CaCO3, (4) Munsell scale, (5) p = subpolyhedrons, P = polyhedrons, Pr = prisms, W =  wedges, C = coherent; (6) 0 = absent, 1 = trace to 3 = many    23    MATERIAL    Bulk analysis and some microscopic work was done on air-dried material  collected in 1979. Other in situ investigations, including some more micro-  morphological work have been made on small, undisturbed samples collected  in 1980, freeze&lt;lried in Argentina and distributed to the various laboratories.    RESULTS    Carbon dating of the O.M (Table I)    The 14C analysis (Scharpenseel and Pietig, 1968/69; Scharpenseel, 1972)  produced an unexpectedly steep age gradient. The sample from only 15--30  cm gives an age of 1100 years, and the age rises to more than 4000 years at  75--90 cm, despite evidence of swelling and shrinking as well as faunal ac-  tivity including a number of earthworm holes visible on the wall.    TABLEI    Carbon dating of O M  Depth                 Age (LIBBY)  (cm)                      years before present    0--15                     0.I  15--30                     1120 -+ 60  30--45                  2320 + 60  45--60                    2610 + 70  60--75                     2890 _+ 70  75--90                  4140 -+ 90  90--105                  3760 + 70    ,I 14C contents 107 + 1% of the modern standard    Micromorphology    Thin sections from air&lt;tried, impregnated samples (Altemiiller, 1974) of  the 1979 material were investigated in order to estimate the number of dis-  tinct organic features (Table II). The results agree quite well with the carbon  dating data. Below a certain depth only 3 types of organic feature can be  recognized, and these do not allow any further differentiation.  The freeze-dried samples were taken at depths of 0--5, 20--25, 40--45 and  60--65 cm, respectively. They were processed as described by Jongerius and  Heintzberger (1975) and show the same basic composition at every depth.  The soil matrix has an asepic fabric, and all samples contain small brown to  black rounded areas up to 50 um in diameter which are definitely of differ-    24  PLATE I    50#m    ---500 #m    -- 200 # rn    -- 20,urn    -- 20#m      .....  50#m    --5 ,urn    ---- [-~ ~LFT1    -- lO#m    -- 20 #m    ----lO#m    --2OO#m    --Spm              --5/~m              -- 20/Jm    25  TABLE II  Orgamc soil conshtuents in thin sections; values from 1 (=traces) up to 5 (= abundant)    Depth(cm)  5--10   25--     55--     85--     120--   137--   150--  30      60      90       125     142     155    Roots contalnmg  cellulose                 3       3       1  ....  Root remnants without  cellulose                 2       2       1  ....  Fruits and seed grams     1  ......  Fungus sclerotia          2  ......  Faecal pellets             3       2       1  ....  Dark particles of  2--6 um size             5       5       5       3       3       3       3  Dark particles smaller  than 2 ~m              5       5       5       3       3       3       3  Suberine, cutine,  chitine etc.              3       2       3       2       2       3       1    ent composition. Below 40 cm there is some evidence of current clay illuvia-  tion processes. The influence of the fauna is important above 25 cm, but is  of minor influence below that depth. The fauna is responsible for the pro-  duction of a relatively small number of primary voids, for the fragmentation  of O.M., for the mixing of organic and mineral materials in their alimentary  canals, and for the transport of organic and mineral particles within the soil.  As a result of the faunal activity the humus form of the topsoil is a mull. The  quantity of O.M. in the form of faecal pellets decreases rapidly with depth;  below 25 cm the void system is mainly determined by physical processes,  and only few of the voids are produced by roots or soil fauna.    PLATE I  Mineral material and organo-rnineral complexes in a Vertisol, investigated with SEM-  EDXRA.  1--5. AI horizon, 0--4.5 cm depth: 1. polyhedric aggregates associated with roots; 2. ag-  gregates on a root fragment; 3 detail of 2, clay and silt particles connected by amorphous  substance; 4. diatom (very clear Si peak with EDXRA) in contact with argillic par-  ticles; 5. detail of 4.  6--10. B~I horizon, 20--24.5 cm depth: 6. poorly individualized aggregates, absence of  roots, presence of numerous pores; 7. fungus filaments in a pore, 8. jointed fungus fila-  ment in contact with clay particles, fragment of a diatom; 9. thecamoeba, St, Al, Ca, Ti;  10. numerous long minerals, amphiboles (?), Si, Fe, Ca, Ti, Na, Mg.  11--13. B~ horizon, 40--44.5 crn depth' 11. poorly individualized aggregates, absence of  roots, numerous nodules; 12. clay cutans, very numerous and of different thmkness; 13.  detail of 12.  14--15. B22 horizon, 60--64 5 cm depth  14. jolntmg cuneiform aggregates, plant debris  with or without visible cell structure; 15 detail of 14, plant debris covered with amor-  phous substance comprising mineral particles.    26  PLATE II    --50,urn    100 #m    25,urn    -- 25 #m    --lO,um    -- 10 ~m    --25#m    --250#m    --5#m    -- 25#m    --50#m    --50 #m    20~m    27    SEM-EDXRA investigation    The submicroscopic investigation of three superficial horizons permits to  characterize: the microstructures; O.M., its alteration and association with  minerals; micro-organisms or the traces of their activity (Jeanson, 1981). It  refines in this way the knowledge and comprehension of the pedogenetic  mechanisms.  The well separated subpolyhedric microaggregates of the A horizon impart  a certain fragility to this material (Plate I, 1). At certain depth however, the  aggregates are hardly individualized and the microstructures more compact  (Plate I, 6, 11, 14).  The abounding plant fragments in the A horizon are only slightly decom-  posed with clearly visible cells (Plate II, 1--3). Anyhow, they are colonized  by fungus mycelium throughout the A and B2, horizon (Plate II, 4, 5), and  the cell walls suffered by fungus lysis and subsequent lysis by bacteria (Plate  II, 6), changing the cell walls into a fine-lamellated amorphous substance  (Plate II, 10--12). In the B22 horizon there are spheric bodies of 4--8 ~m dia-  meter near the well decomposed plant debris, and the hypothesis can be  made that they have been derived from the cell material after the cell walls  have been decomposed. They bear a notable resemblance to certain brown  products of the same shape and size, which are visible by TEM in certain  humus forms.  Micro-organisms occur frequently in the superficial horizons and are often  associated with organic matter. In the A horizon the fungus mycelium is fre-  quently accompanied with protozoa and thecamoebae which have exogenlc  thecae consisting of mineral grains of the environment (Plate II, 1--3). There  are also thecamoebae and diatoms in contact with minerals (Plate I, 4, 5, 9).  Traces of the activity of earth-consuming organisms are well visible till more  than 20 cm depth in the compact B21 horizon. There are pores of 100 gm  diameter (Plate I, 6) and ovoid aggregates of 300 ~m length and 200 pm  width (Plate II, 7, 8). From size, shape, nature and arrangement of the    PLATE II  Organic matter and microorganlsms in a Vertisol, investigated by SEM-EDXRA.  1--4. A~ horizon, 0--4.5 cm: I. surface of a decomposing plant fragment, cell structure  poorly visible, numerous fungus filaments and thecamoebae; 2. detall of 1, clay skin of  a thecamoeba, ~ 60 #m; 3. fresh plant fragment with very clear cell structure, absence of  mycelium, broken thecamoeba, ~ 60 #m; 4 strongly decomposed plant fragment, no  plant cell visible, combined, jointed fungus filaments.  5--8. B~ horizon, 20--24.5 cm: 5. mycehum forming a very dense network on a plant  fragment; 6 detail of a plant cell wall, bacterial lysm (b)~; 7_ cluster-shaped accumulation  of subspheric aggregates, dejections of enchytreids or collemboles~; 8 detail of 7, contact  of two aggregates.  9--12 B~2 horizon, 40--44 5 cm: 9. completely decomposed plant fragment, dlffuse cell  structure; 10. detall of 9; 11. spheric body, brown substance~ ~ 4 #m; 12. lamellated  amorphous substance.  13. B22 horizon, 60--64.5 cm, plant fragment with mmeral cutan.    28    Fig 2. Two EDXRA point analyses (A and B) of different dark-coloured areas (B21 hori-  zon, 20--24.5 cm depth)_ C Rounded, dark-coloured nodules with sharp external boun-  daries, embedded m the groundmass (plane polarized hght)    aggregates, the hypothesis is deduced that they are dejections of enchy-  treldes (small earthworms) or collemboles (apterygote insects). This needs,  however, to be proved by held observations and cultures in the laboratory.  The accumulation of substances may be investigated, too. In all samples  there are small brown to black rounded areas up to 0.5 mm diameter. These  have different chemmal compositions and several origins are possible: humi-  fymg fragments of organic matter, faecal pellets, soil matrix material or O.M.  impregnated with iron and/or manganese, weathered minerals or mineral ag-  gregates. Some of these brown/black areas have been examined with SEM-    29    EDXRA. As shown by Fig. 2, most of them consisted of a clay-rich material  contaming various quantities of manganese and/or iron.    Laser-induced mass spectra    One of the more modern methods for characterismg unknown substances  is mass spectrometry. It is developing into an appropriate tool for the investi-  gation of soil orgamc matter (W. Flaig, pers. comm., 1982), and examples  of mass spectrograms of ions produced by pyrolysis of different soil mate-  rials have already been produced for several characteristic softs (Halma et al.,  1979). Ions from mdividual partmles of microscopm size may be mduced,  however, by both argon or oxygen ions (SIMS) or by a laser beam  (LAMMA). Mass spectroscopy of laser-reduced ions from small (about 1  um) parts of thin sections is practicable with the LAMMA  500 machine of  the Leybold-Heraeus Co. as mentioned by Henstra et al. (1981) and Bisdom  et al. {1981).  The samples were placed m sandwich grids and investigated at carefully  prepared edges. The analysis of some of the spectra (Figs. 3, 4) indmates that  certain particles can be differentiated, but more spectra are needed to con-  firm this. As the intensities cannot be compared with standards, and only are  appointed to five peak heights m the figures, there is no quantitative evalua-  tion possible. Hemen et al. (1979) charactenses spectra from certain types  of organic and morgamc compounds, but the interpretation of individual  mass numbers seems to be rather difficult when apphed to more complicated  systems. In the text which follows, numbers m brackets are mass numbers  observed.    Cation mass spectra (Fig. 3)    In the soil matrix of Vertisols, there are striking dark grains about 3 ~m in  size. Some of the larger ones look like organic remnants, but there also seem  to be transitions to sesquioxide accumulations. The mass spectra of these  various grains are of course quite different. In spectrum 44 Mn (55} is im-  portant whereas Fe (56) has a high peak in 61 and also contributes to the  spectra in 43 and 28. In diagrams 43, 44, 28, 55 and 61 an ion with mass  number (57) most probably represents some component of organic matter,  as do (60) in 65, (89) in 44 and (26) in spectrum 65.  Comparing these ions together with Al (27) and the quite weak peak of  Si  which always gives a rather small signal, one can distinguish between rela-  tively pure O.M. particles represented by spectrum 65, particles with pre-  dominantly inorganm compound such as 61 and mixed materials linked to-  gether by absorption.  Two Fe-Mn nodules have been investigated in order to obtain comparable  spectra of true sesquioxlde materials, here represented by spectrum 32. At    30    il, lr"  65  I    Ill  5,:11~  ~,~, ~o "  ~Y   I,  i1;'  iil !  s~F's J ~1/  ,%1,1 ~  25 30    ?0    ~l !l  7O  ]l ,,I  r  7O    ; I  7O    SMALL  DARK GRAIN                     3-5 cm  t  ,   ,  [,   ,   .         J  ........  80    90   I00    /10   120   130   I~0   ~50   150  SMALL  DARK  GRAIN                     5-10 cm  v  I;  (  .....1  1  80    90  I00   110   120   I30   1/0   150   160  SMALL  DARK GRAIN                      5 - lOcrn  v  jlL,,,ll,  ........ l , 1   ,  11  11  I  ,  I,  O0    90   Ioo   I10   12o   I30   i2o   15o " i6o  SMALL DARK GRAIN                    25-28cm  t  lllli  " ~io " :io " too ' rio " 12o ' F~o" iio t~o" tgo    SMALL DARK GRAIN                     25-30crn  v    i     !   1   ,     ,   ,   ,   ,  .........  70    80     90    tOO    110    120   130    Y/.O    150   160  SMALL DARK GRAIN                   85- 90cm v    II  70    "  '  ' s'o ' 9'0 ' i~o ' iio '  ROOT TISSUE  ,  ,  ,1                1  70   80   90  100   110  ROOt tISSUE  io " ao " 9o " Ibo ' rio '  CUTINE- SUBERINE- CHIrINE    '1~o ' tJo " t2o ' t~o " lao  3 - 5cm  t  ,  .  .l,  ,  ,  I  120   130   I~0   150 ' 160  5- I0 cm  v  ' 1~o' lJo ' iio' 1so" t6b  25- 28 cm  t    , ,,,11,  ,,,1,  40   50     60  II,,l, ,,,,  i  zo' 5'o " go  I     ,ll  1  2o' iodo  I1,:,1,o I o  ~0   50   60  I!h,, ,,,,  ~0   50     60  i  o' s'o '6b  I11         III    li       I  '    .:tO"   S'O   ",gO   "   fO   "   SO   '   ~0   "   IbO '   Ii0 '   I~0 '   fbO"   I~0'    t'SO" 1SO  II       II       FUNGUS 5CLEROFIUM                   25-28 cm  t  , ,,lii ii  ,,,,i.,,,ll ,,Ih,,,I ,i,,., L  ,,,  ,,,  " i '~l ,il~ ' '~ ' ~' " ' '~ '''~,     , ~"~'~', ,,,   , ,,~~'~,,I ,,,  ,, "li(~* '~_, ,o ~     ,,,,"11';,    .........  ,   ,   ,       i   ,  ....  ,  ....  ,lj  ,i, ;ol,j ,o J,i ,oo ,,o 1,,o .o ,o    ,   .   ,  ....  ,   ,   -       ,   ,   .  ......  ,   ,       .   .  z.o   50    60    70    80    90   too   110   120   I30   140   150   160    Fig. 3. Laser-induced cations, t = gilgai top, v = gilgai valley. Horizontal scale, mass num-  bers, vertical scale, strength of signal. I = up to 3, 2 = 4--9, 3 = 10--39, 4 = 40--69, 5 =  at least 70 units recorded.    the pomt analysed, Mn exceeds Fe. Assuming that the peak at mass number  (28) is due to Si, then besides the usual high A1 peak, there is also a strong  peak due to Si. There are also, however, organic compounds in the nodule,    31    e.g. the masses arranged around (136) and {157) as well as the ions (26) and  (57) already mentioned. We are not sure whether the peak (48) is from an  organic compound or from Ti.  Spectrum 8 represents the resin with which the samples have been impreg-  nated. It is possible to recognise spectra due to resin-contaminated matermls  by comparison with this spectrum. It is proved by this that the resin is usu-  ally confined to the pore space, as is already known from micromorphologi-  cal observations. In this spectrum, as well as in other spectra of high mole-  cular weight substances, mass numbers appear in groups of at least three con-  secutive peaks arranged round a maximum, features also visible at higher  mass numbers than those shown here. In spectrum 8 one of these groups is  arranged round (105), the mass number of styrene + H. The differences be-  tween the indwldual mass maxima could not be interpreted unequivocally.  A mass difference of 1 points to single H differences, whereas a difference  of 2 is given by different redox states of (multi-)chinone-hydrochinone sys-  tems. Both cases mentioned are easy to detect. Features hke these also ap-  pear in mass spectra of fungal material, root tissues, some of the small grams  and as is clearly ewdent, in that of the sesqumxide nodule.    Anion  mass spectra    The negative ions are dominated by organic substances. These may be due  to the acid groups which are so abundant in the O.M. of soils. Moreover,  single atoms mainly form cations, and the oxides exhibit various stages of  oxidation. In the sesquioxide nodule, spectrum 30, MnO (71) exceeds Mn  (55) and MnO2 (87), and FeO (72) exceeds Fe (56) and FeO2 (88). The  mass numbers (63) and (79) may belong to PO2 and PO3, respectively. They    5,   II Q       I         II         [ SMALL DARK GRAIN        5 - I0 crn  v  ' ~j    IJJ el lllLllL        ill     ii  ~i    z5  ,        h,   ,,.,,       , ,,...,       . ,  .0  ~0 ' Fo  ' s'o ' go " 7"o " do " 9"o " ~do " do " i~0 ~0" ~Zo ' 7~0 "  Z.     0                                SMALL DARK GRAIN        85-90 cm  v          tt  2  I129  ,,o~;o '~o ',~,o,~ao  _~o.,oo.,,o,~o,.,~o.,So.  1  5."  CUTINE-5UBERINE-CHITINE 25-28cm t/  ~  end of the dlogrorn    Ill   ,  ,,, h,    ,           j_   ,  ,~,..,,,., ~ l i i, llllh,,,lii II,,,llll,,I,,,i,illl,l,,,, I,,I,,,,. hll, l,,/,,l H Ill, i II,  .~o-..~ 1~'l, ~-  ~. ~o.,~o..o. ,'~l...~o. ,.o ,.o  zT  I O  "                         5ESQUIOXIDE NODULE     ]-5-lOcm  2  ,  III  ,Ih, l,, ,,h,I I,,I,,   ,, IIh h I,II1,,, I I   J, I,,11111, ri]  .~o ' so ~b " so do ' ;io " 8o " 9o " 76o " iio ' d,o" ~o" ~;.o ~o"  Fig 4. Laser-reduced anions. For the legend see Fig 3.    32    produce strong peaks in the case of this sesquloxlde nodule, as well as m the  spectrum 45 which belongs to one of the dark grams.  There are more identifications whmh are not yet firmly estabhshed but  which are tentatively submitted to illustrate the situation. Both $102 and  CO~ have the same mass number (60) The presence of both compounds can  be established m spectrum 45 by the appearance of S103 (77) and HCO3  {45). As in the positive spectra, Si (28) is quite inconspicuous. (43) seems to  belong to AIO, and O2 and S overlap at mass number (32).  As with the cations, the negative spectra show that the dark grains have  various quite different compositions The grain from a depth of 85--90 cm  produces a much simpler spectrum than that from 5--10 cm depth, but this  may not be general. The fungal sclerotlum, spectrum 47, generates an ex-  ceptionally large number of different ions, and the negative spectrum also  shows a high proportion of O.M. m the sesquioxide nodule.    DISCUSSION    The Yerua soil as a true Pelludert with gylgai rehef, intersecting shcken-  sides, dark colours and a very high swelling capacity certainly undergoes  swelhng and shrinking which, together with an obviously high biological ac-  tivity are thought to produce complete homogenisation of at least the upper  80 cm. However, the morphological and chemical differentiation of the soil  profile does not seem to permit more than a very slow recent soil mixing,  and the idea of a fast and complete vertical rearrangement is clearly dis-  proved by the differentiation of the minimum O.M. age as indicated by L4C  dating (Table I).  The main problem is to connect these high 14C values with the visible in-  corporation of O.M. which could not be inactive for thousands of years. The  high age might reflect the accumulation of a special form of O.M., of very  high residence time, well protected by the clay matrix and only incorporated  at very low rates, at least after the pool has been saturated. The main part of  O.M., however, is quite short-living (Scharpenseel, 1975).  As a consequence, the farmers must make all efforts to preserve the  humus contents of these soils.  The most constant elements of the mmromorphologic distinct organic  features (Table II) are aboundmg dark grains of a size up to 6 um and some  suberin-like material. The nature of the dark particles is variable without  any possibility of a clear differentiation. This may point to a more compli-  cated structure of these grains. Some bodies look like organic detritus, others  are based on sesquioxides, and even true sesquioxide nodules contain organic  substances, as mentioned. The shape of a gram of course belongs to a distinct  sesquioxide particle or plant debris, respectively; but the chemical nature  and reactivity might be influenced, and sometimes governed, by a number  of adsorbed substances.    33    FURTHER INVESTIGATIONS    The members of the team are now completing the investigations presented  in this paper and performing some additional experiments. As the methods  usually used by Foster (1981) have proved to be unsuitable for the samples  from Yerua, alternative techniques are being tried. Conventional humus in-  vestigations and some special experiments remain to be done, but the team  is hopeful that it will be able to present a more complete report at the Paris  meeting.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We thank Dr. Heinen of Leybold-Heraeus Co., KSln for his introduction  to and help with the LAMMA instrument, and Dr. R.C. Foster of CSIRO,  Glen Osmond who revised the main part of the manuscript.    REFERENCES    Altem~ller, H.J, 1974 Mlkroskopie der B~den mit Hilfe yon Bodend~innschliffen. Hand-  buch der Mlkroskopm in der Technik, Band 4, Tell 2. Umschau-Verlag, Frankfurt, pp.  309--367.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S , Jongerius, A., Heinen, H J. and Meier, S., 1981. Chemical  element detection in thin sections of soils with the Laser Microprobe Mass Analyzer  (LAMMA 500). Neth J. Agric. Sci, 29: 23--36.  Foster, R C., 1981. Localization of organic materials in situ in ultrathin sections of  natural soil fabrms using cytochemical techniques. In: E B.A Bisdom (Editor), Sub-  microscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the International Working-  Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM), 1980, Wage-  ningen, pp. 309--317.  Halma, G., Miedema, R., Posthumus, M.A. and Van de Westeringh, W., 1979. Character-  ization of soil types by pyrolysis-mass spectrometry. Agrochemica, 22:372--382  Heinen, H J., Meier, S., Vogt, H. and Wechsung, R , 1980. Laser induced mass spectro-  metry of orgamc and inorganic compounds with LAMMA. Paper. 8th Triannual In-  ternational Mass Spectrometry Conference, Oslo, 1979, 21 pp.  Henstra, S. Bisdom, E.B.A. and Boekestein, A., 1981 Submicroscopic techniques for in  situ microchemical analysis of soils, III. Destructive techniques. In: E.B A. Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM),  1980, Wageningen, pp. 55--65.  Jeanson, C., 1981 Structuratlon du sol par la faune terricole. Incidences sur les concen-  trations organo-min~rales. In: Colloques internationaux du C.N.R.S. No 303, Migra-  tions organo-mm~rales dans les sols temp~r~s. Paris, pp. 113--123.  Jongerius, A. and Heintzberger, G., 1975. Methods in Soil Micromorphology A Tech-  nique for the Preparation of Large Thin Sections Netherlands Soil Survey Institute,  Wageningen, 49 pp.  PNUD, FAO, INTA, 1976 Suelos y erosion de la provmcia de Entre Rfos Copied manu-  script, 2nd ed., EERA del INTA Paranfi, 2 Vol., 168 pp.    34    Scharpenseel, H W , 1972 Natural radiocarbon measurements on humle substances m the  light of carbon cycle estimates In. Proceedings of the International Meetlnl~ on Humic  Substances, Nieuwershuls. 1972. Pudoc, Wagenmgen, pp 281--292  Scharpenseel, H W., 1975  Relatlvalter und Sukzesslon von Fraktlonen der orgamschen  Bodensubstanz. Mitt Dtsch. Bodenkd_ Ges , 22:453--466  Scharpenseel, H W. and Pmtig, F , 1968/69 Elnfache Boden- und Wasserdatmrung durch  Messungder J4C-oderTntmmkonzentraLion Geoderma 2:273--289                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractThe investigation of residence, alteration and circulation of soil organic matter is an ideal problem for integrated research including microscopy and submicroscopic methods. The subject of the present study is an argillic Pelludert of Argentina. The organic matter in this soil shows an unexpectedly steep gradient of 14C age. Below 25 cm the frequency of microscopic organic features decreases rapidly. Only few types are present at greater depth. Features produced by faunal activity, as well as brown to black areas of different composition have been investigated with SEM-EDXRA. The main subjects of laserinduced mass spectra were dark grains of few microns diameter which abound in the fine mass. Some spectra are presented and discussed. Further investigations are planned in order to demonstrate how submicroscopy, associated to the physico-chemical methods, can contribute to the knowledge and to the comprehension of the genesis of Vertisols. 