 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 177--194                                                  177  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Abdullah, M.; Zaman, M. B.; Khaliquzzaman, M.; et aL Determination of total zinc in soils by external-  beam photon-induced x-ray emission spectrometry: Analytica Chimica Acta. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 18, No. 1, p. 175-178, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Abrams, Miehael J. Lithologic mapping: in Remote sensing in geology (Siegal, Barry S., editor; et al.),  p. 381-418, illus. (incl. plates, tables, geol. sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United  States, 1980.  Ahmed, Ahmed EI-Sayed. Simulation of simultaneous heat and moisture transfer in soils heated by  buried pipes: 130 p., Doctoral, 1980, Ohio State Univ., Columbus, OH. amilable from: Univ. Microfilms.  All, Elfatih M.; Wu, Tien H.; and Chang, Nien-Ying. Stochastic model of flow through stratified soils:  New York, N.Y.: American Society of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol.  106, No. GT6, p. 593-610, illus., 1980.  Amos, William H., Jr.; Arms, Fred S.; Casey, William H. (editors); et aL Mine soil classification and  use; a Kentucky guide for vegetative treatment: 41 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch maps), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Lexington, KY, United States, 1980.  Anderson, G.; Pidgeon, J. D.; Spencer, H. B.; et al. A new hand-held recording penetrometer for soil  studies: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 279-296, illus. (incl. tables, plate), 1980.  Anderson, Richard C. Geology for planning in Rock Island County, Illinois: Urbana: Illinois State  Geological Survey, 1906-, No. 510, 35 p., illus. (incl. tables, sects., charts, geol. sketch map; geol. map  1:33,333; colored environ, geol. map 1:126,720), 1980.  Andrews, J. T.; and Miller, G. H.  Dating Quaternary deposits more than 10,000 years old:  in  Timescales in geomorphology (Cullingford, R. A., editor; et al.), p. 263-287, illus. (incl. tables, charts),  John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Arora, Yogesh; and Singh, N.T. A model for prediction of calcium-sodium exchange reactions in sodic  soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 225-232, illus. (incl. table),  1980.  Atkinson, C. H.; and Grimwood, Thomas D. Soil survey of Ottawa County, Kansas: 89 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Kansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Augustithis, S. S4 Mposkos, E.; and Vgenopoalos, A. Diffusion rings (sphaeroids) in bauxite: Chemical  Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 30, No. 4, p. 351-362, illus.  (incl. tables), 1980.  Averdieek, R.; Hayen, H.; and Wlllkomm, H.  Der Entwicklungsgang im zeitlichen Ablauf und  "Moorarchaeologie" [Evolution in time and moor archaeology]: in Moor- und Torfkunde (Goettlich,  Karlhans, editor), p. 77-129, illus. (incl. tables, charts), E. Schweizerbart'sche Verlagsbuchhandlung  (Naegele u. Obermiller), Stuttgart, Germany, Federal Republic of, 1980.  Bagley, Donald G. Soil survey of Virgin River area, Nevada-Arizona; parts of Clark and Lincoln  counties, Nevada and part of Mohave County, Arizona: 147 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soils  map 1:316,800; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Dep. Int., Bur. Land Manage.; Univ. Nev. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Univ.  Ariz. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Barker, Wesley L.; Angell, Raymond C.; Bell, Elbert L.; et aL Soil survey of Thomas County, Kansas:  57 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Kansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).    178    Bausch, Walter Charles. Development of a soil moisture model for use with passive microwave remote  sensors:  185 p., Univ. Microfilms, 1980, Texas A&amp;M Univ., College Station, TX.  Beales, P. W. The late Devensian and Flandrian vegetational history of Crose Mere, Shropshire: New  Phytologist. London., Vol. 86, No. 1, p. 133-158, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Belanger, d. R.  Landsat et les gisements miniers [Landsat and mineral deposits]:  Ottawa, Ont.:  Department of Energy, Mines and Resources Canada, 1972-, Summer, p. I0-12 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Bellary, V. P.; and Sarma, Y. A. Direct spectrographic analysis of trace elements in soil samples:  Zeitschrift fuer Analytische Chemie. Berlin., Vol. 302, No. 4, p. 278-280 (incl. German sum.), illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Bengtson, Richard Lee. Predicting storm runoff from small grassland watersheds with the USDAHL  hydrologic model: 183 p., Doctoral, 1980, Oklahoma State Univ., Stillwater, OK. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Bennett, d. G.  Aeolian deposition and soil parent materials in northern Nigeria:  Geoderma, an  International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 24, No. 3, p. 241-255,  table, sketch maps, 1980.  Berrow, M. L.; and Mitchell, R. L. Location of trace elements in soil profiles; total and extractable  contents of individual horizons: Royal Society of Edinburgh, Transactions., Vol. 71, Part 2, p. 103-121,  illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Besset, Franeoise. Localisations et repartitions successives du nickel au cours de l'alteration lateritique  des peridotites de Nouvelle-Caledonie [Nickel localization and successive redistribution during lateritic  weathering of peridotites in New Caledonia]: Montpellier, Universite, Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches  Geologiques et Hydrogeologiques, Memoires., Vol. 15, 129 p. (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  plates, geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Bingham, LaMonte C.; Silvernale, Alexandra; MeCain, Patrick E.; et al. Soil survey and interpretations  for resource planning and community development of Helena Valley, part of Lewis and Clark County,  Montana: 57 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Mont. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Birks, H. J.B. The present flora and vegetation of the moraines of the Klutlan Glacier, Yukon Territory,  Canada; a study in plant succession: in Klutlan Glacier issue (Wright, H. E., editor), New York, N.Y.:  Academic Press, 1970-, No. 14, p. 60-86, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Birks, H. J. B. Modern pollen assemblages and vegetational history of the moraines of the Klutlan  Glacier and its surroundings, Yukon Territory, Canada: in Klutlan Glacier issue (VCright, H. E., editor),  New York, N.Y.: Academic Press, 1970-, No. 14, p. 101-129, illus. (incl. tables, charts, sketch map), 1980.  Blaekmore, A.V. Hydroxyl interaction with an alkaline clay soil during column leaching: Australian  Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 233-243, illus., 1980.  Blot, Alain. L'alteration climatique des massifs de granite du Senegal [Climatic alteration of granite  massifs in Senegal]: Travaux et Documents de l' ORSTOM. Paris., No. 114, 434 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates, sects., block diag., geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Borchers, Glenn A. Soil survey of Stanley County, South Dakota: 135 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Dep. Int., Bur. Indian Aft.; S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Bowman, Roy H.; and Estrada, David C. Soil survey of Santa Cruz County, California:  148 p., illus.  (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (PubL in coop. with Univ. Calif., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Brandl, Heinz. New approach to predict lime reactivity of soils: New York, N.Y.: American Society  of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106, No. GT6, p. 731-733, illus.,  1980.  Breteler, Ronald Johannes. The cycling of mercury in Spartina marshes and its availability to selected  biota:  Doctoral, 1980, MeGill Univ., Montreal, Que, Canada. available from: National Library of  Canada.    179    Brichta, A.; Paternoster, K.; Schoell, W. U.; et al. Die Gruta do Salitre bei Diamantina, Minas Gerais,  Brasilien, kein "Einsturzloch" ['The Gruta do Salitre near Diamantina, Minas Gerais, Brazil; no collapse  hole]: Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie--Annals of Geomorphology--Annales de Geomorphologie.  Berlin-Stuttgart., VoL 24, No. 2, p. 236-242 (incl. English, French sum.), strat, col., sect., geol. sketch  map, 1980.  Brooks, Jule F. Soil survey of Coweta, Heard, and Troup counties, Georgia: 102 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Oa., Coll. Agric.; Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Bulloeh, H. Edward, Jr.; and Neher, Raymond E. Soil survey of Dona Ana County area, New Mexico:  177 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:443,520), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Dep. Int., Bur. Land  Manage.; N.M. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Buraymah, Ibrahim M. Land evaluation in Sudan:  in Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-  committee for Soil Correlation and Land Evaluation, United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources  Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 93-105, tables, sketch map, 1980.  Burgess, T. M.; and Webster, R. Optimal interpolation and isarithmic mapping of soil properties; I, The  semi-variogram and punctual kriging: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 315-331, illus.  (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980.  Burgess, T. M.; and Webster, R. Optimal interpolation and isarithmic mapping of soil properties; II,  Block kriging: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford,, Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 333-341, table, sketch maps, 1980.  Burke, R.; Hemond, H.; and Stolzenbaeh, K. An infiltrometer to measure seepage in salt marsh soils:  in Estuarine and wetland processes with emphasis on modeling (Hamilton, Peter, editor; et al.), p. 413-  423, illus. (incl. sketch maps), Plenum Press, New York, NY, United States, 1980.  Burmeister, E. G.; Goettlieh, Karlhans; Grospietsch, Th.; et aL Bergriffsbestimmungen anhand der  Moortypen Mitteleuropas [Definition of moor types in central Europe]:  in Moor- und Torfkunde  (Goettlich,  Karlhans,  editor),  p.  1-46,  illus.  (incl.  tables,  plates),  E.  Schweizerbart'sche  Verlagsbuchhandlung (Naegele u. Obermiller), Stuttgart, Germany, Federal Republic of, 1980.  Butt, C. R.M. Weathered bedrock: in Conceptual models in exploration geochemistry; Australia (Butt,  C. R. M., editor; et al.), Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association of Exploration Geochemists,  Journal). Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., VoL 12, No. 2-3, p. 122-126, 1980.  Cable, DwightR. Seasonal patterns ofsoil water recharge and extraction on semidesert ranges: Denver,  Colorado: Society for Range Management, Vol. 33, No. 1, p. 9-15, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Carpenter, R. H.; and Hayes, W.B. Annual accretion of Fe-Mn-oxides and certain associated metals  in a stream environment:  Chemical Geology; an International Journal Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 29, No. 3-4, p. 249-259, illus., 1980.  Childs, C. W.; and Johnston, J. H. Moessbauer spectra of proto-ferrihydrite at 77 K and 295 K, and  a reappraisal of the possible presence of akaganeite in New Zealand soils: Australian Journal of Soil  Research. Melbourne, Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 245-250, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Christensen, Thomas Hoejlund. Cadmium sorption onto two mineral soils: 325 p., Doctoral, 1980,  Univ. of Washington, Seattle, WA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Christian, John T.  Flow nets from finite element data:  International Journal for Numerical and  Analytical Methods in Geomechanics. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4, No.  2, p. 191-196, illus., 1980.  Collins, J. F.; and O'Dubhain, T. A micromorphological study of silt concentrations in some Irish  podzols: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Pub1. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  24, No. 3, p. 215-224, illus., 1980.  Cox, Frank R., Jr. Soil survey of McLean and Mulhlenberg counties, Kentucky: 124 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour. Environ. Prot.; Ky.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Cox, Nicholas J. On the relationship between bedrock lowering and regolith thickness: Earth Surface  Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons, London-  New York., Vol. 5, No. 3, p. 271-274, 1980.    180    Crook, Richard, Jr.; and Kamb, Barclay. A new method of alluvial age dating based on progressive  weathering, with application to the time-history of fault activity in Southern California: Reston, Va.: U.  S. Geological Survey, No. 80-1144, 44 p., 1980. available from: U. S. Geol. Sure., Open-File Sere. Sect.,  Branch Distrib., Denver, CO, United States.  Czajkowski, RonaldL.;andVinson, TedS. Dynamic properties offrozen silt under cyclic loading: New  York, N.Y.: American Society of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106,  No. GTg, p. 963-980, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Dahiya, I. S.; Abrol, I. P.; and Hajrasuliha, S. Modeling transport of reactive solutes during leaching  saline-sodic soils rich in soluble carbonates:  Agricultural Water Management. Elsevier Scientific  Publishing Company, Amsterdam., Vol. 3, No. 1, p. 3-16, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Dalziel, M. C.; and Donovan, T.J. Chemical and isotopic data from some plants, soils, and carbonate  cements, Recluse oil field, Wyoming: Reston, Va.: U. S. Geological Survey, No. 80-783, 18 p., 1980.  available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., Branch Distrib., Denver, CO, United States.  Datta, P. S.; Desai, B. I.; and Gupta, S. K.  Hydrological investigations in Sabarmati Basin; I,  Groundwater recharge estimation using tritium tagging method: Indian National Science Academy,  Proceedings, Part A, Physical Sciences (continuation of National Institute of Sciences of India,  Proceedings, Part A, Physical Sciences). New Delhi., Vol. 46, No. 1, p. 84-98, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), 1980.  Davcy, John Raymond. Energy flow dynamics of a desert grassland ecosystem: 268 p., Doctoral, 1980,  Northern Arizona Univ., Flagstaff, AZ. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Davidson, J. M.; Rao, P. S. C.; Ou, L. T.; et al. Adsorption, movement, and biological degradation of  large concentrations of selected pesticides in soils:  111 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1980. (Rep. No. EPA-  600/2-80-124) available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.  Davies, Brian E. (editor). Applied soil trace elements: 482 p., illus. (incl. tables, block diags., plates,  sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Davies, Brian E. Trace element pollution: in Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p.  287-351, illus. (incl. tables, block diag., sketch map), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom,  1980.  Davis, Anthony M.  Modern pollen spectra from the tundra-boreal forest transition in northern  Newfoundland, Canada: Boreas; An International Journal of Quaternary Geology. Oslo., Vol, 9, No.  2, p. 89-100, illus. (incl. tables, charts, sketch maps), 1980.  Deleourt, Paul A.; Delcourt, Hazel R.; Brister, Ronaid C.; et al. Quaternary vegetation history of the  Mississippi Embayment: Quaternary Research (Washington, University, Quaternary Research Center).  Academic Press, New York., Vol. 13, No. 1, p. 111-132, illus. (incl. charts, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Des Marais, David J.; Mitchell, J. M.; Meinschein, WG.; et al. The carbon isotope biogeochemistry  of the individual hydrocarbons in bat guano and the ecology of the insectivorous bats in the region of  Carlsbad, New Mexico:  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal).  Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 12, p. 2075-2086, illus., 1980.  Deutscher, R. L.; Mann, A. W.; and Butt, C. R. M. Model for calcrete uranium mineralization:  &amp;  Conceptual models in exploration geochemistry; Australia (Butt, C. R. M., editor; et al.), Journal of  Geochemical Exploration (Association of Exploration Geochemists, Journal). Elsevier Sci. Puhl. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 12, No. 2-3, p. 158-161, block diag., 1980.  Dibble, Walter Earl, Jr. Non-equilibrium water/rock interactions:  177 p.. Doctoral, 1980, Stanford  Univ., Stanford, CA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Dittmar, Glen W.; and Stevens, Jack W. Soil survey of Atascosa County, Texas: 131 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Dong, Allen. Dispersibility of soils and elemental composition of soils, sediments and dust and dirt from  the Menominee River basin, Wisconsin:  158 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Wisconsin, Madison, WI.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Duarte, L.; and Nogueira, M. I. M. Vegetais do Quaternario do Brasil; 1, Florula de Russas, CE  [Quaternary vegetation of Brazil; I, Russas flora, Ceara]: Academia Brasileira de Ciencias, Anais. Rio  de Janeiro., Vol. 52, No. 1, p. 37-48 (incl. English sum.), table, plates, 1980.    181    Duarte, L.; and de Vasconeelos, M. E.G. Vegetais do Quaternario do Brasil; II, Florula de Umbuzeiro,  PB [The Quaternary vegetation of Brazil; I, The Umbuzeiro florule, Paraiba]: Academia Brasileira de  Ciencias, Anais. Rio de Janeiro., Vol. 52, No. 1, p. 93-108, illus. (incl. plates), 1980.  Duddy, Ian R. Redistribution and fractionation of rare-earth and other elements in a weathering profile:  Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sei. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 30, No. 4, p. 363-  381, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Durgaprasada Rao, N. V. N.; and Srihari, Y. Clay mineralogy of the late Pleistocene red sediments of  the Visakhapatnam region, east coast of India:  Sedimentary Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 213-227, illus. (incl. tables; maps 1:95,040), 1980.  Edmeades, D.C. Calcium-magnesium exchange equilibria in a range of New Zealand soils: Australian  Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 251-255, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Eldridge, D. J. Land evaluation methodology in Botswana with particular emphasis on the specific  criteria used:  in Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and Land  Evaluation, United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 89-92, table,  1980.  Ellis, S. An investigation of weathering in some Arctic-Alpine soils on the northeast flank of Oksskolten,  North Norway: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 371-385, illus. (incl. tables, plates,  sketch map), 1980.  Ernst, J. E.; Miller, K. E.; and Hunter, R. L. Soil survey of Seneca County, Ohio: 143 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Die. Lands Soil;  Ohio Agric. Res. Dee. Cent.).  Fedorovich, D. I.; and Shehelokov, V. K. Calculation of the thermal regime of bases of cold-storage  plants with air spaces: New York, N.Y.: Consultants Bureau, 1965-, Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 81-83, 1980  [19803.  FitzPatrick, E. A. Soils; their formation, classification and distribution: 345 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates), Longman, London, United Kingdom, 1980.  Fleming, Garrett A. Essential micronutrients; I, Boron and molybdenum: inApplied soil trace elements  (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 155-197, illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1980.  Fleming, Garrett A. Essential micronutrients; II, Iodine and selenium: in Applied soil trace elements  (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 199-234, illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1980.  Ford, Jimmy G.; Scott, Gregory F.; and Frie, Jimmie W. Soil survey of Beckham County, Oklahoma:  182 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Okla. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Foth, Henry D.; and Schafer, John W. Soil geography and land use: 467 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates,  sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United States, 1980.  Franklin, J. Suggested methods for pressure monitoring using hydraulic cells: International Journal of  Rock Mechanics and Mining Sciences and Geomechanics Abstracts. Pergamon Press, Oxford-New  York., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 119-127, illus., 1980.  Frechen, Josef. Stratigraphie und Chronologic des Pleistozaens am Vulkan Leilenkopf, Laacher-See-  Gebiet [Stratigraphy and chronology of the Pleistocene at the Leilenkopf Volcano, Laach Lake region]:  Neues Jahrbuch fuer Geologie und Palaeontologie, Monatshefte. Stuttgart., No. 4, p. 193-214 (incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. strat, col., sketch map), 1980.  Freytet, P.; and Fort, M. Les formations plioquaternaires de la Kali Gandaki et du bassin de Pokhara  (Himalaya du Nepal) [Plio-Quaternary formations of the Kali Gandaki valley and Pokhara basin;  Himalayas of Nepal]: in Seance thematique; Recherches en geographic physiqu'e dans l'Himalaya central  (Dollfus, O.), Association de (3eographes Francais, Bulletin. Paris., No. 471, p. 249-257 (incl. English  sum.), illus., 1980.  Friedrich, G.; Brunemann, H. G.; Thijssen, T.; et al. Chromite in lateritischen Boeden als potentielle  Lagerstaetten-Vorraete in den Philippinen [Chromite in lateritic soils as a potential ore supply in the  Philippines]: in Niedrigprozentige Erzvorkommen als Potentielle Lagerstaetten, Gesellschaft Deutscher  Metallhuetten- und Bergleute, Schriften. Clausthal-Zellerfeld., No. 35, p. 65-94 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.    182    Friedrich, G.; Brunemann, H. G.; Thijssen, Th.; et al. Chromite in lateritic soils as potential ore reserves  in the Philippines:  Erzmetall (continuation of Zeitschrift fuer Erzbergbau und Metallhuettenwesen).  Stuttgart., Vol. 33, No. 7-8, p. 414-420 (incl. German sum.), illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Froedge, Ronald D. Soil survey of Christian County, Kentucky: 147 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1980. (Pub. in coop. with Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour. Environ. Prot.; Ky. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Froomer, N. Morphologic changes in some Chesapeake Bay tidal marshes resulting from accelerated  soil erosion:  in Coasts under stress (Orme, A. R., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie,  Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 34, p. 242-254 (incl. German, French sum.), sects., tables, sketch  maps, 1980.  Gardner, Leonard Robert. Mobilization of AI and Ti during weathering; isovolumetric geochemical  evidence: Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.. Vol. 30, No.  1-2, p. 151-165, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Gardner, R. H.; Huff, D. D.; O'Neill, R. V.; et al. Application of error analysis to a marsh hydrology  model: Washington, D.C.: American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 4, p. 659-664, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Gay, Alison L; and Grandstaff, D.E. Chemistry and mineralogy of Precambrian paleosols at Elliot Lake,  Ontario, Canada:  in Early Precambrian volcanology and sedimentology in the light of the Recent  (Dimroth, E., editor; et al.), Precambrian Research. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 12, No.  1-4, p. 349-373, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Gennadiyev, A. N. lzucheniye geografii, kartografii i genezisa pochv v universitetakh SShA [The study  of geography, cartography and the genesis of soils in universities of the USA]: Vestnik Moskovskogo  Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 3, p. 67-71 (incl. English sum.), 1980.  Ghorbanzadeh-Rendi, Ali. Non-steady, two-dimensional tile drainage of saturated-unsaturated artesian  lands analyzed by finite element method:  287 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of California, Davis, CA.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Ghuman, B. S.; and Prihar, S. S. Chloride displacement by water in layered soil columns: Australian  Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 207-214, illus., 1980.  Gilpin, R. R. A model for the prediction of ice lensing and frost heave in soils: Washington, D.C.:  American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 5, p. 918-930, illus., 1980.  Glagolev, N. A.  Development features of a supergene zone on a uranium-phosphorous deposit:  International Geology Review. American Geological Institute, Falls Church, Virginia., Vol. 22, No. 9,  p. 1070-1076, illus., 1980.  Glass, Steven W.; and Wilkinson, Bruce H. The Peterson Limestone; Early Cretaceous lacustrine  carbonate deposition in western Wyoming and southeastern Idaho: Sedimentary Geology. Elsevier Sci.  Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 143-160, illus. (incl. block diag., sketch map), 1980.  Glooschenko, W.A. Coastal ecosystems of the James/Hudson Bay area of Ontario, Canada: inCoasts  under stress (Orme, A. R., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-  Stuttgart., Vol. 34, p. 214-224 (incl. German, French sum.), sects., sketch map, 1980.  Godfrey, Michael A. A Sierra Club naturalist's guide to the Piedmont: 475 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates),  Sierra Club Books, San Francisco, CA, United States, 1980.  Goerdel, A.R. Soil survey of Clay County, Texas: 137 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000;  colored soils maps 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States,  1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Golshani-Javadi, Farrokh.  Verteilung der Spurenelemente Kupfer, Zink, Blei und Quecksilber in  verschiedenen Bodenhorizonten und Korngroessenfraktionen ueber vererzten Gesteinen des Saar-Nahe-  Gebietes [Distribution of copper, zinc, lead and mercury in district soil horizons, and grain size fractions  over metallized rocks in the  Saar-Nahe area]:  Mainzer Geowissenschaftliche  Mitteilungen.  Geologisches Landesamt Rhineland-Pfalz. Mainz., Vol. 8, p. 151-168 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl.  strat, cols., sketch maps), 1980.  Gol'tsberg, I. A.; and Davitaya, F. F. (editors). Soil climate: 256 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1980. (Rep.  No. TT 74-52029) available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.    183    Greacen, E. L.; and Sands, R. Compaction of forest soils; a review: Australian Journal of Soil Research.  Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 163-189, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Grieve, I. C. The magnitude and significance of soil structural stability declines under cereal cropping:  Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen,  Germany., Vol. 7, No. 1, p. 79-85 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Grisak, G. E.; and Pickens, J. F. Solute transport through fractured media; 1, The effect of matrix  diffusion: Washington, D.C.: American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 4, p. 719-730, illus.,  1980.  Grosse-Brauckmann, G.  Ablagerungen der Moore [Moor sediments]:  in Moor- und Torfkunde  (Goettlich,  Karlhans,  editor),  p.  130-173,  illus.  (incl.  tables,  plates),  E.  Schweizerbart'sche  Verlagsbuchhandlung (Naegele u. Ohermiller), Stuttgart, Germany, Federal Republic of, 1980.  Hailberg, G. R.; Baker, R. G.; and Legg, T. A mid-Wisconsinan pollen diagram from Des Moines  County, Iowa: Iowa Academy of Science, Proceedings. Des Moines., Vol. 87, No. 2, p. 41-44, illus. (incl.  sketch map), 1980.  Hamilton, Eric I. Analysis for trace elements; I, Sample treatment and laboratory quality control: in  Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 21-68, illus. (incl. tables, plates), John Wiley  &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Hamilton, Eric I. Analysis for trace elements; II, Instrumental analysis: in Applied soil trace elements  (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 69-130, illus. (incl. tables, plates), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1980.  Hardin, Bobby O. Anisotropic shear modulus due to stress anisotropy: New York, N.Y.: American  Society of Civil Engineers, Geotcchnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106, No. GTS, p. 956-958,  1980.  Haynes, C. Vance. Geochronology of Wadi Tushka; lost tributary of the Nile: Washington, D.C.:  American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1883-, Vol. 210, No. 4465, p. 68-71, illus. (incl.  sketch map), 1980.  Head, K. H. Soil classification and compaction tests: in the collection Manual of soil laboratory testing,  Vol. 1, 334 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United States, 1980.  Hillis, J. H. Soil survey of Lagrange County, Indiana:  135 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Hinkley, Todd K.; Herring, ./ames R.; and Ebens, Richard ./. Chemical character and practical pre-  mining sampling needs, Fort Union Formation coal overburden rocks:  in Proceedings of the Fourth  symposium on the geology of Rocky Mountain coal (Carter, Lorna M., editor), Colorado Geological  Survey, Resource Series. Denver., No. 10, p. 45-49, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Horler, D. N. H.; Barber, ./.; and Barringer, A. R. A multi-elemental study of plant surface particles  in relation to geochemistry and biogeochemistry: Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association of  Exploration Geochemists, Journal). Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1, p. 41-50, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Houston, WilliamN.;andHerrmmm, HerbertG. Undrainedcyclicstrengthofmarinesoils: NewYork,  N.Y.: American Society of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106, No.  GT6, p. 691-712, 1980.  Hromadka, T. V., II; and Guymon, G. L. Some effects of linearizing the unsaturated soil moisture  transfer diffusivity model: Washington, D.C.: American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 4, p.  643-650, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Iijima, A. Geology of natural zeolites and zeolitic rocks: in Fifth international conference on zeolites  (Rees, L. V. C., editor), Pure and Applied Chemistry. Pergamon Press, Oxford, England., Vol. 52, No.  9, p. 2115-2130, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Ildefonse, P. Mineral facies developed by weathering of a meta-gabbro, Loire-Atlantique (France):  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 24, No.  3, p. 257-273, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.    184    Imeson, A. C.; Kwaad, F. J. P. M.; and Muecher, H.J. Hillslope processes and deposits in forested areas  of Luxembourg: inTimescales in geomorphology (Cullingford, R. A., editor; et al.), p. 31-42, illus. (incl.  chart, sketch map), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Jaeo, Hubert B. Soil survey of Reeves County, Texas:  123 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soil  map 1:506,880; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Jacobson, G. L., Jr.; and Birks, H. J. B. Soil development on Recent end moraines of the Klutlan  Glacier, Yukon Territory, Canada:  in Klutlan Glacier issue (Wright, H. E., editor), New York, N.Y.:  Academic Press, 1970-, No. 14, p. 87-100, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Jakel, Dale E. Soil survey of Adams County, Wisconsin: 142 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Wis., Res. Div. Coll. Agric. Life Sci.).  Jame, Yih-Wu; and Norum, Donald I. Heat and mass transfer in a freezing unsaturated porous medium:  Washington, D.C.: American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 4, p. 811-819, illus., 1980.  Jenkins, David A.; and Wyn Jones, R. Gareth. Trace elements in rocks, soils, plants, and animals;  introduction: in Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 1-20, illus. (incl. tables), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Johnson, C. Gene. National soils data base from the Soil Conservation Service:  m Cartographic and  statistical data bases and mapping software (Moore, Patricia A., editor), p. 21-29, sketch maps, Harv.  Univ., Cambridge, MA, United States, 1980.  Jones, R. J. A.; and Tinsley, J. Hill land studies in the Grampian region of Scotland; l, Effects of soil  parent material, altitude and aspect on the herbage yields, composition and responses to fertilizer  treatments in the upper Don Basin: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 343-370, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Jungerius, P. D. Holocene surface lowering in the Lias cuesta area of Luxembourg as calculated from  the amount of volcanic minerals of Allerod age remaining in residual soils:  Zeitschrift fuer  Geomorphologie--Annals of Geomorphology--Annales de Geomorphologie. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 24,  No. 2, p. 192-199, sect., tables, sketch map, 1980.  Jusserand, C. Extraction de l'eau interstitielle des sediments et des sols; comparaison des valeurs de  l'oxygene 18 par differentes methodes, premiers resultats [The extraction of interstitial water from  sediments and soils; a comparison of oxygen 18 values using different methods; preliminary results]:  Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen,  Germany., Vol. 7, No. I, p. 87-96, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Km'afiath, L. L. Cone resistance in sand by incremental method: Journal of Terramechanics. Pergamon  Press, Oxford-New York., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 101-113, illus., 1980.  Karammaos, R.E. Potassium status of some soils of northern Greece in relation to clay mineralogy and  other soil properties: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-  Basel., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 723-739, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Kashiwaya, K. A study of rill development process based on field experiments: Geographical Review  of Japan (Chirigaku-Hyoron) (Association of Japanese Geographers--Nippon Chiri-Gakkai). Tokyo.,  Vol. 53, No. 7, p. 419-434 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Keller, C.  Aufnahme yon Radionukliden aus dem Boden [Absorption of radionuclides on soils]:  Naturwissenschaftliche Rundschau. Stuttgart., Vol. 33, No. 7, p. 282-284, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Kempton, John P.; Morse, Walter J.; and Johnson, W. Hilton. Stratigraphy and regional distribution  of Illinoian and pre-Illinoian deposits of East-central Illinois [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with-Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 5, p. 230-231, 1980.  The Geological Society  of America, North-Central Section. 14th annual meeting.  Kerndorff, H.;andSehnitzer, M. Sorptionofmetalsonhumicacid: GeochimicaetCosmochimicaActa  (The Geochemical Society, Journal). Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 11, p. 1701-1708, illus.,  1980.  Kimberley, Michael M.; Tanaka, Roderiek T.; and Farr, Mark R. Composition of middle Precambrian  uraniferous conglomerate in the Elliot Lake-Agnew Lake area of Canada:  in Early Precambrian  volcanology and sedimentology in the light of the Recent (Dimroth, E., editor; et al.), Precambrian  Research. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 12, No. 1-4, p. 375-392, illus. (incl. sketch map),  1980.    185    Kitagawa, Ryuji; Kakitani, Satoru; Kuroda, Yoshimatsu; et al. Hydrogen isotope ratios of clay minerals  constituting clay veins found in granitic rocks of Hiroshima Prefecture: Geological Society of Japan,  Journal. Tokyo., Vol. 86, No, 3, p. 167-177 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, plates), 1980.  Klusman, Ronald W.; Ringrose, Charles D.; Candito, Robert J.; et al. Sampling design for baseline  studies of the Colorado oil shale region: inOil shale symposium; sampling, analysis and quality assurance  (Gale, Charles, editor), p. 32-57, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980. (Rep. No. EPA-600/9-80-  022) available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.  Knecht, ArnoldA. Soil sureey of Riverside County, California, Coachella Valley area: 89 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Consere. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Knezek, Bernard D.; and Ellis, Boyd G. Essential micronutrients; IV, Copper, iron, manganese, and  zinc: in Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 259-286, iUus. (incl. tables), John Wiley  &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Kodama, H.; and Sehnitzer, M. Effect of fulvic acid on the crystallization of aluminum hydroxides:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 24, No.  3, p. 195-205, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Kolarkar, A. S.; Dhir, R. P,; and Singh, N. Characteristics and morphogenesis of salt-affected soils in  southeastern arid Rajasthan: Photonirvachak; Journal of the Indian Society of Photo-Interpretation.  Dehra Dun., Vol. 8, No. 1, p. 31-41, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Kosov, B. F.; and Larionov, G.A. Konferentsiya po teoreticheskim osnovam zashchity pochz ot erozii  [A conference on the theoretical foundations of anti-erosion soil conservation]: Vestnik Moskovskogo  Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 4, p. 95-96, 1980.  Kozyreva, M. G.; and Rubilin, Ye. V. Ob absolyutnom vozraste nekotorykh sovremennykh poch'; I  [Absolute age of some modern soils; I]: Vestnik Leningradskogo Universiteta, Geologiya, Geografiya.  Leningrad., No. 6, Vypusk l, p. 65-72, tables, 1980.  Krishna, J. Hari. Runoff prediction and rainfall utilization in the semi-arid tropics: 155 p., Doctoral,  1980, Utah State Univ., Logan, UT. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Kubota, Joe. Regional distribution of trace element problems in North America: in Applied soil trace  elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 441-466, sketch maps, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United  Kingdom, 1980.  Kutnink, Paul R.; Gier, Donald A.; Haberman, Roger L.; et al. Soil survey of Marshall County, Kansas:  76 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Kans. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Kwun, Soon-Kuk. A mathematical erosion model to simulate soil losses in agricultural watersheds: 261  p., Doctoral, 1980, Iowa State Univ. of Science &amp; Technol., Ames, IA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  LaBrecque, J. J.; Rosales, P. A.; Rada, G. A.; et al. Determination of total manganese in silicates and  Venezuelan laterites, using air-C2H2 and N20-C2H2 flames by atomic absorption spectroscopy:  Chemical Geology; an International Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 29, No. 3-4, p.  313-321, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Larsen, Lynn S. Soil survey of Elbert County, Colorado, western part: 135 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates;  colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Consere. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, 1980. (Colo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Lay, Douglas. Concretions in the Horsefly River Valley: The Canadian Rockhound (The Lapidary,  Rock and Mineral Society of British Columbia). Vancouver., Vol. 24, No. 4, p. 23, 1980.  Lehnardt, Friedrich; and Breehtel, Horst M.  Einrichtung und Anwendung feuchtestabiler  Bodenmonolith-Standardbehaelter fuer Messkontrollen und Nacheichungen yon Neutronensonden [Set-  up and application of moisture~stable soil monolith standards for measuring control and recalibration of  neutron   probes]:    Deutsche   Gewaesserkundliche   Mitteilungen;   Mitteilungsblatt   der  Gewaesserkundlichen Dienststellen des Bundes und der Laender (Germany, Bundesanstalt fuer  Gewaesserkunde). Coblenz,, Vol. 24, No. 4-5, p. 124-128 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Lenfesty, Charles D. Soil survey of Okanogan County area, Washington: 153 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Consere. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Wash. State Univ. Agric. Res. Cent.).    186    Lepretre, J. P. The subsoil data bank of the Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres; objectives,  options and facilities [abstr.]:  in Seventh international CODATA conference (Shimanouchi, T.,  chairperson; et al.), CODATA Bulletin (International Council of Scientific Unions, Committee on Data  for Science and Technology). Paris., No. 37, p. 42, 1980.  Leslie, D.M. Characterisation and comparative classification of soils ofa catena from loess, East Taieri,  Otago, New Zealand: New Zealand Journal of Science. Wellington., Vol. 23, No. 1. p. 19-26, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Liverovskaya, I.T. Karta struktury pochvennogo pokrova Zapadno-Sibirskoy tundry i lesotundry [A  structural map of the soil cover of West Siberian tundras and forested tundras]:  Zhizn' Zemli  (Moskovskiy Universitet, Muzey Zemlevedeniya, Sbornik). Moscow., No. 14, p. 18-22, table, sketch  map, 1980.  Logan, T.J. The role of soil and sediment chemistry in modeling nonpoint sources of phosphorus: in  Environmental impact of nonpoint source pollution (Overcash, Michael R., editor; et al.), p. 189-208.  illus. (incl. tables), Ann Arbor Sci. Publ., Ann Arbor, MI, United States, 1980.  Lovell, Burrell B. Soil survey of Malheur County, Oregon; northeastern part: 94 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Oreg. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Lowe, L. E.  Humus fraction ratios as a means of discriminating between horizon types:  Canadian  Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 60, No. 2, p. 219-229 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Lowole, M. W.; and Ntokotha, E. M. Land evaluation methodology in Malawi with emphasis on criteria  used: in Third meeting  f the Eastern African Sub c mmittee f r S i  C rre ati n and Land Eva uati n   United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 62-72, tables, 1980.  Luong Minh Phong. Phenomenes cycliques dans les sols pulverulents [Cyclical phenomona in granular  soils]: Revue Francaise de Geotechnique. Paris., No. 10, p. 39-53 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Lysenko, M. P. K kharakteristike glinistykh gruntov kochkovskoy svity Kulundy [Clay soils of the  Kochkov suite of Kulunda]: Vestnik Leningradskogo Universiteta, Geologiya, Geografiya. Leningrad.,  No. 6, Vypusk 1, p. 44-48 (incl. English sum.), 1980.  Mabbutt, J. A. Weathering history and landform development:  in Conceptual models in exploration  geochemistry; Australia (Butt, C. R. M., editor; et al.), Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association  of Exploration Geochemists, Journal). Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 12, No. 2-3, p. 96-107,  sketch map, 1980.  Mabesoone, J. M.; and Lobo, H. R. C. Paleosols as stratigraphic indicators for the Cenozoic history  of northeastern Brazil: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology.  Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 7, No. 1, p. 67-78 (incl. French, English sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  strat, cols., sketch map), 1980.  Mahmoud, M. S.; and Deresiewiez, H. Settlement of inhomogeneous consolidating soils; I, The single-  drained layer under confined compression: International Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods  in Geomechanics. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 57-72, illus., 1980.  Mahmound, M. S.; and Deresiewiez, H. Settlement of inhomogeneous consolidating soils; II, The  symmetrically loaded mass:  International Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods in  Geomechanics. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 73-88, illus., 1980.  Makae, T. K. Multiple-use soil surveys as a basis for land use planning in Lesotho: in Third meeting  of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and Land Evaluation, United Nations, F. A.  O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 73-88, tables, 1980.  Maloney, B. K.  Pollen analytical evidence for early forest clearance in North Sumatra:  Nature.  London., Vol. 287, No. 5780, p. 324-326, chart, sketch map, 1980.  Marshall, N.J. Soils:  in Conceptual models in exploration geochemistry; Australia (Butt, C. R. M.,  editor; et al.), Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association of Exploration Geochemists, Journal).  Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 12, No. 2-3, p. 126-129, 1980.  Matheron, G.; and de Marsily, G. Is transport in porous media always diffusive? A counterexample:  Washington, D.C.: American Geophysical Union, 1965-, Vol. 16, No. 5, p. 901-917, illus. (incl. tables),  1980.    187    Matthey, Francois; and Vangneux, Rene. Contribution pollenanalytique a l'histoire postglaciaire de la  vegetation du Fluelathal [Pollen-analytical contribution to the postglacial vegetational history in the  Fluela Valley]: Societe Neuchateloise de Geographie, Bulletin. Neuchatel., Vol. 103 (Quatrieme Serie),  p. 75-83 (incl. German, English sum.), chart, 1980.  McCallan, M. E.; O'Leary, B. M.; and Rose, C. W. Redistribution of caesium-137 by erosion and  deposition on an Australian soil: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 119-  128, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980.  McCarthy, Conrad Joseph.  Sediment transport by rainsplash:  224 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of  Washington, Seattle, WA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  McCarty, Thomas Richard.  A field study of water flow over and through a shallow, sloping,  heterogeneous soih 173 p., Doctoral, 1980, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. available frorr~" Univ. Microfilms.  MeIntosh, P. D. Weathering products in Vitrandept profiles under pine and manuka, New Zealand:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. PuN. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 24, No.  3, p. 225-239, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  McMurphy, Carl J. Soil survey of Kitsap County area, Washington: 127 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Wash. State Dep. Nat. Resour.; Wash. State  Univ., Agric. Res. Cent.).  Medved, J.; and Plsko, E. Spectrochemical determination of microelements in weathered materials on  silicate rocks: Geologicky Zbornik-Geologica Carpathica (Slovenska Akademia Vied). Bratislava., Vol.  31, No. 1-2, p. 177-184 (incl. Russian sum.), tables, 1980.  Mercer, J. W.; and Faust, C. R. Ground-water modeling; mathematical models: Urbana, Ill.: National  Water Well Association, Ground-Water Technology Division, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 212-227, illus. (incl.  sects., table), 1980.  Meunier, Alaln. Les mecanismes de l'alteration des granites et le role des microsystemes; Etude des  arenes du massif granitique de Parthenay (Deux-Sevres) [Mechanisms of alteration of granites and role  of microsystems; study of sands from the granitic massif of Parthenay; Deux-Sevres]: Societe Geologique  de France, Memoires. Paris., Vol. 59, No. 140, 79 p. (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch  map), 1980.  Miall, Andrew D.; Balkwill, H. R.; and Hopkins, W. S., Jr. Cretaceous and Tertiary sediments of  Eclipse Trough, Bylot Island area, Arctic Canada, and their regional setting: Ottawa, Ont.: Geological  Survey of Canada, 1935-, No. 79-23, 20 p. (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sects., strat, cols., charts,  sketch maps), 1980.  Michel, Jaequeline. Mobilization of uranium and thorium decay series isotopes in the hydrologic cycle:  113 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of South Carolina, Columbia, SC. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Millot, G. Les grands aplanissements des socles continentaux clans les pays subtropicaux, tropicaux et  desertiques [Large-scale planation of continental basements in subtropical, tropical and desert regions]:  in Livre jubilaire du cent cinquantenaire 1830-1980, Societe Geologique de France, Memoire Hors Serie.  Paris., No. 10, p. 295-305 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Monakhov, A. K. Primeneniye aerosnimkov dlya revizii krupnomasshtabnykh pochvennykh kart v  Nechernozemnoy zone [Using aerial photography for revisiting large-scale soil map in the non-  Chernozem zone]: Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya. Leningrad., Vol. 112, No.  4, p. 355-356, 1980.  Moorbath, S.; and Thompson, R. N. Strontium isotope geochemistry and petrogenesis of the early  Tertiary lava pile of the Isle of Skye, Scotland, and other basic rocks of the British Tertiary province;  an example of magma-crust interaction: Journal of Petrology. Oxford., Vol. 21, No. 2, p. 295-321, illus.  (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Morgan, William T.; and Hall, Robert D. Stratigraphy and sedimentation of the Christensen Bog,  Hancock County, Indiana [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 5, p. 251o252, 1980. The Geologieal Society of America, North-CentralSection, 14th  annual meeting.  Mroz, g. On hyp~elasticity and plasticity approaches to constitutive modelling of inelastic behaviour  of soils: International Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods in Geomechanics. John Wiley and  Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 45-55, illus., 1980.    188    Mumba, N. E.; and Heilmann, P. G.F. Land evaluation in Zambia with reference to methodology and  use of physical criteria: in Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and  Land Evaluation, United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 16-25,  tables, 1980.  Murff, James D. Vane shear testing of anisotropic, cohesive soils: International Journal for Numerical  and Analytical Methods in Geomechanics. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4,  No. 3, p. 285-289, illus., 1980.  Murphy, M. D. Essential micronutrients; III, Sulphur:  in Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian  E., editor), p. 235-258, illus. (incl. tables, plates), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Nellis, Marvin Duane. Water management in the North Deschutes Unit Irrigation District; geographic  perspectives and remote sensing applications: 267 p., Doctoral, 1980, Oregon State Univ., Corvallis, OR.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Nelson, Alan R.  Chronology of Quaternary landforms, Qivitu Peninsula, northern Cumberland  Peninsula, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada:  Boulder, Colo.: Institute of Arctic &amp; Alpine Research,  University of Colorado, 1969-, Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 265-286, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Nesbitt, H. Wayne; Markovics, G.; and Price, R. C. Chemical processes affecting alkalis and alkaline  earths during continental weathering: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society,  Journal). Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 11, p. 1659-1666, illus., 1980.  Newby, L. C. Phosphorus and nitrogen levels of Spartina foliosa and Salicornia virginica in a disturbed  and undisturbed marsh:  in Coasts under stress (Orme, A. R., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer  Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 34, p. 202-213, block diag., tables, sketch  maps, 1980.  Neyshtadt, M.I. Izucheniye bolot v Federativnoy Respublike Germanii [Bog study in West Germany]:  Akademiya Nauk SSSR, Izvestiya, Seriya Geograficheskaya. Moscow., No. 3, p. 123-128, illus., 1980.  Nikitin, Ye. D.  Strukturno-funktsional'naya model' pochvy i yeye ispol'zovaniye v geneticheskom  pochvovedenii i pri izuchenii ekologii [A structural-functional soils model and its use in soil science and  ecology studies]: Zhizn' Zemli (Moskovskiy Universitet, Muzey Zemlevedeniya, Sbornik). Moscow.,  No. 14, p. 114-120, illus., 1980.  Nikitin, Ye. D.  Zonal'nost' pochvennogo pokrova ravninnykh tayezhno-lesnykh regionov i yeye  otrazheniye v ekspozitsii prirodovedcheskikh muzeyev [The zoning of soil covers of the taiga-forest  lowland regions and their representation in natural history museums]:  Zhizn' Zemli (Moskovskiy  Universitet, Muzey Zemlevedeniya, Sbornik). Moscow., No. 14, p. 146-153, 1980.  Nowicki, H. G.; and Devine, R. F. Application of a conventional purging device interfaced to a  computerized GC/MS for analyzing volatile organic compounds in soil-sedimefit:  Heidelberg: Dr.  Alfred Huthig Publishers, 1978-, Vol. 3, No. 7, p. 360-361, 1980.  Nyandat, N. N.; and Muehena, F.N. Land evaluation in Kenya with particular emphasis on the physical  criteria used:  in Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and Land  Evaluation, United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 26-48, tables,  sketch map, 1980.  Oehtman, L. H.J. A brief account of land evaluation in the settlement authority in Ethiopia: in Third  meeting of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and Land Evaluation, United Nations,  F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 106-108, 1980.  Page, F.; De Kimpe, C. R.; Bourbeau, G. A.; et al. Formation d'horizons cimintes dans les sols sableax  du delta des rivieres Manicouagan et Outardes, Quebec [The formation of cemented horizons in the  deltaic sandy spils of the Manicouagan and Outardes rivers, Quebec]: Canadian Journal of Soil Science  (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 60, No. 2, p. 163-175 (incl. English sum.), tables, plates,  geol. sects., 1980.  Pals, J. P.; Van Geel, B.; and Delfos, A. Paleoecological studies in the Klokkeweel Bog near Hoogkarspel  (prov. of Noord-Holland):  Review of Palaeobotany and Palynology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 30, No. 3-4, p. 371-418, illus. (incl. charts, plates, sketch map), 1980.  Parker, Albert John. Environmental and temporal patterns along compositional and structural gradients  in two montane conifer forests of western North America: 295 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Wisconsin,  Madison, WI. available from: Univ. Microfilms.    189    Parker, John L.; Decker, Gordon L.; and Jackson, Michael T. Soil survey of Stillwater County area,  Montana: 131 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:443,520), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conscrv. Scrv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Mont. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Peck, A. J.; Yendle, P. A.; and Batiml, F. E. Hydraulic conductivity of deeply weathered materials in  the Darling Range, Western Australia: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 18, No.  2, p. 129-138, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Penven, M. J. Observations preliminaires sur les alterites granitiques de Petite Kabylie (Algerie)  [Preliminary observations ofaltered granites of the Lesser Kabylia, Algeria]: Mediterranee. Paris., Vol.  38, p. 47-58 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sktch maps), 1980.  Pescado, Pedro, Jr.; and Brockmann, Lester C. Soil survey of Richland County, Montana: 711 p., illus.  (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:443,520), U.. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Mont. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Peterson, John B. Use of Landsat data to expedite soil survey operations: in Computer mapping of  natural resources and the environment; including applications of satellite-derived data (Moore, Patricia  A., editor), Vol. 10, p. 105-112, illus. (incl. sketch maps), Harv. Univ., Cambridge, MA, United States,  1980.  Petrukhin, V. P.; and Al'perovich, S.V. Deformation mechanism of cemented clayey soils: New York,  N.Y.: Consultants Bureau, 1965-, Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 51-57, illus. (incl. tables), 1980 [1980].  Pfister, P. Essais au dilatometre dans les sols raides et les roches [Dilatometer tests in stiff soils and  in rocks]: International Association of Engineering Geology, Bulletin--Association Internationalc de  Geologic de rlngenieur, Bulletin. Paris., No. 21, p. 53-57 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Pitts, James J. Soil survey of Marion County, South Carolina: 99 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with S.C. Agric. Exp. Stn. and S.C. Land Resour. Conserv. Comm.).  Pokrovskiy, S. G.; and Speranskaya, Ye. S.  K metodike izucheniya vliyaniya me!iorativnykh  osushitel'nykh sistem na prilegayushchiye lugovo-bolotnyye fitotsenozy [The influence of drainage basin  reclamation systems on adjacent meadow-swamp phytocoenoses]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta,  Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 3, p. 51-55 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Popescu, Maria; and Mocanu, Ana. Metoda rapida de urmarire pc tcren a gradului de altcrarc a rocilor  din perimentrul zacamintului Moldova Noua [In situ fast method for determining the weathering degree  of the rocks in the Moldova Noua ore body]: Mine, Petrol si Gaze (Romania, Ministerul Minelor,  Petrolului si Geologiei). Bucharest., Vol. 31, No. 3, p. 116-119 (incl. English, Russian sum.), illus. (incl.  tables, plate), 1980.  Prusinkiewicz, Z.; Bednarek, R.; and Pokojska, U.  Glcby bielicowe w Polsce [The soils of the  podzolozem-class in Poland]: Przeglad Geograficzny. Warsaw., Vol. 2, No. 1, p. 103-113 (incl. English,  Russian sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Pryor, Wayne A.; Potter, Paul Edwin; and Maynard, Barry. Shale; an overview [abstr.]: [Tulsa, Okla.:  American Association of Petroleum Geologists], Vol. 64, No. 5, p. 769, 1980. AAPG-SEPM-EMDannual  meeting.  Puehelt, H.; and Walk, H. Umweltrelevante Spurenelemcnte in Boeden eines alten Bergbaugebietes  [Trace elements of environmental importance in soils of an old mining district]: Naturwissenschaften.  Berlin., Vol. 67, No. 4, p. 190-191, table, sketch map, 1980.  Raghavswamy, V.; and Vaidyanadhan, R. Morphology and land systems of a part of Visakhapatnam  District, Andhra Pradesh from air photo studies: Photonirvachak; Journal of the Indian Society of  Photo-lnterpretation. Dchra Dun., Vol. 8, No. 1, p. 9-21, illus. (incl. table, photos, geol. sketch map),  1980.  Raines, Gary L.; and Canney, Frank C. Vegetation and geology: in Remote sensing in geology (Siegal,  Barry S., editor; et al.), p. 365-380, illus. (incl. table, plates), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United  States, 1980.  Rats, M. V.; and Pyrchenko, V. A. Optimization of the volume of investigations of construction  properties of soils: New York, N.Y.: Consultants Bureau, 1965-, Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 76-81, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980 [1980].    190    Reardon, E. J.; Mozeto, A. A.; and Fritz, P. Recharge in northern clime calcareous sandy soils; soil  water chemical and carbon-14 evolution:  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical  Society, Journal). Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. I 1, p. 1723-1736, illus., 1980.  Renger, M.; and Strebel, O. Jaehrliche Grundwasserneubildung in Abhangigkeit yon Bodennutzung  und Bodeneigenschaften [Annual ground-water recharge rate in regard to vegetation and soil conditions]:  Wasser und Boden. Hamburg., Vol. 32, No. 8, p. 362-366 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Retallaek, Greg. Fossil soils and vegetation of a Mid-Cretaceous coastal plain in central Kansas [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12. No 5, p. 254,  1980.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  Rinaldo-Lee, Marjory B.  Field methods for determining saturated and unsaturated hydraulic  conductivity for potential land disposal sites [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with  Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 5, p. 255, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, North-  Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  Rivard, R.; and De Kimpe, C.R. Proprietes de quelques sols riches en graviers dans la region de Quebec  [Properties of some gravel-rich soils from the Quebec region]:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science  (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 60, No. 2, p. 263-273 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl  tables), 1980.  Roberts, B.A. Some chemical and physical properties of serpentine soils from western Newfoundland:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 60, No. 2, p. 231-240  (incl. French sum.), plates, tables, 1980.  Rogers, John H. Soil survey of Placer County, California, western part: 204 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:380,180), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Rogers, Robert John. A numerical model for simulating pedogenesis in semiarid regions:  296 p.,  Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Rognon, P. L'etude de la surface des continents; pedologie, geomorphologie et Quaternaire [Study of  the surface of continents; pedology, geomorphology and Quaternary]:  in Livre jubilaire du cent  cinquantenaire 1830-1980, Societe Geologique de France, Memoire Hors Serie. Paris., No. 10, p. 307-  321 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Romans, J. C. C.; Robertson, L.; and Dent, D. L. The micromorphology of young soils from South-East  Iceland: Geografiska Annaler, Series A, Physical Geography (Svenska Saellskapet foer Antropologi och  Geografi). Stockholm., Vol. 62, No. 1-2, p. 93-103, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Russell, J. D.; Jones, D.; Vaughan, D.; et al. A prelim!nary study of fungal' melanin by infrared  spectroscopy: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.,  Vol. 24, No. 3, p. 207-213, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Salgado-Labouriau, Maria Lea.  A pollen diagram of the Pleistocene-Holocene boundary of Lake  Valencia, Venezuela: Review of Palaeobotany and Palynology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  30, No. 3-4, p. 297-312, illus. (incl. tables, charts, sketch map), 1980.  Sallee, Kenneth H. Soil survey of Doniphan County, Kansas: 86 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Kans. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Salminen, Reijo. On the geochemistry of copper in the Quaternary deposits in the Kiihtelysvaara area,  North Karelia, Finland: Finland, Geologinen Tutkimuslaitos, Bulletin. Espoo., No. 309, 48 p., illus. (incl.  tables, geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Samki, J. K' Land evaluation methodology with particular emphasis on the physical criteria used in  Tanzania:  in Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-committee for Soil Correlation and Land  Evaluation, United Nations, F. A. O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, p. 49-61, 1980.  Satoh, Iehiro; Yamane, Masakatsu; Matsuda, Keiiehiro; et al. Effect of ridge type on salt accumulation  in dry land conditions; I, Effects of the ridge type on water consumptive use and physical properties of  soils: Sand Dune Research (Tottori University, Sand Dune Research Institute). Tottori, Japan., Vol. 26,  No. 2, p. 41-52 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sects.), 1980.  Satyanarayana, B.;andGarg, R.K. Bearing capacity offootings on layered C-~b soils: NewYork, N.Y.:  American Society of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106, No. GT7, p.  819-824, 1980.    191    Sayago, Jose M. Geomorfologia aplicada a hidrologia y suelos en el Valle de San Alberto, Provincia  de Cordoba [Geomorphology applied to hydrology and soils in San Alberto Valley, Cordoba Province]:  Acta Geologica Lilloana (Universidad Nacional de Tucuman, Instituto Miguel Lillo)., Vol. 15, No. 2,  p. 119-138 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Sayago, Jose Manuel. Estudio de la fisiografia y los suelos en el sureste de la Provincia de Santiago del  Estero, mediante el empleo de imagenes "Landsat" [Study of physiography and soils in southeastern  Santiago del Estero with Landsat imagery]:  Acta Geologica Lilloana (Universidad Nacional de  Tucuman, Instituto Miguel Lillo)., Vol. 15, No. 2, p. 5-19 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. geol. sketch  map), 1980.  Schoer, J.; and Nagel, U. Thallium in Pflanzen und Boeden; Untersuchungen im suedlichen Rhein-  Neckar-Kreis [Thallium in plants and soils; investigations in the southern Rhine-Neckar region]:  Naturwissenschaften. Berlin., Vol. 67, No. 5, p. 261-262, sketch maps, 1980.  Schuch, M. Physik des Torfes und der Moorboeden [Physics of peat and moor soils]: in Moor- und  Torfkunde (Goettlich, Karlhans, editor), p. 205-210, illus. (incl. table), E. Schweizerbart'sche  Verlagsbuchhandlung (Naegele u. Obermiller), Stuttgart, Germany, Federal Republic of, 1980.  Shahghasemi, Ebrahim. Simulation modeling of erosion processes on small agricultural watersheds:  286 p., Doctoral, 1980, Iowa State Univ. of Science &amp; Technol., Ames, IA. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Sheldon, Wayne B. Soil survey of Modoc County, California, Alturas area: 154 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Shimanouchi, T.; Hutchison, W. W.; Mashiko, Y. (chairpersons); et al. Seventh international CODATA  conference: Oct. 8-11, 1980, Japan. CODATA Bulletin (International Council of Scientific Unions,  Committee on Data for Science and Technology). Paris., No. 37, 64 p., 1980.  Sinclair, Alastair J. Statistical analysis of trace element data: in Applied soil trace elements (Davies,  Brian E., editor), p. 131-153, illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Singh, A. N. Comparison of reconnaissance soil maps prepared by conventional method and Landsat  imagery interpretation: Photonirvachak; Journal of the Indian Society of Photo-Interpretation. Dehra  Dun., Vol. 8, No. 1, p. 1-8, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Smalley, I. What's happening in loess stratigraphy: Geological Society of New Zealand, Newsletter.  [Christchurch]., No. 49, p. 7-8, 1980.  Smith, C.J. Ecology of the English Chalk: 573 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), Acad. Press,  London, United Kingdom, 1980.  Sokolovich, V. E. Electrostatic forces in soils: New York, N.Y.: Consultants Bureau, 1965-, Vol. 17,  No. 2, p. 57-64, illus. (incl. tables), 1980 [1980].  Souders, Vernon L.; Smith, Frank A.; and Swinehart, James B. Geology and groundwater supplies of  Box Butte County, Nebraska: Lincoln: Conservation and Survey Division, Institute of Agriculture and  Natural Resources, The University of Nebraska-Lincoln, 1944-, No. 47, 205 p., tables, sketch maps,  1980.  Spaitenstein, Henri. Les principaux types de sols du Bois de Chenes (VD) et modele de repartition  spatiale [The principal types of soils of the Bois de Chenes (Vaud, Switzerland) and model of spatial  distribution]: Societe Vaudoise des Sciences Naturelles, Bulletin. Lausanne., Vol. 75, Fascicule 1, No.  357, p. 23-37 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sects., sketch map), 1980.  Spektor, M. Minimization of the energy consumption of soil deformation: Journal of Terramechanics.  Pergamon Press, Oxford-New York., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 63-77, illus., 1980.  Staender, Wolfgang.  Ermittlung des Kraft-Verformungsverhaltens yon gefrorenen Boeden im  Gefrierschachtbau [Determination of the force-deformation behavior of frozen ground in building  freezing shafts]: Glueckauf-Forschungshefte; Zeitschrift zur Verbreitung von Forschungsergebnissen im  Bergbau., Vol. 41, No. 4, p. 170-180, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Stanley, K. O. Bioturbation of eolian facies of the mid-Tertiary Arikaree Group, eastern Wyoming  [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 5,  p. 256-257, illus., 1980.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.    192    Steger, H. F.  Certified reference materials:  Ottawa: Canada Centre for Mineral and Energy  Technology, No. 80-6E, 30 p., tables, 1980.  Stimpson, Jerry V.; Mathis, Roy L., Jr.; Shope, William I.; et al. Soil survey of Vance County, North  Carolina: 94 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soils map 1:126,720; soils maps [:20,000), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with N.C. Agric. Res.  Serv.; Vance Cty. Board Comm.).  Stone, Kenneth L.; McConoughey, Edwin H.; Bottrell, George D.; et al. Soil survey of Lucas County,  Ohio: 139 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soils maps 1:190,080; soils maps h15,840), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Ohio Dep. Nat.  Resour., Div. Lands Soil; Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).  Straw, Allan.  The age and geomorphological context of a Norfolk palaeosoh  in Timescales in  geomorphology (Cullingford, R. A., editor; et al.), p. 305-315, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), John Wiley  &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Summer, Rebecca Mac.  Alpine soil erodibility of Trail Ridge, Rocky Mountain National Park,  Colorado: 200 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, CO. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Sundberg, K. Effect of impregnating waters on conductivity of soils and rocks: Log Analyst (Society  of Professional Well Log Analysts). Houston, Texas., Vol. 21, No. 3, p. 19-32, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Thorn, Colin E.; and Hall, Kevin. Nivation; an Arctic-alpine comparison and reappraisal: Journal of  Glaciology. Cambridge, England., Vol. 25, No. 91, p. 109-124, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Thornton, Iain; and Webb, John S. Regional distribution of trace element problems in Great Britain:  in Applied soil trace elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 381-439, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1980.  Tieh, Thomas T.; Ledger, Ernest B.; and Rowe, Marvin W. Release of uranium from granitic rocks  during in situ weathering and initial erosion (central Texas):  Chemical Geology; an International  Journal. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 29, No. 3-4, p. 227-248, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch  map), 1980.  Toh, C. T.; and Sloan, S.W. Finite element analyses of isotropic and anisotropic cohesive soils with  a view to correctly predicting impending collapse: International Journal for Numerical and Analytical  Methods in Geomechanics. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, Sussex, England., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 1-23,  illus., 1980.  Tolchel'nikov, . S.; and Kostarev, A. S.  Absolyutnyy vozrast vtorogo gumusovogo gorizonta  vtorichno-podzolistykh pochv Smolenskoy oblasti [The absolute age of the second humus horizon of  secondary Podzols of the Smolensk region]: Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya.  Leningrad., Vol. 112, No. 4, p. 350-355, tables, 1980.  Torgersen, Thomas. Controls on pore-fluid concentration of 4He and n2Rn and the calculation of 4  He/n2Rn ages: Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association of Exploration Geochemists, Journal).  Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1, p. 57-75, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Tout, R. E.; and Chatt, A. A critical evaluation of short-lived and long-lived neutron activation products  for trace element determinations: Analytica Chimica Acta. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  118, No. 2, p. 341-358, tables, 1980.  Townsend, William R.; and Wilson, Curtis R. Soil survey of Conway County, Arkansas: 91 p., illus.  (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map h190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv. For. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Arkansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Trimble, Donald E. Cenozoic tectonic history of the Great Plains contrasted with that of the southern  Rocky Mountains; a synthesis:  Mountain Geologist (Rocky Mountain Association of Geologists).  Denver, Colorado., Vol. 17, No. 3, p. 59-69, illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Tsai, C. F.; Lara, Ignatius; and Martin, Geoffrey R. Seismic response of cohesive marine soils: New  York, N.Y.: American Society of Civil Engineers, Geotechnical Engineering Division, 1974-, Vol. 106,  No. GT9, p. 997-1012, illus., 1980.  Tucker, Glenn Jefferson.  Land application of an industrial sludge and its effect on heavy metal  relationships in a soil-plant system:  161 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Kansas, Lawrence, KS. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.    193    Twidale, C. R. The Devil's Marbles, central Australia: Royal Society of South Australia, Transactions.  Adelaide., Vol. 104, Parts 3-4, p. 41-49, 1980.  Umehara, Yasufumi; and Zen, Kouki. Constant rate of strain consolidation for very soft clayey soils:  Soils and Foundations (The Japanese Society of Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering). Tokyo.,  Vol. 20, No. 2, p. 79-95, illus. (incl. tables, plates), 1980.  United Nations, Food and Agriculture Organization. Third meeting of the Eastern African Sub-  committee for Soil Correlation and Land Evaluation: April 18-30, 1978, Zambia. United Nations, F. A.  O., World Soil Resources Reports. Rome., No. 51, 164 p., tables, geol. sketch maps, 1980.  Ure, A. M.; Ewen, G. J.; and Mitchell. M. C. A three-channel flame atomic absorption/emmission  spectrometer for the rapid, routine determination of major cations in soil extracts and plant ash solutions:  Analytica Chimica Acta. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 18, No. 1, p. 1-9, illus. (incl. tables),  1980.  Urvas, Leila. Etela-ja Pohjois-Suomen luonnontilaisten turpeiden viljavuuserot [Comparison of the  chemical properties of virgin peat soils in southern and northern Finland]: Suo (Suoseura). Helsinki.,  Vol. 31, No. 1, p. 27-32, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Valentine, D. W. G.; Fladmark, K. P.; and Spurling, B. E. The description, chronology and correlation  of buried soils and cultural layers in a terrace section, Peace River valley, British Columbia: Canadian  Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 60, No. 2, p. 185-197 (incl.  French sum.), plates, tables, strat, sect., 1980.  Van Zant, K. L.; Hallberg, G. R.; and Baker, R.G. A Farmdalian pollen diagram from East-central Iowa:  Iowa Academy of Science, Proceedings. Des Moines., Vol. 87, No. 2, p. 52-55, illus. (incl. sketch map),  1980.  Van Zant, Kent L.; and Lamb, William M. Postglacial pollen sequence from Lima Bog, South-central  Wisconsin [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol.  12, No. 5, p. 259, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  Vaos, Stephanos Pantelis. The application of scanning electron microscopy to the study of kaolin with  emphasis on the kaolins of Georgia and South Carolina: 244 p., Doctoral, 1980, Florida State Univ.,  Tallahassee, FL. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Viktorov, S. V. Svyazi rastitel'nosti s litologicheskimi usloviyami v peskakh Tyuye-Sy (ravninnyy  Mangyshlak) [Relationships between vegetation and lithological conditions in sands of the Tyuye-Su  region, the Mangyshlak Plain]: Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya. Leningrad.,  Vol. 112, No. 4, p. 347-350, tables, 1980.  Vincent, Peter; and Clarke, Vieki. Terracette morphology and soil properties; a note on a canonical  correlation study: Earth Surface Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group).  John Wiley and Sons, London-New York., Vol. 5, No. 3, p. 291-295, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Vovk, A.A.; Mikhalyuk, A.V.;Chernyi, G.I.; etal. Mechanical properties offrozen soils under dynamic  loads: New York, N.Y.: Consultants Bureau, 1965-, Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 64-69, illus. (incl. tables), 1980  [1980].  Wada, Koji; and Okamura, Yutaka. Electric charge characteristics of Ando Al and buried A1 horizon  soils: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 31, No. 2, p. 307-314, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Wagle, Shared; and Nagy, George. Development of drainage-basin and soil-type data base in Nebraska:  in Cartographic and statistical data bases and mapping software (Moore, Patricia A., editor), p. 71-102,  illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Harv. Univ., Cambridge, MA, United States, 1980.  Warren, Harry V. Biogeochemistry, trace elements, and mineral exploration:  in Applied soil trace  elements (Davies, Brian E., editor), p. 353-380, tables, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom,  1980.  Watts, F. C.; and Stankey, D.L. Soil survey of St. Lucie County area, Florida: 183 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Fla., Inst. Food. Agric. Sci., Agric. Exp.  Stn., Soil Sci. Dep.; Fla. Dep. Agric. Consum. Serv.).  Weber, Bernard. Histoire de la vegetation du marais de Champ-Buet a la lumiere des macrorestes  vegetaux [History of vegetation in the Champ-Buet Marsh in the light of vegetal macroscopic remains]:  Societe Vaudoise des Sciences Naturelles, Bulletin. Lausanne., Vol. 75, Fascicule 1, No. 357, p. 51-64  (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, chart), 1980.    194    Webster, R. DIVIDE; a Fortran IV program segmenting multivariate one-dimensional spatial series:  Computers and Geoscienees. Pergamon Press, Oxford -New York., Vol. 6, No. 1, p. 61-68, illus., 1980.  Weeks, Herbert H.; Hyde, Adam, G.; Roberts, Alfred; et al. Soil survey of Santa Rosa County, Florida:  150 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Fla. Inst.  Food Agric. Sci., Agric. Exp. Stn. Soil Sci. Dep.; Fla. Dep. Agric. Consum. Serv.).  Woodroffe, C. D. The lowland terraces:  in Symposium on the geomorphology of the Mulu Hills  (Sweeting, M. M., editor; et al.), Geographical Journal (Royal Geographical Society). London., Vol. 146,  Part 1, p. 21-32, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Wright, Herbert E., Jr. Surge moraines of the Klutlan Glacier, Yukon Territory, Canada; origin,  wastage, vegetation succession, lake development, and application to the late-glacial of Minnesota: in  Klutlan Glacier issue (Wright, H. E., editor), New York, N.Y.: Academic Press, 1970-, No. 14, p. 2-18,  illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1980.  Wright, V.P. Climatic fluctuation in the Lower Carboniferous: Naturwissenschaften. Berlin., Vol. 67,  No. 5, p. 252-253, illus., 1980.  Wroblewski, David V.; and Lunde, Nordan d. Soil Survey of Emmons County, North Dakota: 185 p.,  illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with N.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Zaslavskiy, M. N. Zashchita pochv ot erozii; krupnaya prirodookhrannaya problema [Soil erosion  prevention; a major environment conservation problem]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5,  Geograflya. Moscow., No. 3, p. 33-39 (incl. English sum.), 1980.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  