 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 35--53                                                        35  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CHANGES IN SURFACE STRUCTURE (CRUSTING) AFTER  APPLICATION OF SEWAGE SLUDGE AND PIG SLURRY TO  CULTIVATED AGRICULTURAL SOILS IN NORTHERN ITALY    M PAGLIAI, E.B.A. BISDOM and S. LEDIN  C N.R. --Institute for Sod Chemzstry, 78-Pisa (Italy)  Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  Department of Soil Sciences, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, S-75007  Uppsala 7 (Sweden)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Pagliai, M., Bisdom, E.B.A. and Ledin, S., 1983. Changes in surface structure (crusting)  after application of sewage sludge and pig slurry to cultivated agricultural soils in  northern Italy. Geoderma, 30: 35--53.    The first results of a cooperative research project on changes in cultivated agricul-  tural topsoils after treatment with sewage sludge and pig slurry are discussed for a silty  clay soft (Vertic Xerochrept) and a sandy loam soil (Typic Psammaquent) Such changes  are expressed in the surface structure, including crusts, of the soils and have a direct  effect on their fertility. To measure these changes, special attention was paid to porosity  characteristics, especially increases in porosity after application of organic manures to  agricultural soils with crusting problems. Light microscopy,  SEM-EDXRA (scanning  electron microscopy -- energy dispersive X-ray analysis) and Quantimet (electro-optical  image analysis) were applied and allowed quantitation and visualisation of pores. Initial  results clearly demonstrate that the porosity of the topsoil increased after treatment  with urban refuse or pig slurry and that crusting decreased.    INTRODUCTION    This cooperative research project of IWGSUSM (International Working  Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials) was started to de-  termine the effect of the application of livestock effluents and sewage  sludges on the structure of Italian softs with crusting problems. Soft crusting  in cultivated softs is one of the most dangerous phenomena in Italy both  from an agronomic and a soil erosion point of view. The main effects of a  soil crust are: reduction of water infiltration, increase in run-off, reduction  of gas exchange between the soft and atmosphere, and interference with  seed germination.  Many authors have studied the structure and the mechanism of formation  of soil crusts (McIntyre, 1958; Evans and Buol, 1968; Epstein and Grant,  1973; Falayi and Bouma, 1975; Pagliai and La Marca, 1979; Pagliai et al.,    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    3~    1981b; Jongerms, 1981). According to the mechamsm of formation, two  types of crusts can be distinguished, 1.e. those formed as a result of raindrop  impact (structural crusts), and those formed by translocation of free parti-  cles and their deposition at a certain distance from their original location  (deposltional crusts) (Chen et al., 1980).  The principal reason for crust formation in cultivated soils is poor stablh-  ty of soil aggregates upon which the impact of raindrops causes detachment  of constituents. The lnstablhty of aggregates is higher the lighter the texture  of the soft and the lower its organic matter content. This small amount of  orgamc matter IS caused by a severe shortage of manure and by intensive  cultivations whmh replaced the traditional farming rotations. Moreover,  heavy rainfall followed by a strong and dry wind is normal in the Po area  of northern Italy and the decompositmn rate of orgamc matter is high m  the Italian chmate. For these reasons, sources of orgamc matter had to be  found, i.e. hvestock effluents and sewage sludges In which the organic matter  accounts for about 50% of the sludge dry matter. The area with intensive  cultivation Is increasing m Italy and due to a severe shortage of manure,  the use of sewage sludge and pig slurry has become increasingly popular.  This study has been carried out with an m situ investigation of unharden-  ed soil peds and crusts by SEM (scanning electron microscope) and by  examination of soil materials m thin sectmns with the hght microscope,  SEM-EDXRA (scanning electron microscope -- energy dispersive X-ray  analyzer) and Quantlmet 720 (electro-optical image analyzer). Special atten-  tion was paid to the upper 5 cm of the soft, especially to porosity changes  related to the application of manure and sewage sludge.  The present paper ~s the hrst of a serms Only some of the samples have  been examined with all techmques so far, vlz. the upper part of a silty clay  soft --treated with 300 m3/ha of pig slurry -- by hght microscopy, SEM-  EDXRA and Quantlmet, and a sandy loam soil -- treated with compost of  anaerobic sludge and the organic fractions (20--80%} of urban refuse (CANS  m Table I) -- by light microscopy and Quantnnet. Samples of control plots  of both soils were also investigated with the light microscope and Quantlmet.    EXPERIMENTAL PLOTS AND  SAMPLING    Two soils with a strong tendency to form surface crusts were chosen for  experunents with pig slurry and sewage sludge. A silty clay soil (Vertic  Xerochrept) and a sandy loam soil (Typm Psammaquent) were planted with  corn in May 1980. Pig slurry was applied in June to the silty clay, about one  month after the corn was sown, whereas the sewage sludge had been plough-  ed into'the sandy loam before May 1980.  This experiment with silty clay soils was carried out on four plots of 1 ha  each 1 ha represented the control of the Vertic Xerochrept and the other  3 ha were treated with different amounts of pig slurry. 1 ha of the silty clay  soil received 100 m3, a second 200 m~ and the third experimental plot 300    37    m3 of livestock effluent. Surface samples of the Vertic Xerochrept were  taken at the end of September.  The experimental plots on the sandy loam soil (Typic Psammaquent)  were each 500 m:. Six of these plots were studied, viz. one control plot,  four plots which were given different types of sewage sludge, and one  plot that was treated with manure. The four sewage sludges differed in com-  position and were applied in quantities that were equivalent to 50 tons/ha  of manure on an organic carbon basis. The four sludges consisted of aerobic  sludge (AS), anaerobic sludge (ANS), a compost of aerobic sludge and the  organic fraction (40--60%) of urban refuse (CAS), and a compost of an-  aerobic sludge and the organic fraction (20--80%) of urban refuse (CANS).  The sixth plot was treated with manure (M). Surface samples of the sandy  loam soil were taken four months after the application of the sewage sludges,  I.e. at the beginning of September.    SEM  STUDY OF UNHARDENED SOIL MATERIAL    A scanning electron microscope (SEM) study was made of small pieces  of the uppermost part of the silty clay soil which was treated with 300 m3/  ha pig slurry. The secondary electron images (SEI) of pieces of the treated  soil were compared with pieces of the crust of the control soil, i.e. in and  below the dense part of its surface crust. The pieces of soil were attached  to stubs with silver, coated with gold to give conductivity to the insulating  material and studied by SEM. To obtain the right position of the soil pieces  on the stubs these were oriented with the help of stereo microscope and  examined with a Jeol 25S3 scanning electron microscope.  A surface sample of the control plot was broken with pliers to observe  the microstructure of the crust (Fig.l). Three microlayers were distinguish-  able (Fig.la), viz. a very thin top part, a middle part which was much thick-  er, and a lower part of which only the upper section and surface is portray-  ed in the foreground. These three microlayers had different compositions.  The top part was comprised of fine clayey particles (Fig.lb) which were  arranged in platy and other structures. Silt-sized particles were dominant  in the middle microlayer of the crust which was rather clean and fairly free  from adhering clay particles (Fig.lc). A mixture of coarser and finer par-  ticles is distinguishable in the lower part of the crust (Fig.ld).  The crust had formed on nearly horizontal soil surfaces and the following  mechanism of crust formation could be envisaged. Raindrop impact is  believed to be the principal force in the formation of this type of crust  which was called structural crust in the introduction. The raindrops, when  hitting the very top of the soft, separate the finest particles from the silt  and sand which may also move over short distances. The smallest particles  such as single clay minerals, somewhat larger entities and organic materials,  are kept in a dispersed state as long as the rain continues. Water fills every  pore and stands a few millimetres above the surface of the soil because the    38    39    infiltration rate is so low that accumulation of water takes place. When the  rain stops, the finest material sediments on top of the silt and sand particles.  These coarser particles function as a filter and do not allow small particles  to follow the downward movement of percolating water. When the soil  dries, all particles are brought closer together and kept that way by attrac-  tion forces and in the dry state these will affect the clay particles strongest.  Small particles can be brought very close to each other and Van der Waal's  forces will be active; the formation of cation bridges and edge-surface at-  traction is also possible. As long as the crust is dry the short range attrac-  tion forces will remain active.  When 300 m3/ha pig slurry is put onto the silty clay soil, SEM micro-  graphs show that crust formation will continue and that the process as such  remains the same. However, straw fragments (Fig.2a), pig hairs (Fig.2b)  and other organic materials are able to break up the crust (Fig.2c). The re-  sults can be compared with secondary electron images (SEI) of the crust in  the control soft, a top view of which is given at the same magnification in  Fig. 2d.  To allow a continuous view of the upper 0.6 mm of the crust in the  control plot, a photo-montage was made (Fig.3). The very thin top part  with fine clayey material is somewhat less expressed than in Fig.lc and  maximally a few microns thick. It is underlain by the relatively clean middle  part of the crust up to about 0.15 mm depth. This microlayer of silt-sized  particles, without many adhering clay particles, is followed by the lower  part of the studied crust in which a mixture of particles occurs.    LIGHT MICROSCOPY OF THIN SECTIONS    Undisturbed soil samples were taken from the upper 5 cm of a Vertic  Xerochrept {silty clay soil) and of a Typic Psammaquent (sandy loam soil).  At sampling time, m September, the softs were so dry that further shrinkage  was almost negligible. Both the control samples and the samples treated  with pig slurry (silty clay soft) or sewage sludge (sandy loam soil) were air-  dried at room temperature. Samples were subsequently impregnated and  made into thin sections.  The larger part of the upper 5 cm of both softs is portrayed in Figs.4 and  5 (Vertic Xerochrept) and Figs. 6--9 (Typic Psammaquent). Samples treated  with organic material are shown in Figs. 5 and 9.    Fig.1. SEM micrographs of unimpregnated crust of the control plot on silty clay. The  fine clayey material of the Vertic Xerochrept is only a few microns thick at the surface  (a). Detail of the fine clayey material (b). The very thin surface part of the crust is un-  derlain by relatively clean silty particles (c). A mixture of silt and clay can be found in  the lower part of the crust (d).    40    I    c~  o  c~  v  0 ~    41  mm    01    -0.2    .03    .0,4    -0.s    -06    Fig.3. SEM view of about 0.6 mm crust. The same differentiation as given in Fig. I can  be discerned, viz. a very thin surface layer, rather clean slit underneath, and a mixture  of silt and clay particles below 0.15 mm depth. Untreated soil    42    LIGHT MICROSCOPY OF THE SILTY CLAY SOIL    No continuous very thin top part is distinguishable m the surface crust  of the Vertic Xerochrept m Fig. 4 at this small magmflcatlon. The same part  of the crust, however, was clearly indicated on SEI taken by SEM (Fig.l)  and proved to be a few microns think. A pronounced platy structure (Fig.4)  is present in the control plot of the silty clay soil as indicated by the sub-  horizontal fractures. Some orientation of the soil particles was seen with  crossed polarizers at the top of the soil and adjacent to the horizontal frac-  tures.    750 ~m    Fig.4. Platy structure in untreated silty clay crust of a Vertm Xerochrept. Differences  in structure are difficult to estabhsh at this small hght mmroscopic magnification Plane  polarized light (a) and crossed polarizers (b)    A representative area of a thin section from soil treated with 300 m3/  ha of pig slurry is shown in Fig.5. Compared with the untreated soil, a sig-  mficant increase in porosity was discernable. This was thought to be the case  after land spreadings of pig slurry but has now been wsualised. Usually, all  the large pores had an irregular shape. The adhesion of soil particles to or-  ganic materials seemed evident. Cracks and microcracks were also formed in  the thin crust and these are of importance for improved water infiltration.    43    Fig. 5. The silty clay crust of Fig.4 was broken after treatment with pig slurry and con-  slderable macroporosity developed. Plane polarized hght (a) and crossed polarizers (b).    LIGHT MICROSCOPY OF THE SANDY LOAM SOIL    Light microscopy of the Typic Psammaquent shows more variability in  structure than the silty clay soil. A certain microlayering can be observed  in Fig.6, starting with coarser material and ending with clayey material at  the top and at the end of a cycle of sedimentation. On the present surface  of the soil, just above the latest sedimented clay lammella, the start of a  new sedimentation cycle can be discerned and is indicated by a microlayer  of sandy material. A small gully-like structure is present in the lower half  of Fig.6a.  The topography of the soil surfaces in the experimental plots is virtually  flat and it has been indicated above that the impact of raindrops is con-  sidered to be the main force that separates the soil particles in poorly stable  aggregates. Fig.6, however, demonstrates that small-scale sedimentation  processes also do occur in furrows and puddles. Entrapped air may be pres-  ent below a surface sealing of muddy material, and vesicles can form (Fig.  7). In this case, carbon dioxide liberated by biological activity from organic  material added to the soil, may play a role in the formation of vesicles.  Such vesicles can collapse at deeper levels (Fig.7a) or remain intact (Fig.8).  One difference between the bottom part of the two figures is the presence  of a clay lammella in Fig.8 and its absence in Fig.7. It should be noted    44    Fig 6 Two undisturbed layered crusts m sandy loam of an untreated Typm Psammaquent  A new cycle is started at the surface with the deposition of sandy material Near the bot-  tom of the micrograph there is a gully-like structure, a possible origin of whmh is  described in the text. Plane polarized light (a} and crossed polarizers (b)    Fig.7. Vesicles and sealing-layer m sandy loam Collapsed vesmles at the bottom of the  micrograph. Plane polarized light (a) and crossed polarlzers (b). Untreated Typm Psamma-  quent    45    750 ~m  I      J    Fig.8. Uncollapsed vesicles in Typic Psammaquent These are present above a clay lamella  in the centre of the micrograph  Plane polarized light (a) and crossed polarizers (b).  Untreated soil.    Fig.9. Sandy loam of a Typic Psammaquent treated with sewage sludge. Macro-porosity  ~s mainly visible in the form of vertical cracks or channel-shaped pores Plane polarized  light (a) and crossed polarizers (b).    46    that Miller (1971) and Kemper and Miller (1974) regard the presence of  vesicles in the topsoil as an indication of an unstable and transitory struc-  ture helped by a poor stability of soil aggregates.  The other types of pores m Figs.6--8 are often elongated in a subhori-  zontal direction. These pores have irregular walls. The elongated pores  are well expressed underneath the lammellae with fine soil material in Figs.6  and 8, while they also occur at the bottom part of Fig.7. A special type of  pore, related to the collaps of vesicles, is also discernable in the latter figure.  When the sandy loam was treated with sewage sludge (Fig.9) considerable  changes occurred in the surface part of the Typm Psammaquents. Part of  the centre of the silty clay crust on the surface of the soil and the silty  layer underneath have newly formed pores. Channel-type pores are, for ex-  ample, visible at the right hand side of Fig.9b. These pores could also be ob-  served in the field and are therefore regarded as predominantly natural  ones. Frequently, however, such channel-type pores or cracks are regarded  as artificial, caused by drying during sample preparation or by movements  during sampling.    QUANTIMET MEASUREMENTS OF THE LARGER PORES IN THIN SECTIONS    Larger pores,  with diameters larger than 30 pm,  were measured  in the upper 5 cm of the silty clay soil and the sandy loam soil using com-  bmed light mmroscopic and Quantimet techniques. These techmques were  described by Jongerius (1974, 1975), Jongerius et al. (1972, 1979), Ismail    TABLE I    Effect of treatments on porosity of the soil surface layer (0--5 cm), data are the means of  three and five replications, respectively for the silty clay soil and for the sandy loam soil    Treatments    Rounded     Irregular      Elongated      Total  pores         pores         pores           porosity  (%)       (%)       (%)        (%)    Sdty clay sod  Control                       0.3             2.8           6 7             9.8 (1.1)  300 m~/ha of plg slurry       3.0           18.7           9.4            31.1 (2.3)  Sandy loam sod  Control                       2 4             8 2           7 3            17.9 (1.6)  CANS                         1.2           20.5          11.4            33.1 (1.2)    CANS stands for : Compost of anaerobm sludge and the organic fraction of urban refuse  (20--80%). The quantity applied was eqmvalent to 50 tons/ha of manure on an organic  carbon basis  Numbers between parentheses represent the standard error    47    (1975) and Murphy et al. (1977a, b). Such Quantimet measurements of  porosities in thin sections were correlated by Bouma et al. (1977, 1979)  with the saturated hydraulic conductivity of heavy clays.  Quantimet measurements are usually necessary to characterise pore  systems in thin sections. Some of the results of such measurements are  given in Table I for the silty clay and sandy loam soft, 1.e. porosity charac-  teristics of the upper 5 cm of the control plots and of treated plots. Al-  though this is a rather rough approach to porosity measurements, the table  serves to illustrate some differences between the porosities of the control  and treated plots. These measurements will be refined when more thin  sections become available and submicroscopic imaging can be used on a  larger scale, i.e. backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) which are  measured by Quantimet (Bisdom and Thiel, 1981; Jongerius and Bisdom,  1981).    CONTROL                       ORGANICALLY  TREATED    80    60    40  u3  LU  n-  O 20  ,,,   0  er  ~  8e  ~  60  Z  w  ~-  40    20    SILTY  CLAY   SOIL    ELONGATED  PORES    D  IRREGULAR  PORES  [~    ROUNDED  PORES    SANDY  LOAM   SOIL    30  50 500&gt;500     30  50 500&gt;500Jura    Fig.10. Distribution of the size and shape of pores larger than 30 #m before and after  treatment with organic matter    48    The total porosity of the studied mmrographs, made with a light micro-  scope, was determined by Quantimet and shape groups of pores distinguish-  ed, viz. rounded, Irregular and elongated pores. Such shape groups can be  found by measuring the area (A) and the perimeter (Pe) of the pores and  by working with A/Pe2 ratios. Rounded pores have A/Pe2 ~ 0.04, irregular  pores A/Pe2 from 0.04 to 0.015, and elongated pores have A/Pe2 ,~ 0.015  (Bouma et al., 1977). The pores of each shape group were subsequently  subdivided into three size classes, viz.30--50 urn, 50--500 ~m and &gt; 500 pm  (Fig.10). This was done for rounded and irregular pores according to the  equivalent pore diameter, whereas the width, calculated from area and  perimeter data, was used for elongated pores.  In the present study only prehminary results of Quantimet measurements  can be given . The measurements confirm that plots treated with organic  debris have a higher porosity than control plots. The total porosity increased  from 9.8%  (control plot) to 31.1%  (plot treated with 300 m3/ha of pig  slurry) m the Vertic Xerochrept and from 17.9% (control plot) to 33.1%  (plot treated with anaerobic sludge and urban refuse) m the Typic Psamma-  quent (Table I).  The treated plots contained less pores larger than 500 pm than the control  plots (Fig.10), whereas the number of pores smaller than 500 pm increased  in the size classes 30--50 ~m and 50--500 urn. Quantimet measurements  also mdmated that the decrease in pores larger than 500 #m was principally  given by the reduction of elongated pores with respect to the control. This  means that the organic fertilizers were able to reduce cracks which originated  by shrinkage (Paglim et al., 1981a). When rounded pores of Table I are  compared with percentages of rounded pores m Fig.10, it is shown that  large rounded pores occur mainly m plots of the silty clay soils which were  treated with pig slurry, whereas they were present in the control plot of  sandy loam soils. The percentage of irregular pores increased in all organical-  ly treated plots with one exception; pores larger than 500/~m m the sandy  loam soil treated with sewage sludge.    BACKSCATTERED ELECTRON SCANNING IMAGES OF POLISHED BLOCKS AND  THIN SECTIONS    Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) were made of one sample-  block of silty clay treated with 300 m3 of pig slurry. This block represented  the upper 5 cm of a Vertic Xerochrept of which the surface crust had be-  come broken and more porous. The present BESI micrographs only repre-  sent a few examples of what can be done with this submicroscopic technique  on polished blocks and thin sections. High quality micrographs can be ob-  tained of various materials and porosities (Bisdom and Thiel, 1981). With  this technique one can easily obtain images of such quality that even pores  with a diameter smaller than 0.1 um become measurable by Quantimet  (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). If in situ microchemical analysis is also neces-    49    Fig.ll. Backscattered electron scanning image (BESI) of the silty clay crust treated with  pig slurry. Organic matter may take up a position which breaks the crust.    sary, a number of submicroscopic techniques are available (cf. review articles  by Bisdom, 1981a, b).  The present sample-block forms part of a series of which thin sections are  currently being made. These allow microscopic and submicroscopic visualisa-  tlon of the effects of crust formation and destabilisation processes, if present.  For the moment only a few micrographs are given of the surface of the loos-  ened crust (Fig.ll), of part of the former crust at various magnifications  (Fig.12), and of pig slurry which was found 2 to 3 cm below the surface of  the Vertic Xerochrept (Fig.13). These and other BESI images indicate that  the organically treated crust is very heterogeneous in a horizontal and ver-  tical direction.    CONCLUSIONS    Light microscopy, electron microscopy and Quantimet 720 were used to  study the behaviour of surface crusts of Vertic Xerochrepts and Typic  Psammaquents in experimental plots from Italy before and after treatment  with pig slurry and sewage sludge. Only the initial part of our cooperative  research project has been completed and therefore only first results are  discussed in this paper.  SEM observation of unhardened pieces of untreated crust from the  silty clay soil demonstrated that the upper 0.6 mm of the 5 cm thick surface  crust could be subdivided into three microlayers. The uppermost microlayer  was comprised of clayey material and was only a few micrometres thick.  The underlying silty microlayer was about 0.15 mm thick. The lower micro-  layer consisted of a mixture of predominantly silt and clay. The microlayers  are thought to have formed as a result of raindrop impact and the effects of  wetting and drying of the soil together with small-scale sedimentation  processes.  Light microscopy of the 5 cm thick surface crust of the sandy loam soil  demonstrated the existence of various cycles of sedimentation. Each cycle    k    51    Fig.13. Pig slurry (a) and (b) has also been found some centimetres below the surface. A  vaxiety of forms in the organic matter are indicated by BESI.    started with coarser material and ended with clayey material. Microlayering,  although observed by SEM, was far less present in silty clay soil. Sub-hori-  zontal fractures indicated the presence of platy structures in the crusts of  Vertic Xerochrepts.  Porosity changes, going from untreated to treated plots, can be observed  on micrographs from light microscopy or electron microscopy. The attention  in mainly attracted by larger pores and cracks but it is hard to obtain good  insight into the total porosity if no Quantimet techniques are involved. As a  consequence mistakes can be made. In the present case only rough Quan-  timet measurements are involved because additional thin sections must be  prepared for combined BESI and Quantlmet investigation. It is clear, how-  ever, that the increased porosity, after treatment of the soil crust with or-  ganic matter, could be documented by Quantimet and light microscopy.  Pores larger than 500 ~m decreased in number after treatment of the crust,  largely because of a reduction in elongated pores. The percentage of irregular  pores increased in most organically treated plots.  Future research will concentrate on the study of all samples with more  emphasis on submicroscopic techniques to supply backscattered electron  scanning images for Quantimet measurement of capillary and larger pores.  More secondary electron images will also be made of unhardened soil materi-  als in treated and untreated crusts. When all thin sections are ready in the  three laboratories, more light microscopic information will also become  available. The combination of the three techniques will allow better insight  mto the effects of different organic materials on crust formation, especially  on porosity development.    Fig.12 BESI of the crust of a Vertic Xerochrept treated with pig slurry (a). Some organic  fragments of pig slurry axe visible. Microporosity can also be studied by Quantimet if the  black pores are measured in micrographs (b) to (d).    52    REFERENCES    Bisdom, E B A., 1981a A review of the apphcation of submmroscopic techniques m soil  micromorphology, I. Transmissmn electron microscope (TEM) and scanning elec-  tron mmroscope (SEM). In. E.B.A  Bisdom (Editor), Submmroscopy of Soils and  Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the International Working-Group on Submmrosco-  py of Undisturbed Sod Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen Centre for Agricul-  tural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc), Wagenmgen, pp 67--116_  B,sdom, E.B.A., 1981b. A revxew of the application of subm,croscopm techmques m sod  m,cromorphology, II. Electron microprobe analyzer (EMA), scanning electron m,cro-  scope -- energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser mmroprobe mass  analyzer (LAMMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis (ESCA), ion  mmroprobe mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary ion m,croscope (SIM) In_  E B.A Blsdom (Editor), Submmroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop  of the Internatmnal Working-Group on Submmroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Mater,-  als (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wagemngen. Centre for Agr,cultural Pubhsh,ng and Documen-  tat,on (Pudoc), Wagenmgen, pp 117--162  Bisdom, E B A and Thml, F., 1981  Backscattered electron scanning images of porosi-  ties m thin sections of softs, weathered rocks and o,l-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-  EDXRA In E.B.A Bisdom (Editor), Submmroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks.  1st Workshop of the Internat,onal Working Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed  Soft Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Pubhshmg and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp 191--206.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A., Boersma, O, Jager, A and Schoonderbeek, D, 1977_ The  function of different types of macropores during saturated flow through four swel-  hng sod horizons. Soil Scl Soc. Am J., 41(5) 945--950  Bouma, J, Jongerms, A and Schoonderbeek, D., 1979. Calculation of saturated hydrau-  hc conductivity of some pedal clay soils using micromorphometric data  Soil Sci  Soc. Am J,43(2) 261--264.  Chen, Y., Tarchltzky, J, Brouwer, J., Morro, J and Bantu, A, 1980. Scanning electron  microscope observations on soil crusts and their formation, Soil Scl, 130(1) 49--55.  Epste,n, E and Grant, W J, 1973 Soil crust formatmn as affected by ra,ndrop impact.  In  Ecological Studies, 4 Phys,cal Aspects of Soil Water and Salts in Ecosystems, pp  195--201  Evans, D D  and Buol, S W, 1968 Micromorphologmal study of sod crusts  Soil Sci.  Soc Am J,32. 19-22  Falayl, O  and Bouma, J, 1975  Relationships between the hydraulic conductance of  surface crusts and soil management m a Typic Hapludalf Soft Sci. Soc_ Am J., 39:  957--963  Ismad, S_N_A.,  1975  M,cromorphometric soil-porosity characterization by means of  electro-optical image analysxs (Quant,met 720)  Neth. Soil Surv  Inst., Wageningen,  Soil Surv Pap., 9. 104 pp  Jongerms, A, 1974. Recent developments in soil mmromorphology. In G.K Rutherford  (Editor), Soft M,croscopy  Proceedings of the Fourth International Working-Meeting  on Soil Mmromorphology, Kingston, 1973. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont.,  pp 67--83  Jongerms, A , 1975. Micromorphometrm soil analysis by means of Quantimet 720. In  Fortschr,tte der quantltatxven Bildanalyse, Vortrage des IMANCO-Symposmms, pp.  161--185  Jongerms, A, 1981_ Mmromorphological applications ,n agricultural research. Interna-  ,renal Working-Meeting on Soil Mmromorphology. London, 1981. In press    53    Jongerius, A. and Bisdom, E.B.A, 1981. Porosity measurements using the Quantimet  720 on baekscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In E.B A.  Bisdom (Editor), Submieroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the  International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWG-  SUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation  (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp 207--216  Jongerms, A , Schoonderbeek, D. and Jager, A., 1972 The appheatlon of the Quantimet  720 in soil micromorphology The Mmroscope, 20 243--254.  Jongerms, A., Schoonderbeek, D. and Bouma, J, 1979  Micromorphometrm image  analysts of flow patterns in swelling clay softs. In  Proceedings of the Quantlmet-  Symposmm on Advances of Quantitative Image Analysis. Microsc. Acta, Suppl,  3  115--120  Kemper, W.D and Miller, D.E, 1974 Management of crusting soils some practical pos-  sibilities In J.W. Cary and D.D. Evans (Editors), Soil Crusts Agrm Exp Sta, Umv  Ariz., Tech. Bull , 214 1--6  McIntyre, D.S, 1958 Soft splash and the formation of surface crusts by raindrop impact_  So,l Sci., 85 261--266  Miller, D.E., 1971 Formation of vesicular structure m soil. Soil Sci. Soc Am. J , 35(4)  635--637  Murphy, C P., Bullock, P. and Turner, R H, 1977a The measurement and characterlsa-  t,on of voids m soil thin sections by Linage analysis, I Principles and techniques. J  Soil Scl, 28(3). 498--508.  Murphy, C.P., Bullock, P and Btswell, K.J., 1977b. The measurement and charactertsa-  tlon of voids in soil thin sections by image analyms, II Applications. J. Sotl Sci.,  28(3) 509--518  Pagliai, M and La Marca, M., 1979. Mieromorphologieal study of soil crusts. Agrochimi-  ca, 23(1): 16--25.  Paghat, M., Guldl, G., La Marca, M., Giachetti, M. and Lucamente, G., 1981a  Effect  of sewage sludges and composts on soil porosity and aggregation J. Environ. Qual.  In press.  Pagliai, M, La Marca, M_ and Lucamente, G., 1981b Micromorphological mvestigatton  of the effect of sewage sludges applied to soft. Internatmnal Working Meeting on Soil  Mmromorphology, London, 1981 In press                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractThe first results of a cooperative research project on changes in cultivated agricultural topsoils after treatment with sewage sludge and pig slurry are discussed for a silty clay soil (Vertic Xerochrept) and a sandy loam soil (Typic Psammaquent). Such changes are expressed in the surface structure, including crusts, of the soils and have a direct effect on their fertility. To measure these changes, special attention was paid to porosity characteristics; especially increases in porosity after application of organic manures to agricultural soils with crusting problems. Light microscopy, SEM-EDXRA (scanning electron microscopy — energy dispersive X-ray analysis) and Quantimet (electro-optical image analysis) were applied and allowed quantitation and visualisation of pores. Initial results clearly demonstrate that the porosity of the topsoil increased after treatment with urban refuse or pig slurry and that crusting decreased. 