Geoderma, 30 (1983) 219--232  Elsevmr Science Publishers B V., Amsterdam -- Printed m The Netherlands           219    SEM-EDXRA INVESTIGATION OF TUBULAR FEATURES AND IRON  NODULES IN LATERITIC SOILS FROM MALAYSIA    S. ZAUYAH and E.B.A. BISDOM  Sod Sczence Department, Unwersity Pertanmn, Serdang, Selangor (Malaysza)  Netherlands Sod Survey Institute, P.O Box 98, 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Zauyah, S. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1983. SEM--EDXRA investigation of tubular features  and iron nodules in lateritic soils from Malaysia. Geoderma, 30: 219--232.    Tubular features were observed with SEM in unhardened pieces of iron nodules found  in some lateritic soils of Malaysia. EDXRA measurements demonstrated that the tubes  were coated with predominantly Fe and Al They probably represent mycelia encrusted  as a result of lateritization or ferrallitization processes.  The iron nodules frequently exhibited fluidal structures in backscattered electron  scanning images. White areas in the images contained most iron, whilst grey areas of the  nodules were composed of predominantly Al, Si, K and Fe, similar to the composition of  the soil matrix surrounding the iron nodules. The nodules are interpreted as having  formed in clayey material most of which is still present in these features.    INTRODUCTION    Iron nodules are common in many softs of Malaysia. If a soil horizon with  such nodules is more than 25 cm think, the soil is classified as lateritic  (Zauyah, 1982). The profile from which the samples under study were taken  is situated on a very gentle slope in rolling to undulating terrain. The mate-  rial in which the soil formed is interpreted as colluvial. Its age is unknown  but the soil can be classified as a clayey, oxidic isohypothermic Tropeptic  Haplarthox. The horizon in which the nodules with the tubes occur is the  B22cn. The profile is well drained, and rubber trees are growing on it.  Loose unimpregnated pieces of these nodules were studied by S. Zauyah  with a SEM (scanning electron microscope) and by Miss M. Lal of the elec-  tron microscope department of the Pertanian University of Malaysia. Small  tubes that often formed a network in pores or at fracture surfaces were de-  tected. Because no EDXRA (energy dispersive X-ray analysis) system was  available with the SEM, some loose samples of tube-containing iron nodules  were forwarded to E.B.A. Bisdom for microchemical analysis with SEM-  EDXRA.  The present study also concerns SEM-EDXRA investigation of plastic-    0016-7061/83/$03 00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V    220    ~mpregnated polished blocks containing iron nodules embedded in the soft  matrix. Various point analyses were made inside the iron nodules and m the  soft matrix surrounding them. A considerable number of micrographs were  necessary to document and illustrate the matters discussed m this paper    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Loose unlmpregnated pmces of iron nodules and the surfaces of plastm-  Impregnated nodules were studied with a Jeol-JSM-35C equipped with an  EDAX 9100 system with an ECON windowless detector for the detection of  chemical elements. This instrument Is a follow-up of the Jeol-JSM-U3 scan-  nmg electron microscope (SEM) with an EDAX system that consisted of a  $1 (Li) detector with a 707A-type multmhannel analyzer (Henstra et al.,  1973; Bisdom et al., 1975, 1976).  The present study also uses the backscattered electron method (Robinson  and Nickel, 1979; Bisdom and Thlel, 1981). The BE detector used in the  Jeol-JSM-35C is of the semiconductor type and comprises two sohd state de-  tectors. Details of this technique are given by Blsdom and Thiel (1981) and  also in this second issue of the work of IWGSUSM (International Working-  Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials). It is important to  note that hxgh quality backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) can  now be made, and that this techmque allows visual detection of some differ-  ences in chemmal composition between the heavier chemical elements of the  xmages; for example, iron and calcium usually are whitish on BESI, whereas  A1 and Si are greyish on the micrographs. Such differences in chemical com-  positions on BESI are subsequently checked with X-ray images and point  analyses.    Fig  1. A network of tubular features, interpreted as mycelia, with a predominantly  smooth surface inside an iron nodule.    221    RESULTS    Tubular features and iron-containing minerals in unhardened iron nodules    Tubular features and iron-containing minerals were studied m ummpreg-  nated iron nodules with SEM-EDXRA. The tubes often formed a network  (Fig. 1) inside pores of the iron nodules or on fracture surfaces. SEM demon-  strated that the length of the tubes ranged from about 15 pm to about 70  um, with diameters between 3 and 4 pm. However, exceptions to these  figures are rather common because of various degrees of encrustation of the  tubes. Both hollow and partly or wbolly filled tubes were found.    Fig. 2. Small tubes with a rough surface caused by growth of small particles inside an iron  nodule.    .m    Fig. 3. Point analyses (a and b) showing that Fe and A1 are the mare constituents of the  walls of the small tubes in the iron nodules    222    Some of the tubes had a smooth surface (Fig. 1) whereas others were  rough because of very small partmles attached to the smooth subsurface  (Fig. 2). EDXRA measurements indicated that Fe and A1 are usually present  in the wall of the tubes (Fig. 3). Very small amounts of $1 were found espe-  cially in point analyses of tubes with an unfavourable position in the SEM  for EDXRA analysis, and were probably due to contamination. Often, even  when care was taken to position the tubes well for measurement, no S~ was  recorded.  Goethite (Fig. 4) and hematite (Fig. 5) were present m a number of pores    Fig. 4 Lentmular goethite crystals in voids of an iron nodule (a) and goethite in a void at  a higher magmficatlon (b)    223    of the iron nodules. Acicular goethite (Fig. 6) could form cutans (goethans)  on the walls of pores, and form a substrate for a network of tubes (Fig. 7)  in some cases. Similar micrographs as given in Figs. 4--6 were published by  Eswaran et al. (1978) for soils of Malaysia and Zaire.  When not only the vicinity of pores is studied with SEM-EDXRA but the  area in between as well, it soon becomes evident that networks of encrusted  tubular features can be found here also. In various micro-areas, all the poro-  sity in between the tubular features is gone. EDXRA measurements in these  areas give: Fe; Fe plus Al; or Fe, AI, Si and K. Ti was also found locally.    Fig. 5. Rounded grains of hematite (a) in voids of an iron nodule, and hematite in a void  at a higher magnification (b).    224    Fig 6 Acmular goethltein agoethan (a),and detail of the goethan(bl    225    Fig. 7. Acicular goethite of a goethan in an iron nodule with a superimposed network of  small tubes (a), and a view showing a complex of goethans and tubular features (b).    Such measurements probably indmate a combination of encrusted tubes and  tubes situated in a clayey soil matrix with considerable iron and some extra  aluminium. The clay in the iron nodules was found by XRD techniques to  be predominantly kaolinite.    226    i  ,: ~i~~!  L    227    Fluidal structures in iron nodules of plastic-hardened polished blocks    Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) of iron nodules in plastic-  hardened polished blocks demonstrated flmdal structures around pores and  m the matrix of the nodules (Figs. 8, 9). The whitish colour on BESI is given    I  ;e :~, : i~5    Fig. 9. Flmdal structure in the matrix of an iron nodule (a), and X-ray image of Fe (b).    Fig. 8. Fluidai structure mainly associated with the wall of pores in an iron nodule (a),  and X-ray image of Fe (b). Point analyses of a whitish area (c), of an intermediately col-  oured area with more AI and Si (d), and of a greyish area (e) with the least Fe. An expla-  nation for the height of the Fe peaks is given in the text    228    by areas with considerable Fe and only small amounts of A1 and S1, accord-  lng to X-ray images and point analyses (Fig. 10). The greyish areas contain  much more A1 and S1, and less iron.  If point analyses of the greyish areas in the iron nodules are compared with  point analyses of the soil matrix which surrounds the nodules {Fig. 11), a  similarity in measurements is evident. Small areas with a higher Fe content  are also present in the soil matrix. Titanium is also found m a number of    mmro-areas.    Fig 10. View of a micro-area m an lronnodule (a) Most of the iron is present m the whit-  ish sites and most of the clay m the greyish sites. X-ray images of A1 (b), $1 (c) and Fe (d)  Point analyses of the whitish area with most Fe (e) and the greyish area with more A1 and  Si (f)    229    Fig. 11. Point analyses (a and b) of the clay in the soil matrix (c). A1 and Si peaks are vir-  tually of the same height and similar in configuration and height to those measured in the  greyish area (Fig. 10f) of the iron nodule.    DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    Tubular features    The tubular features of Figs. 1 and 2 were observed at various magnifica-  tions with SEM, and analysed by EDXRA.  Interpretation of the tubular  features leads to myceha or fungal hyphae. The composition of the wall of  the tubes, i.e. Fe and A1 (Fig. 3), and the overall morphology of the network  of tubular features, indicate encrustation of the mycelia. This means that a  kind of fossilization affected the original fungal hyphae whereby both Fe  and AI were deposited. Such a process, in which Si is leached and Fe and Al  stay in the profile, is called lateritization or ferrallitization.    230    The loose iron nodules, which were not hardened with plastm, also  demonstrate that Fe can accumulate without A1 in the pores (Figs. 4--6),  viz. as goethite and hematite. Consequently, processes giving only iron ac-  cumulation and those giving both iron and alummium accumulation were  documented to have occurred in the same iron nodule. Apart from physmo-  chemical reasoning, the relative abundance of Fe with respect to A1 may  have played a role.    Iron nodules    When the iron nodules are studmd m the field with the unaided eye or at  low magnifications, the red colour often gives an impression of a homogene-  ous structure of the nodules. Light microscopy and SEM-EDXRA analysis  show, however, that the iron nodules are in reahty heterogeneous and have  various internal fabrics. Fluidal structures (Figs. 8, 9) and bands of soil ma-  terials with different colours (Figs. 8--10) are present in BESI and give a  rather comphcated picture, the origin of which is not yet completely under-  stood.  Whitish colours In the micrographs are given by accumulations of Fe to-  gether with some AI and Si (Figs. 8c and 10e). The greyish areas contain less  Fe and more A1 and Si (Figs. 8e and 10f). Attention was primarily given to  peaks of A1 and Si in the point analyses. This was done on a scale whereby  the much larger quantitms of iron remained at a maximum and showed no  visible differences. However, if the vertical scale is changed, or the counts  per second for iron are read, the differences in iron content of the analysed  points become clear.  A striking feature of the A1 and Si peaks in the whitish, greyish and inter-  mediate areas is the equality of height of both peaks. The configuration  remains similar in all micro-areas of the iron nodule, although the height is  largest for the peaks in the greyish areas and smallest in the iron-containing  whitish parts of BESI. When point analyses are made of clayey material  which surrounds the iron nodules, similar peaks to the ones in the greyish  areas of the iron nodule are obtamed (Fig. 11). The interpretation is there-  fore that the iron nodules were formed in clayey material, most of which  is still present, even though affected by weathering processes.  The hypothesis that the kaohnltic clayey material is weathered in and  outside the nodules is based on the described equal peak height of Al and  $1. This IS too high for A1, which, according to experience with SEM-EDXRA  measurements on clays in various soils, should be about half that of the peak  for S1. Of course, individual clay minerals require TEM (transmission electron  microscope) or STEM (scanning transmission electron mmroscope) analysis  for determination at magnifications larger than the 10,000 possible with  SEM-EDXRA. For the moment, however, we may assume that too much A1  has been measured in numerous points of the soil matrix and the iron nod-  ules. This could indicate that relative accumulation of A1 has occurred and  that Si was leached during the weathering of predominantly kaolinitic clay.    231    Titanmm was measured with EDXRA in some micro-areas and is usually  an element which is relatively difficult to leach. Potassium was very often  measured in point analyses other than those in accumulations of iron mine-  rals and in the crusts of the mycelia. The element is much too common for  this lateritic soil, on which rubber trees have been planted. The occurrence  of K is therefore explained as a leaching product of fertilizer which has ac-  cumulated in the soil profile.  The iron nodules which have been analysed are found in soil material  whmh according to field observation may have colluviated. It is possible that  a few of the iron nodules may have been formed before emplacement in the  present position. However, in the main, lateritization processes were prob-  ably occurring in the soils before colluviation, as they do in the present pro-  files. The encrustatlon of the tubular features, which are relatively rare in the  studied profiles, probably occurred nearer to the surface before colluviatlon  brought the iron nodules to the present and deeper position in the B22cn  horizon. Indications are, however, that encrustatlon of mycelia or fungal  hyphae is also possible in the lateritic soils of today because Fe and A1 are  still accumulating and S1 is leached after weathering of the kaolinitic clay  in and outside the iron nodules.  The submicroscopic study of these lateritlc soils can be improved con-  siderably if, besides electron microscopy, trace elements could be studied  with ion microscopy or laser analysis (Bisdom, 1981). The present rather  rough measurements, due to the presence of very small particles in the  studmd soil material, indicate, however, that in situ microchemical informa-  tion may help to unravel the processes which occur dunng lateritizatlon, and  to relate the measurements to XRD and wet chemical analyses of pre-treated  loose samples.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The first author thanks the Pertanian University of Malaysia for financial  support of part of this study.    REFERENCES    Bmdom, E.B A., 1981. A revmw of the application of submicroscopic techniques in soil  micromorphology, If. Electron microprobe analyzer (EMA), scanning electron micro-  scope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis (ESCA), ion microprobe  mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary ion microscope (SIM) In: E.B.A Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Smls and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp. 117--162.  Bisdom, E.B.A. and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-  EDXRA. In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks.    232    1st Workshop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undlsturbed  Soll Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen Centre for Agrmultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp 191--206  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S , Jongerius, A and Thiel, F., 1975  Energy-disperslve X-ray  analysis on thin sections and unirnpregnated sod material_ Neth J_ Agrm Scl , 23(4)  113--125.  Bisdom, E.B A, Henstra, S, Hornsveld, E M., Jongerlus, A. and Letsch, A_C, 1976.  Wavelength and energy-dispersive X-ray mlcroanalysis with EMA and SEM-EDXRA on  thin sections of soils Neth. J Agnc. Sci., 24(4). 209--222  Eswaren, H , Llm, C , Sooryanarayana, V and Nordin, D , 1978 Scanning e]ectron micro-  scopy of secondary minerals m Fe-Mn glaebules. In: M Delgado (Editor), Soil Mmro-  morphology. Proceedings of the 5th International Working Meeting on Soil Micro-  morphology, 1980, University of Granada, pp 851--885  Henstra, S., Bisdom, E.B.A., Jongerius, A. and Thml, F , 1973. Energy-dispersive analysis  on thin sections of soils  First EDAX European users meeting (Liege, September,  1973) EDAXEditor, 3(1): 5--6.  Robinson, B.W. and Nickel, E.H, 1979  A useful new technique for mineralogy: the  backscattered-electron/low vacuum mode of SEM operation. Am. Mineral., 64: 1322--  1328.  Zauyah, S., 1982 Micromorphology of some laterltlC soils in Malaysia. In: 6th Interna-  tional Working Meeting on Soil Mlcromorphology, 1981, London. In press                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractTubular features were observed with SEM in unhardened pieces of iron nodules found in some lateritic soils of Malaysia. EDXRA measurements demonstrated that the tubes were coated with predominantly Fe and Al. They probably represent mycelia encrusted as a result of lateritization or ferrallitization processes.The iron nodules frequently exhibited fluidal structures in backscattered electron scanning images. White areas in the images contained most iron, whilst grey areas of the nodules were composed of predominantly Al, Si, K and Fe, similar to the composition of the soil matrix surrounding the iron nodules. The nodules are interpreted as having formed in clayey material most of which is still present in these features.