 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 301--323                                                      301  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PATTERNS AND CLASSIFICATION BY SOIL TAXONOMY OF THE  SOILS OF THE SOUTHERN COOK ISLANDS    J.G. BRUCE  Soil Bureau, Department of Scientific and Industrial Research, Gore (New Zealand)  (Received June ll, 1982; revised version accepted March 1, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bruce, J.G., 1983. Patterns and classification by Soil Taxonomy of the softs of the South-  ern Cook Islands. Geoderma 31:301-323.    The soil patterns of the six larger islands of the Southern Cook Group in the South  Pacific are described. Classification is according to Soil Taxonomy, and six soil orders are  recognised: Oxisols, Ultisols, Moilisols, Alfisols, Inceptisols and Entisols, which are  further subdivided into 12 suborders, 15 great groups, and 25 subgroups. Classification to  series level is outlined in tabular form. The soil pattern on individual islands is basically  one of concentricity. The older, more weathered soils (Oxisols and Ultisols) occur on  remnant surfaces and grade with either decreasing altitude or age of land surface to Alfi-  sols, Mollisols, Inceptisols, and Entisols, respectively. Many of the soils associated with  the coralline makateas have shallow contacts to the underlying limestone and have been  separated in lithic subgroups.    INTRODUCTION    The Cook Islands archipelago comprises 15 islands with a total land area  of approximately 240 km: within an oceanic area of over 2 million km2. The  islands are situated entirely within the tropical zone between 9and 22  latitude and between 157and 166 longitude {Fig. 1). Rarotonga, the  largest island and seat of government, lies some 3030 km northeast of Auck-  land, New Zealand. Geographically the Cook Islands archipelago is divided  into two groups.  The Northern Group comprises six low coral atolls and a coral cay that  have a total land area of about 28 km:. The islands of the Southern Group  are more diverse, comprising a mountainous volcanic island with fringing  reef; a near-atoll with a volcanic core; four raised coral or makatea (hard  coral limestone forming a raised fringing platform) islands each with a  volcanic core, as well as a coral atoll and a coral cay (Wood and Hay, 1970).  In 1974, the staff of the New Zealand Soil Bureau carried out soil surveys  on the six larger islands of the Southern Cook Group and the soils of each is-  land are described in a series of New Zealand Soil Survey Reports: Raro-    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    302    20'S    30",~    40%~    180"  , w'   F,I, Islands  o    Auckllnd  ~EW  0    !bl    20'S    Ton9a ISland*    Kerma~eJslat'~Js    :bC= W          Ib9              ]58    p. A,tutak,  4* Manuae  Takutea  At,u~    O Rarotonga  160W    (.'.: ,X~. Island~    SOUTH  PACIFIC  OCEAN    i                   I  teo~                     leo%'v    20"S    O  M~haro  Mauke    ManQala  O'    0            100           200 km  I        I        J  1~8o            J  157   30~S    40    156'    20 S    ?2    23    tonga (Leslie, 1980); Mangaia (Webb, 1981); Atiu (Campbell, 1982); Mitiaro  (Wilde, 1981); Mauke (Wilson, 1982); and Aitutaki (Milne, 1983). Detailed  descriptions of soil taxonomic units recognised are described by Bruce  (1983). Two development sequences of soils formed on basaltic parent mate-  rial on the island of Atiu have also been described by Campbell et al. (1978).  The fertility of selected soils from each island is discussed briefly in an  interim report by Widdowson and Blakemore (1975).  The objectives of this paper are to outline the soil pattern of the islands of  the Southern Cook Group at Soil Order level and to classify the soils at series  level according to Soil Taxonomy (Soft Survey Staff, 1975). This assessment  should allow comparisons to be made with other islands in maritime tropical  environments.    Fig. 1. Locality map of the Cook Ialands in the South Pacific Ocean, and the i~lands of  the Southern Cook Group. (In 1974 soil surveys were carried out on the six islands under-  lined.)    303    THE SOIL ENVIRONMENT    The environmental factors influencing the distribution and nature of the  soils of the Southern Cook Group are discussed in detail in the series of New  Zealand Soil Survey Reports listed previously. Only the main environmental  factors for the group are described below.    CLIMATE    The islands of the Southern Cook Group enjoy a humid tropical climate  with wet summers and moist winters. Throughout the group, mean annual  rainfall ranges from 1626 mm on Mauke to an estimated 2400 mm on Atiu,  with the other islands close to a 2000-mm average. The annual rainfall for  each island may vary widely however, from year to year. June, July, August  and September are normally the driest months, in which the monthly pre-  cipitation may range between 70 mm and 125 mm for the various islands. In  general, rainfall is sufficient for plant growth in all months. Throughout the  group the soil moisture regime is udic (or perudic), though some of the soils  developed on coralline debris may be marginal to an ustic soil-moisture  regime. A relatively small area of soils in low-lying poorly-drained depres-  sions, or on estuarine margins have either aquic or peraquic soil-moisture  regimes. The islands lie in the hurricane belt and from time to time are  devastated by high winds and stormy seas.  Annual temperatures average 25 for all islands, though northernmost  Aitutaki tends to have a slightly higher average than southernmost Mangaia.  The seasonal variations range from 3 to about 4.5 which is slightly less  than the diurnal range. Though no soil temperature data are available at pre-  sent, it is probable that, in terms of Soil Taxonomy, the soil temperature is  isohyperthermic, i.e., the mean annual soil temperature is 22 or higher and  the difference between mean summer and mean winter soil temperatures is  less than 5 at a depth of 50 cm or at a lithic or paralithic contact which-  ever is shallower (Soil Survey Staff, 1975).    GEOLOGY AND TOPOGRAPHY    The six islands belong to three of the island types that occur in the South  Pacific Basin, namely, mountainous island with fringing reef, near-atoll with  volcanic core, and makatea islands. Rarotonga (6724 ha) is a mountainous  island, with a number of sharp peaks rising to over 600 m, surrounded by a  narrow coastal plain and fringing reef. It is composed largely of basalt erup-  tives with younger phonolitic eruptives of late Pliocene age (Wood and Hay,  1970). The coastal plain, which does not exceed 800 m in width, consists of  a sequence of flood plains, terraces, and fans related to eustatic fluctuations  of sea level during the Pleistocene. Weathering of the volcanic rocks on Raro-  tonga is less advanced than on the other islands and it is considered the  youngest island of the group.    304    Aitutaki (1806 ha), the smallest island of the Southern Group, is a near-  atoll with a volcanic core. The island, which rises to about 120 m at its  northern end, lies in the northwest part of a large lagoon enclosed by a tri  angular barrier reef. The main volcanic rocks are nepheline basalts and ba-  saltic pyroclastic rocks, which include bedded tuffs and agglomerates, prob-  ably of Pliocene age {Wood and Hay, 1970). The southern part of the island  consists of a series of flat-topped terraces at various levels between 12 m and  76 m, composed of strongly-weathered alluvium. The occurrence in the  southeast part of the lagoon of two small volcanic islands, of the same rock  type as the main island, suggests that the island may once have been con-  siderably larger than at present.  Atiu (2694 ha), Mangaia (3583 ha), Mauke (1845 ha) and Mitiaro {2227  ha) are makatea islands and have similar forms, though there are consider-  able differences in relief. They each have a raised coral platform or makatea  surrounding a low central hill of weathered volcanic rock. Between the in-  ner margin of the makatea and the central hill lies a swampy depression.  The volcanic rocks are basaltic in nature (Wood and Hay, 1970) but are  very strongly weathered. It is probable that the original volcanoes were ex-  tinct by the Oligocene and have undergone erosion and weathering since that  time. Subsidence, uplift, eustatic change of Pleistocene sea levels and con-  tinued erosion since Miocene times are considered to be responsible for the  present form of the makateas, which commenced as platform reefs.  The central hills are capped by dissected plateaus which differ in height  from island to island; Mangaia 169 m (plateau remnant), Atiu 71 m, and  Mauke 27 m. On Mitiaro the central volcanic mass comprises four rounded  island hills, less than 12 m above sea level in an area of swampland.  With the exception of Mitiaro, erosion products from the central hills have  accumulated along and adjacent to the inner margin of the makatea in the  swamplands. On Mangaia and Mauke the accumulations occur as rolling and  undulating hills which may represent dissected and eroded terraces. On Atiu  the accumulations are still discernible as terraces. Erosion products from the  central hills have also been deposited across substantial parts of the makateas  when the makatea surfaces were close to sea level.  The makateas have an average width of at least 1 km, with that of Mangaia  tending to be wider than those of the other three islands. The surface forms  an irregular and broken karrenfeld of jagged limestone pinnacles up to 6 m in  height. From island to island the makateas show considerable differences in  height and outline {Wood and Hay, 1970).    SOIL CLASSIFICATION AND DESCRIPTION OF SOIL CATEGORIES    The classification of softs of the Southern Cook Group according to Soil  Taxonomy (Soft Survey Staff, 1975) is based on soil descriptions given in the  Soil Survey Reports listed previously and in Bruce (1983), and on analyses    305    (Widdowson and Blakemore, 1975; Campbell et al., 1978) obtained during  the 1974 soil surveys.  As this classification was applied after the completion of the surveys, it  was found that in many cases the data available were insufficient to suit all  the criteria required by Soil Taxonomy and as a result certain assumptions  have had to be made. These relate largely to percentage base saturation at  1.8 m; organic carbon content at 1.25 m; and the period of dryness within  the soil-moisture control section. Some soils were not sampled for chemical  or physical analyses and their classification is based on the comparison of  morphological and environmental properties with similar soils in other parts  of the island group. In some cases the original soil series, as recognised and  defined, included more than one taxonomic class. As a result, additional soil  series were established and defined without further field work, although in a  few instances the additional taxa have been retained as variants or inter-  grades within the original series.  On the bases of the soil descriptions and analyses available, the soils of the  six islands are recognised as belonging to six orders: Oxisols, Ultisols, Molli-  sols, Alfisols, Inceptisols, and Entisols. These have been further classified  into 12 suborders, 15 great groups, and 25 subgroups. In the discussion that  follows the classification of the softs to subgroup level is described briefly  under the headings of the soil orders.  Soil families were also recognised according to criteria given in Soil Taxo-  nomy, although full names are not given. For those placements, several kinds  of analyses were made. Determinations of the particle-size classes and min-  eralogy classes were made by techniques currently in use at the Soil Bureau.  Particle-size analyses were made after ultrasonic dispersion of samples with  sodium hexametaphosphate following pretreatment with hydrogen peroxide.  Sedimentation measurements were carried out by the falling-drop method of  Mourn {1965). Mineralogical analyses included X-ray diffraction, differential  thermal analysis and infrared adsorption measurements (Wells and Smidt,  1978). For those soils not sampled or analysed, classes were estimated from  field descriptions and by comparison with comparable known samples.  The full classification nomenclature to series level is given in Table I, that  also includes, where available, Soil Bureau laboratory numbers of samples  representative of each series. Profile descriptions of soils representative of  each of the six soil orders are given in the Appendix.    Oxisols    One Oxisol -- a Eutrorthox -- has been recognised in the Southern Cook  Group. It is developed on the volcanic detritus that partially covers the  upper benches of the makatea on Mangaia. The inner margin of the makatea  is now separated from the central volcanic mass by cliffs up to 60 m high.  Because of the nature of the makatea surface, the volcanic detritus has not  been further eroded and as a result weathering and soil development has  been operating for a considerable period of time.    TABLE I  Soil Taxonomy nomenclature for soil series of the Southern Cook Islands    O    Order      Suborder Great group    Subgroup                 Family differentiae*            Soil        Soil bureau Island  series      lab. no.  Oxisol     Orthox   Eutrorthox     Ruptic-Lithic Eutrorthox clayey, kaolinitic               Oneroa    (SB9014)  Mangaia    Ultisol     Humult  Palehumult     Orthoxic Palehumuit    Plinthohumult  Tropohumult    (Typic) Plinthohumult  Humoxic Tropohumult    clayey, oxidic                   Rangimotia(SB9010)  Mangaia  Tautu      (SB9045)  Aitutaki  Vaimutu       --      Maukc  clayey, kaolinitic               Ivirua      (SB9016)  Mangaia  Tuapapa       --      Mangaia  Vauroa    (SB9011 )  Mangaia  clayey, kaolinitic               Nuata      (SB9047)  Mauke  Te Autua  (SB9023)  Atiu  clayey, kaolinitic               Areora     (SB9051)  Mauke  Veitatei    (SB9019)  Mangaia    Mollisol    Aquoll   Haplaquoll     Fiuvaquentic Haplaquoll  Rendoll      --          Typic Rendoll  Lithic Rendoll    Udoll     Argiudoli    very fine, kaolinitic  fine over sandy-skeletal, mixed  sandy-skeletal, carbonatic    (with Eutropeptic intergrades)  Typic Argiudoll           very fine, mixed  Oxic Argiudoll            very fine, oxidic    Hapludoll      Typic Hapludoll    clayey-skeletal, mixed  fine, mixed    Cumulic Hapludoil  Fluventic Hapludoll    very fine, mixed  fine, mixed  clayey-skeletal, mixed    Vaikai     (SB8913)  Rarotonga  Ngatangiia    --       Rarotonga  Makatea               Atiu  Mauke  Mitiaro  (SB9022)  Mangaia  Mangarei   (SB9038)  Mitiaro  Anaunga   (SB9058)  Aitutaki  Nikaupara     --      Aitutaki  Punganui  (SB9057)  Aitutaki  Maunga Pu     --      Aitutaki  Atuara         --      Aitutaki  Pouara     (SB9042)  Rarotonga  Tikioki    (SB8907)  Rarotonga  Pirikaitu  ....  Aitutaki  Matavera   (SB904:~ ~  Rarotonga  Takuvaine              Rarotonga    Alfisol     Udalf    Tropudalf    Inceptisol  Aquept   Tropaquept  Tropept  Humitropept    Entisol    Typic Tropudalf  Aquie Tropudalf  Oxic Tropudalf    fine, mixed  very fine, montmorillonitic  very fine, kaolinitic    Eutropept    (with some lithic intergrades)    Aerie Tropaquept  Typic Humitropept  Oxie Humitropept  Typic Eutropept  Fluventic Eutropept    fine, montmorillonitic  fine, kaolinitic  fine, mixed  very fine, oxidic  clayey-skeletal,  montmorillonitic  fine, mixed  fine, montmorillonitie  very fine, kaolinitic    very fine, mixed    Arorangi  Nikao  Ngatiarua  Oiretumu  Rakautai  Teenui  Tetoa  Mokoera    Tongarutu  Te Kapi  Pokoinu  Karanga  Te Manga    Taiki  Rutaki  Kurakei  Mataare  Keia    Aquent   Fluvaquent     Tropic Fluvaquent        coarse, loamy, carbonatic       Toroto  very fine, mixed, nonacid       Tamarua    Tapoki  Lithic Tropic Fluvaquent loamy over sandy, carbonatic   Koromiri  Psamment Tropopsamment Typic Tropopsamment   carbonatic                      Muri    {with some lithic intergrades)  Typic Tropofluvent       sandy-skeletal, mixed           Avana  coarse loamy, carbonatic        Vaipeka  Typic Troporthent        sandy-skeletal, carbonatic       Omutu    Fluvent  Tropofluvent  Orthent  Troporthent    (SB8906)  (SB9044)  (SB9029)  (SB9048)  (SB9046)  (SB9030)  (SB9028)  (SB9033)    (SB9027)  (SB8910)  (SB9012)  (SB8908)  (SB9055)  (SB9199)  (SB9031)  (SB9020)  (SB9015)  (SB9040)  (SB9021)  (SB9032)  (SB9053)  (SB8912)  (SB9060)  (SB9052)  (SB8911)  (SB9035)  (SB9041 )    Rarotonga  Rarotonga  Atiu  Mauke  Aitutaki  Atiu  Atiu  Atiu    Aitutaki  Atiu  Rarotonga  Mangaia  Rarotonga  Mauke  Rarotonga  Atiu  Mangaia  Mangaia  Mitiaro  Mangaia  Atiu  Mauke  Mauke  Rarotonga  Rarotonga  Aitutaki  Mauke  Rarotonga  Aitutaki  Atiu  Mitiaro    GO  *All soils are isohyperthermie.  --o    308    These deep softs are characterised by yellowish red to reddish brown,  friable, subsurface horizons of clay texture. Analyses (SB9014; 9017)show  very low cation-exchange capacities (CEC) and mineralogy dominated by the  presence of kaolinite (L.C. Blakemore, personal communication, 1978).  The high base status of these soils is probably the result of accumulation  of solution products from the surrounding makatea limestone. The soil  occurs in pockets of various sizes (1 m up to 10 m in diameter) between the  limestone outcrops. Buried limestone pinnacles come to within 50 cm of the  ground surface in parts of each pedon and as a consequence the soils are clas-  sifted in a ruptic-lithic subgroup.    Ultisols    Ultisols are widely distributed on planated plateau and plateau-remnant  surfaces and on adjacent hilly and steep slopes of the central volcanic hills on  the makatea islands as well as on broad terrace surfaces on the southern part  of Aitutaki. They are developed on strongly weathered basaltic parent mate-  rials. The analyses (SB9010, 9045, 9016, 9011, 9047, 9023, 9051, 9019)  show that in general they have low to very low base status as well as a  marked clay increases in argillic horizons. Characteristically, these softs have  dark brown or dark reddish brown well-structured friable clay loam surface  horizons overlying blocky structured subsurface horizons which are variously  coloured red, yellowish red, reddish brown or strong brown, depending on  the underlying lithology. Subsurface horizons are dominantly clay-textured  with sticky consistency and have cutans and pressure faces on many peds.  The Ultisols are all Humults -- the humus-rich Ultisols -- as they have high  percentages of organic carbon in the upper parts of their argillic horizons.  They are subdivided into three great groups: Palehumults, Plinthohumults,  and Tropohumults.  On the basis of very low amounts of weatherable minerals, six series of  Palehumults have been separated (Table I). They have a strongly weathered  clay fraction (G.G.C. Claridge, personal communication, 1978) and analyses  available (SB9010, 9011, 9016, 9045) show that the CEC/100 g clay is  &lt;24 me. On the assumption that the cation-retention capacity is also low,  these soils have been placed in the orthoxic subgroup. In general the Or-  thoxic Palehumults occur on flattish surfaces, but on the older higher island  of Mangaia they also occur on hilly and steep land and on hilly land of  Mauke.  Two Plinthohumults have been separated, but as subgroups have not been  developed for this great group (Soil Survey Staff, 1975, p.358) they are  tentatively placed in a typic subgroup. These softs occur on the central  plateau surface of both Mauke and Atiu. The plinthite is not continuous but  is of sufficient extent to constitute more than half of a sub-horizon. In both  softs plinthite occurs at depths between 70 cm and 120 cm.  Tropohumults occur on rolling land at the base of the central hill on    309    Mauke and on rolling and hilly land on parts of the central hill adjacent to  the makatea on Mangaia. The two series separated have low-activity clays  (SB9010, 9051) though one (Areora) is marginal. On the assumption that  the soils do not dry out, they have both been classified in the humoxic sub-  group.    Mollisols    Mollisols occupy over one quarter of the area of the Southern Cook  Group and are recognised on each of the six islands {Table II). They are  developed on either basaltic materials or coralline makatea limestone debris,  although in some places the two types of materials are either mixed or  layered. In general, the soils occur at low elevations on undulating and gently  rolling land.  All soils analysed have either high or very high percentage base saturation  {including free lime} throughout their profiles (Widdowson and Blakemore,  1975).  Three suborders of Mollisols have been recognised: Aquolls, Rendolls, and  Udolls.  One Aquoll, a fluventic subgroup of the Haplaquolls, occurs on Raro-  tonga. This soil is unusual in that it has been modified by man for the  cultivation of the staple taro (Colocasia esculenta). It is developed on fine-  textured alluvium from basalt and coral sand in swampy depressions behind  the beach ridges and is well supplied with nutrients (Leamy et al., 1975,  SB8913). A permanently high water table is maintained by a system of spe-  cially constructed low earth dams and intervening ditches.  Typic Rendolls have been recognised on Rarotonga in depressions behind  the beach ridge. They are developed on fine-textured basaltic alluvium over  broken and comminuted coral sand and reef rock.  Lithic Rendolls are the most abundant soils in the Mollisol order and  cover some 3300 ha. They are developed on the raised coralline makateas of  Atiu, Mauke, and Mitiaro and on the low coastal makatea on Mangaia. They  have thin, dark mollic epipedons and a very shallow lithic contact to the  underlying limestone. On part of the makatea on Mangaia, where there has  been greater comminution of the limestone, weak cambic horizons have  developed under the dark epipedon and these soils are regarded as eutropep-  tic intergrades.  Two great groups of UdoUs are recognised on the islands of the Southern  Cook Group: Argiudolls and Hapludolls. The Argiudolls are developed on  weathered basaltic rocks and in general have comparatively thin argillic hori-  zons. They occur on older eroded hilly surfaces on Aitutaki and on the low  remnant volcanic hills in the central swamp within the makatea on Mitiaro.  On Mitiaro, Typic Argiudolls are the only basalt-derived softs on the island  and cover a relatively small area. Analysis shows (SB90381 that they have  high CEC and are fully base-saturated due to the very high exchangeable cal-    O    TABLE II  Areas of soils on the islands of the Southern Cook Group according to the orders of Soil Taxonomy    Soft ordem    Rarotonga      Mangaia        Atiu           Mitiaro         Mauke  (6724 ha!    (3585 ha)    (2694 ha)    (2227 ha)    (1843 hal  ha     %      ha     %      ha     %      ha     %      ha     %    Aitutaki        Total for Group  (1806 ha)    (18 879 ha)  ha     %       ha     %    Oxisols    Ultisols  MoUisols    Alf~ols    Inceptisols  Entisols  Mi~eUaneous    1047   15.5    175    2.5    4630  69.0  819  12.0  53    1.0  (sealed run-  way;fill)    890  25.0  (lithicsub-  groupin part)  1225 34.0  305    8.5  (lithic          (lithic          (mainlylithic   (lithic  subgroup)      subgroup)      subgroup)      subgroup)  --             1080  40.0     --               56    3.0  (lithicsub-  ~oupin part)  497  14.0     430  16.0     --               76   4.0  88    2.5      316   11.5      570   25.0      266   15.0  580  16.0        4    0.5     190    9.0     --  (bare Makatea; (swamp)        (swamp and  swamps)                        lake)    274   10.0      --               390   21.0  520     22.0         1467      66.0         1055      57.0    890   4.5    684      38.0         2573      14.0  521      29.0         4285      26.5    13  0.6   1324   7.0    28        1.4         5661      30.0  560   31.0    2619   14.0  --               827    4.0    311    cium which reflects the effect of solution products from the adjacent maka-  tea.  Three Argiudolls are recognised on Aitutaki; all have cation exchange  capacities that are dominated by clay fractions with low activity (L.C. Blake-  more, personal communication, 1978), and are placed in the oxic subgroup.  Hapludolls have been recognised only on Aitutaki and Rarotonga. (The  late Dr. GD. Smith (personal communication, 1978) suggested that Haplu-  dolls, which have an isomesic or warmer iso-soil temperature, such as occurs  in the Southern Cook Group should be placed in a proposed great group of  Tropudolls.) The Hapludolls on Aitutaki occur on dominantly hilly land  with partially eroded surfaces and are largely under indigenous forest. All are  classified in the typic subgroup.  On Rarotonga, Hapludolls occur on terraces, fans and flood plains of the  coastal fringe and are developed on fine-textured alluvium and colluvium de-  rived from basalt. They include some of the most intensively used soils  throughout the island group. The older terrace and fan soils are placed in the  typic subgroup, but on younger surfaces which are still subject to flooding  and alluvial deposition the soils may be deep and friable with overthickened  mollic epipedons (cumulic subgroup) or else somewhat stonier, particularly  near streams (fluventic subgroup).    Alfisols    Alfisols have been recognised on four islands; Rarotonga, Atiu, Mauke,  and Aitutaki, and cover some 1324 ha or about 7% of the islands' area. Over  80% of their total area is on the island of Atiu (Table II). The soils are gen-  erally red or reddish brown in colour and have well-expressed argillic hori-  zons. The soils usually occur on older partially-eroded land surfaces of the  central volcanic hills or on older terraces and fans. All the Alfisols have  either high or very high base-saturation (Widdowson and Blakemore, 1975;  Campbell et al., 1978; SB9028-30, 9033} and meet the criteria for the  Tropudalf great group.  On Rarotonga two subgroups of Tropudalfs have been separated: typic  and aquic. These soils are situated on higher fans and older terraces, respec-  tively, with the Aquic Tropudalfs being somewhat waterlogged by perching  of the water table above the argillic horizons.  On the other three islands, where there has been considerably more  weathering, the soils have low CECs and meet the criteria for the oxic sub-  group. Mineralogy is dominated by the presence of kaolinite (G.G.C. Clarid-  ge, personal communication, 1978; Campbell et al., 1978). The soils occur  on hilly and terraced land, as well as extending across part of the makatea  surface on Atiu where, in places, proximity of limestone pinnacles to the  surface has necessitated the inclusion of lithic subgroups within the mapping  unit.    312    lnceptisols    Inceptisols have been recognised on all the islands except Mitiaro. They  cover the largest area {5661 ha) though most of this area is on the steep and  hilly land of the rugged central region of Rarotonga. In general, the soils are  developed on alluvial or colluvial accumulations in valley floors, gullies or  low terraces and fans, though some are developed on weathered or partially  weathered rocks on hilly and steep land surfaces. In general they have only  weak, or at best, moderate profile development.  Two suborders of Inceptisols -- Aquepts and Tropepts -- are recognised.  The Aquepts are represented by a single soil series: an Aeric Tropaquept. It  is developed on fine-textured alluvium and colluvium derived from basalt  on valley floors and small fans near the coast of Aitutaki.  At great-group level the Tropepts are classified into the low-base status  Humitropepts and the higher-base status Eutropepts (Table I). The Humi-  tropepts are developed on the more strongly weathered basaltic parent mate-  rials at generally higher elevations on the islands of Atiu, Rarotonga, and  Mangaia. They are well-drained soils that are rarely used for agriculture be-  cause of their susceptibility to erosion. Vegetation is dominated by second-  growth staghorn fern (Dicranopteris linearis) which has colonised the areas  following burning of the original forest cover.  Of the three series separated, two are classified in the typic subgroup and  one in the oxic subgroup. The soil of the oxic subgroup is developed on deep  colluvial accumulations of strongly preweathered basalt dominated by the  presence of clays with low activity {L.C. Blakemore, personal communica-  tion, 1978).  The Eutropepts in general are developed on dominantly weakly weathered  basaltic parent materials and are recognised as belonging to two subgroups:  typic and fluventic. Softs of the typic subgroup include: (1) a very large area  of steepland softs in the central regions of Rarotonga that are used princi-  pally for conservation and catchment, and (2) deep fine-textured soils cover-  ing the inner part of the makatea on Mauke. The very high base-status of the  Taiki series on Mauke (SB9055) is probably due to solution products from  the makatea limestone. All four series included in the fluventic subgroup  have relatively high organic carbon figures which decrease regularly with  depth, but from the analyses (SB9199, 9031, 9020, 9015) it is assumed the  values for organic carbon will still be in excess of 0.2% within 1.25 m of the  soil surface. The softs are located on Rarotonga, Atiu, and Mangaia (2) and  occur on flood plains or low terraces. In general they are brown or dark  brown, deep fine-textured softs with friable consistence and free-draining  qualities.    En tisols    In the Southern Cook Group, Entisols are represented on each island and  cover a total of 2619 ha (14% of the area). The majority are derived from    313    comminuted coral sand, reef rock and makatea fragments and are dominated  by a carbonatic mineralogy. Others are derived from basaltic alluvium or  mixed basaltic and coral alluvium and are of mixed mineralogy.  Four suborders of Entisols are recognised: Aquents, Psamments, Fluvents,  and Orthents (Table I). The Aquents have organic carbon contents in their  upper profiles (SB9040, 9021, 9032, 9053) that indicate that values will still  be in excess of 0.2% at 1.25 m. They have been classified as Fluvaquents and  are represented by both tropic and lithic tropic subgroups. One series of  Tropic Fluvaquents is recognised on three islands: Mangaia, Atiu, and Mauke.  A soil formed in a fine-textured basaltic alluvium, it has been modified for  the growing of taro in the same way as the Fluvaquentic Hapludolls on Raro-  tonga. A further series (on Mauke) is of similar origin but has not been modi-  fied by man. The Lithic Tropic Fluvaquents are of coralline origin and are  developed on shallow alluvium over cemented beach rock adjacent to the  Muri Lagoon on Rarotonga. They have a halophytic vegetation.  One subgroup of Psamments -- Typic Tropopsamments -- is represented  as a single series, on Rarotonga, Aitutaki and Mauke. The soils are formed  on deep comminuted coral sand, though on Mauke in some places there is  a shallow lithic contact to underlying limestone. The soils are loose and  structureless and strongly alkaline.  One subgroup of Fluvents -- Typic Tropofluvents -- is recognised and is  represented by two series, one on each of Rarotonga and Aitutaki. They are  formed on recent basaltic alluvium, with the series on Aitutaki having addi-  tions of coral sand throughout the profile. The soils are deep and well, to  moderately well, drained but show little profile differentiation.  Orthents are represented by a single subgroup -- Typic Troporthents --  and a single soil series which is recognised on both Atiu and Mitiaro. The  soils are formed on makatea fragments and coral sand on the makatea, and in  general are loose and rubbly. They have a sparse vegetation of coastal scrub  and coconut palms.    SOIL PATTERNS    The basic soil patterns on the islands of the Southern Cook Group are,  apart from irregularly shaped Aitutaki, one of concentricity and are best  discussed according to the three island types outlined in the section on  Geology and Topography. The soil patterns on individual islands are to a  certain extent a reflection of their ages, and degree of weathering and dissec-  tion and are described in terms of soil orders. The areas of soils belonging to  each order are given, by island, in Table II. The soil pattern for each island is  illustrated in Bruce (1983).    The Makatea Islands    On the makatea islands of Mangaia, Atiu, and Mauke (Fig. 2) the central  plateaus (A in Fig. 2), which represent old planated surfaces (Wood and Hay,  1970) are dominated by Ultisols.    I                   Central Voican~ I-~lls  I  I        170 m (554 fl) O~ Ma~, w6~h ~eep s~s  Manga~ makatea. ~        I        72rn (23~ ~ on A~u, Wilh h~y sales                    AI~J &amp; Mauke makate&amp; wffh  hK3h cliffs on inland rna~j~     II     ~  27m (gO It) on fVIauke~ w~h sk)p~g skies               k)w Or no ckffs On inland marg=n  I  ~..-~ - - -  Fig. 2. Generalised cross-section and topographic sketch of makatea type islands (Mangaia, Atiu, Mauke) showing the relationships  between landforms A  1, rock types and soil tmrent materials (!  A), Soil orders occurring on the islands are shown according to the  landforms on which they occur.  Landform                          Soil order (dominant)                                    Rock types/parent material    A. Central Plateau  B. Rolling, hilly, and steep land  marginal to central plateau  C. Rolling land at base of cen-  tral hill (Mangaia and Mauke)  D. Terraces and associated  scarps at base of central  hill (Atiu)  E. Floodplains and swampland  at base of inland Makatea  F. Makatea (inland)    G. Coastal Makatea  H. Lagoon  I. Reef    Mangaia           Atiu               Mauke  Ultisols            Uttisols            Ultisols  Ultisols                            Ultisols  Inceptisols         Inceptisols         Alfisols  Ultisols            --                  Ultisols    InceptisoLs  Entisols  Oxisols  (lithic in part)    Mollisols  (lithic)    Alfisols  Inceptisols    Entisols            Entisols    Alfisols            lnceptisols  (lithic in part)     Mollisols  Mollisols         (lithic)  (lithic)  Entisols            Entisols  (lithic in part)    1. Volcanic rock (basaltic)  2. Old alluvium from volcanic rock  3. Young alluvium from volcanic rock  4. Coral limestone of Makatea  5. Coral sand on Makatea surface    GO    315    On the higher island of Mangaia, the relatively stable steep and hilly slopes  of the dissected central volcanic hill (D) below the plateau are largely Ulti-  sols. Associated with Ultisols are discontinuous occurrences of Inceptisols  developed on erosion products from the adjacent Ultisols. The Inceptisols  occur in concave depressions in generally hilly topography and form an intri-  cate and complex pattern. Low rolling and undulating hills (C) at the base of  the central hill formed from older erosion products are also dominated by  Ultisols. Soils on intervening valley floors and fans (E in part) are Inceptisols.  On Atiu, soils on the moderately steep slopes of gullies dissecting the cen-  tral volcanic hill (D) are largely Inceptisols which indicate a certain amount  of rejuvenation of the regolith as suggested by Campbell et al. (1978). The  lower part of the central volcanic hill has an irregular ring of Alfisols devel-  oped on older terraces, scarps, and terrace risers (I). On lower terraces, In-  ceptisols occur above the flood plains.  The broad low central hill (A and B )on Mauke has had only partial dis-  section. On the few moderately steep gully and valley sides dissecting the  plateau, Alfisols are developed. On the remaining parts of the central  volcanic hill at generally lower levels however, the surfaces are undulating to  rolling and relatively stable, and Ultisols are dominant.  On each of the three makatea islands, Entisols occur in swamps and  stream beds between the base of the central hill and the foot of the inner  margin of the makatea (E).  On the parts of the makatea (F) that have been covered by volcanic  debris, Oxisols have developed on Mangaia, Alfisols on Atiu, and Inceptisols  on Mauke. All have high-base status, due to the presence of the makatea  limestone. Where the limestone is close to the surface, soils have been sepa-  rated into lithic subgroups. This apparent sequential order (Oxisols--Alfi-  sols--Inceptisols) of the volcanic soils on the makateas of the three islands  may reflect the length of time for which the makateas have been covered in  whole or in part by erosional debris from the central hill. The outer parts of  the higher makatea (F) on Atiu and Mauke and the lower benches (G) on  Mangaia have no cover of volcanic debris, and the soils developed on the  coralline limestone and associated debris are lithic subgroups of the Mollisol  order. The lower benches (G) on both Atiu and Mauke have a cover of com-  minuted reef coral over limestone which gives rise to a narrow outer ring of  Entisols, many of which fit lithic subgroups. A large part of the makatea on  Mangaia consists of a broken and jagged karrenfeld of limestone pinnacles  and has no soil. This area, which occupies about 16% of the island, has not  been classified and is designated 'miscellaneous land'.  On Mitiaro {Fig. 3) only two soil orders are recoguised: Mollisols and Enti-  sols. Mollisols are developed on the four low rounded hills or "islands" (A in  Fig. 3) which comprise the remnants of the central volcanic mass. These is-  lands are closely associated with the coral limestone makatea (B) which may  have originally covered the whole island (Wood and Hay, 1970}. In the  swampy alluvial depression (E) between the low hills and the inner edge of    316    ".4~ ',, gm (:~0 "'           ,15 ~', ;,~ ', '411 ~, .fl.,)v'" ~;~a s.vf.I,  ~~ -~    . . ... : ..  Fig. 3. Generalised cross-section and topographic sketch of makatea type island (Mitiaro),  showing relationships between landforms (A--E), rock types and soil parent materials  (1--4). Soil orders occurring on the island are shown according to the landforms on which  they occur.    Landform    Soil order (dominant)   Rock type~parent material    A. "Foodlands" (remnant of  central volcanic mass)  B. Makatea    C. Lagoon    D. Reef    Mollisois  Mollisols (lithic)  Entisols    I. Volcanic rock (basaltic)  2. Coral limestone of Makatea  and reef  3. Coral sand and gravel on  Makatea surface  4. Coralline alluvium of  central swamp    E. Central swamp    Entisols (in part)    the makatea, Entisols occur. On the makatea, the pattern is comparable to  those of Mauke and Atiu. The softs on the main part of the makatea com-  prise a lithic subgroup of Mollisols, whilst the soils on the outer northern and  western margins, where comminuted reef coral has accumulated on the  makatea surface, are Entisols.    Rarotonga    On the larger and younger island of Rarotonga (Fig. 4) four soil orders are  represented. The hilly and steep central regions (A in Fig. 4) that constitute  the major part of the island are subject to regolith movement and erosion  and are dominated by Inceptisols. On the older higher terraces (B) and fans  (C) that discontinuously ring the hilly and steep land there has been suffi-  cient stability to allow the formation of argiUic horizons and Alfisots.  Younger alluvial and colluvial deposits, at generally lower levels, form an  almost complete ring of interconnected fans, terraces and older flood plains,  (B', C, D) including back beach depressions (E), and are dominated by Molli-  sots though there are also small areas of Inceptisots. Entisots, developed on  the coral sand beach ridges (F) and stream flood plains (D'), form a narrow  outermost ring.    317    " //f I .~_:~ ...! ~ " l " ' ' :".'_N  I I1,'. -'~ -."~d.: It, ,~.: .~.  I \t I II i  ( LI ", -~.~.\v, \~" ' ~ ?:v-:-"&gt;.    Fig. 4. Generalised cross section and topographic sketch of Rarotonga from the inland  region to the lagoon and reef, showing the relationships between landforms (A--H), rock  types and parent materials (1--5). Soil orders occurring on the island are shown according  to the landforms on which they occur.    Landform    Soil order (dominant)    Rock type~parent material    A. Steep and hilly land of     Inceptisols              1. Volcanic rocks (basaltic  central volcanic mass                                   and phonolitic)  B. Terraces (older)            Alfisols                 2. Older alluvium/colluvium  B'.Terraces (younger)         Mollisols                   (on terraces and fans)  C. Fans                       Mollisols/Alfisols        3. Flood plain alluvium (older)  D. Flood plains (older)        Mollisols; inceptisols     3. Flood plain alluvium (present)  D' .Flood plains (present)      Inceptisols              4. Coral sand and comminuted  E. Swampy depression         Mollisols                    reef rock  (behind beach ridge)                                 5. Coral limestone (of reef)  F. Beach ridge                Entisols  G. Lagoon  H. Reef    Aitutaki    The irregularly shaped island of Aitutaki has a two-fold pattern (Fig. 5).  At the southern end of the island a sequence of broad flattish old terrace sur-  faces (C in Fig. 5), formed on deeply weathered basaltic material, has a fairly  uniform cover of Ultisols. These merge downslope with a narrow border of  Mollisols on eroded terrace risers and scarps, which in turn grade to Incep-  tisols on discontinuous low terraces, and Entisols on small flood plains (D)  and beach ridges (E). At the more rugged northern end of the island, Molli-  sols predominate on the generally hilly topography (A and B), but on stable  more rounded older surfaces (C), probably equivalent in age to the surfaces  in the south, Alfisols have developed. Inceptisols, and in places Entisols,  occur on narrow alluvial fans and older flood plains marginal to the hilly  land (D) whereas Entisols occur on the beach strand and the contiguous  coralline accumulations on cays inside the reef (E).    318    _ _ ,,,  s..~-~"  I~' c~ ' ,'~'~.,'~';~,:,,::,,i":~_  _~  ~7"~,'" '~)  ~     ,.~   "  ~  ....  L~~  Fig. 5. Generalised cross sections and topographic sketches of Aitutaki across the north-  ern hill country (a) and southern terraced land (b) showing relationships between land-  forms (A--G), rock types and soil parent materials (I--5). Soil orders are shown according  to the landforms on which they occur.    Landform    Soil order (dominant)    A. Hilly and steep land  B. Rolling and hilly land    Mollisols  Mollisols    C. Plateau (terraces)    D. Depressions and flood-  plains  E. Beach ridge  F. Lagoon  G. Reef    Ultisols  (some Alfisols in north)  Inceptisols  entisols  Entisols    Rock type/parent material  1. Volcanic rocks  2. Old alluvium from volcanic  rock  3. Younger alluvium from  volcanic rock and coral sand  4. Coral sand    5. Coral limestone (of reef)    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Thanks are due to Messrs L.C. Blakemore and R.F Thomas, Soil Bureau,  for analytical data and helpful discussion; to the late Dr G.D. Smith, whilst  at Soil Bureau, for assistance and guidance with Soil Taxonomy, and to  Messrs J.D. Cowie and D.M. Leslie, Soil Bureau, for constructive criticism of  the manuscript.    APPENDIX -- REPRESENTATIVE SOIL PROFILE DESCRIPTIONS    OXISOL    Soil name: Oneroa  Profile number: MG V  Classification: Ruptic-Lithic Eutrorthox; clayey, kaolinitic, isohyperthermic  Location: Mangaia, near Temakatea village, 50 m east along road, 100 m north of high  school    319    Physiographic position: raised makatea bench, altitude ca. 50 m  Topography: flat with many coral pinnacles up to 2 m high  Vegetation: garden plot; banana and paw paw with coconut {Cocos nucifera) and Pan-  danus adjacent  Parent material: basaltic alluvium and weathering products from limestone  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB9014 A-D  Sampled by: J.G. Bruce, T.H. Webb  Remarks: buried makatea limestone pinnacles occur within depths of 30--50 cm of sur-  face    Eescrip tion  Apl   0--5 cm    brown to dark brown (7.5YR 4/4} silty clay; very friable; strongly  developed medium and fine nut and nut-like granular structure; many  fine to large roots; distinct smooth boundary  Ap2   5--25 cm   brown to dark brown (7.5YR 4/4) silty clay, very friable; moderately  to strongly developed fine and very fine nut and granular structure;  few roots; distinct smooth boundary  Bwsl 25--33 cm   yellowish red (5YR 4/6) clay; firm; weakly developed medium blocky  structure breaking to fine nut; many medium and fine pores; few  roots; indistinct smooth boundary  Bws2 33--50 cm   yellowish red (5YR 4/6, darker than above) clay; friable; moderately  developed coarse nut structure breaking to medium, fine and very fine  nut; dull ped faces; few fine pores; few medium and fine roots; diffuse  boundary  Bws3 50--80 cm   yellowish red (5YR 4/8) clay; friable; weakly developed medium and  fine blocky structure, some fine granular; rough ped faces; few  medium and fine roots; distinct boundary  C    80 + cm     yellowish red (5YR 4/6) clay; firm; weakly developed fine nut struc-  ture  ULTISOL  Soil name: Ivirua  Profile number: MG VII  Classification: Orthoxic Palehumult; clayey, kaolinitic, isohyperthermic  Location: Mangaia. 40 m WNW of northern tip of Lake Tepeuru Ngau  Physiographic position: central region of broad interfluve, altitude 40 m  Topography: roiling land, southeast-facing 8slope (14%)  Vegetation: scrub consisting mainly of Au (Hibiscus tiliaeceus), guava (Psidium guajava),  staghorn fern (Dicranopteris linearis) and grasses  Parent material: strongly weathered alluvium from basalt  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB9016 A-D  Sampled by: J.G. Bruce, T.H. Webb    Description  Aul   0--25 cm    brown to dark brown (7.5YR 4/4) and dark yellowish brown (10YR  4/6) silty clay; very friable; strongly developed medium and fine nut  structure breaking to very fine nut and granular; many fine to coarse  roots; indistinct wavy boundary    320    Au2  25--35 cm    brown to dark brown (7.5YR 4/4) and strong brown (7.5YR 5/6)  silty clay; very friable; moderately developed medium to very fine nt, t  and granular structure; many medium casts, very porous; distinc~  boundary    Btl  35--45 cm    yellowish red (5YR 4/6) silty clay; friable; moderately developed  coarse blocky structure breaking to fine and very fine nut and  granular; ped faces with thin coatings; roots concentrated near ped  faces; no pores; diffuse boundary    Bt2  45---65 cm    yellowish red (5YR 4/8) clay; sticky; firm; moderately to strongly  developed blocky structure, breaking to weakly developed medium  and fine nut; major ped faces with shiny thick coatings (5YR 4/4-6);  few fine and medium roots, mainly confined to ped faces; indistinct  boundary    BC   65--80 cm    yellowish red (5YR 4/6) clay; sticky; friable; tending massive; vertical  fissures and cracks at 10 cm intervals; roots concentrated in fissures  and cracks.    MOLLISOL    Soil name: Pouara  Profile number: R39  Classification: Typic Hapludoll; fine, mixed, isohyperthermic  Location: Rarotonga. Arorangi district, 40 m S of H. Napa's house  Physiographic position: central region of terrace, altitude 15 m  Topography: gently sloping surface, southwest-facing 2( 3.5% slope)  Vegetation: citrus orchard (30 years) with ground cover of water grass and Mimosa  pudica  Parent material: alluvium derived from basic volcanic rock  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB9042 A-C  Sampled by: D.M. Leslie, L.C. Blakemore, J.P. Widdowson    Description    Ap    0--30 cm    dark brown (7.5YR 3/2) clay loam; firm; non-sticky and non-plastic;  weak to moderately developed coarse blocky tending nut structure  breaking to fine and medium peds; few non-weathered medium  stones; few medium roots; indistinct wavy boundary    Bw    30--55 cm    dark brown (7.5YR 4/4) clay; friable; slightly sticky and mdilihtly palst  plastic; weak to moderately developed medium nut structure with  crumb; many thin faint coatings (7.5YR 4/4); no stones or roots;  smooth indistinct boundary    BC    55---68+ cm    dark brown (7.5YR 4/4) clay; friable; sticky and plastic; weak and  moderately developed fine and medium blocky structure; few thin,  faint coatings (7.5YR 4/4); no stones; no roots    ALFISOL    Soil name: Tetoa  Profile number: At58    321    Classification: Oxic Tropudalf; very fine, kaolinitic, isohyperthermic.  Location: Atiu, west side of track to Mapumai swamp ca. 800 m from Post Office  Physiographic position: near centre of terrace remnant; altitude 27 m  Topography: flat to very gently undulating  Vegetation: mangoes (Mangifera indica), coconut palms (Cocos nucifera) and miscella-  neous weeds.  Parent material: strongly weathered basalt alluvium  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB9028 A-D  Sampled by: I.B. Campbell    Description    A     0--20 cm    dark reddish brown (2.5YR 3/4) clay; friable; moderately developed  fine nut structure; slightly sticky and slightly plastic; few fine roots;  indistinct wavy boundary    Bw   20--38 cm    red (2.5YR 4/6) clay; friable; weakly developed fine nut and granular  structure; slightly sticky and slightly plastic; few fine roots; diffuse  boundary    Btl  38--86 cm    Bt2  86--134 cm    reddish brown (2.5YR 4/4) and red (10R 4/6) clay; friable; moderate-  ly developed fine and medium blocky structure; sticky and plastic;  abundant medium distinct dark red (2.5YR 3/6) and red (10R 4/6)  coatings; diffuse boundary  dark red (2.5YR 3/6) clay; friable to firm; moderately developed  coarse blocky structure; sticky and plastic; few fine distinct red  (2.5YR 4/8) mottles; many medium distinct red (2.5YR 3/6) coat-  ings; diffuse boundary    BC  134--204+ cmred (10R 4/6) clay; firm; very sticky and plastic; many fine and  medium distinct strong brown (7.5YR 5/6) mottles    INCEPTISOL    Soil name: Kurakei  Profile number: At60  Classification: Fluventic Eutropept; very fine, kaolinitic, isohyperthermic  Location: Atiu, adjacent to track to Mapumai swamp, 1200 m NE of Post Office  Physiographic position: Central region of terrace, altitude 15 m  Topography: flat to gently sloping, east-facing slope 2(3.5%)  Vegetation: citrus orchard  Parent material: weathered basaltic alluvium  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB9031 A-D.  Sampled by: I.B. Campbell, A.D. Wilson  Remarks: limestone fragments may have been added to soil; sampled as follows: 9031A  0--10 cm; 9031B 25--40 cm; 9031C 70--85 cm; 9031D 95--115 cm    Description    A    0--13 cm    dark brown (10YR 3/3) clay; firm to friable; sticky and plastic;  moderately developed fine and medium nut structure; few fine and  medium roots; distinct wavy boundary    322    Bw   13--57 cm    dark yellowish brown (10YR 4/4) and yellowish brown (10YR 5/4)  clay; firm; sticky and plastic; weakly developed coarse nut structure;  few small moderately and strongly weathered gravel and stones; in-  distinct wavy boundary    BC   57--94 cm    yellowish brown (10YR 5/4 and 5/6) clay; firm; sticky and plastic;  weakly developed coarse and blocky structure; many small moderate-  ly and strongly weathered gravel and stones; diffuse wavy boundary    C1   94--182 cm yellowish brown (10YR 5/4) clay; firm; sticky and plastic;massive;  many small moderately weathered gravels; diffuse irregular boundary    C2   on    varied clay loam to sandy clay loam; very firm; slightly sticky and  slightly plastic; massive; abundant small and medium moderately and  strongly weathered gravels and stones    ENTISOL    Soil name: Muri  Profile number: Tk6  Classification: Typic Tropopsamment; carbonatic, iaohyperthermic  Location: Rarotonga. Totokoitu Research Station, 10 m SW of managers house, adjacent  to main road and stream  Physiographic position: storm beach ridge, altitude 3 m  Topography: near fiat surface with slight undulations  Vegetation: coconut (Cocos nucifera) and lantana (Lantana camara) with ground cover of  miscellaneous weeds and grasses  Parent material: fine comminuted reef coral (Aroa Sands of Wood and Hay, 1970)  Soil Bureau lab. number: SB8912 A-D  Sampled by: M.L. Leamy  Remarks: large coral fragments may occur in the profile    Description    Au I   0--I 2 cm    very dark greyish brown (10YR 3/2) sandy loam; friable; moderate to  strongly developed fine and medium nut structure; many roots; rare  volcanic stones; many coarse coral sand fragments; indistinct boun-  dary    Au2 12--25cm    very dark greyish brown (10YR 3/2) sandy loam; friable (tending  firm); moderately developed medium nut with some crumb structure;  few roots; indistinct boundary    AC  25--40 cm    dark brown (10YR 4/3) and very pale brown (10YR 7/4) coarse sand;  loose; very weakly developed m~iium nut structure; few roots;  distinct boundary    C    40---90+ cm very pale brown (10YR 8/3) very coarse sand; loose; structureless;  rare roots    REFERENCES  Bruce, J.G., 1983. Soil taxonomic unit descriptions for Southern Cook Group. N.Z. Soil  Bur. Taxonomic Unit Descriptions, 3.    323    Campbell, I.B., 1982. Soils of Atiu, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep., 53.  Campbell, I.B., Claridge, G.G.C. and Blakemore, L.C., 1978. Pedological study of soils  from basaltic parent material on the island of Atiu, Cook Islands. N.Z.J. Sci., 21:  229--248.  Leamy, M.L., Leslie, D.M., Blakemore, L.C. and Balbernie, B.C., 1975: Soils of Totokoitu  Research Station, Rarotonga, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep., 27.  Leslie, D.M., 1980. Soils of Rarotonga, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep. 49.  Milne, J.D.G., 1983. Soils of Aitutaki, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep., 51. In press.  Mourn, J., 1965. Falling drop used for grain-size analysis of fine grained materials. Sedi-  mentology, 5: 343--347.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy, a basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric. (Soil Conserv. Serv.), Agriculture Hand-  book, 436:754 pp.  Webb, T.H., 1981. Soils of Mangaia, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Sur. Rep., 50.  Wells, N. and Smidt, R.E. (Compilers) 1978. D. Methods for mineral and elemental  analysis. N.Z. Soil Bur. Sci. Rep., 10D.  Widdowson, J.P. and Blakemore, L.C., 1975. Fertility of Cook Islands soils. Interim Rep.,  Soil Bur. DSIR.  Wilde, R.H., 1981. Soils of Mitiaro, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep., 54.  Wilson, A.D., 1982. Soils of Mauke, Cook Islands. N.Z. Soil Surv. Rep., 52.  Wood, B.L. and Hay, R.F., 1970. Geology of the Cook Islands. N.Z. Geol. Surv. Bull., 82:  103 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractThe soil patterns of the six larger islands of the Southern Cook Group in the South Pacific are described. Classification is according to Soil Taxonomy, and six soil orders are recognised: Oxisols, Ultisols, Mollisols, Alfisols, Inceptisols and Entisols, which are further subdivided into 12 suborders, 15 great groups, and 25 subgroups. Classification to series level is outlined in tabular form. The soil pattern on individual islands is basically one of concentricity. The older, more weathered soils (Oxisols and Ultisols) occur on remnant surfaces and grade with either decreasing altitude or age of land surface to Alfisols, Mollisols, Inceptisols, and Entisols, respectively. Many of the soils associated with the coralline makateas have shallow contacts to the underlying limestone and have been separated in lithic subgroups. 