 Geoderma, 35 (1985) 197--208                                                   197  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    POTASSIUM RELEASE ON DRYING OF SOIL SAMPLES FROM A  VARIETY   OF   WEATHERING   REGIMES   AND   CLAY   MINERALOGY  IN CHINA    JIA XIAN LUO and MARION L. JACKSON  Institute of Soil Science, Academia Sinica, Nanjing (P.R.C.)  University of Wisconsin, Madison, W153 706 (U.S.A.)  (Received August 21, 1984; accepted after revision March 26, 1985)    ABSTRACT    Luo, J.X. and Jackson, M.L., 1985. Potassium release on drying of soil samples from  a variety of weathering regimes and clay mineralogy in China. Geoderma, 35: 197--208.    Thirty two soil samples from China were analyzed for exchangeable K before and  after drying. Most soil samples were higher in exchangeable K after air-drying and oven-  drying (60) than when wet. Soil clay minerals, especially clay-size mica, affected K  released in air-dry and oven-dry samples. According to composition of clay minerals  of air-dried samples, five classes were recognized. Soil samples with high mica and mont-  morillonite have the highest exchangeable K. Samples that contained higher kaolinite  than mica had lower exchangeable K. Samples with higher kaolinite than quartz and  mica had still lower exchangeable K. Samples of sandy soils contained very low exchange-  able K. When quartz was the main mineral, the samples that had kaolinite and gibbsite  as the main clay minerals had very low exchangeable K. The degree of weathering (weath-  ering mean) bore an inverse relationship to the amount of K released on drying in air  or at 60. Udults and Udalfs (Red Earths) of southeastern China, because of their  high K release on being dried, are inferred to have received fine mica from the Western  Desert dust rainout, reported to Liu et al. (1981).    INTRODUCTION    The need for fertilization of softs in eastern China to produce adequate  crop yields has recently been documented (in English, Liu et al., 1983;  Xi and Zhou, 1983). Those results contrast sharply with the conclusion  of King (1911) that thorough return of organic matter to soils, including  animal and human excrement, would provide "permanent agriculture in  China". The purpose of this paper is to report on the test levels of potassium  in samples of 32 Chinese soils, differing in mineralogy and release of ex-  changeable K on drying the moist soft samples. This is illustrative for one  element of a much broader problem of soil depletion in China of several  elements which has become so severe as to cause human mortality docu-  mented elsewhere (Li et al., 1980; Jackson et al., 1985).    0016-7061/85/$03.30   1985 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    198    RELATED RESEARCH ON SOIL POTASSIUM RELEASE    Some unfertilized samples of Udalfs of Wisconsin, when dried at room  temperature, released more exchangeable K than duplicate samples kept  moist for two months (Att0e, 1947). After addition of K to these samples,  K fixation occurred but this K was reversibly released from non-exchange-  able to exchangeable form by cropping in the greenhouse. After removal  of readily available K by electrodialysis, the sample of a kaolinitic Udult  showed no further K release, whereas a montmorillonitic Aqualf sample  continued to release K {Pearson, 1952). Potassium release from soil samples  is related to the mineralogy of soils, particularly clay mica content (Rouse  and Bertramson, 1950; Milford and Jackson, 1966).  Fluctuations in the exchangeable K of air-dried soil samples were found  to occur in response to changes in water vapor pressure and drying (Luebs  et al., 1956). In an experiment with Parsons silt loam (a Udalf of south-  eastern Kansas) both moist A-horizon and moist B-horizon samples had  relatively low contents of exchangeable K (Scott and Smith, 1957). Drying  these soil samples to 1.5% moisture content approximately doubled the  exchangeable K content in both the A- and B-horizon samples. Uptake  of K by plants was always greater from dried samples of soils from central  USA than from moist samples (Scott et al., 1957). The B-horizon samples  generally released more K on drying than samples of A-horizons (Hanway  and Scott, 1957). There was no relationship between the amount of K  released and that portion of the released K that reverted to the non-ex-  changeable form when the samples were subsequently remoistened and  stored. The wide differences in the contents of exchangeable K in oven-  dried (ll0) samples from North Central USA before (r = 0.90; p &lt;0.01)  and after (r = 0.73; p &lt;0.01) cropping were closely correlated with dif-  ferences in the specific surface of clay-sized mica present (Milford and  Jackson, 1966). Nine samples of soils of China gave a significantly positive  correlation (r = 0.93; p &lt;0.01) between contents of fine mica and release  of exchangeable K (Luo and Jiang, 1981).    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Samples of A-horizons were collected from 32 locations of the soil sub-  orders Udox, Udalf, Udult, Aquult, Aqualf, Aquod, and UstoU softs of  China (Table I). These softs were derived from loess and other Quaternary  deposits, granite, limestone, purple sandstone, shallow-sea deposits, and  river alluvial deposits. Source locations of these samples of soft and the  parent materials are given in Table I and Fig. 1.  Exchangeable potassium was extracted by neutral 1 N NH4OAc solution.  The K in solution was determined by a Perkin-Elmer flame photometer  (Jackson, 1971). The fractions were analyzed for mineralogy by X-ray  diffraction (Jackson, 1979) with a Phillips X-ray diffractometer after satu-  ration with magnesium and solvation with glycerol solution.    199    TABLE I  Sample sites, parent materials and soil identification.    Soil                         Parent material          Soil taxonomy    No.  Locality    Local                  U.S.A.  Suborder    1   Jiangxi Jinxian  2   Fujian Aunan  3   Fujian Zhangpu  4   Guangdong Haikang  5   Zhejiang Kaihua  6   Hunan Henguang  7   Sichuan Chougquing  8   Sichuan Mishan  9   Jiangsu Yixing  10   Jilin  11   Jiangsu Jiangning  12   Guizhou pinba  13   Guangdong Fanru  14   Guangdong Fanru  15   Hunan Huayong  16   Hunan Huayong  17   Hunan Huayong  18   Hunan Taoyuan  19   Jiangxi Yichun  20   Jiangxi Fangcheng  21   Jiangxi Fangcheng  22   Zhejiang Kaihua  23   Henan Fengqiu  24   Hunan Hanshou  25   Jiangsu Xuzhou  26   Jiangsu Siyang  27   Jiangsu Siyang  28   Jiangsu Yixing  29   Fujian Longxi  30   Jiangsu Xuzhou  31   Jiangsu Tougshan  32   Fugiang Longxi    Quaternary coUuvium   Red earth             Udult  Granite                Red earth             Udult  Basalt                  Red earth             Udult  Shallow-sea deposit      Red earth              Udox  Quaternary colluvium   Red earth              Udult  Purple sandstone        Purple                 Udalf  Purple sandstone        Purple                 Udalf  Shale                   Yellow                Udalf  Alluvial                White                Aquod  Loess                   Black                  Ustoll  Loess                  Yellow brown earth   Udalf  Limestone              Paddy                 Aqualf  Alluvial                 Paddy                 Aquult  Alluvial                 Paddy                 Aquult  Quaternary colluvium   Paddy                 Aqualf  Quaternary coUuvium   Paddy                Aquult  Quaternary coUuvium   Paddy                 Aquent  Quaternary colluvium   Paddy                Aquult  Limestone              Paddy                 Aquult  Quaternary alluvium    Paddy                Aquult  Quaternary alluvium    Paddy                Aquult  Quaternary colluvium   Paddy                Udult  Alluvial                Alluvial               Udalf  Alluvial                Alluvial               Udult  Alluvial                Alluvial               Udalf  Alluvial                 Alluvial                Udalf  Alluvial                 Alluvial                Fluvent  Alluvial                 Alluvial                Aquult  Alluvial                Alluvial               Aquult  Alluvial                Alluvial               Fluvent  Alluvial                Alluvial               Fluvent  Alluvial                 Alluvial                Aquent    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Exchangeable K in relation to mineralogy of undried soil samples    Samples of Udalfs 23, 25 and 26, which are alluvial soils derived from  Yellow River deposits, have the highest exchangeable K on a moist basis  (Fig. 2). This river arises in the little-leached, Western (Gobi} Desert and  erodes its way through loess blown from that desert. Also high in available  K, the sample of Ustoll 10 that occurs in northeast China is weakly weath-    200    ~  O ~OC)~    110 \  110   Fig. 1. Localities in China of the soil samples analyzed.    ered and contains much mica; crops do not give a significant response  to applications of K-fertilizer to this soil. Samples of soils derived from  clayey sediments (Udalfs 6 and 7) and shale (Udalf 8) have higher levels  of exchangeable K than other softs in nearby locations. These Purple soils  have about 40% clay, with mica and montmorillonite the dominant clays  (Luo and Jiang, 1981). Samples of Udults (1, 2, 3 and 5) are intermediate  in exchangeable K.    K (mg/1oog)    Soi[ No.    Fig. 2. Exchangeable K in the soil samples, wet from the field, after being air-dried,  and after being dried at 60. For convenience, rag/100 g (above) divided by 39 equals  mequiv./1O0 g (Tables II and IV).    201    In general, the samples of paddy softs are high in kaolinite and provide  intermediate exchangeable K levels, e.g., Aqualfs and Aquults 12, 13, 14,  16, 18, 19 and 21 as well as Aquent 17, Udalf 11, and Udult 22. Soil samples  high in quartz or kaolinite have medium to low exchangeable K (Aquod 9,  Fluvents 27 and 31, Aquent 32, and Aquults 28 and 29). The samples of  soils of south China (Udox 4, and Aquults 13 and 14, Guangdong region),  which have been strongly weathered, provide low exchangeable K. Crops  give significant responses to additions of K-fertilizer (Xie, 1981).    Effect of mineralogy on exchangeable K of air-dry soil samples    According to the amounts of exchangeable K in the air-dry soil samples,  five classes were recognized which had a close relation to mineralogy (Table  II).  (I) The samples with mica and montmorillonite as the main clay minerals  had the highest exchangeable K in the air-dry condition.  (II) When the soil samples had kaolinite as the main clay mineral, although  mica was second in abundance, the contents of exchangeable K were mark-  edly lower.  (III) Soil samples with kaolinite as the main clay mineral and high contents  of quartz and other non-potassiumbearing minerals contained lesser amounts  of exchangeable K and the soils show K-deficiencies with crops.  (IV) Samples of sandy soils that had been severely leached and with quartz  dominant in the mineral composition, even though some mica remained,  had still lower exchangeable K. Release of K from the resistant mica does  not provide enough K for satisfactory crop production.  (V) Soil samples with kaolinite, quartz, gibbsite and lesser amounts of  mica, showed the lowest exchangeable K in the air-dry condition (Table  II).    TABLE II    Relationships between mineralogy and exchangeable K in the air-dry soil samples  Class    Soil samples*~           Clay                Exchangeable K  mineralogy.2       (mequiv. 100 g-l)    I      6,7,10,23,25,26       Mi, Mt, X, Qr      0.37--0.53  II       2,8,15,20              Kl, Mi, Qr          0.25-0.29  III      1,3,5,11,12,16,         K1, Qr, Mi, X       0.15--0.21  17,18,21,22,30,32  IV      13,14,24,27,29         Qr, KI, Mi          0.11--0.13  V      4,9,19,28,31           K1, Qr, Gb, Mi      0.04--0.09    *1Fig. 1. and Table I.  *2Mineralogical content (based on X-ray diffraction peak areas) ranges from higher  to lower in the order given for each class;  Mifmica; Mt=montmorillonite ; X=interstratified; Kl=kaolinite; Qrffiquartz; Gbfgibbsite.    202    Classes (III) and (IV) are unexpectedly higher in exchangeable K than  the mineralogy and location with respect to climate (Fig. 1) might have  indicated. Fluvial and eolian deposition of fine micas over well-weathered  landscapes is a possibility because of proximity to rivers in some cases.  The well-documented distribution of loess in this region (Liu et al., 1981)  could be accompanied by an aerosolic fine micaceous dust at great dis-  tances from loessial sources over long periods of time (Jackson et al., 1971;  Jackson, 1981).    Effect of drying on K-release    The ratios and increased percentages of exchangeable K from air-dry  to wet, oven~lry (60) to wet and oven-dry to air-dry samples are given  in Table III. Of the six soil samples in Class I, which contained the highest  exchangeable K when wet (Nos. 6,7,10,23,25,26; Fig. 2 and Table II),  Nos. 6 and 26 gave the greatest increases in percentage of exchangeable K  from wet to air-dry conditions. Samples Nos. 10 and 23 gave the greatest  percentage releases from air-dry to oven-dry (60) conditions, followed  by Nos. 6 and 26.  Many samples (Fig. 2) that were fairly low in exchangeable K when  wet (Nos. 3,9,11,12,13,14,16,18,19,21,24) showed 30% or more increase  in exchangeable K after air-drying or oven-drying. Six soil samples containing  low exchangeable K (Nos. 3,9,11,12,13,14; Fig. 2) gave very high increases  in percentage of released K from wet to air-dry (&gt;37%) and oven-dry  conditions (&gt;102.6%) (Table III). Samples of a paddy soil derived from  limestone (No. 12) and a sandy Aquod (No. 9) have the highest percentage  increases (169%) in exchangeable K on 60-drying of the wet specimens  (Table III); these two soils, however, have low initial exchangeable K-levels  when wet (Fig. 2). All of the soil samples with high percentage increases  of K on drying had some micas among their constituent clay minerals  (Table II).  Some samples contained as much or more exchangeable K in the wet  condition than when air-dry (Nos. 4,5,29,31; Fig. 2). These samples con-  tained strongly weathered clay (No. 4), contained little clay mica (Nos.  5,29) or had high quartz contents in the clay (No. 31). Low CEC and low  exchangeable K accompanied little fixation or release of K on drying,  indicating a high degree of weathering (Jackson et al., 1952). Four soil  samples had a little higher exchangeable K when wet than when oven-dry  (Nos. 2,17,30,32; negative values, Table III). These samples all contained  intermediate levels of initially exchangeable K (Fig. 2).    Relationships of weathering means to K-release on drying    The weathering mean (Hseung and Jackson, 1952) of four soil samples  from China (Table IV) showed that Udalf 11 (Yellow Brown Earth) near    TABLE III  Ratios of exchangeable K for variously dried soil samples and  exchangeable K on drying.    203    percentage increases of    Soil     Soil      Air-dry soil/  Increase  At 60  Increase  At 60     Increase  sample            wet soil       (%)      wet soil  (%)       air-dry soil  (%)    1     Udult   1.15         15.3   1.24     24.8   1.08         8.0  2     Udult   1.09          8.5    0.97     -2.6   0.90       -10.2  3     Udult    1.38         37.2   2.04    103.6    1.48        48.4  4     Udox    0.80        -20.3    0.88     -12.0    1.11        10.5  5     Udult   0.71        -28.9   0.75    -24.9   1.05         5.5  6     Udalf    1.31         30.6   1.47     46.9    1.13        12.5  7     Udalf    1.16         16.2   1.30     29.0   1.11        11.0  8     Udalf    1.10           9.7    1.11      11.0    1.01          1.3  9      Aquod   1.58           58.1    2.69     169.4    1.70         70.4  10     Ustoll   1.19          19.1    1.66      66.8    1.40        40.1  11      Udalf     1.42           42.3    2.04      103.6    1.43          43.1  12      Aqualf   2.29         129.5    2.69     169.4    1.17         17.4  13      Aquult   1.56           55.8    2.15     115.3    1.38         38.3  14      Aquult   1.50           50.0    2.03      102.6    1.36          35.5  15     Aqualf   1.26         25.9   1.36     36.1    1.08         8.1  16     Aquult   1.37          36.5    1.52      51.9    1.11        11.0  17      Aquent   1.16           15.8    0.99       -0.7    0.86        -14.3  18     Aquult   1.50          50.4    1.61      60.8    1.07          7.0  19     Aquult   1.31          30.9    1.43      43.1    1.09         9.3  20     Aquult  1.41         40.6   1.46     46.0   1.04         3.9  21      Aquult   1.35           35.2    1.47      46.7    1.08          8.7  22      Udult    1.29           29.4    1.37       36.7    1.06          5.7  23      Udalf    1.10           10.0    1.34      33.6    1.21         21.3  24     Udult    1.32          31.9    1.32      31.9    1.00          0  25     Udalf    1.03           2.9    1.08       8.0    1.05          5.0  26     Udalf    1.31          31.3    1.44      43.6    1.09          9.3  27      Fluvent  1.05            5.1    1.20      19.9    1.14         14.0  28      Aquult   1.28           27.5    1.86      85.6    1.46         45.5  29     Aquult   0.92         -7.6    1.04       3.7    1.12        12.2  30      Fluvent  1.00            0      0.96      -4.0    0.96         -3.8  31      Fluvent  0.98           -2.2    1.08        8.0    1.10         10.4  32      Aquent   1.04            4.2    0.95        4.9    0.91         -8.7    Nanjing had the most mica and the lowest weathering mean (6.7); this  soil had the highest percentage release of exchangeable K on air-drying.  The Udalf 6 (Purple soil; weathering mean, 7.3) had a high mica content  and the second highest release of exchangeable K on air-drying. The amounts  of exchangeable K were higher than those of Udalf 11 (Yellow Brown  Earth) because the clay content was higher. The weathering mean indicates  that Udalf 6 in south China had a higher degree of weathering than Udalf  11.  The Udalf 5 (Paddy soft) and Udalf 1 (Red Earth), with distinctly higher    204    weathering means (8.2 and 9.5, respectively), contained low amounts of  mica and gave lower percentages of increases in K-release on air-drying  the samples. From the results shown in Table IV, fine mica appears to  be important for K-release on air-drying soil samples. The soils with higher  weathering means contain lower contents of mica and provide less K avail-  able to crops.    TABLE IV  Mineral composition and release of exchangeable K on air-drying of some soil samples  from China    Mineral.1           Soil, locality and weathering means* 2    Udalf 11        Udalf 6        Udult 5        Udult 1  (Yellow Brown  (Purple soil)    (Paddy soil)    (Red Earth)  Earth)  Jiangsu          Hunan         Hunan         Jiangxi  Jiangning        Hengyang      Huayong       Jinxian    Ab (5)          4.4          7.5         2.3         0.3  Mc (5.5)          10.3           3.0          3.0          0.6  Qr (6)          27.4         14.8        24.6         4.1  Mi (7)          35.3         31.0        16.1         8.0  X (8)           2.8          3.5         6.7         7.1  Vr (8.5)           2.0           2.5          6.8          4.3  Mt (9)           2.7         11.8         0.2         1.9  All (10)          --          --        10.5        10.6  K1 (10)          4.6         14.9        23.3        49.9  Gb (11)          --          2.6         --         0.9  Hm (12)        10.5          8.1         5.0        10.7  An (13)          0.8          0.8         1.7         1.7    Weathering mean     6.7              7.3             8.2             9.5    Exchangeable K  (mequiv. 100 g-L)  Wet soil  Air-dry soil    Release of  exchangeable K  on soil drying  (%)    0.15             0.36           0.23           0.16  0.21                            0.46                         0.29                         0.19    40               28             26             19    *ZAb=albite; Mc=microcline; Qr=quartz; Miffimica; X=interstratified; Vr=vermiculite,  Mt=montmorillonite;  Allffiallophane; Klfkaolinite; Gb=gibbsite; Hmffihematite; An=  anatase; numbers in parenthesis are weathering index numbers.  *2Weathering mean is the sum of weighted index numbers times the mineral percent-  ages (Hseung and Jackson, 1952; Jackson, 1979, p. 561).    205    Probable effects of dustfall on soil mineralogy and exchangeable potassium    Most of the samples contained various contents of mica and quartz.  As shown by Liu et al. (1981), some of these minerals were added as dust  rain-washout onto the soils. Dust has been carried by winds to various  locations globally by rainwash and contributed various contents of quartz  and micas to marine sediments (Griffin and Goldberg, 1962) and soils  (Jackson et al., 1971). Harmattan dust of northern Africa is reported in  Nigeria (McTainsh, 1984). Quartz oxygen isotonic ratios in fine sediments of  southern Africa (Le Roux et al., 1980) have identified a wide distribution of  dusts in the Southern Hemisphere (Jackson, 1981). Similar evidence for the  Northern Hemisphere indicates that atmospheric generation of detrital  eolian dust in dry areas of Asia have given rise to dust that was carried  by the Westerlies to contribute to pelagic sediments of the North Pacific  Ocean (Clayton et al., 1972) and highland areas of Hawaii (Jackson et  al., 1971). Earlier, the quartz (Sherman et al., 1964) and mica (Juang and  Uehara, 1968) in Hawaii were considered to be authigenic.  Dust brought down in rain on the softs of southeastern China (Liu et  al., 1981) apparently has provided fine detrital micas and quartz. The  major dustfaU in southeastern China in 1980 provides a model for Western  Desert origin of the great loess deposits in north China and a drift of fine  dust southeastward (an effect of Siberian winds) into south China (Yang  et al., 1981). Because of dustfall, some soil samples (even in the same area  but with different geomorphology and texture) have various levels of ex-  changeable K (e.g., Udalf 25, Fluvents 30 vs. 31, Aquod 9, Udalf 11 and  Aquult 28). The Udults 1, 2, 3 and 5 (Red Earths) occur in the path of  enrichment by rainwash dust (Figs. 1 and 2). Nonetheless, in south China,  most soil clays have been strongly weathered to interstratified layer silicates,  kaolinite, and gibbsite. As is consistent with our findings, the soils have  relatively low exchangeable K, and application of K-fertilizer produces  increased yields of crops (Xie, 1981).    Mechanism for potassium release on drying    The release of K on drying has been considered (Scott et al., 1957) to  reflect the attainment of an equilibrium distribution among the various  types of sites of K in variously weathered crystals plus an exchange of K  by other ions that might take place during drying. Aluminium replacement  of non-exchangeable K was inferred to be responsible for soil K-release  on drying (Carter, 1961). The contraction of the hydrated interlayer space  to different degrees on drying was considered (Schroeder, 1955) to in-  fluence K-release. Surface tension forces that changed at the weathered  edges of micaceous minerals during drying might cause K-release (Kunishi,  1963). From Table II, it is evident that the amounts of exchangeable K  released on drying are related to the content of clay-sized micas. Soil    206    drying may be accompanied by proton dehydration (from hydronium,  OH+, Jackson, 1960), including OH+ resulting from hydrated cation hy-  drolysis. The protons could readily penetrate through mica crystal sur-  faces at weathering edges or wedges (Jackson, 1963), thus releasing K  into exchangeable form. This conforms to the gradual release of non-ex-  changeable K by roots under intensive cropping (Attoe, 1947). Proton ex-  change for mica-K (hydrolysis) has been established as the mechanism  of mica-K-release to exchangeable form on drying, because ApK+ equals  ApH+  (r=0.99; p&lt;0.001; slope of regression equation, 0.985; Jackson  and Luo, 1985).    CONCLUSIONS    Drying mica-containing samples of soils of China in air or at 60 re-  sulted in release of K from non-exchangeable to exchangeable forms (AT NH4  OAc). This phenomenon, previously known for midwestern U.S.A. soils,  appears to be widespread in China. Desert dust from western China appears  to have added fine mica to soils in southeastern China.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    This research was supported in part by the College of Agricultural and  Life Sciences, University of Wisconsin, Madison, project 1123; in part  by the National Science Foundation, Grant EAR-8405422 to M.L.J.; and  in part through an International Consortium for Interinstitutional Coop-  eration in the Advancement of Learning (ICICAL). Sincere appreciation  is extended to Ms. C. Jackson for her care in editing and typing the manu-  script.    REFERENCES    Attoe, O.J., 1947. Potassium fixation and release in soils occurring under moist and  drying conditions. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 11: 145--149.  Carter, D.L., 1961. Increase in Exchangeable Potassium upon Drying of Soils and Clays.  Ph. D. Thesis, Oregon State College, Corvallis.  Clayton, R.N., Rex, R.W., Syers, J.K. and Jackson, M.L., 1972. Oxygen isotope abun-  dance in quartz from Pacific pelagic sediments. J. Geophys. Res., 77: 3907--3915.  Griffin, J.J. and Goldberg, E.D., 1962. Clay mineral distribution in the Pacific Ocean.  In: M.N. Hill (Editor) The Sea, 3. Intexseience, New York, pp. 728--741.  Hanway, J.J. and Scott, A.D., 1957. Soft potassium--moisture relations, II. Profile dis-  tribution of exchangeable K in Iowa soils as influenced by drying and rewetting.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 21: 501--504.  Hseung, Y. and Jackson, M.L., 1952. Mineral composition of clay fraction, III. Of some  main~oil groups of China. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 16: 294--297.  Jackson, M.L., 1960. Structural role of hydronium in layer silicates during soil genesis.  7th Int. Congr. Soil Sci. (Madison), 2: 445--455.  Jackson, M.L., 1963. Interlayering of expansible layer silicates in soils by chemical  weathering. Clays Clay Miner., 11: 29---46.    207    Jackson, M.L., 1971. Soil Chemical Analysis. Published by the author, Madison, WI,  498 pp.  Jackson, M.L., 1979. Soil Chemical Analysis--Advanced Course (2nd Edn.). Published  by the author, Madison, WI, 895 pp.  Jackson, M.L., 1981. Oxygen isotopic ratios in quartz as an indicator of provenance  of dust. In: Troy L. P~w~ (Editor) Desert Dust Origin Characteristics, and Effect  on Man. Geol. Soc. Am. Spec. Pap., 186: 27--36.  Jackson, M.L. and Luo, J.X., 1985. Potassium release mechanism on drying soils: non-  exchangeable to exchangeable potassium by protonation of micas. Soil Sci. In press.  Jackson, M.L., Hseung, Y., Corey, R.B., Evans, E.J. and Van den Heuvel, R.C., 1952.  Weathering sequence of clay-size minerals in soils and sediments; II. Chemical weath-  ering of layer silicates. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 16: 3--6.  Jackson, M.L., Levelt, T.W.M., Syers, J.K., Rex, R.W., Clayton, R.N., Sherman, G.D.  and Uehara, G., 1971. Geomorphological relationships of tropospherically derived  quartz in the soils of the Hawaiian Islands. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 515--525.  Jackson, M.L., Li, C.S. and Martin, D.F., 1985. Land variables: effect on heart and  stomach-colorectal cancer death rates in Florida counties. Fla. Sci. In press.  Juang, T.C. and Uehara, G., 1968. Mica genesis in Hawaiian soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 32: 31--45.  King, F.H., 1911. Farmers of Forty Centuries or Permanent Agriculture in China, Korea  and Japan. Rodale Press, Emmases, PA, 441 pp.  Kunishi, H2VI., 1963. Factors Affecting the Release of Soil Potassium to Exchangeable  Form on Drying. Ph. D. Thesis, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI.  Le Roux, J., Clayton, R.N. and Jackson, M.L., 1980. Oxygen isotopic ratios in fine  quartz silt from sediments and soils of southern Africa. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta,  44: 533--538.  Li, M., Li, P. and Li, B., 1980. Recent progress in research on esol~hageal cancer in  China. Adv. Cancer Res., 33: 173--249.  Liu, Tung Sheng, Gu Xiong Fei, An Zhi Sheng and Fan Yong Xiang, 1981. The dust  fall in Beijing, China on April 18, 1980. In: Troy L. P~w~ (Editor), Desert Dust  Origin, Characteristics, and Effect on Man. Geol. Soc. Am. Spec. Pap., 186: 149--  158.  Liu, Zheng, Zhu, Qi-Qing and Tang, Li-Hua, 1983. Microelements in the main soils  of China. Soil Sci., 135: 40--46.  Luebs, R.E., Stanford, G. and Scott, A.D., 1956. Relation of available potassium to  soil moisture. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 20: 45--50.  Luo, Jia Xian and Jiang, MeiYin, 1981. Studies on potassium-bearing minerals in soils,  II. The relationship between the contents of potassium in some soils of Hunan prov-  ince. Acta Pedol. Sinica, 18 (i): 87--96 (in Chinese).  McTainsh, G., 1984. The nature and origin of the aeolian mantles of central northern  Nigeria. Geoderma, 33: 13--37.  Milford, M.H. and Jackson, M.L., 1966. Exchangeable potassium as affected by mica  specific surface in some soils of North Central United States. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 30: 735--739.  Pearson, R.W., 1952. Potassium-supplying power of eight Alabama soils. Soil Sci., 74:  301--309.  Rouse, R.D. and Bertramson, B.R., 1950. K-availability in several Indiana soils: its  nature and method of evaluation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 14: 113--123.  Schroeder, P.,  1955. Kaliumfestigung und Kaliumnachschliffenung yon L~ssb6den.  Landwirtsch. Forsch., 5: 1--7;Chem. Abstr., 49: 12757.  Scott, A.D., Hanway, J.J. and Stickney, E.M., 1957. Soil potassium--moisture relations,  I. Potassium release observed on drying Iowa soils with added salts or HC1. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 21: 498--501.  Scott, T.W. and Smith, F.W., 1957. Effect of drying upon availability or potassium  in Parsons silt loam surface soil and subsoil. Agron. J., 49: 377--381.    208    Sherman, G.D., Matsusaka, Y., Ikawa, H. and Uehara, G., 1964. The role of the amor-  phous fraction in the properties of tropical soils. Agrochimica, 8: 146--163.  Xi, Zhen-Bang and Zhou, De-Xing, 1983. Soil productivity and fertilizer effect under  a triple cropping system. Soil Sci., 135: 59--64.  Xie, Zhan Chan, 1981. The present progress of studying on soil potassium. Prog. Soil  Sci., 1:13--15 (in Chinese).  Yang, Shao-Jin, Qian, Qin-Jen, Zhou, Mihg-Yu, Qu, Shao-Hou, Song, Xi-Ming, and  Li, Yu-Yeng, 1981. Some properties of the aerosols during the passage of a dust  storm over Beijing, China, April 17--20, 1980. In: Troy L. PSw~ (Editor) Desert  Dust Origin, Characteristics, and Effect on Man. Geol. Soc. Am. Spec. Pap., 186:  159--167.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractThirty two soil samples from China were analyzed for exchangeable K before and after drying. Most soil samples were higher in exchangeable K after air-drying and ovendrying (60°C) than when wet. Soil clay minerals, especially clay-size mica, affected K released in air-dry and oven-dry samples. According to composition of clay minerals of air-dried samples, five classes were recognized. Soil samples with high mica and montmorillonite have the highest exchangeable K. Samples that contained higher kaolinite than mica had lower exchangeable K. Samples with higher kaolinite than quartz and mica had still lower exchangeable K. Samples of sandy soils contained very low exchangeable K. When quartz was the main mineral, the samples that had kaolinite and gibbsite as the main clay minerals had very low exchangeable K. The degree of weathering (weathering mean) bore an inverse relationship to the amount of K released on drying in air or at 60°C. Udults and Udalfs (Red Earths) of southeastern China, because of their high K release on being dried, are inferred to have received fine mica from the Western Desert dust rainout, reported to Liu et al. (1981). 