 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 285--302                                                  285  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in the Netherlands    THE DEVELOPMENT OF SOIL POROSITY IN EXPERIMENTAL SANDY  SOILS   WITH   CLAY  ADMIXTURES  AS  EXAMINED  BY  QUANTIMET  720 FROM BESI AND BY OTHER TECHNIQUES    J CHRETIEN and E.B.A. BISDOM  I.N.R.A., Station de Science du Sol, 1 7 Rue Sully, 21034 Dijon (France)  Netherlands Sod Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Chr~tien, J. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1983. The development of soil porosity in experimental  sandy soils with clay admixtures as examined by Quantimet 720 from BESI and by  other techniques. Geoderma, 30' 285--302.    For this study thin sections have been prepared of natural and artificial sands mixed  with 20% and 40% clay. These and other samples had already been examined using  soil physical and soil mineralogical methods for loose samples. Initial thin section studies,  with the help of the light microscope alone, have been enlarged upon in this investigation  using backscattered electron scanning images and an image analyzer (Quantimet 720). This  allowed quantitative information to be obtained on the development of different types  of soil porosity patterns using various clay admixtures. Information was also obtained  on the influence the form of mineral grains had on the shape of pores in the mixtures  of sand and clay. It was also possible to obtain quantitative information on the amount  of clays and larger mineral grains in the thin sections. Much of the present data cannot  be obtained automatically but must be manually controlled by using the image editor  of the Quantimet. This type of work, however, may provide basic data which can sub-  sequently be used to help explain various processes which occur in soils.    INTRODUCTION    The influence of the form of sand grains on porosity characteristics of  sandy soils was studied under experimental conditions and in loose samples  by Chr&amp;ien (1971) using soil physical and mineralogical methods. Work  was done in the 100/am to 160 #m sieve-fraction. The roundness and spher-  mity of individual grains were examined with the stereo-microscope and  the results compared with porosity data from physical methods. These  data, however, gave virtually no information on the packing of sand grains  and the framework of sandy soils. The same negative result was obtained  for the form and dimension of individual voids in natural and artificial  sandy soils.  As a consequence, Chr&amp;ien (1979) decided to mix sands with certain    0016--7061/83/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Scmnce Publishers B.V.    286    quantities of clay, vlz. from 10 to 70% clay, and to prepare thin sections  of these mixtures. Light microscopic observations of these thin sections  revealed considerable differences m porosity patterns of the sands which  were mixed with clay. If the sands were mixed with smaller amounts of clay,  sand grmns could exercise considerable influence on the types of pores  which developed. Some observational insight was obtmned m the distribu-  tion and arrangement of soil components, but no confirmatlve exact data  could be obtained on the relation between shapes of soil components and  porosity characteristics.  In the present study, backscattered electron scanning images (BESD  and an image analyzer were used to characterize soil components and soil  porosity in sandy material mixed with 20% and 40% clay. The soil compo-  nents consisted of artificial sand-sized materials, vlz. marbles, and natural  sand-sized mineral grains mixed with different percentages of the same clay_    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Eight sandy materials were used in the experiments by Chr~tien (1979)  and each of these were mixed with 10%, 20%, 30%, 40%, 50%, 60% and  70% clay. Two of the eight were artificial, vlz. glass marbles with rounded  forms and angular artificially crushed quartz. The glass marbles are called  "Marbles" in this paper and the second sample "Bordeaux". All sands  were of the stove-fraction 100 um to 160 #m. The six remaining sands  were: Fontainebleau (marine and dune sands of the Tertiary Fontainebleau  Formation), SaSne (fluviatile sands from the recent terraces of the SaSne),  Serre (sands from the Trias in the forest of Serre), Morvan (sands from  weathered granite of the Morvan Massive), Vivarals (sands from migmatite  of the "Moyen-Vlvarals" of France) and Maures (sands from weathered  micaschist of the Maures Massive). These sand and clay mixtures are indi-  cated in Fig. 1 (Chr~tien, 1979).  Fontainebleau was comprised of rounded quartz. Sa5ne consisted of  slightly rounded quartz and feldspar. Serre had predominantly shghtly  angular quartz and feldspar. Morvan consisted of angular sands with quartz,  feldspar and 10% mica. Vlvarals had slightly rounded sands with quartz,  feldspar and 20% mica. Maures was comprised of 70% lamellar material  (mainly mica), and quartz and feldspar. Only light minerals which floated  in a hquid with a specific gravity of 2.68, viz. quartz, K-feldspar and Na-  feldspar, were studmd. Heavy minerals were not examined because they  were represented in insignificant quantitms. The latter fraction also included  iron-oxides and Ca-feldspar.  In the initial experiments (Chr~tmn, 1971), sands without clay admLxtures  were tested for roundness and sphermity with a stereo-microscope. Porosity  and permeability were determined with methods that are commonly used  m soil physics. In the experiments of 1979, Chr~tien made thin sections  of the sands which were now mixed with various quantities of clay. The    % Porosity  70 "~    287    60.    50-    Bdles (= Marbles)   Bordeaux   Fontainebleau  (I  Sa6ne   Serre    Morvan  A  Vlvarals  Maures    40-    30-    \\                           \\ \  \\  \\  \    2O  0     lb    2'0    3'0    4'o    5'0    6'0      %Clay  Fig. I. Porosities of sands with increasing quantitms of added clay as determined by so]l  physical methods.    clay consisted of a mixture of montmorillonite, ilhte and kaolinite with  a little quartz according to X-ray diffraction analysis. Porosities were again  studied with physical methods and individual pores observed with the light  microscope. Some of the pore patterns were drawn from micrographs (these  are m this study made with the light microscope) of thin sections. Loose  materials were studied with the scanning electron microscope (SEM) and  images (these are m this study made with SEM) made of various mixtures  of sand and clay. In sltu characterisation of pores remained problematic,    288    however, and it was decided that addltmnal techmques were necessary.  Such techniques were possible using an image analyzer (Quantimet 720),  and a scanning electron mmroscope (Philips SEM 505) eqmpped with four  backscattered electron detectors. The Quantlmet can be used to study pores  with diameters larger than 30 um on mmrographs of thin sectmns (Jongerius,  1974, 1975; Jongerius et al., 1972 a, b; Murphy et al., 1977). If back-  scattered electron scanning smages (BESI) are made of thin sections (Blsdom  and Thiel, 1981), pores smaller than 30 ~m can also be measured by Quan-  timet (Jongenus and Bisdom, 1981).    RESULTS    The work by Chr~tien (1971, 1979) on the relation between the form  of soft components and porosity was started with only sandy material.  This allowed certain results to be obtained whmh are discussed briefly below  before the results of the experiments with sand and clay admixtures. This  gives a basis for the results of the present study m whmh BESI axe analyzed  with the Quantimet 720 and used for porosity and mineral quantification.    Results of experiments on loose sands wzthout clay admtxtures    A number of conclusions were reached by Chr~tien (1971) working  with loose artificial and natural sands. The following characteristics were  found for the sands. The density of the sands was often close to that of  quartz, VlZ. 2.65. Maures (sands high m mica) had a density of 2.78. Plaquet-  tes (an artificial sand consisting of platy and angular glass; not used m  later experiments) had a density of 2.48.  The number of grmns per gram was highest in the Maures sands with  750,000 and lowest for Marbles with 200,000. The specific surface m  cm2/g was smallest for Marbles with 126.4 and highest m Maures with  550.9. The weight of the sands was highest for Marbles and smallest in  Maures. The weight differed in loosely packed sands (1.61 g/cm3 for Marbles  and 0.82 g/cm3 for Maures) and compacted sands (1.74 g/cm3 for Marbles  and 1.25 g/cm3 for Maures). The values for the other sands varied between  these extremes.  The porosity of the sands differed significantly. Loosely packed Marbles  had a poromty of 38.92% and compacted Marbles became 33.71%. Marbles  had the lowest porosity values of the sands. The highest porosities were  found in the highly mmaceous Maures sands, viz. 70.35% when loosely  packed and 55.11% when compacted.  Roundness and sphericity were determined for loose grains with the  stereo-microscope and compared with the porosity figures of loosely packed  sands. Marbles had the highest roundness and sphermity values and the  lowest porosity, whereas Maures had a low roundness and the smallest    289    sphericity and porosity values. It could be demonstrated that the shapes  of the sand grains formed a basic criterium which strongly influenced all  other characteristics of the sands; including porosity. It was also found,  however, that very little could be said about the relation between the form  of the sand grains and the form of the pores or the manner of packing.  Only in the case of Marbles could a possible relation between physically  measured porosity values and packing be established. This was impossible  for natural situations such as occur in sandy soils.    Results of experiments on loose sands with clay admixtures, of the study  of thin sections and of SEM-observations of loose sands wzth clay admixtures    Loose sands with clay admixtures  During subsequent studies (Chr6tien, 1979) clay was added to two arti-  ficial and six natural sands, to observe what happened with the forms of  pores going from sands to clay with sand. Thin sections were prepared  to gave some insight into the form of pores by light microscopy. Soil physics  methods were used to obtain figures on total porosity. Unhardened pmces  of soil material were studied with SEM.  Porosities were found to decrease in the sands until 50% clay had been  added (Fig. 1). The strongest decrease in porosity occurred for most sands  during the addition of 10% clay and of 30% to 50% clay. Maures formed  an exception with the largest porosity decrease below 30% clay admixture.  The curves in Fig. 1 demonstrate that Maures {mica plates} always have  a higher porosity than Marbles, independent of the volume of added clay.  The porosities of the rounded and slightly rounded sands of Fontmnebleau  and S~one are slightly higher than for Marbles and axe very similar. The more  angular sands of Bordeaux, Serre, Morvan and Vlvarais have again higher  porosltms and form a group of curves above Fontainebleau and SaSne.  Only a selection, viz. Marbles, SaSne, Morvan and Maures, are used as  examples to discuss the results of these experiments. The decrease in po-  rosity of the sands was largely due to the infilling of pores when 10% clay  was added. The rounded sand grains of Marbles and SaSne were embedded  in clay and contacts between the grains became less if 10% to 30% clay  was added. This was not the case with angular sand grmns (Morvan) and  mma-sands (Maures) in which the contacts between sand grains were main-  tained. As a consequence, with the addition of clay, mainly infilling of  the pores took place m Morvan and Maures. The porosity in Maures de-  creased sigmflcantly due to a considerable decrease m specific surface.  The addition of 30% to 50% clay gave predominantly a dislocation of  sand grmns. Above 50% clay admixture the contacts between individual  sand grains were virtually lost and the grains no longer had a function in  the support of a skeleton. Porosities of individual sands remained virtual-  ly the same and came close to one another (Fig. 1).    290    Sands with clay admtxtures in thin sections  Light microscopic observations of thin sections gave reformation on  the form, size and number of pores, the arrangement of sands and the  distribution of clays. The investigation was done on sands with 20%, 40%  and 70% clay admixtures.  The arrangement of sands, clay and pores m sands with a 20% clay ad-  mixture gave different types of packing. In Marbles, clay was present as  rings around the marbles and formed bridges between them. In the other  sands gram cutans predominated.  The porosity m the thin sections was studmd by making mmrographs  of the sands with clay admixtures and drawing the pores m them (Fig. 2).  In sands with 20% clay the pores of marbles were usually rounded and  had regular forms. Similar, but somewhat more complicated forms were  present in Sabne; a sand with slightly rounded to rounded minerals. Maures,  a highly micaceous sand, showed various complex and elongated forms  of pores. The pores were often angular with their greatest length parallel  to the mica platelets. Pores of Fontainebleau with rounded and slightly  rounded grains were similar to those of SaSne. A variety of frequently com-  phcated forms of pores was found in Serre and Vivarais whmh contained  angular grains.  The size of pores m sands with 20% clay was measured by taking their  largest diameter. The diameters were given m four size classes: smaller  than 50 tzm, 50--100 /am, 100--200 pm and 200--500 ~m. The studied  sands of the analysed stove-fraction, 100--160 pm, had predominantly  pores between 50 tam and 200 /am. The number of pores vaned between  29 and 37 in each micrograph (Fig. 2). An estimation of the total porosity  was obtained by cutting areas occupied by pores free from the paper, de-  termining their weight, and comparing the weight with that of the whole  micrograph. Information on different size classes was also gathered in this  manner. Marbles and Fontainebleau had the lowest porosity, Maures and  Serre a somewhat higher porosity. Form alone, however, was not a de-  termining factor for porosity characteristics because Sabne and Vlvarals  did not demonstrate a relation between the form of sand grains and porosity.  In the clays of Marbles, with an additmn of 40% clay, mlcrocracks oc-  curred. These microcracks were regarded by Fies (1978) and Chr~tlen  (1979) as newly developed. This new type of porosity also demonstrated  that  the influence of sand grams and their forms on the porosity had de-  creased slgmficantly The elongated pores were more or less oriented. SaSne  and Maures showed a considerable number of larger pores  Marbles, SaSne and Maures were also examined in thin sections with  70% clay. Only microcracks were visible m all samples and the influence  of sand grains on porosity had virtually ceased A part of the mlcrocracks,  in sands with 70% and 40% clay, could have been formed artificially during  sample preparation.  The results of the measurements of porosity in thin sections indicated    291    A    B    D    F  '      ~                                   pm    Fig. 2. Drawings of pores from light microscopic micrographs (plane polarized hght)  of sands mixed with 20% clay. Marbles (A, B), .SaSne (C, D) and Maures (E, F)    that the used method was not accurate (Chr~tien, 1979). Drawing of pores  from micrographs was rather arbitrary and positioning of the pores on  the photos before they were drawn was sometimes difficult. Also, the  number of pores selected in this manner is often too small to allow a sta-  tistical evaluation.    292    SEM-observations of loose sands w~th clay admixtures  SEM observations of loose sands with 30% and 70% clay need to be  r, mntioned briefly at the end of this section. Sands with 30% clay had sim-  ilar forms to those with 20% clay, viz. predominantly rounded pores in  Marbles, mainly angular ones m Fontainebleau, and very irregular pores  in Maures. Microcracks started to develop. Sands with 70% clay showed  a continuous coating of the grains with clay in all samples. Micropores  were still discernable in Maures but Marbles and Fontainebleau showed  continuous infillings between the sand grains.    BESI-Quantimet studies of sands with clay admixtures in thin sectmns    Measurement of porosities and minerals  Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) were made from thin  sections of Marbles, SaSne and Maures with 20% and 40% clay admixtures  and analysed with the Quantimet 720 (Bisdom and Thml, 1981; Jongerius  and Bisdom, 1981). Two images were analysed of each sand with 20%  clay. In sands with 40% clay, two images were analysed of Marbles, three  of SaSne and seven of Maures. Of these, two images were selected from each  category giving three figures with four images each, vlz. Marbles (Fig. 3),  SaSne (Fig. 4) and Maures (Fig. 5).  Porosity data could be obtained directly and automatically from BESI  in most cases, but manual work with the image editor of the Quantimet  was also necessary. The present study concentrated on the overall porosity  characterisation of each image. A number of pores, however, continued  beyond the boundary of individual images. This continuation of pores  raises problems in the measurement of individual pores. Consequently  more BESI micrographs should be made along linear traverses on a thin  section to overcome this problem. This was not done in the present study,  and consequently no individual pores were measured. This will be the  subject of a forthcoming publication.  In addition to the measurement of the porosity attention was also prod  to the measurement of coarser minerals and clays. The results are given  in Table I. The average clay percentages measured in BESI were close to  the 20% and 40% clay which was put into the sands. However, data of  some images indicate that considerable deviation of these figures may occur  locally in the thin sections.  A special study was done on the relation between the forms of pores  and the forms of individual minerals. Drawings were made from BESI on  transparent paper for this study. If a mineral bordered a pore, a hne was  drawn along the length of the contact. In some cases a thin clay cutan oc-  curred on mineral grains and was also in contact with a pore. If this grain  cutan was very thin and ran parallel to the surface of a mineral this sur-  face was also considered as a contact zone.    U  .0  0    293    294    ~'~ %1    "6  Q  d  J  O    ~0    295    Fig. 5. BESI of Maures with 20% clay (a, b) and 40% clay (c--f) admixtures.  Porosity characteristics  Changes in porosity with increasing clay content. The porosity percent-  ages of Marbles, SaSne and Maures sands with 20% and 40% clay admixture  are given in Table I. Marbles and SaSne with 20% clay demonstrate vir-  tuaUy the same porosity percentages, whereas the difference is somewhat  larger for Maures. Marbles with 40% clay show virtually the same results  of measurements, while larger differences are found in the measurements  of SaSne and Maures. If average porosity percentages are taken, the changes  are the following for sands with 20% and 40% clay admixtures, respec-  tively 33.94 to 24.06 for Marbles, 28.04 to 25.69 for SaSne, and 27.40  to 19.82 for Maures. These results indicate that the porosity of SaSne de-  creased only slightly when 40% clay was added to the sand, whereas the  loss in porosity was much larger for Marbles and Maures. The area occupied  by pores in a thin section can also he given in/~m2. Fig. 6 illustrates the  trends which were discussed above.    296  TABLE I  Quantimet measurements of porosity, mineral percentages and clay percentages m BESI  of Marbles, SaSne and Maures with 20% and 40% clay admixtures*~    Sample    Clay added     Porosity m          Coarser minerals      Clay m  to sands        thin section         in thin section        thm section  (%)        (%)           (%)            (%)    Marbles     20             35.46               45.69                18.85  Marbles     20             32 42               47.99                19.59    Marbles     40             24 41               38.99                36.60  Marbles     40             23 70               33 28                43.02    Sa6ne       20             28.62               52.26                19.12  SaSne       20             27 45               53.96                18.59    SaSne       40             24 66               36 97                38.37  SaSne       40             28.94               35.92                35 14  SaSne       40             23.48               34 12                42.40    Maures      20             29.38               49.58                21 04  Maures      20             25.41               52.80                21.79    Maures      40             17 79               52.80                29.41  Maures      40             24.52               35 08                40.40  Maures      40             22.78               31.79                45 43  Maures      40             22 08               29.87                48.05  Maures      40             15.00               39.99                45.01  Maures      40             17.53               48 49                33.98  Maures      40             19.10               30.47                50 43    ,i BESI magnification 100    Pore patterns. Apart from the measurements indicated in Table I, attention  was paid to area (A), perimeter (Pe), drawn perimeter (DPe) and horizontal  projection (HPr) of the pores. These allowed some insight to be obtained  into porosity characteristics of Marbles, SaSne and Maures.  Pore patterns or void patterns were classified for clayey soils by Jongenus  (1974) and Ismafl (1975) at a smaller magnification. The same classification  graph has been used in this study for sands mixed with 20% and 40% clay  (Fig. 7). Void pattern classes of sandy soils (Ismail, 1975) have different  class limits which are insufficiently determined at present. The net result  is that data plotted m the classification graph of Jongerius (1974) correlate  with different void patterns than those indicated on the graph.  Marbles with 20% clay are present in class 3.3 and shift to classes 2.2  and 3.2 when 40% clay is added. Smooth-wailed vughs, interconnected  vughs, channels and planes are present in Marbles with 20% clay. Special    297    A  #m2/10000  30-    25-    20-    15-       Marbles  m    Sa6ne      Maures    10  0               2'0               4=0% Clay  Fig. 6. Average area occupied by pores in BESI from three sands with 20% and 40%  clay admixtures.  P= HPr/625  2E    24    2C    C  0     10    20    30    40     Marbles 20 % clay   Marbles 40 % clay  II  Sabne 20 % clay  Sabne 40 %clay   Maures 20 % clay  Maures 40 % clay  50% A    Fig. 7. Classification of pore patterns, for sands mixed with 20% and 40% clay, using  the classification graph introduced in 1974 for clayey soils.    298    types of voids are vemcles which were formed between clay and marbles.  Such vesmles can be connected w~th other types of pores The porosity  pattern of Marbles with 40% clay is strikingly different and consists pre-  dominantly of channels and planes. Vughs shll occur, but become more  elongated, and change into channels. Vesmles can still be discerned  SaSne with 20% clay (class 3.3) has predominantly vughs and intercon-  nected vughs. Many vughs are smooth-walled  Planes, due to shrinkage  of clay, are numerous and have a smaller diameter than planes of the Marble  samples. These shrinkage-planes are also found in SaSne with 40% clay  (classes 2.3 and 3.2) and may mterconnect vughs. The conformation of  the walls of vughs and interconnected vughs has become somewhat more  irregular with an increase of angular forms.  Maures with 20% clay (class 4.2) seem to have a considerable number  of simple packmg voids caused by the random packing of single mmeral  grains (minas, quartz and feldspars). Closer observatmn indicates, however,  that clay coatings are also present in most pores. Vughs and interconnected  vughs are the most predominant. Maures with 40% clay (classes 1.3, 3.1,  3.2, 4.1 and 4.2) demonstrate very large differences in pore patterns. Elon-  gated voids {channels, joint planes, planes, interconnected vughs) are dom-  inant. Some micrographs have onented pores, others virtually lack larger  pores.    Relation between the form of pores and the form of indwldual minerals.  Perimeters of all pores in Marbles, Saone and Maures with 20% and 40% clay  admixtures {Figs. 3--5) were measured on BESI by Quantimet. The pro-  cedure followed has been explained in the section "measurements of po-  rosities and minerals" and the results of the measurements are given in  Fig. 8.  The curves for the penmeter and drawn perimeter of Marbles and SaSne  show similar trends in Fig. 8, whereas this is not the case for Maures. The  average drawn perimeter, when taken as a percentage of the average perim-  eter of all pores, is highest in clays with 20% clay, viz. 15.4% for Marbles,  21.9% for SaSne and 24.4% for Maures. These f, gures become significantly  lower for sands with a 40% clay admixture: 7.1% for Marbles, 16.4% for  S~Sne and 4.3% for Maures. These data indicate that the addition of 20%  clay has the greatest effect on Marbles, 1.e. marbles occupy the smallest  percentage of the walls of voids. If 40% clay is added, the role of Marbles  is taken over by Maures with 4.3%. This means that even larger percentages  of platy micas m the sample have ceased to influence the conformation of  the walls of pores.    CONCLUSIONS    A series of expenments has been conducted over several years to obtain  information on the relation between the shape of mineral grains, pore    299    Pe  ~m/lO00  60-    50-    40-    30-    20-    10-    EE- - -- --!               A----,A    '::::-&gt;--I    0  0      2'0         4'0% Clay     I~erlmeter  o---- -0 drawn perimeter    Fig. 8  Influence of predominantly sandy mineral grains on the conformation of the  walls of pores.    patterns and the form of pores. The first experiments dealt with loose  sands without clays using natural and artificial materials and conventional  methods of soil physics and soil mineralogy. Significant new information  was obtained (Chr~tien, 1971). Secondly, clay was added in various quan-  tities to the sands and thin sections were made. Light microscopy and  the already mentioned methods were agmn not capable of giving a real  answer to the same questions. Basically, poromty patterns and forms axe  too intrmate to study in many cases unless image analyzer systems are avail-  able which can be used in combination with high quality micrographs made  from thin sections. Micrographs made with the light microscope did not  give sufficiently accurate information on the porosity and backscattered  electron scanning images (BESI) therefore must be made with the scanning  electron microscope.  In the present study BESI were measured with the Quantimet to mves-  tigate thin sections of sands with 20% and 40% clay admixtures (Figs. 3--5)  and to obtain further information on the same questions. Magnifications  of 100 were used to study the form of pores, pore patterns and mineral  grains as a totality. The results of this investigation gave a number of new  aspects. One of these was that porosity percentages measured with BESI-  Quantimet methods (Table I and Fig. 6) are different from earlier results  done with soil physical methods (Fig. 1). In Fig. 1 Maures has the highest  porosity at 20% and 40% clay admixtures, followed by Sa5ne and Marbles.  'Fable I and Fig. 6 indicate, however, that the average porosities are smallest  for Maures. Marbles with the lowest porosity (Fig. 1) has the highest porosi-    300    ty at 20% clay admixture according to BESI-Quantimet measurement  results. SaSne has a middle position at 20% clay and a somewhat higher  porosity than Marbles at 40% clay admixture. Only the porosity values for  Marbles with 20% and 40% clay come close to the physically determined  ones in Fig. 1. SaSne and Maures have much smaller porosity values accord-  lng to Quantimet studms from BESI. Such differences in the results of phys-  really determined porosity values and those given by BESI-Quantimet could  possibly be explained by pointing out that the thin section method repre-  sents a two-dimensional area and not a three-dimensional volume. Another  argument is that many thm sections should be measured, and a large number  of fields in each thin section, to allow statistical evaluation of the variability  in the distribution of various types of porosity in the studied samples. Also,  at the present magmficatlon of only 100 no detailed mformation is ob-  tained on very fine pores, whereas this can be done using physical methods.  However, the present BESI-Quantimet analysis of porosities m thin sections  clearly indmates that a discrepancy exists between the results of this method  and soil physical ones. Much more work is necessary to reach final conclu-  sions on this subject but indications are that the BESI-Quantimet method  may be of considerable help to soil physms as was demonstrated for heavy  clay soils by Bouma et al. (1977, 1979) using hght microscopm micrographs  instead of BESI, smaller magmhcations than the present ones, the Quantimet  720 and sml physical methods.  The relation between mineral grains and the form of pores was found  by marking the surfaces of the voids occupied by mineral grains and meas-  using their length with the Quantlmet. These measured perimeter data were  subsequently compared with the total perimeters obtained from all pores.  Due to a magmfmation of only 100 of BESI, done to obtain compar-  able results with earher expenments, the relation between the surface of  minerals and the form of very small pores could not be established with cer-  tainty. However, general trends were obtained for small and larger pores  and these are of interest. The trends for perimeter and drawn perimeter  (Fig. 8) were similar for Marbles and SaSne. Some decrease in perimeter,  influenced by the form of mineral grams, occurred going from a 20% to  a 40% clay admixture. Maures had a completely different upward trend  for the perimeter and a steeper downward slope for the dashed line of the  drawn perimeter. The increase in perimeter occurred because long elon-  gated pores and small pores with varmus shapes replaced vughs and inter-  connected vughs. The drawn penmeter of Maures, at 40% clay admixture,  was situated between SaSne and Marbles m Fig. 8. The presence of platy  mica grains in Maures was therefore of no special significance any longer,  whereas the micas still played a role at 20% clay admixture.  Pore pattern changes can be observed in mlcrographs but the Quantimet  measurements are necessary to bring some type of order m the often in-  tricate patterns. The classification chart (Fig. 7) was used and demonstrated  a number of shifts in patterns going from sands with 20% to sands with    301    40% clay admixture. Marbles showed a variety of pore-types at 20% clay  admixture, whereas predominantly channels and planes were left when  40% clay had been added. SaSne showed only small differences for 20%  and 40% clay admixtures, although angular forms in parts of the pore walls  were discernable in sands with 40% clay. Maures had a significant number  of simple packing voids at 20% clay admixture and showed a large variety  of pore patterns at 40% clay admixture {Fig. 5).  The present results can be considered as preliminary because all sands  with different percentages of clay added have not yet been studied with  BESI-Quantimet. Also, a larger area of the thin section has to be studied  along hnear traverses to gain representative results. Larger magnifications  of BESI will be necessary to obtain more detailed mformation on individual  pore characteristics, especially of the smaller pores. Information can also  be obtained on forms of larger mineral grains and on the place of clay accu-  mulations. This will allow some insight into the development of fabric  and structure of soils, especially if combined with detmled work on and  experiments with soil porosity.    REFERENCES    Bisdom, E.B.A. and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-EDXRA.  In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submiscroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Work-  shop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil  Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Doc-  umentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A., Boersma, O., Jager, A and Schoonderbeek, D., 1977. The  function of different types of macropores during saturated flow through four swelling  soil horizons. Soil. Sci. Soc Am. J., 41 (5): 945--950  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1979. Calculatlon of saturated hy-  draulic conductivity of some pedal clay soils using micromorphometric data. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43(2)" 261--264.  Chr~tten, J., 1971. Essai de caract~risation des sables en tant que squelette mineral du  sol. Ann Agron., 22(6): 615--654.  Chr&amp;ien, J., 1979. Etude exp~rimentale de la porosit~ de m~langes sables-argile Aspects  micromorphologiques. Sci. Sol, 4' 333--353.  Fies, J.C., 1978. Poromt~ du sol: dtude de son origine texturale. Thesis, Strasbourg,  France.  Ismail, S.N.A., 1975  Micromorphometric soil-porosity characterization by means of  electro-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720). Neth Soil Surv. Inst, Wageningen,  Soft Surv Pap., 9,104 pp.  Jongerius, A., 1974. Recent developments in soil mtcromorphology. In. G.K. Rutherford  (Editor), Soil Microscopy, Proceedings of the 4th International Working-Meeting on  Soil Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ontario,  Canada, pp. 67--83.  Jongerius, A., 1975. Micromorphometric sod analysis by means of Quantimet 720.  In: Fortschritte der quantltativen Bildanalyse; Vortrage des IMANCO-Symposmms,  pp. 161--185    302    Jongerius, A. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981 Porosity measurements using the Quantimet  720 on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In' E.B.A.  Bisdom (Editor), Submlcroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of  the International Working-Group on Submlcroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials  (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documen-  tation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 207--216  Jongerius, A, Schoonderbeek, D., Jager, A. and Kowalinski, S, 1972a. Electro-optical  soil poroslty investigation by means of Quantimet-B equipment Geoderrna, 7(3/4)  177--198.  Jongerius, A., Schoonderbeek, D. and Jager A, 1972b. Soil porosity characterization  by means of electro-optical image analysis. In: La Fertilidad Flsica de las Suelos. Rap-  ports del Semenarlo Internacional, Sevilla, pp. 107--123.  Murphy, C.P., Bullock, P. and Turner, R.H., 1977. The measurement and character-  isation of voids in soil thin sections by image analysis, Part I. Princlples and tech-  niques. J. Soil ScI., 28(3). 498--508.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractFor this study thin sections have been prepared of natural and artificial sands mixed with 20% and 40% clay. These and other samples had already been examined using soil physical and soil mineralogical methods for loose samples. Initial thin section studies, with the help of the light microscope alone, have been enlarged upon in this investigation using backscattered electron scanning images and an image analyzer (Quantimet 720). This allowed quantitative information to be obtained on the development of different types of soil porosity patterns using various clay admixtures. Information was also obtained on the influence the form of mineral grains had on the shape of pores in the mixtures of sand and clay. It was also possible to obtain quantitative information on the amount of clays and larger mineral grains in the thin sections. Much of the present data cannot be obtained automatically but must be manually controlled by using the image editor of the Quantimet. This type of work, however, may provide basic data which can subsequently be used to help explain various processes which occur in soils. 