 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 149--160                                                  149  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    LIGHTMICROSCOPE AND SUBMICROSCOPE OBSERVATIONS OF  SALTS IN MARINE ALLUVIUM (INDIA)    M.J. KOOISTRA  Stichting voor Bodemkartering (Stiboka), Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Kooistra, M.J., 1983. Lightmicroscope and submicroscope observations of salts in marine  alluvium (India). Geoderma, 30' 149--160.    In samples from a salt-affected Indian soil series, a curly stem-like salt efflorescence  occurred. Unimpregnated soil material and thin sections from these samples, prepared in  two different ways, were studied with lightmicroscopy and submicroscopy. The samples  came from the Dandi soil series, classified as Halaquepts (Soil Survey Staff U.S.D.A.,  1975), which occur extensively on marine alluvium in the semi-arid parts of Gujarat (India).  In the unimpregnated samples, several habits of halite (massive crusts, cubical forms, thin  threads and curly stem-like forms) were determined with SEM--EDXRA. In large thin  sections (8 x 15 cm) covered with a thin glass slide, which could only he studied under a  lightmicroscope, no halite was observed. However, another salt of unknown composition,  not observed in unimpregnated soil material, was detected. In addition, in small thin  sections (2 x 3 cm) with highly polished surfaces, remmmts of halite could be observed  under the lightmicroscope. With submicroscopy the presence of halite was confirmed and  the unknown salt was proved to be a habit of gypsum. This gypsum forms roughly  circular shapes, that have diameters varying between 80--200 ~m, cracked surfaces and  diffuse extinction patterns under crossed polarizers. It occurs along void walls, often in  association with halite and in the fine-grained groundmass near voids. Halite occurs along  void walls and as angular grains in coarse-grained laminae. The habit of the gypsum  observed and the curly stem-like halite on the unimpregnated soil material, have not  previously been reported in the literature. The habits of halite need not all be pedo-  genetic; though the gypsum, a much less soluble salt, probably is pedogenetic. Techniques  of preparing thin sections must be improved for the further study of easily soluble salts  in soils.    INTRODUCTION    The micromorphology of a large number of Indian benchmark soils was  analysed and interpreted in The Netherlands*. Some of these soils were  salt-affected. Undisturbed soil samples from one of the salt-affected soil    *Co-operation between the Indian National Bureau of Soil Survey and Land Use Planning  and The Netherlands Soil Survey Institue/International Soil Museum.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    150    series (Dandl) showed a special kind of salt efflorescence on void-walls. The  morphology, composition and occurrence of salts m these samples was  studied in unimpregnated soil samples, and in thin sectmns, using light-  microscope and submicroscope techniques.    MATERIAL    The soil materials showing the salt efflorescence were derived from the  Dandl series, classifmd as Halaquepts, salme phases of Ustochrepts (Soil Survey  Staff U.S.D.A., 1975). Halaquepts occur extensively in the semi-arid parts of  southern and eastern Gujarat, one of the western coastal states of India, and  are represented by the Dandi series (Murthy et al., 1980). These soils are  formed in marine alluvium in shallow basins. The soils are deep, slowly  permeable, dark greyish brown, fine textured and have columnar and  pmsmatic structures in the B horizon. The pH is usually mildly to moderately  alkaline, electrical conductivitles vary, but are high, and the exchangeable  sodium exceeds 50% (Murthy et al., 1982). The samples were derived from  uncultivated soils near the coast.    METHODS    For the preparation of thin sections, blocks measuring 8 X 15 X 5 cm  were taken from undisturbed soil material. These samples were air-dried,  impregnated with a plastic, hardened, sawn, mounted on glass slides and  ground into sections 15 um thick, according to the method described by  Jongerius and Heintzberger (1975). The sections were subsequently coated  with a thin layer of plastic of the same composition as the one used for  mounting, and were covered by a thin glass slide.  While the samples were drying, a curly stem-like salt efflorescence was  observed on void walls. A few pieces of soil material with these salts were  removed and kept unimpregnated.  Small thin sections measuring approximately 2 X 3 cm were prepared  from the hardened blocks taken from a number of key areas near voids and  in the groundmass. The surface of these sections was not covered by a glass  slide but was polished. The polishing was done on a disc rotating at a speed of  approximately 50 rpm, covered by a polishing cloth and using diamond  polishing compound pastes first of 3 ttm and then 1 um. The resulting thin  sections were 15 ttm thick and had the highly polished surface essential for  good-quality SEM pictures.  All thin sections were studied under a lightmicroscope. The small thin  sections with polished surfaces and the pieces of unimpregnated soil material  with the salt efflorescence were examined under a scanning electron  microscope (SEM), equipped with a backscattered electron (BE) detector  and an energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (EDXRA).    151    RESULTS    The results are presented below in the following order: (1) submicroscope  data on the salt efflorescence in unimpregnated soil material; (2) light-  microscope data on salts in large and small thin sections; and (3) sub-  microscope data on salts in small thin sections.    Submzcroscope data on the salt efflorescence in unimpregnated soil material    Several morphologms of salts were observed with the SEM: massive crusts,  cubical forms, thin threads with diameters of up to a few microns and the  curly stem-like forms (see Fig. 1). No specific occurrence can be given. All  forms were encountered to a depth of 90 cm, the maximum depth from  which samples were obtained.  The stem-like forms were abundant. They often consisted of a number of  thin threads, 5--15 pm in diameter, that coalesced to form a broad, thin,  elongated, curly band up to several mm long {Fig. lb). The results from the  EDXRA analyses showed that the morphologies invariably consisted of Na  and C1 (Fig. lc) and must be halite.    Fig. la. Legend on p 152.    152    Fig  1  General view (SEI) of a surface crust (a), detail (SEI) of the curly stem-like  material (b), and an EDXRA point-analysis of this material (c) in unimpregnated soil  material    153    Lightmicroscope data on salts in large and small thin sections    Large thin sections. These thin sections were carefully studied for the  presence of salts. In voids and m the groundmass colourless, optically 1so-  tropic halite could not be detected with certainty. In some of the voids, thin  accumulations of predominantly fine-grained soil material with some larger  mineral grains, occurred along the walls. No halite could be detected with  certainty in and around this material either. In the large thin sections, how-  ever, another kind of salt was observed. In plain light loose, very thin  accumulations of soil material, roughly circular in shape and varying between  80--200 ~m in diameter were discerned. No internal structure, colour or  relief could be detected. Under crossed polarizers this material was greyish-  white and had a diffuse extinction pattern (Fig. 2). This type of salt    Fig. 2. Circular shapes of gypsum (arrowed), occurring along a void wall. Large, covered,  thin section: a. plain light; b. crossed polarizers.    154    occurred in voids near the walls, often in association with the above-  mentioned thin accumulations of predominantly fine-grained soil material  and locally m the groundmass near voids, restricted to clay-rich material    Small uncovered th~n sections. In contrast with the large thin sections, in  the small uncovered thin sections, colourless, optically lsotropic material,  showing rectangular cleavage patterns was observed locally. This material  may be halite. It occurred locally as a kind of surface crust along the walls  of voids and was present together with other mineral grains in some sandy  sedimentary laminae. Under crossed polarizers, the optical lsotropy of these  grains caused these sandy sedimentary laminae to appear to have an open  packing. In the large thin sections sandy sedimentary laminae with this open  packing were also observed, but the presence of salt crystals was not proved.    155     soil material               I~,,I psurn   hahte with impurities  Fig 3. Salt accumulation along void walls Small, uncovered thin section, a. plain light;  b crossed polarizers; c. explanation (inset framework Fig 4).    The roughly circular shaped salt detected in the large thin sections, was  also observed in the small thin sections and yielded additional information.  In plain light the surface of this salt generally had a cracked pattern and  when present in voids it was often embedded in the surface crusts formed by  the halite-type of salt observed in the small thin sections (Fig. 3).    Submicroscope data on salts in small thin sections    Both types of salts detected in the small thin sections were studied with  submicroscopy.  The salt type that was colourless and optically isotropic under the light-  microscope was recognizable in secondary electron images (SEIs). But it  could not be seen in backscattered electron scanning images (BESIs: see Fig.  4, a and b). BESIs indicate the chemical composition and variation of the  object under study. The reason that the colourless, optically isotropic  material was not represented in BESIs could be that only lighter elements are  present in this salt. EDXRA point-analyses of this material showed that Na,  Mg, AI, Si, C1, K, Ca and Ti were present in slightly varying quantities. A  typical point-analysis is given in Fig. 4c. In voids where the lightmmroscopy  and submicroscopy showed no other material to be present other than  plastic, only C1 was distinctly measured in point-analyses. The same results,    156    SEIs, BESIs and point-analyses, were obtmned from the gains of salt  matenal present in coarser-grained laminae.  The other type of salt observed both in the large and small thin sections  was clearly visible m the SEIs and BESIs (Fig. 4, a and b). This salt appeared  to be composed mainly of Ca and S and was therefore a habit of gypsum.  Fig. 5 shows an SEI and X-ray images of Ca and S of one of the gypsum  accumulations.    157    Fig 4. Part of the salt accumulation along void walls of Fig. 3' a. scanning electron image;  b.  backscattered electron scanning image; c. EDXRA point-analysis of the zone  containing halite    DISCUSSION OF THE DATA    On the walls of voids in the dried samples, halite was present in various  habits. In Eswaran et al. (1980) the morphologies of halite in softs revealed  by SEM axe discussed. These authors reported that massive crusts and cubical  forms occurred in salic horizons and on the floors and walls of profile pits.    Fig. 5a. Legend on p 158    158    Fig. 5. A gypsum accumulation: a scanning electron image; b X-ray image of Ca; c, X-ray  linage of S    The cubmal, hexahedral, halite crystals occurred only rarely in soils. The  stem-like hahte habit observed in the Dandi series of soils differs from the  fibres mentioned in Eswaran et al. (1980): the individual threads are smaller,  the cross-section is more circular and the way individual threads coalesce  differs. This type of halite has not previously been described in the  hterature. The fibres mentioned by Eswaran et al. occurred in salt crusts at  the surface; the curly stem-like halite was found in dried soil material from  below the surface. No other types of salts were detected in the salt  efflorescence. After impregnation the halite was no longer detectable m the  large thin sections covered by thin glass slides. But in the small thin sections,    159    halitic material could be traced with light-microscopy and submicroscopy.  This material was not only composed of Na and C1 but also included clay  and some other soil material. The latter two materials were visible in the  large thin sections as loose accumulations of usually fine-grained soil  material, which are impurities of the halite. During impregnation some of the  halite dissolved. The CI measured in the hardened plastic was probably  derived from dissolved halite. It is not clear why remnants of this salt were  observed under the hghtmicroscope in uncovered thin sections with polished  surfaces. The low hardness of saline material may reduce its resistance to  polishing, resulting in slightly etched surfaces that mark its occurrence.  In addition to halite, a second type of salt, not detected in the dried un-  impregnated samples, occurred in the large and small thin sections. This salt,  which generally occurred in circular shapes, is a form of gypsum and  occurred locally embedded in the halite crusts along the walls of voids and  in fine-grained soil material near voids. Gypsum commonly occurs as  lentmular crystals in soils. In Hanna and Stoops (1976} a kind of feather-like  gypsum is described; in Stoops et al. (1978) rosette-like aggregates of  gypsum prisms are described. These two habits of gypsum are most related  to the gypsum identified in the Dandi series, but are different. The Dandi  habit of gypsum has not been described in the literature. The diffuse extinc-  tmn patterns may result from crystal splitting which is visible in the cracked  surfaces, and results from small impuritms in the crystals (Grigor'ev, 1961).    CONCLUSIONS    As well as carbonates, which could be unequivocally determined under a  hghtmicroscope, halite and gypsum also occurred to a depth of 90 cm in the  soils of the Dandi series under study. The halite and gypsum could only be  determined with submicroscopy. The habits of the halite observed are not  necessarily pedogenetic. It is unknown whether precipitation habits of salts,  especially of halite, formed during drying in the laboratory are the same as  those formed under natural conditions. Gypsum is a much less soluble salt  and the habit and occurrence observed are likely to be present in nature too.  Before the habits and occurrence of fairly soluble salts (which are very  important in salt-affected soils used for agriculture) can be studied further,  techniques of impregnation and sample preparation must be improved. New  methods will have to be developed. Polishing the surface of thin sections,  instead of covering them with a thin glass slide, seems to enhance the visibili-  ty of halite in light microscopy.    REFERENCES  Eswaran, H., Stoops, G and Abtahi, A., 1980 SEM morphologies of halite (NaCI) in soils.  J. Microsc., 120 (3)' 343--352    160    Grigor'ev, D P., 1961. Ontogony of Minerals. IPST, Jerusalem.  Hanna, F S. and Stoops, G., 1976. Contribution to the micromorphology of some saline  soils of the North Nile Delta in Egypt. Pedologie, 26 (1). 55--73.  Jongerius, A. and Heintzherger, G, 1975. Methods in soil micromorphology. A techmque  for the preparation of large thin sections Soil Surv. Pap., 10. Neth Soil Surv Inst.,  Wageningen.  Murthy, R S., Hirekerur, L.R. and Bhattacharjee, J.C., 1980. The taxonomy of salt-  affected soils of the Indian subcontinent. International Symposium on Salt-Affected  Sods, Karnal, 1980, pp 67--76.  Murthy, R.S, Hirekerur, L.R., Deshpande, S B. and Venteka Rao, B.V. (Editors), 1982  Benchmark Soils of India Morphology, Characterishcs and Classihcation for Resource  Management. Natl. Bur. Soil Surv and Land Use Planning (ICAR), Nagpur, India  Soil Survey Staff SCS, U.S_D.A., 1975 Soil Taxonomy. A Basic System of Soil Classifi-  cation for Making and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U S Gov Print Off., Washington,  DC.  Stoops, G, Eswaran, H. and Abtahi, A., 1978 Scanning electron microscopy of authi-  genic sulphate minerals in soils  In: M  Deigado (Editor), Proc. 5th Int Working  Meeting on Soil Micromorphology, Granada, pp 1093--1113                                           AbstractIn samples from a salt-affected Indian soil series, a curly stem-like salt efflorescence occurred. Unimpregnated soil material and thin sections from these samples, prepared in two different ways, were studied with lightmicroscopy and submicroscopy. The samples came from the Dandi soil series, classified as Halaquepts (Soil Survey Staff U.S.D.A., 1975), which occur extensively on marine alluvium in the semi-arid parts of Gujarat (India). In the unimpregnated samples, several habits of halite (massive crusts, cubical forms, thin threads and curly stem-like forms) were determined with SEM—EDXRA. In large thin sections (8 × 15 cm) covered with a thin glass slide, which could only be studied under a lightmicroscope, no halite was observed. However, another salt of unknown composition, not observed in unimpregnated soil material, was detected. In addition, in small thin sections (2 × 3 cm) with highly polished surfaces, remnants of halite could be observed under the lightmicroscope. With submicroscopy the presence of halite was confirmed and the unknown salt was proved to be a habit of gypsum. This gypsum forms roughly circular shapes, that have diameters varying between 80–200 μm, cracked surfaces and diffuse extinction patterns under crossed polarizers. It occurs along void walls, often in association with halite and in the fine-grained groundmass near voids. Halite occurs along void walls and as angular grains in coarse-grained laminae. The habit of the gypsum observed and the curly stem-like halite on the unimpregnated soil material, have not previously been reported in the literature. The habits of halite need not all be pedogenetic; though the gypsum, a much less soluble salt, probably is pedogenetic. Techniques of preparing thin sections must be improved for the further study of easily soluble salts in soils. 