 377    CONTENTS VOL. 27, 1982    Preface  ...........................  v  Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 1. Morphology, formation and classifi-  cation  F.H. Beinroth (Mayaguez, Puerto Rico, U.S.A.)  ...........  1  Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 2. Mineralogy  R.C. Jones (Honolulu, Hawaii, U.S.A.), W.H. Hudnall (Baton Rouge, La., U.S.A.)  and W.S. Sakai (Hilo, Hawaii, U.S.A.)  ...............  75  Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 3. Chemical properties  R.L. Fox (Honolulu, Hawaii, U.S.A.)  ..............  139  Current Titles in Soil Science  ..................  177  Infrared spectra of Cu2 Pb2 and Ca2complexes of soil humic substances  A. Piccolo and F.J. Stevenson (Urbana, Ill., U.S.A.)  ..........  195  Is there Holocene reddening (hematite formation) in soils of axeric temperate areas?  U. Schwertmann, E. Murad and D.G. Schulze (Freising-Weihenstephan, F.R.G.)  . 209  Clay mineralogy and some chemical properties of Ap horizons of Ando soils used  for paddy rice in Japan  C. Mizota, M.A. Carrasco and K. Wada (Fukuoka, Japan)  ........  225  Gaseous diffusion equations for porous materials  F.R. Troeh, J.D. Jabro and D. Kirkham (Ames, Iowa, U.S.A.)  ......  239  Weathering of chlorite and mica in a New Brunswick podzol developed on till de-  rived from chlorite-mica schist  G.J. Ross, C. Wang (Ottawa, Ont., Canada), A.I. Ozkan (Ankara, Turkey) and  H.W. Rees (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  ...............  255  Current Titles in Soil Sciences  ..................  269  The fertility capability soil classification system: interpretation, applicability and  modification  P.A. Sanchez, W. Couto and S.W. Buol (Raleigh, N.C., U.S.A.)  ......  283  Accuracy of spatial interpolation between point data on soil moisture supply  capacity, compared with estimates from mapping units  J. van Kuilenburg, J.J. de Gruijter, B.A. Marsman and J. Bouma (Wageningen,  The Netherlands)  .....................  311  The relationships of the clay mineral suites to the parent rocks of eight soil profiles  in Sarawak, Malaysia  K.S. Loi (Sarawak, Malaysia), R. Protz (Guelph, Ont., Canada) and G.J. Ross  (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  .....................  327  Al-substituted goethite -- an indication of pedogenic and other weathering environ-  ments in South Africa  R.W. Fitzpatrick (Pretoria, R.S.A.) and U. Schwertmann (Freising-Weihenstephan,  F.R.G.)  .........................  335    Book Reviews  Information Systems for Soil and Related Data, by A.W. Moore, B.G. Cook and  G.L. Lynch (Editors) -- R.H.E. Inkson  ..............  349  Ecology of a Subarctic Mire, by M. Sonesson/Editor) -- Ch. J. Smiley  .....  350  Proceedings of the Second International Soil Classification Workshop, 1978, by  F.H. Beinroth and S. Paramananthan (Editors) -- L.A. Nelson  .....  351  Structure and Function of Northern Coniferous Forests -- An Ecosystem Study,  by T. Persson (Editor) -- J. van Eimern  ..............  353    Books and Bulletins Received  ..................  355  Current Titles in Soil Science  ..................  357                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 