 Geoderma, 33 (1984) 89--99                                                         89  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SOIL FORMATION AS AFFECTED BY PIT AND MOUND  MICRORELIEF IN MASSACHUSETTS, USA*    P.L.M. VENEMAN, P.V. JACKE and S.M. BODINE  Massachusetts Agricultural Experiment Station, Department of Plant and Soil Science,  University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Mass. (U.S.A.)  (Received May 24, 1982; accepted after revision January 13, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Veneman, P.L.M., Jacke, P.V. and Bodine, S.M., 1984. Soil formation as affected by pit  and mound microrelief in Massachusetts, U.S.A. Geoderma, 33: 89--99.    The influence of pit and mound microrelief on soil formation was investigated by  detailed observations of a cross-section through a pit and mound in a hemlock (Tsuga  canadensis) forest in western Massachusetts, in the northeastern United States.  Soil forming processes during the last 140 years have led to taxonomically different  soils due to this microrelief. Part of the annual precipitation apparently does not infil-  trate into the mound but moves laterally through organic surface layers into the pits. This  resulted in more intensified translocation of Fe, A1 and organic matter in the pit profile.  The ensuing soil met the spodic horizon criteria as defined in Soil Taxonomy and was  classified as a Lithic Haplorthod. Neighboring, undisturbed soils had pronounced E, Bhs,  and Bs horizons, the latter qualifying as spodic horizons on the basis of chemical cri-  teria. These soils, however, did not meet the minimum depth requirement of 12.5 cm for  spodic horizons and therefore, were classified as Typic Dystrochrepts. The soil developed  in the mound showed less horizon development and was classified as a Typic Dystro-  chrept.  Taxonomic changes resulting from the pit and mound microrelief affected less than  6% of the area and appeared not ~ have a significant impact on the purity of map delin-  eations.    INTRODUCTION    Occurrence of pit and mound microrelief is quite common in forests in  northeastern North America. The principal cause of this microrelief, some-  times referred to as cradle knolls, is the uprooting of trees by strong winds.  Microrelief appearance is affected by tree distribution (Lyford and MacLean,  1966). Deep rooting specimens such as large hardwoods, white pines and  hemlocks tend to have large bowl-shaped masses of roots and soil material    -.  Contribution of the Massachusetts Agric. Exp. Sta. (Paper No. 2498) Dept. of Plant and  Soil Sci., Univ. of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA 01003, U.S.A.    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    90    when blown over, leaving deep pits and high mounds. The more shallow root  systems of spruce and fir trees result in plate-like root-soil masses with much  less soil material attached and hence affect the topography to a lesser degree.  Stephens (1956) reported that about 14% of a forested area in central  Massachusetts had characteristic pit and mound relief. Lyford and MacLean  (1966) observed that about 48% of unit areas in some forests in New Bruns~  wick, Canada were affected by tree throw. Mounds accounted for 36~,  whereas about 12% of the study sites were pitted. Most pits fill up rapidly  with organic debris which may account for this lower percentage. Pit and  mound microrelief is generally not widespread in Massachusetts because over  90% of the land was in agricultural production until the late 1800's. Re-  peated plowing and harrowing leveled the previous microrelief, and only  after large trees had grown back on these lands, did wind throw again be-  come an important soil disturbing process.  Significant pit and mound microrelief was observed in a small, unplowed  area in western Massachusetts. The site lies in the transition zone between  Spodosols and Inceptisols (Veneman and Bodine, 1982) and significant dif-  ferences in soil formation were apparent when profile development in the  pit and mound were compared with surrounding, undisturbed pedons. The  undisturbed and pit soils showed well expressed horizons, whereas the  mound soil lacked a pronounced E horizon and had a more weakly ex-  pressed Bs horizon. The intent of the reported research was to study the  differences in profile development due to such slight variations in relief and  to provide information about the rate of spodic horizon formation as well as  evaluate the contribution of various soil forming processes to Spodosol  development.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The study site is situated in the Town of Goshen which is located in  western Massachusetts (4227' 03"N 7250' 32"E). The area has an eleva-  tion of 380 m above sea level and is part of the Berkshires, a northern  extension of the Appalachian Mountains. Mean annual precipitation in this  region is 115 cm and the soil moisture regime is udic (Soil Survey Staff,  1975). Mean annual soil temperature is 46 and the temperature regime is  frigid {Soil Survey Staff, 1975). Plow layers were not observed in any of  the profiles and the site currently has a mature stand of hemlock trees  (Tsuga canadensis). Pits and mounds cover about 25% of the area. A large pit  and associated mound were selected for detailed study and a 3-m long trench  was dug parallel to the main axis at a distance of about 0.3 m from the  center line.  To facilitate mapping and delineation of special profile features, strings  were suspended at 10 cm intervals from a horizontal reference bar. The  strings were weighted with stones to assure exact verticality and were  marked at 10 cm spacings. The cross-section of the pit and mound was    91    drawn to scale and 3 profiles were selected for detailed study. One profile  was located at the 40 cm mark in Fig. 1B, and shows the adjacent, undis-  turbed soil hereafter referred to as the original soil. The mound was sampled  at the 180 cm point (Fig. 1A) and the pit was sampled at the 35 cm mark  (Fig. 1A).    0  20   4o  60  T  I'= 80  W  0 100  120    140    DISTANCE   (cm)  0    40    80    120    160   200   240   280      0    40    80  L    L    I    I    L    I    [    ,    I    i    I    I    I    i    I    i       I    ,    I    ,    I    0i    (A)                      (B)    KEY:    ~Oe   IlfllmlA   ~Bhs  ~Bs2  ~BC2  ~2C   ~Rocks    /Oa   I   ]E    ~Bs~   ~BCl  ~C    /Roots ~Burrow    Fig. 1. Cross-section through a pit and mound in Goshen, Massachusetts. The undis-  turbed, original soil profile is depicted in B.    The profiles were described and classified according to procedures detailed  in the Soil Survey Manual (Soil Survey Staff, 1951) and Soil Taxonomy  {Soil Survey Staff, 1975). Average bulk density values for selected horizons  were determined from at least 3 saran resin-coated clods per horizon  (Brasher et al., 1966). Representative samples for laboratory analysis were  taken from horizons in each of the profiles. To estimate minimum age of  the pit and mound microrelief, tree ring cores were obtained at a height of  about 50 cm above the forest floor from 3 mature hemlocks growing on  tops of neighboring mounds.  Physical and chemical analysis were performed according to standard  procedures (Soil Survey Staff, 1972), unless noted otherwise. Numbering  indices refer to specific methods as described in Soil Survey Investigations  Report No. 1 (Soil Survey Staff, 1972). After air-drying of the samples,  existing aggregates were crushed with a wooden rolling pin and the soil  material was passed through a 2-mm sieve. Particle size was determined by  the hydrometer method (Day, 1965) following wet sieving of the sand frac-  tions. Fiber contents of the organic horizons were determined by the solu-  bility of these materials in sodium pyrophosphate (Soil Survey Staff, 1975).    92    Soil acidity was measured in H20 (8.C.l.a.) and 1N KC1 (8.C.l.c.) extracts.  Cation exchange capacity values were obtained by direct distillation (5.A.-  1.a.) of ammonium retained on the soil particles from buffered ammonium  acetate at pH7. Organic carbon and total nitrogen were determined by  acid-dichromate  digestion  (6.A.l.a.)  and  semimicro-Kjeldahl (Bremner,  1965) procedures, respectively. Sesquioxide contents were determined by  atomic absorption in dithionite-citrate (Fe, 6.C.2.b.; A1, 6.G.7.a.) and  sodium-pyrophosphate (Fe, 6.C.5.a.; A1, 6.G.5.a.) extracts.    RESULTS    Age of pit and mound microrelief    Minimum age of the pit and mound microrelief was estimated to be at  least 113 years on the basis of tree ring counts on several trees on the tops  of adjacent mounds. Hemlock trees are not reliable indicators of age because  of their non-uniform radial growth, especially when initial growth is slow  (D. Mader, personal communication, 1983), and tree ring counts of cores  taken at about 50 cm height above the soil surface therefore tend to under-  estimate the true lifetime of the tree. Stephens (1956) observed in tree  throw areas in central Massachusetts that mounds about 500 years old begin  to have uniform and continuous horizons whereas Lyford and MacLean  (1966) studying pit and mound microrelief in New Brunswick, Canada  postulated that the lack of continuous horizons in mound microrelief in-  dicated a fairly recent origin. Fig. 1 shows that soil horizons in the cross-  section are irregular and discontinuous suggesting an age less than 500 years.  It appears that vegetative growth at the study site was initiated at ap-  proximately the same time because all trees in the study area had similar  heights and circumferences. This uniform development can only result  from a sudden removal of the previous vegetation either by clear-cutting or  natural causes such as fire or wind. No stumps or other evidence of tree  cutting activities were observed in the study area. Historical records of the  Town of Goshen (Warner, 1980) showed that during a tornado in 1834  large portions of the forests in that area were leveled by strong southwesterly  winds. The center lines through most pits and mounds in the study area are  oriented in an approximately west---east direction with the mounds always  east of the pits, indicating that the trees were uprooted due to forceful  westerly winds. It can be concluded that the mounds and pits in this area  date before 1868, are not older than 500 years, and most likely result from  the 1834 tornado.    Soil formation    A detailed cross-section of the study site is presented in Fig. l, which  shows that profile development in the mound is much less pronounced than    93    in the pit. Traces of the original sequence are still visible in the mound at  a depth of about 100 cm. During excavation of the trench we observed that  the combination of buried Oa, E and Bs horizons extended towards the  outside of the mound at an upward angle of about 40 It can be postulated  that the dense mixture of soil material and roots at the base of the uprooted  tree did not gradually disintegrate with time but folded in the direction of  tree fall, with the organic surface litter sandwiched between E and Bs hori-  zons. Hemlock trees root fairly deeply and upon tip-over tend to create a  large mass of roots and soil, the latter mainly consisting of BC material.  This soil material buried the original Oa, E and Bs horizons upon folding of  the root-soil mass and became the parent material for the mound soils. The  roots have decayed since the formation of the mound but the resinous hem-  lock litter is still discernible by the fairly decomposed organic material of  the buried Oa horizon.  Selected physical and chemical soil prope~-~::~ of each of the three pro-  files are presented in Table I. Accumulation of clay in the B horizons is  evident, especially in the original soil and to a lesser extent in the pit pro-  file. Loss of clay from overlaying horizons in the original and pit profiles  does not account for the higher clay content in the B horizons and part of  this accumulation can be attributed either to in situ clay formation or to  sedimentation of windblown particles on the soil surface followed by vertical  translocation of clay. Similar processes have been postulated elsewhere  (Franzmeier and Whiteside, 1963; Bouma et al., 1969; Sneddon et al., 1972;  Wang and McKeague, 1982).  The profiles are all extremely acid in the upper horizons, and became very  strongly acid in the lower Bs horizons. Based on base saturation and pH-KCI  values (Table I} leaching of alkaline materials and corresponding acidification  is most evident in the pit profile, slightly less in the original soil, and least  pronounced in the mound. Part of the precipitation onto the mound pre-  sumably does not infiltrate into the mineral soil but runs laterally through  the extremely acid organic litter layers into the pit. This results not only in  larger amounts of water percolating through the pit with corresponding less  flow through the mound, but it also increases the level of complexing or-  ganics in the pit leachate. Messenger et al. (1972) reported that Oi and Oa  layers, particularly under hemlock stands, are major sites of production of  water-soluble organic materials which contribute to complexation. All pro-  files have significant surface accumulations of organic material, consisting of  3--5 cm of undecomposed hemlock needles in the Oi horizon underlain by  an Oa horizon of varying thickness (Table I).  Highest C/N ratios in the three profiles are found in the Bsl horizons  (Fig. 2), whereas the Bhs exhibits maximum accumulation of organic carbon.  Below the Bsl the C/N ratios decrease rapidly with depth to values below  15 indicating stable organic matter, probably the result of microbial oxida-  tion of organic complexing agents.  Distribution of iron and aluminum in the three profiles with depth is    TABLE I    Selected physical and chemical soil properties    Profile    Depth       Horizon  Texture  Clay   B.D.      pH--H 20  (cm)                        (%)   (g/cm3)    Original  18--0       0         --        --     n.d.      2.8  0--3.5       E        vfsl        3.8   n.d.      3.3  3.5--7        Bhs        1           17.2   0.75*~     3.4  7--12.5      Bsl       vfsl         5.4   0.75*~    4.2  12.5--21.5  Bs2      lvfs       0.4   0.86     4.5  21.5--40.5  BC       lvfs       4.3   1.31     4.6  40.5--63.5  C        vfsl       3.4   1.47     4.4  Mound   17.5--0      0         --        --     n.d.      3.2  0--2.5       Bhs      vfsl        7.8   n.d.      3.6  2.5--12.5    Bsl      vfsl        7.6   1.01      4.3  12.5--30   Bs2     vfsl      2.9  0.98     4.6  30--56     BC1     lfs       2.5  1.11     4.9  56--95      BC2      lfs         2.4   1.20      5.6  95--100     C         lvfs        2.4   n.d.      4.8  Pit       39--0       0         --        --     n.d.      3.0  0--10       E        vfsl        3.9   1.13      3.3  10-13.5     Bhs       vfsl         8.0   0.85*~     3.7  13.5--21.5   Bsl       vfsl        5.1   0.85*~    4.0  21.5--35.5  Bs2      sil         1.0   n.d.      4.2  35.5--39    C        vfsl       4.1   1.08     4.6    pH--KC1    2.2  2.4  2.8  3.7  4.3  4.3  4.2  2.5  3.0  3.9  4.5  4.6  5.2  4.7  2.3  2.5  3.1  3.5  3.7  4.2    CEC         Org. C  Base  (me/100g)   (%)     saturation  (%)    n.d.         n.d.     n.d.  10.7      1.68   1  55.4         6.15     1  42.1      4.20   1  21.9         1.82     1  15.0         1.13     1  5.2         0.32     1  n.d.          n.d.     n.d.  33.5      4.71   1  30.5      3.90   1  11.7         1.09     1  6.5         0.38     1  7.6         0.34    2  5.5      0.33   1  n.d.         n.d.     n.d.  8.7         1.64     2  43.6      5.72   1  38.4         4.23     1  20.6      1.89   1  14.0         1.12     1    *~ Bulk density determined for combined Bhs and Bsl horizons.  n.d. = not determined.    95    presented in Table II. Maximum Fe accumulation is generally found in the  upper B horizon, whereas A1 dominates in the Bsl horizons. This is especial-  ly apparent in the original and the pit profiles. The mound soil lacks a pro-  nounced E horizon and translocation of Fe is less apparent.    20      40    Z  i-  n.  60  la,i  a    80    100    C/N RATIO  10    20    30  I      i      |    I  I  1    *----'*ORIGINAL  ~--  ....  MOUND  =    ~PIT    Fig. 2. Distribution of the carbon/nitrogen ratio with depth in each of the profiles studied.    The glacial till parent materials, originating from gneiss and granitic bed-  rock to the north, have been exposed to the influence of climate and vege-  tation during the last 9,000 years (Schafer and Hartshorn, 1965). The present  coniferous vegetation promotes spodic horizon formation although not at a  rapid rate judging from the profile development in the original soil. Effec-  tively greater precipitation appears to result in stronger horizon differentia-  tion and development of a Spodosol (pit profile), while effectively less rain-  fall leads to a lower leaching rate and favors Inceptisol formation (mound).    Soil classification    The appearance of morphologically well expressed E, Bhs, and Bsl hori-  zons in the original and the pit profiles indicates a significant vertical trans-    96    location of organic matter and sesquioxides. Data reported in Tables II and  III show that the Bhs and Bsl of the original, the Bsl of the mound,  and the Bhs, Bsl, and Bs2 horizons in the pit chemically qualify as spodic  horizons (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). Horizons within 12.5 cm of the mineral  soil surface, however, are excluded from the spodic horizons designation, at  least in regions with frigid or warmer soil temperature regimes, because of  the possibility of disturbance by plowing or other agricultural practices.  Only the Bsl, Bs2, and part of the Bhs in the pit profile meet all the spodic  horizon criteria and this soil is classified as a Lithic Haplorthod. The original  soil, although clearly having a spodic nature, as well as the mound profile do  not have any significant accumulations of secondary sesquioxides below a  depth of 12.5 cm and are Typic Dystrochrepts.    TABLE II    Amounts of Fe and A1 extracted with dithionite-citrate and sodium pyrophosphate    Soil      Horizon    % Dithionite-citrate extract.  Fe    A1    % Na-pyrophos. extract.    Fe   A1    Original  E        0.37   0.01                0.17   0.03  Bhs      4.50   0.54                2.47   0.41  Bsl      2.67   1.19                1.46   0.95  Bs2       0.90   0.89                 0.15   0.52  BC        0.70   0.64                   0.11   0.34  C         0.57   0.23                  n.d.    n.d.  Mound   Bhs       1.61   0.31                 1.08   0.26  Bsl      1.83   0.98                0.73   0.79  Bs2      1.32   0.69                0.10   0.27  BC1      0.90   0.26                 0.05   0.13  BC2      0.88   0.34                 0.03   0.14  C         0.48   0.21                 n.d.   n.d.  Pit      E        0.37  tr.                 0.08  0.01  Bhs      2.88   0.41                 1.75   0.35  Bsl      2.97   0.70                1.57   0.57  Bs2       1.55   0.37                 0.88   0.33  C         0.68   0.51                 0.15   0.38    n.d. = not determined; tr. = trace.    Differences in the sequence and nature of the horizons in the three pro-  files indicate divergent soil formation rates. This has resulted in dissimilar  classification of the mound and the pit profiles after a period of presumably  around 140 years. The extent of this classification change is very localized  and most likely not significant for soil survey. Judging from Fig. 1 less than  one-fourth of this pit-mound system qualifies as a Spodosol. This, and the  fact that about 25% of the study area appears altered by tree throw, leads to  the conclusion that at the most only 6% of the total area will be taxonomi-  cally affected. Although the effect of pitted microrelief appears insignificant    97  TABLE III  Summary of data pertaining to spodic horizon classification on the basis of chemical  criteria defined in Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975)    Soil    Hor~on  (Fe+A1)p  (Fe+Al)p  Accumulation  Spodic*'  clay       (Fe+A1)d  index    Original  E         0.01       0.05        31            --  Bhs      0.17       0.57       164            +  Bsl       0.45       0.62       217            +  Bs2      1.68      0.37      195           --  BC      0.10      0.34      253           --  C        --          --           81            --  Mound   Bhs      0.17       0.70        73            --  Bsl      0.20       0.54       267           +  Bs2      0.13       0.18       179           --  BC1      0.07       0.16       135           --  BC2      0.07       0.14       250           --  C        --         --          60           --  Pit       E         0.02       0.24        67            --  Bhs      0.26       0.64       139            +  Bsl      0.42       0.58       286           +  Bs2      1.21       0.63       281           +  C         0.13       0.45        42            --    * 1 A indicates qualification as a spodic horizon.    for the soil surveyor, it certainly affects tree growth as virtually all hemlock  trees tend to favor the slightly better drained conditions on the mounds.    DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    Under favorable conditions spodic horizon formation in soils under hem-  lock stands can be a rapid process. Based on tree ring counts the topography  of the study site predates the year 1868, the discontinuity of the horizons  indicates that the tree throw event did not occur more than 500 years ago,  and historical records show that it most likely happened in 1834. Since the  tree throw occurred, distinctively different soils have developed. Horizons  in the mound profile are not well expressed, and an E horizon is absent.  Secondary sesquioxides are being mobilized in the uppermost horizons,  however, as is evidenced by the relatively high amount of pyrophosphate-  extractable sesquioxides. Soil horizon differentiation is much more pro-  nounced in the original and the pit profiles, even though the pit was created  at the same time as the mound. We postulate that the 60% slope between pit  and mound forced part of the precipitation to move laterally through the  organic litter layer into the pit. The extremely acid litter layer contains  large amounts of organic complexing agents which are flushed into the pit,    98    resulting in a significant translocation of organic matter and sesquioxides in  the pit profile. This leaching process probably is enhanced by low perme-  ability of the raw humus accumulated above the pit profile as has been  reported by Lag and Einevoll (1954) for Podzols in Norway. The original  profile, exposed to leaching processes for a much longer time than the actual  pit and mound soils, show a significant accumulation of organic matter in  the Bhs, Bsl and Bs2 horizons. The thicknesses of these horizons as com-  pared to similar ones in the pit profile are substantially less, however, which  may have resulted from less intense leaching due to shorter contact times in  the litter layer, higher permeabilities of the litter (Lag and Einevoll, 1954)  and comparatively less soil water moving through the profile.  Differences in the rate of soil development are reflected in the classifi-  cation of the 3 profiles. The mound soil shows incipient spodic horizon  formation, with a high amount of pyrophosphate-extractable sesquioxides  in the B horizons. Spodic horizon development does not extend below a  depth of 12.5 cm and the soil is classified as a Typic Dystrochept. In the pit  soil, which originated during the same time as the mound, the spodic horizon  extends to a depth of 35.5 cm and the soil is classified as a Lithic Haplorthod.  The original soil takes an intermediate position in regard to degree of  horizon development. Although the profile exhibits a pronounced spodic  horizon, it does not extend below a depth of 12.5 cm and the soil is clas-  sified as a Typic Dystrochrept.  The effect of pit and mound relief on soil formation and corresponding  changes in classification is not significant for soil survey. Only 6% of the  area was assessed to be taxonomically changed as a result of tree throw. The  effect of pitted topography on tree growth, however, is significant as vir-  tually all hemlock trees were growing on the slightly better drained mounds.    REFERENCES    Bouma, J., Hoeks, J., van der Plas, L. and van Scherrenburg, B., 1969. Genesis and  morphology of some alpine podzol profiles. J. Soil Sci., 20 : 384--398.  Brasher, B.R., Franzmeier, D.P., Valassis, V. and Davidson, S.E., 1966. Use of saran  resin to coat natural soil clods for bulk-density and water-retention measurements.  Soil Sci., 101: 108.  Bremner, J.M., 1965. Total nitrogen. In: C.A. Black (Editor), Methods of Soil Analysis,  Part 2. Agronomy, 9. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wisc., pp. 1149--1178.  Day, P.R., 1965. Particle fractionation and particle-size analysis. In: C.A. Black (Editor)  Methods of Soils Analysis, Part 2. Agronomy, 9. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wisc.,  pp. 545-567.  Franzmeier, D.P. and Whiteside, E.P., 1963. A chronosequence of podzois in northern  Michigan, I. Ecology and description of pedons. Mich. State Univ. Agric. Exp. Sta.  Quart. Bull., 46: 2--20.  Lag, J. and Einevoll, O., 1954. Preliminary studies on the water permeability of raw  humus in podzol profiles in the western part of Norway. Medd. Norg. Landbruks-  hogsk., 34: 525--532.    99    Lyford, W.H. and MacLean, D.W., 1966. Mound and pit microrelief in relation to soil  disturbance and tree distribution in New Brunswick, Canada. Harvard Forest Paper  No. 15, Harvard Forest, Petersharn, Mass.  Messenger, A.S., Whiteside, E.P. and Wolcott, A.R., 1972. Climate, time, and organisms  in relation to podzol development in Michigan sands, I. Site descriptions and micro-  biological observations. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36 : 633--638.  Schafer, J.P. and Hartshorn, J.H., 1965. The Quaternary of New England. In: H.E. Wright,  Jr. and D.G. Frey (Editors). The Quarternary of the United States. Princeton Univ.  Press, Princeton, N.J., pp. 113--127.  Sneddon, J.I., Lavkulich, L.M. and Farstad, L., 1972. The morphology and genesis of  some alpine soils in British Columbia, Canada, If. Physical, chemical and mineralogical  determinations and genesis. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 104--110.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook No. 18. U.S.  Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Soil Survey Staff, 1972. Soil survey laboratory methods and procedures for collecting  soil samples. Soil Survey Investigations Rep. No. 1. U.S. Dep. Agric., U.S. Government  Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy : A basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. Soil Cons. Serv., U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook No. 436.  U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Stephens, E.P., 1956. The uprooting of trees: A forest process. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  20: 113--116.  Veneman, P.L.M. and Bodine, S.M., 1982. Chemical and morphological soil characteris-  tics in a New England drainage-toposequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 359--363.  Wang, C. and McKeague, J.A., 1982. Illuviated clay in sandy podzolic softs of New  Brunswick. Can. J. Soil Sci., 62: 79--89.  Warner, A.S., 1980. A bicentennial history of Goshen,Massachusetts 1971--1981. Goshen  Historical Commission, Goshen, Mass.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               AbstractThe influence of pit and mound microrelief on soil formation was investigated by detailed observations of a cross-section through a pit and mound in a hemlock (Tsuga canadensis) forest in western Massachusetts, in the northeastern United States.Soil forming processes during the last 140 years have led to taxonomically different soils due to this microrelief. Part of the annual precipitation apparently does not infiltrate into the mound but moves laterally through organic surface layers into the pits. This resulted in more intensified translocation of Fe, Al and organic matter in the pit profile. The ensuing soil met the spodic horizon criteria as defined in Soil Taxonomy and was classified as a Lithic Haplorthod. Neighboring, undisturbed soils had pronounced E, Bhs, and Bs horizons, the latter qualifying as spodic horizons on the basis of chemical criteria. These soils, however, did not meet the minimum depth requirement of 12.5 cm for spodic horizons and therefore, were classified as Typic Dystrochrepts. The soil developed in the mound showed less horizon development and was classified as a Typic Dystrochrept.Taxonomic changes resulting from the pit and mound microrelief affected less than 6% of the area and appeared not to have a significant impact on the purity of map delineations. 