 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 327--340                                                   327  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    MORPHOLOGY AND COMPOSITION OF SOME SOILS UNDER  CULTIVATION IN SAUDI ARABIA.1    I.I. BASHOUR, A.S. AL-MASHHADY, J. DEVI PRASAD, T. MILLER and M. MAZROA  Ministry of Agriculture and Water, Research and Development Department,  P.O. Box 17285, Riyadh (Saudi Arabia)  (Received July 10, 1981; accepted after revision August 2, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Bashour, I.I., A1-Mashhady, A.S., Prasad, J. Devi, Miller, T. and Mazroa, M., 1983. Mor-  phology and composition of some soils under cultivation in Saudi Arabia. Geoderma,  29: 327--340.    Twelve profiles representing the principal soils of five major agricultural areas  (AI-Kharj, Gassim, Hofuf, Taif and Wadi Dawasir) in Saudi Arabia were described and  sampled by horizons. Laboratory analyses were then made of the samples to characterize  the profiles more completely. Analyses were also made for certain nutrient elements to  get some measure of their levels in the soils.  The profiles are tentatively classified in the Entisol and Aridisol orders of the  American taxonomy. Five Entisol profiles were considered to be Fluvents and two  Psamments. Four Aridlsol profiles were considered to be Argids and one an Orthid.  All of the profiles are saline and calcareous and most are also sandy. Furthermore,  amounts of nutrient elements such as phosphorus, iron and zinc in surface layers are  below minimum levels established for similar soils in earlier investigations in other coun-  tries. Consequently, the soils are believed to lack sufficient quantities of several elements  for optimum plant growth. Successful use of the soils will thus require reductions in  salinity, increased levels of nutrient elements, and skillful irrigation to provide adequate  moisture.    INTRODUCTION    Saudi Arabia is a vast, arid country occupying almost four-fifths of the  Arabian Peninsula and extending from 16 to 32North latitude and from 36  to 56East longitude. The total area is about 2.2 million km2 and represents  5% of the arid zones of the world. Because of the arid climate, a majority of  the soils of the country are not cultivated. The limited areas in cultivation  have been under irrigation for many years and have produced relatively low    *~ Contribution from Regional Agriculture and Water Research Center, Ministry of Agri-  culture and Water, Riyadh, Sav di Arabia. Presented in Div. S-9 Am. Soc. Agron. Meeting,  "Soils of Dry Regions" Sympcaium, Detroit, MI, Nov. 30--Dec. 5, 1980.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    328    yields. Introduction of modern practices in irrigation and cultivation has,  therefore, been given great attention in recent years. Even so, only a few  studies have been made of the properties of the soils to guide future use and  management.  The purpose of this research is to provide a general framework for under-  standing the soils and their potentialities. Morphological, physical and  chemical properties are described for the principal soils in five major agri-  cultural regions. Comments are also made on levels of fertility and on soil-  management problems. It is hoped that the results reported here will be use-  ful in developing new methods of reclamation and in finding more effective  use and management practices for the soils so as to permit increased crop  production within Saudi Arabia and in other places with similar climates and  soils.    GENERAL NATURE OF STUDY AREA    Soils were examined in the five major agricultural regions with highest  potentials for development: A1-Kharj, Hofuf, Gassim, Taif and Wadi Dawasir  (Fig. 1). These regions are lowlands or valleys in which alluvium has been  deposited. Some of the profile sites are in flood plains, some on low terraces  and some on alluvial fans. More information about the individual sites is  given later together with the descriptions and discussions of the soils formed  or forming in the alluvial sediments.  The climate is of the continental type, characterized by large temperature  differences between day and night and between winter and summer. Rainfall    ..~.~. Arabian shield  --.~              ;';.':'/~"~:AI HiJaz Plateau  c,  " -..  /  ~i  -;"J          ~-.:.'-..;  ~]!.i'!f}i:~i';":":'.4 ii i:.oGassim "~     ,,  "~ ~.,'":::.";:::::'!':~."."',   -RIYADI~,,.)_ ~ ~  --    ' :'"" " :" J' "" "':' '""        o     '"  : .:.:'.,,....'........             : -,  ......   .'~ :.-.:.... ~. :-... :.:                       ,,  |: :;_.:f.'.:.                  ; /  U)" ~,,~.:..-: :.::'::' Wadi   .              ,' (   ~.'::.' ": - "-"  Oawasir      ,,,~,I      J    Fig. 1. Map of Saudi Arabia showing locations of study areas.    329    is low and evaporation is high, resulting in loss of much of the annual  precipitation which tends to come in torrential showers. The mean annual  precipitation, mean annual temperature and the minimum and maximum  temperatures for the five areas are given in Table I.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Field studies    Twelve profiles, representing the major agricultural soils with the greatest  potential for future development were described and sampled. The profiles  were described using standards and terminology from the U.S. Soil Survey  Manual (Soil Survey Staff, 1951). Horizon samples of 2 kg each were col-  lected and placed in plastic bags for subsequent laboratory analysis. For  convenience in discussion, soil profiles are designated with numbers 1--12 as  reported in Table I.    TABLE I    Climatic data for the study areas  Pedon       Location      Study area       AP         AMT     MaT      MiT  Number                                     (mm)      ()      ()      ()    1         Kharj-I      A1-Kharj        132       25.2     49.0     -1.0  2        Kharj-II  3           HIDA farm*  Hofuf           105        25.2      43.9       7.6  4          Shuban  5           A1-Badaeh    Gassim           130        23.9      47.9       4.5  6          Bassamiah  7           ARC farm* *  8          Muzalala      Taif             235        22.1      39.2      -1.0  9          Ashafa  10          Sailkabir  11           Khashm A1-   Wadi Dawasir     30        27.6      47.0       3.2  Ashqar  12          Sullayyal    AP = annual precipitation ; AMT = annual mean temperature; MaT = absolute maximum  temperature; MiT = absolute minimum temperature; *HIDA = Hasa Irrigation and  Drainage Authority farm; **ARC = Agriculture Research Center farm, Unaizah.    Laboratory studies    Soil samples were dried and passed through a 2-mm sieve, using a "Nasco  Asplin" electric soil grinder and siever. All samples were analyzed for pH,  electrical conductivity (EC), sodium saturation percentage (SP), carbonates  and soluble cations and anions. Determinations were made as outlined in  U.S.D.A. Salinity Laboratory Handbook 60 (Richards, 1956). Textural    330    analyses were made by the hydrometer method (Foth et al., 1976). Organic  matter was measured according to the Walkey-Black method (Jackson,  1958). Available phosphorus was determined by the modified NaHCO3  method using ascorbic acid as a reducing agent (Watanabe and Olson, 1965).  Amounts of potassium extracted by ammonium acetate and M HNOa were  determined as described by Pratt (1965). Micronutrients (Fe, Zn, Mn and  Cu) were determined by the DTPA method (Lindsay and Norwell, 1978).    RESULTS    Morphological properties    Table II summarizes the morphological characteristics of the profile  samples.  Profiles 1 and 2 were sampled on a low terrace of a flood plain in the A1-  Kharj area. The selected sites were nearly level, under cultivation, well  drained and showed no evidence of erosion. Profile 1 was a deep calcareous  soil with silty loam texture in the upper and middle sections but underlain  by sand. Although profile 2 appears to have some horizonation, the mor-  phology is not well developed and the solum overlies a deposit that may be  a buried soil.  The HIDA (Profile 3) soil was described and sampled in a recently leached  area on the Hasa Irrigation and Drainage farm at Hofuf, whereas the Shuban  soil (Profile 4) was sampled on an alfalfa farm nearby. Both of the profiles  were calcareous and the parent material at the sampling sites consisted of  moderately coarse-textured alluvium. Although slight differences in tex-  ture, color and thickness of alluvial layers were noted, the parent materials  at the two sites appeared to be quite similar.  The AI-Badaeh, Bassamiah and ARC profiles (Nos. 5, 6 and 7, respective-  ly) were sampled in the Gassim area which has received high attention for  agricultural development in recent years. Profiles 5 and 6 were calcareous  with salty surface layers. The parent materials appeared to be coarse-tex-  tured alluvium with thin layers of organic matter in the profiles. Profile 7  was formed in a sandy colluvium. The Gassim area is mainly under alfalfa,  wheat and date palm cultivation.  The Muzalala, Ashafa and Sailkabir profiles (Nos. 8, 9 and 10, respec-  tively) are wadi (valley) bottom soils, described and sampled in the Taif area  which receives relatively high amounts of rainfall (235 mm annually). Soils  in these three locations have been formed in well-drained, medium to  moderately coarse-textured alluvium from igneous rocks. Occasional thin  layers of organic matter are present in profile 8. All three profiles were sam-  pled in valley bottoms or on older alluvial fans with nearly level relief and  with elevations ranging from 1300 to 2200 m. Salinity is not a serious  problem in the softs of this area. Vegetation is mainly fruit trees, vegetables  and grapes.    331    TABLE II    Morphological properties of the soil profiles  Horizon  Depth    Munsell color Texture Structure     Consister.cy Clay    Boundary  (cm)     (moist)                               (moist)      films    1. Kharj-I: Typic Torrifluvent, fine-silty, hyperthermic  Ap         0--23    10 YR 5/6    sl        fsbk           fr            few     as  B~I        23--55     10 YR 5/6    sl        fsbk            fr             few      gs  B~       55--95    10 YR 5/6    sl        lfsbk          fr            few     cs  C~        95--150  7.5YR5/8    ls        m             vfr           few     --    2. Kharj-H: Typic  Ap         0--20      5 YR 6/6  B2        20--45   7.5 YR 6/6  B3          45--70    7.5 YR 6/6  Cb,        70--104    i0 YR 6/4  Cb:       104--150    10 YR 6/2    Natragid, fine-loamy, hyperthermic  scl      sg             vfr           none    c  scl       lmabk        fr            few     c  scl      lmabk        fr           few     c  c        3mabk        fr           distinct c  sl       2fabk         fr           distinct - -    3. HIDA farm: Typic Torrifluvent, coarse-loamy, hyperthermic  C,          0--15    10 YR 6/4    sl        sg             vfr           none    as  C2        15--32    10 YR 7/3    sl        lcsbk-lmsbk  fr            none    cw  C3        32--62    10 YR 7/3    ls       m             vfr           none    cw  C,        62--80    10 YR 6/4    ls       m             vfr           none    cs  C5        80--95    10 YR 7/4    ls        sg             vfr           none    cw  C6        95--115   10 YR 7/3    Is        m             vfr           none    cs  C~       115--125   10 YR 7/4    sl       sg             vfr           none    cs  C8       125--135    5 YR 6/2    cl       m             fr            none    - -    4. Shuban: Typic Torrifluvent, coarse-loamy, hyperthermic  A~         0--6     7.5 YR 7/4    ls       sg             1             none    as  BI          6--32    7.5 YR 7/6    scl       lfsbk          vfr           none    g  B2        32--75    7.5 YR 7/6    scl       lfsbk          vfr           none    g  B3        75--100    5 YR 6/6    scl      lfsbk          vfr           none    g  C,       100--127  2.5 YR 4/6    scl      m             vfr           none    g  C~       127--150  2.5YR5/6    sl       m             vfr           none    g    Ap  B1  B:  C    Ap  BI  B2  B3  C1  C:    5. Al-Badaeh: Typic Haplargid, clayey, hyperthermic  0--20   7.5 YR 5/4   sl       cgr           fr           none    as  20--45   7.5 YR 5/4   cl       2csbk         vfi          distinct gs  45--125  7.5 YR 5/6   cl       2csbk         vfi          distinct gs  125--165    5 YR 5/6    1        m             vfi           none    - -    6. Bassamiah: Typic Haplargid, fine-loamy hyperthermic  0--20   7.5 YR 5/8   ls       lmgr         fr           none    as  20--50   7.5 YR 4/6   1        lmsbk        fr           few     g  50--80     5 YR 4/6   el       2msbk        fr           few     g  80--115    5 YR 4/4   scl       lmsbk        vfr           few     g  115--150    5 YR 5/8    ls        m             vfr           none    g  150+         5 YR 5/8    s        m             vfr           none    - -    7. ARC farm: Typic Torripsamment, sandy, hyperthermic  C1          0--105  7.5 YR 5/8    s        sg             vfr           none    cw    332  TABLE II (continued)    Horizon  Depth    Munsell color Texture Structure     Consistency Clay  (cm)     (moist)                             (moist)     films    Boundary    8. Muzalala: Typic Torrifluvent, coarse-loamy, thermic  C~         0--15    10 YR 4/3   ls       lcsbk         vfr          none    c  C2        15--35    10 YR 4/3   is       lcsbk         vfr          none    g  C3        35--95    10 YR 4/3   sl       lcsbk         vfr          none    g  C4        95--120   10 YR 4/3   sl       m             vfr          none    g  C5       120--160   10 YR 4/3    s        m             vfr           none    - -    9. Ashafa: Typic Haplargid, coarse-loamy, thermic  Ap        0--18    10 YR 4/3   sl       2vfsbk        vfr          none    a  B2t       18--45    7.5 YR 4/6    1         2fsbk          fr            none    cw  C~        45--90   7.5 YR 4/4   ls       lcsbksm      vfr          none    d  C2        90--150   10 YR 4/3    ls        m             vfr           none    - -    I O. Sailkabir: Typic Torrifluvent, sandy, thermic  C~          0--16    10 YR 4/3    Is        lcsbk         vfr           none    cw  C2        16--45    10 YR 4/4   sl       lcsbk         vfr          none    g  C3        45--80    10 YR 5/3    s        m             vfr           none    g  C,        85--110   10 YR 5/3    s        sg             1             none    di  Cs       110--150   10 YR 5/3    Is       sg             1             none    ~ -    11. Khashm Al-Ashqar: Typic Gypsiorthid,  Clcs       0--4     10 YR 5/3   c        lcsbs  C2cs        4--28    10 YR 5/6    ls       sg  C3cs      28--85    10 YR 4/4   1        lcsbs-m  C,cs      85--110   10 YR 4/3   1        m  C~cs     110--120   10 YR 5/4   1        m    loamy, gypsic, hyperthermic  vfr          distinct as  vfr          none    aw  fr           none    aw  fr          none   cw  fr           none    - -    12. Sulayyal: Typic Torripsamment, coarse-loamy, hyperthermic  C1         0--23   2.5 YR 5/6   s        lcpr          fr           none    cw  C2       23--59   2.5 YR 5/6   s       m            vfr          none   g  C3       59--90   2.5 YR 5/6   s       m            vfr          none   g  C4        90--143  2.5 YR 4/6   s        m            vfr          none    aw  Csca    143--157    5 YR 5/6   sl       m            fr           few     - -    Abbreviations for structures are: (1) strength: 1 = weak, 2 = moderate and 3 = strong;  (2) size: f = fine, m = medium and c = coarse; and (3) kind: gr = granular, abk = angular  blocky, sbk = subangular blocky and q = single grain.  Abbreviations for consistency (moist) are: fr = friable, vfr = very friable, vfi = very firm.    The Khashm AI-Ashqar and Sulayyal soils (Profiles 11 and 12) were  described and sampled in a broad plain filled with coarse-textured alluvium  brought down from the Hijaz highlands. The area around Khashm AI-Ashqar  (Profile 11) was barren and consisted of large fluvial and salt deposits  (Sabkha). Soil deposition across the nearby mountains observed near this site  suggest that anywhere from 3 to 6 m of surface wadi deposits have been re-  moved by wind erosion. Interspersed among sand dunes and these depleted  channels are salt-encrusted (Sabkha) areas. In Profile 11, fine crystals of  gypsum cemented together to form a crust ranging from 2 to 5 cm thick    TABLE III  Physico~chemical properties of the soil profiles    Horizon  Depth     EC 103  (cm)       (mmho/cm)    pH    CaCO3 Soluble cations and anions (meq./liter)  (%)    (saturation extract)  Na     K      Ca     Mg    CO3   HCO3   Cl    Particle size distri-  bution (%),2    SO* ~    sand   silt    clay    Ap     0--23    2.70  B~       23--55      4.10  B22        55--95        3.30  C1        95--150     2.10    Ap      0--20    5.40  B~         20--45       4.80  B3          45--70       4.40  Ubl       70--104     4.80  Cb2      104--150      5.10    C~         0--15     16.3  C2        15--32     51.7  Ca        32--62     50.8  C4        62--80     54.4  C5          80--95      36.3  C6          95--115     22.5  C7        115--125     15.9  C8        125--135    36.3    A~         0--6       2.75  B1          6--32       5.25  B2        32--75      3.80  B~          75--100      4.20  C1       100--127     5.40  C2        127--150      7.50    1. Kha~-I  7.7    21.2     1  7.7   21.3   12  7.9    21.8     8  7.5    18.9     5    0.6   24.9   10.6   ND    3.5       6.7    26.7   72     21      7  0.8   21.7   27.3   ND    5.8      17.5    38.6   75     14     11  0.4   25.7   11.1   ND    2.7      10.5    32.1   75     19      6  1.3      11.9         4.5      ND         4.3               8.4         10.3       88             5             7    2. Khar]-H  7.5    23.0    22     1.8   32.3   16.4   ND    2.7  7.6    14.0    24     0.6   26.5   12.2   ND    3.2  7.6    14.5    23     0.3   22.8   12.2   ND    2.6  7.6    37.5    33     0.4   24.4   12.2   ND    2.2  7.6    21.7    20     0.3   24.4   15.4   ND    2.5    3. HIDA farm  7.7    16.8   123     5.8   45.6   27.1   ND    0.6  8.1    17.4   650    20.0   57.8   37.1   ND    1.3  8.3    19.2   500    15.0   62.0   38.7   ND    2.1  7.2    10.5   750    25.0   58.8   49.7   ND    2.0  8.7    12.0  1600    55.0   19.6   33.4   ND    1.8  8.8    33.4   450    15.0   41.8   28.1   ND    1.3  8.8      5.9   130     8.9   32.9   22.8   ND    2.0  8.1    10.7   650    20.0   47.2   48.2   ND    1.5    4. Shuban  7.8      6.9    13  7.6    16.8    26  8.1    11.7    34  8.1   9.2   41  7.8      3.3    45  7.5      4.1    56    1.2   11.2    8.0   ND    6.4  2.9   24.4   26.6   ND    2.7  1.4    4.2    4.8   ND    3.2  0.9         4.8         3.2      ND         2.5  1.1    8.5    7.1   ND    2.3  1.3       18.5       14.8      ND         2.0    35.7    34.1   57     23     20  30.7    29.4   59     22     19  17.0    38.7   58     20     22  21.7    46.0   44     12     44  28.7    28.8   65     22     13    143     57.9   65     22     13  660  104   69   18    3  217  356   89    3    8  782     99.6   84      6     10  429  1277     88      3      9  297  236   88    2   10  134     58.5   93      1      6  400    355     38     31     31    13.8    13.1   89      3      8  17.5         53.7       62           16          22  15.0    26.2   62     16     22  17.0    31.3   61     13     26  27.0    32.4   71      9     20  58.0    30.6   80      4     16    TABLE III (continued)    Horizon  Depth  (em)    EC X 103  (mmho/cm)    pH    CaCO3 Soluble cations and anions (meq./liter)  (%)    (saturation extract)  Na     K      Ca     Mg    CO3   HCO3   C|    Particle size distri-  bution (%),2    SO* '    sand   silt    clay    Ap     0--20  B,        20--45  B:         45--125  C     125--165    13.3  7.5  7.5  7.7    Ap     0--20    6.0  B1          20--50      15.5  B2         50--80       6.2  B3         80--115      5.5  C,        115--150      5.2  C2       150+          5.8    C,          0--105     1.4    C,           0--15       5.9  C2         15--35       2.2  C3         35--95       3.1  C4        95--120     4.1  Cs        120--160      3.8    Ap         0--18       1.5  B~+       18--45       1.2  C1         45--90       0.9  C~         90--150      0.5    5. Al-Badaeh  7.5    14.0    93  7.6    19.4    58  7.7   20.7   61  7.7    16.6    59    0.8      56.1       16.3      ND        4.1  0.5      28.6       10.6      ND         3.0  1.0      23.6       12.2      ND         3.0  1.4      26.5       19.0      ND         2.6    6. Bassamiah  7.6     4.6    32     1.0   34.5    9.5   ND    2.3  7.5    16.1   108     2.7   42.4   30.7   ND    1.9  7.8    18.6    43     3.4   26.5   16.9   ND    1.9  7.8     9.7    30     3.6   26.5   18.0   ND    1.6  7.8     1.3    25     2.9   26.5   18.0   ND    1.4  7.9      1.3    30     4.4   32.9   15.9   ND    2.0    7. ARC farm  8.0     3.6     1    0.4         9.2         4.4      ND         3.1    8. Muzalala  7.7     4.8    23  8.0   5.9   11  7.9     6.4    13  7.7      6.9    18  7.8   3.3   15    1.0       30.2      29.7      ND         3.6  0.3    8.5    6.9   ND    3.1  0.2       13.5         9.8      ND        2.2  0.3   24.9   14.3   ND    2.4  0.4   22.8   15.4   ND    3.0    9. Ashafa  7.5      3.8      1  7.4      2.0      1  7.4      0.8      1  7.4      1.0      1    1.5   11.1    2.6   ND    7.8  0.4    7.9    3.2   ND    5.1  0.2    5.8    2.1   ND    3.7  0.1     3.2    1.6   ND    2.9    8.8   151.4   56     27     17  47.5    47.2   33     37     30  55.0         40.0       23          35          42  42.5         60.8       37          44           19    37.5   37.2  88    4    8  1.3    18.0   47     31     22  28.7         59.2       27           33          40  20.5    56.0   50     26     24  16.2         54.7       88             6             6  3.8   73.4  90    3    7    4.8      7.6   98      1      1    39.0    41.3   80     14      6  9.5    14.1   80     13      7  18.2         16.1       56          36             8  18.2         37.0       60           28           12  13.2         37.4       88             8             4    12.0   - -   63   31    6  6.2            1.1       46          40           14  9.0   - -   85    7    8  5.7      - -     80     12      8    C,          0--16       5.8  C2          16--45       4.6  C3        45--85      4.2  C,         85--110      3.7  C5        110--150      4.6    C,cs        0--4      115.7  C2cs        4--28     80.1  C3cs       28--85      89.0  C4cs       85--110    46.2  Cscs     110--120    32.4    Ct         0--23       5.5  C~        23--59       5.4  C3        59---90      4.8  C4        90--143     6.3  Csca     143--157     7.5    10. Sailkabir  7.4      5.1    13     1.3   36.0   15.4   ND    6.7      33.2    27.7   83  7.5      5.1    11     1.4   22.8   12.2   ND    3.1      29.2    14.1   75  7.8    16.1    13     0.8   24.9    8.5   ND    2.4      20.1    24.8   91  7.7    16.6    16     0.7   17.5    6.9   ND    2.5      31.2      7.3   92  7.7    16.8    22     0.9   18.5    7.9   ND    2.1      40.0      7.2   87    11. Khashm Al-Ashqar  7.2      8.2  2350  100     59.4  626     ND    1.6       7.5  1415     16  7.7      7.9  1625    13.7  100.7  700     ND    1.6   1714     760     82  7.6    15.6  1587     9.0   94.3   50     ND    1.5   1677      61.6   48  7.8    12.0   600     4.0   70.0   45.5   ND    2.2     626      91.3   42  7.8    13.8   425     2.5   58.0   26.5   ND    2.3     436      68.7   30    11  17  4  4  7    23  8  32  42  48    12. Sulayyal  8.4     7.9    23     0.4   17.1    0.8   ND    2.6       2.5    36.2   94      3  8.0      5.3    22     0.4   13.7    2.1   ND    2.1       3.1    32.3   94      4  7.8      5.8    13     1.2   23.3   15.9   ND    2.1      42.5      8.8   92      4  7.8      3.3    25     1.1   32.3   22.3   ND    1.9      48.7    15.1   94      2  7.5    15.3    32     1.4   38.7   22.3   ND    1.9      63.7    28.7   76     14    61  10  20  16  22    3  2  4  4  10    ND = none detected. * I SO4 = estimated by difference (total soluble cations minus measured anions). * 2 size limits are according to  U.S.D.A. system.    e~  ,    336    were observed in the surface horizon. The numbers of gypsum crystals  decreased with depth. The Sulayyal soil (Profile 12) was formed in coarse-  textured alluvium from reddish colored sandstone. At the site drip irrigation  was in use for a citrus orchard, apparently because the soil poses little  salinity hazard.    Composition and ph ysico-chemical properties    The data in Table III show the physico-chemical characterization by hori-  zons of the profiles. These analyses indicate that the samples generally con-  tained large quantities of soluble salts, mainly NaC1 and CaSO4. The  maximum amount of salts in surface layers is in the Khashm A1-Ashqar sample  (Profile 11) with an EC of 115 mmhos/cm and the minimum is in the ARC  sample (Profile 7) having an EC of 1.4 mmhos/cm. Salinity in other samples  ranged from 0.5 to 54.2 mmhos/cm. Most samples were neutral to slightly  alkaline in reaction, with pH values ranging from 7.2 to 8.8. All the soils  are calcareous, with CaCO3 contents ranging from 0.8 to 33.4%. Profiles 1  and 2 from the A1-Kharj area contained the highest amounts of carbonates  throughout. The Ashafa samples (Profile 9) had the least CaCO3, which may  reflect lower initial amounts in the parent materials and some removal during  the long period of irrigation.  Phosphorus, potassium, iron, zinc, manganese, copper and organic matter  contents of surface layers are presented in Table IV. Phosphorus extractable  by sodium bicarbonate and potassium extracted by ammonium acetate    TABLE IV    Contents of phosphorus, potassium, micronutrients and organic matter in surface horizons    Location         Horizon Depth  P     K     Fe    Zn    Mn  (cm)   (ppm) (ppm) (ppm) (ppm) (ppm)    Cu    Organic  (ppm) matter  (%)    Kharj-I           Ap     0--23    5.8  241   4.0    0.7     4.8  0.5    0.95  Kharj-II          Ap     0--20    5.7    87   2.8    0.2     1.7  0.4    0.42  HIDA farm        C1       0--15     4.1   310    3.6    0.3      3.0   0.5    0.33  Shuban            A1       0--6      5.1    75    3.6    0.4      3.3   0.2    0.53  AI-Badaeh        Ap     0--20    3.5   241   7.5    0.5    20.0   1.1    1.16  Ba~amiah        Ap     0--20    1.6   137   3.0    0.2     5.2   0.4    0.10  ARC farm         C1       0--105   4.1    87    3.3    0.8      1.9   0.2    0.20  Muzalala          C~      0--15    4.5   214   3.5    0.8     7.8   1.1    0.77  Ashafa           Ap     0--18   81.5   619   9.1    3.2    26.0   1.8    4.27  Sailkabir           C1       0--16     9.0    87    3.8    1.9      4.4   0.7    0.60  Khashm A1-Ashqar C~cs    0--4      8.4   137   1.1    0.3     0.6   0.3    0.28  Sulayyal          C~      0--23    4.6   112   3.0    0.3     0.5   1.4    0.14    Critical levels: P = 10 ppm, K = 175 ppm; Fe = 4.5 ppm; Zn = 0.8 ppm; Mn = 1 ppm;  Cu = 0.2 ppm (Kamprath and Watson, 1980; Doll and Lucas, 1973; Lindsay and Norwell,  1978)    337    ranged from 1.6 to 81.5 p.p.m, and from 75 to 619 p.p.m., respectively.  Highest amounts of P and K (81 and 619 p.p.m.) were found in the surface  layer of the Ashafa profile (No. 9) from the Taif area. Contents of Fe, Zn,  Mn and Cu extractable by DTPA (Diethylenetriamine penteacetic acid), ex-  pressed in p.p.m., ranged from 1.1 to 9.2, 0.2 to 3.2, 0.5 to 26.0 and 0.2 to  1.8, respectively. Profile No. 9 (Ashafa} contained the highest amounts of  micronutrients extractable by DTPA.    DISCUSSION    Morphology and classification    Most differences among the 12 profiles seem to be reflections of the initial  character of parent materials, but some can be attributed to horizon dif-  ferentiation after sediments were deposited. Some profiles occupy very  young and others somewhat older land surfaces. Differences between those  two sets of profiles are ascribed to greater horizon differentiation in one  than in the other.  Colors range in hue from 2.5YR to 10YR, with the same color tending  to carry down through each profile. Moreover, colors can be related to those  of the source rocks for the alluvial parent materials generally. For example,  Profile 12 is uniformly reddish in color and the parent rocks are red  Cretaceous and Tertiary sandstones.  Textures of the profiles are mostly sand, loamy sand and sandy loam.  Some horizons in a few profiles are finer in texture because of stratification.  Furthermore, some illuviation of clay seems to have occurred to make  deeper profiles slightly heavier than surface layers in a few instances. For the  group of soils as a whole, however, sandiness is a distinctive characteristic.  Most profiles have little or no horizonation, but a few have evident  horizons. Profiles 3, 7, 8, 10, 11 and 12 lack either or both A and B hori-  zons. The surface layers in most of these profiles are parts of the C horizons.  Profiles 7 and 8 are on very young alluvial fans; not enough time has passed  for development of horizons. More time is thought to have been available  for the development of horizons in Profiles 2, 5, 6 and 9 because those  occupy slightly higher positions in their respective landscapes. The four  profiles have B horizons expressed in one or both of texture and structure.  Profiles 5, 6 and 9 are considered to have weakly developed argillic horizons,  whereas Profile 2 is thought to have a natric horizon marked by some illuvia-  tion of clay plus high levels of sodium.  Tentative placements of the profiles at the family and higher levels in the  American soil taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975) are given in Table II.  Seven profiles are thought to be various kinds of Entisols and the other five  to be Aridisols. Five Entisols are thought to be Fluvents and two to be  Psamments. Among the Aridisols, four are considered to be Argids and one  an Orthid.    338    Composition and physico-chemical properties    Contents of organic matter are less than 1% in the surface layers of all  profiles except Nos. 5 and 9. The content is almost 1% in Profile 1. The  generally low levels of organic matter are attributed to limited additions of  plant residues because of sparse vegetative cover. Kadry and Arar (1975)  and Girgirah et al. (1975} reported that the contents of organic matter in  surface layers of soils of arid regions were commonly below 0.2% because of  the limited biological and chemical activity possible under dry conditions.  The contents of organic matter in surface layers of all 12 profiles were above  0.2%, although by a narrow margin in some instances. The low contents of  organic matter in the soils that were studied are considered to be largely  responsible for the weak grades of structure in Profiles 2, 3, 6, 8, 10, 11 and  12.  The effects of additional moisture and consequent greater vegetative  growth on the amounts of organic matter are indicated by a content of  4.27% in the surface layer of Profile 9 (Ashafa). That profile was sampled in  a vegetable field which has been under intensive cultivation, with both irriga-  tion and fertilization, for many years.  Data in Table III show that most of the profiles are saline. Presence of the  salts is attributed to a combination of originally saline parent materials and  current high water tables. An important source of sediments from which  alluvium originated consisted of saliniferous marls. High ground-water tables  within 1 and 1.5 m of soil surfaces have been observed in the Hofuf and  Gassim areas, respectively. Depths of water tables in the three other areas  commonly range from 2 to 3.5 m.  The concentrations of soluble cations and anions are especially high in  Profile 11 (Table II). That profile was sampled in an uncultivated area and  the high salinity is, therefore, believed to be natural rather than induced by  irrigation. The amounts of salts are highest in the surface layer, and this  distribution is believed to be due to upward movement of water with evap-  oration at the surface.  The HIDA Profile (No. 3) in the Hofuf area was sampled in an area being  reclaimed at the time of sampling. Leaching of salts has started but is not  completed. The profile is still highly saline, as shown in Table III, with elec-  trical conductivities ranging from 16 to 56 mmhos/cm. Salinity is highest in  layers between 15 and 80 cm. This is ascribed to slight downward movement  of salts by leaching.  All samples are calcareous (Table III) with contents mostly between 5 and  15%. Carbonates in the softs are believed to have originated in limestones and  marls that contributed a share of the sediments constituting the alluvial  parent materials. Persistence of carbonates in the soils is to be expected be-  cause of the limited rainfall and high temperatures. The removal of car-  bonates by leaching must be very small under the present climate. The  amounts of carbonates do not seem to be high enough to have impaired  physical properties of the soils for root growth.    339    Implications to usefulness of the soils    All in all, the soils have a number of characteristics that are not favorable  to plant growth, some morphological and others physical or chemical. The  sandiness, the salinity and the low levels of certain nutrient elements are  deficiencies that must be corrected or overcome in some way for successful  crop production.  High proportions of sand in the soils means that they have relatively low  water-holding capacities. Moreover, the sand, assumed to be chiefly quartz,  limits capacities of the soils to provide nutrients to plants as well. On the  other hand, the sandy soils have high infiltration rates, high permeabilities  and good aeration and are easy to till. The sandiness thus offers some ad-  vantages as well as disadvantages.  The contents of plant nutrient elements in surface layers of the soils are  lower than desirable, according to studies made of levels in calcareous soils  of other arid regions. Fuehring (1973} reported that arid, calcareous soils are  usually deficient in N, P, Fe and Zn. Critical levels below which deficiencies  are to be expected were also given as 10 ppm of phosphorus (Kamprath and  Watson, 1980) and 175 ppm of potassium (Doll and Lucas, 1973). The data  for the surface layers given in Table IV show that P is below 10 ppm in all of  the samples but one, whereas potassium is below 175 ppm in seven out of  the 12 samples. The one sample above the critical level in content of phos-  phorus represents the surface layer of Profile 9 (Ashafa). That sample was  much the highest of all in both phosphorus and potassium. The field in  which Profile 9 was sampled has received appreciable amounts of fertilizers  for many years.  Critical levels of micronutrients in calcareous soils have been given by  Lindsay and Norwell (1978). Expressed in ppm, these are 4.5 of Fe, 0.8 of  Zn, 1 of Mn and 0.2 of Cu. Data in Table IV show that all but two of the  surface layers are below 4.5 p.p.m, of Fe and all but three are below 0.8  p.p.m, of Zn. Only two samples are below 1 p.p.m, of Mn and none below  0.2 p.p.m, of Cu. Stewart-Jones and Kelso (1977) found that soils of the  Hofuf area were deficient in Fe and Zn. Profiles 3 and 4 are from that area  and the surface layers are both below the critical levels given for the two  elements.  The generally low levels of many nutrient elements in the surface layers of  the 12 profiles are attributed primarily to their sandy, calcareous nature.  For successful production on the softs studied, the low levels of certain  nutrient elements, the salinity and the sandiness must be offset or overcome.  Softs comparable in all or most characteristics to those that were investigated  are, however, being cultivated in parts of Saudi Arabia. Consequently, it is  believed that all soils represented by the 12 profiles can also be cultivated  successfully. Saline soils such as HIDA and Khashm A1-Ashqar (Profile Nos. 3  and 11) would, however, require proper reclamation practices for successful  use. Careful management that includes applications of fertilizer and much  skill in irrigation practice will be required for effective utilization.    340    REFERENCES    Doll, E.C. and Lucas, R.E., 1973. Testing soils for potassium, calcium and magnesium.  In: L.M. Walsh and J.D. Beaton (Editors), Soil Testing and Plant Analysis. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am., Madison, WI, pp. 133--151.  Foth, H.D., Withee, L.V., Jacobs, H.S. and Thein, S.J., 1976. Laboratory Manual for  Introductory Soil Science. Win. Brown, Dubuque, Iowa, 12 pp.  Fuehring, H.D., 1973. Response of crops grown on calcareous soils to fertilization. In:  Calcareous Soils, FAO Soil Bull., 21: 53--71.  Girgirah, A., AI-Dukail, A. and Smith, M., 1975. Country report on reclamation and  management of sandy soils. In: Sandy Soils, FAO Soils Bull., 25: 197--200.  Jackson, M.L., 1958. Soil Chemical Analysis. Prentice-Hall, Englewood Cliffs, N.J.,  205 pp.  Kadry, L.T. and Afar, A., 1975. Regional applied research on sandy soils. In: Sandy  Soils, FAO Bull. 25 : 147--150.  Kamprath, E.J. and Watson, M.E., 1980. Conventional soil and tissue tests for assessing  the phosphorus status of soils. In: The Role of Phosphorus in Agriculture. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am., Madison, WI, pp. 433--469.  Lindsay, W.L. and Norwell, W.A., 1978. Development of a DPTA soil test for zinc, iron,  manganese and copper. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 421--428.  Pratt, P.F., 1965. Potassium. In: C.A. Black (Editor-in-Chief), Methods of Soil Analysis,  2. Am. Soc. Agron. Inc., Madison, WI, pp. 1022--1030.  Richards, L.A. (Editor), 1956. Diagnosis and Improvement of Saline and Alkali Soils.  U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook 60, 160 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S.D.A. Handbook, 18 U.S. Gov. Print.  Off., Washington, DC.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy. A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric., Handbook 436. U.S. Gov. Print. Off.,  Washington, DC.  Stewart-Jones, W. and Kelso, I., 1977. The micronutrient status of soils in AI-Hasa and at  the Agricultural Research Center, Hofuf. Univ. Coll. North Wales, Bangor. (U.K.) and  Ministry of Agriculture and Water, Saudi Arabia, Joint Publ, 101.  Watanabe, F.S. and Olsen, S.R., 1965. Test of an ascorbic acid method for determining  phosphorus in water and NaHCO~ extracts from soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29:  677--678.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractTwelve profiles representing the principal soils of five major agricultural areas (Al-Kharj, Gassim, Hofuf, Taif and Wadi Dawasir) in Saudi Arabia were described and sampled by horizons. Laboratory analyses were then made of the samples to characterize the profiles more completely. Analyses were also made for certain nutrient elements to get some measure of their levels in the soils.The profiles are tentatively classified in the Entisol and Aridisol orders of the American taxonomy. Five Entisol profiles were considered to be Fluvents and two Psamments. Four Aridisol profiles were considered to be Argids and one an Orthid.All of the profiles are saline and calcareous and most are also sandy. Furthermore, amounts of nutrient elements such as phosphorus, iron and zinc in surface layers are below minimum levels established for similar soils in earlier investigations in other countries. Consequently, the soils are believed to lack sufficient quantities of several elements for optimum plant growth. Successful use of the soils will thus require reductions in salinity, increased levels of nutrient elements, and skillful irrigation to provide adequate moisture. 