 Geoderma, 32 (1984) 227--248                                                     227  Elsevier Science Publishers B V,, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    TEXTURAL DIFFERENTIATION IN CHRONOSEQUENCES FROM  EASTERN AUSTRALIA, III. EVIDENCE FROM ELEMENTAL  CHEMISTRY    D.J. CHITTLEBOROUGH.1 , J.M. OADES and P H WALKER  Department of Agriculture, Box 1671, G P. 0, Adelaide, S A 5001 (A ustraha)  Department  of Soil Science,  Waite Agricultural Research Institute,  Unwerslty of  Adelaide, Glen Osmond, S A. 5064 (Austraha)  Dwlsmn of Sods, CSIRO, Box 639, Canberra Czty, A C T 2601 (Australia)  (Received June 29, 1982, revised versmn accepted May 6, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Chittleborough, D.J, Oades, J M. and Walker, P.H., 1984. Textural differentiation m  chronosequences from eastern Australia, III  Evidence from elemntal chemistry.  Geoderma, 32 227--248.    Proportions of resistant heavy minerals, zircon, rutlle and llmemte, xenotlme and  monazlte, in the fraction &gt; 2.96 g cm-3 were estimated by X-ray fluorescent spectro-  scopic measurement of the elements zirconium, titanium, yttrium and phosphorus, re-  spechvely. Ratios of these elements in various fractions m soils of four terrace sequences  showed statistically insignificant changes with depth, thus ruling out sedimentary layer-  Ing as an explanation for textural differences. Formation of clay by more intense chemi-  cal weathering of coarse minerals in the B horizon was discounted on the basis of con-  stant ratios of Fe203"ZrO2, Na~O:ZrO2 and CaO:ZrO2 m the silt fraction. In the oldest  members of several sequences there was evidence of chemical weathering but moderate  to strong textural contrast was already apparent m younger profiles. Calculations of  losses and gains on the basis of the tri-acid resistant fraction of whole soil samples pro-  vided further strong evidence for the predominant role played by clay translocahon and  the minor contribution to the clay fraction of clay formation in place except in the  oldest soils It was concluded that clay llluviatlon was the main mechanism responsible  for textural differentiation with weathering in situ playing a minor, albeit with time, an  increasingly important role.    INTRODUCTION    Elemental chemistry has been used extensively in pedogenetm studies to  provide evidence for the provenance of the parent material, as an mdmator  of weathering and as a basis for calculating the losses and gains of mobile  constituents.  Establishment of the uniformity of the parent material is a pre-requisite    1 Present address: Department of Soil Science, Waite Agricultural Research Institute,  University of Adelaide, Glen Osmond, S.A. 5064 (Australia).    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    228    for any pedogenetic study in order to enable changes to be ascribed to sml  forming processes and not to lithological discontinuities. Even m a deposit  which was originally uniform in texture, however, differences in the resistant  mineral assemblage, and hence its chemmtry, are to be expected inasmuch as  some degree of sorting has been observed in most recent sedimentary depos-  its (Mitchell, 1975). The significant point therefore, is that differences in the  properties of the parent material should be minor compared to those pro-  duced during soil development (Brewer, 1964).  In view of the difficulties in selecting a suitable resistant mineral as a refer-  ence, there are advantages in examining a number of different minerals and a  number of size fractions. In most soils, however, resistant minerals are pre-  sent in very low concentrations. Statistically sound deductions can only be  made if these minerals can be isolated in sufficient quantities for identifica-  tion and counting. An alternative is to use concentrations of elements specif-  ic for these minerals as a measure of the abundance. Zirconium and titanium,  as indices of zircon and rutile, have been most widely used (e.g. Chapman  and Horn, 1968; Sudorn and Arnaud, 1971; Smith and Wilding, 1972). Re-  cently Murad (1978) suggested yttrium, which occurs predominantly in  xenotime. Another mineral which has been used in sedimentological studies  but not, to the authors' knowledge, in pedogenetic studies, is monazite. In  the 20--100 ~m fraction of density 2.96 gcm-3, phosphorus can be used as a  chemical index (Mitchell, 1975).  Assessment of the degree of chemical weathering can be made using ratios  of the concentrations of weatherable to resistant minerals in the silt fraction.  Beavers et al. (1963) used CaO: ZrO2 molar ratios as an index of weathering  in six loessial softs comprising a chronosequence and were able to show that  the degree of weathering was closely zelated to the pattern of loess thickness.  Foss and Rust (1968) used CaO : ZK)2 and FezO~ : ZrO2 ratios to indicate a  period of soil development between the deposition of two sediments. Most  studies have shown that the intensity of weathering is greatest in the A hori-  zon although the majority appear to have been on Spodosol profiles. These  studies have shown a relatively rapid rate of chemical decomposition of less  resistant minerals, e.g. ferromagneslan minerals. Weathering intensity has also  been studied as a function of time (Ruhe, 1956; Bhattacherya, 1963). Ruhe  (1956) observed little weathering in soils ~ 6,800 years old but that there-  after, up to 100,000 years old, there was a progressive increase in weathering.  Losses and gains of constituents as a result of soil development have been  calculated on the basis of resistant minerals but such calculations are critical-  ly dependent on two factors, the choice of parent material and the choice of  the stable, immobile constituent (Brewer, 1964). Most studies have used on-  ly one stable constituent, often zirconium but occasionally quartz (Bourne  and Whiteside, 1962) and titanium (WiIding et al., 1971). Few workers have  compared values for losses and gains from a number of internal standards.  Sudom and Arnaud (1971) evaluated quartz, zirconium and titanium and  showed that the weathering and mobilisation of titanium in all fractions  limited its usefulness. From softs derived from mudstones in a typxcal caten-    229    ary sequence m Wales, Evans and Adams (1975) assessed the usefulness of  zirconium, titanium, quartz and the residue from tri-acid treatment (Akhtyr-  stev, 1968}. They also found titanium had been mobihsed. Linear regres-  sions showed that there was good agreement between the other indices.  In this paper, data on the elemental chemistry will be used to assess the  uniformity of the parent material and to evaluate the relative importance of  chemmal weathering and clay translocation in the formatmn of textural  contrast    METHODS AND MATERIALS    Seventeen profiles from four chronosequences formed the basis of this  study. Their morphology and classification are described by Chlttleborough  et al. (1984).    Bulk density    Bulk density was measured by modification of the technique described by  Brasher et al. (1966). Clods of soil 7--10 cm diameter were pried from the  pit face immediately adjacent to the section where samples were taken for  chemical analysis. Three or four clods were taken for each horizon. The bulk  density of each clod was measured at -1/3 bar water potential and after  oven-drymg. In order to ensure uniform wetting up after coating with Saran  resin, each clod was ground fiat on one surface by carefully rubbing on a  coarse glass paper. The smooth surface so obtained obviated the necessity  for packing of the clod with glass beads to ensure contact with the plate.  From the bulk density values, the coefficient of linear extensibility (COLE)  was calculated.    Acid residue    Duplicate 1-g samples of free earth from each horizon of every terrace soil  were digested for 1 h with a tri-acld mixture of HC1, HNO3 and _H2SO4  (Hardy and Follet-Smlth, 1931). Each sample was heated to 80. This was  continued until all brown fumes had disappeared, after which heating was  continued for 1 h. The residue was washed several times with distilled water  using a centrifuge, drmd and weighed.    Heavy minerals    From each horizon, fractions of size 10--125 #m were isolated by sedi-  mentation to remove partmles &lt; 10 #m and by wet sieving to remove par-  ticles &gt; 125 #m. Heavy minerals of density &gt; 2.96 g cm-3 were separated  centrifugally in tetrabromoethane from 100 g subsamples of the 10--125 pm  fraction. Because earlier studies had shown that heavy minerals constituted   2% by weight of the fine sand and coarse silt fractions, very large quanti-    230    ties of soil were necessary from those horizons high in clay in order to en-  sure adequate amounts of minerals for analysis.    Clay separations    25 g soil was mixed with 25 ml of 2 M sodium chloride m a 75 ml plastic  vial and shaken on a Spex Mixer Mill for 30 s. 200 g were fractlonated for  horizons low in clay, 50 g for those B horizons with high clay contents. The  samples were dialysed against distilled water until all salt was removed. The  dialysis procedure was adopted to reduce the loss of fine clay which inevi-  tably occurs when salts are removed from suspension during washing and  centrifugation. Clay was removed after gravity sedimentation of larger par-  ticles.  Fme clay (&lt;0.2 #m) was separated from coarse clay (0.2--2 ~m) by two  methods.  In an earlier study on the Urrbrae loam (Chlttleborough and Oades, 1980)  clay was separated m an MSE High Speed 18 centrifuge or a Sorvall RC-2B  centrifuge fitted with a continuous action rotor. Dispersed clay (&lt;0.5% sus-  pension) was pumped at 109 ml min -1 through a flow cell surrounding the  stephorn of an ultrasonic probe immediately prior to entering the rotor. Cen-  trifugation was carried out at 9,000 rpm. The coarse clay inside the rotor  basket was resuspended and recentrifuged three times. Both coarse and fine  clay fractions were concentrated to 2 l in a cyclone evaporator at 40,  further concentrated in a rotary evaporator and finally freeze&lt;tried, weighed  and stored at 0 prior to analysis. This techmque is 1deal when large quanti-  ties of clay are required or where the concentration of fine clay is so low  that large volumes of suspension must be centrifuged. Where these condi-  tions did not apply, clay was fractionated in a centrifuge with swing~ut  buckets at 5,000 rpm. Five or six centrifugations were required to remove  the clay. Concentration and freeze drying were performed as described  above.    Chemical analysis    Fractions of sizes &gt; 5 #rn, i.e., 5--10, 10--20 and &gt; 20 #m, were gTound in  a tungsten carbide mill to a fine powder. After ignition in a furnace at  1000, 0.28 g of each sample was mixed with 1.52 g of lithium borate and  lanthanum oxide and a glass disc was made. Elemental analysis was carried  out by X-ray fluorescent spectroscopy according to the method of Norrish  and Hutton (1969). Yttrium and zirconium were measured with the scintil-  lation counter. Matrix corrections were made for each element.    Calculation of losses and gains of constituents    Reconstruction of elemental and clay gains and losses accompanying soil  development were calculated on the basis of the stable constituent method    231    of Brewer (1964). Changes in volume, thickness and weight were also com-  puted by this method.  An attempt was made to assess the relative importance of clay migration  and clay formation by apportioning the losses and gains to each process by  the method of Barshad (1965). The method is based on the loss of elemental  oxides from the non-clay fraction (2--2,000 ~m) of soil horizons relative to  the parent material.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Parent mater~l uniformity    Three criteria, falling into two general categories, were apphed.  (1) Particle-size distribution (PSD) of resistant mmerals of the non-clay  fractions: (i) ratio of concentrations of T102 in coarse silt and sand fractions.  (2) Ratio of two resistant minerals m any one fraction: (1) Y:O3: ZrO:,  ZrO2 " TiO2 and P205 : T102 of the 10--125 ~m fraction of density &gt; 2.96 g  cm -3, where Y203 is assumed to represent the concentration of xenotlme,  ZrO2 of zircon, TiO2 of rutile + llmenite, P2Os of mon azite; (n) ratio of  TiO2 " ZrO2 m the coarse silt fraction.  Results are presented in Tables I, II, III and IV for Gooromon Ponds,  Shmgle House Creek, Nowra Creek and Hawkesbury River, respectively.  Results for Gooromon Ponds indicate that the parent material for each  soil was initially homogeneous. All ratios show a very high degree of simi-  larity with depth. There is no evidence that the textural differentiation in  the older profiles G4 and G5 is the result of sedimentary layering.  Furthermore, the parent material for all five profiles can be considered  ldentmal because the ratms are the same throughout. Drees and Wildmg  (1978) stated that percentage deviations of more than 22% were reqmred  to detect llthologm discontinuities, whereas Chapman and Horn (1968) con-  sldered differences of 100% or more were required. If the ratms for all soxls  are considered to be normally distributed and part of the same population,  relative standard deviations (rsd) are ~ 24% for all ratios and &lt; 5% for the  yttrium oxide z~rconium oxide ratio (Table V). This result has important  imphcations if these soils are to be considered part of a chronosequence. It  means that the independent soil formmg factor, parent material, can be con-  sidered constant.  Similar conclusions can be drawn from the data for Shingle House Creek  (Table II). Only the surface layer of S1 can be considered to be different.  The P2Os " TiO2 ratios differ apprecmbly in profiles S1 and $2 (rsd &gt; 50%).  In view of the relative constancy of other ratms, the results are probably due  to sampling and analytical error : there is ~ 0.05% phosphorus in many  heavy mineral samples compared to &gt; 30% for titanium, &gt; 5% for zirconium  and &gt; 2% for yttrium. Apart from the ZrO2 " TiO2 ratio, all ratios show a  decrease in rsd with age. The somewhat higher ZrO2 : T102 ratios m the silt  fraction may be caused by some weathering and mobilisatlon of titamum m    232  TABLE I  Ratios of oxides from    various size and denmty fractions of sods from Gooromon Ponds.1    Profile    Depth  (cm)    Ratios of oxldes  Y203     ZrO~     P~O~     ZrO~ cs     TiO2 s  ZrO2      TiO~      TiO2      TIO2 c..s      TiO cs  I0 '               10  (1)    (i)      (i)     (2)       (3)    G1          0      0.43      0 28      0.20      0.31         0.58  6      0.42      0.38      0.23      0 29         0.60  18       0 43      0 36      0_23      0 30         0 62  42              0.44             0  43             0.24             0.33                   0.50  56      0.44      0.35      0 22      0.32         0.51  71       0.42      0_35      0 22      0.33         0 54  G2                      0              0 44             0.20             0  15             0  33                   0.65  20       0.45      0 22      0 18      0.29         0.66  40              0 47             0  18             0.14             0.30                   0 73  50      0 49      0 19      0 15      0 30         0 67  G3                      0              0  50             0  15             0.14             0  32                   0 79  12               0 47             0.19             0.14                 --                         --  24      0.46      0.23      0.15      0.31         0 73  32      0 47      0 25      0.17      0.31         0.64  41               0 44             0.31             0  17             0  33                   0 59  55       0 47      0.26      0 16      0 30         0.53  86              0  46             0  27             0  18             0.28                    0.47  78       0.45      0 22      0_16      0 28         0 40  88               0 47             0.22             0.17             0 29                    0 45  102              0 45             0.24             0  17             0.35                   0.48  115       0.45      0.29      0.20      0 32         0.45  140      0 47      0 24      0 22      0.29         0 43  G4                      0              0.47             0  23             0  18             0  30                   0.64  6      0 47      0.23      0 19      0.30         0.60  13      0.47      0 24      0.19      0 28         0.59  21               0  48             0  22             0  17             0  31                    0.59  31               0.48             0  20             0  17             0.30                   0.61  42               0.50             0  20             0  16             0.27                    0.66  57       0 50      0 20      0.14      0.29         0.72  69      0 40      0.20      0.15      0 33         0.73  81       0 48      0 20      0 16      0.24         0.68  96      0 47      0_23      0.17      0 29         0.59  G5          0       0 45      0.25      0.16      0.31         0.63  8               0  48             0.24             0  16             0  40                   0  63  18      0 48      0.23      0.14      0 38         0 62  30      0.47      0.25      0.15      0.36         0.62  42               0.45             0  24             0.15             0.31                    0.61  52      0 51      0.23      0.17      0.32         0 59  65               0 45             0.25             0.16             0.31                   0  59  73              0.47             0 24             0.15             0.37                    0 48  85              0  47             0.23             0.14             0  39                    0.54  100              0.49             0.22             0.12             0.40                   0.55  120              0.47             0.21             0.13             0.35                    0  56    *' (1) ratios from the 10--125 #m, &gt; 2.96 g cm-3 fraction; (2) ratio from coarse silt (5--20  #m) fraction, (3) ratio from sand (s) and coarse silt (cs) fractions.    233  TABLE II  Ratios of omdes from various size and density fractions of soils from Shingle House  Creek* 1    Profile   Depth    Ratios of oxides.  (cm)      Y203      ZrO2      P~Os      ZrO~ cs      TiO~ s  ZrO2      TiO2      TiO2      T102 cs      TIO2 cs  10-1               x 10-1  (1)     (1)     (1)     (2)       (3)    S1          0        1.45      0 23      0 31      0.47         0.56  10        0.53      0 35      0.27      0.44         0.50  20        0.50      0.35      0 26      0.48         0.52  30        0.47      0.35      0.33      0.47         0.50  50         --         --         --        0.43         0 41  70        0.67      0.26      0 82      0.39         0.43  90        0.62      0.25      0.73      0.38         0.43  $2                    0                 0 54             0.28             0.49             0.31                   0  55  8        0.48      0.27      0 50      0 37         0.47  20        0.63      0.21      0 39      0.35         0 57  30                 0.86             0,17             0.27             0.40                   0 55  42        0 50      0.29      0.73      0 38         0.62  52        0.53      0.29      0 22      0.40         0.62  60                 0.52             0.31             0.19             0.38                   0.61  70        0.56      0.30      0.24      0.41         0 58  90        0.51      0.29      0.15      0.42         0.62  $3         0        0 50      0.30      0 21      0.54         0 57  7        0.48      0.30      0 21      0.59         0.55  17        0.51      0.29      0 18      0.60         0 54  28        0.50      0.24      0.16      0 48         0.56  38        0.54      0.23      0.20      0.44         0 56  48        0.54      0.25      0.17      0 37         0.63  68        0.54      0.25      0.15      0.43         0 58  88                    --                  --                  --              0.44                   0  58    1 (1) ratios from the 10---125 um,&gt; 2.96 g cm-3 fraction, (2) ratio from coarse silt  (5--20 urn) fraction; (3) ratio from sand (s) and coarse silt (cs) fraction.    the A horizon. Because the elemental ratios derived from the heavy mineral  fraction axe constant, the higher ZrO2:TiO2 ratios may be caused by a  breakdown of weatherable minerals of silt size in the light fraction (&lt; 2.96 g  cm-3). These minerals may contain titanium either as part of their mineralog-  real structure or as micro-inclusions of rutile and anatase which axe released  on breakdown.  The ratios for the Nowra sequence show only minor differences, similar to  those for Gooromon Ponds (Table III). Rsd's both within and between pro-  files for all ratios, axe &lt; 20% with the exception of the ZrO2 : T102 ratio of  N1. Each profile can be considered as having been formed from a mineralogi-  cally slmilax parent material.    234    TABLE III  Ratios of oxides from various size and denstty fractions of sods from Nowra Creek.1    Profile   Depth  (cm)    Ratios of oxides'  Y2 03     ZrO~      P20s      ZrO2 cs      TIO2 s  ZrO2      TiO:      TiO:      TiO2 cs      TIO2 cs  10-~               10-~  (1)     (1)     (1)     (2)       (3)    N1           0       0.25      0 46      0.72      0.40         0.61  5       0.23      0 48      0.74      0 53         0.63  18              0.26             0.30             0  92             0.40                   0.61  32              0.24             0.41             0.81             0.41                   0.59  45       0.24      0.30      0 86      0.33         0.52  55  .....  N2                     0              0.25             0 28             0.97             0.39                   0.56  7              0.24             0.28             0.92             0.37                   0.60  20       0.23      0.33      0.82      0 36         0.59  30       0.24      0.29      0 84      0.39         0.58  41              0.22             0  30             0.92             0 41                   0.63  50              0 23             0.30             0.78               --                        --  60       0.23      0 29      0 83      0.41         0.51  N3                     0              0.21             0.31             0,72             0.40                   0 58  10              0.24             0.27             0.75             0.45                   0.58  25       0.26      0.24      0.78      0.41         0 57  35       0_27      0.24      0.80      0.39         0.57  50       0.23      0.31      0.67      0.43         0.51  70              0.22             0.32             0.61               --                        --  90       0.22      0.35      0.72      0 42         0.44  N4                     0              0.20             0.37             0.54             0.35                   0.43  5       0.21      0.34      0.58      0.47         0.40  17       0.22      0.30      0 67      0.49         0.44  30       0.21      0.30      0 75      0.47         0.45  40       0.24      0.28      0.86      0 26         0.41  60       0.23      0.26      0.85      0.43         0.47  80       0.24      0.25      0.75       --            --  120       0.24      0.24      0 78      0.39         0.54    *~ (1) ratios from the 10--125 ~m, &gt; 2.96 gcm-3 fraction; (2) ratio from coarse silt (5--20  urn) fraction; (3) ratio from sand (s) and coarse silt (cs) fraction.    Differences in the Hawkesbury sequence are somewhat greater than those  of the other three sequences but, with the exception of the P2Os: TiO2  ratio for H2 and H4, rsd's are &lt; 25%. The variations in the P2Os : TiO: ratio  are probably due to sampling and analytical error (because of the extremely  low phosphorus values) in H2 and a combination of analytical error and  weathering in H4. Between-profile rsd's (with the exception of P:Os : TiO2 )  indicate that lithological differences in the parent material were not great  and the five soils can be considered part of a chronosequence.    235  TABLE IV  Ratios of oxides from various size and density fractions of soils from Hawkesbury River*'    Profile   Depth  (cm)    Ratios of oxides:  Y203      ZrO2      P,OI      ZrO~ cs      T102 s  ZrO2      T10~      TiO2      TiO2 cs      T102 cs  I0-'                 I0-'  (I)     (1)     (1)     (2)       (3)    H1                   15              0.29             0.25             0.63             0.03                   0_50  40        --         --         --        0.03         0.52  58       0.24      0.23      0_64       --            --  90       0.37      0 25      0.73      0 02         0.47  H2          0       0.23      0 24      0.63      0.03         0.42  15       0_24      0 28      0.59      0 03         0.53  30       0_29      0.23      0.32      0.03         0 54  67       0.25      0.24      0 28      0.03         0 44  88              0.21             0  29             0.17               --                        --  110      0.27      0 24      0.28      0 03         0.35  150       0.23      0.26      0 34      0.03         0.29  H3          0       0 18      0 34      0.18      0 04         0.34  18       0 19      0.33      0.15      0 04         0 33  32              0.19             0  32             0.15             0.04                   0  34  48              0  19             0.35             0.20             0.04                   0  35  90                --                  --                  --                0~04                   0  39  120       0 20      0.30      0.22       --            --  150                --                  --                  --                0  03                   0.41  H4          0       0.20      0 39      0 18      0.03         0 44  11       0 19      0.32      0.16      0.03         0.43  23        --         --         --        0.03         0.40  70       0.23      0.23      0.23      0.03         0.39  130       0.25      0.25      0.24      0 04         0.41  H5                     0              0  15             0 48             0.14             0.04                   0_24  25       0 16      0.48      0.14      0 05         0 20  35              0  14             0.47             0.17             0 03                   0 23  80       0.16      0.40      0.21      0.02         0.36  130       0.16      0 31      0.38      0 02         0 31    ,1 (1) ratios from the 10--125 urn, &gt; 2.96 g cm-3 fraction, (2) ratio from coarse silt  (5--10 urn) fraction, (3) ratio from sand (s) and coarse silt (cs) fraction.    In general there is less variability m the Y203 : ZrO2 ratios derived from  the &gt; 2.96 g cm-3 fraction than other ratios. This is an indication that the  minerals xenotxme and zircon are more resistant and immobile and therefore  more reliable indicators of parent material variations than rutile or monazite.  The problem of monazite may also be due to difficulties in analysis as ex-  plained earlier. Some breakdown and release of titanium may account for  the slightly higher rsd's m the ZrO2 : T102 ratios of the silt fraction and  TiO2 sand :TiO2 silt ratios.    236  TABLE V  Means (m) and relative standard deviations (r, %) of the oxide ratios of various fractions  from the soils of the four sequences    Profile  Y,O3           ZrO2           p20s           ZrO2 cs       TiO~ s  ZrO2           TiO2           TiO=           TiO= cs       TiO2 cs  (x lO-')                (lO-')    m     r      m     r      m     r      m     r      m     r    Gooromon Ponds  G1      0 43    2.3   0.36   13.9   0.22    4.6   0.31    5,2   0.56    8.8  G2      0.46    4.4   0 20   10,0   0 16   12.5   0.31    5 6   0 68    5 3  G3             0 46         4.3      0.24       16.7       0.17       11.8       0.31         7.1       0.54      24.4  G4             0  47         6.4      0.22         9.1       0  17       11.8      0,29         8.4      0.64         8.5  G5      0.47    4.3   0 24    4.2   0.15    6.7   0.35   10.5   0.58    8 1  All  profiles 0.46    4.4   0.25   24.0   0.17   17_7   0.32   10 9   0.59   15 0    Shingle House Creek  S1       0.56   15.0   0.31   16.8   0.48   56.4   0.44    9.1   0.48   11 6  S2      0.57   20.5   0.27   17 3   0.35   54.3   0.38    8,9   0,58    8 5  $3       0 52    4.7   0 27   11.1   0.18   13.5   0.49   16.8   0.57    4.8  All  profiles 0.55   15.9   0.28   16.3   0.33   62.7   0.43   16.4   0 55   11.3    Nowra Creek  N1      0.24    4.8   0.39   22.0   0,31   12.3   0.41   17.6   0.59    7.2  N2      0.23    4.2   0.30    5.7   0.26    5.3   0.39    5.2   0.58    7.0  N3      0.24    9.3   0.29   14 6   0.21   11.1   0.42    5.1   0.54   10 4  N4      0.22    7 3   0.29   15.5   0.21    9.8   0.41   20.0   0.45   10.4  All  profiles, 0.23    7.2   0.31   19 4   0.24   19.2   0.41   12.2   0.53   13.9    Hawkesbury River  H1      0.30   21 9   0 24    4.8   0.67    8.2   0.24    4.8   0.50    5.0  H2      0.25   10.8   0.25    9.2   0 47   59.7   0.25    9.2   0 43   22.9  H3      0.19    3.7   0.33    5.8   0.18   17.1   0.33    5.8   0.36    9.0  H4      0,21   12.0   0.29   22.1   0.21   16 4   0.29   22.1   0.41    5.1  H5      0.15    6.0   0.43   17.2   0.21   47.8   0.43   17.2   0.27   24.2  All  profiles 0,22   23.8   0.31   25.6   0.30   62.0   0,31   25.6   0.39   23.3    m = mean; r = relative standard deviation (%).    Studies by Khangarot et al. (1971) and Drees and Wilding (1978) of the  distribution of elements in the light (&lt;~ 2.89 gcm-3) and heavy mineral frac-  tions have thrown doubt on the validity of assigning elemental percentages  to specific minerals. Not all the heavy minerals may be in the denser fraction  (in this case the fraction ~&gt; 2.96 g cm-3). Both light and heavy fractions were    237    assayed for z~rconmm, titanium, yttrium and phosphorus to check if there  had been a 'clean' separation. Results showed that there is little, if any heavy  mineral present in the light fraction. What little there is may be part of the  crystal structure of other minerals but in no way effects the conclusions.  In the following sections of this paper it will be assumed that all profiles  were formed in an Initially uniform parent material.    Weathering    Changes in the ratios in the coarse silt fraction (5--20 pm) of iron, cal-  cium and sodium to zirconium were used as indices of the degree of chemi-  cal weathering. Depth functions of the three ratios for each soil are present-  ed graphically.  In the Gooromon Ponds sequence (Fig. 1) there is little difference be-  tween the depth functions of the G1, G3 and G4 profiles in spite of the  development of a texture contrast profile in G4 (8% clay in the A horizon,  22% in the B). In G5 the ratios are less throughout the profile in compari-  son to the younger soils. The decrease is most marked m the A horizon in-  dicating that weathering and mobllisatlon of iron, sodium and calcium are  more intense in this part of the profile. The development of a bleached A2  horizon has accompanied this weathering.  Ratms for the Shingle House Creek (Fig. 2) and Nowra Creek (Fig. 3) se-  quences show similar trends with age of profile as Gooromon Ponds, al-    00    EO    40  Depth  (cm}  60    80    I00    120    140    CeO ZrOz  2     4           8    [0   12   14  r   i   1   r   1   i   "1  ,     J  ,    J  il} --     ....  G4  J  /           i  \  \  \    NazO ZrO~  \  /  ;  ./    t  /  /  /  /  /    Fe203 ZrO2  0,246,?,0  "ii)  ,.~  \/  /      :  \  \  \  \  \  \,    F,g. 1 Depth functions of the ratios, CaO:ZrO2, Na20.ZrO2, Fe203"ZrO~ for the 5--20  urn fraction of soils of the Goorornon Ponds sequence.    238    Depth  Icm)    CoO ZrO2  2   4   6   8  i0  12  r   i   ,   ,   ,   ,  ,    /  401  60           ~ ~\  i     "/  801             /~"  t[/  /l:/  pO0  --   33  P20    No20 ZrO2  L  \  /   i  \  )  I  /,    Fe2Q3 ZrO2  /          t//  /  ',,             ///  /'\  /          "\  \             ,     /            "  }'                     \    Fig. 2. Depth functions of the ratios, CaO:ZrO,, Na=O:ZrO,, Fe20~ZrO2 for the 5--20  #m fraction of soils of the Shingle House Creek sequence.    Deplh  (c.~)    20    12C  1401    CoO ZrO2  [   I~   6   8   I0  12  14  r6  f   i   i   i   i   ,  "~    J      !  (         /  \      K,  "\    --- N,  N4    00  20    Na20 ZrO2  \  IL  I  h  t    Fe203 Zr 02  2   4   6   I~   tO  12  0    1   r   i   ,   ~   i  2040       ~//""'\        ~/I~  3  60  80  I00  120    Fig. 3. Depth functions of the ratios, CaO:ZrO~, Na20:ZrO2, Fe203.ZrO2 for the 5--20  .m fraction of soils of the Nowra Creek sequence   though the differences in ratios between $3 and N4 and the younger mem-  bers of their respective sequences are not as marked even though $3 and N4  have stronger textural differentiation than G5 (for 83 % clay in the A hori-  zon is 9 and in the B horizon 37%; N4 % clay in the A horizon is 8 and in  the B horizon 43%). Weathering in-situ appears to have been less intense.  The increase in iron at the base of $1 may be due to lateral movement of  iron and deposition around silt and sand grains. Iron concretions of silt and  sand size were observed in thin section.    239    In the Hawkesbury sequence there is a difference in the depth functions  between ratios with time (Figs. 4, 5, 6). There is a sharp drop m the Na20.  ZrO2 ratio of H5 m the A1 and A2 horizons. The Fe203 :ZrO2 ratios are re-  latively constant with depth for H1, H2 and H3 but there is a very high value  in the B3 horizon of H4. This IS due to the formation of sesquloxlde concre-  tions in sltu, an explanation whmh accounts for simdarly high values m the  B horizon of H5. The ratios show more variability than the other sequences.  Analytical error may account for this. ZrO2 concentrations are one tenth  the values m other sequences (mean ZrO2 is 0.04% compared to 0.4% for  Nowra Creek).  If weathering in sltu were to account for the clay enrichment m the B  horizons of the older soils of these sequences then there should be decreases  In ratios in the B horizons compared to the A and C horizons. This would  indicate the loss of weatherable minerals in those horizons and the forma-  tion of clay from the weathering products. Furthermore, this decrease  should be more pronounced the older the profile. The results show no such  trend. In the older profiles (G4, $3, N4) there is a decrease m the A horizon  showing more intense weathering. If this process has produced some of the  clay of the B horizon, then a combinatmn of the processes of weathering  and llluviatlon is necessary to account for the clay enrichment. On the basis    Oepth  (cm)    0  20    40    60    80    I00    120    2   4  I  f  I   ,  s  I   ,J  1   ,'  /  J  r'H~ \    /  140          ~  1601           1    CaO  ZrO2  6     B     I0    12    14    16     18    20    22   24  I    ,    1    I    r    I    J        I  '\  /  /  H4                                   I  \                 / H2  \ \H~     /  -../  ,//, &gt;  ,/  /  /    Fig. 4 Depth functions of the ratio CaO:ZrO2 for the 5--20 um fraction of soils of the  Hawkesbury River sequence.    240    Depth  (cm)    20    40    60    BO    IO0    120    ,4ol    160    8  IO  ~2  14  16  r    ,   r   ,    ,    i  /  /  "\   /  /  .x,  ,   \  ,   )  /  \\  /  \\,    No20 ZrO2  18       20     22      24      2.6      28      30      32      34  n    v   ,    r    r    I    ,    r  .'~  .///    Fig. 5. Depth functions of the ratio Na~O:ZrO~ for the 5--20 ~m fraction of soils of the  Hawkesbury River sequence    20    40    60    L.._    H3    k  I00            I  h  i  120             LI  q  q  t  140                 I  I  /  160                   l    Depth  (crn)    Fe203 Zr02  I0                  20                  30                 40  i  /  2     'N4                                                "\ .  /                             ~  /                      1  /  /                            /    Fng. 6. Depth functions of the ratio Fe203:ZrO2 for the 5--20 ~m fraction of soils of the  Hawkesbury River sequence    241    of these criteria this mechamsm can be of only relatively minor significance  because texture contrast has already developed in younger profiles (e.g., G3,  N3) prior to any obvious change in the rahos. The weathering indices pro-  vide no evidence that weathering in situ makes a significant contribution to  the development of texture contrast.    Loss and gain of constituents    All calculations of changes in volume and weight of the present soil com-  pared to the parent material were made for a column of soil having dimen-  sions equal to an area of 1 cm2 and length equal to the thickness of the par-  ticular horizon. All calculations were based on bulk density measurements  at-1/3 bar water potential.  Values of losses and gains are critically dependent on the choice of the  stable constituent. Of the five considered, the acid resistant fraction was  chosen because it constituted a large proportion of the whole sample and    TABLE VI    Losses and gains in volume and weight for selected horizons of three soils of the Gooro-  mon Ponds sequence    Prohle    Horizon    Volume          Relative   Weight        Relative  change           volume    change        weight  (cm3/h/cm2).1   change     (g/h/cm2)*l   change  (%)               (%)    G3    G4    G5    All           4 1               51.4         2.0           16.2  A12           4 0               49.4         2 6           20.3  B21           3.1               53 0         1 0           10 7  IIC1          0.4                4.0       -0.2          -1 2  IIC2          0.1                1.5       -0.2          -1 1  IIC3        -1 1                8 0       -1.8          -8 0  Summahon  12.1                9.4       -2.2          -1 1    All         -1.0             -14 2       -1.9         -17 5  A12         -0.3              -3.9       -0.9          -7.5  A21         -1.1              -12.4       -1 6         -11 3  A22         -2.1              -17 2        -2.5         -13.0  B1           -0.1               -0 7         1 0            4.3  B2           -1.0               -7.3       -0.4           -2 0  Summation -9.3              -8 8      -10.7          -6.4    A1            0.8               11.2        -1.8         -13.7  A2           -0.I               -0.7        -2.4         -13 2  B21           1 7               16.3         0.3            1.7  B22          2.1              25.7         1.7          12.0  B31          2.0              18.2        0.8           4 0  Summation  15.1              14.4        2 9           1.5    *~ h for horizon.    242    there was good agreement between replicates of each horizon. Slight errors  in analysis can have a pronounced effect on the losses and gains when calcu-  lated on the basis of constituents occurring in very small quantity. For in-  stance the concentration of zirconium and yttrium in the heavy mineral frac-  tion of the 10--125 ~m fraction, expressed as a proportion of the whole  sample, was &lt;: 0.03% by weight whereas the acid resistant fraction was in  the range 50--70%. Titanium in the sand fraction and/or the heavy mineral  fraction was ruled out because of the hkelihood of weathering and mobih-  zation in some of the older profiles.  Changes in weight, volume, clay content and elemental constituents were  calculated for G3, G4 and G5 profiles of the Gooromon Ponds sequence  (Table VI). The increase in volume and weight in the 0--55 cm layer of G3  was offset by a decrease m the 55--140 cm layer such that there was a sta-  tistically insignificant loss in weight and an overall increase in volume of 9%.  Results for G4 are somewhat surprising in view of the fact that it is a profile  of moderate texture-contrast. There is a loss in weight in all horizons except  the top part of the B2 horizon and a small decrease in volume throughout.  It was expected that the lower B horizon would also show an increase m  weight in order to account for the mcrease in clay. There appears to have  been a loss of constituents from the whole profile, particularly the A hori-  zon. In G5 the A horizons show a loss in weight and the B horizons an in-  crease. The net effect is a negligible weight change indicating that soil de-  velopment primarily involves a redistribution of components inherited from    TABLE VII    Losses and gains in volume and weight for selected horizons of two soils of the Shingle  House Creek sequence    Profile    Horizon    Volume          Relative     Weight        Relative  change           volume      change        weight  (cm3/h/cm~).I   change      (g/h/cm2)*l   change  (%)                (%)    $2    $3    All           0.7                 9.7        -0.9            -9 1  A12           1 5               13.9        -0 5            -3.2  A]3           0.9                 9.8        -0 7            -5.1  A3           -0 1               -0.6        -1.4            -8 4  B1          -0.2              -2.4       -0.3           -2.4  Summation   2 8                5.7       -3 8           -5.5    A1            0 2                 2.6        -2.3           -20 2  A2           -1.6              -13.8        -3.4           -17 5  B22           1.4               15.9         2.2            15 2  B3            2.2               27.6         3.5            26.8  B3C          0 1                0.5         1.6             4.8  Summation   3.7                4.4         4.6             3.3    *~ h for horizon.    243    the parent material. The increase m weight of the B horizon has also been  accompanied by a marked volume increase.  Shingle House Creek (Table VII), Nowra Creek (Table VIII) and Hawkes-  bury (Table IX) sequences have similar trends with age of development as  Gooromon Ponds, VlZ., an Initial increase m volume for the highly orgamc  texturally umform and weakly gradational profiles ($2, N2, H2). The pro-  hles with stronger texture-contrast ($3, N4, H4, H5) have marked decreases  In volume and weight accompanymg the loss of clay and A horizon forma-  tion and vice versa for the B horizon but net profile weight and volume  changes are not great (&lt; 10%).  Changes m clay, iron and silica parallel those for weight and show that  formation of the textural profile revolves a net loss of elemental constituents  from the A and a net increase m the B horizon. Two mechamsms may ac-  count for this, vm.: (1) loss of weathering products from the A by lateral  movement and retention in the B -- the clay formation hypothesis; or (2)  movement of clay from surface to subsurface horizons -- the eluvlatlon--lllu-  vlation hypothesis or lesslvage.    TABLE VIII    Losses and gains m volume and weight for selected horizons of three soils of the Nowra  Creek sequence    Profile    Homzon    Volume          Relative     Weight        Relative  change           volume      change        weight  (cm3/h/cm2).1   change      (g/h/cm2)*l   change  (%)                 (%)    N2    All       0.4           5.5      -0 4       -4 4  A12       0.4           3.0      -0 1       -0.5  B(20)      0.4           4.3       0 5        3 6  B(41)      1 2            18       1 5       10 3  Summation   1.6                2.7          0_2          -0.2    N3    A1            2.8               38.2           0 8            7 0  B1            2.3               19 2           1 7            9 1  B21           1.1               11.9           1.5           10 5  B22           1.4               10.2           2.3           10 2  B3            0,5                 2.4           0 8            2.4  C(70)     -0.1           0.4      -0.1       -0 4  Summation   8.0                9 9          7.0           5_3    N4    A1           -1.2              -19.2         -1.7         -17.1  A2           -3.7              -23.4         -4.5         -18.1  B1           -2,1              -13.8         -3.3         -13 8  B2           -0.4               -3.5         -1.6           -9.6  B3           -0 6               -2 7         -3.3         -10 1  C1             1.4                 7.3           0.6            1 9  Summation -5 3              -5 0       -13,1          -7 8    *' h for horizon.    244  TABLE IX  Losses and gains in volume and weight for selected horizons of four soils of the Hawkes-  bury River sequence    Profile   Horizon    Volume          Relative     Weight        Relative  change          volume      change       weight  (cm3/h/cm~)*l   change      (g/h/cm~)     change  (%)                (%)    H2    H3    H4    H5*~    IIA          2.8              22.7          2.9          13.1  IIB1         4.5              26.0         4.8          15.5  IIB21        4.7              29.1         5 3          18.3  IIB31        2.9              10.6         4.0           8.2  Summation  24.2              20 3        28.9          13.4    A1                      -2.4                            -11.9                   -4.2                   -11  9  A3          -1 5              -9.6        -2.6          -9.6  B1                      -1.6                               -9.0                   -2.9                      -9.5  B21                    -1.6                               -6.9                   -2  0                      -4.8  B23       0.5           2 4       0         0  Summation -6.6             -6.8       -11.7          -7 0    A1           -2.0              -15 7         -4 1         -19.3  B21           2.1               21.5           3.1           19.3  B22          2.8               16.2          4.8          16.9  B23          1.7                6.7          3.3           8.0  B3            1.0                3 3          1 9           3.9  Summation   5.8                4 7         10.6           5,2    A1           -2.6               20.8         -5.3         -25.6  A21         -4.7             -32.0        -6.3         -26.2  B21          10.4               71.4         16.1           67.2  B22           7.3               57.3         13.7           65.9  BC                         4.9                               98.5                   23.2                      93.6    *~ h for horizon.  *~ Changes in H5 were calculated from the parent material of  of H5 was not sampled.    H4 because parent material    Clay mzgration and clay formation    Weight changes due to clay migration and clay formation were calculated  for the older members of each sequence. In the case of N4, particle-size and  micro-morphological evidence indicated that there was input of fine clay in-  to the upper C horizon. The value for the clay percentage which was chosen  for calculation was the value for the parent material of N2. This was deemed  justifiable on the grounds that resistant mineral studies had shown that the  profiles had formed from similar parent materials. Losses and gains could not  be calculated for H5 because the lower B and C horizons were not sampled.  Results of all sequences show that the major cause of the loss of weight    245    m the A and the gain in the B is due to clay migration. The contribution of  clay from chemical weathering of minerals increases, however, with age, ini-  tially in the A horizon (cf. G4, G5) and then throughout the whole profile.  In the case of N4, approximately 30% of the gain of clay m the B2 is the re-  sult of clay formation.  Losses and gains of the elements iron, silicon, and potassmm follow the  trends observed with changes m weight (Table X). Changes are predominant-  ly the outcome of migration. Because weathering is not a slgmficant factor  until the profiles have developed dlstmct horizonatlon, much of the elemen-  tal redistribution must have been by clay movement, i.e., lesslvage (Rode,  1964). In a number of the older profiles (G5, N4, H3, H4) clay formation  has led to a loss of potassium.  Following deposition of the parent material, the clay moves downward.  Clay is also lost from the profile entirely, probably by lateral movement (see  weight change of $2 m Table VII). The quantities translocated, however, are  relatively minor probably because of the homogenisation by soil fauna.  There is a marked increase in the amount of llluviation if the profile is on a  terrace which is only infrequently flooded, or not at all. As the textural con-  trast between A and B horizons becomes more marked, the internal hydrol-  ogy of the profile is altered in such a way that water percolates more freely  through the A than the B horizon. This means that the top of the B and bot-  tom of the A are subject to waterlogging for progressively longer periods of  time during the winter and spring. The reducing conditions which are a con-  sequence of this lead to an increase in weathering. Thus the contributmn to  the profile texture by the process of clay formation is manifest initially m  the A2 horizon. The texture-contrast becomes more pronounced as a result  of the combined effects of migration and weathering leading to a further in-  crease in the length of the period of saturation, more prolonged reducing  conditions and thus further mineral breakdown. This is a feedback process  (Torrent and Nettleton, 1978) produced entirely by intrinsic morphological  changes.    CONCLUSION    The ratios of heavy minerals have small differences within each profile, in-  dicating that texture-contrast in the older members must be due to processes  other than stratification. Furthermore, the soils in each sequence have been  formed from similar parent materials. Thus the soil forming factor, parent  material, has been effectively constant.  From reconstruction of gains and losses of constituents it was concluded  that the major cause of loss of weight m the A horizon and gain in the B is  clay migration. The contribution of clay from chemmal weathering of min-  erals increases with age, however, initially in the A horizon and then  throughout the whole profile. Chemical weathering is more the result of tex-  tural differentiation than its cause.    246  TABLE X  Losses and gains of oxideA due to clay formation (F) and clay migration (M) as a result of  soil formation (g/100 g parent material)    Profile    Horizon     F%O+            SiO2              K~O    M      F       M      F       M      F    Gooromon Ponds  G4       All         -I 1    -0.4    -5.8      1.7    -0 4     0.2  A21         -1.1    -0.3    -6 0      1.1    -0.4     0.2  A32         -1.0    -0.4    -5.4    -0,6    -0.3     0.2  B1            0.5    -0.6     2 4    -2.5     0.1      0.2  B2            0.7    -0.9      3.5      2,6     0.2    -0.1  G5       A1          -0.7      0.1    -6.6     6.9    -0.7    -0.2  A2          -0.5    -0,1    -4.7    13.1    -0.5    -0.2  B21          1.6      1,2    14.6      3.4      1.6    -1.4  B22          1.2      1.2    10.9      1 8      1,2    -1.2  B31          0.8      0.9     7.8      2.8      0.8    -0.9  Shingle House Creek  S1        A12         -0.1      0.7    -0.9    -1.7    -0.1      0  A13         -0.1      0.5    -0,9    -2.8    -0,1      0  B1          -0.1      0.9    -0.9     2.3    -0,1      2.4  $2       A1          -2.4    -0 7    -8.8     0.6    -0.4    -0.4  A2          -1.8    -1.1    -6.7      0.4    -0.3    -0.3  B21          0.1    -1.2      0.3     0.4     0       0.1  B22          2 3    -0.3     8.4    -0.3     0.4     0.4  B3           2.7     1.0     9.8    -0 1     0.4     0.5  Nowra Creek  N3       A1         -0.2    -0.2    -1.1    -2.0     0       0.1  B1           0       0.2     0.2    -0.4     0       0  B22          0.3    -0.2     1.3    -2.2     0 1     0.1  N4        A1           -0.4      1.4    -2.5     13.8    -0.1    -0.1  A2            0.1      2.9      0.7     31.9      0      -0.1  B1           -3.4      9.8     21.5     38.5      0.6    -0.3  B2            5.9      2,7     37.3     35.4      1 0    -0.1  B3           5.3     2.9    33.8    37.4     0.9    -0.1  Hawkesbury River  H3        A1           -1.7      0.3    -9.5     36.1    -0.5      0.4  A3            4.4    -4.3     24.7     45.6      1.3    -0.6  B1            5.4    -4.6     30.7     36.9      1.6    -0.8  B21           0.9    -0.9      4.8      4.6      0.3    -0.2  H4        A1           -1.8      4.0    -9.1     16.0    -0.6    -0.2  B21          3.9      3.1    19.1    13.0      1.2    -0.7  B22          5.3      1.6    26.3    11.0      1.6    -0.6  B3            0.8      0.5      3.8    -3.5      0.2    -0.2    247    The elemental chemistry of the softs is consistent with the partmle-slze  and micromorphologlc data presented m the two other papers (Parts I and  II) and the results lead to the following general conclusions.  Differences m the parent sediments were not responsible for the develop-  ment of texture contrasts between A and B horizons in the older soils of  each sequence.  Although iron segregatmn commences soon after the deposition of sedi-  ment, chemical weathering plays a minor role in the initial development of  texture-contrast.  Clay flluvlation is the most slgmficant process responsible for texture dif-  ferentiation.    REFERENCES    Akhtyrstev, B P., 1968. Removal and accumulation of oxides m so,ls of broadleaf forests  m the central Russian Forest Steppe. Soy. Soil Sci., 1968, pp. 1423--1434.  Barshad, I , 1965. Chemistry of soil development. In: F.E Bear (Editor), Chemistry of  the Soil Reinhold, New York, N Y , pp. 1--70.  Beavers, A.H., Fehrenbacher, J.B., Johnson, P.R. and Jones, R.L., 1963. CaO--ZrO2  molar ratios as an index of weathering. Soil Scl Soc Am. Proc., 27 : 408--412.  Bhattacherya, N, 1963. Weathering of glacial tills in Indiana II Heavy minerals. J. Sedi-  ment. Petrol., 33: 789--794.  Bourne, W C and Whiteside, E.P., 1962. A study of the morphology and pedogenesis o1~  a medial chernozem developed in loess. Soll Scl. Soc. Am. Proc., 26. 484--490  Brasher, B.R., Franzmeier, D.P., Valassls, V. and Davidson, S.E., 1966. Use of Saran resin  to coat natural soft clods for bulk density and water retention measurements. Soil Sci,  101 : 108.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Krieger, New York, N.Y., 482 pp  Chapman, S.L. and Horn, M.E , 1968, Parent material uniformity and origin of silty soils  in northwest Arkansas based on zircomum--tltanmm contents. Soil Sc, Soc Am.  Proc., 32' 265--271.  Chlttleborough, D.J. and Oades, J.M , 1980. The development of a Red-brown earth, III,  The degree of weathering and translocation of clay. Aust. J. Soil Res., 18. 383--393  Chlttleborough, D.J., Walker, P.H. and Oades, J.M, 1984. Textural differentiation in  chronosequences from eastern Australia, I. Description, chemical propertms and micro-  morphology of soils. Geoderma, 32 : 181--202  Drees, L.R. and Wilding, L P., 1978. Elemental distribution m the light mineral isolate of  soil separates Soil Sci Soc. Am. J., 42" 976--978  Evans, L.J  and Adams, W.A., 1975. Quantitative pedological studies on so,Is derived  from Siluman mudstones, IV. Umformity of parent material and evaluation of internal  standards. J. Soil. Sci., 26' 319--326  Foss, J.E and Rust, R.H., 1968. Soil genesis study of a hthologm discontinuity in glac,al  drift in Western Wisconsin Soil ScL Soc. Am. Proc., 32:393--398.  Hardy, F and Follet-Smith, R.R., 1931. Studies in tropical softs, II. Some characteristics  of igneous rock soil profiles in British Guiana, South America. J. Agric. ScL, 21: 739--  761.  Khangarot, A.S., Wildmg, L P. and Hall, G.F., 1971. Compositmn and weathering of  loess-mantled Wisconsin and Illinoan-age terraces in central Ohio. Soil Sci_ Am. Proc,  35- 621--626.  Mitchell, W A., 1975 Heavy minerals. In J.E. Gmseking (Editor), Soil Components, Vol  2. Inorganic Constituents. Springer Verlag, New York, N.Y    248    Murad, E., 1978. Yttrium and zirconium as geochemical guide elements in soil and stream  sediment sequences. J. Soil Sci., 29- 219---223.  Norrish, K. and Hutton, J.R., 1969. An accurate X-ray spectrographic method for the  analysis of a wide range of geological samples. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 33: 431--  453.  Rode, A.A., 1984. Podzolisation and lessivage. Soy. Soil Sci., 660--671.  Ruhe, R.V., 1956. Geomorphic studies and the nature of soils. Soil Sci. 92: 441--455.  Smith, M. and Wilding, L.P., 1972. Genesis of argillic horizons in oehraqualfs derived  from fine textured till deposits of north western Ohio and south eastern Michigan  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 808--815.  Sudom, M.D. and Arnaud, R.J.St., 1971. Use of quartz, zirconium and titanmm as m-  dices in pedological studies. Can. J. Soil Sci., 51' 385--396.  Torrent, J. and Nettleton, W.D., 1978 Feedback processes in soil genests. Geoderma, 20:  281--287.  Wilding, L.P., Drees, L R., Smeck, N.E. and Hall, G.F., 1971. Mineral and elemental  composition of Wisconsin-age till deposits in west central Ohio. In: R.P. Goldthwaite  (Editor), Till -- A Symposium. Ohio State Univ. Press, Ohio, pp. 290--317                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractProportions of resistant heavy minerals, zircon, rutile and ilmenite, xenotime and monazite, in the fraction &gt; 2.96 g cmt3 were estimated by X-ray fluorescent spectroscopic measurement of the elements zirconium, titanium, yttrium and phosphorus, respectively. Ratios of these elements in various fractions in soils of four terrace sequences showed statistically insignificant changes with depth, thus ruling out sedimentary layering as an explanation for textural differences. Formation of clay by more intense chemical weathering of coarse minerals in the B horizon was discounted on the basis of constant ratios of Fe2O3:ZrO2, Na2O:ZrO2 and CaO:ZrO2 in the silt fraction. In the oldest members of several sequences there was evidence of chemical weathering but moderate to strong textural contrast was already apparent in younger profiles. Calculations of losses and gains on the basis of the tri-acid resistant fraction of whole soil samples provided further strong evidence for the predominant role played by clay translocation and the minor contribution to the clay fraction of clay formation in place except in the oldest soils. It was concluded that clay illuviation was the main mechanism responsible for textural differentiation with weathering in situ playing a minor, albeit with time, an increasingly important role. 