Geoderma, 30 (1983) 277--283                                                     277  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    THE CHARACTERIZATION OF MICROPOROSITY IN A PLOUGHPAN  BY SUBMICROSCOPIC AND QUANTIMET TECHNIQUES    A. JAGER, O. BOERSMA and E.B.A. BISDOM  Netherlands Sod Survey Institute, P O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Jager, A., Boersma, O. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1983. The characterization of microporosity  in a ploughpan by submicroscopic and Quantimet techniques. Geoderma, 30:277--283    Ploughpans are usually recognizable in thin sections because of their massiveness  (density) when compared with adjacent parts of the soil. When pores can be measured in  the ploughpan such massiveness can be documented and compared with the porosity of  the underlying soil profile. Such measurements, however, concern only meso- and macro-  pores when done by Quantimet on micrographs obtained with the light microscope. This  is due to the thickness of the thin section and the necessity to work with transmitted  light. The measurement of the smaller mesopores may also be problematic with the light  microscopy--Quantimet t~echnique.  The introduction of backscattered electron scanning images allows to obtain micro-  graphs of a very thin layer and this made it possible to measure micro- and mesopores by  Quantimet. If only small magnifications are used, macropores can also be measured.  In the present investigation, micro- and mesopores were quantified by a combination  of backscattered electron and Quantimet techniques and the macropores by light micro-  scopy and Quantimet. It was demonstrated that macro- and mesopores were less frequent  in a ploughpan than outside, whereas capillary or micropores increased somewhat.    INTRODUCTION    Soil compaction leading to the formation of ploughpans (Fig. 1) is a sig-  nificant problem in sandy loams of arable land from areas with river- and sea  clays. It is usually caused by soil tillage when the soil is too wet. This may  give puddling and compaction of the soil materials underneath the furrow to  form a ploughpan. The soil compaction, however, is not only caused by ma-  chines under humid conditions but can also be influenced by the degree of  structure stability which itself is, amongst other things, dependent on the  clay and humus content. Field and micromorphological observations have  also shown that intensive arable farming may lead to a decrease in the activi-  ty of soil organisms coupled with a degradation of soil structure.  The characterization of compaction in a soil can be done by a comparison  of the porosities in compacted and looser parts of the same soil using light  microscopic and Quantimet techniques (Jongerius et al., 1972, Jongerius,    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    278    Ftg 1 Lacquer peel of sandy loam with a ploughed horizon (1), a ploughpan (2) and an  undisturbed soil horizon with shells (3).    279    1974; Ismail, 1975). However, only pores with diameters larger than 30 ~m  can be analysed, because transmitted light is used and the thickness of a thin  section frequently approaches this value. Consequently, only mesopores with  dmmeters from 30 pm to 100 pm and macropores with diameters larger than  100 um can be analysed. Mlcropores, capillary pores with diameters smaller  than 30 pro, need to be measured with a Quantlmet on micrographs which  are obtained with a submicroscopic technique.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) (Bisdom and Thiel, 1981)  can be used to characterize micro-, meso-and macropores (Jongerlus and  Bisdom, 1981). With this submicroscopic technique, predommantly micro-  pores and mesopores are studied by Quantlmet. The instrument used was a  Jeol-JSM-35C equipped with a backscattered electron detector of the semi-  conductor type comprising two solid state detectors. The smallest diameter  of pores measured in this study was 3 ~m.  A Quantimet 720 image analyzer equipped with a light microscope and  an epidiascope, was used to study negative film obtained with a scanning  electron microscope (SEM). The film was the negative of Polaroid P/N which  also provided paper prints. During Quantimet study of the negatives BESI  were portrayed on the display screen and the porosity was measured.  BESI are obtained from a thin layer at predominantly some mmrometres  depth below the surface of the thin section. Backscattered electrons from  nearer-to-surface parts of the thin section are also involved but the main  image is obtained from a small depth in the thin section. The signal is de-  rived from a thin layer which is a few mlcrometres thick. This layer is usually  situated deeper m plastic-impregnated pores than in minerals. Such a thin  layer allows Quantimet measurements of even very small pores, dependent  on the magnification used to obtain BESI and the type of material whmh is  analysed.  In the present study, both capillary pores (mlcropores) and mesopores  were measured by Quantlmet from BESI, wh:le Quantlmet and light micro-  scopic micrographs were used to obtain porosity figures on macropores.    RESULTS    The characterization of porosities in ploughpans of sandy loams in the  southwest of the Netherlands forms part of a survey in which compaction  phenomena are studied on a number of farms. The aim of this porosity and  structure study is to obtain information which can prevent structure deterio-  ration and improve the structure of compacted soils. This has a direct effect  on the growth of crops.  Ploughpans are usually easy to distinguish from the overlying ploughed  layer and the underlying soil pedon if attention is paid to structure morphol-  ogy (Fig. 1). When only a small amount of clay is present the ploughpan :s    280    frequently rather massive (dense) without structure, or a weakly developed  platy structure can be recognized. If the clay content increases, however,  angular blocky structure elements are common. Most ploughpans are only a  few centimetres thick, but thicknesses up to 15 cm were measured.  The ploughpan in soils with small amounts of clay usually affects water  transport and root penetration more than one m soils with more clay. This  is due to the usually massive structure of the former ploughpan whmh leads    Fig. 2. Backscattered electron scanning image of a small part of the massive ploughpan    Fig. 3. BESI of a small part of the undisturbed and uncompacted soil horizon underneath  the ploughpan.    281    to stagnation of superfluous rainwater and the formation of puddles in the  furrows. Those developed in soils richer in clay usually have the possibility  to form cracks due to swelling and shrinkage of the clay component. This  will not be the case in winter when the soil is swollen but starts during spring.  The result is that an angular blocky structure is formed in the ploughpan.  The present investigation was camed out to obtain BESI-Quantlmet in-  formation on porosities present in the ploughpan itself and in the underlying  more porous part of the soil. Microareas were selected in the massive plough-  pan (Fig. 2) and in the undisturbed soil with a low clay content just under-  neath it (Fig. 3). BESI allowed portrayal of micro-, meso- and macropores.  The latter, however, can be measured better with a combination of light  microscopic and Quantimet techniques because this works faster and is ac-  curate (cf. Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). The results of porosity measure-  ments both m the ploughpan and underneath it are given in Fig. 4. The dif-  ferences m the porosity characteristics between the two are as follows.    Porosity (%)    10-    I  D    Ploughpan    Undisturbed C-material    0                             ,      ,~'l,         I--I  3   6   15  30  100 300 500 1200 3000 (~m)  Pore-d~ameter  Fig. 4. Quantimet measurements of micro-, meso- and macropores from BESI of the  ploughpan and the undisturbed horizon.    282    The undisturbed porous part underneath the ploughpan has macropores,  whereas the largest macropores are absent in the ploughpan and the smaller  macropores have significantly decreased in number. Consequently, most of  the macropores are lost when a massive ploughpan is formed.  Mesopores with diameters of 30 #m to 100 t~m also decrease m the plough-  pan if compared with the underlying undisturbed soil. Mlcropores, in this  case with diameters between 3 pm and 30 um, are present In larger numbers  m the ploughpan. Differences in numbers of mlcropores m the ploughpan  and porous soil are, however, less pronounced than expected.  In the present mvestlgatmn no attention was paid to differences m shapes  of pores and it is, therefore, not yet known which changes m forms occur  during the formation of a massive ploughpan In a sandy loam soft. The reason  for this omission is that we would prefer to study the porosity of a larger  number of ploughpans and underlying soil before figures are given on form  changes of pores during the formation of different types of ploughpans.    CONCLUSIONS    The combination of backscattered electron scanning Images and Quantlmet  measurements has allowed the study of capillary and larger pores. Macro-  pores were measured using light microscopic and Quantimet techniques. It  could be shown that vtrtually no macropores, pores with diameters larger  than 100 pm, remained in the massive ploughpan. Mesopores also decreased  in number, whereas the quantity of pores with diameters between 3 um and  30 pm increased somewhat.  The present combination of light microscopic, submicroscopic and Quan-  timet techmques can be used to study a variety of compaction phenomena m  soils by investigating porosity characteristics. It is important that capillary  pores can also be measured. Pores with diameters less than 3 pm can be  measured with the image analyzer If sufficmnt BESI are made at higher  magnifications. The comparison of the figures on micro-, meso- and macro-  pores will give information on changes m porosity characteristics when soil  is compacted.    REFERENCES    Blsdom, E.B.A. and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-EDXRA  In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Work-  shop of the International Working Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil  Materials (IWGSUM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Docu-  mentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Ismail, S.N.A., 1975. Micromorphometric soil-porosity characterization by means of  electxo-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720). Neth. Soil. Surv_ Inst, Wageningen,  Soil Surv. Pap., 9. 104 pp.    283    Jongerius, A., 1974. Recent developments in soil micromorphology. In: G.K. Rutherford  (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proceedings of the 4th International Working-Meeting on  Soil Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp.  67--83.  Jongerius, A. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981. Porosity measurements using the Quantimet 720  on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In: E.B.A. Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Interna-  tional Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen  Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp. 207--216.  Jongerms, A., Schoonderbeek, D. and Jager, A., 1972. The application of the Quantlmet  720 in soil micromorphology. The Mmroscope, 20: 243--254.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractPloughpans are usually recognizable in thin sections because of their massiveness (density) when compared with adjacent parts of the soil. When pores can be measured in the ploughpan such massiveness can be documented and compared with the porosity of the underlying soil profile. Such measurements, however, concern only meso- and macropores when done by Quantimet on micrographs obtained with the light microscope. This is due to the thickness of the thin section and the necessity to work with transmitted light. The measurement of the smaller mesopores may also be problematic with the light microscopy—Quantimet technique.The introduction of backscattered electron scanning images allows to obtain micrographs of a very thin layer and this made it possible to measure micro- and mesopores by Quantimet. If only small magnifications are used, macropores can also be measured.In the present investigation, micro- and mesopores were quantified by a combination of backscattered electron and Quantimet techniques and the macropores by light microscopy and Quantimet. It was demonstrated that macro- and mesopores were less frequent in a ploughpan than outside, whereas capillary or micropores increased somewhat.