Geoderma, 31(1983) 41--56                                                          41  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CLAY MINERALS AND POTASSIUM STATUS IN SOME SOILS OF  JORDAN    HARBI SHADFAN*  Contribution from the Dept. of Soils and Irrigation, Faculty of Agriculture, University of  Jordan, Amman (Jordan)  (Received June 26, 1981 ; accepted after revision November 1, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Shadfan, H., 1983. Clay minerals and potassium status in some soils of Jordan. Geo-  derma, 31: 41--56.    The physical, chemical and mineralogical characteristics of some soils in the Jordan  Valley (Rift Valley) and the Highland (Irbid-region) were investigated. The soils of the  Highland (Chromoxererts) contained more clay and smectite than those of the Jordan  Valley (Camborthids and Torriorthents). Higher contents of carbonates, salts and mica  were found in the latter. In addition to smectite and mica, interstratified clay minerals  (mica/smectite and smectite/chlorite) and kaolinite were present in the clay fractions of  the soils in the two regions. Soils of the Highland, especially those under higher rainfall  with larger amounts of highly charged smectite, had lower contents of available and total  potassium and higher degrees of potassium fixation than those of the Jordan Valley. Soil  properties such as carbonate, salt and potassium contents and clay mineral composition  were related to the amounts of annual rainfall in soils of the Highland, whereas differ-  ences among the Jordan Valley soils were related to the parent materials, especially the  underlying Lisan Marl.    INTRODUCTION    Limited information is available on properties of the soils of the two agri-  culturally important regions of Jordan, the Highland where annual rainfall  reaches 600 mm and the irrigated parts of the Jordan Valley (Rift Valley)  where annual rainfall is less than 300 mm. More information will be needed  for effective long-time use of these soils. The purpose of this study is there-  fore to determine the mineralogy of the clay fraction, the potassium status,  and some related characteristics of specimen soils from the two regions.    GENERAL NATURE OF STUDY AREAS    Agricultural land use in Jordan is mainly limited to two areas: the High-  *Present address: Faculty of Agriculture, King Saud University, Riyad, Saudi Arabia.    0016-7061]83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    42    land, where annual rainfall is more than 350 mm, is dry-farmed and corn  prises less than 3.5% of the total area in Jordan (98,000 km2), whereas the  Jordan Valley is irrigated and makes up less than 1% of the total area~  Cereals are the main crops in the Highland and vegetables in the irrigated  areas.  Jordan has a semiarid variety of the Mediterranean climate with high tem  peratures and little rain during the summer period (7 months) but is cold and  wet in the winter. The amounts of annual rainfall in the Highland reach  500--600 mm and decrease drastically (within 20 km) towards the desert to  the east and the Jordan Valley to the west. The annual average temperature  is about 18. The climate in the Jordan Valley area is arid with higher tem-  peratures and lower rainfalls than the Highland. The annual rainfall reaches  300 mm in the northern part of the valley near Tiberias Lake (see Fig. 1) and  decreases to less than 100 mm near the Dead Sea. The annual average tem-  perature is about 26.  The Highland is a part of the Transjordan block with an elevation ranging  from about 500 to 1000 m above sea level and is covered mainly with upper  Cretaceous limestone. In the northern part of the block near the Syrian  borders (Fig. 1), Tertiary limestone and Quaternary basalt are exposed  (Bender, 1975). The limestone ranges from hard dolomitic to marly soft  materials. The Jordan Valley is a section (approximately 105 km long and  5--20 km wide) of the East African--Asia Minor Rift system that lies below  sea level, ranging from 212 m at Tiberias Lake in the north to 392 m at the  Dead Sea. Unconsolidated Quaternary and less commonly Miocene and Plio-  cene lacustrine sediments called Lisan marl occupy most of the floor of the  valley. The Lisan marl consists of varve-bedded marl and shale that contain  gypsum and soluble salts. The marl is more calcareous in the north and more  saline in the south near the Dead Sea (Dar A1-Handsah, 1967).  The soils of the Highland were classified as Red Mediterranean soils or  Terra-Rossa-like soils (Moormann, 1959), on the basis of their reddish colors  and carbonate contents throughout their profiles. These soils are formed as  weathering products from limestone and, in some areas, from basalt, with  depth ranges from 40 cm to several metres depending on the slope. They  have high clay and smectite contents and exhibit variable degrees of cracking  during the dry period (Abed E1-Hadi and Badawi, 1973). In the Jordan  Valley, the Ghor soils are formed from colluvial--alluvial materials from the  bordering Highland and from the Lisan marl (Dar Al Handsah, 1967). The  depth of the colluvial--alluvial materials over marl is several metres in the  northern part and about 20--40 cm in the southern part of the valley. The  Ghor--Lisan soils are found along the Jordan River in the transition zone  between the Ghor soils and the Zor soils, which are located 30--60 m below  on the new flood plain of the river. Thus the Ghor--Lisan soils are hilly with  Lisan marl exposed at the surface in many places. Soils in colluvial material  with more than 35% gravel by volume occur in the foothill of the bordering  Highland.    43    I       SYRIA    NORTH  'SHUNA    J2    H4  H5    H3 IRBIO   H:      &lt;~ H2    J3    .LA    TURKEY    SALT    .SOUTH  SHUNA    J5    O  AMMAI~    0  S  1Okra    L [   ae.q   /                 ,' MADABA  Fig. 1. Location map and sampling sites.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Five soil profiles were sampled in the Irbid region of the Highland (see  Fig. 1). Profiles H1, H2 and H3 are over limestone and have annual rainfalls  of 200, 300 and 500 mm, respectively. Profiles H4 and H5 overlie basalt  associated with limestone and have annual rainfalls of 300 and 450 mm. All  profiles are on slopes of less than 3%.    44    Six profiles representing the various soils in the Jordan Valley (Rift  Valley) were studied. Profiles J2, J1 and J3 represent the Ghor soils from  north to south, respectively, where the colluvial--alluvial materials are depo  sited on the Lisan marl. Profile J4 was sampled to represent the Ghor--Lisan  soils where the colluvium is very shallow or the marl outcrops. Profile J5  represents the gravelly softs in the foothills and profile J6 the new flood-  plain of the Jordan River (Zor soils). Profiles J1, J2, J3 and J6 are on slopes  of less than 3%, J4 and J5 on slopes of about 7%.  The following measurements were undertaken in the laboratory on the  less than 2 mm fraction: pH (H20), carbonates (volumetric calcimeter  method), electrical conductivity (in saturated extract), cation exchange capa-  city (Na-OAc), and mechanical analysis (Hydrometer method). The proce-  dures used for all the above analyses are described by Black (1965). After  the removal of carbonates by treating the (50 pm clay fraction with I N  NaOAc, pH = 5 (Jackson, 1969), the (2 um clay fractions were separated by  centrifuging and analyzed with a Philips X-ray diffractometer with a graphite  monochromator and a Cu target X-ray tube operated at 35 kV and 15 mA.  Soil samples of the less than 2 mm fraction were extracted with I N  NH4OAc, pH = 7 for exchangeable or available potassium (Black, 1965),  with 1N HC1 for weatherable potassium (Schachtschabel, cited by Schlich-  ting and Blume, 1966) and with HF for total potassium (Jackson, 1969).  Fixed potassium retained by the soil sample after addition of 0.1 N KC1 fol-  lowed by NH4OAc extraction was also determined (Graf v. Reichenbach and  Schroeder, cited by Schlichting and Blume, 1966). The extracted potassium  was determined by flame photometer.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    General soil characteristics    The soils of the Highland that were described as Red Mediterranean or  Terra-Rossa-like soils (Moormann, 1959) are very fine in texture and exhibit  slickensides and deep cracks (&gt; 1 cm wide) that remain open more than four  months during the summer period (Table I). These soils have the properties  of Chromoxererts in the USDA classification system (Soil Survey Staff,  1975) and include both entic and typic subgroups.  In the Jordan Valley, Aridisols with cambic horizons were formed in the  colluvial--alluvial materials (Table II). The soils on the higher slopes as in the  foothills (profile J5) and on Lisan marl (profile J4) were classified as Torrior-  thents due to their weak horizonation.  Soils of the Highland were calcareous with differing amounts of carbon-  ates and higher pH's (Table III). The presence of appreciable: amounts :of  carbonate (2--19%) throughout the soil profiles makes them different from  the Terra Rossa soils described in other areas of the Mediterranean (Singer,  1976, 1978) where the soils are free of carbonates, at least in the surface    TABLE I  Morphology of soil profiles from the Highlands    45    Horizon   Depth    Moist         Texture Structure Consistence Boundary Slickensides  (cm)     colors  Soils derived from limestone    Profile HI : Entic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap          0--25   7.5YR 4/4    c        2 mgr    mfr, dsh     gw       none  C1         25--55   7.5YR 5]6    c        2 mabk   mfi, dh      d         none  C2         55--85   7.5YR 5/6    c        2 mabk   mfi, dh      d         some  C3         85--115  7.5YR 5]6    c        2 mabk   mfi, dh                some    Profile H2: Entic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap          0--25    10YR 4/3    c        2 fgr     mfr, dsh     gw       none  Ac         25--50    10YR 4/3    c        2 mabk   mfi, dh      gw       none  C1         50--75    10YR 4[4    c        3 mabk   mfi, dh      d         some  C2         75--100   10YR 4/4    c        3 mabk   mfi, dh                many    Profile H3 : Typic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap          0--20    10YR 3/3    c        3 fgr     mfr, dh      gw       none  Ac         20--45    10YR 3]3    c        2 mpr    mfi, deh     gw       some  C1         45--65    10YR 4]3    c        2 mpr    mfi, deh     d         many  C2         65--85    10YR 4]3    c        2 mpr    mfi, deh               many    Soils derived from basalt associated with limestone    Profile H4: Entic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap          0--25    10YR 4/3    c        2 fgr     mfr, dsh     gw       none  C1         25--55    10YR 4/4    c        3 mabk   mfi, dh      d         some  C2         55--85    10YR 4/4    c        3 mabk   mfi, dh      d         some  C3         85--115   10YR 4/4    c        3 mabk   mfi, dh                many    Profile H5 : Entic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonite, thermic  Ap          0--20    10YR 4/3    c        3 fgr     mfr, dh      gw       none  Ac         20--45    10YR 4/3    c        2 mpr    mfi, dvh     gw       some  C1         45--70    10YR 4/4    c       2 mpr    mfi, dvh     d         many  C2         70--100   10YR 4/4    c        2 mpr    mfi, dvh     d         many    The abbreviations for soil characteristics are from Soil Survey Manual (USDA, 1951, p. 139).    layers. The carbonate contents decreased with increased annual rainfall, both  in soils over limestone (profiles HI, H2 and H3) and those over basalt (pro-  files H4 and H5). Slight decreases of carbonates with depth were observed in  all profiles studied. The increases of carbonate among and within the soil  profiles may indicate some leaching by rainwater. The soils of the Highlands  are generally not affected by soluble salts. The electrical conductivity mea-  sured in saturated extract was less than 0.9 mmhos/cm (Table III). The small  decreases of salts in the soil profiles are ascribed to increased amounts of    46  TABLE II  Morphology of soil profiles from the Jordan Valley    Horizon     Depth     Moist       Texture    Structure    Consistence   Boundary  (cm)       colors  Ghor soils derived from colluvium    Profile J1 : Ustollic Camborthid, very fine, illitic, hyperthermic  Ap           0--20      10YR 4/2  c          2 mgr       mfr, dsh      gw  C1          20--40     10YR 4/3  c          2 msbk     mfi, dh       d  C2          40--60     10YR 4/3  c          2 msbk     mfi, dh       d  C3          60--80      10YR 4/3   c          2 msbk      mfi, dh    Profile J2: Ustollic Camborthid, very fine, illitic, hyperthermic  Ap           0--30      10YR 4/2  c          2 fgr        mfr, dsh      gw  Ac          30--55     10YR 4/2  c          2 msbk     mfi, dvh      gs  C1          55--75     10YR 4/3  c          2 msbk     mfi, dvh      d  C2          75--95     10YR 4/3  c          2 msbk     mfi, dvh    Profile J3: Typic Camborthid, fine loamy, mixed hyperthermic  Ap           0--30     7.5YR 4/4  sl           m         mvfr, dsh     gw  C1          30--60     7.5YR 5/4  Scl        1 csbk      mfr, dsh      d  C2          60--85     7.5YR 5/4  Scl        1 csbk      mfr, dsh      d  C3          85--100   7.5YR 5/4  Scl        1 csbk      mfr, dsh    Ghor-Lisan soils derived from lacustrine sediments    Profile J4: Typic Torriorthent, fine loamy, carbonatic, hyperthermic  Ap           0--10     10YR 5/4  1          m          mfr, dsh  Ac          10--20      10YR 5/6   cl          m           mfr, dsh  2C1         20--45     10YR 7/3  cl         0           mvfr, ds    Soils derived from colluvium in foothills    Profile J5 : Typic Torriorthent, loamy skeletal, mixed, hyperthermic  Ap           0--25     10YR 4/4  cl         2 mgr       mfr, dsh  C1          25--50     10YR 5/4  gsl        1 csbk      mfr, dsh  2C1         50--90     10YR 5/4  gsl         1 csbk      mfr, dsh    Zor soils derived from alluvium    gs  as    Cw  gw    Profile J6: Ustollic Camborthid, fine, mixed, hyperthermic  Ap           0--30     10YR 4/2  c          2 mgr       mfr, dsh      ew  C1          30--55     10YR 4/3  c          2 csbk      mfi, dh       gw  2C1         55--85      10YR 4/3  c          2 csbk       mfi, dh    The abbreviations for soil characteristics are from Soil Survey Manual (USDA, 1951,  p. 139).    TABLE Ill  Selected physical and chemical properties of soils from the Highlands    47    Profile  Rainfall  Depth    pH    CaCO3   E.C.      C.E.C.         K           Sand  Silt   Clay  No.     (mrn/yr)  (cm)      H~O  (%)       (mrnhos/ (meq./100g)  (ppm)      2--.05 50--2 &lt;2  (equiv.)  crn)                       (NH4OAc) mm   pln    /~m  (%)  (%)  (%)    Soils derived from limestone  H1      200        0--25   8.2     S.1      0.9       51             712        5.2    33.9  60.9  25--55   8.3     9.9      0.5       52             427        5.2    30.3  64.5  55--85   8.5    10.9      0.3       51             302        5.2    30.1  64.7  85--115  8.6    10.3      0.3       50             292        4.9    29.6  65.5    H2      300    0--25   8.1     7.3      0.4       56             284        2.2    21.5  76.3  25--50       8.2          7.5            0.5               59                           188                 3.1        21.7     75.2  50--75   8.3     7.8      0.6       59             169        3.4    20.0  76.6  75--100  8.4     7.8      0.6       69             182        1.4    20.8  77.8    H3      500    0--20   7.8     1.7      0.2       76               64        2.6    15.6  81.8  20--45   7.8     2.7      0.2       69               47        1.3    18.7  80.0  45--65   7.8     2.9      0.2       67               54        1.1    21.3  77.6  65--85   8.0     3.1      0.2       65              84        1.2    20.8  78.0    Soils derived from basalt associated with limestone  H4            300                0--25       8.4        17.3            0.3               51                           430                 2.0        20.2     77.8  25--55   8.7    17.2      0.4       56             352        0.8    19.3  79.9  55--85       8.9        17.5            0.7               53                           322                 1.0        18.6     80.4  85--115     8.9        18.5            0.8               51                           314                 0.4        24.2     75.4    H5      450    0--20   8.1     7.8      0.3       82             272        1.4    24.2  74.4  20--45   8.2     7.8      0.3       81             172        4.0    17.7  78.3  45--70   8.3     8.0      0.3       80             159        2.9    18.6  78.5  70--100  8.3     8.6      0.5       S0             166        1.9    19.5  78.6    rainfall. All softs studied were very fine textured with high clay contents,  ranging from 60 to 80% (Table III) and with uniform distribution throughout  the profiles. High clay contents (more than 70%) have also been reported in  calcareous Grumusols formed on basalt under similar conditions in Israel  (Dan and Singer, 1973).  The soils of the Jordan Valley were more calcareous than those of the  Highland, with carbonate contents exceeding 60% in some profiles (Table  IV). The soils in the northern part of the valley (profiles J2 and J6) were  more calcareous than profiles J1, J3 and J5 in the southern part. The high  carbonate contents of these soils are attributed to the highly calcareous  nature of Lisan marl in the north (Dar A1-Handsah, 1967). The high carbon-  ate contents in profile J4 (Ghor--Lisan soil) was due to the presence of the  marl near the soil surface (20 cm). The carbonate contents within profiles  showed slight decreases in the surface layers in soils from colluvial--alluvial  {profiles J1, J2 and J3) and alluvial (profile J6) materials. This decrease  could be due to the long term use of these softs in agriculture. The amounts  of soluble salts in the softs had the opposite trend from carbonate in the  valley, where the electrical conductivities of saturated extracts of profiles    48  TABLE IV  Selected physical and chemical properties of soils from the Jordan Valley    Profile  Rainfall  Depth    pH    CaCO3   E.C,      C.E.C.         K          Sand  Silt   Clay  No.     (mrn/yr)  (era)      H:O   (%)       (rnmhos/ (meq./100 g)  (ppm)      2--.05 50--2 &lt;2  (equiv.)   cm)                      (NH4OAc) mm   ~m    ~rn  (%)  (%)  (%)    Ghor soils derived from colluvium  J1      200        0--20   8.4    25.8      3.8       31             755          9.7  34.3  56.0  20--40   8.4    26.1      3.8       32             743          7.1  26.2  66.7  40--60   8.4    26.5      3.4       34             705          4.9  28.4  66.7  60--80   8.4    26.1      3.6       27             713          4.7  27.1  68.2    J2      250    0--30       8.3        53.8            3.1               25                           320                 13.2     28.8     58.0  30--55       8.4        60.0            2.4               20                           300                   6.2     28.5     65.3  55--75   8,4   60.4      2.6       20             285          8.0  25.9  66.1  75--95   8.3    64.0      3.4       22             213          7.8  26.9  65.3    J3      150    0---30   8.1    15.6      4.1         9             176        73.4  13.9  12.7  30--60   8.1    19.0      7.1       10             309        57.4  23.2  19,4  60--85   8.2    21.1      5.6       13             473        58.2  19.3  22.5  85--120  8.2    22.1      7.2       13             534        58.4  18.5  23.1    Ghor-Lisan soilS derived from lacustrine sediments  J4      100        0--10   8.0    55.6      49.9      12             840        51.0  32.2  16.8  10--20   8.3    55.6      93.9      16            1301        38.2  30.3  31.5  20--45   8.2    34.2      78.7      16             899        33.2  30.5  36.3    Soils derived from colluvium in foothills  J5      100        0--25   8.4    33.1      2.7       16             294        44.8  26.5  28.7  25--50   8.5    29.8      2.6       12             191        55.2  27.3  17.5  50--90   8.5    26.5      2.1         8               93        74.8    8.3  16.9    Zor soils derived from alluvium  J6      250        0--30   8.2    42.6      3.5       35             584        11.8  27.8  60,4  30--55   8.4    47.5      2.9       28             288        22.0  27.9  50.1  55--85   8.4    49.7      2.4       20             180        29.6  25.6  44.8    J3 and J4 in the southern part were higher than those of the other profiles  (Table IV). Profile J5, which is on a foothill, was not affected by the Lisan  marl and was also lower in soluble salts. The Ghor--Lisan soil (Profile J4)  had a higher salt content than any other soil in the Jordan Valley, indicating  the effect of the high salinity of the Lisan marl in this part. There were slight  increases in salts in surface layers in some profiles, suggesting accumulations  of salts through upward water movement. The increases in salts with depth  in profiles J2, J3 and J4 indicated the effect of the Lisan marl on deep  horizons. The textures of the soils ranged from sandy loam to clay. There  was no uniformity in texture from one location to another or throughout  the profiles. Soils were formed in alluvial and colluvial materials and have  poor horizonation.    Clay minerals    Large smectite contents in soils of the Highland. are indicated by the high  CEC's of the clay fractions, calculated from those of the whole soil samples    49    (Table III). The X-ray diffraction patterns of the &lt;2 #m clay fractions of  profiles H1, H2, H3 and H5 (Fig. 2) also showed a predominance of smectite  with small amounts of kaolinite and quartz. Mica was found in appreciable  amounts in profile HI and in small amounts in profile H2 and H4 (data for  profile H4 not shown). The swelling of smectite with glycerol to 18 A for the  samples from deeper parts of profiles H2, H3 and H5 are shown in Fig. 3.  The same trend was observed in the surface layers (data not shown). Clay  fractions of profile H1 showed a gradual swelling with glycerol to higher  d-spacing than 18 A (Fig. 3) with low intensities and broader peaks, probably  indicating some interstratified clay in this profile. Broad peaks of the heated  K-saturated samples occurred at d-spacings between 14 and 10 A (Fig. 4).  The degree of contraction of layers at 400 was higher in profile H1 where  the d-spacing was closer to 10 A, indicating the presence of mica/smectite  interstratification. Increases in the d-spacing were observed with profile H2  and still more for profile H3 and H5. A full contraction to 10 A by a major    &lt;2.0 pm  Mg-25                             J    1000   2500c  5000(    5000c    5000c  28   26    22    18    14    10    6     2 2e  Fig. 2. X-ray diffraction patterns for air-dried clay fractions (&lt;2 ~m) from soils of the  Highland.    50    &lt; 2.0pm                H 1(0-25cm)  o&lt;    H 1(85-1151  o&lt;    o.  ~ Jr'l  I          ~, ~12175-1001  j~'     ~t3(65-85)  sooocp,,[~'               \ ~r,(7o-mol  1'2 1'0 8 ~ ,t 2 2e    Fig. 3. X-ray diffraction patterns for glycerol-solvated clay fractions (&lt; 2 um) from soils  of the Highland.    portion of 14 A clay after heating at 550 is shown in Fig. 4 with some still  remaining between 10 and 14 A. This peak indicates some hydroxy-inter-  layering of the smectite or an interstratification of smectite/sweUing chlorite.  Such interstratified clay was reported for similar softs in Israel (Singer,  1971). The presence of chlorite, indicated by a 14 A peak in the 550  heated samples, was found in profiles H3 and H5 (Fig. 4). The degree of  interlayering or interstratification with swelling chlorite was highest in pro-  files H3 and H5, lower in H2, and least in H1 as can be seen from the sam-  ples heated at 400. For soils formed over both limestone (profiles H1, H2,  and H3) and basalt (profiles H4 and H5), smectite was interstratified with  mica in the softs under the lowest rainfalls and interstratified with swelling  chlorite under higher rainfalls. The higher intensities and sharper peaks of  smectite in profiles H3 and H5 indicate high-charge smectite, which is sup-  ported by the higher CEC's (Table III). Such higher values of CEC were ob-  served in similar soils in Israel (Singer, 1971).  The clay mineral composition of similar soils in the area has been reported  with a wide range of results. Yaalon (1955) estimated that montmorillonite    1!    51    K-400    K-550c    12  10  8   6   4   2 2e  Fig. 4. X-ray diffraction patterns for heated clay fractions (&lt;2 ~m) from soils of the  Highland.    accounted for 70% of the clay fractions in some Terra Rossa soils near Jeru-  salem. Lamouroux et al. (1967) found smectite to be dominant and some  kaolinite present in some soils in Lebanon. On the other hand, kaolinite was  found to be dominant in soils formed from basic rocks in Syria {Muir, 1951}  and Israel {Singer and Navrot, 1977). Tuffahah (1970) reported high kao-    52    linite and less montmorillonite in some soils of Jordan. Singer (1978) found  kaolinite to be dominant in Terra Rossa soils in Israel and suggested that  smectite was transformed to kaolinite under high rainfall. Singer (1966) con-  cluded from the clay mineralogy of soils of Galilee in Israel that kaolinite  dominated the softs of high rainfall regions whereas montmorillonite domi-  nated the soils of low rainfall regions. The predominance of smectite in clay  fractions of the soils of the Highland in Jordan with its semiarid Mediterra-  nean climate supports this observation.  The lower CEC's of the soils of the Jordan Valley (Table IV) and the  CEC's of 100 g of clay calculated from these values indicate lower smectite  contents than for soils of the Highland. The XRD patterns of the &lt;2 ~m clay  fraction of profiles J1, J4 and J6 (Fig. 5) indicated higher contents of 10 A  minerals and kaolinite than in clays from the Highland. With the exception  of profiles J1 and J2 (data for J2 not shown), smectite was still the major  component of the clay fractions (data for profiles J3 and J5 not shown). The    &lt; 2.0 pm  Mg-25oc    o~ oet  o    v-  /!'/M_j'    d   l  IO00cp,t  ~ !!l  / 14 ~Jl(eo..eo) J   j   /~% j  , j;V  ,o  ......  ,7/  .I    t  ......  ,,   /  ' 2'6 ' 2'2 ' i8 '  1~4'  10    g     2 2e  Fig. 5. X-ray diffraction patterns for air-dried clay fractions (&lt; 2 ~m) from soils of Jordan  Valley.    o,(  o  &lt; 2.0pm  ,\    /  I    /'x---"/"-xJ/' /  Mg-Gly )~ ~      p~..._.../  2sooc~    ),,. ~    J6(55-85cm)  J4(20-45)    ~s(ss-e6)  J4(20-45)    53    K-4000C  lO00cps  I    J6(55-85)    J4(20-45)    K-550oC  lO00cps  14  12  10  8   6   4   2 2e  Fig. 6. X-ray diffraction patterns for glycerol-solvated and heated clay fractions (&lt; 2 ~m)  from soils of Jordan Valley.    broad X-ray diffraction peaks for surface layers of profiles J4 and J6 (Fig. 5)  may indicate the presence of very fine grained smectite with some interstrati-  fication of mica and chlorite. The interstratification can be inferred from the  broad peaks of the samples heated at 400and 550 (Fig. 6). Small  amounts of chlorite were also present in profile J4 (Fig. 6). The 10 min-  erais found were mica and palygorskite. The high mica contents of soils in  the Jordan Valley are indicated by the high total potassium contents, espe-  ciaily in profile J1 (Fig. 8). Paiygorskite has been reported in the soils of the  Jordan Valley (Wiersma, 1970). The observation by Shamali (1966) indi-    54    cated high contents of montmorillonite but with illite, kaolinite and meta-  halloysite present in appreciable amounts. In the Lisan marl which underlies  the soils of the Jordan Valley, Yaalon (1955), found that kaolinite and  montmorillonite dominated the clay fraction. Abed and Helmdach (1981)  reported the presence of kaolinite, illite, and iUite/montmorillonite mixed  layers in the marl, whereas Wiersma (1970) reported the presence of appre-  ciable amounts of palygorskite. No clear trends were found in the distribu-  tion of clay minerals in the soils of the Jordan Valley, indicating that these  minerals are detrital and derived from other sediments.    Potassium status    NH4OAc-extractable potassium, which is considered as available potassium  (Black, 1965), ranged from less than 60 (profile H3) to more than 700 ppm  (profile H1). The NH4OAc-extractable potassium tended to decrease with in-  creasing rainfall in soils formed over both limestone (H1, H2 and H3) and  basalt (H4 and H5). The HCl-extractable and total potassium showed the  same trend (Fig. 7). These potassium fractions coincided as well with the  amounts of mica and mica/smectite interstratification in the soil clays, which  were highest in profile H1, lower in H2, and even lower in H3. On the other  hand, the amount of potassium that can be fixed by those soils was about  40 mg K/100 g of soil material in profiles H3 and H5 (Fig. 7). The fixing  capacity increased with increases in amounts of rainfall, smectite content,  and the charge on the clay. Additions of potassium to the soils under higher  rainfall in the Highland were found to improve the quality of tobacco and in-  crease the production of corn.    H1  150C -                                                                                        [-7 K-HI:  H4  110C -                                                              [] K-HCI                         H2  0 70(                                             H3                                  H5          [] K-NH4OAc  0~30(                                                                   ~Jll K- filed  P   ,  ,3  (  Depthlcm)    Fig. 7. Forms of potassium in soils of the Highland.    The soils of the Jordan Valley generally had higher amounts of NH4OAc-  extractable potassium (Table IV). The higher salt contents and fertilization  over long periods may be responsible. The HCl-extractable and total potas-  sium (Fig. 8) and the values obtained from these for I00 g of clay were high  and coincided with mica or mica/smectite interstratification, especially in  profiles J1. Feigenbaum and Levy (1977) reported high potassium release in    1500  1100  "~ 700  g aoo  ~   80  40    J1    0-20  -40  -60  -80    J3  J2  0-30  -55  -75  -95     0-30  -60  -85 -120    J4    !!!    Depth(cm)  Fig. 8. Forms of potassium in soils of Jordan Valley.    36  J5  0*25  -50  -90    0-30  -55  -85    55    ~K-HF  ~]K- HCI   K - N H4OAc  K - fixed    similar soils in Israel. The amounts of potassium that can be fixed by the soil  materials (Fig. 8) and the calculated values for 100 g of clay were generally  lower than those for soils of the Highland.    REFERENCES    Abed, A.M. and Helmdach, F., 1981. Biostratigraphy and mineralogy of the Lisan Series  (Pleistocene) in the Jordan Valley. Berliner geowiss. Abh., (A) 32: 123--133.  Abed E1-Hadi, Y. and Badawi, M., 1973. Soil Survey and Land Classification Project:  Irbid-Region Soil (first stage). Ministry of Agriculture, Jordan.  Bender, F., 1975. Geology of the Arabian Peninsula, Jordan. United States Government  Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Black, C.A. (Editor), 1965. Methods of Soil Analysis. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wisc.  Dan, J. and Singer, A., 1973. Soil evolution on basalt and basic pyroclastic materials in  the Golan Heights. Geoderma, 9: 165--192.  Dar A1-Handsah, 1967. Jordan Valley Project. Agro- and Socio-economic Study, Vol. II,  pp. 4--9.  Feigenbaum, S. and Levy, R., 1977. Potassium release in some saline soils of Israel. Geo-  derma, 19: 159--169.  Jackson, M.L., 1969. Soil Chemical Analysis, Advanced Course. Published by Author,  Madison, Wisc., 895 p.  Lamouroux, M., Paquet, H., Pinta, and Millot, G., 1967. Notes preliminaires sur les min~-  raux argileux des altSrations et des sols Mediterran~ens du Liban. Bull. Serv. Carte  g~ol. Als. Lorr., 20(4): 277--292.  Moorman, F., 1959. The Soils of East Jordan. FAO-Report No. 1132, Rome.  Muir, A., 1951. Notes on Syrian soils. J. Soil Sci., 2: 163--183.  Schlichting, E. and Blume, H., 1966. Bodenkundliches Praktikum. Paul Parey, Hamburg  and Berlin.  Shamali, K., 1966. Zur Kenntnis der B~den des Jordangrabens unter besonderer Be-  rilcksichtigung der Tonmineralien. Ph.D. Thesis, Justus-Liebig Universit~t, Giessen.  Singer, A., 1966. The mineralogy of the clay fraction from basalt soils in the Galilee,  Israel. J. Soil Sci., 17 : 136--146.  Singer, A., 1971. Clay minerals in the soils of the southern Golan Heights. Isr. J. Earth  Sci., 20: 105--112.  Singer, A., 1976. The significance of the term "Mediterranean" in the nomenclature of  soils in Europe and Israel. Isr. J. Earth Sci., 25: 76--82.  Singer, A., 1978. Clay minerals in the soils of Mr. Hermon. Isr. J. Earth Sci., 27 : 97--105.    56    Singer, A. and Navrot, J., 1977. Clay formation from basic volcanic rocks in a humid  Mediterranean climate. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 645--650.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. Agric. Handbook, 18, USDA, US Govt.  Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Agric. Handbook, 436, USDA, US Govt. Printing  Office, Wash., D.C., 754 pp.  Tuffahah, M., 1970. Mineralogy and Genesis of Selected Soils in Jordan. M.S. Thesis.  American University of Beirut.  Wiersma, J., 1970. Provenance, Genesis and Paleographical Implications of Microminerals  Occurring in Sedimentary Rocks of the Jordan Valley Area. Publ. Fys.-Geograf.  Bodenkd. Lab. Univ. Amsterdam, Nr. 15.  Yaalon, D.H., 1955. Clays and some non-carbonate minerals in limestones and associated  soils of Israel. Bull. Res. Counc. Isr., 5B, 2, Sect. B Zoo, pp. 161--173.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractThe physical, chemical and mineralogical characteristics of some soils in the Jordan Valley (Rift Valley) and the Highland (Irbid-region) were investigated. The soils of the Highland (Chromoxererts) contained more clay and smectite than those of the Jordan Valley (Camborthids and Torriorthents). Higher contents of carbonates, salts and mica were found in the latter. In addition to smectite and micam interstratified clay minerals (mica/smectite and smectite/chlorite) and kaolinite were present in the clay fractions of the soils in the two regions. Soils of the Highland, especially those under higher rainfall with larger amounts of highly charged smectite, had lower contents of available and total potassium and higher degrees of potassium fixation than those of the Jordan Valley. Soil properties such as carbonate, salt and potassium contents and clay mineral composition were related to the amounts of annual rainfall in soils of the Highland, whereas differences among the Jordan Valley soils were related to the parent materials, especially the underlying Lisan Marl.