 316    postulated in the Framework (oxygen availability, moisture availability,  inherent fertility, etc.), emphasis is placed on those qualities that are con-  straints to cultivation. Papers 5 and 6 also present the placement of the  soils in the fertility capability classification of Buol et al. The referen-  ces cited are comprehensive and reflect dilligent research.  In conjunction with the FAO--Unesco Soil Map of the World, the soil  monolith papers are particularly useful for university teachers and students  of soil science as well as all those interested in the study of soils in relation  to their potential for agricultural use. It is hoped, therefore, that the series  will be continued; perhaps under a new general title such as "Benchmark  Soils of the World", as "Soil Monolith Paper" fails to convey the scope and  depth of the publications.    F.H. BEINROTH  (Mayaguez, P.R. )    C02 and Plants, The Response of Plant to Rising Levels of Atmospheric  Carbon Dioxide. Edgar R. Lemon (Editor). Westview Press, Boulder,  1983. AAAS Selected Symposia Series, 84. XXII + 280 pp., US $25.00  (hardcover).    Plants are intimately involved with the CO2 in our biosphere. Hence  any reasonable attempt to understand the rising levels of CO2 in our atmo-  sphere must include plants. Vast portions of our world are covered with  skin-thick layers of plant cells with metabolize tons of CO2 daily. C02 and  Plants takes a holistic viewpoint of living plants and their known responses  to CO2 with emphasis upon predictable responses of plants to a doubling  or tripling of our atmospheric CO2 level.  C02 and Plants is a thorough presentation of our current level of know-  ledge and understanding of plants and their responses to COz. The motiva-  tion for collecting this information is the well-documented increases in  atmospheric CO2 which have occurred over the last 2.5 decades plus the  uncertainty of how plants may respond to further increases in their CO2  level. The book is an outgrowth of a conference held in Athens, Georgia  in May 1982 which was attended by about 130 persons, with heavy emphasis  upon plant research scientists, from various parts of the world.  The scientists divided into six topical groups to consider CO2 and plants  regarding: carbon metabolism; physiological effects; plant growth and  development; microbial effects; terrestrial plant communities; and aquatic  plant communities. Each group took a holistic approach to documenting  our current understanding of the influences of CO2 upon plants. Thus  this book is more than asking obvious questions such as "how is photo-  synthesis influenced by changing CO2 levels". Indeed many pertinent and    317    currently unanswerable questions are raised about topics such as roots,  plant-associated microbes, and community responses to CO2.  Scientists were free to work in various topical discussion groups. Each  group presents a brief summary of the current status of our knowledge  plus a set of recommendations for necessary research. There seems to be  agreement that plants will benefit from rising CO2 levels since CO2 is the  major substrate for constructing a plant. Indeed plants may grow more  effectively at elevated CO2 levels but use reasonably close to current levels  of other nutrients such as H:O or nitrogen. However, these holistic answers  are not truly known because few long-term plant studies on growth, al-  location, partitioning, or reproduction have been conducted at elevated  CO: levels. No studies are available covering several life cycles of a plant  nor are any short- or long-term community studies available.  CO: and Plants is a concise set of statements outlining our current level  of understanding of the responses plants, plus associated microbes, to  CO2 as they live, grow, and reproduce in this biosphere. In addition the  uncertainties about plants and rising CO2 levels are listed along with potenti-  ally fruitful research topics which should help us to predict future responses  to CO2 of the largest CO2 metabolism factory of the world, namely plants.    CLANTON C. BLACK, JR.  {Athens, GA)    Elements of Soil Physics. P. Koorevaar, G. Menelik and C. Dirksen. Develop-  ments in Soil Science, 13, Elsevier, Amsterdam--Oxford--New York--  Tokyo, 1983, XIV + 228 pp., US $ 32.00 (U.S. and Canada), Dfl. 75.00  (hardcover).    This book, presenting a rigorous, complete and consistent treatment of  concepts, definitions and relationships of physical processes occuring in  soil, is meant to be not only a first introduction in soil physics but also  an auxiliary source for an advanced study. It represents a very valuable  textbook with a particular attention paid to problems studied at agricultural  universities.  The origin of the book goes back to lectures held at the Department of  Soil Science and Plant Nutrition of the Agricultural University, Wageningen,  The Netherlands. Further, some material has been added for use in M.Sc.-  courses on Soil Science and Water Management at the Agricultural University  for students from developing countries.  The need to improve the examination of students and to make this book  particularly suitable for self-study and rapid reference has led the authors  to the introduction of a total of 235 questions and detailed answers. The  book contains seven proper chapters, an epilogue, written by G.H. Bolt,  and three apendices.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            