 Geoderma, 35 (1985) 119-125 119  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam - Printed in The Netherlands    THE PHENOLIC ACID CONTENT OF CASHEW LEAVES (ANACARDIUM OCCIDENTALS L.) AND OF THE ASSOCIATED HUMUS LAYER,  SENEGAL    INGRID KEL and WOLFGANG ZECH    Lehrstuhl f Bodenkunde and Bodengeographie, Uniuersit Bayreuth, Postfach 3008, 8580 Bayreuth (Bundesrepublik Deutschland)    (Received February 23, 1984 ; accepted after revision December 27, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Kel, I, and Zech, W., 1985. The phenolic acid content of cashew leaves (Anacardium  occidentale L.) and of the associated humus layer, Senegal. Geoderma, 35: 119-125.     Phenolic acid content was studied in NaOH- and water-extracts from cashew leaves and from the associated humus profile. Free and bound forms of water-soluble phenolic acids were evaluated separately. Phenolic acid composition in the humus layers is to a high degree determined by the phenolic substances inherited from the leaves. Alkali- and water-extracts were dominated by gallic acid, because of the high contents of hydrolisable gallotannin in cashew leaves. Gallic, protocatechuic, p-hydroxybenzoic, cinnamic, p-coumaric and ferulic acids were derived from the leaves, whereas vanillic acid only occurred in the soil. Considerable proportions of the total phenolic acids are watersoluble and lost by leaching from the humus layers.    INTRODUCTION     Benzoic and cinnamic acid derivatives are ubiquitous phenolic acids in plant materials. They are present in free and bound forms, the latter mostly as glycosides and esters of various plant constituents (Harborne, 1980). During microbial decomposition, a number of phenolic substances is released from the lignin polymer, including vanillic, p-hydroxybenzoic, protocatechuic, syringic, p-coumaric and ferulic acids (Henderson, 1955; Cheng et al., 1982). Recent investigations on the decomposition of phenolic acids using the '4C-labeling technique have shown that they are important intermediates in the formation of humus (Haider and Martin, 1975; Kassim et al., 1981).   Numerous studies have been made of the distribution of phenolic acids soluble in alkali or organic solvents in various soils (Whitehead, 1964; Morita, 1973; Katase, 1981). Although the investigations of Shindo et al. (1978) and Jalal and Read (1983) are concerned with phenolic compounds in forest Oh- and Ah- horizons, information about the contents of phenolic acids in    0016-7061/85/$03.30985 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.  120    whole humus profiles (according to Babel et al., 1980, the term "humus profile" is defined as a vertical section of the organic surface layers differentiated into horizons) is lacking. Whitehead et al. (1983) first reported the occurrence of bound water-soluble forms of phenolic acids in soils and leaf litter. Therefore, the objectives of the present investigation were to examine the distribution of free and bound water-soluble and NaOHsoluble forms of phenolic acids in a complete humus profile and in the leaves of the associated trees. Cashew (Anacardium occidentale L.) was chosen because the leaves are known to be rich in phenolic materials (Howes, 1962). As far as the authors are aware, no such studies on forest humus layers have been undertaken.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Samples     Samples were collected during the dry season (February) near Sokone, Senegal. Soil samples were taken from L-, Of-, Ofh-, OfhAh-, Ah,- and Ah2horizons of an Ustic Dystropept (see Table I for source of horizon designations) supporting a pure stand of cashew (Anacardium occentale L.). Additionally, samples of fresh green and senescent yellow leaves were obtained. Pretreatment of the samples included air drying (25), passing through a 2 mm sieve (mineral soil samples) and grinding of leaf and litter samples (0.5 mm). Some general characteristics of the soil samples are given in Table I.    TABLE I    Selected chemical characteristics of the investigated humus profile    Horizon*' Thickness pH C N C/N   (cm) (0.O1M CaCl,) (9'0)  ()  L 3.0 4.59 46.4  0.54 90  Of 1.5 4.92 43.8 0.66  68  Ofh 1.5 5.37 37.6  0.79 48  OfhAh 3.0 5.76  3.2 0.18 18  Ah, 5.0 5.63  1.2 0.07 17  Ah2 15.0 5.40  0.7 0.04 17    *' Nomenclature is according to Scheffer and Schachtschabel (1982).    Extraction of phenolic acids     Extraction of NaOH-soluble phenolic compounds was described previously (Kel, 1983).  Extraction of free and bound water-soluble phenolic acids was carried out  121    according to the scheme outlined by Whitehead et al. (1983). Air-dried leaf or soil material (5-250 g) was shaken with bidistilled water (50-250 ml) for 20 h at room temperature. The suspension wcentrifuged (3000 rpm) and the supernatant filtered. In order to obtain free phenolic acids, an aliquot of the solution was acidified to pH 2 with 2 M HCI and centrifuged. The supernatant was extracted three times with ethyl acetate, concentrated and subjected to HPLC. To release the bound phenolic acids, another aliquot of the filtered extract was ajusted to pH 13 with 2 M NaOH and allowed to stand for 20 h under NZ before acidification and extraction with ethyl acetate.    Identification and determination o f phenolic acids     Identification and quantitative determination of phenolic acids using reversed -phase HPLC has been described by Kel (1983). To illustrate the decomposition of the phenolic acids all amounts are given in pg g-' organic matter. In the Ah,- and Ah2-horizons determination of the watersoluble phenolic acids was limited by interference of unknown compounds in the chromatogram. Therefore trace amounts (&lt; 1 ug g-' organic matter) of these acids were not computed.    Determination of pH, C and N content     Soil pH was measured in a 1 : 2.5 suspension of soil material in 0.1 M CaC12. Total carbon content was determined by dry combustion with a Wthoff Carmhomat C8, total nitrogen by the Kjeldahl procedure.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION     The phenolic acid contents of leaves, humus layers and soil are shown in Fig.1. The amounts of phenolic acids extracted with 1 M NaOH varied considerably. In the green leaves gallic, protocatechuic, cinnamic, ferulic and pcoumaric acid were detected, whereas p-hydroxybenzoic acid appeared in the senescent leaves and vanillic acid in the L-horizon. Gallic acid was present in greater amounts than any other of the phenolic substances with 20,100 pg g-' organic matter in the green leaves. This is due to the high amounts of hydrolysable gallotannins in cashew leaves (Howes, 1962). Values for the other NaOH-soluble phenolic acids ranged from 39 to 207 jig g-' in the leaves and from 3 to 1500 ug g-1 organic matter in the humus profile.   Except for gallic acid, which shows a steady decrease from the leaves to the mineral soil horizons, there is a relative concentration of NaOHsoluble phenolic acids in the L-horizon, reflecting to some degree the restricted decomposition of the phenolic compounds. Decomposition in vitro of single phenolic acids is found to be similar to those of other plant con-  D    p-HVDROI(YBENZOIC ACID    200 400 600 800 1000pg g-1 org.matter    TOCATECHUIC ACID    0 200 400 600 800Ngg-1org.matter    60 89    380 560 370 514 790 16    0 2000 4000 soap    g.i. S.I.    L Of Ofh    OfhAh AM Ahs    GALLIC ACID    8000 10000 12000        FERRIC ACID  0 200 400 600 800 1000    62 300 131 15 ti.     VANILLIC ACID  0 200 400Ngg-1org.    matter    - tr. 240    50 73 230  49 53 230  9 28 290  - - 105  - - 55    IL    CINNAMIC ACID    0 200 400NAg-1org.matter    NaOH-SOLUBLEPHENOLICACIOS    TOTAL WATER-SOLUBLE  PHENOLIC ACIDS (FREE AND BOUND)    FREE WATER-SOLUBLE PHENOLICACIDS    14000    8443 6228    5007 ton 1338 67 5 1,3    g.l.= GREEN LEAVES s l.= SENESCENTLEAVES    /tr./1090 FREE WATER-SOLUBLEJOTAL WATER-SOLUBLE AND   NaOH -SOLUBLE PHENOLIC ACIDS, RESPECTIVELY    20100 192(10    18100 12770 8140', 2540 335 7,8    p-COUMARIC ACID    200 400 600    Fig.l. Phenolic acid contents of cashew leaves and of the associated humus profile.    39 22    63 64 385 350 238 3,1    800 1000 yA g -1 arg. matter    - NOT DETECTED tr. TRACES  1090 AMOUNTSINPgg-1   ORGANIC MATTER  123    stituents, e.g., glucose or protein (Huntjens et al., 1981). But they are degraded more slowly, if several phenolic acids are present together (Shindo and Kuwatsuka,1975).   Vanillic acid was found in the humus and in the mineral soil horizons but not in the leaves. According to Henderson (1955) and Cheng et al. (1982) vanillic acid is one of the main compounds produced during the decomposition of lignin. Therefore it is considered that vanillic acid is produced in the humus layers during the decomposition of lignin.   Because of decomposition, incorporation into soil humic material and/or leaching, gallic, p-hydroxybenzoic, vanillic cinnamic, ferulic and p-coumaric acid decrease in passing from L- to Of- to Ofh- and Ah-horizons. In contrast, protocatechuic acid increases with depth and shows the highest value in the Ah,-horizon. Although some variation in the decay of the phenolic acids was observed, the most striking feature of the results was the similar behaviour of p-hydroxybenzoic, vanillic, ferulic and p-coumaric acid, all having maxima in the OfhAh-horizon. This represents the microbial production of phenolic acids or the absorption of water-soluble compounds by clay minerals and ferrihydrite as described by Huang et al. (1977). Comparatively high contents of oxalate-soluble iron were found in the OfhAh-horizon as compared to the Ahl- and Ah2-horizons, whereas clay content was generally very low (OfhAh 193 jug g-', Ah 1 168 p.g g ', Ah2 162 mg g ' oxalate-soluble iron). These facts suggest that ferrihydrite is the main absorption site for phydroxybenzoic, vanillic, ferulic and p-coumaric acid in the OfhAh-horizon. The increasing amounts of protocatechuic acid with depth, which is an intermediate in the decomposition of other phenolic acids (Martin and Haider, 1971), are more likely of microbial origin. The high amounts in the mineral soil horizons are explained by the fact that protocatechuic acid is absorbed in greater amounts in mineral soil horizons than other phenolic acids (Shindo and Kuwatsuka, 1976).   The water-soluble phenolic acids in the humic layers accounted for considerable proportions of the alkali-soluble phenolic acids. The water-soluble fraction was also dominated by gallic acid. In the leaves gallic, ferulic, pcoumaric and cinnamic acids were water-soluble, of which only gallic acid was present in the free form in substantial proportions. High contents of these four compounds were also found in free and bound water-soluble forms in the L-horizon. It is considered that the water-soluble forms of these acids are inherited from the leaves.   The leaching of gallic, protocatechuic, ferulic, p-coumaric and cinnamic acid from the humic layers is reflected by decreasing proportional contents of water-soluble compounds with depth. In the mineral soil horizons the investigated phenolic substances were almost entirely bound in a waterinsoluble form, only trace amounts being water-soluble.   These findings suggest that the phenolic acids present in the humic layers under cashews are partly lost by leaching, although small amounts are retained in the OfhAh-horizon as mentioned before. Another part is bound to  124    the soil organic matter in a water-insoluble, alkali-soluble form during humification.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS     The authors are indepted to R. Behrens, Proj Anacardier S6galoAllemand, Sokone, and to Dr. R. Bochter, University of Bayreuth, for their  help during collection of the samples. Appreciation is expressed to the  Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB 137) for financial support of this  work.    REFERENCES    Babal, U., Kreutzer, B., Ulrich, B., von Zeschwitz, E. and Ztl, H.W., 1980. Definitionen zur Humusmorphologie der Waldben. Z. Pflanzenernr. Bodenkd., 143: 564-568.  Cheng, C.-L., Chang, H.-M. and Kirk, T.K., 1982. Aromatic acids produced during degradation of lignin in spruce wood by Phanoerochaete chrysosporium. Holzforschung, 36: 3-9.  Haider, K. and Martin, J.P., 1975. Decomposition of specifically carbon-14-labelled benzoic and cinnamic acid derivatives in soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 657-662.  Harborne, J.B., 1980. Plant phenolics. In: A.E. Bell and B.V. Charlwood (Editors), Secondary Plant Products. Springer Verlag, Berlin, pp. 329-402.  Henderson, M.E.K., 1955. Release of aromatic compounds from birch and spruce sawdust during decomposition by white-rot fungi. Nature, 175: 634-635.  Howes, F.N., 1962. Tanning materials: Botanical part. In: C. von Regel (Editor), Die Rohstoffe des Pflanzenreichs. Cramer-Verlag, Weinheim, pp. 163-284.  Huang, P.M., Wang, T.S.C., Wang, M.K., Wu, M.H. and Hsu, N.W., 1977. Retention of phenolic acids by noncrystalline hydroxy-aluminium and iron compounds and clay materials of soils. Soil Sci., 123: 213-219.  Huntjens, J.L.M., Osterveldt-van Vliet, W.M. and Sayed, S.K.Y., 1981. The decomposition of organic compounds in soil. Plant Soil, 61: 227-242.  Jalal, M.A.F. and Read, DA, 1983. The organic acid composition of Calluna heathland soil with special reference to phyto- and fungitoxicity, II. Monthly quantitative deter-  mination of the organic acid content of Calluna and spruce dominated soils. Plant Soil, 70: 273-286.  Kassim, G., Stott, D.E., Martin, J.P. and Haider, K., 1981. Stabilization and incorporation into biomass of phenolic and benzenoid carbons during biodegradation in soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 305-309.  Katase, T., 1981. The different forms in which p-hydroxybenzoic, vanillic and ferulic acids exist in a peat soil. Soil Sci., 132: 436443.  Kel, I., 1983. Reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography of naturally occurring phenolic acids in soils. Z. Pflanzenerniihr. Bodenk., 146: 525-530.  Martin, J.P. and Haider, K., 1971. Microbial activity in relation to soil humus formation. Soil Sci., 111: 54-63.  Morita, H., 1973. Polyphenols in the benzene-ethanol extractives of an organic soil. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 37: 1587-1591.  Scheffer, F. and Schachtschabel, P., 1982. Lehrbuch der Bodenkunde. Enke-Verlag, Stuttgart, 442 pp.  Shindo, H. and Kuwatsuka, S., 1975. Behaviour of phenolic substances in the decaying process of plants, III. Degradation pathway of phenolic acids. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 21: 227-238.  125    Shindo, H. and Kuwatsuka, S., 1976. IV. Absorption and movement of phenolic acids in soils. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 22: 23-33.  Shindo, H., Ohta, S. and Kuwatsuka, S., 1978. IX. Distribution of phenolic acids in paddy fields and forests. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 24: 233-243.  Whitehead, D.C., 1964. Identification of p-hydroxybenzoic, vanillic, p-coumaric and ferulic acids in soils. Nature, 204: 417-418.  Whitehead, D.C., Dibb, H. and Hartley, R.D., 1983. Bound phenolic compounds in water extracts of soils, plant roots and leaf litter. Soil Biol. Biochem., 15: 133-136.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   AbstractPhenolic acid content was studied in NaOH- and water-extracts from cashew leaves and from the associated humus profile. Free and bound forms of water-soluble phenolic acids were evaluated separately. Phenolic acid composition in the humus layers is to a high degree determined by the phenolic substances inherited from the leaves. Alkali- and water-extracts were dominated by gallic acid, because of the high contents of hydrolisable gallotannin in cashew leaves. Gallic, protocatechuic, p-hydroxybenzoic, cinnamic, p-coumaric and ferulic acids were derived from the leaves, whereas vanillic acid only occurred in the soil. Considerable proportions of the total phenolic acids are water-soluble and lost by leaching from the humus layers. 