 Geoderrna, 31 (1983) 107--116                                               107  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    WATER TRANSMISSION OF UNSATURATED SOIL SAMPLES IN  RELATION TO MIXED Na-(Ca + Mg) SOLUTIONS    R.S. SIYAG, RAJ PAL and S.R. POONIA  Department of Soils, Haryana Agricultural University, Hissar (India)  (Received February 5, 1982; accepted after revision November 8, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Siyag, R.S., Pal, R. and Poonia, S.R., 1983. Water transmission of unsaturated soil sam-  ples in relation to mixed Na-(Ca + Mg) solutions. Geoderma, 31: 107--116.    The effects of electrolyte concentration (i.e., EC: 20, 40, 80, 125 and 250 meq. 1-1)  and sodium adsorption ratios (i.e., SAR: 0, 20, 30, 40, 80 and a mmol~ 1-~) on water  diffusivity (D (0)) and unsaturated hydraulic conductivity (k (e)) were evaluated for sam-  ples of sandy loam and clay loam. Both D(e ) and k(e ) were found to be highly dependent  on soil water content, EC and SAR of the infiltrating solution, and texture of sample. In  general, the values of D(e ) and k(e ) decreased with the decrease of water content and EC  and increase of SAR and clay content of the sample. The magnitude of these parameters  at various degrees of water saturation suggested that the adverse effects of high SAR's  and low electrolyte concentrations on the percentage decrease of k(e ) could be reduced  by maintaining a low water content in the transmission zone during infiltration.    INTRODUCTION    The continuous use of saline--sodic waters for irrigation is known to af-  fect both retention and movement of water in soils under saturated and un-  saturated conditions. Quirk and Schofield (1955), McNeal and Coleman  (1966), McNeal (1968) and Rowell et al. (1969) studied the effects of total  salt concentration and cation compositions of water on its transmission  under steady-state saturated conditions. McNeal et al. (1968), Frankel et al.  (1978) and Pupisky and Shainberg (1979), while studying the salt effects on  the hydraulic conductivity (HC) of soils, observed that the soil HC decreased  with increasing SAR and decreasing electrolyte concentrations (EC). While  studying the transient unsaturated flow of water in Pachappa sandy loam,  Gardner et al. (1959) observed that soil water diffusivity (/9 (0)) near satura-  tion moisture content decreased sharply up to one thousand-fold with a de-  crease in total electrolyte concentration (EC) from 300 to 3 meq. 1-1 when  the exchangeable sodium percentage (ESP) of the soil was greater than 25.  Poonia and Pal (1979) observed that the adverse effect of the sodium adsorp-  tion ratio (SAR) of water on D(O ) was less in soil with long-term applications  of farmyard manure than in soil without such treatment. A model developed    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    108    by Russo and Bresler (1977a) approximated the hydraulic conductivity  function for many practical combinations of SAR and EC for the ranges of  soil water contents in which most of the water flow occurs. While studying  the effect of mixed Na-Ca solutions on the hydraulic properties of unsatu-  rated Gilat loam soil samples from Israel, Russo and Bressler (1977b) ob-  served that the effect of EC (2 to 50 meq. V1) on D(O ) was almost nit, when  the soil was Ca-saturated. Pal et al. (1980) reported a decrease in D(0),  weighted mean diffusivity (/9), penetrability (~) and sorptivity (S), with an  increase in SAR and a decrease in EC, particularly in the saturation moisture  ranges of the soils studied. Yet the information on the quantitative assess-  ment of the combined effects of EC, SAR and moisture content on the re-  lative reduction in k(O ), especially for soils from arid and semi-arid parts of  the world, is scanty.  This paper reports the effect of total salts in water and their composition  with respect to Na+ and Ca2+ + Mg2ions on D(O ), k(O ) and moisture reten-  tion at different water suctions of samples of soils formed in alluvium in a  semi-arid region. The combined effects of EC, SAR and 0 on the relative re-  duction in unsaturated hydraulic conductivity were also evaluated.    EXPERIMENTAL    Surface soil samples (0 15 cm), with textures of sandy loam and clay  loam, collected from the Research Farm, Haryana Agricultural University,  Hissar, and the Government Agricultural Farm, Hansi (India), respectively,  were air-dried and passed through a 2-mm sieve. Some of the physicochemi-  cal characteristics of these soil samples are given in Table I.  Waters of different combinations of SARs (i.e., 0, 20, 30, 40, 80 and  mmol1~ 1-') and ECs (i.e., 20, 40, 80, 125 and 250 meq. 1-1) were prepared  using chloride salts of sodium, calcium and magnesium. Calcium and magne-  sium were kept in a 1:1 proportion on an equivalent basis. These solutions  were treated with thiomersal solution to prevent any microbial activity.  Soil samples were put into buckets containing solutions of the desired  SAR with total electrolyte concentrations of 1000 meq. 1-1, and kept over-  night for equilibration. The suspensions were then transferred to Buchner  funnels connected to a suction pump and further leached with a series of  solutions of gradually decreasing electrolyte concentrations but the same  SAR until the electrical conductivity of the effluent attained a value equiva-  lent to that of a 0.01 N solution. The excess salts were removed by washing  the sample with 90% ethanol followed by petroleum ether.  The procedure for the determination of D(0 ) involved carrying out hori-  zontal absorption experiments. Plexiglass columns of 30 cm length and 4.05  cm internal diameter (i.d.), used for the purpose, were made by joining seg-  ments each having a length of 10.5 cm, width of 5 cm, thickness of 0.9 or  1.5 cm with an offcenter hole 4.05 cm in diameter. The segments were placed  over one another in opposite directions, keeping the offcenter hole in the up-    TABLE I  Some physico-chemical properties of soil samples    109    Properties                           Location    Hissar    Hansi    Soils (Sub-group level  taxonomy, Ahuja et al.,  1978)  Particle size distribution (%)  Sand (2 to 0.02 mm)             65  Silt (0.02 to 0.002 mm)          16  Clay (&lt; 0.002 mm)              19  Cation Exchange Capacity            9.3  (meq. per 100 g)  pH 1:2                               8.2  CaCO~ (%)                             0.3  Mineralogical composition  (% of total clay)  Mica                             68  Kaolinite                         16  Vermiculite                       2  Smectite  Chlorite                           8  Mica-chlorite  Quartz                            2  Feldspars                        4    Typic  Camborthid    Episalic  Natrustalf    42  22  36  14.6    8.6  0.8    65  23  3  5  2  2    right position. This was ensured with a wooden roller of the same diameter as  that of the hole. After fitting the segments together, the screws were tightened  on both sides of the column to keep the segments in position and also to avoid  any leakage of water from a column during infiltration. The inlet end of the  column was fitted with a sintered glass disc (Go) of 4 cm diameter. The col-  umns were filled as uniformly as possible with air-dried sandy loam (B.D.,  1.5 + 0.03 g cm-3) or clay loam (B.D., 1.4 + 0.03 g cm-3) samples. The uni-  formity of packing was ensured by adding 60 gm soil material at a time fol-  lowed by 20 tappings with a wooden roller fitted with nails at the end to  avoid layering.  The columns were placed horizontally and waters of different EC but of  the same SAR with which the soil samples had already been equilibrated  were introduced at the inlet end from a Mariotte burette at a constant suc-  tion of ~ 2 cm of water. Small holes were made in the terminal end of the  column to prevent air compression. The experimental set up is shown in  Fig. 1. The experiment was continued until the wetting front had reached a  distance of ~ 25 cm from the source. The time for infiltration was noted and  the source of water disconnected. The segments were quickly pressed down  vertically to avoid further horizontal movement of water. Soil samples from  the segments were collected for measurements of their gravimetric moisture  contents.    110    --~s cmb.---  I L  i  " i  ', ~,!    ....  i    u    -'"'&lt;'-   .71-         i  LEFT   SlOE  ELEVATION  30 Cff',            FRONT   ELEVATION    _      fcm  BURETTE         i  E~ULATOR    i   [  .RIGHT S!OE ELEVATION    PLAN ELEVATION  Fig. 1. Experimental unit for horizontal infiltration.    The values of volumetric moisture contents (0) were plotted against X  (= x/x/t, where x denotes the distance from the inlet end in cm and t the  time of infiltration in hours). D(O)values were calculated using the follow-  ing formula (Bruce and Klute, 1956):  D(O) =-d~k f: XdO                               (1)  dO   i  where 0 i is the initial soil water content.  The moisture retained by the samples at different suctions, h(O ), (i.e.,  0.1, 0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8 and 1.0 atm.), was determined by pressure plate appa-  ratus. In the sandy loam sample, h(8 ) was obtained for each combination of  SARs 0, 20, 40 and 80 and ECS 20, 40, 80 and 250 meq. 1-1, whereas for clay  loam, the h(O ) function was obtained for each combination of SARs 0, 20,  40 and 80 and ECs 20, 80 and 250 meq. 1-I.  The capillary conductivity (k (0)) was calculated using the relationship:  k(O ) = D(O )  dO  -~                                  (2)  where dO/dh is the change in moisture content per twit change in suction.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The quantitative functional relationships among soil water diffusivities  (D (0)), moisture contents (0), and sodium adsorption ratios (SAR) and total    111    electrolyte concentrations (EC) in the equilibrium solutions for sandy loam  and clay loam samples are given in Figs. 2 and 3. For easier comparison, the  abscissa scale is shifted to the right and the data are translated along the  moisture content axis. D(8) increased with the increase in 0, the increase  being more pronounced near saturation. At high moisture contents, water  is conducted in pores of bigger radii and lower tortuosity.  D(O ) decreased with increase in SAR and decrease in EC, the decrease  being more in the higher moisture content range in both samples. For ex-  ample, in the sandy loam, when SAR increased from 0 to 80, D(O ) decreased  from 2.66 to 0.27 cm2 h-1 at EC 40 and 0 0.44 cm3 cm-3. Further, at SAR  40, D(O) decreased from 1.46 to 0.13 cm2 h-1 at 0 0.1 cm3 cm-3 and from  125 to 2.7 cm2 h-1 at 0 0.44 cm3 cm-3 as EC decreased from 250 to 20 meq.  1-~ in both cases. Similarly, in clay loam, when SAR increased from 0 to 80,  D(O) decreased from 1.48 to 0.02 cm2 h-~ at EC 20, and 0 0.10 cm3 cm-3,  whereas it decreased from 105.6 to 0.27 cm2 h-~ at EC 20 and 6 0.47 cm3    I  %    103    102    10~    D 100    I    I    I    ,    J  C 20  /    I0-2~  0    Ol  0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5    '             I  Sandy loam soil    C 40                       C %0                        C 12'5                      C 250    o            i  !  ./ /    SAR  0 0  20  z~ 30  40  [] 80  xoO    ~9( cm3 cm-3 )  Fig. 2. Soil water diffusivity (D) as a function of volumetric water content (a) and sodium  adsorption ratio (SAR) for different electrolyte concentrations (EC, meq. 1-1) of sandy  loam sample.    103    C20    102    101    CIoy IooFn  SOi    IL  %  u   100    C 125    id2~  0 0.1 020.3040.5    &lt;: .40         C 80  )  ,11  i  f:    O(cm3 cm-3 )    C 250  t,    112    SAR  o  0  20  A 30  a 40   80  x oO    Fig. 3. Soil water diffusivity (D) as a function of volumetric water content (0) and sodium  adsorption ratio (SAR) for different electrolyte concentrations (EC, meq. 1-I) of clay  loam sample.    cm-3. In the same way, at SAR 20, D(8) decreased from 1.34 to 0.53 cm2  h-I at 0 0.10 cm3 cm-3 and from 124.52 to 33.87cm2h-1 at0 0.47cm3  cm-3, corresponding to a decrease of EC from 250 to 20 meq. 1-1.  The effect of SAR on the decrease of D(O ) was greater at low electrolyte  levels at all moisture contents. For example, in the sandy loam the ratio of  the maximum D(0 ) [corresponding to SAR0] to the minimum D(O ) [corres-  ponding to SAR 80] was ~ 72 at EC 20 and 0 0.20 cm3 cm-3, whereas this  ratio was only ~ 4 at EC 250 for the same moisture content. The experimen-  tal data, by and large, are in qualitative agreement with those of Gardner et  al. (1959), Christenson and Ferguson (1966), and Russo and Bresler (1977).  The functional relationships between k(8 ), SAR and EC of the infiltrating  water for sandy loam and clay loam samples indicated that the effects of SAR,  EC and @ on k(O )are similar to those on D(8 ).  D(O) and k(O) functions depend upon the distribution of macro- and    113    micro-pores filled with water and total porosity filled with water (Bresler,  1972). The theory of an electrical diffuse double layer (Kemper and Quirk,  1970; Bresler, 1972), as applied to mixed electrolyte systems, also predicts  that at a given moisture content or suction, the distances between clay plate-  lets increase with increase in SAR and decrease in EC. For a constant total  soil volume, changes in spacings between clay platelets result in changes in  pore size distribution. An increase in spacing would cause a decrease in the  ratio of macro- to micro-pores; thus at a given 0, D(O ) would decrease with  an increase in SAR and a decrease in EC.  The results of this investigation further indicated that in both the sandy  loam and clay loam samples, the decrease in D(0 ) with increase in SAR,  particularly at low electrolyte concentrations was less pronounced at low  moisture contents (i.e., up to 0 0.30 cm3 cm-3 for the sandy loam and 0.40  cm3 cm-3 for the clay loam) than at higher moisture contents. For example,  for the sandy loam sample at EC 20, when 0 increased from 0.10 to 0.30  cm3 cm-3, the ratio of the maximum D(O ) [corresponding to SAR 0] to the    loo    i(]-2    i(]-3  50    10c  &gt;    10-1  -o     10-2  o  ~.  5x10-3    100    \  o  e = 0 44   ~o  I        1         I         I    0 = 0.30  I         I          I         I    0.40  I      I     I    e = 0.20  I      I      1  ,me1-1  o    20    ~  ~.                            4o  v  Q"~        o~'~  ~                        ~     80  10-1 _             $~       ~          u   125  10-2    0=] 0.1                                      I      I  0       20     40      60      80      0       20       40     60  Sodium  odsorption  rotio  (SAR)    Fig. 4. Effect of SAR and electrolyte concentration (EC, meq. 1-1) on relative diffusivity  (D*) of sandy loam sample at different volumetric water contents (e, cm3 cm-3).    114    minimum D(O) [corresponding to SAR 80] rose from 66 to 74, whereas  this ratio abruptly rose to 711 when O was 0.40 cm3 cm-3. Similarly, in the  clay loam sample this ratio increased from 70 to 149 corresponding to an  increase in O from 0.10 to 0.40 cm3 cm-3, and it increased sharply to 391  when O increased from 0.40 to 0.47 cm3 cm-3. This may be attributed to  relatively less swelling of clay at lower moisture contents.  The combined effects of SAR, EC and 0 on soil water diffusivity, D(O),  and soil water capillary conductivity, k(0 ), were evaluated from the values of  relative diffusivity, D*(O ), and relative capillary conductivity, k*(0 ). These  parameters were defined as D*(8) = D(O) (SARiCi)/D(8) (SARoC~50), and  k* (O) = k (SARiCi~*/k(SARoC250 8") where 8" = (O ---6 i)/(O s---O i) with Oi and  8s as the initial air-dry and saturation moisture (i.e., moisture content at the  inlet end) contents, respectively. The D*(6 ) function is given in Figs. 4 and 5  for the sandy loam and clay loam samples, respectively. The values of D*(O )  were more sensitive to EC at higher SARs at all O- and 0*-values. At a partic-  ular O or 8" and SAR 20, there was a gradual decrease in the values of D*(O )    100  162               ~o  10-~    6" = 0.47  I         t         I        1-  100  "~          e = o.3o~o  ~- 3X 10-3  I     i      J     J  1o0  10.2  0      20      40     60      @0    e = 0.40                    i  l      I      I  ,  6' =(220  c f rne1-1  o  20     40  ,,    80  o   12..'5   250    J       ~D      ..I  0    20   4    60   80    Sodium  adsorption  ratio (SAR)  Fig. 5. Effect of BAR and electrolyte concentration (EC, meq. l-=) on relative diffusivity  (D*) of clay loam sample at different volumetric water contents (8, cm3 cm-S).    115    with decreases in EC from 250 to 40 meq. 1-'. A sharp decrease was observed,  however, when the concentration of the infiltrating solution decreased from  40 to 20 meq. 1-1. These relationships showed qualitative agreement with  earlier ones of Russo and Bresler (1977b). There were, however, a few points  of difference between the two sets of results. In contrast to curves of Russo  and Bresler those of the present study did not always start from one. This  was because of the fact that the maximum values of D(O) corresponding to  SAR 0 and EC 250 were no longer unique with respect to 0/0s as was the  case in the study by Russo and Bresler. Secondly, the curves of Russo and  Bresler became closer to one another at high SARs and low Cs, whereas in  the present study the curves showed divergence. This might be due to differ-  ences in concentrations of the infiltrating solutions.  The relationships among k*(O ), SAR, EC and 0* help in determining the  values of EC and SAR at which a given percentage reduction in k (0) would  occur at a given value of 0". Such combinations of EC and SAR values for  k*(O) = 0.3, 0.2, 0.1 and 0* = 1 and 0.5 for the sandy loam and clay loam  samples are given in Table II. These figures indicate that at a particular EC,  water of higher SAR could be used at low degrees of moisture saturation  of these soils for the same percentage reduction in unsaturated hydraulic  conductivity. In other words, for the same percentage reduction in k(O),  water of high SAR, even with comparatively lower electrolyte levels, could  be used under unsaturated conditions.    TABLE II  Combinations of electrolyte concentrations (EC) and sodium adsorption ratios (SAR) for  different relative capillary conductivity (k* (0)) values in sandy loam and clay loam sam-  ples    EC           k* (0):  (meq. 1-t)     0.30                 0.20                 0.10    sandy    clay      sandy    clay      sandy    clay  loam     loam     loam     loam     loam     loam    SAR (mmolV' 1-~/2)  0 * = 1.00  20       21.0  40           29.0  80           39.0  250           78.0  0* = 0.50  2O       23.0  40           33.0  80           43.0  250           91.0    7.5                23.0             10.5             27.0             15.0  --          37.0    --         49.0    --  12.0       54.0      16.5      80.0      30.0  18.0             124.0             27.5          172.0             52.5  16.5       26.0      20.0      38.0      30.0  --          42.0     --          58.0     --  19.0               90.0             35.0          190.0             72.5  40,0      140.00   100.0     --         200.0    116    REFERENCES    Ahuja, R.L., Garalapuri, V.N., Manchanda, M.L. and Khanna, S.S., 1978. Physiography  and soil associations of Haryana. J. Indian Soc. Soil Sci., 26: 261--267.  Bresler, E., 1972. Interacting diffuse double layers in mixed mono-divalent ionic systems.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 891--896.  Bruce, R.R. and Klute, A., 1956. Measurement of soil moisture diffusivity. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 20: 458--462.  Christenson, D.R. and Ferguson, H., 1966. The effect of interactions of salts and clays  on unsaturated water flow. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 30: 549--553.  Frenkel, H., Goertzen, J.O. and Rhoades, J.D., 1978. Effect of clay type and content  exchangeable sodium percentage, and electrolyte concentration on clay dispersion and  soil hydraulic conductivity. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 32--39.  Gardner, W.R., Mayhugh, M.S., Goertzen, J.O. and Bower, C.A., 1959. Effect of electro-  lyte concentrations and exchangeable Na percentage on diffusivity of water in soils.  Soil Sci., 88 : 270--274.  Kemper, W.D. and Quirk, J.P., 1970. Graphic presentation of a mathematical solution for  interacting double layers. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 347--350.  McNeal, B.L., 1968. Prediction of the effects of mixed salt solutions on soil hydraulic  conductivity. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 190--193.  McNeal, B.L. and Coleman, N.T., 1966. Effect of solution composition on soil hydraulic  conductivity. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 30: 308--312.  McNeal, B.L., Layfield, D.A., Norvell, W.A. and Rhoades, J.D., 1968. Factors influencing  hydraulic conductivity of soils in the presence of mixed salt solutions. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 32: 187--190.  Pal, R., Singh, S. and Poonia, S.R., 1980. Effect of water quality on water transmission  parameters of unsaturated soils. J. Indian Soc. Soil Sci., 28: 1--9.  Poonia, S.R. and Pal, R., 1979. The effect of organic manuring and water quality on  water transmission parameters and sodification of a sandy loam soil. Agric. Water  Manage., 2: 163--175.  Pupisky, H. and Shainberg, I., 1979. Salt effects on the hydraulic conductivity of a sandy  soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 429--433.  Quirk, J.P. and Schofield, R.K., 1955. The effect of electrolyte concentration on soil  permeability. J. Soil Sci., 6: 163--176.  RoweU, D.L., Payne, D. and Ahmad, N., 1969. The effect of the concentration and  movement of solutions on swelling, dispersion and movement of clay in saline and  alkali soils. J. Soil Sci., 20: 176--188.  Russo, D. and Bresler, E., 1977a. Analysis of the saturated--unsaturated hydraulic con-  ductivity in a mixed sodium-calcium soil system. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 706--710.  Russo, D. and Bresler, E., 1977b. Effect of mixed Na-Ca solutions on the hydraulic  properties of unsaturated soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 713--717.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                AbstractThe effects of electrolyte concentration (i.e., EC: 20, 40, 80, 125 and 250 meq. l−1) and sodium adsorption ratios (i.e., SAR: 0, 20, 30, 40, 80 and α mmol12l−12) on water diffusivity (D (θ)) and unsaturated hydraulic conductivity (κ (θ)) were evaluated for samples of sandy loam and clay loam. Both D(θ) and κ(θ) were found to be highly dependent on soil water content, EC and SAR of the infiltrating solution, and texture of sample. In general, the values of D(θ) and κ(θ) decreased with the decrease of water content and EC and increase of SAR and clay content of the sample. The magnitude of these parameters at various degrees of water saturation suggested that the adverse effects of high SAR's and low electrolyte concentrations on the percentage decrease of κ(θ) could be reduced by maintaining a low water content in the transmission zone during infiltration. 