 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 97--106                                                        97  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -Printed in The Netherlands    THE  ADSORPTION  OF  COPPER BY  SOIL  SAMPLES FROM SCOTLAND  AT LOW EQUILIBRIUM SOLUTION CONCENTRATIONS    R.G. McLAREN1, J.G. WILLIAMS and R.S. SWIFT1  Edinburgh School of Agriculture, West Mains Road, Edinburgh EH9 3JG (Great Britain)  (Received April 2, 1982; accepted after revision November 4, 1982)    ABSTRACT    McLaren, R.G., Williams, J.G. and Swift, R.S., 1983. The adsorption of copper by soil  samples from Scotland at low equilibrium solution concentrations. Geoderma, 30:  97--106.    At low solution concentrations of copper in the presence of 0.05 M CaC12 , adsorption  isotherms for copper on soil samples were essentially linear. Although no direct correla-  tions were found between isotherm gradients and individual soil properties, the gradients  were of the same order of magnitude as predictions based on gradients obtained for some  specific soil components. The soil components which appear to be most important in cop-  per adsorption and which were used to obtain the predictions were organic matter and  iron and manganese oxides. The amounts of adsorbed copper remaining isotopically ex-  changeable or extractable with EDTA in the short term increased with the amount of  copper adsorbed but the proportions of adsorbed copper estimated by each of these tech-  niques remained constant. Concentrations of copper in solution increased (adsorption de-  creased) at pH values below 4.5 and above 6.5.    INTRODUCTION    A recent study on the adsorption of copper by individual soil components  (McLaren et al., 1981) has shown that, within the range of concentrations of  copper in solution found in natural soils, copper adsorption isotherms are es-  sentially linear. It is not feasible to compare these findings with copper ad-  sorption studies carried out with intact soil samples because most previously  published studies have used copper concentrations well in excess of those  found under normal soil conditions (e.g., Cavallaro and McBride, 1978; Lal  et al., 1971; McLaren and Crawford, 1973). In one recent study (Jarvis,  1981), in which low equilibrium copper concentrations were attained, sorp-  tion by soil samples at low concentrations was also found to have an essen-  tially linear relationship with the final concentration of copper in solution.  The object of this study was to examine adsorption of copper by samples  of a range of soils under the same conditions as those used by the authors    1 Present address: Department of Soil Science, Lincoln College, Canterbury, New Zealand.    0016--7061/83/0000--0000/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    0  OO    TABLE I  Properties of experimental soil samples    Soil        Soil series* 1      Soil classification* 1  No.    pH  (CaC12)    Organic  matter  (%)    Oxide * 2    Oxide * 2    Clay  iron       manganese &lt; 2 #  (% Fe203) (% Mn02) (%)    EDTA  extractable  Cu (ppm)    1         Ettrick          non-calcareous gley soil  2         Lauder          brown forest soil  3         Linhope         brown forest soil  4         Sourhope        brown forest soil  5         Hobkirk         brown forest soil  6         Eckford         brown forest soil  7         Ettrick          non-calcareous gley soil  8         Lauder          brown forest soil  9         Linhope         brown forest soil  10         Sourhope        brown forest soil  11         Hobkirk         brown forest soil    5.1                   6.7                  2.33                0.026             27.3                1.24  5.7         4.0         1.74        0.057      18.0        2.18  5.0        5.3        2.33       0.052      18.3       1.89  5.8                  4.2                  1.40                0.076             13.0                2.68  5.7        3.6        0.76       0.013       7.9       1.98  6.5        3.2        0.60       0.015       5.5       0.35  5.3        6.3        1.82       0.024      27.9       1.77  5.4         4.1         2.14        0.156      18.7        2.11  5.2                  4.5                   2.80                0.099             21.1                1.61  5.4                   2.6                  1.63                0.047             13.7                1.75  5.7                   2.6                  0.70                0.022                7.4                0.99    ,1 See Ragg, 1960.  ,2 Extractable in acid ammonium oxalate under U.V. light.    99    when studying adsorption by individual soil components. In addition, the  extent to which added copper, adsorbed by a soil sample, remains isotopical-  ly exchangeable or extractable with ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA)  was studied.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils    Samples of soil (0--200 mm surface layer) were collected from eleven sites  in south east Scotland, the samples were air-dried and ground to pass a 2 mm  stainless-steel sieve before use. The main properties of the samples are shown  in Table I.    Measurement of adsorption and isotopic exchange    Samples of soil (4 g), in duplicate, were equilibrated in polypropylene  centrifuge tubes with 40 ml 0.05 M CaC12 containing known amounts of cop-  per (as CuC12). The amounts of copper added ranged from 0 to 20 pg Cu g-1  air-dry soil. Equilibration was carried out at 20 on an end-over-end shaker  and after an initial 24 h shaking the tubes were centrifuged. At this point  10 t~l of a solution containing high specific activity 64Cu (McLaren et al.,  1981) were added carefully to the supernatant solution. After gentle shaking  to mix the ~4Cu with the supernatant the tubes were shaken vigorously to re-  mix the soil sample and solution. The samples were then re-equilibrated for  a further 24 h.  At the end of this period the tubes were centrifuged and samples of the  supernatant solution taken for copper analysis and measurement of 64Cu  activity as described by McLaren et al. (1981). The amount of copper ad-  sorbed by the sample was calculated from the difference between the initial  and final solution copper concentrations. The amount of isotopically ex-  changeable copper was calculated as described by McLaren and Crawford  (1974).    EDTA-extractable copper    After the sampling of tubes as described above, any remaining supernatant  solution was decanted carefully from the soil residue. The sample was then  extracted with 20 ml 0.04 M EDTA for 1 h at 20 using an end-over-end  shaker. After centrifuging, the concentration of copper in the supernatant  was determined by flame atomic absorption spectrophotometry.  Amounts of copper adsorbed by the soil sample and remaining isotopical-  ly exchangeable or extractable with EDTA were calculated by subtraction of  the amounts of native soil copper determined in these fractions (i.e., values  determined for softs without added copper).    100    RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS    Adsorption isotherms for all eleven soil samples determined at low solu-  tion copper concentrations, like those obtained previously for individual soil  components (McLaren et al., 1981), were linear. Isotherms are shown in  Fig. 1. The gradients of the isotherms were calculated by regression analysis  and the values obtained, together with the standard errors, are listed in  Table II. The gradients were of the same order of magnitude as those ob-  tained by Jarvis (1981) for a selection of samples of soils from England and  Wales, although the range of values was slightly higher (0.83--2.09 1 g-1 in  this study compared to 0.1--1.17 1 g-1 obtained by Jarvis).  Values for soil organic materials and iron and manganese oxides were  shown to range from 6.0 to 117 1 g-1 and for various clay minerals from    0.3      o  0  L  O_  O_  o  t J    0.2    0.1    0.3    0                            0'.4 ~,IM    O..S    0.1    0     5  x  11  o.1      o'.2     0.3     o14 ~M    ///~m~/"         p l e s                A  ,4   g    7  a 1(]  o.1      o'.2     o'.3    equilibrium  copper  concenSration in solution    Fig. 1. Adsorption isotherms for copper on soil samples.    TABLE II  Observed and predicted copper adsorption isotherm gradients    101    Soil      Observed gradient*~    s.e.           Predicted gradient (gp),2  No.    (1 g-~ )                       (1 g-~ )    1       1,51                   + 0.04        2.34  2        2,09                    -+ 0.24        1.59  3        1,74                    _+ 0.12        2.11  4       1.76                   + 0.09        1.48  5        1.02                    + 0.02        1.03  6       1.83                   + 0.14        0.89  7        1.04                    -+ 0.04        2.04  8        2.04                    +- 0.10        1.87  9        1.34                    -+ 0.15        2.19  10        0.96                    +_ 0.04        1.26  11       0.83                   _+ 0.04        0.83    *~ Linear correlation coefficients (r) for isotherms were all between 0.99 and 1.00.  *: t-test of observed versus predicted values; t - 0.696 -- not significant (20 degrees of free-  dom).    0.02 to 4.7 1 g-1 (McLaren et al., 1981). It is clear that, with the exception  of values for some clay minerals, the gradients for intact soil samples are far  smaller than those determined for individual soil components. This is not  surprising inasmuch as soils contain relatively small amounts of the compo-  nents most active in adsorbing copper and the soil gradients are based on the  total weights of soil samples including any inert material.  Two types of approach were used in an attempt to determine the relative  importance of individual soil components in affecting the copper adsorption  characteristics of entire soil samples. The first approach examined correla-  tions between isotherm gradients and individual soil properties such as organ-  ic matter, oxide content and pH. No significant correlations of this type  were found, however. Similarly, Jarvis (1981), apart from a correlation with  pH, found little direct relationship between isotherm gradients and the soil  properties expected to influence copper adsorption. In both studies the ab-  sence of significant correlations may have been due to several causes.  The number of soil samples was relatively small and the range of values  of different soil properties such as organic matter and oxide content were  limited. In contrast McLaren and Crawford (1973), sampling a much wider  range of soil types, obtained a significant multiple correlation between ad-  sorption of copper and soil organic matter and manganese content. These  workers, however, used the maximum copper adsorption capacity of the  soil sample in the correlation and such a measure is perhaps more likely to  show a correlation with the gross composition of the sample than an index  of adsorption obtained with only a small percentage of possible adsorption  sites occupied. A comparison with soil adsorption capacities determined by    102    McLaren and Crawford (1973) would suggest that less than 2% of possible  adsorption sites were occupied in this present study.  The second approach to investigate the relative importance of individual  soil components in copper adsorption involved the prediction of soil adsorp-  tion gradients from the measured properties of the soil samples and the  gradients obtained by McLaren et al. (1981) for individual materials. It was  considered that organic matter and the iron and manganese oxide contents  were most likely to affect copper adsorption by the samples and therefore  these three properties were used in the prediction.  The gradients were predicted as follows. Predicted gradient for intact soil  sample (gp ) = (gmx cx/lO0);gmx is the gradient for component x (McLaren  et al., 1981); Cx is the percentage content of component x in the sample  (Table I).  The results are shown in Table II and although there is no significant cor-  relation between the predicted and measured values, both sets of data cover  almost exactly the same range of values. In fact some individual pairs of  values are in excellent agreement. The similarity of the two sets of data is  perhaps remarkable when one considers the assumptions involved in the cal-  culation of the predicted values. The soil constituents will certainly not be  identical to the model compounds studied by McLaren et al. (1981) and  would occur in complex associations with one another rather than as discrete  particles. Organic materials and oxides will occur as coatings or bound to  clay minerals and in this way some adsorption sites are likely to be obscured.  The fact that the predicted values were of the same order of magnitude as  the measured values suggests that the hypothesis on the importance of the  oxides and organic matter is plausible.    EDTA-extractability and isotopic-exchangeability of adsorbed added copper    For the range of copper additions examined in this study, the amounts of  added copper adsorbed that remained isotopically exchangeable or extract-  able with EDTA increased with the amounts of copper adsorbed. The pro-  portion of adsorbed copper in both these forms, however, remained con-  stant irrespective of the amount of copper adsorbed. This is clearly demon-  strated for sample number 5 in Fig. 2; both forms of adsorbed copper in-  crease linearly with the equilibrium solution concentration of copper. Sim-  ilar results were obtained for all other soil samples. This suggests that, for  the concentration range studied, there is likely to be little variation in the  strength of bonding of the adsorbed added copper with the amount of cop-  per adsorbed.  Such a conclusion would seem to conflict with the results of Davies et al.  (1969), Plessis and Burger (1971) and Petruzzelli and Guidi (1976). These  workers studying copper adsorption by soil humic and clay fractions found  decreases in the proportion retained with increases in the amounts of copper  adsorbed. Their observations, however, were made in a study of much wider    103    x total  Cu adsorbed  ~"         adsorbed EDTA-extnactable Cu  c~                                                able/~     03    o adsorbed isotopically-exchange  "0  "d  L  +-~   02   L.  o  n  L.  o  0.1  O  L  o  u  i  0        0.~        0.2        0.3       014  equilibrium  copper concentration  in solution  (~M)  Fig. 2. EDTA-extractability and isotopic exchangeability of copper adsorbed by soil  sample number 5.    TABLE III  Percentages of adsorbed copper remaining isotopically exchangeable and EDTA-extract-  able    Soil      Isotopically-      s.c.          EDTA-           s.c.  No.       exchangeable Cu               extractable CU    1        57.6              3.1        87.6              + 1.7  2       54.0             7.0        83.6             1.5  3       58.8             4.2        85.6             0.6  4       49.0             + 5.1        87.4             0.9  5        61.3              2.7        84.8              0.7  6       69.4             8.4        91.2             2.5  7       59.2             2.8        83.3             1.1  8        42.0              2.8        84.9              0.8  9        67.0              7.7        86.7              1.3  10        58.7              5.2        78.9              3.4  11       65.3              2.1        87.6             + 1.0    ranges of copper additions and probably involved a degree of non-specific  adsorption. In addition, in this present study the time of contact between  soil sample and copper was relatively short and the recovery of adsorbed  added copper was high (80--90%, see Table III). Williams and McLaren    104    (1982) have shown that recovery by EDTA can decrease with time and thus  a different picture might emerge with longer contact.  Values for isotopicaUy exchangeable copper are much lower than the  EDTA-extractable levels with only 42% and 69% of the adsorbed copper re-  maining isotopically exchangeable  (Table  III).  It has been suggested  (Williams and McLaren, 1982) that such differences between EDTA-extract-  ability and isotopic exchangeability are an indication that EDTA-extraction  tends to overestimate soil copper availability. There were no significant cor-  relations between soil properties and the amounts of copper remaining iso-  topically exchangeable or extractable with EDTA in individual soil samples.    Effect of pH on copper adsorption    The samples examined in this study adsorbed between 95 and 99% of the  copper added and the effect of pH is demonstrated best by examination of  equilibrium solution concentration of Cu rather than Cu uptake. The results  obtained by varying the pH of soil sample number 10, with and without  added copper, are shown in Fig. 3. In the presence of added copper, concen-  trations of Cu in solution increased markedly (and hence adsorption de-  creased) at pH values below 4.5 and above 6.5 These increases presumably    c  0  0  r'-  c  0  :D  (D  L.   U  C  0  U  a_  0  U  E  E.  I:::)-  19    0,5  added copper  0.4  ~          o no added copper  X  0.3  0.~  011  01                ,                ~                ,                ,  3             4              5             6             7    pH  Fig. 3. Effect of pH on equilibrium solution copper concentrations of soil sample number  I0.    105    included some desorption of native soil copper inasmuch as small increases  in solution concentrations of copper were observed at high and low pH's for  the soil sample without added copper.  The increases in copper concentration at low pH were much smaller than  those observed by many previous workers (e.g., Cavallaro and McBride,  1978; Kuo and Baker, 1980). Those studies were, however, carried out using  unrealistically high copper additions. McLaren et al. (1981) and Williams  (1981), working with individual soil components at low copper concentra-  tions, produced evidence suggesting that changes in soil pH are unlikely to  have major effects on the distribution of copper between soil solution and  solid phases. The result for the unamended soil sample shown in Fig. 3  would appear to support this conclusion. In addition, the differences in cop-  per concentration with pH for the sample with added copper might well  have been smaller had adsorption taken place before rather than concurrent-  ly with pH adjustment. Williams (1981) has demonstrated that copper ad-  sorbed by soil components is by no means as readily desorbed back into so-  lution.  The increased concentrations of copper in solution at high pH are prob-  ably due to the increased solubility of organic matter and resulting forma-  tion of soluble copper--organic matter complexes. Such an increase in cop-  per concentration at higher pH values has also been observed by McBride and  Blasiak (1979) and Jarvis (1981) and does not necessarily indicate an in-  crease in availability.    CONCLUSIONS    Within the range of concentrations of copper in solution found in natural  soils, adsorption isotherms for copper on entire soil samples were essentially  linear. Isotherm gradients were of the same order of magnitude as calculated  predictions based on the organic matter and iron and manganese oxide con-  tents of the samples. It is proposed that these constituents control the ad-  sorption properties of the entire soil samples.  Not all of the added copper adsorbed by the soil samples remained ex-  tractable with EDTA or isotopically exchangeable with 64Cu, however; for  the range of copper additions studied, the proportion of adsorbed copper  estimated by each of these techniques remained constant.  The concentrations of both native and added copper in solution were  influenced by pH showing increases both below pH 4.5 and above pH 6.5.  The increase in copper concentration at low pH, however, was much smaller  than those observed by workers using high copper additions.  It is now generally accepted that the concentrations of copper in soil solu-  tions are controlled by adsorption reactions of copper with the soil's solid  phase and by reactions with soluble organic matter (Robson, 1981). The  amounts of copper added to soil samples in this study were deliberately re-  stricted to the equivalent amounts which might be used for soil treatment    106    of copper deficiency in the field. It is considered that the results obtained,  like those obtained for low concentrations by Jarvis (1981), give a much  more useful picture of soil copper relationships than observations made on  adding abnormally high amounts of copper to soil samples and are far more  likely to relate to the problems of copper availability to plants. Indeed it is  clear from the results described in this paper that there can be substantial  differences in the trends observed at low copper concentrations compared  with those observed by other workers using high concentrations.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS  The authors would like to thank the International Copper Research Asso-  ciation for assisting in the finance of this work.    REFERENCES    Cavallaro, N. and McBride, M.B,, 1978. Copper and cadmium adsorption characteristics  of selected acid and calcareous soils, Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 550--556.  Davies, R.I., Cheshire, M.V. and Graham-Boyce, I.J., 1969. Retention of low levels of  copper by humic acid. J. Soil Sci., 20: 65--71.  Jarvis, S.C., 1981. Copper sorption by soils at low concentrations and relation to uptake  by plants. J. Soil Sci., 32: 257--269.  Kuo, S. and Baker, A.S., 1980. Sorption of copper, zinc and cadmium by some acid soils.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 969--974.  Lal, S., De, S.K. and Chandra, S., 1971. Adsorption of copper by softs in aqueous media  at different temperatures. Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Bodenkd., 128: 54--60.  McBride, M.B. and Blasiak, J.J., 1979. Zinc and copper solubility as a function of pH in  an acid soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 866--870.  McLaren, R.G. and Crawford, D.V., 1973. Studies on soil copper, II. The specific adsorp-  tion of copper by softs. J. Soil Sci., 24: 443--452.  McLaren, R.G. and Crawford, D.V., 1974. Studies on soil copper, III. Isotopically ex-  changeable copper in soils. J. Soil Sci., 25: 111--119.  McLaren, R.G., Swift, R.S. and Williams, J.G., 1981. The adsorption of copper by soil  materials at low equilibrium solution concentrations. J. Soil Sci., 32: 247--256.  Petruzzelli, G. and Guidi, G., 1976. Influence of soil organic matter on copper availabil-  ity to plants. Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Bodenkd., 697-684.  Plessis, S.F.Du. and Burger, R.Du.T., 1971. Die spesifieke adsorptie van koper deur klei-  minerale en grondfraksies. Agrochemophysica, 3: 1--10.  Ragg, J.G., 1960. The Soils of the Country round Kelso and Lauder. Memoirs of the  Soil Survey of Great Britain, H.M.S.O.  Robson, A.D., 1981. Copper in soils and plants: an overview. In: J.F. Loneragan, A.D.  Robson and R.D. Graham (Editors), Copper in Soils and Plants. Academic Press,  Australia, pp. 351--354.  Williams, J.G., 1981. Studies of Soft Copper in Relation to its Availability to Plants. Ph.D.  Thesis, Edinburgh University, Edinburgh.  Williams, J.G. and McLaren, R.G., 1982. Effects of dry and moist incubation of soils on  the extractability of native and applied soil copper. Plant Soil 64: 215--224.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractAt low solution concentrations of copper in the presence of 0.05 M CaCl2, adsorption isotherms for copper on soil samples were essentially linear. Although no direct correlations were found between isotherm gradients and individual soil properties, the gradients were of the same order of magnitude as predictions based on gradients obtained for some specific soil components. The soil components which appear to be most important in copper adsorption and which were used to obtain the predictions were organic matter and iron and manganese oxides. The amounts of adsorbed copper remaining isotopically exchangeable or extractable with EDTA in the short term increased with the amount of copper adsorbed but the proportions of adsorbed copper estimated by each of these techniques remained constant. Concentrations of copper in solution increased (adsorption decreased) at pH values below 4.5 and above 6.5. 