 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 315--322                                                     315  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Soil Monolith Paper 1. Thionic Fluvisol (Sulfic Tropaquept), Thailand. Inter-  national Soil Museum, Wageningen, 1981, 48 pp.    Soil Monolith Paper 5. Humic Acrisol (Orthoxic Palehumult), Jamaica.  J.J. Scholten and W. Andriesse. International Soil Museum, Wageningen,  1982, 64 pp.    ISM Soil Monolith Paper 6. Acri-Orthic Ferralsol (Haplic Acrorthox), Ja-  maica. W. Andriesse and J.J. Scholten. International Soil Museum, Wage-  ningen, 1982, 64 pp.  Price each Dfl. 15.00/US$6.00 plus postage; paperbacks.    These are the first three publications in a series of papers dealing with  soils that represent important units of the FAO-Unesco Soil Map of the  World and of which monoliths are on exhibit at the International Soil Refer-  ence and Information Centre, formerly the International Soil Museum, in  Wageningen, The Netherlands. (Volumes 2, 3, 4, and 7 are presently in  various stages of preparation and describe an Orthic Ferralsol (Typic Haplus-  tox), a Placic Podzol (Placaquod), a Humic Nitosol (Oxic Plaeustalf), and a  Calcic Chernozem (Vermic Haplustoll), respectively.)  The three published papers are structured according to a common outline  that includes major chapters on General Information and Setting, Site  and Soil, Soil Genesis and Classification, Land Evaluation, Suggested Read-  ing, and References. Appendices contain field and laboratory soil data,  micromorphological descriptions, and analytical methods. Each publication  is accompanied by a set of eight color slides showing the landscape, the  soil profile in the field, the soil monolith, and various thin sections.  The papers are logically organized, thoroughly researched and well-  written. A general description of the central concept of the respective soil  and its regional and global extent and use is followed by a detailed and  comprehensive characterization of the environment and a description of the  soil and the associated soil pattern. Subsequently soil formation is discussed  in considerable depth and, commendable, this discussion is based on very  complete field and laboratory data rather than on speculative ideas. The  classification of the soil is represented in various systems, among them the  Legend for the FAO-Unesco Soil Map of the World, the USDA Soil Taxo-  nomy, two French classifications (CPCS 1967 and ORSTOM 1979), the  Brazilian classification, the former American classification of 1938, and  local schemes. The treatment of this subject is exhaustive, particularly in  papers 5 and 6. In the chapter on Land Evaluation interpretative assess-  ments of agricultural land use are made according to (1) local practices and  (2) the FAO Framework for Land Evaluation. In discussing the land qualities    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    316    postulated in the Framework (oxygen availability, moisture availability,  inherent fertility, etc.), emphasis is placed on those qualities that are con-  straints to cultivation. Papers 5 and 6 also present the placement of the  soils in the fertility capability classification of Buol et al. The referen-  ces cited are comprehensive and reflect dilligent research.  In conjunction with the FAO--Unesco Soil Map of the World, the soil  monolith papers are particularly useful for university teachers and students  of soil science as well as all those interested in the study of soils in relation  to their potential for agricultural use. It is hoped, therefore, that the series  will be continued; perhaps under a new general title such as "Benchmark  Soils of the World", as "Soil Monolith Paper" fails to convey the scope and  depth of the publications.    F.H. BEINROTH  (Mayaguez, P.R. )    C02 and Plants, The Response of Plant to Rising Levels of Atmospheric  Carbon Dioxide. Edgar R. Lemon (Editor). Westview Press, Boulder,  1983. AAAS Selected Symposia Series, 84. XXII + 280 pp., US $25.00  (hardcover).    Plants are intimately involved with the CO2 in our biosphere. Hence  any reasonable attempt to understand the rising levels of CO2 in our atmo-  sphere must include plants. Vast portions of our world are covered with  skin-thick layers of plant cells with metabolize tons of CO2 daily. C02 and  Plants takes a holistic viewpoint of living plants and their known responses  to CO2 with emphasis upon predictable responses of plants to a doubling  or tripling of our atmospheric CO2 level.  C02 and Plants is a thorough presentation of our current level of know-  ledge and understanding of plants and their responses to COz. The motiva-  tion for collecting this information is the well-documented increases in  atmospheric CO2 which have occurred over the last 2.5 decades plus the  uncertainty of how plants may respond to further increases in their CO2  level. The book is an outgrowth of a conference held in Athens, Georgia  in May 1982 which was attended by about 130 persons, with heavy emphasis  upon plant research scientists, from various parts of the world.  The scientists divided into six topical groups to consider CO2 and plants  regarding: carbon metabolism; physiological effects; plant growth and  development; microbial effects; terrestrial plant communities; and aquatic  plant communities. Each group took a holistic approach to documenting  our current understanding of the influences of CO2 upon plants. Thus  this book is more than asking obvious questions such as "how is photo-  synthesis influenced by changing CO2 levels". Indeed many pertinent and                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 