 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 107--118                                                  107  I~sevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    FACTORS INFLUENCING INTERACTIONS OF ORGANOPHOSPHORUS  PESTICIDES WITH MONTMORILLONITE    M. S/~NCHEZ CAMAZANO and M.J. S/~NCHEZ MARTfN  Centro de Edafologfa y Biologfa Aplicada del C.S.I.C., Salamanca (Spain)  (Received May 15, 1981; accepted after revision July 1, 1982)    ABSTRACT    S~nchez Camazano, M. and S~nchez Martfn, M.J., 1983. Factors influencing interactions  of organophosphorus pesticides with montmorillonite. Geoderma, 29: 107--118.    A summary is made of the results obtained from the study of the adsorption and inter-  action mechanisms of a series of organophosphorus pesticides (phosphates, phosphorothio-  lates, phosphorothionates and phosphorothiolothionates) with montmorillonite, with the  aim of establishing relationships between the chemical structure of these compounds and  the adsorption and interaction mechanisms with this clay. Many of the organophosphorus  pesticides studied are adsorbed into the interlayer space of montmorillonite. The inter-  calation causes different degrees of expansion (different types of complexes) principally  as a function of the chemical structure of the organic compound. The presence in the or-  ganic molecules of the P-~---O and P--~--S groups and the size and composition (functional  groups present) of the radicals are the two most important factors. Both the nature of in-  terlayer cations and the previous hydration status of montmorillonite influence adsorption.  In some cases the polarizing power of the interlayer cation is a conditioning factor of the  degree of interlayer expansion, whereas in others the cation charge is responsible for this.  Results of infrared spectroscopy show that interaction is of the dipole ion type and that  it depends on the presence of the P-------O or P-~---S group in the molecule and also on the func-  tional groups present in the side chains. These factors, together with the situation of these  latter groups in the side chains, condition the arrangement adopted by the molecules of a  pesticide in the interlayer space.    INTRODUCTION    The adsorption of pesticides by the colloidal fraction is the most important  process among those which condition the evolution of these compounds in  soil. Furthermore, clay minerals are frequently used as a support in the formu-  lation of pesticides. It is therefore of interest to understand (a) the interaction  mechanisms of clays with pesticides, (b) the adsorption--desorption processes  of pesticides by clays in an aqueous medium and (c) the influence of the clays  on the degradation of pesticides. Adsorption not only decreases the bioactivity  and microbial degradation rate of these compounds but also, in certain cases,  may delay or catalyze their degradation by hydrolysis (Mortland and Raman,  1967; Konrad et al., 1967, 1969).    0016-7061/83/0000--0000/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    108    Accordingly, the Unit of Physical Chemistry and Clay Mineralogy of the  Centro de Edafologfa y Biologfa Aplicada de Salamanca has for some years now  been studying the interactions between clays and organophosphorus pesticides.  In the first part of a broad research program, great emphasis has been placed on  the adsorption and interaction mechanisms of these compounds with mont-  morillonite. This silicate, of great adsorption capacity, is a common compo-  nent of large groups of soils.  Studies on the interactions of dichlorvos (S~mchez Camazano and S~nchez  Martfn, 1977); sumithion (Sfinchez Martfn and S~nchez Camazano, 1978);  phosmet (Sfinchez Camazano and Sfinchez Martfn, 1980), phosdrin (Sfinchez  Martfn and Sfinchez Camazano, 1980) and dimethoate (Sfinchez Camazano  and Sfinchez Martfn, 1980) with montmorillonite have already been published.  Pesticides mentioned in text are chemically identified in Table VII. These  works may be consulted by readers interested in the results and interpretations  mentioned briefly in the present paper.  The aim of this paper is to summarize the results obtained in this field up  to the present moment and to make a comparative study of them in order to  establish the relationships between the chemical structure of the compounds  and the adsorption mechanisms by montmoriUonite. This could be of great  value in the manufacture of pesticides and the preparation of formulations  which axe more bioactive and less contaminating in soil.    MATERIAL AND METHODS    Homoionic samples of Tidinit montmorillonite (Morroco) were used in the  study. This mineral has been previously characterized by chemical and physico-  chemical methods (Guti~rrez Rios and Hem~ndo, 1947, 1948; Guti~rrez Rios  and LSpez Gonz~lez, 1952). The sample used has a surface area of 750 m2/g  and a cation exchange capacity of 80 meq./100g.  Adsorption must depend on the chemical structure of the pesticide in ques-  tion and on the characteristics of montmorillonite. Accordingly, a series of  pesticides was used (phosphates, phosphorothiolates, phosphorothionates and  phosphorothiolothionates) and the influence of the nature of the exchangeable  catiort and the hydration status of montmorillonite on adsorption was studied.  Organophosphorus pesticides are only slightly water-soluble and thus an  organic solvent was used in the study. The samples of montmorillonite were  treated with 0.2 M solutions of the pesticides in 1,2,dichloroethane. The du-  ration of treatment was two days at room temperature. It had previously been  ascertained that in general the pesticides were adsorbed by montmorillonite  in a dilute aqueous solution and also that the 1,2 dichloroethane does not  complex with montmorillonite. The techniques used in the study were X-ray  diffraction and I.R spectroscopy. The methods followed in the preparation of  the samples have been described elsewhere (S~nchez Camazano and S~.nchez  Martfn, 1977). The determination of the amounts of phosdrin and phosmet  adsorbed by montmorillonite was carried out by treating the samples of the    109    clay with 0.2 M solutions of the pesticides in 1,2 dichloroethane for two days.  The clay was then separated by centrifugation and the pesticides were deter-  mined in the supernatant fluid by U.V. spectroscopy (adsorption maximum of  phosmet= 232 nm; phosdrin= 230 nm). The difference between the initial con-  centration and that present in the supernatant fluid was considered the amount  adsorbed in each case.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Most of the organophosphorus pesticides studied are adsorbed into the Ca-  montmorillonite interlayer space, forming interlayer complexes of definite  d001 spacings (Table I; Fig. 1). The corresponding crystalline powder diffraction  diagrams show a regular sequence of reflections. The formation of complexes  represents increases which fall between 6.45 A and 17.15 A above the d001  value of 9.6 A of dehydrated montmorillonite.  These different degrees of expansion, caused by the intercalation of the  pesticides into the interlayer space of the silicate, depend on the chemical  structure of the organic compounds. The presence in the molecules of the    TABLE I  Basal spacings d001 of Ca-montmorillonite treated with different organophosphorus pesticides    Pesticide*             dooI (A)   A (A)    A Dichlorvos         26.75      17.15  Phosdrin          20.06     10.46  Bidrin              16.35       6.75  20.06      10.46  Phosphamidon     16.35       6.75  20.06      10.46  Ciodrin            16.35       6.75  Monocrotophos     20.06      10.46  Metasystox         20.06      10.46    B Sumithion         16.05       6.45  Diazinon            15.35       5.75  Dursban           15.35       5.75  Zinophos          17.66       7.06    C Dimethoate        16.35       6.75  Phosmet            16.05       6.45  Azinphosmethyl    16.05       6.45  Malathion           16.05       6.45  Methyltrithion      16.35       6.75  Carbophenothion   15.35       5.75    *A = phosphates and phosphorothiolates; B = phosphorothionates; C = phosphorothiolo-  thionates.    110    Fig. 1. X ray diagrams of: A. Ca--montmorillonite; B. Ca--montmorillonite--dichlorvos  complex (d0o1 = 26.75 A); C. Ca--montmorillonite--phosdrin complex (do0z = 20.06 A);  D. Ca--montmorillonite--dimethoate complex (do0~ = 16.35 A).    P-~--O or P=S groups and the size (in particular the length) and composition  (the functional groups present) of the radicals are the two most important  factors. Therefore, the phosphates and phosphorothiolates tend to form com-  plexes of high basal spacing (Table I). Within this group of compounds, all  with methyl radicals, the size of the third radical, in turn, influences adsorp-  tion. Thus, expansion is greater with dichlorvos, forming a high spacing com-  plex (A = 17.15 A); with phosdrin, monocrotophos and metasystox expansion  is intermediate (A = 10.46 )k), and in the case of those with a larger third rad-  ical they partly form complexes of intermediate and low spacing (bidrin or  phosphamidon) or they form complexes of low spacing (ciodrin). These com-  plexes of high, intermediate and low spacings correspond to the intercalation  of three, two or one molecular layer of pesticide, as will be detailed below.  The phosphorothionates and the phosphorothiolothionates studied never  form two-layer complexes with montmorillonite, in agreement with the values  of the increases shown in Table I. This fact shows the influence of the mole-  cule's polarity on adsorption; the polarity decreases as a result of substitution    111    of the oxygen atom by the sulfur atom. If the radicals are methyl groups  (sumithion, parathion, phosmet, azinphosmethyl, methyltrithion) they form  monolayer complexes, whereas if they are ethyl groups (diazinon, dursban,  carbophenothion), they do not form definite interlayer complexes (lack of  rationality of basal reflections). The increase in spacing which takes place in  these latter cases is due to partial solvation of the montmorillonite layers. An  exception among the latter is zinophos which forms a monolayer complex  and this is probably due to the smaller size of the complex radical and to the  nature and disposition of the functional groups in it. The influence of the ra-  dicals on expansion may be appreciated better if the results of the adsorption  of carbophenothion and methyltrition are compared: their structure differs  only in the radicals, ethyl in the first case and methyl in the second. The ho-  mogeneity of the d001 spacings of the monolayer complexes would suggest the  same interlayer disposition of the molecule in all cases. In the case of zinophos,  with ethyl radicals, the d001 spacing corresponding to the complex increases  slightly, showing that the ethyl or methyl radicals must determine the spacing.  The high spacing complexes formed by phosphates are stable, whereas the  complex formed by phosphorothiolate is unstable for long periods of time in  normal laboratory conditions. On treatment of the complexes under vacuum  at 0.1 mm Hg with simultaneous heating, they consistently move towards the  monolayer complex, this being the stable phase under such conditions.  In general, these compounds are only slightly water-soluble. In a very dilute  aqueous solution, the solvation of montmorillonite is partial. When compounds  are soluble, as in the case of some phosphates, the complexes formed in a con-  centrated aqueous solution have the same basal spacings as those formed in an  organic medium. E~en then, a tendency towards the formation of low-spacing  complexes may be observed. This is due to the competitive effect of the water  for the adsorption sites. Only phosdrin, of smaller molecular size, gives a com-  plex with 20.06 A spacing.  In some cases, the previous hydration status of Ca-montmorillonite is not a  determining factor in the formation of two-layer complexes with phosphates  (dichlorvos, phosdrin), though in other cases it is (monocrotophos, metasystox)  (Table II). In the latter cases, previous hydration is necessary, corresponding  to relative humidities of 16% and 35%, respectively (d00~ spacings of  montmorillonite 11.3 A and 13.2 A, respectively). The situation is the same  in the formation of the monolayer complex by phosphorothiolothionates.  This suggests that the compounds, which due to the aforementioned charac-  teristics are intercalated with less ease, need a certain previous degree of inter-  layer separation for expansion corresponding to one or two molecular layers  of the pesticide to take place.  The nature of the interlayer exchangeable cation of the montmoriUonite is  another of the factors influencing the adsorption of organophosphorus pesti-  cides by this clay (Table III). The samples saturated with cations of high po-  larizing power (Cu2 Ni2+, and Mg2 always form complexes with high spacing  with phosphates and phosphorothiolates other than ciodrin (with a complex    112  TABLE II  Influence of the hydration status of the Ca-montmorillonite in the adsorption of organo-  phosphorus pesticides by montmorillonite; d001 spacings of the complexes    Pesticide*             Relative humidity (%)    0       4.5      16      35      75      100    A Dichlorvos         26.75   26.75   26.75   26.75   26.75   26.75  Phosdrin           20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06  Monocrotophos     16.35   16.35   20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06  Metasystox         15.38   15.38   16.05   20.06   20.06   20.06    B Sumithion          12.10   13.06   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05    C Dimethoate        16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35  Phosmet           16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05  Azinphosmethyl    15.38   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05  Malathion          12.62   15.35   16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35    *A = phosphates and phosphorothiolates; B = phosphorothionates; C = phosphorothio-  lothionates.    TABLE III    Basal spacings (d001 ) of homoionic montmorillonites treated with organophosphorus  pesticides    Pesticide*              Interlayer cation    Na+      K+       Ba2+     Ca2+     Mg2    Cu2+     Ni2+    A Dichlorvos         29.42   25.22   25.22  Phosdrin           20.06   1,6.05   16.05  20.06  Bidrin              16.35   15.77   16.35  20.06  Phosphamidon      16.35   15.77   15.77    Ciodrin            16.05   14.97   15.23  Monocrotophos     16.35   15.78   16.35  Metasystox         16.35   16.05   16.05  20.06    26.75   26.75   26.75   26.75  20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06  ].6.35   20.06   20.06   20.06  20.06  16.35   20.06   20.06   20.06  20.06  16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35  20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06  20.06   20.06   20.06   20.06    B Sumithion          14.01   14.01   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05  Diazinon           --      13.06   14.02   15.35   15.35   17.66   17.66  Zinophos           16.05   14.97   17.66   17.66   17.66   17.66   17.66    C Dimethoate        15.77   15.77   16.05   16.35   16.35   16.35   16.35  Phosmet           14.24   13.38   16.05   16.05   16.05   14.15   16.05  16.05  Azinphosmethyl    14.72   13.10   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05  Malathion         15.77  14.72  16.05  16.35  16.35  16.35   16.35  Methyltrithion      14.97   14.97   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05   16.05    *A ffi phosphates and phosphorothiolates; B = phosphorothionates; C = phosphorothio-  lothionates.    113    radical of greater length). When the polarizing power decreases, so does the  tendency for the formation of two-layer complexes. Thus the Ca2+ and the  Na+ samples form complexes with one or two molecular layers, depending on  the size of the complex radical of the pesticide. The samples saturated with  cations of lower polarizing power (K* and Ba2 form multilayer complexes  with the phosphate of smaller molecular size (dichlorvos) monolayers with  those of intermediate sizes and no definite complexes with those of greater  molecular size.  In the case of the phosphorothionates and the phosphorothiolothionates,  the samples saturated with divalent cations form monolayer complexes,  whereas those saturated with monovalent cations do not. This is in agreement  with the smaller space available in the interlayer per monovalent exchangeable  cation together with the great molecular size and lesser polarity of these com-  pounds.  Diazinon, which does not form a complex with Ca-montmorillonite, does  form one with the Cu2+ and Ni2+ samples. These cations of the transition met-  als with incomplete d orbitals generally interact more strongly than the other  cations with electron donor atoms of organic molecules.  Table IV includes the stretching frequencies of the P==O and P-----S groups of  the I.R. spectra of the pesticides studied, both when free and when adsorbed  by homoionic montmorillonites and Fig. 2 shows some of the spectra. These  frequencies shift to lower values when the pesticides are adsorbed by  montmorillonite. Furthermore, the magnitude of this decrease is a function    TABLE IV    P-~--O and P-------S stretching frequencies (cm-I ) of some organophosphorus pesticides in the  unadsorbed phase and when adsorbed oW montmorillonite containing different interlayer  cations    Pesticide* i             Unadsorbed   Interlayer cation    K+       Na+      Ba2+     Ca2+     Mg2+    Cu=+     Ni2+    A Dichlo~os          1275          1260    1250    1250    1240    1240    1230    1230  Phosdrin            1275          1270    1270    1265    1260    1255    1250    1250  Monocrotophos     1265          1260    1255    1250    1250    1245    1240    1240    B Sumithion          650          648    646    647    646    645    638    638  648*2   636*2   637*2   626*2   620*2   618*2   616*2    C Dimethoate         650          645    635    645    640    635    630    635  645*2   625*2   635*2   620*2   620*2   615*2   610*2  Phosmet             642          642     642     642     642     642     630     630  638*2   632*2   638*2   632*2   630*=   625*=   625*2  Azinphosmethyl     645          640    630    630    628    625    622    620  Malathion           645          640     620     630    620     618     610     610    *J A = phosphates and phosphorothiolates; B = phosphorothionates; C = phosphorothiolothionates.  ,2 Dehydrated complexes (heated under vacum at 100C).    114    ~  000       3000  ,  ,  i  ,  i  ,    2000   1800   1500   1~00  1200   1100  800    500  '  I   '  f  '  I  '   I  '   i  '  I  '  ~  '    V '    f  ~000               :)000                 2000   1600  1500   1400   1200   1100   500    50'0  c m ,-.1  Fig. 2. Infrared spectra of: A. Ca--montmorillonite; ]3. monocrotophos; C. Ca--montmo-  riUonite--monocrotophos complex; D. dimethoate; K Ca--rnontmorillonite--dimethoate  complex.    of the polarizing power of the exchangeable cation. This latter fact shows that  the interactions take place between the exchangeable cation and the P----O and  P-=S groups. The stretching frequencies of the P-----O group do not vary with  the hydration status of the complexes though for those of the P=S group they  do vary as a function of the hydration status of the complex (Table IV), shifting  towards lower values when the complexes are heated to ll0 under vacuum.  This shows that interaction is direct in the case of phosphates and that in the  phosphorothionates and phosphorothiolothionates is either direct or through  the water molecules, according to the hydration status of the complexes.    115    When there are other electron-donor functional groups in the molecule be-  sides P=O and P=S, the I.R. spectra show a shift in the stretching frequencies  of the corresponding groups when the compounds are adsorbed. These shifts  are related to the polarizing power of the exchangeable cation and show that  in monolayer complexes the interaction often takes place simultaneously  through these groups and through the P==O or P=S. Table V shows the  stretching frequencies of the C-~O groups of some of the pesticides when they  are free and when they are adsorbed by different homoionic montmorillonites.  The simultaneous interaction depends on the nature of the electron donor  group in question, on its distance from the P=O or P=S group and on the ro-  tation possibilities of the radical where the group is found. Thus, in sumithion,  interaction takes place only through the P=S group (Fig. 3, a), through the  P=O and C-----O groups in phosdrin and monocrotophos, through the P=S and  C=O groups in dimethoate, phosmet, azinphosmethyl and malathion and  through P---~-S and N in zinophos and diazinon. In all two-layer complexes, in-  teraction takes place only through the P==O group.  Finally, a study was made of the possible arrangements adopted by the  molecules in the interlayer space. The following were taken as bases: (1) the  increases in spacings undergone by montmorillonite in the adsorption of differ-  ent pesticides; (2) the molecular dimensions of the pesticides studied deter-  mined from the angles and bonding distances of crystalline structures of or-  ganophosphorus pesticides given in the literature and by atomic scale models  (Rohrbaugh et al., 1976; Baughman and Jacobson, 1977; Lapp and Jacobson,    TABLE V  C=O stretching frequencies (cm-I) of some pesticides in the unadsorbed phase and when adsorbed on  montmorillonitc containing different interlayer cations    Pesticide            Unadsorbed     Interlayer cation    Na+       K+        Ba2+      Ca2+      Mg2+     Cu2+      Ni2+    Phosdnn           1710           1690     1695     1685     1690     1685     1680     1675  Monocrotophos     1670            1655     1670     1660     1655     1650     1640     1640  Dimetho~e        1645           1635     1645     1640     1635     1632     1620     1615  Phosmet           1710           1700     1703     1695     1700     1695     1690     1690    ~.///.,,///////..,..,/.,[//.,,////./////.  CH3~0  "  ........  .............  ;"  /  /t  ....  ~           /  ,' O'--~..~r ~CH ~CH~        ,,'  I    --~,,         ~'C        I  /      / "~._~C~ ~N07 ,:  ..(  .........  Z  ..........  C__,~  ................  ."  CH3/O'  YlII///I////////I/I/III/////////////////////////////~    ~//////////" // ///////~  CH3 "''" 0  %.  '/0//    --   ~.0       ,/  /"  "~-/C ~CH--C~"        "  ,,,'     / /         ~. ,.,, ,.,'  CH3IU  y/////////////////////////////////////////////~    Fig. 3. Proposed arrangements of pesticides molecules in the interlayer space of montmo-  rillonite: a) sumithion; b) monocrotophos.    116    1980); (3) the atoms involved in the interaction, deduced from the previously  mentioned I.R. results; (4) the fact that the molecules should be oriented with  their positive groups towards the negative surfaces of the oxygen atoms and  with their negative groups towards the interlayer.  According to these bases, the complexes with d00, spacings of 26.75 A and  20.06   should be three- and two-layer, respectively. The molecules must be  arranged with the plane of the P~----O group perpendicular to the surface of ox-  ygen atoms of the montmorillonite, two molecules interacting with exchange-  able cations through the P-~O group. The increases calculated for this dimen-  sion of the molecules, 5.2--5.3 A, are approximately half the experimentally  observed increases for the two-layer complex by X-rays or A = 10.46 A. In  the complex with spacing of 26.75 A, corresponding to dichlorvos, the third  molecule must be bound by a hydrogen bond to one of the other two mole-  cules.  In agreement with the molecular dimensions of the pesticides in question,  the increases in spacing observed experimentally of 6.45--6.75 should cor-  respond to monolayer complexes. The molecular dimensions close to these  increases are the CH3--CH3 distances which range between 6.43 and 6.70, ac-  cording to the pesticide. The molecular arrangements compatible with these  increases, in agreement with what was reported in the preceding paragraph,  are those shown schematically in figure 3 for sumithion and monocrotophos.  The CH3--CH3 distance calculated for these pesticides is 6.43 A. Each of the  methyl groups is on a surface of oxygen atoms and the P=S group and the  third radical are oriented towards the interlayer space. The sulfur atom of  the P=S groups and the oxygen atom of the C-~-O group of the monocrotophos  molecule interact simultaneously with the interlayer cations of montmorillonite.  In the case of sumithion, interaction takes place only through the sulfur atom  of the P=S group.  Finally, the amounts of some pesticides adsorbed by montmoriUonite in the  formation of mono- and two-layer complexes were determined. The results  (Table VI) show that the monolayer complex corresponds to the adsorption    TABLE VI  Amounts of some pesticides adsorbed by homoionic montmorillonites    Pesticide   Interlayer     Amount adsorbed           d001 A   A A     Type of complex  cation    g/100 g clay  molecules  per cation    Phosmet   Na          10.40         0.40          14.24    4.64   partial solvation  Phosmet   Ca2         16.48         1.30          16.05    6.45   monolayer  Phosdrin   K           18.82         1.05          16.05    6.45   monolayer  Phosdrin   Na+           35.48         1.98          20.06   10.46   two-layer  Phosdrin   Ca2+          21.50         2.40          20.06   10.46   two-layer    TABLE VII  Chemical designations of pesticides mentioned in text    Common name     Chemical name    Azinphosmethyl  Bidrin  Carbophenothion  Ciodrin  Diazinon  Dichlorvos  Dimethoate  Dursban  Malathion  Metasystox  Methyltrithion  Monocrotophos  Phosdrin  Phosmet  Phosphamidon  Sumithion  Zinophos    0,0--dimethyl, S--(4--oxobenzotriazino--3--methyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0, 0--dimethyl, 0--(N,N--dimethylcarbamoyl--l--methylvinyl ) phosphate  0,0--diethyl, S--(4--chlorophenylthiomethyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0,0---dimethyl, 0---(1--methyl, 2--(1--phenylethoxycarbonyl)vinyl) phosphate  0,0---diethyl, 0--(2--isopropyl--4--methylpyrimidyl--6) phosphorothionate  0,0--dimethyl, 0--2, 2--dichlorovinyl phosphate  0,0--dimethyl, S---(N--methyl~arbamoylmethyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0,0--diethyl, 0--(3,5,6--trichloropyridyl) phosphorothionate  0,0--dimethyl, S--(1,2--dicarboethoxyethyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0,0--dimethyl, S--(2---ethylsulfinyl)ethyl phosphorothiolate  0,0---dimethyl, S--(4---chlorophenylthiomethyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0,0--dimethyl, 0--(N--methylcarbamoyl--1--methylvinyl) phosphate  0,O-dimethyl, 0--(1--methyl--2---carbomethoxyvinyl) phosphate  0,0--dimethyl, S--(N--phthalimidomethyl) phosphorothiolothionate  0,0--dimethyl, 0---(2--chloro--2--N, N--diethylcarbamoyl--1--methylvinyl) phosphate  0,0---dimethyl, 0---(4--nitro--3--methylphenyl) phosphorothionate  0,0--diethyl, 0--pyrazinyl phosphorothionate    118    of one molecule per exchangeable cation. The formation of the two-layer  complex corresponds to the adsorption of two molecules per exchangeable  cation, which according to what has been reported above, should be arranged  in the form of one molecule on each of the surfaces of the oxygen atoms of  the montmorillonite. The surface occupied by the adsorbed molecules, accord-  ing to their size, is very similar to the surface available in the interlayer per  mono- or divalent exchangeable cation.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    We would like to thank Mr. N. Skinner for his invaluable help in translating  the manuscript.    REFERENCES    Baughman, R.G. and Jacobson, R.A., 1977. Crystal and molecular structure of organo-  phosphorus insecticides 5- Fospirate. J. Agric. Food Chem., 25: 582--587.  Guti~rrez Rios, F. and Heruando, L., 1947. Yacimientos de bentonita en Marruecos  Espafiol (I). An. Edafol. Agrobiol., 6: 53--77.  Guti~rrez Rios, E. and Hernando, L., 1948. Yacimientos de bentonita en Marruecos  Espafiol (II). An. Edafol. Agrobiol., 7: 623--631.  Guti~rrez Rios, E. and LSpez Gonzfdez, J.D., 1952. Accion de los acidos fuertes sobre los  silicatos de la serie isomorfa montmorillonita-beidellita. An. Edafol. Agrobiol., 11:  225--254.  Konrad, J.G., Armstrong, D.E. and Chesters, G., 1967. Soil degradation of diazinon a  phosphorothioate insecticide. Agron. J., 59: 591--594.  '  Konrad, J.G., Chesters, G. and Armstrong, D.C., 1969. Soil degradation of malathion a  phosphorodithioate insecticide. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 259--262.  Lapp, R.L. and Jacobson, R.A., 1980. Crystal and molecular structures of organophosphorus  insecticides. 13.S--Isopropyl O--methyl 0--(3,5,6--trichloro--2--pyridyl)phosphor-  amidothioate and dimethoate. J. Agric. Food Chem., 28: 755--759.  Montland, M.M. and Raman, K.V., 1967. Catalytic hydrolysis of some organic phosphate  pesticides by copper (II). J. Agric. Food Chem., 15: 163--167.  Rohrbaugh, W.J., Meyers, E.K. and Jacobson, R.A., 1976. Crystal and molecular structure  of organophosphorus insecticides, 3. Azinphos--methyl. J. A_gric. Food Chem., 24:  713--717.  S~nchez Camazano, M. and S#[nchez Martin, M.J., 1977. InteracciSn entre pesticidas  organosforados y minerales de la arcilla, 1. Adsorcibn de 0--0 dimetil 0--2,2 diclorovinil  fosfato (diclorvos) pot montmorillonita. An. Edafol. Agrobiol., 36: 725--737.  Sfmchez Martin, M.J. and S~nchez Camazano, M., 1978. InteracciSn de pesticidas  organosfosforados con montmorillonita, 2. Sumition. Anu. Cent. Edafol. Biol. Apl.  Salamanca, 4: 223--236.  S~nchez Camazano, M. and S~nchez Martin, M.J., 1980. Interaction of phosmet with  montmorillonite. Soil Sci., 129: 115--118.  S~nchez Martin, M.J. and S~nchez Camazano, M., 1980. InteracciSn de fosdrin con  montmorillonita. Clay Miner., 15: 15--23.  S,~nchez Camazano, M. and S~nchez Martin, M.J., 1980. InteracciSn de pesticidas organo-  fosforados con montmorillonita, HI. Dimetoato. An. Edafol. Agrobiol., 39: 659--671.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractA summary is made of the results obtained from the study of the adsorption and interaction mechanisms of a series of organophosphorus pesticides (phosphates, phosphorothiolates, phosphorothionates and phosphorothiolothionates) with montmorillonite, with the aim of establishing relationships between the chemical structure of these compounds and the adsorption and interaction mechanisms with this clay. Many of the organophosphorus pesticides studied are adsorbed into the interlayer space of montmorillonite. The intercalation causes different degrees of expansion (different types of complexes) principally as a function of the chemical structure of the organic compound. The presence in the organic molecules of the P0 and PS groups and the size and composition (functional groups present) of the radicals are the two most important factors. Both the nature of interlayer cations and the previous hydration status of montmorillonite influence adsorption. In some cases the polarizing power of the interlayer cation is a conditioning factor of the degree of interlayer expansion, whereas in others the cation charge is responsible for this. Results of infrared spectroscopy show that interaction is of the dipole ion type and that it depends on the presence of the P0 or PS group in the molecule and also on the functional groups present in the side chains. These factors, together with the situation of these latter groups in the side chains, condition the arrangement adopted by the molecules of a pesticide in the interlayer space. 