 Geoderma, 23 (1980) 299--302                                                   299  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    HYDRAZINE DERIVATIVES AT Fe3SITES IN HUMIC MATERIALS    S.M. GRIFFITH', J. SILVER' and M. SCHNITZER2  i Departments of Soil Science and Chemistry, The University of the West Indies, St.  Augustine (Trinidad)  2 Soil Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Central Experimental Farm Ottawa,  Ontario KIAOC6 (Canada)  (Received September 6, 1979; accepted September 25, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Griffith, S.M., Silver, J. and Schnitzer, M., 1980. Hydrazine derivatives at Fe3sites in  humic materials. Geoderma, 23: 299--302.    Data obtained from Mdssbauer spectroscopy and infrared spectrophotometry are inter-  preted to yield additional information on the Fe3environment in humic materials. The  quadrupole doublet with I.S. = 0.94 mm/sec and Q.S. = 2.76 mm/sec is due to the fact  that hydrazine not only reduces Fe3but forms a complex with it. Infrared evidence indi-  cates that an organic hydrazinium salt is formed in the interaction.    INTRODUCTION    Considerable information is available in the literature on the chemistry and  characteristics of Fe--Ha (humic acid) complexes, but relatively little is  known about the physical and chemical properties of Fe-binding sites, their  environments and the oxidation states of these materials. Senesi et al. (1977)  have advanced the idea, on the basis of ESR and preliminary MSssbauer in-  vestigations of Fe~-HA complexes, that two or more Fea* binding sites occur  in humic materials. This paper reports on additional information resulting  from a continuation of the M6ssbauer spectroscopy and infrared spectro-  photometry studies.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Methods used for the extraction, separation and purification of HA's from  the soils have been described previously (Griffith and Schnitzer, 1975).  Chemical reduction of the HA's with hydrazine and details of the M6ssbauer  apparatus are reported elsewhere (Senesi et al., 1977). FeCI3 and mont-  morillonite samples were reduced with hydrazine by the same method.  The Mbssbauer apparatus consisted of a homebuilt spectrometer and  multi-channel analyser. The constant acceleration spectrometer was operated    300    on a sawtooth waveform mode. The source was a I mCi Co5~ in rhodium.  The solid absorbers were sealed on a card with 'sellotape'. The absorber thick  ness was about 0.02 g cm2 . Velocity calibrations were carried out using thin  10 mg cm-2 high purity Fe foils. The spectra were analysed by a simple non-  linear least squares fitting program, and all isomer shifts are referred to  natural iron.  Infrared spectra were obtained with KBr pellets. Either one milligram HA,  fulvic acid (FA) -- a more reactive humic fraction -- or a reduced sample of  these fractions was pelleted with 400 mg KBr. Spectra were taken on a  Beckman IR12 spectrophotometer.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    M6ssbauer data are shown in Table I. The derivative of hydrazine with  FeC13 gives a black compound, which is pyrophobic in the anhydrous state.    TABLE I    Data from M6ssbauer spectra  Samples                   Sites              I.S. (5)         Q.S. (a)  (mm/sec)        (mm/sec)    FeCl3 (NH2NH2 treated)    --  Montmorillonite             1  Reduced montmorillonite    1  2    Original HA2    Reduced HA2    1.02             2.67  0.30         0.61  0.30             0.61  1.06        2.60    1                    0.18             0.67  2                   0.65             0.68  3             0.40         0.60    1             0.14         0.59  2             0.40         0.70  3                     0.94              2.67    To judge from the Mossbauer data and the black colour, the compound re-  sembles the {Fe(N2H4)2 } C12.2H20 complex described in the literature  (Braibanti et al., 1968; Aliev et al., 1972; Starodub et al., 1975). M6ssbauer  parameters for this complex are similar to those for the Fe2site 2 in the  montmorillonite sample treated with hydrazine, suggesting that after the  hydrazine reduces the Fe3in the clay it also complexes with it. M6ssbauer  data for the Fe3site in the untreated montmorillonite and for site 1 in the  reduced montmorillonite sample are similar to those found in dioctahedral  layer silicates by other workers (Weaver et al., 1967; Malathi et al., 1969;  Tennakoon et al., 1974). Our data show that not all of the Fe~in mont-  morillonite can be reduced by hydrazine.    301    Previous work with infrared spectra has indicated that neither purified HA  nor purified FA exhibits intense vibrations between 900 cm-1 and 1000 cm-1  (Griffith and Schnitzer, 1975), yet both hydrazine derivatives of HA and FA  have intense vibrations at 960 cm-1, which can be assigned to the ~ (N--N)  stretching bond of the hydrazine molecule. In fact, a stretching frequency  that is greater than v (N--N) = 885 cm-i implies interaction, either by con-  jugation or by field effect, of one lone pair or both of hydrazine and the  residual of the molecule (Braibanti et al., 1968).  Using the information that Fe3treated with hydrazine may not only be  reduced but during reduction can also complex with hydrazine, we can now  make a more complete interpretation of the HA2 MOssbauer spectra of Senesi  et al. (1977). MOssbauer data for site 3 in the reduced HA2 are similar to  those of the hydrazine reduced FeC13 and for site 2 in the reduced mont-  morillonite (Table I). It appears that this third site in the reduced HA2 is  the only site available for ready attack by hydrazine.  Infrared spectra of the reduced HA and reduced FA indicate that these  compounds contain hydrazinium cations, in that the strong vibration at  960 cm-1 can be assigned to H2N-NH3(Braibanti et al., 1968). The down-  ward shift of frequency for vibrations of CO2 H groups of HA and FA  (1,725 cm-1 C=O of CO2H, C=O stretch of carbonyl and 1230 cm-1 C-O stretch  or OH deformation of CO2H) to broad bands at frequencies consistent with  COO- (near 1,600 cm-1 and 1,100 cm-') (Schnitzer and Griffith, 1975) relate to  a change in the structural arrangement of CO2 H following addition of hydra-  zine. It does not, however, indicate interaction of hydrazine with carbonyl  carbon of the CO2 H groups, for the NH3-derivative has undergone protona-  tion to form the hydrazinium ion, and so conditions, particularly pH, were  not appropriate for addition to proceed. Another possible way in which  hydrazine may interact with humic materials at the Fe3site to form an  organic salt or monodentate complex is as follows:  O                                O         , H  "                                  II             I  R-C-OH+Fe3H2N-NH2 ~R-C-O-Fe-N-NH3I-F  (1)  where R represents the residual of the molecule in the humic materials.  This suggests that Fe3in the other two sites is complexed with HA in such  a way that the HA either sterically hinders reaction with hydrazine and/or  that the Fe3is linked to the HA so energetically, possibly through different  functional groups, that reaction with hydrazine is inhibited.  It appears therefore, that the environment of Fe3in site 3 of the HA  differs significantly from those of Fe3in the other two sites.    REFERENCES    Aiiev, R.Ya., Kuliev, A.D. and Klyuchnikov, N.G., 1972. Reaction of hydrazine with  iron salts and some non-ferrous metals and role of complexing in hydrazine-acid  washings of thermal power equipment. Zh. Neorg. Khim. (Leningrad), 19(10): 2891--  2893 (in Russian).    302    Braibanti, A., Dallavalle, F., Pellinghelli, M.A. and Leporati, E., 1968. The nitrogen--  nitrogen stretching band in hydrazine derivatives and complexes. Inorg. Chem., 7(7):  1430--1433.  Griffith, S.M. and Schnitzer, M., 1975. Analytical characteristics of humic and fulvic  acids extracted from tropical volcanic soils. Proe. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 39: 861--867.  Malathi, N., Purl, S.P. and Saraswat, I.P., 1969. MSssbauer studies of iron in illite and  montmorillonite. J. Phys. Soc. Japan, 26: 680--683.  Schnitzer, M. and Griffith, S.M., 1975. Novel method for estimating hydrogen-bonded  CO: H groups in humic substances. Can. J. Soil Sci., 55: 491--493.  Senesi, M., Griffith, S.M. and Schnitzer, M., 1977. Binding of F'e3+ by humic materials.  Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 41: 969--976.  Starodub, V.A., Novakovshii, M.S., Kirichenko, V.G., Chekin, V.V. and Velikodnyi, A.I.  1975. Study of iron (II) chloride complexes with phenylhydrazine and its derivatives  using nuclear gamma resonance spectroscopy. Koord Khim., 1(12): 1706--1710 (in  Russian).  Tennakoon, D.T.B., Thomas, J.M. and Tricker, M.J., 1974. Surface and intercalate  chemistry of layered silicates, II. An iron-57 MSssbauer study of the role of lattice-  substituted iron in the benzidine blue reaction of montinorillonite. J. Chem. Soc.,  3(DT): 2211--2215.  Weaver, C.E., Wampter, J.M. and Pecuil, T.E., 1967. M~ssbauer analysis of iron in clay  minerals. Science, 156: 504--508.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   AbstractData obtained from Mössbauer spectroscopy and infrared spectrophotometry are interpreted to yield additional information on the Fe3+ environment in humic materials. The quadrupole doublet with I.S. = 0.94 mm/sec and Q.S. = 2.76 mm/sec is due to the fact that hydrazine not only reduces Fe3+ but forms a complex with it. Infrared evidence indicates that an organic hydrazinium salt is formed in the interaction. 