 249    Announcement    Tenth Conference of the International Soil Tillage Research Organization,  8--12 July 1985, at the University of Guelph, Ontario, Canada.    Mare theme. Reduced tillage -- rational use in sustained production.  Invited review papers will discuss the present understanding of soil tillage by  geographic-climatic-soil regions and will consider for each region the essential  requirements for tillage to sustain high yields, the machinery presently avail-  able to execute the required tillage treatments, and any approaches to pre-  dicting tillage requirements for specific soil-crop conditions. Invited review  papers will be published in advance of the Conference in a special issue of  Soil and Tillage Research.  Further mformatzon. The Secretary of the Organizing Committee, Prof.  T.B. Daynard (University of Guelph, Ontario Agricultural College, Depart-  ment of Crop Science, Guelph, Ont. N1G 2Wl, Canada) and the Secretary-  General of ISTRO, Ir. C. van Ouwerkerk (P.O. Box 30003, 9750 TA Haren  (Gn), The Netherlands), will be pleased to answer any questions about the  Conference.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       