 Geoderma, 18 (:977) 241--249                                                     241  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    COMPOSITION AND MINERALOGY OF IRON-MANGANESE CON-  CRETIONS FROM SOME SOILS OF THE INDO-GANGETIC PLAIN IN  NORTHWEST INDIA    P.S. SIDHU*~ , J.L. SEHGAL.2 , M.K. SINHA and N.S. RANDHAWA  Department of Soils, Punjab Agricultural University, Ludhiana, Punjab (India)  (Received November 12, 1976; accepted January 20, 1977)    ABSTRACT    Sidhu, P.S., Sehgal, J.L., Sinha, M.K. and Randhawa, N.S., 1977. Composition and miner-  alogy of iron-manganese concretions from some soils of the Indo-Gangetic plain in  northwest India. Geoderma, 18: 241--249.    Iron-manganese concretions from three reference soil series of the Indo-Gangetic plain  of Punjab have been investigated for their composition, micromorphology and mineralogy.  The data show that amounts of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn in the concretions are higher  than in the surrounding soil matrix. The contents of Mn, Co and Ni increase and that of  Fe decreases with the increasing size of concretions. Cu or Zn contents do not show any  systematic differences with concretion size. A major portion of these elements is oxalate-  and dithionite-extractable. A minor fraction is present in the silicate structure as well as  in the pyrophosphate-extractable forms. The Fe and Mn compounds present in the con-  cretions are x-ray amorphous. The concretions appear to have developed in situ.    INTRODUCTION    Secondary iron and manganese compounds occur in soils in several forms  such as concretions, nodules, pans, coatings and mottles. These features are  often clearly visible in the field and are used as diagnostic indmators of soil  hydromorphism (Bogdanov and Voropayeva, 1969; Soil Survey Staff, 1975).  Numerous studies have indicated that (1) Fe-Mn concretions are character-  ized by higher concentrations of Fe and Mn than the surrounding soil matrix  (Winters, 1938; Taylor et al., 1964; Polteva and Sokolova, 1967; Phillippe  et al., 1972; Gallaher et al., 1973; Pawluk and Dumanski, 1973) and (2) other  metal ions are concentrated at the same time (Taylor and McKenzie, 1966;  Jenne, 1968; Childs, 1975). Cobalt is associated mainly with secondary Mn  minerals in several soils of Australia (Taylor and McKenzie, 1966; Taylor,  1968), and the significance of that association to crop production has been    *~ Present address: Department of Soil Science and Plant Nutrition, University of Western  Australia, Nedlands, WA 6009, Australia.  *2 Present address: Bureau of Soil Studies and Design, SOSLR, Al-Mansur, Baghdad, lraq.    242    demonstrated (Adams et al., 1969). Similar associations of trace elements  with secondary iron oxides and hydroxides have also been reported (Le Riche  and Weir, 1963).  The presence of several minerals and chemical components in Fe-Mn con-  cretions requires the use of differential or selective dissolution techniques  (Mitchell et al., 1964) for elucidating the associations of different elements  in the concretions. The present study is an attempt to differentiate various  forms of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn present in Fe-Mn concretions and to  evaluate their mineralogy and micromorphology.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The Fe-Mn concretions used in this study were separated from the  Ghabdan, Jatwan and Balewal soil series representing the Salic Natraqualf,  Aeric Halaquept and Typic Ustochrept sub-groups, respectively. The Ghabdan  and Jatwan series are saline-sodic and the Balewal series is an associated cul-  tivated soil that is not saline-sodic. Details of the occurrence, properties and  genesis of these soils are available elsewhere (Sehgal et al., 1973), but a pro-  file description of the Jatwan soil is given below:  Ap (0--15 cm)  Dark grayish-brown (10 YR 4/3) clay loam; weak, medium, subangular blocky;  friable; slight effervescence; many, medium and coarse roots; clear, smooth  boundary.    B1 (15--28 cm)  Dark grayish-brown (10 YR 4/3} clay loam; moderate, medium, subangular  blocky; firm; few, fine, faint, dark yellowish-brown (10 YR 4/4) mottles;  slight effervescence; many, fine and medium roots; gradual, smooth boundary.    B21 (28--52 cm)  Dark grayish-brown (2.5 Y 4/2) clay loam; moderate, medium, subangular  blocky; firm; few, fine, distinct, dark yellowish brown (10 YR 4/4) mottles;  few, small Fe-Mn concretions; slight effervescence; few, fine roots; diffuse,  smooth boundary.    B22 (52--76 cm)  Olive brown (2.5 Y 4/3) clay; moderate, medium, subangular blocky; firm;  very dark grayish-brown (2.5 Y 3/4) coatings; many, fine, distinct, dark  yellowish-brown (10 YR 4/4) mottles; common, small Fe-Mn concretions;  slight effervescence; very few, fine roots; diffuse, smooth boundary.    B23 (76--105 cm)  Olive-brown (2.5 Y 4/4) clay loam; moderate, medium, subangular blocky;  firm; very dark grayish brown (2.5 Y 3/2) coatings; many, fine, distinct, dark    243    yellowish-brown (10 YR 4/4) mottles; common, small Fe-Mn concretions;  slight effervescence; gradual, smooth boundary.    B31 (105--150 cm)  Dark grayish-brown (2.5 Y 4/2) clay loam; moderate, medium, subangular  blocky; firm; very dark grayish-brown (2.5 Y 3/2) coatings; many, fine,  distinct, dark yellowish-brown (10 YR4/4) mottles; common, small Fe-Mn  concretions; slight effervescence; gradual, smooth boundary.    B32 (150 cm +)  Olive-brown (2.5 Y 4/4) sandy clay loam; weak, medium, subangular blocky;  friable; abundant, fine, distinct dark brown (7.5 YR 3/2) mottles; common,  small Fe-Mn concretions; slight effervescence.    Concretions from the selected horizons of these soils (Table I) were sepa-  rated by wet sieving after dispersing the soil with sodium hexametaphosphate,  washed repeatedly with deionised water to remove adhering soil particles and  dried at 105C. The concretions from each horizon were subdivided into two  size groups (1/2 mm and &gt;2 mm) by dry sieving and finely ground in an agate  pestle and mortar.  The characterization of different forms of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn was  done by selective dissolution techniques. The extractants used were:  (1) One overnight extraction with sodium pyrophosphate (McKeague,  1967).  (2) Two 4-h extractions with acid ammonium oxalate (McKeague and Day,  1966).  (3) Two 1A-h extractions with dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate mixture (Mehra  and Jackson, 1960).    TABLE I  Description of concretion samples from soils developed on alluvium    Soil                    Location   Horizon    Depth      Concretion  (cm)       content  (% by weight)    Ghabdan loam         305'N   B22t       24--49     2.5  (Salic Natraqualf)      758'E    B23t       49--64     2.7  B31        64--88     3.2  B32        88--107    2.6    Jatwan clay-loam      303'N   B22        52--76     1.9  (Aeric Halaquept)      759~E    B23        76--105    2.3    Balewal sandy-loam    306'N    B22        51--82     1.6  (Typic Ustochrept)    753'E    B23        82--94     1.8    244    (4) Ten 24-h extractions with 0.5 N HC1.  For the estimation of total elemental contents, the concretions were dis-  solved in hydrofluoric acid. The determinations of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn  were carried out using an atomic absorption spectrophotometer.  The x-ray diffraction patterns were obtained on a Philips diffractometer,  using Fe-flltered Co Ks radiations. Thin sections were prepared as described  by Brewer (1964) and examined under a petrographic microscope.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Morphology    The concretions studied were reddish-brown to brown in colour, sub-  rounded in shape and non-magnetic with hardness of 2 to 3 mohs. Under the  microscope, most of the concretions exhibited randomly distributed grains  of primary minerals (quartz, mica and feldspars) which were cemented by  non-birefringent substances (probably Fe-Mn oxides and hydroxides), having  a reddish-brown colour in reflected light. The concretions showed massive  undifferentiated and concentric internal fabrics. Individual concretions ex-  hibited considerable variability in the number and thickness of concentric  rings. In gencral, the concretions from the Ghabdan soil exhibited better  concentric orientation. Thin sections of a soil matrix containing imbedded  concretions showed diffuse boundaries between the concretions and adja-  cent soil materials. No Fe or Mn minerals were identified in the thin sections.    Composition    The contents of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn in the concretions are con-  siderably higher than those in the surrounding soil matrix (Table II). The  highest accumulation is found in the case of Mn, the contents of which are  about 70 times higher in the concretions than in the surrounding soil matrix.  The size of concretions within a particular horizon appears to have a pronounced  effect on Fe, Mn, Co and Ni contents. The amount of Mn, Co and Ni in-  creases with the increasing size of concretions, whereas the reverse happens in  the case of Fe. However, there is no clear relationship between the concre-  tion size and Cu or Zn content.  The Fe : Mn ratio deceases with an increase in concretion size in all hori-  zons (Table II). This could possibly be due to the differences in the geochem-  ical behaviour of these elements. It is welt known that Mn compounds are  more soluble and mobile than Fe compounds under comparable environ-  ments (Cronan and Thomas, 1972; Patrick and Delaune, 1972). It is probable  that as the concretion formation progresses, Mn accumulates at a faster rate  than Fe thus causing a decrease in the Fe : Mn ratios in larger concretions.  The accumulation of Co, Ni, Cu and Zn in these concretions appears to be  due to the scavenging properties of the oxides and hydroxides of Fe and Mn    245    TABLE II  Contents of certain elements in Fe-Mn concretions    Soil        Horizon    Concretion    Fe      Mn     Co      Ni      Cu      Zn      Fe:Mn  series                  size (mm)     (%)     (%)     (ppm)   (ppm)  (ppm)  (ppm)  ratio    Ghabdan   B22t       1--2           10.06   3.12     361     291     251     138       3.22  &gt; 2            8.19   4.43     478     392     361     112       1.85  B23t       1--2           10.39   3.57     406     330     268     127       2.91  &gt; 2            8.47   4.77     512     438     203     126      1.78  B31        1--2           10.21   3.31     380     316     263     133      3.08  &gt; 2            8.39   4.71     506     422     207     113       1.78  B32      1--2         9.82  3.28   377    317    270    126     2.99  &gt; 2         8.23  4.57   492    416    213    117     1.80    Jatwan     R22        1--2            8.39   1.35    151     319      71      95      6.21  &gt; 2            6.46   4.46    344     416      88     128      1.45  B23        1--2            7.15   1.19    135     295      79      77      6.01  &gt; 2            5.98   4.04    304     365      74     134      1.48    Balewal    B22        1--2          13.02   2.97    280     305     111     129      4.38  &gt; 2         9.16  3.62   297    318    169    135     2.53  B23      1--2        13.82  2.77   274    261    137    141     4.99  &gt; 2         8.62  3.40   289    296    165    121     2.54    Average concretions                    9.15   3.47    349     345     177     122      2.64  Average soil                            2.13   0.05      37      63      39      34     42.60    for these transition metal ions whereby these are able to sorb them from  aqueous solutions (McKenzie, 1972; Loganathan and Burau, 1973; Forbes  et al., 1976). Such concretionary matrices have been reported to control the  solubility of Co, Ni, Cu and Zn in soils (Jenne, 1968), and may be regarded  as an important phase regulating the activity of these ions in the soil solution.  The increase in Mn, Co and Ni contents with increasing concretion size in  all horizons suggests that Co and Ni are probably associated with the Mn-  components of concretions. McKenzie (1972) also reported that Co, Ni and  Cu can replace Mn in certain Mn minerals depending upon its valence and  position in the crystal structure. These observations are consistent with pre-  dictions from crystal field theory that elements with high crystal field stabili-  zation energies can displace Mn and this displacement ultimately confers  greater stability on the mineral (McKenzie, 1972; Loganathan and Burau,  1973).    Forms of elements  The amounts of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn extracted from concretions  by pyrophosphate, oxalate and dithionite are plotted in Fig.1. Pyrophosphate    246    6-  ~  2-    1oF                    ~oor-  8 "                  Mn      300~    Co    2o0[-  150  IW~,,rophosphate                                        ~aOxatate  10o                          []]]]] Dithionite  IS~[icatStructure    50    Fig.1. Mean amounts of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn extracted from the concretions by  pyrophosphate, oxalate and dithionite. The silicate structure fraction refers to the difference  between the total content and the amount extractable with dithionite.    extracted the lowest amounts (6--11%) of these elements. This reagent has  been reported to be specific for the dissolution of organically complexed Fe  and Al (McKeague et al., 1971), Although the ability of pyrophosphate to  dissolve different minerals was not evaluated in the present study, it seems  unlikely that this reagent would have dissolved a considerable portion of the  inorganic components of concretions (McKeague, 1967; McKeague et al., 1971).  These results suggest that only a small fraction of the total Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu  and Zn in these concretions is associated with organic matter, a suggestion  supported by the low organic matter content of the soils (Sehgal et al., 1973).  Oxalate extracted 65.2, 72.3, 75.3, 78.6, 83.1 and 74.6% of the total Fe, Mn,  Co, Ni, Cu and Zn, respectively. The amounts of these elements extracted by  dithionite ranged between 86.1 and 98.8%. The amounts of dithionite-in-  soluble Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn are very small. As dithionite dissolves  most of the secondary sesquioxides (Mehra and Jackson, 1960), the present  results suggest that major fractions of the Co, Ni, Cu and Zn are associated  with the Fe-Mn components of concretions and only a small fraction is  present in the silicate matrix (silicate structure form -- total minus dithionite-  extractable).  The dissolution of finely ground concretions in 0.5 N HC1 indicated that  the amounts of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn released per extraction decreased  with the number of extractions (Fig.2). In general the rate of release of Cu  was the highest and that of Fe and Mn the lowest. Other elements were re-  leased at intermediate rates. The lack of congruency in dissolution as shown  by these concretions suggests a non-uniform distribution of elements in the  concretion structure.    247    ~  I0O  ~80  ~  60  ~40   20"  0    /, t--.  //-' .,~"      Mn  '   "  ....  Fe  -- --Ni    .....  Zn    .......  Cu    4   6   8  10  Extraction  Number    Fig.2. Dissolution of the concretions in 0.5 N HCI (Sample: 1--2 mm, B23 horizon of  Balewal sandy-loam).    Mineralogy    The x-ray diffraction patterns of concretions from different horizons were  similar and the diffractograms for a typical sample are shown in Fig.3. Most  of the untreated (Mg-saturated) samples exhibited reflections at 10.05, 4.26  and 3.34 A d-spacings which remained unaltered on glycolation and on  heating to 400C after K-saturation. None of these peaks could be ascribed  to Fe or Mn minerals. Even the long exposure powder patterns obtained with  a Debye--Scherrer camera did not indicate the presence of any Fe or Mn min-  erals. Boiling the untreated samples with sodium hydroxide did not produce  any such peaks. The extraction with sodium pyrophosphate brought no  change in the resulting patterns. The removal of Fe-Mn components by pro-    o~  -4     LO          eO  Hydrochloric acid    Dithionite  Oxatate  Pyrophosphate  Untreated    Fig.3. X-ray diffraction patterns of concretions after various treatments (sample: &gt; 2 mm,  B31 horizon of Ghabdan loam).    248    gressive dissolution in oxalate, dithionite and HC1 not only enhanced the  intensity of reflections in general but also produced new peaks at 6.38, 5.00,  4.05 and 3.24 A d-spacings. The reflections at 10.05 and 5.00 A suggest the  presence of illite (Grim, 1968). The 4.26 and 3.34 A peaks indicate the pres-  ence of quartz (Brown, 1961) in these concretions. The reflections at 6.38,  4.05 and 3.24 2( indicate the presence of feldspars (Brown, 1961). The ab-  sence of various reflections characteristic of Fe or Mn minerals in these con-  cretions suggests that Fe and Mn compounds in the concretions are x-ray  amorphous. From the increased intensities of quartz, illite and feldspars re-  flections after the dissolution of Fe and Mn components in oxalate, dithio-  nite and HC1, it is suggested that the Fe-Mn compounds may be forming  coatings around the skeleton grains of quartz, illite and feldspars. Several  other workers were also unable to detect any crystalline Fe or Mn compounds  in Fe-Mn pans (McKeague et al., 1968) and concretions (Childs, 1975).  The mineralogical analyses suggest that quartz, illite and feldspars are the  principal crystalline components of these concretions. The same minerals  are dominant in the general matrix of these soils (Sehgal et al., 1973). This  similarity between the concretions and adjacent soil matrix indicates that  the concretions may have developed in situ. The micromorphological obser-  vations of the diffuse boundaries between the concretions and surrounding  soil materials also point to the orthic nature of concretions. Similar consider-  ations have been used by Wieder and Yaalon (1974) to identify orthic car-  bonate nodules.    REFERENCES    Adams, S.N., Honeysett, J.L., Tiller, K.G. and Norrish, K., 1969. Factors controlling the  increase of cobalt in plants following the addition of a cobalt fertilizer. Aust. J. Soil  Res., 7: 29--42.  Bogdanov, N.I. and Voropayeva, Z.I., 1969. Mn-Fe concentration in West Siberian Cher-  nozems as an index of their hydromorphic character. Soy. Soil Sci., 1 : 642--656.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. John Wiley, New York, N.Y.,  470 pp.  Brown, G., 1961. Tile X-ray Identification and Crystal Structures of Clay Minerals. Miner.  Soc., London, pp. 467--488.  Childs, C.W., 1975. Composition of iron-manganese concretions from some New Zealand  soils. Geoderma, 13: 141--152.  Cronan, D.S. and Thomas, R.L., 1972. Geochemistry of ferromanganese oxide concretions  and associated deposits in Lake Ontario. Geol. Soc. Am. Bull., 83: 1493--1502.  Forbes, E.A., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1976. The specific adsorption of divalent Cd,  Co, Cu, Pb and Zn on goethite. J. Soil Sci., 27: 154--166.  Gallaher, R.N., Perkins, H.F., Tan, K.H. and Redcliffe, D., 1973. Soil concretions, ti.  Mineralogical analysis. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 37: 469--472.  Grim, R.E., 1968. Clay Mineralogy. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 596 pp.  Jenne, E.A., 1968. Controls on Mn, Fe, Co, Ni and Zn concentrations in soils and water.  In: R.F. Gould (Editor), Trace Inorganics in Water. Am. Chem. Soc. Adv. Chem. Ser.,  73: 337--387.  Le Riche, H.H. and Weir, A.H., ] 963. A method of studying trace elements in soil frac-  tions. J. Soil Sci., 14: 225--235.    249    Loganathan, P. and Burau, R.G., 1973. Sorption of heavy metal ions by a hydrous manga-  nese oxide. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 37: 1277--1293.  McKeague, J.A., 1967. An evaluation of 0.1 M pyrophosphate and pyrophosphate-dithio-  nite in comparison with oxalate as extractants of the accumulation products in podzols  and some other soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 47 : 95--99.  McKeague, J.A. and Day, J.H., 1966. Dithionite and oxalate-extractable Fe and Al as  aids in differentiating various classes of soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 46: 13--22.  McKeague, J.A., Brydon, J.E. and Miles, N.M., 1971. Differentiation of forms of extract-  able iron and aluminium in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 33--38.  McKeague, J.A., Damman, W.H. and Heringa, P.K., 1968. Iron-manganese and other pans  in some soils of Newfoundland. Can. J. Soil Sci., 48: 243--253.  McKenzie, R.M., 1972. The sorption of some metals by the lower oxides of manganese.  Geoderma, 8: 29--35.  Mebra, O,P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by dithionite  citrate system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7: 317--327.  Mitchell, B.D., Farmer, V.C. and McHardy, W.J., 1964. Amorphous inorganic materials  in soils. Adv. Agron., 16: 327--383.  Patrick, W.H.Jr and Delaune, R.D., 1972. Characterization of the oxidised and reduced  zones in flooded soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 573--576.  Pawluk, S. and Dumanski, J., 1973. Ferruginous concretions in a poorly drained soil of  Alberta. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 37: 124--127.  Phillippe, W.R., Blevins, R.L., Barnhisel, R.I. and Bailey, H.H., 1972. Distribution of con-  cretions from selected soils of Inner Bluegrass region of Kentucky. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 36: 171--173.  Polteva, R.N. and Sokolova, T.A., 1967. Investigation of concretions in a strongly pod-  zolic soil profile. Soy. Soil Sci., 7: 884--893.  Sehgal, J.L., Sharma, P.K., Randhawa, N.S., Singh, G. and Associates, 1973. Salt-affected  soils of the Sangrur district and their management. Res. Bull. Punjab Agric. Univ.  Ludhiana, 102 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy. Agriculture handbook No. 436. Soil Cons. Ser.  USDA, Washington, D.C., 754 pp.  Taylor, R.M., 1968. Toe association of manganese and cobalt in soils -- further observa-  tions. J. Soil Sci., 19: 77--80.  Taylor, R.M. and McKenzie, R.M., 1966. The association of trace elements with manga-  nese minerals in soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 4: 29--39.  Taylor, R.M., McKenzie, R.M. and Norrish, K., 1964. The mineralogy and chemistry of  manganese in some Australian soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 2: 235--248.  Wieder, M. and Yaalon, D.H., 1974. Effect of matrix composition on carbonate nodule  crystallization. Geoderma, ll: 95--121.  Winters, E., 1938. Ferromagniferous concretions from some podzolic soils. Soil Sci., 46:  33--40.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               AbstractIron-manganese concretions from three reference soil series of the Indo-Gangetic plain of Punjab have been investigated for their composition, micromorphology and mineralogy. The data show that amounts of Fe, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn in the concretions are higher than in the surrounding soil matrix. The contents of Mn, Co and Ni increase and that of Fe decreases with the increasing size of concretions. Cu or Zn contents do not show any systematic differences with concretion size. A major portion of these elements is oxalate- and dithionite-extractable. A minor fraction is present in the silicate structure as well as in the pyrophosphate-extractable forms. The Fe and Mn compounds present in the concretions are x-ray amorphous. The concretions appear to have developed in situ. 