Geoderma, 30 (1983) 65--76                                                        65  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    MICRORADIOGRAPHY AS A SUBMICROSCOPIC TOOL    L.R DREES and L.P. WILDING  Department of Sod and Crop Sciences, Texas A&amp;M University, and Texas Agricultural  Experimental Station, College Station, Texas 77843 (U.S.A )  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Drees, L.R and Wilding, L.P., 1983. Microradiography as a submicroscopic tool. Geo-  derma, 30: 65--76.    Contact X-ray microradiography is a microscopic application of conventional radio-  graphy. The resulting in situ shadow images on fine-grained photographic film can be  viewed under the light microscope up to 500x wlthout loss of detail or depth of focus  distortions. Differential absorbance of X-rays by the sample offers a non-destructive  means of examining the internal phases of a specimen which may be obscured in light  transmission or SEM microscopy. Such phases include voids, nodules, concretions,  occluded minerals, Uthorelicts, and other chemical segregations. Microradiography is an  especially convenient tool because of minimum sample preparation and the small invest-  ment cost for camera fabrication to existing X-ray equipment.    INTRODUCTION    Radiographic principles and procedures remain essentially unchanged  since the discovery of X-rays by Wilhelm Conrad R5ntgen in 1895. X-ray  radiography is currently employed in many scientific endeavors. It is used  widely in the geological and paleontological fields. Two excellent books that  review these applications are Bouma (1969) and Krinitzsky (1970).  In soil materials, only limited application has been made of radiography.  Carbajal et al. (1966, 1969) used microradiography of thin sections to study  the distribution of various elements and mineral phases in the soil profile.  More recently, Rogaar and Thiadens (1975) used radiography to examine the  natural pore structure in soils. Earthworm burrows and their shapes and  contents have also been investigated using radiography (Rogaar and  Boswinkel, 1978).  Microradiography has proven to be a useful interface between light-  optical and SEM techniques for analysis of occluded mineral phases in  vegetative tissues of grasses and tree leaves. For example, light-optical and  SEM micrographs of biogenic opal isolated from soils and vegetative com-    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    66    ponents have been reported prewously (Wlldmg and Drees, 1971, 1973,  1974; Wflding et al., 1977). Many of these isolates are fragmented and  difficult to relate to in sltu sites of localization. The X-ray m:crorad:ograph  technique has served a vital role in this linkage and prov:des the only known  means to directly visualize the distribution of these occluded phases    THEORY    Contact-microradiography is a submmroscopm techmque for examining  the  internal phases of a specimen which may not be identified by  microscopic or other techniques because of opaqueness, sample thmkness or  lack of resolution. Such phases include voids, nodules, concretions, occluded  minerals, hthorelicts, and other chemical segregations within the specimen.  X-rays tmpingmg on the sample are differentially absorbed by occluded  chemical phases within the sample. Absorption of X-rays within the sample  reduces the intensity of the primary beam by an amount equal to:  I = Io e-(~,/p)px                                                         (1)  where Io = intensity of radiation incident on the sample, I = Intensity of  transmitted radiation after passing through a sample of thickness X, p/p =  mass absorption coefficient (cm2/g) determined by chemical composition  and wavelength of radiation being absorbed, and pX = mass per unit area of  sample thickness X with density p.  Since mass absorption coefficients are dependent on wavelength, intensity  ratios may be maximized by selecting radiation wavelengths which will  maximize differences between the absorptmn coefficients of the matrix  and occluded phases. Table I illustrates the advantages of using specific  wavelengths to optimize image contrast. Differentlai chemical composltmn  can be noted by changes in image contrast when exposure is made w:th  different monochromatic X-ray sources. For example, iron oxide nodules or  concretions appear lighter on radiography film than quartz when Cu-irradia-  tmn is used (Table I). The inverse is true if Cr-irradiation is used. Carbajai  et al. (1969) effectively used different radiation wavelengths to identify  ~ron and manganese concentrations m soil thin sections.    CONTACT MICRORADIOGRAPHY    Contact mmroradiography is a submicroscopic technique to record a  shadow image at unity magnification on a fine-grained photographic  emulsion (Fig. 1). The resulting image is then xaewed with a light microscope  at magmfications up to 500without significant loss of detail. With the  availability of high-resolution films and plates (&gt; 2000 hnes/mm) that  exhibit very fine grain-size and thin emulsion (&lt; 5 ~m), it is possible to  obtmn high-resolution images at magnifications up to 500with contact  mlcroradiography. Because the photographm emulsion is very thin, depth of    67    TABLE I  Numerical difference in mass-absorption coefficients between common soil minerals and  quartz for selected radiations.1    Absorbing material    Radiation    Cr         Fe          Cu  (2.29 A)  (1 937 A)  (1 54 A)    SiO~ (quartz)                          0.0        0.0          0 0  A1203                              --15_6       --6.0        --3 9  Fe203                                  --20.8        --9.7       +195.6  CaCO3 (calcite)                     +111 2      +68.2        +40.7  TIO2 (futile)                        +263 3     +169 2        +98.2  KAISi30s (orthoclase)               +37.1      --28.7        +13.8  NaAISl30, (albite)                    --9.0       --2.0         --1 8  CaA12Si20~ (anorthite)               +48.0      +34.2        +17.9  KAI3SI3OIo(OH)2 (muscovite)       +18.6      +16.1         +7.8    ,1 Negahve values ymld xmages darker than quartz while positive values yield images  lighter than quartz. The greater the difference, the greater the image contrast to quartz    /  I     pet|men      ]  X-ray Film        I  Fig 1. Schematic view and geometric relationship of basic components for contact-micro-  radiography.    focus is not a problem m vmwing microradlographs. By exposing the sample  at slightly different angles, microradiography is also suitable for stereo-  graphic images (Hamblin, 1962; Rogaar and Thiadens, 1975).  X-ray projection radiography m an alternate method which requires the  sample to be placed close to a point-focus X-ray source. An enlarged shadow  image is then obtained depending on the source-sample to sample-film ratio.    68    Fine details of mmrofosslls have been reported by Jongbloed and Porrenga  (1968) using this technique. X-ray projection radiography does have its  limitations In requmng speciahzed equipment to obtain a point source of  X-rays. Such equipment Is not generally available to micromorphologlsts.  This technique also poses problems with image edge distortion due to the  flmte dimensions of the X-ray source.  Optimum image contrast in contact mlcroradiography is usually obtamed  with a monochromatic X-ray source. White continuous radiation may be  used if tube voltages are kept sufficiently low to produce longer wavelengths.  The X-ray source may be a commercial apparatus designed for radiography.  However, an X-ray generator associated with X-ray diffraction equipment is  usually more readily available and convenient Microradlography cameras  are easily fabncated to fit a powder camera track of a diffractometer  (Schmldt, 1952). Fig. 2 illustrates schematically one of two cameras built by  the present authors and mounted on a camera track of a Philips Diffracto-  meter. This arrangement has several advantages for mlcroradlography:  (1) The powder camera track permits quick and accurate alignment of  radiography camera.  (2) The X-ray tubes designed for powder camera usually have smaller  spot focusing that favors optimum resolution.  (3) The diffractometer tube towers generally have built-in safety shutters  and filter monochrometers.  (4) The microradiography camera usually does not interfere with other  simultaneous dfffractometer uses.    Extens,on  Tube (30 crn )    Ccmera track     )~   Ray  tube    Fig 2. Schematic view of a mmroradiography camera mounted on a powder camera track  of a PhUips X-ray diffractometer    X-ray tube voltages can be adjusted to reduce the harder white radiation  while maintaining a high intensity of the characteristic radiation. Tube    69    voltages in the range of 20--40 kV with 10--20 mA are common for micro-  radiography purposes. The authors generally use 20 kV and 10 mA Ni Kfl  filtered Cu-radiation. Excellent results have been achieved using emulsion-  coated glass slides (Kodak Spectroscopic Plates, Type 649-0) and sheet film  cut to size (Kodak High Resolution Film, S0-343).  Close physical contact between sample and film is necessary for maximum  resolution and enlargement. Positive contact during long exposure eliminates  distortion resulting from room or equipment vibrations. Sample-film contact  is most conveniently achieved by a vacuum cassette film holder. The cassette  consists of a metal base with a recessed area milled to accommodate the  photographic film. An outer perimeter and cross channels have been milled  slightly deeper to allow vacuum distribution to the film via a side or back  vacuum port (Fig. 3 ).    Va  P~    i~  ~,  /        Specimen  : / *'-ray  /Film    Fig. 3. Basic components of the vacuum cassette for contact-microradiography. The lead-  backed film holder is designed to accept Kodak Spectroscopic Plate, 649-0. The cassette  fits into a radiation-proof and light-tight camera illustrated in Fng 2.    In practme, photographic film is placed into the machined recess,  emulsion side up, and the sample placed on top of it. A flexible X-ray  transparent sheet is then placed over the sample (Fig. 3). The sheet is of  sufficient size to cover the sample and overlap the perimeter of the cassette.  When vacuum is applied, the sheet presses the sample firmly against the film.  In some instances, however, it may be desirable to place a small thin sheet  of non-absorbing mylar between the sample and film to protect the emulsion  from scratches, moisture, or other physical or chemical contamination.  Mylar serves as an ideal sheeting material; it is strong, flexible and X-ray  transparent. However, if the cassette must be transported from the dark-  room where it is loaded, to the X-ray source in a lighted room, an opaque  sheeting is necessary. Plastic sheeting containing chlorine or other elements  that are highly absorbent of soft X-rays must be avoided. Black paper may  also be used to keep out light, but caution should be exercised because some    70    paper has internal structural components which may be recorded on th,'  photographic film.  Focal distances between X-ray source and the sample commonly range  from 8 to 30 cm. Longer focal lengths reduce edge distortions and blumng  of boundaries, whmh is especially Important if the sample must be placed a  small distance from the film or the sample is thick. However, longer focal  lengths result in greater absorption of softer X-rays in the air path. If the  focal distance is short, sample thmkness is most critical. For practical  purposes, exposure time (intensity of X-rays) follows an inverse square  relatmnship  with distance, except for long focal distances where mr  absorption becomes a significant factor. Exposure times are not given here  since they depend on film speed, focal distance, wavelength, tube voltage,  tube current, and filters. Exposure guides can easily be constructed for each  set of conditions  Caution is adwsed in constructing a radiographic camera. Every precaution  should be taken to ensure that there is no leakage of X-rays around ports or  through the back. Lead shmlds should be used behind the film to reduce  backscattering  and  X-ray  transmission  through the camera  Exposure  momtormg of the camera is advised while in use.    APPLICATIONS    Host mineral inclusions as cellular infillings are evident in a wide variety  of vegetative material including grasses and tree leaves (Fig. 4). Although  the mineralogy of the cellular infilhngs cannot be identified from micro-  radiography, previous X-ray diffraction and hght optmal analysis, the authors  have identified blogenic opal (Wildmg and Drees, 1974}, and calcmm  oxalates. These cellular inclusions generally conform to the shape of the  individual host cell and are concentrated along conductive vesmles (Fig. 4).  In tree leaves (Fig. 4B) the larger discrete white images are calcium oxalate  crystals, Darker laminated gray tones within conductive elements are  biogemc opal and cellulose fibers. In the blades of grass (Fig. 4A), the white  areas are completely sllicified bulliform cells or partially sihcified incrusta-  tions of cell walls. Lighter and darker parallel bands represent variable  degrees of sllicification in midrib sections of the blades. Weakly or partially  silicffied cell wall elements are evident m the microradlographs (Fig. 4).  These cell walls usually fragment when bmgemc opal is extracted by ashing  or acid digestion (Fig. 5). Although the SEM micrograph yields significant  information about the structure and configuration of silicified cell walls (Fig.  5), the X-ray microradiograph (Fig. 4) more clearly shows their continuity  and relationship to the plant tissue as a whole. Precise zones of silicification  can be directly observed in situ without pretreatment modifications.    Fig.  4. X-ray microradiography of grass blades and tree leaves  A. Big bluestem  (Andropogon gerardi); B  Aspen poplar (Populus tremloides). Note: b = silicified bulli-  form cells, c = stliclfied cell wslls; o = calcium oxa]ate crystals, e = stlica- and cellulose-  impregnated conductive elements Both micrographs at same magnification    71    72    Fig 5 Scanning electron micrographs of sihcifmd cell walls A, Fragment isolated from  sugar maple (Acer saccarurn); B Fragment from forest soil isolate. Both micrographs at  same magnification    Contact microradlography has special utility in identifying the fme  structure of soil fabric in thin sections. Many features are not clearly  resolved m plane-polarized or cross-polarized optical microscopy. Plasma  aggregate units, their size and arrangement in thin sections are often more  clearly resolved in microradiographs. This is attributed to differential X-ray  absorption as a consequence of chemical, mineralogical, textural and/or  cementation compositional effects. Specimen variations coupled with very  thin film emulsion reduce the depth of focus and increase apparent resolu-  tion and image sharpness. Increased resolution is illustrated in Fig. 6 where  the definition of two mica flakes is much enhanced in the microradiogzaph    Fig. 6. Photomicrographs of soil thin section showing mica flakes A. Plane-polarized  light, B. Cross-polarized light. Arrows m A and B point to flakes exhibiting higher X-ray  absorbance in microradiograph (C). All micrographs at same magnification.    73    versus either plane or polarized light microscopy. It is probable that the  resolution for these skeleton grains in the microradiograph is enhanced  relative to the s-matrix because they contain iron oxides or other elements  that have a higher relative mass absorption coefficient for Cu-irradiation  (Table I).  Lithorelicts composed of quartz and K-feldspar phases are observed in Fig.  7. Under cross-polarized light optics (Fig. 7A), it is difficult to distinguish  these minerals because optical phenomena of untwinned K-feldspars are  similar to quartz and some of the grains of both minerals are at extinction.  It is easier and more accurate to distinguish these mineral phases by micro-  radiography (Fig. 7B) where feldspars appear lighter than quartz due to higher  relative mass absorption coefficients (Table I). These gray-tone image  contrasts are statable for quantification using advanced automated image  analysis systems.    Fig. 7. Thin section of soil lithorelict composed of quartz and feldspar A. Cross-polarized  light, B. X-ray microradiograph showing image contrast differences for quartz (Q) and  feldspar (F)    Microradiography can also be effectively used to observe opaque or thick  specimens that prohibit light transmission. Fig. 8A illustrates such an  example in a thin section where a nearly opaque shale lithic yields little  fabric or compositional information when observed under plane-polarized  light. In contrast, Fig. 8B illustrates a microradiograph of this same specimen  with greater fabric resolution. Fig. 8C is an enlargement of a select field in  Fig. 8B that clearly depicts the arrangement of plasma aggregates.  Thin sections of organic softs are often so strongly pigmented with organic  matter that the occluded detrital grains are mostly obscured. Microradio-  graphs have proven useful to ascertain the relative abundance of inorganic  phases. In some organic sections, macropores are also better defined.    74    75    CONCLUSIONS    X-ray microradiography is a useful submmroscopic tool to complement  optical and electron microscopy. It permits direct image analyses of com-  ponents that are obscured by occlusion within host materials and thus  cannot be wewed by transmitted-light microscopy or by SEM. This  techmque particularly lends itself to thin sections where it often enhances  fabric and compositional mformation. In thin sections, voids, plasma  aggregates and their distnbutlons may be clearly differentiated from aniso-  tropic components at extinction. Internal structure and compositional  attributes of detrital grams and vegetative tissues may also be obtained  without prior preparation  or sample  destruction.  In most instances,  specimens examined by X-ray microradiography may be examined by other  microscopic techniques with direct image comparison.  X-ray microradlography may be a convement additional tool to most  mineralogical laboratories because of its small investment cost for camera  fabncation and adaptability to existing X-ray equipment.    REFERENCES    Bouma, A.H, 1969. Methods for the Study of Sedimentary Structures  Wiley-Inter-  scmnce, New York, N.Y , 458 pp.  Carbajal, H, Vicente, J.G  and Voltz, M K., 1966. La mmroradiografia de contacto  aphcada al estudio de la micromorfologia de suelos Anal. Edafol. Agrobiol (Madrid),  25 : 491--503  Carbajal, H., Benayas, J., Vicente, J G. and Alonso, J J, 1969 Contact-mmroradiography  as applied to the distribution of iron and manganese in thin secttons of Mediterranean  brown soil. Geoderma, 3. 133--145.  Hambhn, W.K., 1962. X-ray radiography in the study of structures m homogeneous  sediments J. Sediment. Petrol, 32 133--145  Jongebloed, W.L and Porrenga, D H, 1968. Microradiography and X-ray microscope m  geology. Geol Mijnb., 47' 435--442  Krinitzsky, E.L., 1970. Radiography in the Earth Sciences and Soil Mechanics. Plenum  Press, New York, N Y., 163 pp.  Rogaar, H and Boswmkel, J A., 1978 Some soil morphologmal effects of earthworm  activity; f, eld data and X-ray radiography. Neth J Agric. Sci., 26:146--160  Roganr, H and Thiadens, R A.H, 1975 X-rays applied to the study of the pore structure  in soils. Neth J. Agric Sci, 23: 321--333.  Schmidt, R.A.M., 1952 Microradlography of mmrofossils with X-ray diffraction eqmp-  ment. Science, 115: 94--95.  Wilding, L.P. and Drees, L R, 1971 Biogemc opal in Ohio soils. Soil Sci Soc. Am. Proc.,  35" 1004--1010.  Wilding, L.P. and Drees, L R, 1973 Scanning electron mmroscopy of opaque opaline  forms isolated from forest soils in Oh,o Soil Scl. Soc. Am. Proc., 37:647--650    Fig 8 Thin section of nearly opaque shale lithorelict: A. Plane-polarized light; B. X-ray  mmroradiography of same field illustrating enhanced resolution, C  Magnification of  square area in A and B showing individual plasma aggregates (a)    76    Wdding, L P and Drees, L R, 1974. Contributions of forest opal and associated crystal-  line phases to fine silt and clay fractions of soils Clays Clay Miner, 22 295--306  Wllding, L.P, Smeck, N.E  and Drees, L R, 1977  Silica in soils- quartz, cnstobalite,  trldymlte, and opal_ In  J B Dixon and S B Weed (Editors), Minerals m Soil Environ-  ments Soil Sci Soc. Am, Madison, Wlsc., pp 471--552                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractContact X-ray microradiography is a microscopic application of conventional radiography. The resulting in situ shadow images on fine-grained photographic film can be viewed under the light microscope up to 500x without loss of detail or depth of focus distortions. Differential absorbance of X-rays by the sample offers a non-destructive means of examining the internal phases of a specimen which may be obscured in light transmission or SEM microscopy. Such phases include voids, nodules, concretions, occluded minerals, lithorelicts, and other chemical segregations. Microradiography is an especially convenient tool because of minimum sample preparation and the small investment cost for camera fabrication to existing X-ray equipment.