 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 93--116                                                       93  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    VARIATIONS IN BACKSCATTERED ELECTRON (BSE) IMAGES WITH  A SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPE (SEM) AS APPLIED TO  MINERAL GRAINS AND EXCREMENTS IN A PODZOL, TO  PRECIPITATES ON A WATER-TUBE FILTER AND TO BAUXITE    E.B A. BISDOM', F. THIEL2, B. VOLBERT3 and J JACKMAN3  ' Netherlands Sod Survey Instztute, P 0 Box 98, 6700 AB Wagenmgen  (The Netherlands)  2 Technwal and Physzcal Engineering Research Serwce, 6700 AJ Wageningen  (The Netherlands)  3 N V Phdips, Applicatzon Laboratory-Electron Optws, TQ-III-p, 5600 MD Emdhoven  (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    B1sdom, E B A., Thiel, F., Volbert, B. and Jackman, J., 1983. Var,atlons in backscattered  electron (BSE) images with a Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) as applied to min-  eral grains and excrements ,n a podzol, to precipitates on a water-tube filter and to  baumte. Geoderma, 30: 93--116.    The results of experiments on various materials in thin sections, using a Scanning  Electron Microscope with a secondary electron detector and four backscattered electron  detectors, are discussed. The Multi-Function-Detector (MFD) system for backscattered  electrons allows the observahon of the 'real' topography in a thin section with the SE-  BSE mode and is also able to give good information on the contrasts in materials (atomic  contrasts) with the BSE (A+B) mode. Various other possibilities are also present with  this system, e.g. the study of soil materials over different depths below the surface of a  thin section Of considerable interest is the possibility to start the investigation of thin  sechons at 10 magmfieahon without the loss of part of the pmture on the display  screen or mmrograph. As a consequence, interpretational steps from the held observations  to hght mmroscopy and submicroseopy will most probably become easier in the near  future. Maximum magmfications using the BSE-mgnal were dependent on the type of  analysed material, hut were usually significantly higher than with older backscattered  electron detector systems.    INTRODUCTION    Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI), called backscattered elec-  tron (BSE) tmages m this paper, of soft materials were introduced by Bisdom  and Thiel (1981) and macro- and microporoslties measured from them by  Quantimet (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). The instrument used to make  BSE images was a SEM with a backscattered electron detector of the semi-    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    94    conductor type, comprising two solid state detectors A lot of experience  was ginned with this machine by studying materials of softs, weathered rocks  and off--gas reservoir rocks_ BSE mlcrographs of matermls m thin sectlon~  were of a much better quality than SE (secondary electron) mlcrographs,  especmlly up to magnfficatmns of about 4000. The maximal magmfmation  was rather dependent on the type of materml being investigated and often  stopped below 1000 BSE Lmages allow structure and fabric analyses of  soil materials m thm sections at such magmfmatlons. Of special interest to us  was the possibility of studymg soil porosity of all kinds of materials because  the Quantunet could measure pores m BSE mlcrographs  A newer type of instrument allows different modes of operation using  BSE and SE detectors. The results on the portrayal of materials and poro-  sities are discussed below.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil material, occurring m the A horizon of a podzol from The Nether-  lands, was studied with a SEM 505 equipped with a Multi-Function-Detector  (MFD) consisting of four backscattered electron detectors and the common  secondary electron detector (Jackman, 1980). Such horizons often show a  combination of mineral and organic materials m mmro-areas of a thin sec-  tion. BSE perform especlaUy well on soil and other materials with heavier  chemmal elements (Blsdom and Thml, 1981). This means that difficulties  arise when the lighter elements m orgamc material must be portrayed with  BSE due to the small BSE coeffmmnt. These should appear blackish if only  elements like H, C, N and O axe revolved. In practice, however, Fe and other  elements are also often present in the organic tissues and images are ob-  tained, even with BSE, because of these heavier elements. There is also the  posslbihty of working with a combination of BSE and SE detectors, or with  the SE detector alone, to study materials on or near to the surface of a thin  section (Volbert, 1981)  A precipitate on a copper water-tube filter (courtesy of the Dune Water  Works, The Hague, The Netherlands) was studied with the MFD system of  the Philips SEM 505. A separate paper on this precipitate, with BSE and  microchemmal reformation, is also presented m this issue (Blsdom and  Jongerms, 1983). This was done with the Jeol-JSM-35C equipped with an  EDAX 9100 system using an ECON windowless detector for the detection  of chemical elements with a low atomic number. The BSE detector was of  the semiconductor type, comprising two sohd state detectors. Some of the  micrographs in this paper can be compared with those m the paper by  Blsdom and Jongerms (1983).  Bauxite from Surinam (courtesy International Soft Museum, Wagenmgen,  The Netherlands) was the third matenal analysed by the MFD system. Suni-  lar material of the same sample has already been investigated with secondary  mn mass spectrometry (SIMS) and quantifmation done in an area of about    95    300 um diameter (Henstra et al., 1980). The bauxite showed considerable  variation in the composition of mmro-areas and was studied for its trace and  major elements with the Cameca IMS 300 (Henstra et al., 1981). Such analy-  ses can now be done quantitatively from a micro-area with a diameter of  1.5 um with the Cameca IMS 3F (Blsdom et al., 1983a). In the present case,  the occurrence of gibbsite crystals and fluldal structures with a high A1 con-  tent were studmd with backscattered electrons.  A few technical details of the MFD system are given. Four backscattered  electron detectors are connected by fibre optics to two photomultlplier/pre-  amplifier combinations which can be placed outside the specimen chamber  (Jackman, 1980). Each of the four backscattered electron detectors of the  MFD system is fitted with phosphor of the optimal thickness for 30 keV  electrons, and an Al-layer suitable for operation down to 5 keV. Secondary  electrons lack the energy to penetrate the Al-layer and consequently only  backscattered electrons are recorded by a scintillator. The impact of back-  scattered electrons on the detector produces photons of visible light conduc-  ted by the fibre optics to the photomultiplier tube. By replacing the phos-  phor of the BSE-detector by a light-gathering lens which focuses on the fibre  optms bundle, cathodolumlnescence detection is possible depending on the  type of soil material being investigated.  Optmal switches which connect the fibre optics of two BSE-detectors to  one of two photomultiplier tubes allow the rapid switching of detection  modes and any combination of the four signals coming from the detectors  through the fibre optics to the photomultiplier tubes can be chosen. The re-  sult is that rotation of the sample can be simulated without movement of  the analysed material itself due to changes in illumination of the sample.  BSE-detectors can be compared with light sources which illummate the  specnnen. Working with one active BSE-detector therefore causes strong  shadowing effects, four active detectors (homogeneous illumination) reduce  the shadowing, material contrast is optnnised.  Two backscattered electron detectors (scintillators), indicated as detector  A m Fig. 1, can be combined to a signal A, and the other two scintillators  (detector B) to a signal B. The central part of the sample in Fig. 1 has a  higher atomic number (A.N.) than the remainder of the sample. The signal  height is larger if the sample is tilted towards detector A or B. An intermedi-  ate signal height is reached for the flat part of the sample, as indicated by  backscattered electron signals A or B in Fig. 1. Surfaces which tilt away from  the detectors, give the same signal as the flat parts of the remainder of the  sample with a lower atomic number. If both detectors are used, signals A +  B give material contrast and signals A-B topographic contrast, as indicated in  a schematic way in Fig. 1.  In our studies we used signals A+B or A-B, and the secondary electron  (SE) detector. The effects of signal mixing (A+B), (A-B) and SE-BSE, are  discussed below with the results. It will be shown that the separation of dif-  ferent contrasts is possible, vlz. material and topographic contrasts in soil    96    CO  m    [ dlrection of scar~,~/   AN =Z %--    F (Z -.Z')    AN =7    I  n    A-B    F~g I. MFD-scmtlllators can give signals A, B, A+B and A-B. Each of these signals gives a  certain type of reformation of whmh the backscattered electron signal, BSE (A+B), is  very useful for thin section studies (material contrast) The BSE (A-B) signal results m  topographic contrast.    material present in the A-horizon oa podzol and m precipitates which clog  the filter oa water tube. The possibility of observing the studied materials  of the thin section on TV-rate images was of considerable help m this work.  This means that the whole display screen is illuminated simultaneously due  to the very fast reaction time of the detector system.    RESULTS    Sod material in the A-horizon of a podzol    A view of the analysed material in the A horizon of a podzol is shown in  Fig  2. The white grains are predominantly quartz m various size classes,  whereas the greyish material and the small included mineral fragments con-  stltute excrements. The micrograph of Fig. 2 was made with all four scintil-  lators (A+B), whmh give uniform illumination in the hght optmal analogues  and optLrnal material contrast without topography. The same results are ob-  tained in the BSE (A+B) mode of Figs. 3 and 4.  If only two scintillators (BSE-detectors) A or B are used, the illumination  effects can be seen m Fig. 3. BSE (A) and BSE (B) show shadowing or topo-  graphm effects, whereby certain particles seem to rise from the micrograph    97    m one photo and form holes in the other. If the position of the detector  (light source) is known, It can be decided if the surface detail is a hole or  not. Such effects can be used in special studies but were of little interest to  our investigation.  Imaging of the topography of a multi-compositional rough specLmen can  be done in the BSE-mode by subtracting the signal of two scintillators (B)  from the signal of the other two scmtillators (A) as illustrated in Fig. 1. This  BSE (A-B) mode, however, can result in the wrong interpretation of the  specimen's topography due to an artefact called pseudotopography which  occurs at high primary electron (PE)-energies. This pseudotopography is  caused by anisotropic backscattering of the BSE at the material boundaries  (Volbert, 1981).  An example of a BSE(A-B) image at 30 keV primary electron energy is  given in Fig. 5. This mformatlon depth is deeper than the SE and SE-BSE  images taken at the same and high acceleration voltage. SE-BSE images are  considered to approach the real topography best at the surface of the thin  section and to have a smaller information depth than the SE-signal due to  suppression of the BSE-lnformation in the secondary electron signal. The use  of the Multi-Function-Detector in the Phllips SEM 505 allows the generation    BSE [A+ B ]  Fig 2. Low magnification tmage of soil material m the A horizon of a podzol. All the  used signals have been indicated underneath the micrographs. Enlargements in Figs. 3 to  8 are from the central part of this hgure.    98    BSE(A)    BSE (B)    BSE (A-I-B)  Fig. 3 Shadowing effects m Lhe BSE (A) and BSE (B) modes Optimal material contrast  m the BSE (A+B) mode Minerals and mineral fragments m excrements are whitish to  grey and organic matter with or without heavmr chemmal elements greyish to black    99    BSE(A'I'B)  Fig 4. Detail of Fig. 3 in whmh the smaller mineral fragments inside the excrements  become more visible Larger minerals, predominantly quartz grains, were already visible  m Fig. 3.    of (SE-BSE) signals at both high and low primary electron energies. The best  topographic contrast m Fig. 5 is given by SE-BSE, whereas the best material  contrast is found in the BSE (A+B) mode. Of major importance for most of  the submicroscopic studies on thin sections is the material contrast BSE  (A+B) which can started at low magnifications of about X 10 (Fig. 2) and  may continue to Z 1000 and X 30 000 (Figs. 6 -- 8) depending on the type  of soft material.  The difference between SE and BSE (A+B) signals at high primary elec-  tron energies Is clearly demonstrated in the higher magnifications of the mat-  erlals m excrements of Figs. 6 -- 8. The SE-image shows a mixture of depth  and surface information and the BSE-tmage only depth information. The  BSE (A+B) mode gives images at a greater depth than the SE-signal. Usually,  depth of analysis with backscattered electrons is greatest in organm materials  and lower in mineral grmns due to the different penetration depth of the PE.  Images from pores usually come from a maximum depth of about 5 pm,  whereas this is commonly 1 pm to 3 ~m depth for backscattered electrons in  mmeral grains. As already explained above, however, depth of analysis with  BSE depends not only on the type of soil material analysed but also on the  acceleration voltage used. Of practical importance is the fact that high pol-    100     :n  ,  ra ~ ~.~ ~r.~     , ;~ ~    101    SE    Fig 6. Enlargement of the central part of Fig 5. The BSE (A+B) signal gives information  about a somewhat deeper depth below the surface of the thin section than the SE image.  The BSE (A+B) mode provides a clear picture from some I #m to 5 #m depths, whereas  smearing effects due to pohshing axe visible in the SE image.    102    SE    BSE ( A+B )  Fig 7 Partmles which are very small m Fig 6 (central part), are more easily recogmsable  in this figure Information concerning the material ,n the soil matrix can be obtained_    103    SE    BSE (A-I. B )  Fig. 8 Maximal enlargement of the central part of Fig 7 The SE linage ;s still of a good  quahty but the BSE (A+B) image is at its maximum magmflcation The maximal enlarge-  ments with BSE are very dependent on the type of soil material and the instrument used.    104    ishing of the thin section surface is not really necessary for BSE (A+B) imag-  ing but is better when other modes are also used and absolutely essential  when the topographic contrast is mvestigated using the SE-[~SE rood,  (Fig. 5).  An important asset of the use of the SE mode is the possibihty of obtain  mg higher magnifications than with BSE This is observable m Figs. 7 and 8  where the BSE (A+B) images axe becoming unsharp at higher magnifications,  whereas SE Images are still offering detail at the same magmficatmns and  larger. SE-imaging IS often used for the portrayal of organic matter m thin  sections, whereas BSE-lmaging is theoretically unsmtable. In practme, how  ever, heavier chemical elements can be present on or in the organic tissue and  BSE-trnagang becomes possible. This IS also the case with the organic matter  m the A horizon of the podzol (Figs. 5 - 8) and consequently BSE (A+B)  Images could be made of both orgamc materials and minerals    Preczpitates on a water-tube fzlter    Only the more technical details of the Phllips SEM 505 imaging of preci-  pitates on and corrosion of a water-tube filter are discussed here. A separate  paper in this issue, by Bisdom and Jongerius (1983), discusses some of the  processes studied by light mmroscopy and SEM-EDXRA, vlz_ a Jeol4SM  35C (SEM) equipped with an energy dispersive X-ray analysis system Som~,  of the results of the imaging with both machines can be compared  A view of the precipitate and part of the copper filter is shown in Fig. 9,  1.e the BSE (A+B) mode. The corroded filter can be seen in the upper right  position of the images. Exfohated and weathered pieces of the copper tube  are recogmsable going towards the middle of the mmrograph followed by  precipitates that end on the lower left hand side of the photo In the micro-  graph with a bar scale of 20 pm, only the Cu-fllter and exfoliated-weathered  pieces of the tube are portrayed. Maximal magnification with BSE (A+B) is  reached in Fig. 10.  Different operational modes are illustrated in Figs. 11 and 12. The mater-  ials in these figures are the same as those in Fig. 10. Shadowing effects with  two scintillators (BSE-detectors) A or B are given in Fig. 11. It is clearly  demonstrated that the BSE (A) mode of operation gives a picture which is  different from the BSE (B) mode due to the different directions of illumina-  tion. A complete range of different operational systems is given in Fig. 12  whereby BSE (A+B) gives the material contrast and SE-BSE the 'real' topo-    Fig  9. Precipitates on a water-tube filter and corrosion of the copper filter. Details on  the corromon of the filter are shown m Figs 10 -- 13 and details on the precipitate m  Figs  14 -- 15 Exfohated platelets and small pieces of the original filter can be seen at  the upper right hand side of the micrographs with bar scales of 100 ~m and 200 um  Towards the lower left of the images whitish precipitates have settled onto the exfohated  platelets and show a number of growth patterns with intermittent pores that are locally  partly or wholly filled with greyish deposits    105    106    LU       ~-~        ~  ~-i-~r'~  o~    107    BSE (BI  Fig. 11. Shadowing effects if only two backscattered electron detectors are used m the  A or B mode (compare Fig. 12).    I    108    .U    ~;     .~:~  ~.~ ~&lt; ~ a  ~ 0~ ~ ~-~  0  ~ o9  0  ~'i~    109    30keV    BSEIA+BI    6 keV              SE  Fig. 13. SE image made at a low primary electron energy of 6 keV The micrograph at 6  keV gives nearer-to-surface information than the BSE (A+B) image made at a high prima-  ry electron energy of 30 keV.    110    graphm contrast. Figs 9 to 12 were all made with a primary electron energy  of 30 keV When this acceleration voltage becomes smaller imaging of the  surface with SE is easier (Fig 13). This is clear if the SE linage m Fig. 13,  taken at 6 keV, is compared with the BSE (A+B) unage made with 30 keV  acceleration voltage. The SE image of Fig. 13 also represents nearer to sur-  face reformation than the SE image of Fig. 12 taken at 30 keV The 'real'  topographic contrast, however, is given m the SE-BSE mode (Fig 12) at  both high and low pnmary electron energms.  The BSE (A+B) mlcrographs of Figs. 14 and 15 show the precipitate on the  corroded copper filter at various magnifications. All photos were taken at  30 keV acceleration voltage The middle part of Fig. 14 is enlarged m Fig  15. The structure of a 'crystalhsmg' iron, sulphur and copper containing  compound (Blsdom and Jongerms, 1983) is visible in Fig 15. The rings m  the precipitate are partly composed of branching fibres that form a dendritic  pattern.    BSE (A+ B )  Fig. 14. Precipitates and some exfoliated platelets of the copper filter Rings and bands  can be discerned in the precipitate.  Bauxite  BSE Lrnages of A1 concentrations m bauxite from Surinam are shown in  Figs. 16 and 17. The composition of this material was tested with SEM-    i.    111    "0  r~  e~    i!:    J                            ~Ji~:~                                   i~ii~ ! ~ ;~i i~ ~:~    112    m   w    ul    o~i~~  ~    113    16E tAB!  Fig  17. Fluidal structures of whitish to grey mainly amorphous materl~l with a high  aluminium content in a pore. Well crystallized gibbsite, forming a gibbsan, is present in  the pore of the upper micrograph.    114    EDXRA (scanmng electron mmroscopy - energy dispersive X-ray analysis)  and ion microscopy (Henstra et al., 1980}  The mlcrograph with a 200-um bar scale m Fig. 16 shows the general area  m which gibbslte crystals have grown, vlz. assocmted with a void system and  surrounded by a red and yellow coloured matrLx when viewed m the hght  microscope. The A1 content of this matrix was considerable and Fe reached  the highest concentration m the red coloured matrix.  The area m whmh the gibbslte crystals grew, vlz. assocmted with the pores,  was predominantly white when wewed with the hght microscope and highest  In A1 content according to submmroscopm analyses. The blachsh crystals, in  the mlcrographs with bar scales of 50, 20 and 10 mmrons of Fig, 16, grew m  an amorphous substance in which no mlcrostructure could be discerned by  either hght mmroscopy or submmroscopy. This is illustrated best m Fig. 17  Pieces of bauxite were also viewed with STEM (scanning transmlssmn elec  tron mlcroscope}, wz. the Phfllps EM 400T/ST  This instrument allows  examination of the bauxite at even higher magnificatmns than the Phflips  SEM 505, but even here no mlcrostructures were observed.    CONCLUSIONS    Backscattered electron scanning images have been made of mineral grains  and excrements m a podzol, of precipitates on a water-tube filter and of  bauxite. It has been demonstrated that the material contrast is portrayed  best in the BSE (A+B) mode of operation. The best 'real' topographic con-  trast, giving an trnpression of the actual surface of the thin section, was ob-  tained m the SE-BSE mode of operation. The SE-BSE mode can give a good  image of the surface of a thin section at high and low prmaary electron ener-  gies, whereas the BSE (A+B) mode gives subsurface reformation at high  acceleration voltages of 30 keV.  The maximum magnfflcaUon possible w,th the BSE-slgnal is strongly de-  pendent on the type of soil material being investigated m the thm section  and vanes from about 1000 to X 30 000 with the Phllips SEM 505. The  minimum magnffmaUon is about 10 and a picture of the whole display  screen is still possible at such low magnffmation. Consequently, the range of  investigation possiblhties using BSE is considerable, especmlly ff the instru-  ment is also eqmpped with EDXRA and WDXRA (wavelength dispersive  X-ray analysis) for microchemical analysis for in sltu ldent,hcatlon of soft  particles.  BSE can be used to study microfabric and mmrostructure of materials in  thin sectmns The possibility to examine both at low and high magnifications  will facilitate interpretatmn of the results and mterpretation into field ob-  servatmns. The combination of field studies, light mmroscopy and submicro-  scopy will therefore allow a better understanding of processes which take  place in soil profiles. This is especially so because BSE studms are not only  possible with soil materials but also with pores (Bisdom and Thml, 1981)  whmh can also be studmd by Quantlmet (Jongerius and Blsdom, 1981).    115    The high quality of the mmrographs is basically the result of the Multi-  Function-Detector (MFD) system, whmh can be used in combination with a  secondary electron (SE) detector system. The possibility to simulate the  rotation and illumination of the soil sample is of much practical help during  studies. No significant cathodoluminescence was found in the present sam-  ples, but this could be of importance for other types of micromorphologlcal  studies.  The totality of possibilities offered by a SEM with all the different infor-  matron carriers (signals) will have significant lmphcations for present and  future micromorphological research of matenals in thin sectmns and loose  soft matermls. The results of studms m thin sections can be correlated with  those obtained in the SEM-EDXRA, STEM-EDXRA and TEM-EDXRA-  modes at very high magnfficatmns when ultrathm sectmns can be prepared  (Bresson, 1981, Blsdom, 1981; Bisdom et al., 1983b). Apart from these  techniques several other submicroscopic methods have been introduced for  m situ microchemmal element analysis, e.g. EMA (electron microprobe  analyzer), LAMMA (laser mmroprobe mass analyzer) and SIM (secondary  Ion mmroscopy) (Bisdom, 1981).    REFERENCES    Blsdom, E.B.A., 1981. A review of the application of submicroscopic techniques in soil  micromorphology, II Electron-microprobe analyzer (EMA), scanning electron micro-  scope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis (ESCA), ion microprobe  mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary ion microscope (SIM). In' E B.A BIsdom  (Editor), Submmroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  natlonal Working-Group on Submlcroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen  Centre for Agricultural Pubhshing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wagenlngen, pp. 117--162  Bisdom, E.B A., 1982  Microchemical analysls In thin sections of soils. International  Working-Meeting on Soil Micromorphology, August 17th--21st, 1981, London In  press  Bisdom, E B A and Thiel, F, 1981 Backscattered electron scanning images of porositles  in thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM-EDX-  RA. In  E.B A. Bisdom (Edltor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks 1st  Workshop of the Internatlonal Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undlsturbed  Soil Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bmdom, E B A  and Jongerius, A, 1983  SEM-EDXRA studies of precipitates which  clogged a water-tube filter. Geoderma, 30' 253--270  Bisdom, E.B.A, Henstra, S, Werner, H.W., Boudewijn, P., De Grefte, H A M, Knippen-  berg, W F, Gourgout, J.M. and Migeon, H N., 1983a. Quantltative analysis of trace  and other elements in thin sections of soils with the secondary ion microscope  (Cameca). Geoderma, 30: 117--134.  B1sdom, E.B.A, Nauta, R. and Volbert, B, 1983b  STEM-EDXRA and SEM-EDXRA  lnvestigatlon of iron-coated organic material in thin sections with transmltted, second-  ary and backscattered electrons Geoderma, 30- 77--91_    116    Bresson, L.M, 1981. Etude ultramicroscoplque d'assemblages plasmlques sur lames ultra-  minces de sols r4alis4es par bombardement lomque In. E B.A. Blsdom (Editor), Sub-  microscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks 1st Worksop of the International Work-  rag-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wagen-  lngen  Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc), Wagenmgen,  pp 173--189.  Henstra, S, Bisdom, E.B.A., Jongerms, A, Morgan, A E , Werner, H W and De Grefte,  H A M., 1980. Quantitative analysis on thin sections of soils by secondary mn mass  spectrometry In: P Brederoo and V E Cosslett (Editors), Electron Microscopy, 1980  Proceedings of the 7th European Congress on Electron Mmroscopy including the 9th  International Conference on X-ray Optics and Mmroanalysls, The Hague, 1980, Vol  3_ Analysis, pp. 224--225.  Henstra, S, Blsdom, E B A. and Boekestem, A, 1981 Submicroscopic techmques for in  s~tu mlcrochemmal analysis of soils, HI. Destructive techniques. In  E B A_ Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks  1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wagenmgen  Centre for Agrmultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wagenmgen, pp 55--65  Jackman, J J., 1980. New scanning electron mmroscope depends on multlfunctlon detec-  tors Ind. Res. Dev, 22(6). 115--120.  Jongerms, A. and Bisdom, E B.A, 1981. Porosity measurements using the Quantlmet  720 on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In E B A  Blsdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks 1st Workshop of the  International Working-Group on Submmroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGS-  USM) 1980, Wageningen  Centre for Agrmultural Pubhshing and Documentation  (Pudoc), Wagenmgen, pp. 207--216  Volbert, B, 1981  Verbesserung der topographischen Information dutch Ueberlagerung  yon Sekund~;relektronen (SE) --und invertmrtem Rilckstreuelektronen (BSE) --Signal  Beitrage Elektronenmikroskoplsche Dlrektabblldung und Analyse von Oberflachen  (EDO), Innsbruck, 14. 325--330.                                                                                                                   AbstractThe results of experiments on various materials in thin sections, using a Scanning Electron Microscope with a secondary electron detector and four backscattered electron detectors, are discussed. The Multi-Function-Detector (MFD) system for backscattered electrons allows the observation of the ‘real’ topography in a thin section with the SE-BSE mode and is also able to give good information on the contrasts in materials (atomic contrasts) with the BSE (A+B) mode. Various other possibilities are also present with this system, e.g. the study of soil materials over different depths below the surface of a thin section. Of considerable interest is the possibility to start the investigation of thin sections at X 10 magnification without the loss of part of the picture on the display screen or micrograph. As a consequence, interpretational steps from the field observations to light microscopy and submicroscopy will most probably become easier in the near future. Maximum magnifications using the BSE-signal were dependent on the type of analysed material, but were usually significantly higher than with older backscattered electron detector systems. 