Geoderma, 27 (1982) 283--309                                                      283  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE FERTILITY CAPABILITY SOIL CLASSIFICATION SYSTEM:  INTERPRETATION, APPLICABILITY AND MODIFICATION*    PEDRO A. SANCHEZ, WALTER COUTO' and STANLEY W. BUOL'  North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27650 (U.S.A.)  (Received May 22, 1981; accepted October 12, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Sanchez, P.A., Couto, W. and Buol, S.W., 1982. The Fertility Capability Soil Classifica-  tion System: interpretation, applicability and modification. Geoderma, 27: 283--309.    This paper summarizes the first five years of testing and evaluation of the Fertility  Capability Soil Classification System (FCC) and presents an improved version, examples  of interpretation and its applicability. FCC is a technical system for grouping soils accord-  ing to the kinds of problems they present for agronomic management of their chemical  and physical properties. It emphasizes quantifiable topsoil parameters as well as subsoil  properties directly relevant to plant growth. FCC-classes indicate the main fertility-related  soil constraints, which can be interpreted in relation to specific farming systems or land  utilization types. Since its publication in 1975, the FCC has been tested, evaluated and  put to use in various countries. As a result, the definitions of several modifiers have been  changed and additional modifiers have been introduced. Soil maps can be interpreted and  redrawn as FCC-units when the necessary data are available. Portions of the FAO/Unesco  (1971, 1974, 1977) Soil Maps of the World have been converted to FCC-units with minor  difficulties. The system is directly applicable to FAO's (1976) Land Evaluation Guidelines.    INTRODUCTION    The Fertility Capability Soil Classification System (FCC) was developed as  an attempt to bridge the gap between the subdisciplines of soil classification  and soil fertility (Buol, 1972; Buol et al., 1975). As a technical soil classifica-  tion system, it focuses on a specific use of natural soil classification systems,  such as Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975) or of the legend for the FAO-  Unesco Soil Maps of the World (FAO-Unesco, 1971, 1974, 1977) which are  essentially a record of soil properties. The direct interpretation of natural  systems for specific uses is difficult because criteria relevant to a specific soil    *Paper Number 6555 of the Journal Series of the North Carolina Agricultural Research  Service, Raleigh, NC 27650, U.S.A. Contribution of the Tropical Soils Program supported  by Contract AID/ta-C-1236. Presented at a Consultation on Land Evaluation for Rainfed  Agriculture, FAO, Rome, December 13, 1979.  1 Professor, former Visiting Assistant Professor and Professor, Department of Soil Science,  North Carolina State University, respectively. Dr. Couto is now Soil Scientist, Pasture  Development, Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical stationed in Brasilia, Brazil.    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 O 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    284    use are confounded with other criteria, because a natural system attempts  to organize all the features that can be measured in a soil (Cline, 1949}.  Natural soil classification systems place more emphasis on subsurface than on  topsoil properties, because of their more permanent nature, whereas most  soil management practices are largely limited to the plowed layer. In south-  eastern United States, for example, Sopher and McCracken (1973) found  that 70% of crop yield variability were due to soil properties that occurred  in the plowed layer.  There are technical soil classification systems in use for several specific  purposes such as land use capability, suitability for septic tanks, woodland,  wildlife, range sites, roads and airport construction (Bartelli, 1978). To our  knowledge FCC is the first technical soil classification system that groups  soils according to their fertility constraints in a quantitative manner. The  purpose of this paper is to report some improvements in the system as a re-  sult of five years of testing and to set forth examples of interpretations that  can be made of FCC units and their applicability to land resource evaluation  studies. The term "topsoil" refers to the plower layer or the top 20 cm of  the soil, whichever is shallower. The term "subsoil" encompasses the depth  interval between the topsoil and 60 cm depth.    THE SYSTEM    The system consists of three categorical levels: type (topsoil texture), sub-  strata type (subsoil texture), and 15 modifiers, including several changes  from the original version (Buol et al., 1975) making the following, in effect  the second approximation. The classes within each categorical level are  defined below. Class designations from the three categorical levels are com-  bined to form an FCC-unit.    Type. Texture of plow-layer or surface 20 cm, whichever is shallower:  S = sandy topsoils: loamy sands and sands (by USDA definition);  L = loamy topsoils: &lt; 35% clay but not loamy sand or sand;  C = clayey topsoils: &gt; 35% clay;  O = organic soils: &gt; 30% O.M. to a depth of 50 cm or more.    Substrata type (texture of subsoil). Used only if there is a marked textural  change from the surface, or if a hard root-restricting layer is encountered  within 50 cm:  S = sandy subsoil: texture as in type;  L = loamy subsoil: texture as in type;  C = clayey subsoil: texture as in type;  R = rock or other hard root-restricting layer.    Modifiers. Where more than one criterion is listed for each modifier, only  one needs to be met. The criterion listed first is the most desirable one and    285    should be used if data are available. Subsequent criteria are presented for  use where data are limited.  g = (gley): soil or mottles ~&lt; 2 chroma within 60 cm of the soil surface and  below all A horizons, or soil saturated with water for &gt; 60 days in most  years;  d = (dry): ustic, aridic or xeric soil moisture regimes (subsoil dry &gt; 90 cumu-  lative days per year within 20--60 cm depth);  e = (low cation exchange capacity): applies only to plow layer or surface 20  cm, whichever is shallower: CEC &lt; 4 meq./100 g soil by Z bases + KC1-  extractable A1 (effective CEC), or CEC &lt; 7 meq./100 g soft by 2; cations  at pH 7, or CEC ~ 10 meq./100 g soil by E cations + A1 + H at pH 8.2;  a = (aluminum-toxicity): &gt; 60% Al-saturation of the effective CEC within  50 cm of the soil surface, or &gt; 67% acidity saturation of CEC by E ca-  tions at pH 7 within 50 cm of the soil surface, or ~ 86% acidity satura-  tion of CEC by ~ cations at pH 8.2 within 50 cm of the soil surface, or  pH ~ 5.0 in 1:1 H20 within 50 cm, except in organic softs where pH  must be less than 4.7;  h = (acid): 10-60% Al-saturation of the effective CEC within 50 cm of soil  surface, or pH in 1:1 H20 between 5.0 and 6.0;  i = (high P-fixation by iron): % free Fe:O3/% clay &gt; 0.15 and more than  35% clay, or hues of 7.5 YR or redder and granular structure. This  modifier is used only in clay (C) types; it applies only to plow-layer  or surface 20 cm of soil surface, whichever is shallower;  x = (X-ray amorphous): pH &gt; 10 in 1N NaF, or positive to field NaF test, or  other indirect evidences of allophane dominance in the clay fraction;  v = (vertisol): very sticky plastic clay: &gt; 35% clay and &gt; 50% of 2:1 expand-  ing clays, or severe topsoil shrinking and swelling;  k = (low K reserves): &lt; 10% weatherable minerals in silt and sand fraction  within 50 cm of the soil surface, or exchangeable K &lt; 0.20 meq./100 g,  or K ~ 2% of ~ bases; if bases &lt; 10 meq./100 g;  b = (basic reaction): free CaCO3 within 50 cm of soil surface (effervescence  with HC1), or pH &gt; 7.3;  s = (salinity):/&gt; 4 mmhos/cm of electrical conductivity of saturated extract  at 25 within 1 m of the soil surface;  n = (natric): t&gt; 15% Na-saturation of CEC within 50 cm of the soil surface;  c = (cat clay): pH in 1:1 H20 is &lt; 3.5 after drying and jarosite mottles with  hues of 2.5 Y or yellower and chromas 6 or more are present within 60  cm of the soil surface;  '  = (gravel): a prime (') denotes 15--35% gravel or coarser (&gt; 2 mm) particles  by volume to any type or substrata type texture (example: S'L = gravel-  ly, sand over loamy; SL' = sandy over gravelly loam); two prime marks  (") denote more than 35% gravel or coarser particles (&gt; 2 mm) by volume  in any type or substrata type (example: LC" = loamy over clayey skeletal;  L'C" = gravelly loam over clayey skeletal);  % = (slope): where it is desirable to show slope with the FCC, the slope    286    range percentage can be placed in parentheses after the last condition  modifier (example: Sb (1--6%) = uniformly sandy soil, calcareous in  reaction, 1--6% slope).  The soils are classified by determining whether the characteristic is present  or not. Most of the quantitative limits are criteria present in Soil Taxonomy  (Soil Survey Staff, 1975}. The FCC unit then lists the type and substrata  type (if present} in capital letters, and the modifiers in lower-case letters, the  gravel modifier as a prime (') and the slope, if desired, in parentheses. For  example, many Oxisols belong to the FCC unit C a e i k (i.e., clayey, A1-  toxic, low CEC, high P-fixation by iron, low K-reserves), many Vertisols to  C d v b (i.e., clayey, dry season, vertic, calcareous), whereas a young alluvial  Entisol with no fertility limitations is simply classified as L (loamy soil). The  absence of modifiers suggests no major fertility limitations, other than nitro-  gen deficiency.    INTERPRETATION OF FCC NOMENCLATURE    Thus far, only the structure of the FCC-system and the criteria for placing  soils into the system have been discussed. Classification is not an end in itself.  Any classification must convey information in order to be useful. At this  time it has not been feasible to test all possible interpretations from FCC-  units, but some of the applicable interpretations are outlined below. The  statements used are brief and may not reflect the total range of desirable in-  terpretations. They are written in non-technical terms for ease of understand-  ing by users of soil-survey or land-use reports. They attempt to call the user's  attention to the major limitations that will be encountered within an FCC  class.    Interpretation of types and substrata types    S: high rate of infiltration, low water-holding capacity.  L: medium infiltration rate, good water-holding capacity.  C: low infiltration rates, good water-holding capacity, potential high runoff  if sloping, difficult to till; when i modifier is present, these (Ci) soils are  easy to till, have high infiltration rates and low water-holding capacity.  O: artificial drainage is needed and subsidence will occur; possible micro-  nutrient deficiencies; high herbicide rates usually required.  SC, LC, LR, SR: susceptible to severe soil degradation from erosion expos-  ing undesirable subsoil; high priority should be given to erosion control.    In terpre tation of modifiers    When only one modifier is included in the FCC unit, the following limita-  tions or management requirements apply to the soil. Interpretations may differ  when two or more modifiers are present simultaneously or when textural  types are different.    287    g: denitrification frequently occurs in anaerobic subsoil; tillage operations  and certain crops may be adversely affected by excess rain unless drainage  is improved by tiling or other drainage procedures; good soft moisture  regime for rice production.  d: moisture is limiting during the dry season unless soft is irrigated; planting  date should take into account the flush of N at onset of rains; germination  problems are often experienced if first rains are sporadic.  e: low ability to retain nutrients against leaching, mainly K, Ca and Mg;  heavy applications of these nutrients and of N fertilizers should be split;  potential danger of overliming.  a: plants sensitive to Al-toxicity will be affected unless lime is applied; extrac-  tion of soft water below depth of lime incorporation will be restricted;  lime requirements are high unless an e modifier is also indicated; this  modifier is desirable for rapid dissolution of phosphate rocks and for good  latex flow in rubber (Chan, 1980); Mn-toxicity may occur on some of these  softs.  h: low to medium soil acidity; requires liming for Al-sensitive crops, such as  cotton and alfalfa.  i: high P-fixation capacity; requires high levels of P fertilizer or special P man-  agement practices; sources and method of P fertilizer application should be  considered carefully; with C texture, these softs have granular soil structure.  x: high P-fixation capacity; amount and most convenient source of P to be  determined; low organic N mineralization rates.  v: clayey textured topsoil with shrink and swell properties; tillage is difficult  when too dry or too moist, but softs can be highly productive; P-deficiency  common.  k: low ability to supply K; availability of K should be monitored and K  fertilizers may be required frequently; potential K-Mg-Ca imbalances.  b: calcareous soils; rock phosphate and other non-water-soluble phosphates  should be avoided; potential deficiency of certain micronutrients, princi-  pally iron and zinc.  s: presence of soluble salts; requires drainage and special management for  salt-sensitive crops or the use of salt-tolerant species and cultivars.  n: high levels of sodium; requires special soft management practices for alkaline  soils, including use of gypsum amendments and drainage.  c: potential acid sulfate soft; drainage is not recommended without special  practices; should be managed with plants tolerant to high .water table level.  By using the individual guides for each type, substrata type, and modifiers,  it is possible to prepare composite interpretation guidelines for all of the pos-  sible FCC-units. More comprehensive interpretative statements are possible  when interactions of two or more soil conditions are considered. No necessity  is seen for a complete listing of all possible combinations because only a lim-  ited number of FCC-units will be found in any area under consideration. At  the local level, however, interpretation of the FCC-units found in relation to  the main crops and specific farming systems used would be a valuable exten-    288    sion tool and local expertise is expected to supplement the following brief  statements where experience warrants.    Sample interpretations of FCC units    Lehk:    Lgh:    LCgeak:    L:    good water-holding capacity, medium infiltration capacity; low  ability to retain nutrients for plants, mainly K, Ca, Mg; heavy ap.  plications of these nutrients and N fertilizers should be split; re-  quires liming for Al-sensitive crops; potential danger of overlim-  ing because of low CEC; low ability to supply K; availability of  K should be monitored and K-fertilizers may be required fre-  quently for plants requiring high levels of K.  good water-holding capacity, medium infiltration capacity; limi-  tations in drainage so that tillage operations and some crops  may be adversely affected unless drainage is improved by tiling  or other procedures; strong to medium acid soil; liming required  for some crops; excellent soil for flooded rice, as acidity will be  eliminated by flooding.  erosion or other removal of surface soil will expose undesirable  clay-textured subsoil; drainage limited so that tillage operations  and some crops may be adversely affected unless drainage is im-  proved by tiling or other procedures; low ability to retain nu-  trients for plants, mainly K, Ca, Mg; heavy applications of these  nutrients and N fertilizer should be split; plants sensitive to AI-  toxicity will be affected unless lime is deeply incorporated; how-  ever, deep liming practices are difficult because of ciay-textured  substrate; due to low CEC in the surface, there is a danger of  overliming; low ability to supply K; availability of K should be  monitored and K fertilizers may be required frequently for  plants requiring high levels of K.  excellent soil with no major fertility constraints; N deficiency  likely with intensive use.    TESTING THE SYSTEM    The validity of the FCC system has been tested with soil profile data from  various parts of the world, and with field fertilizer response data from Brazil,  Peru, Colombia and the United States. These evaluations have been described  in the annual reports of the Tropical Soils Program (North Carolina State  University, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1976, 1978) and by Couto (1976a, 1977),  Buol and Nicholaides (1980) and Buol and Couto (1981). A summary of the  results follows. The FCC was first tested with data sets on a worldwide basis,  678 soil profiles from one country (Brazil), 73 potato fertilization sites in  Peru and a detailed soil survey map of Wake County, North Carolina (Buol et  al., 1975). These initial studies showed that: (1) soil individuals in one FCC-    289    unit may belong to different orders, suborders, great groups, subgroups or  families in Soil Taxonomy or other natural systems; (2) the number of FCC-  units in a given area or data set is much smaller than Soil Taxonomy units,  thereby simplifying interpretations; (3) making fertilizer recommendations  by FCC units was more profitable than making generalized recommendations.  When fertilizer recommendations were based on a blanket recommenda-  tion, as is often done, the average return to fertilizers in 73 potato fertiliza-  tion trials in Peru was U.S.$770/ha (North Carolina State University, 1973).  When fertilizer recommendations were based on site-specific soil test results  (available P, exchangeable K and pH) the average returns increased to $860/  ha, or 12%. When softs were grouped by FCC-units and the rates determined  from a generalized response curve for each unit, the average returns increased  to U.S.$920/ha, or 20%. Finally, when fertilizer rates were determined for  FCC-units and site-specific soil tests the returns increased to $965/ha, or  25%. This study showed the complementary nature of the FCC-system with  soil testing.  These concepts were further evaluated with fertilizer response data from  542 sites of the FAO/ANDA/ABCAR simple fertilizer trials conducted in  the states of Minas Gerais and Goias, Brazil, from 1969 to 1973. Of these,  248 were with upland rice, 205 with corn, 45 with beans, 31 with cotton and  13 with potatoes. The results summarized in North Carolina State University  (1974} showed that textural differences manifested by the type-substrata  type designation had major effects on yields of all crops. The C soils invariably  produced higher yields than LC soils, which, in turn, gave higher yields than  SL soils. Although these results are applicable only to this data set, differences  were as high as 77% for yields of C vs. SL soils in upland rice and 47% for  yields of C vs. LC softs with cotton. The absence of the e (low CEC) modifier  invariably resulted in higher yields. The a (Al-toxic) modifier reduced yields  in all crops except for potatoes, where yields increased due to this species'  Al-tolerance and reduced incidence of disease in more acid pH ranges. As ex-  pected, the a modifier had a marked detrimental effect on cotton yields, it  being the most aluminum-sensitive crop in this study. The presence of the i  modifier (originally defined as % Fe203/% clay &gt; 0.2 by Buol et al., 1975)  did not indicate yield depressions due to P fixation. The phosphorus fertilizers  rates used in these Brazilian trials were too low to overcome P fixation. In  several cases the results were not as consistent as expected, particularly with  the i and k modifiers. Part of the problem was the limited range in fertilizer  treatments, the absence of liming, differences in crop cultivars used, yield  decreases due to drought, insect attacks and other factors not associated with  fertility problems. In spite of these limitations the system performed satis-  factorily. Subsequent laboratory studies redefined the i modifier as the ratio  of % free Fe:O3/% clay greater than 0.15 and more than 35% clay (Couto,  1976b; Pope, 1976, 1978; Pope and Buol, 1976).  A less extensive evaluation conducted with data from 15 corn experi-  ments in Colombia showed that the h and b modifiers were primarily re-  sponsible for yield differences (Couto, 1976c).    290    Because the system had been tested so far with data from developing  countries, a test of its applicability in more intensive farming systems in the  United States was undertaken. Couto (1978) evaluated the system with  regional soybean trials conducted throughout the southeastern United States  between 1968 and 1973 by the U.S. Department of Agriculture. The 184  sites located from Virginia to Texas were grouped into 26 FCC units, many  of which included different soil orders. In spite of the intensive level of  fertilization used, lower soybean yields were observed when the e and k  modifiers were present, indicating low CEC and low ability to supply K. Sites  with g, d, a and h modifiers produced high yields because moisture and  acidity limitations were corrected by drainage, irrigation and liming. The  presence of the acidity modifiers was well correlated with the use of lime in  these soybean trials. Among those sites showing the a modifier, 80% of them  were limed, as opposed to only 20% of the sites not having the a or h modi-  fier. Likewise 76% of the sites with a k modifier received K fertilization, in  contrast with only 49% for sites without this modifier. In years where above  average rainfall occurred during the crucial month of August, sites with a g  modifier (poor drainage) suffered yield losses, although sites without this  modifier were not affected.  These evaluations showed that the FCC system is a meaningful tool for  relating fertility limitations to crop yield responses in a wide variety of softs  and crops. As expected, FCC classification is not sufficient to predict yield  response as factors not related to fertility obviously affect yields and yield  responses. The FCC system was also found as valid in low input systems of  Central Brazil as in areas with a long history of intensive fertilization in south-  eastern United States.    INTERPRETATION OF SOIL MAPS WITH FCC    Mapping units can be converted into FCC units provided sufficient informa-  tion is available. This is easy to accomplish in detailed soil maps and has been  done for the Yurimaguas region of the Peruvian Amazon and the Centro de  Pesquisa Agropecuhria dos Cerrados near Planaltina, Brazil by W. Couto. In  both cases, the maps show how soil differences within relatively small areas  could affect the interpretation and extrapolation of the experimental results.  It has been possible to convert data for the dominant soils of the FAO  Soil Maps of the World into FCC units based on the definitions of the map-  ping legend, including the information at the phase level, which is necessary  to determine type and substrata type. The conversion is based on the typical  profile data plus the definitions of the mapping units themselves, their phases  and climate. Also, papers by Dudal (1976, 1977) on plant nutrient relation-  ships of FAO Soil Units and Soil Taxonomy equivalents were helpful in this  interpretation. A sample of such conversions from the World Soil Map of  Africa (FAO, 1977) is shown in Table I. In some of these units it was impos-  sible to determine FCC textural types as no textural notation was given, for  example, mapping units Lg 21 and So 1-a.       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd       ~6~--T6u'dd    299    TABLE I    Sample conversion of FAO mapping units of the World Soil Map of Africa (FAO-Unesco,  1977) into FCC classes based on properties of the dominant soil (slope not included as  this is self-explanatory in the FAO units)  Mapping        FAO map legend       FCC unit  unit  symbol    Af 1--1/2a     Ferric Acrisol          L C d a e k  Af 18--1a      Ferric Acrisol          S C d a e k  Ao 63--3b      Orthic Acrisol         C d h  Ap 22--2b      Plinthic Acrisol        L C" d g e h k  Bc 8--2b       Chromic Cambisol     L d  Bd 33--2a      Dystric Cambisol       L h  Bk 2--26       Calcic Cambisol        L d b  E 12--26       Rendzina              L R d b  E 14--2c       Rendzina              L d b  Fh 1--3b       Humic Ferralsol        Ch i k  Fo 90--2/3b    Orthic Ferralsol        C e a i k  Gd 5--2a       Dystric Gleysol        L C g e a k  Ge 32--213a    Eutric Gleysol         L C g h  Hh 9--2b       Haplic Phaeozem      L d  H1 36--2a      Luvic Phaeozem       L R d  Je 1--2a        Eutric Fluvisol         L d  Lc 37--1ab     Chromic Luvisol       S d b  Lf 18--1a      Ferric Luvisol          S C d e h k  Lg 21          Gleyic Luvisol         g d h  Nd 1--2a       Dystric Nitosol        L C e a k  Ne 7--2/3b     Eutric Nitosol         L C" d k  Od 10--1/2a    Dystric Histosol        O g h  Ph 5--1a       Humic Podzol         S e h k  Qa 5--1a       Albic Arenesol         S R d e h k  Qc 30--la      Cambic Arenesol       Se k  Rc 1--1b       Chromic Regosol      S d e k b  Rc 25--3c      Chromic Regosol       C R d e k b  So 1--a         Orthic Solonetz        d n  So 9--2/3a     Orthic Solonetz        L C d n  Tm 8--213c    Mollic Andosol        L d x  To 8--1b       Orthic Andosol        S d x  Vc 26---3a      Chromic Vertisol       C d v b  Vp 10--3a      Pellic Vertisol          C d v b  We 2--1a       Eutric Planosil         S C g d n  Xh 22--1/2ab  Haplic Xerosol         L R d  Xk 10--2a      Calcic Xerosol         L d b  Y 1--1a        Yermosol              S' d  Yh 17--2c      Haplic Yermosol       L R d  Zg 3--3a       Gleyic Solonchak      C g d b s  Zo 5--213a     Orthic Solonchak      L C d s    300    Fig. 1 shows the conversion of the World Soil Map of South America  (FAO, 1971) into FCC-units. Figs. 2, 3, 4 and 5 extract from the FCC-map  of South America the locations where certain fertility constraints are more  prevalent. Fig. 2 shows the distribution of toxic levels of A1, where the a  modifier predominates. Likewise, Fig. 3 shows the regions with the i modi-  fier, indicating severe P fixation and Fig. 4 those with low K reserves, as in-  dicated by the k modifier. By using plastic overlays, Fig. 5 shows the areas  affected by these three factors, aluminum toxicity, high phosphorus fixation  and low potassium reserves.    SYSTEM UTILIZATION    Small scale maps may be useful for worldwide assessments, but similar  techniques at a large scale can be very helpful in providing a framework for  assessing fertility problems at the regional or local level. FONAIAP (the  National Agricultural Research Foundation of Venezuela), is mapping sys-  tematically the country according to FCC at scales ranging from 1:100 000  to 1:500 000 depending on the intensity of agricultural development in a  particular state or region. Reports and maps have already been published for  the States of Barinas, Portuguesa, Cojedes and parts of Zulia and Anzohtegui  (Luque and Avilhn, 1976; Avilhn et al., 1977, 1978, 1979; Brito et al., 1979).  Similarly, the soil maps of Ecuador are being interpreted according to FCC by  the Regionalization Program. Maps or interpretations have also been made  for the Campinas quadrangle of S~o Paulo (Oliveira, 1978) in Brazil, through-  out Latin America by CIAT's Land Resource Evaluation Study (CIAT, 1978,  1979, 1980; Cochrane, 1979}, and by Sanchez and Cochrane (1980) in an  assessment of soil constraints in tropical America. The FCC-system is also  being used in land resource evaluation studies in Liberia, Ivory Coast and  Indonesia.    FURTHER SYSTEM MODIFICATIONS    Because the FCC-system was developed as an attempt to convey fertility  management information, several soil features related to other soil manage-  ment problems were not included. Suggestions have been made for certain  features to be included which would make the system more applicable to soil  management limitations for instance, in toposequences of West Africa. The  particular features desired include gravel content, slope and perhaps more  than one organic matter class. In response, gravel and slope modifiers are  now included in the system.  Organic matter has been deliberately excluded until there is evidence of a  certain critical organic-matter content below which a sufficiently different  set of fertility management practices is required for a wide range of soils and  farming systems. Where such knowledge already exists, as a critical C/N ratio  for rubber in Malaysia {Chan, 1980), an additional modifier can be added for    301    Fig. 2. Areas of South America where dominant soils have potential Al-toxicity problems  (a modifier).    O~c~  0  C)  e~  e~  0  =r  e~  e~    G    C~  0  ~D  0  iv    0    304    Fig. 5. Areas of South America where dominant soils have Al-toxicity, high P-fixation by  iron and low K-reserves (a, i and k modifers; only areas having triple cross-hatching have  the three modifiers).    305    this specific land use. The limits must be quantitative and capable of being  determined with straightforward analytical techniques.  Modifications introduced by Venezuelan and Brazilian users so far have  concentrated on changing the type and modifier symbols to correspond with  Spanish and Portuguese equivalents of "sandy", "clayey", etc. Although  such translations may cause confusion at the international level, they certain-  ly facilitate the understanding of FCC-units by the local users, and therefore,  we favor them. In the Campinas study, however, Oliveira (1978) proposed an  additional definition of the i modifier, in order to include the role of gibb-  site in P fixation, as follows:    % free Fe203 + 1.5 (% gibbsite) + 2 (% clay) &gt;/ 25    4.5    In his publication, however, Oliveira was careful to classify his soils accord-  ing to both the present FCC-system and his changed system. In order to  facilitate international communications, we suggest users of the system fol-  low Oliveira's approach.  Rather than adding additional classes, the more commonly expected  changes of the FCC-system are subdivisions of the modifiers themselves, in  order to establish more precise limits for specific land use purposes. Users of  the system are encouraged to use an asterisk (*) or two (**) in such cases.  Care should be taken, however, to identify the limits of each modification in  a quantitative fashion.  There are several instances in which such modifications are obviously  desirable. For example, the conductivity limit set for salinity stress in the s  modifier (4 mmho/cm) is too broad for salt-sensitive crops such as cassava,  which suffers from salinity stress at 0.4 mmho/cm (Lebn and Medina, 1977).  For cassava land use systems, therefore, a new s* modifier may be defined as  having a conductivity of 0.4 mmho/cm or above.  At the other end of the soil fertility spectrum, it appears necessary to sub-  divide the a modifier in order to distinguish extremely Al-tolerant pasture  species such as Andropogon gayanus and Stylosanthes capitata from some-  what less tolerant ones such as Panicum maximum and Pueraria phaseoloides.  An a* modifier defined as 80% Al-saturation of the effective CEC or above  would make this distinction while retaining the original a modifier with its  &gt; 60% definition. Similar modifications for rubber or oil palm plantations  appear necessary according to Chan (1980).  When introducing such changes, the present FCC-modifiers should remain  without asterisk (*) marks. The new ones with the asterisks should be ac-  companied by a footnote on the specific report or map.    APPLICABILITY TO FAO LAND-EVALUATION GUIDELINES    The FCC-system can be incorporated in FAO's Framework for Land    306    Evaluation (FAO, 1976) and the guidelines being prepared for rainfed and ir-  rigated agriculture. Because of its likely use on a worldwide basis, these land  evaluation guidelines are of significance. Each FCC type, substrata type and  modifier fits FAO's definition of a land characteristic, "an attribute of land  that can be measured or estimated" (FAO, 1976). This document correctly  states that if land characteristics are evaluated by themselves, problems arise  by ignoring interactions between characteristics. The use of FCC units elimi-  nates this problem, insofar as fertility-related characteristics, by using inter-  pretations such as the ones previously described in this paper. The "Frame-  work" defines land qualities as "a complex attribute of land which acts in a  distinct manner in its influence on the suitability of land for a specific kind  of use" (FAO, 1976). The authors of this paper interpret this concept as a  qualitative grouping of interacting land characteristics. Land qualities can be  quantified in terms of the cost of removing constraints or of potential gains  in relation to specific land use at a specific location and time frame. The use  of FCC units and similarly defined technical systems for classifying other  land attributes can lead to the quantification of land qualities in physical  terms.  The "Framework for Land Evaluation" lists seventeen land qualities re-  lated to productivity or plant growth. Seven of them are related to FCC-  parameters: "Nutrient availability", "salinity and alkalinity", "soil tox-  icities", "oxygen availability to the root zone", "moisture availability",  "adequacy of foothold for roots" (physical support), and "resistance to soil  erosion".    Nutrient availability    Interpretations of FCC units such as those previously described in this  paper are a direct expression of this land quality. Soil test critical levels are  not recommended in assessing this land quality as these are transient mea-  sures increased or decreased by management. When dealing with a well de-  fined land use system using specific crops and cultivars, then the critical soil  test or foliar analysis levels could complement the FCC units which reflect  the more stable fertility constraints.    Salinity and alkalinity    The presence of s and n modifiers will define this land quality. The pres-  ence of the g modifier indicating poor drainage, and the v modifier indicat-  ing difficulties in tillage will further aid the interpretation. Outside of the  FCC system, the availability of water for leaching out salts and of a sink to  deposit the drainage waters are other important considerations. The avail-  ability of gypsum for reclaiming sodic soils enters into the interpretation at  the local level. As mentioned before, the limits of these modifiers may need  to be changed in accordance with accepted critical levels for the crops and  cultivars in question.    307    Soil toxicities    This land quality will be present as indicated by the following FCC-units:  (1) For non-flooded farming systems: a = Al-toxicity, ag = possible Mn-  toxicity if organic matter contents are above 5%. c = toxic acidity levels when  acid sulfate softs are drained.  Again, local modifications, such as a*, a** could be used for specific crops.  (2) For flooded farming systems, mainly rice: Ci = potential iron toxicity,  Oa = potential organic acid toxicity, b = potential CO2-toxicity, c = potential  AI-, Fe- and H2S-toxicities.    Oxygen availability to the root zone    The g modifier is an indication that oxygen will not be available in some  layers within the top 50 cm during part or all of the growing season. For rice  this is irrelevant.    Moisture availability    The type-substrata types play a major role in defining soil water holding  capacity whereas the g and d modifiers indicate either an excess or deficit of  soil moisture. Some examples: S, Ci: low water holding capacity; L: medium  water holding capacity; C {except Ci): high water-holding capacity; R: physical  limitation of water availability due to shallow depth; a: chemical limitation of  subsoil water availability to Al-sensitive plants.  Climatic factors such as rainfall distribution obviously have to be taken in-  to account in regard to this land quality. FCC does little in this respect, how-  ever, the d modifier indicates potential germination and seedling mortality  problems caused by planting during the dry season and sporadic rainfall at  the onset of the rainy season.    Adequacy of foothold to roots    R = physical barrier within 50 cm limits growth; O = subsidence when  drained may hamper permanent crops; a = chemical barrier within 50 cm, will  limit root development to Al-sensitive crops; L', L", S', S", C', C" = moderate  to severe limitations due to gravel or concretionary materials in the topsoil.    Resistance to soil erosion    Ci, Cx, Lx = deterioration of soil productivity is less affected by erosion in  these highly permeable soils; SC, LC, SR, LR, S'C, L'C, S"C, L"C, S'C, S"R,  L'R, L"R = severe deterioration caused by erosion; v, bv = high erodibility  soils.  The % {slope) factor when added to the FCC-system will help evaluate  resistance to soil erosion. Rainfall erosivity also has to be taken into account.    308    REFERENCES    Avil~n, L., Granados, F., Hidalgo, E. and P~rez, O., 1977. Clasificacibn interpretiva de los  suelos del Estado Portuguesa en base a su fertilidad. FONAIAP, Sub-Programa Suelos,  Maracay, Venezuela.  Avil~n, L., P~rez, O. and Mazzi, L., 1978. Clasificacibn interpretiva de los suelos del Estado  Barinas en base a su fertilidad. In: Resfimenes de trabajo. 5th Congr. Venezolano  Cienc. Suelo. Jusepfn, Venezuela.  Avil~n, L., P~rez, O. and Massi, L., 1979. Clasificacibn interpretiva de los suelos de los  Llanos Occidentales en base a su fertilidad. FONAIAP-CENIAP. Secc. Fert. Nutr. Miner.  Bol. Tec., 15.  Bartelli, L.J., 1978. Technical classification systems for soil survey interpretations. Adv.  Agron., 30: 247--289.  Brito, J.G., Brito, P. and Mazzi, L., 1979. Sistema de clasificacibn de suelos en base a su  fertilidad. FONAIAP-CENIAP. Sub-Programa Suelos. Bol. Tec., 18.  Buol, S.W., 1972. Fertility capability classification system. In: Agronomic-Economic  Research on Tropical Soils, Annual Report for 1971. Soil Sci. Dep., N.C. State Univ.,  Raleigh, NC, pp. 45--50.  Buol, S.W., Sanchez, P.A., Care, R.B., Jr. and Granger, M.A., 1975. Soil fertility capabil-  ity classification: a technical soil classification system for fertility management. In:  E. Bornemlsza and A. Alvarado (Editors), Soil Management in Tropical America. N.C.  State Univ., Raleigh, NC, pp. 126--145 (also in Spanish).  Buol, S.W. and Couto, W., 1978. Fertility management interpretations and soil surveys of  the tropics. In: Diversity of Soils in the Tropics. ASA Spec. Publ., 34: 65--75.  Buol, S.W. and Couto, W., 1981. Soil fertility capability assessment for use in the humid  tropics. In: D.J. Greenland (Editor), Characterization and Classification of Some Soils  of the Humid Tropics. Wiley, London, pp. 254--261.  Buol, S.W. and Nicholaides, J.J., III, 1980. Constraints to soil fertility evaluation and  extrapolation of research results. In: Priorities for Alleviating Soil-Related Constraints  to Food Production in the Tropics. IRRI, Los Banos, Philippines, pp. 425--438.  Chan, H.Y., 1980. Tropical tree crop requirements and land evaluation: a case experience  of Malaysia. Rubber Res. Inst. Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur.  CLAT, 1978, 1979, 1980. Annual Reports for 1977, 1978, 1979. Cent. Int. Agric. Tropic.,  Call, Colombia.  Cline, M.G., 1949. Basic principles of soil classification. Soil Sci., 67: 81--91.  Cochrane, T.T., 1979. An ongoing appraisal of the savanna ecosystems of tropical America  for beef cattle production. In: P.A. Sanchez and L.E. Tergas (Editors), Pasture Produc-  tion in Acid Soils of the Tropics. CIAT, Call, Colombia, pp. 1--12 (also in Spanish).  Couto, W,, 1976a. ClasificaciSn de suelos en base a su fertilidad. In: 4th Congr. Nac.  Cienc. Suelo, Maturin. Univ. Oriente, Jusepin, Venezuela, pp. 85--87.  Couto, W., 1976b. Evaluation of the i modifier (high phosphorus fixation by iron) with  corn experiments from Brazil. In: Agronomic-Economic Research on Soils of the  Tropics, Annual Report for 1975. NC State Univ., Raleigh, pp. 239--242.  Couto, W., 1976c. System evaluation in Colombia. In: Agronomic-Economic Research on  Soils of the Tropics. Annual Report for 1975. NC State Univ., Raleigh, pp. 240--245.  Couto, W., 1977. Fertility capability classification: a summary report. Tropical Soils  Program, N.C. State Univ., 73 pp. (mimeographed).  Couto, W., 1978. System assessment in the U.S. In: Agronomic-Economic Research on  Soils of the Tropics. Annual Report for 1976--1977. N.C. State Univ., Raleigh, pp.  235--243.  Dudal, R., 1976. Inventory of major soils of the world with special reference to mineral  stress hazards. In: M.J. Wright (Editor), Plant Adaptation to Mineral Stress in Problem  Soils. Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY, pp. 3--14.    309    Dudal, R., 1977. Plant nutrient relationships in major soil regions, pp. 78--88. In: Proc.  Int. Seminar Soil Environ. Fertil. Manage., Intensive Agric. (SEFMIA). Soc. Sci. Soil  Manure, Japan.  FAO, 1971. Soil Map of the World, 4. South America. Unesco, Paris.  FAO, 1974. FAO-Unesco Soil Map of the World, 7. Legend. Unesco, Paris.  FAO, 1976. A Framework on Land Evaluation. FAO Soil Resour. Bull., FAO, Rome.  FAO, Unesco, 1977. Soil Map of the World, 6. Africa. Unesco, Paris.  LeSn, L.A. and Medina, C., 1977. DiagnSstico y recuperaciSn de suelos salinos y sSdicos  en relaciSn al cultivo de frijol. CIAT, Cali, Colombia, 25 pp.  Luque, O. and Avil~n, R.L., 1976. ClasificaciSn conforme a la fertilidad de los suelos de  la mesa de Guanipa, Estado Anzo~tegui. In: Resdmenes de trabajo, Congr. Venezolano  Cienc. Suelo. Maturfn, p. 4.  North Carolina State University, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1976, 1978. Annual Reports, Tropic-  al Soils Program. Soil Sci. Dep., Raleigh, NC.  Oliveira, J.B., 1978. Classificaqa'o de solos de quadrfcula de Campinas. Inst. Agron. Cam-  pinas, Bol. Tec., 59.  Pope, R.A., 1976. Use of soil survey information to estimate phosphate sorption by high-  ly weathered soils. Ph.D. Thesis, N.C. State Univ., Raleigh, 82 pp.  Pope, R.A. and Buol, S.W., 1976. Improving the i modifier. In: Agronomic-Economic  Research on Soils of the Tropics. Annual Report for 1975. NC State Univ., Raleigh,  pp. 245--250.  Pope, R.A., 1978. Modification of the i modifier. In: Agronomic-Economic Research on  Soils of the Tropics. Annual Report for 1976--1977. NC State Univ., Raleigh, pp.  229--235.  Sanchez, P.A. and Cochrane, T.T., 1980. Soil constraints in relation to major farming  systems in tropical America. In: Soil Constraints Conference, IRRI, Los Banos, Philip-  pines, pp. 107--140.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S.Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436, U.S. Dep. Agric., Washing-  ton, DC.  Sopher, C.D. and McCracken, R.J., 1973. Relationships below soil properties manage-  ment practices and corn yields on South Atlantic Coastal Plain soils. Agron. J., 65:  595--600.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractThis paper summarizes the first five years of testing and evaluation of the Fertility Capability Soil Classification System (FCC) and presents an improved version, examples of interpretation and its applicability. FCC is a technical system for grouping soils according to the kinds of problems they present for agronomic management of their chemical and physical properties. It emphasizes quantifiable topsoil parameters as well as subsoil properties directly relevant to plant growth. FCC-classes indicate the main fertility-related soil constraints, which can be interpreted in relation to specific farming systems or land utilization types. Since its publication in 1975, the FCC has been tested, evaluated and put to use in various countries. As a result, the definitions of several modifiers have been changed and additional modifiers have been introduced. Soil maps can be interpreted and redrawn as FCC-units when the necessary data are available. Portions of the FAO/Unesco (1971, 1974, 1977) Soil Maps of the World have been converted to FCC-units with minor difficulties. The system is directly applicable to FAO's (1976) Land Evaluation Guidelines.