 Geoderrna, 31 (1983) 133--150                                                  133  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    POINT  COUNTING  PORES  AND  ILLUVIAL  CLAY  IN  THIN  SECTION    C.P. MURPHY  Soil Survey of England and Wales, Rothamsted Experimental Station, Harpenden,  Herts. (U.K.)  (Received May 12, 1982; accepted after revision November 23, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Murphy, C.P., 1983. Point counting pores and illuvial clay in thin section. Geoderma,  31: 133--150.    Six soil thin sections containing various amounts of illuvial clay, previously estimated  by ten operators, were point-counted four times by an additional experienced operator.  The results indicate that a count of 6000 points over a section area of 25 x 25 mm is  sufficient to quantify satisfactorily the pore space of the section. Replicated results for  illuvial clay, however, differed widely for some sections. These differences are attributed  both to difficulties in recognising illuvial clay and to orientation and variability of soil  components. Variability of results for illuvial clay in this study was less than that re-  ported for ten operators but, nonetheless, it is evident that for most sections the amount  of illuvial clay cannot be estimated precisely by a single count of 6000 points. Sugges-  tions are made for improving the reliability of estimates of illuvial clay in soil thin sec-  tions and an improved basis for reporting results is proposed.    INTRODUCTION    Soil identification according to several current classification systems (e.g.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975; FAO, 1974; Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978;  Avery, 1980) entails recognition of subsurface horizons enriched in silicate  clay, either by field evidence or by the presence of more than a specified  amount (1 or 2%) of illuvial clay in a representative thin section. Sampling  problems and the imprecision of recognition criteria for illuvial clay lead to  difficulties. For example, less than half of the 44 horizons designated as Bt  (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978) in the field by McKeague et al.  (1978) were estimated to contain more than 1% illuvial clay identifiable  in thin section as required by the American and Canadian systems, and  more than one-third contained less than 0.2%. Such discrepancies between  field identification of argillic horizons, based on clay distribution and the  occurrence of visible "clay skins" on the one hand, and micromorpholog-  ical evidence of clay illuviation on the other, have also been noted by Hill  (1970), Fedoroff (1973) and Osman and Eswaran (1974). In describing thin    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    134    sections to support classification and mapping of soils in England and Wales,  these problems have been evident for several years and point counts on "rep-  resentative" thin sections have always been acknowledged as no more than  guides. Nevertheless, many workers (e.g. Kwaad and Mficher, 1979; Bullock  and Murphy, 1979) have attempted to measure the amounts of argillans  and other clay concentrations in thin sections and have treated the results as  representative of the materials from which samples were taken.  A study to determine the precision (reproducibility) of estimates of  illuvial clay by ten operators using similar techniques (McKeague et al.,  1980) highlighted large differences between operators. In one of the six  sections studied (7737-2) estimates of illuvial clay ranged from 1.7% to  17.8%. The authors concluded that quantitative estimates of illuvial clay by  different operators are not comparable at present, and that workshops are  needed to develop improved recognition criteria and "round robins" to test  the uniformity of interpretation. To this end the six thin sections analysed  by McKeague et al. (1980) were acquired at Rothamsted so that the docu-  mented results could be "checked" in this laboratory.  The aim of this study was therefore to examine the usefulness of point  counting soil thin sections for quantifying pores and iUuvial clay or other  micromorphological features present in small amounts, to show the problems  involved and to assess the reproducibility of results obtained by a single  operator. Brief details of the six sampled horizons are given in Table I.    Methods    The proportion of illuvial clay in each of the six thin sections was esti-  mated by point counting four times over the same area of 25 X 25 mm as  by McKeague et al. (1980) but with a different orientation to the section  for each count. The four counts on each section were performed with the  section oriented north--south, eastwwest, south--north and west--east on  the mechanical stage; measurements on each orientation were non-sequen-  tial. The magnification was 125 X and at least 6000 points were counted  each time. Pore space, argillans, intra-matrix illuvial clay and all other solid  material were counted. The counts were noted after every 300--400 points  to monitor the progress of each count until the whole area had been covered.    RESULTS    The results on each section (Figs. 1--6, Table II) are given in the order of  difficulty of estimation of iUuvial clay as judged by two of the operators in  McKeague et al. (1980). The calculations of standard error (Table II) assume  that the observations are randomly associated. As this is not so they are  conservative estimates; the true standard errors would in fact be less. The  thin sections were described using terminology based on Brewer (1964),  Bullock and Murphy (1976, 1979) and Murphy (1982); in the micromorpho-    TABLE I  Brief details of the sampled soils used in estimating illuvia] clay    Thin     Depth    Colour       Horizon.1   Series  section   of                                     or (site)  number  horizon  (cm)    Subgroup * 1    Province   Clay  Silt   Sand  Org.      pH in     CaCO3  (%)   (%)   (%)   carbon   water     equiv..2  (%)     ( 1: 2.5)  (%)    77151-2  38--46   (10YR512)  Bt2  7795-1   11--22   (10YR4/4)  Bt  7744-2   16--24   (10YR313)  Bn/Bnt  77170-1  40--54   (10YR312)  Bt2  7773-2  28--37  (10YR2[2)  Bnt2  7737-2  15--23  (10YR3/3)  Btl    Renffew     Orthic Gray Luvisol  Ont.        50    40    10    0.4       5.8  (Signal Mt.) Orthic Gray Luvisol  Alta.      30   34   36    0.7      7.2  Brooking    Solonetzic Dark      Sask.       35    29    36    0.9       7.4  Brown  Cashel       Orthic Gray          Ont.       54    33    13    0.3       7.6  Brown Luvisol  Camrose     Black Solodized      Alta.       33    47    20    1.2       5.8  Solonetz  Waitville     Orthic Gray Luvisol  Sask.      40    22    38    0.8       6.4    nil  2.1  nil  2.7  nil    ,1 Horizon designation and cl~fication according to the Canadian system (Canada Soil Surv. Comm., 1978).  ,2 Carbonates were absent where the thin section was taken.    Ol    136  TABLE II  Final point counts of iUuvial    clay in the six thin sections    Thin     Count  Argillans Intra-matrix  Total  section           (%),i    clay conc.    illuvial  number                      (%)* 1         clay (%),1    Standard  error (%),,,,3    77151-2  1        6.03      nil             6.03 (7.21)*2    0.30  2     4.55    nil          4.55 (5.48)     0.27  3      5.38    nil           5.38 (6.43)     0.29  4      3.56     nil           3.56 (4.33)     0.24  mean   4.88     nil            4.88 (5.86)      0.14  7795-1   1       2.71     0.97           3.68 (4.25)      0.24  2       2.20     0.72           2.92 (3.39)      0.21  3       2.37     0.88           3.25 (3.78)      0.22  4       2.82     0.51          3.33 (3.90)      0.23  mean   2.53     0.77          3.30 (3.83)      0.11  7744-2  1     1.39    nil          1.39 (1.51)     0.15  2      0.77     nil           0.77 (1.00)     0.11  3     0.97    nil          0.97 (1.24)     0.12  4      1.53     nil           1.53 (1.98)     0.16  mean   1.17     nil             1.17 (1.51)      0.07  77170-1  1       5.07     2.24           7.31 (9.15)      0.33  2     5.05    1.82        6.87 (8.68)    0.32  3     5.42    1.91        7.33 (9.25)    0.32  4       4.21     0.99          5.20 (6.51)      0.28  mean   4.94     1.74          6.68 (8.40)      0.16  7773-2   1       2.28     0.98          3.26 (3.99)      0.22  2       3.99     0.19          4.18 (5.11)      0.25  3     2.71    0.28        2.99 (3.63)    0.21  4     2.68    0.97        3.65 (4.43)    0.23  mean   2.92     0.61          3.52 (4.29)      0.11  7737-2   1       7.74     2.88         10.62 (15.13)     0.37  2       5.38     1.82          7.20 (10.18)     0.33  3       5.80     2.50          8.30 (11.65)     0.35  4       8.64     3.17          11.81 (17.12)     0.40  mean   6.89     2.59           9.48 (13.52)     0.18    i Calculated on a whole-soil basis (soil + pores). ,2 Calculated on a pore-free basis.  s Standard error =   ~/~-~/    (N - 1 )       , where N ffi total number of  points counted, C = total number of points counted as illuvial clay.    logical descriptions proportions of features present were initially estimated  by visual observation. The estimates of illuvial clay by point counting dis-  cussed below are those calculated on a total area of section basis (i.e., solid +  pores).    137    Section 77151-2    Micromorphology. Homogeneous; well expressed angular and subangular  blocky aggregation (Plate I, A); continuous planes up to 1200/~m wide with  rare to few intra-aggregate pores; no faunal activity evident; many (&gt;4%)  fine and medium plane argillans up to 800 pm wide, easily distinguished  (Plate I, B); s-matrix of laminated (some graded bedding) silty-clay; rare  prominent clear ferruginous segregations; silasepic plasmic fabric; porphy-  roskelic related distribution.  briefringence  approximately three-quarters of the counts have been completed when they  merge to around 17%.    30-    25-    A  20-    15-  0  10-  0  5-  0    8'0-    Section 77151-2    ' .....,.,..,..,.  ...................  ..,'    I          I          I          I          I          I    7"0-    6'0 i.    5"0-  ~--  4'0-  &gt;    3.0-    s J'^'.  li  .'''''.     J               '''" 3rd  ,I :: //        ~\  I  !             ~x~  ! /'\      /'~..                .-2nd  I   ";                 \~               //  I     "..//~zj.."'4th  ~  '.                                .,"  I                                 ....  ..  ............  ...,..  ..  ...........  .,.  ........     I              I  2000           3000          4000  Points counted    2oi  1'0    I       I       I  5000     6000     7000    i  i000    Fig. 1. Point counts on section 77151-2.    8    E  E    E _  ._c    PLATE I    A. Blocky aggregation in section 77151-2 (plane-polarised light). B, Discontinuous ar.  gillans (a) on planes in section 77151-2. (cross-polarised light), C and D. Micaceous  s-matrix (speckled) and pore argillans (a) in section 7795-1 (C. plane-polarised light;  D. cross-polarised light). E. Argillans (a), and stress reorganisation of clay (s) in section  77170-I (cross-polarised light), F. Stress reorganisation (s) subsequent to illuviation in  section 7737-2 (cross-polarised light).    139    In agreement with McKeague et al. (1980) this is undoubtedly the easiest  of the six sections in which to recognise illuvial clay, inasmuch as there are  very clear differences in colour, texture, orientation and birefringence  between the yellowish illuviated clay coatings and the paler s-matrix material.  The results for illuvial clay, however, (Fig. 1) show considerable discrepan-  cies among the four counts, two of which finish with larger values than the  maximum reported by McKeague et al. (1980), and the range (3.56--6.03%)  is very similar; the mean value of 4.88% for counts of 6000 is close to the  maximum of 4.5% reported by McKeague et al. (1980).    Section 7795-1    Micromorphology. Homogeneous; moderately expressed fine and medium  subangular blocky aggregation; continuous and discontinuous planes gener-  ally &lt; 300 ~m wide with many smoothed intra-aggregate channels, chambers  and vughs; much of the material appears to have been mined by fauna but  casts are now coalesced to give vughy aggregates; few partially decomposed  roots in channels; common (2--4%) fine and very fine pore argillans and  irregular intra-matrix clay concentrations, easily distinguished; some micro-  scope fields show rare argillans; much weathering mica in s-matrix of silty-  clay with few grains &gt; 30 ~m diameter; few faint diffuse and clear ferrugin-  ous segregations; argillasepic plasmic fabric; porphyroskelic related distri-  bution.    Section 7795-1    25  o~  20   lO  ~  5    4.0-    _     3.0-    2.0-    1'0      ............  .'~::,..C:~.:E:~,..=:~..=.~..~...;:.~:.~:3:.E:~  .................  __~,  ....  -    I        I    ,.'"'""""'""'"""'""'""'"'""~,  .....  ~:~  '          .~                           .~  ......  ~2nd  j,  .[ //  S/"    0             I         !         I          I          I          I          I  0              1000          2000          3000          4000           5000          6000           7000  Points counted  Fig. 2. Point counts on section 7795-1.      E    140    Point counts. There are appreciable differences between the counts of  porosity in the early stages (Fig. 2) but after 6000 points all four converge to  give similar values around 14%.  This is the second easiest of the six materials as regards the recognition  and counting of i]luvial clay, although the intra-matrix clay concentrations  (23% of total illuvial clay (Table II)) are occasionally difficult to identify  because of the presence of weathering mica in the s-matrix (Plate 1, C, D).  The range of values obtained from 6000 points (Fig. 2) is fairly small  (2.92--3.68%) although it is large at the halfway stage. The values at 6000  points are at or slightly larger (by 0.7%) than the maximum reported by  McKeague et al. (1980).    Section 7744-2    Micromorphology. Homogeneous, except for few small irregular patches  of more sepic material (turbated from below?); moderately to well expressed  medium to coarse subangular blocky aggregation; continuous and discontin-  uous planes up to 900/~m wide with intra-aggregate pores mostly smoothed  sections through channels; few to common channels contain few faecal  pellets 20--140/~m diameter; few (&lt;(2%) fine and very fine pore argillans,  generally easy to distinguish; few moderately weathered sandstone frag-  ments, some plagioclase feldspar grains virtually unweathered; few, to com-  mon in parts, small prominent ferri-manganiferous nodules; argillasepic to  weak skel-insepic plasmic fabric; porphyroskelic related distribution.    30    v 20  0    Section 7744-2    .+i.~ -.    I            I            I            l            I            ;            I    &gt;- 2.0  ~  1.0  N  0      ....   ................  ...+.    I           I           I           I           I           I           I  0     1000    2000    3000    4000    5000    6000    7000  Points counted    Fig. 3. Point counts on section 7744,2.    8   S  v   "F-    141    Point counts. The measurements of porosity (Fig. 3) show some variation  between counts in the early stages but converge to around 22% after approx-  imately three-quarters of the sections have been completed.  The illuvial clay is moderately easy to identify, the main difficulty in  counting arising from the fineness of some of the coats. Results of all four  counts are within the range obtained by McKeague et al. (1980) and the  estimates change comparatively little as progressively more points are exam-  ined. The final estimates are within 0.76% of each other.    Section 77170-1    Micromorphology. Moderately homogeneous except for few irregular  patches of more sandy material up to 6 mm across; well expressed fine and  medium subangular blocky aggregation; continuous planes up to 1 mm wide  with smoothed and rounded sections of (root?) channels within aggregates;  few earthworm casts; few undecomposed sections of roots; many (4--10%)  fine pore argillans and intra-matrix clay concentrations (due to infill and  turbation?) and few silty-argillans (infill?), moderately easy to distinguish;  few "ghosts" of argillaceous rock fragments and few moderately weathered  siltstone and quartz/feldspar fragments embedded in the s-matrix; rare  small prominent sharp ferruginous and ferri-manganiferous nodules and  segregations; skel-ma-insepic plasmic fabric; porphyroskelic related distribu-  tion.  Point counts. Identification of illuvial clay is easy in many parts but more  difficult in the areas of masepic plasmic fabric. Twenty-six per cent of the  measured clay concentrations occur within the s-matrix (Table II), caused  either by infilling of pores or by turbation, the rest occurring as pore coat-  ings (argillans). Some of the clay concentrations have evidently been reor-  ganised later by stress (Plate I, E). Identification of illuvial clay is also hin-  dered by the presence of some argillaceous lithorelicts in which much of  the clay has moderate to strong orientation.  Three of the four illuvial clay point counts (Fig. 4) attain values within  0.5% of each other but only merge towards the end of each count. They are  close to the maximum estimate reported by McKeague et al. (1980). The  fourth count gave a very significant divergent value about 2% lower.    Section 7773-2    Micromorphology. Heterogeneous with a patch of strongly oriented, more  clayey material towards one comer of the section enclosed within predom-  inantly asepic material; moderately to slightly expressed subangular blocky  aggregation; discontinuous planes with smoothed and irregular intra-aggre-  gate channels, chambers and vughs; common faunal pores (one 2.5 mm    142    25    ~ 20   15-  0  I0-    &gt;. 5~-  ~J   4'0-  3'0-    Section 77170-1  TC_-. ~23~2- - ~:,,v,~=--.~.--  ......    I       I       I       I       I       I       I    /"     ,.'            .         ~t   ~d  , II    ,i,I/                                          d  :1   /-  6'0-    ~  /  ~'"'""  .................  ,  ....................  4th    2'0-    0  I            I            I            I            I            I            I  0      1000    2000    3000    4000    5000    6000    7000  Points counted    1"0    8    E_ --    Fig. 4. Point counts on section 77170-1.    diameter) containing rounded faecal pellets 120--930 /~m diameter; few  partially decomposed roots in channels; very many (10--15%)fine pore  argillans and intra-matrix clay concentrations in the clayey patch, few (ca.  1%) fine argillans elsewhere, moderately easily distinguished; few fairly  discrete mudstone and fine siltstone lithorelicts with much weathering mica  in s-matrix; rare small irregular prominent ferri-manganiferous nodules and  segregations; argillasepic to insepic plasmic fabric (ma-insepic in clayey  patch); porphyroskelic related distribution.  Point counts. There are differences in the porosity counts in the early  stages (Fig. 5) but the estimates converge to a value of 18 per cent at the  end of the counts.  The illuvial clay has apparently been modified locally by stress, making  identification difficult, but on the whole the concentrations are moderately    143    Section 7773-2    25    -- 2O   15  o 10  2  5    701  6,0    I      I      I    // ~:.'"  .........  ...  I'     ,: \  /'    ,: \        .  !       \  i        \        "...  \        ..  I  ""%.  ,,\     "-....  ..~        .....    .    I      I      I    5.01   t,                \x.\  .:                     '\  ....  .2r~              E   4.0        :                           "..                 ;~.,v...                 ~           "                         "  ......  /"      '"'"'4th      ~  '~  3"0                                         3rd      '~  2.0                                                    ~  I           I           I          I           I           I           I  0       1000     2000     3000    4000     5000     6000     7000  Points counted    Fig. 5. Point counts on section 7773-2.    easy to identify. The presence of mudstone and siltstone lithorelicts and  much weathered mica in the s-matrix also causes difficulty. Between one-  third and one-eighth of the illuvial clay occurs as irregular intra-matrix con-  centrations (Table II) which result largely from faunal turbation.  The very marked initial differences in the illuvial clay counts (Fig. 5) are  attributed to the presence of the irregular clayey patch at one comer of the  analysed square. After 6000 points the estimates range from 2.99 to 4.18%,  at or around the maximum count (3.8%) reported by McKeague et al.  (1980).    Section 7737-2    Micromorphology. Homogeneous; well expressed fine and medium sub-  angular blocky aggregation; continuous planes up to 800 pm wide with  intra-aggregate pores generally smoothed channels, chambers and vughs; few    x_~  3--    ~t    "g-LgL,/, uoDaes uo slunoa ~u!od "9 "$!~    Pm, unoo stu!pd  O00L   0009   000~   O00t7   000~   000~   000 t  L           1           I           1           l           I           I    /"  /I  I  I  /  I  /  /  /  /  /                        /  iI              /  i  /          //  i  i  i'  ,/  ,/  /  pjE;..~'~"   ~'" ~         ~'--'- -   ~,~/    lSL                                        ""'" " ' """"I  f      1      I      i      J      i      I    /  _/    ~'LL uo!~oS    O'L    0"~    0,   0"~'    0.~  E  0.9  &lt;  f~  O"L  "&lt;    0'8    0-6    O, Ol    O.LL  -O.~t    O.~t    Ol  8  =0    OP    145    pores contain faecal pellets mostly 40--200 pm diameter; few undecom-  posed and partially decomposed roots in channels; very many (&gt;10%) pore  argillans and intra-matrix clay concentrations, locally stress modified, partly  easy and partly difficult to distinguish; material appears to consist of pedo-  relicts enveloped by strongly oriented clayey material; few unweathered  and moderately weathered feldspar grains; few to rare small irregular prom-  inent ferri-manganiferous nodules; insepic plasmic fabric (pedorelicts),  masepic (clayey material); porphyroskelic related distribution.  Point counts. The estimates of porosity (Fig. 6) differ significantly until  more than half the points have been counted and then converge to around  30%.  Identification of illuvial clay, and thus also point counting, is difficult in  this section; clear identification was only possible in 50--60% of the in-  stances. Much, if not all, of the very clayey material enveloping the pedo-  relicts is probably of illuvial origin but boundaries of many of the plasma  concentrations are indistinct, presumably as a result of stress reorganisation,  and are hence difficult to identify and count (Plate I, F). Twenty seven  per cent of the illuvial clay counted occurs as intra-matrix concentrations  (Table II), attributable to pore infill and/or pedoturbation.  The range of estimates of illuvial clay after 6000 counts (7.20--11.81%)  is large and all four are well below the maximum count of 17.8% reported  by McKeague et al. (1980).    DISCUSSION    The relationship between pore space and illuvial clay    Pore space in a thin section of size 25 X 25 mm can be satisfactorily  quantified by counting 6000 points over the section area. Any uneven  distribution of pores is corrected for by the end of the count. In five of the  six sections there is an uneven distribution of pores, shown by the variable  values in the early stages of the point counts, the sixth (section 77170-1,  Fig. 4) showing even, random distribution of pores throughout the section.  Such small sections (25 X 25 mm) may, however, be unrepresentative of  the horizon sampled. The considerable heterogeneity of pore space was shown  by Murphy and Banfield (1978). Macroporosity (pores greater than 120 um  diameter) ranged from 1 to 33% in 18 X 14 mm areas of thin sections of a  clay loam, indicating the need for many replicated thin sections to obtain  estimates of sample means with acceptable accuracy using image analysis.  They concluded that, as a compromise, six Kubiena tin samples should be  taken from each studied horizon, with one thin section (75 X 60 mm) made  from each tin. As clay concentrations are generally on pore walls and are  usually finer and of much smaller percentage area than the pores, propor-  tionally more sections are needed for the quantification of illuvial clay  within the same limits of accuracy. The relationship between proportions    146    of mineral grains in thin section, number of points counted, percentage error  and confidence intervals was shown by Brewer (1964, p. 48). The need for  many replicates of thin sections when point counting a number of features  in soil thin sections was also shown by Milfred et al. (1967) and Perecin  and Campos (1977); the former demonstrated that more sections are needed  for the estimation of the proportion of illuvial clay than of pore space.  Further statistical analyses of point counts of illuvial clay have been made  by Perecin (1979) who related the counts to a negative binomial distribution.  Although this study, on single thin sections, is not able to establish a  link between pore space variability and variation in amounts of illuvial clay,  it is evident that in many instances such a link exists. It is probably better,  therefore, and more meaningful, to calculate percentage illuvial clay in thin  section on a pore-free basis, this value being better related to particle size  analysis (which takes no account of pore space). Further discussion, how-  ever, concerns the results calculated on a "total area of thin section" basis  (i.e., solid + pores) as this has been the most widely accepted method to  date; estimates on a pore-free basis can be considerably larger (Table II).    Distribution of illuvial clay in thin section    Replicate point counting of illuvial clay on the same section can give very  different results. Even though the illuvial clay in section 77151-2 (Fig. 1)  was the easiest to identify and therefore to count, the final results for suc-  cessive replicates proved to be the second most variable. These discrepancies  are apparently related to the orientation and alignment of the pores and  the clay coats; continuous planes are mostly aligned orthogonal to each  other in the plane of the section and parallel to its edges and hence also to  the count scan lines (Plate I, A, B). As the a gillans are usually considerably  finer than the distances between the scan lines, these scans may coincide  with linear argillans giving a large estimate of illuvial clay, or, more often,  may "miss" most argillans and run along the planes or through the matrix  giving a small estimate. Therefore, whereas a count of 6000 points over the  area sufficed to estimate the pore space in this section, it was insufficient  to estimate the flluvial clay consistently. A grid of much closer point spacing  (of 12,000 points or more?) over the same area might have enabled better,  more consistent, quantification of the illuvial clay.  Identification of illuvial clay in thin section can be easy, but uneven dis-  tribution of this clay within the section can cause different results. With the  sampling scheme used (6000 points counted over a relatively small area) the  final counts could be expected to be the same. In section 7773-2 (Fig. 5)  a patch of strongly argillic (10--15% illuvial clay) material towards one  corner is enclosed by weakly argillic (ca. 1%) material. The counts shown in  Fig. 5 reflect this situation; the clay-enriched patch was counted early during  the third and fourth counts but was not counted until towards the end of  the first and second counts. (If this patch had been at the centre of the    147    square, all four counts would have peaked at around 3000 points.) The  final counts show that overall there is about 3.0--4.2% illuvial clay present  in this section. Two points are worth noting here: firstly, if the clayey patch  is of material brought up from below the sampling depth by fauna, agricul-  tural machinery, etc., then the overall estimate of illuvial clay is unrep-  resentative of the sampled horizon. Secondly, if this clayey patch had been  just outside the measuring area a value of around 1% would have resulted  and the area as a whole would have appeared homogeneous. Such a problem  would probably be overcome by larger and/or replicated samples.  The difference among the four counts of illuvial clay in section 7795-1  (Fig. 2) is relatively small after 6000 points (2.92--3.68%) but is large at the  halfway stage, showing that the illuvial clay is irregularly distributed through-  out the section. This difference was surprising because, overall, the material  in this section appeared more homogeneous than any of the others. The ex-  tent of illuvial clay probably differs with that of the associated irregularly  distributed pore space.  With section 7744-2 (Fig. 3), on the other hand, the range of estimates  is attributed to the fineness of some of the argillans, which makes it diffi-  cult to decide whether or not the eyepiece cross-hair is actually on the fine  argillan. The intensity of illumination may also affect the recognition of  such fine coats. The 0.76% range achieved on this section comes from only  46 of 6000 counts.    Stress reorganisation and operator bias    It is probable that five of the six ranges of estimates of illuvial clay reflect,  in part, an operator bias due to uncertainty when the illuvial clay is diffi-  cult to identify and/or count. In the estimation of illuvial clay in section  77151-2 (Fig. 1), the difference between the four replicate counts by one  operator is similar to that between ten operators; this range has been shown  to be due to the alignment of pores and argillans and not to difficulty of  recognition of illuvial clay. The range of estimates on the other five sections  are distinctly narrower than those reported by McKeague et al. {1980).  Stress reorganisation through shrinking and swelling following illuviation  can cause difficulties in recognition of illuvial clay (as in sections 77170-1,  7773-2, 7737-2) because the clay concentrations so affected lose their dis-  tinct boundaries and merge gradually into the s-matrix (Plate I, E, F). This  problem is usually most evident in material which contains more than 30%  clay when the plasma can be strongly reorganised (in-masepic plasmic fabric  or stronger).  Some of the results reported here indicate another aspect of operator  bias, an "uncertainty" linked to the degree of difficulty, and subjectivity,  during identification of illuvial clay. The operator may, unconsciously,  identify illuvial clay on one occasion but not another. The counts on sec-  tions 77170-1 (Fig. 4) and 7737-2 (Fig. 6) probably reflect this. In the first    148    instance the fourth count gave a significantly lower value than the other  three, indicating underestimation. Secondly, with section 7737-2, the most  difficult of the six for the recognition of illuvial clay, the increasing values  with time during the second and third counts indicate a greater "awareness"  as more of the section was counted. Both of these counts finish with signif-  icantly smaller estimates that the other two on this section and are hence  likely to be under-estimates.  There is, therefore, a need for, at least, duplicating the point count when  identification of illuvial clay is difficult; two otherwise unexplainable differ-  ing results indicating the need for a third.    Other comments    The presence of weathered fragments of argillaceous rock (lithoreticts)  (as in sections 77170-1 and 7773-2) or much weathered mica (section  7795-1; Plate I, C, D) (or glauconite) in the s-matrix can confuse identifica-  tion of illuvial clay in thin section. Although not noted in this study, diffi-  culties of recognition can also arise in soil with strong ferruginous or ferri-  manganiferous segregation (mottling) or high iron content (e.g. from iron-  stone), the staining tending to mask other features, and in soil with inherited  strongly oriented clay, e.g. in layered clayey sediments.  Estimating iltuvial clay by point counting in thin section may also be  unreliable in horizons in which there are differing proportions (heteroge-  neous distribution} of features such as coarse stones or rock fragments  (lithorelicts), for example. The proportionate areas of these in a thin sec-  tion, whether large or small, will differ greatly depending on random sec-  tioning and will probably not represent their "true" proportions in the  horizon, yet their presence is used in the calculation of percentage illuvial  clay, as is pore space. Presuming that the flluvial clay is evenly distributed,  a section containing a large proportion of stone or rock fragment will give a  smaller percentage of illuvial clay than one containing a much smaller areal  proportion. In this case it is probably more meaningful to calculate percen-  tage illuvial clay on a less than 2 mm basis, if possible.  A final consideration regards classification. In 5 of the 6 sections studied  here the materials are clearly identifiable as argillic and provide little diffi-  culty in their identification. In one of the sections analysed, however,  7744-2 (Fig. 3), the estimates range from 0.77 to 1.53% and can be taken to  indicate that the horizon sampled is marginally argfllic according to the  U.S. Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975) inasmuch as the required limiting  value is 1%, or non-argillic according to the system of England and Wales  (Avery, 1980) where the cut-off at 2~o illuvial clay in a representative thin  section is employed partly because it was considered easier to estimate  visually the presence or absence of this amount.    149    CONCLUSIONS    Pore space in a 25 X 25 mm thin section of soil can be reproducibly  estimated by counting 6000 points over the section, but the result is likely  to be unrepresentative of the sampled horizon unless replicate and/or very  much larger sections are analysed.  The variation of estimates of illuvial clay in thin section by ten operators  using similar techniques has been established by McKeague et al. (1980). The  present work shows that less, but nonetheless marked, variation is obtained  on replication by a single operator. In either case the variations are due both  to difficulties in identifying illuvial clay consistently and to the orientation  and variability of the soil material. More reliable results may often be achieved  by suitable replication and/or by using larger sections.  Identification and point counting of illuvial clay in thin section can be  difficult in soils with one or more of the following characteristics or fea-  tures:  -- generally more than 30% clay;  -- very fine argillans;  -- moderately to strongly oriented plasmic fabric (in-masepic or stronger);  -- moderate to strong turbation (e.g. by fauna, ice);  -- weathered mica or glauconite in the s-matrix;  -- weathered argillaceous lithorelicts in the s-matrix;  -- irregularly distributed coarse (&gt; 2mm) fragments;  -- s-matrix stained by strong ferruginous or ferri-manganiferous segregation  or with high iron content (e.g. from ironstone);  --s-matrix which is heterogeneous with respect to pores or particle-size  distribution;  -- s-matrix which is strongly oriented by inheritance (sedimentary?).  It is therefore evident that in many cases illuvial clay in all its forms can-  not be identified precisely in thin sections; single point counts may be un-  reliable and visual estimates by experienced operators may be as reliable  (McKeague et al., 1981). It is recommended that, in research studies, at  least duplication of point counting of illuvial clay in thin section should be  carried out, with the sections re-oriented at right angles and that some  estimation of the degree of difficulty of recognition of the illuvial clay be  given, linked probably to the degree of plasma separation (plasmic fabric).  At least 6000 points per section need be counted and the estimates cal-  culated on a pore-free and, if necessary, on a less than 2 mm basis.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    I thank Dr J.A. McKeague for the loan of the six thin sections studied  here, his permission to use the data and for additional data on the sampled  soils.    150    REFERENCES    Avery, B.W., 1980. Soil Classification for England and Wales (Higher Categories). Soil  Surv., Harpenden, Tech. Monogr., 14.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 470 pp.  Bullock, P. and Murphy, C.P., 1976. The microscopic examination of the structure of  sub-surface horizons of soils. Outlook Agric., 8 : 348--354.  Bullock, P. and Murphy, C.P., 1979. Evolution of a paleo-argillic brown earth (Paleudalf)  from Oxfordshire, England. Geoderma, 22: 225--252.  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian system of soil classification. Agric.  Can., (Ottawa) Publ., 1646.  FAO, 1974. Unesco Soil Map of the World, 1. UNESCO, Paris.  Fedoroff, N., 1974. Classification of accumulations of translocated particles. In: G.K.  Rutherford (Editor) Soil Microscopy. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp.  695--713.  Hill, I.D., 1970. Quantitative micromorphological evidence of clay movement. In: D.A,  Osmond and P. Bullock, (Eds.), Micromorphological Techniques and Applications.  Soil Surv., Harpenden, Tech. Monogr., 5.  Kwaad, F.J.P.M. and Miicher, H.J., 1979. The formation and evolution of colluvium on  arable land in northern Luxembourg. Geoderma, 22: 173--192.  McKeague, J.A., Guertin, R.K., Page, F. and Valentine, K.W.G., 1978. Micromorpholog-  ical evidence of illuvial clay in horizons designated Bt in the field. Can. J. Soil Sci.,  58: 179--186.  McKeague, J.A., Guertin, R.K., Valentine, K.W.G., Belisle, J., Bourbeau, G.A., Howell,  A., Michalyna, W., Hopkins, L., Page, F. and Bresson, L.M., 1980, Estimating illuvial  clay in soils by micromorphology. Soil Sci., 129(6): 386--388.  McKeague, J.A., Wang, C., Ross, G.J., Acton, C.J., Smith, R.E., Anderson, D.W., Petta-  piece, W.W. and Lord, T.M., 1981. Evaluation of criteria for argillic horizons (Bt)  of softs in Canada. Geoderma, 25: 63--74.  Milfred, C.J., Hole, F,D., and Torrie, J.H., 1967. Sampling for pedographic modal analysis  of an argillic horizon. Proc. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 31: 244--247.  Murphy, C.P. and Banfield, C.F., 1978. Pore space variability in a sub-surface horizon of  two soils. J. Soil Sci., 29: 156--166.  Murphy, C.P., 1982. A comparative study of three methods of water removal prior to  resin impregnation of two soils. J. Soft Sci., 33: 719--735.  Osman, A. and Eswaran, H., 1974. Clay tramdocation and vertic properties of some red  Mediterranean soils. In: G.K. Rutherford (Editor) Soil Microscopy. The Limestone  Press, Kingston, Ont., pp. 846--857.  Perecin, D., 1979. Anltlise estat~tica de azgila iluviada em solos, baseada na distribuio  binomial negativa. Cient~fica, 7(3): 371--376.  Perecin, D. and Campos, D.A.F., 1977. Amostragem mais econSmica para determinao  microestereom~ica de argila illuviada. Cient~flca, 4(5): 113--121,  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy. Agricultural Handbook, 436. Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, D.C.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractSix soil thin sections containing various amounts of illuvial clay, previously estimated by ten operators, were point-counted four times by an additional experienced operator. The results indicate that a count of 6000 points over a section area of 25 × 25 mm is sufficient to quantify satisfactorily the pore space of the section. Replicated results for illuvial clay, however, differed widely for some sections. These differences are attributed both to difficulties in recognising illuvial clay and to orientation and variability of soil components. Variability of results for illuvial clay in this study was less than that reported for ten operators but, nonetheless, it is evident that for most sections the amount of illuvial clay cannot be estimated precisely by a single count of 6000 points. Suggestions are made for improving the reliability of estimates of illuvial clay in soil thin sections and an improved basis for reporting results is proposed. 