 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 77--92                                                         77  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V , Amsterdam -- Printed m The Netherlands    STEM-EDXRA AND SEM-EDXRA INVESTIGATION OF IRON-COATED  ORGANIC MATTER IN THIN SECTIONS WITH TRANSMITTED,  SECONDARY AND BACKSCATTERED ELECTRONS    E.B A BISDOM', R. NAUTA2 and B VOLBERT2     Netherlands So~l Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wagemngen (The Netherlands)  2 N V Philips, Application Laboratory--Electron Optics, TQ-III-p, 5600 MD Eindhoven  (The Netherlands)    (Accepted for pubhcation February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bisdom, E.B.A., Nauta, R. and Volbert, B., 1983. STEM-EDXRA and SEM-EDXRA  investigation  of  iron-coated  organic  matter in thin sections with transmitted,  secondary and backscattered electrons. Geoderma, 30  77--92.    Experiments have been carried out wlth STEM-EDXRA (scanning transmission  electron microscope--energy dispersive X-ray analyzer) and SEM- EDXRA (scanning  electron microscope--energy dispersive X-ray analyzer) on thin sections with thicknesses  of about 5 #m and 20 ~m, respectlvely.  Common thin sections with a thickness of about 20 urn, were analysed with the Philips  SEM 505 and the JeoI-JSM-35C. Such thick preparations only allow near-surface imaging  with secondary and backscattered electrons plus microchemical analysis up to 10 000.  The beam spot of the Phdips EM 400T/ST, which can operate as a STEM-SEM-TEM with  EDXRA, can be made smaller than is possible with the other two machines whlch were  spemfically built as SEM-instruments. Consequently, microchemical analysis could be  performed at magnifications of more than 10 000. Indications are that analysis at  50 000 with EDXRA gave additional elements to those measured with SEM-EDXRA at  10 000 In this manner near-trace-element quantities become measurable.  Inveshgation of 5 #m thick thin sections was mainly done with the Philips EM  400T/ST in the SEM-EDXRA and STEM--EDXRA mode In this experiment the thin  section was throned maximally by normal grinding processes and subsequently removed  in small pieces from the object glass together with the plastic used for mounting These  pieces were then placed in a copper grid and studied close to their surfaces with SEM-  EDXRA and m the transmission mode with STEM-EDXRA. The use of TEM-EDXRA  was not possible because this requires ultrathm sections of about 1 #m thickness. Even  when the plastic, used for mounting the soil material on the object glass, is replaced by  dissolvable material, the 5 #m thick thin section would still be a few microns thick. No  diamond knife or ion thinning technique, used for the preparation of ultrathin sections of  soft sod materials such as organic matter and clay, was applied in this study_    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V    7~    INTRODUCTION    Modem soil microanalysis of thin sections is often performed with  SEM-EDXRA  (scanning  electron  microscope--energy  dispersive  X-ray  analysis) and EMA (electron microprobe analysis) (Blsdom et al., 1975,  1976; Blsdom, 1981a, b; Boekestein et al., 1981). Such microchemical  analysis of soil material, however, frequently stops at magnifications which  are insufficient for the study of very small soil particles, viz. at about  X 10 000 for the microanalysis of chemical elements. Secondary electron  images (SEI) and backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) can be  obtained   dependent on the soil material being studied -- at higher magnifi-  cations but such micrographs are no longer supported by mlcrochemmal  in situ information.  There are instruments, such as the Phllips EM 400T/ST, which are able to  perform mlcrochemical analysis in thin sections at magnifications of more  than X 10 000. This is due to smaller beam spot diameters than are present in  normal SEM instruments which were also used in the present study. Ideally,  thin sections should always be ultrathin or about 1 pm thick. This would  allow the microchemical investigations of individual small soil components  and give some idea of the composition of small masses of the smallest soil  particles. In practme, however, the preparation of ultrathm sectmns IS still  diffmult except of relatively soft soil materials such as orgamc matter and  rather pure clays. Such ultrathln sections were made and studied with TEM  by Bresson (1981) and Foster (1981).  The pieces of thin section in the copper grid were also studmd m the SEM-  EDXRA mode of the scanning transmissmn electron microscope (EM  400T/ST). Similar materials were investigated m thin sections mounted on  the object glasses by SEM-EDXRA (Jeol-JSM-35C). In this manner, some  control of the mmrochemmal measurements of the EM 400T/ST was  obtained. Both backscattered and secondary electron images were made  close to the surface of the thin section using the Phlhps SEM 505 and EM  400T/ST. Such pictures could be compared with STEM-EDXRA micro-  graphs made with transmitted electrons which passed a pmce of thin section  that was about 5 ~m thick. This thickness was obtained by maximal grinding  of the soil material until it was virtually gone, and keeping the plastm layer,  used for mounting on the object glass, intact. The technique is rapid and  could be used to find out whether ion thinning, a process which takes much  longer, is necessary for a certain research problem or not.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The soil material used in these experiments is iron-coated organic matenal  from peat of a sandy Typic Humaquept with bog iron ore. Processing of the  peaty material to a thin section was done according to methods described by  Jongerius and Heintzberger (1975). Usually, these are mammoth-sized thin    79    sections of 15 8 cm whmh are 15 pm to 25 ~m thick. For the present  analyses, much smaller thin sections are used, viz. of about 3.5 2.5 cm and  the same thickness as the mammoth one. The surface of these thin sections  was studied using specific SEM instruments, viz. the Jeol-JSM-35C and the  Philips SEM 505. Pieces of the small thin sections were also maximally  ground and taken from the object glass at about 5 ~m thick. They were  subsequently inserted in a copper grid for inspection with the Philips EM  400 T/ST scanning transmission electron microscope in both the SEM and  STEM mode.  To obtain some insight into the mmrochemistry and morphology of Iron-  coated organic material, SEM-EDXRA was done with a Jeol-JSM-35C using  an ECON windowless detector for the detection of chemical elements down  to carbon at a mgnification of about 10 000 (Bisdom et al., 1975}. The  morphology of the material in the thin section was also studied in the back-  scattered electron mode. This is possible with a backscattered electron  detector of the semi-conductor type which comprised two solid-state  detectors (Bisdom and Thiel, 1981}. No satisfactory backscattered electron  scannmg images (BESI) could be obtained from the iron-coated organic  material and it was decided to do tests with other detector systems as well.  The Multi-Function-Detector (MFD) system of the Philips SEM 505,  which was described by Volbert (1981) and m short in Bisdom et al. (1983,  this issue), uses four detectors for the registration of backscattered electrons.  This results in a good detector efficiency. Imaging can start at 10 and  frequently stops at 10 000 or more depending on the type of soil material.  The four detectors allow the production of high-quality micrographs, even of  difficult soft materials such as the present ones. So far, experiments with soft  materials indicate that BESI are obtainable with a SEM (SEM 505) and are  frequently comparable to those of a Scanning Transmission Electron  Microscope (EM 400T/ST) in the BSE (backscattered electron)-mode, an  instrument whmh has a smaller beam spot diameter and a different back-  scattered electron detector system. Consequently, the step from the con-  ventional SEM (SEM 505) to the STEM (EM 400T/ST)in the BSE-mode,  was rather simple although the SEM worked with about 20 um thick thin  sections and the STEM with about 5 pm thick ones.  The Philips EM 400T/ST (T stands for twin lens and ST for scanning  transmission) has been used for investigating iron-coated organic material  at low and very high magnifications. The instrument can be used as a SEM-  EDXRA, STEM-EDXRA and TEM-EDXRA as discussed m the introduction.  Only  SEM-EDXRA  and  STEM-EDXRA  modes  were  used  on  the  approximately 5 pm thick thin sections made by maxlmai grinding of the  thin sectmn at one side. This gives a type of wedge shape going from the  common thickness of about 20 ~m for light microscopy to 5 pm for trans-  mitted electron microscopy. All thicknesses can be studied with SEM-  EDXKA of the EM 400 T/ST but only the thinnest parts of the wedge with  STEM-EDXRA. If the thin sections could be made about 1 pm thick, the  work could also be done with the TEM-EDXRA mode of the STEM.    80    RESULTS    BSE and SE tmaging by SEM 505    BESI of iron-coated orgamc material in peat are shown m Fig. 1. As is the  case with light mmroscopy, the morphology and details on structure and  fabric of the soil materials may change considerably with the magnification  m submicroscopy. Shortly, what is not visible at low magnifications may  become recognizable at higher ones. This is illustrated in backscattered  electron scanning images of Figs. 1 and 2, vlz. in the BSE (A+B) mode. These  micrographs were made with the four detectors of the MFD (multi-function-  detector) system (Volbert, 1981; Bisdom et al., 1983} and just underneath  the surface of a 20 pm think thin section.  No orientations are visible at a low magnification in Fig. 1, 1.e., m the  central part of the micrograph with a bar scale of 200 ~m (50 on the  original micrograph). The next figure at 200 shows a weak lamellar orienta-  tion which becomes evident at 500 (micrograph with bar scale of 20 #m).  This ormntatlon occurs m orgamc material which is covered and impregnated  with iron hydroxide. The iron hydroxide is usually poorly crystallized or  amorphous but goethlte ~s locally present. The poorly crystalhzed nature of  the Iron hydroxide Is demonstrated best in the BSE (A+B) image of Fig. 2 at  2000. Such poorly crystalhzed and amorphous matemals do not usually  allow backscattered electron imaging at much higher magnifications.  A secondary electron (SE) image is also given m Fig. 2 to allow a  comparison of the results of SE and BSE techmques when applied to iron-  coated orgamc material. Lmeatlon is visible in the SE image but much  better and more "~naturally" developed orientation is present m the BSE  (A+B) image of Fig. 2. This example also demonstrates that backscattered  electrons give images which come from a shallow depth, estimated to be  from 1 pm to 5/~m beneath the surface of the thin section. The SE-lmage, at  30 keV primary electron energy, comes from a shallower depth near to the  surface of the thin section. This secondary electron linage gives the  impressmn that smearing of the soft material occurred during polishing of the  soft constituents. Such polishing effects are no longer visible in the BSE-  mode.    STEM zmaging and STEM-EDXRA analysis by EM 400T/ST    When iron-coated organic material was studmd with the Philips EM 400  T/ST (Figs. 3 to 6), maximally thinned and hand-polished specimens of    Fig  1. BESI (backscattered electron scanning image) of iron-coated organic material in  peat from a sandy Typic Humaquept (50 to 500) Structure in the peat fragment  becomes clearly visible at 500 magmfication. Enlargements with the SEM 505 axe made  from central parts of preceding micrographs BSE means backscattered electrons The  highest BSE (A + B) magnification of the studmd soil material is shown m Fig 2.    81    BSE[A1    82    SE    BSE (A + B)    83    about 5 #m thickness were placed in a copper grid after removal from the  object glass. Subsequently, the copper grid was placed in a sample holder  which in turn was inserted into the STEM. A series of submicroscopic  techniques thus become possible, of which only a few have been used in this  study, vlz. the SEM-EDXRA mode at 20 keV to study close-to-surface  material in the thin section (Figs. 3 and 4), and the STEM--EDXRA mode  at 120 keV to investigate the total thmkness of 5 pm in the transmission  mode (Figs. 5 and 6).  The LM (low-magnification) scanning mode at 20 keV was used to obtain  micrographs at 100 to 800 magnifications (Fig. 3). The LM SEM mode  uses the condenser lens as the probe-forming lens and images were made  from backscattered electrons. The ring in the right hand corner of the micro-  graph with a bar scale of 1, O0 t~m was caused by the sample holder. The  white of the four photos ~v l, ig. 3 indicates the presence of i~on-containing  compounds m the peaty materials.  The images of Fig. 4 were made in a SEM mode whereby the standard  objective lens was used as the probe-forming lens. This operational mode  allows imaging with backscattered electrons at higher magnifications than  the LM SEM mode of Fig. 3. To allow a comparison with the LM SEM  mode, magnifications were started at 800. The maximum magnification  was reached at 6400 using backscattered electrons.  To allow a comparison of SEM and STEM modes of operation, STEM  was started at 3200 and followed by an image of X 6400. The latter two  mlcrographs can be compared with the last two in Fig. 4 and are the  begmning of a series of STEM images in Figs. 5 and 6. It is clear that there is  a great deal of difference between the SEM (close-to-surface) and STEM  (transmission) mode of operation of the EM 400T/ST and in the results  obtained. STEM gives the best imaging near the edges of a thin section or  where the soil material borders on a pore or artificial crack caused by  charging and heating of the soil sample. This is understandable because the  thin sections are thinnest at such places.  Bright-field imaging was done with the STEM mode of operation in Figs. 5  and 6. Imaging was started at 3200 and finished at 50 000 in Fig. 6. Due  to the number of micrographs made, the results of one example are spread  over two figures. The channel which runs more or less horizontally, in the  mlcrographs with magnifications 3200, 6400 and 12 500 in Fig. 5, has  been enlarged artificially after charging and heating. All micrographs in Figs.  5 and 6 show that some details can be discerned but that these studies need  EDXRA for chemical identification purposes.    Fig 2. The difference between secondary electron (SE) and BSE images made with the  SEM 505 (x 2000). The structure in the BSE (A + B) image, obtained from I to 5 #m  depth in the thin section, is clearly discernable. The SE image comes from a shallower  depth in the thin section and gives only little information on structure in the iron-coated  organic material    84    1    85    Point-analyses with STEM-EDXRA were made at 50 000 in black and  grey coloured microareas of the soil matrix in Fig. 6. Even at this scale some  variety in chemical elements could be discerned, especially in the peaks of  A1 and $1. Another important result was the possibility of measuring P, Ca  and Cu in the four analyses. Such elements were not detected with a con-  ventmnal SEM-EDXRA such as the JSM-35C and the SEM 505. This is due  to the higher primary electron energy of STEM-EDXRA which allows micro-  chemical analyses at larger depths than in the SEM apparatus used for  scanning electron microscopy of surfaces only. The detection of minute  quantities of P, Ca and Cu in the thin section is important because this could  indicate that STEM-EDXRA work can be done in situ on near-trace-element  quantities at large magnifications. The reliability of such measurements  becomes even better, however, if ultrathin samples can be measured because  less soil material is then available below the surface of the specimen. The  added possibility, using a Scanning Transmission Electron Microscope to in-  vestigate chemical elements at magnifications larger than 0 000, is im-  portant for the study of thin sections and ultrathin sections because such  microvariety is frequently present in many soils.    CONCLUSIONS    SEM-EDXRA analysis with a conventional SEM (JSM-35C or SEM 505)  allows a quick inventarisation of predominantly the heavmr chemical  elements in a thin section up to magnifications of 10 000. Experiments  with iron-coated organic material from peat have shown that this can be  done at much higher magnifications with an instrument such as the EM  400T/ST which can operate as a SEM, STEM and TEM combined with  EDXRA equipment.  For this particular material a maximal magnification for EDXRA analysis  was reached on a 5 ~m thick thin section using the STEM-EDXRA mode of  the EM 400T/ST. Indications are that elements hke P, Ca and Cu, which  were not measured with conventional SEM-EDXRA point-analyses at  0 000, represent near-to-trace-element quantities analysed by STEM-  EDXttA at 50 000. As a consequence, STEM-EDXRA investigation can be  used in cases where insufficient microchemical detail is obtained during  SEM-EDXRA, SEM-WDXRA (scanning electron microscopy--wavelength  dispersive X-ray analysis) or EMA (electron microprobe analysis).  Other elements measured were A1, Si, Fe and C1. Chlorine was indicated  only once with STEM-EDXRA. The quantity of A1 and Si could vary signi-  ficantly in the four point-analyses. Considerable iron was present. The    Fig 3  Low-magnifmatlon scanning mode at 20 keV with the EM 400T/ST (100 to  00)  Operation as a SEM (scanning electron microscope) on Iron-coated organic  material from peat without orientation. White areas contain larger quantities of iron  compounds than grey ones. This figure is continued in Fig. 4 with another mode of opera-  tion using the same instrument    86    87    elements A1, Si and Fe were also found with a conventional SEM and  represent major elements in the iron-coated peaty material. Even at larger  magnifications, also reached by conventional SEM-EDXRA in machines  specifically built for scanning electron microscopy (JSM-35C and SEM 505),  STEM-EDXRA analysis may be of Lmportance because of the higher  accuracy which can be obtained.  The quality of the mmrochemical analysis would be even better if the 5  ~m thick thin section could become ultrathin. For this, ion thinning or  cutting with a diamond cutter are necessary. In practice, however, such  methods are only applied to relatively pure and soft soil materials such as  clays and orgamc matter. The more common soil materials are, however,  mixtures of harder and softer substances from which it is difficult to obtain  ultrathin sections. Ion thmnlng can be a good method, but preparation, in  order to guarantee the necessary very small thickness of about 1 ~m, is often  difficult. As a consequence, TEM-EDXRA work on such ultrathm sections  could possibly be started with the examination of thicker samples with  STEM-EDXRA.  The present experiments indicate that STEM-EDXRA work can only be  done on or near the boundary of soil material and voids where the sample  is thinnest. It therefore becomes necessary to make future samples thinner  than 5 ~m to obtain results in the middle of the soil matrix as well as in cases  where no voids are present. The simplest way seems to be to replace the  plastic used for mounting on the object glass by dissolvable material. In this  way, the 5 pm thick thin section would become about 3 ~m thick. Polishing  of both sides of the thin section should be done to guarantee minimal  thickness differences. In practice, however, such parallelism will be difficult  to obtain between the surfaces of the thin section due to hardness  differences of the soil constituents. Microthickness differences will therefore  remain.  Backscattered electron imaging was done with three instruments, viz. the  Jeol-JSM-35C, the Philips SEM 505 and the Philips EM 400T/ST. The first  two instruments were built for SEM work, whereas the latter machine can  operate in SEM, STEM and TEM modes. All these instruments offer  possibilities of obtaining backscattered electron scanning images (BESI). In  the present case the SEM stopped at 2000 magnification and the Scanning  Transmission Electron Microscope In the BSE-mode at 400. A lot of  detail on the structure and fabric of soil materials can be obtained in this  way, especially because BESI contain information from a somewhat greater    Fig. 4 SEM mode of the EM 400T/ST at 20 keV (800 to 6400)_ The smallest magnifi-  catmn used in this mode has a somewhat better resolution than the last micrograph in  Fig  3 which was also taken at 800 Ormntations remain absent Very fine threads are  barely visible in the central pore These indicate breakage of the thin section material at  such sites followed by dislocation. Such movements were caused by charging and heating  of the soil material at 120 keV in the STEM mode, of micrographs which are given in  Figs 5 and 6    88    depth m the thin section than the secondary electron images, a depth whmh  is not affected by pohshlng. Another advantage of BESI is the portrayal of  iron accumulations In white without needing to make X-ray images of the  element to find its distribution over the thin section. The positionmg of hne  scans and point analyses for mmrochemlcal mformatlon therefore becomes  easier with BESI.  Due to the very high accelerating voltage of 120 keV in STEM, instead of  the 20 keV in LM SEM and other SEM modes, pieces of thin section in the  copper grid may break. At such surfaces the thin section may be thinner  than normal and therefore Interesting for transmitted electron study by  STEM. The best way to study small soil particles will be by TEM-EDXRA  using ultrathln sections As long as these are still difficult to make, it seems  reasonable to use thicker thin sections and to study them by STEM-EDXRA.  In this manner the edges of 5 pm thick maximally ground thin sections and  3 pm think thin sections of which the layer used for mounting has been  removed could play a role in transmitted electron microscopy. The Ideal  remains, however, a techmque which allows the easy preparation of ultrathin  sections of all kinds of soil materials. This is not only because of EDXRA  measurements but also to allow in situ electron diffraction of individual soil  minerals. The possibihty to study ultrafabnc and ultrastructure in ultrathin  sections also indicates the necessity of their regular manufacturing to obtain  a basic Insight into soil environments. The machines are ready to help us but  better preparation techniques for ultrathin sections must be found.    Fig. 5. STEM (scanning transmmmon electron microscopy) bmght-field imaging at 120  keV with the EM 400T/ST (3200 to 25 000) Transmltted electron micrographs were  made of the same iron-coated organic material as was present in the last two images of  Fig 4 The very fine threads in the pore of Fig. 4, caused by chaxgmg and heating, have  now become easy to observe and exhibit a certain topography. Small soil fragments are  distinguishable in the soil matrix  Fig 6 STEM bright-field imaging with the EM 400T/ST (Figs 6a and 6b) and EDXRA  (energy disperslve X-ray analysis) of the same material as m Fig. 5 at x 50 000 and under  similar conditions (Figs. 6c to 6f). Overlap m present in Figs. 6a and 6b, with Fig. 6b  starting about halfway across Fig. 6a, i.e., point-analysis e (Fig. 6e) therefore also lies in  Fig 6a, while number 4 is situated at the lower boundary of Fig. 6a. Point analyses c--f  of Fig  6b axe given in the same order in Figs. 6c to 6f. EDXRA point analyses at  x 50 000, measured with the EM 400T/ST in the STEM-EDXRA mode, seemed to give  additional chemical elements to those measured at x 10 000, the highest magnification for  EDXRA analysis wlth a SEM 0-e-, JSM-35C or SEM 505) used for scanning electron  microscopy of surfaces only    89    c~  aO  C~  i-  q~  b-1    90    w  'I    ao  ao  ~L  o    91    REFERENCES  Bisdom, E.B A., 1981a. A review of the application of submicroscopic techniques in soil  micromorphology, I. Transmission electron microscope (TEM) and scanning electron  microscope  (SEM).  In:  E.B.A  Bisdom  (Editor),  Suhmicroscopy of Sods and  Weathered  Rocks.  1st Workshop of the International Working-Group on Sub-  microscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM), 1980, Wageningen. Centre  for Agricultural Pubhshing and Documentatton (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 67--116.  Bisdom, E B.A, 1981b. A review of the application of submicroscopic techniques m soil  micromorphology,  II  Electron  microprobe  analyzer  (EMA),  scanning electron  microscope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser microprobe mass  analyzer (LA.MMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis (ESCA), ion  microprobe mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary 1on microscope (SLM) In'  E.B A Blsdom (Editor), Submlcroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks_ 1st Workshop  of the International Working-Group on Submlcroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials  (IWGSUSM), 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documenta-  tion (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp 117--162  B~dom, E B A and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservoir rocks using SEM  EDXRA. In_ E.B.A Blsdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks  1st Workshop of the International Working-Group on Suhmicroscopy of Undisturbed  Soil Materials (IWGSUSM), 1980, Wagenlngen Centre for Agricultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206  Bisdom, E B A., Henstra, S , Jongerlus, A and Thiel, F_, 1975 Energy-dispersive X-ray  analysis on thin sections and ummpregnated soil material. Neth J Agric Sei , 23 (4)  113--125  Bisdom, E B.A., Henstra, S., Hornsveld, E M, Jongerlus, A and Letsch, A.C., 1976.  Wavelength and energy dmpersive X-ray microanalysis with EMA and SEM-EDXRA on  thin sections of soils. Neth J. Agrlc Sci., 24 (4) 209--222.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Thlel, F., Volbert, B and Jackman, J., 1983. Variations in backscattered  electron scanning images with the Philips SEM 505 as apphed to mineral grains and  excrements in a podzol, to precipitates on a water-tube filter and to bauxite Geo-  derma, 30:93--116 (this issue).  Boekestein, A., Henstra, S. and Blsdom, E.B A., 1981 Submicroscopic techniques for in  situ mtcrochemical analysis of soils, I  Non-destructive techniques, 1  In  E B A  Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the  International  Working-Group  on  Submicroscopy  of  Undisturbed Sod Materials  (IWGSUSM), 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Pubhshing and Documenta-  tion (Pudoc), Wagemngen, pp. 29--44  Bresson, L M, 1981 Etude ultramicroseopique d'assemblages plasmiques sur lames ultra-  minces de sols r~alis4~es par bombardement ionique  In  E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor),  Submlcroscopy of Sods and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the International  Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM), 1980,  Wageningen.  Centre  for  Agricultural  Pubhshing  and  Documentation  (Pudoc),  Wagenmgen, pp. 173--189.  Foster, R C., 1981. Localization of organic materials in situ in ultrathin sections of  natural soil fabrics using cytochemical techniques. In' E.B.A Bisdom (Editor), Sub-  microscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the International Working-  Group  on  Submicroscopy  of  Undisturbed  Soil  Materials  (IWGSUSM),  1980,  Wageningen.  Centre  for  Agricultural  Pubhshing  and  Documentation  (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp_ 309--317    92    Jongerlus, A and Helntzberger, G , 1975 Methods in soil mlcromorphology. A techmque  for the preparation of large thin sections_ Neth Soil Surv Inst , Wagenlngen, Soil Surv  Pap., 10' 48 pp  Volbert, B., 1981  Verbesserung der topographlschen Informatlon dutch Ueberlagerung  yon Sekund~relektronen (SE) - und invertlertem Riickstreuelektronen (BSE) - Signal  Beitr~ge Elektronenmikroskoplsche Direktabbddung und Analyse yon Oberfl~chen  (EDO), Innsbruck, 14 325--330                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractExperiments have been carried out with STEM-EDXRA (scanning transmission electron microscope—energy dispersive X-ray analyzer) and SEM- EDXRA (scanning electron microscope—energy dispersive X-ray analyzer) on thin sections with thicknesses of about 5 μm and 0 μm, respectively.Common thin sections with a thickness of about 20 μm, were analysed with the Philips SEM 505 and the Jeol-JSM-35C. Such thick preparations only allow near-surface imaging with secondary and backscattered electrons plus microchemical analysis up to x 10 000. The beam spot of the Philips EM 400T/ST, which can operate as a STEM-SEM-TEM with EDXRA, can be made smaller than is possible with the other two machines which were specifically built as SEM-instruments. Consequently, microchemical analysis could be performed at magnifications of more than x 10 000. Indications are that analysis at x 50 000 with EDXRA gave additional elements to those measured with SEM-EDXRA at x 10 000. In this manner near-trace-element quantities become measurable.Investigation of 5 μm thick thin sections was mainly done with the Philips EM 400T/ST in the SEM-EDXRA and STEM—EDXRA mode. In this experiment the thin section was thinned maximally by normal grinding processes and subsequently removed in small pieces from the object glass together with the plastic used for mounting. These pieces were then placed in a copper grid and studied close to their surfaces with SEM-EDXRA and in the transmission mode with STEM-EDXRA. The use of TEM-EDXRA was not possible because this requires ultrathin sections of about 1 μm thickness. Even whrn the plastic, used for mounting the soil material on the object glass, is replaced by dissolvable material, the 5 μm thick thin section would still be a few microns thick. No diamond knife or ion thinning technique, used for the preparation of ultrathin sections of soft soil materials such as organic matter and clay, was applied in this study. 