Geoderma, 34 (1984) 293--314                                                     293  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    AN ASSESSMENT OF CHEMICAL PROPERTIES FOR SOILS OF  RWANDA WITH THE USE OF GEOSTATISTICAL TECHNIQUES    P. VANDER ZAAG', R.S. YOST2, B.B. TRANGMAR2, K. HAYASHI2 and R.L. FOX:  'International Potato Center c/o PCARRD, Los Balms (Philippines)  2Department of Agronomy and Soil Science, University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii  96822 (U.S.A.)  (Received September 22, 1983 ; revised version accepted July 2, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Vander Zaag, P., Yost, R.S., Trangmar, B.B., Hayashi, K. and Fox, R.L., 1984. An assess-  ment of chemical properties for soils of Rwanda with the use of geostatistical tech-  niques. Geoderma, 34: 293--314.    Surface soil (0--15 cm) and subsoil (30--45 cm) samples from 121 locations in  Rwanda were collected and analyzed for pH, soluble Si, effective CEC (ECEC), Ca, Mg,  K, Na, NH,, Al, P and S. Most of these properties were mapped using geostatistical tech-  niques.  Soil pH in the Gikongoro and Byumba regions was usually less than 5.0 and high levels  of extractable Al were measured. Soils from volcanic ash contained the highest levels of  total nitrogen (Karisimbi, 1.63% N), followed by soils under forest (Gikongoro, 0.25% N)  and soils of the dry southwest (0.11% N). Exchangeable Mg ranged from 0.19 to 4.1  meq./100 g and exchangeable K from 0.27 to 1.64 meq./100 g.  The P sorption capacities of Rwandan soils were low compared with many soils of the  tropics. Soils from volcanic materials had the greatest concentration of P in solution  (median 0.02 ~g P/ml) and greatest P sorption (approximately 370 ~g P/g of soil material  required to provide 0.2 ug P/ml in solution.  The phosphate-extractable sulfate levels ranged from 0 to 1372 ug/g. Subsoil samples  were always higher in S than surface soils.  Erosion hazard estimates were based on the loss of the surface soils (0--30 cm) which  would expose subsoils that are more acid, higher in exchangeable A1 and Na and signif-  icantly lower in N, P, K, Ca, and Mg.    INTRODUCTION    Agricultural production is low in many tropical countries as a result of  nutrient deficiencies and acidity of the highly weathered soils that dominate  the tropical scene. In such countries, agricultural development is often con-  strained by limited financial resources, untrained personnel, and inadequate    *' Journal Series No. 2979, University of Hawaii, College of Tropical Agriculture and  Human Resources.    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science PublishersB.V.    294    facilities for soil analysis and agronomic experimentation. It would be help-  ful if management information developed in other areas with similar soils  and crops could be used to increase the efficiency of food production in  areas of limited agricultural development. Management information can be  transferred more readily if the softs are classified according to their proper-  ties and to climatic characteristics.  This paper presents the results of a reconnaisance survey of soil fertility in  Rwanda. The soil analysis results were used to prepare maps of fertility levels  of several nutrients. Fertilizer needs based on these results are discussed.    Landscape of Rwanda    Rwanda is a small country of 26,000 km2 located just south of the  Equator in Central Africa (Fig. 1). Delepierre (1974) identified three major  agricultural zones: high elevation (&gt;1900 m altitude), medium elevation  (1500--1900 m) and low elevation (&lt;1500 m). The high elevation zone,  named the Zaire--Nile Ridge, stretches the full length of the country from  Gisenyi and Ruhengeri in the north, passing between Gitarama and Kibuye  and in the south between Gikongoro and Cyangugu. The high plateau of  Byumba is also included. The high elevation zone is often strongly dissected  and a small part of the region is still in native forest. Softs are mostly Eutran-  depts in the volcanic northwest and Dystrandepts in the southwest, whereas  the rest of the softs are generally Tropepts. Udults and Humults often form  associations with Fluvents and Orthents in the river valleys. Histosols occur  locally in swampy areas on valley floors. With annual rainfall of 1250--2000    ~x       ~ ~',~"       x  SOIL SI::INPLE SITE    Fig. 1. General map of Rwanda and location of sampling transects.    295    mm per annum, the moisture regime is udic (Fig. 2). Temperatures are most-  ly isothermic with some isomesic areas at the highest elevations. Agriculture  is generally limited to areas less than 2500 m altitude. The principal crops  grown are maize, peas, potatoes, tea and pyrethrum.    M8A  Fig. 2. Annual rainfall distribution (mm).    The medium elevation zone is the most important agriculturally. In  Rwanda, it occurs along the Zaire--Nile Ridge occupying the region along  Lake Kivu and the central plateau from Byumba southward between Gita-  rama and Kigali and Gikongoro east and southward to the Burundi border.  Humults, Udults, and Tropepts are the most common soil suborders where-  as softs of the suborders Humox, Orthox and Fluvents occur locally. This  region is isothermic and the moisture regime is predominantly udic. The  main food crops are banana, sorghum, sweet potato, maize and taro while  coffee is the major cash crop.  The low elevation zone is gently sloping and covers the eastern 30% of the  country. The temperature regime is isohyperthermic and the moisture regime  is ustic with less than 1000 mm annual rainfall {Fig. 2). The predominant  suborders are Ustults, Humox, Orthox, Ustox and Ustalfs. The main crops  are peanut, sorghum, bean, sweet potato, banana and coffee.  The agricultural potential of a region can be best realized if the crops used  are well-adapted to the region and their nutritional requirements can be pro-  vided with minimal fertilizer amendments. For broad-scale management pur-  poses, general maps of the status of essential plant nutrients are needed to  estimate suitability of crops and efficiency of fertilizer use. In compiling  such maps, detailed sampling of individual fields is not usually feasible so an  approach is needed to estimate soil fertility status based on a minimum num-    296    ber of soil samples. Yost et al. (1982a, b) described the use of geostatistical  methods to obtain optimal estimates of soil properties from available sample  data. This approach uses spatial relationships of soil properties to improve  estimates of soil properties and to determine the precision of such estimates.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil sampling    Soil samples were collected across the three agricultural zones along  9 transects at 4--8 km intervals. The transects followed the main road across  Rwanda (Fig. 1). At each of the 121 sites, surface {0--15 cm) and subsoil  {30--45 cm) samples were collected. The sites were located in forest or  cultivated fields at least 200 m from roads or houses to avoid sampling con-  taminated areas.    Laboratory analysis    Phosphorus and Si in saturation extracts were determined by placing  about 50 g soil material in leaching tubes and saturating them with water.  After three days, 1 ml aliquots of water were repeatedly added to displace  about 12 ml of solution. The leachates were centrifuged and P and Si were  determined in the clear extracts.  Data for constructing P sorption curves were obtained by equilibrating 3 g  samples of soil material for 6 days at 25 in 30 ml of 0.01 MCaC12 contain-  ing various amounts of Ca(H2PO4)2 (Fox and Kamprath, 1970). Shaking was  for two 30-min periods each day. Phosphorus required to obtain 0.02 and  0.2 ~g P/ml in solution was interpolated from the P sorption curve. The  polyacrylamide method of Banderis et al. (1976) was used to determine  NaHCO3-extractable P.  Sulfate was extracted with a Ca(H2PO4)2 solution containing 500 pg P/ml.  The extraction was repeated 4 times using a soil:solution ratio of 1:5 (Fox  et al., 1964). The extracts were digested with nitricperchloric acid before sul-  fate was determined using the method of Tabatabai (1974) which was modi-  fied to include the addition of solid BaC12 to each sample.  Nitrogen mineralization was determined in soil samples incubated for  14 days at 30 using the method of Stanford and Hanway (1955) except  that the soil materials were mixed with equal amounts of crushed sponge  rock. Following incubation, nitrate and ammonium were extracted with 1 M  KC1. Separate samples were used to determine initial ammonium in the soils.  Ammonium was determined by steam distillation and acid titration.  Calcium, Mg, K and Na were extracted with one normal ammonium ace-  tate (pH 7.0). Effective cation exchange capacity (ECEC) was the sum of Ca,  Mg, K and Na plus extractable A1.  Aluminum was extracted with 1 M KC1 using a soil:solution ratio of 1:25.    297    Shaking was for 30 min followed by centrifugation. A1 was determined in  the extract by titration by base, adding excess NaF and titrating with acid.  Soil pH was determined in 1:1 soil--water suspensions.    Soil classification    Soils were classified according to Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975)  based on observations at each sampling site, laboratory analyses for the  0--15 and 30--45 cm samples and existing soil taxonomic information.    Mapping    The spatial variability of the soil nutrient parameters was analyzed using  semi-variograms and kriging. The semi-variogram describes how soil proper-  ties vary with distance between sample locations. Kriging is an optimal inter-  polation procedure which uses the description of soil variability with  distance as provided by the semi-variogram to obtain estimates for the soil  property at unsampled locations (Journel and Huijbregts, 1978}. Precision of  these kriged estimates is obtained from the variance term associated with  each estimate.  By using the measured values and semi-variograms, kriged values of  selected soil properties were computed for 148 locations distributed in a  square grid across Rwanda. Maps of selected properties were then compiled  using those kriged values.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Soluble silicon    Although silicate materials are often added to Si-depleted soils in the  humid tropics, the purpose of including Si in this survey was not to discover  nutritional problems relating to Si per se, but rather to use soluble Si as an  indication of the degree to which soils have been weathered.  Weathering and leaching in the tropics is a desilication process that leads  to an accumulation of A1, Fe and Mn compounds. Generally, the solubility  of Si is related to soil mineralogy; the order of Si solubility being: relatively  unweathered noncrystalline material &gt; 2:1 clay &gt; 1:1 clay &gt; A1 and Fe  oxides (Fox et al., 1967; Fox, 1974). Silicon in solution is a useful index of  weathering of soil minerals. Silicon in saturation extracts of softs generally  decreases as weathering increases, reflecting the extent of chemical, physical,  and biological alteration of soil material over time.  The map of soluble silicon (Fig. 3) shows areas of high Si, in both the  volcanic region between Ruhengeri and Gisenyi and the dry east part of the  country where Si levels are greater than 10 t~g/ml. These values are high in  comparison with highly weathered soils from Puerto Rico (Table I). Con-    298    sistently high values of Si in Rwandan soil suggests rejuvenation from recent  volcanic ash, perhaps from the volcanoes of the northeast and southwest.  The Si levels are much lower in the subsoil (Table I). This may be a com-  bined result of less influence of recent ash and recycling of Si by the plant  roots to the surface as plant material is returned to the soil surface.    )o    Fig. 3. Concentrations of soluble Si as predicted by kriging.    TABLE I  Soluble silicon levels (t~g/ml) for representative soils of Rwanda compared with some soils  of Puerto Rico (after Fox, 1982)    Soil                Location           Surface        Subsoil    Andept             Karisimbi           13             6.4  Tropept            Gikongoro           7             3.7  Udult              Gitarama            8             7.5  Ustox              Akagera            15             4.4  4 Ultisols           Puerto Rico          5.8            1.6  60xisols           Puerto Rico          2.4            0.9    Silicon solubility is related to the availability of P and S as indicated by  the strong negative correlation between Si concentration in solution and P  required to obtain a standard concentration of P in solution (Fig. 4). Similar  trends exist for the other soils of Rwanda although the slopes of the curves  are not so steep.    299    Soil pH and lime requiremen ts    A major soil fertility constraint to crop production in Rwanda is soil aci-  dity (Fig. 5). Softs with pH less than 5.3 predominate in the regions of  Byumba and Gikongoro (Table II, Fig. 5).  As soil pH decreased below 5.3, extractable A1 levels increased markedly  (Fig. 6). Extractable A1 was detected in 41 of the 121 surface soil samples.    ca  c3  o  cb  Z:oo   o  (.9  tEN  ~ u~.  (3=  (_3o  2~  t~Do  (/3  [~- oK    !    o  '    l'o.o '    ;s.o '   ~0.0 '   ~s.o  SI  (HG/L)    Fig. 4. Relationship between phosphorus requirement and Si concentration.    Fig. 5. Soil pH as measured by water for various agricultural regions.    300  TABLE II  Estimated lime(CaCO3) requirements using 4 methods for 12 acid surface soilsof Rwanda    Soil No. Location    Classification  pH    Exchangeable  AI (meq./  100 g)    Lime requirement.1 (CaCO3 T/ha)    Incubation Kamprath, Lathwcll, Cochrancet  1970        1979      al., 1980    1--6    Sab yinyo   D ystrandept   4.4  2.1             2.4         3.2         4.2       1.4  4--5    Ruhengeri  Udult          4.6  1.4             1.4         2.1         2.8       0.7  4---6     Ruhengeri  Udult           4.8  2.0             4.6          3.0          4.0        1.4  4--13   Kigali       Udult           4.7  2.4              2.2          3.6          4.8        2.1  6--3     Cyangugu  Tropept         4.1  0.9               1.8           1.4           2.3        0.4  6--7     Gikongoro Tropept        4.5  3.3              3.2          5.0          6.6        2.9  6--8     Gikongoro Tropept        4.8  1.9              1.8          2.8          5.2        1.9  6--10   Gikongoro Tropept        4.1  4.6              2.0          6.9        10.0        4.9  9--7    B yumba    Udult          3.7  4.5            6.8         6.8         9.0       3.6  9--9    Byumba    Udul~          3.9  2             3.8         3.0         4.0       0.1  9--10   Byumba    Udult           4.3  2.1              5.1          3.2          4.2        1.2  9--11   Byumba    Udult          3.7  3.1             5.5         4,6         6.2       2.5  Mean                                4.3  2.5             4.1         3.8         5.3       1.9    *1Methods. Incubation: various amounts of saturated Ca(OH)2 and or water were added to soil to  make soil--solution ratio of 1:4; samples were stirred daily and the suspension pH was read after  8 days.  Kamprath, 1970: meq. CaCOJIO0 g required is equal to 1.5 X Al meq./100 g.  Lathwell,  1979: meq. CaCO3/100 g = 2 X exchangeable A1 (meq./100 g) + 2 -- meq. (Ca+Mg)  Cochrane et al. (1980): meq. CaCO3/100 g - 1.5 X [Al -RAS (A1 + Ca + Mg)]. Where RAS = required  A1 saturation, and A1, Ca, Mg are expressed in meq./100 g. Required A1 saturation of 20% was used for  these calculations.    At pH 5.0, softs were 20% saturated with A1. Twenty percent is considered  the limit for optimum growth of crops such as soybeans and cotton (Kamp-  rath, 1970)Maize and cassava tolerate higher levels of A1. Subsoil (30--45  cm) samples were more acid than the surface soil samples. Thirty-six percent  of the subsoil samples had pH less than 5.0.    S  OK  0  c~  Z  _J  c3    .50    J  i|   00 '   ;5o '   ~.oo '             .                       5.50  PH    Fig. 6. Relationship between soil pH and extractable A1.    301    Liming these acid soils is not absolutely essential, but maintaining soil pH  of about 5.6 to keep extractable A1 low is a desirable management practice.  Four methods for determining the lime requirements for the 14 acid surface  soils are presented in Table II. The four methods differ considerably in their  estimates of the lime requirements. The methods proposed by Kamprath  (1970) and Lathwell (1979) give average requirements of 3.8 and 5.3 tons of  lime/ha, respectively. The method of Cochrane et al. (1980) predicts lime  requirements that are lower than those obtained by using the formulae of  Lathwell (1979) and Kamprath (1970). The average requirement for the  12 surface soils was 5.3 T/ha using the formulae which also consider Ca +  Mg. The incubation method indicates that about 4.1 tons of lime/ha is suffi-  cient. Rutunga and Neel {1980) in studies in Gikongoro observed that 4 tons  of lime/ha produced significant yield increases over a 4-year period. Even  though titration curves indicate a weak buffering capacity below pH 6,  Rutunga and Neel {1980) report that 1 ton of lime/ha did not significantly  improve yields over the control. Based on a rough estimate using the method  of Cochrane et al. {1980), approximately one million tons of lime would be  required to reduce extractable A1 to a satisfactory level for crops such as  beans on about 50% of the soils with pH 5.0 or less.  Limited amounts of lime will render some of the soils more productive for  sensitive crops such as beans and vegetables. Varieties of sorghum and maize  which are tolerant of soil acidity need to be identified and the current varie-  ties should be given an opportunity to be more productive. Placing lime with  the seed has possibilities for making more efficient use of a costly and scarce  resource (J.M. Spain, personal communication, 1983). At the same time, a  strong program of soil conservation needs to be encouraged.    Total N and nitrogen mineralization    The Andepts near Sabyinyo and Karisimbi volcanoes contained large  amounts of N (0.6--1.63% N; Table IV). The soils of Kibungo, Gabiro arid  Byumba and the softs under forest in Cyangugu--Butare contained smaller  amounts of total N. Nevertheless, N may be deficient for crops growing in  these Andepts because of restricted mineralization of organic matter. Stable  organic matter--soil mineral compounds result in unfavorable conditions for  organic matter decomposition leading to organic matter accumulation. In  such cases, high organic matter may indicate infertility (Fox, 1980). For  example, soils under forest were generally low in total N (Table III). These  will probably require substantial fertilizer N applications to satisfy crop re-  quirements.  In all cases, the subsoil N levels were about one-half of the surface soil  levels except for the Andepts where the N levels were 30--40% less. Such  data reinforce the importance of protecting the surface soil against erosion  and returning crop residue and manures to the soil.  For the surface soils extractable ammonium ranged from 37 to 203 pg N/g    302    TABLE III  Nitrogen mineralization rates of Rwandan surface soils during 14 days of incubation at 30    Soil       Location    Transcct  TotalN NHainitial N mineralized (pg/g)  NHa--N   pH  Al  and site  (%)     (pg/g)                                             (meq./  number                          NHa--N     NO3--N   NO3--N         1 00 g)    Andept   Karisimbi  (3--1)     0.5       83          0            51  Andept  Sabyinyo  (1--4)    0.43    103        16         130  Tropcpt  Gikongoro (6--7)     0.25     149         38            31  (forest)  Tropept  Gikongoro (6--14)   0.14     143         40            14  (forest)  Tropept  Gitarama   (5--9)    0.09     66          4           36  Ustox     Bugcsera   (7--8)     0.09      64          2            29  Ustox     Kayonza   (8--9)    0.14     54           3            38  Ustox     Gabiro      (9--1)     0.39      91           2            28  Udult     Byumba    (9--11)   0.31      66         35            15    0          6.0  0  .12      5.7  0  1.21    4.5 5.26  2.9        5.0  3.53  .11       5.3  1.26  .07      5.8  0  .08      7.4  0  .07    5.5  .84  2.3        3.7  5.13    TABLE IV  Nitrogen levels for the various regions of Rwanda for both the  subsoil (30--45 cm) samples    surface (0--15 cm) and    Transect                Soil                   No. of samples    Total N (%)    surface      subsoil    Sabyinyo              Andept                7                0.6          0.44  Karisimbi              Andept                7                1.63         1.24  Limit of Karisimbi     Andept              11                0.84         0.55  Ruhengeri--Kigali      Udult                15                0.2          0.12  Kigali--Kibuye         Tropept/Humult      18                0.17         0.08  Cyangugu-Butare      Tropept/Humult     21                0.26         0.10  Bugesera               Orthox]Ustox          9                 0.11         0.08  Kibungo               Ustox/Ustalf         19                0.25         0.13  Gabiro--Byumba       Ustox/Udult         13                0.24         0.13    (see also Fig. 7). The highest levels were determined in softs from the high  rainfall areas. These are the acid softs of the southwest and of the Andept re-  gion of the northwest. Ammonium levels often were greater in softs with  much extractable A1 {Table III). This relationship was observed by Wetselaar  {1972) in Australia and is similar to results reported by Fox {1982} for soils  from Puerto Rico. Nitrification rate usually increases with increasing pH  {Gallagher and Bartholomew, 1964). Results reported here also demonstrate  that effect. Meanwhile, ammonification rates usually decrease to almost zero  for softs with pH above 5.3. The soils of Sabyinyo {only one presented in  Table III) produced 8 to 17 gg/g ammonium during the incubation period  even though the soil pH was above 5.7. Nitrification in the Sabyinyo soils,  however, was about 10 times greater than ammonification.    303    Exchangeable cations    Exchangeable calcium levels differ considerably (Fig. 8). Levels of less  than 3 meq./100 g were observed in Gikongoro whereas values greater than  9 meq./100 g were observed in the Andepts of the northwest and in the  fertile ustic southeastern region. Soils derived from volcanic ash {transects 1,  2, 3) and soils from the eastern region of the country (transect 8) were high  in exchangeable Ca, Mg and K (Table V). Soils of the Gikongoro and Kibuye    Fig. 7. Extractable ammonium levels in soil (pg NH4 -N/g).    Fig. 8. Exchangeable soil calcium levels (meq. Ca/100 g).    304  TABLE V  pH and cation levels in Rwandan softs (means)    Transect           Soil                 Transcct  No. of  pH    Ca       Mg    K      Na    A1   ECEC  samples  (meq./lOOg)    Surface (0--15 cm):  Sabyinyo           Andept              1             7       5.9      9.7     1.2    0.32   0.16   0     11.38  Karisimbi          Andept             3            7       5.7    30.2     3.3    1.0    0.17  0    14.67  Karisimbi           Andept              2           11       6.3     12.5     4.1     1.18   0.22   0     17.90  R uhengeri--Kigali Udult                4           15       5.5      6.0     1.2    0.4    O.12   1.0    8.72  Kigali--Kibuye     Tropept/Humult   5           18       5.6      5.7     0.19   0.41   0.21   0.73  7.23  Gikongoro          Tropept/Humult   6           16       5.0      2.8     0.66   0.27   0.49   2.96  7.18  Butare               Tropept/Udult     6            5       5.8      7.7     1.72   0.54   0.49   O.'31 10.74  Bugesera            Ustox/Orthox      7            9       5.8      4.1     (}.97   0.63   0.45   0.96  7.11  Kibungo            Ustox/Ustalf       8           19       6.7      9.9     3.02   1.64   (/.78   O     15.37  Gabiro  Byumba  Ustox/Udult        9           13       5.0      6.0     1.67   0.53   0.90   1.65 10.80    Subsoil (30--45 cm):  Sabyinyo                                  1             7       6.0      7.8     1.1     {).29   0.95   0     10.14  Karisimbi                             3           7      5.5    11.0    3.1    0.90  0.19  0.8  15.99  Karisimbi                               2          11       6.5    10.9    4.1    0.57   0.95  0    16.52  R uhengeri--Kigali                        4           15      51.        2.95   0.54   O.16   O.31   2.26  6.22  Kigali--Kibuye                        5         18      5.2     2.84   0.87  0.24  0.30  1.94  6.18  Gikongoro                              6          16       4.8     0.93   0.18  0.16   0.29   3.87  5.43  Butare                                      6            5       5.6      1.1     1.1     0.18   0.32   {).56  8.46  Bugesera                                   7            9       5.l      1.9     1.19   (I.15   0.27   0.76  4.27  Kibungo                                   8           19       5.7      6.27   2.0    0.25   0.29   0.79  9.60  Gabiro  Byumba                         9           13       5.0    4.08     1.15   0.28   0.29   2.05  7.85    and Bugesera transects (5, 6, 7) were low in cations. The Gikongoro and  Byumba soils have high A1 saturation. Subsoil samples were more acidic,  containing lower levels of basic cations and higher amounts of Al than sur-  face soil samples.  Calcium was the dominant exchangeable cation in most soils. Therefore,  effective cation exchange capacity was well correlated with exchangeable Ca    Fig. 9. Effective cation exchange capacity as obtained by sum of the cations.    305    and this relationship can be seen in similarities of the maps of the two proper-  ties (Figs. 8 and 9).    Phosphorus    Phosphorus sorption curves were prepared for the 121 surface and subsoil  samples. Curves for four representative soils from four regions are presented  in Fig. 10. A Eutrandept, a soil with much noncrystalline material, had the  highest P sorption capacity. The P requirement, which is the amount of P  required to attain 0.2 pg P/ml in solutions (Juo and Fox, 1977), for Andepts  of this study was 370 pg/g of soil. Phosphate sorption by the Tropept from  Gikongoro, is in the medium range. Mean standard P sorption by all softs of  Gikongoro was 234 pg P/g. Soils belonging to the Eutrustox and the Humult  groups sorb less P. These soils respectively represent the drier eastern one-  third of the country and the Gitarama area. Olsen's extractable P and P in  saturation extracts (Table VI) indicate more than adequate available P for  nearly all food crops in the Kibungo and Karisimbi areas. Soils from Volcano  Sabyinyo were generally low in P whereas soils of Gikongoro, Bugesera and  Butare were very low (less than 0.008 gg P/ml). Substantial amounts of P  fertilizer would probably be required to bring these soils to an adequate P  level for crops such as beans, sorghum and maize. According to published  external P requirements, cassava would not experience P deficiency and  sweet potatoes should produce about 75% of maximum attainable yield  (Fox, 1979; Vander Zaag et al., 1979) without P fertilization.  Erosion would, in most cases, render these soils even more infertile with  respect to P as can be seen from the Erosion Hazard Indexes presented in  Table VI. For the Karisimbi soil, the similar surface and subsoil P levels may  be due to intensive farming with no P additions, thus reducing surface soil to  levels similar to those of the subsoil and just recently cleared or natural  forest (Transect 3). The Ustox soils of Bugesera have sandy surface softs and  more clay in the subsoils {although not enough to classify them as argillic  horizons) and have similar higher available P in the subsoil.  500-                                                   ///~  400-  S  o 300L  R  B  DE 200-  02                       ~  I          I          I          i          I          I  O. 008    0.016    0.032    0.064    O. 128    0.256    0,512  P IN SOIL S(~LUTION,  MG/L  LEGEND: SOIL      EUTRRNDEPT      ;'. ".'." ;." EUTRUSTBX  ". ". ~ HUMULT          ~ ..n ~ TROPEPT  Fig. 10. Phosphorus sorption curves determined in 0.01 M CaCI~.    306  TABLE ~'I  P levels in surface soil (0--15 cm) and subsoil (30--45 cm) samples for 9 transects of Rwanda ~ data for  Olsen's method are presented as mean values; for P in saturation extracts (median values) are given    Name                      Transect  Soil                  Olscn                P in solution   Erosion index*l  No.                         (ug/g)            (pg]ml)       (0--15 era)    0--15       30--45       0--15   30--45    (30--45)    Sabyinyo               1         Andept            131     55        .015  .01       1.5  Karisimbi               3         Andept             49     12        .041   .012     3.4  Karisimbi               2         Andept             43     43        .008  .013       .6  R uhengeri--Kigali       4          Udult                17     10         .014  .01        1.4  Kigali--Kibuye          5          Tropept]Humult    18     10         .01    .01        1.0  Cyangugu--Gikongoro  6          Tropept/Humult    19     11         .008   .009       .9  Butare                   6          Tropept/Humult    20       8         .001   .009      1.1  Bugesera                7         Ustox/Orthox      12     10        .004  .012       .33  Kigali (East)            8         Ustox               15     10        .01    .002     5.0  Kibungo                 8          Ustox/Ustalf        66     14        .11    .005    22.0  Byumba                9         Ustox/Udult        22     10        .001   .004     2.8    *ICalculated as the ratio of P in saturation extracts of surface and subsoil.    Sulfate    Sulfur has been described as a neglected nutrient for crop production. In  tropical regions, where there is little industrial activity, the SO4-S concentra-  tions in rain water are usually less than 1 ppm. Rainfall contributed 1.4 kg  S/ha annually in northern Nigeria (Bromfield, 1974). In Rwanda, sulfate was  generally a little more abundant in the subsoil samples than in the 0 to 15-  cm samples (Table VII). In three profiles from Kibungo the subsoil samples    TABLE VII    Sulfate-S (ug/g soil) in the soils of Rwanda as determined by repeated phosphate extrac-  tion    Transect (No.)             Soil               Surface (~g/g)     Subsoil (ug/g)    mean      range                  mean      range    Sabyinyo (1)               Andept           27     2--84      19     2--24  Karisim bi (3)                Andept            64     6--136     50     14--138  Karisim bi (2)              Andept           29    2--66      15    2--44  Ruhengeri-Kigali (4)        Udult             23     2--46      28     8--50  Kigali--Kibuye (5)          Tropept/Humult  19     2--54      26     8--72  Cyangugu--Gikongoro (6)  Tropept/Humult  45     4--180     48     8--94  Butare (6)                  Tropept            5.6   0--16       4     1--12  Bugesera (7)               Ustox/Orthox     11     0--32      34     6--62  Kigali--Kibungo (8)         Ustox/Ustalf       11.5   4--28      41     6--1372*~  Gabiro--Byumba (9)        Ustox/Udult -     27     4--120     24     4--102  Mean                                         26.2              29.0    ,1 Values greater than 200 not included in the average.    307    contained more than 200 pg SO2-S/g of soil. The availability of subsoil sul-  fate is unknown at this time.  Generally the SO4-S levels as determined in these soils appear to be defi-  cient or near deficient. For soils from volcanic ash in Hawaii (Dystrandepts)  25 pg/g of soil was inadequate (Fox et al., 1965), but for softs that do not  adsorb much sulfate even 8--10 pg/g may be adequate (Kang and Osiname,  1976). In the Butare area, however, S levels generally were lower whereas  the acid soils of Gikongoro were high in S. Soil pH was negatively correlated  with SO4-S. For soils from volcanic materials the correlation coefficients  between pH and SO4-S were 0.45 and 0.44 for surface soils and subsoils,  respectively. Sulfate sorption is pH-dependent, therefore this result was  expected.    Spatial variability of selected nutrients    For properties with log-normally distributed values, semi-variograms were  computed from natural logarithms of the data. Semi-variances for selected  properties of surface soils are summarized in Table VIII.  The range (or distance) over which sample values were spatially related  varied considerably for different soil properties (Table VIII). Soluble Si was  least variable and was spatially dependent over the longest distance (about  60 km). Effective CEC (ECEC), exchangeable Ca, Mg and extractable NH4  were spatially related over distances of about 50 km. Soil pH, exchangeable  Na, A1 and K were slightly more variable as indicated by a shorter range of  spatial dependence (38, 28, 28 and 29 km, respectively). Greatest variation  was shown by the amount of P sorbed to obtain 0.02 t~g/ml P in soil solu-  tion. When all values were included in the calculations, the range of spatial  dependence for P sorption was about 5 km. Such short range was probably  caused by large differences of P sorption between the soils from volcanic  materials and other soils. Because of this, soils were separated into two  groups: those with P sorption &lt; 80 ~g P/g and those with &gt; 80 g P/g. The  semi-variogram computed for softs with a requirement of ~&lt; 80 t~g P/g were  extremely variable with a range less than the minimum sample spacing of  4 km.  The semi-variogram of pH and in K (Fig. 11) represents extremes in the  strength of the relationship between semi-variance and distance. The raw  data for pH have a low variance relative to the mean, and semi-variance is  highly correlated with distance. For soil pH the semi-variance increases with  distance in a curvilinear relationship up to about 37.5 km. Beyond this  distance, there is no easily described mathematical relationship between  semi-variance and distance. For exchangeable K the intercept of the semi-  variogram (0.76) is close to the general variance (0.90) of the data and the  range is relatively short (20 km) (Table VIII). These factors and the relative-  ly poor fit of the semi-variogram equation (R2 = 0.36) suggest a poorly de-  fined relationship between semi-variance and distance for exchangeable K.    TABLE VIII    Summary of variograms for selected soil properties of  Soil                           Variogram              R~       Range            General    General    Re-expressed   Re-expressed  property                    equation              value   h       km     mean      variance    mean (M)      variance (V)  pH                                0.71X- 0.00087X~     0.85     15        37.5       5.71         0.78         --                 --  ECEC (meq./100 g)         21.58 + 0.29X        0.46    20     50      11.35     31.30      --            --  exch. Ca (meq./100 g)        8.69 + 0.31X        0.70    20      50       7.14      17.69       --              --  In exch. Mg (meq./100 g)      0.73 + 0.069X        0.32     21       52.5      0.25        1.05      2.17            7.84  In exch. K (meq./100 g)       0.76 + 0.0082X      0.36    16      20      -0.78       0.90      0.72            0.84  exch. Al (meq./100 g)       -0.019 + 0.010X      0.92    11      27.5     0.43       0.093      --  exch. Al (meq./100 g)         1.85 + 0.037X       0.34    11      27.5     0.97       3.08       --              --  In N total (%)                0.38 + 0.0048X      0.05    15      37.5    -1.37       0.61      0.34           0.12  In NH4                           0.030 + 0.005X       0.95     22       55        4.41        0.17     89.6            1430  *P 0.02 (~g/g)              376.2 + 121.4X       0.99     5      12.5   32.3       762.50       --             --  In Si (ug/g)               0.05 + 0.004X        0.84    25     62.5     2.22      0.15     9.96         16.4    Rwanda    50  O  O0    Note. The mean (M) and variance (V) of data transformed by natural logarithms were re-expressed using the equations: M = exp.  (~y + oy2/2) and V = gx2 [exp(oy2~--l] from Haan (1977), where M is the re-expressed mean, ~y and ay2 are the mean and general  variance respectively, of the data logarithms, V is the re-expressed variance and ux is the mean of the original data values.  *P sorption 0.02 gg/g variogram calculated for values ~&lt; 80 ug P/g.    309    The differences in spatial variability between pH and K are reflected in the  kriged values because the description of spatial variability embodied in the  semi-variogram is used in the kriging operation. Estimation variances for soil  pH were relatively low compared to the kriged values due to the small    ~&gt;         o   ;-  ~o    15 -  20    25    30    35    40    45    50    DISTANCE CKH)    Fig. 11. Semi-variogram of soil pH (*), and semi-variogram of log extractable potassium  (.).    variance in the data. This implies that the kriged estimates for pH are quite  reliable. The estimation variances for K are large relative to the kriged values  indicating that the reliability of the kriged K values is low.  Estimation variance increases with distance from sampled locations (Figs.  12 and 13). In areas where the estimation variance exceeds acceptable levels,  additional samples can be collected to improve the reliability of the kriged  estimates unless no spatial dependence is present. In this way, maps of es-  timation variance can be used to design optimal sampling schemes in specific  areas following sampling on a reconnaissance level as in this survey.    The fertility of the soils of the 12 agricultural regions as defined by Dele-  pierre (19 74)    Delepierre (1974) identified 12 agricultural regions in Rwanda based on  potential crop productivity as influenced by climate and soil information  (Fig. 14). The 12 regions are listed in Table IX. We collected soil samples  from all of the regions recognized by Delepierre except for Region 1, a small  area in an isolated corner of the southwest. Soil fertility is about average in  the Impara region, border of Lake Kivu, softs from volcanic materials, the  central plateau and the southern part of the eastern plateau. Nitrogen and P  are undoubtedly deficient but pH, Ca, Mg, and S are at acceptable levels.    310    Low Si indicates weathered softs in the Impara region; K is low there also.  The other regions have low soil fertility levels and are especially deficient in  N and P. The Zaire--Nile ridge, the Grantic Dorsal and the Mayaga regions  are also low in K. High acidity of the Zaire--Nile ridge, in Buberuka, and the  northern part of the eastern plateau, indicates the need for lime applications  for better crop production. Exchangeable A1 (2--3 meq./100 g) makes up  20--30% of the exchange complex in these regions. Some individual sites  have up to 80% A1 saturation.    0    Fig. 12. Estimation variance for soil pH.    Fig. 13. Estimation variance for soil potassium.    311    In general, all of the 12 agricultural regions need N, P, and K to obtain  higher crop yields. Cases of A1 toxicity and deficiency of Mg exist. Neel et al.  {1976) in a pot study using samples of 41 soils from throughout the country  determined that 39 soils were deficient in N, 37 in P, 27 in K, 8 in Mg and  2 in Ca. This order of importance is affirmed by the results of this study.    Fig. 14. Agricultural regions of Rwanda as delineated by Delepierre (1974).    CONCLUSIONS    The maps based on kriged values for Si, pH, Ca, effective CEC, NH4 and K  constitute a first approximation of the fertility of soils in the several regions  of Rwanda, though the range over which sampled values were spatially re-  lated ranged from 20 to 62 km. Soil pH was generally greater than 5.0 ex-  cept for the Byumba and Gikongoro regions. In those regions, A1 toxicity  probably is a problem for most food crops. Lime applications as high as  5 tons of CaCO3/ha may be necessary to remove this constraint.  The volcanic region and the southeast have high Si levels. Nitrogen levels  are high in the Andepts but low for the rest of the country (0.11--0.26%).  The subsoils have up to 50% less total N than the surface soils. This indicates  the importance of erosion control and the need to add organic matter {crop  residues, green manure crops, and animal manures) to maintain the soil N  levels. Nitrogen fertilizers are necessary to obtain better crop yields.  Phosphorus sorption and retention is generally low in Rwanda soils. Yet  large quantities of P fertilizer will be required for the country to remove the  P deficiency constraint for most cereal, legumes and vegetable crops. Sulfate  levels are probably adequate for most of the softs except for the Butare  region. Sulfate-S is relatively high in the acid soils of Gikongoro.    TABLE IX    The fertility levels for the soils of the 12 agricultural regions identified by Delepierre (1974)    Agricultural           No. of  Soil  Si       N      P      P         p           S      Ca  region               soil     pH                   Olsen  Solution  Required  samples                                           to obtain  0.02 ug/ml  (~g/ml) (%)   (~g/g) (ug/ml)  (~gP/g)   (ug/g)    1. Imbo  .....  2. Impara            6      5.4   6.0      0.35   11  3. Border Lake       3       5.8   9.9      0.20   10  Kivu  4. Volcanic soils    25      6.0 15.1      0.98   67  5. Zaire--Nile       15      4.9   8.1      0.28   18  Ridge  6. Buberuka         6      4.6   9.5      0.27   24  7. Central Plateau   22      5.5   8.4     0.19   17  8. Granitique        9      5.9   7.6      0.14   24  Dorsal  9. Mayaga           2      5.8   8.1      0.13   21  10. Bugesera          9      5.8   6.5      0.11   12  11. Eastern Plateau N 4      5.1   9.0     0.22   22  11. Eastern Plateau S 19       5.7   6.6      0.13   14  12. Eastern Savanna   3      5.6 11.8      0.21   20    Level (requirement)  Adequate (&gt;)                 5.5 10       1.0  Low      (&lt;)                5.0  6       0.5    Mg    K      Na     A!     ECEC    (meq./100 g)    0.008          75                    42          4.2          1.7         0.16       0.50       1.3         7.8  0.011           16                    15           8.1         3.8         0.75       0.51         --       13.2    0.017          39                    38        11.0  0.008     42          44     3.2    0.009     59          26     5.9  0.015          47                    23           5.7  0.011           14                    13          6.3    0.001   58       5   5.5  0.004          48                    11           4.1  0.009          35                    32          5.5  0.011          82                    41           6.3  0.004          30                    43           7.2    3.1  0.7    1.3  1.2  2.7    1.6  1.0  2.1  2.0  1.8    3.0  1.5    0.002   20      15   6.0  0.01    60       8   3.0    0.90      0.19         --       15.2  0.28   0.40   2.93   7.5    0.34       0.96       1.85    10.4  0.48   0.20   1.11   8.7  0.24       0.11       0.22       9.6    0.23   0.48   0.75   8.6  0.63   0.45   0.96   7.1  0.70   0.82   2.37  11.5  0.25       0.29      0.79      9.6  0.70   0.90   0.28  10.8    0.50  0.25    5O    313    Potassium is deficient with the exceptions of the Kibungo and the Andept  regions. In some cases, Mg and Ca levels are also low. Lime, nitrogen and  phosphorus fertilizers will be needed in part of any crop improvement pro-  gram for the country. Erosion control is necessary to maintain the present  level of soil fertility.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Thanks to Koffi Nicolas and Nazir Ahmad for assisting with the soils  analysis and to G. Uehara for assisting with the kriging and mapping work.  This research was supported in part by a grant from the Foundation for  Agronomic Research.    REFERENCES    Banderis, A., Barter, D.H. and Henderson, K., 1976. The use of polyacrylamide to replace  carbon in the determination of Olsen's extractable phosphate in soil. J. Soil Sci., 27:  71--74.  Bromfield, A.R., 1974. The deposition of sulphur in the rain water of Northern Nigeria.  Tellus, 26: 408--411.  Cochrane, T.T., Salinas, J.G. and Sanchez, P.A., 1980. An equation for liming acid min-  eral soils to compensate aluminum tolerance. Trop. Agric. (Trinidad), 57 : 133--140.  Delepierre, G., 1974. Les r~gions agricoles du Rwanda. Note Technique No. 13, ISAR-  Rubona-Rwanda, 24 pp.  Fox, R.L., 1974. Examples of anion and cation adsorption by soils of tropical America.  Trop. Agric. (Trinidad), 51: 200--210.  Fox, R.L., 1979. Comparative responses of field grown crops to phosphate concentra-  tions in soil solutions, In: H. Mussell and R. Stapes (Editors), Stress Physiology  in Crop Plants. Wiley, New York, N.Y., pp. 81--106.  Fox, R.L., 1980. Soils with variable charge. Agronomic and fertility aspects. In:  B.K.G. Theng (Editor), Soils with Variable Charge. New Zealand Society of Soil  Science, pp. 195--224.  Fox, R.L., 1982. Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 3. Chemical properties.  Geoderma, 27: 139--176.  Fox, R.L. and Kamprath, E.J., 1970. P sorption isotherms for evaluating the P re-  quirements of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 902--907.  Fox, R.L., Olson, R.A. and Rhoades, H.F., 1964. Evaluating the sulfur status of soils  by plant and soil tests. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 28: 243--246.  Fox, R.L., Moore, D.G., Wang, J.M., Plucknett, D.L. and Furr, R.D., 1965. Hawaii  Farm Sci., 14(3): 9--12.  Fox, R.L., Silva, J.A., Younge, O.R., Plucknett, D.L. and Sherman, G.D., 1967. Soil  and plant silicon and silicate response by sugarcane. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31:  775--779.  Gallagher, P.A. and Bartholomew, W.V., 1964. Comparison of nitrate production and  other procedures in determining N availability in SE coastal plain soils. Agron. J., 56:  179--184.  Haan, C.T., 1977. Statistical Methods in Hydrology. Iowa State University Press, Ames,  Iowa.  Journel, A.G. and Huijbregts, C.J., 1978. Mining Geostatistics. Academic Press, London,  600 pp.  Juo, A.S.R. and Fox, R.L., 1977. P sorption characteristics of some benchmark soils of  W. Africa. Soil Sci., 124: 370--376.    314    Kamprath, E.J., 1970. Exchangeable AI as a criterion for liming leached mineral soils.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 252--254.  Kang, B.T. and Osiname, O.A., 1976. Sulfur responses of maize in western Nigeria.  Agron. J., 68 : 333--336.  Lathwell, D.J., 1979. Crop reponse to liming Ultisols and Oxisols. Cornell Int. Agric.  Bull., 35.  Neel, J., De Prins, H.J. and Vindevogel, E., 1976. Etude de la fertilit~ de sols ~ l'aide des  vases de v~g6tations. Note Technique 1, ISAR-Rubona-Rwanda, 72 pp.  Rutunga, V. and Neel, H., 1980. Problemes de fertilisations des sols de praire. Eregrastis  de haute altitude (Mata). Note Technique 4, ISAR-Rubona-Rwanda, 78 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: Basic Classification for Making and Interpreting  Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric., Agriculture Handbook 436,754 pp.  Stanford, G. and Hanway, J., 1955. Predicting N fertilizer needs of Iowa soils, II. A sim-  plified technique for determining relative nitrate production in soils. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 19: 74--66.  Tabatabai, M.A., 1974. Determination of sulphate in water samples. Sulphur Inst. J., 10:  11--13.  Vander Zaag, P., Fox, R.L., de la Pena, R.S. and Yost, R.S., 1979. P nutrition of cassava,  including mycorrhizal effects on P, K, S, Zn, and Ca uptake. Field Crops Res., 2:  253--263.  Yost, R.S., Uehara, G. and Fox, R.L., 1982a. Geostatistical analysis of soil chemical pro-  perties of large land areas, I. Semi-variograms. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 1028--1032.  Yost, R.S., Uehara, G. and Fox, R.L., 1982b. Geostatistical analysis of soil chemical  properties of large land areas, II. Kriging. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 1033--1037.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractSurface soil (0–15 cm) and subsoil (30–45 cm) samples from 121 locations in Rwanda were collected and analyzed for pH, soluble Si, effective CEC (ECEC), Ca, Mg, K, Na, NH4, Al, P and S. Most of these properties were mapped using geostatistical techniques.Soil pH in the Gikongoro and Byumba regions was usually less than 5.0 and high levels of extractable Al were measured. Soils from volcanic ash contained the highest levels of total nitrogen (Karisimbi, 1.63% N), followed by soils under forest (Gikongoro, 0.25% N) and soils of the dry southwest (0.11% N). Exchangeable Mg ranged from 0.19 to 4.1 meq./100 g and exchangeable K from 0.27 to 1.64 meq./100 g.The P sorption capacities of Rwandan soils were low compared with many soils the tropics. Soils from volcanic materials had the greatest concentration of P in solution (median 0.02 μg P/ml) and greatest P sorption (approximately 370 μg P/g of soil material required to provide 0.2 μg P/ml in solution.The phosphate-extractable sulfate levels ranged from 0 to 1372 μg/g. Subsoil samples were always higher in S than surface soils.Erosion hazard estimates were based on the loss of the surface soils (0–30 cm) which would expose subsoils that are more acid, higher in exchangeable A1 and Na and significantly lower in N, P, K, Ca, and Mg.