 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 195--208                                                     195  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    INFRARED SPECTRA OF Cu:+, Pb2+, AND Ca2+ COMPLEXES OF SOIL  HUMIC SUBSTANCES    A. PICCOLO and F.J. STEVENSON  Department of Agronomy, University of Illinois, Urbana, IL 61801 (U.S.A.)  {Received January 15, 1981; accepted June 17, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Piccolo, A. and Stevenson, F.J., 1982. Infrared spectra of Cu~+, Pb2+, and Ca2complexes  of soil humic substances. Geoderma, 27: 195--208.    An infrared spectroscopic investigation of the complexes of Cu2 +, Pb2 +, and Ca2+ with  humic and fulvic acids demonstrated the participation of OH and C=O groups in addition  to COOH in the binding of heavy-metal cations. The degree to which metal-carboxylate  linkages are ionic or covalent cannot be accurately determined from the positions of anti-  symmetric and symmetric carboxylate stretching vibrations due to interference from  covalent bonding with other groups. The apparent order of the reaction of three divalent  cations with humic and fuivic acids was Cu2+ &gt; Pb~+ &gt; Ca2+.    INTRODUCTION    Humic substances are capable of interacting with metal ions in soil to form  metal--organic complexes of different stabilities and characteristics. The capac-  ity of humic and fulvic acids to combine with metals is usually attributed to  their high contents of oxygen-containing functional groups, such as carboxyl  (COOH), hydroxyl (OH), and carbonyl (C= O). Considerable controversy  exists regarding the relative importance of each group and whether the link-  ages are ionic or covalent (e.g., see Stevenson and Fitch, 1981). According to  one school of thought, humic substances are spherical, cross-linked polymers  which, although capable of retaining metal ions in readily exchangeable forms,  are incapable of forming structures characteristic of chelate complexes. Several  workers have suggested two main types of chelate linkages, one involving a  COOH and an adjacent phenolic OH group to form a salicylate-like ring and  the other involving two COOH groups in close proximity to form a phthalate-  like ring (Schnitzer and Skinner, 1965; Gamble et al., 1970). The formation  of mixed complexes is likely (Stevenson, 1976).  The discordant results recorded in the literature (see review of Stevenson  and Fitch, 1981) may be due to variations in experimental conditions, includ-  ing metal/fulvate and metal/humate ratios. Covalent bonds may be formed at  low degrees of metal-ion saturation but bonding may become increasingly    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    196    ionic in character as binding capacity is approached. In the work reported  herein, infrared spectra were obtained of complexes formed by adding increas-  ing amounts of Cu2 Pb2+, and Ca2+ to humic and fulvic acids, the rationale  being that a variety of sites may be involved in complexation ranging from  those which form strong coordinate bonds to those in which the linkages are  ionic. Major objectives were: (1) to determine the contribution, if any, of  groups other than COOH in the binding of metal ions, and (2) to ascertain the  nature of the binding sites.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The fulvic acid was obtained from Rifle peat, a Terric Medihemist from  Ohio; the humic acid originated from an Aquic Argiudoll soil from Illinois.  The two preparations are those designated as "Brunizen humic acid" and  "peat fulvic acid FN-2" by Stevenson and Goh (1971, 1972). The reader is  referred to these papers for additional details of methods of extraction and  chemical properties.  The humic acid was further treated by dissolving a 1-g sample of the  freeze&lt;tried preparation in 200 ml of 0.1 N NaOH under a blanket of N2 gas.  The solution was immediately diluted with 300 ml of distilled water, neutral-  ized to pH 7, and dialyzed extensively against distilled water to remove excess  salt. The resulting Na-humate was passed first through an anion-exchange  resin (Dowex 1, OH-form) and then through a cation-exchange resin (Dowex  50, H-form) for conversion to the fully protonated form. The final volume was  adjusted to 1 1. The fulvic acid was prepared by dissolving 0.5 g in 500 ml of  distilled water.  The metal complexes were prepared by dispensing increasing amounts of  0.02 M chloride salt solutions of Cu2 Pb~ and Ca2to 10-ml aliquots of  the humic and fulvic acid solutions. Prior to the additions, the pH was adjusted  to 5.0 using 0.05 N KOH. The pH was readjusted after each incremental addi-  tion of metal ion. All samples were freeze-dried and stored in a vacuum desic-  cator until analyzed.  The reactions involving COOH and COO- are as follows:  (1) RCOOH + KOH ~ RCOO-I~ + H20 sample titrated to pH 5;  (2) 2 RCOO- K+ + MCI~ ~ (RCOO)2M + 2 KC1 addition of metal ion;  (3) RCOOH + KC1 ~ RCOO- + HC1 re-establishment of ionization equilib-  rium with lowering of pH;  (4) HC1 + KOH -~ KC1 + H20  pH returned to 5.0.  At high levels of M2additions, e~entially all COOH groups would be in  the form shown on the right side of reaction (2), provided bind~ was highly  selective for the divalent cation. The highest quantity of M2 * add'e~l, was  equivalent to 1.5 times total acidic functional groups (COOH), as determined  by titration. The quantities of M2added are expressed in terms of the    197    meq. M2meq. acidic H+ ratio and ranged from 0.1 to 1.5. Van Dijk (1971)  concluded that the binding capacity of humic acids for polyvalent cations was  equivalent to the number of titratable H+ ions divided by the valency of the  interacting metal ion.  Infrared spectra were recorded using a Beckman 4260 double-beam grat-  ing spectrophotometer. Samples for infrared analysis were prepared by mix-  ing 1 mg of freeze-dried humic material with 300 mg of pre-dried and pulver-  ized spectroscopic-grade KBr. The KBr pellets were prepared using the precau-  tions outlined by Stevenson and Goh (1972) for eliminating moisture inter-  ference. Spectra were obtained on both heated and unheated pellets (Steven-  son and Goh, 1974).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Spectra of metal-fulvate complexes    Infrared spectra of the fulvic acid and its K*-salts at pH 5 and 10 are shown  in Fig. 1. Major absorption bands for the fully protonated fulvic acid (Fig. 1~4)  occur at 3400 cm-' (primarily O--H stretching), from 2680--2580 cm-1)  strongly H-bonded OH of COOH), 1730 cm-' (C=O stretching of COOH and  ketones), 1630 cm-' (aromatic C= C, strongly H-bonded C=O, C= C conjugated  with C=O, or a combination of these), 1400 cm-1 (C--H deformation of    __i  z         ~     ,   i      ,     i     ,     i     ,     i     ,     i     ,  3410  I        i  4000         3000      2200      1700       '1300       900        500  FREQUENCY, CM-~    Fig. 1. Infrared spectra of fulvic acid and its Ksalts. A. Original sample; B. Partial K  salt, pH 5;C. K*-salt, pH 10.    198    aliphatic groups), and 1210 cm-~ (C--O stretching and OH deformation of  COOH). The shoulder at 2980 cm-~ can be assigned to aliphatic C--H stretch-  ing; the one at 1100 cm-~ to OH deformation and C--O stretching of phenolic  and alcoholic OH groups.  Conversion of COOH to CO0- (Fig. 1, A and C) led to the expected loss of  absorption at 1730 cm-~ (C=O of COOH) and 1200 (C--O stretching and OH  deformation of COOH). The concomitant reduction at 2680--2580 cm-1 con-  firms that absorption in this region was due to OH stretching of H-bonded  carboxylic acids (see Bellamy, 1975). Neutralization of COOH was accom-  panied by the appearance of characteristic bands due to asymmetric and sym-  metric stretching of CO0- near 1610 and 1400 cm-1, respectively. At complete  neutralization (Fig. 1, C), absorption in these regions was centered at 1598  and 1395 cm- 1, respectively.  Spectra of the complexes with Cu2 Pb2 and Ca2are shown in Figs. 2--4.    _  1    4000    F    ~   - T    r  34Z0  i    t  " "~  ......  3+  .....  T          t  --~  /  ,V,,, W    /  l  ',, j AVe,' X._H/ 1  \tU " \/,'  140:3    3(~:1  '     '     '     , ~J67~,           ,     ,     ,  2200    1700    13~00900            5LOO  FREQUENCY, CM-1    Fig. 2. Infrared spectra of Cu2-fulvic acid complexes. R = meq. Cu2meq. acidic H (COOH).  A. R = 0.05; B. R = 0.10;C. R = 0.20; D. R = 0.40; E. R ffi 0.60; F. R = 0.80; G. R = 1.00;  H. R = 1.50.    Fig. 4. Infrared spectra of Ca2+--fulvic acid complexes. R ffi meq. Ca2+/meq. acidic H+  (COOH).  A. R = 0.10;B. R = 0.20;C. R = 0.30; D. R = 0.40;E. R = 0.60;F. R = 0.75;G. R = 1.00;  H. R = 1.50.    199    m    '       I     '     I           I           I           I           I  ,a~              - B f  ,,,o      ,,                       CD~  H_J~  3420                            kJ  160o    I       i       I       ,       I       i       I       ~       I       ,       I  4000      3000    2200    1700    1300     900     500  FREQUENCY, CM4    Fig. 3. Infrared spectra of Pb2+--fulvic acid complexes. R = meq. Pb2+/meq. acidic H (COOH).  A. R = 0.10; B. R -- 0.20;C. R = 0.30; D. R -- 0.40; E. R = 0.60; F. R -- 0.75; G. R = 1.00;  H. R = 1.50.    T  IJJ  U  Z  I--  -7  Z  n-  l---    4000    3000    2200    1700     1300  FREQUENCY, CM-1    900    500    200    Because the metal ions were added to the fulvic acid at pH 5.0, the reference  to which the metal complexes must be compared is the spectrum of the  partial K+-salt (Fig. 1, B). Reactions leading to the formation of metal com-  plexes were depicted earlier by reactions 1--4.  For the 3450--3000 cm-~ region, the strong band centered at 3420 cm-~  was progressively enhanced with and increase in the amount of metal-ion  added. This suggests that part of the absorption at 3420 cm-~ was due to hy-  dration water of the metal in 1 : 1 complexes, such as the following.  COO  /M ( H2O)n  0    A major difference between spectra of the three metal complexes is that  the shoulder at 3280 cm-~ was less pronounced for the Cu~and Pb2+ com-  plexes (Figs. 2 and 3) than for the Ca2+ complexes (Fig. 4). This indicates  that phenolic and/or alcoholic OH groups (O--H stretching band near 3280  cm-~) participated along with COOH in complexing of Cu2* and Pb2* (forma-    hi  (9  Z  &lt;  I'--  I--  1,11  I--      .........  4--     ~  .......  ..~i "~il  .....  ~'  /~,~/2860    i  I'/ 2930         2340  t   '  \  i '~'         ii  2930          '  ,            ,/  3460    i             I    ---~        i  4000        3000     22OO    WAV~ENGTH, ~M    ~4  ../   780   --.   -A""    ~Y         1390  ~  /i,I        1130  I   .  1620J  ",.,,  '7  I    I  I ,    i  I,    '  i   ,i  //\  il)    '\~  /'        1130  1  \  1620  I        I        I        L  ' 1700      1300  FREQUENCY, CM-~      ......  i    .~       ~,~ "--c"     I  I  i  / "~'~v''~          ~1-~-~ i  ,r"    800   ~v~-- D/"7    i  !,  i  i  L        ~_      l        x___a  900          500    Fig. 5. Infrared spectra of Cu;+--fulvic acid complexes whose pellets were heated at 100  for 24 h. R = meq. Cu2+/meq. acidic H+ (COOH).  A. R = 0.20;B. R = 0.40; C. R = 0.80; D. R = 1.25.    201    tion of salicylate-like structures). Tan et al. (1971) observed a shift in OH ab-  sorption from 3500 cm-~ to 3200 cm-~ for a zinc-fulvate preparation, which  was taken as evidence for the formation of coordinate covalent linkages.  The effect of hygroscopic water on absorption near 3420 cm-~ was in-  vestigated by obtaining spectra on pellets heated at 100 for 24 h (Steven-  son and Goh, 1974). Results for the Cu~+ and Pb~+ complexes are shown in  Figs. 5 and 6, respectively. Absorption at 3420 cm-~, although somewhat  reduced, was still pronounced, thereby confirming the formation of aquo-  complexes between the metal and fulvic acid. Only minimal changes were ob-  served when pellets of the Ca~complexes were heated.    %  3440    WAVELENGTH ,~,~    i             .\,       ~34o  ',       /~   2930           ~ ~                                                     8~0 ~  '        J  ", 3440  "    ~'~                                                     "~.     B  ,                            ,            ,, ,!~o   , r,, ',,  '   '   "/",4'                     ' '~  ,' " ~t3~'o '~"  ,~   "~ "~  I~"'  /     &lt;_-~,.,      ~,,',  ~,~o;/"t',,,..~,...~  LU , , , kj                              "~" \~                  z  ......  D  I                                                                        ,    / ,   !  I                  j J J-%'           L    ,, \,' ,  i ~,,,          .~' ,/                           \    I    ,"     ~      800   "\   ~ G  /    2930                             '   '  / \~      "'12"40 "~'~'                                        ~=~'~',--,, ',  ,,  ,,                   1090    I  I  i  r    !      j    iJ~  ~,/~600  4000           3000            2200        1700        1300         900         500  FREOUENCY, cM~    Fig. 6. Infrared spectra of Pb; +--fulvic acid complexes whose pellets were heated at 100  for 24 h. R = meq. Pb2*/meq. acidic H* (COOH).  A. R = 0.20; B. R = 0.30;C. R = 0.40; D. R = 0.60;E. R -- 0.75;F. R = 1.00;G. R = 1.50.    Absorption bands due to C--H stretching of aliphatic CH2 and CH3 groups  near 2900 cm-1 are visible in spectra of the metal complexes. A peculiarity is  observed for Cu2 where spectra for the complexes at the low additions  (Fig. 2, B--D) showed unusually pronounced absorption near 2940 cm-1,    202    with two strong bands being evident at 2910 and 2860 cm-1. At the higher  Cu2 + additions, absorption was reduced and the two bands appeared as  shoulders superimposed on the broad band at 3420 cm-1. This effect was  even more pronounced in spectra of the heated pellets (Fig. 5). Possible in-  terpretations of this behavior include: (1) an initial reduction in OH-absorp-  tion in the 3300--3100 cm-1 region resulted in unmasking of C--H absorption  bands, which were again masked at higher amounts of Cu2+ due to OH-ab-  sorption originating from hydration water of the metal; and (2) a chemical  modification occurred in the fulvic acid through its interaction with Cu~ *,  such as transfer of a proton from an oxygen atom to a carbon atom with an  increase in the number of aliphatic groups and hence absorption near 2900  cm-1. The second explanation fails to account for the less intense C--H ab-  sorption bands at the high Cu2 additions. The apparent order of reaction of  the metals with OH groups was Cu2.~ Pb2+ &gt;&gt; Ca2+.  Spectra of the heated samples (Figs. 5 and 6) show a pronounced band at  2340 cm-1. This band has been assigned to CO2. There was no evidence for  loss of C=O absorption at 1720 cm-', indicating little decarboxylation of  COOH groups. An alternate source of the COs is from HCO~ held to or  bound to the fulvic acid, a subject now under investigation. The presence of  bands due to COs is evident in spectra of the fungal humic acids examined by  Russell et al. (1980), where preformed pellets were heated at 150 for 16 h  to remove adsorbed moisture.  Absorption in the 1800--1400 cm-1 region was similar for all complexes  (Figs. 2--4), namely, a progressive decrease in C= O absorption near 1720 cm-  and a simultaneous increase in CO0- absorption near 1610 cm-~ and 1400  cm-~. Absorption at 1720 cm-~ was not decreased to the same extent as for  the Ksalt at pH 10 (Fig. 1, C). Apparently, not all COOH groups had reacted  with the metal-ions. Evidence in support of this conclusion is provided by  changes in the 1260--1220 cm-~ region (C-O stretching and O--H deforma-  tion of COOH groups), where reduction in absorption was somewhat less for  the metal complexes than for the K*-salt (pH 10). Spectra of the heated pel-  lets gave similar results. One explanation for this effect is that protons com-  pete favorably with metals for COOH groups (additions were made at pH 5.0);  a second is that the stereochemical arrangement of some COOH groups was  unfavorable for complex formation. Indeed, the spectrum of a Cu2complex  (not shown) obtained by passing the humic material through a cation-ex-  change resin saturated with Cu~still showed strong residual absorption at  1720 cm-~. Rashid (1971) reported that about one third of the COOH groups  in humic materials existed in "non-chelating" forms. Another factor to con-  sider is that precipitation of fulvic acid occurred at the higher levels of metal-  ion additions, with possible masking of complexing sites.  The incomplete reduction of the 1720 cm"' band implies that fewer COO-  groups should be revealed in spectra of the metal complexes as compared to  the Ksalt at pH 10. This was not the case. In fact, absorption bands for  COO- groups near 1610 and 1400 cm-~ were stronger and sharper in spectra    203    of the Cu2 Pb2 and Ca2complexes than for the Ksalt, especially for  asymmetrical stretching of CO0- at 1610 cm-~. This effect was particularly  pronounced at the higher levels of metal-ion additions, where the increased  absorption at 1610 cm-1 appeared to be greater than could be accounted for  by conversion of COOH to COO- (as indicated by reduction of the C=O band  at 1710 cm-~). Also, in comparison to the spectra of the Ksalt (pH 10), the  band at 1610 cm-1 was strong in relation to the one at 1400 cm-1.  These observations indicate that groups other than COOH had reacted with  the metal ions, particularly Cu~ Absorption in the 1660--1600 cm-~ region  may be due in part to conjugated ketonic structures (Theng and Posner,  1967; Stevenson and Goh, 1971). These structures are known to form com-  plexes with transition metal ions.  o     o           OH  .....  o                    O/M'O  II      II   ~   I      II   + ~             I!      ii      H+  ~C\cH~C~       7"C~CH/C~"    2 M2+ ~J'C&lt;&lt;"cH'C ~              +    OH     0                          0/M ~0  I      II     4- M24" ~   Ii     !1  /c c" ...c ~.                  /C~cH. c~    +H+    The C= O group in conjugated ketones, when weakened by resonance be-  tween C--O--M and C=O--M, fall in the frequency ranges of 1620--1610 cm-~  and 1390--1309 cm-~ (Bellamy, 1975). In the spectra reported herein, fre-  quency shifts in these two regions were hardly detectable due to the breadth  of absorption. Nevertheless, the band at 1810 cm-1 for the Cu2complexes  showed a shift to a lower frequency that could be attributed to complexing  by C=O (Fig. 2). The band centered at 1400 cm for the control spectrum  (Fig. 1, B) initially shifted to 1390 and 1385 cm-1 for the Cu2complexes  and then shifted back to 1400 cm-~ as more Cu2was added {Fig. 2, B--D).  Similar shifts are evident in spectra of the Ca~complexes (Fig. 4, A--H); for  the Pb2complexes, absorption initially centered at 1385 cm-1 was shifted  only as far as 1390 cm-1 (Fig. 3, A--H). An explanation for these findings is  that ketonic structures are among the first to form complexes with metal-  ions. This would account for the unusually strong intensity of the 1610 cm-~  band relative to the one at 1710 cm-~ and for the shift of the 1400 cm-~  band to 1385 cm-~. With increasing amounts of metal ions, metal-carboxylate  bonds are formed, thereby enhancing absorption near 1610 cm-~.  The asymmetric stretching vibration of COO- in most ionic bonds (e.g.,  with Na K and alkaline earth cations) occurs in the 1630--1575 cm-~  region; when coordinate linkages are formed with heavy metals (e.g., Cu2,  the frequency shifts to between 1650 and 1620 cm-~ (Nakamoto, 1963).  The position of the asymmetric absorption band has been used in soil-organic  studies to establish the ionic-covalent nature of metal-carboxylate linkages  (Banerjee and Mukherjee, 1972; Vinkler et al., 1976). Until the question of    204    the participation of ketonic groups in complexation has been resolved, spectral  changes in the 1610 and 1410 cm-1 regions cannot be used with certainty to  establish the ionic-covalent nature of metal-carboxylate linkages.  The pH was maintained at pH 5.0 during formation of the metal complexes  through additions of KOH (see reactions 1--4). At high levels of metal-ion ad-  ditions shifts in CO0- absorption frequencies could have resulted from the  formation of Ksalts in addition to complexes with the divalent cations.  A further complication of interpreting changes in the 1400 cm-1 band is  that carbonates absorb in this region (1450--1410 cm-1, strong intensity).  Carbonates could have been introduced with the base used for titration  (formation of the partial Ksalt) and during neutralization following the ad-  dition of metals (pH returned to 5.0). Carbonates also show a medium inten-  sity band in the 880--850 cm-1 region and it is possible that this is the source  of some of the absorption near these frequencies for the fulvic acid.  Bands in the 1150--1050 cm-1 region are assigned to O--H deformation  and C--O stretching of phenolic and/or alcoholic OH groups. For the Ksalt  (Fig. 1, C), absorption in this region was enhanced in comparison to the fully  protonated samples (Fig. 1, A). This was attributed to loss of absorption due  to C--O stretching and O--H deformation of COOH groups (1250--1200 cm-1  region). In as much as spectra of the metal complexes still showed absorption  at 1250--1200 cm-1 (incomplete dissociation of COOH groups), absorption at  1050--1150 cm-1 was not enhanced to the same extent. Absorption in this  region was more intense for the Ca2complexes (Fig. 4, E--H) than for Cu2 {Fig. 2, E--H); Pb~complexes exhibited an intermediate behavior (Fig. 3,  E--H). This confirms that the order of reaction of the three metal-cations with  phenolic and/or alcoholic OH groups was Cu2+ ~ Pb~+ &gt;~ Ca2+.  A small but sharp band near 1130 cm-1 was noticeable in spectra of the  Cu2and Pb2* complexes (Figs. 3 and 4); for the Ca2complexes (Fig. 5) the  band was visible only at low amounts of metal added, and it was absent in  spectra of the K+salts. Tan (1978) assigned a similar band to hydrated Cu2+  vibrations. In our study, which was carried out at pH 5, hydrolysis of the  metal was unlikely and the band can best be assigned to vibrations between  the metals and the oxygen of water molecules in 1:1 complexes, as described  earlier. The appearance of this band was not substantially changed in spectra  of heated pellets.  Broad absorption bands at lower frequencies (900--400 cm-~) are of un-  certain interpretations. A small broad band near 785--775 cm-~ was slightly  enhanced at high levels of metal ion additions, especially for Cu2 Absorp-  tion in this region can be assigned to C--H out-of-plane deformation of olefins  and/or C--H out-of-plane deformation of aromatic rings. As noted earlier,  carbonates absorb in this region although at higher frequencies (880--860  cm-~). PbCO3 shows only weak absorption at 840 cm-1 (Bellamy, 1975),  which may account for the slight difference in absorption in this region for  Cu2and Pb2{e.g., compare Figs. 5 and 6).    205    Spectra of metal-humate complexes    Infrared spectra of the Cu:and Ca2+ complexes with humic acid are  shown in Figs. 7 and 8, respectively. Spectra of the Pb2complexes were in-  termediate between those for Cu:and Ca2and are not reported. Consider-  able light scattering occurred in the 4000--2000 cm-1 region, particularly at  the higher levels of metal-ion additions. Attempts to eliminate this scatter-  ing by modification of pellet preparation parameters were unsuccessful, sug-  gesting that the effect was characteristic of the metal--humate complexes.  Due to the scattering phenomena, valid interpretations of changes in the  O--H region could not be made. Banerjee and Mukherjee (1972) found that  O--H adsorption frequencies in humic acids were strongly affected by metals  whereas Rashid (1971) failed to detect changes which could be attributed to  complexation.  A small band at 1855 cm-1, noticeable in the spectra of the humic acid  (Fig. 7, A) and attributed to cyclic anhydrides, was also observed in spectra of  the metal complexes. This band disappeared at high metal-ion additions, in-    40(::)0     3000    2200   1700    1300    900     500  FREQUENCY, CM4    Fig. 7. Infrared spectra of Cu:-humic acid complexes. The spectrum of the partial K  salt (pH 5.0) was similar to that of spectrum A, with the exception that the bands at  1375 and 1250 cm-1 were centered at 1400 and 1225 cm-1, respectively. R = meq. Cu2*/  meq. acidic H(COOH).  A. R = 0.10;B. R ffi 0.30;C. R = 0.50; D. R = 0.60;E. R = 0.80;F. R = 0.90;G. R = 1.00;  H.R =1.25;I.R =1.50.    206    ]    T    T--;:: 7J:(.- T ---w  ........  T-- '    I     ' ----V--~  .f  /~A "/    ,3420                           I 00    I  4000    L   J    i   i  _A__L_  I    J    I    I    f  3000    2200    1700     1300    900     500  FREQUENCY, CM4    Fig. 8. Infrared spectra of Ca:+--humic acid complexes. R = meq. Ca2meq. acidic H (COOH).  A. R = 0.10;B. R = 0.20; C. R = 0.30; D. R = 0.40;E. R = 0.75; F. R = 1.00; G. R = 1.50~    dicating that complexes may have been formed with COOH groups located at  adjacent positions on aromatic rings. The formation of phthalate-like metal  complexes in humic substances has been postulated by Schnitzer and Skinner  (1965) and Gamble et al. (1970).  As was.the case for the fulvic acid, the 1720 cm-~ band showed a slight  decrease in intensity with an increase in the amount of metal-ion added. Ab-  sorption was not lost to the same extent as for the Ksalt at pH 10 (see  Stevenson and Goh, 1971), suggesting incomplete reactions of COOH groups.  For all complexes, absorption at 1610 cm-1 was enhanced with an increase in  the amount of metal-ion added. Also, despite incomplete ionization of COOH  groups, absorption at 1610 cm-1 was more pronounced than was observed for  the Ksalt {spectrum not shown). Specifically, the band was broadened con-  siderably through increased absorption from 1550--1500 cm-', particularly  for the Cu2complexes {Fig. 7, F--I). In the case of the 1610 cm-1 band,  broadening in the direction of lower frequencies was less pronounced for  Cu2than for Ca2(or Pb2*). The broadening effect cannot be attributed to  absorbed moisture because no changes were observed when preformed pellets  were heated. Also, water absorbs closer to 1660 cm-~ rather than in the  1550--1500 cm-1 region. Although difficult to explain, this effect may be    207    due to C= O groups which absorb at lower frequencies through complexation  with metals, such as conjugated ketones (mentioned in the discussion of the  fulvic acid results). As with fulvic acid, spectral changes near 1610 cm-1 can-  not be properly interpreted in terms of metal--carboxylate linkages.  Another feature of spectra of the humic-acid--metal complexes is that the  intensity of the symmetric CO0- stretching band {1400 cm-I) was less than  for the Ksalt at pH 10 (spectrum not shown). This finding is consistent with  the observation that not all COOH groups had reacted and that other oxygen-  containing functional groups were probably involved in the binding of metal  ions.  Spectra were also obtained for the metal--humic-acid complexes using pre-  heated KBr pellets (100 in vacuo for seven days). As with the metal--  fulvate complexes, a sharp band was introduced for CO2 at 2330 cm-~, the  order for the complexes being Cu:+ &gt; Pb:+ &gt; Ca:+. A band presumed to be  C=O of anhydrides (1850 cm-1) was also introduced in some spectra. Changes  were also evident in the 800--400 cm-~ region, the significance of which will  require further study. Only minor changes, if any, were produced in the  1700--1000 cm-1 region, thereby confirming observations arrived at for the  unheated pellets.    REFERENCES    Banerjee, S.K. and Mukherjee, S.K., 1972. Studies on the infrared spectra of some divalent  transitional metal humates. J. Indian Soc. Soil Sci., 20: 91--94.  Bellamy, L.J., 1975. The Infrared Spectra of Complex Molecules. Wiley, New York, NY.  Gamble, D.S., Schnitzer, M. and Hoffman, I., 1970. Cu:+--fulvic acid chelation equilib-  rium in 0.1 M KC1 at 25.0. Can. J. Chem., 48: 3197--3204.  Nakamoto, K., 1963. Infrared Spectra of Inorganic and Coordination Compounds. Wiley,  New York, NY, 206 pp.  Rashid, M.A., 1971. Role of humic acids of marine origin and their different molecular  weight fractions in complexing di- and tri-valent metals. Soil Sci., 111 : 298--306.  Russell, J.D., Jones, D., Vaughan, D. and Fraser, A.R., 1980. A preliminary study of  fungal melanin by infrared spectroscopy. Geoderma, 24: 207--213.  Schnitzer, M. and Skinner, S.I.M., 1965. Organo-metallic interactions in soils, 4. Carboxyl  and hydroxyl groups in organic matter and metal-ion retention. Soil Sci., 99: 278--  284.  Stevenson, F.J., 1976. Stability constants of Cu2+, Pb2+, and Cd~+ complexes with humic  acids. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 665--672.  Stevenson, F.J. and Fitch, A., 1981. Reactions with organic matter. In: J.F. Loneragan,  A.D. Robson and R.D. Graham (Editors}, Copper in Soils and Plants. Academic Press,  New York, NY, pp. 69--95.  Stevenson, F.J. and Goh, K.M., 1971. Infrared spectra of humic acids and related sub-  stances. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 35: 471--483.  Stevenson, F.J. and Goh, K.M., 1972. Infrared spectra of humic and fulvic acids and their  methylated derivatives: evidence for non-specificity of analytical methods for oxygen-  containing functional groups. Soil Sci., 113 : 334--345.  Stevenson, F.J. and Goh, K.M., 1974. Infrared spectra of humic acids: elimination of in-  terference due to hygroscopic moisture and structural changes accompanying heating  with KBr. Soil Sci., 117: 34--41.    208    Tan, K.H., 1978. Formation of metal-humic acid complexes by titration and their charac-  terization by differential thermal analysis and infrared spectroscopy. Soil Biol. Biochem  10: 123--129.  Tan, K.H., King, L.D. and Morris, H.D., 1971. Complex reactions of zinc with organic  matter extracted from sewage sludge. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 748--752.  Theng, B.K.G. and Posner, A.M., 1967. Nature of the carbonyl group in soil humic acid.  Soil Sci., 104: 191--201.  Van Dijk, H., 1971. Cation binding by humic acids. Geoderma, 5: 53--67.  Vinkler, P., Lakatos, B. and Meisel, J., 1976. Infrared spectroscopic investigations of  humic substances and their metal complexes. Geoderma, 15: 231--242.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractAn infrared spectroscopic investigation of the complexes of Cu2+, Pb2+, and Ca2+ with humic and fulvic acids demonstrated the participation of OH and CO groups in addition to COOH in the binding of heavy-metal cations. The degree to which metal-carboxylate linkages are ionic or covalent cannot be accurately determined from the positions of antisymmetric and symmetric carboxylate stretching vibrations due to interference from covalent bonding with other groups. The apparent order of the reaction of three divalent cations with humic and fulvic acids was Cu2+ &gt; Pb2+ &gt; Ca2+. 