Geoderma, 32 (1984) 319--327                                                     319  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PHOSPHATE ADSORPTION BY DARK ALKALINE VERTISOLS IN  GREECE    ANASTASIOS E. NYCHAS.1 and CONSTANTINOS S. KOSMAS.1  Department of Soils and Agricultural Chemistry, A thcns Faculty of Agriculture, Athens  (Greece)  Department of Agricultural Research, Ministry of Agriculture, Athens (Greece)  (Received April 14, 1982; revised version accepted May 16, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Nychas, A.E. and Kosmas, C.S., 1984. Phosphate adsorption by dark alkaline vertisols in  Greece. Geoderma, 32: 319--327.    Phosphorus adsorption isotherms are presented for samples from agricultural areas in  central Greece. The soils contain montmorillonitic clays, have high exchange capacities  and range in pH from 6.8 to 8.1. The amounts of P adsorption are high for surface and  subsurface samples and are comparable to the adsorption observed in acid kaolinitic soils.  The fit of the Freundlich equation to the experimental data was significantly improved  when NaHCO3 extractable P was used as an estimate of the labile soil P to account for P  already adsorbed in the soil. No conclusive relationship was established between the  Freundlich parameters and selected soil properties though in some cases a values (capacity  term) increased with increasing organic carbon content.    INTRODUCTION    The problem of relating the availability of soil phosphorus to plants and  soil characteristics is well recognized. Soil pH and the contents of iron, alu-  minum, calcium carbonate and organic matter are factors affecting immobi-  lization of soluble P applied to soil through adsorption and/or precipitation  reactions (Olsen et al., 1977; Velayutham, 1980). Thus, knowledge of behav-  ior of P in soils is of primary importance in efficient use of P fertilizers, espe-  cially in areas of intensive agriculture where soil characteristics favour P re-  tention or fixation (Ballard and Fiskell, 1974; Olsen et al., 1977; Kunishi  and Vickers, 1980).  In central Greece, one such area contains alkaline dark clays, Vertisols,  cultivated mainly for sugar beets, cotton and tomatoes. The presence of 2:1  clays and wetting---drying cycles cause turning and mixing of the soil mate-    *1Present  address:  CEC, Directorate General of Agriculture, Brussel, Belgium; and  Agronomy Dept., Purdue University, W. Lafayette, Indiana, respectively.    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    320    rial within the soil profile at least to a depth of 50 cm (Soil Survey Staff,  1975); therefore adsorption of P by deeper soil horizons is important.  This paper reports P retention/adsorption throughout the profiles of three  alkaline Vertisols. Adsorption is evaluated using phosphate equilibration  techniques to obtain isotherms. An attempt is also made to relate adsorption  to physical and chemical characteristics of the soils.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils and analyses    Samples from all horizons down to 150 cm depth of 3 Vertisols from cen-  tral Greece were used in this study: a Typic Chromoxerert (D1) and a Typic  Pelloxerert (D2) from Domokos and a Typic Chromoxerert (K1) from  Karditsa agricultural areas. Brief profile descriptions are given in Table I.  Air~lried subsamples passing a 2-mm sieve were used for all analyses, and  analytical results were corrected to an oven-dry basis. Particle-size distribu-  tion was determined using the hydrometer method (Day, 1965). Soil pH was  measured with a glass electrode of a Beckman pH meter at a soil/water ratio  of 1:1 (Peech, 1965). Organic carbon was determined with the Walkley-  Black wet combustion method (Allison, 1965). Calcium carbonate was mea-  sured with the volumetric calcimetric method (Allison and Moodie, 1965).  The NH4OAc method at pH 7 was employed for cation exchange capacity  (Chapman, 1965). Iron and aluminum were extracted with NH4OAc at pH  4.8 (McLean, 1965) and iron also with citrate~iithionite (Holmgren, 1967).  Available P was extracted with 0.5 N NaHCO3 (Olsen and Dean, 1965) and  Ca, Mg, K and Na were extracted with NH4OAc at pH 7.0 (Chapman, 1965).  For references to the above methods, see Black (1965) with the exception of  the citrate~lithionite iron extraction (Holmgren, 1967).    Phosphate adsorption    Phosphate adsorption was studied by equilibrating duplicate 5-g soil  samples with 50 ml of Ca(HzPO4)2 solutions in 0.01 M CaC12, with various P  concentrations ranging from 0 to 60 ppm corresponding with additions of  0--600 ug P/g soil material (0--1.92 pmol/ml and 0--19.20 pmol/g soil mate-  rial, respectively). A 7&lt;tay equilibration period was established from a pre-  liminary study, at the end of which an apparent equilibrium was assumed to  have been reached. Samples were shaken for 3 h every day using a mechani-  cal end-to-end shaker. The quantity of P retained by the soil sample was cal-  culated from the difference of P concentration in the solution before and  after the equilibration. Phosphorus in the equilibrium solution (ES) was mea-  sured colorimetrically (Murphy and Riley, 1962).    TABLEI    Morphology and classification of the soils studied    Horizon    Depth       Predominant  Texture*'  (cm)        Munsell color  (moist)    Structure* '    Consistence*' Lower*'  (moist)       boundary    Carbonates*'    Other.2    Dr, Typic Chromoxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap           0-- 28    IOYR 3/3     C          2 m sbk  Ct           28-- 60    IOYR 4/4     C          2 m sbk  C2           60--140    IOYR 3/3     C           3 c abk    fi                c, s          --  fi             g, s        --  efi            g, s        e    few fine distinct mottles  slickensides and common  fine distinct mottles    C3          140+        IOYR 3/3     C           3 c abk  D~, Typic Pelloxerert, very fine, montmorillonitic, thermic  Ap          0-- 15   IOYR 3/1    C         2 m gr  C,           15-- 42    IOYR 3/1     C           2 m abk  C2           42--100    IOYR 3/1     C           3 c abk    C3          100+        IOYR 4/4     C  Kt, Typic Chromoxerert, very fine, mixed,  Ap             0-- 25    IOYR 3/2     C  C,            25-- 60    IOYR 3/3     C  C2             60-- 90     IOYR 3/3      C  C3             90--125     IOYR 3/2      C  C,          125+         IOYR 3/2     CL    thermic    efi  vfi              c, s  vfi            g, s  efi              c, s    2 c abk       vfi    es    e  es    slickensides and common  fine distinct mottles    2 m abk      fi             c, s        e  3 m abk      fi             g, s        e  3 c sbk        vfi             g, s         e              slickensides  2 m sbk       fi              c, s         e              slickensides  massive       fi                         e             slickensides    *' Symbols used according to abbreviations given by Soil Survey Staff (1951).  *:All soils are well--moderately-well drained and have been developed on alluvial deposits derived from basic igneous rocks and occur-  ring on level slopes.    322    Evaluation of adsorption data    For the evaluation of the adsorption data, the Freundlich-equation (1)  was employed, modified (2) in order to take into account the phosphorus al-  ready adsorbed in the soil (Fitter and Sutton, 1975):  x /m = acb                                                         ( 1 )    x/m + q = acb                                                     (2)    where: x/m = amount of P experimentally adsorbed (pg P/g soil sample); q =  amount of labile pool of native soil P (~g P/g soil); c = P concentration in ES  (/~g P/ml) and a, b = Freundlich constants.  The NaHCO3 extractable P was used as an estimate of q (Nychas, 1982).  Statistical evaluation was done according to Steel and Torrie (1960).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Physical and chemical properties of the soil samples    Physical and chemical properties of the samples are given in Table II.  Samples from all depths were rich in clay (&gt;55%) dominated by montmoril-  lonite (verified by X-ray and DTA analysis). Soils D1 and D2 were developed  in thick alluvial deposits which resulted from weathering of basic igneous  rocks rich in Mg, whereas soil K1 was developed on alluvial deposits of sedi-  mentary origin relatively rich in Ca. Phosphorus extracted in NaHCO3 was  relatively low throughout the profiles but surface samples contained more  than deeper ones, probably because of recently applied phosphorus fertil-  izers.    Phosphate adsorption isotherms    Plots of x/m against c yielded the typical adsorption isotherms (T = 25C)  shown in Fig. 1, where the points represent averages of 2--3 replicates. (Devi-  ation around the mean value did not exceed + 3%). The terms "adsorbed P"  for x/m and "adsorption" for P retention by the soils from the ES, are used  throughout the following discussion.  The three soils gave similar shaped isotherms for samples from all profiles  and depths. Similarities within each profile were more striking, especially at  low c values. The figures indicate a rather high P adsorption at common fer-  tilizer rates which do not exceed 250 kg P2Os/ha in the agricultural areas in  question. Hence large quantities of phosphorus fertilizers need to be added  to maintain a satisfactory phosphate activity in soil solution.  Limited information is available in the literature on adsorption of P by alo  kaline montmorillonitic soils in contrast with that available for acid kaolinit-  ic soils. Recently, Burnham and Lopez-Hernandez (1982), studying phos-    TABLE I!  Selected physical and chemical properties of the soils studied. Percentages refer to CaCO3 and organic-matter-free fine earth, &lt; 2 mm    Sample        pH      Silta     Clayb   Organic CaCO3  CEC    Extractable cations           NaHCO3  NH4OAc      Citrate-  depth       (1:1)   (%)    (%)    C      (%)           (meq./100 g)             P       (pH 4.8)     dithionite  (cm)                                (%)                                               (ppm)                 Fe  Ca    Mg    K     Na               A1     Fe     (%)    Soil Dz  0--30      8.0      16.4    67.4     1.06      0       57.4     31.10  24.89  0.36   0.70    8.4      38.5   1.8    0.33  30--70      8.1      14.8     70.4     0.90      0       55.5     29.00  23.00  0.12   0.74    5.6      51.5   2.1    0.26  70--120      8.0      13.4     73.4    0.89      2.0    60.3     31.50  30.85  0.20   2.70    4.0      42.0   3.0    0.53  120--150      8.2      16.2     71.4     0.73      2.4     56.7     27.00  31.25  0.34   3.20    2.8      48.5   2.0    0.55    Soil D2  0--15      8.0      16.7     60.1     0.93      0       68.4     28.65  41.00  0.36   1.40   13.0       30.1   2.2     0.46  15--42      8.4      12.8     66.4     1.25      0       70.0     24.75  44.20  0.22   2.50     3.0       27.4   1.8     0.30  42--99      8.7      11.4    71.8     0.77      2.8     59.6     20.15  40.10  0.20   5.20    3.6      30.3   2.0    0.33  99--141      8.1       9.8     75.0    0.63     13.6     56.0     21.00  36.33  0.24   7.20    2.0      30.5   4.1     1.66    Soil KI  0-- 25     7.1      22.0    61.3    0.82     7.3    32.4    28.20   5.64  1.56   0.70    9.3      30.1   2.3    0.28  25-- 50      7.1      25.8     56.2     0.78      8.2     34.0     29.50   6.04  0.68   0.90    6.2      28.0   2.2    0.32  50-- 87      7.0      21.0    67.3     0.92      7.3     35.2     31.25   4.08  0.48   0.90    4.1      46.0   2.6    0.32  87--130      6.8      23.4     59.3     0.56      2.6     36.0     29.80   6.67  0.20   0.60    2.6      53.0   2.6    0.51    aDiameter 0.05--0.002 mm; bdiameter &lt;0.002 mm.    O  bD  Oa    324    400    300    200    100    0  4.00    300  0   200  01  Z1-   100  E  0    400    300    200    100    0  0    Soil KI    4  O~  BAO    o  []  0 /,    0 n    D~    a : 0-25 cm  o : 25-50  o : 50-87  4 : 87-130    Soil D1  %  o                I              I  r  ~ao  4  Z~D  A 0-30 c m   @                                        [] : 30-70  o 70-120                                          - 120-150  t     4O  El  0  []  i n         ~                            a : 0-15 cm  to      AO                              O : 15-42  6                                     O : 42-9999_141      ,]  hO~                                       :   I  i  ;  ,  I  i  I  ,  F  ,  {  ,  I  ....  I  , ~__.~ ,  1  , I ~1  ,  I  ,  I  4      8      12     16     20    24     28    32  C (lag P/ml)    Fig. 1. Phosphate adsorption isotherms for the soils studied (25C).    phate retention in different taxonomic classes concluded that sorption in 22  surface samples from Pellusterts of Venezuela was very high. Those Vertisols,  however, also contained significant levels of extractable aluminum, and only  a single-point sorption index was used (Bache and Williams, 1971) making  comparison impossible.    325    Adsorption parameters evaluated by the modified Freundlich equation    The values of a and b were determined with regression analysis using eq.  2 (Table III). Fitter and Sutton (1975), studying this equation with 29 acid  and neutral to calcareous soils, used resin-extractable P as a measure of na-  tive labile P, in order to improve the fit of phosphate sorption data to the  Freundlich adsorption isotherm. Nychas (1982), working with ten alkaline  surface soils, concluded that the fit was also improved when NaHCO3-  extractable P values were used for q.  Use of NaHCO3-extractable P in this work resulted in similar results, as  the coefficients of determination were in no case lower for eq. 2 compared  to those for eq. 1. Further analyses showed statistical significance at the  0.01 probability level (t-test for comparison of r2, means of paired observa-  tions t = 4.21, ttab = 3.11, 11 degrees of freedom).    TABLE III  Freundlich constants a, b and coefficients of determination, r:, for the best fit of the  data to eq. 2    Soils studied    Sample depth    a                  b                 r:  Soil DI              0-- 30          98.07           0.432             0.997  30-- 70          92.07           0.451             0.994  70--120          76.38           0.488             0.995  120--150          67.31           0.498             0.993    Soil D2    Soil D3    o- 15          64.69           0.425             0.990  15--  40                     90.30                       0.554                          0.998  40--100          53.23           0.490             0.994  100-140         112.00           0.494             0.994    o- 25        48.49            0.529            0.991  25-  50                  60.44                          0.508                          0.990  50-  90                  43.07                          0.573                          0.997  90-130                  82.29                          0.509                          0.997    Relationship between adsorption parameters and soil properties    The Freundlich parameter a is in fact a capacity factor, corresponding to  the amount of adsorbed P needed to maintain c at 1 concentration unit  (Shayan and Davey, 1978). On this basis a relationship between a and vari-  ous soil characteristics affecting P adsorption could be expected. Recently,  Nychas (1982) reported a significant positive correlation between a and  organic matter content of surface samples of alkaline soils of Greece. No    326    such relationship was established in this work when all samples were con-  sidered, underlining the complex nature and different mechanisms of P  adsorption as well as the many soil factors involved. The limited number of  samples within each soil profile did not allow either for any conclusive re-  lationship to appear when the three soils were examined separately. In soils  D1 and D2, however, a values generally increased with increased organic car-  bon content. The high a-value for the deepest sample of soil D: with the  lowest organic C content, may be explained by its higher CaCO3 and iron  contents.  The exponent of the Freundlich equation, b, being the slope of the loga-  rithmic plot of P adsorbed against P concentration in the ES (Q/I relation),  may be related to changes in the chemical potential of the adsorbed and  solution phases of phosphate (Bache and Williams, 1971). Fitter and Sutton  (1975), thinking of this parameter indeed as a function of the sorption pro-  cess, found it to be positively related to the exchangeable A1 (log A1) in acid  soils and to exchangeable Ca(log Ca) in neutral and calcareous soils, some-  thing which was not confirmed in this work. The authors believe, however,  that similar relationships of b with various soil characteristics should be  interpreted with caution as b by its definition represents both extensive (Q)  and intensive (I) parameters.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENT    The assistance of Mrs. Georgia Lachanas-Nychas in preparing the manu-  script is gratefully acknowledged.    REFERENCES    Bache, B.W. and Williams, E.G., 1971. A phosphate sorption index for soils. J. Soil Sci.,  22: 289--301.  Ballard, B. and Fiskell, J.G., 1974. Phosphorus retention in coastal plain forest soils, I.  Relationship to soll properties. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 250--255.  Black, C.A. (Editor), 1965. Methods of Soil Analysis--Agronomy, 9. Am. Soc. Agron.,  Madison, U.S.A.  Burnham, C.P. and Lopez-Hernandez, D., 1982. Phosphate retention in different Soil  Taxonomic Classes. Soil Sci., 134: 376--380.  Fitter, A.H. and Sutton, P.D., 1975. The use of the Freundlich-isotherm for soil phos-  phate sorption data. J. Soil Sci., 26: 241--246.  Holmgren, G.G.S., 1967. A rapid citrate-dithionite extractable iron procedure. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 31: 210--211.  Kunishi, H.M. and Vickers, J.C., 1980. Adsorption curves and phosphorus requirements  of acid soils. Soil Sci., 129: 28--35.  Murphy, J. and Riley, J.P., 1962. A modified single solution method for the determina-  tion of phosphate in natural waters. Anal. Chlm. Acta, 27: 31--36.  Nychas, A., 1982. Phosphate sorption by Greek alkaline soils evaluated with a modified  Freundlich~quation. Pflanzenern~hr. Bodenkd., 145: 593--599.  Olsen, S.R., Bowman, R.A. and Watanabe, F.S., 1977. Behavior of phosphorus in the  soil and interactions with other nutrients. Phosphorus Agric., 70: 31--46.    327    Shayan, A. and Davey, B.G., 1978. A universal dimensionless phosphate adsorption iso-  therm for soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 878--882.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Dep. Agriculture Handbook, 18:  136--141.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Mak-  ing and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436.  Steel, R.G.D. and Torrie, J.H., 1960. Principles and Procedures of Statistics. McGraw-  Hill, New York-Toronto-London.  Velayutham, M., 1980. The problem of phosphate fixation by minerals and soil col-  loids. Phosphorus Agric., 77: 1--8.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractPhosphorus adsorption isotherms are presented for samples from agricultural areas in central Greece. The soils contain montmorillonitic clays, have high exchange capacities and range in pH from 6.8 to 8.1. The amounts of P adsorption are high for surface and subsurface samples and are comparable to the adsorption observed in acid kaolinitic soils. The fit of the Freundlich equation to the experimental data was significantly improved when NaHCO3 extractable P was used as an estimate of the labile soil P to account for P already adsorbed in the soil. No conclusive relationship was established between the Freundlich parameters and selected soil properties though in some cases a values (capacity term) increased with increasing organic carbon content.