Geoderma, 31 (1983) 151--162                                                  151  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE DETERMINATION OF 1,2-DICARBOXYLATE STRUCTURES IN  HUMIC ACID BY FLUORESCEIN FORMATION    SHIGEMITSU ARAI and KYOICHI KUMADA  Faculty of Agriculture, Nagoya University, Nagoya, 464 (Japan)  (Received July 6, 1982; accepted November 30, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Arai, S, and Kumada, K., 1983. The determination of 1,2-dicarboxylate structures in  humic acid by fluorescein formation. Geoderma, 31: 151--162.    To detect and quantify 1,2-dicarboxylate structures in humic acid, a chemical reaction  forming fluoresceins from 1,2-dicarboxylates and resorcinol was tested. Resorcinol re-  acted with humic acid to form products having absorption maxima at about 490 nm. A  procedure was then developed for quantitative analysis of the radicals. Eight humic acid  samples tested contained 0.4--1.0 mmol/g of 1,2-dicarboxylate structures. The 1,2-Di-  carboxylates detected in humic acid were considered as ophthalate homologs.    INTRODUCTION    Various kinds of functional groups of soil organic matter have attracted  attention as factors governing chemical or physical processes in soil. Exten-  sive data are available on the content of functional groups in humic and ful-  vic acids, but little is known about their arrangement in the molecules. In-  formation of this type is considered necessary for an understanding of the  reactions of organic matter in soils.  The objective of this report is to identify 1,2&lt;iicarboxylate units in humic  acids by application of Feigl's method. Feigl (1961) described a qualitative  test for detecting 1,2-dicarboxylates, utilizing a reaction in which 1,2-dicar-  boxylates condense with resorcinol to produce fluoresceins. Several condi-  tions were examined for the modification of this method for quantitative  analysis, and the amounts of 1,2-dicarboxylates of humic acids were spec-  trophotometrically and fluorometrically compared with those of model  compounds.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Materials    Eight humic acid samples which belong to A, B, Rp and P types, ac-    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    152    cording to Kumada's classification (Kumada et al., 1967), were used. Their  names, types and origins are as follows:  Shitara:              A type, kuroboku or humic non-allophanic soil  (A horizon), approximate equivalent suborder in U.S.  classification, Umbrept.  Inogashira:           A type, humic allophane soil (A), Andept.  Kuragari:             B type, acid brown forest soil (A), Umbrept.  Kinshozan F:         B type, rendzina-like soil (A), Rendoll?  Higashiyama H/A:    B type, red-yellow soil (H/A), Ochrept.  Sanage:              Rp type, grey lowland paddy soil (Ap), Aquent?  Kinshozan OH:       Rp type, rendzina-like soil (A), Rendoll?  Tsubame:            P type, muck soil (humic buried layer)?  All samples were described in a previous report (Arai and Kumada, 1977).  Humic acid samples were extracted with 0.1 N NaOH, with the exception of  Kinshozan F, which was extracted with 0.1 N NaF. In order to obtain humic  acid in solution, a powdered sample of humic acid was dissolved in 0.1 N  NaOH and purified by passage through ion exchange resins (IR 120 B and  IRA 400).  Model compounds tested were o-phthalic, succinic, 1,2,3-propanetricar-  boxylic, maleic, glutaric, 1,3,5-pentanetricarboxylic, malonic, malic, tartaric,  and citric acids. They were commercially obtained and of analytical grade.  Fluorescein and succinylfluorescein were used as models of reaction prod-  ucts.    Modification of the original method    Feigl's original procedure (Feigl, 1961) is as follows: "A small amount of  resorcinol and a few drops of conc. H2SO4 are added to a few mg of a solid  sample. The mixture is heated at less than 130 for 5 minutes, dissolved  into water after cooling, and made alkaline with NaOH. Fluorescence occurs  if 1,2-dicarboxylates are present in the sample."  Preliminary tests showed that resocinol did not react with powdered sam-  ples of humic acid but did react with dissolved samples. Although both acid  and alkaline solutions of humic acid could react with resorcinol, the reac-  tion mixture was colored by resorcinol alone in the absence of humic acid  in an alkaline medium. The acid solution of humic acid was therefore used  after being purified with ion exchange resins. The temperature of a glycerol  bath was controlled carefully using a mercury thermocontroUer with con-  stant stirring, o-Phthalic acid was used as a reference substance, because it  reacted readily, as shown later.  Based on the  results of preliminary tests, the authors examined various  modifications of Feigl's method to develop a quantitative determination in  aqueous solution. Checked conditions were the amounts of H2SO4 and resor-  cinol, pH, heating time, absorption maximum, and stability of reaction prod-  ucts. Recovery of o-phthalic acid from humic acid solutions and the effects  of H2SO4 treatment on humic acids were also tested.    153    To find out the optimum amount of H2SO4, 0.25 ml of o-phthalic acid  (4.0 mg/ml) solution and 0.25 ml of resorcinol (400 mg/ml) solution were  placed in test tubes. After the addition of each different volume of 0.3--2 ml  of conc. H2SO4, the mixture was heated at 130 for 5 minutes in a glycerol  bath and then cooled in an ice bath. The reaction mixture was poured into  a 250-ml volumetric flask with about 150 ml of water, made alkaline with  the suitable amount of 2.4 N NaOH, made up to volume, and measured  spectrophotometrically over the range of 550--400 nm, using a Hitachi  124 or Shimazu UV-240 spectrophotometer.  To find the optimum amount of resocinol, 0.25 ml of the o-phthalic acid  (4.0 mg/ml) solution, 0.25 ml of the resorcinol (80--2000 mg/ml) solution  and 0.75 ml of conc. H2SO4 were placed in test tubes. The procedures fol-  lowed thereafter were the same as described above.  The optimum pH of the final solution was checked on a reaction mixture  comprising 0.25 ml of o-phthalic acid (3.2 mg/ml) solution, 0.25 ml of re-  sorcinol (200 mg/ml) solution and 0.75 ml of H2SO4. Final values of pH  were adjusted from ca. 4 to ca. 12 with 2.4 N NaOH and measured exactly.  The absorbance was measured at 490 nm.  To determine the most suitable heating time, 0.25 ml of o-phthalic acid  (0.4 mg/ml) or humic acid (4 mg/ml) solution, 0.25 ml of resorcinol (400  mg/ml) solution and 0.75 ml of H2SO4 were placed in test tubes. The mix-  ture was heated for periods ranging from 5 to 15 minutes. To minimize color-  ing of the control, the temperature was lowered to 127. The other proce-  dures were the same as described above.  To check the stability of reaction products, the absorbance at 490 nm was  measured at various time intervals, after 0 or 2 ml of sodium thioglycolate  (5%) solution were added to each of the two 250-ml flask containing the  reaction products.  Recovery of 1,2&lt;licarboxylate in a system including humic acid was mea-  sured by mixing equal volumes of o-phthalic acid (0.4 mg/ml) and humic  acid (ca. 4 mg/ml) solutions. A 0.25-ml portion of this mixture was added to  0.25 ml of resorcinol (400 mg/ml) solution. After adding 0.75 ml of H2SO4  the mixture was kept at 127 for 10 minutes. The color that developed  was then compared with the control.  To check possible degradation of humic acid by H2SO4, which may form  1,2-dicarboxylates or some other products reactive to resorcinol, 0.25 ml of  humic acid (ca. 4 mg/ml) solution was placed into a test tube. To this test  tube 0.75 ml of con. H2SO4 was added carefully with the tube in an ice  bath to avoid raising the temperature. The mixture was kept at 127 for  10 minutes, cooled in an ice bath, and, after the addition of 0.25 ml resor-  cinol (400 mg/ml) solution, it was again heated at 127 for 10 minutes. The  color that developed was then compared with the control.    154    Determination of 1,2-dicarboxylate content in humic acid    A 0.25 ml portion of resorcinol (400 mg/ml) solution and 0.25 ml of  humic acid (ca. 4 mg/ml) solution (or 0.125 ml of the same humic acid solu-  tion and 0.125 ml of water) were placed into a test tube. Immediately after  0.75 ml of conc. H2SO4 was added, the tube was kept at 127 for 10 min-  utes in a glycerol bath and then cooled in an ice bath. The reaction mixture  was poured into a 250-ml volumetric flask with about 150 ml of water, ad-  justed to pH 11--12 with 2.4 N NaOH, made up to volume and measured  spectrophotometricaUy over the range of 550--400 nm. Absorbance at 490  nm was converted to the amount of 1,2&lt;licarboxylate using the calibration  line made with 0 to 200 t~g of o-phthalic acid in the same procedure (y =  0.00112 x + 0.01, y: absorbance at 490 nm, x: o-phthalic acid pg, correlation  coefficient: 1.00).  To examine the characteristics of reaction products, their excitation and  fuorescence emission spectra were also measured in ranges of 400--500 and  480--600 nm, respectively, using a Hitachi MPF-3A fluorometer.    Comparison of humic acid with model compounds    Model compounds were treated with resorcinol according to both Feigl's  method and the modified method described in previous section. Color devel.  opment was compared with respect to the wavelength and intensity of the  maximum absorption. The reaction products of model compounds were  compared with those of hurnic acid.  To ascertain the relationships between the absorbances and the concen-  trations of reaction products, molar absorptions of fluorescein and succinyl-  fluorescein were determined at pH 11--12.    Possible contamination with monomeric o-phthalic acid or its esters    To assess the possible presence of o-phthalic acid in the humic acid solu-  tion, 0.25 ml of humic acid solution was acidified to below pH2 and ex-  tracted with 2.0 ml of ethyl ether by shaking for 1 rain. A 2.0 pl sample of  the extract was injected into a Hitachi gaschromatograph 063 equipped with  a flame ionization detector. The operating conditions were as follows: in-  jector temp. 240, column temp. 100, detector temp. 250 , column  length 1 m, packing agent OV 17.  To examine o-phthalate esters, 0.25 ml of humic acid solution was ex-  tracted with methylene dichloride (1.25 ml), 2.0/~1 of which were injected  into the same GC. It was operated under temperatures increasing from 90  to 250.    155    RESULTS    Modification of the original method (Figs. 1--4)    The optimum amount of H2 SO4 for the reaction of o-phthalic acid with  resorcinol in the presence of 0.5 ml of water was 0.75 ml (Fig. la). The  more resorcinol added, the more the color developed in the same reaction  (Fig. lb). The absorbance of the control solution without o-phthalic acid,  however, increased with increasing the amount of resorcinol added, especi-  ally in the range higher than 100 mg. Therefore, 100 mg of resorcinol were  added to each tube. The final pH value of the reaction mixture was found  to be optimum at 11--12 (Fig. lc).    A490 a)  0"10I  0'05I  o!  0  A491  O.3  0.2  0.1  0  4    c)    Q,e  i       i  1  H2S04, ml    ~o_o/o-o-''4 -  o  Q  J    7     10    13  pH    A490 b)  0.6l       ~~"  o,l   /"          o  Resorcinol, mg    Fig. 1. Effects of the amounts of H2SO4 (a), resorcinol (b), and pH (c) on the color  development. H20, 0.5 ml; o-phthalic acid 1.0 mg (a and b) or 0.8 mg (c); resorcinol, 20  mg (a) or 50 mg (c); H2804, 0.75 ml (b and c). heat 130, 5 rain; final vol., 250 ml,  wavelength 490 nm.    The reaction products of humic acid had absorption maxima at 488 to  490 nm as shown for examples in Fig. 2. Similar results were obtained for  the other samples. These values are nearly the same as that for o-phthalic  acid (490 nm). Although absorbance maxima differed slightly in locations  near 490 nm, the maxima had broad peaks so that 490 nm could be used  satisfactorily for comparisons of different humic acids.  As heating was prolonged, the color increased in both o-phthalic and  humic acids (Fig. 3a). When the absorbances of humic acid samples were    156    converted to the amounts of o-phthalic acid, however, they became nearly  constant after heating for 7--10 minutes (Fig. 3b).    1                 ~?'t  ~.__j/    ~l     P20   \    o   ,,.,   ~   ,,,8   ~  ...........~   ~  '..,1'           "-..T                        U~ ..,,T           M  ,~, nm                       ~, nm  Fig. 2. Absorption spectra of reaction products of humic and o-phthalic acids with resor-  cinol. H~O, 0.5 ml. Humic acids, ca. 1 rag; o-phthalic acid, 0, 100 and 200 ~; resorcino],  100 rag; heat, 127, 10 rain; final vol., 250 ml. 8ht = Shitara;/g = Inoguhira; P ffi o-  phthalic acid; (--R) ffi without resorcinol,    A49C  0.2    0.1    a)    5 7  10    15  Time, rain    150[ o b)  z lo\o   ,oot    Time, min    Fig. 3. Effect of heating time on color deW,eat. H20, 0.5 ml; humic ~, ca. 1 rag;  o-phthalic acid, 100 #g; ~ol, 100 rag, H~O4, 0,75 ml~ heat 127; final vol., 250  ml.; wavelength, 490 nm.  = Shitara; o = Kuragari; v ffi Sanage; = Tsubama; A  o-phthalic acid. 100 jag; ~ = blank.    157    The color of reaction products of humic acid with resorcinol was not so  stable as the color due to o-phthalic acid {Fig. 4). The change of color in-  tensity was prevented by adding sodium thioglycolate as a reducing agent  (Fig. 4}. But we considered that the addition of thioglycolate was not neces-  sary when the absorbance was measured immediately after a solution was  made alkaline because the color change was slow.  A490  I  ?-..  ! .-~" -"m..,  .........  .  ..........  ,  o,+t  0.13:~,-I  .........  ,   ,  0.0   2  4~+.. z~.. _ -z~  .........  z&amp;  .........  l        ~        i  0 0   1   2  ..1  Time( hour )  Fig. 4. Stability of the color developed. H20, 0.5 ml; humic acid ca. 1 rag; o-phthalic acid  100 ug; H2SO,, 0.75 ml; heat 127, 10 rain.; Na thioglycolate 0 or 200 rag; final voi.  250 ml; wavelength 490 nm. The values except for the blanks are the net ones, after the  blank values are subtracted.  = Shitara humic acid; * = o-phthalic acid; s = blank. -- = Na-thioglycolate was not  added. + - - = Na-thioglycolate was added.    The recovery of o-phthalic acid from the mixture which humic acid was  106 + 0.2%. This result shows that humic acid does not block the reaction  of o-phthalic acid with resorcinol.  Pretreatment of humic acid with H2SO+ did not increase the absorbances  at 490 nm but decreased them by 20--39% for the four humic acid samples  tested. This indicates that the cleavage of the molecule by reactions such as  hydrolysis, which may produce 1,2&lt;licarboxylates as an artifact, did not oc-  cur.  According to these results, the procedure for determining 1,2-dicarboxy-  late content in humic acid was established as described in the foregoing  section.    1,2-Dicarboxylate content in humic acids    The contents of 1,2~licarboxylates in humic acid calculated on the basis  of o-phthalate are tabulated in Table I. They were in a range of 0.4--1.0  mmol/g. Those values and percentages of the total acidities (DC/T, about    158    20--50%) were higher in Rp and B types of humic acid than in P and A types  (Table I). The percentages of the easily dissociable acid groups (refered to as  S clusters by Arai and Kumada, 1977)specified as 1,2-dicarboxylates (DC/S),  are also shown in Table I. If there were an o-phthalate unit in humic acid,  one of two carboxyl groups could be included in the S cluster, DC/S de-  creased in the order of Rp :&gt; B, P &gt; A types. These results suggest that the  contents of 1,2&lt;iicarboxylates may tend to decrease with increasing degree  of humification.    TABLE I    Amounts of 1,2 dicarboxylic acid units in humic acids    Name        Type of     Amount of  1,2-dicarboxyl-  Total      Amount of     DC/T   DC/S  humic acid  subsample   lic acid (DC,    acidity.1   S cluster*l,*2   (%)     (%)  (ml)        raM/g)         (T, meq./g) (S, meq./g)    Shitara      A           0.125       0.64           5,92       1.90           21     33  0.25         0.59                                           20      31  Inogashira   A           0.125       0.71            5.78       1.94            24      36  0.25         0.73                                           25      37  Kuragarl    B           0.125       0.71           4.17       1.27           34     55  0.25         0.71                                         34      56  Kinshozan-  B            0.125       0.93            4.56       1.33            41      69  F .3                        0.25         0.84                                           37      63  Higashi-     B          0.125       0.78           4.22      1.07           37     72  yama H/A              0.25        0.69                                    32     64  Sanage      Rp         0.125      0.76           4.01      0.83           38     92  0.25         0.76                                         38      91  Kinshozan-  Rp          0.125        1.01            3.91       1.15            52      88  OH*s                      0.25         0.96                                           49      83  Tsubame    P            0.125       0.43            4,42       1.18            19      36  0.25         0.42                                           19      35    i A~al and Kumada (1977).  2 Strongly dis~e4ating acid ftmctional gzoup,  SSufflxes F and OH denote extraetants, NaF    pKa &lt; ca. 3.8.  and NaOH, respectively.    Comparison of humic acid with model compounds    Model compounds were treated with both Feigl's (1961) and the modified  method. The model samples tested had absorption maxima between 480 and  490 nm (Table II). The examples of spectra for o-phthalic acid are shown in  Fig. 2. The absorptive intensity was in the order of o-phthalic &gt; succinic &gt;  maleic, 1,2,3-propanetricarboxylic &gt; glutaric, 1,3,5-pentanetricarboxylic and  fumaric acids (Table II). Feigl's original method was found to be more sensi-  tive for detecting dicarboxylates than the modified method. Thus, the rela-  tive absorbance of o-phthalic acid was two times (in Feigl's method) and ten  times (in the modified method) as high as that of succinic acid. The relative  absorbances were considered to be approximately proportional to the rela-  tive yields or velocities of reactions, because the molar absorptivities were  of the same order, i.e., 7.25 104 for fluorescein, and 7.96 104 for suc-    159  cinyl fluorescein, the reaction products of resorcinol with o-phthalic and  succinic acids, respectively.  TABLE II  Reactions of model compounds with resorcinol by different methods    Sample         Method.1   Wavelength of           Absorbance/     Relative  maximum absorption    mmo1.2          absorbance  (nm)    o-Phthalic      1           490                    235             100  acid           2           491                     97             100  Succinic       1           488                    118              50  acid           2           487                      9               9  1,2,3-Propane-  1           490                     29              12  tricarboxylic   2             --                        0                0  acid  Maleic acid     1            488                      40               17  2            489                        9                9  Fumaric        1            488                        7                3  acid           2           487                      3               3  Glutaric        1            486                      15                6  acid           2           487                      2               2  1,3,5-Pentane-  1            485                      11                5  tricarboxylic    2              --                          0                 0  acid    *' i = H20, 0 ml; Resorcinol, 100 mg; H2SO+, three drops;heat 127, 5 min; Final vol.,  250 ml. 2 = H20, 0.5 ml; Resorcinol, 100 mg;H2SO4, 0.75 rag;heat 127, 7 rain.; final  vol., 250 ml.  .2 Absorbance/sample (mg)/molecular weight.    The strongest excitation in wavelengths of the reaction products of humic  acid was the same as that of o-phthalic acid, 492 nm, but different from that  of succinic acid, 483 nm. The emission maxima of the reaction products of  humic acid were between those of o-phthalic acid, 513 nm, and succinic  acid, 503 nm (Fig. 5).  The o-phthalic acid and its esters, i.e., dimethyl, diethyl, dibutyl, dicyclo-  hexyl and dioctyl esters, were not detected (not shown in the illustrations).  The limits of detection were ca. 0.08 mmol/g for o-phthalic acid and the  esters.    DISCUSSION    It is believed that humic acid contains various types of 1,2&lt;iicarboxyl  units. Visible absorption and fluorometric spectra of the reaction products  of humic acid with resorcinol resembled those of model compounds tested,  so that we could not know from spectrophotometric data which types of  units were involved in this reaction.    160    .g    a)       !1  P  450 "Sht bl    500  h, nm    b)  /  /\  ~.    RO.3  500 \Sht bl     550  ~, nm    Fig. 5. Fluorescence excitation and emission spectra of reaction products of hurnic,  o-phthalic and succinic acids with resorcinol.  a. Excitation spectra. Emi~ion radiation wavelength, 505 nm for Shitara humic acid  (8ht), 512 nm for o-phthalic acid (P) and 504 nm for succinic acid (S).  b. Emission spectra. Excitation wavelength, 492 nm for 8ht. and P., 484 nm for S. H~O,  0.5 ml; humic acid, ca. 1 rag; o-phthalic acid, 100 I~g; succinic acid, 142 l~g; resorcinot,  100 rag; H,SO4, 0.75 ml; heat, 127, 10 mLn; final vol., 500 ml. R 0.3 is control corre-  sponding to 8ht. and P., and R3 to 8. 8ht bl. shows blank value of the humic acid not re-  acted with resorcinol.    On the other hand, the model compounds tested showed considerable  differences in the relative absorbances of reaction products with resorcinol  (Table II). Because the relative absorbance of the reaction product is con-  sidered to approximate the relative yield of that product or the velocity of  the reaction, as described in the foregoing section, o-phthalate unit in humic  acid, if any, will react with resorcinol with about ten times the efficiency of  succinate or the other units. Moreover, if constituents other than o.phtha-  lates were assumed to take part mainly in the reaction, the contents of 1,2-  dicarboxylates in humic acid would be overestimated.  For these reasons, we concluded that the 1,2-dicarboxyl constituents of  humic acid which reacted easily with resorcinol were o.phthalate homologs.  Calculation of the contents of 1,2-dicarboxylates in humic acid using o--  phthatic acid as a standard did seem to give reasonable values. Some differ-  ences between humic and o-phthalic acids in photometric characteristics and  in stabilities of the reaction products may be attributed to the effects of  substituents in the phthalate units.  Feigt (1961) listed compounds that can produce fluorescein homologs by  the reaction with resorcinol. They a~ 1,2-dicarboxylic acids or their deriva-  tives, such as esters, anhydrides, or imides. One carboxyl group may be re-  placed by a sulfonyl group. Accordingly, constituents of phthalate deriva-  tives such as esters may be involved in the 1,2-dicarboxyl content of humic  acid as determined by our method. On the other hand, various types of 1,2-    161    dicarboxylates other than o-phthalate homologs will be largely undetected  in the same method, though they may play important roles in soil. The poly-  maleic structure proposed by Anderson and Russell (1976) is considered as  an example of such cases.  The contents of 1,2-dicarboxylates in humic acid estimated in this study  (20--50% of the total acidity) approximate, or are a little lower than those  of dicarboxylates determined with the infrared method, i.e., 30--50% (Wood  et al., 1961) or 30--90% (Wagner and Stevenson, 1965).  The o-phthalate homologs were found in a bitumenous fraction (Cifrulak,  1969), fulvic acid (Khan and Schnitzer, 1971; Gamble and Schnitzer, 1973)  and degradation products of humic acid (Hayashi and Nagai, 1961; Scheffer  and Kickuth, 1961; Matsuda and Schnitzer, 1972; Ortiz de Serra and  Schnitzer, 1973). Various phthalic diesters identified in the former two  fractions seem to be involved directly. In the last case, however, it was not  certain whether humic acid had o-phthalate structure originally or not. The  reaction of humic acid with resorcinol described in a previous section sug-  gests its existence in untreated macromolecules, though there remains a pos-  sibility that the results were partly affected by contamination with fulvic  acid.  The source of o-phthalate units in soil organic matter is not known, but it  may come from lignin or microbial metabolites. Conidendrin, a component  of lignin (Flaig et al., 1975), is also a possible source of o-phthalate homo-  logs. Not only o-phthalic acid, but also its derivatives have been found in  microbial products (Cross et al., 1963; Miyoshi et al., 1974). These may be  inherited by fulvic and humic acids. The differences in the relative amounts  of the o-phthalate units among humic acid samples are thought to reflect  the differences in their starting materials and/or in their synthetic path-  ways and degree of subsequent alteration, following initial synthesis.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors are indebted to Mr. R. Shiroya and Mr. Y. Kawamura for  supplying humic acid samples and also thank Dr. Laurence E. Lowe of the  University of British Columbia for reading the manuscript.    REFERENCES    Anderson, H.A. and Russel, J.D., 1976. Possible relationship between soil fulvic acid and  polymaleic acid. Nature, 260: 597.  Arai, S. and Kumada, K., 1977. Fractional determination of functional groups of humic  acids by conductometric titration. Geoderma, 19: 307--317.  Cifrulak, S.D., 1969. Spectroscopic evidence of phthalates in soil organic matter. Soil  Sci., 107: 63--69.  Cross, B.E., Galt, R.H.B., Hanson, J,R. and Curtis, P.J., 1963. New metabolites of  Gibberella fujikuroi, 2. The isolation of fourteen new metabolites. J. Chem. Soc.,  2937--2943.    162    Feigl, F., 1961. Spot Test in Organic Analysis. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 256--258.  Flaig, W., Beutelspacher, H. and Rietz, E., 1975. Chemical composition and physical  properties of humic substances. In: J.E. Gieseking (Editor), Soil Components,  Volume 1. Springer-Verlag, Berlin, pp. 1--212.  Gamble, D.S. and Schnitzer, M., 1973. The chemistry of fulvic acid and its reaction with  metal ions. In: P.C. Singer (Editor), Trace Metals and Metal-Organic Interactions in  Natural Water. Ann Arbor Sci. Publ., MI, pp. 265--302.  Hayashi, T. and Nagai, T., 1961. On the components of soil humic acids, 8. The oxida-  tive decomposition by alkaline potassium permanganate and nitric acid. Soil Plant  Food, 6: 170--175.  Khan, S.U. and Schnitzer, M., 1971. Sephadex gel filtration of fulvic acid: the identifi-  cation of major components in two low-molecular weight fractions. Soil Sci., 112:  231--238.  Kumada, K., Sato, O., Ohsumi, Y. and Ohta, S., 1967. Humus composition of mountain  soils in central Japan with special reference to the distribution of P-type humic acid.  Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 13: 151--158.  Matsuda, K. and Schnitzer, M., 1972. The permanganate oxidation of humic acids ex-  tracted from acid soils. Soil Sci., 114: 185--193.  Miyoshi, T., Sato, H. and Harada, T., 1974. New Metabolites, 2,4,6-triketosuberic acid  and 2,4,6,8-tetraketosebacic acid, formed from 2,6-butyne-l,4-diol by Fusarium  merismoides Bll. Agric. Biol. Chem., 38: 1935--1939.  Ortiz de Serra, M.I. and Schnitzer, M., 1973. The chemistry of humic and fulvic acid  extracted from Argentine soils, 2. Permanganate oxidation of ethylated humic and  fulvic acids. Soil Biol. Biochem., 5: 287--296.  Scheffer, F. and Kickuth, R., 1961. Chemische Abbauversuche an einer nattirlichen Humin-  s~/ure, 2. Z. Pflanzenerna]lr., Dilng., Bodenkd., 94: 189--198.  Wagner, G.H. and Stevenson, F.J., 1965. Structural arrangement of functional groups in  soil humic acids as revealed by infrared analysis. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29: 43--48.  Wood, J.C., Moschopedis, S.E. and Den Hertog, W., 1961. Studies in humic acid chem-  istry, II. Humic anhydrides. Fuel, 40: 491--502.                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractTo detect and quantify 1,2-dicarboxylate structures in humic acid, a chemical reaction forming fluoresceins from 1,2-dicarboxylates and resorcinol was tested. Resorcinol reacted with humic acid to form products having absorption maxima at about 490 nm. A procedure was then developed for quantitative analysis of the radicals. Eight humic acid samples tested contained 0.4–1.0 mmol/g of 1,2-dicarboxylate structures. The 1,2-Dicarboxylates detected in humic acid were considered as ophthalate homologs.