 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 311--325                                                      311  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    ACCURACY OF SPATIAL INTERPOLATION BETWEEN POINT DATA  ON SOIL MOISTURE SUPPLY CAPACITY, COMPARED WITH ESTIMATES  FROM MAPPING UNITS1    J. VAN KUILENBURG, J.J. DE GRUIJTER, B.A. MARSMAN and J. BOUMA2  The Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Received June 5, 1981; accepted December 9, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Van Kuilenburg, J., De Gruijter, J.J., Marsman, B.A. and Bouma, J., 1982. Accuracy of  spatial interpolation between point data on soil moisture supply capacity, compared  with estimates from mapping units. Geoderma, 27: 311--325.    Three interpolation techniques were applied to point data on soil moisture supply  capacity in a 2 km x 2 km area of cover sand in the eastern part of The Netherlands. The  interpolation techniques are: Proximal, Weighted Average and Kriging; survey points  used for interpolation were stratified random, with an average density of 1.5 per ha. The  Root Mean Squared (RMS) Error of these techniques, as estimated from an independent  statistical sample, was 37, 29 and 29 ram, respectively, whereas the moisture supply  capacity in the area ranged from 50 to 240 mm. Profile descriptions at the same survey  points were used to make a soil map (scale 1 : 10 000), the mapping units of which were  delineated in the field. Using the means of these mapping units as estimates for points in  the area would e.g. have led to an RMS Error of 32 mm if the means were estimated  from an additional random sample of 5 profile descriptions per mapping unit or 0.4 per  ha. This lower efficiency, compared with Weighted Average and Kriging, should be weigh-  ed against the advantage of the soil map of being a basic document that can be directly  used for various purposes.    INTRODUCTION    Detailed soil maps are widely used to help determine soil suitabilities  for a variety of uses within a region. These suitabilities are based on soil  survey interpretations for particular soil types which are assumed to be  representative of mapping units, as defined by the legend of the soil map.  The soil surveyor determines the soil type and the delineations of the mapping  units. By necessity, his work is based on a limited number of observed profiles    ' Contribution from The Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6700 AB Wage-  ningen (The Netherlands).  : Head Computer Dept., Soil Survey Inst.; Statistician, Inst. TNO for Mathematics, Infor-  mation Processing and Statistics; Soil Scientist; and Head Soil Physics Dep., respectively.    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    312    and on an interpretation of landscape features. This procedure has therefore  a subjective character.  Mapping units usually include soils which do not fit the description of the  legend: the so-called "impurities". In addition, soil properties usually also  vary within the pure part of mapping units. Recent studies on variation  within mapping units have raised the question of how suitable these units  are as a basis for soil survey interpretations. This question is relevant because  automated derivation of assessment factors and suitabilities from profile  data, and automated interpolation between profiles are now technically and  economically within reach.  This study focuses on the problem of choosing between mathematical  interpolation techniques and delineation of mapping units in the field for  estimating soil properties at given points in an area. Attention will be con-  fined to one soil property: the soil moisture supply capacity. This is a crucial  assessment factor for many soil survey interpretations in The Netherlands,  where there is a precipitation deficit in the growing season (Bouma et al.,  19805).  The purpose of this study is: (1) to evaluate and compare the accuracies  of three interpolation techniques when applied to profile data on soil moisture  supply capacity, and (2) to compare these accuracies to that achieved by  using data of the mapping units of a soil map.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils and soil map    The study area was a 2 km X 2 km square in a rural landscape developed  on cover sand, near the village of Laren in the province of Gelderland, The  Netherlands. Its location is indicated in Fig.1. As built-up parts were exclud-  ed, the study area measured 359 instead of 400 ha. A soil map of the study  area was made using a scale of 1 : 10 000. Its mapping units were delineated  in the field by interpretation of landscape features. To obtain comparable  results, the same profile data were used both for the soil map and for the  mathematical interpolations. The profile data are in this case field estimates  of basic soil properties, obtained by borings at randomly selected locations  with a density of 1.48 per ha. The sampling scheme is discussed in the sec-  tion "Interpolation techniques".  Some major properties of the soil types in the study area and their classifi-  cation according to Soil Survey Staff (1975) are presented in Table I. More  detailed information is presented by De Bakker {1979). All soils had a sand  fraction with a median size value between 150 and 155 tam. The soil map has  30 different mapping units, which are defined in terms of one of the nine  soil types and the fluctuation of the groundwater level during the year (e.g.  Van Heesen, 1970). This fluctuation is expressed in classes of the average  highest (GHG) and lowest (GLG) groundwater levels (see Table II). For    i  ::"   /  ,                           }:  ~   '"~ ~ ~IE .~  ~ Pleistocene, sandy soils (after De Bakker, 19791  '   3,0kin  Fig.1. Location of the study area within the Pleistocene sandy soils of The Netherlands.    313    clarity, two separate maps are presented in Figs.2 and 3. The soil map in  Fig,2 shows only the soil types and the map of Fig.3 shows only the ground-  water classes. Normally, both types of maps are combined into one.    Moisture supply capacity    The moisture supply capacity (to be abbreviated hereafter as MSC) is  defined as the amount of moisture that can be supplied by the soil to a crop  in a 10 per cent dry year. This is a relatively dry year with an evapotranspira-  tion surplus (= rainfall deficit} in the growing season from .April 15th to  September 15th, that has a probability of being exceeded only once in 10  years (Rijtema, 1971). Moisture absorption is usually schematically represent  ed to include a fraction which is absorbed within the root zone and a frac-  tion which is absorbed at the lower boundary of the root zone. Water rises  to this level by upward unsaturated flow from the water table. The lower    ~0    TABLE I    Soil types in the study area, characterized by soil classification and average values of some major soil properties    Code     Classification  soil map    Percentage of:    org. matter  silt   clay   org. matter  silt   clay  (10 cm below surface)    (70 cm below surface)    Hn33    Typic Haplaquods; fine sand                  6.8         12   3      1.5         10   2  Hn35    Typic Haplaquods; loamy fine sand            6.0         19   3      1.5         15   2  cHn33   Plaggeptic Haplaquods; fine sand              6.5         15   3      2.0         12   2  cHn35   Plaggeptic Haplaquods; loamy fine sand        7.5         19   3      3.0         15   2  EZ35    Plaggepts; loamy fine sand                    8.0         20   3      5.0         17   2  pZg35   Typic Humaquepts; loamy fine sand           7.0         20   3      1.0         15   2  fkZn35   Typic Psammaquents; loamy fine sand*        5.0          25   9      1.0          15   2  pZn33   Weakly spodic Humaquepts; fine sand         6.0         12   3      1.0           9   2  pZn35   Weakly spodic Humaquepts; loamy fine sand   6.0         19   3      1.0         12   2    Rooting  depth    *With bog iron ore.    (cm)    45  50  60  60  60  70  55  40  45    315  TABLE II  Groundwater classes defined in terms of average highest (GHG) and average ]owest (GLG)  groundwater levels (cm be]ow surface)    Groundwater   GHG       GLG  class    III                0--40     80--120  III*             25--40     80--120  V           0--40   &gt; 120  V*            25--40     &gt; 120  VI           40--80    &gt; 120  VII           80--140   &gt; 120  VII*           &gt; 140     &gt; 140    Hn33  Hn35  cHn33  cHn35  EZ35  pZg35  fkZn35  pZn33  pZn35  not  surveyed  0                 0,5                 lkm  LIIIII                    1  Fig.2. Soil map of the study area. Data on the various soiltypes are presented in Table I.    316    !    :   :  1   /:;12i  F';'::'";:  [  0                   (]5                  1 km  Fig.3. Groundwater classes in the study area (see Table II for definitions).    III  II1"  v  v~  Vl  vii  vii"  not  surveyed    boundary of the root zone is the level above which approximately 80% of  the roots occur (Rijtema, 1971). The MSC can be calculated with a computer  simulation model which requires moisture retention data for the root zone  and the subsoil, and hydraulic conductivity data for the subsoil. Necessary  boundary conditions of the flow system are formed by climatic data and  data on water table fluctuations (De Laat, 1980; Bouma et al., 1980a,b). Cal-  culations of the MSC are made for each boring. They are based on field esti-  mates of the water table fluctuation, the thickness of the root zone, soil  textures, bulk densities and organic-matter contents of the various soil hori-  zons. The latter three characteristics are used to predict moisture retention  and hydraulic conductivity data, as discussed by Bouma et al. (1980a). The  most recent version of the simulation model {De Laat, 1980) was not avail-  able when the calculations, as cited here, were made. The calculation proce-  dure, as such, is, however, not essential to the discussion in this paper. The  crucial point is that data from each boring were used to calculate the MSC  with a well-defined, consistent and reproducible procedure.    317    Interpolation techniques    Three interpolation techniques were compared with respect to accuracy.  For this purpose two sets of borings were available: a set of random survey  borings and a set of random test borings. In the analysis the geographical  coordinates of each boring were used, together with its calculated MSC  value. Survey and test set form two mutually independent, stratified random  samples with (apart from some dropping out), respectively, 9 and 11 random-  ly located borings per stratum. The same strata were used for both samples,  namely squares of 250 m X 250 m. Thus, in total, there were 530 random  survey borings and 661 test borings, resulting in average densities of 1.48  and 1.84 per ha, respectively.  The three techniques were successively applied, so that for each test  boring an interpolated MSC value was obtained, using the calculated MSC  values of the random survey borings in the neighbourhood of that test  boring. The difference between the calculated and the interpolated MSC  value for a given test boring was treated as the error made by the interpola-  tion technique in question at that point in the area. From these individual  errors the Mean Squared Error of each interpolation technique was estimated  by the usual estimation procedure for stratified random samples (see e.g.  Cochran, 1977). The design of this experiment is roughly similar to that  used by Braile {1978), although that author compared other interpolation  techniques in other circumstances.  The interpolation techniques can be characterized as follows, in order of  increasing sophistication.    Proximal. By this method the value of the nearest survey boring is taken as  the interpolated value for a given test boring. The method is simple and  cheap. No explicit weighting is carried out, because only one value is used.    Weighted Average. By this method {see e.g. Davis, 1973) the interpolated val-  ue for a test boring is calculated as a weighted average of the values of the  nearest survey borings. The weighting function can be any function which  decreases with distance. Both the number of neighbouring values and the  exact form of the weighting function can be chosen. In this study the values  of the ten nearest survey borings were used, with weights proportional to  the inverse of the squared distance from the test boring.    Kriging. Here the interpolated value for a test boring is also a weighted aver-  age of the values of survey borings in the neighbourhood. The difference  with the previous technique is that with Kriging the weights are explicitly  chosen so that each interpolated value is an unbiased estimate with mini-  mum variance, i.e., with smallest possible expected error. The Kriging  technique is a result of the statistical theory of regionalized variables, devel-  oped by G. Matheron and coworkers (Matheron, 1971). An introduction to    318    Kriging can be found in David (1977) and, with more mathematical detail,  in Olea (1975). Other applications to soil data have been reported by Giltrap  (1978) and Buxgess and Webster (1980).  Mathematically, the weights of the n survey borings in a neighbourhood  of a test boring are found by solving the following system of n + 1 linear  equations:    rl  Z ay7ij + p = 7i0                    (i = 1  .....  n)  j=l    (1)    T(Ih[) = Co + c               for Ihl &gt; a    (2)    /2  Z aj=l  j=l  where aj is the weight of the jth neighbouring boring, # is a Lagrange multi-  plier, and 7ij is the semi-variance between the ith and jth boring, the test  boring being indexed by j = 0. As indicated hereafter, the semi-variances in  these equations can be estimated from the available data, so that only the n  weights and # remain as unknowns. Now the system of equations can be  solved.  The semi-variances represent the spatial correlations in the area. For two  points i and j the correlation is defined as:  1  7iJ= 2 E{z(xi)-z(xJ)}2  where E denotes expectation and z(xi) the studied variable (here MSC) at  location xi. With the simple Kriging technique used here, it is assumed that  the values at points in the area can be described by a stationary random pro-  cess. This implies that 7i1 is the same for each pair of points with the same  difference in location. It may therefore be written as a function of this dif-  ference only:  1  T(h) = -~ E {z(x)-z(x + h)y  Note that in the present case the difference h is a two-dimensional vector  like x, that can be represented by a distance and adirection component.  The function 7(h) has been estimated by averaging the squared difference  between MSC values of pairs of test borings, after sorting these pairs into  classes defined in terms of distance and direction. It appeared that 7 dit not  clearly depend on direction, so the averages were pooled over all directions.  This resulted in a two&lt;limenaional variogram, i.e., a graph of semi-variance  versus distance Ihl (Fig.4), to which the "spherical model" was fitted:  ~(Ihl)=c0+c  --   2aa    for0&lt;lhi&lt;~a     1500,   1000-  '~ 500-    2000    ~ a    /  /  /  o'  o/]"  ./  /  q  'co    e  OI Q              000  O~  io                         0                                 O    average distance (km)  Fig.4. Variogram of Moisture Supply Capacity in the study area, to be used for the  Kriging technique. The dotted lines were drawn to obtain estimates of the constants c,  co and a of the spherical variogram model (2).    319    The three parameters a, Co and c were estimated from the variogram as  shown in Fig.4: a = 0.6 km, Co = 600 mm2 and c = 1200 mm2. These param-  eters have a useful descriptive meaning. Parameter a denotes the distance  beyond which two points are practically uncorrelated; it is called the "range".  Parameter Co denotes the so-called "nugget-effect" (from gold mining),  representing variability among samples at the shortest possible sampling  distance. The sum Co + c is called the "sill" and denotes the semi-variance  of uncorrelated points. Once these parameters were determined the semi-  variance of any pair of borings could be calculated by substituting their  mutual distance in (2).  As mentioned before, a system (1) of n + 1 equations had to be solved for  each interpolation, with n denoting the number of survey borings in a  neighbourhood of the test boring. To avoid a large amount of unnecessary  computation, this number had to be as low as possible, yet high enough to  avoid loss of accuracy. As with the Weighted Average technique it was  decided to use the ten nearest borings; preliminary analysis showed that  using more would have given almost the same results.  Proximal, Weighted Average and Kriging are of increasing complexity and  demand increasing computer time. The number of computer operations  depends primarily on the number of neighbouring points carried along in  the interpolation. With Proximal the number of operations is lowest. With  Weighted Average the number of operations increases linearly, and with  Kriging the number increases at least quadratically.    320    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Data exploration    The variation among the MSC values calculated for all random test and  survey borings is shown in the frequency diagram of Fig.5. The distribution    2O  ~15  ==  ~10-  5-  0 , ,  v i ,  0        50       100       150      200       2~$0  Moisture Supply Capacity (mm)  Fig.5. Frequency diagram of Moisture Supply Capacity calculated for 1191 random survey  and test borings.    is highly skewed. The MSC class occurring most frequently is that of 230--  240 mm, which equals the potential evapotranspiration in a 10% dry year.  Obviously, the MSC cannot exceed this maximum value. So the skewness  indicates that in a relatively large part of this area the soil can supply all  the moisture that is needed by the plants in a 10% dry year.  Information on the spatial distribution of the MSC values is not provided  by Fig.5. This aspect is shown in Fig.6, which indicates locations and MSC  values for all test borings. This map suggests a general spatial continuity of  the data and does not obviously conflict with the assumption underlying  the Kriging technique (David, 1977). The spatial distribution is also re-  flected in Fig.7. This shows frequency and average distance for 25 classes  of the absolute values of differences in MSC of pairs of nearest test borings.  It indicates, for example, that 25% of the adjacent borings differs less than 5  mm in MSC, whereas less than 1% differs more than 110 mm. Although  many adjacent borings have small differences in MSC, a substantial percentage  of the neighbouring values differ largely. Fig.7 shows that larger distances  between borings also tend to correspond with larger differences in MSC; the  same tendency had already been observed in the variogram (Fig.4) for a  larger range of distances.  Data exploration thus demonstrates the considerable spatial variability of  MSC even at short distances in the study area. This phenomenon is reflected    "     ~lb           :        .  .   ...~  I: . --    .** -_ ..  .         ~..   6. |  "  d"                 ',,We      oe "                 -                                          .~"    .      |       O               .        'pP'O        -     |  o0 o         '   go     .           oo  /  _      ..         ,,          Co.  ..               o.p        |  I_U   ,  ~  ,ore.       .," .    o.     !  ~"    '~ q'e_    i   _                        |  L  ,'~  s  "....o-4o.. -" ..5 /  / 'j~P -"..%":" . ,..5"- ""./                     'w                   /  ~o    oo.     ~   &amp;  . .-  .   ."    /  ~/ ".  ..Ir.:. ,.. :~..: .-  /,..  .   ...;-....              .~  . .  ..o  ~:....'..-" :'....    :    ,g~  .,     t "6".'...    .      ""  ~                 "       "~"T,  .. ~ ' ~..... :  .,     .   .       ~ ODe            "O                                                      ,                                  4mO   .  : -.~ .~    ~  ;~ -.    ./( l/"t.i  0                 0.5                 1 km  I     I      I      ~      I      I                                J  Fig.6. Locations and Moisture Supply Capacities of 530 random survey borings.       &lt; 75 mm  75- 175 mm  175- 225 mm   :&gt; 225 mm    321    90~  20               "        ""   60  15         .     -o.     ."          o          ~5  0                   50                  100  difference in Moisture Supply Capacity (mm)  Fig.7. Frequency of differences in Moisture Supply Capacities and average distance for  25 classes of differences in Moisture Supply Capacity between 661 random test borings  and their nearest neighbours.    322    by the results of the various interpolation techniques as will now be dis-  cussed.    In terpolation    As mentioned in the preceding paragraph on interpolation techniques, an  estimate of the Mean Square Error of each interpolation technique was  calculated together with the standard deviation of this estimate. From each  estimate and its standard deviation, the 95% confidence limits were calculated  for the Mean Square Error. Square root transformation of these limits re-  sulted in 95% confidence intervals for the Root Mean Squared (RMS) Errors  as given in Table III. The RMS Error of both Weighted Average and Kriging    TABLE III  Root Mean Squared Error of three techniques used to interpolate calculated Moisture  Supply Capacities of random survey borings (1.48 per ha)  Interpolation       95% Confidence interval of RMS Error  technique    lower limit (ram)   upper limit (ram)    Proximal           36.4               36.9  Weighted Average   29.2                29.7  Kriging            28.9               29.4    turned out to be about 29.1 mm, that of Proximal is 36.6 mm. As assessed  with the Student test on the mean of the pairwise differences between squar-  ed errors, all three RMS Errors differ significantly at the l00 level and de-  crease in the order: Proximal, Weighted Average, Kriging. The difference in  accuracy between Kriging and the relatively simple Weighted Average tech-  nique can, however, be neglected in practice. Further simplification by using  the Proximal technique leads to substantially larger errors.  One weakness of the Weighted Average technique, which is avoided in  Kriging, is that possible clusters of survey points are weighted too heavily.  Due to the stratification, however, such clusters do not occur in this study.  This is probably the main reason for the relatively good result of Weighted  Average in this instance.    Use of the soil map    Estimates of MSC cannot be derived directly from the soil map as its  mapping units are not defined in terms of MSC. Each mapping unit as  delineated on the map could, however, be used as a more or less homogeneous  stratum, the mean MSC value of which might be taken as an estimate for any  point within that unit.    323    The rationale of this approach is that in both defining and delineating the  mapping units one attempts to divide the area into parts that are as homo-  geneous as possible with respect to primary soil properties. Because MSC is  related to these properties, the mapping units may also be expected to have  a degree of homogeneity with respect to MSC. The success of the approach  depends, of course, on the degree of homogeneity actually attained, and on  the accuracy with which the means of the units are estimated. The former is  completely determined by the quality of the map, whereas the latter varies  with the effort spent on collecting profile data. These two components are  therefore dealt with separately.  The homogeneity of one mapping unit with respect to MSC can be numeri-  cally expressed as the standard deviation of MSC within that unit. Similarly,  the homogeneity of the map as a whole can be expressed as the standard  deviation within all units of that map, conceptually obtained by pooling  all individual deviations from the means of the respective units. This standard  deviation has been estimated (as the square root of the pooled variance  within units) from the calculated MSC values of the 661 random test borings.  The estimate turned out to be 29 mm. This result implies that if the true  mean MSC of each mapping unit could be used as the estimate for any  point within that unit, that estimate would have the same RMS Error (29 mm)  as interpolation by Weighted Average or Kriging.  In practice, the true means are unknown, and will have to be estimated  with limited accuracy, which adds an extra error to the 29 mm. The size of  this extra error will depend on the estimation procedure followed. Various  procedures are possible, for instance:  {a) construct a "modal" soil profile description for the mapping unit and  calculate its MSC;  (b) select one or more "representative" profile descriptions from those  that were made within the unit, and calculate their mean MSC;  (c) calculate the MSC for each of the profile descriptions also used for  delineating, and calculate their mean;  (d) calculate the MSC for each of the profile descriptions in a statistical  sample not used for delineating, and calculate their mean.  It is beyond the scope of this paper to go into the relative merits of these  procedures. It should be noted, however, that procedure (d) is especially  interesting in the context of this study because it is the only one which enables  the accuracy to be objectively quantified beforehand. For instance, if a  simple random sample of n profiles is taken from a mapping unit, then the  variance s2 (x-) of the estimated mean x equals s2 (x)/n, where s2 (x) denotes  the variance of the property concerned. If x- is also used as the estimate for  any profile in the unit, the Mean Squared Error of that estimate equals  s2(x) + s2(x)/n = s2(x) (n + 1)/n, so the RMS Error equals s(x)x/ (n + 1)/n.  For an "average" unit of the present soil map, having a standard deviation of  29 mm and 22 test borings, this would result in an RMS Error of 29.7 mm.  With a more realistic sample size of 5 borings, for instance, the RMS Errors    324    would be 31.9 mm. The same values would apply to the map as a whole if  these sample sizes were allocated to each unit. In general, it will be possible to  achieve some reduction of these values by using a more efficient sampling  strategy than simple random, and by more efficient allocation of sample  sizes to units, taking their area and standard deviation into account. The  standard deviations of the largest mapping units of the soil map are present-  ed in Table IV; they appear to range between 6.6 and 38.3 mm. The RMS  Error would differ accordingly from unit to unit.    TABLE IV    Areas and standard deviation of Moisture Supply Capacity of the largest mapping units,  estimated from 661 random test borings    Code      Groundwater   Area    Standard  soil map   class           (%)     deviation (mm)  Hn33      Ill              2.8    14.4  Hn33      V               3.7    22.4  Hn33       V*              16.3     34.4  Hn33      VI             19.0    36.8  Hn33     VII           4.3   38.3  Hn35      V               3.5    14.0  cHn33     VI              3.0    27.0  cHn35     VI              6.6    33.2  EZ35      VII             11.4    26.0  EZ35      VII*             2.0    15.0  fkZn35    III              3.1    15.2  fkZn35    III*              2.3     6.6  pZn35     V               1.6    12.1    In conclusion, an extra sampling effort of e.g. 5 random borings on average  in each of the 30 mapping units to estimate their mean MSC, would increase  the sampling density by 28%, and lead to an expected RMS Error which is  10% higher than that of Weighted Average and Kriging. This difference in  efficiency should be weighed against the advantage of the soil map as being a  multiple-purpose document. The map as such gives a comprehensive over-  view of many soil properties simultaneously and can serve as a basis for vari-  ous soil survey interpretations.  One difficulty not yet mentioned is that of observational errors. The  calculated MSC values not only reflect variations present in the area, they  also contain errors due to the fact that the MSC values were calculated from  field estimates. These errors are present in both survey and test data, and  have affected the results. As no reliable information about the magnitude of  these errors was available, however, it was not possible to make appropriate  corrections. If the observational errors in the calculated MSC values were  independently distributed with zero mean and equal variance, then they    325    would have raised the variogram by that variance. We do not know how this  affects the optimality of the Kriging interpolations. Similarly, the obser-  vational errors will have increased the estimated RMS Errors and standard  deviation within mapping units. The authors expect this increase to be less  than 3 mm.  The results of this study can only be generalized to situations with a simi-  lar type of variability and with a similar pattern of observation points. The  conclusions, of course, remain limited to the survey method and interpola-  tion techniques included in this experiment.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors wish to express their thanks to Dr. P.A. Burrough and  Dr. J. Schelling of The Netherlands Soil Survey Institute for their useful  comments to an earlier draft of this paper.    REFERENCES    Bouma, J., De Laat, P.J.M., Awater, R.C.H.M., Van Holst, A.F., Van Heesen, H.C. and  Van de Nes, Th.J.M., 1980a. Use of soil survey data in a simulation model for predict-  ing regional soil moisture regimes. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 808--814.  Bouma, J., De Laat, P.J.M., Van Holst, A.F. and Van de Nes, Th. J.M., 1980b. Predicting  the effects of changing water-table levels and associated moisture regimes for soil survey  interpretations. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 797--802.  Bouma, J., 1981. Soil Survey Interpretation: estimating use-potentials of a clay soil under  various moisture regimes. Geoderma, 26: 165--177.  Braile, L.W., 1978. Comparison of four random to grid methods. Comput. Geosci., 4:  341--349.  Burgess, T.M. and Webster, R., 1980. Optimal interpolation and isarithmic mapping of  soil properties, 1. The semi-variogram and punctual kriging. J. Soil Sci., 31 : 315--331.  Cochran, W.G., 1977. Sampling Techniques. Wiley, New York.  David, M., 1977. Geostatistical Ore Reserve Estimation. Elsevier, Amsterdam.  Davis, J.C., 1973. Statistics and Data Analysis in Geology. Wiley, New York.  De Bakker, H., 1979. Major soils and soil regions in The Netherlands. Pudoc, Wageningen/  Junk, Den Haag.  De Laat, P.J.M., 1980. Model for unsaturated flow above a shallow water tabel, applied  to a regional sub-surface flow problem. Pudoc, Wageningen, Agric. Res. Rep., 895.  Giltrap, D.J., 1978. Mathematical Techniques for Soil Survey Design. Doct. thesis, Univ.  Oxford.  Matheron, G., 1971. The theory of regionalized variables and its applications. Cah.  CMM Fasc., 5 (ENSMP, Paris.)  Olea, R.A., 1975. Optimal mapping techniques using regionalized variable theory. Series  on spatial analysis, 2. Kans. Geol. Surv., Lawrence.  Rijtema, P.E., 1971. Een berekeningsmethode voor de benadering van de landbouwschade  ten gevolge van grondwateronttrekking. ICW, Wageningen, ICW Nota 587 (in Dutch).  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: a Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Soil Conserv. Serv., USDA. Agric. Handbook, 436.  Washington, DC, 754 pp.  Van Heesen, H.C., 1970. Presentation of seasonal fluctuation of the water table on soil  maps. Geoderma, 4: 257--279.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractThree interpolation techniques were applied to point data on soil moisture supply capacity in a 2km x 2 km area of cover sand in the eastern part of The Netherlands. The interpolation techniques are: Proximal, Weighted Average and Kriging; survey points used for interpolation were stratified random, with an average density of 1.5 per ha. The Root Mean Squared (RMS) Error of these techniques, as estimated from an independent statistical sample, was 37, 29 and 29 mm, respectively, whereas the moisture supply capacity in the area ranged from 50 to 240 mm. Profile descriptions at the same survey points were used to make a soil map (scale 1 : 10 000), the mapping units of which were delineated in the field. Using the means of these mapping units as estimates for points in the area would e.g. have led to an RMS Error of 32 mm if the means were estimated from an additional random sample of 5 profile descriptions per mapping unit or 0.4 per ha. This lower efficiency, compared with Weighted Average and Kriging, should be weighed against the advantage of the soil map of being a basic document that can be directly used for various purposes. 