 Geoderma. 32 (1984) 329--334                                                         329  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CONCENTRIC ZONATION OF GLEYED SOILS UNDER INDIVIDUAL  TREE CANOPIES IN SOUTHWESTERN BRITISH  COLUMBIA,  CANADA    C.B. CRAMPTON  Department of Geography, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, British Columbia, V5A  IS6 (Canada)  (Received October 12, 1982; revised version accepted September 14, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Crampton, C.B., 1984. Concentric zonation of gleyed soils under individual tree canopies  in southwestern British Columbia, Canada. Geoderma, 32: 329--334.    A study was undertaken of concentric zoning of imperfectly and poorly drained,  medium-textured soils around the stems of western hemlock and western red cedar in  the coastal rainforest of British Columbia. The most acid profiles occur near each stem,  and those having the greatest contrast in chroma between mottles and matrix occur be-  neath the periphery of the canopy of each tree. These circular belts of gleyed soils appear  to be associated with, respectively, a limited flow of very acid water from precipitation  down the stem and a much greater flow of less acid water from the periphery of the  canopy.    INTRODUCTION    The distribution of gleyed soils on wetter mountain footslopes in south-  western British Columbia often shows a complex, localized pattern. To help  elucidate this distribution, micro-site studies around individual trees were  undertaken at an elevation of around 200 m on the lower slopes of Burnaby  Mountain. This mountain is a Tertiary sandstone cuesta, 365 m high on its  summit, with a mean annual precipitation of about 2000 mm, decreasing to  about 1250 mm across the lower slopes, an.d falling mostly during the period  November--February. Melting of the Wisconsin ice sheet deposited a mantle  of till over the mountain, thin on the summit, but increasing to about 4 m  on more gently inclined, lower slopes.    METHOD    This study interprets soil profile descriptions below 20 western hemlock  (Tsuga heterophylla (Raf.) Sarg.) and 20 western red cedar (Thuja plicata  Donn.) trees with stem diameters of 54 cm (DBH) and greater, within an    0016-7061/84/$03.00   1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    330    area of about 2 km2 across the lower southern dipslope of Burnaby Moun-  tain. Below each tree a set of profile pits was dug, one as close as was practi-  cal to the stem of the tree, a second beneath the mid-canopy position and a  third under the periphery of the tree canopy.  Systematic, micro-site profile descriptions included measurements of the  horizon thicknesses, the horizon colours recorded in terms of the Munsell  notations and the pH values determined colorimetrically, using bromcresol    I'tiE .%\:r~CA';]  /1"  2E~ ~-V:fI:.. } C]',L: ,if: Wi:.:'!:?b &lt;/:~tl.OC~': ,:C;[" t;l:::';!:!~rJ !.i:D .'K' AI/ ';C: :    Ail    , :ml  C  I    4."  5.4    -,vT{  6 I  %.    ' }: .: ~,    Inlp&lt;,~ fe,at~" dr'air:, ,'.    m    '"I    .4  5. ?  r,','~z    ....  J  6.4    Fig. 1. Average profile characteristics below a tree, from the stem to below the canopy  periphery.    Fig. 2. Photomicrograph of the B horizon of a Fera-Gleysol or Dystric Gteysol below  periphery of the canopy of a tree, showing dark, ochreous deposits around pores and  channels, ferro-manganiferous concretions and a few rootlets in the sandy clay loam.    331  TABLE I  Description of a sequence of profiles below a single tree, from the stem to below the  canopy edge* '    Depth  (cm)  Horizon    Description    At hemlock  0--13  Ah    13--21  Ae    21--30  Bgj    30--48+  C    tree stem:  Very dark gray (5YR 3/1), dry, fibrous organic matter, merging down into  black (5YR 2/1), powdery organic matter with rootlets, pH 4.8. Merging  boundary.  Light gray (5YR 7/1), slightly moist, friable sandy loam having weak, fine,  crumb structure, dissected by pockets and wedges filled with organic-mineral  soil, dark reddish brown (5YR 3/2) mixtures, pH 5.2. Narrow boundary.  Gray (5YR 5/1), with few, fine, faint, reddish gray (5YR 5/2) mottles, moist,  labile sandy clay loam having weak, medium, crumb structure, crossed by  large roots, pH 5.9. Merging boundary.  Light brown (7.5YR 6/4), moist, loose, structureless sandy clay loam blocked  by a few, major roots, pH 6.3.    Below middle canopy:  0--7      Very dark gray (5YR 3/1), slightly moist, fibrous organic matter, merging  Ah      down into black (5YR 2/1), amorphous organic matter with abundant root-  lets. pH 5.5. Merging boundary.  7--21     Very faintly mottled pinkish gray and gray (5YR 7/2 and 6/1), moist, friable  Aej     sandy loam having weak, medium, crumb structure, with roots, pH 6.0. Merg-  ing boundary.  Pinkish gray (5YR 7/2), with common, medium, distinct, reddish brown  (5YR 5/4) mottles, moist, friable sandy clay loam having weak, medium, sub-  angular blocky structure, with roots and rootlets, pH 6.2. Merging boundary.  Light brown (7.5YR 6/4), moist, loose, structureless sandy clay loam with  crystalline erratics and some roots, pH 6.5.    21--30  B~g    30--48+  C    Below canopy periphery:  0--15     Very dark gray (5YR 3/1), slightly moist, thin, fibrous organic matter, merg-  Ah      ing down into thicker, labile organic matter with abundant rootlets, pH 5.4.  Merging boundary.  15--22     Pinkish gray (5YR 6/2), moist, labile sandy loam having medium, blocky  Aegj    structure with roots, pH 5.7. Narrow boundary.  22--37     Pinkish gray (5YR 6/2), with common, large, prominent, yellowish red (5YR  Bfg     5/6 mottles, moist, labile sandy clay loam having weak, medium prismatic  structure, with manganiferous concretions and a few roots, pH 6.4. Merging  boundary.  37--48+    Light brown (7.5YR 6/4), with few, fine, faint, brown (7.5YR 5/2--5/4)  Cgj     mottles, moist, labile sandy clay loam having weak, medium, sub-angular,  blocky structure near top, becoming massive at greater depths, with a few  crystalline erratic boulders, and a few roots, pH 6.4.    *' Horizon notation as in Clayton et al. (1977)    332    green and chlorphenol red indicators. Although colorimetric determinations  of pH are approximate, their use gave means in Fig. 1 ranging from 4.9 to  6.4, with standard deviations of 0.1. These results are sufficiently accurate to  indicate any trends in changing pH values, and yet the method also allowed  extensive field work. Samples from a selection of soil profiles, three of which  are tabulated in Table I, were collected for laboratory analysis of pH electro-  metrically, using a pH meter and of texture, using the pipette method. Soil  thin sections were prepared, one of which is illustrated in Fig. 2.  Within the study area, soils around trees of diameter smaller than 54 cm  (DBH) were examined in the same way so that any soil changes wrought by  the more mature trees could be compared with soil conditions present be-  fore the trees matured.    RESULTS    As in the previous study (Crampton, 1982), a reasonably consistent pat-  tern of profile differences, particularly in soil colours, was observed beneath  tree canopies of western hemlock and western red cedar. Environmental dif-  ferences between sites were minimized by keeping the study area small.  Thus, it has been possible to illustrate the typical profile distribution (Fig.  1), the field differences nowhere obliterating the basic pattern (e.g., Table I).  All the soils showed colour mottling, ranging from faint mottles barely  discernible from the grayer matrix in profiles near the stem, to large reddish  mottles contrasting distinctly with the very light gray matrix in profiles be-  low the canopy periphery. The typical profile near a tree stem was generally  dull in colour and had only a small contrast in chroma between widely separ-  ated, small mottles (each about 2 mm in diameter and 5YR 5/2, reddish  gray), and the matrix (5YR 5/1, gray). This small contrast in colours was  very different from the large contrast in chroma between the closely spaced,  large mottles (each about 5 mm or greater in diameter and 5YR 5/6, yellow-  ish red), and the matrix (5YR 6/2, pinkish gray)in the B horizon of the pro-  file under the periphery of the tree canopy. These ochreous mottles were  often concentrated in root channels (Fig. 2) below a pinkish gray A horizon.  The profile midway between a tree stem and the periphery of the canopy  was intermediate in character, with moderately prominent and medium-  size mottles. These different features were progressively less well expressed  below trees with progressively smaller tree diameters.  The differences in mottling patterns suggest degrees of impedance of the  movement of water through soil profiles. These gleyed soils range generally  from Humic Gleysols near the tree stems to Fera-Gleysols or Dystric Gley-  sols at the edges of the canopies with Gleyed Dystric Brunisols or Gleyic  Cambisols between the two extremes. Placements in the Canadian system  (Clayton et al., 1977) are given first and identification in the legend for the  FAO--Unesco soil map of the world (FAO, 1974) is given second except  where the names are identical, as for Humic Gleysols.    333    Near the tree stem the sub-surface layer of finely comminuted organic  matter, merging into black stains, forms irregular wedges downward into the  grayish sandy loam to an average depth of 20 cm. Below the periphery of the  tree canopy the organic matter was more fibrous in character, and there was  much less evidence of its extension down into the grayish sandy loam. Aver-  age pH values were most acid near the stem of a tree (4.9 in the organic hori-  zon, increasing to 5.9 in the B horizon), less acid beneath the periphery of a  tree canopy (5.4 in the organic horizon, increasing to 6.1 in the B horizon)  and least acid in the site midway between a tree stem and the periphery of  the canopy.  After a rainshower, the soil profile near a tree stem was normally the  driest of the three micro-sites, only isolated trickles occurring as stemflow.  In contrast, because of their form, the trees normally shed most precipita-  tion at the periphery of the canopy (Crampton, 1982).    INTERPRETATIONS    Rainfall flowing through a conifer canopy is acidified, especially near the  stem, though the bulk of the water is concentrated in a peripheral curtain  (Crampton, 1982). The amounts of water near the stem and at the periphery  saturate the medium-textured soils below for a period of time. The wet con-  ditions alternate with relatively dry conditions during seasonal periods with  little rainfall, especially under the canopy edges. The prominent mottling  found under the peripheries of the trees is thus attributed to reduction and  movement of iron during wet periods with oxidation and precipitation dur-  ing dry periods. A photomicrograph of a thin section from the B horizon of  a Gleysol under the canopy edge shows ochreous deposits lining natural  micro-conduits (Fig. 2). The maximum color differentiation between mottles  and matrix in the medium-textured Gleysols under the canopy edges paral-  lels the contrast between eluvial and illuvial horizons of excessively drained  Podzols found in similar positions with respect to tree stems and canopies  in the same area (Crampton, 1982).  As already mentioned, the amounts of water from stemflow are smaller  than those at the periphery, but the stemflow waters are more acid and the  profiles near the stems are also more acid. Moreover, black stains extend to  greater depths in profiles near the stems, and these are ascribed to downward  movement of organic matter. The greater penetration of organic matter, in  turn, is believed responsible for less prominent mottling in the B horizons  of these soil profiles. As with the Gleysols at the edges of the canopies, those  near the tree stems also parallel in some way the Podzols at the bases of  conifer stems in the area (Crampton, 1982).  Zoning of soils around smaller and younger trees in the area is less well  expressed than around larger and older trees. This difference suggests that  the zoning is produced by the normal maturing of the two species of  conifers.    334    CONCLUSIONS    Studies of profiles at various distances from stems of two species of coni-  ferous trees in the temperate rainforest of southwestern British Columbia  demonstrate a number of distinctions in morphology and some in reaction.  These differences are believed to reflect differences in moisture regimes  under the canopy of a single tree. A small volume of strongly acid water  flowing down the stem acidifies the profile and permits deeper migration  of organic matter, causing limited contrast between mottles and matrix.  Associated with a much greater but less acid volume of water at the canopy  edges are less acid softs with marked contrasts between mottles and matrices.  That contrast is considered to reflect alternating intervals of anaerobic and  aerobic conditions and less interference by organic matter in precipitation of  iron oxides. Differences in moisture regimes can apparently be substantial  under a single tree, a condition with implications to understanding soil pat-  terns under forest cover and to forestry practice.    REFERENCES    Clayton, J.S., Ehrlich, W.A., Cann, D.B., Day, J.H. and Marshall, I.B., 1977. Soils of  Canada. Research Branch, Can. Dept. Agric., Ottawa, Ont., 243 pp.  Crampton, C.B., 1982. Podzolization of soils under individual tree canopies in south-  western British Columbia, Canada. Geoderma, 28: 57---61.  FAO, 1974. FAO--Unesco Soil Map of the World, Vol. 1, Legend. Unesco, Paris, 59 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractA study was undertaken of concentric zoning of imperfectly and poorly drained, medium-textured soils around the stems of western hemlock and western red cedar in the coastal rainforest of British Columbia. The most acid profiles occur near each stem, and those having the greatest contrast in chroma between mottles and matrix occur beneath the periphery of the canopy of each tree. These circular belts of gleyed soils appear to be associated with, respectively, a limited flow of very acid water from precipitation down the stem and a much greater flow of less acid water from the periphery of the canopy. 