 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 355--371                                                     355  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    MORPHOLOGY, SPATIAL ARRANGEMENT AND ORIGIN OF  MACROPORES IN SOME HAPLUDALFS, WEST GERMANY    R. TIPPKOTTER  Institut fiir Bodenkunde, Universit~'t Hannover, D 3000 Hannover 21 (Bundesrepublik  Deutschland)  (Received November 4, 1981; accepted after revision October 6, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Tippk6tter, R., 1983. Morphology, spatial arrangement and origin of macropores in some  Hapludalfs, West Germany. Geoderma, 29: 355--371.    Twenty oriented blocks, roughly 10 cm along each edge, were collected from the Bv  and C horizons of four Hapludalfs near Hannover (West Germany). At least two blocks  were obtained from each horizon of each profile. The macropores (0.1--1 mm) in these  blocks were then examined by micromorphological methods. The 3-dimensional arrange-  ments of pores were observed by two approaches, viz., (1) preparing photographic  sequences of successive polished sections obtained from the sample blocks and then stack-  ing photographs to simulate pore geometry; (2) preparing resin casts of tubular pores.  Examination of stacked photographs and the resin casts by scanning electron microscopy  (SEM) followed by electron-optical image analyses indicate interconnected systems of pores  with the most frequently occurring diameters between 150 and 250 urn. Interconnections  among pores are very similar in numbers throughout the Bv horizons.  Comparisons of the diameters, branching, and tapering of macropores with similar  features of plant roots suggest that most pores between 0.1 and 1 mm have been produced  by roots. Some may be due to fauna, but all seem to have been of biological origin and  are therefore considered biopores.    INTRODUCTION    Many soils formed in loess in the Federal Republic of Germany have promi-  nent systems of tubular macropores, 0.1--1 mm in diameter, throughout their  profiles (Bailly, 1973). These are the so-called "Nadelstichporen" or "pin-  holes". The origin of these pores down to depths of 0.5--1 m can be attributed  to recent biological activities (Bailly and Hartge, 1967). Below depths of 1 m,  however, both roots and animals are far less common.  Pinholes are of ecological importance in relation to the growth of roots and  the balance of air and water of soils (Hartge, 1978; Jenny, 1980). Consequent-  ly, the nature of macropores has been studied by soil physicists and micro-  morphologists for a long time. Methods in soil physics provide indirect informa-  tion on the nature of the pores, whereas those of micromorphologists furnish    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    356    direct observation but are essentially limited to polished sections or thin  sections. In addition to the observations of thin sections, efforts have been  made to get 3-dimensional images by stacking photographs of successively cut  thin sections (Beckmann, 1964; Lafeber, 1965). Examination of voids or  pores with stereomicroscopes and SEM's has largely been restricted to natural  partings and fractures in the soil matrix. Thus far, such methods have not  provided clear images of the spatial arrangements of macropores.  The aim of this investigation was to devise methods for examination of pin-  holes that would characterize their geometry and thereby permit evaluations  of their dimensions, continuity and origins.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Twenty undisturbed blocks were selected from the Bv and C horizons of  four profiles, Hapludalfs according to the U.S.D.A. system (Soil Survey Staff,  1975) and Parabraunerde according to Milckenhausen (1962). These softs were  developed in loess, 2.0--2.2 m thick, over glacial till resting on gravel in a high  river bank south of Hannover (West Germany). All four profiles were free of  groundwater. The samples were taken at depths between 1.15 and 2.15 m.  Vegetation at the four locations was either meadow (mixed grasses) or  "ruderal" roadside communities (Arternisia, Taraxacum officinale, Cirsium  arvense, Dactylis glornerata and others).  Two methods were used to obtain 3-dimensional records of tubular macro-  pores. These were: (1) optical reconstruction of pores; (2) isolation of resin-  filled pores.  The optical reconstruction of pores consisted of several steps. The first was  to obtain successive polished sections of soil material from the undisturbed  blocks as described by Beckmann (1964). Several small cubes with edge lengths  of approximately 5 cm were cut from each block, air-dried, and completely  impregnated with a polyester resin (Vestopal, Chemische Werke Hills, FRG)  coloured with a white dye (pigment size &lt; 1 pm) at a vacuum pressure of  about 8 mbar (800 Pa). After the resin had hardened, 2--3 cm of the cubes  were ground down with a diamond disc at 100 pm intervals. At each stage a  plane surface of 12 18 mm of the polished sections was photographed in such  a way that the white resin-filled pores were clearly distinguishable from the  dark solids on an orthochromatic film, then copied on industrial lith-film (see  Figs. 4, 15).  The sequence of photographs thus produced, converted to a digitized form  and distorted into parallelograms (Optronics P 1700), was photographically  copied along a vertical axis. As a result block diagrams were obtained which  allow an initial impression of systems of tubular macropores (Fig. 1).  The photographs of polished sections were used, moreover, to construct a  parallel projection in one plane of layers 3--4 mm thick (Fig. 2). For this  purpose 30--40 photographs, taken of successive polished sections as describ-  ed above, were enlarged on 13 18 cm planfilms which were subsequently  copied to outline the tubular macropores in that slice of the soil block.    357                                           15ram  Fig. 1. Block diagram of pores in the Bv horizon of a Hapludalf. Pores smaller than 30 ~m  were omitted (solid substance white; pores grey).    The two methods provide a simple way of using diagrams for the study of  several aspects of void morphology, i.e. diameters, lengths and interconnec-  tions.  The photographs were also used to determine pore size distribution in the  range of 50--2000/~m by means of an automatic image analyzer on a televi-  sion base (Leitz T.A.S.). In this procedure, the pores are black in the photo-  graphs and can easily be identified on the TV screen. Subsequently, the largest  possible hexagon is placed within each marked pore on the TV screen with the  aid of an integral computer (Mfiller, 1973; TippkStter and Reichenbach, 1977).  A program to count pores within size intervals of 50 ~m is then used to  estimate numbers with various diameters (see Fig. 8).  The second method of describing the macropores consisted of the isolation  of resin-filled pores. Blocks of undisturbed soil material with an edge length  of 5--10 cm were completely impregnated with molten paraffin wax. Next  the paraffin in pores greater than 20--30 pm diameter was removed by the  method of Richards (1949). The pressure necessary for the removal of the  paraffin cannot be calculated exactly because the magnitude of the interfacial  tension between the paraffin wax and the residual soil water is unknown due  to pollution of the paraffin by soil components and to changes of temper-  ature during the procedure. Experiments have shown, however, that placing  the soil blocks at room temperature on an absorbent surface (filter paper) is  sufficient for drainage of pores greater than 20--30 pm.  After the residual paraffin had hardened, the blocks were impregnated with  Araldite resin which does not adhere to the paraffin. After polymerization of  the resin some of the paraffin was evaporated at 120. Subsequently, the  framework of resin was cleaned of soil materials and residual paraffin wax in    358    Fig. 2. Combination of 30 successive polished sections (cut level distance 0.1 ram) show-  ing tubular macropores photographed and assembled one on top of the other (solid  substance grey; pores black).    an ultrasonic bath with hot water (80). The result was a resin cast of those  pores which were interconnected and linked with the base of the block (Fig. 3).  Isolated voids do not appear.  The advantage of this method over similar approaches of other workers  (Martin and Survant, 1958; Green and Askew, 1965; Rogaar, 1974) is that a  stable cast is obtained showing details of pores down to 5 ~m.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Morphology and arrangement of macropores    Diagrams based on the photographs of polished sections indicate that the  systems of pores consist mostly of interconnected tubular pores forming a    359    Fig. 3. Resin cast of tubular macropores in the Bv horizon of a Hapludalf.    3-dimensional network (Fig. 4). For macropores, this conclusion is supported  by optical reconstruction of the systems within soil blocks and also by the  isolation of the framework formed by filling pores with resin (Fig. 5). The  very fine "texture" of the spatial arrangement does not become evident, how-  ever, except from SEM observations of soil blocks impregnated with resin.  The interconnections among pores then appear in detail (Fig. 6).  Stereometric observations with T.A.S. equipment indicate that frequency  distribution of tubular pores according to diameters has a maximum between  150 and 250 pm in these sample blocks (Fig. 7a). Moreover, the observations  also show that macropores between 100 and 400/~m in diameter are significant  ly more numerous in the upper (1.15--1.5 m) than lower (1.5--2.15 m) parts  of the Bv horizons (Fig. 8). The cause or causes of this difference cannot be  established from the data at hand, but it seems highly probable that the total  number of macropores in that size range are directly correlated with depth of  rooting. The number of roots is much greater in the upper parts of these hori-  zons than in the lower ones. Even so, the possibility that changes in vegetation  during periods of loess deposition were responsible for present differences  cannot be eliminated.  Interconnections among tubular pores are the same in the upper and lower  parts of the Bv horizons. This finding is consistent with previous results by  Hartge and Bailly (1967) who concluded from indirect determinations that  differences in the continuity of pores with depth were negligible in a Para-  braunerde from loess.    360    Fig. 4. Interconnection of pores shown in a polished section (solid substance grey; pores  black).    Origin of tubular macropores    The formation of tubular macropores in soils has been attributed to the  effects of both fauna and flora {Brewer, 1964). Possible contributions of both  types of organisms to the formation of the pores in the horizons of the Haplu-  dalfs are therefore considered in this section.  Animals responsible for tubular pores would presumably be burrowing  species with cylindrical bodies having diameters of 0.1--12 mm. Ants and  earthworms have those dimensions (Miiller, 1965). These species seem likely  to be most commonly present as well.  Ants tend to produce galleries of various dimensions connecting chambers  of irregular shapes. In Germany, ants and their galleries generally are absent    361    Fig. 5. Scanning electron micrograph displaying the resin cast of tubular macropores.    below depths of 1 m (Miiller, 1965). Consequently, it is believed that ants  were not responsible for the pores in the Bv and C horizons that were studied.  Observations in western Europe also indicate that most of the earthworms  extend their burrows to maximum depths near 1.5 m (Dunger, 1964). Hoekse-  ma and Jongerius (1959) found earthworm channels ranging from 1 to 8 mm  in diameter to depths of 1.2 to 1.5 m in The Netherlands. Dunger (1964) re-  ported that only large species such as Lumbricus terrestris and Allolobophora  terrestris produce burrows, 3 to 11 mm in diameter, down to the water table  or the solid rock. Earthworms of diameters smaller than 1 mm have penetra-  tion depths less than 1.2 m. Therefore, they may be largely excluded as  producers of tubular pores smaller than 1 mm in the Bv and C horizons stu-  died.    362    Fig. 6. Scanning electron micrograph of the interconnection of two resin-filled tubular  macropores.    If the tubular pores are formed by roots, they should have the following  characteristics: (1) diameters similar to those of roots alive now or in the recent  past, (2) root-like ramifications; (3) lateral spurs of subsidiary pores caused by  root hairs; (4) tapering of diameters if roots were perennial.  Correspondence of pore diameters with those of living roots can readily be  demonstrated. The frequency distribution of diameters of macropores in these  soil blocks shows a maximum between 150 and 250 ~m (Fig. 7a). Thus, pore  diameters closely parallel those of living roots of a roadside vegetation and  cereals in the same horizons {Fig. 7b, c). Roots were separated after ultrasonic  dispersion of soil materials. Diameters of roots were measured on SEM photo-  graphs.  Root-like ramifications of pores are best characterized by three features.    363    tel.  frequ.  %  30=    20-    10-    100    a.    I          I          I          I  200    300    400    500    600 ~m  Pore diameter groups    rel.  frequ  %  30-    201  10-  I  100    b.    I           I           I           I  200      300      400      500      600 pm  Diameters of living roots    re I.  frequ  %    30-    12.    20-  10-  100     200     300     400     500    600 pm  Diameters  of cereal  roots  Fig. 7. Frequency distribution of diameters: a. resin-filled tubular macropores (n = 108,  roadside vegetation); b. roots (n = 46, roadside vegetation); c. roots (n = 52, cereals).    364    14-  12-  10-  8-  6"  4-  2-  50-  100    prOld,' dept h~     115-150m                        1  Pore Ch:H~,eH~r grolJps    Fig. 8. Volume of macropores in different regions of Bv horizons (Hapludalf).    Fig. 9. Scanning electron micrograph of root-like ramifications of resin-filled biopores.    365    These are: (1) the frequency of branching side channels from main channels  (dendritic character); (2) side channels with smaller diameters than main  channels; and (3) constant angles between main and side channels, commonly  close to 90(Fig. 9). Main and side channels are attributable to both higher  and lower order roots. As shown in Figs. 10 and 11, side channel pores or  branches correspond exactly in morphology to those patterns formed by root  hairs branching from larger roots.  To detect tapering of tubular pores, their diameter must be examined over  a distance of at least 10 mm. Such observations cannot be made with the SEM.  Consequently, a sequence of images from polished faces of a block was used  to identify tapering. Fig. 12 shows the projection of a pinhole derived from 70  separate photographs. This pore, which extended laterally from a larger vertical  pore, has a length of 15 mm and tapers from about 600 #m at one end to 220  pm at the other.  Evidence that fauna not responsible for macropores less than 1 mm in  diameter at depths of I m or more is provided by SEM observations of channel  cutans. The term, cutan, is used as defined by Brewer (1964). Some of the  tunneling animals eject excrements which coat the walls of their burrows or  channels stabilizing them at the same time; e.g. earthworms cement their  channels with an "earthworm-calcite" (Graff, 1953; Dunger, 1964) produced  by the endocrine glands. Called channel cutans by Brewer (1964), these coat-  ings have a distinctive morphology (Fig. 13) and are easily distinguished from  grain cutans, which occur on surfaces of discrete units. Remnants of grain  cutans are preserved in bowl-shaped particle impressions (ca. 20-200 pm in  diameter) on the framework of resin (Fig. 14). Channel cutans that can be  ascribed to animals appear sporadically. These observations indicate that fauna  is responsible for practically none of the tubular pores 0.1 to 1 mm in diameter  at depths of 1 m or more in these Hapludalfs.  Observations made on these Bv and C horizons strongly support the inter-  pretation that the pinholes are due chiefly to roots, although a few may have  been formed by animals. Consequently, these pores are labeled biopores,  following the definition given by Jongerius and Rutherford (1979).    Some reflections on the age of pinholes in the soils studied    Pinholes occur in loess deposits up to quite considerable depths at many  different places all over the world (Stace et al., 1968; Jenny~ 1980; R.W.  Simonson, personal communication, 1982). It seems probable that these pores  are formed partly by roots, which are present during the loess accumulation as  reported by Rieger and Juve (1961). Observations on buried soils from loess  (Sabelberg et al., 1976) show that a great number of such tubular pores can be  preserved over a number of glacial periods.  In the soils studied pinholes are found down to the base of the loess (2.0-  2.2 m). Micromorphological investigations of thin sections (prepared according  to Altemiiller, 1974) indicate that some of the pinholes, approximately 10--20%    366    Fig. 10. Scanning electron micrograph of roots (a) and roothairs (b), taken from a Bv  horizon of a Hapludalf.    367    Fig. 11. Scanning electron micrograph of a resin cast of tubular macropores produced by  roots (a) and roothairs (b) (location: refer to Fig. 10).    368            ,2mm    /    Fig. 12. Biopore caused by roots, reconstructed from 70 photographs of successive polish-  ed sections (distance: 0.1 mm).    !  t  1  i    Fig. 13. Scanning electron micrograph displaying excrements of an earthworm on the wall  on a resin cast of a tubular macropore.    369    Fig. 14. Scanning electron micrograph showing residual cutans of minerals left in bowl-  shaped impressions on the surface of a resin cast of a tubular macropore.    are destroyed by burrowing animals. Fig. 15 shows two tubular pores 250 pm  in diameter which are met by an earthworm tube.  It seems that this destruction of pinholes is a process that has lasted from the  beginning of loess deposition up to the present in certain soils containing deep  burrowing animals. Inasmuch as the population of earthworms in silty soils in  West Germany occurs with an average density of 50 to 90 per m2 (Niklas et al.,  1979), it can be assumed that most of the pinholes will disappear due to the  activities of the earthworms over time unless new pinholes are produced. The  number of pinholes apparently does not decrease though. Presumably deep  rooting plants such as Taraxacum officinale, Cirsium arvense and A rtem isia  vulgaris (2.0--2.8 m root depths according to Oberdorfer, 1979) are forming    370    Fig. 15. Destruction of tubular macropores (arrows) caused by an earthworm (solid  substance grey; pores black; between lines: filled earthworm tube).    new pinholes at present while burrowing animals destroy part of them. It seems  likely, therefore, that the biopores smaller than 1 mm are of different ages in  the soils studied.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Financial support of this work by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft is  gratefully acknowledged.    371    REFERENCES    Altemiiller, H.J., 1974. Mikroskopie der BSden mit Hilfe yon Diinnschliffen. In: H. Freund  (Editor), Handbuch der Mikroskopie in der Technik, IV., DLG-Verlag, Frankfurt, pp.  309--367.  Bailly, F., 1973. Zur Vergesellschaftung der BSden in der nSrdlichen Calenberger BSrde.  Geol. Jahrb., F. 1,135 pp.  Bailly, F. and Hartge, K.H., 1967. Porenvolumen und PorengrSssenverteilung in LSss-  Parabraunerden im siidlichen Niedersachsen. Z. Pflanzenern~/hr. Bodenkd., 115 : 17--28.  Beckmann, W., 1964. Zur Ermittlung des dreidimensionalen Aufbaues der Bodenstruktur  mit Hilfe mikromorphometrischer Methoden. In: A. Jongerius (Editor), Soil Micro-  morphology, Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 429--444.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 470 pp.  Dunger, W., 1964. Tiere im Boden. Ziemsen, Wittenberg, 265 pp.  Graft O., 1953. Die Regenw/irmer Deutschlands. Schaper, Hannover, 81 pp.  Green, R.D. and Askew, G.P., 1965. Observations on the biological development of macro-  pores in soils of Romney Marsh. J. Soil Sci., 16: 342--349.  Hartge, K.H., 1978. Einf/ihrung in die Bodenphysik. Enke, Stuttgart, 364 pp.  Hartge, K.H. and Bailly, F., 1967. Beziehungen zwischen Staun~issemerkmalen, Wasserleit-  f~/higkeit und Porenkontinuit~'t in LSss-Parabraunerden im siidlichen Niedersachsen.  Z. Pflanzenern~ihr. Bodenkd., 116: 10--25.  Hoeksema, K.J. and Jongerius, A., 1959. On the influence of earthworms on the soil  structure in mulched orchards. Proc. Int. Symp. Soil Structure, Ghent, pp. 188--194.  Jenny, H., 1980. The Soil Resource. Springer, New York, N.Y., 377 pp.  Jongerius, A. and Rutherford, G.K. (Editors), 1979. Glossary of Soil Micromorphology.  Pudoc, Wageningen, 138 pp.  Lafeber, D. 1965. The graphical representation of planar pore pattern in soils. Aust. J. Soil  Res., 3: 143--164.  Martin, C.K. and Survant, W.G., 1958. A visual aid for studying soil pore space. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 22: 184--185.  M/ickenhausen, E., 1962. Entstehung, Eigenschaften und Systematik der BSden der Bundes-  republik Deutschland. DLG-Verlag, Frankfurt/M., 148 pp.  Miiller, G., 1965. Bodenbiologie. Fischer, Jena, 889 pp.  M/iUer, W. 1973. Das Leitz Textur-Analyse-System. Leitz Mitt., Suppl. I, 4: 101--116.  Niklas, F., Weller, F. and Kennel, W., 1979. Zum Einfluss von obstbaulichen Bodenpflege-  massnahmen auf Lumbriciden, insbesondere Lumbricus terrestris L. Z. Pflanzenern~/hr.  Bodenkd., 142: 411--421.  Oberdorfer, E., 1979. Pflanzensoziologische Exkursionsflora. Ulmer, Stuttgart, 997 pp.  Richards, L.A., 1949. Methods of measuring soil moisture tension. Soil Sci., 68: 95--112.  Rieger, S. and Jure, R.L., 1961. Soil development in recent loess in the Matanuska Valley,  Alaska. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 25: 243--248.  Rogaar~ H., 1974. Polyester casts for study of the pore structure in soils. Neth. J. Agricult.  Sci., 22: 143--152.  Sabelberg, U., Mavrocordat, G., Rohdenburg, H. and SchSnhals, E., 1976. Quart~gliederung  und Aufbau von Warmzeit-Kaltzeit-Zyklen in Bereichen mit Dominanz periglazialer  Hangsedimente, dargestellt am Quar~rprofil Dreihausen/Hessen. Eiszeitalter Ggw., 27:  93--120.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A basic system of soil classification for making and  interpreting soil surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436,754 pp.  Stace, H.C.T., Hubble, G.D., Brewer, R., Northcote, K.H., Sleeman, J.R., Mulcahy, M.J.  and Hallsworth, E.G., 1968. A Handbook of Australian Soils. Rellim, Glenside, S.A.,  435 pp.  Tippk6tter R. and Reichenbach, H. Graf v., 1977. Einige Ergebnisse der Gefiigeunter-  suchungen mit Hilfe der quantitativen elektronischen Bildanalyse an BSden der Hildes-  heimer BSrde. Mitt. Dtsch. Bodenkdl. Ges., 25: 767--772.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractTwenty oriented blocks, roughly 10 cm along each edge, were collected from the Bv and C horizons of four Hapludalfs near Hannover (West Germany). At least two blocks were obtained from each horizon of each profile. The macropores (0.1–1 mm) in these blocks were then examined by micromorphological methods. The 3-dimensional arrangements of pores were observed by two approaches, viz., (1) preparing photographic sequences of successive polished sections obtained from the sample blocks and then stacking photographs to simulate pore geometry; (2) preparing resin casts of tubular pores.Examination of stacked photographs and the resin casts by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) followed by electron-optical image analyses indicate interconnected systems of pores with the most frequently occurring diameters between 150 and 250 μm. Interconnections among pores are very similar in numbers throughout the Bv horizons.Comparisons of the diameters, branching, and tapering of macropores with similar features of plant roots suggest that most pores between 0.1 and 1 mm have been produced by roots. Some may be due to fauna, but all seem to have been of biological origin and are therefore considered biopores. 