Geoderma, 31 (1983) 355--356                                                  355  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Proceedings of the Symposium on Peatlands Below Sea Level. H. de Bakker  and M.W. van den Berg (Editors). International Institute for Land Rec-  lamation and Improvement (ILRI) P.O. Box, 6700 AA Wageningen,  1982, 296 pp.    This publication includes the proceedings of a symposium on peatlands  lying below sea level in the western part of The Netherlands, held August  24--28, 1981. It was jointly sponsored by Commission III (Chemistry  and Physics) of the International Peat Society and the Netherlands Soil  Science Society. The proceedings were published by the International  Institute for Land Reclamation and Improvement.  The subjects discussed at this symposium on peatlands below sea level  include their geology, soils, reclamation history, engineering properties,  management and utilization. Twenty four papers delivered at the sym-  posium were divided into three sections: geography, engineering and land  use with a review for each section. In addition, a two-day excursion was  held in the western Netherlands including a visit to an experimental farm  for cattle husbandry and a research station for ornamental nursery crops,  flowers and vegetables.  These proceedings include an excellent historical record of early peat-  tand reclamation efforts in Holland, England and N.W. Germany. The  authors discussed early attempts at reclaiming these lands for agriculture  with details of methods of drainage and water control. Settlement and  reclamation of the Dutch fenlands (non-acid peatlands) began in earnest  about 1100 A.D. After this period dikes were systematically constructed  to control the water and permit the growing of grain crops. Production  of grain crops ceased in the 15th century due to peat shrinkage and was  replaced by perennial grass crops and dairy farming.  Regional water control boards were established early for handling proj-  ects of diking and drainage. The drained areas surrounded and protected  by dikes became known as the famous Dutch polders. The water control  boards continued to administer laws governing drainage and water control.  Water pumping became sophisticated with the advent of windmills but  in more modem times gave way to pumping with mechanical power.  The papers concerning the formation and properties of soil and their  genesis are both informative and quite detailed. Peats formed in these  lowland areas because of rising groundwaters due to sea level rises in post-  glacial time. Initially, the peat-covered areas were above mean sea level  but due to intensive use and cutting of peat for fuel, shrinkage (subsidence)  took place and the surfaces are presently a few meters below sea level.  Very few undrained peatlands remain in Holland and most of the reclaimed  areas have been altered by additions of sand, manure and muds to fields.    356    The paper discussing the effects of drainage on the behavior of peat  softs is of interest to peatland developers. The causes of subsidence related  to water levels, type of crops grown, management and mechanization were  discussed and detailed data given.  In the section on land use, uses of peatlands for both agriculture and  urban developments were discussed. The principal agricultural use of these  lands is for grass production. The paper on urban uses of peatlands dis-  cussed the problems with building foundations, road construction and  recreation area developments.  The most extensive reclamation efforts in Holland as reported in this  publication took place in the Holland--Utrecht lowland plain roughly  bounded by Amsterdam, Utrecht and Rotterdam near where the Rhine  and Meuse rivers flow to the North Sea.  The reviewer of the papers about soils stated that only the Dutch and  Polish systems for classification of organic soil distinguish between natural  undrained peat soils and the drained peat soils subject to oxidation. The  U.S. Soil Taxonomy does not account for altered organic soils in his opin-  ion.  The proceedings are valuable in that the long experience of the Dutch  in developing their peatlands, including all the problems they encountered,  should greatly contribute to the development of peatland areas in other  parts of the world. This publication should be of interest to peat scien-  tists, horticulturists, agronomists and land use planners.    R.S. FARNHAM  (St. Paul, Minn.)    Soil Conservation --Problems and Prospects. R.P.C. Morgan (Editor). John  Wiley, Chichester, 1981, xvi + 576 pp., 22.00.    This book is a collection of papers presented at an International Confer-  ence on Soft Conservation held in Silsoe, United Kingdom in July 1980.  The 42 papers presented include contributions from most areas of the world  with soil conservation problems, including China and U.S.S.R.  Four major aspects are explored: land classification and erosion assess-  ment for conservation design, preventative and control measures, erosion  models and economic, social and legal aspects. Of particular note in the  modelling sections, is a number of papers describing the progress made  in developing models based on sounder physical principles than those con-  sidered in the Universal Soil Loss Equation, which will allow in future con-  servation practices to be included. The volume provides a useful up-to-date  assessment of the current position in soil conservation research, develop-  ment and field application, and will be of particular interest to those con-  cerned with soil erosion evaluation and soil conservation practice.    G. SPOOR  (Silsoe, Bedford)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  