Geoderma, 34 (1984) 69--100                                                    69  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    TENTATIVE ASSESSMENT OF SOIL SURVEY APPROACHES TO THE  CHARACTERIZATION AND INTERPRETATION OF AIR--WATER  PROPERTIES OF SOILS.1    J.A. McKEAGUE', R.G. EILERS', A.J. THOMASSON2, M.J. REEVE2, J. BOUMA3,  R.B. GROSSMAN4, J.C. FAVROTs, M. RENGER~ and O. STREBEL6  1 Land Resource Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, Ont. (Canada)  2 Soil Survey of England and Wales, Rothamsted Experimental Station, Harpenden, Herts.  (Great Britain)  3 Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, Wageningen (The Netherlands)  4 Soil Conservation Service, U.S.D.A., Lincoln, Nebraska (U.S.A.)  S Service d'Etude des Sols, LN.R.A., Montpellier (France)  6 Niedersachsisches Landesamt fiir Bodenforschung, Hannover (F.R.G.)  (Received March 7, 1984; revised version accepted July 12, 1984)    ABSTRACT    McKeague, J.A., Eilers, R.G., Thomasson, A.J., Reeve, M.J., Bouma, J., Grossman, R.B.,  Favrot, J.C., Renger, M. and Strebel, O., 1984. Tentative assessment of soil survey  approaches to the characterization and interpretation of air--water properties of soils.  Geoderma, 34: 69--100.    Procedures used by soil survey organizations in characterizing and interpreting the air--  water regimes of soils in France, Germany, The Netherlands, England and Wales, the  United States and Canada are summarized and compared. The strengths and weaknesses  of the systems are discussed, and research is suggested to resolve problems and to improve  the basis of interpretations. The importance of sound field estimates supported regularly  by reliable measurements is emphasized. Field estimates are essential in view of the  dynamic nature and the spatial variability of some soil physical properties related to the  air--water regimes. Research needs include continued development of improved methods  of measuring air--water properties of soils, development of improved guidelines for esti-  mating these properties from soil morphology, and identification of the relevant soil  properties that can be estimated reliably. Interdisciplinary research is required to inte-  grate expertise in hydrology, soil physics, agronomy and pedology with a view to im-  proving the characterization and interpretation of air--water properties of soils.    INTRODUCTION    Soil survey organizations in many countries are interested in both the  water regime of soil in relation to soil genesis and the seasonal sequence of  air--water states of soils as applied to the evaluation of soils for crop produc-    *Contribution No. 84-10 L.R.R.I.    0016-7061/84/$03.00     1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    70    tion and other uses. The latter aspect has been in the forefront for some  years as soil survey organizations have worked to increase the practical inter-  pretation of soil maps. Some of the relevant air--water properties of soils  are: depth to saturated layer and duration of saturation by groundwater or  surface water; capacity of the soil to retain water available to plants; this is  referred to as 'plant-available water' (Av); percentage of the soil volume at a  low negative pressure (-5 to -10 kPa) occupied by air, referred to as 'air  capacity' (Ca); saturated and unsaturated hydraulic conductivity (Ksat and  Kunsat of soil horizons; typical water content profile.from month to month.  Soil survey organizations of different countries have used different kinds  and combinations of field observations, field measurements and laboratory  measurements in assembling data on air--water properties of soils. They have  also used different approaches in extrapolating and interpreting the data in  relation to evaluating land for production of crops and for other uses. Some  differences in methods may be related to unique properties of soils, to climat-  ic differences, and to particular major crops in the different countries. Other  differences are probably due to independent development of methods and  interpretations. The purposes of this report are to summarize the approaches  used in several countries, to note similarities and differences, to evaluate  the approaches, to note some research needs, and to suggest improved  approaches or combinations of approaches that might lead to simpler and  better techniques for evaluation by soil survey organizations of the air--  water properties of soils in relation to their potential for crop production.    SUMMARY OF APPROACHES    Most soil survey organizations assess air--water properties of soils relative  to their potential for crop production. Six such approaches are summarized  here. The basis of the choice is somewhat arbitrary; the intention is to in-  clude the most advanced approaches that would apply in cool temperate  regions.    The Netherlands    The Netherlands is unique in having comprehensive data on water table  fluctuations throughout many years for most soils of the country (Van  Heesen, 1970). There is also an impressive amount of data on measured soil  properties such as bulk density, water release characteristics and hydraulic  conductivity.  Characterization by the soil survey of air--water regimes of Dutch soils  (Haans, 1980) is part of a system of land evaluation that follows the concepts  of FAO (1976). Air--water properties are associated with four land qualities:  drainage status, moisture supply capacity (plant-available water), internal  drainage and bearing capacity (Table I). Suitabilities for different types of  land use are derived from these land qualities, using tables that have been  compiled with empirical methods based on field experience (e.g. Table II).    71  TABLE I  Classes (levels) of drainage status, moisture supply capacity and bearing capacity used by  the Netherlands soil survey    Level  Drainage status              Moisture supply capacity*~   Bearing capacity.2  mean highest groundwater  level (cm below surface)    level   moisture supply      level    soil strength  (mm)                        (MPa)    1         ~80                                                         1         -*200                                       1             -*0.75  2             40--80                                                2             150--200                            2                0.50--0.75  3      25--40                       3      100--150             3      *-0.50  4      15--25                      4       50--100  5      *-15                         5     ,-50    ,1 Water retained between-10 and-1500 kPa in the root zone plus upward flow from  the water table.  ,2 Determined by penetrometer resistance of surface soil at the time of mean highest  groundwater level.    TABLE II    Simplified key for grassland suitability assessment in The Netherlands derived from drainage status,  moisture supply capacity and bearing capacity*~    Moisture supply  Drainage status:   1+2              3               4               5  capacity  Bearing capacity: 1       2         1     2         2     3    2    3    1                                      I.I     1.2       I.I    1.2       2.1    3.1       2.1    3.1  2                                      1.3     1.4       1.3    1.4       2.1    3.1       2.1    --  3                                      2.2     2.3       2.2    2.3       2.3    3.1       3.1    --  4                                                                            3.2           --                 3.2  .....  5                                      3.2  .......    ,I Suitability main class and subclass are indicated in order, e.g. 1.3. See Table I for ranges of drainage  status and bearing capacity classes.    Current estimation of land qualities  Drainage status. The assessment of drainage status is based on measured  water table data (Van Heesen, 1970; Van der Sluijs and de Gruijter, 1984).  Attempts to estimate water table fluctuations from soil mottling features  have been largely abandoned. Many mottling features are relict, whereas  water table levels have been altered markedly by man's activities in recent  centuries. Five classes of mean highest groundwater level (Table I) are used  in making interpretations.  Plant-available water. Estimates of plant-available water are based on  observed depths of rooting in the soft, measured water retention data (de-  sorption curves) and estimates of upward unsaturated flow of water from the  water table to the root zone. Water retained between pressures of -10 and  -1500 kPa is usually considered to be readily available to plants; the -1500  kPa limit is, however, being strongly questioned. Water retention data for    72    horizons have been obtained in the past for many soils using desorption of  small soil cores with the standard sand-bed technique. Estimates for soil  horizons are being made now from regression equations relating particle size  distribution (% clay), organic matter content and bulk density to v~ater con-  tents at different pressure heads.  Upward flow of water from a water table to the root zone cannot be  measured directly; it is calculated from measured K(S) curves (see example  in Bouma, 1977). Based on such calculations, upward flow is being estimated  from soil texture data in very broad classes. An estimate is made of the  height above the water table to which a steady flux of 2 mm/day can be  maintained. This height is compared with the lower boundary of the root  zone. Three classes are distinguished:  (1) Upward flow into the root zone of at least 2 mm/day throughout the  growing season (always class 1 in Table I).  (2) Upward flow of 2 mm/day never reaches the root zone during the  growing season.  (3) Upward flow of 2 mm/day reaches the root zone only during an early  part of the growing season, the duration of which can be estimated.  The total amount of water that flows upward from the water table to the  root zone in class 3 is estimated by considering the period during which the  flux of 2 mm/day reaches the root zone. It is an important component of  plant available water in many Dutch soils.  Rooting depth is determined by observation in soil pits. The effective  depth of rooting is taken to be the depth above which 80% of the roots oc-  cur (Bouma, 1981b). Water extraction patterns in the growing season are  also measured to estimate the "effective" depth of rooting. Plant-available  water is defined for the root zone; it is determined by adding water retained  between -10 and -1500 kPa to the upward flow from the water table. Five  classes are defined (Table I).  Internal drainage. Assessment of internal drainage is based on measure-  ment of Ksat (Bouma, 1983a) in selected representative soils. Extrapolation  of these data to other soils is based on empirical comparisons of soil texture,  structure and classification. Soil structure observations, pedality and macro-  porosity (Jongerius, 1957), are interpreted qualitatively.  Bearing capacity. This land quality is strongly related to the soil water  regime. It is determined by measuring penetrometer resistance of surface  soil at the time when the mean highest groundwater-level occurs. Three  classes are distinguished as shown in Table I.    Associated research on land qualities  The land evaluation system being used now has limitations. Drainage  status, for example, is derived only from water-table levels although drainage  characteristics of clays and sands are quite different, requiring a different  approach (Bouma, 1981b). A major problem is the selection of static criteria  to define land qualities that are dynamic by nature.    73    Research is therefore strongly focused now on using dynamic computer  simulation models not only to characterize existing air--water regimes but  also to predict potential regimes. Use of simulation models introduces a  much needed flexibility, avoiding, for example, arbitrary decisions about  static definitions of "available" water. The model being used calculates the  water regime for a range of climatic conditions and management measures,  such as lowering of the watertable. The modelling approach is gradually  being introduced in the soil survey program. For further details see Bouma  et al. (1981a, b) and Bouma (1983b).  An extensive research program is in progress to improve the soil physical  data base that is essential for modelling. New field methods have been  developed for measuring hydraulic conductivity (Bouma, 1977, 1983a). Soil  morphology has been used in improving the understanding of flow processes  in softs in the field (Bouma, 1981a, b). Characterization of soil pores on  macro- and mic:co-scales (Bouma and Dekker, 1978; Bouma et al., 1979,  1982), including staining to define pore functioning, has broadened informa-  tion from previous studies (Jongerius, 1974; Ismael, 1975).  In-situ measurements of soil water content and pressure relationships yield  lower estimates of plant-available water than those derived from laboratory  desorption data for soil cores. This phenomenon is due to different wetting  procedures and to hysteresis. The standard laboratory data used so far over-  estimate plant-available water in some soils. Therefore, water retention  properties of major soils are being measured in the field, using tensiometers  and neutron probes. Rooting patterns and the associated moisture extraction  by different crops are also being studied.    West Germany    The approach of Renger and Henseler (1971), as modified by Renger and  Strebel (1980), for estimating air--water properties during the survey of soils  in Lower Saxony is summarized. This approach is used commonly in soil  survey in West Germany. It is not widely known in North America, but it has  had a major influence on the Soil Survey of England and Wales (Hodgson,  1976; Hall et al., 1977).  The system involves: (1) field assessment of morphology, texture and  packing density (bulk density + 0.009% clay); and (2) estimates based on  measured data and computed relationships of several parameters. The latter  are listed and bases of estimates are summarized.  Groundwater levels. Depths to groundwater measured in dip-wells at  various seasons are extrapolated by relating soil morphology to water table  fluctuations. Examples of such estimates are given in Arbeitsgemeinschaft  Bodenkunde (1983). Classification of groundwater depth is based on mean  levels. Six classes are defined from very shallow, mean level ~ 20 cm; to ex-  tremely deep, mean level ~ 200 cm. Mean high and low groundwater levels  are given for each of the classes (Renger and Strebel, 1980).    74    TABLE III    Estimates (Germany) of capillary rise (ram water/day) in relation to packing density,  texture, and depth of groundwater below the effective root zone.1    Texture.2      Packing.3      Depth of ground-water below root zone (cm):  density        30       50       70     90       110       150    Capillary rise (mm water/day)    Sand, mS       medium        5.0       3.0       0.5     0.1       --          --  (92,5,3)  Sandy loam, ls  medium        5.0       5.0       3.5      1.5       0.5        0.1  (65,25,10)  Clay, u'T       medium        2.0       0.7       0.4     0.3       0.2        0.1  (15,30,55)  Clay, u'T      high           0.7      0.3      0.2     0.1     ,--0.1       --  (12,33,55)    .1 Examples are based on a more complete table (Renger and Strebel, 1980).  *~ Texture class names are from Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). The German  texture symbol for the particle size distribution indicated (sand, silt, clay %) is given  following the texture class.  .3 The packing density classes are: low ~1.40 g/cm3, medium 1.40--1.75 g/cm3, and high  ~1.75 g/cm3. They can be estimated from texture and structure or calculated (bulk  density + 0.009 clay, percent).    Capillary rise from groundwater to root zone. The amount of water  moving upward to the root zone from a water table is estimated from the  distance between the lower boundary of the effective root zone and the  water table, packing density and texture (Table III). The data indicate that  capillary rise from groundwater may be a significant source of water to  crops growing in sandy and loamy soils.  Soil wetness class. Soil wetness due to groundwater is assigned to six  classes by adjusting the groundwater class on the basis of height of the  capillary fringe (Table IV). Specific guidelines are given for these estimates  (Arbeitsgemeinschaft Bodenkunde, 1983; Table V).  Soil impedance class. Seven classes indicate the degree of waterlogging due  to impermeable soil horizons. They are estimated from profile features such  as rusty mottles, content of organic matter and depth to an impermeable  horizon. Specific guidelines for estimating the seven classes defined are given  in Arbeitsgemeinschaft Bodenkunde (1983).  Saturated hydraulic conductivity (horizontal). Estimates for soils with  &lt;2% organic matter are based on field assessment of packing density and  texture (Table V). Guidelines were developed by relating measured values of  Ksat to measured packing density and texture. Horizontal Ksat is emphasized  because of its importance in drainage. Renger and Henseler (1971) showed  that vertical Ksat values of small cores were approximately three times those  of either horizontal Ksat values for the same cores or vertical Ksat values for  large cores (more than 1 m3).    75    TABLE IV  Soil wetness class (Gen~aany) in relation to groundwater level class and height of capillary fringe  General        Height of             Wetness classes for different mean groundwater level (cm):  texture        capillary  classes         fringe (cm)  *-20    20--40     40--80     80--130    130--160   160--200  --~200  Coarse sand   10           5--6    4          3          2          1          0          0  and gravel  Medium to    10           6       4--5        3--4        2--3        2           1           0  fine sand  Loamy sand   20           6        5           4           3           2           1           0  Sandy loam   30           6       5--6       4          3--4       2--3       1          0  Loam to       40           6       6           4--5        4           3           1--2        0--1  clay loam  Silt loam      50           6       6          5          4          3          2          1  to silt    TABLE V  Estimates (Germany) of Ksat, horizontal, in relation to texture and packing density*~    Texture    Ksat (cm/day) for packing densities:    low                  medium              high    Sand, mS                   4300               100--300             40--100  (92,5,3)  Sandy loam, IS              -~100                 40--100            *-40  (65,25,10)  Clay loam, stL                 40--300           10--40             *-10  (40,30,30)  Clay, u'T                    -*40                 10--40             ~-10    ,1 The footnotes in Table III apply.    Air capacity (Ca). The percentage (volume) of air in the soil at -6 kPa  (total pore volume - volume of water retained at -6 kPa) is estimated from  packing density, texture and organic matter content. High Ca values are  associated with coarse texture, low packing density and low organic matter,  low values with fine texture, high packing density and high organic matter  (Table VI).  Plant-available water (Av). Water retained at -6 kPa minus water retained  at -1500 kPa is estimated from packing density, texture and organic matter  content as illustrated in Table VII. The estimates are based on regression  equations relating Av to measured parameters (Renger and Henseler, 1971).  For peat soils, Av is estimated on the basis of kind of peat (2 classes),  degree of decomposition (3 classes), and percentage of the volume occupied  by solids (3 classes). Estimates range from 75% (volume) for decomposed,  high moor peats with solid volume less than 2.5%, to 35% for decomposed,  low moor peats with more than 7.5% of the volume occupied by solids  (Renger and Strebel, 1980).    76  TABLE VI  Estimates (Germany) of air capacity (Ca) at -6 kPa in relation to texture, packing density  and organic matter content.1    Texture               Packing density                    Packing density    low       medium   high       low       medium   high  ,-2% organic matter               10% organic matter    Ca (vol. %):                        Ca (vol. %):  Sand, mS             27         24         19         23         20         15  (92,5,3)  Sandy loam, 1S         19         15          9         16         12          6  (65,25,10)  Clay loam, stL         11          7          4         10          6          3  (40,30,30)  Clay, u'T               8          4          2         11          7          5  (12,33,55)    .1 Footnotes in Table III apply.  TABLE VII  Estimates (Germany) of plant available water (Av, -6 to -1500 kPa) in relation to tex-  ture, packing density and organic matter content.1    Texture* 2             Packing density                    Packing density    low        medium   high       low        medium   high  *-2% organic matter               10% organic matter    Av (vol. %):                       Av (vol. %):  Sand, mS             10          9          9         22         21         21  (92,5,3)  Sandy loam, 1S        23         17         15         33         27         25  (65,25,10)  Clay loam, stL        22         16         12         30         24         20  (40,30,30)  Clay, u'T             20         14         11         24         18         15  (15,30,55)    *~ Footnotes in Table III apply.    Plant-available water in the effective root zone. This parameter is derived  from the Av values of horizons in the effective root zone assuming that all  -6 to -1500 kPa water is taken up. The lower boundary of the zone depends  on the crop and the soils; it may be deduced (Fig. 1) from the depth func-  tion of water content in groundwater-free soils at the end of the growing  period in years of low rainfall. Estimates of effective root zones for cereals in  relation to texture and packing density are: 40 cm for coarse sands of high    77    Depth  cm    0    40    60-    80-  100-    120-    140-    500 k    Water content vol %  5     10     15     20  ~o               /Field  jo Soil water        /f"capacity  ~ooAug. 1976      /  7     i  B / ~o           //Effective  ~D~      ////rooting depth  dii] Deepest position  ::J of the zero-flux plane  hydraulic gradient = 0)    Fig. 1. Plant-available water in the effective root zone (area A) for winter wheat grown on  a fine sandy soil. The effective rooting depth is deduced from water content measurements  at maximum dryness; the depth at which area B = area C is taken as effective rooting  depth.    packing density (50 cm for low-medium), 70 cm for sandy loams of high  packing density (80 cm for low-medium), 90 cm for silty clay of high packing  density (110 cm for low-medium).    England and Wales    The Soil Survey of England and Wales uses an approach based on the work  of Renger and Henseler (1971). Procedures of estimation are clearly docu-  mented (Thomasson, 1975; Hodgson, 1976; Hall et al., 1977) and based on  data for British soils (Hall et al., 1977; Robson and Thomasson~ 1977).  Estimates of Ca and Av for a given packing density and texture differ some-  what from the German (Renger and 8trebel, 1980) estimates (Table VIII).  Estimates of Ca and Av can be derived directly in the field from ratings  of texture and of packing density, using the same classes as in West Germany,  on the basis of structure and consistence (see Table IV; Hodgson, 1976).  Alternatively, specific values of Ca and Av can be obtained by extracting  water at each of various pressures from core samples. Though water reten-  tion at -5, -10, -40, -200 and -1500 kPa is being measured for samples  from 75 to 100 pedons each year, most of the Ca and Av values are esti-  mated in the field. In rare cases bulk density is measured without acquiring  water desorption data; measuring bulk density and stone content makes  possible a more specific estimate of packing density.    78  TABLE VIII  Estimates of Av and Ca for soils of a given texture and packing density according to  guidelines in Germany and England and Wales.1    Texture class.2       Packing     Av (vol. %)                 Ca (vol. %)  density  class         Germany    England      Germany    England  and Wales                  and Wales.3    Loamy sand, l'S      low         20           16            23           22  (80,14,6)             medium     16           12            19           22  Silt loam, sU         low         26           20            15           22  (35,60,5)             medium     22           18            11           12  Silty clay loam, uT   medium     17           17             7           12  (16,52,32)        high      12       12         4        7  Clay, u'T            medium     14          15            4           7  (10,35,55)           high        11          13            2           2    *' In the German system,-6 kPa is used to delimit the boundary between Ca and Av; in  England and Wales -5 kPa is used; the difference is trivial. The German values are for soils  with less than 2% organic matter (clay less than 17%), or less than 3% organic matter  (clay more than 17%); values for England and Wales are for subsoils.  .5 Texture classes are as in Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). The German symbol  for the particle size distribution shown (% sand, silt, clay) follows the texture class name.  Particle size distributions were chosen to fit within a texture class in the systems involved.  .3 Ca values for England and Wales are the approximate mid value of the Ca classes. For  example, moderately porous (10.0 to 14.9%) is assigned a value of 12% (see Tables 6 and  8 in Hall et al., 1977, for basis of Ca and Av estimates in the system of England and  Wales).    In addition to estimating or measuring Ca and Av, the Soil Survey of  England and Wales estimates the following air--water properties of soils:  (1) Depth to an impeding layer, a layer with an estimated Ksat of &lt;:10%  that of the layer above (Thomasson, 1975). No specific guidelines are stated  for estimating the hydraulic conductivity of soils, though general relation-  ships with texture and structure are indicated (Thomasson, 1975). Six Ksat  classes are defined: from very slow, &lt;0.01 m/day to very rapid, &gt;10 m day.  Ksat values below 0.1 m/day are considered to be associated with Ca values  below 5% (Farquharson et al., 1978; Thomasson, 1982).  (2) Soil wetness class. Six classes of increasing wetness are defined from:  I. the soil profile is not wet within 70 cm depth for more than 30 days in  most years ('wet' means that water extractable at -1 kPa is present); to VI.  the soil profile is wet within 40 cm depth for more than 335 days in most  years. (Hodgson, 1976, Table VIII).  The estimates of wetness classes are based on one or more of measured  data from dip-weUs (Robson and Thomasson, 1977), data for similar sites,  interpretation or observation of soil water states of similar soils in different  seasons, and inferences from morphology and water state of a particular  profile at a particular time (Hodgson, 1976). The last basis, which is the    79    principal one used, was strengthened by the provision of additional clues  (Jones, 1983). Specific guidelines are given for assignment of wetness classes  on the basis of: gleying, depth to impermeable horizon, field capacity days  (Robson and Thomasson, 1977) and whether outfalls are limiting (Table IX).  (3) Soil dryness class. Four classes, a to d, of increasing dryness are de-  fined on the basis of Av to a depth of 1 m and "average potential maximum  soil moisture deficit" (the difference between growing season rainfall and  transpiration under grass growing with adequate available water). These  classes can be assigned from Av estimates and meteorological data (Hall et al.,  1977).    TABLE IX    Relationship of soil wetness class to field capacity (FC) period and depth to impermeable  horizon assuming appropriate drainage measures.I    FC days         Gley Features within 70 cm                              Ungleyed  (median)  Depth to Impermeable Horizon (cm)    &lt;40        40-80      &gt;80                        &gt;80 cm    outfalls       outfalls  limiting      not  limiting    Wetness classes:  &lt; 100           x          II          II-VI         I             I  100--125      x            III          III-VI         I               I  125--150      x            III          III-VI         I               I  150--175       x            III          III-VI         I               I  175--200      IV          III-IV       IV-VI         I               I  200--225       V           IV          V-VI          I-II             I  225--250      V           IV-V        V-VI          II              I  250--300      V-VI        V           V-VI          III             I  &gt;300         VI        VI        VI         VI(?)        I(?)    ,1 Wetness classes are: I, not wet within 70 cm of the surface for more than 30 days, to  VI, wet within 40 cm for more than 335 days in most years. The field capacity period is  days per year when the soil is estimated to be at field capacity or wetter. Gley features  are grey colors or rusty mottles due to reduction. The symbol x below &lt;40 cm (depth  to impermeable horizon) implies the assumption that impermeable horizons within 40  cm of the surface can be loosened by appropriate tillage treatments.    (4) Plant-available water. Hall et al. (1977) refined the available water  estimates (from the difference between water retained at -5 and -1500 kPa)  by introducing plant factors. For example, in the case of winter wheat, the  available water is considered to be the sum of the -5 to -1500 kPa water in  the 0--50 cm layer and the -5 to -200 kPa water in the 50--120 cm layer.  For potato crops, on the other hand, available water is calculated as the-5    8O  TABLE X  Workability and trafficability: Integration of soil and climatic components to estimate potential  Machinery Work Days for the period 1st September to 30th April    Climatic assessment (days)    Soil assessment (days)* i    median     main soil            col. (2)     a         b         c         d         e         f  field       working period     minus      +30      0--25      --40-55      --70  capacity    1st Sept.--          col (1)  period      30th April                       (Machinery work days 1st Sept.--30th April)  (1)      (2)    125        240                 115        145      115      90        75         60        45  150        240                  90        120        90      65        50         35        20  175        240                  65          95        65      40        25         10        --5  200        240                  40          70        40      15         0        --15      --30    ,i The adjustment for soil factors is based on wetness class, depth to impermeable layer and water  retention capacity of topsoils (Thomasson, 1982).    Water  Regime  Class    Slope Classes  Depth to               &lt; 2                     2-8"                      8'  Impermeable  Horizon (cm)    &gt; 80  80 -40    &lt; 40  &gt; 80    80-40  &lt; 40  &gt; 80  80 -40    &lt; 40    Permeability Class (above impermeable horizon)  Rapid [ Medium  Slow  RapidI Medium Slow  Rapid  Medium  m  1            2       1         2  1  2                      3    I  2             3    Slow  3  4    Winter Rain Acceptance Class                              Winter Run-off Potential  1  Very high                                            1  Very low  2  High                                                2  Low  3  Moderate                                            3  Moderate  4  Low                                                    4  High  5  Very low                                                5  Very high    Fig. 2. Winter rain acceptance (and winter runoff) potential class in relation to soil and  site properties (Farquharson et al., 1978). Water-regime classes are based on depth and  duration of waterlogging (Hodgson, 1974).    81    to -1500 kPa water in the 0--70 cm layer. Thus adjustments axe made on the  basis of knowledge of rooting depth and distribution for various crops. Ad-  justed values for plant-available water reserves can be estimated in the field  or measured; they axe used for land evaluation (Bibby et al., 1982).  (5) Machinery work days (Thomasson, 1982). Soil and climatic data axe  integrated to provide an estimate of the number of days during the main  working period (Sept. I to April 30) when the soil is at a water content  suitable for working. Details of the procedure are given by Thomasson  (1982); only the basic steps are given here.  (a) Record median field capacity days (days when the soil water deficit  is effectively zero) for the area of concern. This is based on climatic data and  assumptions about evapotranspiration in relation to soil water content  (Smith and Trafford, 1976). The original estimates have been refined and  updated (Jones and Thomasson, 1984).  (b) Adjust the estimate based on climatic data by introducing corrections  {+30 to -70 days) based on soil factors; the major soil factors axe wetness  class, depth to a slowly permeable horizon, and retained water capacity  (Table X). For details, see Thomasson, 1982.  (c) Estimates of machinery work days are made for autumn and spring  periods for median, wet and dry years, and the suitability of soil for particu-  lar crops can be assessed.  (6) Winter rain acceptance (Farquhaxson et al., 1978). The assessment of  winter rain acceptance potential and hence of winter runoff potential is  based on four site and soil properties: soil water regime, depth to imper-  meable horizon (&lt;10 cm/day), permeability above impermeable horizons,  and slope (Fig. 2).    France    In France, the assessment by soil survey of the soil water regime is based  mainly on morphology, supported by some measurements of soil properties  (Favrot, 1983). As in other countries, the degree of detail of information  and the specificity of interpretations depend upon the scale of mapping and  the purpose of the survey. The most detailed information is available for  large-scale maps (1:10,000) for example "secteurs de r~f~rence" mapped  mainly for drainage applications.  The kinds of estimated and measured data involved in the French system  are listed and discussed briefly.    Plant-available water  For each horizon, this is the difference between field capacity (volumetric  water content after 48 h of drainage of saturated soil) and wilting point  (-1500 kPa). Field capacity is commonly estimated from laboratory analysis  of disturbed, &lt;2 mm, samples (Bonfils, 1967). Negative pressures of -10  (sand) to -100 kPa (clays) axe applied to saturated samples. Water content    82    data (weight basis) are corrected to a volumetric basis by multiplying by  bulk density. Water reserve values by horizon are summed to the rooting  depth with a maximum of 1.5 m, and classified in one of eight classes from  &lt;25 mm (excessively low) to &gt;300 mm (very high) (G.E.P.P.A., 1981).  Readily available water is calculated by multiplying plant available water  (mm) by an empirical factor ranging from 0.5 (soil dries rapidly and struc-  ture is coarse) to 1.0 (soft dries slowly and has very fine structure). In some  cases the coefficient is assigned a value of 0.66.  Information on plant available water is used in rating soils and in assessing  irrigation needs.    Natural soil drainage  (a) Internal drainage. Several systems of classifying internal drainage are  used in France; basically they are detailed (Jamagne, 1967) and simplified  (Favrot and Devillers, 1976) systems involving from 20 to 6 classes (Favrot,  1983). The classes are based on morphology and the intensity and depth of  gley phenomena. For example, in the simple system, classes are defined as  follows:  h0 -- no gley mottles within 120--130 cm.  hl -- Fe, Mn mottles, coatings or concretions below 80 cm.  h2 --weakly contrasting brown and grey material within a depth of 50--80  cm.  h3 -- rusty mottles, or Fe, Mn concretions between 0 and 50 cm; below 50  cm the material is strongly contrasting ochreous and grey.  h4 -- mottled or grey to the surface, and grey to blue-grey below.  These classes conform well with evaluations of internal drainage based  on ratings by farmers and on piezometric measurements (Favrot and Devil-  lers, 1976).  (b) External drainage. This parameter is little used as it is closely asso-  ciated with internal drainage. It depends on position in the landscape and  infiltration rate. Five classes are named: none -- depressions, to very rapid --  steep slopes and slow infiltration.  (c) Zoning of wet land. Four classes are defined from well drained land  (too wet to work for less than one week in the spring) to very wet land (too  wet for more than three weeks in the spring). This assessment can be done  rapidly and it is useful with internal drainage estimates in planning drainage  of an area.    Measurements related to soil water flow  (a) Infiltration. In the field, measurements are made with a double ring  infiltrometer (Muntz et al., 1905) and by the auger hole method (Porchet  and Laferrere, 1935). Similar measurements are made in the laboratory using  1 dm3 blocks of soil and a 1--10 cm head of water. Ratings of infiltration  are assigned: ,=1 cm/h (slowly permeable) to &gt;5 cm/h (permeable) and used  in planning irrigation rates.    83    (b) Saturated hydraulic conductivity. The auger hole method and the well  and piezometer methods (Guyon, 1971) are used when possible.  (c) Drainage porosity is the fraction of the soil volume that drains under  gravity. It is measured by the well and piezometer methods (Guyon, 1971).  (d) Depth to impermeable layer. This is usually estimated from morphol-  ogy (low porosity, absence of peds, compaction); in some cases perched  water is noted in boreholes.    Other measurements  (a) Atterberg limits are measured periodically for some soils, and related  to periods favourable for working the soil (Favrot, 1983).  (b) Comparisons of estimates based on morphology with measured data  on soil-water are in progress.  (c) Studies are in progress of criteria for determining the choice of drain-  age systems based on estimates from soil morphology (Bouzigues et al.,  1981).    United States    This discussion pertains to current standard operations and to material in  the new soil survey manual draft (Soil Survey Staff, 1983). It covers neither  a wide range of research and development activities nor the program of non-  federal participants in the National Cooperative Soil Survey. The criteria  used in establishing soil map units largely determine the air--water proper-  ties that are recognized. The soil map units in the United States are defined,  in part, in terms of taxa (usually to the series level) of Soil Taxonomy (Soil  Survey Staff, 1975). For detailed surveys of agricultural land, one or more  non-taxonomic criteria (slope, degree of erosion, near-surface particle size)  are included in the map unit definitions. Thus, both taxonomic and non-  taxonomic criteria may indicate soil air--water properties.  Soil Taxonomy includes information related to air--water properties of  soils at most levels from order to series. Taxonomic criteria related to air--  water properties may be separated into two general groups: Ca) those that  pertain to the yearly pattern of water states (aquic, perudic, udic, ustic,  aridic, xeric) and (b) those that pertain to organization and composition of  the soil material as they influence hydraulic conductivity, root penetration,  and plant-available water (fragipan, very fine family particle-size class, etc.).  In general, the yearly pattern of water states is specified at higher categorical  levels than the organization and compositional criteria. Thus soils having an  aquic moisture regime throughout are separated from others at either the  order (Histosols) or suborder levels (Aquepts, etc.). Other soils that are  mottled in some horizon indicating periodic saturation with water, but that  lack evidence of complete saturation from the ground surface downward,  are classified in Aquic subgroups (Aquic Hapludalf, etc.). At the family level,  the particle-size classes and to an extent the mineralogical classes are related    84    to water retention and transmission. Additional differentiation related to the  air--water regime may be made at the series level. For example, restriction of  rooting to depths of less than 0.5, 0.5--1.0 or 1.0--1.5 m is a series criterion  that is related to plant-available water.    TABLE XI    Water-related standard soil survey documentation for Marshall soils; map unit description  and taxonomy* t    Map Unit 9 C2. Marshall silty clay loam, 5 to 9 percent slopes, moderately eroded. This  moderately sloping, well drained soil  ....  Included with this soil ... are small areas of  Adair, Dickman, and Ida soils. The Adair soil is in the lower part of the unit and some-  what poorly drained. The Dickman and Ida soils are on the more convex, sloping part of  the unit  ....  The sandy Dickman soil has low available water capacity  ....  The Marshall soil  is moderately permeable and surface runoff is medium. Available water capacity is high.    Taxonomy of components of unit and implications regarding water regime    Marshall  Adair    Typic Hapludolls, fine-  silty, mixed, mesic  Aquic Argiudolls, fine,  montmorillonitic, mesic    Dickman       Typic Hapludolls,  sandy, mixed, mesic    Ida    Typic Udorthents, fine-silty,  mixed (calcareous), mesic    -- Udic moisture regime; fine-  silty particle-size class  -- Aquic restrictions on udic  moisture regime; family  particle-size class  -- Udic moisture regimes; sandy  particle size class suggests  low water retention    *~ Abbreviated version of map unit description from Soil Survey of Carroll County,  Iowa (Sherwood, 1982). Underlining draws attention to terms related to water regime.    An abbreviated map unit description (Table XI) illustrates the information  on air--water properties that can be derived from taxonomic and non-taxo-  nomic criteria. The map unit name specifies the soil series (Marshall) and  hence several taxonomically derived air--water properties such as udic mois-  ture regime, water characteristics associated with a mollic epipedon, and  water retention capacity associated with the fine silty particle size class. The  name also indicates non-taxonomic properties such as slope class, near-sur-  face texture and erosion class, all of which are related to infiltration and  runoff. The map unit description names the appreciably different soil series  included with Marshall in the unit. It gives the relative location of these  other series in the landscape and by implication, their role in runoff. The  description also lists several air--water regime features (drainage class, avail-  able water capacity class, etc.) for both Marshall and the other series named.  Further water--related data and interpretation for Marshall soils are present-  ed in the interpretation record (Table XII). The National Soil Handbook  draft, part 603, provides related interpretations (Soft Survey Staff, 1983).  Selected terms from Tables XI and XII are defined briefly.    85    TABLE XlI  Water-related standard soil survey documentation for Marshall soils; soil interpretations record* 1    Depth      Particle size (%)                 Moist bulk   Permeability   Available        Shrink--  (cm)                                         density      (cm/h)         water capacity  swell  &gt;2 mm   &lt;75 Pm    clay      (g/cms)                      (cm/cm)    0--45   0         95--100    27--35   1.25--1.30   1.5--5         0.21--0.23      moderate  0--45   0         95--100    25--27   1.25--1.30   1.5--5         0.21--0.23      low  45--142  0         95--100    25--27   1.30--1.35   1.5--5         0.18--0.20      moderate  142--172  0         95--100    25--27   1.30--1.40   1.5--5         0.20--0.22      moderate    Hydrologic  Potential  Flooding              High Water Table Cemented Pan   Bedrock       Group       Frost Action--  Frequency--~aone     Depth &gt;150 cm   Depth---none    Depth--none   B            high  Duration--            Kind--x           Hardness--x     Hardness--x  Months--x    .l The terms are defined in the text. The interpretations record gives estimated information based on  measured values for and observations of similar soils. Two ranges of clay content are given for the 0--  45 cm depth becasue surface texture is not a series criterion. Data have been changed to metric. The  symbol 'x' indicates 'non-specified'.    Available-water capacity is based on volume fraction of water at 'field  capacity' that is considered exploitable by plant roots. The classes (from  low, 8--16 cm; to high, 23--30 cm) indicate the estimate of available water  from the ground surface to a depth usually of 1--1.5 m, depending on the  region. The estimate is based upon measured water retention difference  between -10 or -33 kPa and -1500 kPa.  Drainage class. Seven drainage classes are defined. Well drained implies  that wetness is not a problem and that, for the climate of the area, the soil  is not unusually subject to insufficient available water. Somewhat poorly  drained implies wetness for significant periods in the growing season.  Erosion class is based on an estimate of the proportion of the original A  horizon that has been lost by erosion. The implication is that infiltration  rate decreases and runoff increases with increased erosion. A moderate ero-  sion class placement implies loss of 25 to 75 percent of the original A  horizon.  Flooding is described by the frequency, duration and time of the year  flowing water covers the ground.  Hydrologic group indicates an estimate of the water transmission rate  through the thoroughly wetted soil, including the effect of a shallow water  table, if present. Four classes, A to D, cover the range from approximately  1 to less than 0.1 cm/h. The hydrologic groups, the antecedent water state  of the near-surface soil, and specific aspects related to the use of the soil  (tillage practice, canopy, mulch) are assessed together and a relationship  between daily rainfall and daily runoff is assigned; this estimated relationship  is referred to as the Curve Number.  Permeability is an estimate of vertical saturated hydraulic conductivity  (Ksat) based on morphology and some measurements. It is given for both  individual horizons and for the control section. For the latter, the horizon    86    with the lowest permeability usually determines the class assigned; two  classes may be given if an underlying zone has markedly higher permeability  than overlying horizons. The moderate permeability class indicates Ksat of  1.5 to 2.5 cm/h.  Potential frost action pertains to potential movement of soil due to the  formation of ice lenses; class definitions are qualitative.  Runoff class refers to the relative proportion of the water received by the  ground surface that flows off and does not enter the soil. Runoff class in-  creases with slope; numerical classes are not defined. Curve Number (see  Hydrologic group) is commonly used rather than runoff class in hydrological  computations.  Shrink-swell class is based on laboratory measurements of the coefficient  of linear extensibility, COLE (Soil Conservation Service, 1972). COLE is  computed from bulk densities of the &lt;2 mm material at either -10 or -33  kPa and oven dryness. Low shrink-swell means a COLE of less than 0.03 and  moderate, 0.03 to 0.06. The concept of shrink-swell pertains to potential for  volume change rather than actual change.  Water tables are estimated from observations during surveys related to  data for some monitored sites. The following features are estimated: shallow-  est depth, period when this occurs and whether perched (above a layer of  low permeability) or continuous.  A soil interpretation record is available for each soil series defined in the  United States; some 15,000 records, such as that shown in Table XII, have  been completed. Laboratory data obtained by Federal laboratories are avail-  able for some 10,000 pedons.  The U.S. Soil Survey has been working through subcommittees for more  than a decade to improve the classification of soil water regimes and the  assessment of air--water relationships of soils as they relate to plant growth  (see NTS reports, National Technical Work -- Planning Conferences of the  Cooperative Soil Survey, 1970--1981). The proposals accepted currently are  included in a draft of the new U.S. Soil Survey manual (Soil Conservation  Service, 1979--1983). Chapter 4 of that manual recommends that soil  descriptions include the following soil water-related properties.  Soil-water state for each soil layer. Three soil-water states can be esti-  mated in the field: dry (~&lt;-1500 kPa), moist (-10 to -1500 kPa) and wet  (0 to -10 kPa).  Soil wetness -- depth and duration of saturation; this information may be  obtained by measurements through the year at specific sites, or by relating  soil color and mottling to water table data and extrapolation to similar soils  in the area. Five classes of depth to wet state and four duration classes of  wetness are defined; for example, class 4c means wet in some part above a  depth of 50 cm but not above a depth of 25 cm for a quarter to half of the  time.  Water retention difference -- water retained between -10 or -33 and  -1500 kPa. Five classes are defined (from &lt;7.5 to &gt;30 cm of water retained    87    per 150 cm depth). This property is measured or estimated. Factors related  to "water retention difference" are listed but no general guidelines are given;  it is said that relationships apply only within a limited range of soils.  Runoff-- six classes, ponded to very rapid, are defined.  Hydraulic conductivity --six classes of Ksat are defined; within class range  is 10 X (e.g. 1--10 pm/s). The overall range of values is from &gt; 100 to &lt; 0.01  #m/s (approx. 9 to 0.0009 pm/d). These classes have not yet replaced the  permeability classes defined previously. Classes for various horizons are  estimated from structure and porosity but no clear guidelines are stated.  Several soil properties closely related to air--water relations are included  in basic soil descriptions: depth to restricting layer; structure (pedality);  porosity (separate from structure).    Canada    Proposals for improvements over the "soil drainage classes" for character-  izing the soil water regime in soil survey were made throughout the 70's and  a new system was accepted for trial in 1981 (see Proceedings of Canada Soil  Survey Committee meetings from 1970 to 1978 and of the Expert Commit-  tee on Soil Survey 1979--1981). The system as outlined in 1981 (Nowland,  1981) is summarized.  Aridity classes. Twelve classes are defined with aridity indices ranging  from &lt;100 mm for class 1 to &gt;600 mm for class 12. The aridity index is  defined as "the long term average" of supplemental water required to main-  tain plant-available water equal to or greater than 1/2 of capacity throughout  the growing season for a perennial crop. They are applicable to soils in semi-  arid or drier climates. Estimates are based upon measured data for some  soils, soil properties such as texture, and climatic data (Shields and Sly,  1984).  Saturated hydraulic conductivity (K) classes. Eight vertical Ksat classes  are defined, from H1 &gt;1.39 10-4 m/s (&gt;50 cm/h), to L3 &lt;4.63 10-s m/s  (&lt;0.017 cm/h). These have been modified (Eilers, 1983) to: 1 -- very rapid,  H2&gt;50 cm/h; to 8 -- extremely slow, L1 &lt;0.05 cm/h. The K class of the  pedon is determined by the layer of lowest vertical Ksat. The intention is  that K estimates should be based on morphology and checked periodically  by field measurements. Checking has been facilitated by Topp's work (1976,  1980) on the development of convenient methods. Guidelines for estimating  Ksat from field observations of porosity, pedality, texture and consistency  have been proposed (McKeague et al., 1982).  Saturated hydraulic conductivity (K) subclasses. These are used to indi-  cate the kind and depth of an impeding soil layer or a pore space disconti-  nuity between 20 and 200 cm.  Subclass A: reduction in macroporosity, Ksat &lt;30% that of the overlying  horizon.  Subclass B: increase in macroporosity sufficient to restrict water move-    88    ment significantly, e.g. loam/gravel. Four depth classes are included: 1, 20--  50 cm, to 4, 150--200 cm. These are estimated from macromorphology.  Saturated zone classes (water table or S classes). Seven depth classes  (from H1 0--50 cm to L2 &gt;300 cm) are defined. The highest (saturated  for two consecutive days) and the lowest water tables are estimated. Esti-  mates are based on any measurements for similar soils and on colours and  mottling (no clear guidelines). Three classes for duration of saturation and  three seepage subclasses may be added.  Man-made modifiers. These are used to indicate kind of modification of  "natural" soil water regime (tile-drained, etc.) and two degrees of impact,  major and minor (e.g., I -- minor change due to irrigation, II -- major change  due to irrigation).  Year round water state matrix. Similar to U.S. monthly soil water states.  Other estimates. Plant-available water is estimated either directly from  water retained between -33 and -1500 kPa (-10 to -1500 by some workers  in the humid region) or from models relating particle size (De Jong, 1982)  or particle size and organic matter (De Jong and Loebel, 1982) to measured  water retention between the pressures indicated.    DISCUSSION OF APPROACHES    Some problems    The discussion is based insofar as possible on published information out-  lining approaches used in the various countries. In some cases, specific,  recent bulletins and papers on the topic are available; for example, England  and Wales (Hodgson, 1976; Hall et al., 1977; Thomasson, 1982). In other  cases, the documentation is not so readily available; for example, the new  U.S. soil survey manual (Soil Survey Staff, 1983) is not yet published.  Another problem arises from the fact that there are differences between the  current practices of soil surveyors and procedures recommended by the  national soil survey organizations. This is probably especially true in coun-  tries such as Canada where a major change in characterization of the air--  water regime of soils was accepted recently for use in soil survey (Nowland,  1981).  The problem of incomplete documentation is resolved, in part, by the fact  that one or more of the authors is familiar with the official approach in each  country. We assume for purposes of the discussion that these approaches  are being used in soil survey.    Similarities and differences    The approaches used by soil survey organizations in the six countries to  characterize and interpret the air--water regimes of soils are broadly similar  (Table XIII). Many of the same soil properties are estimated or measured,    8g    '0  o  o  '0  o  o~    0 0 "" ~ "~   ~ m      "~          =        ~.       ag.~  ~o~  I~.~       o    ~u  ~ op~   "~ "1=.    0  ~  ~     ~  ~ ~    ~    .~  .~  ~.~           ~    ~  ~    '0   ~0     ~   O.'~    m  ~c~    .Q    e~         ~w  &lt;     o    ..o :~  Q;  r~    90    and similar kinds of interpretations are made. Though the amounts of mea-  sured data relative to the areas of the countries differ enormously, all of the  soil survey organizations base estimates of air--water regime on measured  data for some soils. The methods of measurements used are similar in many  cases.  The focus of this section, however, is on differences of approaches and  methods. Some of these can be rationalized on the basis of differences in  climate, land areas, and intensity of land use in the six countries. For ex-  ample, the intensive land use and the general high groundwater level in The  Netherlands require a more thorough knowledge of groundwater levels and  fluctuations thereof than is either feasible or necessary in large areas of  extensively used land in Canada. Furthermore, climatic factors dictate to a  degree the kinds of air--water regime properties that are of primary im-  portance. In arid regions, the capacity of the soil to retain water available to  plants is of primary importance. Plant-available water is important in humid  regions also, but capacity of the soil to transmit water may be even more  critical. Many of the differences of approaches and methods, however, are  not clearly related to the general factors mentioned in this paragraph; they  are probably due largely to relatively independent development of soil air--  water regime technology by individuals in the six countries.  Some of these differences in approaches and methods are apparent from  Table XIII; a few of the most striking are listed.    Water table fluctuations  In The Netherlands, classes indicating the mean highest level are based on  measured data which are extrapolated to similar soils; soil morphology is not  used in estimating water tables. In West Germany, on the other hand, specif-  ic guidelines relate morphology (gley colors and mottles} to water tables. In  France, water table is neither measured nor estimated routinely; internal  drainage classes are based on specific morphological criteria.    Plant-available water  Some differences in bases of the estimates are:  (a) The upper limit of available water is taken to be -5 to -10 kPa in the  four countries of western Europe and generally -33 kPa in the United States  and Canada.  (b) Upward flow from a shallow water table is taken into account in The  Netherlands and West Germany but not generally in the other countries.  {c} Depths to which available water is calculated differ, as does the degree  of adjustment for abundance of roots in the deeper layers.  {d) Undisturbed samples are used in most countries for measuring water  retention at the upper limit; data from France are based mainly on disturbed  samples as are the older data from Canada.    91    Air capacity  Air capacity at -10 kPa or higher is estimated from packing density and  texture or measured in West Germany and England and Wales and it can be  derived from measured water-release data in The Netherlands. Except for  special studies, it is not estimated or measured in the United States, France  and Canada.    Saturated hydraulic conductivity  Procedures differ greatly; the extremes are probably The Netherlands  where many measurements are made and France where Ksat is neither mea-  sured nor estimated routinely. Estimates of horizontal Ksat in West Germany  are based on packing density and texture; no clear guidelines are stated for  estimates of vertical Ksat made routinely in the United States, and tentative  guidelines, based on structure, including porosity, texture and "packing" are  available in Canada.    Other features  It is obvious from the last row in Table XIII that widely different air--  water-related properties are estimated routinely by the various soil survey  organizations. A particularly wide range of features related to interpretations  is estimated in the United States.  Several of the differences summarized above are major. In addition there  are numerous minor differences in approaches and methods used in charac-  terizing and interpreting air--water regimes of soils. Some of the approaches  and methods must be better than others and an attempt is made here to  evaluate them.    EVALUATION OF APPROACHES    A rigorous evaluation of the approaches presented would require mucl~  research; the material that follows is a tentative evaluation.    Water table fluctuations    The best approach if practical applications to drainage, irrigation and  other practices justify the expenditures involved is to monitor water tables  at many sites over several years as in The Netherlands. The data can be  extrapolated to other sites and programs can be developed to simulate water  tables given the required soil, climatic and crop data. In most areas, however,  obtaining such comprehensive measured data on water tables is not feasible.  Water table fluctuations must be estimated from simple observations and  recorded data on water table and soil properties at a few sites on different  materials. Guidelines for estimating water table fluctuations from soil color,    92    mottling or other soil and site properties should be developed and tested in  different climatic regions on major soil materials. Thorough recording of  approximate water tables, soil and site properties, and date of observation  during the soil survey of an area will contribute to the development of guide-  lines. Obviously, in areas where groundwater is deep, there is no need to  estimate water table fluctuations; other aspects of the water regime are more  important.    Plant-available water    Progress has been made in estimating plant-available water capacities of  soils, and estimates based on -33 kPa to -1500 kPa water content of dis-  turbed samples to an arbitrary depth are not generally adequate. Estimates  can be improved by taking into account several factors.  (1) Plant factors. Rooting depth of a crop in the soil under consideration  determines the depth to which water storage is calculated (Hall et al., 1977;  NTS Report, 1981). In addition, the lowest pressure at which plant roots  can extract adequate water from the soil at various depths must be considered.  No firm recommendations can be made, but a lower limit of -70 kPa for  available water is being considered in The Netherlands. Probably the appro-  priate limit depends on climatic and plant factors.  (2} Soil factors. Changes in structure and bulk density affected by soil  management practices change plant-available water. Estimates for a soil of a  series at one site may not apply to a soil of the same series at another site  under different management. In addition, an appropriate upper limit of  available water must be selected. It may be -33 kPa in some soils of semi-  arid regions and -5 kPa or less in clayey soils of humid regions. If the soil has  a shallow groundwater table upward flow of water to the root zone should  be estimated as in Germany and The Netherlands.  (3) Measurement methods. Undisturbed samples should be used for labo-  ratory estimates of water retention at least for pressures above -200 kPa.  Disturbed samples are probably adequate at -1500 kPa. Field estimates of  plant-available water must be based on estimates of bulk density or packing  density in addition to texture and organic matter. Such estimates should be  checked frequenly against measured data. Similarly, bulk density is a neces-  sary term in equations for estimating plant-available water from basic soil  data.    Air capacity    Air capacity at -5 kPa (or perhaps -10 kPa) should be estimated as it is  related to adequacy of aeration of plant roots after heavy rains or irrigation  and to saturated hydraulic conductivity. Texture, bulk density or packing  density, and structure should be considered in estimating air capacity and  estimates should be checked regularly against measured values.    93    Saturated hydraulic conductivity    Vertical and horizontal Ksat should be estimated in the field from guide-  lines based upon structure, texture and packing density or bulk density  related to measured values of Ksat. Estimates should be checked regularly  against measured values; numerous methods are available (Bouma, 1983a).  Though Ksat is closely associated with texture in some areas, the relationship  is not generally applicable (Bouma, 1980; Topp et al., 1980). Guidelines  based on observations of structure, texture and bulk density can provide  reasonable and useful estimates of Ksat (McKeague et al., 1982; Wang and  McKeague, 1983). For most purposes, it is necessary to estimate Ksat of only  the least permeable horizon or horizons; a general assessment of all horizons  is necessary, however, in order to detect those of low permeability. Esti-  mates of vertical Ksat of horizons at or near the surface are important as  these are related to probability of ponding or of runoff. Horizontal Ksat is  important for horizons below 50 cm as this governs lateral flow of water to  drains.    Other air--water regime properties and interpretations    Estimates of several other air--water regime properties and interpretations  thereof, apart from those discussed above, probably should be included in  most surveys. These are listed briefly as it is not possible to evaluate the  approaches used.  (1) Soil--water states both at the time of sampling and throughout the  year as suggested by the Soil Conservation Service (1979--81).  (2) Soil strength or a related property such as bearing capacity as mea-  sured in The Netherlands in relation to interpretations of workability (Tho-  masson, 1982). The period of the year during which workability is important  differs according to climate and crop.  (3) Runoff potential in relation to soil and landform properties (Farqu-  harson et al., 1978; NTS, 1981). Water erosion potential is a related property.    RESEARCH NEEDS    A summary of research needs associated with specific aspects of soil air--  water regime characterization and interpretation is followed by a statement  on more general needs.    Water table fluctuations    (1) Investigations are necessary to check the accuracy of estimates of  water table fluctuation or wetness classes from guidelines based on morphol-  ogy (Arbeitsgemeinschaft Bodenkunde, 1983; Favrot, 1983) or several  factors (Jones, 1983). This would involve making estimates according to the    94    guidelines and checking them by measurements over a period of several  years. Most soil survey organizations will have to rely mainly on estimates  as monitoring groundwater is expensive.  (2) In Canada and the United States, and probably in other countries, it  is necessary to develop specific guidelines for estimating water table regimes  in specific regions for specific kinds of material. The next step would be to  check the guidelines as in item No. 1.  (3) Evaluation is required of the relative feasibility and practical signifi-  cance of estimating water tables as in most countries or estimating wetness  (water &gt;--1 kPa) as in England. For many applied purposes, a soil that is  wet to -1 kPa for an extended period is as limiting as one that is fully  saturated. Water table and "wetness table" could be monitored with tensio-  meters (Bouma, 1977).  (4) Investigations to determine how soon the effects of improved drainage  can be detected in soil morphology might be useful. A related need in most  countries is to determine the effectiveness of soil drainage systems in de-  creasing soil wetness (e.g., Bouma, 1981b).  (5) Work is needed to develop guidelines for estimating the duration of  saturation or wetness of soils on long slopes, especially those having an im-  permeable layer such as an ironpan or fragipan within one meter of the sur-  face. Another requirement is to assess the degree of oxygenation of the  water in such soils.    Plant-available water    (1) More information is needed on rooting depth and distribution of  major crops in major soils of various regions. For example, softs cold at  depth may be a significant factor in parts of Canada.  (2) Testing the estimates of available water in relation to plant response  in regions of different climate is required. Differences in the upper limits  set for available water (-5 to -33 kPa) must be major for some soils. The  lower limit at -1500 kPa probably involves enough water for survival of  most plants but growth may be hampered; a higher value may be needed to  relate to optimum growth of many crops.  (3) Testing of estimates of available water based on packing density and  texture or other field techniques is required. This has been done to a degree  in Germany and Britain.  (4) Comparing estimates of plant-available water based on data for soil  cores with those based on in-situ measurements of water content--pressure  relationships and assessing the validities of the estimates in relation to plant  growth are necessary.  (5) Testing the "lag effect" in gley soils is necessary. It is thought that  potentially available water in wet softs is not exploited by plants until the  water table has receded to some depth below the layer in question. In shrink-  ing clay soils, on the other hand, more water may be accessible to plants  than would be indicated by the guidelines.    95    (6) The applicability of models for estimating available water in soils sub-  ject to severe cracking and short circuiting of flow after heavy rains (Bouma  and Dekker, 1978; Topp and Davis, 1981) needs to be tested.    Air capacity    (1) In the Soil Survey of England and Wales, air capacity is derived from  either field estimates of packing density and texture or from measured pack-  ing density and particle size data. Estimates by the two procedures should be  compared with measured values. It seems that in the case of very clayey  soils (/&gt;60% clay) an estimate of air capacity based on observation of struc-  ture and texture (Hodgson, 1976) might be better than one based on mea-  sured bulk density and particle size. Clayey soils with the same bulk densities  might have markedly different structures and air porosities. It is possible that  air capacity could be estimated directly from field observations without  involving an estimate of packing density.  (2) Relationships between air capacity and Ksat should be determined.    Saturated hydraulic conductivity    (1) Guidelines for estimating vertical and horizontal Ksat in a wide range  of soil materials should be tested and revised as required on the basis of field  measurements. Soil morphology should be considered in estimating optimal  sample sizes for K measurements in different soils (Bouma, 1983a).  (2) Estimates of Ksat from air capacity should be compared with those  based on guidelines mentioned in item No. 1.  (3) Further improvement is required in techniques for field measurement  of Ksat.  (4) Variability of Ksat from season to season should be assessed. Guide-  lines for estimating Ksat of soils at various states of initial wetness might be  developed. Such work might include consideration of how to assess Ksat in  cracking soils where short circuiting is often a dominant process (Bouma,  1981a).  (5) The feasibility of estimating Kumat in the most range should be as-  sessed. Such estimates might be useful for soils having enough large pores  (&gt;60 pm) to give moderate Ksat values but very low proportions of pores in  the 60--5 pm range and hence low Kunsat values. The crust test has been used  successfully in this context (e.g. Bouma et al., 1982).    Other specific aspects of air--water regime    (1) Guidelines for recognition of slowly permeable layers should be devel-  oped and checked by field measurements.  (2) The extent to which layers slowly permeable with respect to flow of  water are restrictive to root development should be assessed.    96    (3) Guidelines for rating soil-water states throughout the year should be  developed and tested.  (4} Similarly, guidelines should be developed and tested for assessing soil  strength relative to workability and for assessing runoff potential of areas of  land.    More general related research needs    In most countries, soil classes are characterized and interpretations of  drainability, rooting depth, etc. are based on the concept that properties of  soils of a class are relatively uniform for similar land use and management.  It is known, however, that air--water properties such as Ksat of pedons of the  same series differ widely (Topp et al., 1980). Cropping systems and tillage  practices can result in dramatic changes in Ksat, porosity, etc. of soils of the  same series under different management systems (Wilkinson, 1975; and other  papers in Min. of Agric., Fisheries and Food, 1975; Thomasson, 1978; Wang  and McKeague, 1983). The major changes occur in the top 40 or 50 cm.  Interpretations might be based on the assumption that a good physical con-  dition of the 0--40 cm layer is maintained, though this is difficult to achieve.  Clearly, if soil maps are to be useful in land evaluation, the ranges of intrinsic  and induced variation within soil units must be distinguished. The following  research would help to make such interpretations more realistic.  (1) Determination of the range of properties of pedons of the same series  at depths below the Ap, perhaps 50--100 cm.  (2) Determination of the range of properties of Ap horizons of pedons of  the same series and of the relationship among cropping system, tillage prac-  tices and properties such as bulk density, Ksat and Ca.  (3) Determination of the rate of recovery of soils of particular series under  grass, etc.  (4) Determination of seasonal changes in air--water properties of soils of  a series.  Such research would improve the possibility of making realistic estimates  of the properties and behaviour of soils of a series under various cropping  systems, of the probable range of properties likely to occur in soils of a given  series, and of the probable recovery time of soils subjected to compaction,  etc. (Bullock et al., 1984}.    Integration of information from different disciplines    Most of the major interpretations regarding the potential of a land area for  a possible use such as production of a certain crop require information from  several disciplines. This statement of the obvious has been accepted to a  degree, as indicated by the emphasis on land evaluation in the last decade.  Examples of integration of several kinds of information are the Technical  Monographs of the Soil Survey of England and Wales (Thomasson, 1975;    97    Hall et al., 1977; Robson and Thomasson, 1977; Jones and Thomasson,  1984).  In spite of the promising trends, however, the integration of soil survey  information with plant, climatic, engineering, hydrological, etc. information  is not adequate in most soil survey organizations. Integration is best achieved,  probably, by specialists from different disciplines working with soil survey-  ors in developing specific interpretations. This is preferable to the accumula-  tion of data from separate disciplines and integration and interpretation of  them by an individual. The former procedure can result in more interchange  of ideas, acceptance of the reality of soil variability, questioning of tech-  niques and assumptions of specialists in each field and identification of key  properties relevant to the interpretation. Key requirements for such an ap-  proach to work are that the specialists can cooperate, are open to different  points of view and are able to accept the idea that the interpretation can be  no better than the map.  Examples of needs for interdisciplinary approaches for developing im-  proved interpretations of soil survey are: (a) cooperation of agronomists,  climatologists and soil physicists with soil surveyors in improving estimates  of plant-available water reserves for various crops in different soils and in  similar soils subjected to different tillage; (b) cooperation of drainage engi-  neers, hydrologists, agronomists and soil physicists with pedologists in im-  proving interpretations of drainability of land from soil survey information.  Similar interdisciplinary approaches are desirable for other interpretations  such as irrigation requirements, trafficability, especially in soils with seasonal  or permanently frozen layers, erosion hazards and so on.    CONCLUSIONS    This tentative summary and assessment shows that different approaches  are used by soil survey organizations in estimating and interpreting the air--  water properties of soils. Some approaches are more clearly defined and  more adequately tested than others. Improvements could be made by  adopting, with some adaptation perhaps, the superior procedures that can be  identified. Research is required both for improving estimates by soil survey  organizations of specific air--water properties of soils and for the improve-  ment of interpretations of soil survey information in terms of the potential  of land areas for particular uses. The latter research is more likely to be  effective if it is interdisciplinary.    REFERENCES    Arbeitsgemeinschaft Bodenkunde, 1983. Bodenkundliche Kartieranleitung (3rd edition).  Hannover.  Bibby, J.S., Douglas, H.A., Thomasson, A.J. and Robertson, J.S., 1982. Land capability  classification for agriculture. Soil Survey of Scotland, Macauly Institute for Soil  Research, Aberdeen.    98    Bonfils, P., 1967. M~thodes d'analyses des sols. SES-INRA No. 91,156 pp.  Bouma, J., 1977. Soil Survey and the study of water in unsaturated soil. Soil Survey  Paper No. 13. Soil Survey Institute, Wageningen, 107 pp.  Bouma, J., 1981a. Soil morphology and preferential flow along macropores. Agric. Water  Manage. 3 (4): 235--250.  Bouma, J., 1981b. Soil survey interpretation: estimating use-potentials of a clay soil  under various moisture regimes. Geoderma, 26: 165--177.  Bouma, J., 1983a. Use of soil survey data to select measurement techniques for hydraulic  conductivity. Agric. Water Manage., 6: 177--190.  Bouma, J., 1983b. Estimating moisture-related land qualities for land evaluation. In:  F.P. Miller (Editor), Land Use Planning Techniques and Policies. Am. Soc. Agron.  Spec. Publ., No. 12, pp. 61--77.  Bouma, J. and Dekker, L.W., 1978. A case study of infiltration into dry clay soil, 1.  Morphological observations. Geoderma, 20: 27--40.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1979. Calculation of hydraulic conduc-  tivity of some saturated clay soils using micromorphometric data. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  J., 43: 261--265.  Bouma, J., De Laat, P.J.M., Awater, R.H.C.M., Van Heesen, H.C., Van Holst, A.F. and  Van de Nes, Th.J., 1980. Use of soil survey data in a model for simulating regional soil  moisture regimes. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44 : 808--814.  Bouma, J., De Laat, P.J.M., Van Hoist, A.F. and Van de Nes, Th.J., 1980. Predicting the  effects of changing water-table levels and associated soil moisture regimes for soil  survey interpretations. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 727--802.  Bouma, J., Belmans, C.F.M. and Dekker, L.W., 1982. Water infiltration and redistribution  in a silt loam subsoil with vertical worm channels. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 917--921.  Bouzigues, R., Favrot, J.C. and Hallaire, U., 1981. French heavy soils: characterization  and cartography in relation to drainage. In: M.J. Gardiner (Editor), Land Drainage.  Balkema, Rotterdam, pp. 33--56.  Bullock, P., Newman, A.C.D. and Thomasson, A.J., 1984. Porosity aspects of the re-  generation of soil structure after compaction. J. Soil Tillage Res. In press.  Canada Soil Survey Committee and Expert Committee on Soil Survey, 1970--1982.  Proceedings of Meetings. Agr. Can., Ottawa.  De Jong, R., 1982. Assessment of empirical parameters that describe soil water charac-  teristics. Can. Agric. Eng., 24: 65--70.  De Jong, R. and Loebel, K., 1982. Empirical relations between soil components and  water retention at 1/3 and 15 atmospheres. Can. J. Soil Sci., 62: 343--350.  Eilers, R.G., 1983. Soil water regime classification, 1982. In: J.H. Day and J.C. McMena-  min (Editors). Proc. 4th Meet. Expert Committee on Soil Survey, Agri. Can., pp. 39--  51.  FAO, 1976. A framework for land evaluation. Soils Bulletin 32. Rome.  Farquharson, F.A.K., Mackney, D., Newson, M.D. and Thomasson, A.J., 1978. Estima-  tion of run-off potential of river catchments from soil surveys. Special Survey No. 11,  Harpenden, 29 pp.  Favrot, J.C., 1983. Cartographie et caractdrisation du comportement hydrique des sols.  INRA, Montpellier, 32 pp.  Favrot, J.C. and Devillers, J.L., 1976. l~valuation des besoins en drainage des terres agri-  coles. Colloque CENECA, Paris, 5 pp.  Feodoroff, A., 1962. Ressuyage au sol et capacit~ de r~tention pour l'eau. Ann. Agron.,  16 : 523--547.  G.E.P.P.A., 1981. Synth~se des travaux de la commission de cartographie 1970--1981.  Document du Groupe d'Etude des Probl~mes de P6dologie Appliqu~e, Paris.  Guyon, G., 1971. Mesure de la conductivit6 hydraulique d'un sol par la m6thode du  rabattement de nappe en vue des calculs de drainage. Bull. Tech. du G~nie Rural, No.  110.    99    Haans, J.C.F.M., 1980. Soil resource inventories and their application in the Netherlands.  In: J. Lee and L. van der Plas (Editors), Land Resource Evaluation. Comm. European  Communities, Proc. Wexford Seminar on Land Use and Rural Resources.  Hall, D.G.M., Reeve, M.J., Thomasson, A.J. and Wright, V.F., 1977. Water retention  porosity and density of field soils. Soil Survey Tech. Monograph No. 9, Harpenden,  75 pp.  Hodgson, J.M., 1976. Soil survey field handbook. Soil Survey Tech. Monograph No. 5,  Harpenden, 99 pp.  Hodgson, J.M., 1978. Soil Sampling and Soil Description. Clarendon Press, Oxford,  241 pp.  Ismail, S.N.A., 1975. Micromorphometric soil porosity characterization by means of  electro-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720). Soil Survey Papers, No. 9 Neth. Soil  Survey Inst., Wageningen, 104 pp.  Jamagne, M., 1967. Bases et techniques d'une cartographie des sols. Ann. Agron., 18:  142 pp.  Jones, R.J.A., 1983. The soil survey's field capacity dataset -- an aid to assessing soil  wetness. Text of paper given at British Soc. of Soil Sci. Meeting on 'Soil Water', School  of Agric., Sutton Bonington, Loughborough, 6--8 April, 1983.  Jones, R.J.A. anct Thomasson, A.J., 1984. An agro-climatic data base for England and  Wales. Soil Survey Tech. Monogr. In press.  Jongerius, A., 1957. Morphological investigations of soil structure. Mededelingen van de  Stichting voor Bodemkartering (English summary).  Jongerius, A., 1974. Recent developments in soil micromorphometry. In: G.K. Ruther-  ford (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proc. 4th Int. Work. Meet. Soil Micromorphology.  The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp. 67--83.  McKeague, J.A., Wang, C. and Topp, G.C., 1982. Estimating saturated hydraulic con-  ductivity from soil morphology. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46 : 1239--1244.  Meriaux, S., 1979. Caract~ristiques hydriques des soils. In: M. Bonneau et B. Souchier  (Editors), P~dologie, Tome 2. Masson, Paris, pp. 266--312.  Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, 1975. Soil physical conditions and crop  production. Tech. Bull. 29, H.M.S.O., London, 505 pp.  Muntz, A., Faure, L. and Laine, E., 1905. Etude sur la permeabilit~ des terres faite en vue  de l'arrosage. Ann. Direction de l'Hydraulique, 33: 45--90. (Voir aussi Vols. 37 et 39,  1907).  Nowland, J.L., 1981. Soil water regime classification. In: J.H. Day (Editor), Minutes 3rd  Meet. Expert Comm. Soil Survey Agr. Can., Ottawa, pp. 64--74.  NTS (National Technical Survey), 1970--1981. Reports of Committee on Soil Water.  National Technical Work Planning Conference of the Cooperative Soil Survey, Soil  Conservation Service, U.S.D.A.  Porchet, M. et Laferrere, H., 1935. D4termination des caract~ristiques hydrodynamiques  des sols en place. Ann. Direction de l'Hydraulique, Fascicule 64.  Renger, M. and Henseler, K.L., 1971. Investigation and numerical classification of im-  pedance classes in stagnogley soils of Lower Saxony. Mimeo. Report, Niedersachsi-  schen Landesamtes ffir Bodenforschung, Hannover. (Transl. from German by M.  Reeve ).  Renger, M. and Strebel, O., 1980. Beregnungsbedarf landwirtschaftlicher Kulturen.  In: Abh~ingigkeit vom Boden, Wasser und Boden, 32: 572--576.  Robson, J.D. and Thomasson, A.J., 1977. Soil water regimes. Soil Survey Tech. Mono-  graph No. 11, Harpenden, 57 pp.  Sherwood, M.A., 1982. Soil Survey of Carroll County, Iowa. U.S. Dept. Agric., Soil  Cons. Serv., Washington, D.C.  Shields, J.A. and Sly, W.K., 1984. Aridity indices derived from soil and climatic param-  eters. Tech. Bull., LRRI No. 84-09.    100    Smith, L.P. and Trafford, B.D., 1976. Climate and drainage. Tech. Bull. Min. Agric. Fish.  Fd., London, No. 34.  Soil Conservation Service, 1979--83. Drafts of chapters of the Soil Survey Manual.  U.S.D.A., Washington, D.C.  Soil Conservation Service, 1972. Soil survey laboratory methods and procedures for col-  lecting soil samples. Soil survey Investigation Report No. 1, U.S.D.A., U.S. Govt.  Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Soil Conservation Service, 1983. National Soils Handbook, Part 603. Soil Cons. Serv.,  U.S.D.A., Washington, D.C.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S.D.A., Handbook, No. 18.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S.D.A. Handbook, 436,754 pp.  Thomasson, A.J. (Editor), 1975. Soils and field drainage. Soil Survey Tech. Monograph  No. 7, Harpenden, 80 pp.  Thomasson, A.J. (Editor), 1982. Soil and climatic aspects of workability and trafficabil-  ity. 9th Conf. Int. Soil Tillage Res. Organization, Osijek, Yugoslavia, pp. 551--557.  Topp, G.C. and Binns, M.R., 1976. Field measurement of hydraulic conductivity with a  modified air-entry permeameter. Can. J. Soil Sci., 56: 139--147.  Topp, G.C. and Davis, J.L., 1981. Detecting infiltration of water through soil cracks by  time-domain reflectometry. Geoderma, 26: 13--23.  Topp, G.C., Zebchuk, W.D. and Dumanski, J., 1980. The variation of in situ measured  soil water properties within soil map units. Can. J. Soil Sci., 60: 497--510.  Van Heesen, H.D., 1970. Presentation of the seasonal fluctuation of water table on soil  maps. Geoderma, 4: 257--278.  Van der Sluijs, P. and De Gruijter, J.J., 1984. Water table classes: a method to indicate  seasonal fluctuation and duration of water tables on Dutch soil maps. Agr. Water  Manage. In Press.  Van Wallenburg, C., 1973. Hydromorphic soil characteristics in alluvial soils in connec-  tion with soil drainage. In: Pseudology and Gley. Verlag Chimie, pp. 343--403.  Wang, C. and McKeague, J.A., 1983. Assessing soil structure degradation by field observa-  tions. Canada Agriculture, 29 (2): 13--15.  Wilkinson, B., 1975. Field experience on heavy soils. In: Soil Physical Conditions and  Crop Production. Tech. Bull., 29, Min. Agric. Fish. Food, H.M.S.O., London, pp. 76--  93.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractProcedures used by soil survey organizations in characterizing and interpreting the airwater regimes of soils in France, Germany, The Netherlands, England and Wales, the United States and Canada are summarized and compared. The strengths and weaknesses of the systems are discussed, and research is suggested to resolve problems and to improve the basis of interpretations. The importance of sound field estimates supported regularly by reliable measurements is emphasized. Field estimates are essential in view of the dynamic nature and the spatial variability of some soil physical properties related to the airwater regimes. Research needs include continued development of improved methods of measuring airwater properties of soils, development of improved guidelines for estimating these properties from soil morphology, and identification of the relevant soil properties that can be estimated reliably. Interdisciplinary research is required to integrate expertise in hydrology, soil physics, agronomy and pedology with a view to improving the characterization and interpretation of airwater properties of soils.