 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 205--237                                                      205  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PROCESS STUDIES OF A CHERNOZEMIC PEDON, ALBERTA  (CANADA)    P. SANBORN*' and S. PAWLUK  College of Forest Resources AR-IO, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA  98105  Department of Soil Science, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada T6G 2E3  (Received May 11, 1982; revised version accepted February 9, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Sanborn, P. and Pawluk, S., 1983. Process studies of a Chernozemic pedon, Alberta  (Canada). Geoderma, 31: 205--237.    Soil-forming processes in a Gleyed Black Chernozemic (Aquic Cryoboroll) pedon in  central Alberta, Canada, were investigated. Vegetation similar to the present Boreal  Transition Forest seems to have occupied the region during the Late Holocene. The in-  fluence of this forest ecosystem appears compatible with observed pedon properties,  notably a well-structured, base-saturated mull A horizon. Rapid soil moisture depletion  during the growing season limits the potential for leaching. Readily decomposed, calcium-  rich litter, particularly from understorey shrubs, and cation leaching from the forest  canopy maintain a high base status and mild weathering environment. Faunal and other  processes promote rapid formation of characteristic A horizon fabrics. The suitability  of some current Canadian soil taxonomic concepts is discussed.    INTRODUCTION    An earlier study of Black Chernozemic soils in Alberta (Dudas and  Pawluk, 1969a) found regional differences in Ah horizon structure, appa-  rently related to clay-organic complex properties. Other pedologists have  observed that soils developed on clay-rich glacio-lacustrine materials in the  northern part of the Black Chernozemic soil zone have distinctive Ah hori-  zon properties: a more grayish colour and a stronger granular structure. Be-  cause Black Chernozemic soils occur in more than one vegetation zone in  Alberta, the relationship between their genesis and environmental factors  is evidently complex, yet has received insufficient study.  Pedologists have viewed the Black Chernozemic soils of western Canada  as products of tall-grass prairie (Pettapiece, 1969). Deciduous forest invasion  of grassland is thought to change the direction of soil development, resulting  in degradation of the Chernozemic A horizon. Pettapiece acknowledged that  this view does not account for Black Chernozemic soils which may have    *Present address: Department of Soil Science, University of British Columbia, Vancouver,  B.C., Canada, V6T 2A2.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    206    formed under deciduous forests (Populus balsamifera and Salix spp.) assocl  ated with impaired drainage conditions.  Although the Chernozemic A horizon and the mull humus form have been  defined separately in Canadian soil terminology (Canada Soil Survey Com-  mittee, 1978), they share important characteristics. Recognizing this similar-  ity, Klinka et al. (1981) redefined mull to include the intimately combined  organic and mineral materials characteristic of Chernozemic A horizons. Ac-  cordingly, it is significant that the mull humus form is increasingly viewed as  a polygenetic feature (Duchaufour, 1976). Faunal activity (Nielson and Hole,  1964) and biochemical effects of inorganic constituents such as iron, clay,  manganese, and calcium (Vedy and Jacquin, 1972; Duchaufour, 1973) are  some of the factors involved in mull formation in diverse environments.  Therefore, it may be appropriate to question the view that the mull humus  form of Canadian Black Chernozemic soils is incompatible with the pedo-  genic influence of deciduous forest.  The objectives of this study are to characterize the properties, document  the major current pedogenic processes, and interpret the genesis of a Black  Chernozemic pedon located in central Alberta. Because significant Holocene  environmental change has occurred in the region, process studies are em-  phasized in order to assess the extent to which pedon properties reflect the  present environment. These process studies involve examination of the phys-  ical environment, estimation of litterfall, base return, and litter decomposi-  tion rates, monitoring of the solute composition of precipitation, through-  fall, stemflow, and soil leachates, and an experimental study of soil fabric  reorganization.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The pedon sampled was located at the Ellerslie Research Station of the  University of Alberta (N.E. 24--Tp., 51--R., 25--W 4th) (Fig. 1).  Routine physical and chemical analyses were performed on airdried sam-  ples (passed through a 2-mm sieve) according to the methods described by  the Canada Soft Survey Committee (McKeague, 1978), unless indicated  otherwise. Particle-size analysis was performed by the pipette method, with  ultrasonification used to assist dispersion. Fine clay (&lt; 0.2 ~m) was deter-  mined by centrifugation. Soil pH was measured on saturated-soil/distilled-  water pastes. Exchangeable cations were displaced by 1 N buffered ammo-  nium acetate (pH 7), with total cation exchange capacity determined by  steam distillation of NH3 from ammonium-saturated samples. A Perkin-  Elmer Model 503 atomic absorption spectrophotometer was used to measure  Ca2+, Mg2 Na, and Kin the extracts. The Walkley-Black method for or-  ganic carbon analysis was used and total nitrogen was measured by the semi-  micro Kjeldahl method. Calcium carbonate equivalent was determined by  the method of Bundy and Bremner (1972). Iron and aluminum were ex-  tracted by the dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate method. Humic acids from the  L-F, H, Ahl, ABgj, and Bmgj horizons were extracted by NaOH and Na-pyro-    207     Black Chernozemic Soils  ~  Grassland  Aspen Parkland  Transition Zone  Boreal Forest  0          100        200  I.         I         I    km    Fig. 1. Vegetation zones of southern Alberta (after Zoltai, 1975). Phytolith sampling  locations: 1 = Hay Lakes, 2 = Olds, 3 = Calgary, and 4 = Edmonton.    phosphate (Dormaar, 1967). Extracted humic acids were dialysed against  H+-resin in deionized water and freeze-dried. The humic acids were pressed  into KBr pellets for which infrared spectra were obtained on a Beckman  IR-20 infrared spectrophotometer.  Micromorphological studies were carried out on 7.5 X 5 cm sections cut  from intact sample blocks impregnated with epoxy resin.  Hydrogen-peroxide-treated Ah horizon samples from 4 sites in Alberta  were fractionated by sedimentation and the opal phytolith content of the  silts was estimated by the method of Norgren (1973).  Ca-saturated clay fractions were separated into fine (&lt; 0.2 pm) and coarse  (0.2--2.0 ttm) fractions by centrifugation, freeze-dried, and analysed as fol-  lows.  (1) X-ray diffraction analysis was performed with a Philips diffractometer  and Cu-K-aX-radiation with seven pretreatments: Ca-saturated (54% relative  humidity, glycerol-solvated, and ethylene-glycol-solvated) and K-saturated  (105 at 0% relative humidity, 54% relative humidity, 300, and 550).  Clay samples were mounted on glass slides by the paste method (Theisen and  Harward, 1962).    208    (2) Cation exchange capacity (C.E.C.) was determined on Ca-saturated,  H202-treated samples by extraction with 2 N NaC1 and measurement of the  displaced Ca2by atomic absorption.  (3) Surface area was measured by a modified ethylene glycol monoethyi  ether method (Carter et al., 1965).  (4) Mica content was estimated from the K20 content as determined by  HC1-HF dissolution analysis (Pawluk, 1967), assuming a 10% K20 content  in the mineral.  In spring 1976, the following equipment was installed at the study site:  (1) three piezometers at 4.2, 7.3, and 10.4 m, and a water table well (3.6 m),  (2) Soil Test fiberglass soil moisture cells (MC-310A) in the H, Ah, Bmgj,  Ckgjl, and Ckgj2 horizons, and (3) a Soil Test thermistor temperature probe  (G160). This equipment was monitored weekly during April--November,  1978, and May--October, 1979. Soil temperatures were measured every 3 or  4 weeks during the winter. Precipitation data for the Station were provided  by the Division of Meteorology, Department of Geography, University of  Alberta.  Three lysimeters were installed in May, 1978. Using hydraulic pressure,  three 10-cm diameter plastic cylinders were forced to different depths in the  soil. The cylinders and their enclosed soil columns were withdrawn and suf-  ficient soil was removed from the bottom of each column so that the follow-  ing horizon sequences remained in the cylinders: (1) L-F; (2) L-F, H; and (3)  L-F, H, Ahl, Ah2. Below the soil columns, the collection apparatus was in-  stalled in each cylinder, consisting of a 125-ml plastic beaker fastened below  a funnel filled with plastic beads. The cylinders were placed back in the soil,  with a sampling tube extending from the beaker to the surface. The collec-  tion beakers were pumped out weekly during the growing season.  Precipitation was collected in an open field 150 m east of the site and  throughfall was sampled under three different forest canopy densities (col-  lectors T1, T2, and T3). Stemflow was obtained from two Populus balsami-  fera trees with collectors consisting of a rubber gutter secured to the trunk,  emptying via a funnel and tubing into a 5-1 plastic jug. Sample collectors  for precipitation, throughfall, and stemflow were changed weekly during the  growing season.  After collection, all samples were filtered with Whatman No. 41 ashless  filter paper and pH and bicarbonate were determined. The remainder of each  sample was frozen until other analyses could be performed.  The inorganic constituents measured were: (1) sulphate, by a turbidi-  metric procedure using Sulfaver reagent pillows (Hach Chemical) and a con-  ditioning reagent; (2) cations (Ca2+, Mg2+, Na K+) and Fe and A1 by atomic  absorption; and (3) Si, by the molybdate method (Weaver et al., 1968).  Four soluble organic constituents were determined: (1) organic carbon  (Mebius, 1960); (2) carbohydrates, by the anthrone method as modified by  Oades (1967); (3) total phenols (Swain and Hillis, 1959); and (4) uronic  acids, by the carbazole method (Lynch et al., 1957). Samples of the August    209    4, 1979, collection of throughfall, stemflow, and soil leachates were freeze-  dried and infrared spectra were produced by Spectral Services, Dept. Chem-  istry, Univ. Alberta.  Litter traps similar to those used by Cragg et al. (1977}, were placed at  ground level on plastic sheets at 6 locations in an undisturbed portion of the  forest stand at the site. Collections were made at intervals ranging from 1 to  6 weeks from mid-May to late October, 1979. Litter was oven-dried at 80,  and stored for analysis. Subsamples from Populus balsamifera, P. tremuloi-  des, and Cornus stolonifera leaf litter were taken on a weighted basis, allow-  ing for the proportion of the year's total litter collected in each sampling  period. These subsamples were combined for each species, ground in a Wiley-  mill and digested for elemental analysis by the method of Parkinson and  Allen (1975). Ca2+, Mg2 and Kcontents of these digests were determined  by atomic absorption.  Litter bags (20 X 20 cm) were prepared in October, 1978, using freshly  fallen leaves of the same three species. A 3-mm mesh was used to permit  entry and feeding by soil mesofauna (Gosz et al., 1973). Ten sets, each with  one bag of the three species (5 g per bag), were placed at the base of the  1978 litter layer at the beginning of November. In 1979, one set was recov-  ered monthly from May until November; a final collection was made in  March, 1980. The initial litter materials and the monthly litter bag samples  were dried, weighed, ground, and digested as for the litter trap samples.  Duplicate 2-g samples of the original leaf materials were ground to pass a  2-mm sieve and incubated according to the method described by I.A.E.A.-  F.A.O. (1976). Evolved CO2 was collected in NaOH and measured by titra-  tion with standardized HC1. The carbon content of the leaf materials before  incubation was measured with the LECO induction furnace.  Cylindrical cores (7.5 diameter 8 cm) were taken from the Ckgj2 hori-  zon with a Uhland corer and inserted beneath the L-F horizon and within  the Ahl horizon. The cores were installed in September, 1977, and two were  retrieved in October, 1979, oven~lried, and thin sections prepared.    ENVIRONMENTAL SETTING    The study site is on the level to undulating Lake Edmonton Plain (West-  gate, 1969) which is mantled by glacio-lacustrine deposits that have silt loam  to silty clay loam textures at the Research Station. These sediments were  deposited when the Laurentide glacier retreated, ca. 12000--11000 B.P. (St.  Onge, 1972). The subdued topography and fine textured materials have cre-  ated imperfectly to poorly drained conditions at many sites.  The present climate of central Alberta is continental, with a large summer  to winter temperature range (July mean, 16.4, vs. January mean, -13.2)  and unevenly distributed precipitation. Half of the mean annual precipita-  tion (44.5 cm) falls in June--August (Bowser et al., 1962).  The study site vegetation fits the concept of the Parkland--Boreal Forest  transition zone identified by Zoltai (1975). Dominated by 80--85 year old    210    Populus balsamifera and some P. tremuloides, the stand has a dense low  shrub layer (~ 2 m) of red osier dogwood (Comus stolonifera). White spruce  (Picea glauca) would be the next dominant if a seed source were available  (I. Corns, pers. commun., 1982). Land survey records (ca. 1883)indicate  that similar forests covered the Lake Edmonton region before European  settlement.  During the Holocene, vegetation changes in central Alberta may not have  been as marked as in the other prairie provinces of Canada. Some northward  movement of the grassland zone likely occurred ca. 8700--6000 B.P. (C.  Schweger, pets. commun., 1982), but pollen studies 30 km east of Edmon-  ton indicate that forest cover has existed with little change since ca. 2800  B.P. (Vance, 1979).  Plant opal in soil is produced mostly by grasses (Norgren, 1973), so it is  significant that Ah horizons at the Research Station and another site near  Edmonton, Hay Lakes (Fig. 1), contained 10 times less opal than a similar  horizon from a Black Chernozemic soil in the grassland near Calgary (0.48  and 0.83%, vs. 6.00%). A Black Chernozemic Ah sample from Olds (Fig. 1),  on the boundary of the Transition Forest and Parkland zones, had an inter-  mediate plant opal content (3.20%). This pattern is consistent with the other  evidence for a predominance of forest vegetation during the Late Holocene  in the Edmonton area.    PEDON CHARACTERISTICS    On the basis of morphological and analytical properties, the pedon under  study is classified as a Gleyed Black Chernozem (Canada Soil Survey Com-  mittee, 1978) (Fig. 2). The equivalent in "Soil Taxonomy" is Aquic Cryo-  boroll (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). A complete morphological description,  using criteria defined by the Canada Soft Survey Committee (1978), is pro-  vided in the Appendix. A micromorphological description, using the format  and terminology of Brewer (1976) and Brewer and Pawluk {1975), is avail-  able on request from the authors.  The 18 cm thick sequence of organic horizons consists mostly of Populus  spp. leaf litter in various stages of decomposition. Fecal pellets, comprising  humigranic units, occur in two size groups in the L-F: 0.25~0.75 mm in  diameter (randomly distributed) and 50 pm in diameter (concentrated near  leaf residues) (Fig. 3). These fecal materials are most abundant at the base of  the H-horizon, where some mineral material is also present, producing mull-  humigranic fabrics.  Fabrics of the Ah horizon are dominantly mullgranoidic and mullgranic,  with structural units ranging from 0.1 to 1.0 mm in diameter (Fig. 4). The  Ah horizons have a lower organic matter content, fewer roots, and a transi-  tion from granular to subangular blocky structure with depth. The Ah4 hori-  zon shows greater coalescence of units (mullgranoidic--vughy porphyric).  Plasma fabrics are weakly skelmosepic in all Ah horizons because of partial  masking of fabrics by organic plasma.    211    Fig. 2. Gleyed Black Chernozemic profile, Ellerslie Research Station study site.    Fig. 3. Thin section view of L-F horizon, with dominance of 50 um diameter fecal pellets  (a), beside leaf residues (b).    The ABgj horizon is discontinuous, with weak structure, mottling, and a  somewhat bleached appearance.  The B horizon is divided into upper (Bmgj) and lower (Bmkgj) portions  because of weaker subangular blocky structure and weak effervescence in the    212    Fig. 4. Thin section view of mullgranoidic fabric, Ahl horizon. Units range from 0.2 to  1.0 mm diameter.    latter. Mottles are fewer than in the ABgj, although of similar size and colour.  The structural units are more angular and coalesced than in the Ah horizons,  resulting in a dominantly vughy porphyric and fragmoidic fabric. Root chan-  nels and aggrotubules are evident. Plasma fabrics are argillasepic and insepic.  The BCkgj and Ckgj horizons have moderate effervescence, weak struc-  ture, and heavy clay textures. Mottles become more distinct with depth and  are both beside voids and within structural units. Mangans occur on joint  plane surfaces, particularly in the Ckgj horizons (Fig. 5). Rare void argillans  were noted in the Ckgj2. Fabrics range between fragmoidic and vughy por-  phyric, and local elongated zones contain higher contents of sand and coarse  silt. Plasma fabrics are dominantly argillasepic and omnisepic, the latter in  zones of higher clay content.  All mineral horizons are clay-rich, ranging from 42 to 64% clay (Table I).  The genetic horizon type has no relationship to texture and the clay content  generally increases with depth.  Both organic C and total N contents are highest in the organic horizons  and the upper Ah horizons.  Cation exchange capacity is highest in the horizons with a high organic  matter content (Table I) and base saturation is almost 100%, with Ca2and  Mg2+ as the dominant cations (Sanborn, 1981). Carbonates are present in  small amounts, with a maximum of 1.10% in the Ckgjl horizon. Soil    r    213    Fig. 5. Thin section view of iron (a) and manganese (b) nodules, BCkgj horizon. Lower  manganese nodule is approximately 0.2 mm diameter.    TABLEI    Selected physical and chemical properties of studied site    Horizon    Sand     Clay  Fine   CaCO3     Organic  N     pH    C.E.C..1    Fed.2   Ald.3  (%)       (%)   clay   equiv,      carbon   (%)  (%)  (%)      (%)    L-F        n.d..4    n.d.   n.d.   n.d.        48.5      1.80  7.2    138.6      n.d.     n.d.  F-H        n.d.       n.d.   n.d.   n.d.        39.4      2.20  6.9    140.7      n.d.     n.d.  H          n.d.      n.d.   n.d.   n.d.        41.1      2.40  6.6    159.9      n.d.     n.d.  Ahl         9       48    20    n.d.         5.9     0.53  6.1     54.2      0.44    0.09  Ah2         9       46    16    n.d.         2.7     0.13  6.4    41.1      0.39    0.08  Ah3        10        46    17    n.d.          1.4      0.16  6.8     40.1      0.53    0.09  Ah4        9       49    23    n.d.        0.5     0.08  6.7    35.9      0.87    0.10  ABgj       11        42    19    n.d.          0.3      0.06  6.9     24.1      0.90    0.09  Bmgj        7        53    19    0.00         0.5      0.07  7.3     39.1      1.14    0.10  Bmkgj      16        51    15    0.48         0.4      0.06  7.3     43.0*s    0.99    0.08  BCkgj       5        61    19    0.52         0.6      0.07  7.6     55.0*s    1.07    0.06  Ckgjl        3        63    18    1.10         0.6      0.06  7.8     51.1*s    1.12    0.06  Ckgj2       2       64    19    1.04        0.6     0.06  7.4     59.4*s    1.17    0.07    ,lmeq./100   ,2   g;   dlthionite-extractable Fe; ,3 dithionite-extractable AI; *4n.d. = not determined;  , s includes both exchangeable and extractable cations; carbonates present.    reaction values range from slightly acid to mildly alkaline (pH 6.1 to 7.8),  with the lowest value in the Ahl horizon.  Dithionite-extractable Fe occurs at about half the concentration in the  Ah horizons as in the B and C horizons, whereas dithionite~xtractable A1 is  present at low, more constant levels throughout the pedon (Table I).  The fine clays are dominantly smectite (60--70%) and mica (20--25%)  with some kaolinite, whereas the coarse clays contain 35--40% smectite,  30--34% mica, 10--15% kaolinite, and small amounts of chlorite and quartz  (Table II). Diffraction peaks are usually sharp and well-defined, suggesting  little mineral weathering.    214    TABLE II  Clay mineralogy*'    Horizon    Smectite.2     Mica.3      Kaolinite.4     Chlorite.4     Quartz.4  (%)        (%)      (%)        (%)       (%)    Ahl     42 (69)      33 (23)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       3--6  Ah2     37 (67)      31 (22)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       3--6  Ah3     42 (67)      31 (22)    10--15 (&lt;5)   4--7         0  Ah4     35 (65)      34 (23)    10--15 (&lt;5)   4--7       2--4  ABgj     38 (66)      31 (22)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       2--4  Bmgj     38 (65)      31 (24)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       2--4  Bmkgj    42 (66)      30 (24)    10--15 (&lt;5)   6--10      3--6  BCkgj    38 (70)      30 (25)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       2--4  Ckgjl     37 (63)      31 (25)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       2--4  Ckgj2    42 (61)      32 (27)    10--15 (&lt;5)   5--9       2--4    *' Mineral content in 0.2--2.0-um clay given first, followed by value for &lt; 0.2-um  clay in parentheses.  ,2 Average smectite values based on surface area, using 850 m2/g for montmorillonite  standard, and cation exchange capacity, using 110 m.e./100 g for smectite.  ,3 Based on 10% K20 content.  ,4 Estimated from X-ray diffraction patterns. Chlorite and quartz not detected in  &lt; 0.2-urn clays.    i                                             '                         L-F                                           J    3000               2500               2000           1800            1600           1400  Wavenumber (cm"1)  Fig. 6. Infrared spectra of humic acids from selected horizons.    Infrared spectra of extracted humic acids show only subtle differences  between horizons, For the 2500--1800 cm-' spectral region, the three upper  horizons have a slight upward slope, but for the Ah4 and Brag} humic acids  the same region is essentially fiat (Fig. 6). Three other absorption bands    215    identified in humic acid spectra by Dormaar (1967) and Dormaar and  Lutwick (1966) appear in these samples. The 2920 and 2850 cm-' bands in-  dicate aliphatic CHx groups; the former is strongest in the L-F humic acid  spectrum and absent or extremely weak in the others. Carbonyl stretch of  carboxylic acids or of ester linkages is indicated by absorption at 1725 cm-'.  This band is strongest in the L-F and H horizon spectra and is absent lower  in the solum. Finally, the 1525 cm-1 band, assigned to aromatic C---C, is ab-  sent in all spectra.    PROCESS STUDIES    Physical environment    In 1978 and 1979, the calculated 50 cm mean annual soil temperatures  were 4.7 and 2.5, whereas the mean summer soil temperatures (MSST)  were 9.8 and 7.4. Except for the 1979 MSST, these data fit the Cryo-  boreal soil temperature class (Clayton et al., 1977). Frozen soil persisted un-  til late May in 1979, as against late April in 1978 (Fig. 7}. During spring  thaw, temperatures stabilized at close to 0 throughout the soil profile.  Isothermal conditions (8--9) also occurred in the September--October  periods. Summer maximum and winter minimum temperatures occurred  1--2 months later at 100 cm rather than at 20 cm.  Changes in soil moisture content during the April--November periods of  1978 and 1979 reflected several factors: rainfall amounts and frequency,  winter snow depth, interception by vegetation and litter, and water use by  vegetation. Total precipitation was 47% higher during the 1978 period (468  mm vs. 319 mm). Snow cover persisted 2--3 weeks longer in spring 1979.  The H horizon had both the highest levels and widest fluctuations of mois-  ture content, reflecting the high water-holding capacity of organic matter  and the effect of evapotranspiration (Figs. 8 and 9). The Ah horizon usually  showed the next highest moisture contents and variability. The B and C  horizons showed lower moisture contents and very subdued fluctuations.  In April and May, 1978, moisture levels remained high in both the H and  Ah horizons as a result of snowmelt, rainfall, and lack of plant growth.  During June--August, water use by plants depleted soil moisture, although  major storms in mid-July (90 ram) and mid-August (55 mm) briefly in-  creased the H horizon moisture content. As plant growth slowed in Septem-  ber, H horizon moisture levels rose, but no change occurred in the Ah hori-  zon. Few readings were obtained from the B or C horizons.  In 1979, a deeper snowpack and higher April precipitation resulted in all  horizons having higher moisture contents than during the previous spring.  Lower summer and fall precipitation caused a progressive drying in all hori-  zons, with the  result that spring moisture levels were not restored before  winter. Because the lower summer precipitation of 1979 was closer to the  average for the Edmonton area, the soil moisture regime that year probably  represents more typical conditions at the study site.    t~3    oC  '51                   __~                  :2oom         r ~       ~ocm     ~~  10!              ~i~,2~,,~ ~            100 cm    4  -sl  F   M   A ~M---J ~ j~ A~ s " o "  N ;  D~  J  ~-~---~---~--A--~  M ' J '  j "  A ~  s '  o ~ .'  D-~-T  1978                                                              1979  Fig. 7. Soil temperatures at 20, 50, and 100 cm, February, 1978, to January, 1980.      .....             ~    i  c  o  c ,4  o  0  (1)  ~o  S    oH  ql0,J~,                                    ,Ah                                    Bmgj    '            "I,,   ~----~-~  .....  ,i    ,I '  (}            -          '                             A  Fig. 8. Soil moisture content and precipitation, April to November, 1978.    Precip  mm    20('     Hu  O  O  @   100  e)  0  ~e    ,,,  ~,"  ',,  ,I    \    /    ,__J~    oH  mAh  oBmgj  ACkgjl  ',,'Ckgj2    A '     M     '     J     '     J     '    A     '    S     '     0  Fig. 9. Soil moisture content and precipitation, April to November, 1979.    Precip  rnrn  f '    N    217    218    Interception by the vegetation canopy and litter layer at the site reduced  the amount of rainfall entering the soil. For example, Populus tremuloides  stands in northern Alberta have interception losses of 8--9% of total rainfall  (Parker, 1978). When combined with soil moisture depletion during the  growing season, this restricts major leaching events to the spring snowmelt  period and infrequent large summer rainstorms.  Piezometric head values showed gradual seasonal changes during the  study. In 1978, head values fell between mid-June and late September and  then rose until late November. In spring, 1979, head values were higher than  in 1978 and this trend continued until late June, probably reflecting the  above average precipitation in 1978. At all times, the head was highest in the  10.4 m piezometer while the 4.5-m piezometer remained dry. This indicated  upward movement of groundwater, which likely moved into a more perme-  able sand and gravel layer approximately 4.5 m below the surface, to dis-  charge elsewhere in the landscape. The water table well remained dry except  in May, 1979, when it was within 1.5 m of the surface for 2--3 weeks. This  condition was a perched water table because the 4.5-m piezometer remained  dry. Except for this short episode, groundwater was not close enough to the  surface to affect the pedon, even though discharge was occurring at the  depth of the lowest piezometer.    Litterfall    The total litterfall from May 17 to October 31, 1979, amounted to 3538  kg ha-', with most accumulating from mid-September to mid-October.  Populus balsamifera leaf litter, including a small amount of bud scales and  seeds, accounted for 70.2% of the total, Populus tremuloides leaves amoun-  ted to 7.1%, and leaves and reproductive structures of Comus stolonifera  contributed 16.3%.  Three important components of the organic matter returned to the soil  are neglected by these litter trap data. (1) Herbaceous plant biomass was not  measured. (2) Root death was not estimated. The few studies of root turn-  over in soils under deciduous forest suggest that this source contributes at  least as much organic matter as above-ground litterfall (Cox et al., 1978;  Harris et al., 1977). (3) Because litter was not collected during winter and  early spring, branch and twig litter was underestimated considerably.  The annual litterfall estimate from this site is within the range reported  for aspen forests in the cool temperate zone: 1123--2291 kg ha-1 in south-  western Quebec (Coldwell and DeLong, 1950), 1734 kg ha-1 in the Kana-  naskis valley, Alberta (Cragg et al., 1977) and 3620--4470 kg ha-I in the  U.S.S.R. (Rodin and Brazflevich, 1967).  For three major nutrient elements, Ca, Mg, and K, the leaves and repro-  ductive structures of Populus spp. and Cornus stolonifera showed differing  concentrations (Table III). Although both Populus species had similar Ca and  Mg contents, the K content ofP. trernutoides was closer to that of C. stoloni-    TABLE III  Nutrient contents of leaf litter    Species         Ca                            Mg                          K    %      kg ha-1 yr-i    % of     %      kg ha-I yr-1  % of  total*l                        total.1    %    kg ha-1 yr-~  % of  total.1    P. balsamifera  2.17   52.6          71.9    0.36    8.76       77.9  P. tremuloides  2.08    5.1            7.0    0.36    0.88         7.8  C. stolonifera   2.77   15.5          21.2    0.29    1.60       14.2    0.73       17.80                80.3  0.60    1.47         6.6  0.52    2.90        13.1    Total                 73.2                         11.24                      22.17    ,1% of total returned by leaf litter of the three dominant species.    b=a  CD    220    fera. The latter had the lowest K and Mg contents, but was about 30% higher  in Ca content than the average of the two Populus species. P. balsamifera re~  turned the largest total amounts of these elements to the soil, but because  of its higher Ca content, C. stolonifera accounted for more than 20% of the  Ca returned in leaf litterfall. This parallels the finding that another Cornus  species has a significant role in Ca-cycling in eastern U.S. forests (Thomas,  1969). The nutrient quantities returned in litterfall at the study site are  within the higher range of values reported for aspen forests (Table IV).    TABLE IV    Comparative data for nutrient return in aspen forest (kg ha-1 yr-1)  Location and         Ca            Mg         K           References  particulars  U.S.S.R. (total litter) 66.0--105.1  9.9--14.2  22.4--84.7  6.8          9.6  6.2          6.2    Alaska (50 years old, 48.0  leaf litter only)  Alaska (120 years old, 40.2  leaf litter only)  Kananaskis, Alberta  (leaf litter only)   35.8    Remezov and Pogrebnyak  (1969)  Van Cleve and Noonan  (1975)  Van Cleve and Noonan  (1975)    5.7         10.6         Cragg et al. (1977)    Litter decomposition    Decomposition studies of the three dominant leaf litter types showed  broadly similar trends for the two methods employed. In the incubation  experiment, C. stolonifera leaves decomposed twice as fast as the Populus  spp. leaves when particle size, temperature, and moisture content were held  constant in the absence of mesofauna {Fig. 10). In litterbags, C. stolonifera  leaves also showed the fastest weight loss, altho~h the differences between  this species and Populus spp. were not statistically significant because of the  limited number of samples (Fig. 11). The marked over-winter weight losses  likely resulted from leaching of soluble constituents during the March--April  snowmelt and spring rains. P. balsamifera leaves were larger, thicker, and less  brittle than both other types and therefore had a slower rate of weight loss.  By the end of the experiment, the P. tremuloides leaves were more skeleton-  ized than those of P. balsamifera, whereas little remained of the C. stoloni-  fera leaves other than petioles, major veins, and masses of fecal pellets.  The litterbag weight losses after 12 months for P. tremuloides and P. bal-  samifera were 37.4% and 30.0%. The more rapid weight loss by the former  is attributed to a higher content of leachable substances (Lousier and Par-  kinson, 1976). A similar rate for this species was observed in New Brunswick  (MacLean and Wein, 1978). Comparative data were not available for C.  stolonifera but it is significant that leaves of the related C. florida have a    40    35  030  0  69    -o 25  =&gt;  o  &gt; 20  {3  lO  5    C. stolonifera  P. balsamifera  P. tremuloides    /    /  /  1 o      2'0      3ro      4'0      5'0      6'0      7'0    Incubation time (days)  Fig. 10. Incubation experiment: rates of CO2 production from leaf litter materials.    221    100    80    ~.60  ~-40  c  2o     a                                                                    ~  1: I~ balsamifera  0.93    2: R tremuloides  0.97    3: C. stolonifera   0.85    0       1       2       3      4       5      (~  Fig. 11. Litter bag weight loss rates.    Months    shorter half-life than those of any other species cited by Lousier and Parkin-  son (1976).  Comparisons of nutrient contents in the litterbag samples during the ex-  periment showed trends that differed by species and element. In C. stoloni-    222    fera leaf litter, Ca content showed wide fluctuations converging on the initial  value, compared to Populus spp. which displayed an increasing Ca content  after several months (Fig. 12). The Mg-content remained close to the original  value for C. stolonifera and about 50% lower for Populus spp. K showed the  smallest species-related difference in its behaviour and the largest rates of  loss, ranging from 45 to 75%. Most of this loss occurred during late winter  and early spring.  These data suggest a mobility ranking of K &gt; Mg &gt; Ca. Calcium is concen-  trated in structural components of leaves, so its rate of loss is controlled by    4.2-  q  4,0-  ~Ca  3.8-  3.6-  3.4-  3.2-  3,0-  2.e ~.7----- -  2.6  %~o.  0.2~  0,1~    0.9  ~K8  o~\  \  0.6  0.5 ~  \\  0.4  0.3  0.2  0.1.  1   2   3    ~Y  11\    Q  =y       "1[    C. stolonifera  P. balsamifera  P. tremuloides       s   "~   e   9   to  11   12  Months    Fig. 12. Nutrient content of decomposing leaf litter: Ca, Mg, and K.    223    the rate of tissue weight loss (Gosz et al., 1973; Attiwill, 1968). K is rapidly  leached from leaves of all species, whereas Mg has an intermediate rate of  loss (Lousier and Parkinson, 1978).    Water chemistry: precipitation, throughfall, stemflow and lysimeter leach-  ates    This part of the study documents trends in water chemistry at the study  site rather than attempting to establish chemical budgets. The latter would  require many more collectors to allow for spatial variability in the amounts  and composition of lysimeter leachates. In particular, large voids in the soil  are unpredictably distributed but can affect the movement and composition  of soil water. Exclusion of plant roots by the lysimeter walls affects the soil  solution by: (1) prevention of water uptake for transpiration, producing  leachate volumes greater than would be expected from soil moisture trends;  (2) prevention of nutrient uptake, resulting in higher solute concentrations  (Feller, 1977); and (3) elimination of rhizosphere effects, such as root exu-  dation and respiration. For these reasons, the data are presented as un-  weighted means and only general trends are discussed.  The mean pH was lowest in incoming precipitation andincreased down-  ward through the ecosystem, with the greatest change occurring as the preci-  pitation passed through the forest canopy (Table V). The major cations were  present in low concentrations in precipitation, but large amounts of Kwere  added to throughfall, along with lesser amounts of Ca 2+, Mg2+, and Na  Stemflow, compared to throughfall, was enriched in three of these elements,  while having similar concentrations of Na  K was about ten times more  concentrated in stemflow than in throughfall. Cation concentrations in stem-  flow, except for Ca2+, were equal to or greater than those in the soil leach-  ates.  Once throughfall entered the soil, cation behaviour differed with the ele-  ment. K  which was most abundant in the L-F leachate, decreased by about  50% between each sampling level. Naremained least abundant, increasing  slightly in the Ah horizon leachate. Ca2+ and Mg2+ behaved almost identi-  cally, each with concentrations in the L-F leachate being much greater than  in the throughfall. These two cations then decreased in the H-horizon lea-  chates but reached a maximum in the Ah leachate.  Sample volumes permitted determination of only two anions, HCO~ and  SO42-. Other anions were likely present: NO3-, which was identified by in-  frared analysis of concentrated samples, and C1-, which occurs in small  amounts, averaging 0.5 mg 1-1, in precipitation in central Alberta (Summers  and Hitchon, 1973). HCO3- was the dominant anion and its behaviour fol-  lowed the trend of increasing cation concentration from precipitation to soil  leachate samples. Stemflow contained HCO3- concentrations equal to or  greater than those in the soil leachates. SO~- concentrations were lowest in  precipitation, higher in throughfall and stemflow, and increased with depth  in the soil leachates.    b~  b~    TABLE V  Precipitation, throughfall, sternflow, and soil leachate chemistry: inorganic constituents*'    Source.2   pH           K+            Ca2+         Na+            Mg2+          SO~           HCO~        Si  (meq. 1-')    (meq. l-')   (meq. 1-')    (meq. 1-')    (rneq. 1-~)    (meq. 1-')   (mg 1-~)    P       6.33 (0.45) 0.01 (0.008) 0.05 (0.06) 0.01 (0.009) 0.01 (0.007) 0.04 (0.006) 0.21 (0.08) n.d..3  T1      6.90 (0.42) 0.36 (0.25)  0.26 (0.18) 0.06 (0.06)  0.11 (0.07)  n.d.        0.47 (0.30) n.d.  T2      6.89 (0.37) 0.18 (0.12   0.18 (0.12) 0.04 (0.04)  0.07 (0.04)  0.06 (0.0)   0.30 (0.16) n.d.  T3      7.20 (0.22) 0.46 (0.36)  0.25 (0.20) 0.06 (0.06)  0.11 (0.08)  0.21 (0.17)  0.74 (0.57) n.d.  S1       7.44 (0.31) 3.48 (1.56)  1.02 (0.65) 0.04 (0.03)  0.54 (0.19)  n.d.       5.61 (2.83) n.d.  S2      7.20 (0.08) 2.47 (1.18)  0.79 (0.67) 0.07 (0.06)  0.47 (0.29)  0.16 (0.12)  1.67 (1.34) n.d.  L-F     7.33 (0.24) 0.94 (0.22)  1.93 (0.96) 0.08 (0.04)  0.48 (0.31)  0.06 (0.06)  2.20 (0.33) n.d.  H       7.21 (0.28) 0.49 (0.21)  1.61 (0.59) 0.08 (0.04)  0.34 (0.11)  0.28 (0.11)  1.64 (0.86) n.d.  Ah      7.33 (0.31) 0.26 (0.15)  2.01 (0.71) 0.10 (0.06)  0.61 (0.30)  0.40 (0.12)  1.64 (0.77) 6.29 (4.04)    *~ Mean values, with standard deviation in (),  *2 p = precipitation, T = throughfall, S = sternflow, L-F, H, and Ah are lowest horizon in each of three lysirneter columns.  .3 n.d. -- not determined.    225    Silicon was detected only in the Ah-horizon leachates, with an average  concentration of 6.29 mg 1-1 and a range of 0.40 to 10.35 mg 1-1. No dis-  solved Fe and A1 were detected by atomic absorption. Filtering of Ah-hori-  zon leachates did not indicate suspended clay.  For organic constituents in solution, soil leachates had concentrations  either roughly equal to those in throughfall (C, uronides, and saccharides)  or lower, as in the case of total phenols (Table VI). The neutral pH values  for the soil leachates indicate that only limited amounts of organic acids  are being produced in the soil.    TABLE VI  Precipitation, throughfall, stemflow, and soil leachate chemistry: organic constituents*'    Source.2    Soluble C     Uronides       Saccharides     Phenols  (rag 1-1)     (rag 1-~)      (mg 1-1)      (rag 1-')    P             n.d.            n.d.             n.d.             n.d..3  T1        40 (19.7)    12 (0)       24 (23.8)     20 (18.3)  W2        28 (15.1)    9 (2.1)      9 (5.6)      8 (4.6)  T3        35 (17.3)    12 (3.2)      12 (9.6)      14 (13.5)  S,        83 (56.3)    35 (16.2)     33 (21.1)     21 (10.0)  S2        53 (24.6)    21 (5.0)      32 (24.1)     31 (29.5)  a-F       46 (17.7)    15 (6.3)      10 (7.3)      4 (1.4)  H        51 (21.4)   13 (3.4)      6 (3.0)      4 (2.7)  Ah       41 (22.9)   12 (13.3)     10 (4.8)      2 (1.1)    1 Mean values, with standard deviation in ().  2 p = precipitation, T = throughfall, S = stemflow; L-F, H, and Ah are lowest horizon in  each of three lysimeter columns.  3 n.d. = not determined.    Infrared spectra of freeze-dried soil leachates, throughfall, and stemflow  were interpreted according to criteria set out by Dormaar (1970, 1978).  Inorganic salts (carbonates, sulphates, and nitrates) dominated the five spec-  tra, obscuring most absorption bands for organic components (Fig. 13). The  2900 cm-1 band for aliphatic CHx stretch was evident only in throughfall,  stemflow, and L-F leachate samples. Carbonyl absorption (1729 cm-1) was  not detected. The 1380 cm-1 absorption band attributed to the carboxylate  anion partially coincided with the strong CO3~- and NO~ bands and was  apparent only in the L-F leachates. Benzenoid (900--700 cm-') and phenol  (1330--1110 cm-1 ) bands were hidden by adjacent absorptions by inorganic  salts.  The data indicate that forest canopy leaching exerts a significant and  spatially variable influence on the chemistry of intercepted precipitation.  For inorganic substances, their particular form in plant tissues governs their  rate of leaching. While Na and K occur in easily leached ionic forms, Ca oc-  curs in structural components and is more slowly released by ion exchange    226         \"~"       /         ' 'v/  "k.J   'v' i IJ il'  .'"  ',       / \     /' ~ ~,~    / ~H  13  Wavenurnber {cm-')  Fig. 18. Infrared spectra of freeze-dried throughfal] (T), stemflow (S), and lysimeter  leachates (L-F, H, and Ah).    at the leaf surface involving Hfrom carbonic acid in precipitation (Mecklen-  burg et al., 1966). The ranked abundances, K &gt; Ca &gt; Mg &gt; Na, reflect these  differences in mobility, along with the low content of Na in plant tissues  (Lousier and Parkinson, 1978). In stemflow, concentrations of dissolved in-  organic substances were often higher than in throughfall because of longer  contact between the leaching water and the plant surface.  For soluble organic substances, the throughfaU and stemflow data agree  with findings of other studies, notably in the abundance of carbohydrates  (Eaton et al., 1973; Mahendruppa, 1976). Because soluble carbohydrate  concentrations in throughfall and stemflow exceeded those in the soil  leachates, these constituents of the soil solutions may partially originate  outside the soft.  Cation transport in soil is controlled by the anion content of the soil solu-  tion, inasmuch as the negative charges of the exchange complex are immo-  bile (McCoU, 1973; Johnson, 1975). For the Ellerslie site, the soil leachate  analyses indicate a bicarbonate&lt;tominated system which is typical of the  temperate zone. The declining soil leachate Kconcentration with depth re-  flects several influences. Peak K concentrations in the L-F leachates result  from leaching of both the tree canopy and the decomposing litter. Inasmuch  as the lysimeter design excluded roots, the drop in Kconcentrations in the  H-horizon leachates may indicate K accumulation by soil flora such as fungi    227    (Lousier and Parkinson, 1978). The further loss of Kwhich occurred after  leachates passed through the Ah horizon likely resulted from fixation by  micaceous minerals. In contrast to K  other cations, notably Ca2 main-  tained more constant concentrations in the soil leachates, suggesting greater  mobility (Riekerk, 1971). The abundance of Ca2in the soil leachates pre-  sumably results from its release through canopy leaching and litter decompo-  sition and accounts for its dominance on the exchange complex.    Micromorphological change    After two years, pedogenic fabric reorganization was most evident in the  parent material core placed immediately under the litter layer. The upper  surface of that core had become quite irregular, with many rounded aggre-  gates (1--3 mm diameter) being partially or completely detached (Fig. 14).  Surface staining by organic matter had occurred, resulting in a browner  colour than at the bottom of the core. Litter materials were partially mixed  with the core surface and leaf petioles had been drawn into larger voids. In  thin section, the structure of the upper half of the core appeared more open.  Planar voids had widened and there was a larger number of smaller (&lt; 2 mm  diameter) granoidic and fragmoidic units (Fig. 15). Under magnification,  surface changes were evident, with newly-formed granic and granoidic units  being intermingled with litter or humified material (Fig. 16). The core placed     i i iiiii  i~ ~ ii~~I~    Fig. 14. Upper surface of parent-material core placed beneath litter layer for two years  (7.5 cm diameter). Note numerous rounded aggregates and partial incorporation of or-  ganic debris.    228    Fig. 15. Granic unit (a), 1.0 mm diameter, at surface of core shown in Fig. 8.    Fig. 16. Granic unit (a) incorporating 0,1 mm thick leaf fragments, at surface of core  shown in Fig. 8.    229    in the Ah horizon showed fewer changes, principally a more pronounced  development of joint planes and some entry of mullgranic units into the  larger voids near the upper surface.  Several processes were likely responsible for these effects. The widening  of planar voids may have resulted from frost action and the shrink-swell  activity of the smectite-rich clays. Biological processes, such as feeding by  mesofauna, probably caused the incorporation of organic debris, particularly  in the upper core. Formation of granic and granoidic units at the core sur-  face could be the result of excretion by soil-ingesting fauna, notably earth-  worms.    GENETIC IMPLICATIONS    It is clear that even in wet years, major leaching events at the site are in-  frequent, largely because of rapid moisture depletion from the solum by the  forest vegetation. Forest canopy interception of rainfall and the moisture--  holding capacity of the organic surface horizons act as buffers against infil-  tration of minor rainfalls. Therefore, it cannot be assumed that forest cover  in itself promotes a greater degree of leaching than occurs in grasslands.  Although the stratified, texturally variable parent material would obscure  any clay illuviation, the evidence points to an insignificant role for this  process. No enrichment of fine clay exists in the B horizons. The few ar-  gillans in the Ckgj2 horizon are probably the result of shrink-swell processes,  as shown by diffuse boundaries with the adjacent matrix. Illuvial argillans  would have more abrupt contacts with the matrix. Finally, the lack of sus-  pended clay in the Ah-horizon leachates contrasts with the visible turbidity  of natural leachates from the eluvial horizon of a Gray Luvisol (Alfisol),  also in central Alberta, in which clay translocation is active (Howitt, 1981}.  The low hydraulic conductivity of the clay-rich parent material is at least  partially responsible for the hydromorphic features of the pedon. Mottling  below the Ah horizons and the extractable Fe data indicate redistribution  of that element. The pattern of dithionite-extractable Fe concentration re-  sembles that in Gleysolic rather than Chernozemic soils (Stonehouse and  St. Arnaud, 1971), that is, a greater degree of Fe removal from the A hori-  zons. Iron depletion from the Ah horizon does occur in well drained Cher-  nozemic pedons (St. Arnaud and Whiteside, 1964), but its extent at this site,  plus the degree of mottling, suggests a hydromorphic influence. This redis-  tribution may be a relict feature, as indicated by the lack of soluble Fe in  the Ah-horizon leachates. Furthermore, when a perched water table existed  at the site in 1979, in situ measurements of Eh and pH in both the Ah2 and  Ckgj2 horizons indicated oxidizing conditions. Therefore, past drainage con-  ditions at the site may have been poorer, because longer periods of satura-  tion than occur today seem to be needed for Fe reduction and mobilization.  The lack of measurable soluble Fe in the Ah leachates also discounts any cur-  rent role for phenolics and uronic acids in pedogenic mobilization of Fe, al-  though these organic substances did occur in the soil solution.    230    The presence of Mn as mangans in the C horizons suggests that it has nli-  grated farther in response to hydromorphic conditions than Fe. This is to be  expected, because the degree of reduction needed to solubilize Mn (IV) com-  pounds is much less than the required for Fe(III).  The evidence suggests that weathering processes have had only mild ef-  fects on the mineral material of this pedon. The between-horizon differences  in clay mineralogy are subtle and show no trends attributable to weathering.  This finding agrees with other studies which have found little weathering of  the clay fractions of Chernozemic soils in western Canada and North Dakota  (Dudas and Pawluk, 1969b; Redmond and Omodt, 1967, Kodama, 1979).  Some workers have suggested that "illitization" of smectite occurs in the  upper horizons of these soils (Dudas and Pawluk, 1969b; St. Arnaud and  Mortland, 1963). The significant addition of K through leaching of the forest  canopy and stemflow would certainly assist such a process. In addition, the  apparent depletion of K+ in the Ah-horizon leachates is consistent with some  type of Kfixation process, but the parent material stratification obscures  any resulting effects on the clay mineralogy.  The small amounts of extractable A1 present agree with published data for  other Chernozemic pedons (Stonehouse and St. Arnaud, 1971) and further  indicate the lack of weathering. The lack of Al in the Ah leachates reflects  the negligible solubility of alumina at near-neutral pH.  The Si concentrations in the Ah leachates were similar to those found by  McKeagne and Cline (1963) in soil extracts (0.9--15.0 mg 1-'). This finding  agrees with that of Elgawhary and Lindsay (1972) who concluded that solu-  ble Si in soils will occur at levels between those maintained by amorphous  silica (51 mg 1-1 at pH 8.0) and quartz (2.8 mg 1-1 ). Because the Si data in  this study were not obtained from solutions equilibrated with the soil, their  significance cannot be interpreted in terms of weathering processes and rates.  Biological processes have several direct and indirect effects on the  morphological and analytical characteristics of the pedon. The most obvious  is the role of mesofauna in litter breakdown and fabric genesis in the organic  and Ah horizons. This is particularly the case with the H horizon, which con-  sists mostly of fecal pellets. Although there is some faunal mixing of mineral  material in this horizon, its thickness suggests that the organic matter accu-  mulation rate exceeds the rate of mixing. The greater thickness of the F-H  and H than that of the L-F horizon may indicate rapid litter breakdown (Bal,  1970). The results of the decomposition experiments support this conclusion  and point out the more rapid rate of breakdown of litter from the major  shrub species, Cornus stolonifera.  Compared to those in F-H and H horizons, the Ah-horizon aggregates are  larger and richer in mineral material, resembling those typical of mull  (Bernier, 1975; Klinka et al., 1981). The uniformity of shape and size in  such mullgranic units suggests their origin in faunal ingestion and mixing of  organic and mineral materials {Brewer and Pawluk, 1975). Although the role  of earthworms in this process is emphasized in European studies (e.g.    231    Kubiena, 1953), these animals may not be native to the Canadian Prairies.  Other mesofauna have received little attention, with Ah formation in Cher-  nozems usually being attributed to in situ decomposition and humification  of root residues. It is not clear how the latter would produce a mullgranic  fabric. The experiment monitoring micromorphological changes suggested a  significant role for faunal activity in producing this fabric type. Perhaps car-  bohydrates leached from the tree canopy and litter layer, are also involved in  the formation of Ah-horizon aggregates; these substances are thought to be  significant in soil structure development (Lowe, 1978).  In the Ah-horizon clay fractions, organic and mineral constituents are  closely associated, particularly in the fine clays (Sanborn, 1981), a finding  similar to that of Dudas and Pawluk (1969a) for other Black Chernozemic  soils in Alberta. This organo-mineral association and the strong mullgranic  fabric must account partially for the lack of current or past clay eluviation  from the upper solum.  The apparent loss of soluble phenolic substances as the forest canopy  throughfall moved through the soil may have several causes: (1) rapid miner-  alization in the biologically active solum with high base status (Davies,  1971); (2) precipitation of insoluble complexes formed by reaction with ca-  tions; (3) absorption by inorganic colloids; and (4) condensation of aromatic  nuclei (Duchaufour, 1977). Thus, the formation of stable humic materials  in the upper solum may occur partly through biologically-controlled break-  down of litter materials and also through transformations of phenolic sub-  stances entering the soil in solution.  The infrared spectra for humic acids are of interest because Dormaar  (1967, 1973) suggested a relationship between certain spectral characteris-  tics and the vegetation history and drainage conditions of a site. Using his  criteria, the humic acid infrared spectra for this pedon do not have a clear  interpreation. For example, the slopes of the 2500--1800 cm-1 region in  the humic acids of the mineral soil could indicate either hydromorphic in-  fluences or the early stages of transformation to a Luvisol (Alfisol). Inas-  much as the pedon is only moderately well to imperfectly drained, the first  interpretation cannot be dismissed. Three other spectral bands, the intensi-  fication of which is thought to indicate a "Podzolic" character, are either  absent or weakly expressed.  Because forest vegetation has likely occupied the study site for much of  the late Holocene, this lack of "Podzolic" humic characteristics is note-  worthy. By contrast, in southwestern Alberta, Dormaar and Lutwick (1966)  found marked changes in humic acid infrared spectra of Black Chernozemic  soils on which poplar forest has invaded grassland since 1884.  If the Ah  horizon at the study site is a product of a past grassland environment, its  persistence may be related to impaired drainage conditions. For example,  Geis et al. (1970) found that for an Illinois area occupied by forest for  400--600 years, Prairie soils persisted under imperfectly drained conditions,  whereas more eluviated soils had formed at upland sites.    232    The end result of this complex of biological processes seems to suggest  that many of the important pedon properties are in equilibrium with the  existing forest ecosystem. Thus, the production of large amounts of base-  rich, rapidly decomposing litter, coupled with a significant return of K and  Ca from forest canopy leaching, serves to maintain both a high base status  and high soil organic matter content. This high level of base saturation and  neutral soil pH limit the rates of mineral weathering and appear to provide  a benign environment for mesofauna active in litter breakdown and soil  fabric modification. The moisture regime of the pedon, which is strongly  modified by the water demands of the forest vegetation, limits the number  of potential leaching events.    IMPLICATIONS FOR CANADIAN SOIL CLASSIFICATION SYSTEM    The studied pedon, on account of its inferred genesis and environmental  history, is difficult to accommodate within the genetically-biased Canadian  soil classification system. The process studies seem to indicate that many sig-  nificant pedon properties are consistent with the influence of forest cover  during the Late Holocene. Therefore, although its chemical and morpholog-  ical properties allow the pedon to be placed within the Black Chernozemic  Great Group (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978), these characteristics do  not necessarily reflect genesis in a grassland environment.  It is significant that Chernozems, as the term is used by European pedo-  logists, are more narrowly defined than in Canada. Forest soils with promi-  nent mull A horizons are identified as distinct types, such as Brown Forest  Softs and Dark Grey Forest Soils (Duchaufour, 1978; Gerasimov and Gla-  zovskaya, 1965), rather than being assumed to be relict Chernozems formed  in a past grassland environment. The Meadow Chernozem type (Gerasimov  and Glazowskaya, 1965) also has relevance because of the hydromorphic fea-  tures in this pedon. This genetic pathway has received little attention from  North American pedologists, even though some mid~ontinent soils with  mull A horizons may have evolved from Humic Gleysols. Therefore, if gene-  sis is to be emphasized in classifying pedons such as the one described in this  study, the relevance of these European concepts is considerable.    CONCLUSIONS    Although the hydromorphic features of the pedon may reflect a more im-  paired drainage regime in the past, other significant characteristics appear  consistent with present soil-forming processes. The rapid breakdown of the  base-rich tree leaf litter, along with cation leaching from the forest canopy,  serve to maintain a high soil base status. The resulting neutral reaction limits  the rate of mineral weathering, while the modification of the soil moisture  regime by the forest vegetation restricts the number of leaching events.  Structural units similar in size to those in the Ah horizons appear to be  forming currently, with a significant role inferred for the soil mesofauna.    233    Because the pedon appears to be in some degree of equilibrium with its  present forest environment, a more suitable approach to classification may  be found in European pedology. The mid-continent forest soils with mull A  horizons in Europe appear to be a more appropriate equivalent than the  Chernozems.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors thank Dr. I. Corns, Canadian Forestry Service, for describing  the study site vegetation, and Dr. C. Schweger, Department of Anthropol-  ogy, University of Alberta, for providing unpublished palynological informa-  tion. The Alberta Department of Transportation made available the original  field notebooks of the Dominion Land Survey. Financial support was pro-  vided by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada  through a Postgraduate Scholarship to P.S. and grants to S.P.    APPENDIX    PEDON DESCRIPTION    Horizon       Depth (cm)   Description    L-F            18--13    F-H        13--5    H          5--0    Ahl             0--10    Ah2        10--20    Ah3            20--29    Ah4            29--35    Dark brown (7.5YR 3]2 m) partially decomposed Populus  balsamifera leaves, with a few partially decomposed roots;  abundant medium fine and very fine random and horizontal  roots; 2--6 cm thick; abrupt, smooth boundary; pH 7.2.  Dark reddish brown (5YR 3/3 m) humified and partially  humified organic matter; loose and fluffy; abundant coarse  and medium horizontal, fine and very fine random roots;  clear, smooth boundary; 5--9 cm thick; pH 6.9.  Dark reddish brown (5YR 2/2 m) humified organic matter;  loose; abundant coarse and medium horizontal, fine and  very fine random roots; abrupt, smooth boundary; 4--6 cm  thick; pH 6.6.  Black (10YR 2/1 m) silty clay; strong granular; slightly  firm; common fine and very fine and few medium and  coarse oblique inped and exped roots; gradual, wavy bound-  ary; 8--11 cm thick; pH 6.1.  Very dark gray (10YR 311 m) silty clay; strong medium  and fine granular; slightly firm; common fine and very fine  oblique inped and exped roots; clear wavy boundary; 7--9  cm thick; pH 6.4.  Dark gray (10YR 4/1 m) to very dark gray (10YR 3/1 m)  silty clay; strong fine granular; slightly firm; few very fine  random inped and exped roots; clear wavy boundary;  7--9 cm thick; pH 6.8.  Very dark grayish brown (2.5Y 3/2 m) silty clay; strong  granular to fine subangular blocky; firm; very few fine and  very fine random inped and exped roots; abrupt, wavy  boundary; 4--7 cm thick; pH 6.7.    234  ABgj    35--42    Bmgj          42--57    Bmkgj         57--67    BCkgj      67--103    Ckgjl      103--128    Ckgj2        128+    Grayish brown (2.5Y 5/2 m) silty clay; many, fine, promi  nent (2.5Y 5/6) mottles; very weak fine platy to weak fine  granular; firm; very few fine and medium random inped  and exped roots; abrupt, broken boundary; 0--8 cm thick;  pH 6.9.  Dark grayish brown (2.5Y 4/2 m) silty clay; common fine,  distinct (2.5Y 4/4) mottles; moderate  fine subangular  blocky; very firm; very few fine and medium random inped  and exped roots; gradual wavy boundary; 15--20 cm thick;  pH 7.3.  Dark grayish brown (2.5Y 4/2 m) clay; common, fine,  distinct (2.5Y 4/4) mottles; weak subangular blocky; very  firm; very few large oblique inped and exped roots; weakly  effervescent; gradual, wavy boundary; 8--12 cm thick ; pH  7.3.  Dark grayish brown (2.5Y 4/2 m) heavy clay; many, fine,  distinct (2.5Y 4]3-4/4) mottles; massive to weak fine sub-  angular blocky; very firm; very few, medium, fine, and very  fine random and oblique roots; moderately effervescent;  gradual wavy boundary; 25--30 cm thick; pH 7.8.  Dark grayish brown (2.5Y 4/2 m) heavy clay; many, fine,  prominent (2.5Y 5/4-5/6) mottles; massive to weak sub-  angular blocky; very firm; very few, medium, fine, and very  fine random and oblique roots; moderately effervescent;  gradual wavy boundary; 25--30 cm thick; pH 7.8.  Dark grayish brown (2.5Y 4/2 m) heavy clay; many, fine,  prominent (2.5Y 5]4-5/6) mottles, massive, fragmental;  moderately effervescent; pH 7.4.    REFERENCES    Attiwill, P.M., 1968. The loss of elements from decomposing litter. Ecology, 49: 142--  145.  Bal, L., 1970. Morphological investigation in two moder-humus profiles and the role of  the soil fauna in their genesis. Geoderma, 4: 5--36.  Bernier, B., 1975. Descriptive outline of forest humus-form classification. In: Soil Res.  Inst., Ottawa, CanSIS Working Group on Soil Survey Data, Manual for Describing Soils  in the Field, pp. 4.1--4.16.  Bowser, W.E., Kjearsgaard, A,A., Peters, T.W. and Wells, R.E., 1962. Soil survey of the  Edmonton sheet (83-H). Alberta Soil Surv. Rep., 21:66 pp.  Brewer, R., 1976. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Krieger, Huntington, 482 pp.  Brewer, R. and Pawluk, S., 1975. Investigations of some soils developed in hummocks of  the Canadian Subarctic and Southern Arctic regions, I. Morphology and micromorph-  ology. Can. J. Soil Sci., 55: 301--319.  Bundy, L.G. and Brenmer, J.M., 1972. A simple titrimetric method for determination of  inorganic carbon in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 273--275.  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classification. Agric.  Can. Publ., 1646:163 pp.  Carter, D.L., Heilman, M.D, and Gonzalez, C.L., 1965. Ethylene glycol monoethyl ether  for determining surface area for silicate minerals. Soil Sci., 100: 356--360.  Clayton, J.S., Ehrlich, W.A., Cann, D.B., Day, J.H. and Marshall, I.B., 1977. Soils of  Canada, 1. Soil Report. Res. Branch Agric. Can., Ottawa, 243 pp.    235    Coldwell, B. and DeLong, W.A., 1950. Studies of the composition of deciduous forest  tree leaves before and after partial decomposition. Sci. Agric., 30: 456--466.  Cox, T.L., Harris, W.F., Ausmus, B.S. and Edwards, N.T., 1978. The role of roots in bio-  geochemical cycles in an eastern deciduous forest. Pedobiologia, 18: 264--271.  Cragg. J.B., Carter, A., Leischner, C., Peterson, E.B. and Sykes, G.N., 1977. Litter fall and  chemical cycling in an aspen (Populus tremuloides) woodland ecosystem in the Can-  adian Rockies. Pedobiologia, 17: 428--443.  Davies, R.I., 1971. Relation of polyphenols to decomposition of organic matter and to  pedogenetic processes. Soil Sci., 111: 80--85.  Dormaar, J.F., 1967. Infrared spectra of humic acids from soils formed under grass or  trees. Geoderma, 1: 37--45.  Dormaar, J.F., 1970. Seasonal patterns of water-soluble constituents from leaves of Popu-  lus x Northwest (Hort.). J. Soil Sci., 21: 105--110.  Dormaar, J.F., 1973. A diagnostic technique to differentiate between buried gleysolic and  chernozemic B horizons. Boreas, 2: 13--16.  Dormaar, J.F., 1978. Water-soluble constituents in defrost water of Black Chernozemic A  horizons during spring thaw. Can. J. Soil Sci., 58: 135--144.  Dormaar, J.F. and Lutwick, L.E., 1966. A biosequence of soils of the rough fescue  prairie--poplar transition in southwestern Alberta. Can. J. Earth Sci., 3:457--471.  Duchaufour, P., 1973. Action des cations sur les processus d'humification. Sci. Sol, 3:  151--163.  Duchaufour, P., 1976. Dynamics of organic matter in soils of temperate regions: its ac-  tion on pedogenesis. Geoderma, 15: 31--40.  Duchaufour, P., 1977. Pedologie, 1. Pedogen~se et Classification. Masson, Paris, 477 pp.  Duchaufour, P., 1978. Ecological Atlas of Soils of the World. Masson, New York, 178 pp.  Dudas, M.J. and Pawluk, S., 1969a. Naturally occurring organo-clay complexes of Orthic  Black Chernozems. Geoderma, 3: 5--17.  Dudas, M.J. and Pawluk, S., 1969b. Chernozems of the Alberta parklands. Geoderma, 3 :  19--36.  Eaton, J.S., Likens, G.E. and Bormann, F.H., 1973. Throughfall and stemflow chemistry  in a northern hardwood forest. J. Ecol., 61 : 495--508.  Elgawhary, S.M. and Lindsay, W.L., 1972. Solubility of silica in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 36: 439--442.  Feller, M., 1977. Nutrient movement through western hemlock--western red cedar eco-  systems in southwestern British Columbia. Ecology, 58 : 1269--1283.  Gels, J.W., Boggess, W.R. and Alexander, J.D., 1970. Early effects of forest vegetation  and topographic position on dark-colored, prairie-derived soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 34: 105--111.  Gerasimov, I.P. and Glazovskaya, M.A., 1965. Fundamentals of Soil Science and Soil Geo-  graphy. Isr. Program Sci. Transl., Jerusalem, 382 pp.  Gosz, J.R., Likens, G.E. and Bormann, F.H., 1973. Nutrient release from decomposing  leaf and branch litter in the Hubbard Brook Forest, New Hampshire. Ecol. Monogr.,  43: 173--191.  Harris, W.F., Kinerson, R.S. and Edwards, N.T., 1977. Comparison of below-ground bio-  mass of natural deciduous forests and loblolly pine plantations. Pedobiologia, 17:  369--381.  Howitt, R.W., 1981. Dynamics of a Gray Luvisol. M.Sc. thesis, Univ. Alberta, Edmonton.  I.A.E.A.--Food Agric. Org., U.N., 1976. Tech. Rep. Ser., 171: Tracer manual on crops  and soils, 277 pp.  Johnson, D.W., 1975. Processes of Elemental Transfer in Some Tropical, Temperate,  Alpine, and Northern Forest Soils: Factors Influencing the Availability of Major  Leaching Agents. Ph.D. thesis, Univ. Washington, Seattle, 169 pp.  Klinka, K., Green, R.N, Trowbridge, R.L. and Lowe, L.E., 1981. Taxonomic classifica-  tion of humus forms in ecosystems of British Columbia: first approximation. B.C.  Min. For. Land Manage. Rep. 8 : 54 pp.    236    Kodama, H., 1969. Clay minerals in Canadian soils: their origin, distribution, and altera-  tion. Can. J. Soil Sci., 59: 37--58.  Kubiena, W.L., 1953. The Soils of Europe. Murby, London, 317 pp.  Lousier, J.D. and Parkinson, D., 1976. Litter decomposition in a cool temperate decidu-  ous forest. Can. J. Bot., 54: 419--436.  Lousier, J.D. and Parkinson, D., 1978. Chemical element dynamics in decomposing leaf  litter. Can. J. Bot., 56: 2795--2812.  Lowe, L.E.., 1978. Carbohydrates in soil. In: M. Schnitzer and S.U. Khan (Editors), Soil  Organic Matter. Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 65--93.  Lynch, D.L., Hearns, E.E. and Cotnoir, L.J., 1957. The determination of polyuronides in  soils with carbazole. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 21: 160--162.  MacLean, D.A. and Wein, R.W., 1978. Weight loss and nutrient changes in decomposing  litter and forest floor material in New Brunswick forest stands. Can. J. Bot., 56:  2730--2749.  Mahendruppa, M.S., 1974. Chemical composition of stemflow of some eastern Canadian  hardwood species. Can. J. For. Res., 4: 1--7.  McColl, J.G., 1973. A model of ion transport during moisture flow from a Douglas fir  forest floor. Ecology, 54: 181--187.  McKeague, J.A. (Editor), 1978. Manual of Soil Sampling and Methods of Analysis. Can.  Soil Surv. Comm.--Can. Soc. Soil Sci. Ottawa, 2nd ed., 212 pp.  McKeague, J.A. and Cline, M.G., 1963. Silica in soil solutions. I. The form and concentra-  tion of dissolved silica in aqueous extracts of some soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 43: 70--82.  Mebius, L.J., 1960. A rapid method for the determination of organic carbon in soil. Anal.  Chim. Acta, 22: 120--124.  Mecklenburg, R.A., Tukey, H,B, and Morgan, J.V., 1966. A mechanism for the leaching  of calcium from foliage. Plant Physiol., 41: 610---613.  Nielson, G.A. and Hole, F.D., 1964. Earthworms and the development of coprogenous  A1 horizons in forest soils of Wisconsin. Soil Sci. Soc, Am. Proc., 28: 426--430.  Norgren, J.A., 1973. Distribution, Form and Significance of Plant Opal in Oregon Soils.  Ph.D. thesis, Oregon State Univ., Corvallis, 165 pp.  Oades, J.M., 1967. Carbohydrates in some Australian soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 5: 103--115.  Parker, R., 1978. The Influence of Atmospheric Sulphur Emissions on Nutrient Return  via Throughfall and Stemflow in Three Boreal Forest Ecosystems. M.Sc. thesis, Univ.  Alberta, Edmonton, 198 pp.  Parkinson, J.A. and Allen, S.E., 1975. A wet oxidation procedure suitable for the deter-  mination of nitrogen and mineral nutrients in biological material. Commun. Soil Sci.  Plant Anal., 6 : 1--11.  Pawluk, S., 1967. Soil analysis by atomic absorption spectrophotometry. At. Absorpt.  Newsl., 6 : 52--56.  Pettapiece, W.W., 1969. The forest--grassland transition. In: S. Pawluk (Editor), Pedology  and Quaternary Research. Univ. Alberta, Edmonton, pp. 103--113.  Redmond, C.E. and Omodt, H.W., 1967. Some till-derived Chernozem soils of eastern  North Dakota, I. Morphology, genesis, and classification, II. Mineralogy, micromorph-  ology, and development. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31: 89--107.  Remezov, N.P. and Pogrebnyak, P.S., 1969. Forest Soil Science. Israel Program Sci.  Transl., Jerusalem, 251 pp.  Riekerk, H., 1971. The mobility of phosphorus, potassium, and calcium in a forest soil.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 350--356.  Rodin, L.E. and Bazilevich, N.I., 1967. Production and Mineral Cycling in Terrestrial  Vegetation. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh, 288 pp.  Sanborn, P., 1981. Dynamics of a Chernozemic Soil System. M.Sc. thesis, Univ. Alberta,  Edmonton, 167 pp.  St. Arnaud, R.J. and Mortland, M.M., 1963. Characteristics of the clay fractions in a  Chernozemic to Podzolic sequence of soil profiles in Saskatchewan. Can. J. Soil Sci.,  43 : 336--349.    237    St. Arnaud, R.J. and Whiteside, E.P., 1964. Morphology and genesis of a Chernozemic to  Podzolic sequence of soil profiles in Saskatchewan. Can. J. Soil Sci., 44: 88---99.  St. Onge, D., 1972. Sequence of glacial lakes in north central Alberta. Geol. Surv. Can.  Bull., 213, 14 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy. Soil Conserv. Serv., U.S. Dept. Agric. Agricul-  ture Handbook, 436:754 pp.  Stonehouse, H.B. and St. Arnaud, R.J., 1971. Distribution of iron, clay and extractable  iron and aluminum in some Saskatchewan soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 51 : 283--292.  Summers, P.W. and Hitchon, B., 1973. Source and budget of sulfate in precipitation from  central Alberta, Canada. J. Air Pollut. Control Assoc., 23: 194--199.  Swain, T. and Hillis, W.E., 1959. The phenolic constituents of Prunus domestica, I. The  quantitative analysis of phenolic constituents. J. Sci. Food Agric., 10: 63--68.  Theisen, A.A. and Harward, M.E., 1962. A paste method for preparation of slides for  clay-mineral identification by X-ray diffraction. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 25: 90--91.  Thomas, W.A., 1969. Accumulation and cycling of calcium by dogwood trees. Ecol.  Monogr., 39: 101--120.  Van Cleve, K. and Noonan, L.L., 1975. Litter fall and nutrient cycling in the forest floor  of birch and aspen stands in interior Alaska. Can. J. For. Res., 5: 626--639.  Vance, R.E., 1979. Late Holocene Paleoecology of the Aspen Parkland Region of Wes-  tern Canada. M.A. thesis, Univ. Alberta, Edmonton, 113 pp.  Vedy, J.C. and Jacquin, F., 1972. Formation 'in situ' d'horizons humif~res sur 'materiau'  acide en presence de liti~res am61iorantes ou acidifiantes. Sci. Sol., 2:102--113.  Weaver, R.M., Syers, J.K. and Jackson, M.L., 1968. Determination of silica in citrate-  bicarbonate-dithionite extracts of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32:'497--501.  Westgate, J.A., 1969. The Quaternary geology of the Edmonton area. In: S. Pawluk  (Editor), Pedology and Quaternary Research. Univ. Alberta, Edmonton, pp. 129--151.  Zoltai, S.C., 1975. Southern limit of coniferous trees on the Canadian Prairies. Environ.  Can., Can. For. Serv., North. For. Res. Cent., Edmonton, Inf. Rep., NOR-X-128, 12  PP.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   AbstractSoil-forming processes in a Gleyed Black Chernozemic (Aquic Cryoboroll) pedon in central Alberta, Canada, were investigated. Vegetation similar to the present Boreal Transition Forest seems to have occupied the region during the Late Holocene. The influence of this forest ecosystem appears compatible with observed pedon properties, notably a well-structured, base-saturated mull A horizon. Rapid soil moisture depletion during the growing season limits the potential for leaching. Readily decomposed, calciumrich litter, particularly from understorey shrubs, and cation leaching from the forest canopy maintain a high base status and mild weathering environment. Faunal and other processes promote rapid formation of characteristic A horizon fabrics. The suitability of some current Canadian soil taxonomic concepts is discussed. 