 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 265--276                                                     265  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Adepoju, A. Y.; Pratt, P. F.; and Mattigod, S.V. Availability and extractability of phosphorus from soils  having high residual phosphorus: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 583-588,  illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1982.  AI-Durrah, M. M.; and Bradford, J. M.  Parameters for describing soil detachment due to single  waterdrop impact: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 836-840, illus. (incl. 4  tables), 1982.  Alford, John J. San Vicente Arroyo: Annals of the Association of American Geographers, Vol. 72, No.  3, p. 398-403, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1982.  Ashworth, Allan C.; and Cvaneara, Alan M. Paleoecotogy of the southern part of the Lake Agassiz Basin  [abstr.]:  in GAC-MAC; program with abstracts; joint annual meeting (Brisbin, W. C., chairperson),  Program with Abstracts - Geological Association of Canada, Vol. 7, p. 37, 1982.  Atkin, Steven Allen. Magmatic history, alteration, and mineralization of the Clayton Peak Stock, Utah:  282 p., Doctoral, 1982, Johns Hopkins Univ., Baltimore, MD. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Axelrod, Daniel I. Vegetation and climate during middle Ridge Basin deposition: in Geologic history  of Ridge Basin, southern California (Crowell, John C., editor; eta/.), p. 247-252, illus. (incl. 1 table),  SEPM, Pac. Sec., Los Angeles, CA, United States, 1982.  Bahorieh, Michael S.; Coruh, Cahit; Robinson, Edwin S.; et al. Static corrections on the southeastern  Piedmont of the United States: Geophysics, Vol. 47, No. 11, p. 1540-1549, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch  map), 1982.  Barcelona, Michael J.; and Wang, Woodrow. Usefulness of sediment oxygen demand as a tool for  impoundment management: W.R.C. Research Report, Vol. 169, 35 p., illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Barnes, James R. Soil survey of Starke County, Indiana:  122 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour., Soil Water  Conserv. Comm.).  Barnhisel, R. I.; Powell, J. L.; Akin, G. W.; et al. Characteristics and reclamation of "acid sulfate" mine  spoils:  in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA  Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 225-234, 5 tables, 1982.  Bartlett, Richard J. Reactive aluminum in the Vermont soil test: Communications in Soil Science and  Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 7, p. 497-506, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Berkheiser, V. E.; and Monsees, M. B. Dispersion of clays on graphite supports for X-ray microprobe  analysis: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 663-666, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Boast, C. W.; and Robertson, T.M. A "micro-lysimeter" method for determining evaporation from bare  soil; description and laboratory evaluation: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p.  689-696, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Bowman, B.T. Conversion of Freundlich adsorption K values to the mole fraction format and the use  of Sy values to express relative adsorption of pesticides: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  46, No. 4, p. 740-743, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Boyle, R. W. Geochemical methods for the discovery of blind mineral deposits; Part 2: CIM Bulletin  (1974), Vol. 75, No. 845, p. 113-132, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.    2,q6    Buckner, Russell L.  Soil survey of Butler County, Iowa:  209 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables: soils map~,  1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Oep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, Unitcd  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. stn. coop. Ext. serv.; Iowa Stale 17ni~  Dep. Soil Conserv.L  Callebaut, F.; Gabriels, D.; Minjauw, W.; et aL Redox potential, oxygen diffusion rate. and soil gas  composition in relation to water table level in two soils: Soil Science, Vol. 134, No. 3, p. i4~)-156, illus..  1982.  Campbell, LuDene B.; and Lacey, Celestine A. Soil survey of Rich County, Utah: 273 p., illus. (in~l.  17 tables; soils maps 1:24,000: colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv Serv,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Utah Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Carson, C. D.; Fanning, D. S.; and Dixon, J.B. Alfisols and Uttisols with acid sulfate weathering features  in Texas: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA  Special Publication, Vol. 10, p 127-146, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Cuss, A.; and Sumner, M. E. Soil pore structural stability and irrigation water quality; 1, Empirical  sodium stability model: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 503-506, illus., 1982.  Cass, A.; and Sumner, M.E. Soil pore structural stability and irrigation water quality; If, Sodium stability  data: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 50%512, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Cass, A.; and Sumner, M. E. Soil pore structural stability and irrigation water quality; Ill, Evaluation  of soil stability and crop yield in relation to salinity and sodicity: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 513-517, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Cavallaro, Nancy. Sorption and fixation ofCu, Zn and phosphate by soil clays as influenced by the oxide  fraction:  153 p., Doctoral, 1982, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Cheerers, Craig Wallace. Weathering, genesis and classification of selected basaltic soils of the San  Francisco volcanic field, northern Arizona: 254 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of California, Riverside, CA  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Cho, C.M. Oxygen consumption and denitrification kinetics in soils: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 756-762, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Christiansen, Earl A. Saskatchewan River delta of Lake Agassiz near Nipawin, Saskatchewan [abstr.]:  in GAC-MAC; program with abstracts; joint annual meeting (Brisbin, W. C., chairperson), Program with  Abstracts - Geological Association of Canada, Vol. 7, p. 43, 1982.  Clothier, B. E.; and Scotter, D.R. Constant-flux infiltration from a hemispherical cavity: Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 696-700, illus., 1982.  Cole, Kenneth. Late Quaternary zonation of vegetation in the eastern Grand Canyon: Science, Vol.  217, No. 4565, p. 1142-1145, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Collins, M. E.; and Fenton, T. E. Characteristics of the Colo soil series as mapped in the North Central  region: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 599-607, illus. (incl. 11 tables, sketch  map), 1982.  Comtois, Paul.  Histoire holocene du climat et de la vegetation a Lanoraie (Quebec) [History of  Holocene climate and vegetation at Lanoraie, Quebec]: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal  Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, Vol. 19, No. 10, p. 1938-1952 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 17 anal.,  2 tables, charts, sketch maps), 1982.  Constantz, Jim. Temperature dependence of unsaturated hydraulic conductivity of two soils:  Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 466-470, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  Corwin, D. L.; and Rhoades, J. D. An improved technique for determining soil electrical conductivity-  depth relations from above-ground electromagnetic measurements: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 517-520, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Crabb, James A. Soil survey of Weld County, Colorado; northern part: 145 p., illus. (incl. 11 tables;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  DC, United States, 1982. (Pubt. in coop. with Colt). Agric. Exp. Stn.).  D~urmody, R. G.; and Foss, J.E. Soil-landscape relationships in the Piedmont of Maryland: Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 589-592, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), I982.    267    David, M. B.; Mitchell, M. J.; and Nakas, J. P. Organic and inorganic sulfur constituents of a forest  soil and their relationship to microbial activity: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol 46, No.  4, p. 847-852, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982,  David, Peter P. Late Pleistocene and Holocene climatic changes based on the eolian stratigraphic record  of the Canadian prairies; an update [abstr.]: in GAC-MAC; program with abstracts; joint annual meeting  (Brisbin, W. C., chairperson), Program with Abstracts - Geological Association of Canada, Vol. 7, p 44.  1982.  Davis, Owen Kent. Vegetation migration in southern Idaho during the late-Quaternary and Holocene:  262 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN. available frorn: Univ. Microfilms.  Dejou, J.; De Kimpe, C. R.; and Lasallc, P.  Evolution geochimique superficielle naissante des  anorthosites; cas du profil de Chateau-Richer (Quebec), Canada [Geochemical evolution of initial stages  of superficial weathering of anorthosites; case of the Chateau-Richer profile, Quebec]: Canadian Journal  of Earth Sciences = Journal Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, Vol. 19, No. 8, p. 1697-1706 (incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. 4 anal., 2 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Delcourt, Hazel R.; Deleourt, Paul A.; and Spiker, Elliott. Holocene paleohydrologic changes in the  southern Ridge and Valley Province of Alabama [abstr.]:  in Northeastern and Southeastern combined  section meetings; 17th annual meeting of the Northeastern Section and the 31st annual meeting of the  Southeastern Section (Wright, T. O., chairperson: et al.), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society  of America, Vol. 14, No. 1-2, p. 14, 1982.  Delcourt, Paul A.; and Deleourt, Hazel R.  Modern pollen/vegetation mapping and calibration:  quantitative basis for Quaternary paleovegetational reconstructions in southeastern North America  [abstr.]:  in Northeastern and Southeastern combined section meetings; 17th annual meeting of the  Northeastern Section and the 31st annual meeting of the Southeastern Section (Wright, T. O.,  chairperson; et al.), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, Vol. 14, No. 1-2, p. 14,  1982.  Dever, L.; Hillaire-Marcel, C.; Belhadfa, A.; et al. Geochimie isotopique de palses recentes du sud-est  de la Baie d'Hudson [Isotopic geochemistry of Recent palsas in southeastern Hudson Bay] [abstr.]:  in  GAC-MAC; program with abstracts; joint annual meeting (Brisbin, W. C., chairperson), Program with  Abstracts - Geological Association of Canada, Vol. 7, p. 45, 1982.  Dixon, J. B.; Hossner, L. R.; Senkayi, A. L.; et al. Mineralogical properties of lignite overburden as they  relate to mine spoil reclamation:  in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J.  A., editor; et al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 169-191, 8 tables, 1982.  Donaldson, Norman C.; DeFraneeseo, Joseph T.; and Barton, Don W. Soil survey of Stevens County,  Washington: 459 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. For. Serv.;  Bur. Indian Aft.; Wash. State Dep. Nat. Resour.; Wash. State Univ,, Agric. Res. Cent.).  Doner, H. E.; Pukite, A.; and Yang, E. Mobility through soils of certain heavy metals in geothermal  brine water: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 389-394, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Doner, H. E.; Traina, S. J.; and Pukite, A.  Interaction of nickel, copper, and cadmium with soil  manganese in saline solutions: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 369-377, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Drake, E. H.; and Motto, H.L. An analysis of the effect of clay and organic matter content on the cation  exchange capacity of New Jersey soils: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No, 5, p. 281-288, 7 tables, 1982.  EI-Sharkawi, M. A.; and AI-Awadi, S.A. Alteration products of glauconite in Burgan oil field, Kuwait:  Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, Vol. 52, No. 3, p. 999-1002, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1982.  Elprinee, A. M.; AI-Shammary, M. A.; and Magboul, A. M.  Kinetics of thermal dehydration of  gypsiferous soils:  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 530-535, illus. (incl. 2  tables), 1982.  Ervin, Christine A.; and Ervin, David E.  Factors affecting the use of soil conservation practices;  hypotheses, evidence, and policy implications: Land Economics, Vol. 58, No. 3, p. 277-292, 2 tables,  1982.  Evangelou, V. P.; Phillips, R. E.; and Shepard, J. S. Salt generation in pyritic coal spoils and its effect  on saturated hydraulic conductivity: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 457-  460, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.    268    Evans, L.J. Paleosols: Geoscience Canada, Vol. 9, No. 3, p. 155-160, sect., t982.  Everett, K. R.; and Brown, J. Some recent trends in the physical and chemical characterization and  mapping of Tundra soils, Arctic slope of Alaska: Soil Science, Vok 133. No. 5, p. 264-280, illus. (inck  2 tables, sects., sketch map), 1982  Eyles, N.; Sasseville, D. R.; Slatt, R. M.; et aL Geochemical denudation rates and solute transport  mechanisms in a maritime temperate glacier basin:  Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences ~ Journal  Canadien des Sciences de la Terre. Vol. 1 O, No. 8, p. 1570-1581 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 35 anal..  8 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Flewelling, Lawreee R.; and Lisante, Robert H. Soil survey of York County, Maine: 143 p., illus. (inck  19 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Maine Agric. Exp. Stn.; Maine Soil Water  Conserv. Comm.).  Foster, G.R. Modeling the erosion process: in Hydrologic modeling of small watersheds (Haan, C. T.,  editor; et al.), Vol. 5, p, 297-380, illus. (incl. 18 tables), Am. Soc. Agric. Eng., St. Joseph, MI, United  States, 1982.  Frolking, Tod A. The genesis and distribution of upland red clays in Wisconsin's Driftless Area:  in  Quaternary history of the Driftless Area, with special papers (Knox, J. C, chairperson), Field Trip Guide  Book (Madison), Vol. 5, p. 88-97, illus. (incl. 4 anal., 2 tables, sects., sketch maps), 1982.  Gillette, Dale A.; Adams, John; Muhs, Daniel; et al. Threshold friction velocities and rupture moduli  for crusted desert soils for the input of soil particles into the air: JGR. Journal of Geophysical Research.  C. Oceans and Atmospheres, Vol. 87, No. 11, p. 9003-9015, illus. (incl. 10 tables), 1982.  Goldhaber, M. B.; and Kaplan, I. R. Controls and consequences of sulfate reduction in Recent marine  sediments: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et aL), SSSA  Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 19-36, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Grant, C. L.; and Seitz, W. R. The potential of fluorescence polarization for measuring sorption  isotherms of organics: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 5, p, 289-294, 1982.  Grube, W. E., Jr.; Smith, R. M.; and Ammons, J. T. Mineralogical alterations that affect pedogenesis  in minesoils from bituminous coal overburdens: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium  (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 209-223, illus. (incl. strat, col.), 1982.  Gupta, R. K.; Chhabra, R.; and Abrol, I. P. Fluorine adsorption behavior in alkali soils; relative roles  of pH and sodicity: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 364-368, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Haekenmueller, J.; Marvin, J.; and Banerjee, S. K. Soil profiles from Minnesota; a magnetic study  [abstr.]: in American Geophysical Union; 7th annual Midwest meeting (Murthy, V. Rama, convener),  Eos, Transactions, American Geophysical Union, Vol. 63, No. 33, p. 615, 1982.  Hadas, A.; and Frenkel, H. Infiltration as affected by long-term use of sodic-saline water for irrigation:  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 524-530, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  Haines, B. L.; Waide, J. B.; and Todd, R.L. Soil solution nutrient concentrations sampled with tension  and zero-tension lysimeters; report of discrepancies: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46,  No. 3, p. 658-661, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Hamilton, David Bennett. Plant succession and the influence of disturbance in the Okefenokee Swamp,  Georgia: 277 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Georgia, Athens, GA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Hammermeister, D. P.; Kling, G. F.; and Vomoeil, J. A. Perched water tables on hillsides in western  Oregon; I, Some factors affecting their development and longevity: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 811-818, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Hammermeister, D. P.; Kling, G. F.; and Vomoeil, J. A. Perched water tables on hillsides in western  Oregon; II, Preferential downslope movement of water and anions: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 819-826, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Harris, W. G.; Zelazny, L. W.; Parker, J. C.; et al. Mineralogy of a chronosequence formed in New  River alluvium [abstr.]:  in Northeastern and Southeastern combined section meetings; 17th annual  meeting of the Northeastern Section and the 31st annual meeting of the Southeastern Section (Wright,  T. O., chairperson; et al.), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, VoL 14, No. 1-2,  p. 23, 1982.    269    Hayes, Miles O.; and Domeraeki, Daniel D. Role of climate and sediment availability in the evolution  of back barrier environments [abstr.]:  in Northeastern and Southeastern combined section meetings;  17th annual meeting of the Northeastern Section and the 31st annual meeting of the Southeastern Section  (Wright, T. O., chairperson; et al.), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, Vol. 14,  No. 1-2, p. 24, 1982.  Haynes, C. Vance, Jr.  Great Sand Sea and Selima sand sheet, eastern Sahara; geochronology of  desertification: Science, Vol. 217, No. 4560, p. 629-633, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1982.  Heehinger, E.; Raffy, M.; and Becker, F. Comparison between the accuracies of a new discretization  method and an improved Fourier method to evaluate heat transfers between soil and atmosphere: JGR.  Journal of Geophysical Research. C. Oceans and Atmospheres, Vol. 87, No. 9, p. 7325-7339, illus. (incl.  9 tables), 1982.  Hill, D.E. Soils in tidal marshes of the Northeast: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 5, p. 298-304, illus. (incl.  1 table), 1982.  Hill, R. L.; and King, L.D. A permeameter which eliminates boundary flow errors in saturated hydraulic  conductivity measurements: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 877-880, illus..  1982.  Hinesly, T. D.; Redborg, K. E.; Ziegler, E. L.; et al. Effect of soil cation exchange capacity on the uptake  of cadmium by corn: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 490-497, illus. (incl.  6 tables), 1982.  Ho, D. Y. F.; and Fredlund, D. G. A multistage triaxial test for unsaturated soils: ASTM Geotechnical  Testing Journal, Vol. 5, No. 1-2, p. 18-25, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Hoek, Evert. Analysis of slope stability in very heavily jointed or weathered rock masses:  in Third  international conference on stability in surface mining (Brawner, C. O., editor), p" 375-406, illus. (incl.  2 tables), Am. Inst. Min. Metall. and Pet. Eng., New York, NY, United States, 1982.  Hofmann, G.W. The environmental impact of mining in Australia: Queensland Government Mining  Journal, Vol. 83, No. 968, p. 276-283, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Hole, Francis D. Soils of Crawford, Vernon, and western Richland counties, Wisconsin: in Quaternary  history of the Driftless Area, with special papers (Knox, J. C., chairperson), Field Trip Guide Book  (Madison), Vol. 5, p. 98-102, 21 anal., 1 table, sketch maps, 1982.  Horton, R.; Wierenga, P. J.; and Nielsen, D.R. A rapid technique for obtaining uniform water content  distributions in unsaturated soil columns: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 397-399, 3 tables, 1982.  Hsu, P.H. Crystallization of variscite at room temperature: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 5, p. 305-313,  illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Huggins, L. F.; and Burney, J.R. Surface runoff, storage and routing: in Hydrologic modeling of small  watersheds (Haan, C. T., editor; et al.), Vol. 5, p. 169-225, illus. (incl. 2 tables), Am. Soc. Agric. Eng.,  St. Joseph, MI, United States, 1982.  Hunter, R. B.; Romney, E. M.; and Wallace, A. Nitrate distribution in Mojave Desert soils:  Soil  Science, Vol. 134, No. 1, p. 22-30, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Iniguez, J.; and Val, R. M. Variable charge characteristic of Andosols from Navarre, Spain:  Soil  Science, Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 390-396, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Intraweeh, A.; Stone, L. R.; Ellis, R., Jr.; et al. Influence of fertilizer nigrogen source on soil physical  and chemical properties: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 832-836, illus. (incl.  3 tables), 1982.  Inyang, Aniefiok David. Environmental transport of heavy metals from soil amended with undigested  sludge:  165 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Oklahoma, Norman, OK. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Ivarson, K. C,; Ross, G. J.; and Miles, N. M. Microbiological transformations of iron and sulfur and  their applications to acid sulfate soils and tidal marshes:  in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a  symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 57-75, 1 table, 1982.  Jackson, Thomas J.; Sehmugge, Thomas J.; and Wang, James R. Passive microwave sensing of soil  moisture under vegetation canopies: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 4, p. 1137-1142, illus. (incl.  3 tables), 1982.    270    Jantz, Donald R.; Wehmueller, William A.; and Owens, Homer D. Soil survey of Russell County.  Kansas: 103 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U S. Dep. Agric.  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC. United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Kansas Agric. Exp. Strl~  Jensen, Earnest L. Soil survey of DeKalb County, Indiana:  109 p., 20 tables, soils maps 1:15,84(L  colored soils map 1:126,720, U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States.  1982. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour. Soil Water Conser~  Comm.).  Johnston, Carol Arlene. Effects of a seasonally flooded freshwater wetland on water quality from an  agricultural watershed: 146 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Wisconsin, Madison, WI. available from: Umv.  Microfilms.  Karrow, P. F.; Hebda, R. J.; Presant, E. W.; et al. Late Quaternary inter-till Paleosol and biota at  Guelph, Ontario: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences - Journal Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, Vol.  19, No. 9, p. 1857-1872 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 7 tables, charts, sketch maps), 1982.  Keren, R.; and O'Connor, G.A. Effect of exchangeable ions and ionic strength on boron adsorption by  montmorillonite and illite: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 30, No. 5, p. 341-346 (incl. Russian, German,  French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Keren, R.; and O'Connor, G.A. Gypsum dissolution and sodic soil reclamation as affected by water flow  velocity: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 726-732, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Kies, Bouziane. Solute transport in unsaturated field soil and in groundwater: 369 p., Doctoral, 1982,  New Mexico State Univ., Las Cruces, NM. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  King, R. H.; Kingston, M. S.; and Barnett, R. L. A numerical approach toward the classification of  magnetites from tephra in southern Alberta: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal Canadien  des Sciences de la Terre, Vol. 19, No. 10, p, 2012-2019 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 anal., 6 tables),  1982.  Kireher, Harry B.; and Wallace, Donald L. Our natural resources, 5th edition: 425 p., illus., Interstate  Printers &amp; Publ., Danville, IL, United States, 1982.  Kittriek, J. A.; Fanning, D. S.; Hossner, L R. (editors); et al. Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of  a symposium: Aug. 5-10, 1979, United States. SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, 234 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps), 1982.  Kolbe, Edward; Corell, R. W.; and Nielsen, J. P. A probe to measure friction coefficient of cohesionless  soils: ASTM Geotechnical Testing Journal, Vol. 5, No. 1-2, p. 42-46, illus., 1982.  Kopas, Frank A. Soil survey of Schuylkill County, Pennsylvania: 134 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Argic., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep Environ. Resour., State Conserv  Comm.).  Knehl, Ronald J. Soil survey of Clayton County, Iowa: 238 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps 1:15,840;  colored soils map 1:253,440), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States,  1982. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Stn.; Iowa State Univ., Coop. Ext. Serw; Iowa, Dep.  Soil Conserv.).  Kutnink, Paul R.; Gier, Donald A.; l-labermma, Roger L.; et al. Soil survey of Nemaha County, Kansas:  89 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Kansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Laird, David; mad ltarward, M.E. Relationship of the nature of suspended clay minerals to hydrologic  conditions: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 433-436, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1982.  Lange, Robert T.; and Nieolson, Kym P. Vegetation apparently recording former extensions of a  Paleosol: Transactions of the Royal Society of South Australia, Vol. 106, No. 1-2, p. 77-78, sketch maps,  1982.  Laryea, K. B.; Elriek, D. E.; mad Robin, M. d.L. Hydrodynamic dispersion involving cationic adsorption  during unsaturated, transient water flow in soil: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No.  4, p. 667-671, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Lereb, N. K.; Hale, W. F.; and Lem~ter, D. D. Soil survey of Hamilton County, Ohio: 219 p., illus.  (incl. 19 tables; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Div. Lands Soil;  Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).    271    Levesque, M. P.; and Dinel, H. Some morphological and chemical aspects of peats applied to the  characterization of Histosols: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 5, p. 324-332, 6 tables, 1982.  Levy, Rachel; Whittig, L. D.; and Tanji, K.K. Ionic activity products and crystal forms of calcium and  magnesium carbonates precipitated from calcium-magnesium bentonites:  Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 497-502, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1982.  Lewis, David T.; and Brown, Laurence E. Clay in loess and clay content of loessial soils in southeastern  Nebraska: Transactions of the Nebraska Academy of Sciences and Affiliated Societies, Vol. 10, p. 43-  47, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1982.  Lindau, C. W.; and Hossner, L. R.  Sediment fractionation of Cu, Ni, Zn, Cr, Mn, and Fe in one  experimental and three natural marshes: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 540-545,  3 tables, sketch map, 1982.  Lindgren, R.J. Determination of irrigation pumpage for an area in southwestern Kansas [abstr.]:  in  American Geophysical Union; 7th annual Midwest meeting (Murthy, V. Rama, convener), Eos,  Transactions, American Geophysical Union, Vol. 63, No. 33, p. 614, 1982.  Lopez-Hernandez, D.; and Burnham, C.P. Phosphate retention in some tropical soils in relation to soil  taxonomic classes: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 13, No. 7, p. 573-583, 20  anal., 4 tables, 1982.  Low, Alison J.; Douglas, Lowell A.; and Platt, David W. Soil-pore orientation and faults: Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 789-792, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Marston, Richard A.  The geomorphic significance of log steps in forest streams:  Annals of the  Association of American Geographers, Vol. 72, No. 1, p. 99-108, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1982.  McCarthy, Kevin P.; Been, Josh; Reimer, G. M.; et al. Helium and ground temperature surveys at  Steamboat Springs, Colorado:  in Geothermal Direct Heat Program; roundup technical conference  proceedings; Volume I; papers presented; State Coupled Resource Assessment Program (Ruscetta, Carl  A., editor), p. 64-75, 1 table, sketch maps, 1982. (Rep. No. DOE/ID/12079-71) (Rep. No. ESL-98)  available from: Univ. Utah Res. Inst., Earth Sci. Lab., Salt Lake City, UT, United States.  MeCullough, M. Bruce; Anderson, David L.; Hawn, William S.; et al. Soil survey of Custer County area,  Colorado:  135 p., illus. (incl. 15 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:90,080), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Colo. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  McDowell, Patricia F. Soil development in late Wisconsinan and Holocene valley deposits, Brush Creek  valley, Wisconsin:  in Quaternary history of the Driftless Area, with special papers (Knox, J. C.,  chairperson), Field Trip Guide Book (Madison), Vol. 5, p. 136-154, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sect.), 1982.  MeKeague, J. A.; and Guertin, R.K. Fabrics of some Canadian soils in relation to particle size and other  factors: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 87-102, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1982.  Miekelson, David M.; Knox, J. C.; and Clayton, Lee. Glaciation of the Driftless Area; an evaluation  of the evidence:  in Quaternary history of the Driftless Area, with special papers (Knox, J. C.,  chairperson), Field Trip Guide Book (Madison), Vol. 5, p. 155-169, sect., sketch maps, 1982.  Miller, G. A. Depletion of lowa soils [abstr.]:  in Iowa natural resources; issues in the 80's; abstracts  of a symposium at the 1982 annual Academy meeting (Anonymous), The Proceedings of the Iowa  Academy of Science, Vol. 89, No. 3, p. 121, 1982.  Morrison, Robert D. A modified vacuum-pressure lysimeter for soil water sampling: Soil Science, Vol.  134, No. 3, p. 206-210, illus., 1982.  Munro, D, S. On determining volumetric soil moisture variations in peat by the gravimetric method:  Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 103-110, illus, (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Murray, R. S.; and Quirk, J. P. The physical swelling of clays in solvents:  Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 865-868, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Murtha, G. G.  Soils and land use on the southern section of the Townsville coastal plain, North  Queensland: Soils and Land Use Series, VoL 59, 78 p., illus. (incl. 5 tables; colored soils map 1:100,000),  1982.  Nadler, Arie. Estimating the soil water dependence of the electrical conductivity soil solution/electrical  conductivity bulk soil ratio: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 722-726, illus.  (incl. 1 table), 1982.    272    Neitseh, Conrad L. Soil survey of Jasper and Newton counties, Texas: 198 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables.  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington.  DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Nettleton, W. D.; Parsons, R. B.; Ness, A. 04 et al. Spodosols along the Southwest Oregon coast: Soii  Science Society of America Journal. Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 593-598, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Niehols, Harvey. Review of the late Quaternary history of vegetation and climate in the mountains of  Colorado: in Ecological studies in the Colorado alpine (Halfpenny, James C., editor), Occasional Paper  - Colorado, University, Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research, Vol. 37, p. 27-33, illus. (incl. sketch  maps), 1982.  Nkedi.Kizza, P.; Rap, P. S. C.; Jessup, R. E.; et al. Ion exchange and diffusive mass transfer during  miscible displacement through an aggregated oxisol: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46.  No. 3, p. 471-476, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Nordstrom, Darrell Kirk. Aqueous pyrite oxidation and the consequent formation of secondary iron  minerals: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA  Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 37-56, illus., 1982.  Norvell, W. A.; and Lindsay, W. L. Estimation of the concentration of Fe3+ and the (Fe3+) (OH-)3  ion product from equilibria EDTA in soil: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p  710-715, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Odin, Gilles S.; and Rex, D. C. Potassium-argon dating of washed, leached, weathered and reworked  glauconies:  in Numerical dating in stratigraphy (Odin, Gilles Serge, editor), p. 363-385 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 8 tables, geol. sketch map), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, United Kingdom, 1982.  (A Wiley-lnterscience publ.).  Oliver, George Rick. Effects of tillage and soil properties on infiltration in a Histosol: 127 p., Doctoral,  1982, Ohio State Univ., Columbus, OH. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Olson, Robert Kenneth.  Factors controlling uranium distribution in Upper Devonian-Lower  Mississippian black shales of Oklahoma and Arkansas: 224 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Tulsa, Tulsa,  OK. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Pan Shu-Zheng; Liu Zhi-Guang; and Yu Tian-Ren. Chemical equilibria of sulfides in submerged soils  as studied with a hydrogen sulfide sensor: Soil Science, Vol. 134, No. 3, p. 171-175, illus. (incl. 2 tables),  1982.  Parker, J. C. The lost constants of Coulomb's law: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46,  No. 4, p. 886-887, 1982.  Parker, J. C.; Amos, D. F.; and Zelazny, L.W. Water adsorption and swelling of clay minerals in soil  systems: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 450-456, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Parlange, J.Y. Simple method for predicting drainage from field plots: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 887-888, 1982.  Parlange, J. Y.; Lisle, I.; Braddock, R. D,; et al. The three-parameter infiltration equation: Soil Science,  Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 337-341, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Parlange, J. Y.; Starr, J. L.; Barry, D. A.; et al. A theoretical study of the inclusion of dispersion in  boundary conditions and transport equations for zero-order kinetics: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 701-704, illus., 1982.  Perkins, H. F.; and Lawrence, B. Sesquioxide segregation in plinthic and nonplinthic counterpart soils:  Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 5, p. 314-318, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Persaud, N.; and Wierenga, P.J. A differential model for one-dimensional cation transport in discrete  homoionic ion-exchange media: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 482-490,  illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Pierce, F. J.; Dowdy, R. H.; and Grlgal, D. F. Concentrations of six trace metals in some major  Minnesota soil series: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 416-422, illus. (incl. 7 tables,  sketch map), 1982.  Pons, L. J.; Van Breemen, N.; and Driessen, P.M. Physiography of coastal sediments and development  of potential soil acidity: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor;  et al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 1-18, illus. (incl. block diags., sketch maps), 1982.    273    Posner, Joshua L.; Antonini, Gustavo A.; Montanez, Gustavo; et al. A classification of the steeplands  in the Northern Andes: Mountain Research and Development, Vol. 2, No. 3 (Special issue), p. 273-280,  5 tables, 1 plate, environ, geol. map 1:3,300,000, 1982.  Prasad, S. N.; and Romkens, M. J. M. An approximate integral solution of vertical infiltration under  changing boundary conditions: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 4, p. 1022-1028, illus., 1982.  Proskurin, G. P.; and Tarasenko, V. S. Increase in rock volume in the weathering crust of gabbroic rocks  in the Korosten Pluton: Lithology and Mineral Resources (USSR), Vol. 17, No. 1, p. 8-13, 6 tables, 1982  [1982].  Pyle, Roy E.; Beverage, Woodrow W.; Yoakum, Troy; et al. Soil survey of Randolph County area, main  part, West Virginia: 167 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U.  S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with W. Va.  Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Queiroz, Joao; Southard, A. R.; and Wooldridge, G. L. Characteristics of soils in a stone-free surficial  deposit in central Utah: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 777-781, illus. (incl.  4 tables), 1982.  Rabenhorst, M. C.; Foss, J. E.; and Fanning, D.S. Genesis of Maryland soils formed from serpentinite:  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 607-616, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map),  1982.  Raines, Gary L.; and Wynn, Jeffrey C. Mapping of ultramafic rocks in a heavily vegetated terrain using  Landsat data: Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, Vol. 77, No.  7, p. 1755-1761, illus. (incl. 3 anal., 2 tables), 1982.  Rawat, P. C.; Agarwal, S. L.; Malhotra, A. K.; et al. Determination of thermal conductivity of soils;  a need for computing heat loss through buried submarine pipelines:  SPEJ. Society of Petroleum  Engineers Journal, Vol. 22, No. 4, p. 558-562, illus., 1982.  Rawitz, E.; Etkin, H.; and Hazan, A. Calibration and field testing of a two-probe gamma gauge: Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 461-465, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Reddy, K.R. Mineralization of nitrogen in organic soils: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  46, No. 3, p. 561-566, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  Retallack, Greg J. Paleopedological perspectives on the development of grasslands during the Tertiary:  Proceedings - North American Paleontological Convention, Vol. 3, p. 417-421, 1982.  Risser, Jeffrey Allen.  Phosphate buffering behavior of soils estimated from retention-release  measurements: 87 p., Doctoral, 1982, Pennsylvania State Univ., University Park, PA. available from:  Univ. Microfilms.  Ritchey, K. Dale; Silva, J. Euripedes; and Costa, Ubirajara F. Calcium deficiency in clayey B horizons  of savanna Oxisols: Soil Science, Vol. 133, No. 6, p. 378-382, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Ross, G. J.; Ivarson, K. C.; and Miles, N. M. Microbial formation of basic ferric sulfates in laboratory  systems and in soils: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et  al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 77-94, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Ross, G. J.; and Wang, C. Lepidocrocite in a calcareous, well-drained soil: Clays and Clay Minerals,  Vol. 30, No. 5, p. 394-396, illus. (incl. 2 anal., 2 tables), 1982.  Ross, James C.; and Leathers, Thomas R. Soil survey of Green and Taylor counties, Kentucky:  t 16  p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour.  Environ. Prot.; Ky: Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Ruark, G. A.; Veneman, P. L. M.; Mader, D. L; et al. Use of circular polarization on soil thin sections  to distinguish voids from mineral grains: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 880-  882, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Saxton, K. E.; and MeGuinness, J. L Evapotranspiration: in Hydrologic modeling of small watersheds  (Haan, C. T., editor; et al.), Vol. 5, p. 229-273, illus. (incl. 8 tables), Am. Soc. Agric. Eng., St. Joseph,  MI, United States, 1982.  Sehaff, B. E.; and Skogley, E.O. Diffusion of potassium, calcium, and magnesium in Bozeman slit loam  as influenced by temperature and moisture: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3,  p. 521-524, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.    274    Scheinost, Steven A. Soil survey of Hayes County, Nebraska:  112 p., illus. (incl. 20 tabtcs; soils map~  1:20,000; colored soil map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Univ Nebr. Conserv. Surv. Div.).  Schwertmann, U.; Schulze, D. G.; and Murad, E. Identification of ferrihydrite in soils by dissolution  kinetics, differential X-ray diffraction, and Mossbauer spectroscopy: Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 869-875, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Seeland, David; Christiansen, A. C.; Denson, N. M.; et al. Torrington Quadrangle, Wyoming and  Nebraska: 52 p., illus. (incl. econ. geol. maps 1:500,000; radioactivity surv. map 1:500,000), 1982. (Rep.  No. PGJ/F-067(82)) available from: Bendix Field Eng. Corp., Tech. Libr., Grand Junction, CO. United  States.  Sherwood, Max A. Soil survey of Carroll County, Iowa:  165 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables: soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U.S. Dep. Agriv, Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. Stn.; Iowa State Univ. Coop. Ext. Serv.:  Iowa Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Shoji, S.; Fujiwara, Y.; Yamada, I.; eta/. Chemistry and clay mineralogy of ando soils, Brown forest  soils, and podzolic soils formed from Recent Towada ashes, northeastern Japan: Soil Science, Vol. 133,  No. 2, p. 69-86, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Showers, Kate Barger. Assessment of the land use potential of Ha Makhopo, Lesotho, southern Africa:  a holistic approach to agricultural evaluation:  333 p., Doctoral, 1982, Cornwell Univ., Ithaca, NY.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Sims, James Thomas.  Phosphorus adsorption studies with an acid, aluminous soil and aluminum  hydroxide suspensions: 99 p., Doctoral. 1982, Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, M1. available from:  Univ. Microfilms.  Singh, J. B.; Grube, W. E., Jr.; Smith, R. M.; et al. Relation of pyritic sandstone weathering to soil and  minesoil properties: in Acid sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et  al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 193-208, illus. (incl. 8 tables, sketch map), 1982  Skaggs, R. W.; and Khaleel, R. Infiltration: in Hydrologic modeling of small watersheds (Haan, C. T.,  editor; et al.), Vol. 5, p. 12 I-166, illus. (incl. 6 tables), Am. Soc. Agric. Eng., St. Joseph, MI, United States,  1982.  Smiles, D. E.; Knight, J. H.; and Perroux, K. M. Absorption of water by soil; the effect of a surface  crust: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 476-481, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Smith, C. J.; DeLaune, R. D.; and Patrick, W. H., Jr. Nitrate reduction in Spartina alternifiora marsh  soil: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 748-750, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Sparks, D. L; and Rechcigl, J.E. Comparison of batch and miscible displacement techniques to describe  potassium adsorption kinetics in Delaware soils: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No~  4, p. 875-877, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Spivey, Lawson D., Jr, Soil survey of Jefferson County, Alabama: 140 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils  maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Ala. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Ala. Dep. Agric. Ind.; Ala. Sur. Min.  Reclam. Comm., U. S. Bur. Land Manage.).  Starr, J. L.; Parlange, J. Y.; and Braddock, R.D. Dispersion in soil columns; the precursor effect: Soil  Science, Vol. 133, No. 2, p. 111-115, illus., 1982.  Steinhardt, G. C.; Franzmeier, D. P.; and Norton, L.D. Silica associated with fragipan and non-fragipan  horizons: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 656-657, illus., 1982.  Suarez, D. L.; and Rhondes, J. D. The apparent solubility of calcium carbonate in soils: Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 716-722, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982.  Tant, Phillip L. Soil survey of Currituck County, North Carolina:  102 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils  maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in  coop. with N.C. Dep. Nat. Resour. Comm. Dev.; N.C. Agric. Res. Serv.; N.C. Agric. Ext. Serv.; Currituck  Cty. Board Comm.).  Thomas, Grover J., Jr. Soil survey of DeKalb County, Georgia: 107 p., illus. (incl. 14 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:78,740), U. S. Dep. Agrie., Soil Conserv. Serv., United States, 1982. (Publ.  in coop. with Univ. Ga., Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp. Stn.; DeKalb Cty. Plann. Dep.).    275    Thorn, Colin E. Bedrock microclimatology and the freeze-thaw cycle; a brief illustration: Annals of the  Association of American Geographers, Vol. 72, No. 1, p. 131-137, 5 tables, sketch map, 1982.  Thorsen, John W.; and Stensby, David G. Impact of chromium waste spill in glacial till soils:  in  Conference proceedings of the 1982 hazardous materials spills (Biglane, Kenneth E., chairperson; et al.),  p. 305-310, illus., Gov. Inst., Rockville, MD, United States, 1982.  Topp, G. C.; Davis, J. L.; and Annan, A. P. Electromagnetic determination of soil water content using  TDR; I, Applications to wetting fronts and steep gradients: Soil Science Society of America Journal,  Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 672-678, illus., 1982.  Topp, G. C.; Davis, J. L.; and Annan, A. P. Electromagnetic determination of soil water content using  TDR; II, Evaluation of installation and configuration of parallel transmission lines: Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 678-684, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  Torrent, J.; Guzman, R.; and Parra, M.A. Influence of relative humidity on the crystallization of Fe(lll)  oxides from ferrihydrite: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vot. 30, No. 5, p. 337-340 (incl. Russian, German,  French sum.), illus., 1982.  Tremblay, L. P.  Geology of the uranium deposits related to the sub-Athabasca unconformity,  Saskatchewan: Paper - Geological Survey of Canada, Vol. 81-20, 56 p. (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl.  5 tables, geol. sketch maps; geomorphol, map 1:250,000), 1982.  Tyler, Lucia D.; and McBride, Murray B. Mobility and extractability of cadmium, copper, nickel, and  zinc in organic and mineral soil columns: Soil Science, Vol. 134, No. 3, p. 198-205, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1982.  Van Breemen, N. Genesis, morphology and classification of acid sulfate soils in coastal plains:  in Acid  sulfate weathering; proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et aL), SSSA Special Publication,  Vol. 10, p. 95-108, illus., 1982.  Vazin, Hassan.  Finite element analysis of soil compaction resulting from vibratory tillage:  93 p.,  Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN usa. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Wagner, D. P.; Fanning, D. S.; Foss, J. E.; et al. Morphological and mineralogical features related to  sulfide oxidation under natural and disturbed land surfaces in Maryland:  in Acid sulfate weathering;  proceedings of a symposium (Kittrick, J. A., editor; et al.), SSSA Special Publication, Vol. 10, p. 10%  125, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1982.  Wall, B. H.; John, R. D.; Ahuja, L. R.; et al. A simplified functions approach for determining soil  hydraulic conductivities and water characteristics in situ: Water Resources Research, Vol. 18, No. 4,  p. 1299-1301, 1982.  Wailer, R. M.; Holeeek, T. J.; Stelz, W. B.; et al. Geohydrology of the preglacial Genesee Valley in  Monroe County, New York:  Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), 5 sheets,  hydrogeol, maps, surficial geol. map 1:24,000, 1982. (Rep. No. 82-0552) availablefrom:U. S. Geol. Surv.,  Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Warner, Barry G.; Mathewes, Rolf W.; and Clague, John J. Ice-free conditions on the Queen Charlotte  Islands, British Columbia, at the height of late Wisconsin glaciation: Science, Vol. 218, No. 4573, p. 675-  677, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1982.  Watts, F. C.; Huekle, H. F.; and Paetzold, R. F.  Field vs. laboratory determined hydraulic  conductivities of some slowly permeable horizons: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No.  4, p. 782-784, 5 tables, 1982.  Wayne, William J. Depositional environment of the type section of the Seward Formation (lower  Pleistocene), Nebraska: Transactions of the Nebraska Academy of Sciences and Affiliated Societies,  Vol. 10, p. 49-55, illus. (incl. 2 tables, geol. sketch map), 1982.  Welch, Jerome E.; and Dickey, H. P.  Soil:  in Environmental effects of coal surface mining and  reclamation on land and water in southeastern Kansas (Welch, Jerome E.; et al.), Mineral Resources  Series (Lawrence), Vol. 7, p. 38-72, illus. (incl. 25 anal.), 1982.  White, GeorgeW. GlacialgeologyofnortheasternOhio: Bulletin- Ohio, Division of Geotogical Survey,  Vol. 68, 75 p., illus. (incl. 7 tables, sects., strat, cols., geol. sketch map; colored geol. map 1:250,000;  geomorphol, map), 1982.    276    Wilson, Jay R.; Vanek, Wayne; Carlson, Jan; et al. Soil survey of Custer County, Nebraska:  166 p.  illus. (incl. 19 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv  Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Nebr. Conserv. Surv. Div.).  Wintle, A. G. Thermoluminescence properties of fine-grain minerals in loess: Soil Science, Vok 134,  No. 3, p. 164-170, illus., 1982.  Witeher, James C. Exploration for geothermal energy in Arizona Basin and Range:  ,n Geothermal  Direct Heat Program; roundup technical conference proceedings; Volume I; papers presented; State  Coupled Resource Assessment Program (Ruscetta, Carl A., editor), p. 33-61, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch  maps), 1982. (Rep. No. DOE/ID/12079-71) (Rep. No. ESL-98) available frorn: Univ. Utah Res. Inst.,  Earth Sci. Lab., Salt Lake City, UT, United States.  Wolt, J. D.; and Lietzke, D.A. The influence of anthropogenic sulfur inputs upon soil properties in the  Copper Basin region of Tennessee: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 3, p. 651-656.  illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1982.  Wright, Edward L.; Delp, Charles H.; Sponaugle, Kelley; et al. Soil survey of Marion and Monongalia  Counties, West Virginia: 157 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1982. (Publ. in coop. with W.Va.  Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Zaehmann, D. W.; Du Chateau, P. C.; and Klute, A. Simultaneous approximation of water capacity and  soil hydraulic conductivity by parameter identification: Soil Science, Vol. 134, No. 3, p. 157-163, illus.  (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Zobeek, T. M.; and Daugherty, L. A. Calculating the depths of soil moisture control sections from  laboratory data: Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 792-795, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1982.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      