Geoderma, 34 (1984) 185--200                                                        185  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    ASSESSING  SOIL  AGGREGATE  STABILITY BY WATER-DROP IMPACT  AND ULTRASONIC DISPERSION    A.C. IMESON and M. VIS  Laboratory of Physical Geography and Soil Science, University of Amsterdam,  Dapperstraat 115, 1093 BS A msterdam (The Netherlands)  (Received October 17, 1983; accepted after revision July 11, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Imeson, A.C. and Vis, M., 1984. Assessing soil aggregate stability by water-drop impact  and ultrasonic dispersion. Geoderma, 34 : 185--200.    Simple procedures for estimating soil aggregate stability by the water-drop method  and ultrasonic dispersion are compared for a wide range of soils from Colombia, Kenya,  Lesotho, Luxembourg and Spain. For both methods, two test procedures are compared.  All of the procedures give similar results. For the most unstable soils, the simple form  of the water-drop test provides the best resolution, but this procedure is not suitable  for the more stable soils. The longer water-drop and low-energy ultrasound procedures  do not appear to produce different amounts of breakdown products in the size-fractions  examined. Aggregate disruption by wet sieving also produced a similar size range of  breakdown products. Recommendations are made concerning the most appropriate  test for soils similar to those tested. Both water-drop impact and ultrasonic dispersion  procedures were found to be consistent and reproducible.    INTRODUCTION    Many methods of estimating soil erodibility from simple laboratory  tests or indices have been described (Williams et al., 1966; Bryan, 1968)  and yet the field scientist is still confronted with a problem when having  to characterize the erodibility of a large number of soils. Many simple  tests require basic analytical data which restrict the number of samples  that can be handled or involve procedures which may only indirectly be  related to the response of a soil to raindrop impact. Another difficulty  is the relatively limited range of soil types that are usually considered when  erodibility indices or measurements are compared.  In this paper, two simple methods for assessing soil aggregate stability  are discussed and compared for a range of soil types. These two methods  were chosen because of their simplicity and speed. For each method, two  procedures are described; a rapid procedure whereby the proportion of  stable aggregates is obtained simply by counting the number of aggregates    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    186    surviving a particular treatment, and a somewhat longer procedure providing  more insight into the nature of aggregate disruption.    Aggregate disruption by water-drop impact and ultrasound    Simple procedures for estimating aggregate stability by the water-drop  test have been described by McCalla (1944), Smith and Cernuda (1951),  Low (1965, 1967) and Bruce-Okine and Lal (1975). The test involves  counting the number of water-drop impacts of known force required to  break down a soil aggregate to a certain state of disruption. It is attractive  in its simplicity and obvious reproduction of an erosive mechanism. Arbi-  trary standardizations concerning the pre-treatment and size of the soil  aggregates to be tested are needed, however, and the criteria used to identify  the point of disruption have to be chosen. The standardizations adopted  here are basically those suggested by Low (1967).  The disruption of soil aggregates by ultrasound has been described by  Edwards and Bremner (1967) and used as a measure of soil structural sta-  bility by North {1976) and Koenigs (1978). Edwards and Bremner (1967)  describe how soil aggregates are initially broken by ultrasound into micro-  aggregates before dispersion takes place. Insofar as the forces resisting  disruption by ultrasound are related to the same soil properties as those  resisting breakdown by water-drop impact, the two tests might be expected  to give comparable results. The procedures for estimating aggregate stability  described by Koenigs (1978) and North (1976) involve measuring the  amount of energy absorbed by the material being tested before disruption  into micro-aggregates or dispersion occur.    Soil samples    The soil samples considered in this paper (Table I), were collected mainly  from A-horizons, and were chosen to represent a wide range of conditions.  Andepts from Colombia were selected because of their very stable structure.  They were collected at various elevations under tropical rainforest on a  transect across the Central Andean Cordillera. The soils from the higher  elevations contain large amounts of allophane and organic material. These  permanently moist soils were collected in air-tight containers to prevent  the formation of stable aggregates by irreversible drying. The soils from  lower elevations are more erodible and contain admixtures of non-volcanic  material.  The soils from Spain were sampled because under cultivation they are  subject to slaking and are very erodible. Except for samples from forested  sites, the A-horizons are very low in organic material. The samples are  from an area of badlands north of Guadix (Granada) and from a site near  Teulada in SE Spain (Alicante). All of these sampled soils are highly cal-  careous (Calciorthids) and sometimes contain gypsum (Gypsiorthids) or  sodium salts (Torriorthents).    TABLE I  Soil samples referred to in text and illustrations    187    Samples             Description    Kenya  K2                 A-horizon, Typic Paleustalf, Athi Plains, Kenya (clay 44%)  K7 and K8          AB- and Bt-horizons respectively of a Udic Rhodustalf, Bissel, Kenya  (clay 20 and 34%)  Lesotho (soils subject to tunnel erosion):  1A, 2A, 3A, 4A     A2-horizons, Typic Albaqualfs near Roma, Lesotho (clay 20--25%)  1B, 2B, 3B, 4B,  4C and 4D          B-horizons, Typic Albaqualfs near Roma, Lesotho (clay 30--60%)  Spain  (Granada, soils in area of badlands):  ESP 1, 2, 3 and 4   calcareous soils from badlands near Baza,  southern Spain (car-  bonates and gypsum 70--90%)  ESP 6, 7, 8 and 9   calcareous soils from badlands north of Guadix, Spain (carbonates  64--74%)  ESP 10             saline soil from badlands north of Guadix, Spain (carbonates 8%,  clay 40%, silt 50%)  (Alicante, soils subject to slaking) :  ESP 11, 12, 13,     calcareous soils from Teulada under, respectively, fallow, vine,  14 and 15          grain, fallow and pine forest (carbonates 66--79%)  ESP 16, 17         red soils on terrace deposits Teulada, under vine (carbonates 41  and 61%)  ESP 18             saline soils from gully side, Teulada (carbonates 68%)  Luxembourg (soils having stable aggregates):  LK                 Al-horizon of Albaqualf, soil under forest on the Steinmergel  Keuper Formation {clay 17,5%)  Colombia (soils having very stable aggregates ):  41, 42, 50 and 51   A-horizons from soils developed on volcanic ash under Andean  forest vegetation in the Central Cordillera at altitudes &gt;2500 m:  Hydrandepts  (clay  &lt;15%, organic carbon:  10--15%, allophane  &gt;20%)  43 to 48 and 52     A-horizons from soils developed on volcanic ash under sub-Andean  to 57               forest in the Central Cordillera at altitudes &lt; 1300 m: Typic Dystran-  and 1300 m: Hydric Dystrandepts (clay 15--25%, organic carbon  5--12%, allophane 5--20%.  49 and 58 to 63     A-horizons from soils developed on volcanic ash under warm tropical  forest in the Central Cordillera at altitudes &lt; 1300 m: Typic Dystran-  depts (clay 25--60%, organic carbon &lt; 5%, allophane &lt; 5%)    The soil samples from Lesotho are taken from different horizons of  Typic Albaqualfs exposed in the sides of gullies and pipes. Whilst being  relatively resistant to raindrop impact, these soils are nevertheless subject  to severe tunnel erosion and gullying.  The Luxembourg sample (Albaqualf) is from the Al-horizon of a soil    188    under forest in the Steinmergelkeuper (see Imeson and Jungerius, 1977).  To increase the range of materials tested some soil samples from Kenya  (Table I) were also included.    METHODS    Pretreatment for all tests involved gently sieving the 4--4.8-mm fraction  of soil aggregates from bulk samples, and moistening these at pF 1 for  24 h with distilled water.  For the water-drop test a supply system with a constant head was fitted  to a burette, and water-drops 0.1 g in weight (5.8 mm diameter) were ob-  tained by fitting silicon tubing to the burette nozzle. The water-drops were  allowed to fall 1 m through a 15-cm diameter polythene pipe on aggregates  placed on a 2.8-mm metal sieve.  The first test procedure (CND) simply involved Counting the Number  of water-Drop impacts required to disrupt the aggregate sufficiently for  it to pass through the 2.8-mm sieve. This was repeated for at least 20 ag-  gregates. The second procedure (TDI) consisted of subjecting ten aggregates  4--4.8 mm in diameter to Ten water-Drop Impacts. The weight of the  aggregates retained on the 2.8-mm sieve was determined, together with  the weight of aggregate fragments coarser than 50 pm. These fractions  are expressed as percentages of the air-dry weight of the tested aggregates.  The manner in which the aggregates broke down under this treatment was  also noted.  For the ultra-sonic dispersion tests, a Sanfier 1312 cell destructor (Bran-  son Sonic Power Company, Danbury, Connecticut} was used with an energy  output which could be varied between 30 and 45 W. For the simpler pro-  cedure (UD, Ultrasonic Disruption), 10 moistened aggregates 4--4.8 mm  in diameter were immersed in 40 ml of distilled water in a standard 32-mm  diameter polythene test-tube. These were then subjected to the probe  output for 10 sec with the probe tip placed 11 mm under the water surface.  This test was repeated 4 or 5 times for each of a range of power levels,  the aim being to establish the threshold energy level required for disruption.  Following these treatments, the number of aggregates retained on a 2.8-mm  sieve was counted. The more detailed procedures involved testing 50 moist-  ened 4--4.8-mm diameter aggregates, placed in 100 ml of water, for 20  sec at power outputs of 30 and 45 W (procedures UD30 and UD45, respect-  ively). The amount of material &gt; 2.8 mm following this treatment was  weighed, together with the fraction &lt; 50 pm. Also determined was the  amount of material in 10 ml pipetted from the top of the suspension in the  37-mm diameter test tubes which were used, 1 min after radiation.    DISCUSSION OF THE TEST PROCEDURES    Before giving results obtained with the different procedures we shall  comment on their selection and limitations. The water-drop test procedure    189    (CND) as described by Low (1967) compensates for the low fall-height  of the water-drop by using water-drops having a large mass. Increasing the  fall-height makes aiming the water-drops difficult and uncertain. The large  drops used supply energy at a very rapid rate, the energy of impact of  one drop on an aggregate of 4--4.8 mm diameter being roughly equivalent to  the energy of 2.18 mm of rain. When large numbers of water-drop impacts  are applied to an aggregate, amounts of rainfall supplied are far higher than  those which occur in nature. Energy is transmitted to the aggregate in a  series of equal value pulses. If the aggregate fails to respond to the first  40 of 50 impacts, this usually means that the strength of the bonds re-  taining the elements from which the aggregate is composed forms a threshold  which is not overcome by the discrete impacts of the individual drops.  Summing these impacts is consequently unnecessary. For the above reasons  the water-drop test based on counting the number of drop impacts is best  suited for the more erodible soils.  The second water-drop test procedure (TDI) was chosen because it was  clear that the criterion of retention on a 2.8-mm sieve had several disadvan-  tages. Aggregates break down in different ways under drop impact (Table  II). The fact that an aggregate is retained on a 2.8-mm sieve does not imply  that the drop impacts have not eroded material from it. By weighing the  material retained on the sieve, this limitation is minimized. Also, by restrict-  ing the number of drop impacts to 10 a more realistic amount of water  is applied during the test. Further, in this way it is possible to obtain an  index of stability for the more stable samples which all have a maximum  value under procedure CND.    TABLE II    Reaction of aggregates to water-drop impact  Type  Reaction    1  2  3  4  5    Fragments of the aggregates (micro-aggregates) are gradually lost until the ag-  gregate is forced through the 2.8-ram diameter mesh.  Aggregates break into 2--4 fragments of more or less equal size.  Aggregates are soft and forced in a semi-liquified state rapidly through the 2.8-mm  diameter mesh.  Aggregates lose fine dispersed material from their surfaces.  Aggregates rapidly break down into many microaggregates.    The first procedure of the ultrasonic disruption (UD) test was chosen  to facilitate comparison with the water-drop test. At first an alternative  procedure was tested whereby aggregate disruption was compared at the  same energy level, so that the threshold exposure time required for disrup-  tion could be determined. This procedure (Fig. 1) was not suited to a wide  range of soil types because, as with the water-drop test, stable aggregates    190    had a threshold of disruption related to the power level of the test and not  to the amount of energy supplied at levels below the threshold of disruption.  Much better differentiation was obtained when aggregate disruption was  compared at different power levels. Adopting this approach permitted  comparisons of the more stable aggregates but meant that an essential dif-  ference existed between the ultrasonic and water-drop procedures. Sta-  bility is compared at different rates of energy transfer with the ultrasound  test and at different amounts of energy transfer with the water-drop test.  For the other ultrasonic procedures (UD30 and UD45), in addition to  the fractions &gt; 2.8 mm and &lt; 50 ~m, the concentrations of material in  suspension (SC) were also determined.    100 -    80-  &gt;  ~.~ 60-  DE  ~ 4o-  'S  20-  ~e    \  \  \  \  \    K8    "~" 35W    30W    \                  30W                    K7  N    \  N30W K2    140W K7  \K2 40W  10           20  t (seconds)    ~........, 4 0 W  i0       2~       30                                3~  t (seconds)    Fig. 1. Percentage of tested aggregates surviving ultrasonic radiation at different rates  of energy application and different times of exposure. For description of samples, see  Table I.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The results of procedures CND and UD    The results of the two, CND and UD, procedures are indicated in the  form of cumulative curves showing the proportion of the tested aggregates  surviving the indicated treatment. A wide range in stability is suggested  by both tests and there is in general a high level of agreement (Figs. 2 and  3). Both tests indicate a high resistance for samples from the A-horizons  at forested sites (Colombia, Luxembourg and Spain) and a low stability  for the badland and calcareous samples from Spain. The horizons from  the Lesotho soils present a more varied range of results. The badland soils  were unstable at the lowest power output which could be achieved with  the ultrasonic probe (30 W); thus, the results can not be plotted in Fig. 3.  For the most unstable samples, the water-drop test provides much greater  resolution. The opposite is the case for the more resistant materials, where  frequently all of the aggregates were unbroken after 200 drop impacts.  These samples, not included in Fig. 2, could be tested by procedure UD.    191     ost  ~o4~  5 021  o    lol  !oo   O6  ~c  ~o2  o    E   08  ~o~  "6  2    \                                    ',      4b i  ,j~, PA '  ~   J  \    i  ilUf~lbe~ ()t drop impa(:ls (procedure II       , \\                B   "I/,                    t   I!I \                     !  06[      \k                           !  go2~    "     V,   \  9,'    '      "3  '~  ntlmOer of drop ,mpacls (procedure 1}    1li~~,~~',~/~ \ \~1 \x~o ~  4         r Spat      12  number of drop i   ts  (prc&lt; edure 1 )    number of drop impacts (procedure 1)    I    \           E  \  \  \  \  \ 28   _    "'~.-~ .,~_  ......  4          8         12         16  numbe~ of drop impacts tprocedure 11    1.0   08  i06  ~04  ~o2i  o  o[    2A     "~  20         40        60         80  number of drOp impacts [procedure 1)    Fig. 2. Proportion of aggregates surviving the indicated number of water-drop impacts  (procedure CND). A. A selection of volcanic-ash soils from Colombia. B and C. Soils  from badlands north of Guadix, Spain. D. Calcareous soils from southeast Spain. E and  F. Soils from the neighbourhood of Roma, Lesotho.    192     o81-  --   o4l    :,,,      .  ,4  o  3~     --,6        ,4  power supply Watts    ~o8  ~ 0.6  &amp;  ~o4F  0    !~  463                B  iX X  \59 PAl            /  ! ",\. \x,\         4  !',\ "R',~        !  1  \\  '\                  45 2 \  \  \  3~g-s --X- ,  40        45  power supply Watts    E   08   06   04   02    \\  \ \ 17\\\\           \\\  30               35               4~0  power supply Watts    \    45    ~2~           D1     /   \  ,,                        /   08!   \ ,\         J     '        1h--~-~ \  /             Lumbourg   o0t-  \~',\      ,  q   041      ~\ ',\      ,,&lt;  35            40            45  power supply Watts    Fig. 3. Proportion of aggregates surviving ultrasonic  radiation at the indicated energy  level (procedure UD). A and B. A selection of volcanic ash soils from Colombia. C.  Calcareous soils from southeast Spain. D. A selection of soils from the neighbourhood of  Roma, Lesotho, and sample LK from Luxembourg.    Those calcareous samples which could be tested by procedure UD began  to break down at threshold power outputs between 30 and 36.5 W. The  relationships between the number of surviving aggregates and the probe  output for the different samples show a parallel alignment indicating a  rather constant rate of breakdown above the threshold value. The Lesothan  samples have breakdown curves which are all very similar, irrespective of  differences suggested by the water-drop test. The steep gradients of these  curves indicate a homogeneous aggregate population. The Colombian  samples, except those containing admixtures of non-volcanic material or    193    those under cultivation, require threshold power outputs of 45 W before  breakdown is recorded and in many cases power outputs above this level  failed to reduce all aggregates.  In Fig. 4, envelope curves define the fields within which the results for  the different samples fall. These fields reflect basic differences in soil sta-  bility. The badland samples are not included in this diagram as they oc-  cupy a position to the left of the minimum power output.    10  E  E   os  ~D  C  D   0.6  ~D  ~ o.4  C  0  ~ o.2  0    Cc    30             35                 40            45  power supply of probe (Watts)     Spain  calcareous soils   Lesotho  ~=~ Colombia    Fig. 4. Envelope curves using procedure UD for the soils tested from Spain, Colombia  and Lesotho.    A comparison of procedures CND and UD    For each sample it is possible to compare the two procedures by com-  paring the number of drop impacts and the power output necessary to  break down a similar proportion of aggregates. This shows general agree-  ment, for example when the values are compared for 50% and 25% dis-  ruption (Fig. 5). The number of samples that can be compared in this  way is limited, however, to those in the middle of the stability range in-  asmuch as 25 to 50% of the more resistant aggregates are not destroyed  by the water-drop test and the weaker aggregates could not be tested by  the ultrasound procedures. In spite of the broad agreement between the  two tests, it is apparent that the relationship between disruption by ultra-  sound and breakdown by water-drop impact is not independent of the    194    material being tested. For most samples the correspondence is good, but  in the case of the samples from Lesotho, where the water-drop test indicated  seemingly unstable materials which proved to be relatively resistant to ultra-  sonic disruption, the general relationship does not hold. This is even more  apparent when the number of water-drop impacts and ultrasonic exposure  are compared for the same soil (Fig. 6). Also this Figure shows that for  the more stable samples, above a threshold of about 50 drop impacts an  increasing number of impacts has much less effect on aggregate breakdown  than an increase in ultrasonic exposure.    ]            A             I  45                      median values                   j  *[    45                     25 % unstable    i  `5                                       :                              "5    ,                                                   1      #    o*    &lt;  0                              ,~ Lesotho      o  i                                        1 Spare                        i  I                                  ~ Luxembourg  I             II ~  30~.   ~                        ~         ]        3C  ......;-~  40         80         ~                     200  120                                               40         8()--    120        160  160  number of drop impacts                                                           number of drop impacts    ,5         c          1  10 % unstable  i                   "~ 4ot                        I                     ,  .5            o  .-&gt;     X    t,    ""   *               4   3sF,,,                        ]    Q            Luxembourg  I  o~                         0 Spain  cL                         ~ Colombia  Lesotbo         i  30 -  .b     s'0     ,20  number of drop impacts    0 Lesot ho  Spain  , Colombia    200    Fig. 5. Corresponding values of the number of drop-impacts (procedure CND) and ultra-  sonic power supply (procedure UD) at the median value of stability for the different  samples (A); at the level of disruption survived by 75% of the aggregates (B) and at  the level of disruption survived by 90% of the aggregates (C).    45    195    CD  J~    40  0  O.  0      ....  . 16  t^/    i /                               samples: Spain 15,16,17  /////"                                        Lesotho  A 1C  17.-'"    /  ,,/        /  /.  16    30         2         4         60                 100      125  150 175 200  number of drop impacts    Fig. 6. Corresponding values of ultrasonic power supply and water-drop impacts required  to disrupt equivalent proportions of the sample. Corresponding values are plotted for  the percentile points.    Results and comparison of procedures TDI, UD30 and UD45    For these procedures, data could be obtained for all samples. A selection  of the results obtained is given in Table III. For the samples from Spain  and Lesotho, the fractions &lt; 50 #m produced by ultrasonic disruption  at 30 W and by the water-drop test were in general similar (Table III) and  the correlation between these two amounts high (Fig. 7,A). Although  more material was retained on the 2.8-mm sieve following the ultrasonic  dispersion procedure UD30, the amounts retained were also highly cor-  related (Fig. 7,B). Where soils deviated from the general relationship this  could occasionally be explained by unusual properties of the material,  such as large numbers of gypsum fragments (Table I, Spain 1--4).  The samples from Lesotho break down into relatively similar fractions  under the TDI and UD30 treatments (Table III). Only for sample 4 was  there a difference in the &gt; 2.8-ram fraction. The fraction 2.8 mm--50 #m  is fairly similar for both procedures. The more intensive ultrasonic treat-  ment at 45 W produces a much larger fraction &lt; 50 #m than the other  two procedures in all except the more stable samples. For the Andept  samples UD30 and TDI again give similar results, with very little fine ma-  terial being produced. The UD45 procedure is so severe that nearly all  of the material is dispersed. For the more erodible samples, UD30 and  TDI produce very similar results (Fig. 7).    196  TABLE IlI  Breakdown of aggregates (4--4.8 ram) into fractions &gt; 2.8 mm and &lt; 50 pm under the indicated  procedure (also shown is the type of breakdown occurring under waterdrop impact)    Ultrasonic                         Ultrasonic                         Disruption by      Type of  dispersion 45 W                 dispersion 30 W                 water-drop impact aggregate  (UD45)                        (UD30)                        (TDI)             breakdown  %dry weight                    % dry weight                    % dry weight     (see Table II)    in                              in  Sample suspension &gt;2.8 mm &lt;50 ~m suspension &gt;2.8 mm &lt;50 ~m &gt;2.8 mm &lt;50 pm    Lesotho:  3A       6.4         0        72.0    0.2          1.2      21.7     0         20.1    3/5  3B        5.4          0        49.6    0.3           0         18.7      0         13.5    3  4A        4.0          0        38.7    0.2          10.0        5.2     77.2        1.7    2  4B        4.4          0        50.3    0.1          39.0        4.4     74.9        0.7    3]5  4b       4.5         0        40.2    0.2         22.0      11.5     0        17.4    3/5  Colombia:  62/1     2.6         0        24.4    0.1         84.2       0.9    86,7      &lt;0.1    1  58/1     2.3        30.0      21.8    0           41.0       1.0    98,0      &lt;0.1    1  51/4     5.5         8.4      37.4    0           97.3       1.4    95.2      &lt;0.1    1  46]3     1.9        26.0      69.5    0           97.6       1.0    99.9      &lt;0.1    1  Spain:  1        7.7         0        70.1    0.2         10.2      45.3    40.2      35.8    1/3  3        7.2         0        62.5    0.1         58.3      10.3     0        22.7  6       9.0         0        80.0    0.1         10.2      48.1      0        48.3    3[5  7       8.5         0        79.4    0.1         24.1      16.2    24.5      17.9    1/2  8       6.8         0        57.8    0.1         63.4       3.4    56.5      12.8    4  9       5.5         0        54.1    0.1         43.2       6,8    17.1       11.2    1  10      10.1         0        86.4    0.1          8.1      36,5     0        43.9    1  11        6.1         0        58.5    0.1         81.0       3.6    71.3        3.5    1  12       6.3         0        70.8    0.2         38.8       8.3    12.1       10.0    1/5  13        7.5          0        66.3    0.1          57.1        4.3     26.8        6.1    1  15       5.9         4        50.8    0.1         98.2       1.2    47.9        0      1  17       6.3         0        62.2    0.1         96.3       1.0    64.0        0.3    1  18       4.9         0        45.7    0.2          0        15.0     0          9.8    5    100  E  2  V  8O  o- 60  ~ ~40  ~o  g    x   x    20        40        60        80                         20        40        60  %of aggragate broken into particles &lt; 50.m                         % of aggregate fragments &gt;2.8ram  ultrasound  IUD 30)                                       ultrasound ( UD 30)    B  100~~  ....  ~ ,"  E    100    Fig. 7. Scattergram comparing the weight of aggregate fragments in the fraction &lt; 50 ~m  (A) and &gt;2.8 mm (B) following procedures TDI and UD30.    197    The similarity of the results for the UD30 and the TDI procedures sug-  gest that soil aggregate properties control the size fractions into which  aggregates disrupt.  For a small number of samples, the size distribution of the ultrasound  breakdown products of the 4--4.8-mm aggregates was examined in greater  detail. These size distributions were then compared with those obtained  by a simple wet sieving treatment, by which the pre-moistened 4--4.8-mm  aggregates were placed on a nest of sieves and very gently raised and lowered  12 times under water (Cyganov, 1967). The purpose of these determinations  was initially to select the most important fractions for use as indices of  erodibility under procedures TDI and UD30. The results also provide ad-  ditional information on the different effects of ultrasonic and other forms  of disruption on aggregate breakdown.  For sample ESP12 (Fig. 8), the size distributions produced by wet-  sieving and 30 and 36 W ultrasonic treatments are indeed very similar but  at 42 W the ultrasound procedure produces far more material &lt; 50 ~m  than the other treatments.    100-         A  80                              42 W                                                     36 W                                            30 W                           I wet sieving  L  5O  4O    12345678         12345678         12345678         12345678    lOO-          B  58/1                58/1  80   I   45 W          i 36w  L  t  6O  50  40    12345678         12345678    58/'1  wet sJevmg    12345678    1      &gt;28mm  2   2 8 -2mm  3     2-1mm  4  1ram -500 ,urn  5  500 -210 ,um  6  210 -100 ,urn  7   100 - 50 ~m  8    &lt;50 ~*m    Fig. 8. Breakdown of 4--2.8-mm aggregates into the indicated fractions following ultra-  sonic disruption and wet sieving procedures.    SELECTING AN INDEX OF ERODIBILITY  If the procedures outlined above are to be used to estimate or compare  the stability of different soil aggregates, the most appropriate procedure    198    for a given set of conditions needs to be chosen. It is also necessary to  decide which of the measures used to indicate the reaction of the sample  to the procedure are most useful. The general similarity of the results of  the water-drop and ultrasonic dispersion procedures has been described  above as well as the fact that few indices consistently produce the same  relationship for each sample. Where two measures indicate similar relative  stabilities for all samples, these parameters are likely to be useful because  they are applicable to a wide range of soils.  To facilitate the selection of appropriate indices a correlation matrix  was computed for all of the test data listed in Table IV and the relationships  between the data examined through scattergrams. This was done for all  of the data as a group and also separately for the different soil types. In  addition to median values for procedures CND and UD, values required  to disrupt only 10% of the tested aggregates were included to increase  the number of cases. Further, even a small percentage of unstable aggregates  may have an important effect on erodibility and infiltration. Although  the correlation coefficients for nearly all of the test results are highly sig-  nificant, an inspection of the scatterdiagrams showed only a few measures  with the degree of correspondence indicated in Fig. 7 for the results of  TDI and UD30. Consistent relationships (Table V) included those between  the median values of procedures CND and UD and between the fractions   2.8 mm and &lt; 50 pm for procedures TDI and UD30 respectively. The  median values of both from the simpler procedures (CND and UD)are  also significantly correlated with the fractions &gt; 2.8 mm of procedures  TDI and UD30. The easily determined parameter UD45--SC (Table IV) ap-  pears to be the most useful which is highly correlated with other variables    TABLE IV    Parameters used in the statistical analysis    CND  TDI    UD  UD30    UD45    Median (CND-med) and 10% (CND-ten) disruption values of samples subjected  to water-drop impact.  Weight percentage of the sample remaining on a 2.8-mm sieve (TDI) after 10  water-drop impacts.  Weight percentage of the sample passing through a 50-~m sieve (TDI) after 10  water-drop impacts.  Median (UD-med) and 10% (UD-ten) disruption values.  Concentration of sediment in suspension (UD30-SC) after disruption of the  aggregates by ultra-sound at 30 W output.  Weight percentage of the aggregates remaining on a 2.8-mm sieve (UD-30--2.8)  after ultrasonic disruption of the aggregates at 30 W output.  Weight percentage of the aggregates passing through a 50-~m sieve (UD30--50)  after ultrasonic disruption at 30 W output.  Idem ditto procedure UD45 at 45 W output, variables: UD45--SC, UD45--2.8,  UD45--50.    199    TABLE V  Spearman correlation coefficients between selected parameters for the total data set (N.S. = not  significant at P ( 0.01); for explanations of abbreviations, see Table IV    CND Med.  UD Med.    0.88  UD45--SC -0.62      -0.63  UD45--50  -0.55      N.S.       0.80  UD30--2.8  0.81        0.65     -0.52      N.S.  UD30---50   0.82        0.68      0.60      0.56        -0.94  TDI--2.8    0.94        0.72      0.61      N.S.         0.81      -0.81  TDI--.50    -0.85      -0.74      0.73      0.56        -0.75        0.84      -0.87  CND-med. UD-med. UD45--SC UD45--50  UD30--2.8 UD30--50 TDI--2.8 TDI--50    (except for the samples from Colombia). This is not the case for UD30--SC.  In general, the correlation coefficients between the results of the water&lt;lrop  and the ultrasonic dispersion tests are highly significant.    CONCLUSION    The most suitable procedure for rapidly evaluating the aggregate sta-  bility of highly erodible soils was found to be CND. In this case highly  erodible samples are considered to be those in which aggregate disruption  occurs prior to 20--30 impacts. The results can best be expressed in terms  of the median number of drop impacts required to disrupt the aggregate  inasmuch as this is highly correlated with the results of other tests, more  suitable for the more stable soils. In general the simple ultrasonic procedure  (UD) was much less satisfactory for the more stable soils than the slightly  more lengthy procedure UD30. When either UD30 or TDI are used, the most  useful indicator of stability was found to be the fraction &gt; 2.8 mm. It makes  little difference which test is used. For very stable soils such as those from  Colombia UD30 is recommended. For very weak aggregates ultrasonic  procedures are too aggressive. When greater resolution is required procedures  TD! and UD30 should be used in preference to CND.  The ultrasonic dispersion procedure UD45 is too disruptive to be used  as an indicator of stability. Nevertheless, the turbidity of the suspension  produced by this disruption is related to many of the other indices and  reflects ways in which aggregates break down.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We wish to thank P.D. Jungerius and J.M. Verstraten for helpful sug-  gestions and Mrs. M.C.G. Keijzer-v.d. Lubbe for preparing the manuscript.  This research was made possible by a research grant from the University  of Amsterdam and by the Netherlands Foundation of Pure Scientific  Research (Z.W.O.).    200    REFERENCES    Bruce-Okine, E. and Lal, R., 1975. Soil erodibility as determined by raindrop technique.  Soil Sci., 119: 149--157.  Bryan, R.B., 1968. The development, use and efficiency of indices of soil erodibility.  Geoderma, 2: 5--26.  Cyganov, M.S., 1967. Wet sieving for direct determination of aggregate stability by  Tjulin-Savvinov, modified by Cyganov. In: West-European Methods for Soil Structure  Determination, p. VI--45. Ghent, Belgium.  Edwards, A.P. and Bremner, J.M., 1967. Dispersion of soil particles by sonic vibration.  J. Soil Sci., 18: 47--63.  Imeson, A.C. and Jungerius, P.D., 1977. The widening of valley incisions by soil fall in  a forested Keuper area, Luxembourg. Earth Surf. Proc., 2: 141--152.  Koenigs, F.F.R., 1978. Comments on the paper by P.F. North (1976): "Towards an  absolute measurement of soil structural stability using ultrasound". J. Soil Sci., 29:  117--119.  Low, A.J., 1965. The study of soil structure in the field and laboratory. J. Soil Sci.,  5: 57--74.  Low, A.J., 1967. Measurement of stability of moist soil aggregates to falling waterdrops  according to Low. In: West-European Methods for Soil Structure Determination,  Ghent, p. VI--78.  Mc Calla, T.M., 1944. Waterdrop method of determining the stability of soil structure.  Soil Sci., 58: 117--123.  North, P.F., 1976. Towards an absolute measurement of soil structural stability using  ultrasound. J. Soil Sci., 27: 451--459.  Smith, R.M. and Cernuda, C.F., 1951. Some applications of the water-drop stability  testing to tropical soils of Puerto Rico. Soil Sci., 71: 337--345.  Williams, B.G., Greenland, D.J., Lindstrom, G.R. and Quirk, I.P., 1966. Techniques for  the determination of the stability of soil aggregates. Soil Sci., 101 : 157--163.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractSimple procedures for estimating soil aggregate stability by the water-drop method and ultrasonic dispersion are compared for a wide range of soils from Colombia, Kenya, Lesotho, Luxembeurg and Spain. For both methods, two test procedures are compared. All of the procedures give similar results. For the most unstable soils, the simple form of the water-drop test provides the best resolution, but this procedure is not suitable for the more stable soils. The longer water-drop and low-energy ultrasound procedures do not appear to produce different amounts of breakdown products in the site-fractions examined. Aggregate disruption by wet sieving also produced a similar size range of breakdown products. Recommendations are made concerning the most appropriate test for soils similar to those tested. Both water-drop impact and ultrasonic dispersion procedures were found to be consistent and reproducible.