 Gcoderma, 24 (1980) 1--16                                                        1  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    QUANTITATIVE EVALUATIO~    OF PEDON FORMATION IN CALCAREOUS  GLACIAL DEPOSITS IN OHIO~    NEIL E. SMECK and L.P. WILDING  Agronomy Department, Ohio Agricultural Research and Development Center, Wooster,  Ohio (U.S.A.)  Soil and Crop Sciences Department, Texas Agricultural Experiment Station, College Station,  Texas (U.S.A.)  (Received January 24, 1979; accepted November 7, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Smeck, N.E. and Wilding, L.P., 1980. Quantitative evaluation of pedon formation in cal-  careous glacial deposits in Ohio. Geoderma, 24: 1--16.    The genesis of 24 pedons derived from calcareous glacial deposits in Ohio was studied  with quantitative (reconstruction) techniques. This report summarizes refinements in quan-  titative techniques and discusses problems encountered during those studies.  In most of our studies, elemental Zr was employed as the stable index constituent. Unit  volume factors, which are based on Zr distribution, were found to be a function of size  separates employed for analysis. Therefore, it is suggested that the index constituent  should be determined on all fractions &gt; 2 ~m in order to provide the most reliable estima-  tions of gains and losses. Elemental ratios of Ti/Zr were employed in our studies as the  primary indicators of parent-material uniformity; however, additional lines of evidence  are advisable because: (1) micro-occlusions of rutile and zircon have been found in host  light minerals, (2) elemental Ti exhibits depth distributions indicative of weathering trends,  and (3) Ti is preferentially lost from gravel and sand due to the disintegration of shale.  Calculated particle-size distribution in the reference base supposing carbonate removal  and/or shale disintegration can be employed to partition computed clay gains and losses  to such processes as attrition of sand- and gravel-size shale, carbonate leaching, in situ neo-  formation of clay, and clay translocation. Sub-sampling can greatly increase the sensitivity  of reconstruction analysis, but even the most precise sampling scheme will not permit  identification of differences in soil development below 10%.    INTRODUCTION    Since Marshall and Haseman (1942) reported an improved technique for  quantitative evaluations of soft formation, numerous pedogenetic studies have  involved what are commonly known as reconstruction techniques to evaluate  soil-forming processes (Nikiforoff and Drosdoff, 1943; Mick, 1949; Westin,  1953; Khan, 1959; Oertel, 1961; Bourne and Whiteside, 1962; Green, 1966;    *Approved for publication as journal article No.34-79 of the Ohio Agricultural Research  and Development Center, Wooster, Ohio 44691 (U.S.A.)    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    Redmond and Whiteside, 1967; Smeck and Runge, 1971; Wang and Arnold,  1973; Evans and Adams, 1975; Brewer and Coventry, 1977). Detailed dis-  cussions and reviews of quantitative pedogenesis have been published by  Barshad (1955}, Brewer (1964), and Evans (1978). In Ohio, numerous genetic  studies of soils derived from calcareous glacial deposits have employed recon-  struction techniques to calculate gains and losses of various soil components,  such as Ti, Fe, Ca, K, Mn, gravel, sand, silt and clay, during pedogenesis (Smeck  et al., 1968; Smith and Wilding, 1972; Ritchie et al., 1974; Rostad et al., 1976).  The objective of this report is: (1) to summarize problems encountered with  quantitative evaluations, (2) to describe refinements in reconstruction tech-  niques applied to calcareous glacial deposits, and (3) to illustrate the use of  pedons as the units for reconstruction.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    During the past 10 years, 24 pedons, representing 15 soil series, from the  glaciated regions of Ohio and Michigan (Fig. 1) have been investigated using    Fig.1. Location of pedons sampled for reconstruction analyses.    quantitative pedogenetic techniques. The soft, series studied and Family clas-  sifications (Soft Survey Staff, 1975) are reported in Table I. The analytical  methods employed in each study differed slightly in order to accommodate  unique objectives or conditions; thus, the various references cited (Table I)  should be consulted for detailed analytical techniques. The best general dis-  cussion of the analytical and reconstruction techniques employed is pre-  sented by Wilding et al. (1971).    TABLE I  Soils employed in quantitative evaluations of soil formation    Series            Family                                        Reference    Celina           fine, mixed, mesic Aquic Hapludalfs  Morley          fine, illitic, mesic Typic Hapludalfs  Canfield         fine-loamy, mixed, mesic Aquic Fragiudalfs  Rittman         fine-loamy, mixed, mesic Aquic Fragiudalfs  Nappanee        fine, illitic, mesic Aeric Ochraqualfs  Bennington      fine, illitic, mesic Aeric Ochraqualfs  Canfield         fine-loamy, mixed, mesic Aquic Fragiudalfs  Mahoning        fine, illitic, mesic Aeric Ochraqualfs  Platea           fine-silty, mixed, mesie Aeric Fragiaqualfs  Wadsworth      fine-silty, mixed, mesic Aeric Fragiaqualfs  Eldean           fine, mixed, mesic Typic Hapludalfs  Fox             fine-loamy over sandy-skeletal, mixed, mesic  Typic Hapludalfs  Ockley          fine-loamy, mixed, mesic Typic Hapludalfs    Rostad et al. (1976)  Brookston       fine-loamy, mixed, mesic Typic Argiaquolls    unpublished  Hoytville        fine, illitic, mesic Mollic Ochraqualfs           unpublished  Pewamo         fine, mixed, mesic Typic Argiaquolls          unpublished    Smeck et al. (1968)  Smeck et al. (1968)  Calhoun (1968)  Calhoun (1968)  Smith and Wilding (1972)  Ritchie et al. {1974)    Ritchie et al. (1974)  Ritchie et al. (1974)  Ritchie et al. (1974)  Ritchie et al. (1974)  Rostad et al. (1976)  Rostad et al. (1976)    BASIC CONSIDERATIONS    In nearly all reconstruction studies, it is desirable that each pedon: (1)  possess a reference base; (2) be derived from uniform parent material, and  (3) include a stable index constituent.  In the Ohio studies, pedons were selected to satisfy these basic considera-  tions which were subsequently evaluated analytically for each pedon. The  following discussion examines these considerations in detail as applied to re-  construction of soils developed from calcareous glacial deposits in Ohio.    Reference base    The degree of weathering of the zone selected as the reference base for    quantitative evaluation has a direct bearing on the magnitude of gains or losses  calculated. In soils derived from glacial deposits in Ohio, the upper 65 cm of  calcareous material commonly considered C horizon is sufficiently altered to  render it unsuitable as a base for estimating maximum pedogenic weathering  (Wenner et al., 1961). Evidence for this is a progressive decrease in clay content  with depth (Smith and Wilding, 1972} accompanied by progressive increases  in calcite, calcium carbonate equivalent and calcite/dolomite ratios (Wenner  et al., 1961). Consequently, assuming no evidence of lithologic discontinuities,  we have generally utilized materials, below the partially weathered calcareous  zone, which yield constant-depth functions of particle-size separates, calcite,  dolomite, Ti, Zr, and clay mineralogy as a base for reconstruction. Sampling  errors are minimized by employing values for the parameters of interest which  are the computed average of several sub-samples from the unaltered zone selected  as the reference base.    Parent-material uniformity    Numerous techniques have been suggested and employed to establish parent-  material uniformity. Brewer (1964) indicates that depth distributions of  stable constituents which exhibit smooth curves without inflections imply  parent-material uniformity; however, he cautions that this must be supported  by additional evidence to be conclusive. Depth distributions of such resistant  minerals as quartz, rutile, tourmaline, and zircon, as well as the complete  heavy-mineral suite and various particle-size fractions have been employed for  this purpose (Evans, 1978). In calcareous deposits, depth distributions are  more definitive if plotted on a carbonate-free and clay-free basis to remove  inflections due to carbonate leaching and clay movement. An even more use-  ful technique to remove such confounding effects is to plot ratios of resistant  minerals inasmuch as both minerals should be equally concentrated or diluted  by clays or carbonates. Sufficient grain counts to be statistically sound are  quite laborious and time-consuming, whereas the ratio of micro-elements  found primarily in resistant minerals can be determined readily by X-ray  spectroscopy. In most of our studies, Ti/Zr ratios, coupled with particle-size  parameters, have been employed as an indicator of parent-material uniformity.  Constant Ti/Zr ratios with depth are not conclusive evidence of parent-mate-  rial uniformity inasmuch as similar Ti/Zr ratios have been observed across  evident stratigraphic breaks (Rostad et al., 1976).  Whereas it is commonly assumed that Ti and Zr are primarily associated  with the more resistant heavy minerals, recent work suggests that significant  quantities of these elements (50--70% of the Ti and 20--50% of the Zr) occur  as micro-occlusions of primary minerals within host quartz and feldspar grains  or proxy for other metallic ions in silicate structures (Khangarot et al., 1971;  Drees and Wilding, 1978). Whatever the mechanism for inclusion of Ti and Zr  in the light-mineral fraction, it affects the reliability of Ti/Zr ratios as indica-  tors of parent-material uniformity and points out that Ti/Zr ratios should not  be used as sole indices of parent-material uniformity.    Additionally, Ti contents of some pedons employed in our studies show  depth distributions which are indicative of slight weathering trends (Smith  and Wilding, 1972). Calculated losses of Ti in four Nappanee pedons are  shown in Table II. The calculations employed Zr as the stable index. In all  four pedons, there is generally a progressive decrease in Ti losses with depth;  this trend is particularly evident from the A to B horizons.    TABLE II  Calculated losses of Ti (g]100 cma) in four Nappanee profiles based on total Zr  (0.002--2 ram) as a stable constituent    Profile designation    Horizon      PT-28      HN-97     FT-18     Mich 46    Ap           --0.29     --0.22     --0.22     --0.34  B21tg       --0.05    --0.04    -0.13    --0.05  B22tg       --0.09    -0.04    -0.04    -0.02  B23tg                             0.00      0.00  B3tg        -0.04      0.00     +0.02    -0.03    The disintegration of shales has also been found to exert a pronounced  effect on Ti/Zr ratios in the 2-~m--2-mm fraction. Shale, which contains a  relatively high content of Ti in Ohio (0.3--0.8% Ti, Wilding et al., 1971), is  quite susceptible to physical weathering which results in attrition of sand- and  gravel-size shale to silt- and clay-size particles. The attrition of sand- and  gravel-size shale as a function of increasing weathering is illustrated in Table  III by decreasing shale contents on approaching soil surfaces. Shale attrition    TABLE III    Percent* shale in the sand, 2--4 mm gravel, and ~ 4-mm gravel fractions on a carbonate-free basis in  three soils from western Ohio    Horizon  Brookston                        Pewamo                       Hoy tvilie  sand     2--4 mm    ~ 4 mm  sand  2--4 mm    &gt; 4 mm  sand  2--4 mm     4ram    Ap         0        N.D.**       N.D.      &lt; 1   N.D.         N.D.       0      9             4  B2         7        N.D.         N.D.        6   N.D.          60        3    15             0  B3        17        N.D.         N.D.       14   N.D.         100      15    34           40  C         27        85           54         34   79           100      41    39            57    *Percentage calculated on a weight basis for the &gt; 4-ram fraction and on grain counts for the sand  and 2--4-mm fractions. **N.D. indicates that the sample did not contain a sufficient number of grains  for a reliable determination.    seems to be initiated in B3 horizons which coincide with zones of partial car-  bonate leaching. Upon shale disintegration from the sand and gravel fractions  by weathering, the Ti content of the remaining sand and gravel decreases as  illustrated by data in Table IV. The Ti content of shale is nearly double that    6  TABLE IV  Titanium content of shale and sand from the B and C horizons of three pedons from western  Ohio    Percent on carbonate-free basis    Sample       Brookston       Pewamo      Hoytville  B2-Sand      0.20             0.19          0.22  B3-Sand       0.20              0.22           0.27  C-Sand        0.29             0.24          0.29  Shale         0.40             0.34          0.42    of sand from B2 horizons, which contains 3--7% shale. Sand from C horizons  which contains 27--41% shale is intermediate in Ti content. Thus the effect  of physical disintegration of sand-size shale to clay-size is a reduction in Ti/Zr  ratios of the 2-pm--2-mm fraction in sola relative to C horizons. Inflections  in Ti/Zr ratios near the bases of sola could be interpreted as lithologic dis-  continuities, but are actually a consequence of pedogenesis. Ti/Zr depth func-  tions for two such soils are shown in Fig. 2. The dashed lines in this  figure show Ti/Zr values which have been corrected for shale loss by adding  Ti to the measured Ti content in the sand fraction of each horizon in propor-  tion to the Ti content in a quantity of shale equal to the difference between  the observed shale content and that of the C horizon. That is, an estimation  of the quantity of Ti lost from sand in each horizon due to shale disintegration  Ti/Zr RATIO (Sand Fraction)  Brookston           Pewamo  10      20     30  10     20      30  0  f/,  '      '   ~i. '~      '  t  I  I  5O  I  I  I    150  200  ....  Corrected for Shale Loss  250  Fig.2. Ti/Zr depth functions for a Brookston and a Pewamo pedon before and after cor-  rection for shale attrition.    has been added to the measured Ti content before computation of the ratios.  After this correction, Ti/Zr depth functions show less evidence for a lithologic  discontinuity; however, the Brookston pedon still appears to possess a lithologic  discontinuity whereas the Pewamo pedon shows little evidence for a lithologic  break.  Although reconstruction techniques are much more useful and definitive  if parent materials do not exhibit lithologic discontinuities, a lack of parent-  material uniformity does not preclude the use of reconstruction techniques.  In soils studied to evaluate the development of argillic horizons over calcareous  glacial outwash, the C horizons were found to be stratified with respect to  particle-size distribution and carbonate content; thus it could reasonably be  expected that the material in which the sola formed was also originally stratified  (Rostad et al., 1976). Quantitative Dedogenesis demonstrated that these ar-  gillic horizons could have formed in materials similar to the observed C hori-  zons but could not confirm such a derivation for the argillic horizons due to  the presence of lithologic discontinuities.    Stable index constituent    The index constituent must possess two essential properties: (1) it must be  immobile, that is, it must occur in a size separate and form which is not trans-  located, and (2) it must be very resistant to weathering. Most commonly, the  resistant minerals, zircon, quartz and tourmaline, or elements specific for re-  sistant minerals, Zr, B, and Ti, are employed as the index constituent. In most  of our studies, total elemental Zr as determined by X-ray spectroscopy has  been employed as the index rather than Ti because of the weathering trends  noted with the latter. In one study of soils formed in highly calcareous deposits  in which Zr was difficult to measure accurately, a combination of elemental  Ti and Zr, weighted eqtvally, was employed (Rostad et al., 1976}. Due to the  possible occurrence of zirconium in relatively unstable minerals as well as the  stable mineral zircon, elemental analysis is not as reliable as mineral counts;  however, inasmuch as zircon is essentially the only source of zirconium in our  soils and in view of expediency, elemental analysis has been employed.  Besides choice of index constituent, one must decide which soil fraction  should be analysed. The clay fraction must be eliminated from consideration  due to the possibility of translocation. Even though silt translocation has  been documented in sand columns (Wright and Foss, 1968) and is probable  in very sandy or gravelly soils, there is little evidence for the movement of silt  particles (&gt; 5 pm) in soils which were employed in our studies in Ohio. Inas-  much as Ti tends to concentrate in the fine silt fraction and Zr in the coarse  silt fraction (Wilding et al., 1971}, the index chosen may favor the selection  of certain particle-size classes. Unit volume factors (defined in the following  section on calculations) based on the Zr content in fine silt, coarse silt, total  sand, and sand plus silt for the horizons from a Canfield pedon are given in  Table V. Unit volume factors based on the fine silt fraction are greatest where-    8  TABLE V  Unit volume factors for horizons of a Canfield pedon based on the Zr content of the fine  silt, coarse silt, total sand, and silt + sand fractions (after Calhoun, 1968)    Horizon      Depth     Unit volume factors  (cm)    fine     coarse  total    silt +  silt     silt     sand    sand    Ap           0--23   1.78   1.19   0.44   0.97  B1          23--33   1.24   0.97   0.64   0.87  B21t         33--48   1.02   0.67   0.59   0.70  B22t         48--60   0.83   0.80   0.68   0.75  Bxl         60--75   0.97   0.94   0.89   0.92  Bx2            75--90    0.91    0.83    0.77    0.82  Bx3            90--105  1.10    0.93    0.69    0.86  Bx4           105--130  0.95     0.78    0.86    0.85  C1             130--155  0.93    0.89     1.01     0.95  C2             155--175   1.00     0.85     1.01     0.95  C3             175--195   1.00     1.00     1.00     1.00    as those based on the total sand fraction are lowest. The high unit volume  factors based on the fine silt fraction are attributed to weathering of consti-  tuents less stable than zircon. Low unit volume factors can often be attributed  to dilution of the separate with a secondary pedogenic product low in Zr; in  this case, the sand fraction contained pedogenic Fe-Mn nodules. The coarse  silt fraction yields unit volume factors of essentially the same magnitude as  the combined sand and silt. Thus, the Zr content of the coarse silt fraction  may be a reliable index for reconstruction work in soils such as the Canfield  series derived from materials with a low carbonate content. For softs derived  from highly calcareous deposits, the Zr content of the coarse silt fraction is a  suitable index only if the calculations are made on a carbonate-free basis be-  cause carbonates exhibit a bimodal distribution in glacial deposits with one  of the maxima occurring in the coarse silt fraction (Fig. 3). Thus, unit volume  factors based on the Zr content in coarse silt fractions will be disproportio-  nately high for calcareous softs which will result in underestimations of con-  stituent gains or overestimation of losses. To avoid such problems, we advo-  cate the use of the Zr content of the &gt; 2-pm fraction as an index for quanti-  tative evaluations.    CALCULATIONS    Although some quantitative evaluations of soil formation have invoked a  constant volume relationship between parent material and the solum (Oertel,  1961; Wild, 1961 ), there are evident volume changes accompanying pedo-  genesis in calcareous glacial deposits due to the loss of carbonates. Thus one    lf  -  70  6O  50                                          ~,  ,.o ..._  ........  \ -.,. ....  ".,\  %           eg,."*'*"  c~ 20  10  Y  t    I    I    i    I    I    I    I    i    i    I    I    I  32-64 1632 8"16 4-8  2-4  1-2  .5"1 .25".5  .I".25 .05- .02- .OOQ" &lt;.002  .1 .05  .02  Particle size class Imml  Fig.3. Carbonate distribution in C horizon size fractions for three representative glacial  soils from western Ohio (Fox, Celina, and Nappanee).    of the principal tasks is to evaluate pedogenic volume changes with the use  of a stable index constituent. We suggest that volume relationships be ex-  pressed in terms of a "Unit Volume Factor" (UVF) which relates the number  of unit volumes of parent material necessary to yield a unit volume of a soil  horizon. The unit volume factor is the same as the weathering factor com-  puted by Westin (1953) and is the reciprocal of the volume factor defined by  Brewer (1964).  Formulae utilized for calculation of the unit volume factors and gains and  losses are-adequately discussed elsewhere (Brewer, 1964; Wilding et al., 1971).  Soil parameters which must be obtained to make such calculations include  bulk density, particle-size distribution, weight percentages of the index con-  stituent in given size fractions and weight percentages of other constituents  for which gains and losses are to be calculated. For further refinements in  these calculations, data may also be needed on carbonate contents of various  size separates, insoluble residues from calcareous components and shale per-  centages.  The gain or loss of a constituent on a net volume basis (g/100 cm3) can be  meaningfully compared among horizons of the same or separate pedons be-  cause such calculations are not confounded by horizon thickness. If we wish  to determine the total gain or loss of a constituent for an entire pedon or sec-  tion thereof, however, it is necessary to multiply the net volume change of    10    each horizon by its respective horizon thickness and sum resulting products.  An example of such a calculation is given in Table VI for an Ockley pedon which  exhibits a net gain in the solum of all separates except gravel; the loss of gravel  is essentially balanced by the gain in other separates.    TABLE VI    Calculated (g/100 cm3) gains (+) and losses (--) of particle-size separates in an Ockley  pedon in Ohio    Horizon    Depth      Fine    Coarse     Silt     Sand    Gravel  Net  (cm)       clay     clay                                    change**  Ap            0--25    + 1     + 6        +45     + 7     --80     --21  Blt         25--36    + 7     + 9        +42       0     --66    -- 8  B21t        36--46    + 7     +14        +28     + 6     --55        0  B22t        46--58    +13     + 7        +21     + 9     --49     + 1  B23t        58--68    +12     + 6        +18     +15     --44     + 7  B24t        68--84    +12     + 5        +12     +17     --43     + 3  B31t        84--104  +10     + 6        +14     +21     --38     +13  B32t       104--119  +14     + 5        + 5     +22     --35    +11  B33t       119--132   + 8     + 4        + 4     -- 6     -- 8     + 2  C                        0       0          0       0       0    Summation* Ap--B33t +11.5   + 8.6      +29.0   +14.4  --63.8  -- 0.3  *Summation values represent the total gain or loss for a unit cross-sectional area, the thick-  ness of the entire solum or uniform portion of the solum.**The net change is the gain or  loss of soil material occurring in a horizon or the complete solum.    After the reference base is selected, there are several transformations of  particle-size data for this zone that will foster more informative evaluations  of changes in particle-size distribution accompanying pedogenesis. In calcare-  ous glacial deposits, the particle-size distribution generally changes upon leaching  of carbonates due to non-uniform particle-size distribution of carbonates  (Fig. 3). Leaching of carbonates from such materials yields carbonate-free  particle-size distributions with lower gravel, coarse sand, and coarse silt sepa-  rates and considerably higher clay contents. In soils derived from highly cal-  careous deposits, the gains and losses due to carbonate removal may mask  changes due to such processes as clay translocation or in situ neoformation of  clay. Quantitative evaluations on a carbonate-free basis solves that problem  as illustrated by data in Fig. 4. In this example, note that reconstruction on a  carbonate-free basis, which eliminates the effects of carbonate leaching from  calculated gains and losses, results in a total clay gain in every horizon below  the Ap and a net gain in the solum, whereas reconstruction on a calcareous  basis yields only a gain in one horizon and a net loss in the solum. Calculation  of a carbonate-free particle-size distribution for the reference base is not only  dependent on the availability of carbonate particle-size data (Fig. 3) but also    . @    25    50    75    100    125    Clay lg/lOOccl  Loss                         Gain  30        20        10         0         10  I         I         i         I         I  I  ~:':~i:~.  .....  !  [  /i  Calcareous total soll  .o..oo,ooo Carbonate-free total soil  ...ow--. Carbonate-free total soil  corrected for shate attrition    20    0,1:    32    B~    C    11    Fig.4. Gains and losses of total clay in a Hoytville pedon as calculated using three means of  expressing the particle-size distribution in the base horizon.    on data regarding content and particle size of insoluble residues upon carbo-  nate removal. A summary of acid-insoluble residue contents in carbonates in  glacial deposits in Ohio is shown in Table VII. As particle-sizes of carbonates  decrease, residues increase and particle sizes of residues decrease. In soils de-  rived from low-carbonate materials, corrections for carbonate residues show  minimal effects and thus are not essential.  Another process affecting particle-size distribution in sola is disintegration  of noncarbonate sand and gravel separates to finer fractions. Attrition of  shale is quite evident during weathering of glacial deposits (Table III). Studies  conducted to determine the particle-size distribution of disintegrated shale  are summarized in Table VIII. Over 80% of the particles from disintegrated  shale occur as fine silt or coarse clay. With this information, the particle-size  distribution of the reference base can be corrected for shale disintegration so  that a reconstruction can be computed which will remove the effects of shale  disintegration from the calculated gains and losses. This not only permits an    12  TABLE VII  Content and particle-size of acid-insoluble residues in carbonates of glacial deposits in Ohio    Carbonate  size-fraction    Particle size of residues  (% of carbonate size fraction)    silt        clay    2--16 mm           2--5      1--3  Sand                10--40     3--15  Silt             --     6--20    TABLE VIII  Particle-size distribution of shale, which passes a 50-am sieve after sonification,  collected from three Ohio soils    Soil           Silt (%)                                 Clay (%)    50--20 am      20--2 am     5--2 am      2--0.2 am    &lt; 0.2 am  Brookston         9                55             24             29             7  Pewamo         10               53            22            30            7  Hoytville          9               53            20            31            7    evaluation of the effects of shale disintegration on particle-size distribution of  resultant softs but allows partitioning clay gains or losses to other processes  without obfuscation by shale disintegration. An example of a reconstruction  which removes the effects of shale disintegration from calculated gains and  losses is shown in Fig. 4. Removing the effects of shale disintegration reduces  the calculated total clay gain somewhat as one would expect because shale  disintegration contributes clay-size particles to the solum. After removing the  effects of both carbonate leaching and shale disintegration, there is an evident  total clay gain in the B horizons of the Hoytville pedon used for illustrative  purposes (Fig. 4) which must be attributed to other processes. In this pedon, clay  translocation appears to be an important process.    SAMPLING AND VARIABILITY CONSIDERATIONS    Variables utilized for reconstruction calculations each contain sampling  and analytical error terms. Figs. 5 and 6 illustrate coefficients of variation  (CV) for bulk density, particle size and elemental parameters sampled within  a pedon. Coefficient of variation is a statistical measure of sample variation  and is defined as sample standard deviation expressed as a percentage of sample  mean. It is appropriate for comparing dispersion of different soil properties  free from scale factors but assumes normal frequency distribution, no co-    13    20    ~" 15  v    10  o  '_~  llz  ~  s    - 37    PEDON VARIABILITY    Total Sand    Range    Total Silt   Total Clay  Bulk Density    Fig.5. Variability of total sand, silt, and clay contents and bulk density due to combined  sampling and analytical errors for five morphologically uniform pedons of about 1 m: area.    PEDON VARIABILITY  20   15                                                              R,,  "6 10  i                 :::::.'~:~?~i~                                     T      nd  T~llt  TI          Zr         Fe         K         Ca  Fig.6. Variability of elemental Ti, Zr, Fe, K, and Ca in sand and silt fractions due to com-  bined sampling and analytical errors for five morphologically uniform pedons of about 1 m2.    variance between the sample mean and standard deviation, and data where  the mean does not approach 0. For the data presented herein, these assump-  tions appear to be closely approximated. For most properties, the CV's average  less than 10% but often range from ~ 5% up to 20%.  The accuracy of reconstruction is determined not only by the three basic  considerations outlined earlier but also by the magnitude of pedon variability.  In the context of this discussion we are considering pedons which exhibit  morphological uniformity over a scale of one to several meters squared. Under  such conditions, one must always be concerned about the representativeness  of the sample collected for a given horizon. In other words, what is the magni-    14    tude of sampling errors? The accuracy of estimating the property mean for a  given horizon is directly proportional to the number of horizon sub-samples  collected laterally within the confines of a pedon. Thus, one way to increase  accuracy is to employ a multiple sub- sampling scheme similar to those illustrated  in Fig. 7; this increases the probability that the sample is representative of    PEDON SAMPLING SCHEMES  Pedon Area 1-10m=  Pedon Sampling Intsrvsl '/a-~m    I   t   I  I   I   I  ---t--~--f--   ', ,,    vv vv    Grid                 Cross                Pit Face    Fig.7. Multiple sub-sampling schemes for sampling pedons.    the horizon in question. Sub-samples may subsequently be composited for  analytical purposes, assuming a measure of soil variability has previously been  established to document probable errors for the sampling scheme employed.  Such sampling schemes are not advocated for pedons that illustrate cyclic or  interrupted horizonation or other kinds of extreme morphological variability.  Using CV values, the probable errors to be expected in reconstruction  analysis can be statistically estimated. Such calculations indicate that the  volume factor and reconstructed gains and losses of clay would yield CV's of  about 10%. This means that if only one sample per horizon is collected, the  probable error about the calculated gain or loss of clay would be about + 20%  (95% confidence interval). On the other hand, if four sub-samples per horizon  are collected, the probable error would be + 10% at the same confidence inter-  val. It is apparent from this discussion that more precise sampling schemes  can greatly increase the sensitivity of reconstruction analysis but even the  most precise sampling scheme will not likely permit identification of differ-  ences in soil development below 5--10%; these values correspond to analyti-  cal errors of property determination.    REFERENCES    Barshad, I., 1955. Soil development. In: F.E. Bear (Editor), Chemistry of the Soil. Reinhold,  New York, N.Y., 373 pp.  Bourne, W.C. and Whiteside, E.P., 1962. A study of the morphology and pedogenesis of a  medial chernozem developed in loess. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 26: 484--490.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 470 pp.  Brewer, R. and Coventry, R.J., 1977. Some aspects of genesis of a Red Earth profile at  Townsville, Queensland. CSIRO Div. Soils Tech. Pap., 32:21 pp.    15    Calhoun, F.G., 1968. A Weathering Characterization of Two Northeastern Ohio Aquic  Fragiudalfs. M.S. thesis, Ohio State Univ., Columbus, Ohio.  Drees, L.R. and Wilding, L.P., 1978. Elemental distribution in the light-mineral isolate  of soil separates. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., J., 42: 976--978.  Evans, L.J., 1978. Quantification and pedological processes. In: Quaternary Soils. Geo-  Abstracts, Norwich.  Evans, L.J. and Adams, W.A., 1975. Quantitative pedological studies on soils derived from  Silurian mudstones, 5. Redistribution and loss of mobilised constituents. J. Soil Sci.,  26: 327--335.  Green, P., 1966. Mineralogical and weathering study of a Red Brown Earth formed on  granodiorite. Aust. J. Soil Res., 4: 181--197.  Khan, D.H., 1959. Studies on translocation of chemical constituents in some Red-Brown  soils, terra rosas, and rendzinas, using zirconium as a weathering index. Soil Sci., 88:  196--200.  Khangarot, A.S., Wilding, L.P. and Hall, G.F., 1971. Composition and weathering of loess-  mantled Wisconsin- and Illinoian-age terraces in central Ohio. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  35: 621--626.  Marshall, C.E. and Haseman, J.F., 1942. The quantitative evaluation of soil formation and  development by heavy-mineral studies: a Grundy silt loam profile. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 7: 448--453.  Mick, A.H., 1949. The pedology of several profiles developed from calcareous drift of  eastern Michigan. Tech. Bull. Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn., 212.  Nikiforoff, C.C. and Drosdoff, M., 1943. Genesis of a clay-pan soil. Soil Sci., 55: 459--482.  Oertel, A.C., 1961. Pedogenesls of some Red-Brown Earths based on trace-element profiles.  J, Soil Sci., 12: 242--258.  Redmond, C.E. and Whiteside, E.P., 1967. Some till-derived Chernozem soils in eastern  North Dakota, 2. Mineralogy, micromorphology, and development. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 31: 100--107.  Ritchie, A., Wilding, L.P., Hall, G.F. and Stahnke, C.R., 1974. Genetic implications of B  horizons in Aqualfs of northeastern Ohio. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 351--358.  Rostad, H.P.W., Smeck, N.E. and Wilding, L.P., 1976. Genesis of argillic horizons in soils  derived from coarse-textured calcareous gravels. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 40: 739--744.  Smeck, N.E. and Runge, E.C.A., 1971. Phosphorus availability and redistribution in relation  to profile development in an Illinois landscape segment. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35:  952--959.  Smeck, N.E., Wilding, L.P. and Holowaychuk, N., 1968. Genesis of argillic horizons in  Celina and Morley soils of western Ohio. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 550--556.  Smith, H. and Wilding, L.P., 1972. Genesis of argillic horizons in Ochraqualfs derived from  fine-textured till deposits of northwestern Ohio and southeastern Michigan. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 808--815.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil taxonomy, a basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. In: Agriculture Handbook, 436. U.S. Government Printing  Office, Washington, D,C.  Wang, C. and Arnold, R.W., 1973. Quantifying pedogenesis for soils with discontinuities.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 37: 271--278.  Wenner, K.A., Holowaychuk, N. and Schafer, G.M., 1961. Changes in the clay content,  calcium carbonate equivalent, and calcium/magnesium ratio with depth in parent  materials of soils derived from calcareous till of Wisconsin age. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  25: 312--316.  Westin, F.C., 1953. Solonetz soils of eastern South Dakota: their properties and genesis.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 17: 287--293.  Wild, A., 1961. Loss of zirconium from 12 soils derived from granite. Aust. J. Agric. Res.,  12: 300--305.    16    Wilding, L.P., Drees, L.R., Smeck, N.E. and Hall, G.F., 1971. Mineral and elemental com-  position of Wisconsin-age till deposits in west-central Ohio. In: Till-- a symposium. Ohio  State Univ. Press, Columbus, Ohio.  Wright, W.R. and Foss, J.E., 1968. Movement of silt-sized particles in sand columns. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 446--448.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      AbstractThe genesis of 24 pedons derived from calcareous glacial deposits in Ohio was studied with quantitative (reconstruction) techniques. This report summarizes refinements in quantitative techniques and discusses problems encountered during those studies.In most of our studies, elemental Zr was employed as the stable index constituent. Unit volume factors, which are based on Zr distribution, were found to be a function of size separates employed for analysis. Therefore, it is suggested that the index constituent should be determined on all fractions &gt; 2 μm in order to provide the most reliable estimations of gains and losses. Elemental ratios of Ti/Zr were employed in our studies as the primary indicators of parent-material uniformity; however, additional lines of evidence are advisable because: (1) micro-occlusions of rutile and zircon have been found in host light minerals, (2) elemental Ti exhibits depth distributions indicative of weathering trends, and (3) Ti is preferentially lost from gravel and sand due to the disintegration of shale. Calculated particle-size distribution in the reference base supposing carbonate removal and/or shale disintegration can be employed to partition computed clay gains and losses to such processes as attrition of sand- and gravel-size shale, carbonate leaching, in situ neoformation of clay, and clay translocation. Sub-sampling can greatly increase the sensitivity of reconstruction analysis, but even the most precise sampling scheme will not permit identification of differences in soil development below 10%. 