Geoderma, 29 (1983) 373--374                                                  373  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Review    Benchmark Soils of India -- Morphology, Characteristics and Classification  for Resource Management. R.S. Murthy, L.R. Hirekerur, S.B. Deshpande  and B.V. Venkata Rao (Editors) and H.S. Shankaranarayana (Project  Coordinator). National Bureau of Soil Survey and Land Use Planning,  Nagpur, 1982, 374 pp.    The occasion for publication of this book was the 12th International  Congress of Soil Science held at New Delhi, India, in February 1982. In  preparation for the Congress, a major effort was made to gather and publish  information on representative soils of India so as to make that available to  participating soil scientists.  Subdivision of the book into two main parts readily follows from the sub-  ject matter and its arrangement. The first main part, after a two-page intro-  duction, consists of four chapters (101 pages) of general information. The  second main part (369 pages) comprises detailed information on the 64  series selected at benchmark soils.  The first main part consists largely but not entirely of background infor-  mation for the second. The first chapter covers physiography, climate,  natural vegetation and land use. The second chapter has two sections, one on  the factors of soil formation and the other comprising single-paragraph de-  scriptions of the benchmark series. The discussion of soil formation is ar-  ranged by regions, seven in all, and is couched in traditional terms. The third  chapter offers a brief explanation of micromorphology and indicates the  kinds of observations made on samples from the benchmark soils. The fourth  chapter is about the applications of soil survey data in land use planning.  The second main part constitutes two-thirds of the book and provides  detailed information on each of the 64 benchmark soil series. Sites at which  the softs were described and sampled are shown on a page-size map of India.  The detailed information on each series then follows, with the series grouped  according to the seven regions used in the earlier discussion of soil forma-  tion. The same information is arranged in the same sequence for all series,  thus facilitating comparisons.  The information consists of: (1) placement of the series in the American  soil taxonomy; (2) a chart to show precipitation, temperature and water  balance; (3) general characteristics and occurrence of the soils; (4) detailed  description of a pedon; (5) remarks on micromorphology; (6) statements  about ranges in characteristics, drainage and permeability, native vegetation,  use, distribution and extent; (7) interpretative groupings and yield estimates;  and (8) laboratory characterization by horizons for the typifying profiles.  Included among the laboratory characterization data are particle size distri-  bution, organic carbon, carbonates if present, pH, electrical conductivity,  bulk density, water retention, micronutrient levels, extractable bases, cation    374    exchange capacities, base saturation, and mineralogy of clay fractions.  The book provides a substantial body of information, much of it detailed,  about important soils of India. The book should thus be a useful reference  for those wanting knowledge of the soil resources of the country.    ROY W. SIMONSON  (College Park, MD)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  