Geoderma, 26 (1981) 83--94                                                       83  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE INTERPRETATION AND CLASSIFICATION OF FEATURES PRO-  DUCED BY PELECYPODS (MOLLUSCA) IN MARINE INTERTIDAL DE-  POSITS IN THE NETHERLANDS    M. J. KOOISTRA  Department of Soil Micromorphology, Soil Survey Institute, Wageningen (The Netherlands)  (Received June 17, 1980; accepted March 16, 1981)    ABSTRACT  Kooistra, M. J., 1981. The interpretation and classification of features produced by  pelecypods (MoUusca) in marine intertidal deposits in The Netherlands. Geoderma,  26: 83--94.  Marine sediments in the southwestern Netherlands, situated between Mean Low Tide  level and highest levels reached by salt water, were sampled systematically. Evidence for  pedogenic processes occurring in these sediments has been examined and preservation of  the effects of these processes in reclaimed soils were studied. The principal technique was  the micromorphological study of large thin sections (8 x 15 cm). The fauna was respon-  sible for a large variety of features, many of them complex. A group of these features, pro-  duced by peiecypods, which are very persistent and common phenomena in polder soils,  were studied in detail. The occurrence of these animals is largely restricted to intertidal  fiats, where high populations can be found.  The features produced by pelecypods could be ascribed to three basic movements of the  animals namely: downward, upward and lateral. Differences in these three basic patterns  are indications of the species which produced them.  The majority of the features due to the activity of pelecypods and present in thin sec-  tions cannot be described according to existing micromorphological classifications. As there  is still insufficient knowledge about micromorphological features due to animal activities  to permit defining new concepts, modifications of existing concepts and descriptive terms  are proposed.    INTRODUCTION  A study of soil-forming processes occurring during development of coastal  accretions before reclamation was carried out since 1972. Representative sed-  iments between Mean Low Tide level and highest levels reached by salt water  (the intertidal zone) were sampled systematically to trace existing processes  and to establish relationships between these processes and tidal levels. Secondly,  attention was paid to the preservation of the effects of these processes in re-  claimed polder soils. This research was restricted to marine sediments in the  southwestern part of The Netherlands. In brackish or fresh-water sediments,  the chemical processes, flora and fauna are different.    84    The principal technique was micromorphological study of large thin sections  (8 15 cm). The features present in the thin sections were due to physical,  chemical and biological processes. The fauna were responsible for a great vari-  ety of features, many of them complicated. In this paper the interpretation and  classification is treated of a group of complicated features produced by  pelecypods. These features are very persistent and in polder soils they can be  distinguished for at least several centuries.    PELECYI~'ODS AND THEIR ENVIRONMENT    Pelecypods are bivalves of the phylum Mollusca and their occurrence in in-  tertidal zones is restricted to the intertidal-flat deposits. Intertidal flats occupy  the lowest part of the intertidal zone and are bare, slightly undulating flats dis-  sected by a few gullies.  The marine intertidal-flat deposits in the southwestern part of The Nether-  lands consist largely o f fine-grained sands with a maximum of 10% o f clay. The  deposits are finely laminated as a rule, with succesive layers differing in granu-  lometric composition. Laminae composed only of clay minerals do not exist.  The finest grained laminae are largely composed of clay minerals but include a  limited number of organic and mineral particles of 2--30 #m in diameter, re-  flecting the composition of the marine suspended matter that built up these  laminae (Kooistra, 1978). When this clay-rich material has a consistency  ranging from semi-fluid to soft and plastic, it is called mud (Gary et al., 1973).  The intertidal-flat deposits are loosely packed and have a high initial water con-  tent.  The environmental conditions in the intertidal flats set many limits for per-  manent macrofauna. The fauna must be adapted to: (1) continuous fluctua-  tions from wet to dry; (2) extreme and rapid changes of temperature; (3) large  differences in amounts of oxygen and salt~ and (4) the force of water {waves  and tidal currents) and resulting deposition or erosion (Kooistra, 1978). Al-  though few forms of life are adapted to these extreme conditions, the popula-  tions of fauna are often very large. The most important species present belong  to the Mollusca, Vermes and Crustacea (Wolff, 1973).  Most of the pelecypods present are true burrowing forrls which are normal-  ly active below the surface. They are to a greater or lesser degree sessile. The  depth at which pelecypods occur ranges from one centimetre below the surface  for Card ium edule to about 30 cm for Mya arenaria. These animals have siphons  reaching the surface which, depending on the species, are separated or fused.  According to the classification of faunal feeding habits {Hunt, 1925; Sanders  et al., 1962}, most pelecypods are suspension-feeders and/or selective deposit-  feeders. Suspension-feeders filter suspended matter from the sea water during  flood tides, whereas selective deposit-feeders choose clay-rich fine-grained ma-  terial at or below the surface. Both groups of organisms feed on organic matter  (e.g. algae and diatoms) that occurs separately or bound to mineral matter.  Cardium edule {cockle), for example, is a true suspension-feeder whereas  Macoma balthica practices both feeding habits.    85    The excrements of pelecypods are as a rule well shaped pellets, which are  more compact than the surrounding sediment. These excrements have an or-  gano-mineral composition which reflects the mode of feeding of the animal.  Excrements are composed of compacted mud, only clay-sized material or a  mixture of sand and mud.  The depth of the animal below the surface, separation of the siphons and  composition and shape of the excrements are important for identification of  the species from features present in thin sections.    METHODS    The determination and interpretation of the effects of pelecypods on soil  material were based on: (1) the literature {e.g. Sch~ifer, 1962; Moore, 1969;  Reineck and Singh, 1973; Frey, 1975); (2) many field observations; and (3) evi.  dence from large, vertically and horizontally taken thin sections. Samples for  thin sections were taken from present-day and buried intertidal-flat deposits  present below salt-marsh sediments and in polder soils. These samples were  processed to thin sections according to the method described by Jongerius and  Heintzberger (1975). Using this method, slices (8 15 2 cm) of undisturbed  soil material were freeze-dried, impregnated with a plastic, hardened, sawn and  ground into 15 ~m thick sections mounted on glass slides. The animals were  studied in the field in two ways. Their activities were examined by excavation  without disturbing their original positions. The animals were also removed and  placed on the surface so that their actions could then be observed.    INTERPRETATION OF THE MICROMORPHOLOGICAL FEATURES    General    The pelecypods are responsible for a large variety of characteristic features  in the sediment. The main features are given in Fig. 1. Most features consist  of two different elements, namely (1) channels above the animal andreachina  to the surface, and (2) features consisting of soil material with a generally dis-  tinct external form and a strial configuration. In a strial configuration the direc.  tional arrangement is semi-ellipsoidal, related to the external form of the fea-  ture.  (1) The channels are formed by the siphons of the animal. As these siphons  are separated or fused, single or double channels occur. The sediment in the  intertidal zone is loosely packed and unstable when disturbed. In order to pre-  vent collapse, the channels are often coated, almost certainly by the animals  themselves, with clay-rich material. Distinctly shaped excrements are some-  times found embedded in these coatings. The excrements are ellipsoidal or  cylindrical (Bal, 1973) and are more compact than sedimentary mud material  (Kooistra, 1978). Similar coatings are also known from channels produced by  species of Vermes (Doeksen and Minderman, 1963; Reineck and Singh, 1973).    86  A          13         C         D              E1            E2   E3     E4 surface  ._  ..  x                                      ~[I        o    II   X'          ~' ~'l        ~.,.,~    .,  .,  "~      y :'~,~,;       ,...   Y'  x      A            g          C           D      x'        x"                  ,~.  0                                                                          "     y    A        B     y'         y"  .-                                                                                                  ~,,~ : void  O                   .~      -~..,,,~.       .               -~  ,~  ....  o :excrement  z          ,  ,  ,                 ,I       .    ".  -                           ~ '    %                                 ,  ZOne fth distinctly larger  amount of clay rich matericl    Fig. 1. Schematic sections of features produced by pelecypods. Vertical sections: A, B  result of upward movement" C, D result of downward movement; E1--4 results of lateral move.  ment. Horizontal sections: x--x', x" cross-sections of features due to vertical movements,  taken above the animal; y y', y" cross-sections of features due to vertical movements,  taken beneath the animal; z--z' cross-sections of features due to lateral movements.    (2) The features consisting of soil material with a generally distinct tubular  external form are produced by the movement of the animals. A bivalve mollusc  moves by repeated movements of its foot over short distances. During these  movements, soil material is pressed alongside its body and redeposited in a  strial configuration behind it. These features usually contain more clay-rich  material than the surrounding sediment due to the addition of clearly recog-  nimble excrements. The excrements may be embedded in mud striae, some of  which may be composed entirely of oriented individual excrements.  The tubular features in the vertical sections are the result o f: (1) upward  movement of the ~mimal (Fig. 1, A and B), mainly to keep pace with continuing  sedimentation; (2) downward movement of the animal (Fig. 1, C and D), be-  cause of erosion, because the animal migrates and retreats deeper into the sedi-  ment or because of growth of the animal; (3) lateral movement of the animal  (Fig. 1, E 1--4), often due to local disturbance or instability of the sediment.  Features in vertical sections (Fig. 1, upper part)  The striae in the tubular features can be very finely laminated {Fig. 2). Due  to the different shapes of the shells and differences in shape and position of  the foot of an animal {Moore, 1969), the curves of the striae are not always  centered in the middle of the tubular feature.    87  The "tubular" features are not always strictly tubular (see Fig. 1, B and Fig. 3)  During upward movement animals may rotate on their long axis, and if the  mollusc's valves differ in width and length or are asymmetrical they produce  striae of different sizes. Such is the case with Scrobicularia plana and Mya  arenaria. When the valves have slight differences in width and length, true tu-  bular features are produced. No differences in width of the striae are observed  in the tubular features due to downward and lateral movements.  When, under special conditions, thick deposits are formed in a short time,  the animal has to move upwards quickly. In these cases, tubular features are  formed which lack distinct external boundaries.  Cr~ss-sections of horizontal tubular features are given in Fig. 1, E 2--4.  They c,:~nsist of circular to ellipsoidal zones of clay-rich material in which ex-  crements can be embedded. Depending on the location of the section, one or  two clay-rich zones are present.    .i :~~".~~~'~.~,~. ::'-4~~'?~..* ,:,::"  Fig. 2. Striotubule due to upward movement with fine internal lamination. Recent inter-  tidal-flat deposits.    88    i~a~     Fig. 3. Striotubulic feature produced by Mya arenaria in which the difference in width of  the pedotubule corresponds to a rotation on the long axis.  The tubular features that have a largely vertical orientation (Fig. 1, A, B, C  and D) are the most pronounced due to perpendicular crossing of the laminae  of the sediment. Although these tubular features are mostly vertical, some are  inclined slightly.  The chmmels and tubular features of soil material noted above in vertical  section may occur separately (Fig. 1, A, B, E1 and E4) or in combinations  (Fig. 1, C and D}. When the two phenomena are combined, complex features  result. In slightly inclined tubular features, the siphonal channels may cross  the reverse striations near the edge of the feature, thereby increasing the com-  plexity.    89    Features in horizontal sections (Fig. 1, lower part)  In horizontal sections channels and tubular features of soil material are also  found. The cross-sections of the channels are circular to ellipsoidal. The chan-  nels are often coated with clay-rich material. The cross-sections of the tubular  features are comparable to the cross-sections of the vertical tubular strial fea-  tures (see Fig. 4) but there are two additional aspects in the former, namely  (1) that the two strial zopes may be elongated in different directions due to  the rotation of the animal (Fig. 1, y--y'B); (2) due to the different positions  of the foot the strial zG.nes need not be centered in the middle of the feature.  Cross-sections containing only one strial zone also occur (Fig. 1, y", Fig. 4).  Combinations of channels and the tubular features are given in Fig. 1, x--x'  C and D: fused siphons giving rise to a single channel, separated ones giving  rise to two channels. In Fig. 1, x" the channel is not centered due to a slight  inclination of the vertical, tubular strial feature. In Fig. 1, z--z' two longitudinal  sections of a horizontal tubular feature with different widths are given and in  Fig. 4 a longitudinal section of a horizontal tubular feature with faint striae  can be seen.        ~2.~crrl~  ...... ,[~i:!  ......  Fig. 4. Horizontal. section of a recent intertidal-flat deposit showing two cross-sections of  vertical striotubulLes, one eonsksting of one strial zone (right lower corner) and one con-  taining two strial zones (left upper eorner), and a longitudinal section of a horizontal  tubular feature crossing the picture from left to right. This tubular feature has only faint  striae composed of oriented excrements.    90    Conch:sion  Pelecypods produce a large variety of features, many of them complex. In  spite of the~.~ variability and complexity they all point to three basic kinds of  movement cf the animals, namely: upward, downward and lateral.  The features due to pelecypods are both common and characteristic of de-  posits in intertidal flats. The features due to pelecypods and evident in thin  sections can be used for identification of the species. From evidence in thin  sections info, mation about length, width and depth of the tubular features,  sizes and ratios of the shells, position of the foot and whether siphons are  fused or not can be obtained. When excrements are present they add informa-  tion on size, shape and composition. The composition reflects the way of  feeding: suspension feeding and/or selective deposit feeding. As locally high  concentrations of the same species occur, many of the features present in one  or more adjoining thin sections are produced by the same species. Combinations  of features provide a great deal of essential information about one species and  this species can often then be identified.  Pelecypod features in intertidal-flat deposits become, due to compaztion,  more pronounced when covered with younger sediments. In polder soils, buried  beneath salt-marsh sediments, they remain virtually unchanged for centuries  if not disturbed by cultivation. An example of two open siphonal channels,  more than 260 years old, in a horizontal thin section is given in Fig. 5.  Only rarely are features due to pelecypods found which are not tubular. In  Fig. 6 an example produced by Cardium eclule is given. The animal has mainly       .    Fig. 5. Horizontal section through siphonal channels of a pelecypod, probably Scrobicularia  plan,.~ in a polder soil ca. 260 years after reclamation.    91    Fig. 6. Horizontal section through a non-tubular feature produced by Cardium edule in  recent intertidal-flat deposits. The darker coloured material is derived from pseudo-faeces  and excrements deposited within the sediment by the animal itself.    moved sideways over small distances, adding pseudo-faeces and excrements to  the sediment. Pseudo-faeces are compressed, undigested sedimentary materials,  often clay-rich, leaving the animal by the inhalant siphon.    CLASSIFICATION OF THE MICROMORPHOLOGICAL FEATURES    Classification according to existing micromorphological systems    The majority of the features due to the activity of pelecypods and visible  in thin sections can not be described within existing systems. A s~Lrvey is given  below.  The siphonal channels are described as channels and their mud coatings as  cutans in the Brewer system (i964). Depending on their composition, they  can be classified as a plasman-skeletan (Bal, 1973) which is a cutan composed  of a mixture of plasma (~ 2/~m} and skeleton grains; although this term is not  completely satisfactory because the composition of the mud (see Introduction)  as basic sedimentary material is ignored. These cutans are not argillans (Brewer,  1964} because they do not consist of clay alone. They are also not matraus  (Bal, 1973) because the sediment is laminated and composed of sand as well  as mud laminae; nor are they plasmans (Bal, loc.cit. ) because the mud includes  some fine particles !. 30 urn.    92    The features consisting of soil mater:~l with a generally tubular form, a rela-  tively sharp external boundary and a strml configuration are pedotubules  {Brewer, 1964). Although they look like typical striotubules they cannot be  so classified because they contain recognisable aggregates in the form of ex-  crements, and according to Brewer ,,striotubules contain no evidence of faunal  activity". Th.ey are not scatotubules or modexotubules (Bal, 197 3) as only  part of the soil material is organised into recognisable aggregates. The features  of soil material shown in Fig. 1, B, C and D cannot be classified by any known  system. No classification is possible either if the features ccnsisting of soil mate.  rial do not have relatively sharp external boundaries.  The cross-section of a feature with a strial configuration without cross-sec-  tions of siphonal channels does not fit Brewer's definitions of glaebules.  When the cross-sectional features have one siphonal channel they may be  classified as a form of sub-cutanic feature (Brewer, 1964), similar to quasi-  cutans, but because the channel shows no relationship to the generally concen-  tric rings of clay-rich material, they are not true quasi-cutans. When the cross-  sectional features are crossed by two channels (Fig. 1, x--x'D) the resulting  feature cannot be classified within existing systems.    Proposed classification of the micromorphological features    Pelecypods produce a number of different features of which only ~.he siphon-  al channels can be correctly classified according to existing systems. There is  a need for a system by ~vhich the features can be classified. The following are  possibilities: (1) pule descriptive terms; (2) pure genetic terms or (3) a mixture  of these. As it is not reasonable to introduce a new terminology for a small  group of animals, the following modifications to existing terminology are pro-  posed.  As the tubular features with strial configurations are perfect examples of  ~riotubules except that they contain excrements, it is proposed that Brewer's  current definition of striotubules be modified to read: "Pedotubules composed  of skeleton grains and plasma, which only to a minor extent can be organised  into recognisable aggregates, but exhibit a basic fabric with a directional ar-  rangement related to the external form. The directional arrangement is semi-  ellipsoidal with the walls of the pedotubule approximately tangential to the  semi-ellipsoid."  The feature shown in Fig. 1, B, resulting from the rotation along the long  axis of an animal with valves of different lengths and widths, can be described  as a striotubulic feature. In the same way, the features in Fig. 1, C and D, can  be described as striotubules with channels. All the sections through the differ-  ent striotubules can be characterised by indicating that they are a cross- or  longitudinal section of a vertical~horizontal striotubule, with or without chan-  nel(~}, together with information on the number of clay-rich zones, shape of  the rings, and the number and position of channel cross-sections. The cutans  of clay-rich material can best be defined as cutans composed of mud. As these    93    cutans are the result of animal activity, it is proposed that they be defined as  zoocutans (Kooistra, 1978) to distinguish them from illuviation cutans. They  would, in fact, be mud-zoocutans. When the tubular features produced by  pelecypods lack a distinct external boundary, they are not pedotubules. In  these cases the strial configuration is often absent and it is proposed to indicate  these phenomena as passage features (Kooistr~, 1978).    Conclusion    Features produced by pelecypods are common in intertidal flat deposits and  remain virtually unchanged after reclamation. As about 30% of the total area  of the Netherlands has been reclaimed from m~ine deposits, the features pro-  duced by pelecypods are common phenomena in the soils. For this reason, it  is important to indicate them properly. Most features could not be described  according to existing micromorphological classifications, but there are several  possibilities to describe the features. As there is still insufficient knowledge  about many micromorphological features due to animal activities, the features  are indicated with descriptive terms added to existing systems. With knowledge  of the interpretation of the features they can be adequately described with  redefinition of Brewers term 'striotubule' and the use of a few descriptive and  new terms. Only after ample research on features produced by animals, can  new concepts be defined satisfactorily.    REFERENCES    I~d, L., 1973. Micromorphological Analysis of Soils. Ser. Soil Surv. Pap. No. 6, Netherlands  Soil Survey Institute, Wageningen.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y.  l)~eksen, J. and Minderman, G., 1963. Typical soil structures as the result of the activities  of mudworms. In: J. Doeksen and J. van der Drift (Editors), Soil Organisms. Proceedings  of the Colloquium on Soil Fauna, Soil Microfauna and Their Relationships. North-Holland,  Amsterdam, pp. 134--137.  Frey, R. W., (Editor), 1975. The Study of Trace Fossils. A Synthesis of Principles, Problems  and Procedures in Ichnology. Springer, Berlin.  Gary, M., McAfee Jr., R. and Wolf, C. L. (Editors), 1973. Glossary of Geology. American  Geological Institute, Washington D.C.  Hunt, O. D., 1925. The food of the bottom fauna of the Plymouth fishing grounds. J. Mar.  Biol.Ass.U.K., 13: 560--599.  Jongerius, A. and Heintzberger, G., 1975. Methods in Soil Micromorphology. A Technique  for the Preparation of Large Thin Sections. Soil Surv. Pap. No. 10. Netherlands Soil  Survey Institute, Wageningen.  Kooistra, M. J., 1978. Soil Development in Recent Marine Sediments of the Intertidal Zone  in the Oosterschelde, The Netherlands. A Soil Micromorphological Approach. Soil Surv.  Pap. No. 14. Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, Wageningen.  Moore, R. C. (Editor), 1969. Treatise on Invertebrate Paleontology. Part N. The Geological  Society of America, Inc. and the University of Kansas, Boulder, Colo.  Reineck, H. E. and Singh, I. B., 1973. Depositional Sedimentary Environments. Springer,  Berlin.    94    Sanders, H. L., Goudsmit, E. M., Mills, E.L. and Hampson, G.E., 1962. A study of the inter  tidal fauna of Barnstable Harbor, Mass. Limnol. Oceanogr., 7 : 63--79.  Schgfer, W., 1962. Actuo-pal~iontologie nach Studien in der Nordsee. Waldemar Kramer,  Frankfurt am Main.  Wolff, W.J., 1973. The Estuary as a Habitat. An Analysis of Data on the Soft-Bottom  Macrofauna of the Estuarine Area of the Rivers Rhine, Meuse and Scheldt. Zoologische  Verhandelingen No. 126, Brill, Leiden.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractMarine sediments in the southwestern Netherlands, situated between Mean Low Tide level and highest levels reached by salt water, were sampled systematically. Evidence for pedogenic processes occurring in these sediments has been examined and preservation of the effects of these processes in reclaimed soils were studied. The principal technique was the micromorphological study of large thin sections (8 × 15 cm). The fauna was responsible for a large variety of features, many of them complex. A group of these features, produced by pelecypods, which are very persistent and common phenomena in polder soils, were studied in detail. The occurrence of these animals is largely restricted to intertidal flats, where high populations can be found.The features produced by pelecypods could be ascribed to three basic movements of the animals namely: downward, upward and lateral. Differences in these three basic patterns are indications of the species which produced them.The majority of the features due to the activity of pelecypods and present in thin sections cannot be described according to existing micromorphological classifications. As there is still insufficient knowledge about micromorphological features due to animal activities to permit defining new concepts, modifications of existing concepts and descripitive terms are proposed.