Geoderma, 30 (1983) 271--275                                                         271  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    QUANTIMET 720 ANALYSIS OF POROSITIES IN BACKSCATTERED  ELECTRON SCANNING IMAGES MADE WITH DIFFERENT PHOTO-  TECHNIQUES    D SCHOONDERBEEK', F. THIEL2 and E.B.A. BISDOM'  1Netherlands Sod Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  2Techmcal and Physical Engmeerzng Research Service, 6700 AJ Wagenzngen  (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Schoonderbeek, D., Thml, F. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1983. Quantimet 720 analysis of  porosities m backscattered electron scanning images made with different photo-techni-  ques. Geoderma, 30: 271--275.    Three photo-techniques were used to make backscattered electron scanning images  (BESI) of the same area in a thin section of soil using a scanning electron microscope  (SEM). Subsequent porosity analysis with an image analyzer (Quantimet 720) showed  that different results could be obtained in a number of diameter classes while the total  porosity was virtually the same, a phenomenon which may be related to beam instability  of SEM. Under such conditions, one needs a dependable photo-technique in which soil  constituents on a BESI micrograph can be compared with the same constituents on the  display screen of SEM and Quantimet. Such a photo-technique is suggested and can be  used to obtain a limited number of measurable BESI micrographs.    INTRODUCTION    Larger pores in thin sections can be measured and characterized by a com-  bination of hght microscopic and Quanhmet techniques (Jongerlus et al.,  1972, Jongerius, 1974; Ismail, 1975; Bouma et al., 1977; Murphy et al.,  1977). The image analyzer can analyse voids with diameters larger than 30  um in structure photograms made with transmitted light. Smaller voids can-  not be measured using this technique due to the thickness of a thin section  which is usually about 30 pm or less.  Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) can be used for the por-  trayal of mmrovoids and larger, because information is predominantly ob-  tained from a thin layer at a depth of a few micrometres below the surface  of a thin section (Bisdom and Thlel, 1981). BESI can therefore be used to  measure both smaller and larger pores (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). In  practice, pores smaller than 100 um are measured on BESI by Quantimet.  Larger pores can also be analysed in this way but it is more economical to do  this using light microscopic and Quantimet techniques.    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevier Science Pubhshers B.V.    272    The present paper discusses the variation in porosity measurements with  the Quantlmet 720 on BESI made with different photo-techniques and with  a SEM in which beam instability occurred. This study has been performed to  obtmn a dependable photo-technique which allows porosity analysis from a  small number of BESI micrographs under such conditmns.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Backscattered electron scanning images were obtained using different  photo-techniques from the same area m a thin section of a ploughpan de-  veloped in sandy loam of southwest Netherlands. BESI were made with a  Jeol-JSM-35C scanning electron microscope equipped with a backscattered  electron detector of the semi-conductor type contammg two solid state de-  tectors. BESI can be made on film, photographic paper, or both.  Quantimet 720 analysis of porosities in thm sections of soils is usually  done from film negatives or positives. The input to the Quantlmet of such  film is done via a light mmroscope or an epidiascope. Photographic paper  can be used as a control, to compare images from the film on the display  screen of the Quantlmet. In the present case, three different photo-techni-  ques were used to obtain BESI on a film; with or without paper prints as a  control.  The first photo-technique revolved a 24 mm 36 mm negative from  Ilford Pan F. No paper print was made. The second method used a 9 cm  12 cm positive and a paper print made from the small film negative obtained  with the first technique. Polaroid 55 P/N film was used m the third techm-  que in which a negative as well as a 9 cm 12 cm paper print was obtained.  For the Quantimet measurements, the mlcrographs obtained with these  three techniques from the same area in a thin section, were subdivided into  a number of fields.    RESULTS    The area of which the porosity was studmd by Quantimet ts given m Fig.  1. The ongmal magnification of the BESI micrograph, made with the third  technique on Polaroid 55 P/N film, was 100. Such an enlargement is re-  latively low for submicroscopm work but is sufficient to include capillary  pores which have a diameter of 30 um or less (Table I). If smaller pores axe  also of interest, larger magnifications can be made until a maximum is reached.  The maximum magnifmation is strongly dependent on the type of material  being investigated in the thin section and on the posslbdlties of the back-  scattered electron detector system of the SEM used.  For measurements by Quantimet the area on BESI was subdivided into  four fields on the small film negative of 24 mm 36 mm (first photo-tech-  tuque) and into twenty-four fmlds on the positives and negative of 9 cm  12 cm (second and third techmque). An average of all Quantlmet measure-  ments, done on BESI at X 100 and with the three techmques, is given m    273    Fig. 1. BESI of a microarea in a ploughpan which was used to test different photo-techni-  ques    Table I. In this table seven pore diameter classes are presented together with  their porosities and the total porosity of all the voids measured. The smallest  pores analysed had a diameter of 0.3 urn, while the largest diameters were  more than 100 ~m.  Measurements of the porosity on the enlarged 9 cm 12 cm positive  (second photo-technique) were different from the porosity measurements ob-  tained with techniques one and three (Table I). The measured total porosity  was 30.9% instead of 23.5% or 23.6%. This is a large difference which must  be due to enlargement of the negative of 24 mm 36 mm to a positive of  9 cm X 12 cm. Apparently, the area occupied by black to grey colours in-  creases significantly on the positive film during enlargement.  The total porosity on the 24 mm X 36 mm negative film (photo-technique  no. 1) is 23.5% and hardly differs from the total porosity measured with  technique no. 3. Both techniques,*however, show differences of porosities m  a number of diameter classes. For example, from 3.0 to 6.0 gm and 6.0 to  15.0 ~m. Such differences in porosity measurements may be related to beam  instability of the SEM which is being used.  If the Polaroid 55 P/N film of photo-technique no. 3 is used, we obtain  simultaneously a paper print and a film negative of 9 cm 12 cm. This paper  print can be used directly to determine the quality of BESI and subsequently  to control the detection and measurements by Quantimet 720. The result is  that one has controlled Quantimet measurements from BESI that are of  a good quality. Such control is not possible with technique no. 1 in which    274  TABLE I  Quantimet measurements on BESI (100) of the porosity of the same microarea by  three different photo-techniques    Photo-techniques         Diameter classes       Poros,ty     Total porosity  (~m)               (%)        (%)    No. 1 24ram 36mm  negative -- Ilford  Pan F    0.30--  0.90           0 1         23 5  0.91-- 3 00       0 9  3.01-- 6.00       37  6.01-- 15 00           2.6  15.01-- 30.00         7.0  30.01--100.00         8.3  &gt; 100 00         0 9    No. 2 9cm12cm  pos,tlve and paper  print -- enlargement  of the small film  negative obtained  with photo-technique  no 1    0.30--  0.90          0.1  0.91-- 3 00       2 0  3.01--  6.00           9.0  6.01-- 15.00           1.8  15 01r  30.00          10.0  30.01--100.00                      8.0  &gt; 100.00       0 0    30 9    No. 3' 9cm12cm  direct negat,ve and  paper print - Polaroid  55 P/N    030-- 090       0.1      23 6  0.91-  3 oo           0 6  3 01- 6.00       5 1  6.01- 15.00           09  15  01-  30.00                      6  7  30.01-100.00           8.9  ,100.00           1 3    only negatives are used. It was also demonstrated that enlarged positives or  paper prints (9 cm X 12 cm) of photo-technique no. 2, obtained from the  24 mm X 36 mm negatives (photo-technique no. 1), did not give dependable  porosity measurements. Consequently, we prefer to work with Polaroid 55  P/N film if a scanning electron microscope is used in whmh beam instability  may occur.    CONCLUSIONS    If a SEM is used which, due to beam instability, can cause problems in the  production of constant high quality micrographs, a controlling photo-tech-  nique should be used. Such control can be exerted by using a Polaroid 55  P/N film (photo-technique no. 3) in which both negative and paper print are  9 cm X 12 cm. On the paper print, one can observe whether this BESI micro-  graph is of a good quality and compare it with what is visible on the display  screen of the SEM. The same BESI paper print is subsequently used to check  the image on the display screen, often called display, of the Quantimet 720.  Enlarged 9 cm X 12 cm film and paper print (photo-technique no. 2),  from a 24 mm X 36 mm negative, did not give accurate porosity measure-    275    ments due to photographic processing. Quantlmet measurements done on a  small film negative (photo-techmque no. 1) gave a similar total porosity mea-  surement to the one found with the Polaroid 55 P/N film (photo-technique  no. 3). Differences existed, however, m porosltms of a number of diameter  classes. Under such conditions, possibly due to beam instability, photo-tech-  nique no. 3 is preferred. Only a limited number of htgh quahty BESI micro-  graphs can be obtained with photo-technique no. 3. If a large quantity of  BESI rmcrographs is requtred, equipment for beam stabilization is necessary  m the SEM. Under such condltmns, one can also work with photo-technique  no. 1 using 24 mm 36 mm negatives of Ilford Pan F or another film.    REFERENCES    Bmdom, E.B.A. and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of poromtms  m thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil-gas reservolr rocks using SEM-EDXRA.  In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Work-  shop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soll  Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agrmultural Publishing and Docu-  mentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A., Boersma, O., Jager, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1977. The func-  tion of different types of macropores during saturated flow through four swelling soil  horizons. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41 (5). 945--950.  Ismail, S.N.A., 1975. Micromorphometric soil-porosity characterization by means of  electro-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720)  Neth. Soil Surv. Inst. Wageningen,  Soil. Surv. Pap., 9:104 pp.  Jongerius, A., 1974. Recent developments in soil micromorphology In: G.K. Rutherford  (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proceedings of the 4th International Working-Meeting on  So:l Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp  67--83.  Jongerius, A. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981 Porosity measurements using the Quantimet  720 on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In: E.B.A.  Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the  International  Working-Group  on  Submicroscopy  of Undisturbed Soil Materials  (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documenta-  tion (Pudoc), Wageningen. pp. 207--216.  Jongerius, A., Schoonderbeek, D. and Jager, A., 1972. The applicatlon of the Quantimet  720 in soil micromorphology. The Microscope, 20: 243--254.  Murphy, C.P. Bullock, P. and Turner, R.H., 1977. The measurement and charactensatlon  of voids in soll thin sections by image analysm, Part I. Principles and techmques. J.  Soil Sci, 28 (3)' 498--508.                                                                AbstractThree photo-techniques were used to make backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) of the same area in a thin section of soil using a scanning electron microscope (SEM). Subsequent porosity analysis with an image analyzer (Quantimet 720) showed that different results could be obtained in a number of diameter classes while the total porosity was virtually the same, a phenomenon which may be related to beam instability of SEM. Under such conditions, one needs a dependable photo-technique in which soil constituents on a BESI micrograph can be compared with the same constituents on the display screen of SEM and Quantimet. Such a photo-technique is suggested and can be used to obtain a limited number of measurable BESI micrographs.