 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 55--64                                                      55  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in the Netherlands    ETCHED THIN SECTIONS FOR COUPLED OPTICAL AND ELECTRON  MICROSCOPY AND MICRO-ANALYSIS~    L.D. NORTON, J.M. BIGHAM, G.F HALL, and N.E. SMECK  Department of Agronomy, The Ohio State Unwersity, Columbus, Ohio (U.S.A )  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Norton, L.D., Bigham, J.M., Hall, G.F., and Smeck, N.E., 1983. Etched thin sections  for coupled optical and electron microscopy and micro-analysis Geoderma,  30: 55--64.    Coupled use of optical transmission microscopy and SEM--EDXRA in the study  of soil thin sections initially proved difficult because of problems in differentiation  of mineral grains and impregnating medium with the secondary electron detector of  the SEM. It was also difficult to locate the same small micromorphological features  with both techniques, especially when the feature was hidden below the surface of  the thin section. A procedure was developed that included selective dissolution (etching)  of the impregnating medium and is presented here. After etching, many micromor-  phological features could be more easily recognized and those immediately below the  surface were partially exposed. Application of the procedure proved useful in analyzing  bridging plasma too small to identify by optical transmission microscopy that connected  silt grains in fragipan horizons.    INTRODUCTION    Optical transmission microscopy (OTM) is a highly refined tool for  acquiring two-dimensional optical data from soil thin sections; however,  much additional information is often hidden in the 30 #m thickness of the  standard thin section. The scanning electron microscope (SEM) offers  great depth of field and is capable of supplementing OTM analyses with  three-dimensional electron optical data. Unfortunately, the impregnating  resin in soil thin sections severely restricts the retrieval of such information.  The secondary electron detectors employed on most SEM's provide a col-  orless image of the thin section surface with little difference in gray-scale  between soil fabric and impregnating medium. The featureless surface of  the polished thin section makes discrimination of many micromorphological  features with SEM difficult and information on the third-dimension attain-    i The material presented here was given in part before Division S--5 of the Soft Science  Society  of America Meetings,  December  3,  1981  in  Atlanta,  Georgia(USA).    0016--7061/83/$ 03.00 1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam    56    able only with specialized equipment. Certainly, procedures whereby micro-  morphological features in soils could be studmd in thin section by OTM  and then with enhanced relief by SEM would be of considerable value  (Jenkins, 1981).  In a pedologlc study revolving loess-derived soils with fragipans, micro-  morphological examination of thin sections at magnifications of 250  revealed that the fragipans contained plasma connecting silt grains. The  arrangement and size of these plasmic bodies did not facilitate identification  by light optical techniques (Le., refractive mdex, blrefringence, interference  figures, or dlspersmn). Therefore, a methodology was developed whereby  optical techmques and SEM-EDXRA could be coupled to observe and  analyze these and varmus other micromorphologlcal features m thin section  and also observe part of the third dimension.  Similar approaches have been employed by McKeague and Wang (1980)  to successfully determine that A1 complexed with organic matter was the  bonding agent in ortstein horizons of New Brunswmk soils, and by McKeague  and Protz (1980) to show that SI, Fe, and A1 were all present m variable  amounts in the cementing material of dunpans m British Columbia. In  this study, the incorporation of an etching procedure revolving partial  selective dissolution of the impregnatmg medium was found to be ex-  tremely useful.  After etching, overlapping magnifications of the OTM and SEM facil-  itated locating and observing the same features with both instruments, and  EDXRA added further lnformatmn on the elemental composition and  distribution of elements in the soil fabric. The complementary nature  of these techniques (Wlldmg and Geissinger, 1973) enabled the optical  and chemical properties of exposed bndges between skeleton grams in the  fragupan to be determined. The mam emphasis of this article IS to descnbe  the method used and to provide examples related to our study.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Oriented peds taken from excavated soil pits were dried at 95 prior  to impregnation with Scotchcast #3 epoxy resin using a method similar  to that described by Innes and Pluth (1970). The two parts of the resin  heated to 95 were mixed immediately prior to impregnation of the  soil at 4 mm Hg pressure. Vacuum was maintained until bubbling ceased.  The impregnated samples were cured at 95 overnight, cooled, cut into  blocks, and 5 7.5 cm polished thin sections prepared.  After polishing to near 30 /zm the thin sections were left uncovered.  Dunng observation with OTM a temporary cover slip was applied with  refractive off. Areas of interest on the thin sections were noted, and ap-  proximately a 1 cm2 area was removed by cutting an outline around the  area and gently hfting from the glass shde with a razor blade. The specimen  was uniquely shaped in order to mmntain the known orientation. After rem-    57    oval from the glass slide the subsections were still quite durable, but were  handled with care to avoid dislodging skeletal gains or cracking the fabric.  Selective removal of the impregnating resin was accomplished by placing  the specimen in a beaker containing methylene chloride and slowly swirling  for approximately 2 minutes at room temperature. The solution was then  poured off and the film gently washed with acetone to remove the meth-  ylene chloride. Dissolution with methylene chloride constituted our etching  in which only part of the epoxy resin was removed from the thin section.  The specimens were mounted for SEM-EDXRA by a method similar  to that described by Bisdom et al. (1976) and McKeague and Wang {1980).  Prior to mounting, the specimens were photographed under reflected, plane-  polarized, and cross-polarized light at low magnifications. Various micro-  morphological features of interest were photographed at successively higher  magnifications to provide images for helping to locate them with the SEM.  The specimen was attached to a Cambridge style SEM stub and vacuum  coated with 50 nm carbon. The samples were observed and analyzed on a  JEOL JXA--35 SEM with an EDAX--9100 computerized X--ray spectro-  meter or on a Cambridge stereoscan with an ORTEC 6200 X--ray spectro-  meter.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Discussion of the procedure    Problems encountered m sample preparation, locating areas of interest,  and differentiation of soil material with the secondary electron image of  the SEM were overcome by the described procedure. Scotchcast #3 resin  was used as the impregnating medium because it is stable under vacuum  and the electron beam of the SEM (Innes and Pluth, 1970), while yielding  only very low intensity peaks for Na and Cl with EDXRA. Removal of the  thin section from the glass slide eliminated the possibility of obtaining back-  ground X-rays through holes in the thin section, especially when the sample  was etched and elemental Si mapping was performed. The etched speci-  mens were noticeably more fragile after etching but after mounting to the  SEM stub, no special precautions were required as with Low Temperature  Ashing (LTA) {Jenkins, 1981). The etching procedure greatly improved  the usefulness of the specimens for secondary electron observation by creat-  ing relief and exposing internal surfaces (Fig. 1). Likewise, where polished  mineral surfaces remained after etching, EDXRA could be performed with-  out interferences created by surface roughness. Mineral grains that could  be identified using petrographic techniques could then be analyzed with  EDXRA to obtain spectra representative for the species. The use of trans-  mitted and reflected light images of the specimen at overlapping magnif-  ications greatly enhanced the usefulness of the SEM-EDXRA as a power-  ful tool in this type of micromorphological study. As an example, Fig. 2    Fig.1. Secondary electron images of unetched (a) and etched (b) thin sections from  a fragipan horizon of a Hosmer soil    59    illustrates the various images of a simple void axgillan truncated at the rater-  face of a fragipan prism interior and a vertical eluvial seam.  The procedure employed was not extremely time consuming and did  not restrict observations with OTM, either before or after application of  SEM-EDXRA. If an area of interest was found on the SEM the specimen  could be washed free of the conductive coating, remounted on a glass  slide and reanalyzed with OTM. Such cognitive use of the two types of  observatmns proved very effective in analyzing the bridging material oc-  curring in fragipans found in loess. A possible disadvantage is that heating  of some soils to 95 could considerably alter their fabrics through desicca-  tion. However, comparative studies involving replicate unheated samples im-  pregnated with methylmethacrylate throned with styrene revealed only  slightly more desiccation of the fabrics with heating than air-drying. Un-  fortunately, the etching procedure ~s probably only applicable to mineral  soils low in organic matter since both methylene chloride and acetone may  solubilize some organic constituents.    Application of SEM-EDXRA to the study of fragipans    A fragipan (modified from L. fragilis brittle, and pan: meaning brittle  pan) is a dense soil layer that is brittle when moist and very hard when  dry. Fragipans severely restrict plant root profusion in soils and thereby  limit agricultural productivity. They also reduce the suitability of soil  for many engineering and urban uses. Although fragipans are geographi-  cally extensive their genesis remains obscure. The source of their brittleness  has been widely studmd and has generally been attributed to weak cemen-  tation by one or more soil components (Grossman and Carlisle, 1969).  However, there is still no consensus regarding composition of the cementing  material.  OTM examination of the fragipan horizons from a loess derived Hosmer  soft (fine-silty, mixed, mesic, Typic Fragiudult; Soil Survey Staff, 1975)  revealed isotic to highly blrefringent plasma bridging silt grains at mag-  nifications greater than 250 (Fig. 3). The plasmic bodies were too small  to yield interference figures or to identify with other optical techniques.  Since the bridges could not be identified by conventional OTM, SEM-EDXRA  was used to locate and analyze the composition of the material.  Qualitatively, the composition of mineral grains and major micromor-  phological features in the fragipan horizon were easily determined by  EDXRA of the polished, pedestal-like surfaces in the thin section. Plasma  separations of clay occurred mainly around skeleton grains, which was  reasonable since it was determined that the fragipan had skel-insepic plasmic  fabric (Brewer, 1976) from optical techniques (Fig. 3). The plasma separa-  tions were characterized by small desiccation cracks and by EDXRA spectra  that exhibited roughly a 2:1 ratio of Si:A1 peak heights with substantial  but variable peaks for K, Ca and Fe. The spectra were very similar to those    60    im C~  N  C~ r~  p~  ~o    61    Fig.3 Plane-polarized (a) and cross-polarized (b) light micrographs of soil fabric from  the interior of a fragipan prism from a Hosmer soil developed in loess illustrating plasma  bridging skeleton grains    for large argillans and papules that could be differentiated on the basis  of their texture and conductance under the SEM.  After etching, mineral grains were easily recognized at magnifications  greater than 200 ; at magnifications of 250--2000 small features forming  bridges between silt grains could be seen in the fragipan. These bridges  were conspicuous in that they did not appear to be cracked due to desic-  cation as were the argillans and other plasma separations. The bridges could  also be found between grains of differing composition. Fig. 4 is an example  of such a case and Fig. 5 illustrates the EDXRA spectra at points a, b, and    62    Fig.4_ Secondary electron image of a silicate bridge m the fragipan of a Hosmer soil  showing locatlons of EDXRA spectra at points a, b, and c    a                       b    Sl  A  i         i    ,        |    !    ,    ,    i              i    !    .         .    .    ,    !         -  0      2       4      6      8      I0       0      2       4      6      8      I  o  keV                                           keY    Si    AI       K         Fe  i         i    w             i    |  0           4     6     8     I0  keV  Fig.5 EDXRA spectra from the corresponding points a, b, and c, on Fig.4.    c, on Fig. 4. The upper grain was identified as being quartz while the lower  grain is probably a feldspar. The EDXRA spectrum of the bridging material  (Fig. 5c) was very characteristic for other bridges observed in the fragipan.  These features always contained a large Si peak with smaller peaks for    63    AI, K and Fe. The spectrum, if the Si peak was not so intense, would closely  resemble the spectra from argillans observed in large papules and cutans.  Possibly, the bridges have some silicate clay incorporated in them. The high  Si content of the bridges was a characteristic feature; however, the Al  content was somewhat variable. The variabihty may be due to diffenng  amounts of exchangeable Al associated with clay, or to Al-mterlayering  of clay minerals; however, after considering data from an infrared spectro-  scopic study of the softs (Norton, 1981), both $1 and A1 probably occur  m the structure of a poorly crystallized hydrous oxide occurring in the  bridges. It is possible that these bridges are the source of brittleness in the  fragipan.    CONCLUSION    The advantages of the technique described were that the same specimen  could be observed interchangeably with OTM and SEM-EDXRA and that  very little additional effort was required to make the transition from con-  ventional OTM to SEM-EDXRA observation. The etching and the use of  OTM photographs made the location and identification of soil features  much easmr than with non-etched samples.    REFERENCES    B1sdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerius, A. and Thie], F , 1975. Energy dispersive X--ray  analysis on thin sections and unimpregnated soil material. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 23  113--125.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Hornsveld, E.M and Jongerius, A., 1976. Wavelength and  energy dispersive microanalysis with EMA and SEM-EDXRA on thin sections of soils.  Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 24.209--222.  Brewer, R., 1976. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. R.E. Krieger Publishing,  Huntington, N.Y., 482 pp.  Grossman, R.B. and Carlisle, F.J., 1969. Fragipan soils of the eastern United States. Adv.  Agron., 21: 237--239.  Innes, R.P. and Pluth, D.J., 1970. Thin section preparation using an epoxy impregnation  for petrographic and electron microprobe analysis  Soil Sci  Soc. Am. Proe., 34  483--485  Jenkins, D A, 1981. The transition from optical microscopic to scanning electron sub-  microscopic studms on soils. In E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and  Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the International Working--Group on Submicro-  scopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen. Centre for  Agricultural Pubhshing and Documentation, Wageningen, pp. 163--172.  McKeague, J.A. and Protz, R., 1980 Cement of duric horizons, micromorphology and  energy dispersive analysis. Can. J. Soil Sci., 60 45--52.  McKeague, J.A. and Wang, C., 1980. Micromorphology and energy dmpersive analysis  of ortstein horizons of podzolic soils from New Brunswick and Nova Scotia, Canada  Can. J. Soil Sci., 60 9--21.  Norton, L.D., 1981. Loess Distribution and Pedogenesis of Loess-Derived Soils m East-  Central Ohio. Unpublished Ph.D. dissertation, Ohio State University, Columbus,  Ohio, 230 pp.    64    Soil Survey Staff, 1975 Soil Taxonomy A Basle System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys U S. Dep. Agric., Handbook Number 436 U S. Govt.  Print. Off., Washington, D C, 754 pp.  Wilding, L P and Geissmger, H.D , 1973. Correlative light optmal and scanning electron  microscopy of minerals  A methodology study J Sediment Petrol, 43"280--286                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractCoupled use of optical transmission microscopy and SEM—EDXRA in the study of soil thin sections initially proved difficult because of problems in differentiation of mineral grains and impregnating medium with the secondary electron detector of the SEM. It was also difficult to locate the same small micromorphological features with both techniques, especially when the feature was hidden below the surface of the thin section. A procedure was developed that included selective dissolution (etching) of the impregnating medium and is presented here. After etching, many micromorphological features could be more easily recognized and those immediately below the surface were partially exposed. Application of the procedure proved useful in analyzing bridging plasma too small to identify by optical transmission microscopy that connected silt grains in fragipan horizons. 