 Geoderma, 35 (1985) 91-107  91  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam - Printed in The Netherlands    SHAPES OF AGGREGATES FROM TILLED LAYERS OF SOME DUTCH  AND AUSTRALIAN SOILS    A.R. DEXTER    Department of Soil Science, Waite Agricultural Research Institute, The University of  Adelaide, Glen Osmond, South Australia 5064 (Australia)    (Received August 21, 1984; accepted after revision February 14, 1985)    ABSTRACT    Dexter, A.R., 1985. Shapes of aggregates from tilled layers of some Dutch and Australian  soils. Geoderma, 35: 91-107.     Five different methods were used to study the shapes of soil aggregates oriented in their planes of maximum projection. A measure of roundness was found to be relatively insensitive to shape features. The shortest aspect ratio (the ratio of the shortest to the longest diameters through the centroid) was found to be most sensitive of the "single value" shape measures. More comprehensive shape information was given by values of the radius spectra and the curvature spectra. The curvature spectra method seems to be slightly more sensitive than the radius spectra method and can also be applied to reentrant particles.   Generally it was found that aggregates are less round with increasing clay content and decreasing organic matter content. There was also a hint that aggregates of the Dutch soils may become less round with increasing age since their reclamation. The Australian soil aggregates were slightly rounder than the Dutch aggregates.    INTRODUCTION     The shape of soil aggregates is of interest because it can yield clues to the mechanisms of aggregate formation. Shape also influences a number of important soil physical properties including packing density or porosity and the relationship between aggregate crushing force and the tensile strength of the aggregate material. This latter problem was encountered by Dexter and Kroesbergen (1985).   Aggregate shape is usually considered in descriptive categories such as "rounded", "sub-rounded", "angular", "blocky", etc. Comparison of actual aggregates with pictures of standard shapes of particles enables the shapes of the aggregates to be put into the appropriate categories. Often, the standard shapes have been put into their categories on the basis of some quantitative criteria such as that of Wadell (1935). Examples of charts of standard shapes are those of Powers (1953) and of Krumbein and Sloss (1963) which was also used by Morse et al. (1982).    0016-7061/85/$03.301985 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.  92     Several simple measures of particle shape have been devised and used. Cox (1927) defined roundness, R, to be the ratio of the projected area, A, of the particle to the area of a circle having the same perimeter, P:    R = 47/P2  (1)    This gives R = 1 for a sphere and R = 0 for a thin needle.   Another simple measure is the "aspect ratio" of a particle which is the ratio of the longest: intermediate: shortest axis lengths, x:y:z. These may be rendered dimensionless by dividing by the longest axis length to give l:xly: zlx. Using this method, Braunack et al. (1979) obtained mean aspect ratios for aggregates of several normally swelling soils of 1:0.73:0.50 at -153 MPa matric water potential and 1:0.87:0.70 at -100 kPa matric water potential. The reason for these apparent differences of shape with water potential remains unclear. For three Dutch soils, Dexter et al. (1984) reported aspect ratios around 1:0.78:0.65. For a soil of the Winton series from Penicuick, Scotland an aspect ratio of 1:0.75:0.60 has been found (S.T. Willatt, personal communication, 1984). The above aspect ratios are close to l:q:q2. This will be discussed later.   The advent of automatic scanning devices and computers has made particle shape measurements easier to make and has enabled more complex mathematical analysis of particle shapes to be done (e.g., Beddow and Meloy, 1980). The most commonly used of these methods is to perform a Fourier analysis of a radius vector within the particle (Schwarcz and Shane, 1969; Ehrlich and Weinberg, 1970; Cheng and Sutton, 1971). The radius vector, r(B ), is usually considered to revolve about the centroid of the particle (Fig.l). Fourier analysis shows that, for any shape, the radius can be expressed exactly as a sum of sine and cosine terms of harmonics:    r(e) = A(o) + E [A(m)cos(ne) + B(m)sin(ne )] (2)  n=1    V    t    8  B=O    Fig.l. Profile of a particle, Radius vector, r, rotates about the centroid. Sampling points are spaced at equal angles for radius spectra studies and at equal distances apart for curvature spectra studies. Vector V crosses the perimeter at three points in this example of a re-entrant particle.  93    Here, A(o) is equal to the mean radius of the particle, and the A(m) and B(m) describe the amplitudes of the mth harmonic components of the radius spectrum. Alternatively, eq. 2 can be expressed on complex form:    n-1  ime/No (3)  r(B ) = E P(m)e m    where P(m) is the complex radius given by:    P(m) = C(m)ei0m = A(m)-iB(m) (4)    and where i = V-1, N = 2n is the number of sampling points spaced at equal angles, A is the sampling interval such that NA = 21r, C(m) is the amplitude of the mth harmonic and O(m) is the phase angle of the mth harmonic (m) = arctan (-B(m)/A(m)) relative to the reference angle 0 = 0). The coefficients of eq. 2 can be separated to give:    A(m) -Ns~ln rs cos2 s , and (5)    ln-1  27rms  B(m) -- E rs sin (6)  Ns=-n  N    where s is the index number of the sampling points (Jenkins and Watts, 1968).   The relative magnitudes of A(m) and B(m) for any given value of m depend on the phase angle, m), of the mth harmonic. It can be shown by multiplying eq. 4 by its complex conjugate, P(m)*, however, that the quantity:    C(m) = [A (M)2 +B(m)2] '/2  (7)    is independent of the phase angle. Values of A(m), B(m) and C(m) given above are dependent on the absolute size of the particle. They can, however, be normalized or made size-independent by dividing them by A(o).   Fourier analysis of the radius vector relies upon the radius, r, always being a single-valued function of the angle, B . This is not always the case as is shown for a re-entrant particle in Fig.1. In this example, the radius vector V crosses the profile at three points.   Davis and Dexter (1972) devised two measures of particle shape which are applicable to re-entrant particles. The first of these is based on comparisons of chord and arc lengths on the profile perimeter and will not be considered further here. The second is based on the distribution of curvature around the perimeter of the outline of the particles.   A curvature spectrum is produced as follows. Firstly, the perimeter is divided into N points equally spaced a distance d apart, as shown in Fig.2. The angle  is the slope of the perimeter between two consecutive points  94 n and n+1 such that:     On = arctan( yn+1 - yn (8)   xn+l - xn    A measure of the curvature is given by the function fn in terms of the difference between two consecutive values of     fn  = ei(+1 - ) _ 1 (  such that for a straight line, which has zero curvature, fn = 0.  r  x_,. Y..,    d    ~,Y~    x  Fig.2. Definitions of some terms used in the curvature spectra method (Davis and Dexter, 1972).    The discrete Fourier transform of fn is then calculated from    r, (k) = I 1 fn . 27rikn/N (10)   n=0    Finally, the discrete curvature spectrum, S(k), is obtained by multiplying eq. 10 by its complex conjugate:    S(k) = F(k) X F(k)*  (11)    As pointed out by Davis and Dexter (1972), S(k) for a regular n-gon takes equal and finite values for k = 0, n, 2n, 3n, . . ., etc., whilst it is,zero for all other k.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Standard shapes     The standard comparison shapes given by Krumbein and Sloss (1963) were analysed for the purposes of quantitative comparison with the soil aggregates. These standard shapes, which were originally developed to aid the description of quartz particles, are reproduced in Fig.3.  95    0.9     0.7  U    0.5    0.     4W 6* 490 40  ~ ~ ab Ap  en    0.1 0.3 05 07 0.9    Roundness, X  Fig.3. Standard particle shapes reproduced from Krumbein and Sloss (1963). (With permission of W.H. Freeman and Company.)    40 #le I qe    Sample D2    rt 4 % d    Sample D7    Fig.4. Profiles of aggregates of 4.8-6.8 mm size sieved from the Dutch soil samples D2 and D7.     Aggregates were collected from eight Dutch soils and from one Australian soil which had been under five different cropping rotations.  96     The Dutch samples were collected from the arable layers (0-200 mm) from eight sites in the IJsselmeer polders in mid-1982. Samples D1 and D2 were from the North East Polder which was reclaimed around 1940; samples D3, D4 and D5 were from the East Flevopolder which was reclaimed around 1957; and samples D6, D7 and D8 were from the South Flevopolder which was reclaimed around 1968. Some details of the soils are given in Table I. The soils are Entisols, and are classified as Aquic Udifluvents (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). Outlines of some aggregates of soils D2 and D7 are shown in Fig.4.   The Australian samples were collected from the 0-100 mm layer of the C1 permanent rotation experiment at the Waite Agricultural Research Institute. Sample A1 is from Plot 6 of that experiment which is a wheat-pasture-fallow (WPF) rotation; sample A2 is from Plot 9 which is a wheatoats-fallow (WOF) rotation; sample A3 is from Plot 25 which is a wheat--oats-pasture-fallow (WOPF) rotation; sample A4 is from Plot 32 which is a wheat-pasture-pasture-fallow (WPPF) rotation; and sample A5 is from Plot 35 which is a wheat-fallow (WF) rotation. The plots were all sampled in April 1984 towards the end of the fallow (bare) year. They had been tilled with a chisel plow to 15 cm in early August 1983, with a spring tine    TABLE I    Details of the experimental soil samples    (a) Dutch soils    Soil Age Land Organic Particle size distribution (9'0)  sample (yrs) parcel matter     (96) &lt;2 jum 2-50 um &gt;50 gem  Dl 42 M70 3.2 26.6 59.1 14.3  D2 42 P92 2.4 14.4 52.4 33.2  D3' 25 H91 3.1 18.9 66.3 14.8  D4 25 K21 3.3 25.2 61.7 13.1  D5 25 U16 4.4 40.8 48.5 10.7  D6 14 QZ52 3.3 39.6 49.0 11.4  D7 14 NZ70 4.4 42.8 48.5  8.7  D8 14 NZ47 2.9 15.1 44.1 40.8    (b) Australian soil samples    Soil Crop Organic Particle size distribution (%)  sample rotation matter    (%) &lt;2 jum 2-50 jum &gt;50 Am  A1 WPF 1.9 17 58 25  A2 WOF 1.8 17 58 25  A3 WOPF 2.9 17 58 25  A4 WPPF 2.7 17 58 25  A5 WF 1.9 17 58 25  97    cultivator with narrow points to 10 cm in mid-August 1983, and with a spring tine cultivator with wide points to 10 cm depth in October 1983. The soil is Urrbrae loam which is a member of the Red-brown earth group (Oades et al., 1981) and is a Calcic Rodoxeralf (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). Some details of the soils are given in Table I.   The Dutch samples were air-dried and sieved into the following size ranges: 3.4-4.0 mm, 4.8-6.8 mm, and 8.0-9.6 mm. The Australian samples were air-dried and sieved to collect aggregates in the 4.0-6.7 mm size range. In the remainder of this paper, these aggregates will be described by the means of these ranges only: i.e. for the Dutch samples, 3.7, 5.8 and 8.8 mm, and for the Australian samples, 5.4 mm.   Twenty aggregates of each type were photographed. They were placed on a ground-glass screen in their most stable positions (the orientation which gives maximum projected area). The ground-glass screen was illuminated from behind so that there were no shadows to spoil the definition of the edges of the aggregates.    Scanning and data processing     The photographs of the aggregates were scanned automatically with a television camera which was connected to a digitizer and a micro-computer. Each picture was scanned with a resolution of 256 X 256 picture elements or pixels. The linearity of the scanning was adjusted and checked using standard shapes. In order to minimize the data for each aggregate, only the coordinates (x,y) of the perimeter were stored. This was done as follows.   Firstly, a quick scan was done along every tenth line and row of the picture so that the approximate centre of the aggregate could be determined. Then a pair of diagonal lines at + zr /4 and -7r /4 were generated through this point as shown in Fig.5. Scanning was then done along every line or column within each quadrant, and the coordinates of the edge of the particle were stored. About 500-600 coordinate pairs (x,y) were stored for each particle in this way.    Fig.5. Directions of scanning in four quadrants defined by two diagonal lines through the approximate centre of a photograph of an aggregate.  98     The above method was used because it is simple and gives fairly uniformly spaced data points, because it works with rather irregular images, and because it is faster than scanning the whole picture. Faster but more complex edge-following algorithms could have been applied.   From the coordinates of the edges, the centroid, area and perimeter of the aggregate image were calculated. This enabled values of the roundness, R, from eq. 1 to be determined. Two types of aspect ratios were calculated both of which are based on the maximum diameter, Dmax, of an aggregate which passes through the centroid. The right-angled aspect ratio, ARr, is the ratio of Dr to Dmax where Dr is the diameter through the centroid at right-angles to Dm ax    ARr =Dr/Dm ax  (12)    The shortest aspect ratio, AR,, is the ratio of the shortest diameter, Ds, which passes through the centroid, to Dmax    AR, =Ds/Dmax  (13)     For calculation of the Fourier spectrum of the radius using eqs. 2--7, the scanned points along the aggregate perimeter were linearly interpolated to give an arbitrary number (N = 128) of points spaced at equal angles (0 = 21r/128 radians) about the centroid.   For calculation of the curvature spectrum of the perimeter using eqs. 8-11 the scanned points along the perimeter were linearly interpolated to give an arbitrary number (N = 128) of points equally spaced in distance along the perimeter.    RESULTS    Cox's measure o f roundness     For the standard shapes shown in Fig.3, the roundness values are given by:    R =  0.463 + 0.122X + 0.325Y, (14)   (.027) (.028) (0.035)    where X and Y are the "roundness" and "sphericity" values of Krumbein and Sloss (1963) as shown in Fig.3.   For the Dutch aggregates, roundness values are given in Table II. The best correlation is between these and the clay (&lt; 2 pm) content values given in Table I. This gives    R = 0.740 - 0.0017 (clay)  (15)   (.017) (.0006)    which shows that the aggregates of the soils with higher clay contents are less round than those with lower clay contents.  99    TABLE II    Values of Cox's measure of roundness, R, and of the right-angle, ARr, and shortest, ARs, aspect ratios (figures in parentheses are standard errors)  Soil Roundness (R) Aspect ratios    ARr ARS    Dutch aggregates  D1 0.722 (0.009) 0.744 (0.019) 0.685 (0.016)  D2 0.702 (0.008) 0.681 (0.044) 0.648 (0.021)  D3 0.708 (0.010) 0.760 (0.027) 0.686 (0.021)  D4 0.716 (0.009) 0.739 (0.021) 0.668 (0.015)  D5 0.659 (0.011) 0.720 (0.026) 0.645 (0.025)  D6 0.679 (0.010) 0.679 (0.022) 0.633 (0.019)  D7 0.652 (0.013) 0.702 (0.046) 0.659 (0.027)  D8 0.700 (0.011) 0.772 (0.020) 0.728 (0.018)    Australian aggregates  A1 0.695 (0.010) 0.766 (0.020) 0.713 (0.016)  A2 0.673 (0.014) 0.712 (0.028) 0.656 (0.024)  A3 0.708 (0.012) 0.822 (0.028) 0.752 (0.021)  A4 0.713 (0.006) 0.734 (0.025) 0.696 (0.020)  A5 0.722 (0.010) 0.757 (0.026) 0.706 (0.021)    For the Australian aggregates, the mean value of roundness is  R = 0.702(.005) (16)  with no significant effect of organic matter content.    Aspect ratios    Aspect ratios of the standard shapes are given approximately by:  ARr = 0.172 + 0.770Y (17)   (0.055) (0.068)  and  AR, = 0.202 + 0.658Y (18)   (0.038) (0.050)  For the Dutch aggregates, aspect ratios are given in Table II. These give:  ARr = 0.676 - 0.0047(clay) + 0.058(OM) - 0.0007(age) (19)   (0.083) (0.0019) (0.032) (0.0011)  and  AR, = 0.682 - 0.0038(clay) + 0.034(OM) - 0.0010(age) (20)   (.066) (0.0015) (t 0.026) (0.0008)  100    For the Australian aggregates:    ARr = 0.656 + 0.046(OM) (21)   (.086) (0.038)  ARs = 0.610 + 0.042(OM)  (22)   (.067) (.030)    Radius spectra     Normalized harmonic components, C(m), of the radius spectra were correlated with various sample features. For the standard shapes, the equation used was:    C(m) = al + b,X + c,Y  (23)     For the Dutch soil aggregates, the equation was:    C(m) = a2 + b2(clay) + e2(OM) + d2(age)  (24)     For the Australian aggregates, C(m) was regressed with organic matter content:    C(m) = a3 + bs(OM)  (25)    Fitted parameters of eqs. 23-25 are given in Tables III, IV and V. When a factor did not give a significant correlation, it was omitted from the regression.   Mean, smoothed values of C(m) are plotted for the Dutch and Australian soil aggregates in Fig.6.    TABLE III    Regression coefficients for the normalized radius spectra, C(m), of eq. 23 for the standard shapes shown in Fig.3 (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficients)    m  a, b,  c1   1 0.043 (0.008) -0.003 (0.008) -0.041 (0.010)   2 0.290 (0.017)  0.021 (0.018) -0.302 (0.023)   3 0.049 (0.018) -0.017 (0.012) -0.018 (0.015)   4 0.099 (0.012) -0.033 (0.013) -0.072 (0.017)   5 0.014 (0.002)   6 0.045 (0.008) -0.032 (0.009) -0.021 (0.011)   7 0.022 (0.003) -0.014 (0.003) -0.008 (0.004)   8 0.022 (0.003) -0.016 (0.004) -0.010 (0.005)   9 0.017 (0.002) -0.012 (0.003) -0.088 (0.003)   10 0.014 (0.003) -0.009 (0.004) -0.008 (0.004)    'Not significant.  TABLE IV    Regression coefficients for the normalized radius spectra, C(m), of eq. 24 for the Dutch soil aggregates (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficients)    m az    bz    cz     1 0.01439(0.00245)   2 0.09404(0.02072)   3 0.01731(0.01427)   4 0.00705(0.00200)   5 0.01875(0.00092)   6 0.01053(0.00353)   7 0.01334(0.00228)   8 0.00704(0.00103)   9 0.01103(0.00185)   10 0.00628(0.00038)   11 0.00394(0.00044)   12 0.00396(0.00062)   13 0.00381(0.00013)   14 0.00647(0.00118)   15 0.00220(0.00024)   16 0.00194(0.00015)   17 0.00281(0.00049)   18 0.00186(0.00025)   19 0.00155(0.00015)   20 0.00143(0.00026)    0,00012(0.00008)    0.00123(0.00068) -0,00071(0.00040)    0.00005(0.00004)  *    0,00021(0,00008)  0.00023(0.00006)  0.00005(0,00003)  0.00009(0.00004)  *    0.00006(0.00001)  0.000100.00002)  *    0.00004(0.00003) 0.00003(0.00001) 0.00002(0.00000) 0.00006(0.00001) 0.00002(0.00001) 0.00002(0.00001) 0.00002(0.00001)    -0.01447(0.00978)  0.01316(0.00674)  0.00361(0.00077)  *    -0.00133(0.00137)  -0.00275(0.00089)  *    -0.00135(0.00072)  *  *    -0.00073(0.00029)    -0,00064(0.00046)  *  *    -0,00065(0.00023)    0.00022(0.00003)  *    0.00008(0.00004)  0.00004(0.00003)  *    -0.00005( 0.00002)  *  *  *  *    -0.00003(0.00001)    TABLE V    Regression coefficients for the normalized radius spectra, C(m), of eq. 25 for the Australian soil aggregates (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficient)    m a3    b3     1 0.0137 (0.0011)   2 0.1067 (0.0268)   3 0.0220 (0.0083)   4 0.0326 (0.0068)   5 0.0151 (0.0003)   6 0.0113 (0.0007)   7 0.0116 (0.0025)   8 0.0070 (0.0004)   9 0.0056 (0.0002)   10 0.0042 (0.0003)   11 0.0035 (0.0001)   12 0.0031 (0.0003)   13 0.0030 (0.0002)   14 0.0022 (0.0001)   15 0.0029 (0.0003)   16 0.0018 (0.0001)   17 0.0021 (0.0003)   18 0.0016 (0.0001)   19 0.0015 (0.0001)   20 0.0014 (0.0001)    -0.0156 (0.0117)   0.0056 (0.0036)  -0.0038 (0.0030)    -0.0015 (0.0011)    -0.0004 (0.0001)    -0.0002 (0.0001)  102    0    _1      o  of  `.  4) VV  , 11    -3    0 5 10 15 __    harmonic number, m    Fig.6. Plots of logarithms of the normalized radius spectra, C(m), against harmonic number, m. Curves are the envelopes of the mean, smoothed, discrete values for all of the Dutch (solid line) and all of the Australian (broken line) aggregates.    TABLE VI    Regression coefficients for the discrete curvature spectra S(k) of eq. 26 for the standard particle shapes of Fig. 3 (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficients)    k a4 b, c4     1 0.30 (0.08)   2 16.17 (1.69) 1.21 (1.78) -18.55 (2.25)   3 2.24 (0.49)   4 20.61 (5.55) -16.44 (5.83) -8.69 (7.37)   5 7.08 (4.61) -5.57 (4.84) 3.00 (6.13)   6 9.66 (4.99) -18.54 (5.25) 10.51 (6.64)   7 9.03 (4.23) -18.03 (4.45) 10.99 (5.63)   8 7.80 (1.60) -7.84 (2.79)   9 8.71 (1.96) -10.09 (3.41)   10 10.03 (2.78) -11.13 (4.84)   11 8.29 (2.14) -7.82 (2.25) -2.16 (2.84)   12 5.75 (1.72) -5.30 (3.00)   13 9.13 (5.27) -17.72 (5.53) 7.24 (7.00)   14 9.58 (2.46) -10.25 (4.29)   15 3.17 (0.99) -2.75 (1.73)   16 4.82 (1.16) -5.00 (2.01)   17 9.22 (2.66) -7.23 (2.79) -4.86 (3.53)   18 1.84 (2.24) -6.05 (2.35) 6.39 (2.97)   19 5.18 (1.26) -3.75 (1.33) -2.11 (1.67)   20 12.63 (2.59) -9.03 (2.72) -5.55 (3.44)  103    Curvature spectra     Values of the discrete curvature spectra, S(k), for the standard shapes were fitted to    S(k) = a4 + b4X+ C4 Y  (26)    Values of the fitted parameters are given in Table VI. These do not give very good fits to the data.  For the Dutch soil aggregates, the spectral values were fitted to:    S(k) = as + bs(clay) + cs (OM)  (27)    Again, only significant correlations are given in Table VII. There was no significant effect of the age of the soil since reclamation on the S(k) values.  For the Australian aggregates, the spectral values were fitted to:    S(k) = ab + bb (OM)  (28)    and the coefficients are given in Table VIII.   Mean, smoothed values of the curvature spectra are plotted in Fig.7. The spectra, S(k), decreased in the order: Dutch samples with high clay contents &gt; Dutch samples with lower clay contents &gt; Australian samples.    TABLE VII    Regression coefficients for the curvature spectra, S(k), of eq. 27 for the Dutch soil aggregates (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficients)    k a,,   bs cs   1  2.37 (1.06) 0.07 (0.03) -0.86 (0.50)   2  3.60 (0.21)   3  4.59 (0.79) 0.03 (0.02)   4  5.43 (0.70) 0.05 (0.02)   5  7.86 (1.34) 0.11 (0.03) -0.95 (0.54)   6 12.31 (1.71) 0.18 (0.04)  -2.45 (0.66)   7 10.67 (1.96)  0.18 (0.06) -1.85 (0.93)   8  7.32 (1.11) 0.10 (0.04)   9  7.18 (1.39) 0.13 (0.05)  10 6.57 (1.20) 0.16 (0.04)  11 5.83 (1.06) 0.19 (0.04)  12 5.61 (1.45) 0.21 (0.05)  13 10.85 (4.59) 0.32 (0.13) -2.35 (2.16)  14 7.59 (2.00) 0.16 (0.07)  15 12.23 (3.75) 0.24 (0.11) -1.94 (1.77)  16 12.70 (3.11) 0.27 (0.09) -2.18 (1.47)  17 8.03 (1.23) 0.18 (0.04)  18 7.60 (1.13) 0.20 (0.04)  19 7.63 (1.13) 0.20 (0.04)  20 8.42 (1.77) 0.18 (0.06)  104    TABLE VIII    Regression coefficients for the curvature spectra, S(k), of eq. 28 for the Australian soil aggregates (figures in parentheses are standard errors of the fitted coefficients)    k ab    bb    1 2.59 (0.60)  2 3.67 (0.39)  3 5.00 (0.44)  4 5.92 (0.50)  5 6.37 (0.49)  6 6.58 (0.47)  7 9.63 (2.50) -1.30 (1.09)  8 10.93 (2.97) -1.87 (1.30)  9 10.59 (2.79) -1.68 (1.22)  10 9.25 (1.82) -0.92 (0.80)  11 7.64 (0.41)  12 7.58 (0.29)  13 7.62 (0.52)  14 7.93 (0.67)  15 8.59 (0.74)  16 9.33 (0.73)  17 9.80 (0.76)  18 9.72 (0.72)    19 12.80 (3.01)  20 9.54 (0.64)    -1.52 (1.32)    20 r    15    10 ~-    -------------    i    2    0 5    10 15 20     k Fig.7. Plots of the curvature spectra, S(k), for different values of k. Curves are the envelopes of the mean, smoothed, discrete values for the Dutch samples D5, D6 and D7 with high clay content (1); the Dutch samples Dl, D2, D3, D4 and D8 with lower clay content (2); and the Australian samples (3).  105    Effects of aggregate size     There was no trend in any of the shape parameters of the Dutch aggregates with aggregate size over the narrow range of sizes investigated.    DISCUSSION     The measurements of the aspect ratios reported previously in the literature can be considered in terms of a simple model of aggregate fragmentation. Soil aggregates are likely to be most susceptible to breaking by bending stresses applied to their longest axes. It can be readily shown that if small aggregates are formed by the breaking in half of larger aggregates along their longest axes, and if aggregate shape is independent of aggregate size, then the aggregate aspect ratios must be:    l:q:q`  (29)    where q = (0.5)'3 = 0.794. This value is very similar to that which has been observed with several different soil types, although this does not mean that this is the only, or even the principal, mechanism of aggregate formation.   The values of q reported previously are directly comparable with the values of the right-angled aspect ratio, AR,, reported here. For the Dutch soil samples D1, D4 and D6, the new results obtained by scanning and computation are the same to within experimental error as the previous results (Dexter et al.,1984) obtained by measurement with calipers.   The results for the standard shapes of Krumbein and Sloss (1963) shown in Fig.5 are summarized in eqs. 14, 17, 18, 23 and 26. The lack of sensitivity of the aspect ratios to "roundness", X, in eqs. 17 and 18 was as expected and illustrates well the deficiency of simple aspect ratio measurements. There were not smooth trends in the spectra C(m) and S(k) with increasing m or k because of the rather arbitrary nature of the standard shapes and because there was only one example of a shape available for each combination of X and Y. The values are given here in full, however, as they are likely to be useful as a check in future studies.   The Dutch aggregates exhibited a decreasing roundness with increasing clay content (eq. 15) and this was consistent with the decreasing aspect ratios with increasing clay content (eqs. 19, 20). This is also consistent with the positive signs of the coefficients, b2, of eq. 24 given in Table IV, and the coefficients, bs, of eq. 27 given in Table VII. The aspect ratios of the Dutch aggregates are positively correlated with soil organic matter content (eqs. 19, 20) and this is consistent with the generally negative signs of the coefficients, c2, of eq. 24 given in Table IV, and of the coefficients, cs, of eq. 27 given in Table VII. There is, however, a strong positive correlation between clay content and organic matter content in these Dutch soils (Dexter et al., 1984). The apparent slight negative correlation between age of the soil since reclamation and aspect ratios (eqs. 19, 20) is consistent  106    with the slight tendency towards positive coefficients, d2, in eq. 24 and Table IV may indicate a small trend of increasing angularity of aggregates with age. Increased experimental replication would be necessary before a definite statement about this could be made.   With the Australian aggregates, the only variable considered was different organic matter contents resulting from a history of different crop rotations. Eqs. 21 and 22 show a slight increase in aspect ratios with increasing organic matter content. This is consistent with the generally negative coefficients b3 of eq. 25 given in Table V and bb of eq. 28 given in Table VIII.   The reason for the difference in shape between the Dutch and Australian aggregates remains unknown. The similarity of the trend of aggregate shape with increasing organic matter content in the samples from the two countries suggests that a similar mechanism may be responsible.   Of the different methods, the measure of roundness, R, was the worst because it was the least sensitive. The shortest aspect ratio, AR, was better than the right-angled aspect ratio, ARr, because it gave smaller relative standard errors. The radius spectra method came nearer to showing a trend of shape with age than did the curvature spectra method. The curvature spectra method clearly distinguished between the Dutch samples with high and lower clay contents which the radius spectra method did not. The curvature spectra method can be applied to re-entrant particles, whereas the radius spectra method cannot.   Future studies should use the shortest aspect ratio if quick, simple measurements are needed and possibly the curvature spectra method for more detailed studies especially where re-entrant particles are involved.   All of this work has been based on two-dimensional profiles or outlines of particles, whereas any complete description of particle shape would need to be three-dimensional. Tilmann (1973) concluded from a study of 50 sand-sized quartz grains that the shape information carried by the grains when in their orientation of maximum projected area does not differ significantly from the shape information carried by such grains in other orientations. Whether this is true or not for soil aggregates is not yet known. The plane of maximum projected area should be used in future studies.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS     This work was supported by the Wheat Industry Research Council of Australia. Mr. B. Kroesbergen of the Tillage Laboratory of the Agricultural University Wageningen, The Netherlands photographed the Dutch aggregates and Mr. B. Palk photographed the Australian aggregates. Mr. P. Brown assisted with the scanning and the computing. W.H. Freeman &amp; Co. of New York are thanked for permission to reproduce Figure 3.  107    REFERENCES    Beddow, J.K. and Meloy, T.P., 1980. Advanced Particulate Morphology. CRC Press, Boca Raton.  Braunack, M.V., Hewitt, J.S. and Dexter, A.R., 1979. Brittle fracture of soil aggregates and the compaction of aggregate beds. J. Soil Sci., 30: 653-667.  Cheng, D.C-H. and Sutton, H.M., 1971. Absolute determination of particle size and shape. Nature (Physical Science), 232: 192-193.  Cox, E.P., 1927. A method for assigning numerical and percentage values to the degree of roundness. J. Palaeontol., 1: 179-183.  Davis, P.F. and Dexter, A.R., 1972. Two methods for quantitative description of soil particle shape. J. Soil Sci., 23: 448-455.  Dexter, A.R. and Kroesbergen, B., 1985. Methodology for determination of tensile strength of soil aggregates. J. Agric. Eng. Res. In press.  Dexter, A.R., Kroesbergen, B. and Kuipers, H., 1984. Some mechanical properties of aggregates of top soils from the IJsselmeerpolders. 1. Undisturbed soil aggregates. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 32: 205-214.  Ehrlich, R. and Weinberg, B., 1970. An exact method for characterization of grain shape. J. Sediment. Petrol., 40: 205-212.  Jenkins, G.M. and Watts, D.G., 1968. Spectral Analysis and its Applications. HoldenDay, San Francisco, Calif.  Krumbein, W.C. and Sloss, L.L., 1963. Stratigraphy and Sedimentation. (2nd edn.) Freeman, Si.ri Francisco, Calif.  Morse, R.J., Atkinson, G. and Craze, B., 1982. Soil Data Card Handbook. Tech. Handb. No. 4, Soil Cons. Service of NSW. NSW Govt. Printer, Sydney.  Oades, J.M., Lewis, D.G. and Norrish, K., 1981. Red-Brown Earths of Australia. Waite Agricultural Research Institute and CSIRO Division of Soils, Adelaide, South Australia.  Powers, M.C., 1953. A new roundness scale for sedimentary particles. J. Sediment. Petrol., 23: 117-119.  Schwarcz, H.P. and Shane, K.C., 1969. Measurement of particle shape by Fourier analysis. Sedimentology, 13: 213-231.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy, A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Agric. Handb. No. 436, USDA-SCS. US Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C.  Tilmann, S.E., 1973. The effect of grain orientation on Fourier shape analysis. J. Sediment. Petrol., 43: 867-869.  Wadell, H., 1935. Volume, shape and roundness of quartz particles. J. Geol., 43: 250280.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractFive different methods were used to study the shapes of soil aggregates oriented in their planes of maximum projection. A measure of roundness was found to be relatively insensitive to shape features. The shortest aspect ratio (the ratio of the shortest to the longest diameters through the centroid) was found to be most sensitive of the Ã¢Â€Âœsingle valueÃ¢Â€Â shape measures. More comprehensive shape information was given by values of the radius spectra and the curvature spectra. The curvature spectra method seems to be slightly more sensitive than the radius spectra method and can also be applied to reentrant particles.Generally it was found that aggregates are less round with increasing clay content and decreasing organic matter content. There was also a hint that aggregates of the Dutch soils may become less round with increasing age since their reclamation. The Australian soil aggregates were slightly rounder than the Dutch aggregates. 