320    Physikalische Eigenschaften yon Bbden der Schweiz. Felix Richard und Peter  LSscher. ETH Zikrich, 1983, Band 3,368 pp, SFr 58,--.    In dem vorliegenden dritten Band der Publikationsreihe Physikalische  Eigenschaften yon Boden der Schweiz werden 8 weitere Lokalformen  vorgestellt. (1) Braunerde/Gley (Lokalform "Abist", Nr. 10). (2) Para-  braunerde fiber Schotter (Lokalform "Winzlerboden", Nr. 11). (3) Para-  braunerde (Lokalform "Steig", Nr. 12). (4) Rendzinen (Lokalformen "Oster-  liwald", Nr. 13 und "Schitterwald", Nr. 14). (5) Toposequenz Langenthal:  Parabraunerde (Lokalform "Riedhof", Nr. 15); Stark saurer Moder-Pseu-  dogley mit parabraunerdigem Oberboden (Lokalform "Ober-Rickenzopfen",  Nr. 16); Stark saurer Hydro-Rohhumus-Stagnogley (Lokalform "Unter-  Rickenzopfen", Nr. 17).  Die Gliederung der Ergebnisse entspricht der der ersten beiden B~/nde.  Die 6kologischen Aussagen wichtiger bodenphysikalischer Kennwerte (z.B.  Wasserdurchl~issigkeit,  pF-Kurven,  PorengrSssenverteilung  und  verwert-  bares Wasser) stehen dabei wiederum im Vordergrund. Bei der Beschreibung  und Deutung der bodenphysikalischen Eigenschaften werden je nach 5kolo-  gischer Bedeutung die Schwerpunkte unterschiedlich gesetzt.  Auch im 3. Band ist es den Autoren gelungen, durch Auswertungen und  Heranziehung weiterer Literaturergebnisse zwischen dem Messergebnis und  der praktischen Aussage einen auf physikalischen Grundlagen basierenden  Zusammenhang herzustellen.  Besonders hervorzuheben sind die sehr anschaulichen Abbildungen und  informativen Tabellen.  Dem Standortkundler und Bodenphysiker dfirfte auch dieser Band yon  grossem Nutzen sein.    M. RENGER  (Berlin)    Residual Deposits: Surface Related Weathering Processes and Materials.  R.C.L. Wilson (Editor). Geological Society Special Publication No. 11.  Publ. for the Geological Society of London by Blackwell Scientific  Publications, Oxford, 1983, 258 pp., tg. 25.00 (hardcover).    This is a welcome contribution to a multidisciplinary subject. The book  contains papers on weathering profiles and surficial alteration products from  a conference sponsored by the Geological Society of London in 1981. The  25 papers by 30 authors from six continents cover a wide range of subjects.  About 1/3 are reviews, others are data-packed research reports or just  summary conclusions. About half deal with what essentially are pre-Holo-  cene paleosols.    321    While the papers on laterite and bauxite (by McFarlane, Esson, and  Valeton) follow largely the conventional models, the three papers on silcrete  are more provocative. Two authors (Wopfner and Summerfield) suggest on  the basis of their Australian and South African data that the silcretes studied  by them were formed in a humid tropical environment, from silica released  at low pH under restricted drainage (desilication) and precipitated close to  the water table. On the other hand, Van der Graaf postulates a tropical en-  vironment and soil catenary differentiation with Fe release leading to resi-  dual silcrete formation on the well-drained upper slope and absolute Fe  accumulation in laterites on the poorly drained footslope. Thus tropical  silcretes, in addition to the previously more researched semiarid silcrete  types, need to be recognized in the future. Further study of the actual sep-  aration and precipitation processes is obviously needed.  Three papers on red beds describe widely different weathering environ-  ments: Carboniferous paleosols in mudstone (Besly and Turner); kaolinized  dune sand, originally feldspar and heavy minerals rich (Gardner); and a deep  podzolized (spodic) B-horizon in quartz dune sand (Pye). The last two  authors contrast the Late Quaternary tropical leaching environments, lead-  ing to a relatively rapid reddening, with the much slower diagenetic redden-  ing in desert alluvium.  Six papers deal with pedogenic and non-pedogenic calcretes and their  properties. It is gratifying to note that even C.C. Reeves now uses the cal-  crete terminology in preference to caliche. The calcrete and other duricrust  facies of Devonian (Old Red Sandstone) age in the Orcadian Basin (Scotland)  are shown to be mostly of lacustrine origin, only in part fluvial and pedo-  genic (Parnell). There are also papers on kaolinite deposits, fluorite-baryte  residuals, weathering by lichens, experimental weathering, and Cenozoic  pedogenesis in SE England.  With the inclusion of the calcrete and other duricrust papers, where  accumulation and/or displacement are clearly evident and the dominant pro-  cess involved, the term "Residual Deposits" as unifying title for the book  became inappropriate. A different title could have been chosen; perhaps  "Weathering Profiles and Surface Related Alteration Products". Editing and  book production are of a high standard, but an index is lacking.  The recognition and interpretation of many ancient residual and other  supergene alteration products as essentially pedogenic, and the interpretation  of their genesis by lateral and vertical differentiation processes, is growing,  well exemplified by the contribution of Ida Valeton. But citation to  pedological papers, especially those where such separation processes have  been studied in modern soils or the use of pedological nomenclature, is still  an exception rather than a rule. A recent book reviewing the chemical and  geomorphic aspects of the same and additional environments (Goudie and  Pye (Editors), Chemical Sediments and Geomorphology, Academic Press,  1983), may well help to bridge somewhat the gap between practitioners ap-  proaching the subject from different backgrounds. When studied together    322    with Goudie and Pye's collection of reviews, the present book becomes more  than just an assemblage of vaguely related papers. It becomes a supplemen-  tary illustration of many of the weathering and surficial alteration processes  and products which characterize large segments of our landscapes.    DAN H. YAALON  (Jerusalem)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 