Geoderma, 24 (1980) 283--297                                                      283  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CLAY-MINERAL INDICATORS OF GLACIAL AND NONGLACIAL  SOURCES OF WISCONSINAN LOESSES IN SOUTHERN  INDIANA, U.S.A.    ROBERT V. RUHE and CAROLYN G. OLSON.1  Water Resources Research Center and Department of Geology, Indiana University,  Bloomington, Indiana (U.S.A.)  (Received October 29, 1979; accepted February 28, 1980)    ABSTRACT    Ruhe, R.V. and Olson, C.G., 1980. Clay-mineral indicators of glacial and nonglacial sources  of Wisconsinan loesses in southern Indiana, U.S.A. Geoderma, 24: 283--297.    Clay-mineral compositions of Peoria loess of later Wisconsinan age derived from Wabash  Basin and Ohio Basin riverine sources differ in southern Indiana. In the Wabash province  the composition is illite &gt; expandable clay minerals &gt; kaolinite and relates to the clay-  mineral composition of glacial drift in the basin of 91% glacial cover. In the Ohio province  the composition is expandable clay minerals &gt; or ~ illite &gt; kaolinite and relates indirectly  to the clay-mineral composition of the Sangamon Soil terrain on bedrock. Above the  confluent Wabash Basin, 77% of the Ohio Basin is unglaciated. The clay-mineral composi-  tion of thin Farmdale loess of earlier Wisconsinan age also relates to the composition of  the paleosol terrain. During Peorian time while glacial outwash was supplying loess source  materials to the valleys in the Wabash Basin, ordinary alluvium derived from soils and  bedrock in unglaciated terrain was supplying loess source materials to the valleys in the  Ohio Basin.    INTRODUCTION    The well-known methods for determining sources of loess in midwestern  United States involve the decreasing thickness and particle~size changes that  relate to increasing distance from riverine source areas. In southwestern  Indiana {Fig. 1) previous studies resulted in mathematical models derived  along generally linear traverses that extended southeastward from the Wabash  River Valley (Caldwell and White, 1956; Frazee et al., 1970; Hall, 1973).  Loess thickness distribution, however, is more complicated in that area. Loess-  thickness contours have a parabolic distribution with one limb of the parabola  paralleling the Wabash River Valley and the other limb paralleling the Ohio  River Valley (Fehrenbacher et al., 1965). The parabolic distribution fits be-  tween the confluent riverine systems.  Clay-mineral composition, as a source indicator of loess, was added to the    *1Present address: U.S. Geological Survey, Menlo Park, Calif., U.S.A.    284    RU    IV  B  CH     HAUTE     ,NO,AN pOL,S / C  /           E-,~.    =o    0    l/  ~MADISON  M ,,~..---~  /    NEW ALBANY    T     ~.~ k,,,,~.~ Omi          44)                                 I     I    ii     t    J  -1 '    '  ' 66    Fig. 1. Locations of stratigraphic sections in southern Indiana are indicated by letter  symbols. Symbols are identified in text.    loess&lt;listribution model in !Uinois (Glass et al., 1968), but there changes in  composition, mainly contents of illite and expandable clay minerals, are  attributed to modifications in major drainage lines caused by Pleistocene  glacial diversions (Frye et al., 1968). These charges in glacial source materials  resulted in a stratigraphic clay-mineral zoning in the later Wisco~ loess  near the source area (Frye et al., 1968)and along traverses downwind from  the source area (Kleiss, 1973).  The dual riverine source system in Indiana differs from that of Illinois.  The Wabash River is the western boundary of southern Indiana, and the Ohio  River is the southern bound~ (Fig. 1). The Wabash River drainage basin has  an area of 87,300 km2 (33,100 sq. mi.). Wisconsinan gl~ial driR covers  47,400 km2 (18,300 sq. mi.). Illinoian glacial drift mantles 32,375 km2  (12,500 sq. mi.). Nongiacial terrain south of the Hlinoian drift border occu-    285    pies 7,380 km2 (2,850 sq. mi.) in southern Indiana (Fig. 1). The bedrock in  this reentrant is Mississippian and Pennsylvanian carbonate and clastic rocks  including coal measures. Thus, about 91% of the Wabash River drainage basin  is covered with glacial drift, and the major valleys carried the glacial outwash  and alluvium that provided source material for loess.  The Ohio River drainage basin differs radically. Its area is about 261,500  km2 (101,000 sq. mi.) above the mouth of the Wabash River. Wisconsinan  drift covers only 46,880 km~ (18,100 sq. mi.}, and Illinoian drift covers only  13,440 km2 (5,190 sq. mi.). The major part of the drainage basin {77%) is  nonglacial, and the bedrock is Paleozoic carbonate and clastic rocks including  coal measures. The soils in the nonglacial terrain range from Inceptisols to  Alfisols and to Ultisols. Thus, not only was glacial outwash ultimately carried  by the Ohio River from 23% of its drainage basin, but alluvium derived from  erosion of the soils and bedrock also was carried by the Ohio River from 77%  of its drainage basin and along the southern boundary of Indiana.  The question arises: does the mineralogy of the loess derived from the  Wabash Valley of dominantly glacial origin differ from the mineralogy of the  loess derived from the Ohio Valley which may be dominantly of nonglacial  origin? This problem is approached by determining the clay-mineral composi-  tion of stratigraphic sections of loess in both provinces (Fig. 1).  Quantitative estimates of kaolinite (K, 7.2 A }, illite (I, 10 A ), and expand-  able clay minerals (X, 14--17 A ) were made by using the method of additions  of proportions of soil clay to a constant standard (Ruhe and Olson, 1979).  The reference standard is a 1:1:1 mix by weight of the ~2 ~m fractions of  kaolinite KGA-1 and montmorillonite TX-1 (Clay Minerals Society standards)  and a reference illite from the Blaylock Formation, Oklahoma (Mankin and  Dodd, 1963 }. In the study reported here, new prediction equations for  estimating K%, I%, and X% are based on experimental mixes of 31 samples  selected from the total array of samples. The prediction equations are:  K (%) = --2.67 + 70.88 Ki, where R2 = 0.92 and Se = + 3%  In I (%) = In 104.61 + 0.67 In Ii, where R2 = 0.96 and Se = + 6%  X (%) = -0.26 + 92.1 Xi, where R2 = 0.88 and Se = +- 6%  and where Ki, Ii, and Xi are intensity ratios calculated from X-ray powder  diffraction patterns. The R2 values give the proportions of the total estimate  that are explained by the prediction equations. The Se values are the statis-  tical standard errors of estimate.  Within the expandable clay mir~erals, vermiculite (14 A ) and montmoril-  lonite (17 A ) are reported as proportions or parts of 100. In this paper the  symbols K, I, X, and 14 A will be used to avoid incessant repetition of min-  eral-group names.    WISCONSINAN LOESSES    Two Wisconsinan loesses are in southern Indiana (Ruhe, 1976). An upper  Peoria loess is the thicker one, is yellowish brown or gray, and near a source    286    area may be calcareous. In areas where the loess is thinner, it is noncalcareous.  Peoria loess buries a Farmdale loess, and the latter is distinguished by  brown and reddish-brown color and by the presence at places of organic  matter. It is universally noncalcareous although it may be secondarily en-  riched with carbonate where overlain by calcareous Peoria loess. The Farm-  dale loess, where prominent, is readily distinguished from the overlying Peoria  loess (Fehrenbacher et al., 1965; Ruhe, 1976). Farmdale loess or its strati-  graphic equivalent has been identified in the Wabash Basin from Russellville  and Fillmore (Fig. 1, R U, F), where it is buried beneath Wisconsinan glacial  till, down the Wabash Valley to Mount Vernon (Fig. 1, MV). It has been  identified up the Ohio Valley to Troy (Fig. 1, T). Where buried beneath  Peoria loess in these sections, the Peoria loess is 10 to &gt; 50 times thicker than  the Farmdale loess.  The chronology of the Wisconsinan loesses is demonstrated in the strati-  graphic correlation of the group of sections northeast of Terre Haute (Fig. 1).  At RusseUville (R U), an organic silt 70 cm thick contains coniferous wood  and is buried beneath 6.8 m of early Wisconsinan-glacial till. The silt, in turn,  overlies the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in Illinoian till. Soft-  horizon nomenclature follows the Soil Survey Staff (Supp., 1962). A wood  sample from the silt is radiocarbon dated at 20,110 -+ 360 years (ISGS-475).  At Fillmore (F) a stratigraphically equivalent organic silt 5 cm thick is buried  beneath early Wisconsinan glacial till and again overlies the Bb horizon of  the Sangamon Soil formed in Illinoian till. A coniferous wood sample at the  contact of the upper till and the organic silt is 20,660 +- 180 years old {ISGS-  541).  At a site in Parke County in front of the Wisconsinan drift border (Fig. 1,  PK), a peat 90 cm thick is buried beneath 3.65 m of Peoria loess and the  peat in turn buries the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in Illinoian  till. Conferous wood fragments from mid&lt;lepth of the peat are 23,700 +-  1000 years old (W-4212). Nearby at a site in Vigo County (V) a peaty organ-  ic Ob horizon 15 cm thick is buried beneath 3.6 m of Peoria loess and in  turn overlies 1.4 m of gleyed muck, Cgb horizon. The muck buries the Bb  horizon of the Sangamon Soil in IUinoian till. Coniferous wood from the Ob  horizon is 22,700 + 500 years old (W4215).  At Brazil (Fig. 1, B) a silty organic Alb horizon 28 cm thick is buried  beneath 1.15 m of Peoria loess and overlies the Bb horizon of the Sangamon  Soil formed in Illinoian drift. Because of shallow burial and possible con-  tamination, humic acids were extracted from the organic carbon of a sample  of the Alb horizon. The radiocarbon date of the humin (residue) is 25,480 +  420 years, and the date of the humic-acid extract is 23,690 + 980 years and in  reasonable agreement age-wise.  These radiocarbon dates range from 20,100 to 25,500 years and fit within  the time-transgressive span of the Farmdale Soil (Ruhe, 1976). They date the  Farmdale loess and equivalent deposits and also give the maximum ages for  the Peoria loess and early Wisconsinan till. This stratigraphic framework    287    provides the basis for examining the loesses on the Illinoian drift plain and in  the nonglacial area of southern Indiana (Fig. 1). Specific stratigraphic sections  will be analyzed within the Wabash Valley province and in the Ohio Valley  province.    WABASH VALLEY PROVINCE    New Harmoney section (Fig. 1, NH)    This section is a road cut in the bluffs bordering the Wabash River Valley.  Peoria loess is 10.4 m thick. The upper 8 m are yellowish brown, calcareous  and fossiliferous. This zone is termed oxidized loess. The lower 2.4 m are  gray, with reddish brown, iron-oxide mottles and pipestems, and calcareous.  This zone is termed deoxidized loess (Ruhe, 1969). Beneath this zone is  brown, noncalcareous Farmdale loess that is 0.7 m thick. The Farmdale loess  rests on the Sangamon Soil formed in Illinoian till.  The Peoria loess has very uniform clay (&lt;2 ~m), fine silt (2--16 t~m), coarse  silt (16--62 pm), sand (&gt;62 pm), and CaCO3 contents throughout its thick-  ness (Fig. 2). Clay and fine silt abruptly increase and coarse silt and CaCO3  abruptly decrease in the Farmdale loess. The mean clay-mineral composition  of the Peoria loess is kaolinite or K, 16 + 2.8%; illite or I, 57 + 3.7%; and ex-  pandable clay minerals or X, 30 -+ 4.0%. The sum of the means is 103%, but  the standard deviations compensate for the excessive sum. Such compensation  applies to all mean compositions reported in this paper. The mean clay-  mineral composition of the Farmdale loess is K, 13 + 1.0%; I, 19 -+ 1.0%; and    P  OU  P  du  F  SB    CaCO5 o  0%    20         40        60         80       1(30     0%     20         40         60           0%     20        40  ~                                   .N          --      -  4   /z     16/zm          6 2/zm  is2_ }___  [2              %        L  ~ I   I  J                                  o    40% 20    0                      14A 0           IO0   7  I00    Fig. 2. Particle-size (2, 16, and 62 um), clay-mineral, and CaCO3 distributions in the New  Harmony section. P = Peoria loess; ou = oxidized and unleached; du = deoxidized and un-  leached; F = Farmdale loess; SB = Bb horizon of Sangamon Soil ; K = kaolinite; I = illite;  X = expandable clay minerals (14--17 A ); 14A = vermiculite; 1 7A = montmorillonite; N =  not significant; S = significant difference (see text).    288    X, 65 -+ 1.5%. In two-tailed "t-statistic" testing of means and standard devia-  tions, the clay-mineral compositions differ significantly in the I and X com-  ponents but not in the K component.  The Peoria loess is now examined to determine if there are any clay-mineral  zones within it such as in Illinois (Glass et al., 1968; Frye et al., 1968). By  visual inspection (Fig. 2), composition changes seem to be at depths of 2.8  and 6.4 m and at the Farmdale loess contact at 10.4 m depth. The Peoria loess  loess samples are grouped within the three zones, and means and standard  deviations are tested by a two-tailed t-test. The only significant differences  are in the K distribution at 6.4 m, in the I distribution at 2.8 m and the  Farmdale contact at 10.4 m, and in the X distribution at 10.4 m. The only  boundary where two of the components differ is at the contact with the  Farmdale loess. Within the vermiculite or 14   fraction of the X component,  significant differences by t-test are at depths of 6.1, 8.5, and 10.4 m. Again,  the only coincident difference is at the contact with the Farmdale loess. Clay-  mineral zoning is obscure, at best, in the Peoria loess in the New Harmony  section.    Patoka section (Fig. 1, P)    The Patoka section also is a road cut in the bluffs bordering the Wabash  River Valley. Peoria loess is 9.8 m thick and beneath a ground soil (the soil  at the ground}, and exclusive of a bed of sand at depths of 1.4 to 1.7 m, has  quite uniform clay, fine silt, coarse silt, sand, and CaCO3 contents (Fig. 3).  Dark~colored bands (Daniels et al., 1960; Ruhe et al., 1971) occur at depths  of 1.0 and 1.9 m. The lower brown, noncalcareous Farmdale loess is 60 cm    o%  20   4.o   6o   8o  i00  r~4   ;      PATOKA  --SB 8    '~         6~m ~~62~  ---  12  Rw                             I    I    I  J.    t   I  5O%  0    0%  K    CoC05o  20     40     60      0%   20     40  '  ' x~-'~'__~i '  '   ~'~'+_    '  --SZ-  o"  14AO               I00  17 IOO          o    Fig. 3. Particle~ize, clay-mineral, and CaCO~ distributions in the Patoka section. Addi-  tional symbols: B = B horizon of ground soil; stippled = darkcolored bands; S ffi sand bed;  RW = weathered bedrock.    289    thick and rests on the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in siltstone  bedrock. Clay, silt, sand, and CaCO3 contents abruptly change across the  Peoria--Farmdale loess boundary.  The mean clay-mineral composition of the Peoria loess is K, 14 + 2.1%;  I, 58 + 7.9%; and X, 31 + 7.4% and is very similar to that at New Harmony.  The mean composition of the Farmdale loess is K, 18 + 1.0%; I, 31 -+ 5.2%;  and X, 50 + 3.2%. By t-test the compositions significantly differ among the  three components and also in the 14 A part of the X component.  Visual inspection of the clay-mineral distributions in the Peoria loess (Fig.  3) suggest possible changes at depths of 2.4, 4.5,7.4, and 8.5 m as well as at  the contact with the Farmdale loess. Applying the same testing technique as  at New Harmony, significant differences in the I and X components occur  only at depths of 2.4 and 8.5 m. Above 2.4 m the loess is complicated by the  inclusions of the sand bed and the dark-colored bands. The sand of local  origin and the dark-colored bands, whether "incipient soils" (Daniels et al.,  1960} or local ground surfaces reworked by slope wash during pauses in loess  deposition (Ruhe et al., 1971), could cause changes in clay-mineral composi-  tion.  In the Peoria loess below 8.5 m the K, I, X, and 14 A components change  progressively toward the composition of the Farmdale loess and in turn to  the composition of the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in bedrock.  These changes suggest that the landscape of the Sangamon Soil and its sub-  strata were a source of materials for the Farmdale loess and even the basal  part of the Peoria loess.    Cumback section {Fig. 1, C)    The Cumback section is a road cut in the upland near the confluence of  the East and West Forks of the White River. The Peoria loess is 3.5 mm thick  and overlies 50 cm of Farmdale loess which rests on the Bb horizon of the  Sangamon Soil formed in a sandy, siltstone bedrock. Beneath the solum of  the ground soil formed in sand, textural properties and the CaCO3 content  of the Peoria loess progressively change downward, and the changes continue  into and through the lower Farmdale loess and into the Bb horizon of the  Sangamon Soft. The trends of these changes {Fig. 4} are so systematic that  they may be expressed mathematically in depth-trend analysis:  &lt;2 pm clay (%) = 21.9 -- 13.47 D + 3.203 D2 where R2 = 0.74  16 pm fine silt (%) = 16.8 + 1.42 D + 1.696 D2 where R2 = 0.85  62 pm sand (%) = 67.9 -- 54.4 D + 10.86 D2 where R2 = 0.98  CaCO3 (%) = --18.5 + 49.57 D -- 12.225 D2 where R2 = 0.98  and where D is depth and R2 (100) is the % of the variation expressed by  the equation. Similar trends are in the clay-mineral distributions:  K (%) = 23.9- 18.32 D + 5.15 D2 where R2 = 0.92  I (%) = 38.4 + 27.25D- 7.05 D2 where R2 = 0.92  14 A (%) = 73.8 - 56.75 D + 14.75 D2 where R2 = 0.90    290    0%     20        40       60         80      I00    "Bt  I !7o  3     F'n     6u.m        6 2  o          4   2b ' ;    CQC03o  0%  20    40   60   80  0%  20    40  1  '  '  '  '  '  '  '  '              --1  j  K ~' q~,:  tl    4              ,  o                   o  o0     ,%    Fig. 4. Particle-size, clay-mineral, and CaCO3 distributions in the Cumback section. Addi-  tional symbols: Ap, B1, B2, B3 are horizons of ground soil. Smooth curves below sand  zone (S) are mathematically fitted (see text).    These trends in physical and mineralogic properties indicate that the com-  position of the Farmdale loess and about a meter of the lower part of the  Peoria loess relate to the composition of the materials of the Sangamon Soft  landscape which they bury. That landscape was the ground surface prior to  Wisconsinan loess depos~ion and until 25,000 to 20,000 years ago. Ordinary  subaerial erosion of that landscape could have supplied debris to streams and  their valleys. This nonglacial debris could then have been the source for loess  that was blown to the uplands and deposited there. The progressive domi-  nance of contributions to Peoria loess from glacial debris in the source  valleys is indicated by progressive decrease upward to a depth of 2.75 m of  the 2 #m clay, the fine silt, the sand, and the K and the 14 A clay-mineral  components and also the progressive increase in the coarse silt, CaCO3, and  the I clay-mineral component. All of these properties of the Peoria loess  between depths of 1.5 and 2.75 m are similar quantitatively to those of the  thick, calcareous loess at New Harmony and Patoka. Conversely, downward  below 2.75 m the progressive dominance of the nonglacial material is indi-  cated by the depth trends.  The depth trends also negate any possibility of stratigraphically zoning the  Peoria loess on the basis of clay-mineral composition. In fact, when compar-  ing this section to New Harmony and Patoka sections, demonstration of the  occurrence of clay-mineral zones that have any regional significance would  be impossible.    291    The other sections along the Wabash Valley (Fig. 1) were analyzed similar-  ly to the foregoing three sections. The mean clay-mineral composition of the  Peoria loess of all sections is K, 13 + 2.1%; I, 56 + 5.6%; and X, 33 + 6.5%  (Table I). Possible nonglacial increments as at Cumback were excluded in the  analysis. The glacial tills in these sections have a mean clay-mineral composi-  tion of K, 15 + 5.9%; I, 53 + 19%; and X, 33 + 19%. The similarity of loess  composition to glacial source material is evident, and in the Peoria loess, I  greatly dominates X which in turn greatly dominates K in quantity. Compar-  ison can be made now to the Ohio Valley province.    TABLEI    Summarized means and standard deviations of clay-mineral components of stratigraphic  sections    Unit                n*  K(%)    I(%)     X(%)     14A (of X)    Peoria loess (Wabash)    56   13 2.1  56 +  5.6  33 -+  5.6  34 10  Peoria loess (Ohio)      54   22 2.1  30 +  6.8  47  4.6  80  7.6  Farmdale loess          20   20 4.6  30  9.0  48 12    58 26    Sangamon Soil  B horizon/till :  Wabash            42   14-+ 5.4  22 6.3  62 8.0  62-+ 28  Ohio              17     92.5  28 7.1  62 3.2  1016    Sangamon Soil  B horizon/rock       24   35 5.2  28 -+ 10    33  9.1  55 39    Glacial till :  Wabash               20   155.9  5319    33-+ 19    6122  Ohio                 19     51.5  57-+ 10    42+  9.2  1420    *n is number of samples; K is kaolinite; I is illite; X is expandable clay minerals (14--17A);  and 14A is estimate of proportion .of 14A clay minerals in 14--17A range with numerical  base of 100. E K, I, X = 100 + 4.    OHIO VALLEY PROVINCE    Bayou Creek section (Fig. 1, BC)    Bayou Creek section is the first site up the Ohio Valley above the mouth  of the Wabash River and is a borrow pit in a bluff forming the north valley  wall. Peoria loess is 5 m thick and is leached of CaCO3 to a depth of 2.5 m  (Fig. 5). The CaCO3 content is 15--20% in the calcareous loess and is 5--15%  less than in the Peoria loess in the three sections described in the Wabash  province. The Peoria loess at Bayou Creek overlies 90 cm of brown, noncal-  careous Farmdale loess which rests on the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil  formed in shale bedrock.    292    'I  B2    0%  0  ,E    21    I    4    4_    20   40   60   80  I00  OU CREEK  m        62/Xm   .....  /  I  I..~A  20%   0    O%  I    20   40   60  o  14AO  17  I00    CoC05o  0%   20     40  II1~  0    Fig. 5. Particle~size, clay-mineral, and CaCO3 distributions in the Bayou Creek section.  Additional symbols: C = C horizon of ground soil; o/= oxidized and leached.    The mean clay-mineral composition of the leached and calcareous Peoria  loess is K, 15 + 3.1%; I, 42 + 4.9%; and X, 45 + 4.5%. The mean composition  of the Farmdale loess is K, 19 -+ 3.5%; I, 25 + 3.5%; and X, 55 + 6.6%. The  composition of the Peoria loess differs distinctly from the sections in the  Wabash province. The I and X components are almost equivalent in contrast  to the great dominance of I over X in the Wabash Valley area. The composi-  tions of the Farmdale loess, however, are similar.  The K and 14 A components progressively increase and the I component  progressively decreases from the lower part of the Peoria loess downward  through the Farmdale loess and into the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil.  Depth trends can be fitted as at Cumback. The impact of the old soil land-  scape and bedrock terrain is again indicated by these relations.    Troy section (Fig. 1, T)    The Troy section is farther up the Ohio Valley and is an upland road cut  in the bluffs bordering the valley. Peoria loess is 2.75 m thick, is noncal-  careous, and overlies 30 cm of brown, noncalcareous Farrndale loess that  rests on the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in shale bedrock (Fig.  6).  The mean clay-mineral composition of the Peoria loess is K, 18 3.0%; I,  45 + 5.0%; and X, 39 + 5.2%. The mean composition of the Farmdale loess is  K, 22 + 1.0%; I, 20 1.4%; and X, 56 t.5%. In comparison to the Bayou  Creek section, K content is slightly greater in both Peoria and Farmdale loess,  The 14 A component has very little change upward from the Bb horizon of  the Sangamon Soil thro~ ~ Farmdale loess and the noncalcareous Peoria  loess (Fig. 6). Although the Peoria loess thins away from the Ohio Valley to    293    0%  20    40    60    80   I00  0%  20    40    60    , ' ' ' 1 I' "  20%L~~                  ,14~,0  E  ,  I  17 I00         0    Fig. 6. Particle-size and clay-mineral distributions in the Troy section.    less than a meter in thickness in the nonglacial reentrant, the unique clay-  mineral composition, with dominance of the 14 A fraction of the X com-  ponent, can be traced through considerable distance from the valley (Fig. 1,  O). The impact of the old soil landscape and bedrock terrain is emphasized  by the mineral association.    Madison section (Fig. 1, M)    The Madison section is again farther upstream and is a drill core site on an  upland summit near the OhioValley wall. Peoria loess is 1.85 m thick and  directly overlies the Bb horizon of the Sangamon Soil formed in IUinoian till.  Farmdale loess is not identifiable in the section, and the contact zone of  Peoria loess and Sangamon Soil is complicated by the presence of a fragipan  (Fig. 7, BX horizons; Ruhe et al., 1974).  Even with these pedological complications the Peoria loess is readily  separated by the clay-mineral assemblages (Fig. 7). The mean clay-mineral  composition of Peoria loess is K, 21 -+ 2.5%; I, 29 + 3.3%; and X, 47 -+ 4.4%.  The 14 A fraction dominates the X component. At the contact with the Bb  horizon of the Sangamon Soft, K abruptly decreases to 7%, I and X abruptly  increase to 40 and 53%, respectively, and the 17 A fraction dominates the X  component.  Of pedological significance is the alteration sequence of the clay minerals  in the Bt and upper part of the BX horizons in the solum of the ground soil in  Peoria loess. Between depths of 0.2 and 1.15 m, the &lt;2 pm clay has a pro-    294    nounced increase. The I clay-mineral component has a corresponding de-  crease, and the X component has an increase. Within the X component, the  17 A fraction increases at the expense of a decrease of the 14 A fraction. Illite  (I) apparently alters to montmorillonite (17 A).  In comparison to the clay mineralogy in sections at Troy and Bayou Creek,  the X component in Peoria loess at Madison greatly dominates the ! com-  ponent which in turn is greater than the K component. The amounts of K and  X increase up-valley in the Ohio province. In this upper part of the province  similar clay-mineral relations also occur away from the valley as the Peoria  loess thins {Fig. 1, R1, R2).  oQIK  0%    20        40        60        80      I00     0%    20        40        60           0   2    4    6    8   tO  ~b  2F-  C.c  I                                      \'b  I 4_                            I   I           DS N I             J   l   I   I  40% 20   0                    4,~ 0          I00  17 I00        0  Fig. 7. Particle~ize, cla4y-mineral, and quartz-kaolinite ratio (Q/K} distribution in the  Madison section. Additional symbols: BX = fragipan horizon;//, II1, IV = field-determined  lithology changes; Bb = horizons of Sangamon Soil; Cc = calcareous C horizon.    DISCUSSION AND SUMMARY    In the discussions of the individual sections, the obvious differences have  been indicated between the clay-mineral suites in the Peoria loess in the  Wabash province and in the Ohio province, If the mean clay-minexal composi-  tion of all samples of Peoria loess for each province {Fig. 1) are compared,  the distinct difference is more evident {Table I). The mean compositions are:  Peoria loess (Wabash)--K, 13 + 2.1%; I, 56 + 5.6%; and X, 33 + 6.5% where  14 A is 34 + 10%; Peoria loess (Ohio)--K, 22 + 2.1%; I, 30 + 6.8%; and X,  47 + 4.6% where 14 A is 80 + 7.6%. The differences are significant in two-  tailed t~tatistic testing (Table II). The t value for each of the four com-    TABLE II  Comparison of means and standard deviations of clay-mineral components by use of t-statistic    295    Pairs                                  df*    t, 95%    K           I           X           14A    Peoria loess  Wabash vs. Ohio                   108   1.98      --20.30      21.39    --13.05    --27.12    Peoria loess (Wabash) vs.  Farm dale loess                    74   2.00       --8.14      14.65     --6.85     --5.74  Sangamon Soil B horizon/till       98   1.99      (---0.04)     27.68    --19.83      --6.79  Sangamon Soil B horizon/rock     88   1.99     --25.65      15.22      (0.09)     --3.76  Glacial till (Wabash)            74  2.00     (--1.59)    (1.11)    (0.09)    --7.40    Peoria loess (Ohio) vs.  Farmdale loess                    72   2.00       (2.11)     (0.09)    (---0.40)      5.60  Sangamon Soil B horizon/till       71   2.00        20.95       (0.96)    --12.51      24.62  Sangamon Soil B horizon/rock     76   1.99      --15.62       (0.94)       9.07        4.47  Glacial till (Ohio)                 71   2.00       31.57    --12.56       3.38      20.10    Farmdale loess vs.  Sangarnon Soil B horizon/till  Wabash                        60   2.00        4.43       3.91     --5.52      (0.47)  Ohio                          35   2.03        8.70      (0.61)    --4.71       6.45    Sangamon Soil B horizon/rock        42   2.02       --9.59       (0.57)       4.64       (0.26)    Glacial till  Wabash                           38   2.02        2.83     --4.66       2.95      (0.44)  Ohio                                37   2.02        13.00      --8.48       (1.82)       5.76    *df is degrees of freedom and t-statistic at 95% level of confidence; (t) means no significant difference  between pairs.    ponents greatly exceeds the t value for pairs at the 95% confidence limit.  The Farmdale loess, however, does not differ in clay-mineral composition  between the provinces. Its mean composition for all samples is K, 20 + 4.6%;  I, 30 + 9.0%; and X, 48 + 12%. This composition differs from Peoria loess of  the Wabash province (Tables I, II) but does not differ significantly from the  composition of the Peoria loess of the Ohio province. In this last pairing the  t values for I and X fall within the t value for the 95% confidence limit, and  the value for K only slightly exceeds the critical value.  In order to determine the possible source materials for clay-mineral com-  ponents of Peoria loess and Farmdale loess, comparisons are made between  the compositions of these loesses and the other materials with which they are  associated in the field. On the basis of all samples, Peoria loess is successively  compared to Farmdale loess, to the Sangamon Soil B horizon formed in  glacial till, to the Sangamon Soil B horizon formed in bedrock, and to the  glacial till. The Farmdale loess is similarly analyzed. Other pairings also are  tested (Tables I, II). Within this analytical array, three relations emerge. The  clay-mineral compositions of the Peoria loess and glacial tills in the Wabash  province are similar in major components. There are no statistically significant  differences between paired K, I, or X (Table II). Glacial sediments are the  dominant source materials for the clay-mineral composition of the Peoria  loess in the thicker loess belt. As noted in the introduction about 91% of the  Wabash Basin is covered with glacial drift.    296    A second relation is the similarity in part of the composition of Farmdale  loess and the Sangamon Soil B horizon formed in bedrock. If the 14 A com-  ponent is included in the analysis, then two of four of the clay-mineral com-  ponents do not differ statistically, I and 14 A. A third relation is the similar-  ity of compositions of Peoria loess of the Ohio province and the Farmdale  loess. There are no significant differences in the I and X components, and the  t-value of K only slightly exceeds the value at the 95% confidence limit  {Table II).  The upward continuity of clay-mineral composition from the paleosol into  overlying Farmdale loess and even the Peoria.loess was discussed previously  for the Bayou Creek, Cumback, and Troy sections where the Paleosol is  formed in bedrock. In general, the Wisconsinan loess is thinner in the bedrock  region and throughout the Ohio province. The impact of source materials  from the paleosol terrain on bedrock probably accounts for similarity in part  of clay-mineral composition of paleosol to Farmdale loess and in turn to  Peoria loess in the Ohio province. As noted in the introduction, about 77% of  the Ohio Basin is nonglacial terrain. Alluvium derived from erosion of that  terrain was carried by the Ohio River during Farmdalian and Peorian times.  Debris deposited along the valley could have been the source for loess onto  the uplands.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Elizabeth Matney did the X-ray powder diffraction work in the laboratory.  Parts of the field studies were done in Quaternary geology with H.H. Gray  and N.K. Bleuer, indiana Geological Survey and in soils with A.K. NickeU  and K.M. McWilliams, Soil Conservation Service, U.S. Department of Agricul-  ture. Radiocarbon dating was provided by M. Rubin, U.S. Geological Survey  (W&lt;lates) and D.D. Coleman, Illinois Geological Survey (ISGS~lates). Their  cooperative work is appreciated.    REFERENCES    Caldwell, R.E. and White, J.L., 1956. A study of the origin and distribution of loess in  southern Indiana. Soll Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 20: 258--263.  Daniels, R.B., Handy, R.L. and Simormon, G.H., 1960. Dark-colored bands in the thick  loess of Western Iowa. J. Geol., 68: 450--458~  Fehrenbacher, J.B., White, J.L., Ulrich, H.P. and Ode]/, R.T., 1965. Loess distribution in  southeastern Illinois and southwestern Indiana. Soil Sci. Am. Proc., 29: 566--572.  Frazee, C.G., Fehrenbacher, J.B. and Krumbein, W.C., 1970. Loess distribution from a  source. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 296--301.  Frye, J.C., Glass, H.D. and Wiilman, H.B., 1968. Mineral zonation of Woodfordian loesses  of Illinois. Ill. Geol. Surv. Circ., 427, 44 pp.  Glass, H.D., Frye, J.C. and Willman, H.B., 1968. Clay mineral composition, a source in-  dicator of Midwest loem. In: The Quaternary of Illinois. University of Illinois, College  of Agriculture, Spec. Publ., 14: 35---40.    297    Hall, R.D., 1973. Sedimentation and Alteration of loess in Southwestern Indiana. Thesis,  Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind., 103 pp.  Kleiss, H.J., 1973. Loess distribution along the Illinois soil-development sequence. Soil  Sci., 115: 194--198.  Mankin, C.J. and Dodd, C.G., 1963. Proposed reference illite from the Quachita Moun-  tains of southeastern Oklahoma. In: E. Ingerson (Editor), Clays and Clay Minerals.  Proc. 10th Natl. Conf. Clays Clay Minerals. MacMillan, New York, N.Y., 10: 372--379.  Ruhe, R.V., 1969. Quaternary Landscapes in Iowa. Iowa State University Press, Ames,  Iowa, 255 pp.  Ruhe, R.V., 1976. Stratigraphy of mid-continent loess, U.S.A. In: W.C. Mahaney  (Editor), Quaternary Stratigraphy of North America. Dowden, Hutchinson, Ross,  Stroudsburg, Penn., pp. 197--211.  Ruhe, R.V. and Olson, C.G., 1979. Estimate of clay-mineral content: Additions of propor.  tions of soil clay to constant standard. Clays Clay Miner., 27 : 322--326.  Ruhe, R.V., Miller, G.A. and Vreekan, W.J., 1971. Paleosols, loess sedimentation and soil  stratigraphy. In: D.H. Yaalon (Editor), Paleopedology -- Origin, Nature and Dating of  Paleosols. Hebrew Universities Press, Jerusalem, pp. 41--60.  Ruhe, R.V., Hall, R.D. and Canepa, A.P., 1974. Sangamon paleosols of southwestern  Indiana, U.S.A. Geoderma, 12: 191--200.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Handbook  18,503 pp. (Supplement, 1962, pp. 173--188).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           AbstractClay-mineral compositions of Peoria loess of later Wisconsinan age derived from Wabash Basin and Ohio Basin riverine sources differ in southern Indiana. In the Wabash province the composition is illite &gt; expandable clay minerals &gt; kaolinite and relates to the clay-mineral composition of glacial drift in the basin of 91% glacial cover. In the Ohio province the composition is expandable clay minerals &gt; or Ã¢Â‹Â illite &gt; kaolinite and relates indirectly to the clay-mineral composition of the Sangamon Soil terrain on bedrock. Above the confluent Wabash Basin, 77% of the Ohio Basin is unglaciated. The clay-mineral composition of thin Farmdale loess of earlier Wisconsinan age also relates to the composition of the paleosol terrain. During Peorian time while glacial outwash was supplying loess source materials to the valleys in the Wabash Basin, ordinary alluvium derived from soils and bedrock in unglaciated terrain was supplying loess source materials to the valleys in the Ohio Basin.