 327    CONTENTS VOLUME 25, 1981    Flow resistance in soil and plant during field growth of oats  W. Ehlers, K. Grimme, K. Baeumer, R .~t~ilpnagel, U. KSpke and W. BShm  (GSttingen, F.R.G.)  ................................................  1  The movement of soil materials during a rainy season in western Nigeria  L.A. Lewis (Worcester, Mass., U.S.A.)  ..................................  13  A pedological investigation of an archaeological site in Ontario, Canada, II. Use of  chemical data to discriminate features of the Benson Site  M.A. Griffith (Kingston, Ont., Canada)  ..................................  27  Wheathering of a soil glauconite in southern England  P.J. Loveland (Harpenden, Great Britain)  ................................  35  Exchange equilibria of potassium versus calcium-plus-magnesium in soils in arid and  semi-arid regions, India  Dalel Singh, Raj Pal and S.R. Poonia (Hissar, India)  .........................  55  Evaluation of criteria for argilic horizons (Bt) of soils in Canada  J.A. McKeague, C. Wang, G.J. Ross, C.J. Acton, R.E. Smith, D.W. Anderson,  W.W. Pettapiece and T.M. Lord (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  ....................  63  Effects of animals on soil  F.D. Hole (Madison, Wisc., U.S.A.)  ....................................  75  Clay-mineral studies of a soil chronosequence in southern Turkey  N. Giizel and M.J. Wilson (Aberdeen, Great Britain)  ......................  113  Characterisation of some spodic horir as of the Campine (Belgium), with dithionite-  citrate, pyrophosphate and sodium hydroxide-tetraborate  T. Higashi, F. de Coninck and F. Gelaude (Ghent, Belgium)  ..................  131  Current Titles in Soil Science  ...........................................  143  Calcium carbonate nodules in soils: ~ aO/~ 60 and ~ 3C/~ 2C ratios and ~4C contents  M. Magaritz, A. Kaufman (Rehovo~, Israel) and D.H. Yaalon (Jerusalem, Israel).. 157  Chemical and mineralogical trends in a chronosequence developed on alluvium in  eastern Victoria, Australia  I.P. Little and W.T. Ward (St. Lucia, Qid., Australia)  ......................  173  Imogolite in cemented horizons of some British Columbia soils  J.A. McKeague and H. Kodama (Ottawa, Ont., Canada)  ....................  189  Clay influence on the crystallization of aluminum hydroxide polymorphs in the  presence of citrate, sulfate or chloride  A. Violante and M.L. Jackson (Madison, Wisc., U.S.A.)  ....................  199  Soil erosion problems on alfisols in Western Nigeria, VI. Effects of erosion on experi-  mental plots  R. Lal (Ibadan, Nigeria)  ...........................................  215  The soils of the Faeroe Islands  G.K. Rutherford (Kingston, Ont., Canada) and C.E.B. Taylor (Toronto, Ont.,  Canada)  .........................................................  231  Gehalte an organischer Substanz, Schwermetallen und Phosphor in Dichtefraktio-  hen yon fluvialen Unterwasserb6den (Distribution of organic matter, heavy  metals and phosphorus among speciIi,~ gravity fractions of fluvial Unterwasser-  bSden)  R. Lichtfluss und G. Briimmer (Kiel, Bundesrepublik Deutschland)  ..........  245  Crop yield predictions based on properties of soils in Sevilla, Spain  D. de la Rosa, F. Cardona and J. Almorza (Sevilla, Spain)  .................  26',"    328    Time responses of sugar beet germination, oxygen diffusion and redox potential  to crust formation, polyacrylamide stabilization and peroxide fertilization  F. Callebaut (Ghent, Belgium), D. Gabriels (Brussels, Belgium) and M. de  Boodt (Ghent, Belgium)  ...........................................  275  Comparison of sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and sodium pyrophosphate as extrac-  tants of Al/Fe--humus "complexes" in Dystrandepts, Japan  T. Higashi and A. Shinagawa (Kagoshima, Japan)  ........................  285    Book Reviews  Silcrete in Australia, by T. Langford-Sndth (Editor) -- M. Kastner  .............  293  Geochemistry of Colloid Systems for Earth Scientists, by S. Yariv and H. Cross-  A. Nissenbaum  ..................................................  294  Environment Impact Assessment, Principles and Procedures, by R.E. Munn (Editor)  -- P.M. Fleming  .................................................  294  Constituants et Propri~t~s du Sol, by M. Bonneau and B. Souchier -- D. Baize  ......  296  Major Soils and Soil Regions in The Netherlands, by H. de Bakker -- D. Bent  ......  298  Evolution Superficielle des Roches Cristallines et Cristallophylliennes dan~ iqs  R~gions Temper~es, by J. Delou, J. Guyot and M. Robert -- Y. Tardy  ........  299  Uses of Soil Information Systems- L.A. Nelson  ...........................  299  Factual Data Banks in Agriculture -- L.A. Nelson  ..........................  301  P~dologie appliqu~e, by J. Boulaine -- D. Baize  .............................  303  Land Assessment in Scotland, by M.F. Thomas and J.T. Coppock (Editors)  -- G.E.D. Cole  ....................................................  304    Current Titles in Soil Science  ...........................................  307  Contents Volume 25, 1981  ...........................................  327                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     