 Geoderma, 32 (1984) 347--357                                                     347  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    AI-Taweel, Bashir Hashim. Soil genesis in relation to groundwater regimes in a hummocky ground  moraine area near Hamiota, Manitoba: Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada.  available from: National Library of Canada.  Alvarado, Alfredo. Phosphate retention in Andepts from Guatemala and Costa Rica as related to other  soil properties: 89 p., Doctoral, 1982, North Carolina State Univ., Raleigh. NC. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Anderson, T. W.  Preliminary evidence for late Wisconsinan climatic fluctuations from pollen  stratigraphy in Burin Peninsula, Newfoundland: Paper - Geological Survey of Canada, 83-1 B, p. 185-  188 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1983. (Current research, Part B).  Arkhipov, N. P.; Zyrin, N. G.; Rerikh, V. I.; et aL Influence of application of Tertiary clays on trace  element content of soils and plants: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 63-66, 4 tables,  1982.  Assaad, F. F.; Shams, M. S.; Sabet, V.; et aL Thermodynamic considerations on the reversibility of the  exchange reaction Na-Ca clay soil: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(2), p. 123-133. illus. (incl. 2  tables), 1982.  Atwater, Brian F.; Waitt, Richard B., Jr.; Colman, Steven (leaders); et aL Guidebook for field trip of  Rocky Mountain Cell, August 26-28, 1983; Day l, Jokulhlaups into the Sanpoil Arm of glacial Lake  Columbia, Washington; Day 2, Jokulhlaups near Spokane, Washington and Lewiston, Idaho; Day 3,  Glacial sequence near McCall, Idaho: 29 p., illus. (incl. 2 tables, strat, col.s, sects., geol. sketch map),  Friends of the Pleistocene, United States, 1983.  Basta, E. Z.; Philip, G.; and Halaka, S. G. Mineralogical studies on the clay fractions of some soil  sediments from E1 Beheira Governorate, El Tahrir Province and Wadi El Natrun area, north and south  of Nubariya Canal, Egypt: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(2), p. 111-122, illus. (incl. 2 tables,  sketch map), 1982.  Beedlow, P. A.; Cadwell, L. L.; and McShane, M. C. Designing surface covers; an approach to long-  term waste site stabilization: in Waste management '83; Waste isolation in the U.S., technical programs  and public education; proceedings of the symposium on waste management; Volume 2, Waste regulations  and programs; high-level waste (Post, Roy G.. editor; et aL), p. 31 l-314, illus., 1983. available from: Univ.  Ariz., Coll. Eng., Tucson, AZ, United States.  Bellotti, R.; Ghionna, V.; Jamiolkowski, i.; et aL  Ko-OCR relationships in soils; discussions and  closure: Journal of Geotechnical Engineering, 109(6), p. 859-869, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1983.  Berner, Robert A.; Lasaga, Antonio C.; and Garrels, Robert M. The carbonate-silicate geochemical  cycle and its effect on atmospheric carbon dioxide over the past 100 million years: American Journal  of Science, 283(7), p. 641-683, illus., 1983.  Bhasker, Rao Kidiyoor.  A water flow-salt transport model to simulate salt efflorescence:  165 p.,  Doctoral, 1982, Utah State Univ., Logan, UT. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Bidin, Abdul-Aziz. Phosphate in Malaysian Ultisols and Oxisols as evaluated by a mechanistic model:  151 p., Doctoral, 1982, Purdue Univ., West Lafayette, IN. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; Boekestein, A.; Curtal, P.; et aL Submicroscopy and chemistry of heavy-metal-  contaminated precipitates from column experiments simulating conditions in a soil beneath a landfill: in  Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aLL Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 1-20, illus. (incl.  1 tables), 1983.    348    Bisdom, E. B. A.; and Dueloux, J. (editors). Submicroscopic studies of soils: Geoderma, 30(1-4), 356  p., illus., 1983.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; Henstra, S.; Werner, H. W.; et al. Quantitative analysis of trace and major elements  in thin sections of soils with the secondary ion microscope (Cameca): in Submicroscopic studies of soils  (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 117-134, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1983.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; and Jongerius, A. SEM-EDXRA studies of precipitates which clogged a water-tube  filter: in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 253-  270, illus., 1983.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; Nauta, R.; and Volbert, B. STEM-EDXRA and SEM-EDXRA investigation of iron-  coated organic matter in thin sections with transmitted, secondary and backscattered electrons:  in  Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; etal.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 77-92, illus., 1983.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; and Schoonderbeek, D. The characterization of the shape of mineral grains in thin  sections of soils by Quantimet and BESI: in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom. E. B. A., editor;  et aL), Geoderma, 30(t-4), p. 303-322, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1983.  Bisdom, E. B. A.; Thiel, F.; Volbert, B.; et al. Variations in backscattered electron (BSE) images with  a scanning electron microscope (SEM) as applied to mineral grains and excrements in a Podzol, to  precipitates on a water-tube filter and to bauxite: in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A.,  editor; et al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 93-116, illus., 1983.  Boghrat, Alireza. The design and construction of a piezoblade and an evaluation of the Marchetti  dilatometer in some Florida soils: 334 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Florida, Gainsville, FL. available from:  Univ. Microfilms.  Brooks, Robert Richard. Biological methods of prospecting for minerals: 322 p., illus. (incl. tables).  John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United States, 1983.  Bugel'skiy, Yu. Yu,; Vltovskaya, I. V.; Nikitina, A. P.; etaL Zakonomernosti formirovaniya orudeneniya  v kore vyvetrivaniya [Formation mechanisms for mineralization in weathering crust]:  in Problemy  petrologii, mineralogii i rudogeneza (Chukhrov, F. V., editor; et al.), p. 56-60, Izd. Nauka, Moscow,  USSR, 1983.  Busacea, Alan Jmes.  Geologic history and soil development, northeastern Sacramento Valley,  California: 372 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of California, Davis, CA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Carter, Cade E.; McDaniei, Victor; and Beagtson, R. L. Potential for subsurface drainage in the Lower  Mississippi Valley: inAdvances in drainage (Willardson, Lyman S., chairperson), Proceedings - National  Drainage Symposium, 4, p. 23-33, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1982. (ASAE Publ. 12-82).  Casagrande, D. J.; and Ferguson, A. The distribution of fatty acids in coal precursors in the Okefenokee  Swamp, Georgia: in Advances in organic geochemistry, 1981 (Bjoroy, M., editor; et al.), Proceedings of  the International Meeting on Organic Geochemistry, 10, p. 628-634, illus., 1983. (A Wiley Heyden  publication).  Castillo, Rolando. Geoquimica ambiental de la Peninsula de Nicoya; comparacion entre horizontes de  suelo [Environmental geochemistry of Nicoya Peninsula; comparison between soil horizons]: Informe  Semestral - Instituto Geografico Nacional, Enero a junio, p. 27-70, 1982.  Catto, N.R. Loess in the Cypress Hills, Alberta, Canada: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal  Canadien des Sciences de la Terre, 20(7), p. 1159-1167 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. I table, sketch  maps), 1983.  Chartres, C.J. The pedogenesis of desert loam soils in the Barrier Range, western New South Wales;  ll, Weathering and soil formation: Australian Journal ofSoil Research, 21(1),p. 1-13, illus.(incl. 1 table),  1983.  Chela, Y.; Bmfia, A.; and Boroehoviteh, A. Effect of potassium on soil structure in relation to hydraulic  conductivity: in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aD, Geoderma, 30(1-4),  p. 135-147, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1983.  Childls, C. W.; Downs, C. $.; and Wells, N. Hydrous iron oxide minerals with short range order  deposited in a spring/stream system, Tongariro National Park, New Zealand: Australian Journal of Soil  Research, 20(2), p. 119-129, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch maps), 1982.    349    Chretien, J.; and Bisdom, E. B. A. The development of soil porosity in experimental sandy soils with  clay admixtures as examined by Quantimet 720 from BESI and by other techniques: in Submicroscopic  studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; etaL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 285-302, illus. (incl. 1 table). 1983.  Cowart, James B. Geological age determinations by non-radiometric methods [abstr.]: in 32nd annual  meeting, Southeastern Section, Geological Society of America; with the Southeast Section of the  National Association of Geology Teachers and the Southeastern Section of the Paleontological Society.  Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 15(2), p. 49, 1983.  Cranweli, P. A.  Alkyl esters in Recent sediments of two productive lakes: in Advances in organic  geochemistry, 1981 (Bjoroy, M., editor; et al.), Proceedings of the International Meeting on Organic  Geochemistry, 10, p. 299-308, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1983. (A Wiley Heyden publication).  Creasey, Dale. Increased irrigation efficiency will ultimately silence the water-short blues of the wasteful  West: Ground Water, 21(4),p. 485, 1983.  Culling, W. E. H. Steady state distributions in the measurement of soil creep: Geographical Analysis.  15(3), p. 212-230. illus., 1983.  Cundy, Terrance William. An analysis of the effects of spatial variability of point infiltration rates on  the comparison of small and large plot rainfall-runoff:  137 p., Doctoral, 1982, Utah State Univ., Logan,  UT. availablefrorn: Univ. Microfilms.  Debose, Alfonso; and Klungland, Miehael W. Soil survey of Snohomish County area, Washington: 197  p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington. DC, United States, 1983. (Publ. in coop. with Wash. State Dep. Nat.  Resour,; Wash. State Univ., Agric. Res. Cent.).  Delgado Calvo-Flores, R.; Barahona, E.; and Linares, J. Factores formadores de los suelos de la Cuenca  alta del Rio Dilar (Sierra Nevada) [Formational factors of soils of the upper Dilar Basin, Sierra Nevada]:  Anales de Edafologia y Agrobiologia, 41(1-2), p. 21-37 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map),  1982.  Diment, Glen Aroun. Analysis of wetting front instability in unsaturated porous materials: Doctoral,  1982, Univ. of New South Wales, Australia. availablefrorn: Univ. Microfilms.  Doering, E. J.; Benz, L. C.; and Reiehman, G.A. Shallow-water-table concept for drainage design in  semiarid and subhumid regions:  in Advances in drainage (Willardson, Lyman S., chairperson).  Proceedings - National Drainage Symposium, 4, p. 34-41, illus., 1982. (ASAE Publ. 12-82).  Dorioz, J. M.; and Rober, M.  Etude experimentale de l'interaction entre champignons et argile;  consequences sur la microstructure des sols [Experimental study of interaction between mushrooms and  clay; effects of soil ultrastructure]: Comptes-Rendus des Seances de l'Academie des Sciences, Serie 2:  Mecanique-Physique, Chimie, Sciences de l'Univers, Sciences de la Terre, 295(4), p. 511-516 (incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. plate), 1982.  Dredge, L.A. Surficial geology of the Sept-lies area, Quebec north shore: Memoir - Geological Survey  of Canada, 408, 40 p. (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 8 anal., geol. sketch maps; colored geomorphol.  map 1:250,000), 1983.  Drees, L. R.; and Wilding, L.P. Microradiography as a submicroscopic tool: in Submicroscopic studies  of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 65-76, illus., 1983.  Dronova, T. Ya. Processes by which argillic material is converted in podzolized Brown forest soils on  graded clay deposits:  Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 41-48, illus. (incl. 5 tables),  1982.  Edlund, S. A.  Reconnaissance vegetation studies on western Victoria Island, Canadian Arctic  Archipelago: Paper - Geological Survey of Canada, 83-1 B, p. 75-81 (incl. French sum.). 1983. (Current  research, Part B).  El-Attar, H. A.A. Soil and land use classifications of northern Oman: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science,  22(1), p. 97-109, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1982.  EI-Badry, D. D.; and El-Sherif, A. F. Sulphate determination in some alluvial soils of Egypt: Egyptian  Journal of Soil Science, 22(2), p. 207-211, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  EI-Demerdashe, S.; EI-Kadi, H. A.; Foda, M. S.; et al. Manganese adsorption isotherms on some clay  minerals:  Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(2), p. 199-205, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.    350    EI-Kholei, M. S.; Hamdi, H.; and Wasif, S. A comparative study of the effect of cations and anions  on hydrolysis and nitrification of urea phosphate: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(2). p. 189-197.  illus., 1982.  EI-Kholei, M. S.; Wasif, S.; and Hamdi, H. Comparative effects of varying levels of chlorides, sulphates  and carbonates of sodium, potassium, calcium and magnesium on hydrolysis and nitrification of urea in  soil: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science. 22(2), p. 179-187, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1982.  EI-Shazly, M. A.; Harga, A. A.; and Hammad, M. Simplified technique for preparation of thin section  of soils and unconsolidated materials: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(1), p. 53-56, illus. (incl. I  table), 1982.  Elwan, A. A.; Kassem, Y. S.; and Harga, A.A. A note on the soils of Adendan area, southeastern part  of Egypt: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science. 22(2), p, 163-177, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Filippini, Mark G.; and Krothe, Noel C.  The impact of urbanization on a flood-plain aquifer;  Bloomington, Indiana: Technical Report - Purdue University, Water Resources Research Center, 156,  103 p., illus. (incl. strat, col., sketch maps), 1983.  Foda, M. S.;.,EI,Kadi, H. A.; EI-Demerdashe, S.; et al. Effect of temperature on manganese adsorption  by clay minerals: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(1), p. 23-29, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Forsberg, A.; and Bjoroy, M. A sedimentological and organic geochemical study of the Botneheia  Formation, Svalbard, with special emphasis on the effects of weathering on the organic matter in shales:  in Advances in organic geochemistry, 1981 (Bjoroy, M., editor; et al.), Proceedings of the International  Meeting on Organic Geochemistry, 10, p. 60-68. illus. (incl. 1 table, strat, cols., sketch map), 1983. (A  Wiley Heyden publication).  Fuller, Wallace H. Predicting radioactive heavy metal movement through soil: in Waste management  '83; Waste isolation in the U.S., technical programs and public education; proceedings of the symposium  on waste management; Volume 2, Waste regulations and programs; high-level waste (Post, Roy G.,  editor; etal.), p. 341-351, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1983. available from." Univ. Ariz., Coll. Eng., Tucson, AZ.  United States.  Gent, James Albert, Jr. The impact of intensive forest management practices on the physical properties  of lower coastal plain and Piedmont soils: 53 p., Doctoral, 1982, North Carolina State Univ., Raleigh.  NC. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Gerasimenko, N. P. Osobennosti pleystotsenovykh pochvennykh pokrovov Kievskogo Pridneprov'ya  [Pleistocene soil cover of Kiev on the Dniester]: Fizichna Geografiya ta Geomorfologiya (Kiev), 27, p.  111-117, illus., 1982.  Geyh, Mebus A.; Roeselunann, Gunter; Wijmstra, T. A.; et al. The unreliability of t4C dates obtained  from buried sandy Podzols:  in Proceedings of the Eleventh international radiocarbon conference  (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et al.), Radiocarbon, 25(2), p. 409-416, illus. (incl. 2 tables, strat, cols.), 1983.  Ghazy, A. E. M, Pore size distribution, moisture behaviour, their relations to water movement in highly  calcareous soils: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(I), p. 57-67, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1982,  Ghazy, A. E.M. Pore size distribution as affected by aggregation: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science.  22(2), p. 155-161, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Ghazy, A. E. M. The influence of soil structure and fineness of CaCO3 on water movement in highly  calcareous soils: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(2), p. 143-154, illus. (inck 7 tables), 1982.  Ghazy, A. E. M.; and Talha, M. Soil aggregation as affected by CaCO3 fineness: Egyptian Journal of  Soil Science, 22(1), p. 69-81, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Gibson, Gaff G. Vadose pisolite; additional evidence for a shallow marine to supratidal carbonate origin  for the Caballos Novaculite, Trans-Pecos Texas [abstr.]: in 32nd annual meeting, Southeastern Section,  Geological Society of America; with the Southeast Section of the National Association of Geology  Teachers and the Southeastern Section of the Paleontological Society, Abstracts with Programs -  Geological Society of America, 15(2), p. 54, 1983.  Gillmlm, G. P.; and Murtha, G.G. Effects of sample handling on some chemical properties of soils from  high rainfall coastal North Queensland: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 21(1), p. 67-72, illus. (incl.  2 tables), 1983.    351    Glasmann, J.R. Alteration of andesite in wet, unstable soils of Oregon's western Cascades: Clays and  Clay Minerals, 30(4), p. 253-263 (incl. Russian, German, French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 plates), 1982.  Goebel, J. Jeffery; and Schmude, Keith O. Integrating soil, water, and related resource data through  survey sampling: in Proceedings of the 1982 integrated data users workshop (Olson, Richard J., editor;  et al.), p. 42-44, illus., 1982. (Rep. No. CONF-8210120) available from:Oak Ridge Natl. Lab., Oak Ridge,  TN, United States.  Goettelman, Robert C.; Grass, Luther B.; Millard, John P.; et al. Comparison of multispectral remote-  sensing techniques for monitoring subsurface drain conditions: NASA Technical Memorandum, 84317,  16 p., illus. (incl. I table), 1983. available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.  Goldhammer, Robert K. Constructive and destructive paleosoils capping regressive carbonate cycles,  Cochise County, Arizona: Master's, 1982, Univ. of Oklahoma, Norman, OK.  Goodroad, Lewis Leonard.  Nitrous oxide production in natural and agricultural ecosystem soils of  Wisconsin:  160 p., Doctoral, 1983, Univ. of Wisconsin, Madison, WI. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Haas, Herbert; Fisher, D. W.; Thorstenson, D. C.; et al.  13CO2 and 14CO2 measurements on soil  atmosphere sampled in the western Great Plains of the US: in Proceedings of the Eleventh international  radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor: et al.), Radiocarbon, 25(2), p. 301-314, illus. (incl. 2  tables, sect.), 1983.  Harga, A. A.; and EI-Shazly, M.A. Calcium carbonate status among the soils of the north western coast  of Egypt: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(1), p. 83-95, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Harriss, Robert C.; Sebaeher, Daniel I.; and Day, Frank P., ,Jr. Methane flux in the Great Dismal  Swamp: Nature (London), 297(5868), p. 673-674, illus., 1982.  Hasenohr, E. J.; and Pride, D.E. Computer mapping of soil and rock geochemistry; a comparison using  data from the Breckenridge mining district, Colorado:  in 17th application of computers and operations  research in the mineral industry (Johnson, Thys B., editor; et al.), Application of Computer Methods in  the Mineral Industry, 17, p, 728-739, illus. (incl. geol. sketch map), 1982.  Herman, Janet Suzanne. The dissolution kinetics of calcite, dolomite, and dolomitic rocks in the CO2  -water system: 235 p., Doctoral, 1982, Pennsylvania State Univ., University Park, PA. available from:  Univ. Microfilms.  Hickok, Eugene A.; and Erdmann, John B.  Well system for control of extensive creosote waste  contamination [abstr.]: in International water well exhibition; abstracts of papers to be presented at the  Ground-Water Technology Division's Education Session, Ground Water, 21(4), p. 518, 1983.  Hill, V. G.; and Ostojic, Slavko. A bauxite resources classification scheme: Int. Bauxite Assoc., Q. Rev.,  8(4), p. 17-26, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1983.  Holliday, Vance Terreil. Morphological and chemical trends in Holocene soils at the Lubbock Lake  archeological site, Texas: 306 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, CO. available from:Univ.  Microfilms.  Horng, Fu-Wen. Anion retention mechanisms in four Forest soils; relevance to the leaching process:  182 p., Doctoral, 1983, Univ. of Wasington, Seattle, WA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Hughes, R. E.; and Bargh, B. L. The weathering of brick; causes, assessment and measurement: Open-  File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), 92 p., 1983. (Rep. No. 83-0272) available from: U.  S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch, Denver Fed. Cent., Lakewood, CO, United  States.  Hurni, Hans. Soil erosion and soil formation in agricultural ecosystems; Ethiopia and northern Thailand:  in Workshop on the stability and instability of mountain ecosystems (Messerli, Bruno; et al.), Mountain  Research and Development, 3(2), p. 131-142 (incl. French, German sum.), illus. (incl. 2 table), 1983.  Jager, A.; Boersma, O.; and Bisdom, E. B.A. The characterization of microporosity in a ploughpan by  submicroscopic and Quantimet techniques: in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor;  et al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 277-283, illus., 1983.  Jayawardane, N. S. Further examination of the use of the equivalent salt solutions method for predicting  hydraulic conductivity of soils for different salt solutions: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 21(1),  p. 105-108, illus., 1983.    352    Jones, Malcolm John.  Numerical studies of nonreactive solute movement in unsaturated porous  materials: Doctoral, 1982. Univ. of New South Wales, Australia. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Juarez-Badillo, Eulalio; Koppula, Sivajogi D.; Ly, B.; et el. Permeability and consolidation of normally  consolidated soils; discussions and closure: Journal of Geotechnical Engineering, 109(6), p. 86982,  illus., 1983.  Kalisz, Paul John. The longleaf pine islands of the Ocala National Forest, Florida; a soil study:  14:~  p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Florida, Gainesville, FL. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Kharin, N. G. Geobotanical maps of Algeria: a survey: Problems of Desert Development, l, p. 44-46,  1982.  Klaer, W.; and Krieter, M. Uber die Bedeutung des Humus fur Bodenerosion und Hangstabilitat in den  feuchten und wechselfeuchten Tropen von Papua Neuguinea [The importance of humus for the erosion  of soils and slope stability in very humid regions and alternations of humidity in Papua New Guinea]:  Erdkunde, 36(3), p. 15360 (incl. English sum.), illus.. 1982.  Klement, Alfred W., Jr.  Natural sources of environmental radiation:  in CRC handbook ot'  environmental radiation (Klement, Alfred W., Jr.), p. 5-21, illus. (incl. 20 tables), CRC Press, Boca Raton.  FL, United S, tates, 1982.  Kobzistyy, P. I.; and Oleshehenko, V. 1, Ob osobennostyakh raspredeleniya zapasov vlagi v pochvakh  yestestvennykh i preobrazovannykh geosistem Kanevskogo Pridneprov'ya [Particularities of the  distribution of soil-moisture reserves in geosystems which have been naturally transformed at Kanev,  Dniester region]: Fizichna Geografiya ta Geomorfologiya (Kiev), 27, p. 101-103, illus. (incl. 7 anal., 1  table), 1982.  Kooistra, M.J. Lightmicroscope and submicroscope observations of salts in marine alluvium (India):  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A.. editor; et el.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 149-160, illus.,  1983.  Kreig, Raymond A.; and Reger, Richard D. Air-photo analysis and summary of landform soil properties  along the route of the Trans-Alaska Pipeline System: Geologic Report (College), 66, 149 p., illus. (incl.  tables, geol. sketch maps), 1982.  Krug, Edward C.; and Frink, Charles R. Acid rain on acid soil; a new perspective: Science, 217(4610).  p. 520-525, illus., 1983.  Kuntze, H.; and Wetjen, F.A. Subsurface drainage of a heavy alluvial soil: in Advances in drainage  (Willardson, Lyman S,, chairperson), Proceedings - National Drainage Symposium. 4, p. 156-162. illus.  (incl. 4 tables), 1982. (ASAE Publ. 12-82).  Labib, F. The mineralogical characteristics of some important shale deposits in Egypt: Egyptian Journal  of Soil Science, 22(1), p. 41-51, illus. (incl. 2 tables). 1982,  Lampert, Jordan Keith." Measurement of trace cation activities by Donnan membrane equilibrium and  atomic absorption analysis:  189 p.. Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Wisconsin, Madison, Wl, available from:  Univ. Microfilms.  Langford-Smith, T. New perspectives on the Australian deserts: Australian Geographer, 15(5), p. 269-  284, illus. (incl. chart, sketch maps), 1983.  Layas, Fathi mohlmed.  Response and stability of oceanfloor soils under random waves:  169 p.,  Doctoral, 1982, North Carolina State Univ., Raleigh, NC. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Leitman, H. M.; Sohm, J. E.; and Franklin, M. A. Wetland hydrology and tree distribution of thc  Apalachicola River flood plain, Florida: Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper (Washington), 2196-  A, p. A1-A52, illus. (incl. 14 tables, sketch maps), 1983.  Lenhardt, Duane Rudolph. Characterization and strength analysis of representative Fragipans of New  York State: 388 p., Doctoral, 1983, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Lindsey, Wesley C. Soil survey of San Luis Obispo County, California, Paso Robles area: 236 p., illus.  (incl. 16 tables; colored soils map 1:380,160; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States. 1983. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Loeh, R. J.; and Dommollan, T. E, Field rainfall simulator studies on two clay soils of the Darling Downs,  Queensland; I, The effects of plot length and tillage orientation on erosion processes and runoff and  erosion rates: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 21(1), p. 33-46, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1983.    353    Loch, R. J.; and Donnollan, T. E. Field rainfall simulator studies on two clay soils of the Darling Downs,  Queensland; 11, Aggregate breakdown, sediment properties and soil erodibility: Australian Journal of  Soil Research, 21(1), p. 47-58, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1983.  Lueas, Paul E. Subsurface drainage; a comparison between field evaluation and estimated properties for  fourteen soils in the Midwest with restrictive layers:  in Advances in drainage (Willardson, Lyman S.,  chairperson), Proceedings - National Drainage Symposium, 4, p. 14%155, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  (ASAE Publ. 12-82).  Lukashev, V. K.; Veeher, V. A.; and Zingerman, A. Ya. Pestrotsvetnye kory vyvetrivaniya morskogo  paleogena Belorussii [Red weathering crust of the marine Paleogene of Byelorussia]: Doklady Akademii  Nauk BSSR, 26(8), p. 731-734 (incl. English sum.), 1982.  Mackay, J. Ross. Oxygen isotope variations in permafrost, Tuktoyaktuk Peninsula area, Northwest  Territories: Paper - Geological Survey of Canada. 83-1B, p. 67-74 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table,  strat, col., sketch map), 1983. (Current research, Part B).  Magette, William Lawson. Wastewater treatment in soil: effect of residence time: 459 p., Doctoral,  1982, Virginia Polyteeh. Inst. and State Univ., Blacksburg, VA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Makeeva,  V.  I4 Tugushi,  N.  K.;  and  Gogoberidze,  I.  V.  Low-sodium  solonetzes  of the  Nizhnekartlinskaya Plain in Georgia: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 8-13, 2 tables,  1982.  Markewieh, Helaine W.; Pavieh, Milan J.; and Gonzalez, Virginia M. Soil chronosequences from the  Virginia to South Carolina Quaternary coastal plain deposits [abstr.]:  in 32nd annual meeting,  Southeastern Section, Geological Society of America; with the Southeast Section of the National  Association of Geology Teachers and the Southeastern Section of the Paleontological Society, Abstracts  with Programs- Geological Society of America, 15(2), p. 56, 1983.  Markewieh, Helaine W.; and Soller, David R. The Cape Fear River; a late Quaternary drainage [abstr.]:  in 32rid annual meeting, Southeastern Section, Geological Society of America; with the Southeast Section  of the National Association of Geology Teachers and the Southeastern Section of the Paleontological  Society, Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 15(2), p. 56, 1983.  Matviishina, Zh. N.  Osobennosti pozdnekaynozojskogo pochvoobrazovaniya na Kerchenskom  poluostrove po mikromorfologicheskim dannym [Pedogenesis during the upper Cenozoic of Kerch  Peninsula from micromorphologic data]: Fizichna Geografiya ta Geomorfologiya (Kiev), 27, p. 117-125.  illus., 1982.  Mays, Major Dewayne. A comparison of Mollisols from three different climatic regions in the United  States:. 203 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Nebraska, Lincoln, NE. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  McCarthy, Kevin P.  Helium exploration survey for the Animas Valley, Colorado:  Bulletin -  Geothermal Resources Council, 12(7), p. 9-14, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch maps), 1983.  McFadden, Leslie David. The impacts of temporal and spatial climatic changes on Alluvial soils genesis  in Southern California:  449 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Arizona, Tucson, AZ. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  McHardy, W. J.; and Robertson, L. An optical, scanning electron microscopic and microanalytical  study of cementation in some Podzols:  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et  al.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p.'161-170, illus., 1983.  Melntyre, D. S.; Watson, C. L.; and Loveday, J.  Swelling of a clay soil profile under ponding:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, 20(2), p. 71-79, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  MeNulty, Edmund Gregory. Consolidation with axisymmetric flow in soils having radial and vertical  variation of properties:  168 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Texas, Austin, TX. available from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Mills, Hugh H. Long-term episodic deposition on mountain foot slopes in the Blue Ridge Province of  North Carolina; evidence from relative-age dating: Southeastern Geology, 23(3), p. 123-128, illus. (incl.  1 table), 1982.  Montalegre, d.; Gil, J.; Corral, L.; et al. Fertilidad quimica de Suelos del Valle del Guadalquivir; Zona  Andujar-Mengibar (Jaen) [Chemical fertility of soils of Guadalquivir Valley; Andujar-Mengibar Zone,  Jaen]: Anales de Edafologia y Agrobiologia, 41(1-2), p. 259-270 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 4 anal.,  4 tables), 1982.    354    Moon, David Earl. The genesis of three Podzot-like soils occurring over a climatic gradient on  Vancouver Island: Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada. available from:  National Library of Canada.  Morras, Hector J. M. Submicroscopic characterisation of phosphatic and sesquioxidic nodules of some  soils of the "Chaco Deprimido'" (Argentina); preliminary results:  in Submicroscopic studies of soils  (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 187-194, illus., 1983.  iothes, G. Sedimentation und Sedimentanalytik im Muggelsee [Sedimentation and sediment analysis  of Lake Mueggel]: Acta Hydrochimica et Hydrobiologica, 11(1), p. 75-99 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. 1 table), 1983.  Mugridge, Samantha-Jane; and Young, Harvey R. Erratum; Disintegration of shale by cyclic wetting  and drying and frost action: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences --- Journal Canadien des Sciences de  la Terre, 20(7), p. 1217, illus., 1983.  Murray-Rust, Douglas Hammond. Irrigation water management in Sri Lanka; an evaluation of technical  and policy factors affecting operation of the main channel system: 374 p., Doctoral, 1983, Cornell Univ.,  lthaca, NY. available from:Univ. Microfilms.  mustafa, M~ahamed Fatih Hassan; and Samoilova, E. m.  Forms of iron in soils of the semiarid  subtropics: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 60-62, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Nixon, Ronnie. The analytical chemistry of saltpeter measurement in soil samples: The Huntsville  Grotto Newsletter, 24(5-6), p. 44-45, illus., 1983.  Norton, L. D.; Bigham, J. M.; Hall, G. F.; et al. Etched thin sections for coupled optical and electron  microscopy and micro-analysis:  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aL),  Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 55-64, illus., 1983.  Obukhov, A. I.; and Mints, E.B. Influence of sample composition on atomic-absorption determination  of manganese in environmental entities: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 14-20, illus.  (incl, 3 tables), 1982.  Omar, i. S.; and Aziz, M. A. The use of saline irrigation water, its effect on soil properties and plant  growth; I, Soil aggregation: Egyptian Journal of Soil Science, 22(1), p. 11-21, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1982.  Pagliai, M.; Bisdom, E. B. A.; and I_,din, S. Changes in surface structure (crusting) after application  of sewage sludge and pig slurry to cultivated agricultural soils in northern Italy:  in Submicroscopic  studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 35-53, illus., 1983.  Pawluk, S. Fabric sequences as related to genetic processes in two Alberta soils:  in Submicroscopic  studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 233-242, illus., 1983.  Perry, Dale L.; Tsao, Leon; and Gaugler, Kenneth A. Surface study of HF- and HF/H2SO4-treated  feldspar using Auger electron spectroscopy: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 47(7), p. 1289-1291.  1983.  Pittman, Walter E., Jr. Eugene W. Hilgard and scientific education in Mississippi [abstr.]:  in 32nd  annual meeting, Southeastern Section, Geological Society of America; with the Southeast Section of the  National Association of Geology Teachers and the Southeastern Section of the Paleontological Society,  Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 15(2). p. 61, 1983.  Protz, Richard. Calcium-dominated organans in Humic Podzols from the Hudson and James Bay  lowlands of Ontario (Canada):  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor: et aLL  Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 171-177, illus., 1983.  Rakhmatov, Yu. B.; and Nazarov, I. K. Principal types of aeolian relief in the Karakul Delta of the  Zeravshan River and problems of their development: Problems of Desert Development, 1, p. 47-52,  1982.  Reeve, R.; and Fergus, I.F. Black and white waters and their possible relationship to the podzolization  process: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 21(1), p. 59-66, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch maps), 1983.  Rengasamy, P. Dispersion of calcium clay: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 20(2), p. 153-157, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Rieger, Samuel. The genesis and classification of cold soils: 230 p., illus. (incl. 1 table), Academic Press,  New York, NY, United States, 1983.    355    Riezebos, P. A.; and Lustenhouwer, W.J. Characteristics and significance of composite particles derived  from a Colombian Andosol profile:  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor: et al.),  Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 195-217, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1983.  Robert, Pierre Camille. Evaluation of some remote sensing techniques for soil and crop management:  131 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Robinove, C. J.; Bonner, William; Andresen, Kenneth; et al. Landsat monitoring of albedo changes in  northwestern Arizona, 1977-1980: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), 14 p.,  illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982. (Rep. No. 82-0014) available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect.,  West. Distrib. Branch, Denver Fed. Cent., Lakewood, CO, United States.  Rogers, Jonathan David. The genesis, properties and significance of fracturing in Colorado Plateau  sandstones: 724 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA. available from:Univ. Microfilms.  Sai, Joseph Obodai, Effect of capillary hysteresis and spatial variability of hydraulic conductivity on  two-dimensional hillslope soil moisture flow: 120 p., Doctoral, 1982, Texas A&amp;M Univ., College Station,  TX. available from: Univ, Microfilms.  Sanzolone, R. F.; and Chao, T.T. Atomic-absorption determination of mercury in geological materials  by flame and carbon-rod atomisation after solvent extraction and using co-extracted silver as a matrix  modifier: Analyst (London), 108(1282), p, 58-63, illus. (incl. table, anal.), 1983.  Sapozhnikov, D. G.; Bogatyrev, B. A.; Demina, V. N.; et al. Usloviya obrazovaniya i zakonomernosti  razmeshcheniya mestorozhdeniy boksitov [The formation conditions and distribution mechanisms of  bauxite deposits]:  in Problemy petrologii, mineralogii i rudogeneza (Chukhrov, F. V., editor: et aLL p.  50-55, lzd. Nauka, Moscow, USSR, 1983.  Schimel, David Steven. Nutrient and organic matter dynamics in grasslands; effects of fire and erosion:  80 p., Doctoral, 1982, Colorado State Univ., Fort Collins, CO. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Schoonderbeek, D.; Thiel, F.; and Bisdom, E. B. A.  Quantimet 720 analysis of porosities in  backscattered electron scanning images made with different photo-techniques:  in Submicroscopic  studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; etal.), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 271-275, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1983.  Scott, W. E.; McCoy, W. D.; and Shroba, R. R. The last two cycles of Lake Bonneville [abstr.]:  in  Geological Society of America, Rocky Mountain Section, 36th annual meeting; Cordilleran Section, 79th  annual meeting, Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 15(5), p. 300, 1983.  Sharma, Sudhirendar; and Singh, Ramendra. Selenium in soil, plant, and animal systems: CRC Critical  Reviews in Environmental Control, 13(1), p. 23-50, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1983.  Shcherbov, B. L. Forms of boron occurrence in weathering crusts: Soviet Geology and Geophysics,  23(7), p. 55-61, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1982.  Sheldon, Elisabeth Shepard. Continuity and change in plant usage from the Mississippian to the historic  period:  144 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of Alabama, University, AL. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Shepard, J. Scott.  Modeling water contents of Kentucky soils:  122 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of  Kentucky, Lexington, KY. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Sheridan, Richard C.  Mineral fertilizers in Southern agriculture:  in The geological sciences in the  Antebellum South (Corgan, James X., editor), p. 73-82, illus., Univ. Ala. Press, University, AL, United  States, 1982.  Shikha, A.; Osipova, N. N.; and Sokolva, T. A.  Feasibility of characterizing the mineralogical  composition of soils by infrared spectrophotometry: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p,  34-40, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.  Simoneit, B. R. T.; Mazurek, M. A.; and Reed, W. E. Characterization of organic matter in aerosols  over rural sites; phytosterols: in Advances in organic geochemistry, 198l (Bjoroy, M., editor; et al.),  Proceedings of the International Meeting on Organic Geochemistry, 10, p. 355-361, illus. (incl. sketch  maps), 1983. (A Wiley Heyden publication).  Smith, R. T.  Quaternary environmental change in equatorial regions with particular reference to  vegetation history; a bibliography: Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 39(3-4),p. 331-  345, 1982.  Smolin, P. P.  Minerageniya, evolyutsionnyye vzaimosvyazi i prognoz magnezial'nykh poleznykh  iskopayemykh (magnezit, brusit, tal'k) [Mineral genesis, evolutionary interrelationships and prediction    356    of magnesian mineral resources; magnesite, brucite, talc]:  in Problemy petrologii, mineralogii i  rudogeneza (Chukhrov, F. V., editor; et al.), p. 66-76, illus. (incl. strat, cots., geol. sketch maps), Izd.  Nauka, Moscow, USSR, 1983.  Sondheim, Mark Weiss. Numerical assessment of soil properties in relation to classification and genesis:  Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada. available from: National Library of  Canada.  Soyer, J.; Miti, T.; and Aloni, K. Effets compares de l'erosion pluviale en milieu peri-urbain de region  tropicale (Lubumbashi, Shaba, Zaire) [Comparative effects of pluvial erosion in a peri-urban environment  of a tropical region, Lubumbashi, Shaba, Zaire]: Revue de Geomorphologie Dynamique, 31(2), p. 71-  80 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1982.  Spain, A. V.; Probert, M. E.; Isbell, R. F.; et aL Loss-on-ignition and the carbon contents of Australian  soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 20(2), p. 14%152, 766 anal., 3 tables, 1982.  Stantarf, John Alvin, IV. Effects of added nitrogen on trees and soil of deciduous forests in southern  New York:  153 p., Doctoral, 1983, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Stephan, S.; Berrier, J.; De Petre, A. A.; et al. Characterization of in situ organic matter constituents  in Vertisols, from Argentina, using submicroscopic and cytochemical methods; first report:  in  Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; etaL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 21-34, illus., 1983.  Stoops, G. SEM and light microscopic observations of minerals in bog-ores of the Belgian Campine: in  Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A., editor; et aL), Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 179-186, itlus..  1983.  Strathouse, Scott Mitchell. Genesis and mineralogy of soils on an alluvial fan, western Mojave Desert.  California: 180 p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of California, Riverside, CA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Svendsen, Mark T. Water management strategies and practices at the tertiary level; three Philippine  irrigation systems: 311 p., Doctoral, 1983, Cornel1 Univ., Ithaca, NY. available from:Univ. Microfilms.  Svetlova, E. I.; and Urusevskaya, I. S. Humus of soddy-podzolic and Gray forest soils in the Preural  region: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 1-7, 2 tables, 1982.  Swanson, Sherman Roser. Infiltration, soil erosion, nitrogen loss and soil profile characteristics of  OregonlandsoccupiedbythreesubspeciesofArtemisiatridentata: 149 p., Doctoral, 1983, Oregon State  Univ., Corvallis, OR. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Takahashi, Haruu; Sato, Jan; and Sato, Kazuo. Environmental radioactivity and radon content of  ground water around the Fuji Volcano: Bulletin of the Earthquake Research Institute = Tokyo Daigaku  Jishin Kenkyusho lho, 57(2), p. 351-358 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Tamari, Y.; lnoue, Y4 Tsuji, A.; et al. Ultrasonic extraction of several cations with dilute nitric acid  solutions from soils: Bunseki Kagaku, 31(11), p. E409-E412, illus., 1982.  Tauber, Henrik. Possible depletion in 14C in trees growing in calcareous soils: in Proceedings of the  Eleventh international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et al.), Radiocarbon, 25(2), p. 417-  420, 1 table, 1983.  Tyugai, Z.  Influence of long-term systematic application of mineral fertilizers on silt-fraction  mineralogical properties and physicochemical properties in a soddy-podzolic soil: Moscow University  Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 54-59. illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1982.  Varec, K.  Ispol'zovaniye termolyuminestsentsii kvartsa dlya otsenki pochvennykh protsessov  [Application of thermoluminescence to quartz for the study of pedogenesis processes]:  Eesti NSV  Teaduste Akadeemia Toimetised, Geoloogia = Izvestiya Akademii Nauk Estonskoy SSR, Geologiya,  31(3), p. 117-118 (incl. Estonian, Russian sum.), 1982.  Vorobyeve, L.A. Acidic and basic components of soil solutions and soil extracts: Moscow University  Soil Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 29-33, 1982.  Wada, Kojl; and Kakuto, Yasuko. lntergradient vermiculite-kaolin mineral in a Korean Ultisol: Clays  and Clay Minerals, 31(3), p. 183-190 (incl. Russian, German, French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1983.  Wana-Etyem, Charles. Static and dynamic water content-pressure head relations of porous media: 155  p., Doctoral, 1982, Colorado State Univ., Fort Collins, CO. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Welbourn, Martha Lynne. Ecologically based forest policy analysis; fire management and land disposals  in the Tanana River basin, Alaska: 248 p., Doctoral, 1983, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. available from:  Univ. Microfilms.    357    Willardson, Lyman S. (chairperson).  Advances in drainage:  Dec. 13-14, 1982, United States.  Proceedings - National Drainage Symposium, 4, 177 p., 1982. (ASAE Publ. 12-82).  Williams, Baden G.; and Baker, G. C. An electromagnetic induction technique for reconnaissance  surveys of soil salinity hazards:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, 20(2), p. 107-118, illus, (incl. 2  tables, strat, col., sketch maps), 1982.  Williams, John; Prebble, R. E.; Williams, W. T.; et al. The influence of texture, structure and clay  mineralogy on the soil moisture characteristic: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 2 l ( 1 ). p. 15- 32, illus.  (incl. 5 tables), 1983.  Wimmenauer, W.;  Hurrle,  H.;  and  Renk,  A.  Geochemie  umweltrelevanter  Spurenelemente  [Geochemistry of trace elements important for the environment]: Forschungsbericht - Albert-Ludwigs-  Universitat Freiburg im Breisgau, 1, 14-003 p., 1982.  Wimmenauer, W.; and Viehl, B.  Ursachen des Verwitterungsverhaltens von Sandsteinen einer  Grossbaustelle im Schwarzwald [Causes of the behavior in relation to weathering of sandstones in the  Black Forest region]: Forschungsbericht - Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat Freiburg im Breisgau, 1. 14-004  p., 1982.  Youngs, Robert Riggs. A three-dimensional effective stress model for cyclicly loaded granular soils: 330  p., Doctoral, 1982, Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA. available from:Univ. Microfilms.  Yu, S. L; and Cruise, J. F. Time series analysis of soil data:  in Time series methods in hydrosciencesz  proceedings of an international conference held at Canada Centre for Inland Waters (EI-Shaarawi, A.  H., editor; etal.), p. 600-607, illus. (incl. 1 table), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1982.  Zaidel'man, F. R.~ Gel'tser, V. Yu.; and Nikiforova, A.S. Influence of gleization on microstructure and  mineralogical composition of soddy-podzolic soils on a calcareous moraine:  Moscow University Soil  Science Bulletin, 37(3), p. 4%53, illus., 1982.  Zauyah, S.; and Bisdom, E. B. A. SEM-EDXRA investigation of tubular features and iron nodules in  lateritic soils from Malaysia:  in Submicroscopic studies of soils (Bisdom, E. B. A.. editor: et al.).  Geoderma, 30(1-4), p. 219-232, illus., 1983.  Zinchuk, N. N. On the main sources of the clay minerals in the diamond-bearing Mesozoic continental  deposits of western Yakutia: Soviet Geology and Geophysics, 23(8), p. 76-83. illus. (incl. 1 table), 1982.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      