 Geoderma 26 (1981) 95--105                                                   95  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE OCCURRENCE OF SUSPENDED FERRUGINOUS PARTICLES IN  PYROPHOSPHATE EXTRACTS OF SOME SOIL HORIZONS    E. JEANROY and B. GUILLET  Centre de P~dologie Biologique, C.N.R.S., B.P. 5. 54500 Vandoeuvre-les-Nancy (France)  Received April 14, 1980; accepted March 13, 1981)    ABSTRACT  J,eanroy, E. and Guillet, B., 1981. The occurrence of suspended ferruginous particles in  pyrophosphate extracts of some soil horizons. Geoderma, 26: 95--105.  Iron was extracted by pyrophosphate and Na,-EDTA at pH 10 from samples of the  A2g horizon of a hydromorphic soil and the BFehorizon of a podzolic soil. Amounts of  iron removed by the two reagents from the horizons differed appreciably although the  Feo/Fed ratios for the two were almost the same.  Phase separations of the two extracts were attempted by ultrafiltration, ultracentrifuga-  tion and oxidation. A solid ferruginous phase with an Fe/C atomic ratio of approximately  1 was separated from the pyrophosphate extract by both filtration and centrifuging. Those  pz~ticles were a major proportion (about 70%) of the iron removed from the BFe horizon.  The high proportion of extracted iron in the solid phase and the Fe/C ratio are incompat-  ible with exclusive extraction of iron complexed with organic matter. The EDTA extract  could not be separated into ph~es. Oxidation also indicated a difference of iron forms  present in the two extracts.  We concluded that pyrophosphate mainly disperses finely divided, ferruginous par-  ticles and that EDTA largely dissolves iron in the form of amorphous oxides, Neverthe-  less, iron in complex form with organic matter can be removed by both reagents, especial-  ly from the Bh horizons of podzols. These findings indicate that levels of amorphous  oxides in soils with moderate to large contents of organic matter are lower than shown  by currently accepted extraction techniques.    INTRODUCTION  Extraction of soil samlvles with pyrophosphate at pH 10 has been widely  used to estimate amounts of organically bound iron (Bascomb, 1968; McKea-  g.~e et al., 1971). The results have then been used in defining certain diagnos-  tic horizons and in the classification of soils. Our efforts to apply pyrophos-  phate extraction as a diagnostic test have raised questions about the forms  of iron being removed. In an attempt to resolve those questions and to identi-  fy more completely the forms of iron being extracted, we have conducted a  two-part investigation. The first part entailed preliminary studies of synthetic  J~on oxides and the Screening of a number of soil horizons. The second part  consisted of more detailed comparisons of pyrophosphate and EDTA ex-    0016-7061/81/0000--0000/$ 02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    96    tracts of two samples, those representing single horizons of two soils differing  in their genesis. The results of the investigation are reported in this paper.    PRELIMINARY INVESTIGATIONS    Methods followed in ex~actions with pyrophosphate and Na4-EDTA are  described in the next section. Oxalate extractions were made at pH 3 accord-  ing to the method described by Schwertmann (1964}.  Pyrophosphate extracted little or no iron from poorly crystallized, syn-  thetic hematite and goethite, whereas oxalate dissolved more of the materials.  EDTA extracted less than oxalate, but much more than did pyrophosphate.  Borggaard (1976) has shown that amounts of iron extracted by EDTA were  closely related to the amounts of iron in amorphous form in poorly crystal-  lized oxides.  Pyrophosphate and oxalate extracted the same or very similar amounts  of iron from samples of 40 horizons of acid soils derived from rocks such as  sandstones and granites in the Vosges Mountains of France. These softs  ranged from acid brown types to podzols. EDTA extracted much less iron  from the samples than did the other two reagents.  The differences in amounts of iron dissolved by the three reagents from  synthetic iron oxides and from soil samples might be related to mode of for-  mation of the oxides. The synthetic forms are entirely mineral in origin. The  forms of iron in soils, on the other hand, originated in an organic environ-  ment, by which we mean in the presence of organic matter. The main part  of this investigation was consequently an effort to identify more fully the  forms of iron removed by pyrophosphate and EDTA from soil horizons.    COMPARISONS OF PYROPHOSPHATE AND EDTA EXTRACTS    Samples of a single horizon from each of two profiles were chosen because  the pair had almost identical ratios of iron extracted by oxalate and dithionite  (Feo/Fed). Moreover, the soils themselve~ differed greatly in their genesis.    Identification of soil samples    One sample represented the A2g horizon of an Aquic Fraglossudalf (sol  lessiv~ glossique) formed in Pleistocene silts near Girmont in the Vosges  Mountains of France. This soil had been formed through hydromorphy.  Detailed information on the profile is given by Caillier (1977).  The second sample represented the BFe horizon of a sol ocre podzolique  derived from granite near Rudlin in the Vosges Mountains. The soil has been  formed by podzolization. Detailed infolznation on the profile is given by  Souchier {1971).  Several characteristics of the samples are reported in Table I. Note especial-  ly the Feo/Fed ratios of 0.74 for the A2g horizon and 0.69 for the BFe    97    TABLE I  Data on pH and amounts of clay, organic C and Fe in the A2g and BFe horizons  pH H:O Clay  C     Feo   Fed   Feo/Fed  (%)  (%)  (%)  (%)  A2g   4.3    20.2  0.8   2.75  3.7   0.74  BFe   4.3     11.2   3.9    1.17   1.7    0.69    horizon. Such ratios are currently considered evidence of high contents of  amorphous iron.  Extraction procedure and determination of iron  Both reagents (Na4P207 and Na4-EDTA) were used at a pH of 10 and a  concentration of 0.1 M. Extraction with pyrophosphate followed the proce-  dure described by McKeague et al. {1971) in which the sol-to-solvent ratio  is 1/100, the suspension is stirred for 16 h at room temperature and finally  centrifuged for 20 min at 40,000 g. Centrifugation under those conditions  was found to remove clay from suspension (Sheldrick and McKeague, 1975).  The EDTA solution at a concentration of 0.1 M is a flocculant. High-speed  centrifugation is therefore not necessary (5 min at 3,000 g is sufficient to  obtain a clay-free extract}. The rate of iron removal at room temperature,  however, is very slow (3 weeks are required for the curve to reach a plateau).  Consequently, extraction for 30 min at 80 was used to shorten the time.  Amounts of iron were all determined by atomic absorption without pre-  vious acid digestion.  Results  The amounts of iron extracted by the two reagents are given in Table II.    TABLE II  Fe and organic C extracted by pyrophosphate and Fe by Na4-EDTA from the A2g and the  BFe horizons  Fepy (%)  FeEDTA (~) Cpy (%)  A2g    0.33      0.88       0.32  BFe     1.21       0.50         1.32    Pyrophosphate removed less iron from the one and more from the other  sample than did EDTA. For the A2g horizon, EDTA was more effective and  for the BFe horizon, pyrophosphate was. The apparent reversal in efficiency    98    of the two reagents could be explained in either of two ways.  One explanation would be that pyrophosphate was largely a specific ex-  tractant for organically bound iron and EDTA for amorphous iron oxides.  At first glance, this explanation seems promising. Amounts of organically  bound iron could be higher in the BFe than in the A2g horizon because the  former is much higher in organic carbon and the latter higher in iron extract-  able by oxalate and dithionite. The amounts of iron extracted in the two  horizons by the two reagents are thus consistent with the proposition that  pyrophosphate is largely specific for organically bound iron and EDTA for  amorphous iron oxides. Contrary evidence was also obtained, however, which  does not support this explanation.  To judge from the colors of the extracts, EDTA removed as much organic  matter from the BFe horizon as did pyrophosphate. The extracts by the two  reagents were equally dark in color for the BFe horizon and equally clear  for the A2g horizon. Moreover, the pH of 10 was the same for the two  reagents and should permit extraction of organic matter by both. Direct  measurement of the amounts of organic carbon in the EDTA extracts was  not possible because the reagent is itself organic. From the similar colors  of the extracts and because of the high pH, however, we concluded that  similar amounts of organic matter had been extracted (see Cpy % in Table II).  Similar amounts of "iron-organic" complexes should therefore have been ex-  tracted as well.  A possible second explanation for the larger amounts of iron removed  from the BFe horizon by pyrophosphate is that it disperses finely divided  ferruginous particles but that EDTA does not. The peptizing capacity of  pyrophosphate is well known (Van Olphen, 1963}. For that reason, it could  also have dispersed silicate clays, but any such dispersion seems to have been  negligible. Total amounts of Si in the pyrophosphate extract from the BFe  horizon was 6 ppm, as compared to 121 ppm of Fe. An amount of 6 ppm is  equivalent to 0.06% of the horizon, which could easily be extractable Si.  If all of that Si were from silicate clays, only traces need be present in the  extract. We therefore concluded that dispersion of silicate clays could be ig-  nored for the pyrophosphate extracts of the horizons. EDTA is a flocculant  rather than a dispersing agent. Ferruginous particles would therefore not be  expected in the EDTA extracts.  To examine the alternative explanations further, several complementary  tests were made on the pyrophosphate and EDTA extracts. The nature of  those extracts is critical to the validity of any explanation.    COMPLEMENTARY TESTS    Four tests were made, two quantitative and two qualitative in nature. The  quantitative tests were based on physical separations by ultrafiltration and  ::Atracentrifugation. The qualitative tests consisted of (1) additions of alcohol  and (2) oxidation of organic matter.    99  Ultrafiltration  Methods. Extracts were passed under pressure (1.8 bars) through a milli-  pore filter calibrated for a molecular size of about 10,000 (pore size of about  100 A). The phase passing through the membrane is caUled the ultrafiltrate  and the phase remaining on the membrane the retentate. The latter was re-  cycled into the filter for further filtration in order to wash out any residual  small molecules.  Ultrafiltration, like Sephadex gels, changes the pH of the extract if adjust-  ments are not made. To avoid precipitation of compounds of low molecular  weight, the retentate was returned to the original solvent condition before  each cycle. The pH was thus kept the same during the entire operation.  After the last cycle the retentate was returned to the initial volume of the  extract in order to compare the concenJ~rations.  Results. The amounts of Fe and C i~. the initial extracts and in the reten-  rates are given in Table III. The contrast between the EDTA and pyrophos-    TABLE III  Fe and organic C contents of the initial extracts and the retentates after ultrafiltration    ..........................................  EDTA-A2g  PyrO-BFe  Initial Fe (ppm)       88         121  Retentate Fe (ppm)      0           85  Retentate Fe  (%)     0       70  Initial Fe  Initial C (ppm)        --         132  Retentate C (ppm)     --           16  C retentate  (%)  C initial               --           12    phate extracts is striking. All of the iron in the EDTA extract of the A2g  horizon passed through the membrane {possibly as EDTA-Fe chelates or  complexes). Most of the iron (70%) in the pyrophosphate extract of the  BFe horizon, however, remained on the membrane as did a much smaller  proportion of the carbon. The large amount of iron in the retentate is con-  sidered evidence that such iron is in the form of ferruginous particles rather  than as complexes with pyrophosphate. Moreover, the Fe/C atomic ratio  of the retentate is 1.1, too high for chelates or complexes. The organic matter  present could thus be various compounds adsorbed on oxide particles.    100    Ultracen trifuga tio n  Because the data from ultraffltration indicated the presence of ferruginous  particles of large molecular size in the pyrophosphate extract, we thought a  more complete separation might be accomplished by ultracentrifugation. The  pyrophosphate extract of the BFe horizon and the EDTA extract of the  A2g horizon were cer~trifuged again but at 100,000 g for 6 h.  Results. Marked differences were observed between the EDTA and pyro-  phosphate extracts. No phase separation was evident in the EDTA extract  as a result of ultracentrifugation. On the other hand, separations of Fe and C  were obtained for the pyrophosphate extract, as shown in Table IV. The  TABLE IV  Fe and organic C contents of the initial pyrophosphate extract and of the supernatant after  ultracentrifugation  Fe (ppm)   C (ppm)  Initial pyro extract      121         132  Supernate                29         100  Precipitated % of initial   76          24    0,sj   Fig. 1. Electron micrograph ef ultracentrifugate from pyrophosphate extract of the BFe  horizon.    101  Fe/C atomic ratio of the pyrophosphate eentrifugate was 0.6 as compared  to 1.1 for the retentate in ultrafiltration. Centrifuging was thus a less effect-  ive technique than ultrafiltration for the separation of phases, although it  did permit a marginally better isolation of suspended iron (76% versus 70%}.  With an Fe/C ratio of 0.6, however, the materials in the eentrifugate are not  chelates or complexes of iron with organic matter. Rather, the materials  could be colloidal iron oxides with some associated organic compounds.  After separation from the supernatant, the centrifugate was resuspended  in demineralized water. The materials were then examined by transmission  electron microscopy as shown in Fig. 1. Aggregates of small spheroids, the  latter less than 150 A in diameter, are evident in the electron micrograph  (Fig. 1). Electron diffraction demonstrated that the spheroids were not  erystalli~,e.  Effects of ethanol  Fe(III) hydroxide suspensions are readily flocculated by ethanol. It lowers  the dielectric constant of a suspension and also modifies the charge densities  of hydroxide particles (Kruyt, 1952). Alcohol was therefore added to ali-  quots of each of the two extracts.  Six ml of ethanol were added to 50 ml of each of the EDTA and pyro-  ,~  .      e   /                                  ~,    i  , i  Fig. 2. Electron micrograph of the ethanol-flocculate from the pyrophosphate extract of  the BFe horizon.    102    phosphate extracts. No flocculation occurred in the EDTA extract, wherea~  it was immediate in the pyrophosphate extract. Furthermore, 95% of the  initial amount of iron in the pyrophosphate extract was eventually flocculat-  ed. The effects of ethanol thus indicate the presence of colloidal oxides in  one extract (pyrophosphate) but not in the other (EDTA).  The flocculate in the pyrophosphate extract was re-suspended in water so  that it could be examined with a transmission electron microscope. The elec-  tron micrograph in Fig. 2 shows stains with dendritic interconnections.    Oxidation of organic matter    Further evidence on the forms of iron in the two extracts was obtabled by  oxidation of the organic reagent (EDTA extract) and of the extracted organic  matter (pyrophosphate extract).  First, a preliminary experiment was conducted by oxidizing an Fe-oxalate  complex in solution. When hot hypochlorite was added to the Fe-oxalate  solution, Fe(III) oxide was precipitated (10 ml of 4.5 M hypochlorite were  added at 80 to 10 ml of 0.2 M oxalate containing 1 mg of iron). The  oxidation destroys the organic substance and thus breaks the ligands binding  the iron. No iron is precipitated, however, if pyrophosphate, a mineral com-  plexing agent not subject to oxidation, is added to the Fe-oxalate ahead of  the hypochlorite. Presumably, the iron released when oxalate is destroyed, is  re-complexed by the pyrophosphate.  Additions of hypochlorite were subsequently made to the EDTA and  pyrophosphate extracts because of the probability that reactions of the  former would parallel those of Fe-oxalate.  Methods. 10 ml of 4.5 M hypochlorite were added at 80 to 10 ml of the  BFe pyrophosphate extract and to 10 ml of the A2g EDTA extract.  Results. Effects of additions of hypochlorite to the EDTA and pyrophos-  phate extracts were in part parallel and in part different from those with Fe-  oxalate.  After hypochlorite was added to an aliquot of the EDTA extract ,af the  A2g horizon, Fe (III) oxide was precipitated. This change demonstrated  oxidation of the EDTA to release iron from its complex with EDTA. As a  next step, pyrophosphate was added to another aliquot of the EDTA ex-  tract ahead of the hypochlorite. No iron was precipitated. The behavior of  the EDTA extract thtls paralleled that of the Fe-oxalate. We concluded that  in the EDTA extract, iron had initially been in complex form either with  EDTA {especially in this A2g horizon from which little organic matter was  extracted) or with extracted organic matter (in organic horizons such as the  Bh horizons of podzols) but could be re-complexed by pyrophosphate as  initial forms were destroyed.  For the oxidation test of organic matter in the pyrophosphate extract of  the BFe horizon, obviously no further addition of pyrophosphate was nec-  e~csary. When hypochlorite was added to an aliquot of the pyrophosphate    103    extract and heated, the dark color disappeared, the liquid became clear and  one reddish floc settled to the bottom of the test tube, showing that some  iron had been precipitated. Behavior of the pyrophosphate extract was thus  different from that of the EDTA e?:tract and the Fe-oxalate.  Iron could have been present in the pyrophosphate extract initially in one  or more of three forms, viz., (1) complexed with pyrophosphate, (2) com-  plexed with the extracted organic matter and (3) as solids in suspension. The  element could not be in ionic form at pH 10.  If all the extracted iron was complexed either with organic matter or with  pyrophosphate, it would remain in solution after oxidation.  The iron in complex with pyrophosphate would not be affected by oxida-  tion. It remained in solution. The iron complexed with the extracted organic  matter and released when the organic ligands were destroyed by hypochlorite,  would be re-complexed by the pyrophosphate present in the extract.  We concluded therefore that the reddish floc observed after oxidation  could only have been iron in finely divided ferruginous particles, most like-  ly Fe(III) hydroxides, initially present as solids in suspension in the pyrophos-  phate extract.    CONCLUSIONS    The results from extractions by pyrophosphate and EDTA of the two soil  samples with similar Feo/Fed ratios indicate large differences in forms of  iron being removed. The results also bear on currently accepted concepts of  amorphous iron in softs. Both reagents are efficient chelators of iron in  ionic form. Both were used at the same concentrations and ionic strengths  and at the same high pH (10), which favors extraction of organic matter. The  differing results are therefore attributed to removal of different forms or  iron from the samples.  Our data, as well as those in previous studies, indicate that Na4-EDTA acts  as a dissolving and complexing agent, si:'ailar in action to reagents such as  oxalate and citrate. For example, EDTA extracted iron from ferruginous  concretions in the A2g horizon of a hydromorphic soil. Iron in those con-  cretions parallels the dissolving of the element from poorly crystallized,  synthetic oxides (Borggaard, 1976). The synthetic oxides are also brought  into solution in a similar way by oxalate.  Furthermore, the high pH of the EDTA solution favors extraction of  organic matter, including that which carries iron in complex form. This form  was presumably all but absent from the A2g horizon, poor in organic matter,  but is widely present in other organic horizons such as the Bh horizons of  podzols. We will discuss this point further later. Nevertheless, the behavior  of the EDTA extracts under ultrafiltration, ultracentrifugation, treatment  with ethanol and oxidation, supports the interpretation that iron present  was all in solution in complex forms.  In contrast to the action of EDTA, pyrophosphate seemed not to act as a    104    complexing agent of amorphous iron oxides. Moreover, it not only extracted  iron in complex with organic matter but also peptized finely divided ferrugi-  nous particles so that they were dispersed and removed from the samples.  Our data indicate that most of the iron removed from the BFe horizon,  which was relatively high in the element, consisted of fe~ginous particles.  As much as 70% of the iron in the pyrophosphate extract was in forms that  would not pass through a millipore filter. Moreover, discrete particles isola-  ted by ultracentrifugation are evident in the electron micrograph in Fig. 1.  The high Fe/C atomic ratio of the particles also indicates that they are not  iron- organic matter complexes but most likely Fe(iII) hydroxides on which  relatively few organic compounds are adsorbed.  To demonstrate the occurrence of such particles in pyrophosphate extracts  we deliberately selected a BFe horizon high but not too rich in organic matter.  We also checked the Bh horizon overlying the BFe horizon in that same soil.  A greater amount of organic matter was extracted by pyrophosphate from  the Bh (Cpy = 2.6%) than from the BFe horizon (Cpy = 1.32%). The amount  of iron extracted from the Bh horizon wa slightly higher with pyrophosphate  (Fepy = 0.78%) than with EDTA (FeEDTA = 0.62%). Furthermore, the com-  plementary tests indicated few suspended ferruginous particles in the pyro-  phosphate extract of the Bh horizon. From these data we concluded that the  main action of pyrophosphate was to extract organic complexes from the Bh  horizon rather than peptizing ferruginous particles.  As to the general state of iron in soils, we think that the ferruginous par-  ticles occurring in pyrophosphate extracts do exist in soils, especially in BFe  or spodic horizons, as demonstrated by our results. In such an organic envi-  ronment, dominated by fulvic acids, the thinness and short range order of  the particles can be attributed to their coexistence with forms of organic  matter that inhibit crystallization of iron oxides (Schwertmann, 1966; Ko-  dama and Schnitzer, 1977).  Moreover, we think that the action of oxalate is different in the two cases.  In the first situation, represented by horizons of hydromorphic softs poor in  organic matter such as the A2g horizon examined in this investigation, oxalate  removed amorphous iron, as did EDTA. Our results show, however, that  oxalate removed more iron than did EDTA {Tables I and II), which can be  explained by the capacity of oxalate to attack minerals such as lepidocrocite  (Schwertmann, 1973) in addition to the poorly crystallized iron oxides.  In the second situation, represented by the BFe horizon (an organic en-  vironment) the amounts of iron removed by pyrophosphate and oxalate are  about the same {Tables I and II). Similar results were obtained in the pre-  liminary screening of samples of 40 horizons of acid brown soils and podzols.  We therefore suggest that in such soils oxalate dissolves ferruginous particles  of the kind dispersed and removed by pyrophosphate. 'We suggest further  that these particles of Fe(III) hydroxide constitute nearly all of the iron  extractable by oxalate. That all of this iron is amorphous seems doubtful be-  cause only part of it is extractable by EDTA despite the effectiveness of that  reagent in dissolving synthetic amorphous oxides.    105    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Thanks are due to Dr. R. Anderson, the Macaulay Institute for Soil Re-  search, Aberdeen, Scotland, for his critical advice.    REFERENCES    Bascomb, C.L., 1968. Distribution of pyrophosphate-extractable iron and organic carbon  in soils of various groups. J. Soil Sci., 19 (2): 251--268.  Borggaard, O.K., 1976. Selective extraction of amorphous iron oxide by EDTA from a  mixture of amorphous iron oxide, goethite and hematite. J. Soil. Sci., 27 (4): 478--486.  Caillier, M., 1977. Etude chronos~quentielle des sols sur terrasses alluviales de la Moselle.  Gen~se et dvolution des sols lessiv~s glossiques. Th~se Doc. sp~c. Univ. Nancy I, 87 pp.  Kodama, H. and Schnitzer, M., 1977. Effect of fulvic acid on the crystallization of Fe(III)  oxides. Geoderma, 19: 279--291.  Kruyt, H.R., 1952. Colloid Science. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 2 vols.  McKeague, J.A., Brydon, J.E. and Miles, N.M., 1971. Differentiation of forms of extract-  able iron and aluminium in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 33--38.  Schwertmann, U., 1964. Differenzierung der Eisenoxide des Bodens dutch Extraktion mit  Ammoniumoxalat- L~sung. Z. Pflanzenernaehr. Bodenkd., 105: 195--202.  Schwertmann, U., 1966. Inhibitory effect of soil organic matter on the crystallization of  amorphous ferric hydroxide. Nature, 212: 645--646.  Schwertmann, U., 1973. Use of oxalate for Fe extraction from soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 53:  244--245.  Sheldrick, B.H. and McKeague, J.A., 1975. A comparison of extractable Fe and Al data  using methods followed in the U.S.A. and Canada. Can. J. Soil Sci., 55 (1): 77--78.  Souchier, B., 1971. Evolution des sols sur roches cristallines ~ l'dtage montagnard (Vosges).  Th~se Doc. Sci. Nat. Univ. Nancy I, 130 pp.  Van Olphen, H., 1963. An Introduction to Clay Colloid Chemistry. Interscience, New  York, N.Y., 301 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractIron was extracted by pyrophosphate and Na4-EDTA at pH 10 from samples of the A2g horizon of a hydromorphic soil and the BFe horizon of a podzolic soil. Amounts of iron removed by the two reagents from the horizons differed appreciably although the Feo/Fed ratios for the two were almost the same.Phase separations of the two extracts were attempted by ultrafiltration, ultracentrifugation and oxidation. A solid ferruginous phase with an Fe/C atomic ratio of approximately 1 was separated from the pyrophosphate extract by both filtration and centrifuging. Those particles were a major proportion (about 70%) of the iron removed from the BFe horizon. The high proportion of extracted iron in the solid phase and the Fe/C ratio are incompatible with exclusive extraction of iron complexed with organic matter. The EDTA extract could not be separated into phases. Oxidation also indicated a difference of iron forms present in the two extracts.We concluded that pyrophosphate mainly disperses finely divided, ferruginous particles and that EDTA largely dissolves iron in the form of amorphous oxides. Nevertheless, iron in complex form with organic matter can be removed by both reagents, especially from the Bh horizons of podzols. These findings indicate that levels of amorphous oxides in soils with moderate to large contents of organic matter are lower than shown by currently accepted extraction techniques. 