 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 117--134                                                     117  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    QUANTITATIVE ANALYSIS OF TRACE AND MAJOR ELEMENTS IN  THIN SECTIONS OF SOILS WITH THE SECONDARY ION  MICROSCOPE (CAMECA)    E B.A. BISDOMl , S. HENSTRA2 , H.W. WERNER~ , P.R. BOUDEWIJN~ ,  W F. KNIPPENBERG3, H.A.M. de GREFTE3, J M. GOURGOUT4 and H.N. MIGEON4  'Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O Box 98, 6700 AB Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  2 Technical and Physical Engzneermg Research Serwce, P.O. Box 356, 6700 AJ  Wagenmgen (The Netherlands)  3 Phihps Research Laboratorzes, 5600 MD Eindhoven (The Netherlands)  4 Cameca, B_P. 6, 92403 Courbevole C$dex (France)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S, Werner, H.W., Boudewljn, P.R., Knippenberg, W.F, De  Grefte, H.A M., Gourgout, J.M and Migeon, H,N Quantitative analysis of trace and  major elements in thin sections of soils with the secondary ion microscope (Cameca).  Geoderma, 30:117--134    A series of experiments have been performed for a number of years to obtain quanti-  tative microchemical analysis by secondary ion microscopy of materials in thin sections  of soils. The first successful quantification was obtained from an area with a diameter of  300 um in bauxite and done with an IMS 300 at Philips Research Laboratories Such an  area, however, is frequently too large for most soil samples which are extremely hetero-  geneous even on a microscale A second generation IMS 3F was tested for soils at the  Cameca factory m Paris. This instrument allows the quantifmahon of trace and major ele-  ments of soil constituents in a spot with 1.5 um diameter, using a computer program  developed by Philips Research Laboratories. Calcite and clay from a Petrocalcic Xero-  chrept were used for this test. Ion spectra, ion images and linear traverses were made giv-  ing information on the nature and distribution of both major and trace elements. The  possibility of investigating a larger number of chemical elements simultaneously in hnear  traverses is of considerable help in the study of thin sections. Various submicroscopm and  other techniques are discussed to give some insight into the position of ion microscopy  amongst these    INTRODUCTION    Ion microscopy can be regarded as an advanced form of submicroscopic  research of materials in thin sections of soils. This technique can be used if  other forms of analyses have already been done. Such analyses may include  wet chemistry or beam techniques which require more soil material than is  necessary for most of the submicroscopic techniques.  Submicroscopy of thin sections is preceded by light microscopy, by which  a number of questions cannot be solved. The next step is the choice of in-    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    118    strument to be used for in sltu analysis to solve these questions. For soil  scientists such a choice is usually restricted to electron microscopy with ol  without equipment for mmrochemlcal analysis, the hghtest elements and  trace elements cannot be determined by this type of analysis  A preliminary knowledge of the mlcrochemlstry of the materials under  study is frequently obtained with SEM-EDXRA {scanning electron mmro-  scope -- energy dispersive X-ray analyzer). When an EMA (electron micro-  probe analyzer) or a SEM-WDXRA (scanning electron microscope -- wave-  length disperswe X-ray analyzer) are used one can obtain semi-quantitative  or quantitative data on most elements present m concentrations above trace  element level (Bisdom, 1981).  Ion microscopy is necessary for In sltu microchemical investigation of all  chemical elements and trace elements in a thin section. The first experiments  were done with an 1on microprobe mass analyzer (IMMA) (Bisdom et al.,  1977). These tests gave ion images of hydrogen and allowed the detection of  both major and trace elements. However, no quantification program for soil  materials was available at that time.  Experiments with the laser microprobe mass analyzer (LAMMA 500) also  allowed the detection of ions from thin sections by using the laser beam m  grazing incidence and from the edges of the piece of thin section inward; a  method which was called laser milling (Blsdom et al., 1981; Henstra et al.,  1981). However, the amount of sample analysed was significant m these  thicker samples. Ideally, the thin section should be ultra thin giving a much  smaller microvolume for analysis when shot through. Quantification is not  yet possible with the LAMMA 500.  Experiments with the Cameca mn microscope started m 1977 at the Bio-  physical Laboratory of the Umverslty of Paris in Cr&amp;eil, France. The team  consisted of P. Galle and A. Quettmr of this laboratory and J.M. Gourgout  of Cameca. Work was done with the IMS 300 on pieces of thin section.  Charging problems were slgnifmant and no accurate results could be ob-  tained.  In 1978 H.W. Werner of Phllips Research Laboratories invited the first  two authors for experiments with a Cameca IMS 300. A conductive and  round tantalum plate, with a 400 pm dmmeter orlfme In the centre, took  care of the charging problem Together with A.E. Morgan and H.A.M. de  Grefte, quantitative analysis was performed on a piece of thin section from  bauxite with 300 um diameter (Henstra et al., 1980). Wet chemical and opti-  cal emission spectroscopy data were provided by the analytical department  of Phllips Research Laboratorms. To evaluate the concentration of the ele-  ments from the measured secondary ions set free during sputtering of the  thin section, computer programs made by H.W. Werner, J. v.d. Berg and  A.E. Morgan were used (Werner, 1974; Morgan and Werner, 1977a, b, 1978).  The 300 pm diameter of the analysed area in the thin sectmn, however, was  too large for the study of most soil materials because of their heterogeneity  even on a mlcroscale.    119    In 1980, a visit was made to the Cameca factory in Paris. Quantitative ana-  lysis was done with the new Cameca IMS 3F ion microscope in a spot with  1.5 ~m diameter using computer programs by H.W. Werner and A.E. Morgan.  These data were afterwards screened by H.W. Werner and P.R. Boudewijn.  W.F. Knippenberg included a section on the comparison of data from wet  chemical analysis and analyses by beam techniques. Wet chemical methods  are often used at Philips Research Laboratories before secondary ion mass  spectroscopy (SIMS) is started. A section on various instrumental techniques  for bulk, thin film and microanalysis was inserted by H.W. Werner to illus-  trate the place of ion microscopy.    INSTRUMENT    A secondary ion mass spectrometry (SIMS) analysis is accomplished by  bombarding the surface of a solid sample with a beam of energetic ions. Due  to the impact of these primary ions, atoms from the near-surface region of  the sample will be sputtered away. Depending on the primary ion energy, the  incident angle and the nature of the primary ions a fraction of the sputtered  particles will be charged. These secondary ions (positive or negative) are col-  lected and analysed according to their mass-to-charge ratio in a mass spectro-  meter, thereby providing qualitative and quantitative information about the  elemental composition of the near-surface region of the sample.  Previous experiments were carned out with the ion microprobe mass ana-  lyzer, IMMA (Bisdom et al., 1977} and the 1on microscope Cameca IMS 300  (Henstra et al., 1980). The present investigations were performed with a  second generation SIMS instrument, the Cameca IMS 3F (Fig. la), which is  a direct imaging secondary ion microscope. Fig. lb shows a schematm dia-  gram of the instrument. The primary ions are supplied by a duoplasmatron  ion source capable of producing 02*, N2 Ar+ and O- ions. These primary  ions are accelerated to energies ranging from 5 to 20 keV; an ion optmal  column containing three electrostatic lenses focuses the ion beam to small  diameter; the diameter on the sample varies from 200 pm to 1.5 pm. Deflec-  tion plates enable steering of the primary beam for localized spot analysis  and rastering for high-quality depth profiling.  In contrast to ion microprobe instruments, which require rastermg of a  focused primary beam to obtain ion images, the Cameca instrument uses 1on  optical concepts with direct imaging; the lateral resolution (0.5 ~m) is con-  trolled by the secondary ion optics rather than the primary beam diameter.  The secondary ions are extracted by a high extraction field and focused  onto the entrance slit of the mass spectrometer; for a given mass resolution  the overall transmission of the spectrometer can be optimized by means of a  transfer optics as a function of the analysed sample area.  The mass spectrometer is double focusing resulting in a combination of  high transmission with high mass resolvmg power. The mass range extends  from 1 to 250 amu (atomic mass units).    120  a    121    The mass-analysed secondary ions are detected by a Faraday cup or an  electron multiplier in the pulse-counting mode, thus providing a high dynam-  ic range and high sensitivity.  In the ion microscope mode, ion images are obtained by a microchannel-  plate electron multiplier and a fluorescent screen; the images can be viewed  using a binocular microscope, or photographed with a 35 mm camera.  Quantitative information about the sample composition cannot be ob-  tained in the ion microscope mode, the electron multiplier must be used to  measure the secondary ion currents. Consequently, the lateral resolution in  quantitative microspot analysis is determined by the primary ion beam dia-  meter (~&gt; 1.5 ~m).  Several operational modes of the instrument are available: e.g., mass spec-  trum, depth profiling, step scanning of sample and isotopm analysis.    Quantitatwe analysis    Direct quantitative analysis by SIMS is complicated by the large variations  In ion yield found from one element to another and, for a particular ele-  ment, from one matrix to another. Quantifmatlon with an uncertainty of a  few per cent can only be accomplished after calibration using standard  samples of similar composition. In many cases, however, preparation of such  standards is impossible and other methods of quantification of SIMS results  must be used.  One method is based upon the local thermal equilibrium model (LTE  model} of secondary ion emission proposed by Anderson and Hinthorn  (1973} whereby concentrations can be specified in general to within an ac-  curacy of a factor of 2--3. Although the physical basis of the model is ques-  tionable, results on a variety of samples have shown that quantitative inter-  pretation of SIMS measurements is possible (Morgan and Werner, 1977a,  1978; Morgan, 1980).  According to the LTE model the sample compositions can be estimated  directly from the secondary 1on currents using the equation:  CM = K IM + M~ [ZM0 (Ti)/ZM+(T~)] exp(EM/kTi)  where CM is the atomic concentration of an element M In the sample, K is  an element-independent constant (Henstra et al., 1980), IM* is the measured  secondary ion current corrected for isotopic abundance and M is the mass    Fig. 1. The Cameca IMS 3F ion microscope (a) and schematic diagram (b). I ion gun;  2 = primary column; 3 = immersion lens; 4 = specimen; 5 = specimen chamber; 6 = trans-  fer optics; 7 = entrance slit; 8 = electrostatic analyzer; 9 = energy slit; 10 = image transfer  lens; 11 = spectrometer; 12 = electro-magnet; 13 = final slit; 14 = projection lenses; 15 =  projection, display and detection system; 16 = deflector; 17 = channel-plate; 18 = fluores-  cent screen; 19 = deflector; 20 = remote controlled Faraday cup; 21 = electron multi-  plier; 22 = detection system.    122    number of the isotope monitored. ZMo (T1) and ZM(T~) are the electromc  partitmn functions of the neutrals Mand Mions at temperature Ti, respec-  tively. EM is the first ionizatmn potential of M, h is the Boltzman constant  and T1 (iomzation temperature) is a matrix-dependent fitting parameter.  For a quantitative analysis knowledge of T~ is required. This parameter can  be derived if the concentratmns of one or more elements m the investigated  sample are known (internal standard method) or from suitable, standard  samples since samples of a given matrix have similar TI values (Morgan and  Werner, 1977a, 1978). In the case of complex matrmes T~ can be estimated  on a proportmnal basis from the values of the constituent components  (Morgan, 1980).  Obtaining the data for the partition functions and EM from the literature,  and given the value of Ti, quantitative interpretation of SIMS results can be  made both for major and trace elements.    EXAMPLE OF THIS METHOD    Calcite from a carbonate sample with clay inclusions of a Petrocalclc  Xerochrept from southern Spare was taken for the experiment with the  Cameca IMS 3F. The distribution pattern of calcite and clay may vary slgm-  ficantly in the thin section which was made from a plastic-hardened sample  using the method described by Jongerms and Heintzberger (1975). This may  give some difficulty at the start of the work because locallsatlon with the ion  mmroscope is not easy for soil samples. The following procedure was there-  fore chosen. A micrograph of the thin section was made with the petrograph-  ic mmroscope before the piece of thin section was removed from the object  glass for insertion in and analysis with the 1on microscope. The latter mstru-  ment can make Ion images similar to X-ray images m electron mmroscopy.  These 1on images can be used for locahzatlon purposes, 1.e. the distribution  pattern of the chemical elements in the 1on images allow localization of the  area of analysis and of the larger soil components in the micrograph made  with the petrographic mmroscope. An extra orientation mark forms the tan-  talum plate which surrounds the area to be analysed. The tantalum plate is  used to counteract charging.  Ion mmroscopy offers operational modes whmh can be compared with  those of electron microscopy, i.e. images, line scans and point analyses can  also be made. Images are now called ion images, line scans are also indmated  as step scan analysis and point analyses have the same name    Ion spectra    Positive and negative 1on spectra can be made of areas which can differ in  diameter. During our experiment, predominantly positive secondary ion  spectra were made of areas with diameters of 150/~m, 60/~m, 25/~m and  8 pm. Spectra were also obtained from spots with a diameter of 1.5 pm.    123    A positive secondary ion spectrum of an area with 150/~m diameter in  calcite is given in Fig. 2. A large number of positive ions is indicated: H, Li,  B, C, O, Ca, Na, Mg, AI, Si, K, Ca, Ti and Cr, as well as the molecular ions  CaO, Ca20 and Ca202. This wealth of elements, including trace elements,  in calcite seems to suggest that some of the elements have been derived from  clay inclusions found m the carbonate. X-ray diffraction demonstrated that  montmorillonite, palygorskite and kaohnite were the dominant clay mine-  rals.    lo6                   +  N             o             u  105         + '~+     + ~                   0   104                                                             {,.)  102                                                         I  101~                      I  100                                                               ,I         I ,  10  2'0  30  40  50  60  70  80  90  100  110  =~ mass number    Fig. 2. Positive secondary ion spectrum of calcite. Analysed area ~ 150 .m    Ion zmages    Ion images can be made of trace and major elements due to high count  rates and good peak to background ratios. Of special interest is the high mass  resolving power of the Cameca IMS 3F whmh allows the separation of ele-  mental and molecular ions which occur at the same mass number. Not only  the diameter of the field used for secondary 1on imaging can be changed but  also the mass resolving power. As a consequence it is possible to investigate  the soil sample in different modes.  The first example are 1on images from calcite (CaCO3) mveshgated with a  mass resolving power M/AM of 300 {Fig. 3). Positwe secondary ion images  are given of ~H, 23Na, 24Mg, 2sSi, 39K, 4a, 48T1 and S2Cr. The 1on images  were made with various exposure times ranging from half a second for cal-  cium to thirty seconds for tltanmm and chromium. The calcium is present    124    F~g. 3 Positive secondary ion images of some elements present in calcite Mass resolving  power M/AM = 300. Field of view ~ = 150 um    over virtually the whole image; the sodmm, magnesmm, silicon and potas-  sium are represented m similar distribution patterns over the calcite; the  titanmm and chromium are concentrated in a few areas; hydrogen is present  over a larger part of the sample and probably indicates the presence of plas-  tm whmh was used for hardening of the sample. No obvious distribution re-  lation is present between hydrogen and other ions In the images. It is there-  fore postulated that ions other than hydrogen may also be associated with  the calcite and not only with plashc.  The second example concerns the distinction between S6CaO and S6Fe  positive ions. Mass interference of CaO and Fe occurs because both have  56 amu (atomm mass units). To solve this problem, an instrument is neces-    125    sary which has a high mass resolving power. The Cameca IMS 3F is able to  obl~ilin ~t goocl l:c~ul} (Fig, 'i) by inereaoin$ the ma~$ re~olvin$ power M{AM  to 5000. Consequently, different distribution patterns can be rec0gnized for  56CaO and S6Fe in the images.    Fig 4 Positive secondary ion images of Fe and CaO present in calcite. Mass resolving  power M/AM = 5000. Field of view ~ ffi 150 #m    The third and last example of ion images was made from a sample with  calcite and clay (Fig. 5). Positive secondary ion images are given of 23Na,  24Mg, 27A1, 28S1, 39K, 4a, 48Ti and S2Cr. Exposure times varied from half  a second for calcium to thirty seconds for potassium, titanmm and chromi-  um. These ton images indicate that calcite is mamly concentrated in the  northwest part of the images and clay in the southeast. Potassium is the only  element found m the whole image. The calcite part of the image contained  sodium, titanium and chromium besides calcium, whereas the clay part had  predominantly aluminium and silicon. To obtain more insight into the dis-  trtbutlon and quantity of chemical elements, a line scan was made.    Line scan or step scan analys~s    Line scanning is also called step scan analysis in ion microscopy because it  is done in steps which involve 50 point analyses along a line AB (Fig. 6). The  elements can be scanned simultaneously, up to ten elements with the present  computer capacity. Only the elements Mg, Si, Ca and A1 are portrayed in  Fig. 6 for readability reasons. T1 and Na were also scanned and these ele-  ments had low count rates varying between 10and 101 cts/sec m both cal-  cite and clay.  Clay is present near point A of Fig. 6. The amount of clay is at a maxi-  mum up to 4 steps in the direction of point B and thereafter gradually de-    126    Fig  5 Positive secondary 1on images of some elements present in a sample with calcite  and clay Mass resolving power M/AM = 300. Field of view ~ = 150 urn    creases in quantity up to about 8 steps from A. Calcite is dominant in the  other part of the line scan  Ion images of Ca and Mg m Fig. 6 are the same as m Fig. 5 and were used  to indicate the position of line AB. Minor differences in distribution patterns  of chemical elements may occur because the sample is very slowly eroded  during analysis. The fifty point analyses of the line scan mdmated that Mg,  Si, Ca and A1 are present and give about 103 cts/sec in the clay fraction. The  number of counts for calcium m the calcite is not much higher than mea-  sured m clay, whereas the figure is much lower for Mg, Si and A1. To obtain  some insight into the quantity of individual elements in point analyses, cal-  culations were done with a computer.    a  106   10s  (D  0  i  104  10a    102    101  100  0  A    __ 27AI+  m m. 4OCa*    .....  28Si *    .....  24Mg*    10        20        30        40    i  5O      steps          B    127    Fig. 6. Step scan analysis along the line AB in secondary ion images of Ca and Mg from a  sample with calcite and clay (cf Fig 5). The diameter of the primary ion beam is 1.5 urn.    Point analyses    Point analyses were done in a spot with 1.5 pm diameter in both calcite  and clay. Quantification of data was possible using the procedure described  in the section on quantitative analysis. A quantitative SIMS analysis of the  elements in calcite is given in Table I and of clay m Table II. All elements  other than Ca are present in small quantities in the calcite. The clay of Table    128    TABLE I  Quantitative SIMS analysis of calctte  Element                  Calculated  concentration  (atomic per cent)    Ca                      19 17  Na                       0 07  Mg                         0 30  AI                0 11  S]                          0 27  K                          001  T1                         0 07    Calculated concentrations have been summed to a substance fraction of atoms of 20%  TABLE II  Quantitative SIMS analysis of clay inclusions m calcite    Element    Calculated  concentration  (atomic per cent)    Ca                       0.05  Na                       0.02  Mg                3.33  AI                4.49  Sl                        28.23  K                        002  Ti                         0.04  Cr                     &lt;0 01  Fe                       0 66    Calculated concentrations have been summed to a substance fraction of atoms of 36.85%.    II had Mg, A1 and Si as the principal elements. The results indicate that even  trace elements can be measured quantitatively in point analyses of soil  samples. As was explamed, however, electron microscope techmques should  help to obtain a prehmmary insight into the quantity of chemmal elements  which are represented above trace element quantity m the sample. Wet  chemical and other techniques for the research of bulk samples can also be  used. These are described briefly below together with a number of other  submicroscopic techniques for in sltu mvestigation of materials in thin sec-  tions.    WET CHEMICAL ANALYSIS AND ANALYSIS BY BEAM TECHNIQUES    A characteristic of wet chemmal bulk analysis is its mono-element sequen-  tial mode of operation: after dissolution of the sample, sometimes followed    129    by extraction procedures, each element is determined under optimized non-  compromise conditions. For the determination, instrumental detection  techniques are usually used, each with specific detection limits. Well above  the detection hmlt quantitative determinations can be performed with ac-  curacies better than 0.1% (Kmppenberg, 1974). To be able to perform these  operations in a rational way a semiquantitatlve instrumental survey analysis,  e.g. by optmal emission or X-ray spectrometry, usually precedes wet chemi-  cal analysis.  Because of the high accuracy obtainable, wet chemical analysis is used m  the analysis of standard samples for purely instrumental techniques like the  beam techmques.  The analysis yields an average value of the composition of the analysed  mass. One distmguishes methods of macro-, micro-, or ultra-mmroanalysis  depending on whether the analysed samples mvolve amounts of material in  the order of 100 mg, 100 ~g or 100 ng, respectively. Sampling of these  amounts can be performed mechanically, chemically or by sputtering tech-  tuques. Even in cases where the amount of material available would allow  macroanalysis, microanalysis is often preferred to check on homogeneity and  to reach a better statistical evaluation. The reproducibility of the beam tech-  tuques is rather high (order of %) so that both the homogeneity of the stan-  dard samples and the heterogeneity of the mvestigated sample can be  checked. The information volume of the beam techniques can be some  orders of magnitude smaller than the "information volume" of the sample  investigated in practice by wet chemical analysis; the absolute detection lim-  it may be of the same order of magnitude.    INSTRUMENTAL TECHNIQUES FOR BULK, THIN FILM AND MICROANALYSIS    A large number of sophisticated instrumental techniques for chemical  analysis is available at present wherewith -- contrary to wet chemistry -- a  multi-element analysis can be carried out simultaneously. The speed of the  analysis is thereby mcreased significantly. The detectable elements -- in par-  ticular when mass spectrometric methods (SSMS or SIMS; cf. Table III) are  used -- range from hydrogen to uranium.  A distraction must be made between methods for bulk analysis and for  thin film and microanalysls (Werner, 1982/83): in bulk analytical methods,  such as spark source mass spectrometry, optical emission spectroscopy and  X-ray fluorescence (cf. Table IV), 10 to 50 mg of sample is used per analysis  corresponding to a large probed volume (2 109 to 10~~m3 per analysis).  Bulk analytical methods obviously give the average chemical concentration  of the probed volume.  In thin film and microanalysls information about the distribution (one-,  two- and three-dimensional) of the elements m the sample is needed. In that  case methods with small information depths and widths must be used. With  respect to information depth two groups can be distinguished. Group (a) has    130  TABLE III  Abbrevmtmns of instrumental techniques for chemmal analysis    AES  BLE  EELS  EMP    ESCA  HEIS  ISS  LAMMA  LEIS  LMP  LOES  OES  PIXE  RBS  SAM  SEM  SIMS  SSMS  STEM  TEM  TEELS  XPS  XRF    Auger Electron Spectroscopy  Bombardment-reduced Lxght Emlssxon  Electron Energy-Loss Spectrometry (=ELS)  Electron Microprobe analysis, used In two modes wz. Energy  Dtsperslve X-ray analysis (EDX) and Wavelength Dispersive X-  ray analysis (WDX)  Electron Spectroscopy for Chemical Analysis  High Energy Ion Scattering = RBS  Ion Scattering Spectrometry = LEIS  Laser Microprobe Mass Analysis = LMP  Low Energy Ion Scattering = ISS  Laser Microprobe Analysis = LAMMA  Laser Optical Emission Spectrometry  Optical Emission Spectrometry  Partmle Induced X-ray Emission  Rutherford Backscattering Spectrometry = HEIS  Scanning Auger Microprobe  Scanning Electron Microscopy  Secondary Ion Mass Spectrometry  Spark Source Mass Spectrometry  Scanning-Transmission Electron Microscope  Transmission Electron Microscope  Tran~missmn Electron Energy Loss Spectrometry  X-Ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy  X-ray Fluorescence Spectrometry    an reformation depth of maximally 3 nm, such as m SIMS, AES, ESCA,  LEIS, BLE {cf. Table V). Depth profiles are obtained using these methods  (with the exception of HEIS) by continuous bombardment of the sample  with an 1on beam; the sample is thereby sputtered w~th a constant erosion  rate. By tuning the mstrument to one or several elements and recording the  corresponding signals as a function of time (depth) depth profiles are ob-  tained. In HEIS a depth profile is obtained without the need to sputter the  sample (Werner, 1980, 1982/83). Depth resolutions down to about 3 nm  can be achieved with group (a) methods.  Group (b) (cf. first column m Table V) has an reformation depth of about  1 ~m or is limited by the sample thickness. With LOES and LAMMA the  material is evaporated by the laser beam. Depth profiles analogous, as were  described under (a) for sputtering, can be obtamed. The depth resolution is  about 1 ~m.  The detection hmlt in thm film and microtechnlques ~s between some per  cent down to the ppm and even to the ppb range (Table V, 2nd column).  The lateral resolution (Table V, 3rd column) is m the micron and submicron  range; with analytical electron mmroscopy it can even be 5 nm. This lateral  resolution allows inclusions with the above mentioned dimensions to be    131    &lt;    ~, .~ o        ,,  .El  r~ "~" ~11   ~    %  "  =   ,~        oo  ~ ~ ~ -~.~    oo  ~ II  ~,"~  =L   ~      ~                ~1  ._    0  =  ,=  =.  .g 3  ~    L~    =L  v?~,    E       =  0    ~4  0  ,~ ~ o~  o   ~   ~    ~      -"   [.~    0    13    0   0      0  0    0  L  'S    132  TABLE V  Selected analytical features of the different methods    Information      Detection        Lateral           Element  depth            limit (frac-       resolution       range  tlonal concen-  tratmn.1 )    (a) AES  ESCA  LEIS  HEIS  SIMS  BLE    (b) LAMMA  LOES  SEM-EDX  EMP-EDX  TEM-EDX  EELS-TEM  PIXE    0.4--2 5 nm      10-3                0 1--3 um     &gt;/ Lt  1--3 nm          10 2                15 pm--1 nm   &gt;/ He  0 3--1 nm        10 ~             100 pm          &gt; L~  3--103 nm         lOL~--lOJS/cm:      1--3 pm        &gt;/ C  100 ppm (bulk)                  (M&gt; Msubstrate)  0 3--1 nm                           0.1--1 um      &gt;1 H  0.3--1rim         10-s%=01ppm  100pro          1&gt; H    0.1--1 pm       &lt;0_1 ppm-ppb   -~ pm           H-U  0 2--1 um        10-3                10 pm           69 elements   um              10-3                  1 pm           ~ Na   pm             10-3                 1 pm           &gt; Na  -~ sample thick-  10 3              ~ 5 nm           &gt; Na  hess (~100 nm)   sample thick-  &lt;10-3            -~ 5 nm           &gt; B, C  ness (~ 100 nm)   um            0 1--10 ppm     3--1000 um      ~ Na    *~ Unless otherwise stated    analysed, a feature that may turn out to be most important for further  chemical analysis of soil materials in the mmron and nanometer range.    CONCLUSIONS    During earlier experiments with the 1on mmroscope, a Cameca IMS 300  was used to obtain quantitative data from secondary ions sputtered from an  area in the thin section with 300 ~m diameter. The present experiment was  done with a second generation ion mmroscope, the Cameca IMS 3F. This  instrument allowed quantification of soil material in a spot with 1.5 pm  diameter. Such point analyses can be used well in soil micromorphology be-  cause they even allow quantification of trace elements in thin sections of  materials which vary in composition over micron-distances.  Electron mmroscopy, EMA (electron rmcroprobe analysis) and SEM-  WDXRA (scanning electron microscope - wavelength dispersive X-ray anal-  ysis) allow the investigation of most elements quantitatively when not  present as trace elements. Ion mmroscopy is able to analyse all elements,  including hydrogen, and gives data on trace elements. If research interests  include trace elements, electron microscopy should therefore be followed by  1on microscopy.    133    In the present experiment with calcite and clay, a wealth of chemical ele-  ments were analysed. Such information may be difficult to compare with  data obtained by electron microscopy and light microscopy because no such  detail on in situ microchemistry has been encountered so far. Consequently,  only tentative interpretations are allowed. In the present case, it seems that  some of the elements, analysed with the Cameca IMS 3F in the calcite, have  been derived from clay inclusions. Light microscopy, electron microscopy  and Ion microscopy seem to indicate that such elements may have been em-  placed in the calcite during the replacement of clay.  Ion microscopy will usually represent a final stage of in situ soil research.  Quantifmation of the chemical elements in soil materials will not be easy,  even if computer programs are available. It will remain necessary to include  other techniques based on in situ research of thin sections or on bulk anal-  ysis of pre-treated and disturbed samples. Several of these techniques have  been indicated briefly in this paper and should allow some insight into ana-  lytical possibihties and the position of ion microscopy. So far, only a few of  the most promising instruments have been tested on soft materials in thin  sections. However, with ion microscopy, it will be possible to investigate a  large number of problems in soil mlcromorphology in the reqmred detail.  Such detail may be of importance for the study of thin sections from the  natural soil environment and for the investigation of samples derived from  physicochemical experiments.    REFERENCES    Anderson, C A. and Hinthorne, J., 1973. Thermodynamic approach to the quantltative  mterpretation of sputtered ion spectra. Anal. Chem., 45: 1421--1438.  Bisdom, E.B A., 1981. A review of the application of submicroscopic techniques in soil  micromorphology, If. Electron microprobe analyzer (EMA), scanning electron micro-  scope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis (ESCA), ion microprobe  mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary ion microscope (SIM) In: E.B.A. Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Interna-  tlonal Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentatlon (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp. 117--162.  Bisdom, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerius, A., Brown, J.D., Von Rosenstiel, A.P. and Gras,  D.J , 1977  Light and heavy element detection in thin sections of soils with the ion  microprobe mass analyzer (IMMA). Neth. J Agric. Sci., 25 (1): 1--13.  Bisdorn, E.B.A., Henstra, S., Jongerlus, A., Heinen, H.J. and Meier, S., 1981. Chemical  element detection in thin sections of soils with the laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500). Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 29 (1) 23--36.  Henstra, S., Bisdom, E.B.A., Jongerlus, A., Morgan, A.E., Werner, H.W. and De Grefte,  H A.M., 1980. Quantltative analysis on thin sections of soils by secondaxy ion mass  spectrometry. In: P Brederoo and V.E Cosslett (Editors), Electron Microscopy 1980.  Proceedings of the 7th European Congress on Electron Microscopy including the  9th International Conference on X-ray Optics and Microanalysis, The Hague.  Seventh European Congress on Electron Microscopy Foundation, Leiden, 1980 Vol.  3. Analysis, pp. 224--225.    134    Henstra, S., Bisdom, E B A and Boekestein, A., 1981. Submicroscopm techniques for m  situ microchemical analysis of soils, III Destructive techmques. In: E B.A Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submmroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen  Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc~,  Wagenmgen, pp. 55--65  Jongerius, A. and Heintzberger, G., 1975 Methods m soil mmromorphology A technique  for the preparation of large thin sections Neth Soil Surv Inst., Soil Surv Pap., 10:  48 pp.  Knlppenberg, W F , 1974 Inorganic chemmal analysis Philips Techn. Rev_, 34 (11/12):  298--304  Morgan, A E., 1980. An alternative to the relative sensitivity factor approach to quanti-  tative SIMS analysis. Surf. Interface Anal, 2:123--133  Morgan, A.E. and Werner, H W , 1977a Test of a quantitative approach to secondary Ion  mass spectrometry on glass and sihcate standards Anal. Chem., 49:927--931  Morgan, A.E. and Werner, H.W, 1977b. Semlquantitative analysis by secondary mn mass  spectrometry. J. Micros. Spectros Electron , 2:285--290  Morgan, A E and Werner, H.W , 1978 Semiquantitatlve analyses by secondary ion mass  spectrometry using one fitting parameter Mikrochlm. Acta (Wien), 11:31--50  Werner, H.W , 1974. Theoretical and experimental aspects of secondary ion mass spectro-  metry Vacuum, 24:493--505  Werner, H.W., 1980. Modern methods for thin film and surface analysis In P. Brederoo  and V.E  Cosslett (Editors), Electron Microscopy 1980. Proceedings of the 7th  European Congress on Electron Microscopy including the 9th International Confer-  ence on X-ray Optms and Microanalysis, The Hague. Seventh European Congress on  Electron Mmroscopy Foundation, Leiden, 1980 Vol. 3. Analysis, pp. 200--207.  Werner, H.W , 1982/83. The apphcation of beam and diffraction techniques for thin film  and surface torero-analysis  In: H. Oechsner (Editor), Thin Film Analysis  Springer-  Verlag, Berlin.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractA series of experiments have been performed for a number of years to obtain quantitative microchemical analysis by secondary ion microscopy of materials in thin sections of soils. The first successful quantification was obtained from an area with a diameter of 300 μm in bauxite and done with an IMS 300 at Philips Research Laboratories. Such an area, however, is frequently too large for most soil samples which are extremely heterogeneous even on a microscale. A second generation IMS 3F was tested for soils at the Cameca factory in Paris. This instrument allows the quantification of trace and major elements of soil constituents in a spot with 1.5 μm diameter, using a computer program developed by Philips Research Laboratories. Calcite and clay from a Petrocalcic Xerochrept were used for this test. Ion spectra, ion images and linear traverses were made giving information on the nature and distribution of both major and trace elements. The possibility of investigating a larger number of chemical elements simultaneously in linear traverses is of considerable help in the study of thin sections. Various submicroscopic and other techniques are discussed to give some insight into the position of ion microscopy amongst these. 