 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 171--177                                                     171  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    CALCIUM-DOMINATED ORGANANS IN HUMIC PODZOLS FROM THE  HUDSON AND JAMES BAY LOWLANDS OF ONTARIO (CANADA)    RICHARD PROTZ  Department of Land Resource Science, Unwerszty of Guelph, Guelph, Ont. NIG 2WI  (Canada)  (Accepted for publicahon February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Protz, R., 1983. Calcium-dominated organans m Humic Podzols from the Hudson and  James Bay Lowlands of Ontario (Canada) Geoderma, 30: 171--177.    The SEM-EDXRA analysis of cutans within five Humlc Podzolic soils derived from  calcareous sands and gravels revealed the presence of Ca-dominated organans. It is postu-  lated that organic matter saturated by H and Al is translocated through the Ae-honzon  and prempitated within the Bh horizon in the presence of calcareous material. Weathering  of the calcareous material within the Bh horizon results in the partial replacement of the  H and A1 in the organans by Ca.    INTRODUCTION    Developmental sequences of Podzolic soils formed under black spruce  (Picea manana (Mill.) B.S.P.) and lichen (dominantly Cladina rangiferina  (L.) Harm) vegetation within the Hudson and James Bay Lowlands of Ontario  have been reported by Protz (1982). It was shown that a Humic Podzol  develops on coarse textured calcareous beach ridges before the evolution  of Humo-Ferric Podzol (terminology of the Canada Soil Survey Committee,  1978). The Bh horizons of the Humic Podzols had large amounts of organic  matter (from 6 to 25 percent) but low amounts of Na-pyrophosphate-  extractable Fe and A1. Initial work indicated the organic matter in the Bh  horizons was Ca-saturated. In previous studies of chemical compositions of  cutans of Canadian soils none were found to be dominated by Ca (Brewer  et al., 1973; McKeague and Protz, 1980; McKeague and Wang, 1980; Mc-  Keague, 1981).  The purpose of this paper is to report the SEM-EDXRA results which  indicate the presence of Ca-dominated organans in Humic Podzols and to  suggest the genetic process by which they form.    0016-7061/83/$03.00     1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V    172    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The field soil samphng procedures used are described m Protz (1982).  The particle-size distribution, organic matter, pH, CaCO3 equivalent, pyro-  phosphate-extractable Fe and A1 analyses were made following procedures  outlined by McKeague (1978). Exchangeable cations (A1, Ca, Mg, H, K and  Na), were determined using the Ag-Thiourea extraction procedure of Pleysmr  and Juo (1980). Impregnation of undisturbed samples followed procedures  outhned by McCarrick and Protz (1978). The SEM-EDXRA analyses were  made using a JEOL JSM-35C Scanning Electron Microscope with a Tracor  X-ray detector and a TN-2000 Data System. Thin sections were coated with  Au-Pd for analyses using 15KV.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Thin sections from five Humic Podzols were studied. Organans coated all  sand grams within the Bh horizon (Fig. 1). These grmns consisted of quartz,  feldspar and calcite as well as sandstone and hmestone fragments. The orga-  hanS were reddish-orange in color and are similar to those in Bhc horizons  of Ortstein softs reported by McKeague and Wang (1980). A backscattered  electron image of the organans (Fig. 2a) shows their fractured nature due to  drying before impregnation. The X-ray image of Si (Fig. 2b) indicates the    Fig. 1. Ca-dominated organans coating all sand grains within a Bh horizon of a Humm  Podzol. Plane polarized light (55.    173    Fig. 2. a. Backscattered electron scanning image of a typical Ca-dominated organan, b.  X-ray image of Si. c. X-ray image of AI. d. X-ray image of Ca. e. X-ray image of Fe. f.  Representative X-ray spectrum of a Ca-dominated organan.    174    Fig, 2 (continued),    175    presence of some silicon within the organans. A1 in Fig. 2c is present in  feldspar grains and within organans. The X-ray image of Ca (Fig. 2d) isolates  the Ca-dominated organans from the covered mineral grains. The presence  of a minimal amount of Fe m the organans is demonstrated in Fig. 2e. A  typical EDXRA spectrum of a Ca-dominated organan is shown in Fig. 2f.    176    To establish the variation in elemental composition of organans, twenty  spots were examined by SEM-EDXRA. The mean, standard deviation and  variance of the relative amounts of S1, Ca, A1 and Fe withm these twenty  spots are given in Table I. The average Sl: Ca: Al: Fe ratios are 4: 13: 6. 1  within these organans.    TABLE I    Mean, standard deviation and vazlance of relative amounts of Si, Ca, A1 and Fe in twenty  spots of calcium-dominated organans in the Bh horizon of Humic Podzols    Statistm    Sl       Ca      A1      Fe  Mean       0 123   0.566   0.268   0 042  Std. dev.  0.092  0.116  0 096  0.020  Variance   0.008   0.013   0.009   0 000    As the black spruce (Picea mariana (Mill.) B.S.P.) and lichens (dominantly  Cladina rangiferina (L.) Harm) mature, the organic surface is thmkened on  the calcareous sand and gravels. This results in the dissolution of calcareous  mineral material resulting in an increase m the void space, the leaching of  Ca and Mg from the solum and the formation of thin Ae horizons (Protz,  1982). Through this acid horizon organic materials can move mechamcally  because of increased void size and faunal activity. Bal {1970) has stated  that faunal excrements as large as 30 ~m could be transported in a coarse  textured Podzol. Ugohnl et al. (1977) have shown that organic particles  contaming traces of aluminum, iron, silicon and sulfur migrated from the  upper A and B to lower horizons. Dispersed organic matter can also move  in suspension.  De Conmck (1980) has suggested two different mechamsms for the forma-  tion of two types of spodic horizons. In loose spodic horizons an excess of  polyvalent cations are present which immobilize potentially mobile organic  substances formed dunng the breakdown of plant remains. In cemented  spodlc horizons the polyvalent cations have been previously removed and  mobile organic substances migrate downward to depths of higher ionic  concentrations, to drier soil material. In the Ae horizons of four of the five  soils studmd, the sum of exchangeable Al and H was greater than the sum of  exchangeable Ca and Mg. Within the Bh horizons of all five soils, exchange-  able Ca and Mg were much higher than A1 and H.  The acidic organic material is precipitated on all sand grains and as such  holds water around grains. Under this moist condition the calcareous mate-  rial m the Bh horizon dissolves releasing Ca to saturate the organans. The  original H- and Al-saturated organic matter thus becomes Ca-saturated.  The age of the organic matter within the Bh horizons of four Hum]c  Podzols has been determined by 14C analyses. The dates range from 940 -+ 80  years B.P. to 4470 -+ 120 years B.P. Therefore it can be said that these Ca-    177    dominated organans formed within 1000 years of beach ridge development  and may have persisted for 3500 years in the Hudson and James Bay Low-  lands of Ontario.    CONCLUSIONS    Calcmm-dominated organans exist in Bh horizons of Humic Podzols  according to EDXRA measurements in softs derived from coarse textured  calcareous deposits under black spruce and lichen vegetatmn. The Bh horizons  have been formed withm 1000 years after beach ridge development and  have persisted for the last 3500 years.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    I gratefully acknowledge: NSERC Grant No. A-3547, O.M.A.F. Program  39 and D.S.S. contract No. 05479-00097 for financial support; the Labora-  tory of the Ontario Institute of Pedology for many of the analyses; Mr.  Cameron Ackerly for assistance with the SEM-EDXRA portion of this  study; Dr. Leo Bal and Martin Shlpitalo for commenting on an earlier draft  of this manuscript, and Sheree Henry for typing this manuscript.    REFERENCES    Bal, L, 1970. Morphological mvestigation in two moder -- humus profiles and the role  of the soil fauna in their genesis Geoderma, 4: 5--36.  Brewer, R , Protz, R. and McKeague, J.A., 1973. Microscopy and electron microprobe  analysls of some iron-manganese pans from Newfoundland. Can. J. Soil Sci., 53  349--361  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classifmation. Res.  Branch, Can Dep. Agric. Publ., 1646; 164 pp.  De Coninck, F., 1980. Major mechanisms in formation of spodm horizons. Geoderma,  24: 101--128.  McCarrick, T. and Protz, R., 1978. The effects of soil composition upon three acrylic  soil impregnating resins. Commun. Soil Scl Plant Analysis, 9 955--962.  McKeague, J.A (Editor), 1978 Manual on soil sampling and methods of analysis: Can.  Soc. Soil Sci., 212 pp.  McKeague, J.A. and Wang, C., 1980. Micromorphology and microprobe analysis of ort-  stein horizons of podzolic soils from New Brunswick and Nova Scotia, Canada. Can.  J. Soil Sci., 60: 9--21.  McKeague, J.A. and Protz, R., 1980. Cement of duric horizons, micromorphology and  energy dispersive analysis. Can. J Soil Sci., 60" 45--52.  McKeague, J.A., 1981. SEM-EDXRA as an extension of light microscopy in smi charac-  terization and genesis studies. In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils  and Weathered Rocks. Pudoc, Wageningen, pp. 277--282.  Pleysier, J.L. and Juo, A.S.R., 1980. A single extraction method for measuring exchange-  able cations and effective CEC in soils with variable charges. Soft Sci., 129: 205--211.  Protz, R., 1982. Development of podzolic soils in the Hudson Bay and James Bay Low-  land, Ontario. Naturallste Can., 109: 501--510.  Ugolini, F.C., Dawson, H. and Zachara, J., 1977. Direct evidence of paxticle migration  in the soil solution of a Podzol. Science, 198:603--605                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractThe SEM-EDXRA analysis of cutans within five Humic Podzolic soils derived from calcareous sands and gravels revealed the presence of Ca-dominated organans. It is postulated that organic matter saturated by H and Al is translocated through the Ae-horizon and precipitated within the Bh horizon in the presence of calcareous material. Weathering of the calcareous material within the Bh horizon results in the partial replacement of the H and Al in the organans by Ca. 