 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 87-88                                                      87  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    IN MEMORIAM  CHARLES E. KELLOGG    A member of the original Editorial Board of Geoderma, Dr. Kellogg died  March 9, 1980, after an illness of several months. He was born in Ionia County,  Michigan, on August 2, 1902. He earned his bachelor's and doctoral degrees  in soil science at Michigan State University. As a student, he acquired an in-  terest in the applications of soil science which never left him.  Initial jobs were with the Wisconsin Geological and Natural History Survey,  where he remained for two years, and on the faculty of North Dakota State  University, which he joined in 1930. In addition to teaching, he was active in  soil surveys then being made in western North Dakota to provide a basis for  tax assessment of rural lands.    88    Dr. Kellogg joined the staff of the U.S. Department of Agriculture in Wash-  ington, D.C., in 1934 and became Chief of the Division of Soil Survey, Bureau  of Chemistry and Soils, a year later. He continued to be a national leader in  the soil survey program of the United States until he retired from the post of  Deputy Administrator for Soil Survey in the Soil Conservation Service 37  years later.  He was president of the Soil Science Society of America in 1941, vice presi-  dent of the International Society of Soil Science from 1956 to 1960, and a  vice president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science  in 1949. In recognition of his services to soil science in those countries, he  was made an honorary member of each of the Royal Society of New Zealand  and the Indian Society of Soil Science. He served as secretary of the Committee  on Agriculture during the conference in Quebec in 1945 through which the  Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations was established.  Dr. Kellogg published more than 150 scientific papers as well as a number  of books. The titles of the latter indicate much of his outlook and philosophy.  His first book was called The Soils that Support Us and his last Agricultural  Development: Soils, Food, People, Work. He firmly believed and always strove  to see that soil science contributed to human welfare.  Throughout his career, he was interested in a wide range of knowledge, as  witness the titles in his paper "Reading for soil scientists, together with a libra-  ry" (Journal of the American Society of Agronomy, 32(11): 867--876, 1940).  A long-time bibliophile, he was especially keen on the writings of James Joyce.  Dr. Kellogg made many contributions to soil science and to soil surveys  during a long and distinguished career. Only one major contribution will be  cited, the Soil Survey Manual; published in 1951 to replace a much smaller  volume with the same title issued in 1937. He conducted conferences over a  period of five years during which the guides were hammered out in discussion  and debate that were later pulled together and published in the Manual. More-  over, he did most of the work of getting the conference reports consolidated  in publishable form. The 1951 Manual represented a great step forward in  the identification, description, and mapping of soils, something that was vital  to the effective organization and dissemination of information about useful-  ness of soils for any purpose.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             