Geoderma, 25 (1981) 293--305                                                   293  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Silcrete in Australia. T. Langford-Smith (Editor). Departraent of Geography,  University of New England, 1979, 304 pp.    This book is a collection of papers by various authors, based on a sympo-  sium on silcretes which was held in 1973, but the editor has made some wel-  come effo~ to update the material. A volume on the origin of silcretes has  long been awaited, as this subject is only rarely discussed in the international  literature on siliceous sediments.  As pointed out by the editor, the papers can be divided into four groups.  The first deals with general characteristics of silcrete, with some information  on weathering processes. The second describes silcretes and siliceous hard-  pans, mainly in the Great Artesian Basin. The third includes studies of sil-  crete occurrences from the coastal zone of New South Wales; and the fourth  contains a comparison of Australian silcretes with those of South Africa,  N.W. Europe, mid the U.S. interior.  While the descriptive papers are largely of .local interests, other are illumi-  nating to the general reader, as they emphasize tho strong disagreements ex-  isting between different researchers regarding the major prt, blems of silcrete  formation, and provide detailed information, which it is hoped will lead or  has led to new lines of research. Thc most controversial problems discussed  are: the relationship between silcrete and lateritic duricrasts and between sil-  cretes and calcretes; the relationship between silcretes and underlying deep  weathering profiles, and the possible relationship between some silcretes and  associated or nearby basalts; the climatic conditions under which silcretes  form--humid or arid; the ages of widespread silcrete occurrences; the relation-  ship between silica mineralogy of younger silcretes and their ervironment of  deposition; source of silica and the mode of its transport; the problem of sil-  crete formation at or below the surface; the importance of topography for sil-  crete formation. Thus, much remains to be done, particularly on the geo-  chemistry of the various types of silcretes, a subject unfortunately underre-  presented in this volume.  As in most symposium volumes, the quality of the papers is uneven, and  a certain amount of redundancy is unavoidable, although some of it seems  excessive. The reviewer was'particularly impressed by the contributions of  Hutton et al., Van Dijk and Beckmann, Wopfner, and Watts, and to some ex-  tent also by the contributions of Gunn and Galloway. The comparative study  of Australian silcretes with those of N.W. Europe and the U.S. interior, by  Dury and Habermann is, however, not very informative.    M. KASTNER  (La Jolla, Calif.)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             