 Geoderma, 30 (1983) 195--217                                                     195  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CHARACTERISTICS AND SIGNIFICANCE OF COMPOSITE PARTICLES  DERIVED FROM A COLOMBIAN ANDOSOL PROFILE    P.A RIEZEBOS and W.J. LUSTENHOUWER  Laboratory of Phystcal Geography and Sod Science, Unwersity of Amsterdam, Dapper-  straat 115, 1093 BS Amsterdam (The Netherlands)  Netherlands Orgamzatmn for the Advancement of Pure Research (ZWO), De Boelelaan  1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam (The Netherlands)  (Accepted for pubhcatmn February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Riezebos, P.A. and Lustenhouwer, W.J., 1983. Charactermtics and sigmfmance of com-  posite particles derived from a Colomblan andosol profile Geoderma, 30: 195--217.    Composite partmles, frequently observed m sand and coarse sdt from laboratory-  treated andosol materials, have been collected at eight levels m an andosol profile near  Guasca (Colombia) and studmd by microscopic, SEM and electron microprobe tech-  tuques. The particles appear to be made up of a varying number of fine sand- to clay-  sized grains of various shape and nature, cemented together by an optically isotropic  material of allophanic composihon. Plots of the chemical parameters of this cement  against depth reveal a zonal arrangement of malor and minor elements. A stratified  arrangement is also shown by petrographic features of the light- and heavy-mineral  fractions of the associated sample material, and by the fabric of small undisturbed lumps  from depths between the eight levels.  The composite particles are obviously the product of allophane-generating sites in  surficlal layers containing unstable solids as volcamc glass and minerals. Although in  this study the partmles have been investigated in the form of artifmial fragments, more  or less similar ones will originate under natural conditions It is argued that their occur-  rence as sand- and silt-sized individuals m natural erosion products, and thus also in ag-  gradational soils, must drastmally affect chemmal soil parameters, when obtained by  wet chemmal analysis of bulk samples.    INTRODUCTION    Routine-microscopic observations of sand-sized material from andosols  developed from surficial volcanic ashes on the Sabana de Bogota {Colom-  bia), reveal the frequent occurrence of composite particles. Apparently  their stability was sufficiently large to resist disintegration during common  laboratory pretreatments.  Since m volcanic softs various types of composite particles may be found,  ranging from actual rock fragments to aggregates the discrete components  of whmh are held together by unlike charges only, their characteristms  were studied more closely.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevmr Science Publishers B V.    196    Examination of grain mounts and thin secttons of different size frac-  tions showed one partmular type to be dominant. This type could not be  classed among rock fragments (fresh or altered) nor among glassy frag-  ments containing phenocrysts.  When mechanical forces are apphed, they are rather easily reduced,  although the Impression has been gamed that there is a variation in firm-  ness. Ultrasomc treatment during 30 rain of a 32--50 pm size fraction,  e.g., showed a rather low susceptlblhty of the particles to disintegration.  After sieving over a 32 pm stove, the treated material lost about half of  Its weight only.  Additional microscopm investlgatmn of undisturbed lumps from these  softs often suggested that pulverismg actions as carried out during the labo-  ratory pretreatment would easily result in a high number of individual  composite particles of different size and shape. If these composite particles  can originate m this way, it also means that they must be a rather usual  constituent of natural soil erosion products.  In discussing the genesis of Indonesmn volcamc soils at altitudes above  1300 m, Mohr and Van Baren (1954) already mentmned probably this kind  of composite partmles. They denominated the mechanism producing them  "mountain granulation" and the products formed "pseudo sands".  Present-day geomorphological research is often focussed on the unravel-  ment of the various erosmnal processes. Hence it was decided to investigate  their propertms in one single soft profile, to find out whether this knowledge  might be of use to increase our judgement in landscape dynamics.    EXPERIMENTAL    Stte and general setting of the profzle    The profile is situated about 6 km east of the village of Guasca (Fig. 1)  along the road to Sueva on a westward facing slope at an elevation of  2805 m (T. van der Hammen, oral commumcation, 1981}, Van der Hammen  collected the profile in brass containers and made it available for investiga-  tion. Jungerius denominated the soil horizons (see Fig. 12).  According to Botero (1972} soils occurring m this area must be classified  as Andic Humitropepts and Andlc Cryumbrepts. The profile developed  m the Qal umt (Anonymous, 1969) belonging to the Sabana Formation of  middle and late Quaternary age. The Qal unit is described as a fine-grained  fluvlo-lacustrine deposit with glacially derived detrital material. Field evi-  dence, however, shows that the deposit is covered by or highly mixed with  volcanm ashes. As a result soil profiles have been developed in pure tephra  or m a mixture of ashes and non-volcanic material.  From numerous studies (Van der Hammen et al., 1973; Van Geel and  Van der Hammen, 1973; Correal and Van der Hammen, 1977; Van der  Hammen, 1978; Duefias-J., 1977) it has become clear that deposition of    197    TOLIMA  /  i    I  I  x                -                 -run,a_ J  , /  /  \~ J                     BOYACA  ~            ",  CUNDINAMARCA  (        N  m~Bogota  /   /  f-  /  "        META  !  /                                   o  200 40Okra     II  -%    Fig. 1 Map showing the location (+) of the Guasca soil profile.    volcanic ashes on the Sabana de Bogot~ has been a frequently repeated  event. The investigation of a core from the Laguna de Fuquene area just  north of the Sabana de Bogota showed that depomtion must have occurred  at least fifteen times during the last 45,000 years (Riezebos, 1978). This  study also indicates that these tephra are crystal-vitric ashes with glass con-  tents varying between 25 and 60 grain percentages in the 50-75 #m frac-  tions. On the basis of the mineralogical composition two "types" could  be distinguished. The first type contains mainly micas and amphiboles as  heavy minerals, while the bulk of the heavy minerals in the second one  consists of amphiboles and pyroxenes. The latter type of ashes has probably  been deposited after ca. 20,000 yr BP.  Two wet and two dry seasons with an annual rainfall varying between  700 and 900 mm can be distinguished in the Guasca Valley. The annual  precipitation in the Eastern Cordilleras, east of the Guasca Valley, varies  between 1800 and 2200 mm and seems to be concentrated in the period  May--August (Botero, 1972). Hence the amount and distribution of precipi-  tation on the soil profile must have been highly influenced by the altitude  and aspect of its topographic position. The mean annual temperature at  the soil location must be 11--12, calculated according to Van der Hammen  (1963).    Treatment of the sampled material    From eight levels of the profile (0--5, 25--30, 50--56, 94--100, 144--  150, 190-195, 207--215 and 243--250 cm depth) material was sampled.    198    Usually the preliminary treatment is directed on the disintegration of the  material and the removal of particle coatings, organic and colloidal mate-  hal, m order to obtain an accurate size distribution of the primary particles.  As this study mainly focusses on the composite partmles, the common  treatment with acid or alkaline digestion was omitted. After being suspended  m deminerahzed water, the soil material was pulverised by gentle rubbing.  Only a H202 (30%) treatment was applied in order to remove as much as  posmble the organic matter_ The peroxide treatment, however, was stopped  after 60 h, because the suspensmns remained active.  After washing and drying the material was separated in different particle  size fractmns by sieving (&gt; 32 #m). Subsequently the heavy minerals m  the size fractions 50--75, 75--105, 105--150 and 150--210 pm were sep-  arated by using bromoform (s.g. 2.89) and their weight percentages deter-  mined. The remaining "hght" mineral fractions were used for the study of  the composite particles.  From several other depths (11--12, 46--47, 82--87, 134--136, 154--156,  195--200, 220--222 and 238--241 cm), undisturbed soil fragments for the  preparation of thin sections were taken, in order to examine the soft fabric.    Me th o ds    In addition to the petrologmal microscope, a SEM (Mark II Cambridge  Instruments) was used for the morphological study of the composite  particles. Individual specimens collected by handpicking using a binocular  magnifier (Bausch and Lomb) were mounted on an aluminum stub with  aluminum paint, and subsequently sputter-coated with gold m a vacuum  evaporator under continuous rotation of the sample holders. For the exami-  nation of the fabric of the composite particles a SEM (type JSM-35C) was  applied after embedding m an artifmial resin, sectioning, pohshing and coat-  ing specimens collected by handpicking.  Because of the intimately associated constituents in the composite  particles and our incompetence to separate them properly, aqueous suspen-  sions of sand fractions (mineral/distilled water ratio -~ 1:40) were subjected  for 1.5 h to ultrasonic vibration (Engisomc 50 Kc). During vibration water  temperature increased to ca. 35. After homogemzatlon of the suspension  and the required waiting time (Stoke's formula), drops of the suspenmon  containing clay-sized  particles of 1 ~m and smaller were placed on the  aluminum stubs and the water evaporated at 35C. After gold-sputtenng the  samples were also examined using the SEM {Mark II).  The close association of the different constituents also forms a con-  siderable drawback for the assessment of their chemmal characteristics.  Hence for this purpose an m sltu microchemmal analysing techmque (Boeke-  stem et al., 1981) seemed most appropriate. Electron mmroprobe analyses  (Mmroscan 9, Cambridge Instruments) were carried out. Handpicked com-  posite particles were embedded m artifmial resin, sectioned (+ 30 Urn),    TABLE I  Standards used for quantitative electron microprobe analyses    199    Na -- jadeite           S -- barite          Cr -- chrommm oxide  Mg -- olivine           CI -- hahte          Mn -- rhodonite  Al -- corundum        K -- orthoclase      Fe -- hemahte  S1 -- diopslde          Ca -- diopside       Ni -- mckel oxide  P -- apatlte            T1 -- ilmenite    polished and carbon-coated. For quantitative analyses the standards listed  in Table I were used. Percentages were corrected (ZAF-correctlons) by an  on-line computer program provided by the manufacturer.    RESULTS    Morphology and fabric of the composite particles    The particles show in general a subangular to rounded shape (Fig. 2).  At higher magnifications, however, their outhnes are often very irregular,  showing sometimes a frayed appearance. This is evidently more clear in  thin sections than in grain mounts (Fig. 3). The irregularity of the particle  edges is occasionally effected by protruding inclusions, but the scanning    Fig. 2. Photommrograph of the light-mineral fraction (105--150 #m) from level V of  the Guasca soil profile (see Fig. 11).    200    ~   i ~i~i~~    201    electron micrographs (Figs. 3 and 4) testify, that crevmes and cavities start-  ing at the particle surface contribute more substantially to the irregular  surface.  Angular specimens have been observed, but mainly in level I (0--5 cm  depth) where they were largely outnumbered, however, by subangular and  rounded particles. The surface irregularity of the rounded particles mostly  leads, especially under low magmfications, to mammillated shapes. Only  once, a local coating with a plain gel-like material has been notmed.  Especially the thin sections show the composite particles to be made  of optically isotropic and anisotropic materials. Only the angular specimens  mainly found in level I appeared mostly to consist of isotropic material  only (Fig. 3). So actually the denomination "composite" particle is not  completely justifmd. As the latter are far in the minority the use of the  adjective will be continued. Moreover, X-ray powder analysis performed  on the clay fraction of a number of angular composite particles, collected  by handpmking and subsequently crushed, yielded an X-ray pattern with  clear lines of quartz and cristobalite. Further, very weak 14 and 7 A reflec-  tions were recorded.  As is illustrated m the micrographs of Figs. 3 and 4 the lsotropic com-  ponent envelopes and cements particles of different size, shape and nature.  Their number may vary per composite particle. Idlomorphic shapes are  not uncommon.  The frequent occurrence of biohtes or opal phytolites among the Included  partmles supports the suggestion that the inclusions have been incorporated  by the isotropic constituent. Fretted outlines of optically anisotropm and  isotropic (glass, biolites) inclusions may be interpreted as a sign that these  components are still being dissolved.  The included crystalline constituents represent in general quartz, feld-  spars, amphiboles, iron oxide, pyroxenes etc. Among the smallest ones  (&lt; 8 ~m) phyllosilicates seem to dominate. From a genetical point of view,  the amorphous, yellow to dark-brown coloured material, by which the  other constituents are cemented, seems to be the most interesting com-  ponent.  The composite particles dominate the light-mineral spectra in the m-  vestlgated levels; only in level II and III, corresponding with the B2 and BC  horizons, their abundance is considerably lowered (see Fig. 12).    Thin-section analysis of associated sod lumps    A careful inspection of the thin sections showed that cutan formation  nor plasma separations could be detected at the sampled depths. At the    Fig. 3. Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) of sectioned and polished com-  posite particles (SEM:JSM-35C). The second one represents an inclusion-free angular  specimen from level I of the soil profile (see Fig. 11). Magmfication: 525.    202          ~ ii~     203    depths above 156 cm, however, small-sized areas could be distinguished  deviating from the adjacent S-matrix by colour and/or rather clear bound-  arms (Fig. 5).  As these areas sometimes exhibit straight and angular boundarms, fail  to show a close relationship with channels and jomts, have a colour and  internal matrix differing from the surrounding S-matrix and have highly  variable dimensions, it is hardly possible to interpret them as pedological  features (pedotubules, fecal pellets, glaebules, nodules).    Fig. 5 Photommrographs showing the fabric at depth of 134--136 cm (upper) and of  195--200 cm (lower) of the soil profile Magmfmation 8    Fig 4. Oblique (tilt of the sample holder 45 scanning electron mlcrographs of com-  poslte particles (SEM- Mark II Cambridge Instruments)    204    0  "6    X~XX    =L =1. =:1.  aO c~1 aO  co    0  0    0  d  o    D  D  ~d  Z  D  Z  0  0  0  0  o  o    odoo6    I =11 I  I    oo ~66o   o66o  I         I    oo666  Ioolo  I ~11 I  0    L~  ~Sdo    lO ~"3  66o  dlo  cSod  LO  ~1 'r'-'l ~1  LO  0  LO    XXXXXXXX     XXX     XXX    205    66666666   o66   o66    o6o6o666   666   666  I I =1 =f d~   I I ~   611    ~ddd~d6~   ooo    I o d  dgddd~g~   b~e   ~b    T-i    oO    c~    206    Below the depth of 156 cm, these partmular areas were lacking m the  thin sections. So, they hkely represent pedorehcs, incorporated in the  matrix of the present soil. Another difference Is that above 156 cm the  fabric units are m general more rounded while below this depth they are  more angular.    Chemical features of the amorphous component    From the 210--300 pm size fractions a number of composite partmles  was sampled randomly and used for electron probe micro-analyses of the  amorphous component The results and the calculated SIO2/A1203 molar  ratios are presented m Table II.  The results mdmate a considerable difference between the investigated  levels. Levels I and IV, e.g., display a wide range in the measured abundances  of several elements (P~Os, A1203, FeO and SiO2) while the measured range  of these elements m other levels, e.g. II and VII, is much more hmlted.  A conspmuous anomaly is shown by the high N1 content m level II  This relatively high amount of mckel could not be related to any specific  inclusion. Commonly such abundances are found in the weathering products    /i  (61    I  1311  (4)    (5) ~   F    {3)    (8)  I  I  ~.7I]I  (3)  I    .  O~    07    08    (~q     lt~     11     12     13     14     1'~     ]t~     17     l~q     lq     20  SlO,_  m,~lar ral,~  AI-O  Fig. 6. SiO~IAI20~ molar ratios against depth Data are from Table II Black dots indicate  average values and bars standard devlatmns_    207    of mafic to ultramafic rocks which, however, are unknown in this part of  Colombia.  Another notable phenomenon are the relatively high P2Os concentra-  tions in the amorphous component of the measured particles from levels  VI and I. The measured values of CaO, Na20 and C1 do not vary very much.  Fig. 6 g]ves the arithmic averages and standard deviations of the SiO2/  A1203 molar ratios as a function of depth. Figs. 7, 8 and 9 present the values  of some measured elements m various plots. They illustrate in several  respects the differences between the levels. The SIO2/A1203 molar ratio,  whmh varies between 0.49 and 2.08, shows in particular that the amorphous  cementmg constituent of the composite partmles from the levels VIII, VII    SIO2  %  36  35  34  33  32 F    %NI  (3)                                            I  {8}  5~    29~  28-  27  26  25  24  23  22  21  20  19  18  17  16  ]5~  13  12  2~    2'8  29  30  31  3~Z  3'3  3~4  3'5  36  3'/  3a  3'9  40  4~1  42  43  44.  45  46  4tZ  48  49  5~3  5'l%Al:~O~    Fig. 7. S102 vs  AI203 plot. Data are from Table II. Mean values are indicated by black  dots, standard deviations by bars. Roman numerals represent the investigated level,  number between brackets the number of analyses    208    ll(')  r  'l  I    1~,~   in,  1,,L  I    T    --     }4             I(~)    I          i  /,L,,  .....    ii    T  (&gt;)    T  k    I  l       L  ~7  ....        L  ~,    ,h    1'7 % Mq(    Fig. 8 Plot of TnO2 vs. MgO (see Fig. 7)    and VI deviates sigmfmantly from that m the remaining ones. Further, that  among these remammg ones, V and IV can be discrimmated from III and II,  which mutually also differ signifmantly.    Morphology of the dispersed amorphous component    Because SEM observations on the surface of composite particles hardly  provided information about whether the amorphous component consisted  of individual units and if so, of what morphology, it has been assumed that  this information might be found by examination of the finest (&lt; 1 ~m)  products obtained by ultrasonic vibration of sand-sized composite particles.  The micrographs (Fig. 10) show that discrete particles seem to be discern-  able and also that their majority has a spherical shape. Clustering of these  spherules can be observed, with themselves and with differently shaped  partmles. The dimensions of apparently indwidual spherules seem to vary  between ca. 400 and 1000 A. In view of their abundance, it seems likely  that these spherules represent the dispersion products of the amorphous  cement.    209    ~205  %  20  ]9  18  17  16  ]5  14  13  12  11  10  09  08  07  (34  0 3  O2    (3)  0     L    i              I    I    I1    i    i  5     6      7     8      9     10    1      12     13  Fig. 9. Plot of P205 vs. FeO (see Fig. 7).    t  ]]E  I5)    4    i     i    i     i    i    I0    /    i     i    213  14    15    16    17    18    19    2     21    22        % FeO    Compositions of the assoczated heavy- and light-mineral fractions    For the sake of completeness the mineral compositions of the heavy  and light concentrates of the samples from whmh the composite particles  have been studied, were established using the petrological microscope.  These results are summarized in Fig. 11 together with the weight per-  centages of the heavy concentrates. Only the mineral spectra of the 105--  150 #m size fraction are presented, as the other sand-sized fractions show  almost similar ratios in their spectra.    210    Fig 10 Oblique (tilt 45 scanning electron photomicrographs (SEM Mark II Cambridge  Instruments) of the &lt; 1 ~m fraction obtained by ultrasomc treatment In the upper  part of the lower mmrograph (use magnifying glass) many spheres show a regular ar-  rangement of dagger-shaped protuberances    211    ~= ~   NO ~-~       compos,tlon ) 105 - 150~m size range)  ~ --                              ~     legend                   ,i,/ Ii/, i- 7  ,o A~I    ~:z!::=-:=-:=-:=-:=-:z~/2 ~ ,,,,,?//, ,  : ,  ," '  _  ~~                                                                   amphiboles  20  ....  :  30 B2      vY.%'.'z-'~-~"~Y,'-'.                     - -   ortho   .....  ",',.,zZ,~..~ ~  .                 E      pyroKenes  4O                                   ___  50   41111                               -~"  = ~resl group  70 ,J  -  aoi  I  9o       ,                           --  ~oo   1'v                          --  - ]  110  120   C                                                                   _~ ---   felspars  =   -  13(]  =  140                                                    volcanic  15o    I V                               ="  E ~ glass  160                                              m ~,  composite  170  180   rest group  lvl  210 A :IVII                           ] ~  23Q  240  C  ;2s   Iv'" "22~- U  .....  !  ;    :o   -4'0    6;    ~7,    ~,~o ,,    we,ghl % of heavy mineral separates  4    i f  ,'     i  /  "X  /    legend  ,'      -- ,n 210-150 ,,m  /'       --  ,n 150 - 105 .m     3 4 5       TO       I~  Fig. 11 Summary of various petrographic propertms as a function of soil depth.    20 ~    A discrimlnat,on of the sampled levels on the basis of the heavy-mineral  composition ,s not possible. The change shown by the light-mineral com-  positions m level II and III coincides with a cons,derable increase of the  heavy-mineral weight percentages.    DISCUSSION    Composite particle characteristics    The present observations support the initial supposition that they must  be considered as artificially produced fragments of the three-dimensionally  connected matrix of the present soft. Subrounded to rounded shapes ob-  served may be co-produced by the peroxide treatment.  Theoretically, however, two "types" of composite particles might be  expected to occur in the size fractions obtained from that part of the profile    212    above a depth of 156 cm: one representing the pedorehcs recogmzed in  the thm sections of the soil lumps, and another representing fresh fragments  However, due to the very heterogeneous nature of the composite particles,  no rehable criteria for distraction in grain mounts could be defined.  The angular, optically inclusion-free specimens as found m level I (see  Fig. 3), are probably artifmlally produced cutan fragments. In thin sections  they exhibit occasionally hght and dark banding. Spot analysis of these  differently coloured bands m one single partmle showed the dark band to  contain more FeO and S102 and less A1203 than the hghter coloured band.  A similar correlation m chemmal composition and colour depth is apparent  when partmles with a dark brown cement are compared with specimens  having a yellowish brown cement  Position and function of the amorphous component m the individual  composite partmles strongly suggest that their existence is exclusively due  to this particular constituent Hence, from a genetmal point of vmw this  component seems to be the most mtrigumg one  The continuous reactivity of composite particles with H:O2 as observed  under the microscope testifies that humm substances must form part of the  amorphous cement. Very probably these substances have also played a role  m its genesis  Because techmcal facilities to establish their nature and  amount m surface areas of a few microns were not available, their possible  contnbutmn cannot be discussed.  The first solid phase, originating by precipitation from weathering solu-  tions of primary volcanic minerals and the associated glass, is generally  named allophane. This name is used to describe naturally occurring hydrous  alummosihcates ranging rather widely in composition  For its chemical  characterization usually the SiO2/A12Oa molar ratm is apphed.  Table II shows that these ratios observed m the lsotropm cement vary  between 0.49 and 2 08. These values seem to be m agreement with those  reported in literature for allophane-hke materials of clay sizes (Henml and  Wada, 1976)  The questmn arises, however, whether comparison is com-  pletely justified. The latter ratios often have been determined in solutions  containing the dissolved components from clays treated by  dlthionite-  citrate (Mehra and Jackson, 1960), and by Na2CO3 (Wada and Greenland,  1970), and even m solutions containing completely dissolved clays (Henml  and Wada, 1976).  With exception of mckel, and perhaps sulphur and chlorine, the remain-  mg elements (Table II) have frequently been reported as constituents of  allophanes and allophane-hke materials (see e.g. Hamblin and Greenland,  1972). The phosphate adsorptmn capacity of allophane is rather well-  documented (see, e.g., Taylor and Wilson, 1979; Parfitt and Henmi, 1980).  Work done dunng the last decade reveals that allophane consists of  morphologmally similar particles (Kitagawa, 1971; Wada et al., 1972; Henml  and Wada, 1976; Wada and Wada, 1977; Shoji and Smgusa, 1977; Parfitt  and Henmi, 1980, etc.) These particles appear as rings m hlgh-resolutmn    213    electron mmrographs and are three&lt;limensionally interpreted as hollow  spherules with outside diameters of 35--50 h.  The SEM observations (Fig. 10) show that the &lt; 1/~m particles separated  by ultrasonic vibration from sand-sized composite particles also have pre-  dominantly a sphermal shape, but the dimensions are considerably larger,  approximately varying between 400 and 1000 A. De Vilhers and Jackson  (1967) and Cloos et al. {1968, 1969) proposed a structural model of allo-  phane with alumlnosilicate cores of 50 A, being covered with a complex  form of hydroxy--aluminon cations. These coverings are thought to play  an Important role in the phosphate adsorption process. In vmw of the  ability of allophane to adsorb acid organic material of high molecular weight  from aqueous solutions (Taylor and Wilson, 1979) it is thinkable that this,  to a certain degree, might result in larger dimensions of the spherules. Some  of the individual clusters illustrate conwncingly (see arrows m Fig. 10)  the mmromorphological model of allophane micro-aggregates proposed by  Kltagawa (1971), only the composing spherules are much greater.  In summary, the data suggest that the amorphous cementing component  of the composite particles is of allophane nature. Probably it originated  from interstitial waters in surflclal layers with dissolving volcamc glass and  minerals. Indications pointing to separate phases in this segragation could  optically not be recognized. Composition and nature of the parent glass  fragments In particular (Klrkman and McHardy, 1980), but also relative  proportions of glass and crystalline phases have undoubtedly been important  controls in the cement formation. However, in view of the variations In  single-element abundances, even in the restricted mmro-envlronment of  one level, the precipitation seems hardly to have followed a rigid scheme.    A bundance--depth relationships    Fig. 11 shows that, in terms of light-mineral compositions and in terms  of weight percentages of the heavy minerals, the Guasca profile exhibits  an evident zonal development. The presence and absence of pedorelics  above and below the depth of 156 cm, also pomt to such a development.  Combining these data the following sedimentary history of the Guasca  profile may be framed. A soil developed in volcanic ash (Fig. 11, level VIII  and VII) has been covered by material also of volcanic origin. Initially this  material came from close by (level VI), but later on, it arrived from other  sources, or sources at greater distance because of the presence of "exotic"  micropeds above a depth of 156 cm. These soil-derived rehcs have substan-  tially contributed to this covering (level V and IV). In the further course  of this accumulation another change in material occurred, indicated by an  increase of the associated heavy-mineral weight percentages, and m the  light-mineral fraction by an increase of quartz next to the appearance of  minor amounts of volcanic glass (levels III and II). It might be possible  that this change has been intensified by contemporaneous or subsequent    214    differentiation at the depositlonal surface. The final stage of accumulation  is  characterized  by  a  decrease  of quartz  and heavy-mineral  weight  percentages {level I) and probably represents the present "in transit" sur-  face layer.  It is surprising that this fourfold zonatlon {levels VIII, VII and VI, levels  V and IV, levels III and II, and level I), running more or less concurrently  with some soil-horizon boundaries, is confirmed by the chemical features  of the allophanic cement in associated composite particles Certain element  abundances allow to recogmze this zonatlon even in greater detail.  Fig. 6 illustrates that the third zone e.g. can be subdivided using the  SIO2/A1203 molar ratio. Corroborative evidence for this are the observed  N1 abundances m level II {Table II). The plot of Fig. 7 illustrates the great  lack of affinity in terms of silica between the first {levels VIII, VII and VI)  and second zone {levels V and IV), suggesting that the allophanic constituent  precipitated from different solutions or under completely different condi-  tions.  Also the vertical variability of some minor-element abundances supports  the phenomenon of a zonal arrangement. The average Mg content in level  VIII is significantly lower than that in levels VII and VI (Fig. 8). This  plot also shows that the average T1 abundance m level V is much higher  than In level IV. Conspicuous are the high phosphorus abundances recorded  in levels VI and I (Fig. 9).  Of vital importance, however, is the question whether the chemical  stratification shown by the allophanic constituent of the composite particles  at different depths, results from micro-environmental conditions govern-  ing at the various depths of the present soil column, or whether it is a  reflection of the differences m material supplied.  As signs for cement segregation in distinctly different phases could not be  detected, its formation from evaporating interstitial water by co-precipita-  tion of silica and alumina creating S1--O--A1 hnkages, has to be considered  as a continual process occurring as long as moisture is periodmally supplied  and easily weatherable mineral phases are available. In this view, the wide  ranges of some element abundances (A1, S1, Fe, Mg, P and TI) found at  certain levels (see Table II and Figs. 7, 8 and 9) could be accounted for  by variations in controlling conditions at a microscale resulting, within  one level, in chemically varying cement compositions.  But the significantly different averages of element contents between  the levels cannot so easily be explained. Neither can be ignored the agree-  ment in zonal arrangement between the petrographic characteristics and the  allophanic cement chemistry of the composite particles.  Hence, it seems that the vertmal changes In cement chemistry of the  composite partmles measured, in the first place are related to the petro-  graphical propertms of the associated parent material. But undoubtedly  they also reflect the influence of depth-dependent precipitation in the  soil column, as is demonstrated by phosphorus (Fig. 9).    215    Without a systematic m situ microchemical analysis of the isotropic  component m optically manifest pedorelics and m the adjacent S-matrix  areas, it will not be possible to distinguish between the effects of these  two contributing factors.    CONCLUDING REMARKS    The composite particles found in sand-sized fractions isolated from  Colombian andosol material, constitute another illustration of the fact  that dispersion of volcamc sod material and peptizatlon of the associated  clay might be a difficult process to effect m the laboratory. Hence grain-  size distributions of such materials could be rather unrehable.  The persistency of the origmal fabrm must also have consequences under  natural conditions. Andosols on the Sabana de Bogot~ have a low bulk  density and consist in general for a great deal of water-stable peds bemg  individual natural sod aggregates (Soil Survey Staff, 1951). When their  parent materials are continuously moist, they form heavy, smeary clays.  Upon drying, however, these peds originate which do not rehydrate easily.  As a result these soils have a large storage capacity, whmh is probably the  reason that they can form a protective cover m the landscape.  When these soils are destroyed by erosional processes, these peds and  their fragments will initially constitute the erosional products. But in course  of time, progressive diminution during transport along the land surface  will produce finally sand- and silt-sized aggregates resembling composite  particles. At a certain moment these units may even form the bulk of the  erosional products.  Soil development in aggradatlonal sites of such landscapes may conse-  quently take place in parent materials rich in composite particles being  actually fragments of previous soils. The upper part of the Guasca profile  apparently demonstrates such a situation.  It is obvious that chemical parameters obtained by wet chemical analysis  of bulk samples from the different horizons of such softs will be of little  use for a better understandmg of the pedogenetic and weathering processes  in a particular site or area, nor will contribute significantly to the develop-  ment of theories. This applies in particular when the composite particles  arrived from several distant places, e.g. by aeolian transport.  The work done on the Guasca profile illustrates that the only way to  collect relevant information in order to attack such problems successfully  is a.o. a thorough mmroscopic fabric analysis followed by the use of a sub-  microscopic technique for mmrochemical analysis (Bisdom, 1981).    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Financial support was supphed by the Netherlands Foundation for the  Advancement of Tropical Research (WOTRO). Scanning electron microscope    216    facllitms were provided by the Workmg Group SEM, University of Amster-  dam and by TFDL, Department EM, Wageningen  Electron microprobe  facilitms were provided by the Free University, Amsterdam, and the  WACOM, a working group for analytmal geochemistry subsidized by the  Netherlands Organization for the Advancement of Pure Research (ZWO).  The authors thank the following persons who assisted with the prepara-  tmn of the manuscript: Mrs. O.M. Bergmeijer-de Vrd, Mrs. M C.G. Keljzer-  v.d. Lubbe and Mr. C. van der Bliek.    REFERENCES    Anonymous, 1969. Geologmal Map of Colombia, Sheet K-11, Zlpaqulra Instltuto Naclo-  nal de Investlgaciones Geologmo-Mineras  BLsdom, E B.A., 1981. A revmw of the application of submmroscoplc techniques in soil  mlcromorphology, I and II. In: E.B.A. Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and  Weathered Rocks. Pudoc, Wagenmgen, pp 67--162  Boekesteln, A., Henstra, S. and Bisdom, E.B A., 1981. Submicroscopic techniques for in  situ mlcrochemical analysm of soils, I_ Non-destructive techniques 1 In E.B.A_ Bis-  dora (Editor), Submlcroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks Pudoc, Wageningen,  pp. 29--44  Botero, P J_, 1972  Soils of Guasca-Guatavita (Colombia). Unpublished MSc thesls,  Institute for Aerial Survey and Earth Scmnces, Enschede  Cloos, P., Herblllon, A. and Echeverria, J., 1968. Allophane-hke synthetic sihco-alummas  Phosphate adsorptlon and avallabdity. Trans. 9th Intern Congr Soil Sci, II  733--  743.  Cloos, P , L~onard, A J., Moreau, J.P., Herblllon, A  and Fripiat, J J., 1969 Structural  organization in amorphous sthco-aluminas Clays Clay Miner., 17 279--287.  Correal Urrego, G and Van der Hammen, T, 1977 Investigaclones Arqueologlcas en los  Abngos rocosos dei Tequendama Bibliotheca Banco Popular  De Villiers, J.M and Jackson, M.L., 1967 Cation exchange capacity variations with pH  in soil clays. Soft Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31 473--476  Duefias-J , H , 1977. Estudlo palinologico de los 35 rots superlores de la seccion Tar-  ragona, Sabana de Bogota. Caldasia, 12' 539--571.  Hambhn, A.P. and Greenland, D.J , 1972. Mineralogy of soils from the Holocene volcanic  areas of southern Australia. Aust J. Soil Res., I0' 61--79.  Henmi, T and Wada, K., 1976. Morphology and composition of allophane Am Mineral ,  61 379--39O.  Kirkman, J H  and McHardy, W.J., 1980  A comparatlve study of the morphology,  chemical composltlon and weathering of rhyolitic and andesitic glass Clay Miner,  15 165--173.  Kitagawa, Y., 1971 The "umt-paxticle" of allophane Am Miner, 56 465--475  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L_, 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a  dithlonlte-citrate system with sodium bicarbonate buffer. Clays Clay Miner, 7: 307--  327  Mohr, E.C.T. and Van Baren, 1954. Tropical Softs. Van Hoeve, The Hague, Bandung --  Interscience Publishers, London, New York, 498 pp.  Parfltt, R L  and Henmi, T., 1980. Structure of some allophanes from New Zealand  Clays Clay Miner , 28 285--294  Riezebos, P A , 1978 Petrographic aspects of a sequence of Quaternary volcanm ashes  from the Laguna de Fuquene area, Colombia, and their stratIgraphIc significance.  Quaternary Res., 10 401--424.    217    Shoji, S. and Salgusa, M., 1977  Amorphous clay materials m Towada Ando soil Soil  Sci Plant Nutr., 23. 437--455  Soil Survey Staff, 1951  Soil Survey Manual Handbook 18. U.S. Dept of Agrmulture,  Wash, D C., 503 pp.  Taylor, D.H and Wilson, A.T., 1979. The adsorption of yeast RNA by allophane. Clays  Clay Miner., 27. 261--268  Van Geel, B and Van der Hammen, T, 1973 Upper Quaternary vegetational and chmatic  sequence of the Fuquene area (Eastern Cordillera, Colombia). Palaeogeogr , Palaeo-  climatol, Palaeoecol, 14.9--92  Van der Hammen, T, 1963. Hlstoria de china y vegetac16n del Pleistoceno superior y  del Holoceno de la Sabana de Bogota_ Bol. Geol, 11. 189--226.  Van der Hammen, T., 1978  Stratigraphy and environments of the Upper Quaternary  of the E1 Abra corridor and rock shelters (Colombia) Palaeogeogr., Palaeoclimatol ,  Palaeoecol., 25 111--162_  Van der Hammen, T, Werner, J.H. and Van Dommelen, H., 1973. Palynologmal record  of the upheaval of the Northern Andes a study of the Phocene and lower Quaternary  of the Colombian Eastern Cordillera and the early evolution of its high-andean biota  Res Palaeobot Palynol , 16: 1--22.  Wada, K. and Greenland, D J, 1970  Selective dissolution and differential infrared  spectroscopy for characterization of "amorphous" constituents in soil clays. Clay  Miner, 8 241--254  Wada, S  and Wada, K., 1977  Density and structure of allophane Clay Miner , 12  289--298.  Wada, K., Henml, T, Yo~hinaga, N. and Patterson, S.H., 1972 Imogohte and allophane  formed in saprolite of basalt on Maul, Hawaii Clays Clay Miner., 20- 375--380.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                AbstractComposite particles, frequently observed in sand and coarse silt from laboratory-treated andosol materials, have been collected at eight levels in an andosol profile near Guasca (Colombia) and studied by microscopic, SEM and electron microprobe techniques. The particles appear to be made up of a varying number of fine sand- to claysized grains of various shape and nature, cemented together by an optically isotropic material of allophanic composition. Plots of the chemical parameters of this cement against depth reveal a zonal arrangement of major and minor elements. A stratified arrangement is also shown by petrographic features of the light- and heavy-mineral fractions of the associated sample material, and by the fabric of small undisturbed lumps from depths between the eight levels.The composite particles are obviously the product of allophane-generating sites in surficial layers containing unstable solids as volcanic glass and minerals. Although in this study the particles have been investigated in the form of artificial fragments, more or less similar ones will originate under natural conditions. It is argued that their occurrence as sand- and silt-sized individuals in natural erosion products, and thus also in aggradational soils, must drastically affect chemical soil parameters, when obtained by wet chemical analysis of bulk samples. 