 Geoderma, 25 (1981) 63--74  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    63    EVALUATION OF CRITERIA FOR ARGILLIC HORIZONS (Bt) OF  SOILS IN CANADA*    J.A. McKEAGUE, C. WANG, G.J. ROSS, C.J. ACTON, R.E. SMITH, D.W. ANDERSON,  W.W. PETTAPIECE and T.M. LORD  Land Resource Research Institute, Central Experimental Farm, Ottawa (Canada)  (Received January 30, 1980; accepted April 4, 1980)    ABSTRACT    McKeague, J.A.~ Wang, C., Ross, G.J., Aeton, C.J., Smith, P~.W., Anderson, D.W.,  Pettapiece, W.W. and Lord, T.M., 1981. Evaluation of criteria for argillic horizons  (Bt) of soils in Canada. Geoderma, 25: 63--74.    Studies of 71 pedons in Canada showed that improvements are required in the  estimation of argillic horizon development by both macro- and micro-morphological  methods. Fifty-four of the pedons were considered by pedologists of the area to have  argillic horizons but only 32 of them had at least 1% oriented, illuvial clay as estimated  by point counting of thin sections. A high proportion of the soils thought to have ar-  gillic horizons but that lacked 1% oriented clay were either soils from semi-arid areas  or soils of very high clay content. However, several clayey soils with COLE values  more than 5% had well*developed argillans on ped surfaces and more than 1% oriented,  illuvial clay.  The results indicate that reference pedons and reference thin sections would be use-  ful in improving the uniformity of designation of horizons as argillie. Useful estimates  can be made of illuvial clay by rapid scanning of thin sections at a magnification of  approximately 100 if reference sections with established point count values are avail-  able. Current criteria of argillic horizons are adequate except that the 1% oriented clay  criteria should not be applied rigidly and that clay skins probably should be required  in clayey soils of frigid and cryic temperature regimes (cool to very cold temperature  classes in Canada).    INTRODUCTION    The process of clay'eluvia~ion--illuviation is recognized at a high level  in most systems of soil taxonomy. Translocation of clay is considered to  be an important process in pedogene~is; in addition, accessory properLies  of soils with argillic horizons are significant to the understanding of land-  scapes and the use of soils (Soil Survey Staff, 1975). In soil classification  systems of North Ame~ca (Soil Survey Staff, 1975; Canada Soil Survey  Committee, 1978), specific e~.teria are given that are intended to define  objectively the minimum evidence of clay illuviation required for an ~rgillic    *Contribution No. LRRI 57. C.B.R.I. 1221.    NN1 ~-7N~1 IR1 I~NNfl-..~fl(INlgNg..~fl ~ 1 .qgl ~lsp.vier Scientific Publishin~ Comuany    64    horizon. The criteria used in Canada for Bt horizons were adapted from  criteria for the argiUic horizon developed in the United States and differ  in some details. Major criteria of an argillic horizon are:  (1) It contains more clay (&lt; 2 #m) and more fine clay (&lt; 0.2 ~m) by  specified amounts depending on texture, than the overlying eluvial horizon.  (2) It has a minimum thickness of 7.5--15 cm depending on texture and  thickness of overlying horizons.  (3) If structureless, it has oriented clay bridging sand grains and in some  pores (occupying approximately 1% or more of the cross-section).  (4) In the case of pedal argillic horizons, either clay skins occur on some  ped surfaces and in pores, or oriented (apparently illuvial) clay occupies at  least 1% of the cross-section. If the illuvial horizon is clayey (at least 35%  clay) with 2:1 lattice clays resulting in COLE values of 0.04 or more, how-  ever, the clay skin criterion is waived.  Canadian criteria for Bt horizons differ from those listed for argillic  horizons only iri having a different minimum thickness (5 cm) and in main-  raining the clay skin criterion for clayey~ pedal soils (Canada Soil Survey  Committee, 1978).  Though argil]ic horizon criteria have been used since 1960 and modified  only slightly (Soil Survey Staff, 1960, 1975), further testing is required for  several reasons:  (1) It is not certain that application of argillic horizon criteria results  consistently in the identification of horizons that conform J~o the genetic  concept intended (Arnold, 1978).  (2) It is not certain that the criteria can be applied objectively even if  all of the relevant field observations and laboratory tests are made. Little  evidence is available that pedologists can identify clay skins consistently  or that soil micromorphologists can estimate oriented clay in thin section  consistently.  (8) Some horizons lacking oriented, apparently illuvial clay as judged by  study of thin sections, have been classified as axgillic horizons (Bronger,  1978; McKeague et al., 1978).  This study developed from micromorphological investigations of samples  from the International Congress of Soil Science (ICSS) sites in Canada.  The data showed that more than a third of the horizons designated as Bt  horizons had only 0.2% or less of the cross-section occupied by oriented,  apparently flluvial clay (McKeague et al., 1978). It was thought that this  might be due, in part, to the fact that pedologists from various regions did  the sampling and that their standards for judging Bt horizon development  might differ. Also, a number of the horizons designated Bt that lacked  oriented, apparently illuvial, clay were of clayey texture. According to the  United States' criteria, based in part on studies of Nettleton et al. (1969)  and Holzhey et al. (1973), such horizons are argillic if they meet the other  requirements. Clayey Bt horizons in the Canadian system, however, are  expected to have oriented clay on ped surfaces or in pores. There appeared    65    to be a need to test both the consistency of Bt horizon criteria with the  concept of horizons having significant amounts of iUuvial clay and the de-  gree of consistency of application of Bt horizon criteria.  Specific purposes of the study were:  (1) To check the degree of consistency of pedologists in identification  of Bt horizons in the field.  (2) To check the degree of conformity of micromorphological and macro-  morphological estimates of illuvial clay.  (3) To evaluate the evidence of illuvial clay in clayey Bt horizons with  COLE values of 0.04 or more.  (4) To evaluate some microscopic techniques for identifying horizons of  clay illuviation.  (5) To analyze the results with a view to suggesting improvements both  in techniques of identifying illuvial clays and in criteria of Bt horizons.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils    Samples were obtained from a total of 72 pedons (Table I) representing  six orders in the Canadian system (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978).  Of the 72 pedons, 39 were studied in the field by the senior author with  pedologists of the area. The remaining 33 pedons were described and sampled  by pedologists of the area or by regional soil correlators, and samples were  sent to Ottawa for micromorphological study.  Sampling was concentrated in Ontario and western Canada because  previous studies using micromorphology as an aid in evaluating Bt horizon    TABLE I  Distribution and classification of the soils studied    Province(s)      Number of pedons  Brunisolic Chernozemic Gleysolic  Luvisolic  Podzolic   Solonetzic    New Brunswick  and Nova Scotia                                      5  Ontario and  Quebec         1                       4           9  Manitoba                    7           1           7  Saskatchewan                6                       2  Alberta         1          4          1           5  British  Columbia       2          2          1           6  Total         4        19         7        34    1  2    1  2  3    6    66    de~elopment had been done in the Maritime Provinces (McKeague et al.,  1969, 1973}. Selection of sampling sites was designed to include a range  of apparent Bt horizon development, from slight to strong evidence of il-  luvial clay. The majority of the sampling was done south of 50 but most  of the samples from Alberta and some from Manitoba and British Columbia  were taker, between 50 and 55. The samples from Ontario were all from  the Great Lakes--St. Lawrence Lowlands region.    Methods    Field. During sampling, particular attention was given to evidence of clay  illuviation. For 39 of the pedons, the pedologists present made independent  estimates of the degree of expression of clay skins and decided if the B  horizon would satisfy the criteria of a Bt. Oriented samples, in metal boxes  or as clods, were taken for thin section preparation, and bulk samples were  taken of those pedons that had not been sampled previously. For most of  the pedons, clods were taken for s~udy under a stereomicroscope.    Thin sections. Oriented samples were dried and impregnated with a polyester  resin-acetone mixture; duplicate thin sections were prepared as outlined  by Guertin and Bourbeau (1971) for a total of 102 hor~.zons and 4 or more  sections were prepared of three horizons. The proportion of the area of the  section occ~l~ied by oriented, apparently illuvial clay was estimated by three  procedures.  (1) Scanning a section in a few minutes and estimating percent of illuvial  clay using as references sections of which numerous point counts had been  made (McKeague et al., 1980).  (2) Point counting at a magnification of 126x; at least 5000 points even-  ly distributed throughout an area of 2.5 cm2 were counted.  (3) Grid counting (McKeague et al., 1980) of some sections.    Stereomicroscopy. Intact and broken moist peds or clods were examined  at magnifications of 10--30 times under a stereomicroscope. Apparent con-  tinuity and thickness of clay skins were recorded and an estimate was made  of whether the horizon would meet the limits of a Bt horizon.    Other analyses. The particle-size distribution of most samples was measured  in ~:he soil survey laboratory of the province concerned; usually the procedure  involved peroxide treatment, dispersion with sodium hexametaphosphate  and pipette analysis. Shrinkage of some clayey samples was measured by  both the clod method, COLE (Grossman et al., 1968) and the method  with disturbed samples, COLErod (Schafer and Singer, 1976). Surface area  was determined without pretreatment by the method of Heilman et 81.  (1965).    67    RESULTS    For 31 of 39 pedons examined in the field by one or more pedologists  from the area plus McKeague, there was agreement on designation of the B  horizon as either Bt or not Bt (Table II). Consistency of these estimates  was high in British Columbia and Ontario. Independent stereomicroscopic  and field estimates made by McKeague of whether a B horizon would meet  the Bt criteria were generally consistent; they differed for 4 of the 39  pedons. The micromorphological criterion (at least 1% oriented, illuvial  clay), however, indicated fewer Bt horizons than were estimated by the  other methods. Overall, consistent estimates by all methods were made for  only 17 of the 39 pedons.  The degree of consistency of estimates of Bt horizons by different methods  differed according to soil order (Table III). High proportions of the Cher-  nozemic and Solonetzic soils considered by pedologists of the area to have  Bt horizons had much less than 1% of the area of thin sections occupied  by oriented, apparently illuvial clay. More than 2/3 of the soils classified  as Luvisolic, however, had Bt horizons with more than 1% oriented, illuvial  clay. Two soils designated as Luvisolic had less than 1% oriented, illuvial  clay in subhorizons designated Bt but more than 1% in a subhorizon desig-  nated AB; thus a total of 26 of the 34 soils classified as Luvisolic had a  horizon that met the micromorphological criterion of a Bt. Two of the    TABLE II  Consistency of designation of pedons with argillic horizons (Bt) on the basis of field  and laboratory studies of 39 pedons    British       Alberta       Saskatchewan      Ontario  Columbia    Pedons studied          1--9         1--10  Pedons with Bt  as judged by:  Pedologist(s) of area   :~_: 2, 3, 7    1--10    McKeague            1, 2, 3, 7     1, 2, 5, 6  7, 10    Stereomicroscope    1, 2,7,8     1,2,4, 5  6, 7, 9, 10    Rapid scan of thin  sections             1~ 2, 8  Point counting of     3~ 7, 8    Estimate (Bt or not)  uniform by all criteria 4, 5, 6    1, 2, 3, 4  6, 10  1, 2, 4, 6,  7, 10    1, 2, 6, 10    1--8  1,2,3,4,6, 8    2, 4, 6, 8  2, 4, 6, 8  1,2,6,8  1, 2, 6, 8    2, 5, 6, 8    1--12    1, 2, 4, 5,6,  71 8, 9, 11,  12  1, 2, 4, 6, 7  8, 9, 10, 11,  12  1, 2, 4, 6, 7  8, 9, 10, 11  12  1, 3, 4, 6, 7,  8,11  1,4,6,7,8,  11    1,4,6, 7, 8,  11    68    TABLE llI  Number of pedons having Bt horizons as estimated by different techniquesI    Brunisolic   Chernozemic    Gleysolic    Luvisolic    Podz olie Solonetzie    Total pedons            4           19             7           34          2        6  Bt macromorphology2    0           11             5           34          1        5  Bt stereomicroscope      0              6              3            26           1         2  Bt scan of t hln sections  0            5            2          26         1        1  Bt point counting  of thin sections          0             4            8           24          1        1    1 The V2 pedons include the 39 indicated in Table II and 83 not studied in the field by McKeague.  Classification of the soils at the order level in the Canadian system is based on f~eld and laboratory  data excluding micromorphology. 2 Maeromorphologieal estimate of Bt by pedologist(s) of the area.    five Gleysolic soils thought to have Bt horizons lacked the required 1%  oriented, illuvial clay.  Estimates of horizons having at least 1% oriented, illuvial clay by rapid  sc~mning of thin sections were similar to those by point counting (Tables  II and III). Estimates by ~he two methods for 136 sections were highly  correlated (r = 0.92) and the rapid scan estimate {x) was related to the  point count value (Y) as follows: x -- 0.69 Y + 0.15.  For a number of clayey B horizons with blocky or prismatic structure,  illuvial clay as estimated by micromorphology exceeded 1% even though  the COLE values were well above 4% (Table IV). A notable example is the  Waitville B horizon; it had very distinct clay skins and planar void argillans  though the COLE value was 6.4%. For the Moose Mt. Bt horizon, with a  very high COLE value, clay skins were less distinct and different iatiom of  oriented, illuvial elay from oriented, matrix clay was not clear-cut. In sharp  contrast, the Renfrew B horizon with mixed-clay mineralogy, including a  large proportion of finely ground primary minerals, and relatively low  COLE value had distinct, well-oriented argillans sharply differentiated from  the gray, silasepic matrix material. Soils of the prairie provinces with their  generally smectitic clays (Kodama, 1979) generally had higher surface areas  and COLE values relative to clay content than the Ontario and British  Columbia soils studied. COLE values were highly significantly correlated  with surface area (r = 0.93), but not with clay content (r = 0.30).    DISCUSSION    Field estimates of illuoial clay    Observations and discussions in the field showed that in estimating the  degree of clay illuviation in B horizons some groups of pedologist con-  sidered particle~size differentiation from A to B horizon and structure  (blocky or prismatic) to be the criteria of paramount importance. Others,  more concerned with lack of homogeneity of surficial materials, insisted    TABLE IV  Properties of some clayey B horizons designated as Bt in the field    Soil'             Subgroup2    Province   Structure3    Clay %    Clay skins       COLE4    COLEmd  Surface  Bulk density Illuvial  (m2/g)    (g/cm8)   clay %    Renfrew        O.GL        Ont.       m 3 5bk     50      thin continuous    0.031     0.134     148       1.50      5.0  Onondaga       O.GBL       Ont.       m-c 3 5bk    68      thin continuous   (0.055)     0.133     164                  1.8  Brantford       O.GBL       Ont.       m 3 pr       50      discontinuous      0.032     0.014                1.59       0.5  (Lynn L.1)     SZ.GL      Man.                89                    0.074                      1.44     6.0  (Lynn L.2)     O.GL       Man.      c 3 gr       58                       0.043                         1.52      0.2  Peltura          GL.DG       Man.      c 2 gr        51                         0.143     0.173     320       1.77       0.3  Dezwood       O.DG        Man.      f 3 sbk       30                         0.072     0.090                1.72       1.9  Moose Mr.       D.GL         Sask.      f 2-3 sbk     57      thin discontinuous  0.130      0.219      350        1.54       3.1  Waitvflle        O.GL        Sask.      m 2-3 sbk    39      continuous         0.064     0.159     230       1.45       5.5  Moose Mt.      E.BL         Sask.      m 2-3 pr     40      continuous thin    0.078     0.166     253       1.57       1.6  Trossachs       B.SS         Sask.      m-c 3 cpr    38                        0.066     0.162     230       1.61      0.1  Norma          SZ.BL       Alta.      m 3 sbk      32      continuous thin    0.033     0.114     208       1.53       2.0  Camrose        BL.SS        Alta.      m 2-3 cpr    3~      discontinuous      0.060     0.170     217       1.80       2.0  Ponoka         E.BL        Alta.      m 2 sbk      27     thin discontinuous  0.030     0.070     182       1.47      0.5  Cooking Lake   O.LG        Alta.      c 3 abk      36      thirf continuous   ((~.071)     0.159     195       1.59       1.4  Tappen         O.GL        B.C.       f-m 2 sbk    29      thin continuous   (0.00)      0.030     103                  0.1  Langley         O.HG        B.C.       m 1-2 sbk    45      thin discontinuous (0.050)     0.125      192                   1.8    z Series or association name, place names in parentheses; 2 Abbreviations of Canadian subgroups (Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978);  3 Abbreviations of structure terms (Soil Survey Staff, 1951); 4 Values in parentheses are estimated from COLErod by the equation;  COLE ffi -0.024 + 0.595 COLErod (r = 0.89); this equation was obtained from paired COLE and COLErod values obtained for 33  samples in this study,    70    on the presence of clay skins on ped surfaces in addition to an increase of  clay from A to B horizon. Pedologists working witi. weakly structured softs  looked for clay skins associated with vughs and channels. Though the con-  sistency of estimation of Bt horizons in the field by different pedologists  was reasonably good, it could be improved if all used the same criteria.  Both this and previous studies (McKeague et al., 1978; Bronger, 1978)  showed that designation of Bt horizons on the basis of particle-size differ-  entiation alone resulted in the inclusion of horizons lacking clear evidence  of iUuvial clay. Some of these horizons occurred in soils subject to very  little leaching under the present climatic regimes. Thus, relying solely on  particle-size differentiation as a criterion of Bt horizons disregards the  genetic implication intended. Structure is not a generally useful criterion  of Bt horizons; some massive and some weakly structured soils contain  appreciable ~-nounts of oriented, apparently illuvial clay (McKeague et al.,  1969), and =ome strong prismatic or blocky B horizons have no clay skins  and little or no illuvial clay on the basis of micromorphological observations.  Improved consistency of designation of argillic (or Bt) horizons could  be achieved if all pedologists based their estimate on both particle-size and  clay skin criteria. Skill at recognizing clay skins with the aid of a 10-power  lens could probably attain the level of skill at hand texturing. Use of  thoroughly characterized reference pedons and periodic field workshops  would be necessary, however, to achieve uniformity of estimates of the  extent, continuity and thickness of clay skins. Most B horizons contain  some clay skins visible under a lens although clay skins are difficult to  distinguish from diffusion and stress cutans in some soils.    Microscopic techniques for estimating illuvial clay    Examination of peds and clods of B horizons under the stereomicroscope  in the laboratory did not prove to be clearly superior to field observation  for estimating illuvial clay (Table If). The technique does, however, permit  the examination of ped faces and voids under good lighting and probably  the estimation of illuvial clay would improve with experience of the operator,  including checking against benchmark samples.  Though quantitative micromorphological estimates of features indicating  flluvial clay are common in the literature (Sleeman, 1964; Brewer, 1968;  Smeck et al., 1968; Hill, 1970; Miedema and Slager, 1972; Bullock and  Murp'~.y, 1979) and though Holzhey and his co-authors (Holzhey et al., 1973)  made similar estimates, most of the limited evidence available (McKeague  et al., 1978, 1980) shows that estimates by different micromorphologists  are not comparable unless they have worked together to develop common  standards. Both methods of counting illuvial clay and concepts of what  features distinguish illuvial clay from matrix clay probably contribute to  differences of estimates by different operators, but the latter is probably  the major reason for discrepancies (McKeague et al., 1980). For example,    71    point counting yielded estimates approximately double those obtained by  grid counting by the same operator but estimates by ten operators of illuvial  clay ranged from 1.1 to 4.6% for an "easy" section, to 1.7--17.8% for a  "difficult" section (McKeague et al., 1980). Clearly, there is a major element  of subjectivity in quantitative estimates of illuvial clay, and results by in-  dependent operators are not comparable.  In spite of the inconsistency of micromorphological estimates of illuvial  clay and problems associated with differences in amounts of illuvial clay in  replicate sections of the same horizons, it is generally agreed that micro-  morphology is a useful tool for detecting illuvial clay in soils (Brewer  and Sleeman, 1970; Fedoroff, 1973). If oriented clay in thin sections is to  be a useful, quantitative criterion of an argillic horizon, however, major  improvements must be made in the compatibility of estimates by different  operators. The route toward achievement of such improvement is clear.  As in other fields of analysis, such as chemistry, it is necessary to have  reference samples, "round robins" to compare results by different opera-  tors, and perhaps workshops devoted to the standardization of procedures  and concepts.  Illuvial clay may be impossible to estimate in materials with inherited  bodies of oriented clay such as papules or with oriented clay derived from  in-situ weathering of clayey limestone. Reasonably reliable estimates could  probably be achieved, however, for about 3/4 of the soils we have studied.  Difficulties are probably greater in old softs subjected to several cycles of  weathering. The high correlation between results by point counting and  estimates by rapid scanning of a section in relational to reference sections  with measured illuvial clay (Table III) suggests theft point counting of all  samples is not necessary if the major interest is a yes or no decision on 1%  oriented clay.    Evidence of clay illuviation in clayey horizons    Results of this study indicate that the clay skin criterion should not be  waived for some clayey soils with COLE values above 4%. Several horizons  with such properties had clay skins that were visible macromorphologically  and more than 1% oriented, illuvial clay as estimated by micromorphology  (Table IV). This finding is at odds only superficially with the conclusions  of Holzhey et al. (1973). They showed that for argillic horizons of soils  with mesic temperature regimes, large seasonal changes in water content,  2:1 clays and linear extensibilities above 5% (smectite) or 9% (other clays  dominant) clay skins did not usually occur though much of the matrix clay  was oriented. Presumably clay skins were disrupted by frequent cycles of  shrinking and swelling. Only two of the soils they studied had frigid tem-  perature regimes and those differed from the other soils in general relation-  ships among linear extensibility, plasma fabric and presence of clay skins.  Most of the soils in the present study had frigid or cryic temperature    72    regimes (cool to very cold temperature classes in Canada). Further work  may be required to refine argillic horizon criteria so as to take into ac-  count the effects of temperature and moisture regimes on the persistence  of clay skins.    Genetic concepts in relation to Bt horizon criteria    Application of the present criteria of Bt horizons in Canada seems, in  general, to result in the identification of soils in which translocation and  deposition of clay is plausible. Such soils are associated with sub-humid  or wetter climates and materials that are permeable enough to permit  leaching. Results from this and a previous study (McKeague et al., 1978)  indicate that the soils from semi-arid areas where leaching is minimal under  t~  present climate do not have Bt horizons. Further research is necessary,  however, to explain the increase of clay in the B horizon relative to the A  horizon. Approaches used by Chittleborough and Oades (1979) to investi-  gate a related problem in an Australian soil may be useful.    Implications relative to argillic horizon criteria    Until more uniform micromorphological estimates of illuvial clay are  achieved, the 1% oriented, illuvial clay criteria for argillic horizons should  be considered as a guideline oniy. Thus, a B horizon meeting the particle-  size and clay-skin criteria of an argillic horizon should be considered as  such even if an individual micromorphologist estimates an average of 0.5%  illuvial clay after counting several sections. If the estimate is only 0.1--0.2%,  however, the designation is questionable. It is noteworthy that in a previous  study of 64 horizon samples, only 2 had between 0.2 and 0.5% illuvial clay  as estimated by micromorphology and 21 of the 41 samples with less than  1% illuvial clay had 0.1% or less (McKeague et al., 1978). In this study of  the 102 horizons for which thin sections were made, estimates of illuvial  clay were 1% or more in 45 and 0.2% or less in 34. The point is that in  approximately 3/4 of the samples, thin sections showed either very little  illuvial clay or adequate illuvial clay to meet this argillic horizon criterion.  Highly precise counts of illuvial clay are not essential to aid in identifying  most argiUic horizons but the uniformity of estimates by different operators  is inadequate at present.    C ONCLUSIONS    Results of this study are interpreted as indicating that standardization  of techniques for evaluating B horizon properties are essential to the uni-  form application of Bt horizon criteria. Both identification of clay skins  in the field and estimation of illuvial clay in thin section require standardi-  zation. Reference pedons and samples of these pedons for reference thin    73    sections are required. If accepted values could be achieved for illuvial clay  in reference sections, micromorphologists could learn to make adequate  estimates of illuvial clay by rapid scanning of thin sections after checking  their estimates against established values for the reference sections.  The present criteria for the Bt horizon in the Canadian system (Canada  Soil Survey Committee, 1978} are adequate except that the 1% oriented-  clay criterion should be used as a guideline only until a greater degree of  uniformity is achieved in the estimation of illuvial clay in thin section.  Current evidence suggests that the clay-skin criterion for clayey argillic  horizons should be maintained for soils of frigid and cryic temperature  regimes.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We thank W. Michalyna, G.F. Mills, H. Veldhuis, W.D. Eilers, G.M. Coen,  A.J. Green, J.A. Shields, H. Luttmerding, R. van der Broek, M. Langman,  G. Patterson, E.W. Presant, G.J. Beke, J.L. Nowland and R. Marcoux for  aid in site selection and sampling;.and R.K. Guertin for analysing the  samples.    REFERENCES    Arnold, R.W., 1978. Concept of the 0xgillic horizon and problems of its identification.  Interm. Soil Classification Workshop, Malaysia and Thailand, Aug. 28--Sept. 9, 1978,  Pap., 17; 13 pp.  Brewer, R., 1968. Clay illuviation as a factor in particle-size differentiations in soil  profiles. Trans. 9th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 4: 489--499.  Brewer, R. and Sleeman, J.R., 1970. Some trends in pedology. Earth-Sci. Rev., 6:  297--335.  Bronger, A., 1978. Climatic sequences of steppe soils from eastern Europe and the  U.S.A. with emphasis on the genesis of the "argillic horizon". Catena, 5: 33--51.  Bullock, P. and Murphy, C.P., 1979. Evaluation of a paleo-argillie brown earth (paleudalf)  from Oxfordshire, England. Geoderma, 22: 225--252.  Canada Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian system of soil classification.  Agric. Can. Supply Serv., Ottawa, Publ., 1646:164 pp.  Chittleborough, D.J. and Oades, J.M., 1979. The development of a red-brown earth, 1.  A reinterpretation of published data. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17: 371--381.  Fedoroff, N., 1973. Classification of accumulations of translocated particles. In: G.K.  Rutherford (Editor), Soil Microscopy. The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont. pp. 695--  713.  Grossman, R.B., Brasher, B.R., Tranzmeier, D.P. and Walker, J.L., 1968. Linear ex-  tensibility as calculated from natural clod bulk density measurements. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 32: 570--573.  Guertin, R.K. and Bourbeau, G.A., 1971. Dry grinding of soil thin sections. Can. J. Soil  Sei., 51: 243--248.  Heilman, M.D., Carter, D.L. and Gonzalez, C.L., 1965. The ethylene-glycol monoethyl  ether (EGME) technique for determining soil surface area. Soil Sci., 100: 409--413.  Hill, J.D., 1970. Quantitative micromorphological evidence of clay movement. In:  D.A. Osmond and P. Bullock (Editors), Micromorphological Techniques and Applica-  tions. Agric. Res. Counc. Soil Surv., Harpenden, Tech. Monogr., 2: 33--42.    74    Holzhey, C.S., Yeck, R.D. and Nettleton, W.D.~ 1973. Microfabri~: of some argillic  horizons in udic, xeric and torric soil environments of the United States. In: G.K.  Rutherford (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp. 747--760.  Kodama, H., 1979. Clay minerals in Canadian soils: Their origin, distribution and alteration.  Can. J. Soil Sei., 59: 37--58.  McKeague, J.A., MacDougall, J.I. and Miles, N.M., 1973. Micromorphological, physical,  chemical and mineralogical properties of a catena of soils from Prince Edward Island  in relation to their classification and genesis. Can. J. Soil Sei., 53: 281--295.  McKeague, J.A., MacDougall, J.I., Langmald, K.K. and Bourbeau, G.A., 1969. Maero-  and micromorphology of ten reddlsh-brown soils from the Atlantic provinces. Can.  J. Soil Sci., 49: 53--63.  McKeague, J.A., Guertin, R.K., Page, F. and Valentine, K.W.G., 1978. Micromorphologi-  cal evidence of illuvial clay in horizons designated Bt in the field. Can. J. Soil Sei.,  58: 179--186.  MeKeague, J.A., Guertin, R.K., Valentine, K.W.G., B~lisle, J., Bourbeau, G.A.,  Michalyna, W., Hopkins, L., Howell, A., Page, F. and Bresson, L.M., 1980. Varia-  bility of estimates of illuvial clay in soils by mieromorphology. Soil Sci. (in press).  Miedema, R. and Slager, S., 1972. Micromorphological quantification of clay illuvia-  tion. J. Soil Sci., 23: 309--314.  Nettleton, W.D., Flach, K.W. and Brasher, B.R., 1969. Argillic horizons without clay  skins. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 121--125~  Schafer, W.M. and Singer, M.J., 1976. A new method of measuring shrink--swell  potential using soil pastes. Soil Sei. Soe. Am. J., 40: 805--806.  Sleeman, J.K., 1964. Structure variation within two red-brown earth profiles. Aust. J.  Soil Res., 2: 146--161.  Smeck, N.E., Wilding, L.P. and Holowaychuk, N., 1968. Genesis of argillie horizons  in Celina and Morley soils of western Ohio. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Proc., 32: 550--556.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil survey manual. U.S. Dep. Agrie. Handbook, 18. U.S.  Gov. Print. Off., Washington, D.C.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil taxonomy. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436. U.S. Gov.  Print. Off., Washington, D.C.                          AbstractStudies of 71 pedons in Canada showed that improvements are required in the estimation of argillic horizon development by both macro- and micro-morphological methods. Fifty-four of the pedons were considered by pedologists of the area to have argillic horizons but only 32 of them had at least 1% oriented, illuvial clay as estimated by point counting of thin sections. A high proportion of the soils thought to have argillic horizons but that lacked 1% oriented clay were either soils from semi-arid areas or soils of very high clay content. However, several clayey soils with COLE values more than 5% had well-developed argillans on ped surfaces and more than 1% oriented, illuvial clay.The results indicate that reference pedons and reference thin sections would be useful in improving the uniformity of designation of horizons as argillic. Useful estimates can be made of illuvial clay by rapid scanning of thin sections at a magnification of approximately 100 if reference sections with established point count values are available. Current criteria of argillic horizons are adequate except that the 1% oriented clay criteria should not be applied rigidly and that clay skins probably should be required in clayey soils of frigid and cryic temperature regimes (cool to very cold temperature classes in Canada). 