 Geoderma, 32 (1984) 251--271                                                     251  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V , Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Acevedo, William; Walker, Donald; Gaydos, Leonard; et al. Vegetation and land cover, Arctm Natmnal  Wddlife Refuge, coastal plato, Alaska  Miscellaneous Investigations Series - U- S_ Geologmal Survey,  1-1443, 1 sheet, environ, geol map 1 250,000, 1982  Adams, Fred; and Moore, B. L. Chemmal factors affecting root growth m subsoil horizons of Coastal  Plato soils' Soil Science Socmty of America Journal, 47(1), p 99-102, 2 tables, 1983  Adams, W. A.; and Kassim, J. K. The origin of vermmuhte in soils developed from lower Palaeozoic  sedimentary rocks in mid-Wales Soll Scmnce Society of America Journal, 47(2), p_ 316-320, dlus, 1983  Aime, S.; and Penven, M. J. Le complexe dunalre du Cap Falcon (Oran), Etude morphodynamlque  apphquee et perspectives d'amenagement [The dune complex of Cape Falcon (Oran); applied  morphodynamm study and management perspectives]  Medlterranee, 45(2), p 3-13 (mcl English sum ),  dlus, (mcL sketch map), 1982  Aleala del Olmo, L.; and Monturiol Rodriguez, F. Taxonomla numerma, su aphcacion a la claslficaclon  de los suelos re]os espanoles [Numermal taxonomy; application to the classification of Spamsh Red softs]  Anales de Edafologia y Agrobiologta, 41 (1-2), p. 183-196 (mcl English sum ), fllus (mcl 3 tables), 1982  Alias, L. J.; and Martinez Sanchez, J. Caractenstmas bmelimatieas de mteres edafologmo de las Smrras  de Orce y Marm [Bmclimatm characteristics of pedologic interest of the Smrras de Orce y Marm]  Anales  de Edafologm y Agrobmlogm, 41(1-2), p 11-20 (mcl Enghsh sum), fllus (reel_ 2 tables), 1982_  Anderson, Catherine L. Geobotany, an aid to geologm mapping  Cahfornia Geology, 36(2), p. 35-43,  illus. (reel 1 tables), 1983_  Anderson, J.H. Soil palynology and paleoecology of the Washington Creek Black Spruce Experimental  Forest, interior Alaska [abstr ]  in Character and timing of rapid environmental and cllmatm changes  (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al.), Am Quat Assoc., Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p 57, 1982  Seventh  btennial conference of the Amertcan Quaternary Association  Anderson, R. S.; Jacobson, G. L., Jr.; and Davis, R.B. Late- and postglacial environmental change m  central Maine; a record of marine, lacustnne and terrestrial fossils from Gould Pond [abstr_]  m  Character and hmlng of rapid environmental and ehmatm changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al),  Am Quat_ Assoc, Natl Conf-, Abstr_, 7, p  55, 1982  Seventh btenntal conference of the ,4merlcan  Quaternary Associatwn_  Anderson, Wayne I. Geology of Iowa, over two bllhon years of change: 268 p, lllus (mcl tables, sketch  maps), Iowa State Univ. Press, Ames, IO, Umted States, 1983  Andrejko, M. J.; Cohen, A. D.; Raymond, R., Jr.; et aL The strahgraphm dlStrlbutmn of morgamc  constituents within Okefenokee peats, a cross-sectional comparison through two major peat-forming  environments [abstr.]. m 95th annual meeting, The Geologmal Socmty of Amerma (Braunstem, Jules,  chairperson; et al), Abstracts with Programs - Geologmal Socmty of America, 14(7), p 433, 1982  Andrews, John T.; Birkeland, P. W.; Kihl, R.; et al Holocene lake sediments from subalpme and alpine  lakes, Colorado Front Range, basehne studies [abstr ]  m 95th annual meeting, The Geological Socmty  of Amerma (Braunstein, Jules, chairperson; et al), Abstracts with Programs - Geologmal Socmty of  America, 14(7), p. 433, 1982  Andriesse, Wire; and Scholten, Jules J.  Land capabihty assessment for a smallholders settlement  scheme m Jamama  Geoderma, 29(3), p 195-214, lllus (incl. 4 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Anonymous. Professor Dr sc. agr Dr h c. mult Georg Muller zum 65 Geburtstag [Professor Georg  Mueller on his 65th birthday]  Archly fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde, 26(10), p 615-616,  dlus. (incl. portr), 1982    252    Antwefler, Ronuld C.; and Drever, Jmes I. The weathering of a late Tertiary volcanic ash, ,mportance  of organic solutes: Geochimica  Cosmochlmica Acta, 47(3), p 623-629, sketch map, 1983  Arid~l)OV, N, P.; Tynmentseva, L. M.; Fevraleva, L. T.; et al.  Povedeniy e yestestvennykh  radloaknvnykh nukhdov tekhnogennogo prmskozhdemya v pochvakh [The behawor of natural  radioactive nuclides of technogemc ongm in soils]. Ekologlya, 1982(1), p 31-38, 1982_  Arulsasadsa, K.; and Perry, Edward B. Erosion m relation to filter design criteria in earth dams  Journal of Geotechmcal Engineering, 109(5), p. 682-698, illus (incl. 3 tables), 1983  Baker, Victor R. Stratlgraphic geology and natural hazards evaluation [abstr.]: m 95th annual meeting,  The Geological Society of America (Braunstein, Jules, chairperson; et al), Abstracts with Programs -  Geological Society of America, 14(7), p 438, 1982  Barnhardt, Michael L. Late Quaternary glacial chronology of the Bighorn Mountains, Wyoming  [abstr.]:  in Character and timing of rapid environmental and clunatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et aL), Am Quat. Assoc., Natl Conf, Abstr., 7, p. 64, 1982. Seventh biennial conference of  the Amerwan Quaternary Assocsat~on.  Barnosky, C. W.  Development of postglaclal vegetation and climate in southwestern Washington  [abstr ]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vcra,  chairperson; et aL), Am. Quat Assoc, Natl. Conf, Abstr,, 7, p 65, 1982  SeventA bienntal conference of  the American Quaternary Association  Barron, P. F.; Wilson, M. A.; C.,am~ A. S.; et al. Detection of imogollte m sods using sohd state  29Si NMR: Nature (London), 299(5884), p 616-618, dills_ (incl. table), 1982  Bartleln, Patrick J.; and Webh, ThOmlamn, IIl. Holocene precipitation vartatmns m the midwestern  Umted States [abstr.]. m Character and timing of rapid enwronmental and climatic changes (Markgraf,  Vera, chairperson, et aL), Am Quat. Assoc, Natl. Conf., Abstr, 7, p 66, sketch maps, 1982  Seventh  btennial conference of the American Quaternary As, mciat~o~  Barton, P. B., Jr. The many roles of organic matter m the genesis of mineral deposits [abstr ]. m 95th  annual meeting, The Geological Society of America (Brannstein, Jules, chairperson; etal.), Abstracts with  Programs - Geological Society of America, 14(7), p 440, 1982  Bsshoar, L I.; Al=Msaklamly, A. S.; Dovi Pruad, J.; et aL Morphology and composition of some soils  under coltivatmn in Saudi Arabia  Geoderma, 29(4), p. 327-340, 12 anal, 4 tables, sketch maps, 1983.  Beenaas, Mark; and Ksauth, L. Paul. Preserved stable isotopic signature of subaerial diagenes~s m the  1.2 b y Mescal Ltmestone of central Arizona [abstr.]. m 95th annual meeting, The Geological Society  of America (Braunstein, Jules, chmrperson; et al.), Abstracts wRh Programs - Geological Society of  America, 14(7), p 441, 1982  Beiswenger, Jane M.  Late Pleistocene and Holocene vegetation history of Grays Lake Basra,  southeastern Idaho [abstr.]: m Abstracts for the Fifty-fourth annual meetang of the Colorado-Wyoming  Academy of Science, The Journid of the Colorado-Wyoming Academy of Science, 15(1), p 26, 1983.  Ben-Ashar, J.; Matthl~, ,4,. D.; and Win'rick, A. W, Assessment of evaporatmn from bare sod by  infrared thermometry- Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 185-191, dlus (mcl 2 tables),  1983_  Benetti, Michael. Rock fertilizer and other low-cost methods to increase crop yields: 93 p., dlus,  Privately published, Salinas, CA, United States, 1982  Benltoz, C.; Mearida, J.; Corral, L.; et aL Morfologm y propiedades qutmlcas de suelos forestales de  Grszalema, Cadiz, Espana, I, Sualos bajo Quercos rotundifoliae y Quercos fagineae [Morphology and  chemical properties of forested sods in Grazalema, Cadre Province, Spain; I, Softs under Quercus  rotundffohae and Quercus fagmeae]- Anales de Edafologia y Agrobiologia, 41(1-2), p 211-229 0ncl  Enghsh sum), dlus. 0ncl- 5 anal, 8 tables), 1982  Bealtez, C.; M~ J.; Corral, L.; et al. Morfologia y propnedades quinucas de Suelos forestales de  Grazalema, Cadiz, Espsaa; II, Suelos bajo Quercus suber y Alnes lansapo [Morphology and chenucal  properues of forested sods in Grazalema, Cadiy Province, Spain; II, Sods under Quercus suber and Ables  pinsapo]. Anales de Edafologia y Agrnbiologia, 41(1-2), p. 231-250 (me1. Enghsh sum ), dlus. (incl. 4  anal., 8 tables), 1982.  Blllo, Saleh M.  Geochemistry of trace elements m modern and ancient marine and fresh water  environments [abstr.]: in Abstracts of papers of the 149th Nauonal meeting of the American Association  of Science (Hersehman, Arthur, editor), AAAS Publication, 83-2, p. 149-150, 1983    253    Birkeland, P. W.; and Burke, R.M. Quantitative data for an alpine soil chronosequence, Colorado Front  Range [abstr.]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am, Quat Assoc_, Natl Conf., Abstr, 7, p 70, 1982  Seventh btenntal conference of  the Arnertcan Quaternary Assoclatton.  Birks, H. J. B.  Holocene tree migrations and populauon dynamics m the British Isles [abstr ]  In  Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al),  Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf., Abstr., 7, p 71, 1982  Seventh blenntal conference of the Amerwan  Quaternary Assoctatton.  Birat, Pierre; Godard, Alain; and Pelletier, Jean. L'erosion dlfferentlelle dans les reliefs de l'Estrle et  de la Nouvelle-Angleterre, entre Montreal et le piedmont sud-est des White Mountains [The Influence  of differential erosion on the relief of the Eastern Townships and on New England between Montreal  and the southeastern piedmont of the White Mountains]  Geographic Physique et Quaternalre, 37(l),  p 3-25 (mcl English, German sum), dlus (mcl 6 tables, sects_, geol sketch map), 1983  Black, Robert F.; Miekelson, David M.; and MeCartney, M. Carol. Late Woodfordlan and Greatlakean  history of the Green Bay Lobe, Wisconsin  Geological Society of America Bulletin, 94(7), p 936-938,  illus_, 1983  Bloom, P. R. The kinetics of glbbslte dlssolutton in mtrlc acid  Soll Science Society of America Journal,  47(1), p 164-168, fllus (lncl 1 table), 1983  Bloom, Paul R. (reviewer). The mineralogy, chemistry and physics of Tropical soils with variable charge  clays  American Journal of Science, 238(6), p 634-636, 1983  Borsuk, O. A.  Vhyaniye snosa s ostrovov na razvltlye veregovykh protsessov [Impact of island  weathering on coastal processes]  m Morsklye berega (Kovalev, S A, editor, et al), Voprosy Geografil,  119, p 153-159 (incl. Enghsh sum.), 1 table, 1982  Bowyer-Beaudoin, Alwynne.  Holocene palaeoenvlronmental change and the local pollen record in  Sunwapta Pass, Jasper National Park, Alberta [abstr ]  in Character and hmlng of rapid environmental  and chmatlc changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al), Am Quat. Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p  74, 1982  Seventh bienntal conference of the Amertcan Quaternary Assoctatton  Boyd, Stephen A.; Sommers, Lee E.; Nelson, Darrell W.; et al Copper (II) binding by humlc acid  extracted from sewage sludge, an electron spin resonance study  Soil Science Society of America  Journal, 47(1), p 43-46, dlus (incl 2 tables), 1983  Brakenridge, G. R.  Alluvml stratigraphy and radiocarbon dating, Duck River, central Tennessee,  floodplain response to environmental change [abstr.]  m Character and timing of rapid enwronmental  and chmatlc changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p_  75, 1982  Seventh btenmal conference of the Amertcan Quaternary Assoctatton_  Brown, Melvin D. Soft survey of Des Momes County, Iowa  199 p, dlus (lncl_ 18 tables, sods map  1 15,840, colored soils map 1 190,080). U_ S Dep. Agrtc, Soil Conserv Serv, Washington, DC, United  States, 1983 (Publ in coop. with Iowa Agric Home Econ Exp Stn, Iowa State Umv, Coop Ext Serv,  State Iowa, Dep Sod Conserv)  Brubaker, Linda B.; Garfinkel, Harriet L.; and Edwards, Mary E. A new look at vegetation change  in the central Brooks Range, Alaska [abstr_]. m Character and timing of rapid enwronmental and chmatlc  changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et al), Am Quat_ Assoc, Natl_ Conf, Abstr, 7, p 77, 1982  Seventh bwnmal conference of the Amertcan Quaternary Assoclatwn  Bruque, S.; Martinez Lara, M.; and Moreno Real, L. Fertihdad quimlca de los suelos del Valle del Rio  Guadalhorce, Malaga [Chemical fertdlty of soils in the Guadalhorce Valley, Malaga Province]  Anales  de Edafologm y Agroblologm, 41(1-2), p 283-310 (mcl_ English sum ), illus (incl. 286 anal, 9 tables),  1982  Bryant, R. B.; Curl, N.; Roth, C. B.; et al. Use of an internal standard with differential X-ray diffraction  analysm for iron oxides  Soll Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 168-173, illus (mcl_ 3 tables),  1983  Buckingham, William F.; and Sommer, Sheldon E.  Mineralogical characterization of rock surfaces  formed by hydrothermal alteration and weathering, application to remote sensing  m An issue devoted  to techniques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H, editor, et al), Economic Geology  and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 664-674, dlus (mcl- 6 tables), 1983    254    Bull, William B.; and KnHlffer, Peter L. Frequency and magmtude of late Quaternary faulting of  alluvial geomorpluc surfaces [abstr.]-  in 95th annual meeting, The Geological Society of America  (Braunstein, Jules, chairperson; et al.), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 14(7),  p 455, 1982  Burns, Scott F,; and Toakin, P.J. Windthrow as a geomorphm and pedologic agent, Craigleburn Range,  New Zealand [abstr ]: m 95th annual meeting, The Geulogmal Socmty of America (grannsteln, Jules,  chairperson; eta/.), Abstracts wRh Programs - Geological Society of America, 14(7), p 456, 1982  Calhoun, John W. Soil survey of Tilt County, Georgm: 102 p., illus (mci. 19 tables; soils maps 1 20,000,  colored soils map 1.126,720), U. S Dep, Agrm., Soil Conserv. Serv., Waslungton, DC, United States,  1983 (Publ. in coop with Univ. Ga Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp. Stns; Tift Cty)  Cairo de Aata, R. M.; mad Diaz-Fierros, F. Minerahzacton del Carbono y del Nitrogeno en suelos  forest.ales de Galicia [Carbon and nitrogen mineralizatton in forested soils of Galicta]: Anales de  Edafologla y Agrobiologta, 41(1-2), p. 1-10 (incl English sum ), illus. (incl_ 6 anal, 2 tables), 1982  Capmmo, RegiJ M. DeposRional environments of trace elements m soils over an active hydrothermal  system, Roosevelt Hot Springs, Utah [ahstr ].  in 95th annual meeting, The Geological Soc,ety of  America (Braunstein, Jules, chairperson, et al), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of  America, 14(7), p. 459, 1982  Card, K. D.; and Stilts, W. W. Geological research on potentml effects of acid rain, Eastern Canada  [abstr.]: in 95th annual meetang, The Geological Society of America (Braunstem, Jules, chairperson; et  a/), Abstracts with Programs - Geological Society of America, 14(7), p. 459, 1982  Cassel, D. K. Spatial and temporal varlablhty of sod physmal properties following tillage of Norfolk  loamy sand: Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 196-201, illus. Croci- 3 tables), 1983  C'haey, Rounld C.; Slunlm, S. M.; and Sloalm, S. S. Suggested test method for determination of the  soluble salt content of soils by refractometer'_ ASTM Geoteehnical Testing Journal, 6(2), p 93-95, illus,  1983  Chang, Sheag-Huei; and Collins, William.  Confirmation of the atrborne biogeophysmal mineral  exploration teehmque using laboratory methods: iaAn issue devoted to techniques and results of remote  sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H., editor; et al), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of  Economic Geologists, 78(4), p. 723-736, illus,, 1983  Chao, T. T.; and Zhoe, Llyi. Extraction techmques for selective dissolutmn of amorphous tron oxides  from soils and sediments  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 225-232, fllus (mcl 3  tables), 1983  Chesworth, Ward; MaelawVmulaez, Fellpe; Aequaye, David; et al Agriculture alchemy, stones into  bread: Episodes, 1983(1), p 3-7, illus, 1983.  ChJlds, C. W.; Pm-fltt, R. L.; and Lee, R. Movement of alummmm as an morgamc complex in some  podzolised smls, New Zealand. Geoderma, 29(2), p. 139-155, 4 anal, 3 tables, sketch map, 1983_  Chrts~iaasoa, C. B.; and Cho, C. M. Chemical demtrificatton of nitrite m frozen soils  Soil Science  Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 38-42, illus (mcl 1 table), 1983  C'hu, Shu-Yunn; SlmSlto, Garrisoa; and Jury, William A. The cross-couphng transport coefficient for  the steady flow of heat m soil under a gradient of water content: Soil Science Socmty of America Journal,  47(1), p. 21-25, 1983  Chun, Joeng H.; and Jacewttz, Chester A. The weathering stattcs problem and first arrival rtme surfaces  [abstr ]: in Midwest meeting abstracts, Geophysics, 47(7), p. 1118-1119, 1982.  Clapp, R. B.; Hornberger, G. M.; gad Cosby, B. J. Estimating spatial variability in soft moxsture wtth  a simplified dynamm model: Water Resources Research, 19(3), p. 739-745, illus. (incl 2 tables), 1983  Clement, Pierre; Bonn, F~; and Dubois, Jm-Mm'ie M.  Teledetactmn et caracteristiques  physiques des depots meubles duns un milieu anciennemeot englace du sud du Quebec [The remote  sensing and physical characteristics of the surficial deposits of a glactated area of southern Quebec]-  Geographie Physique et Quaternalre, 37(1), p 107-117 (incl English, German sum ), illus. (incl. 1 table,  block diag, sect), 1983.  Cole, Kenneth L. Plemtocene packrat middens from the western Sierra Nevada, Cattforma [abstr.]  m  Character and tirmng of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et al.),  Am. Quat Assoc., Natl. Conf., Abstr, 7, p. 83, 1982  Sewath biennial conference of the .4mertcan  Quaternary Association.    255    Collins, William; Chang, Sheng-Huei; Raines, Gary; et al. Airborne blogeophyslcal mapping of hidden  mineral deposits_ m An ~ssue devoted to techmques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander  F H, editor, et al.), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, 78(4),  p 737-749, lllus (mcl geol. sketch maps), 1983  Connor, C. L. Pollen evidence for a mid-Wisconsin mterstadlal event m south central Alaskan glaclo-  lacustrine sediments [abstr ]:  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatic changes  (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et al.), Am Quat Assoc., Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p_ 84, 1982  Seventh  bwnmal conference of the American Quaternary Association  Cowan, E. Selden. Sod survey of St Joseph County, Michigan. 108 p, fllus (mcl_ 18 tables, soils maps  1 15,840; colored sods map 1 190,080), U. S. Dep Agric., Soil Conserv Serv, Washington, DC, Umted  States, 1983 (Publ m coop. with Mlch_ Agnc Exp Stn)  Curry, B. Brandon (editor). Old Dad-Kelso Mountains resource survey  477 p, illus. (mcl sketch  maps, geomorphol maps 1 29,528), 1983  avadable from Purdue Univ, West Lafayette, IN, United  States  Dal'berg, Ye.  Geokhlmlchesklye metody poiskov v dokembru Sunnama (Gvlanskiy shchit)  [Geochemical exploration within the PrecambrIan terrain of Sunnam, Guyana Shield]  m MmeraI'nyye  mestorozhdeniya dokcmbriya (Sidorenko, A V, editor, et al), Problemy Osadochnoy Geologiy  Dokembnya : Problems of the Sedimentary Geology of the Precambnan, 8, p 196-205 (incl English  sum), 1 table, 1982  D'Almeida, Guillaume A.; and Schutz, Lothar. Number, mass and volume distributions of mineral  aerosol and soils of the Sahara  Journal of Climate and Applied Meteorology, 22(2), p 233-243, lllus  (mcl sketch maps), 1983.  Daniel, D. E. Permeability test for unsaturated soft  ASTM Geotechmcal Testing Journal, 6(2), p 81-  86, illus (incl 1 table), 1983  Dareh, J. P.; and Barber, J. Multitemporal remote sensing of a geobotamcal anomaly  ~n An issue  devoted to techniques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H., editor, et al), Economic  Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 770-782, dlus (mcl 11 tables,  sketch maps), 1983  David, Peter P.  Sensitivity of the parabolic-dune environment to short-term climatic fluctuations  [abstr ]   in Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc., Natl Conf, Abstr_, 7, p 85, 198:2  Seventh bwnmal conference of  the Amerwan Quaternary Assoclatwn.  Davis, R. B.; and Jaeobson, G. L., Jr. Vegetation from 14,000 - 9,000 b p m northern New England  and adjacent Canada [abstr ]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatlc changes  (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et al), Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p_ 88, 1982_  Seventh  blenmal conference of the American Quaternary Association  De Jong, R.; Campbell, C. A.; and Nicholaiehuk, W. Water retention equations and their relauonsh~p  to sod organic matter and particle size distribution for disturbed samples: Canadian Journal o[" Soil  Science, 63(2), p 291-302 (mcl French sum), illus (incl 8 tables), 1983  Delgado Calvo-Flores, R.; Barahona, E.; I-Iuertas, F.; et al Los MollIsoles de la Cuenca alta del Rio  Dflar, Sierra Nevada [Molhsols of the Dilar high basra, Spanish Sierra Nevada]- Anales de Edafologm  y Agrohiologia, 41(1-2), p 59-82 (mcl English sum), dlus (mcl 9 tables, sketch map), 1982  Delgado Calvo-Flores, R.; Barahona, E.; I-Iuertas, F.; et al Los lnceptlsoles de la Cuenca alta del Rio  Dflar, Sierra Nevada [Inceptlsols of the Dflar high basin, Spamsh Sierra Nevada]  Anales de Edafologia  y Agrobiologla, 41(1-2), p 83-111 (mcl_ English sum), dlus (mcl 14 tables, sketch map), 1982,  Delgado Calvo-Flores, R.; Barahona, E.; Huertas, F.; et al. Los ent~soles de la Cuenca alta del Rio Dilar,  Sierra Nevada [Entisols of the Dflar high basin, Spanish Sierra Nevada]-  Anales de Edafologm y  Agroblologia, 41(1-2), p 113-129 (lncl English sum), dlus (incl. 7 tables, sketch map), 1982  Delgado Calvo-Flores, R.; Barahona, E.; and Linares, J. DIstnbucion de los suelos de la Cuenca alta  del Rio Dilar, Sierra Nevada [Distribution of soils of the Ddar high basin, Spanish Sierra Nevada]  Anales de Edafologia y Agrobiologia, 41(1-2), p 39-57 (mcl English sum ), dlus (lncl_ 1 table, sketch  map, geol sketch map), 1982    256    Dick, W.A. Orgamc carbon, nitrogen, and phosphorus concentrations and pH in soil profiles as affected  by tillage intensity: Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p. 102-107, illus. (incl. 2 tables),  1983  Domuchuk, L. Frost heave forces on embedded structural unlts: m Proceedings of the Fourth Canadlan  permafrost conference; the Roger 3. E. Brown memorial volume (French, H M., editor), 19810302, p  487-496 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), Natl. Res. Counc of Canada, Ontario, ON, Canada,  1982 (The Roger J E Brown Memorial Volume).  Dormant, J. F.  Aliphatic carboxylic acids m buried Ah horizons in Alberta, Canada as  paleoenwronmental indicators  CanmJian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal Canadian des Scmnces  de la Terre, 20(5), p 859-866 (incl French sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1983  Duane, Thomas; gad Dietrich, W~. Sediment sources in tropmal drainage basins, in Soil erosmn  and conservation in the tropms (Kussow, W., editor, eta/), ASA Special Publication, 43, p. 41-55, illus_  (incl. sketch map), 1982.  F_omhir~ Kl~,~ko; and Ohtsubo, Musmi. Swelhng and mineralogy of smectites in paddy sods derived  from marine alluvium, Japan  Geoderma, 29(2), p. 119-127, dlus (incl 10 anal, 5 tables), 1983.  EI-Swmify, S. A.; gad ~, E. W. Rainfall erosion in the tropics, a state-of-the-art: m Sod erosion  and conservation in the tropics (Kussow, W, editor, et aL), ASA Special Publication, 43, p. 1-25, illus  (incl. 11 tables, sketch maps), 1982_  Elder, J. F.; aml Cairns, D. J. ProducUon and decomposition of forest litter fall on the Apalachicola  River flood plain, Florida: Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper (Washington), 2196-B, p B1-B42,  illus (incl 10 tables, sketch maps), 1982  Eiir, aide, B.; and Fernandez, M. Q/I ratio m sahne soils belongm8 to Ebro Valley, Spain. Anales de  Edafologia y Agrobiologia, 41(1-2), p 271-281, illus. (incl. 6 anal, 3 tables), 1982  Elfies, A.  Die WLrkungen yon Bodenerhitzungen auf die Benetzungselgenschaften emiger Boden  Sudchiles [Effects of heat treatment on the wettabflity of some soils from southern Chile]' Geoderma,  29(2), p 129-138 (incl. English sum.), 6 anal., 7 tables, 1983_  Eiwonger, W. G. Soil survey of Crook County, Wyoming  320 p., illus. (incl 13 tables; sods maps  1:24,000, colored soils map 1:380,160), U S Dep. Agric Sod Conserv Sere, Washington, DC, United  States, 1983. (Publ in coop. with U S. Dep. Agric., For Sere.; Wyo. Agric. Exp Stn ).  Er~inuAr, J.; gad Pueitelt, H.  Methoden zur Bestimmung umweltrelevanter Spurenelemente m  geologischem Material [Methv~is for the determinations of trace elements of environmental interest in  geologic materials] Erzmetail, 35(4), p. 173-179 (incl. English sum.), illus (incl 4 tables, 4 plates), 1982  Evans, L. J.; and Cmlrou, B. H. The Brookston series in southwestern Ontario; characteristics,  classification and problems in deflnin~ a soil senas. Canadian Journal nfSofl Science, 63(2), p. 339-352  (incl. French sum ), illus (incl 4 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Ferreh-a, V. A.; and Ammmsea, L. F., The agricultural resource picture, focus on the Southeast: m Studies  of the hydrogeology oft.he southeastern United States; 1981 (Beck, Barry F., editor), Special Publications  - Georgia Southwestern College, 1, p, 38-45, illus (incl 1 table, sketch maps), 1982. 5th southeastern  groundwoter conference.  Fialayson, Brimt. Gramte caves in Girraween National Park, Southeast Queensland  Hellctite, 20(2),  p. 53-59, illus (incl. sketch maps), 1983  Fiaber, P. F. Pedogenesis wiflun the archaeological landscape at South Lodge Camp, Wiltslure, England  Geoderma, 29(2), p 93-105, illus (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), 1983.  Fodor, R.V. Chiaeling the'F.,m-th; how erosion shapes the land- 96 p., Illus. (incl. sketch maps), Emslow  Publ, Hilimde, NJ, United States, 1983  FnrtmeB, Jeim A. C. Geochemical prostmctmg for gold in Ontario: m The geology of gold in Ontario  (Colvme, A, C, editor), Ontario Geological Survey Miscellaneous Paper, 110, p 251-271, illus (incl  5 tables, sects, sketch maps), 1983  Foster, G. R.; M~, W. C.; mad WimJamim-, W. H. Transferabihty of U.S. technology for  prediction and control of erosion in the tropics: in Soil erosion and conservation in the tropics (Kussow,  W, editor; eta/), ASA Special Publicatmn, 43, p 135-149, 1 table, 1982.    257    Francey, R. J,; and Farquhar, G. D.  An explanation of 13C/t2C vartations m tree rings  Nature  (London), 297(5861),p 28-31, 1982  Francou, Bernard,  Regimes thermtques de sols de l'etage perlglacia~re et leurs consequences  geomorphologlques, Exemple de la combe de Launchard, Alpes du Bnanconnais, France [Thermal  regimes of soils of the penglaclal stage and their geomorphic consequences, example of the Combe de  Launchard, Alps of the Bnanconnals, France]  Geographle Physique et Quaternalre, 37(1), p 27-38  (mcl Enghsh, German sum), lUus (mcl 4 tables, sketch map), 1983  Fry, Brlall; Scalan, Richard S.; Winters, J. Kenneth; et al Sulphur uptake by salt grasses, mangroves,  and seagrasses m anaerobic se&amp;ments  Geochlmica et Cosmochlmlca Acta, 46(6), p 1121-1124, dlus  (mcl table), 1982.  Fullen, Michael A. Laboratory and field studies m the use of the isotope 59Fe for tracing soil particle  movement  Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(3), p 285-293, dlus. (incl 2 tables), 1982  Furlan, V.; and Felix, C. La degradation de la pierre et les moyens de protection [The degradation of  stones and the means of protection]- Chimla, 36(7-8), p 313-319 (lncl Enghsh sum), dlus, 1982  Ganapathy, Ramachandran. The Tunguska explosion of 1908, discovery of meteorite debris near the  explosion site and at the South Pole- Science, 220(4602), p 1158-1161, dlus (mcl 8 anal_, 1 table), 1983  Gardner, Leonard Robert.  Mechanics and kinetics of incongruent feldspar dissolution  Geology  (Boulder), 11(7), p_ 418-421, lllus, 1983_  Gaudreau, D. C. Holocene vegetational history of central New England and the Hudson R~ver valley  [abstr ]   m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc, Natl_ Conf_, Abstr, 7, p 93, 1982  Seventh bwnmal conference of  the Amertcan Quaternary Assoetatlon  Gauthier, Benoit; and Goudrean, Michel. Mares glaclelles et non glacielles dans le marais sale de l'lsle-  Verte, estuaire du Samt-Laurent, Quebec [Ice-formed and non-ice-formed depressions in the salt marshes  of Verte Island, Samt Lawrence Estuary, Quebec]_ Geographle Physique et Quaternalre. 37(1), p 49-  66 (lncl English, German sum), lllus (mcl 4 tables, sketch map), 1983  Gent, J. A., Jr. A computer program for determmmg particle size dlstrlbutmn and soil textural class  Communicatmns m Soft Science and Plant Analysis, 14(4), p 347-351, 3 tables, 1983  Gerber, T. D.; and Buzard, R.W. Soil survey of Carroll County, Ohio  156 p., tllus (mcl 18 tables,  sods maps 1 15,840, colored sods map 1190,080), U S Dep Agrlc, Soft Conserv. Serv, Washington,  DC, Umted States, 1983 (Publ m coop with Ohio Dep Nat Resour, Dlv_ Lands Soil, Ohm Agnc_ Res  Dev Cent )  Ghebre-Egziabhier, K,; and St. Arnaud, R.J. Carbonate mineralogy of lake sediments and surrounding  sods, 1, Blackstrap Lake. Canadmn Journal of Soft Science, 63(2), p 245-257 (mcl_ French sum ), dlus  (mcl 4 tables, sketch map), 1983  Ghebre-Egziabhier, K.; and St. Arnaud, R.J. Carbonate mineralogy of lake sediments and surrounding  sotls, 2, The Qu'Appelle lakes: Canadian Journal of Soll Science, 63(2), p 259-269 (incl French sum,),  filus (mcl 3 tables, sketch map), 1983.  Ghosh, Knnal; Chattopadhyay, Amitabha; and Varadachari, Chanduka. Electron exchange behavtors  of humic substances with iron, copper, and manganese_ Sod Science, 135(3), p 193-196, illus (mcl 2  tables), 1983  Giltrap, D. J.  Computer production of soil maps, 1, Productmn of grid maps by interpolatmn  Geoderma, 29(4), p 295-311, 2 tables, sketch maps, 1983  Gilt'rap, D.J. Computer productmn of sod maps, II, Interactive map display  Geoderma, 29(4), p_ 313-  325, illus, 1983  Giovannmi, G.; Luechesi, S.; and Cervelh, S. Water-repellent substances and aggregate stability in  hydrophoblc soil- Soil Science, 135(2), p 110-113, 4 tables, 1983  Goetz, Alexander F. H.; Rock, Barrett N.; and Rowan, Lawrence C. Remote sensing for exploratmn,  an overview  tn An Issue devoted to techniques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H,  editor; et al.), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 573-  590, illus_ (incl 3 tables), 1983    258    Goldin, Aim-.- and Parsons, R. B. Geomorphic surfaces and soils in the Camas Prairie area, Washington.  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 275-280, illus_ (mcl 4 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Goodman, B. A.; and ~, M. V, Reduction of molybdate by soft organic matter, EPR evidence  for formation of both Mo(V) and Mo(III)- Nature (London), 299(5884), p. 61g-620, iUus (incl. 1 table),  1982  Gorman, L. T.; and Van Sickle, V. R. Environmental monitoring, Gladys McCall No 1 well site  tn  Geopressured-geothermal energy resource appraisal; hydrogeology and well testing determine  produclbility (Wallace, Raymond H., Jr, editor), 14, p. 72-78, illus. (incl. 2 tables, geol. sketch maps),  Geol Soc Am., New Orleans, LA, United States, 1982 (Guidebook Series No 2 of La. Geol. Sure.).  Gough, L. P.; and Severson, R. C. Chemical analyses of native soil and vegetation samples, Capps coal  field, Alaska: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey 1978), 58 p., 4 tables, sketch maps,  1983. 0tep. No. 83-0246) amilablefrom'U. S. Geol. Sure, Open-Fde Sere. Sect., West Distrib Branch,  Denver Fed. Cent, Lakewood, CO, United States  Grisheheako, O. M. Botanicheskiye anomalti kak poiskovo-razvedochnyy krlterly neftegazonosnostl  [Botanical anomahes as prospecting-surveying criterion for petroleum and gas exploration]- Ekologiya,  1982(1), p 18-22, 1982  Gaeniot, B.; Galltet, B.; and Souchi~, B. FLXatlon de ruranium sur lea surfaces d'oxyhydroxydes de  far (lepidocrocite) des horizons placiques de sols hydromorphes; example des stag~ogleys des Vosges  cnstallines [Uramum fixation on surfaces of iron oxyhydroxides (lepidocrocite) in horizons of  Hydromorphlc soils, stanogleys from the Vosges crystalline rocks]. Comptes-Rendus des Seances de  l'Academie des Sciences, Serie 2: Mecanique-Phy-~ique, Chimle, Sciences de l'Univers, Sciences de la  Terre, 295(1), p 31-36 (incl English sum), Illus., 1982.  Gemazzio Fernandez, J.; Astuddl!le PDtor, J.; and Battle Sales, J. Aspectos edafogeoqmmicos en la  salinidad en la Submeseta sur (Toledo), I, Estudto hidrogeoquimico [Pedo-geochenucal aspects of salimty  in the Submeseta Sud, Toledo Province; I, Hydrochemistry]: Anales de Edafologia y Agroblologia,  41(1-2), p. 131-148 (incl. English sum.), dlus (incl 133 anal, 4 tables, gaol sketch map, sketch map),  1982  Hakonson, T. E.; White, G. C.; m'd Kin'lea, E. M. EvaluaUon of geologic materials to lumt biological  intrusion of low-level waste site covers  m Proceedings of the American Nuclear Society topical meeting  on the treatment and handling of radioacuve wastes (Blasewttz, A. G., editor; et aL), p. 471-476, illus.  (incl. 7 tables), Battelle Press, Columbus, OH, United States, Springer-Verlag, New York, NY, Umted  States, 1983 (0-935470-14-X)  Hall, G. F.; Daalels, R. B.; and Foss, J. E. Rate of soft formation and renewal in the USA:  tn  Determinants of sod loss (Schmidt, B L., chairperson), ASA Special Publlcatmn, 45, p. 23-39, illus. (mcl  3 tables), 1982.  Harter, RobertD. Effect of sod pH on adsorptlon of lead, copper, zlnc, andnickel' Soil Science Soclety  of America Journal, 47(1), p. 47-51, illus. (incl 2 tables), 1983_  Haynes, R. J. Effect of lime and phosphate appfications on the adsorption of phosphate, sulfate, and  molybdate by a Spodosol. Soil Science, 135(4), p 221-227, illus (incl. 1 table), 1983  Hebda, ]~lehat.d J.  A 13,000 year record of vegetation, Hat Creek Valley, south central, British  Columbia [abstr ]" mCharacter and tLming of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chan'person, et aL), Am. Quat. Assoc., Natl. Conf, Abstr, 7, p 99, 1982  Seventh biennial conference of  the American Quaternary Association.  Heusser, Calvin J.  Quaternary palynology of a core from Laguna de Tagua Tagua m central Chde  [abstr.]:  in Character and tinung of rapid environmental and chmatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson: eta/.), Am. Quat Assoc., Nail Conf, Abstr., 7, p. 103, 1982.  Seventh bienn/al conference  of the American Quaternary Association_  Heasser, Calvin J. Holocene vegetation history of the Prince William Sound region, south-central  Alaska' Quaternary Research (New York), 19(3), p. 337-355, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Heusser, Lind8 E. Palynology and paieoecology of post41acial sediments m an anoxic basra, Saamch  Inlet, British Columbia: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal Canadian des Sciences de la  Terra, 20(5), p. 873-885 (incl. French sum.), 2 tables, charts, sketch maps, 1983.    259    Hicock, Stephen R.; Hebda, Richard J.; and Armstrong, John E. Pollen and macrofossd evidence for  a late Wisconsin glacial lag in the Pacific Northwest, from western Fraser Lowland, British Columbia  [abstr_]   In Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am Quit Assoc., Nail Conf_, Abstr, 7, p 105, 1982  Seventh biennial conference  of the American Quaternary Association.  Hodges, Steven C.; and Zelazny, L. W.  [nteractlons of dilute, hydrolyzed aluminum solutions with  clays, peat, and resin  Sml Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 206-212, Illus_ (mcl 5 tables),  1983  Hodges, Steven C.; and Zelazny, L. W. Influences of OH/AI ratios and loadmg rates on aluminum-  kaolinite interactions  Soll Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 221-225, lllus (mcl 2 tables),  1983  Hoganson, J. W.; and Ashworth, A. C. The Chilean lake region Late-glacial climate, interpreted from  beetle assemblages [abstr_]   m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes  (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al), Am Quit Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p 106, 1982  Seventh  biennial conference of the American Quaternary Association  Holder, M. B.; and Griftith, S. M. Some characteristics of humlc materials m Caribbean Vertlsols  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, 63(2), p 151-160 (reel French sum), dlus (mcl 6 tables), 1983  Horton, R.; and Wierenga, P.J. Estimating the soil heat flux from observations of soft temperature near  the surface  Sod Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 14-20, fllus (mcl 2 tables), 1983  Horton, R.; Wierenga, P, J.; and Nielsen, D. R. Evaluation of methods for determining the apparent  thermal dlffuslvlty of soil near the surface  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 25-32, lllus  (lncl 8 tables), 1983  Horvath, John S. A case for the extension of the unified soil classification system, discussion Canadian  Geotechmcal Journal = Revue Canadienne de Geotechmque, 20(2), p 369, 1983  Hoyos de Castro, A.; Hernando Costa, J.; Hernando Massanet, I.; et at._ Modelo experimental de  alteraclon de ohgisto, aphcacion al estudio opttco de minerales opacos [Experimental model of hematite  alteration, application to the optical exammatlon of opaque minerals]   Anales de Edafologla y  Agrobmlogla, 41(1-2), p 149-163 (incl Enghsh sum), lllus_ (lncl 14 tables), 1982  Hoyos de Castro, A.; Hernando Massanet, L; Hernando Costa, J.; et al  Modelo experimental de  alteraclon de feldespatos, apllcaclon de tmclon, I, Ortosa [Experimental model of feldspar alteration,  application to coloration, I, Orthoclase]  Anales de Edafologla y Agroblologla, 41(1-2), p 165-175 (mcl  English sum), dlus (mcl 2 tables), 1982  Hoyos de Castro, A.; Hernando Massanet, I.; Hernando Costa, d.; et al  Modelo experimental de  alteraclon de feldespatos, aphcacmn al metodo de tmclon, II, Labradonta [Experimental model of  feldspar alteration; application to the method of coloration, II, Labradonte]  Anales de Edafologla y  Agrobiologla, 41(1-2), p 177-182 (incl Enghsh sum), illus (mcl 5 tables), 1982.  Hudson, N. W. Soil conservation research and training requirements in developing tropical countries  In Soil erosion and conservation in the tropics (Kussow, W, editor, et al), ASA Special Publication, 43,  p 121-133, 2 tables, 1982  Hundley, Steven J. Soil survey of Dakota County, Minnesota  272 p, illus. (lncl_ 18 tables, soils maps  1 15,840, colored sods map 1.253,440), U S_ Dep Agric, Soil Conserv Serv, Washington, DC, United  States, 1983 (Publ in coop. with Mmn Agnc Exp Sin_)  Hyde, Adam G.; and Huckle, Horace F. Soil survey of Manatee County, Florida  159 p, lllus (mcl  16 tables, soils maps 1 24,000, colored soils map 1 253,440), U S Dep Agrlc, Soil Conserv Serv,  Washington, DC, United States, 1983. (Publ in coop with Umv Flor, Inst Food and Agric Scl, Agric  Exp. Stn Soil Scl Dep, Flor Dep Agnc_ Consum Serv)  Ingrain, H. A. P. Size and shape in raised mire ecosystems; a geophysical model  Nature (London),  297(5864),p 300-303, dlus, 1982  Ito, Emi; and Clayton, Robert N. Submarine metamorphism of gabbros from the Mid-Cayman Rise,  an oxygen isotopic study- Geochlmica et Cosmochimtca Acta, 47(3), p 535-546, 1983  Ivanov, V. D.  Erozlya na pakhotnykh sklonakh Voronezhskoy oblastl i ocherednost' provedemya  protwoerozlonnoy melloratsil [Erosion of arable slopes in the Voronezh region and the succession of  erosion prevention measures] Geomorfologlya, 1983(2), p 35-38 (mcl English sum ), 2 tables, sketch  map, 1983    260    Jackson, Lloael F_,., Jr4 Fo~olos, A. F-,4 end MmcD~udd, G. M. An mterglaclal or preglscial Paleosol  from the Selwyn Mountains, N.W T., Canada [abstr.]: m Character and timing of rapid envlronmental  and climatic chooses (Markgraf, Vcra, chairperson; eta/.), Am Quat. Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p  109, 1982  Seventh triennial conference of the American Quaternary AssoctatwrL  James, Bruce R.; and Bartlett, Richmond J. Behavior of chrommm in smls, V, Fate of orgamcally  complexed Cr(III) added to sml  Journal of Env]ronmental Quality, 12(2), p. 169-172, illus, 1983  James, Bruce R.; and Bartlett, Riebmond J. Behavior of chromium m soils, VI, Interactions between  oxidation-reduction and organic complexatlon  Journal of Environmental Quality, 12(2), p. 173-176,  illus. 0ncl- 2 tables), 1983.  James, Bruce R.; and Bartlett, Richmond J. Behavior of chrormum m soils, VII, Adsorption and  reduction of hcxavalent forms  Journal of Environmental Quahty, 12(2), p 177-181, 5 tables, 1983  Jennings, J.N. Prmciples and problems in reconstructing karst history Hehctite, 20(2), p. 37-52, illus.  0ncl sketch maps), 1983  Jones, Glenn A.; and Kaiteris, Peter. A vacuum-gasometnc techmque for rapid and precise analysis of  calcium carbonate in sediments and soils  Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, 53(2), p 655-660, dlus  (incl. 1 table), 1983  Jolge, H.; and TlllRlsamns~ W.  Morphologischund scdimentpetrngraphische Untersuchungan lm  Bervich der Sotemcher und BlankenheJmer Mulde [Morphologic and sedimentologic petrographic  stu&amp;es m the Soetenich Synchne region and Blankenhelm]. Dechemana, 135, p 205-218 (mcl English  sum ), dlus. (incl. 46 anal, 3 tables, sketch map, geol. sketch map, sect ), 1982.  Karstbanesis, A. D.; and HItjek, B. F. Traosformatlon of smectlte to kaolimte in naturally acid soil  systems; structural and thermodynamic considerations- Sod Science Society of America Journal, 47(1),  p 158-163, ]llus (incl 7 tables), 1983_  Karlstrom, Eric T.  Late Quaternary glacial and pedologlcal history, Glacler-Waterton parks,  international boundary area [abstr.].  in Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatic  changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et aL), Am_ Quat Assoc., Natl. Conf, Abstr_, 7, p 112, 1982.  Seventh biennial conference of the American Quaternary Association.  Karter, U. D. Dlstantslonnyye metody poiskov mineral'nykh mestorozhdeniy dokembnya [Remote  sensing applications in Precambnan mineral deposits prospecting]: m Mineral'nyye mestorozhdemya  dokembriya (Sidoranko, A. V., editor; et aL), Problemy Osadochnoy Geologiy Dokembriya = Problems  of the Sedimentary Geology of the Precambrian, 8, p 175-186 (incl. English sum.), 1982  Kotase, Talum. The significance to humificauon of different forms of p-coumaric and feruhc acids in  a pond sediment: Soil Science, 135(3), p 151-155, illus (incl 2 tables), 1983  Kazman, Z.; Sboi~erg, I.; and God, M. Effect of low levels of exchangeable sodium and apphed  phosphogypsum on the inffltrauon rate of various soils: Soil Sclance, 135(3), p. 184-192, lllos. (incl 1  table), 1983.  Kearney, M. S.; stud Lo~ B.H. Postglacial vegetational lustory of Tonqmn Pass, British Columbia  Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences = Journal Canadian des Sciences de la Terre, 20(5), p 776-786 (incl  French sum), dlus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1983  Kesruey, Michel S. Postglacial altitudinal changes m vegetation zones m Jasper National Park, Alberta  [abstr.]: in Abstracts of papers of the 149th National meeting of the American Association of Science  (Herschman, Arthur, editor), AAAS Publication, 83-2, p_ 150, 1983_  Kelley, John A.; end Newton, Darwin L. Soil survey of Carter County, Kentucky- 131 p_, dlus_ 0ncl  17 tables; soils maps 1-20,000; colored sods map 1.126,720), U. S Dep Agric, Sod Conscrv Sere,  Washington, DC, Umted States, 1983 (Publ in coop with Ky Nat. Resour Envaron. Prot. Cabinet; Ky  Agric Exp. Stn).  Keramidgs, V. Z.; and Polyzopoulos, N. A. Phosphorus intensity, quanttty, and capacity factors of  representative Alfisols of Greece. Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p. 232-236, illus (incl.  4 tables), 1983  Killg, Jolkn W.; Haekmunse~der, J.; Bluserjee, S. K.; et aL  The apphcation of palcomagnetlc  measurements to paleoclimatic and palcocnvtronmeatal problems [abetr ]: m Character and timing of  rapid environmental and climatic changes (Maxkgraf, Vera, chairperson; et al), Am. Qua).- Assoc, Natl.  Conf, Abstr., 7, p 115, 1982.  Seventh biennial conference of the American Quaternary Association    261    King, Roger H. Use of tephrochronology in estabhshmg the sequence of Holocene pedogenesls in the  south central Canadian Rockies [abstr ]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic  changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc., Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p 116, 1982  Seventh biennial conference of the American Quaternary Association.  Kompakova, S. G.; Lukashev, K. I.; and Petukhova, N  N.  lod pochvakh 1 torfakh severnoy  geokhimicheskoy provmtsii Belorussit [Iodine m the soils and peats of the northern geochemical province  of Byelorussia]_ Doklady Akademii Nauk BSSR, 26(12), p l 118-1121 (lncl English sum_), illus (mcl  17 anal, 2 tables), 1982  Kornblau, M. L.; and Cipra, J. E. Investigation of digital Landsat data for mapping soils under range  vegetation  Remote Sensing of Envlronrnent, 13(2), p 103-112, tllus (incl 2 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Kruse, E. Gordon; Burdiek, Chuck R.; and Yousef, Yousef A. (editors). Proceedings of the Specialty  conference on environmentally sound water and sod management  July 20-23, 1982, United States 524  p_, illus. (lncl tables, sketch maps), Am_ Soc Clv Eng, New York, NY, United States, 1982  Kuo, S.; Heilman, P. E.; and Baker, A. S. Distribution and forms of copper, zinc, cadmmm, iron, and  manganese in soils near a copper smelter  Sod Science, 135(2), p 101-109, dlus (lncl 6 tables, sketch  map), 1983_  Kussow, W.; EI-Swaify, S. A.; and Mannering, J. (editors). Soil erosion and conservation m the tropics  Aug- 5-10, 1979, United States_ ASA Special Puhhcatlon, 43, 149 p, 1982  Labovitz, M. L.; Masuoka, E. J.; Bell, R.; et al The apphcation of remote sensing to geobotanIcal  exploration for metal sulfides, results from the 1980 field season at Mineral, Virginia  in An issue devoted  to techniques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H_, editor, et al), Economic Geology  and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 750-760, illus (mcl 6 tables), 1983  Lanyon, L. E. Basic cation fractions of contrasting Pennsylvania soils  Communications in Soil Science  and Plant Analysis, 14(6), p 541-551, illus (incl 1 table), 1983  Lee, S. Y.; Dixon, J. B.; and Aba-Husayn, M. M. Mineralogy of Saudi Arabian soils, eastern region  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p_ 321-326, dlus (lncl 2 tables, sketch map), 1983  Lewis, James S. Reservoir rocks of the "Catskill Delta" of northern West Vlrglma, stratlgraphlc basin  analysis emphasizing deposystems: m Proceedings of the Fifty-eighth annual session of the West Vtrginia  Academy of Science (Keller, E C, Jr, editor), Proceedings of the West Virginia Academy of Science,  55(1), p 17-18, 1983  Liegel, Leon H.  Effect of dry-heat sterilization on chemical propertLes of Puerto Rican soils  Communlcatmns in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, 14(4), p 277-286, 3 tables, 1983_  Lukashev, K. I.; and Vadkovskaya, I. K.  Terrttonal'nyye osobennosti mikroelementnogo sostava  drevesnokustarmkovoy rastitel'nosti Belorusskoy SSR [Regional characteristics of the trace element  composition of the woody scrub vegetation of Byelorussla]  Doklady Akademn Nauk BSSR, 26(10), p  925-927 (mcl English sum), dlus (incl_ 10 anal, 1 table), 1982  MacDonald, G.M. Holocene vegetation history of the upper Natla River area, Northwest Territories,  Canada [abstr_]: m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc_, Natl. Conf_, Abstr, 7, p 125, 1982  Seventh biennial conference  of the American Quaternary Association  MacDonald, G. M, Holocene vegetatmn history of the Upper Natla River area, Northwest Territories,  Canada  Arctic and Alpine Research, 15(2), p 169-180, dlus (incl 2 tables, sketch map), 1983  Mack, Richard N. Holocene vegetation history of the Kootenai River drainage, Montana [abstr ]  tn  Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatm changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al.),  Am. Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p  126, 1982  Seventh btenmal conference of the American  Quaternary Association  MaeLean, Kenneth S.; and Langille, Winston M. The extractable trace element content of coarse  textured Annapolis Valley soils and  the influence of pH, organic matter and clay content  CommunlcaUons in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, 14(6), p 463-469, 2 tables, 1983  MacLeod, D.A.;andVita-Finzi, C. Environment and provenance in the development of Recent alluvial  deposits in Epirus, NW Greece  Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(1), p 29-43, illus (incl. 5  tables, sketch map, geol sketch map, sect), 1982.    262    Medsen, D. B.; ~ Kay, P. A. Late Quaternary pollen analysis m the Bonnevdle Basra [abstr ]. ~n  Character and timing of ntpld environmental and climatic changes (Markgntf, Vent, chairperson, et al_),  Am Quat. Assoc., Natl. Conf, Abstr, 7, p  128, 1982.  Seventh bienntal conference of the American  Quaternary Association  M~thaney, W. C. Chronology of glacml and periglaelal deposits, Mount Kenya, East Africa, descnpUon  of type secUons: P~lAeoeeology of Africa and of the Surrounding Islands and Antarctica, 14, p 25-43  dlus (reel 3 tables, sketch map), 1982  Mldaon, D. 12.; and Matl~wes, R. W. Uptake of naturally occurring radioisotopes by vegetation m a  region of high radioactivity: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, 63(2), p 281-290 (incl_ French sum ),  9 tables, 1983  MakslmovL M. F.; and Skmario~lda, Ye. M.  Rhemum m infiltration untmum-coal deposits  International Geology Review, 25(2), p. 189-195, illus 0ncl. 4 tables, sects, stntt cols ), 1983  Maker, J. P. Hehum emanometry and the Andersonviile Fault [abstr.]: m The Georgia Academy ot  Science, slxueth annual meeting (Murray, Malcolm A., president), Georgia Journal of Science, 41 (1-2),  p. 22-23, 1983  Mann, D. H.; and Ugolim, F. C. Glacial geology near Lttuya Bay, South East Alaska [abstr.]:  m  Character and taming of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Marlqgntf, Vers, chairperson, et al.),  Am. Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr., 7, p 129, 1982  Seventh btenmal conference of the Amerfcan  Quaternary Associatton_  Marrett, D. J.; Uilollnl, F. C.; and Stoner, M.G. Arctic soil catena, pedogenesis in relation to vegetation  structure, landscape and community stability [abstr.]: m Character and timing of ntpxd environmental  and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vent, chairperson; et a, Am. Quat. Assoc_, Natl Conf., Abstr, 7, p  131, 1982. Seventh bienntal conference of the American Quaternary Association  Mathur, S. P.; aid I,e~iue, M. P. The effects of using copper for mitigating H,stosol subsidence on  2, The distribution of copper, manganese, zinc, and iron in an organic sod, mineral sublayers, and their  mixtures ,n the context of setting a threshold of phytotoxle soil-copper- Soil Science, 135(3), p 166-  176, 7 tables, 1983  McAndrews, John H. Pollen analysis of the 1973 ice core from Devon Island ice cap, Canada [abstr ]  m Character and timing of ntptd environmental and chmattc changes 0Vlarkgntf, Vent, chairperson, et  al.), Am Quat. Assoc., Natl Conf., Abstr, 7, p 133, 1982_ Seventh btennial conference of the American  Quaternary Association  MeBratney, A. B.; and Webster, R. How many observations are needed for regional est,matlon of soil  properties?. Soil Science, 135(3), p. 177-183, dlus. 0ncl 1 table), 1983.  MeC.arthy, Kevin P.; Been, Jodq Reimar, G. M.; et aHelium and ground temperature surveys at  Steamboat Springs, Colorado- Special Pubfication - Colorado Geological Survey, 21, 11 p., dlus. (incl  1 table, geol. sketch maps), 1982 (Rep No. DOE]ET/28365-21) availablefmm:Colo Geol. Surv., Dep  Nat. Resour., Denver, CO, United States.  McCarthy, Kevlm P.; Zl~lm~ti&amp; Ted G.; mMI P~wl, ~lcl~rd Howard. Geothermal resource assessment  of Hartsel, Colorado: Resource Series - Coloredo Geological Survey, Department of Natttntl Resources,  State of Colorado, 19, 86 p, illus (incl. 20 tables, geol sketch maps), 1982. (Rep. No DOEIET/28365-  19) available from Colo Geol. Surv, Dep. Nat Resour, Denver, CO, United States.  McCarthy, Kevln P.; Zadtarakleb Ted G.; mad Ria~ose, Charles D. Geothermal resource assessment  of the Aromas Valley, Colorado- Resource Sertes- Colorado Geological Survey, Department of Natural  Resources, State of Colorado, 17, 60 p., illus (incl. 9 tables, sects., sketch maps), 1982. (Rep. No,  DOE/ET/28365-18) availablefror, vColo. Geol Sure, Dep Nat Resour., Denver, CO, United States.  McFadden, L. D.; and Headricks, D. M. Temporal changes m the clay mmentlogy of Quaternary  alluvial soils forming in a xeric climate, southern California [abatr.]-  m Character and timing of rapid  environmental and climatic changes (Msrkgntf, Vent, chairperson, et at), Am Quat. Assoc., Natl Conf.,  Abstr, 7, p_ 136, 1982.  Seventh biennial conference of the American Quaternary Associatiort  Mc]Ful, Mlek~i.  Environmental charactenstacs of the Sage Creek Site 48CR3815 [abstr.]:  tn  Abstracts for the Fifty-fourth annual meeung of the Colontdo-Wyormng Academy of Science, The  Journal of the Colorado-Wyoming Academy of Science, 15(1), p. 6, 1983    263    McGowen, J. H.; Granata, G. E.; and Seni, S. J. Depositlonal setting of the Triassic Dockum Group,  Texas Panhandle and eastern New Mexico  m Mesozoic paleogeography of the West-Central United  States (Reynolds, Mitchell W, editor, et al), Rocky Mountain Paleogeography Symposium, 2, p_ 13-38,  lllus (me1 sects, strat cols, sketch maps), 1983  McGreevy, J. P. Hydrothermal alteration and Earth surface rock weathering, a basalt example  Earth  Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(2), p_ 189-195, lllus, 1982_  MeKone, Thomas E. The use of environmental risk analysis for ranking hazardous substances released  to soil or groundwater  m Enwronmental technology, a key to product acceptablhty (Ellerbe, Thomas  R, Jr, chairperson), Proceedings Technical Meeting - Institute of Environmental Sciences, 29, p 380-  384, lllus (mcl 3 tables), 1983  MeManus, J.; and Alizai, S. A. K. Sediment-filled reed stems as contributors to marsh sediment fabrics  Journal of Se&amp;mentary Petrology, 53(2), p 407-409, dlus, 1983  Mehta, S. C.; Poonia, S. R.; and Pal, Raj. Exchange equlhbna of potassium versus calcmm and sodium  in soils from a semiarid region, India" Soil Science, 135(4), p 214-220, dlus (incl 4 tables), 1983  Merida, J.; Corral, L.; and Paneque, G. Morfologm y propiedades qmmlcas de Suelos forestales de  Grazalema, Cadiz, Espana, Ill, Tipovergencla de1 perfil humlco [Morphology and chemical properties  of forested sods m Grazalema, Cadiz Province, Spare; III, Typical variations of the humlc profile]  Anales de Edafologla y Agrobiologla, 41(1-2), p 251-258 (mcl English sum ), illus. (mcl 4 tables), 1982  Mills, Hugh H.  Elevations and weathering intensities of terraces along the New River, Southwest  Virginia [abstr_]- m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmauc changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al.), Am. Quat. Assoc, Natl Conf_, Abstr, 7, p_ 142, 1982  Seventh bwnmal conference  of the American Quaternary Association  Milton, N. M. Use of reflectance spectra of native plant species for interpreting airborne multmpectral  scanner data m the East Tintlc Mountains, Utah  in An issue devoted to techniques and results of remote  sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H_, editor, et al), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of  Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 761-769, dlus (mcl 4 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Milton, N. M.; Collins, William; Chang, Sheng-Huei; et al Remote detection of metal anomahes on  Pilot Mountain, Randolph County, North Carolina  m An issue devoted to techniques and results of  remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F_ H., editor, et al), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society  of Economic Geologists, 78(4), p 605-617, lllus (lncl_ 6 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Minero, Charles J. Deposittonal environments and porosity evolution, El Abra Limestone (Cretaceous),  Mexico [abstr.]  mAAPG annual convention with divisions SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 66(5),  p 6O7, 1982  Minor, Paul E.; and Daws, Keith O. Soil survey of Chnton County, Missouri  112 p, lllus (mcl 17  tables, sods maps 1 24,000, colored soils map 1 190,080), U S_ Dep Agnc, Sod Conserv Serv,  Washington, DC, United States, 1983. (Publ m coop with Mo Agric Exp. Stn)  Miskovsky, J. C. L'envlronnement geologlque de l'Homme de Tautavel (Caune de l'Arago, Pyrenees  Ormentales) [The geologic environment of Tautavel man, Caune de l'Arago, Pyrenees-Orlentales]  Comptes-Rendus des Seances de l'Academie des Sciences, Serie 2. Mecamque-Physique, Chlmle,  Sciences de l'Umvers, Sciences de la Terre, 295(3), p_ 381-384 (mcl English sum.), 1982  Molina, J. A. E.; Clapp, C. E.; Shaffer, M. J.; et al  NCSOIL, a model of nitrogen and carbon  transformations in soil, description, calibration, and behavior  Soil Science Society of America Journal,  47(1), p 85-91, dlus (lncl 2 tables), 1983.  Moody, Ula; Fosberg, Maynard; and Palen, Anita. Soil preparation and chemical properties, a progress  report [abstr ]. m Proceedings of Mount St. Helens, one year later (Keller, S A_ C, e&amp;tor), p 239-240,  East Wash Umv Press, Cheney, WA, United States, 1982  Moore, Peter D.  Snail shells suggest past changes m British chalk vegetation  Nature (London),  299(5886),p 780-781, 1982  Moraghan, J. T.; Rego, T. J.; and Sahrawat, K.L. Effect of water pretreatment on total mtrogen analysis  of soils by the Kjeldahl method  Sol1 Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p_ 213-217, illus (me1  5 tables), 1983.  Morgan, W. T.; and Hail, R. D. Pediments m the North Boulder Rwer basin, southwestern Montana  [abstr.]-  :n Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am- Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p 143, 1982  Seventh bwnmal conference  of the American Quaternary Association    264    Morita, H. Monosaccharides as geochermcal markers in peat. Canadian Journal of Sod Science, 63(2),  p 161-166 (incl. French sum.), 5 tables, 1983.  Morton, John P.; and Long, Leon E. Rb-Sr dating of fllite diagenesis [abstr.]:  m AAPG annual  convention with divisions SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 66(5), p_ 610, 1982_  Mosley, M. Paul. The effect of a New Zealand beech forest canopy on the kinetic energy of water drops  and on surface erosion  Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(2), p. 103-107, illus_, 1982  Mandul, G. Untersuchungen uber die Evapotranspirauon yon Grasland auf Grundwasserstandorten, I_  Mitteilung, Bezlehungen zwlschen meteorologtschen Faktoren und Evapotransplration [Studies on the  evapotranspiration of grasslands from ground water; I, Relationships between meteorologic factors and  evapotransplration] ArchIvfurAcker-undPflanzenbauund Bodenkunde, 26(8),p 507-513, ftlus, 1982.  Mundel, G. Untersuchungen uber die Evapotranspirauon yon Grasland auf Grundwasserstandorten, I1  Mitteftung,  Beziehungen  zwxschen  Bodenfaktoren  und  Evapotranspiration  [Studies  on  the  evapotranspiratton of grasslands from ground water; If, Relationships between soil factors and  evapotranspiration]: Archly fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde, 26(8), p. 515-521, dlus, 1982  Mandul, G. Untersuchungen uber die EvapotranspixatIon yon Grasland auf Grundwaaserstandorten; 3.  Mitteftung,  Bezelhungan  zwischen  Stoffproduktion  und  Evapotransl~rauon  [Stuches  on  the  evapotranspiration of grasslands from ground water; 3, Relationslups between production and  evapotranspirauon]: Archly fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde, 26(10), p. 629-638, fllus,  1982.  Mundel, G. Untersuchungen uber die Evapotranspiration von Grasland auf Grundwasserstandorten; 4_  Mitteilung, Verlauf der Verdunstung wahrend der Vegetationszeit [Studies on the evapotranspiraUon of  grasslands from ground water, 4, Evaporation during vegetation time]:  Archiv fur Acker-und  Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde, 26(10), p_ 639-646, illus, 1982  Muruli, V.; and Aylmure, L. A. G.  Competitive adsorption during solute transport m soils; 1,  Mathematical models  Soil Science, 135(3), p 143-150, 1983.  Muruli, V.; and Aylmore, L. A. G. Competitive adsorption dunng solute transport in softs, 2, SimulaUons  of competitive adsorption: Soil Science, 135(4), p. 203-213, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1983  Mustafa, M. A.; De Jong, R4 Ilame, N. H.; et aL Intermittent infiltration and evaporation from soil  columns  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, 63(2), p 303-314 (incl French sum ), illus (incl 3 tables),  1983.  Nailaraj, T. S.; and Jayadeva, M. S.  CriUcal reappraisal of plasticity index of soils:  Journal of  Geotechnical Engineering, 109(7), p. 994-1000, illus (incl_ 3 tables), 1983  National Assoeiatlon of Comervattoa Districts. Sludge and the land, the role of soil and water  conservation &amp;stricts in land application of sewage sludge:  17 p., 1982. (Rep. No 430/9-82-007)  avadablefrom:U S. Environ. Prot Agency, Washington, DC, United States.  Newman, Deborah E. Postglaclal vegatation history of Mercer Slongh, Lake Washington, King Co., Wa.  [abstr.]   m Character and tuning of rapid environmental and climalac changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al.), Am. Quat Assoc., Natl. Conf., Abstr., 7, p. 147, 1982  Seventh biennial conference  of the American Quaternary Assgczat/on.  Nkedl-Kizza, P.; Bill~tr, J. W.; van Geaaehtea, M. T.; et aL Modeling tritium and chloride 36 transport  through an aggregated Oxisol: Water Resources Research, 19(3), p. 691-700, illus (incl. 5 tables), 1983  O'Connor, G. A.; Euinlton, M. E.; Eh'mhddt, M.; et aNickel and zinc sorptmn m sludge-amended  soils  Soil Science, 135(4), p 228-235, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1983  Oilier, G. 31p.NMR spectra of hun'uc acids; a comparison of four different raw humus types m Norway  Geoderma, 29(3), p 215-219, illus (incl. 1 table), 1983  Parent, L. E.; Aid Pen-on, Y. L'adsorption maximale du cuivre par trois types de tourbe [Maximum  absorption of copper by three types of peat]: Le Naturaliste Canadten, 110(l), p. 67-70 (incl. English  sum.), 1 table, 1983.  Pem'i, ~ Howm-d; Zaciarak~ Ted G4 m~R/mllCO~ C~u, les I~. Geothermal resource assessment  of Hot Sulphur Sprinp, Colorado: Resource Series - Colorado Geological Survey, Department of  Natural Resources, State of Colorado, 23, 50 p., illus. (incl. 11 tables, sketch maps), 1982. (Rep. No  DOE/ET/28365-23) avadable from: Colo. Geol Surv., Dep. Nat. Resour., Denver, CO, United States.    265    Pearl, Richard Howard; Zacharakis, Ted G.; and Ringrose, Charles D. Geothermal resource assessment  of the Steamboat-Routt Hot Springs area, Colorado  Resource Series - Colorado Geological Survey,  Department of Natural Resources, State of Colorado, 22, 86 p_, dlus_ (incl, 20 tables), 1983 (Rep No  DOE/ET/28365-24) avadablefmm Colo- Geol Surv., Dep_ Nat Resour, Denver, CO, Umted States  Peters, Douglas C. Use of airborne multlspectral scanner data to map alteration related to roll-front  uramum migration, m An Issue devoted to techmques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander  F H, e&amp;tor; et al), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Socmty of Economic Geologists, 78(4),  p 641-653, tllus (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), 1983  Peterson, Ivars. Acid lakes and thin smls  Science News (Washington), 123(21), p_ 332-333, dlus,  1983  Petukhova, N. N.; and Shimko, G. A. Formy soyedinemy mikroelementov (Ti, Mn, Cu, Co, V) v  pochvakh [Forms of trace elements TI, Mn. Cu, Co, V in sods]- Doklady Akademn Nauk BSSR, 26(10),  p 928-931 (incl. English sum), illus_ (incl_ 27 anal, 1 table), 1982  Pregitzer, Kurt S.; Barnes, Burton V.; and Lemme, Gary D. Relationship of topography to soils and  vegetation in an upper Mmhlgan ecosystem: Soll Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 117-123,  dlus (lncl 2 tables, sketch map), 1983  Prost, Gary. Mineral exploration with Skylab photography in central Colorado. m An ~ssue devoted  to techniques and results of remote sensing (Goetz, Alexander F H, editor, et al), Economm Geology  and the Bulletin of the Society of Economm Geologists, 78(4), p 633-640, tllus (mcl 1 table, geol_ sketch  map), 1983  Proust, D. Supergene alteratlonofmetamorphlcchloritemanamphlbolite from Masslf Central, France  Clay Minerals, 17(2), p 159-173 (incl. French, German sum), lllus (lncl table). 1982  PufahI, D. E.; Fredlund, D. G.; and Rahardjo, H. Lateral earth pressures m expansive clay soils  Canadian Geotechnical Journal = Revue Canadmnne de Geotechmque, 20(2), p. 228-24l (mcl French  sum), dlus, 1983  Pye, K. Characteristics and significance of some humate-cemented sands (humlcretes) at Cape Flattery,  Queensland, Australia  Geological Magazine, 119(3), p 229-242, lllus (lncl 4 tables, 2 plates, sketch  map, geol sketch map, sect.), 1982  Ragon, Larry G.; Seevers, Vernon C.; Indra, Orville; et al Sod survey of Holt County, Nebraska" 307  p, dlus_ (mcl 20 tables; softs maps 1 20,000; colored soils map 1 253,440), U S Dep Agrlc, Soil  Conserv Serv, Washington, DC, United States, 1983. (Publ in coop with Umv Nebr Conserv Surv  Dlv )_  Rawls, Walter J. Estimating soil hulk density from particle size analysis and organic matter content  Soil Scmnce, 135(2), p 123-125, illus (mcl 1 table), 1983.  Reanier, R. E.; and Ugolini, F. C. Paleoenvlronmental potential of Brooks Range gehfluctton deposits  [abstr_]:  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am Quat_ Assoc, Natl. Conf, Abstr, 7, p 154, 1982  Seventh bwnmal conference  of the Amerwan Quaternary Assoctatton  Reider, Richard G. The soil of Clovis age at the Sheaman archaeological site, eastern Wyoming  Contributions to Geology, 21(2), p 195-200, illus. (mcl 1 table, sketch map), 1982  Reider, Richard G. A sod catena m the Medicine Bow Mountains, Wyoming, U S.A, with reference  to paleoenvlronmental influences  Arctic and Alpine Research, 15(2), p 181-192, illus. (mcl 1 table,  strat, cols., sketch map), 1983  Retallaek, Greg J. A system for naming fossil soils in paleoenvtronmental stu&amp;es [abstr ]  tn Character  and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al.), Am Quat  Assoc., Natl. Conf, Abstr, 7, p  155, 1982  Seventh blenmal conference of the Amertcan Quaternary  Assoctatlon.  Retallack, Greg J. A paleopedologlcal approach to the interpretation of terrestrial sedimentary rocks,  the mid-Tertiary fossil soils of Badlands National Park, South Dakota  Geological Socmty of Amenca  Bulletin, 94(7), p 823-840, lllus (lncl 1 table, sketch maps), 1983  Retallack, Greg J. Late Eocene and Ohgocene Paleosols from Badlands National Park, South Dakota  Special Paper - Geological Society of America, 193, 82 p, lllus (mcl 7 tables, sketch maps), 1983    266    Rich, Fredlek J. Modern wetlands; grades to understanding coal bed deposiUon and morphology  [abstr.]: in Genesls and exploration of metalfic and nonmetallic mineral and ore doposits of Wyoming  and adjacent areas (extended abstracts) (Hausel, W. Dan, editor; et al), Public Information Circular -  Geological Survey of Wyoming, 19, p. 26-3 I, 1983  Joint conference of the GeologicalSurrey of Wyoming,  Wyoming Geological Association, and the University of Wyoming, Department of Geology and Geophysics,"  annual spnng conferenc~  Richardson, J. L; and Lietzke, D.A. Weathenng profiles in fluvial sediments of the middle Coastal  Plain of Virginia Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p. 301-304, illus 0ncl. 3 tables, sketch  map), 1983  Riese, Walter C.; alad Arp, Gerald K. Bingeochemical prospecting in the Stlllwater (Pt) Complex,  Montana, a case study [abstr,]. in Genesis and exploration of metalhc and nonmetallic mineral and ore  deposits of Wyoming and adjacent areas (extended abstracts) (Hausel, W Dan, editor; et aL), Public  Information Circular - Geological Survey of Wyoming, 19, p. 18-19, 1983.  Joint conference of the  Geological Survey of Wyomm~ Wyoming Geological A~ociatwn, and the Umversity of Wyoming, Department  of Geology and Geophysics" annual spring conference  Roberts, KirthelL Soil survey of Upshur and Gregg counties, Texas: 122 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables, soils  maps 1.24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U S. Dep. Agric, Soil Conserv. Scrv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1983. (Publ. in coop with Tex Agric Exp. Sm )_  Robinson, M.; =ml Blytlk, K. The effect of forestry drainage operations on upland sediments yields; a  case study. Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(1), p. 85-90, illus, 1982  Rose, C. W.; ~ter, F. W.; and ~ L Nltrngen-15-1abcled nitrate transport in a soil with  fissured shale substratum: Journal of Env/runmental Quahty, 12(2), p. 249-252, illus. (incl 1 table),  1983.  Ross, D. J. Soils of the Sandy Creek experimental catchment, Stapylton, South-east Queensland  Division of Soils Divisional Report, 59, 32 p, illus. 0ncl_ 18 tables, geol. sketch maps), 1982  Ross, G. J.; Kod~: H.; WmNI~ C.; et al Halloysite from a strongly weathered sod at Mont Jacques  Caruer, Quebec: Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p. 327-332, Illus, 1983  Rott, Donald E. Sod survey of McPherson County, Kansas:  105 p, illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1.253,440), U. S Dep. Agric., Soil Conaerv. Serv, Washington, DC, United  States, 1983. (Publ. in coop. with Kansas Agnc Exp. Sin )_  Rovner, Irwin. Multldlsciphnary sense and nonsense; is a science of phytoliths really necessary? [abstr ]  m Abstracts of papers of the 149th National meeting of the American Associatmn of Science  (Herschman, Arthur, editor), AAAS Publication" 83-2, p 46, 1983  Rowe, R. K.; Lo, K. Y4 a~l IEack, G. J. A method of estimating surface settlement above tunnels  constructed in soft ground: Canadian Geotochnical Journal - Revue Canadienne de Geotechmque,  20(1), p. 11-22 (incl French sum.), illus (incl. 2 tables), 1983.  Rhea, David. A geostatistlcal approach to the trickle irrigation design in heterogeneous soil, 1, Theory'  Water Resources Research, 19(3), p. 632-642, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1983.  Ryan, J. Phosphorus and Its utihzation in soils of dry regions  Geoderma, 29(4), p. 341-354, 1983  Ryan, P. J.; and MeGm.ity, J. W. The nature and spatial variability of soil properOes adjacent to large  forest eucalypts: Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 286-293, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1983.  Rysn, P. J.; and MeGadty, J. W. Procedure for recording spatial variabthty of soil properties along  trench faces. Sod Science Society of Amet-ica Journal, 47(2), p 332-334, illus, 1983.  Sdmet=l, Rllmh~ J.; ~ Joklsm~ W~ C. Pollen and spore stratigraphy of a Mollie hapludaff  (degraded Chernozem) in northeastern Kansas- The Professional Geographer, 35(2), p 183-191, illus  (incl strat, col., sketch maps), 1983  Scltladler, U. Untersuchun4cn zum ka~laren Wasscraufstie8 aus dem Grundwaucr; 2, Mittctlung; Ein  graphisches Veffahren zur Quantifizierun8 de= stationaren kapillmen Wuseraufatings in mehrschichtigen  Boden [Studies on the capillary rise of water from ground water; II, A graphic procedure for quantifying  the stable capillary rise in multi-layered soils]: Archiv fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde,  26(10), p 623-628, illus. (incl chart), 1982.    267    Schmidt, B, L. (chairperson). Determinants of soil loss- Aug 5-10, 1979, United States ASA Special  Publication, 45, 153 p, 1982  Schrader, L. Erlauterungen zur Bodenkarte von Hessen, 1.25000; Blatt 5418 Giessen [Explanatory note  on the Hesse soils map at 1 25,000, Glessen Sheet 5418]- Erlauterung Bodenkarte Hessen 1_25000, 5418,  124 p, lllus (incl. 8 tables, sect, soils map 1 25,000), 1982_  Schramm, William E.; and Nummedal, Dag. Humid alluvial fans [abstr ]  in AAPG annual convention  with dtvmlons SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 66(5), p 627-628, 1982  Schulnm, S. A.; and Harvey, M. D. Natural erosion in the USA_ m Determinants of soil loss (Schmidt,  B L_, chairperson), ASA Special Pubhcatmn, 45, p 15-22, illus (incl 2 tables, sketch map), 1982  Schwab, A. P.; and Lindsay, W. L. Effect of redox on the solubility and avallabihty of iron  Soil Science  Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 201-205, dlus (mcl 2 tables), 1983  Schwab, A. P.; and Lindsay, W. L. The effect of redox on the solubility and availability of manganese  in a Calcareous soil  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 217-220, lllus (lncl 1 table),  1983  Schweich, D.; Sardin, M.; and Gaudet, J. P. Measurement of a cation exchange isotherm from elutlon  curves obtained in a soil column; preliminary results  Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(1),  p 32-37, illus (incl. 3 tables), 1983.  Scott, L. A 5000-year old pollen sequence from spnng deposits in the bushveld at the north of the  Soutpansberg, South Africa  Palaeoecology of Africa and of the Surrounding Islands and Antarctica, 14,  p. 45-55, iUus (mcl sketch map), 1982.  Segal, Donald B. Use of Landsat multispectral scanner data for the definition of hmonitlc exposures  m heavily vegetated areas'  in An issue devoted to techmques and results of remote sensing (Goetz,  Alexander F H, editor, et al_), Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic  Geologists, 78(4), p 711-722, Illus (mcl 1 table), 1983  Severson, R. C.; and Gough, L. P. Chemical composition and variability of soils from the Capps coal  field, Alaska  Open-File Report (Umted States Geological Survey 1978), 39 p, 3 tables, sketch maps,  1983_ (Rep No 83-0190)avadablefrom-U S_ Geol Surv, Open-File Serv Sect, West Dlstrib Branch,  Denver Fed Cent, Lakewood, CO, United States  Shanmuganathan, R. T.; and Oades, J. M. Influence of anmns on dispersion and physical properties  of the A horizon of a Red-brown earth Geoderma, 29(3), p 257-277, illus. (incl 1 anal, 11 tables), 1983  Sherwood-Pike, Martha A. Fungi and fungus-feeding Arthropoda, the decomposer niche [abstr ]  m  Abstracts of papers of the 149th National meeting of the American Assoctatmn of Science (Herschman,  Arthur, editor), AAAS Pubhcation, 83-2, p 39, 1983  Silva Morlel, J. Roberto. Estudtos biogeoqulmicos aphcados en la exploraclon mmera de IMMSA  [Blogeochemical studies apphed to mineral exploration at Industrial Minera Mexico S A ]  Geomlmet,  3(122), p 71-84, illus (mcl sect, sketch map), 1983_  Singh, M.; and Singh, S. P. Effects of zinc and phosphorus on absorption of iron and mtrogen by  submerged paddy. Soil Science, 135(2), p 71-78, lllus (mcl 3 tables), 1983,  Sink, Larry T. Soil survey of Wilson County, North Carolina  112 p, illus (incl 17 tables, soils maps  1 24,000; colored softs map 1 190,080), U S. Dep Agrlc, Sod Conserv Serv_, Washington, DC, United  States, 1983 (Publ mcoop withN C Dep Nat Resour and Comm Dev, N C Agrlc Res Serv;N_C  Agric Ext Serv.; Wilson Cty Board Comm.)  Sklash, Michael G.; and Farvolden, Robert N. The use of enwronmental isotopes m the study of high-  runoff episodes in streams. In Isotope studies of hydrologic processes, selected papers from a symposium  (Perry, Eugene C, Jr, editor, et al), p 65-73, dlus (incl sketch maps), North Ill Unlv Press, De Kalb,  IL, United States, 1982  Smith, M.A. Tentauve guidehnes for acceptable concentratmns of contaminants In soils [abstr ]  rathe  hazards of contaminated land, report of a discussion meeting (Beckett, M J_; et al), Journal of the  Geological Society of London, 139, Part 1, p 101-102, 1982  Smith, Roger E. Approximate soil water movement by kinematic characteristics: Soil Science Society  of America Journal, 47(1), p 3-8, dlus_, 1983    268    Smith, Roller E, Unsaturated sod water flow  m U S. national report to IUGG 1979-1982 (James,  Dawd E, editor), Reviews of Geophysms and Space Physics, 21(3), p 755-760, 1983  Sokolova, T. N,; gm-lakov, V. A.; and ~ov, N. P.  Spetslfika autigennogo sihkatnego  mineraloobrazovaniya na vysoklkh stndiynkh osoloneniya (kupol Inder, Privolzhskaya monoklinal')  [Specifics of authigenic silicate mineral formation at high levels of salt accumulation, the lnder Cupola,  Volga region monocline]: in Novyye dannyye po geologii, gkhlmd, podzemnym vodam t poleznym  iskopayemym solenosnykh has~ynov (Yanshirt, A. L., editor; eta/.), p 101-111, dlus., lzd. Nauka, Sib.  Otd., Novosibtrsk, USSR,  1982.  1I Vsesoyuznoye solevoye soveshchamye; Solenosnyye formatstt t  prakticheskoye znachemye tkh tzuchemya~  Solomon, Allen M. Plant community response to decreased seasonality dunng full-glacial tame [abstr ]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et  al.), Am Quat. Assoc., Natl. Conf., Abstr, 7, p. 18, 1982  Seventh bienntal conference of the Amerwan  Quaternary Association  Spauiding, W. Geollrey. ProcessesandratesofvegetataonchangemthearidWest[abstr.]. mCharacter  and tlrmng of rapid environmental and climatac changes (Markgraf, Vera, chaarperson; et al), Am_ Quat  Assoc., Natl. Conf, Abstr, 7, p. 22-24, 1982  Seventh btenmal conference of the American Quaternary  Assoctattott  Sposito, Garrison; Holtzclaw, Kenneth M.; C'narlet, Lsurent; et al  Sodmm-calcmm and sodium-  magnesium exchange on Wyoming bentonite m perchlorate and chlonde background mine media  Soft  Science Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 51-56, dlus (inel 7 tables), 1983.  Spyeher, Gody; Solll~, Phflllp; and Rose, Sharon. Carbon and nitrogen m the hght fraclaon of a forest  soil; vertical distribution and seasonal patterns. Sod Scmnce, 135(2), p 79-87, illus. (incl 3 tables), 1983.  Stein, Jean; lead Kane, Douslm L. Momtonng the unfrozen water content of sod using tame domain  reflectometry [abstr.]: m Americetla Geophysical Umon 29th Pacific Northwest regmnal meeting and  Alaska Scmnce Conference (AAAS) 33rd meeting, Eos, Transactmns, American Geophysical Umon,  64(9), p 88, 1983.  Sternbel'8, Leonel; and DeNlro, Mlehllel J. Isotopic composition of cellulose from C3, C4, and CAM  plants growing near one another. Science, 220(4600), p. 947-949, illus. 0ncl. 1 table), 1983  Stevenson, F. J. Humus chemsstry, genesis, composition, reactions. 443 p., illus. (reel tables), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, NY, United States, 1982. (A Wiley-interscienee pubhcataon)  Stevenson, F. J. IsolaUon and ldenttficataon of amino sugars in soil  Soil Science Socmty of America  Journal, 47(1), p 61-65, illus. (incl 1 table), 1983  Stoner, M. G.; Ugollml, F. C.; and Mm'rett, D.J. Current pedogemc processes m Arctic Alaska [abstr.]  m Character and tuning of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; et  a/), Am. Quat Assoc., Natl. Conf., Abstr., 7, p 164, 1982_ Seventh bwnnial conference of the American  Quaternary Assoctatton.  Stoyko, S. M.; Tretyah, P. R.; Komsristyy, A. A.; etal Novyye darmyye o pnrodnoy ritmike ekoslstem  v verldaov'ye reki Prut (Ukrainskiye Karpaty) v pozdnem golotsene [New data on the natural rhythm  of ecosystems in the region of the upper course of the Prut River (Ukrainian Carpathmns) in the upper  Holocene]: Ekologiya, 1982(1), p. 14-18, illus (incl. 3 anal, I table), 1982.  Succow, M.; and Lieberoth, I. Flachenumfang und regtonale Dtfferenzaerung der Ntedermoorstandorte  in der DDR auf der Grundlage der Mittelma~tabigen Landwirtschaftlichen Standortkartierung  [Exteosmn at surface and regional differentmtion of low peat localities in East Germany from cartography  at freddie scale of agricultural environments]: Arehiv fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde,  26(6), p. 369-376, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1982.  Summer, Rebeces M. Fmld and laboratory studies on alpine soil erodibihty, southern Rocky Mountains,  Colorado. Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 7(3), p 253-266, illus (incl. 5 tables, sketch map),  1982  Svobodn, Joeef. Due to the Little Ice Age climatic impact most of the vegetatave cover m the Canadian  High Arctic is of a recent origin; a hypothesis [almtr.]:  m Science in the North (Alexander, Vera,  president), Proceedings - Alaska Scmnce Conference, 33, p 206, 1982   Thin'y-third Alaska science  co~ feFE'ffCe.    269    Tabatabai, M. A.; and Dick, W. A.  Simultaneous determination of nitrate, chloride, sulfate, and  phosphate in natural waters by 1on chromatography  Journal of Environmental Quahty, 12(2), p 209-  213, dlus (mcl 1 table), 1983  Taylor, F.C. Reconnaissance geology of a part of the Canadian Shield, northern Quebec and Northwest  Temtories  Memoir - Geological Survey of Canada, 399, 32 p- (lncl French sum), lllos (incl sketch  map, colored geol maps I 250,000), 1982  Thirriot, C. L'infiltratIon dans les sols vue atravers l'lmage des modeles capillaires [Infiltration in sods  observed from capillary model images]  Eau du Quebec, 15(2), p_ 124-130, dlus, 1982.  Thompson, Robert S.; and VanDevender, Thomas R. Late Pleistocene vegetational records from desert  grassland m the Santa Catalina Mountains, Arizona [abstr ]-  m Character and timing of rapid  environmental and chmatic changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson, et al), Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf,  Abstr, 7, p 167, 1982  Seventh btenmal conference of the American Quaternary Assoczatlon  Thorsen, Gerald W. West Beach salt, a late Pleistocene loess, central Puget Lowland, Washington  Washington Geologm Newsletter, 11(2), p 1-4, dlus_, 1983  Tippkotter, R. Morphology, spatial arrangement and origin of macropores in some Hapludalfs, West  Germany: Geoderma, 29(4), p 355-371, illus., 1983  Torrent, G.; Dejou, J.; Manier, M.; et al Presence d'lmogohte dans la composition mIneraloglque des  fractions fines extraltes des croutes d'alteratIon observees sur le basalte de Roudadou, pres d'Aurlllac,  Cantal [Presence of lmogohte m the maneralogIc composition of the fine fractions extracted from  weathering crusts observed on the Roudadou Basalt, near Aurillac, Cantal]  Clay Minerals, 17(2), p 185-  194 (Incl English, German sum_), illus, 1982  Tsukada, Matsuo; and Sugita, Shinya. Coniferous forests during the last maximum glacml period m  Japan [abstr ]  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatlc changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chmrperson; et al), Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr_, 7, p 168, sketch map, 1982  Seventh btenmal  conference of the Amerwan Quaternary Association  Twiss, Page C. Morphology of opal phytohths m C3 and C4 grasses [abstr ]  in Abstracts of papers of  the 149th National meeting of the American Association of Science (Herschman, Arthur, editor), AAAS  Publication, 83-2, p 44, 1983  Ugolini, F. C.; and Sletten, R.S. A study of soil development of newly perturbed sites on Mt St Helens  [abstr_]:  m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatlc changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson, et al), Am_ Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p_ 169, 1982  Seventh bmnntal conference  of the American Quaternary Association  Van Devender, Thomas R. Rates of Late Quaternary vegetation changes in the Southwest [abstr ]  tn  Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf. Vera, chairperson, et al),  Am Quat Assoc, Natl Conf, Abstr, 7, p 26-27, 1982  Seventh bwnnial conference of the American  Quaternary Association  Vauelin, M.; Vieira, S. R.; Vachaud, G.; et al. The use of cokrlging with limited field sod observations  Soil Science Society of Amenca Journal, 47(2), p 175-184, illus (mcl 6 tables, maps), 1983  Vepraskas, M. J.; and Wildlng, L. P. AquIc moisture regimes m sods with and without low chroma  colors. Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 280-285, illus (Incl 4 tables), 1983_  Vepraskas, M. J.; and Wilding, L. P. Deeply weathered soils in the Texas Coastal Plato  Sod Scmnce  Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 293-300, lllus (mcl 5 tables, sketch map), 1983  Viani, B. E.; AI-Mashhady, A. S.; and Dixon, J. B. Mineralogy of Saudi Arabmn soils, central alluwal  basins  Soil Scmnce Society of America Journal, 47(1), p 149-157, illus_ (incl 4 tables, sketch map),  1983  Violante, P.; and Wilson, M.J. Mineralogy of some Italian Andosols with specml reference to the origin  of the clay fractmn  Geoderma, 29(2), p 157-174, illus (lncl 6 tables), 1983  Wall, G. J.; Dickinson, W. T.; and Greuel, J. W  Rainfall erosion indices for Canada east of the Rocky  Mountains  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, 63(2), p_ 271-280 (mcl French sum ), illus (mcl 3 tables,  sketch maps), 1983  Wang, C.; Ross, G. J.; Gray, J. T.; et al Mineralogy and genesis of saprohte and strongly weathered  soils in the Appalachian region of Canada  Maritime Sediments and Atlantm Geology, 18(3), p 130-  138 (mcl French sum), lllus (incl 1 table, sketch map), 1982    270    Win'd, Larry B. Sml survey of Stone County, Arkansas: 152 p., lllus 0ncl. 23 tables, sods maps 1:20,000,  colored soils map 1'.253,440), U. S. Dep. Agrie., Soil Conserv. Sen'., Washington, DC, United States.  1983 (Publ in coop with U S. Dep Agnc, For Sen', Arkansas Agric Exp Sin)  Waring, S. A.; ad Gilliam, J. W. The effect of acidity on nitrate reduction and denitrificatlon in lower  Coastal Plain sods Soil Science Society of America Journal, 47(2), p 246-250, illus (incl 4 tables),  1983  Warren, H. V.; Towers, G. H. N.; Horsky, S. J.; et al Mineral Indications along the Pmchl Fault  Western Miner (Vancouver), 56(6), p 25-28, 30, illus. (incl sketch map), 1983  Watts, W. A. Response of biotic populations to rapid environmental and chmatic changes [abstr ]. m  Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatac changes (Markgraf, Vera, chairperson; eta/.),  Am. Quat. Assoc_, Natl. Conf_, Abstr., 7, p 19-21, 1982  Seventh biennial conference of the American  Quaternary Assoclat~on  Wells, Stephen G.; Bulim'd, 111omas F.; ud Gardner, Thomas W. Chronology, rates, and magmtudes  of Holocene landscape changes m the southeastern Colorado Plateau; implications for paleoclimatic  changes [abstr.]  in Character and timing of rapid environmental and climatic changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chmrperson; et at), Am. Quat. Assoc, Natl. Conf., Abstr, 7, p 178, illus., 1982  Seventh blenmal  conference of the American Quaternary Association  West, Terry g.; ud Warder, David L. Geology of Indianapolis, Indiana, United States of America:  Bulletin of the Association of Engineering Geologists, 20(2), p. 105-124, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch maps),  1983  Wh/pple, W~. Erosion and stormwater  m Stormwater management m urbanizing areas (Whipple,  William, et at), p 123-133, Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ, United States, 1983.  WUdh, D, L. P.; and Drees, L. R. Factors affecting bmgenic opal stabdity in soils and geologLc deposits  [abstr.] in Abstracts of papers of the 149th National meeting of the American Association of Science  (Herschman, Arthur, editor), AAAS Publication, 83-2, p. 45, 1983  Wilitsms, J.H. Metalcontamination;agriculturallmpIicat~ons[abstr.]: m The hazards of contaminated  land, report of a discussion meeting (Beckett, M. J., et aL), Journal of the Geological Society of London,  139, Part 1, p. 102, 1982  Wfltsh/re, R. J.  Solution of the heat conductmn equation m a non-uniform soil  Earth Surfaces  Processes and Landforms, 7(3), p 241-252, 1982  Woods, K. D.; and Davis, Marg~et B. Sensltavity of Michigan pollen dmgrams to Little Ice Age climatic  change [abstr.]. m Character and timing of rapid environmental and chmatlc changes (Markgraf, Vera,  chairperson; et at), Am Quat. Assoc, Natl Con/:, Abstr, 7, p 181, 1982. Seventh &amp;enmalconference  of the Amerwan Quaternary Association  Wright, V. Paul. Paleokarsts at unconformmes [abstr.]  m AAPG annual convention w~th divisions  SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 66(5), p. 645, 1982  Yong, R. N.; and Tug, K. Y.  Soil remolding and sensitivity measurements.  ASTM Geotechnlcal  Testing Journal, 6(2), p. 73-80, illus. (mcl 3 tables), 1983  Zachar, Dnsaa. Soil erosion-  547 p, illus. (incl. table, geol. sketch map), Elsevier ScL Publ Co,  Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1982.  ~s, Ted G.; Purl, R/cimrd Howard; and Ri~p-o0e, Cluu-les D. Geothermal resource assessment  of Ranger Warm Spring, Colorado"  Resource Series - Colorado Geolngical Survey, Department of  Natural Resources, State of Colorado, 24, 65 p, illus (mcl 16 tables, sketch maps), 1983. (Rep. No  DOE/ET/28365-26) available from Coin Geol_ Sure, Dep_ Nat. Resour., Denver, CO, Umted States  Z.au:/uw~t~, Ted G.; Pearl, ~ Howm-d; mul gi~groN, Charles D. Geothermal resource assessment  of western San Luis Valley, Colorado: Resource Series - Colorado Geological Survey, Department of  Natural Resources, State of Colorado, 19, 71 p., illus (incl. 13 tables, geol. sketch maps), 1983. (Rep.  No. DOE/ET/28365-25) available from: Colo. Geol Sun,, Dep Nat. Resour, Denver, CO, Umted  States  Zeitz, J.; Tltze, E.; mad Wertz, G. Gefugemelioration und Dranung auf Tieflehm-Staugleyen im Norden  der DDR [Amelioration of structure and drainage of retention gleys on the thick loam of northern East  Germany]  Archly fur Acker-und Pflanzenbau und Bodenkunde, 26(9), p. 561-570, illus. (incl 10 anal,  2 tables, chart), 1982    271    Zhu Xianmo; Li Yushan; Peng Xianglin; et aL Sods of the loess region in China  Geoderma, 29(3), p  237-255, lllus (mcl 3 tables, sketch maps), 1983  Ziehen, W. Die Geburt der blldhchen Darstellung des geologisch-bodenkundlichen Profils mder 2  Halfte des 18 Jahrhunderts [The birth of schematic representation of the geologic-pedologlc profile m  the second half of the 18th century]  Der Aufschluss, 33(10), p 389-393, illus (mcl sect), 1982  Zielinski, Gary W.; and Bruehhausen, Peter i. Shallow thermal anomaly over San Sebastian oil and  gas  field,  eastern  Tierra  del  Fuego  [abstr_]   :n AAPG  annual  convention  with  divisions  SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 66(5), p 646, 1982                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            