 Geoderma, 28 (1982) 53--56                                                     53  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Short Communication    A SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPIC STUDY OF EFFECTS OF  ADDING NEUTRAL ELECTROLYTES TO SOLUTIONS OF HUMIC  SUBSTANCES*    KUNAL GHOSH and M. SCHNITZER  Department of Agricultural Chemistry and Soil Science, University of Calcutta,  Calcutta (India)  Chemistry and Biology Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, Ont. KIA 0C6  (Canada)  (Received August 21, 1981; accepted February 3, 1982)    ABSTRACT  Ghosh, K. and Schnitzer, M., 1982. A scanning electron microscopic study of effects of  adding neutral electrolytes to solutions of humic substances. Geoderma, 28: 53--56.  Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) was used to observe effects of adding increasing  concentrations of neutral salts on the shapes and sizes of humic acid (HA) and fulvic acid  (FA) particles. The SEM micrographs showed gradual decreases in particle orientation as  well as increases in fiber thicknesses as the neutral salt concentration was increased.    INTRODUCTION    Data obtained recently by the authors from surface pressure and viscosity  measurements (Ghosh and Schnitzer, !980) as well as from UV and visible  absorption studies (Ghosh and Schnitzer, 1979) showed that at pH 6.5, HA  and FA particles were fully uncoiled, that is, linear when dissolved in 0.001 M  NaC1. As the salt concentration was increased, the particles or molecules  began to coil. Thus, in 0.1 M NaC1, the molecules were completely coiled  to form condensed structures. The purpose of this study was to provide  visual evidence of the effects of adding increasing electrolyte concentrations  on the configuration of humic substances. While attempts have been made  earlier (Flaig and Beutelspacher, 1954; Schnitzer and Kodama, 1975; Chen  and Schnitzer, 1976) to elucidate effects of pH on the parameters mentioned  above, no SEM investigation on effects of neutral salts has, to our knowledge,  so far been undertaken. The objective of this communication is to report  on such effects.    *Contribution No. 1294    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 Elsevier Scientific.PublishingCompany    54    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The two humic substances used in this investigation were a FA extracted  from the Bh horizon (15--22 cm; 4.2% organic C; 0.1% total N; pH = 4.0,  soil:water 1:2.5) of the Armadale soft, a Spodosol in Prince Edward Island,  Canada, and a HA extracted from the Ah horizon (0--25 cm; 6.1% organic  C; 0.5% total N; pH = 6.4, soil: water 1: 2.5) of Beaverhills soil, a Mollisol  in Central Alberta, Canada. The methods used for the extraction, fractiona-  tion and purification of FA and HA as well as their elemental and functional  group analyses were the same as those described by Griffith and Schnitzer  {1975). Specimens for SEM were prepared by spotting one drop of 1%  (w/v) solutions of FA or HA in NaC1 solutions of different initial molarities  (0.001--0.100 M) and adjusted to pH 6.5 with dilute NaOH, on a glass slide,  10 mm in diameter. The specimen slide was rapidly immersed in liquid  Freon 22 at --155, held in a stainless-steel cup submerged in liquid nitrogen  in a Dewar flask. After freezing, the specimen was transferred to a Speedivac  Pearse tissue dryer (Model 1) placed on a cold stage maintained at --80,  and freeze-dried. The dry specimen was then attached to an aluminum stub  with the aid of colloidal silver paint and coated in a Speedivac coating unit  {model 21 E6/1258), first with a thin layer of carbon and then with a layer  of gold (Chen and Schnitzer, 1976). The prepared specimen was examined  with the help of a Cambridge Instruments Stereoscan Mark 2A SEM, oper-  ating at 20 kV. We used quick freezing and freeze-drying for preparing our  samples because these techniques avoid structural deformations and the  formation of artefacts (Boyde and Wood, 1969).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    As SEM observations showed no significant differences between effects  of 0.001 M and 0.005 M NaCI on one hand, and between 0.050 M and  0.100 M NaCl on the other hand, we are presenting typical SEM micrographs  of both FA and HA dissolved in 0.001 M, 0.010 M and 0.100 M NaC1 only  (Fig. 1). Micrographs A, B and C as well as D, E and F show that both FA  and HA were similarly affected by neutral electrolytes. Micrographs A and  D present FA and HA dissolved in 0.001 M NaC1, respectively. The pH was  6.5, which was always maintained in the solutions spotted, and at which  the dissociation of the oxygen-containing functional groups in humic mate-  rials is thought to be complete (Schnitzer, 1978). Because 0.001 M NaC1  has little effect on the dissociation of humic molecules, it is electrostatic  repulsion between HA and FA molecules that appears to disperse these  materials into fine particles. In micrographs A and D we observe the follow-  ing: (a) the fibers are thin because the particles are small; (b) a high degree  of orientation, resulting from electrostatic repulsion of the particles; and (c)  with HA only (micrographs D and especially F), the formation of relatively  massive structures and a tendency to form films resulting from the coalescence    55    Fig. 1. SE micrographs: (A) FA in 0.001 M NaC1; (B) FA in 0.010 M NaC1; (C) FA in  0.100 M NaC1; (D) HA in 0.001 M NaC1; (E) HA in 0.010 M NaC1; (F) HA in 0.100 M  NaCI.    56    of fibers during drying (Chen et al., 1976), but the thicknesses of individual  fibers are comparable to those in micrograph A. As the neutral salt concen-  tration was increased, the electrostatic repulsion between the particles men-  tioned above was suppressed more and more, so that the degree of orienta-  tion decreased. With FA and HA dissolved in 0.010 M NaC1 (micrographs  B and E), the thickness of the fibers remained unchanged but their orienta-  tion became more random. With a further increase in the neutral salt concen-  tration to 0.100 M (micrographs C and F) the orientation became more  random, but the most notable feature was an increase in fiber thickness.  Random orientation and low electrostatic repulsion contribute to the forma-  tion of large irregular structures when aqueous solutions of FA and HA are  dried (Chen et al., 1976}, and this is what we observed with our samples.  In general, our observations are in harmony with observations made by  earlier workers (Chen and Schnitzer, 1976). Essentially, effects of increas-  ing the neutral electrolyte concentration on the configuration of humic  materials are similar to those observed when the pH is decreased from neu-  trality to the moderately acidic region. This is in line with expectations  because both the hydrogen ion and the neutral electrolyte concentration  affect the dissociation and configuration of humic molecules in a similar  manner.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We thank S. Itz and E. Bond for valuable technical help during this in-  vestigation.    REFERENCES    Boyde, A. and Wood, C., 1969. Preparation of animal tissues for surface-scanning electron  microscopy. J. of Micros., 90: 241--249.  Chen, Y. and Schnitzer, M., 1976. Scanning electron microscopy of a humic acid and of  a fulvic acid and its metal and clay complexes. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 682--686.  Chen, Y., Banin, A. and Schnitzer, M., 1976. Use of the scanning electron microscope  for structural studies on soils and soil components. In: Scanning Electron Microscopy,  Part III. Proceedings of the Workshop on Techniques for Particulate Matter Studies  in SEM, Chicago, Illinois, pp. 425--432.  Flaig, W. and Beutelspacher, H., 1954. Physikalische Chemie der Huminsauren. Land-  bouwkd., Tijdschr., 66: 306--336.  Ghosh, K. and Schnitzer, M., 1979. UV and visible absorption spectroscopic investigation  in relation to macromolecular characteristics of humic substances. J. Soil Sci., 30:  735--745.  Ghosh, K. and Schnitzel M., 1980. Macromolecular structures of humic substances. Soil  Sci., 129: 266--276.  Griffith, S.M. and Schnitzel M., 1975. Analytical characteristics of humic and fulvic  acids extracted from tropical volcanic soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 861--867.  Schnitzer, M., 1978. Humic substances: chemistry and reactions. In: M. Schnitzer and  S.U. Khan (Editors), Soil Organic Matter. Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 1--64.  Schnitzer, M. and Kodama, H., 1975. An electron microscopic examination of fulvic  acid. Geoderma, 13: 279--287.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractScanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) was used to observe effects of adding increasing concentrations of neutral salts on the shapes and sizes of humic acid (HA) and fulvic acid (FA) particles. The SEM micrographs showed gradual decreases in particle orientation as well as increases in fiber thicknesses as the neutral salt concentration was increased. 