 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 241--255                                                  241  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    AEOLIAN DEPOSITION AND SOIL PARENT MATERIALS IN NORTHERN  NIGERIA    J.G. BENNETT  Land Resources Development Centre, Overseas Development Administration, Surbiton  (Great Britain)  (Received June 21, 1978; accepted December 3, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Bennett, J.G,, 1980. Aeolian Deposition and soil parent materials in northern Nigeria.  Geoderma: 24: 241--255.    The introduction considers the nature of the problem of "drift" soils in northern  Nigeria. The physical environment of the survey area is described briefly and the percen-  tages of silt, very fine sand and fine sand occurring in the soils are mapped. Textural belts  are identified and the profile distribution frequencies within the belts are tabulated. Parent  material origins are discussed and attempts are made to reconcile the apparently aeolian  nature of the soil materials, in terms of the particle-size distribution pattern, with the  various soil profile morphologies of today.    INTRODUCTION    The Land Resources Development Centre of the Overseas Development  Administration of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office recently com-  pleted a land resources appraisal of an area in central northern Nigeria. This  paper is concerned with the northernmost part of that area shown on the  location map (Fig. 1).  The subject of aeolian deposition, or "drift" as it is widely and loosely  termed in Nigeria, is controversial. Although the presence of wind-blown  material in northern Nigeria has been generally accepted, there has been no  attempt to define the properties, range and distribution of the material in  the present area. Falconer (1911) used the term "drift" in the geological  sense of any superficial deposit while emphasising the importance of water  movement. More recently, workers from the Institute for Agricultural Re-  search at Samaru have referred to any supposed wind-blown deposit as  "drift" or "aeolian drift" (Tomlinson, 1961; Higgins, 1963; Klinkenberg and  Higgins, 1968). Vine (1953) referred to a northerly group of soils formed from  "wind-sorted desert sands which accumulated in a geologically recent period  when the Sahara desert encroached hundreds of miles south of its present  limit". He also referred to "silty fine sands of the Zaria group of soils". Lawes    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$ 02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    242       SOKOTO        x ~               ~ +  + x ::::::::::::::::::::::: .        / ~ ,,                              '   :: ill!! ~:~ -  +                     :: CdX,~g:                                  ~+       ~ t-          f       KAOUNA       kl4                                      ]~  BENIN                                                                                             /~  ~                      t              -\                                *  ~,         x  a       MrNNA    ABOJA        /                                   CAMEROON  -- --   LAGOS ~  k    !            I        ENLGU               \          /~"    :          / \               +   :: ::::                   ,,- _            ./,  : ::             t  :          \     ~   :,;: ;to:~:aB: U R d a r y                            ,  ............  BouRdary   + + +   :                           State Boundary _    Fig. 1. Location map.    (1962) regarded these latter as being derived from loess and referred to "the  loess plains of northern Nigeria". Sombroek and Zonneveld (1971), working  to the west of the present area, recognised different dune forms and deter-  mined their separate origins. They also termed finer textured material, occurr-  ing further south, "Funtua loess" thus supporting Vine's primary separation.  Sand dunes form a ready means of identifying aeolian deposition but they  are largely absent from the area of the present survey, with the exception of  a few degraded linear forms in the north and the occurrence of the western  extremity of the ancient erg of Hausaland (Grove, 1958) along the eastern  edge. The use of land forms as a means of rapid identification of aeolian depo-  sition by workers to the east and west is therefore largely excluded and soil  profile characteristics alone remained for consideration by the survey team  when assessing the influence of aeolian deposition on the soils of most of the  area.  The team entered the area from the south and were alerted to changes  occurring in the parent materials of the soils by the increasing silt content.  Subsequently, there was a tendency to regard morphologically distinct upper  horizons as aeolian in conformity with the generally accepted view of the  soils. This was, however, irreconcilable with the wide variety of profile forms  encountered and their relative distributions.    243    Profile characteristics, therefore, having proved largely inadequate to the  task, this paper attempts to show the extent and form of aeolian influence  by mapping the distribution of particle-size classes of comparable horizons  of the soils, irrespective of profile morphology or geomorphic position of  the site.    THE PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT    The area is situated within the northern Guinea and Sudan vegetation zones  (Keay, 1949).  Rainfall ranges from 1200 mm in the south to less than 650 mm in the  north and falls within a single season extending from May/June to September.  The highest 10-day mean daily maximum temperature of 40 occurs in the  north during April and the lowest, 27, in the south in August. The highest  10-day mean daily minimum of 25 occurs in the north during May and the  lowest, 12, also in the north during January (Kowal and Knabe, 1972). The  prevailing wind during the dry season, known locally as the Harmattan, is  from the northeast and often carries dust. (Kalu, 1979).  The terrain consists of gently undulating plains which rise gradually towards  the south and west. The geomorphology, according to King (1967), relates to  the early Tertiary "African" surface in the south and west and to the later  "post-African" surface in the lower regions. Ironpan-capped mesas are associa-  ted with the higher areas. The plains are underlain by Basement Complex  granites, gneisses, migmatites and schists (McCurry, 1976). Cretaceous sedi-  ments occur in the far north (Du Preez, 1958) and Pleistocene lacustrine sedi-  ments on the extreme eastern fringe of the area (Grove, 1958). Isolated  Jurassic granite hills occur in the south.  The soils are varied and the pattern of distribution can be complex. Except  for relatively minor features of prominence such as valley bottoms, relict sand  dunes, ironstone-capped mesas and granite hills, landform correlates poorly  with soils. Soils per se were not mapped by the survey on which this paper is  based. Considered from a regional viewpoint, however, certain soil charac-  teristics are widespread and others exhibit regional trends.  (1) A coarse-textured surface horizon is ubiquitous. It may be due to the  coarse texture of the parent material in the north, but is more often related  to clay removal in the south.  (2) Secondary pedogenic ironstone occurs widely in various forms, at various  depths, with various thicknesses and with little predictability. Quartz gravel  is also widespread.  (3) Chemical weathering and pedogenesis increase Southwards, with clay  translocation and iron segregation leading t~ greater horizon differentiation.  Clay illuviation north of Kano is mostly manifested by clay lamellae.  (4) P.lanosols and related profile forms, often sodium-affected, occur local-  ly in the central part of the area.  Many of the soils are therefore pedogenetically well developed and although    244    pronounced discontinuities occur in several forms, they are not always -- and  indeed are often clearly not -- directly related to aeolian deposition. A blanket  surface deposit of aeolian material of uniform properties such as occurs on  the Jos Plateau to the south (Macload et al. 1971) does not occur here.  Examples are given below of profiles of a Cambic Arenosol from the north  and a Ferric Luvisol, representing a typical plains soil in the south. Description  is based on the FAO Guidelines for Soil Description but horizon designations  are from FAO-UNESCO (1974).    Cambic Arenosol    0--12 cm   Aul  12--33 cm   Au2    33--80 cm   Bwl    80--153 cm  Bul  153 cm +     2ms    1OYR 4/4 (moist); sand; single grain; loose.  1OYR 4/4 (moist); loamy sand; single grain to  massive, slightly hard; less than 5% subrounded  ironstone concretions.  5YR 5/6 (moist); loamy sand; single grain to mas-  sive; hard; less than 5% subrounded ironstone con-  cretions.  7.5YR 5/6 (moist); fine sandy loam; weak, coarse,  subangular blocky; very hard.  continuous vesicular indurated ironstone or ironpan.    Perric Luvisol    0--12 cm   A1  12--28 cm   2Abl  28--63 cm   2Btsl    63--104 cm  2Bts2    104--124 cm  2Bsl    1OYR 4/3 (moist); sandy loam; very weak, medium,  subangular blocky; soft.  1OYR 4/2 (moist); sandy loam; massive; hard; less  than 5% subrounded ironstone concretions.  1OYR 5/6 (moist), 15% 2.5YR 4/6 mottles; clay  loam; weak, medium, subangular blocky; slightly  hard; less than 5% angular quartz gravel, less than  5% subrounded ironstone concretions; weak thin  clay skins.  1OYR 5/4 (moist), 20% 2.5YR 4/6 mottles, 5%  7.5YR 5/6 mottles; clay loam; very weak, coarse,  subangular blocky; very hard; weak thin clayskins.  1OYR 5/4 (moist); 15% 2.5YR 4/6 mottles, 10%  7.5YR 5/6 mottles; clay loam; weak, coarse, sub-  angular blocky; very hard.    DATA COLLECTION AND ANALYSIS    The soil survey was carried out by sampling sites, selected with the aid of  air photographs, within upland (i.e., non-valley bottom) facets of land systems  (Brink et al., 1966).    245    Samples from the natural horizons of over 500 profiles were analysed by  the Tropical Soils Analysis Unit of the Land Resources Development Centre  to assist with the characterisation and classification of the soils. Organic  matter was first removed by hydrogen peroxide digestion. Dispersion was  by vibration in an ultrasonic cleaning tank for 15 min with continuous stirr-  ing using Calgon (sodium hexametaphosphate and sodium carbonate) as dis-  persing agent. The 4~-1 tank accomodated eight samples simultaneously, each  sample consisting of 10 g of soil in 200 ml. Vibration frequency was 25 kHz at  7                                            8"                                             9"  I                                     I    13" -    12"    il6              *    ~ Zaria  ',    "I  ,,   :*    O I    :J     t " 2  ,                     *  *  &gt; = "  o,  o           SCALE  1" ~ 108kin     ~o    r  t    ,0oK~    o--9%  10--19%         20-- 29 %  ,       30-- 39 %  40--49%  50--59%  c~       60-- 69 %  Textural Belt  3  Fig. 2. Soil sample sites. Fine sand % (100--200 urn) in the surface horizon.    246    7"    13"    12"    8"  I    9"  I    " t,  !    SCALE  I" ~ 108km    -y  ao  o      '       o   ~--~        .  .a  ~, %                /s  o                                             5  2      5            E                                        |  t  f    0--9%  10--19%         20 -- 29 %  .        30-- 39 %  40 -- 49 %  50-- 59%         60--69%  Textural  Belt  3  Fig. 3. Soil sample sites. Fine sand % (100--200 urn) in the horizon of maximum clay  content.    150 Watt. Clay and fine silt were determined by weighing samples of suspen-  sion extracted by a pressure box. This modification of the pipette method  consists of an "air-tight box, with fitted pipettes, into which dispersed samples  are introduced. At the appropriate time air is pumped into the box, thereby  forcing out samples of suspension through the pipettes. Sand was collected by  wet sieving and fractionated by dry sieving; coarse silt was obtained by dif-  ference. The particle-size classes separated were clay (&lt; 2 pm), fine silt (2--20 pm),    247    coarse silt (20--50 Urn), very fine sand (50--100 um), fine sand (100--200  um), medium sand (200--500 pm) and coarse sand (500--2000 pm). The silt  fractions were subsequently combined because of the very low fine silt content  For each profile the percentages of clay, silt, very fine, fine, medium and  coarse sand were plotted on separate maps. A separate map was plotted in  each case for the surface horizon and the horizon of maximum clay content  irrespective of the depth at which the latter occurred. This was considered to    13"    12   7                                        8"                                          9"  I                                  I    110o Km  ~*                                            "                 6   "     O-- 9%  10- 19 %          20-- 29 %  ,        30- 39 %  40- 49%  50- 59%  o        60- 69 %  Textural Belt  3  Fig. 4. Soil sample sites. Very fine sand % (50--100 urn) in the surface horizon.    248    afford a basis for comparison between soils of the part of the profile most  recently affected by aeolian deposition and that most developed pedogenetical-  ly and in which the character of the aeolian material (if any) is most altered.  For simplification, the actual percentages were grouped in 10% class intervals,  i.e., 0--9%, 10--19%, 20--29%, etc. Only the most informative maps, those  showing the distribution of silt, very fine sand and fine sand, are presented  here (Figs. 2--7).    13"    12   7                                        8"                                          9"  I                                   r    OES kO ~,-  1 tOOKm   ,,*+           I~   ~*                                I    0--9%  10--19%  ~,       20- 29 %  .        30-- 39 %  40--49%  50-- 59%  D       60--69%  Textural Belt  3  Fig. 5. Soil sample sites. Very fine sand % (50--100 um) in the horizon of maximum clay  content.    249    7   13"    12"    8"                                    9"  I                                   I    ,m     . o  ~.f..  ~Sz~':? ;  .-  5  ",~.                  ""   ~          I,   ,"                                I    0--9%  10-- 19 %          20-- 29 %  ,        30-- 39 %  40 -- 49 %  50-- 59%          60--69%  Textural  Belt  3  Fig. 6. Soil sample sites. Silt % (2--50 ~m) in the surface horizon.    250    7   13"    12"    8"                                    9"  I                                I    \    c I    SCALE  1" ~ 108km      5,   -~.           ~         ~ .  -       _._.4 ~+   .  2+    0--9%  10-- 19%          20-- 29 %  30-- 39 %  40 -- 49 %  50-- 59%         60-- 69 %  3        Textural Belt    Fig. 7. Soil sample sites. Silt % (2--50 ~m) in the horizon of maximum clay content.    251    RESULTS    Each map shows a very clear linear distribution pattern orientated broadly  along an east--west axis. To emphasize and describe the nature of the distri-  bution, trend lines were drawn subjectively on the maps dividing the area into  textural belts, these being areas of the greatest uniformity of particle size. The  composition of the belts in terms of profile distribution in each 10%-class is  given in Table I.  TABLE I  Profile distribution-frequency (%) by textural belt of particle-size classes (fractions) in  10%-intervals    Textural     Particle-size class intervals  belt  0--9%        10--19%     20-29%     30-39%     40--49%     50--59%     60--69%    Fine sand in the surface horizon--Fig. 2  1                          4       15      (40)  2                        (47)     (47)       6  3                (62)      36        2  4        (84)       15        I  5                  3      (50)      39        8    Fine sand in the horizon of maximum clay content--Fig. 3  1              2           12           16           20          (33)  2          2        25       (41)       23        9  3              17           (67)           15             1  4        (95)       5  5                    14       (50)       31         5    Very fine sand in the surface horizon--Fig.4  1         5      (77)      18  2                 18      (73)       9  3                          36      (61)       3  4                                 11      (76)  5                  1                8      (41)  6                   2        9      (46)       39  7                            25          (51)           22             2    Very fine sand in the horizon of maximum clay content--Fig.5  1         24      (65)       11  2                  11       (78)       11  3                            10      (76)       14  4                  9        8      (37)      36  5                 15      (49)      36  6         7      (79)      12        2    Silt in the surface horizow-Fig. 6  1         (83)       15         2  2              11           (69)           18             2  3                  14      (62)       23        1  4                          13      (63)      24  5                   4        6       21       (54)    Silt in the horizon of maximum clay content--Fig. 7  1        (72)      26        2  2         9       (72)       17        2  3                 14      (58)      26        2  4                   2       23       (68)       7  5                  3                30      (67)  6                           13      (71)       13    36        5    15    13  39  2    15    11  2    252    Examination of the data shows the belts to have some obvious properties.  (1) In each belt the frequency distribution of profiles in the 10% class  intervals shows a single peak either at the low, medium or high content of  the range.  (2) For all maps the highest-peaked profile frequency distributions tend  to occur in belts with low contents of the particle-size class being mapped.  Broad peaks occur in belts of high content.  (3) The data indicate pronounced regional trends in particle-size distribu-  tions. Silt is seen to increase regularly towards the south; very fine sand to  increase regularly southwards and then decrease, and fine sand to decrease  towards the south. The exception to this is fine-sand belt 5 which shows the  controlling influence of the high fine-sand content of the Pleistocene lacus-  trine sediments, and silt in belt 6, Fig. 7, which is perhaps an indication that  this is (or was) the area of greatest silt deposition.  A comparison may be made between surface and subsoil horizons of softs  in those belts which have coincident boundaries. Silt belt I has slightly more  silt in the subsoil than at the surface but belts 2 and 3 show little difference.  The peak-frequency distribution is the same in both horizons, 0--10% belt 1,  10--20% belt 2 and 20--30% belt 3. All fine-sand belts show more sand at  the surface than in the subsoil but the difference is less towards the south.  Common peak-frequency distributions again occur, 40--50% belt 1, 20--30%  belt 2, 10--20% belt 3 and 0--10% belt 4.  The regularity of particle-size class distribution, both within and between  belts, at the surface and in the subsoil (properties 1 and 3 above), indicates  a closer regional relationship between soils than would be expected to result  from pedogenic processes acting upon i n-situ or locally derived parent  materials.    DISCUSSION OF PARENT-MATERIAL ORIGIN    During the Quaternary period climatic changes occurred which brought  about alternating periods of both wetter and drier conditions south of the  Sahara Desert than the present climate (Grove and Warren, 1968; Burke et al.,  1971), or alternating periods of morphodynamic activity and stability (Rohden-  burg, 1970). During stable phases, deep chemical weathering would have oc-  curred with downwasting of the land surface, the removal of soil components  mainly in solution and the concentration of less soluble substances. During  active phases, loose surface material would be subjected to wind action, oc-  casional high-intensity rainfall would bring about mass movement of unsta-  bilised surfaces, previously segregated iron would harden on exposure, and  exposed rock would be subjected to physical .weathering.  Aeolian movement of material into or out of an area would be a corollary  of such changes taking place over a wider region. Although there has been  climatic fluctuation and corresponding environmental change, the north has  overall been drier than the south and the sandstone in the north has given rise    253    to a coarser-textured weathering product than the Basement Complex rocks  in the south. Conditions in the north have favoured dune formation and  presumably the removal of fine material southwards. Climatic shifts have  resulted in dune encroachment southwards or degradation northwards, de-  pending on the direction of the shift, and correspondingly the dust accretion  zone has become a source area for the removal of dust further south or has  extended northwards.  A site may, therefore, have been acted upon during several periods by wind  or water, erosional or depositional, or any combination of these processes.  Parent materials of upland soils over most of the area (neglecting the small  area of Pleistocene deposits) can be seen as a function of a number of materials  plus process combinations. If, as a model, we consider a land surface without  regolith, the composition of the soils' parent materials after an initial stable-  phase--active-phase sequence is some combination of the following, the com-  position at any site depending on the history of that particular site.  (1) In-situ weathered Basement Complex and Cretaceous derived material.  (2) Basement Complex and Cretaceous-derived material of local origin  transported by coUuvial processes.  (3) Basement Complex and Cretaceous-derived material of local origin  transported by wind action.  (4) Material of unknown origin imported from further afield by wind  action.  (5) Material originating locally from the erosion of ironpan cappings by  colluvial processes (a variant of 2).  A second stable-phase--active-phase sequence would produce the same  combination of processes, the effects of which would be superimposed on the  soils parent materials, monophase or polyphase, produced by the first se-  quence. The second sequence would then tend to homogenise the results of  the first sequence while creating discontinuities anew. This chain of events  would continue through successive sequences. Parent materials of present-day  profile forms can be associated with each of these individual processes to  greater or lesser extents depending on the properties of particular materials.  (1) In-situ weathering can be clearly identified in the gradually altered  parent rock at the bases of many profiles. It is most evident in the north and  southeast of the survey area, where overlying deposits have been stripped or  thinned or where deposition has been slight.  (2) Local colluvial material occurs widely. Clear evidence is the presence  of quartz gravel or detrital ironpan gravel through the provile. The occurrence  of aeolian material throughout the profile (a statement this paper attempts  to make), is also proof of homogenisation, possibly by faunal activity in part,  but more significantly by mass movement (see 5). The wide distribution range  of a particle-size class in areas of maximum deposition (property 2) may also  be explained by local surface movement of material.  (3) Wind action, by particle movement along the surface or saltation, on  coarse-textured Cretaceous material is assumed to have brought about dune  formation in the north of the area. Subsequent degradation, perhaps involving    254    water in a similar manner to that described by Talbot and Williams (1978) has  resulted in a relatively even cover of coarse material with only vestigial dune  formations remaining in parts. The Cambic Arenosol previously described is  an example of a soil formed in this type of material.  (4) The transport of material in aeolian suspension is an active process at  the present time. It is proposed here that the very fine sand and silt distribu-  tion patterns are evidence of the significance of the process in the past and  that the progressive change southwards from coarse to fine particle size indi-  cates a source area to the north. The very fine sand has presumably not  travelled far and some may have originated in the north of the survey area.  Sombroek and Zonneveld (1971, p.71) identify a possible source of their  Funtua loess south of Lake Chad and east of its deposition zone. Kalu (1979)  gives the source area of present-day Saharan dust as the Bilma--Faya Largeau  area much further north. Soils formed in material covering ironstone-capped  mesas in the south of the area are of this type.  (5) Material originating from the destruction of ironpan caps has been  mentioned already as evidence of widespread local reworking. From the  amount of detrital material encountered, the ironpan mesas of today must  be remnants of much larger ironpan formations. Material similar to that in (4),  resting on previously more extensive ironpan caps, will also have been redis-  tributed downslope in this way.    CONCLUSIONS    The textural distribution patterns support the findings of previous workers  to the extent that soils throughout the area contain elements of aeolian origin,  and that aeolian material is a significant component of the pedologicaUy well-  developed soils with argillic horizons in the south as well as of the coarse-  textured soils in the north. The results do, however, support impressions  gained during the survey of the inadvisability of applying the term "drift",  meaning wind-deposited, to some soils (or parts of soils) on the basis of a  cursory field examination and the identification of certain "aeolian" proper-  ties such as silt, while regarding others as "non-drift" on the basis of "non-  aeolian" properties such as ironstone gravel. Components of various origins  and with varied and indeterminate histories have contributed in various  amounts to parent materials homogenised to greater or lesser extents.  The exceptions to this perhaps are sand covers in the north of the area,  providing the dune degradation process has not introduced extraneous  material, and silty mesa covers in the south. It may be appropriate to regard  the latter as loess.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    I would like to thank the Cartography Section and the Data Management  Unit of the Land Resources Development Centre for their assistance with  mapping and data handling.    255    NOTE    Compatible particle-size analysis results are not available for deposits  further south than shown on the maps, but field work indicated that a signif-  icant silt content does not extend much further south than 1030', and that  the southern limit of significant silt accretion lies between Zaria and Kaduna.    REFERENCES    Brink, A.B., Mabbutt, J.A., Webster, R. and Beckett, P.H.T., 1966. Report of the Working  Group on Land Classification and Data Storage. Milit. Eng. Exp. Establ., Christchurch,  England, Rep., 940.  Burke, K., Durotoye, A.B.,and Whiteman, A.J., 1971. A dry phase south of the Sahara  20 000 years ago. W. Afr. J. Archaeol., 1: 1--8.  Du Preez, J.W., 1958. The water supply of Katsina town Rec. Geol. Surv. Niger., 1955:  59--64.  Falconer, J.D., 1911. The Geology and Geography of Northern Nigeria. MacMillan, London,  FAO-UNESCO, 1974. Soil Map of the World, 1. Legend. Unesco, Paris.  Grove, A.T., 1958. The ancient erg of Hausaland, and similar formations on the south side  of the Sahara. Geogr. J., 124(4): 526--533.  Grove, A.T., and Warren, A., 1968. Quaternary landform and climate on the south side of  the Sahara. Geogr. J., 134(2): 194--208.  Higgins, G.M., 1963. Upland soils of Samaru and Kano plains. Inst. Agric. Res., Samaru  (Unnumbered Soil. Surv. Rep.).  Kalu, A.E., 1979. The African dust plume: its characteristics and propagation across West  Africa in winter. In: C. Morales (Editor), Saharan Dust. Wiley, New York, N.Y., (Pub-  lished on behalf of the Scientific Committee on Problems of the Environment).  Keay, R.W., 1949. An outline of Nigerian vegetation. Gov. Printer, Lagos.  King, L.C., 1967. The Morphology of the Earth. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh.  Klinkenberg, K. and Higgins, G.M., 1968. An outline of Northern Nigerian soils. Niger. J.  Sci., 2(2): 91--115.  Kowal, J.M. and Knabe, D.T., 1972. An Agroclimatological Atlas of the Northern States  of Nigeria. Ahmadu Bello Univ. Press, Samaru, Zaria, Nigeria.  Lawes, D.A., 1962. The influence of rainfall conservation on the fertility of the loess plain  soil of northern Nigeria. Niger. Geogr. J., 5.  Macload, W.N., Turner, D.C. and Wright, E.P., 1971. The geology of the Jos Plateau. Bull.  Geol. Surv. Niger., 32.  McCurry, P., 1976. The geology of the Precambrian to Lower Palaeozoic rocks of Northern  Nigeria--a review. In: C.A. Kogbe (Editor), Geology of Nigeria. Elizabethan Publishing,  Surulere (Lagos), pp. 15--39.  Rohdenburg, H., 1970. Morphodynamische Aktivit~ten und Stabilit~tszeiten start Pluvial-  und Interpluvialzeiten. Eiszeitalt. Gegenwart, 21: 81--96.  S0mbroek, W.G. and Zonneveld, I.S., 1971. Ancient dune fields and fluviatile deposits in  the Rima-Sokoto river basin. Neth. Soil Surv. Inst., Wageningen, Soil Surv., Pap., 5.  Talbot, M.R.~nd Williams, M.A.J., 1978. Erosion of fixed dunes in the Sahel, Central  Niger. Earth Surf. Proc., 3(2): 107--113.  Tomlinson, P.R., 1961. Report on the detailed soil survey of the Livestock Investigation  Centre, Katsina, and the reconnaissance survey of the ~urrounding area. Inst. Agric.  Res., Samaru, Soil Surv. Publ., 11.  Vine, H., 195~. Notes on the main types of Nigerian soils. Gov. Printer, Lagos.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractThe introduction considers the nature of the problem of Ã¢Â€ÂœdriftÃ¢Â€Â soils in northern Nigeria. The physical environment of the survey area is described briefly and the percentages of silt, very fine sand and fine sand occurring in the soils are mapped. Textural belts are identified and the profile distribution frequencies within the belts are tabulated. Parent material origins are discussed and attempts are made to reconcile the apparently aeolian nature of the soil materials, in terms of the particle-size distribution pattern, with the various soil profile morphologies of today. 