Geoderma, 29 (1983) 119--127                                                   119  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in the Netherlands    SWELLING AND MINERALOGY OF SMECTITES IN PADDY SOILS  DERIVED FROM MARINE ALLUVIUM, JAPAN    KAZUHIKO EGASHIRA and MASAMI OHTSUBO  Faculty of Agriculture, Kyushu University, Fukuoka (Japan)  (Received January 12, 1982; accepted after revision July 9, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Egashira, K. and Ohtsubo, M., 1983. Swelling and mineralogy of smectites in paddy soils  derived from marine alluvium, Japan. Geoderma, 29: 119--127.    A low-swelling smectite exhibiting little intra-crystaliine swelling even after saturation  with Na was found in paddy soils derived from marine alluvium of Ariake Bay in Kyushu,  Japan. The low-swelling smectite was considered to be a beidellite-nontronite mineral con-  taining as much as 10% F%Os. The low-swelling characteristics of this smectite are ascribed  to the considerable substitution of Fe2+ for AIs+ in the octahedral layer which depresses  the dissociation of unit layers of smectite. Transformation of low-swelling to high-swelling  smectite is believed to be due to the oxidation of Fe2+ to Fes+ in the octahedral layer.    INTRODUCTION    Paddy softs derived from marine alluvium which was drained naturally or  artificially are widely distributed around Ariake Bay, Kyushu, Japan  (3250'--330'N 13010'--25'E). Two types of smectite, namely high-swel-  ling and low,swelling, were found in these soils. The high-swelling smectite is  a clay with swelling properties characteristic of montmorillonite. On the oth-  er hand, the low,welling smectite has swelling properties similar to those of  kaolinite and illite. The Na-form of low-swelling smectite expands only to the  same extent as the Ca-form. The presence of low-swelling smectite was first  proposed, based on the measurement of sediment volume and viscosity, in re-  cent marine mud of Ariake Bay by the authors (Egashira and Ohtsubo, 1981).  Its mineralogical properties and reason for its low-swelling characteristics,  however, were not clarified. The present study was undertaken to compare  the properties of low- and high,swelling smectites and to determine why some  smectites do not swell as much as others.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil samples were taken from paddy soils at two localities, Chiyoda-machi  and Kawazoe-machi (Saga Agricultural Experiment Station) of Saga Prefec-    0016-7061/83/0000--0000/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    120  TABLE I  Soil samples used in this study    Locality               Sample   Depth (horizon)  (m)    Content of  &lt;2 ~m clay  (%)    Water  content  (%)    Chiyoda-machi, Saga    Ch-2     0.13-0.4 (B)      50.8  Prefecture              Ch-4     0.85--1.3  (Cg)     45.5  Ch-5    1.3--1.6 (G)    37.1  Ch-6    1.6 --2.15 (G)    33.3  Ch-7    2.15--   (G)    31.1    Saga Agricultural       SN-I     0.25--0.6 (Bg)     42.4         69  Experiment Station,    SN-2     0.7 -0.8  (Cg)     46.2        119  Nanri, Kawazoe-machi,  SN-3     1.0 --1.1  (Cg)     47.0        121  Saga Prefecture         SN-4     1.2 --1.3  (G)     47.6        130    W-179-3  0.20--0.65 (B2gmn) 40.5          51    ture (Table I). The paddy soils are classified as Gray Lowland Soils in the clas-  sification system of Japan which are almost equivalent to Fluvic Gleysols in  the "FAO/UNESCO Soil Map of the World". Sample W-179-3, employed in  the previous study (Egashira and Ohtsubo, 1981), was taken at a different site  from the SN samples in the paddy field of the Saga Agricultural Experiment  Station.  Field-moist soil samples were treated with 7% H202 to remove organic mat-  ter, adjusted to pH 10 by addition of NaOH and dispersed by shaking. The  ~2/~m clay fractions were collected by repeated sedimentation and siphoning.  The ~2 ~m clays were washed 4 times with 1 M NaCl or 0.5 M CaCl2, then  dialyzed or washed with distilled water to remove excess salt. The sodium and  calcium clays were shaken for 5 h to ensure dispersion.  The surface areas of the &lt;~2 ~m clays, freeze-dried from dispersed clay sus-  pensions, were measured with ethylene glycol monoethyl ether (Eltantawy  and Arnold, 1973; Egashira et al., 1977). The sediment volume was measured  by transferring duplicate dispersed clay suspensions containing 100 mg clay  into 25-cm3 measuring cylinders. An aliquot of NaCI or CaCl2 solution was  added to give final concentrations of 0.04 and 1.0 M for NaCI and 0.02 and  0.5 M for CaCI2 and to flocculate each clay suspension. The suspensions were  diluted to about 22 cm3 with water, the measuring cylinders sealed with rub-  ber stoppers, shaken vigorously for 15 sec and the volume was finally diluted  to 25 cm3. The cylinders were allowed to stand at 25. The sediment volume  was read every 24 h until it became constant. The coefficient of variation of  the measurements was less than 5%.  Specimens for X-ray diffraction were prepared by taking replicate clay sus-  pensions (without Na2S204-Na citrate-NaHCO3 treatment) containing 50 mg    121    clay. One set of samples was washed with 0.5 M MgC12, another with 1 M KC1  and a third with 2 M LiC1. Excess salt was removed by washing with water.  One cm3 of water was added and an aliquot of the suspension containing  30 mg of clay was dropped onto a glass slide (28 48 mm), air-dried and  X-rayed. The specimens were all solvated with glycerol, the Mg- and K-satu-  rated samples after air-drying and the Li-saturated samples after heating at  250 for 5--6 h. An aqueous solution of glycerol (10% v/v) was sprayed on  the samples in slight excess. The K-saturated specimens were heated at 300  and 550. Filtered CoK~ radiation from a Rigaku diffractometer was used  for X-ray analysis.  Iron oxide contents of the &lt;2 ~m clays were determined according to the  method of Bernas (1968) with a little modification. Duplicate clay samples of  60--65 rag, previously treated with Na2S204--Na citrate--NaHCO3 to remove  free iron oxide (Mehra and Jackson, 1960), were placed into 100 cm3 polyeth-  ylene volumetric flasks having air-tight caps. Aqua regia (0.5 cm3) was added  to wet the entire sample, then 3 cm3 of 47% HF were added. The flasks were  shaken at 25 for 24 h. Then 5 cm3 of water and 2.8 g of boric acid were  added. After a few minutes of shaking 20 cm3 of water was added and shaking  was continued until complete dissolution of boric acid. The solutions were  made up to volume with water. Iron was measured by atomic absorption spec-  trophotometry.    RESULTS    Figs. 1 and 2 show the X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns of the &lt;2 ~m clay  fractions of the Chiyoda-machi and Saga A.E.S. (Agricultural Experiment  Station) samples. Only the patterns of the Mg-saturated and glycerol-solvated  specimen (Fig. 1) and of the K-saturated and air-dried specimen (Fig. 2) are  reproduced here. The XRD patterns of samples Ch-5 and Ch-7 are represented  by those of sample Ch-6, because these three samples exhibit similar patterns.  Similar patterns were obtained for samples SN-1 and SN-2, and for samples  SN-3 and SN-4. The strong peaks at 1.80 nm in the Mg-saturated and glycerol-  solvated specimen and at 1.28 nm in the K-saturated and air-dried specimen  show clearly that all of the clay fractions contain a large amount of smectite.  Other clay minerals are koalinite, mica and vermiculite. The silt fractions  (2--20 ~m) contain quartz, feldspars and cristobalite. Small quantities of these  primary minerals also are present in the clay fractions.  Specific surface areas of the &lt;2 ~m clay fractions (Table II) for Ca-clay are  always higher than those of Na~lay and are more than 400 m2/g for all of the  samples, suggesting a predominance of smectite (Egashira, 1981). The approx-  imate smectite contents of the clay fractions were estimated from their specif-  ic surface areas. A value of 800 m2/g was assumed as the specific surface area  of smectite and a value of 200 m2/g was chosen as the average specific surface  area of the other minerals because this value had been measured as the lowest  value for soil clays devoid of smectite by one of the authors (Egashira, 1981).    122    1.80NM    1,q2  ~J  1,00~       ~/    W-179-3    SN-I  SN-4    1.28 NM  I    1.80 N,~  ~ Ch-2  Ch-4  Ch-6  1 .q2  0.9O ~A   II   V  ~I I I I I il i i~i iii  15       I0       5  oEe CoKcx    1.0O NM    0.71 NM  I    15       i0       5                                                    15       10       5  0 CoK~                                              0 CoK~    W-179-3      I'~  SN-I  1.00             /  SN-4  O'7i!t'!  IIIIIIIIIlllll  15      i0       5  e2O CoKa    Ch-2  Ch-4  Ch-6    Fig. 1. X-ray diffraction patterns of the Mg-saturated and glycerol-solvated specimen of the  &lt; 2 ~m fractions of the samples from Chiyoda-machi and Saga A.E.S.    Fig. 2. X-ray diffraction patterns of the K-saturated and air-dried specimen of the &lt; 2 ~m  fractions of the samples from Chiyoda-machi and Saga A.E.S.    TABLE II  Specific surface area and smectite content of the &lt; 2 ~m clay fractions    Sample Specific surface  Smectite Sample   Specific surface  Smectite  area (m=/g)      content            area (m2/g)      content  (%)                      (%)    Na-clay Ca-clay    Na-clay Ca-clay    Ch-2    426    500    38--50   SN-1     421     480    37--47  Ch-4        427          471          38--45       SN-2          449         488         42---48  Ch-5    450    480    42--47   SN-3     454    502    42--50  Ch-6    443    476    41--46   SN-4     442    489    40--48  Ch-7    438    472    40-45   W-179-3  432       --    39--    The smectite content of each sample was calculated by 800x + 200(100--x) =  100S, where x is the smectite content (%) and S is the specific surface area  (m2/g), from the specific surface areas of Na- and Ca~lays and is listed as the  minimum and maximum values, respectively, in Table II. The smectite con-  tent in the clay fractions is in the range of 38 to 50% and 37 to 50% for the    123    samples from Chiyoda-machi and Saga A.E.S., respectively, and does not ap-  pear to differ significantly with depth. Based on these surface area and XRD  estimates of mineral contents, the clay fractions of the samples used in this  study appear to contain smectite as the main component.  Swelling characteristics of the smectite, namely high-swelling or low-swel-  ling, were estimated from the measurements of sediment volumes (Egashira  and Ohtsubo, 1981). Table III lists the sediment volumes of clay fractions  measured after saturation with Na and Ca. The sediment volumes of samples  Ch-2 and W-179-3 are clearly greater for the Na-clay than for the Ca-clay at  0.04 or 0.02 and 1.0 or 0.5 M salt concentrations. The higher sediment vol-  ume of the Na-clay is probably due to the swelling of Na-smectite with sepa-  ration into unit layers in the dispersed suspension and preservation of the unit  layers in the flocculated suspension. Therefore, the smectite of samples Ch-2  and W-179-3 is a high-swelling clay, the property characteristic of montmo-  rillonite. The increase in the sediment volume of Na-clay with decreasing NaC1  concentration, observed for sample Ch-2, is also characteristic of high-swelling  clay.  On the other hand, the sediment volumes of the Na-clay are almost equal  to those of the Ca-clay, especially at 0.04 or 0.02 M salt concentrations, for  samples Ch-4~Ch-7 and SN-I~SN-4. This tendency is clearly different from  that observed for samples Ch-2 and W-179-3 but essentially the same as that  of the sample containing low-swelling smectite reported by Egashira and  Ohtsubo (1981). The Na-smectite in those samples appears to expand only to    TABLE III    Sediment volumes of the &lt; 2 ~m clay fractions  Sample   Sediment volume (cm3/100 mg)    At 0.04 or 0.02 M salt  concentration    Na-clay Ca-clay Ratio  (a)    (b)    (a)/(b)    At 1.0 or 0.5 M salt  concentration    Na-clay Ca-clay Ratio  (c)    (d)    (c)/(d)    Ch-2     4.52    2.91    1.55   4.20    2.99    1.40  Ch-4     3.02    2.95    1.02   3.36    3.07    1.09  Ch-5           3.36        2.83        1.19      3.18        2.83        1.12  Ch-6           2.88        2.68        1.07      3.01        2.78        1.08  Ch-7      2.77    2.59    1.07   2.94    2.63    1.12    SN-1     2.98    2.83    1.05   3.43    2.92    1.17  SN-2     2.64    2.94    0.90   3.16    3.05    1.04  SN-3     2.76    2.82    0.98   3.27    2.89    1.13  SN-4     2.96    2.81    1.05   3.32    2.86    1.16    W-179-3  4.10    2.58    1.59   4.09    2.49    1.64    124  TABLE IV  X-ray diffraction data of smectite for soft and reference clays    Sample and                 Cation      001 spacing of the  sample source                exchange    Li-saturated0  capacity     heated at 250  (meq./100g) and glycerol-  solvated specimen  (am)    001 spacing of the  K-saturated and  glycerol-solvated  specimen (nm)    060 spacing  (nm, random  powder mount)    Soil clay  Ch-2                                     1.83                1.53  Ch-4                                   1.83               1.65  Ch-6                                   no peak or shoulder 1.71  8N-1                                     1.83                1.45  SN-2                                     1.80                1.55  SN-4                                 1.79 (shoulder)    1.70  W-179-3                                  1.83                1.42    0.I 500  0.I 500  0.1501  0.1499  0.1501    Montmormonite  Matsuida, Gunma          75         1.82:&gt;0.97         1.77              0.1493  Osage, Wyoming           96         0.97              1.74              0.1494  Clay SIro~, Wyoming       97         0.97~1.75      1.74              0.1494  PolkvUle, Mis~iss/ppi      112        0.96             1.72             0.1494  Otay, California         119        0.96              1,42             0.1497    Nontronite  Trinidad Hill, Washington 109         1.80:&gt;~0.98       1.44              0.1509    about the same extent as the Ca-smectite. Therefore, this smectite is consid-  ered a low-swelling clay, similar to kaolinite and illite. As shown above, the  paddy soils contain both high-swelling and low-swelling smectites in the same  profile (the Chiyoda-machi samples) or in the same paddy field (the Saga  A.E.S. samples and W-179-3).  Mineralogical properties of high-swelling and low-swelling smectites investi-  gated by XRD technique are compared with reference montmorillonites and  nontronite in Table IV. The Greene-Kelly test (Greene-Kelly, 1953), which  serves to distinguish montmorillonites with isomorphous substitution mainly  in the octahedral layer from beidellites and nontronites with isomorphous  substitution mainly in the tetrahedral layer, of the Li-saturated samples gave  001 spacings for the specimens as listed in the third column of Table IV. Ac-  cording to the results for reference specimens of octahedrally substituted  montmorillonites (Osage, Clay Spur, Polkville and Otay) these minerals col-  lapse to 0.96--0.97 nm, whereas tetrahedrally substituted nontronite retains  its 1.80 nm spacing. Montmorillonite from Matsuida, Gunma is considered to  be a beidellite-nontronite mineral rather than a montmorillonite. The 001  spacing of the soil smectites is 1.79--1.83 nm, which is characteristic of  beidellite and nontronite.  Cation exchange capacities (CEC) of the soil smectites were roughly esti-  mated from the 001 spacing of the K-saturated and glycerol-solvated specimens.  This method was originally proposed by Barshad (1960) for differentiation of  high exchange and low exchange forms of smectites. The 001 spacing of the  K-saturated specimens is listed in the fourth column of Table IV. Barshad    125    (1960) stated that prevention of drying of clays is essential for the differentia-  tion. In the present study, however, Otay montmorillonite having a CEC of  119 meq./100 g expands only to 1.42 nm, the equivalent thickness of a mono-  layer of glycerol, whereas the other montmorillonites having CEC less than  112 meq./100 g expand to 1.72--1.77 nm, the equivalent thickness of two lay-  ers of glycerol, in spite of air-drying. The position of the isomorphous substi-  tution is another factor to determine the 001 spacing. The 001 spacings of the  soil smectites range from 1.42 to 1.71 nm, from monolayer to near bilayer of  glycerol through a mixed-layer. Because the soil smectites have isomorphous  substitution mainly in the tetrahedral layer, they can be compared to Trinidad  Hill nontronite and Matsuida montmorillonite. Therefore, CEC's of the soil  smectites are less than 109 meq./100 g and more than 75 meq./100 g. The in-  crease in the 001 spacing of the K-saturated and glycerol-solvated specimen  with depth found for the Chiyoda-machi and Saga A.E.S. profiles is inter-  preted as a decrease in CEC and/or the degree of tetrahedral substitution.  The 060 spacings for soil smectites obtained from random powder mounts,  listed in the last column of Table IV, are around 0.1500 nm, but the reflec-  tion peaks are very broad. These spacings are smaller than for Trinidad Hill  nontronite but clearly greater than those for montmorillonites. The presence  of a significant amount of iron in the octahedral layer is believed responsible  for the slightly greater 060 spacing of the soil smectites compared with the  montmorillonites.    TABLE V    Iron oxide contents of the &lt;2 um clay fractions  Sample              Ch-2    Ch-4    Ch-6    SN-1   SN-4   W-179-3  %F%O3 in clay         7.8      6.3      5.2      7.5      6.3         7.7  %Fe203 in smectite   16--21  14--17  11--13  16--20  13--16     --20    Table V gives the iron oxide content, expressed as Fe203, of the &lt;2 #m  clay fractions from which free iron oxide had been extracted. The Fe203 con-  tents in the clay fractions range from 5.2 to 7.8%. The contents of Fe203 in  smectites (Table V), calculated on the assumption that all iron in the clays is  contained in those minerals, range from 11--13 to 16--21%. Some part of the  iron, however, must be allocated to the mica (dioctahedral) and vermiculite  present. Moreover, the smectite contents calculated from specific surface areas  are uncertain. Thus, determination of the exact iron contents of smectites was  not possible. Even so, a value of about 10% seems reasonable for the minerals.  This proportion of Fe203 is lower than the usual amount in nontronite and  near the upper limits reported for montmorillonite and beidellite (Weaver and  Pollard, 1973). Based on these mineralogical studies, the smectite found in the    126    paddy soil samples can be regarded as a beidellite-nontronite mineral or an  iron bearing beidellite containing about 10% Fe203. No essential difference  could be found in mineralogy, CEC, and Fe203 content of high- and low-swel-  ling smectites.    DISCUSSION    Foster (1953) studied the influence of chemical composition on the swel-  ling of montmorillonites in detail. According to her, the degree of swelling  showed no correlation with CEC or with tetrahedral charge but did show a  correlation with octahedral substitution in the direction of decrease in swel-  ling with increase in octahedral substitution. Foster (1953) further stated that  substituted Fe2+ had the greatest depressing effect on swelling followed by  Fe3+ and Mg2+. This statement is valuable in considering the reason why some  smectites exhibit such low,welling characteristics. The low-swelling smectites  appear to be beidellite-nontronite minerals, containing as much as 7% Fe (i.e.,  10% Fe203). Most of iron in the smectites is probably present as Fe2+ in the  octahedral layer, substituting for A13+, because the smectites are likely to have  been formed in the marine environment of Ariake Bay (Kanno et al., 1962)  where iron would be present as Fe2+. Iron would also be present in the re-  duced form in the lower layers of the paddy soils. Thus low-swelling charac-  teristics of some smectites could be due to substitution of Fe2+ for A13+ in the  octahedral layer depressing the dissociation of unit layers of smectite and  leading to a low swelling volume even after saturation with Na (Foster, 1953).  The observation that low-swelling smectites were in both upper and lower  layers of the paddy soils, whereas the high-swelling smectites were only in the  upper layers suggests transformation of low-swelling into high-swelling smectite  in the upper layers (B horizons) of paddy soils where more oxidizing condi-  tions prevail. Oxidation of Fe2+ to Fe3+ in the octahedral layer may be a  cause of the transformation of low-swelling into high-swelling smectite.    CONCLUSION    The low,swelling smectite is a beidellite-nontronite mineral. Low-swelling  characteristics of this smectite are ascribed to the substitution of Fe2+ for  AP+ in the octahedral layer.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors wish to thank Dr. J.B. Dixon for providing reference clay min-  erals and Mr. Y. Koyanagi for his kind help in collecting the soil samples.  They also wish to thank Dr. B.P. Warkentin for critically reading the manu-  script.    127    REFERENCES    Barshad, I., 1960. X-ray analysis of the soil colloids by a modified salted paste method.  Clays Clay Miner., 7 : 350--364.  Bernas, B., 1968. A new method for decomposition and comprehensive analysis of silicates  by atomic absorption spectrometry. Anal. Chem., 40: 1682--1686.  Egashira, K., 1981. Relationship between mineral composition and surface area of soil  clays. J. Sci. Soil Manure, Japan, 52:225--229 (in Japanese).  Egashira, K. and Ohtsubo, M., 1981. Low-swelling smectite in a recent marine mud of  Ariake Bay. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 27: 205--211.  Egashira, K., Kajiyama, T. and Arimizu, N., 1977. Effects of the Na2S~O4--NaHCO3--Na  citrate and 2% Na2CO3 treatments on the surface area of allophane and imogolite.  Nendo Kagaku, 17:38--47 (in Japanese with English abstract).  Eltantawy, I.M. and Arnold, P.W., 1973. Reappraisal of ethylene glycol mono-ethyl ether  (EGME) method for surface area estimations of clays. J. Soil Sci., 24: 232--238.  Foster, M.D., 1953. Geochemical studies of clay minerals, II. Relation between ionic sub-  stitution and swelling in montmorillonites. Am. Miner., 38: 994--1006.  Greene-Kelly, R., 1953. Identification of montmorillonoids. J. Soil Sci., 4: 233--237.  Kanno, I., Honjo, Y., Kuwano, Y., Arimura, S. and Tokudome, S., 1962. Clay minerals of  recent shallow sea (near-shore) sediments from Ariake Bay in Kyushu. Nendo Kagaku  no Shinpo, 4: 227--238 (in Japanese with English abstract).  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a  dithionite-citrate system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7: 317--  327.  Weaver, C.E. and Pollard, L.D., 1973. The Chemistry of Clay Minerals. Elsevier Scientific  Publ. Co., New York, pp. 55--86.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractA low-swelling smectite exhibiting little intra-crystalline swelling even after saturation with Na was found in paddy soils derived from marine alluvium of Ariake Bay in Kyushu, Japan. The low-swelling smectite was considered to be beidellite-nontronite mineral containing as much as 10% Fe2O3. The low-swelling characteristics of this smectite are ascribed to the considerable substitution of Fe2+ for Al3+ in the ochtahedral layer which depresses the dissociation of unit layers of smectite. Transformation of low-swelling to high-swelling smectite is believed to be due to the oxidation of Fe2+ to Fe3+ in the octahedral layer.