 Geoderma, 35 (1985) 359--376                                                 359  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Akeson, Mark; and Singer, Michael J. A preliminary length factor for erosion on steep slopes in  Guatemala and its use to evaluate "curvas a nivel": Geoderma, 33(4), p. 265-282, illus. (incl. 6 tables,  sketch map), 1984.  Aleksandrovskaya, Ye. I.; Mazepova, V. I.; and Vakhrashin, N. A.  Khimicheskiye svoystva  pridorozhnykh pochv, razvitykh na razlichnykh pochvoobrazuyushchikh pordakh trassy Moskva-  Leningrad [Chemical properties of road-side soils derived from various soil-forming rocks along the  Moscow-Leningrad Motorway]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5: Geografiya, 1984(3), p.  77-82 (incl. English sum.), 2 tables, diag., 1984.  Alley, William M. On the treatment of evapotranspiration, soil moisture accounting, and aquifer  recharge in monthly water balance models: Water Resources Research, 20(8), p. 1137-1149, illus. (incl.  6 tables), 1984.  Ambroise, Bruno; Amiet, Yves; and Mercier, Jean-Luc. Spatial variability of soil hydrodynamic  properties in the Petite Fecht catchment, Soultzeren, France; preliminary results:  in Catchment  experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 35-53, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch  map), Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  American Farmland Trust. Soil conservation in America, what do we have to lose?: 133 p., illus. (incl.  28 tables), Am. Farmland Trust, Washington, DC, United States, 1984.  Amphlett, M.B. Measurement of soil loss from experimental basins in Malawi: in Proceedings of the  HararSymposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.),  IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 351-362 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1984.  Amundson, Ronald Gene. A chronosequential evaluation of the effects of reclamation on a saline-sodic  soil:  159 p., Doctoral, 1984, Univ. of California, Riverside, CA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Anderson, Ewan W.; and Cox, Nicholas J. The relationship between soil creep rate and certain  controlling variables in a catchment in Upper Weardale, northern England: in Catchment experiments  in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 419-430, illus. (incl. 1 table), Geo Books, Norwich,  United Kingdom, 1984.  Anonymous. Investigation and analysis of problem municipal land application systems in Wisconsin: in  Municipal and industrial waste, Annual Madison Waste Conference Proceedings, 7, separately paginated,  illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1984.  Anton, Danflo. Aspects of geomorphological evolution; Paleosols and dunes in Saudi Arabia:  in  Quaternary period in Saudi Arabia; Volume 2, Sedimentoiogical, hydrogeological, hydrochemical,  geomorphological, geochronological and climatological investigations in western Saudi Arabia (Jado,  Abdul Raof, editor; et aL), p. 275-296, 1 table, sketch map, Springer-Verlag, Vienna, Austria, 1984.  Archer, Warren M. Soil survey of Lyon County area, Nevada: 513 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables, sketch map;  colored soils map 1:380,160; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, 1984. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Forest Sere., U. S. Bur. Land Manage., U. S. Bur.  Indian Affairs, and Univ. Nee. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Ardnino, E.; Barberis, E.; Carraro, F.; et al. Estimating relative ages from iron-oxide/total-iron ratios  of soils in the western Po Valley, Italy: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 39-52, illus. (incl. 19 anal., 7 tables, geol.  sketch map), 1984.  Arvidson, Raymond. Geophysical processes; solid Earth, geology: in Earth observing system; science  and mission requirements, working group report appendix; Volume 1 (Part 2 of 2), NASA Technical  Memorandum, 86129, A28-A30, 1 table, 1984.    360    Baars, Don L.; and Ellingson, J. A. Geology of the western San Juan Mountains:  in Field trip  guidebook; paleotectonics; San Juan Mountains; Dolores Formation; Paleosols and depositional systems;  Jurassic depositional systems; San Juan Basin; Quaternary deposits and soils; Durango area (Brew,  Douglas C., editor), p. 1-45, illus. (incl. sects., strat, cols., geol. sketch map), Geol. Soc. Am., Rocky  Mountain Sect., United States, 1984.  Bagby, W. C.; Pickthorn, W. J.; and Goldfarb, Richard J. Pathfinder elements in soils over the Dee  disseminated gold deposit, ElkoCounty, Nevada [abstr.]: in USGS research on mineral resources, 1985;  program and abstracts (Krafft, Kathleen, editor), Geological Survey Circular, 0949, p. 1, illus., 1985. First  V. E. McKelvey forum on mineral and energy resources.  Bartow, J. Alan. Tertiary nonmarine sedimentation and its role in the evolution of the San Joaquin  Basin, California [abstr.]: in The Geological Society of America, 1984 annual meeting, Abstracts with  Programs - Geological Society of America, 16(6), p. 439, 1984.  Bazant, Zdenek J., Jr. Estimating soil moduli from drilled pier load tests: Journal of Geotechnical  Engineering, 110(9), p. 1323-1341, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Beekmann, G. G. Paleosols, pedoderms, and problems in presenting pedologicai data:  Australian  Geographer, 16(1), p. 15-21, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sects., strat, cols., sketch map), 1984.  Beggs, C.J. A review of investigation and sampling methods in the Recent sediments of Hong Kong:  in Geology of surficial deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of  Hong Kong, 1, p. 13-18, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Belperio, A. P.; Hails, J. R.; Gostin, V. A.; et al. The stratigraphy of coastal carbonate banks and  Holocene sea levels of northern Spencer Gulf, South Australia: in The Spencer Gulf region (Hails, J.  R., editor; et al.), Marine Geology, 61(2-4), p. 297-313, illus., 1984.  Berestovskiy, I. F.; Gitel'son, A. A.; Sabo, D.; et al. Opyt provedeniya podsputnikovykh eksperimentov  na vodnykh ob"ektakh SSSR i VNR [Results of subsatellite experiments on water bodies in the USSR  and Hungary]: Issledovaniye Zemli iz Kosmosa, 1984(5), p. 107-111 (incl. English sum.), 1984.  Billing, N. B.  Palaeosol development in Quaternary marine sediments and palaeoclimatic  interpretations, Spencer Gulf, Australia: in The Spencer Gulf region (Hails, J. R., editor; et al.), Marine  Geology, 61(2-4), p. 315-343, 1984.  Bjorklnnd, A. J. (editor). Geochemical exploration, 1983: Elsevier, Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984.  (Assoc. of Explor. Geochem. Spec. Publ. No. 11).  Blodgett, Robert H. Nonmarine depositional environments and Paieosol development in the Upper  Triassic Dolores Formation, southwestern Colorado: in Field trip guidebook; paleotectonics; San Juan  Mountains; Dolores Formation; Paleosols and depositional systems; Jurassic depositional systems; San  Juan Basin; Quaternary deposits and soils; Durango area (Brew, Douglas C., editor), p. 46-92, illus. (incl.  sketch map), Geol. Soc. Am., Rocky Mountain Sect., United States, 1984.  Bose, S.S. A geochemical approach to delineate target areas for copper mineralization around Kesarpur  in northern Orissa, India: Journal of the Geological Society of India, 25(8), p. 475-483, illus. (incl. 4  tables, geol. sketch map), 1984.  Boyle, R. W.; and Jonasson, I. R. The geochemistry of antimony and its use as an indicator element  in geochemical prospecting: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 20(3), p. 223-302, illus. (incl. 14  tables), 1984.  Brady, Nyle G. The nature and properties of soils, 9th edition: 750 p., illus., Macmillan Publ. Co., New  York, NY, United States, 1984.  Brew, Douglas C. (editor).  Field trip guidebook; paleotcctonics; San Juan Mountains; Dolores  Formation; Paleosols and depositional systems; Jurassic depositional systems; San Juan Basin;  Quaternary deposits and soils; Durango area: 209 p., illus. (incl. sects., strat, cols., sketch maps), Geol.  Soc. Am., Rocky Mountain Sect., United States, 1984.  BHem, Elmar;, and Blumel, Wolf-Dieter.  Midyan region; contributions to the Quaternary  geomorphology of the Ifal Depression:  in Quaternary period in Saudi Arabia; Volume 2,  Sedimentologieal,  hydrogeoiogical,  hydrochemical,  geomorphological,  geochronological  and  climatological investigations in western Saudi Arabia (Jado, Abdul Raof, editor; et al.), p. 47-60, illus.  (incl. 1 table, sects., sketch maps), Springer-Verlag, Vienna, Austria, 1984.    361    Brimicombe, A.J. Computer-stored databases and the analysis of superficial deposits: in Geology of  surficial deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of Hong Kong,  1, p. 19-24, illus., 1984.  Bruggenwert, M. G. M. (reviewer). Principles of soil chemistry: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 83-84, 1984.  Brush, Grace S. Patterns of Recent sediment accumulation in Chesapeake Bay (Virginia-Maryland,  U.S.A.) tributaries:  in Geochronology of Recent deposits; a selection of papers presented to a  Symposium on the geochronology of Recent deposits as part of the Eleventh International Association  of Sedimentologists' congress (Robbins, John A., editor), Chemical Geology, 44(1-3), p. 227-242, illus.  (incl. 5 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Budesheim, Werner. Die entwicklung der mittelalterlichen Kulturlandschaft des heutigen Kreises  Herzogtum Lauenberg unter besonderer Berucksichtigung der slawischen Besiedlung [The development  of the Middle Ages cultural regions in the current region of the Lauenberg dukedom with special  attention to the Slavic colonization]: Mitteilungen der Geographischen GeseUschaft in Hamburg, 74,  270 p., illus. (incl. 1 table, geol. sketch map; colored archaeol, map), 1984.  Burnett, A. D, A proposed framework for the classification and description of superficial deposits: in  Geology of surficial deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of Hong  Kong, 1, p. 5-12, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Bnrt, T. P.; Crabtree, R. W.; and Fielder, N.A. Patterns of hillslope solutional denudation in relation  to the spatial distribution of soil moisture and soil chemistry over a hillslope hollow and spur:  in  Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Butt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 431-445, illus., Geo Books,  Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Buselli, G.; MeCraeken, K. G.; and Ralehe, A. F. Transient electromagnetics in a highly weathered  terrain [abstr.]:  in 1983 annual meeting abstracts, Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Geophysics,  49(5), p. 671, 674, 1984.  Society of Exploration Geophysicis~ 53rd annual international meeting.  Calderoni, Gilberto; and Sehnitzer, Morris. Effects of age on the chemical structure of paleosol humic  acids and fulvic acids: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(10), p. 2045-2051, illus. (incl. 8 tables,  strat, col., sketch map), 1984.  Callen, Roger A.  Clays of the palygorskite-sepiolite group; depositional environment, age and  distribution: in Palygorskite - sepiolite occurrences, genesis and uses (Singer, Arieh, editor; et aL), 37,  p. 1-37, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), Elsevier Sci. Publ., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984.  7th  international clay conference.  Chao, T.T. Use of partial dissolution techniques in geochemical exploration: Journal of Geochemical  Exploration, 20(2), p. 101-135, illus., 1984.  Charles, J. A.; and Sore,s, M. M. The stability of slopes in soils with nonlinear failure envelopes:  Canadian Geotechnical Journal ----- Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, 21 (3), p. 397-406 (incl. French  sum.), illus., 1984.  Chen Yijian; Jiao Wenqiang; and Li Hongchun. Faulting events occurring in Yishu fault zone in the  past 40,000 years; application of the 14C technique to active fault study: Marine Geology &amp; Quaternary  Geology, 4(4), p. 57-66 (Chinese, incl. English sum.), 1984.  Childs, C. W.; Dickson, D. P. E.; Goodman, B. A.; et aL Moessbauer parameters for ferrihydrites at 4  K: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 22(2), p. 149-154, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  ChiIton, P. J.; and Smith-Curington, A.K. Characteristics of the weathered basement aquifer in Malawi  in relation to rural water supplies:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African  hydrology and water resources (Wailing, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 57-72  (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Churchman, G. J.; and Theng, B. K. G. Interactions of halloysites with amides; mineralogical factors  affecting complex formation: Clay Minerals, 19(2), p. 161-175, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1984.  Cole, David R.; and Rose, Arthur W. Distribution and mode of occurrence of zinc and lead in glacial  soils: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 20(2), p. 137-160, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Colhmm, Eric A.; and Moon, Alan. Estuarinc sediments at the Bowen Bridge on the Derwent River,  southeastern Tasmania: Search (Sydney), 15(7-8), p. 224-226, sect., sketch maps, 1984.    362    Collinet, J. Hydrodynamique superficielle et erosion comparees de quelques sols ferrallitiques sur  defriches forestieres traditionnelles (Cote d'Ivoire) [Surficial hydrodynamics and comparative erosion of  ferralitic soils in traditional shifting cultivation; Ivory Coast]: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium;  Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH  Publication, 144, p. 499-516 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Coiliuet, J.; and Valentin, C. Evaluation of factors influencing water erosion in West Africa using rainfall  simulation:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water  resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 451-461 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. 6 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Colombani, J.; and Olivry, J.C. Phenomenes exceptionnels d'erosion et de transport solide en Afrique  aride et semi-aride [Exceptional events in erosion and sediment transport in arid and semiarid Africa]:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling,  D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 295-300 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table),  1984.  Cooper, L. R.; Haverlmtd, R. L.; Hendrieks, D. M.; et al. Microtrac particle-size analyzer; an alternative  particle-size determination method for sediment and soils: Soil Science, 138(2), p. 138-146, illus. (incl.  5 tables), 1984.  Cooper, Terence H. (reviewer). Principles and applications of soil geography: Geoderma, 33(4),p. 346-  347, 1984.  Cortes, E. Determination of rare earth elements in international geochemical reference materials:  Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry, 84(1), p. 157-164, 4 tables, 1984.  Coventry, Ross J.; and Williams, John. Quantitative relationships between morphology and current soil  hydrology in some Alfisols in semiarid tropical Australia: Geoderma, 33(3), p. 191-218, illus. (incl. 4  tables, sketch map), 1984.  Crampton, C. B. Concentric zonation of gleyed soils under individual tree canopies in southwestern  British Columbia, Canada: Geoderma, 32(4), p. 329-334, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  Crowtber, J. Soil carbon dioxide and weathering potentials in tropical karst terrain, Peninsular Malaysia;  a preliminary model: Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 9(5), p. 397-407, illus. (incl. 3 tables,  sketch map), 1984.  Conningham, R. L.; Petersen, G. W.; and Sacksteder, C. J. Microcomputer delivery of soil survey  information: Journal of Soil and Water Conservation, 39(4), p. 241, illus., 1984.  Cushman, Robert A., Jr.; Buehheim, H. Paul; and Fisk, Lanny H. Palynology and oil shale genesis in  Fossil Butte Member of Eocene Green River Formation, Wyoming [abstr.]: in 1984 annual convention  with divisions; SEPM/EMD/DPA, AAPG Bulletin, 68(9), p. 1208, 1984. (late abstract).  Dalrymple, J. B.; and Jim, C: Y. Experimental study of soil microfabrics induced by isotropic stresses  of wetting and drying: Geoderma, 34(1), p. 43-68, illus., 1984.  Dalrymple, J. B.; and Theocharopoulos, S. P.  Intrapedal cutans; experimental production of  depositional (illuviation) channel argillans: Geoderma, 33(3), p. 237-243, illus., 1984.  David, Mark B.; and Driscoll, Charles T. Aluminum speciation and equilibria in soil solutions of a  Haplorthod in the Adirondack Mountains (New York, U.S.A.): Geoderma, 33(4), p. 297-318, illus. (incl.  2 tables), 1984.  Davidson, Gordon M. Site safety at the Middletown Road removal: in Municipal and industrial waste,  Annual Madison Waste Conference Proceedings, 7, p. 267-282, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1984.  De Kimpe, C. R.; Laverdiere, M, R.; Dejou, J.; et aL Effects of acidic and basic parent materials on  formation of some soils in Quebec (Canada): Geoderma, 33(2), p. 101-118, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch  map), 1984.  Dekker, L. W.; Wosten, J. H. M.; and Bourns, J. Characterizing the soil moisture regime of a Typic  Haplohumod: Geoderma, 34(1), p. 37-42, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Delwiche C. C. Global biogeochemical cycles; biogeochemical considerations:  in Earth observing  system; science and mission requirements, working group report appendix; Volume 1 (Part 2 of 2), NASA  Technical Memorandum, 86129, AS-A10, 2 tables, 1984.    363    Demmak, Abdelmadjid.  Recherche d'une relation empirique entre apports solides specifiques et  parametres physico-climatiques des bassins; application all cas algerien [Development of an empirical  relationship between specific sediment discharge and catchment physico-climatic parameters; an  Algerian case study]: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and  water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 403-414 (incl. English  sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Dent, David (reviewer). Constituents and properties of soils: Geoderma, 33(3), p. 257, 1984.  Derbyshire, Edward; Li Jijun; Perrott, Frances Alayne; et al. Quaternary glacial history of the Hunza  Valley, Karakoram Mountains, Pakistan: in The International Karadoram Project; Vol. 2 (Miller, Keith  John), p. 456-495, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sects., strat, cola., sketch maps), Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge,  United Kingdom, 1984.  Ding, C. P.; Liu, Z. G.; and Yu, T. R. Oxidation-reduction regimes in some Oxisols of tropical China:  Geoderma, 32(4), p. 287-295, illus., 1984.  Dobrovorskiy, V.V. Krasnotsvetnyye otlozheniya Severnoy Vengrii [Red-colored deposits of North  Hungary]: Zemlevedeniye. Novaya Seriya, 15(55), p. 107-111, illus. (incl. 1 table, sect.), 1984.  Dorn, Ronald I. Cause and implications of rock varnish microchemical laminations: Nature (London),  310(5980), p. 767-770, illus., 1984.  Dolt, Wakefield, Jr. Quaternary geology, geomorphology, and archaeology; eastern Snake River plain  and adjacent mountains: in Geology, tectonics, and mineral resources of western and southern Idaho  (Beaver, Patricia C., editor), Guidebook of the Annual Tobacco Root Geological Society Field  Conference, 9, p. 6-12, sketch map, 1984.  Dragovich, D. The survival of desert varnish in subsurface positions, western New South Wales,  Australia: Earth Surfaces Processes and Landforms, 9(5), p. 425-434, illus. (incl. 1 table, 3 plates, sketch  map), 1984.  Dreschhoff, Gisela A. M.; Siegel, Frederic R.; Vas, Edurdo; et al. Field test of thermoluminescence  dosimeters for measurement of the natural radiation environment on Ross Island: Antarctic Journal of  the United States, 18(5), p. 45-46, 1 table, 1984. (1983 review).  Dugan, Jack T. Hydrologic characteristics of Nebraska soils: Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper  (Washington), 2222, 19 p., 3 tables, sketch maps, soils map 1:750,000, soils maps h250,000, 1984.  Durgin, Philip B. Subsurface drainage erode forested granitic terrane: Physical Geography, 5(1), p. 24-  39, illus., 1984.  Dvornikova, L. L.  Ob usloviyakh formirovaniya pochv yugo-zapadnoy chasti yuzhno-tayezhnoy  podzony (ha primere Sablinskoy stantsii LGU). [Formation of soils in the southwestern part of the south  taiga subzone; Sablinsky Station, Leningrad University]:  Vestnik Leningradskogo Universiteta.  Geologiya-Geografiya, 12(2), p. 73-79, 3 tables, 1984.  Egboka, B. C. E.; and Okpoko, E. I. Gully erosion in the Agulu-Nanka region of Anambra State,  Nigeria: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources  (Walling, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 335-347 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl.  sect., sketch maps), 1984.  Ellies, A.; and Oayoso, J. Verdichtung yon Proben eines Dystrandepts und Palehumults aus Sudchile  [Compressibility of Dystrandept and Palehumult samples from southern Chile]: Geoderma, 33(3), p.  227-235 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1984.  Elwell, H.A. Sheet erosion from arable lands in Zimbabwe; prediction and control: in Proceedings of  the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et  a/.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 429-438 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. I table), 1984.  Engler, M. L.; and Fenton, P.J. Seismic profiling using a laser/inertial terrain profiler [abstr.]: in 1983  annual meeting abstracts, Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Geophysics, 49(5), p. 656, 1984. Society  of Exploration Geophysicist~ 53rd annual international meeting.  Ertel, John R.; and Hedges, John I. The lignin component of humic substances; distribution among soil  and sedimentary humic, fulvic, and base-insoluble fractions: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(10),  p. 2065-2074, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.    364    Fei Qi; and Wang Xie-Pei. Significant role of structural fractures in Renqiu buried-hill oil field in eastern  China: AAPG Bulletin, 68(8), p. 971-982, illus. (incl. sects., geol. sketch maps), 1984.  Fergason, Dick V.; McFadden, Clarence E.; and Brown, James H. Soil survey of Sharp County,  Arkansas: 111 p., illus. (incl. 16 tables, sketch map; colored soils mpa 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1984. (Prep. in coop. with Ark.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Finial, Charles W., Jr.  Chronology of weathered materials and soil age determination in  pedostratigraphic sequences: in Geochronology of Recent deposits; a selection of papers presented to  a Symposium on the geochronology of Recent deposits as part of the Eleventh International Association  of Sedimentologists' congress (Robbins, John A., editor), Chemical Geology, 44(1-3), p. 311-335, illus.  (incl. 13 analyses, 1 table), 1984.  Fisher, G.C.;andgam, Oi-Lai. Iron mobilization by heathland plant extracts: Geoderma, 32(4),p. 339-  345, 3 tables, 1984.  Flieoteoux, Rene; and Lueas, Jacques. Weathering of phosphate minerals: in Phosphate minerals; their  properties and general modes of occurrence (Nriagu, Jerome O., editor; et aL), p. 292-317, illus. (incl.  6 tables, strat, cols., sect. geol. sketch map), Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany, 1984.  Foster, I. D. L,; and Grieve, I. C.  Some implications of small catchment solute studies for  geomorphological research: in Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Butt, T. P., editor; et  a, p. 359-378, illus. (incl. 6 tables, sketch map), Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Frank, Thomas D. The effect of change in vegetation cover and erosion patterns on albedo and texture  of Landsat images in a semiarid environment: Annals of the Association of American Geographers,  74(3), p. 393-407, illus. (incl. 8 tables, geol. sketch maps), 1984.  Fredlund, D.G. Consolidation of unsaturated porous media: in Fundamentals of transport phenomena  in porous media (Bear, Jacob, editor; et a, p. 525-578, illus., Martinus Nijhoff Publ., Dordrecht,  Netherlands, 1984.  NATO Advanced Study Institute on Mechanics of fluids in porous media.  Fried, Gunter. Gestein, Relief und Boden im Buntsandstein, Odenwald [Rock, relief and soils in Bunter,  Odenwald]: Frankfurter Geowissenschaftliche Arbeiten, Serie D: Physische Geographic, 4, 201 p., illus.  (incl. 11 tables, sects.), 1984.  Fnraes, Harold. Chemical changes during progressive subaerial palagonitization of a subglacial olivine  tholeiite hyaloclastite; a microprobe study: Chemical Geology, 43(3-4), p. 271-285, illus. (incl. 8 tables),  1984.  Gallic, T, M.; and Slaymaker, H. Olav. Variable solute sources and hydrological pathways in a coastal  subalpine environment: in Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P.,editor; etal.),  p. 347-357, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Gammon, J. R.A. Weathering of shoreline rock masses; an introduction: inGeology of surficial deposits  in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of Hong Kong, 1, p. 35-47, illus.  (incl. strat, cols., sects., geol. sketch map), 1984.  Gun Guorui.  The microstructure of loess soil in China relative to its geographic and geologic  environment: Dizhixue Boo = Acts Geologies Sinica, 58(3), p. 265-272 (Chinese, incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. 2 tables, 2 plates, geol. sketch map), 1984.  Garcia-Mirogaya, J. Levels, chemical fractionation, and solubility of lead in roadside soils of Caracas,  Venezuela: Soil Science, 138(2), p. 147-152, illus. (incl. 3 tables), I984.  Gardner, A. R.; Jones, R. H.; and Harris, J. S. A new creep equation for frozen soils and ice: Cold  Regions Science and Technology, 9(3), p. 271-275, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Gibbons, Boyd. Do we treat our soil like dirt?: National Geographic, 166(3), p. 351-389, illus., 1984.  Gillam, Mary L.; Moore, David W.; and Scott, Glenn R. Quaternary deposits and soils in the Durango  area, southwestern Colorado:  in Field trip guidebook; paleotectonics; San Juan Mountains; Dolores  Formation; Paleosols and depositional systems; Jurassic depositional systems; San Juan Basin;  Quaternary deposits and soils; Durango area (Brew, Douglas C., editor), p. 149, illus. (incl. 5 tables,  sketch maps), Geol. Soc. Am., Rocky Mountain Sect., United States, 1984.  Giordano, Andrea.  Some methods for evaluating soil erosion risk:  in Proceedings of the Harare  Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-  AISH Publication, 144, p. 385-395 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1984.    365    Glushko, Ye. V.; and Kondrat'yeva, T.I. Kompleksnoye kartografirovaniye aridnykh tcrritoriy Arizony  po kosmicheskim snimkam [Complex mapping of arid territories of Arizona using cosmic photographs]:  Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5: Geografiya, 1984(3), p. 72-77 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. geol. sketch map), 1984.  Guldbery, R.; and Beyth, M. Lateritization and ground water alteration phenomena in the Triassic  Budra Formation, south-western Sinai: Sedimentoiogy, 31(4), p. 575-594, 1984.  Golestaneh, F.; and Hakim, M. Kaolin als Zersetzungsprodukt der tertiaren Vulkanite im Iran [Kaolin  as a disintegration product of Tertiary volcanic rocks in Iran] [abstr.]:  in Referate der Vortraage und  Poster auf der 62. Jahrestagung der Deutschen Mineralogischen GeseUschaft, gemeinsam mitder  Osterreichischen Mineralogischen Gesellschaft und der Schweizerischen Mineralogischen and  Petrographischen Gesellschaft, Fortschritte der Mineralogie, Beiheft, 62(1), p. 76, 1984.  Gosselink, J. G.; Hatton, R.; and Hopkinson, C.S. Relationship of organic carbon and mineral content  to bulk density in Louisiana marsh soils: Soil Science, 137(3), p. 177-180, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Gust'in, V. A.; Sargent, G. E. G.; and Hails, J. R, Quaternary seismic stratigraphy of northern Spencer  Gulf, South Australia: in The Spencer Gulf region (Hails, J. R.,editor; etaL),MarineGeology, 61(2-4),  p. 167-179, 1984.  Goudie, Andrew Shaw.  Salt efflorescences and salt weathering in the Hunza Valley, Karakoram  Mountains, Pakistan: in The International Karadoram Project; Vol. 2 (Miller, Keith John), p. 607-615,  6 tables, sketch map, Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 1984.  Goudie, Andrew Shaw; Brnasden, Denys; Collins, David Nigel; et al. The geomorphology of the Hunza  Valley, Karakoram Mountains, Pakistan: in The International Karadoram Project; Vol. 2 (Miller, Keith  John), p. 359-410, illus. (incl. 9 tables, sects., sketch maps), Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge, United  Kingdom, 1984.  Goudie, Andrew Shaw; Rendell, Helen M.; and Bull, P.A. The loess of Tajik SSR: inThelnternational  Karakoram Project; VoL 1 (Miller, Keith John), p. 399-412, illus. (incl. 1 table, sects., strat, cols., sketdh  map), Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 1984.  The International Karakoram Project.  Grolier, Mauriee J.; Tlbbitts, G. C., Jr.; and Ibrahim, Mohammed Makred. A qualitative appraisal of  the hydrology of the Yemen Arab Republic from Landsat images: Geological Survey Water-Supply  Paper (Washington), 1757-P, p. PI-P70, illus. (incl. 3 tables, geol. sketch map; colored map 1:500,000),  1984.  Gruneberg, Frmm; Laken, Halo; and Muller, Warner. Bodenkunde [Soil science]:  in 25 Jahre  Bundesanstalt fur Geowissenschaften  und  Rohstoffe  und  Niedersachsisches  Landesamt fur  Bodenforschung (Bender, Friedrich, prefacer; et aL), Geoiogisches Jahrbuch. Reihe A: Allgemeine und  Regionale Geologic BR Deutschland und Nachbargebiete, Tektonik, Stratigraphie, Palaontologie, 73, p.  143-167, illus. (incl. 3 tables; index map), 1984. Festueranstahung.  Gul'yants, G. M.; and Avakyan, A. Kh. Vliyaniye uglekislogo gaza mineral'nykh rod na tsementnyy  kamen' [Effects of carbon dioxide gases in mineral water on cement rocks]: Izvestiya Akademii Nauk  Armyanskoy SSR, Nauki o Zemle, 37(2), p. 73-77, 2 tables, 1984.  Gapta, R. K.; Bhumbla, D. K.; and Abrul, I.P. Sodium-calcium exchange equilibria in soils as affected  by calcium carbonate and organic matter: Soil Science, 138(2), p. 109-114, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Gut-nell, A. M.; and Gregory, K. J. The influence of vegetation on stream channel processes:  in  Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 515-535, illus. (incl. 3  tables, sketch maps), Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Haigh, Martin J. Microerosion processes and sediment mobilization in a roadbank gully catchment in  centralOklahoma: inCatchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 247-  264, illus. (incl. 2 tables), Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Hails, J. R.; Beiperio, A. P.; GosUn, V. A.; et aL The submarine Quaternary stratigraphy of northern  Spencer Gulf, South Australia: inThe Spencer Gulf region (Hails, J. R., editor; etaL), Marine Geology,  61(2-4), p. 345-372, 1984.  Hall, N. T.; and Harms, K. K. Uncertainties in slip-rates determination for the Pleito thrust fault,  northern Transverse Ranges, California [abstr.]:  in Eastern Section of the Seismological Society of  America, Earthquake Notes, 55, p. 9, 1984.    366    Hamilton, Thomas D.; Ashley, Gall M.; Reed, Katherine M.; et al. Stratigraphy and sedimentology of  Epiguruk Bluff; a preliminary account:  in The United States Geological Survey in Alaska;  accomplishments during 1982 (Reed, Katherine M., editor; et al.), Geological Survey Circular, 0939, p.  12-14, sect., sketch map, 1984.  Happs, John C. Soil genesis and development; views held by New Zealand students: Journal of  Geography, 83(4), p. 177-180, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Harden, Jennifer W.  Techniques and uncertainties in using soil development for stratigraphic,  geomorphic and age analyses [abstr.]:  in Eastern Section of the Seismological Society of America,  Earthquake Notes, 55, p. 7, 1984.  Harms, K. K.; Harden, Jennifer W.; Hoose, S. N.; et al. Estimating slip rates along the Calaveras Fault,  California, using soil chronology and geometry of stream terraces [abstr.]:  in Eastern Section of the  Seismological Society of America, Earthquake Notes, 55, p. 9, 1984.  Haynes, R. J.; and Swift, R. S. Amounts and forms of micronutrient cations in a group of loessial  grassland soils of New Zealand: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 53-62, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Hazlett, P. W.; Rutherford, G. K.; and Van Loon, G. W. Characteristics of soil profiles afected by  smelting of nickel and copper at Coniston, Ontario, Canada: Geoderma, 32(4), p. 273-285, illus. (incl.  2 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Hedstrom, Gary T.; and Popp, David J. Soil survey of Waldo County, Maine: 158 p., illus. (incl. 18  tables, sketch map; colored soils map 1:253,440; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1984. (Publ. in coop. with Me. Agric. Exp. Stn. and Me. Soil and  Water Conserv. Comm.).  Hegedus, Ervin; and Khosla, Vijay K.  Pullout resistance of "H" piles:  Journal of Geotechnical  Engineering, 110(9), p. 1274-1290, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1984.  Herzog, Beverly L.; and Morse, Walter J. A comparison of laboratory and field determined values of  hydraulic conductivity at a waste disposal site: in Municipal and industrial waste, Annual Madison  Waste Conference Proceedings, 7, p. 30-52, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sect., sketch map), 1984.  Hiekey, M. G.; and Kittrick, J.A. Chemical partitioning of cadmium, copper, nickel, and zinc in soils  and sediments containing high levels of heavy metals: Journal of Environmental Quality, 13(3),p. 372-  376, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Hickin, Edward J,  Vegetation and river channel dynamics:  The Canadian Geographer = Le  Geographe Canadien, 28(2), p. 111-126 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1984.  Hinkle, Margaret E.; and Dilbert, Clifford A. Gases and trace elements in soils at the North Silver Bell  Deposit, Pima County, Arizona: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 20(3), p. 323-336, illus. (incl. 1  table, sketch maps), 1984.  Hodge, T.; Turebenek, L. W.; and Oades, J. M. Occurrence of palygorskite in ground-water Rendzinas  (petrocalcic calciaquolls) in South-East South Australia: in Palygorskite - sepiolite occarrences, genesis  and uses (Singer, Arieh, editor; et al.), 37, p. 199-210, illus. (incl. 3 tables, 2 plates, sect., sketch map),  Elsevier Sci. Publ., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984.  7th international clay conference.  Hofmann, W.; and Fiedler, H.J. Reliefabhangige Bodengenese auf Gneis im Sachsischen Erzgebirge  [Relief-dependent soil genesis on gneiss in the Saxon Erzgebirge]: Chemie der Erde, 43(3), p. 205-215  (incl. English sum.), 8 tables, 1984.  Hooffstetter, Loals;andCarew, JamesL. Paleosols of San Salvador, Bahamas[abstr.]: inFifty-scventh  annual meeting of the South Carolina Academy of Science (Cowley, Gerald T., president), Bulletin of  the South Carolina Academy of Science, 46, p. 101-102, 1984.  Hopkins, R. T.; Tucker, Robert E.; Roemer, T. A.; et al. Analytical results from a geochemical survey  of St. Thomas and St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands, using soil, rock, and panned concentrate samples: Open-  File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), 66 p., 7 tables, sketch maps, 1984. (Rep. No. OF  84-0785) available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch, Fed. Cent.,  Denver, CO, United States.  Huddleston, J.H. Development and use of soil productivity ratings in the United States: Geoderma,  32(4), p. 297-317, 1984.    367    Hal, S. S. F. Geological recognition of a colluvial deposit at Woodland Heights, Happy Valley, Hong  Kong: in Geology of surficial deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological  Society of Hong Kong, 1, p. 87-91, illus. (incl. geol. sketch map), 1984.  Hussaln, M. S.; Amadi, T. H.; and Sulalman, M. S. Characteristics of soils of a toposequence in  northeastern Iraq: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 63-82, illus. (incl. 6 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Huyakorn, P. S.; Thomas, S. D.; and Thompson, B. M. Techniques for making finite elements  competitive in modeling flow in variably saturated porous: Water Resources Research, 20(8), p. 1099-  1115, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1984.  Iniguez, Jalme; and Val, Rosa M. Evaluation of phosphorus sorption by an allophanic soil: Geoderma,  33(2), p. 119-134, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Jamagne, M.; De Coninck, F.; Robert, M.; et al. Mineralogy of clay fractions of some soils on loess in  northern France: Geoderma, 33(4), p. 319-342, illus. (incl. 12 tables), 1984.  Jayawardane, N. S.; Meyer, W. S.; and Barrs, H.D. Moisture measurement in a swelling clay soil using  neutron moisture meters: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 22(2), p. 109-117, 6 tables, 1984.  Johnson, Noye M.; Likens, Gene E.; Feller, Michael C.; et al. Acid rain and soil chemistry: Science,  225(4669), p. 1424-1434, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Jones, K. C.; Peterson, P. J.; and Davies, B. E. Extraction of silver from soils and its determination  by atomic absorption spectrometry: Geoderma, 33(2), p. 157-168, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1984.  Judson, S. (reviewer). Soil erosion: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 85-86, 1984.  Jungerius, P. D.; and van Zon, H. J.M. Sources of variation of soil erodibility in wooded drainage basins  in Luxembourg: in Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 235-  246, 5 tables, Geo Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Jurinak, J. J.; Amrkein, C.; and Wagenet, R.J. Sodic hazard; the effect of SAR and salinity in soils  and overburden materials: Soil Science, 137(3), p. 152-159, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1984.  Kabata-Pendias, Alina; and Pendias, Henryk. Trace elements in soils and plants: 315 p., illus. (incl.  tables), CRC Press, Boca Raton, FL, United States, 1984.  Kachanoski, Reginald Gary. Spatial and spectral relationships of soil and soil forming factors: 121 p.,  Doctoral, 1984, Univ. of California, Davis, CA. available frorrc Univ. Microfilms.  Kawamura, Masayori. A geothermal cause for anomalous ground surface temperature patterns derived  from aerial infrared images around Mt. Waita in central Kyushu:  Butsuri-Tanko, 37(1), p. 27-41  (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Keeeh, M. A. (reviewer). Handbook on soil resistivity surveying; interpretation of data of earthen  archaeological sites: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 83, 1984.  Kempe, Stephan. Sinks of the anthropogenically enhanced carbon cycle in surface fresh waters: JGR.  Journal of Geophysical Research. D. Atmospheres, 89(3), p. 4657-4676, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Kendall, Douglas S.; Lowry, Joe H.; Boar, Edward L.; etal. A comparison of trace metal determinations  in contaminated soils by XRF and ICAP spectroscopies:  in Proceedings of the thirty-second annual  conference on applications of X-ray analysis (Cohen, Jerome B., editor; et aL), Advances in X-Ray  Analysis, 27, p. 467-473, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  King, Harley D.; Curtin, Gary C.; and Shacklette, Hansford T. Metal uptake by young conifer trees:  Geological Survey Bulletin (Washington), 1617, 23 p., illus. (incl. 9 tables), 1984.  Kiselev, I. I.  Vyvetrelyy oblomochnyy material v morenakh Korskogo poluostrova i yego  paleogeograficheskoye [Weathering products in moraines of the Kola Peninsula and its paleogeographic  interpretation]: lzvestiya Vsesoyuznogo Geograficheskogo Obshchestva, 116(3), p. 256-262, illus. (incl.  2 tables), 1984.  Kuntze, Herbert; and Bartels, Rudiger. Bodentechnologie [Soil technology]: in25 Jahre Bundesanstalt  fur Geowissenschaften und Rohstoffe und Niedersachsisches Landesamt fur Bodenforschung (Bender,  Friedrich, prefacer; et aL), Geologisches Jahrbuch. Reihe A: Allgemeine und Regionale Geologie BR  Deutschland und Nachbargebiete, Tektonik, Stratigraphie, Palaontologie, 73, p. 169-181, illus. (incl. 4  tables), 1984.  Festueranstaltung.  Kusaka, Yuzuru; Tsuji, Haruo; Tamari, Yazo; et al. Studies on chemical species dissolved in the shallow  groundwaters of Arima Rhyolite strata: Rikusuigaku Zasshi = Japanese Journal of Limnology, 45(2),  p. 93-99 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables, geol. sketch map), 1984.    368    LaBreeque, J. J.; and Preiss, Ivor L. Determination of barium and selected rare-earth elements in  geological materials employing a HpGe detector by radioisotope excited X-ray fluorescence:  in  Proceedings of the thirty-second annual conference on applications of X-ray analysis (Cohen, Jerome  B., editor; et al.), Advances in X-Ray Analysis, 27, p. 475-480, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Lai, K. W.; and Taylor, B.W. The classification of colluvium in Hong Kong: in Geology of surficial  deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of Hong Kong, 1, p. 75-  85, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Lal, R. Mulch requirements for erosion control with the no-till system in the tropics; a review:  in  Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling,  D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 475-484 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1984.  Lal, R. Effects of slope length on erosion of some Alfisols in Western Nigeria: Geoderma, 33(3), p.  181-189, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  LaMarehe, Valmore C., Jr.; Graybill, Donald A.; Fritts, Harold C.; et al. Increasing atmospheric carbon  dioxide; tree ring evidence for growth enhancement in natural vegetation: Science, 225(4666), p. 1019-  1021, illus., 1984.  Law, Dennis L. Mined-land rehabilitation: 184 p., illus. (incl. tables, charts, sects., sketch maps), Van  Nostrand Reinhold Co., New York, NY, United States, 1984.  Ledgard, S. F.; Freney, J. R.; and Simpson, J.R. Variations in natural enrichment of 15N in the profiles  of some Australian pasture soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research, 22(2), p. 155-164, illus. (incl. 4  tables), 1984.  Leitman, H. M. Forest map and hydrologic conditions, Apalachicola River flood plain, Florida:  Hydrologic Investigations Atlas, HA-0672, 1 sheet, map 1:100,000, 1984 [1985].  Lewis, Glenn C.; Fosberg, Maynard A.; Falen, A. L.; et al. Identification of loess by particle size  distribution using the Coulter counter TA II: Soil Science, 137(3),p. 172-176, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Li, Yuan-Hal; Teraoka, Hisayuki; Yang, Tsuo-Sheng; et al. The elemental composition of suspended  particles from the Yellow and Yangtze rivers: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(7), p. 1561-1564,  illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch maps), 1984.  Lia, K. H.; and Gammon, J. R.A. Quaternary geology, weathering and geomorphology of Hong Kong:  in Geology of surficial deposits in Hong Kong (Yim, W. W. S., editor), Bulletin - Geological Society of  Hong Kong, 1, p. 49-59, illus. (incl. 1 table, sects., sketch map), 1984.  Low, AHson J.; Low, Eric J.; and Douglas, Lowell A. A motorized grinder for making soil thin sections:  Geoderma, 32(4), p. 335-337, illus., 1984.  MacKenzie, R. C.; Wilson, M. J.; and Mashhady, A. S. Origin of palygorskite in some soils of the  Arabian Peninsula: in Palygorskite - sepiolite occurrences, genesis and uses (Singer, Arieh, editor; et al.),  37, p. 177-186, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), Elsevier Sci. Pubi., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984. 7th  international clay conference.  Madison, Patrick James. The feasibility of satellite remote sensing as a technique for evaluating coal  mine surface features: 133p, Doctoral, 1984, Indiana State Univ., Terre Haute, IN. availablefrom:Univ.  Microfilms.  Mahnra, Yasanori; and Miyahara, Shojiro. Residual plutonium migration in soil of Nagasaki: JGR.  Journal of Geophysical Research. B, 89(9), p. 7931-7936, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Maltar, John A. Oil spill debris disposal [abstr.]: in Seventh annual winter meeting of the Vermont  Geological Society (Doolan, Barry L., convener), The Green Mountain Geologist, 10(4), p. 7-8, 1984.  Marshall, P.; Rasor, E.; Lawson, Donna; et al. Investigation of breccia facies, San Salvador, Bahamas  [ahstr.]:  in Fifty-seventh annual meeting of the South Carolina Academy of Science (Cowley, Gerald  T., president), Bulletin of the South Carolina Academy of Science, 46, p. 109, 1984.  Mayer, Larry. Constraints on slip-rate determinations based on geomorphologic investigations in the  Southwestern U.S. [abstr.]:  in Eastern Section of the Seismological Society of America, Earthquake  Notes, 55, p. 8, 1984.  Maynard, J. Barry. Composition of plagioclase feldspar in modern deep-sea sands; relationship to  tectonic setting: Sedimentology, 31(4), p. 493-501, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1984.    369    McConnell, James B.; Hicks, DavidW.;Lowe, Luis E.; etal. Investigation ofethylene dibromide (EDB)  in ground water in Seminole County, Georgia: Geological Survey Circular, 0933, 20 p., illus. (incl. 5  tables, sketch maps), 1984.  McDonald, L. M.; and Raymond, G. P. Repetitive load testing; reversal or rotation: Canadian  Geotechnical Journal ~ Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, 21 (3), p. 456-474 (incl. French sum.), illus.  (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  MeFarlane, M.J. International Interdisciplinary Laterite Reference Collection; (IILRC): Newsletter  - I. G. C. P. Project 129: Lateritisation Processes, 6, p. 13-21, 1984.  McIver, Richard D. Near-surface hydrocarbon surveys in oil and gas exploration: Oil and Gas Journal,  82(39), p. 115-117, illus., 1984.  MeKeague, J. A.; Eilers, R. G.; Thomasson, A. J.; et aL Tentative assessment of soil survey approaches  to the characterization annd interpretation of air-water properties of soils: Geoderma, 34(1), p. 69-100,  illus. (incl. 13 tables), 1984.  MeTainsh, Grant. The nature and origin of the aeolian mantles of central Northern Nigeria: Geoderma,  33(1), p. 13-37, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1984.  Medus, Jueques. Essai de reconstitution de la vegetation et du climat holocenes de la cote Septentrionale  du senegal [Reconstruction of the Holocene vegetation and climate of the northern Senegal coast]:  Review of Palaeobotany and Palynology, 41 (1-2), p. 31-38 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sect. sketch  map), 1984.  Mil'hov, F. N.  Pravilo triady v fizicheskoy geografii [The triad rule in physical geography]:  Zemlevedeniye. Novaya Seriya, 15(55), p. 18-25, illus., 1984.  MilHngton, A. C. Indigenous soil conservation studies in Sierra Leone: in Proceedings of the Harare  Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-  AISH Publication, 144, p. 529-538 (incl. French sum.), 5 tables, 1984.  Millington, A. C.; and Townshend, J. R. G. Remote sensing applications in African erosion and  sedimentaton studies: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and  water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 373-384 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Milly, P. C.D. A linear analysis of thermal effects on evaporation from soil: Water Resources Research,  20(8), p. 1075-1085, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Mokma, D. L.; and Abdulla, O. H.D. Classification of five pedons near Afgoi, Somalia: Geoderma,  33(3), p. 219-226, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Moon, B. P. The forms of rock slopes in the Cape fold mountains: South African Geographical Journal,  66(1), p. 16-31, illus., 1984.  Moore, David W.; and Giilam, Mary L. Road Log; Quaternary deposits and soils in the Durango area,  southwestern Colorado:  in Field trip guidebook; paleotectonics; San Juan Mountains; Dolores  Formation; Paleosols and depositional systems; Jurassic depositional systems; San Juan Basin;  Quaternary deposits and soils; Durango area (Brew, Douglas C., editor), p. 183-209, illus. (incl. 2 tables,  sketch maps), Geol. Soc. Am., Rocky Mountain Sect., United States, 1984.  Muhle, K.; and Stiehl, G. Die Anwendung der isotopenverhaltnisse yon Wasserstoff, Kohlenstoff,  Stickstoff und Sauerstoff als Hilfsmittel bei der Klarung sicherheitstechnischer Fragen in der  geologischen Praxis [The application of H-, C-, N- and O-isotopic ratios as a tool to clear up questions  of safety in the geological industry]: in Isotope und ihre Anwendung in den Geowissenschaften, in der  Bergbausicherheit und im Umweltschutz (Rosler, H. J., prefacer; et al.), Freiberger Forschungshefte,  Reihe C: Geowissenschaften, Mineralogie-Geochemie, 389, p. 174-18 (incl. English, Russian sum.), illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Nakamul'a, Sakalchi. Soil survey of American Samoa: 95 p., illus. (incl. 11 tables; colored soils maps  1:126,720; colored soils maps h24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1984.  Nesbitt, H. Wayne; and Young, G. M. Prediction of some weathering trends of plutonic and volcanic  rocks based on thermodynamic and kinetic considerations: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(7),  p. 1523-1534, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.    370    Ngatunga, E. L. N.; Lal, R.; and Uriyo, A.P. Effects of surface management on runoff and soil erosion  from some plots at Mlingano, Tanzania: Geoderma, 33(1), p. 1-12, 9 tables, 1984.  Nguyen Tranh. The composition and structure of the Quaternary crusts of weathering on the ultrabasic  and basic rocks in the humid tropical regions: International Geology Review, 26(2), p. 178-188, illus.  (incl. 25 anal., 2 tables, geol. sketch map), 1984.  Nixon, (Deriek) J. F.; and Lem, G. Creep and strength testing of frozen saline fine-grained soils:  Canadian Geotechnical Journal = Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, 21(3), p. 518-529 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Nkedi-Kizza, P.; Blggar, J. W.; Selim, H. M.; et al. On the equivalence of two conceptual models for  describing ion exchange during transport through an aggregated Oxisol: Water Resources Research,  20(8), p. 1123-1130, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Nriap, Jerome O.  Formation and stability of base metal phosphates in soils and sediments:  in  Phosphate minerals; their properties and general modes of occurrence (Nriagu, Jerome O., editor; et al.),  p. 318-329, illus. (incl. 1 table), Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany, 1984.  Nyehas, Anastasios E.; and Kosmas, Constantinos S. Phosphate adsorption by dark alkaline Vertisols  in Greece: Geoderma, 32(4), p. 319-327, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  O'Connor, G.A. Characterizing solute retention in New Mexico soils:  in Selected papers on water  quality and pollution in New Mexico (Stone, William J., compiler), Hydrologic Report - New Mexico  Bureau of Mines and Mineral Resources, 7, p. 260-270, 1 table, 1984.  Olorunfemi, B.N. Mineralogical and physico-chemical properties of Niger Delta soils in relation with  geotechnical problems: Journal of African Earth Sciences, 2(3), p. 259-266, illus. (incl. 4 tables, 6 plates,  geol. sketch map), 1984.  Olorunfemi, B. N.; and Fyfe, W. S. Factors influencing the geochemistry of surface sediments in the  supratidal Niger Delta: Journal of African Earth Sciences, 2(3), p. 247-258, illus. (incl. 50 anal., 4 tables,  geol. sketch maps), 1984.  Onstad, C. A.; Kilewe, A. M.; and Ulsaker, L. G. An approach to testing the USLE factor values in  Kenya: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources  (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 439-450 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl.  6 tables), 1984.  Osborne, R. A.L. Multiple karstification in the Lachlan fold belt in New South Wales; reconnaissance  evidence: Journal and Proceedings of the Royal Society of New South Wales, 117(1&amp;2), p. 15-34, illus.  (incl. strat, cols., geol. sketch map), 1984.  Paal, "lamas; Post, J. L.; Nagaraj, T. S.; et al. Critical reappraisal of plasticity index of soils: Journal  of Geoteehnical Engineering, 110(9), p. 1367-1370, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  Papa~ianakis, A. T.; and Fredlund, D. G. A steady state model for flow in saturated-unsaturated soils:  Canadian Geotechnical Journal = Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, 21 (3), p. 419-430 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Pawluk, S. (reviewer). Soil micromorphology; Vol. 1, Techniques and applications; Vol. 2, Soil genesis:  Geoderma, 33(4), p. 344-346, 1984.  Pearson, Charles E. Late prehistoric settlement systems on Ossabaw Island, Georgia: in Excursions  in Southeastern geology; the archaeology-geology of the Georgia coast (Howard, James D., editor; et aL),  p. 179-191, illus. (incl. sketch maps), Geol. Soc. Am., Boulder, CO, United States, 1984. (Guidebook 20).  Pena, F.; and Torrent, J. Relationships between phosphate sorption and iron oxides in Alfisols from  a river terrace sequence of Mediterranean Spain: Geoderma, 33(4), p. 283-296, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1984.  Perdue, E. M. Analytical constraints on the structural features of humic substances: Geochimica et  Cosmochimica Acta, 48(7), p. 1435-1442, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1984.  Perrott, Frances Alayne; and Goudie, Andre Shaw. Techniques for the study of glacial fluctuations: in  The International Karakoram Project; Vol. 1 (Miller, Keith John), p. 94-100, illus. (incl. sketch maps),  Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 1984.  The International Karakoram Project.  Phillips, Fred M.; Trotman, Kenneth N.; Bentley, Harold W.; et al. The bomb-36 C1 pulse as a tracer  for soil-water movement near Socorro, New Mexico: in Selected papers on water quality and pollution  in New Mexico (Stone, William J., compiler), Hydrologic Report - New Mexico Bureau of Mines and  Mineral Resources, 7, p. 271-280, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.    371    Pope, Kevin O.; and van Andel, Tjeerd H. Late Quaternary alluviation and soil formation in the  southern Argolid; its history, canses and archaeological implications: Journal of Archaeological Science,  11(4), p. 281-306, illus. (incl. strat, cols., geol. sketch map), 1984.  Popov, A. I. O dislokatsiyakh i kriolitogeneze v pleystotsene sevarnoy Evrazii [Dislocations and  cryogenesis in the Pleistocene of northern Eurasia]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5:  Geografiya, 1984(3), 3-9 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1984.  Potter, Noel, Jr.; and Wilson, Scott C. Glacial geology and soils in Beacon Valley: Antarctic Journal  of the United States, 18(5), p. 100-103, 2 tables, sketch map, 1984. (1983 review).  Preston, C. M.; Dudley, R. L.; Fyfe, C. A.; et al. Effects of variations in contact times and copper  contents in a 13C CPMAS NMR study of samples of four organic soils: Geoderma, 33(3), p. 245-253,  illus., 1984.  Price, Paul Ross. Size fraction distribution of radium-226 in soils: 32 p., Bachelor's, 1984, Carleton  Univ., Ottawa, ON, Canada.  Purushottam, A.; Murty, B. V. S. R.; Chandra, S.; et al. A modified sequential extraction technique and  its usefulness in geochemical exploration: Journal of the Geological Society of India, 25(7), p. 414-426,  illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Purvis, A. C.  Metamorphosed altered komatites at Mount Martin, Western Australia; Axchaen  weathering products metamorphosed at the aluminosilicate triple point: Australian Journal of Earth  Sciences, 31(1), p. 91-106, illus. (incl. 13 tables, geol. sketch map), 1984.  Pye, Kenneth; Goudie, A. S.; and Thomas, D. S. G. A test of petrological control in the development  of bornhardts and koppics on the Matopos Batholith, Zimbabwe:  Earth Surfaces Processes and  Landforms, 9(5), p. 455-467, illus. (incl. 40 analyses, 2 tables, geol. sketch map), 1984.  Ragnarsdottir, Kristin Vala; Walther, John V.; and Arnorsson, Stefan. Description and interpretation  of the composition of fluid and alteration mineralogy in the geothermal system, at Svartsengi, Iceland:  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(7), p. 1535-1553, illus. (incl. 8 tables, sect., geol. sketch map),  1984.  Ralnes, Gary L.; McGee, Linda G.; and Sutley, Steven J. Spectra of massive sulfide gossan and false  gossan in the near infrared (800 nm to 2500 nm) [abstr.]: in USGS research on mineral resources, 1985;  program and abstracts (Krafft, Kathleen, editor), Geological Survey Circular, 0949, p. 44-45, 1985. First  V. E. McKelvey forum on mineral and energy resourcez  Rango, Albert. Global hydrologic cycle: in Earth observing system; science and mission requirements,  working group report appendix; Volume 1 (Part 2 of 2), NASA Technical Memorandum, 86129, A1-  A4, 1 table, 1984.  Raymahashay, B. C.; Bhavana, P. R.; RaG, K. S.; et al. Ion exchange properties of lateritic soil from  Calicut, Kerala: Journal of the Geological Society of India, 25(7), p. 466-470, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  Raymahashay, B. C.; and Papa RaG, B. Water chemistry as an index to lateritisation: Newsletter - I.  G. C. P. Project 129: Lateritisation Processes, 6, p. 7-9, illus., 1984.  Rebels, Marith C.; Pulmquist, Robert C.; and Ritter, Dale F. (leaders). Road log for 1984 Rocky  Mountain FOP/AMQUA field trip: in Late Cenozoic history and soil development, northern Bighorn  Basin, Wyoming and Montana; guidebook for the joint field trip of the Friends of the Pleistocene, Rocky  Mountain Cell, and the American Quaternary Association (Rebels, Marith C., leader; et al.), p. 2-10,  sketch map, Friends Pleistocene, United States, Am. Quat. Assoc., United States, 1984.  Rebels, Maritb C.; Ritter, Dale F.; and Palmqulst, Robert C. (leaders). Late Cenozoic history and soil  development, northern Bighorn Basin, Wyoming and Montana; guidebook for the joint field trip of the  Friends of the Pleistocene, Rocky Mountain Ceil, and the American Quaternary Association: p. 49, illus.  (incl. tables, sects., sketch maps), Friends Pleistocene, United States, Am. Quat. Assoc., United States,  1984.  Richardson, J. L. The relationship of soil organic-c to soil color, soil texture, and other soil properties  of selected North Dakota soils: in Proceedings of the North Dakota Academy of Science, 76th annual  meeting (Johnson, A. William, editor), Proceedings of the North Dakota Academy of Science, 38, p. 41,  illus., 1984.  Rltcl, ie, James ChnninghP~ll. Past and present vegetation of the far northwest of Canada: 251 p., illus.  (incl. tables, sketchmaps), Univ. Toronto Press, Toronto, ON, Canada, 1984.    372    Rodriguez Ronda, Angel; and Paez Montero, Ricardo. Preparacion y utilizacion de metaborato de litio  para la descomposicion de lateritas, bauxitas y sus minerales constituyentes [Preparation and utilization  of lithium metaborate by decomposition of laterites, bauxites and their mineral constituents]: Serie  Geologica - Centro de Investigaciones Geologicas, 1984(1), p. 13-33 (incl. English sum.), 8 tables, 1984.  Roose, E.; and Plot, J. Runoff, erosion and soil fertility restoration on the Mossi Plateau (central Upper  Volta): in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources  (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 485-498 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl.  4 tables), 1984.  Roy, William R.; Ainsworth, Calvin C.; Griffin, Robert A.; et al. Development and application of batch  adsorption procedures for designing earthen landfill liners: in Municipal and industrial waste, Annual  Madison Waste Conference Proceedings, 7, p. 390-398, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Ruhe, Robert V. Clay-mineral regions in Peoria Loess, Mississippi River basin: Journal of Geology,  92(3), p. 339-343, illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1984.  Ruppert, Hans. Kreide-Eisenerzlagerstatten in Nordostbayern; physikochemische Uberlegungen zur  Genese [Cretaceous iron ore deposits in northeastern Bavaria; physico-chemical conditions on their  genesis] [abstr.]:  in Referate der Vortraage und Poster auf der 62. Jahrestagung der Deutschen  Mineralogischen Gesellschaft, gemeinsam mit der Osterreichischen Mineralogischen Gesellschaft und  der Schweizerischen Mineralogischen und Petrographischen Gesellschaft, Fortschritte der Mineralogie,  Beiheft, 62(1), p. 200-201, 1984.  Ruppert, Hans.  Spurenmetallgehalte in Boden als Ausdruck des geologischen Substrates und der  Umweltbelastung [Trace metal contents in soils as an expression of the geologic substrate and  environmental stress] [abstr.]:  in Referate der Vortraage und Poster auf der 62. Jahrestagung der  Deutschen Mineralogischen Gesellschaft, gemeinsam mit der Osterreichischen Mineralogischen  Gesellschaft und der Schweizerischen Mineralogischen und Petrographischen Gesellschaft, Fortschritte  der Mineralogie, Beiheft, 62(1), p. 201-202, 1984.  Ryden, J. C.; Ball, P. R.; and Garwood, E. A. Nitrate leaching from grassland: Nature (London),  311(5981), p. 50-53, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Satehell, Loretta Simmonds. Patterns of disturbance and vegetation change in the Miocene Succor  CreekfioraofOregon-Idaho: 172 p., Doctoral, 1984, Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, MI. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.  Satyanarayana Murty, B. V.; Panehanathan, P. V.; and Markandeyulu, C. Surface magnetic data  inversion toward estimating bedded iron ore; an example from Kumaraswamy, India [abstr.]: in 1983  annual meeting abstracts, Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Geophysics, 49(5), p. 619, 1984. Society  of Exploration Geophysicists, 53rd annual international meeting.  Scott, Edward R. D.; Rnbin, Alan E.; Taylor, G. Jeffrey; et al. Matrix material in type 3 chondrites;  occurrence, heterogeneity and relationship with chondrules: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 48(9),  p. 1741-1757, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1984.  Scott, K. M.; and Rampe, M. Integrated mineralogical and geochemical exploration for tin in the Bygoo  region of the Ardlethan tin field, southern N.S.W., Australia: Journal of Geochemical Exploration,  20(3), p. 337-354, illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch maps), 1984.  Severson, R. C.; and Gongh, L.P. Estimated physiological tolerance ranges for selected elements in soils,  Capps coal field:  in The United States Geological Survey in Alaska; accomplishments during 1982  (Reed, Katherine M., editor; et al.), Geological Survey Circular, 0939, p. 75-78, 2 tables, sketch map,  1984.  Shadfan, H4 and Dixon, J. B. Occurrence of palygorskite in the soils and rocks of the Jordan Valley:  in Palygorskite - sepiolite occurrences, genesis and uses (Singer, Arieh, editor; et al.), 37, p. 187-198, illus.  (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), Elsevier Sci. Publ., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984.  7th international clay  conference.  Shumlyanskiy, V. A.; Sergeyev, I. P.; and Korneva, N. G. Usloviya nakopleniya urana i toriya v  bazal'nykh sloyakh osadochnogo chekhla krupnykh platformennykh vpadin [Uranium and thorium  accumulation conditions in the basal layers of a sedimentary cover of large platform depressions]:  Geologicheskiy Zhurnal (Kiev, 1968), 44(4), p. 46-58, illus. (incl. 1 table, strat, cols.), 1984.    373    Singer, A. (reviewer). Aridic soils of Israel; properties, genesis and management: Geoderma, 33(1), p.  86-87, 1984.  Singer, Arieh. Pedogenic palygorskite in the arid environment: in Palygorskite - sepiolite occurrences,  genesis and uses (Singer, Arieh, editor; et al.), 37, p. 169-175, Elsevier Sci. Publ., Amsterdam,  Netherlands, 1984.  7th international clay conference.  Singh, J. S.; Rawat, Y. S.; and Chaturvedi, O. P. Replacement of oak forest with pine in the Himalaya  affects the nitrogen cycle: Nature (London), 311(5981), p. 54-56, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  Singh, Jaswant; Wapakala, W. W.; and Chebosi, P. K. Estimating groundwater recharge based on  infiltration characteristics of layered soil:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in  African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p.  37-45 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Smalley, Ian J. Canada's silty soils; loess in disguise?: Geos (Ottawa), 13(1), p. 20-21 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1984.  Sobkowiez, J. C.; and Morgenstern, N. R. The undrained equilibrium behaviour of gassy sediments:  Canadian Geotechnical Journal = Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, 21 (3), p. 439-448 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Sorenson, Curtis J. Preliminary soils map of the Fremont Lake South Quadrangle, Sublette County,  Wyoming: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), 10p., 1 sheet, soils map 1:24,000,  1984. (Rep. No. OF 84-0844) available from: U. S. Geol. Sure., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib.  Branch, Fed. Cent., Denver, CO, United States.  Sparks, D. L.; and Jardine, P. M. Comparison of kinetic equations to describe potassium-calcium  exchange in pure and in mixed systems: Soil Science, 138(2), p. 115-122, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Stalker, Arehie. Ice age bones; a clue: Geos (Ottawa), 13(2), p. 11-14 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl.  chart, sketch maps), 1984.  Stavnitser, L. R. Similarity of solutions of the theory of limiting equilibrium for cohesive soils: Soil  Mechanics and Foundation Engineering, 21(1), p. 42-48, 1 table, 1984.  Steudler, P. A.; and Peterson, B. J. Contribution of gaseous sulphur from salt marshes to the global  sulphur cycle: Nature (London), 311(5985), p. 455-457, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Stevenson, I. L.; and Sehnitzer, M. Energy-dispersive X-ray microanalysis of saturated fulvic acid-iron  and copper complexes: Soil Science, 138(2), p. 123-126, illus., 1984.  Stocking, Michael. Rates of erosion and sediment yield in the African environment:  in Proceedings  of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor;  et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 285-293 (incl. French sum.), 5 tables, 1984.  Strom, Donald E. Soil survey of McCone County, Montana: 361 p., illus. (incl. 14 tables, sketch map;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep. Agric, Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, 1984. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Bur. Land Manage., U. S. Fish and Wildlife Sere.,  and Mont. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Tarbox, D. L.; and White, C. M.  Evaluation of predicting groundwater behavior under on-site  wastewater treatment systems [abstr.]:  in Seventh annual winter meeting of the Vermont Geological  Society (Doolan, Barry L., convener), The Green Mountain Geologist, 10(4), p. 9-10, 1984.  Tarehitzky, J.; Banin, A.; Morin, J.; et aL Nature, formation and effects of soil crusts formed by water  drop impact: Geoderma, 33(2), p. 135-155, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1984.  Ter-Martirosyan, Z. G.; Kyatov, N. Kh.; and Sidorehuk, V. F. Eksperimental'nyye i teoreticheskiye  osnovy opredeleniya napryazhennogo sostoyaniya gruntov yestestvennogo slozheniya [Experimental  and theoretical fundamentals for determining strain state in soils with natural composition]:  Inzhenernaya Geologiya, 1984(4), p. 13-25, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Tiller, Kevin G.; Gerth, J.; and Brummer, G. The sorption of Cd, Zn and Ni by soil clay fractions;  procedures for partition of bound forms and their interpretation: Geoderma, 34(1), p. 1-16, illus. (incl.  2 tables), 1984.  Tiller, Kevin G.; Gerth, J.; and Brnmmer, G. The relative affinities of Cd, Ni and Zn for different soil  clay fractions and goethite: Geoderma, 34(1), p. 17-35, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1984.    374    Townsend, Frank C.  Geotechnical characteristics of residual soils:  Journal of Geotechnical  Engineering, 111(1), p. 77-94, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1985.  Trudgill, S. T.; Crabtree, R. W.; Pickles, A. M.; et al. Hydrology and solute uptake in hillslope soils  on Magnesian Limestone; the Whitwell Wood Project:  in Catchment experiments in fluvial  geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 183-215, illus. (incl. 6 tables), Geo Books, Norwich, United  Kingdom, 1984.  Turner, Russell T.; Duvadl, Pakawan; and Mancke, Rudy E. The physical geography of Mt. Kaijende,  Papua New Guinea [abstr.]: in Fifty-seventh annual meeting of the South Carolina Academy of Science  (Cowley, Gerald T., president), Bulletin of the South Carolina Academy of Science, 46, p. 129, 1984.  Uchrin, C.G. Modelling transport processes and differential accumulation of persistent toxic organic  substances in groundwater systems:  in Modelling the fate and effect of toxic substances in the  environment; proceedings of a symposium (Joorgensen, S. E., editor), 6, p. 135-143, illus., Elsevier,  Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1984.  Uvarov, A. A. Izucheniye nekotorykh fiziko-mekhanicheskikh kharakteristik gruntov s pomoshch'yu  geofizichcskikh metodov [A study of some physico-mechanical characteristics of soils with geophysical  methods]: Inzhenernaya Geologiya, 1984(4), p. 126-130, 1984.  Vanelslande, A.; Rousseau, P.; Lad, R.; et al. Testing the applicability of a soil erodibility nomogram for  some tropical soils: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology and water  resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 463-473 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch map), 1984.  Vauclin, M. Infiltration in unsaturated soils: in Fundamentals of transport phenomena in porous media  (Bear, Jacob, editor; et al.), p. 257-312, illus. (incl. 1 table), Martinus Nijhoff Publ., Dordreeht,  Netherlands, 1984. NATO Advanced Study Institute on Mechanics of fluids in porous medicL  Veneman, P. L. M.; Jaeke, P. V.; and Bodine, S. M. Soil formation as affected by pit and mound  microrelief in Massachusetts, USA: Geoderma, 33(2), p. 89-99, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sect.), 1984.  Viets, J. G.; Clark, J. R.; and Campbell, W. L. A rapid, partial leach and organic separation for the  sensitive determination of Ag, Bi, Cd, Cu, Mo, Pb, Sb, and Zn in surface geologic materials by flame  atomic absorption: Journal of Geochemical Exploration, 20(3), p. 355-366, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1984.  Wace, Nigel M.; and Olfiar, Cliff D. Biogeography and geomorphology of South Atlantic islands: in  On research and exploration projects supported by the National Geographic Society, for which an initial  grant or continuing support was provided in the year 1975 (Oehser, Paul H., editor; et aL), Research  Reports - National Geographic Society, 16, p. 733-758, illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1984.  Wahl, Frank; Wilson, Jay; and Scheinost, Steve. Soil survey of Kearney County, Nebraska: 157 p.,  illus. (incl. 19 tables, block diags., sketch map; colored soil map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S.  Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv., Washington, DC, United States, 1984. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Nebr.,  Conserv. and Sure. Die.).  Waning, D. E.  Soil erosion papers; an introduction:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium;  Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH  Publication, 144, p. 261-262, 1984.  Walling, D. E. The sediment yields of African rivers:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium;  Challenges in African hydrology and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et al.), IAHS-AISH  Publication, 144, p. 265-283 (incl. French sum.), 3 tables, sketch maps, 1984.  Ward, Andy; and Middleton, Brian. Sediment yield estimation and the design of sediment control  structures in rural Africa:  in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology  and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 415-425 (incl. French  sum.), 1984.  Ward, Andy; Smith, Adrian; and Caddwell, Jack. Surface erosion and sediment control at open-cast  mines in Southern Africa: in Proceedings of the Harare Symposium; Challenges in African hydrology  and water resources (Walling, D. E., editor; et aL), IAHS-AISH Publication, 144, p. 517-527 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Warren, Harry V.  Biogeochemistry, a valuable tool in mineral exploration and environmental  assessment: TRAC. Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 3(10), p. 275-280, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1984.    375    Watson, K. K.; and Jones, M.J. Algebraic equations for solute movement during absorption: Water  Resources Research, 20(8), p. 1131-1136, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Wanehope, R. D.; and McDowell, L. L. Adsorption of phosphate, arsenate, methanearsonate, and  cacodylate by lake and stream sediments; comparisons with soils: Journal of Environmental Quality,  13(3), p. 499-504, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1984.  Wayne, William J. Relative dating techniques to distinguish late Pleistocene-Holocene continental  sediments: in Geochronology of Recent deposits; a selection of papers presented to a Symposium on  the geochronology of Recent deposits as part of the Eleventh International Association of  Sedimentoiogists' congress (Robbins, John A., editor), Chemical Geology, 44(1-3), p. 33%348, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1984.  Wendorf, Fred; Sehild, Romuald; Close, Angela E.; et aL New radiocarbon dates on the cereals from  Wadi Kubbaniya: Science, 225(4662), p. 645-646, 8 tables, 1 plate, 1984.  Whalley, W. Brian. High altitude rock weathering processes: in The International Karakoram Project;  Vol. 1 (Miller, Keith John), p. 365-373, illus. (incl. 2 tables), Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge, United  Kingdom, 1984.  The International Karakoram Project.  Whalley, W. Brian; McGreevy, J. P.; and Ferguson, Robert Ion. Rock temperature observations and  chemical weathering in the Hunza region, Karakoram; preliminary data: in The International Karadoram  Project; Vol. 2 (Miller, Keith John), p. 616-633, illus. (incl. 4 tables), Univ. Cambridge, Cambridge,  United Kingdom, 1984.  White, R.E. Nitrogen cyclc; nitrate leaching from grassland: Naturc(London),311(5981),p. 10, 1984.  Wieden, P.  Interkristallinc Quellung, Schwellung und rheologisch-dynamisches Verhalten von  Tonmineralen [Inter-crystal swelling and rheologic-dynamic behavior of clay minerals] [abstr.]:  in  Referate der Vortraage und Poster auf der 62. Jahrestagung der Deutschen Mineralogischen Gcsellschaft,  gemeinsam mit der Osterreichischen Mineralogischen Gcsellschaft und der Schweizerischen  Mineralogischen und Petrographischen Gesellschaft, Fortschritte der Mineralogie, Beiheft, 62(1), p. 260-  261, 1984.  Wiesner, C. Howard. Soil survey of Gregory County, South Dakota: 175 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables, sketch  map; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1984. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Bur. Indian Aft. and S. D. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Williams, A. G.; Ternan, J. L.; and Kent, M. Hydrochemical characteristics of a Dartmoor hillslope:  in Catchment experiments in fluvial geomorphology (Burt, T. P., editor; et al.), p. 379-398, illus. (incl.  4 tables), Gco Books, Norwich, United Kingdom, 1984.  Wintle, A. G.; Shaekleton, Nicholas J.; and Laotridou, J. P. Thcrmolumincscence dating of periods of  loess deposition and soil formation in Normandy: Nature (London), 310(5977), p. 491-493, illus. (incl.  1 table), 1984.  Wood, M. Karl; and Blackburn, Wilbert H. An evaluation of the hydrologic soil groups as used in the  SCS runoff method on rangelands: Water Resources Bulletin (Urbana), 20(3), p. 379-389, 1984.  Woods, W. I.; and Fowler, M. L. Tunnel erosion; an aid to on-ground feature identification at the  Amalucan site, Pueblo, Mexico [abstr.]: in 1984 symposium on archaeometry; abstracts (Olin, J. S.,  organizer; et aD, p. 159-160, Smithson. Inst., Washington, DC, United States, 1984.  Wroth, C.P. The interpretation of in situ soil tests: Geotechnique, 34(4), p. 449-489 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1984.  Wu Shiming; Gray, Donald H.; and Richart, F. E., Jr. Capillary effects on dynamic modulus of sands  and silts: Journal of Geotechnical Engineering, 110(9), p. 1188-1203, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1984.  Wyckoff, John W. A late Holocene environmental record from the Knife River region, North Dakota:  in Proceedings of the North Dakota Academy of Science, 76th annual meeting (Johnson, A. William,  editor), Proceedings of the North Dakota Academy of Science, 38, p. 39, 1 table, 1984.  Wynn, J. C.; and Grosz, Andrew E. Geophysical response of titanium-bearing deposits of placer heavy  minerals in northeastern Florida [abstr.]:  in 1983 annual meeting abstracts, Society of Exploration  Geophysicists, Geophysics, 49(5), p. 616, 1984.  Society of Exploration Geophysicists, 53rd annual  international meeting.    376    Yonetani, Hiroshi; and Terashima, Shigeru. The n-paraffin distribution in plant, soil, peat and bottom  sediments: Sekiyu Gijutsu Kyokaishi = Journal of the Japanese Association of Petroleum Technologists,  49(3), p. 141-154 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table, sketch map), 1984.  Zbik, Marek; and Lang, Bruno. Beardsley vs. Faith; physical diversity among H5 cbondrites: Earth  and Planetary Science Letters, 70(2), p. 169-174, illus., 1984.  Zhang Zibin. Processes and factors controlling Holocene soil formation in the Beijing area: Marine  Geology &amp; Quaternary Geology, 4(4), p. 79-85 (Chinese, incl. English sum.), 1 table, sketch map, 1984.  Znidareie, Dobroslav; Cruee, Paolo; Pane, Vineenzo; et al. The theory of one-dimensional consolidation  of saturated clays; III, Existing testing procedures and analyses: ASTM Geotecbnical Testing Journal,  7(3), p. 123-134, 1 table, 1984.  Zutie, Vera; and Stumm, Werner. Effect of organic acids and fluoride on the dissolution kinetics of  hydrous alumina; a model study using the rotating disc electrode: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta,  48(7), p. 1493-1503, illus., 1984.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  