 Geoderma, 25 (1981) 285--292  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    285    COMPARISON OF SODIUM HYDROXIDE-TETRABORATE AND SODIUM  PYROPHOSPHATE AS EXTRACTANTS OF AI/Fe--HUMUS "COMPLEXES"  IN DYSTRANDEPTS, JAPAN    T. HIGASHI and A. SHINAGAWA  Faculty of Agriculture, Kagoshima University, Kagoshima (Japan)  (Received September 17, 1979; accepted June 13, 1980)    ABSTRACT    Higashi, T. and Shinagawa, A., 1981. Comuarison of sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and  sodium pyrophosphate as extractants of Al/Fe--humus "complexes" in Dystrandepts,  Japan. Geoderma, 25: 285--292.    Extractions were made with tetraborate and pyrophosphate of the samples of 26 Al  horizons of soils derived from volcanic ash differing in origins and ages. The samples were  divided into three groups. Group 1 comprised eight samples from soils in ash less than,  and Group 2 five samples from soils in ash more than 1,000 years old. Group 3 comprised  thirteen samples from soils in ash more than 2,500 years old that had also been buried.  Effectiveness of the two reagents was gauged by the amounts of C, A1 and Fe removed  by the treatments. Amounts extracted by tetraborate ranged from 0.26 to 7.02% of C,  0.06 to 1.05% of AI and 0.01 to 0.07% of Fe. Those extracted by pyrophosphate ranged  from 0.32 to 13.02% of C, 0.09 to 3.92% of AI and 0.05 to 3.16% of Fe. Tetraborate ex-  tracted smaller quantities of all three elements from every sample than did pyrophosphate.  Similar results were obtained by multiple extractions. The comparisons thus indicate that  pyrophosphate is the more effective extractant of Al/Fe--humus complexes in AI horizons  of soils formed in volcanic ash.  Amounts of the elements, especially AI, extracted by the two reagents differed among  the three groups of soil samples. The amounts of AI were smallest for samples from the  youngest ash deposits, larger for the samples from older ash deposits still at the land sur-  face, and smaller again in the samples of buried soils. Ratios of the amounts of AI and C  extracted by tetraborate and those extracted by pyrophosphate were ~.,rogressively lower  from soils in the youngest ash to soils in the older ash to the buried soils. These ratios and  the differences in am,rants extracted from samples of the different groups suggest that  the nature of the Al-humus complexes changes as soils become older and also if they are  buried.    INTRODUCTION    Previous work (Wada and Higashi, 1976) has shown that sodium pyro-  phosphate (called pyrophosphate throughout this paper) is an effective ex-  tractant of "complexes" of AI and Fe with humus in soils derived from vol-  canic ash. As used here, "complexes" refers to intim'ate associations of AI    0016-7061/81/0000--0000/$02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    286    and Fe with organic matter, regardless of the nature of bonding. In recent  years, sodium hydroxide-tetraborate (called tetraborate throughout this  paper) has been used as an extractant of B horizons of some podzolic soils in  France (Bruckert, 1979). Pyrophosphate and tetraborate have been com-  pared as extractants of spodic horizons in Canada (McKeague and Sheldrick,  1977) and in Belgium (Higashi et al., 1981). So far as we know, however,  tetraborate has not been tried on samples of Dystrandepts. Consequently, we  have compared the amounts of C, A1 and Fe extracted by the two reagents  from samples of A~ horizons formed in ash deposits of different origins and  ages. In addition to the comparison, we hoped as well to shed some light on  changes in the nature of A1/Fe--humus complexes as soils became older.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soil samples    Samples of 26 A~ horizons were used in this investigation. They were  collected in various parts of Kyushu and Hokkaido for a previous study  (Wada and Higashi, 1976). Identification numbers, source locations, and re-  lative ages of ash deposits are given for the samples in Table I. All soils from  which samples were taken are classified tentatively as Typic Dystrandepts  according to the American system of soil classification (Soil Survey Staff,  1975). All of those at the land surface were under vegetation that was main-  iy grass.  Most of the individual samples are identified by a capital letter followed  by two numbers. All samples from one geological section have the same capi-  tal letter and first number, thus, T-1. Samples of individual horizons v,'thin  that section are distinguished by a second number, thus, T-1-I, T-1-2 and so  on. A few samples are identified by arabic numerals without any capital  letters. Horizon notations are according to Taylor and Pohlen (1962) except  that the prefix letter "u" identifies buried horizons The 26 samples have been subdivided into three groups, shown in Table I.  The first and second groups are set apart entirely on ages of the ash deposits,  whereas the third group consists of buried AI horizons. Group 1 comprises  eight samples from soils in ash deposits less than 1,000 years old. Group 2  comprises five samples from soils in ash deposits more than 1,000 years old.  Two deposits are between 2,500 and 5,000 years old but one exceeds 10,000  years. All samples in Groups 1 and 2 represent AI horizons at the present  land surface. Group 3 comprises 13 samples of buried A~ horizons in older  ash deposits. The ages of deposits were estimated from 14C dating of wood,  charcoal or humus preserved in the horizons and from stratigraphic relation-  ships to other soils of known ages. Sample S-l-1 is much the youngest of the  lot, having been collected from ash ejected by Mt. Sakurijima in Kagoshima  in 1914.    TABLE I  Identification of and amounts of organic C in samples and the quantities of C, Al and Fe removed by simple extractions with tetra-  borate and pyrophosphate (given on oven-dry basis for soil materials less than 2 ram)    Group and Hori-    Depth   Age.2     Locality.3           Total    Cna      Alna     Fena     Cpyr     Alpyr    Fep~,r  soil num-  zon*~   (era)                                    C  ber                                          (%)    (%)    (%)    (%)    (%)   (%)    (%)    Group 1  586  S-l-1  M-l-1  M-2-1  M-3-1  M-4-1  M-5-1  M-6-1  Group 2  T-l-1  H-l-1  1040  904  M-7-1  Group 3  T-l-2  H-l-2  T-l-3  T-l-4  T-l-6  W-144-2  W-144-5  H-l-3  H-l-4  H-l-6  W-167-3  W-167-6  T-l-8    * I    A,         0--14    1      Kishimadake, Ku     0.83   0.26    0.06    0.01      0.32   0.09    0.05  A~        0--10    1      Onobaru, Ka         3.60   0.75    0.13    0.02     0.95   0.16    0.10  A~       0--10   1     Bibi, Ho            3.36  0.78    0.12    0.01     1.18  0.14    0.08  A~         0--10    1      Kenebetsu, Ho       5.67   2.32    0.38    0.05      2.81   0.51    0.37  A~        0--15    1      Shimo-oshoppu, Ho  6.48   1.55    0.21    0.02     2.34   0.43    0.26  A~         0--10    1      Beppu, Ho           7.78   2.00    0.27    0.03      2.31   0.27    0.20  A~         0--13    1      Kamisatsunai, Ho     7.80   2.48    0.34    0.07      2.48   0.34    0.25  A~         0--25    1      Asahiyama, Ho      11.61   3.64    0.63    0.04      4.73   0.86    0.40    Az         0--25    2      Asahidai, Oi         15.00   3.67    0.75    0.03      5.53   1.54    0.93  AI        0--25    2      Daikanbo, Ku       16.60   5.21    0.79    0.06     6.23   1.67    1.12  A,         0--30    3      Choyo, Ku           8.58   1.93    0.33    0.02      2.99   0.85    0.83  A,        0--25    3      Kodonharu, Ku     17.71   5.73    1.05    0.03    10.81   3.04    1.51  AI         0--30    4      Togeyama, Fu        9.48   4.45    0.77    0.04      5.64   1.81    0.75    uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA  uA    25--50   3     Asahidai, Oi        13.85   4.10    0.73    0.03     6.81   2.31    1.45  25--45    3      Daikanbo, Ku       24.10   7.02    0.90    0.05    13.02   3.92    3.16  50--70   3     Asahidai, Oi        7.94   0.83    0.30    0.02     2.07   0.82   0.18  70--90   3     Asahidai, Oi        8.45  0.63   0.27   0.02    1.80  0.85   0.05  100--115  3     Asahidai, Oi        8.68  1.13   0.40   0.02    2.84  1.13   0.12  22--50    3      Miyakonojou, Mi     5.66   1.06    0.20    0.02      2.02   0.54    0.22  220--260  3      Miyakonojou, Mi   10.86   1.48    0.13    0.02     5.82   0.60    0.76  45--80   3      Daikanbo, Ku       16.90   1.54    0.52    0.02     7.31   1.96    0.94  80--105  3      Daikanbo, Ku       16.40   2.37    0.70    0.02      9.30   2.56    1..39  120--135  4      Daikanbo, Ku       11.40   1.16    0.43    6.02     3.80   1.31    0.12  60--90   4      Okubo, Ku          6.39   1.43    0.22    0.02     3.06   0.65    0.98  170--195  4      Okuho, Ku          5.13   0.55    0.14    0.01     1.92   0.50    0.13  130--180  4     Asahidai, Oi        14.61   5.77    0.87    0.03    10.26   2.29    1.96    * 2 Horizon designations after Taylor and Pohlen (1962), "u" = buried.  . ~ i = 0-1000 yrs. ; 2 = 0-2500 yrs. ; 3 = 2500-5000 yrs. ; 4 = more than 10,000 yrs.  00  Fu, Fukuoka; Ho, Hokkaido; Ka, Kagoshima; Ku, Kumamoto; Mi, Miyazaki, Oi; Oita.    288    Methods    Tetraborate and pyrophosphate ex tractions  50 ml of 0.1N NaOH-Na2B4OT (0.1N with respect to each component) or  0.1M Na4PeO7 solution and 1.0 g of air-dry soil material (less than 2 mm)  were shaken in a polyet!%iene centrifuge tube at about 30 for 16 h. The  suspension was then centrifuged at 8000 g for 10 min and the centrifugate  collected in a volumetric flask. Each subsample was extracted twice with one  reagent or the other. Moreover, paired subsamples of each sample were ex-  tracted with each reagent; data given in Table I are thus averse values for a  pair of subsamples. For identification in this paper, the extractions with a  single reagent are called "simple" extractions or treatments.  Multiple extractions with both reagents were made of duplicate subsamples  of samples T-l-1 and T-l-6. Paired subsamples were extracted in the usual  way five successive times with tetraborate followed by two successive times  with pyrophosphate. Other pairs of subsamples were extracted five succes-  sive times with pyrophosphate followed by two successive times with tetra-  borate. These extractions are identified later in the paper as "multiple" ex-  tractions or treatments.    Determination orAl, Fe and C in extracts  Detailed procedures for the determination of A1, Fe and C in the pyro-  phosphate extracts were given by Wada and Higashi (1976). Those proce-  dures were followed in the pre:~ent investigation for extracts obtained with  both reagents. 25 ml of 1M Na2SO4 were added to 10 ml of the initial cen-  trifugate from an extraction, and this was then centrifuged again at 8000 g  for 10 rain to remove fine materials in suspension. Appropriate aliquots of  this second centrifugate were then used for determinations of the three ele-  ments. One aliquot was evaporated to near-dryness on a wa~er bath, after  which C was determined by the method of Tyurin (Kononova, 1961). Other  aliquots of the same centrifugate were analyzed for A1 and Fe by atomic ab-  sorption spectrophotometry. The same amounts of Na2SO4 and reagent were  added to the reference solutions of A1 and Fe as were present in the centri-  fugates. In the case of tetraborate extracts, Na-EDTA was also added to the  reference solutions of A1 and Fe, following McKeague and Sheldrick (1977).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Extracted amounts of C, Al and Fe    Amounts of the three elements extracted from each of the samples by  simple treatments with one reagent are given in Table I, as are the total  amounts of C. Quantities extracted by tetraborate are identified by the sub-  script "na" with the symbol for each element. Quantities extracted by pyro-  phosphate are identified by the subscript "pyr." All quantities are calculated  on the bases of oven-dry soii materials.    289    The data for pyrophosphate extractions of the 26 samples were reported  earlier by Wada and Higashi (1976). The data are repeated here, however,  to facilitate comparisons of the amounts removed by the two reagents.  Amounts of A1 and Fe removed by dithionite-citrate treatment are also re-  ported in the earlier paper.  Tetraborate extracted smaller amounts of all three elements from every  sample than did pyrophosphate. The amounts of Fe removed by both re-  agents were mostly low or very low. Quantities removed ranged from 0.01  to 0.07% for tetraborate and from 0.05 to 3.16% for pyrophosphate, with  most values below 1.00%. Because the amounts of Fe removed were so  low for many samples, that element is not considered further. The minimum  amounts of A1 extracted were also low, being 0.06% for tetraborate and 0.09%  for pyrophosphate. The full range for A1, however, was from 0.06 to 1.05%  for tetraborate and from 0.09 to 3.92% for pyrophosphate. The full range  was wider for C, with amounts of 0.26 to 7.02% for tetraborate and of 0.32  to 13.02%for pyrophosphate. The latter reagent was thus more effective in  extracting A1/Fe--humus complexes from the A I horizons of the soils from  volcanic ash (Dystrandepts).  The amounts of A1 extracted by both reagents tended to be lower for  samples of Group 1 than for those of Groups 2 and 3. This was especially  true for pyrophosphate. Average amounts extracted by tetraborate for  Groups 1, 2 and 3 were 0.27%, 0.74% and 0.45%, respectively. The ranges in  amounts extracted overlap slightly for Groups 1 and 2 and appreciably for  Groups 1 and 3. The average amounts of A1 removed by pyrophosphate from  Groups 1, 2 and 3 were 0.35%, 1.78% and 1.50%, respectively. Thus, the rel-  ative rankings of the three groups axe the same as they were for tetraborate  extractions with the lowest for Group 1, the highest for Group 2, and inter-  mediate for Group 3. The full ranges in amounts overlap barely for Groups 1  and 2 and somewhat more for Groups 1 and 3.  Differences among the three groups ~n the amount of A1 extracted from  samples suggest that the Al-humus complexes undergo changes as soils be-  come older and also if they axe buried. More A1 seems to become extractable  a~ soils become older but remain at the land surface and are still subject to  weathering. Both reagents removed more A1, on the average, from soil sam-  ples in Group 2 than in Group 1. Both reagents removed less A1, on the  average, from samples in Group 3 than in Group 2 but more than in Group 1.  A further indication that the nature of the complexes does undergo change  is provided by the differing amounts of A1 removed by the two reagents.  Pyrophosphate extracted very little more Al than did tetraborate, on the  average, from samples in Group 1 but more than twice as much from samples  in Group 2 and more than three times as much from samples in Group 3.  These differences also point to probable changes in the complexes.  In contrast to the data for A1, those for C have substantially overlapping  ranges for tne three groups of samples. Those data consequently do not in  themselves suggest any trends.    290    For further comparisons of the two extractants, ratios between the ~mounts  of AI and the amounts of C removed by ~,he respective treatments have been  computed. The amounts removed by te~raborate were used as numerators  and those removed by pyrophosphate as denominators in the calculations.  The ratios, for A1 are plotted against those for C in Fig.1. The ratios for A1  range from 0.67 to 1.00 for Group 1, from 0.34 to 0.43 for Group 2, and  from 0.22 to 0.38 for Group 3. The ratios for C range from 0.66 to 1.00 for  Group 1, from 0.53 to 0.84 for Group 2 and from 0.21 to 0.60 for Group 3.    --   Alna/Alpyr  1.0    0.5    0 group 1         O  (]) group 2              0  group 3             0 0  0    0 0    (P      @    I     i     i     I     I     i     i     i     ~     |  0           0.5          1.0  Cna/Cpyr    Fig.1. Ratios between quantities of A1 extracted by each of tetraborate and pyrophos-  phate plotted (on the ordinate) against comparable ratios for C (on the abscissa).    Average values of the ratio, Alna/Alpy~ are 0.79, 0.42 and 0.31 and of the  ratio, Cna/Cpyr, are 0.80, 0.69 and 0.40 for Groups 1, 2 and 3, respectively.  Thus, the ~vetage ratios are progressively lower from Group 1 to Group 3.  Difference~ in the ratios are readily evident in Fig.1. The ratios of AI for  Group 1, revresenting the A1 horizons of softs derived from the youngest  ash deposits, stand out clearly from the others. Slight overlapping and  smaller differences are evident for Groups 2 and 3, both representing A~  horizons formed in older deposits of ash. The ratios for Group 3 are the  !owest, on the whole; those samples are not only from older ash deposits,  especially as compared to Group 1, but are also from buried softs. Ratios of  amounts of C extracted overlap substantially for Groups I and 2, somewhat  less for Groups 2 and 3, and not at all for Groups I and 3. Thus, the ratios  provide further indications that Al-humu s complexes undergo alteration as  softs become older at the land surface and that additional alterations occur  is soils are buried.    291    Multiple extractions    As a further comparison of tetrabora :e and pyropho~hate, multiple ex-  tractions were made of two samples. T~:ose were samples T-l-1 and T-l-6,  the first representing an A~ horizon at ~he ground surface and the second a  deeply buried A~ horizon in the same geological section. Cumulative  amounts of C, A1 and Fe extracted by each reagent and by both are given in  Table II.    TABLE !I    Cumulative amounts of C, AI and Fe removed from samples T-l-1 and T-l-6 by multiple  extractions with both reagents, first five times with tetraborate and twice with pyro-  phosphate, and then vice versa (given on oven-dry basis for soil materials less than 2 mm)    Treat-               Sample: T-l-1                T-l-6  ment                C        AI       Fe       C        Al       Fe  (%)    (%)    (%)    (%)    (%)    (%)    NaOH-Na2B407        4.80      1.19      0.07       1.87       0.75      0.04  (5)  Na4P20~               0.99      0.78      0.59      1.21       0.60      0.11  (2)  Total              5.79     1.97     0.66     3.0l~     1.35     0.15  Na,P20~                5.91       1.86       1.06      3.29       1.45      0.22  (5)  NaOH-Na2B,O7        0.37      0.06      0.02      0.26       0.10      0.02  (2)  Total              6.28     1.93     1.08     3.55     1.55     0.24    The initial extractions of sample T-1-6 with tetraborate removed very little  Fe. Moreover, amo~unts removed by the two subsequent extractions with  pyrophosphate were also small. On the other hand, if initial extractions were  made with pyrophosphate, a larger amount of Fe was removed. Reasons for  this difference are not known.  Results from multiple extractions of the samples are, on the whole, con-  sistent with data from simple extractions. Tetraborate removed smaller  amounts of all elements than did p~,zopho~,phate. Further, cumulative  amounts removed by the multiple extractions were roughly similar tc those  removed by simple extractions with pyrophospbate. Thus, the multiple ex-  tractions also indicate that pyrophosphate is more effective than tetraborate  in extractions of Al/Fe--humus complexes in the AI horizons of soils derived  from volcanic ash (Dystrandepts).    292    ACKNOW LEDGEMENTS    The authors wish to express their thanks to ProL K. Wada, Department of  Agricultural Chemistry, Kyushu University, for his helpful comments and to  Mr. Kihara M. for his assistance in the investigation.    REFERENCES    Bruckert, S., 1979. Classification des sols bruns ocreux et crypto-podzoliques par analyse  des extraits tetraborate tamponn~s a pH 9,5. Geoderma, 2~,: 205--212.  Higashi, T., De Coninck, F. and Gelaude, F., 1981. Characterization of some spodic hori-  zons of the Campine (Belgium) by dithivnite-citrate, pyrophosphate and sodium  hydroxide-tetraborate. Geoderma, 25: 131--142.  Kononova, M.M., 1961. Soil Organic Matter. Pergamon Press, Oxford, pp.400--404.  McKcague, J.A. and Sheldrick, B.H., 1977. Sodium hydroxide-tetraborate in compari-  son with sodium pyrophosphate as an extractant of "complexes" characteristic of  spodic horizons. Geoderma, 19: 97--104.  Soi~ Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Cl~sification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook No. 436, pp. 230--236.  Taylor, N.H. and Pohlen, I.J., 1962. Soil Survey Method. Soil Bureau, Taita Experimental  Station, Lower Hutt.  Wada, K. and Higashi, T., 1976. The categories of aluminum- and iron-humus co~,p|exe;  in Ando ~ils determined by selective dissolution. J. Soil Sci., 27 : 357--368.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                AbstractExtractions were made with tetraborate and pyrophosphate of the samples of 26 A1 horizons of soils derived from volcanic ash differing in origins and ages. The samples were divided into three groups. Group 1 comprised eight samples from soils in ash less than, and Group 2 five samples from soils in ash more than 1,000 years old. Group 3 comprised thirteen samples from soils in ash more than 2,500 years old that had also been buried.Effectiveness of the two reagents was gauged by the amounts of C, Al and Fe removed by the treatments. Amounts extracted by tetraborate ranged from 0.26 to 7.02% of C, 0.06 to 1.05% of Al and 0.01 to 0.07% of Fe. Those extracted by pyrophosphate ranged from 0.32 to 13.02% of C, 0.09 to 3.92% of Al and 0.05 to 3.16% of Fe. Tetraborate extracted smaller quantities of all three elements from every sample than did pyrophosphate. Similar results were obtained by multiple extractions. The comparisons thus indicate that pyrophosphate is the more effective extractant of Al/Fe—humus complexes in A1 horizons of soils formed in volcanic ash.Amounts of the elements, especially Al, extracted by the two reagents differed among the three groups of soil samples. The amounts of Al were smallest for samples from the youngest ash deposits, larger for the samples from older ash deposits still at the land surface, and smaller again in the samples of buried soils. Ratios of the amounts of Al and C extracted by tetraborate and those extracted by pyrophosphate were progressively lower from soils in the youngest ash to soils in the older ash to the buried soils. These ratios and the differences in amounts extracted from samples of the different groups suggest that the nature of the Al-humus complexes changes as soils become older and also if they are buried. 