 30    chemical, to separate podzolised soils (Spodosols in "Soil Taxonomy", Soil  Survey Staff, 1975). This paper proposes a simple technique for identifying  podzolised soils in New Zealand, based on the measurement of the optical  density of acid oxalate extracts of soil.  Current concepts of the formation of podzolised soils stress the role of  organic matter in the translocation of aluminium and iron, as one of the  major processes leading to the development of this type of soil {e.g. Petersen  1976; McKeague et al., 1978). The probable mechanism involves the produc-  tion in the organic horizons of water-soluble organic matter (referred to in  some literature as fulvic acid). If certain preconditions, such as low pH,  base status and available Al and Fe in the A horizon are met, the water-  soluble organic matter will be leached down the profile. During its down-  ward movement the organic matter reacts through its functional groups  with Al and Fe released from soil minerals by weathering. Once enough of  the functional groups have been saturated, precipitation of the mineral-  organic complex occurs in the B horizon.  In view of this role of organic matter in the formation of podzolised  soils, it is reasonable to assume that an index based on measurement of or-  ganic matter movement would be effective and possibly more relevant than  indices based on measurement of inorganic constituents. The method should,  however, be based on an extraction of as nearly as possible the same frac-  tion of organic matter (fulvic acid) as that involved in the podzolising pro-  cess. Assuming this condition is fulfilled, the presence of any appreciable  quantities of extractable organic matter below the A1 horizon can be taken  as evidence for podzolisation. Also, because the method would be based on  organic matter which originates in the A horizon, heterogeneity of parent  material will not be a problem, and parameters based on distribution could  be used.  Of the many extractants commonly used to extract the products of soil  weathering processes, (e.g. NaOH, pyrophosphate, dithionite-citrate, acid  oxalate) the acid-oxalate reagent originally proposed by Tamm (1922)  for the extraction of Al, Fe and Si, appears to be the most suitable for the  purpose described above. The reagent is a strong complexing agent for Fe  and A1, and extracts these metals from fulvic-metal complexes, thereby  making the organic component water-soluble. McKeague et al. (1967)  reported that acid-oxalate reagent almost completely dissolved an iron pan,  which was shown to be an Fe-fulvic acid complex. Bascomb (1968) showed  that acid oxalate is a very poor extractant for humic acid, which would be  expected because of its low pH {3.2). Therefore it seems probable that  acid oxalate is a relatively selective extractant for the organic matter believ-  ed to be involved in the translocation of A1 and Fe in the podzolisation  process.  The disadvantage of this reagent is that, because of the high carbon con-  tent of oxalate, extracted organic matter cannot be measured directly in  the extract as carbon. In view of this difficulty it was decided to measure the    31    colour intensity of the extracts as a means of quantifying the extracted  organic matter.    METHODS AND MATERIALS    Extraction    The acid-oxalate extracts were obtained using the leaching method of Daly  and Binnie (1974). This involves leaching 5 g soil with 200 ml of acid-oxalate  reagent.    Development of spectrophotometric method    Absorbance versus wavelength plots were produced for a number of sample  extracts using a scanning spectrophotometer. Broad peaks at approximately  350 nm were obtained but a bathochromic shift and possibly more than  one peak were observed. Because of this, and because it was intended merely  to quantify a range of colour intensity that could be seen by eye, a simple  colorimeter with a filter in the visible range was used. This was a Hilger and  Watts Spekker with an Ilford No. 1 filter, which passes a broad band (ap-  proximately 50 nm) of light at around 430 nm. With this instrument, solu-  tions diluted successively and read using a I cm cell gave near-linear curves.  No direct calibration was made and it is probable that the measurement of  the colour does not follow Beer's Law in being exactly proportional to the  concentration of the absorbing species. Also the extracted organic matter  from different soils is likely to have different spectrophotometric proper-  ties. The fulvic acid within one soil profile, however, should have similar  spectrometric properties and the relative amounts or distribution down the  profile rather than the absolute amount of extracted organic matter in each  horizon is the important consideration.  Each measurement is quoted as optical density of the oxalate extract  (ODOE).    Soi/s    A range of New Zealand soils was used to test the proposed method.  That range included three soil sequences which, because of differences in  altitude and rainfall or in age, had progressively better expressed podzol  characteristics from one end to the other. Those characteristics were the  appearance of A2 horizons, greater redness of B horizons, and evidence of  redistribution of extractable Fe and A1 in the podzolised members. Samples  for study were collected by horizons, the notations for which are according  to Taylor and Pohlen (1962). Classification of the soils in the New Zealand  system (Taylor and Pohlen, 1968) and in the American soft taxonomy (Soft  Survey Staff, 1975) plus some relevant properties are given in Tables I and II.    32    TABLE I    Soils and classification  Soil number                S.B.      Classification  and type                   Lab No.  New Zealand*    Soil Taxonomy    1  Taupo deep sand      8846     yellow-brown pumice soil  Typic Vitrandept  2  Oruanui sand          9293     yellow-brown pumice soil  Typic Haplohumod  3  Tihoi loamy sand      8848     podzolised yellow-brown   Typic Haplohumod  pumice soil  4 Tihoi loamy sand      8991     podzolised yellow-brown   Typic Haplohumod  (podocarp forest)               pumice soil  5  Haparangi sandy loam  8994     yellow-brown loam        Entic Dystrandept  6  Ngongataha loamy sand 8993    yellow-brown loam        Typic Haplohumod  7  Mamaku loamy sand   8992     podzolised yellow-brown   Typic Haplorthod  loam  8  Hokitika sandy loam   8858     recent soil                 Typic Udipsamment  9  Ikamatua silt loam     8861     yellow-brown earth        Typic Dystrochrept  10  Ahaura silt loam       8863     yellow-brown earth        Entic Haplorthod  11  Hukarere silt loam     8867     gley podzol               Typic Fragiaquod  12 Taipoiti hill soil       8888     gleyed podzolised          Histic Sideraquod  yellow-brown earth  13 Wairaurihiri silt loam   8983     gley podzol               Placic Haplaquod  14 Wharekohe silt loam   9535     northern podzol           Typic Albaquult  15  Te Kopuru sand       9534     northern podzol           Typic Duraquod    *According to Taylor and Pohlen (1968)    Soils 1--4, 5--7 and 8--11 represent the sequences. 1--4 are a sequence of  soils on air-fall Taupo Pumice with rhyolitic characteristics from the central  North Island, New Zealand, under increasing rainfall from approximately  1200 mm for soil 1 to 1800 mm for soils 3 and 4. Soil 4 was sampled from a  forest environment and the remaining three soils of the sequence are under  pasture.  Sequence 5--7 is also from the central North Island area and is on air-fall  rhyolitic ash. The rainfall increases from 1600 to 2300 ram.  Sequence 8--11 was sampled from the west coast of the South Island and  is predominantly an age sequence on river terraces, on alluvium and loess  derived from greywacke, granite and schist. The sequence has been de-  scribed by Ross et al. (1977). Soil 11 is different from the oldest member of  their sequence (not examined here) but is from the same terrace.  Soils 12 and 13 are from the South Island: soil 12 from the west coast,  being a gleyed podzolised yellow-brown earth derived from greywacke col-  luvium and with a rainfall of 2300 mm; soil 13, from Southland, is a weakly  gleyed podzol from loess over gravels and has a rainfall of 1600 + mm.  Soils 14 and 15 are both northern podzols from North Auckland, 14 being  derived from strongly argillised shales with a rainfall of 1800--2000 ram, and  15 being formed on dune sands over glauconitic sandstone with a rainfall  of 1400 mm.    TABLE II  Characterisation properties    of the soils used    33    Soft number   B horizon  Pyrophosphate     Dithionite-citrate     Cation  (see Table I)   depth (on0 extractable         extractable           exchange  capacity,  Fe    AI    C     Fe     AI          pH 8.2  (%)  (%)  (%)  (%)   (%)       (me. %)    Clay (%)*    1             11--19     0.09  0.15  --     0.31    0.19         10.6         2  2             10--30     0.23  0.39  --     0.29    0.48         20.7         2  3a          21--37    0.49  0.58  --    0.57    0.59        29.0        3  b            40-50     0.18  0.41  --     0.33    0.68         23.2         3  4a           22--42     0.68  1.3   --    0.83    1.2          73.4        3  b            42-47     0.20  0.65  --     0.31    1.1           33.5         3  5           16--25    0.35  0.56  --    0.57   1.0         32.6       0+  6            11--20    0.63  1.2   --    0.98   1.8         49.0        0+  7a           24--30    0.71  0.49  --    0.86   0.47        32.9        0+  b          30--44    1.5   2.1   --    1.7     2.5         72.0        0+  c           44--67     0.69  1.3   --     1.3     2.7          67.7        0+  8             23-40     0.06  0.06  --     0.15    0.06           4.0         1  9             23--36     1.0   0.75  --     1.2     0.65         26.4        14  10             24--43     1.0    1.3   --     1.3     1.2           33.7         6  II             44--56     0.03  0.90  5.9    0.22    0.85         74.6        25  12             40--50     0.67  0.57  --     1.5     0.61          38.4        13  13a           23--37     0.38  0.55  --     0.62    0.56         49.0        6  b            37--52     0.71  0.67  --     1.9     1.1           29.9        15  14a           14--29     0.01  0.14  2.0   0.00    0.16         24.3       18  b            29-41     0.06  0.42  1.0   0.11    0.34         52.0        66  15a          69---85    0.00  0.19  2.7   0.00   0.24        28.1        3  b            85--90     0.01  0.19  2.2   0.00    0.24         25.5         4  c           90--101    0.00  0.22  1.9   0.00    0.24         23.5        9    *Dispersed with sodium polymetaPhosphate buffered to pH 8.5 with sodium carbonate; +Did not  disperse    0.2     0"4     0.6     0"8    ............  t  ...........  I    i    i  iC1      SOIL 1  ~,":..,::'i c2  iiii!iiii ii!  :  i!i ii! ::i%::..   IB)    SOIL 2    ODOE  0-2     0-4     0.6     0.8     1.0     1-2    ............  I  ...........  I  ...........  I    I  .....::..:..:......:..::.:...:::..v.:.~A~  ::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: Bfe   !  r.',;:v.:::v.:','.:v C1                                        I    B    SOIL 4    Fig.1. ODOE versus depth for the soils of sequence 1--4.    34    RESULTS  AND DISCUSSION    Soil 1 has a maximum level of extractable organic matter (as estimated by  ODOE) in the A horizon (Fig.l) where it is assumed to have formed. Soil 2  shows a larger amount in the B horizon, whereas soils 3 and 4 show the typical  pattern for podzols with minima in the A2 and large maxima in the Bfe  horizons. Soil 4, which is still under podocarp forest, has the best expression  of the pattern.  The ODOE values for this sequence demonstrate increasing degrees of  movement of organic matter in the soils (from 1 to 4) and also that the ratios  of the ODOE of the B to the A, horizons (Table III) reflect the increasing  expression of podzolic characteristics with increasing rainfall and vegetation  difference between soils 3 and 4.  The age sequence (8--11) (Fig.2) demonstrates a similar trend to those of    TABLE III    B horizon ODOE results and "Soil Taxonomy" spodic horizon criteria  Soil number ODOE             Soil Taxonomy spodic horizon ratios  (see Table I)  B        B/A      (Fep + Alp) (Fep + Alp) index of  horizon  horizon  (Fed + Aldi (% clay)    accumulation    Horizon  type3    1           0.20        0.5    0.48         0.12           77           NS  2          0.74        1.5    0.81        0.31         394          S  3a         0.95        1.7    0.92        0.36         440          S  b        0.65       1.1    0.58       0.20        217         S  4a        1.12       3.2    0.98       0.66       1440         S  b        0.70       2.0    0.60       0.28        160         S  5          0.52        0.4    0.58         0.12          290           NS  6           0.97        1.0    0.66         0.2           420           S  7a        1.09       3.5   0.90       0.25        170         S  b         1.11        3.6    0.86         0.25          900           S  c         0.92        3,0    0.50         0.2           815           S  8          0,05        0.3    0.57         0.12           60           NS  9           0.30        0.7    0.95         0.13          252           NS  10          0.62        1.9    0.92         0,38          583           S  11           1.20       13.0    0.87         0.27'         745           S  12           0.53       10.6    0.68         0.11          319           NS  13a         0.95        9.5    0.79        0.16          644           S  b         0.30        3.0    0.46         0.09          336           NS  14a           0.92        31       0.83          0.12'          230            NS  b           0.63         21        1.1            0.02'           228             NS  15a          0.82       41       0,79         0.96'          426            S  b           3.7         185        0.83           0.60!           118             S  c          2.0       100       0.92         0.241          209            S    ' Calculated using Cp not Fe_ ; ~ did not disperse using standard techniques, therefore ratios  in italics calculated using an ~stimated % clay from field textures; 3 NS = not spodic, S =  spodic.    ODOE  0.2  0'4  0-6  0.8  1.0  1.2  1.4  1.6  0 ~~~~~/~I__I    I  ~ f~ii~t8~  7O   il AI  ii!iii!ii!iiiiiiiiiiii ,   SO,L ,  iiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiii     9O  Fig.2. ODOE versus depth for the soils of sequence 8--11.    1-8    80  0       8O  6"    8O    ODOE  0.2  0.4  0.6  0-8  1.0  1-2  1.4  1.6  1.8  __  I    I    I    I    I    I    t    I  ::::::::::::::::::::::::::: , "8"         SOIL 5  :::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::  ~ ~  ~l(8)    !i!i!~!~i!i!i~iiiiiiiii!! iiiiiiiiililililiiiiiiiiiiii !ii iiiiiii!iii! A  ~ii}iiiii!iii!,iiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiii~i~i~i~i~i~i~i~i~i~i~i~8'e'  ililiiiiiiiii::iii!iiiililili~i! ,,B  SOIL 6    iiiiiiiiii iiil A1  A2                            IBfeh  ii!iliiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiiUiiii!i///iiI  i         IVuAfe  :iiiiiiiiiil ivc2    SOIL 7    Fig.3. ODOE versus depth for the soils of sequence 5--7.    C~  O1    36    the rainfall sequences. Soil 8 has very low ODOE values with the maximum  in the A horizon. This was the normal pattern found for soils not classified  as podzolised and is consistent with theories that little fulvic acid is formed  and that it is not mobile in soils unaffected by podzolisation. The second soil  in the sequence (9) shows a large increase in the ODOE of the A horizon  with an appreciable level in the B horizon. The next older soil exhibits a  maximum in the B horizon, whereas the oldest soil (11) has a large maximum  in the B horizon indicating considerable movement of organic matter.  Sequence 5 to 7 (Fig.3) again shows patterns similar to those of the other  sequences with the development of maximum ODOE in the B horizon of  more podzolised members of the sequence.  Soil 12, a podzolised soil and soils 13, 14 and 15, which are podzols, all  have large ODOE values in their B horizons and have high B/A ODOE ratios.  To compare the proposed method with a method which uses objective criteria,  calculated values for Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975) spodic horizon  criteria are given in Table III. Also, in Table IV the results for the B hori-    TABLE IV    B horizons listed in increasing order of B/A ODOE ratio and podzol/podzolised soil  and/or spodic horizon status    Soil        B/A      Podzol or      Satisfies spodic  number    ODOE   podzolised*    horizon criteria    8              0.3  5            0.4  1            0.5  9            0.7  6         1.0                 X  3b         1.1    X             X  2          1.5                 X  3a         1.7                x  10         1.9                 X  4b         2.0    x             X  7c         3.0    x              X  13b        3.0    X  4a         3.2    x              7a         3.5                x  7b        3.6    X            x  13a         9.5    x             x  12         10.6    x  11        13.0   x             14b        21     x  14a         31      x  15a        41      X             X  15c       I00     x            x  15b      185     x            x    *According to New Zealand Genetic Classification (Taylor and Pohlen, 1968).    38    Petersen, L., 1976. Podzols and Podzolization. DSR Forlag, Copenhagen, 293 pp.  Ross, C.W., Mew, G. and Searle, P.L., 1977. Soil sequences on two terrace systems in the  North Westland area, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Sci., 20: 231--244.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436:754 pp.  Tarnm, O., 1922. Eine Methode Zur Bestimmung der anorganischen Komponente des  Gelkomplexes im B~den. Medd. Statens Skogsforskningsinst. (Sweden), 19:387--404  Taylor, N.H. and Pohlen, I.J., 1962. Soil Survey Method. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 25:242 pp.  Taylor, N.H. and Pohlen, I.J., 1968. Classification of New Zealand soils. In: Soils of New  Zealand. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 26(1): 15--46.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractA method for separating podzols and podzolised soils from other New Zealand soils is proposed. The method is based on measurement of the optical density of acid oxalate extracts of soils. A number of soil leaching sequences and some individual soils are examined.It is assumed that the optical density of the oxalate extracts is due mainly to extracted fulvic acid and that detection of appreciable quantities of this material in the B horizon indicates that podzolisation is an active process in the soil.The technique separated the soils of the leaching sequences well, following the observable increase of podzolic characteristics with increased leaching.When the B horizon/A horizon ODOE (optical density of the oxalate extracts) ratios were compared with the criteria for the spodic horizon in Ã¢Â€ÂœSoil TaxonomyÃ¢Â€Â (Soil Survey Staff, 1975), it was found that all soils with a ratio of less than 1.0 did not satisfy spodic horizon criteria and were not classified as podzol/podzolised. All the soils examined with ratios &gt; 1.0 satisfied spodic horizon criteria or were classified as podzol/podzolised, usually both. 