 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 349--354                                                     349  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Information Systems for Soil and Related Data. A.W. Moore, B.G. Cook  and L.G. Lynch (Editors). Proceedings of the Second Australian Meeting  of the ISSS Working Group on Soil Information Systems, Canberra,  Australia, 19--21 February, 1980. PUDOC, Wageningen, 1981, 161 pp.,  Dfl. 25.00.    This book contains the papers presented at the fourth in a series of  workshop meetings of members of the Working Group on Soil Information  Systems which was formed within Commission V of the International  Society of Soil Science. The workshop was the second to be held in Canberra  and this obviously reflects the degree of interest and activity in the subject  area.  The topics covered range from the more philosophical aspects of the  nature and structure of data and data modeling to proposals for an infor-  mation system which will allow the modelling of the effects of open-cast  coal mining on subsequent land use through its effects on water-table devel-  opment, and on ground water and tributary stream water quality. At the  data collection stage fill-in and tick-off types of field record sheets are discus-  sed and have their uses depending on the experience of the surveyor and on  whether they need to be readily understood for manual sorting.  Several papers dealt with different aspects of map production. Compari-  sons were made between grid-cell and polygon representation of spatial data.  Both can be handled and the techniques exist to convert from one to the  other to obtain the advantages from both methods. A method of interpolation  converts random point data to a rectangular grid and the grid-cell values are  stored as the database for map production. The integration of LANDSAT  (multispectral imagery) data with traditional land resource surveys is also  discussed.  The extensive use of computer-based soil information systems in Australia  and New Zealand has obviously generated a great deal of critical assessment  of the type of data to he collected, the method of collection, the structure  and maintenance of databases and their use. In some of the systems described  the actual and potential users were not clearly identified. In others the  direction of further development was indicated and there was a requirement  for more software to improve methods of retrival.  The participants agreed that they should meet again in approximately  four years' time. If the next four years show the same amount of progress as  the last, then further significant advances in the subject will be made.    R.H.E. INKSON  (Aberdeen)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            