Geoderma, 24 (1980) 89-100                                                    89  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Ahuja, L. R.; and El-Swaify, S. A. Determining soil hydrologic characteristics on a remote forest  watershed by continuous monitoring of soil-water pressures, rainfall and runoff: Journal of Hydrology.  Elsevier Sci, Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 44, No. 1-2, p. 135-147, 1979.  Alonso, C. V. Applicability of a water and sediment yield routing model [abstr.]:  Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 255, 1979.  American  Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Anderson, M. G. On the potential of radiography to aid studies of hillslope hydrology: Earth Surface  Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons, London-  New York., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 77-83, illus., 1979.  Anonymous. Proposed mining and reclamation plan; Coal Creek Mine, Campbell County, Wyoming:  213 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; topogr, maps 1:24,000), 1979. available from: U. S. Geol. Surv.,  Reston, Va., United States.  Antia, D. D.J. Bone-beds; a review of their classification, occurrence, genesis, diagenesis, geochemistry,  palaeoecology, weathering and microbiotas: Mercian Geologist (East Midlands Geological Society,  Journal). Nc.'tingham., Vol. 7, No. 2, p. 93-174, illus. (incl. sects., plates), 1979.  Atkinson, ~:; and Waugh, B. Morphology and mineralogy of Red Desert Soils in the Libyan Sahara:  Earth Surface Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and  Sons, London-New York., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 103-115, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Babu, D. K. Steady state moisture flows in unsaturated soil containing a plane, isolated, impermeable  barrier: Advances in Water Resources. Southampton, England., Vol. 2, No. 2, p. 35-46, illus., 1979.  Babu, D. K. The retarding influence of an unsaturated zone on a saturated flow under axial symmetry  in three dimensions [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol.  60, No. 18, p. 249, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Baker, F.E. Soil survey of Bastrop County, Texas: 70 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored  soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with Texas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Baker, S. W. Pore size distribution; a factor to be consideret in infiltration studies?: Journal of  Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol, 41, No. 3-4, p. 279-290, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Balyasova, Ye. L.  Metody otsenki nadezhnosti eksperimental'nogo opredeleniya osnovnykh  gidrologicheskikh kharakteristik bolot [Methods of analyzing the reliability of experimental analysis of  the basic hydrological characteristics of marshes]: in Voprosy gidrologii bolot (Novikova, S. M., editor),  Trudy Gosudarstvennogo Gidrologicheskogo Instituta. Leningrad., No. 261, p. 96-109, illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Baragar, W. R. A.; Plant, A. G.; Pringle, G. J.; et al. Diagenetic and postdiagenetic changes in the  composition of an Archean pillow: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences (National Research Council of  Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 16, No. 11, p. 2102-2121 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Bartlett, R.; and James, B. Behavior of chromium in softs; III, Oxidation: Journal of Environmental  Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vo!. 8, No. 1, p. 31-35, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Basak, P. An analytical solution for the transient ditch drainage problem: Journal of Hydrology.  Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No. 3-4, p. 377-382, illus., 1979.  Belobrov, V. P.; and Mazikov, V. M. Ispol'zovaniye azrofotosnimkov pri opredelenii kontrastnosti  pochvennogo pokrova po zasoleniyu [Use of aerial photographs for defining contrasts in salinization of  soil cover]: Akademiya Nauk SSSR, Izvestiya, Seriya Geograficheskaya. Moscow., No. 2, p. 121-128,  illus. (incl. tables), 1979.    90    Berner, R. A.; and Holdren, G. R., Jr. Mechanism of feldspar weathering; II, Observations of feldspars  from soils: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal). Pergamon Press,  Oxford., Vol. 43, No. 8, p. 1173-1186, illus., 1979.  Beven, K. A sensitivity analysis of the Penman-Monteith actual evapotranspiration estimates: Journal  of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 44, No. 3-4, p. 169-190, 1979.  Birkeland, P.W.;Colman, S.M.;Burke, R.M.; etal. Nomenclature ofalpine glacial deposits, or, What's  in a name?: Geology (Geological Society of America). Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 7, No. 11, p. 532-536,  1979.  Blackstoek, D.A. Soil survey of Lubbock County, Texas: 105 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000;  colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Texas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Blanehard, B. J.; and Bausch, W.  A conceptual soil moisture model [abstr.]:  Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 260-261, 1979. American  Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Bonazountas, M.; Hawes, W.; and Tucker, W. Heuristic unsaturated flow/quality soil zone model  [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 249,  1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Bond, W. J.; Collis-George, N.; and Gill, M. A. A layered infiltration model for homogeneous soils:  Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No. 3-4, p. 387-391, 1979.  Bonneton, J. R.; and Truillet, R. Mise en evidence dans la plaine de la Mitidja d'accidents profonds;  consequences hydrologiques et pedologiques (Algerie septentrionale) [Evidence of deep fractures in the  Mitidja Plain; hydrologic and pedologic consequences, northern Algeria]: Societe Geologique de France,  Bulletin. Paris., Vol. 21, No. 1, Supplement, p. 23-25 (incl. English sum.), plate, sketch map, 1979.  Bourlier, B. G.; Nichols, J. D.; Ringwald, W. J.; et al. Soil survey of Osage County, Oklahoma: 164  p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Oklahoma Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Bremner, J. M.; and Blackmer, A. M. Effects of acetylene and soil water content on emission of nitrous  oxide from soils: Nature. London., Vol. 280, No. 5721, p. 380-381, tables, 1979.  Bryan, R. B. The influence of slope angle on soil entrainment by sheetwash and rainsplash: Earth  Surface Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons,  London-New York., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 43-58, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Bulatov, V. K.; Gradusov, B. P.; and Zotov, A. V. Acid leaching of phlogopite: International Geology  Review. American Geological Institute, Falls Church, Virginia., Vol. 21, No. 5, p. 588-596, illus., 1979.  Burke, H. K.; and Burke, W. J. Feasibility of detecting subsurface moisture content utilizing multi-  frequency microwave radiometers [abstr.]:  Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 262, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Burrows, C. J.; and Heine, M. The older moraines of the Stocking Glacier, Mount Cook region: Royal  Society of New Zealand, Journal (supersedesRoyal Society of New Zealand, Transactions). Wellington.,  Vol. 9, No. 1, p. 5-12, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Butt, C. R. M. Geochemistry of a pseudo-gossan developed on a black shale-dolerite contact, Killara,  Western Australia: Journal of Geochemical Exploration (Association of Exploration Geochemists,  Journal). Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 11, No. 2, p. 131-156, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch  maps), 1979.  Campbell, H.V. Soil survey of Jackson County, Kansas: 86 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000;  colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Kansas Agr. Exp. Stn.).  Carpenter, R. H.; and Hayes, W. B. Annual accretion rates of Fe-Mn oxides and certain associated  metals in a stream environment [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 4, p. 173, 1979. The Geological Society of America, Southeastern Section,  28th annual meeting.  Carroll, T. R.; Peek, E. L; and Fritzsehe, A. E. Natural gamma radiation detection to measure soil  moisture [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No.  18, p. 261, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.    91    Case, C. M.; and Welch, A, Pore size distribution, suction and hysteresis in unsaturated groundwater  flow: in Contemporary hydrogeology; the George Burke Maxey memorial volume (Back, W., editor; et  al.), Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 43, No. 1-4, p. 99-120, 1979.  Chamberlain, E. J.; and Gow, A.J. Effect of freezing and thawing on the permeability and structure  of soils: in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 73-92, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  First international symposium.  Cilek, V.  The origin and development of primary and secondary kaolin deposits in Tanzania:  Ceskoslovenska Akademie Ved, Rozpravy, Rada Matematickych Prirodnich Ved. Prague., Vol. 89, No.  1, 62 p. (incl. Czech, Russian sum.), illus. (incl. plates, tables, sects., geol. sketch maps; geol. map  1:5,000,000; geol. map 1:200,000), 1979.  Coates, W. E.; and Scott, O.R. A study of pit and quarry rehabilitation in southern Ontario: Ontario  Geological Survey Miscellaneous Paper (Ontario, Division of Mines, Geological Branch). Toronto., No.  83, 67 p., illus. (incl. tables; land use maps 1:126,720), 1979.  Cole, W. A.; Smith, R. W.; Keyes, J. W.; et al. Soil survey of Hinds County, Mississippi: 112 p., illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep, Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Mississippi Agric. For. Exp. Stn.).  Corapcioglu, M. Y.  Diffusion of dissolved gas in consolidating porous media:  Water Resources  Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 3, p. 563-568, illus., 1979.  Cotton, J. A.; and Fox, B. C. Soil survey of Marion County, Alabama: I00 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Alabama Agric. Exp. Stn.; Alabama Dep. Agric. Indus).  Cuenca, R. H. Soil moisture measurement and evapotranspiration modeling in production function  experiments [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No.  18, p. 260, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Dagan, G.; and Bresler, E. A stochastic model for solute movement through the unsaturated zone  [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 249,  1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Davidson, J. M.; and Rao, P. S.C. Use of pesticide and soil parameters for management of pesticide  waste disposal sites [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol.  60, No. 18, p. 256, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Davies, T. C.; and Bloxam, T.W. Heavy metal distribution in laterites, southwest of Regent, Freetown  igneous complex, Sierra Leone:  Economic Geology and the Bulletin of the Society of Economic  Geologists. New Haven, Connecticut., Vol. 74, No. 3, p. 638-644, tables, geol. sketch map, 1979.  Davis, R. E.; and Byers, K. H. Soil survey of Forrest County, Mississippi: 101 p., illus. (incl. tables;  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agr., Soil Conserv. Serv. and Forestry Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in Cooper. with Mississippi Agr. Forestry Exp. Stn.).  Doyle, P. J.; and Fletcher, W. K. Regional geochemical mapping in areas lacking surface drainages; Cu,  Fe, Mn, and Zn content of overburden and soil in South-central Saskatchewan: Canadian Journal of  Earth Sciences (National Research Council of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 16, No. 5, p. 1086-1093 (incl.  French sum.), tables, sketch maps, 1979.  Dunne, T. Sediment yield and land use in tropical catchments: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier ScL Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 42, No. 3-4, p. 281-300, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch map), 1979.  Dupree, J. A.; and Maslyn, R.M. Paleokarst controls on localization of uranium at Pitch Mine, Sawatch  Range, Colorado [abstr.]: American Association of Petroleum Geologists, Bulletin. Tulsa, Oklahoma.,  Vol. 63, No. 5, p. 826, 1979.  AAPG-SEPM-EMD Rocky Mountain sections, 28th annual meeting.  Dybczynski, R.; Tugsavul, A.; and Suschny, O. SOIL-5, a new IAEA certified reference material for  trace element determinations:  Geostandards Newsletter (Association Nationale de la Recherche  Technique). Paris., Vol. 3, No. 1, p. 61-87 (incl. French sum.), tables, 1979.  Eckardt, H.  Creep behaviour of frozen soils in uniaxial compression tests:  in Ground freezing  (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4,  p. 185-195, illus., 1979.  First international symposium.    92    Elzeftawy, A.; Johnson, T. M.; and Cartwright, K. Field and laboratory study of water and ion transport  in the unsaturated zone beneath waste disposal sites [abstr.]:  Eos (American Geophysical Union,  Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 258, 1979. American Geophys&amp;al Union, 1979spring  annual meeting.  Ernst, J. E.; Hunter, R. L.; and Miller, K.E. An inventory of Ohio soils; Seneca County: Ohio, Division  of Lands and Soil, Progress Report. [Columbus]., No. 55, 57 p., illus. (incl. tables; colored soils map  1:126,720), 1979.  Evans, R. Air photos for soil survey in lowland England; factors affecting the photographic images of  bare soils and their relevance to assessing soil moisture content and discrimination of soils by remote  sensing: Remote Sensing of Environment. American Elsevier Publ. Co., New York., Vol. 8, No. 1, p.  39-63, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Everitt, B. L.; and Graf, W. L. Fluvial adjustments to the spread of tamarisk in the Colorado Plateau  region: Geological Society of America, Bulletin, Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 90, No. 12, p. I 1183-I 1184,  1979.  Feenstra, J. E. Soil survey of Gratiot County, Michigan: 141 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000;  colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Michigan Agr. Exp. Stn.).  Fenwiek, R. W.; and Ratcliff, L W., Jr. Soil survey of Sumner County, Kansas: 110 p., illus. (incl. tables;  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Kansas Agr. Exp. Stn.).  Fernandez-Mareos, M. L.; Maeias, F.; and Guitian-Ojea, F. A contribution to the study of the stability  of clay minerals from the soil solution composition at different pF values: Clay Minerals (Mineralogical  Society, Clay Minerals Group, Journal). Oxford-Edinburgh., Vol. 14, No. 1, tables (incl. French,  German, Spanish sum.), 1979.  Firman, J. B.  Paleopedology applied to land use studies in southern Australia:  Geoderma, an  International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 22, No. 2, p. 105-117,  illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Fuller, W. H. Soil and leachate parameters affecting heavy metal transport [abstr.]: Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 256, 1979.  American  Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Gaipova, A.; and Aranbayev, M.P. Valovoy khimicheskiy sostav pochv drevney del'ty r. Tedzhen [The  total chemical composition of soils supported by the ancient delta of the Tedzhen River]: Problemy  Osvoyeniya Pustyn' (Akademiya Nauk Turkmenskoy SSR, Institut Pustyn'). Ashkhabad., No. 1, p. 34-  42 (incl. English sum.), tables, 1979.  Gardner, W. S.; and Hanson, R.B. Dissolved free amino acids in interstitial waters of Georgia salt marsh  soils:  Estuaries (Estuarine Research Federation, Journal) (formerly Chesapeake Science). Solomons,  Maryland., Vol. 2, No. 2, p. 113-118, tables, 1979.  Gee, G. W.; and Simmons, C.S. Simulation of variable climate and layered soil effects on water transport  at an arid zone burial ground [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington,  D. C., Vo[. 60, No. 18, p. 258, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Gifford, G.F. Infiltration dynamics under various rangeland treatments on uniform sandy-loam soils in  southeastern Utah: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 42, No. 1-2, p. 179-  185, illus, (incl. table), 1979.  Glazovskaya, M. A.  Landshaftno-geokhimicheskoye rayonirovaniye Nechernozemnoy zony po  usloviyam razlozheniya i rasseyaniya organicheskikh zagryaznyayushchikh veshchestv [A landscape-  geochemical regionalization of the Non-Chernozem Zone according to the conditions of decomposition  and dispersion of organic contaminating substances]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5,  Geografiya. Moscow., No. 2, p. 10-18 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Graf, W. L. The development of montane arroyos and gullies: Earth Surface Processes (Journal of the  British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons, London-New York., Vol. 4, No. 1,  p. 1-14, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Graustein, W. C.; and Owens, L.B. Landscape reduction by weathering in small Rhodesian watersheds:  Geology (Geological Society of America) Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 7, No. 11, p. 515-517, 1979.    93    Greenwood, E. A. N.; and Beresford, J. D. Evaporation from vegetation in landscapes developing  secondary salinity using the ventilated-chamber technique; I, Comparative transpiration from juvenile  Eucalyptus above saline groundwater seeps: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.,  Vol. 42, No. 3-4, p. 369-382, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Grimes, K. G. The stratigraphic sequence of old land surfaces in northern Queensland: BMR Journal  of Australian Geology and Geophysics (Australia, Bureau of Mineral Resources, Geology and  Geophysics). Canberra., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 33-46, sects., plates, strat, cols., sketch maps, 1979.  Guecione, M. J. Recognition and time significance of buried soils developed on Quaternary tills,  Midcontinent, U.S.A. [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 5, p. 231, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 13th  annual meeting.  Gureghian, A.B. A two dimensional finite element solution for the prediction of soil-water pressure and  soil-water content distribution in drained soils under steady and transient state conditions [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 249, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Gureghian, A. B.; Ward, D. S.; and Cleary, R.W. Simultaneous transport of water and reacting solutes  through multilayered soils under transient unsaturated flow conditions: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier  Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No. 3-4, p. 253-278, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Haig, M. J, Ground retreat and slope evolution on regraded surface-mine dumps, Waunafon, Gwent:  Earth Surface Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and  Sons, London-New York., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 183-189, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Hall, N. W.; and Dalrymple, J. B. A method for making serial thin sections of soils and other  unconsolidated materials: Earth Surface Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research  Group). John Wiley and Sons, London-New York., Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 85-88, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Hanken, N. M. The use of sodium tetraphenylborate and sodium chloride in the extraction of fossils  from shales: Journal of Paleontology. Tulsa, Oklahoma., Vol. 53, No. 3, p. 738-741, illus., 1979.  Heiken, G. H.; and Bevier, M. L. Petrology of tuff units from the J- 13 drill site, Jackass Flats, Nevada:  Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory (University of California), [Report]. Los Alamos, New Mexico., 55  p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. LA-7563-MS) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United  States.  Heilman, J. L.; and Moore, D. G, Thermal remote sensing of soil moisture for developing crop canopies  [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261,  1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Helling, C.S. Useofpesticide-soildataforevaluatinglanddisposaloftoxicorganicwastes [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 256, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Henriksen, A. A simple approach for identifying and measuring acidification of freshwater: Nature.  London., Vol. 278, No. 5704, p. 542-545, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Herriman, R. C.; and Parsons, R. B.  Land use and management of soils with relict duripans,  southwestern Oregon (U.S.A.): Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 22, No. 2, p. 99-103, 1979.  Hey, R. D. Dynamic process-response model of river channel development: Earth Surface Processes  (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons, London-New York.,  Vol. 4, No. 1, p. 59-72, illus. (incl. charts), 1979.  Holdren, G. R., Jr.; and Berner, R. A. Mechanism of feldspar weathering; I, Experimental studies:  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal). Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol.  43, No. 8, p. 1161-1172, illus., 1979.  Holeman, J. N. The national erosion inventory in progress; U. S. Department of Agriculture, Soil  Conservation Service [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions), Washington, D. C.,  Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 255, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Hoskin, C. M.; and Sundeen, D.A. Enchanted Rock Batholith, Texas; a study of coarse-grained granite  and its derived sediments [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 4, p. 183, 1979. The Geological Society of America, Southeastern Section, 28th annual  meeting.    94    Howard, K. W. F.; and Lloyd, J.W. The sensitivity of parameters in the Penman evaporation equations  and direct recharge balance: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No.  3-4, p. 329-344, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Hsu, W. W. Potassium release by some Delaware soils: Communications in Soil Science and Plant  Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-Basel., Vol. 10, No. 7, p. 1037-1055, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Hutehison, D. E. Soil survey of Midland County, Michigan: 98 p., illus. (incl. tables; colored soils maps  1:190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1979.  Ireland, P. Geomorphological variations of 'case-hardening' in Puerto Rico:  in Problems in karst  environments (Sweeting, M., editor), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-  Stuttgart., No. 32, p. 9-20 (incl. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. plates, sketch map), 1979.  Jackson, R. D.  Remote sensing of soil moisture using the visible and infrared regions of the  electromagnetic spectrum [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D,  C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Jaeobson, R.B. Podzolization associated with a 40 year jack pine community in southeastern Minnesota  [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 5,  p. 232, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 13th annual meeting.  Johnson, R. Grouting silt and sand at low temperatures; a laboratory investigation: CRREL (Cold  Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory) Report. Hanover, New Hampshire., No. 79-5, 33 p., illus.  (incl. tables), 1979. available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Johnson, T. C.; Cole, D. M.; and Chamberlain, E.J. Effect of freeze-thaw cycles on resilient properties  of fine-grained soils: in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci.  Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 247-276, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  First international  symposium.  Jumikis, A. R. Cryogenic texture and strength aspects of artificially frozen soils: in Ground freezing  (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Puhl. Co., Amsterdam., Vol, 13, No. 1-4,  p. 125-135, illus., 1979.  First international symposium.  Jumikis, A.R. Some aspects of artificial thawing of frozen soils: in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L,,  editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Puhl. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 287-297, illus.,  1979.  First international symposium.  Kalyuzhnyy, L L. Teploakkumulyatsiya i teplooborot v torfyanoy zalezhi oligotrofnykh bolotnykh  massivov [Heat accumulations and heat circulation in peat deposits of oligotrophic marshlands]:  in  Voprosy gidrologii bolot (Novikova, S. M., editor), Trudy Gosudarstvennogo Gidrologicheskogo  Instituta. Leningrad., No. 261, p. 81-89, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Karlov, V, D.  Frost heave of unsaturated loamy soil under field conditions:  in Ground freezing  (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4,  p. 53-62, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  First international symposium.  Kelly, J.M. Camp Branch and Cross Creek experimental watershed projects; objectives, facilities, and  ecological characteristics: 153 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979. (Rep, No. EPA-600/7-79-053)  (Rep. No. TVA/ONR-79/04) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Khan, I. A.; and Labadie, J.W. River basin salinity management via the ASTRAN method; I, Model  development: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 42, No. 3-4, p. 301-321,  illus., 1979.  Kharehenko, K. L  Izmeneniye ispareniya s sel'skokhozyaystvennykh poley pod vliyaniyem  osushitel'noy melioratsii [Altering evaporation in agricultural fields under the influence of drainage  improvement]:  in Voprosy gidrologii bolot (Novikova, S. M., editor), Trudy Gosudarstvennogo  Gidrologicheskogo Instituta. Leningrad., No. 261, p. 116-124, tables, 1979.  Klappa, C.F. Lichen stromatolites; criterion for subaerial exposure and a mechanism for the formation  of laminar calcretes (caliche): Journal of Sedimentary Petrology. Tulsa, Oklahoma., Vol. 49, No. 2, p.  387-400, illus., 1979.  Klein, J.; and Jessberger, H.L. Creep stress analysis of frozen soils under multiaxial states of stress:  in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.,  Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 353-365, illus., 1979.  First internationalsymposium.    95    Knapp, B.J. Elements of geographical hydrology: 80 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), George Allen  &amp; Unwin, London, United Kingdom, 1979.  Koenig, B.A. Compositional change and chemical mass transport as a result of supergene processes at  the San Xavier North porphyry copper deposit, Arizona [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 87, 1979.  The Geological Society of  America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Koussis, A. D.; and Chow, S. L, An analytical-numerical solution of transient flow through unsaturated  porous media [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60,  No. 18, p. 249, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Kreitler, C.W. Nitrogen-isotope ratio studies of soils and groundwater nitrate from alluvial fan aquifers  in Texas: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 42, No. 1-2, p. 147-170, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Ku, T. L.; Bull, W. B.; Freeman, S. T.; et al. Th230-UTM dating of pedogenic carbonates in gravelly desert  soils of Vidal Valley, southeastern California:  Geological Society of America, Bulletin. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 90, No. 11, p. 1 1063-I 1073, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Labadie, J. W.; and Khan, I.A. River basin salinity management via the ASTRAN method; II, Case  study: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 42, No. 3-4, p. 323-345, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Lantz, R. B.; and Baea, R.G. Nuclide migration from tank leaks into the unsaturated zone [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 256, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Lin, S.;andShih, G. Management possibilities ofdrought moderation in Southeast Florida [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 251, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Loijens, H. S.; and Topp, G.C. Measurement of surface soil water content from natural gamma radiation  using a portable gamma-ray spectrometer [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Lovell, J. P. B. Composition of Holocene sands of Mull and adjacent offshore areas; a study of  provenance: Great Britain, Institute of Geological Sciences, Report. London., No. 79/2, 9 p. (incl.  French, German sum.), table, sketch map, 1979.  Ludden, J. N.; and Thompson, G. An evaluation of the behavior of the rare earth elements during the  weathering of sea-floor basalt: Earth and Planetary Science Letters; a Letter Journal Devoted to the  Development in Time of the Earth and Planetary System. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 43,  No. 1, p. 85-92, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Mannion, A. M. Chemical analyses of a peat profile from Threepwood Moss, Southeast Scotland:  Chemosphere. Pergamon Press, Oxford-New York-Paris., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 233-242, illus. (incl. tables,  strat, cols., sketch maps), 1979.  Mapes, D.R. Soil survey of Du Page and part of Cook counties, Illinois: 217 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol.  sketch maps; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Ill. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Marehand, D. E.; and Harden, J. W. A stratigraphic sequence of Quaternary colluvial and alluvial  deposits and soils, western Sierra Nevada foothills, California [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 90, 1979.  The Geological Society of  America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Matsuo, S.; Nishida, K.; and Sasaki, S. Physical properties of weathered granite soil particles and their  effect on permeability: Soils and Foundations (Japanese Society of Soil Mechanics and Foundation  Engineering). Tokyo., Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 13-22, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  May, J.P. Quaternary geology of Hobcaw Barony, coastal plain of South Carolina [abstr.]: Geological  Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 4, p. 205, 1979.  The  Geological Society of America, Southeastern Section, 28th annual meeting.  Mayhugh, R. E.; and Bartolina, D.G. Soil survey of Seminole County, Oklahoma: 142 p., illus. (incl.  tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agr., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Oklahoma Agr. Exp. Stn.).    96    McCormick, G. W. Till fabrics and pedoturbations in some soils of Minnesota: Minnesota Academy  of Science, Journal. Minneapolis., Vol. 45, No. 1, p. 6-7, illus., 1979.  McDuff, R. E.; Edmond, J. M.; and Grant, B. Strontium in the Amazon and its tributaries [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 293, 1979.  American Geophysical Union; 1979 spring annual meeting.  McFarland, M. J.; Blanchard, B. J.; and Theis, S, W. Correlations of brightness temperatures from the  electrically scanning microwave radiometer (ESMR) with antecedent precipitation indices (API) [abstr.]:  Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 262, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  McKim, H. L. A review of methods for measurement of in-situ soil moisture conditions [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 260, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Megumi, K. Radioactive disequilibrium of uranium and actinium series nuclides in soil: Journal of  Geophysical Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D. C., Vol. 84, No. B7, p. 3677-  3682, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Miller, B. A.; Daniel, T. C.; and Berkowitz, S.J. Computer programs for calculating soil loss on a  watershed basis: Environmental Management. Springer-Verlag, New York-Heidelberg-Berlin., Vol. 3,  No. 3, p, 237-270, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Miller, C.D. A statistical method for relative-age dating of moraines in the Sawatch Range, Colorado:  Geological Society of America, Bulletin. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 90, No. 12, p, I 1151-I 1164, illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Moebius, G. E.; and Sparwasser, W.A. Soil survey of McClain County, Oklahoma: 103 p., illus. (incl.  tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Oklahoma Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Monakhov, A. K. Ob ispol'zovanii aerosnimkov pri kartirovanii kamenistosti pochv [Application of  aerial photography for rock outcrop soil mapping]:  Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo,  Izvestiya. Leningrad., Vol. 3, No. 2, p. 160-163, 1979.  Murali, V.; Krishna Murti, G. S. R.; and Sinha, A.K. Statistical relationships of water flow parameters  with soil matrix and porosity properties: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  41, No. 3-4, p. 371-377, 1979.  Nambudiri, E. M. V.; Shay, C. T.; and Teller, J.T. Pollen stratigraphy of late Pleistocene and Holocene  sediments from Lake Manitoba, Canada [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with  Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 5, p. 253, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, North-  Central Section, 13th annual meeting.  Narasimhan, T.N. The significance of the storage parameter in saturated-unsaturated groundwater flow:  Water Resources Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 15, No. 3, p. 569-  576, illus., 1979.  Nelson, A. R.; Millington, A. C.; Andrews, J. T.; et al. Radiocarbon-dated upper Pleistocene glacial  sequence, Fraser Valley, Colorado Front Range: Geology (Geological Society of America). Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 7, No. 8, p. 410-414, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Neumeister, H.  Das "Schichtkonzept" und einfache Algorithmen zur Vertikalverknuepfung von  "Schichten" in der physischen Geographie [The "stratum concept" and simple algorithms on the vertical  linking of "strata" in physical geography]: Petermanns Geographische Mitteilungen. Gotha., Vol. 123,  No. 1, p. 19-23, illus., 1979.  Nixon, R. A. Formation of allophane from some granitic rocks [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 4, p. 207, 1979.  The Geological Society of  America, Southeastern Section, 28th annual meeting.  Nixon, R.A. Weathering of the Panola Granite to gibbsite in an acidic environment; a model for bauxite  genesis [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11,  No. 4, p. 207, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Southeastern Section, 28th annual meeting.  Njoku, E. G.; Kahle, A. B.; Schieldge, J.; et al. Microwave and infrared radiometric measurements of  soil moisture in Kern County, California [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 262, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.    97    Novikov, F. Ya. Pressure of thawing soils on the concrete lining of vertical mine shafts:  in Ground  freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13,  No. 1-4, p. 277-286, 1979. First international symposium.  Page, A. L.; and Sposito, G. Trace metal attenuation in soils [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical  Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., VoL 60, No. 18, p. 256, 1979. American Geophysical Union,  1979 spring annual meeting.  Palland, C. L. The "evaporation brush", an evaporimeter for measuring the potential evaporation of  meadow grass: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No. 3-4, p. 363-369,  illus., 1979.  Pavich, M. J.; and Markewieh, H. W. Soil stratigraphy of fluvial terraces along the Potomac and  Rappahannock rivers, Virginia [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 1 l, No. 4, p. 207, 1979.  The GeologicalSociety of America, Southeastern Section,  28th annual meeting.  Pease, R.C. Fault scarp degradation in alluvium near Carson City, Nevada [abstr.]: Geological Society  of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. ll, No. 3, p. 121, 1979.  The Geological  Society of America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Pestrong, R. Coastaltafoni;thecaseoftheblue-eyedMadonna[abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 121, 1979.  The Geological Society of  America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Peterson, D.M. Hillslope erosional processes related to bedrock, soils, and topography in the Three  Peaks area, Marin County, California [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 121, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Cordilleran Section,  75th annual meeting.  Peterson, H. V.; and Melin, K. R. Investigations by the U. S. Geological Survey of soil and moisture  conservation on public domain lands, 1941-1964: U. S. Geological Survey, Open-File Report. Reston,  Virginia., No. 79-987, 271 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv.  Sect., Branch Distrib., Denver, Colo., United States.  Price, J. C. The role of remotely sensed infra red data in assessing the surface moisture budget [abstr.]:  Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Ralston, C. W.; Woodwell, G. M.; Whittaker, R. H.; et al. Where has all the carbon gone?: Science  (American Association for the Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., Vol. 204, No. 4399, p.  1345-1346, 1979.  Readle, E.L. Soil survey of Osceola County area, Florida: 151 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000;  colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Florida; Inst. Food Agric. Sci. Agric. Exp. Stn., Soil Sci. Dep.).  Reardon, E. J.; Allison, G. B.; and Fritz, P. Seasonal chemical and isotopic variations of soil CO2 at  Trout Creek, Ontario:  in Contemporary hydrogeology; the George Burke Maxey memorial volume  (Back, W., editor; et al.), Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 43, No. 1-4,  p. 355-371, 1979.  Richardson, M. L.; Clemmons, S.; and Walker, J. C. Soil survey of Santa Cruz and parts of Cochise  and Pima counties, Arizona: 100 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:380,160),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., For. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in  cooperation with Arizona Agr. Exp. Stn.).  Robinson, A. R.  Erosion and sedimentation research in the USDA, Science and Education  Administration [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60,  No. 18, p. 255, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Rouse, J. W., Jr.  Capabilities of microwave for soil moisture monitoring [abstr.]:  Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D, C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261, 1979.  American  Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Rushton, K. R.; and Ward, C. The estimation of groundwater recharge: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier  Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 41, No. 3-4, p. 345-361, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.    98    Safai, N. M.; and Pinder, G. F. Vertical and horizontal land deformation in a desaturating porous  medium: Advances in Water Resources. Southampton, England., Vol. 2, No. 2, p. 19-25, illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Savinkin, A. P. Vodnyy rezhim burykh pochv i transpiratsiya rasteniy v seropolynnikakh Severnogo  Priatal'ya [Water regime in brown soils profiles and plant transpiration in Artemisia terrae albae  communities of the northern Aral region]:  Problemy Osvoyeniya Pustyn' (Akademiya Nauk  Turkmenskoy SSR, Institut Pustyn'). Ashkhabad., No. 1, p. 44-50 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Saxton, K.E. Modeling approaches to soil moisture determination [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical  Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 260, 1979. American Geophysical Union,  1979 spring annual meeting.  Shamakhov, A. F.; and Zemtsov, A. A. Mnogoletnyaya reliktovaya merzlota v Zapadnoy Sibiri i yeye  paleogeograficheskoye  znacheniye  [Perennial  relict  Frozen ground  in West Siberia and its  paleogeographic meaning]: Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, lzvestiya. Leningrad., Vol.  3, No. 2, p. 150-155, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Shearman, D.J. A field test for identification of gypsum in soils and sediments: Quarterly Journal of  Engineering Geology (Geological Society of London)., Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 51, 1979.  Simons, R. K.; and Keefer, T. N. Use of Landsat imagery in sediment modeling of strip mined areas  [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D, C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 260,  1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Singler, C. R.; and Pieard, M.D. Paleosols as environmental indicators in nonmarine sedimentary rocks;  example from Brule Formation [abstr.]: American Association of Petroleum Geologists, Bulletin. Tulsa,  Oklahoma., Vol. 63, No. 5, p. 841, 1979.  AAPG-SEPM-EMD Rocky Mountain sections, 28th annual  meeting.  Sissons, J. B. The Loch Lomond Stadial in the British Isles: Nature. London., Vol. 280, No. 5719, p.  199-203, sketch maps, 1979.  Smiles, D. E.; and Knight, J. H. The transient water table beneath a leaking canal:  Journal of  Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 44, No. 1-2, p. 149-162, 1979.  Soni, J. P.; and Basak, P. Drainage due to gravity under non-Darcy flow: Irrigation and Power (India,  Central Board of Irrigation and Power). New Delhi., Vol. 36, No. 1, p. 75-79, illus. (incl. tables, sect.),  1979.  Spivey, L. D., Jr. Soil survey of Cleburne County, Alabama:  58 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps  1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agr., Soil Conserv. Serv. and Forest Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with Alabama Agr. Exp. Stn. and Alabama Dep. Agr. Industries).  Stallard, R. F.; and Edmond, J. M. Cyclic salt balance in the Amazon Basin [abstr.]: Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 292-293, 1979.  American  Geophysical Union; 1979 spring annual meeting.  Stephenson, G.R. Effect of drought conditions on groundwater supplies in a Southwest Idaho rangeland  watershed [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No.  18, p. 251, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Takegawa, K.; Nakazawa, A.; Ryokai, K.; etal. Creep characteristics of frozen soils: inGround freezing  (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4,  p. 197-205, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  First international symposium.  Taylor, R. M.; and Bond, R.D. Electrolytic weathering effects in minerals: Geoderma, an International  Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 22, No. 2, p. 85-97, illus. (incl. table),  1979.  Topp, G. C.; Davis, J. L.; and Annan, A. P. Electromagnetic determination of soil water content;  measurements in coaxial transmission lines [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 260, 1979. American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Tsytovieh, N. A.; and Kronik, Ya. A.  Interrelationship of the principal physicomechanical and  thermophysical properties of coarse-grained frozen soils: in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor),  Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 163-167, 1979. First  international symposium.    99    Uiaby, F. T.; Bradley, G. A.; and Dobson, M. C.  Microwave backscatter dependence on surface  roughness, soil moisture, and soil texture; Part II, Vegetation covered soil: IEEE (Institute of Electrical  and Electronics Engineers) Transactions on Geoscience Electronics, New York., Vol. GE-17, No. 2, p.  33-40, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Van Zant, K. Late- and postglacial pollen and plant macrofossil sequences from Lake West Okoboji,  Iowa [ahstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No.  5, p. 259, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 13th annual meeting.  Vieillard, P.; Tardy, Y.; and Nahon, D. Stability fields of clays and aluminum phosphates; parageneses  in lateritic weathering of argillaceous phosphatic sediments: American Mineralogist (Mineralogical  Society of America, Journal). Washington, D. C., Vol. 64, No. 5-6, p. 626-634, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Villamil, R. J., Jr.; and Magdoff, F. R. Water flow and liquid waste disposal in a clay soil [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 258-259, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Volebok, H. L. An analytical intercomparison exercise [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union,  Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 283, 1979. American Geophysical Union; 1979spring  annual meeting.  Vyalov, S. S.; Zaretsky, Yu. K..; and Gorodetsky, S. E. Stability of mine workings in frozen soils: in  Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.,  Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 339-351, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  First international symposium.  Walsb, B. L.; and Griggs, G. B. Hydrology of Hungry Valley, California [abstr.]: Geological Society  of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 133, 1979.  The Geological  Society of America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Wang, J. R.; and Newton, R. W. The passive microwave remote sensing of soil moisture content; the  effect of tilled row structure [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington,  D. C., Vol. 60, No. 18, p. 261-262, 1979.  American Geophysical Union, 1979 spring annual meeting.  Wasson, R. J.; Hunt, P. A.; and Clarke, M. F. A re-evaluation of the "silcretes" of the Cobar area,  Australia: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  22, No. 2, p. 137-159, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1979.  Watts, S. H. Some observations on rock weathering, Cumberland Peninsula, Baffin Island: Canadian  Journal of Earth Sciences (National Research Council of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 16, No. 5, p. 977-983  (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Waylen, M.J. Chemical weathering in a drainage basin underlain by Old Red Sandstone: Earth Surface  Processes (Journal of the British Geomorphological Research Group). John Wiley and Sons, London  New York., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 167-178, tables, sketch map, 1979.  Weaver, W. E.; Kelsey, H. M.; Madej, M. A.; et al. Minimizing concentrated runoff, surface erosion  and mass slope movement in Redwood National Park by removing former logging haul roads [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 134,  1979.  TheGeological Society of America, Cordilleran Section, 75th annual meeting.  Westman, W.E. Oxidant effects on Californian coastal sage scrub: Science (American Association for  the Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., Vol. 205, No. 4410, p. 1001-1003, illus., 1979.  Whittaker, E. L.; and Grothaus, G. E. Acid dissolution method for the analysis of plutonium in soil;  evaluation of an interlaboratory collaborative test and comparison with results of a fusion method test:  61 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. EPA-600/7-79-081) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va.,  United States.  Whitteear, G.R. Late Pleistocene geomorphic history of the Pecatonica River valley, Wisconsin and  Illinois [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11,  No. 5, p. 259, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, North-Central Section, 13th annual meeting.  Wild, A.; and Mazaheri, A.  Prediction of the leaching rate of boric acid under field conditions:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 22, No.  2, p. 127-136, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Wilson, M.J. Penecontemporaneous weathering of the Old Red Sandstone in the Midland Valley of  Scotland; discussion: Scottish Journal of Geology. Edinburgh., Vol. 15, Part 1, p. 65-66, 1979.    100    Woods, J. C. Soil survey of Bibb County, Georgia: 88 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored  soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Georgia, Coll. Agr., Agr. Exp. Stn.).  Yamaguchi, H.; Kimura, T.; and Fuji-I, N. On the influence of progressive failure on the bearing capacity  of shallow foundations in dense sand; reply: Soils and Foundations (Japanese Society of Soil Mechanics  and Foundation Engineering). Tokyo., Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 93-95, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Yariv, S.; Mendelovici, E.; Villalba, R.; et al. Transformation of goethite to maghaemite in CsI disks:  Nature, London., Vol. 279, No. 5713, p. 519-520, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Yaworski, M.; Rector, D.; Eckenrode, J.; et al. Soil survey of Crawford County, Pennsylvania: 73 p.,  illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agr., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Penna. Dep. Environ, Resour. State  Con. Comm.).  Yeh, H. W.; and Eslinger, E. V. D/H and 180/160 ratios and the mineralogy of Mississippi River  sediments [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No.  18, p. 294, 1979. American Geophysical Union; 1979 spring annual meeting.  Yong, R. N.; Cheung, C. H.; and Sheeran, D.E. Prediction of salt influence on unfrozen water content  in frozen soils: in Ground freezing (Jessberger, H. L., editor), Engineering Geology. Elsevier Sci, Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 13, No. 1-4, p. 137-155, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  First international symposium.  Zientek, M. L.; Radtke, A. S.; and Oscarson, R.L. Mineralogy of oxidized vanadiferous carbonaceous  siltstone, Cockalorum Wash, Nevada [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 137, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, Cordilleran Section,  75th annual meeting.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               