35]    Proceedings of the Second International Soil Classification Workshop, 1978.  I. Malaysia; II. Thailand. F.H. Beinroth and S. Paramananthan (Editors).  Soil Survey Division, Land Development Department, Bangkok, 1979.  I: 345 pp.; lI: 432 pp.    The Second International Workshop on Soil Classification consisted of  two parts, one held in Malaysia and one in Thailand. This workshop was part  of a comprehensive international effort to adapt Soil Taxonomy to the  edaphic conditions of the tropics and subtropics. One of the major accom-  plishments was to bring together soil scientists who would not normally be  able to meet together for an exchange of ideas about the classification of  soils of the tropics and subtropics. Many of these scientists were from the  lesser developed countries (LDC's).  The Malaysian part was heavily devoted to discussions of the concepts and  classification of Oxisols including descriptions of these soils occurring in  Asia, Oceania, Africa and the Americas.  Following an excellent keynote address by Dr. Fred H. Beinroth which set  forth the rationale, intent and perspective of the workshop, the meeting in  Malaysia consisted of five work sessions. The first dealt with a general topic,  "Soil Taxonomy and Soils of the Tropics", which included a paper by Dr.  Rudy Dudal of FAO, "Adequacy of Soil Surveys and Soil Classification for  Practical Applications in Developing Countries". This paper set the tone for  further papers and discussions.  The remaining four workshops dealt with various topics related to Oxisols.  Titles of these were: Concepts of Oxisols; Classification of Oxisols; Oxisols  in Asia and Oceania; and Oxisols in Africa and the Americas.  There is a tremendous amount of information i J these proceedings although  the format and writing style varies from paper to paer. For example, the  chemistry and mineralogy of Oxisols as well as their geomorphology are  discussed in detail. Soil descriptions and data from soil characterizations of  Oxisols from various countries are also given. There is a report of the Inter-  national Committee on the classification of Oxisols.  In the Appendix of the Proceedings are given detailed descriptions of the  soil profiles and analytical data for eleven soil series studied during the  field trips in Malaysia.    H. Thailand  With a format similar to that of the Malaysian meetings, the workshop  continued with fruitful discussions among the conference participants and  also visits to some 20 Thai soil series sites in the field. The focus of the Thai  sessions was on low-activity clay Alfisols and Ultisols. There were, however,  discussions on related subject matter areas in the Summary Session of the  Workshop.  The practical aspects of the Thai portion of the workshop were empha-  sized in an opening address by Dr. Guy D. Smith of the United States, en-    352    titled, "Problems of Application of Soil Taxonomy with Special Reference  to Tropical Soils with Low-Activity Clays".  The volume contains a wealth of information relating to the chemistry  and mineralogy of low-activity clays and the micromorphology of Alfisols  and Ultisols. There is a useful discussion of the concept of the argillic hori-  zon. Descriptions of low-activity clay soils from different countries repre-  senting several continents were also included. Concepts for the classification  of Alfisols and Ultisols with low activity clays were discussed.  An excellent presentation by R. Guerro of the University of Puerto Rico,  "Soil Taxonomy in Tropical America", gave the participants an insight into  the progress which has been made in the past ten years of soil classification  in the tropical American countries.  More than half of the pages of this volume are devoted to the Tour Guide  of Thailand. There are descriptions of the physical environment, soils of the  excursion area, detailed descriptions of the profile sites and an abundance of  soil characterization data from these sites. These even include plates of soil  thin sections in color. This should be a very useful collection for those in-  terested in Thai soils (and those of neighboring countries).  Some of the principal tasks which remain for the group were spelled out  in detail by Dr. Beinroth at the close of the sessions. The intent to plan simi-  lar workshops in other parts of the world in the future by the University of  Puerto Rico subject to availability of funds was indicated. Dr. Beinroth urged  that soil taxonomy be used as the universal system for attempts to solve  practical problems including agro-technology transfer and agricultural develop-  ment in the LDC's. He recommended the establishment of an authoritative  international entity which can arbitrate the discrepancies that will emerge in  worldwide soil correlation. Finally he urged that the most challenging task  ahead for pedologists is land evaluation. Although a conceptual framework  for modern land evaluation has been established under the able leadership of  FAO, enormous interdisciplinary efforts are still needed to translate these  concepts into practicality.  The Proceedings are recommended for those interested in the philosophy  of how soil taxonomic information may be put into practical use. There is  useful technical information for those interested in Oxisols and in low-activity  clay Alfisols and Ultisols. And finally the proceedings demonstrate that an  exchange of information by Asians, Latin Americans, North Americans and  Europeans on a topic which is vital to world food production can be very  beneficial both to the participants and to those of us who were not privileged  to be able to attend the workshops.    L.A. NELSON  (Raleigh, N.C.)                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       