 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 341--354  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    341    PHOSPHORUS AND ITS UTILIZATION IN SOILS OF DRY REGIONS*    J. RYAN  American University at Beirut, Beirut (Lebanon)  (Received November 17, 1981; accepted after revision October 6, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Ryan, J., 1983. Phosphorus and its utilization in soils of dry regions. Geoderma, 29:  341--354.    This review deals with selected aspects of the forms, behavior and utilization of phos-  phorus in soils of dry regions. Such regions embrace most developing nations in the world.  Amounts and major forms of phosphorus in the soils, indices of availability, fertilizer  sources, initial and residual effects, modes of application and possibilities for improved  utilization are considered. The supply and availability of phosphorus is a key factor in  crop production. Consequently, for appreciable increases in production in dry regions,  improvements in utilization of phosphorus are needed. Several possible improvements are  therefore proposed as the final part of this paper.    INTRODUCTION    The purpose of this paper is to highlight certain aspects of the behavior  of both native and added phosphorus unique to soils of dry regions. In ad-  dition to consideration of the nature and forms of phosphorus, possibilities  for increased efficiency in utilization of the element are also discussed. The  paper reflects the experience of the author in the southwestern United  States and in the Middle East. Limitations of space preclude full considera-  tion of all aspects of phosphorus behavior. For the same reasons, an effort is  not made to cover all dry parts of the world. Data are drawn instead from  sample areas. Finally, comprehensive reviews are available on the role of  phosphorus in agriculture (Khasawneh et al., 1980), phosphorus in softs  (Larsen, 1967) and organic phosphorus in soils (Dalal, 1977).  Much remains to be learned about phosphorus in soils of dry regions,  especially in the large portion that are calcareous. Such soils have received  limited attention in the past, primarily because research centers were located    *Contribution from the Department of Soils, Irrigation, and Mechanization, Faculty of  Agricultural and Food Sciences, American University of Beirut, Beirut, Lebanon, Journal  Paper No. 574B. Presented at "Symposium on Soils of Dry Regions", Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  meetings, Detroit, Michigan, USA, 1980.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    342    in humid regions with greater possibilities for crop production. Interest  in greater production from softs of dry regions has increased in recent  years, however, with the growing world population. Major research centers  have been established in semi-arid and arid regions, as for example the Inter-  national Center for Agricultural Research in Dry Areas (ICARDA) in Syria  and Lebanon. Summarizing current understanding of the behavior of phos-  phorus in the soils of arid and semi-arid regions should be of value to the  research being started at the present time and also to the poor countries  predominant in dry parts of the world.    AMOUNTS AND FORMS OF PHOSPHORUS    The amounts of phosphorus in agricultural softs of the world range from  virtually none to a maximum near 0.4% (4,000 ppm). The amounts in soils  of dry regions seem to bracket all or much of that range, with values of 860  to 1,290 ppm in the western United States (Pierre and Norman, 1953),  375 to 2,535 in Lebanon (Hasan, 1980) and only 3 to 11 ppm in Saudi Arabia  (I. Bashour, personal communication, 1980). Extremely low values place a  ceiling on the capacity of soils to release phosphorus to available forms.  Crop production from such softs will thus be heavily dependent on added  phosphorus.  Like total amounts, profile distribution of phosphorus has a wide range.  Amounts tend to be higher in the surface layers than in deeper horizons,  although that trend is reversed in some instances. The profile distribution  seems related to the rock source of the soil parent materials, the degree of  profile development, past fertilization, and removals of soil materials by  erosion.  In contrast to soils of humid regions, those under dry climates have  small amounts of phosphorus in organic form. In samples from the Punjab  of Pakistan, Ryan and Zghard (1980) found that organic phosphorus was  less than 10% of the total. Phosphorus in organic forms was virtually absent  from softs studied in Saudi Arabia (I. Bashour, personal communication,  1980).  Although measurements of the total amounts of phosphorus and portions  in organic forms are relatively simple, identification of the mineralogical  and chemical forms is difficult and uncertain. First of all, the element is a  minor constituent of the soil mass. Moreover, phosphorus-bearing minerals  contain only part of the amount present. Portions are in solution and in  adsorbed forms. Attempts have therefore been made to identify the forms  of phosphorus in softs by indirect means such as solubility relationships,  synthesis of phosphorus minerals for comparison, and differential solubili-  ties in various extractants. Conclusive evidence cannot be obtained by in-  direct methods and hence the solubilities and stabilities of phosphorus  minerals are still poorly understood.  Since it was developed, the method of Chang and Jackson (1957) for the    343    fractionation of inorganic phosphorus in soils has found considerable cur-  rency. Criticisms of both methodology and interpretations have led to  modifications of the original procedure (Petersen and Corey, 1966). Without  implications as to the actual minerals present, the procedure has helped to  identify forms of phosphorus in calcareous soils and thus to indicate stages  of development (Walker and Syers, 1976). In parent materials and in soils  that are weakly weathered or virtually unweathered, the dominant phos-  phorus fraction is extractable with acid, indicating some compound or com-  plex of phosphorus with calcium (Ryan and Stroehlein, 1979). Further in-  dications are that as weathering proceeds, the calcium fraction is progres-  sively transformed to non-occluded and finally to occluded forms. From the  distribution of phosphorus among fractions in soil samples from the Punjab  of Pakistan, Ryan and Zghard (1980) inferred that rates of soil development  were considerably slower in that region than in New Zealand, as observed  by Walker and Syers (1976). Some exceptions to the predominance of the  calcium fraction were noted in the Punjab samples. The acid~extractable  fractions were lower and the occluded ones higher than expected. These  departures were ascribed to weathering of sediments prior to deposition at  their present sites.    INDICES OF AVAILABLE PHOSPHORUS    Assessments of the amount of phosphorus a soil can supply to a crop  during the growing season are commonly made by means of chemical extrac-  tions, with a great variety of procedures and reagents in use in the world as  a whole. The common acid extractants are not suitable, however, for soils  of arid regions, most of which are calcareous. Acid extractants dissolve  slowly soluble forms of calcium phosphates which are not usually available  to plants. Procedures that rely on other extractants are therefore needed in  dry regions.  A solution of NaHCO3 has found wide acceptance as an extractant for  soils of dry regions of the world, including the Middle East (Anonymous,  1979). As the method was proposed originally (Olsen et al., 1954), 10 ppm  of phosphorus were considered the critical value but recently a level of  17 ppm has been proposed (Varvel et al., 1981).  As an alternative to extracting solutions, anion exchange resins have been  used to assess availability of phosphorus in softs (Sibbensen, 1978). Recent  studies in Colorado (Bowman and Olsen, 1979) and in Lebanon (Ryan and  Ayubi, 1981) have shown that results with resins are closely related to up-  take of phosphorus by crops during both short and long term growth. The  superiority of the procedure is offset, however, by the time and care it re-  quires. The method thus does not seem suitable for routine testing of soil  samples.  Still another approach has been equilibration of p32 with P in soil samples  (Bowman and Olsen, 1979; Amer et al., 1955). This procedure requires a    344    high degree of laboratory sophistication which mitigates against its adoption  in less developed countries.  Several further approaches have also been tried. The use of EDTA to ex-  tract phosphorus from soil samples has potential usefulness. Onken et al.  (1980) found that EDTA data permitted better predictions of fertilizer  needs than did extractions with solutions of ammonium acetate or sodium  bicarbonate. Water charged with carbon dioxide has been used as an extrac-  tant in western parts of the United States, e.g., Arizona, but that procedure  has not gained wide acceptance because of poor relationships of the results  with plant growth. Another development with important possibilities for  softs of dry regions is the use of NH4HCO3-DTPA for simultaneous extrac-  tion of the macro-elements, P and K, and the micro-elements, Cu, Fe, Mn and  Zn (Soltanpour and Schwab, 1977). All of these elements, except potassium,  tend to be in short supply for crop production in soils of arid regions.    ACIDIFYING AMENDMENTS IN RELATION TO AVAILABLE PHOSPHORUS    Applications of acid or acid-producing materials such as H2SO4, elemental  S, polysulfides and metal sulfates have been used mainly for reclamation of  Na-affected soils. These materials either supply or generate H2SO4 which  subsequently reacts with CaCO3 in the soil to form gypsum (CaSO4 H20).  Although earlier studies in the southwestern United States were focused  mainly on elemental sulfur (Miyamoto et al., 1975a), recent developments  have underlined the potentials of sulfuric acid, a byproduct of SO2 emissions  from smelters and from power plants burning coal. Such emissions can best  be trapped as sulfuric acid, which is thus much more widely available than  before. Moreover, other acidifying amendments are becoming more costly  which is an additional basis for increased interest in sulfuric acid.  Applications of sulfuric acid can increase availability of native phosphorus  in P-deficient softs (Ryan and Stroehlein, 1973). Localized injection of  acid or spot treatments at a rate of 1200 kg/ha were most effective, equaling  300 kg/ha of superphosphate in responses obtained with tomatoes. Mixing  the acid into the soil and application in the irrigation water resulted in  poorer responses. Spot treatment of Fe-deficient soils, also deficient in P,  with sulfuric acid eliminated chlorosis and produced significant increases  in the growth of sorghum (Ryan et al., 1973).  Very large amounts of H2SO4 would be required to neutralize the CaCO3  in softs of arid regions. Thus, costs of reducing pH values to improve avail-  ibility of nutrients would be very high. Neutralizing part of the CaCO3 is a  more practical approach. Ryan and Stroehlein (1979) found that offsetting  about 20% of the CaCOa with H2SO4 resulted in significant and persistent  improvements in plant growth. Moreover, water-soluble P and the capacity  of the soil to release P in available form continuously were increased. En-  hancement of the availibility of P seemed related to substantial shifts among  inorganic forms of the element. Comparatively insoluble calcium phosphates  were converted to mono-calcium and di-calcium phosphates.    345    The use of H2SO4 on irrigated calcareous softs of dry regions may have  further beneficial effects. Additions of the acid to irrigation water reduces  volatilization of ammonia (Miyamoto et al., 1975b) and the precipitation of  calcite (Miyamoto and Ryan, 1976), the latter being a serious problem in  drip irrigation lines. Sulfuric acid can also increase water infiltration and  thus facilitate reclamation of Na-affected soils (Miyamoto et al., 1975c)  and those with toxic levels of boron (Prather, 1977).  Although sulfuric acid can contribute toward solution of a number of  problems in soils of dry regions, recommendations for its use must be quali-  fied. Such use seems appropriate in the southwestern United States with  its large-scale irrigation agriculture and surpluses of sulfuric acid from smel-  ters, but similar conditions do not obtain generally in dry parts of the world.  Handling of sulfuric acid is hazardous and requires well-educated farmers  plus the necessary infrastructure for transportation and distribution.    PHOSPHATE FERTILIZERS AND THEIR USE    Fertilizer sources of phosphorus    Primary attention is given here to fertilizer materials suitable for calcare-  ous soils. All of those would be suitable for soils of dry regions in general.  By and large, the group of acid-treated rock phosphates constitute the most  effective materials, viz., ordinary and triple superphosphates and ammonium  phosphates. Although higher analysis materials have economic advantages,  the less concentrated ordinary superphosphate appeals to less developed  countries because of simpler processes in manufacture, lower production  costs and more uniform distribution with hand spreading. The higher con-  tents of calcium and sulfur in such materials are not advantages for soils of  dry regions.  Ammonium phosphates, especially di-ammonium phosphate, are popular  on a worldwide basis because of their high analyses and good physical prop-  erties. Such fertilizers do have distinct advantages in those soils of dry re-  gions where primary or exclusive needs are for nitrogen and phosphorus,  despite the possibilities of ammonia toxicity from banded applications at  high rates (Creamer and Fox, 1980). Fertilizers that also contain potassium  are more expensive relative to costs of the two elements that are needed  most.  Ground rock phosphates and other materials of similar reaction are  virtually ineffective because of their insolubility in calcareous soils. Thus,  various low-grade calcined phosphate rock materials from Christmas Island  have been tested, especially in Australia, and found to be inferior to other  phosphorus carriers (Smith, 1977). Industrial byproducts such as basic slag  are also of little or no value in calcareous soils.  A comparatively recent and promising development has been the use of  high-analysis polyphosphates in solid and liquid form and in suspensions.    346    The polyphosphates hydrolyze rapidly in soils and subsequently behave like  orthophosphates (Khasawneh et al., 1979) while also providing micronutri-  ents and increasing uptakes of those elements by plants. High production  costs are likely to deter the use of these materials in developing countries.  One possible application of phosphoric acid in addition to providing  phosphorus has been found in reducing crusting of fine-textured soils and  those high in sodium in dry regions. Robbins et al. (1972) found that spray-  ing of phosphoric acid in bands over planted seed enhanced seedling emer-  gence by reducing formation of crusts. Furthermore, Thien (1976) showed  that the phosphoric acid tended to maintain contents of fine particles in  aggregates and thereby increase their water stability.    Initial and residual availability of phosphorus    After being added to soil, fertilizer gradually dissolves and the phosphorus  thus released reacts with soluble constituents, is precipitated as a solid  phase and participates in surface reactions with solid components. The  combination of reactions ultimately leads to a quasi-equilibrium involving  phosphorus in solution and in labile and non-labile forms (Larsen, 1967).  The initial removal of phosphorus from solution has been described in  terms of the Langmuir and Freundlich isotherms and various modifications  (Shayan and Davey, 1978). The Langmuir isotherm has been used more  frequently to characterize adsorption; identify the soil properties involved;  provide parameters related in intensity, quantity and buffering capacity of  soil phosphorus; and fertilizer requirements and plant growth (Olsen and  Watanabe, 1957; Fox and Kamprath, 1970; Holford and Mattingly, 1976).  Even though modifications have been made of the parameters derived from  isotherms (Hatter and Baker, 1977), applications to plant response have  given conflicting results (Holford and Mattingly, 1976). Use of isotherms in  routine soil testing is therefore not feasible. Moreover, laboratory facilities  in less developed countries are commonly inadequate for generating reliable  isotherms. Beyond that, kinds of softs are poorly characterized as a rule,  further limiting possible applications.  Recently available results of long-term studies call for reassessment of  the view that phosphorus removed from the soil solution is irretrievably  lost to possible uptake by plants. In general, the products of phosphorus  reactions continue to decrease in solubility with the passing of time, the rate  depending on the soft type (Munns and Fox, 1976; Hooker et al., 1980).  Such transformations consequently determine effectiveness during a growing  season and also the residual value in subsequent years of phosphorus applied  in fertilizers. Olsen and Watanabe (1957) found that calcareous soils held  phosphorus less tightly than did acid softs and, further, that rates of rever-  sion to insoluble forms were slower. Consequently, the residual value of  added phosphorus promises to be greater in calcareous than in acid soils.  Indeed, studies have shown buildups of residual phosphorus in calcareous    347    soils which can then be taken up by later crops (Sadler and Stewart, 1974).  Williams and Colwell (1977) found that an application of superphosphate at  the rate of 50--70 kg/ha of phosphorus provided enough of the element  for crops over the next five years. Effects of residual phosphorus have also  been found to be more important to yields in some instances than currently  applied phosphate fertilizer (McClelland, 1968). Despite a buildup of residu-  al phosphorus from previous fertilizer applications, however, increases in  current yields were obtained from banded applications of phosphorus  fertilizer where levels of the element extractable by sodium bicarbonate  solution were at or slightly above 15 ppm (Alessi and Power, 1980). Given  the low levels of fertilizer application in many less developed countries, the  effects of residual phosphorus can be significant in calcareous soils generally.    Use considerations    Among the concerns of farmers in dry regions as elsewhere, the foremost  is the extent of the crop response to applications of phosphate fertilizers.  That response depends greatly on the amount of native phosphorus available  in the soft. Crop response to phosphate fertilization can be expected, how-  ever, on most soils of dry regions (Dregne, 1976; Williams and Colwell,  1977). To cite one example, lettuce and barley grown in the greenhouse  responded to phosphorus on 31 samples from as many soils from all parts  of Lebanon (Adams and Sayegh, 1955). In general, the responses to phos-  phate fertilizer are greater in arid and semi-arid regions than in humid regions.  Soil moisture is an especially crucial factor in arid regions because it is  limited. Moisture in the soil affects the dissolution and diffusion of phos-  phorus and its uptake by plants. Consequently, plant responses to phosphate  fertilizers differ between irrigated and rain-fed agriculture on the same kinds  of soils in dry regions. Recommendations for application of phosphorus  must therefore be location-specific. In the low rainfall zones of Syria and  Jordan, for example, crops such as wheat, lentils and vetches responded to  applications ranging from 12 to 21 kg/ha of phosphorus (Matar, 1979).  These responses were obtained in rain-fed agriculture. Corresponding ap-  plications for irrigated crops were 3 or 4 times as great.  Applications of phosphate fertilizers have increased in countries of the  Middle East in recent years but room for much further expansion remains.  Average annual use of phosphorus in kg/ha has ranged from 12.3 in Lebanon  to 1.7 and 1.0 in Syria and Jordan, respectively (F.A.O., 1977). Rates for  semi-arid regions of Australia have been 20 kg/ha of phosphorus for cereals  and 10 kg/ha for pastures, both considered low by world standards (Smith,  1977).  Factors such as inadequate incorporation of fertilizers in softs and defi-  ciencies of nutrients other than phosphorus can limit crop responses (Elba-  gouri, 1979). Shallow cultivation, usually with animal-drawn plows of light  weight, is common farm practice in dry regions generally and in underde-    348    veloped countries in particular. Given the limited mobility of phosphorus  in soils, shallow cultivation leaves it near the surface out of reach of deep-  rooted field crops and fruit trees.  Recent research suggests that organic matter has more significance to  phosphorus uptake by plants than generally recognized, even though amounts  in the softs of arid regions are extremely low. Singh and Jones (1976) showed  that organic residues reduced phosphorus sorption in softs and at the same  time increased desorption, thus improving the efficiency of utilization of  the element. In another study of irrigated desert softs, Abbott (1978) found  that mineralization of organic phosphorus was significant for crop growth  and suggested that such mineralization should be taken into account in test-  ing samples for available phosphorus. These studies are especially relevant to  developing countries of dry regions where animal manures assume greater  importance than commercial fertilizers.  Comparatively minor concerns about the use of phosphate on soils of dry  regions are the possible accumulations of toxic metals carried by the fer-  tilizers, phosphorus "toxicity" to plants and the loss of phosphorus through  leaching. Smith (1977) cited reports of superphosphate containing as much  as 2% of fluorine and from 18 to 91 ppm of cadmium, depending on the  source of the original rock. Whether those levels do have significance has not  been determined. Reports of "toxicity" of phosphorus to plants are few  and are based mainly on greenhouse studies (Williams and Colwell, 1977)  with light-textured or sandy softs. That "toxicity" would occur under field  conditions is highly doubtful. Williams and Colwell (1977) reported sub-  stantial movement of phosphorus in light-textured or sandy soils, even under  conditions of low rainfall. Such movement does not promise to be of prac-  tical importance, however, because the transported phosphorus can eventual-  ly be recovered by deep-rooted crops.    Phosphate application in irrigation water    Irrespective of the system used for irrigation, applications of fertilizers in  the water have certain advantages, if the method is feasible. Energy and labor  can be saved and the timing of applications is flexible. Unfortunately, ap-  plications of phosphorus in irrigation water are not generally satisfactory  with surface and sprinkler systems, largely because of the reactions of phos-  phorus with soft particles and the consequent immobility of the element  (Campbell et al., 1980). Moreover, distribution from open systems is uneven  within fields, the phosphorus being concentrated near the point of applica-  tion and on the soft surface where it is largely ineffective. Similar problems  arise with sprinkler irrigation and applications of phosphorus in the water  are then similarly ineffective. More promising is the possibility of using or-  thophosphoric acid in water applied by trickle irrigation; O'Neill et al. (1979)  having found that clogged emitters were avoided and that the distribution of  phosphorus in the soft was satisfactory.    349    Applications of phosphates in drip irrigation systems also seem possible,  although that method has its problems as well. The emitters can be clogged  by insoluble residues, precipitates may form in the lines, and the phos-  phorus will have low mobility once it reaches the soil. To ameliorate these  problems, the phosphate fertilizers should be dissolved and the resulting  solution filtered before it is added to irrigation water. Even in filtered solu-  tions, however, materials such as ammonium orthophosphate and ammoni-  um polyphosphate may react with calcium in irrigation water to form  precipitates that plug emitters. This problem becomes acute with irrigation  water high in calcium.  Recent research has suggested a possible solution for the problem of low  mobility of phosphorus in orthophosphates. Rauschkolb et al. (1976) found  that glycerophosphate moved deeper in the soil near the emitter nozzle  than did orthophosphate. Glycerophosphate is water-soluble, does not  hydrolyze in irrigation water, does not react with soil and has a relatively  high content of phosphorus. Despite these advantages, the wide use of  glycerophosphate in dry regions does not seem warranted under present  circumstances. The material is considerably more expensive than orthophos-  phate and hence is likely to be economically superior only at comparatively  low rates of application.  Flood irrigation may affect the behavior of native or added phosphorus  in soils. Brandon and Mikkelsen (1979) showed that submergence of soils  for the growing of lowland rice followed by removal of the water induced  phosphorus deficiency in succeeding crops of wheat and barley. Such defi-  ciencies could be due to formation of insoluble compounds of phosphorus  with iron which had been released by reducing conditions due to the flood-  ing.    FOLIAR APPLICATION    Phosphorus has not been widely applied in sprays because of two con-  siderations. First, the greatest needs of plants occur during early stages of  growth when leaf areas are small. Second, if enough phosphorus is applied  to benefit crop growth the sprays damage plants. Even though orthophos-  phoric acid is one of the better forms for foliar application, concentrations  must be no greater than 0.5%. Barel and Black (1979) screened a wide range  of inorganic and organic phosphorus compounds to appraise their suitabili-  ties for foliar applications. Several condensed phosphates, which hydrolyzed  to form orthophosphates, could be applied at concentrations 2.5 to 3 times  as great as that of orthophosphate. Examples of these forms are ammonium  tripolyphosphate, ammonium tetrapolyphosphate, and phosphoryl triamide.  Organic forms were not satisfactory in sprays. Foliar applications of phos-  phorus thus seem unlikely to have significance in the agriculture of dry  regions.    350    An alternative to phosphorus fertilization    Because of relatively high costs, phosphate fertilizers have been used  sparingly in developing countries. Consumption promises to remain at very  low levels despite need for such fertilizers in efforts to increase crop produc-  tion. Attempts have therefore been made to find alternatives to phosphate  fertilizers. One type of effort has been to develop cultivars that will grow  well despite low levels of native phosphorus. Although the genetic potential  exists for adaptation of plant species to low levels of phosphorus in soils,  Mortvedt (1976) concluded that limited supplies of the element could not  be completely offset by modifications of plant species and that some fertili-  zation would be necessary for economic crop production. For one thing,  cultivars adapted to low and very low levels of native phosphorus in softs  are likely to have inferior nutritional qualities. Plant breeding for more  efficient use of phosphorus would still seem to have promise, especially if  the cultivars could also perform well despite limited supplies of micronutri-  ents, limited supplies of water, and some salinity.    Phosphorus losses by erosion    Movement of nutrients, either laterally or vertically in soils, has impor-  tant implications to fertility. Phosphorus, either added or native, can move  with clay fractions when those are removed from surface layers of soils by  erosion. Water erosion is especially severe in semi-arid regions in the tropics  because the rainfall, although low, often comes in downpours with con-  sequent high erosivity. Differential losses of phosphorus from surface layers  of softs by water erosion can be especially harmful in dry regions because  limited applications of fertilizer are normal practice. Erosion by wind may  also winnow the surface layers of softs to carry away clay and phosphorus.  Practices to control erosion and to conserve water are well known in de-  veloped countries, especially in humid parts of the world. Such practices  have been applied very little in the developing countries of dry regions.  Hudson {1980) concluded that barriers to the applications of erosion control  measures were primarily economic, political and social.  In contrast to losses of phosphorus through erosion are the possibilities  of using phosphate fertilizers to help control it. Additions of phosphate  fertilizers can enhance the density of plant cover and promote greater ag-  gregation of surface layers, thereby reducing erosion.    Other management considerations    Various techniques have been tried in management of soils of arid and  semi-arid regions; some have been beneficial and others harmful. For ex-  ample, deep plowing has been tried in parts of the Middle East, North Africa  and Australia. Sims (1977) concluded from his review of results that deep    351    plowing had not been beneficial but may even have been harmful. By in-  verting the soil, the plowing had buried the surface layers highest in avail-  able phosphorus and replaced it with phosphorus-deficient materials. An-  other practice questioned by Sims (1977) is fallowing, which is common  in Australia. He believes that fallowing facilitates losses through erosion of  fine particles which carry the bulk of the phosphorus. Thus, depletion of  native phosphorus could offset the gains in moisture and nitrogen. On the  other hand, incorporation of plant residues into soils seems to promote  more effective cycling of phosphorus because organic matter serves as a  "sink" for the element (Clarke and Russell, 1977). Careful irrigation to  avoid or reduce secondary salinity can also be beneficial in that it helps to  increase utilization of phosphorus by crops.    POSSIBLE IMPROVEMENTS    Utilization of phosphate fertilizers in arid and semi-arid regions could be  improved by a number of steps.  (1) More soil testing combined with judicious use of field trials to improve  bases for making fertilizer recommendations.  (2) Elimination or reduction of the constraints to crop production in  salinity and micronutrient shortages.  (3) Applications of fertilizer in bands and at greater depths in the soil  rather than broadcast. Light machinery would have to be adapted for this  purpose in developing countries.  (4) Improved information on phosphorus requirements of crops of econo-  mic importance in dry regions to permit development of more appropriate  fertilizer recommendations.  (5) Development of crop varieties more tolerant of deficiencies in phos-  phorus and of other mineral stresses in soils.  (6) Adoption of management practices that reduce erosion and conserve  moisture.  (7) Use of soil survey information to extend research findings more ef-  fectively.  (8) Reorganization and expansion of agricultural extension services so  that more and better information can be provided to farmers.    REFERENCES    Abbott, J., 1978. Importance of the organic phosphorus fraction in extracts of calcare-  ous soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 81--85.  Adams, F. and Sayegh, A.H., 1955. Plant response to nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium  in soils of Lebanon as indicated by greenhouse pot experiments. Fac. Agric. Bull.,  I. Amer. Univ., Beirut, 10 pp.  Alessi, J. and Power, J.F., 1980. Effects of banded and residual fertilizer phosphorus on  dryland spring wheat yield in the Northern Plains. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 792--796.    352    Amer, F., Bouldin, D.R., Black, C.A. and Duke, F.R., 1955. Characterization of soil  phosphorus by anion exchange resin adsorption and 32p equilibration. Plant Soil, 6 :  391--408.  Anonymous, 1979. Handbook on Phosphate Fertilization. World Phosphate Industry As-  sociation, Paris, 108 pp.  Barel, D., and Black, C.A., 1979. Fotiar application of P, I. Screening of various inorganic  and organic P compounds. Agron. J., 71: 15--21.  Bowman, R.A. and Olsen, S.R., 1979. A reevaluation of phosphorus-32 and resin meth-  ods in calcareous soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43:121--124.  Brandon, D.M. and Mikkelsen, D.S., 1979. Phosphorus transformations in alternatively  flooded California soils, I. Cause of plant phosphorus deficiency in rice rotation crops  and correctional methods. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 989---994.  Campbell, K.B., Helgested, E., Shaw, E.J. and Hawkes, G.R., 1980. Western Fertilizer  Handbook, 6th ed. Interstate Printers and Publishers, Danville, Ill., 269 pp.  Chang, S.C. and Jackson, M.L., 1957. Fractionation of soil phosphorus.Soil Sci., 84:  133--144.  Clarke, A.L. and Russell, J.S., 1977. Crop sequential practices. In: J.S. Russell and E.L.  Greacen (Editors), Soil Factors in Crop Production in a Semi-arid Environment.  Univ. Queensland Press, St. Lucia, pp. 279--300.  Creamer, F.L. and Fox, R.H., 1980. The toxicity of banded urea or diammonium phos-  phate to corn as influenced by soil temperature, moisture, and pH. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  J., 44: 296--300.  Dalal, R.C., 1977. Soil organic phosphorus. Adv. Agron., 29: 83--117.  Dregne, H.E., 1976. Soils of Arid Regions. Elsevier Scientific Publishing Co., Amsterdam,  237 pp.  Elbagouri, I.H., 1979. Efficiency of fertilizers under dry farming conditions. Paper  presented at FAO regional seminar on rain-fed agriculture in the Near East, Amman,  1979.  Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (F.A.O.), 1977. Fertilizer  Review. Rome.  Fox, R.L. and Kamprath, E.J., 1970. Phosphate sorption isotherms for evaluating the  phosphate requirement of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34 : 902--906.  Hatter, R.D. and Baker, D.E., 1977. Applications and mis-applications of the Langmuir  equation to soil adsorption phenomena. Soil Sci. Soc. Amer. J., 41 : 1077--1080.  Hasan, H., 1980. Availability and Transformation of Applied Phosphorus in Calcareous  Lebanese Soils. M.S. Thesis, Am. Univ. Beirut, Beirut, 66 pp.  Holford, I.C.R. and Mattingly, G.E.G., 1976. Phosphate adsorption and plant availability  of phosphate. Plant Soil, 44: 377--389.  Hooker, M.L., Peterson, G.A., Sander, D.H. and Daigger, L.A., 1980. Phosphate fractions  in calcareous soils as altered by time and amounts of added phosphate. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. J., 44: 269--276.  Hudson, N.W., 1980. Social, political and economic aspects of soil conservation. In:  R.P.C. Morgan (Editor), Soil Conservation: Problems and Prospects. Wiley and Sons  Ltd., London, pp. 45--54.  Khasawneh, F.E., Hashimoto, I. and Sample, E.C., 1979. Reactions of ammonium ortho-  and polyphosphate fertilizers in soil, II. Hydrolysis and reactions with soil. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. J., 43: 52--58.  Khasawneh, F.E., Sample, E.C. and Kamprath, E.J. (Editors), 1980. The Role of Phos-  phorus in Agriculture. Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wisc., 928 pp.  Larsen, S., 1967. Soil phosphorus. Adv. Agron., 19: 151--210.  Matar, A., 1979. Fertilization studies under the rainfed agriculture of Syria. Paper  presented at the FAO regional seminar on rainfed agriculture in the Near East,  Amman, 1979.  McClelland, V.F., 1968. Superphosphate on wheat: the cumulative effect of repeated  applications on yield response. Aust. J. Agric. Res., 19 : 1--8.    353    Miyamoto, S. and Ryan, J., 1976. Sulfuric acid for the treatment of ammoniated irriga-  tion water, II. Reducing calcite precipitation and sodium hazard. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  J., 40: 305--309.  Miyamoto, S., Ryan, J. and Stroehlein, J.L., 1975a. Potentially beneficial uses of sulfuric  acid in southwestern agriculture. J. Environ. Qual., 4: 431--437.  Miyamoto, S., Ryan, J. and Stroehlein, J.L., 1975b. Sulfuric acid for the treatment of  ammoniated irrigation water, I. Reducing ammonia volatization. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 39: 544--548.  Miyamoto, S., Prather, R.T. and Stroehlein, J.L., 1975c. Sulfuric acid and leaching  requirement for reclaiming sodium-affected soils. Plant Soil, 43: 573--585.  Mortvedt, J.J., 1976. Alkaline soils. In: M.J. Wright (Editor), Plant Adaptation to Mineral  Stress in Problem Soils. Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y., pp. 141-158.  Munns, D.N. and Fox, R.L., 1976. The slow reaction which continues after phosphate  adsorption: Kinetics and equilibrium in some tropical soils. Soil Sei. Soe. Am. J.,  40 : 46---51.  Olsen, S.R. and Watanabe, F.S., 1957. A method to determine a phosphate adsorption  maximum on soils as measured by the Langmuir isotherm. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.,  21: 144--149.  Olsen, S.R., Cole, C.V., Watanabe, F.S. and Dean, L.A., 1954. Estimation of available  phosphorus in soils by extraction with sodium bicarbonate. U.S. Dept. Agric. Circ.,  939.  O'Neill, M.K., Gardner, B.K. and Roth, R.L., 1979. Orthophosphoric acid as a phos-  phorus fertilizer in trickle irrigation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43 : 283--286.  Onken, A.B., Matkeson, R. and Williams, E.J., 1980. Evaluation of EDTA-extractable  phosphorus as a soil test procedure. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 783--786.  Petersen, G.W. and Corey, R.B., 1966. A modified Chang and Jackson procedure for  routine fractionation of inorganic soil phosphates. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 30:  563--565.  Pierre, W.H. and Norman, A.G. (Editors), 1953. Soil and Fertilizer Phosphorus in Crop  Nutrition. Academic Press, Inc., New York, N.Y.  Prather, R.J., 1977. Sulfuric acid as an amendment for soils high in boron. Soil Sei. Soc.  Am. J., 41 : 1098--1101.  Rauschkolb, R.S., Rolston, D.E., Miller, R.J., Carlton, A.B. and Burau, R.G., 1976.  Phosphorus fertilization with drip irrigation. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 68--72.  Robbins, C.W., Carter, D.L. and Leggett, G.E., 1972. Controlling soil crusting with phos-  phoric acid to enhance seedling emergence. Agron. J., 64: 180--183.  Ryan, J. and Ayubi, A.G., 1981. Phosphorus availability indices in calcareous Lebanese  soils. Plant Soil, 62: 141--145.  Ryan, J. and Stroehlein, J.L., 1973. Use of sulfuric acid on phosphorus-deficient Arizona  soils. Prog. Agric. Ariz., 25(8): 11--13.  Ryan, J. and Stroehlein, J.L., 1979. Sulfuric acid treatment of calcareous soils: Effects on  phosphorus solubility, inorganic phosphorus forms, and plant growth. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. J., 43: 731--735.  Ryan, J., Miyamoto, S. and Bohn, H.L., 1973. Prevent chlorosis in plants with use of  sulfuric acid. Prog. Agric. Ariz., 25(2): 3--5.  Ryan, J. and Zghard, M. Alem, 1980. Phosphorus transformations with age in a calcare-  ous soil chronosequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44: 168--169.  Sadler, J.M. and Stewart, J.W.B., 1974. Residual phosphorus in western Canadian soils:  A review. Saskatchewan Inst. Pedol. Publ., No. R136, 37 pp.  Shayan, A. and Davey, B.G., 1978. A universal dimensionless phosphate adsorption iso-  therm for soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 878--882.  Sibbensen, E., 1978. An investigation of the anion exchange resin method for soil phos-  phate extraction. Plant Soil, 50: 305--321.    354    Sims, H.J., 1977. Cultivation and fallowing practices. In: J.S. Russell and E.L. Greacan  (Editors), Soil Factors in Crop Production in a Semi-arid Environment. Univ. Queens-  land Press, St. Lucia, Australia, pp. 243-261.  Singh, B.C. and Jones, J.P., 1976. Phosphorus sorption and desorption characteristics of  soil as affected by organic residues. Soil Sci. SOc. Am. J., 40: 389--394.  Smith, A.N., 1977. Fertilization. In: J.S. Russell and E.L. Greacen (Editors), Soil Factors  in Crop Production in a Semi-arid Environment. Univ. Queensland Press, St. Lucia,  Australia, pp. 262--278.  Soltanpour, P.N. and Schwab, A.P., 1977. A new soil test for simultaneous extraction of  macro- and micronutrients in alkaline soils. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal., 8 : 195--  207.  Thien, S., 1976. Stabilizing soil aggregates with phosphoric acid. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.,  40: 105--108.  Varvel, G.E., Anderson, F.N. and Peterson, G.A., 1981. Soil test correlation problems  with two phosphorus methods in similar soils. Agron. J., 73 : 516--520.  Walker, T.W. and Syers, J.K., 1976. The fate of phosphorus during pedogenesis.  Geoderma, 15: 1--19.  Williams, C.H. and Colwell, J.D., 1977. Inorganic chemical properties. In: J.S. Russell  and E.L. Greacen (Editors), Soil Factors in Crop Production in a Semi-arid Environ-  ment. Univ. Queensland Press, St. Lucia, Australia, pp. 105--126.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractThis review deals with selected aspects of the forms, behavior and utilization of phosphorus in soils of dry regions. Such regions embrace most developing nations in the world. Amounts and major forms of phosphorus in the soils, indices of availability, fertilizer sources, initial and residual effects, modes of application and possibilities for improved utilization are considered. The supply and availability of phosphorus is a key factor in crop production. Consequently, for appreciable increases in production in dry regions, improvements in utilization of phosphorus are needed. Several possible improvements are therefore proposed as the final part of this paper. 