 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 327--334                                                      327  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE RELATIONSHIPS OF THE CLAY MINERAL SUITES TO THE  PARENT ROCKS OF EIGHT SOIL PROFILES IN SARAWAK, MALAYSIA*    K.S. LOI, R. PROTZ and G.J. ROSS  Soil Survey Division, Department of Agriculture, Kuching, Sarawak (Malaysia)  Land Resource Science, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario N1G 2W1 (Canada)  Chemistry and Biology Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, Ontario KIA 0C6  (Canada)  (Received June 19, 1981; accepted October 22, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Loi, K.S., Protz, R. and Ross, G.J., 1982. The relationships of the clay mineral suites to  the parent rocks of eight soil profiles in Sarawak, Malaysia. Geoderma, 27 : 327--334.    The clay mineralogy of eight selected soil profiles developed on acid igneous, pyro-  clastic and sedimentary rocks was investigated. The effects on the clay mineralogy of the  parent-rock mineralogy and physical conditions within each soil profile were evaluated.  The results indicate that the mineralogies of the parent rocks control the type of clay  minerals formed in Sarawak. In the soils derived from pyroclastic and coarse-grained acid  igneous rocks without muscovite, the clay-mineral suites consist almost exclusively of  kaolinite and gibbsite with small amounts of goethite. In contrast, in the soils developed  from fine-grained acid igneous and sedimentary rocks with muscovite, the clays contain  relatively large amounts of interstratified mica-vermiculite and chlorite-vermiculite in  addition to gibbsite and/or kaolinite. The presence of gibbsite in these soils depends on  the presence of plagioclase feldspar in the parent rock.    INTRODUCTION    The importance of the parent rocks in determining the mineralogical com-  position of the resultant soils was recognized by early workers (Stephen,  1952; Smith, 1962; Grant, 1964; Kato, 1965). In the tropical regions, the  relation of the parent rocks to soil clay-mineralogy has not been intensively  investigated. The few studies include those of Ojanuga (1973, 1979),  Eswaran and Yeow (1976), Eswaran and Wong (1978) and Eswaran (1979).  Such research has been concentrated either on the transformation of individual  primary minerals or on the parent rocks, with no reference to the specific  mineralogy of the parent rocks which gave rise to the resultant clay minerals  in the soils. Even in the temperate region, where most of such studies have  been carried out, literature on the direct effect of parent-rock mineralogy  on clay-mineral formation in soils is meagre.    *C.B.R.I. Contribution No. 1243.    0016-7061/82/0000-0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    328    The present study is an attempt to identify the relationship of the clay-  mineral suites in softs with respect to the mineralogy of the parent rock  under the tropical conditions in Sarawak. Such a relationship would en-  able one to predict, under given climatic conditions, and time periods, the  clay-mineral suite in soils if the mineralogy of the parent rock is known  and vice versa.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Eight soil profiles from four rock types were included in this study: (1)  the Mujan, Nibong and Ujek derived from pyroclastic rocks; {2) the Gading  and Changgan derived from coarse-grained acid igneous rocks; (3) the Abok  from a fine-grained acid igneous rock; (4) the Keladan and Arip from sedi-  mentary rocks (Fig. 1). The complete data set of descriptions, chemical,  physical and micromorphological properties are reported in Loi (1980). To  eliminate the effect of topography, all soil profiles were sampled at most  stable landscape positions. Climatic environment of the study area is perudic  isohyperthermic (Soil Survey Staff, 1975}.  The Na-saturated clays (&lt; 2 ~m) of each profile were separated by repeated  centrifugation. They were Mg-saturated by 1 N MgC12, washed free of excess  salt, and freeze-dried. Oriented clay samples were prepared for X-ray diffrac-  tion studies by sedimenting 40 mg of clay on 25 by 37 mm glass slides. One    G- GADING                                   ./~   '~.-~'          (  C CHANGGAN  b - UJEK                                k N ~  A- ABOK                        \5'-'  K - KELADAN                                                                                              ~)  R - ARIP                                                                                            J~'~""  AM    ~"  ]./    '-x.       . A    \    f  ....  x"'x ~  AA.~_        -... f - ----@           ,f     "---" "1~. ~"Y                               0    Fig. 1. Location of soil profile sites.    !    100Miles  J    329    g of clay from each sample was treated with dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate  (Mehra and Jackson, 1960) to get rid of "free" iron. Another set of slides  was made from the deferrated clays. A Philips X-ray diffractometer with Fe-  filtered and Co radiation was used. Diffractograms of clay samples were ob-  tained for air-dry, glycerol-solvated, 550C treatments. Identification and  quantification of the clay minerals in different horizons of each profile were  carried out by methods of Kodama et al. (1977).  Thin sections were made using the methods described in McKeague (1978).  The thin sections were studied using a polarizing microscope.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The classification of the soil profiles studied and the mineralogy of their  parent rocks are shown in Table I. The clay mineralogy of the major horizons  of the soil profiles is summarized in Table II.    Soil profiles derived from pyroclastic rocks    The Mujan, Nibong and Ujek soil profiles were derived from similar parent  materials and have similar clay mineralogy (Table II). The presence of trace    TABLE I    Classification of soil and mineralogy of the parent rocks    Soil           Classification  profile        (Soil Survey Staff, 1975)  Pyroclastic rocks:  Mujan        Typic  Haplorthox  Nibong        Ultic Haplorthox  Ujek          Tropeptic Haplorthox  Coarse-grained acid igneous rocks  Gading        Quartzipsammentic  Haplorthox  Changgan     Typic  Haplorthox  Fine-grained acid igneous rocks:  Abok          Orthoxic  Tropudult  Sedimentary rocks:  Keladan       Oxic  Dystropept  Arip           Oxic  Dystropept    Parent         Dominant minerals  rock    dacite tuff    plagioclase, hypersthene,  quartz, felsic matrix  tuff           plagioclase, hypersthene,  felsicmatrix    ademillite  granodiorite    orthoclase, plagioclase, quartz,  biotite  andesine, microperthite,  quartz, biotite    micrograno-   plagioclase, alkali feldspar,  diorite        quartz, muscovite    conglomerate  siltstone    quartz, magnetite, musco-  vite, rock fragment  quartz, muscovite, rock  fragment    TABLE II    Clay minerals and their relative abundance determined by XRD  Horizon  Depth        Ka0.  Gibb. Chl.   Verm. Mica  Mica-  (cm)                                          verm.  Soil profiles derived from pyroclastic rocks    Mujan profile  A           0--10     +++   +  B1        10--30     +++   +  B2        30--75     +++   +  B3        75--130    +++   +  B/C 1    13{)--150    ++    +  B/C 2    150--170    ++    +  Nibong profile  A1          0--9       +++   +  B1          9--30     +++   +  B22       70---100    +++   +  B24      140---170    +++   +  Ujek profile  A1          0--2       +++   +  B1          2--33      +++   +  B2        33--80     +++   +  B3        80--100    +++   +  C1       100--120    ++    t  C2       120--150    ++    t  R        150--170    ++    t    t    Soil profiles derived from coarse-grained acid igneous rocks    Gading profile  A           0--8      +++   +  B1          8--22     +++   +  B3         56--90      +++   +  C       +-200         +++   +  Changgan profile  A           0--13      ++    ++    t  B2         45--86      ++    ++    t  B/C      13@--170    ++    ++  C        190--250    ++    ++  Soil profiles derived from fine-grained igneous rocks  Abok profile  A           0--5       +      ++    t                    +(reg.)l  B21         5--15      +      ++    t                    +(reg.)  B23       38--58     +     ++    t            t      +(reg.)  B/C       97--140    +     ++    t            t      +(ran.)  C2      -+292          +      ++    t             t      +(ran.)  Soil profiles derived from sedimen tary rocks  Keladan profile  A           0--8      +++         t      t            +(ran.)  II B21     28--58     ++           t                   +(ran.)  III B23    89--114    +            ++           t      +(ran.)  III B25   142--163    +             ++           t      +(ran.)  V B/C   -+305          ++           +             t      +(ran.)  Arip profile  A           0--10      ++                                 +(ran.)  B2         35--75      ++                                 +(ran.)  B3        75--110    ++                        t      +(ran.)  B/C      170--210    ++                 t      +     +(ran.)  C2      +-340          ++                          +      +(ran.)    Chl-      Goet. Qtz.   Feld.  X-  verm.                                         amor    t     t     t  t  t  t  +                   +    t  t  t  t  t                    +  t                    +  t                    ++    t       t  t       t  t       t  t       t    t  t       t  t       t  t    +(ran.)2  t      t  +(ran.)   t     t  +(ran.)   t      t  +(ran.)   t      t  +(ran.)   t      t      t    t         t      +  ++(ran.)  t      t  ++(ran.)  t      t  ++(ran.)  t      t  t       t    t    ++(ran.)  t3     t  ++(ran.)  t      t  ++(ran.)  t      t  t    t  t      +    Notes: i Regularly interstratified; 2 randomly interstratified; 31ess than 2% in Arip profile.  Symbols: t = trace (~ 10%); + = minor (10--25%)" ++ = moderate (25--50%); +++ = major (50---75%).    331    amounts of minerals other than kaolinite, gibbsite and goethite in the clay  fraction of the A horizon of the Mujan soil profile is due to a slight differ-  ence in the lithology as observed in thin sections. The high amount of kaolin-  ite in these three soil profiles is possibly due to the presence of microlites  of alkali feldspar (felsic matrix). The microlites are abundant in the matrix  which forms the major part of the parent rocks. The clay mineralogies of  these three soil profiles are similar to that of the Gading and Changgan soil  profiles (Table II).  In the Ujek soil profile there is a decrease in the crystallinity of the clay  minerals with depth from the C1 to R layer. No gibbsite is present in the  R layer. Although hypersthene was identified in thin sections of the soil  profiles, 2:1 clay minerals were not detected in the clays. It is most prob-  able that hypersthene in this soil does not weather to silicate clays. Mg and  Si have largely been leached out of the soil profile and goethite remained  as the residual product. Eswaran (1979), studying the weathering of the  related mineral, augite, in soils from Sabah, found the residual mineral to  be geothite.    Soil profiles derived from coarse-grained acid igneous rocks    The clay mineralogies of the Gading and Changgan soil profiles are com-  posed mainly of kaolinite and gibbsite and are therefore similar to those of  the soils derived from pyroclastic rocks (Table II). Kaolinite and gibbsite are  derived from the feldspars. There is a relatively higher amount of gibbsite  in the Changgan soil profile. This could be due to a higher amount of plagio-  clase (andesine) present in the parent rock. With a similar leaching rate in  both soil profiles, as determined by the physical environment and texture  of the weathering material, gibbsite may be preferentially formed from  the plagioclase which has a higher Si/A1 ratio and is more easily weathered  than the alkali feldspars. The faster removal of Si as a result of a greater sus-  ceptibility to breakdown in the plagioclase creates a microenvironment  around the crystals favouring the formation of gibbsite. Gibbsite as an early  weathering product is indicated by its presence in the X-ray diffraction  analysis of the crushed rock.    Soil profiles derived from fine-grained acid igneous rocks    The Abok profile, derived from a microgranodiorite which has more plagio-  clase than alkali feldspars (Table I), has a relatively higher amount of gibb-  site. The randomly interstratified chlorite-vermiculite is an alteration product  of muscovite. The alteration of muscovite to chlorite was also observed in  thin sections of the parent rocks.  In the Abok soil profile, in addition to kaolinite and gibbsite, chlorite-  vermiculite and mica-vermiculite occur in significant amounts (Table II).  The mica-vermiculite is derived from the muscovite in the parent rock. This    332    conclusion is supported by the presence of mica-vermiculite in the three  soil profiles having muscovite in their parent rocks and the absence of mica-  vermiculite in the remaining five soil profiles not having muscovite in their  parent rocks. The higher stability of muscovite as compared to biotite is a  contributing factor to the formation of mica-vermiculite in the intensive  weathering environment. In the Abok soil profile the presence of calcite in  the parent rock and the slow percolation rate due to its inherent fine tex-  ture probably contribute to a lower state of weathering.  The presence of a stoneline at 50--63 cm in the Abok profile also affects  the clay mineralogy (Loi, 1980). Regularly interstratified mica-vermiculite  above the stoneline was indicated by the presence of 24-A and 12-A peaks  in Mg-saturated, glycerol-solvated clays. Below the stoneline only a broad  peak in the 10- to 14-A region was present, indicating randomly interstrati-  fied mica-vermiculite. The presence of the more K-depleted mica-vermiculite  only above the stoneline suggests that more intensive weathering has oc-  curred in this part of the profile. The fibrous fan-shaped nature of the musco-  vite observed in thin sections may also have contributed to its greater K de-  pletion (Loi, 1980). No regularly interstratified mica-vermiculite was found  in the other soil profiles. The higher intensity of weathering above the stone-  line is confirmed by the absence of clay-sized muscovite in the surface hori-  zons. Apparently, the stoneline serves as a physical barrier in the downward  percolation of water and hence retards weathering below it. The chlorite is  inherited from the parent rock as indicated by the X-ray diffraction analysis  of the crushed rock.  Although derivation of chlorite-vermiculite from chlorite is possible, as in  the case of the Gading and Changgan profiles, the presence of only a trace  amount of chlorite in the parent rock but a significant amount of chlorite-  vermiculite in the soil suggest some other mineral sources. The present data  suggest muscovite through the intermediary vermiculite. In the B and C hori-  zons the weathering of feldspar can supply A1 for the formation of pedo-  genic chlorite-vermiculite from vermiculite. A trace amount of clay-sized  feldspar is found in the C2 horizon. Chloritization of vermiculite could oc-  cur in the surface horizons as dioctahedral vermiculite would be derived  from muscovite. The conversion of expansible dioctahedml minerals to  vermiculite-chlorite in acid soils containing high A1 contents has been shown  to occur by Jackson (1963).    Soil profiles derived from sedimentary rocks    The clay mineralogy of the Keladan soil profile is similar to that of the  Abok soil profile (Table II). Gibbsite is absent, however, and chlorite and  chlorite-vermiculite are the main clay minerals. Lithological stratification  makes the interpretation of the genesis of the clay minerals in this profile  less certain. Some of the chlorite and chlorite-vermiculite may have been  derived from chlorite. The chlorite and chlorite-vermiculite appear to have  been weathered to kaolinite in the surface horizon. The mica-vermiculite seems  to be fairly stable.    333    The absence of gibbsite in this soil profile is noteworthy. Velde (1977)  indicates that gibbsite is lost upon transport due to its low tolerance for  silica in solution. Hence it is unlikely to be inherited from sedimentary  rocks. The absence of gibbsite is therefore attributed to the absence of feld-  spar in the parent rock. The absence of feldspar was verified by the thin-  section study of the parent rock (Table I).  The clay mineralogy of the Arip soil profile developed on siltstone is  similar to that of the Keladan soil profile except that chlorite is absent  (Table II). The absence of chlorite and the presence of a trace amount of  vermiculite in the B/C horizon indicate that the muscovite is converted to  chlorite-vermiculite through intermediary vermiculite. This supports the con-  tention that the origin of chlorite-vermiculite in the Abok profile is most  likely by the same mechanism.  An intermittent water table is present at 1.7 m in the Arip profile (Loi,  1980). The clay-mineralogical data of this soil profile suggest that the inter-  mittent water table did not affect alteration of muscovite to mica-vermiculite  but inhibited the formation of chlorite-vermiculite. This also applies to the  alteration of muscovite to vermiculite.    CONCLUSION    In the soils derived from the pyroclastic and coarse-grained acid igneous  rocks without muscovite, in Sarawak, the clay-mineral suite consists mainly  of kaolinite and gibbsite. In contrast, soils derived from fine-grained acid  igneous and sedimentary rocks with muscovite have clays consisting largely  of interstratified mica-vermiculite and chlorite-vermiculite in addition to  gibbsite and/or kaolinite. Thus the presence of mica-vermiculite and  chlorite-vermiculite in the soils depends on the presence of muscovite in  the parent rocks. These interstratified minerals are formed by the interlayer  hydration of muscovite and the subsequent chloritization of the vermiculitic  components. Where present, chlorite may also have weathered to form some  chlorite-vermiculite.  Furthermore, in the soils where kaolinite has not yet been desilicated to  gibbsite, the presence of gibbsite depends on the presence of feldspar (plagio-  clase) in the parent rock.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    To the Canadian International Development Agency for financial support  and the Department of Agriculture, Sarawak, for the in-service study leave.  To Messrs. G.W. Scott and R. Hill for assistance in the X-ray diffraction and  other analyses.    334    REFERENCES    Eswaran, H. and Yeow, Y.H., 1976. The weathering of biotite in a profile on gneiss in  Malaysia. Geoderma, 16: 9--20.  Eswaran, H. and Wong, C.B., 1978. A study of a deep weathering profile on granite in  peninsular Malaysia, III. Alteration of feldspars. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 154--158.  Eswaran, H., 1979. The alteration of plagioclases and augites under differing pedo-  environmental conditions. J. Soil Sci., 30: 547--555.  Grant, W.H., 1964. Chemical weathering of biotite-plagioclase gneiss. Clay Clay Miner.,  12: 455--463.  Jackson, M.L., 1963. Aluminium bonding in soils: a unifying principle in soil science.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 27: 1--10.  Kato, Y., 1965. Mineralogical study of weathering products of granodiorite at Shinshiro  City, III. Weathering of primary minerals. 2. Mineralogical characteristics of weathered  mineral grains. Soil Sci. Plant Nutrit., 11: 30--40.  Kodama, H., Scott, G.C. and Miles, N.M., 1977. X-ray quantitative analysis of minerals  in soils. Spec. Publ. Land Resour. Inst., Agric. Can., Ottawa, Ont.  Loi, K.S., 1980. Genesis and classification of selected soils intermediate between the Red-  Yellow Podzolic and Lateritic Groups in Sarawak, Malaysia. M.Sc. Thesis, Land Re-  source Science, Univ. of Guelph, Guelph, Ont.  McKeague, J.A. (Editor), 1978. Manual on Soil Sampling and Methods of Analysis. Can.  Soc. Sci., Ottawa, Ont., 2nd ed.  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron-oxide removal from soils and clays by a  dithionite-citrate-system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7 :  317--327.  Ojanuga, A.G., 1973. Weathering of biotite in soils of a humid tropical climate. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 37: 544--646.  Ojanuga, A.G., 1979. Clay mineralogy of soils in the Nigerian tropical savanna regions.  Soil Sci. Soc. J., 43: 1237--1242.  Smith, W.W., 1962. Weathering of some Scottish basic igenous rocks with reference to  soil formation. J. Soil Sci., 13: 202--215.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. U.S.D.A. Handbook, 435. U.S. Gov. Print. Off., Washing-  ton, DC.  Stephen, I., 1952. A study of rock weathering with reference to the soils of the Malvern  Hills, I. Weathering of biotite and granite. J. Soil Sci., 3: 219--237.  Velde, B., 1977. Clay and Clay Minerals in Natural and Synthetic Systems. (Develop-  ments in Sedimentology, 21). Elsevier, Amsterdam, 8 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractThe clay mineralogy of eight selected soil profiles developed on acid igneous, pyroclastic and sedimentary rocks was investigated. The effects on the clay mineralogy of the parent-rock mineralogy and physical conditions within each soil profile were evaluated.The results indicate that the mineralogies of the parent rocks control the type of clay minerals formed in Sarawak. In the soils derived from pyroclastic and coarse-grained acid igneous rocks without muscovite, the clay-mineral suites consist almost exclusively of kaolinite and gibbsite with small amounts of goethite. In contrast, in the soils developed from fine-grained acid igneous and sedimentary rocks with muscovite, the clays contain relatively large amounts of interstratified mica-vermiculite and chlorite-vermiculite in addition to gibbsite and/or kaolinite. The presence of gibbsite in these soils depends on the presence of plagioclase feldspar in the parent rock. 