 Geoderma, 31 (1983) 277--288                                                     277  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CHARACTERIZATION OF AI/Fe--HUMUS COMPLEXES IN  DYSTRANDEPTS THROUGH COMPARISON WITH SYNTHETIC FORMS    T. HIGASHI  Faculty of Agriculture, Kagoshima University, Kagoshima 890 (Japan)  (Received May 1, 1981 ; revised version accepted March 23, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Higashi, T., 1983. Characterization of A1/Fe-humus complexes in Dystrandepts through  comparison with synthetic forms. Geoderma, 31: 277--288.    The A1/Fe--humus complexes in A, horizons of Dystrandepts from several parts of  Japan were compared with synthetic complexes prepared from hydroxy ions and from  two kinds of humic substances and at several pH values. Samples represented 26 A~ hori-  zons of soils differing in age, including some that had been buried. The comparisons were  based chiefly on extractions of the synthetic complexes and the soil samples with solu-  tions of sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and sodium pyrophosphate.  The Al--humus complexes in the Dystrandept samples appeared to be similar to those  of synthetic complexes prepared at pH 4--5. Those have OH/AI molar ratios of 0.7--2.5 1.  Distribution of the data for the soil samples suggested further that the proportions of  polymeric hydroxy A1 ions increased as soils became older and also if they were buried.  The Fe---humus complexes in the soil samples seemed to be like the synthetic complexes  prepared with Fe and humus at pH 4--5 for the most part.    INTRODUCTION    Andepts in general have high contents of humic substances in their A~  horizons {even up to 25% carbon per oven-dry soil material}. Moreover, the  humic substances are rich in highly polymerized humic acid fractions, giving  black colors to those horizons. Several previous studies in Japan (Shinagawa,  1962; Kato, 1970; Kobo and Oba, 1974) indicated that aluminum and iron  played an important role in the accumulation of humic substances, probably  through the formation of A1/Fe--humus complexes. Later studies (Wada and  Higashi, 1976; Mizota, 1978) based on selective dissolution analyses with  solutions of sodium pyrophosphate and/or dithionite-bicarbonate-citrate  supported the earlier findings. At present, the forms of aluminum and iron  in humus complexes in the A, horizons of Dystrandepts axe thought to be  their hydroxy ions (Higashi and Wada, 1977; Yoshida and Nakano, 1978;  Shinagawa et al., 1982). Even so, the detailed nature of the complexes and  of the hydroxy A1 and Fe ions in those complexes is not fully understood.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  O 1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    278    In the present study, characterization of Al/Fe--humus complexes ~,  Dystrandepts, especially the nature of the complexed aluminum and iror,  was attempted through comparisons with synthetic forms. As a means of  comparison, extractions were made with sodium pyrophosphate and sodium  hydroxide-tetraborate solutions. The two extractants were expected to shed  some light on the different forms of aluminum and iron complexed with  humus in Dystrandepts (Higashi and Shinagawa, 1981).    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Preparation of synthetic Al-- and Fe--humus complexes    Three steps were followed in the preparation of the complexes. These  were: (1) preparation of the humic substances, (2) preparation of ionic solu-  tions of hydroxy A1 and Fe, and (3) the synthesis of the complexes. Each  step is described individually.  Preparation of humic substances. The humic substances were obtained by  separate extractions of samples of an A~ horizon of a Dystrandept with  0.5 M acetyl acetone and 0.1 M Na,P2OT. The Dystrandept profile was from  Daikanbo, Kumamoto, Japan. Fine soil particles suspended in both extracts  were removed by centrifuging after addition of "super floc" (Sheldrick and  McKeague, 1975). Humic substances in the 0.5 M acetyl acetone extract  were separated from the extractant in a separator] funnel containing CC14,  with subsequent removal of remaining small amounts of CCI4 and acetyl  acetone under reduced pressure with a rotary evaporator at about 35. The  resulting humic substances in water were treated with a cation exchange  resin (IR-120) in Hform. Humic substances in the 0.1 M Na4P207 extract  were obtained by dialysis against distilled water until the extractant had dis-  appeared, as determined by lack of a white precipitate of Ag4P:OT upon  addition of a silver solution. The resulting humic substances were also treat-  ed with the cation exchange resin in Hform. Humic substances extracted  by acetyl acetone and by pyrophosphate are called Sample I and Sample II,  respectively, throughout this paper.  Preparation of solutions of hydroxy Al and Fe. Four separate ionic solu-  tions of hydroxy A1 were formed at pH values of 4, 5, 5.5 and 6 by the slow  addition of 0.1 M NaOH with an automatic titrator (0.38 ml/min) to a con-  tinuously stirred 0.1 N solution of A1Cla. The resulting solutions, with con  centrations of about 2 10-: molar (Table I), were aged for 24 h at room  temperature. Generally, the pH values of the solutions decreased slightly  after aging (about 0.2).  The same procedure was followed in preparation of solutions of hydroxy  Fe, using 0.1 N Fe421a solution, except that pH values were 2, 3, 4 and 5. In  the case of Fe, however, formation of fine colloidal hydroxides was observed  in the solutions of higher pH. Moreover, the hydroxy Fe solutions were not  aged but were used for synthesis of complexes immediately after preparation  because of the rapid hydrolytic reactions.    TABLE I  Composition of prepared solutions of hydroxy AI- and Fe-ions    279    Hydroxy Al~solutions~    Hydroxy Fe solutions2    Concentra-  pH value Mole-ratio Almono.3  Concentra-  pH value Mole-ratio Femono3.  tion (mole)  at prepa- of OH/A]  AltotaI    tion (mole)  at prepa-  of OH/Fe  Fetota1  ration                                        ration    2.0 10-2   4         0.7        64.4      2.7 10-5   2         0.5         70.4  1.9- 10-2    5           2.5            3.7       2.5 10-2    3           2.7            6.8  1.9 10-2   5.5       2.6          1.4      2.5 10 2   4         2.75         2.7  1.8 10 2   6          2.8         trace      2.4 10 2    5          2.8         trace    ~Aged for 24 hours at room temperature. 2Not aged as were Al-solutions; include fine  colloidal Fe hydroxides (especially pH 4 and 5). 3Percentages of the total AI or Fe in  monomeric species.    Synthesis of Al-- and Fe--humus complexes. The pH values for synthesis  of complexes were chosen to match those of the hydroxy A1 (or Fe) solu-  tions already prepared. The pH of the solution of humic substances was ad-  justed with dilute NaOH to that of the hydroxy A1 (or Fe) solution with  which it was to be mixed. Hydroxy A1 (or Fe) solution was added to the  solution of humic substances until the latter were completely flocculated.  The resulting flocculated A1-- (or Fe--)humus complexes were centrifuged  and washed with distilled water and/or ethanol until free of C1- in the super-  natants, dried at room temperature and then ground to fine powders. Syn-  theses of all complexes were carried out three times on as many different  days and samples from all of the syntheses were extracted with pyrophos-  phate or tetraborate.    Soil samples    The soft samples used in the present study are those described in a previous  paper (Higashi and Shinagawa, 1981). The full-set comprised samples of 13  A1 horizons now at the land surface and 13 samples of buried A1 horizons.  All softs represented by samples are considered to be Dystrandepts and occur  in Kyushu and Hokkaido, Japan. The 26 samples were divided into three  groups according to the age of parent ash and burial. Group 1 comprised  eight samples from softs in ash less than 1000 years old. Group 2 comprised  five samples from softs in ash more than 1000 years old. All samples from  Groups 1 and 2 were from AI horizons at the land surface. Group 3 compris-  ed 13 samples of buried A~ horizons of softs in ash more than 2500 years old  (see Table IV).    Analytical methods    Determination of monomeric hydroxy Al and Fe ions. The monomeric    280  TABLE II  Total contents of A[ and C in synthetic Al--humus complexes and extractable  (shown as % on oven~lry basis)    Al and ("    Com-     Total            Altotal* 2   Alna   Alpyr    Cna      Cpyr     Alva     A]pyr.  plexes.1                         (%)   (%)     (%)     (%)  C (%) Al (%)  Ctal                                     Alpyr   Cpyr    I,       27.25 10.37   0.17     7.09    9.66   20.59   26.71   0.73    0.16  II4      34.97  7.04  0.09     6.64   6.72  31.94  32.59  0.99   0.09  Is         19.28  14.69    0.34       3.25    13.87    11.50    16.92    0.23     0.36  IIs       25.99 13.51   0.23     3.72   13.04   10.06   23.32   0.29    0.25  Is.s        14.40  20.73    0.64       2.87    19.04     3.81    14.20    0.15     0.60  IIs.s      18.82 18.25   0.43      3.08   16.17    2.42   16.28   0.19    0.44  Is        6.95 27.84   1.78     1.97    4.71    0.64    1.34   0.42    1.56  II,        8.80 30.20   1.53     1.76    4.77    0.36    1.02   0.37    2.08    ** I and II refer to the coml~lexes from the humic substances of samples I and II, respec-  tively, and the subscript f'~ures indicate pH values for synthesis of complexes..2 Atomic  ratio. *3Subscripts "na" and "pyr", denote tetraborate and pyrophosphate extraction,  respectively.    TABLE HI    Total contents of Fe and C in synthetic Fe---humus complexes and the extractable Fe and  C (shown as % on oven-dry basis)    Com-     Total           Fetotal2   Fena   Fepyr   Cna     Cpyr    Feva    Fepyr* ~  plexes*z                         (%)   (%)     (%)     (%)  C (%)  Fe (%)  Ctal                                     FepYr   CpYr    II~         32.88  15.48    0.10       9.01    13.31    28.98    29.93    0.68     0.10  II~         24.61  28.07    0.25       3.53    18.24    14.73    23.42    0.19     0.17  II,       18.56 36.38   0.42     1.96   17.20    9.49   16.01   0.11    0.23  LIs       16.05 41.74   0.56     0.37  18.98    5.83   13.17   0.02    0.28    ,1,5 Designations are the same as for Al--humus complexes in Table II.    hydroxy AI and Fe ions in the solutions prepared for the syntheses of com-  plexes were determined by extraction with 8-hydroxy quinoline in chloroform  (Turner, 1969). Total amounts of A1 and Fe in the solutions were determin-  ed by the same method after depolymerization of the monomeric ions by  HC1. The latter analyses were made to permit calculation of the proportions  of total A1 and Fe in monomeric forms. Solutions of both Al and Fe at all  pH values were prepared three times on as many different days with essen  tiaUy similar results in proportions of total A1 and Fe in monomeric forms.  Al, Fe and C in extracts of synthetic complexes and soil samples. Ten ml  of 0.1 N sodium hydroxide-tetmborate or 0.1 M sodium pyrophosphate    281    TABLE IV    Ratios of A1 and Fe extracted with two reagents (Alna/Alpyr and Fena/Fepyr) and the  atomic ratios of (AI + Fe)pyr/Cpyr from soil samples plus ~ log K values of pyrophosphate  extracts from soil samples and humic substances of Samples I and II    Sample                Alna/Alpyr    Fena/Fepyr    Alpyr/CpyrI     A Iog K    Humic substances:  Sample I             --             --             --              0.757  Sample II            --             --             --              0.524  Soil samples  Group 1  586                  0.67          0.20          0.13            0.880  S-1-1                 0.81          0.20          0.07            0.826  M-l-1                0.86          0.13          0.05            0.731  M-2-1                0.75          0.14          0.08            0.631  M-3-1                0.49          0.08          0.08            0.664  M-4-1                1.00          0.15          0.05            0.616  M-5-1                1.00          0.28          0.06            0.676  M-6-1                0.73          0.10          0.08            0.628  Group 2  T-l-1                 0.49          0.03          0.12            0.612  H-l-1                 0.47          0.05          0.12            0.618  1040                 0.39          0.02          0.13            0.649  904                  0.35          0.02          0.13            0.579  M-7-1                0.43          0.05          0.14            0.623  Group 3  T-1-2                 0.32          0.02          0.15            0.592  H-1-2                0.23          0.02          0.13            0.614  T-l-3                 0.37          0.11          0.18            0.638  T-1-4                 0.32          0.40          0.21            0.632  T-l-6                 0.35          0.17          0.18            0.589  W-144-2              0.37          0.09          0.12            0.585  W-144-5              0.22          0.03          0.05            0.614  H-l-3                0.27          0.02          0.12            0.616  H-l-4                0.27          0.01          0.12            0.613  H-1-6                0.33          0.17          0.15           0.587  W-167-3              0.34          0.02          0.09            0.645  W-167-6              0.28          0.08          0.12           0.623  T-1-8                 0.38          0.02          0.10            0.605     Atomic ratio. 2 Used for the synthesis of complexes.    solution and about 20 mg of a synthetic complex were shaken in a poly  ethylene centrifuge tube for about 16 h at about 30. 25 ml of 1 M Na2SO4  were then added and the suspension centrifuged for 10 min at 8000 g. The  centrifugate was collected in a volumetric flask. Each subsample of a syn-  thetic complex was treated twice with each of the two reagents. The double  extractions were made on three individual subsamples of each synthetic corn-    282    plex. All data given later for the extractions, represent averages for three sub  samples of each complex.  The procedure for extraction of soil samples and for determinations of ex  tractable A1, Fe and C are given by Higashi and Wada {1977) and Higashi and  Shinagawa ( 1981 ).  Al and Fe in the extracts were determined by atomic absorption, whereas  C was determined by the method of Tyurin (Kononova, 1961) after evapora  tion of aliquots of the extracts to near dryness (Wada and Higashi, 1976}. To  determine total A1 and Fe in the complexes, subsamples were decomposed  first with H:O2. For determination of A1, the residue was taken up with 0.5  N NaOH, whereas for Fe the residue was dissolved in 1 N HC1. Total C was  determined on other subsamples, again by the method of Tyurin.  Amounts of A1, Fe and C extracted by the two reagents from the synthet-  ic complexes are given in Tables II and III, whereas those from soil samples  are given in Table IV. Throughout this paper, the subscripts "na" and "pyr"  are used with symbols for the three elements to identify the amounts ex  tracted by sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and sodium pyrophosphate, respec-  tively.  Measurements of A log K values in pyrophosphate extracts. After appro-  priate dilution of a pyrophosphate extract (Kumada et al., 1967), the A log-K  value was determined This is the difference between log K400m~ and log  K600mu where K represents the absoprtion coefficients at the respective wave-  lengths. The values serve as an index of the degree of humification of organic  matter in soils, that degree being related in turn to proportions of different  functional groups in humic substances (Schnitzer and Khan, 1972}.  Infrared spectroscopy. The infrared spectra for the synthetic A1-- and Fe--  humus complexes were obtained from KBr discs (1.5 mg sample/200 mg  KBr).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Composition of prepared solutions of hydroxy AI and Fe    Monomeric ions constituted 64.4% of the total A1 in solution at pH 4  (Table I). The forms may have been A13and AI(H20)s(OH)2as those were  described by Turner (1969) and Goto and Yotsuyanagi (1968). The propor-  tion of total AI in monomeric form was sharply lower in the solution prepar-  ed at pH 5, being only 3.7%. Accompanying this change was an increase in  the moleratio of OH to AI from 0.7 to 2.5. Rengaamy and Oades (1978)  reported that solutions with concentrations of 1 10-2 moles had OH/AI  molar ratios of 0.5 and 2.6 with 70% and 14.8% of the total AI in mono-  meric form, respectively.  Hydroxy Fe-ions in monomeric form were high only in the solution pre-  pared at pH 2 (70.4% of the total Fe) and the amounts were very small  above pH 3 (Table I).    283    Nature of complexes and extractable Al, Fe and C    When suspensions of humic substances and solutions of either AI or Fe  with the same pH values were mixed, the resulting suspension would general-  ly have a pH about 1 unit lower. The change in pH suggests that undissociat-  ed radicals such as COOH in the humic substances released protons during  formation of the humic complexes with the hydroxy ions. Contents of Na in  the complexes were so small as to be negligible and hence were believed to  have little or no influence. At the same time, some uncertainty remains as to  the specific nature of the hydroxy ions of both metals before and after syn-  thesis of the complexes. It has been assumed, however, that the hydroxy  ions in the solutions were fairly stable both before and after complex forma-  tion. Such stability is suggested by the infrared absorption spectra, especially  those for the Al--humus complexes shown in Fig. 1. Those curves show  regular increases in absorptions near 730-' and 980-' cm which are attribut-  ed to additional A1--O bonding with progressively higher pH values during  synthesis of the complexes.  Complexes are designated as I4, II4 and so on in Tables II and III. The  Roman numerals refer to Sample ! and Sample II, the first consisting of  humic substances extracted with acetyl acetone and the second those ex-  tracted with sodium pyrophosphate. The subscript figures indicate the pH  values at which the complexes were synthesized.  On an oven-dry basis, Sample I contained 1.52% and 0.4% whereas Sample  II contained 1.90% and 3.04% of A1 and Fe, respectively. These amounts are  considered small enough as compared to total amounts of the ions in the  complexes to have had little or no effect on their behavior.  The atomic ratios of total A1 to total C, as shown in Table II, increased  from 0.17 to 1.78 in the complexes from Sample I and from 0.09 to 1.53 in  those from Sample II as the pH at the time of synthesis was increased from 4  to 6 (Table II). These differences are attributed to increased amounts of  hydroxy A1 in polymeric form (Table I) and to increases in the amounts of  functional groups involved in the reactions at the higher pH values. The A1/C  ratios were higher in all cases of corresponding pH values for Sample I as  compared to Sample II. The differences could be due to higher proportions  of functional radicals in Sample I, indicated by the lower A log-K values  {Table IV).  Sodium pyrophosphate solution extracted nearly all of the Al and C from  the complexes except for Samples I6 and II6. From these complexes, the  reagent extracted only 17% and 16% of the total A1 and 19% and 12% of the  total C, respectively.  Sodium hydroxide-tetraborate extracted most of the total AI and C from  complexes prepared at pH 4 (see data for I4 and II4 in Table II), although the  amounts were smaller than those extracted by pyrophosphate. For com-  plexes formed at pH 5 and higher, however, the tetraborate extracted far less  of the A1 and C. Thus, the latter reagent was less effective than pyrophos-    284    %t  I    2;'""   "'" ':'  I      Al-humus complexes    I I    730Cm-I             Fe-humus complexes  I  _ ,       a  I/    T     I  I      ,    18  17  16 15  14  1_3  12  I] i0  9   8    7    6  5   4  x i00 m'n-I  Fig. 1. Infrared spectra of synthetic AI-- and Fe--humtts complexes (solid line) and humic  substances of Sample II (dotted line).    phate in extracting AI and C from synthetic complexes.  Fe--humus complexes were synthesized only from Sample II, the humic  substances extracted from the soil sample with pyrophosphate. The atomic  ratios of total Fe to C increased from 0.10 to 0.56 for the complexes prepar-  ed at pH 2 and 5, respectively (Table III). Neither pyrophosphate nor tetra-  borate could extract all of the Fe in the complexes. The proportion of total  Fe extracted by pyrophosplmte was 86% and 48% from II2 and IIs, respec-  tively. Tetraborate was even leas effective, extracting 58% from II~ and only  0.9% from IIs. As compared to the proportions of Fe extracted by pyro-    285    phosphate, those of C were relatively high, being 91% for II2 and 82% for  II~. Extraction of the greater proportions of C suggests that part of the  humic substances were not bonded to the added Fe.  McKeague and Sheldrick (1977) extracted A1 and Fe from synthetic com-  plexes prepared with various ratios of metals to fulvic acids. From their data,  the authors concluded that the amounts of A1 and Fe extracted by pyro-  phosphate and tetraborate depended on the ratios of metals to fulvic acids,  which seems reasonable. Complexes used by McKeague and Sheldrick (1977)  had been prepared at pH values of 4.5 for A1 and 2.5 for Fe, which are  within the pH ranges chosen for the present study. The results obtained  should therefore be generally similar, as they seem to be. One further con-  sideration can be taken from the data given in Table I, which suggest that  differences exist in the nature of the hydroxy Al and Fe ions when com-  plexes are prepared at different pH values. Distinctions in the nature of the  hydroxy ions may also affect the character of the resulting complexes and in  turn influence the amounts of the ions extractable by the two reagents.    Comparisons of natural complexes in Dystrandepts with synthetic forms    The chief bases for the comparisons consist of the quantities and propor-  tions of A1, Fe and C extracted from natural and synthetic complexes by  tetraborate and pyrophosphate. The pyrophosphate extracts of the 26 A~  horizons of Dystrandepts were considered to be A1 and Fe complexes with  humic substances (Wada and Higashi, 1976). The A log K values for those  complexes fall between those of Sample I and Sample II (Table IV), which  are also extracts from the A~ horizon of a Dystrandept. Sample I was obtain-  ed by extraction with acetyl acetone, whereas Sample II was obtained by ex-  traction with pyrophosphate. The two samples were used to prepare the syn-  thetic complexes. The A log K values thus indicate that Sample I had the  lowest and Sample II the highest degree of humffication among the  substances that form complexes with A1 and Fe in Dystrandepts.  Among the synthetic complexes prepared at a given pH, those from Sam-  ple I have higher Alpyr/Cpyr ratios and lower Alna/Alpyr ratios than those  prepared from Sample II (Table II). The relationships between ratios at dif-  fering pH values are shown in Fig. 2A (points for I6 and II6 were omitted be-  cause the complexes were not completely soluble in sodium pyrophosphate).  The two ratios were chosen for characterizations and comparisons of com-  plexes because the Alpyr/Cpyr ratio represents a measure of sorts of the com-  plexing capacity of humus, whereas the Alna/Alpyr ratio is related to the  nature of the complexed A1. Differences in the amounts of Al extracted by  the two reagents were discussed in an earlier section of the manuscript.  The Alna/Alpyr ratios versus Alpyr/Cpyr ratios are plotted for the 26 soil  samples in Fig. 2B. Data for the same ratios at different pH values for the  synthetic complexes are plotted in the graph as dotted lines. Values of ratios  for the soil samples fall mostly between those of the synthetic complexes    286    \  1.0    0.5    0    Alna/Alpyr    A    I       I       A       I       L       |  0.1   0.2  0.3  0.4  0.5  0.6  Alpyr/Cpyr    Alna/Alpyr    [  1-01 C~:~;,,  ,                 O group 1  ~-   ~ ", :-i        () group 2  i     O, ',       group 3  !               "" :':':": ::'J  .......  :i':  I @ i                         1  l         I         I    ,              ii  0   0.1  0.2  G3  0A  0.5  0.6  B        Alpyr/Cpyr    Fig. 2.A. Relationships between the ratios of Al extracted with the two reagents (Alna/  Alpy: on the ordinate and Alpyt/Cp~r on the abscissa) for synthetic Al-humtm complexes.  B. Relationships between the ratios of Al extracted with the two reagents (Alna/Alpyr on  the ordinate and Alpyr/Cpyr on the ablcimm) for 26 soil samples.    prepared at pH 4 and pH 5. For a given Alna/Alpyr ratio, however, the Alpyr/  Cpyr ratios of the soil samples tend to be lower than ratios for synthetic  complexes. The differences may be due to complexing of both Fe and AI  with the same hurnic molecules in the soils, for one thing. For another, it  may also be due to lack of complex formation between some humic mole-  cules and A1. The similarities between data for the soil samples and for the  synthetic complexes suggest that the Al--humus complexes in AI horizons  of Dystrandepts are closely similar in nature to synthetic complexes of hy-  droxy A] ions with humus prepared at pH 4 to 5. The OH/A] ratios in those  synthetic complexes ranged from 0.7 to 2.5 {Table I).  A second relationship is brought out in Fig. 2 by the clustering of the data  for soil samples of Groups 1, 2 and 3. Nearly all samples of the A1 horizons  of Group 1, representing softs formed in ash less than 1000 years old, plot  near the values for the synthetic complexes prepared at pH 4. The data for  the A~ horizons of softs in Groups 2 and 3 plot near the values for the syn-  thetic complexes prepared at pH 5. Higher proportions of the total A1 were  in polymeric hydroxyl ions in the complexes prepared at pH 5 than at pH 4.  Assuming that the reactions in the natural complexes and the synthetic com-  plexes are closely similar, I inferred that the proportions of polymerized  hydroxy A1 ions complexed with humus increase with the passing of time in  the A~ horizons of Dys~andepts. The distribution of the data for samples in  Groups 2 and 3 suggests that burial of AI horizons further promotes con-  version of A1 into polymerized forms.    287    Although the data for Fe--humus complexes have not been analyzed as  fully as those for A1 complexes, a comparison of Fena/Fepyr ratios suggests  similarities in the nature of the Fe in humus complexes of Dystrandepts to  that in synthetic complexes prepared at pH values of 3 to 5, mostly between  4 and 5. Moreover, differences in the probable nature of the Fe--humus com-  plexes seem smaller than differences among the A1 complexes in the 26 soil  samples.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The author wishes to express his thanks to Mrs. Y. Tanabata and K.  Tanoue for their assistance in the present study. A part of this work was  supported by a grant from the Science Research Fund of the Japanese  Ministry of Education (No. 576039).    REFERENCES    Goto, K. and Yotsuyanagi, T., 1968. Determination of mononuclear aluminum complex  ions in the presence of large amounts of polynuclear aluminum species. Nippon Kaga-  ku Zasshi, 89:49--53 (in Japanese).  Higashi, T. and Shinagawa, A., 1981. Comparison of sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and  sodium pyrophosphate as extractants of Al]Fe-humus "complexes" in Dystrandepts,  Japan. Geoderma, 25: 285--292.  Higashi, T. and Wada, K., 1977. Size fractionation, dissolution analysis, and infrared  spectroscopy of humus complexes in Ando soils. J. Soil Sci., 28: 653---663.  Kato, Y., 1970. A model for amorphous matter of humic soils in Japan -- a preliminary  report. Pedologist, 14:16--21 (in Japanese).  Kobo, K. and Oba, Y., 1974. Factors of humus accumulation in volcanic ash soils and the  influence of humus on some properties of soils. Genesis and characteristic of volcanic  ash soils in Japan (part 8). J. Sci. Soil Manure, Japan, 45:293--297 (in Japanese).  Kononova, M., 1961. Soil Organic Matter. Pergamon, Oxford, pp. 342--344.  Kumada, K., Sato, O., Ohsumi, Y. and Ohta, S., 1967. Humus composition of mountain  soils in central Japan with special reference to the distribution of P-type humic acid.  Soil Sci. Plant Nutr. (Tokyo), 13: 151--158.  McKeague, J.A. and Sheldrick, B.H., 1977. Sodium hydroxide-tetraborate in comparison  with sodium pyrophosphate as an extractant of "complexes" characteristic of spodic  horizons. Geoderma, 19: 97--104.  Mizota, C., 1978. Clay mineralogy of A horizons of seven Ando soils, central Kyushu.  Soil Sci. Plant Nutr. (Tokyo), 24: 63--73.  Rengsamy, P. and Oades, J.M., 1978. Interaction of monomeric and polymeric species of  metal ions with clay surfaces, III. Aluminum (III) and chromium (III). Aust. J. Soil  Res., 15: 53--66.  Schnitzer, M. and Khan, S.U., 1972. Humic substances in the environment. Marcel Dek-  ker, New York, N.Y., pp. 55--82.  Sheldrick, B.H. and McKeague, J.A., 1975. A comparison of extractable Fe and AI data  using methods followed in the U.S.A. and Canada. Can. J. Soil Sci., 55: 77--78.  Shinagawa, A., 1962. Further accumulation of humus on the volcanic ash soils originated  from volcano Sakurajima's ashes. Bull. Fac. Agric. Kagoshima Univ., 11:155--205 (in  Japanese).    288    Shinagawa, A., Miyauchi, N. and Higashi, T., 1982. Preparation of Al-humates and their  aluminum content and cation exchange capacity. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr. (Tokyo), 28:  1--7.  Turner, R.C., 1969. Three forms of aluminum in aqueous systems determined by 8-  quinoline extraction methods. Can. J. Chem., 47: 2521--2527.  Wada, K. and Higashi, T., 1976. The categories of aluminum- and iron-humus complexes  in Ando soils determined by selective dissolution. J. Soil Sci., 27: 357--368.  Yoshida, M. and Nakano, K., 1978. Decrease in the cation absorption ability of soil or-  ganic matter caused by the absorption of basic aluminum. J. Sci. Soil Manure, Japan.  49:513--515 (in Japanese).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        AbstractThe Al/Fe—humus complexes in A1 horizons of Dystrandepts from several parts of Japan were compared with synthetic complexes prepared from hydroxy ions and from two kinds of humic substances and at several pH values. Samples represented 26 A1 horizons of soils differing in age, including some that had been buried. The comparisons were based chiefly on extractions of the synthetic complexes and the soil samples with solutions of sodium hydroxide-tetraborate and sodium pyrophosphate.The Al—humus complexes in the Dystrandept samples appeared to be similar to those of synthetic complexes prepared at pH 4–5. Those have OH/Al molar ratios of 0.7–2.5 1. Distribution of the data for the soil samples suggested further that the proportions of polymeric hydroxy Al ions increased as soils became older and also if they were buried. The Fe—humus complexes in the soil samples seemed to be like the synthetic complexes prepared with Fe and humus at pH 4–5 for the most part. 