 Geoderma, 28 (1982) 203--220                                                  203  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    MICROMORPHOLOGICAL FABRICS AND DEVELOPMENTAL STAGES  OF CARBONATE NODULAR FORMS RELATED TO SOIL  CHARACTERISTICS    MOSHE WIEDER and D.H. YAALON  Department of Geography, Bar-Ilan University, Ramat-Gan (Israel)  Department of Geology, The Hebrew University, Jerusalem (Israel)  (Received August 11, 1981; accepted after revision May 10, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Wieder, M. and Yaalon, D.H., 1982. Micromorphological fabrics and developmental stages  of carbonate nodular forms related to soil characteristics. Geoderma, 28: 203--220.    Carbonate nodules often constitute the first stage of calcrete formation. Micromorpholog-  ical analysis of carbonate nodules and nodular fabrics in different soil materials shows that  their development is a function of several factors: nature of the host matrix (texture,  porosity), carbonate and non-carbonate clay distribution, bulk density and the interactions  among them. Different micromorphological stages, therefore, exist in different soil materials.  In calcareous, medium-textured soil materials, the stages of nodule formation are  related to the increase of the density of the nodule caused by the accumulation of micro-  calcites. In such a soil material the following stages occur: (1) microcalcites within the low-  to-moderate density matrix; (2) microcalcites of moderate to high density and moderately  dense, diffuse nodules; parallel calcans may occur; (3) microcalcites of high density with  dense microcalcitic nodules. During these stages the amount of non-carbonate clay de-  creases but is homogeneously dispersed and disseminated with the microcalcites. In general,  the size of microcalcites, 1--8 ~m, is inversely related to the clay content.  In non-calcareous, medium-to-fine textured soil materials, secondary carbonate pre-  cipitates in intrapedal and/or interpedal voids as large sparry crystals. Due to pedoturba-  tion processes, the nodules thus formed are subjected to recrystallization, resulting in a  microsparry pattern. The development stages are: (1) few calcans and crystal chambers;  (2) crystic nodules mainly of sparry crystals and an increase of calcans and crystic cham-  bers; (3) recrystallized nodules composed mainly of microspars.  In coarse-grained materials, secondary carbonates precipitate directly in voids as sparry  crystals and the resulting nodules are of the crystic type. The large crystals are often sub-  jected to recrystallization.  In partly calcareous, coarse-grained materials with additions of calcareous dust, partic-  ular micromorphological carbonate forms occur. In the C horizon, cutanic calciasepic  fabric forms besides zones of crystic fabric which gradually become calciasepic in the B  horizon and include the typical nodular forms of the calcareous medium-textured soil  material, together with appreciable amounts of glaebular halos.  The processes leading to the formation of these stages occur essentially without a sig-  nificant biogenic influence. Where carbonate segregation occurs as rhizomorphs surround-  ing active roots, the fabric is always micritic even in coarse textural soil material.    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    204    INTRODUCTION    The nature and distribution of carbonate nodules in soil materials are im-  portant features in pedogenetic studies of arid regions. The nodules are sig-  nificant in the study of both buried and exposed paleosols and their influence  on physical and chemical properties is important in land-use planning.  The morphological character of secondary carbonates in the field generally  changes with the different stages of carbonate accumulation (Gile et al.,  1966; Netterberg, 1969; Ruellan, 1970). Macroscopic morphogenetic sequences  have been suggested for gravelly and non-gravelly soil materials leading to  calcrete (Gile et al., 1966). Brewer (1972a) proposed in a general way a cor-  relation of macroscopic carbonate forms with probable equivalents in micro-  morphological patterns.  Carbonate nodule formation is observed to be a function of several internal  characteristics, such as the character of the matrix (texture, porosity), carbonate  and non-carbonate clay distribution, bulk density of the peds and the reciprocal  influences between these factors (Wieder and Yaalon, 1974; Wieder, 1977}.  Additional external factors are also involved, including carbonate content in  the parent material, water regime, rate of dust deposition, duration of soil  development and others. Therefore, the micromorphological sequences are  not identical in all environmental conditions and general, universal stages can-  not be established.  In the present paper micromorphogenetic stages of carbonate fabrics arising  from differences in soil characteristics and environmental conditions are  presented, and the occurrence of particular micromorphological patterns for  certain nodular stages and their causal formation are discussed. A nodule is  understood here as a local concentration of chemical compounds within a  soil formed by soil-forming processes (Yaalon, 1976). Orthic, disorthic and  allothic nodules are distinguished (Wieder and Yaalon, 1974).    FACTORS AFFECTING NODULAR FABRIC DEVELOPMENT    The construction of micromorphogenetic stages takes into consideration  those factors that give rise to the diversity of nodular fabrics. Detailed data  about the factors and conditions affecting carbonate nodule formation were  presented in a previous paper (Wieder and Yaalon, 1974). The present micro-  morphogenetic sequence is based on these and many additional observations  of calcic horizons and nodules in various profiles in Israel, which are reported  elsewhere (e.g., Dan et al., 1981).  Factors found to be responsible for the nature and behavior of the car-  bonate nodules and carbonate forms are: (1) occurrence of clay minerals; (2)  occurrence of carbonates; (3) soil structure stability; (4) soil texture; and (5)  occurrence of organisms.  The role of these factors and their interrelationships are treated below, but  first, the size grades of calcites are defined. Three size grades of calcite crystals  are recognized:    205    Microcalcites: small calcite crystallites within the range of 1--8 pm (Figs. 1  and 2), uniformly distributed and strongly integrated with the clay minerals  (cf. findings of SEM and electron-microprobe analysis, Wieder and Yaalon,  1974, pp. 108--114). Microcalcites are constituents of calciasepic fabrics. In  such a fabric the degree of integration of the non-carbonate clay and fine  carbonates (clay and very fine silt} is so high that the birefringence of the  clay minerals cannot be distinguished. This criterion is somewhat different    Fig. 1. Microcalcites of nodules in loessial material in B~3 Ca + Cs (100--130 cm). Note the  main size between 2--4 #m, SEM 5500x.    Fig. 2. Microcalcites of nodules of quartzic Arid Brown soil material, in II Bbca (234--  265 cm). Note the main size between 4--8 #m. SEM 2750)&lt;.    206    from that defined by Mulders (1969) but is useful and practical in micro-  morphological descriptions. Microcalcite is considered a product of soil form-  ing processes, hence this term is preferred instead of micrite, which frequently  has a sedimentological-genetic meaning (microcrystalline ooze, Folk, 1959),  unusual in soil processes.  Microsparites: recognisable small crystals between 8--20 tam. These tend to  be locally distributed and there is no uniform distribution throughout the  non-carbonate clay. Usually they are associated with recrystallization pro-  cesses.  Sparites: pure crystals, larger than 20 tam, usually lacking clay-mineral in-  clusions. They are generally the result of direct precipitation. Microsparites  and sparites are constituents of crystic fabrics. These terms were adopted  from sedimentology (Folk, 1962; Bathurst, 1971) because processes of direct  precipitation and recrystallization are active in soils also. The size limits used  here, however, are not exactly the same as those used by sedimentologists.    Effects of clay minerals    The occurrence of clay minerals controls the size of the calcite crystals that  compose the carbonate nodules.  The relation between the crystal size and the occurrence of non-carbonate  clay depends on the microenvironmental conditions.  (1 } In conditions of uniform dissemination and good integration between  non-carbonate clay and microcalcites an inverse relation exists between the  carbonate crystal size and the amount of clay minerals. This is true for both  the calciasepic fabric and the carbonate nodules built up from microcalcites.  The higher the amount of clay minerals in the calciasepic fabric the smaller  are the microcalcites and vice versa, within the range of 1--8 tam. In unaltered  calcareous loessial material the size of the microcalcite is generally smaller  than 2 tam, an observation supported by the high correlation between the  carbonate content in the clay fraction and the total carbonate content (Table  I). In the calcic horizons of the loessial materials with low proportions of clay  minerals within the plasma, the size of the microcalcites is between 2--4 tam  (Fig. 1); this fact is also supported by the lack of correlation between car-  bonate content in the clay fraction and total carbonates (Table I). The low  proportion of clay minerals is probably a result of their partial expulsion. In  the B horizons of quartzic Arid Brown soils which have a calciasepic fabric  with very low contents of clay minerals, the size of microcalcites is mostly be-  tween 4--8 tam (Fig. 2). (The quartzic Arid Brown softs are developed.in two  parent materials: calcareous sand and eolian dust; the buried B horizon in  Table I of Wieder and Yaalon, 1974, is representative of this soil type.)  (2) The inverse relation which exists between the size of microcalcites and  the amount of clay minerals within the range of 1--8 tam is not applicable to  large sparry calcite crystals. In the case of the latter, the opposite trend is  true, i.e., the more clay minerals there are in the microenvironment, the bet-  ter are the conditions for growth of large crystals.    207    &lt;    ~Q  o~       ~0  .~ ~           II  II     ~  II II  e~  m   e~  ~2    I       II     II     I    ~   ~+      ~+      ~+  ++   ++M     +~     +~  I  II   II      II  II  II          II  II          II  II  I ~I ~I I ~I I ~I           ~A  + M   + + M     + M     + +  II  II      II  II  II         II  II         II  II  I ~I ~I I ~xi I ~I    0        ~D        O0        Cq              ~         o~  0000000000000000  ssaeeesessseaese    ~'~        0    c~  ~D  C~    208    These two different trends suggest that the calcite crystal size in the environ-  ment of precipitation depends to a large extent on the distribution of non-  carbonate clay. The latter trend frequently appears in highly decalcified soils  in which the non-carbonate clay becomes dominant.  (3) Local accumulation of clay cutans in voids of a soil material which con-  sists of calciasepic fabric creates microenvironmental conditions for crystal-  lization of large calcite crystals. For instance, void argillans frequently coat the  sides of calciasepic fabric and permit the precipitation of calcans on crystal  chambers built up from large sparry crystals. Also, in local zones of asepic  fabric free of carbonates, calcite crystals precipitate as large sparry crystals  in voids (Fig. 3). It seems that the nucleation taking place on a substrate free  of carbonates favors large crystal growth. Such cases outline the clay effects  apart from the carbonate effects.    Fig. 3. Calcan to crystal chamber on asepic plasmic fabric free of microcalcites, in Brown  Rendzina soil; crossed polarizers, 100    Effects of carbonates    The strong reciprocal influence which exists between carbonates and clay  minerals prevents an assessment of the real individual effects of the car-  bonates. Even so, differences exist in nodular fabrics of the secondary car-  bonates that precipitate in calcareous soil materials as compared to non-  calcareous soil materials.  Calcareous soil material of strictly calciasepic plasmic fabric usually prevents  crystallization of large crystals. To judge from the distribution of the coarse  calcite grains in the profiles of calcareous loessial material, it seems that  calciasepic fabric has an inhibiting effect on large calcite crystallization. The    209    A horizons of the loessial soils contain relatively high amounts of large calcite  crystals inherited from the eolian dust, whereas in the lower B horizons a  significant decrease in the proportion of coarse calcite grains exists. The high  negative correlation between the carbonate content of the coarse silt fraction  and total carbonate (Table I) confirms the tendency of inhibition of large  calcite crystal growth.  In non-calcareous soil materials, secondary carbonates usually precipitate  as large sparry crystals with clear faces. In leached Red Mediterranean soils,  secondary carbonates prevail as microspars and spars.    Effects of structure    The dynamic activity of swelling and shrinking processes develops a soil  structure which affects the nodular fabric and the crystal forms.  In non-calcareous soil materials, the better expressed and stable the peds  are, the more the crystals are subjected to recrystallization processes; con-  sequently, crystals with planar faces are getting rounded faces (see next sec-  tion). Particularly in soils with slickensides, associated with pedoturbation as  in Grumusols (Vertisols), the recrystallization process is very intensive. Thus,  mainly microspars with poorly expressed faces occur with some local zones  of microcalcites.  In soil materials free of carbonates and with less developed structure, more  microcalcites occur than in more developed structure of the same soil ma-  terial. This is indicated by higher contents of microcalcites in the less stable  peds of the lower B horizons (Wieder, 1977).  Stable peds may directly effect calcite crystallization because the peds  are frequently associated with high bulk density and fewer microvoids and  thus there are large intrapedal voids in which calcite precipitates as sparry  crystals (see Fig. 8 in Wieder and Yaalon, 1974).    Effects of texture    Besides the specific effects of clay minerals in medium to fine textured  softs (cf above), the main factor which controls the carbonate forms in soils  with coarse texture is the texture itself. In such soils carbonates do not ap-  pear to have a controlling influence and the tendency is for carbonate precipita-  tion in the form of large crystals by direct precipitation (Folk, 1965; Bathurst,  1971) as pore space fillings. Thus, in soil materials with granular or intertextic  fabric (Brewer's terminology) with many zones of single packing voids or in  grain-supported texture as defined by sedimentologists (Dunham, 1962),  large calcite crystals prevail. The larger the void space between grains, the  larger is the calcite crystal grown. The further away from the grain, the larger  are the calcite crystals (drusy mosaic).  Large crystals are sometimes subjected to recrystallization. The extent of  the crystallization or recrystallization processes can be followed according to    210    the criteria used by Bathurst {1971). For direct precipitation the following  four criteria are frequently useful in soil micromorphology:  --spars incompletely fill the cavities;  -- the intercrystalline boundaries in the mosaic are made up by plane inter-  faces;  --the contacts between spars and substrate are sharp;  -- the mosaics are characterized by a high percentage of enfacial junctions (in  a triple crystic junction one of the angles is 180.  The original fabric resulting from direct precipitation may be subjected to  recrystallization processes. A neomorphic fabric then results in which the  crystal size is usually irregular and patchy with curved intercrystaUine bound-  aries. With advances of the soil-forming processes neomorphic fabric will  prevail.  Coarse material to which calcareous dust is added has zones with cutanic  calciasepic fabric (skeleton grains surrounded by microcalcites with empty  cavities among the grains) besides zones with large calcite crystals character-  istic of direct precipitation. The reason for the two kinds of carbonate dif-  ferentiation is not clear. Local environmental conditions affecting the rate  of precipitation or mixing of non-carbonate clay with carbonate clay in dust  are probably responsible for this particular morphology.    Effects of organisms    The presence of biota of both plants and animals give rise to particular  carbonate forms. The biogenic effect can be very strong, altering the effect  of the other factors to a large extent. Two kinds of influences are distinguished:  (a) bioturbation of existing carbonate forms; (b) direct influence on the eno  vironment of precipitation.  Bioturbation is frequently due to activity of various earthworms. It is the  cause of disorthic carbonate nodules (fragments of larger orthic nodules  formed in situ). Up to 30% of the upper 70 cm of loessial soils in the North-  ern Negev are composed of pedotubules produced by earthworms.  The direct influence of organisms on carbonate precipitation is related to  the metabolism of roots. The most characteristic pattern resulting from root  influence is a dense micrite growth surrounding root remnants. Even in a  soil material with only sparitic crystals a micritic layer surrounds the roots.  In the local environment surrounding the roots, carbon-dioxide pressure is  high and presumably a release of CO2 from the dessicating soil solution con-  tributes to a relatively rapid crystallization of dissolved calcium in the form  of micrites.  The relationship between micritic growth and organic matter is frequently  discussed by sedimentologists. For instance, the association of micrite and  mud of organic origin is stressed by Folk (1965). The genesis of micritic  envelopes is also related to organic metabolism (Bathurst, 1971, p. 388).  In the softs considered in this paper micritic growth surrounding the roots  produced neocalcans and elongated rhizomorph concretions.    211    Neocalcans occur frequently in biogenic pores with root remnants (Figs. 4  and 5). Later the voids become filled completely and biogenic carbonate  nodules result which usually lack inclusions of skeleton grains. It is partic-  ularly difficult to distinguish the latter from the disorthic carbonate nodules,  but they include frequently less non-carbonate clay than the disorthic car-  bonate nodules and have slightly greyer colours in transmitted light whereas    Fig. 4. Neocalcans showing gradual transition to the matrix. Birefringence zones within  the void are root remnants. Grumosol; croued polarizers, 25x.    Fig. 5. Neocalcans with gradual transition to the matrix. Detail of Fig. 4, crossed polarizers,  lOOx.    212    the disorthic carbonate nodules are more yellowish. Neither the disorthic  carbonate nodules nor the biogenic carbonate nodules are considered as a  micromorphogenic stage but rather are particular forms in the population of  carbonate nodule patterns. They are not a particular stage of soil develop-  ment and are not a necessary condition for carbonate nodule formation but  are related to particular causal conditions. Similarly, pseudomycelia, which  are built up from needle-shaped crystals, are mainly a biogenic product of  decomposed roots following the root pattern and considered therefore a result  of particular local conditions.  The micritic growth surrounding the roots is easily recognized in the case  of elongated rhizomorph concretions (Fig. 6); secondary carbonates pre-  cipitate in the paleo-Hamra layers (Red Mediterranean paleosols underlying  eolianites). Three distinct layers occur around channels with root remnants:  (1) an inner micritic layer without skeleton inclusions; (2) a transition layer  of micritic and microsparitic crystals; (3) a sparitic layer including skeleton  grains but free of biorelicts.    Fig. 6. Transverse section of rhizomorph concretion. Note the microcalcitic layer sur-  rounding the channel. Crossed polarizers, 25    The layer differentiation is related to the decreasing influence of a root;  the further from the root the fewer the micritic crystals.  A common feature of nodular carbonate forms in different soil materials  is that uncommon nodular fabrics beside the characteristic nodules of the  soil material are frequently due to biotic influence.    DEVELOPMENT STAGES OF NODULE FORMATION    The main approach in the study of nodular fabrics is usually descriptive  (Parfenova and Yarilova, 1972; Bal, 1975; Fedoroff, 1975; Stoops, 1980).    213    The sequence of micromorphological stages and forms presented in our study  is based on morphogenetic nodular features. Although there are some inherent  difficulties in this approach, e.g., carbonate nodules are frequently removed  from their original environment and continue to develop in the new location  or undergo recrystallization and consequently change their initial form, it  remains a useful way to relate nodular forms to various soil-forming processes.  The sequence of micromorphological stages was established by considering  two aspects of carbonate nodule interpretation: (1) the morphogenetic clas-  sification of carbonate nodules as orthic, disorthic and allothic (Wieder and  Yaalon, 1974; Wieder, 1977); (2) the effects of the main environmental fac-  tors on carbonate nodular formation as described earlier above. The mor-  phogenetic classification makes possible an elaboration of the micromorpholog-  ical sequence by following only the developmental stages of the orthic nodules,  at the same time avoiding consideration of disorthic and allothic nodules as  developmental stages. The models are presented further according to the  usual nodule development in the profile, but one or more micromorphological  stages can occur in the same profile according to the nature of each horizon.    STAGES OF NODULE FORMATION IN CALCAREOUS MEDIUM-TEXTURED SOIL  MATERIALS    In calcareous medium-textured soil materials, the plasmic fabric is almost  entirely calciasepic, the calcareous part of which is composed of microcal-  cites. The increase in carbonate segregation is associated with an increase of  microcalcites. Thus, the gradual increase of microcalcites and of carbonate  nodules is the main feature in the model for calcareous medium-textured  soil material (Table II and Fig. 7).  There is a direct relationship between the amount of fine silt and micro-  calcite. Consequently, the increased carbonate content is in the very fine silt  fraction in the calcic horizons or adjacent to the calcic horizons. This is con-  firmed by the correlation between the fine silt and total carbonate content  in all soil materials with calciasepic fabric (Table I). This indicates that the  degree of soil development can be assessed by following the fine silt accumula-  tion.    TABLE II    Sequence of micromorphogenetic stages of nodule formation  Stage   Calcareous medium-textured soil materials   Non-calcareous medium- to fine-  (Fig. 7)                                    textured soil materials (Fig. 8)    Microcalcites of low to moderate density  Microcalcites of moderate to high density  and moderate to dense nodules  Microcalcites of high density and dense  microcalcitic nodules    Few calcans to crystal chambers  Crystic nodules and calcans to  crystal chambers  Recrystallized nodules including  mainly microspars    214    STAGE 1  LOW   TO     MODERATE  CONCENTRATION  OF  MICROCALCITES.    A    C    STAG E 2  MODERATE TO  DENSE    ",  MICROCALCITES,  MODERATELY  DENSE   DIFFUSE  ' NODULES, CALCANS.      ,'"    ::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::  A    STAGE 3    i HIGHLY  DENSE  MICROCALCITIC             "-  :NODULE,  FEW   CALCANS.             MICROCALCITES (MICRITE  CALCAN(INCLUDING  SPARRY  CRYSTALS)  NODULE  (DENSE   MICROCALCITES)    Fig. 7. Model of micromorphological stage of nodule formation in calcareous medium-  textured soil material   STAGES OF NODULE FORMATION IN NON-CALCAREOUS MEDIUM-TO-FINE-  TEXTURED SOIL MATERIALS    A model of nodular stages for secondary carbonates for pedal but leached  soil materials is presented in Table II and Fig. 8. The nodular forms are  usually composed of coarse calcite crystals (crystic fabric). In the first stage  the nodular forms usually lack skeleton grains or other extraneous features.    STAGE 1    FEW    CALCANSI  CRYSTAL   CHAMBERS.    A    B    215    STAG E 2  CRYSTIC  NODULESt  CALCANS  AND  CRYSTAL   CHAMBERS.    STAGE 3    RECRYSTALLIZED       NODULES    MAINLY   INCLUDING  MICROSPAR       CALCAN  B       CRYSTIC     NODULE         RECRYSTALLIZ ED     NODULE    skeleton    grains (quarlz)    Fig. 8. Model of micromorphological stages of nodule formation in non-calcareous medium-  to-heavy textured soil material.    Carbonates accumulate as calcans or crystal chambers. Crystal tubes may also  occur but are considered as a variety of crystal chambers with developed long  axes. Needle-shaped crystals may also occur. With increasing carbonate  segregation, undifferentiated carbonate nodules occur incorporating skeleton  grains from the surrounding fabric. The forms of precipitated carbonate in-  clude many euhedral crystals with clear plane interfaces.  Well expressed blocky or prismatic peds are dense and characterized by    216    high bulk density and fewer intrapedal microvoids. Precipitation occurs in  the larger voids, particularly interpedal voids. The transition to the adjacent  sepic fabric is usually sharp.  The more active are the other soil-forming processes such as clay illuvia-  tion, pedoturbation and vertic processes the more are the calcite crystals  subject to recrystallization and thus most of the crystals appear as microspars  with rounded faces. Such a pattern characterizes the third stage. This recrystal-  lization is relatively rapid and the transition between stages 2 and 3 is not  always apparent. The nodular pattern is mainly associated with an advanced  stage of soil development. Pedoturbation, together with dissolution and  reprecipitation, causes zones in the plasmic fabric where there is more in-  tegration of clay minerals and carbonate, producing patchy zones of cal-  ciasepic fabric and only in such zones do iron-manganese impregnations ap-  pear in the nodule. Frequently such nodules occur as dentritic iron-man-  ganese nodules as reported also by Blokhuis et al. (1969).    MICROMORPHOLOGICAL CARBONATE FORMS IN COARSE-TEXTURED SOIL  MATERIALS    A coarse texture provides ideal conditions for direct precipitation of large  calcite crystals (Fig. 9). Nodular stages in coarse-textured materials are diffi-  cult to establish because soil development leads usually to alteration of the  coarse texture to a finer texture. Even a small addition of finer material in  the coarse sandy material causes changes in the carbonate forms. Calcareous  dust which accumulates in partly calcareous coarse sandy material, gradually  changes the soil fabric. In the initial stages cutanic calciasepic fabric occurs  around skeleton grains. Later, as the texture becomes finer, the content of  coarse calcite grains decreases and a calciasepic fabric gradually forms. The  fabric of a coarse C horizon is subjected to strong differentiation as B horizon  development proceeds. In the final stage the fabric pattern is very similar to  that in typical calcareous medium-textured soil materials (Fig. 7). In the  calcic B horizon, as well as the characteristic undifferentiated nodules, there  are glaebular halos, or more correctly, compound carbonate nodules made  up of an inner crystic fabric and an outer calciasepic halo which shows a  gradual transition to the matrix. The microcalcitic layer surrounding the  crystic fabric frequently includes silt-size grains (Fig. 10) characteristic of  the loessial material, thus confirming that the two layers are formed under  different conditions. Brewer (1964) considers that both parts have to be  authigenic in a glaebular halo. In our case, it is preferable therefore to con-  sider them as compound carbonate nodules.    DISCUSSION OF PROPOSED STAGES    Several micromorphological stages proposed by various authors in the past  are discussed below. Brewer (1972a) tried to correlate morphological car-    /COARSE    SOIL   MATERIAL    CRYSTIC  NODULES  AND/OR  CRYSTIC      FABRIC    SKELETON  GRAIN  WITH  CALCITE   CRYSTALS.    SPARRY    :. 7':,        -,' .  A :,!   i::, ,:,!i    217    m  I/  CALCAREOUS  COARSE   PARENT   MATERIAL  WITH   ADDITIONAL  CALCAREOUS  DUST    ::.::. , -::.;.:::.:::.;:.::: :. -.: .::. .,:  HIGHLY DENSE MICROCALCITES,    A  .............  MICROCALCITIC AND SPARITIC    :!:i:i  .....................  I                            .~!iii!~:~  NODULES  GLAEBULAR  HALO.BCa              ..:t  '  .....................  :~:~!~!:!i!: !!~i~::~  C RYS TICCA LC I A S E Pl cFABRIC ANDFABRIc.C UTA N I C       C  ..................  ~::::i::i::iiii=:ii?~::i~i~::~iiiiiiiiii~i~i.;~,~m i      COMPOUND  CARBONATE  NODULE (glacbular hal())        CUTANIC    CALC1ASEPIC    FABRIC         M1CROCALCITIC       NODULE    Fig. 9. Micromorphological forms of carbonates in coarse-textured soil material.    bonate forms established by Gile et al. (1966) to probable equivalent micro-  morphological forms and related them to soil age. He proposed the following  micromorphological stages: (1) crystallites (equivalent to microcalcites in  this paper); (2) cutans or neocutans (calcans or neocalcans); nodules; crystal  sheets or cementation of a nodular horizon; and (3) petrocalcic horizons.  Stages (2) and (3) were not characterized micromorphologically. In another  paper, Brewer (1972b) includes large intercalary crystals between crystallites  and calcans also, as an additional stage in the micromorphological progres-  sional development of carbonates. In view of the findings of our studies the  following comments seem reasonable:    218    Fig. 10. Glaebular halo (compound carbonate nodule). The inner zone is crystic fabric  including pellets and the outer zone is microcalcitic with skeleton grains; crossed polarizers,  25    (1) The carbonate nodules show various fabrics in different soil materials,  thus universal stages cannot be established.  (2) Calcite crystallites (microcalcites) are the first stage in nodule forma-  tion only in a calcareous fine-to-medium-textured soil material. In a decalci-  fied medium to heavy textured soil material, e.g., in polygenetic Husmas soil  in Israel, no calcite crystallites occur.  (3) Intercalary large crystals do not form at all in our calcareous medium-  textured soil material and there is no tendency for the formation of large  calcite crystals from microcalcites. The occurrence of large intercalary crystals  in fine-textured soils was also observed by Brewer (1964). The association  of large crystals with fine texture could be due to very dense soil material  which prevents carbonate precipitation in the microvoids of the matrix. Be-  cause of this the carbonate precipitates as large crystals in the larger voids  and is then incorporated into the matrix by pedoturbation.  (4) The occurrence of calcans and neocalcans as a pre-nodule stage seems  to be correct only in the case of non-calcareous soil material. In calcareous  medium-textured soil material in semi-arid climates, calcans can form con-  comitantly with nodules and are virtually absent in the arid climate. At least  we found no indications of calcans as a morphogenetic stage in such soil  materials.  Sehgal and Stoops (1972) proposed three main micromorphological stages  for nodule formation: microcrystalline calcite crystals (microcalcites), diffuse  calcitic nodules and compact calcitic nodules. The stages are in agreement  with our observations in calcareous medium-textured soils but only in respect  to the compact form. Diffuse carbonate nodules can occur in a calcic horizon    219    associated with compact nodules. Moreover, they can be present as such in  paleosols.  The stages proposed by Sehgal and Stoops (1972) do not appear to be  characteristic of the stages in non-carbonate soil material or coarse-textured  soil material. These authors believe that the coarsely crystalline calcites are  an advanced stage of profile development, forming the compact calcitic  nodules. From our studies it is clear that coarse crystals are frequently an  initial stage of pedological carbonates, either as calcans or crystal chambers,  or as undifferentiated nodules which include coarse skeleton grains, similar  to initial cementation by spars in porous sediments.  The first stage of the morphogenetic sequences of Gile et al. (1966) in non-  gravelly soils consists of few filaments or faint coatings. This is in accordance  with the results obtained in non-carbonate soil material unless both filaments  and coatings are considered to be calcans or neocalcans. Filaments such as  needle-shaped crystals (pseudomycelia) cannot be considered a micromor-  phogenetic stage because they usually occur in our samples in unstable cumula-  tive soil profiles particularly on toeslopes without relation to other micro-  morphological forms present in other members of catenary sequences. Sehgal  and Stoops (1972) also consider the needle-shaped crystals as a formation of  particular conditions of precipitation (above a high water table) and not as a  development stage.    CONCLUSIONS    (1) Carbonate nodules show micromorphological differences according to  the stages of soil development, the nature of the soil material in which they  are formed and other surrounding environmental conditions.  (2) Some basic relations exist between the nodular fabric formed and tex-  ture, structure and carbonate contents of the soil materials.  (3) Biogenic processes create particular carbonate forms which are dif-  ferent from the characteristic nodular fabric of the surrounding soil materials.  With reference to the differences from the characteristic nodular fabric special  attention should be given to possible biogenic effects.  (4) Nodular fabric variations may arise in particular environmental condi-  tions. Such specificity was observed in the case of dust accretion on coarse-  textured soil material. Other deviations may be expected in other specific  environments.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors wish to express their sincere thanks to Drs. P. Bullock and  J.A. Catt, Department of Soil Survey and Soil Nutrition, Rothamsted Ex-  perimental Station, Harpenden, for reviewing the manuscript.    REFERENCES    Bal, L., 1975. Carbonate in soil: a theoretical consideration on, and proposal for its fabric  analysis, 1. Crystic, calcic and fibrous fabric. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 23: 18--35.    220    Bal, L., 1975. Carbonate in soil: a theoretical consideration on, and proposal for its fabric  analysis, 2. Crystal tubes, intercalary crystals, K fabric. Neth. J. Agric. Sci., 23: 163--  176.  Bathurst, R.G.G., 1971. Carbonate Sediments and Their Diagenesis. Elsevier, Amsterdam,  620 pp.  Blokhuis, W.A., Pape, Th and Slager, S., 1969. Morphology and distribution of pedogenic  carbonate in some Vertisols of the Sudan. Geoderma, 2: 173--200.  Brewer, R., 1964. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, NY, 470 pp.  Brewer, R., 1972a. Microfabrics and soil history. In: R. Protz (Editor), Microfabrics of  Soil and Sedimentary Deposits. Centre for Resources Development, Guelph, Ont.,  Publ., 69: 161--196.  Brewer, R., 1972b. The basis of interpretation of soil micromorphological data. Geoderma,  8: 81--94.  Dan, J., Gerson, R., Koyumdjisky, H. and Yaalon, D.H., 1981. Aridic Soils of Israel -- Prop-  erties, Genesis and Management. Div. Sci. Publ., Volcani Center, Bet Dagan, Spec.  Publ., 190:353 pp.  Dunham, R.J., 1962. Classification of carbonate rocks according to depositional texture.  In: W.E. Ham (Editor), Classification of Carbonate Rocks. Am. Assoc. Pet. Geol.,  Tulsa, Okla., pp. 108--121.  Fedoroff, N., 1975. Classification micromorphologique des carbonates dans les sols.  Types de Croute calcaires et leur Repartition regionale. Univ. Louis Pasteur, Strasbourg,  pp. 35--41.  Fisher, R.A. and Yates, F., 1963. Statistical Tables for Biological, Agricultural and Medical  Research, Table VI. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh.  Folk, R.L., 1959. Practical petrographic classification of limestones. Bull. Am. Assoc.  Pet. Geol., 43: 1--38.  Folk, R.L., 1962. Spectral subdivision of limestone types. In: W.E. Ham (Editor), Clas-  sification of Carbonate Rocks. Am. Assoc. Pet. Geol., Tulsa, Okla., pp. 62--84.  Folk, R.L., 1965. Some aspects of recrystallization in ancient limestones. In: C. Pray and  R.C. Murray (Editors), Dolomitization and Limestone Diagenesis. Soc. Econ. Paleontol.  Miner., Spec. Publ., 13: 14--48.  Gile, L.H., Peterson, F.F. and Grossman, R.B., 1966. Morphological and genetic sequences  of carbonate accumulation in desert soils. Soil Sci., 101: 347--360.  Mulders, M.A., 1969. The arid soils of the Balikh basin (Syria). Thesis, State Univ., Utrecht,  197 pp.  Netterberg, F., 1969. The interpretation of some basic calcrete types. S. Afr. Archaeol.  Bull., 24: 117--122.  Parfenova, E.I. and Yarilova, E.A., 1972. Schemes of soil fabric components. In: Soil  Micromorphology. Proc. Int. Working-Meeting, Warsaw 1969. Polska Acad. Nauk,  Warsaw, pp. 39--55.  Ruellan, A., 1970. Contribution ~ la connaissance des sols des regions Mediterran~enes:  le sols ~ profil calcaire differenci~ de plains de la basse Moulouya (Moroc oriental).  Thesis, Strasbourg Univ., 482 pp.  Sehgal, J.L. and Stoops, G., 1972. Pedogenic calcite accumulation in arid and semi-arid  regions of the Indo-Gangetic alluvial plain of erstwhile Punjab (India). Their morphology  and origin. Geoderma, 8:59--72.  Stoops, G., 1980. Proposal for the micromorphological description of crystalline and micro-  crystalline minerals in soil thin sections. In press.  Wieder, M., 1977. Occurrence and genesis of carbonate nodules in soil. Ph.D. thesis, Hebrew  Univ., Jerusalem, 255 pp.  Wieder, M. and Yaalon, D.H., 1974. Effect of matrix composition on carbonate nodule  crystallization. Geoderma, 11 : 95--121.  Yaalon, D.H., 1976. Nodules in sediments. In: R.W. Fairbridge and J. Bourgeois (Editors),  Encyclopedia of Sedimentology. Acad. Press, pp. 303--304.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               AbstractCarbonate nodules often constitute the first stage of calcrete formation. Micromorphological analysis of carbonate nodules and nodular fabrics in different soil materials shows that their development is a function of several factors: nature of the host matrix (texture, porosity), carbonate and non-carbonate clay distribution, bulk density and the interactions among them. Different micromorphological stages, therefore, exist in different soil materials.In calcareous, medium-textured soil materials, the stages of nodule formation are related to the increase of the density of the nodule caused by the accumulation of microcalcites. In such a soil material the following stages occur: (1) microcalcites within the low-to-moderate density matrix; (2) microcalcites of moderate to high density and moderately dense, diffuse nodules; parallel calcans may occur; (3) microcalcites of high density with dense microcalcitic nodules. During these stages the amount of non-carbonate clay decreases but is homogeneously dispersed and disseminated with the microcalcites. In general, the size of microcalcites, 1–8 μm, is inversely related to the clay content.In non-calcareous, medium-to-fine textured soil materials, secondary carbonate precipitates in intrapedal and/or interpedal voids as large sparry crystals. Due to pedoturbation processes, the nodules thus formed are subjected to recrystallization, resulting in a microsparry pattern. The development stages are: (1) few calcans and crystal chambers; (2) crystic nodules mainly of sparry crystals and an increase of calcans and crystic chambers; (3) recrystallized nodules composed mainly of microspars.In coarse-grained materials, secondary carbonates precipitate directly in voids as sparry crystals and the resulting nodules are of the crystic type. The large crystals are often subjected to recrystallization.In partly calcareous, coarse-grained materials with additions of calcareous dust, particular micromorphological carbonate forms occur. In the C horizon, cutanic calciasepic fabric forms besides zones of crystic fabric which gradually become calciasepic in the B horizon and include the typical nodular forms of the calcareous medium-textured soil material, together with appreciable amounts of glaebular halos.The processes leading to the formation of these stages occur essentially without a significant biogenic influence. Where carbonate segregation occurs as rhizomorphs surrounding active roots, the fabric is always micritic even in coarse textural soil material. 