Geoderma, 29 (1983) 41-57  41  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam - Printed in The Netherlands    WEATHERING SEQUENCE OF SOILS FROM VOLCANIC ASH INVOLVING ALLOPHANE AND HALLOYSITE, NEW ZEALAND    R.L. PARFITT, M. RUSSELL and G.E. ORBELL    Soil Bureau, DSIR, Lower Hutt (New Zealand)    (Received December 8, 1981; accepted after revision June 8, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Parfitt, R.L., Russell, M. and Orbell, G.E., 1983. Weathering sequence of soils from vol-  canic ash involving allophane and halloysite, New Zealand. Geoderma, 29: 41-57.     The clay minerals in a series of soils from rhyolitic ash having the same stratigraphy but different leaching environments were estimated quantitatively by oxalate dissolution, infrared spectroscopy, differential thermal analysis, electron microscopy and X-ray diffraction.   Three soils were studied in detail. These were the Kereone soil (mean annual rainfall 1200 mm), the Ohaupo soil (1400 mm) and the Mairoa soil (2600 mm). The Kereone soil contained halloysite as the predominant clay mineral, whereas the Mairoa soil was mainly allophanic. The Ohaupo soil contained considerable amounts of both allophane and halloysite. Thus the allophane content of the soils increased as rainfall increased, reflecting a sequence of increased leaching.   The Si concentration in soil solution decreased as rainfall increased, also reflecting increasing leaching of the soils. At Mairoa Si is rapidly removed and allophane (AI/Si = 2/1) with monomeric silicate is formed, whereas at Kereone less leaching occurs, Si levels are higher and halloysite (Al/Si = 1/1) with polymeric silicate is formed.   At intermediate sites either allophane or halloysite may form. The often-reported situation of younger allophanic beds overlying older, &gt; 10,000 year halloysitic beds may not be due to allophane weathering to halloysite but may result from lower temperature and drier climate during the last glacial maximum between 10,000 and 26,000 years before present (BP).   A new weathering scheme for volcanic ash in New Zealand is presented.    INTRODUCTION    In soils derived from volcanic ash the weathering sequence: ash - allophane - halloysite which was first suggested by Fieldes (1955) in New Zealand appears to have been accepted in later review articles (Wada and Harward, 1974; Fieldes and Claridge, 1975). The evidence for this weathering sequence comes from observations in Chile, Japan and New Zealand that halloysite is found in older, usually buried, ashes (Fieldes and Claridge, 1975).  In more recent reviews, Wada (1977, 1980) has stated that "the formation    0016-7061/83/0000-0000/$03.00 983 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company  42    of hallosyite is favoured by a thick overburden which produces a silica-rich environment" and by a "stagnant moisture regime". Thus the transformation of allophane to halloysite is thought to occur when allophane reacts with a silica-rich soil solution (Saigusa et al., 1978). There is increasing evidence, however, that ash or some components of the ash may weather directly to halloysite. This evidence comes from electron microscopy where (1) spherical halloysite has been observed to form directly from glass (Dixon and McKee, 1974) and (2) halloysite with various micromorphological forms has been observed on plagioclase surfaces in ash-derived soils (Tazaki, 1979). These papers support earlier conclusions of Hay (1960) and Bates (1962).   Previous studies have involved ash layers at one location. In this study we have examined the mineralogy of the same ash layers at different locations and under differing weathering environments to test the hypothesis that ash may weather directly either to halloysite or to allophane and that both minerals persist for long periods of time in temperate regions.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Field sampling     Three representative sites, Kereone, Ohaupo and Mairoa, were carefully selected on the basis of considerable experience of mapping soils and tephras in the Hamilton region (Fig. 1) using field techniques pioneered by Pullar and others in New Zealand (Pullar and Birrell, 1973 ). Pullar and Birrell's Tirau site (Pullar and Birrell, 1973) was used as the main stratigraphic control site and key beds at the selected sampling sites were correlated to this standard using frequent field examinations of intermediate sites between the sampling sites and the Tirau control section (Fig. 2). There are two major tephra marker beds, the Rotoehu Ash and the Aokautere Ash (Fig. 2) (Pullar et al., 1973). The older Rotoehu Ash (42,000 years B.P.) was identified on the basis of stratigraphic position, coarse grain size relative to the under and overlying layers and by the presence of the distinctive amphibole, cummingtonite, identified at all sites. The younger marker bed, the Aokautere Ash (20,000 years B.P.) was also recognised by its stratigraphic position and its coarse grain size or colour relative to under and overlying beds: its tephric nature was confirmed by the presence of relatively unweathered coarse rhyolitic glass particles in the sand fraction.   Recent work (Lowe et al., 1980) indicates that during the last 15,000 years the landscape in the study area has received at least 12 thin distal airfall tephras which would form the parent material of the top 25 cm of these soils.   The sites were chosen where present isohyets cross tephra isopachs approximately at right angles so that the tephra stratigraphy remains relatively constant at each site (Fig. 2) with the rainfall being the major variant (Fig. 1). Co-variant with the rainfall gradient is an overall change in native vegetation  43    ~' i`nl -1  AUCKlANOv  ~, , Z- Il    HAMILTON,'  J  6HOTGNUA.  11111 \\    r __    WELLINGTON i,    :..  :~':~:::y..:,;.:.:20,000 year ash'.::::.  . , ~20cm iso..ach.. '.     ...  "",., ilton ` ::.: , ::.   ...... .. ~~KERnEON ata r ':  : ., ...  . Ham    '::: ':;v:       42 000 year ash   AUPO~Oambridga   ` isopachs    T RAU  ,     Lake ':  400   14 p0 Rotorua ~,':;     Rotorua-~ 200  Otorohanga  1400   cm    1600    :" MAIP    ' 100 cm - _   1    X20,000 year ash  isopachs    140    Ihsoo    Lake  Taupo    Mt Tongariro    Fig. 1. Map showing the Kereone, Ohaupo, Mairoa and Tirau sites; the isopachs (cm) for the Aokautere Ash (20,000 years BP) and the Rotoehu Ash (42,000 years BP), and the rainfall isohyets (mm).    from fern and scrub (Leptospermum sp.) with broadleaf/podocarp forest at the two drier sites to mixed broadleaf/podocarp forest at the wettest site. The climatic and vegetation history of the sites during the total period of the accumulation of the tephras is not known with certainty. All sites are present ly under perennial grass/fern vegetation and have been so for approximately 100 years.   The soils are all well drained and occur at interfluve positions in the landscape. The profiles are described in the Appendix.   The Kereone soil, an Andic Dystric Eutrochrept, occurs at an altitude of 93 m, mean annual rainfall 1200 mm, mean annual temperature 15C; the Ohaupo soil, an Entic Dystrandept is at an altitude of 60 m, mean annual rainfall 1400 mm, mean annual temperature 14C; and the Mairoa soil, a  44    Depth (cm)    270    Tirau    r,    - F;r&gt;t_:r :a    Ohaupo    r4_ her,w:uzkaaitu T,sh    Mairoa    14,?0 tl c&lt;t.     e,sh r  20,000 y-m_ f,I    i?,: - itotoc:iZU Ish     .. _ "Hamilton Ash"    c.42,000 ye,sr:: 1,:    Fig. 2. Correlation sections from Tirau to Kereone, Ohaupo and Mairoa soils.  45    Hydric Dystrandept is at an altitude of 400 m, mean annual rainfall 2600 mm, mean annual temperature 12C.   The results for the Tirau site were also included because the stratigraphy has been defined (Pullar and Birrell, 1973). The ash layers are thickest because this site is closer to the source of the ash.   Samples of 6 cm thickness were taken from each layer (see Tables III-VI), using a bulk density sampler, in Spring 1979. Samples were stored field moist in sealed polythene bags. The clay fraction (&lt; 2 , m) was extracted from the samples by gentle crushing and dispersing in water using an ultrasonic probe for 2 min and then centrifuging. To obtain an adequate yield the upper four samples from the Tirau and Ohaupo sites were dispersed at pH 10 using NaOH. The clay samples were stored as dilute suspensions.    Chemical analysis     Acid oxalate extractable Al, Si and Fe values were obtained on subsamples of 3 g moist soil shaken in the dark with 200 ml ammonium oxalate (0.2 M, pH 3.5) at 20 for 2 h. Pyrophosphate extracts were also obtained by shaking 2 g moist soil with 200 ml of 0.1 M sodium pyrophosphate solution overnight. For the clay fraction, suspensions containing about 20 mg clay were shaken in the dark with 40 ml of ammonium oxalate (0.2 M, pH 3.5) at 20C for 2 h. Pyrophosphate extractions of suspensions containing about 20 mg clay were performed by shaking overnight with 30 ml of sodium pyrophosphate solution (0.1 M). Al and Fe in the resulting solutions were determined by high-temperature flame emission and Si by atomic absorption using a Techtron AA5 spectrophotometer.   Soil solution was extracted immediately after a further sampling, from samples taken after autumn rain, in June 1981, by centrifuging 10 g moist soil at 5000 g for 30 min using double tubes, the solution passing through a 1 mm hole in the inner tube and being collected in the outer tube. The solutions contained some sediment which was removed after flocculation with "superfloc" and by further centrifugation. Sodium pyrophosphate was added as an ionization suppressant and Al, Si and Fe were determined as described above.   Carbon contents were determined by the induction furnace method and total elements by X-ray fluorescence.    Instrumental techniques     KBr discs for infrared spectroscopy were prepared using 1.0 mg air-dried sample and 200 mg KBr. Spectra were recorded between 200 and 4000 cm-' on a Pye Unicam SP 2000 spectrophotometer.   Differential thermal analysis was carried out on 150 dry samples (50 mg) using a Du Pont 900 Differential Thermal Analyser.   X-ray diffraction analyses of the acid-oxalate treated clay (&lt;2 pm) frac-  46    tions were carried out after drying the suspensions on glass slides at room temperature.   Electron micrographs were obtained with a transmission electron microscope.    Determination of allophane     The Al/Si ratio of the allophane at the Mairoa site was determined from the data in Table 1. Acid-oxalate reagent extracts Al and Fe humus complexes together with allophane and ferrihydrite but the A1 and Fe in the humus complexes can be estimated with pyrophosphate reagent (Parfitt and Henmi, 1982). When the Al in humus complexes is taken into account in calculating the Al/Si mole ratios (Table 1), they are somewhat lower but nevertheless close to a ratio of .2/1, the value obtained for allophane with a disordered imogolite structure (Parfitt and Henmi, 1980). Allophane with ratios close to 2/1 can be estimated in clay fractions from the infrared absorbance at 348 cm-' (Farmer et al., 1977) and from the Si extracted by    TABLE I    Dissolution analysis and estimation of allophane for &lt;2 Mm clay fractions  ------ - ---- - ---    Acid oxalate: Pyrophosphate:  A1 Sip, Fe Al Fe Alo Alo - Alp Allo  (%I (%) (%~ (%5 (%~  .___._ phane  Sio Sio (%)    (mole ratio)    Kereone soil  20,000 yr.ash 0.8 0.6 0.7 0.3 0.2 1.4 0.9 5  42,000 yr.ash 1.1 0.9 0.5 0.5 0.3 1.3 0.6 5  Ohaupo soil  20,000 yr.ash 8.8 5.8 2.1 0.5 nd 1.6 1.5 35  42,000 yr.ash 2.8 2.4 1.4 0.3 nd 1.2 1.1 15  Mairoa soil  20,000 yr.ash 21.9 10.7 5.1 4.3 0.7 2.1 1.7 80*'  42,000 yr.ash 18.1 8.7 5.7 2.6 0.5 2.2 1.8 75*'  Tirau soil  20,000 yr.ash  at 140 cm 11.9 8.3 1.1 0.8 nd 1.5 1.3 50  42,000 yr.ash  at 200 cm 4.3 4.2 2.2 0.5 0.2 1.1 0.7 25    *' Determined from oxalate dissolution and infrared absorbance, the values were 85 and 78%, respectively.  47    acid oxalate (Higashi and Ikeda, 1974; Parfitt and Henmi, 1982) and the results agree closely. The allophane content of soils can also be estimated from the A1 and Si extracted by acid oxalate (Russell et al., 1981).   The allophane at the other sites has Al/Si molar ratios between 2 and 1 and the percent allophane was estimated from acid-oxalate Al and Si values, using the imogolite and kaolinite structures as reference points for allophane Al/Si = 2/1 and 1/1, respectively (Parfitt et al., 1980).    Determination of other minerals     Halloysite was identified by X-ray diffraction and amounts were determined from the area of the DTA endotherm near 530C and imogolite, layer silicates and amorphous silica were estimated from electron microscopy. Layer silicates, amorphous silica and halloysite were more clearly seen by electron microscopy after removing allophane by acid-oxalate pretreatment.   Iron oxides were estimated from oxalate dissolution and electron microscopy; gibbsite was determined from the DTA endotherm at 275.    RESULTS     The allophane content of the &lt;2 gm fractions from the 20,000 and 42,000 year marker beds increases from the Kereone site to the Ohaupo site and again to the Mairoa site and there is a corresponding increase in rainfall from 1200 mm to 2600 mm (Table II). A similar trend is also observed for imogolite and iron oxides.   In the Ohaupo soil the allophane content decreases with depth whereas the halloysite content increases with depth (Table II) but at the Mairoa site the beds are largely allophanic and at the Kereone site the beds are predominantly halloysitic.   Other components of the clay fractions were estimated by difference (Table II). The layer silicate was a poorly defined 14 .A material and was present in trace amounts. It was probably derived from eolian additions (loess), the source being adjacent mudstones.   The Al and Si extracted by acid-oxalate and pyrophosphate have been used to estimate the Al/Si ratio of the allophane in the samples (Table I). The ratio is close to 2 at the Mairoa site, where the clay samples contain up to 80%o allophane, whereas the ratios are nearer to 1 at the Kereone site where the clay samples contain about 5% allophane and where significant amounts of halloysite are also present. Where the extractable A1 and Si values are low, as in the Kereone samples, there is considerable uncertainty in the Al/Si ratios because errors are compounded in the calculation. Nevertheless, the Al/Si ratios in the Kereone samples are markedly lower than those for the Mairoa samples.   The Al, Si and Fe extracted from the whole soil samples using acid-oxalate and pyrophosphate are given in Tables III-VI. The results indicate that the  48    TABLE 11    Estimation of the composition of the &lt; 2 Mm fractions of the 20,000 and 42,000 year marker ashes at different locations    Allophane Halloy- Other Imogolite Iron Gibbsite   (%o) site*' compo- (%) oxides (%)    (%) nents*2  (%)      (%)  Kereone soil  (1200 mm rainfall)  20,000 yr.ash 5 65*' &lt;30 nd  &lt;3 -:1  42,000 yr.ash 5 70*' &lt;25 nd  &lt;3 nd  Ohaupo soil  (1400 mm rainfall)  20,000 yr.ash 35 25 &lt;35 nd  &lt;5 1  42,000 yr.ash 15 60*4 &lt;20 nd  &lt;5 1.--2  Mairoa soil  (2600 mm rainfall)  20,000 yr.ash 80 nd &lt; 10 &lt; 5 &lt; 10  nd  42,000 yr.ash 70  1 11 10 &lt; 5 &lt; 10  nd  Tirau soil  (1270 mm rainfall)  20,000 yr.ash 50  5 &lt;40 &lt; 5  &lt; 5 nd  42,000 yr.ash 25 60*5 &lt; 10 &lt; 3  &lt; 5 -_ 0.1    *' Short tubes and spherules present. *2 These components include organic matter (up to 10% of clay fraction), layer silicates (possibly chlorite), amorphous silica. *' Ratio tubes/spherules = 5/1. "Ratio tubes/spherules = 2/1. *5 Ratio tubes/spherules = 1/3. nd = not detected.    Kereone soil, like the clay fractions described in Table II, contains considerable amounts of halloysite, whereas the Mairoa soil largely contains allophane (Al/Si = 2/1).   In the strongly leached Mairoa soil (Table III) the amount of allophane increases with depth, reaching 35% in the older Hamilton Ash beds (Fig. 2). The parent materials for the soil are a series of fine rhyolitic ashes together with some redistributed rhyolitic ash, thought to be loess from local sources. Traces of basaltic hornblende and augite in the loess layer indicate some additions of andesitic ash. The lowest allophane content occurs in the gritty surface layer which contains the 2000 year BP Taupo Pumice. The combination of hard rhyolitic Taupo material and the complexing of A1 with humus have probably prevented large amounts of allophane forming in this layer (Wada, 1980; Kirkman and McHardy, 1980).  49    TABLE III    Mairoa soil: oxalate and pyrophosphate dissolution, allophane content in soil, and bulk density; halloysite in clay fraction    Depth Layer Acid oxalate: Pyrophosphate: Allo- Halloy- Bulk  (cm) Al. Sio Feo Alp Fep Al,, - Alp phane site density   (%) (%) (%) (%) (%) Sio (%) (%) (g cm-')       (mole ratio)    0-18 Ash 3.4 0.7 2.8 2.5 2.4 1.4 5 &lt; 1 0.58  23-29 Ash 6.1 2.0 3.1 2.2 2.1 2.1 15 &lt; 1 0.54  46-52 Loess 8.4 3.5 2.6 1.4 0.4 2.1 26 &lt; 1 0.41  54-60 20,000 yr.   ash 7.9 3.5 2.0 1.1 0.1 2.0 26 &lt; 1 0.54  65-71 Paleosol 7.4 3.4 2.4 1.0 0.1 2.0 25 1 0.57  84-90 42,000 yr.   ash 7.1 3.4 3.2 0.8 0.1 1.9 25 1 0.62  98-104 Ash 9.9 4.7 3.5 1.2 0.1 1.9 35 &lt; 1 0.48     Sand mineralogy showed that the parent materials of the layers in the Mairoa soil were similar to those for the Ohaupo soil, confirming the field stratigraphy. At the Ohaupo section the amount of allophane decreases and halloysite increases with depth (Table IV) as has often been observed in ashderived.soils. The Al/Si ratio also decreases as the amount of allophane decreases. The Ohaupo soil has lower extractable Fe values (Table IV) than the Mairoa soil, possibly associated with the lower degree of leaching at the Ohaupo site.   At the weakly leached Kereone section, where sand mineralogy confirmed that the stratigraphy was similar to the other two sections, only small amounts of allophane were detected, the clay fraction being predominantly halloysite (Table V). It is difficult to determine low Al, Si and Fe values accurately and the Al/Si ratio may be subject to considerable error. Nevertheless, the layers between 40 and 100 cm appear to have Al/Si ratios close to 1.   The various layers in the Tirau soil give extractable Al, Si and Fe values (Table VI) similar to those for equivalent layers in the Ohaupo soil (Table IV). Being closer to the source of the ashes, the layers in the Tirau soil are considerably thicker than those for the other soils.   The bulk densities of the various layers are inversly related to their allophane contents (Tables III-VI).   The elemental composition of the 42,000 year marker bed was determined by X-ray fluorescence analysis and differences in composition were observed among the Mairoa, Ohaupo and Kereone sites. Total iron and titanium decreased from 6.7% to 4.2% and from 0.8%o to 0.5%, respectively, and silicon increased from 21.6% at Mairoa to 27.4% at Kereone. Similar results were obtained for the 20,000 year marker bed, reflecting the more strongly leached  50    TABLE IV    Ohaupo soil: oxalate and pyrophosphate dissolution, allophane content in soil, and bulk density; halloysite in clay fraction    Depth Layer Acid oxalate: Pyrophosphate: Allo- Halloy- Bulk  (cm) Al,, Si" Fe. Alp Fep Al,, - Alp phane site density    (%) (%) (%) (%) Sio (%) (%) (gcm ')       (mole ratio)    0-15 Ash 3.0 1.4 0.8 0.6 0.2 1.7 10  22-28 Ash 4.4 2.4 1.1 0.3 nd 1.8 18 8 0.66  40-46 Loess 4.1 2.2 1.0 0.3 nd 1.8 16 12 0.59  52-58 20,000 yr.   ash 3.6 2.2 1.0 0.3 nd 1.6 1-2 25 0.64  64-70 Paleosol 1.9 1.1 0.8 0.2 nd 1.6 7 45 0.73  78-84 Paleosol 0.9 0.6 0.7 0.1 nd 1.4 3 55 0.76  98-104 42,000 yr.  ash 1.4 1.0 0.7 0.1 nd 1.3 6 60  0.81  110-  116 Ash 0.5 0.4 0.8 0.1 nd 1.3 2 70 0.86    TABLE V    Kereone soil: oxalate and pyrophosphate dissolution, allophane content in soil, and bulk density; halloysite in clay fraction    Depth Layer Acid oxalate: Pyrophosphate: Allo- Halloy- Bulk  (cm) Al,) Sio Fe,, Alp Fep Al,,--Alp phane site density   (%) (%) (%) (%) (%)  Sio (%) (%) (g cm-.,)        (mole ratio)    0-24 Ash 0.62 0.06 0.60 0.24 0.16 6.6 0.5 -- 0.98  32-38 Loess 0.69 0.12 0.57 0.25 0.09 3.8 1 60 0.69  44-50 20,000 yr.    ash 0.52 0.41 0.43 0.15 0.10 0.9 2 65 0.82  60-66 Paleosol 0.40 0.23 0.42 0.11 0.08 1.3 1 65 0.94  90-96 42,000 yr.    ash 0.38 0.20 0.33 0.15 0.10 1.2 1 70 1.19  108   114 Ash 0.16 0.08 0.27 0.02 0.05 1.8 0.5 70 1.34    environment at Mairoa than at Kereone (Taylor, 1933; Wilson, 1980).   The analyses of the soil solution from the 20,000 and 42,000 year marker beds at Mairoa and Kereone are shown in Table V11. The results clearly show that the amount of silicon in the soil solution is greater at Kereone than at Mairoa and that the Al/Si ratio is larger at Mairoa than at Kereone. The results for the Ohaupo soil gave intermediate values.  51    TABLE VI    Tirau soil: oxalate and pyrophosphate dissolution, allophane content in soil, and bulk density; halloysite in clay fraction    Depth Layer Acid oxalate: Pyrophosphate: Allo- Halloy- Bulk  (cm) Al,, Sio Fe,, Alp Fep Alo - Alp phane site density   (%) (%) (%) (%) (%)  Sio (%) (%) (g cm-' )        (mole ratio)    0-18 Ash 3. 3 1. 3 0. 6 0. 7 0.17 2.1 8 1 0. 7 5  18-24 Ash 4.0 2.4 0.7 0.4 0.04 1.6 14 1 0.73  32-38 Ash 4.3 2.8 0.8 0.2 0.01 1.5 16 5 0.70  54--60 Ash 4.3 2.9 0.8 0.2 nd 1.5 17 10 0.70  77-83 Loess 2.7 2.0 0.7 0.2 0.01 1.3 11 15 0.77  100-106 Loess 2.5 1.8 0.5 0.2 nd 1.4 10 20 0.83  137-143 20,000   yr.ash 2.2 1.3 0.3 0.2 0.02 1.6 8 1 0.88  147-153 20,000   yr.ash 1.9 1.2 0.3 0.1 nd 1.6 7 5 0.90  170-176 Paleosol 0.5 0.3 0.6 0.04 0.07 1.7 2 75 1.07  188-194 Paleoso11.4 1.0 1.1 0.2 0.10 1.3 5 55 0.83  200-205 42,000   yr,ash 1.4 1.1 0.9 0.2 0.04 1.1 5 60 0.70  250-256 42,000   yr.ash 0.8 0.5 0.4 0.1 0.05 1.4 3 65 1.16  274-280 Ash 0.4 0.3 0.5 0.05 nd 1.4 1 60 0.96    TABLE VII    Analysis of soil solution extracted immediately after sampling in autumn 1981    Ash AI si Fe AI/Si    (gg cm-') (mg cm-') (ug cm-')  Mairoa 20,000 year ash  5  2  6 2.5   42,000 year ash  4  2  6 2.0  Ohaupo 20,000 year ash  6  6 14 1.0   42,000 year ash  4  8  6 0.5  Kereone 20,000 year ash 10  12  13 0.9   42,000 year ash  3 19  5  0.2    DISCUSSION     The results for the Mairoa, Ohaupo and Kereone soils, and in particular for the 20,000 and 42,000 year ash layers, show that for fine rhyolitic ash parent materials the allophane content increases and the halloysite content decreases with increasing rainfall and increasing leaching through the soil.  52     Using the Penman evapotranspiration model and assuming a plantavailable soil water store of 100 mm, the summer moisture deficit has been estimated for the three sites (Table VIII). These results have been calculated    TABLE VIII    Soil water regime for the leaching sequence of the three soils    Site Mean Winter Months of Potential Months of   annual rain- leaching leaching summer deficit   fall (mm) (rnm)   moisture       deficit (mm)  Kereone 1200 400  5 170 5  Ohaupo 1400 550  6 140  Mairoa 2600 1600 10    using recent data from the nearest Meteorological Stations (N.Z. Meteorological Service, 1979). The rainfall leaching through the soil has also been estimated (Table VIII) assuming no runoff occurs for these porous friable soils. The results indicate that leaching occurs in the Mairoa soil for 10 months of the year whereas the Ohaupo and Kereone soils are leached fro 5 to 6 months of the year. The strongly leached Mairoa soil does not normally show moisture deficits in the summer except in very dry years, whereas the Ohaupo and Kereone soils have summer moisture deficits for several months in normal years.   Although the climate has fluctuated over the last 42,000 years (Fleming, 1979, p. 80) it is reasonable to assume that the Mairoa site has been the wettest and most leached site and the Kereone site the driest and least leached site in this time period. Fleming (1979) has presented data which indicates that temperatures fluctuated from present-day temperatures to temperatures about 6C colder than at present. With air masses travelling to New Zealand across oceans about 6C colder than at present the amount of moisture available for precipitation would be expected to be somewhat lower than at present. Precipitation was controlled by westerly to northwesterly winds (Fleming, 1979) and the distribution would have been controlled by the same orographic effects throughout the last 42,000 years. Thus, the Mairoa plateau in the west of the study area would have always been wetter than the Kereone site in a rain shadow area to the east. The Ohaupo site occurs in an intermediate situation.   There may also have been changes in vegetation from scrub to forest due to changes in climate (Fleming, 1979) which would affect the leaching regime because of different interception losses (Jackson and Aldridge, 1973 ). These changes would have taken place over the whole region, however, and the leaching sequence from Mairoa through Ohaupo to Kereone has probably been present over the last 42,000 years.  53     The results in Table VII show that soil solution Si levels are lower in the Mairoa allophanic soil than in the halloysitic Kereone soil. Wada (1980) has suggested that Al is relatively immobile in volcanic ash soils compared with Si, the A1 being held by humus or forming allophane as it weathers from primary minerals. Although the results in Table VII show that Al is in fact present in soil solution the results indicate that the level of Si in soil solution is related to the Si content of allophane or halloysite in these soils. We suggest that when Si in soil solution is low as a result of strong leaching, as at Mairoa, the Al-rich allophane (Al/Si = 2/1) with monomeric silicate is formed, but when Si is removed only on a seasonal basis, as at the Kereone site, the Si in soil solution is significantly higher (Table VII) and the Si-rich halloysite (Al/Si = 1/1) with polymeric silicate is formed.   Allophane (Al/Si = 2/1) has a disordered imogolite structure (Parfitt and Henmi, 1980) and therefore it is not surprising that some imogolite is also formed in the Mairoa soil (Table II). Imogolite is less common than allophane in soils, however, and it requires a unique environment to form in large amounts (Wada, 1980).   Allophane with AI/Si molar ratios close to 1 are found in small amounts (0.5-2%) in the Kereone soil (Table V) and it is possible that either this allophane weathers to halloysite or it is formed together with halloysite in this less strongly leached environment.   At the Ohaupo site the halloysite content increases and the allophane content decreases with depth. This is also true for the Tirau site where the ash layers are thicker. These soils occur in intermediate environments where leaching is less marked than at the Mairoa site (Taylor, 1933) and where drying is not as frequent as at the Kereone site (Wilson, 1980; Table VIII). It is possible that halloysite at the Ohaupo and Tirau sites has formed in a zone which is enriched with Si as has been noted recently at Kaingaroa, New Zealand (McIntosh, 1980) and in Japan (Saigusa et al., 1978). The halloysite may, however, have formed at a time when rainfall was lower and when temperatures were colder. The results of Farmer et al. (1979) show that the equilibrium between halloysite and imogolite (and allophane with an imogolite structure) are controlled by temperature as well as concentration of Si in solution and our results are consistent with these data.   The amounts of allophane and halloysite in Ohaupo and Kereone soils differ considerably, although the soil water regimes are similar. The Kereone soil, having a moisture regime that is only slightly drier than the Ohaupo soil, is richer in halloysite and thus it appears that only a slight change in leaching regime or temperature is sufficient to alter the composition of these soils.   Birrell et al. (1977) have shown that similar soils have become predominant ly allophanic in more leached sites where the present rainfall is greater than 1600 mm. This is consistent with the leaching model where Si in soil solution is lowered by high rainfall and frequent leaching.   If Si in soil solution influences weathering, then plant roots which remove  54    Si will favour the formation of allophane (Al/Si = 2/1) or even gibbsite (Table 11) in root channels in these soils (Wada and Matsubara, 1968). Different vegetation (grassland, forest, scrub) will also influence the formation of allophane and halloysite because leaching regimes change with vegetation and this will cause local differences in soil solution.   On andesitic ash, which has a lower Si content than rhyolitic ash, allophane (Al/Si = 2/1) is the predominant clay mineral over a wide range of rainfalls, even in the oldest ash beds (Kirkman, 1980; Kirkman and McHardy, 1980; Russell et al., 1981), and halloysite is not common.   On the basis of our results and other recent work in New Zealand (Birrell et al., 1977; Parfitt and Henmi, 1980; McIntosh, 1980; Kirkman, 1981), the following weathering scheme for rhyolitic ash deposited between 2,000 and 100,000 years BP is suggested as a hypothesis which should be tested in future work. In this scheme mean annual rainfall is given as an indication of the leaching regime. If the scheme could be developed to take account of Si in soil solution, it would probably also apply to andesitic ash.    Imogolite + allophane (AI/Si = 2/1)    Halloysite    Increasing with  leaching of Si          Decreasing with  Allophane (AI/Si = 1/1)   leaching of Si    Gibbsite    Present in root        channels  800 1200 1600 2000 2400    Rainfall (mm)     This weathering scheme gives greater consideration to climate and parent materials than to time of weathering, suggested by Wada (1977, 1980). Nevertheless, time of weathering is also important. Older buried soils do tend to contain halloysite in less strongly leached environments and the level of Si in soil solution appears to be a very important factor governing allophane and halloyse formation in soils from volcanic ash.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS     The authors thank S. Robertson, B.K. Daly and J. Garnham, N.Z. Soil Bureau, for mineralogical examination of sand fractions and technical assistance, and we also thank J.H. Kirkman, Soil Science Department, Massey University, for kind assistance in obtaining electron micrographs of treated and untreated clay fractions. We also wish to thank LB. Campbell, G.J. Churchman, J.D.G. Milne and A.D. Wilson, N.Z. Soil Bureau, for helpful criticism of the manuscript.  55    REFERENCES    Bates, T.F., 1962. Halloysite and gibbsite formation in Hawaii. Clay and Clay Minerals. Proc. Ninth Nat. Conf. Clays Clay Miner., Monograph 11, Vol. 9, pp. 315-328.  Birrell, K.S., Pullar, W.A. and Searle, P.L., 1977. Weathering of Rotoehu Ash in the Bay of Plenty district. N.Z.J. Sci., 20: 303-310.  Dixon, J.B. and McKee, T.R., 1974. Spherical halloysite formation in a volcanic soil of Mexico. Trans. Int. Conf. Soil Sci., 10th, Moscow, VII, pp. 115-124.  Farmer, V.C., Fraser, A.R., Russell, J.D. and Yoshinaga, N., 1977. Recognition of imogolite structures in allophanic clays by infrared spectroscopy. Clay Miner., 12: 55-57.  Farmer, V.C., Smith, B.F.L. and Tait, J.M., 1979. The stability, free energy and heat of formation of imogolite. Clay Miner., 14: 103-107.  Fleming, C.A., 1979. The Geological History of New Zealand. Auckland University Press, Auckland, 141 pp.  Fieldes, M. and Claridge, G.G.C., 1975. Allophane. In: J.E. Gieseking (Editor), Soil Components, Vol. 2. Springer Verlag, New York, NY, 351-393.  Fieldes, M., 1955. Clay Mineralogy of New Zealand Soils. N.Z. J. Sci. Technol., B37: 336-350.  Hay, R.L., 1960. Rate of clay formation and mineral alteration in a 4.000 years ash soil of St. Vicent. Am. J. Sci., 258: 354-368.  Higashi, T. and Ikeda, H., 1974. Dissolution of allophane by acid oxalate solution. Clay Sci., 4: 205-211.  Jackson, R.J. and Aldridge, R., 1973. Interception of rainfall by kamahi at Taita, New Zealand. N.Z. J. Sci., 16: 573-590.  Kirkman, J.H., 1980. Clay mineralogy of a sequence of andesitic tephra beds in Western Taranaki, New Zealand. Clay Miner., 15: 157-163.  Kirkman, J.H., 1981. Morphology and structure of halloysite in New Zealand tephra. Clays Clay Miner., 29: 1-9.  Kirkman, J.H. and McHardy, N.J., 1980. A comparative study of the morphology, chemical composition and weathering of rhyolitic and andesitic glass. Clay Miner., 15: 165-173.  Lowe, D.J., Hogg, A.G., Green, J.D. and Boubee, J.A.T., 1980. Stratigraphy and chronology of late Quaternary tephras in Lake Maratoto, Hamilton, New Zealand. N.Z. J. Geol. Geophys., 23: 481-485.  McIntosh, P.D., 1980. Weathering products in Vitrandept profiles under pine and manuka, New Zealand. Geoderma, 24: 225-239.  New Zealand Meteorological Service, 1979. Rainfall parameters for stations in New Zealand and the Pacific Islands. Misc. Publ., 163.  Parfitt, R.L. and Henmi, T., 1980. Structure of some allophanes from New Zealand. Clays Clay Miner., 28: 285-294.  Parfitt, R.L. and Henmi, T., 1982. Methods for estimating the amount of allophane in soil clays formed from basalt and volcanic ash and in podzolised soils. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 28: 183-190.  Parfitt, R.L., Furkett, R.J. and Henmi, T., 1980. Identification and structure of two types of allophane from volcanic ash soils and tephra. Clays Clay Miner., 28: 328-334.  Pullar, W.A. and Birrell, K.S., 1973. Parent materials of Tirau silt loam. N.Z. J. Geol. Geophys., 16: 677-686.  Pullar, W.A., Birrell, K.S. and Heine, J.C., 1973. Named tephras and tephra formations occurring in the central North Island, with notes on derived soils and buried paleosols. N.Z. J. Geol. Geophys., 16: 497-518.  Russell, M., Parfitt, R.L. and Claridge, G.G.C., 1981. Estimation of the amounts of allophane and other minerals in the clay fraction of an Egmont loam profile and other volcanic ash soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 19: 185-195.  56    Saigusa, M., Shoji, S. and Kato, T., 1978. Origin and nature of halloysite in Ando soils from Towada Tephra, Japan. Geoderma, 20: 115-129.  Taylor, N.H., 1933. Soil processes in volcanic ash-beds. N.Z. J. Sci. Tech., 14: 338-352.  Tazaki, K., 1979. Micromorphology of halloysite produced by weathering of plagioclase in volcanic ash. In: M.M. Mortland and V.C. Farmer (Editors), International Clay Conference, 1978. Elsevier, Amsterdam, pp. 415-422.  Wada, K., 1977. Allophane and imogolite. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Weed (Editors), Minerals in Soil Environments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Madison, Wise., pp. 603-638.  Wada, K., 1980. Mineralogical characteristics of Andisols. In: B.K.G. Theng (Editor), Soils with Variable Charge. N.Z. Soc. Soil Sci., Lower Hutt, pp. 87-107.  Wada, K. and Harward, M.E., 1974. Amorphous clay constituents of soils. Adv. Agron., 26: 211-260.  Wilson, A.D., 1980. Soils of Piako County, North Island, New Zealand. N.Z. Soil Bur., N.Z. Soil Survey Rep., 39.    APPENDIX - PROFILE DESCRIPTIONS FOR KEREONE, OHAUPO AND MAIROA  SOILS    Kereone soil    Depth (cm)    0-24 5YR 2.5/1 gritty silt loam; very friable; moderate fine granular to strong    fine crumb structure; diffuse boundary,  24-30 5YR 3/4 and 5YR 2.5/2 silt loam; friable; weak medium nut structure;    distinct wavy boundary,  30--41 5YR 3/3 crushing to 7.5YR 4/4 very slightly gritty silt loam; slightly firm;    weak fine blocky structure, firm 1 cm rounded aggregates; few channels    filled with topsoil; many thin continuous 2.5YR 3/3 cutans; diffuse boundary  41--53 7.5YR 4/4 crushing to 7.5YR 5/6 heavy silt loam; slightly sticky, friable;    weak fine nut structure; many firm up to 2 cm rounded aggregates; few    very thin discontinuous cutans 5YR 4/4; abundant coarse pores; distinct    boundary.  53-75 7.5YR 4/4 clay loam; slightly firm; moderate medium and coarse blocky    structure; many coarse pores; very few fine manganese concretions; diffuse    boundary,  75-87 7.5YR 4/4 crushing to l0YR 5/6 heavy silt loam; slightly firm; moderate    coarse and fine blocky structure; abundant fine manganese concretions;    many coarse pores; cutans; diffuse boundary,  87-101 7.5YR 4/4 fine sandy loam; slightly firm; moderate coarse crumb structure;    coarse pores; many fine white lapilli; diffuse boundary,  101-108 7.5YR 4/4 sandy loam; slightly firm; near structureless; many coarse pores;    distinct boundary,  108+ 5YR 3/4 clay loam; firm; moderate medium nut structure; many discon    tinuous black manganese patches.   Ohaupo soil  Depth (cm)    0-15 10YR 3/2 fine sandy loam; very few soft brownish lapilli; very friable; strong granular and crumb structure; distinct boundary ,  57    15-36 7.5YR 4/4 silt loam; very friable; strong fine crumb structure; few medium    slightly firm rounded aggregates; root channels infilled with 7.5YR 3/2    silt; diffuse boundary;  36-50 7.5YR 3/4 silt loam; friable; strong fine crumb structure; many medium    coarse firm rounded aggregates; distinct boundary,  50-60 7.5YR 4/4 slippery silt loam; very friable; weak medium blocky structure;    coarse pores; distinct boundary,  60-74 7.5YR 3/4 heavy silt loam; firm; moderate medium fine blocky structure;    few pores; diffuse boundary,  74-90 7.5YR 4/4 very heavy silt loam; firm; weak medium fine blocky structure;    distinct boundary,  90-110 7.5YR 4/4 (70%) and lOYR 5/6 (30%) silt loam; very few coarse grits;    slightly firm; very weak fine blocky structure; many coarse pores; distinct    boundary,  110+ 5YR 3/4 clay loam; plastic; sticky; very firm; moderate medium block    structure.   Mairoa soil  Depth (cm)  0-18 7.5YR 3/2 gritty silt loam; slippery; very friable; strong medium granular    fine crumb structure; distinct wavy boundary,  18-33 5YR 3/4 crushes to 7.5YR 5/6 slippery silt loam; friable; moderate medium    and fine blocky structure; many brittle peds; many roots; diffuse wavy    boundary,  33-46 7.5YR 4/6 crushes to 7.5YR 5/6 slippery and slightly sticky silt loam;    friable; weak medium blocky structure; peds brittle; many coarse pores;    many distinct 2 cm rounded aggregates; diffuse boundary,  46-53 as above but less developed structure; more aggregates; diffuse boundary,  53-60 10YR 4/6, 5/6 and 6/4 fine sandy loam; slippery; firm; near massive;    abundant coarse pores; many fine 5YR 3/3 mottles; many thin 5YR 4/4    coatings on crack faces; few fine yellowish aggregates; distinct wavy    boundary,  60-77 7.5YR 4/4 slightly slippery heavy silt loam; firm; moderate medium and    fine blocky structure; many coarse pores; distinct stains down root channels;    diffuse boundary,  77-81 as above but with many fine block nodules; distinct boundary,  81-94 7.5YR 4/4 fine sandy loam; slippery; many fine 7.5YR 5/2 patches; few    distinct 2.5YR 2.5/4 iron plates; many shining sand grains; firm; near    massive; weak coarse blocky structure; few coarse pores; near continuous    1 cm iron pan near base of horizon; distinct boundary,  94+ 7.5YR 4/6 crushing to 7.5YR 5/8 clay loam; non plastic; non sticky; firm;    weak to moderate medium blocky structure; few near 2.5YR 2.5/4 stains    on structure faces; very few coarse pores.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractThe clay minerals in a series of soils from rhyolitic ash having the same stratigraphy but different leaching environments were estimated quantitatively by oxalate dissolution, infrared spectroscopy, differential thermal analysis, electron microscopy and X-ray diffraction.Three soils were studied in detail. These were the Kereone soil (mean annual rainfall 1200 mm), the Ohaupo soil (1400 mm) and the Mairoa soil (2600 mm). The Kereone soil contained halloysite as the predominant clay mineral, whereas the Mairoa soil was mainly allophanic. The Ohaupo soil contained considerable amounts of both allophane and halloysite. Thus the allophane content of the soils increased as rainfall increased, reflecting a sequence of increased l leaching.The Si concentration in soil solution decreased as rainfall increased, also reflecting increasing leaching of the soils. At Mairoa Si is rapidly removed and allophane (Al/Si = 21) with monomeric silicate is formed, whereas at Kereone less leaching occurs, Si levels are higher and halloysite (Al/Si = 11) with polymeric silicate is formed.At intermediate sites either allophane or halloysite may form. The often-reported situation of younger allophanic beds overlying older, &gt; 10,000 year halloysitic beds may not be due to allophane weathering to halloysite but may result from lower temperature and drier climate during the last glacial maximum between 10,000 and 26,000 years before present (BP).A new weathering scheme for volcanic ash in New Zealand is presented.