Geoderma, 33 (1984) 191--218                                                     191  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    QUANTITATIVE RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN MORPHOLOGY AND  CURRENT SOIL HYDROLOGY IN SOME ALFISOLS IN SEMIARID  TROPICAL AUSTRALIA    ROSS J. COVENTRY and JOHN WILLIAMS  Division of Soils, CSIRO, Private Mail Bag, P.O. Aitkenvale, Townsville, Queensland 4814  (Australia)  (Received August 22, 1983; revised version accepted January 23, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Coventry, R.J. and Williams, J., 1984. Quantitative relationships between morphology  and current soil hydrology in some Alfisols in semiarid tropical Australia. Geoderma,  33: 191--218.    The shallow groundwater hydrology of a sequence of red, yellow, and grey earths  (Paleustalfs, Plinthustalfs and Ochraqualfs of "Soil Taxonomy") was monitored over a  9-year period (1973--1982) along a drilled transect of 30 boreholes near Torrens Creek,  in northeastern Australia. Climatic analysis shows an aridic soil moisture regime under  which soil water surpluses should not occur, and thus significant hydromorphism would  not be expected in the soils. The present study has demonstrated, however, that profile  saturation and groundwater tables may be expected to develop at various depths in the  soils as often as 1 year in 3. Besides, strong linear relationships were found between a  number of morphological features of the soils and various hydrological regimes currently  active in the profiles: the depths to the upper limits of brown, brownish red, or red  mottles, to the upper limit of ironstone gravels, and to the maximum content of clay are  all most closely related to the mean position of the shallowest water tables observed; the  depths to grey mottles and to mottles with chromas of two or less are most directly re-  lated to the depths at which the soils are saturated for 5 weeks; the depth to the maxi-  mum content of ironstone gravels and to the base of the solum are most closely associ-  ated with the depth at which the soils are saturated for 10 to 15 weeks; and dominantly  grey colours in the strongly mottled subsola are best related to profile saturations for at  least 21 weeks. The results indicate that the gtey features present in the soil profiles could  have developed, at least in part, in response to the current soil hydrological regime.    INTRODUCTION    Experienced field pedologists invariably develop empirical relationships to  explain associations between soil profile morphological characteristics and  inferred, causative pedological processes. Over the years, these ideas have  evolved into a body of conventional pedological experience that, although  seldom underpinned by rigorous quantitative analysis, has been found to  work in the interpretation of soil features in a variety of environments. An    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    192    example of "pedological experience" of widespread application is the know-  ledge that, all else being equal, red soils will usually occupy better drained  sites than yellow soils (Soil Survey Staff, 1951, p. 190). Another example is  the knowledge that the occurrence of mottles with chromas of two or less in  the soil profile imply saturation at that depth for some unspecified period  throughout the year (Soil Survey Staff, 1975, pp. 48--49).  These examples highlight the qualitative nature of many aspects of our  current understanding of the hydrological significance of a variety of mor-  phological features in soil profiles. Field workers in the temperate zone in  North America (e.g., Daniels et al., 1970, 1971, 1973; Simonson and Boers-  ma, 1972; Richardson and Hole, 1979; Veneman and Bodine, 1982), and in  Europe (e.g., Van Heesen, 1970; Van Wallenburg, 1973; Moore, 1974), have  attempted to define quantitatively the soil moisture regimes that have pro-  duced certain hydromorphic soil profile features such as specific mottle  colours or patterns. The processes of mottle genesis have also been studied in  the laboratory (e.g., McKeague, 1965; Veneman et al., 1976; Vepraskas and  Bouma, 1976).  This paper seeks to quantify the depths and durations of soil profile satura-  tions that are associated with a range of morphological features in a sequence  of soils from semiarid tropical Australia. The study has been prompted by  field observations and the results of analyses of long-term rainfall records  indicating that profile saturation and groundwater tables may be expected to  develop within the solum as often as once every 3 years. An attempt will be  made to demonstrate some quantitative relationships between various soil  morphological features and the hydrological regimes currently prevailing in  the soils.    STUDY AREA AND METHODS    Regional setting    Red, yellow, and grey earths (Stace et al., 1968) are widespread soils  throughout northern Australia and mantle some 34 Mha or 37% of tropical  Queensland (Isbell and Smith, 1976). Since 1973, we have made detailed  studies of the pedology and hydrology of such soils in the Torrens Creek  area (145lYE 203'S) which lies 250--300 km southwest of Townsville  in central north Queensland (Fig. 1}. The soils are characterised by non-  calcareous profiles, massive structure, earthy fabric, mineralogy dominated  by quartz, kaolin, and iron oxides and hydroxides, low natural fertility, and  gradual texture changes through the sola of most profiles. The soils in the  vicinity of Torrens Creek have been mapped at the soil family taxonomic  level by Coventry and Fett (1982), and some of the factors controlling their  distribution patterns have been discussed previously (Coventry, 1979a,  1982). An aridic soil moisture regime prevails (Isbell and Williams, 1981)  but, because of their hard-setting surface soils and the nature of their diag-    ~]           (a) ANNUAL  RAINFALL                                                     (b)  RED, YELLOW, AND  I~         (Median; rnm)                                                                      GREY  EARTHS  LOCALITY MAF  ~                                      I  i: '  -  i     . . "   ." "      Townsville                                                                        Townsville                                            41                      Chits  !  ~   "  .........  i  .........  :" "  ]  .......................  %",    193    Fig. 1. a. Location of the Torrens Creek area with respect to the annual rainfall over  Queensland (median for all years of record (ram) to 1973). Data from Commonw. Aust.,  Bur. Meteorol. (1977).  b. Distribution of red, yellow, and grey earths in Queensland (from Stace et al., 1968).    nostic horizons, most of the soils are classified as Alfisols and only a few as  Oxisols or Aridisols (Soil Survey Staff, 1975).  The study area lies in a landscape of subdued relief with slopes generally  less than 3.5%. Extensive undissected plains, lacking integrated stream chan-  nel systems, are underlain by a gently dipping sequence of coarse-grained  sandstones and some mudstones. The rocks of Permian to Jurassic age have  been exposed since the Late Mesozoic to weathering and erosion and have  yielded a widespread mantle of Late Cainozoic sediments up to 120 m thick  (Coventry, 1979a).  In general, yellow and grey earths (0.4--2.5 m deep), many with strongly  developed mottles and ironstone gravels, have formed in the erosional parts  of the landscape on broad low ridges where weathered bedrock lies close to  the surface. Red earths with much thicker sola (3--20+ m) have formed in  the lower, depositional parts of the landscape in wide drainage lines where  thick alluvial sequences have accumulated. Current evidence suggests that  many of the soils of the area are relict features (Gunn, 1967; Isbell and  Smith, 1976), and many developed during the Late Tertiary or Early Quater-  nary (Coventry, 1979a,b; Coventry et al., 1980). The soils now support  woodlands and low open woodlands dominated by Eucalyptus and/or Acacia  species.    194    The soil sequence    The sequence of 30 profiles of this study is located along an easterly-  facing midslope site, 19 km east of Torrens Creek. The soil distribution pat-  terns and topography of the landscape adjacent to the drilled transect (part  of 'Transect MTE') are shown in fig. 2 of Coventry (1982). Yellow earths,  gravelly grey earths, and loamy grey earths (some of which grade laterally  into lateritic or gleyed podzolic soils (Stace et al., 1968), all lie upslope of  much deeper red earths (Fig. 2a) that are known from nearby boreholes to  extend as red sandy clays to below 20 m (Coventry, 1982). The main char-  acteristics of each soil group on the transect are summarised in descriptions  of representative soil profiles (Table I). Lateral differences along the transect  in the depths to the morphological features analysed in this paper (mottles  of different colours, ferruginous gravels, the top of the B2 horizon, the base  of the solum, and the maximum clay content) are shown in Figs. 2b,c; mean  depths to these features in each great soil group are listed in Table II. De-  tailed descriptions are available on request of the 30 profiles studied, of  particle-size analyses for 15 of them, of the groundwater observation wells  installed along the transect, and of our water level observations (CSIRO  Aust., Div. Soils, Tech. Mem. 34/1977, 6/1979, and 10/1983). Throughout  this paper the soil colour group names of Coventry and Robinson (1981) are  used.    Climate    The climate of the study area is semiarid tropical. It is warm and dry in  winter, and hot and intermittently wet in summer. Weekly rainfall data for  a 3-year period (1945--1974) from Pentland, 50 km east of the study area,  were analysed by the method of McCown (1981) to define the onset and  cessation of the dry and "green" or wet seasons for each year. The mean    Fig. 2. Pedological and hydrological characteristics of the 30 described profiles along the  studied transect. Data from CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils, Tech. Mem., 10/1983 and 14/1983.  a. Topography and soil groups. Topography of the transect, the locations of great soil  groups (Stace et al., 1968), and representative profiles (A--H; see Table I). The locations  of all 30 profiles of this study are indicated by the short lines projecting above the ground  surface.  b. Mottle distributions. Depths to the upper limits of brown, brownish red, or red  mottles, of mottles with chromas of 2 or less, and of dominantly grey colours in profiles  along the transect.  c. B horizons and ferruginous gravels. Depths to upper boundaries of the B~ horizons, to  the lower boundaries of the sola, and to the upper limits of ferruginous gravels (ironstone  gravels and clay nodules).  d. Hydrological regimes. Mean depths to the shallowest water tables observed and mean  depths at which the profiles were saturated for 5, 10, 15 and 21 weeks (i.e., 10%, 20%,  30% and 40% of the year). The depths in each observation well are averaged over the  three periods when water tables were observed.    195    (a)  THE SOIL GROUPS              ~  Red earth  ~  Yellow earth  0      A    Grey , , o  00 : B  O*  , r  0    ;'', ~ / /-~, / , ~L.   ^           I: :" : : " :J  Red / yellow earth   /o   h\  g  *  o                  ~   /         L.,                              -               ~L~I~,/'1~' ~'~'~-~             ,ntergrade so,Is  oo o  o-I Oo '~,1,',  ,~o ~,  .          r~  o./~oo$,,A~/  ~,_%l:~~u  o  {j     oo |  ~ o           i/      /  o o oOZ.oo:5,-,l,/ ~o1~O. ~2-/,&gt;;5)~-,,,,,-~..~. q,  D 0  ~ 0~        I/   /I                        ii/I  I//////                       I  I                 I                      /                      "    o  .~&gt;11 "i~/lll., ~/.~.'.'.:.1.'~1.~  ".\..,  "r t L(" \  /                                  ~;" " "'/"/" " / ~ ~ / "5'-"-:1;;&lt;~'1\ \ \ ~ ,' \t  3 I-                                          "/"," ",'/ ~ ~ ~'~-.:."l:~J\\ \\  "~ 2                                                               /1// /          \\\ \  "   x\t      V/H = 20/1  ' V                                                       ",~.":~2" ~'" \ ", "\ \ -~  /                                                                      ~:.'::'-'.&lt; ~ \ \ \, ",\    I  X  \ "  \\  \\  \x  _X  \\    100 metres                                                   ~\ \ \ \ \\i', "  \\\ \ ",i-  x  \\I\\  \,  \1\\=  #    (b)    MOTTLE  DISTRIBUTIONS           B  %                        L                                                      ~  ~-    ..............  Upper limit of brown, brownish red, or red mottles         "~-           o    ................  Upper limit of grey mottles  o  = o o o o o o o o o o o o o   Upper limit of mottles with chromas of two or less  Upper limit of dominantly grey colours in the soil matrix    196    (C)    B  HORIZONS AND FERRUGINOUS GRAVELS    ~C  \                            E  \  /  Maximum content of clay                              \              o~  \                 oo \~ \\i/"---\    ...........  Upper boundary of B2 horizon  \  Lower boundary of solum                                               \\      Upper limit of ironstone gravels    o o o o o o o o  Upper limit of clay nodules    (d)    HYDROLOGICAL  REGIMES    SWT    A  "]'-..   g    15--~~  ........  I  I  L                  -    C    \ _.\ "~ ....~'~    Mean depth of shallowest water tables observed    5  ......  Soils saturated for  5 weeks    10 -- Soils saturated for 10 weeks    1 5 ---- -- Soils saturated for 1 5 weeks    21  .....  Soils saturated for 21 weeks    D    \  \    \ \  \\  21 \1~!    L    Fig. 2, c and d (legend p. 194)    197    time of the onset of the wet season was found to be in week 47 (i.e., Nov.  20--26; standard weeks as defined by Keig and McAlpine, 1969), and the  onset of the dry season to be in week 21 (i.e., May 21--27). Therefore, in  order to simplify the use of long-term montly rainfall data in this study,  the wet season is taken as December to May, and the dry season as June to  November inclusive; annual totals are calculated for the period June to May.  The rainfall distribution is both strongly seasonal and highly variable: 80%  of the mean annual total of 585 mm at Torrens Creek, and 84% of the  707 mm at Pentland falls in the wet season. This rain comes in both localised  heavy falls of short duration (we have recorded peak 1-min intensities in  thunderstorms of up to the equivalent of 480 mm/hr) and in widespread falls  of low intensity.  The 1973--1982 rainfalls include a broad range of the long-term seasonal  and annual totals recorded at Torrens Creek (Fig. 3a). Thus our observations  have not been restricted to years with atypical rainfall distributions, and our  interpretations based on these data should be valid for the long-term climatic  conditions in the area.  The only available temperature and evaporation data are from Charters  Towers, 150 km to the east, and from Hughenden, 100 km to the west (Fig.  1; Burdekin Project Committee, 1976}. Monthly average maximum tempera-  tures range from 25 to 36, and monthly average minima from 9.5 to  21. Although about 150 days per year can be expected to have tempera-  tures greater than 32, several light frosts occur in most winters. A mean  Australian Tank evaporation of 2150 mm, and a mean annual evapotranspi-  ration  of 500--600 mm are probable over the area (Commonwealth of  Australia, Bureau of Meteorology, 1970).  There is no month in the year when the mean rainfall exceeds the poten-  tial evapotranspiration estimated by the methods of Thornthwaite and  Mather (1957). A conventional.interpretation implies that a water surplus  in the soil profile would not, therefore, occur. Such an analysis, however,  does not consider the temporal distribution and seasonal variability of the  rainfall, both of which in the Torrens Creek environment contribute to im-  portant water recharging conditions in the profile.  A weekly water balance model (computer program WATBAL; Keig and  McAlpine, 1974; McCown, 1981), which employs actual rainfall and long-  term mean evaporation data, was used to calculate the water content of  the soil profile store and the excess to that store for Torrens Creek over the  period 1974--1981. A soil store of 100 mm used in this analysis corresponds  to the water retained between -1500 Kpa and -10 Kpa to a depth of 130  cm and approximates the profile water store of the shallower profiles of the  transect. Complete recharging of the soil profile occurs briefly in most wet  seasons, and in some years, a water excess or saturated conditions can be  expected to persist in the profile (CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils, Tech. Mem. 9/  1983). Variations in rainfall and the computed relative water content of the  soil store for two of these wet periods that produced water tables in the    TABLE I  Morphological characteristics of representative profiles on transect MTE (the profiles are located in Fig. 2a)    (]0    Horizon        Matrix           Mottle  Mottle  Mottle     Field    pH      Gravel  colour            abun-   size      colour      texture  (moist)           dance             (moist)                        kind    Particle-size  (wt.% of fine earth)  amount  (wt.%   c. sand  f. sand  silt  of whole(2--0.2  (0.2--   (0.02--  soil)     ram)     0.02     0.002  ram)    ram)    clay  ( &lt;- 0.002  mm)    Profile A: Plinthustalf; grey earth: Gn 2.42; Burra soil family  0--I0 A,    10 YR 4/3     --             --        (g) SL  6.1     I  10--20A,/B,  10YR4/3  ......  (g)SL  6.1     I  20--30 B,    10 YR 5/4     --     --     --        (g) SCL 6.3    I  30--60 Bn   I0 YR 3.5/6    --     -     --        gCL (Sy)6.3    Q, I  60--90 B~:    10 YR 3.5/6     f        f--c     10 R 3/6   g SC    6.5      Q, I  425*    5    37    43    S     12  8       35       42       7        16  6       36       36       7        21  65    31    32    7     30  64       29       21       6        44    Profile B." Paleustalf yellow earth: Gn 2.6 l : Boston soil [amily    0--10 Au    10 YR 4/2.5     --       -       --          SL      6.1      Q  10--20 A,2    10 YR 5.5/3     -       --                   SL      5.7      Q  20--30A~     10YR5/5                --       --          (g) SCL 6.1      Q,I  30--70 B,     10 YR 5/6       f        f        7.5 YR 5/8 gCL    6.3      I  70--90 Bn     10 YR 5/6       f        m--c    7.5 YR5/8 gCL    6.3      I  90--180B.~   10YR5/2        m       m--c    2.5YR3/5 gCL    6.5      I,Q  180--270 B,    10 YR 6/1       m       m       7.5 YR5/8 ~SC    6.3      I,Q  2.5 YR 3/5  270--330 C     10 YR 6/1        m       m       5 YR 5/8   (g) CL   6.2      Q  2.5 YR 3/6    3    35    43    6     16  2    33    4O    6     21  4       30       38       8        24  10       29       32       6        33  57       32       28       5        35  37       39       23       6        32  37       34       19       6        41  5    42    24    6     28    Pro fib! C" Oehraqualf; grey earth 'gleyed podzolic Dy 3.8'2, Bungarec soil famil3  0--20A,     10YR 3/1       f       f       7.5YR5/6 SL      5.9      -  20--45 A2     10YR4.5/1      f         f        7.5YR5/6 LS      6.2  45--120B~,    10YR 5.5/1      m        m--f     7.5YR5/8  (g)MC   6.3      Q,I  5 Y RR 5/6  120--165 B2,   10YR5.5/1     m      m--f    5 YR5/6  gLC    6.6     Q,I  2.5 YR4/7    1     35    47    ~     10  -:.1       37       50       7          6      30    '27    5     38    14    36    24    7     33    165--180B,   10YR5.5/1    m     m--f   5 YR5/6  gCL(Sy)6.8    I,Q    25     38     25     7      30  180--272C     7.5 YR4/7    m     m--f   5 YR5/8  gCL(Sy)6.7    Q,I    46     23     23     7      34  10 YR 6/1    Profde D: Paleustalf; yellow earth; Gn 2.62; Boston soil family    0--I0 A,     10 YR 3/2       --       --       --          SL      6.3     --       &lt;1      35      38      11      16  10--20A,/A3  10YR4.5/4     --       --       --          SL      5.8      --       &lt;1      34      40      10      16  20--30 A~     10 YR 4.5/3     --       --       --          SL      6.1      --       &lt;1      38      34      10      18  30--60 B,     10 YR 5/7       --       --       --          SCL     5.8      --       &lt;I      32      35      10      23  60--150B,,   10YR5/7      m      f--c    7.5YR5/7 CL(Sy) 6.5     I        2     30     26      9     35  2.5YR3/6  150--210B77   10YR5/4       m       f~    10YR5/2  SC      7.4      I         2      25      25      11      39  2.5YR3/6  210--270 B~    10 YR 5/2       m       f--c    10 YR 5/4  (g)CL   6.8      I         8      30      26      10      34  2.5YR4/8  270--350C,    10YR5/2       m       m--c   10YR5/8  (g)SCL  7.0      I         5      37      31       10      22  2.5YR4/8  350--450 C2      2.5 YR 6/3      m       m--c    7.5YR 5/8 gCL     7.3      I         15       38       25        9       28  2.5 YR 4/8  450--465 R      2.5 YR 3/5     c        m--c   10YR6.5/1 gSL     7.5      Q       20      59      21        5      15  7.5YR5/6    Profile H: Paleustalf; red earth; Gn 2.11; Pentland soil family    0--10 A,     2.5 YR 3/6    --     --     --        SCL   6.9    Q       1     31     37     10     22  10--20 Bt    10 R 3/6       --     --     --        CL(Sy) 6.4    Q     &lt; 1     31     34      9     26  20---90 B2,    I0 R 3/6         --       --       --          SC      6.7      --       &lt; 1      27      31        8      34  90--240B2~   10R 3/6         --       --       --          MC(Sy) 6.6      C       ~1      22      25        6      48  240--450B,3   IOR3/6         --       --       --          MC(Sy) 6.4      C       &lt;1      25      22        7      46  450--491B24  10R3/6       f      c      7.5YR5/8 MC(Sy) 6.6     C      &lt;1     25     24      9     42  1910"    *Continuous spiral auger holes were drilled to 425 cm at profile A and to 1910 cm at profile H; strongly disturbed samples recovered  from below 90 cm and 491 cm, respectively, are from imprecisely known depths and profile descriptions could not be made from  them.  Soil classification: Soil Taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975); Australian great soil group (Stace et al., 1968); principal profile form  (Northcote, 1979); soil family (Coventry and Fett, 1982).  Soil nomenclature is that of Soil Survey Staff (1975); field textures were determined by manipulation of moist soil (Northcote, 1979).  Colours are Munsell codes for moist soil. Mottle abundances: f = few; c = common; m = many. Mottle sizes: f = fine (&lt;5 mm); m =  medium (5--15 ram); c = coarse (&gt;15 mm).  Dominant composition of the gravel fraction: I = ironstone; Q = quartz and/or siliceous rock fragments; C = clay nodules (Isbell and  Smith, 1976).    o      TABLE II  Mean depth (~; cm), standard deviation (S.D.), and sample size (n) of various soil profile morphological features in the 30 profiles com-  prising the three great soil groups studied  (Data are from CSIRO Aust., Div. Soil, Tech. Mem., 10/1983)    Morphological            Grey earth                Yellow earth              Intergrade soils           Red earths  feature                   (9 profiles)               (14 profiles)              (2 profiles)               (5 profiles)            S.D.     n               S.D.     n        ~        S.D.     n        ~        S.D.     n    Upper limit of brown,      43.9   16.3    9         41.1    18.5   14       95     77.5    2        355.0   43.7    5  brownish red, or red  mottles  Upper limit of grey         69.3   28.5    7        166.2   100.4   13      255.0   21.2    2        350.0   85.9    4  mottles  Upper limit of mottles     55.7   16.6    7        204.5    92.4   10      295.0   77.8    2        350.0   74.4    4  with chromas &lt; 2  Upper limit of domi-      186.7   23.1    3       263.8    89.9    8      470.0     --     1        &gt;526.1          5  nantly grey colours in  subsola  Upper limit of ironstone   87.2   36.1    9         90.4    54.2   14      135.0   21.2    2       215.0   49.5    2  gravels  Maximum content of     135.0   56.1    5        127.1    45.7    7      255.0     --     1        475.0     --     ]  ironstone gravels  Upper boundary of the     47.2   11.8    9         40.0    13.4   14       80.0   56.6    2         52.0   40.9    5  B2 horizon  Maximum content of       60.0   22.4    5        103.6    50.4    7      195.0     -     1        225.0   84.9    2  clay in the whole soil    Base of the solum         160.7   30.6    7        190.8    80.5   13      405.0    7.1    2       &gt;414*2          4  ,1 None of the five red earth profiles examined in the field to a mean depth of 526 cm displayed dominantly grey colours in the soil  matrix.  *~ Base of the solum was not intersected in one 491 cm deep profile.    201    100    8   75  g  Q-  ~ 50  u_  ~ 2s    0  0    lOOO  900  8o0  E  E E 700   600   500  400  300  2O0    (a)    1975/76 J~'1973/74  1980/81 k  1976/77~, ~["    _             1981/82 ,~,~                  1978/79 ~1  'iL  i  -        1974/75--.,.        II  _          ;/ ,I  -       [i  !    It  1977/78         I      II  -  ',    ,,  , 4"V, V, VL  ,rl  ~  i  I  ,  500                     1000  Annual Rainfall (June-May; mm)    Median = 490 mm    III  1500    o    I  I    57 - year median rainfall: wet season (430 mm)  dry season (91 mm)  I I  Season :  Dry   Wet    00     ,i !,,I  !   i       |   |  Year:  ~    ~'    ~'    ~    r--    ~mr"    ~    @  Fig. 3. Rainfall data from Torrens Creek (CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils, TecJa. Mere., 9/1983).  a. Cumulative frequency distribution of annual rainfall (June--May) calculated from 57  years' record (1925--1982) at Torrens Creek. The solid vertical arrows indicate annual  rainfall in years when groundwater tables were observed. The broken vertical arrows in-  dicate annual rainfall in years when groundwater tables did not occur.  b. Wet season (December--May) and dry season (June--November) rainfalls at Torrens  Creek for the period of our study. Groundwater tables were observed in years when the  dry-season rainfall exceeded the median and was followed by a wet season of above  median rainfall. This sequence of seasons is indicated by an asterisk.    studied soils are illustrated in Fig. 4. The appearance of free water in soils of  the transect is clearly related to the recharge of the soil water store. Such  estimates of the water content of the soil profile water store provide a single  integrated measure of climate for a specific location. The semiarid tropical  climate of the Torrens Creek area produces long periods with very dry soil  profiles interspersed with much shorter wet periods with saturated soil con-  ditions.    202  (a)  o    100    E- 200  E  ~ 300  E 4oo    500    600    150    E  v lOO  .-g  "5  _~ so    No  water  tables  occurred  in 1979  prior to  week 11    Weeks from January 1, 1979  o        10        20        30  i i i  []1 I I  I'  i     i-,,.~-Qbservation  A    ~  D. \ "'...   "N   %    \  --          \   " \\  E  '\        A  X                 ,,B  "\  "\              D    I  Dry   i                              I  Dry  SeasonlI         Wet  Season         t  Season  I  ~'''I  ....  I~   ''~'I''''I  ....  I'-'~"I ' ' ~ ' I ' ' ' '  40            50               10            20  Weeks, 1978              Weeks, 1979    100    Relative  water  50 content  of the  soil store  (percent)    0  30    Soil hydrology    Shallow groundwater tables were observed in the soils along the transect  during and after the wet seasons of 1973/74, 1975/76, 1978/79, and 1980/  81. Previous work in the study area, based on recording free water levels in  observation wells, measurements with a neutron moisture meter, and piezo-  meter readings (Williams and Coventry, 1979, 1981), has shown that in wet  seasons with the rainfall distributed as a relatively continuous sequence of  events, the yellow and grey earths develop free water levels in the underlying  weathered rock. These can rise to within 0.5 m of the soil surface in many  years and have occasionally been observed at the soil surface. The nearby,    203    (b)  o    100    2200  0~   300  ~400    500    600  150     100  _~ 50  oo    Weeks from January 1, 1981  o            lO           20           30           40  G          \,,                   \\\       D  2---",,  To 1431 cm                                        F  in week 18                    ~  Water tables observed  between 950 cm and  1173 cm in profile G.    No  water  tables  occurred  in 1981  prior to  week 3    I  Dry    I  Season I  I    Wet Season    Dry  Season    -           -                                  100  0                                                        0 ~  40         50            1 )         20         30         40  Weeks, 1980                     Weeks, 1981  Fig. 4. Variations in the depth to the shallow groundwater tables in representative profiles  (profiles A--G of Fig. 2) during: a. 1978/79; and b. 1980/81. The groundwater tables of  1975/76 responded to rainfall in a similar manner to those of 1978/79, and therefore  have not been included in this diagram. The relative water content of the soil store was  calculated by computer program WATBAL (Keig and McAlpine, 1974; McCown, 1981)  using actual weekly rainfall at Torrens Creek Post Office, estimates of long-term mean  weekly U.S. Class A Pan evaporations at Hughenden, Pentland, and Charters Towers, and  a profile water store of 100 mm (CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils Tech. Mere., 9/1983).    deeper red earths -- many downslope of the saturated yellow and grey soils  (as in Fig. 2) -- behave as freely draining profiles in which water may pene-  trate on occasions to below 6 m. In parallel studies on similar red earths in  the Australian semiarid tropics at Katherine, N.T., a recharge below 4.5 m  depth of approximately 75 mm has beeh estimated (Williams et al., 1980).    204    This estimate is consistent with the observations of Williams and Coventry  (1979, 1981) at Torrens Creek. The upper sola (3--4 m deep) of the red  earths of the studied transect show no evidence of impeded drainage (Table  I) such as grey mottles, the accumulation of ironstone gravels, or other fea-  tures of soils of poorly drained sites as described by the Soil Survey Staff  (1951, 1975), Veneman et al. (1976), and Richardson and Hole (1979).    Frequency of occurrence of profile saturation. The years of this study in  which water tables were observed are usually, but not exclusively, the years  in which total annual rainfall was higher than the median value. The excep-  tions are years 1976/77 and 1981/82 (Fig. 3a). Similarly, water tables were  observed in almost all the wet seasons that followed dry seasons with above-  median rainfall. Although 1981 had a very high dry season rainfall at both  Torrens Creek (Fig. 3b) and Pentland (exceeded twice in the 57 years of  records for the former (1925--1981), and once only in the 37 years of  records for the latter (1945--1981)), water tables did not develop in any of  the softs in the 1981/82 wet season.  Water tables were always observed when above-median rainfall in the dry  season at Torrens Creek and Pentland was followed by above-median rainfall  in the subsequent wet season (Fig. 3b). Such a rainfall sequence has occurred  17 times in the 52 years of complete monthly rainfall records at Torrens  Creek (frequency of occurrence = 33%) and 14 times in 37 years of com-  plete records at Pentland (frequency of occurrence = 38%). Hence it is rea-  sonable to conclude that water tables may be expected to develop in the  soils as often as 1 year in 3, and, therefore, are not abnormal occurrences in  this semiarid area.    Duration of profile saturation. Shallow groundwater tables were observed at,  or within 20--50 cm of the surface in almost all the yellow and grey earths  of the Torrens Creek--Pentland area in 1973/74, a very wet year (Fig. 3).  The changes in groundwater level in each of the 30 observation wells were  measured systematically after water tables were found to have developed  again in 1975/76. Successive positions of the groundwater tables along the  transect through the 1976 wet season have been illustrated previously (Wil-  liams and Coventry, 1979).  In week 13 of 1976 and week 11 of 1979 there were abrupt rises in  groundwater levels early in the wet season followed by a slow decline into  the subsequent dry seasons (Fig. 4a). A similar trend developed in week 3  of 1981 for the upslope profiles and by week 9 for the downslope profiles;  sufficient rain fell in weeks 20 and 21, at the end of the wet season, to in-  duce a second major rise in the groundwater levels observed in all the pro-  files early in the 1981 dry season (Fig. 4b). These times of major rises in the  shallow groundwater tables are reflected in the large increases in the relative  water content of the soil store. Their occurrences can be accurately esti-  mated from weekly rainfall records and computer program WATBAL, and    205    are consistent with our field observations that water tables did not develop  in 1979 prior to week 11 (Fig. 4a), or in 1981 prior to week 3 (Fig. 4b).  From groundwater&lt;lepth/duration curves, such as those of Figs. 4a and  4b, reliable estimates can be made of the minimum periods for which water  tables lay at or above specific depths in the individual soil profiles. If these  durations are averaged over the three periods when water tables were ob-  served and are plotted against profile depth (as is done in Fig. 5 for the re-  presentative profiles), estimates of the mean duration of profile saturation  can be made for any depth in each soil profile. Conversely, the depths at  which each profile was saturated for certain periods can be determined. The  lateral variation in profile saturation for 5, 10, 15 and 21 weeks (i.e., 10%,  20%, 30%, and 40% of the years when groundwater tables developed) is  shown on Fig. 2d, as is the depth to the mean height at which the shallowest  water tables were observed in the three periods of groundwater occurrences  during this study.    100    200    ~- 300   400    500    600    700    Weeks of profile saturation  0     5     10     "~     20    25  I     I     I     I  -A        c  \                      \.\.  ",:  I  \   ':  F                                  \    ~    Fig. 5. Mean durations of profile saturation at various depths in representative profiles  that are located on Fig. 2. The data are from CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils Tech. Mere., 10/  1983 and 14/1983.    206    Quantitative analyses    If a morphological feature lying at a certain depth in a soil profile is  directly associated with a particular soil hydrological regime, then the depths  to both variables should be simply and linearly related, and described by a  mathematical model of the form y = a + bx. The expected relationship  would have a = 0 and b = 1. In assessing the pedological significance of such  quantitative analyses of the relationships between all of the soil morphologi-  cal features and all of the hydrological regimes, we have attached the greatest  importance to the linear regressions (calculated by an intercept-suppressed  model) in which the slope is not significantly different from unity (p ~&lt;  0.05), and which also account for the greatest amount of variance (Fisher's  A).  At this stage we are not concerned with the development of predictive  mathematical models but with finding a quantitative means of evaluating the  validity of 1:1 relationships between soil morphology and hydrology. In par-  ticular, we have attempted to demonstrate which of the range of soil hydro-  logical regimes is most directly related to each soil morphological feature. We  have thereby extended the scope of the earlier work of Schelling (1960),  Van Wallenburg (1973), and Moore (1974).    RESULTS    Some clear 1:1 relationships were found between the depths to soil mor-  phological features and to different soil hydrological regimes in the studied  profiles (Table III). With the exception of one soil property (the depth to  the upper boundary of the B2 horizon), the depths to all of the soil morpho-  logical features were found to be well correlated with the depth to at least  one of the soil hydrological regimes. The strongest of these relationships for  each soil morphological feature are illustrated in Fig. 6 and are discussed  below.    Soil colour characteristics and soil hydrology    The mean depths to the upper limit of brown, brownish red, or red mot-  tles increase from the yellow and grey earths to the red earths (Table II;  Fig. 2b). The correlation of the depth to the upper limit of these mottles  with the depth to the shallowest water tables observed in each of the 30 soil  profiles was found to be one of the stror~gest relationships between any of  the morphological and hydrological properties considered (Table III; Fig. 6a).  Grey mottles lie at slightly greater depths than the brown or red mottles  in the yellow and grey earths (Fig. 2b). The mean depths to grey mottles are  significantly different between soil groups and increase from the grey earths  to the yellow earths to the red earths (Table II}. The depths to the grey  mottles in the individual profiles were found to be most closely related to    207    TABLE III    Slopes and percentages of variance accounted for by simple linear regression of the form  y = bx where y is the depth to each soil morphological feature and x is the depth to dif-  ferent soil hydrological regimes  (Data are from CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils Tech. Mem., 10/1983)    Soil morphological feature    Slope   Depth to  and     the  vari-    shallowest  ance*l  water  tables    Soil hydrological regime  Depth at which the profile is  satured for:    5 weeks 10 weeks 15 weeks 21 weeks    Upper limit of brown,        b       0.948      0.648   0.573    0.474    0.359  brownish red, or red        %A         93         85      83        78        75  mottles in 28 profiles  Upper limit of grey          b       1.279      0.920   0.857     0.794    0.598  mottles in 26 profiles       %A        80         86      94        94        94  Upper limit of mottles       b       1.302      0.939   0.877     0.829    0.617  with chromas &lt; 2 in       %A        78         90      92       93       95  23 profiles  Upper limit of dominantly   b       3.743      2.176   1.874    1.488    1.091  grey colours in subsola      %A         78*2       91      93        93        94  in 11 profiles  Upper limit of ironstone     b       0.935      0.717   0.649    0.552    0.437  gravels in 27 profiles        %A         66*2       80      81        82        87  Maximum contents of iron-  b       1.561      1.177   1.061    0.881    0.710  stone gravels in 14 profiles  %A         78         85      86        84        86  Maximum content of clay    b      * 1.051      0.830   0.746    0.618    0.482  in the whole soil in 14      %A         78         94      95        92        94  profiles  Base of the solum in         b       1.553      1.111   1.043    1.039    0.784  25 profiles                  %A         71*2       80*2    83        87        90  Upper boundary of the      b       0.257      0.191   0.182    0.213    0.154  horizon in 30 profiles       %A         47*2       50*2    54*2      72*2      75*2    ,1 b is the slope of the y = bx regression model and %A is the percentage of the variance  (Fisher's A) accounted for by the regression. Slopes that are not significantly different  from unity (P &lt; 0.05) are indicated by bold type.  *2The variance of the residual is greater than the variance of the y-variate.    the depths at which the profile was saturated for 5 weeks (Table III; Fig. 6b).  Mottles with Munsell chromas of two or less and Munsell values of four  or more, indicative of saturation of the soil for some unspecified period of  the year (Soil Survey Staff, 1975, pp. 48--49), were found to occur at mean    v  Dominantly grey colours  in mottled subsola    o  +:f  E~  ~o    II    o  I    \     Mottles with chromas  of 2 or less  o           o  e-  ~            --.                            o  o  3     o  il-o  H            ]+ ] M  '-'+    &lt;~  o    o  c  oi    &lt;?&gt;  o    Grey mottles  o  Io     t      I      ]  o             o  II  0':,             o    \    o  o    Red, brownish red, or  red mottles  o    o  1      I      l      I  \  -\  ",\ o  \.  II                  "  \    b~  Oo    c)  Or)  eB  0  5~  01  o    Base of the solum    I    I    1    I  oo    o  o  o  \  II               o  ]  N~    A    A  tim    Maximum content of clay    o  I    I  ~       II                "\.'  E      .~.                  \    o  I    c~  E  3  CO    Maximum content of  ironstone gravels      I    i         +  \  o  4.   o o  o     o  \  II ""   o  ",\    --h  v    (/)  E  0-  0    Upper limit of  ironstone gravels    o  \  \o    \,  a    ,\\              &lt;,    ".\  It                   \,,,7  i'.,D                 \',,:' ]    209    depths in each soil group that were not significantly different from those of  the grey mottles (Table II). The depth to the upper limit of mottles with  chromas of two or less in all 30 profiles is also most closely related to the  depth to profile saturation for 5 weeks (Table III; Fig. 6c).  The mean depths at which the matrix of the strongly mottled subsola of  the yellow earth and grey earth profiles assumes a dominantly grey colour  were found to be not significantly different (Table II; Fig. 2b). None of the  five profiles of red earths, however, displayed dominantly grey colours with-  in the depths of profile examined. In the strongly mottled subsola of the  yellow and grey earths the depth to dominantly grey colours is most closely  related to the depth at which the profiles were saturated for the longest  durations of any of the hydrological regimes considered in this study (Table  III; Fig. 6d).    B horizon characteristics and soil hydrology    Ironstone gravels occur in the B horizons of the yellow and grey earths be-  low about 90 cm and achieve their maximum abundances at 130--140 cm in  both soil groups (Table II). In the red earths, however, ironstone gravels were  observed in only two profiles (those nearest the red earth/yellow earth inter-  intergrade soils} below depths of 180 cm and 250 cm (Fig. 2c). The depth to  the upper limit of ironstone gravels in all the soils was found to be most  closely related to the depth of the shallowest water tables observed (Table  III; Fig. 6e).  The mean depth to the upper limit of the ironstone gravels in each of the  30 soil profiles almost coincides with that of red and brown mottles, and  the gravels extend downwards to attain their greatest abundance slightly be-    Fig. 6. Relationships between the depths to various soil profile morphological features  and the depths to different soil hydrological regimes. Slopes of the linear regressions and  the proportions of the variance accounted for are listed in Table III. The data are from  CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils, Tech. Mere., 10/1983.  a. The upper limit of brown, brownish red, or red mottles is compared with the depth to  the shallowest water tables observed.  b. The upper limit of grey mottles is compared with the depth to total profile saturation  for 5 weeks.  c. The upper limit of mottles with chrornas of 2 or less is compared with the depth to  total profile saturation for 5 weeks.  d. The upper limit of dominantly grey colours in strongly mottled subsola is compared  with the depth to total profile saturation for 21 weeks.  e. The upper limit of ironstone gravels is compared with the depth to the shallowest  water tables observed.  f. The depth to the maximum content of ironstone gravels is compared with the depth  to total profile saturation for 10 weeks.  g. The depth to the maximum content of clay is compared with the depth to the shallow-  est observed water tables.  h. The depth to the base of the solum is compared with the depth to profile saturation  for 15 weeks.    210    low the depths at which the grey mottles have developed (Table II). The  depth to the midpoint of the sampling interval in which the gravels achieve  their maximum abundance in each of the 14 soil profiles for which particle-  size data are available are related to the depths of profile saturation for 5--  15 weeks (Table III; Fig. 6f). Hence, in the studied soils, the ironstone  gravels are most closely associated with currently active hydrological regimes  of shorter duration that lie at the shallower depths.  The mean depth to the midpoint of the sampling interval containing the  maximum content of clay is not significantly different between the yellow  and grey earths but lay at much greater depths in the red earths (Table II;  Fig. 2c). These depths have a close 1:1 relationship with the depths to the  shallowest water tables (Table III; Fig. 6g).  The mean depth to the base of the solum is not significantly different be-  tween the yellow and grey earths but lies at greater depths in the red earth  profiles (Table II; Fig. 2c). The depth to the base of the solum in the 25  profiles in which this feature was observed has strongest 1:1 relationships  with the depths at which the profiles were saturated for 10 and 15 weeks  (Table III; Fig. 6h).  The depth to the upper boundary of the B2 horizon marks the depth in  the soil profile where the soil texture increases most rapidly. It has been  determined in the field largely on the basis of the manual manipulation of  moist soil (Northcote, 1979). This depth was found to have no direct rela-  tionships with any of the hydrological regimes considered (Table III).    Hydrology of the soil groups    Mean durations of profile saturation for the soil groups are shown in  Fig. 7. There is no doubt that the poorly to very poorly drained grey earths  have water tables at shallower depths and for longer periods of time than the  somewhat less poorly drained yellow earths. Any water tables occurring in  the well-drained red earths are much deeper; those less than 300 cm deep  are of very short duration. A practical recognition of these differences by  landowners in the region is that the soils in which the shallow water tables  frequently develop (grey and yellow earths) have been avoided where pos-  sible in locating unsealed access roads to homesteads but are used as sites for  earth dams for surface water storage.  It is now possible to quantify such commonly observed and practically  utilized differences in the drainage status of some semiarid tropical soils.  Fig. 7 indicates that, at any particular depth, the sola of the grey earths are  saturated for about 5--8 weeks longer than are the sola of the yellow earths;  at any depth to at least 300 cm, the yellow earths are saturated for up to 21  weeks longer than are the red earths. Alternatively, Fig. 7 shows that, if  water tables are to develop in the studied soils, then they can be expected to  lie at shallower (30-60 cm) depths in the grey earths than in the yellow  earths, and about 250--450 cm shallower in the yellow earths than in the  red earths.    211    0  O,    100    200     300     400    500    Weeks of profile saturation  5     10    15    20  I     I     I     I  "*'---... @to  "-4.,%e~_\  4,%. "~  (Q  x&lt;2o  o                 o    25  I    4    I  700      I      I      I            I  Fig. 7. Durations of profile saturation at various depths in profiles comprising the three  Australian great soil groups on the transect. The values are averaged over the three periods  when water tables were observed (CSIRO Aust., Div. Soils, Tech. Mere., 10/1983 and  14/1983).    DISCUSSION    In all 30 profiles, the occurrence of mottles of any kind was consistently  restricted to that part of the solum subjected to some profile saturation. The  base of the mottle-free zone, the "matrix zone" of Moore (1974), is defined  by the upper limit to brown, brownish red or red mottles and lies above the  depths at which even the shallowest water tables have been observed. The  mean thickness of the mottle-free zone is about 40 cm thick in the moder-  ately to poorly drained yellow and grey earths and is 355 cm thick in the  well&lt;lrained red earths. A similar result was found by Simonson and Boers-  ma (1972) for a range of soils in Oregon, U.S.A., in that the depth below the  soil surface to the upper limit of mottles was also found to increase as the  drainage condition of the soil improved.  For all the profiles, the observed mottles were located in the zone of fluc-  tuating water tables that produced profile saturations of varying duration. A  similar conclusion was drawn by Van Wallenburg (1973) from a study of a    212    range of Dutch soils. The depth to the brown, brownish red, or red mottles,  the shallowest mottles in each of the 30 described soil profiles of our study,  is closely associated with the shallowest and most ephemeral of the soil  water regimes considered and is less closely related to the depths of profile  saturation for 5 weeks. If a causal relationship is inferred, this result suggests  that the development of such mottles requires some soil-profile saturation,  but that need not necessarily be of prolonged duration.  Similar hydrological conditions are associated with the distribution of  ironstone gravels in that their upper limit in the studied soil profiles is close-  ly related to the depth to the shallowest water tables observed. The maxi-  mum abundance of ironstone gravels lies at greater depths in all the soil pro-  files and was found to relate to slightly longer periods of profile saturation  (5--15 weeks).  The problem of recognizing fossil gley phenomena in soils (grey mottles,  ferruginous gravels, etc.) as relict features, related to past hydrological condi-  tions and not to those currently influencing the soil, has been recognized and  discussed by a number of authors (e.g., Ruhe et al., 1955; Schelling, 1960;  Van Heesen, 1970; Daniels et al., 1973; Van Wallenburg, 1973; Vepraskas  and Bouma, 1976). A mineralogical and micromorphological study of a  gravelly grey earth, located in the same mapping unit, but 900 m from pro-  file A of Fig. 2a, has shown that some of the abundant ironstone gravels in  the upper part of the profile are relict features (Coventry et al., 1983). These  gravels had undergone significant transportation prior to their incorporation  in the Late Tertiary sediment in which the soil subsequently developed.  Other ferruginous accumulations lying deeper in the profile and in the zone  of maximum abundance of ironstone gravels, showed clear mineralogical and  micromorphological characteristics indicative of formation in situ. Hence,  both allochthonous (relict) and autochthonous ironstone gravels are thought  to occur in the studied profiles. The time of formation of the autochthonous  features is unknown.  Relatively short durations of profile saturation (5 weeks, 10% of the year)  were found to be related to the depths to the upper limits of grey mottles  and of mottles with chromas of 2 or less. These results agree in part with the  findings of Daniels et al. (1971) from some soils in North Carolina, U.S.A.,  in which grey mottles (10 YR 6/3-7/3) were related to profile saturations for  25% of the time but not with their observation that mottles with chromas  of 2 or less were found to relate to profile saturations for as much as 50% of  the time.  For one somewhat restricted group of soils in a particular environment,  we can now make a step towards quantifying the "period of the year" for  which the Soil Survey Staff (1975) implies that mottles with chromas of 2 or  less are indicative of profile saturation. If a causal relationship is accepted,  the results of our study show that, for the range of Alfisols studied at  Torrens Creek, this "period of the year" is equivalent to 5 weeks of profile  saturation recurring once every 3 years.    213    It is clear from our analysis that grey mottles are associated with longer  periods of profile saturation than are brown or red mottles. Consequently,  the grey mottles appear at a greater depth in each soil profile than do the  redder mottles, with the exception of the poorly drained grey earth/gleyed  podzolic profiles in the vicinity of profile D in which the depths to both  kinds of mottles are coincident (Fig. 2b). Other works in the temperate zone  of the Northern Hemisphere (e.g., Daniels et al., 1971; Simonson and Boers-  ma, 1972; Van Wallenburg, 1973; Veneman et al., 1976) have also demon-  strated that red or brown mottles lie at shallower depths, and are associated  with shorter periods of profile saturation than are grey mottles.  Our results are consistent with the considerable body of field and labora-  tory evidence to suggest that grey mottles, mottles with chromas of 2 or less,  or dominantly grey colours of strongly mottled subsola are associated with  soil saturations of sufficient intensity and duration to allow reducing condi-  tions to develop in the more poorly drained soils; oxidizing conditions are  responsible for the brighter or redder colours in the better drained soils (e.g.,  Soil Survey Staff, 1951; 1975; Bloomfield, 1963; McKeague, 1965; Vepras-  kas and Bouma, 1976; Veneman and Bodine, 1982). Although profile satura-  tion is a useful parameter relating soil morphological features to soil hydrol-  ogy, Siuta (1967) and Daniels et al. (1973) have also discussed the impor-  tance of the oxygen content of the groundwater. It should be recognized  that the reducing conditions required to produce grey mottles may not al-  ways be related to high regional water tables that maintain saturation condi-  tions for long time periods (Vepraskas et al., 1974). Perched water tables  rather than high regional groundwater tables can be responsible for the phe-  nomenon (Guthrie and Hajek, 1979). Mottles can also develop in fine-  textured soil horizons immediately overlying a coarse-textured layer in pro-  files in which perched or regional groundwater tables may never occur  (Clothier et al., 1978).  The depths to the maximum content of clay in the whole soil, and to the  base of the solum in each of the 30 studied profiles are closely related to the  depths of the shallowest water tables observed and to profile saturation for  10--15 weeks, respectively. These may be fortuitous associations but we are  inclined to believe that they have some genetic significance: weathering, clay  production, and profile development must be influenced by the saturation  history of the soil profile. This idea is supported by the work of Daniels et  al. (1970, 1971) who found that as the depth to the water table increased, so  also did the solum thickness; solum thickening was thought to be impeded  by high ground water tables inhibiting the downward translocation of soil  materials. Our results show that those portions of each of the 30 studied soil  profiles lying between the maximum clay content and the base of the solum  (i.e., the major portion of each B horizon) relate to the depths of profile  saturation for less than 5 weeks to as much as 15 weeks.  The lack of correlation between the upper boundary of the B2 horizon  and any of the soil moisture conditions considered suggests that the upper    2]4    part of all the soil profiles is influenced more strongly by factors other than  fluctuating hydrological regimes in the soil. The derivation of sandy, clay-  deficient A horizons of similar soils in central north Queensland from the  erosional degradation of former termite mounds has been proposed by Holt  et al. (1980). Their conservatively estimated rates of soil accumulation indi-  cate that one generation of termite mounds could rework up to 20 t/ha of  soil, and that the 20 cm thick A horizons could have accumulated in 8000  years in a landscape where the soils may be of the order of 2 million years  old. As termite mounds are abundant in the Torrens Creek area, a similar  process may have governed the depth to the B2 horizons of the studied soils.  The soil morphological/hydrological relationships discussed in this paper  have been established for only a small number (30) and a limited range of  soil profiles (3 Australian great soil groups) at a single locality. Although  strongly site-specific, our study has quantified the hydrological significance  of a range of morphological features of soils in the semiarid tropics. These  associations between soil morphological and hydrological properties have  been established in an environment with an aridic soil moisture regime (as  defined by the Soil Survey Staff, 1975). It is an environment in which a sim-  ple water-balance analysis such as that of Thornthwaite and Mather (1957)  implies that water surpluses should not occur in any year, and where a signif-  icant development of hydromorphic soil features is most unlikely. The fact  that the opposite appears to be the case can be attributed to: the concentra-  tion of the rainfall in a marked wet season; the subdued relief of the land-  scape; the high infiltration rates and low water-holding capacities of the  soils; and the occurrence of barriers to deep drainage beneath many of the  profiles (Williams and Coventry, 1979, 1981).    CONCLUSIONS    Certain morphological features of the studied sequence of red, yellow, and  grey earths have been observed at similar depths in the soil profiles as various  hydrological regimes that occur as frequently as once every 3 years in the  semiarid tropical environment (Table IV).  Differences in soil profile saturation can be quantified at the individual  soil profile level (Fig. 5), and also at the Australian great soil group taxonom-  ic level (Fig. 7). This quantification has been carried out on two bases: dif-  ferences in numbers of weeks of profile saturation at a particular depth in  the soil or soil group, and differences in the depth in the profile to the water  that persists for a particular period.  A wide variety of soil morphological features has been related to different  soil hydrological regimes in this study in a quantitative manner that is con-  sistent with the qualitative findings of other workers elsewhere in the world.  Our results are also consistent with interpretations based on conventional  pedological experience. The close correlation of a number of soil morpho-  logical features with different shallow groundwater regimes strongly suggests    215    a close association between profile morphology and the present climate of  the area. Eight of the nine soil morphological features studied occur in the  zone of fluctuating water tables along the transect. Our results have shown  that soil profile saturations of less than 5 weeks to as much as 21 weeks, oc-  curring as frequently as once every 3 years, would appear to be sufficient for  the development of a range of hydromorphic soil characteristics. This raises  the interesting possibility of a group of old soils (Late Tertiary--Early  Quaternary in age), lying in a semiarid tropical landscape, displaying hydro-  morphic features that appear to be in harmony with their current hydrology.    TABLE IV    Summary of relationships between the depths to profile morphological features and  hydrological regimes in the studied sequence of 30 soil profiles    Morphological feature                     Hydrological regime  (i)   Upper limit of brown, brownish     Shallowest water tables observed  red or red mottles  (ii)   Upper limit of ironstone gravels  (iii)  Maximum content of clay  Upper limit of:  grey mottles  mottles with chromas of 2 or less    (i)  (ii)    Maximum content of ironstone gravels    Base of the solum    Dominantly grey colours in strongly  mottled subsola  Upper boundary of the B: horizon    Profile saturation for 5 weeks  (10% of the year)    Profile saturation for 5--15 weeks  (10--30% of the year)  Profile saturation for 10--15 weeks  (20--30% of the year)  Profile saturation for 21 weeks  (40% of the year)  Not related to any of the soil hydrological  regimes considered    Nevertheless, although causal relationships are strongly suggested by our  results, they are not proven. One of the soil morphological features studied  could not be related to any of the soil hydrological regimes analysed. Also,  the uncertainty still remains that the morphological features may be relict  and therefore owe their genesis to a previous climatic regime that may have  been similar to, or indeed quite different from that at present. Much depends  on the time of formation of the soil features and on the poorly understood  palaeoclimatic history of the region.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    A number of the staff of CSIRO, Townsville, have assisted us in many  ways at various times throughout this long project. In particular, we are  grateful to R.S. Penny and D.E.R. Fett for expert technical assistance with    216    many tasks in the field and laboratory, and to Michele Smith for her com-  putational skills. Unpublished rainfall data and analyses were generously sup-  plied by R.L. McCown, CSIRO, Division of Tropical Crops and Pastures.  Early drafts of this manuscript have benefited from constructive criticisms  of our colleagues within CSIRO, Division of Soils: R.F. Isbell, M.E. Probert,  P.H. Walker, and D.C. van Dijk. We thank the journal referee for his percep-  tive and helpful comments.    REFERENCES    Bloomfield, C., 1963. Mobilization phenomena in soils. Rep. Rothamsted Exp. Stn.,  Engl., for 1963, pp. 226--239.  Burdekin Project Committee, 1976. Resources and potential of the Burdekin River Basin,  Queensland. Appendix 2a: Land and associated features. Aust. Gov. Publ. Serv., Can-  berra, Australia.  Clothier, B.E., Pollok, J.A. and Scotter, D.R., 1978. Mottling in soil profiles containing  a coarse-textured horizon. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 42: 761--763.  Commonwealth of Australia, Bureau of Meteorology, 1970. Climate Burdekin-Townsville  Region (Queensland), Resour. Ser., Dep. Nat. Dev., Geogr. Sect., Canberra, Australia.  Commonwealth of Australia, Bureau of Meteorology, 1977. Climatic Atlas of Australia,  Map 5: Rainfall. Aust. Gov. Publ. Serv., Canberra, Australia.  Coventry, R.J., 1979a. Late Cainozoic geology, soils, and landscape evolution of the  Torrens Creek area, North Queensland. J. Geol. Soc. Aust., 25: 415--427.  Coventry, R.J., 1979b. The age of a red earth profile in central north Queensland. Aust.  J. Soil Res., 17: 505--510.  Coventry, R.J., 1982. The distribution of red, yellow, and grey earths in the Torrens  Creek area, central north Queensland. Aust. J. Soil Res., 20: 1--14.  Coventry, R.J. and Fett, D.E.R., 1982. Morphology and particle-size characteristics of  red, yellow, and grey earths and associated soils of the Torrens Creek area, central  north Queensland, CSIRO Australia, Div. Soils, Div. Rep., 60:54 pp.  Coventry, R.J. and Robinson, P.J., 1981. Colour groups derived from numerical classifi-  cation of the Munsell soil colour chips. Aust. J. Soil Res., 19: 103--112.  Coventry, R.J., Hopley, D., Campbell, J.B., Douglas, I., Harvey, N., Kershaw, A.P.,  Oliver, J., Phipps, C.V.G. and Pye, K., 1980. The Quaternary of northeastern Austra-  lia. In: R.A. Henderson and P.J. Stephenson (Editors), The Geology and Geophysics  of Northeastern Australia. Geol. Soc. Aust., Qld. Div., Brisbane, pp. 375--418.  Coventry, R.J., Taylor, R.M. and Fitzpatrick, R.W., 1983. Pedological significance of the  gravels in some red and grey earths of central north Queensland. Aust. J. Soil Res., 21:  219--240.  Daniels, R.B., Gamble, E.E. and Cady, J.G., 1970. Some relations among Coastal Plain  soils and geomorphic surfaces in North Carolina. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 648--  653.  Daniels, R.B., Gamble, E.E. and Nelson, L.A., 1971. Relations between soil morphology  and water-table levels on a dissected North Carolina Coastal Plain surface. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 781--784.  Daniels, R.B., Gamble, E.E. and Buol, S.W., 1973. Oxygen content in the ground water  of some North Carolina Aquults and Udults. In: Field Soil Water Regime. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am., Madison, Wisc., U.S.A., pp. 153--166.  Gunn, R.H., 1967. A soil catena on denuded laterite profiles in Queensland. Aust. J. Soil  Res., 5: 117--132.  Guthrie, R.L. and Hajek, B.F., 1979. Morphology and water regime of a Dothan soil. Soil  Sci. 8oc. Am. Proc., 43: 142--144.    217    Holt, J.A., Coventry, R.J. and Sinclair, D.F., 1980. Some aspects of the biology and  pedological significance of mound-building termites in a red and yellow earth land-  scape near Charters Towers, north Queensland. Aust. J. Soil Res., 18: 97--109.  Isbell, R.F. and Smith, G.McL., 1976. Some properties of red, yellow, and grey massive  earths in North Queensland. CSIRO Australia, Div. Soils, Tech. Pap., 30:52 pp.  Isbell, R.F. and Williams, J., 1981. Dry soils of Australia: characteristics and classifica-  tion. In: F.H. Beinroth and A. Osman (Editors), Proc. 3rd Int. Soil Classif. Workshop,  Syria-Lebanon, 1980, Damascus, Syria, ACSAD, pp. 124--150.  Keig, G. and McAlpine, J.R., 1969. Instructions for preparation of daily rainfall data as  input to land research climate programs. CSIRO Aust., Div. Land Res., Tech. Mere.,  69 8.  Keig, G. and McAlpine, J.R., 1974. WATBAL: a computer system for the estimation and  analysis of soil moisture regimes from simple climatic data. CSIRO Aust., Div. Land  Use Res., Tech. Mem. (2nd edn.), 74/4.  McCown, R.L., 1981. The climatic potential for beef cattle production in tropical Austra-  lia, I. Simulating the annual cycle of live-weight change. Agric. Systems, 6: 303--317.  McKeague, J.A., 1965. A laboratory study of gleying. Can. J. Soil Sci., 45: 199--206.  Moore, T.R., 1974 Gley morphology and soil water regimes in some soils in south-central  England. Geoderma, 11: 297--304.  Northcote, K.H., 1979. A Factual Key for the Description of Australian Soils. Rellim  Tech. Publ., Glenside, S.A., 4th edn., 124 pp.  Richardson, J.L. and Hole, F.D., 1979. Mottling and iron distribution in a Glossoboralf-  Haplaquoll hydrosequence on a glacial moraine in northeastern Wisconsin. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 43: 552--558.  Ruhe, R.V., Prill, R.C. and Riecken, F.F., 1955. Profile characteristics of some loess-  derived soils and soil aeration. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 19: 345--347.  Schelling, J., 1960. New aspects of soil classification with particular reference to re-  claimed hydromorphic soils. Trans. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 7th, Madison, 4: 218--224.  Simonson, G.H. and Boersma, L., 1972. Soil morphology and water table relations. II.  Correlation between annual water table fluctuations and profile features. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 34: 649--653.  Siuta, J., 1967. Gleying as an indicator of the water and air regime of the soil. Soy. Soil  Sci., 3, March 1967; 356--363.  Soil Science Society of America, 1975. Glossary of Soil Science Terms. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am., Madison, WI, 34 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 18:503 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy -- a Basic System for Making and Interpreting  Soil Surveys. U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook, 436:754 pp.  Stace, H.C.T., Hubble, G.D., Brewer, R., Northcote, K.H., Sleeman, J.R., Mulcahy, M.J.  and HaUsworth, E.G., 1968. A Handbook of Australian Soils. Rellim Tech. Publ.,  Glenside, SA, 429 pp.  Thornthwaite, C.W. and Mather, J.R., 1957. Instructions and tables for computing poten-  tial evapotranspiration and the water balance. Lab. Climatol., Centerton, NJ., Publ.  Climatol., 127 pp.  Van Heesen, H.C., 1970. Presentation of the seasonal fluctuation of the water table on  soil maps. Geoderma, 4: 257--278.  Van Wallenburg, C., 1973. Hydromorphic soil characteristics in alluvial soils in connec-  tion with soil drainage. In: E. Schlichting and U. Schwertmann (Editors), Pseudogley  and Gley-Genesis and Use of Hydromorphic Soils. Trans. Comm. V and VI. Int. Soc.  Soil Sci. Verlag Chemie, Weinheim, pp. 393--403.  Veneman, P.L.M. and Bodine, S.M., 1982. Chemical and morphological soil characteris-  tics in a New England drainage-toposequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 46: 359--363.  Veneman, P.L.M., Vepraskas, M.J. and Bouma, J., 1976. The physical significance of soil  mottling in a Wisconsin toposequence. Geoderma, 15: 108--118.    218    Vepraskas, M.J. and Bouma, J., 1976. Model experiments on mottle formation simulating  field conditions. Geoderma, 15: 217--230.  Vepraskas, M.J., Baker, F.G. and Bouma, J., 1974. Soil mottling and drainage in a Mollic  Hapludalf as related to suitability for septic tank construction. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc.  38: 497--501.  Williams, J. and Coventry, R.J., 1979. The contrasting hydrology of red and yellow earths  in a landscape of low relief. In: The Hydrology of Areas of Low Precipitation. Proc.  Canberra Syrup. (Int. Assoc. Sci. Hydrol.), Publ., 128, pp. 385--395.  Williams, J. and Coventry, R.J., 1981. The potential for groundwater recharge through  red, yellow, and grey earth profiles in central north  Queensland. In: Groundwater  Recharge, Australian Water Resources Council, Conf. Set., 3, pp. 169--181.  Williams, J., Wall, B.H. and McCown, R.L., 1980. Estimation of deep drainage and plant  water extraction from soil water measurements. In: Hydrology of Water Resources  Symposium, Adelaide. Inst. Eng. Aust. Natl. Conf., Publ. 80/9" pp. 96--100.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          AbstractThe shallow groundwater hydrology of a sequence of red, yellow, and grey earths (Paleustalfs, Plinthustalfs and Ochraqualfs of Soil Taxonomy) was monitored over a 9-year period (19731982) along a drilled transect of 30 boreholes near Torrens Creek, in northeastern Australia. Climatic analysis shows an aridic soil moisture regime under which soil water surpluses should not occur, and thus significant hydromorphism would not be expected in the soils. The present study has demonstrated, however, that profile saturation and groundwater tables may be expected to develop at various depths in the soils as often as 1 year in 3. Besides, strong linear relationships were found between a number of morphological features of the soils and various hydrological regimes currently active in the profiles: the depths to the upper limits of brown, brownish red, or red mottles, to the upper limit of ironstone gravels, and to the maximum content of clay are all most closely related to the mean position of the shallowest water tables observed; the depths to grey mottles and to mottles with chromas of two or less are most directly related to the depths at which the soils are saturated for 5 weeks; the depth to the maximum content of ironstone gravels and to the base of the solum are most closely associated with the depth at which the soils are saturated for 10 to 15 weeks; and dominantly grey colours in the strongly mottled subsols are best related to profile saturations for at least 21 weeks. The results indicate that the gley features present in the soil profiles could have developed, at least in part, in response to the current soil hydrological regime.