Geoderma, 31 (1983) 57--69                                                      57  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    PHOSPHATE ADSORPTION MECHANISMS IN OXIDIC SOILS:  IMPLICATIONS FOR P-AVAILABILITY TO PLANTS*    W.A. STOOP  Royal Tropical Institute, Mauritskade 63, Amsterdam (The Netherlands)  (Received November 22, 1978; accepted after revision November 3, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Stoop, W.A., 1983. Phosphate adsorption mechanisms in oxidic soils: implications for  P-availability to plants. Geoderma, 31 : 57--69.    Factors affecting P solubility were studied for four Hawaiian soils: the Waialua,  Wahiawa, Halii and Honokaa series, classified, respectively, as: Haplustoll, Eutrustox,  Gibbsihumox and Hydrandept.  Phosphate solubility in the oxidic soils depended mainly on salt concentration and  cation valency. It was decreased by the accompanying cation according to: K&lt;Mg~&lt;Ca.  This cation effect on P solubility decreased with increasing contents of layer silicate clay  minerals and/or increasing base saturation of the soil. Consequently, it was almost absent  in the Haplustoll which contains montmorillonite and kaolinite.  The P solubility in all four soils increased greatly when the pH was raised with NaOH.  When Ca (OH)2 was used, however, this effect was almost completely eliminated due to  the action of Ca ions. This result explains why in many fertility studies of oxidic soils  even moderate liming rates were not found to increase the P availability.  In a subsequent pot experiment evidence was obtained on the negative effect of the Ca  ion on P uptake by Sudangrass from the Gibbsihumox and Eutrustox.    INTRODUCTION    Phosphate availability in soils is often a limiting factor for plant growth,  even though the total amount of soil-P may be great. In this respect it is  important to fully understand the nature of the adsorption and precipita-  tion reactions which occur when fertilizer phosphate is added to soils of  different mineralogical compositions.  If P sorption by soils were mainly the result of precipitation as Fe-, A1- or  Ca-phosphates, it should theoretically be possible to calculate P solubilities  from solubility products (Kittrick and Jackson, 1955, 1956; Molina and  Fassbender, 1972). The actual P solubilities in softs are generally higher, how-    *The investigations were carried out in the Department of Agronomy and Soils, Uni-  versity of Hawaii, as part of the PhD dissertation of the author.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    58    ever, than those predicted by solubility products, thus indicating the reLe-  vance of P adsorption processes (Bache, 1964). Nevertheless, slow trans-  formations from adsorbed into precipitated forms are indicated by the de-  composition of kaolin and other clay minerals in the presence of concen-  trated P solutions (Kittrick and Jackson, 1955).  Phosphate sorption through adsorption implies that the process will be  limited by the sizes of surface areas and furthermore that phosphate can be  desorbed as a result of anion exchange. Basic research along these lines has  mainly been carried out with pure systems, e.g., gibbsite, hematite and kao-  linite (Bache, 1964; Muljadi et al., 1966; Hingston et al., 1967, 1968, 1972;  Breeuwsma and Lyklema, 1973).  Studies on P availability in softs as a function of soil pH do not, however,  indicate similar clear-cut results. For instance, liming reduced P adsorption  in softs which were high in exchangeable A13(Fox et al., 1962, 1964). Yet  for many tropical soils with pH values between 5 and 6, liming had an ad-  verse effect on P availability (Abruna et al., 1964; Fox et al., 1964; Amara-  siri and Olsen, 1973).  The discrepancy between the behaviour of phosphate in a pure oxide  system as compared with an oxidic soil system should probably be attri-  buted, among other factors, to the presence of calcium in the latter. After  all, softs in the pH range of 5 to 6 or higher, will at least contain a fair  amount of calcium, which may be further increased by the application of  lime and superphosphate fertilizers.  Finally, P adsorption is known to be influenced by clay mineralogy and  decreases as follows:  amorphous hydrated oxides&gt;goethite-gibbsite&gt;  kaolin&gt;&gt;montmorillonite (Fox et al., 1968). Under natural conditions, how-  ever, this sequence will be confounded with soil pH and levels of exchange-  able cations.  The aim of this investigation was to study separately various factors (e.g.,  pH, cation valency and salt concentration) which affect P adsorption for a  range of soils reflecting different weathering stages. Moreover, the experi-  mental conditions (e.g., a pH range from 4.8 to 5.8 and a salt concentration  of 0.01 N) were chosen to favour P sorption through adsorption rather than  precipitation so that P adsorption reactions will be clearly reflected. In that  way certain colloid chemical concepts developed for pure systems can be  utilized to better understand the various soil systems. Because plants must  obtain most of their nutrients directly from the soil solution (Barber et al.,  1963), these reactions are likely to influence also the P and cation uptake by  plants. Therefore, the investigation was concluded with a small pot experi-  ment which combined calcium and phosphate treatments.    THEORY    In previous articles (Stoop, 1980 and 1981) certain aspects of the inter-  actions between P adsorption and cation adsorption for different softs were    59    discussed. These aspects included: a lowering of the point of zero charge  (PZC) as a result of adsorbed phosphate; increased cation adsorption by  phosphated softs; increased adsorption preference for divalent cations, par-  ticularly calcium, over monovalent cations in phosphated soils.  These aspects proved to be particularly relevant for soils containing  mainly hydrous Fe- and Al-oxide colloids, known for their extremely large P  sorption capacities. For those softs, e.g. the Halii, Honokaa and to a lesser  extent Wahiawa softs, phosphate also increased the stability of the respective  soft suspensions, whereas calcium was particularly effective in causing floccu-  lation for the Halii and Honokaa softs. Those results strongly indicated that  adsorbed phosphate increased the negative surface charge density on oxidic  colloids.  A similar result was obtained by Breeuwsma and Lyklema (1973) for P  adsorption by hematite. They proposed a set of six possible reactions be-  tween phosphate and hematite suspensions, assuming that the colloid sur-  faces have three types of active groups:  -OHI, --OH and --O-, the relative  importance of each group being determined by pH. The following two reac-  tions are examples of how P adsorption could cause an increase in the nega-  tive surface charge:  Fe - OH2+ + H2PO4- -* FeH2PO4 + H20                                    (1)  Fe- OH  + HPO42--~ FeHPO4- + OH-                                    (2)  Reaction 2 also explains the release of hydroxyls and the subsequent in-  crease in suspension pH, recorded also in this study when P solutions were  added to soil suspensions containing mainly hydrous oxide colloids.  Being a surface reaction, P adsorption will likely be affected by the nature  and magnitude of the colloidal surface charge, which could be described by  the Gouy-Chapman-Stern-Grahame (G.C.S.G.) model for the electric double  layer on oxides (Breeuwsma, 1973). This model explains the increase in the  double layer potential (~d) upon raising pH. Moreover, the model predicts  that for a negative surface, ~I, d will be decreased by increasing salt concen-  tration and by specific adsorption of divalent cations in the Stern layer.  For pH values close to the point of zero charge (PZC) specific adsorption  could even lead to charge reversal (Breeuwsma, 1973). In either case ~I, d is  reduced, causing a decrease in the repulsive forces between negatively  charged colloid surface and phosphate ions in solution, after which an in-  crease in P adsorption should occur.  Oxidic softs in particular have large P adsorption capacities and conse-  quently their P concentrations in solution are generally very low. Thus, even  minor changes in the rate of P adsorption could easily cause large changes in  the P concentration in solution, thereby greatly influencing the availability  of P to plants.    60    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils    Samples were used of four surface soils belonging to the following series  and classified as: Waialua (variant) -- a Vertic Haplustoll; Wahiawa -- a  Tropeptic Eutrostox; Honokaa -- a Typic Hydrandept and Halii  .....  a Typic  Gibbsihumox.  The samples were secured from unfertilized sites on experimental farms  on the islands of Oahu, Hawaii and Kauai. Descriptions of these softs were  given in a previous article (Stoop, 1981).    Phosphate adsorption studies    Phosphate adsorption was studied in the same samples as used in the  earlier study on cation adsorption--release curves (Stoop, 1981). In that  study 3 g soil samples (on an oven&lt;iry basis) were equilibrated for 3 days,  using a 1:10 soil--solution ratio, at various P levels. These P levels were  roughly comparable with P fertilizer rates recommended for the different  soils.  Phosphate was added to the soil suspension either as NH4H2PO4 or as  Ca(H2PO4)2 solutions to study the effect of the accompanying cation on P  solubility. Next, 0.01 N chloride solutions of K, Mg or Ca were added and  the pH was adjusted to 4.8 or 5.8 except for the Waialua soil, for which the  pH levels were 5.8 and 6.8. The suspension pH was raised by using either  0.01 N NaOH or saturated Ca(OH)2. Equilibration was continued for another  24 h, after which the samples were centrifuged and the concentration in the  equilibrium extract was determined using the molybdenum blue method  with SnCI2 in HC1. The intensity of the blue colour was measured on a Tech-  nicon Autoanalyser.  Basically the various aspects studied in this way can be divided into:  (a) cation and cation valency effects on P solubility; (b) pH effect on P-solu-  bility.  The required duration of the equilibration process was studied as well to  investigate whether the cation effect on P solubility was independent of  time. Suspensions of phosphated soil samples were equilibrated from 0 to  16 days in either 0.01 N KC1 or 0.01 N CaC12 and P solubility was deter-  mined afterwards in the equilibrium extract, as described before.    Pot experiment    The pot experiment combined calcium and phosphate treatments in a 32  factorial with three replications. The objective was to investigate whether the  cation effect on P solubility, as measured in oxidic soils, would also signifi-  cantly influence the P nutrition of plants grown on these soils. Soil samples    61    of the Halii and Wahiawa series were thoroughly mixed and sieved prior to  weighing 2 kg of soil on an over-dry basis. Next the following blanket appli-  cations were added to each 2 kg sample: 2 gram Ca (OH)2 (= 2.7 meq.  Ca/100 g soft) and 1.62 gram KNO3 (= 0.8 meq. K/100 g soil).  Subsequently three phosphate (PI=100, P2=450 and P3=800 ppm P as  either NaH2PO4 or Ca(H2PO4)2) and three calcium treatments (Ca1=0,  Ca2=1.3 and Ca3=2.6 meq. Ca/100 g soil as either CaC12 or Ca(H2PO4)2) were  applied. The sum of applied Ca+Na was equal for all treatments and NaC1  was used to balance the cations.  Following an equilibration period of ten days the samples were transferred  to weighed one-gallon cans and Sudangrass (Sorghum vulgate var. Sudanense)  was planted.  The plants were harvested after three to four weeks; dried, weighed and  analysed for P, K, Ca and Mg following wet digestion with a mixture of nitric  and perchloric acids.  The soils were air-dried overnight following the harvest and analysed for  phosphate (measured in 1:10 extractions with water and with 0.01 M CaC12)  and for cations (measured in 1:10 water extracts). The same analytical pro-  cedures were used as those described previously (Stoop, 1981).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    In a study of this type large differences are possible in the relative im-  portance of processes that may occur under a laboratory situation where  dilute P solutions react with soil suspensions as compared with those under  field conditions where P fertilizer granules are in direct contact with soil  particles. Nevertheless, the laboratory provides an opportunity to clarify a  number of P sorption mechanisms by separating several factors which, under  natural conditions, are always confounded. Thereupon, it is possible to test  the practical relevance of laboratory results as was attempted by a pot expe-  riment in this case.    Effects of cations and cation valency on P solubility    The effect of various cations upon P adsorption was studied for the four  soils while salt concentration and pH were controlled.  Phosphate was added as NH4H2PO4 and the concentration of P in solution  determined after equilibration in 0.01 N CaCI2, MgC12, or KC1 solution. The  results demonstrated that the P concentration was much lower following  equilibration in solutions containing divalent cations such as Ca2+ and Mg2 than for a solution with K+ (Table I).  Another experiment, in which the effects of NH4H2PO4 and Ca(H2PO4)2  on P solubility were compared after equilibration in 0.01 N KC1 gave very  similar results. Phosphate solubility in the NH4-- phosphate systems was 79%,  57%, 24% and 16% higher for the Halii, Honokaa, Wahiawa and Waialua soil    62    TABLE I  Effects of cations on the concentration of P in solution following equilibration with  0.01 N KCI, MgCI2 and CaCI2 solutions.I    Soil          Treatments                    P in solution (ppm)    Honokaa    added P          pH            KCI        MgCl:      CaCl~  (u g P/g soil)  3000                           4.8                         0.63                0.44                0.40  1500             4.8            0.11        0.09        0.08    Halii         1500            4.8           1.70       1.20       1.00  750            4.8           0.12       0.10       0.09    Wahiawa       750            4.8           2.30       2.24       1.88  375            4.8           0.26       0.23       0.23    Waialua        375            5.8           3.90       3.57       3.59    *IPhosphate was added as NH4H2PO,.  samples, respectively, than in a system in which Ca-phosphate had been used  as a P source.  The cation effect on P solubility could be evaluated more easily for a  range of conditions, e.g., differences in soils, pH and adsorbed phosphate,  when expressed as a ratio (Rp):  PK  Rp   -  PCa  in which PK and PCa are the P concentrations after equilibration in 0.01 N  solutions of KCI and CaCl2, respectively. When Rp=l, P solubility was not  affected by one cation any more than the other.  Some of the Rp results are summarized in Table II. Note that Rp ap-  proached unity with increasing contents of permanent charge type clay min-  erals (2:1 layer silicate clays) and increasing contents of exchangeable  divalent cations in the soil (see also Fig. 1). Therefore, P solubility in the  Waialua soil will be independent on the P source used (NH4-, or Ca-phos-  phate). This result is similar to those obtained by Rajan and Fox (1972)  in their comparison of a Black soil from India, a Wahiawa soil and an Akaka  soil (Hydrandept).  Raising the suspension pH with Ca(OH)2 and the addition of phosphate as  NH4H2PO4 were both associated with increased Rp values (Table II). These  effects were most pronounced for the soils with the largest P sorption capa-  cities. In those highly weathered acid soils it appears therefore that the  amount of calcium present in the system is of critical importance to the  amount of phosphate remaining in solution.  Moreover, the cation effect, which was also studied as a function of equil-    63  TABLE II  Values for cation effects (Rp) on P solubility calculated for phosphate and pH treatments  after equilibration in 0.01 N KC1 and 0.01 N CaCl~; NH4H2PO, and Ca (OH)2 were used in  these treatments    Soil            Treatments                     Rp    added P            pH  (pg P/g soil)    Honokaa    Halii    Wahiawa    3000                4.8         1.58  1500          4.8      1.38  3000          5.8      2.25  1500                5.8         2.00    1500          4.8      1.66  750          4.8      1.33  1500                5.8         1.88    750                4.8         1.16  375                4.8         1.21  750           5.8      1.18  375                5.8         1.36    Waialua          375               5.8        1.06  190                5.8         1.08    ibration time, proved rather stable (Fig. 1). Only a slight decrease in _Rp with  time was recorded for the Honokaa and Wahiawa soils, thus indicating the  possibility of P precipitation. This result agrees with the lower residual effi-  ciencies of P fertilizers in these soils as reported by Fox et al. (1974).    2.5    1.0  k"  0    2.0  &gt;  a_ 1.5  n,*     Honokaa  Wahlawa  .~" tx------___.___..~              .A. Walalua    I            1               1  2         8           16  Days    Fig. 1. Cation effects on P solubility (Rp values) as a function of equilibration time.    64    The presence of a cation effect on P solubility, especially in the highly  weathered acid soils, could be attributed to processes such as specific adsorp-  tion of divalent cations and Ca fixation, as described previously {Stoop,  1980, 1981). Both processes will reduce the double-layer potential (~d) of  variable charge colloids. As a result, P adsorption could increase and P solu-  bility decrease. Obviously such a process will be less significant in the case of  nonspecific Ca adsorption by permanent charge type clay minerals or in soils  with high base status.  As could be expected on the basis of the Gouy-Chapman-Stern-Grahame  model, P solubilities are similarly affected by changes in salt concentration.  In an investigation by Barrow {1972) on highly weathered Australian soils,  the results demonstrated that increasing concentrations of CaC12 caused  major reductions in P solubility in the salt concentration range from 0 to  0.01 N, the range present in most soils under field conditions. Above 0.01 N  the effect levelled off strongly. Increasing CaC12 concentrations not only  enhanced the adsorption of phosphate but also of sulphate and molybdate,  indicating that interactions between Ca adsorption and anion adsorption are  not limited to phosphate alone.    Effect of pH on P solubility    Applying the Gouy-Chapman-Stern-Grahame model of the electrical  double layer on oxides, one can predict that with increasing pH, P adsorp-  tion should decrease. This phenomenon has been reported before, but in all  those studies pH was raised with NaOH, whereas for agricultural purposes  CaCO3 or Ca(OH)2 is applied.  Table III demonstrates the effects on P solubility when Ca(OH)2 is sub-  stituted for NaOH to raise pH from 4.8 to 5.8. As expected, P solubility in-  creased considerably when the pH was raised with NaOH. When Ca(OH)2 was  used to obtain the same pH increase, P solubility was only slightly increased,  or even decreased as in the Halii soil.  The results indicate that predicting changes in P solubility due to liming of  oxidic soils is uncertain, especially in the pH range of 5.0--6.5. The presence  of Ca:in liming materials will tend to counteract the effect of increased pH  per se, whereas the presence of exchangeable Ca: (e.g., from previous fer-  tilizer applications) may further lower P solubility in soils.  Obviously, the whole situation is rather different for a non-oxidic soil,  such as the Waialua series, with higher pH and higher exchangeable Ca levels  than the oxidic soils and a far lower P sorption capacity.    Cation effects on P solubility in relation to plant nutrient uptake    To test the relevance for plant nutrition of the previously described cation  effects on P solubility in oxidic softs, pot experiments were conducted and  the following data were considered: (1) P and cation solubility in the soils    65  TABLE III  Effect of pH on the concentration of P in solution when using NaOH and Ca(OH)2 to  raise the pH*~    Soil            Treatments                              P in  solution    added P            pH  (ug P/g soil)                        (ppm)    Honokaa    Halii    Wahiawa    Waialua    3000                4.8                  0.6  3000               5.8 NaOH          7.6  3000             5.8 Ca(OH)2       0.9    1500                4.8                  1.7  1500               5.8 NaOH          3.3  1500                  5.8 Ca(OH)2         1.5    750                4.8                  2.3  750               5.8 NaOH          5.1  750                  5.8 Ca(OH)2         2.7    375                5.8                  4.1  375               6.8 NaOH          3.8  375                6.8 Ca(OH)~         2.5    *1Equilibration was in 0.01 N KC1 and phosphate was added as NH4H~PO,.    following the harvest; (2) P and cation uptake (rag/pot); (3) dry matter yield  of the plants.  Following the harvest, soil samples from the various treatments were ana-  lysed for water-soluble cations and phosphate. In addition, P was also ana-  lysed in a 0.01 M CaCI2 medium, which is the standard medium used for  determinations of P adsorption isotherms.  Some of the results are presented in Table IV. The data for cation solubil-  ity were in general agreement with those obtained earlier with cation adsorp-  tion-release curves (Stoop, 1981) and show a lower solubility of all cations  with increasing P and/or decreasing Ca applications. As expected, P solubility  evaluated from water extracts dropped greatly with increasing Ca applica-  tions. This phenomenon was not reflected by P measurements in 0.01 M  CaC12 extracts (Table IV).  In response to the Ca and P applications, highly significant effects (P   0.01) on plant growth were recorded (Fig. 2). The major responses were  due to phosphate, but in addition a significant negative linear response was  recorded for Ca in the Wahiawa soil and a significant quadratic response to  Ca on the Halii soil. Summarizing, the maximum P response was obtained at  a higher Ca application rate in the Halii than in the Wahiawa soil, which was  consistent with the lower initial Ca content of the former (1.5 and 2.6 meq.  Ca/100 g soil for the Halii and Wahiawa samples, respectively). Any addi-    66  TABLE IV  Effects of Ca and P applications to the Wahiawa and Halii soils on the concentrations of P  and cations in solution as measured in 1:10 soil/water extracts*'    Soil      Treatment   Molar ratio  P in solution         Cations in solution  Ca:P of     (ppm)               (meq./1)  treatment    in water  in 0.01 M  Ca    Mg    K     Na  CaCI2    Wahiawa Ca3P2        2.0          0.21      0.14       1.53   0.44   0.41   2.38  Ca=P=         0.5           0.29       0.15        0.76   0.26   0.33   2.30  CaIP2.2       0              0.43       0.14         0.22   0.10   0.23   2.08    Halii      Ca3P~        0.5           0.09      0.03        0.85   0.30   0.63   2.30  Ca=P3*:      0.25          0.29      0.03        0.31   0.15   0.55   2.10  CaIP3         0             0.67       0.03        0.14   0.06   0.45   1.29    ,1 A comparison of P in solution measured in a 1:10 soil/0.01 M CaC12 extract is also in-  cluded.  *2Treatments giving maximum yields.    1.6    1.2    0,8  o    d  "u  &gt;-  1.6    1.2    0.8    o   LSD01  --..&lt;..  Hal{i  i        J        l  L.:aI       Ca 2       Ca 3  c~  [LsD  0  wah[aw~  I        ,I        I  CaI      Ca2      Ca3    Fig. 2. Yields of Sudangrass (g dry matter/pot) as a function of Ca and P treatments for  the Haiti and Wahiawa soils.    67    tional Ca applications to the Wahiawa soil only served to make the phos-  phate less available for uptake by plants, thereby reducing the overall dry  matter production (Table V). A similar process is suggested for the Halii soil  but only for the two highest Ca application rates.  With respect to cation availability, the Mg uptake data for the Halii soil  tend to confirm the notion of a reduction in the availability of particular  divalent cations in the presence of large P applications as salts of monovalent  cations.    TABLE V    Effects of Ca and P applications to the Wahiawa and Halii soils on dry matter production  (g/pot) and on nutrient uptake (mg/pot) by Sudangrass    Soil        Treatment    Molar ratio   Dry matter  Ca: P of      yield  treatment     (g/pot)    Nutrient uptake (rag/pot)    P       Ca     Mg     K    Wahiawa    Halii    Ca3P2         2.0             1.39             7.7     12.9     8.0      52  Ca2P2         0.5             1.49             8.7     11.2     8.5      59  CalP~.1      0               1.75            10.8     10.9     9.7      77    Ca3P3         0.5             1.42             5.6      9.7     7.8      65  Ca2P3         0.25            1.53             6.9      8.8     8.6      76  Ca1P3.1       0                1.42              5.8       5.5     6.9       78    *lTreatments giving maximum yields.    SUMMARY    In oxidic soils P solubility will generally be very low. As a consequence,  a minor change in P adsorption may greatly alter the amount of P in solu-  tion. It was found that Ca2+ drastically lowered P solubility, especially in  highly weathered acid soils, a phenomenon that could be predicted from the  Gouy-Chapman-Stern-Grahame model for the electric double layers of  variable charge colloids.  Growth and P-uptake of Sudangrass in a pot experiment were reduced by  Ca applications, indicating that the Ca: P ratio in phosphate fertilizers could  be an important factor in determining P fertilizer efficiency on highly  weathered soils. In this respect, further field experimentation using a range  of P fertilizers with increasing contents of calcium may offer interesting  results.  Another implication of the Ca/P interaction in highly weathered oxidic  softs refers to laboratory analyses for phosphate. Measurements of phosphate  in solution were greatly altered, depending on the extraction medium (water  or 0.01 M CaC12).    68    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Many thanks are due to the members of the Department of Agronomy  and Soils at the University of Hawaii. I am particularly indebted to Dr.  Robert L. Fox for providing the assistantship which made this study possible  but also for his valuable advice and criticism during the course of the various  investigations.    REFERENCES    Abruna, F., Chandler, J.V. and Pearson, R.W., 1964. Effects of liming on yield and com-  position of heavily fertilized grasses and on soil properties under humid tropical condi-  tions. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 28: 657--661.  Amarasiri, S.L. and Olsen, S.R., 1973. Liming as related to P solubility and plant growth  in an acid tropical soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 37: 716--721.  Bache, B.W., 1964. Aluminium and iron phosphate studies relating to soil, II. Reactions  between phosphate and hydrous oxide. J. Soil Sci., 15: 110--116.  Barber, S.A., Walker, J,M. and Vasey, E.H., 1963. Mechanisms for the movement of plant  nutrients from the soil and fertilizer to the plant root. S. Agric. Fd. Chem., 11: 204--  207.  Barrow, N.J., 1972. Influence of solution concentration of calcium on the adsorption of  phosphate, sulphate and molybdate by soils. Soil Sci., 113: 175--180.  Breeuwsma, A., 1973. Adsorption of ions on hematite (Fe203). Meded. Landbouw-  hogesch., Wageningen, 73-1.  Breeuwsma, A. and Lyklema, J., 1973. Physical and chemical adsorption of ions in the  electrical double layer on hematite (~ Fe20~). J. Colloid Interf. Sci., 43: 437--448.  Fox, R.L., De Datta, S.K. and Sherman, G.D., 1962. Phosphorus solubility and avail-  ability to plants and the aluminium status of Hawaiian soils as influenced by liming.  Trans. Int. Soc. Soft Sci. Joint Meeting Comm. IV and V, N.Z., pp. 574--583.  Fox, R.L., De Datta, S K. and Wang, J.M., 1964. Phosphorus and aluminium uptake by  plants from Latosols in relation to liming. Trans. 8th. Int. Congr. Soil Sci. Bucharest,  IV : 595--602.  Fox, R.L., Plucknett, D.L. and Whitney, A.S., 1968. Phosphate requirements of Hawaiian  Latosols and residual effects of fertilizer phosphorus. Trans. 9th. Int. Congr. Soil Sci.,  2 : 301--310.  Fox, R.L., Nishimoto, R.K., Thompson, J.R. and de la Pena, R.S., 1974. Comparative  external phosphorus requirements of plants growing in tropical soils. Trans. 10th.  Congr. Soil Sci. Moscow, IV : 232--239.  Hingston, F.J., Atkinson, R.J., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1967. Specific adsorption  of anions. Nature, 215 : 1459--1461.  Hingston, F.J., Atkinson, R,J., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1968. Specific adsorption  on goethite. Trans. 9th. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., I: 669--678.  Hingston, F.J., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1972. Anion adsorption by goethite and  gibbsite, I. The role of the proton in determining adsorption envelopes. J. Soil Sci.,  23 : 177--192.  Kittrick, J.A. and Jackson, M.L., 1955. Rate of phosphate reaction with soil minerals  and electron microscope observations on the reaction mechanism. Soil Sci. Soc. Am,  Proc., 19: 292--295.  Kittrick, J.A. and Jackson, M.L,, 1956. Electron microscope observations on the reaction  of phosphate with minerals leading to a unified theory of phosphate fixation in soils.  J. Soil Sci.. 7: 81--89.    69    Larsen, S., 1967. Soil phosphorus. Adv. Agron., 19: 151--210.  Molina, R. and Fassbender, H.W., 1972. Effect of liming on the forms and availability of  phosphorus and its uptake by plants in six Costa Rican soils. Z. Pflanzenernaehr.  Dueng. Bodenkd., 132: 81--87.  Muljadi, D., Posner, A.M. and Quirk, J.P., 1966. The mechanism of phosphate adsorption  by kaolinite, gibbsite and pseudo boehmite. J. Soil Sci., 17: 212--247.  Rajah, S.S.S. and Fox, R.L., 1972. Phosphate adsorption by soils, I. Influence of time  and ionic environment on phosphate adsorption. Comm. Soil Sci. Plant Anal., 3:  493--504.  Stoop, W.A., 1980. Ion adsorption mechanisms in oxidic soils; implications for point of  zero charge determinations. Geoderma, 23: 303--314.  Stoop, W.A., 1981. Evaluation of the cation status of oxidic soils using adsorption--  release curves. Geoderma, 26: 107--119.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           AbstractFactors affecting P solubility were studied for four Hawaiian soils: the Waialua, Wahiawa, Halii and Honokaa series, classified, respectively, as: Haplustoll, Eutrustox, Gibbsihumox and Hydrandept.Phosphate solubility in the oxidic soils depended mainly on salt concentration and cation valency. It was decreased by the accompanying cation according to: K &lt; Mg &lt;/ Ca. This cation effect on P solubility decreasedwith increasing contents of layer silicate clay minerals and/or increasing base saturation of the soil. Consequently, it was almost absent in the Haplustoll which contains montmorillonite and kaolinite.The P solubility in all four soils increased greatly when the pH was raised with NaOH. When Ca (OH)2 was used, however, this effect was almost completely eliminated due to the action of Ca ions. This result explains why in many fertility studies of oxidic soils even moderate liming rates were not found to increase the P availability.In a subsequent pot experiment evidence was obtained on the negative effect of the Ca ion on P uptake by Sudangrass from the Gibbsihumox and Eutrustox.