 126    conclusive results, the way in which they have been set up can be a good  guide to avoid future errors.  The volume is well printed, with clearly represented tables and figures,  and any person interested in tropical agriculture will find in it a great amount  of very valuable data.    FRANS DE CONINCK  (Ghent)    Soil Chemistry. H. Bohn, B. McNeal and G. O'Connor. Wiley, New York,  N.Y., 1979, 2.50.    Soil chemistry texts are beginning to appear in some numbers nowadays  on publishers lists, to the great benefit of both teachers and the taught in  colleges and universities. Up to only a very few years ago the amount of  secondary literature was sparse and such as there was only selectively recom-  mendable; we mostly relied on the relevant portions of the "bible"-- Russell's  Soil Conditions and Plant Growth, and such reviews as had sufficient peda-  gogic clarity to illuminate the darker areas of research uncertainty. All this  is changing, and not before time. Perhaps publisher.~ are realising that, in the  modern world, soil chemistry might just be one of t~e most important  branches of chemistry there is.  So, now that we have the responsibility of evaluating and comparing  books on soil chemistry, how does Soil Chemistry by Bohn, McNeal and  O'Connor {Professors of Soil Chemistry at, respectively, the universities of  Arizona, Washington State and New Mexico State} stand? The book can  briefly be described as a fairly elementary text almost wholly devoted to  inorganic aspects of the subject. It is strikingly clearly written, as would be  expected in a volume which stems from long experience of actually teaching  the material involved, and indeed in places has a relaxed and almost conver-  sational style which when succesful, as here, can only be produced by writers  wholly in command of their subject. It initially seems strange that three  authors should be thought desb/able for a text at this level in a not very wide  area of toil science, but there is throughout a remarkable uniformity of style.  In short, this book has the virtues of authority and clarity, is reasonably  priced, and might be thought worthy of a large undergraduate audience.  Unfortunately there are qualifications to be made, though perhaps some  relate only to the book's title. First, the book, since it contains only 41/~ pages  on organic matter out of some 300, cannot really claim to cover soil chem-  istry even at an elementary level; the material in this over-brief survey, which  consists cf Bear's (1964) version of the acid/base fractionation followed by  an hypothetical humic acid structure, can hardly be held tobe illuminating.  There is a more serious point to be made with respect te soil chemistry as it  affects plan nutrition, obviously ,an area of key application. Presumably the    127    book is aimed at students who may not be able to afford a wide range of  textbooks and who may justifiably hope that Soil Chemistry covers soil  chemistry. But what do we find, for example, on nitrogen, that hardy annual  of the soil chemistry examination paper?: 3 pages (beginning, "Nitrogen...  is still the most-studied element of soil chemistry...") in the chapter on  "Important Ions" (42 pages in total); just over 2 pages on N as a redox element,  plus a few mentions in a short composite survey of C, N, S and O in the same  context; approximately a page in a 2 page look at major anions (NO] com-  pared to SO4:-, CI- and HCO]); and finally, short single mentions of N in the  atmosphere, with respect to mineralisation inhibition, and with respect to  the role of Mo in N-fixing microorganisms. In summary, nitrogen is treated  scrappily and themelessly -- and this is not useful in a textbook with this  title.  The book is far stronger on the main physicochemical topics: cation ex-  change (difficult at this level), acidity, solid phase chemistry, redox etc. Thus  it has a good chapter on basic chemical principles (because the perceived  readers will have "varied educational backgrounds") and a very good one on  "weathering and soil development". Given this bias to the subject, it was an  error of judgement to have used so many non- SI units. Litres and angstroms  are all very well, but a teaching text still using kcal. and dynes (! p. 157) can  only puzzle students long taught in the ways of joules and newtons. Some  other points should be looked at in any future edition. The proposed mech-  anism for phosphate adsorption on an iron oxide surface (Fig. 6.4) is incor-  rect: Parfitt has convincingly demonstrated the non.reactivity of C-type  hydroxyls, though these are shown as exchanging here. Indeed Fig. 6.2 shows  essentially the same reaction, but in a different way, and is also wrong. What  does an elementary student make of the quite unexplained (and perhaps  unexplainable) ligand group- PO4HI.s ? Earlier we have been told that SO~-  is non-specifically adsorbed, a myth encouraged only by the wide separation  of the pK of the acid and the pzc (point of zero charge, unfortunately abbre-  viated to the non-standard zpc in the text) of most soil materials. Altogether,  the chapter on "Anion and Molecular Retention" leaves a lot to be desired.  There are a number of mostly smaller points in other chapters. It might just be  enough to quote from p. 207: "Presently base saturation is a criterion of  genesis in the United States classification scheme" -- a statement which would,  I hazard, stimulate mixed feelings in the U.S. Soil Survey.  A first edition cannot be expected to be perfect in production. The book  is generally attractively laid out, but there are quite a number of examples  of either sleepy proof-reading or sub-editing. Somebody should have spotted  the repetition of p.252, "The alkali metals are strong electron donors, are  strong reducing agents, and are avid electron donors", not to mention the  misprint in tbe Preface. More serious are, for example, the unnumbered ref-  erences appended to Table 2.10 (which culpably includes Standard Gibbs  Free Energies for compounds as important as gibbsite and kaolinite apparently  taken from an unpublished PhD thesis} and an uncomplete reference (to    128    Lindsay) on p. 66. The publisher's inability to decide which of two type founts  to use for the lower case "1" in the AI appearing in mineral structure diagrams  is irritating and unnecessary.  I find this a limited book; it does some things well, with clear explanations.  It is only of intermediate level (it could not be recommended for degree  students in soil science) and does not tackle soil chemistry confidently as a  part ,~f soil science. I shall recommend students reading soils as a subsidiary  degree subject to look at some sections, though not the book as a whole.    CHRISTOPHER MOTT  (Reading)    Stabilized Earth Roads. Developments in Geotechnical Engineering, 19. A.  K~zdi. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 1979, 327 pp., Dfl. 145.00.    In this most interesting book, the author reviews the theoretical principles  (physical, chemical and of soil mechanics), on which is based the praxis of  earth roads stabilization, as well as the experience accumulated during the  last 40 years on this subject. Much of the presented data originates from  the research carried out by the author in the Soil Mechanics Laboratory of  the Budapest Technical University.  Although some lime stabilization had already been used in the antiquity,  re~d road development was made only in the 19th century (macadam roads)  and especially at the beginning of the 20th century, where speed and eco-  nomics were essential. This led to the use of stabilized soil for secondary  roads. In Chapter 1, a short economic and historical background is presented.  In Chapter 2, the author describes the physical and chemical aspects of  soil stabilization. Fundamental notions of soil physics are recollected  (A~terberg limits, grain-size distribution, soil classifications, etc.). Testing  methods are given. Emphasis is put on particles components properties and  their intercorrelation (water-solid relations).  Chapter 3 deals with mechanical soil stabilization, i.e., without the addi-  tion of any foreign matter. Notion of void ratio is discussed, as well as  mixtures methods, mixtures properties and effects of water on the mix.  Stabilization with cement is studied in Chapter 4. Different types are  considered, according to the content of cement, the type of soil and of  additives. Interaction between cement and soil, properties of cement-treated  soils, effects of construction processes and additives are fully considered,  while design and testing of soil--cement mixtures are explained.  The object of Chapter 5 is stabilization with lime (calcium oxide or  hydroxide). Physical and chemical effects of lime are studied, together with  the influence of lime on the physical properties of the soil, with or without  additives. Design of soil--lime mixtures is also explained.  Similarly, Chapter 6 deals with stabilization with bitumen and tar. The                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              