Geoderma, 27 (1982) 139--176                                                  139  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SOME HIGHLY WEATHERED SOILS OF PUERTO RICO, 3. CHEMICAL  PROPERTIES* 1    ROBERT L. FOX  Department of Agronomy and Soil Science, University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii  (U.S.A.)  (Accepted for publication June 18, 1981 )    ABSTRACT    Fox, R.L., 1982. Some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 3. Chemical properties.  Geoderma, 27 : 139--176.    Some chemical properties of 11 soils developed in highly weathered regoliths in Puerto  Rico have been recorded. Particular attention has been given to properties which reflect  the extent to which weathering has progressed and to properties which may be most use-  ful for developing valid soil management practices.  If the PiCa soil were excluded the saturation extracts of Oxisols generally contained  less Si than the Ultisols. The saturation extract of Pifia soil, which was 89% quartz sand,  contained 10 ppm Si, a value out of keeping with highly weathered soils. Phosphate solu-  bility was greatest in the Pi~'a soil also. Phosphate adsorption by the Puerto Rico soils,  when corrected for dilution by sand, was approximately that of highly weathered soils of  Hawaii, North Carolina or Colombia. Most of the soils contained more than 4000 kg S/ha  in the 120~m profiles. The most striking difference between the Oxisol and Ultisol  groups was in extractable aluminum. In general, these Oxisols have been weathered be-  yond the point where aluminum is readily extracted with a neutral salt. The pH at which  net charge of the soils was zero was lower than the soil pH usually encountered in the  field. The soils were poorly buffered at low pH. As a group, the Oxisols contained less ex-  changeable K than the Ultisols. In 6 of the 11 soils, both calcium and magnesium were  &lt; 1 meq./100 g in some horizon. In most soil samples, the balance among exchangeable  cations was appropriate for reasonable potassium nutrition. Even so, the quantity of ex-  changeable nutrient cations was low in most cases. Mineralization of organic nitrogen  tended to stop with NH4+ in the acid soils.    INTRODUCTION    Many generalizations of doubtful validity have been promulgated and per-  petuated about "tropical soils". One example is the concept that soils of the  tropics are invariably highly weathered. In fact, many soils of the tropics are  so highly weathered that little remains except sesquioxides and some 1:1  layer silicatesbut there are also numerous examples of soils in which 2:1-    * ~Journal Series No. 1745 of the Hawaii Agricultural Experiment Station.    0016-706118110000--00001502.75 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    140    type clays influence, or even dominate, the chemistry and physics of the soil.  Because many soils of the tropics have reached an advanced stage of  weathering, it is frequently assumed that chemical weathering is greatly  accelerated there as compared with the temperate zone. This is not always  the case. In most tropical areas rainfall is seasonal. The dry season may re-  tard chemical processes just as effectively as the cool season does in tem-  perate zones. Some land surfaces have been stable enough, however, so that  weathering processes have operated upon the same soil material during a very  long period of time, thus leading to advanced stages of weathering.  But even in the tropics, rejuvenating influences have operated on soils.  A study of tropospherically derived quartz in soils of the Hawaiian Islands  suggests that the oldest softs may be on the order of 200 000--500 000 years  old (Jackson et al., 1971). Syers et al. (1969) have reported on accessions of  quartz from North Africa in the Caribbean Islands. This suggests that soil  materials on the older geomorphic surfaces are appreciably diluted with  aeolian materials. Dilution continues to the present time. A dust haze, which  had its origin in the Sahara, recently appeared over Puerto Rico (see for ex-  ample, The San Juan Star, August 1, 1972 and January 11, 1974).  One of the commonly held misconceptions about the tropics is that tem-  peratures there are torrid. Temperatures in most areas of the humid tropics  can be described as continuously warm. The unique feature about tropical  temperatures is the absence of extremes. Temperatures of 40 such as can  be experienced on a hot summer day in the Great Plains of North America  are seldom, if ever, recorded in most of the tropical zone. The 30 soil tem-  perature isotherm (at 10 cm depth) moves into the southern U.S.A., in July  while at the same time the 25 isotherm falls in tropical South America  (Chang, 1958). It is probable, however, that microbiological processes are  different for softs which are continuously warm and for those which are  seasonally warm.  Inasmuch as some concepts about the tropical environment may be in-  appropriate, if not inaccurate, it follows that some of the concepts about the  chemistry and nutritional status of softs of the tropics based on those  assumptions should be reexamined. A partial listing includes concepts about  soil pH and A1 in relation to liming; organic matter content and N mineraliza.  tion; cation and anion exchange capacities and the nature of the charge on  soil colloids;silicon solubility as it relates to weathering and availability of P  and S; and'~he magnitude and reversibility of phosphate and sulfate adsorp-  tion.  An important point should be made here: there is no such thing as a  unique "tropical soil". All 10 orders in the U.S. Soil Taxonomy (Soft Survey  Staff, 1975) occur in Puerto Rico and Hawaii. This is not to imply that  climate has had no effect in soft formation. The properties which are most  frequently associated with softs of the tropics are also expressed in some  degree by certain softs of the temperate zone.  This is a study of selected, highly weathered soils representing a range of    141    soils formed in highly weathered regoliths of Puerto Rico. The soils studied  do not necessarily represent the tropics as a whole, although the combina-  tion of soil forming factors which have produced these soils can be found  elsewhere in the tropics.  Part 1 of this study (Beinroth, 1982) describes the environmental setting  and classification of the 11 soils investigated here. Part 2 (Jones et al., 1982)  deals with the mineralogy of the same soils. The immediate purpose of the  present study is to record some chemical properties of these same highly  weathered soils. As data accumulate, comparisons may be made among high-  ly weathered soils from Puerto Rico, Hawaii and elsewhere. The ultimate ob-  jective is to transfer soil management data more widely and with greater con-  fidence within the tropics and between climatic zones.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Eleven soils, described in detail in Parts 1 and 2 of this study were ex-  amined. The soils chiefly represent a range of Ultisols and Oxisols of Puerto  Rico. One Inceptisol is included.  The list of chemical properties examined is not exhaustive. The idea was  to give particular attention to those properties that would reflect the extent  to which these soils are presumed to have been weathered and to those prop-  erties that might be most useful for developing sound soil management  practices.  In some instances data were utilized from other investigations, chiefly soil  characterization data from the U.S.D.A. Soil Conservation Service (Soil  Survey Staff, 1967) and unpublished data of J. Figarella, Agricultural Re-  search Service, U.S.D.A., Rio Piedras, Puerto Rico.  Silicon was extracted with water in the ratio 1:10 soil to water and with  buffered phosphate solutions as described by Fox et al. (1967).  Silicon in saturation extracts was determined by placing soil samples  (&gt; 50 g) into leaching tubes. Water was added until the soils were saturated  after which the systems were covered and allowed to stand for 3 days. Then  1-ml aliquots of water were added to the columns until 8--10 ml of solution  was displaced. The displaced solution was clarified by high-speed centrifuga-  tion and Si was determined in 1- to 5-ml aliquots of the extract.  Phosphate adsorption curves were constructed from data obtained by  equilibrating 3-g samples of soil for 6 days at 25 in 30 ml of 0.01 M CaCI2  containing various amounts of Ca(H~PO4)2 (Fox and Kamprath, 1970).  Shaking was for 2 one-half hour periods each day. Standard phosphate ad-  sorption was determined by interpolating phosphate adsorption isotherms at  0.2 ppm P in solution (Beckwith, 1964).  Sulfate adsorption curves were constructed as for phosphate curves except  that equilibration was with Na2SO4 in 0.01 M CaCl2 for 24 hours with  constant shaking (Hasan et al., 1970).  Adsorbed sulfate was extracted by four repeated extractions of soil sam-    142    ples with a Ca(H:PO4)2 solution containing 500 ppm P. The soil solution  ratio for each extraction was 1:5 (Fox et al., 1964).  Point of zero net charge. 4-g samples of soil and 20-ml aliquots of 0.002 M  NaC1 were placed into eight weighed 50-ml centrifuge tubes. The tubes were  shaken 30 min, centrifuged and the supernatant solution discarded. Volume  was adjusted to 10 ml by weighing 0.002 M NaC1 into the tubes. Increments  of HC1 or NaOH were added to establish pH from about 3 to 8. One tube re-  ceived only 0.002 M NaC1 and water. Volume was made to 20 ml with water  (final concentration = 0.001 M NaCl). The soil material was resuspended  daily for at least 4 days. Suspension pH was determined in the centrifuge  tube with a combination electrode (slow KC1 release). After pH was deter-  mined, 0.2 M NaC1 (about 0.9 ml) was added to give 0.01 M NaC1; the sus-  pension was again equilibrated for 1 day and pH determined again. The cycle  was repeated at 0.1 M and 1.0 M NaC1, making these concentrations by  adding weighed portions of solid salt. Suspension pH was plotted against  amounts of added acid or base. The point of intersection of the curves con-  necting points of equal concentration of salt is the point of zero net charge.  The intersection has been referred to as the zero point of charge or ZPC. The  notation PZNC is more appropriate because the system is not without charge  but, in the ideal system, is one with equal positive and negative charges. The  potentiometric titration method used here does not take into account any  permanent charge the soil may have. Thus in nearly all soils there will be  some negative charge at the point (pH0) where the curves intersect. When the  permanent component of charge is taken into account, as is the case when  equal anion and cation adsorption is the criterion, the pH will usually be less  than the pH0.  Liming curves were based on titrations with Ca(OH)2. The final soil to  water ratio was 1:6. Suspensions were shaken every day and pH was read  after 8 days of equilibration.  Aluminum was extracted with 1 N KC1 at a ratio of 1 g soil material per  25 ml extractant. Shaking was for 30 min followed by centrifugation. There  was no washing with KC1.  Exchangeable basic cations were displaced with neutral, N NH4OAc using  the batch method.  Calcium-potassium adsorption curves were constructed from data ob-  tained by equilibrating 3-g samples of each surface soil in 30 ml of 0.0025 N  solution of KC1 and/or CaC12. The soil solution ratio was 1:10 and equilib-  rium time was 2 days. There were 6 points on the adsorption curves.  Incomplete (small) exchange was measured by equilibrating soil materials  in 0.0025 N solutions of NaCL. The soft:solution ratio was 1:10 and equilib-  rium time was 2 days. Cations that had been displaced into the solution  were determined in a clear extract obtained by centrifugation.  Nitrogen mineralization was determined during 14 days incubation at  30 using methods of incubation described by Stanford and Hanway  (1955) except that the soil was mixed with crushed Perlite (&lt; 2 mm).    143    Following incubation, and after nitrate had been removed by leaching,  ammonium was extracted with 1 M KCI. Separate samples were used for  determinations of initial NH4in the soils. Ammonium was determined, fol-  lowing replacement with K by steam distillation and acid titration.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Silicon solubility in highly weathered soils    Silicate weathering and leaching results in the removal of Si from soils and  the accumulation of A1, Fe, Ti and other oxides. These changes are accom-  panied by decreased Si-solubility in water. Soils having distinct mineralogical  systems can be ranked with respect to Si-content and -solubility, as follows:  2:1 clays &gt; 1:1 clays &gt; Al and Fe oxides (Fox et al., 1967). The relationship  is probably indirect, inasmuch as crystalline mineral surfaces frequently are  coated with amorphous, gel-like materials (Jones and Uehara, 1973). The  composition of amorphous materials probably reflects the composition of  underlying crystalline minerals (Fox et al., 1971).  The implication is that Si-solubility, when combined with information on  phosphate-extractable Si, can give valuable integrated information about the    0    y  40   "/~f"  /.~DAGUEY  I  12 ~t~ LOS GUINEO$  o    2 .~    ,Io  40    " _._._J  ~RRI~q    A  ~a  o    !  S  i         a    L~j, To.-',~  ....     v_CATAU.A  j/  z,,           (/  (   /            if  ,.         c  [     // o  o     2:,    ~o    o    2'.,,.o'    ;,    '  I0.0  SI     (ppm)  Fig. 1. Concentration of Si in saturation extracts from profile samples of 11 highly  weathered soils from Puerto Rico.    144    extent and degree of Si-saturation of reactive surfaces in soils, and, indirect~  ly, information about the crystalline materials as well.  Silicon in the saturation extracts of soils (Fig. 1) should be a better  measure of the intensity factors associated with weathering than is Si ex-  tractable at wide solution-to-soil ratios because extractable Si is dependent  upon capacity factors of soils and these capacity factors, in their turn, are  greatly dependent on specific surface. As evaluated by Si-concentrations in  saturation extracts, the Carreras and PiCa soils are less weathered than the  other soils. Highest Si-concentration was associated with the Pifia A horizon.  Although the Pifia soil is mostly quartz sand, the surface horizon equilibrated  at 10 ppm Si whereas the 95--125-cm sample equilibrated with less than 5  ppm Si in solution. Apparently quartz was not controlling Si-solubility at all  depths. The pattern of Si-solubility as a function of depth (Fig. 1D) suggests  that recycled Si (amorphous phytoliths) is responsible for relatively high Si-  solubility in the Ap horizon and that Si-depletion by roots is responsible for  relatively low solubility of Si in the depth increment 20--34 cm.  For three Oxisols (Coto, Matanzas and Nipe soils) and one Ultisol (Los  Guineos Soil) Si-solubility in the subsoil horizons was extremely low and this  was accompanied by low Si in saturation extracts from the surface horizons.  The ratio of phosphate-extractable Si to water-extractable Si has been sug-  gested as being related to the surface areas with which silicate and phosphate  may interact. For example, Fox et al. (1967} report that this ratio was  greatest for Hydrandepts (Hydrol Humic Latosols) and lowest for a Gibbsi-  humox (Humic Ferruginous Latosols). Means for Puerto Rico soils are as  follows:    Surface soil    Subsoil  (about 50 cm depth)    Ultisols and Inceptisol        4.2            13.2  Oxisols                    13.5            35.9    Although the means for the two soil groups are distinctly different, there  was considerable overlap, the most noticeable examples being the PiCa and  Torres soils (Table I).  Absolute values for Si extracted with water and phosphate are presented  in Table I. For comparative purposes, Table I contains data on extractable  Si from some Hawaii soils (Fox et al., 1967). Note that the PiCa soil was ex-  cluded when the means for Oxisols were calculated. The PiCa soil is distinct-  ly different from other softs from the standpoint of Si-solubility. This is a  consequence of its quartz mineralogy and sandy texture, which, unfortu-  nately, are not taken into account above the family level of classification.  The means suggest that, as a group, the Puerto Rico soils are weathered to  approximately the same degree as the Hawaiian Oxisols; that the Puerto Rico  Oxisols, taken collectively, are slightly more weathered than the Ultisols; and    TABLE I  Silicon extracted from Puerto Rico soils as compared with selected soils of Hawaii    145    Soil              Si-extracted    1:10 water extract  (ppm in solution)    saturation extract  (ppm in solution)    phosphate extractable  (ug/g in soil)    surface     subsoil.1   surface    subsoil     surface    subsoil  soil                    soil                    soil    Puerto Rico soils:    Inceptisol  Picacho        0.80       1.06       2.16       2.88        34        52  Ultisols  Los Guineos    1.66       0.19       1.98       0.21        49        76  Carreras        1.90       0.99       7.71       3.84        67        34  Daguey        1.95       0.90       5.6        1.26        77        42  Torres         2.54       0.67       8.08       0.91       159         76    Mean          2.0        0.7        5.8        1.6         88        55    Oxisols  Matanzas       0.86       0.42       1.54       0.54       399        341  Catalina        1.78       0.83       4.70       1.21       109        127  Coto           1.14       0.51       1.86       0.82       104        118  Bayamon       1.07       1.25       2.38       1.63        67        147  PiCa            0.24       0.67      10.0        7.6           8         36  Nipe         0.66      0.32      1.41      0.46       66      148    Mean* ~          1.1         0.7         2.4         0.9         149        176    Hawaii soils:  Torrox and  Eutrustox  Mean 11 soils   1.7        --         --         --         162  Gibbsihumox  Mean 6 soils    0.7        --         --         --          40    w    *~Subsoil depth is about 50 cm; *2PiHa excluded from means.    that the Gibbsihumox in Hawaii are further along in a weathering sequence  than the Ultisols or Oxisols of Puerto Rico.    Phosphorus in highly weathered soils    Phosphorus contents of softs have been proposed as an indicator of pedo-  genetic weathering processes (Smeck, 1973) and doubtless have value in that  regard. The approach taken here with regard to P, however, was different  from those discussed by Smeck. Phosphate adsorption isotherms were con-    146    structed for all surface soil and some subsurface samples. The value of the  approach was discussed by Beckwith (1964).  When values for phosphate sorbed are plotted against log P remaining in  equilibrium soil solutions, approximately straight-line curves are obtained.  The slopes of these curves give information about the phosphate buffering  capacities of soils. The intercept at zero sorption of added phosphate is an  estimate of phosphate in the soil solution, a value which is related to plant  nutrition (Fox and Kamprath, 1970). Amounts of phosphate required to  attain desired levels of P in the equilibrium solution can be estimated direct-  ly from the graph.  Many factors -- soil mineralogy, chemistry, biology, and management-  history -- are integrated in phosphate adsorption isotherms, which suggests  this measurement as a valuable adjunct to soil classification criteria. It would  therefore seem appropriate to include phosphate adsorption characteristics in  the criteria for soil classification at the management level, i.e., among the soil  family criteria.  Phosphate adsorption curves for the surface horizons of all soils are pre-  sented in Fig. 2. Clearly, there are great differences among the soils. The ad-  sorption curve for the PiCa soil has little slope and the curve is displaced far  to the right in comparison with other soils. The obvious explanation for the  relatively fiat slope is that the soil contains 89% quartz sand. When the slope  of the adsorption curve, in the interval 0.15--0.25 ppm P in solution, was  corrected for clay content, adsorption by the PiCa soil was 125 ~g/g, which    IOO(  Q 50C  {~.  o    ////    ,  I CATALI NA                      II  /i      //,"        //  2 N,PE                        II   ' I     ,~//       I/   ~o~ ~o.os          // //   #/    /7  4 TORREB                    //  I /     /7 ,"        //  5 P.cAc.o                 Z~ ,//    ,'/I      I  ~.~TANZAS               /~  / /     ///  a COTO               / I / /    //,'      /7  aC~RERAS            / / / /"   -,i  /   //    //  ,o_o.    ////  //        //,?" s.X.-'  0.01             0.1               1.0              I0  P IN SOLUTION    (ppm)    Fig. 2. Phosphate adsorption curves for surface soil samples of selected highly weathered  soils from Puerto Rico.    147  TABLE II  Adsorption of phosphate by highly weathered surface soil materials of Puerto Rico in  relation to soil pH, clay content and Si in the saturation extract    Soils              P sorbed at standard      Slope of P   pH       Clay      Si  concentration            adsorption  (water)   (%)       (ppm)  curve* 1    (ug P/g     (ug P/g     (#g P/g  soil)         clay)        clay)    Inceptisol  Picacho         365        1140         280       4.7       32        2.2  Ultisols  Los Guineos     555         760         180        4.8       73         2.0  Carreras         210         340          88        5.0       62         7.7  Daguey        340       520       108      5.0     66       5.6  Torres           490         750         142        5.3       65         8.1    Mean (5 soils)   392         702         160       5.0      60        5.1    Oxisois  Matanzas        365         430          88       7.9      85        1.5  Catalina         710         860         166        5.1       83         4.7  Coto            260         420          90        5.8       62         1.9  Bayamon       155         390          60       5.9      40        2.4  PiCa               8          90         125        4.6        9        10.0  Nipe            660        1200         290        5.1       55         1.4    Mean (PiKa  excluded)       430         660         139        5.5*2     65         2.4    * ~Phosphate adsorbed per gram clay for the increment 0.15---0.25 ppm P in solution.  *2Both the PiKa and Matanzas soils omitted from this mean.    was only slightly lower than the mean for the other Oxisols, 139 pg/g  {Table II).  Phosphate solubility at zero P added ranged from 0.006 to 0.016 pg/ml  for all except the PiCa soil which was higher by an order of magnitude.  Relatively small P inputs from the use of fertilizers, or as the result of P-  mobilization in the P-cycle, will cause big positive shifts of P-solubility in the  poorly buffered PiCa soil. Phosphate withdrawal by plants will produce com-  parable shifts in the opposite direction.  There are some apparent relationships between soluble Si and phosphate  sorption. For example the displacement of the P adsorption isotherm (PiCa  soil) to the right may well be related to relatively high Si-solubility. Likewise  the Carreras soil has relatively low phosphate adsorption and high Si-solubfl-  ity, whereas the Nipe and Los Guineos softs are among the highest in P-  retention and are among the lowest in Si-solubility.    148    This is consistent with the relationship between P-sorption and degree of  Si-depletion from amorphous materials as was determined along a transect  of Hawaii soils (Fox et al., 1971) and with the observation that capacity for  P-adsorption increased with increasing soil weathering (decreasing Si-solubil-  ity) in Andepts of Costa Rica {Fox, 1974).  Mean standard P-adsorption for the Puerto Rico soils was 374 pg P/g soil,  similar in magnitude to that reported for soils of the Llanos Orientales of  Colombia (Fox, 1974) and for a Hapludult of North Carolina (Fox and  Kamprath, 1970). It ranks medium on a scale suggested by Juo and Fox  (1977), but it is an order of magnitude higher than for representative soils of  north-central USA (R.L. Fox and E.J. Kamprath, unpublished data, 1968).  There were no differences in phosphate adsorption between the soil orders  represented by the Puerto Rico softs. Mean phosphate adsorption at standard  P concentration (0.2 ppm) was about 10% greater for the Oxisols than for  the Ultisols, but the Oxisols contained about 9% more clay than the Ultisols.  In one respect, it is not surprising that there was no clear separation in  phosphate adsorption between the Ultisols and Oxisols. Mineralogy and tex-  ture, important factors controlling many important soil properties including  phosphate adsorption, are the main criteria used at the family level of Soil  Taxonomy but are used less prominently at higher-categoric levels. To rele-  gate such important criteria to low categories in the classification scheme is  not, in my opinion, in the best interest of a taxonomic system that aspires  to usefulness.    Phosphate adsorption by subsurface soil materials    Phosphate adsorption by materials from B21 horizons was greater than by  surface soil materials. Table III presents some examples. The relative dif-  ference between B21 and surface soil samples in the amounts of P adsorbed is  approximately the same for Oxisols and the Ultisols. Differences between  the surface soil and B horizon were less for the Picacho series, an Inceptisol,  than for three of the other four softs.  Probably at least four factors are responsible for less P adsorption by sur-  face soil than by subsurface samples even when clay and oxide contents are  uniform.  (1) Cycling of P by plants has enriched the surface horizon with P at the  expense of subsurface horizons.  (2) Blocking of phosphate adsorption sites by organic anions associated  with plant residue decomposition.  (3) Cycling of Si by plants so that the surface soil is enriched at the ex-  pense of the subsurface horizons. Silicates then react with weathering pro-  ducts which would otherwise immobilize P by precipitation or adsorption.  (4) Periodic dessication of the surface leading to relatively low reactivity  of amorphous gel materials in the surface soft.    149  TABLE III  Phosphate sorbed from solution at 0.2 ppm P in the final solution by surface and sub-  surface (B21 horizon) soil materials of selected highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico    Soil           Phosphate adsorbed (ug P/g soil)            Sorption subsurface    surface               subsurface           Sorption surface  (B21)    Picacho        320                  480                 1.5  Torres         370                  860                 2.3  Catalina        700                 1130                 1.6  Bayamon      150                  280                 1.9  Nipe          650                1450                2.2    Apparently the argillic horizon in the Ultisol profiles, one of the main  features which distinguishes Ultisols from Oxisols, is not the significant  factor responsible for increased phosphate adsorption in the Torres soil.  Oxisols gave the same pattern. Neither are there apparent relationships be-  tween soil pH or active aluminum and phosphate adsorption. This should  come as no surprise inasmuch as phosphate adsorption is much less pH-de-  pendent than sulfate or molybdate adsorption (Barrow, 1970). In fact, if Ca  was held constant, phosphate adsorption by one Hawaii Oxisol was not  changed by adjusting soil pH with Ca(OH)2 over the range usually en-  countered in Oxisols (Fox and Benav~des, 1974). Coleman et al. (1960)  demonstrated that phosphate sorption increased to a maximum near pH 7 as  an Al--clay system was titrated with Ca(OH)2 but differences in sorption in  the pH range 5.5--7.0 were small.  The ratios of P sorbed by the B12 horizons (mean depth 30 cm) to P  sorbed by the surface horizon was, on average, 1.9. This suggests that loss of  the surface soil by erosion will increase the P fertilizer requirement for P-  demanding crops by a factor of about 2 because such crops require about 0.2  ppm P in solution (Fox, 1979).    Amounts and distribution of sulfate sulfur in soil profiles    One of the striking features of most highly weathered soils is that large  quantities of sulfate have accumulated somewhere in the profile, assuming of  course that there is sufficient surface area to hold the sulfate. This is the  pattern for most of the Puerto Rico soils investigated in this study. Details of  the data are presented in Table IV. Typically, adsorbed sulfate increased as a  function of depth in a profile until a maximum was reached at about 100 cm.  Usually, water solubility of the adsorbed sulfate was low but much of the  sulfate could be desorbed by repeated extractions with phosphate solutions.  Barrow (1970) has shown that sulfate adsorption is inversely related to  soil pH which explains why the Matanzas soil (pH 7.9, Table II) contained    150    TABLE IV    Extractable sulfate sulfur, solubility of sulfate, and calculated sulfate adsorption maxima  of some highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico  Soil             Depth       Extractable* ~   SO4-S.2    Sulfate-S      Sulfate     sat.  increment   SO4-S          0--120 cm solubility* ~   adsorpt.  (cm)        (~g/g)         (kg/ha)    (ppm)        max.*'  (~g S/g   (%)  soil)    Inceptisol  Picacho        0--18        16           4000        0.5             94        17  18--35        16                        1.5           280         6  35--80       60                        1.0           640        10  60--85      340                        0.8           710        48  85--130     597                         0.8            970        62  130--165    392                         0.7            720        55    Ultisols  Los Guineos   0--8         20           4540        0.4             98        20  8--25       80                        0.4           209        40  25--45      190                        1.2           670        28  45--65      326                        4.2           830        25  65--90      452                        3.2          1330        34  90--150     441                        4.0           870        51  150--200     381                        1.8           793        48  200--250     200                        0.3           410        49    Ca~er~          0--14        46           4200        4.9             70        66  14--28      180                       12.0           210        86  28---55      356                       22             370        96  55--80      353                       19             400        88  80--110     307                       20             340        90  110--125     290                       20             320        91    Daguey          0--10       10          4120       0.6           51       20  10--30      170                        3.0           435        39  30--60      250                        1.5           548        46  60--95      373                        1.5           671        56    To~es            0--10      280           9210       19             270       104  10--30      819                       10             990        83  30--50      740                        9.4           800        92  50--90      589                        1.6           910        65  90--125     537                        2.8           830        65    Oxmo~  Matanz~      0--35       12           266      12              12      100  35--70       20                      2.5            67       28  70--100      30                        1.8             50        60    151    Catalina          0--16      414         16 780        6             930        45  16--35     1080                       16            1180        92  35--60     1310                       16            1430        92  60--80     1267                        2            1720        74  80--120    1225                        5            1730        71  120--130     195                        3             860        23    Coto              0--13        17           5620        0.4            48        35  13--25      293                       10             323        91  25--45      265                        5             311        85  45--65      380                       21             411        92  65--90      480                        8             475       101  90--125     553                        8             590        94    Bayamon    0--9         38           2230        9               38      100  9--30      160                       24             139      115  30--60      100                        8             116        86  60--120     190                        5             276        70    0--20         2           2370        1.7             10        20  20--34         8                        1.7             10        80  34--60      210                        7             262        80  60--90      260                        7.5           280        93  90--125     190                        7             235        81    PiKa    Nipe            0--25      40         7330      0.5          200      20  25--40      255                        1.6           360        71  45--70      373                        1.1           430        87  70--95      463                        4.0           770        60  95--120     792                        7.7          1250        63  120--160    1234                        9.8          2140        58    , i Repeated extraction (4 times) with 500 ppm P (CaH2PO4). Soil:extracting solution  ratio was 1:5 for each extraction. In the case of the Picacho, Daguey, Coto and PiCa soils  there was insufficient sulfate in the surface soil extracts to detect in the combined ex-  tracts. The values given here are for single phosphate extracts and should be regarded as  minimum values.  *2Assumed bulk density was 1.25.  *3Sulfate-sulfur solubility was interpolated from adsorption curves at zero sulfate sorbed.  *'Calculated from the linear form of the Langmuir plot.    very little sulfate. For easy comparison the quantity of adsorbed sulfate in  the 120-cm profile was estimated. A bulk density of 1.25 was assumed in  these calculations. These data are presented in Fig. 3.  Among the Oxisols (the PiCa soil excluded) there is a relationship between  pH and adsorbed sulfate. The Ultisols differed from the Oxisols. They ad-  sorbed less sulfate than the Oxisols for a given pH. Three of the four Ultisols  and the Inceptisol desorbed almost identical amounts of sulfate (mean 4200  kg/ha). This was regardless of the fact that soil pH {mean of the several  depth increments) ranged from 4.5 to 5.1. The Tortes soil was peculiar. Its  behavior was intermediate between the other Ultisols and the acid end of the    152    20000    J=  c3  LIJ  I--  0  &lt; K)O00  X  m.J  I      4 6     5.0     5.4    5.8     62.         82    PUERTO RICO SOILS  x INCEPTI$OL  ULTI$OL                  o OXI$OL  OXI$OL (PINA)  *  i       i       i    ~'~ .:.  SOIL pH    Fig. 3. Sulfate sulfur desorbed from profiles (0--120 cm) of some highly weathered soils  in relation to mean pH of the soil profiles. (Some extrapolation and interpolation of data  was required and a bulk density of 1.25 was assumed.)    Oxisol curve. The electron-microscope evidence presented in Part 2 of this  study (Jones et al., 1982) provides a plausible explanation for sulfate reten-  tion by the Tortes soil. The crystalline oxides, although constituting a small  percentage of the total mass, are seen as very small particles. Furthermore,  surfaces of kaolinitic clay minerals appear to have been etched, suggesting  that desilication is progressing. Such materials, if in acid media, would  readily adsorb sulfate.  The PiCa soils did not contain the expected amounts of adsorbed sulfates  even if allowances were made for low clay content. This probably is due to  enhanced leaching, because (1) leaching has been intense since the surface  horizon texture is sand, and (2) the saturation extract was high in Si. The im  plication is that amorphous materials in this soil which would otherwise sorb  sulfate, being richer in Si, have fewer adsorption sites, and that Si, as silicate,  is in competition with sulfate for adsorption sites.    Sulfate adsorption curves    Sulfate concentrations in solutions are related to the degree of saturation  of the exchange complex with sulfate (or with other specifically adsorbed  anions). These relationships are illustrated by the Tortes soil (Fig. 4). When  the surface soil (0--10 cm) was equilibrated in a solution containing 20 ppm  SO4-S, sulfate was neither adsorbed nor desorbed. The concentration at  which sulfate is neither adsorbed nor desorbed is approximately the imme-    153    ~zoo  r'~  l.iJ  nn  n-  O  l.iJ  ~) I00  I  ff o  Or)    -50    PUERTO RICO ULTISOL  /~O-gOcm  TORRES      /  /        //o  //o/  / 90-,25..  /    //  7o /            30-50.  ./ ,  ---]i'Z-/-"// ~0-'//"/~lOcm  i     I   i  I  i i i i |         ~     I   i  I  5    I0          50  S04-S IN SOLUTION (ppm)    Fig. 4. Relationships between sulfate sorbed or desorbed and equilibrium solution  concentrations of sulfate for various horizons of a Tortes soil (Ultisol).    diate concentration at which sulfate should be available to plants and indi-  cates the concentration of sulfate in water draining from that horizon. These  kinds of data for other depth increments and other soils are presented in  Table IV.  For the Tortes surface soil, the Langmuir plot (Fig. 5) indicates an adsorp-  tion maximum at 270 #g SO,-S/g soil material, which is close to the 280 #g/g  actually extracted (Table IV). The Tortes surface soil is saturated, or perhaps  supersaturated, at a soluble SO,-S concentration of 19 ppm. In this respect,  the Tortes soil resembles the most weathered Andepts of Hawaii, where  saturation occurs at about 16 ppm SO4-S (Hasan et al., 1970). Less highly  weathered Andepts of Hawaii reach the predicted SO, adsorption maximum  at 30--35 ppm SO,-S in solution. Thus, the Torres soil has sulfate adsorption  characteristics similar to those of the Hydrandepts of Hawaii. Even though  parent materials have little in common, soil forming processes have produced  materials which have similar sulfate adsorption properties.  The general agreement between the sulfate adsorption c.haracteristics of  the Puerto Rico soils and soils of Hawaii derived from volcanic ash suggest  that the material responsible for sulfate adsorption in both soils is similar. In  the Andepts of Hawaii the reactive component is almost certainly amor-  phous gel-like material. It thus seems probable that gel-hull coatings are also  responsible for sulfate adsorption in the Puerto Rico soils.    154    .06    E   .0~  ~0    .02    O- I0 cm  TORRES      / (27o)  0   4   8   12   16  20  24    C  (ppm)    Fig. 5. Linear plot of Langmuir isotherms for the Tortes soil giving calculated adsorption  maxima in parenthesis. Equilibrium conditions was 24 h at 25 in 0.01 M CaCI2.    Calculations for the subsurface horizons of the Tortes soil give adsorption  maxima in the range 830--990/~g/g (Fig. 5). Inasmuch as adsorbed sulfate  was in the range 537--819 pg/g {saturation percentage 65--83), sulfate  solubility should be lower in the subsoil horizons than in the surface soil.  Such was the case (Table IV). When no SO4 was adsorbed or desorbed, con-  centrations of SO4 were in the range 1.6--10 ppm (Table IV).  These calculations suggest that the high sulfate content of the Tortes sur-  face horizon is not a stable condition because additions of about 19 ppm  SO4-S in the rainwater (or some equivalent source) would be required to  maintain saturation. Additions of that magnitude are unlikely except in in-  dustriai areas. Apparently SO4 in large quantities has been added to the sur-  face soil as fertilizer.  Sulfate concentrations in soil solutions depend on degree of saturation of  surfaces with SO4. The data of Fig. 6 present that relationship for all soil  samples exa~nined. The data agree with the conclusion reached by Hasan et  al. (1970) for Andepts of Hawaii: that is, if the softs are to have 5 ppm of  sulfate in solution the sulfate adsorption capacity should be 60--80%  saturated. A smooth curve drawn through the class interval means in Fig. 6  intersects the 5-ppm concentration line at about 70% saturation of the soil  with SOn. The curve predicts complete saturation at about 17 ppm SO4-S in  solution. Fig. 6 does not indicate apparent differences between the Ultisols  and Oxisols. In all samples of the Inceptisol profile, sulfate solubilities were  &lt; 2 ppm. Sulfate solubilities in the range 2--5 ppm S suggest a S-deficiency  (Fox, 1976; Fox et al., 1977), but only one profile is represented.    25  E  Q,  v 20  Z  0  .J  0  0')  z I0  n  I  0"5  u)    CLASS INTERVAL MEAN   INCEPTISOL                  o /  ULTISOL            .14/  = OXISOL                 ~i/  0    20   40   60   80   I00  SATURATION OF SOIL WITH  SO4    (%)    Fig. 6. Relationship between percentage saturation of soils with sulfate and sulfate in  equilibrated solutions of 0.01 M CaCI2. All horizons of all soils are represented.    155    Point of zero net charge (PZNC)    Acid--base titration curves for selected horizons of six soils were per-  formed in four different NaC1 concentrations. Sample results for three soils  are presented in Fig. 7. As has been stated in the section on materials and  methods, this methodology does not take into account the permanent  charge. The point at which a change in salt concentration does not produce  a pH shift is assumed to be the pH (point) at which variable charge is zero. A  condition more acid than the point of intersection gives rise to net variable  positive charge, whereas net negative charge corresponds to less acid (more  basic) pH values. Acid--base titration curves of this sort for Oxisols and Alfi-  sols from tropical Brazil have been discussed by Van Ralj and Peech (1972).  Soil management implications have been discussed by Uehara and Keng  (1975).  For a well defined zero point of net charge, all curves should have a  common point of intersection. The general pattern for Puerto Rico soils was  one of converging curves instead of clear-cut points of intersection (Fig. 7).  The only well defined point of zero net charge, pH 5.2, was obtained for the  Nipe subsoil between depths of 45 and 70 cm (Fig. 7). Converging curves at  low pH suggest soil minerals with a significant component of permanent  negative charge.  The main implication of the observations is that, at pH values which can  be expected in the field, a net positive charge should be expected only in  subsoil horizoris of the most highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, such as  the Nipe soil.  Van Raij and Peech (1972) believe that their data show a striking effect of    156    A  o  E 4  c~  bJ  a  c~  ,&lt;  bJ  o9  rv-  o  &lt;~    l   L   r   i  ///  II    CARRERAS  O-8cm/'       ~//  ////  !  2  3  4  5  6  7      .....  /if  CATALINA     ///  O- 16 crn      ,//  J  ,/  //,  i  L/  CON~'RATION  ,.     ~.OOl M  ]      ---- .01  "  I'    o-25:m  //  //  ,,!/!         ///I////             ~1 /7  45-'tOcm     ////-  35-6ocm  /'/i//,/                I, I /  .   ,i  |   |   !   i  2  3  4  5  6  7     3  4  5  6  7  8  pH    Fig. 7. Potentiometric titration curves in the presence of various levels of an indifferent  electrolyte (NaCl) zero point of net charge is the point (pH) at which a change in electro-  lyte concentration does not produce a change in pH.    organic matter in lowering the zero point of net charge inasmuch as values  for B2 horizons were higher than values for the Ap horizons.  One cannot draw the same conclusion from the data of Table V. The data  for the Nipe soil fit the pattern described by Van Raij and Peech very well  but data for the Catalina soil are just as convincing in the opposite direction.  Perhaps adsorbed sulfate in the soil is the overriding factor. In the case of the  Nipe soft, PZNC was 0.9 pH units greater in the B21 horizon than in the A  horizon. This difference was associated with 4.7% less organic carbon and  330 pg/g more absorbed sulfate-sulfur in the B21 horizon than in the A  horizon. For the Catalina soil, however, the PZNC was one pH unit lower in  the B22 horizon (35--60 cm depth). This difference was associated with  2.9% less organic C and 900 pg/g more SO4-S in the B22 horizon than in the  A horizon. The behavior of other soils falls between these extremes.  Some specifically adsorbed anions and structural anionic impurities can  render oxide surfaces more negative, thus shifting the PZNC to lower pH  values. The PZNC of synthetic hematite, corundum, boehmite, and goethite  occurs at pH values greater than 7 and hydration can increase the PZNC  {Parks, 1965). The PZNC of the surface horizons of ferruginous soils, how-    157  TABLE V  Point of zero net charge for selected Puerto Rico soils as determined by potentiometric  titration    Soil              Depth           PZNC  Picacho          0--18          4.0  18--35           3.7    Carreras    0--8            3.2  8--25       3.0  45--65           3.0    Daguey* 1          0--10  10--30    Catalina    4.0 (indefinite)  4.1 (indefinite)    0--16           4.5  16--35           4.2  35--60           3.5  60--80           3.5    PiCa              0--20           3.2  34--60           3.4    Nipe              0--25           4.4  45--70           5.2    * ~There were no common points of convergence or intersection for this soil. Values re-  corded are for intersection of the 0.001 and 0.1 M curves.    ever, is usually below pH 5. Mekaru and Uehara (1972) demonstrated that  phosphate adsorption increased the CEC of highly weathered soils of Hawaii  and negative adsorption of NO~ and C1- was measured when sulfate ions were  added to a soil that initially had net positive charge. Ayres and Hagihara  (1953} demonstrated that K added as K2SO4 or KH2PO4 leached less readily  from highly weathered ferruginous soils than did K applied as KC1.  The pH of zero net charge of quartz and hydrous SiO2 is about 2 (Parks,  1965). It is thus not surprising that the PiCa and Carreras softs have the  lowest PZNC (3.2} of the softs investigated; these soils also have the highest  concentrations of Si in saturation extracts (Table II).    Buffer curves of highly weathered soils    Highly weathered softs are weak buffers in the range about pH 5 but base  consumption increases rapidly as pH 7 is approached. Soils which are com-  posed predominantly of hydrated iron and aluminum oxides are extreme  cases, but softs that are predominantly kaolinitic have the same pattern.  Buffer curves for the eleven surface softs investigated are presented in  Fig. 8. The data, as put into tabular form {Table VI), demonstrate that ap-    158    r,     e~  0  E  0  e~    Ee  0~    0    D--  I  L~  ~6    D--    qD    C'q    QO    c'Q    ~00    I    o    O  0  0  c'q  P~  Q; ~J  3~    159    6    ,/// /S  Z.Z..  i z        oA,, __  ' /         I TOflRES                    ~//               I MATANZAS  j         z P,cAc.o                   ~/              z ~,  ~'          $ CARRERAS                  ~/               3 BAYAMON                  4 LOS GUINEOS                       5r"                       4 COTO   DAGUEY                     I                 5 CATALINA                            6 NIPI:  ,'o         ;o  Co(OH)2  ADDED (me/lOO9)                 Ca(OH)2 ADDED (me/lOOg)    Fig. 8. Calcium hydroxide titration curves for highly weathered surface soils of Puerto  Rico. A. Inceptisol and Ultisols; B. Oxisols.    proximately twice as much base is consumed in the interval pH 6.5--7.0 as  in the interval 5.5-6.0. Similar results have been obtained using variable-  charge soil material from New Zealand and Hawaii (Fox, 1980).  Although there are notable exceptions, buffer capacities of the Oxisols  are generally less than for the Inceptisol and Ultisols, at least in the acid pH  range. The Nipe soil is highly buffered in comparison with other Oxisols. An  attempt has been made to normalize discrepancies caused by different clay  and organic matter contents by expressing the base requirements as milli-  equivalents per unit clay equivalent. The results of this calculation are pre-  sented in the final column of Table VI. Two softs do not conform to the  standards of others within their orders. These are the TorTes soil which be-  haves like an Oxisol and the Pi~'a soil which behaves like an Ultisol.    Extractable aluminum and suspension pH    Although weathered softs frequently are rich in hydrated oxides of alumi-  num, it does not follow that extractable aluminum is present in proportion  to the abundance of free aluminum oxides in soils. In fact, gibbsite is much  more stable in acid soil environments than are the layer silicate minerals.  Fig. 9 presents the quantity of A1 which was extracted with 1 M KC1 from  selected soil horizons, plotted against soil pH in a water suspension. Extract-  able A1 was essentially zero at pH values greater than 5.2.  Data on soil pH and extractable aluminum are presented in Tables VII and  VIII. Extractable A1 usually was less, and pH higher, in the Oxisols than in  the Inceptisol and Ultisols. The single exception was the Piffa soil which was  extremely acid. Extractable Al in Oxisol profiles to depths of 120 cm was    160    TABLE VII    Total soil N and C, soil pH, exchangeable cations and CEC of Puerto Rico soils as a function  of depth  Classification:    Depth    Total  Organic       Exchangeable cations (meq./100 g)  Great Group     (cm)     N     C       pH  Subgroup               (%)    (%)           K    Mg    Ca   A1   Na   Total CEC    Series  Humitropept  Udoxic  Picacho    Tropohumults  Epiaquic  Orthoxic  Los  Guineos    Aquic  Carreras    0--18     0.140    2.60         4.7      0.12   1.04  18--35     0.110    1.35         4.7      0.09   1.01  35---60     0.090    0.97         4.8      0.06   1.20  60--85  0.064 0.32    5.0   0.12 0.61  85--130  0.032    0.39          5.2      0.25   0.97  130--165  0.035    0.32         4.9      0.12   0.60  165--200  0.045    0.49          5.0      0.12   0.54    0.87   2.2 0.17   4.4 10.1  0.80      4.8   0.15      6.8      9.3  0.87   5.1 0.13   7.4 10.9  0.83      5.0   0.11      6.7      6.6  0.64   1.8 0.14   3.8   4.2  1.05   3.7 0.15   5.6   6.7  0.69      4.5   0.13      6.0      5.6    0--8   0.380 3.31  8--25     0.250    1.52  25--45     0.140    1.12  45---65  0.093  1.04  65-90  0.078 0.85  70--150 0.066 1.00  150--200 0.034 1.00  200--250 0.016 0.04    0--14     0.260    2.41  14--28     0.170    1.57  28--55  0.080 0.82  55--80  0.060 0.32  80--110 0.053 0.49  110--125 0.070 0.42    4.8      0.25   1.28      2.28      2.2   0.12      6.1    12.6  5.0      0.15   0.68      1.51      2.1    0.07      4.5      9.4  5.1   0.17 0.56   0.48   2.5 0.07   3.8   6.8  5.2  0.09 0.55   0.42  2.1 0.06  3.2   6.7  5.2      0.15   0.49      0.35      3.4   0.06      4.4      7.2  5.2      0.12   0.50      0.66      4.0   0.05      5.3      7.4  5.0      0.12   0.33      1.11      5.9   0.08      7.5      8.5  4.9      0.19   0.70      0.62      8.4   0.12   10.0   10.4    5.0      0.93   0.33    10.16      1.6   0.16   13.2   19.0  4.5  0.69 0.77   6.51   9.2 0.08 17.2 16.9  4.3  0.64 0.66   2.17 11.7 0.07 15.2 14.6  4.3      0.40   0.92      1.35   15.7   0.05   18.4   13.9  4.2      0.40   0.97      1.42   14.1   0.04   16.9   12.8  4.4      0.27   1.57      1.99   11.9   0.04   15.8   15.2    Orthoxic  Daguey    0--10  0.346 3.62  10--30     0.100    0.97  30--60  0.060 0.65  60-95  0.034  0.26  95--140  0.035    0.22  140--200 0.030 0.27    5.0   0.46 3.23   5.54   0.1  0.10   9.4 15.6  5.1   0.15 1.53   3.46   0.3 0.10   5.5   9.0  5.0      0.17   1.50      1.78      3.9   0.12      7.5      9.1  4.8      0.09   0.90      0.87      6.6   0.16      8.6      9.7  4.8      0.12   0.42      0.93      7.0   0.15      8.5      9.4  4.7      0.15   0.71       0.87      6.4   0.15      8.3      8.5    Orthoxic  Tortes    Eutrorthox  Tropeptic  Mattanzas    0--10  0.290 3.20  10--30  0.110  0.71  30--50  0.090 0.54  50--90     0.061    0.60  90--125  0.027    0.32    0--35  0.292 2.84  35--70  0.155  1.03  70--100 0.133  0.55    5.3      1.16   1.23      0.12      0.1   0.07   8.7      13.5  4.8   0.62 1.96   1.85   1.8 0.08   6.3   6.7  4.8      0.64   1.88      1.25      3.8   0.06      7.6      7.2  4.8  0.22 0.19   1.49  4.9 0.07   6.9   7.8  4.9      0.29   1.49      1.12      6.4   0.11      9.4      8.1    7.9   0.21 1.19  53.6* 0.00 0.43 55.4 14.9  7.8   0.11 0.60  16.9   0.00 0.18 17.8   8.4  7.8   0.06 0.39  13.9   0.32 0.15 14.9   7.1    Haplorthoxs  Tropeptic  Catalina    Tropeptic  Coto    Tropeptic  Bayamon    Typic  PiEa    Acrothox  Typic  Nipe    161    0--16    0.313   3.68        5.1     0.62   0.68     4.50   0.7     0.10     6.5   11.5  16--35  0.134 1.11    5.0  0.22 0.35   2.42 0.9  0.05  3.9  6.3  35--60    0.103   0.80        4.8     0.22   0.47      1.47   0.7     0.04     2.2     6.1  60--80  0.067 0.50    4.9  0.06 0.48   1.12 0.6  0.04   2.3   3.8  80--120 0.048 0.37    4.9  0.09 0.44   0.99 0.7  0.03   2.2  4.6  120--130 0.037 0.23    4.9   0.29 0.59   0.73 1.8  0.03   3.4  4.6    0--13  0.252 2.44    5.6  0.15 1.08   7.3  0.01 0.25  8.8 13.3  13--25  0.197  1.69    5.5  0.04 0.41   2.8  0.01 0.10  3.4 10.6  25--45  0.143 0.99    5.5  0.04 0.39   4.6  0.05 0.11   5.2  7.1  45-65  0.127 0.62    5.6  0.04 0.25   5.3  0.05 0.10   5.7   5.8  65-90  0.113 0.46    5.7   0.08 0.26   4.0  0.28 0.18  4.8   5.8  90--125 0.104 0.25    5.8  0.04 0.65   4.3  0.00 0.11   5.1   5.7    0--9       0.096   0.63        5.9     0.13   0.51      5.0     0.03   0.10     5.8     7.7  0--30  0.076 0.44    5.9   0.06 0.56   3.8  0.01 0.15   4.2  9.0  30-60  0.091  0.28    6.1   0.04 0.49   4.7  0.14 0.10   5.5   7.5  60--120 0.076 0.26    6.0  0.04 0.59   4.2  0.12 0.15   5.1   8.6  120--150 0.090 0.23    5.8  0.04 0.67   5.9  0.07 0.25  6.9 10.8  150--175  0.053    0.21          5.9      0.04   0.64      4.2      0.10   0.21      5.2   11.4    0--20  0.045 0.32    4.6  0.06 0.27   0.62 0.6  0.01   1.6   1.3  20--34  0.040 0.32    4.5  0.09 0.14   0.31 0.6  0.01   1.4   2.4  34--60  0.056 0.16    4.1   0.17 0.25   0.33 1.7   0.03  2.4  2.6  60--90  0.040 0.05    4.2  0.06 0.35   0.42 1.9  0.04  2.8   2.2  90--125 0.035 0.05    4.4  0.12 0.22   0.45 1.6  0.03   2.4  2.2    0--25  0.390 6.04    5.1   0.12 1.04   3.4   1.01 0.10   5.7 25.4  25--45  0.131  2.04    5.0  0.03 0.21   0.4  0.29 0.08   1.0 12.1  45--70  0.067 1.33    5.4  0.03 0.24   0.3  0.04 0.10  0.7   8.2  70--95  0.057  0.86    5.4  0.03 0.30   0.4  0.04 0.10  0.9   6.4  95--120 0.048 0.72    5.5  0.02 0.19   1.1   0.00 0.07   1.4   5.3  120--160 0.029 0.56    5.5  0.02 0.19   0.4  0.00 0.15  0.8  3.8    Note Values for pH are in water and A1 is KCl~extractable. Both values are means of ARS  and RLF data except for Matanzas, Coto, Bayamon and Nipe samples which are RLF data.    about 0.5 meq./100 g, whereas in the Ultisol mean extractable A1 was  5.8 meq./100 g (Table VIII). Large amounts of A1 were extracted from the  Carreras soil. The Carreras soil contained amorphous colloids and vermiculite  with hydroxy aluminum interlayers in addition to 1:1 type clays but no  gibbsite (see Jones et al., 1982).  The clay mineral most frequently associated with small quantities of ex-  tractable A1 {typical of the Oxisols) was chlorite. Minerals of the kaolin  group were present in every soft. This seems to imply that Al-interlayered  chlorite is one of the most stable secondary minerals in soils (see also Soil  Survey Staff, 1970, ch. 3, p. 28), large amounts of extractable A1 in softs  from the Llanos Orientales of Colombia in association with chlorite (Fox,  1974) notwithstanding.    162    &gt;,,  8  _8  E   4    PUERTO  RICO   SOILS  KCl  EXTRACTABLE   AI    4.6  KO  6.4  SOIL pH    .L  .....  i  58  "   e.O    Fig. 9. Aluminum extracted with 1 N KCI from the surface soil and the B21 horizon from  each of the 11 highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico. Aluminum is expressed per gram  clay.    TABLE VIII    Weighted means for exchangeable cations in the 120-cm profiles of some highly  weathered soils of Puerto Rico    Soil    Exchangeable cation (meq./1 O0 g soil)    K        Mg       Ca       Al        Na       Total    Inceptisol  Picacho             0.12      1.0       0.8        3.6      0.14       5.6    Ultisols  Los Guineos        0.14     0.6      0.8        2.9     0.07       4.5  Carreras            0.55      0.8       2.6       11.7      0.07      15.7  Daguey             0.16      1.2       2.0        4.4      0.13       8.0  Tortes             0.24     0.4       1.6        4.0     0.08      6.4  Mean (Ultisols)     0.27     0.8       1.8        5.8     0.09      8.6    Oxisol  Matanzas.1         0.12      0.7       --         0.0      0.24       --  Catalina            0.19      0.5       1.8        0.7      0.05       3.2  Coto               0.06     0.5      4.6        0.1     0.11       5.4  Bayamon           0.05      0.6       4.3        0.1      0.15       5.2  PiCa                0.10      0.3       0.4        1.4      0.03       2.2  Nipe                0.05      0.4       1.2        0.3      0.09       2.0  Mean (Oxisols,     0.09     0.5       2.5        0.5     0.09       3.6  Matanzas  excluded)    ,1 Calcareous    163    Exchangeable bases in relation to cation exchange capacity    Exchangeable bases in the eleven soils covered the range from supersatura-  tion to almost total depletion. Details of cation distribution in the profiles  are presented in Table VII, but easier comparison is possible in Table VIII  where the data are summarized to depths of 120 cm.  Clearly the Oxisols, as a group, contain less exchangeable K than the  Inceptisol and Ultisols. The same trend is less clear for Mg and was not  evident for Ca and Na. These results are not unexpected if it is assumed that  the Ultisols, although highly weathered, are less highly weathered than the  Oxisols.  No traces of primary minerals were detected, except for quartz and  perhaps mica (see Jones et al., 1982). But, even though the primary minerals  have disappeared, evidence of their former presence may still be detected as  exchangeable cations because some elements have been recycled by vegeta-  tion or were retained in secondary minerals formed from weathering prod-  ucts of the primary minerals. A case in point is the Carreras soil which con-  tained vermiculite, a 2 :l-type clay mineral believed to have been formed  upon the loss of K from mica. The Carreras soil contained 3 times more ex-  changeable K than the other Ultisols.  The Cato and Bayamon soils are underlain by limestone and this is re-  flected in the high levels of exchangeable Ca in these soils.  A comparison of cation exchange capacity, as determined by the neutral,  N, NH4OAc method, with sum of exchangeable cations (Table VII) gives an  indication of the problems encountered when CEC determinations are made  in the usual way for highly weathered soils. Moss and Coulter (1964) re-  ported that the slopes of curves obtained by plotting final equilibrium K  against K taken up by some West Indian soils were not related to the cation  exchange capacities, but were proportional to the sums of exchangeable  cations. Juo et al. (1976) investigated this problem for a group of West  African softs and recommended that the sum of exchangeable cations in-  cluding KCI exchangeable acidity should be used for routine soil analyses of  highly weathered soils of the tropics. The discrepancy between CEC, as  determined with NH4OAc at pH 7, and sum of exchangeable cations, in-  cluding extractable A1, is usually attributed to pH-dependent negative  charges which develop as the pH of an acid soil is increased to near 7 by the  NH4OAc. The tendency of the discrepancy to diminish with depth (Table  VII) suggests that pH-dependent charge is predominantly a function of or-  ganic matter. In this study, the notable exception to that generalization was  the very highly weathered Nipe soft.    Cations in equilibrium with soil in dilute solution    Calcium and potassium adsorption curves were constructed from data ob-  tained by equilibrating surface soil materials with 0.0025 M solutions of    164    CaC12, KC1 or with mixtures of these solutions. Calcium or K adsorbed from,  or desorbed to, the equilibrating solution were algebraically added to ex-  changeable cations of the same species to obtain adsorbed Ca or K. The K  adsorption curves are presented in Fig. 10. Curves differ greatly from each  other within the orders. Some of the differences among soils can be ascribed  to textural differences. The PiWa soil, for example, which contains only 9%  clay in the A horizon, and the Matanzas soil, which has 85% clay, are at op-  posite extremes in the Oxisol group.    CARRERAS      DAGUEY /  TORRES   ,oL  l///    -..c,c.o     ,0           .o.   "/,'/,"  /                        ~.iI///  0         I.O        z.o            o         i.o        2o  K IN SOLUTION (me/I)               K IN SOLUTION (me/I)    Fig. 10. Potassium remaining in solution in relation to adsorbed K (original exchangeable  K plus K adsorbed from solution) in surface soil material from 11 highly weathered  Puerto Rico soils. The equilibrating conditions were: 48 h of continuous shaking at 25  in 0.0025 N solutions of Ca and/or K as chloride. A. Inceptisol and Ultisols; B. Oxisols.    Potassium adsorption curves were used to interpolate K adsorbed at 0.2  meq./l K in the equilibrated solutions (0.0025 N C1). The standard concen-  tration for K in the 0.0025 N salt solutions chosen for comparison was  0.2 meq./l because a concentration of 0.1 meq./1 has been associated with  borderline deficiency of K for banana (Warner et al., 1974). Thus 0.2  meq./1 should indicate adequate nutrition in a field situation, although pot  studies frequently suggest that the requirements for maximum growth may  be greater (Graham and Fox, 1971; Grimme et al., 1971). These values are  presented in Table IX. The values are in the range usually reported for good  K nutrition (Fox, 1974). Note that there was a 10-fold range in K adsorbed  at 0.2 meq./l K in solution when data were expressed on the basis of whole    TABLE IX  Adsorbed K in surface samples of Puerto Rico soils at a solution concentration of  0.2 meq./l K and total salt concentration of 0.0025 M C1    165    Soil                Adsorbed K  (meq./100 g     (meq./100 g     percent of       percent of  soil)             clay)            exchangeable    CEC  cations    Inceptisol  Picacho         0.16            0.50            3.6             1.6    Ultisol  Los Guineos     0.21             0.28             3.4              1.7  Carreras         0.55             0.89             4.2              2.9  Daguey          0.57             0.86             6.1              3.7  Torres           0.60             0.92             6.9              4.4    Oxisols  Matanzas        0.49             0.58             3.3              3.3  Catalina         0.40             0.48             6.1              3.5  Coto           0.25            0.40            2.8             1.9  Bayamon        0.19             0.48             3.3              2.5  PiCa             0.06             0.67             3.8              4.6  Nipe            0.17            0.31            3.0             0.7    Mean            0.33             0.58             4.2              2.8    soil samples. The range was reduced to 3-fold when data were calculated as  meq./100 g clay and to 2.3-fold when data were expressed as percent of  exchangeable cations.  Coleman et al. (1959) suggested that the sum of metal cations, including  aluminum, could be used as an estimate of the effective CEC of highly  weathered soils. The data presented in Table VII agree with that conclusion.  When the K data are expressed as percent of CEC (Table IX) some  interesting trends emerge. First, the Nipe soil is in a class apart. Also, CEC  seems to bear no relationship to K adsorbed at standard conditions. Probably  this relates to the nature of the soil colloids. The Nipe soil contains much or-  ganic matter and hydrated sesquioxides. It is usually believed that these col-  loids do not have high affinities for K. Second, the Picacho and Los Guineos  soils do not behave as expected of materials which contain at least detectable  amounts of 2:1 layer silicates. Both of these soils do contain gibbsite, how-  ever, which suggests prolonged weathering even if great pedological age is not  evident.  The curves plotted in Fig. 10 suggest that some softs will retain apprecia-  ble quantities of exchangeable K at exceedingly low concentrations of K in  solution. This seems to be especially true for the Daguey soft, which contains    166    some vermiculite, for the Carreras soil, which contains beidellite, and for the  Torres soil, for which there is no obvious explanation. Nye et al. (1961} have  concluded that at low equivalent K sorbed, K is held almost as tightly as A1.  Calcium adsorption curves are presented in Fig. 11. In the Inceptisol and  Ultisol orders, the Carreras, Daguey and Torres soils form a group apart,  much as they did in the plot of adsorbed K (Fig. ll,A). In the Oxisol group  (Fig. ll,B), slopes of the curves are usually less than for the Inceptisol-  Ultisol group. The curves suggest that the first increment of Ca is held very  tightly by the Nipe soft and the trend of the remaining curves predict that  the Oxisols they represent will behave the same way if Ca is sufficiently de-  pleted. Further examination of Fig. 11,A shows that the slope and y-inter-  cept of the adsorption curve for the Torres soil are similar to those of the  curves for the Oxisols.    IC  Ob  8    o5  (D  w  m  n-  o  ,,-,,  0.0    A                   cA,~ER~ ~,~,             I0  INCEPTISOL          , .///"  ANO             t;,  ULTISOLS                          o  o  OAGUEY ~C''o  o/                                E  o~/,,...~A                           5  LaS GU,~E~o  W  ,.-,,,  Ca IN SOLUTION (me/I)    B  OXlSOLS    x   /  x  CATAliNA  ,,.,e....,,.,l~rQ  BAYAMO N    I        I  Ca IN SOLUTION (me/I)    Fig. 11. Calcium remaining in solution in relation to adsorbed Ca (original exchangeable  Ca plus Ca adsorbed from solution) in surface soil material of 11 highly weathered soils of  Puerto Rico. The equilibrating conditions were: 48 h of continuous shaking at 25 in  0.0025 N solutions of Ca and/or K as chloride. Soil :solution ratio was 1:10. A. Inceptisol  and Ultisols; B. Oxisols.    An evaluation of residual effects of liming highly weathered softs of  Hawaii demonstrated that Ca was depleted to a uniformly low level regard-  less of the original amount added, suggesting that the first small increment of  Ca was retained much more strongly than later increments even though the  maximum added was far less than the CEC (Mahftum et al., 1970}. These  data support the concept that specific adsorption of calcium is an important  attribute of highly weathered softs.  Adsorbed Ca at 1.0 meq./l Ca in solution is presented in Table 10. Extra-  polationwas necessary in two cases. (No claim is made that 1.0 meq./l has  special significance for plant nutrition. It is used here for purposes of com-  paring exchange properties of softs.} Calcium adsorbed, as a percentage of  total exchangeable cations, including A1, at 1 meq./1 Ca in solution is about    167    60. The only soft which is outstandingly different (low) is the Picacho soft  which contained more amorphous material than others.  The percentage Ca~aturation required to establish 1 meq./1 Ca in solution  generally increases from top to bottom of the list of softs presented in  Table X. The order in which the softs are listed was based on our original  notions of increasing weathering. If some validity in our original notions is  assumed, the data would indicate that Ca competes most strongly for adsorp-  tion sites in softs which have been most highly weathered. It should be re-  membered that this observation is based on a group of soils which are highly  weathered and that, in most instances, the data represent low saturation  values.    TABLE X    Adsorbed Ca in surface soil material from highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico at a  solution concentration of 1.0 meq./1 and total salt concentration of 0.0025 M C1    Soil             Adsorbed Ca  (meq./100 g  (meq./100 g  Per cent of  soil)          clay)         exchangeable  cations    Inceptisol  Picacho      1.2            3.8          27    Ultisol  Los Guineos  3.0            4.1          49  Carreras      7.0           11.3          53  Daguey      5.8          8.8        62  Tortes        5.4            8.3         62    Oxisols  Matanzas     Calcareous  Catalina      4.0            4.8         62  Coto        6.3          10.2         72  Bayamon     4.2           10.5         72  Pifia          0.8            8.9         50  Nipe        4.0           7.3         70    Mean                                         58    Complementary ion effects    The Ca--K equftibriurn study was used to examine complementary ion ef-  fects of Ca and K on Na and Mg desorption. Magnesium desorption from the  soft materials was related to the species of ion being adsorbed (Table XI). In  some cases, the effect was substantial. The most notable example was the  Matanzas soft where displaced Mg increased more than 700% as the dis-  placing cation changed from K to Ca. For other softs, the effect was less pro-  nounced and in the case of the Dagney soil was only 60%.    168  TABLE XI  Displacement of Mg by 0.0025 N KC1 and CaC12, alone and as mixtures, from highly  weathered surface soil materials of Puerto Rico    Soil               Initial composition of equilibrating solution (meq./1)    2.5 Ca     2.0 Ca     1.5 Ca     1.0 Ca     0.5 Ca     0.0 Ca  0.0 K      0.5 K      1.0 K      1.5 K      2.0 K      2.5 K    Inceptisol  Picacho        0.45       0.42       0.39       0.39       0.33       0.23    Ultisols  Los Guineos    0.35       0.31       0.29       0.28       0.17       0.13  Carreras        0.15       0.12       0.10       0.12       0.12       0.05  Daguey        0.66      0.63      0.64      0.59      0.51      0.41  Torres          0.23       0.23       0.22       0.21       0.23       0.10    Oxisols  Matanzas       0.17       0.15       0.12       0.10       0.08       0.02  Catalina       0.20       0.17       0.19       0.18       0.15       0.08  Coto           0.43       0.44       0.35       0.42       0.28       0.20  Bayamon       0.23       0.21       0.22       0.20       0,15       0.08  PiCa          0.06      0.05      0.06      0.05      0.03      0.03  Nipe          0.20      0.15      0.12      0.13      0.08      0.11    Values are Mg in equilibrium solutions (meq./1).  TABLE XII  Displacement of Na by 0.0025 N KC1 and CaCl:, alone  weathered surface soil materials of Puerto Rico    and as mixtures, from highly    Soil               Initial composition of equilibrating solution (meq./1)  2.5 Ca     2.0 Ca     1.5 Ca     1.0 Ca     0.5 Ca     0.0 Ca  0.0 K      0.5 K      1.0 K      1.5 K      2.0 K      2.5 K    Inceptisol  Picacho        0.139      0.152      0.144      0.144      0.152      0.152    Ultisols  Los Guineos    0.096      0.100      0.100      0.109      0.087      0.091  Carreras       0.148      0.130     0.130     0.130     0.122     0.148  Daguey         0.183      0.174      0.170      0.165      0.161      0.165  Torres          0.061      0.078      0.070      0.061      0.061      --    Oxisols  Matanzas      0.144     0.148     0.152     0.157      0.148      0.161  Catalina       0.035     0.044     0.039      0.052     0.035     0.035  Coto          0.135     0.135     0.139     0.139     0.122     0.126  Bayamon      0.070     0.070     0.083     0.061      0.052      0.052  PiCa            0.044      0.044      0.035      0.026      0.022      0.035  Nipe           0.075      0.044      0.035      0.035      0.035      0.048    Values are Na in equilibrium solutions (meq./1).    169    There probably are mineralogical explanations for these relationships but  I cannot offer a specific explanation except to point out that only the  Matanzas soil contains boehmite.  Complementary ion effects were less obvious as far as Na desorption was  concerned (Table XII). In most cases, Na was more readily desorbed by Ca  than by K but in the case of the Matanzas soil, and to a lesser degree the  Picacho soil, Na desorption decreased with increasing proportion of Ca in the  desorbing solutions.    Displacement of cations by incomplete exchange    A causal description of the nutrient status of soils requires an intensity  factor and a quantity factor. The intensity of cation nutrition is related to  the relative ease of replacement of exchangeable cations during an incom-  plete cation exchange reaction. For this purpose cations (except Na) were  determined in solutions produced by equilibrating 0.0025 M NaC1 with all of  the soil samples. In addition, surface soil samples were equilibrated with  0.0025M KCI and sodium was determined in these solutions. Partial results  (representative horizons} are tabulated in Table XIII. General infertility of B  and C horizons is indicated. In several instances Ca and Mg were undetect-  able or nearly so in the lower B and C horizons. Potassium concentrations  were frequently in the range of suspected deficiency. If it is assumed that 0.1  meq./1 K is a border-line deficient situation, the B and C horizons of only  two softs were well supplied with K. The Nipe soil represents an extreme case  of infertility in the deeper profile. The data indicate that below a depth of  25 cm in the Nipe soil all macro-nutrient cations are essentially unavailable  to plants.  The Matanzas soil is a special case. Because the soil is calcareous, Ca2was  dominant on the exchange complex (Table VII) and in equilibrated salt solu-  tions (Table XIII). But even on an absolute basis Kand Mg2were low in  the solution equilibrated with this soil. If there is any justification for the  "lime-potash law" of Ehrenberg, the Matanzas soil should be deficient in K  for crop production.  The data on incomplete exchange permitted calculations of activity ratios  and energies of exchange between Kand (Ca2+ and Mg2 as described by  Woodruff (1955). Values for surface and B22-horizons are presented in  Table XIV. The utility of activity ratios for defining the K status of some  tropical soils has been studied by Acquaye et al. (1967) and Maida (1979}.  Graham and Fox (1970} reported on activity ratios for eleven Hawaii soils  and K uptake by corn. A value of about 0.001 mole/~~ represented a Sharp  break in K uptake. This corresponds to an energy of exchange (A F) of  -4092 cal./mole. Woodruff's (1955) Energy of Exchange is based on the  activity ratio K/x/(Ca + Mg). Woodruff and McIntosh (1960) suggested that  -3500 cal/mole would provide adequately for the K nutrition of Zea mays  with an ample margin of safety and that -4000 calories represents a maxi-    170  TABLE XIII  Cations in 0.0025 N solutions of NaC1 or  Puerto Rico soils    KCI equilibrated with selected horizons of    Soil            Horizon     Depth  Series                       (cm)    Cations in solution (meq./l)    K        Mg       Ca       AI        Na    Picacho    Los Guineos    Ca~er~    Daguey    Tortes    Matanzas    Catalina    Coto    Bayamon    A             0--18     0.102     0.152     0.07      0.002  B21         18--35     0.070    0.121     0.07      0.009  B22                    35-60           0.036          0.114          0.05             0.005  C1                       85--130        0.030          0.048          0.01             0.004    Ap                        0--8             0.100          0.110          0.16             0.041  B21          8--25     0.066    0.038    0.05      0.002  B22                    25--45           0.042          0.019          0.02             0.007  C1                       90--150        0.032          0.000          0.00             0.004    Ap            0--14     0.228     0.052     0.55      0.011  B21          14--28     0.224     0.041     0.48      0.021  B22                    28--55           0.376          0.046          0.39            0.017  C1                       80--110        0.160          0.036          0.24             0.018    A1           0--10     0.070    0.220    0.22      0.012  B21                    10--30           0.012          0.104          0.10             0.013  B22                    30-60           0.029          0.128          0.14             0.011  C1                       95--140        0.015          0.051          0.02             0.012    Ap                        0--10           0.320          0.063          0.20             0.002  B21                    10--30           0.190          0.033          0.20            0.002  B22                    30--50           0.092          0.029          0.15             0.010  C1                       90--125        0.080          0.012          0.02             0.002    A1                         0--35           0.031          0.031          1.78             0.010  B21         35--70     0.016    0.006    1.06      0.009  B22                    70--100        0.006          0.000          0.96             0.002    Ap                        0--16           0.190          0.085          0.36            0.005  B21          16--35     0.196     0.072     0.39      0.006  B22                    35--60           0.128          0.080          0.32             0.003  B24                    80--120        0.046          0.019          0.00             0.005    Ap           0--13     0.040    0.136    0.40      0.001  A12         13--25     0.024     0.059     0.30      0.000  B21         25--45     0.020    0.048    0.29      0.002  B24                    90--125        0.018          0.079          0.33             0.000    A                           0--9             0.063          0.074          0.37             0.002  B21                       9--30           0.021          0.095          0.48            0.004  B22                    30--60           0.009          0.066          0.36             0.004  B23          60--120    0.010     0.074     0.35      0.006    0.15    0.09    0.15    0.16    0.06    0.16    0.04    0.13    0.05    PiCa    Ap           0--20     0.041    0.008    0.004    0.019  Ap+B21    20--34    0.028    0.003    0.004    0.007  B21        34--60    0.057    0.013    0.05     0.033  B23        90--125   0.025    0.001    0.02     0,023    171  0.04    Nipe           Ap           0--25     0.103    0.170    0.15      0.10      0.04  B1          25--40     0.010    0.017    0.004    0.015  B21         45--70     0.009    0.003    0.000    0.009  B23         95--120    0.012    0.000    0.000    0.010    mum that should not be exceeded without unfavourable consequences.  Banana responds to K fertilization when pK - lh p (Ca + Mg) is about  2.3,/~ F = -3860 (Moss, 1964). According to these standards the Matanzas  soil is decidedly deficient in K, whereas the Coto, Bayamon and Daguey are  in a questionable range.  Tinker (1964) reported that such an activity ratio (AR) was not adequate  to describe the nutrition of oil palm growing in acid soils. He proposed a  Unified Activity Ratio (ARu) which included a term for the cube root of    TABLE XIV    Calculated activity ratios (AR), unified activity ratios (ARu), and energies of exchange  (AF) between K+ and Ca2for two horizons of eleven Puerto Rico soils    Surface horizon                   B22 horizon  AR       ARu      AF       AR       ARa      AF  (mole/l (mole/l~)  (cal./mole) (mole/1  (mole/1~)  (cal./mole)    Inceptisol  Picacho    0.0101     0.0053    -2720     0.0041     0.0018     -3248    Ultisols  Los Guineos    0.0090  Carreras        0.0137  Daguey         0.0049  Torres         0.0290  Mean          0.0142    Oxisols  Matanzas      0.0011  Catalina        0.0133  Coto           0.0026  Bayamon       0.0044  PiCa       0.0174  Nipe           0.0085  Mean           0.0079    0.0030    -2790     0.0098     0.0026     -2739  0.0073          -2538            0.0263          0.0122          -2154  0.0024          -3145            0.0026          0.0011          -3520  0.0158    -2095     0.0102     0.0041     -2716  0.0072                0.0122     0.0050    0.0007     -4041     0.0003     0.0002    -4828  0.0074    -2556     0.0094     0.0056     -2760  0.0026          -3534            0.0012          0.0071          -3977  0.0027     -3210     0.0006     0.0004    -4350  0.0021          -2397            0.0130          0.0010          -2570  0.0041          -2822            0.0073          0.0005          -2913  0.0033                0.0053     0.0025    172    the activity of A1. The importance of A1 on the magnitude of these ratios is  apparent from these data (Table XIV).  It now remains to determine experimentally what importance can be at-  tached to these nutrient potentials in the supply of nutrients to plants  (Scheffer and Ulrich, 1962).    Nitrogen mineralization    Ammonium accumulated to high levels in some surface soil materials  during incubation, but in most of the softs, nitrification was scarecly detect-  able (Table XV). Ammonium accumulation was associated with low soil pH  and high extractable A1 in softs which came from areas of relatively low  mean annual temperature. The general relationship between soft pH and the  ratio of NH4+ to NO3- in incubated soils is presented in Fig. 12. Nitrification  of NH4usually proceeded readily at pH 5.4 or above.  Similar relationships have been observed for acid soils elsewhere. For  example, Morrill and Dawson (1967) worked with 55 soils derived from  glacial till in New York State. In 24 of those softs NH4oxidation was not  detectable. Mean initial pH of those was 5.12. In 20 softs, NH4was slowly  oxidized to nitrate. Mean pH of that group was 5.39. The nitrogen cycle of  highly weathered soils of Ghana has been studied by Meiklejohn (1962)  who reports that the grassland softs were devoid of nitrifying bacteria. The  forest softs were more fertile, with more exchangeable bases and organic    TABLE XV    Nitrogen mineralization by surface soil materials of Puerto Rico soils during 14 days  incubation at 30.1    Soil                Initial       N mineralized.3           NH4-N  NH4-N*2                                      NOs_N  (ppm)        NH4-N       NOs-N  (ppm)     (ppm)    Picacho             10          66           1.4         47  Los Guineos       103         293           3.7         79  Carreras            19          69          4.0         17  Daguey            35         110          4.9        22  Torres              20          68          9.4          7  Matanzas           21           15         10.0          2  Catalina            19          68           2.4         28  Coto              16           5          5.8         1  Bayamon          13          27          2.0        14  PiCa                 14            8           2.6           3  Nipe                18          37           1.6         23    "IA1 or Ap horizons.  *:I M KCl-extractable NH4-N in air dried samples prior to leaching.  *SAfter leaching and incubation.    173    70    60    Z  i;ro40  Z   30  Z  *~20    I 5!o  514" s  612 ' io  SOIL pH    Fig. 12. Ratio of NH4 to NO3 produced during incubation of highly weathered surface  soil materials of weathered soils of Puerto Rico.    matter. Gallagher and Bartholomew (1964) have examined mineralization of  N in acid soils of North Carolina. Nitrification rates were very slow when pH  was 5.4 or less. Above pH 5.6, NH4present initially in soils became NO3-  during incubation.    CONCLUSIONS    To the extent that the soil classification system separated soils according  to the degree they had been weathered, it also separated the soils along lines  which could have value for agricultural purposes. In a weathering sequence  we expect that Oxisols will be further advanced than Ultisols. If silicon  solubility is used as the criterion for estimating weathering to which this  group of soils have been subjected, the Oxisols generally were more  weathered than the Ultisols. There was some overlap, however, and for one soil,  the PiCa, Si solubility was completely out of keeping with what is expected  of a highly weathered soil.  The PiCa soil which contains up to 89% quartz sand was the lowest of all  soils as regards water-extractable and phosphate-extractable Si but equili-  brated at 10 ppm Si in the saturation extract. This suggests that quartz, even  when most of it is in sand-sized particles, may be more important chemically  than is generally believed. Silicon in soil saturation extracts should give a  better evaluation of the state of weathering than Si in a 1:10 soil:water ex-  tract because soils which have an abundance of sand-sized quartz lack the  capacity to supply Si at high concentrations to large volumes of extractant.  The range in Si for 10 other soils was 1.4--8.1 ppm. If the PiCa soil were ex-    174    cluded, the Oxisols of Puerto Rico generally equilibrated at lower levels of Si  in their saturation extracts than the Ultisols. Silicon values of the Oxisols  were generally consistent with leached kaolinitic soils.  Phosphate adsorption by the Puerto Rico soils, when corrected for dilu-  tion by sand, was in the same range as for highly weathered softs of Hawaii,  North Carolina and Colombia. Adsorption was an order of magnitude higher  than is usual for most soils developed in loess in the North Central United  States. For the Catalina Ap horizon, phosphate at 700 pg P/g soil was re-  quired to adjust solution concentration to 0.2 ppm P. The corresponding  requirement for the Catalina B21 horizon was 1130 ~g/g.  Large amounts of sulfate have accumulated in the pedons of all the acid  softs. For most soils, phosphate-extractable sulfur in the 120-cm profile ex-  ceeded 4000 kg/ha. The Catalina soil contained over 16 000 kg/ha. Sulfate  solubility is about 5 ppm S at 70% saturation of the softs with sulfate.  Saturation of the soil with sulfate corresponds to about 17 ppm S in solu-  tion.  The softs examined do not exhibit well defined points of zero net charge.  A significant net positive charge cannot be expected within the pH range  usually encountered in the field.  Buffer curves indicate that the soils are poorly buffered at low pH. Ex-  tractable Al was closely related to soil pH, with KCl-extractable A1 increasing  sharply as pH fell below 5.0.  As a group, the Oxisols contained less exchangeable K than the Inceptisol  and Ultisols. Extrapolation of K and Ca adsorption curves indicate that these  cations are held very tightly when solution concentrations fall to very low  levels. A suggestion of specific adsorption of Ca seems to be justified by the  data. When exchangeable K was about 4% of the sum of exchangeable  cations including A1, K in 0.0025 N equilibrated solutions was 0.2 meq./l.  General infertility of subsurface horizons was indicated by low concentra-  tions of nutrient cations in equilibrium with 0.0025 M NaC1 solutions. In  several instances Ca and Mg were undetectable, or nearly so, in the lower B  or C horizons.  When acid soils from areas with isothermic temperature regimes of Puerto  Rico were incubated, large amounts of NH4accumulated. Nitrification was  almost nil when soil pH was less than 5.    REFERENCES    Abruna, F., Vicente-Chandler, J. and Pearson, R.W., 1964. Effects of liming on yields and  composition ofheavUy fertilized grasses and on soil properties under humid tropical  conditions. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 28: 657--661.  Acquaye, D.K., MacLean, A.J. and Rice, H.M., 1967. Potential and capacity of potassium  in some representative soils of Ghana. Soil Sci., 103: 79--89.  Ayres, A.S. and Hagihara, H.H., 1953. Effect of the anion on the sorption of potassium  by some Humic and Hydrol Humic Latosols. Soil Sci., 75: 1--17.    175    Barrow, N.J., 1970. Comparison of the adsorption of molybdate, sulfate and phosphate  by soils. Soil Sci., 109: 282--288.  Beckwith, R.S., 1964. Sorbed phosphate at standard supernatant concentration as an  estimate of the phosphate needs of soils. Aust. J. Exp. Agric. Anita. Husb., 5: 52--58.  Beinroth, F.H., 1982. A study of highly weathered soils of Puerto Rico, 1. Morphology,  formation and classification. Geoderma, 27: 1--73.  Chang, Jen-hu, 1958. Ground temperature, I, II. Blue Hill Meteorological Observatory.  Harvard Univ., 300 pp.  Coleman, N.T., Weed, S.B. and McCracken, R.J., 1959. Cation-exchange capacity and ex-  changeable cations in Piedmont soils of North Carolina. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 23 :  146--149.  Coleman, N.T., Thorup, J.T. and Jackson, W.A., 1960. Phosphate-sorption reactions that  involve exchangeable AI. Soil Sci., 90: 1--7.  Cornfield, A.H., 1953. The mineralization of nitrogen in a soil acidified with sulfur,  aluminum sulfate or ferrous sulfate. J. Sci. Food Agric., 4: 298--301.  Fox, R.L., 1974. Examples of anion and cation adsorption by some soils of tropical  America. Trop. Agric. (Trinidad), 51: 200--210.  Fox, R.L., 1976. Sulfur and nitrogen requirements of sugarcane. Agron. J., 68:  891--896.  Fox, R.L., 1979. Comparative responses of field-grown crops to phosphate concentra-  tions in soil solutions. In: H. Mussell and R. Staples (Editors), Stress Physiology in  Crop Plants. Wiley, New York, N.Y., pp. 81--106.  Fox, R.L., 1980. Soils with variable charge: Agronomic and fertility aspects. In:  B.K.G. Theng (Editor), Soils With Variable Charge. New Zealand Society of Soil  Science, Wellington, pp. 195--224.  Fox, R.L. and Benav~des, S.R., 1974. Phosphorus of Oxisols. In: III Coloq., Soc.  Colomb. Cienc. Suelo, Bogota, Colombia, pp. 137--175.  Fox, R.L. and Kamprath, E.J., 1970. Phosphate sorption isotherms for evaluating the  phosphate requirement of soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34 : 902--907.  Fox, R.L., Olson, R.A. and Rhoades, H.F., 1964. Evaluating the sulfur status of soils by  plant and soil tests. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 28: 243--246.  Fox, R.L., Hasan, S. and Jones, R.C., 1971. Phosphate and sulfate sorption by Latosols.  Proc. Int. Syrup. Soil Fert. Eval., New Delhi, 1 : 857--864.  Fox, R.L., Kang, B.T. and Nangju, D., 1977. Sulfur requirements of cowpea and impli-  cations for production in the tropics. Agron. J., 69: 201--205.  Fox, R.L., Silva, J.A., Younge, O.R., Plucknett, D.L. and Sherman, G.D., 1967. Soil and  plant silicon and silicate response by sugar cane. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31 :  775--779.  Gallagher, P.A. and Bartholomew, W.V., 1964. Comparison of nitrate production and  other procedures in determining nitrogen availaility in Southeastern Coastal Plain  soils. Agron. J., 56: 179--184.  Graham, E.R. and Fox, R.L., 1971. Tropical soil potassium as related to labile pool and  calcium exchange equilibria. Soil Sci., 111: 318--322.  Grimme, H., Nemeth, K. and Braunschweg, L.C.V., 1971. Some factors controlling potas-  sium availability in soils. Proc. Int. Syrup. Soil Fert. Eval., New Delhi, 1 : 33--43.  Hasan, S., Fox, R.L. and Boyd, C.C., 1970. Solubility and availability of sorbed sulfate in  Hawaiian soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Proc., 34: 897--901.  Jackson, M.L., Levett, T.W.M., Syers, J.K., Rex, R.W., Clayton, R.N., Sherman, G.D. and  Uehara, G., 1971. Geomorphological relationships of tropospherically derived quartz  in the soils of the Hawaiian Islands. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 515--525.  Jones, R.C. and Uehara, G., 1973. Amorphous coatings on mineral surfaces. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 37: 792--798.  Jones, R.C., Hudnall, W.H. and Sakai, W.S., 1982. Some highly weathered soils of Puerto  Rico, 2. Mineralogy Geoderma, 27: 75--137.    176    Juo, A.S.R. and Fox, R.L., 1977. Phosphate sorption characteristics of some benchmark  soils of West Africa. Soil Sci., 124: 370--376.  Juo, A.S.R., Ayanlaja, S.A. and Ogunwale, J.A., 1976. An evaluation of cation exchange  capacity measurements for soils in the tropics. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal., 7 :  751--761.  Mahilum, B.C., Fox, R.L. and Silva, J.A., 1970. Residual effects of liming volcanic ash  soils in the tropics. Soil Sci., 109: 102--109.  Maida, J.H.A., 1979. Evaluation of K availability indices for Malawi ferrisols cropped to  tea (Camellia sinensis). Trop. Agric. (Trinidad), 56: 143--151.  Meiklejohn, Jane, 1962. Microbiology of the nitrogen cycle in some Ghana soils. Empire  J. Exp. Agric., 30: 115--126.  Mekaru, T. and Uehara, G., 1972. Anion adsorption in ferruginous tropical soils.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 36: 296--300.  Morrill, L.G. and Dawson, J.E., 1967. Patterns observed for the oxidation of ammonia  to nitrate by soil organisms. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31: 757--760.  Moss, P., 1964. A potassium relationship between soil solution and cocoa bark. Nature  (London), 201 : 729--730.  Moss, P. and Coulter, J.K., 1964. The potassium status of West Indian volcanic soils. J.  Soil Sci., 15: 284--298.  Nye, Peter, Craig, Doris, Coleman, N.T. and Ragland, J.L., 1961. Ion exchange equilibria  involving aluminum. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 25: 14--17.  Parks, G.A., 1965. The isoelectric points of solid oxides, solid hydroxides, and aqueous  hydroxo complex systems. Chem. Rev., 65: 177--198.  Pearson, R.W. Soil acidity and liming in the Humid Tropics. Cornell Int. Agric. Bull., 30:  66 pp.  Scheffer, F. and Ulrich, B., 1962. Considerations regarding the availability to plants of  the soil potassium. Potash Rev., 16/23: 1--7.  Smeck, N.E., 1973. Phosphorus: an indicator of pedogenetic weathering processes. Soil  Sci., 115: 199--206.  Soil Survey Staff, 1967. Soil Survey Laboratory data and descriptions for some soils of  Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. U.S. Dep. Agric. Soil Surv. Invest. Rep., 12.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil taxonomy: A basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. In: U.S. Dep. Agric. Handbook 436, 754 pp.  Stanford, G. and Hanway, J., 1955. Predicting nitrogen fertilizer needs of Iowa Soils, 2. A  simplified technique for determining relative nitrate production in soils. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 19: 74--77.  Syers, J.K., Jackson, M.L., Berkheiser, V.E., Clayton, R.W. and Rex, R.W., 1969. Aeolian  sediments' influence on pedogenesis during the Quaternary. Soil Sci., 107 : 421-427.  Tinker, P.B., 1964. Studies on soil potassium, 4. Equilibrium cation activity ratios and  responses to potassium fertilizer of Nigerian oil palms. J. Soil Sci., 15: 35--41.  Uehara, G. and Keng, J., 1975. Management implications of soil mineralogy in Latin  America. In: E. Bornemisza and A. Alvarado (Editors), Soil Management In Tropical  America, pp. 351--363.  Van Raij, B. and Peech, M., 1972. Electrochemical properties of some Oxisols and Alfi-  sols of the Tropics. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 587--593.  Van der Zaag, P., Fox, R.L., de la Pena, R., Laughlin, W.M., Ryskamp, A., Villagarcia, S.,  and Westermann, D.T., 1979. The utility of phosphate sorption curves for transferring  soil management information. Trop. Agric. (Trinidad), 56:153--160.  Warner, R.M., Fox, R.L. and Prasomsook, S., 1974. Nutritional guidelines for the  "Williams Hybrid" banana. Hawaii Farm Sci., 21/22 (4): 4--6.  Woodruff, C.M., 1955. The energies of replacement of calcium by potassium in soils. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 19: 167--171.  Woodruff, C.M. and McIntosh, J.L., 1960. Testing soils for potassium. Trans 7th Int.  Congr. Soil Sci., Madison, 4: 80--84.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractSome chemical properties of 11 soils developed in highly weathered regoliths in Puerto Rico have been recorded. Particular attention has been given to properties which reflect the extent to which weathering has progressed and to properties which may be most useful for developing valid soil management practices.If the Pia soil were excluded the saturation extracts of Oxisols generally contained less Si than the Ultisols. The saturation extract of Pia soil, which was 89% quartz sand, contained 10 ppm Si, a value out of keeping with highly weathered soils. Phosphate solubility was greatest in the Pia soil also. Phosphate adsorption by the Puerto Rico soils, when corrected for dilution by sand, was approximately that of highly weathered soils of Hawaii, North Carolina or Colombia. Most of the soils contained more than 4000 kg S/ha in the 120-cm profiles. The most striking difference between the Oxisol and Ultisol groups was in extractable aluminum. In general, these Oxisols have been weathered beyond the point where aluminum is readily extracted with a neutral salt. The pH at which net charge of the soils was zero was lower than the soil pH usually encountered in the field. The soils were poorly buffered at low pH. As a group, the Oxisols contained less exchangeable K than the Ultisols. In 6 of the 11 soils both calcium and magnesium were &lt; 1 meq./100 g in some horizon. In most soil samples, the balance among exchangeable cations was appropriate for reasonable potassium nutrition. Even so, the quantity of exchangeable nutrient cations was low in most cases. Mineralization of organic nitrogen tended to stop with NH4+ in the acid soils.