Geoderma, 25 (1981) 75--112  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    75    EFFECTS OF ANIMALS ON SOIL    FRANCIS D. HOLE  University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wise. (U.S.A.)  (Received March 10, 1980; accepted April 3, 1980)    ABSTRACT    Hole, Francis D., 1981. Effects of animals on soil. Geoderma, 25: 75--112.    Soil is defined here in terms of arbitrary boundaries rather than of functions of a soil  body. Soil animals are defined in relation to their effects on the soil body. Animals living  in the soll body and intimately related to it are indeed part of the soil. Animals living above  the soil make contributions to it. Many animals are amphihabitant, that is, they live for a  time in the soft and then in environments outside the soil. Exopedonic (outside the soil)  and endopedonic (inside the soil) animals are considered with respect to twelve activities:  mounding, mixing, forming voids, back-filling voids, forming and destroying peds, regulat-  ing soil erosion, regulating movement of water and air in soil, regulating plant litter, regulat-  ing nutrient cycling, regulating biota, and producing special constituents. Animals partici-  pate in numerous processes of soil formation and affect the usefulness of soils.    INTRODUCTION    Animals that affect the soil constitute a biotic community that has received  inadequate attention from pedologists for a long time, despite early work by  Gilbert White (1720--1793) and Charles Darwin (1809--1882). A recent  "scaled array" of pedological components of the land areas of the earth  (Hole, 1978) did not include soft animals. This is a common omission. Fig. 1  of this paper presents an alternative array of entities with emphasis on fauna.  The tendency among soil scientists has been to stress the aspects of soils that  are clearly important to their usefulness (Simonson, 1966). Some attention  has been given to animals that are pests, such as the potato beetle, Leptino-  tarsa sp. (Ushatinskaya, 1978), but otherwise the fauna have been de-empha-  sized by pedologists. Soil zoologists have done more work on effects of soil  environments on fauna that on effects of the fauna on soft. For example, a  direct relationship has been noted between productivity of plant communities  and diversity of arthropod fauna in the soil (Lussenhop, 1976}. It is apparent  that the great variety of food preferences, needs, adaptations and activities of  soil fauna is related to the diversity of microhabitats in softs and to the low  degree of inter-specific competition (Ghilarov, 1977). A soft. may be regarded    0016-7061/81/0000--0000]$02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    76    HUMAN  BEINGS  i!            !  WoocI lice  ~e~    svri~  ~   .Eart~_Wms    ti~,       t~ltes        ~     . ~  .....  ~  S~ Sna  ~v;x~s.     ttin~,"_'~   ~  beetle larvae   snails ~  ~,~  .;~?\e ~e.s  t~:~~36r          ---ed as to increasing size, With e~--    .L~  ~  ~qle                     ~  A SO,!.L_ BODY    Fig. 1. Scaled array of pedological components, with emphasis on soil animals (which are  underlined).    as a part of the equipment of inhabiting animals as they function as "survival  machines" that assure "immortality" to those "duplicating machines" called  genes (Dawkins, 1976).  Pedologists may characterize in their profile descriptions the fabric created  by animals but commonly omit observations of the animals themselves. Of  the 130 detailed pedon descriptions in Soil Taxonomy {Soil Survey Staff,  1975) only 22, representing seven soil orders, principally Mollisols, note  evidence of animal activity, as follows, and in the numbers of pedons indi-  cated: worm casts (10), worm holes (7), krotovinas (3), rodent burrows (2),  insect cavities (10) and nests (1), termite runs (1), snail shells (1) and cattle  trampling (I). Names of three great groups of the Soil Taxonomy recognize  evidences o~ animal activity: Vermiborolls (Chernozems), Vermudolls and  Vermustolls. The extremely detailed descriptions of profiles of worm-worked  "fat Chernozems" by Buntley and Papendick (1960) were made from soil  samples that were observed under controlled light conditions in the labora-  tory. No observations of worms were reported. Brewer (1976) listed fecal  pellets as non-specific soil morphological features of faunal origin. Evidences  of impact of animals on soil are more easily observed than are the animals  themselves (Van der Drift, 1965).  Th~s paper is concerned with the effects of animals on the soil with em-  phasis on those that live in the soil. More animals on this planet may live in  the soil than above it. The biomass and work of animals in the soil may well  exceed those of animals outside it. Because emphasis is placed on animals, no  effort is made to cover the effects of human beings which are already dis-  cussed elsewhere (Bidwell and Hole, 1965; Yaalon and Yaron, 1966). It is  recognized, however, tl~at tillage, additions of fertilizers and lime, and solid  and liquid wastes do have impacts on animals in the soil (Alejnikova, 1976;    77    McLennan and Pottinger, 1976; Aritajat et al., 1977; Popovici et al., 1977)  and consequently on the soil.  As a guide to selection of information to be included, two questions were  first asked: Would both natural and cultural landscapes be different if there  were no effects of animals on soft? If so, in what ways and to what extent?  Preliminary replies to those questions are that without soil fauna (1) the ac-  cumulation of plant litter might be great enough to suppress normal ground  cover in forests and to alter forest regeneration; (2) nutrient cycling would be  slowed with consequent alteration of vegetative cover; (3) soil porosity wouJd  be much diminished and movement of air and water in soil would be different;  (4) the soil would no longer be mounded and mixed by animals to depths as  great as 2 m, as now happens in many places; and (5) disturbance, infection  and consumption of living underground plant fluids and parts by animals  would cease, as would underground consumption by them of dead plant parts.  Efforts have been made in preparing this review to assemble representative  currently available information related to each of these five topics.    GENERALBACKGROUND    The soil biologist is confronted with a vast number of kinds of entities,  possibly involving a million species of soil animals, and many kinds of inter-  actions between them and the soil environment. Numerous soil animals are  yet to be identified and classified. We do not know which soil animals, if any,  may be endangered species. It is an arduous task to make reliable collections  of soil fauna, to identify them, to follow their activities in landscapes through  the seasons and to interpret the resulting data. A paper by Thorp (1949) of-  fers a comprehensive report on "Effects of certain animals that live in soils",  based on field observations by him and his colleagues. Jacot (1940) and  Heath (1965) have considered the role of animals in pedogenesis. Evidence of  rapid expansion since 1950 of the discipline of soil zoology has been present-  ed by Wallwork (1970, 1976), Ghilarov (1974), and Franz (1974). Further  discussion of relationships is provided by Macfadyen (1969), who urged  functional classification of soils, and Van der Drift (1965) who discussed dy-  namics of the soil community. Volz (1966) attempted a classification of soils  based on fauna.  The species diversity of soil animals, even within a small area, typically  equals that of a coral reef (Wallwork, 1970). All major animal phyla, except  Coelenterata and Echinodermata, are represented in the soils of the world. The  higher taxa (orders, classes) of the smallest soil animals are the most wide-  spread in ubiquitous microsites in organic debris on land the world over.  Endemism is notable in lower taxa, in larger soil fauna and in isolated habitats  on land masses. Data indicate that soft animals are not organized into well-  defined regional communities, "perhaps because bulk samples include a vari-  ety of microsites and because microsite conditions change rapidly with time"    78    (Anderson, 1977}. Some spatial distribution of soil animals is a result of ero-  sion. Heavy rains in Italy were observed to wash certain small soil animals  from the 0--20 cm depth to the 30--40 cm depth (D'Errico and Cancellam,  1976). Erosion of earthworms down hillsides has also been observed  (Atlavinyt~, 1965}.  Soil zoologists in Europe and the U.S.S.R. are major contributors to litera-  ture on soil fauna. Russian pedologists have traditionally included data on  diagnostic assemblages of soft animals (populations and ratios between species)  in their descriptions of soft regions (Molodova, 1976). Polivanova (1977)  found abundant and diversified soil faunal populations in Chernozem-like softs  of depressions; in uplands, a very poor animal population in a sagebrush alkali  soil; and in a forest plantation a very diversified and abundant soil faunal  population. Valiachemdov (1977} identified subtypes of Sierozems on the  basis of special cellular structures in soil that are built by arthropods and  earthworms for pupating and estivating. Ghilarov (1978) stated that "soil in-  vertebrate population studies can be used to characterize the soil type, the  direction of soil formation processes.., as well as change under the influence  of human activity". He noted that, with human impact on ecosystems,  arthropod populations in soils are slower to change than are plant communi-  ties. Therefore, not only features such as krotovinas but also persisting popu-  lations of certain animals may identify the nature of the original genetic soil  type at a site. Ghilarov (1978) enunciated the general principle that the more  similar the faunal populations of two soils, the more genetically similar are  the soils with respect to climate, hydrology, chemistry and ecological region-  alism. Certain Staphylinid beetles are reliable indicators of presence of salts  in Solonetz--Solochak complexes. Relative thicknesses of snail shells and  exoskeletons of certain arthropods may correspond to amounts of calcium  and carbonates present in a soil. Metallic-irridescent beetles are frequent in  sandy soils; less brightly colored beetles frequent finer textured soils. Gisin  (1955) used collembola assemblages to judge quality of soil for vineyards. An  increase of 2.5 percent in yield of apples in an orchard on new polder soil  was correlated with presence of earthworms (Van Rhee, 1977).  Soil fauna are thought to include ancient forms of terrestrial life (South-  wood, 1978) that evolved before continental drift processes had dismembered  the primary land mass. Many particular groups of soft animals have developed  since the separations of the continents and in response to the movement of  the land masses from one climatic zone to another. Shifting of climatic zones  on land masses have been accompanied by shifts in populations of soil fauna.  At a given site the microclimate in the soil is quite uniform as compared to  the macroclimate. Soil air is humid, which makes possible the presence even  in desert soils of animals that respire by means of skin and gills. The Quatern-  ary glaciations affected populations of animals living above ground far more  than of animals in the soil (May, 1978; Hibbard et al., 1965).    79    A question can be raised as to the possible effect on soils of the extinction  of an animal species. For example, prior to its extinction in 1900, the pas-  senger pigeon (Ectopestes migratorius; Schorger, 1973} migrated in flocks  with as many as 2 million birds in each. In April these birds nested en masse  in the upper Mississippi River Valley, building as many as 50 nests in a single  oak tree. The consumption of insects and mast and the deposition on the  soil of excreta and nest debris were on a large scale. Although other animals  may now occupy the niche vacated by the pigeons, that niche has greatly  diminished in area with the conversion of many woodlands and oak savannas  to cropland and pasture.    DEFINITION OF SOIL IN TERMS OF BOUNDARIES    The pedological literature abounds in definitions of soil in terms of its  state, of its functions and of factors and processes of its formation. Soil is  defined here in a way to emphasize boundaries of the soil body: Soil is that  land cover of solid, liquid and gaseous materials that lies (1) below the observ-  able interface between the atmosphere and forest floor or grass-sedge or  cropped land floor (all of which are considered to be a part of the soil), and  (2) above the geologic substratum that appears relatively unaltered. A soft is  actually a major multflayered stratum in a larger and even more complex  biocenose or ecosystem (Ghilarov, 1968). Lateral boundaries of a particular  soil body are lines that connect similar pedons that have equal contrast to  those on either side of them. In Fig. 2 a dashed line delineates soil body  number two as seen in cross-section. This soil was developed from loess under-  lain abruptly by glacial till (IIC horizon). Soil body number one developed  entirely in till. Soil body number three developed in deep loess and has a C  horizon in the loess that rests on a glacially striated surface of limestone bed-  rock. Included in the soil bodies are the litter of organic debris and also two  special features, namely, an ant mound and a fallen log. A standing dead tree  and other starred items in the legend of Fig. 2 are volumes of soil material  that are positioned above and below the soil body but which by convention  are not considered to be parts of it. These starred units are called soil-body-  extensions. A boundary between soil and not-soil (water, glacial ice, salty  playa, bedrock outcrop) would be placed in a preferred position in a transi-  tion zone. An extreme example is found in Scotland. The water in Loch Ness  is brown with suspended organic particles. Even floating chunks of peat are  present (Holden, 1979). The boundary between the water (the Loch and  tributary streams) and adjacent bodies of Histosols is easily established as the  interface at which there is a cessation of water movement in response to wind.    80    A    'b    !    h    ~"   ..g      %   Q  o~ a     o   o  [   _   I      A       l       I I        I        I    I  I l I  I  l   I/_ :~%~  I   I  I    I   I  I  ~     I   I   I  L~,to~ ~d~k   I    I~  I     I  I    '        I o y,   'II   i  _i        I ' [       i         [ ' I ' I         I      [         I    Fig. 2. Sketch to illustrate the concept of soil as a defined volume of material and to il-  lustrate the relationships of a variety of biologic features to that volume. Items listed with  an asterisk are not considered part of the soft proper. Explanation of symbols: O, organic  soil horizon (litter of plant debris and associated animal materials); A, surface mineral-  organic horizon (the A1 is the thin dark surface soil; the A2 or E is the pale layer below  that and above the B; B, subsurface horizon (argillie) that is more clayey than the A hori-  zon; C*, parent material like that from which the A and B horizon were formed: IIC*,  parent material unlike that from which the overlying A, B and C horizons were formed;  a, wood-pulp nest* of hornets (social wasps: Vespidae); b, clayey nests* of barn swallow  (Hirundo rustica); d, loam nests* of mud daubers (wasps: Sphecidae); e, crow (Corvus  brachyrhynchos) which deposits excreta (from crop) on the soft; f, dead tree*;g, earth-  worms and microarthropods in debris* under bark of dead tree; h, earthworm midden with  Lumbricus terrestri~ individual in burrow below; i, human being whose gut contains a speci-  al soil material* ; j, rotting log; k, nest* of a robin (Turdus m igratorius) consisting of layers  of organic materia!s and puddled mineral loam; l, nonliving core* of a living tree; m, green  leaves*, already partially consumed by insects; n, carcass of a small mammal (Scurius  carolinensi8 ~ypophaeus); o, enlarged view of a cross-section of ~ small portion of the B  horizon (Cr, chamber; ct, cutan or clay coating on wall of crack; pl, plasma or potentially  mobile clay m,d fine silt mass; PV, packing void or crack, on the moist walls of which  protozoa, nematodes and small arthropods feed on bacteria, fungal hyphae and root  debris; s, skeleton grain of quartz; see Brewer, 1976; q, occupied mound of western mound  building ant (Formica cinerea); r, translocated clay deposits* in a joint in glacial till and  bedrock; t, clay pod* formed in dolomite bedrock by a process of "argillifaction" in which  carbonate rock was replaced volume for volume by clay in such a way that the chert stone  line (solid triangles) remained continuous in its original position through the clay pod  (Frolking, 19781; u, stalactite* and stalagmite*. Light dotted line represents the position  of the surface of a snowfall* in winter. The heavy dashed line represents the boundary, as  seen in cross-section, of the volume of soil body number 2, which was formed from about  1.2 m of loess over glacial till.    81    DEFINITIONS OF ANIMALS THAT AFFECT THE SOIL    A soil animal may be defined as one that participates in the dynamics of a  soil body. "True soil animal" is a phrase reserved by some workers for perma-  nent endopedonic animals (Table I) that live in the dark and have special  characteristics (differentiating them from animals that live above-ground)  such as limited mobility (wing reduction), visual reduction, skin and gill  respiration, increased development of tactile organs, lowered resistance to  desiccation, little pigmentation or markings, relatively small size, reproduc-  tion not limited to a brief season and emphasis on formation of spermato-  phores (stalked sperm packets fastened to substrate) (Kilhnelt et al., 1966).  Fauna associated with disposal of dung of large vertebrates and fauna that  move into dens and burrows with bears, rodents and other digging vertebrates  are not considered to be true soil animals by some soil zoologists. This issue  is not addressed here; rather attention is turned to all animals that affect soil,  whether from within or without.    TABLE I  A classification of animals inside soil bodies (endopedonic fauna).1 on the basis of in-  cidence in the soil, including both organic and mineral horizons    Category  of soil  fauna    Explanation    Representative fauna    Permanent  Temporary.2    Periodic.2    Alternating    Transient    Accidental    All stages of the animal reside in the soil    One active stage of the animal lives in the  soil; another active stage does not or is  periodic    The animal moves in and out of the soil  frequently    One or more generations of the animal  live in the soil; the other generation(s)  live(s) above the soil    Inactive stages (eggs, pupae; hibernating  stages) of the animal are in the soil;  active stages are not    The animal falls or is blown or washed in-  to the soil; the animal is a geoxene    Acari; Collembola  Larvae of many Insecta    Active forms of many  Inseeta    Potato aphid (Rhopalosi-  phoninus); oak-apple gall  wasp ( Biorhiza )    Many Insecta    Insect larvae of the forest  canopy; surface animals that  fail into cracks of Vertisols    ,! See Kevan, 1962.  * ~ An animal that is temporary in an early stage and periodic in the adult stage is said to  be partial.    82    Endopedonic animals are those inside the soil body; exopedonic animals are  those that are outside the soil body. Exopedonic animals such as marine fauna  do not affect the soil and are not considered here. An endopedonic soil animal  may be classified on the basis of: (1) the proportion of its life span spent in  the soil body (Table I) and/or of its required nutrients obtained within the  soil body; (2) the position of the animal in the food chain; (3) the animal's  body size (Fig. 3); (4) its capacity for making voids in the soil; (5) its philo-  genetic relationship with other animals (Fig. 4); and (6) its ecological siting or  niche (Table III). An exopedonic animal may be classified on the basis of (1)  proportion of its life span spent impinging on the soft (Table II) and (2) its  ecological siti~-~g or niche (Table III). Faunal communities have both above-  ground and below-ground components, as do plant communities. Both with-    NUMBERS OF SO IL ORGAN I SMS    MICROFI.ORA  0. I     I     I0    I00   I. 000  r         w          ,         i         o  BACIERIA (50 g)  ACIINOMYCETES (50)  FUNGI (100l  ALGAE (111  MICROFAUNA  FLAGELLATA (PROTOZOA) (6)  RHIZOPODA (PROTOZOA) (I. 5)    Millions per mz  I0. 000  I00. 000 I, 000, 000    I  I    I  C ILIOPHORA IPROTOZOA) {I. 5)  M[SOFAUNA  I       10      I00     I, O00  I    RC)TIFERA (0. OI)    NEMATODA (10)    ACARI(I)    ~urnbers per m2  I0, 000  100, 000 I, 000, I)00  i         i         |  I    COLLEMBOLA" (0. fi)                     l  PROrdRA (0.005)          [  PALl ROPODA (0. 01)    MACROFAUNA     L'NCHYTRA E I_.._ DAE (2~               J  SYMPHYL~, (0. 05)           F  D I PTERA LARVAE(2. 5;-'-  COLEOPTERA [Z 5)       ]--  DIPLOPODA {2. 5~    J    GASTROPODA (11             ]  CHILOPODA (0. 5)  OIHER INSECIA (0. 5)  ARAt~ZAE (~. i)     ]--    MEGAFAUNA   IC IDAE (40)  LUMBR    Fig. 3. Representative estimates of numbers and biomass (in parentheses) of soil organisms.  Wallwork (1970) defines size categories: microfauna, &lt; 0.2 ram; mesofauna, 0.2 rnm--1 cm;  macrofauna, &gt; I era. Van der Drift (1951) defines size categories: microfauna, 0.02--0.2 ram;  mesofauna, 0.2--2 ram; maerofau:la, 2--20 ram; megafauna, &gt; 20 mm diameter.    83    in and over the soil surface is a complex, changing mosaic of overlapping  micro- and macro-habitats which allows co-existence of a great variety of  animals with a minimum of competition (Wallwork, 1976; Phillipan et al.,  1976). Functional boundaries between soil faunal habitats are created by soil  biochemical, structural and micro-climatic (on diurnal and seasonal scales)  sequences of conditions, and by predator--prey, parasite--host and disease--  host phenomena.    .J  m  o    !    il    A    Arthropoda                           ~.   5mm ,  0pilonesi"harvest men"~  ~1~  Arachnida,                    ~  ~  ~     ,  Pedipalpi ("whip scorpions")     :~  Acari ("mites") ~0, 2mm,  lsopoda ("armadil!o bugs", "pill bugs", "wood lice") "~  0strac~a  ~0. 5rnm       0.Smm   ~4Gm   i  Copepoda--                  "~~  Tardi, rada("stow of step")   ~~e.~.  '#/|;  0nychophora ("clawed creatures". Peripatus)  r 0ligochaeta ~'Enchyt raeidae ("Pot worms")    &gt; ~.Scm  Annelida    J        [ Lumbricidae ('adhworms"l  /  LHirudlnea ("leaches") ~~,  Mollusca     (Gastropoda- snails, slugs )                ~-                                       . (,i.J~m:  Rotifera                   ~  ~  .O.3mm.  ~-'1.~,=~._ _  hschelminthes, Gastrot ric.a~  " ~  Nematoda ("round worms") ~.2mm~  PlatyhelminthesiTorbellari, "flat worms")      -- ~~   '  .  'Myxomycetes (Suctorl&amp;"slime molds")                 2turn  Ciliophora (Cillata)   ~    ~  O. 5ram,   O. 3ml~"~lmt~--~im    Rnizopo0a (Sarcodina~ A~a)         &gt;  Mastigoph:ra (Flagellate) ~    84    Animals inside the soil body    The zoo-edaphon comprises animals hying in the soil. Some soil animals do  not move freely about in soil, and some do. The term zoo-edaphon is inclu-  sive and analogous to both of the terms used by students of aquatic animals:  zooplankton, which passively float or weakly swim, and nekton, which free-  1~ and strongly swim. Some reptiles in soil are called "sand-swimmers". The    ..J  |    B    Arthrol~la    Hexal~a.    , Imm  "Cole~era ("beetles")              Olplera ("true riles")  Lepldoptera ("scale wings;b~tterflies, moths")  Trichopter,' 4m,~n,~~ ~ ~..~_  "' , 4ram,  !caddlsflies ~ ~ l~m,  l~optera (Panorpata;"scorpion flies")~'J~'~-)  ,      ,,   ~ /2p /  '~ :~,m~  pleuroptera (' ant lions l-- ,'Tb~,/~ i--~-_~3ZltZtltillw  Thysanoptera ("thrips") d~~~'~0"I~--~-4m v :~"~  Ho r~pteral"Cicadas;aphids")     ,r  Hemlptera (,~:rue bugs',)~i%. ~"~-~-.- 2c~~'  Psocoptera (Corrodentia:,"bark lice") ~ ~L~I~[~  Bsoptera ("termites")~[l~'-[]~. dram J   I  Embioptera lEmbiderla;"web spinne,'s") ~~L]~:, 3ram ,  \"-~e~_ _-' 3ram.  Dermaptera I"earwigs")~    roaches")  Dictyoptera ("mantiOs.        ~~  Phasmida ("welkin9 slicks")   -~~ ~ ~'~ ~5.~.,cm  Orthoptera ("crickets; 9rasshoppers")  Collemb?~ ('~rinjgtalls") ~/  Oiplura~mm,  "~   ('~telsontails")               ~  Protura  Thysanura ("silverflsh")~;5 cnlm'-~'-'  L JiJiW, r.t,,~.  Icm  rChlloda 1' 'c e ntt pedes"i"~&amp;v4~~         2ram  /          I   '~'~ ~'~,3,   ,  I Dlplc~(xle ("millipedes";Glomeridae or "pill bugs") ~.~-~.~"~.~  Myrlapoda,~            "        2ram         ~ "'~'~'/~"  I SymphYI  ~,    ~.  Araneae ("spiders") e~iz~[,._~-    ~ " ~  Pseudozcorplones         ~ q~~/,  Arachnida~ Scorpiones ~1 cm :~"    85    (Jl    o    r  ~C    C    "Chordata &lt;~Vertebrata,    Others  Leporidae ("hares, rabbits"l  "Mammatia,        (~h~e~s' prairie'd  ;lem --~-,=  Insectivora ("moles")          ' ~_'~~  Edenlata ("armadillo") ~    Aves  ~.~..~  Replilia                         &gt;  ,.Amphibia ~"~ '     &amp;in 4    Fig. 4. An illustrated classification of animals that affect soil (after Edey, 1965; Wallwork,  1966). "Other" includes fossorial (digging and burrowing)rnarnmals and certain birds,  and herding animals that trample the soil.    TABLE II  A classification of animals that affect soils from the outside.1    Category of    Explanation  animal    Representative fauna    Permanent    Periodic    Accidental    The animal impinges significantly on the  soil at all stages    The animal alternately impinges on the  soil from outside, and then is absent from  the soil surface    The animal falls onto the soil by circum-  stance of weather, injury, illness or tipping  of a trees    Ground dwellers; grazers,  browsers, scavengers, wal-  lowers    Water birds (petrels, puffins,  shear wings); ground feeding  birds (sparrows, robins);  arboreal-ground-feeding  rodents (squirrels); raptors  (hawks, owls)    Birds, bats, oeeupants of dead  trees    ,I Many exopedonic animals do not affect soil at all. These include whales, fish, other  aquatic animals, and animals of deep caves.    astonishing variety of soil animals is indicated by the illustrated taxonomy  (Fig. 4) and the pin-head illustration (Fig. 5). Invertebrates are commonly  reported to constitute about 90% of the biomass of animals in the soil. The  endopedonic fauna are a complex community of herbivores (phytophages    86    TABLE HI  An ecological classification of representative anim~ls* ! that affect soil    1. Endo-  pedonie  animals    2, Exo-  pedoni animals    A. Litter dwellers  B. Soil builders  at the surface    C. Soil burrowers    D. Soil pore oc-  eupiem  A. Ground walkers l  B. Tree dwellers    1  C. Cliff. bluff and  I     building dwellers  D. Cave dwellers  E. Water dwellers   !    I so,, caste    worms  l                        Millipedes  [ a. Termites  J b. Ants  2. Soil mounders     ) e. Crayfish  | d. Mammals    /  I. In litter            ~ a. Koilers (l~opoda; Glomeridae)   b. Crawlers and ~nnen (Diplopoda)  ~e. Leapers (Collembola)  2. In refuges under stohes, logs, near seeps, in cavities    l a. Earthworms  b. Potworms    1. Moles  2. Rodents  3. Rabbits  4. Badgers    1  1. Peristaltic  contractors  2. Non-peristaltic  movers  a. Large predatory nematodes  b. Ants  e. Termite  d. Bumble bees, crickets, wasps, hornets,  spiders, beetles  e. Millipedes  f. Mole crickets, moles  g. Skunks, lizards, snakes  h. Bears, badgers  i. Birds (desert owl, petrel)  1. Non-aquatic mites, etc.  2. Aquatic or semi-aquatic dwellers in water films in soil (protozoa,  nematodes, tardigrades)  1. Ungulates  2. PlanfiBrades  1. Insects  2. Amphibia  3. Birds  4. Mammals  1. Wasps  2. Bixds  1. Bats  1. Amphibia  2. Petrels    ,1 Some animals belong to more than one category. The contrasting life forms of many insects during  a lif~ history permit operation of one form in a different realm from that of another form of the same  animal.    I    3    Fig. 5. Sketch of three members of the mesofauna: 1: mite (Acari); 2: a nematode (Nerrm-  toda); and 3: a springtail (Collembola) on a pin head.    87    that feed on live plant cells, leaves, roots and wood}, microvores (animals that  feed on microflora, i.e. bacteria and fungi), saprovores (including saprophages,  that are consumers of carcasses and dung), carnivores (predators and parasites)  and pedivores (eartheaters, such as certain earthworms).    Animals outside the soil    Exopedonic animals that affect soil range widely in size and proportion of  time spent impinging on the soil from outside. A few examples will be mention-  ed.  Before European settlement, about 50 million buffalo (Bison bison} on the  Great Plains of North America had the following kinds of impacts on soils: (1)  soil compaction under hooves and reclining and wallowing bodies; (2) exposm:e  of soil to erosion at wallows and watering places; (3) enrichment in organic  matter with dung and c~casses. Suppression of bur oak (Quercus macrocarpa)  by trampling favored the development of prairie vegetation and corresponding  soils (Mollisols) rather than forest and forest soils (Alfisols). Elephants affect  soils through trampling and distribution of dung, uprooting of trees and blow-  ing of soil over their backs. Many birds are periodic in their impact on soil  (Tables II and III). Nests that are soil-body-extensions eventually fall to the  ground. Excreta and gravel (from the crops of birds) rain down from crows  (Corvus brachyrhynchos, Fig. 2) onto the soil, especially at roosting sites.  Penguins form ornithogenic soils at nesting sites, where excreta, feathers, egg  shells and bone debris accumulate (Tedrow and Ugolini, 1966). The meta-  morphosis of insects (Table I and II) allows one active stage in a life cycle to  impinge on the soil from without and another active stage to exert influence  from within the soil.    Range of movement of animals    Ranges of movements of animals that affect soil are as different as the fauna  themselves. Movement may be related to food distribution, shelter require-  ments of life development stages, diurnal and seasonal moisture and tempera-  ture gradients and other environmental stimuli. Soil arthropods may even  move in response to electrical charges induced in the soil by passing storms  (Tschemyskev et al., 1973). The range of an animal may be "trivial" (in local  "home" territory), "emigmtional" (departing fromhome territory), or  "migrational" (departing and returning) (Heape, 1931; Southwood, 1978).  The trivial range may extend from a centimeter or so in the case of micro-  fauna to many kilometers with respect to large mammals. Collembola may  climb several meters up plant stems (Bowden et al., 1976). In autumn and  spring, Lyford (1975) observed daytime movement at a rate of 6 m per day  for a total of 20 to 25 m across the forest floor in central New England,  U.S.A. of colonies of 0.5 to I million Collembola in masses measuring 30 cm  i~ d!alneter that finally and suddenly vanished without a trace. Much more    88    restricted are movements of amoeboids as they collect to form slime-mould  masses on the surface of a forest floor (Clark et al., 1979}. Male black bear  (Ursus americanus) may have a home territorial range of 119 km2 in central  Alberta (Young, 1976) and may spend the winter sleeping in burrows that it  excavates in the soil. Migl'ating birds and even insects transport raaterials, in-  cluding their own constituents, between sites that may be hundred of kilo-  meters apart.    EFFECTS OF ANIMALS ON SOIL    Impacts on soil of animals, both endo- and exo-pedonic, are grouped un-  der twelve headings (Fig. 6) that deal with manipulations of soil material and  regulations of processes. Work of animals in and on soil results in changes in  soil fabric, i.e., the size, shape and arrangement of soil components (Brewer,  1976), as well as changes in composition.    3. FORMING VOIDS  4. BACK-FILLING  2. MIXING                   VOIDS  (faunal pedotu rbation)            /  \           //     5. FORMING AND DESTROYING  i. MOUNDING ..~      ~           ~" /       PEI)S  12. PRODUCING SPECIAL     f SOIL RODY ~  4---"        conn~t  6.  REGULATING SOIL  CONSTITUENTS --~ ~,, - "" - -" " J.  ....  ,v,.  - J    ~   .~        7 REGULATING MOVEMENT  It. REGULATING/-       ~ ~ ~        ' ^'"'A  ................  BIOTA         /I~           '~       UI" W I1~1( P~PlU ~IK IN bUlL  10. REGULATING NUTRIENT  \       8. REGULATING PLANT  CYCLING          \             ~ ITTER  9. REGULATING ANIMAL  LITTER    Fig. 6. A diagrammaLic classification of effects of animals on soil.    Mounding    Mounding is point-centered deposition on the surface of the ground of  material that is mined by animals from within and/or from beneath the soil  body. Mounds may be defined as hummocks having at least 5 cm of local  relief. Some earthworm mounds are large enough to qualify (Fig. 7). Nye  (1954) describes earthworm casts in Nigeria that stand on the soil surface as  hollow columns 6 cm tall and 1.5 cm in diameter. Termite mounds may a~-  tain dramatic proportions (Fig. 8). The largest mound reported, built by  Macrotermitinae, was 9 m tall and 30 m in diameter (Lee and Wood, 1971;  Wood and Sands, 1978).  "Mires" and "pimple" mounds of faunal origin are ascribed chiefly to the  activity of pocket gophers (Thomomys spp., Dalquest and Scheffer, 1942;  Scheffer, 1958) that work most of the time in the soil during the growing    89    Fig. 7. Earthworm mounds near Polannaruwa, Sri Lanka. (Photograph by R.W. Simonson.)    season, consuming underground plant parts, and under snow cover in the  winter, consuming above-ground vegetation. EUison (1946) counted 33  gophers per acre (81 per hectare) in an Alpine grassland. Usually each gopher  occupies a separate mound (Ingles, 1952), which may stand 30--60 cm high  and be spaced 7 m from neighboring mounds. Gophers build larger mounds  farther apart on poorly drained or very shallow soils on which food plants  are sparse (Arkley and Brown, 1954; Scheffer, 1958). In addition to mounds,  gophers in alpine grasslands accumulate "ropy winter earth cores" and organic  debris in tunnels and nests located in the lowest layers of seasonal snow banks  (Ellison, 1946). The average volume of mounds made by the arctic ground  squirrel (Citellus undulatus) is 70 1 or 2.5 ft.3 (Price, 1971). Both this animal  and the pocket gopher are reported to excavate 18 metric tons of soil material  per hectare (8 tons per acre) per year. Mound-building creates a space in which  a microclimate may be maintained that is favorable to the builder~  Faunal mounds are not to be confused with non-biologic features such as  aeolian "pimple mounds", measuring as much as 1 m in height and 50 m in  diameter (Slusher, 1967), periglacial "mima mounds" that are as much as 2 m  tall and 2--15 m in diameter (Thornbury, 1965), "puffs" 60 cm high and 6 m  across in gilgai microrelief (Oakes and Thorp, 1951), tree-tip mounds  (Troedsson and Lyford, 1973), and Indian mounds and raised beds of antro-  phic origin.    90    Fig. 8. Abandoned termite mound (height about 1 re)near Polannaruwa, Sri Lanka (Photo-  graph by R.W. Simonson.)    Table IV list,~ some representative data on distribution and weight of  mounds. It may be seen that the same animal, Formica cinema, builds much  smaller mounds (25 cm tall; 40 cm wide; Fig. 9) on naturally well drained  uplands (Baxter and Hole, 1967 ) th~n in wetlands, where the high seasonal wa  ter table probably has forced queens to start new colonies on edges of the few  existing permanent mounds. These have thereby been expanded to as much as  2 m in diameter and 40 cm in height. In such a wetland {Denning et al., 1977)  some ephemeral nests also were built by the same ant around stems and leaves  to a height of as much as 35 cm. These slender structures collapse along with  the vegetation upon the approach of winter. Mounding counteracts eluviation  and illuviation (Thorp, 1949; Ba~ter and Hole, 1967; Salem and Hole, 1968}.    TABLE IV  Representative data on distribution and magnitude of    faunal mounds    91    Animal              Soil*~    Number  Percent    Dry weight  of       of area     of mounds  mounds  occupied   (t/ha)  per      by  hectare  mounds    Reference    Formica cinerea  (western mound-  building ant,  North America)  Formica exsectoides  (Eastern mound-  building ant,  North America  Formica spp.  (ant)  Macrotermes spp.  (Termite)  Cambarus spp.    (Crayfish)  Thornomys spp.  (Pocket gopher)    Cynomys spp.       Ustoll  (Prairie dog)    Typic              1,530    1.7        31          Baxter and  Argiudoli;                                          Hole, 1967  Typic                  25    0.5         20           Denning et  Haplaquoll                                         al., 1977    Typic  Hapludalf            240    1.9        31          Salem and  Hole, 1968  Vertic              1,730    2.0         19           Forcella,  HapPudoll                                         1977  Oxisol,                  5    0.d         12*2        Lee and  Ultisol                                             Wood, 1971  Albaqualf, Aquent,   625*3  0.3*3      5*~          Thorp, 1949  Aquept, Alboll,  Aquoll  Cryorthent            81    1.5        18          Ingles, 1952  Ellison and  'Aldous, 1952  18    5.0        70          Thorp, 1949    ,i Classification is according to the scheme of the Soil Survey Staff (1975).  ,2 In Uganda Macrotermes bellicosis was observed to bring up subsoil to the surface at the  rate of at least 1 m3 h-I y-1 (Pomeroy, 1976).  ,3 These deposits are usually called chimneys rather than mounds.    Two new soil horizons, called the creep-termite layer and the underlying  creep-gravel layer, were ascribed by Nye (1955} to work of termites in bring-  ing fine material up from the sedentary saprolite, leaving gravel concentrated  at the bottom of the worked zone. Where vegetative cover is lacking, mound-  ing and construction of tributary runways by termites accelerate erosion by  by wind and water. One observer suggested that Egypt is not only the "gift of  the Nile" but also, in part, the gift of termites that worked on the high pla-  teau between lakes Nyasa and Tanganyika (Lee and Wood, 1971). Point-  centered deposits of soil material are also made by land crabs, armadillos,  moles, rabbits, prairie dogs, badgers, foxes, bear, anteaters and many other  animals not listed in Fig. 4.    Mixing    Mixing of soil. called biological homogenization by Hoeksema and Edelman    92    Fig. 9. Cross-section of A1 horizon (Mollie epipedon) and two ant mounds (Formica cinerea)  in a stand of mesic prairie vegetation, Wisconsin, U.S.A. (Photograph by F.D. Hole.}    (1960) and faunal pedoturbation by Hole (1961; Buol et al., 1980). is in-  volved in the construction of the mounds just mentioned. Much mixing of  upper soil layers, however, takes place without construction of conspicuous  mounds (Troedsson and Lyford, 1973}. Animals that make point-centered  surficial deposits with a relief less than 5 cm handle large quanti:~ies of soil.  This is well exemplified by the work of Lumbricus terrestris in a Wisconsin  deciduous ~orest soil in pulling leaf litter from the forest floor into the surface  mineral horizon in which the organic and mineral materials may then be  further blended by other Annelidae and by Myriapoda. Lumbric,,~s terrestris  was introduced into North America from Europe and is currently being spread  across Wisconsin via waterways and highways by fishermen who use the ani-  mal for bait. The work of these worms has locally altered A1 horizons by con-  verting ochric epipedons that were originally as thin as 2.5 cm to 10-cm thick  dark grayish brown horizons looking like incipient mollic epipedons. The  worms commonly pull leaves into their burrows to a depth of 10 cm (Fig. 10;  Nielsen and Hole, 1964). About 300 years are estimated to be necessary for an  orchic epipedon to be formed by mixing of A2(E) and O horizon materials by  these animals in a deciduous forest at experimental sites from with the A1 hori.  zon had been removed by the investigators (Van Rooyen, 1973). R.W. Simonson  (personal communication, 1979} observed a 50-cm thick mollic epipedon in a    Middens ond  Burrows of Lumbricus_  .  restr,,$    93    Fig. 10. Earthworm middens and burrows (Lumbricus terrestris) in a deciduous forest soil  (Typic Hapludalf) in Wisconsin, U.S.A.    well mulched orchard soil in which earthworms abounded and a much thinner  ochric epipedon in an adjacent pasture where few earthworms were present.  The same observer reported from Vermustolls in Romania evidence of the  formation by earthworms of thick A1 horizons at the expense of preexisting  cambic (B) horizons. A Nigerian earthworm (Hyperiodrillus africanus) makes  surficial deposits weighing 36 t ha-1 yr-1 which is about seven times the weight  of casts deposited by Lum bricus terrestris in humid temperate regions (Madge,  1965). Nye (1955} e~timated that during a 6-month rainy season in Nigeria,  earthworms deposited 45 t per ha of castings on the land surface. A 90 cm-  thick blanket of earthworm casts buried pottery shards in Inceptisols on the  Palau Islands (Vessel and Simonson, 1958}. Lyford (1963) concluded from a  study of Dystrochrepts in the Harvard Forest that the ant Formica neogagates,  which builds 55,000 mounds per ha, each measuring 1 cm high and 7 cm in  diameter, mixes the upper 35 cm of the soil. On emerging from soil, cicadas  create numerous small, ephemeral earthen "chimneys" (Kevan, 1962). Moles  may bring up as many as 55 t per ha of soil to the surface within a year, and,  in a more arid landscape, gophers may deposit 1.5 t per ha (Abaturov, 1972).  Mixing on a small scale by insects is illustrated by a specific activity of some  ants. By means of stridulations (production of vibrations of 2{) to 60 kilo-  cycles per second), Atta ants that become buried under miniature landslides    94    can summon to their rescue fellow ants that dig out and free the victims  (Markl, 1965}.  Hoeksema and Edelman (1960) noted evidence that biological homogeniza-  tion by earthworms and moles destroys stratification in alluvial soils, brings  up calcareous material and impedes eluviation of clay from the A horizon.  They suggested that clay-enriched B (argillic) horizons in Europe are fossil,  dating from the end of a period of permafrost {8,900--8,300 B.C.) when  there was a lull in biological activity in soils during which translocation of  clay down-profile could proceed uninterrupted by faunal mixing.  Exopedonic animals participate in mixing. In a subtropical rainforest in  New South Wales, birds completely turn over the litter on the forest floor  about once every three weeks (Burges, 1965). The male bower bird (Amby-  lornis subalaris) of New Guinea builds an elaborate floral "hut" of a variety  of plant materials as a mating ground (Frisch, 1974}. Jacot (1940) notes that  H.D. Thoreau observed for a period of 30 minutes a skunk thoroughly churn-  ing a forest floor over an area of several square meters. Wild boar and domes-  ticated swine churn soil. Trampling by herds of large animals mixes soil when  it is wet.    Forming void8    The construction of mounds and the mixing of upper soil horizon:; by ani-  mals entails formation of voids in the soil. Animals that are incapable of mak-  ing voids but use preexisting openings made by other animals, plant roots and  frost or desiccation phenomena are not considered here. An estimated 7.7% in-  crease in volume of the Grundy soil (Aquic Argiudoll of a Missouri prairie)  during its genesis was ascribed by Haseman and Marshall (1945) to activity of  living organisms that created voids. Voids are formed by enclosure and by  removal through pressure or excavation. Termite runways, constructed of  soil and special faunal materials on the surface of the ground, rock outcrops  and tree trunks are enclosure voids, as are galleries in mounds built by ter-  mites and ants. Termites have been observed to extend galleries into the air,  and even to curve extensions of two parallel vertical tubes to join into one  continuous arch (Frisch, 1974). Voids of removal are made by: (1) fossers  (animals that excavate) equipped with digging limbs like those of moles  (Tapla europea, Crysochloris capensis, Notoacytes tyhlops), mole-crickets  (Gryllotalpidae), false mole-crickets (Cylindrachetidae), crickets (Anurogryl-  lus muticus), mole-beetles (Hypocephalus), gopher tortoises (Testuda poly-  phemus) and gophers; by (2) miners, including ants and termites, that ~eize  sand grains or bite off fragments of aggregates with their mandibles, leaving a  pitted surface on gallery walls; and by (3) tunnelers that push or eat their  way through soils, with peristalsis (earthworms) or without it (snakes, iimbless  lizards, amphibians). In a sheep pasture, work of gophers tended to increase  porosity and lower bulk density of the soil (Laycock and Richardson, 1975).  The earthworm Allolobophora calignosa was observed to tunnel indifferently,    95    by ingestion, through soil masses of different strengths as measured by a  penetrometer (Dexter, 1978). Cicada nymphs make extensive galleries in soil  as they move from root to root (Kevan, 1972). A solitary ant or termite  would have little capacity to make voids, but a colony of many thousands to  a million insects may have an impact on soil comparable to that of a larger  animal such as a mole. Weber (1966) reports that a large Atta ant nest in  Brazil contained below ground a refuse and cemetery chamber that measured  90 cm in height and 120 cm in diameter.  Bryson (1939) carefully excavated burrows of a number of insects, includ-  ing (with depth of burrow indicated): a cicada killer wasp (Sphecius speciosus  Drury; vertical burrow, 50 cm), tiger beetle larve Cincindelinae; vertical bur-  row, 40 cm}, a solitary wasp (Bembex spp.; sloping burrow, 30 cm long,  periodically opened to replenish with captured flies, then reclosed), nocturnal  ground beetle (Goepinus fluvicatus; sloping burrow, 15 cm long, dug each  morning in sand dune to escape heat of the day), dung beetle (Cathon lecontei;  burying rabbit droppings by rolling, then undermining them in burrow; 4 cm).  Ground beetle larvae, in search of food, make grooves in the very surface of  the AI horizon of a forest soil. These are horizontal burrows open to the  atmosphere, as much as 25 cm long, and as abundant as 100 per quare meter.  Jacot (1940} reports that colonies of solitary wasps and of solitary bees may  riddle the soil with vertical burrows to a depth of about 30 cm. Yellow  jacket wasps build nests 25 cm by 15 cm in clay banks and also in the forest  floor. Grasshoppers may drill 300,000 holes 3 cm deep and 5 mm in diameter  per hectare to lay eggs once or twice a year.  Burrowers in the soil also include wireworms (larvae of Elaterid beetles),  dipterous (Tipilid) larvae, planaria (Rhynchodermus), trap-door spiders, in-  sects that make funnel-shaped traps into the soil to catch other insects (ant  lions, Myrmeleontidae), mudworms (Tibincidae) whose channels made in  flooded alluvium persist after soil drainage (Doeksen and Minderman, 1963),  and tortoises and amphibians (Jacot, 1940}.    Back-filling of voids    Brewer's definition (1976) ofpedotubule as a soft feature with tubular form  is purely morphologic without reference to origin. The pedotubules (back-  filled voids} discussed below are of faunal origin.  Perhaps the best-known term for back-filled voids made by animals is the  Russian word krotovina (Gerasimov and Glazovskaya, 1965), meaning mole-  hole but used in pedology for relatively large soil-filled burrows made by  various animals, including moles (Talpa), marmots (Marmota) and badgers  (Taxidae), prairie dogs (Cynomys), pocket gophers (Geomyidae), and cray-  fish (Astacidae: Soil Survey Staff, 1951}. Krotovinas may appear as pale oval  spots in dark soil horizons or as the reverse. Simonson (1978} observed 10  krotovinas per square meter between the depths of I and 2 m on the face of  a pit in a Vermustoll in Romania and estimated that they occupied about 5%    98    of the volume of the B horizon. In winter, certain gophers burrow just above  the ground surface in snowbanks in the Alpine tundra, and backfill the tun-  nels with soil materials (Thorp, 1949). These fillings are exposed when the  snow melts in summer. They are emphemeral, branching, serpentine rolls of  soil about 7 cm in diameter.  By back-filling their vertical burrows under excreta with coprogenous  material, dung beeries increase the fertility of softs in Rhodesia to depths of  1 or 2 m (Wood and Lee, 1973}. Termite galleries to depths of 8.6 m may be  back-filled with clayey and silty soft materials in which roots of native plants  and crops (including coffee trees) proliferate (Lee and Wood, 1971). Filled  earthworm channels are abundant in worm-worked Chemozems (Buntley and  Papendick, 1960). In softs of recently reclaimed polders, invading earthworms  filled root channels with their porous excreta, thus obliterating the previous  channeled structure of the soft (Rogaar and Boswinkel, 1978). Some wasps  lay eggs in soil voids and back-fill with paralyzed flies or spiders and with soil  materials.    Forming and destroying peds    Peds are natural units of soiJ structure such as crumbs, granules, blocks and  prisms (Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 1978). Some animals are ped-formers and some  create apedal (massive) conditions in soil.  Collembola and Acari produce fecal pellets which in sand dune soils con-  tain most of the soil organic matter (Jacks, 1965). Entire profiles of proto-  rendzinas and rankers may consist mainly of small pellets of these micro-  arthropods (Rusek, 1975). Earthworms feeding on decomposing seeds and  other organic debris in ant nests in fine-textured soils of the Great Plains pro-  duce a fine granular structure in the surface soil. Introduction of earthworms  in new polder soils increased stability of soil aggregates by 70% in nine years  (Van Rhee, 1977) Good soil structure resulted in nitrogen-fertilized orchard  soils on which mowed grass clippings were left in place to serve as mulch and as  food for earthworms. Poor soil structure obtained in adjacent areas where  tillage damaged both peds and earthworms (Hoeksema and Jongerius, 1959).  Millipedes, isopods and termites also produce granular structure in many  kinds of soils. Mollusca (slugs, snails) exude a mucus that helps glue soil  particles together (Wallwork, 1976). Granular peds may be quite ephemeral  unless well cemented with materials that may include bacterial gums, fungal  hyphae and plant roots (Wallwork, 1970) and saliva-excreta cements made by  termites (Pathak and Lehri, 1959). Granular peds high in content of clay may  subdivide into blocks on drying qhrink--swell action has transformed worm-  induced granular structure into ~.:y fine blocky structure to a depth of 78 cm  in Chernozem profiles described by Buntley and Papendick (1960). Soil ero-  sion by water on fallow fields not only washes away granules made by earth-  worms but also the earthworms themselves, to the extent in one growing  season of 36% of the popu!ation (Atlavinyt~ et al., 1974). Burrowing cicada    97    nymphs create special "cylindrical blocky" structure by packing soil behind  them into vertical "krotovinas" in the B horizons of Ustolls and Ustalfs in  Idaho, U.S.A. (Hugie and Passey, 1963).  Presence of water stable aggregates (as well as of numerous voids) in un-  cultivated softs in Western Australia were largely ascribed by Abbott et al.,  (1979) to the work of ants, termites and beetles, that were more abundant in  those soils than in adjacent cultivated and stocked (trampled) soils.  In clayey Chernozems (Borolls) in a garden near Edmonton, Canada, earth-  worm activity is reported to have broken down friable granular structure in-  to an apedal sticky mass (Thorp, 1949). Some termites cement soil peds into  a pedolithic mass (Pathak and Lehri, 1959). Trampling by large animals, in-  cluding elephants and ungulates, near watering places may compact granular  and blocky soil layers into massive, coarse platy surficial pans or crusts.    Regulating soil erosion    Animals help to check or to accelerate soil erosion, depending on the degree  to which they contribute to the maintenance of a protective cover on the soil,  including plant canopy, litter layer, gravel mulch or crust, and the degree to  which they expose the soil to moving water and wind and to mass wasting. A  cemented surface on a termitarium may serve to reduce erosion there but by  accelerating runoff may contribute to erosion of soil nearby. Removal of the  termite Gnathamitermes tubiformans from Texas rangeland resulted in in-  creases in infiltration of rainwater and in evapotranspiration, and decreases in  runoff and sediment load (Spears et al., 1975). Lumbricus terrestris exposes  soil to erosion by removal of leaf litter from the surface (Nielsen and Hole,  1964). Ants and rodents on the Great Plains expose bare soil to erosion a-  round their burrows. The European mole (Talpa europea) makes open trenches  that erode. The relation of work of termites in west Africa to erosion has al-  ready mentioned (p. 91). Concentration on the soil surface by A llolobophora  ealignosa of casts that are enriched in clay and in available phosphorus results  in increased pollution of run-off waters where the soil is unprotected (Sharpley  and Syers, 1976).  The cumulative effect on microrelief of processes of mounding, void forma-  tion and mixing provides many microdepressions and channels for the tempo-  rary storage and infiltration of rainwater into soil. Native prairie (Argiudoll)  soils have higher hydraulic conductivity than do cultivated counterparts  (Bouma and Hole, 1971) that in a century have lost about 15 cm of soil by  erosion on slopes of less than 2%.  The effect of cattle trails in initiating and accelerating gully formation is  common knowledge. In wetlands, trails made by ungulates are commonly  depressed by compaction as much as 30 cm below the surface of the surround-  ing soil.    98    Regulating movement of water and air in soil    Activities of animals may impede or facilitate the flow of water and air in  soft.  In a soil with enough clay for a shrink--swell response to wetting and dry-  ing, a system of cracks develops without much continuity of connection from  one crack to an adjacent one except in vertic (deeply cracking) soils in a dry  season. The major change that small soil animals make in this regard is to  form vertical channels (commonly about 10 mm in diameter) that are con-  tinuous for tens of centimeters if not a meter or two. If a vertical channel  does not reach the surface of the ground, it cannot fill with water until all  fine pores in surrounding soil are saturated, because it is shielded from the  rainfall source of water by an impeding soft layer (such as a crust on a ter-  mitarium) that has a relatively low hydraulic conductivity (Dixon and Peter-  son, 1971). If the channels do reach the surface, then water may flow down  them in a matter of minutes, largely by-passing surrounding soil that absorbs  water through channel walls at a comparatively slow rate (Bouma and Ander-  son, 1977). If a rain does not add enough water to saturate an entire solum  (a meter thick, for example}, then the channels remain air-filled in the first  instance and conduct water only briefly in the second instance. A large ant  mound with numerous channels opening to the surface may well provide an  excess of macropores relative to rainfall during a given storm. For example,  Denning et al. (1977} studied a mound built by Formica cinerea measuring  140 cm across and 40 cm high that had 16% by volume of macropores in the  upper part, and a saturated conductivity there between 10,000 and 44,000  cm per day. This is one thousand to four thousand times the conductivity  needed to handle maximum precipitation expected in a 24-h period. The  hydraulic behavior of the clayey mound was in this regard like that of a mass  of gravel. The abundant voids could not possibly be filled by natural rainfall,  thus insuring that plenty of air would remain in the mound even during a  heavy rain. In addition, impacts of raindrops created a partial clay seal on the  mound, thus reducing infiltration during the course of a storm. After the rain,  the ants reopened voids to the surface and placed an additional veneer of  spongy mound material on top.  Concentration of fine earth and organic matter locally in soil increases the  water-holding capacity of the material. For example, Termervitermes gemi-  natus and Odontotermes have been observed to move down fissures in weather  ed bedrock and construct pockets of clay which served as water storage units  (Leprun, 1976).  A channel, both ends of which connect to the ground surface, may serve as  a conduit for moving air. Where one end of a burrow of a mole, rodent or  termite colony is situated on a higher point in the landscape than the other  exit of the burrow, forced air circulation takes place. Faster moving wind at  the higher point produces a flow of air by the velocity gradient between the  differing wind speeds at the two orifices. Vogel and Bretz (1972) calculated    99    that a typical burrow of the prairie dog (Cynomys ludovicianus) has an oxygen  reserve adequate for only five to ten hours in the absence of the kind of circu-  lation just described. Wind velocities of 20 cm/sec and 10 cm/sec, respective-  ly, at the two openings would replace the air in the burrow every 10 min.  Relative dimensions of animals, of their burrows and relative velocity gradi-  ents are important in determining habitat characteristics. Liischer (1955} sug-  gested that convection ventilation in mounds of Macrotermes natalensis is  driven by metabolic heat in the central brood chamber. Air permeability of  soil was increased by earthworm casting in the A1 horizon of a soil of recent-  ly reclaimed polders (Rogaar and Boswinkel, 1978).  By precise routines of testing for temperatures and manipulation of mate-  rials in large compost heaps that they build, the Australian brush turkey  (Alectura lathami) and thermometer fowl (Leipoa ocellata) maintain optimum  temperatures in the heaps which serve as incubation units for the eggs that are  duly laid in them (Frisch, 1974).  The formation of a crust on soil by trampling of large animals inhibits in-  filtration and accelerates runoff at the site.  Flooding of soil by beaver (Castor canadensis michiganensis) changes the  hydrologic regime from aerobic to anaerobic, with corresponding changes in  soil faunal activity. This phenomenon was reported by Cook (1929) from the  vicinity of Havre, Montana where moist "low prairies" were thus created in  the midst of semiarid rangeland. Cutworms that are commv~ in eastern humid  areas (U.S.A.) appeared in the low prairie soils.    Regulating plant litter    Animals regulate plant litter through various means (Van der Drift, 1963).  They are active in the decomposition of litter, they make conditions better or  worse for the growth of microflora and microfauna and they may add litter  to or remove it from the soil surface.  Soil fauna increase the total surface area and also help mix and aerate plant  materials, thereby accelerating decomposition of litter (Edwards et al., 1970),  over and above use of some part as food. The surface area is increased 15-fold  by pelletization; a faecal pellet of an Enoicycla larva contains 3,000 particles  60 ~m in diameter (Van der Drift, 1965). The weight of Quercus leaf litter was re  duced five times faster by soil animals and microflora than by the latter alone  over a period of 140 days (Kurcheva, 1960). Samples of Quercus and Fagus leaf  litter (from a mixed woodland at Rothamsted, England) that was undamaged  by animals showed no significant decrease in weight per unit area in a period of  12 months (Edwards and Heath, 1963). These examples illustrate some ef-  fects of animals in decomposition of litter.  A small part of the energy bound up in litter is utilized by soil animals, as  indicated by decomposition of plant materials passed through their intestinal  tracts. 89--95% of the leaf tissue was found to have passed through a milli-  pede (Glomeris rnarginata) unused. The tissue passes through the animal in    100    as little as 3 hours, which allows no more than partial digestion. Even so, 100  of these animals per m2 may consume between 1.7 and 10% of the annual  litter fall in a deciduous forest (Bocock, 1967; Bocock and Heath, 1967). In  another investigation, between 8 and 20% of the plant litter was found to  have been used by millipedes (Van der Drift, 1965,1975). Not all observations  indicate that partial decomposition by millipedes promotes decomposition of  litter. Webb (1,c" i/) has suggested that the faeces of millipedes on the floor of  an Appalachian forest provide less surface area for attack by microarthropods  than do rotting leaves. An abundance of faeces thus slows down decomposi-  tion of litter. Differences in decomposition rates of faeces of different soil  animals, however, may not be large. Dunger (1963) compared the gut contents  of 28 species and found the rates of decomposition to be much the same.  Animals can make conditions better or worse for growth of microflora and  microfauna. Thus, for example, the microfloral population is reduced through  grazing by microarthropods. At the same time, the microarthropods promote  growth of microflora by: (1) creating conditions in their intestines favorable  for microflora; and (2) spreading spores through the soil. As another example,  flagellate protozoa live in the gut of the termite and decompose cellulose in-  gested by that animal.  Disappearance of leaves from the forest floor can be related to soft animals  in places. Near Moscow, 30--50% of leaves in the litter were destroyed by  microarthropods and other small animals, and 68--87% by these fauna plus  large earthworms in five months in a mixed forest (Perel and Karpacevskij,  1967). R.W. Simonson (personal communication, 1979) observed in New  York State (U.S.A.) an Eutrochrept with little or no leaf litter but many  earthworms under basswood (Tilia americana) and a nearby Hapludalf with  abundant litter and few earthworms under oak--hickory (Quercus--Carya)  forest.  The kind of fauna present determines whether beech litter will be con-  verted to a mull horizon (homogenized mineral soil and humus) or a mor  horizon (litter and humus lying abruptly on mineral soils). About the same  total annual metabolism of soil fauna occurred in each of nine ecosystems, but  make-up of populations doing the work differed. Proportions of herbivores,  large decomposers, small decomposers and predators, respective!y, were: in  mull: 28%, 36%, 34%, 2%, and in mor: 32%, 3%, 45% and 20% (Macfadyen,  1963).  Above-ground animals participate in depositing plant debris on the ground.  Leaf-cutting ants accelerate decomposition of leaves by removing them from  trees and inoculating them with fungi in underground compost heaps (Thorp,  1949; Weber, 1972). According to Weber (1966) the Attine ants "are the  chief agents for introducing organic matter into the soil in tropical rain forests".  These ants are known to prosper in close coordination with termites. This  combined impact of social insects on soils is significant.  The effect of consumption of grass litter by rodents is similar to that of  fire in reducing shading and insulation of the soil and in accelerating recycl-  ing of nutrients.    I01    Regulating animal litter    In Antarctica, cold and arid conditions and the absence of scavengers ac-  count for the prolonged survival of seal cadavers lying as far as 200 km from  the coast. Faunal litter is long-lasting in ornithogenic soils of Antarctica  (Tedrow and Ugolini, 1966).  Dung and carrion fauna constitute a special assemblage of animals that dis-  pose of excreta and carcasses where moisture and temperature conditions are  favorable (Wallwork, 1976). In a pasture ecosystem in Poland, coprophagic  activity of micro- and meso-fauna doubled the rate of decomposition of sheep  dung over the rate at which only microflora (bacteria and fungi) decomposed  the faeces (Olechowicz, 1976). The giant dung beetle, Helmcopris dilloni, is  the principal decomposer of elephant dung in Tsavo National Park in Kenya  (Kingston and Coe, 1977). During one season in a sheep pasture in the Car-  pathian Mountains, scarab beetles carry 12--126 g (dry weight) of sheep ex-  crement per m2 into the soil (Breymeyer, 1974). Soil animals are active in  compost toilets and sewage sludge disposal facilities (Huhta et al., 1977;  Dindal and Levitan, 1977). Hallsworth (1965) reported that manure spread  on ~he land surface gradually disappeared over a period of two years in the  absence of earthworms but was gone within six months when earthworms  were present.    Regulating nu trien t cycling    Soil animals may make little quantitative difference in the flow of energy  through an ecosystem, but they have a definite effect on nutrient cycling  which they accelerate (Edwards et al., 1970; Van der Drift, 1975; Reichle,  1977). Animals change patterns of distribution of organic materials and have  a multiplier effect by concentrating certain elements in their bodies.  One role of soil fauna is to prepare litter, by fragmentation and mixing, for  microflora to do their work inside the guts of the animals and in their excreta.  Field mice (Microtus arvalis) in meadow steppe Chernozem softs sped biocycl-  ing of nutrients. Presence of the droppings of these animals correlated with ac-  celerated decomposition of plant debris (Kchodachova, 1971). The total  metabolism of tropical termites per unit area may equal that of the largest  known herbivore mammal population (Wood and Lee, 1973).  The physical movement of litter and nutrients contained in it from place of  litter fall to termite and ant nests, where it is degraded and where nutrients  are stored for considerable periods, is a system of plant decomposition and  mineral cycling that differs from the traditional mull- and mor-systems of  cool temperate regions. The nest-centered cycle probably affects more than  half of the land surface that is useful to people. There are about one thousand  to ten thousand termites present per square meter in many intertropical areas  to carry out the point-centered cycling (Lee and Butler, 1977). Organic mat-  ter contents of the interiors of termite mounds may be more than ten times    102    that of the surrounding soil {Lee and Wood, 1971}. A millipede in India was  found to enrich soil in oxidizable carbon anzl non-protein nitrogen (Bano and  Krishnamoorthy, 1977 }.  Ants in ~ouston and Wilson clayey so:is of Texas deposit balls of limy  materiM o, the surfaces of their mounds.  Although animal activity, such as that of certain termites, may lower soil  pH, repots of the opposite effect are numerous. Some termites rejuvenate  soils as they concentrate calcium and other nutrients in the soils by (1) bring-  ing up subsoil material and by (2) inducing a moisture stream into and through  the mound where calcium carbonate is precipitated as a result of evaporation.  Caliche forms in some mounds (Thorp, 1949). In parts of East Africa, portions  of termite mounds are used by farmers as soil amendments.  Increases in yields of orchards on new polder soil in The Netherlands were  correlated with casting activity of earthworms (Rogaar and Boswinkel, 1978).  Not only were the casts higher in plant nutrients than the surrounding soil,  but the increased aeration due to casting accelerated mineralization of nitrogen.  Fresh excreta and dead bodies of Lumbricus earthworms in the forest floor  contain glandularly secreted nodules of calcite as large as 1.2 mm in diameter.  This takes place in both calcareous and acid (pH 5.7} soils (Bal, ;977). The an-  nual death of 500,000 of these worms per hectare in a deciduous forest floor  may contribute 1.1 kg per year of calcite nodules (Wiecek and Messenger,  1972). Helmke et al. (1979) reported the selective concentration of cadmium,  nickel, leacl and zinc and, in some instances, selenium, in earthworms in Wis-  consin.  In an English dune grassland, an isopod concentrated in its tissues (relative  to dead plant tissue food} 27 23and 4)&lt; more sodium, calcium and potas-  sium, respectively. The same isopod consumed 5.1% of the annual litter pro-  duction, rapidly defecated 80.6% of the energy equivalent ingested and con-  tributed only 0.82% to the total energy dissipated in the decomposition of  the leaf litter (Hassall, 1977).  Where a soil is the repository for guano, the nutrient cycle of phosphorus  from fish to bird to sea is interrupted. Fosberg {1954} noted that sea birds  nesting and roosting in trees (Pisoma grandis) on northern Marshall atolls  deposited on the acid mor soil horizon finely divided calcium phosphate. This  was apparently translocated down the soil profile to the calcareous substratum,  where it precipitated to form a phosphate hardpan that contained 4 to 14% of  phosphorus.  The biomass of soil animals in the upper 30 cm of soil may amount to about  1% on a dry-weight basis, although it accounts for about 25% of the consump-  tion of oxygen of a forest floor, according to Barley (1961). This biomass is  itself a nutrient reserve that temporarily immobilizes ions and prevents their  being leached. Maldague (1959) estimated that the termites in 1 m2 of a rain  forest in the Congo numbered 1,000 and had a mass per ha of 100 kg and  consumed per ha per year 10 metric tons of fresh forest litter.    103    Regulating biota    By affecting properties of soils and populations of organisms, animals  manipulate the biota numerically and spatially. T.M. Ballard (personal com-  munication, 1980) considers that regulation of soil fungi in mor and moder  forest floors by Collembola and Acarina is a major effect of animals in soft.  In dispersing fungal spores by their movements, animals may bring about ag-  gregations of the spores. Resulting concentrations of hyphae may attract graz-  ing animals. Aggregation of animals may also result when reproduction of  the animals occurs more rapidly than the offspring can disperse. Effects of  the animals on the soil are concentrated at such sites. Excrement of soil in-  vertebrates are centers of biochemical degradation of the organic matter of  the soil (Kozlovoskaya, 1971). Activity of Lumbricidae may increase density  of soil microorganisms five-fold locally (Atlavinyt~ and Lugauskas, 1970}. In  field and box experiments at Rothamsted, Edwards and Lofty (1977) observ-  ed that presence of arthropods and earthworms correlated with good germina-  tion and growth of barley plants in direct-drilled, unplowed soil. It must be  noted, however, that plant growth was just as good in plowed soil in which  none of these animals were present.  Mounds made by gopher tortoises, ants, termites and moles become habitats  of complex communities of animals that may include spiders, beetles, insect  larvae, amphibians, mice, shrews, voles and snakes. Mole-hills in woodlands  may be colonized by grasses and ants rather than by tree seedlings, thus  initiating openings in the forest (Wallwork, 1970). The eastern mound-build-  ing ant, Formica excestoides may create openings in forest by killing (through  damage to roots) trees that stand within 7 m of the mounds. Earthworms  digest algae and thereby reduce algal populations in softs (Atlavinyt$ and  Pociene, 1973). The digging activity of field mice (Microtus arvalis) may be so  great as to reduce primary production by 20% in a meadow steppe Chernozem  in the U.S.S.R. (Kchodachova, 1971). Termites in the serpentine barrens of the  great dyke of Rhodesia improve the Mg/Ca ratio of soil in the mounds, mak-  ing it possible for grasses which do not tolerate conditions on soils between  mounds to produce a dense sward on the mounds (Wild, 1975). On pampas of  Argentina, the presence of underground nests of Adromyrmex ants is reflected  in a richer growth of plants at mound sites than in adjacent areas (Weber,  1966}. Under a climatic that is too dry for the growth of basidiomycetes  (fungi) in the soil, Microtermes creates favorable conditions for its growth in  an organic structure which the insect constructs in its nest (Rohrmann, 1978).  The fungus-growing Attine ants are able to culture a single species of fungus  on a leaf substrate on which many other organisms would outcompete the  fungus were it not for the constant attention of the ants and addition by  them of excreta and exudates that apparently contain growth-controlling  substances (Weber, 1966). Some ants and termites wear trails as much as 30  cm wide and many meters long. Cicada nymphs, caterpillars of swift-moths  (Hopialidae) and certain nematodes feed on plant roots, and thereby alter    104    plant cover (Ausmus et al., 1978). By converting cattle faeces into brood balls  and burying them, dung beetles in British Columbia reduce the larval popula-  tions of horn flies (MacQueen and Beirne, 1975). Activities of pocket gophers  (Thomonys talpoides) increased contents of organic matter and phosphorus  iu softs and changed a plant community in a way to eliminate the dandelion  (Laycock and Richardson, I975).    Producing special constituents    Animals that swallow and then regurgitate materials or that mix saliva or  excreta with soil materials add special constituents to the soil. Fungus-growing  Attine ants pulp and salivate fragments of fresh leaves and flowers in prepar-  ing substrate for fungi. Ant gardens consist of vegetal or faecal materials from  various insects, to which the saliva and liquid faecal drops of ants have been  added (Weber, 1972). Termite gardens consist of vegetal and soil material plus  faecal matter from the termites. Termites create clayey cements and use them  to bind sand grains in walls of termitaria. Termites also create special soil  textures and fabric in the mounds by selectively concentrating soft separates,  notably clay, and by plastering materials together in certain patterns. Lithic  masses of soil may be formed by these insects. Carton and similar cellulose-  rich materials are formed into comb in nests of fungus-garden ants and ter-  mites and in the principal structures of nests of hornets and other social in-  sects. Earthworms may increase the content of soil in vitamin B12 7-fold,  which may affect crops and other organisms (A0.avinyt$ and Daciulyt~,  1969).  Biological accumulations of heavy metals may be ~eat enough in earth-  worms to convert them into sources of toxic materials that traverup the food  chain (Van Hook, 1974; Helmke et al., 1979).  Entire soil horizons of special texture may be created by worms, ants and  termites that preferentially move particics of a certain size range to the land  surface. Nye (1954) reported such special constituents of soil profiles as the  creep-worm (CrW) layer (2.5 cm thick), the creep-termite (CrT) layer (about  45 cm thick) and the underlying lag creep-gravel (CrG) layer overlying weather.  ed sedentary saprolite.    CONCLUSION    Animals participate significantly in processes of soil formation, function  and maintenance. They may serve as sensitive indicators of states of softs and  o,~ the impacts of environmental changes. Small animals, like particles and ag-  gregates of fine earth, eluviate and illuviate in the pedon and are translocated  by erosion down-slope across toposequences of soils. The biomass of fauna is  a relatively small proportion of the total soil massy particularly in a mineral  soil, yet the activity of these animals is important in moving material upward  against the forces of gravity and of the flow of fluids, in altering soil fabric    105    and microtopography, in changing distribution patterns of soil materials and  plant nutrients and in regulating processes and assemblages of materials and  organisms. Unusually high population densities of animals may in a single  season make remarkable changes in soil fabric which, in lower horizons, may  last for a very long time.  Farmers and ranchers are well aware of deleterious effects of certain ani-  mals on the productivity of soils for crops. Less well publicized are the posi-  tive contributions of animals, particularly endopedonic fauna, in improving  and maintaining soil conditions favorable to forest and field crops. The rela-  tionships are complex, however, and statements must be made case by case.  For example, some earthworm activity accelerates erosion of the most fertile  component of soils, whereas activity at some sites stabilizes soil and increases  productivity with respect to tree fruits. Researchers have produced surpris-  ingly few maps showing patterns of geographic distributions of soil animals  and of regimes of impact of animals on soils. Soil zoological investigations are  preparing a basis for a functional classification of soils that supplements clas-  sic morphological, physical and chemical classifications, by contributing in-  formation about the nature and activity of fauna as they affect the nature of  soils and hence their usefulness.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Grateful acknowledgement is made of the assistance in the preparation of  this manuscript of T.M. Ballard of the Department of Soil Science, University  of British Columbia, J.G. Bockheim of the Department of Soil Science, Uni-  versity of Wisconsin-Madison :rod J.T. Medler of the Department of Entomol-  ogy, University of Wisconsin-Madison.    REFERENCES    Abaturov, B.D., 1972. The role of burrowing animals in the transport of mineral substances  in soil. Pedobiologia, 12: 261--266.  Abbott, I., Parker, C.A. and Sills, I.D., 1979. Changes in the abundance of large soil ani-  mals and physical properties of soils following cultivation. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17: 343--  353.  Alejnikova, M.M., 1976. Soil animal population and its changes under the influence of  anthropogenic factors. Pedobiologia, 16: 195--205.  Anderson, J.M., 1977. The organization of soil animal communities. In. U. Lohm and  T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components of Ecosystems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll.  Soil Zool. Ecol. Bull. {Stockholm), 25: 15--23.  Aritajat, U., Madge, D.S. and Gooderham, P.T., 1977. The effects of compaction of agri-  cultural soils of soil fauna, I. Field investigations. Pedobiologia, 17: 262--282.  Arkley, R.J. and Brown, H.C., 1954. The origin of mima mound (h0gwallow) microrelief  in the far western states. Proc. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., 18: 195--199.  Atlavinyt~, O. et al., 1965. The effect of erosion on the population of earthworms (Lum-  bricidae) in the soil under different crops. Pedobiologia, 5: 178--188.    106    Atlavinyt~, O. and Da~iulyt~, J., 1969. The effect of earthworms on the accumulation ~f  vitamin B12 in soil. Pedobiologia, 9: 165--170.  Atlavinyt~, O., Kuginyt~, Z. and Pileckis, S., 1974. Erosion effect on sol! fauna under  different crops. Pedobiologia, 14: 35--40.  Atlavinyt~, O. and Lugauskas, A., 1970. The effect of Lumbricidae on soil microorganisms.  In: J. D'Aguilar, C.A. Henriot, A. Bessard, M.B. Bouch~ and M. Pussard (Editors), Proc.  4th Int. Coll. Zool. Comm., Intl. Soc. Soil Sci. Inst. Natl. Recherche'Agron., 71-7:  73--80.  Atlavinyt~, O. and Pocien~, C., 1973. The effect of earthworms and their activity on the  amount of algae in the soil. Pedobiologia, 13: 445--455.  Ausmus, B.S., Ferris, J.M., Reiehle, D.E. and Williams, E.C., 1978. The role of belowground  herbivores in mesic forest root dynamics. Pedobiologia, 18: 289--295.  Bal, L., 1977. The formation of carbonate nodules and intercalary crystals in the soil by  the earthworm Lumbricus robeUes. Pedobiologia, 17 : 102--106.  Bano, K. and Krishnamoorthy, R.V., 1977. Changes in composition of soils due to defaeca-  tion by the millipede Jonespeltis splendidus. Mysore J. Agric. Sci., 11: 561--566.  Barley, K.P., 1961. The abundance of earthworms in agricultural land and their possible  significance in agriculture. Adv. Agron., 13: 249--268.  Baxter, F.P. and Hole, F.D., 1967. Ant (Formica cinerea) pedoturbation in a prairie soil.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 31: 425--428.  Bidwell, O.W. and Hole. F.D., 1965. Man as a factor of soil formation. Soil Sci., 99: 65--  72.  Bocock, K.L., 1967. The digestion and assimilation of food by Glomeris. In: O. Graff and  J.E. Satchell (Editors), Progress in Soil Biology, Proc. Coll. Dynamics of Soil Communi-  ties. North-Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 233--240.  Bocock, K L. and Heath, J., 1967. Feeding activity of the millipede Glomeris marginata  (Villers) in relation to its vertical distribution in soil. In: O. Graft and J.R. Satchell  (Editors), Progress in Soil Biology. Proc. Coll. on Dynamics of Soil Communities.  North-Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 233--240.  Bouma, J. and Anderson, J.L., 1977. Water and chloride movement through soil columns  simulating pedal soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 766--770.  Bouma, J. and Hole, F.D., 1971. Soil structure and hydraulic conductivity of adjacent  virgin and cultivated pedons at two sites: a Typic Argiudoll (silt loam) and a Typic  Eutrochrept (clay). Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 316--319.  Bowden, J., Haines, LH. and Mercer, D., 1976. Climbing collembola. Pedobiologia, 16:  298--312.  Bveymeyer, A., 1974. Analysis of a sheep pasture ecosystem in the Pieniny Mountains  (Carpathians), XL The role of Coprophagus beetles (Coleoptera, Scarabidae) in the  utilization of sheep dung. Ekologia Polska, 22: 617--634.  Brewer, R., 1976. Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 482 pp.  Bryson, H.R., 1939. The identification of soil animals by their burrow characteristics.  Trans. Kansas Acad. Sci., 42: 245--254.  Buntley, G.J. and Papendick, R.I., 1960. Worm-worked soils of eastern South Dakota,  their morphology and classification. Soil Sei. Soe. Am. Proe., 24: 128--132.  Buol, S.W., Hole, F.D. and McCracken, R.J., 1980. Soil Genesis and Classification. 2nd ed.  Iowa State University Press, Ames, Iowa, 404 pp.  Burges, N.A., 1965. Biological processes in the decomposition of organic matter. In: E.G.  Hallsworth and D.V. Crawford (Editors}, Experimental Pedology. Butterworth, Lon-  don, pp. 189--198.  Clark, R.L. and Steck, T.L., 1979. Morphogenesis in Dictyostelium: an orbital hypothesis.  Science, 204: 1163--1168.  Cook, W.C., 1929. A bioelimatic zonation for studying the economic distribution of in-  jurious insects. Ecology, 10: 282--293.    107    Darwin, Charles, 1896. The Formation of Vegetable Mould through the Action of Worms,  with Observations on their Habits. Appleton, New York, N.Y., 326 pp.  Dalquest, W.W. and Scheffer, V.B., 1942. The origin of mima mounds of western Washing-  ton. J. Geol., 50: 68--84.  Dawkins, R., 1976. The Selfish Gene. Oxford University Press, 224 pp.  Denning, J.L., Hole, F.D. and Bouma, J., 1977. Effects of Formica cinerea on a wetland  soil on West Blue Mound, Wisconsin. In: Calvin C.B. DeWitt and E. Soloway (Editors),  Wetlands, Ecology, Values and Impacts. Proc. Waubesa Conf. Wetlands. Inst. of En-  vironmental Studies, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisc., pp. 276--287.  D'Errico, F.P. and Cancellara, I., 1976. Morphological and biological observations on  Meloidogyne incognita and data relating to its horizontal and vertical distribution. Bol-  letino del Laboratorio di Entomologia Agraria "Filippo Silvestri" Portici, 33: 272--  282.  Dexter, A.R., 1978. Tunnelling in soil by earthworms. Soil Biol. Biochem., 10: 447--449.  Dixon, R.M. and Peterson, A.E., 1971. Water infiltration control: a channel system con-  cept. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 968--973.  Dindal, D.L. and Levitan, L., 1977. The soil invertebrate community of composting toilet  systems. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components of Eco-  systems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll. Soil Zool., Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 570--573.  Doeksen, J. and Minderman, G., 1963. Typical soil structures as the result of the activities  of mudworms. In: J. Doeksen and J. van der Drift (Editors), Soil Organisms. North-  Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 134--136.  Dunger, W., 1963. Leistungsspezifit~/t bei Streu~.ersetzen. In: J. Doeksen and J. van der  Drift (Editors), Soil Organisms. North-Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 92--102.  Edey, M.A. (Editor), 1965. A Guide to the Natural World. Life Nature Library, New York,  N.Y.  Edwards, C.A. and Heath, G.W., 1963. The role of soil animals in breakdown of leaf  material. In: J. Doeksen and J. van der Drift (Editors), Soil Organisms. North-Holland,  Amsterdam, pp. 76--84.  Edwards, C.A. and Lofty, J.R., 1969. The influence of agricultural practices on soil micro-  arthropod populations. In: J.G. Sheals (Editor), The Soil Ecosystem. The Systemat~cs  Ass., London, pp. 237--247.  Edwards, C.A. and Lofty, J.R., 1977. The influence of invertebrates on root growth of  crops with minimal or zero cultivation. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), ~e;!  Organisms as Components of Ecosystems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll. Soil Zool., Ecol. Bull.~  25: 348--356.  Edwards, C.A., Reichle, D.E. and Crossley, D.A. Jr., 1970. The role of invertebrates in  turnover of organic matter and nutrients: In: D.E. Reichle (Editor), Analysis of Tem-~  perate Forest Ecosystems. Springer Verlag, New York, N.Y., pp. 147--172.  Ellison, L., 1946. The pocket gopher in relation to soil erosion on mountain range.  Ecology, 27: 101--114.  Ellison L. and Aldous, C.M., 1952. Influence of pocket gophers on vegetation of subalpine  grass-lands in central Utah. Ecology, 33: 177--186.  Forcella, F., 1977. Ants on a Holocene mudflow in the Coast Range of Oregc,n. Soil  Surv. Horizons, 18(4): 3--8.  Fosberg, F.R., 1954. Soils of the northern Marshall atolls, with special reference to the  Jemo Series. Soil Sci., 78: 99--107.  Franz, H., 1974. Die Geschichte der Bodenzoologie und ihre Einbeziehung in die Boden-  kundliche Forschung. Geoderma, 12: 299--309.  Frisch, Karl yon, 1974. Animal Architecture. Translated from the German by Lisbeth  Gombrich. Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, N.Y., 306 pp.  Frolking, Tod A., 1978. The Upland Red Clays of the driftless area of Southwestern  Wisconsin; Their Genesis, Distributiop and Geomorphic Significance. M.S. Thesis,  University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisc., 175 pp.    108    Gerasimov, I.P. and Glazovskaya, M.A., 1965. Fundamentals of pedology and the geog-  raphy of soils. Gesud. Izdat. Geog. Lit., Moscow (1960). Israel program for Sci. Trans.  Jerusalem, 382 pp.  Ghilarov, M.S., 1968. Soil stratum of terrestrial biocen-.ses. Pedobiologia, 8: 82--96.  Ghilarov, M.S., 1974. Entstehung und Entwicklung der Bodenzoologie in der U.S.S.R.  Pedobiologia, 14: 61--75.  Ghilarov, M.S., 1977. Why so many species and so many individuals can coexist in the soil.  In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components of Ecosystems.  Prec. 6th Int. Coll. Soil Zool., Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 593--597.  Ghilarov, M.S., 1978. Bodenwirbellose als Indikatoren des Bodenhaushaltes und yon  bodenbildenden Prozessen. Pedohiologia, 18: 300--309.  Gisin, H., 1955. Recherches sur la relation entre la faune endogene de Collemboles et les  qualit~s agronomiques de sols viticoles. Rev. Swisse Zool., 62: 601-648.  Hallworth, E.G., 1965. Discussion of a paper by Monnier, G. and Jeanson, C. Studies on  the stability of soil structure: influence of moulds and soil fauna. In: E.G. Hallsworth  and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimental Pedology. Butterworths, London, pp.  244--254.  Haseman, J.F. and Marshall, C.E., 1~45. The use of heavy minerals in studies of the origin  and development of s6ils. MO. Agric., Exp. Sta. Res. Bull., 387 : 75 pp.  Hassall, M., 1977. Consumption of leaf litter by the telTestrial isopod Philoscia muscorum  in relation to food availability in a drive grassland ecosystem, In: U. Lohm and T.  Persson (Editors), Soft Organisms as Components of Ecosystems. Prec. 6th Int. Coll.  Soil Zool. Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 550--553.  Heape, W., 1931. Emigration, Migration and Nomadism. The University Press, Cambridge,  England, 369 pp.  Heath, G.W., 1965. The part played by animals in soil formation. In: E.G. Hallsworth  and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimeiltal Pedology. Butterworths, London, pp.  236--243.  Helmke, P.A., Robarge, W.P., Korotev, R.L. and Schomberg, P.J., 1979. Effects of soil-  applied sewage sludge on concentrations of elements in earthworms. J. Environ.  Quality~ 8: 322-327.  Hibbard, C.W., Ray, D.E., Savage, D.E., Taylor, D.W. and Guilday, J.E., 1965. Quaternary  mammals of North America. In: H.E. Wright, Jr. and D.G. Frey (Editors), The Quater-  nary of the United States. Princeton University Press, Princeton, pp. 509--525.  Hoeksema, K.J. and Edelman, C.H., 1960. The role of biological homogenization in the  formation of Gray-Brown Podzolic soils. 7th Int. Congr. Soil Sei. Trans. (Madison),  4: 402--405.  Hoeksema, K.J. and Jongerius, A., 1959. On the influence of earthworms on the soil  structure of mulched orchard~. Prec. Int. Syrup. on Soil Structure, Wageningen, pp.  188--194.  Holden, C., 1979. Dolphins to look for Nessie. Science, 204: 159.  Hole, F.D., 1961. A classification of pedoturbations and some other processes and factors  of soil formation in relation to isotropism and anisotropism. Soil Sci., 91: 375--377.  Hole, F.D., 1978. An approach to landscape analysis with emphasis on soils. Geoderma,  21 : 1--23.  Hugie, V.K. and Passey, H.B., 1963. Cicadas and their effect upon soil genesis in certain  soils in southern Idaho, northern Utah and northeastern Nevada. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Prec., 27: 78--82.  Huhta, V., Ikonen, E. and Vilkamma, P., 1977. Animal succession in artificial soil made of  sewage sludge and crushed bark. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms  as Components of Ecosystems. Prec. 6th Int. CoIL Soil Zool. Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm),  25: 573--577.  Ingles, L.G., 1952. The ecology of the mountain pocket gopher Thomomys monticola.  Ecology, 33: 87--95.    109    Jacks, J.V., 1965. The role of organisms in the early stages of soil formation. In: E.G.  Hallswo.-th and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimental Pedology. Butterworths, Lon-  don, pp. 219--226.  Jacot, A.P., 1940. The fauna of soil. Q. Rev. Biol., 15: 28--58.  Kchodachova, K.S., 1971. Influences des rongeurs souterrains en masse sur la producti-  vit~ biologique des steppes-prairies. In: J. d'Aguilar, C.A. Henriot, A. Bessard, M.-B.  Bouch~ and M. Pussard (Editors), Proc. 4th Coll. Zool. Comm., Int. Soc. Soil Sci.  Inst. Nat. Rech. Agron., Pub. 71-7. Paris, pp. 49--55.  Koran, D.K. McE., 1962. Soil animals. Philosophical Library, New York, 237 pp.  Kingston, T.J. and Coe, M., 1977. The biology of a giant dung-beetle (I-leliocopris dilloni).  J. Zool., 181: 243--263.  Kozlovoskaya, L.S., 1971. Der Einfluss der WirbeUosen auf di~ T~/tigkeit der Mikroorga-  nismen in Torfb~den. In: J. d'Aguilar, C.A. Henriot, A. Bessard, M.-B. Boueh~ and  M. Pussard (Editors), Proc. 4th Coll. Zool Comm. Int. Soc. Soil Sci. Inst. Natl. Rech.  Agron., Publ. 71-7, pp. 87_--88.  Kiihnelt, W., Walker, N., Butcher, J.W. and Laughlin, C., 1966. Soil Biology, with Special  Reference to the Animal Kingdom. Faber and Faber, London, 485 pp.  Kurcheva, G.F., 1960. The role of invertebrates in the decomposition of oak litter. Soy.  Soft Sci., April, pp. 360--365 (Translated from Russian, Pochvovedeniye, April, 1960,  pp. 16--23.)  Laycock, W.A. and Richardson, B.Z., 1975. Long-term effects of pocket gopher control  on vegetation and soils of a subalpine grassland. J. Range Manage., 28: 458--462.  Lee, K.E. and Butler, J.H.A., 1977. Termites, soil organic matter decomposition and  nutrient cycling. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components  of Ecosystems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll. Soil Zoology, Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 544--  548.  Lee, K.E. and Wood, T.G., 1971. Termites and Soils. Academic Press, London, 250 pp.  Leprun, J.-C., 1976. An original underground structure for storage of water by termites  in the Sahelian region of the Sudan zone of Upper Volta. Pedobiologia, 16: 451--  456.  Liischer, M. yon, 1955. Der Sauarstoffverbrauch bei Termiten und die Ventilation des  Nestes bei Macrotermes natalensis (Hariland). Acta Trop., 12: 289--307.  Lussenhop, J., 1976. Soil arthropod response to prairie burning. Ecology, 57: 88--98.  Lyford, W.H., 1963. Importance of ants to Brown Podzolic soil genesis in New England.  Harvard Forest Pap. No. 7, Harvard University, Petersham, Mass.  Lyford, W.H., 1975. Overland migration of collembola (Hypogastrura nirila Fitch)  colonies. Am. Midland Naturalist., 94: 205--209.  Madge, D.S., 1965. Leaf fall and litter disappearance in a tropical ~orest. Pedobiologia,  5: 273--288.  Macfadyen, A., 1963. The contribution of the microfauna to total soil metabolism. In:  J. Doeksen and J. van der Drift (Editors), Soil Organisms. North-Holland, Amsterdam,  pp. 3--17.  Macfadyen, A., 1969. The systematic study of soil ecosystems. In: J.G. Shoals (Editor),  The Soil Ecosystem. The Systematics Assoc., London, pp. 191--197.  MacQueen, A. and Beirne, B.P., 1975. Dung burial activity and fly control potential of  On thophagus muchicornis (Coleoptera :Scarabaeinae) in British Columbia. Can. Entomol.,  107: 1215--1220.  Maldague, M., 1969. Importance et r~)le de la microfaune du sol. Bull. Agric. Congo Belge,  50: 5--34.  Markl, H., 1965. Stridulation in leaf-cutting ants. Science, 149: 1392--1393.  May, R., 1978. The dynamics and diversity of insect faunas. In: L.A. Mound and N. Waloff  (Editors), Diversity of Insect Faunas. Symposia of the Royal Entomological Society  of London. Blackwell Scientific Publications, London, No. 9, pp. 188--204.    110    McLennan, J.A. and Pottinger, R.P., 1976. Mortality of grass grub, Costelytra zealandica  (White) and earthworms (Lumbricidae) during autumn cultivation. N.Z.J. Agric. Res.,  19: 257--263.  Molodova, L.P., 1976. Pedozoological data for characterization or soft types in the southern  Sakhalin. Pedobiologia, 16: 401--417.  Nielsen. O.A. and Hole, F.D., 1964. Earthworms and the development of coprogenous A1  horizons in forest soils of Wisconsin. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 28: 426--430.  Nye, P.H., 1954. Some soil-forming processes in the humid tropics, I. A field study of a  catena in the West African forest. J. Soil Sci., 5: 7--21.  Nye, P.H., 1955. Some soft-forming processes in the humid tropics, IV. The action of soil  fauna. J. Soil Sei., 6: 73--83.  Oakes, H. and Thorp, J., 1951. Dark-clay soils of warm regions variousally called Rendzina,  Black Cotton soils, Regur and Tits. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 15: 347--354.  Olechowicz, E., 1977. The effect of coprophages on faeces decomposition in a pasture  ecosystem. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components of  Ecosystems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll. Soil Zool., Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 553--556.  Pathak, A.N. and Lehri, L.K., 1959. Studies on termite nests, I. Chemical, physical and  biological characteristics of a termitarium in relation to its surroundings. J. Indian Soc.  Soil Sci., 7: 87--90.  Perel, T.S. and Karpe~evskij, L.O., 1967. Report on 2nd all-union conference in U.S.S.R.  on soil zoology. Pedobiologia, 7 : 307.  Phillipan, J., Able, R., Steel, J. and WoodeU, S.R.J., 1976. Earthworms and the factors  governing their distribution in an English beechwood. Pedobiologia, 16: 258--285.  Polivanova, E.N., 1977. Patterns of soil fauna distribution in the south of arid steppes and  their changes under forest plantations. In: U. Lohm and T. Persson (Editors), Soil  Organisms as Components of Ecosystems. Proc. 6th Int. Coll. Soil ZooI., Ecol. Bull.  (Stockholm), 25: 529.  Pomeroy, D.E., 1976. Studies on a population of large termine mounds in Uganda. Ecol.  Entomol., 1: 49--61.  Popovici, I., Stan, G., Stefan, V., Tomescu, R., Dumea, A., Tarta, A. and Dan, F., 1977.  The influence of atrazine on soil fauna. Pedobiologia, 17 : 209--215.  Price, L.W., 1971. Geomorphic effect of the Arctic ground squirrel in an alpine environ-  ment. Geograf. Annal., 53A: 100--106.  Reichle, D.E., 1977. The role of soil invertebrates in nutrient cycling. In: U. Lohm and  T. Persson (Editors), Soil Organisms as Components of the Ecosystem. Proc. 6th Int.  Coll. Soil Zool., Ecol. Bull. (Stockholm), 25: 145--156.  Rogaar, H. and Boswinkel, J.A., 1978. Some soil morphological effects of earthworm  activity: field data and X-ray radiography. Neth. J. Agric. Sei., 26: 145--160.  Rohrmann, G.F., 1978. The origin, structure and nutritional importance of the comb in  two species of Macrotermitinae. Pedobiologia, 18: 89--98.  Rusek, J., 1975. Collembola and Acarina as factors in soil formation, Pedobiologia, 15:  299--308.  Salem, M.Z. and Hole, F.D., 1968. Ant (Formica exsectoides) pedoturhation in a forest  soil. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 563--567~  Scheffer, V.B., 1958. Do fossorial rodents originate Mima-type microrelief? Am. Midland  Naturalist, 59: 505--510.  Schorger, Arlie W., 1973. The passenger pigeon: its natural history and extinction. Uni-  versity of Oklahoma Press, Norma, Okla., 424 pp.  Sharpley, A.N. and Syers, J.K., 1976. Potential role of earthworm casts for the phosphorus  enrichment of run-off waters. Soil Biol. Biochem., 8: 341--346.  Simonson, R.W., 1966. Shifts' in the usefulness of soil resources in the U.S.A. Agriculture  (Quebec), 23(3): 11--21.  Simonson, R.W., 1978. A multiple-proces model of soil genesis. In: W.C. Mahaney (Editor),  Quaternary Soils, pp. 1-25.    111    Slusher, D.F., 1967. "Pimple mounds" of Louisiana. Soil Sure. Horizons, 8(1): 3--5.  Soil Science Society of America, 1978. Glossary of Soil Science Terms. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.,  677 So. Segoe Road, Madison, Wisconsin, 35 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1951. Soil Survey Manual. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook 18, U.S. Govt.  Printing Office, Washington, D.C., 503 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Agricultural Handbook No. 436. Soil Conservation  Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Gov. Printing Office, Washington, D.C.,  754 pp.  Southwood, T.R.E., 1978. The components of diversity. In: L.A. Mound and B. Waloff  (Editors), Diversity of Insects Faunas. Symposia of the Royal Entomological Society  of London, Blackwell Scientific Publications, London, No. 9, pp. 19--40.  Spears, B.M., Ueekert, D.N. and Whigham, T.L., 1975. Desert termite control in a short-  grass prairie: effect on soft physical properties. Environ. Entomol., 4: 899--904.  Tedrow, J.C.F. and Ugolini, F.C., 1966. Antarctic Soils. Publ. Natl. Acad. Sci., Natl. Res.  Counc., Washington, D.C. No. 1418: 161--177.  Thornbury, W.D., 1965. Regional geomorphology of the United States. Wiley, New York,  N.Y. 609 pp.  Thorp, J., 1949. Effects of certain animals that live in the soil. Sci. Mon., 68: 180--191.  Troedsson, T. and Lyford, W.H., 1973. Biological disturbance and small-scale spatial varia-  tions in a fore.~ted soil n~ar Garpenberg, Sweden. Stud. For. Suec., 109:23 pp.  Tshernyshev, W.B., Ershova, N.I., Tikhonova, E.V. and Shakhanova, E.M., 1973. Influence  of electrical charges of earth surface on some soil arthropods. Pedobiologia, 13: 437--  440.  Ushatinskaya, R.S., 1978. Seasonal migration of adult Leptinotarsa decemlineata in dif-  ferent types of soil and physiological variations of individuals in hibernating popula-  tions. Pedobiologia, 18: 120--126.  Valiachmedov, B., 1977. Spuren der Lebenst~itigkeit yon Bodenwirbellosen als diagnostische  Merkmale fiir Subtypen yon Grauen WiistenbSden in Tadshikistan. Pedobiologia, 17:  60--69.  Van der Drift, J., 1951. Analysis of the animal community in a beech forest floor.  Tijdschr. Enotomol., 94: 1--168.  Van der Drift, J., 1963. The disappearance of litter in mull and mot in conr, ection with  weather conditions and the activity of macrofauna. In: J. Doeksen and J. van der Drift  (Editors), Soil Organisms. North-Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 125--133.  Van der Drift, J., 1965. The effects of animal activity in the litter layer. In: E.G. Hallsworth  and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimental Pedology. Butterworths, London, pp.  227--235.  Van der Drift, J., 1975. The significance of the millipede Glomeris rnargi~2ata (Villers) for  oak-litter decomposition and an approach of its part in energy flow. In: J. Van~k  (Editor), Progress in Soil Zoology, Proc. 5th Int. Coll. Soil Zool. Prague, pp. 293--298.  Van Hook, R.J., 1974. Cadmium, lead and zinc distribution between earthworms and  soils: potentials for contamination. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol., Oak Ridge Natl.  Lab., Oak Ridge, Tenn, 12: 509--512.  Van Rhee, J.A., 1977. A study of the effect of earthworms on orchard productivity.  Pedobiologia, 17: 107--114.  Van Rooyen, D.G., 1973. I. Organic Carbon and Nitrogen States in Two Hapludalfs under  Prairie and Deciduous Forest, as Related to Mositure Regime, Some Morphological  Features and Response to Manipulation of Cover. II. Co:inparison of the Hydrologic  Regimes of Adjacent Virgin and Cultivated Pedons at Two Sites. Ph.D. Thesis, Uni-  versity of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisc., 176 pp.  Vessel, A.J. and Simonson, R.W., 1958. Soils and agriculture of the Palau Islands. Pacific  Sci., 12: 281--298.    112    Volz, P., 1966. In: O. Graft and J.E. Satehell (Editors), Progress in Soil Biology. North-  Holland, Amsterdam, pp. 547--550.  Vogel, Steven and Bretz, W.L., 1972. Interfacial organisms: passive ventilation in the  velocity gradients near surfaces. Science, 175: 210--211.  Wallwork, J.A., 1966. Classification. In: W. Kiihnelt, N. Walker, J.W. Butcher and C.  Laughlin (Editors), Soil Biology. Faber and Faber, London, pp. 379--384.  Watlwork, J.A., 1970. Ecology of Soft Animals. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 283 pp.  Watlwork, J.A., 1976. The Distribution and Diversity of Soil Fauna. Academic Press,  New York, N.Y., 355 pp.  Webb, D.P., 1977. Report on soil zoology problems of the XVth International Congress  of Entomology. Pedobiologia, 17: 350.  Weber, N.A., 1966. Fungus growing-ants. Science, 153: 587--604.  Weber, N.A., 1972. The Attines: the fungus-culturing ants. Am. Sci., 60: 447--456.  Weber, N.A., 1972. Gardening Ants: The Attines. The Am. Philosophical Soe., Philadel-  phia, 146 pp.  White, G., 1877. The Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne. MacMillan, London,  591 pp.  Wiecek, C.S. and Messenger, AoS., 1972. Calcite contributions by earthworms to forest  soils in northern Illinois. Soil Sci. Sco. Am. Proc., 36: 478--480.  Wild, H., 1975. Termites and the serpentine of the Great Dyke of Rhodesia. Trans. Rhode-  sian Sci. Assoc., 57: 1--11.  Wood, T.G. and Lee, K.E., 1971. Abundance of mounds and competition among colonies  of some Australian termite species. Pedobiologia, 11: 341--366.  Wood, T.G. and Lee, K.E., 1973. Report of the 14th International Congress of Entomology.  Pedobiologia, 13: 248.  Wood, T.G. and Sands, W.A., 1078. The role of termites in ecosystems. In: M.V. Brian  (Editor), Production Ecology of Ants and Termites. Cambridge Univ. Press,  Cambridge, pp. 245--292.  Yaalon, D.H. and Yaron, B., 1966. Framework for man-made soil changes -- an outline  of metapedogenesis. Soil Sci., 102: 272--277.  Young, B.F., 1976. Numbers, Distribution and Structures of a Black Bear Population in  East-Central Alberta. M. Sci. Thesis, Univ. of Wisc, Madison, Wisc., 35 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractSoil is defined here in terms of arbitrary boundaries rather than of functions of a soil body. Soil animals are defined in relation to their effects on the soil body. Animals living in the soil body and intimately related to it are indeed part of the soil. Animals living above the soil make contributions to it. Many animals are amphihabitant, that is, they live for a time in the soil and then in environments outside the soil. Exopedonic (outside the soil) and endopedonic (inside the soil) animals are considered with respect to twelve activities: mounding, mixing, forming voids, back-filling voids, forming and destroying peds, regulating soil erosion, regulating movement of water and air in soil, regulating plant litter, regulating nutrient cycling, regulating biota, and producing special constituents. Animals participate in numerous processes of soil formation and effect the usefulness of soils.