 Geoderma, 26 (1981) 135--156                                                   135  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam --Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Aeharya, C. L.; and Daudet, F.A. Some difficulties in the interpretation of experimental outflow curves  for hydraulic conductivity determinations: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier  Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 4, p. 285-297, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Adams, B.; and Kitehing, R. The simulation of transmissivity, storativity and evapotranspiration in a  digital model of a fissured dolomite aquifer near Ndola, Zambia:  Hydrological Sciences Bulletin  (International Association of Hydrological Sciences (continuation of International Association of  Scientific Hydrology, Bulletin). Blackwell Scientific Publications, Oxford-London-Victoria., Vol. 24, No.  4, p. 487-498 (incl. French, English sum.), illus. (incl. table, sect., geol. sketch maps), 1979.  Afanas'eva, T. V.; Tereshina, T. V.; and Bilyk, A. M. Humus group and fractional composition in the  excessively wet soils of the Ob River valley: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation  of Moskovskiy Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No.  1, p. 53-59, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Aibertsen, M.; and Matthess, G. Transport of technetium, iodine, ruthenium, and zirconium in the  unsaturated zone [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol.  61, No. 17, p. 233, 1980. American Geophysical Union; 1980 spring annual meeting.  Allen, H. R. Erosion control in water supply catchments: Victoria's Resources. Natural Resources  Conservation League of Victoria. Springvale., Vol. 21, No. 4, p. 21-26, illus., !979.  Anderson, J. Catchment education: Victoria's Resour~.es. Natural Resources Conservation League of  Victoria. Springvale., Vol. 21, No. 4, p. 27-30, illus., 1979.  Anderson, M. G.; and Kneale, P. E. Topography and hillslope soil water relationships in a catchment  of low relief: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 47, No. 1-2, p. 115-128,  illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1980.  Andreux, F.  Genese et proprietes des n~olecules humiques [Formation and properties of humic  molecules]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 97-118, illus. (incl. tables),  Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Annovi, A.; Cremaschi, M.; Fregni, P.; et al. La successione pleistocenica marina e continental,~. del T.  Tiepido (Appennino modenese~ [Marine and continental Pleistocene succession of Tiepido River,  Modenese Apennines]: Geog~'a,ia Fisica e Dinamica Quaternaria (Bolletino del Comitato Glaciologico  Italiano, Serie 3). Torino., "v~.: 2, No. 1, p. 83-104 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, strat, cols.,  geol. sketch map), 1979.  Anonymous.  Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ccorcc terrestrc, ATP-CNRS; Action  Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques  [Material transport phenomena in the terrestrinl crust; scientific, results of the CNRS thematic research  program]:  Sciences Geologiques, Memoires (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, Institut de  Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No.  53, 162 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979  Anonymous. Alpine catchments: Victoria's Resources. Natural Resources Conservation League of  Victoria. Springvale., Vol. 21, No. 4, p. 2-6, i!!us,, 1979.  Anonymous. Soil conservation policies; an assessment: Nov. ! 5-!6, !979, United States. 154 p, it!us.  (incl. tables), Soil Conserv, Soc. Am., Ankeny, Iowa, United States, 1979.  Anonymous. Wisconsin River Basin; Soil loss, land treatment and best management practices: 13 p.,  illus. (incl. tables; en'~'iion, geol. map 1:1,000,000), 1979 (Rep. No. 11) available from: U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., United States.    136    Areola, O. Multivariate statistical analysis of soil laboratory data from Montgomeryshire, Wales: inThe  geomorphological  approach  to  environment  (Barsch,  D.,  editor),  GeoJournal.  Akademische  Verlagsgesellschaft, Wiesbaden., Vol. 3, No. 4, p. 371-378, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Austin, F.R. Soil survey of Kalamazoo County, Michigan: 102 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils  maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Mich. ~gric. Res. Stn.).  Ayyar, T. S. R.; Rao, N. R.; and Nair, T. K. G. Design and performance of a hydraulic type pressure  cell for stress measurements in soils: Indian Journal of Technology (Council of Scientific and Industrial  Research). New Delhi., Vol. 17, No. 4, p. 145-147, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Badham, J. P. N.; Cosgrove, M. E.; Crump, D. R.; et al. Geochemical and ecological investigations at  the South M:flton Consols mine site: in Proceedings of the Ussher Society conference (Bristow, C. M.,  chairperson), Ussher Society, Proceedings. London., Vol. 4, Part 3, p. 449-466, illus. (incl. tables, geol.  sketch maps), 1979.  Baldwin, R.; Bush, C. L.; Hi:':ton, R. B.; et al. Soil survey of Volusia County, Florida: 207 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates: soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Pubi. in cooperation with Univ. Fla., Inst. Food Agric. Sci.,  Agric. Exp. Stn., Soil Sci. Dep.).  Bonsai, K. N.; Sharma, D. N.; and Singh, D. Evaluation of some soil test methods for measuring  available sulfur in alluvial soils of Madhya Pradesh: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi.,  Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 308-313, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Barker, I. C.; Barnes, L. C.; and Benhow, M.C. The Russo Beds: South Australia, Geological Survey,  Quarterly Geologl::al Notes. Adelaide., No. 71, p. 2-7, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Begheijn, L.T. Determination of iron (II) in rock, soil and clay: Analyst (Chemical Society). London.,  Vol. 104, No. 1244, p. 1055-1061, illus., 1979.  Begon, J. C. Sur la mise en evidence de sequences d'evolution dans les formations limoneuses des  terrasses de la Garonne [Evidence for evolutionary sequences in lime formations of Garonne terraces]:  Academie des Sciences, Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Seances, Serie D, Sciences Naturelles.  Paris., Vol. 288, No. 5, p. 481-484 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1979.  Bennett, J. G.; Rains, A. B.; Gosden, P. N.; et al. Land resources of central Nigeria; agricultural  development possibilities; Volume 4, The Benue Valley, maps and executive summary: Great Britain,  Land Resources Division, Land Resource Study. Surbiton, England., No. 29, Vol. 4, 165 p., tables, sketch  maps, 1979.  Bennett, J. G.; Rains, A. B.; Gosden, P. N.; et al. Land resources of central Nigeria; agricultural  development possibilities; Volume 3, The .lema'a Platform; maps and executive summary: Great Britain,  Land Resources Division, Land Resource Study. Surbiton, England., No. 29, Vol. 3, 138 p., tables, sketch  maps, 1979.  Berg, N. A.  Soil conservation; the physical resources setting:  in Soil conservation policies; an  assessment (Anonymous), p. 8-17, Soil Conserv. Soc. Am., Ankeny, Iowa, United States, 1979. National  conference.  Berthelin, J.; and Toutain, F. Biologic des sols [Soil biology]:  in Constituants et proprietes du sol  (Bonneau, M.; et aL), p. 123-153, illus. (incl. tables, plates), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  BertouiUe, H.; Coutard, J. P.; Soleilhavoup, F.; et al. Les galets fissures; etude de la fissuration des galets  sahariens; comparaison avec des galets issus des diverses zones climatiques [Study of fractured Saharan  pebbles; comparison with pebbles from other climatic zones]: Revue de Geomorphologie Dynamique.  Paris., Vol. 28, No. 2, p. 33-48 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1979.  Besler, H.; and Marker, M. E. Namib Sandstone; a distinct lithological unit: Geological Society of  South Africa, Transactions. Johannesburg., Vol. 82, Part 1, p. 155-160, illus. (incl. tables, plates, geol.  sketch map), 1979.  Biernatowski, K.; and Kaczmarczyk, J. Problemy analizy statecznosci zboczy [Stability analyses of  slopes]: Archiwum Hydrotechniki (Polska Akademia Nauk, Instytut Budownictwa Wodnego). Warsaw.,  Vol. 26, No. 1, p. 129-137 (incl. Russian, English sum.), illus., 1979.  Bishop, P. M.; Mitchell, P. B.; and Paton, T. R. The formation of Duplex soils on hilislopes in the  Sydney Basin, Australia: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 175-189, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980.    137    Blackburn, G.; and Wright, D. A. Soil mapping in County Cardwell, South Australia 1933-1954:  Australia, Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization, Division of Soils, Divisional  Report. [Adelaide]., No. 37, 5 p., 2 sheets, illus. (incl. tables; land use map 1:100,000). 1979.  Blanchet, R. Les formes des elements dans le sol et la nutrition des plantes; generalites [Forms of  nutrients and their availability; generalities]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.),  p. 366-371, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Blanchet, R. Conclusion; relations entre la nutrition des plantes et les proprietes physiques [Conclusion;  relations between plant nutrition and physical properties]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau,  M.; et al.), p. 416-418, Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Blanck, J. P.; and Korosec, B. P. Etude des courbes granulometriques globales (0,002-2 MM) par  l'analyse factorielle des correspondances; application aux formations superficielles des "Llanos centrales"  du Venezuela [Global (0.002-2 MM) granulometric curves for correspondence factor analysis;  application to the surficial formation of the Venezuelan "Central Llanos"]: Revue de Geomorphologie  Dynamique. Paris., Vol. 27, No. 1, p. 1-14 (incl. English, Spanish sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Bocquier, G. Les structures d'accueil et les mecanismes d'accumulation de matiere dans les paysages;  modeles experimentaux correspondants [Structures for receiving and accumulating mechanisms of  matter in landforms; corresponding experimental models]: in Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans  l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche  Scientifique; resultats scientifiques (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires (Strasbourg,  Universite Louis Pasteur, Institut de Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte  Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No. 53, p. 19-21, 1979.  Bohn, H.; McNeal, B. L.; and O'Connor, G.A. Soil chemistry: 315 p., illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley  &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Bonneau, M. La temperature du sol [Soil temperature]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau,  M.; et a, p. 324-328, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Bonneau, M. Notion de pedoclimat [Concepts of pedoclimate]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol  (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 329-332, table, Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Bonneau, M.; and Levy, G. Assemblage et organisation physique des particules [Assemblage and  physical organization of particles]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 234-250,  illus. (incl. tables, plates), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Bonneau, M.; and Souchier, B. Constituants et proprietes du sol [Soil constituents and properties]: in  the collection Pedologie, Vol. 2, 454 p., illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Bowen, C. D.; Fox, B. C.; Lewis, D. E.; et al. Soil survey of Blount County, Alabama: 73 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Ala. Dep. Agric. and Ind. and Ala.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Boyarskaya, T. D.; and Kaplina, T. N. Novyye dannyye o razvitii rastiternosti Severnoy Yakutii v  golotsene [New data on the development of the vegetation of northern Yakutia in the Holocene]:  Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 5, p. 70-75 (incl. English sum.),  illus., 1979.  Brewster, G. R. Genesis of volcanic ash-charged soils having Podzolic morphologies, Banff and Jasper  national parks,'Alberta: Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Western Ontario, London, Ont., Canada. available  from: National Library of Canada, Ottawa, Ont., Canada.  Brierley, C. L.; and Thornton, I. Preliminary observations on the effect of heavy metals from mining  and smelting on nitrogen-fixing bacteria in some British soils: Minerals and the Environment. London.,  Vol. 1, No. 4, p. 161-167, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Brown, F. H. Environments in the lower Omo Valley 1-4 m.y. ago [abstr.]: in Abstracts of papers of  the 146th national meeting (Herschman, A., editor), AAAS (American Association for the Advancement  of Science) Publication. Washington, D.C., No. 80-2, p. 13, 1980.  Bruckert, S. Analyse des complexes organo-mineraux des sols [Study of organo-mineral compounds of  soils]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 187-207, illus. (incl. tables, plates),  Masson, Paris, France, 1979.    t38    ~ruckert, S.; and Rouiller, J. Mecanismes de regulation du pH des sols [Regulation mechanisms of soil  pH]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; eta!.), p. 354-364, illus. (incl. tables), Masson,  Paris, France, 1979.  Burger, P. A. The Greenvale nickel laterite orebody: in International laterite symposium (Evans, D.  J. I., editor; et al.), p. 24-37, illus. (incl. sects., geol. sketch map), Am. Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet. Eng.,  Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Burke, R. M. Multiparameter relative dating techniques used to differentiate tills near Wallowa Lake,  Oregon [abstr.]: Geological Society of America. Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12,  No. 3, p. 99, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, Cordilleran Section, 76th annual meeting.  Burnham, C. P. Soil formation on land reclaimed for agriculture:  in Estuarine and coastal land  reclamation and water storage (Knights, B., editor; et al.), p. 82-96, illus. (incl. tables), Saxon House,  Farnborough, England, United Kingdom, 1979.  Butzer, K.W. Geomorphology and geo-archeology at Elandsbaai western Cape, South Africa: Catena;  An  Interdisciplinary  Journal  of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology.  Lenz-Verlag,  Giessen,  Germany., Vol. 6, No. 2, p. 157-166 (incl. German sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Caine, N.  Rock weathering rates at the soil surface in an alpine environment:  Catena; An  Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany.,  Vol. 6, No. 2, p. 131-144 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Candland, D.M. Soil survey of Big Smoky Valley area, Nevada; part of Nye County: 140 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with U. S. Dep. Int., Bur. Land Manage.  and Univ. Nev., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Carlisle, D. Possible variations on the calcrete-gypcrete uranium model: 38 p., illus. (incl. sketch maps),  1980. (Rep. No. GJBX-53-80) available from: U. S. Dep. Energy, Grand Junction Off., Grand Junction,  Colo., United States.  Carlson, C.R. Soil survey of Freeborn County, Minnesota: 228 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:190,080; colored soils map 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Minn. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Casella, V. R.; Bishop, C. T.; and Glosby, A.A. Radiometric method for the determination of uranium  in soil and air; single-laboratory evaluation and interlaboratory collaborative study: 45 p., illus. (incl.  tables), 1980. (Rep. No. EPA-600/7-80-019) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Chakraborty, G.; Banerjee, S. K.; and Gupta, S. K. Molecular weights and total acidities of humic acids  extracted from soil aggregates of different sizes: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi.,  Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 129-132, tables, 1979.  Chandler, R. L. Water and chemical transport in layered porous mediz.::  165 p., Doctoral, 1979,  Colorado State Univ., Fort Collins, Colo. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Chartres, C.J. A Quaternary soil sequence in the Kennet Valley, central southern England: Geoderma,  an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 125-146,  illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Chatelin, Y. Une epistemologie des sciences du sol [An epistemology of soil science]: France, Office  de la Recherche Scientifique et Technique Outre-Mer, Memoires. Paris., No. 88, 151 p., illus., 1979.  Chaussidon, J. Complexe absorbant; ldis generales d'echange des anions et des cations [Absorbing  complex; anions and cations exchange, properties]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.;  et al.), p. 333-352, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Chilingar, G. V.; Bisseli, H. J.; and Wolf, K.H. Diagenesis of carbonate sediments and epigenesis (or  catagenesis) of limestones: in Diagenesis in sediments and sedimentary rocks (Larsen, G., editor; et al.),  Vol. 25A, p. 247-422, illus. (incl. plates, tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., New York, N.Y., United States,  1979.  Choudhari, J. S.; and Jain, S.V. Forms of potassium and K fixing capacity of soils in different agro-  climatic regions of Rajasthan: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 2, p.  123-128, tables, 1979.    139    Choudhari, J. S.; Pareek, B. L.; and Seth, S. P. Distribution of different forms of iron in some major  soil groups of Rajasthan: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 338-  340, table, 1979.  Christiansson, C. Imagt Dam; a study of soil erosion, reservoir sedimentation and water supply at  Dodoma, central Tanzania: Geografiska Annaler, Series A, Physical Geography (Svenska Saellskapet  foer Antropologi och Geografi). Stockholm., Vol. 61A, No. 3-4, p. 113-145, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), 1979.  Churchman, G.J. Clay minerals from micas and chlorites in some New Zealand soils: Clay Minerals  (Mineralogical Society, Clay Minerals Group, Journal). Oxford-Edinburgh., Vol. 15, No. 1, p. 59-76  (incl. French, German, English, Spanish sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Cole, G.; and Knights, B. An introduction to estuarine and coastal land reclamation and water storage:  in Estuarine and coastal land reclamation and water storage (Knights, B., editor; et aL), p. 3-20, Saxon  House, Farnborough, England, United Kingdom, 1979.  Coleman, D. D. The origin of drift-gas deposits as determined by radiocarbon dating of methane: in  Radiocarbon dating (Berger, R., editor; et aL), Proceedings of the International Conference [on]  Radiocarbon Dating., No. 9, p. 365-387, illus. (incl. sketch maps, geol. sects., tables), 1979.  Collins, J. F.; Fan'ell, E. P.; and O'Toole, P. Topo-, litho- and chronosequences of soil in Avondale  Forest Park, County Wicklow: Journal of Earth Sciences, Royal Dublin Society., Vol. 2, No. 1, p. 71-  83, tables, 1979.  Combes, P.J. Observations sedimentologiques, paleogeographiques, mineralogiques et geochimiques  ~;ur les bauxites du deuxieme horizon darts la zone du Parnasse (Grece) [Sedimentological,  paleogeographical, mineralogical and geochemical observefions on the bauxites of the second horizon in  the Parnassus Zone, Greece]: Bulletin de la Societe Geologique de France. Paris., Vol. 2 i, No. 4, p. 485-  494 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. strat, col., sect., geol. sketch map), 1979.  Conesa, A. P.; Fardeau, J. C.; and Simon-Sylvestre, G. Le phosphore et le soufre [Phosphorus and  sulfur]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 395-406, illus. (incl. tables, plates),  Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Coppenet, M.; and Juste, C. Oligoelements indispensables a la vie des plantes; phenomenes de toxicite  [Plant needs of micronutrients; deficiency and toxocity]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau,  M.; et al.), p. 408-415, tables, Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Corbett, E.S. Hydrologic evaluation of the stormflow generation process on a forested watershed: 149  p., Doctoral, 1979, Pennsylvania State Univ., University Park, Pa. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Corwin, R. V. (editor). The geomorphic evolution of the Grand Prairie: ! 8 p., illus. (incl. sects., strat.  cols., tables), Baylor Univ., Moody, Tex., United States, 1979.  Corwin, R. V. Soils of the Washita Prairie, part l: in The geomorphic evolution of the Grand Prairie  (Corwin, R. V., editor), p. 9, illus. (incl. sects.), Baylor Univ., Moody, Tex., United States, 1979.  Corwin, R. V. Soils of the Washita Prairie; part 2: in The geomorphic evolution of the Grand Prairie  (Corwin, R. V., editor), p. 1 l, illus. (incl. sects.), Baylo~ Univ,, Moody, Tex., United States, 1979.  Cottenie, A.; Camerlynek, R.; Verioo, M.; et al. Fractioration and determination of trace elements in  plants, soils and sediments: Pure and Applied Chemistry, Pergamon Press, Oxford, England., Vol. 52,  No. l, p. 45-52, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Coventry, R. J.; and Fett, D. E. R. A pipette and sieve method of particle-size analysis and some  observations on its efficiency:  Australia, Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research  Organization, Division of Soils, Divisional Report. [Adelaide], No. 38, 26 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Culver, J. Soil conservation; a partial commitment is not enough: in Soil conservation policies; an  assessment (Anonymous), p. 3-7, Soil Conserv. Soc. Am., Ankeny, Iowa, United States, 1979. National  conference.  Curtal, P. Genese d'une structure litee a granulometrie heterogene dans une arene granitique [Genesis  of a bedded structure with a heterogeneous particle size distribution in granite saprolite]: Academie des  Sciences, Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Seances, Serie D, Sciences Naturelles. Paris., Vol. 288,  No. 8, p. 731-733 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. plate, sect.), 1979.    140    Curtin, D.; and Smillie, G. W. Variatio, in cation exchange capacities of Irish soils in relation to sail  properties and method of measurement: Journal of Earth Sciences, Royal Dublin Society., Vol. 2, No.  1, p. 85-95, tables, 1979.  Curtis, A. A.; and Watson, K. K. Numerical analysis of infiltration into a sand profile bounded by a  capillary fringe: Water Resources Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 16,  No. 2, p. 365-'371, illus., 1980.  Darab, K.; Csillag, d.; and Pinter, I. Studies on the ion composition of salt solutions and of saturation  extracts of salt-affected soils: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Pub1. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 95-111, tables, 1980.  Day, A. D.; Tucker, T. C.; and Thames, J. L, Reclamation and water relations of strip mine spoils in  northern Arizona (1976-1978): 46 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. EPA-600/7-79-258) available  from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Day, M. d. Rock hardness; field assessment and geomorphic importance: Professional Geographer  (Association of American Geographers). Washington, D. C., Vol. 32, No. 1, p. 72-81, illus. (incl. tables),  1980.  Dearman, W. R.; and Baynes, F.J. Etch-pit weathering of feldspars: in Proceedings of the Ussher  Society conference (Bristow, C. M., chairperson), Ussher Society, Proceedings. London., Vol. 4, Part 3,  p. 390-401, illus., 1979.  Deearreau, A.; Courtois, C.; and Steinberg, M. Comportement des elements de la premiere serie de  transition et des lanthanides dans les alterations naturelles et experimentales [Behavior of elements of  the first transition series and lanthanides in natural and experimental alterations]: in Phenomenes de  transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action Thematique Programmee du Centre  National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques,  Memoires (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, lnstitut de Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine,  Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No. 53, p. 29-34, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Dejou, J.; and Cb~sworth, W. Nouvelles observations concernant l'evolution geochimique superticieile  des basaltes mieeenes du bassin d'Aurillac (Cantal); Nature fersiallitique de cette evolution et  consequences paleoclimatiques [New observations on the surficial geochemical evolution of Miocene  basalts in Aurillac Basin, Cantal; fersiailitic nature of that evolution and paleoclimatologic consequences]:  Academie des Sciences, Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Seances, Serie D, Sciences Naturelles.  Paris., Vol. 288, No. 3, p. 295-298 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Dejou, d.; and Ildefonse, P. Analogies et differences enregistrees au cours des alterations superficielies  naissantes et anciennes developpees sur roches basiques en regions temperees humides; cas des roches  gabbroiques de la haute vallee de la Jordanne (Cantal) et du massif du Pallet (Loire-Atlantique)  [Comparative study of recent and ancient weathering materials developed on basic rocks in humid  temperate climate; example of gabbros from the Jordanne upper valley, Cantal, and from the Pallet  Massif, Loire-Atlantic]: Academie des Sciences, Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Seances, Serie  D, Sciences Naturelles. Paris., Vol. 288, No. 5, p. 465-468 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Delcourt, H, R. Late Quaternary vegetation history of the eastern Highland Rim and adjacent  Cumberland Plateau of Tennessee: Ecological Monographs (Ecological Society of America). Durham,  North Carolina., Vol. 49, No. 3, p. 255-280, 1979.  Delibrias, G.; Di P~o|a, G. M.; Rosi, M.; et al. La storia eruttiva del complesso vulcanico Somma  Vesuvio ricostru~ta dalle successioni piroclastiche del Monte Somma [Eruptive history of the Somma-  Vesuvius vo!,~anic complex as deduced from the pyroclastic sequences of Monte Somma]: Societa  ltaliana di Mineralogia e Petrologia, Rendiconti. Milan., Vol. 35, No. 1, p. 4 ! 1-438 (incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. tables, strat, cols., sketch map), 1979.  Dent, D. (reviewer); and Hodgson, J.M. Monographs on soil survey, soil sampling and soil description:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No.  2, p. 161-162, 1980.  Devyatkin, Ye. V.; and Murzayeva, V. E.  Opyt raschleneniya moren po kompleksu litologo-  geomorfologicheskikh priznakov (na primere Mongorskogo Altaya) [Moraine subdivision according to  li~.hological-geomorphological features; the Mongolian Altai as an example]:  Vsesoyuznoye  Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya. Leningrad., Vol. 111, No. 4, p. 342-348, illus. (incl. tables),  1979.    141    Dissanayake, C. B. Mineralogy and chemical composition of some laterites of Sri Lanka: Geoderma,  a~ International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 147-155,  illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  Dobrovol'skaya, N. G. Osobennosti subakval'nogo vyvetrivaniya na ravninnykh i gornykh rekakh (na  primere Leny i Kara-Bau, Zapadnyy Tyan'-Shan') [Characteristic features of subaqueous weathering on  plain and mountain rivers; exemplified by the Lena and Kara Bau River in the western Tien Shan]:  "v'estnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 2, p. 71-75 (incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Dolezel, R. Soil survey of Nacogdoches County, Texas: 146 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Douglas, I. (reviewer); and Morgan,, R. P. C, Soil erosion: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil  Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 220-221, 1980.  Douglas, L. A.; and Trela, J. J. Mineralogy of Pine Barrens soils:  in Pine Barrens; ecosystem and  landscape (Forman, R. T. T., editor), p. 95-109, illus., Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Drake, J. J. The effect of soil activity on the chemistry of carbonate groundwaters: Water Resources  Research (American Geophysical Uniol,). Washington, D.C., Vol. 16, No. 2, p. 381-386, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Dupuis, J.; Dupui% T.; Jambu, P.; et al. Role des acides fulviques dans la mobilisation du fer et de  l'aluminium [Role of fulvic acids in the mobilization of iron and aluminum]: in Phenomenes de transport  de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action Thematique Programmee du Centre National de  la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires  (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, lnstitut de Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de  la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No. 53, p. 7-11, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Durgin, P. B. The influence of ash leachate on forest erosion [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado,, Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 104, 1980.  The Geological Society of  America, Cordilleran Section, 76th annual meeting.  Dutil, P. Le calcaire dans les sols; calcium et magnesium [Lime, calcium and magnesium in soils]: in  Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et ai.), p. 372-378, tables, Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Eiten, G.; and Goodland, R. J. A, Ecology and management of semi-arid ecosystems in Brazil: in  Management of semi-arid ecosystems (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 277-300, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  map), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Evans, D. J. I.; Shoemaker, R. S.; and Veltman, H. (editors). International laterite symposium: Feb.  19-21, 1979, United States. 677 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Am. Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet.  Eng., Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Fedoroff, N. Organisation du sol a l'echelle microscopique [Soil organization at microscopical scale]:  in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 251-265, illus., Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Fields, P. F. The Miocene Payette flora; a new lo0k at an old probler~ [abstr.]: Geological Society of  America, Abstracts with Programs. Bouldcz, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 106, 1980.  The Geological  Society of America, rdilleran Section, 76th annual meeting.  Firestone, M. K.; Firestone, R. B.; and Tiedje, J. M. Nitrous oxide from soil denitrification; factors  controlling its biological production: Science (American Association for the Advancement of Science).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 208, No. 4445, p. 749-751, chart, 1980.  Folque, J. Prdpriedades mecanicas de" solos; algumas reflexoes sobre ensaios de laboratorio e ensaios  in situ [Mechanical properties of soils; laboratory and in situ tests]: Geotecnia (Sociedade Portuguesa  de Geotecnia, Revista)(continuation ofGeotecnia; Agrupamento Portugues de Mecanica dos Solos e das  Rochas, Revista). Lisbon., No. 26, p. 3-14 (incl. English sum.), 1979.  Ford, A.; and Pauls, E. Soil survey of Dentoii County, Texas: 160 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Foster, I. D. L. Chemistry of bulk precipitation throughfall, soil water and stream water in a small  catchment in Devon, England: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-  Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 6, No. 2, p. 145-155 (incl. German sum.), illus. (incl.  tables, sketch map), 1979.    142    Fountain, J. C.; and Aioysius, D. L. Rare earth mobility during weathering of granitoids [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 36-37,  1980.  The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th annual meeting.  Fox, R. E.; and Lee, G.B. Soil survey of Dodge County, Wisconsin: 201 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates;  soils maps 1:15,840: colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Wis., Res. Div. Coll. Agric., Life Sci.).  Frank, T. D. Categorization of watershed land cover units with Landsat data: 187 p., Doctoral, 1979,  Univ. of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Fridland, V. M.; and Glazovskaya, M. A. Osnovnyye formy struktur pochvennogo pokrova Zemli  [Fundamental forms of the structure of the Earth's soil cover]: Priroda (Akademiya Nauk SSSR).  Moscow., No. 11, p. 61-69, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Froedge, R. B.; and Weisenburger, B. C. Soil survey of Grant and Pendleton counties, Kentucky: 85  p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour.  Environ. Prot. and Ky. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Frydman, S.; Melnik, J.; and Baker, R. The effect of prefreezing on the strength and deformation  properties of granular soils: Soils and Foundations (The Japanese Society of Soil Mechanics and  Foundation Engineering). Tokyo., Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 31-42, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Fujimura, H.; Kiyama, H.; and Sugitsue, Y. Laboratory measurements of permeability of soft rock  ground; fundamental studies on the permeability analysis for in-place leaching: Japan, Mining and  Metallurgical Institute, Journal. Tokyo., Vol. 95, No. 1100, p. 715-720 (Japanese, incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Gallagher, M. N.; Adams, J. K.; and Grandstaff, D. E. Hydrology and geochemistry of central Bucks  County, South-eastern Pennsylvania [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 37, 1980. The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section,  15th annual meeting.  Garland, G. G. Rural, non-agricultural land-use and rates of erosion in the Natal Drakensberg:  Environmental Conservation. Elsevier Sequoia, Lausanne., Vol. 6, No. 4, p. 273-276, illus. (incl. table,  sect., sketch map), 1979.  Garner, B. A.; and Cox, J.B. Soil survey of Crawford County, Arkansas: 91 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates;  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Arkansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Gerasimova, M. I.; and Lazakova, G. G. O partsellyarnosti biogeotsenozov sosnovykh lesov na  polimineral'nykh peskakh tsentra Russkoy ravniny [Parcella structures of the biogeocenoses of pine  woods on polymineral sands of the central Russian Plain]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya  5, Geografiya. Moscow., No: 2, p. 46-53 (incl. English sum.), tables, 1980.  German, R. Beobachtungen am Dauerfrostboden Nordkanadas; zur Deutung quartaerer Sedimente und  Formen XIII [The permafrost of northern Canada; interpretation of Quaternary sediments and  landforms; Part 13]: Gesellschaft fuer Naturkunde in Wuerttemberg, Jahreshefte ( continuation of Verein  fuer Vaterlaendische Naturkunde in Wuerttemberg, Jahreshefte). Stuttgart., Vol. 134, p. 104-110, illus.,  1979.  Gill, H. V.; L'~rance, F. C.; Fultz, C. L.; et al. Soil survey of Calhoun and Dallas counties, Arkansas:  80 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Arkansas Agric.  Exp. Stn.).  Gillman, G. P~; and Bakker, P. The. compulsive exchange method for measuring surface charge  characteristics of soil: Australia, Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization,  Division of Soils, Divisional Report. [Adelaide]., No. 40, 7 p., illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Gientworth, R. Observations on the soils of the Outer Hebrides: in The natural environment of the  Outer Hebrides (Boyd, J. M., editor), Royal Society of Edinburgh, Proceedings, Section B (3iology).,  Vol. 77, p. 123-137, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Godfrey, P. J.; Benedict, M.; and Zaremba, R. Overwash and vegetation response on barrier islands  and beaches of eastern North America [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 38, 1980. The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section,  15th annual meeting.    143    Golightly, d. P. Nickeliferous laterites; a general description:  in International laterite symposium  (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 3-23, illus. (incl. table), Am. Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet. Eng. Soc.  Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Golightly, J.P. Geology of Soroako nickeliferous laterite deposits: m International laterite symposium  (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 38-56, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), Am. Inst. Min., Metall.,  and Pet. Eng., Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Griffith, S. M.; Silver, J.; and Sehnitzer, M. Hydrazine derivatives at Fe3+ sites in humic materials:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Sci'nce. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No.  4, p. 299-302, table, 1980.  Guillet, B. Etude du renouvellement des matieres organiques des sols par les radioisotopes (14C) [Study  of the turnover of organic matter through radiioisotopes; C-14]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol  (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 210-225, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Guillet, B.; and Rouiller, J. La granulometrie [Granulometry]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol  (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 227-232, illus. (incl. t~tbles), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Guillet, B.; and Souchier, B. Les oxyhydroxydes amorphes et cristallins dans les sols (fer, aluminium,  manganese, silicium) [Amorphous and crystalline oxyhydroxides in soils; iron, aluminum, manganese,  silica]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, N~ ; et al.), p. 16-35, illus. (incl. tables), Masson,  Paris, France, 1979.  Guillet, B.; Vedy, J. C.; Rouiller, J.; et al. Migrations de particules argileuses dans les milieux de  geochimie organique tres acide; exemple des podzols sur coUuvium de gres vosgien [Clay particle  migration in very acid organic geochemical environments; podzols below Vosges sand colluvium]: in  Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action Thematique  Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques (Anonymous),  Sciences  Geologiques,   Memoires   (Strasbourg,   Universite   Louis  Pasteur,   Institut  de  Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No.  53, p. 13-18, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Gundlach, H. F. Soil survey of Sauk County, Wisconsin: 248 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Wis., Coll. Agric. Life Sci., Res. Div.).  Haekansson, S. Radiocarbon activity in submerged plants from various South Swedish lakes:  in  Radiocarbon dating (Berger, R., editor; et ai.), Proceedings of the International Conference [on]  Radiocarbon Dating., No. 9, p. 433-443, illus. (incl. tables), i979.  Hail, C. W.; Whitaker, O. J.; McDonald, H. P.; et al. Soil survey of Shelby County, Kentucky: 84 p.,  illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Pub1. in coop. with Ky. Agric. Exp. Stn. and  Ky. Dep. Nat. Resour. Environ. Prot.).  Haidemann, E. G,; Buchan, R.; Blowes, J. H.; et al. Geology of lateritic nickel deposits, Dominican  Republic: in International laterite symposium (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 57-84, illus. (incl. tables,  geol. sketch map), Am. Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet. Eng., Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States,  1979.  Hannibal, J.; and Palermo, A. Sidewalk geology: Explorer. Cleveland Museum of Natural History,  Cleveland, Ohio., Vol. 22, No. 1, p. 25,30, illus., 1980.  Harju, H. O. Exploration of Exmiba's nickel laterite deposits in Guatemala: in International laterite  symposium (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 245-251, illus. (incl. sketch map), Am. Inst. Min., Metall.,  and Pet. Eng., Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Harju, H. O.  Exploration of P.T. INCO's nickel laterite deposits in Sulawesi, Indonesia:  in  International laterite symposium (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 292-299, illus. (incl. sketch maps), Am.  Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet. Eng., Soc. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Hauge, C. J.; Furniss, M. J.; and Euphrat, F.D. Forest practice rules and soil erosion in the coast forest  district: in A field trip to observe natural and management-related erosion in Franciscan terrane of  northern California (Anonymous), p. 1-18, illus. (incl tables, geol. sketch maps), Geol. Soc. Am., San  Jose, Calif., United States, 1979.    Hay, R.L. Paleoenvironment of the Laetolil Beds [abstr.]: in Abstracts of papers of the 146th national  meeting (Herschman, A., editor), AAAS (American Association for the Advancement of Science)  Publication. Washington, D.C., No. 80-2, p. 13, 1980.  Hebert, J. L'azote [Nitrogen]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et at), p. 386-393,  illus., Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Heil, D. M.; and Mausbaeh, M.J. Soil survey of McCook County, South Dakota: 123 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Heine, R. W. Microanalysis of planation surfaces in the Port Nicholson Basin (Wellington City), and  relationship of tectonic features: New Zealand Journal of Geology and Geophysics. Wellington., Vol.  22, No. 3, p. 379-390, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Heusser, C. J. Vegetational history of the Pine Barrens: in Pine Barrens; ecosystem and landscape  (Forman, R. T. T., editor), p. 215-227, illus., ?~.cad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Hirobe, R.; and Ikarashi, T. Unconfined compression test of frozen sandy soil: National Research  Center for Disaster Prevention, Report. Tokyo., No. 22, p. 167-173 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus.,  1979.  Hoilingshead, G. W.; and Slater, R. R. A novel method of deriving weathering statics from first arrival  refractions [abstr.]: Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Annual International Meeting, Abstracts., No.  49, p. 53-54, 1979.  Hopps, H. C. The geochemical environment in relationship to health and disease: Interface (Society  for Environmental Geochemistry and health). Morgantown, West Virginia., Vol. 8, No. 3, p. 24-29, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Horn, H. M. North American experience in ~ampling and laboratory dynamic testing: Geotechnical  Testing Journal (American Society for Testing and Materials). Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., Vol. 2, No.  2, p. 84-97, illus. (incl. tables, plates), i979.  Horowitz, A. The Quaternary of israel: 394 p., illus. (incl. tables, strat, cols., plates, geol. sketch maps),  Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Horsch, M. L. Soil survey of Cowle~ County, Kansas: 123 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440),. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Kansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Imai, T,; and Kanemori, T. Dynamic deformation characteristics of soils by seismic method and  laboratory test [abstr.]: Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Annual International Meeting, Abstracts.,  No. 49, p. 76, 1979.  Ivanov, G. I. Pochvy yuga Dal'nego Vostoka [Soils of the southern Soviet Far East]:  Priroda  (Akademiya Navk SSSR). Moscow., No. 8, p. 44-51, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Jamagne, M. La cartographic des sols [Soil cartography]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau,  M.; et al.), p. 419-438, geol. sketch maps, Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Janetzko, P. Die Elbmarschen zwischen Glueckstadt und Elmshorn (Schleswig-Holstein) [The Elbe  marshes between Glueckstadt and Elmshorn, Schleswig-Holstein]:  Meyniana (Kiel, Universitaet,  Geologisches lnstitu0. Neumunster., Vol. 31, p. 1-13 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  John, B. Planet Earth and its seasons of cold: in The winters of the world; Earth under the ice ages  (John, B. S., editor), p. 9-28, illus. (incl. tables, plates, geol. sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York,  N.Y., United States, 1979.  Johnson, G. D. Pedogenic character of the Miocene-Pliocene Siwalik Group, Pakistan [abstr.]: in  Abstracts of papers of the 146th national meeting (Herschman, A., editor), AAAS (American  Association for the Advancement of Science) Publication. Washington, D.C., No. 80-2, p. 14, 1980.  Jones, T. L.; and Jordan, W. A. Using field measured and laboratory measured hydraulic parameters  to predict infiltration and drainage [abstr.]:  Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions).  Washington, D. C., Vol. 61, No. 17, p. 232, 1980. American Geophysical Union; 1980 spring annual meeting.  Joshi, D. C.; and Ghonsikar, C. P. Studies on humus characterisation and distribution in particle size  separates in some typical soils of Rajasthan: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol.  27, No. 3, p. 252-260, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.    145    Kagami, H.; and Kishi, S. An evaluation of liquefaction potentials in Kawasaki City using a new  simplified discrimination method: National Research Center for Disaster Prevention, Report. Tokyo.,  No. 22, p. 101-111 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Kalyuzhnyy, I. L.; and Pavlova, K. K. Teoreticheskiy analiz zavisimosd koeffitsiyenta vodootdachi  pochvy ot skorosti izmeneniya urovnya gruntovykh rod [A theoretical analysis of the relationship  between the water yield coefficient of soils and the rate of soil water level change]: Meteorologiya i  Gidrologiya (USSR, Glavnoye Upravleniye Gidrometeorologicheskoy Sluzhby). Moscow., No. 12, p. 83-  90 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Kanevskiy, A. Ya. Otbor i obrabotka prob gipergennykh nikelevykh rud [Sampling and developing tests  for hypogene nickel ores]: Razvedka i Okhrana Nedr (Ministerstvo Geologii SSSR). Moscow., No. 10,  p. 53-55, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Karavaev, A. I.; Shevtsov, N. M.; and Sudnitsyn, I. I. Automatic regulation of soil water regime:  Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya  Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. I, p. 35-38, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Kemper, W. D. (reviewer). Modification of soil structure: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil  Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 226-227, 1980.  Kerndorff, H.; and Sehnitzer, M. Humic and fulvic acids es indicators of soil and water pollution:  Water, Air, and Soil Poqution. D. Reidel Publ. Co., Dordrecht., Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 319-329, illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Kerr, J. W.; and Christman, R. L. Soil survey of Pickaway County, Ohio: 172 p., illus. (incl. tv-bles.  plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Div. Lands Soil,  and Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).  Kharin, G. S.; and Zangalis, K.P. Clay minerals in the redbed on the Faeroe-lcelandic Ledge (northern  Atlantic):  Lithology  and  Mineral  Resources  (English  translation  of Litologiya  i  Poleznyye  Iskopayemyye). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 14, No. 3, p. 299-306, illus. (incl. sect., table,  plates, sketch map), 1979 [1980].  Kilmer, V. J.  Minerals and agricultare:  in Biogeochemical cycling of mineral-forming elements  (Trudinger, P. A., editor; et aLL p. 515-554, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam,  Netherlands, 1979.  Kipp, K. L. Mathematical modeling of chemical transport in soil columns [abstr.]: Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 61, No. 17, p. 234, 1980.  American  Geophysical Union; 1980 spring annual meeting.  Kiselev, I. I.  Paleogeografiya zapadnoy chasti Kol'skogo poluostro,:a v ne~,gene i antropogene  [Paleogeography of the western portion of the Kola Peninsula in the Neogene and Anthropogene]:  Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya. Leningrad., Vol. 111, No. 4, p. 316-323, sketch  maps, 1979.  Knight, M. J. Structural analysis and mechanical origins of gilgai at Boorook, Victoria, Australia:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No.  4, p. 245-283, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Knights, B. Reclamation in the Netherlands:  in Estuarine and coastal land reclamation and water  storage (Knights, B., editor; et aL), p. 209-233, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Saxon House.  Farnborough, England, United Kingdom, 1979.  Krenkel, P. A.; and Ruane, R.J. Basic approach to water quality modeling: in Modeling of rivers (Shen,  H. W., editor), 38 p., illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979. (A  Wiley-lnterscience publication).  Kress, B. M.; and Schneider, H. Thallium-205 nuclear magnetic resonance study of thallium(I)  complexes with humic substances in non-aqueous solvents" Chemie der Erde; Zeitschrift fuer Chemische  Mineralogie, Petrographie, Bodenkunde, Geochemie und Meteoritenkunde. Jena, Germany., Vol. 38,  No. 3, p. 255-258 (incl. German sum.), illus., 1979.  Krouse, H. R.; and MeCready, R. G. L. Biogeochemical cycling of sulfur: in Biogeochemical cycling  of mineral-forming elements (Trudinger, P. A., editor; et al.), p. 401-425, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci.  Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.    146    Kumai, M. Electron microscope investigations of frozen and unfrozen bentonite:  CRREL (Cold  Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory) Report. Hanover, New Hampshire., 17 p., illus., 1979.  (Eep. No. 79-28) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., Unit,~.d States.  Lnnouroux, M. Importance et nature des processus d'entrainement des constituants mineraux dans  d~erents sols de regions temperees, mediterraneennes et tropicales [Importance and nature of the  p:ocesses of removal of mineral constituents in different soils of temperate, mediterranean and tropical  regions]:  in Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action  Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques  (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, lnstitut de  Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No.  53, p. 3-6, 1979.  Laryea, K. B.; Robin, M. J. L.; and Elrick, D.E. Solute transport during infiltration into reactive soils  [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 61, No. 17, p. 234,  "980. American Geophysical Union; 1980 spring annual meeting.  Leatherman, S. P.; Zaremba, R.; and Anders, F. Overwash processes and barrier dynamics; Nauset spit,  Cane Cod, Massachusetts [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 68-69, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th  annual meeting.  Leifer, L.; and Rabey, D. F. Soil survey of Los Angeles County, California, West San Fernando Valley  area: 107 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv. and West Los Ang. County Resour. Conserv. Dist., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Lelong, F.; and Souehier, B.  Methodes d'identification et de quantification des constituants  [Identification and quantitative evaluation of the mineral constituents]: in Constituants et proprietes du  sol (Bonneau, M.; et aL), p. 1-14, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Lelong, F.; and Souchier, B. Signification ecmogique du complexe d'aiteration; importance relative des  facteurs generaux et stationnels [Ecological significance of the weathering complex; bioclimatic and local  site factors]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 73-94, illus. (incl. tables),  Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Lepele, J. M.; and Lewis, D.T. Soil loss and sediment produced from an eroded map unit within the  Wyomore soil series [abstr.]: Nebraska Academy of Sciences and Affiliated Societies, Proceedings.  Lincoln., No. 89, p. 50-51, 1979.  Levashov, A.A. Rasprostraneniye merzlykh gruntov v ruslakh i poymakh rek i ikh vliyaniye na ruslovoy  protsess [The extent of frozen soils in channels and high-water beds of rivers and their influence on river  bed evolution]: Meteorologiya i Gidrologiya (USSR, Glavnoye Upravleniye Gidrometeorologicheskoy  Sluzhby). Moscow., No. 4, p. 88-92 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1979.  Le~,eque, A. Pedogenese sur le socle granito-gneissique du Togo; differenciation des sols ct remaniements  superficiels [Pedogenesis on the granitic-gneissic basement of Togo; differentiation of soils and superficial  alterations]: Travaux et Documents de 1' ORSTOM. Paris., No. 108, 224 p., illus., 1979.  Levy, G.; and Toutain, F. Aeration et phenomenes d'oxydo-reduction dans le sol [Aeration and redox  potential of seils]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et al.), p. 313-321, illus., Masson,  Paris, France, 1979.  Levy, R. Sources of soluble calcium and magnesium and their effects on sodium "lsorption ratios of  solutions in two soils of Israel: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 113-123, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Ligon, J. T.; Wilson, T. V.; Allen, J. F.; et al. Water distribution and movement in an unsaturated  Piedmont soil profile: Clemson University, Water Resources Research Institute, Report. Clemson, South  Carolina., No. 82, 103 p., illus. (incl. charts), i980. available from: Clemson Univ., Water Resour. Res.  Inst., Clemson, S.C., United States.  Liguori, V.; and Cusimano, G. II sottosuolo della citta di Palermo; caratterizzazione geologica del centro  storico [The subsoil of the city of Palermo; geological data of the historical center]:  Societa dei  Naturalisti in Napoli, Bollettino. Naples., Vol. 87, p. 289-317 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. plates,  sketch maps), 1979.    147    Lindsay, W. L. Chemical equilibria in soils: 412 p., illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York,  N.Y., United States, 1979.  I,insemier, L. H. Soil survey of Huron County, Michigan: 145 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Mich. Agric. Exp. St.).  Litehfield, C. D.; and Seyfried, P. L. (editors). Methodology for biomass determinations and microbial  activities in sediments: Jan. 30-31, 1978, United States. American Society for Testing and Materials,  Special Technical Publication. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., No. 673, 199 p., illus., 1979.  Lord, A. E., Jr.; Koerner, R. M.; and Reif, J. S. Determination of attenuation and penetration depth  of microwaves in soil: Geotechnical Testing Journal (American Society for Testing and Materials).  Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., Vol. 2, No. 2, p. 77-83, illus. (incl. plates), 1979.  Lucas, J.; Knick, Y.; and Gouleau, D. Aspects mineralogiques et chimiques des sediments et des sols  des mangroves du Senegal [Mineralogical and chemical aspects of sedments and soils of the Senegalese  mangroves]:  in Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action  Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques  (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, Institut de  Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No.  53, p. 53-56, tables, plate, 1979.  Lueas, J. N. The transpgrt of a radioactive salt through a semi-infinite column of porous medium; a  physical model: Water Resources Research (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 16,  No. 2, p. 387-390, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Mahaney, W. C.; and Rahey, B.D. Morphology, composition and age of a buried Paleosol, Front Range,  Colorado, U.S.A.:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 209-218, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Markley, M. L. Soil series of the Pine Barrens: in Pine Barrens; ecosystem and landscape (Forman,  R. T. T., editor), p. 81-93, illus. (incl. tables), Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Marks, G. P.; and Nelson, C. S. Sedimentology and evolution of Omaro Spit, Coromandel Peninsula:  New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research. Wellington., Vol. 13, No. 3, p. 347-37 l, illus.  (incl. tables, strat, cols., sketch map), 1979.  Marshall, K.C. Biogeochemistry of manganese minerals: in Biogeochemical cycling of mineral-forming  elements (Trudinger, P. A., editor; et al.), p. 253-286, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Marshall, T. J.; and Holmes, J. W. Soil physics: 345 p., illus. (incl. tables), Cambridge Univ. Press,  Cambridge, United Kingdom, 1979.  Martini, I. P.; Morrison, R. I. G.; Gloosehenko, W. A.; et al. Coastal studies in James Bay, Ontario:  Geoscience Canada (supersedes Geological Association of Canada, Proceedings). Toronto., Vol. 7, No.  l, p. 11-21, illus. (incl. sect., sketch maps), 1980.  Maruyama, A. Zum Vergleich der Boeden zwischen schwach- und starkgesellter Topographie auf dem  Kitakami-Gebirgsland [A comparison of soils covering weakly and strongly folded regions of the  Kitakami Mountains]: Tohoku University, Science Reports, Series 7, Geography. Sendai., Vol. 29, No.  2, p. 185-194, illus., 1979.  Matthews, J. A. Refutation of convergence in a vegetation succession: Naturwissenschaften. Berlin.,  Vol. 66, No. I, p. 47-49, illus., 1979.  MeFee, W.W. Sensitivity of soil regions to acid precipitation: 179 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps),  1980. (Rep. No. EPA-600/ 3-80-013) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  MeIntyre, D. S.; and Loveday, J. Sodicity, hydraulic conductivity and swelling of clay soils: Australia,  Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization, Division of Soils, Divisional Report.  [Adelaide]., No. 39, 9 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  MeLoda, N. A.; and Parkinson, R.J. Soil survey of Franklin County, Ohio: 188 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour. Div. Lands  Soil and Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).    148    Meriaux, S. Le sol et l'eau [Soil and water]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et ai.),  p. 266-310, illus. (incl. tables, plates), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Miller, G. H. Late Foxe glaciation of southern Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada: Geological Society of  America, Bulletin. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 91, No. 7, p. I 399-I 405, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps),  1980.  Miliot, G.; Bocquier, G.; Boulet, R.; et al. Geochimie de la surface, pedogenese, aplanissements et formes  du relief dans los pays mediterraneens et tropicaux [Geochemistry of the surface, pedogenesis,  denudation and relief forms in the mediterranean and tropical regions]: in Phenomenes de transport de  matiere dans I'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS; Action Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la  Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires  (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur, Institut de Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de  la Carte Geologique, Memoires). Strasbourg., No. 53, p. 39-43, 1979.  Moore, W.; and Miehel, J. Sources and behavior of natural radioactivity in fall line aquifers near  Leesville, South Carolina: Clemson University, Water Resources Research Institute, Report. Clemson,  South Carolina., No. 83, 73 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Moriwaki, H.; Hirobe, R.; Kumagai, T.; et al. Study of the accumulated volcanic ash layers of Usa  Volcano: National Research Center for Disaster Prevention, Report. Tokyo., No. 22, p. 83-92 (Japanese,  incl. English sum.), illus., 1979.  Morris, D. The benchland and flat lower prairie: in The geomorphic evolution of the Grand Prairie  (Corwin, R. V., editor), p. 10, sects., Baylor Univ., Moody, Tex., United States, 1979.  Moss, C. M.; Zarth, R. J.; and Matsch, C. L. Quaternary geology of the Duluth area: 54 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates, geol. sketch maps), Univ. Minn., Dep. Geol., Duluth, Minn., United States, 1979.  Moss, M. R.; and Dickinson, G. Evolution of the dune and machair grassland surface of South Uist,  Outer Hebrides, Scotland: Environmental Conservation. Elsevier Sequoia, Lausanne., Vol. 6, No. 4, p.  287-292, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1979.  Mueller, G. Cadmium in Schlaemmen; alte and neue Probleme [Cadmium in muds; old and new  problems]: Naturwissenschaften. Berlin., Vol. 66, No. 7, p. 359-360, table, 1979.  Mueller, K. H.  Der Bleigehalt innerstaedtischer Boeden als Mass fuer die Entsorgung yon  Kraftfahrzeug-Abgasen [The lead content of inner-city soils as an indicator of contamination by motor  vehicle exhausts]: Naturwissenschaften. Berlin., Vol. 66, No. 2, p. 108-109, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Mukherjee, S. K. The status of soil science in India: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi.,  Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 103-109, 1979.  Mukhopadhyay, P.; and Mukhopadhyay, A. K. Rethinking on the similarity in N:S and C:N:S ratios  of soils: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 189-190, table, 1979.  Murakami, Y.  Excess pore-water pressure and preconsolidation effect developed in normally  consolidated clays of some age: Soils and Foundations (The Japanese Society of Soil Mechanics and  Foundation Engineering). Tokyo., Vol. 19, No. 4, p. 17-29, illus., 1979.  Muromtsev, N. A.  O nekotorykh metodicheskikh voprosakh ispol'zovaniya tenziometrov v  issledovaniyakh vodnogo rezhima pochv [Problems using tensiometers for investigating soil water  regimes]:  Meteorologiya i Gidrologiya (USSR, Glavnoye Upravleniye Gidrometeorologicheskoy  Sluzl:by). Moscow., No. 10, p. lll-ll7, illus., 1979.  Naik, S. B. R.; Kumar, G. N.; and Raghava, M. S. V. The correlation refraction method as applied to  weathered zone studies in a granite terrain:  Geophysical Prospecting (European Association of  Exploration Geophysicists). The Hague., Vol. 28, No. 1, p. 18-29, illus., 1980.  Nakano, Y. Particular solutions to the problem of horizontal flow of water and air through porous media  near a water table: Advances in Water Resources. Southampton, England., Vol. 3, No. 1, p. 19-24, illus.,  1980.  Negi, A. S.; Sharma, R. C.; Sud, K. C.; oral. Forms of potassium and Q/I relationship in the acidic brown  hill soils of Simla: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 268-27 l, illus.,  tables, 1979.  Nicholson, J. C.; Burruss, T. R.; and Jones, D. L. Soil survey of Goochland County, Virginia: 137 p.,  illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Va. Polytech. Inst.).    149    Niedzieiski, A. Badania nad pecznieniem gruntow spoistych z Niziny Wielkopolskiej [Tests on the  swelling properties of cir.', soils from the Wielkopolska Lowlands]: Archiwum Hydrotechniki (Polska  Akademia Nauk, lnsty~:,', dudownictwa Wodnego). Warsaw., Vol. 26, No. 1, p. 117-128 (incl. Russian,  English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Nielson, W.; and Eriekson, A.d. Soil survey of Navajo Indian Reservation, San Juan County, Utah: 119  p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:63,360; colored soils map 1:506,880), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv. and U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur. Indian Aff., Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in  cooperation with Utah Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Nikiforova, Ye. M.; and Teplitskaya, T. A. Tekhnogennyye geokhimicheskiye anomalii tyazhelykh  uglevodorodov v pochvakh severo-zapada Russkoy ravniny [Technogenic geochemical anomalies of  heavy hydrocarbons in soils of the Northwest Russian Plain]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya  5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 5, p. 29-36 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Norris, R. M.; Keller, E. A.; and Meyer, G.L. Geomorphology of the Salton Basin, California: selected  observations: in Geological excursions in the Southern California area (Abbott, P. L., editor), p. 19-46,  illus. (incl. geol. sketch map), San Diego State Univ., Dep. Geol. Sci., San Diego, Calif., United States,  1979.  Noy-Meir, I.; and Seligman, N.G. Management of semi-arid ecosystems in Israel: m Management of  semi-arid ecosystems (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 113-160, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Obarska-Pempkowiak, H.  Samooczyszczanie sie filtrow gruntowych z substancji organicznej  pochodzacej ze sciekow [Natural decay of organic waste in soil filters]: Archiwum Hydrotechniki  (Polska Akademia Nauk, Instytut Budownictwa Wodnego). Warsaw., Vol. 26, No. 3, p. 405-418 (incl.  English, Russian sum.), illus., 1979.  O'Brien, R. M. G.; Romans, J. C. C.; and Robertson, L. Three soil profiles from Elephant Island, South  Shetland Islands: British Antarctic Survey, Bulletin. London., No. 47, p. 1-12. tables, plates, sketch map,  1979.  Oehler, J. H. Deposition and diagenesis of biogenic silica:  in Biogeochemical cycling of mineral-  forming elements (Trudinger, P. A., editor; et al.), p. 467-480, Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.  Netherlands, 1979.  Otter, A. J. Soil survey of Calumet and Manitowoc counties, Wisconsin: 176 p.. illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Res. Div. of Coll. Agric. Life Sci., Univ.  Wis.).  Outerbridge, W. F. Lithologic control of landslides in part of the southern Appalachian Plateau [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 76, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th annual meeting.  Overpeek, J. T.; and Potter, D.B. A palynological and geological investigation of a northern New York  State peat bog; some insights into the late- and post-glacial history of the Adirondack Mountains [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 76-77,  1980.  The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th annual meeting.  Pahlavanpour, B.; Pullen, J. H.; and Thompson, M. Determination of trace concentrations of selenium  in soils and sediments by the introduction of hydrogen selenide into an inductively coupled plasma source  for emission spectrometry: Analyst (Chemical Society). London., Vol. 105, No. 1248, p. 274-278, tables,  1980.  Pal, B.; and Tripathi, B.R. Physicochemical characteristics of soils of semi-desert tract of Uttar Pradesh  as affected by irrigation water quality: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No.  3, p. 246-251, illus., tables, 1979.  Paleehek, L. A. The trace elements Cr, Mn, B, and Ti in the water of the middle reaches of the Ob River  and its tributaries:  Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy  Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 60-64, illus.  (incl. table), 1979.  Pathak, A. N.; Tiwari, K. N.; and Prasad, D. D. An appraisal of available and potentially available iron  status of alluvial soils of Uttar Pradesh: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27,  No. 2, p. 191-193, table, 1979.    150    Paulk, H. L. Soil survey of Candler, Evans, and Tattnall counties, Georgia: 96 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Ga., Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Peehmann, E.; and Voultsidis, V. Kuenstliche Verwitterung yon Uran-Nickel-Erz yon Key Lake, Sask.,  Canada; ein Beitrag der Uranmineralogie zum Umweltschutz [Simulation of weathering processes of  uranium-nickel ore from Key Lake, Saskatchewan, Canada; a contribution of uranium mineralogy to  environmental protection]: Deutsche Geologische Gesellschaft, Zeitschrift. Hanover., Vol. 130, No. 2,  p. 513-526 (incl. English, French sum.), plates, 1979.  Peesi, M.; and Donath, E. Thermal investigation of the loesses and fossil soils of Paks: in Guide-book  for conference and field-wo~'kshop on the stratigraphy of loess and alluvial deposits (Pecsi, M., editor),  p. 125-135, illus. (incl. strat, col.), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest, Hungary, 1979.  Peesi, M.; and Donath, E. Thermal analysis of fossil red soils from the Dunakomlod 1977/1 borehole:  in Guide-book for conference and field-workshop on the stratigraphy of loess and alluvial deposits (Pecsi,  M., editor), p. 181-186, illus. (incl. strat, col.), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest, Hungary, 1979.  Peesi, M.; Donath, E.; Pevzner, M. A.; et al. A complex evaluation of Dunafoldvar loesses and fossil  soils; bio- and lithostratigraphical, paleopedological, thermal and paleomagnetic investigation: in Guide-  book for conference and field-workshop on the stratigraphy of loess and alluvial deposits (Pecsi, M.,  editor), p. 203-236, illus. (incl. strat, col.), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest, Hungary, 1979.  Peesi, M.; Pevzner, M. A.; and Szebenyi, E. Upper Pleistocene litho- and chronostratigraphical type  profile from the loess exposures at Mende: in Guide-book for conference and field-workshop on the  stratigraphy of loess and alluvial deposits (Pecsi, M., editor), p. 11-38, illus. (incl. strat, col., tables, sketch  maps), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest, Hungary, 1979.  Pecsi, M.; Seheuer, G.; Szebenyi, E.; et aL Lithological, pedological analysis of the Dunakomlod 1977 / 1  borehole: in Guide-book for confc:'ence and field-workshop on the stratigraphy of loess and alluvial  deposits (Pecsi, M., editor), p. 167-180, illus. (incl. table, strat, col.), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest,  Hungary, 1979.  Pedersen, B.; Wiilems, M.; and Joergensen, S.S. Determination of copper, lead, cadmium, nickel and  cobalt in EDTA extracts of soil by solvent extraction and graphite furnace atomic-absorption  spectrophotometry: Analyst (Chemical Society). London., Vol. 105, No. 1247, p. 119-124, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Pedro, G. Les mineraux argileux [Clay minerals]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.;  et al.), p. 38-56, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Pedro, G. Les conditions de formation des constituants secondaires [Conditions of formation of  secondary minerals]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.; et aL), p. 58-71, illus. (incl.  tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Peru, Ofieina Naeionai de Evaluaeion de Reeursos Naturales. Guide to cartographic and natural  resources information of Peru: 99 p., illus., index maps 1:10,000,000, Inst. Panam. Geogr. Hist., Mexico  City, Mexico, 1979.  Petrov, M. P. Land-use of semi-deserts in the U.S.S.R.:  in Management of semi-arid ecosystems  (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 301-327, illus. (incl, tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Ce., Amsterdam,  Netherlands, 1979.  Petrov, M. P. Land-use of semi-deserts in Central Asia:  in Management of semi-arid ecosystems  (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 329-349, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Poonia, S. R,; and Pal, R. Sodification of soil in relation to sodium activity ratios and Ca: Mg in soil  solutions: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 116-122, illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Pozdnyakov, A. I.; and Khan, K. Yu. DC electric probing and profile sequencing in soil studies: Moscow  University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya  Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 46-52, illus., 1979.  Pringle, F.B. Soil survey of Potter County, Texas: 139 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000;  colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States,  1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).    151    Prusinkiewicz, Z. A mathematical model of energy budgets of forest humus of the Mull, Moder and  Mor types in Poland: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 79-93, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Pullan, R. A. Termite hills in Africa; their characteristics and evolution: Catena; An Interdisciplinary  Journal of Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 6, No. 3-4, p.  267-291, illus.. 1979.  Redmond, C. E.; and Brown, D. L. Soil survey of Ashland County, Ohio: 179 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Div. Lands  Soil, and Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).  Rekshinskaya, L. G.; and Feolilova, A.P. Alterations of Carborfiferous paleosoils in the Donets Basin:  Lithvlogy and Mineral Resources (English translation of Litologiya i Poleznyye Iskopayemyye).  Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 14, No. 3, p. 307-320, illus. (incl. sects., table, plates, sketch maps),  1979 [1980].  Remmelzwaal, A. Translocation and transformation of clay in Alols in early, middle and late  Pleistocene coastal sands of southern Italy: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-  Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Voi. 6, No. 3-4, p. 379-398, illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1979.  Red,nails, K.; Carnell, R.; and Tee, V. A descriptive model of the relationship between rainfall and soil  water table: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 47, No. 1-2, p. 103-114,  illus., 1980.  Reynolds, C.A. Soil survey of Middlesex County, Connecticut: 155 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Conn. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Storrs Agric. Exp. Stn.j.  Rhaades, J. D. Salinity management and monitoring: in Proceedings of the Twelfth biennial conference  on ground water (Anonymous), California, University, Water Resources Center, Report. Davis., No. 45,  p. 73-87, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Richard, P. Contribution a l'histoire postglaciaire de la vegetation au nord-est de la Jamesie [The post-  glacial history of the vegetation northeast of the James Bay area, New Quebec]: Geographic Physique  et Quaternaire. Montreal., Vol. 33, No. l, p. 93-115 (incl. English, German sum.), 1979.  Ritchie, J. C.; and Hawks, P. H. Natural gamma radioactivity in North Mississippi sods: Mississippi  Academy of Sciences, Journal., Vol. 24, p. 92-103, illus. (incl. sketch map, table), 1979.  Robb, L.J. The distribution of granitophile elements in Archaean granites of the eastern Transvaal, and  their bearing on geomorphological and geological features of the area: Geological Society of South  Africa, Transactions. Johannesburg., Vol. 82, Part 1, p. 169-178, illus. (incl. table, geol. sketch maps),  1979.  Robert, M.; and Trocine, S. Le potassium [Potassium]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau,  M.; et al.), p. 379-385, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.  Robinson, G. D., Jr. Possible quartz synthesis during weathering of quartz-free mafic rock, Jasper  County, Georgia: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, Tulsa, Oklahoma., Vol. 50, No. 1, p. 193-203, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Rolling, R.E. Soil survey of Cottonwood County, Minnesota: 142 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch  maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Minn. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Rubin, R. M.; Price, J.; and Wells, M. B. The effects of vegetation on the energy and angular  distribution of uranium daughter gamma rays at an altitude of 121.9 meters: 132 p., illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1979. (Rep. No. GJBX-55(80)) (Rep. No. RRA-T7906) available from: U. S. Dep. Energy,  Grand Junction Off., Grand Junction, Colo., United States.  Russell, R. C.; and Lockridge, L. D. Soil survey of Marion County, Iowa: 183 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. Stn.,  Coop. Ext. Serv., Iowa State Univ., and Dep. Soil Conserv., State Iowa).    152    Ryazanov, P. N. Humus-composition characteristics of the soils and silt deposits of the Protva River  valley: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy Universitet, Vestr, ik,  Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 3a, No. 1, p. 65-69, illus. (incl. table), 197'.."  Seharpenseel, H.W. Soil fraction dating: in Radiocarbon dating (Berger, R., editor; et al.), Proceedings  of the International Conference [on] Radiocarbon Dating., No. 9, p. 277-283, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Sehiebout, J. A. An overview of the terrestrial early Tertiary of southern North America; fossil sites  and paleopedology: Tulane Studies in Geology and Paleontology (Tulane University). New Orleans,  Louisiana., Vol. 15, No. 1-4, p. 75-94, illus., 1979.  Sehroeder, S. A.; Moldenhauer, W. C.; and Mannering, J. V. Studies of tillage-induced effects on  hydraulic conductivitY:  Purdue University, Water Resources Research Center, Technical Report.  Lafayette, Indiana., No. 117, 79 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Sehwaar, J. Spaet- und postglaziale Pflanzengesellschaften im Duemmer-Gebiet [Late- and postglacial  plant c~,mmunities in the Duemmer area]: Naturwissenschaftlicher Verein zu Bremen, Abhandlungen.  Bremen., Vol. 39, p. 129-152 (incl. English sum.), tables, sketch map, sects., pollen diagrams, 1979.  SemmeL A.; and Rohdenburg, H. Untersuchungen zur Boden- und Reliefentwicklung in Sud-Brasilien  [Smdks of soil and relief development in southern Brazil]: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of  Gcomorpho~ogy-Hydroiogy Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 6, No. 2, p. 203-217 (incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), !979.  Sener, C.  An endochronic nonlinear inelastic constitutive law for cohesionless soils subjected to  dynamic loading:  332 p., Doctoral, 1979, Northwestern Univ., Evanston, Ill. available from: Univ.  Microtilms.  Sen'kovskaya, N. F.; and Sushchevskiy, A. G.  Osobennosti formirovaniya subekvatorial'nykh  landshaftov Yuzhnoy Indii [Formational peculiarities of the subequatorial landscapes of South India]:  Vestni.~ Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 1, p. 56-64 (incl. English sum.),  sketch map, 1980.  Sharpley, A. N.; and Syers, J. K. Phosphorus inputs into a stream draining an agricultural watershed;  II, Amounts contributed and relative significance of runoff types: Water, Air, and Soil Pollution. D.  Reidel Publ. Co., Dordrecht., Vol. 11, No. 4, p. 417-427, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Sheppard, J. C.; All, S.  and Mehringer, P. J., Jr. Radiocarbon dating ot organic components of  sediments and peats: in Radiocarbon dating (Berger, R., editor; et al.), Proceedings of the International  Conference [on] Radiocarbon Dating., No. 9, p. 284-305, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Shtykov, V. I. Vodopronitsayemost' merzlykh nesvyaznykh gruntov i analiz dinamiki yeye izmeneniya  v period snegotayaniya i ottaivaniya [The permeability of frozen unconsolidated soils and an analysis of  change during snowmelt and ~?~aw periods]: Meteorologiya i Gidrologiya (USSR, Glavnoye Upravleniye  Gidrormteorologicheskoy S',uzhby). Moscow., No. 12, p. 91-98 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Silic, ;r. Applications of magnetometric resistivity (MMR) and magnetic induced-polarization (MIP)  methods in deeply weathered terrains [abstr.]:  Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Annual  International Meeting, Abstracts., No. 49, p. 72, 1979.  Silverraan, M.P. Biological and organic chemical decomposition of silicates: in Biogeochemical cycling  of mineral-forming elements (Trudinger, P. A, editor; et al.), p. 445-461, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci.  Publ. (7o., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Simmens, G.T. Soil survey ot Johnson County, Missouri: 116 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Mo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Singh, i) - Mannikar, N. D.; and Srivas, N. C. Efficiency of indigenous phosphate rocks as influenced  by pyrite; lal:oratory studies: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 334-  337, illus., table, 1979.  Singh, J. S.; and Joshi, M.C. Ecology of the semi-arid regions of India with emphasis on land-use: in  Manageme,at of semi-arid ecosystems (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 243-275, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), Elsexier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Smirnov, Yu. A.; and Chernova, G. N. Use of magnetic parameters for diagnosis of certain soils in  Kaliningrad region:  Moscow Uni, ersity Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy  Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 39-45, illus.  (incl. table), 1979.    153    Smoak, W. G.; and Stodolski, M. #. Polymer impregnation and collection of undisturbed soil and rock  samples: 41 p., plates, tables, 1979. (Rep. No. REC-ERC-79-11) available from: U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur.  Reclam., Denver, Colo., United States.  Smolikova, L.; and Zeman, A. Fossilboeden im Profil yon Sedlesovice und ihre Beziehung zu den  Flussablagerungen [Fossil soils in the section near Sedlesovice and their relationship to fluvial  accumulations]: Vestnik Ustredniho Ustavu Geologickeho. Prague., Vol. 54, No. 4, p. 215-224 (incl.  English, Czech sum.), illus. (incl. sects.), 1979.  Soller, D. R.  An identification and description of the Sidney interstadial weathering profile in  southwestern Ohio [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 84, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th annual  meeting.  Sriram, K.; and Prasad, K.N. Observations on the geomorphology of Goa: Geological Society of India,  Journal. Bangalore., Vol. 20, No. 12, p. 608-614, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Stanford, G. (reviewer); Greenland, D. J. (editor); and Hayes, M. H. B. (editor). The chemistry of soil  constituents: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam.,  Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 223, 1980.  Stephens, D. B. Analysis of constant head borehole infiltration tests in the vadose zone: 3~'4 p.,  Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Arizona, Tucson, Ariz. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Stepkowska, E.T. Typical cohesive soils in Poland: Archiwum Hyd~'otechniki (Polska Akademia Nauk,  Instytut Budownictwa Wodnego). Warsaw., Vol. 26, No. 3, p. 495-503 (incl. Polish, Russian sum.), illus.  (incl. tables), 1979.  Stepkowska, E.T. Wplyw wibracji na wlasciwosci odpadow pofiotacyjnych w zaleznosci od uziarnienia  [The effect of vibrations on properties of tailings as related to grain size]: Archiwum Hydrotechniki  (Polska Akademia Nauk, Instytut Budownictwa Wodnego). Warsaw., Vol. 26, No. 1, p. 139-152 (incl.  English, Russian sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Stevenson, F. J. (reviewer); Sehnitzer, M. (editor); and Khan, S. U. (editor). Soil organic matter:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No.  2, p. 157-158, 1980.  Stoop, W. A.  I,:m adsorption mechanisms in oxidic soils; implications for point of zero charge  determinations:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 4, p. 303-314, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Sur, H. S.; Silkgh, C.; and Singh, N.T. Density and porosity relationships of aggregates of Alluvial soils:  Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 3, p. 236-241, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Swanson, F.J. Comments on geomorphology in ecosystem studies: in A field trip to observe natural  and management-related erosion in Franciscan terrane of northern California (Anonymous), p. 1-8, illus.  (incl. tables), Geol. Soc. Am., San Jose, Calif., United States, 1979.  Szabo, J. P. Two pollen diagrams from Quaternary deposits in East-central Iowa, U.S.A.: Canadian  Journal of Earth Sciences (National Research Council of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 17, No. 4, p. 453-458  (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. charts, sketch map), 1980.  Szpila, K.; and Stepisiewiez, M. Phosphate minerals in basaltic weathering products from Turoszow  (Lower Silesia): Archiwum Mineralogiczne (Polska Akademia Nauk, Komitet Nauk Geologicznych).  Warsaw., Vol. 35, No. 2, p. 5-15, illus., 1979.  Taylor, G. H. Biogeochemistry of uranium minerals: in Biogeochemical cycling of mineral-forming  elements (Trudinger, P. A., editor; et al.), p. 485-511, illus. (incl. tables), Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Tedrow, J. C.F. Development of Pine Barrens soils: in Pine Barrens; ecosystem and landscape (Forman,  R. T. T., editor), p. 61-79, illus., Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Templ~ton, G. D., III; and Chasteen, N. D. Vanadium-fulvic acid chemistry; conformational and  binding studies by electron spin probe techniques:  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The  Geochemical Society, Journal). Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 5, p. 741-752, illus., 1980.  Thomassin, J. H.; Touray, C.; and Triehet, J. Etude des mecanismes d'alteration d'une obsidienne; les  donnees de l'analyse de surface (spectrometrie de photoelectrons et microscopie electronique a balayage)    154    [Study of obsidian alteration mechanisms; results of surface analysis; photoelectron spectrometry and  scanning electron microscopy]: in Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-  CNRS; Action Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats  scientifiques (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires (Strasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur,  Institut de Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Memoires).  Strasbourg., No. 53, p. 23-27, illus., 1979.  Timofeev, B.V. Soil-genesis characteristics in the semiarid zone of North Africa: Moscow University  Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye).  Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. l, p. 9-16, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Tolehei'nikov, Yu. S.; and Komyakov, A. K.  Fotometricheskiye metody opredeleniya opticheski  aktivnykh sloyev rykhlykh porod i pochv [Photometrical methods of determining the optical active layers  of loose rock and soils]: Vsesoyuznoye Geograficheskoye Obshchestvo, Izvestiya. Leningrad., Vol. l 12,  No. l, p. 64-68, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Torrent, J.; Sehwertmann, U.; and Sehulze, D. G. Iron oxide mineralogy of some soils of two river  terrace sequences in Spain: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co.,  Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 191-208, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Troly, G.; Esterle, M.; Pelletier, B. G.; et al. Nickel deposits in New Caledonia; some factors influencing  their formation: in International laterite symposium (Evans, D. J. I., editor; et al.), p. 85-117, illus. (incl.  tables, sects., geol. sketch map), Am. Inst. Min., Metall., and Pet. Eng., Sac. Min. Eng., New York, N.Y.,  United States, 1979.  Trubetskoi, O. A.  Electrokinetic properties of a meadow-chernozemic solonetz-solonchak and a  krasnozem: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy Unive, sitet,  Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 30-34, illus. (incl. ta~les),  1979.  Tsatskin,  A.  I.   Opyt  izucheniya  drevnikh  struktur  pochvennogo  pskrova  na  primere  verkhnepleystotsenovykh pochv yugo-zapada Russkoy rabniny [Ancient structures in soil cover; a case  study of upper Pleistocene soils of the southwestern Russian Plain]: Akademiya Nauk SSSR, lzvestiya,  Seriya Geograficheskaya. Moscow., No. 6. p. 89-97, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Tsuzuki, Y.; and Suzuki, K. Experimental study of the alteration process of labradorite in acid  hydrothermal solutions: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal).  Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 5, p. 673-684, illus., 1980.  Tumel', N. V.; and Snopkov, A. Ye. Sezotmoye promerzaniye gn-ltov nechernozemnoy zany RSFSR  i yego kartografirovaniye [Seasona! freezing of soils of the Nonchernozem Zone of European Russia and  its mapping]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 5, p. 36-41 (incl.  English sum.), table, 1979.  Van Devender, T. R.; and Riskind, D.H. Late Pleistocene and early Holocene plant remains from Hueco  Tanks State Historical Park; the deve,opment of a refugium: Southwestern Naturalist. Austin, Texas.,  Vol. 24, No. 1, p. 127-140, table, 1979.  Van Houten, F. B. Ancient soils and ancient climates [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union,  Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 61, No. 17, p. 250, 1980. American Geophysical Union, 1980 spring  annual meeting.  Vaneura, V. (reviewer); Dommergues, Y. R. (editor); and Krupa, S. V. (editor). Interactions between  non-pathogenic soil microorganisms and 131ants: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science.  Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 3, p. 219-220, 1980.  Vaudour, J. Les environs nard etest de Madrid; presentation d'une carte morphopedologique au  1 / 100.000 en couleurs [The region to the north and east of Madrid; presentation of a colored morpho-  pedologic map 1:100,000]:  in Aspects physiques de Ia Peninsule Iberique (Vaudour, J., compiler),  Mediterranee. Paris., Vol. 36, No. 3, p. 45-56 (incl. Spanish, English sum.), plat~, strat, cols., sect., col.  geol. map 1:100,000, 1979.  Vedy, J. C.; and Bruekert, S. Les solutions du sol; composition et signification pedogenetique [Soil  solutions; composition and p~dological signification]: in Constituants et proprietes du sol (Bonneau, M.;  et al.), p. 161-181, illus. (incl. tables), Masson, Paris, France, 1979.    155    Velde, B.; Proust, D.; and Meunier, A. Chlorite compositions during sedimentation, diagenesis and low  grade metamorphism:  in Phenomenes de transport de matiere dans l'ecorce terrestre, ATP-CNRS;  Action Thematique Programmee du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; resultats scientifiques  (Anonymous), Sciences Geologiques, Memoires ($trasbourg, Universite Louis Pasteur~ Institut de  Geologie)(continuation of Alsace-Lorraine, Service de la Carte Geologique, Mcmoires). Strasbourg., No.  53, p. 71-73 (incl. French sum.), illus., 1979.  Verheye, W. Le profil d'aiteration pcdogeologique sur granodiorites en Cote d'Ivoire centrale [Pedo-  geological weathering profile on granodiorites in the central Ivory Coast]: Revue de Geomorphologie  Dynamique. Paris., Vol. 28, No. 2, p. 49-60 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Veselov, I.A. Analiz svyazi reryefa vodorazdel'nykh prostranstv Sredney Sibiri s litologiyey [Analysis  of the relation of the relief of the watershed areas of central Siberia to their lithology]:  Vestnik  Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 5, Geografiya. Moscow., No. 4, p. 81-84 (incl. English sum.), 1979.  Vishnoi, R. K.; and Tripathi, R.P. Influence of intial water content and temperature gradients on water  transport in soil: Indian Society of Soil Science, Journal. New Delhi., Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 110-115, illus.,  1979.  Voronin, A. D. Methodological principles and significance of the concept of a hierarchy of structural-  organization levels in soil: Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy  Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Allerton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 1-8, 1979.  Wagner, M. Molluscan fauna of the Mende loess profile:  in Guide-book for conference and field-  workshop on the stratigraphy of loess and alluvial deposits (Pecsi, M., editor), p. 47-53, illus. (incl. strat.  col.), Hung. Acad. Sci., Budapest, Hungary, 1979.  Walden, M.; and Thompson, R. C. Geochemistry of selected lakes in New York State with simple  morphometry [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 61,  No. 17, p. 227, 1980. American Geophysical Union; 1980 spring annual meeting.  Waines, R. H.  Late Wisconsinan-Recent geology of the lower Rondout Valley, Ulster County,  southeastern New York: in Joint annual meeting: of New York State Geological Association, 51 st annual  meeting and New England intercollegiate geological conference, 71st annual meeting; guidebook  (Friedman, G. M., editor), New York State Geological Association, Annual Meeting, Field Trip  Guidebook., No. 5J, p. 447-457, table, geol. sketch map, 1979.  Walter, H. Vegetation of the Earth and ecological systems of the geo-biosphere, 2nd edition: 274 p.,  illus. (incl. sects., tables, plates, geol. sketch maps), Springer-Verlag, New York, N.Y., United States,  1979.  Ward, T. E.; and Frea, J. I. Estimation of microbial activities i:~ lake sediments by measurement of  sediment gas evolution:  in Methodology for biomass determinations and microbial activities in  sediments (Litchfield, C. D., editor; et al.), American Society for Testing and Materials, Special Technical  Publication. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., No. 673, p. 156-166, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Werner, G. Bodengesellschaften im Zentralen Hochland von Mexico Ergebnisse einer Bodenkartierung  des Hochbeckens yon Puebla-Tlaxcala und seiner Umgebung [Soil groups in the central Mexican Meseta  soil survey of the Puebla-Tlaxcala Basin and its environs]: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of  Geomorphology-Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 6, No. 3-4, p. 331-347  (incl. English, Spanish sum.), illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1979.  West, R. G. The pre-glacial Pleistocene of the Norfolk and Suffolk coasts: 203 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates, sects., sketch maps), Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, Eng., United Kingdom, 1980.  White, F. C.; Halrston, J. E.; Musser, W. N.; et al. Environmental and economic impact of agricultural  land use conversion; an evaluation methodology: 117 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980. (Rep.  No. EPA-600/5-80-002) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Wiekens, G. E.; and White, L.P. Land-use in the southern margins of the Sahara: in Management of  semi-arid ecosystems (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 205-242, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Elsevier  Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Williams, J. C.; and Crump, J.O. Soil survey of Donley County, Texas: 127 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).    156    Wilson, A. D.; and Graetz, R. D. Management of the semi-arid and arid rangeland,; of Australia: in  Management of semi-arid ecosystems (Walker, B. H., editor), Vol. 7, p. 83-111, illus. (incl. table, sketch  maps), t'lsevicr Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1979.  Wolfe, J. A.; and Poore, R. Z. Tertiary marine and nonmarine climatic trends [abstr.]: Eos (American  Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 61, No. 17, p. 250, 1980.  American  Geophysical Union, 1980 spring annual meeting.  Yaalon, D. H.'(reviewer); and Mahaney, W. C. (editor). Quaternary soils: Geoderma, an International  Journal of Soft Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 158-160, 1980.  Yair, A.; and de Pioey, ,I. Field observations and laboratory experiments concerning the creep process  of rock blocks in an arid environment: Catena; An Interdisciplinary Journal of Geomorphology-  Hydrology-Pedology. Lenz-Verlag, Giessen, Germany., Vol. 6, No. 3-4, p. 245-258, illus., 1979.  Young, A. Mapping the world's soils: New Scientist. London., Vol. 81, No. 1139, p. 252-254, illus. (incl.  sketch maps), 1979.  Zaiderman, F. R.; and Tagunova, R.A. Elements of the temperature regime of undrained and drained  soddy-podzolic soils:  Moscow University Soil Science Bulletin ( English translation of Moskovskiy  Universitet, Vestnik, Seriya Pochvovedeniye). Alierton Press, New York., Vol. 34, No. 1, p. 17-29, illus.  (incl. tables), 1979.  Zakosek, H.; and Asthalter, K. Bad Schwa!bach: in the collection Erlaeuterungen zur Bodenkarte von  Hessen, 1:25 000, No. 5814, 35 p., illus. (incl. colored soils map 1:25,000), Hess. Landesamt  Bodenforsch., Wiesbaden, Germany, Federal Republic of, 1979.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 