 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 225--239                                                  225  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    WEATHERING PRODUCTS IN VITRANDEPT PROFILES UNDER PINE  AND MANUKA, NEW ZEALAND    P.D. McINTOSH  Geology Department, Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington (New Zealand) *  (Received August 7, 1979; accepted January 4, 1980)    ABSTRACT    McIntosh, P.D., 1980. Weathering products in Vitrandept profiles under pine and manuka,  New Zealand, Geoderma, 24: 225--239.    Weathering products of Vitrandept profiles on the Kaingaroa plateau, central North  Island, New Zealand, were investigated by analysis of oxalate extracts and by chemical  and mineralogical analysis of clays of selected soil horizons. Comparisons were made be-  tween profiles under a Pinus radiata (D. Don) stand and profiles under an adjacent area of  manuka native scrub, Leptospermum scoparium (Myrtaceae).  Clay fractions (&lt; 2 ,m) of A, horizon under pine had significantly higher SiO2/A1203  mole-ratios (mean SiO2/A1203 = 12.2) than A. horizon under manuka (mean SiO2/A1203 =  7.1). No effect of vegetation on clay fractions of B horizon was evident, these clays hav-  ing much lower SiO2/Al203 mole-ratio (1.5). Oxalate-extractable A1, Fe and Si values of  &lt; 8-ram fractions of A, B and C horizons showed no differences attributable to present  vegetative cover.  SiO~/AI203 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts increased with increasing depth, and paleo-  sols at &gt; 2 m depth under pine had significantly higher SiO2/A1203 mole-ratios in oxalate  extracts (mean SiO2/A1203 = 2.0) than paleosols under manuka (mean SiO2/A1203 = 1.6).  That soil horizons at &gt; 2 m depth are in the zone of resilication is indicated by: (1) the  greater SiO2/A1203 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts of paleosols than surface horizons; (2)  lysimeter leachate composition; and (3) the presence of authigenic halloysite at &gt; 2 m  depth in soil profiles.    INTRODUCTION    Leaching and resilication strongly influence the nature of the clay-sized  weathering products of tephra in temperate environments (Saigusa et al.,  1978). Near the surface of tephra deposits, weathering products are charac-  teristically aUophane and imogolite (Kanno et al., 1968; Yoshinaga and Yama-  guchi, 1970). Resilication processes are favoured by burial ~f tephra to depths  &gt; 2.5 m (Kurahayashi and Tsuchiya, 1961; Mejia et al., 1968; Calhoun et al.,  1972; Saigusa et al., 1978), wet conditions at depth (Dudas and Harward,  1975) and organic matter in the horizon concerned (Kurahayashi and Tsuchi-    *Present address: Invermay Agricultural Research Centre, Mosgiel, New Zealand.    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$ 02.25 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    226    ya, 1961). The weathering product found in the zone of resilication by the  above authors was characteristically halloysite.  Taylor (1933) was one of the first workers in New Zealand to relate tephra  weathering to plant cover; he found that the clay fraction of topsoil (0--7.5  cm) under forest with acid litter had a higher SIO2/A1203 mole ratio (3.6)  than the clay fraction of topsoil under scrub and fern (SIO2/A1203 = 1.3) and  attributed the higher ratio under the former vegetation to the degradation of  amorphous colloids and leaching of AI. Ward (1967), in an investigation of  buried tephras in New Zealand, related the presence of halloysite root pseudo-  morphs to previous presence of kauri (Agathis australis) trees. Other research  on non-tephric parent materials has shown that iron and aluminium tend to  be mobilised near trees with acid litter (Gersper and Holowaychuk, 1970;  Campbell, 1975). Local effects of podzolising species are well illustrated by  the formation of "egg-cup podzols" in New Zealand podocarp forest (Vuce-  tich and Wells, 1978).  This paper describes a study aimed at determining the properties of clay  fractions and oxalate-extractable amorphous components of selected horizons  of soil derived from tephra on the Kaingaroa plateau, central North Island,  New Zealand, and determining the effect, if any, of the introduced conifer  Pinus radiata (D. Don) on such weathering products. The effects of radiata  pine on soil acidity, exchangeable cations, and phosphorus fractions of softs  in the same study area have been considered by McIntosh (1980), and the  properties of the halloysite found in the tephra profiles are detailed by McIn-  tosh (1979).    CHARACTERISTICS OF STUDY AREA    The study area is located in Compartment 336, Kaingaroa Forest, New  Zealand (Fig. 1) at an elevation of 520 m. Mean annual rainfall at the study  area is approximately 1200 mm (Knight, 1974). The vegetation of the study  area consists of a 45-year old stand of radiata pine with a discontinuous un-  derstorey of native shrubs and herbs. Within the pine stand is a small area, ca.  0.2 ha, of manuka (Leptospermum scoparium).  Before planting of exotic conifers in the 1930's the vegetation of the Kain-  garoa plateau consisted of native scrub species dominated by manuka (Ure,  1950). The scrub cover was probably burned intermittently to provide rough  grazing and replaced podocarp forest destroyed by Maori fires in the mid-  nineteenth century (Ure, 1950; Nicholls, 1963; Vucetich and Pullar, 1963).  Further details of climate and vegetation are given by McIntosh (1980).  Rhyolitic deposits from Taupo Volcanic Centre dominate the tephras of  the study area (Vucetich and Pullar, 1973). The Taupo Pumice Formation was  erupted 1800 years B.P. and comprises thin basal lapilli and ash layers (Hate-  pe Lapilli) and Rotongaio Ash overlain by coarse pumice gravel (Taupo Lapilli)  in turn overlain by Upper Taupo Pumice members (Fig. 2). Below the Taupo  Pumice Formation is a sequence of tephras and associated paleosols of which the    227    tephra soil  stratigraphy horizons    Au L.  ,   ~                                       WAIRAPUKAO    ?  ,k,,o~,,;,  .  2..    Om    mat1  A12  Upper  Taupo  Pumice        Members    cl  c2    Taupo          Dr~  Lapilii    Rotongaio  Ash~  --,~AB--  Maim  Tephra  Whakaipo    =.As  Tephra      2.c  Waimihia     3.AB  Formation  3uc    Fig. 1. Location of study area, North Island, New Zealand, Cpt 336 = Compartment 336,  Kaingaroa Forest.    Fig. 2. Tephra stratigraphy and soils in the study area. Tephra stratigraphy from Vucetich  and Pullar (1973).    following were encountered in the present study: Mapara Tephra (2100 years  B.P.), Whakaipo Tephra (2700 years B.P.) and the Waimihia Formation  (3400 years B.P.). Paleosols developed in these tephras, are referred to in this  paper as the Mapara, Whakaipo and Waimihia paleosols, respectively. Podo-  carp forest is likely to have grown on these soils before their burial by later  tephras (McIntosh, 1980).  The softs in the study area were mapped in the Kaingaroa soil set by New  Zealand Soil Bureau (1954), the typifying type being Kaingaroa silty sand, a  very strongly leached yellow-brown pumice soil (New Zealand Soil Bureau,  1968), a Typic Vitrandept, cindery and mesic, in the USDA classification  (Soil Survey Staff, 1975).    228    METHODS    Field sampling    Five pits were dug under the pine stand in Compartment 336, Kaingaroa  Forest (Fig. 1 ) and five pits were also dug in the area of manuka within this  compartment. Pits under pine were located 2--4 m from the nearest living  pine tree in areas with no understorey.  Pits under manuka were located 0.5--2 m from living manuka plants. A de-  scription of one soil profile under each stand is given in the Appendix, and  mean thicknesses of horizons sampled are shown in Fig. 2.  Profiles under pine differed morphologically from those under manuka in  having "bleached" soil volumes of light colour and friable to loose consistence  (Thornton et al., 1956; Vucetich et al., 1960) in and between A and B hori-  zons and in the Rotongaio Ash and paleosols. Such soil volumes contained  visible fungal mycelia and were associated with fine bifurcating pine roots si-  milar to those described by Harley (1969) as mycorrhizal. Pine roots were  found in all horizons under the pine stand, but under manuka roots were con-  fined to Upper Taupo Pumice members.  Soil horizons shown by Knight and Will (1970) to contain nutrients avail-  able to radiata pine, and those which were observed to be penetrated by many  fine pine roots, were sampled for analysis as it was thought that these hori-  zons might be most sensitive to changes brought about by the conifer stand.  Soil horizons developed within the Upper Taupo Pumice members and paleo-  sols were therefore sampled. In addition, the fine-textured Rotongaio Ash  was sampled to investigate the effect of vegetation on a tephra that has not  been exposed to surficial weathering. Clays were extracted from the A ll and  B horizons of soils forming the present ground surface, from a buried tephra  (the Rotongalo Ash) and from a paleosol (the Mapara paleosol). Roots and  lapilli :&gt; 8 mm were removed by hand picking and gentle sieving.    Separation of clays from AI~ and B horizons    The &lt; 63-ttm fraction of each sample was separated from finer material by  washing each sample through a nylon mesh with distilled water. The silt and  clay fraction was dispersed by successive ultrasonic vibration of I min dura-  tion (total 6 min) at 150 Watts using a Branson ultrasonic probe without pre-  vious treatment of samples with hydrogen peroxide. The silt fractions were  separated by centrifuging; clay fractions were decanted, flocculated with  NaC1 solution, washed 3 times in absolute alcohol and 3 times in Analar ace-  tone and dried at 80.    Separation of clays from Rotongaio Ash and Mapara paleosol    Preliminary investigations showed that the ~ 2-pm fractions of the Roton-  gaio Ash and Mapara paleosol were dominated by volcanic glass, making de-    229    tection of clay minerals difficult. The &lt; 1-pm clay fractions rather than the   2-~m clay fractions were therefore separated from these soil horizons by  the method outlined above using appropriate centrifuging times. Clays were  dried at 30C.    Chemical and instrumental methods    Tamm-oxalate-extractable A1, Fe and Si of &lt; 8-mm samples was determin-  ed by the method of Blakemore et al. (1977). Total A1, Fe and Si in clay  fractions was determined by fusing ignited clay samples with sodium hydrox-  ide, dissolving the fused products in water and determining A1, Fe and Si in  solution by the method of Blakemore et al. (1977). Infra-red spectra of the  clay fractions were obtained using KBr discs and a Perkin-Elmer 337 infra-red  spectrometer. Electron micrographs were obtained using a Zeiss EM 95 instru-  ment.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    Oxalate extracts    Comparison between horizons under different vegetation. Tamm's acid  oxalate extract gives an indication of the amount of iron and aluminium pre-  sent in soils as amorphous compounds (Saunders, 1968; McKeague et al.,  1971). Mean oxalate extractable A1, Fe and Si values for the five profiles un-  der manuka and the five profiles under pine are given in Fig. 3. There are no  significant differences between oxalate-extractable A1, Fe and Si ~ralues of  horizons under pine compared with respective horizons under manuka. Con-  sidered as a group, however, paleosols under pine have a significantly higher  (P &lt; 0.001) SiOJA1203 mole-ratio (8iO2/A1203 = 2.0) than paleosols under  manuka (SIO2/A1203 = 1.6), a feature possibly related to the lower pH of    paleosols under pine (McIntosh, 1980).    AI %  A~I I   ~'~  Rotongaio Ash i  Mapara Paleosol ~  ~,  Whakaipo Paleoso, ~  "~"~  Waimihia Paleosol i      b~  /  0     OA    0"8    1.2    Fe %           Si %                  SIO2//AI203    P,     i          ~)  0   0.4 0-4"    ,   /  i  o~  11o  115  21o  2.s    Fig. 3. Mean oxalate-extractable A1, Fe and Si values of soil horizons under manuka (o)  and radiata pine (o). Dashed lines link data from discontinuous sampling depths. Vertical  scale arbitrary.    230    Comparison between soil horizons. Values of oxalate-extractable A1, and  Fe {Fig. 3), peak in the B horizon, indicating illuviation of A1 and Fe in-  to the B horizon (Saunders, 1968). Si shows a similar pattern. The mean  SIO2/A1203 mole-ratio for B horizons is 1.0; Harada (1955) concluded that  oxalate extracts with a SIO2/A1203 mole ratio of approximately 1 from vol-  canic ash softs near Mt. Daisen, Japan, were indicative of allophane-like com-  plexes in the soil. In contrast, SIO2/A1203 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts of  paleosols are much higher (mean SiO2/A1203 = 1.8) indicating considerable  resilication of amorphous material in buried horizons. Saigusa et al. (1978)  have pointed out that in the zone of resilication in tephra profiles halloysite  can be expected to form from amorphous material with a SiO2/A1203 mole-  ratio of about 2.    Clay fractions of A 11 and B horizons    Comparison between horizons under different vegetation. Properties of All  and B horizon clays are summarised in Table 1. All horizon clays under pine  have significantly higher SiO2/Al:O3 mole-ratios, and significantly less Fe,  than All horizon clays under manuka, a difference possibly induced by the    TABLEI    Properties of clay fractions extracted from A~ and B horizons and from the Rotongaio  Ash and Mapara paleosol    Mean value    Mean value       Significant  under         under            difference*  manuka       radiat a pine    A,,-horizon clays :  % clay &lt;2 ~m         2.5           3.5            N.S.  % loss on ignition      67            62               N.S.  SiO2/AI~O3              7.1             12.2               *  % Fe                   3.8             2.7             *    B-horizon clays:  % clay &lt;2 ~m         4.0           3.3            N.S.  % loss on ignition      44            41               N.S.  SiO2/AI203               1.4               1.6                N.S.  % Fe                  3.6            3.3            N.S.    Rotongaio Ash clays:  % clay &lt;1 ~m         0.50          0.74          N.S.  % halloysite in clay    15            17               N.S.    Mapara paleosol clays:  % clay &lt;1 #m         0.34          0.42          N.S.  % halloysite in clay      3            14               N.S.    *' N.S. = not significant; * = significant difference (P &lt; 0.05).    microns               3                              4                  5           6    231  T'-'I    C    -!  cm            ~           3000                                  2000    8  A    microns    I)          10                                   15                20    om-i   1200                 1000                 800             600  Fig. 4. Infra-red spectra of A11 and B horizon clays &lt; 2 ~m. A ffi AI~-horizon clay under  manuka; B = A~ -horizon clay under pine; C = B-horizon clay under manuka; D = B-hori-  zon clay under pine.    232    lower pH of the A~ horizon under pine (McIntosh, 1980) and the resulting  enhanced mobility of A1 and Fe (Taylor, 1933; Curtis, 1970). In contrast,  B horizon clays show no chemical differences attributable to pine cover. Typ-  ical infra-red traces from clays of AI~ horizons under pine show stronger ab-  sorption in the 2920 cm-~ and 2850--2860 cm-' region due to aliphatic  compounds than the traces from clays of All horizons under manuka and  also have a more intense absorption at 800 cm-1 (Fig. 4), in keeping with the  higher SiO2/A1203 mole-ratio of clays from A~ horizons under pine. Clay  samples showed no peaks attributable to crystalline clay minerals when sub-  jected to X-ray diffraction.    Comparisons between soil horizons. Comparisons of 8iO2/A12Oa mole-ratios  of oxalate extracts of softs with 8iO2/A1~O3 mole-ratios of clay fractions pro-  vides information on the proportions of fine-glass and non-glass amorphous  components in clay fractions (Campbell et al., 1977). SiO2/Al~O3 mole-ratios  of oxalate extracts from B horizon samples (mean SIO2/A1203 = 1; Fig. 3) are  only slightly lower than SIO2/A1203 mole-ratios of the respective clays (mean  SIO2/A1203 = 1.5; Table I). In contrast, SiO~/A1203 mole-ratios of oxalate ex-  tracts from A1, horizon samples (mean SIO2/A1203 = 0.6; Fig. 3) are much  lower than the SIO2/A1203 mole-ratio of respective clays (mean SiO2/A12Oa =  9.6; Table I) indicating that much of the siliceous component of A,, horizon  clays is not extractable by oxalate. The A1, horizon clays show absorption  peaks due to Si--O--Si bonds of tetrahedral silica at 800 cm-', absent from  B-horizon clays; a shoulder at approximately 1200 cm-' in A,1 horizon clays,  attributed to a silica phase of high condensation (Kirkman, 1975), is also ab-  sent from B-horizon clays (Fig. 4). It is inferred that AI~ horizon clays con-  tain two silica phases; one of high condensation (volcanic glass) and one of  low condensation (gel). The B-horizon clays consist mainly of the low con-  densation (gel) phase. The presence of large amounts of volcanic glass, as  well as amorphous masses, in A-horizon clays, was confirmed by electron  microscopy (Fig. 5). Volcanic glass was not observed in clays from B horizons.  The above inferences are in accord with the results of Campbell et al.  (1977) who characterised poorly ordered aluminosilicates of Taupo sandy  silt, a Vitrandept formed in the same parent material as the soil of the present  study. Molar SiO2/A1203 ratios of rhyolitic glass in clay fractions extracted  by these authors were found to be considerably higher than those of a "non-  glass" phase. Clays from B horizons contained substantial amounts of the  "non-glass" phase.  Absorption in the 950--1100 cm-~ region gives information on the proper-  ties of Si--O--Si and Si--O--A1 linkages in silica-alumina gels (Mitchell et al.,  1964). Clays from B horizons show maximum absorption in the 950--1000 cm-'  region, indicating a greater proportion of Si--O--AI bonds in the amorphous  material of B-horizon clays than in Au -horizon clays which show a broad  maximum in the 1050--1100 cm-~ region (Fig. 4). These observations are  consistent with the lower SiO2/A1203 mole-ratio of oxalate extracts of &lt; 8-  mm soil of B horizons.    233    Fig. 5. Electron micrograph of A-horizon clay, showing angular volcanic glass fragments  and amorphous masses. (Carbon replica shadowed at 45 with platinum.)    Clay fractions of Rotongaio Ash and Mapara paleosol    Comparison between horizons under different vegetation. There were no  significant differences in amounts of &lt; 1-um clay in the Rotongaio Ash and  Mapara paleosol under manuka and pine (Table I). Mineralogical studies using  X-ray diffraction, infra-red spectrometry, differential thermal analysis and  electron-microscope examination demonstrated the presence of halloysite in  the Rotongaio Ash and Mapara paleosol in three profiles under pine and in  one profile under manuka (McIntosh, 1979). From the low dehydroxylation  temperature (475) of the halloysite, the relative strength of infra-red ab-  sorption at 3620 cm-1 over that at 3690 cm-1, and the ill-defined coiled struc  tures of the halloysite in electron micrographs (Fig. 6), McIntosh (1979) con-  cluded that the halloysite was poorly crystalline. Two possible modes of for-  mation of halloysite in the tephra profiles of the Kaingaroaplateau are: (1)  by pre-eruption hydrothermal processes; (2) by authigenic processes in the  tephra profiles. As halloysite of hydrothermal origin is generally well crystal-  lised and has a dehydroxylation temperature of &gt; 550 (Murray et al.,    234    Fig. 6. Electron micrograph of halloysitic clay &lt; 1 #m from the Mapara paleosol under  pine. (Untreated clay supported on collodion film.)    1977), it is concluded that the halloysite found in this study is authigenic.  The presence of allophane in both halloysitic and non-halloysitic clays was in-  dicated by strong absorption due to hydroxyl stretching in the 3450 cm-~ re-  gion in infra-red spectra and the strong dehydration peak at ll0 on DTA  curves.    Comparison between soil horizons. The presence of authigenic halloysite  at depths &gt; 2 m supports the earlier inference, made on the basis of SiO2/  A12Oa mole-ratios of oxalate extracts, that horizons at this depth are in the  zone of resilication as defined by Saigusa et al. (1978). That resilication pro-  cesses favouring production of 1:1 clay minerals are dominant in horizons at  this depth, is also indicated by the mean composition of soil leachate collect-  ed at 3 m depth beneath a pine stand in Kaingaroa Forest by Knight (1974);  the composition falls in the kaolinite stability field (Fig. 7).    235    10  LOG  K/H                            AR  7  6  5  GIBB'ITEKAOL'I'T'~  I    KAOLI                  MONT  \,  5           4         ~            2    - LOG SlO2    Fig. 7. Phase diagram for clay-mineral stability fields in the system K20--Na~O--SiO2-  H20 at 25 and 1 arm, reproduced from Hess (1966) with permission. Isoplethic section  at log Na/H = 4. MONT = montmorillonite. Dashed line = solubility of amorphous silica  at 25. Full circle represents the mean composition of leachate from 3 m depth in Com-  partment 69, Kaingaroa Forest (Knight, 1974).    CONCLUSIONS    In comparison with softs in unplanted areas under manuka, softs under  pine have higher SiO2/Al203 mole-ratios and lower Fe contents in clays of  the AI~ horizon. These properties of clays of the Alt horizon under pine are  attributed to the lower pH of this horizon under pine than under manuka  (McIntosh, 1980), which is likely to have enhanced the mobility of A1 and  Fe (Taylor, 1933; Curtis, 1970).  No detectable influence of present vegetation on the composition of clays  or oxalate extracts of the B horizon was noted. It appears probable that the  characteristics of this horizon described in this paper are chiefly the result of  soil processes that took place under previous podocarp forest cover.  The greater SIO2/A1203 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts from paleosols at  &gt; 2 m depth under pine, the mildly acidic environment (McIntosh, 1980),  and the soil leachate composition under this species (Knight, 1974) should  theoretically provide a favourable environment for crystallisation of 1:1 clay  minerals in these horizons under pine. Both mildly acidic environments and  organic acids have been shown to favour formation of minerals in the kaolinite  group in laboratory studies (De Kimpe et al., 1964; La Iglesia, 1978). Although  halloysite was found in more profiles under radiata pine than under manuka,  conclusive evidence of an influence of the conifer on halloysite formation  would require the study of more profiles than investigated in this study.    236    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    I would like to thank Mr. C. Vucetich for help during fieldwork and for  advice during this project, staff of New Zealand Soil Bureau for use of infra-  red facilities, Mr. M. Loper for preparing electron micrographs, and New Zea-  land Forest Service for providing financial assistance (Research Grant 113).    Appendix    SOIL PROFILES UNDER MANUKA AND RADIATA PINE    Soil colours are those in Revised Standard Colour Charts, 1967. Conventions used are  those of Taylor and Pohlen, 1962.    Soil profile under manuka    Vegetation forming the canopy: Leptospermum scopariurn up to 5 m tall. Vegetation  forming ground cover: dense growth of Paesia scaberula and Lycopodium volubile up to  1 m high; tree ferns (Cyathea sp.) within 2 m of site.    L  F2             1  -- 0 cm  A~I            0  -- 1.5 em    AI~            1.5--10.5 cm    B            10.5--22.5 cm t    CI               22.5-- 46.5 cm    C2              46.5-- 90 cm    Drt             90  --180 cm  Dr~            180  --184 cm  Dr3            184  --211 cm  luAB         211  --214 cm  luC          214 --225 cm  2uAB        225 --232 cm    fronds of Paesia and Lycopodium; manuka twigs and  bark  twigs and bark of manuka and some Lycopodium  fragments, but mostly unidentifiable  brownish black (5YR 2/2)sandy loam; friable to  loose; fine crumb structure; abundant fine roots 1--2  mm diameter; boundary distinct and wavy  brownish black (10YR 2/3) with many medium mot-  tles of dark brown (10YR 3/3), similar to horizon be-  low, coarse sandy loam; friable; moderately developed  medium crumb structure with minor granules; many  roots 2 mm diameter; boundary distinct  dark brown (10YR 3/3) with many coarse mottles of  bright yellowish brown (10YR 6/6) loamy coarse sand  with some pumice lapilli; friable; weakly developed me-  dium crumb structure; few roots up to 2 mm diameter;  boundary indistinct  bright yellowish brown (10YR 6/8) with many med-  ium to coarse mottles of dark brown (10YR 3/4)  loamy coarse sand; slightly firm; massive; few roots  1--3 ram; boundary indistinct  dull yellow (2.5YR 6/4) coarse sand; indurated; mas-  sive; some lapilli up to 2 cm diameter; boundary  sharp  coarse pumice gravel (Taupo Lapilli)  bluish grey (5PB 5/1) (pale pink at top) loamy sand  (Rotongaio Ash)  very coarse sand (Hatepe Lapilli)  dark greyish brown (2.5Y 5/2) coarse sand; firm; mas-  sive; boundary indistinct (Mapara paleosol)  coarse sand (Mapara Tephra)  brown (10YR 4/4) loamy coarse sand with a few  faint mottles of lighter hue; firm; massive; boundary  distinct and irregular (Whakaipo paleosol)    237    2uC          232 --242 cm  3uAB        242 --255 cm    3uC          on    coarse sand (Whakaipo Tephra)  dark brown (10YR 3/3) loamy sand; firm; massive;  boundary sharp (Waimihia paleosol)  coarse sand (Waimihia LapUli)    Soil profile under radiata pine    Vegetation forming the canopy: Pinus radiata; nearest pine tree: 2.04 m (dead); 4.03 m  (live). Ground vegetation: complete cover of the herb Nertera depressa; a few grasses    L  F~  F2    5--  0 cm    AH                O--   4 cm    A,~               4-- 15 cm    bleached       15-- 20.5 cm    B              20.5-- 27 cm    C~               27  -- 39 cm    C2               39  -- 85 cm    Dr,             85  -- 95 cm  Dr~             95  --190 cm  Dr3            190  --194 cm    Dr,            194  --220 cm  luAB        220 --223 cm  luC          223 --244 cm  2uAB         244 --246 cm  2uC          246 --251.5 cm  3uAB         251.5--268 cm  3uC          on    pine needles, cones, twigs with lichen  pine needles, cones, twigs, somewhat decomposed  pine needles, male and female cones, but mostly un-  identifiable; many pine roots I mm diameter and abun-  dant white roots of Nertera  brownish black (10YR 2/2) sandy loam; very friable  to loose; compound fine granular and crumb structure;  slightly greasy; abundant pine roots up to 2 mm dia-  meter; few roots of Nertera; boundary diffuse  brownish black (5YR 2/I) gravelly sandy loam; friable;  moderately developed medium to fine-granular and  crumb structure; greasy; few pumice lapilli up to 7 cm  diameter, mostly 1 cm diameter; boundary distinct  yellowish brown (2.5Y 5/3) loamy sand with fine gra-  vel, occurring in pockets between A and B horizons;  very friable; strongly developed fine crumb structure;  few pumice lapilli up to 2 cm diameter; fungal mycel-  ium visible, few roots 1--2 mm diameter, some dead;  boundary sharp  brown (7.5YR 4/4) sandy loam with many medium  to coarse mottles of dull yellow orange (10YR 6/4)  similar to C horizon; massive, breaking to weakly de-  veloped crumb structure; few roots I--4 mm diameter;  boundary indistinct  dull yellow orange (10YR 6/4) gravelly sand; massive  and slightly indurated; few pumice lapilli up to 8 cm  diameter; boundary sharp  dull yellow (2.5YR 6/4) sand; massive, indurated,  breaking to single grain structure; some rhyolite frag-  ments; few roots 2--5 ram; boundary sharp  coarse sand (Rhyolite Block Member)  coarse pumice gravel (Taupo Lapilli)  bluish grey (5PB 5/I) (pale pink at top) loamy fine  sand; fungal mycelium following dead roots (Roton-  gaio Ash)  very coarse sand (Hatepe Lapilli)  yellowish grey (2.5Y 5/1 ) coarse sand; firm; massive;  boundary distinct (Mapara paleosol)  coarse sand (Mapara Tephra)  brown (10YR 4/4) silty coarse sand; firm; massive;  boundary diffuse (Whakaipo paleosol)  coarse sand (Whakaipo Tephra)  dark brown (10YR 3/3) silty sand; firm; massive;  boundary sharp (Waimihia paleosol)  very coarse sand (Waimihia Lapilli)    238    REFERENCES    Blakemore, L.C., Searle, P.L. and Daly, B.K., 1977. Soil Bureau Laboratory Methods. N.  Z. Soil Bur. Sci. Rep. 10.  Calhoun, F.G., Carlisle, V.W. and Luna, Z.C., 1972. Properties and genesis of selected  Colombian andosols. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 480--485.  Campbell, A.S., 1975. Chemical and mineralogical properties of a sequence of terrace  soils near Reefton, New Zealand. Thesis, Lincoln College, University of Canterbury.  Campbell, A.S., Young, A.W., Livingstone, L.G., Wilson, M.A. and Walker, T.W., 1977.  Characterisation of poorly ordered aluminosilicates in a vitric andosol from New Zea-  land. Soil Sci., 123: 362--368.  Curtis, C.D., 1970. Differences between lateritic and podzolic weathering. Geochim. Cos-  mochim. Acta, 34: 1351--1353.  De Kimpe, C., Gastuche, M.C. and Brindley, G.W., 1964. Low-temperature synthesis of  kaolin minerals. Am. Mineral., 49: 1--16.  Dudas, M.J. and Harward, M.E., 1975. Weathering and authigenic halloysite in soil develop-  ed in Mazama Ash. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 39: 561--566.  Gersper, P.L. and Holowaychuk, N., 1970. Effects of stemflow water on a Miami soil un-  der a beech tree, 2. Chemical properties. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 34: 786--794.  Harada, M., 1955. Studies on the volcanic ash soils in the environs of Mr. Daisen. Soil  Plant Food, 1: 81--83.  Harley, J.L., 1969. The Biology of Mycorrhizae. Leonard Hill, London,  Hess, P.C., 1966. Phase equilibria in the K20--Na20--SiO2--H20 system at 25 and 1 at-  mosphere. Am. J. Sci., 264: 289--309.  Kanno, I., Onikura, Y. and Higashi, T., 1968. Weathering and clay-mineralogical character-  istics of volcanic ashes and pumices in Japan. Trans. 9th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 3: 111--  122.  Kirkman, J.H., 1975. Clay mineralogy of some tephra beds of Rotorua area, North Island,  New Zealand. Clay Miner., 10: 437--449.  Knight, P.J., 1974. Natural losses from a pumice soil planted with Pinus radiata: results of  ten years of lysimetric observations in central Kaingaroa Forest. N.Z. For. Serv. Soils  Site Prod. Rep., 48 (unpublished).  Knight, P.J. and Will, G.M., 1970. An appraisal of nutrient supplies available for tree  growth in a pumice soil. Earth Sci. J., 4: 1--15,  Kurahayashi, S. and Tsuchiya, T., 1961. Quantitative estimation of hydrated halloysite in  volcanic ash beds. Clay Sci., 1: 15--23.  La Iglesia, A., Van Oosterwyck-Gastuche, 1978. Kaolinite synthesis, 1. Crystallisation con-  ditions at low temperatures and calculation of thermodynamic equilibria. Application  to laboratory and field observations. Clays Clay Miner., 26 : 397--408.  Mejia, G., Kohnke, H. and White, J.L., 1968. Clay minerals of certain soils of Colombia.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 665--670.  Mitchell, B.D., Farmer, V.C. and McHardy, W.J., 1964. Amorphous inorganic materials in  soils. Adv. Agron., 16: 327--383.  McIntosh, P.D., 1979. Halloysite in a New Zealand tephra and paleosol less than 2500  years old. N.Z.J. Sci., 22: 49--54.  McIntosh, P.D., 1980. Soil changes under radiata pine in Kaingaroa Forest, central North  Island, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Sci., 23: 83--92.  McKeague, J.A., Brydon, J.E. and Miles, N.M., 1971. Differentiation of extractable iron  and aluminium in soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 35: 33--38.  Murray, H.H., Harvey, C. and Smith, J.M,, 1977. Mineralogy and geology of the Maunga-  parerua halloysite deposit in New Zealand. Clays Clay Miner., 25: 1--5.  Nicholls, J.L., 1963. Vulcanicity and indigenous vegetation in the Rotorua district. N.Z.  Ecol. Soc. Proc., 10: 58--65.  New Zealand Soil Bureau, 1954. General Survey of Soils of the North Island, New Zealand.  N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 5.    239    New Zealand Soil Bureau, 1968. Soils of New Zealand, 3. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 26(3).  Revised Standard Colour Charts, 1967. Fujihara, Tokyo.  Saigusa, M., Shoji, S. and Kato, T., 1978. Origin and nature of halloysite in Ando soils  from Towada Tephra, Japan. Geoderma, 20: 115--129.  Saunders, W.M.H., 1968. Iron and aluminium extracted by Tamm's reagent. In: Soils of  New Zealand. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 26(2), pp. 109--114.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy. A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. Soil Conserv. Serv., U.S. Dep. Agric., Agric. Handb., 436.  Taylor, N.H., 1933. Soil processes in volcanic ash beds. N.Z.J. Sci. Technol., 14: 338--  352.  Taylor, N.H. and Pohlen, I.J., 1962. Soil Survey Method. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 25.  Thornton, R.H., Cowie, J.D. and McDonald, D.C., 1956. Mycelial aggregation of sand soil  under Pinus radiata. Nature, 177: 231--232.  Ure, J., 1950. The natural vegetation of the Kaingaroa Plains as an indicator of site quality  for exotic conifers. N.Z.J. For., 6: 112--123.  Vucetich, C.G. and Pullar, W.A., 1963. Ash beds and soils in the Rotorua district. N.Z.  Ecol. Soc. Proc., 10: 65--72.  Vucetich, C.G. and Pullar, W.A., 1973. Holocene tephra formations erupted in the Taupo  area, and interbedded tephras from other volcanic sources. N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 16:  745--780.  Vucetich, C.G. and Wells, N., 1978. Soils, agriculture and forestry of Waiotapu region,  central North Island, New Zealand. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 31:  Vucetich, C.G., Leamy, M.L., Popplewell, M.A., Ure, J., Taylor, C.R., Will, G.M., Sutton,  J.A. and Blakemore, L.C., 1960. Soils, forestry and agriculture of the northern part,  Kaingaroa State Forest and the Galatea Basin. N.Z. Soil Bur. Bull., 18.  Ward, W.T., 1967. Volcanic ash beds of the lower Walkato Basin, North Island, New Zea-  land. N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 10: 1109--1135.  Yoshinaga, N. and Yamaguchi, M., 1970. Occurrence of imogolite as a gel film in the pu-  mice and scoria beds of Western and Central Honshu and Hokkaido. Soil Sci. Plant  Nutr., 16: 215--223.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              AbstractWeathering products of Vitrandept profiles on the Kaingaroa plateau, central North Island, New Zealand, were investigated by analysis of oxalate extracts and by chemical and mineralogical analysis of clays of selected soil horizons. Comparisons were made between profiles under a Pinus radiata (D. Don) stand and profiles under an adjacent area of manuka native scrub, Leptospermum scoparium (Myrtaceae).Clay fractions (&lt; 2 μm) of A11 horizon under pine had significantly higher SiO2/Al2O3 mole-ratios (mean SiO2/Al2O3 = 12.2) than A11 horizon under manuka (mean SiO2/Al2O3 = 7.1). No effect of vegetation on clay fractions of B horizon was evident, these clays having much lower SiO2/Al2O3 mole-ratio (1.5). Oxalate-extractable Al, Fe and Si values of &lt; 8-mm fractions of A, B and C horizons showed no differences attributable to present vegetative cover.SiO2/Al2O3 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts increased with increasing depth, and paleosols at &gt; 2 m depth under pine had significantly higher SiO2/Al2O3 mole-ratios in oxalate extracts (mean SiO2/Al2O3 = 2.0) than paleosols under manuka (mean SiO2/Al2O3 = 1.6). That soil horizons at &gt; 2 m depth are in the zone of resilication is indicated by: (1) the greater SiO2/Al2O3 mole-ratios of oxalate extracts of paleosols than surface horizons; (2) lysimeter leachate composition; and (3) the presence of authigenic halloysite at &gt; 2 m depth in soil profiles. 