 294    Geochemistry of Colloid Systems for Earth Scientists. S. Yariv and H. Cross.  Springer Verlag, Berlin, 1979, 450 pp., US $ 60.-, DM. 110.00.    In their preface to the book the authors state "... It would be useful at  this stage to attempt to summarize the progress made and to try to examine  what col.loid science has contributed and could further contribute to geo-  chemistry". Considering the amount of work done in this field and the grow-  ing awareness of its importance, the authors took on themselves an impor-  tant, but formidable task. The book covers the whole gamut of geochemical  colloid systems from low to high temperature environments and from atmo-  spheric through terrestrial to manne environments. The book is organised  into ten chapters. Some of them deal with general physico-chemical proper-  ties of colloidal systems -- kinetics, surface chemistry, interactions between  solid particles dispersed in colloid systems. Others deal with specific geo-  chemical themes -- clay minerals, silica, organic materials, and finally with  the colloid geochemistry of argillaceous sediments. The organization of the  chapters does not always follow a logical s~quence, although the internal or-  ganization is quite orderly. The authors have succeeded quite well in their  message of emphasizing the importance of colloid systems in geochemistry.  One can only be surprised that no such book was published before. The pio-  neering and unconventional approach to a multi-disciplinary subject should  be highly praised. But then again, such broad view suffers from some imbal-  ances. In their (commendable) enthusiasm the authors have used the term  "colloids" for systems which are not usually defined as such. Examples can  be found in the treatment of organic matter in sea water where the authors  discuss dissolved and particulate organic matter in the same breath as col-  loidal organic matter. The same is true in the chapter on rheology which in-  cludes discussion of sands.  All in all the book is recommended to practicing geo-scientists of every  brand and flavour. Although the book is based on a graduate course, the  price of the book will probably put it beyond the reach of most students,  but it should find its way to every library of soil science and geoscience.    A. NISSENBAUM  (Rehovot)    Environment Impact Assessment, Pr.inciples end Procedures, SCOPE 5, 2nd  ed. R.E. Munn (Editor}. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, 1979, 190 pp.,  7.50.    It is certainly unusual to be asked to review a book in 1980 with its earliest  reference dated 1967 and most references later than 1973, but that is a re-  flection of its topicality, in the best possible sense. It is also a reflection on    295    how recent and rapidly has our concern with environmental matters matured.  Further, the book I am reviewing is the second and extensively revised edi-  tion of one originally published early in 1975 as the result of a workshop in  1974. Its topic is of course central to the whole purpose of its sponsoring  committee. The mandate of SCOPE is, as pointed out by Frank Fenner, editor.  in-chief of SCOPE publications ... 'to evaluate the methodologies of the mea-  surement of environmental parameters; ... to establish itself as a corpus of  informed advice for the benefit of centres of fundamental research and of  organizations and agencies operationally engaged in studies of the environmeni  The text runs to a mere 94 pages followed by a similar length of appen-  dices and a brief index. It is therefore neither a textbook nor a hand-book,  indeed as the editor says, no attempt has been made to describe methods of  undertaking the detailed investigations and calculations required to meet  specified environmental standards. The text is written with a remarkable uni-  formity of style and directed principally at decision-makers and their policy  and management advisors, in both public and private sectors. As a result it is  strongly reminiscent of a management seminar or a better class Rotary Con-  ference; however, the information content is very high and the references  important, relevant, up-to-date and directed at the subsidiary audience of  assessors, reviewers and their technical staff. The editor also suggests the  book is relevant to laymen interested in environmental quality. It could only  help all three classes of reader and it would greatly comfort any interested  layman to know that any planning executives ant, their technical advisers  operating in his region were conversant with the principles enunciated.  But is it of real help to the technical person involved in planning, design,  or the preparation of an environmental impact statement? I believe it is most  helpful, and particularly in the manner it clearly and objectively sets out the  strengths and weaknesses of the various alternative approaches, in particular  the Leopold matrix, the overlay method, and the Battelle environment eval-  uation system. Unfortunately, the workshop panel which set up the original  report was strongly North American oriented or from fully developed econ-  omies and so there is no real criticism of the check list items of the Leopold  Matrix or the Battelle System. However, in other places the editor very  strongly points out the relevance of environmental impact assessments in de-  veloping countries. He also indicates the different weights and concerns ap-  propriate to such economies.  Another important thematic thread through both the text and its appen-  dices is the importance of true communication between assessor and execu-  tive, writer and reader, hard and soft sciences, and between the public, the  proponent developer, the reviewer and the decision-maker. The text is a  model of such communication.  The appendices are more difficult to assess, and rather more variable in  style and level of complexity. They also generate responses mo~e strongly  aligned with the knowledge, expertise and prejudices of the reader. For ex-    296    ample, Appendix 2 is devoted to some examples of E.I.S. procedures from  various countries, and contains a five page commentary on Australian proce-  dures, concerns, and selected references, which is masterly. It may not be so  neat a summation to someone unfamiliar, with Australia's complex politics  and ingenuous society. The other reviews are all shorter and rather more ex-  plicit about procedures adopted.  Appendix 4 is an annotated bibliography with a special note in the preface  commending a new section giving engineering references. It is unusual to find  engineering texts with any strong cross-disciplinary tendency and those in  the appendix known to me are strongly 'hard-hat', indeed the annotation on  a recent text on large dams notes it... 'contains only superficial information  on environmental considerations.' Yet as anyone with experience in trying to  explain engineering concepts to other scientists knows, engineering texts  confuse more often than help. Let us hope that the next generation of engi-  neering text books will be able to properly take their place in the third or  fourth edition of SCOPE 5.  This second edition of SCOPE 5 can be unreservedly recommended to  decision-makers, who should provide multiple copies for their technical staff.  It should erlighten and reassure interest laymen.    P.M. FLEMING  (Canberra, A.C.T.)    Constituants et Propri'~t$s du Sol. Pedolo_gie, Vol. 2. M. Bonneau et B.  Souchier. Masson, Paris, 459 pp.    Le premier volume de cet ouvrage, publid en 1977 sous la seule signature  de Philippe Duchaufour, dtait consacrd ~ l'dtude de la formation et de l'dvo-  lution des sols en liaison avec les facteurs du milieu. I1 ~tait intitul~ Pddoge-  n~se et Classification.  Ce second volume traite des constituants du sol et de ses propridt~s ap-  oel~es souvent "fonctionnelles", c'est-~-dire celles qui pr~sentent une impor-  tance particuli~re sur le plan des applications agronomiques ou sylvicoles de  la pddologie; ces propri~tds, tant physiques que chimiques ou biologiques,  conditionnent de mani~re dfroite la physiologic et la nutrition des plant, s,  donc leur croissance: elles permettent de d~finir la fertilitd du sol.  Ce volume comporte deux parties: la premi4re passe en revue les divers  constituants min~raux et organiques du sol et met en relief leur interaction  rdciproque dans la phase solide comme dans la phase liquide.  Les principaux chapitres s'intitulent: 1. Mdthodes d'identification et de  quantification des constituants; 2. Les oxyhydroxydes amorphes et cristaliins  dans les sols (fer, aluminium, manganese, silicium); 3. Les mindmux argileux;  4. Les conditions de formation des constituants secondaires; 5. Signification                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             