 Geoderma, 26 (1981) 125--133                                                   125  lsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    Book Reviews    Soil Physical Properties and Crop Production in the Tropics. R. Lal and D.J.  Greenland {Editors}. Wiley and Sons, Chichester, 1979, 551 pp., 29.50.    This volume does not present a systematic study of the subject, but it  contains 39 papers, presented at a meeting held at the International Institute  of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria in December 1977. The papers have  been subdivided into eight parts, with a postscript of the editors and some  recommendations.  Part 1 discusses the role, determination and management of the physical  properties. Part 2 has studies on the nature of structure stability, its mea-  surements and relation with crop production. Parts 3 and 4 discuss soil be-  havior and plant responze in different water regimes. Some crops are dis-  cussed in detail: upland rice on a Red Yellow Latosol in Brazil, rice on a  reconstructed Mollisol in lysimeters, Phaseolus vulgaris in greenhouses, wheat  in a Cerrado soil in Brazil, cowpea on an Oxic Paleustalf from Nigeria recon-  structed in lysimeters, effect of the transient flooding in field lysimeters with  loamy sand and with clay loam on cowpea, maize and soybeam Part 5 in-  cludes contributions on the measurements of soil temperature, the influence  of different tillage treatments, mulching and irrigation on it, emd the res-  ponse of different crops on soil temperature. Part 6 discusses the effect of  different physical characteristics on root growth: bulk densities, penetration  resistance, hydraulic conductivity. Specific studies report the behavior of  pineapple, oil palm and upland rice in soils with different physical proper-  ties. Part 7 treats the relationship between physical properties and land use.  It draws attention on soil degradation and erosion as a result of cultivation  and presents systems of land capability and land evaluation using physical  characteristics. Part 8 discusses soil and water conservation. It is mainly con-  cerned with the measurements of soil erosion and runoff in different conditions  of cultivation and in different countries.  In the postscript, the editors explain the purpose of the book: bring to-  gether information on the physical properties of soils and their effect on crop  production in tropical regions and draw the attention on some important  conclusions'resulting from the reported studies: the deleterious effects of  high temperature, waterlogging and pans on crop yields, and the strong erosion  hazards of cultivation practices. Most of these effects would be avoided by  no tillage-mulching farming methods in climates with sufficieut precipitation.  The appendix lists a series of recommendations for further study: root  growth, plant--water relationships, soil structural investigations, research on  tillage systems.  It can be inferred from this description of the discussed subjects that the  book contains a very broad spectrum of data. The reported experiments  cover a wide variety of crops, soils and climates. If" they do not always give    126    conclusive results, the way in which they have been set up can be a good  guide to avoid future errors.  The volume is well printed, with clearly represented tables and figures,  and any person interested in tropical agriculture will find in it a great amount  of very valuable data.    FRANS DE CONINCK  (Ghent)    Soil Chemistry. H. Bohn, B. McNeal and G. O'Connor. Wiley, New York,  N.Y., 1979, 2.50.    Soil chemistry texts are beginning to appear in some numbers nowadays  on publishers lists, to the great benefit of both teachers and the taught in  colleges and universities. Up to only a very few years ago the amount of  secondary literature was sparse and such as there was only selectively recom-  mendable; we mostly relied on the relevant portions of the "bible"-- Russell's  Soil Conditions and Plant Growth, and such reviews as had sufficient peda-  gogic clarity to illuminate the darker areas of research uncertainty. All this  is changing, and not before time. Perhaps publisher.~ are realising that, in the  modern world, soil chemistry might just be one of t~e most important  branches of chemistry there is.  So, now that we have the responsibility of evaluating and comparing  books on soil chemistry, how does Soil Chemistry by Bohn, McNeal and  O'Connor {Professors of Soil Chemistry at, respectively, the universities of  Arizona, Washington State and New Mexico State} stand? The book can  briefly be described as a fairly elementary text almost wholly devoted to  inorganic aspects of the subject. It is strikingly clearly written, as would be  expected in a volume which stems from long experience of actually teaching  the material involved, and indeed in places has a relaxed and almost conver-  sational style which when succesful, as here, can only be produced by writers  wholly in command of their subject. It initially seems strange that three  authors should be thought desb/able for a text at this level in a not very wide  area of toil science, but there is throughout a remarkable uniformity of style.  In short, this book has the virtues of authority and clarity, is reasonably  priced, and might be thought worthy of a large undergraduate audience.  Unfortunately there are qualifications to be made, though perhaps some  relate only to the book's title. First, the book, since it contains only 41/~ pages  on organic matter out of some 300, cannot really claim to cover soil chem-  istry even at an elementary level; the material in this over-brief survey, which  consists cf Bear's (1964) version of the acid/base fractionation followed by  an hypothetical humic acid structure, can hardly be held tobe illuminating.  There is a more serious point to be made with respect te soil chemistry as it  affects plan nutrition, obviously ,an area of key application. Presumably the                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               