 128    Lindsay) on p. 66. The publisher's inability to decide which of two type founts  to use for the lower case "1" in the AI appearing in mineral structure diagrams  is irritating and unnecessary.  I find this a limited book; it does some things well, with clear explanations.  It is only of intermediate level (it could not be recommended for degree  students in soil science) and does not tackle soil chemistry confidently as a  part ,~f soil science. I shall recommend students reading soils as a subsidiary  degree subject to look at some sections, though not the book as a whole.    CHRISTOPHER MOTT  (Reading)    Stabilized Earth Roads. Developments in Geotechnical Engineering, 19. A.  K~zdi. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 1979, 327 pp., Dfl. 145.00.    In this most interesting book, the author reviews the theoretical principles  (physical, chemical and of soil mechanics), on which is based the praxis of  earth roads stabilization, as well as the experience accumulated during the  last 40 years on this subject. Much of the presented data originates from  the research carried out by the author in the Soil Mechanics Laboratory of  the Budapest Technical University.  Although some lime stabilization had already been used in the antiquity,  re~d road development was made only in the 19th century (macadam roads)  and especially at the beginning of the 20th century, where speed and eco-  nomics were essential. This led to the use of stabilized soil for secondary  roads. In Chapter 1, a short economic and historical background is presented.  In Chapter 2, the author describes the physical and chemical aspects of  soil stabilization. Fundamental notions of soil physics are recollected  (A~terberg limits, grain-size distribution, soil classifications, etc.). Testing  methods are given. Emphasis is put on particles components properties and  their intercorrelation (water-solid relations).  Chapter 3 deals with mechanical soil stabilization, i.e., without the addi-  tion of any foreign matter. Notion of void ratio is discussed, as well as  mixtures methods, mixtures properties and effects of water on the mix.  Stabilization with cement is studied in Chapter 4. Different types are  considered, according to the content of cement, the type of soil and of  additives. Interaction between cement and soil, properties of cement-treated  soils, effects of construction processes and additives are fully considered,  while design and testing of soil--cement mixtures are explained.  The object of Chapter 5 is stabilization with lime (calcium oxide or  hydroxide). Physical and chemical effects of lime are studied, together with  the influence of lime on the physical properties of the soil, with or without  additives. Design of soil--lime mixtures is also explained.  Similarly, Chapter 6 deals with stabilization with bitumen and tar. The    129  physical, chemical and mechanical aspects of stabilization are studied for  both types, together with the effect of addition and properties of stabilized  soils.  In Chapter 7 chemical soil stabilization methods are shown; use may be  made of chlorites, phosphoric acid, resins or other polymers. For each of  these additives are given the effects of variable contents, as well as the  mechanism of the process.  A different point of view is shown in Chapter 8: Design of stabilized  earth roads, mainly for agricultural areas, under various soil and climate  conditions. Miscellaneous profiles are considered, together with slopes, width,  radius and traction forces and velocities. Stresses, deflections and required  thickness are determined.  Finally, Chapter 9 {Construction of Stabilized Earth Roads) deals with  various construction techniques and adequate equipment. Different methods  are considered. Soil mixing and compaction are thoroughly described, as well  as the in-situ mixing and the pulverization operations.  Conclusion: What makes the book so interesting is not the "recipes" for  soil stabilization in different cases, but the systematical way in which the  author explains the principles on which the operations are to be carried out.  There are a lot of figures, diagrams and tables, and some photographs. The  book will be of much assistance to engineers and technicians dealing with  stabilized earth roads.    BORIS AISENSTEIN  (Jerusalem)    Comparison of Forest Water and Energy Exchange Models. Swen Haldin  {Editor). Proceedings from an IUFRO Workshop, Uppsala, ?4--30 Sep-  tember, 1978. Elsevier, Amsterdam - Oxford - New York, 1979, xi +  258 pp., Dfl. 110.00,  US $ 53.75.  The precise determination of forest water and energy exchanges is a bio-  physical problem of exceptional magnitude; a high degree of scientific  sophistication is required, and measurement problems, lack of strict exper-  imental control, and a variety of logistical limitations compound the diffi-  culty. A recent concentrated effort to resolve some of the uncertainties  through micrometeorological and hydrological modeling is reported in these  Proceedings of a workshop, in Sweden, sponsored by the International  Union of Forestry Research Organizations. The central purpose of the work-  shop was to compare results obtained when diverse participant models were  supplied with a common set of observational data.  The Proceedings (in English, offset lithography) report the work of 26  participants from 10 European countries; English usage, and other writing  conventions, reflect national backgrounds of the authors in predictable ways.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  