 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 59-66 59  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam - Printed in The Netherlands  OCCURRENCE OF MAGNESIUM-BEARING CALCITES IN PAMPEAN  SOILS, ARGENTINA  RAUL S. LAVADO  Conicet, Cisaua, 532 esq. 14-1900 La Plata (Argentina)  (Received October 16, 1981; accepted after revision June 16, 1982)  ABSTRACT  Lavado, Raul S., 1983. Occurrence of magnesium-bearing calcites in Pampean soils,   Argentina. Geoderma, 29: 59-66.     Eight soil profiles, representing major soils of the Pampean Plain, were sampled by horizons and analyzed for various properties, including magnesium contents of calcites. Samples of four horizons were further analyzed by X-ray diffraction for additional identification of carbonates. Five samples of groundwater were also analyzed.   Contents of magnesium in calcites were low (0-7.8%) in the well-drained soils (all Mollisols) and higher (mostly 15-25%) in soils with natric or salic horizons. Furthermore, the mol-% of magnesium in calcites was directly correlated with Mg/Ca ratios of saturation extracts from horizon samples. From the evidence obtained, the origin of these magnesium-bearing calcites was attributed to groundwaters affecting the soils.    INTRODUCTION     The primary purpose was to characterize the magnesium-bearing calcites in soils of the Pampean Plain, Argentina. Earlier, Arens (1969) had postulated that such calcites were present in some of the soils. Occurrence of such calcites has been reported from a number of countries (Magaritz and Kafri, 1979; Rostad and St. Arnaud, 1970; St. Arnaud and Herbillon, 1973; Szendrei, 1977; Watts, 1980), usually in soils affected by sodium or soluble salts.   The origin of the calcites has also been the subject of several studies and some disagreement (De Boer, 1977; Doner and Lynn, 1977; Suarez, 1977). Consequently, a second purpose of this investigation was to throw further light on possible modes of origin of magnesium-bearing calcites. The findings might also be helpful in evaluation of salinization-desalinization processes (St. Arnaud, 1978).    0016-7061/83/0000-0000/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company  60    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Soils and groundwaters     The soils of the Pampean Plain are mainly Mollisols. These are associated with Alfisols in the eastern, more humid parts and with Entisols in the western, semi-arid parts. Soils of other orders such as Vertisols are present but far less important (Moscatelli et al., 1980).   The soils have been derived almost entirely from loess and loess-like sediments with differing contents of lime. No dolomite has been found and no significant quantities of magnesium are present in the lime. Moreover, the contents of magnesium-bearing silicates such as amphiboles and pyroxenes are low (Teruggi, 1957). Consequently, minerals within soils could provide only small quantities of magnesium.   Some of the soils have petrocalcic horizons which, in total analyses, have Mg/Ca ratios of 0.023 to 0.054 in the eastern Pampa (Martinez et al., 1972 and 0.017 to 0.045 in the western parts (Kilmurray, 1966). These figures are a further indication that inherent quantities of magnesium in the soils are low.   Phreatic waters usually rich in magnesium are present at shallow depths in parts of the Pampean Plain, mainly in the area known as Pampa Deprimida in the eastern part of Buenos Aires Province (Sala et al., 1977). A majority of the Mollisols and Alfisols with natric horizons are in the Pampa Deprimida. Earlier studies (Lavado, 1978) indicated that these phreatic waters had affected the composition of soil solutions and properties of the soils.    Sampling     Samples were collected by horizons from four pairs of profiles. Five samples were also collected of phreatic waters. In each pair of soil profiles, one was well drained and the other not. The second profile had either a natric or salic horizon. Profiles in the four pairs are classified according to the American taxonomy (Soil Survey Staff, 1975) as an Argiudoll and a Natraquoll, a Hapludoll and a Natralboll, a Haplustoll and a Salorthid, and a Rendoll and a Natraqualf. All profiles of the first three pairs are believed to have been formed from the same kinds of parent materials, whereas the final pair was not. Paired profiles are short distances apart so that the climate could be considered the same for both. The positions in the landscape were the main differences between profiles of the first three pairs, whereas a difference in parent materials also exists for the fourth.    Analytical methods     Soil samples were ground to pass a 2-mm sieve and then analyzed for pH in paste, cation exchange capacity (Na acetate at pH 8.2), exchangeable ca-  61    tions (NH, acetate at pH 7) with corrections for soluble cations if necessary, CaC03 equivalent (gasometric method), electrical conductivity and soluble  cations in the saturation extract, calcium (EDTA volumetry), sodium (flame photometer) and particle size distribution by the pipette method (Black, 1965). To measure the Mg in calcites a citrate buffer method used by St. Arnaud and Herbillon (1973) was followed to extract samples with subsequent determinations of magnesium and calcium. X-ray diffraction patterns were obtained on samples 1, 5, 9 and 15 using Cu-K a radiation.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION     Sample sites, identifications of profiles, horizons and their depths, clay contents and the depth at which phreatic waters were samples are given in Table 1. Some chemical properties of soil samples and groundwaters are given in Table Il. Proportions of magnesium in the calcites in soil horizons are  given in Table lIl.    TABLE I    Some profile characteristics, sampling sites and groundwater depths for the four pairs of profiles    Soil Soil sample Taxonomy Location Horizons Depth Clay  pair  (cm) content (%)    1  1 Argiudoll Cnel. Suez  B22t 58-70 50.1    2  (BA)  B3 70-90 22.7    3    Cca 90-98 20.1   phreatic water   -  133+ -    4 Natraquoll   B21t 19-30 46.2    5    B22t 30-45 45.4    6    B3 45-70 18.4    7    C 70-82 16.2   phreatic water   -  90+ -  2  8 Hapludoll Pringles (BA)  B32 102-126 16.8    9    C1 126-225 12.6   10    C2ca 225+  9.9   11 Natralboll    Bl 26-36 28.1   12    B21t 36-44 44.1   13    B22t 44-56 46.5   14    B3x 56-68 22.9   15     Clcax 68-93 14.9   16   11 C2cax  93+  9.8   phreatic water   -  101+ -  3 17 Haplustoll Santa Rosa (LP)  C2  90-115 14.2   18 Salorthid   Alsa   0-12 34.5   phreatic water   -   63+ -  4 19 Rendoll Pipinas (BA)  A1   0-45  7.1   20    C  45+  4.4   21 Natraqualf   B21t  13-37 49.4   22    B22t  37-55 49.0   phreatic water   -   70+ -  62    TABLE II    Some chemical properties of soil samples and groundwaters and the Mg/Ca ratios    Soil sample Electrical pH*2 lCEC J Exch. CaC03 Soluble Mg/Ca  conductivity* i (meq. 100 g-') sodium (%) equiv. calcium*' ratio*  (dS m-t)   (%) (me 1-')     1 0.17 7.2 21.8 _  _ __6 -- _ 2.25 - -1.2G _ 0.21    2 0.36 8.3 20.1  0.8 2.71 2.85 0.20  3 0.39 8.3 19.2  0.8 33.50 2.28 0.33  Phreatic water . 0.82 7.9 ---  -  - 1.55 0.41  4 3.18 8.5 21.6 47.6 0.28 1.90 1,00  5 3.47 9.1 28.9 73.7 3.06 1.52 1.50  6 2.02 9.5 17.4 76.9 4.92 2.28 5.09  7 1.41 9.6 16.2 44.1 1.67 0.98 4.39  Phreatic water 1.53 8.7 --  -  - 0.65 1.20  8 0.24 7.1 20.9  0.03 0.46 0.88 0.51  9 0.40 8.0 13.0  0.03 4.32 2.00 1.22  10 0.39 8.1 --  -  5.96 1.78 1.68  11 0.92 7.9 14.9 49.1 0.25 0.44 4.04  12 1.62 8.7 30.4 49.3 0.56 0.24 9.25  13 1.62 9.0 38.8 44.1 3.10 0.46 1.45  14 2.74 8.8 31.8 44.9 0.69 0.10 11.20  15 1.62 8.7 27.3 44.9 0.73 0.10 20.00  16 1.84 7.9 --  -  20.23 0.22 7.40  Phreatic water 2.06 8.2 -  -  - 0.26 4.30  17 4.12 7.9 14.2  0.1 3.14 3.40 0.34  18 38.50 7.7 35.2 42.0 2.68 38.50 0.86  Phreatic water 62.57 7.6 -  --  - 61.21 1.24  19 0.31 7.7 12.2  0.1 13.56 0.97 0.84  20 0.33 8.1  6.5  0.2 49.33 1.41 0.62  21 2.98 9.2 39.3 51.3 1.27 1.41 3.00  22 2.21 9.2 39.5 52.7 4.39 1.19 1.00  Phreatic water 3.11 8.3 --  -  -- 0,40 2.6;;    *' In saturation extract for soil samples  * 2In paste for soil samples     The distinctions between paired profiles are as would be expected from their classification. Samples of the soils with natric or salic horizons are much higher in electrical conductivity of saturation extracts and in percent exchangeable Na and somewhat higher in pH than the well-drained profiles (Table II). Distribution of carbonates within the four well-drained Mollisol profiles is systematic, with greater quantities at depth, but in the other four profiles distribution is erratic. This distribution is considered later in discussion of the origins of the magnesium-bearing calcites. Note further that the Mg/Ca ratios of the saturation extracts are lower in the better drained profile of each pair.   Proportions of magnesium in the calcites have a wide range. In the welldrained Mollisols, the proportions range from 0 to 7.8 mol-% MgC03 . Among nine samples, three have no magnesium, whereas three are above 7 mol-%. Among the profiles with natric or salic horizons, proportions range from 0 to 67.9 mol-% of magnesium carbonate. Three of 13 samples have no magnesium and seven have 15 to 25 mol-% of magnesium carbonate. Thus, despite a considerable range in proportions, the latter group of profiles has more magnesium in calcites, on the whole. For one sample (No. 15, from the  63    TABLE III    MgC03 contents in calcites    Sample Profiles Horizons Mol.% MgCO,  Nos.    in calcite   1 Argiudoll  B22t  0.0   2   B3  7.8   3   Cca  2.0   4 Natraquoll  B21t  0.0   5   B22t 18.3   6   B3 18.9   7   C 24.3   8 Hapludoll  B32  4.6   9   C1  7.4   10   C2ca  7.7   11 Natralboll  B1  0.0   12   B21t 10.7   13   B22t 20.6   14   B3x 25.5   15   Clca 67.9   16  IIC2cax  1.1   17 Haplustoll  C2  4.5   18 Salorthid  A1  2.8   19 Rendoll  A1  0.0   20   C  0.0   21 Natraqualf  B21t  9.9   22   B22t 16.6    Natralboll profile), a value of 67.9 mol-% was obtained. With that proportion, the minerals could not be either magnesium-bearing calcites or dolomite. What the source of the magnesium may have been is not yet known.   Further identification of the probable forms of magnesium in the calcites was obtained from X-ray diffraction. Diffractograms from four samples in Fig. 1 show only the 3.03 A peaks with none for dolomite at 2.88 A. The diffractograms for horizons of the Natraquoll and Natralboll profiles are both weaker and broader and the shifts from the 3.03 A peak are higher than in those for horizons of the Argiudoll and Hapludoll profiles. The X-ray data are thus consistent with chemical composition of the calcites which are higher in magnesium in the Natraquoll and Natralboll horizons. The diffractogramsfor the Argiudoll and Hapludoll horizons are not typical for those of calcite, particularly for the former which shows a broadened base toward 30. The sample from the one horizon of the Argiudoll profile has 7.8 mol-% MgC03 in the calcite. Although a direct relationship was found between the chemical composition and the X-ray data for the magnesium-bearing calcites in the samples from soils of the Pampean Plain, that relationship is not as clear and good as those reported earlier by Magaritz and Kafri (1979) and by St. Arnaud and Herbillon (1973).  64    3.03 A 3.03 A    B22 t    Argiudoll ~    C/    Hopludoll    822 t    Na traqu o Il    C/cv    Notralbol(    30 29    DEGREES 2 - Cu - K -    Fig. 1. The 3.03 A peak in the X-ray diffractograms of four soil samples.     The occurrence of magnesium-bearing calcites has been found to be associated with the Mg/Ca ratios of soil solutions in some places (Magarit2 and Kafri, 1979; St. Arnaud, 1979; Watts, 1980). Comparisons of these ratios were therefore made for the profiles from the Pampean Plain. The four welldrained profiles have Mg/Ca ratios of the saturation extract of 0.2 to 1.7, with mol-% of Mg in the calcites ranging from 0 to 7.8. In the profiles with natric or sal horizons, the Mg/Ca ratios range from 0 to 20 and the mol-% of Mg mostly between 15 and 25 although it was 0 in some cases.   The data on mol-% of MgC03 in calcites for all samples are plotted against the Mg/Ca ratios of saturation extracts in Fig. 2. The correlation coefficient (r) between the two variables is 0.?97, which is higher than that for some Canadian Mollisols (St. Arnaud, 1979). Moreover, data in Table II indicate that the Mg/Ca ratios of the saturation extracts are directly related  turn to those of the phreatic waters. The number of data are limited but all point to the same relationship.   Several lines of evidence suggest that groundwaters are the source of the magnesium-bearing calcites in soils of the Pampean Plain. The Mg/Ca ratios of the calcites are highest, generally much higher, in soils with natric or salic horizons which, because of their landscape positions, are most affected by groundwaters. The high positive correlation between the Mg/Ca ratios of the calcites and the saturation extracts is a further bit of evidence. The effects of groundwaters are also indicated by the distribution of carbonates in profiles. The distribution is erratic in the soils most likely to be affected by ground-  65     65    I   60   55   50   45 -   40 I  _a   35 -  I  30    251 y=2.705512x   20J~* r=0797    75 -    7o .    0 2 4 6 8 70 72 74 16 78 20    Mgr/ Ca ratio in sat extract    Fig. 2. Mg/Ca ratios in the saturation extracts versus Mol. % MgC03 calcites.    waters but systematic in the well-drained Mollisols. Postulating a source of magnesium apart from the soils themselves also seems necessary in view of the small amount of that element in the loess and loess-like sediments from which the soils were formed.    ACKNOWLEDGMENTS     The author wants to thank L. Alvarez and M.C. Camilion for their help. Thanks are also due to the laboratory directed by A.M. Iniguez Rodriguez for the X-ray analyses.    REFERENCES    Arens, P.L., 1969. Algunos paisajes geoquimicos en la regi pampeana. Actas 5a Reuni Argentina de la Ciencia del Suelo, Santa Fe, pp. 107-115. Black, C.A. (Editor), 1965. Methods of Soil Analysis, Parts 1 and 2. Agronomy 9, Madison, Wisc. De Boer, R.B., 1977. Stability of Mg/Ca carbonates. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 41: 265-270.  66    Doner, H.E. and Lynn, W.C., 1977. Carbonate, halide, sulfate and sulfide minerals. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Wood (Editors), Minerals in Soil Environments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Publ., Madison, Wisc., pp. 75-98.    Killmurray, J.C., 1966. Rasgos petrogricos y fisicos de toscas de la Provincia de Buenos Aires. LEMIT, Ser. II, 104, 68 pp.    Lavado, R.S., 1978. Algunas causas de la variabilidad en el contenido salino de un Salortide pampeano y su influencia en el muestreo. Turrialba, 28 (4): 315-324.  Magaritz, M. and Kafri, U., 1979. Concentration of magnesium in carbonate nodules of soils: an indication of fresh groundwater contamination by intruding seawater. Chem. Geol., 27: 143--155.    Martinez, H.M., Sighel, R.R. and Calamar N., 1972. Contribuci al conocimiento de los suelos del Departamento Capital. Provincia de La Pampa, 51 pp.    Moscatelli, G., Salazar, J.C., Godagnone, R., Grimberg, H., Sanchez, J., Ferrao, R. and Cuenca, M., 1980. Mapa de suelos de la Provincia de Buenos Aires. Actas 9a Reunion Argentina de to Ciencia de Suelo, Parana III: 1079-1089.    Rostad, H.P.W. and St. Arnaud, R.J., 1970. Nature of carbonate minerals in two Saskatchewan soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 50: 65-70.    Sala, J.M., Gonzalez, N. and Hernandez, M.A., 1977. Efectos de una barrera hidraulica natural en les aguas subterraneas del litoral de la Bahia de Samborombon. Obra Centenario Museo de la Plata, IV: 153--166.    Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for the Making and Interpreting of Soil Surveys. U.S. Department of Agriculture Handbook No. 436, 754 pp.    St. Arnaud, R.J., 1978. The relationship between salinity and secondary soil carbonates. Proc. Mtg. Subcomm. Salt Affected Soils, Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 11th, Edmonton, Can., 2: 30-39.  St. Arnaud, R.J., 1979. Nature and distribution of secondary soil carbonates within landscapes in relation to soluble Mg/Ca ratios. Can. J. Soil Sci., 59: 87-98.  St. Arnaud, R.J. and Herbillon, A.J., 1973. Occurrence and genesis of secondary magnesium-bearing calcite in soils. Geoderma, 9: 279-298.    Suarez, D.L., 1977. Ion activity products of calcium carbonate in waters below the root. zone. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41 (2): 310-315.    Szendrei, G., 1977. Investigations on calcite and dolomite distribution in the soils of Kiskunsag area (Hungary). Agrokem. Talajtan, 26 (1/2): 1-18 (in hungarian).  Teruggi, M.E., 1957. The nature and origin of Argentine Loess. J. Sediment. Petrol., 27 (3): 322-332.    Watts, N.L., 1980. Quaternary pedogenic calcretes from the Kalahari (Southern Africa): Mineralogy, genesis and diagenesis. Sedimentology, 27 (6): 661-686.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       AbstractEight soil profiles, representing major soils of the Pampean Plain, were sampled by horizons and analyzed for various properties, including magnesium contents of calcites. Samples of four horizons were further analyzed by X-ray diffraction for additional identification of carbonates. Five samples of groundwater were also analyzed.Contents of magnesium in calcites were low (0–7.8%) in the well-drained soils (all Mollisols) and higher (mostly 15–25%) in soils with natric or salic horizons. Furthermore, the mol-% of magnesium in calcites was directly correlated with Mg/Ca ratios of saturation extracts from horizon samples. From the evidence obtained, the origin of these magnesium-bearing calcites was attributed to groundwaters affecting the soils. 