Geoderma, 30 (1983) 323--337                                                     323  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    POROSITY MEASUREMENTS AND FORM ANALYSIS OF MINERAL  GRAINS IN THIN SECTIONS FROM OIL- GAS RESERVOIR ROCKS  USING QUANTIMET 720 AND BESI    E.B.A. BISDOM~, H.A. van ADRICHEM BOOGAERT2, G. HEINTZBERGER~,  D. SCHOONDERBEEK~ and F. THIEL3   Netherlands Soil Survey Institute, P.O. Box 98, 6 700 AB Wageningen (The Netherlands)   Geological Survey of The Netherlands, 2000 AD Haarlem (The Netherlands)  3 Technical and Physical Engineering Research Service, 6 700 AJ Wageningen (The  Ne therlands)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Bisdom, E.B.A, van Adrichem Boogaert, H.A., Heintzberger, G., Schoonderbeek, D. and  Thiel, F., 1983. Porosity measurements and form analysis of mineral grains in thin sec-  tions from oil--gas reservoir rocks using Quantimet 720 and BESI. Geoderma, 30  323--337.    Submicroscopic and image analyzer techniques have been applied for the measurement  of the porosities of oil---gas--water reservoir rocks from thin sections. Backscattered elec-  tron scanning images (BESI) were made predominantly at low magnifications of x 30 and  x 60 Porosity data from linear traverses were obtained and differences in porosities be-  tween two sandstone reservoirs and a carbonate reservoir were determined. A large num-  ber of the measured pores contained clayey material. The surface occupied by this ma-  terial was subtracted from the apparent porosity measurements with the image editor of  the Quantimet 720 to give the real porosity  A sample from one of two sandstone reservoirs contained oil and could not be hard-  ened using the common procedure for impregnation of the sample by a polyester resin.  Gamma radiation was applied and hardening occurred in one weekend after 5 Mrad  (50 kGy) had been absorbed. Hardening of this sample gave no problems, if the oil had  been removed by monostyrene before a start was made with the impregnation process;  such a sample was used for the present porosity study.  Form analysis was done of individual mineral grains using BESI and Quantimet. The  grains were represented in a number of shape classes of a diagram used for shape classifi-  cation. Form-separation of individual minerals was also possible.    INTRODUCTION    Earlier measurements of porosities in thin sections often used an integra-  tion ocular for point counting in conjunction with a light microscope. More  recently, an image analyzer (Quantimet) has been introduced (Jongerius et  al., 1972). This allowed the measurement of the total area occupied by  pores; especially in clayey soils. Subsequent investigations and more modern    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Pubhshers B.V    324    equipment has allowed better in sltu porosity analysis of soils (Jongerius,  1974; Ismail, 1975; Murphy et al., 1977; Bouma et al., 1977, 1979). The  analyses concerned pores larger than 30 ~m in diameter. Due to the use of  transmitted hght and the thickness of the thin section, ~t was hardly possible  to analyse pores with smaller diameters. Incident light gave no better results.  Moreover, the study of sandy soils caused problems. Because of their orien-  tation minerals could remain extinguished using crossed polarizers, or suffi-  cient contrast could not be made between a number of minerals and the  pores. Various light microscopic techniques were tested to see whmh could  provide measurable porosities, by Quantimet. This was not successful and,  consequently, other techniques had to be tried.  With the Introduction of backscattered electron scannmg images (BESI)  (Blsdom and Thml, 1981) the above problem was solved. These images were  of such high quality and could be taken at such a variety of magnifications,  that pores with diameters smaller and larger than 30 um (the smallest pore  diameter measurable on mmrographs made with transmitted light) could be  measured by Quantlmet (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981). The latter paper gave  examples of such Quantlmet measurements on BESI for soils. In the paper  by Blsdom and Thiel (1981), examples of pores in BESI of soils, weathered  rocks, and oil--gas reservoir rocks were given, but only the soil porosity was  measured (Jongenus and Blsdom, 1981) The present study is primarily in-  tended to give an example of measurements in oil--gas reservoir rocks. A  special case was the presence of clays in many pores of the sandstone reser-  voirs. These, however, were also measured and subtracted from the total area  of the pores to give the real porosity.  BESI were taken at a low magniflcatmn, because porosity measurements  at smaller magniflcatmns can cover a larger area in one mmrograph and are  therefore more economic. Contiguous mmrographs were made along linear  traverses.  Form analysis was done of 50 larger mmerai grains whmh were easy to  distingmsh at a magnification of 60. Usually, and especially for smaller  silt-sized mineral grams, good results are obtained if form analysis is done  on BESI at 240 or 480 (Blsdom and Schoonderbeek, 1983).    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Light microscopy    The thin sections for this study were obtained from core samples of two  sandstone and one carbonate reservoirs. The first sample came from a Lower  Cretaceous sandstone reservoir and from a depth of about 1300 m. The  sample contained oil and comprised mainly well-sorted subangular quartz  grains, deposited in a former beach ridge environment. The matrix contained  a little clay, usually in small patches. No cement was present.  The second sandstone reservoir provided samples from depths above and    325    below a gas--water contact-level situated at about 3080 m depth. Physical  measurements indicated about 10% porosity and a permeability of maximal-  ly 0.6 millidarcy. The Lower Permian sandstone consisted of predominantly  well-sorted subrounded to rounded quartz with several grains of flint. The  sands were deposited as aeolian sands in a desert enwronment. The matrix  contained a small percentage of clay, which was partly fibrous. The cement  consisted of quartz and dolomite. Most of the pores were filled with cement.  Some of the dolomite in the pores was subsequently leached.  The third reservoir, an Upper Permian dolomite, gave a core sample from a  depth of about 1950 m. The carbonate was originally an algal oolite which  formed in a shallow marine to lagoon environment. The oolite was subse-  quently dolomitized. The leached centres of the ooides were either empty  or filled with anhydrite and carbonate crystals. The latter crystals are coarser  than those of the original rock.    SEM, BESI, Quantimet    Two scanning electron microscopes were used: a Philips SEM 505 and a  Jeol-JSM-35C. The SEM 505 provided backscattered electron scanning im-  ages of contiguous microareas in a thin section which could be analysed with  an image analyzer, the Quantimet 720. Magnifications were usually 60, and  X 30 was used in one case. Larger magnifications were also used to study the  morphology of clays in the pores. Energy dispersive X-ray analysis (EDXRA),  used for the measurement of chemical elements, was done with the  JSM-35C.  If clay occupied a pore partly or completely, porosity measurements re-  quired the use of the image editor of the Quantimet. Such manual work was  necessary, because the contrast of the clay with the pore on BESI was not  sufficient to be measured automatically by Quantimet. The occurrence of  clay on the display screen of the Quantimet was carefully checked and com-  pared with the clay on BESI. The apparent porosity was the total area occu-  pied by pores; with or without clay in the pores. The real porosity was ob-  tained by subtracting, with the image editor, the area occupied by clay from  the area occupied by the apparent porosity. If no clay was present the ap-  parent porosity and the real porosity were identical.    The hardening of oil-containing sample by gamma radiation    The off-containing sample, similar to the other core-samples in this study,  was treated first with a polyester resin according to the method described  by Jongerius and Heintzberger (1975). However, the sample did not harden  in this manner. Recently, due to experiments done at the Netherlands Soil  Survey Institute, hardening of the ofl~ontaining sample succeeded by using  deep-penetrating gamma radiation. This gamma radiation was obtained from  a plate-shaped source in which a number of bars with Cobalt-60 were placed    326    m a rack. Each bar is able to provide 1000 C1 (37-1012 Bq) or more, depend-  ing on the type of installation.  The absorbed dose for this oil-containing sample was 5 Mrad (50 kGy).  The treatment which worked best was the "train" principle whereby samples  moved past the source a number of times with intermittent rest periods of an  hour or more dunng which time they were not affected by radiation. Poly-  merization and hardenmg of the sample was thus performed m a weekend.    RESULTS    Od-contaming sandstone    A light microscopic mlcrograph of the oil-impregnated sample which was  treated with gamma radiation is shown in Fig. 1. Some of the mineral grmns  show a relatively thick coating (grain cutan) of oil but most of the grams had  thin skins of oil. Some of it was dissolved dunng and after the impregnation  process. The impression is, however, that the micrograph gives a rather good  picture of the in situ situation of the oil-containing rather loose sandstone.  The porosity, which represents the percentage of the total area of a micro-  graph that is occupied by pores, was measured by Quantlmet from BESI of a  thin section from which the oil had been removed using monostyrene {Fig.    Fig. 1. Off-impregnated sandstone. The oil is vis,ble as thick and thin blackish coatings on  some of the mineral grains. Plane polarized light.    327    2). Pores with or without clay were present m Fig. 2a, whereas no clay was  found m Fig. 2b. Consequently, the real porosity could be measured m Fig.  2b, i.e. 21.17%. The apparent porosity was 24.95% m Fig. 2a. The real poros-  ity was found by subtracting the percentage occupied by clay from the ap-  parent porosity. The percentage of clay was 2.53% and the real porosity  22.42%.    Fig 2. Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) of the same oil-containing sand-  stone as m Fig 1. However, the oil was removed from the sample with monostyrene in  order to demonstrate the real poroslty. Micrograph a shows that clay patches occupy  some of the pores whereas no clay could be detected in micrograph b. Porosity-values in  text.  The central part of Fig. 2a and other areas of the micrograh have patches  of light grey to dark grey clayey material. The central part of Fig. 2a was  subsequently enlarged with the SEM 505 to a maxlmum of 16,000 (Fig. 3).  The platy aspect of clay minerals in the packets became visible at the maxi-  mum magnification. The maximum magnification, at which the materials in  the micrograph become vague, is dependent on the type of material and the  posslbilitms of the instrument which is used.  The micrographs in Fig. 3 also indicate that the morphology of the clay  changes at different magnlfications. Only a few strings with clay packets are  discernable in Fig. 3b but many become visible at higher magnificatlons. This  indicates that the fine-grained clay in Fig. 3b has a similar morphology if the  clay can be enlarged sufficiently. Another point is the appearance of micro-  pores m the fine-grained clays of Fig. 3b at hlgher magnifications (Fig. 3d).  This phenomenon was also found in soils where smaller pores could be  measured at higher magnifications (Jongerius and Bisdom, 1981}.    Sandstone reservoir with gas--water contact    The second sandstone reservoir, with the gas--water contact at about  3080 m, had a much smaller apparent and real porosity than the oil-impreg-  nated one. Quantlmet porosity measurements were done on sixteen micro-  graphs, vlz. twelve mmrographs from two thin sections from the gas-contain-    328    ing part of the core at 3071 m and four micrographs of one thin section  from the water-containing part of the reservoir at a depth of 3084 m. All  mlcrographs were taken in a series of four and of contiguous microareas on  the thin section (Figs. 4 and 5). Such an approach allows a contmuous mea-  surement of pores along hnear traverses.    Fig. 3. Enlargements of the clay in the central part of Fig. 2a. A few strings of clay  packets occur at low magnifications (b) and increase in number with higher magnifica-  tions (d). At a magnification of 16,000 individual clay platelets just start to appear in  the clay packets    329    is    Fig. 4. Four contiguous BESI micrographs of the gas-containing part of the second sand-  stone reservoir. Greyish to white colours represent predominantly dolomite. Individual  mineral grains are discernable. Porosity-values in text.    Fig. 5. Four contiguous BESI micrographs of the water-containing part of the second  sandstone reservoir. The grains are smaller and less rounded than in Fig 4. Porosity-values  in text.    330    The twelve micrographs of the gas-contmnmg part of the core had 9.12%  apparent porosity as a maximum, followed by a value of 5.00% and up to  2.30% as a minimum. If the same micrographs are investigated for the real  porosity the values were: 1.16%, 1.04% and 0.28% in the same order. This  left 8.04%, 3.96% and 2.02% for the clay in the pores. The clay occupied,  therefore, 87.39%, 79.20% and 87.82% of the apparent porosity. The smal-  lest real porosity does not appear in these values. It was only 0.12%.  The four micrographs from the water-containing section (Fig. 5) of the  core had apparent porosities of 1.07%, 2.24%, 3.27% and 3.13%. In the  same order the real porosities were: 0.45%, 0.69%, 1.24% and 1.46%. The  percentage of clay was: 0.62%, 1.55%, 2.03% and 1.67%. This gave 57.94%,  69.20%, 62.07% and 53.35% of the apparent porosity occupmd by clay.  The above figures indicate that the apparent porosity of the gas-containing  part of the core could be higher than that of the underlymg water-contmning  section. The real porosity in all measured rmcrographs was always smaller  than 1.79% and often even smaller than 1%. The clay occupied less volume  of the pores in the water~ontainmg part of the reservoir.  The morphology of the clay was studied at various magnifications with a  JSM-35C (Fig. 6). The clay which was studied, was present m the gas-    Fig  6. BESI enlargements of fibrous clay in pores. Differences in exposure times of  micrographs (c) and (d) give an idea of the distribution of the clay in the pore. Only a low  microporosity is left.    331    containing part of the reservoir and was fibrous. Details are most visible at  higher magnifications. It was also demonstrated that the type of detml in the  micrograph can be changed by varying the conditions under which the  micrograph is taken (Fig. 6, c and d). Such detailed information can be of im-  portance at especially the lower magnifications of 30 and X 60 used in this  porosity study. It allows some msight into the real quantity of clay present  m the pores and into the real porosities which can be expected. If necessary,  porosity analysis can also be done at larger magnifications (Jongerius and  Bisdom, 1981; Bisdom and Schoonderbeek, 1983).  Chemical elements were measured in the clay patches of the gas-contain-  ing section of the core (Fig. 7). The elements Na, Mg, A1, Si, S, CI, K and Fe  were present. These elements were interpreted to represent clay, dolomite  and halite (Fig. 7, a and b). No Fe is wsible in Fig. 7b because the scale has  been changed with respect to Fig. 7a. An EDXRA measurement of some-  what impure halite is given in Fig. 7c. The measurements are point analyses  at 10,000 magnification. This allows analysis of microareas of the clays  in the pores. In this case, the occurrence of halite could be added to the hght  microscopic observations which indicated the presence of clay and dolomite.    Fig. 7. Energy dispersive X-ray analysis of the fibrous clay in Fig. 6. Very small partmles  of dolomite and halite are associated with the fibrous clay (cf. text).    Dolomitized algal oolite reservoir    No clay was found m the examined pores of the dolomitized algal oohte.  Consequently, porosities could be measured automatically by Quantimet and  no image editing was necessary. Three micrographs are given in Fig. 8 and re-  present a linear traverse over a small part of the thin section. Anhydrite and  carbonate, deposited in pores that occupy the leached centres of ooldes,  were not measured. If necessary, however, these minerals could be included  in porosity measurements in a similar way to that done for clays. The real  porosity in the upper mmrographs was 5.24%, in the middle 6.59% and in  the lower micrograph 9.13%. This real porosity was higher than that of the  off--gas containing sandstone reservoir but lower than measured in the oil-  Impregnated sandstone reservoir.    332    333    Area and perimeter of the pores in the three reservoirs    If the area and perimeter of the pores in the three reservoirs are measured,  these data can be used to distinguish the different pores (Fig. 9). The dia-  gram in Fig. 9A indicates that the pores of the dolomitized algal oolite have  the largest perimeter and have an area whmh is somewhat comparable to that  of the oil-containing sandstone. The larger perimeter of the pores m the  carbonate reservoir is due to the inclusion of numerous small particles in the  measurements.    A (# m2/10000)  80-  A  r--t  60  mm  40  20-  0  o    ~o    4o    ~o    8o    ,60   ~o p, (.rn/~ 000)  [::30li impregnated sandstone        [] OolormtlZed algal oohte  I~ Oil ,mpre~nated sandstone  with clay in the pores    O  []    A  20-  15'  10-  5-  0    o Second sandstone reservoir       [] .~nd sandstone reservoir  -gas containing S~tlon            -water containing section  rm2/1000)     Second sandstone reservomr-gas      -P Second sandstone reservomr  containing section wbth clay in      -water containing section  pores                         with clay In pore~  B                                                                        o66    .++ "  .~:.   []    o  oO  o  o  o      1'o     ,'~    2'o    2's    3'o     ~s    4'o  Pe (urnll 0(3(3)    Fig. 9. Differences in area and perimeter measurements of pores from three reservoirs us-  mg BESI-Quantimet techniques. The first sandstone reservoir (oil-containing) and the  carbonate reservoir (A) have a much higher real porosity than the second sandstone reser-  voir (B) with the gas--water contact. A differentiation was also made for the two sand-  stone reservoirs in area and perimeter measurements of pores w,th and without clay in-  fillings.    Fig 8. Three contiguous BESI micrographs of dolomitized algal oolite. The white colour  in the leached centres of the ooides represents anhydrite and carbonate Porosity-values in  text    334    The area and perimeter diagram of the sandstone reservoir with the gas--  water contact is given in Fig. 9B. The area is much smaller than that of the  oil-contmnmg sandstone reservoir which is given in Fig. 9A. The horizontal  and vertical scale of the diagram m Fig. 9B had to be adjusted to accommo-  date all measurements; especially those of the area and perimeter of the  pores which provide the real porosity. It is clearly demonstrated that the  latter had smaller areas and perimeters than the pores which gave the total  porosity. No larger differences were found in area and perimeter measure-  ments of clay-filled pores m the gas- and water-containing sections of the  second sandstone reservoir (Fig 9B).    Form characterization of mdwldual mineral grams in sandstone reservoirs    Form analysis of individual mineral grams and pores has been described by  Bisdom and Schoonderbeek {1983). It was found during that study that  shape analysis of the slit-sized grams was done best at magmfmatlons of  240 and more. This allowed good observation of the grain boundaries on  the display screen of the Quantimet and good comparison of such images  with BESI micrographs. In this investigation, BESI were made at 60 of the  two sandstone reservoirs. The mineral grains were sufflcmntly large to dis-  tlngulsh on BESI and consequently form (shape) analysis was done.  A total of 50 mineral grams was measured: 10 in the oil-containing sand-  stone, 30 m the gas-contammg section of the second sandstone reservoir, and  10 m the water-contamyng section. No individual mineral grams were present  in the analysed part of the dolomltized algal oohte and, consequently, no  shape analysis could be done.  Form characterization of individual mineral grains is possible by using area  (A), perimeter (Pe) and the largest and smallest Feret's diameters (Fmax and  Fmm). Shape analysis is mainly based on the A/Pe2 ratio which is related to  the lobation ratio (Lr) and the indentation ratio (It) by formula and diagram  (Blsdom and Schoonderbeek, 1983) Eight shape classes were distinguished  in that study using knowledge from porosity studies and shape analyses of  mineral grains. It was also explained m the latter publication that the same  point, on the curve which relates A/Pe2 and Lr and Ir, may represent differ-  ent forms. In such cases Fmax/Fmln ratios of the grains are usually different  and can be used to distinguish forms with the same A/Pe2 ratio.  The 10 grams, which have been measured in the oil-containing sandstone  from which the oll has been removed (Fig. 2), had A/Pe2 ratios between 32  and 47. They are numbered 1 to 10 m Fig. 10. The 30 grams of the gas-  containing section of the second sandstone reservoir had A/Pe2 ratios of 31  to 57 and have numbers 11 to 40 in Fig. 10. The 10 grams of the water-  containing section of this reservoir had A/Pe2 ratios of 41 to 55 and form  the numbers 41 to 50 m Fig. 10. The minerals of the oil-containing sand-  stone reservoir were represented m shape classes IV and V; those of the gas-  containing second sandstone reservoir m shape classes III to V; and of the    335    A/Pe2  (xl 000)  B0 ii~ 20.3~2 ~3  75-  63  iv     13, 16, 2~, ~4, 3 ,  ,34s~ S~o,~ 461  40V                                                                      B, 12 ~.~..~.  ,oo         1;o          1~o          1~o          i~         i~o          16o         1~o  Lr, Ir    Fig. 10. Form characterzzatlon by Quantlmet 720 of 50 mineral grains in BESI from two  sandstone reservoirs. Area (A) and perimeter (Pe) measurements of individual grains were  plotted on a curve which relates the A/Pe2 ratios to the lobation (Lr) and the indentation  (Ir) ratios.    water~ontainmg part of the second sandstone reservoir m shape class IV. Not  all the eight shape classes mtroduced by Bisdom and Schoonderbeek (1983)  are given in Fig. 10 and the horizontal scale was modified to accommodate  all measurements from the two sandstone reservoirs. Most of the shape  measurements by Quantimet occurred in class V and have A/Pe2 ratios from  40 to 56.  The Fmax/Fmin ratios of the 50 mineral grains are presented m Fig. 11.  They have the same place as in Fig. 10. It has been explained (Bisdom and  Schoonderbeek, 1983) that if Fmax/Fmin = 2.00 and higher, this usually    A/Pe2  (x1000)  BO-  F max/F rnin  56                       J 02,1 712, 1 06   10  161 105                                     ~,  1 18, I 09-""'%~'12~ '1 5O, 1 67, 1 11, 1 22, 1 30, 1 11, 1 23, 1 54~  1o7 113 116-r"':,~'1  IV         '    '    1 54J ~',.~L1 17, 1 2B, 1 05                  ~,  114, 107~  ~)=",,~L1 09, 1 16  122,119,153J                             ,   ~'~09, 1 11   ,47," 1-~3, 1   02~  40 1 I 12~"="L,,~1 51, 1 13  1 67, 1 11 J1 33~  V  ~o            , ;o          , ?o          , '3o          , ~o          ,'so          , ~         , )o  Lr, Ir  Fig 11. The largest (Fmax) and smallest (Fmin) Feret's diameters indicated as a Fmax/  Fmin ratio for each of the 50 mineral grains. The position of the grains is the same as in  Fig. 10 (cf. text).    336    indicates elongated forms; the largest diameter of the grmn or pore being  double, or more, the size of the smallest diameter. In the present study,  no elongated forms were encountered. The largest Fmax/Fmin ratio was  1.67 and the smallest 1.00. The Fmax/Fmin ratios in Fig. 11 were indepen-  dent of the shape classes. Several of these ratios can be present m one point  on the curve, Indicating that a number of minerals with different shapes can  have the same A/Pe2 ratio.    CONCLUSIONS    The present study has demonstrated that porosity measurements can be  done m thin sections from oil--gas--water reservoir rocks by using combined  submicroscopm and Quantimet techniques. Low magnifmations were used  for practical reasons. Contiguous micrographs, at 30 and 60 magnifica-  tions, were made along linear traverses in various thm sections. Shape anal-  ysis was done of 50 mineral grains at magnifications of 60. These grains  were so large that their forms were interesting to analyse at this low magnifi-  cation. If the same measurements are done at higher magnifications, the peri-  meter will usually become larger. This will affect the A/Pe2 ratio which will  become smaller and a shift of the points will occur to the right on the curve  which shows the relation between the A/Pe2 ratios and the lobation (Lr)  and mdentation (It) ratios. This could mean that certain pomts on the curve  shift from one shape class to another.  It has been found that the porosity characteristics of the two sandstone  reservoirs and of the carbonate reservoir were rather easy to distinguish by  using area and perimeter measurements of the pores. The presence of clayey  matenal in many pores of the sandstone reservoirs caused an important prob-  lem. However, the area occupied by clay could be separated m the pore from  the area without clay. In this way an accurate measurement of the porosity  could be given. Porosity measurements of the oil-containing sandstone reser-  voir and of the carbonate reservoir were similar to the ones found by physi-  cal methods. The real porosity of the second sandstone reservoir with the  gas--water contact, however, was smaller than indicated by physical meth-  ods. This was possibly due to the high quantity of clay in the pores; measur-  able by Quantimet and visible on BESI. Consequently, the real porosity was  significantly lower than the apparent porosity. Physical measurements indi-  cated, however, that the clay in the pores formed less of a flow-barrmr than  expected from the BESI-Quantimet data.  Of importance for the study of oil-containing samples is the possibility of  being able to harden these with gamma radiation, i.e. usually 5 Mrad (50  kGy) or more, if polyester resin was used. The process is also much quicker  and the hardening can take place m one weekend. A large number of soil  samples of the Netherlands Soft Survey Institute and of the International  Soft Museum, with hardening problems, were also treated in this manner and  hardened. Consequently, it seems reasonable to assume that polyester resin-    337  hardening by gamma radiation can be an important preparation technique  from now on and also for certain core samples.    REFERENCES    Bisdom, E.B.A. and Thiel, F., 1981. Backscattered electron scanning images of porosities  in thin sections of soils, weathered rocks and oil--gas reservoir rocks using SEM-EDXRA.  In. E.B.A Bisdom (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Work-  shop of the International Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil  Materials (IWGSUSM) 1980, Wageningen  Centre for Agricultural Publishing and  Documentation (Pudoc), Wageningen, pp. 191--206.  Bisdom, E.B.A. and Schoonderbeek, D, 1983  The characterization of the shape of  mineral grains in thin sections of soils by Quantimet and BESI. Geoderma, 30: 303--  322 (this issue).  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A., Boersma, O., Jager, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1977. The func-  tion of different types of macropores during saturated flow through four swelling soil  horizons. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41(5). 945--950.  Bouma, J., Jongerius, A. and Schoonderbeek, D., 1979. Calculation of saturated hydraul-  ic conductivity of some pedal clay soils using micromorphometric data. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. J., 43 (2): 261--264.  Ismall, S N.A, 1975. Micromorphometric soil-porosity characterization by means o;  electro-optical image analysis (Quantimet 720) Neth. Soil Surv. Inst., Wageningen,  Soil Surv. Pap., 9' 104 pp.  Jongerius, A., 1974 Recent developments in soil micromorphology. In: G.K. Rutherford  (Editor), Soil Microscopy. Proceedings of the 4th International Working-Meeting  on Soil Micromorphology, Kingston, 1973 The Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont, pp  67--83.  Jongerius, A. and Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981 Porosity measurements using the Quantimet 720  on backscattered electron scanning images of thin sections of soils. In: E.B.A. Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Interna-  tional Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp. 207--216.  Jongerius, A. and Heintzberger, G., 1975. Methods in soil micromorphology. A technique  for the preparation of large thin sections. Neth. Soil Survey Inst., Wageningen, Soil.  Surv. Pap., 10:48 pp.  Jongerius, A., Schoonderbeek, D and Jager, A., 1972. The application of the Quantimet  720 in soil micromorphology. The Microscope, 20: 243--254.  Murphy, C.P., Bullock, P. and Turner, R.H., 1977. The measurement and characterisation  of voids in soil thin sections by image analysis, Part I. Principles and techniques. J. Soil  Sci , 28 (3): 498--508.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         AbstractSubmicroscopic and image analyzer techniques have been applied for the measurement of the porosities of oil—gas—water reservoir rocks from thin sections. Backscattered electron scanning images (BESI) were made predominantly at low magnifications of × 30 and × 60. Porosity data from linear traverses were obtained and differences in porosities between two sandstone reservoirs and a carbonate reservoir were determined. A large number of the measured pores contained clayey material. The surface occupied by this material was subtracted from the apparent porosity measurements with the image editor of the Quantimet 720 to give the real porosity.A sample from one of two sandstone reservoirs contained oil and could not be hardened using the common procedure for impregnation of the sample by a polyester resin. Gamma radiation was applied and hardening occurred in one weekend after 5 Mrad (50 kGy) had been absorbed. Hardening of this sample gave no problems, if the oil had been removed by monostyrene before a start was made with the impregnation process; such a sample was used for the present porosity study.Form analysis was done of individual mineral grains using BESI and Quantimet. The grains were represented in a number of shape classes of a diagram used for shape classification. Form-separation of individual minerals was also possible.