 Geoderma, 27 (1982) 357--375                                                     357  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Abdou, F. M.; Hanna, F. S.; Rabie, F.; et al. Mineralogical studies on some gley soils in the northern  part of the Nile Delta: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 29-43, illus. (incl. plates, sketch map), 1980.  Abtahi, A.; Eswaran, H.; Stoops, G.; et al. Mineralogy of a soil sequence formed under the influence  of saline and alkaline conditions in the Sarvestan Basin (Iran): Pedologie, Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 283-304  (incl. Flemish, French sum.), illus. (incl. 9 tables), 1980.  Adams, J. A.; and Wilde, R. H. Comparison of the variability in a soil taxonomic unit with that of the  associated soil mapping unit: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 285-297, 7 tables,  1980.  AI-Gailani, M. B.  Geochemical identification of unconformities using semi-quantitative X-ray  fluorescence analysis: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, Vol. 50, No. 4, p. 1261-1270, illus. (incl. sketch  maps), 1980.  AI-Ghabsha, T. S.; Bogdanski, S. L; and Townshend, Alan. Molecular emission cavity analysis; Part  18, Determination of soluble sulphate in waters, soil, dusts and other samples: Anal. Chim. Acta, Vol.  120, p. 383-387, tables, 1980.  Albertsen, Manfred; and Matthess, Genrg.  Verhalten relevanter Radioisotope in drei typischen  Sandboeden des Norddeutschen Flachlandes [Behavior of radioisotopes in three typical sandy soils of  the North German Plain]: Meyniana, Vol. 32, p. 7-72 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps,  tables), 1980.  Alian, A.; and Sansoni, B.  Instrumental neutron activation analysis of geological and pedological  samples; further investiagation of epithermal neutron activation analysis using monostandard method:  J. Radioanal. Chem., Vol. 59, No. 2, p. 511-543, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Allen, R. H.; and Sturdy, R. G. Soils in Essex III; Sheet TLTI (Little Waltham): Soil Surv. Rec., No.  62, 172 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps; soils map 1:25,000), 1980.  Anonymous.  Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils:  Sept. 1979, United Kingdom. J.  Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, 129 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates), 1980.  Archer, Warren M. Soil survey of Diamond Valley area, parts of Eureka, Elko, and White Pine counties,  Nevada: 122 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv.; U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur. Land Manage., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ.  in coop. with Univ. Nev., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Armstrong, A. C. Soils and slopes in a humid temperate environment; a simulation study: Catena, Vol.  7, No. 4, p. 327-338, illus. (incl. block diags.), 1980.  Avery, B.W. Soil classification for England and Wales: G. B., Soil Surv., Tech. Monogr., No. 14, 67  p., illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Awad, F.; and Mikhaei, M. L A contribution to the boron content in some selected soils of Egypt:  Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 89-97, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Badov, V. V.; and Kiselev, A.A. Identifikatsiya parametrov vlagoperenosa [Parameter identification of  moisture transport]: Razved. Okhr. Nedr, No. 8, p. 40-45, illus., 1980.  Bain, D. C.; and Russell, J.D. Swelling minerals in a basalt and its weathering products from Morvern,  Scotland; I, Interstratified montmorillonite-vermiculite-illite: Clay Miner., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 445-451  (incl. French, German, Spanish sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1980.    358    Banerji, P. K. (convener). Lateritization processes: mReport of the International Geologic Correlation  Programme (IGCP) (Anonymous), Geol. Correl., No. 8, p. 159-163, 1980.  Barmore, Russel L. Soil survey of Yuma-Wellton area, parts of Yuma County, Arizona, and Imperial  County, California: 104 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:633,360), U. S.  Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Agrig. Agric.  Exp. Stn.; Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Bartels, Gerhard; and Steinmann, Solveig. Quartaergeomorphologische Untersuchungen im Nordteil  der "Tunesischen Dorsale" [Quaternary geomorphologic investigations in northern Tunisia]: Catena,  Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 383-405 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Bartoli, Francois; Monrozier, Lucile Joctenr; and Rapaire, Jean-Louis. Sur la stabilisation des matieres  organiques azotees par les mineraux silico-alumineux dans les podzols; phytolithes et argiles  [Stabilization of nitrogenous organic matter by silico-aluminous minerals in Podzols; phytoliths and  clays]: Acad. Sci. (Paris), C. R., Ser. D, Vol. 291, No. 2, p. 183-186 (incl. English sum.), tables, plate,  1980.  Bashyal, R. P. Gondwana type of formation with phosphatic rocks in Southeast Nepal: Geol. Soc.  India, J., Vol. 21, No. 10, p. 484-491, illus. (incl. tables, sects., geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Beek, K. J.  From soil survey interpretation to land evaluation:  in Land reclamation and water  management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the occasion  of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulzc, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land Reclam. Improv., Publ., No.  27, p. 29-42, illus. (incl. tables, chart), 1980.  Beek, K. J.; Blakhais, W. A.; Driessen, P. M.; et al. Problem soils; their reclamation and management:  in Land reclamation and water management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of  articles published at the occasion of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst.  Land Reclam. Improv., Publ., No. 27, p. 43-72, tables, sketch maps, 1980.  Beinroth, F. H.; Uehara, G.; Silva, J. A.; et al. Agrotechnology transfer in the tropics based on soil  taxonomy: Advances in Agronomy, Vol. 33, p. 303-339, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Beriault, John G. The natural features and prehistory of Marco Island, Florida: in Water, oil, and the  geology of Collier, Lee and Hendry counties (Gleason, Patrick J., editor), p. 10-14, illus., Miami Geol.  Soc., Miami, FL, United States, 1980.  Birkenhauer, JoseL Rezente Bodenerosion und periglaziale Vorgaenge (Ein Beitrag zum oekologischen  Verstaendnis aufgrund geomorphotogischer Zusammenhaenge und zum Stand de Forschung in den  deutschcn Mittelgebirgen [Recent soil erosion and perigtacial processes; contribution to an ecological  understanding based on geomorphological relations and state of research in German central mountains]:  Geogr. Rundsch., Vol. 32, No. l 1, p. 488-496, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Blackburn, G.; and Hutton, J. T. Soil conditions and the occurrence of salt damp in buildings of  metropolitan Adelaide: Australian Geographer, Vol. 14, No. 6, p. 360-365, illus. (incl. 5 sketch maps),  1980.  Boels, D.  Effects of soil deformation in trenchless drain laying:  Wagcningen, Inst. Cultuurtech,  Waterhuishouding, Tech. Bull., No. 117, p. 154-159, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1980.  Boerngen, Josephine G.; and Shnddette, Hansford T. Chemical analyses of soils and other surficial  materials of the conterminous United States: Open-File Report (United States GeologicalSurvey. 1978),  No. 81-0197, 145 p., tables, 1981. availablefrorn:U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib.  Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Bogatyrev, B. A. Trias-yurskiye kory vyvetrivaniya i boksity yuga Sredney Azii i Severnogo Kavkaza  [The Triassic-Jurassic weathering crusts and bauxites in southern Central Asia and the Northern  Caucasus]:  199 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sects, geol. sketch maps), lzd. Nauka, Moscow, Union of  Soviet Socialist Republics, 1980.  Bollinne, A.; Pissart, A.; Bastin, B.; et al. Etude d'une depression fermee pres de Gembloux; vitesse  de l'erosion des terres cultivces de Hesbaye [Study on an enclosed depression near Gembloux; rate of  erosion of cultivated land in Hesbaye]: Soc. Geol. Belg., Ann., Vol. 103, p. 143-152 (incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. sects., sketch map), 1980.  Borchardt, Glenn; Taylor, Gary; and Rice, Salem. Fault features in soils of the Mehrten Formation,  Auburn Damsite, California: Special Report - California Division of Mines and Geology, No. 141, 45  p., illus. (incl. tables, sects., sketch maps), 1980.    359    Bosmans, H.; and Paenhuys, J. The distribution of heavy metals in the soils of the Kempen: Pedologie,  Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 191-223 (incl. Flemish, French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Bottema, Sytze. Palynological investigations on Crete: Rev. Palaeobot. Palynol., VoL 31, No. 1-2, p.  193-217, tables, charts, sketch maps, 1980.  Bouma, J.; and De Laat, P. J.M. Estimation of the moisture supply capacity of some swelling clay soils  in the Netherlands: J. Hydrol., VoL 49, No. 3-4, p. 247-259, 1981.  Bouma, J.; Van Hoorn, J. W.; and Stoffelsen, G. H.  Measuring the hydraulic conductivity of soil  adjacent to tile drains in a heavy clay soil in the Netherlands: J. Hydrol., Vol. 50, No. 1-4, p. 371-381,  1981.  Bourgeat, F.; Balas, B.; and Revel, J. C.  Influence de la morphogenese et de la pedogenese sur  l'opposition des versants en moyenne montagne; etude de la vallee de la Ballongue (Pyrenees ariegeoises)  [Influence of morphogenesis and pedogenesis on opposite slopes in median mountains; study of the  Ballongue Valley; Ariege Pyrenees]:  Rev. Geomorphol. Dyn., Vol. 29, No. 2, p. 65-78 (incl. English  sum.), 2 tables, 1980.  Bradley, R. I. Soils in Dyfed V; Sheet SN 24 (Llechryd): Soil Surv. Rec., No. 63, 89 p. (incl. Welsh  sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils map 1:25,000), 1980.  Brewster, Gordon Ross. Effect of chemical pretreatment on X-ray powder diffraction characteristics of  clay minerals derived from volcanic ash: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 28, No. 4, p. 303-310 (incl.  Russian, German, French sum.), illus., 1980.  Bridges, E. M.; and Burnham, C. P. Soils of the State of Bahrain: J. Soil Sci., Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 689-  707, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Brunnacker, K. Young Pleistocene loess as an indicator for the climate in the Mediterranean area:  in  Sahara and surrounding seas; sediments and climatic changes; proceedings of an international symposium  (Sarnthein, M., editor; et al.), Palaeoecol. Aft., Vol. 12, p. 99-113, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  Brzezniak, Eligiusz; Klimek, Kazimierz; Kowalkowski, Alojzy; et al. Vertical zonality in the southern  Khangai Mountains (Mongolia); result of the Polish-Mongolian physico-geographical expedition, Vol. l:  Prace Geograficzne (PAN Instytut Geografii), No. 136, 107 p. (incl. Russian sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  plates), 1980.  Brzezniak, Eligiusz; Kowalkowski, Alojzy; Niedzwiedz, Tadeusz; et al. Environment of the Sant Valley  (southern Khangai Mountains); results of the Polish-Mongolian physico-geographical expedition, Vol. II:  Prace Geograficzne (PAN instytut Geografii), No. 137, 87 p. (incl. Russian sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1980.  Buchanan, R. A.  The Lambert Peninsula, Ku-ring-gai Chase National Park; physiography and the  distribution of podzols, shrublands and swamps with details of the swamp vegetation and sediments:  Proceedings of the Linnean Society of New South Wales, Vol. 104, Parts 1-2, p. 73-94, illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1980.  Bullock, P.; and Murphy, C. P. Towards the quantification of soil structure:  in Symposium on the  Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 317-328, illus., 1980.  Buol, S. W.; Hole, F. D.; and McCracken, R.J. Soil genesis and classification, 2nd edition: 404 p.,  illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Iowa State Univ. Press, Ames, IA, United States, 1980.  Buresh, R. J.; Casselman, M. E.; and Patrick, W. H., Jr. Nitrogen fixation in flooded soil systems, a  review: Advances in Agronomy, Vol. 33, p. 149-192, tables, 1980.  Burnham, C. P.; Avery, B. W.; Findlay, D. C.; et al. The soils of England and Wales: Field Stud. (Lond.),  Vol. 5, No. 2, p. 349-363, illus. (incl. sects.), 1980.  Buselli, G. The application ofSirotem in weathered terrain: Bulletin - Australian Society of Exploration  Geophysicists, Vol. 11, No. 3, p. 99-109, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Buurman, P.  Palaeosols in the Reading Beds (Paleocene) of Alum Bay, Isle of Wight, U.K.:  Sedimentology, Vol. 27, No. 5, p. 593-606, illus., 1980.  Cabrera, J. G.; and Eddleston, M.  Chemical and mineralogical transformations in red tropical soil  profiles from N.E. Brazil [abstr.]: inAninternationalsymposiumonmetallogenyofmaficandultramafic  complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic  environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 18, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep.  Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.    360    Calaplkalu, F.; and Pifltdn, G. Contribution to the metallogenic study of the Galdag (Manisa-Turkey)  nickeliferrous mineralization [abstr.]:  in An international symposium on metallogeny of mafic and  ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with similar  metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 19, UNESCO, Natl. Tech.  Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Carr, R. G.; Rodgars, K. A.; and Black, P. M. The chemical and mineralogical changes accompanying  the laterization of basalt at Kerikeri, North Auckland: R. Soc. N. Z., J., Vol. 10, No. 3, p. 247-258, illus.  (incl. 4 tables, geol. sketch map), 1980.  Carroll, D. M.  The soils of Mid-Northumberland:  in The properties of upland soils and their  implications for agriculture and forestry (Horning, M., chairperson), North Engl., Soils Discuss. Group,  Proc., No. 15, p. I-7, sketch map, 1980.  Proceedings of the North of England Soils lh'scussion Group.  C~thcm't, James B. World phosphate reserves and resources: in Proceedings of The role of phosphorus  in agriculture (Khasawneh, F. E., chairperson; et al.), p. 1-8, illus. (incl. 4 tables), Am. Soc. Agron.,  Madison, WI, United States, 1980.  then Shiek Pei; and Unya, Alexander. Evaluation of the Bukit Punda iron deposit: Malays., Geol.  Sure., Annu. Rep., Vol. 1978, p. 277-287, illus. (incl. table; geol. maps 1:21120), 1980.  Chernyakhovskiy, A. G. Klimaticheskaya zonal'nost' elyuvial'nogo protsessa [Climatic zonation of the  eluvial process]: in Protessy kontinentarnogo litogeneza (Shantser, Ye. V., editor), Akad. Nauk SSSR,  Geol. Inst., Tr., No. 350, p. 28-59, illus. (incl. charts and sketch map), 1980.  Chittlelmrough, D. J.; and Oadns, J. M. The development of a red-brown earth; If, Uniformity of the  parent material: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 4, p. 375-382, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Chittleborou~h, D. J.; and Oades, J. M. The development of a red-brown earth; III, The degree of  weathering and translocation of clay: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 4, p. 383-393,  illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Cllne, Marlin G. Experience with soil taxonomy of the United States: Advances in Agronomy, Vol.  33, p. 193-226, tables, 1980.  Clower, Dennis F. Soil survey of Brown and Mills counties, Texas: 170 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Colman, S. M.; sad Pierce, K. L. Weathering rinds on andesitic and basaltic stones as a Quaternary  age indicator, western United States: Geological Survey Professional Paper (Washington, D.C.), No.  1210, 56 p., 1981.  Coppens, Rene; Gnlllet, Bernhard; Jsegy, Robert;, et al. Nancy natural radiocarbon measurements VI:  Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No. 4, p. 1064-1072, 1980.  Cowie, J.D. Slsfrandesitictephraandtheirvariability'Tgatapu'KingdTga: Australian  Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 273-284, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Cowle, J. D. The M.A.F.F. hills and uplands survey; an approach to the classification of agricultural  land in hill and upland areas of England and Wales:  in The properties of upland soils and their  implications for agriculture and forestry (Horning, M., chairperson), North Engl., Soils Discuss. Group,  Proc., No. 15, p. 65-74, tables, sketch map, 1980. Proceedings of the North of England Soils Discussion  Group.  Crock, J. G.; and Seversou, R.C. Four reference soil and rock samples for measuring element availability  in the Western energy regions: Geological Survey Circular (Washington, D. C.), No. 0841, 16 p., 1980  [1981].  Czarnecki, J.; Voeikle, H.; and Geerliclk, W. Environmental radioactivity measurements in Switzerland:  in Traceability and quality control in the measurement of environmental activity; seminar sponsored by  the International Committee for Rudlonuclide Metrology (Hutchinson, J. M. R., editor; et aL), Environ.  Int., Vol. 3, No. 5, p. 401-407, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Datta, P. S.; Gupta, S. K.; lind Sharma, S, C. A conceptual model of water transport through unsaturated  soil zone: Mausam, Vol. 31, No. 1, p. 9-18, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Davies, Keitl~ C. Heulandite deposition in fossil reptile bones from the Karroo of Zambia: Journal of  Paleontology, VoL 55, No. 1, p. 47-61, plates, sketch maps, 1981.    361    Davin, Jewel E. (compiler).  Publications by Soil Bureau staff, 1930-1979; listed alphabetically by  author: N. Z. Soil Bur. Bibliogr. Rep., No. 25, 186 p., 1980.  Davin, Jewel E. (compiler). Publications by Soil Bureau staff, 1975-1979; titles: N.Z. Soil Bur. Bibliogr.  Rep., No. 24, 114 p., 1980.  Davis, Philip Thompson. Late Holocene glacial, vegetational, and climatic history of Pangnirtung and  Kingnait Fiord area, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada: 378 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Colorado, Boulder  CO. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  de Gans, W.  Outlines of the late Quaternary history of the Drentsche Aa Valley (Drente, The  Netherlands): Geol. Mijnb., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 353-362, illus. (incl. sects., sketch map), 1980.  de Ridder, N. A.  Groundwater resources management research:  in Land reclamation and water  management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the occasion  of 1LRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land Reclam. Improv., Publ., No.  27, p. 73-84, illus. (incl. sects.), 1980.  de Wolf, J.  Rice cultivation and water control:  in Land reclamation and water management;  developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the occasion of ILRI's silver  jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. lnst. Land Reclam. lmprov., Publ., No. 27, p. 113-  124, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1980.  DeAngelis, Robert. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Hockley and Lamb counties, Texas: Open-File Report  (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0168, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980. available  from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Rocky Mt. Mapp. Cent., Denver, CO, United States.  Deleeour, F. Essai de classification pratique des humus [Practical classification of humus]: Pedologie,  Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 225-241 (incl. English, Flemish sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1980.  Doerr, Helmot; and ioennich, K. O. Carbon-14 and carbon-13 in soil CO2:  in Proceedings of the  Tenth international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et aL), Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No.  3, p. 90%918, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Dollarhide, William E.; and Staidl, George J. Soil survey of Tuscarora Mountain area, Nevada; parts  of Elko, Eureka, and Lander counties: 462 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map  1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop.  with Univ. New Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Doornkamp, J. C.; Brunsden, D.; and Jones, D. K. C. (editors). Geology, geomorphology and pedology  of Bahrain:  443 p., illus. (incl. tables, sects., plates, geol. sketch maps; colored geomorphol, maps  1:50,000), Geo. Abst., Norwick, United Kingdom, 1980.  Douglas, I.  Climatic geomorphology; present-day processes and landform evolution; problems of  interpretation: in Perspectives in geomorphology; papers from the First British-German symposium on  geomorphology (Hagedorn, Horst, editor; et aL), Z. Geomorphol., Supplementband, Vol. 36, p. 27-47  (incl. German, French sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Driessen, James L. Soil survey of Sanborn County, South Dakota: 191 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map I:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Dueloux, J.  Nickeliferous phyllosilicate as a weathering product of ultramafic rocks [abstr.]:  in An  international symposium on metallogeny of mafic and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-  western Asia area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis,  S. S., chairperson), p. 31, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece,  1980.  Duysings, Sjef; and Vis, Rinus. Statistisch onderzoek naar de relatie tussen bodem en vegetatie in een  heideterrein bij Loenen [A statistical investigation of the relationship between soils and vegetation in a  moor near Loenen]: Interne Rapp. Fys: Geogr. Bodemkd. Lab., Univ. Amst., No..9, 36 p., illus. (incl.  sketch maps, 12 tables), 1980.  Edmonds, T. E.; Pu Guogang; and West, T. S. The differential pulse anodic stripping voltammetry of  copper and lead and their determination in EDTA extracts of soils with the mercury film glassy carbon  electrode: Anal. Chim. Acta, Vol. 120, p. 41-53, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  El-Attar, H.; EI-Sokkary, 1. H.; and Badr El-Din, A. G. Some effects of alkalinity and organic matter  in soil formation: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 83-88, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.    362    Eldridge, D.J. Soils in Norfolk V; sheet TG 11 (Attlebridge): Soil Surv. Rec., No. 64, 161 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sects., sketch maps), 1980.  Ellis, Stephen. Physical and chemical characteristics of a podzolic soil formed in neoglacial till,  Okstindan, northern Norway: Arctic and Alpine Research, Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 65-72, 2 tables, sketch  maps, 1980.  Ellis, Stephen. Soil-environmental relationships in the Okstindan Mountains, North Norway: Nor.  Geogr. Tidsskr., Vol. 34, No. 4, p. 167-176, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  Elwan, A. A.; Harga, A. A.; Abd El l~ahm~l, S. M. H4 et al. Genesis and uniformity of soil terraces  on both sides of Nile Delta: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 99-110, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map),  1980.  Faqfindola, Carlos R.; Galhego, Heleio R.; and Gareia, G.J. Pedogenese na regiao de Conchas-Anhembi  (SP) [Pedogenesis in the Conchas-Anhembi region, Sao Paulo]: Notic. Geomorfol., Vol. 20, No. 39/40.  p. 35-48 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1980.  Eswaran, H.; Stoops, G.; and Abtahi, A. SEM morphologies of halite (NaCI) in soils: in Symposium  on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 343-352, illus., 1980.  Everitt, Benjamin L. Vegetation and sediment migration in the Henry Mountains region, Utah:  in  Henry Mountains symposium (Picard, M. Dane, editor), Utah Geological Association Publication, No.  8, p. 209-215, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Everitt, Benjamin L. Vegetation of the northern Henry Mountains region, Utah: in Henry Mountains  symposium (Picard, M. Dane, editor), Utah Geological Association Publication, No. 8, p. 216-218, 1980.  Fabriee, Colin; Gerard, Bocquier; Patron, Claude; et aL Nickel and chrome concentrations by chemical  weathering of pyroxenes and olivines under latefitic conditions [abstr.]: in An international symposium  on metallogeny of marie and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and  its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p.  25, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Farmer, V. C.; Russell, J. D.; and Barrow, M. L. lmogolite and proto-imogolite allophane in spodic  horizons; evidence for a mobile aluminium silicate complex in podzol formation: J. Soil Sci., Vol. 31,  No. 4, p. 673-684, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Feddes, R. A.; Wind, G. P.; and van Wijk, A. L.M. Soil-plant-atmosphere systems: Wageningen, Inst.  Cultuurtech. Waterhuishouding, Tech. BulL, No. 117, p. 84-114, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1980.  Fltze, Peter. Zur Bodenentwicklung auf Moraenen in den Alpen [Soil evolution on moraines in the  Alps]: Geogr. Helv., Vol. 35, No. 3, p. 97-106, 1980.  Fodor-Csanyi, Piroaka; Takala, Stina; Alhonen-Hoallisto, Leena; et al. Penetration and distribution of  tritiated water in soils of a lysimeter: Nord. Hydrol., Vol. 11, No. 3/4, p. 169-186, illus. (incl. tables),  1980.  Folque, Jose. Liquefaccao de solos arenosos [Liquefaction of sandy soils]:  Geotecnia (Soc. Port.  Geotecnia), No. 29, p. 3-22 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Fox, Richard W. Soil survey of Bowie County, Texas: 128 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch maps;  soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Fraenzle, Otto; glllthw.h, Wiadh'ied F,; IngealmSS, Aatje; et al. Die Klassifizierung yon Bodenprofilen  als Grundlage agrarer Standortplanung in Entwicklongslaendern; ein Beispiel aus dem Savannengehiet  Nordost-Ghanas [The classification of soil profiles as a basis for agricultural planning; an example from  the savannah region of northeastern Ghana]: Catena, Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 353-381 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. table), 1980.  Fredriekson, David W. Soil mottling and groundwater monitoring:  Individual Onsite Wastewater  Systems, No. 6, p. 97-107, illus., 1980.  Frledmman, E. Imre.  Endolithic microbial life in hot and cold deserts:  in Completion of papers  presented at the Fourth CoUege Park colloquium on chemical evolution; Limits of life (Ponnamperuma,  Cyril, editor), Origins Life, Vol. 10, No. 3, p. 223-235, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Friedrieh, G.; Brtmemmm, H. G.; Wileke, J.; etaL Chrome-spinels in lateritic soils and ultramafic source  rocks, Acoje Mine, Zambales, Philippines [abstr.]:  in An international symposium on metallogeny of    363    mafic and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with  similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 39, UNESCO, Natl.  Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Furbush, Clarence E.; Koepke, Byron E.; and Sehoephorster, Dale B. Soil survey of Totchaket area,  Alaska: 68 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Alaska Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Galhego, Helcio R.; and Espindola, Carlos R. Ocorrencias de sotne-lines em solos e mantos de alteracao  [The occurrence of stone lines in soils and alteration mantles]: Notic. Geomorfol., Vol. 20, No. 39/40,  p. 87-91 (incl. English sum.), 1980.  Garner, Bill A.; Cox, John B.; Vodrazka, Frank M.; et al. Soil survey of Logan County, Arkansas: 100  p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps l:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Arkansas Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Gust, H.; Froehlich, K.; and Stolz, W. Geophysikalisch-montanwissenschaftliche Anwendungen der  Radonexhalation des Bodens [Geophysical-mining applications of radon exhalations from the soil]:  in  Rundtischgespraech    Geophysikalische    Untersuchungsmoeglichkeiten    in    Gebieten    mit  Senkungsgeschehenin Round table conference on Geophysical survey possibilities in regions with  subsidence activities (Anonymous), Neue Bergbautech., Vol. 10, No. 11, p. 640-643, illus., 1 table, 1980.  Gut, J.R. The relationship between surface and subsurface waters; water quality aspects in areas of low  precipitation: Hydrol. Sci. Bull. (Int. Assoc. Hydrol. Sci.), Vol. 25, No. 3, p. 257-267 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. table, sect.), 1980.  Ghabru, S. K.; and Sudhansu, K. Ghosh. Morphology, genesis and classification of two soil profiles from  the Dhauladhar Range of middle Siwaliks: Indian Soc. Soil Sci., J., Vol. 28, No. 2, p. 154-161, tables,  1980.  Gilet-Blein, Nieole; Marien, Gerard; and Evin, Jacques. Unreliability of C- 14 dates from organic matter  of soils: in Proceedings of the Tenth international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et al.),  Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No. 3, p. 919-929, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Gill, Hiram V.; Laranee, Fred C.; and Fortner, Thomas W. Soil survey of Jefferson and Lincoln counties,  Arkansas:  107 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Arkansas Agric.  Exp. Stn.).  Gillott, J. E.  Use of the scanning electron microscope and Fourier methods in characterization of  microfabric and texture of sediments: in Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous),  J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 261-277, illus. (incl. plates), 1980.  Godfrey, Andrew E. Porphyry weathering in a desert climate: in Henry Mountains symposium (Picard,  M. Dane, editor), Utah Geological Association Publication, No. 8, p. 189-196, illus., 1980.  Great Britain, Soil Survey of England and Wales, Ordnance Survey. Llechryd: in the collection Soil,  No. SN 24, 1 sheet, colored soils map, Soil Surv. Engl. and Wales, Ord. Surv., United Kingdom, 1980.  Great Britain, Soil Survey of England and Wales, Ordnance Survey. Attlebridge: in the collection Land  use capability, No. TG 11, 1 sheet, colored soils map 1:25,000, Soil Surv. Engl. and Wales, Ord. Surv.,  United Kingdom, 1980.  Great Britain, Soil Survey of England and Wales, Ordnance Survey. Attlebridge: in the collection Soil,  No. TG 11, 1 sheet, colored soils map 1:25,000, Soil Surv. Engl. and Wales, Ord. Surv., United Kingdom,  1980.  Great Britain, Soil Survey of England and Wales, Ordnance Survey. Little Waltham: in the collection  Land use capability, No. TL 71, 1 sheet, colored land use map 1:25,000, Soil Surv. Engl. and Wales, Ord.  Surv., United Kingdom, 1980.  Greenwood, E. A. N.; Beresford, J. D~; and Battle, J.R. Evaporation from vegetation in landscapes  developing secondary salinity using the ventilated-chamber technique; III, Evaporation from a Pinus  radiata tree and the surrounding pasture in an agroforestry plantation: J. Hydrol., Vol. 50, No. 1-4, p.  155-166, 1981.  Groner, Urs; and Suter, Juerg.  Profil Jenatsch-Huette; eine pollenanalytisch-sedimentologische  untersuchung in der Val Bever (Engadin) [Jenatsch Hut profile; a pollen analytical-sedimentological  study in Val Bever; Engadin]: Geogr. Helv., Vol. 35, No. 3, p. 113-121, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.    364    Gruas-Cavagnetto, C.; Lauraln, M.; and Meyer, R. Un sol de mangrove fossilise dans les lignites du  Soissonnais (Ypresien) a Verzenay (Marne) [A soil of fossilized mangrove in the "Lignites du  Soissonnais" (Ypresian) at Verzenay; Marne]:  Geobios; Paleontol., Stratigr., Paleoecol., No. 13,  fascicule 5, p. 795 (incl. English sum.), strut, col., table, sect., Schem. anal., 1980.  Gureghian, A. B. A two-dimensional finite-element solution scheme for the saturated-unsaturated flow  with applications to flow through ditch-drained soils: J. Hydrol., Vol. 50, No. 1-4, p. 333-353, 1981.  Hale, Allan M. Reclamation in the Eastern U.S.; planning and coordination provide solutions to the  problems: Engineering Bulletin (Los Angeles), No. 52, p. 33-40, illus., 1980.  Hansel, Michael J. Two onsite options for problem soils: Individual Onsite Wastewater Systems, No.  6, p. 109-132, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Hanzawa, Hideo; Matsuda, FAichi; Suzuki, Kazayaki; et al. Stability analysis and field behaviour of  earth fills on an alluvial marine clay: Soils Found.(Tokyo), Vol. 20, No. 4, p. 37-51, illus. (incl. table),  1980.  Hassanein, H. G.; EI-Bagouri, I. H.; and Yousry, M. Evaluating of chemical extractants for determining  the availability of iron, manganese, zinc and copper in different soils: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vot. 20, No  2, p. 151-157 (incl. Arabic sum.), tables, 1980.  Hatton, Denise; and Pickerins, William F. The effect of pH on the retention of Cu, Pb, Zn and Cd by  clay-humic acid mixtures: Water, Air, Soil Pollut., Vol. 14, p. 13-21, illus., 1980.  Heikkinen, Olavi; and Fogelberg, Paul. Bodenentwicklung im Hochgebirge; ein Beispiel yore Vorfeld  des Steingletschers in der Schweiz [Soil development in high mountains; example of the Steingletscher  foreland in Switzerland]: Geogr. Helv., Vol. 35, No. 3, p. 107-I 12 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch  map), 1980.  Henry, Christopher D.; and Kapadia, Rajesh R. Trace elements in soils of the South Texas uranium  district; concentrations, origin, and environmental significance:  Report of Investigations - Texas,  University, Bureau of Economic Geology, No. 101, 52 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Hession, Paul; and Bruce, W. D. Geologic et teledetection; un mariage reussi [Geology and remote  sensing; a successful marriage]: Geos (Ottawa), Fall, p. 10-12 (incl. English sum.), illus., 1980.  Hillel, Daniel. Fundamentals of soil physics: 413 p., illus., Acad. Press, New York, United States, 1980  Hillel, Daniel. Applications of soil physics:  385 p., illus. (incl. tables), Acad. Press, New York, NY,  United States, 1980.  Hinrichs, G.; Johannes, D.; and Krause, H. Rechnergesteuerte Kartendarstellung am Beispiel der  regionalen Verteilung von Elementgehalten in veraschten Pflanzenproben aus dem nordwestlichen Harz  und dem angrenzenden Harzvorland [Computer-drawn maps of the regional distribution of element  concentrations in plant ashes from the northwestern Harz and adjacent foreland]: Erzmetall, Vol. 33.  No. 11, p. 536-540 (incl. English sum.), sketch maps, 1980.  Hinze, E.; and Will, G. Diffusion and decomposition in the pressure gradient of a diamond anvil  squeezer: Neues Jahrb. Mineral., Monatsh., No. 1 t, p. 481-497, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Hocks,  J.  Transport  and  interaction  processes  in  soil:   Wageningen,  Inst.  Cultuurtech.  Waterhuishouding, Tech. Bull., No. 117, p. 115-120, illus. (incl. 2 chem. anals., 1 table), 1980.  Hooley, A. D.; Southern, Wendy; and Kershaw, A.P. Holocene vegetation and environments of Sperm  Whale Head, Victoria, Australia: J. Biogeogr., Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 349-362, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps),  1980.  Horning, M. (chairperson). The properties of upland soils and their implications for agriculture and  forestry: 1978, United Kingdom. North Engl., Soils Discuss. Group, Proc., No. 15, 82 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Hosteler, William D. Soil survey of Clinton County, Indiana:  141 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour., Soil Water Conserv. Comm.; Purdue  Univ., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Howard, J. A.; and Mitchell, C.W. Phyto-geomorphic class:- -ation of the landscape: Geoforum, Vol.  11, No. 2, p. 85-106, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980    365    Hromadka, T. V., II; and Guymon, G. L. A note on time integration of unsaturated soil-moisture  transport: Adv. Water Resour., Vol. 3, No. 4, p. 181-186, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Ivanov, V. D. Metod rascheta intensivnosti poverkhnostnogo smyva s pakhotnykh sklonov v TsChO  [A measurement technique for sheet erosion intensity for arable slopes in the central chernozem region]:  Geomorfologiya, No. 4, p. 61-66 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Janiec, Bronislaw.  Przystosowanie wzoru doroszewskiego do badan denudacji chemicznej na  przykladzie wod drenujacych weglanowe zbiorniki Wyzyny Lubelskiej [Adjusting the Doroszewski  formula to studies on chemical denudation, for example, the waters draining the carbonate reservoirs of  the Lublin Upland]: Przegl. Geol., Vol. 28, No. 8(328), p. 457-459 (incl. Russian, English sum.), table,  1980.  Johnson, R. A.; and Stipp, d.d. University of Miami radiocarbon dates XVIII: Radiocarbon, Vol. 22,  No. 4, p. 1116-1124, 1980.  Johnson, Robert.  Irrigated cropland, 1978, Cheyenne and Sherman counties, Kansas:  Open-File  Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0640, 1 sheet, land use map h250,000, 1980.  available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Mid-Continent Mapp. Cent., Rolla, MO, United States.  Johnson, Robert. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Chase, Dundy, and Perkins counties, Nebraska: Open-File  Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0641, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980.  available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Mid-Continent Mapp. Cent., Rolla, MO, United States.  Johnson, Thomas. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Laramie County, Wyoming: Open-File Report (United  States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0638, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980. available from: U.  S. Geol. Surv., Rocky Mt. Mapp. Cent., Denver, CO, United States.  Johnson, Thomas. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Kit Carson, Phillips, and Yuma counties, Colorado: Open-  File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0639, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980.  available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Rocky Mt. Mapp. Cent., Denver, CO, United States.  Jonea, Edmund. Toczence gliniaste na stokach ornych w Sudetach [Clay balls on the arable slope of  the Sudeten Mountains]: Czas. Geogr., Vol. 51, No. 3, p. 287-297 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sketch  map), 1980.  Juvigne, Etienne.  Vulkanische Schwerminerale in rezenten Boeden Mitteleuropas [Volcanic heavy  minerals in Recent soils from Central Europe]: Geol. Rundsch., Vol. 69, No. 3, p. 982-996 (incl. English,  French, Russian sum.), illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980.  Kalinin, V. V.; and Fadeyev, V. Ye. A nonasymptotic method of determining the thermophysical  parameters of soils: Moscow University Geology Bulletin, Vol. 35, No. 2, p. 60-67, illus. (incl. l table),  1980.  Kassem, Y. S.; and Elwan, A. A. Origin and uniformity of the soils adjacent to Qarun Lake, Fayoum  Governorate: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 57-63, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Katsikatsos, G.; Fytrolakis, N.; and Perdikatsis, V. Contribution to the genesis of lateritic deposits of  the Upper Cretaceous transgression [abstr.]: in An international symposium on metallogeny of mafic and  ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with similar  metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 53, UNESCO, Natl. Tech.  Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Kavazanjian, Edward, Jr.; and Hadj-Hamou, Tarik. Determination of the dynamic material properties  of soils from the results of static shear tests: Report - John A. Blume Earthquake Engineering Center,  Department of Civil Engineering, Stanford University, No. 45, 37 p., 1980.  Keeteh, C. Wesley. Soil survey of San Juan County, New Mexico; eastern part: 173 p., illus. (incl. tables;  soils maps 1:63,360; colored soils map h506,880), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur. Indian Aft.; Bur. Reclam.; N.M.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Kelletat, D. Studies on the age of honeycombs and tafoni features: Catena, Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 317-325  (incl. German sum.), illus., 1980.  Khalil, J. B.; and Labib, F. B. The mineralogical nature of silt and sand fractions of some soils and clay  deposits in Bahariya oases: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 45-56, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map),  1980.    366    Khasawneh, F. E. (chairperson); Sample, E. C. (editor); and Kamprath, E. J. (editor). Proceedings of  The role of phosphorus in agriculture: June 1-3, 1976, United States. 886 p., illus. (incl. tables), Am.  Soc. Agron., Madison, Wl, United States, 1980.  Kigoshi, gudihiko; Suzuki, Nobuko; and Skiraki, Marl. Soil dating by fractional extraction of humic  acid: in Proceedings of the Tenth international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et aLL  Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No. 3, p. 853-857, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Kishi, S. Aerial photographic study on the volcanic disaster of Usu; state of damaged trees one year  after the eruption: Natl. Res. Cent. Disaster Prev., Rep., No. 24, p. 183-191, illus. (incl. sketch maps),  1980.  Klappa, Colin F. Brecciation textures and tepee structures in Quaternary calcrete (caliche) profiles from  eastern Spain; the plant factor in their formation: Geol. J. (Liverpool), Vol. 15, Part 2, p. 81-89, illus.  (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Kobori, Takuji; and Kusakibe, Kunru.  Estimation of dynamic soil-foundation properties through  vibration tests: Kyoto Univ., Disaster Prey. Res. Inst., Ann., No. 23 B-I, p. 121-135 (Japanese, incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Kokona, P.; Shalio, i.; Cina, A.; et al. Outline of the metallogeny of the ophiolites of the Albanides  [abstr.]: in An international symposium on metallogeny of marie and ultramafic complexes; the eastern  Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the  world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 59-60, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-  Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Kondratyev, K. Ya.;andFedehenko, P,P. Recognition of soils by their reflection spectra: Proceedings  of the International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 14, p. 409-413, illus., 1980.  Konstmatinov, A. R.; and Lakhovskaya, V. Ya.  Otsenka tochnosti rascheta srednikh vlagozapasov  pochvy za dozhdlivyye periody [Estimating the accuracy of mean soil moisture reserve calculations for  rainy periods]: Meteorol. Gidrol., No. 1 t, p. 100-107 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1980.  Koppi, A. J.; and Williams, D. J. Weathering and development of two contrasting soils formed from  grandodiorite in South-east Queensland: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 25%  271, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Kortenhorst, L. F. Factors affecting the viability of smallholders irrigation: in Land reclamation and  water management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the  occasion of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land Reclam. Improv.,  Publ., No. 27, p. 125-138, illus., 1980.  Kowalkowsld, Alojzy. The structure of altitudinal zonation of soils in the Donoin Dzun-nuruu Massif,  Khangai Mts (Mongolia): Geogr. Pol., No. 43, p. 111-124, illus., 1980.  24th international geographical  congres~  Krolikowski, Czeslaw. Rola geofizyki w realizacji "Programu Wlsla" [The role of geophysics in works  connected with the Vistula Program]: Przegl. Geol., Vol. 28, No. 9(329), p. 521-529 (incl. English,  Russian sum.), illus. (incl. sect., sketch map), 1980.  Kukoe, A. H. Natural gamma-ray spectra of Terra rossa soil and phosphate ore: in Traceability and  quality control in the measurement of environmental activity; seminar sponsored by the International  Committee for Radionuclide Metrology (Hutchinson, J. M. R., editor; et al.), Environ. Int., Vol. 3, No.  5, p. 385-387, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  La Breeque, J. J.; Parker, W. C.; and Adames, D. Application of an americium-241 source for the  determinationofbarium, lanthanum and cerium in lateritic material by X-ray fluorescence: J. Radioanal.  Chem., Vol. 59, No. 1, p. 193-201, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Ledyman, S. J.; and Harimess, D. D. Carbon isotope measurement as an index of soil development:  in Proceedings of the Tenth international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor; et aLL  Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No. 3, p. 885-891, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Lagasquie, J. J. Problemes de geomorphologie structurale dans les roches granitoides; rexemple du  Querigut-Madres [Problems of structural geomorphology in granitic rocks; the case of the "Querigut-  Madres" igneous complex]: Rev. Geomorphol. Dyn., Vol. 29, No. 1, p. 8-14 (incl. English sum.), sect.,  geol. sketch maps, 1980.    367    Larson, Jerry D. Soil survey of Berrien County, Michigan:  192 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch  maps; soils maps 1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Lauer, W.; and Frankenberg, P. Modelling of climate and plant cover in the Sahara for 5 500 B.P. and  18 000 B.P.:  in Sahara and surrounding seas; sediments and climatic changes; proceedings of an  international symposium (Sarnthein, M., editor; etal.), Palaeoecol. Afr., Vol. 12, p. 307-314, sketch maps,  1980.  Lehr, James R. Phosphate raw materials and fertilizers; Part 1, A look ahead:  in Proceedings of The  role of phosphorus in agriculture (Khasawneh, F. E., chairperson; et al.), p. 81-120, illus. (incl. 12 tables),  Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, Wl, United States, 1980.  Lewis, J.W. Environmental aspects of mineral sand mining in Australia: Miner. Environ., Vol. 2, No.  4, p. 145-158, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Limbird, A. Wisconsin versus lllinoian age soils; their effect on agricultural types in Ohio: The Ohio  Journal of Science, Vol. 80, No. 6, p. 273-279, tables, sketch map, 1980.  Lloret, A.; and Alonso, E.E. Consolidation of unsaturated soils including swelling and collapse behavior:  Geotechnique, Vol. 30, No. 4, p. 449-477 (incl. French sum.), illus., 1980.  Long, John H. Soil factors as they relate to onsite sewage disposal:  Individual Onsite Wastewater  Systems, No. 6, p. 93-96, 1980.  Lulla, Kamlesh. Remote sensing and soil studies; a brief review: Remote Sensing Quarterly, Vol. 2, No.  3, p. 4-20, illus. (incl. sketch map, table), 1980.  Lundgren, Lill. Comparison of surface runoff and soil loss from runoff plots in forest and small-scale  agriculture in the Usambara Mrs., Tanzania: Geogr. Ann., Ser. A, Vol. 62A, No. 3-4, p. 113-148, illus.  (incl. tables), 1980.  MaeLean, Kenneth S.; and Langille, Winston M. Extractable heavy metals in Atlantic Coast soils:  Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 11, No. 11, p. 1041-1049, tables, 1980.  Madrid, L. Some errors found in the use of the Stern model for ion adsorption: J. Soil Sci., Vol. 31,  No. 4, p. 709-711, 1980.  Maksimovie, Z.  Metallogenesis of nickel in fossil ultramafic laterites of SE Europe [abstr.]:  in An  international symposium on metallogeny of mafic and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-  western Asia area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis,  S. S., chairperson), p. 67-68, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece,  1980.  Mareuson, William F., III; and Franklin, Arley G.  State of the art of undisturbed sampling of  cohesionless soils: Geotech. Eng., Vol. 11, No. 1, p. 31-53, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Mariotti, A.; Pierre, D.; Vedy, J. C.; et al. The abundance of natural nitrogen 15 in the organic matter  of soils along an altitudinal gradient (Chablais, Haute Savoie, France): Catena, Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 293-  300 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1980.  Matthews, J. Some problems and implications of 14C dates from a podzol buried beneath an end moraine  at Haugabreen, southern Norway: Geogr. Ann., Ser. A, Vol. 62A, No. 3-4, p. 185-208 (incl. German  sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Mataszek, J. M.  A survey of environmental radioactivity measurements in the United States:  in  Traceability and quality control in the measurement of environmental activity; seminar sponsored by the  International Committee for Radionuclide Metrology (Hutchinson, J. M. R., editor; et al.), Environ. Int.,  Vol. 3, No. 5, p. 417-424, tables, 1980.  McBride, M. B. Interpretation of the variability of selectivity coefficients for exchange between ions  of unequal charge on smectites: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 28, No. 4, p. 255-261 (incl. Russian,  English, French sum.), illus., 1980.  McClellan, G. H.; and Gremiilion, L. R. Evaluation of phosphatic raw materials: in Proceedings of The  role of phosphorus in agriculture (Khasawneh, F. E., chairperson; et al.), p. 43-80, illus. (incl. 10 tables),  Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, W1, United States, 1980.  MeFadgen, B.G. A stone row system at Okoropunga on the Southeast Wairarapa coast and inferences  about coastal stone rows elsewhere in central New Zealand:  N. Z. J. Sci., Vol. 23, No. 2, p. 189-197,  illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.    368    McGhie, D. A. The contribution of the mallet hill surface to runoff and erosion in the Narrogin region  of Western Australia: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 299-307, sketch map, sect.,  tables, 1980.  MeGhie, D. A.; sad Posner, A. M. Water repellance of a heavy-textured Western Australian surface  soil: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 309-323, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  McGreevy, L. J.; ~ Sloto, R. A. Development of a digital model of ground-water flow in deeply  weathered crystalline rock, Chester County, Pennsylvania: Water-Resources Investigations, No. PB-81  132 896 (WRI 80-02), 48 p., 1980 [1981]. available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA, United States.  McGregor, D. F. M. An investigation of soil erosion in the Colombian rainforest zone: Catena, Vol.  7, No. 4, p. 265-273, 3 tables, sketch map, 1980.  McKenzie, R. M. The manganese oxides in soils:  in General problems, mineralogy, geochemistry,  methods (Varentsov, I. M., editor; et al.), Vol. 1, p. 259-269, illus. (incl. 3 tables), E. Schweizerbart'sche  Verlagsbuchhandlung, Stuttgart, FederalRepublic of Germany, 1980. Second international symposium on  Geology and geochemistry of manganese.  Mengei, Koara~ sad IgJrkby, Ernest A. Potassium in crop production: Advances in Agronomy, Vol.  33, p. 59-110, tables, 1980.  Mesri, G.; Choi, Y. K.; mad Muralkami, Yukitoshi. Excess pore-water pressure and preconsolidation  effect developed in normally consolidated clays of some age: Soils Found.(Tokyo), Vol. 20, No. 4, p.  143-148, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Miller, Norton G. Mosses as paleoecological indicators of late glacial terrestrial environments; some  North American studies: in Using "lower" plants to solve "higher" plant problems, Bulletin of the Torrey  Botanical Club, Vol. 107, No. 3, p. 373-391, tables, sketch maps, 1980. American Institute of Biological  Science symposium.  Minkin, M. B.; sad Ostrikov, M. S. O mekhanicheskom deystvii molekulyarno-poverkhnostnykh sil  v pochvakh pri vysykhanii i uvlazhnenii [The mechanical action of the molecular-surficial strength in soils  during drying and wetting]: Svyazannaya Voda v Dispersnykh Sistemakh, No. 5, p. 170-176, illus., 1980.  Misik, Milan. Predkvarterne sintre (speleotemy) a fosilne zvetravacie kory typu caliche (calcrete) v  Zapadnych Karpatoch [Pre-Quaternary sintres (speleothemes) and fossil weathering crusts of caliche  (caltrete) type in the Western Carpathians]: Mineral. Slovaca, Vol. 12, No. 4, p. 440, 1980.  Morita, Richard Y. Biological limits of temperature and pressure: in Completion of papers presented  at the Fourth College Park colloquium on chemical evolution; Limits of life (Ponnamperuma, Cyril,  editor), Origins Life, Vol. 10, No. 3, p. 215-222, tables, 1980.  Morris, D. F. C.; Gharib, A.; and Saber, H. Distribution of lanthanum, europium, germanium, tin,  phosphorus, and sulphur in nickeliferous lateritic profiles: Mineral Mag., Vol. 43, No. 330, p. 816-820,  illus., table, 1980.  Motti, P.; Motti, C. P.; and Sacramento, M. G. P. Relacoes dos solos com o modelado em condicoes  semi-aridas num setor dabacia do Rio Paraguacu [The relationship of soils with the model in semi-arid  conditions in part of the Paraguacu River basin]: Notic. Geomorfol., Vol. 20, No. 39/40, p. 49-60 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Mposkos, E. The Ni-Fe laterite ore deposits of Almopia Zone [abstr.]: inAn international symposium  on metallogeny of mafm and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia area, and  its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p.  72, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Mudroch, A. Biogeochemical investigation of Big Creek Marsh, Lake Erie, Ontario: Journal of Great  Lakes Research, Vol. 6, No. 4, p. 338-347, tables, sketch map, 1980.  Muhs, Daniel Robert. Quaternary stratigraphy and soil development, San Clemente Island, California:  255 p., Doctoral, 1980, Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, CO. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Munoz J., N. G.; Sqovia, A. V.; sad Foes, J. E. Geology, morphotectonic analysis, and soils mapping  of central Haiti, based on Landsat image and aerial photographs:  Proceedings of the International  Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 14, p. 1529-1535, table, sketch maps, 1980.  Nehon, D. Soil accumulations and climatic variations in western Sahara:  in Sahara and surrounding  seas; sediments and climatic changes; proceedings of an international symposium (Sarnthein, M., editor;  et al.), Palaeoecol. Aft., Vol. 12, p. 63-68, illus., 1980.    369    Nahon, Daniel; Carozzi, Albert V.; and Parron, Claude. Lateritic weathering as a mechanism for the  generation of ferruginous ooids: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, Vol. 50, No. 4, p. 1287-1298, illus.  (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Nathwani, Jatin S.; and Phillips, Colin R.  Leachability of Ra-226 from uranium mill railings  consolidated with naturally occurring materials and/or cement; Part 1, Empirical analysis: Water, Air,  Soil Pollut., Vol. 14, p. 379-387, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Nathwani, Jatin S.; and Phillips, Colin R.  Leachability of Ra-226 from uranium mill tailings  consolidated with naturally occurring materials and/or cement; Part 2, Analysis based on mass transport  equations: Water, Air, Soil Pollut., Vol. 14, p. 389-402, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Navarre, J. L.; Ronneau, C.; and Priest, P. Deposition of heavy elements of Belgian agricultural soils:  Water, Air, Soii Pollut., Vol. 14, p. 207-213, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Neese, Elizabeth. Vegetation of the Henry Mountains:  in Henry Mountains symposium (Picard, M.  Dane, editor), Utah Geological Association Publication, No. 8, p. 219-236, illus., 1980.  Newman, R. H.; Tate, K. R.; Barton, P. F.; et al.  Towards a direct, non-destructive method of  characterising soil humic substances using 13C N.M.R.: J. Soil Sci., Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 623-631, illus.,  1980.  Niemi, Les. Cyprus Bagdad; successful expansion creates a "state-of-the-art'" copper-moly producer in  Northwest Arizona: E &amp; MJ, Engineering and Mining Journal, Vol. 181, No. 8, p. 56-63, illus., 1980.  Ogner, G. Automatic determination of boron in water samples and soil extracts: Communications in  Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 11, No. 12, p. 1209-1219, illus,, 1980.  Okruszko, H.  Klassifizierung yon Feuchtgebieten auf der Grundlage der in ihnen entstehenden  hydromorphen Bodensubstrate [Wetland classification based upon the original hydromorphic soil  material]: Telma, Vol. 10, p. 17-24 (incl. English sum.), table, 1980.  Olsen, S. R.; and Khasawneh, F.E. Use and limitations of physical-chemical criteria for assessing the  status of phosphorus in soils:  in Proceedings of The role of phosphorus in agriculture (Khasawneh, F.  E., chairperson; et al.), p. 361-410, illus. (incl. 3 tables), Am. Soc. Agron., Madison, WI, United States,  1980.  Olszyezka, B.; and Crowther, d. M. The application of gamma-ray attenuation to the determination of  canopy mass and canopy surfacewater storage: J. Hydrol., Vol. 49, No. 3-4, p. 355-368, 1981.  Papayannopoulou-Eeonomou, Ath.; and Kiskyras, Dem.  Some remarks on the application of the  geophysical prospecting for chromites and Fe-Ni laterite deposits [abstr.]:  in An international  symposium on metallogeny of mafic and ultramafic complexes; the eastern Mediterranean-western Asia  area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the world (Augustithis, S. S..  chairperson), p. 87, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Parfitt, Roger Lynhurst; Furkert, R. J.; and Henmi, Teruo. Identification and structure of two types  of allophane from volcanic ash soils and tephra: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 28, No. 5, p. 328-334  (incl. Russian, German, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Perel'man, A. I. Paleogeochemical landscape maps: Geochemistry International, Vol. 17, No. 1, p. 39-  50, tables, sketch maps, 1980 [1981].  Pickens, John F.; and Gillham, Robert W. Finite element analysis of solute transport under hysteretic  unsaturated flow conditions: Water Resources Research, Vol. 16, No. 6, p. 1071-1078, illus. (incl. table),  1980.  Piotrovskaya, T. Yu.; and Naumov, M. S. Stadiynost' orogennogo razvitiya zapadnoy chasti Stanovogo  khrebta i prilegayushchikh territoriy [Stages of orogenic evolution of the western Stanovoy Ridge and  adjacent areas]: Geomorfologiya, No. 4, p. 94-100 (incl. English sum.), table, chart, 1980.  Pisarczyk, Stanislaw. Badanie 'Ydmax~ W opt gruntow gruboziarnistych metoda wibracyjna [Testing "Ydmax  and W opt of coarse-grained soils using the vibration method]: Arch. Hydrotech., Vol. 27, No. 1, p. 139-  151 (incl. English, Russian sum.), illus., 1980.  Plantz, Merritt; and Zink, Richard. Soil survey of Keya Paha County, Nebraska: 224 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates, sketch maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Nebr. Conserv. Surv.  Div.).    370    Price, F. R.; and JeRkins, D.A. Removal of resin from standard soil thin sections by low temperature  ashing as a means of following transmitted optical by scanning electron microscopy: Clay Miner., Vol.  15, No. 3, p. 309-315, illus., 1980.  Pringle, Fred B. Soil survey of Oldham County, Texas:  124 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Pump, E.; and Albania, University of Tirana, Faculty of Geology and Mining. The nickel-silicate and  iron-nickel ore deposits derived from lateritic weathering of ultrabasic-basic rocks of Albanides [abstr.]:  in An international symposium on metallogeny of mafic and ultramafic complexes; the eastern  Mediterranean-western Asia area, and its comparison with similar metallogenic environments in the  world (Augustithis, S. S., chairperson), p. 94-95, UNESCO, Natl. Tech. Univ., Dep. Miner.-Petrogr.-  Geol., Athens, Greece, 1980.  Puseh, R.; and Feltham, P. A stochastic model of the creep of soils: Geotechnique, VoL 30, No. 4, p.  497-506 (incl. French sum.), illus., 1980.  Pyatt, G. D.; MeLaren, D. T.; and Craven, Mairi M. Physical properties of four soils at Newcastleton  Forest, South Scotland:  in The properties of upland soils and their implications for agriculture and  forestry (Horning, M., chairperson), North Engl., Soils Discuss. Group, Proc., No. 15, p. 35-63, illus.  (incl. tables), 1980.  Proceedings of the North of England Soils Discussion Group.  Pytkowiez, Rleardo M. Further thoughts on the excess crustal calcium: Geochem. J.- Geochem. Soc.  Jap., Vol. 14, No. 1, p. 47-50, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Ruble, F.; Mady, F.; and AI Araby, A. Amorphous materials of Mg-affected soils: Egypt. J. Soil Sci.,  Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 65-74, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Radu, C.; Poiol~e, G.; and Apopei, I. Geological phenomena associated with Vrancea Earthquake of  March 4, 1977: in Proceedings of the XVI general assembly of the European Seismological Commission  (Teisseyre, Roman, editor; et al.), Pol. Acad. Sci., Inst. Geophys., Publ., Set. A: Phys. Earth Inter., No.  A-9(139), p. 51-62, sketch maps, 1980.  Rambouskova,  Hana.  Water  dynamics of some  abandoned  fields of the  Bohemian  karst  (Czechoslovakia): Folia Geobot. Phytotaxon., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 369-385, illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), 1980.  Ramsay, J.W. A soil conservator at work: Soil Water (N. Z., Min. Works Dev., Water Soil Div.), Vol.  16, No. 4, p. 9-11, plates, 1980.  Ranganathan, A.; and Satyanarayana, T. Studies on potassium status of soils of Karnataka: Indian Soc.  Soil Sci., J., Vol. 28, No. 2, p. 148-153, 3 tables, 1980.  Rassel, A.; and Deleeour, F. Matieres organiques au microscope electronique [Organic matter under the  electron microscope]: Pedologie, Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 275-281 (incl. Flemish, English sum.), illus., 1980.  Razumova, V. N.  K voprosu o proiskhozhdenii boksitov [The origin of bauxites]:  in Protessy  kontinental'nogo litogeneza (Shantser, Ye. V., editor), Akad. Nauk SSSR, Geol. Inst., Tr., No. 350, p.  60-93, illus. (incl. sects., plates), 1980.  Reid, A. M.; Gulllck, C. M.; and Reid, S. A. Tomlinson.  A preliminary study of the Etholen  Conglomerate, Etholen Knobs, Hudspeth County, Texas: in Geology of the Finlay Mountains, South  central Hudspeth County, Texas; 1980 field trip guidebook, p. 64-77, Soc. Econ. Paleontol. Mineral.,  Permian Basin Sect., Midland, TX, United States, 1980.  Reider, Richard G. Late Pleistocene and Holocene soils of the Carter/Kerr-McGee archeological site,  Powder River basin, Wyoming: Catena, Vol. 7, No. 4, p. 301-315, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sect.), 1980.  Retullaek, Greg; and Fritz, William J.  Reinterpretation of the depositional environment of the  Yellowstone fossil forests: Geology (Boulder), Vol. 9, No. 2, p. 52-54, illus. (incl. chart), 1981.  Riehason, Benjamin F., Jr. International symposia on machine processing of remotely sensed data, soil  information systems, and remote sensing and soil survey: Remote Sensing Quarterly, Vol. 2, No. 3, p.  21-24, illus., 1980.  Rigdon, Thomas A.; and Green, Alfred J. Soil survey of Camden and Glynn counties, Georgia: 82 p.,  illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Ga., Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp.  Stn.).    371    Rognon, P.  Pluvial and arid phases in the Sahara; the role of nonclimatic factors:  in Sahara and  surrounding seas; sediments and climatic changes; proceedings of an international symposium (Sarnthein,  M., editor; et al.), Palaeoecol. Afr., Vol. 12, p. 45-62, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1980.  Rohdenburg, H.; and Sabelberg, U. Northwestern Sahara margin; terrestrial stratigraphy of the upper  Quaternary and some paleoclimatic implications: in Sahara and surrounding seas; sediments and climatic  changes; proceedings of an international symposium (Sarnthein, M., editor; et al.), Palaeoecol. Aft., Vol.  12, p. 267-275, illus. (incl. strat, col.), 1980.  Rohrlich, V.; Metzer, A.; and Zohar, E. Potential iron ores in the Lower Cretaceous of lsrael and their  origin: lsr. J. Earth-Sci., Vol. 29, No. 1-2, p. 73-80, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Sacramento, Maria da Gloria P.  Relacao entre tipos de encostas e caracteristicas das formacoes  superficiais (area a nordeste de Salvador, Bahia) [The relationship between slope types and characteristics  of surficial deposits, northeast of Salvador, Bahia]: Notic. Geomorfol., Vol. 20, No. 39/40, p. 21-33 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1980.  Sanders, d. R. The use of adsorption equations to describe copper complexing by humified organic  matter: .l. Soil Sci., Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 633-641, tables, 1980.  Sapozhnikov, D. G. (editor).  Vtorichnyye izmeneniya boksitov iz mestorozhdeniy SSSR [The  secondary alteration of bauxite in deposits of the USSR]: 327 p., illus. (incl. 50 tables, 16 plates, sects.),  lzd. Nauka, Moscow, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1980.  Sarquis, Miekey; and Miekey, Charles D. Chem 1; Supplement; Selenium; Part I, Its chemistry and  occurrence: Journal of Chemical Education, Vol. 57, No. 12, p. 886-889, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Savel'yev, B.A. Znacheniye adsorbirovannoy vody v formirovanii strukturnogo stsepleniya v merzlykh  porodakh [The significance of adsorbed water in the formation of structural filtration in frozen rock]:  Svyazannaya Voda v Dispersnykh Sistemakh, No. 5, p. 25-33, table, 1980.  Schlepp, Richard L. Soil survey of Aurora County, South Dakota: 148 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Schmugge, T.J. Effect of texture on microwave emission from soils: 1EEE Transactions on Geoscience  and Remote Sensing, Vol. GE-18, No. 4, p. 353-361, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Schmugge, T. J.; Jackson, T. d.; and McKim, H. L. Survey of methods for soil moisture determination:  Water Resources Research, Vol. 16, No. 6, p. 961-979, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Schothorst, C.J. Subsidence of peat soils: Wageningen, Inst. Cultuurtech. Waterhuishouding, Tech.  Bull., No. 117, p. 159-165, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1980.  Schulze, F. E. (director).  Land reclamation and water management; developments, problems and  challenges; a collection of articles published at the occasion of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980): lnt.  Inst. Land Reclam. Improv., Publ., No. 27, 191 p., illus. (incl. tables, sects., block diag., sketch map),  1980.  Schulze, F. E.; and Van Staveren, d. M. Land and water development in the Third World:  in Land  reclamation and water management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles  published at the occasion of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land  Reclam. Improv., Publ., No. 27, p. 13-28, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Schwaller, Mathew R.; and Tkaeh, Steven d. Premature leaf senescence as an indicator for geobotanical  prospecting with remote sensing techniques: Proceedings of the International Symposium on Remote  Sensing of Environment, No. 14, p. 347-358, illus., 1980.  Schweieh, D.; and Sardin, M.  Adsorption, partition, ion exchange and chemical reaction in batch  reactors or in columns; a review: J. Hydrol., Vol. 50, No. 1-4, p. 1-33, 1981.  Segovia, A. V.; Foss, J. E.; and Soler, E.A. Evaluation of soils and landscapes of the seasonal tropics  by means of remote sensing images; an interdisciplinary study:  Proceedings of the International  Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No. 14, p. 915-927, illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch  maps), 1980.  Senger, Clyde M.  Observations on the cave basalt lava flow, Mt. St. Helens, 23-24 August 1980:  Washington Speleological Survey Bulletin, Vol. 62, No. 15, 6 p., 1980.    372    Sergeyev, Y. M.; Grtd~wska-Oiszewska, B.; Osipov, V. I.; et aL The classification of microstructures  of clay soils: in Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vot. 120,  Part 3, p. 237-260, illus. (incl. plates), 1980.  Sevea-son, R. C.; and Gough, L. P. Chemical character of minesoils at one Alaskan and twelve western  conterminous United States coal-stripmines: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978),  No. 81-0243, 82 p., 1981. available from." U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch,  Denver, CO, United States.  Sevnst'ysnov, V. V.  Periodichnost' obrazovaniya struktur i tekstur v lessovykh otlozheniyakh  Yavanskoy doliny (Tadzhikistan) [Periodicity in the evolution of structure and texture in loess deposits  of the Yavan valley; Tadzhikistan]: inTsiklichnost'formirovaniyasubaeral'nykhporodinTheformation  cycle of subaerial rocks (Volkov, I. A., editor), Akad. Nauk SSSR, Sib. Otd., Inst. Geol. Geofiz., Tr., No.  457, p. 143-149, illus., 1980.  Sieffermmt, G. Contribution to soil mapping of southern Venezuela using computer analysis of Landsat  II data [abstr.]: Proceedings of the International Symposium on Remote Sensing of Environment, No.  14, p. 1221-1222, 1980.  Siegel, S. M.; Okasako, JoB; I(~ii~ea, Pamela; et aL Release of volatile mercury from soils and  nonvascular plants: Org. Geochem., Vol. 2, No. 3/4, p. 139-140, tables, 1980.  Sine, L.; and Agn.aessens, J.P. Model/sat/on de la migration d'elements duns les sols; IV, Les modeles  discontinus [Modeling of element migration in soils;IV, Discontinuous models]: Pedologie, Vol. 30, No.  2, p. 177-189 (incl. Flemish, English sum.), illus., 1980.  Singh, Indra Bit; and Vaidiy~ K. S. Discovery of late Palaeozoic brachiopod in the upper Krot of the  Naintal Hills, Kumaon Himalaya; discussion and reply: Geol. Soc. India, J., Vol. 21, No. 10, p. 518-  520, 1980.  Slanders, P. J. Crop response to water under irrigated conditions:  in Land reclamation and water  management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the occasion  of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land Reclam. lmprov., Publ., No.  27, p. 139-147, illus., 1980.  Smalley, Ima J.; mad Davm, Jewel E. The first hundred years; a historical bibliography of New Zealand  loess, 1878-1978: N. Z. Soil Bur. Bibliogr. Rep., No. 28, 166 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Smallwood, Benjamin F. Soil survey of Marshall County, Indiana: 136 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils  maps 1:15,840; colored soil map h190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour., Soil  Water Conserv. Comm.).  Smith, David B.; Zielinski, Robert A.; and Rose, W.I. Leachability of uranium and other elements from  freshly erupted volcanic ash: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 81-0118,  99 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1981. available from: U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West.  Distrib. Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Sokolov, V. N.; Osipov, V. I.; and Toikaehev, M. D. The electron microscopic studies of pore space  of solids by a method of conjugate surfaces:  /n Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils  (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 363-366, illus., 1980.  Stocking, i. Soil loss estimation for rural development; a position for geomorphology: in Perspectives  in geomorphology; papers from the First British-German symposium on geomorphology (Hagedorn,  Horst, editor; et al.), Z. Geomorphol., Supplementband, Vol. 36, p. 264-273 (incl. German, French sum.),  1980.  Stout, J. D.; and 6oh, K. i. The use of radiocarbon to measure the effects of earthworms on soil  development: in Proceedings of the Tenth international radiocarbon conference (Stuiver, Minze, editor;  et al.), Radiocarbon, Vol. 22, No. 3, p. 892-896, tables, 1980.  Szezepkowski, Bolulan. Ochrona przyrody nieozywionej w wojewodztwie olsztynskim [Conservation  of inanimate nature in Olsztyn and environs]: Przegl. Geol., Vol. 28, No. 10(330), p. 574-578 (incl.  English, Russian sum.), illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  Takeshi, Hideo; and Uno, Yasuaki. Mineralogical properties and transformation of montmorillonites:  Nendo Kagaku, Vol. 20, No. 3, p. 67-78 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1980.    373    Talsma, T.; Mansell, R. S.; and Hallam, P.M. Potassium and chloride movement in a forest soil under  simulated rainfall: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 333-342, illus. (incl. tables),  1980.  Tateyama, Hiroshi; Kimbara, Keiji; Jinnai, Kazuhiro; eta/. Crystalstructureofaninterstratified mineral  of muscovite and vermiculite: Nendo Kagaku, Vol. 20, No. 3, p. 91-96 (Japanese, incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. 1 table), 1980.  Tateyama, H!roshi; Kimbara, Keiji; Jinnai, Kazuhiro; et al. An interstratified mineral of muscovite and  vermiculite in the weathered crystalline schist from Mikamo-cho, Miyoshi-gun, Tokushima Prefecture:  Nendo Kagaku, Vol. 20, No. 2, p. 55-59 (Japanese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1980.  Tayel, M. Y.; Abdalla, M. M.; Showky, M. E.; et al. The effect of moisture stress and Na:Ca:Mg ratio  on soil aggregation: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 2, p. 159-168 (incl. Arabic sum.), illus., 1980.  Tayel, M. Y.; Abdalla, M. M.; Showky, M. E.; et al. Hydraulic conductivity as affected by moisture  stress and Na:Ca:Mg ratio: Egypt. J. Soil Sci., Vol. 20, No. 2, p. 179-185 (incl. Arabic sum.), illus. (incl.  table), 1980.  Taylor, R.M. Formation and properties of Fe(II)Fe(IlI) hydroxy-carbonate and its possible significance  in soil formation: Clay Miner., Vol. 15, No. 4, p. 369-382 (incl. French, German, Spanish sum.), illus.  (incl. tables), 1980.  Taylor, R. M.; and Schwertmann, U. The influence of aluminum on iron oxides; VII, Substitution of  Al for Fe in synthetic lepidocrocite: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 28, No. 4, p. 267-271 (incl. Russian,  German, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Tenyakov, V. A.; and Sidorenko, Sv. A. Inversionno-tsiklicheskiye protsessy migratsii gazov v zemnoy  kore v svyazi s osadochno-metamorficheskimi tsiklami [Inversion-cyclic processes of gas migration in  the Earth's crust in relation to sedimentary-metamorphic cycles]: inDegazatsiyaZemliigeotektonikain  Degasification of the Earth and geotectonics (Kropotkin, P. N., editor; et al.), p. 14-22, lzd. Nauka,  Moscow, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1980.  Thomas, M. F.; and Thorp, M. B. Some aspects of the geomorphological interpretation of Quaternary  alluvial sediments in Sierra Leone:  in Perspectives in geomorphology; papers from the First British-  German  symposium  on  geomorphology  (Hagedorn,  Horst,  editor;  et al.),  Z.  Geomorphol.,  Supplementband, Vol. 36, p. 140-161 (incl. German, French sum.), table, sects., geol. sketch maps, 1980.  Thorn, Colin E. Alpine bedrock temperatures; an empirical study: Arctic and Alpine Research, Vol.  12, No. 1, p. 73-86, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Tovey, N. K. A digital computer technique for orientation analysis of micrographs of soil fabric:  in  Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 303-  315, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Tovey, N. K.; and Krinsley, D. H. A cathodoluminescent study of quartz sand grains:  in Symposium  on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 279-289, illus., 1980.  Tovey, N. K.; and Wong, K.Y. The microfabric of deformed kaolin: in Symposium on the Microscopy  of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 329-342, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Towner, (;. D. Theory of time response of tensiometers: J. Soil Sci., Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 607-621, illus.  (incl. tables), 1980.  Tulyagauov, Kh. T.  Osobennosti  formirovaniya chetvertichnykh  rossypey  zolota Uzbekistana  [Formation characteristics of the Quaternary gold placers in Uzbekistan]: Sov. Geol., Vol. 9, p. 27-36,  table, 1980.  Tummavuori, Jouni; and Aho, Martti. On the ion-exchange properties of peat; Part lI, On the adsorption  of alkali, earth alkali, aluminium (III), chromium (Ill), iron (III), silver, mercury (III), and ammonium  ions to the peat: Suo, Vol. 31, No. 4, p. 79-83, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Twidale, C. R.  The origin of bornhardts:  in Symposium on the Gawler Craton (Parker, A. J.,  chairperson), Journal of the Geological Society of Australia, Vol. 27, No. 1-2, p. 195-208, illus. (incl.  sects., geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Twidale, C. R. Castellated inselberg: Australian Geographer, Vol. 14, No. 6, p. 368-371, illus. (incl.  sect., sketch map), 1980.    374    Unller, P. W.; and MeC.,alla, T. M. Conservation tillage systems: Advances in Agronomy, Vol. 33. p.  1-58, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Vaehaud, G.; Vanelin, M.; and Colombani, J. Bilan hydrique dans le Sud-Tunisien; l, Caracterisation  experimentale des transferts darts la zone non saturee [Hydrologic balance in southern Tunisia; I,  Experimental characterization of water movement in the unsaturated zone]: J. Hydrol., Vol. 49, No. 1-2,  p. 31-52 (incl. English sum.), 1981.  van Alphen, d. G. A note on the irrigation of Red soils in the Upper Tana Catchment, Kenya: Int. Inst.  Land Reclam. Improv., Annu. Rep., Vol. 1979, p. 39-42, illus., 1980.  Van den Brock, J. M. M.; and Van der Marel, H.W. Properties and origin of sediments of the Meuse  River in the Netherlands and Belgium: Pedologie, Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 243-273 (incl. Flemish, French  sum.), illus. (incl. 7 tables, geol. sketch maps), 1980.  Van Genaehten, Martinus Th. Analytical solutions for chemical transport with simultaneous adsorption,  zero-order production and first-order decay: J. Hydrol., Vol. 49, No. 3-4, p. 213-233, 1981.  Van Hoorn, J. W.; and Van Aart, R. The use of saline water for irrigation: in Land reclamation and  water management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles published at the  occasion of ILR,"s silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land Reclam. tmprov.,  Publ., No. 27, p. 148-159, illus., 1980.  van Ranst, E.; Righi, D.; de Coninek, F.; et al. Morphology, composition and genesis of argillans and  organans in soils: in Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J. Microsc., Vot  120, Part 3, p. 353-361, illus., 1980.  Vauelin, M.; and Vaehaad, G. Bilan hydrique dans le Sud-Tunisien; lI, Modelisation numerique et  prevision des transferts hydriques en sol stratifie [Hydrologic balance in southern Tunisia; II,  Mathematical modeling and estimation of water movement in layered soil]: J. Hydrol., Vol. 49, No. 1-2,  p. 53-73 (incl. English sum.), 1981.  Vergne, Olivia C. tie Azevedo. Caracteristicas das formacoes superficiais nos tabuleiros costeiros a SE  de Camacari [Characteristics of surficial formations in the coastal tablelands southeast of Camacari]:  Notic. Geomorfol., Vol. 20, No. 39/40, p. 91-99 (incl. English sum.), 1 table, sketch map, 1980.  Verloo, M.; Kiekens, L.; and Cottenie, A. Distribution patterns of essential and non-essential trace  elements in the soil-soil solution system: Pedologie, Vol. 30, No. 2, p. 163-175 (incl. French, Flemish  sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1980.  Volehok, H.L.;Feiner, M.;Inn, K.G.W.; etal. Development of some natural matrix standards; progress  report:  in Traceability and quality control in the measurement of environmental activity; seminar  sponsored by the International Committee for Radionuclide Metrology (Hutchinson, J. M. R., editor;  et al.), Environ. Int., Vol. 3, No. 5, p. 395-398, tables, sketch map, 1980.  Wad~ Eltarn; and Naksunura, Koiehi. Nitrogen and carbon isotopes in soil with special reference to  the diagenesis of organic matter: Chikyukagaku (Geochem.), Vol. 14, No. 1, p. 7-15 (incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Walsh, R. P. D. Runoff processes and models in the humid tropics: in Perspectives in geomorphology;  papers from the First British-German symposium on geomorphology (Hagedorn, Horst, editor; et al.),  Z. Geomorphol., Supplementband, Vol. 36, p. 176-202 (incl. German, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1980.  Wang, J. R.; and Sehmugge, T. J. An empirical model for the complex dielectric permittivity of soils  as a function of water content: IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, Vol. GE-18,  No. 4, p. 288-295, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Weiner, Karl Ludwig. Grubenhund und Huettensau; vom Prospektieren (2. Teil) ["Grubenhund" and  "Huettensau"; Prospecting; Part 2]: Lapis, Vol. 5, No. 12, p. 29-31, illus., 1980.  Wenk, H. R.; and Nmk~ima, Y. Structure, formation, and decomposition of APB's in calcic plagioclase:  Phys. Chem. Miner., Vol. 6, No. 3, p. 169-186, illus. (incl. table, plate), 1980.  Wilson, M. J.; and MeHardy, W. J. Experimental etching of a microcline perthite and implications  regarding natural weathering:  in Symposium on the Microscopy of clays and soils (Anonymous), J.  Microsc., Vol. 120, Part 3, p. 291-302, illus., 1980.    375    Wilson, P. Surface textures of regolith quartz from the southern Pennines: Geol. J. (Liverpool), VoL  15, Part 2, p. 113-129, illus. (incl. geol. map), 1980.  Windom, Kenneth E.; Stewart, Dion C.; and Thornton, Charles P.  Development of columnar-  spheroidal structures by meteoric water in a New Mexico basalt: Geology (Boulder), Vol. 9, No. 2, p.  73-76, illus. (incl. table), 1981.  Worthington, Richard D.  Vascular plants for the north end of the Quitman Mountains, Hudspeth  County, Texas: in Geology of the Finlay Mountains, South central Hudspeth County, Texas; 1980 field  trip guidebook, p. 88-92, Soc. Econ. Paleontol. Mineral., Permian Basin Sect., Midland, TX, United  States, 1980.  Wright, Bruce. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Curry County, New Mexico: Open-File Report (United States  Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0169, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980. availablefrorn:U. S. Geol.  Surv., Rocky Mt. Mapp. Cent., Denver, CO, United States.  Wright, Bruce. Irrigated cropland, 1978, Texas County, Oklahoma: Open-File Report (United States  Geological Survey. 1978), No. 80-0170, 1 sheet, land use map 1:250,000, 1980. availablefrom:U. S. Geol.  Surv., Mid-Continent Mapp. Cent., Rolla, MO, United States.  Wright, P. S. Soils in Dyfed IV; Sheet SN62 (Llandeilo): Soil Surv. Rec., No. 61, 171 p. (incl. Welsh  sum.), illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps; soils map 1:25,000), 1980.  Yair, ; Goldberg, P.; Bryan, R. B.; et al. Present and past geomorphic evidences in the development  of a badlands landscape; Zin Valley, northern Ncgev, Israel: in Sahara and surrounding seas; sediments  and climatic changes; proceedings of an international symposium (Sarnthein, M., editor; et aLL  Palaeoecol. Aft., Vol. 12, p. 125-135, illus. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1980.  Yenter, James M.; Schmitt, Gerald J.; Johnson, William W., Jr.; et al. Soil survey of Conejos County  area, Colorado:  144 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U.  S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1980. (Publ. in coop. with Colo.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Yoshinaka, Ryunoshin; and Yamabe, Tadashi. Strength criterion of rocks: Soils Found.(Tokyo), Vol.  20, No. 4, p. 113-126, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Zcntay, T. A talajtan, az agrokemia es a foldtani tudomanyagak kolcsonhatasa az agrogcologiaban [Soils,  agrochemistry and applications of geological sciences in agrogeology]: Foeldt. Koezl., Vol. 110, No. 2,  p. 140-158, 1980.  Zhang Zunghu. Loess in China: GeoJournal, Vol. 4, No. 6 (Recent research in China), p. 525-540, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980.  Zienkiewicz, O. C.; Chang, C. T.; and Bettes, P.  Drained, undrained, consolidating and dynamic  behaviour assumptions in soils: Geotechnique, Vol. 30, No. 4, p. 385-395 (incl. French sum.), illus.,  1980.  Zijistra, G.; and Van Someren, C. L.  Developments in subsurface drainage techniques:  in Land  reclamation and water management; developments, problems and challenges; a collection of articles  published at the occasion of ILRI's silver jubilee (1955-1980) (Schulze, F. E., director), Int. Inst. Land  Reclam. Improv., Publ., No. 27, p. 171-180, illus., 1980.  Zinchuk, N. N.; Khar'kiv, A. D.; and Afanas'yev, V. P.  Ispol'zovaniye vtorichnykh mineralov  kimberlitov pri poiskakh almazov [Using secondary minerals in kimberlites while prospecting for  diamonds]: Geokhim. Rudoobraz., No. 8, p. 78-87, illus., 1980.  Zurawske, Ann; Burchett, C. R.; and Sparkes, A. K. Ground water related to weathering products of  facies of Fort Payne Formation [abstr.]: Geological Survey Professional Paper (Washington, D.C.), No.  1175, p. 132-133, 1980 [1981].  Zykina, V. S. Tsiklichnost' stroyeniya chetvertichnoy tolshchi subaeral'nykh osadkov na osnovanii  izucheniya iskopaycmykh pochv v Iskitimskom rayone [Ccmpositional cycles in the Quaternary strata  of subaerial sediments as a basis for the study of fossil ~ils in the Iskitim region]:  in Tsiklichnost'  formirovaniya subaeral'nykh porod in The formation cycle of subaerial rocks (Volkoy, I. A., editor), Akad.  Nauk SSSR, Sib. Otd., Inst. Geol. Gcofiz., Tr., No. 457, p. 139-143, 1980.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              