 Geoderma, 24 (1980) 71--85                                                         71  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SOLUTION AND USE OF CHRONOFUNCTIONS IN STUDYING SOIL  DEVELOPMENT    J.G. BOCKHEIM  Department of Soil Science, University of Wisconsin, Madison, W1, 53706 (U.S.A.)  (Received May 1, 1979; accepted November 12, 1979)    ABSTRACT    Bockheim, J.G., 1980. Solution and use of chronofunctions in studying soil development.  Geoderma, 24: 71--85.    Thirty-two chronosequences from 27 areas were selected from the literature for con-  structing chronofunctions and for correlating rates of change in soil properties with vari-  ables representing climate and parent material. The chronosequences originate from areas  situated between 66 and 78S latitude and represent seven climatic regions, ranging  from tropical rainy to cold desert, and seven types of parent materials, including till,  aeolian sand, alluvium, mine spoil, volcanic ash, raised beach deposits, and mudflows.  Fourteen of the chronosequences contain soils which range in age from 0 to 500 yr; seven  span a 12,000-yr period, three a 100,000-yr period, and eight a period of greater than one  million yr. Three linear and non-linear models were tested on 15 soil properties. The single-  logarithmic ( Y = a + b log X) model yielded the best correlation coefficients, when soil  property (Y) was correlated with time iX), using linear regression techniques. The dates  and equations allow for the following conclusions:  (1) The rates of decrease in pH and in base saturation are similar, regardless of the na-  ture of the parent material or climate.  (2) The rates of increase in clay content of the B horizon and solum thickness are posi-  tively correlated with clay content of the parent material.  (3) The rates of increase in solum thickness, oxidation depth, soluble salt content of  the salt-enriched horizon, and clay content of the B horizon are positively correlated with  mean annual temperature whereas the rate of increase in total N in the surface mineral  soil is negatively correlated with present-day mean annual temperature.  (4) The increase in bulk density of the surface soil is positively correlated with present  mean annual precipitation.  (5) The rate of change in C:N is not correlated with variables representing climate and  parent material.    INTRODUCTION    Jenny (1941, 1961) defined a chronosequence as an array of related soils  in a geographic area that differ primarily as a result of the soil-forming factor,  time. He identified a chronofunction as the mathematical solution of the rela-  tionship:  s = f(t)cl, o, r, p...                                                (1)    0016-7061/80/0000--0000/$02.25 1980 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    72    where the soil (s) and the properties that define it are functions of time (t),  with the variables of climate (cl), organisms (o), relief (r), and parent material  (p) remaining constant.  There are more than seventy published reports of chronosequences in the  pedological, ecological, and geological literature. Some of these were reviewed  by Stevens and Walker (1970). Yaalon (1975) reviewed univariant solutions of  Jenny's soil-forming equation, pointing out the lack of time-variant functions.  Olson's (1958) study of a chronosequence of soils on sand dunes in northern  Indiana may represent the only published attempt to define a chronofunction  using more than one date. He used an exponential function to show the rela-  tionship between time and soil properties, including cation exchange, exchange  acidity, exchangeable bases, and amounts of carbon, nitrogen and carbonates.  He obtained correlation coefficients as high as 0.997 (P &lt; 0.01).  The changes in a given soil property as a function of time have been shown  graphically by numerous investigators (e.g., Dickson and Crocker, 1953a, b;  1954; Crocker and Major, 1955; Crocker and Dickson, 1957; Ugolini, 1968).  The few quantitative solutions of the rate functions generally have been based  on a single date and the use of a model selected in accordance with chemical  kinetics (e.g., Hay, 1960; Ruxton, 1968; Behling, 1972). Numerous investiga-  tors have depicted the relationship between soil properties (and soil taxa) and  time as being exponential or logarithmic even though dates may not be avail-  able (e.g., Yaalon, 1971; Birkeland, 1974).  Vreeken (1975) discussed four principal kinds of chronosequences distin-  guished on the basis of times of the initiation and termination of soil develop-  ment and on the degree of overlap in soil history. He suggested that only  chronosequences containing soils which began forming at the same point in  time but which terminated development at different points in time are useful  in studying rates of soil development. Few of the chronosequences in the  literature fall into this category.  Soil chronofunctions are useful for studying pedogenesis, for providing  relative dates of geologic events (e.g., Campbell and Claridge, 1975) and for  predicting recovery rates of disturbed soils. Yaalon (1971) grouped soil pro-  perties according to the periods required for attainment of a dynamic steady  state: (1) rapidly adjusting (&lt; 103 yr); (2) slowly adjusting (&lt; 10a yr); and  (3) persistent. The latter were viewed as produced by irreversible or "self-  terminating" processes.  The objectives of this study are: (1) to review the literature regarding soil  chronosequences and evaluate its suitability as a basis for development of  chronofunctions, (2) to derive soil chronofunctions using different linear and  non-linear models, and (3) to compare chronofunctions of a given soil pro-  perty for different climatic regions and parent materials.    METHODS    About half of the published reports of chronosequences in the literature  were rejected because of poor dating control and/or incompleteness of analyt-    73    ical data. Others were disqualified because of difficulties in processing the  data because of the wide variety of soil properties considered (about 75 pro-  perties) and differences in depth of sampling, analytical techniques, and units  for expressing data. A major restriction in using some of the more complete  chronosequences was that the data were displayed graphically rather than  numerically.  Several steps were taken in calculating chronofunctions. The most useful  data were first organized into tables with measurements converted into the  same units. Each soil property was correlated with time using linear regres-    sion techniques and the three models:  Y=a+bX  Y = a + (b logX)  logY=a+{blogX)    (2)  (3)  (4)    where Y = soil property and X = time. Exponential and polynomial models  were employed at the beginning of the study but were discarded because they  did not fit the data. The quality of the relationship between a soil property and  time was expressed through the use of the correlation coefficient, r. Fifteen  soil properties were included in the analysis. The b regression coefficient, or  slope of the chronofunction of a particular soil property, was regressed on  variables representing climate, including mean annual temperature, mean an-  nual precipitation, average annual potential evapotranspiration, and moisture  index. A major limitation to the use of these climatic variables is that they  represent present-day climate and do not reflect past climate changes. For ex-  ample, Leamy (1974) discovered that pedogenic carbonate accumulated  faster in post-glacial times than during the latter part of the Wiirm glaciation  in western Europe. Parent material was represented by the clay content of  the C horizon. There were insufficient data to include mineralogy of the  parent material in the analysis.  Because most of the sampling sites were located on flat or gently sloping  landforms, the soil-forming factor, topography, was not considered in the  analysis. The factor, organisms, is difficult to quantify and was not evaluated.    RESULTS    Examples of chronosequences    Data from 32 chronosequences from 27 areas were selected as a suitable  basis for developing chronofunctions (Table I). The chronosequences were  situated from 66 to 78 latitude and encompass seven climatic regions,  ranging from tropical rainy to cold desert, and seven types of parent materials,  including till, aeolian sand, alluvium, mine spoil, raised beach deposits, volcan-  ic ash, and mudflow materials. Till was the parent material in 17 of the 32  studies.    TABLE I    Soil chronosequences used for preparing chronofunctions  Location           Latitude   Climatic   Parent  region'     material    Mt. Shasta, CA     41      Cb         mudflows  (USA)                                     (andesitic)  Manawata, North   40S       Cbf        aeolian  Island (NZ)                                sand  No. IN (USA)       42      Daf        aeolian sand  No. MI (USA)      45N      Dbf        sandy beach  deposits  Rocky Mtns, CO    40N      H          till, rock  (USA)                                     glacier depos-  its (granitic)  Glacier Bay, AK    59      Cb         till (granitic  (USA)                                      mixed)  Baffin Island        66      ET         till (granitic)    Dating  method2  HD  HC  C  C  CL    Range in time  (yr BP)  0--1,200+  60--10,000  0--12,000  2,250--10,000  50--30,000    HDL  LCKS    15--250  200--100,000    British Columbia    49      Cb         sandy beach  (Canada)                                   deposits  Elbrus area         43N      H          till (granitic)  (USSR)  Taylor and Wright  77       ET         till (granitic)  Valleys (Antarctica)  Wind River Mtns,    43N       H           till (granitic)  WY (USA)  Chena River, AK    65N      Dcf        alluvium  San Joaquin Valley  36      BWh       alluvium  CA (USA)                           (granitic)  Adair Co., IA       41 N       Daf        till (mixed)  (USA)  Muldrow Glacier,    63       Dcf        till (mixed}  AK (USA)    D  HLS  CUKS  CD  D  CK  CKS  DC    127--550  0--300+  3,100--- 3.9 my  300--15,000  15--220  7,000--400,000  6,800--200,000  25--9,000    Reference    Dickson and Crocker (1953a, b; 1954)    Cowie (1968); Syers and Walker (1969a, b);  Syers et al. (1970); Walker and Syers (1976)  Olson (1958)  Franzmeier and Whiteside ( 1963a, b);  Franzmeier et al. (1963)  Mahaney (1974)    Crocker and Major (1955); Ugolini (1968)    Birkeland (1978); Bockheim (1979a);  Evans and Cameron {1979)  Hendershot et al. (1979)    Gennadiyev (1978); Gennadiyev and  Sokolova (1978)  Behling (1971, 1972); Bockheim (1977,  1979b); Pastor and Bockheim (1980)  Birkeland and Shroba (1974); Birkeland  (unpubl.) ; Miller and Birkeland ( 1974 )  Viereck (1970)  Janda and Croft (1967)    Ruhe (1956)    Viereck (1966)    TABLE I (continued)    Location           Latitude   Climatic   Parent  region~     material    59N       Cb         till (granitic)    Herbert &amp; Menden-  hall Glaciers, AK  (USA)  South Haven        54N      Cbf        aeolian         H          0--350  Peninsula (UK)                             sand  Central PA (USA)   41      Dbf        alluvium       C  (mixed)  Sierra Nevada, NV  39      BWh       granitic, ande-  CKS       &lt;14,000-  (USA)                                     sitic, basaltic               N 0.4 my  alluvium  UK                             Cbf        mine spoil      H  Kebnekajse         68      Dcf        till (granitic)    LD  (No. Sweden)  N.E. Papua           8       Af         volcanic ash    C  (Oceania)  Arena Valley        78       ET        till (sandstone, UKS  (Antarctica)                                diabase)  No. MN (USA)      47      Dbf        mine spoil      H    Dating     Range in time    Reference  method2   (yr BP)  HD         0--1,000+        Chandler ( 1942) ; Crocker and Dickson  (1957)    Salisbury (1925); Wilson (1960)    &lt;205--1,955     Bilzi and Ciolkosz (1977)    Birkeland ( 1968, 1971 ); Alexander (1974)    0--178           Down (1975a, b)  0-200          Stork (1963)    0--23,000        Ruxton (1968)    ~ 220,000--     Bockheim (unpubl.)  2.7--3.5 my  2--51             Leisman (1957)    ' Af = tropical rainy; BWh = subtropical desert; Cb = humid-marine west coast; Da = humid continental, warm summer; Db = humid  continental, cool summer; Dc = humid continental, subarctic; ET = polar-tundra; H = undifferentiated, mountainous. (After  Trewartha, 1968)  2 H = historical; D = dendrochronology; L = lichenometry; C = radiocarbon; K = potassium-argon; U = uranium-thorium; S = strati-  graphic and radiometric in places.    O1    76    Fourteen of the chronosequences contain soils that range in age from 0 to  500 years, as dated by historical, dendrochronological, and lichenometric  procedures. Seven of the chronosequences correspond to the 12,000-yr period  since the last major continental glaciation. In these chronosequences, radio-  carbon dates predominated. Three of the chronosequences cover a 100,000-yr  period, and eight a period exceeding 1 million years. These long-term studies  relied on radiometric dating and correlation with dated landforms or deposits  using principles of stratigraphy.    Mathematical solution    The logarithmic functions generally provided the best correlations between  time and the four soil properties most frequently cited in the chronosequence  literature (Table II). Eighty-five percent of the correlation coefficients derived  by regressing the soil properties on the log of time were statistically significant.    TABLE II    Degree of statistical significance between soil property (Y) and time (X) using three models  Soil property               Frequency of    Y =      log Y =         Y =  occurrence      a + bX   a + (b log X)    a + (b log X)    Percent statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05)  pH, surface                   15              60         87              93  Extractable Fe, B horizon    11             82         64             64  Organic matter (%), surface  11             73         82             82  Clay (%), B horizon            8              75        100             100  Total                                        71         82             85    Comparison of chronofunctions derived for individual soil properties    Individual soil properties can be identified as univariant or multivariant rela-  tive to the number of soil-forming factors controlling their development. A  chronofunction is an example of a univariant function, where the magnitude  of a given property is correlated only with time. Multivariant soil properties  are dependent on two or more soil-forming factors. For example, multivariant  soil properties include those for which the rate of development, or the slope  of soil property versus time, can be correlated with a variable representing  some other soil-forming factor, such as climate or parent material.    Univariant chronofunctions. Of the 15 properties considered in the analysis,  only base saturation and pH of the surface mineral soil had similar regression  coefficients, regardless of differences in climate, parent material, and organ-  isms. For example, the rate of decrease in pH with time is similar for chrono-  sequences derived from dune sand in the United Kingdom, till in southeastern    77    Alaska, and alluvium in interior Alaska (Fig. 1). The rate of decrease in per-  cent base saturation is similar for chronosequences in areas with mean annual  temperatures ranging from 34 to 138 cm (Fig. 2). This suggests that not only  do the processes of leaching of bases and development of acidity occur very  rapidly in soils, but also that they occur independently of climate, parent  material, and organisms, at least within the ranges of these factors considered  in this study. These trends contrast with the findings of Jenny et al. (1968)  who reported a strong relationship between degree of acidity and mean annu-  al precipitation. These differences in interpretation are even more puzzling in    lOO       ~             Mean annual         precipitation (cm)  80                          1   138  \\   \\    2  118   60                                 84  20  3  0~~      102      103     104      105  Time (years)  Fig. 1. Chronofunction of base saturation for four climatic regions: 1 = Glacier Bay,  Alaska (Ugolini, 1968): Y = 136 -- 43.4 log X, r = --0.90**; 2 = Mt. Shasta, CA (Diekson  and Crocker, 1954): Y = 115 -- 26.6 log X, r = --0.85*;3 = Baffin Island, Canada  (Bockheim, 1979a): Y = 146 -- 29.2 logX, r = 0.97**;4 = North Island, N.Z. (Cowie,  1968): Y = 145 -- 26.5 log X, r = --0.97**.    8  V  7 t~',     \             1  Dune sand, UK    / ",  ~       2 Till, AK (USA)  6[-  ',,, ~      3 Alluvium, AK (USA)  {  2  -----3  3,        ~b       ~o      1~o      ~o  Time (years)  Fig. 2. Relationship between pH of the surface mineral soil and time for (1) dune sand in  United Kingdom (Wilson, 1960); (2) till from Mendenhall Glacier, Alaska (Crocker and  Diekson, 1957 ); and (3) alluvium from the Chena River, Alaska (Viereck, 1970).    78    view that the sites selected for both studies have a similar range in mean annu-  al precipitation (ca. 8--200 cm).  The chrofiofunctions of organic matter content and C:N ratio in the surface  mineral, horizon and that of extractable iron in the B horizon differed among  study areas but could not be related to the variables representing climate or  parent material. In contrast, Jenny et al. (1968} showed a strong correlation  between the organic carbon content of a variety of California soils and both  mean annual temperature and mean annual precipitation.  The carbon:nitrogen ratio of the surface mineral horizon was either posi-  tively or negatively correlated (P = 0.01) with time. The trends in C:N could  be due to the composition of the plant litter which has been incorporated in-  to the surface mineral horizon. The increase in C:N ratio in soils of northern  California (Dickson and Crocker, 1953b) and southeastern Alaska (Crocker  and Dickson, 1957) may be attributed to a decrease in nitrogen-fixing species  and a concurrent increase in coniferous litter byproducts in the soils with  time. In contrast, the decrease in C:N ratio in soils of northern Minnesota  (Leisman, 1957) and interior Alaska (Viereck, 1966) may be due to the ab-  sence of conifers in the successional sequence. Jenny et al. {1968) reported  that vegetation accounted for 40% of the variation in C:N of soils in  California. Carbon:nitrogen ratio was the only soil property examined by  Jenny et al. (1968} which was related to vegetation.    50    40  N   20  U  10    1    Clay [o),  C horizon  1   39  2   9  3     0.5  4     3.5  5   11  I           I           I          J  io~      ios      1o6      io~  Time (years)    Fig. 3. Chronofunctions of clay content in the B horizon for five tills. 1 = Iowa (Ruhe,  1956): Y -- --26.1 + 15.3 log X, r = 0.99**; 2 = San Joachin Valley, CA (Janda and Croft,  1967): Y = --41.1 + 12.6 log X, r = 0.91"*; 3 = northern Michigan (Franzmeier and  Whiteside, 1963b): Y = 16.3 + 4.89 log X, r = 0.94**; 4 = Taylor Valley, Antarctica  (Pastor and Bockheirn, 1980): Y ='--7.88 + 2.23 log X, r = 0.85 ** ; 5 = Sierra Nevada, CA  (Birkeland, 1968): Y=--68.4 + 17.21ogX, r ffi 0.99**.    79    Multivariant functions--time and parent material. The rate of increase in the  amount of clay in the B horizon was not correlated with variables represent-  ing climate but was correlated with the clay content of the parent material  (Fig. 3, Table III). Argillic horizons form under a wide variety of tempera-  ture and moisture regimes and are found in Aridisols, Alfisols, Ultisols and  Mollisols. Clay enrichment may also occur in B horizons of Spodosols and  Vertisols. Cline (1957) reported what are now recognized as argiUic horizons  in soils derived from loamy drift in New York, but not in soils formed from  silt loam and fine sandy loam drift. Jenny et al. (1968) found no relation-  ship between clay content of California soils and any of the five soil-forming  factors.  In this study rate of increase in thickness of solum was correlated with clay  content of the parent material (Table III). Analysis of lithosequence data  given by Yassaglou et al. (1969} and Holt and McMiller (1956) showed signifi-  cant positive correlations between thickness of solum and clay content of the  C horizon. Clay content of parent materials considered in this study and in  those cited above ranged from less than 2 to a maximum of 38% so that ex-  tremely fine textured materials which could restrict water movement were  not sampled.    TABLE III  Correlation between rate function (b0) and variables representing parent material and  climate (Y~)    Y0                                     n      a              b i                    r    Clay, C horizon (%)  Solum thickness (cm)         8    16.6         2.84             0.783**  Clay, B horizon (%)           8      3.34        0.418            0.664*  Mean annual temperature (o C)  Electrical conductivity,        5    --2.36      --0.503            0.948**  salt-enriched horizon  (mmho/cm)  Oxidation depth {cm)         5    64.4         3.08             0.887**  Bulk density, surface          5    --0.788      0.0752          0.862*  mineral horizon (g/cm~)  Total N, surface mineral       5      0.151    --0.0155         --0.845*  horizon (%)  Clay, B horizon (%)           8      7.87        0.319            0.722*  Solum thickness (cm)         8    47.3        2.29            0.695*  Mean annual precipitation (cm)  Bulk density, surface          5    --1.43        0.00861         0.988**  mineral horizon (g/cm~)    Y0 = a + (b0 log X); Y0 = soil property, X ffi time (yr); Y1 ffi a + bl(bo).  n = number of observations; a, b~ = regression coefficients; r = correlation coefficient;  *P = 0.05; **P = 0.01.    80    Multivariant functions--time and climate. The rates of change in oxidation  depth, solum thickness, electrical conductivity of the salt-enriched horizon,  total N and bulk density of the surface mineral horizon, and clay content of  the B horizon were correlated with variables representing climate (Table III).  For example, the rate of increase in electrical conductivity of the salt-enriched  horizon was inversely correlated with mean annual temperature (Fig. 4). A  comparison of the chronofunctions of electrical conductivity shows that solu-  ble salts accumulate 20 times more rapidly in Antarctica than on Baffin Island  (66) or in the Rocky Mountains (40).  As the mean annual temperature increases, the rate of increase in total N  in the surface soil decreases (Fig. 5). These trends are consistent with the find-  ings of Jenny et al. (1949). This can be attributed to increased microbial de-  composition at higher temperatures.  Bulk density of the surface mineral horizon increased with mean annual  precipitation and was the only soil property correlated with that climatic  variable (Table III).    104       Mean annual"                         /1  ten'cer~ure ('C)               /         0.4  1   -22                   /                /  2  -3e                i                          MEAN   ANNUAL  /  3   - 8.0  ~             ~~                   o~           ,      -~               /  2      -4.6              /  0.2  0        I0z     103     10      ~          I                                            104    Time (years)  Time  ,  Yeors    Fig. 4. Chronofunction of electrical conductivity of the salt-enriched zone for four climat-  ic regions: 1 = Wright Valley, Antarctica (Boekheim, 1979b): Y = --41.1 + 10.7 log X, r =  0.93**; 2 = Rocky Mtns., CO (Mahaney, 1974): Y = --0.099 + 0.167 log X, r = 0.86; 3 =  Baffin Island, Canada (Bockheim, 1979a): Y = --0.00373 + 0.00368 log X, r = 0.69; 4 =  interior Alaska (Viereck, 1970): Y = --0.000736 + 0.00144 log X, r = 0.97**.    Fig. 5. Chronofunctions of total nitrogen content of the surface mineral soil for four  climatic regions. 1 = Rocky Mtns.,.CO (Mahaney, 1974): I/" = --0.613 + 0.278 log X, r =  0.95*; 2 = Muldrow Glacier, Alaska (Viereck, 1966): Y = --0.178 + 0.149 log X, r = 0.99**;  3 = northern Minnesota (Leisman, 1957): Y = --0.0172 0.054 log X, r = 0.81"; 4 = north-  ern Indiana (Ruhe, 1956): Y = --0.00673 + 0.0169 log X, r = 0.83**.    81    "Self-terminating" processes. Whereas the magnitude of most of the soil pro-  perties examined in the present study continued to increase with time, the  values for several properties reached a maximum, then decreased with further  time. These properties included color development of the B horizon (two of  three chronofunctions), amount of forest floor (two of three cases), organic-  matter content of the surface mineral horizon (three of 11 cases), and percent  of dithionite-extractable iron in the B horizon (two of 11 cases).  Yaalon (1971) attributed these types of trends to "self-terminating" or ir-  reversible processes. For example, the decrease in free iron and of the strength  of color of the B horizon may represent a depletion in weatherable, iron-bear-  ing minerals in the solum. The trend in forest-floor accumulation may be ex-  plained by the effect on leaf fall of stocking and competition among trees dur-  ing vegetational succession (Dickson and Crocker, 1953b). Successional stage  could also have influenced the amount of organic matter in the surface miner-  al horizon in those instances where a decrease was noted after a certain point  in time.    CONCLUSIONS    Data contained in 32 chronosequences from the literature were used to  test three models for deriving soil chronofunctions. Fifteen soil properties  were selected for the analysis. The model, Y = a + (b log X), yielded the best  correlation between soil property (Y) and time (X). Because the chronose-  quences represented seven climatic regions and seven types of parent materi-  als, it was possible to compare the rate of change in a particular property  with variables representing these soil-forming factors, using linear regression  techniques.  The study provides a basis for identifying important trends in soil develop-  ment with time and future research needs. The trends shown in this study  cast some doubt as to whether soils reach a steady-state (dynamic equilibrium)  with their environment. Most of the properties investigated continued to  change, despite the passage of as many as 106 years. Moreover, there was no  difference in the capacity of the model, Y = a + (b log X), to predict the pro-  petty--age relationship for chronosequences spanning a 500-yr period than  for those covering a 10~-yr period. More than 85% of the correlation coeffici-  ents were statistically significant.  Climate plays an important role in controlling the rate of soil development.  In this study the rates of increase in solum thickness, oxidation depth, soluble-  salt content of the salt-enriched horizon, and clay content of the B horizon  are positively correlated with mean annual temperature, whereas the rate of in-  crease in total N in the surface mineral horizon is negatively correlated with  present-day mean annual temperature. The rate of increase in bulk density of  the surface soil is positively correlated with present mean annual precipitation.  The rate of soil development is also influenced by the nature of the parent  material. In this study, the rates of increase in clay content of the B horizon    82    and solum thickness are positively correlated with clay content of the parent  material.  Soil pH and base saturation decrease with time independently of climate,  parent material, and biotic factors.  For future research dealing with soil chronosequences, the following sug-  gestions are given. In constructing chronosequences, extreme care must be  exercised in making certain that the other soil-forming factors are invariant.  Dating of the sediments or landscapes on which the soils occur must be ac-  curate. Chronosequences established without dating or based on one date are  of limited value in the study of rates of soil formation.  Additional chronofunctions, particularly in tropical rainy, subtropical  desert, and humid continental regions, need to be prepared using the models  considered in this study and other more sophisticated models. Chronose-  quence data should be expressed in tables rather than graphs so that the rate  functions can be quantitatively solved. A standardization of methodology for  preparing chronofunctions would be useful, especially with regard to establish-  ing sampling depths or intervals, determining which properties are to be con-  sidered, and selecting laboratory methods and units for expressing the data.  Vreeken (1975) questioned the validity of what he called "post-incisive"  chronosequences, i.e., those which contain soils beginning at different points  in time and with a partial overlap in soil history, for studying pathways and  rates of soil development. Most chronosequences in the literature are post-  incisive. Those individuals preparing such chronosequences assume that the  soils have developed at the same rate, although some of the soils may be  polygenetic. Therefore, additional effort should be made to test the validity  of post-incisive chronosequences through an investigation of the effects of  climatic change, vegetational succession, and landscape evolution on soil  chronosequences.  Finally, we need to test the prediction equations established from the data  compiled in this study. New equations are needed for relating rates of change  in soil properties with variables representing climate and parent material. Ad-  ditional parameters expressing climate, parent material, and vegetation should  be considered.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    F.D. Hole, P.W. Birkeland and J.E. Leide kindly read an earlier draft of the  manuscript.    REFERENCES    Alexander, E.B., 1974. Extractable iron in relation to soil age on terraces along the Truckee  River, Nevada. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 38: 121--124.  Behling, E.R., 1971. Pedological Development on the Moraines of the Meserve Glacier,  Antarctica. Ph.D. Diss., Ohio State Univ., Columbus, OH., 216 pp.    ,f    83    Behling, R.E., 1972. Calculated dates of selected glacial events in Wright Valley. Antarct.  J. U.S., 7 (6): 247--248.  Bilzi, A.F. and Ciolkosz, E.J., 1977. Time as a factor in the genesis of four soils develop-  ed in recent alluvium in Pennsylvania. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 122--127.  Birkeland, P.W., 1968. Correlation of Quaternary stratigraphy of the Sierra Nevada with  that of the Lake Lahontan area. In: R.B. Morrison and H.E. Wright, Jr. (Editors), Means  of Correlation of Quaternary Successions. Utah Univ. Press, Salt Lake City, Utah, pp.  465--500.  Birkeland, P.W., 1974. Pedology, Weathering, and Geomorphological Research. Oxford  Univ. Press, London, 285 pp.  Birkeland, P.W., 1978. Soil development as an indication of relative age of Quaternary  deposits, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada. Arct. Alp. Res., 10 (4): 733--747.  Birkeland, P.W. and Shroba, R.R., 1974. The status of the concept of Quaternary soil-  forming intervals in the western United States. In: W.C. Mahaney (Editor), Quaternary  Environments. Proc. Syrup. Geogr. Monogr., York Univ., Atkinson College, Toronto,  pp. 241--276.  Bockheim, J.G., 1977. Soil development in the Taylor Valley and McMurdo Sound area.  Antarct. J. U.S., 12 (4): 105--108.  Bockheim, J.G., 1979a. Properties and relative age of soils of southwestern Cumberland  Peninsula, Baffin Island, N.W.T., Canada. Arct. Alp. Res., 11 (3): 289--306.  Bockheim, J.G., 1979b. Relative age and origin of soils in eastern Wright Valley,  Antarctica. Soil Sci.,~128: 142--152.  Campbell, I.B. and Claridge, G.G.C., 1975. Morphology and age relationships of  Antarctic soils. In: R.P. Suggate and M.M. Cresswell (Editors), Quaternary Studies. R.  Soc. N.Z., Bull., 13: 83--88.  Chandler Jr., R.F., 1942. The time required for podzol profile formation as evidenced by  the Mendenhall glacial deposits near Juneau, Alaska. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 7 : 454--  459.  Cline, M.G., 1957. Major kinds of profiles and their relationships in New York. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 17: 18--28.  Cowie, J.D., 1968. Soil--age relationships in the Manawatu District, New Zealand. Trans.  9th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., Adelaide, 4: 113--120.  Crocker, R.L. and Dickson, B.A., 1957. Soil development on the recessional moraines of  the Herbert and Mendenhall Glaciers, southeastern Alaska. J. Ecol., 45: 169--185.  Crocker, R.L. and Major, J., 1955. Soil development in relation to vegetation and surface  age at Glacier Bay, Alaska. J. Ecol., 43: 427--448.  Dickson, B.A. and Crocker, R.L., 1953a. A chronosequence of soils and vegetation near  Mt. Shasta, California, I. Definition of the ecosystem investigated and features of the  plant successions. J. Soil. Sci., 4: 123--141.  Dickson, B.A. and Crocker, R.L., 1953b. A chronosequence of soils and vegetation near  Mt. Shasta, California, II. The development of the forest floors and the carbon and  nitrogen profiles of the soils. J. Soil Sci., 4: 142--154.  Dickson, B.A. and Crocker, R.L., 1954. A chronosequence of soils and vegetation near Mt.  Shasta, California, III. Some properties of the mineral soils. J. Soil Sci., 5: 173--191.  Down, C.G., 1975a. Soil development on colliery waste tips in relation to age; introduction  and physical factors. J. Appl. Ecol., 12: 613--622.  Down, C.G., 1975b. Soil development on colliery waste tips in relation to age; chemical  factors. J. Appl. Ecol., 12: 623---635.  Evans, L.J. and Cameron, B.A., 1979. A ehronosequence of soils developed from granitic  morainal material, Baffin Island, N.W.T. Can. J. Soil Sci., 59: 203--210.  Franzmeier, D.P. and Whiteside, E.P., 1963a. A chronosequence of podzols in northern  Michigan, I. Ecology and description of pedons. Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn. Q. Bull., 46:  2--20.    84    Franzmeier, D.P. and Whiteside, E.P., 1963b. A chronosequence of podzols in northern  Michigan, II. Physical and chemical properties. Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn. Q. Bull., 46:  21--36.  Franzmeier, D.P., Whiteside, E.P. and Mortland, M.M., 1963. A chronosequence of podzols  in northern Michigan, III. Mineralogy, micromorphology, and net changes during soil  formation. Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn. Q. Bull., 46: 37--57.  Gennadiyev, A.N., 1978. Studying soil evolution by the method of chronological series  (exemplified by the soils of the Elbrus area). Pochvovedeniye, 12: 33--45.  Gennadiyev, A.N. and Sokolova, T.A., 1977. Trend and rate of clay formation in some  soils of the Elbrus area. Soy. Soil Sci., (6): 345--353.  Hay, R.L., 1960. Rate of clay formation and mineral alteration in a 4000 year old volcan-  ic ash soil on St. Vincent, B.W.I. Am. J. Sci., 258: 354--368.  Hendershot, W.H., Singleton, G.A. and Lavkulich, L.M., 1979. Variation in surface charge  characteristics in a soil chronosequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 387--389.  Holt, R.F. and McMUler, P.R., 1956. Characteristics of some forest soils from the gray-  brown podzolic-podzol transition zone in northeastern Minnesota. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  Proc., 20: 84--87.  Janda, R.J. and Croft, M.G., 1967. The stratigraphic significance of a sequence of noncalcic  brown soils formed on the Quaternary alluvium of the northeastern San Joaquin  Valley, California. In: R.B. Morrison and H.E. Wright, Jr. (Editors), Quaternary Soils.  Desert Res. Inst., Univ. Nevada, Reno, pp. 157--190.  Jenny, H., 1941. Factors of Soil Formation. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 281 pp.  denny, H., 1961. Deri,:a0on of state factor equations of soils and ecosystems. Soil Sci.  Soc. Am. Proc., 25: 385--388.  denny, H., Gessel, S.P. and Bingham, F.T., 1949. Comparative study of decomposition  rates of organic matter in temperate and tropical regions. Soil Sci., 68: 419--432.  denny, H., Salem, A.E. and Wallis, J.R., 1968. Interplay of soil organic matter and soil  fertility with state factors and soil properties. In: Organic Matter and Soil Fertility.  Pontif. Acad. Sci., Scr. Varia, 32: 1--33.  Leamy, M.L., 1974. The use of pedogenic carbonate to determine the absolute age of  soils and to assess rates of soil formation. 10th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., Moscow, 6 (2):  331--339.  Leisman, G.A., 1957. A vegetation and soil chronosequence on the Mesabi iron range  spoil banks, Minnesota. Ecol. Monogr., 27 : 221--245.  Mahaney, W.C., 1974. Soil stratigraphy and genesis of neoglacial deposits in the  Arapaho and Henderson cirques, central Colorado Front Range. In: W.C. Mahaney  (Editor), Quaternary Environments. Proc. Syrup. Geogr. Monogr., 5. York Univ.,  Atkinson College, Toronto, pp. 197--240.  Miller, C.D. and Birkeland, P.W., 1974. Probable pre-Neoglacial age of the type Temple  Lake moraine, Wyoming: discussion along with additional relative-age data. Arct. Alp.  Res., 6: 301--306.  Olson, J.S., 1958. Rates of succession and soil changes on southern Lake Michigan sand  dunes. Bot. Gaz., 119 (3): 125--170.  Pastor, J. and Bockheim, J.G., 1980. Soil development on moraines of Taylor Glacier,  Lower Taylor Valley, Antarctica. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 44 (in press).  Ruhe, R.V., 1956. Geomorphic surfaces and the nature of soils. Soil Sci., 82: 441--445.  Ruxton, B.P., 1968. Rates of weathering of Quaternary volcanic ash in northeast Papua.  Trans. 9th Int. Congr. Soil Sci., Adelaide, 4: 551--560.  Salisbury, E.J., 1925. Note on the edaphic succession in some dune soils, with special  reference to the time factor. J. Ecol., 13: 322--328.  Stevens, P.R. and Walker, T.W., 1970. The chronosequence concept and soil formation.  Q. Rev. Biol., 45: 333--350.  Stork, A., 1963. Plant immigration in front of retreating glaciers with examples from the  Kebnekajse area, northern Sweden. Geogr. Ann., 45 (1): 1--21.    85    Syers, J.K. and Walker, T.W., 1969a. Phosphorus transformations in a chronosequence of  soils developed on wind-blown sand in New Zealand, I. Total and organic phosphorus.  J. Soil Sci., 20 (1): 57--64.  Syers, J.K. and Walker, T.W., 1969b. Phosphorus transformations in a chronosequence of  soils developed on wind-blown sand in New Zealand, II. Inorganic phosphorus. J. Soil  Sci., 20 (2): 318--324.  Syers, J.K., Adams, J.A. and Walker, T.W., 1970. Accumulation of organic matter in a  ehronosequence of soils developed on wind-blown sand in New Zealand. J. Soil Sci.,  21: 146--153.  Trewartha, G.T., 1968. An Introduction to Climate. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 4th ed.,  408 pp.  Ugolini, G.C., 1968. Soil development and alder invasion in a recently deglaciated area of  Glacier Bay, Alaska. In: Biology of Alder. U.S. Dep. Agric., For. Serv., Pac. Northwest  For. Range Exp. Stn., Portland, OR., pp. 115--140.  Viereck, L.A., 1966. Plant succession and soil development on gravel outwash of the  Muldrow Glacier, Alaska. Ecol. Monogr., 36: 181--199.  Viereck, L.A., 1970. Forest succession and soil development adjacent to the Chena River  in interior Alaska. Arct. Alp. Res., 2 (1): 1--26.  Vreeken, W.J., 1975. Principal kinds of chronosequences and their significance in soil  history. J. Soil Sci., 26: 378--394.  Walker, T.W. and Syers, J.K., 1976. The fate of phosphorus during pedogenesis. Geoderma,  15: 1--19.  Wilson, K., 1960. The time factor in the development of dune soils at South Haven Penin-  sula, Dorset. J. Ecol., 48: 341--359.  Yaalon, D.H., 1971. Soil-forming processes in time and space. In: D.H. Yaalon (Editor),  Paleopedology--Origin, Nature and Dating of Paleosols. Int. Soc. Soil Sci. and Israel  Univ. Press, Jerusalem, pp. 29--39.  Yaalon, D.H., 1975. Conceptual models of pedogenesis: can soil-forming functions be  solved? Geoderma, 14 : 189--205.  Yassaglou, N.J., Nobeli, C. and Vrahamis, S.C., 1969. Study of some biosequences and  lithosequences in the zone of brown forest soils in northern Greece: morphological,  physical, and chemical properties. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 291--296.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractThirty-two chronosequences from 27 areas were selected from the literature for constructing chronofunctions and for correlating rates of change in soil properties with variables representing climate and parent material. The chronosequences originate from areas situated between 66°N and 78°S latitude and represent seven climatic regions, ranging from tropical rainy to cold desert, and seven types of parent materials, including till, aeolian sand, alluvium, mine spoil, volcanic ash, raised beach deposits, and mudflows. Fourteen of the chronosequences contain soils which range in age from 0 to 500 yr; seven span a 12,000-yr period, three a 100,000-yr period, and eight a period of greater than one million yr. Three linear and non-linear models were tested on 15 soil properties. The single-logarithmic (Y = a + b log X) model yielded the best correlation coefficients, when soil property (Y) was correlated with time (X), using linear regression techniques. The dates and equations allow for the following conclusions: 1.(1) The rates of decrease in pH and in base saturation are similar, regardless of the nature of the parent material or climate.2.(2) The rates of increase in clay content of the B horizon and solum thickness are positively correlated with clay content of the parent material.3.(3) The rates of increase in solum thickness, oxidation depth, soluble salt content of the salt-enriched horizon, and clay content of the B horizon are positively correlated with mean annual temperature whereas the rate of increase in total N in the surface mineral soil is negatively correlated with present-day mean annual temperature.4.(4) The increase in bulk density of the surface soil is positively correlated with present mean annual precipitation.5.(5) The rate of change in C:N is not correlated with variables representing climate and parent material. 