 Geoderma, 25 (1981) 307--326  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    307    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Ablayev, A. G.; and Sehmidt, I. N. The Neogene stage in the development of Sikhote Alin florae and  vegetation [abstr.]: in XIV Pacific science congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pacific  ring's Cenozoic (Shilo, N. A., editor), Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid  Earth., No. 14, Vol. 2, p. 3-5, 1979.  Adam, K. M.; Shariatmadar.Taleghani, M.; Henderson, I. G.; et aL Layered soil model criteria for  unsteady drainage: in Proceedings of the First national hydrogeological conference (Ozoray, G. F.,  editor), p. 195-217, illus. (incl. tables), Int. Assoc. Hydrogeol., Can. Natl. Chapter, Edmonton, Alberta,  Canada, 1979.  Adams, R.; Adams, M.; Willens, A.; et aL Dry lands; man and plants: 152 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), St. Martin's Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Afanas'yeva, T. V.; Tereshina, T. V.; and Bflyk, A. M. Gruppovoy i fraktsionnyy sostavy gumusa  izbytochno vlazhnykh pochv poymy reki Obi [Organic matter composition in over-moistened soils of the  Ob River plain]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye. Moscow., No. 1, p.  55-61, tables, 1979.  Akhanov, Zh. U.; Km'azhanov, K. D.; and Terekhov, G.S. Effektivnost' ornsheniya pochv v severnom  Kazakhstane [Effectiveness of irrigating soils in northern Kazakhstan]: 131 p., illus. (incl. tables), lzd.  ]~auka, Alma-Ata, Kazakhskoy SSR, Union of Soviet Socialist Repubfics, 1979.  Amayo, C. Holozaene Reliefentwicklung im mittleren Rheingau (Hessen) [Holocene relief development  in the middle RhcLngau, Hesse]: Geoiogisches Jahrbuch Hessen. Wiesbaden.,Vol. 107, p. 179-191 (incl.  English sum.), sects., color geol. map 1:25,000, 1979.  Anderson, C. E.; and Briggs, J. M. Planning erosion control for coal mining and restoration: Journal  of Soil and Water Conservation (Soil Conservation Society of America). Ankeny, Iowa., Vol. 34, No.  5, p. 234-236, illus., 1979.  Anderson, D.W. Processes of humus formation and transformation in soils of the Canadian Great Plains:  Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 77-84, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Anderson, D. W.; De Jong, E.; and McDonald, D. S. The pedogenetic origin and characteristics of  organic matter of Solod soils: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada).  Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, tables (incl. French sum.), 1979.  Anonymous.. La informacion de la Comision de Estudios de Territorio Nacional (CETENAL) en la  zonificacion agropecuaria y forestal con fines de una mejor planificacion y desarrollo de los recursos  naturales [Information provided by the National Land Survey Commission (CETENAL) in the  agricultural zoning of forestry reso.urces and major planning of natural resources]: in First United  Nations regional cartographic conference for the An tericas; Volume II; technical papers (Anonymous),  p. 320-338, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), U~,ted Nations, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Anonymous. Shorter contributions to geochem.~try, 1979: U.S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper.  Reston, Virginia., No. 1129 A-I, 66 p., 1980.  Anpfdnv, V. E.; and Lugovoi, V.P. Observation data on moisture-temperature regime of foundation soi!.~:  Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (English translation ofOsnovaniya Fundamenty i Mekhanika  Gruntov). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 16, No. 2, p. 74-77, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Antrop, M. The interpretation of soil marks on aerial photographs recorded over the Famenne (Belgium)  natural region: Pedologie (Societe Belge de Pedologie--Belgische Bodemkundige Vereniging, Bulletin).  Ghent., Vol. 29, No. 2, p. 209-240 (incl. French, Dutch sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.    308    Artiole, J.; and Fuller, W. H. Effect of crushed limestone barriers on chromium attenuation in soils:  Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 503-510, illus~ (incl. tables),  1979.  Atwater, B. F.; Canard, S. G.; Dowden, J. N.; et aL History, landforms, and vegetation of the estuary's  tidal marshes: in San Francisco Bay; the urbanized estuary; investigations into the natural history of San  Francisco Bay and delta with reference to the influence of man (Conomos, T. J., editor; eta/), p. 347-  ~7~, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), Pac. Div. Am. Assoc. Adv. Sci., San Francisco, Calif., United  Sta:es, 1.979. Fifty-eighth annual meeting of the Pacific Division~American Association for the Advancement  of Science.  Auffarth, J.; mid glockow, D. Fluoride microdetermination and its application to the analysis of rocks,  soil~, precipitation, and airborne dust: Analytica Chimica Acta. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol.  111, No. i, p. 89-102, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Averill, S.P. Late Woodfordian history of the Hackensack River valley, N.J.-N.Y. [ahstr.]: Geological  Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 2, p. 22, 1980.  The  Geological Society of America, Northeastern Section, 15th annual meeting.  Bain, W. R.; and Wattersun, A., Jr. Soil survey of Pushmataha County, Oklahoma: 153 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates, sketch maps; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in coop. with Okla. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Baldi, F.; Bm~gagll, R.; and Renzoni, A. The distribution of mercury in the surficial sediments of the  northern Tyrrhenian Sea: Marine Pollution Bulletin. Pergamon Press, Oxford-New York., Vol. 10, No.  10, p. 301-303, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  B~anova, Yu. P.; and Biske, S. F. Tertiary climates in Northeast Asia [abstr.]: in XIV Pacific science  congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pacific ring's Cenozoic (Shilo, N. A., editor),  Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid Earth., No. 14, Vol. 2, p. 25-26, 1979.  Barnes, J. R.; Bowman, W. L.; Earle, G. H., Jr.; et aZ Soil survey of Ingham County, Michigan: 142  p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Puhl. in cooperation with Mich. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Barnherdt, M.L. Late Quaternary glacial geomorphology of the Kearn Creek-Seuth Piney Creek area,  Bighorn Mountains, Wyoming: 241 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Illinois, Urbana, Ill. available from:Univ.  Microfilms.  Bm'raclough, D.; ~nd Ny% P.H. The effect of molecular size on diffusion characteristics in soil: Journal  of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 29-42, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Barrow, N. J.; and Shaw, T. C. Effects of ionic strength and nature of the cation on desorption of  phosphate from soil: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 53-65, illus. (il~cl. tables), 1979.  Barrow, N. J.; and Shaw, T. C. Effects of solution; soil ratio and vigour of shaking on the rate of  phosphate adsorption by soil: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 67-76, illus. (incl.  tables), 1979.  Barrett, M. S.; Brown, L. C.; Hanes, N. B.; et aL Denitrification in freshwater wetland soft: Journal  of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., VoL 8, No. 4, p. 460-464, illus. (incl. tables~ 1979.  Bathurst, R. G.C. Stromatactis; origin related to submarine-cemented crusts in Paleozoic mud mounds:  Geology (Geological Society of America). Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 8, No. 3, p. 131-134, illus., 1980.  Beauchmmp, E. G.; Soon, Y. K.; and Mayer, J. R. Nitrate-production from chemically treated sewage  sludges in soil: Journal of Environmental Quali~y. Madison, Wisconsin., Voi. 8, No. 4, p. 557-560, illus.  (incl. tables), 19"/9.  Benians, G.; and Helmy, A. K. A comment on the paper 'Isotopic exchange of phosphate on some  phosphatic compounds' by S. G. de Bussetti. E. A. Ferreiro and A. K. Helmy, J. Soil Sci. 28, 610-23:  Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 183-186, 1979.  Berner, R. A.; Sjoeberg, E. L,; Velbel, M. A.; et aL Dissolution of pyroxenes and amphiboles during  weathering: Science (American Association for the Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., VoL  207, No. 4436, p. 1205-1206, illus., 1980.    309    Best, E. K.; and Drover, D. P. The downward movement of surface applied K ions in a Papnan soil:  Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis. Marcel Dekker, New York-BaseL, Vol. 10, No. 12,  p. 1469-1479, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Bhattacharya, B. B.; Hazra, P. K.; Palaeky~ G. J.; et aL Effect of tropical weathering on electrical and  electromagnetic measurements: Geophysics (Society of Exploration Geophysicists, Journal). Tulsa,  Oklahoma., VoL 45, No. 7, p. 1205-1209, illus., 1980.  Birkeland, P. W.; Burke, R. M.; and Walker, A. L. Soils and subsurface rock-weathering features of  Sherwin and pre-Sherwin glacial deposits, eastern Sierra Nevada, California: Geological Society of  America, Bulletin. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 91, No. 4, p. 1 238-I 244, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1980.  Black, A. S.; and Wariag, S. A. Adsorption of nitrate, chloride and sulfate by some highly weathered  soils f~om South-east Queensland: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p.  271-282, illus. (incl. sketch map, tables), 1979.  Bleieh, K. E.; and SeMiehtiag, E. Nachweis und Vorkommen von Palaeoboeden in SW-Deutscbland  [Evidence of occurrence of Paleo~ols in :,outhwestern Gen,~-ny]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H.,  editor; et aL), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 168-181  (incl. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Biuemel, W. D.  Zur Struktur,  Reliefgebundenheit und Genese suedwestafrikanischer  und  suednstspanischer Kalkkrusten [The structure, relief relationship, and genesis of Southwest African and  Southeast Spanish fossil calcretes]: in Relief u~d Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et aL), Zeitschrift fver  Geomorpho]ogie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 154-167 (incl. English, French sum.),  illus. (incl. plates), 1979.  Biume, H.; and Barth, H.K. Lateritische Krus~stufe~-. in Australien [Lateritic crusts in Australia]: in  Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Z~itschrift flier Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-  Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 45-56 (incl. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Blume, H. P.; Hoffmann, R.; and Pachur, H. J. Periglaziaere Steinring- und Fr:~tkeilbildungen  norddeutscher Parabraunerden [Periglacial layering and frost wedge formation in the North German Para  brown soils]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et aL), Zeitschrifl fuer Geomorphologie,  Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 257-265 (incI. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. table),  1979.  Bollag, J. M.; and B,'~'abasz, W. Effect of heavy metals on the denitrification process in soil: Journal  of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 196-201, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Bradhury, J. P. Late Quaternery vegetation history" of the central Great Plains and its relationship to  eolian processes in the Ncbreska Sand Hills: ir Geologic and paler,ecologic studies of the Nebraska Sand  Hills (Anonymous), U. S. Geological ~urvey, ProfessionM Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1120 A-C, 1980.  Bremer, H. Relief und Boeden in den Tropen [Landforms and soils in the tropics~,: in Relief ,,~nd Boden  (Bremer, H., editor; et aL), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, !~upplementband. Berlin-Stuttga':t., Vol. 33,  p. 25-37 (incl. English, French sum.), illu~., 1979.  Brent, F. V., Jr. Soil survey of Lowndes County, Mississippi: 137 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1979.'~ubL in cooperation with Miss. Agric. For. Exp. Stn.).  Broekmum, L. C.; Eveason, E. E.; Strum, J. F.; et aL Soil survey of McLean County, North Dakota:  218 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:380,160), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.; U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur. Indian A~., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with North .D~kota Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Brooks, R.A. The geological parameters affecting in situ leaching of uranium deposits: U.S. Geological  Survey, Open-File Report. Reston, Virginia., No. 79-1238, 44 F., 1979. available from: U. S. Geol. Surv.,  Open-File Serv. Sect., Branch Distrib., Denver, Colo., United States.  Brown, L. R. Where has all the soil gone?: Mazin~ira (English edition). Pergamon Press, Oxford,  England., No. 10, p. 61-68, illus., 1979.  Bruanaeker, K. Zur Bodengeschichte des Jungquartaers im mediterranen Raum [Quaternary soils in the  Mediterranean region]: in Refief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Oeomorphologie,  Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 109-117 (incl. French, English sum.), illus., 1979.    310    Brtmsden, D. Weathering: in Process in geomorphology (Embleton, C., editor; et al.), ~. 73-129, illus.  (incl. tables, charts, sketch maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Bugrov, A. K.; and Zarkhi, A.A. Solution of mixed problems of the theories of elasticity and plasticity  of soils fo[ various schemes of bases: Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (English translation  ofOsnovaniya Fundamenty i Mekhanika Gruntov). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 16, No. 2, p.  85-90, illus., 1979.  Bull, W. B.; Menges, C. M.; and McFadden, L.D. South front of ~he San Gabriel Mountains, Southern  California; tectonic geomorphology of the Palmdale Uplift region; stream terraces of the San Gabriel  Mountains, Southern California: IG0 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979. amilablefrom:U. S. Geol.  Surv., Menlo Park, Calif., United States.  Burrows, C. J.; and Greenland, D. E. An analysis of the evidence for climatic change in New Zealand  in the last thousand years; evidence from diverse natural phenomena and from instrumental records:  Royal Society of New Zealand, Journal (supersedes Royal Society of New Zeahnd, Transactions).  Wellington., Vol. 9, No. 3, p. 321-373, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Bushue, L. ,L Soil survey of Adams County, Illinois: 143 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps; colored  soils map 1:253,440; soils map 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Pubi. in cooperation with Ul. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Calkin, P. E.; and MeAndrews, J. H. Geology and paleontology of two late Wisconsin sites in western  New York State: Geological Society of America, Bulletin. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 91, No. 5, p. 1 295-  I 306, illus. (incl. tables, charts, sketch map), 1980.  Campbell, N. Alpine karst of the Scapegoat-Bob Marshall Wilderness and adjoining areas, North-  Central Montana: in Alpine karst symposium OVerner, E., editor), The NSS (National Speleological  Society) Bulletin. Hunstville, Alabama., V ol. 41, No. 3, p. 66-69, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Geomorpt, ology and geohydrology of alpine karat terrains of the Rocky Mountaing" annual meeting of the  Geological Society of Americ,,  Candland, D. M. Soil survey of Carson City area, Nevada: 169 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps;  colored soils map 1:126,720; soils maps 1:24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Forest Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Nev. Agric. Exp. Stn., U. S. Dep.  Inter., Bur. Land Manage., Bur. Indian Affairs).  Cannon, H. L.; and Swanson, V. E. Contributions of major and minor elements to soils and vegetation  by the coal-fired Four Corners Power Plant, San Juan County, New Mexico: in Shorter contributions  to geochemistry, 1979 (Anonymous), U. S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston. Virginia., No.  1129 A-I, p. BI-B13, 1980.  Carbon, B. A.; Murray, A. M.; and Bartle, G.A. Prediction of depth to water table in bauxite residue  ponds: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 263-269, illus., 1979.  Car~gnan, R.; and Kaiff, J.  Phosphorus sources for aquatic weeds; water or sediments?:  Science  (American Association for the Advancement of Science). Washington, D. C., Vol. 207, No. 4434, p. 987-  989, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Carter, M. R.; Webster, G. R.; and Cairns, R. R. Effect of moisture change and salinity on the Mg/Ca  ratio of Ca/total cations in soil solutions: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of  Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 439-443, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Chalmers, J. A.; and Western, P. G. A Tertiary igneous centre north of the Shetland Islands: Scottish  Journal of Geology. Edinburgh., Vol. 15, Part 4, p. 333-341, illus., !979.  Clhauhan, R. P. S.; and Chauhan, C. P. S. A modification to Schoonover's method, of gypsum  requirement determination ef soil: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p.  365-370, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Chlehester, F. W.; Van Keuren, R. W.; and McGuinness, J.L. Hydrology and chemical quality of flow  from small pastured watersheds; II, Chemical quality: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison,  Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 167-t71, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Cho, C. M.; and Mills, J.G. Kinetic formulation of the denitrification process in soil: Canadian Journal  of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vole 59, No. 3, p. 249-257 (incl. French sum.),  illus., 1979.    311    Cleary, W. J.; and Hosier, P. E. Geomorphology, washover history, and inlet zonation; Cape Lookout,  North Carolina to Bird Island, North Carolina: in Barrier islands from the Gulf of St. Lawrence to the  Gulf of Mexico (Leatherman, S. P., editor), p. 237-271, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Acad. Press,  New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Coastal research symposium.  Coote, D. R.; and Hore, F.R. Contamination of shallow groundwater by an unpaved feedlot: Canadian  Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 401-412 (incl.  French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Cortez, J.; and Sehnitzer, M. Nt~cleic acid ba~es in soils and their association with organic and inorganic  soil components: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Cana,la). Ottawa., Vol. 59,  No. 3, p. 277-286 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Crosby, E. C. Simulation of the effects of contour coal strip mining on stormwater response and  suspended sediment yield in the New River watershed, Tennessee: 223 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of  Tennessee, Knoxville, Tenn. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Crowner, D. The well drained soils of Arctic Alaska; a taxonomic challenge [abstr.]: in 89th annual  meeting of the Ohio Academy of Science (DiDio, L. J. A., president), Ohio Journal of Science.  Columbus., Vol. 80, p. 33, 1980.  Dahm-Arens, H. Boeden und Relief der Warburger Boerde und ihrer Umrahmung [Soils and relief of  the Warburg Boerde and its surroundings]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift  fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin--Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 207-215 (incl. English, French  sum.), illus., 1979.  de Bakker, H. Major soils and soil regions in the Netherlands: 203 p., illus. (incl. plates, tables, sketch  maps), Dr. W. Junk i~. V. Publ., The Hague, Netherlands, 1979.  De Kimpe, C. R.; Laverdiere, M. R.; and Met'tel, Y. A. Surface area and exchange capacity of clay in  relation to the mineralogical composition of Gieysolic soils:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science  (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 341-347, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  de Mautort, J.; and Paloe, H. Exemples d'evaluation de la eapacite d'absorption des eaux pluviales par  le sous-sol calcaire a l'occasion de projets d'assainissement en zones urbaines [Evaluation of the  absorption capacity of rain water by limestone subsoil; purification projects in urban zones]: in Connaitre  le sous-sol un atout pour l'amenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau  de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Pari,.,., No. 8, p. 793-803, illus., 1979.  Dormant, J. F. Organic matter characteristics of undisturbed and cultivated Chernozemic and  Solonetzic A horizons: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa.,  Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 349-356 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Dufaure, J. J.; Bousquet, B.; and Pechanx, P.  Contributions de la geomorphoiogie a la connaissance  du Quaternaire continental grec, en relation avec les etudes de neotectonique [Geomorphological  contributions to the knowledge of the continemal Quaternary of Greece, in connection with studies in  neotecto~ics]: in Neotectonique de rAre Egeea (Raoult, J, F., editor), Revue de (3eographie Physique  et de Geologic Dynamique. Paris., Vol. 21, No. 1, p. 29-40 (incl. English sum.), table, sects., block diags.,  geol. sket=h maps, 1979.  Dumanski, J.; Marshall, I. B.; and Huffman, E.C. Soil capability analysis for regional land use planning;  a study of the Ottawa urban fringe: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada).  Ottawa., Vok 59, No. 4, p. 363-379 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Dumanski, J.; Pawluk, S.; Vueetieh, C. G.; 2t ~Pedogenesis and tephrochronology of loess derived  soils, Hinton, Alberta: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences (National Research Council of Canada).  Ottawa., Vol. 17, No. 1, p. 52-59 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.  Dupuis, T.; Jambn, P.; and Righi, D. Reaction des acides fulviques avec des hydroxydes metalliques;  cas des hydroxydes d'aluminium [Reactions of fulvic acids with metallic hydroxides; especially aluminum  hydroxide]: Pedologie (Societe Beige de Pedologie--Belgisehe Bodemkundige Vereniging, Bulletin).  Ghent., Vol. 29, No. 2, p. 191-207 (incl. English, Dutch sum ~ illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Ei'yanov, M. D.; Khorosheva, D. P.; and Timoshenko, I.L. Metallogenicheskoye rayonirovaniye kory  vyvetrivaniya Ukrainskog shchita [Metallogenetic zonation of the Ukrainian Shield crust of weathering]:  Geologicheskiy Zhurrml (Russian edition ofGeologichniy ZhurnsI). Akademiya Nauk URSR, Kiev., Vol.  39, No. !, p. 1-11 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.    312    Embleton, C. Nival processes: m Process in geomorphology (Embleton, C., editor; et al.)~ p. 307-324,  illus. (incl. tables, charts), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Embleton, C.; and Thornes, J. (editors). Process in geomorphology: 436 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Embleton, C.; and Thomes, J. Sub-surface processes: it, Process in geomorphology (Embleton, C.,  editor; et aL), p. 187-212, illus. (incl. table, chart), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States,  1979.  Embleton, C.; and Whalley, B. Energy, forces, resistances and responses: in Process in geomorphology  (Embleton, C., editor; et aL), p. 11-38, illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United  States, 1979.  Ensz, E.H. Soil survey of Yankton County, South Dakota: 172 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with South Dakota Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Eswaran, H.; and Sys, C. Argiilic horizon in LAC soils; formation and significance to classification:  Pedologie (Societe Beige de Pedologie--Belgische Bodemkundige Vereniging, Bulletin). Ghent., Vol. 29,  No. 2, p. 175-190 (incl. French, Dutch sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Eswaran, H.; Van Wambeke, A,; and Beinroth, F.. H. A study of some highly weathered soils of Puerto  Rico, micromorphological properties: Pedologie (Societe Beige de Pedoiogie--Belgische Bodemkundige  Vereniging, Bulletin). Ghent., Vol. 29, No. 2, p. 139-162 (incl. French, Dutch sum.), illus. (incl. plate),  1979.  Felix-Henningsen, P. Genese und Stratigraphie maechtiger Palaeoboeden in der Drenthe-Moraene des  Roten Kliffs yon Syit [Genesis and stratigraphy of Paleosols in the Drenthe moraine of the red cliffs of  Sy!t]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et aL), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband.  Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 223-231 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Ferguson, D. V. Soil survey of Craighead County, Arkansas: 110 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps;  colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Arkansas Agrie. Exp. Stn.).  Fiskeil, J. G. A.; Mansell, R, S.; Selim, H. M.; et aL Kinetic behavior of phosphate sorption by acid,  sandy soil: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 579-584, illus.,  1979.  Foelster, H. Holozaene Umlagerung pedogenen Materials und ihre Bedeutung fuer fersiallitische  Bodendecken [Holocene soil distribution and its significance for fersiallitic soil crusts]: in Relief und  Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et aLL Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart.,  Vol. 33, p. 38-45 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Follmer, L. R. A historical review of the Sangamon Soil: in Wisconsinan, Sangamonian, and lllinoian  (Follmer, L. R., leader; et aL), Illinois, State Geological Survey, Guidebook Series. Urbana., No. 13, p.  79-91, illus. (ind. sketch map), 1979.  Fordham, A. W.; and Norrish, K. Electron microprobe and electron microscope studies of soil clay  particles: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 283-306, illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Fordham, A. W.; and Norr~h, K. Arsenate-73 uptake by components of several acidic soils and its  implications for phosphate retention: Avg,'ralian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2,  p. 307-316, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Foster, S. S. D.; and Smith-Carington, A. The interpretation of tritium in the Chalk unsaturated zone:  Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 46, No. 3-4, p. 343-364, illus. (incl.  tables, sketch map), 1980.  Fuller+ W. H.; and Alesfi, B.A. Behavior of municipal solid waste leachates; II, Iri soil: Jou~al of  Environmental Science and Health; Part A, Environmental Science and Engineering (formerly  Environmental Letters). Marcel Dekker, New York., Vol. 14, No. 7, p. 559-592, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Fung, P. C.; Bird, G. W.; and Sanipelli, G. G. Surface studies of feldspar alteration [abstr.]: Eos  (American Geophysical Union, Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 46, p. 975, 1979.  American Geophysical Union; 1979faii annual meeting.    313    Gardner, W. M. The Thunderbird Paleo-Indian site and the Middle Shenando.Jh Valley Research  Program, 1971-1974: in On research and exploration supported by grants from the I~Tational Gengrt, phic  Society during the year 1970 (Oehser, P. H., compiler; et al.), National Geographic Society, Research  Reports. Washington, D. C., No. 11, p. 165-175, 1979.  Gehrenkemlrer, J. Sediment- und Bodendifferenzierung am mittleren Tajo ~Zentralspanien) [Sediment  and soil differences at the central Tagus River, central Spain]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor;  et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 143-151 (incl.  English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Gerasimov, I. P. (editor). Genet[cheskiye tipy pochv subtropikov Zakavkaz'ya [Genetic soil types of  the Transcaucasus subtropics]: 271 p., tables, Izd. Nauka, Moscow, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics,  1979.  Gierbofini, R. E. Soil survey of the Ponce area of southern Puerto Rico: 81 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch  maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Pubi. in cooperation with Univ. P.R., Coll. Agric. Sci.).  Gill, H. V.; Avery, D. C.; Larance, F. C.; et aL Soil survey of Ashley County, Arkansas: 92 p., illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps; colored soils map 1:253,440; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv. For. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Arkansas  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Giterman, R. E.; and Kartashova, G. G. On Pliocene vegetation of the Far Northeast USSR [abstr.]:  in XIV Pacific science congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pacific ring's Cenozoic  (Shilo, N. A., editor), Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid Earth., No. 14,  Voi. 2, p. 54-55, 1979.  Glenn, G.R. Analysis of soils, construction, and geologic materials from the Ai (et Tell) excavations,  Israel: inOn research and exploration supported by grants from the National Geographic Society during  the year 1970 (Oehser, P. H., compiler; et aL), National Geographic Society, Research Reports.  Washington, D. C., No. 11, p. 177-205, illus., 1979.  Godfrey, P. 3.; Leatherman, S. P.; and Zaremba, R. A geobotanieai approach to classification of barrier  beach systems: in Barrier islands from the Gulf of St. Lawrence to the Gulf of Mexico (Leatherman,  S. P., editor), p. 99-126, illus. (incl. tables, sects., sketch maps), Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United  States, 1979. Coastal research symposium.  Golden, J. M. Percolation theory and models of unsaturated porous media: Water Resources Research  (American Geophysical Union). Washington, D.C., Vol. 16, No. 1, p. 201-209, illus., 1980.  Goodman, B. A.; and Cheshire, M. V. A Mossbauer spectroscopic study of the effect of pH on the  reaction between iron and humic acid in aqueous media: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No.  1, p. 85-91, illus., 1979.  Goodwin, R. A., Jr. Soil survey of Edgecombe County, North Carolina: 118 p., illus. (incl. tables, p!ates,  sketch maps; colored soils map 1:253,440; soils maps 1:20,000), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with N.C. Agric. Exp. Stn. Edgecombe Cty.  Board Comm.).  Gozzi, J.; and Millies.Laeroix, A. La connaissance du sous-sol; cle de l'amenagement du territoire [The  understanding of the subsoil is the key to management of the land]: in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout  pour, ramenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de Recherches  Geolngiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 655.660, 1979.  Grabandt, R. A.J. Pollen rain in relation to arboreal vegetation in the Colombian Cordillera Oriental:  Review of Palaeobotany and Palynolngy. Elsevier Sei. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 29, No. 1-2, p. 65-  147 (incl. Spanish sum.), illus. (incl. tables, charts, sketch map), 1980.  Graetz, D.; and Perry, R. Land use in arid Australia: in Advances in desert and arid land technology  and development; Volume 1 (Bishay, A., editor; et aL), p. 151-178, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps),  Harwood Acad. Publ., Chin, Switzerland, 1979. International conference on the applications of ~cience and  technology for desert development  Gulllope, P.; and Poter, M. Cartngraphie des risques ZERMOS appliques a des plans d'occupation  des sols en Normandie [ZERMOS cartography of hazards applied to the soil maps in Normandy]: in  Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour ramenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM  (Bureau de Recherches Geolngiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 667-676, 1979.    314    Gunn, R. H.; and Richardson, D. P. The nature and possible origins of soluble salts in deeply weathered  landscapes ofeastern Australia: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 197-  215, sketch map, table, 1979.  Hail, C. W.; Love, P. M.; and Forsythe, P. Soil survey of Boyd and Greenup counties, Kentucky: 128  p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric.,  Soil Conserv. Sere, Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Kent. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Haith, D. A.; and Loehr, R. C. (editors). Effectiveness of soil and water conservation practices for  pollution control: 474 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. EPA-600/ 3-79-106) available from: NTIS,  Springfield, Va., United States.  Hanna, A. A. Y.; Harlan, P. W.; and Lewis, D.T. Runoff and soil loss under a center pivot irrigation  system ~n Crete and Wymore soils in Nebraska: Nebraska Academy of Sciences, Transactions. Lincoln.,  Voi. 7, t~- 31-35, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Harden, J. W.; and Marehand, D. E. Quaternary stratigraphy and interpretation of soil data from the  Auburn, Oroviile, and Sonora areas along the foothills fault system, western Sierra Nevada, California:  U. S. Geological Survey, Open-File Report. Reston, Virginia., No. 80-305, 60 p., 1980. available from:  U. S. Geol. Sure., Open-File Sere. Sect., Branch Distrib., Denver, Colo., United States.  Harris, C.; and Ellis, S. Micromorphology of soils in solifiucted materials, Okstindan, northern Norway:  Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Voi. 23, No.  1, p. 11-29, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1980..  Hartley, A. Weathering studies of Bougainville mine tailings in lysimeters: Australian Journal of Soil  Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 355-360, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Hashimoto, T.; Taniguehi, K.; Sugiyama, H.; et aL Simultaneous determination of uranium and  plutonium isotopes in soils by means of single alpha-spectrometry:  Journal of Radioanalytical  Chemistry. Elsevier Sequoia, Lausanne., Vol. 52, No. 1, p. 133-142, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Hatherly, D. T.; Mays, D.; and Holt, T.H. Soil survey of Henderson County, Texas: 125 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Headyt E. 04 and Voeke, G.  Programmed impacts of environmental restraints applied I o U.S.  agriculture: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 143-148, illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Hell, D. M. Soil survey of.Beadle County, South Dakota: 169 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agrie., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with South Dakota Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Hemley, J. J.; Montoya, J. W.; Marinenko, J. W.; et aL Equilibria in the system AI203-SiO2-H20 and  some get~eral implications for alteration/mineralization processes: Economic Geology and the Bulletin  of the Society of Economic Geologists. New Haven, Connecticut., Vol. 75, No. 2, p. 210-228, illus. (incl.  tables), 1980.  Herren, E.C. Soil survey of Anderson County, South Carolina: 79 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps;  soil maps !:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with South Carolina Agric. Exp. Stn. and South Carolina  Land Resour. Conserv. Comm.).  Hersman, L. E.; and Klein, D. A. Retorted oil shale effects on soil microbiological characteristics:  Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 520-524, illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Hetseh, W.; and Foelster, H. Klimazonale Bodenbildung und Palaeobodenreste in den venezolanischen  und kolumbianischen Anden [Climate controlled soil formation and Paleosols in the Andes Mountains  of Colombia and Venezuela]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer  Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 72-83 (incl. English, French sum.),  illus., 1979.  Hohberger, K.; and Einsele, G. Die Bedeutung des Loesungsabtrags verschiedener Gesteine fuer die  Landschaftsentwicklung in Mitteleuropa [The significance of chemical denudations of different rock  types of Central Europe]: Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphoiogie--Annals of Geomorphology--Annales de  Geomo.~phologie. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 23, No. 4, p. 361-382 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1979.    315    II'in, A. G.; Eremeev, V. G.; and Svetinskii, E.V. Preconstruction consolidation of weak saturated soils  using earth drains:  Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (English translation of Osnovaniya  Fundamenty i Mekhanika Gruntov). Consultants B,reau, New York., Vol. 16, No. 2, p. 103-105, illus.  (incl. plate), 1979.  Irnitskii, K. N.; and Shvets, V.B. Standardized characteristics of eluvial clay soils formed by weathering  of argillitcs and aleurolites:  Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (English translation of  Osnovaniya Fundamenty i Mekhanika Gruntov). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 16, No. 2, p. 70-  73, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Isaev, B. N.; Zelenskii, V. Yu.; Shuvalova, L. P.; et al. Stabilization of saturated loess soils by gas  silication: Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (English translation ofOsnovaniya Fundamcnty  i Mekhanika Gruntov). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 16, No. 2, p. 65-69, illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Jantz, D. R.; and Sniffy, O. W. Soil survey of Dickinson County, Kansas: 94 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; colored soils maps 1:253,440; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Kans. Agric. Exp, Stn.).  Jennings, J. N. Arnhem Land, city that never was: Geographical Magazine. London., Vol. 51, No. 12,  p. 822-827, illus. (incl. sketea map), 1979.  Johns, G. G. Selection and use of representative sites in a large neutron moisture meter network:  Australian 3ournal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 249-261, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Johnson, B. Formation of grus; fracture mechanics considerations [abstr.]: Geological Society of  America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 4, 1980. The GeologicalSociety  of America, South-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  -Iohnson, D. W.; Breuer, D. W.; and Cole, D. W. The influence of anion mobility on ionic retention in  waste water-irrigated soils: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8. No. 2, p.  246-250, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Jones, L. M. The case for Recent chemical weathering in Antarctica; an application of strontiam isotc, pc  geochemistry [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol.  12, No. 1, p. 4, 1980.  The Geological Society of America, South-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  Jorgensen, W. Soil survey of Jefferson County, Idaho: 219 p., illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:24,000),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979.  Kabata-Pendias, A. Geochemia pierwiastkow sladowych w glebach [The geochemistry of trace elements  in soils]: Przeglad Geologiczny. Warsaw., Vol. 27, No. 10(318), p. 543-546 (incl. English, Russian sum.),  illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Kaveh, F. Tile drainage on sloping land including uns tturated flow: 210 p., Doctoral, 1979, Utah State  Univ., Logan, Utah. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Kilpatriek, P.A. Simulation of the effects of transpira :ion losses from the unsaturated zone on seepage  from a soil slope: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 46, No. 3-4, p. 301-  309, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  King, J. E.  Pollen analysis of some Farmdalian and Woodfordian deposits, central Illinois:  in  Wisconsinan, Sangamoniar., and IIlinoian (Follmer, L. R., leader; et al.), Illinois, State Geological Survey,  Guidebook Series. Urbana., No. 13, p. 109-113, illus., 1979.  Knauss, K. G.; and Ku. "7- ~. ~'~esert varnish; potential for age dating via uranium-series isotopes: Journal  of Geology. Chicage lilinois., Vol. 88, No. 1, p. 95-100, tables, 1980.  Kopsick, D.A. Chemical characteristics of a coal processing waste pile, SE Kansas [abstr.]: Geological  Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 5, 1980.  The  Geological Society of America, South-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  Korniyenko, V. A.; Kreyzo, N. P.; Grabarov, P. G. (editors); et al. Genezis i melioratsiya zasolennykh  pochv Kazakhstana [The genesis and development of saline soils of Kazakhstan]: 192 p., Izd. Nauka,  Alma-Ata, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1979.  Korzhinskiy, A.F. Vtorichnyye mineraly grafitovykh rud Zavaryevskogo mestorozhdeniya [Secondary  minerals of the graphite ores in the Zavarye Deposit]:  Mineralogicheskiy Sbornik (L'vovskiy  Gosudarstvennyy Universitet). Lvov., Vol. 33, No. 1, p. 110-116 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables),  1979.    316    Kress0 B. M.; and Vogt, H. Untersuchungen yon Moorbrei mit Ultrasehall [Ultrasound examination of  swamp mud]: Telma; Berichte der Deutschen Gesselschaft fuer Moor-und Torf~.unde. Hannover., Vol.  9, p. 225-228 incl. English sum.), illus., 1979.  Krings, T. Der Sahel yon Obervolta [The Sahel of Upper Volta]: Oeographische Rundschau. Georg  Westermann Verlag, Braunschweig., VoL 31, No. 9, p. 372-378, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Kuroda, T.; and Hatauaka, K. Palynologieal study of the late Quaternary in the coastal plain along  Hakata Bay, in Fukuoka City, northern Kyushu, Japan: Quaternary Research (Japan Association for  Quaternary Research). Tokyo., Vol. 18, No. 2, p. 53-68 (incl. Japanese sum.), illus. (incl. tables, plates,  sketch map), 1979.  LaBrecque, J. J.  Application of radioisotope excited energy dispersive X-ray fluorescence  determination of palladium in catalysts and doped Venezuelan laterites: Journal of Radioanalyticai  Chemistry. Elsevier Sequoia, Lausanne., Voi. 53, No. 1-2, p. 213-223, illus. (incl. tables, plates), 1979.  Lange, R.T. Evidence of lid-cells and host-specific microfungi in the search for Tertiary Eucalyptus:  Review of Palaeobotany and Palynology. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., Voi. 29, No. 1-2, p. 29-  33, plate, 1980.  Lmagford, K. J.; Moran, R. J.; and O'Shaughnessy, P. J. The North Maroondah Experiment  pretreatment phase comparison of catchment water balances: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 43, No. 1-2, p. 123-145, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Larsen, R. J.; Wiggins, T. J.; Holden, D. L.; et ai. Soil survey of Pueblo area, Colorado; parts of Pueblo  and Cust.er counties: 90 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map  1:380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in  cooperation with Colo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Le Roux, J.; Clayton, R. N.; and Jackson, M.L. Oxygen isotopic ratios in fine quartz silt from sediments  and soils of southern Africa: Geochimica et Cosmoehimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal).  Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 3, I:- 533-538, tables, 1980.  Lerch, N. K.; Hale, W. F.; and Lemaster, D.D. Soil survey of Butler County, Ohio: 175 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; colored, soils map h190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Die. Lands  Soils; Ohio Agri Res. Dee. Cent.).  Levesque, M. P.; and Mathur, S. P. A comparison of various means of measuring the degree of  decomposition of virgin peat materials in the context of their relative biode3radability: Canadian Journal  of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 397-400 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Lilidberg, S. E.; Jackson, D. R.; Haekabee, J. W.; et al. Atmospheric emission and plant uptake of  mercury from zgricultural soils near the Almaden mercury mine: Journal of Environmental Quality.  Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 572-578, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Linebaek, J. A. The status of the lllinoian glacial stage: in Wisconsinan, Sangamonian, and lllinoian  (Follmer, L. R., leader; et al.), Illinois, State Geological Survey, Guidebook Series. Urbanao, No. ! 3, p.  69-78, illus. (incl. table, sketch map), 1979.  Loevborg, L.; Botter-Jensen, L.; Kirkegam.d, P.; et aL Monitoring of natural soil radioactivity with  portable gamma-ray spectrometers: Nuclear Instruments and Methods. North-Holland Publishing  Company, Amsterdam., Vol. 167, No. 2, p. 341-348, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Lohmar, J. 1~.; Macdonald, K. B.; and Janes, S. A. Late Pleistocene-Holocene ~imentary infilling  and faunal change in a southern California coastal lagoon [abstr.]: AAPG (American Association of  Petroleum Geologists) Bulletin. Tulsa., Vol. 6 No. 3, p. 445-446, 1980.  ,4APG-SEPM-SEG Pacific  sections, annual meeting.  Long, B. M. Soil survey of Berkeley County, South Carolina: 94 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored  soils map 1:316,800; soils maps h20,000), U. S. Dep. Agile., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with S.C. Land Resour. Conserv. Comm. and S.C. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Longworth, G.; Beeker, L.W.;Thompson, R.; eta~ Mossba~ereffect and magnetic studies of secondary  iron oxides in soils: Journal of Sol! Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 93-110, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.    317    Lyle, E. S., Jr.; Wood, P. A.; and Hajek, B. F., Jr. Classification of coal surface mine soil material for  vegetation management and soil water quality: 40 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. 600/79-123)  available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Malaisse, F.; Gregoire, J.; Morrison, R. S.; et al. Copper and cobalt in vegetation of Fungurume, Shaba  Province, Zaire: Oikos (Acta Oecologica Scandinavica). Copenhagen., Vol. 33, No. 3, p. 472-477 (incl.  Bulgarian sum.), illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979.  Markmaas, L. D.; Barry, E. F.; Giuffre, G. P.; et al. An improved procedure for the determination of  lead in environmental samples by atomic absorption spectroscopy: Journal of Environmental Science  and Health; Part A, Environmental Science and Engineering (formerly Environmental Letters). Marcel  Dekker, New York., Vol. 14, No. 6, p. 501-506, tables, 1979.  Martin, P. L'infiltration dans le sons-sol des eaux de ruisse!lement des zones urbanisees [Infiltration of  running water in the subsoil of urban zones]: in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour l'amenagement  urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres).  Paris., No. 8, p. 749-752, 1979.  Martin, P. La pollution du sous-sol des zones urbanisees par les hydrocarbures [Pollution of urban  subsoil zones by hydrocarbons]: in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour l'amenagement urbain; tome 2  (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8,  p 753-761, 1979.  Matsatani, A. Microscopic study of the amorphous silica and charcoal from the Douara Cave: Tokyo,  University, University Museum, Bulletin., No. 16, p. 225-233, sketch map, tables, pian, plates. 1979.  MeCammon, C. A.; and Burns, R. G. The oxidation mechanism of vivianite as studied by Mossbauer  spectroscopy and Monte Carlo simulation methods [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts  with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 474, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd  annual meeting  MeHugh, J. B.; and Turner, J. H. Indirect determination of chloride in plants by atomic-absorption  spectrophotometry: in Shorter contributions to geochemistry, 1979 (Anonymous), U. S. Geological  Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1129 A-I, p. FI-F3, 1980.  MeKeague, J. A.; and Wolynetz, M. L. Strontium-calcium relationship in Canadian soils: Canadian  Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 4, p. 445-450, 1979.  MeWillims, K. M. Soil survey of Posey County, Indiana: 155 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps;  colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Mehrota, R. C.; Varma, S. N.; and Singh, B. K. Physico-chemical behaviour of hydrated aluminium  oxides and associated clay minerals occurring around Pipra, District Sidhi, India: Jgurnal of Thermal  Analysis. Heyden &amp; Son, London-Akademiai Kiado, Budapest., Vo!. 16, No. 2, p. 453-462 (incl. French,  German, Russian sum.), illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Merrilees, D. The prehistoric environment in Western Australia: Royal Society of Western Australia,  Journal. Perth., Voi. 62, Parts 1-4, p. 109-128, illus. (incl. sketch map, table), 1979.  Metson, A. J.; Biakemore, L. C,; and Rlhoades, D. A. Methods for the determination of soil organic  carbon; a review, and application to New Zealand soils: New Zealand Journal of Science. Wellington.,  VoL 22, No. 3, p. 205-228, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Mikhayliehenko, V. N.; and Borovskiy; V. M. (editor}. Galogenez i osolontsevaniye pochv ravnin  Severnogo Kazakhstana [Ilaiogenesis and the salinization of soils in the lowlands of northern  Kazakhstan]: 170 p., illus. (incl. tables), Izd. Nauka, Alma-Ata, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics,  !979.  Miles, N. M.; Wang, C.; and MeKeague, J.A. Chemical and clay mineralogical prope~ies of Ortstein  soils from the Maritime Provinces: Canadian Journal of Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada).  Ottawa., Vol. 59, No. 3, p. 287-299 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Miller, K.F. Soil survey of Grant County, South Dakota: 177 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch maps;  colored soils maps 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation witi, 3.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Minzenmayer, Fo E. Soil survey of Jim Wells County, Texas: 111 p., illus. (incl. t~tbles, plates; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1979. (PubL in cooperation with "rex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).    318    Mitchell, W. W.; Loynachan, T. E.; and McKendrick, J. D. Effects of tillage and fertilization on  persistence of crude oil contamination in an Alaskan soil: Journal of El vironmental Quality. Madison,  Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 525-532, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map~, 1979.  Miyamoto, S.; and Tram, J. Sorption of a dispersed dye by sand and soil: Journal of Environmental  Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 3, p. 412-416, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Mizota, .C.; and Wada, K. Implications of clay mineralogy to the weathering and chemistry of Ap  horizons of Ando soils in Japan: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ.  Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 1, p. 49-63, illus. (incl. tables), 1980.  Mode, W. N. Late Quaternary glacial and marine stratigraphy, Clyde foreland, Baffin Island, N.W.T.,  Canada [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. I I,  No. 7, p. 481, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Moeller, H.  Untersuchungen zum Saccharase- und Ureasegehalt yon Bruchwaidtorfen und  Anmoorhumus nordwestdeutscher Erlenwaelder [Sugar and urea contents of peat and humic materials  of the Erlenwaeld communities of northwestern Germany]: Telma; Berichte der Deutschen Gesselschaft  fuer Moor-und Torfkunde. Hannover., Vol. 9, p. 175-192 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Momeni, M. H.; Roberts, C. J.; and Kisieleski, W. E. Dispersion-dosimetry and effects of uranium  mining and milling in the United States [abstr.]-  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with  Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 482, 1979. The GeologicaiSociety of America, 92nd annual  meeting.  Monot, G,; and Verret, J.F. L'information gcologique a la ville de Paris [Geologic information for Paris]:  in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour ramenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous)~ Documents du  BRGM (Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 841-850, illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps), 1979.  Moore, L D.  Infiltration into tillage affected soils:  233 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Minnesota,  Minneapolis, Minn. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Mueckenhausen, E. Die Pa!aeoboeden der Eifel in Abhaengigkeit vonder Gcomorphologie [Paleosols  of the Eifel and their relationship to geomorphology]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et aL),  Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 16-24 (incl. English,  French sum.), 1979.  Murali, V.; and Aylmure, L. A.G. No-flow equilibration and adsorption dynamics during ionic transport  in soils: Nature. London., Voi. 283, No. 5746, p. 467-469, illus., 1980.  Murali, V.; Krishna Mufti, G. S. R.; and Sinha, A. K. Note on the three-parameter functions for soil  water diffusivity-water content relationships: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne., Vol. 17,  No. 2, p. 361-366, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Murav'ev, V. I.; and Voronin, B. L. Composition of zeolites in siliceous glauconite formations and the  problem of classifying the clinoptilolite-heulandite group: Lithology and Mineral Resources (English  translation ofLitologiya i Poleznyye Iskopayemyye). Consultants Bureau, New York., Vol. 14, No. 2, p.  188-193, illus. (incl. table), 1979 [1979].  Murphree, L. C.; Miller, K. H.; and Garber, M. C. Soil survey of ltawamba County, Mississippi: 86  p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps h 190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (PubL in cooperation with Miss. Agric. For. Exp.  Stn.).  Murphy, J. O. Soil survey of Clayton, Fayette, and Henry counties, Georgia: 74 p., illus. (incl. tables,  sketch maps; soils maps h20,000; colored soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Georgia, Coll. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv.).  Myanlna, N. IL; and Ariaushkina, Ye. V.  Metodicheskoye posobiye dlya chteniya rezurtatov  khimicheskikh analizov pochv [A methods manual for calculating the results of soil analyses]: 62 p.,  tables, lzd. Mosk. Univ., Moscow, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1979.  Ntiamoah-Agyakwe, Y. Relationship between gold a~d manganese mineralizations in the Birimian of  Ghana, West Africa: Geological Magazine. Cambridge, England., Vol. 116, No. 5, p. 345-352, table,  geol. sketch map, 1979.    319    Palanehon,  logements)  dwellings]:  Documents  1979.    Ogner, G. Analysis of the carbohydrates of fulvic and humic acids as their partially methylated alditol  acetates: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., VoL  23, No. 1, p. 1-10, tables, 1980.  Olivier, G. Cartographie geotechnique pour l'amenagement; e'~emples de Saint Martin de Bellevitle  (Savoie) et de Bellegarde (Ain) [Geotechnical cartography for management; examples of Saint Martin  de Belleville, Savoie and Bellegarde, Ain]: in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour ramenagement urbain;  tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris.,  No. 8, p. 881-898, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Ovander, M, G.; Kaplina, T. N.; and Basblavin, D. K. Ice complex of the Khroma River basin (Yana-  Indigirka Lowland): in XIV Pacific science congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pacific  ring's Cenozoic (Sh[Io, N. A., editor), Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid  Earth., No. 14, Vol. 2, p. 177-178, 1979.  A. Le sol et les caux dans l'etude d'impact de la zone d'habitatioa de la Petite Plaine (500  [The soil and water in the impact study of the habitation zone of the "small plain"; 500  in Connaitre le sous-sol un atout pour ramenagemcnt urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous),  du BRGM (Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 899-904, illus.,    Palechek, L.A. Mikroelementy Cr, Mn, B, Ti v vodakh srednego techeniya reki Obi i yeye pritokov  [Cr, Mn, B, Ti microelements in water of the middle Ob and its tributaries]: Vestnik Moskovskogo  Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvo~edeniye. Moscow., No. 1, p. 61-65, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Patyk-Kara, N. L; Gapon, O. J.; and Kolesnikov, S. F. Regional features of neotectonic movements  apparition in structure of coastal plains sedimentary cover (North-East Asia) [abstr.]: in XIV Pacific  science congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pacific ring's Cenozoic (Shilo, N. A.,  editor), Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid Earth., No. 14; Vol. 2, p. 200-  202, 1979.  Phung, H. T.; Lund, L. J.; Page, A. I.; et a/. Trace elements in fly ash and their release in water and  treated soils: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., we!. 8, No. 2, p. 171-175, illus.  (incl. tables), 1979.  Pitty, A.F. Geography and soil properties: 287 p., illus. (incl. sketch maps), Methuen and Co., London,  United Kingdom, 1979.  Ponti, D. J.; and Burke, D. B. Stratigraphy and deformation of Quaternary sediments in the Antelope  Valley, northern Los Angeles County, California [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with  Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 497, 1979, The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual  meeting.  Pozdnyakov, A. I.; and Khan, K. Yu.  Metodika elektricheskikh zondirovan:ya i profilirovaniya  postoyannym tokom I~i !ssledovanii pochv [Techniques of electric probing and profiling by continuous  current applied in soil investigations]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye.  Moscow., No. 1, p. 46-54, illus., 1979.  Pussemier, L. Etude de radsorption de quelques carbamates aromatiques par un horizon spodique,  correlations "structure-adsorption" [Adsorption of aromatic carbamates by soils; structure-adsorption  correlations1: Pedologle (Societe Beige de Pedologle--Belglsche Bodemkundige Vereniging, Bulletin).  Ghent., Vol. 29, No. 2, p. 163-174 (incl. English, Dutch sum.), tables, 1979.  Read, D. W, L.; and Cameron, D. R. Relationship between salinity and Wenner resistivity for some  dryland soils: Canadian Journal of .Soil Science (Agricultural Institute of Canada). Ottawa., Vol. 59, No.  4, p. 381-385 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Reeder, J. W.; Freyberg, D. L.; Franzini, J. B.; et al. Infiltration under rapidly varying surface depths:  Water Resources Research (American Geophysical Union). Waahington, D.C., Vol. 16, No. 1, p. 97-104,  illus., 1980.  Rees, J.D. Effects of the eruption of Paricut~n Volcano on landforms, vegetation, and human occupancy:  in Volcanic activity and human ecology (Sheets, P. D., editor; et a, p. 249-291, illus. (incl. tables, plates,  geol. sketch maps), Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Retallaek, G. F.ariy Tertiary fossil soils in the Badlands National Monument, South Dakota [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., VoL 11, No. 7, p. 502,  1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.    320    Rich, F. J. The distribution of plant communities and their peat types in the Okefenokee Swamp; a  modern analogue to guide exploitation of Fort Union coals in Wyoming [abstr.]: Geological Society of  America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Color'~do., Voi. 11, No. 7, p. 503, 1979.  The Geological  Society of America. 92nd annual meeting.  Riedel, W. Zur Klimamorphogenese extremer Verwitterung und Bodenbildung in lberien [The climato-  morphogenetical effects on soil formation during extreme weathering in lberia]: in Relief und Baden  (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33,  p. 127-134 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Rieger, S.; Schoephorster, D. B.; and Furbash, C.E. Exploratory soil survey of Alaska: 208 p., illus.  (incl. tables, sketch maps; colored soils maps 1:1,000,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington. D.C., United States, 1979.  Riezebos, H.T. Geomorphology and soils of Sipaliwini savanna (South Suriname): 168 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps; geomorphol, map 1:100,000), Doctoral, 1979, Rijksuniv. te Utrecht, Utrecht,  Netherlands.  Rohl, T. L. The geochemistry of vadose and soil waters in a limestone terrain [abstr.]: Geological  Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Voi. 11, No. 7, p. 504, 1979.  The  Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Rochon, J. Barrieres geochimiques pour la transfert de polluents darts le sol; aspect methodologique  [Geochemical barriers for the transfer of pollutants in the soils; methodologic aspect]: in Connaitre le  anus-sol un atout pour l'amenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de  Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 975-977, 1979.  Rodgers, R. D.; and MeFarlane, J. C. Factors influencing the volatilization of mercury from soil:  Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, F'. 255-260, illus. (incl. tables),  1979.  Rose, A. W.; Hawkes, H. E.; and Wehb, J. S. Geochemistry in mineral exploratior,, 2nd edition: 657  p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), Acad. Precs, London, United Kingdom, 1979.  Rose, D. A. Soil water; quantities, units and symbols: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No.  1, p. 1-15, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Rowan, L. C.; Krohn, M D.; and Purdy, T. L. Generalized map of occurrences of limonitic rocks in  the Walker Lake 1by 20 quadrangle, Nevada-California: U. S. Geological Survey, OpewFile Report.  Reston, Virginia., No. 1t0-232, 1 sheet, econ. geol. map 1:250,000, 1980. available from: U. S. Geol. Sarv.,  Open-File Serv. Sect., Branch Distrib., Denver, Colo., United States.  Ruggiero, P.; ]~nteresse, F. S.; Cassidei, L.; et aL IH NMR spectra of humic and fulvic acids and their  peracetic oxidation products: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta (The Geochemical Society, Journal).  Pergamon Press, Oxford., Vol. 44, No. 4, p. 603-610, illus., 1980.  Rummery, T. A.; Blnemendal, J.; Dearing, $.; et al. The persistence of fire-induced magnetic oxides in  soils and lake sediments: Annales de Geophysique (Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique).  Paris., Voi. 35, No. 2, p. 103-107 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. charts, sketch maps), 1979.  Rutherford, G. K.; and Bray, C.R. Extent and distribution of soil heavy metal contamination near a  nickel smelter at Coniston, Ontario: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8,  No. 2, p. 219-222, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Ryall, W. R.; and Nicholas, T. Surface geochemical and biogeochemical expression of base-metal  mineralization at Woodlawn, New South Wales, Australia: Geological Society of Australia, Journal.  Adelaide., Vol. 26, No. 3-4, p. 187-195, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Ryazanov, P. N. Osobennosti sostava gumusa pochv i nailkov poymy reki Protvy [Organic matter  composition in soils and silt deposits in the Protva River floodplain]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta,  Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye. Moscow., No. 1, p. 66-70, table, 1979.  Scambilis, N. A. Land disposal of chemical sludges:  195 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Missouri,  Columbia, Mo. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Sehafer, B. M.; and McGarity, J.W. Genesis of red and dark brown soils on basaltic p,rent materials  near Armidale, N.S.W., Australia: Geoderma, an International Journal of Soil Science. Elsevier Sci.  PubL Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 23, No. 1, p. 31-47, illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1980.    321    Scharpenseel, H. W.; and Zakosek, H. Phasen der Bodenbildung in Tunesien [Phases in soil formation  in Tunisia]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie,  Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 118-126 (incl. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables,  plates), 1979.  Seheidegger, K. F. An oxidative diagenetic overprint on hydrothermaily altered tholeitic basalts;  chemical and mineral consequences [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs.  Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 511, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92rid annual meeting.  Sehermerhorn, E. J.; Harmon, L. I.; Rieeken, F. F.; et al. Soil survey of Cedar County, Iowa: !71 p.,  illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soils maps h190,080; soils maps 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Iowa Agric. Home  Econ. Exp. Stn., Coop. Ext. Serv. Iowa State Univ.; Iowa Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Selunidt-Collerus, J.J. Investigation of the relationship between organic matter and uranium deposits:  281 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1979. (Rep. No. GJBX-130-79) available from: U. S. Dep. Energy, Grand  Junction Off., Denver, Colo., United States.  Sehroeder, C. Problemes poses par rexploitation de carrieres clans la region Liegoise (Belgique)  [Problems posed by the exploitation of quarnes in the Liege region; Belgium]: in Connaitre le sous-soi  un atout pour ramenagement urbain; tome 2 (Anonymous), Documents du BRGM (Bureau de  Recherches Geologiques et Minieres). Paris., No. 8, p. 1021-1026, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Sehroeder, E. Erlaeuternngen zu Blatt 5305 Zuelpich [Explanations to sheet 5305 Zuelpich]: in the  collection Geologische Karte yon Nordrhein-Westfalen h25,000, 2nd edition, No. 5305, 65 p., 1 sheet,  illus. (incl. tables; geol. map h25,000), Geol. Landesamt Nordrhein-Westfalen, Krefeld, Germany,  Federal Republic of, 1979.  Sehumaeher, T. M.; and Hell, K.J. Soil survey of Campbell County, South Dakota: 175 p., illus. (incl.  tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Senior, B. R. Mineralogy and chemistry of weathered and parent sedimentary rocks in Southwest  Queensland: BMR Journal of Australian Geology and Geophysics (Australia, Bureau of Mineral  Resources, Geology and Geophysics). Canberra., Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 111-124, illus. (incl. tables, strat, cola.  geol. sketch map), 1979.  Senior, B. R.; and Mabbutt, J. A. A proposed method of defining deeply weathered rock units based  on regional geological mapping in Southwest Queensland: Geological Society of Australia, Journal.  Adelaide., Vol. 26, No. 5-6, p. 237-254, geol. sketch map, sects., plates, 1979.  Shaffer, K. A.; Fritton, D. D.; and Baker, D.E. Drainage water sampling in a wet, dual-pore soil system:  Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 241-246, illus. (incl. tables).  1979.  Shah, R. K.; Chokshi, M. R.; Joshi, B. C.; et aL Electrochemical properties of bumic acids extracted  from Gujarat soils: Metals and Minerals Review. Calcutta., Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 71-72, tables, 1979.  Sharma, P. K.; Sahnl, J. S.; and Sharma, K. R. Pedogenesis of soils from various land forms in the  central Punjab: Indian National Science Academy, Proceedings, Part A, Physical Sciences (continuation  of National Institute of Sciences of India, Proceedings, Part A, Physical Sciences). New Delhi., Vol. 45,  No. 2, p. 159-171, illus. (incl. sketch map, tables), 1979.  Shilo, N. A:; Riabehtm, V. K.; and Tomirdiaro, S. V. Ice-loess Yedoma complex as unknown to the  science overthick soil formations of periglacial regions [abstr.]:  in XIV Pacific science congress;  Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the Pac;fic ring's Cenozoic (Shilo, N. A., editor), Abstract of  Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee B: Solid Earth., No. 14, Vol. 2, p. 180-182, 1979.  Shingleton, L. C.; and Watterson, g., Jr. Soil survey of Atoka County, Oklahoma: 153 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map h 190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Oklahoma Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Sidle, R. C.; Stout, W. L.; Hem, ,L L.; ~-t aL Solute movement from fluidized bed combustion waste in  acid soil and mine spoil columns: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No.  2, p. 236-241, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Simons, A. P.; and Magdoff, F. R. Disposal oI septic tank effluent in mound and sand filter-trench  systems on a clay soil: Journal of Environmental Quafity. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 469-  473, illus. (incl. tables, sects.), 1979.    322    Sinclair, D. F.; and Williams, J. Components of variance involved in estimating soil water content and  water content change using a neutron moisture meter: Australian Journal of Soil Research. Melbourne.,  Vol. 17, No. 2, p. 237-247, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Singer, A. The paleoclimatic interpretation of clay minerals in soils and weathering profiles: Earth-  Science Reviews; International Magazine for Geo-Scientists. Elsevier Sci. Publ. Co., Amsterdam., VoL  15, No. 4, p. 303-326, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1980.  Singleton, P. C.; and Barker, D.A. Soil development and nitrates in minesoil: 42 p., illus. (incl. tables),  1979. (Rap. No. EPA-600/7-79-253) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Sirkin, L.; and Stuekem-ath, R. The Portwashingtonian warm interval in the northern Atlantic Coastal  Plain: Geological Society of America, Bulletin. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 91, No. 6, p. ! 332-I 336, illus.  (incl. chart, sketch map), 1980. print, microfiche.  Sitar, N. Behavior of slopes in weakly cemented soils under static and dynamic loading:  183 p.,  Doctoral, 1979, Stanford Univ., Stanford, Calif. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Skowronek, A.  Die Terra rossa in Spanien und ihre Bedeutung fuer klimageomorphologische  Fragesteilungen [The Terra rosa of Spain and its significance in climatogeomorphology]: in Relief und  Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementhand. Berlin-Stuttgart.,  Vol. 33, p. 135-142 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Siukin, A. D.; and Dombrovskaya, Zh. V. Kory vyvetrivaniya i boksity Sibirskoy platformy [Weathering  crusts and bauxites of the Siberian Platform]: 118 p., illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), Izd. Nauka,  Moscow, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1979.  Smalley, I. J.; and Xidakis, G. S. Thermogravimetry of an expansive clay soil from Adelaide:  approximate mineralogical analysis using standard montmorillonites:  Clay Science (Clay Science  Society of Japan). Tokyo., Vol. 5, No. 4, p. 189-193, illus., 1979.  Smirnov, Yu. A.; and Chernova, G.N. Primeneniye magnimykh parametrov dlya diagnostiki nekotorykh  pochv Kaliningradskoy oblasti [Application of magnetic properties for a diagnosis of some soils of the  Kaliningrad District]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye. Moscow., No. 1,  p. 39-45, illus. (incl. table).. 1979.  Smith, D. B.; and Zielinski, R, A. Uranium leachabi!'ty from freshly erupted volcanic ash of basaltic  and dacitic composition [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 518-519, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Shelling, A. A.; and Diekson, B. L. Uranium i daughter disequilibrium in the Koongarra uranium deposit,  Australia: Mineralium Deposita; International Journal for Geology, Mineralogy, and Geochemistry of  Mineral Deposits. Heidelberg., Vol. 14, No. 1, p. 109-118, illus. (incl. tables, sects., sketch map), 1979.  Sombroek, W. G.; and van Baren, J. H. V. The International Soil Museum: Nature and Resources  (InternationM Hydrological Decade, Bulletin) (UNESCO). Paris., Vol. 15, No. 1, p. 4-7, 1979.  Sommer, S. E.; and Buckingham, W.F. Optical and chemical properties of rock surfaces as a function  of weathering and alteration application to remote sensing [abstr.]: Eos (American Geophysical Union,  Transactions). Washington, D. C., Vol. 60, No. 46, p. 975, 1979. American Geophysical Union," 1979fall  annual meeting.  Spaeth, H. Laterite und Lateritstufen in Nordwestaustralien [Laterites and laterite steps in northwestern  Australia]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et at), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie,  Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 57-71 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.  Sposito, G.; Page, A. L.; and Frink, M.g. Effects of acid precipitation on soil ieachate quafity; computer  calculations:  39 p., illus. (incl. tables), 1980. (Rap. No. EPA-600/3-80-015) available from: NTIS,  Springfield, Va., United States.  Srehroderskiy, B. I. Izmeneniya yantarya [The alteration of amber]:  Mineralogicheskiy Sbornik  (L'vovskiy Gosudarstvennyy Universitet). Lvov., Vol. 33, No. 1, p. 120-124 (incl. English sum.), tables,  plates, 1979.  Staeblein, G. Boeden und Relief in Westgroenland [Soil and relief of western Greenland]: in Relief und  Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschfift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart.,  Vol. 33, p. 232-245 (incl. English, French sum.), illus., 1979.    323    Stephan, S. Die Ergaenzung bodenkundlicher Felduntersuchungen durch Kleinproben, gezeigt an zwei  Beispielen aus Ecuador [The results of analysis of small soil samples from Ecuador]: in Reliefund Boden  0]remer, H., editor; et a[), Zeitschrift fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33,  p. 84-98 (il. English, French sum.), illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Stevens, J.G. Soil survey of Lowndes County, Georgia: 77 p:, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; colored  soils maps 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Wasl'~.ngton, D.C., United States, 1979.  (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Georgia, Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Stiehting voor Bodemkartering. Oost Apeldoorn [East Apeldoorn]: in the collection Bodemkaart van  Nederland; Schaal h50,000, No. 33, 173 p., 1 sheet, illus. (incl. tables; soils maps 1:50,000), Stichting  Bodemkart., Wageningen, Netherlands, 1979.  Stocking, M.A. Catena of sodium-rich soil in Rhodesia: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No.  1, p. 139-146, 1979.  Stremme, H.E. Boeden, Relief und Landschaftsgeschichte im nordwestdeutschen Raum [Soil, relief and  landform history in northwestern Germany]: in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift  fuer Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 216-222 (incl. English, French  sum.), illus., 1979.  Strum, J. F.; Heidt, C. J.; and Bigler, RJ. Soil survey of Benson County area, North Dakota: 245  p., illus. (incl. tables~ plates; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soil map h316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv. and U. S. Dep. Inter., Bur. Indian Aft., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in  cooperation with N.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Stuck, W. M. Soil survey of Beaufort and Jasper counties, South Carolina: 179 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; soils maps h20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U.S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with S.C. Agric. Exp. Stn. and S.C. Land  Resour. Conserv. Comm.).  Sturdy, R. G.; Allen, R. H.; Bullock, P.; et aL Paleosols developed on Chalky Boulder Clay in Essex:  Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 117-137, illu~. (incl. table, sketch maps), 1979.  Swafford, B, G.; and Reasoner, R.C. Soil survey of Choctaw County, Oklahoma: 145 p., illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv.  Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Oklahoma Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Talapatra, A. E.; and Bose, B. B. Mercurometric survey techniques for exploration of base metal  sulphide mineralization in parts of Rajasthan: Indian Journal of Earth Sciences. Calcutta., Vol. 6, No.  2, p. 162-174, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1979.  Taylor, S. E. Measured emissivity of soils in the Southeast United States:  Remote Sensing of  Environment. American Elsevier Publ. Co., New York., Vol. 8, No. 4, p. 359-363, illus. (incl. tables, geol.  sketch maps), 1979.  Thibodeaex, L.J. Chemodynamics; environmental movement of chemicals in air, water, and soil: 501  p., illus. (incl. tables), John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, United States, 1979.  Thomas, G..W.; and Phillips, R. E. Consequences of water movement in macropores: Journal of  Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 149-152, illus., 1979.  Thompson, T. R. E.  A comprehensive system of soil description and classification:  Journal of  Environmental Management. Academic Press, London-New York-San Francisco., Vol. 9, No. 3, p. 247-  253, illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Thony, J. L.; e~,d Vaehand, G. Automatic measurement of soil-water pressure using a capacitance  manometer: Journal of Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Pubi. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 46, No. 1-2, p. 189-196,  illus., 1980.  Thornes, ,1I. Fluvial processes: in Process in geomorphology (Embleton, C., editor; eta/), p. 213-271,  illus. (incl. cables, sketch maps), $ohn Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, N.Y., United States, 1979.  Thornton, I.; Nordberg, G. F.; Baritrop, D.; et aL Panel; interaction of metals: inTrace metals; exposure  and health effects; proceedings of the research seminar (Di Ferrante, E., editor), p. 147-162, illus. (incl.  tables, sketch maps), Pergamon Press, Oxford, Unite6 States, 1979. (Commission of the European  Communities).    324    Thurston, P. C.; Sage, P. R.; and Siragusa, G.M. Geology of the Winisk Lake area; District of Kenora,  Patricia portion: Ontario Geological Survey Report (Ontario, Division of Mines, Geological Branch).  Toronto., No. 193, 169 p., illus. (incl. geol. skc~,:h maps, tables, plates; geol. maps 1:253,440), 1979.  Timofeyev, B. V. Osobennosti genezisa pochv semiaridnoy zony Severnoy Afriki [Soil genesis in  semiarid zones of North Africa]: Vestnik Moskovskogo Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye.  Moscow., No. 1, p. 11-17, tables, 1979.  Tomes, L.A. Soil survey of Ulster County, New York: 273 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps; soils  maps 1:15,840; colored soils map h316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C.,  United States, 1979. (Publ. in cooperation with Corneil Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Tricurt, J. L. F. Alteration et dissection differentielles darts un socle cratonise; rexemplede la dorsale  bresiliene [Alteration and ~ifferential dissection in a cratonized base; the Brazilian Ridge as an example]:  Annales de Geographic (Societe de Geographic, Bulletin). Paris., Vol. 88, No. 487, p. 265-314 (incl.  English sum.), illus. (incl. geol. sketch map), 1979.  Tuexen, J. Vorschlag einer typologischen Ordnung der niedersaechsischen Hochmoore; Vorlaeufi~e  Mitteilung [Classification of raised bogs in Lower Saxony by type, a provisional report]: Teima; Berichte  der Deutschen Gesselschaft fuer Moor-and Torfkunde. Hannover., Vol. 9, p. 15-29 (incl. English sum.),  illus. (incl. table), 1979.  Twiss, Po C. Opal phytoliths as indicators of C3 and C4 grasses [abstr.]: Geological Society of America,  Abst=~acts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 17, 1980.  The Geological Society of  AmeJ~ca, South-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  U. S. Department of Agriculture, Soil Conservation Service. Report on water and related land  resources; Wisconsin River basin, Wisconsin-Michigan: variously paginated, illus. (incl. tables; environ.  geol. maps 1:1,000,000; geol. map 1:1,000,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., United States,  1979.  U. S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management, Montana State Orate. Draft  environmental statement on grazing management in the Missouri Breaks of Montana:  variously  paginated, illus. (incl. tables, geol. sketch maps), 1979. availablefmm:U. S. Dep. Int., Bur. Land Manage.,  Mont. State Off., Montana, United States.  Ugolini, F. C.; and Zasoski, R. J, Soils derived from tephra: in Volcanic activity and human ecology  (Sheets, P. D., editor; et aZ), p. 83-114, illus. (incl. tables, plates), Acad. Press, New York, N.Y., United  States, 1979.  University of Wisconsin-Extension, Geological and Natural History Survey. An introduction to  Wisconsin wetlands: 19 p., U. S. Geol. Surv., United States, 1979.  Van Keuren, R. W.; McGnlnness, J. L.; and Chichester, F.W. Hydrology and chemical quality of flow  from small pastured watersheds; I, Hydrology: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin.,  Vo|. 8, No. 2, p. 162-166~ illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Van Til, C. J. Guidelines manual for surface monitoring of geothermal areas: Lawrence Berkeley  Laboratory (California, University), [Report], LBL. Berkeley., No. 8617, variously paginated, illus. (incl.  ~bles, sketch maps), 1979. (Rep. No. GSRMP-3) available from`" NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Varailyay, G.; and Szacs, L, Magyarorszag uj, 1 : 1000 000 meretaranyu talajterkepe es felhasznalasi  lehetosegei [New 1:1000,000 scale soil maps of Hungary and their applicability]:  Geodezia es  K.~rtografia. Budapest., Vol. 31, No. 5, p. 358-361, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1979.  Vaughan, H.H. Prehistoric disturbance of vegetation in the area of Lake Yaxha, Peten, Guatemala; 186  p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Florida, Gainesviile, Fla. available from." Univ. Microfilms.  Vitek, J. D.; Dearth, A. L.; and Parson, C.G. Variability in the dissolved loads of alpine streams [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 12, No. 1, p. 17, 1980.  T~e Geological Society of America. South-Central Section, 14th annual meeting.  V@igt, G. K. (reviewer); and Paton, T. R. The formation of soil material: American Journal of Science.  New Haven, Connecticut., Vol. 280, No. 3, p. 288, 1980.  Vo~onin, A. D. Metodologicheskiye printsipy i metodicheskoye znacheniye kontseptsii iyerarkhii  urovney strukturnoy organizatsii pochvy [Methodological aspects and methodical significance of a  concept concerning the hierarchy of structural levels of soil organization]: Vestnik Moskovskogo  Universiteta, Seriya 17, Pochvovedeniye. Moscow., No. 1, p. 3-10 (incl. English sum.), 1979.    325    Vtiurin, B. I.; Bolikhovskaya, N. S.; Bolikhovsky, V. F.; et ai. The structure of Yedoma deposits in lower  lndigirka River [abstr.]: in XlV Pacific science congress; Stratigraphy and paleobiogeography of the  Pacific ring's Cenozoic (Shilo, N. A., editor), Abstract of Papers - Pacific Science Congress, Committee  B: Solid Earth., No. 14, Vol. 2, p. 186-188, 1979.  Waldron, H. A.; Khera, A.; Walker, G.; et aL Lead concentrations in bones and soil: Journal of  Archaeological Science. Academic Press, London., VoL 6, No. 3, p. 295-298, tables, 1979.  Walker, T. R. Red color in dune sand: in A study of global sand seas (McKee, E. D., editor), U. S.  Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1052, p. 61-81, illus. (incl. table, geol.  sketch map), 1979 [1980].  Warne, S. St. J.; and Mitchell, B. D. Variable a':mosphere DTA in identification and determination of  anhydrous carbonate minerals in soils: Journal of Soil Science. Oxford., Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 111-116, illus.,  1979.  Waterbury, G. R. (compiler). Environmental and radiological safety studies; interaction of 238PUO2 heat  sources with terrestrial and aquatic environments; April l-June 30, 1979:  Los Alamos Seierttifie  Laboratory (University of California), [Report]. Los Alamos, New Mexico., No. 7986, 37 p., illus. (incl.  tables), 1979. availablefnJm: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Waters, D. D.; and Sieger, thaler, V. L. Soil survey of Logan County, Ohio: 181 p., illus. (incl. tables,  plates; colored soils map 1:190,080; soils map 1:15,840), U. S. Dep. Agrie., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Pubi. in cooperation with Ohio Dep. Nat. Resour., Div. Lands  Soil, Ohio Agric. Res. Dev. Cent.).  Webb, R. H.; and Wilshire, H. G. Soil and vegetation recovery in a Nevada ghost town [abstr.]:  Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 536,  1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Weesies, G.A. Soil survey of Bay County, Michigan: 105 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates, sketch maps;  colored soils map 1:190,080; soils maps 1:20,000), U. S. Dep. Agrie., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington,  D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Mich. Agrie. Exp. Stn.).  Wells, A. M.N. Evolution of a humid tropical landscape in Northcentral Costa Rica as deduced from  geomorphic and pedogenic evidence: 285 p., Doctoral, 1979, Univ. of Kansas, Lawrence, Kans. available  from: Univ. Microfilms.  Wells, S. G.; and Schultz, J.D. Some factors influencing Quaternary calcrete f~rmation and distribution  in alluvial fill of arid basins [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts ~vith Programs. Boulder,  Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7, p. 538, 1979.  The Geological Society of America, 92~d annual meeting.  Wen Qizhong; Yah Jinshou; Diao Guiyi; et al. Trace element variations during the reclamation of loess:  Geochimiea. Academica Sinica., No. 2, p. 145-155 (Chinese, incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. sect.), 1979.  Werner, R. Periglaziale Ablagerungen und Hangentwicklung am Kapellen-Berg bei Hofheim am Taunus  [Periglacial sediment~ and slope development at the KapeUen-Berg near Hofheim, southern Taunus  Mountains]: Geologisehes Jahrbuch Hessen. Wiesbaden., Vol. 107, p. 163-177 (incl. English sum.), illus.  (incl. sects., table, sketch map), 1979.  White, G. C.; and Hakonson, T. E. Statistical considerations and survey of plutonium concentration  variability in some terrestrial ecosystem components: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison,  Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 176-182, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  White, R.E. Introduction to the principles and practice of soil science: 198 p., illus. (incl. tables), John  Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, ~!.Y., United States, 1979.  Wiedenfeld, C.C. Soil survey of Schleicher County, Texas: 64 p., illus. (incl. tables, plates; colored soils  map 1:253,440; soils maps h31,680), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United  States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Wiersma, G. B.; Brown, g. W.; Hen'mann, R.; et ai. Great Smoky Mountains preliminary study for  biosphere reserve pollutant monitoring: 47 p., illus. (incl. tables, sketch map), 1979. (Rep. No. EPA-  600/4-79-072) available from: NTIS, Springfield, Va., United States.  Wildung, R. E.; McFadden, K. M.; and Garland, T. R. Technetium sources and behavior in the  environment: Journal of Environmental Quality. Madison, Wisconsin., Vol. 8, No. 2, p. 156-161, 1979.    326    Wilke, B. M.; and Zeeh, W. Analytische Kennzeichnung der Palaeoboeden von Hoermating [The  Paleosols of Hoermating]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitsehrift fuer  Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Vol. 33, p. 246-256 (inc' French, English sum.),  illus. (incl. plates), 1979.  Wilkey, M.; and Zcllmer, S. Land reclamation at abandoned deep coal mine: American Society of Civil  Engineers, Proceedings, Journal of the Environmental Engineering Division. New York., Vol. 105, No.  EES, p. 843-853, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Williams, T. H. L. An automatic electrical resistance soil-moisture measuring system: Journal of  Hydrology. Elsevier Sci. Puhl. Co., Amsterdam., Vol. 46, No. 3-4, p. 385-390, illus., 1980.  Willman, H. B. Comments on the Sangamon Soil:  in Wiseonsinan, Sangamonian, and Illinoian  (Folimer, L. R., leader; et ai.), Illinois, State Geological Survey, Guidebook Series. Urbana., No. 13, p.  92-94, 1979.  Wilshire, H. G.; and Nakata, J. K. The December 1977 windstorm, San Joaquin Valley, California  [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder, Colorado., Vol. 11, No. 7,  p. 541, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Winkler, E. M.; Bradley, W. C.; Hutton, J. T.; et ai. Role of salts in development of granitic tafoni, South  Australia: Journal of Geology. Chicago, Illinois., Vol. 88, No. 1, p. 119-122, illus., 1980.  Wolfe, J. A.; and Toshimasa, T. The Miocene Seldovia Point flora from the Kenai Group, Alaska: U.  S. Geological Survey, Professional Paper. Reston, Virginia., No. 1105, 52 p., plates, 1980.  Woodruff, G. A. Soil survey of San Bernardino County; southwestern part, California: 65 p., illus. (incl.  tables, plates; colored soils map 1:253,440; soils maps h24,000), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv.,  Washington, D.C., United States, 1980. (Publ. in cooperation with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Woolson, W.A. Effects of overburden, snow cover, soil porosity and flight altitude on signal radiation  during airborne reconnaissance for uranium: in Analysis of airborne radiometric data; Volume 3, Topical  reports (Reed, J. H.; eta/.), p. 29-61, illus. (incl. table), 1979. (Rep. No. GJBX-169-79) (Rep. No. SAI-  78-997-LJ) available from: U. S. Dep. Energy, Grand Junction Off., Grand Junction, Colo., United States.  Yeargan, M. E.; and Manley, F. H. Reconnaissance remote sensing in atypical wetlands, coastal  Mississippi [abstr.]: Geological Society of America, Abstracts with Programs. Boulder. Colorado., Voi.  11, No, 7, p. 545, 1979. The Geological Society of America, 92nd annual meeting.  Young, A. W.; Campbell, A. 84 and Walker, T.W. Allophane isolated from a Podsol developed on a  non-vitric parent material: Nature. London., Vol. 284, No. 5751, p. 46-48, illus. (incl. table), 1980.  Zakosek, H.; Becket, H.; and Brandtner, E. Einfuehrung in die Weinbau-Standortkarte Rheingau i.M.  1:5000 [Introduction to the map for vinicultural site selection in the Rheingau area with scale hS,000]:  Geologisches Jahrbuch Hessen. Wiesbaden., Vol. 107, p. 261-381 (incl. English, French sum.), illus. (incl.  table, geol. sketch map), 1979.  Zeeh, W.; Wilke, B. M.; and Drexler, O. Analytische Kennzeichnung yon Karstschlotten-Fuellungen  in der Fraenkischen und Schwaehischen Alb [Analytical signs of karst weathered fissure fillings in the  Franconian and Swabian Alb]:  in Relief und Boden (Bremer, H., editor; et al.), Zeitschrift fuer  Geomorphologie, Supplementband. Berlin-Stuttgart., Voi. 33, p. 182-193, illus. (incl. tables), 1979.  Zellmer, S.; and Wilkey, M. A reclamation demonstration project at an abandoned deep mine:  Minerals and the Environment. London., Vol. 1, No. 2, p. 57-63, illus. (incl. tables, sketch maps), 1979.  Zulauf, A. S.; and Start., W.A. Soil survey of North Ferry area, Washington; parts of Ferry and Stevens  counties: 118 p., illus. (incl. tables, sects., sketch maps; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440),  U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, D.C., United States, 1979. (Publ. in coop. with Wash.  Agric. Exp. Stn.).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   