Geoderma, 29 (1983) 1-12  1  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -Printed in The Netherlands    AN IR SPECTROSCOPIC STUDY OF SOIL HUMIN AND ITS RELATIONSHIP TO OTHER SOIL HUMIC SUBSTANCES AND FUNGAL PIGMENTS    J.D. RUSSELL, D. VAUGHAN, D. JONES and A.R. FRASER    Macaulay Institute for Soil Research, Craigiebuchler, Aberdeen, AB9 2QJ (Great Britain)    (Received January 12, 1982; accepted after revision June 17, 1982)    ABSTRACT    Russell, J.D., Vaughan, D., Jones, D. and Fraser, A.R., 1983. An IR spectroscopic study  of soil humin and its relationship to other soil humic substances and fungal pigments.    Geoderma, 29: 1-12.     Humin, with a relatively low ash content, was isolated from a sandy soil by exhaustively dissolving humic and fulvic fractions in cold 0.5 M NaOH, and the mineral components in 20% HF. The infrared spectrum of the insoluble humin was similar to that of humic acid derived from the same soil, and resembled those of the humic-like pigments obtained from the soil fungi Coniothyrium minitans and Rhizoctonia solani. It was less like the spectrum of the pigment from Aspergillus niger which closely resembled that of the melanin pigment from Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. The brown debris remaining after extracting some of the fungi with NaOH, produced, on acid hydrolysis, fractions having IR spectra similar to acid hydrolysed humin. It is concluded from the similarity of humin, humic acid and fungal pigments, that well humified soil organic matter is to a large extent microbial in origin.   When "C-labelled humin from a sandy loam was incubated with fresh soil, about 20% of the radioactivity was lost after 3 months and 25% after 6 months, but subsequently there was virtually no further loss. A similar pattern of stability was obtained using "Clabelled humic acid and this result, in conjunction with those from infrared spectroscopy, indicates a close relationship between humin and humic acid in terms of their structure, and their turnover in the soil. It is concluded that the composition of a soil humin is likely to be determined by the soil's microbial population.    INTRODUCTION     Although there is an extensive literature on the chemical composition and origin of humic and fulvic acids, virtually no information exists for humin. This is because of the difficulties encountered in isolating the insoluble humin free from mineral and other organic components in the soil.   In a previous study (Russell et al., 1980), it was suggested that humin is derived in part from melanin-type pigments from cell walls of fungi similar to Sclerotinia sclerotiorum whose pigments are particularly resistant to decomposition (Jones and Webley, 1968). In a continuation of that work, a method for the isolation of humin is now reported. The infrared spectrum and chemical composition of the humin is compared with that of a humic acid prepared    0016-7061/83/0000-0000/$03.00 1983 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company  2    from the same soil, and with those of humic-like pigments obtained from three soil fungi. These fungi were chosen because their propagules are darkly pigmented and can persist for long periods in the soil. In addition a comparison is made between the stability of humin and humic acids in soils using '4C-labelled preparations of these soil components.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Preparation of soil organic matter fractions     Humin, and humic (HA) and fulvic (FA) acids were prepared from a soil sample taken from the top 15 cm of a profile of the Boyndie Series (Grant, 1960) obtained from the Aldroughty Farm, Elgin, Morayshire. The soil (20 g was first refluxed with ethanol/toluene (1:1 v/v) to remove fats and waxes. then extracted seven times with 1 dm' 0.5 M NaOH, each time for 18 h, the soil being separated and collected between extractions by centrifugation at 2,OOOg for 20 min. The first two alkaline extracts were combined, acidified to pH 1.0 with HCl and the HA and FA were recovered as described by Vaughan and Ord (1980). Some of the HA was hydrolised with 6M HCl for 6 h. The insoluble fraction resulting from this treatment is referred to in Table I as HCl-insoluble HA.   The soil debris, from which no further brown material could be extracted with NaOH, was suspended in 1 dm' water and decanted several times to remove particles of sand, then centrifuged at 2,000 g for 30 min. The remaining debris was treated three times with 500 cm; 20%0 (v/v) HF, each time for 1 h, once with 500 cm' 20% HF overnight, then washed with 5 X 500 cm' water and finally dried at 50. The final humin preparation was dark brown. The    TABLE I    Yields, ash contents and elemental analyses of soil organic matter fractions obtained from Aldroughty Farm soil, and of humin from the Countesswells soil    Fraction Yield*' Ash Elemental analyses*' (%)       (; H N C)*'  Humic acid (HA) 21.7 2.2 51.7 5.1 2.9 40.3  Fulvic acid 10.2 8.5 43.6 4.9 1.7 .19.8  Humin 34.2 12.5 55.9 5.9 0.9 a 7 .3  Alkali-soluble humin 3.1 6. 7 54.3 5. 7 1.5 38.5  HCI-insoluble HA 12.5 1. 7 52.1 4.7 2.4 40.8  Countesswells humin -- 28.3 60.1 6.1 0.5 :33.3    *' Expressed as percentage of total organic matter in soil. *2 Elemental analyses are expressed on an ash free basis. *' By difference.  3    initial durations of HF treatments were critical as longer periods gave rise to insoluble fluoride salts which could not be removed by subsequent extraction.   Samples of the humin and HA preparations were refluxed with 1.5 M HCl to remove carbohydrates then with 6 M HCl for 6 h (50 mg sample: 25 cm' HCl) to hydrolyse proteins; suspensions were then centrifuged and the debris washed with 4 X 50 cm' water and dried at 50. Humin was also methylated using diazomethane as described previously giving a product (IR spectrum Fig.3c) containing 11.2% methoxyl, a value similar to that reported for the methylated melanin from S. sclerotiorum (Russell et al., 1980).   Yields of humin, HA and FA from the Aldroughty soil, together with their ash and C, H, N, and O contents are given in Table I.    Fungal pigments     Rhizoctonia solani, isolated from the surface of potato tubers, was cultured on malt extract agar (MEA) for 3 weeks at 20 (Jones et al., 1972). The light brown sclerotia (total fresh weight 3.4 g) were harvested from the agar surface and treated as described below. Coniothyrium minitans, a mycoparasite of sclerotia of Sclerotinia sclerotiorum (Lib.) de Bary (Jones and Watson, 1969) was cultured on MEA for 3 weeks at 20. The pycnidiospores, and some of the pycnidia were washed from the surface of the culture and filtered through miracloth (Chicopee Mills Inc., New York). The filtrate contained the pycnidiospores only and these (total fr. wt. 1.6 g) were used as experimental material.   Aspergillus niger was grown on MEA for 2 weeks at 20. The spores were removed by means of a Pasteur pipette under reduced pressure and collected in a water trap. The spores (total fr. wt. 1.4 g) were recovered by centrifugation at 2,000 g for 10 min.   All fungal material was extracted five times with 250 cm' 0.5 M NaOH, each time for 18 h, the material being separated from the alkali liquor by centrifugation at 2,000 g for 10 min. Sclerotia of S. sclerotiorum were ground using a mortar and pestle before extraction. The alkaline solutions were combined and brought to pH 1.0 with HCl, and the insoluble material, resembling humic acid (referred to as humic-like fractions in Table 11), separated by centrifugation, washed with 4 X 50 cm' water, and dried at 50. Samples of the HA-like material were refluxed with 6 M HCl for 6 h as described above for humin. In contrast to A. niger and R. solani, C. minitans produced little HA-like material.   Fungal debris remaining after repeated NaOH extraction was washed in 4 X 50 cm' water to remove alkali, boiled in 1.5 M HCl for 1.5 h to remove carbohydrates then extracted with 150 cm' 9 M HCl for 4 h at 2 to remove chi+in, a known constituent of the fungal species used. The debris was recovered by centrifugation and hydrolysed with 25 cm' 6 M HCl at 100 for 6 h and the debris again recovered by centrifugation. The debris was then  4    treated with 50 cm' 20% (v/v) HF overnight, washed with 5 X 50 cm-' water and finally dried at 50. The dark brown residues obtained in this way are designated final residue (Table 11) to distinguish them from alkali-soluble HA-like pigments. All fungal pigments were subjected to infrared (IR) and elemental analyses.    TABLE 11    Elemental analyses of fungal pigments    Organism Fraction Elemental analyses (%)      C H N O  C. minitans Humic-like 51.7 5.2 3.2 39.9  (spores) Final residue 52.3 5.3 2.6 39.8  A. niger Humic-like 50.3 5.0 3.1 41.6  (spores) Final residue 52.1 4.8 2.6 40.5  R. solani Humic-like 52.5 5.4 4.8 37.3  (sclerotia) Final residue 51.7 5.1 4.1 39.1  S. sclerotiorum Final residue 60.3 3.7 1.2 34.8  (sclerotia) (melanin)    Analyses     IR spectra of samples (0.8 mg in 13 mm diameter KBr pressed disks) were recorded on a Perkin-Elmer 577 spectrophotometer over the range 4000-200 cm-'. Total C, H and N were determined on 0.6 mg of each sample using a Hewlett-Packard 185 Analyser, and oxygen was calculated by difference. All results are presented on an ash-free basis for samples ignited at 450 for 1811.    Soil incubation experiments     Soil from the Countesswells series (Glentworth and Muir, 1963) was incubated with '4C-labelled rye straw for 224 days (Cheshire et al., 1973). Samples (10 g) of this soil were extracted successively with 100 cm' CC14, 0.1 M HCl and water, and recovered each time by centrifugation at 2,000 g for 10 min. The extracted soil was then treated as described above for the isolation of humic acid and humin fractions. The combined alkaline extracts were recentrifuged at 16,000 g for 30 min to minimize inorganic components in the humic acid. The HA obtained had  ash content of 3.2% and a specific activity of 2,100 dpm mg'', and the humin, 28.3% ash and a specific activity of 420 dpm mg-' .   The labelled humin or humic acids (1 g of each) were mixed with 15 g Aldroughty farm soil and the moisture level adjusted to 15.1% with water.  5    The mixtures were incubated at 25 and 0.5 g samples taken at regular intervals, dried at 50 and their radioactivity determined as 14C0z after combustion. The moisture levels of the incubation mixtures were maintained at 15.1% by adjusting the weights of the samples with water.    RESULTS AND INTERPRETATION    Composition of organic fractions     The elemental composition of humin obtained from the Aldroughtv soil was similar to that of the humic acid prepared from the same soil, but had a considerably lower N content (Table I); from the calculated oxygen contents, both humin and humic acid were less oxidized than the corresponding fulvic acid. When humin was subjected to boiling in 1.0 M NaOH, some 8-10% was brought into solution but precipitated again when the pH was brought to 2.0 with HCI. This fraction is referred to as alkali-soluble humin in Table 1. The chemical composition of this precipitate was similar to that of humic acid and there was an increase in the N content compared to the humin from which it was derived. This finding agrees with the observations of Saiz-Jimenez et al. (1979), who have reported a similarity in the composition of humic acid and an alkali-soluble "humin".   Acid hydrolysis of the soil humic acid resulted in a decrease in the N content from 2.9 to 2.4%, the full extent of the loss of protein N being masked by the simultaneous loss of components such as polysaccharide (Table I). The release of N as amino acids and NH, was 1.5% of the original humic acid or 52% of total N, clearly indicating that about half of the humic acid N occurs in a relatively stable non-hydrolysable form. The nature of this fixed N is as yet not known.   Table I also shows that the ash content of the NaOH-soluble humin (6.7%) was about half of that in the original humin (12.5%). X-ray crystallographic analysis revealed that the humin ash comprised mainly mica (80-90%) and Ti02, with traces of quartz.   A comparison between the elemental analyses of humic acid-like pigments of some fungi and the brown pigments remaining after NaOH extraction shows a striking resemblance between the two components for each organism (Table II). The overall pattern reveals a strong similarity between the fungal pigments and the soil humic acid and humin. The residual fungal fractions are analogous to the soil humin in being insoluble in alkali, but with the exception of the melanin of S. selerotiorum, they have much higher N contents, comparable with that of the soil humic acid.    IR spectroscopy     Although the humin fraction of soil organic matter and the melanin-type pigments of various fungi are the main subject of this investigation (that is  6    materials that are insoluble in acid and alkali), it is pertinent first of all to consider the alkali soluble-acid insoluble humic acid-like components from these sources to obtain as broad a basis as possible from which to study the structure and composition of the humin and melanins.   With the exception of that of the A. niger extract (Fig. 1,B) infrared spectra of the humic-like components from various sources (Fig. 1,4, C, D) are generally similar, differing only in minor detail. The spectra show absorption due to carboxylic acid groups at 2600, 1710 (a relatively weak feature in Fig. 1,C) and 1210-1250 cm-' , proteinaceous material at about 1650 and 1530 cm-' and polysaccharides at 1000-1100 cm-' , and resemble quite closely that of the type III protein-rich soil humic acids described by Stevenson and Goh (1971). The spectrum of the humic-like compound from A. niger (Fig. 1,B) is dominated by the absorption band at 1605 cm-'and differs from those of the other three humic-like fractions in not displaying clearly defined carboxylic acid absorption at 1710 cm' . In this respect the pigment from A. niger resembles that from S. sclerotiorum described previously (Russell et al., 1980).     ___ 1225 1030  1640    ~~2600    2600 lszo     ,~_~ ~ 1605 ~~.   ~11520 1313   1410 1190   `1645  1616  I ~2600  i Il ~. _    1070  525 1230    35 30    25 20    1~1,65i 550 583    loss s7o 774    1 1 z20  elt    15 ~ 12 8 4    Fig. 1. Infrared absorption spectra of humic acid from Aldroughty soil (A ), and humiclike pigments from the soil fungi A. niger (B), C. minitans (C) and R. solani (D).    R   Spectra of the humic-type materials after hydrolysis with 6 M HCl (Fig. 2) all show a considerable reduction in the intensity of the 1540 and 1650 cm-' peptide bands and the 1000-1100 cm-' polysaccharide bands, accompanied by enhancement of the C = O stretching band of free carboxyl groups at 1705-1710 cm-'. From the intensities of the 1710 cm-' band, the contents of free carboxyl follow the sequence A. niger &lt; R. solani &lt; Aldroughty soil &lt; C. minitans. The spectral changes resulting from the HCl hydrolysis agree with those reported by Stevenson and Goh (1971) for hydrolysis of type III soil humic acids. In addition to the 1710 cm-'carboxyl band, all spectra show an intense broad band in the range 1608-1615 cm`' which resembles that reported for the melanin from S. sclerotiorum (Russell et al., 1980). Again the hydrolysed A. niger pigment is different ,from the other three humic structures in showing little change in the spectrum following HCl treatments; the 1710 cm-' COOH band remains weak and the spectrum is dominated by the 1608 cm-' band.    zszD    zsoo    'zsoo    i 1- 1- 1  35 30 ZS zo    lsio  12, 0    log    lzzo    1203  lsos    Ulsls  ~lo7    17o6v   Isis     16  ~ /1D0 CM    _1    1220    eso sas use    12 0  4    Fig. 2. Infrared absorption spectra of soil humic acid and fungal pigments after hydrolysis with 6 M HCl (see text). A-D as in Fig.l.  s     The spectrum of the soil humin (Fig. 3A) resembles closely that of the soil humic acid (Fig. 1A ), in agreement with their similar chemical analyses (Table I). Hydrolysis of the humin removes protein and polysaccharides and the spectrum (Fig. 3B) exhibits the same COON band at 1708 cm-' and a broad band arising from conjugated H-bonded COON near 1610 cm-' , as does hydrolysed soil humic acid (Fig. 2A). These results place the soil humin closer to the humic acid from the soil and the humic-like pigments from C. minitans and R. solani than to either the A. niker pigment or to the melanin from S. sclerotiorum.     ____~_T-___._ ___  T___ _- __. T._ T.___- _ ... _T__-._ ______ T_    1    I  1705 1550 1245 i"  B  1632 1030 7532  1  i'  345    2600 w 1236   ,f ee   1708    i   U  1725 1250  '' 345   1638  1030    1055    35 30 25 20 16 ;z e 4      /100 cm ,  Fig. 3. Infrared absorption spectra of humin from Aldroughty soil, as isolated (see text)  (A), hydrolysed with 6 M HCl (B) methylated with CH,NZ(C). Spurious absorption bands  occur at 1030, 532 and 472 cm`' (layer silicate), and broad underlying absorption near  550 cm-' and at 345 cm-' (anatase as identified by X-ray diffraction).     Following exhaustive dissolution of alkali-soluble pigment, debris from the three fungi, still strongly coloured, was hydrolysed with 6 M HCl to remove wall polysaccharide. These residues correspond to the soil humin in their method of isolation, and their IR spectra (Fig. 4) resemble that of soil humin in having strong bands due to free (1710 cm-') and conjugated/Hbonded (1610 cm-') carboxyl groups. There are, however, significant differences between these spectra and those of the corresponding hydrolysed humid acids. This is particularly so for debris from A. niger which shows a strong carboxyl band at 1710 cm-'(Fig. 4,A), whereas the hydrolysed humic acid has a very weak carboxyl at this frequency (Fig. 2,B). For C. minitans the corresponding band in the spectrum of the debris fraction occurs at 1745 cm(Fig.4,B) compared with 1708 cm-' in the hydrolysed humic acid (Fig. 2,C).  9    2620 a54 7z0 V   seD     3280      1058  3340      1030    2050 1710 1460 1230 1110  I    2910 1600    2620    1720 875725  B    I    1745 1078     1417132 1 0    195  1615    2600 ,     870 718 C      1072   1708 1450 1220  3400    1616  1285  35 30 25 20 16 _1  12 8  4      v /100 CH    Fig. 4. Infrared absorption spectra of 6 M HCl hydrolysed fungal debris after removal of humic-like pigments from A. niger (A), C. minitans (B) and R. solani (D).    This high frequency band is perhaps more appropriately assigned to ester carbonyl than to carboxyl, the ester carbonyl originating in a lactone ring (not smaller than 6-membered) formed between suitably positioned COOH and OH groups. In contrast, the spectra of debris and humic acid from R. solani are very similar (Fig. 4,C and Fig. 2,D). Spectra of the fungal pigments in all three debris samples show much more fine structure in the 1200-1400 cm-' range compared to the humic acids, illustrating the persistence of better organized non-hydrolysable cell-wall components in the debris. It is not known whether these components are an integral part of the pigment. As expected for HCl hydrolysed specimens, none of the fungal residues shows the 1650 and 1530 cm-'absorption bands of proteinaceous components in their IR spectra (Fig. 4). Before hydrolysis, however, these bands were present and indicated a significant protein contribution, a result which helps to explain the relatively large N contents of the fungal residues compared to humin (Table II).   From their elemental analyses and IR spectra, humin and humic acid are similar. This is in agreement with the pyrolysis-mass spectra studies of Saiz-  10    Jimenez et al. (1979). Furthermore it seems likely that the humin is derived, at least in part, from the dark pigments of several soil fungi, particularly those pigments which are insoluble in alkali and acid.    Soil incubation experiments     When'-labelled humin from a sandy loam was incubated with fresh soil, there was a rapid loss of radioactivity during the first 3 months (20%), but this rate of loss decreased during the subsequent 3 months (5%) after which time there was no further appreciable loss. Humic acid behaved in a similar manner (Fig. 5). The rates of decomposition of humin and humic acid in the soil would thus appear to be similar, a result that agrees with the observation of Paul et al. (1964), who have shown that in a Black Chernozem, the mean residence times of humin and humic acid were similar (1240 and 1308 years. respectively). This finding of comparable stabilities of humic acid and humin in soil indicates that the ratio of these fractions in a given soil should remain    nor    I    r 1    ?   F _ -- i^, _C. __ - j--   I   . iT    T/ Y  :-. zo  l.~  ~   1  o  i  f ,v     .f  io  0    I  71  -1  o I  ii    i&lt; 4 6 8     Inc t~rnP ,IYIO'1;h5)  Fig. 5. Degradation of "C-labelled humin (circles) and humic acid (triangles) during  incubation with fresh soil. Bar lines indicate standard errors of means of four replicates.  11    relatively constant with time. That the insoluble humin fraction undergoes significant biodegradation is at first surprising, but the observation clearly points to the dynamic state in which even apparently intractible organicmatter fractions exist in soil.    CONCLUSIONS     Soil humic substances have been defined broadly as having plant or microbial origins. However, the inherent complexity of soil, and the many and varied inputs to it, makes these origins necessarily obscure. In the upper litter horizons, the plant origin of organic matter may be more obvious, but in lower horizons, material of plant origin becomes progressively attenuated by the intense activity of the microbial population that occurs at these levels. The results presented here describing strong similarities between humin, humic acid and fungal pigments lead us to conclude that well humified soil organic matter is largely microbial detritus whose composition and structure is likely to vary with the microfloral population in the soil. It is of course recognised that organic matter components originating from sources other than the microbial population, and with spectral characteristics similar to those of humin, may also make some contribution to the humin fraction. Although humin is insoluble, it is shown to be degraded by soil organisms, with a pattern of stability very similar to that of humic acid, illustrating that both of these fractions contribute significantly to the pool of biological feedstock in the soil. From the close similarity between humin and fungal pigments as shown by their composition and IR spectra it is suggested that fungal pigment will have a stability in soil similar to that of humin. The conclusion that soil organic matter is predominantly microbial in origin is substantially the same as that expressed by Kang and Felbeck (1966) who proposed, from work on the nature of the humic acid-like pigment from A. niger, that humic acid in soil could be entirely of microbial origin. The hypothesis is also supported by the work of Filip et al. (1974) on various fungal pigments using IR and chemical analysis.    REFERENCES    Cheshire, M.V., Mundie, C.M. and Shepherd, H., 1973. The origin of soil polysaccharide: Transformation of sugars during the decomposition in soil of plant material labelled with "C. J. Soil Sci., 24: 54-68. Filip, A., Haider, K., Beutelspacher, H. and Martin, J.P., 1974. Comparison of IR-spectra from melanins of microscopic soil fungi, humic acids and model phenol polymers. Geoderma, 11: 37-52, Glentworth, R. and Muir, J.S., 1963. The Soils of the Country round Aberdeen, Inverurie and Fraserburgh. Memoirs of the Soil Survey of Great Britain (Scotland), Edinburgh, H.M.S.O. Grant, R., 1960. The Soils of the Country round Elgin. Sheet 95. Memoirs of the Soil Survey of Scotland (Interim memoir) Macaulay Institute for Soil Research, Aberdeen.  12    Jones, D. and Watson, D., 1969. Parasitism and lysis by soil fungi of Selerotinia selerotiorurn (Lib.) de Bary, a phytopathogenic fungus. Nature, 224: 287-288.  Jones, D. and Webley, D.M., 1968. A new enrichment technique for studying lysis of fungal cell walls in soil. Plant Soil, 28: 147-157.  Jones, D., Farmer, V.C., Bacon, J.S.D. and Wilson, M.J., 1972. Comparison of ultrastrurture and chemical components of cell walls of certain plant pathogenic fungi. Trans. Br. Mycol. Soc., 59: 11-23.  Kang, K.S. and Felbeck, G.T., 1966. A comparison of the alkaline extracts of tissues of Aspergillus niger with humic acids from three soils. Soil Sci., 99: 175-181.  Paul, E.A., Campbell, C.A., Rennie, D.A. and McCallum, K.J., 1964. In: The 8th International Congress of Soil Science, Bucharest', 3: 201-208.  Russell, J.D., Jones, D., Vaughan, D. and Fraser, A.R., 1980. A preliminary study of fungal melanin by infrared spectroscopy. Geoderma, 24: 207-213.  SaiznJimenez, C., Haider, K. and Meuzelaar, H.L.C., 1979. Comparisons of soil organic matter and its fractions by pyrolysis-mass spectrometry. Geoderma, 22: 25--3 7 .  Stevenson, F.J. and Goh, M.K., 1971. Infrared spectra of humic acids and related substances. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 35: 471-483.  Vaughan, D. and Ord, B.G., 1980. An effect of soil organic matter on invertase activity in soil. Soil Biol. Biochem., 12: 449-450.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 AbstractHumin, with a relatively low ash content, was isolated from a sandy soil by exhaustively dissolving humic and fulvic fractions in cold 0.5 M NaOH, and the mineral components in 20% HF. The infrared spectrum of the insoluble humin was similar to that of humic acid derived from the same soil, and resembled those of the humic-like pigments obtained from the soil fungi Coniothyrium minitans and Rhizoctonia solani. It was less like the spectrum of the pigment from Aspergillus niger which closely resembled that of the melanin pigment from Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. The brown debris remaining after extracting some of the fungi with NaOH, produced, on acid hydrolysis, fractions having IR spectra similar to acid hydrolysed humin. It is concluded from the similarity of humin, humic acid and fungal pigments, that well humified soil organic matter is to a large extent microbial in origin.When 14C-labelled humin from a sandy loam was incubated with fresh soil, about 20% of the radioactivity was lost after 3 months and 25% after 6 months, but subsequently there was virtually no further loss. A similar pattern of stability was obtained using 14C-labelled humic acid and this result, in conjunction with those from infrared spectroscopy, indicates a close relationship between humin and humic acid in terms of their structure, and their turnover in the soil. It is concluded that the composition of a soil humin is likely to be determined by the soil's microbial population.