 Geoderma, 33 (1984) 13--37                                                             13  Elsevier Science Publishers B V , Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    THE NATURE AND ORIGIN OF THE AEOLIAN MANTLES OF CENTRAL  NORTHERN NIGERIA    GRANT McTAINSH  School of Austrahan Enwronmental Studzes, Grlffzth Unwerszty, Brisbane 4111, Qld  ( A ustraha )  (Received March 28, 1983, revised versmn accepted November 1, 1983)    ABSTRACT    McTainsh, G , 1984. The nature and origin of the aeohan mantles of central northern  Nigeria Geoderma, 33. 13--37.    Evidence is presented here to show that the upland soils of central northern Nigeria  are formed in aeolian mantles deposited by two aeolian processes: aeolian suspension  (or dust) deposition and aeohan saltatlon (or dune sand) deposition. The soils to the  south and west of Kano are largely the product of Harmattan dust deposition, whereas  the northern soils appear to originate from dune sand migration from the Quaternary  dune fmlds to the east of the study area. The spatial pattern of particle-size populations  (or quanta) and quartz gram roundness characteristms, within the mantles and dune  sands, indicates that considerable mixing of dune sands and dust has occurred in the for-  mation of these mantles_    INTRODUCTION    In a recent issue of this journal Bennett (1980) described a distractive  spatial pattern of soft texture within the upland soils of central northern  Nigeria (Fig. 1). Recognition of this spatial pattern emerged from the results  of a land resource survey carrmd out by the Land Resources Development  Centre of the U.K. Overseas Development Administration (Bennett et al,,  1978). In his paper, Bennett (1980) uses the spatial pattern of soft texture to  propose an aeolian origin for the so-called "drift soils" of central northern  Nigeria. The aim of the present study is to further explain the ongm of the  drift softs.    Early studies    Falconer (1911) introduced the term "drift" when describing the soils on  the basement complex plains to the southwest of Kano (Fig. 1), noting that  they have "little affinity with the rocks whmh anywhere underhe them".  Falconer initially suggested an alluvial origin, explaining the remarkable    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B V    14    depth of soft upon mterfluves m terms of regional uplift and rejuvenaUon of  the drainage network of a once low-lying area There is, however, httle evi-  dence in support of structural movements on such a grand scale w~thm this  area of the Chad Basin durmg the Quaternary    I  I                               '!  ....  ~ J  )    ,-~                                ,~ "X.  ....  ~,l  ~'~"    ~'~             .'                 ....~. ~         ~,-       x H~,o    ~1  %_~   )  ......  ?'%'=E' // "', 1:  .='  ........  ".=   I){ ~"      -   , ~*?d~o "?~ ;::-,:'"',:~   ',    ";. :f...-'"  (,.                                     ,   //?/;~   ,.                 ~  ~-.  ,                   /                   ' ,        J         /    i      I'1C                 "                             "*- '~J] ~]~ ,  BoL~d ]r    \  ~q  /  eJ[    Fig. 1 Central northern Nigeria -- study area    During the first half of this century there developed a general awareness  amongst soil surveyors that the drift soils had an aeohan origin, but insuffi-  cient evidence was available to support this hypothesis. The later introduc-  tion of large-scale reconnaissance land resource surveys (Sombroek and  Zonneveld, 1971; Bennett et al., 1978) provided valuable new environmental  data and revwed interest m the question of the ongm of the drift soils.    This study    The present study may be viewed as a development of the work started  by the Land Resources Development Centre, m the sense that ~t tests further  the aeohan hypothesis for the origin of the soils of central northern Nigeria.    15    The principal working hypothesis of this research was that the spatial pat-  tern of soil texture as described by Bennett (1980) could be explained in  terms of two major aeohan processes operating throughout the Quaternary  to the present day. These two processes are: (1) the movement and deposi-  tion of aeolian suspended sediments, known at present as Harmattan dust,  and (2) the movement and deposition of aeolian saltation or dune sediments.  Evidence for the operation of these processes during the Quaternary is  presented and discussed here, in the following manner. Firstly, the methods  of laboratory analysis from which most of the data derive, are described,  then the characteristics of the Harmattan wind and its dust (present and  past) are discussed within the context of the Harmattan aeolian system. This  information is then used along with particle-size evidence to explain the  origin of the upland soil materials in the south of the study area. The char-  acteristlcs and origin of the soil materials in the north are then explained in  terms of dune sand migratmn from the relict dune fields to the east. Finally,  the interaction of the dune and the dust~lerived sediments m the formation  of the mantles is explained using partmle-size and quartz grain roundness  evidence. The principal conclusions of this research are then summarised.    METHODS    Particle-size analysis    Special analytical procedures were used to measure the size characteristics  of the Harmattan dust because of small sample sizes (around 0.1 g). Dust in  the size range 2--44 pm (9 -- 4.5 ~) fraction was dry-staved at 1/~ intervals.  The dust particle-size analysis methods are described m more detail by Mc-  TaInsh and Walker (1982).  Particle-size analysis of the &lt;31 ~m (5  material in the mantles and dune  sands was by the pipette method of Day (1965). Organic matter was re-  moved by digestion In H202 (30%) and samples were dispersed In Calgon and  NaOH. Samples were taken at C-intervals and aliquot weights of subsamples  were reproducible to within 3%.  The &gt;37 pm (4.75  fraction of the mantles and dune sands was dry-  sieved at 1A intervals for 20 minutes on a Rotap sieve shaker. A distinctive  feature of the sieve analysis was the recurrence of modes in the same size  fractions. This phenomenon occurred with such regularity that it was sus-  pected that particular sieves were damaged and although microscopic study  of the stove apertures did not confirm this, a set of new sieves were subse-  quently used to eliminate this possible source of error. The results of the  sieve analyses were reproducible to within a few per cent (Fig. 2).    Analysis and interpretation of the particle-size data  As considerable significance is given here to the interpretation of the par-  tlcle-size characteristics of the mantles, dune sands and dusts, the conceptual    16    model used for the presentation and Interpretation of the paxtmle-slze data is  described. The model used here was proposed by Folk (1971) in a study of  the Simpson Desert dunes, Australia. The distinctive features of the model  may, however, best be described within the broader context of partmle-size  statlstmal methods.    20_    %    15_    I0.    4  5  2  I~  65  125 250 500pro    Fig 2 Reproducibihty of dry sieve analysis results -- sand mantle (2Ts)    Udden (1914) and Krumbein (1937, 1938) recognised the sigmflcance of  the fact that most particle-size distributions are log-normal, however Bagnold  {1941) and Pettijohn (1957) emphasised that some sediments do depart  from log-normality. Subsequently, various graphical statistical methods  have been used to define those departures from log-normality whmh result  from the mixing of two or more sediment populations. Doeglas (1946),  Tanner {1958, 1964), Vlsher (1965, 1969) and Allen et al. (1972) used the  method of delimiting straight-line segments of log-probability cumulatwe  curves to discriminate populations, whereas Folk and Ward (1957) measured  the parameters of skewness and kurtosis using frequency curves. Spencer  (1963) demonstrated a method for identifying population mixing using fre-  quency curves which was later developed by Folk (1971) m his quantum  model.  In Folk's (1971) model the concept of a quantum or population IS used  to interpret poly-modal particle-size frequency curves. A quantum is as-  sumed to represent a deposit of well-sorted partmles, transported and de-  posited under particular conditions (e.g. windspeed, direction, turbulence) or  from a particular sediment supply. Because of changes in these condltmns  through time an aeolian deposit will comprise a mixture of different popu-  lations or quanta, each with its own particle-size character    17    Particle-size frequency curves are used in the present study to represent  the modal relationships within and between particle-size distributions. Fig. 3  shows the partmle-slze distributmns of three samples presented as relative-  frequency curves (A) and cumulative probability curves (B). Although the  same modal relationships can be seen on both curve types, the frequency  curve method displays more explicitly the modal characteristms of the  mantles and dune sands   ,  'il  Iq  'C  9  6  4  C    Nlar go Ounesond  qample MD IQ,  LCqI~L and M,3n lu  LS ample LE~  ZOrlo Loess Mon le  d~qmple ZI ,    q   8   ~   6   5   4  im,~~9    7'B   J56   315    65  PARTICLE SIZE    '1o  ,/  II  /    II  ,'   II    ,uo]  r  9~  b.J~  %   ,  7O  3O-  s~  I    Manqo Dunesand  (SGmple MD Io)  Lonlewa Sond Monlle  (Semple L6)  Zorlo Loess Manlle  kSample Z II)    I  /--J  I    /  /  /       QUANTA    45~  /         375gi  O    275    225 J~    125   250   500  I000               B                  PARTICLE   SIZE  ~"    Fig  3  Comparison of relative frequency and cumulative probability curve methods of  partmle-s]ze data presentation A  Relatwe frequency curves B Cumulative probability  curves    A potential disadvantage of frequency curves is that their shape can be in-  fluenced by size-class mterval, and as the dry-sieve data are at 1~ and the  pipette data are at 1/2 the method of curve construction had to accommo-  date this.  If a frequency curve is constructed from a relative-frequency histogram by  joining the midpoints of blocks which represent unequal size-class intervals,  the resulting curve ~s not a valid representation of a relatwe-frequency curve,  because the frequencies have been weighted by the widths of the class inter-  vals. To draw a correct relatwe-frequency curve it is essential to preserve the  relativity of the size-class mtervals over the whole range of particle-sizes. The  method used here is to adjust the percentage frequencms of the larger size-  class intervals to match those of the smallest size-class interval.    Fig. 4 illustrates an example of the method used. In histogram A, blocks  (or relative frequencms) A and B have a % ~ size-class interval, whereas block  C has a Y2 C-interval and block D a C-interval, and a frequency curve is shown  hnkmg the midpoints of each of the blocks; this is a misleading procedure In  histogram B, Fig. 4, the percentage frequencies of blocks C and D are ad-  justed to correspond to the smallest class interval, whmh is the % 0-interval  of blocks A and B. This involves dividing block C (originally 10%) into two  1/4 blocks each of 5%, whereas block D (originally 12%) is divided into four  14 ~ blocks each of 3%. These adjustments produce a corrected representa-  tion of the histogram, preserwng the relative values of the original blocks  Comparison of the frequency curve drawn from this histogram (Fig 4C) with  the unadjusted curve of histogram A shows a slgmflcant change m the ap  pearance of the frequency curve.    15_    I0.    c  '    5~    4    I}  o  o    r    ~Tq  l  JIiL J ~    '0  5    i    Fig 4 An example of the method of relative frequency curve construction.    Fig. 3A shows an example of the kind of partmle-size relationships which  emerge from the present study; the Lantewa sand mantle curve comprises  four partmle-size quanta: two coarse quanta (2.25 and 2.75 ~) whmh are  also found within the Manga dune sand and two freer quanta (3.75 ~ and  4.5 ~) whmh are typical of the Zana loess mantle. The significance of these  relationships will be discussed later in this paper.    19    Quartz gram roundness analysis methods  Roundness determinations were made on sieved 1A ~ size fractions using a  Leltz Weltzlar stereomlscroscope with point counter and a Joel JSM T20 scan-  nmg electron microscope. The samples for the scanning electron microscope  were mounted on alummmm stubs and made conductive by a coating of gold  with a Polaron gold sputterer. A back-scattered electron detector was used  with an accelerating voltage of 12.5 kV. The roundness images of Powers  (1953) were used, along with the numerical roundness scale (p) of Folk  (1955).  The scanning electron mmroscope was used initially for roundness deter-  mmatlons within the finer size range of the Harmattan dusts. Also, it was  used to check on the accuracy of the sterommroscope determinations, the re-  sults of which showed that the stereomicroscope roundness determinations  were biased towards the more rounded classes (Fig. 5). It was not, however,  necessary to apply a correction to the stereomlcroscope roundness data be-  cause these data for the dune sands and mantles remain valid in relative  terms.    o  n'~  co 3  Z  1:3  Z  ~2    "/  / X  ./  J  &amp; o  Sample Z12 (Zarla Loess  mantle )  x  Sample GDI (Gumel dunesand)  NOTE   Each data poml represents (~ gram  counl &gt;tO0 gralns    MEAN    ROUNDNESS  (S E  M)    Fig. 5. Comparison of quartz roundness values from the use of binocular and scanmng  electron mmroscopes    THE HARMATTAN AEOLIAN SYSTEM    The character of the Harmattan aeolian system in the present day is de-  scribed by McTamsh and Walker (1982) and is summarized here. During the    20    months of October to April the Harmattan wind carnes dust over northern  Nigeria in periodic pulses or plumes which reduce visibility (down to 500 m  during intense plumes), air temperatures and relative hunudlty. The dust  plumes studmd by Kalu (1979), McTalnsh (1982)and McTainsh and Walker  (1982) appear to originate from the Bodele Depression area of the Chad  Basra, however, Bertrand et al. {1974) have suggested on the basis of visibil-  ity records that the Tenere Desert area may also be a dust source area From  these source areas the dust is entrained by strong local surface winds and the  plumes travel to the W.S.W. out over the Chad Basra, the West Africa savan-  na lands and over the Tropical Atlantic Ocean, gradually depositing their  load of dust as they go {Prospero and Carlson, 1972; Morales, 1977; Pros-  pero et al., 1981). Measurements m northern Nigeria (McTamsh and Walker,  1982) indicate that both the rate of dust deposition and the partwle-slze of  the deposited dust, decrease with distance downwind.  Evidence from stratlgraphic studies of Atlantic Ocean sediments off the  West African coast (Parmenter and Folger, 1974; Bowles, 1975; Sarnthein,  1978; Sarnthem et al., 1981) has shown a substantial aeolian dust compo-  nent, and Bowles (1975) suggests a minimum timespan of 600,000 years of  aeolian deposition. McTainsh (1982) has concluded on the basis of these and  other studies of dust within and over the Atlantic Ocean, that Harmattan  dust is a principal source of these sediments  Given the contmental scale of operation and Quaternary time span of this  aeolian system the question arises: where are the aeolian mantles which must  have accumulated on the African continent? Perhaps the logical place to  look for such mantles is w~thin the area of the Chad Basm downwind from a  major source area, where dust deposition rates are relatively high. It could  also be argued that dust mantles are less likely to develop within the area of  Quaternary dunes because dune field mobfllsation would tend to remobihze  dust deposits  If we accept the evidence of Sarnthem (1978) and Sarnthein et al. (1981)  that there was no latitudinal shift m the Harmattan wind during the Qua-  ternary, the most likely areas of dust mantle formation would be within the  path of present-day dust plumes and on the humid margins of the Quatern-  ary dune fields. The area to the south of Kano meets all of these require-  lnents    HARMATTAN DUST AND THE ZARIA AEOLIAN MANTLES    A common theme within the various descriptions of the soils of central  northern Nigeria (Doyne et al., 1938; Vine, 1944, 1953; Higgins, 1963;  Klinkenberg and Hlggms, 1968) is the differentiation of the softs to the  north and south of the generahzed border running ESE--WNW through the  latitude of Kano. The northern softs are described as having relatively lower  clay percentages and coarser sand than the fine sandy and high clay southern    21    soils. This pattern is also evident within the spatial pattern of soil textural  bands resulting from the survey of the Land Resources Development Centre  (Fig. 6).  The area of so-called Zarm aeolian mantles (McTainsh, 1982) and the  Kano plains to the south of Kano includes soil textural bands 7, 8, 10, 11  and 12 (Fig. 6) and corresponds approximately with the Zaria group soils of  earlier investigations (Doyne et al., 1938; Lawes, 1962; Khnkenberg and  Hlggms, 1968) and also is continuous with the Funtua loessic deposit to the  west, described by Sombroek and Zonneveld (1971). The northern border  coincides roughly with the southern limit of rehct dunes.    Harmattan dust deposttion rates    Usmg the average primary dust deposition rate of 96 t/km2 measured at  Kano during 1976 to 1979, (McTainsh, 1982} and assummg a dust mantle  bulk density of 1.3 g/cm3, a theoretical layer of dust 74 ~m depth could be  deposited each year. If deposition has been occurring at this rate over the  past 40,000 years (which is Sombroek and Zonneveld's (1971) estimated  age of the nelghbourlng Funtua loessic deposit), then a mantle of 3 m could  theoretically accumulate.  Parmenter and Folger's (1974) work on tropical Atlantic Ocean sediments  indicates that dust may have been accumulating throughout the last two  rmlhon years of the Quaternary, therefore, even allowing for remobihsation  of sediment during and after depos~tlon, which has been demonstrated in  N~geria m the present day (McTainsh, 1980), Harmattan dust deposition dur-  ing the Quaternary in northern Nigeria has been competent to produce an  aeolian mantle of geological significance.  The depth of the Zarm aeohan mantle today ranges from 10--50 cm on  crests and to depths in excess of 5 m on lower slopes. Sombroek and Zonne-  veld (1971) estimate a "non~lisplaced" mantle thickness of 2--3 m for the  neighbourlng Funtua loessic deposit.    Harmattan dust and mantle partzcle-size    All of the Zaria aeohan mantle samples analysed displayed common  partmle-size characteristms, namely two clearly defined quanta: a coarse  quantum of size 75 ~m (3.75  and a finer quantum of 44 gm (4.5 , plus  a ~ 2 pm clay quantum and minor sand tail. By comparison, the coarsest  quantum size of dusts collected over northern Nigeria (McTainsh and Walker,  1982) is the 90 gm (3.5  Maldugurl dust sample and the finest dust quan-  tum is 15.6 pm (6  in dust collected at Jos and Sokoto (locations in Fig.  1). Evidently the particle-size range of the Zaria aeohan mantles falls within  the particle-size range of present-day dust. The Harmattan wind is therefore  competent to transport and deposit dusts of the size found in the Zaria  aeolian mantles.    22    ,i"~ "~,~  ,i            ",,~  ,,,,I'                   "~.  \                 ~..~.  /~r'4    te Katslna                       ,.,  ',._            Kazaure~/  L             '-,    ,,,,'~:~&lt;op~ ~odooo: m.  (---       '&lt;&lt;"/-4T~j            f,  I/  ,:         "i.,adu,~           1"  J  ' NIGERIA  (           .   ,--'  p- -i- --j   .    SOKOTO_ RIMA / h 2~,_ ..,_. ~                  l  RIVER BASIN (' ~,~"~~ -- ~ ...,     DUNEFIELDS  I    5              -,  /  ij                    /"--..s              8             f  t""  ) ~    iTun Wada      ,%.F-  ,b    2C   40    60km"" ~. ~                            I    /I N                                \                        ,..,\       2  ~  Kdno PId~ns Projec!         ""]                 C j  Area (Inset)                  "t              f  _~- Kano Plains (LR DO)             I,,             ,.~  -~-    Projecl Boundary                """l         ~'  /      L,                                           [  "" ,-,,.- International Boundary              t..,     .,-"   Soil Textural Bands                        ..--  LLJ                                  LLJ  ~DI                            ~l (efler Bennett" et el 1978)    Fig. 6  Pro]ecL    U K  Land Resources Development Centre, sml textural bands -- Kano Plains    23    Fig. 7 compares the particle-s~ze of a typmal Zana mantle with the par-  ticle-slze range of dust deposited at Zaria at present. The dusts axe generally  finer than the mantle, although the primary modes, or quanta, of three dust  samples approximate the 44 ~m (4.5  quantum of the mantle.    32 2A    24                          Zer,o Montle (Zll)  f        HARMATTAN DUST DEPOSITS DURING  22            1978-1979 SEASON  I         --  HD3  20  II              HD6  14  %    '1  12  ,o   LI  8  6  4  2    ~9    3   2    I~  125    250  500~m    "&lt;2    8     7     6     5     4  3 9       7 8        15 6      515       63  PARTICLE -SIZE    Fig  7  Partmle-mze characteristics of Harmattan dust deposited at Zaria and a Zarla  mantle.    The relative fineness of the dusts in the present day may be explamed by  invoking higher wmdspeeds and therefore coarser dust depomts during Qua-  ternary arid phases. Such an explanation receives support from the dust de-  posit evidence within Atlantic sediments (Parkin and Shackleton, 1973;  Bowles, 1975; Sarnthem, 1978; Sarnthem et al., 1981) and from the coastal  dune evidence of Talbot (1981) m southeast Ghana, which mdmates m-  creased wind vigour during arid phases. It is also m general agreement with    24    the hypothesis of decreased present-day wind velocity proposed by Higgms  (1963) in probably the first attempt to relate the characteristics of Harmat-  tan dust to those of the Zaria area soils.  An examination of the particle-size quantum characteristics of the Zaria  mantles and the dust, however, firstly in mantle stratlgraphic terms and then  in spatial terms, provides evidence of the operation of a different set of  aeolian processes.  Fig 8 shows the particle-size characteristics of three soil profiles from soil  textural bands 7, 8 and 10. In each mantle profile the two characteristic  quanta (4 5 ~ and 3 75  persist at depth, even in situations where the  mantle sediment is mixed with local coarse material at the discontinuity with  underlying laterltic ironstone. It is apparent from these three examples that  the mantle sediment being deposited upon this old landscape contained these  two particle-size quanta, although as shown in Mantle 10, the relative pro-  portions of the quanta may have changed through time This homogeneity  with depth was earlier described by the Land Resources Development Centre  (Bennett et al., 1978; Bennett, 1980} who found that, allowing for increase  m clay with depth due to eluvlation, plus local coarse material additmns, the  soil textural-band spatial pattern was essentially the same for the surface  horizons as for the horizons of maximum clay.  The general spatial pattern within the soil textural bands IS a fining to-  wards the SSW. This pattern has been interpreted by Ologe (1973), and more  recently by Whalley and Smith (1981), to reflect distance from the Harmat-  tan dust source area. Evidence in support of this process arises from the pres-  ent-day southward decreasing dust deposit particle-size demonstrated by Mc-  Talnsh and Walker (1982), but a closer study of the spatial pattern of mantle  particle-size quanta, in relation to the adjacent dune fields, leads to an alter-  native hypothesis.  The spatial pattern of particle-size in Fig. 9 shows a southward increase in  the 44 pm (4.5  quantum and decrease in the 75 tzm (3.75  quantum  within bands, 7, 8, 11 and 12 but in the neIghbourmg dune field (band 13,  Fig. 9) the 4 5 ~ quantum is barely dlscernable, whereas the 3.75 ~ quantum  remains substantial, along with two additmnal quanta of size 150 t~m  (2.75 ~) and 210 tim (2.25 4), which are typical of all dune sands within the  area. The mantle 9 curve displays a primary 3.75 quantum with subdued  2 75 ~ and 2.25 quanta which, in particle-size and spatial terms, is transi-  tional between the dune field and the Zaria aeolian mantle In summary, all  the mantles display 4.5 ~ and 3.75 ~ quanta whereas the dune sands com-  prise 3.75 4, 2.75 ~ and 2.25 quanta. The only common quantum is  3.75  These spatial patterns suggest that during Quaternary arid phases, when  Harmattan dust depositmn rates were apparently high, the dune field to the  east would have been receiving a large Input of dust, which according to the  present-day spatial pattern of dust deposition of McTainsh and Walker  (1982), would be coarser than the 4.5 quantum dust being deposited on    1-         ~       ~"/~ /~    I  I'    o          I   o_    N,   u~  L         i         i         ~          A            c~  ~      ~ ;I:':~  2~  u  ~b-O  Zfl-  I          1         t          I         I         I    E    2~  E  ~  /l  E  i ~o-~    E    E  c  ~     Q    o~     -4      &lt;1    o_  g   o  ~    ~    o-   -    E    25    b~  0  o~  c~  e,  oo    26    MAN'L[- 8It~               MANTLE 1             MANTLE 9            ~'II  ['~                                   !,  i          '  ,           I~,  '                                    I                               ~  IJ~i  I                            't,'                       ,      ]             %              !     i   - ..  j  7'-',.-.' '    --    I0       ,     "  .....  ': ~ ~         '  1-~. ''   .            '.~-   '..  13  /  ....  ....  MANTLE II  12  '           :    ,/ I  ~= J-/   ',    I    L /_ -_  _    i   q    [ ~    I k  ~ JANT*4    D,JNESAND ( ~URMA~  ")1    DUNESAND  JBIRNIN KUDU;    %              I'  I   '  /    MANTLE 12    i    Fig. 9  Particle-raze characterlstms of the Zarla aeohan mantles and neighbourmg dune  sands    the mantle plato further downwind. During an and phase, however, the dune  fields themselves would be mobile, so that dust deposits on the dunes would  soon be remoblllsed and transported downwind. The coarser fractions of this  remobilised dust (the 3.75 quantum) would not be expected to travel far  and may accumulate on the downwind margins of the dune field, on the  Zarla mantle plam, where remobilisatlon would be reduced. Such an aeolian  process would be expected to produce the largest (3.75  quantum compo-  nent close to the dune field, diminishing m a downwind direction. This is  evident in the downwind transect from bands 13-9-10-11 (Fig. 9), in which  the proportion of the 3.75 quantum diminishes relative to the 4.5 ~ quan-  tum. The predominance of this quantum in the drier northern bands (7 and  8) is also consistent with this hypothesis.    27    Fining of loess deposits with increasing d~stance from source has also been  demonstrated m the U.S.A. by Smith (1942). More recently, Frazee et al.  (1970) identified a two-stage process, with a higher rate of partmle-slze de-  crease over short distances near source, changing to a more gradual rate of  particle-size decrease over larger distances. Frazee et al. explain this spatial  pattern m terms of greater settling velocities of coarser silt particles (&gt;25  Urn), compared with the free silts and clays (&lt;25 urn). The same process  could be operating m northern Nigeria but the partmle-slze evidence within  the mantles may be masked by the mixing of the 4.5 and 3.75 quanta  produced by dust remobilisation from the dune field upwind. The spatml  pattern described by Frazee et al. (1970) may, however, still emerge from  more extensive studies over greater distances from the dune field source of  remoblhsed dust, where the mean deposit particle-size decreases to &lt; 25 pm.  In summary, therefore, the particle-size quantum characteristics of the  Zaria aeohan mantle indmate that it may have been formed by primary dust  deposition, which has produced the 4.5 quantum, and also by secondary  depositmn of dust remobihsed from the dune field upwind, producing the  3.75 quantum. A present-day analogue is the remobflisatmn of Harmattan  dust described by McTamsh (1980).  These conclusions gwe support to the use of the term loess to describe  these aeohan mantles. The term loess was originally used m Nigeria by  Higgins and Tomhnson (1961) and Lawes (1962, 1968), but without ex-  planation. The name Zaria loess mantle is proposed here for the soils cover-  Ing the area of bands 7 to 12 m Figs. 6 and 9. Maley (1982) has also identi-  fied soils formed on "loess-hke deposits" in nelghbouring Cameroun.    THE NORTHERN SAND MANTLES AND ADJACENT DUNE FIELDS    To the north of Kano the aeolian mantles are distinctly coarser textured  (bands 1 to 5 in Fig. 6), which puts them beyond the particle-sine range of  present-day Harmattan dust. It is proposed that these sand mantles resulted  from the movement of dune sands from the dune fields m the east, out over  the upland plains north of Kano during the Quaternary. In contrast to Har-  mattan dust, the processes of dune sand transportation and deposition are  seldom observed today.  The rehct dune fields were first identified by Falconer (1911), who called  them the Ancient Erg of Hausaland. More recently, Grove (1958) mapped  and subdivided the Ancient Erg into three smaller dune fmlds using aerial  photographs and McTainsh (1982) elaborated the pattern defining an addi-  tional dune field.  There is morphologmal evidence of a relationship between the dune fields  and sand mantles on the so-called Kazaure sand plato (McTainsh, 1982) south-  east of Katsina. In this area the Gumel dune field butts against a string of  quartzite hills, known as the Kazaure hills. To the west of the Kazaure hills,  Grove (1957) described an aerial photo pattern of east--west strips of park-    2~    land vegetation w~th shallow sotls over lateritm ~ronstone, ~mmedmtely west  of the gaps between the hills (F~g. 10). Th~s pattern was confirmed by Clay-  ton (1963). Satellite ~magery of the area shows a pattern of discontinuous  elongate strmtions (McTamsh, 1982) w~thm the sandy corndors. These stria-  t~ons proved elusive to definition on the ground and have been tentatively  traced to low elongate sand mounds. Grove and Pullan (1963) and Grove and  Warren (1968) suggested that the strip pattern ~s produced by the funnelhng    j 0-~ cuu-'-  .-            ~     ~ t  __  ,2oso'N b-b)    c,                              _ - ~_..~--  ,.~  .    .                   ~  ~ -,,f  (From KAZAURE I;lO0,O00Sheet  I"  I Scrublapd cr, d parkland               prepored by/he Directorate of Colonial  .                                           Surveys 1955 ~romaerlalphotographs)    [~ Arecls ot cuitlvOflOB and  piantahons  ~ Qugrtztte hills    NOTE The Quartzite Hills continue beyond  the eastern margins of this mop as foros  lot 125'    Fig. 10 Land use and vegetation patterns on the Kazaure Plato    29    of sand-carrying winds through the Kazaure hills. The striation evidence sup-  ports this hypothesis.  Further south,  on the sand plain immediately north and west of Kano,  morphological evidence of dune sand migration westwards is apparent in the  form of a small cluster of subdued dunes alongside the Gan River, immedi-  ately downwind from a gap withm the southern extension of the Kazaure  hills. Immediately northeast of Kano the presence of rehct dunes is evident  on aerial photos of the Jakara River. As the river cuts across each longitu-  dinal dune the channel is restricted whereas in the dune swales the river  spreads laterally producing a distinctive aerial photo pattern.  On the Kano sand plato the sand mantles display a marked uniformity  over large distances as described by Bennett et al. (1978), also noted by  earher workers, yet the underlying basement complex rocks and laterltic  ironstone display complex spatial varmbihty, which is further evidence of the  external origin of these sand mantles.  The spatial pattern of sand mantle depth from the dune fmlds westward  over the Kano sandplam shows an overall thinning with distance downwind  which may reflect sand movement from the dune fields (McTainsh, 1982).  The dune sands are generally greater than 2 m depth within the dune fmld  whereas on the lowland sand plam the mantle depth (averaged within 35  topo-sequences) is 1.4 m and on the upland sandplaln, further west, the  mantle depth decreases to 0.9 m (19 topo-sequences).    HARMATTAN DUST, DUNE SANDS AND AEOLIAN MANTLES    The results and discussion so far indicate that the Zarla loess mantle to  the south of Kano was formed principally by Harmattan dust deposition,  whereas the northern sand mantles were formed by the westward migration  of dune sands. Although there is evidence that the intensity of dust trans-  port and deposition was greater before than after 7,000 yr BP (Maley, 1982),  it is reasonable to assume that dune sand and dust transportation and de-  position would have operated simultaneously during the Quaternary, with  a bias towards dune sand accumulation in the drier north of the study area  and dust accumulation in the less arid south, although mixing of the two  aeohan sediments would also have occurred. A detailed study of the partmle-  size quantum charactenstms of the dune sands and sand mantles, dust and  loess mantles, provides evidence of the nature of the interaction between  these Quatemary aeohan processes and their sediments.    Parttcle-stze evidence  Two particle-size quantum groups are evident in various proportions with-  in all the dune sands, and mantles and loess mantles. The loess quanta of    size 75 ~m (3.75 0~ and 44 t~m (4.5 0) as discussed earher, orgmate from  Harmattan dust, whereas the dune sand quanta of size 210 t~m (2.25 0) and  150 t~m t2.75 ~) are pecuhar to the dune helds. In addition, there are two  rmnor quanta  tl) the clay quantum &lt;2 t~m (9 0), originates from dust de-  position, with a possible post-depomtlonal weathering component: In) the  coarse material quantum ,&gt; 250 ~m 12 ) whmh is manifest as a coarse tail is  probably of local basement complex origin. Maternal within the 3.25--3.5  s~ze range is probably a residue, resulting from the mlxmg of the two major  quantum groups  Fig. 3A shows an example of this partlcle-sxze quantum  m~xmg The coarsest sample tMDla) is made entxrely of the two dune sand  quanta, whereas the freest sample (Zll) compmses the two loess quanta and  the intermediate size sample ~ L6) consists of a mixture of the two quantum  groups  The spatial aspect of th~s m~xmg of particle-size quanta is shown m F~g.  11 The dune sands in the north show a predominance of the dune sand  quanta, best developed within the Manga dune field (see MD lb, Fig. 11).  In the Lantewa dune field, further south, the dune sand quanta are supple-  mented by the loess quanta, and m the Gumel dune field, in the central area,  there is a more equal mixture of the two quantum groups,  The sand mantles m Fig. 11 display basically the same partmle-slze quan-  tum characteristics as the dune sands upwind, from whmh they originated.  Compare in F~g  11 the particle-size curves of the Gumel dune sand and  Gumel sand mantle (GD3 and G3, respectively), and also the Lantewa dune  sand and sand mantle ILD5 and L5, respectively) The two samples on the  Kano upland plain (2Ts and 2Ad) d~splay reduced Manga dune sand quanta  which may reflect their ~reater distance from and height abow~ the dune  fields.  The provenance of the two dune sand quanta appear to be the Cretaceous  sedimentary rocks of northern N~gerla and southern Niger, because the dune  GD, Fig, 11) and northeast (sample MDlb, Fig. 11) display the most pro-  nounced dune sand quanta, and furthermore, the proportion of 2.75 quan-  tum material increases at the expense of the 2.25 0 quantum with dmtanee  downwind from the Manga dune field (compare MDlb, MDlc, GD2, GD3  and G3). The exception to this spatxal trend is GD1, but as indicated earlier,  its partmle-slze character is conmstent w~th its locatmn on the small area of  Cretaceous sedimentary rocks in the northwest. Sombroek and Zonneveld  11971) also found dune fields best developed over Cretaceous sedimentary  rocks m northwest Nigeria.  lmphelt in this explanation is the notion that the distances of dune sand  transport during the Quaternary have been of the order of 1000 km. This is  consistent with Sombroek and Zonneveld's (1971) contentmn that dune  sand transport m northwest Nlgema has been on a local scale, but is at vam-  anee with the conclusmns of Wilson (1971), Guy and Mamguet (1975),  Mainguet and Canon (1976) and Mamguet (1977), who describe Saharan  dune sand transport on a continental scale. In southern Niger, Mainguet et    31    z ~" L~ U3 LQ  &lt;~   0      -- z  o   ~  x   ,  "J^m~    .~  ......  "1  U,   ,   ,Jl,  o     _    o    ~    o   z   /              ~    o    Lo    o    ~    o       ~n    o    ~    o  ,-k X   \,~',                    m'           ,,~  _ ,     #    \\  ____-~Jl: o   I i     '~     '4 \\ ~       _ Jl:.  .~   - o   ~             I                 ',     2"-.                         ,.-,  --  ~      /~                I,   'j.~      ~        .~        I.~ "~  -    -  ~                                                                      .2_        ~           _o     ~     o               o     ~     o              _'2     (:2_     ~     o        ~     _(2     ~     o    ,-4                            S                             .'4                          ,-4            ~.~    32    al. (1980) describe partmle-size decreases in dune sand in a southwest direc-  tmn over a distance of 600 kin, although they did recogmse mixing with  local materials.  The greater dune transport distances observed closer to and within the  Sahara Desert, compared with northern Nigeria, may be explicable m terms  of the longer duration of aeohan processes in the more arid regmns.    Quartz gram roundness evzdence    The results of quartz gram roundness analyses (Fig, 12) show size-depen-  dent changes m roundness within and between the dune sands, sand mantles  and loess mantles. It is immediately evident m Fig. 12, that the roundness  decrease with decreasing size, often found m single population or quantum  sediments (Russell and Taylor, 1937; Pettl]ohn, 1957) is not found here,  rather, each of the quanta has a distinctive roundness character    4 50 475  4 25 -450    375-400    350 375  w  3 25-350  r~  u   2 75-3 O0  t.    225-250    I 75-20Q    \    \  -%-  ,&lt;.:-  //,f;," v,  /    l L;  :',  ~  h.,,c  ,  /   ,  i        'di,    ,"  / i,i  / I,  /  I    711  21) ZIr, 7N    ,,,/   ~   i'!,1  / /              I  , /    Gumel Dunesonds8, Sond Monlleq  Zor,o Loess Montles  Lonfewa Dunesonds 8, Sond  Monlles  Erich dot(] poln~ lepre~en/s o grolr  , eunt , IOO )    "             '1  -        I  i,     \  I,     \              tD~     I     \  ~SZ~  GD4     ,;5 rsD~  GDI  LD9    4'8    ~O   24    2'B    ~ '    ~h    40    4'4-  ME&amp;N  B',]UNDNESb %,)  Fig. 12. Quartz roundness characteristms in relation to particle-size of dune sands, sand  mantles, and loess mantles    33    In the partmle-slze range, 1.75 to 3 (300--125 ~m), which incorpo-  rates the 2.25 and 2.75 dune sand quanta the samples fall into the same  three groups defined earlier usmg particle-size criteria: (1) Gumel dune sands  and sand mantles, (2) Lantewa dune sands and sand mantles, and (3) Zaria  loess mantles. The Gumel dune sands and sand mantles are the most rounded  (&gt;3.6 p), the Lantewa dune sands and sand mantles fall within the rater-  mediate roundness values (3.3--3.7 p), and the Zarla loess mantles are the  most angular (&lt; 3.2 p).  From the previous discussion of particle-size it was apparent that the  Manga quanta are best developed m the Manga dune sands, and to a slightly  lesser extent, m the Gumel dune sands and sand mantles. These quanta  dlmimsh within the Lantewa dune sands and sand mantles and are entirely  absent from the loess mantles. It follows, therefore, from these roundness  results, that the Manga quanta are charactensed by well-rounded quartz  grams m contrast to the Zaria loess mantles whmh have angular quartz grains,    4 75-5 O0  4 50-4 75  400-450    3 75 - 4 00_    3 50-3 75_  3 O0- 3 50_  co   2 50-300  ,cI  CL    2 25-2 50.    I 75- 2 25.    Fig    I I~~ ~              HARMATTAN DUST  \~  ....  HD26  ------ HD29/30  \ ,(~.\           -- HD 24  ~.,      MANTLES / DUNESANDS   \  - - GD,  \ \  ,-   \   \  /          '  I  I  I            \\\    13    i  ,'2   ,'G  2'0  2'4  2'e  ~2  ~6  40  44  MEAN  ROUNDNESS (p)  Quartz roundness characteristics of Harmattan dust and the aeolian mantles,    34    within this 1.75--3 ~ (300--125 pm) size range, and as this particle-size  range is generally too coarse for suspended aeolian transport, it appears that  this material is derived from local m sltu basement complex regoliths. The  Lantewa dune sands and sand mantles occupy an intermediate position in  roundness terms, reflecting a mixture of the Manga quanta and basement  complex material.  In the particle-size range 3.25--3.75 (104--75 t~m), which incorporates  the 3 75 ~ loess quantum m Fig. 12, the three dune sand and mantle groups  have converged to cover a much more restricted range in roundness classes.  The Gumel dune sands and sand mantles remain slightly more rounded,  which is probably produced by the fine tail of the 2.75 Manga quantum  spilling over into the smaller sizes m these samples. The Zana loess mantles  remain slightly more angular, perhaps for the same reason  In the 3 75--4.75 ~ (75--37 pm) size range, which incorporates the 4 5  loess quantum, all the samples appear to occupy a relatively narrow band of  roundness, shown by the greatest and least rounded samples (GD1 and Z10,  Fig. 12), the overall roundness of which decreases more rapidly with de-  creasing particle-size than in the coarser partmle-mze ranges  Fig. 13 demonstrates that within the size range 3 5--4.75 ~ there is a good  roundness relationship between the mantles, dune sands and Harmattan  dusts deposited today, which supports the hypothesis that the Zaria loess  mantles originate from Harmattan dust deposltmn, and furthermore suggests  that material of this size m the dune sands and sand mantles may also origi-  nate from Harmattan dust depositmn.  In summary, the results of the quartz roundness analyses provide further  support for the hypothesis based upon particle-size evidence.    CONCLUSIONS    The evidence on particle-size and quartz grain roundness presented here  indicates that the soils of the Kano plains are formed in aeolian mantles  deposited during the Quaternary by the mixing of aeolian suspension and  saltation sediments, Harmattan dust and dune sands, and that the range of  sml charactenstms reflects the degree of mixing of these two aeolian sedi-  ments.  In the north of the Kano plains where dune sand sediments predominate,  the soils are coarse textured, structureless, well-drained and of low chemmal  fertyhty. In the south where dust deposition is the major process in the for-  mation of loess mantles, the soils are fine-textured, well-structured, poorly  drained and of higher chemical fertihty.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS  The research work reported In this paper was initiated in Nigeria through  the valuable contact with the LRDC scientists working there. Financial as-    35    sistance was provided m Nigeria by Bayero University, Kano, where the  author was employed, and in Austraha by Macquarm University, where the  author was a PhD student. Sincere thanks to Assoc. Prof. Martin Williams  for his critical comments on this paper and for his constructive supervision  of the PhD thesis from whmh it is derived.    REFERENCES    Allen, G P , Castalng, P. and Kllngebiel, A , 1972 Distinction of elementary sand popula-  tions in the Gironde Estuary (France) by R-mode Factor Analysis of graln-size data.  Sedlmentology, 19 21--35  Bagnold, R A , 1941 Physics of Blown Sand and Desert Dunes Methuen, London, 265  pp-  Bennett, J.G, 1980. Aeolian deposition and soil parent materials in northern Nigeria.  Geoderma, 24 241--255  Bennett, J G., Hutcheon, A A., Ibanga, J , Kerr, W.B., Mansfield, J E., Rackham, L.J and  Valette, J., 1981. Land Resources of Central Nigeria: Environmental Aspects of the  Kano Plains, 1 Landforms and Soils Land Resour. Dev. Cent , U K. Rep., 20.  Bertrand, J J., Baudet, J and Drochon, A., 1974_ Importance des aerosols naturals en  Afrlque de l'Ouest. J Rech Atmos., 8 845--860.  Bowles, F A., 1975. Paleoclimatic significance of quartz/llllte variation in cores from the  Eastern Equatorial North Atlantic. Quat Res., 5  225--235  Clayton, W.D., 1963 The vegetation of Katslna Province, Nigeria J Ecol , 51  345--351  Day, P R, 1965  Particle fractlonatlon and particle-size analysis In  C A Black et al.  (Editors), Methods of Soil Analysis Am Soc_ Agron , pp. 545--567  Doeglas, D J, 1946  Interpretation of the results of mechanical analyses  Sediment.  Petrol., 16 19--40  Doyne, H.C , Harley, K T and Watson, W A, 1938 Soil types and manurial experiments  in Nigeria. 3rd West Afr Agric_ Conf, 1938  Falconer, J D_, 1911. The Geology and Geography of Northern Nigeria. MacMillan,  London  Folk, R.L., 1955 Student operator error in determlnatlon of roundness, sphericity and  grain size. J Sediment Petrol., 25 297--301_  Folk, R.L, 1971 Longitudinal dunes on the northwestern edge of the Simpson Desert,  Northern Territory, Australia, 1. Geomorphology and grain-size relationships Sedl-  mentology, 16" 5--54.  Folk, R L and Ward, W C., 1957. Brazos River Bar: A study in the significance of grain-  size parameters. J. Sediment Petrol., 27 3--26.  Frazee, C.J., Fehrenbacher, J B  and Krumbeln, W C , 1970  Loess distribution from a  source Proc Soil Scl. Soc Am., 34(2) 296--301  Grove, A T , 1957. Patterned ground in northern Nigeria Geogr J, 123 271--274.  Grove, A T, 1958. Ancient Erg of Hausaland and similar formations on the south side of  the Sahara Geogr J., 124(4) 528--533.  Grove, A.T and Pullan, R A, 1963 Some aspects of the Pleistocene paleogeography of  the Chad Basin. In: F.C. Howell and F. Bourll~re (Editors), African Ecology and Hu-  man Evolution_ Aldlne, Chicago  Grove, A.T and Warren, A , 1968. Quaternary landforms and climate on the south side of  the Sahara. Geogr J,134:194--208  Guy, N.M. and Malnguet, M., 1975. Geomorphologle dynamique -- les courants de trans-  port eohen au Sahara et leurs manifestations au sol C R Acad Scl , 281: 103--106_  Higglns, G M., 1963. Upland soils of the Samaru and Kano area Inst. Agrm Res , Samura,  Nigeria, unpubl. Rep    36    Hlggms, G,M  and Tomhnson, P R , 1961, Soils of the western chmatm middle belt m  northern Ntgerla. Prec. 4th Meet C R O A C U S , Samaru/Mokwa, Nigeria  Hutka, J , Walker, P H  and McTamsh, G H , 1981  Particle-size analysis of Harmattan  dust deposited m Nigeria Tech Menlo , C S I R O Division of Soils, 6/198l  Kalu, AE, 1979 The Afrmandust plume' ltscharacteristmsandpropagatlonacrossWest  Africa in winter  In. C Morales (Ed~toi), Saharan Dust  Moblhsation, Transport and  Deposition J Wiley, New York, Ch 5  Klinkenberg, K_ and Htggms, G M   1968  An outhne of Northern Nigeria soils, Nlg J  Sc) ,2(2)" 01-115  Krumbem, W C , 1937 Sedlmentsand exponential craves J Geol , 45. 577 -601  Krumbem, W C , 1938  S~ze frequency distributions and the normal ph~ curve. J Sedv  ment Petrol ,8" 84--90  Lawes, DA, 1962  The influence of rainfall conservation on the fertfl~tV of the loess  plains sods of northern Nlgerm. Niger Geogr J , 5:33--38  Lawe% DA, 1965  A note of the sod moisture storage capacity of the Samaru s(nl%  northern Nxgerm Inst Agrm Res , Samaru Misc. Pap , 5  McTamsh, G H, 1980  Harmattan dust deposition m northern Nigeria, Nature, 286  587--588  McTainsh, G H , 1982 Harmattan dust, Aeolian Mantles and Dunesands of Central North-  ern N,gena Unpubhshed PhD thesis, Macquarm University, N S_W , Austraha  McTamsh, G H and Walker, PH , 1982  Nature and distribution of Harmattan Dust  Z  Geomorphol , 26. 417--435  Mamguet, M , 1977  Geomorphologle -- Analyse quantitative de l'extr6mlt6 sahelhenne  du courant eohen iransporteur de sable au Sahara mgerien. C R  Acad  Scl., Paris,  285 1029--1032  Mamguet, M and Canon, L , 1976 Vents et paleovents du Sahara Tentative d'approche  paleochmatlque Rev Geogr Phys Geol Dyn,2(18)' 241  250  Mamguet, M , Cossus, L and Chapelle, A.M , 1980 Utdlsatmn des images Meteosat pour  preclser les trajecto~)es eohennes au sol, au Sahara et sur les marges Sahelliennes_ Soc  Fr Photogr , Bull , 2  Maley, J , 1982  Dust, chluds, ram types and ehmatlc variations m tropmal North Africa  Quat Res, 18" 1--16  Morales, C (Editor), 1977 Saharan Dust. MobihsatLon, Transport, Deposition Ecol Res  ('omm_ Swed  Nat  Sci  Re~ Couns  and S C O,P E  Comm , Gothenburg, Sweden,  April 1977  Ologe, K O, 1973 Soft erosion, sedlmentyield and water resources development m the  savanna areas of Nigeria  Proc  Conf  Environ  Resour  Manage  Nigerm, July 1973,  Univ ofIfe, N,germ  Parkm, D,W and Shackleton, N J , 1973 Trade wind and temperature correlations down  a deep-sea core off the Saharan coast Nature, 245- 455--457  Parmenter, C and Folger, DW, 1974 Eohan bmgemc detritus m deep-sea sediments, a  possible index of equatorml Ice Age aridity Scmnce, 185. 695--697  Pettljohn, F J  1957 Sedimentary Rocks Harper and Bros, New York, 2nd ed , 718 pp  Powers, M C , 1933  A new roundness scale for sedimentary partwles Sediment Petrol ,  23 117-119  Prospero, J M and Carlson, T,W , 1972  Vertical and aereal dlstributmn of Saharan Dust  over the western Equatorial North Atlantm Ocean J Geophys Res_, 77(27)' 5255--  5265  Prospero, J M , Glaccum, R A and Nees, R.T , 1981 Atmospheric transport of soft dust  from Africa to South America Nature, 289  570--572  Russell, R D and Taylor, R.E_, 1937 Roundness and shape of Mississippi River sands_ J  Geol , 45" 225--267  Sarntheln, M , 1978 Sand deserts during glacml maximum and climatm optimum Nature,  271 45--51    37    Sarnthein, M., Tetzlaff, G , Koopmann, B., Walter, K and Pflaumann, U , 1981 Glacial  and interglacial wind regimes over the eastern subtropmal Atlantm and Northwest  Afrma. Nature, 293:193--196  Smith, G.D, 1942. Illinois Loess--variations m its propertms and distribution a pedologm  interpretation. Umv Ill. Agrm. Exp. Sta Bull., 490' 139--184.  Sombroek, W G. and Zonneveld, I S., 1971 Ancmnt dunefields and fluviatde deposits m  the Rima-Sokoto Rwer Basra (N.W Nigeria) Sod Surv Inst , Wageningen Soil Surv  Pap , 6" 102 pp  Spencer, D W , 1963. The interpretation of grain-size distribution curves of clastic sedi-  ments J Sediment Petrol, 33(1): 180--190  Talbot, M R., 1981  Holocene changes m tropical wind intensity and rainfall' evidence  fromS.E Ghana Quat Res,16:201--220  Tanner, W_F., 1958  Comparison of phi-percentile deviations J Sediment Petrol, 28  203--204.  Tanner, W_F , 1964 Modification of sediment size distributions J Sediment Petrol , 34:  156--164  Udden, J A , 1914  Mechanical composition of clastic sediments. Geol_ Soc. Am. Bull ,  25:655--744  Vine, H, 1944. Soil work of the Chemical Section Agricultural Department, Nigeria  Farm Forest, 5(3).  Vine, H_, 1953  Notes on the main types of Nigerian soils Spec Bull , 5, Gov Printer,  Lagos  Visher, G S , 1965_ Fluvial processes as interpreted from ancient and recent fluvial de-  posits  In: G V Middleton (Editor), Primary sedimentary structures and their hydro-  dynamic interpretation Soc Econ. Paleontol Mineral., Spec Publ., 12: 84--115.  Vlsher, G S_, 1969_ Gram size distributions and depositlonal processes. Sediment. Petrol ,  39(3): 1074--1106  Walker, P H , Woodyer, K.D and Hutka, J., 1974 Particle-size measurements by Coulter  Counter of very small deposits and low suspended sediment concentrations in streams  J_Sediment Petrol,44:673--679  Whalley, W B and Smith, B.J_, 1981 Mineral content of Harmattan dust from northern  Nigeria examined by scanning electron microscopy. J Arid Environ., 4:21--29  Wilson, I G, 1971  Desert sandflow basins and a model for the development of ergs.  Geogr. J_, 137. 180--198_                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    AbstractEvidence is presented here to show that the upland soils of central northern Nigeria are formed in aeolian mantles deposited by two aeolian processes: aeolian suspension (or dust) deposition and aeolian saltation (or dune sand) deposition. The soils to the south and west of Kano are largely the product of Harmattan dust deposition, whereas the northern soils appear to originate from dune sand migration from the Quaternary dune fields to the east of the study area. The spatial pattern of particle-size populations (or quanta) and quartz grain roundness characteristics, within the mantles and dune sands, indicates that considerable mixing of dune sands and dust has occurred in the formation of these mantles. 