 Geoderma, 29 (1983) 175--193                                                  175  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    CURRENT TITLES IN SOIL SCIENCE    Alfano, John Joseph. A two-layer ground hydrology model interactive with an atmospheric general  circulation model:  641 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Connecticut, Storrs, CT. amilable from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Alvarado, Alfredo; Berish, Cory W.; and Peralta, Francisco. Leaf-cutter ant (Atta cephalotes) influence  on the morphology of Andepts in Costa Rica: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  1-6, p. 790-794, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Anderson, D. W.; Saggar, S.; Bettany, J. R.; et aL Particle size fractions and their use in studies of soil  organic matter; I, The nature and distribution of forms of carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur: in Proceedings  of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 767-772, 4 tables, 1981.  Anderson, David L.; Lesh, John G.; and Wickmn, Donald W. Soil survey of Kiowa County, Colorado:  125 p., illus. (incl. 15 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map 1:316,800), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Ser., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Colo. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Anderson, J.H. Soil palynology and paleoecology of the Washington Creek Black Spruce Experimental  Forest, interior Alaska [abstr.]:  in Life sciences in the service of Alaska (Bligh, J., chairperson),  Proceedings - Alaska Science Conference, No. 32, p. 41-42, 1981.  Angelides, Demosthenes C.; and Roesset, Jose Manuel. Nonlinear lateral dynamic stiffness of piles:  Journal of the Geotechnical Engineering Division, Vol. 107, No. GT11, p. 1443-1460, illus., 1981.  Arkley, R. J.; and Nettleton, W.D. Genesis of a Typic Durixeraif of southern California; comment and  reply:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 672, 1981.  Atkinson, David J. The Roosevelt Field; new model and geochemical evaluation:  in Geothermal  energy; the international success story (Edmiston, R. C., chairperson), Transactions - Geothermal  Resources Council, Vol. 5, p. 149-152, 1981.  Geothermal Resources Council, 1981 annual meeting.  Ayodele, Olufemi; and Agboola, ,~kinola A. Evaluation of phosphorus fixation capacity of tropical  savannah soils of western Nigeria: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 462-464,  4 tables, 1981.  Baker, A. S.; Kuo, S.; and Chae, Y.M. Comparisons of arithmetic average soil pH values with pH values  of composite samples: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 828-830, illus.  (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Bell, Elaine J.; and Juncal, Russell W. Solid-sample geochemistry study of western Dixie Valley,  Churchill Connty, Nevada; Part I, Petrochemistry: in Genthermal energy; the international success story  (Edmiston, R. C., chairperson), Transactions - Geothermal Resources Council, Vol. 5, p. 47-50, illus.  (incl. sketch map), 1981. Geothermal Resources Council, 1981 annual meeting.  Bell, Keith; and Card, J.W. Grant 38; Radon decay products and uranium exploration: in Geoscience  Research Grant Program; summary of research, 1980-1981 (Pye, E. G., editor), Ontario Geological  Survey Miscellaneous Paper, No. 98, p. 18-24, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Berquist, C.R. Lamellae in soils; modern secondary structures [abstr.]: inVirginlaAcademyofScience;  Fifty-ninth annual meeting (Anonymous), Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 32, No. 3, p. 126, 1981.    176    Betaneourt, JuIlo L.; and Van Devender, Thomas R. Holocene vegatation in Chaco Canyon, New  Mexico: Science, Vol. 214, No. 4521, p. 656-658, chart, I table, 1981.  Beven, Kelth. Kinematic subsurface stormfiow: Water Resources Research, VoL 17, No. 5, p. 1419-  1424, I tables, 1981.  Bick/, Thomas James. Geomorphology, stratigraphy, and soil development in the Iowa and Cedar River  valleys in southeastern Iowa: 348 p., Doctoral, 1981, Iowa State Univ., Ames, IA. available /rom." Univ.  Microfilms.  Biggar, Norma E.; Harden, Deborah R.; and Gillam, Mm-y L. Quaternary deposits of the Paradox Basin:  in Geology of the Paradox Basin 0Niegand, Del L., editor), Field Conference - Rocky Mountain  Association of Geologists, Vol. 1981, p. 129-145, illus. (incl. sect., strat, cols., geol. sketch map), 1981.  Biota, Ronld; and Daily, Mike. Seasat views California with imaging radar: California Geology, Vol.  34, No. II, p. 231-240, illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1981.  Bloem, P.R. Phosphorus adsorption by an aluminum-peat complex: in Proceedings of the 45th annual  meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 267-272, 5 tables, 1981.  Boegli, Alfred. Scallops: in Proceedings of the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry  F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 82-83 (incl. German sum.),  1981.  Bond, Richard W.; and Handler, John F. Soil survey of Hillsborough County, New Hampshire, eastern  part: 152 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric.  Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with N.H. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Bonmmn, B. T.; and DeBeil, D.S. Nitrogen content and other soil properties related to age of red alder  stands: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 428-432, illus. (incl. 2 tables),  1981.  Boscn, J. R.; and Robinson, G.D. Trace mercury in surficial materials associated with sulfide deposits  near Mineral, Virginia [abstr.]:  in Virginia Academy of Science; Fifty-ninth annual meeting  (Anonymous), Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 32, No. 3, p. 126, 1981.  Boamn, J.; and Dekker, L. W. A method for measuring the vertical and horizontal Ksat of Clay soils  with macropores: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 662-663, illus. (incl. 1 table),  1981.  Bouwer, Herman. Reactive solutes and materials in groundwater: in Proceedings of the Groundwater  pollution conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et aL), Australian Water Resources Council Conference  Series, No. 1, p. 242-262, illus., 1981.  Bowman, William L. Soil survey of Monroe County, Michigan: 138 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Mich. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Box, J. E., Jr. The effects of surface slaty fragments on soil erosion by water: in Proceedings of the  45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 111-116, 5 tables, 1981.  Boyd, Stephen A.; Sommers, Lee F_,.; Nelson, Darrell W.; et al. The mechanism of copper (II) binding  by humic acid; an electron spin resonance study of a copper (II); humic acid complex and some adducts  with nitrogen donors:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 745-749, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Braddock, R. D.; Parlange, J. Y.; and Lisle, I.G. Properties of the sorptivity for exponential diffusivity  and application to the measurement of the soil water diffusivity: in Proceedings of the 45th annual  meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 705-709, 3 tables, 1981.  Bradford, J. M. The shear strength of a moderately well-structured soil in its natural and remolded  states: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 9-12, illus., 1981.    177    Breisch, Richard L.; and Wefer, Fred L. The shape of gypsum bubbles: in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 757-759 (incl. German sum.), illus., 1981.  Breason, L. M. Ion micromllling applied to the ultramicroscopic study of soils: in Proceedings of the  45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 568-573, illus., 1981.  Briggs, G. G, Adsorption of pesticides by some Australian soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research,  Vol. 19, No. l, p. 61-68, I0 tables, 1981.  Brown, J.L. Calcium phosphate precipitation; identification of kinetic parameters in aqueous limestone  suspensions: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B.  A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 475-477, illus. (incl. 1 table),  1981.  Brown, J.L. Calcium phosphate precipitation; effects of common and foreign ions on hydroxyapatite  crystal growth: in Proceedings of the 45tb annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 482-486, illus. (incl. 1 table),  1981.  Brown, Lester R. World population growth, soil erosion, and food security: Science, Vol. 214, No.  4524, p. 995-1002, 5 tables, 1981.  Bryan, Rorke B.; sad Luk, Shiu-Hng. Laboratory experiments on the variation of soil erosion under  simulated rainfall: Geoderma, Vol. 26, No. 4, p. 245-265, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1981.  Burns, S.; and Rawitz, E. The effects of sodium and organic matter in sewage effluent on water retention  properties of soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 487-493, illus. (incl. 3 tables),  1981.  Bush, R. Dennis. Soil survey of Luzerne County, Pennsylvania: 106 p., illus. (incl. 13 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored softs maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep. Environ. Resour., State Conserv.  Comm.).  Calhoun, John W. Soil survey of Crisp and Turner counties, Georgia: 120 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps 1:126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC,  United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Ga.; Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Carter, Virginia; Gammon, P. T.; and Garrett, M.K. Relationship of vegetation to hydrology and soils  in the Great Dismal Swamp, Virginia and North Carnlina [abstr.]: in Virginia Academy of Science; Fifty-  ninth annual meeting (Anonymous), Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 32, No. 3, p. 101, 1981.  Cusselman, Mieke E.; Patrick, W. H., Jr.; and DeLmme, R.D. Nitrogen fixation in a Gulf Coast salt  marsh: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 51-56, 1 tables, 1981.  Chae, Y. M.; and Tabstabi, M.A. Sulfolipid and phospholipid in soils and sewage sludges in Iowa: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 21-25, 7 tables, 1981.  Chaker, Victor. Simplified method for the electrical soil resistivity measurement:  in Underground  corrosion (Escalante, Edward, editor), ASTM Special Technical Publication=American Society for  Testing and Materials Special Technical Publication, No. 741, p. 61-91, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Chsa, K.Y. Representative sampling for Bulk density in a Vertisol: in Proceedings of the 45th annual  meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 668-669, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Childs, C.W. Field tests for ferrous iron and ferric-organic complexes (on exchange sites or in water-  soluble forms) in soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 175-180, 1 table, 1981.  Clothier, B. E.; sad White, I. Measurement of sorptivity and soil water diffusivity in the field: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 241-245, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.    178    Clothier, B. E.; White, I.; and Hmmilton, G.J. Constant-rate rainfall infiltration; field experiments: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 245-249, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  ' Coventry, R. J.; and Robinson, P.J. Colour groups derived from numerical classification of the Munsell  soil colour chips: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 103-112, illus., 1981.  Cox, Malcolm E. An approach to problems of a geothermal mercury survey, Puna, Hawaii:  in  Geothermal energy; the international success story (Edmiston, R. C., chairperson), Transactions -  Geothermal Resources Council, Vol. 5, p. 67-70, illus. (incl. geol. sketch maps), 1981.  Geothermal  Resources Counci~ 1981 annual meeting.  CoOer, E. J. B. The textile profile forms of New Zealand soils: Australian Journal of Soil Research,  Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 97-102, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Datta, B.; and Siagh, O.P. Comparative study of moisture release behaviour of soils, soil clays and pure  clays: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 79-82, illus. (incl. I table), 1981.  Day, Michael J. Limestone hardness and tropical karst terrain types: in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 327-329 (incl. German sum.), 2 tables, 1981.  De Jong, R.; and Shaykewich, C. F. A soil water budget model with a nearly impermeable layer:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 361-371 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 3 tables),  1981.  Dethier, David P.; and Bethel, John. Surficial deposits along the Cowlitz River near Toledo, Lewis  County, Washington: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 81-1043, 11 p.,  geomorphol, map 1:62,500, 1981. arailablefrom:U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib.  Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  DeWitt, Thomas A. Soil survey of Cerro Gordo County, Iowa: 214 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps  h l 5,840; colored soils map h190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. Stn.; Iowa State Univ., Coop. Ext. Serv.;  Iowa, Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Douglas, Walter W. Soil survey of Cass County, Indiana: 125 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; soils maps  h l 5,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn. and Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour. Soil Water  Conserv. Comm.).  Dudley, L. M.; Wagenet, R. J.; and Jurlaalk, J.J. Description of soil chemistry during transient solute  transport: Water Resources Research, Vol. 17, No. 5, p. 1498-1504, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Dnnin, F. X.; and Aston, A. R. Spatial variability in the water balance of an experimental catchment:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, VoL 19, No. 2, p. 113-120, 4 tables, 1981.  Ellwood, Brooks B. Weathering effects on the magnetic properties of the MiUedgeville Granite,  Georgia: Earth Planet. Sci. Lett., Vol. 55, No. 2, p. 311-316, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Elprtnco, Adel M.; and Sposite, Garrison. Thermodynamic derivation of eqnations of the Langmuir type  for ion equilibria in soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 277-282, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Evangelou, Vasllins Petrns. Chemical and mineralogical composition and behavior of the Mancos Shale  as a diffuse source of salts in the upper Colorado River basin: 210 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of California,  Davis, CA. am/lable from: Univ. Microfilms.  Fabre, Gnnhem. Specific dissolution in the Mediterranean karstic areas of France: in Proceedings of  the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International  Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 192-195 (incl. French sum.), 1 table, sketch maps, 1981.  Faltondjiev, L. P. On the determination of total heavy metal content in saline soils and soils rich in  organic matter: Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis, Vol. 12, No. 9, p. 949-957, 2 tables,  1981.  Farmer, Denver L. Soil survey of Steuben County, Indiana: 163 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; soils maps  h20,000; colored soils map h 126,720), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Purdue Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.; Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour., Soil Water  Conserv. Comm.).    179    Farmer, J. G,; and Gibson, M.J. Direct determination of cadmium, chromium, copper and lead in  siliceous standard reference materials from a fluoboric acid matrix by graphite furnace atomic absorption  spectrometry: Atomic Spectroscopy, Vol. 2, No. 6, p. 176-178, 3 tables, 1981.  Federoff, N.; and Aurousseau, P. Micromorphologie de sols bruns acides sur materiaux granitiques  [Micromorphology of acid brown soils on granitic materials]: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61,  No. 3, p. 483-495 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Feigenbanm, S.; Edelstein, R.; and Shalaberg, I. Release rate of potassium and structural cations from  micas to ion exchangers in dilute solutions: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  3, p. 501-506, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Fenner, F. Microbiological pollution of groundwater: in Proceedings of the Groundwater pollution  conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et aL), Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No.  1, p. 333-355, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Feofilova, A. P.; Tsekhovskii, Yu. G.; and Gradnsov, B.P. Early Cenozoic subtropical soils in the Oornyi  Altai: Lithology and Mineral Resources (USSR), Vol. 16, No. 1, p. 10-24, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981  [1981].  Fielder, Richard T.; Crader, Kenneth J.; Simon, Marcella, A.; et aL Soil survey of Lonoke and Prairie  counties, Arkansas: 122 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U.  S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Arkansas  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Fielder, Richard T.; Crader, Kenneth J.; Simon, MarceIla A.; et al. Soil survey of Lonoke and Prairie  counties, Arkansas: 122 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; soils maps h20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U.  S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (PubL in coop. with Arkansas  Agric. Exp. Stn.).  FoIlett, Roy H.; Murphy, Larry S.; and Donahue, Roy L. Fertilizers and soil amendments: 532 p., illus.  (incl. 163 tables, sketch maps), Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, N J, United States, 1981.  Foster, R. C. Polysaccharides in soil fabrics: Science, Vol. 214, No. 4521, p. 665-667, illus., 1981.  Foster, R. C.; and Martin, J. IL In situ analysis of soil components of biological origin:  in Soil  biochemistry (Paul, E. A., editor; et aL), VoL 5, p. 75-104, illus. (incl. 4 tables), Marcel Dekker, New  York, NY, United States, 1981.  Freebairn, D. M.; and Boughton, W. C. Surface runoff experiments on the eastern Darling Downs:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 133-146, illus. (incl. 10 tables), 1981.  Frenkel, R. E.; Eilers, H. P.; and Jefferson, C.A. Oregon coastal salt marsh upper limits and tidal  datums: Estuaries, Vol. 4, No. 3, p. 198-204, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Gajem, Y. M.; Win-rich, A. W.; and Myers, D.E. Spatial dependence of physical properties of a typic  torrifiuvent soil: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 709-715, illus. (incl. 3  tables), 1981.  Cams, Ivan.  Comparative research of limestone solution by means of standard tablets (Second  preliminary report of the Commission of Karat Denudation, ISU):  in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 273-275 (incl. German sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Gardner, L. R.; Kheoruem-omne, I.; and Chen, H. S. Geochemistry and mineralogy of an unusual  diabase saprolite near Columbia, South Carolina: Clays and Clay Minerals, Vol. 29, No. 3, p. 184-190  (incl. Russian, German, French sum.), illus. (incl. 18 anals., 1 table), 1981.  Ghosh, Igun*l~ and Schnitzer, M. Fluorescence excitation spectra and viscosity behavior of a fulvic acid  and its copper and iron complexes: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 25-  29, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  GiiIman, G.P. Effects of pH and ionic strength on the cation exchange capacity of soils with variable  charge: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 93-96, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.    180    Gottesfeld, A. S.; Swanson, F. J.; and Gottesfeld, L. M. Johnson. A Pleistocene low-elevation subalpine  forest in the western Cascades, Oregon: Northwest Science, Vol. 55, No. 3, p. 157-167, 1 table, sect.,  sketch map, 1981.  Graustein, William Chandler. The effects of forest vegetation on solute acquisition and chemical  weathering; a study of the Tesuque watersheds near Santa Fe, New Mexico: 671 p., Doctoral, 1981, Yale  Univ., New Haven, CT. available from: Univ. Microf'flms.  Grlmm~ Eric Christopher. An ecological and paleoecologica] study of the vegetation in the Big Woods  region of Minnesota: 379 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN. available front"  Univ. Microfilms.  Groenevelt, P. H.; and Kay, B. D. On pressure distribution and effective stress in unsaturated softs:  Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 431-443 (incl. French sum.), illus., 1981.  Gross, Edward R. Forest-soil site relationship for the forests of southeast and southcentral Alaska  [abstr.]: in Life sciences in the service of Alaska (Bligh, J., chairperson), Proceedings - Alaska Science  Conference, No. 32, p. 138, 1981.  Grove, J. H.; Sumner, M. E.; and Syers, J. K. Effect of lime on exchangeable magnesium in variable  surface charge softs:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 497-500, illus.  (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  H. Xichou; Z. yunmlng; F. Deyi; et aL The chemical structure of ecological environment in the Changbai  Mountain Nature Reserve [abstr.]: in Life sciences in the service of Alaska (Bligh, J., chairperson),  Proceedings - Alaska Science Conference, No. 32, p. 63, 1981.  H. Xichon; Z. Yunming; F. Deyi; et aL The chemical structure of vegetative ecological environment on  northern slope of Changbai Shun Mountains [abstr.]: in Life sciences in the service of Alaska (Bligh,  J., chairperson), Proceedings - Alaska Science Conference, No. 32, p. 64, 1981.  Habic, Peter. Dinaric karst poljes and neotectonics [abstr.]: in Proceedings of the Eighth international  congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress of Speleology,  No. 8, p. 797 (incl. English, French sum.), 1981.  Haines, Sharon G.; and Cleveland, Glenn.  Seasonal variation in properties of five forest soils in  Southwest Georgia:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 139-143, illus.  (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Hall, William G.; Jackson, Bedford W.; and Love, Theodore R. Soft survey of Monroe County,  Tennessee: 107 p., illus. (incl. 7 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Tenn. Agric.  Exp. Stn.).  Hanna, A. M.  Bearing capacity of footings on layered C-~ soils: Journal of the Geotechnical  Engineering Division, Vol. 107, No. GT11, p. 1586-1587, 1981.  Hassett, John J.; Banwart, W. L.; Wood, S. G.; et aL Sorption of a-Naphthol; implications concerning  the limits of hydrophobic sorption: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 38-  42, 3 tables, 1981.  HuvarkRmp, R.; and Vuuclin, M. A comparative study of three forms of the Richard equation used for  predicting one-dimensional infiltration in unsaturated soft: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting,  Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 1-6, p. 13-20, illus., 1981.  Huvlin, J. L.; and Soitanpour, P. N. Evaluation of NH4HCO3-DTPA soil test for iron and zinc: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 70-75, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Heatwole, Harold; Levins, Rickard; and Byer, Michael D. Biogeography of the Puerto Rican bank:  Atoll Research Bulletin, No. 251, 14 p., illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch maps), 1981.  Hegemmm, David Alan. Algal availability of soft phosphorus: 229 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of  Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA. available front" Univ. Microfilms.    181    Hemym'i, Parlchehr;, and Nofziger, D.L. Super slurper effects on crust strength, water retention, and  water infiltration of soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 799-801, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Higuhi, T.; and Jackson, M. L. HalJoysite and kaolinite cesium chloride-urea intercalation facilitated  by a trace of water at elevated temperature: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No.  1-6, p. 815-818, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Hoiford, I. C. R.; and Patrick, W. H., Jr. Effects of duration of anaerobiosis and reoxidation on  phosphate sorption characteristics of an acid soil: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 1,  p. 69-78, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Holzer, Donald B. Soil survey of Lebanon County, Pennsylvania: 155 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils  maps h20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agsic., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep. Environ. Resour. State  Conserv. Comm.).  Horowitz, Aharon; Gerald, Rex E.; and Chal~etz, Michael S.  Preliminary paleoeuvironmental  implications of pollen analyzed from archaic, formative, and historic sites near El Paso, Texas: The Texas  Journal of Science, Vol. 33, No. 1, p. 61-71, 1 table, sketch map, 1981,  Howard, Richard F.; Singer, Michael J.; and Frantz, Gregory A. Effects of soil properties, water  content, and compactive effort on the compaction of selected California forest and range soils:  in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 231-236, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Howes, Brian L.; Howarth, Robert W.; Teal, John M.; et aL Oxidation-reduction potentials in a salt  marsh; spatial patterns and interactions with primary production: Limnology and Oceanography, Vol.  26, No. 2, p. 350-368, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Hrom~dkA; T. V., II; Guymon, G. L.; and Pardoen, G.C. Nodal domain integration model of unsaturated  two-dimensionalsoil-water flow; development: Water Resources Research, Vol. 17, No. 5,p. 1425-1430,  illus., 1981.  Hnsock, Bernard. A statistical probability method for soil resistivity determination: in Underground  corrosion (Escalante, Edward, editor), ASTM Special Technical Publication=American Society for  Testing and Materials Special Technical Publication, No. 741, p. 53-60, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Hutton, J. T.; and Dixon, J. C. The chemistry and mineralogy of some South Australian calcretes and  associated soft carbonates and their dolomitisation: Journal of the Geological Society of Australia, Vol.  28, No. 1, p. 71-79, illus. (incl. 2 anals., 1 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Ibrahim, Ismail K. Use of thermodynamic data to evaluate iron availability from different iron materials  in calcareous soils: 191 p., Doctoral, 1981, Kansas State Univ., Manhattan, KS. amilablefrom: Univ.  Microfilms.  Idike, lVrsmcis Igboji. Modeling the effects of conservation practices on soil moisture: 192 p., Doctoral,  1981, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN. arailable from" Univ. Microfilms.  Indorante, S. J.; and Jansen, I.J. Soil variability on surface-mined and undisturbed land in southern  Illinois: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 3, p. 564-568, 4 tables, 1981.  Iverson, Louis Robert. The role of pioneering species on the reclamation of North Dakota surface mined  lands:  218 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of North Dakota, Grand Forks, ND. amilable from: Univ.  Microfilms.  Iyengar, S. S.; Martens, D. C.; and Miller, W.P. Distribution and plant availability of soil zinc fractions:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 735-739, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  James, Julia M. The relationship between the availability of organic carbon and cavern development  in the phreatic zone: in Proceedings of the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F.,  editor), Proceedings of the International Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 237-240 (incl. French sum.),  illus., 1981.    182    Jefferis, S.A. Soil-bentonite slurry trench cutoffs; discussion: Journal of the Geotechnical Engineering  Division, Vol. 107, No. GT11, p. 1581-1583, illus., 1981.  Jeunlngs, J. N. Further results form limestone tablet experiments at Cooleman Plain: Australian  Geographical Studies, VoL 19, No. 2, p. 224-227, 1 table, 1981.  Johnson, Thomas M.; Cartwright, Keros; and Schuller, Rudolph M. Monitoring of leachate migration  in the unsaturated zone in the vicinity of sanitary landfills: Ground Water Monitoring Review, Vol. 1,  No. 3, p. 55-63, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Jones, R. C. X-ray diffraction line profile analysis vs. phosphorus sorption by 11 Puerto Rican soils: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Col. 45, No. 1-6, p. 818-825, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Juncal, Russell W.; and Bell, Elaine J. Solid-sample geochemistry study of western Dixie Valley,  Churchill County, Nevada; Part II, Soil:  in Geothermal energy; t~e international success story  (Edmiston, R. C., chairperson), Transactions - Geothermal Resources Council, Vol. 5, p. 51-54, sketch  maps, 1981.  Geothermal Resources Council, 1981 annual meeting.  Karamanos, R. E.; Voroney, R. P.; and Rennie, D.A. Variation in natural N- 15 abundance of central  Saskatchewan soils:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 826-828, 3 tables,  sketch map, 1981.  Kansel, Eduardo; and Roesset, Jose Manuel. Stiffness matrices for layered soils: Bulletin of the  Seismological Society of America, Vol. 71, No. 6, p. 1743-1761, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Kearney, Michael Sean. Late Quaternary vegetational and environmental history of Jasper National  Park, Alberta: Doctoral, 1981, Univ. ofWesternOntario, London, ON, Canada. arailablefrom:National  Library of Canada, Ottawa, ON.  Kelly, J. M. Carbon flux to surface mineral soil after nitrogen and phosphorus fertilization:  in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 669-670, 1 table, 1981.  Kelly, William E.; and Gularte, Ronald C. Erosion resistance of cohesive soils: Journal of the  Hydraulics Division, Vol. 107, No. HYI0, p. 1211-, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Kempe, Stephan.  Dissolution experiments with facets [abstr.]:  in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 647 (incl. English, German sum.), 1981.  Keren, R.; and Gast, R. G. Effects of wetting and drying, and of exchangeable cations, on boron  adsorption and release by montmorillonite: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  3, p. 478-482, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Keren, R.; Gast, R. G.; and Bar-Yosef, B. pH-dependent boron adsorption by Na-montmorillonite: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 45-48, illus., 1981.  Keren, R.; and Slminberg, I. Effect of dissolution rate on the efficiency of industrial and mined gypsum  in improving infiltration of a sodic soil: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 103-  107, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Kesler, Stephen E.; Russell, N.; Seaward, M.; etaL Geology and geochemistry of sulfide mineralization  underlying the Pueblo Viejo gold-silver oxide deposit, Dominican Republic: Economic Geology and the  Bulletin of the Society of Economic Geologists, Vol. 76, No. 5, p. 1096-1117, illus. (incl. 23 anals., 8  tables, sects., geol. sketch maps), 1981.  Kinnell, P. I.A. Rainfall intensity-kinetic energy relationships for soil loss prediction: in Proceedings  of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 153-155, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Kieijn, Willem Bastlaan. The physical chemistry of clays and oxides: 174 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ.  of California, Riverside, CA. available from: Univ. Microfilms.    183    Knight, W. G.; and Skujins, J. ATP concentration and soil respiration at reduced water potentials in  arid soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 657-660, illus., 1981.  Kohl, Daniel H.; Bryn, Barbara A.; Shearer, Georgia; et al. Concerning the heterogeneity of the natural  abundance of 15N in soil nitrogen: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. I-6, p. 450-  452, 1 table, 1981.  Kopp|, A.J. A soil toposequence on Bunya Phylilte in Brisbane: Australian Journal of Soil Research,  Vol. 19, No. l, p. I-II, illus. (incl. 4 anals., 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Kosa, Attila. Desert gypsum karst in Bit al Ghanam, Libya: in Proceedings of the Eighth international  congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress of Speleology,  No. 8, p. 154-155, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1981,  Lanyoa, L. E.; and Hall, G. It. Application of autocorrelation analysis to transect data from a drainage  basin in eastern Ohio: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 368-373, illus.  (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Lavardiere, M. R.; De Igimge, C. R.; and D'Avignon, A. Caracteristiques mineralogiques et chimiques  de quelques sols sableux du Quebec en regard de leur evolution pedologique [Mineralogical and chemical  characteristics of some sandy soils of Quebec and their genesis]: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol.  61, No. 2, p. 273-283 (incl. English sum.), 1 anal., 3 tables, sketch map, 1981.  I.x,~mey, Adelle J.; and Morris, Saltlaa. The Bella Coola River estuary, status of environmental  knowledge to 1981: Special Estuary Series, No. 10, 266 p., illus. (incl. 2 anals., tables, geol. sketch map),  1981.  Leppanen, O. E. Evapotranspiration from forage grass replacing native vegetation in the Gila River  valley of Arizona: Open-File Report (United States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 81-1018, 43 p., 1981.  amilablefrom:U. S. Geol. Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Letey, J.; Valorss, N.; lcht, D. D.; et aL Nitrous oxide production and reduction during denitrification  as affected by redox potential:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 727-  730, illus., 1981.  Levy, Rachel. Effect of dissolution of aluminosilicates and carbonates on ionic activity products of  calcium carbonate in soil extracts: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 250-  255, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  Lewis, D. C.; Clarke, A. L.; and Hall, W.B. Factors affecting the retention of phosphorus applied as  superphosphate to the sandy soils in southeastern South Australia: Australian Journal of Soil Research,  Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 16%174, 1981.  Llchhardt, William C  The basic cation saturation ratio concept and lime and potassium  recommendations on Delaware's coastal plain soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil  Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 3, p. 544-549, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1981.  Lietzke, D. A.; and Weber, R.S. The importance of Cr horizons in soil classification and interpretations:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 593-599, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Lietzke, D. A.; and Whiteside, E. P. Characterization and classification of some Belize soils:  in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 378-385, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Ltm.~ C, H.; J~?Jksoo, M. L.; and Hipshi, T. Intercalation of soil clays with dimethysulfoxide:  in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 433-436, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Lin, Feng-C'nilL Dissolution kinetics of some phyllosilicate minerals: 155 p., Doctoral, 1981, State  Univ. of New York, Buffalo, Amherst, NY. amilablefrom: Univ. Microfilms.    184    Lin Jnnshu; Zhang Yaoguang; Wang Yam-a; et aL An analysis on the palaeographic elements of karst  development in the Wumin Basin, Guangxi, southern China [abstr.]:  in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 738, illus., 1981.  Liverovsimya, I. T. K izucheniyu pochv zapadnogo otrezka BAMa [Soils of the western edge of the  Baikal-Amur Railroad]: Zhizn' Zemli, No. 16, p. 86-92, 2 tables, 1981.  Lowther, A. C. Soil survey of Nolan County, Texas: 138 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps 1:24,000;  colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States,  1981. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Land, L J.; Betty, E. E.; Page, A. L.; et aL Occurrence of naturally high cadmium levels in soils and  its accumulation by vegetation: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 10, No. 4, p. 551-555, 8 tables,  sketch map, 1981.  Luxmoore, R.J. Micro-, meso-, and macroporosity of soil: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting,  Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 3, p. 671-672, 1981.  Laxmoore, R. J.; Spalding, B. P.; and Munro, I. M. Areal variation and chemical modification of  weathered shale infiltration characteristics: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  1-6, p. 687-691, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Lyons, B. J.; Skerry, G. P.; and Parker, C. D. Influence of microbiological transformations on  groundwater quality: in Proceedings of the Groundwater pollution conference CLawrence, C. R., editor;  et aL), Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No. 1, p. 356-373, 1981.  MacKay, D. C.; and Carcfoot, J. M.  Control of water content in laboratory determination of  mineralizable nitrogen in soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p, 444-  446, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Mahaney, W. C.; Fahey, B. D.; and Lloyd, D.T. Late Quaternary glacial deposits, soils, and chronology,  Hell Roaring Valley, Mount Adams, Cascade Range, Washington: Arctic and Alpine Research, Vol. 13,  No. 3, p. 339-356, illus. (incl. 4 tables, geol. sketch maps), 1981.  Matlick, $. S., III; and Shiraki, M. Evaluation of the mercury soil mapping geothermal exploration  technique:  in Geothermal energy; the international success story (Edmiston, R. C., chairperson),  Transactions - Geothermal Resources Council, Vol. 5, p. 95-98, sketch maps, 1981. GeothermalResources  Counci~ 1981 annual meeting.  Maxwell, Harold B. Soil survey of Cassia County, Idaho, western part: 150 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables;  soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Consvrv. Sere., Washington,  DC, United States, U. S. Bur. Land Manage., Washington, DC, United States, 1981.  McBride, M. B.; Tyler, L. D.; and Horde, D. A. Cadmium adsorption by soils and uptake by plants  as affected by soil chemical properties: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 739-  744, illus. (incl. 4 tables), 1981.  McFarland, E. R.; and Sherwood, W. C. Geochemistry of an unusual carbonate-rich soil in Rockingham  County, Virginia [abstr.]: in Virginia Academy of Science; Fifty-ninth annual meeting (Anonymous),  Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 32, No. 3, p. 128, 1981.  McGill, W. B.; and Cole, C.V. Comparative aspects of cycling of organic C, N, S and P through soil  organic matter: Gcoderma, Vol. 26, No. 4, p. 267-286, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  MeKeazie, 11. M. The surface charge on manganese dioxides: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol.  19, No. 1, p. 41-50, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  MeSweeney, K.; Jansen, I. J.; and Dancer, W.S. Subsurface horizon blending; an alternative strategy  to B horizon replacement for the construction of post-mined soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual  meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 794-799, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Means, Jeffrey Lysm. Geochemical controls on trace metal transport in aqueous environmental systems:  260 p., Doctoral, 1981, Princeton Univ., Princeton, NJ. available from." Univ. Microfilms.    185    Meq Xian-xL The alpine tundra soil on the Changbai Mountain of China [abstr.]: in Life sciences in  the service of Alaska (Bligh, J., chairperson), Proceedings - Alaska Science Conference, No. 32, p. 62-  63, 1981.  Merkel, Edward J. Soil survey of Blair County, Pennsylvania: 190 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps  1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Pa. State Univ., Coll. Agric.; Pa. Dep. Environ. Resour., State Conserv.  Comm.).  Mermnt, A. R.; and St. Araand, IL J. A micromorphological study of calcareous soil horizons in  Saskatchewan soils: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 243-260 (incl. French sum.),  illus. (incl. 1 anal., 2 tables), 1981.  Mermnt, A. R.; and St. Araaad, R. J. A study of microcrystalline pedogenic carbonates using  submicroscopic techniques: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 261-272 (incl. French  sum.), illus. (incl. I anal., 1 table, 5 plates), 1981.  Met-mat, A. R.; and St. Arnand, R.J. Microband fabric in seasonally frozen soils: in Proceedings of  the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 578-586, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Meznmm; U.; and Kerea, R. Boron adsorption by soils using a phenomenological adsorption equation:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 722-726, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Miles, R. ,/4 and Frmzmeler, D.P. A fithochroneaequence of soils formed in dune sand: in Proceedings  of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science  Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 362-367, illus. (incl. 2 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Miller, William Paul. Sequential extraction of Cu from soil components and Cu-amended soils: 171  p., Doctoral, 1981, Virginia Polytech. Inst. and State Univ., Blacksburg, VA. available fmr~" Univ.  Microfilms.  Mohsenisaravt, Mohsen. Forecasting subsurface water flow and storage on forested slopes using a finite  element model: 176 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Idaho, Moscow, ID. amilablefmm: Univ. Microfdms.  Moneym*ker, Rector H. Soil survey of Anderson County, Tennessee: 165 p., illus. (incl. 16 tables; soils  maps 1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1981. (Pubi. in coop. with Tenn. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Meore, Barbara E.; S~lik, B. P.; and Sorber, Charles A. Viral transport to ground water at a wastewater  land application site: Journal - Water Pollution Control Federation, Vol. 53, No. 10, p. 1492-1502, 9  tables, sketch map, 1981.  Moore, Joe D. Soil survey of Palo Pinto County, Texas:  150 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps  1:24,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Morimwa, Marie; and Moatz, BurrelL Some environmental problems in the Binghamton area:  in  Guidebook for field trips in South-central New York (Enos, Paul, editor), p. 231-249, illus. (incl. 6 tables,  sketch maps), N.Y. State Geol. Assoc., NY, United States, 1981.  Mulmimeed, Altmad Salek Soil property relationships on selected landscape segments under cultivated  vs. rangeland conditions: 190 p., Doctoral, 1981, Colorado State Univ., Fort Collins, CO. amilablefrom:  Univ. Microfilms.  Murali, V.; and Aylmore, L. A.G. A convective-dispersive-adsorptive flow model for solute transport  in soils; I, Model description and some simulations: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No.  1, p. 23-39, illus., 1981.  Nadler, A. Field application of the four-electrode technique for determinin$ soil solution conductivity:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 30-34, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Newman; P.; mad Mm'luk P.  Removal of heavy metals by Perth sands:  in Proceedings of the  Groundwater pollution conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et aL), Australian Water Resources Council  Conference Series, No. 1, p. 267-287, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1981.    186    Nikitia, E.D. Pochvoobrazovaniye v sredney tayge Russkoy ravniny [Soft formation in the central taiga  of the Russian Plain]: Zhizn' Zemli, No. 16, p. 80-85, 1981.  Nikitin, Ye. D. Metodicbeskiye aspekty izucheniya zonarnosti pochv i nekotorykh drugikh prirodnykh  ob"yektov [Methods for studying the zoning of soils and certain other natural features]: Zhizn' Zemli,  No. 16, p. 135-140, 1981.  Nixon, Roy Arthur, III. Rates and mechanisms of chemical weathering in an organic environment at  Panola Mountain, Georgia: 182 p., Doctoral, 1981, Emory Univ., Atlanta, GA. available from: Univ.  Microfftms.  Norman, R. J.; and Stueki, J.W. The determination of nitrate and nitrite in soft extracts by ultraviolet  spectrophotometry:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 347-353, illus.  (incl. 8 tables), 1981.  Novak, M.; and l~im~ T. C. Resonant column technique for dynamic testing of cohesive softs: Canadian  Geotechnicai Journal=Revue Canadienne de Geotechnique, Vol. 18, No. 3, p. 448-455 (incl. French  sum.), illus., 1981.  Nulsen,R.A. Critical depth to saline groundwater in non-irrigated situations: AustralianJournaiofSoil  Research, Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 83-86, illus., 1981.  Nulsen, R.A. Salt-affected land in the Shire of Wongan-Ballidu, Western Australia: Australian Journal  of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 1, p. 87-91, 2 tables, sketch maps, 1981.  Oelmann, Douglas B. Soft survey of Marshall County, Iowa: 206 p., illus. (incl. 18 tables; softs maps  1:15,840; colored soils map h190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Iowa State Univ., Iowa Agric. Home Econ. Exp. Stn., Coop. Exten.  Serv.; State Iowa, Dep. Soil Conserv.).  Olson, Gerald W. Archaeology; lessons on future soil use: Journal of Soft and Water Conservation, Vol.  36, No. 5, p. 261-264, illus., 1981.  Owe, Manfi, ed. The distribution of heavy metals and petroleum residues in the soft from urban surface  runoff:  193 p., Doctoral, 1981, State Univ. of New York, College of Environmental Science and  Forestry, Syracuse, NY. available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Pal, D.; and Broadbent, F.E. Leaching of calcium and magnesium from soft columns as affected by  form of nitrogen in applied sewage: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 56-  60, illus. (incl. 8 tables), 1981.  Palmer, Arthur N. Hydrochemical factors in the origin of limestone caves: in Proceedings oftbe Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 120-122 (incl. French sum.), illus., 1981.  Puredes, J. R.; and Baol, S.W. Soils in an aridic, ustic, udic, climosequence in the Maracaibo Lake basin,  Venezuela: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 385-391, 4 tables, sketch maps,  1981.  Parker, W. F.; Carbon, B. A.; and Grubb, W. B. Coliform bacteria in sandy soils beneath septic tank  sites in Perth, Western Australia: in Proceedings of the Groundwater pollution conference (Lawrence,  C. R., editor; et aL), Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No. 1, p. 402-412, 4 tables,  1981.  Patrick, W. H., Jr.; and Henderson, R.E. A method for controlling redox potential in packed soft cores:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 35-38, illus., 1981.  Paul, E. A.; and Ladd, J. N. (editors). Soil biochemistry:  in the collection Books in soils and the  environment, Vol. 5, 471 p., illus. (incl. tables), Marcel Dekker, New York, NY, United States, 1981.  Paulk, Herschel L. Soil survey of Richmond County, Georgia: 128 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; softs maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Ga., Coll. Agric., Agric. Exp. Stn.).    187    Pechorkin, I. A.; Pechorkin, A. I.; and Bolotov, G. B. Jointing as an index of sulphate massif  karstification: in Proceedings of the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor),  Proceedings of the International Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 181-182, 1981.  Penven, M. J.; Fedoroff, N.; and Robert, M. Alteration meteorique des biotites en Algerie [Weathering  of biotites in Algeria]: Geoderma, Vol. 26, No. 4, p. 287-309 (incl. English sum.), illus. (incl. 2 tables,  geol. sketch map), 1981.  Perrott, K. W. Effects of pH and aluminosilicate composition on K-Mg exchange selectivity of  amorphous aluminosiilcates: Geoderma, Vol. 26, No. 4, p. 311-322, illus. (incl. 11 anals., 4 tables), 1981.  Perrous, K. M.; Smiles, D. E.; and White, I. Water movement in uniform soils during constant-flux  infiltration: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 237-240, illus., 1981.  Pettry, D. E.; Brent, F. V.; Nash, V. E.; et al. Properties of Natraqualfs in the Upper Coastal Plain of  Mississippi:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B.  A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 587-593, 4 tables, sketch map,  1981.  Pleysier, J. L.; and Juo, A. S.R. Leaching of fertilizer ions in a Ultisol from the high rainfall tropics;  leaching through undisturbed soil columns: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  1-6, p. 754-760, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Prasad, S. Surya; and Motto, Harry L. Evaluation of P as a limiting macronutrient in volcanic ash soils  of Guatemala: Communications in SoilScience and Plant Analysis, VoL 12, No. 10, p. 1021-1029, illus.  (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Pye, Keueth; and Switsur, V. Roy. Radiocarbon dates from the Cape Bedford and Cape Flattery  dunefields, North Queensland: Search (Sydney), Vol. 12, No. 7, p. 225-226, 1 table, sketch map, 1981.  Raloff, Janet. Bigfoot or big feet7: Science News (Washington), Vol. 120, No. 11, p. 172-173, 1981.  Ransom, M. D.; Phillips, W. W.; and Rutledge, E. M. Suitability for septic tank filter fields and  taxonomic composition of three soil mapping units in Arkansas: in Proceedings of the 45th annual  meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America  Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 357-361, 2 tables, 1981.  RapparHe, Donald F. Soil survey of Oswego County, New York: 173 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:62,500), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (PubL in coop. with Cornell Univ. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Rapparlie, Donald F. Soil survey of Oswego County, New York: 173 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps  1:15,840; colored soils map 1:62,500), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Cornell Univ., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Rashid-Noah, Augustine Bundu. Designing subsurface drainage systems to avoid excessive drainage of  sands: Doctoral, 1981, McGillUniv.,Montreal, PQ, Canada. available from: Nafional Library of Canada.  Reeder, Jean Dolan. Nitrogen transformations in revegetated coal spoils:  85 p., Doctoral, 1981,  Colorado State Univ., Fort Collins, CO. amilable from: Univ. Microfilms.  Reicosky, D. C.; Voorbees, W. B.; and Radke, J. K. Unsaturated water flow through a simulated wheel  track: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 3-8, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Rengur, M. (reviewer); Richard, Felix; Luescber, Peter;, et al. Physikalische Eigenschaften yon Boeden  der Schweiz [Physical properties of soils in Switzerland]: Geoderma, VoL 26, No. 4, p. 331, 1981.  Rhoades, J. D. Predicting bulk soil electrical conductivity versus saturation paste extract electrical  conductivity calibrations from soil properties: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  1-6, p. 42-44, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Rhoudes, J. D.; and Corwin, D. L. Determining soil electrical conductivity-depth relations using an  inductive electromagnetic soil conductivity meter:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil  Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 1-6, p. 255-260, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.    188    Rhoton, F. E.; Bighsm, J. M.; Norton, L. D.; et al. Contribution of magnetite to oxalate-extractable iron  in soils and sediments from the Maumee River basin of Ohio: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting,  Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 3, p. 645-649, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Riggs, Charles 0. Utilization of field borehole data for pile design and installation: in Associated Pile  and Fitting Corporation's Geopile 81 conference (Hunt, H. W., editor), p. 43-60, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  Assoc. Pile Fitting Corp., Clifton, NJ, United States, 1981.  Rimsalte, J. Petrochemical and mineralogical evolution of radioactive rocks in the Baie-Johan-Beetz  area, Quebec; a preliminary report: in Current research, Part A, Paper - Geological Survey of Canada,  No. 81-1A, p. 115-131, illus. (incl. 29 anals., 2 tables, geol. sketch map), 1981.  Roberge, Jean. La genese des formes du karst de la Hante-Saumons; Facteurs determinants [Genesis  of karst forms in the Upper Salmon River; determining factors]:  in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 391-392 (incl. English sum.), block diag., 1981.  Roflinoli, Rino J.; and Fletcher, Peter C. Soil survey of Bristol County, Massachusetts, southern part:  124 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Mass. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Rogers, Bruce W. Soil pipe caves in the Death Valley region, California: in Proceedings of the Eighth  international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of the International Congress  of Speleology, No. 8, p. 547-548, 1981.  Roloff, G.; Bradford, J. M.; and Scrivner, C. L. Gully development in the deep loess hills region of  central Missouri: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 119-123, illus. (incl. sects.,  3 tables), 1981.  Rosales, AnibalMarciaL. A methodology for quantifying pedogenesis: 262 p., Doctoral, 1981,Cornell  Univ., Ithaca, NY. amilablefrom: Univ. Microfilms.  Ross, James C.; Johnson, Albert S.; and Avers, Peter E. Soil survey of Laurel and Rockcastle counties,  Kentucky: 95 p., illus. (incl. 9 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:190,080), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Ky. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Rule, Joseph H.; and Mathews, Terri Manfredi. Characteristics of some soils of the Dismal Swamp  [abstr.]: in Virginia Academy of Science; Fifty-ninth annual meeting (Anonymous), Virginia Journal of  Science, Vol. 32, No. 3, p. 128, 1981.  Russo, David; and Bresler, Eshel. Effect of field variability in soil hydraulic properties on solutions of  unsaturated water and salt flows: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of  America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 675-  681, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Russo, David; and Bresler, Eshel. Soil hydraulic properties as stochastic processes; I, An analysis of  field spatial variability: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 682-687, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Ssada, Adel S.; and Townsend, F.C. State of the art; laboratory strength testing of soils: in Laboratory  shear strength of soil (Tong, R. N., editor; et at), ASTM Special Technical Publication=American  Society for Testing and Materials Special Technical Publication, No. 740, p. 7-77, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1981.  Sabry, M. A.; Reed, Lester W.; and Parcher, J. V. Mineralogy of compacted clay-lime mixtures: in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 144-150, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Saggar, Surinder Kumar. Studies of sulfur in relationship to carbon and nitrogen in soil organic matter:  Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, SK, Canada. amilable frotm National Library of  Canada, Ottawa, ON.  Selmitzer, M.; Lowe, L. E.; Dormaar, J. F.; et aL A procedure for the characterization of soil organic  matter: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 3, p. 517-519 (incl. French sum.), 1 table, 1981.    189    Sehrale, G.; and Magarey, A.A. Determining criteria for land treatment of wastewater from a cheese  factory near Mount Gambler, South Australia; a case study: inProceedingsoftheGroundwaterpollution  conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et al.), Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No.  I, p. 437-454, illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Schultz, Loren D. Soil survey of McPherson County, South Dakota: 204 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils  maps 1:20,000; colored soils map 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC,  United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with S.D. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Schalze, D.G. Identification of soft iron oxide minerals by differentiaI X-ray diffraction: inProceedings  of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science  Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. I-6, p. 437-440, illus. (incl. I tables), 1981.  Schwarz, David E.; and Ellefsen, Richard E. Field site selection: in Field study for remote sensing; an  instructor's manual (Wake, William H., editor; et al), NASA Conference Publication, No. 2155, p. 29-  33, sketch map, 1981. Landsat C educator's/user's workshop.  Senkayi, A. L.; Dixon, J. B.; and Hoasner, L. R. Transformation of chlorite to smectite through regularly  interstratified intermediates: in Proceedings of the 4 5th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of Amcrica  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 650-656, illus.  (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Severson, R.C. Evaluating chemical character of soft material for suitability in rehabilitating mined land  in the San Juan Basin, New Mexico: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 396-  404, illus. (incl. 3 tables, sketch maps), 1981.  Shainberg, I.; Rhoades, J. D.; and Prather, R. J. Effect of low electrolyte concentration on clay  dispersion and hydraulic conductivity of a sodic soil: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil  Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol.  45, No. 1-6, p. 273-277, illus., 1981.  Shainberg, I.; Rhoades, J. D.; Suarez, D. L.; et al. Effect of mineral weathering on clay dispersion and  hydraulic conductivity of sodic softs: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 287-  291, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Sharpley, A. N.; Ahnja, L R.; Yamamoto, M.; et aL The kinetics of phosphorus desorption from soil:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 493-496, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Sheppard, M. I.; Kay, B. D.; and Loch, J. P. G. The coupled transport of water and heat in freezing  softs; a field study: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, VoL 61, No. 2, p. 417-429 (incl. French sum.),  illus., 1981.  Sheta, Tarek H.; Gobran, George R.; Dufey, Joseph E.; et al. Sodium-calcium exchange in Nile Delta  soils; single values for Vauselow and Gaines-Thomas selectivity coefficients: in Proceedings of the 45th  annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 749-753, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Short, S. K.; Mode, W. M.; Baker, S. A.; et aL Vegetation and modern pollen transects from central  Alaska to the Arctic Ocean [abstr.]: in Life sciences in the service of Alaska (Bligh, J., chairperson),  Proceedings - Alaska Science Conference, No. 32, p. 40, 1981.  Sldhu, P. S.; Gilkes, R. J.; and Posnar, A.M. Oxidation and ejection of nickel and zinc from natural  and synthetic magnetites: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 3, p. 641-644, illus.,  1981.  Siegel, Donald Ira. Hydrogeochemistry and kinetics of silicate weathering in a gabbroic watershed;  Filson Creek, northeastern Minnesota: 289 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN.  available from: Univ. Microfilms.  Slngler, Charles R.; and Plcard, M. Dane. Paleosols in the Oligocvne of Northwest Nebraska:  Contributions to Geology, Vol. 20, No. 1, p. 57-68, illus. (incl. 5 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Sisson, J. B.; and Wlerenga, P.J. Spatial variability of steady-state infiltration rates as a stochastic  process: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 699-704, illus. (incl. 1 table),  1981.    190    Smeck, Neff E.; Rltchie, A.; Wi]dlna~ L. P.; et aL Clay accumulation in sola of poorly drained soils of  western Ohio: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B.  A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 95-102, illus. (incl. 8 tables,  sketch map), 1981.  Smiles, D. E.; Perroux, K. M.; Zegelin, S. J.; et aL Hydrodynamic dispersion during constant rate  absorption of water by soil: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 453-458, illus.  (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Smiles, D. E.; and Philllp, J.R. Salt transport during absorption of water of soil: in Proceedings of the  Groundwater pollution conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et al.), Australian Water Resources Council  Conference Series, No. 1, p. 71-80, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Smith, C. A. S.; Coen, G. M.; and Pluth, D.J. Podzolic soils with Luvisolic-like morphologies in the  upper subalpine subzone of the Canadian Rockies; I, Stratigraphy and mineralogy: Canadian Journal of  Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 325-335 (incl. French sum.)~ 4 tables, sketch map, 1981.  Smith, C. A. S.; Coen, G. M.; and Pluth, D.J. Podzolic soils with Luvisolic-like morphologies in the  upper subalpine subzone of the Canadian Rockies; 2, Genesis: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol.  61, No. 2, p. 337-350 (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 4 tables, 1 plate), 1981.  Smith, William I.; Nichols, Paul, Jr.; Walton, Lloyd B.; et aL Soil survey of Hancock County,  Mississippi: 103 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps 1:20,000; colored soils maps h190,080), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Miss. Agric. For.  Exp. Stn.).  Snarski, R. R.; Fehrenbacher, J. B.; and Jansen, I.J. Physical and chemical characteristics of pre-mine  soils and post-mine soil mixtures in Illinois: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  1-6, p. 806-812, 5 tables, 1981.  Sollins, P.; and MeCorison, F.M. Nitrogen and carbon solution chemistry of an old growth coniferous  forest watershed before and after cutting: Water Resources Research, Vol. 17, No. 5, p. 1409-1417, illus.  (incl. 4 tables, sketch map), 1981.  Sondheim, M. W.; Singleton, G. A.; and Lavkulich, L. M. Numerical analysis of a chronosequence,  including the development of a chronofunction: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  3, p. 558-563, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Spear, Ray William. The history of high-elevation vegetation in the White Mountains of New  Hampshire:  257 p., Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN. available frorfL' Univ.  Microfilms.  Sposito, Garrison. The operational definition of the zero point of charge in soils: in Proceedings of the  45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Voi. 45, No. 1-6, p. 292-297, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Sposito, Garrison; Holtzelaw, K. M.; and LeVesque.Madore, C. S. Trace metal complexation by fulvic  acid extracted from sewage sludge; I, Determination of stability constants and linear correlation analysis:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president),  Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 465-468, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Stewart, B. A. (president). Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America:  Nov. 29-Dec. 4, 1981, United States. Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, 155 p.,  1981.  Stewart, James Pirtle, Jr. An experimental investigation into the uplift capacity of drilled shaft  foundations in cohesionless soils: 427 p., Doctoral, 1981, Cornell Univ., Ithaca, NY. availablefron~'Univ.  Microf'flms.  Stockman, Dale D. Soil survey of Lincoln County, Washington: 167 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps  h24,000; colored soils map h380,160), U. S'. Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Wash. State Univ. Agric. Res. Serv.).  Stoddart, D. R.; and Fosberg, F.R. Bird and Denis islands, Seychelles: Atoll Research Bulletin, No.  252, 43 p., illus. (incl. 7 tables, sketch maps), 1981.    191    Stoddart, D. R.; and Fosberg, F.R. Topographic and floristic change, Dry Tortugas, Florida, 1904-1977:  Atoll Research Bulletin, No. 253, 28 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables, sketch maps), 1981.  Stone, Claudia. Mercury soil surveys; a good reconnaissance tool: in Geothermal Direct Heat Program;  Glenwood Springs technical conference proceedings; Volume 1, Papers presented; State Coupled  Geothermal Resource Assessment Program (Ruscetta, Carl A., editor; et aL), p. 90-97, illus. (incl. sketch  maps), 1981. (Rep. No. DOE/ID/12079-39) (Rep. No. ESL-59) arailablefram:Univ. Utah Res. Inst.,  Earth Sci. Lab., Salt Lake City, UT, United States. Geothermal energy exploration and resource assessment  technical conference.  Stout, J. D.; Gob, K. M.; and Rafter, T. A. Chemistry and turnover of naturally occurring resistant  organic compounds in soil: in Soil biochemistry (Paul, E. A., editor; et aL), Vol. 5, p. 1-51, 9 tables,  Marcel Dekker, New York, NY, United States, 1981.  Strong, W. L.; and Limbird, A. A key for classifying soils to the sub-group level of the Canadian system  of soil classification: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 285-294 (incl. French sum.),  10 tables, 1981.  Stueki, J.W. The quantitative assay of minerals for Fe2+ and Fe3+ using 1,10-phenanthroline; II, A  photochemical method: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 3, p. 638-641, 2 tables,  1981.  Stucki, J. W.; and Anderson, W. L. The quantitative assay of minerals for Fe2+ and Fe3+ using 1,10-  Phenanthroline; I, Sources of variability: in proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 633-  637, illus. (incl. 3 tables), 1981.  Sturm, Ralph H. Soil survey of Morgan County, Indiana: 181 p., illus. (incl. 19 tables; softs maps  1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soft Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United  States, 1981. (PubL in coop. with Purdue Univ., Agric. Exp. Stn.; Indiana Dep. Nat. Resour., Soil Water  Conserv. Comm.).  Snarez, Donald L. Relation between pHc and sodium adsorption ratio (SAR) and an alternative method  of estimating SAR soft or drainage waters: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No.  3, p. 469-475, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Suarez, Donald L.; and Frenkel, Haim. Cation release from sodium- and calcium-saturated clay-sized  soil fractions: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B.  A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Voi. 45, No. 1-6, p. 716-721, illus. (incl. 3 tables),  1981.  Swenson, Erie I. Soft survey of Hampshire County, Massachusetts, central part; communities of  Amherst, Easthampton, Granby, Hadley, Hatfield, Northampton, Southampton, South Hadley, and  Williamburg: 172 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; softs maps 1:15,840; colored soils maps 1:190,080), U. S. Dep.  Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (PubL in coop. with Mass. Agric. Exp.  Stn.).  Tahba, Myassar M.; and Yong, Raymond N. Mapping and predicting soil properties; applications:  Journal of the Engineering Mechanics Division, Vol. 107, No. EM5, p. 795-81, illus. (incl. 6 tables, sketch  map), 1981.  Tan, K. H.; and Troth, P. S. Increasing sensitivity of organic matter and nitrogen analysis using soft  separates: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 3, p. 574-577, 6 tables, 1981.  Taylor, G. S.; Hnndal, S. S.; Fausey, N. R.; et aL Backfill alteration effects on pipe drainage of a Clay  soft:  in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soft Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 611-616, illus., 1981.  Taylor, Robert W.; and Woods, Jonathan. Inorganic phosphorus in calcareous rockland soils of the  Bahamas: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 730-734, illus. (incl. 7 tables),  1981.    192    Terry, R. E.; Nelson, D. W.; and Sommers, Lee E. Nitrogen transformation in sewage sludge-amended  soils as affected by soil environmental factors: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science  Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No.  3, p. 506-513, 6 tables, 1981.  Terry, T. A.; Cassel, D. K.; and Wollum, A. G., II. Effects of soil sample size and included root and  wood on bulk density in forested soils: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soft Science Society of America Journal, VoL 45, No. 1-6, p. 135-  138, illus. (incl. sect., 5 tables), 1981.  Thompson, D. R.; Haas, R. H.; and Milford, M.H. Evaluation of Landsat multispectral scanner data  for mapping vegetated soil landscapes: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society  of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 91-  95, illus. (incl. 5 tables), 1981.  Trudgill, S. T.; Pickles, A. M.; and Crabtree, R.W. Solute uptake on a magnesian limestone hillslop  in Proceedings of the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings  of the International Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 351-352 (incl. French sum.), 3 tables, 1981.  Tyler, D. D.; and Thomas, G.W. Chloride movement in undisturbed soil columns: in Proceedings of  the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society  of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 3, p. 459-461, illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  U. S. Department of Agriculture, Soft Conservation Service.  Soil survey laboratory data and  descriptions for some soils of Kansas: Soil Survey Investigations Report, No. 37, 143 p., tables, 1981.  U. S., National Research Council, Commission on Natural Resources, Committee on Soft as a Resource  in Relation to Surface Mining for Coal. Surface mining; soft, coal, and society: 220 p., illus. (incl.  tables), 1981. acailablefrom: Natl. Acad. Press, Washington, DC, United States.  Urbani, France.  Karst development in siliceous rocks, Venezuelan Guiana Shield [abstr.]:  in  Proceedings of the Eighth international congress of speleology (Beck, Barry F., editor), Proceedings of  the International Congress of Speleology, No. 8, p. 548 (incl. English, Spanish sum.), 1981.  Vaisman, I.; Shulhevet, J.; Kipnis, T.; et al. Reducing ground-water pollution from municipal waste-  water irrigation of Rhodes grass grown on sand dunes: Journal of Environmental Quality, Vol. 10, No.  4, p. 434-438, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Vulverde, Mario A.; and Hill, Hal L. Soil survey of Kern County, California, southeastern part: 195  p., illus. (incl. 15 tables; soils maps 1:24,000; colored soils map h380,160), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil  Conserv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif., Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Van Houten, David G.; Childs, Francis D.; Teets, Charles C.; et al. Soil survey of Kanawha County,  West Virginia: 111 p., illus. (incl. 17 tables; soils maps h20,000; colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S.  Dep. Agric., Soil Conserv. Serv., Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with W.Va. Agric.  Exp. Stn.; Kanawha Cty. Comm.).  van Riemsdijk, W. H.; and de Hun, F. A.M. Reaction of orthophosphate with a sandy soil at constant  supersaturation: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart,  B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 261-266, illus. (incl. 3  tables), 1981.  VanVliet, L.J.P.;andWall, G.J. Soil ernsion losses frnm winter runoffin southern Ontario: Canadian  Journal of Soil Science, Vol. 61, No. 2, p. 451-454 (incl. French sum.), 2 tables, 1981.  Varadachari, Chandrika; Ghosh, K.; and Schnitzer, M.  Effect of pH and neutral electrolyte  concentration on free radicals in humic substances; discussion and reply: in Proceedings of the 45th  annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of  America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 830-831, 1981.  Vaughn, Danny M. A preliminary analysis of associations between glaciofluvial deposits and vegetative  types in the Jackson, Wyoming quadrangle using remote sensing techniques: Professional Paper -  Department of Geography and Geology, No. 13, p. 30-35, illus., 1981.  Walker, L. W.; Turner, A. K.; and Vanselow, D. G. Inflow to groundwater from a large cattle feedlot  in Victoria: in Proceedings of the Groundwater pollution conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et aL),  Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No. 1, p. 375-389, illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981.    193    Wang, C.; Kodama, H.; and Miles, N.M. Effect of various pretreatments on X-ray diffraction patterns  of clay fractions of podzolic B horizons: Canadian Journal of Soil Science, VoL 61, No. 2, p. 311-316  (incl. French sum.), illus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Watterson, John R. Reactions of 12 strains of soil bacteria to 15 metals: Opan-File Report (United  States Geological Survey. 1978), No. 81-1082, 14 p., illus. (incl. 2 tables), 1981. availablefrom:U. S. Geol.  Surv., Open-File Serv. Sect., West. Distrib. Branch, Denver, CO, United States.  Watts, Stephen H. Near-coastal and incipient weathering features in the Cape Herschei-Alexandra  Fiord area, Ellesmere Island, District of Franklin: in Current research, Part A, Paper - Geological Survey  of Canada, No. 81-1A, p. 389-394, illus. (incl. sketch map), 1981.  Weseott, Eugene. Helium and mercury in the central Seward Peninsula rift system, Alaska:  in  Geothermal Direct Heat Program; Glenwood Springs technical conference proceedings; Volume 1,  Papers presented; State Coupled Geothermal Resource Assessment Program (Ruscetta, Carl A., editor;  et aL), p. 63-77, illus. (incl. sketch maps), 1981. (Rep. No. DOE/ID/12079-39) (Rep. No. ESL-59)  available from: Univ. Utah Res. Inst., Earth Sci. Lab., Salt Lake City, LIT, United States.  Geothermal  energy exploration and resource assessment technical conference.  Whitaker, Donald P. The economy: in Ethiopia; a country study (Nelson, Harold D., editor; et a,  p. 143-187, illus. (incl. sketch maps), Am. Univ., Foreign Area Stud., Washington, DC, United States,  U. S. Dep. Army, United States, 1981.  Whelan, B. R.; Barrow, N. J.; and Carbon, B, A. Movement of phosphate and nitrogen from septic tank  effluent in sand soils near Perth, Western Australia:  in Proceedings of the Groundwater pollution  conference (Lawrence, C. R., editor; et al.), Australian Water Resources Council Conference Series, No.  1, p. 391-400, illus., 1981.  Wilde, Steven L. Morphological evolution of a coastal dune field [abstr.]: in Proceedings of the 39th  annual meeting of the Oregon Academy of Science (Evett, Jay F., editor), Proceedings of the Oregon  Academy of Science, Vol. 17, p. 19, 1981.  Wilson, A. T. A review of the geochemistry and lake physics of the Antarctic dry areas: in Dry Valley  Drilling Project (McGinnis, Lyle D., editor), Antarctic Research Series, Vol. 33, p. 185-192, 1 table,  1981.  Wilson, L. G. Monitoring in the vadose zone; Part I, Storage changes: Ground Water Monitoring  Review, Vol. 1, No. 3, p. 32-41, iUus. (incl. 1 table), 1981.  Wilson, Malcolm Alan. The climatic and vegetational history of the Post[lacial in central Saskatchewan:  Doctoral, 1981, Univ. of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, SK, Canada. available from: National Library of  Canada, Ottawa, ON.  Wilson, Michael A.; Barton, Peter F.; and Goh, Kuan M. Differences in structure of organic matter  in two soils as demonstrated by 13C cross polarisation nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy with  magic angle spinning: Geodcrma, Vol. 26, No. 4, p. 323-327, illus. (incl. 2 anals., 1 table), 1981.  Wolt, J. D. Sulfate retention by acid sulfate-polluted soils in the Copper Basin area of Tennessee:  in  Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil  Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 283-287, illus, (incl. 2 tables), 1981.  Wood, A. L.; Wilson, J. T.; Cosby, R. L.; et al. Apparatus and procedure for sampling soil profiles for  volatile organic compounds: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America  (Stewart, B. A., president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 442-444, illus.,  1981.  Wyrich, Jim C. Soil survey of Roberts County, Texas: 120 p., illus. (incl. 20 tables; soils maps 1:24,000;  colored soils maps 1:253,440), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soil Consarv. Sere., Washington, DC, United States,  1981. (Publ. in coop. with Tex. Agric. Exp. Stn.).  Yeoh, N. S.; and Oades, J. M. Properties of soils and clays after acid treatment; I, Clay minerals:  Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 147-158, illus. (incl. 6 tables), 1981.  Yeoh, N. S,; and Oades, J.M. Properties of clays and soils after acid treatment; II; Urrbrae fine sandy  loam: Australian Journal of Soil Research, Vol. 19, No. 2, p. 159-166, illus. (incl. 7 tables), 1981.  Yost, R. S.; and Fox, R. L. Partitioning variation in soil chemical properties of some Andepts using soil  taxonomy: in Proceedings of the 45th annual meeting, Soil Science Society of America (Stewart, B. A.,  president), Soil Science Society of America Journal, Vol. 45, No. 1-6, p. 373-377, illus. (incl. 4 tables),  1981.  Zimmerman, Robert P. Soil survey of Imperial County, California, Imperial Valley area: 112 p., illus.  (incl. 14 tables; soils maps h24,000; colored soils map h443,520), U. S. Dep. Agric., Soft Conserv. Dist.,  Washington, DC, United States, 1981. (Publ. in coop. with Univ. Calif. Agric. Exp. Stn. and Imp. Irrig.  Dist.).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               