Geoderma,  26 (1981) 1--12                                                          1  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    FACTORS CONTROLLING STABILITY OF A1-HUMATE    SHIGEMITSU ARAI and KYOICHI KUMADA  Faculty of Agriculture, Nagoya University, Nagoya (Japan)  (Received July 10, 1979; accepted after revision March 24, 1981)    ABSTRACT  Arai, S. and Kumada, K., 1981. Factors controlling stability of Al-humate. Geoderma, 26:  1--12.  Some of the factors controlling Al bumate bonding, a major aspect of organo-mineral  interactions in soils, were studied. The methods used were potentiometric titration and  stability measurement. The samples consisted of 4 humic acids plus 2 polymeric and  several monomeric carboxylic acids as model compounds. Humic acids as well as alginic  and polyacrylic acids were shown to form complexes with AI. The stability of Al humate  complexes was shown to be controlled by polymerization of carboxyl-containing units  and by the arrangement of carboxyl groups in the units. A contribution by salicylate type  units was doubtful.    INTRODUCTION  One of the main aspects of organo-mineral interactions in softs is complex  formation between soil organic matter and metal ions. Many investigations  were devoted ~o the nature of these complexes and it is therefore possible  nowadays to refer to the formation constants of metal complexes with soil  organic matter {Coleman et al., 1956; Himes and Barber, 1957; Gcering and  Hodgson, 1969; Schnitzer and Khan, 1972; Langford and Khan, 1975; Steven-  son, 1976; Rosell et al., 1977; Bresnahan et al., 1978; Takamatsu and Yoshida,  1978, etc.) or to data on the characteristics of this bonding (Schnitzer and  Skinner, 1965; Yariv et al., 1966; Schnitzer and Khan, 1972; Gamble et al.,  1976; Gamble et al., 1977; Senesi et al., 1977; McBride, 1978; Bresnahan et  al., 1978, etc.). More information has also been obtained on the chemical  structure of soil organic matter which is intimately related to complex forma-  tion (Beckwith, 1959; Wood et al., 1961; Wagner and Stevenson, 1965;  Gamble, 1970; Van Dijk, 1971, etc.).  Nevertheless, there are many problems still remaining to be solved. Although  aluminum is universal in softs and is closely related to soil organic matter ac-  ,cumulation {Greenland, 1971), the relationships between aluminum and soil  organic matter have not been fully investigated. This is due to the diversity of  aluminum compounds in soils and to the complexity of soil organic matter.    0016-7061/81/0000--0000/$ 02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    Thus, the purpose of this study was to ascertain the nature of Al-humate  formation, to determine conditional stability constants and to examine the  factors affecting complex formation, such as chemical structure and polymer-  ization. For the study, high and low molecular weight model compounds  and humic acids were used.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    Materials    Four humic acid samples which belong to the A, B, Rp and l) types, accord-  ing to Kumada's classification (Kumada et al., 1967}, were used. These were  Shitara humic acid extracted from a so-called "kuroboku soil" (Umbrept)-A  type, Kuragari sample from an acid brown forest soil (Umbrept)-B type,  Sanage sample from a grey lowland soil (Aquent ?)-Rp type and Tsubame  sample from a buried horizon-P type. These were the same samples as those  covered by the authors in a previous report (Arai and Kumada, 1977). The  humic acids were extracted with 0.1N NaOH, refined by repeated acidifica-  tion and dissolution and stored as dried powders. Prior to determining pH and  stability constants, the samples were redissolved in 0.1N NaOH and refined  through ion exchange resins (IR 120 and IRA 400). The ash contents (dry  weight basis) were as follows: Shitara 3.02%, Kuragari 3.66%, Sanage 0.79%  and Tsubame 2.62%. Polyacrylic acid and alginic acid samples were prepared  from sodium polyacrylate (average degree of polymerization, 3--4 104,  Nakarai Chemicals Ltd.) and alginic acid (Nakarai) after being dissolved in  water and 0.1N NaOH solutions, respectively, and passed through anion and  cation exchangers as was done with the humic acids. Concentrations (N) were  determined conductometrically. The other carboxylic acids were: acetic acid  (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd., JIS special grade), malonic acid (Wako,  Wako special grade), succinic acid (Kanto Chemicals Co., Inc., guaranteed  grade}, glutaric acid (Nakarai, extra pure grade), adipic acid {Wako, JIS special  grade), 1,2,3-propanetricarboxylic acid (Wako, Wako special grade), 1,3,5-  pentanetricarboxylic acid (Nakarai, extra pure grade), benzoic acid (Wako,  JIS special grade) and o-phthalic acid (Tokyo Chemical Industry Co., Ltd.  guaranteed grade). Their concentrations were determined volumetrically.    Potentiometric titration curves    An automatic titrator RAT-11S produced by Hiranuma Sangyo Co., Ltd.  equipped with a reference electrode K-421N and a glass electrode MG-511  produced by Denki Kagaku Keiki Co., Ltd. was used. The pH values were  measured without any supporting electrolyte. The interval of titration was  set at 30 sec but, if equilibrium was not attained during that period, the inter-  val was extended automatically. Calibration was done with use of standard  pH buffers, i.e. K-phthalate (pH 7) and K-oxalate (pH 4), according to Japanese  Industrial Standard (JIS K8802-1958).    TABLE I  Complexation constants of AI with humic and the other acids in 1M NaCIO,  Sample          pKa*~     n.2        log b=p([HA]/[H]);i=o.5.3  pHi- =0.5 a~=0.5*'  TA(equiv./l):Al(mole/l).5  Shitara          4.60       4.44       0.33                         2.91      0.3        1.09810-s:4.56510-4 = 2.4  4.86       5.25       0.34                         2.92     0.3  Kuragari         4.64       2.89       0.27                         2.92      0.2        1.10510-3:4.565x 10-4 = 2.4  4.77       3.24       0.27                        2.92     0.2  Sanage          4.86       2.42       0.27                        2.88     0.1        1.09410-3:4.56510-4 = 2.4  5.35       3.20       0.25                         2.90      0.1  Tsubame        4.89       4.00       0.37                         2.85      0.2        1.09310-3:4.565x 10-4 = 2.4  4.72       4.00       0.36                         2.85     0.2  Alginic acid      2.89       1.18       0.57                         2.80      0.4        1.05510-3:4.56510.4 = 2.3  2.91       1.29       0.53                        2.84     0.5  Poly~crylic acid  4.76       0.90       0.23                        3.15     0.1        0.575x 10-a:3.043x 10-4 = 1.9  4.88       1.02       0.25                         3.14      0.1  log ~,s     log 13.6  Malonic acid     5.0946    2.5673    0.60                        1.67      --         9.87 10-3:7.60810-4 = 13.0  5.1863     2.5849     0.58                         1.77      --  Succinic acid     4.8461     3.9444   --1.65                         3.97      --         9.95 10-3:7.60810-' = 13.1  4.8831     3.9363   --1.64                         3.92      --  Acetic acid      4.5272        --     --1.91                         3.69      --         1.97610-2:1.52110-3 = 13.0  4.5317       --    --1.91                        3.70      --  Note: total volume 30 ml and titrated by 0.1N NaOH(Shitara--polyacrylic acid) or 1N NaOH(malonic--acetic acid).  ,1 and ,2 Constants in modified Henderson--Hasselbach equation, pH = pKa--nlog(1--~)/,~.  ,3 HA; undissociated acid group. ~; average number of acid group boand to metal ion.  "4 ~ ; degree of dissociation.  , s TA; total concentration of acid.  ,6 ~1 and 132; (ionization constant)-l.  50    TABLE II  Complexation constants of AI with several low molecular compounds in 0.1M NaCIO4  ,.  Acid      log ~*~          log ~2*~          log 53*~          log k=PLn=o.~2pH~=o.5 TL(mole/l):Al(mole/l),3  Acetic     4.538              --               --             2.66           3.66      1.99x 10-2:1.52x 10-3 = 13  av. 4.537                                         av. 2.65  acid       4.537              --               --            2.63           3.68  Benzoic    3.972              --               --             2.77           3.22      1.29x 10-2:9.13x 10-4 = 14  av. 3.972                                        av. 2.70  acid       3.972             --               --            2.83           3.11  Malonic    5.018            2.976             --              6.7             1.76     4.9510-3:7.16x 10-4 =  6.4  av. 5.017        av. 2.980                        av. 6.8  acid        5.016            2.983              --             6.8             1.80  Succinic   5.160            3.986              --             3.94           3.91      4.95x 10-3:7.61x 10-4 =  6.4  acid       5.155 av. 5.158  3.984 av. 3.985    _             3.96 av. 3.~5   3.91  0-Phthalic  4.911           2.676              --            4.07           3.17     5.9810-3:9.13x 10-4 = 6.5  av. 4.908        av. 2.672                        av. 4.06  acid      4.906         2.668           --          4.05         3.21  Glutaric   4.977 av. 4.976  4.130 av. 4.131    --             3.85 av. 3.85   3.92     4.9810-3:7.b3 10-4 =  6.5  acid       4.973           4.133             --            3.85           3.92  Adipic     4.982           4.238              --            3.79           3.98     4.9710-3:7.6110-* L  6.5  acid       4.990 av. 4.986  4.233 av. 4.235    _            3.79 av. 3.79   3.98  1,2,3-Pro-  5.744            4.515            3.440            5.09           3.97      3.3010-3:7.6110-4 =  4.3  panetricar- 5.745 av. 5.744  4.515 av. 4.515  3.433 av. 3.437  5.13 av. 5.11   3.96  boxylic acid  4.603            3.750            4.52           4.01      3.2910-3:7.6110-4 = 4.3  1,3,5-Pen- 5.186   5.184         av. 4.605        av. 3.746       av. 4.53  tanetricar- 5.182av"         4.606           3.743           4.53           4.00  boxylic acid  Note. Total volume 30 ml and titrated by 1N NaOH.  ,1 ~1--~3 (ionization constant)-i.  ,2 L = dissociated acid group.  ,3 TL = total concentration of acid.    Conditional stability constants    The potential difference (E, mV) was measured in 1M NaC104 solution  (humic acids etc.) or 0.1M NaClO4 (low molecular weight organic acids). The  value was then converted to the hydrogen ion concentration using a calibra-  tion curve prepared from an HCIO4 standard solution at the same NaC104  level. In these measurements, the KC1 solution of the reference electrode was  replaced by NaC1 solution to avoid interference due to the precipitation of  KC104. The ionic strength of a polymeric acid system, u = 1, was selected  after a preliminary test so that gelation was almost complete without A13  Titration was begun after allowing the mixed solution to stand for 2--3 h. The  NaOH standard solution was added using a microsyringe. Enough time was al-  lowed for equilibrium to be attained and, in most cases, the interval was 0.5--  10 min. Each determination was made in a range of pH (---log [H] ) less than  4 to minimize the effect of the hydrolysis of A1 ions, because the hydrolysis  constant of A1, Q,1, is about 10-s (Baes and Mesmer, 1976). To keep the pH  low, a suitable amount of perchloric acid was added if necessary. The ratio of  ligand to metal (mole or equivalent to mole) was kept as high as possible.  These ratios are shown in Table I and II.    Calculation    Conditional stability constants (b) of high molecular-weight polymeric  acids, including humic acids, and some low molecular-weight acids were deter-  mined with a modification of Bjerrum's method (Gregor et al., 1955) by  m  calculating p([HA]/[H] ) = log ka.le = log b, against n, where [HA] is the con-  centration of the undissociated acid group, ka the dissociation constant, k the  formation constant and n the average number of ligands to the total concentra  tion of metal ions. Constants for low molecular-weight acids were obtained by  Bjerrum's method. In these cases, the formation of mixed complexes, such as  MLpXq, where M is the metal, L the ligand and X hydronium or hydroxyl ion  and p and q are constants, was not taken into consideration for the first ap-  proximation.    RESULTS    The pH titration curves    Fig. 1 shows the pH titration curves of Shitara humic acid, polyacrylic acid,  alginic acid and acetic acid, with and without A1 ions. In these figures, the  dotted lines are hypothetical curves obtained by additions of titration curves  of the organic acids to those of A1 with a correction as described below. It is  shown that the titration curve for an acid HA and a strong base B follows the  equation, t = CB/CHA = (Kw/[H]--[H])/CHA + (1 + [H]KHA)-I, where t is  the degree of neutralization, CB and CHA the cor4centrations of the added    I0                                                 I0    (b)                                                    ..'Ib'"  9                             9   7                                                  7                                6                                             6                        .~'  5                             5  "o  .........  ;  .........  ;, "  o  ......  "o'.,  .........  0'2  ........  'o'3  ,o9          ,o (d 9 /  8'# ~"                             8  ~7                   7  6                .,"                  6  5     ~ + f "ll" " .~                             5  l "    ............  |  .........  !  .....  0                 I                           0                 I                  2  O.INHCI   O.INNaOH                      O.INHCI   0.1N NaOH  ml        ml                             ml        ml    Fig. 1. The potentiometric titration curves of Shitara humic acid (a), polyacrylic acid (b),  alginic acid (c) and acetic acid (d) with and without Al. Total volume 25 ml; o - acid, A =  AI, = acid with Al and + = quasi-theoretical values assuming the simple mixing of acid  and Al.    base and the acid, respectively, Kw the ionic product of water ([H] .[OH] ),  and KHA the dissociation constant of the acid (Tanaka and Nakagawa, 1966).  When two titration curves are added together, the first term in the above  equation will be summed up also so that correction of this term is necessary.  The effect of this correction was almost negligible between pH 4 and 10. In a  mixed solution of acetic and oxalic acids, the curve thus corrected agreed well  with the measured one (not shown in a figure).  The titration curves for humic acid and other acids with AI crossed the  dotted curves at about pH 5, i.e. excess proton was set free in the acidic  range whereas the hydroxyl ion increased more than expected if the hydro-  lysis of the Al ion took place at a pH of more than about 5 (Fig. 1). This  phenomenon seems due to coordination of the ligands of acids with cations  instead of water. The same results were obtained regardless of the type of the  humic acid or the ratio of humic acid to Al. Similar observations were made  by earlier Kawaguchi and Kyuma (1959) and Yoshida and Nakao (1971). The  effect of acetic acid on Al titration was similar to that of humic acid although    the effect of the former was slight (Fig. l(d)). Thus, coordination of the  carboxyl group with the A1 ion appears common to carboxylic acids.  Conditional stability constants (b, or K,)  Modified Bjerrum plots for humic and other acids are shown in Fig. 2 and  m  the values of p([HA]/[H] ) at n = 0.5 are tabulated in Table I. If successive  formation constants are separated far enough, p([HA]/[H] ) at n = 0.5 equals  log b, - log [MA] [H]/[M] [HA] (Gregor et al., 1955). But, as seen in Fig. 2,  the separation was not large enough, although circumstances differed from  sample to sample. Thus, the p([HA]/[H] ) value should be taken as an index  describing the relative tendency of complex formation at a condition of  w  n =0.5.  L~   o            ~                         o                         "~  o  o., E  It     0.6        !                                                                                                     I  ii       "                                    '  I        I                I        I        I        I        I       ..I  -0.2           -0.1                0               0.1              0.2             0.3             0.4             0.5              0.6  Fig. 2. Modified Blerrum plot of AI humates, polyaerylate, alginate, malonate, sueeinate  and acetate.  Conditional ,c~ability measurements are reported to be theoretically incom-  plete for polydisperse systems, because stability can be influenced by experi-  mental conditions such as degree of dissociation, cation concentration etc.  (Gamble et al., 1970; Stevenson, 1976; Saar and Weber, 1979). The effect of  sample concentration was relatively small in Cu2fulvate system (Gamble et  al., 19"/0) or in the solution of low Cd2to fulvic acid ratio (Saar and Weber,  19"/9). In our measurements, as indicated in Table I, the ratio of A1 to humie  or other polymeric acids (ca. 1 mole: 2.4 equiv.) or the degree of dissociation  (~ 0.1--0.3) was low and pH values (&lt; 4) remained within a limited range.  Therefore, the values of conditional stability could be used for relative com-  parison.  For humic acids, the n values in the modified Henderson-Hasselbalch equa-  tion were higher than the ones usually observed, viz. 1--2 (Table I). This may    be due to the fact that different types of acid groups occur together even  though the equation seems applicable within a restricted range of ~ (0.1--0.4).  The values of p([HA]/[H] } at n = 0.5 were slightly greater in Shitara (A type)  and Tsubame (P) than in Kuragari (B) and Sanage (Rp). These results appear  reasonable because the amounts of acid functional groups and strongly dis-  sociating groups in these humic acids are in the order of A&gt;B, P&gt; Rp (Arai  and Kumada, 1977). The degree of dissociation ~ at n = 0.5 differed between  Shitara (0.3) and Tsubame (0.2) ~.nd between Kuragari (0.2) and Sanage  (0.1) (Table I). Consequently, if it were possible to compare them at identical  conditions, the difference among the p([HA]/[H] ) values of various types of  humic acid would become clearer.  The values of p([HA]/[H] ) at n = 0.5 for the humic acids were between  those for alginic and polyacrylic acids, though there remained some uncer-  tainty about the value of polyacrylic acid because the pH at n = 0.5 was so  low that the constants Ka and n in the modified Henderson-Hasselbalch equa-  tion might also include some uncertainty. The values of pC[HAl/[H] ) at  n = 0.5 of humic and other polymeric acids were less than that of malonic  acid and greater than those of acetic and succinic acids.  Bjerrum plots of low molecular weight carboxylic acids are shown in Fig. 3,  and the pL values at n = 0.5 are listed in Table II. The compounds used ranged  from mono- to tri-basic acids. Among polybasic acids, the number of carbon  atoms between two carboxyl groups ranged from 1 to 4. Two aromatic acids,  benzoic and phthalic acids, were also included. The value n = 0.5 was attained  at pH less than 4 in each case. The pL at n = 0.5 would be log k, if the succes-  sive complexations were sufficiently separated and mixed complexes were  absent.  ~_ ~                                                    .o  _         .-  ~           ~_ o =o          ~oo~e     ;~oo:~e                   \  C:].~  0                I               I               I               I               i               I               I               :               I  2.5                   30                  3.0                  4.0                  4.5                   5,0                   5,0                  6.0                   6,5                  7.0  pL  Fig. 3. Bjei~rum plot of AI complex with several low molecular weight carboxylic acids.  The pL value at ~ = 0.5 was greater in polybasic acid than in a monobasic  acid, greater in a tribasic acid than in a dibasic acid and decreased with the in-  crease in the number of carbon atoms between two functional groups. The  decrease in pL value was large between malonic acid and succinic acid but was  slight among succinic, glutaric and adipic acids (Table II). The tendencies ob-    served among acetate, malonate, succinate etc were similar to those observed  for Zn, Pb and Cu complexes (Yasuda et al., 1960).    DISCUSSION    The effect of the hydrolysis of A1 ion will be considered first. The hydro-  lysis constant Q,1 = [MOH]/[M] is about 10-s, so the formation constant of  hydroxide KMOn -=[MOH]/[M] [OH] - QI~/Kw amounts to 109. This value  is far greater than the stability of Al acetate, about 103, which was calculated  ignoring hydrolysis. Thus it may be possible for a mixed complex with hy-  droxyl groups to occur even though the concentration of acetate ion, ca. 10-3  mole/l was far greater than that of hydroxyl, ca. 10-'in the system. The  hydrolysis, however, did not appear to affect the determination of pH nor the  concentration of the dissociated ligand. On the other hand, there is a pos-  sibility that some mixed complexes with protons may occur in the acidic  systems described in the preceding section. On these premises, the stability  of the A1 complex will be discussed by comparing the values of pL or p-  {[HA]/[H] ) at n = 0.5 with each other.  The examination of potentiometric titration curves suggests that the car-  boxyl group can be coordinated with the A1 ion regardless of its dissociation  constant {Fig. 1). Moreover, the stability of an A1 complex with a low molec-  ular-weight acid was shown to increase with decreasing distance between two  adjacent carboxylic groups in a molecule or with increasing basicity {Table II).  According to these results, complex formation of A1 with a polymeric car-  boxylic acid of high molecular weight can be ascribed partly to the inherent  ability of carboxyl group to bind A1 and partly to intensified binding caused  by certain arrangements of ligands or by the increased basicity in the polymer.  The bonding between A1 and carboxyl may not be a primary bond but an  electrostatic bond because the A1 ion is a typical "hard" acid {Pearson, 1963).  Recent studies, however, have indicated various types of bonding in metal  complexes with humic substances. Ferric ions {"hard" acids) could form com-  plexes of inner spheric character {Gamble et al., 1976; Senesi et al., 1977).  Yariv et al. {1966) suggested a water bridge combining organic molecules  with exchangeable cations on montmorillonite. This mechanism was sup-  ported by (3amble et al. (1977) for an Mn2-fulvate complex, where the wa-  ter of hydration was kept unexchanged with the ligand (Gamble et al., 1976).  Mn2+--humate was also shown to be an outer sphere complex (McBride,  1978). Mn2ion is of a "borderline" nature between "hard" and "soft" acids.  The cupric ion (a "borderline" acid) was considered to form a covalent com-  plex (Gamble et al., 1976) or electrostatic and partly covalent complex with  humic substances (McBride, 1978).  Concerning the additional electrostatic field effect or polymeric effect,  Gamble {1973) concluded that Naand Kions are held by these forces in  the fulvate system. Gregor et al. (1955) analysed the complex formation of  Cu2with various carboxylic acids ranging from acetic to polyacrylic acids    10    and they explained polymeric effects as due to the stabilization of 8-mem-  bered chelates by the powerful field effects of the polyelectrolyte chains.  Similarly, some contribution of electrostatic field effects to the stabilization  of A1 complexes seems probable, because the stability of A1 complexes  tended to increase in the compounds having easily disssociating ligands, e.g.  alginic acid&gt;humic acids&gt;polyacrylic acids, or malonic acids&gt;other low  molecular weight acids (Tables I and II).  In the acid mediums used in this experiment, the reacting functional group  might be easily dissociated (Type I according to Gamble, 1970, or S cluster  of Arai and Kumada, 1977), whereas weakly acidic groups might react only  with difficulty. Among the former are the ortho-carboxy-phenol(salicylate)  and ortho&lt;licarboxylate(phthalate) units.  The salicylate unit in humic substances presumed by Beckwith (1959), Van  Dijk (1971) and Gamble et al. (1970) to react with metal cations. In our ex-  periments, however, the participation of salicylate as well as a ma!onate type  of unit in the Al--humate complexation was not confirmed because the  stability of Al--humate was lower than that of Al--malonate (Fig. 2). On the  other hand, the stability of the latter (Table II) was much lower than that of  Al--salicylate (log K = 14, Babko and Rychkova, 1948). This discrepancy is  considered to be partly due to differences among the samples used, because  the humic acids examined here contained phenolic OH, ca. 1 mequiv./g, and  carboxyl groups, 4--6 mequiv./g, whereas Gamble et al. (1970) used fulvic  acid with 3.3 mequiv./g of phenolic OH and 7.7 mequiv./g of carboxyl groups  (Schnitzer and Desjardins, 1962; Gamble, 1970).  Wood et al. (1961} and Wagner and Stevenson (1965) reported that a fairly  large share of the carboxyl groups in humic acids (about 1/3 to almost all}  were mutually adjacent (phthalate type) or in a position to form cyclic an-  hydrides which were possibly 5--7 membered rings. In our experiments, the  stability of Al--humate was higher than that of Al--phthalate (Table II). A1-  theugh the stability of Al--humate may seem too high to be explained using  the phthalate type model of Wood et al. {1961), this is not necessarily incon-  sistent with that model because the stability could be increased by polymer-  izatic.n.  Recently Bloom and McBride (1979} indicated that chelation mechanisms  or sites such as those of the catechol and salicylate types, differing greatly in  acid strength, need not function in adsorption of metal ions by acid-washed  peats. Their conclusion is the same as ours, as far as the universal ability of  carboxx lic acids to form metal'complexes is concerned. In fulvic and humic  acids, however, acid groups differing in degree of dissociation do exist. These  acid groups are not considered to be uniform in their capacity to form metal  complexes, as described in the foregoing sections. The stabilities of A1 com-  plexes, log K,, were high in the complexes from compounds of low first dis-  sociation constants, pK,'s (Table II), and high molecular-weight polymeric  carboxylic acids having acid groups of strong dissociation tended to form  stable A1 complexes (p.8, Table I). Therefore, acid sites of different struc-    11    tures or dissociations could contribute in different ways to the formation of  A1 complexes, at least in fulvic and humic acids.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    We are indebted to Dr. N. Nakasuka for several helpful discussions and to  Mr. Stephen Duah-Yentumi for reading through the English manuscript and  wish to thank Mrs. Iwatsuki for technical assistance. The research was sup-  ported in part by a "Grant-in-Aid" from the Ministry for Education Japan,  on soil organic matter {subject No. 347096).    REFERENCES    Arai, S. and Kumada, K., 1977. An interpretation of the conductometric titration curve  of humic acid. Geoderma, 19: 21--35.  Babko, H. and Rychkova, T.N., 1949. Salicylate complex of aluminum. Zhur. Obschei  Khim., (J. Gen. Chem.), 18: 1617--1725. C.A., 43: 2536d (1949).  Baes, C.F. Jr. and Mesmer, R.E., 1976. The Hydrolysis of Cations. Wiley, New York,  N.Y., pp. 112--123.  Beckwith, R.S., 1959. Titration curves of soil organic matter. Nature, 184 : 745.  Bloom, P.R. and McBride, M.B., 1979. Metal ion binding and exchange with hydrogen  ions in acid washed peat. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 43: 687--692.  Bresnahan, W.T., Grant, C.L. and Weber, J.H., 1978. Stability constants for the com-  plexation of copper(II) ions with water and soil fulvic acids measured by an ion selec-  tive electrode. Anal. Chem., 50: 1675--1679.  Coleman, N.T., McClung, A.C. and Moore, D.P., 1956. Formation constants for Cu(II)-  peat complexes. Science, 123: 330--331.  Gamble, D.S., 1970. Titration curves of fulvic acid: the analytical chemistry of a weak  acid polyelectrolyte. Can. J. Chem., 48: 2662--2669.  Gamble, D.S., 1973. Naand K+ binding by fulvic acid. Can. J. Chem., 51: 3217--3222.  Gamble, D.S., Schnitzer, M. and Hoffman, I., 1970. Cu:fulvic acid chelation equilibrium  in 0.1 M KCI at 25.0. Can. J. Chem., 48: 3197--3204.  Gamble, D.S., Langford, C.H. and Tong, J.P.K., 1976. The structure and equilibria of a  manganese(II) complex of fulvic acid studied by ion exchange and nuclear resonance.  Can. J. Chem., 54: 1239--1245.  Gamble, D.S., Schmitzer, M. and Skinner, D.S., 1977. MnII--fulvic acid complexing equi-  librium measurements by electron spin resonance spectroscopy. Can. J. Soil Sci., 57:  47--53.  Geering, H.R. and Hodgeson, J.F., 1969. Micronutrient cation complexes in soil solution,  III. Characterization of soil solutior ligands and their complexes with Zn~* and Cu~*.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 33: 54--59.  Greenland, D.J., 1971. Interactions between humic and fulvic acids and clays. Soil Sci.,  111 : 34--41.  Gregor, H.P., Luttinger, L.B. and Loebl, E.M., 1955. Metal--polyelectrolyte complexes, I.  The polyacrylic acid---copper complex. J. Phys. Chem., 59: 34--39.  Himes, F.L. and Barber, S.A., 1957. Chelating ability of soil organic matter. Soil Sci. Soc.  Am. Proc., 21: 363--373.  Kawaguchi, K. and Kyuma, K., 1959. On the complex formation between soil humus and  polyvalent cations. Soil Plant Food, 5: 54---63.    12    Kumada, K., Sato, O., Ohsumi, Y. and Ohta, S., 1967. Humus composition of mountain  soils in central Japan with special reference to the distribution of P type humic acid.  Soil Sci. Plant Nutr., 13: 151--158.  Langford, C.H. and Khan, T.R., 1975. Kinetics and equilibrium of binding of Fe3by a  fulvic acid: a study by stopped flow methods. Can. J. Chem., 53: 2979--2984.  McBride, M.B., 1978. Transition metal bonding in h~,mic acid: an ESR study. Soil Sci.,  126: 200--209.  Pearson, R.G., 1963. Hard and soft acids and bases. J. Am. Chem. Soc., 85: 3533--3539.  Rosell, R.A., Miglierina, A.M. and De Novilla, L.Q., 1977. Stability constants of some com-  plexes of Argentine humic acids and micronutrients. Soil O~ganic Matter Studies, II:  15--21.  Saar, R.A. and Weber, J.H., 1979. Complexation of cadmium(II) with water- and soil-  derived fulvic acids: effect of pH and fulvic acid concentration. Can. J. Chem., 57 :  1263-1268.  Schnitzer, M. and Desjardins, J.G., 1962. Molec,:lar and equivalent weights of the organic  matter of a podzol. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 26: 362--365.  Schnitzer, M. and Skinner, S.I.M., 1965. Organo-metallic interactions in soils, 4. Carboxyl  and hydroxyl groups in organic matter and metal retention. Soil Sci., 99: 278--284.  Schnitzer, M. and Khan, S.U., 1972. Humic substances in the Environment. Dekker,  New York, N.Y., pp. 203--251.  Senesi, N., Griffith, S.M. and Schnitzer, M., 1977. Binding of Fe3by humic materials.  Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 41: 969--976.  Stevenson, F.J., 1976. Stability constants of Cu~ Pb~ and Cd~complexes with humic  acids. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 40: 665--672.  Takamatsu, T. and Yoshida, T., 1978. Determination of stability constants of metal--  humic acid complexes by potentiometric titration and ion-selective electrodes. Soil Sci.,  125 : 377--386.  Tanaka, M. and Nakagawa, M, 1966. San-enki heiko to chuwa tekitei (acid-base equi-  librium and neutralization analysis). In: M. Kotake et al. (Editors), Jikken Kagaku Koza  (experimental chemistry). Maruzen, Tokyo, II-7, pp. 1--14 (in Japanese).  Van Dijk, H., 1971. Cation binding of humic acids. Geoderma, 5: 53--67.  Wagner, G.H. and Stevenson, F.J., 1965. Structural arrangement of functional groups in  soil humic acids as revealec by infrared analysis. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29: 43--48.  Wood, J.C., Moschopedis, S.E. and Den Hertog, W., 1961. Studies in humic acid chemistry.  II. Humic anhydrides. Fuel, 40: 491--502.  Yariv, S., Russel, J.D. and Farmer, V.C., 1966. Infrared study of the adsorption of benzoic  acid and nitrobenzene in montmorillonite. Israel J. Chem., 4: 201--213.  Yasuda, M., Yamasaki, K. and Ohtaki, H., 1960. Stability of complexes of several carboxyl-  ic acids formed with bivalent metals. Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn., 33: 1067--1070.  Yoshida, M. and Nakao, Y., 1971. Behavior of aluminum--humic acid complexes as revealed  by titration curves. J. Sci. Soil Manure, Jpn., 42 : 333--337 (in Japanese with English  abstract).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractSome of the factors controlling Al humate bonding, a major aspect of organo-mineral interactions in soils, were studied. The methods used were potentiometric titration and stability measurement. The samples consisted of 4 humic acids plus 2 polymeric and several monomeric carboxylic acids as model compounds. Humic acids as well as alginic complexes was shown to be controlled by polymerization of carboxyl-containing units and by the arrangement of carboxyl groups in the units. A contribution by salicyclate type units was doubtful.