Geoderma, 30 (1983) 179--186                                                    179  Elsevier Science Publishers B V, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    SEM AND LIGHT MICROSCOPIC OBSERVATIONS OF MINERALS IN  BOG-ORES OF THE BELGIAN CAMPINE*    G. STOOPS  Laboratory for Mineralogy, Petrography and Micropedology, Kr~jgslaan 281, 9000-Gent  (Belgmm)  (Accepted for publication February 17, 1983)    ABSTRACT    Stoops, G., 1983. SEM and hght mmroscopic observations of minerals in bog-ores of the  Belgian Campine. Geoderma, 30: 179--186.    Soft bog-ore deposits are frequently present in alluvial sods of the Nete Valley, Pro-  vince of Antwerp, Belgium. A profile was studmd consisting of four layers of whmh the  upper three were analyzed with the light microscope and SEM (scanning electron mmro-  scope). The top layer consmted mainly of clay and fragmented diatom shells. Isotropic  Fe-oxihydrates and radiating goethite needles were present in the underlying limonitic  layer Siderite and vlvianite were found in the third layer, the former often present in the  wall of root channels, whereas the latter was frequently found within the channels.  Vivianite was also found associated with decaying roots or alone inside root channels  Pyrite frambolds were also found m the lower part of the profile  The presence, close to each other, of different minerals such as goethlte, pyrite, mder-  lte and vivianite cannot be explained by macroenvironmental mineral eqmlibria alone. It  requires the existence of different mmroenvlronments which can vary in hme and place.  The study of such microenvironments, however, requires additional in mtu microchemmal  submicroscopm techniques    INTRODUCTION    A research project on soft bog-ore deposits of the Belgian Campme is cur-  rently in progress. These deposits are frequently observed in alluwal soils of  the Nete Valley in the Province of Antwerp, Belgium. A typmal profile was  exposed m these deposits and results of preliminary investigations are re-  ported here. The profile had a high groundwater level and all horizons were  oversaturated. Four layers could be distinguished: a greyish, clayey topsoil  of 20 cm thmkness with "rust" coated channels; a 20 cm thick hmonite nch    *Contribution to the research program: "Weathering and neosynthesm in relation to soil  genesis" Fonds voor Kollektief Fundamenteel Onderzoek -- Belgium.  The material presented here was given in part before Division S-5 of the Soil Science So-  ciety of Amerma Meetings, December 3, 1981 in Atlanta, Georgia, U.S A.    0016-7061/83/$03.00  1983 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    180    greyish-yellow layer with orange-yellow mottles; a vlwanlte-nch layer of  30 cm, whmh after oxidation consisted of alternating bluish flecks (viviamte)  and white veins and tubes (siderite); and layered alluvial deposits startmg at  a depth of 70 cm m the profile. The present study gives data on the upper  three layers.    METHODS    Large undisturbed soil blocks were impregnated with polyester resin for  thin  section  preparation  following  drying  by  acetone  replacement  (Fltzpatrmk, 1980). These thin sections were studied with the light micro-  scope. Undisturbed clods, which were not hardened, were investigated with a  binocular microscope, which allowed subsamphng for SEM studms. Samples  for SEM study were mounted with collodion on alummmm stubs, coated  with gold and examined with a Cambndge Stereoscan (Stoops and De Mets,  1970). Mineralogical determinations were confirmed by XRD-analyses, using  a Gandolfi camera.    Results    The clayey surface layer of the bog-ore profile was sampled between 10  and 15 cm depth. It is characterised by a porous microstructure in whmh  rust-coated channels, occasionally containing roots, dominate m the thin sec-  tion. The greyish fine fraction consists mainly of small opaline bodies  (phytoliths and diatoms) and clay. SEM showed that much of the fine frac-  tion comprises fragments of diatoms (Fig. 1).    5~m  Fig. 1. Fragments of diatom shells and clay m the groundmass of the surface horizon  (SEM).    181    The underlying limonitic layer was sampled between 20 and 30 cm. It has  a porous microstructure with many root channels. The sample consists of  alternating greyish and brownish zones. The small greyish zones are similar  to those of the topsoil, whereas the larger brownish zones exhibit dark red-  dish-brown, compact, structureless isotropm domains and yellowish to  brownish bands of goethite.  The browmsh bands consist of weakly birefnngent, length-slow goethite  fibres (first order grey up to yellow) forming a radiating pattern perpendicu-  lar to the walls of voids. Sometimes several layers could be distinguished m  thin sections (Fig. 2). Similar goethite coatings were observed by Eswaran  (1972} in an Ultisol from Nicaragua.    Fig. 2. Fan-like goethite coating on the wall of a pore in the lirnonitic layer. Polarised  light.    SEM of the seemingly structureless isotropic limonitic material did not  reveal structure at higher magnifications, although numerous shrinkage  cracks could be seen (Fig. 3). The radiating goethite fibres could be disting-  uished, however, and are about 1.6 pm thick (Fig. 4). Orientation of the  fibres perpendicular to the wall of pores was also found m the clods (Fig. 5a)  as was layering of the goethite (Fig. 5b). Such surfaces of goethite coatmgs  have the aspect of a micropore filter (Fig. 5c). Apparently individual entitles  of radiating fibrous goethite leave intermittent spaces during growth.  The upper part of the vivianite and siderite containing layer was sampled  between 40 cm and 50 cm and the lower part between 60 cm and 70 cm.  The very heterogeneous upper part has a porous microstructure sometimes  disturbed by shrinkage fissures in zones that are rich in orgamc material.    lOpm  Fig  .q  Amorphous iron oxlhydrates in limomtic layer with shrinkage cracks (SEMI    Fig 4 Goethite needles in fan-hke goethitic coating (SEM)    Most frequently, the groundmass in thin sections consists of a yellowish, 1so-  tropic clay with very few coarse detrltal grains. Siderite spherulites with a  diameter of 20--25 pm occur subcutaneously on the root channels. Their  radial fabric is evidenced by the orthogonal extraction cross seen under  crossed polarizers. Vlviamte is present in the channels as a blue, fine, granu-  lar mass, sometimes mixed with root-residues (Fig. 6).  SEM studies of the soft bog~re did not give clear morphologmal charac-    183    50 um    b    Fig 5. Goethlte coatings on the walls of pores in the limonitic layer: a) coating of radiat-  ing goethite needles, b) layered goethite, and c) topography of the surface of a goethite  coating (SEM).    teristics of the subcutaneous siderite spheruhtes. In a sample of hard bog-ore  from the same area optically comparable, but cutaneous siderite deposits  were observed. These grmns seem to be composed of a parallel growth of  rhombohedral crystals (Fig. 7). The fine grained vivianite of the soft bog~)re  was observed as irregular lathlike crystallites (Fig. 8).  The lower part of the vivmnite- and siderite-containing layer is st]ll porous  in thin section, with channels and packing pores. A brownish, isotroplc or-  ganic substance with recognizable cell structures dominated strongly over the  coarse demtal grmns, (quartz and glauconite). Siderite is less frequent than  m the upper part of this layer. Vivianite sometimes occurs as relatively large,    184    Fig 6 Root remnant m soft bog-ore, partly filled with fine granular vivlanite and partly  surrounded by siderite. Polarlsed light_  -I    :i  I    lSOurn                                 ;l  b . -                            b  Fig, 7. Siderite' a) siderite spheres covering the wall of a pore m a hard bog-ore, b) detail  of the central sphere (SEM).    200  m long, lathlike crystals on organic matter. It forms frequently radiat-  ing aggregates but is found in most cases as mffllings of fissures and channels,  surrounded by siderite spherulites. In some places pyrite framboids were ob-  served between siderite spherulites.    CONCLUSIONS    A sequence of a number of minerals was observed m a soft bog-ore in the  Nete Valley, Province of Antwerp, Belgium. Field studies established four    185    Fig. 8. Anhedral and elongated granular vivianlte in a root channel; a) and b) (SEM).  layers, vlz. a clayey surface layer, a hmomtic layer, a layer containing vivian-  ite and siderite, and layered alluvlal deposlts below a depth of 70 cm.  Light mmroscopy allowed the identlflcation of phytoliths and diatoms m  the clayey layer. Both goethite fibres and structureless isotropic domains  with Iron oxihydrates were present in the reddish-brown zone of the limon-  Itm layer. Siderite and viviamte were dlstinguished m the third layer. Vivlan-  ire was often assoclated wlth orgamc material, whereas siderite occurred sub-  cutaneously to root channels. Pyrite framboids were also recogmsed in this  layer.  SEM observatlons of the same material in unhardened clods of soil helped  to establish the morphology of various minerals at both lower and hlgher  magnifications. In this manner m situ observations made with the hght  microscope in thin sections could be compared with SEM data on loose  materials.  The above data mdmate that goethite, slderite, vivianite and pyrite have  formed m the soft bog-ore. All of these may crystallise near to each other  in the lower part of the profile. Such crystallisatlon cannot be explained by  macroenvironmental mineral equilibria alone. This indicates that various  mlcroenvironments with different conditmns must exlst and have existed  beside each other; even in these profiles wlth a hlgh groundwater table. It  also emphasizes that further m situ studies of these micro-envlronments re-  qulre mmrochemical analyses with a number of submicroscopic techmques  such as described by B1sdom (1981), especlally EMA (electron microprobe  analysis)  and  SEM-WDXRA  (scanning electron  microscopy-wavelength  dlspersive X-ray analyms).    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    Dr. F. De Coninck, Dr. E. Van Ranst and Dr. R. Vochten are thanked for  providing the undisturbed samples. Mr. Bohain of the Laboratory of Elec-    186  tron Microscopy of the State University of Ghent is thanked for his assis-  tance.    REFERENCES    Bisdom, E.B.A., 1981. A review of the application of submicroscopic techniques in soil  micromorphology, II Electron microprobe analyzer (EMA), scanning electron micro-  scope-energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (SEM-EDXRA), laser microprobe mass analyzer  (LAMMA 500), electron spectroscopy for chemmal analysis (ESCA), ion microprobe  mass analyzer (IMMA), and the secondary ion microscope (SIM). In. E.B.A. Bisdom  (Editor), Submicroscopy of Soils and Weathered Rocks. 1st Workshop of the Inter-  national Working-Group on Submicroscopy of Undisturbed Soil Materials (IWGSUSM)  1980, Wageningen. Centre for Agricultural Publishing and Documentation (Pudoc),  Wageningen, pp. 117--162_  Eswaran, H., 1972. Micromorphological indicators of pedogenesis m some tropmal soils  derived from basalts from Nmaragua. Geoderma, 7  15--31_  Fitzpatrick, E.A,, 1980  The Micromorphology of Soils  Department of Soil Science,  University of Aberdeen, 186 pp.  Stoops, G  and De Mets, M, 1970  Scanning elektronenmikroskopie toegepast m de  bodemmlkromorfologie Natuurwet. Ti]dschr_, 52 10--16                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             AbstractSoft bog-ore deposits are frequently present in alluvial soils of the Nete Valley, Province of Antwerp, Belgium. A profile was studied consisting of four layers of which the upper three were analyzed with the light microscope and SEM (scanning electron microscope). The top layer consisted mainly of clay and fragmented diatom shells. Isotropic Fe-oxihydrates and radiating goethite needles were present in the underlying limonitic layer. Siderite and vivianite were found in the third layer, the former often present in the wall of root channels, whereas the latter was frequently found within the channels. Vivianite was also found associated with decaying roots or alone inside root channels. Pyrite framboids were also found in the lower part of the profile.The presence, close to each other, of different minerals such as goethite, pyrite, siderite and vivianite cannot be explained by macroenvironmental mineral equilibria alone. It requires the existence of different microenvironments which can vary in time and place. The study of such microenvironments, however, requires additional in situ microchemical submicroscopic techniques.