 Geoderma, 25 (1981) 275--283  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    275    TIME RESPONSES OF S'~AR BEET GERMINATION, OXYGEN  DIFFUSION AND REDOX POTENTIAL TO CRUST FORMATION,  POLYACRYLAMIDE STABILIZATION AND PEROXIDE FERTILIZATION    F. CALLEBAUT', D. GABRIELS2 and M. DE BOODT'  'Laboratory of Soil Physics, Faculty of Agricultural Sciences, State University, Gheat  (Belgium)  2National Science Research Funds, Brussels (Belgium)  (Received October 15, 1979; accepted July 3, 1980)    ABSTRACT    Callebaut, F., Gabriels, D. and De Boodt, M., 1981. Time responses of sugar beet germin-  ation, oxygen diffusion and redox potential to crust formation, polyacrylamide stabi-  lization.and peroxide fertilization. Geoderma, 25: 275--283.    Oxygen diffusion rates (ODR) and redox potentials at the 1 cm soil depth were  reported for different treatments on soil samples subjected to simulated rainfall in the  laboratory. Soil samples treated with polyacrylamide or CaO~ at a rate of 0.25% or  higher showed highest ODR during each drying period between successive rainfall simu-  lator runs. Sugar beet germination was low on soil samples with low ODR and where  crust formation occurred. Redox potential measurements did not reflect temporary ox-  ygen fluxes in the soil and could be useful only in completely saturated and reduced con-  ditions.    INTRODUCTION    Successful growth of crops starts with favorable conditions for germination  and seedling emergence. Bayer and Farnsworth (1940) earlier suggested from  numerous field obscrvations that "poor aeration resulting from unfavorable  soil structure conditions may be the dominant factor in the declining yields  of beets".  Although Phillips and Kirkham (1962) found great differences in air  permeability between compacted and uncompacted soil surfaces, they found  no differences in oxygen content of the soil air. Domby and Khonke (1956)  stated that although infiltration of water or mass flow of gases through the  soil was determined by pore size, the latter seems to have no influence on  the gas diffusion rate; there is seldom a lack of a partial pressure gradient for  gases to diffuse through a soil crust. According to an aeration theory devel-  oped by Van Bavel (1951), the diffusion through a compacted soil surface  layer is mainly affected by the physical properties of the soil layer immedi-  ately under the crust.    0016-7061/81t0000--000015 02.50 1981 Elsevier Seienti.fi-~ Publishing Company    276    Melsted et al. (1949) showed a response in yields of corn and sugar-beets  to peroxide fertilization as an oxygen source. De Vleeschauwer and Gabriels  (1976) found that surface treatment with a polyacrylamide solution could  prevent breakdown and slaking of the soil aggregates in the top layer.  By analogy with the platinum micro-electrode technique for soil aeration  measurements developed by Lemon and Erickson (1952), the present study  aims: (1) to determine the effects of soil crusting by rainfall on oxygen dif-  fusion, redox potential and germination of sugar-beets; and (2) to evaluate  the effects of peroxide fertilization and soil surface stabilization with poly-  acrylamide solution as preventatives of possible soil oxygen deficiency.    APPARATUS AND METHODS    In the present investigation, soil aeration was characterized by the deter-  mination of the oxygen diffusion rate and the redox potential, the latter  providing a measure of the intensity of reduction in oxygen-poor environ-  ments.    Electrodes    A saturated calomel electrode, with a salt bridge of saturated potassium  chloride and ending into a small hollow glass tube filled with agar-agar  saturated with potassium chloride, was used as a reference electrode. Because  of its small surface area the resistance of the reference electrode and the salt  bridge was 3000 ~.  Fou'~ :~:,re platinum micro-electrodes (6 mm long and 0.46 mm in dia-  meter) sealed with a polyester resin {Mann and Stolzy, 1972) were used. The  micro-electrcdes were cleaned by applying a voltage of 4.5 V between a micro-  electrode and a common carbon electrode, for 2 min after immersion in a  0.1N HC1 solution. The electrodes were kept in distilled water in order to  avoid the formation of an irreversible oxide on the surface when exposed to  air. A solution of potassium ferrocyanide ( 3 10-s tool/l) and potassium  ferricyanide (3 10-3 tool/l) in 0.1N KCI was used for the standardization  of the electrodes so that when immersed in this solution the redox potential  should range around 185 mV + 10 mV at 23. A lower potential usually  indicates a breakdown in the polyester resin at the tip of the electrode so  that leakage occurs.    Measurement of redox-potential and oxygen diffusion rate    Successively, the redox-potential and the oxygen reduction current were  recerded. The redox-potential of each platinum-reference electrode system  was registered on a voltmeter with an internal resistance of 100 M~2 so that  the current was low, permitting the electrode to express the potential without  discharge. The oxygen diffusion rates were measured at a potential of    277    - 0.700 V on the electrodes. The circuit was closed and the cu~ent allowed  to flow for 4 min before a reading was taken. The current is proportional to  the electrolytic reduction of oxygen at the platinum cathode (Lemon and  Erickson, 1952; Letey and Stolzy, 1964) and the oxygen flux can be expres-  sed by the equation:  i.m.60  f =           X 10-6 (g crn-2 rain-1)  n.F.A    where i is the current in microamp~res after 4 min, m the molecular weight  of oxygen (32 g/mole), n the number of gram equivalents per mole of oxygen  (= 4), F = Faraday constant = 96,500 C/gequiv, A the surface area of the  e!.ectrode in square centimeters and f the flux of oxygen to the electrode  surface or the ODR (Letey and Stolzy, 1964).    Measurement of soil resistance    The rate of oxygen diffusing to the micro-electrode is inversely propor-  tional to the internal resistance of the circuit. The internal resistance is the  sum of the resistance of the reference calomel electrode (3000 ~ ) and the  soil resistance which varies with soil water, texture, temperature and salt  content.  Immediately after the measurement of the 02 reduction current, measure-  ments were taken of the soil resistance by means of an AC conductivity  bridge between each platinum micro-electrode and a copper rod inserted in  the sample. The conductivity values were used to calculate the actual soil  resistance and with this the effective voltage at the electrode by correcting  for ohmic losses (Kristensen, 1966). All ODR measurement values axe convert~  ed to a standard potential of- 0.700 V.    Measurement of the soil water pressure    The water status of each soil sample was monitored by means of mercury  tensiometers with porous cups and the soil water pressure was measured  together with the redox potential, the ODR and the conductivity readings.    EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURE    The soil samples consisted of sandy loam with mechanical composition:  53.3% sand (&gt; 50 p), 33.5% silt (2 U--50 p), 13.2% clay (&lt; 2 p), 3.35%  organic matter and 0.75% CaCO3.  Plastic containers (16 cm by 35 cm and 11 cm deep) with fritted bottoms  were filled with air-dry soil aggregates (0.5--5.0 mm) to a depth of 9 cm at a  density of 1.2 g/cm3.  Five different treatments were carried out. A first treatment consisted of    278    a .qurlace application with a polyacrylamide solution at a rate of 20 g/m2.  The other treatments consisted of additions of calciumpero~ide at rates of  0.05%, 0.25%, 0.5% and 1.0%, incorporated in the upper 5 cm layer. Each  treatment was replicated twice.  After being wetted by capillary rise until a pressure head of about --4 to  - 6 cm water was obtained, the soil samples were subjected to three succes-  sive simulated rainfalls 4, 7 and 11 days after the wetting. The rainfall was  at a rate of 42 mm/h for a period of 10 rain.  Another similar experiment was carried out in a controlled environment  with sugar-beet seeds (Beta vulgaris L. vat -- saccharifera L) planted at 1 cm  depth, 4 days before the first rain. The room temperature was between 22 and 24 and the relative humidity was 50% + 5%.  Soil water pressures, redox potentials, oxygen diffusion rates and con-  ductivities were measured at 1 cm depth immediately before and 4 h after  each rainfall.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    The oxygen  treatments are    90    8O  Ig:  'E   60   50  o    40  30    diffusion rates (ODR) at the 1 cm depth for the different  reported in Fig. 1 for the bare soil sample and in Fig. 2 for    20    lO    -- Unlreated  --~ PoLyacryl amide    ....  CaO2 0.05%  ~.~ CaO2 0.25%    ........  C~O2 0.50 "1,    ............  CaO2 1.00 "1,    !   ",                 ..  -     '""..          ,""         i  &lt;,,   J  k  i  k    /   IX....-   -\.  "-,,,   i v  ":',,  ,,it./..-"  -.\  I "I  ..     I /7~ V    /\  ~. \      g,' ! ~.,     I   \    o  ,  ~  ~  ~  ~  ~  ~  ~  ~ ~ ;, ,'2 6 ~'~  Time |d~ysl  Fig. 1. Evolution of the oxygen diffusion rate at 1 cm depth in bare sandy loam soil sam-  pies treated with polyacrylamide mulch or peroxide fertilization.    279    100    90    8C    "To  E  '~"   ?C  'E  u  m,   60  0  Q'  50  0  n,,  g  ~  ~0  i5  x  o    -- Untreated  Polyocrylamide    ....  CaO2 0.05%  --.-- Ca02 0.25%    .......  CaO2 0.50%    ............  CoO2  1.00%    20    ;'-.  % ,    ,"      et:  I1  ."     I t"  I  t.         "i~  "  /    t  T  /is                .-"    I          |    I  *  .|  v.            ,'/  -'      .','/  '-:~       ';:.   y /    .-   .-  -  "-  "  V"II  ii  "-----.~,',~'  /    /  V. I   ..  ~ .i~....... /~I I     l~  ': I\11 ~ i  ).,    /  "i    o__.~.~, ~ ~    ~  ....  1    2    3             6   ?        9   10   11   12  13  !l,  Timeldoys )  Fig, 2. Evolution of the oxygen diffusion rate at 1 r:m depth in sandy loam soil samples  treated with polyacrylamide mulch or peroxide fertilization during the germination of  sugar beets.    the cropped soil samples during a 14-day period with three rainfalls (on the  4th, the 7th and the llth day). The values of oxygen diffusion rates are  averages of 8 readings (4 electrodes per duplicate) and are obtained from  measurements of the current and the soil electrical resistance which varied  between 1000 and 2000 ohm as the soil dried out. Immediately after each  rainfall a negative soil water pressvre ranging from --4 to - 6 cm water was  measured at 1 cm depth and at the end of the drying period, in between the  rainfalls, a negative pressure'ranging from --33 to --45 cm water was observed.  Stolzy and Fliihler (1978) and FILihler et al. (1976) stated that average  ODR values, based on the assumption that the observed variables are normal-  ly distributed, do not provide as much information on the aeration status of  a soil as does the frequency distribution of soft aeration measurements.  Because only 8 replicated measurements are not enough to draw a reliable  frequency distribution, the average ODR values are reported here only with  the aim of finding tendencies of the soil aeration status immediately under  the surface crust. Each measurement with the platinum electrode gives an  indication of the aeration status of a micro-site.    280    Figs I and 2 indicate that after each rainfall the oxygen diffusion rate is  low and increases during the drying period. This increase during each drying  period is most pronounced on the samples treated with polyacrylamide or  CaO2 at a rate of 0.25% or higher, i.e. on the samples where the surface  structure remained undisturbed by rainfall. In general the poorest aeration  conditions could be observed on the untreated sample and those treated with  CaO2 at rates of 0.25% and less. Those were the surfaces on which a crust  formed after the first rainfall was applied.  Not only treatment with polyacrylamide but also an application of CaO2  (besides of being an oxygen supplier) at rates of (}.25% or more will stabilize  the surface clods against the impact of raindrops.  In a review of oxygen diffusion studies, Stolzy and Letey (1964) reported  a critical ODR value for root growth of 20 10-s g cm-2 rain-j, whereas  Wiersma and Mortland (1953) found a critical ODR value between 13 and  23 10-8 g cm-2 rain-~ for the growth of sugar beets. Those critical ODR  values were also obtained in our experiment for the untreated soil sample  and the treatment with CaO2 at a rate of 0.05%.  Fig. 3 shows that the germination of sugar beets was low on those plots  with low ODR and where crust formation occurred (control sample and  CaO 0.C5% treatment). It is possible that the low ODR values by them-    100    90    80    7C  o. 6C  z   40  o  c  o   30    20    10  0I  0    ~-~ Untrealed  ---~ Polyacrylamide    ....  CaO2 0.05%    ....  CaO2 0.25"/.  .............  ""  ./"       ,~...~,    .........  CaO2 0.50o    ..'    ............  coo2 loo'/,  j //        fj  /,      /  //'    /  /  ///            /  / J /  /  /    /J  ////  !//)"  '    '    '    '8    "    '    '   1'1   '    '    '  1   2   3   4   5   6   7       9  10      12  13  14  Time {days )    Fig. 3. Germination of sugar beet seeds in sandy loam soil samph;~i treated with polyacryl-  amide mulch or peroxide fertilization.    281    selves are sufficient for the germination but because of the additional crust  formation the need for oxygen is higher for the emergence of plants through  the crust.  Several researchers (Allarup, 1959; Vegis, 1964; Forsberg, 1965) inten-  sively studied the so called "soaking injury", a phenomenon by which seed  germination is reduced or completely inhibited in the presence of excess  water. The longer the soaking period the lower the germination and seedling  vigor. Polyvinylpyrrolidone and H:O2 solutions effectively prevented injury  by holding water absorption to "normal" levels during soaking. Besides its  stabilizing effect, CaO: also attracts excess water to form H202 and hence  water entry into germinating seedlings is prevented. In our soil samples  "soaking injury" could temporarily occur immediately following rainfall.  The results of the redox potential measurements at 1 cm depth for the  bare and cropped samples are illustrated in Figs. 4 and 5. The data presented  are averages of eight readings. Fluctuations in redox potential were observed  during the drying and wetting cycles. Some influence of CaO; occurs at  rates of 0.25% and higher. Treatment with 0.05% CaO2 did not change the  redox potential as compared to the untreated soil samples. A further increase  of CaO2 to 0.5 and 1% levels results in a decrease of the redox potential, this    600    35C    &gt;  E  - 30C  o  I  E_    250    UntreQted  Po|y~rrylomide    ....  CaO20. 05"1.  CaO2 0.25%    .........  CoO2 0.50%  \         coo2 i.oo'/../         \                  /    /',                       I-  \  I                                  /            ;    ,    ',       ..~ ~..~  ',.      /     / / .~,_/'-  ",,   \   //, /..~J ,,  ",,,,,  "~_..---~,.//   ,.    2%  ;  ;  ;  ,  ~  ~  ;  ~  ~  ,'0 ,',  ;2  h ,',  Time |doys }  Fig. 4. Evolution of the redox potential at 1 cm depth in sandy loam soil samples treated  with polyacrylamide mulch or peroxide fertilization.    282    ~,00    -- Untreaied  --~PoLyacry[amide    ....  C O 02 0.05%  --- ~CaO2 0.25%    .........  CaO2 0.50%  3so  ............  caoz 1.oo-~/  \.~~.\  /  /                      \.  _   ~                , ~,   ',  /~.l~   ~I      "-. -.-~-C~.'    J"        '\        I    (;E    2-30    200    ,  1    Time (days]  Fig. 5. Evolution of the redox potential at 1 cm depth in sandy loam soil samples treated  with polyacrylamide mulch or peroxide fertilization during the germination of sugar beets.    decrease being related to the increase of pH. The 0.5% and 1% CaO2 treat-  ments resulted in pH values of 8.1 and 8.5, respectively, whereas the un-  treated samples had pH values of 7.0 -- 7.2.  Grable and Siemer (1968) found good correlations between the redox  potential and the O 2 concentration and between the redox potential and air  porosity in moist soils. Dasberg and Bakker (1970) did not find any consis-  tent relationship, possibly because of the fact that the O: concentrations in  their experiments were not low enough to cause any measurable decrease in  redox potential. Indeed, a study of redox potential changes in 10 soil samples  with gases passing through them at different oxygen concentrations showed  that a change in oxygen concentration from 21% to 4% produced only a  slight reduction in redox potential. A sharp decrease in redox potential oc-  curred below 4% (Turner and Patrick, 1968).  Our experiments showed, however, that redox potential measurements do  not reflect temporary oxygen fluxes in the soil. Redox potential measure-    283  ments appear to be useful only in completely saturated and reduced condi-  tions.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS  The authors gratefully acknowledge the support of the National Science  Research Funds of Belgium.    REFERENCES    Allarup, J., 1959. Respiration in water inhibiting Berley Caryopsys. Physiol. Plantarum,  12: 118--123.  Baver, L.D. and Farnsworth, R.B., 1940. Soil structure effects in the growth of sugar-  beets. SoilL Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 5: 45--48.  Dasberg, J. a~ad Bakker, J.W., 1970. Characterizing soil aeration under changing moisture  condition[~ for bean growth. Agron. J., 62: 689--692.  De Vleeschauwer, D. and Gabriels, D., 1976. The effect of a polyacrylamide treatment  on the germination of sugar-beets in a heavy sandy loam soil. Med. Fak. Landbouw-  wetensch., Rijksuniv. Gent, 41/1.  Domby, C.W. and Khonke, H., 1956. The influence of soil crusts on gaseous diffusion.  Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 20: 1--5.  Fliihler, M., Ardakani, M.S., Szuszkiewicz, T.E. and Stolzy, H., 1976. Field measured  nitrous oxide concentration, redox potentials, oxygen diffusion rates and oxygen  partial pressure in relation to denitrification. Soil Sci., 122: 107.  Forsberg, C., 1965. Sterile germination of o~Sspores of Chara and seeds of Najas marina.  Physiol. Plantarum, 18: 128--137.  Grable, A.R. and Siemer, E.G., 1968. Effect of bulk density, aggregate size and soil  water suction on oxygen diffusion, redox potentials and elongation of corn roots. Soil  Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 32: 180--186.  Kristensen, K.J., 1966. Factors affecting measurement of oxygen diffusion rate (ODR)  with bare platinum micro-electrode. Agron. J., 58: 351--554.  Lemon, E.R. and Erickson, A.E., 1952. The measurement of oxygen diffusion in the  soil with a platinum micro-electrode. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 16: 160--163.  Letey, J. ~ad Stolzy, L.H., 1964. Measurements of oxygen diffusion rates with the  platinum micro-electrode. Hilgardia, 35 (20): 545--576.  Mann, L.D. and Stolzy, L.M., 1972. An improved constructiGn method for platinum  micro-electrodes. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 853--854.  Melsted, S.W., Kurtz, T. and Bray, R., 1949. Hydrogen peroxide as an oxygen fertilizer.  J. Am. Soc. Agron., 41: 97.  Phillips, R.E. and Ki~kham, D., 1962. Soil compaction in the field and corn growth.  Agron. J., 54: 29--34.  Stolzy, L.H. and FlUhler, H., 1978. Measurement and prediction of anaerobiosis in soils.  In: D.R. Nielsen and J.G. Mac Donald (Editors), Nitrogen in the Environment.  Academic Press, New York, N.Y., pp. 363--426.  Stolzy, L.H. and Letey, J., 1964. Characterizing soil oxygen conditions with a platinum  micro-electrode. Adv. Agron., 16: 249--279.  Turner, F.T. and Patrick, W.H., 1968. Chemical changes in the waterlogged soils as a  result of oxygen depletion. Proc. Int. Congr. Soil Sci., 9th, Adelal~le, Vol. 4, p. 53.  Van Bavel, C.H.M., 1951. A soil aeration theory based on diffusion. Soil Sci., 72: 33.  Vegis, A., 1964. Dormancy in higher plants. Ann. Rev. Plant Physiol., 15: 185--224.  Wiersma, D. and Mortland, M.M., 1953. Response of sugar-beets to peroxide fertilization  and its relationship to oxygen diffusion. Soil Sci., 75: 355--360.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractOxygen diffusion rates (ODR) and redox potentials at the 1 cm soil depth were reported for different treatments on soil samples subjected to simulated rainfall in the laboratory. Soil samples treated with polyacrylamide or CaO2 at a rate of 0.25% or higher showed highest ODR during each drying period between successive stimulator runs. Sugar beet germination was low on soil samples with low ODR and where crust formation occurred. Redox potential measurements did not reflect temporary oxygen fluxes in the soil and could be useful only in completely saturated and reduced conditions. 