 323    CONTENTS VOL. 34, 1984    The sorption of Cd, Zn and Ni by soil clay fractions: procedures for partition of  bound forms and their interpretation  K.G. Tiller, J. Gerth and G. Br~lmmer (Kiel, B.R.D.)  ....................  1  The relative affinities of Cd, Ni and Zn for different soil clay fractions and goethite  K.G. Tiller, J. Gerth and G. Br~mmer (Kiel, B.R.D.)  ....................  17  Characterizing the soil moisture regime of a Typic Haplohumod  L.W. Dekker, J.H.M. WSsten, and J. Bouma (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  .....  37  Experimental study of soil microfabrics induced by isotropic stresses of wetting and  drying  J.B. Dalrymple and C.Y. Jim (Reading, Great Britain)  ...................  43  Tentative assessment of soil survey approaches to the characterization and  interpretation of air--water properties of soils  J.A. McKeague, R.G. Eilers (Ottawa, Ont., Canada), A.J. Thomasson, M.J. Reeve  (Harpenden, Great Britain), J. Bouma (Wageningen, The Netherlands),  R.B. Grossman (Lincoln, Nebr., U.S.A. ), J.C. Favrot (Montpellier, France),  M. Renger and O. Strebel (Hannover, B.R.D.)  .........................  69  Physical assessment of a soil with respect to rooting potential  P.H. Groenevelt, B.D. Kay and C.D. Grant (Guelph, Ont., Canada)  ...........  101  Holocene soil chronofunctions, Southern Alps, New Zealand  P.W. Birkeland (Boulder, Colo., U.S.A.)  .............................  115  Occurrence of microcrystalline goethite in an unusual fibrous form  A.W. Fordham, R.H. Merry and K. Norrish (Glen Osmond, S.A., Australia)  .....  135  Soil--landscape chronograms for pedochronological analysis  W.J. Vreeken (Kingston, Ont., Canada)  .............................  149    Book Review  Soil Survey and Land Evaluation, by D. Dent and A. Young --T.H. Cooper  .......  165    Current Titles in Soil Science  ......................................  167  Assessing soil aggregate stability by water-drop impact and ultrasonic dispersion  A.C. Imeson and M. Vis (Amsterdam, The Netherlands)  ..................  185  Soil-climate system across the prairies in midwestern U.S.A.  R.V. Ruhe (Bloomington, Ind., U.S.A.)  .............................  201  The effect of weathering in the silt fractions on the apparent stability of chlorite  in Scottish soil clays  D.C. Bain and D.M.L. Duthie (Aberdeen, Great Britain)  ..................  221  Recent and ancient traces of scarab beetle activity in sandy soils of The Netheralnds  L. Brussaard and L.T. Runia (Wageningen, The Netherlands)  ...............  229  Contribution of inorganic polyphosphates to migration of elements in a grey forest  soil, U.S.S.R.  A. Yu. Kudeyarova and M.Z. Kvaratskheliya (Moscow, U.S.S.R.)  ............  251  Weathering of hornblende, plagioclase and chlorite in meta-dolerite, Australia  R.R. Anand and R.J. Gilkes (Nedlands, W.A., Australia)  ..................  261  Predicting transport of three cations in soil columns under conditions of steady-state  flow, India  R.S. Siyag, R. Pal, S.R. Poonia and T.C. Baruah {Hissar, India)  ..............  281  As assessment of chemical properties for soils of Rwanda with the use of  geostatistical techniques  P. Vander Zaag (Loss Banos, Philippines), R.S. Yost, B.B. Trangmar, K. Hayashi  and R.L. Fox (Honolulu, Hawaii, U.S.A.)  ............................  293    324    Book Reviews  Soil Monolith Papers, 1, 5, and 6, by J.J. Scholten and W. Andriesse -- F.H. Beinroth. 315  CO2 and Plants, The Response of Plant to Rising Levels of Atmospheric Carbon  Dioxide, by E.R. Lemon (Editor) -- C.C. Black, Jr  ......................  316  Elements of Soil Physics, by P. Koorevaar, G. Menelik and C. Dirksen -- A. Myslivec. 317  Physikatische Eigenschaften yon B~den der Schweiz, by F. Richard and P. Liischer  -- M. Renger  ...............................................  320  Residual Deposits: Surface Related Weathering Processes and Materials, by  R.C.L. Wilson (Editor)-- D.H. Yaalon  ..............................  321                                                                                                