 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 135--148                                                  135  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    OCCURRENCE OF MICROCRYSTALLINE GOETHITE IN AN UN-  USUAL FIBROUS FORM    A.W. FORDHAM, R.H. MERRY and K. NORRISH  CSIRO Division of Soils, Glen Osmond, S.A. 5064 (Australia)  (Received February 14, 1984; revised version accepted August 1, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Fordham, A.W., Merry, R.H. and Norrish, K., 1984. Occurrence of microcrystalline  goethite in an unusual fibrous form. Geoderma, 34: 135--148.    Small fragments of intermeshed fibrous material of high electron density-were ob-  served by electron microscopy in the fine (&lt; 0.5 #m) clay taken from an iron-rich ce-  mented layer forming part of the B horizon of a Podzol (Typic Haplorthod). Each fibre  was about 5 nm in width and about 100 nm in length. Similar material was also com-  mon in larger (0.5--2.0 #m) clay fractions but here it occurred as unbroken particles  which resembled bacteria in shape and size. At high magnifications, individual fibres  were seen to consist of very small (5 nm) particles aligned along the length of each  fibre.  Electron microanalysis of the fibrous material showed it to consist of iron, aluminium  and silicon. The average composition (water-free basis) of seventeen bacteria-like parti-  cles was 66% Fe203, 22% Al203 and 11% SiO~. The particles were positively identified  as aluminium-substituted goethite by selected-area electron diffraction.  The fibrous material was completely dissolved by dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate  treatment but was only slightly affected, if at all, by ammonium oxalate, pH3, in dark-  ness. Other extraction data and X-ray diffraction results showed that the clay also con-  tained considerable amounts of material of short range order, probably in the form  of ferrihydrite and allophane.    INTRODUCTION    In soils, iron oxide minerals do not normally develop into single crystals  with well-defined shapes easily observable at the microscopic level. They  do so, however, when prepared in the laboratory. For instance, hematite  often occurs as hexagonal plates, goethite as acicular crystals, and lepi-  docrocite as elongated laths (Schwertmann and Taylor, 1977). None with  fibrous morphology have been reported, except those described by Nakai  and Yoshinaga (1980). These authors found fragments of fibrous material,  identified as goethite by electron diffraction, in a number of soils from  Scotland and Japan.  We also have found fibrous material in a podzol from Tasmania. In this    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    136    paper, we describe its appearance, its interesting overall morphology, its  composition, identification and extraction by some chemical reagents.  Its presence in the podzol may have some bearing on the genesis of the  soil.    MATERIALS AND METHODS    The sample was taken at a depth of 60--65 cm from a profile situated  at Grove in southern Tasmania. The profile is classified as a Podzol (Stace  et al., 1968), Uc2.36 (Northcote, 1979) or Typic Haplorthod (Soil Survey  Staff, 1975), and has been described by Taylor and Stephens (1935) and  Merry et al. (1983). It consists of a black A1 horizon (0--30 cm) with accu-  mulated organic matter, overlying a light grey A: horizon (30--55 cm)  and a yellowish brown B horizon containing an iron-rich cemented layer  (ortstein) at 60--65 cm. The profile is acidic and sandy throughout, with  no more than 7% clay in any horizon. Some properties of the fine-earth  (&lt; 2 mm) samples are listed in Table I. Organic carbon was measured using  a modified Walkley-Black method and extractions with pyrophosphate  and with oxalate for 4 h in darkness were those detailed by McKeague  (1978).  The clay fraction was obtained by the method of Farmer et al. (1980),  in which a &lt; 2 mm air-dried sample was boiled for 1 h in 6% hydrogen  peroxide, washed, then suspended in dilute hydrochloric acid, pH 3.5.  The &lt; 0.5-pm and 0.5--2.0-#m size fractions were separated by controlled  centrifugation (Jackson, 1956), redispersing at times by ultrasonification.  Samples were extracted by oxaiate for 4 h in darkness (McKeague, 1978,  following Schwertmann, 1964) and also by dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate  (Mehra and Jackson, 1960). These two treatments have frequently been    TABLE I    Some properties of &lt; 2-mm samples from the profile    Depth    Colour      pH          Clay   Organic  Pyrophosphate   Oxalate  (cm)                 (1:5 water)  (%)   carbon   (~g/g)           (#g/g)  (%)    Fe    A1        Fe    A1    0-- 5    10YR 2/1    5.3           5         1.7       470    500       740  5--10    10YR 2/1    5.5           5         1.6       530    610       760  25--30    10YR 2/1    6.2           2         0.5       190    140       190  30--35    10YR 6/2    6.3           3       &lt;0.1          8     26         10  50--55    10YR 6/2    5.9           4         0.1          7     34         10  55--60    10YR 4/2   4.9           7         0.4       530    860       700  60--65*~  7.5YR 5/8   4.3           7         0.3      1240   1590      4980  65         10YR 5/6  ......    460  470  130  27  22  630  5180  i    *~ This is the sample which was later fractionated and examined in detail.    137    used to estimate iron oxides of short range order and total "free" iron  oxides, respectively. Fe, A1 and Si in the extracts were measured using  an inductively coupled plasma unit.  Samples were examined on the electron microscope (Philips EM400)  after drying drops of ultrasonically dispersed suspensions on alphanumeric  grids coated with holey films. Particles selected for microanalysis were  as free as possible from contamination by other components. Their posi-  tions were marked on photographs of single frames of the grid so that  they could be relocated subsequently in a Cambridge Geoscan microanal-  yser. Further details of the technique used have been reported previously  (Fordham and Norrish, 1979). Selected area electron diffraction patterns  were obtained by normal procedures, except they were calibrated against  patterns taken from nearby kaolinite particles within the same frame.  By this means, there were no instrumental adjustments between photo-  graphing the specimen and the kaolinite, apart from translating the small  distance from one particle to the other.    RESULTS    Electron microscope observations    Thin fragments of intermeshed fibres, irregular in shape and from 0.2  pm to 0.5 pm in size, were observed in the &lt; 0.5-pm clay fraction (Fig. 1).  The fibres, 5 nm in width and about 100 nm long, were often entangled  with kaolinite particles. At high magnifications (Fig. 2), each fibre was  seen to consist of many small (5 nm) electron-dense particles aligned along  the length of the fibre. The same type of small particles also occurred  elsewhere in the sample as rounded microaggregates or clusters and as  deposits upon the surface of kaolinite particles.  Similar fibrous material was common in the larger 0.5 tLm--2.0 pm clay  fraction, but in this instance it occurred as intact units with the distinctive  size and shape of bacteria (Fig. 3). Enhanced electron density around the  perimeters of these particles indicates they were hollow tubes with rounded  ends.  Treatment of the clay with dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate caused com-  plete removal of the fibrous material. On the other hand, no distinct changes  were obvious under the electron microscope as a result of mild oxalate  treatment. The electron-dense structure of the fibrous material appeared  to be unaltered, although some changes in less dense components may  have occurred. The ability of similar microcrystalline but non-fibrous ma-  terial to resist dissolution by oxalate was also observed in a previous study  (Fordham and Norrish, 1983).  To check whether or not the fibrous material was an artefact created  during sample preparation, clay fractions were also obtained without prior  H202 treatment. They were separated by the more conventional method    138    Fig. 1, (a and b). Fragments of fibrous material from the &lt; 0.5-#m fraction of hydrogen  peroxide-treated clay. Marker is 0.2 ~m.    Fig. 2. Highly magnified fibres in a fragment from the &lt; 0.5-~m fraction of hydrogen  peroxide-treated clay. Marker is 10 nm.    139    (a)  Fig. 3, (a and b). Intact fibrous particles with distinctive bacteria-like morphology,  in the 0.5--2.0-~m fraction of hydrogen peroxide-treated clay. Marker is 0.5 urn.    of sodium saturation and centrifugation in deionised water. Such fractions  contained as much fibrous material, both intact particles and fragments,  as those prepared by H202 treatment and dispersion in dilute acid solutions.    Electron microprobe analysis    The fibrous material was composed of iron, aluminium and silicon.  The other elements measured (Ti, K, Ca, P and S), if present at all, were  in concentrations of no significance. The average composition of nine  bacteria-like particles analysed in the 0.5--2.0 ~m fraction separated after  H202 treatment was 63.8% Fe203, 23.1% A1203 and 12.0% SiO2, on a water-  free basis. These had standard deviations of 2.5%, 2.7% and 2.2%, respec-  tively. After the same fraction was subsequently treated with oxalate,  eight more bacteria-like particles were analyzed. These contained 68.1%  Fe203, 21.2% A1203 and 9.9% SiO2, with standard deviations of 4.5%,  1.6% and 4.8%, respectively.  Unfortunately, the above analyses showed too much variation in the  composition of individual particles within each sample to assess unequivo-  cally whether or not oxalate treatment had had any effect. Applying t-test  statistics to Fe/A1 ratios within the particles showed that the difference    140    in composition after oxalate treatment was significant, but only at the  5% confidence level. If this difference is regarded as real, then the A1- and  Si-contents of the particles after treatment were lower relative to that  of Fe.  Taking all seventeen bacteria-like particles together, the average compo-  sition was 65.8% Fe203, 22.3% A1203 and 11.0% SiO2, with standard devia-  tions of 4.1%, 2.4% and 3.7%, respectively.  Fragments of fibrous material were more variable in composition than  the intact particles and this was seen to be due to frequent adherence of  small kaolinite particles. On the basis of t-tests, their average composition  was not significantly different from that of the intact particles in either  of the samples before or after oxalate treatment.    Electron diffraction analysis    Selected area electron diffraction of the intact bacteria-like particles  produced patterns of broad concentric rings, indicative of very small parti-  cles in random orientation. The d-spacings of a typical pattern are given  in Table II, together with X-ray diffraction data for a goethite containing  33 mole % substitution of Fe by A1 (Brindley and Brown, 1980). The  correspondence is very close. The fibrous material can thus be positively  identified as aluminium-substituted goethite, the ring in the vicinity of  4.12 A serving best to distinguish it from hematite and ferrihydrite. The  electron microprobe analysis of 66% Fe203 and 22% A1203 represents  a substitution of Fe by A1 of 34 mole %, which is the same degree of sub-  stitution in the goethite listed by Brindley and Brown.  The electron diffraction pattern presented by Nakai and Yoshinaga  (1980) for fibrous goethite is similar in its major features to that described  here, except that those authors obtained slightly higher d-spacings, possibly  indicative of less substitution of iron by aluminium in their samples.  To see if the broad diffuse band in the region of 2.70--2.41 A was a fea-  ture to be expected in the electron diffraction pattern of microcrystalline  goethite, a number of aluminium-substituted goethites were examined,  including several artifically prepared by Dr. R.M. Taylor (Division of Soils,  CSIRO, Adelaide). The artificial preparation shown in Fig. 4, which had  microcrystals of the same size and shape as those of fibrous goethite, gave  an identical electron diffraction pattern. The diffuse band was also produced  by other artificial aluminium-substituted goethites which were of small  but various particle sizes, in some instances up to 12 nm. Sometimes a  well-defined ring occurred at the inner edge of the diffuse band, but its  presence or otherwise did not appear to be related to particle size of the  preparations. When goethite was prepared in the absence of aluminium  so that it grew into acicular crystals 500 nm in length (Fig. 5), there were  distinct rings and spots in place of the diffuse band. Most d-spacings quoted  by Brindley and Brown (1980) for pure goethite were found in this par-    141    ticular sample, but some had very different intensities from those listed  because the long crystals were oriented fiat upon the grid surface. Natu-  rally occurring aluminium-substituted goethites, such as that (Fig. 6) with  a particle size of about 6 nm from a lateritic podzol, also showed a diffuse  band in the 2.70--2.41 A region. Thus it seems that the rings at 2.65, 2.53,  2.44 and 2.41 A will be unresolved when goethite is of microcrystalline  size, and a continuous band will be produced instead.    TABLE II    Selected area electron diffraction measurements of bacteria-like particles compared  with X-ray diffraction data of aluminium-substituted goethite (Brindley and Brown,  1980)    Bacteria-like particles    Al-substituted goethite    d(A)  I               d(A) 1.1    4.13  2.70    2.41    strong    weak-medium band    strong    2.25 } weak-medium band  2.16  1.88   very weak  1.69  medium    1.55   very weak  1.47   weak    1.29  very weak  1.18   very weak    4.88    11  4.12   100  3.33     9  2.65    40  2.53    16  2.48     6  2.44    14  2.41    78  2.21    19  2.15    26  1.97     4  1.88     7  1.77    13  1.69  42  1.66    12  1.63     4  1.58     8  1.53    27  1.48    13  1.45     9  1.43  13  1.39     7  1.37     6  1.35     5  1.33   7  1.29     8  1.22     4  1.18     4    ,1 Relative intensities of less than 4 have been. omitted.    142    Fig. 4. Aluminium-substituted goethite artificially prepared by oxidation of iron (II)  carbonate solution in the presence of aluminium at pH values between 6 and 7. Marker  is 10 nm.    Fig. 5. Goethite artificially prepared from iron (III) nitrate solution in the absence  of aluminium and aged in 1 M KOH at 80. Marker is 0.5 urn.    143    Fig. 6. Natural aluminium-substituted goethite obtained after ammonium oxalate treat-  ment of a lateritic podzol. Marker is 20 nm.    Chemical extractions    The results in Table I for the extraction of Fe and A1 by pyrophosphate  and by oxalate clearly show the accumulation of these elements in the  sample taken at 60--65 cm. Later data for oxalate and dithionite-citrate-  bicarbonate (DCB) extractions of both the ~ 2-~m and ~ 2-mm samples  are given in Table III.  It is known from electron microscope examination that microcrystals  of goethite found in fibrous material and elsewhere in the sample in loca-  lized deposits and micro-aggregates were not removed by oxalate. Further-    TABLE III    Extraction of &lt; 2-~m and &lt; 2-ram samples by ammonium oxalate and dithionite-citrate-  bicarbonate    Sample Extractant  %Fe203  %A1203   %SIO2  Fe/AI    &lt; 2 ~m Oxalate      5.2     6.6       3.0     1.1  DCB        13.1     6.0       1.5     2.9   2 mm Oxalate    0.68     0.82     0.38    1.1  DCB       1.29     0.66     0.17    2.6    144    more, electron microprobe analysis of individual fibrous particles showed  that there was no major change of composition after oxalate treatment.  Consequently, the Fe, A1 and Si extracted by oxalate were not derived  from the microcrystals but from other sources. The presence of ferrihy-  drite -- an iron oxide of short range order -- is suggested by the values  of the ratio (Feo/Fed) of Fe extracted by oxalate to that extracted by  DCB, which were 0.40 and 0.53 for the &lt; 2-pm and &lt; 2-mm samples,  respectively. Ferrihydrite, however, cannot account for all the extraction  data. For example, the amount of A1 in the oxalate extract was about  the same as that of Fe {Table III) and thus was too high for all of it to be  derived from ferrihydrite alone. In addition, ferrihydrite is also dissolved  by DCB, yet much lower amounts of A1 relative to Fe were extracted by  this reagent. These facts point to the presence of allophane in the sample  as well. Allophane is soluble in oxalate but not to any appreciable extent  in DCB (Wada, 1980). Silicon in the oxalate extracts would be derived  from allophane and also ferrihydrite which has the ability to adsorb con-  siderable amounts of silicon (Carlson and Schwertmann, 1981; Henmi  et al., 1980).  X-ray diffraction of the &lt; 2-pm sample supported the presence of mate-  rial of short range order. Goethite (5--10%), kaolinite (30--40%) and quartz  {10--20%) were identified, but more than 30% of the sample was X-ray  amorphous.  The &lt; 2-vm sample was treated with H202 prior to fractionation, yet  it produced the same Fe/A1 ratios in the extracts {Table III) as those from  the &lt; 2-mm sample which was not H202-treated. This suggests the absence  of Fe or A1 organic complexes, because such complexes would be decom-  posed to insoluble oxides during H202 treatment and subsequently be  extracted by both oxalate and DCB. If this had occurred, it is unlikely  the same Fe/A1 ratios would be maintained before and after treatment.  The actual amount of goethite present in any particular fraction of  Grove Sand varied from preparation to preparation, presumably due to  the degree of ultrasonification applied during fractionation. For this reason,  X-ray diffraction was carried out on the same preparation as the chemical  extractions.    DISCUSSION    The fact that the basic structural units of the fibrous material were  very small crystals of goethite is in agreement with several other reports  on the form of iron oxides in soils. Earlier studies (Fordham and Norrish,  1979, 1983} have shown the occurrence of microcrystalline iron oxides  in several soils of different types, in which they formed microaggregates  (0.5--1.0 pm} and surface deposits upon kaolinite flakes. Other workers,  especially those using M5ssbauer spectroscopy {Goodman and Berrow,  1976; Bigham et al., 1978; Golden et al., 1979; Ross and Longworth, 1980)    145    have also reported natural iron oxide minerals of very small unit particle  size, which nevertheless exhibit crystalline characteristics.  Relatively constant amounts of A1 and Si were measured by electron  microprobe in the intact bacteria-like particles of goethite. Because of this  consistency, the A1 and Si contents were probably not a result of incidental  association with other components, such as kaolinite flakes, entangled  at random within the mesh of fibres. Similarly, a more homogeneous mix-  ture with very finely divided allophane is unlikely because substantial  amounts of A1 and Si still remained after the oxalate treatment reported  to remove allophane. The obvious alternative is that A1 and Si were part  of the goethite microcrystals, either within the lattice or adsorbed on the  surface. Substitution of Fe by A1 in soil goethites is now an established  fact and, in view of the electron diffraction results for intact particles,  it must be concluded that most of the A1 was contained within the crystal  structure. The degree of substitution was high, but not uncommonly so  (Norrish and Taylor, 1961; Nahon et ai., 1977; Bigham et al., 1978; Fitz-  patrick and Schwertmann, 1982).  The location of Si is less defined, but its resistance to oxalate extrac-  tion in the present study shows that it occupied a relatively stable position.  Nakai and Yoshinaga (1980) also reported that the small amount of Si  in the fibrous goethite they examined was still there after oxalate treat~  ment. Fordham and Norrish (1983) found that up to 7% SiO2 was retained  in hematite/goethite pellets of about 1 pm throughout a series of extrac-  tions which included oxalate. Again using the electron microprobe, Fordham  and Norrish (1979) analyzed a large number of iron oxide pellets occurring  in a range of soils and, while many were undoubtedly mixed with small  particles of other components, some were believed free of contamination,  and these contained from 3% to 9% SiO2. In addition, Schwertmann and  Taylor (1972) and Schwertmann and Thalmann (1976) showed how syn-  thetic iron oxides prepared in the presence of Si retained small amounts  of Si which were then difficult to extract. Others (Schwertmann and Fischer,  1973; Henmi et al., 1980; Carlson and Schwertmann, 1981) examined  natural ferrihydrites and concluded from infra-red evidence that the Si  present was bonded through O to Fe. All this work indicates that Si is  capable of at least strong chemisorption on iron oxide surfaces. By inhibiting  crystal growth, adsorbed Si could explain the microcrystalline nature of  iron oxides in soils, and it could promote aggregation between microcrys-  tals which otherwise might have similar charge and so repel each other.  If, in addition, the Si acted as a bridge forming strong bonds with adjacent  microcrystals within microaggregates, then it would be very difficult to  remove it by reagents such as oxalate.  The regular arrangement of goethite microcrystals into fibres was thought  by Nakai and Yashinaga (1980) to be due to precipitation of the mineral  from transported solutions, in contrast to a weathering process in which  other components are removed and goethite remains in situ. These workers    146    had only fragments to consider, however, not the intact particles which  were available in Grove Sand. The sizes and shapes of the intact particles  show that microorganisms were involved, either directly by the action  of iron-oxidizing bacteria or indirectly by adsorption of inorganically pre-  cipitated goethite on cellular debris.  Chukhrov and his coworkers (1974) made a study of iron oxides pro-  duced by microbial processes. They examined fresh deposits formed at  the outlets of a number of springs, bores and seepage waters, both hot  and cold, both on land surfaces and under the sea. There was abundant  evidence of the presence of iron-oxidizing bacteria, mainly Gallionella  and Leptothrix, in the form of filamentous sheaths composed of ferri-  hydrite and protoferrihydrite, both iron oxides of short range order. These  residues consisted of microcrystals of about 5 nm in size. In a later publica-  tion, Chukhrov and Gorshkov (1981) reported the presence of similar  relicts in podzolic and chernozem soils. None of the particles they des-  cribed in either paper, however, had the particular morphology of those  observed in Grove Sand. Aristovskaya and Zavarzin (1971) reviewed the  role of iron-oxidizing microorganisms in soils. They attributed much of  the iron oxides accumulated biologically in soils to members of the genus  Pedomicrobium, which acts upon complexes formed between iron and  soil organic matter. These bacteria are able to deposit iron oxide on their  surfaces, until it ultimately covers the whole organism.  Conversion of iron from organic to inorganic microcrystalline forms  by iron-oxidizing bacteria provides an explanation of some of the objections  raised by Farmer et al. (1980) against the formation of podzols by move-  ment of metal-organic complexes from upper to lower horizons in the  profile. It does not, however, refute the evidence collected by these authors  to support the translocation of elements, particularly aluminium, as in-  organic "imogolite-type" materials.  As might be expected of a podzol, Grove Sand as a whole contained  material of short range order, probably ferrihydrite and allophane, but  apparently neither was closely associated with the fibrous goethite.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors thank J. Pickering of the Division of Soils, CSIRO, Adelaide,  for X-ray diffraction measurements, and are grateful to Dr. V.C. Farmer  of the Macaulay Institute for Soil Research for initially suggesting an ex-  amination of this sample.    REFERENCES    Aristovskaya, T.V. and Zavarzin, G.A., 1971. Biochemistry of iron in soil. In: A.D.  McLaren and J. Skujins (Editors), Soil Biochemistry. Marcel Dekker, New York,  vol. 2, pp. 385--408.    147    Bigham, J.M., Golden, D.C., Bowen, L.H., Buol, S.W. and Weed, S.B., 1978. Iron oxide  mineralogy in well-drained Ultisols and Oxisols, I. Characterization of iron oxides  in soil clays by M6ssbauer spectroscopy, X-ray diffractometry and selected chemical  techniques. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 42: 816--825.  Brindley, G.W. and Brown, G., 1980. Crystal structures of clay minerals and their X-ray  identification. Mineral. Soc. Monogr. 5, Mineralogical Society, London.  Carlson, L. and Schwertmann, U., 1981. Natural ferrihydrites in surface deposits from  Finland and their association with silica. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 45: 421--429.  Chukhrov, F.V., Ermilova, L.P., Gorshkov, A.I.:, Zyvagin, B.B., Shukchlistov, A.P.,  Siderenko, O.V. and Balashova, V.V., 1974. Uber die Natur der Eisenoxide in geol-  ogisch jungen Bildungen. Chem. Erde, 33: 109--124.  Chukhrov, F.V. and Gorshkov, A.I., 1981. Iron and manganese oxide minerals in soils.  Trans. R. Soc. Edinburgh, Earth Sci., 72: 195--200.  Farmer, V.C., Russell, J.D. and Berrow, M.L., 1980. Imogolite and proto-imogolite  allophane in spodic horizons: evidence for a mobile aluminium silicate complex  in podzol formation. J. Soil Sci., 31: 673--684.  Fitzpatrick, R.W. and Schwertmann, U., 1982. Aluminium-substituted goethite--an  indicator of pedogenic and other weathering environments in South Africa. Geoderma,  27: 335--347.  Fordharn, A.W. and Norrish, K., 1979. Electron microprobe and electron microscope  studies of soil clay particles. Aust. J. Soil Res., 17: 283--306.  Fordham, A.W. and Norrish, K., 1983. The nature of soil particles particularly those  reacting with arsenate in a series of chemically treated samples. Aust. J. Soil Res.,  21: 455--477.  Golden, D.C., Bowen, L.C., Weed, S.B. and Bigham, J.M., 1979. MSssbauer studies  of synthetic and soil-occurring aluminium-substituted goethites. Soil Sci. Soc. Am.  J., 43: 802--808.  Goodman, B.A. and Berrow, M.L., 1976. The characterization by MSssbauer spectros-  copy of the secondary iron in pans formed in Scottish podzolic soils. J. Phys., Coll.  C6, 37: 849--855.  Henmi, T., Wells, N., Childs, C.W. and Parfitt, R.L., 1980. Poorly ordered iron-rich  precipitates from springs and streams on andesitic volcanoes. Geochim. Cosmochim.  Acta, 44 : 365--372.  Jackson, M.L., 1956. Soil Chemical Analysis-Advanced Course. Published by the author,  Univ. Wisconsin, Madison.  McKeague, J.A. (Editor), 1978. Manual on Soil Sampling and Methods of Analysis,  2nd edn. Can. Soc. Soil Sci., Ottawa, Ontario.  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a  dithionite-citrate system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7:  317--327.  Merry, R.H., Tiller, K.G. and Alston, A.M., 1983. Accumulation of copper, lead and  arsenic in some Australian orchard soils. Aust. J. Soil Res., 21 : 549--561.  Nahon, D., Janot, C., Karpoff, A.M., Paquet, H. and Tardy, Y., 1977. Mineralogy, petro-  graphy and structures of iron crusts (ferricretes) developed on sandstones in the  western part of Senegal. Geoderma, 19: 263--277.  Nakai, M. and Yoshinaga, N., 1980. Fibrous goethite in some soils from Japan and  Scotland. Geoderma, 24: 143--158.  Norrish, K. and Taylor, R.M., 1961. The isomorphous replacement of iron by aluminium  in soil goethites. J. Soil Sci., 12: 294--306.  Northcote, K.H., 1979. A Factual Key for the Recognition of Australian Soils, 4th  edn. Rellim, Glenside, S.A.  Ross, C.A.M. and Longworth, G., 1980. M6ssbauer study of the attenuation of iron  in an irrigated Greensand lysimeter. Clays Clay Miner., 28: 43--49.    148    Schwertmann, U., 1964. The differentiation of iron oxides in soils by extraction with  ammonium oxalate solution. Z. Pflanzenern~ihr. Bodenkd., 105: 194--201.  Schwertmann, U. and Fischer, W.R., 1973. Natural "amorphous" ferric hydroxide.  Geoderma, 10: 237--247.  Schwertmann, U. and Taylor, R.M., 1972. The influence of silicate on the transforma-  tion of lepidocrocite to goethite. Clays Clay Miner., 20: 159--164.  Schwertmann, U. and Taylor, R.M., 1977. Iron oxides. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Weed  (Editors), Minerals in Soil Environments. Soil Sci. Soc. Am., Madison, WI, pp. 145--  180.  Schwertmann, U. and Thalmann, H., 1976. The influence of [Fe(II)], [Si] and pH  on the formation of lepidocrocite and ferrihydrite during oxidation of aqueous FeCI2  solutions. Clay Miner., 11: 189--200.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making  and Interpreting Soil Surveys. USDA Handbook, 436, Washington, D.C.  Stace, H.C.T., Hubble, G.D., Brewer, R., Northcote, K.H., Sleeman, J.R., Mulcahy,  M.J. and Hallsworth, E.G., 1968. A Handbook of Australian Soils. Rellim, Glenside,  S.A.  Taylor, J.K. and Stephens, C.G., 1935. The apple-growing soils of Tasmania. CSIR  Bull., 92.  Wada, K., 1980. Mineralogical characteristics of Andisols. In: B.K.G. Theng (Editor),  Soils with Variable Charge. New Zealand Soc. Soil Sci., Lower Hutt, pp. 87--107.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractSmall fragments of intermeshed fibrous material of high electron density were observed by electron microscopy in the fine (&lt; 0.5 μm) clay taken from an iron-rich cemented layer forming part of the B horizon of a Podzol (Typic Haplorthod). Each fibre was about 5 nm in width and about 100 nm in length. Similar material was also common in larger (0.5–2.0 μm) clay fractions but here it occurred as unbroken particles which resembled bacteria in shape and size. At high magnifications, individual fibres were seen to consist of very small (5 nm) particles aligned along the length of each fibre.Electron microanalysis of the fibrous material showed it to consist of iron, aluminium and silicon. The average composition (water-free basis) of seventeen bacteria-like particles was 66% Fe2O3, 22% Al2O3 and 11% SiO2. The particles were positively identified as aluminium-substituted goethite by selected-area electron diffraction.The fibrous material was completely dissolved by dithionite-citrate-bicarbonate treatment but was only slightly affected, if at all, by ammonium oxalate, pH3, in darkness. Other extraction data and X-ray diffraction results showed that the clay also contained considerable amounts of material of short range order, probably in the form of ferrihydrite and allophane. 