 GEOD_Ee, MA    AN INIERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SOIL SCIENCE  VOL. 30 (19831    EDI TO R -IN-CHIEF  R.W S~monson, College Park, Md    P W Arnold, Newcastle upon Tyne  J Bennema, Wagentngen  E Besoam Monasterio, Sant=ago  V.O Blederbeck, Sw=ft Current, Sask  G_H Bolt, Wagenmgen  G Br~Jmmer, Kiel  P Bullock, Harpenden  B T Bunting, Hamdton, Ont  J V J Carvalho Cardoso, Lisbon  F_E Clark, Fort Colhns, Colo  R.B Darnels, Washington, D C  F. de Coninck, Ghent  J M. de Villiers, Pmtermar=tzburg  R. Dudal, Rome  A E Ermkson, East Lansing, M=ch  J.J. Fripiat, Heverlee  W.H. Gardner, Pullman, Wash  D J. Greenland, Manilla  F.J. Hingston, Wembley, W.A  A Hoyos de Castro, Madrid  R.F. Isbell, Attkenvale, QId.  Y Ishizuka, Sapporo  M L. Jackson, Madison, Wisc.  M Jamagne, Versailles  J.J Jurinak, Logan, Utah    EDITORIAL BOARD  E J. Kamprath, Raleigh, N.C  V. Kovda, Moscow  J LSg, As  P F Low, West Lafayette, Ind  A F MacKenzte, Ste Anne de  Bellevue, Que.  F Manmm, Florence  J A McKeague, Ottawa, Ont  F R Moormann, Utrecht  L A Nelson, Rale=gh, N C  S Pawluk, Edmonton, Alta  D A Rennie. Saskatoon, Sask  F Richard, Z~rtch  R H. Rust, St Paul, Minn.  G K Rutherford, Kingston, Ont.  M. Schmtzer, Ottawa, Ont.  U Schwertmann, Mun=ch  J_R Sleeman, Canberra, A.C T.  F J. Stevenson, Urbena, II1.  D. Swartzendruber, Lincoln, Nebr.  R S Sw=ft, Canterbury  I. Szabolcs, Budapest  A van Wambeke, Ithaca, N.Y  D.H. Yaalon, Jerusalem    ELSEVIER SCIENTIFIC PUBLISHING COMPANY  Amsterdam - Oxford -- New York                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      