 Geoderma, 26 (1981) 13-23                                                        13  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    DETECTING INFILTRATION OF WATER THROUGH SOIL CRACKS BY  TIME-DOMAIN REFLECTOMETRY*1    G.C. TOPP and J.L. DAVIS.2  Land Resource Research Institute, Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, Ont., KIA 0C6 (Canada)  Geophysics and Geochemistry Division, Geological Survey of Canada, Ottawa, Ont.  KIA OE8 (Canada)  (Received February 1, 1980; accepted November 11, 1980~    ABSTRACT  Topp, G.C. and Davis, J.L., 1981. Detecting infiltration of water through soil cracks by  time-domain reflectometry. Geoderma, 26: 13--23.  During an experiment where simulated rainfall was applied to cracked soil, time-domain  reflectometry (TDR) was used to measure the water content of cracks and adjacent soil  vs. water content at some distance from the cracks. At a depth of 10 to 30 cm the rate of  wetting of soil immediately adjacent to the cracks was more ~ apid than that of the soil at  some distance from the cracks. Independent predictions of when water should begin  flowing down the cracks were deduced from knowledge of the applied "rainfall" rate,  field-measured hydraulic conductivity, initial water content and bulk density. These pre-  dictions checked well with those TDR measurements which indicated when water began  to accumulate in and adjacent to the cracks in a clay soil under corn and soybeans. More  than 1 cm of rainfall at rates greater than 0.1 cm/h contributed water to the soil cracks.  The water content profiles showed the very limited depth of wetting in the soil at some  distance away from the cracks as opposed to the much greater depth of wetting within  and adjacent to the cracks.  INTRODUCTION  Cracks or large pores in soil play a significant role in the distribution of  rainwater within the soil. The distribution of water entering the soil body is  of great importance in relation to plant water supply and also in relation to  solute transport of surface and subsurface water. Shuford et al. (1977) have  shown in infiltration experiments that large pores represent major pathways  for the trangmittance of nitrates and chlorides in the applied water. Bolton  et al. (1970) reported that in Brookston clay soil, subsurface drains carried  more water and nutrients from corn plots than from blue-grass sod or other  crops in rotations. From later experiments on the same type of soil, the rate  of response to rainfall of subsurface drains at two depths indicated that cracks    ,1 L.R.R.I. Contribution No. 20  ,2 Current address: Ensco Inc., Springfield, Va. (U.S.A.)    0016-7061/81/0000--0000/$02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    14    or large pores were operative in conducting rainwater to the drains (Bolton  and Hore, 1976).  Soil cracks, as major components in the water transport network, make  mathematical analysis of water flow in such soils virtually impossible. Even  so, a better understanding of the role of cracks in the water transport will  clarify the limits of current mathematical approaches and perhaps indicate  new directions.  The object of the experiments reported here was to demonstrate that  time-domain reflectometry (TDR) techniques can be used to measure the  occurrence of water in soil cracks and adjacent soil at greater depth and in  greater amounts than that accumulating in the main body of the soil during  simulated rainfall conditions. The field measured hydraulic conductivity  obtained with the air-entry permeameter (Topp and Binns, 1976) crust-top  permeameter (Bouma and Denning, 1972) and initial soil parameters such as  water content and bulk density were used to make independent predictions  of when water was expected to flow to the cracks. The results of the two  techniques are compared and discussed.  I~fATERIALS AND METHODS  Soil, sites and infiltration procedure  Three infiltration trials were conducted on each of two sites in Brookston  clay in Essex County, southwest Ontario, Canada. The crops grown on the  two sites were soybeans and corn. The experiment,,~ were conducted in late  summer {August 1976) after dehydration of the clay soil by evapotranspira-  tion had opened up numerous cracks ranging in width up to 5 cm at the sur-  face.  The infiltration trials took place within a 76 cm diameter region enclosed  by a galvanized steel ring which was hammered 4 cm into the soil leaving 6 cm  above the soil. Three infiltration rings (A, B and C) were installed between  corn rows and three rings (D, E and F) were instal]ted with a row of soybeans    "~ ,,~TRANSMISSION  LINE  "'3        I\~          INFILTRATION  C R A C K "~.~.j~~.~.p"~ GUAR D RING   -- x   '~                 -~  Fig. 1. Layout of infiltration ring showing location of the four transmission lines relative  to the crack.    15    passing within the ring. All locations were chosen to have a significant crack  passing across each ring as shown in Fig. 1.  During a four hour period simulated rainfe]l was added to give a total ac-  cumulated water depth of 2.5 cm. The rainfall rate was varied according to a  half cycle of a sine function as depicted in F'~. 2. This pattern and amount  approximated a once-in-five-year precipitation event. The water was applied  in measured volume increments which corresponded to 15-min time intervals.  The simulated rainfall was applied in a fine spray from a hand sprayer over  the first half of each 15-min interval. The TDR measurements for soil water  content were carried out during the second half of the interval as described  below.  TIME-DOMAIN    REFLECTOMETER  '  '  '  I  '  '  '  I  '  '  '  I  '  '  '              r"  .9                               TIMING ~, DISPLAY I  .e                                                 UNIT  .6                                 2.4           GENERATOR      RECEIVER  Alpplcation                                               Water                           _!.  Rate  .5                                       2.0   AddedCABLE.=-  (cm/hr)                                               (cm)           CONNECTOR ---~.c  J  .4                                  I.s -     AIR  .3                                  ,.2                          J   !  DISCONTINUITIES ----=.  i                                  o.,                        \i  ,                                   o.,                             il  O0           I           2           :3  '  '  '  40  TRANSMISSION   LINE .ji  TIME (hr)  Fig. 2. Rate of application of water and depth of water added during infiltration experi-  ments.  Fig. 3. Schematic of time-domain reflectometer and a transmission line with discontinui-  ties in soil.    TDR technique for measuring water content  Time-domain reflectometry (TDR) has been applied to measurement of  soil water content in the laboratory (Hoekstra and Delaney, 1974; Davis and  Annan, 1977; Davis et al., 1977; Toppet al., 1980). The technique has poten-  tial for field measurements when applied to parallel transmission lines (Davis  and Chudobiak, 1975; Davis et al., 1977). The approach used here follows  that of Davis et al. (1977) and is depicted schematically in Fig. 3. The por-  table TDR unit was a Tektronix 15{)2 TDR cable tester.    16    Parallel transmission lines made from two 12-mm diameter brass rods with  a centre to centre spacing of 50 mm were inserted vertically 110 cm into  the soil. To reduce the disturbance to the soil, pilot holes of the same  diameter as the rods were drilled using a centreless auger bit and a specially  designed drill press. The transmission lines were constructed with electrical  discontinuities which consisted of short lengths of the line at a diameter of  9 mm. The discontinuities provided the opportunity to measure water con-  tent profiles from a single transmission line rather than from a number of  transmission lines of various lengths at slightly different locations in the soil.  Discontinuities were placed at 10, 30 and 60 cm depths. The increments over  which water content was determined were 0 to 10 cm, 10 to 30 cm, 30 to  60 cm and 60 to 110 cm. The major part of the electromagnetic field was  confined to an elliptical cross-section where the rods are the verticles of the  ellipse. Thus the measured sample was of elliptical cross-section and &gt; 20 X l  cm3 where l is the length of the transmission line section.  The profile of water content with depth was determined at four locations  and at various times in each ring from the transmission lines placed vertically  in the soil as follows' one in a soil crack, one near the soil crack (about 5 cm  away), and two in the uncracked portion of the soil as shown in Fig. 1. The  cracks in the soil were not straight to a depth of 110 cm, the length of the  transmission lines, thus it was impossible to keep the rods solely in cracks  or to determine for certain that the rods near the cracks did not eventually  enter a crack at some depth. Measurements of soil-water content versus depth  were taken once before any infiltration, five times during infiltration and up  to three times after termination of infiltration. Each TDR measurement took  about two minutes accounting for set up time and checking. The TDR oscillo.  scope was photographed using a polaroid camera. The travel times were mea-  sured from each photograph and the apparent dielectric constant, Ka, was  calculated following Davis et al. {1977) and Topp et al. (1980). The empirical  equation:  2  Ka = 2.26 + 17.60v + 1060v                  (1)  given by Davis et al. (1977) for four different soils was used to determine the  corresponding volumetric water content, 0 v, for each measured Ka.  Attempts were made to validate eq. 1 for this soil by gravimetric sampling  immediately following the last electrical measurement. The soil samples were  taken from within the transmission lines i.e. between the rods inserted in  the soil. Sample volumes and thus densities were uncertain as a result of  sample breakage in dry samples or compaction of wetted soil. Thus a direct  comparison of electrical and gravimetric water content was impossible. It  was assumed that within the cultivated layer (0--20 cm) and away from  cracks the soil was of uniform density. A linear regression of 0 v from eq. 1  on 0w by gravimetric sampling gave standard error of estimates of 3.3% for  the corn field and 3.8% for the soybean field. Because these errors of esti-  mate are much larger than those found by Davis et al. {1977} and Topp et    17    al. {1980) it was concluded that the variability of measured density con-  tributed much more error than did eq. 1.    Hydraulic conductivity and estimation of iufiltrability    The hydraulic conductivity of the surface soil was measured to provide  data for estimating the infiltrability of the non-cracked soil and thus another  estimate of when the added water would flow to the soil cracks. The air-  entry permeameter (Topp and Binns, 1976} was used to determine the satu-  rated hydraulic conductivity of the soil early in the growing season before  cracks developed. Later as cracks began to appear, the unsaturated hydraulic  conductivity was determined at several negative pressure heads using the  crust-top permeameter (Bouma and Denning, 1972}.  Observations at the locations of the infiltration rings indicated that there  was about 2 cm of crumbly soil material on the surface of the essentially  unstructured soil between the cracks. It was assumed that, on addition of  water to the soil surface, the crumbly surface soil wetted to 85% of satura-  tion without restricting the infiltration rate. The quantity of water which  was added in this way was obtained by subtraction of the initial water con-  tent as measured by TDR and selected gravimetric sampling from 85% of the  saturated value. After sufficient water had been added to wet the surface  2 cm, we assumed the rate of infiltration was equal to the measured saturated  hydraulic conductivity. The applied rainfall rate in excess of this infiltration  rate was assumed to flow to the cracks in addition to that already there  directly from the rainfall intercepted by the exposed crack area. Thus, it was  possible to estimate not only when water began flowing to the cracks but  also the quantity which was in excess of the infiltrability of the soil.  By observing the soil surface during the application of the "rainfall" it was  possible to estimate when free water appeared. The appearance of free water  was interpreted as the time when the "rainfall" rate exceeded the infiltra-  bility of soil. This time was recorded as a third measure of when water was  expected to flow to the cracks.    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    To determine when water appeared in the soil cracks as a result of the ap-  plied "rain" it was advantageous to compare rates of wetting in the different  depth intervals. Fig. 4 and 5 show the average change of water content, A0 v,  for three depth increments 0--10, 10--30, and 30--110 cm from the trans-  mission lines some distance away from the cracks and from the lines in the  cracks.  Under both corn and soybeans the top 10 cm showed similar rates of  wetting, and slightly more water was measured some distance away from  the cracks than in the cracks. Although open initially, the cracks contained  some soil material which was carried there with water and by swelling but  the cracks held less water than some distance away from the cracks.    18  CORN FIELD  0 3!   ~.~~~_~.._~SOYBEAN   FIELD                                                             0.30.2 1         ~~  Ao.  01~     /  yf                                                                            I     I     I     I     I     I  N    '                 i_  .....  ~     ~     ~     J  ,,u-J                           0    I     2    3    4    8    12    16  - 0   I   2   3   4   8   12   16  27                            (a)  TIME (hr)  TIME (~r)  (a)  O 2 F                                                                    2F ..~  .....  ~  ........  -~  Ae,, i         '                   Ae,,r          o  [.                             -.  0 ~=~-_~'-T-   ~ - --z-----r-. _.  r----I ~                          0 ~   '     '     '     ~     J  0    I    2   3   4   8   12   16   27                    0   I    2   3   4   8   12   I=6  TIME (hr)                                            (b)  TIME (hr)  (b)  005r                                                                        O.I~A    ""~  .....  0 0    I    2    3    4    8    12   16  -0 05~)   I    2   3   4   8   12   16   27  TIME (hr)                                              (C)   TIME (hr)  (c)   owoy from crock   owoy from crock                                                 A___~__.~ in crock   ""~-- ~"-~'  In crock  Fig. 4. The mean changes of water content (h0v) during and following infiltration in the  soybeans. The data are presented for three depth increments: (a) 0 to 10 cm; (b) 10 to  30 cm; and (c) 30 to 110 cm.  Fig. 5. The mean changes of water content (h0v) during infiltration between corn rows.  The data are presented for three depths increments. (a) 0 to 10 cm; (b) 10 to 30 cm;  and (c) 30 to 110 cm.    It was in the 10--30 cm depth increment where an indication that water  entered the cracks was observed. Figs. 4(b) and 5(b) show that in both cases  the wetting in and adjacent to the cracks was always greater than at some  distance away from the cracks. This is more dramatically shown for the soy-  bean field where no wetting took place away from the cracks but within the  crack the water content had increased more than 10%. In the corn plot the  overall change in water content in the crack was almost 20% but a change of  10% was measured away from the crack. Therefore, in both cases there was  a large increase in water content at the 10--30 cm depth which was not mea-  sured elsewhere.  The change with time of water content of the i0--30 cm depth in the crack  in each infiltration ring is shown in Fig. 6. Three types of wetting patterns  were observed. At the 1.6-h reading transmission lines B and C were in cracks  which were measured to have considerably more water than would result  from direct fall of the added water. Transmission lines A, D and E showed  a later arrival of water in the cracks but after 2 hrs, the measured change in  water content was greater than could have resulted from an even distribu-  tion or" the added water. Transmission line F showed less than half as much    19  !-                   B  //,~,"  ,/  .......  ,,i --  O.l~    ,.."//    C  ~,.&lt;  0_~-~~-J~j~ ,    ,,    ,    ,    ,    ,  0      2   3  4   8   12  16  TIME (hr)  (0)  CORN FIELD    F                     :D  n~..           ,i     _x-   ,E  ~-         .I    - ~ ~  .....  01~-     . &lt; x- --x "        ..F  ....  x  0    1    2    3   4    8    12   16   27  TIME ( hr!  (b)   SOYBEAN   FIELD  Fig. 6. The changes of water content (i0v) for the 10 to 30 cm increment in the individual  transmission lines placed in the soil cracks. The letters on each line correspond to the  infiltration site.    change in water content as the majority of the other lines. From these data  we estimated that water was entering directly into the cracks at between 1.5  and 2.25 h or after 1 to 1.5 cm of "rainfall" had been applied. The range in  the determination of when water entered the cracks reflected the differing  conditions in the field, e.g., cracks of various widths and not running full of  water at any time.  The TDR technique is useful for measuring changes in water content of  soil in and adjacent to cracks as well as some distance away from the cracks.  This technique, however, does not provide information on how the greater  amount of water got to the greater depth in and adjacent to the cracks than  at greater distances from the cracks.  Fig. 7 shows water content versus depth at two locations in infiltration  ring D in the soybean field. Each line is labeled with the time in hours since  application of water was started. Fig. 7(a) shows the development of the  water content profiles some distance away from cracks and Fig. 7(b) shows  the profiles in and adjacent to a crack. Away from the cracks no measureable  water penetrated below 10 cm. After the reading at 2.25 h none of the added  water was measured at the location of the transmission whose data appears in  Fig. 7(a). By contrast, at the measured location in the crack in this ring  water penetrated to about 30 cm but not deeper. By the time measurements  were made at 2.25 h more water was measured at this transmission line loca-  tion than in previous case. In addition, the amount of water measured here  at 2.25 h is greater than would have resulted from a uniform distribution of  the water added. The x symbols in Fig. 7(b) show the expected water content  if the water had been distributed with a vertical pattern similar to the 0.75 h    20    WATER CONTENT 8v  0.2            0.3            O.4  o             ,,~ 12.-  :       0"'~i   ~/~                             WATER CONTENT 0v  /( ~/~i~"~-              O0          0.1          0.2         0.3         0.4  20 ~                                                                      -~   ~   T------- "~-   ~'"  ~  T-~   ~       !  ......  '--~      3              ~-. "-~.  - ~_.. ~._._  :       2o'-             "',  o7s"~"           -+ ~       +  ]            7!!'                                                                            +                        ,       ,                  /  / i  60+         , ,,, t   ~                                          '     8-    i                           ' '\' ' " ""                         '      +,oi-                     '~   "--,,            -+  ,,\ .  ....  .\       \:;7, ",                '    i                   ,     !  ,%,           "-.  :                                                                                                                                            ,    (               ",,  ;                                                       -i                                                                   l  O-RING-AWAY FROM THf CRACK                    ~           ~-                         O-RING-IN THE CRACK         "i    ~__._L.__.,__._ L~_~__'~A          '   L+ _L._+~_~__] L_+ L.__++  .....  ~_  ....  __...~__.u_t___L  I  '  '  L+*. : ~                                                                                                            LRR#    Fig. 7, Ca). Volumetric water content (0v) versus depth profiles obtained during infiltra-  tion experiments in the soybean crop. The parameter labelling each line is the time, in  hours, from the beginning of infiltration. The data points plotted at depths of 5, 20, 45,  85 cm and joined by line segments are water contents for 0--10, 10--30, 30--60, and  60--110 cm intervals, respectively. Measurements were made some distance away from  the crack.  (b). Volumetric water content (0v) versus depth profiles obtained in the same infiltration  ring as for Ca) except measurements were made from the transmission line in the crack.    measurement. Thus, these data indicated that prior to 2.25 h the infiltrability  of the uncracked soil was exceeded and the rapid increase in water content  in or adjacent to the cracks resulted from lateral flow at or near the soil sur-  face. A great variety of wetting patterns were observed and summaries and  discussion of other water content profiles can be obtained from Topp (1978).  The hydraulic conductivity was measured to estimate how infiltration took  place. In Fig. 8 the large range of values from l~he air-entry permeameter  (AEP) resulted from cracks in the soil. Although the data from the crust-top  permeameter (CTP) were highly variable they fell consistently at the low  range of those from the AEP. Thus the AEP gave l-,igh values of hydraulic  conductivity later in the growing season when cracks were forming. The early  season AEP values were, however, confirmed by the CTP. The value of 0.12  cm/h was chosen visually as representative of the saturated hdyraulic con-  ductivity of soil at the soybean site and away from cracks. Similar measure-  ments in the corn field gave a value of 0.10 cm/h.  By making assumptions about how the initial infiltration took place, we  estimated when the applied "rainfall" rate exceeded the infiltrability of the  soil. Initially measured values of water content and density, along with obser-    21  A             - 20  A             I0  5.0  --                                          20 "~  &amp;                       o  " AEP  x CTP                                      1.0  |                 ,-  I--  z  "x              .2   0  x x                   f"-')  Jax              .t   _o  x                 x                      ~  x    x        '~                .05On"  .02  ,   ,  x~.___L__~   ~   ~   t   ~   ~   ,     0.01  -4(          -20           0           20  PRESSURE HEAD (crn of woter)    Fig. 8. Hydraulic conductivity versus pressured head for soil at the 3--5 cm depth in the  soybean site. The hydraulic conductivities plotted at h = 0 were measured by air- entry  permeameter (AEP); the other data were obtained by crust-top permeameter (CTP).    vations of the surface condition of the soil under the soybean plants, indicated  that 0.81 cm of the initially applied "rain" was absorbed in the 2 cm at the  soil's surface. This amount of water was added during the first 1.5 h. The  rate of addition of water from 1.5 to 1.75 h was 0.88 cm/h (Fig. 2) which  was in excess of the saturated hydraulic conductivity of 0.12 cm/h {Fig. 8).  Therefore, this method predicted that free water would have entered the  cracks between 1.5 and 1.75 h after the infiltration started. Similar measure-  ments and calculations for the corn field predicted free water would have  entered the cracks slightly later, at 1.75 h after start of experiment. These  independent predictions correspond well to 1.5 to 2.25 h range estimated  from the TDR data of Figs. 6 and 7.  During the experiments, the surface soil was observed carefully for the  presence of free water. Only in ring (B) was free water not observed. The  times of first occurrence of free water at the surface ranged from 1.25 to  2.25 h. Thus, this observational method gave results similar to the other two  methods.  The data given here can be interpreted in relation to the drainage studies  reported by Bolten and Hore (1976). On the same soil type, they showed  flow in subsurface drains at 60 and 95 cm depth after rainfalls of 2.0--3.0 cm.  In addition, the rate of response of the drain flow was extremely rapid,  going from zero flow to peak flow in less than 1 h (figs. 3 and 4 in Bolton and  Hore, 1976). The time between initiation of flow at 60 cm depth and 95 cm    22    depth was less than 2 h. Such a short time would only result from water  reaching the drains by way of cracks and large pores. Our findings that water  appeared in soil cracks after addition of about 1 cm of water to the soil sur-  face is consistent with those of Bolton and Hore (1976). Both indicate that  the flow of water in soil cracks is an especially important component of the  water moving to subsurface drains.    SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS    The volumetric water contents measured by the TDR technique using trans-  mission lines, both in soil cracks and away from cracks, were used to estimate  when water entered the cracks. The change of water content with time in the  individual cracks at the 10--30 cm depth was the most definite indicator of  when water was entering the measured zone of the crack. Comparable esti-  mates of when water entered the soil cracks were obtained with greater  effort from the use o!~ field-measured hydraulic conductivity values, initial  water contents, and bulk density. In these experiments both methods showed  that rainfall rates in excess of 0.1 cm/hr after 1 cm had fallen contributed  to a relatively large accumulation of water in and adjacent to the cracks.  The water content profiles from the TDR technique showed that changes  in water content away from cracks were confined mostly to the top 10 cm,  whereas changes in the cracks occurred over upper 30 cm but much less in the  top 10 cm than immediately below. The sample volume, the nondestructive  nature and the simplicity of measurement with the TDR technique are advan-  tages over any other available techniques when applied to studying water  flow in soils with cracks.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors gratefully recognize the efforts of Keith Wires and Walter  Zebchuk during the infiltration experiments and also those of Douglas McLean  and Craig Miller for assistance with hydraulic conductivity determinations.  Dr. A.P. Annan's suggestions during execution of this project are appreciated.  The study discussed herein was carried out as part of the efforts of the In-  ternational Reference Group on Great Lakes Pollution from Land Use Activi-  ties (PLUARG), an organization of the International Joint Commission (IJC),  established under the Canada--U.S. Great Lakes Quality Agreement of 1972.  Findings and conclusions are those of the authors and do not necessarily re-  flect the views of the Reference Group or its recommendations to the Com-  mission.    REFERENCES    Bolton, E.F., Aylesworth, J.W. and Hore, F.R., 1970. Nutrient losses through tile drains  under three cropping systems and two fertility levels on a Brookston Clay soil. Can. J.  Soil Sci., 50: 275--279.    23    Bolton, E.F. and Hore, F.R., 1976. Sub-surface drainage related to agronomic factors on  Brookston Clay soil. Proc. of Specialty Conference "Environmental Impact of Irriga-  tion and Drainage, Am. Soc. Civ. Eng., New York, N.Y., pp. 221--228.  Bouma, J. and Denning, J.L., 1972. Field measurement of unsaturated hydraulic conduc-  tivity by infiltration through gypsum crusts. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 36: 846--847.  Davis, J.L. and Chudobiak, W.J., 1975. In-situ meter for measuring relative permittivity  of soils. Geol. Surv. Can., Pap., 75-1A, pp. 75--79.  Davis, J.L. and Annan, A.P., 1977. Electromagnetic detection of soil moisture: Progress  report I. Can. J. Remote Sensing, 3: 76--86.  Davis, J.L., Topp, G.C. and Annan, A.P., 1977. Electromagnetic detection of soil water  content: Progress Report II. In: Remote Sensing of Soil Moisture and Groundwater.  Workshop Proceedings, Canadian Aeronautics and Space Institute, Ottawa, November  1976, pp. 96--109.  Hoekstra, P. and Delaney, A., 1974. Dielectric properties of soils at UHF and microwave  frequencies. J. Geophys. Res., 79: 1699---1708.  Shuford, J.W., Fritton, D.D. and Baker, D.E., 1977. Nitrate-nitrogen and chloride move-  ment through undisturbed field soil. J. Environ. Qual. 6: 255-259.  Topp, C.G., 1978. Physical properties of the soils of agricultural watersheds which control  moisture storage and transport. Task C studies (Canadian) International Ref. Gro,~  on Great Lakes Pollution from Land Use Activities, U.S.--Can. International Join Com-  mission, Windsor, Ont., 43 pp.  Topp, G.C. and Binns, M.R., 1976. Field measurement of hydraulic conductivity with a  modified air-entry permeameter. Can. J. Soil Sci., 56: 139--147.  Topp, G.C., Davis, J.L. and Annan, A.P., 1980. Electromagnetic determination of soil  water content: measurements in coaxial transmission lines. Water Resour. Res., 16:  574--582.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     AbstractDuring an experiment where simulated rainfall was applied to cracked soil, time-domain reflectometry (TDR) was used to measure the water content of cracks and adjacent soil vs. water content at some distance from the cracks. At a depth of 10 to 30 cm the rate of wetting of soil immediately adjacent to the cracks was more rapid than thatof the soil at some distance from the cracks. Independent predictions of when water should begin flowing down the cracks were deduced from knowledge of the applied Ã¢Â€ÂœrainfallÃ¢Â€Â rate, field-measured hydraulic conductivity, initial water content and bulk density. These predictions checked well with those TDR measurements which indicated when water began to accumulate in and adjacent to the cracks in a clay soil under corn and soybeans. More than 1 cm of rainfall at rates greater than 0.1 cm/h contributed water to the soil cracks. The water content profiles showed the very limited depth of wetting in the soil at some distance away from the cracks as opposed to the much greater depth of wetting within and adjacent to the cracks. 