 159    Other Publications Received    I.K. lskandar (Editor), 1981. Modeling Wastewater Renovation -  Land  Treatment. John Wiley and Sons, Inc., New York, N.Y., 817 pp.,  hard-  cover, tg. 40.00.  The book is organized into six principal sections which cover: an over-  view of modeling; soil-water, solute and virus transport modeling; soil  nitrogen modeling; soil phosphorus modeling; site selection, optimization  and economic modeling; concluding remarks and research needs. Models  presented by the authors include both research-oriented and management-  oriented types. The research models were developed for the purpose of  elucidating the complex processes involved in wastewater renovation. The  management-oriented models will be of practical benefit to design engineers  and decision makers.    F.M. D'itri, J.A. Martfnez, M.A.  L~imbarri (Editors),  1981. Municipal  Wastewater in Agriculture. Academic Press, New York, N.Y., 508 pp.,  hardcover, $39.50.  Proceedings of the International Conference on the Status of Knowledge,  Critical Research Needs, and Potential Research Facilities Relating to: The  Cooperative Research Needs For The Renovation and Reuse of Municipal  Wastewater in Agriculture, Held at The Hotel Hacienda Cocoyoc, Morelos,  Mexico, December 15--19, 1980.  The book is divided into 20 chapters covering six different sections:  I.  Administrative and legal aspects of wastewater renovation and reuse.  II. Reuse alternatives for municipal wastewater.  Ill. Operation of land treatment systems.  IV. Pathogens and heavy metals in municipal wastewater.  V. Design and cost criteria for land treatment systems.  VI. Research needs for renovation and reuse.  Primary topic on the conference was: how to renovate and reuse waste-  water by agricultural irrigation.    T. Rosswall (Editor), 1980. Nitrogen Cycling in West African Ecosystems.  SCOPE/UNEP, Sweden, 449 pp., US $15.00.  Proceedings of a workshop arranged by the SCOPE/UNEP International  Nitrogen Unit in collaboration with MAB (Unesco)and IITA at the inter-  national Institute for Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria, held December  11--15, 1978.  A major part of the meeting was devoted to discussions of present know-  ledge of nitrogen cycling in three major ecosystem types in West-Africa,  viz., savannas, forests and agro-ecosystems. The reports from these work  group discussions are included together with a report on the final discussion  on research priorities and future cooperation.    160    R.F. Thomas, L.C. Blakemore and D.I. Kinloch, 1981. Flow-Diagram Keys  for "Soft Taxonomy", Oxisols and Vertisols. N.Z. Soil Bureau Scientific  Reports, 39E; and: Flow-Diagram keys for "Soil Taxonomy", Aridisols.  N.Z. Soil Bureau Scientific Reports 39F. Department of Scientific and  industrial Research, New Ze~fland.  These Series seek to explain, in flow-diagram form, the definitions and  keys given in the USDA Agriculture Handbook "Soft Taxonomy". In  volume 39 E + F flow diagrams are presented which permit determination  down to subgroup level, of the taxonomic classes of soils in the Oxisol and  Vertisol/Aridisol soil orders.    R. Wetselaar, J.R. Simpson and T. Rosswall (Editors), 1981. Nitrogen  Cycling in South-East Asian Wet Monsoonal Ecosystems. Published by the  Australian Academy of Science. Proceedings of a regional workshop arranged  by the SCOPE/UNEP, international nitrogen unit of the Royal Swedish  Academy of Sciences and the Chiang Mai University, sponsored by the  MAB program of UNESCO. Held at Chian Mai, Thailand 5--10 November,  1979. A$25.00, 214 pp.  A collection of papers that reflect current knowledge of nitrogen cycling  in Southeast Asian ecosystems. Half of the papers are related to rice, and the  importance of nitrogen. The other papers cover a variety of ecosystems;  such as forest and mangrove ecosystems. Also environmental problems,  associated with terrestrial nitrogen transformations, methods for studying  nitrogen cycle processes under field conditions, and nitrogen imput are  considered.    H. de Bakker and M.W. van den Berg (Editors), 1982. ILRI Publication 30.  Proceedings of the Symposium on Peat Lands Below Sea Level. Published by  International Institute for Land Reclamation and Improvement, The Nether-  lands, 295 pp., Dfl. 36.00.  Proceedings of the Int. Symposium, organized under the sponsorship of  Commission III of the Int. Peat Society and the Netherlands Soil Science  Society, Wageningen, August 24--28, 1981. The proceedings of this sym-  posium contain 24 papers. The papers were presented in three sessions:  Geography; Engineering; Land Use.    H. Dost and N. van Breemen (Editors), 1982. ILRI publication 31. Proceed-  ings of the Bangkok Symposium on Acid Sulphate Soils. International Insti-  tute for Land Reclamation and Improvement, The Netherlands, 449 pp.,  Dfl. 54.00.  Proceedings of the Second International Symposium on Acid Sulphate  Soils, Bangkok, Thailand January 18--24, 1981. The emphasis of the Sym-  posium was on the management of soil/water/plant systems under acid  sulphate soft conditions in tropical agro-ecological zones in Southeast Asia  and West Africa. This was a sequel to the first symposium held in Wageningen,  1972.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      