 Geoderma, 25 (1981) 231--244  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    231    THE SOILS OF THE FAEROE ISLANDS    G.K. RUTHERFORD and C.E.B. TAYLOR  Department of Geography, Queen's University, Kingston, Ont. (Canada)  Ontario Hydro, Toronto, Ont. (Canada)  (Received March 28, 1979; accepted after revision November 11, 1980)    ABSTRACT    Rutherford, G.K. and Taylor, C.E.B., 1981. The soils of the Faeroe Islands. Geoderma,  25: 231--244.    The soils of the Faeroe Islands are developed from fairly homogeneous basalt parent  materials under humid and cool to cold conditions. The soil-forming processes and short  time through which these have functioned have produced soil profiles which may be clas-  sified as Regosols, Brunisols, Podzols, Gieysols and Organic Soils in the Canadian system  of soil classification. The soils are conti,mously moist or wet and generally have thick  organic horizons. The mineral portion is high in silt and low in clay-sized particles. The  soils are strongly acidic with high cation exchange capacities (23 to 82 me./100 g) and  low base saturations (20%): sodium of marine origin may be a dominant exchangeable  cation. Podzols may have convoluted iron pans and some Brunisols exhibit stone stripes  and polygons. Weathered pseudomorph regoliths and boulders occur.    INTRODUCTION    One of the problems commonly inherent in any study of pedogenesis is the  lack of precise knowledge of the original nature of the parent material. The  Faeroe Islands are the glaciated remnants of plateau basalt, thus constituting  relatively homogeneous parent materials. The archipelago with its homogeneous  lithology is a favourable area for the study of pedogenesis in a cool humid  climate.  As virtually no previous information on soil genesis in the islands is available,  the object of this paper is to present some aspects of the properties, classifica-  tion, distribution and genesis of soils formed from basaltic parent materials  of the Faeroe Islands.    PHYSICAL SETTING    The Faeroe Islands, located in the North Atlantic Ocean (62 70)  consist of 21 islands, skerries and outcroppings constituting a landmass of  approximately 1,400 km2. The archipelago occurs as a series of ridges and hill    0016-7061/81/0000-0000/$02.50 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    232    remnants projecting above sea level from a broad submarine ridge that sepa-  rates the Norwegian Sea from the Atlantic Ocean. The relief is rugged and  mountainous resulting from the reduction of plateau basalts by glacial, peri-  glacial and fluvial erosion (Fig.l). The mean elevation is 300 m above sea level  (a.s.l.): over 1000 peaks attain elevations greater than 300 m and ten are  greater than 800 m. The climate is cool, wet and windy (KSppen, Cfc). Pre-  cipitation occurs on more than 281 days a year and averages 1461 mm an-  nually: snow rarely remains more than a few days at a time at sea level. The  mean annual temperature at ~ea level is about 5C. Grass and heath are the  dominant vegetation types and there is evidence that the islands have never  supported significant tree vegetation.    Fig. 1. Typical landscape on the Faeroe Islands showing basalt flows and glacial landforms.    Ahnost the entire Faeroe landscape is treeless and covered w~th a variety  of grasses, although the higher land areas remain virtually devoid of vegetation  except for lichens, mosses and some rough grasses. Low-lying, poorly drained  areas support cotton grass and sedge, whereas heath vegetation occupies  slightly better drained areas.  Borgensen (1902) reported that no significant tree vegetation existed prior  to 1800. Introduced trees, in a few small plantations are chiefly pine but  inchlde willow, maple and rowan. Only 6% of the total land area of the Faeroc  Islands is enclosed as improved agricultural land and 90% of this is cultivated.  Crops are barley, oats, potatoes and turnips. By far the greater share of the  land, 194%) is not arable and is used as pasture for sheep.    233    Settlement of the Faeroes began around 700 AD with the arrival of Irish  monks and subsequent colonization by Vikings from 820 to 900 AD. The  islands were annexed by Norway in 1035 and remained under this rule f ,r  800 years, after which they were transferred to Danish rule.    Bedrock and Quaternary geology    The Faeroe Islands are remnants of plateau basalts (Fig. 2) formed by suc-  cessive lava flows of Early Tertiary age (50--60 million years; T,~rling and  Gale, 1968) some 3 km thick. The pre-Quaternary geology has beer, described  in considerable detail by Rasmussen and Noe-Nygaard (1963, 1970} who have  divided the strata into the following members.    Fig. 2. Aerial photograph of the southern part of Esturoy showing glacial landscape features  and basalt flows. (altitude 12,000 m).    (1) Upper Lava Series. 675 m of clearly separable lava flows similar to  Lower Lava series; olivine tholeiite with magnesium olivine, augite, vughs filled  with zeolites and rare glass; plagioclase 84--64% An; fairly resistant to physical  weatheringl  {2) Middle Lava Series. 1350 m of very tl-,in ropy quartz tholeiite lavas,  augite, pigeonite, magnesium olivine, iddingsite, labradorite (65% An) and  common zeolite; about 10% glass, significantly less resistant to physical erosion  than the lava series above and below.  (3) Tuff--Agglomerate. A local zone consisting of lapilli, bombs and ash on  Suderoy only.    234    (4) Coal Measures. 10 m, mainly on Suderoy, with erratic occurrences of  fireclay (kaolin} and Fullers earth (montmorillonite).  (5) Lower Lava Series. 900 m of quartz tholeiite lava flows, average thick-  ness 20 m; augite, pigeonite, labradorite (65% An), and 10% glass, minor zeo-  lites in uppermost flows.  Glacial till and boulder clay occur as localized deposits with common oc-  currences of mass wasting, terracettes, solifluction deposits and sorted and  patterned ground in higher parts. There is an apparent lack of raised beaches  and other evidence of isostatic emergence yet the ancient Viking landing site  at Vikar is now several metres out of water.    MATERL~LS AND METHODS    Sixty-five soil profiles were sampled during the field work in the summers  of 1975 and 1976, when all the main islands were visited. These samples and  others of pedological interest were collected and sealed in airtight containers  and sent to Canada for analysis. Particle size distribution was determined by  hydrometer (Day, 1965), pH in 0.01 M CaC12, exchangeable cations with  normal neutral ammonium acetate and exchangeable hydrogen by titration  {Brown, 1943}.  Extractable Fe, A1 and Mn were determined using dithionite-citrate-bicar-  bonate, ammonium oxalate and sodium pyrophosphate (McKeague and Day,  1966). Selected soil samples were impregnated with resin and thin sections  were made and described, using methods suggested by Brewer (1964). Loss  on ignition was determined on heating to 375 for 16 h.    RESULTS    Soils of the island generally have deeper organic surface horizons than  similar soils in more southerly latitudes (Bouma et al., 1969}. Some B and C  horizons are composed almost entirely Gf strongly humified, dark colored  amorphous materials. Most of the soils are continuously wet and deap peat  surface horizons are formed in poorly drained sites up to 800 m a.s.1. With  the exception o:f bright colored ironpan horizons (Table I), strong colors and  horizonation are uncommon. Strong textural differentiation is commonplace  in soil profiles but this is of sedimentological rather than pedological origin as  most lower sites are constantly receiving materials eroded from higher sites.  The texture of materials at depositional sites is influenced by a number of  environmental factors including: rainfall and wind velocity, slope angle and  intensity of sheep grazing. Textural differences within the same major soil  horizon may be clearly observed in many profiles.  The mineral softs of the Faeroe Islands are friable and composed of pre-  dominantly silt-sized materials {Table II). Loss on ignition values range from  6% in a C horizon to 98% in a buried humic layer. Surface horizons are strong.  ly acidic and the profiles become less acidic with depth; horizons with higher    TABLE I  Morphological data from some sG!l profiles on the Faeroe Islands  Horizon      Depth        Colour          Texture      Structure/consistency    235    Regosols  Of + Om        8--0        10 YR 2/1  A            0--19      10 YR 2/1     sl  Bh            19--40      10 YR 2/1      sl  Cc            40--62      10 YR 5/4      fsl    c        3bk; mfi, cw, sir    Brunisols  Of        10--8                        (H4)  Om          8--3        5 YR 2/1     s           (H5)  Oh             3--0        10 YR 3/1      s    m      2sbk; wso  Al             0--43      10 YR 3/1      sl    c       2bk; ws  Bh            43--108      10 YR 3/2      sil    Podzols  Of            10--80  Om          3--3      7.5 YR 4/2     fs          (H2)  Oh          3--0      7.5 YR 4/4     sl   c      2blk; (H6)  AI             0--20      7.5 YR 4/3      gsl   f       3sbl:~ sbk; wps-mfr  Aej           20--35      10 YR 4/3      Is    f       2bk; wso-mfr  Bli             35--36       2.5 YR 4/8      consir  L2c           36--87       10 YR 4/3      gls   c       2sbk; mvfr, cw  B3            87--120      10 YR 5/4      gls   c       2sbk: mff  Cc           120--150     7.5 YR 5/4      gls   c       2m; mfi, cs    Gleysols  Of              2--0  A              0--6        10 YR 3/1      sl    f       lsbK; wss-wp  Ag             6--18      10 YR 3/1      sl    m      2sbk;  Bl            18--26      7.5 YR 5/6(w)   Is    m      2sbk; ws-mfi  B2g           26--55      2.5 YR 6/2      sl    m      3bk  (N4/0)  B3g           55--69        5 YR 3/1      sil   e       2m; mfr  C             69--         10 YR 4/3      sl    vf      wsp-mfi    Organic Soils,  Aj             0--22      10 YR 2/2      sil   f       lsg; wso-mfr  Of          22--40     2.5 YR 2/2                    wss (H4)  Om          40--55      2.5 YR N2/0                    ws (H5)  Oh            55--117     2.5 YR 3/2                       (5-6)  Cj           117--         10 YR 3/2      asil  m      3sbk; ws    losses on ignition are always the most acidic. The cation exchange capacity  ranges from 23 me,/100 g in Regosols to 82 me./100 g in organic soils. The  average base saturation is about 20% and the exchange complex is dominated  by H but Ca and Mg are also significant. Extremely high values for Na were  found in several profiles, particularly in windy sites near coasts, although all  sites in the archipelago are less than 2--3 km from a coast.    236    TABLE II    Results of some physical and chemical analyses of Faeroe Island soils (&lt; 2 mm)    Horizon      Depth        Particle-         Organic         pH  (cm)         size (%)*        matter (%)       0.01n    sa   si    cl    C       LoI     CaCI2    Regosols*  Om             8--0       45   52   3             47.0    4.8  A               0--19      48   47   5     8.7    25.5    5.2  Clh         19--32                          38.7   5.0  C2c         40--50     55  43   2    6.5   26.3   5.3  C2c           50--62      53   43   4     3.4    12.2    5.5    Brunisols  Oh  AI    Bh    4--0               65      35      0           5.2         27.1         5.16  0--20             72       28      0           5.4         31.9         5.39  20--43      21   79   0             46.9    4.87  43--75             43       54       0           4.6         27.5        4.55  75--95      72   25   3     3.7    22.5    3.74  95--103          86       13      0           4.2        22.1         4.24    Podzols  Al  Aej  Bli  B2c  B3c  Cc    0--20             51       42      7                          11.6        4.4  20--35             55      41       4           2.0           6.6        4.9  35--36      66   32   2     0.3     5.1    5.1  36--87             76       24       0           0.4           5.3         5.3  87--120          79       21       0           0.2           6.5         5.5  120--150     85   15   0     0.0     5.4    5.5    Gleysols  A  Ag  Blg  B2g  B3g  C    4--0       43   51   6    10.5    19.3    4.7  0--17                        6.7    17.0    4.7  17--26             51       41       8           3.3         11.5        4.9  26--55      48   47   5             33.9    5.1  55--69             48      46       8                          25.8        4.9  69--        52   45   3             12.8    5.0    Organic Soils    0--22                     36.2  4.6  22--40                               63.3    4.2  40--55                                80.1    4.5  55--117                                                             98.5        4.5    *As many soils, and in particular Regosols may contain high amounts of gravel it must be  emphasized that these results will greatly exaggerate whole soil values. LoI = Loss on  ignition to 375; sa = 2000--50 u; si = 50--2 ~, cl ~ 2 a.    237    Exchange cations (me./lO0 g)*    BS    Na     K    Ca    Mg    C.E.C.  (%)    1.8  1.3  1.1  0.7  1.7    1.1  0.7  0.4  0.4  1.0    1.5    0.8     58.0     9  1.3  0.6   56.O   7  1.5    0.9     57.9     7  1.1         1.6           33.2        11  1.3        0.3           30.6         14    3.9  3.6  3.4  6.7  3.3  4.5    1  1.3  1.3  1.3  1.3  1.0    3.6   1.5   35.2   29  4.8    3.3     39.8    33  3.9        3.9           47.5        26  4.8    2.0     38.3    39  3.9    3.3     41.7    28  2.9    1.4     30.7    32    1.9           0.7              1.1         1.9           35.4  1.1           0.6             1.2        1.4           21.7  2.1     1.1       8.9    7.7     29.3  4.4     2.2      4.5    6.6     35.5  1.2     0.6     10.0            38.3  2.1   0.6   19.5    15  26  22  56    2.8           1.2             3.9        6.9           38.8        38  2.3           0.9             2.2        3.5           36.8        25  1.2     0.7      1.1    1.5     26.0    19  1.7           0.3             1.0        1.8           25.9         19  2.2           0.5             1.2        2.0           34.9        17  2.0     0.7       1.7    2.0     28.4    23    1.5     0.5      2.6    0.8     58.5     9  1.1           0.2             1.5        0.5           59.2           5  1.7           0.1              4.2        0.9           81.7         24  1.8           0.1              5.0        0.9           80.5         23    238    The description and grouping of the Faeroe Islands soils is based on profile  descriptions. The soils have been classified at Great Soil Group level using the  Canadian system of soil classification (Table III; Canadian Soil Survey Com-  mittee, 1978)J    TABLE III    Soil classification systems  Canadian system       U.S.D.A. system (1975)    Great Soil Group  Regosols  Brunisols  Podsols  Gleysols  Organic Soils    Great Group  Cryorthents  Mainly Fragiorthods, some Udipsamments  Placaquepts, Fragihumods  Fragiaquepts  Medihemists    Regosols    Regosols have thick, fine-sandy, turf surface horizons over moderately to  imperfectly drained mineral materials on steep convex slopes and broken topo-  graphy. Much of the area of Regosols is devoid of vegetation as a result of the  removal of peat for fuel, over-grazing by sheep, unstable geomorphic condi-  tions, violent wind and fluvial erosion or a combination of two or more of  these.  Regosols are characterized by gravelly sandy loam textures with high silt  and very low clay contents (0--5%). They are strongly acidic and have very  high organic matter contents similar to other soil groups in the islands. The  CEC is high considering the skeletal nature of the soils, but the base saturation  is extremely low: less than 1/4 that of apparently similar soils in Iceland  (Johannesson, 1960). Organically bouud and amorphous iron may attain sig-  nificant dimensions.    BRUNISOLS    The Brunisols occur in well to moderately well drained sites, from sea level  to 400 m a.s.1. Thick 1Lo thin organic horizons overlie dark brown to black  sandy loam mineral surface horizons and very dark brown to yellowish brown  sandy loam to sandy clay loam subsurface horizons. Field textures are con-  sistently more clayey than laboratory analyses suggest. Upper mineral hori-  zons have weakly expressed subangular structure which may persist to depth.     Detailed information on the chemical, physical and mineralogical properties of the soils  and on their landscape distribution may be obtained from the senior author.    239    Bh horizons occur in many profiles and in some the B horizon is very com-  pact. Yet other profiles exhibit yellowish brown subsoils. C horizons may be  thin to relatively thick and mottled. Soils with characteristics similar to some  of these profiles have been described in upland areas in Scotland (Romans  and Robertson, 1974). On some upland plateau areas, over frost-shattered  bedrock and undifferentiated till, Brunisols have gravelly silt loam surface  horizons with stone polygons and soil stripes overlying dark grayish brown  horizons which become yellow brown with depth (Fig.3). These appear to be  similar to Artic Brown soils of well drained periglacial areas (Tedrow, 1977).    Fig. 3. Stone stripes on Brunisols at 350 m a.s.1, on Esturoy.    These Brunisolic soils also exhibit similarities to soils in comparable sites in the  Orkney and Shetland Islands (F. Dry, personal communication, 1976). The  clay content of these soils is generally insignificant with sand constituting  more than 50% and silt about 30%. Loss on ignition in the mineral horizons is  commonly greater than 25%, and they have somewhat acidic reactions. CEC  ranges from 24 to 50 me./100 g and base saturation from 6 to 40%. Whereas  sodium may dominate the exchangeable bases, calcium and magnesium to-  gether are most common. Illuviation of Fe, A1 and Mn into the B horizons is  not apparent in all profiles (Table IV) but in soils with arctic polygon forma-  tion very clear increases in extractable Fe, A1 and Mn were recorded with  depth.    240    TABLE IV    Contents of extractable Fe, AI and Mn in some soiJs of the Faeroe Islands    Horizon     Depth           Fed      Feo       Fep      Aid       Alo       Alp       Mnd      Mno  (era)          (%)     (%)     (%)     (%)     (%)     (%)     (Ppm)   (ppm)    Regosols  Om           8--0         1.92     1,00     1,20     1,56     2,58              160       68  A              0--19         2,08      1,08      0,68      1,46      3,18                140        42  Clh          19--32       3,52     3,18     2,05     2,04     2,68               69      19  C2c         40--50       4,52     0,52     1,56     0,14     3,20               75      80  C2          50--62       1.00     0,18     0,31     0,46     1,28               45    Brunisols  Oh               4--0            1.68       1,36       1,04      1,32       2,62                    55       110  AI                            0--20                  1078            1,62            1,70            1,66            2,40                                 280             165  20--43         2,80      1,82      1,38      1,40      1,22  Bh                         43--75                   2.22            1.83            1.80            1.39            1.62                                   90             180  75--95                   2.00            1.50            1.02            1.24            1.50                                    80             195  95--108                  0.94            0.85            0.84            1.08            2.32                                                         20    Podzols  A1            0--20       1.10     0.76     0.52     0.62     0.94     0.58      34      10  Aej          20--35       1,48     0,96     0,72     0,40     1,00     0,64      35       6  Bli           35--36        0,68     0,40     0,50     0,22     0,82     0,20       35       13  B2e          36--87        0,68     0,42     0,20     0,20     1,20     0.20       35        6  B3e          87--120       4,92     1,70     0,03     0,14     0,62     0,14     120       60  Cc           120--150       0,80     0,20     0,06     0,08     0,42     0,08       80       26    Gleysols  A               4----0          1.30      0.90      1.00      0.58      0.64                            60  Ag             0--17         4.20      2.62      0.76      0.84      0.76  Big            17--26         1.20      0.80      0.48      0.64      1.30                            11  B2g           26--55         2.20      1.38      1.27      3.32      4.78  B3g           55--69         0.48      0.34      0.38      2.72      2.06                            18  C             69--            1.08      0.40      0.42      0.76      0.78                             4    Organic soils  0--22         1.62      1.04      1.40      1.44      2.70                120      420  22--40         2.28      1.80      1.64      1,60      1.75                180  40--55         0.98      0.40      0.62      0.38      0.40                690      I00  55--177        0.90      0.41      0.62      0.32      0.56                300      150  d = dithionitc; o = oxalate', p = pyrophosphate.    Podzols    Podzols have thick organic layers overlying dark brown sandy to silt loam  mineral horizons. The presence of a thin, often strongly convoluted, ironpan  (Fig. 4) immediately under the upper mineral horizons is characteristic of these  soils, below which the horizons are brown or yellowish brown. There is a light  coloured and slightly to moderately compact incipient Ae horizon and the B  horizon is mottled. Bog iron ore may occur. The Podzols occur on gently  sloping upland surfaces on tills and colluvium under 100 m a.s.1. The total  solum is usually less than 65 cm thick. The Podzols are strongly acidic in the  upper horizons and commonly become markedly less acid with depth: pH of  5.5 in a C horizon was the highest measured in the islands. Clay contents are  less than 5% and sand usually ranges from 60 to 80% although in several    241    Fig. 4. Strongly convolu*~ed, thin ironpan de-,eloped in a Podzol.    profiles the deeper horizons contained substantially more silt than sand. The  organic matter content of the mineral horizons is the lowest for any group in  the islands. Values for Fed, Feo, Fep, Ald and Alo are lower than for most  other mineral soils but they increase sharply below the ironpan horizon.    Gleysols    Gleysols display a variety of morphologies but mostly occur as gray, mediun  to fine zx~,ared, surface mineral horizons high in organic matter grading into  gleyed, brown, loamy sand subsoils. Organic staining and manganiferrous con-  cretions may occur in the B2g horizons {subsoils}. Humose surface and peaty  layers commonly overlie gray mineral horizons. There may be a dense, black,  organic layer at the bedrock contact in shallow profiles of this group. The  soils usually occur in poorly drained sites on backslopes of cirques and low  lying regions adjacent to organic soils up to about 400 m a.s.1.  The clay content is higher.in these soils than any other group, ranging from  5 to 8%, and although organic matter is relatively low it increases significantly  in the B2g horizon. Exchangeable Mg is quite high in surface horizons (3.53  me./100 g} followed by high values for Na and Ca. Surface inundation by  runoff from higher slopes may account for the cation levels in the A horizon.  Extractable Fe and A1 values in the B2g horizon are significantly lower than  those in the hori'.:ons above and below.    242    Organic soils    Soils in the Faeroe Islands having organic surface layers of 40 cm or more  in thickness, with at least 30% organic matter have been classed as Organic  Soils. On the scale devised by yon Post and Granlund (1926), these soils range  from weakly decomposed (H3) to well decomposed (H6) peats, and have high  amounts of fibric and mesic materials. The mineral fraction is erratically dis-  tributea through the profiles as lenses and sedimentary layers or merely  dispersed through the organic material. The size composition of the mineral  fraction is commonly about 30% fine sand, 50% silt and 20% clay-sized  materials. The organic horizons overlie gray, gravelly, loamy sand subsoils  and are waterlogged most of the year. This soil group is found from sea level  to over 700 m a.s.1.  These are the most acid soils in the islands with the highest cation ex-  change capacities. Base saturation is less than 10% in the surface layers and  becomes greater than 20% with depth. Sodium is highest among exchangeable  bases with calcium significantly higher than magnesium. Extractable Fe and  A1 are significantly higher in the surface than in deeper horizons, whereas  extractable Mn is usually very high, indeed the highest values measured in the  Faeroe Islands. In some profiles, however, the extractable Mn values were the  lowest measured in the soils of the islands.    Soil microscopy    The micromorphology of the soils of the Faeroe Islands is typical of soils  with modest pedogenetic development: fabrics comprise subangular skeletal  grains of very uneven size distribution, randomly set in a somewhat homo-  geneous s-matrix. They have mainly porphyroskelic related distribution pat-  terns with minor agglomeroplasmic in some Brunisols. Most thin sections  have isotic plasmic fabrics, with silasepic in some B horizons and minor skelin-  sepic in an eluviated Podzol horizon.  The soils are characterised by large amounts of void space consisting of an  intricate system of interconnected and mammillated vughs and channels. In  plain light, organic matter commonly appears as black to reddish brown  nodules around skeletal grains. In Podzolic Ae and Aej horizons, fine pellety  amorphous organic matter loosely binds mineral grains. No true cutans were  observed although in Podzols, subcutanic features resembling diffusion cutans  composed of sesquioxides, manganese or organic matter occur throughout the  solum. Sesquioxidic glaebules in the s-matrix around old root channels are  common in Gleysols.    SOIL/LANDSCAPE RELATIONSHIPS    Although the Faeroe islands are small in area, they are rugged and moun-  tainous so the soils exhibit a moderate range in characteristics. At altitudes    243    above 400 m, the landscape is usually steep and strongly exposed to wind and  water erosion. Regosols are by far the most common soils, although some  Brunisols occur in better drained sites on cirque floors and Organic Soils in  the poorly drained plateau areas of considerable extent between 300 m and  400 m. In the flat and gently rolling areas, Brunisols, both with and without  various forms of patterned ground, are most common. Gleysols and Organic  Soils occur in the depressions and Regosols occur on the steeper slopes.  In the glaciated valleys and valley floors below 300 m, Podzols occur on  gentle slopes, Brunisols in similar but less well drained sites, Gleysols in, inor  depressions, Organic Soils in basins and Regosols on the steep slopes.    CONCLUDING REMARKS    The softs of the Faeroe Islands are formed from a fairly homogeneous  basalt parent material rich in iron and bases under humid and cool to cold  conditions. The soil-forming processes and the short time through which these  have functioned have produced soil profiles with limited morphological dif-  ferences but which nevertheless may be classified into five Great Soil Groups  of the Canadian system.  Soils in sites at lower elevations are constantly receiving suspended and  dissolved materials from higher ones which affect the course of pedcgenesis  in such soils. Wind erosion is also an important agent in the distribution of  particles and dissolved cations over the land surface.  The soils of the Faeroe Islands are high in silt and low in clay-size particles,  something recorded in many soils of northern latitudes (Rieger, 1966; Helga-  son, 1963, 1968; Bouma et al., 1969}. The soils have high cation exchange  capacities and low base saturation. The porphyritic Lower Lava tends to be  more resistant than the equigranular Middle Lava so that soils developed on  the former are significantly shallower and coarser textured than those on the  latter.  Despite the cool climate and modest time since deglaciation there 9xe some  weathering zones and weathered rocks in till that are so altered that they may  be sliced with a spade. This evidence, although limited, suggests that chemical  weathering has proceeded quite substantially, Further clay mineral evidence  (senior author) indicates that chlorite minerals are common although chlorite  was found to be entirely absent from the parent rock materials. Similar  weathered regoliths are reported from high altitudes in Scotland.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    The authors wish to express their appreciation to many friends on the  Faeroe Islands for their hospitali~,~ and unlimited kindness. Particular thanks  to resident geologist Dr. J. Rasmussen and the Rigsombudsmanden, Leif  Groth. Appreciation is also due to Messrs. J.C.C. Romans, and F. Dry, mem-  bers of the Soil Survey of Scotland at Aberdeen and Kirkwall respectively.    244    A grant from the Science Division of NATO in Brussels made the field work  possible.    REFERENCES    Borgenson, F., 1902. Gardening and tre~ planting. In: C.H. Ostenfeld (Editor), Botany of  the Faeroes, Based upon Danish Investigations. London, pp.1028--1043.  Bouma, J., Van der Plas, L. and Van Scherrenburg, B., 1969. Genesis and morphology of  some Alpine Podzol profiles. J. Soil Sci., 20: 385--398.  Brewer, R., 1964 Fabric and Mineral Analysis of Soils. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 437 pp.  Brown, I.C., 1943. A rapid method of determining exchangeable hydrogen and total ex-  changeable bases in soils. Soil Sci., 56: 353--357.  Canadian Soil Survey Committee, 1978. The Canadian System of Soil Classification. Can.  Dept. Agric. Publ., 1646:164 pp.  Day, P.R., 1965. Particle fractionation and particle-size analysis. In: C.A. Black (Editor),  Methods of Soil Analysis, 9 (1). Agronomy. American Society of Agronomy, Madison,  Wisc.  Helgason, B., 1963. Basaltic soils in southwest Iceland. J. Soil Sci., 14 (1): 64--72.  Helgason, B., 1968. Basaltic soils of Southwest Iceland, II. J. Soil Sci., 19 (1): 127--134.  Johannesson, B., 1960. The soils of Iceland. Univ. Res. Inst., Dep. Agric. Rep., Ser. B,  13:141 pp.  MeKeague, A. and Day, J.H., 1966. Dithionite and oxalate extractable iron and aluminum  as aids in differentiating various classes of soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 46: 13--22.  Rasmussen, J., 1963. Recent studies on the Faeroes. In: North Atlantic Brota and their  History. Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp. 29--44.  Rasmussen, J. and Noe-Nygaard, A., 1970. Geology of the Faeroe Islands (Prequaternary).  Translated by G. Henderson, Geol. Surv. Denmark Ser. 1(25): 139 pp.  Rieger, S., 1966. Tundra soils in western Alaska. J. Soil Sci., 17(2): 264--273.  Romans, J.C.C. and Robertson, L., 1974. Some aspects of the genesis of alpine and upland  soils in the British Isles. In: G.K. Rutherford (Editor), Proceedings of Fourth Working-  Meeting on Soil Micromorph. Limestone Press, Kingston, Ont., pp. 498--510.  Soil Survey Staff., 1975. Soil Taxonomy. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook, 436: U.S. Gov.  Printing Office, Washington, D.C. 754 pp.  Tarling, D.H. and Gale, N.H., 1968. Isotopic dating and Palaeomagnetic polarity in the  Faeroe Islands. Nature, 218: 1043--1066.  Tedrow, R.F.C., 1977. Soils of the Polar Landscapes. Rutgers University Press, N.J., 638 pp.  Von Post, L. and Granlund, E., 1926. SSndra Sveriges torvtillg~nger, 1. Sveriges Geol.  UndersSkn. Arsbok. Ser. C., Avhandl. Uppsat., 336:172 pp.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            AbstractThe soils of the Faeroe Islands are developed from fairly homogeneous basalt parent materials under humid and cool to cold conditions. The soil-forming processes and short time through which these have functioned have produced soil profiles which may be classified as Regosols, Brunisols, Podzols, Gleysols and Organic Soils in the Canadian system of soil classification. The soils are continuously moist or wet and generally have thick organic horizons. The mineral portion is high in silt and low in clay-sized particles. The soils are strongly acidic with high cation exchange capacities (23 to 82 me./100 g) and low base saturations (20%): sodium of marine origin may be a dominant exchangeable cation. Podzols may have convoluted iron pans and some Brunisols exhibit stone stripes and polygons. Weathered pseudomorph regoliths and boulders occur. 