Geoderma, 27 (1982) 335--347                                                     335  Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company, Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    A1-SUBSTITUTED GOETHITE--AN INDICATOR OF PEDOGENIC AND  OTHER WEATHERING ENVIRONMENTS IN SOUTH AFRICA    R.W. FITZPATRICK and U. SCHWERTMANN  Soil and Irrigation Research Institute, P/Bag X 79, Pretoria (Republic of South Africa)  Institut fiir Bodenkunde, Technische Universita't M~nchen, 8050 Freising-Weihenstephan  (FRG)  (Received June 6, 1981; accepted October 28, 1981)    ABSTRACT    Fitzpatrick, R.W. and Schwertmann, U., 1982. Al-substituted goethite--an indicator of  pedogenic and other weathering environments in South Africa. Geoderma, 27 : 335--347.    Over 200 goethite-containing samples from widely diverse environments along the  eastern seaboard of South Africa were examined and described, mainly by X-ray powder  diffraction (XRD).  Aluminium-substituted goethites ranging from 0 to about 32 mole % AIOOH were  identified mainly by XRD line-shift and chemical extraction. They occur in every soil  zone and major soil type in one or other form from sources such as: (1) non-hydromor-  phic highly weathered (strongly acid soils, ferruginous bauxites, saprolites) and moderate-  ly weathered (moderately acid soils) environments; (2) hydromorphic environments  (mottles, concretions, pipe stems, crusts, ferricretes, geodes); and (3) crusts in calcare-  ous environments. These goethites, formed in different climatic and weathering environ-  ments, were grouped according to their amount of Al-substitution and crystallinity (as  determined by XRD line broadening). Al-substitution in goethite formed in hydromor-  phic, moderately acid soils and calcareous environments was generally low (0--15 mole  % ). Goethite formed in non-hydromorphic highly weathered environments was generally  high in Al-substitution (15--32 mole % ) and increased in the following order: saprolites  and strongly acid, freely drained soils &lt; ferruginous bauxites &lt; strongly acid soils overly-  ing plinthite.  This study showed that the degree of Al-substitution and crystallinity of goethites  may reflect the environment in which they have formed and serve as an indicator of soil-  forming processes.    INTRODUCTION    Goethite is b:y far the most widespread form of pedogenic iron oxide  (Schwertmann and Taylor, 1977) and is the main yellow-brown pigment in  soils and other weathering environments. Consequently, it may originate and  persist in widely diverse environments, ranging from temperate to tropical  regions (Schwertmann et al., 1974). Furthermore, it has been reported in  nature to occur in association with hematite, maghemite and lepidocrocite.    0016-7061/82/0000--0000/$02.75 1982 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company    336    So far, little specific attention has been paid to occurrence, properties and  function of goethite in South African soils (Fitzpatrick, 1974, 1978b).  Diverse environmental conditions along the eastern seaboard of South Africa  have given rise to a great variety of sesquioxidic soils (Fitzpatrick, 1978b),  containing a wide range of pedogenic iron-rich accumulations (e.g., ferri-  cretes, concretions, ferruginous bauxites, etc.) most of which contain goethite  as a dominant Fe-oxide.  The variability of goethite can be described by crystallinity and degree  of substitution of Al for Fe in the structure. The latter phenomenon was  observed by Correns and Von Engelhardt (1941) and has subsequently been  described for soil goethites in various areas (Beneslavsky, 1957; Norrish and  Taylor, 1961; Davey et al., 1975; Nahon et al., 1977; Torrent et al., 1980).  The conditions under which A1 enters the goethite structure have been ex-  tensively studied in synthetic media by Thiel (1963) and Jonas and Solymar  (1970) and more recently by Taylor and Schwertmann (1978) and Lewis  and Schwertmann (1979a, b). Although the high stability of goethite in soils  has been attributed mainly to its inherent structural and thermodynamic  stability (Schwertmann and Taylor, 1977), isomorphous substitution of Al  for Fe may also account for this stability, possibly by releasing structural  strain.  With exception of Kiihnel et al. (1975) and Nahon et al. (1977), very  little work has been done in relating crystaUinity and Al-substitution in  goethite, respectively, to different kinds of pedogenic conditions.  For these reasons, a detailed study of goethites from a variety of weather-  ing environments and pedoclimates along the eastern seaboard of South  Africa appears worthwhile. The aims of this paper are to determine the  variability in the AI substitution and crystaUinity of goethite as a function  of pedogeochemical environment.    STUDY AREA    The eastern seaboard of South Africa contains many sharply divergent  landforms (King, 1967; Fitzpatrick, 1978b). Within 200 km the vegetative  cover changes from coastal forest (Coast Lowlands), to Acacia savanna in  the incised river valleys (Riverine and dryer Basin Plainlands), to Afro-  alpine grassland at an altitude over 3000 m (Lesotho Plateau). The com-  plexity of soil forming factors in the area results in a varied but repetitive  pattern of a large number of different soils (Van der Eyk et al., 1969;  Fitzpatrick, 1978b), which partly conforms with the present-day bioclimate  of the area but may also be representative of periods during which pre-  weathering and colluviation of parent materials took place (De Villiers,  1964).    337    MATERIALS    Natural samples    During a 5-year reconnaissance soil survey over 200 samples suspected of  containing goethite (i.e., as suggested by yellow-brown colours ranging  mainly between 7.5YR to 10YR) were collected from a wide range of  pedogenic materials, altitudinal sequences and soil environments. For the  purpose of this study these samples were grouped according to their origin  and morphology, into goethite from:  (1) non-hydromorphic highly weathered [strongly acid --pH {H20) &lt; 5.2  -- soils, ferruginous bauxites, saprolites] and moderately weathered environ-  ments [moderately acid -- pH (H20) 5.2--6.0 -- soils], and  (2) hydromorphic environments {mottles, concretions, pipe stems, crusts,  ferricretes).  Details regarding the distribution and morphology of the samples and  their mineralogical and chemical properties cannot be given here; the readers  are referred to Fitzpatrick (1978b). Relevant features will be mentioned in  the section 'Results and discussion'.    Synthetic samples    In order to provide an adequate range for comparison with natural samples,  synthetic goethites of differing Al-substitution were also prepared. Freshly  precipitated ferrihydrite was prepared by adding, dropwise over 3 h at room  temperature, an equivalent amount of Fe(III)-chloride (AR) to 250 ml of 2  M KOH with rapid stirring. Mixed Fe--A1 coprecipitates were prepared in  the same manner, except that 5 and 10 mole % A1C13 (AR) replaced Fe in  the initial solution. The precipitates were then kept in 0.2 M KOH at 60C in  polyethylene bottles for 30 days, then dialyzed exhaustively against distilled  water.    METHODS    Sample pretreatment    In cemented iron-rich samples the concentration of goethite was high  enough to be easily detected by XRD without pretreatment. Samples (frag-  ments} were finely ground by hand in an agate mortar to pass a 300-mesh  sieve and used as such. Weakly cemented, friable samples with high amounts  of quartz were first lightly ground by hand in an agate mortar. Heavy grind-  ing was avoided wherever possible so as not to pulverize quartz. The clay  (&lt; 2 pm) fraction was separated after 10--15 min of an ultrasonic treatment  by repeating settling in dilute aqueous suspension.  Samples in which kaolinite and/or gibbsite predominated {i.e., 50--90%)    338    were weakly ground, soaked overnight in water or 0.0003 M NaOH and then  treated ultrasonically for 10--20 min. The clay (&lt; 2 #m)-fraction was  separated from all samples as well as the fine clay (&lt; 0.2 pm) from selected  samples by centrifugation (Jackson, 1968).  Strongly ferromagnetic particles were separated from the suspensions by  three successive extractions with a small horseshoe magnet. The dispersed  soil clay and bauxite samples were then either freeze-dried or dried on a  water bath and lightly ground using an agate mortar. To concentrate the Fe-  oxides all soil clays and bauxites (except the Fe-rich rinds on bauxite nodules)  were pretreated with 5 M NaOH for 1 h at 90C (method similar to that of  Norrish and Taylor, 1961) in order to selectively dissolve kaolinite and  gibbsite.    Chemical extractions    Oxalate (Fe0) (Schwertmann, 1964) and citrate bicarbonate dithionite  (CBD) (Mehra and Jackson, 1960) extractable Fe (Fed)' Mn (Mnd) and A1  (Ald) were determined on selected samples. Strongly cemented samples  (~ 100 mg) were extracted with 5 ml boiling 5 M HC1 for 5--10 min. The  extracts were analyzed for Fe, Mn and A1 by atomic absorption.    X-ray diffraction    XRD analysis, using a Philips PW 1050/70 instrument with CoKa radia-  tion and a graphite monochromator, was conducted on all pretreated samples  by pressing the dry powder gently into aluminium or PVC holders against a  filter paper surface. Patterns were run at a rate of 1/4per min over the ap-  propriate range. The spacings and widths at half height (WHH; corrected for  instrumental line broadening) of the (110) and (111) goethite peaks were  determined graphically. An amount of lead nitrate between 10--20% was  added occasionally as an internal standard for the measurements of the (111)  spacings of goethite (Norrish and Taylor, 1961).    RESULTS AND DISCUSSION    General relationships between d-spacing, Al-substitution and crystallinity of  goethites    The Fed values of the samples range between 4 and 51% Fe. Except for  soil clays from the soils of the Afro-alpine zone, the Feo/Fed ratio is less  than 0.1, usually even lower. This suggests that goethite, hematite and other  Fe(III) oxides rather than ferrihydrite are present. In all 200 samples goethite  was identified by its strongest XRD-line (110), but also by the (111) and  (130) lines, except in soils of the Afro-alpine zone where these were too weak  to be measured. Furthermore, where hematite or lepidocrocite was present,  the (130) and (111) lines, respectively, could not be measured.    339    The d(111) and d(130) spacings obtained for pure synthetic goethite are  2.452 and 2.698 A, respectively, the latter being slightly larger than that  given by the ASTM card index No.17-536 but agreeing fairly well with the  work of Thiel (1963), Jonas and Solymar (1970) and Golden (1978).  In several samples (soil clays, bauxites, saprolites) the Al-substitution, as  estimated from A1 extracted by CBD or HC1, was higher before than after  NaOH pretreatment (Fig.l). This is probably due to the extraction of some  A1 from other sources. After pretreatment with 5 M NaOH the relationship  between the A1 extracted by CBD or HC1 (e.g. ferricretes) and the d(lll)  spacing is in good agreement with the line joining d(ll 1) of goethite and  diaspore (Vegard line) (Fig.l). Furthermore, the data for synthetic Al-sub-  stituted samples (i.e., 6 and 10 mole % AlOOH) also fall on this line. There-  fore only the values after NaOH treatment should be used for the "calibra-  tion curve" (Fig.l).  The high amounts of A1d in soil clays from Transvaal and Natal (Fitzpatrick,  1974, p.119; Fey and Le Roux, 1976, 1977) which are not matched by the  XRD line shift and would lead to an A1 substitution in excess of 33 mole %,  might be high for the same reason. The possibility of explaining this shift  by some loss of goethite A1 through the NaOH treatment can not be ruled  out (K~[mpf and Schwertmann, 1982).  The Vegard line was then used for determining the degree of Al-substitu-  tion in the goethites using the equations: d(lll) = 2.452--0.001377 (A1  mole %) and d(130) = 2.698--0.00146 (A1 mole %). These relationships  differ from various experimental calibration curves (Thiel, 1963; Jonas and  Solymar, 1970; Golden, 1978) probably because of the non-Vegard behavi-  our of the a-parameter of the unit cell (Schulze*, pers. comm.). Besides the  (111) line, a shift due to Al-substitution is also measurable with the (110)  line so that a correlation exists between the positions of these two lines  (Fig.2). Therefore, in those cases where the (111 ) line is not measurable, the  position of the (110) line can be used to estimate the Al-substitution with  the aid of this relation.  Some confirmation of these Al-substitution values comes from MSssbauer  measurements by Golden (1978) on two identical samples (Fitzpatrick, 1974,  1978b, p.59). On the basis of a linear decrease of the internal magnetic  field Heft with increasing Al-substitution in synthetic goethites at 77 K  [Heft = 500--1.77 (A1 mole %)], Golden (1978) arrived at 28 and 24 mole  % At-substitution as compared to 25 and 19 mole % in this study.  Histograms for most of the samples analysed (Fig.3) indicate a range in A1-  substitution between 0 and about 32 mole % A1OOH. These data refute a  recent statement by Nahon et al. (1977) that "lower substitu'tion rates  (3--10%) are certainly known but they concern a type of Al-goethite little  represented in nature".  In Fig.4, the width of the (111) line at half height (WHH) as an index for    *]nstitut filr Bodenkunde, T.U., Miinchen, Freising-Weihenstephan (FRG).    340    .&lt;[  E    2.45~,,  2,44          ~,    2./+3'    2,42    \  \  ',\  \  \,    Lbne jOln5 ~he d(1!II         x       x  spoclflg of goethJte and d,clspors  2,~I       ib      2'0      3'0  At subsfituh0h (m0Jeo)  Fig.l. Relationships between d(111 ) and Al-substitution of goethites as determined by  CBD or HCI. The subscripts I, 2 and 3 refer to untreated samples (1), treatment with 5 M  NaOH on water bath for 1 h (2), and treatment with 5M NaOH at 90 for 1 h (3). For  symbols, see Fig.2.    2,45-    2,44.     2,/~3-    2,~2"  x  M  2,~1  /,,14    v  Ax  x xx x  x         ~     ~  x                      x  +           +   x  x      x              x       K w  o      Ax       xx   8         &amp;             o   o.  A~ x    za   +  +          ~v     ',ls     &lt;16      119      12o  Fig.2. Relationships between position of the d(111 ) and d(110) of goethite for 183  samples (y = 0.742,x-0.656; r -- 0.884;P &lt; 10-3).  = synthetic goethites; = geodes; o = concretions; ~ = pipe stems; + = saprolites; V =  mottles and bands; * = calcareous environments; a = ferricretes; * = crusts; = ferruginous  bauxites; x = soil clays.    341    ,~ non hydromorphJc  strongty ood so~ts  L--~   non-hydromorphff- moderetety  (Iod sods     ferruglnous   bauxites     ~ ~ saprohtes  ~'  ~ Fr/~ I~ mottles ,~ bonds      ~ concrehons  "6  .~  geodes  Scale    ~ ~ plpesfems                   Ic  /~~  ferrlcretes  F///////~ (o[coreous envlronmenls  0        S        10       15      20      25       30  At subshtuhon Imote %} in goefhlte  Fig.3. Frequency distribution of Al-substitution in 183 goethites from various environments.                                       ~     A   ~,0   o.5  c,     ~ xz~  0  ....  i  ....  ,  ....  i  ....  ,  ....  i  ....  T  ,  ,  0          5         10         15        20        25        30  AI substitution (mole %)  Fig.4. Relationships between width at half height of the (111) line and Al-substitution  of 183 goethites from various environments (r = 0.51 ; P &lt; 0.001). Symbols as in Fig.2.  A = Humic A-horizons of strongly acid red and yellow-brown soils; B '-- B-horizons of  strongly acid red and yellow-brown soils; C = ferruginous bauxites; D = saprolites.  crystallinity of the goethite is plotted against Al-substitution for 183 samples.  A weak (r = 0.51) but significant (P &lt; 10-3) correlation exists for all the  samples but not within each group of samples. No such relationship was  found if the width of the (110) instead of (111) line were used although a  correlation exists between the positions of the two lines (Fig.2).    342    Goethites from non-hydromorphic environments    These goethites may be grouped (Fig.3) into: (1) strongly acid (dystrophic*)  red and yellow-brown soils with and without plinthite in the subsoil; (2) Afro-  alpine yellow-brown soils (not included in Fig.3);(3) moderately acid (meso-  trophic) red soils; (4) ferruginous bauxites; and (5) saprolites.  Soils with strongly acid (dystrophic) red and yellow-brown B horizons  which overly either a friable mottled horizon (plinthite) or ferricrete (Plin-  thic Haplorthox) occur mainly on relatively old land surfaces in the Plateau  (Highveld) and Basin Plainland regions (Fitzpatrick, 1974, 1978b; Van der  Eyk et al., 1969). They are derived mainly from sandstones and shales and  occur mostly on midslopes in a gently undulating topography.  The goethites in the red and yellow-brown B horizons of these soils from  various localities show the highest Al-substitution (up to ~ 32% ). This may  be due to a high degree of weathering creating a high Al-availability. Deviat-  ing from the highly Al-substituted goethite in the yellow B2 horizons is the  goethite within the hematitic red mottles of the plinthite in which the A1-  substitution is much lower (~ 15%). This could mean that the goethite in  the mottles was formed during an earlier period of soil formation under  hydromorphic conditions which caused the mottling. As shown later, hydro-  morphically formed goethite has less Al-substitution.  Soils with strongly acid (dystrophic) red (Umbriorthox, Haplohumox ) and  yellow-brown (Haplorthox) B horizons which generally overlie deeply  weathered saprolite or bauxite occur on old land surfaces, ranging from  gentle to steep slopes in the Highland/Montane and Mistbelt areas (Fitz-  patrick, 1978b; Van der Eyk et al., 1969). The majority of samples from  non-hydromorphic environments belong to the B horizons of this group of  soils in which the Al-substitution in goethite ranges between 15--25 mole %  A1. Low pH's in these highly weathered soils produce A1 which is easily  available for incorporation in the goethite structure. Goethites in A-horizons  of humic phases (&gt; 3%C) of these soils show a lower crystallinity (as indicat-  ed in the WHH) than those from horizons with lower C contents (A in Fig.4).  This could be due to organic matter impeding the crystallization of goethite  (Schwertmann, 1966).  The yellow-brown soils of the Afro-alpine zone (Cryumbrepts) occur at  altitudes above 2280 m with higher pH (5.2--6.1 in KC1), base saturation  (eutrophic) and carbon contents (3--8% C) than the other soils under dis-  cussion and are weakly developed, having been formed under a cooler,  carbon-preserving climate in periglacial conditions (Fitzpatrick, 1978a).  They contain very poorly crystalline goethite with intermediate Al-substitu-    *Refers to the degree of base status and is expressed as the sum of the exchangeable cations  in me/100 g clay, where: less than 5 = dystrophic, 5--15 = mesotrophic, and greater than  15 = eutrophic.    343    ~ion. The same explanation applies as to the humic phases of the non-hydro-  morphic soils discussed above.  The moderately acid (mesotrophic) red soils (Rhodoxeralfs) occur at  lower altitudes and under somewhat drier conditions (Riverine). Their re-  latively lower rate of desilicification is supported by the presence or domi-  nance of smectite and vermiculite rather than kaolinite and by the absence  of gibbsite (Fitzpatrick, 1978b). The goethites of these soils are lower in  Al-substitution (7--12 mole %) than those in the dystrophic soils. This is  probably because the mesotrophic soils have higher pH's and therefore lower  Al-availability.  The ferruginous bauxites are found in scattered plateau areas (old land  surfaces, possibly Tertiary) between 1000 and 2000 m elevation, 50--100  km inland, parallel to the coastline and with present-day rainfall of ~ 1000  mm. In a typical profile, ferruginous bauxite is underlain by a red and/or  yellow mottled saprolite and overlain by a red or yellow soil. These ferrugi-  nous bauxites are formed by in situ weathering of primary Fe-minerals such  as augite and hornblende (from thin-section evidence; Fitzpatrick, 1978b),  mainly of dolerites, but also from lidianite and sandstone under severe leach-  ing, resulting in a brittle, yellow-brown porous massive residuum. The Fed  values for 20 samples range between 12 and 23% Fe.  Goethites in the ferruginous bauxites are highly Al-substituted, contain-  ing between 20 and 25 mole % A1 (Fig.3), possibly because they formed in  an Al-rich environment as indicated by the presence of gibbsite. Compared  with goethites of similar high levels of Al-substitution from acid soil clays  the goethites in ferruginous bauxites are more crystalline (compare C and  B in Fig.4). No reason can be offered for this.  The highly weathered soils associated with ferruginous bauxites often con-  tain nodules 2--50 cm in diameter consisting of a dark, hard rind and a brittle,  much lighter interior. The rinds contain higher amounts of Fed (20--23% Fe)  than the interiors {12--19% Fe) and largely goethite with lower Al-substitu-  tion (14--18 mole % A1) than the goethite in the interior material (20--27  mole % A1). Because such a high concentration of Fe in the rind requires  a high Fe mobility, it is assumed that the rinds were formed under hydro-  morphic conditions in which iron has moved asFe(II) from adjacent areas  to the nodule. This is supported by the lower degree of Al-substitution.  The saprolites occurring on older land surfaces in most of the high rain-  fall areas consist of a mantle of weathered material in which the original  rock structure is preserved. In contrast to the brittle bauxite overlying the  saprolite, the latter is usually soft and is composed chiefly of kaolinite--  halloysite with various amounts of goethite, quartz, anatase, ilmenite and  titano-magnetite. Due to a very similar weathering environment the goethites  of the saprolites have a similar although slightly lower Al-substitution (13--  21 mole % A1, for 11 of the 15 samples) than those of the bauxites. This  underlines the close genetic association between the two. The somewhat  lower substitution is in line with a lower degree of weathering as indicated by    344    less gibbsite and more kaolinite in the saprolites. The crystallinity of A1-  goethites in saprolites appears to be similar to that in bauxites (D in Fig.4).    Goethites from hydromorphic environments    Goethite formation in hydromorphic environments is dominated by ab-  solute Fe-accumulation. This requires the mobilization of considerable  amounts of Fe by microbial reduction under O2-deficiency, i.e., water-  logging. On reoxidation the Fe-oxides may accumulate as mottles and bands,  concretions, geodes, pipe stems, crusts and ferricretes.  Five samples were taken of orange and yellow mottles and bands from  various gleys and pseudogleys, i.e., soils with active hydromorphism (aquic  moisture regime) occurring on slopes and in low-lying areas. They may con-  tain lepidocrocite (Schwertmann and Fitzpatrick, 1977). Their goethites are  low in Al-substitution (2--10 mole % ).  Except for soils of the Afro-alpine zone, concretions occur generally in  all soil groups of the study area and may comprise up to 30--40% of the soil  volume. In these concretions goethite is often associated with hematite and/  or maghemite. It is likely that many of these concretions were formed un-  der the influence of at least some hydromorphism in the past, although they  occur in soils which are presently freely drained, e.g., paleoplinthitic soils.  Many concretions have hard yellow-brown rinds with higher goethite contents  than the interiors. This might indicate that the hematitic-maghemitic cores  were converted to goethite in a later phase of pedogenesis.  The goethites of the 7 samples measured had Fed values of 12--25% and an  Al-substitution between 5 and 10%. Concretions sampled from three soils  which overlie ferricretes have similar Al-substitution of their goethites,  thereby indicating their common hydromorphic genesis. In accordance  with their lower Al-substitution the goethites from concretions have low  WHH values (see Fig.4). Larger (2--10 cm diameter) hollow concretions of  spherical to ellipsoidal form are sometimes called geodes. They often occur  in stone lines at various depths and consist of a hard goethite-rich rind. The  core may contain pyrite. The goethites show very little Al-substitution, so  they must have grown in an environment almost free of accessible Al.  Other common features of hydromorphic environments are Fe-oxide ac-  cumulations around roots or worm channels. These channels supply air,  thereby oxidizing Fe(II) which has moved from the matrix to the channel.  This leads to the formation of pipe stems. In Natal, they occur as fossil  formations in deep-red coastal sands or in recent (hydromorphic) gieys and  pseudogleys. In the latter, goethite is again often associated with lepidocro-  cite (Schwertmann and Fitzpatrick, 1977) indicating the involvement and  presence of Fe(II).  The degree of Al-substitution in the 7 pipe stems is only between 1 and  6 mole %, again indicating an environment of low Al-availability. This is  further supported by the presence of lepidocrocite which is suppressed in  an Fe(II) system containing A1 (Taylor and Schwertmann, 1978).    345    Iron-rich, hard and dense crusts occur in saprolites and in hydromorphic  soils adjacent to lepidocrocite bands (Schwertmann and Fitzpatrick, 1977).  Their goethites range in Al-substitution between 0 and 12 mole %. This  wide range might indicate their differing genesis although the rather low sub-  stitution of most of them is in accord with their presumed hydromorphic  formation.  The ferricretes are horizon-type, cemented Fe-oxide accumulations with a  vesicular, cellular, pisolitic or nodular internal structure. Within a valley  they occur not only in the valley bottom but also at higher levels thereby  indicating former valley systems. They are widespread in Natal and Transvaal  in various altitudinal positions (Maud, 1965, 1968a, b; Van der Eyk et al.,  1969) (see also maps in Fitzpatrick, 1974, 1978b).  The Fed values of ferricretes range between 12 and 27% Fe. In 50% of the  ferricretes goethite is the only Fe-oxide detected. These samples also have  relatively high Mnd values which underline their low degree of leaching.  This in turn also explains why the Al-substitution of their goethites {3--14  mole %) is significantly lower than that of goethites from non-hydromor-  phic environments.  Five goethite samples were collected from calcareous environments. These  occur as veins in limestones and also in ammonites and mollusca and may  have been formed from the oxidation of Fe(II) in carbonates (ankerite,  siderite). The Al-substitution of these goethites is &lt; 5%, which indicates the  low Al-availability in such an environment.    GENERAL DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS    Some 200 samples from widely differing pedogenic environments contain  goethite as a major crystalline Fe-oxide together with hematite, maghemite  and lepidocrocite. As indicated by low Feo/Fed ratios (&lt; 0.1) the amounts  of ferrihydrite appear low except in the less weathered soils of the Afro-  alpine zone, formed under an organic matter-preserving, cooler climate.  The goethite varies greatly in crystallinity (as judged from width at half  height of the XRD lines) and Al-substitution (XRD line shift). The necessary  XRD measurements were greatly facilitated by a concentration procedure  (hot 5 M NaOH) in those samples with low goethite contents.  The Al-substitution of the goethites ranged between 0 and 32 mole %. A  significant negative relationship between Al-substitution and crystallinity (as  measured by WHH) indicates that A1 might be one factor hampering crystal-  lization. Organic matter is possibly another factor.  If samples are grouped genetically and tentatively into goethites formed  under hydromorphic (mottles, pipe stems, concretions, ferricretes, etc.) and  non-hydromorphic (freely drained softs, saprolites, bauxites) conditions, a  certain trend is evident. Goethites formed under hydromorphic and meso-  trophic (weakly acid softs) conditions, are lower in Al-substitution {0--15  mole %) than those formed under strongly weathered, non-hydromorphic    346    and more acid conditions (15--32 mole % ). The reason tentatively offered  for this trend is the increasing activity of A1 as pH decreases and consequent-  ly the increasing availability of A1 to be incorporated into the goethite struc-  ture as it forms.  The lower substitution under hydromorphic conditions may be partly  due to the same effect, i.e., to a generally higher pH of hydromorphic  soils as compared to freely drained soils. Hydromorphic environments general-  ly have restricted leaching or even accumulation of basic cations and thereby  a higher pH. Therefore, in as much as goethites are formed by oxidation of  mobilized Fe(II), Al is not equally mobile. A second factor, however, may  also contribute to the lower Al-substitution under hydromorphic conditions.  Iron oxides in such soils form from mobilized Fe(II) which moves to centres  of higher partial pressure of 02 (or soil water higher in dissolved O2) such as  the larger pores. The goethite would thus form without any solid Al-source  in the immediate vicinity, i.e., in a relatively pure environment.  Softs with fossilized hydromorphic features, such as plinthite, also have  fossilized ("primary") goethites with low Al-substitution, whereas the more  recently formed goethites in these soils ("secondary goethites") have higher  substitution reflecting the new acid and freely drained environment. Con-  versely, if a former highly substituted goethite (e.g., saprolite) undergoes  redissolution and recrystallization under hydromorphic conditions to form  ferricretes, for example, the newly formed ("secondary") goethites appear  less substituted (see also Nahon et al., 1977). This study of the 200 samples  thus shows that degree of Al-substitution reflects the immediate environment  of pedogenesis.    REFERENCES    Beneslavsky, S.I., 1957. New aluminium-bearing minerals in bauxites. Dokl. Akad.  Nauk. S.S.S.R., 113: 367--369.  Correns, C.W. and Von Engelhardt, W., 1941. R6ntgenographische Untersuchungen fiber  den Mineralbestand sediment~rer Eisenerze. Nachr. Akad. Wiss. GSttingen, Math.-  Phys. KI., 213: 131--137.  Davey, B.G., Russell, J.D. and Wilson, M.J., 1975. Iron oxide and clay minerals and their  relation to colours of red and yellow podzolic soils near Sydney, Australia. Geoderma  14: 125--138.  De Villiers, J.M., 1964, The genesis of some Natal soils, 1. CloveUy, Kranskop and Bal-  moral Series. S. Aft. J. Agric. Sci., 7: 417--438.  Fey, M.V. and Le Roux, J., 1976. Quantitative determination of allophane in soil clays.  In: S.W. Bailey (Editor) Proc. Int. Clay Conf., Mexico City, 1975: 451--463.  Fey, M.V. and Le Roux, J., 1977. Properties and quantitative estimation of poorly crys-  talline components in sesquioxidic soil clays. Clays Clay Miner., 25: 285--294.  Fitzpatrick, R.W., 1974. Mineralogo-chemical studies on soils and related material from  pedosystems in the southeastern Transvaal. M.Sc. Agric. Dissertation, Univ. Natal.  Fitzpatrick, R.W., 1978a. Periglacial soils with fossil permafrost horizons in southern  Africa. Proc. 4th S. Aft. Soc. Quat. Res., 1977. Ann. Natal Mus., 23: 475--484.  Fitzpatrick, R.W., 1978b. Occurrence and properties of iron and titanium oxides in soils  along the eastern seaboard of South Africa. Ph.D. dissertation, Univ. Natal.    347    Golden, D.C., 1978. Physical and chemical properties of aluminum-substituted goethite.  Ph.D. dissertation, Dep. Soil Sci., N.C. State Univ. Raleigh (unpubl.).  Jackson, M.L., 1968. Soil chemical analysis. Advanced course, published by the author,  Dep. Soil Sci., Univ. Wisconsin, Madison, WI.  Jonas, K. and Solymar, K., 1970. Preparation, X-ray derivatographic and infrared study of  aluminium-substituted goethites. Acta Chim. Acad. Sci. Hung., 66: 383--394.  K~mp[, N. and Schwertmann, U., 1982. The 5M-NaOH concentration treatment for iron  oxides in soil. Clays Clay Miner., 30. In print.  King, L.C., 1967. South African Scenery. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh, 3rd ed.  Kiihnel, R.A., Roorda, H.J. and Steensma, J.J., 1975. The crystallinity of minerals~a  new variable in pedogenic processes. A study of goethite and associated silicates in  laterites. Clays Clay Miner., 23: 349--354.  Lewis, D.G. and Schwertmann, U., 1979a. The influence of aluminium on the formation  of iron oxides, 4. The influence of [All, [OH], and temperature. Clays Clay Miner.,  27 : 195--200.  Lewis, D.G. and Schwertmann, U., 1979b. The influence of A1 on iron oxides, 3. Prepara-  tion of A1 goethites in M KOH. Clay Miner., 14: 115--126.  Maud, R.R., 1965. Laterite and lateritic soils in coastal Natal, South Africa. J. Soil Sci.,  16: 60--72.  Maud, R.R., 1968a. Quaternary geomorphology and soil formation in coastal Natal. Z.  Geomorphol. Suppl., 7 : 155--199.  Maud, R.R., 1968b. Further observations on the laterites of coastal Natal. Trans. 9th  Int. Congr. Soil Sci., Adelaide, 4: 151--158.  Mehra, O.P. and Jackson, M.L., 1960. Iron oxide removal from soils and clays by a di-  thionite-citrate system buffered with sodium bicarbonate. Clays Clay Miner., 7:  317--327.  Nahon, D., Janot, C., Karpoff, A.M., Paquet, H. and Tardy, Y., 1977. Mineralogy, petro-  graphy and structures of iron crusts (ferricretes) developed on sandstones in the wes-  tern part of Senegal. Geoderma, 19: 263--277.  Norrish, K. and Taylor, R.M., 1961. The isomorphous replacement of iron by aluminium  in soil goethites. J. Soil Sci., 12: 294--306.  Schwertmann, U., 1964. Differenzierung der Eisenoxide des Bodens durch Extraktion mit  Ammoniumoxalat-LSsung. Z. Pflanzenern~hr. Diing. Bodenkd., 105: 194--202.  Schwertmann, U., 1966. Inhibitory effect of soil organic matter on the crystallization  of amorphous ferric hydroxide. Nature, 212: 645--646.  Schwertmann, U. and Fitzpatrick, R.W., 1977. Occurrence of lepidocrocite and its associa-  tion with goethite in Natal Soils. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 41: 1013--1018.  Schwertmann, U. and Taylor, R.M., 1977. Iron oxides. In: J.B. Dixon and S.B. Weed  (Editors) Minerals in Soil Environments. Agron. Soc. Am. Publ.  Schwertmaan, U., Fischer, W.R. and Taylor, R.M., 1974. New aspects of iron oxide for-  mation in soils. Trans. llth Int. Congr. Soil Sci., Moscow, 1974, pp. 237--247.  Taylor, R.M. and Schwertmann, U., 1978. The influence of aluminium on iron oxides, 1.  The influence of Al on Fe-oxide formation from the Fe(II) system. Clays Clay Miner.,  26: 373--383.  Thiel, R., 1963. Zum System ~FeOOH--~A1OOH. Z. Anorg. Altg. Chem., 326: 70--78.  Torrent, J., Schwertmann, U. and Schulze, D.G., 1980. Iron oxide mineralogy of some  soils of two river terrace sequences in Spain. Geoderma, 23: 191--20~.  Van der Eyk, J.J., Macvicar, C.N. and De Villiers, J.M., 1969. Soils of the Tugela Basin.  Natal Town Reg. Plann. Rep., 15.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  AbstractOver 200 goethite-containing samples from widely diverse environments along the eastern seaboard of South Africa were examined and described, mainly by X-ray powder diffraction (XRD).Aluminium-substituted goethites ranging from 0 to about 32 mole % AlOOH were identified mainly by XRD line-shift and chemical extraction. They occur in every soil zone and major soil type in one or other form from sources such as: (1) non-hydromorphic- highly weathered (strongly acid soils, ferruginous bauxites, saprolites) and moderately weathered (moderately acid soils) environments; (2) hydromorphic environments (mottles, concentrations, pipe stems, crusts, ferricretes, geodes); and (3) crusts in calcareous environments. These goethites, formed in different climatic and weathering environments were grouped according to their amount of Al-substitution and crystallinity (as determined by XRD line broadening). Al-substitution in goethite formed in hydromorphic, moderately acid soils and calcareous environments was generally low (0–15 mole %). Goethite formed in non-hydromorphic highly weathered environments was generally high in Al-substitution (15–32 mole %) and increased in the following order: saprolites and strongly acid, freely drained soils &lt; ferruginous bauxites &lt; strongly acid soils overlying plinthite.This study showed that the degree of Al-substitution and crystallinity of goethites may reflect the environment in which they have formed and serve as an indicator of soilforming processes.