 Geoderma, 34 (1984) 115--134                                                  115  Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., Amsterdam -- Printed in The Netherlands    HOLOCENE SOIL CHRONOFUNCTIONS, SOUTHERN ALPS,  NEW ZEALAND    PETER W. BIRKELAND  Department of Geological Sciences and Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research,  University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309 (U.S.A.)  (Received November 8, 1982; revised version accepted August 9, 1984)    ABSTRACT    Birkeland, P.W., 1984. Holocene soil chronofunctions, Southern Alps, New Zealand.  Geoderma, 34: 115--134.    Field and laboratory data for two soil chronosequences from the high country of the  South Island of New Zealand suggest rapid soil formation rates. The areas studied are the  Ben Ohau Range and the Mt. Cook area, where mean annual precipitation is about 1 and  4 m, respectively. Most soil ages are estimated from the thicknesses of rock weathering  rinds. Soil chronofunctions are derived for indices that depict field profile and color  development, and a modified index of profile anisotropy for laboratory data. Out of a  possible 21 chronofunctions, 16 are statistically significant (at the 0.05 level) and 8 are  from each area. Most (13) of the chronofunctions best fit a power model, and the remain-  ing ones are split between linear (2) and exponential (1) models. Although problems exist  in the purity of the chronosequences because other soil-forming factors are not constant,  duration of pedogenesis seems to be the most significant factor in explaining the trends.  Despite the large differences in mean annual precipitation between the two areas, many  of the derived curves for property vs. time are quite similar.    INTRODUCTION    Many studies have shown that soils differ in morphology and chemical  properties with time (Jenny, 1941; Stevens and Walker, 1970; Yaalon, 1975;  Bockheim, 1980; Birkeland, 1984). Several methods have been used to por-  tray these differences with time, from graphical methods to linear and non-  linear mathematical equations. The purpose of this study is twofold: (1) to  discuss the differences in soil properties with age of parent material in the  Southern Alps of New Zealand; and (2) to indicate the usefulness of soil in-  dices in soil chronofunction studies. This latter objective is important be-  cause a particular soil horizon in this study can be characterized by some six  field properties and nine laboratory properties, the number of horizons per  profile ranges from two to six, and most horizons are of unequal thickness.  Soil indices provide a means of condensing these data to a single number per  profile to portray total change with time. Such indices have been shown to    0016-7061/84/$03.00  1984 Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.    116    be useful in studies that use soils for correlation of deposits between areas of  markedly contrasting environments (Harden and Taylor, 1983).  The chronosequences studied are post-incisive, according to the classifica-  tion of Vreeken (1975). This means that the deposits from which the soils  have formed are of different ages, the soils are not buried except for some  thin younger loess in places and the duration of development for each soil is  the interval from the end of deposition of the respective parent material to  the present. Chronosequence studies have been done at lower altitudes in  New Zealand (Stevens and Walker, 1970; Mokma et al., 1973; Campbell,  1975; Ross et al., 1977), and although cursory soil data have been used as  part of geological studies in the high country (Burrows, 1975), no previous  chronosequence studies have been carried out in the mountainous environ-  ments described here; Harrison (1982) has done the most recent work on  such soils, but his emphasis is mainly on soil catena relationships.    LOCATION AND SITE FACTORS    The soils formed from a sequence of Holocene deposits in the Mt. Cook  area and the Ben Ohau Range, Southern Alps, New Zealand (Fig. 1). In the  Mt. Cook area, softs formed from till, loess over till, loess over colluvium  which overlies till, and loess over a debris-flow deposit; in the Ben Ohau area  soils formed from till and loess over till near the head of Whale Stream (Tables  I and II; for specific locations match locality numbers in tables of this paper  with those in figs. 8a and 11 in Birkeland, 1982). Bedrock from which the  above deposits are derived is indurated, weakly schistose to nonfollated gray-  wacke and argillite of late Paleozoic to Mesozoic age, with quartz, feldspar,  muscovite, biotite, sphene, epidote, and rock fragments making up the major-  ity of the grains (Gait, 1967; SpSrli and Lillie, 1974). Ages of the Holocene  deposits are estimates mainly determined from weathering rind thicknesses  of clasts and some 14C dates (Birkeland, 1982; Gellatly, 1984). According to  Chinn (1981), ages estimates from rind thicknesses have a plus-minus of about  20%. Loess is an important component in the upper part of many soils, and  the lack of buried softs at the contact between the loess and the underlying  deposit and within the loess suggest that much of the loess was deposited  shortly after deposition of the substrate beneath the loess. Climate differs  markedly in the two areas: mean annual precipitation ranges from about 4 m  at most Mt. Cook sites to about 1 m at the Ben Ohau sites, and the respec-  tive approximate mean annual temperatures are 7--8 and 4 (Archer,  1970, 1973; O'Connor, 1976). Vegetation follows the climate contrasts. The  younger deposits in the Ben Ohau Range have little vegetation, whereas tall  tussock grasses (Chionochloa sp.) are dominant on deposits over 3000 yr.  old. In the Mt. Cook area there is a succession to subalpine scrub and low  forest (details are in Burrows, 1973). The only exceptions to the latter are  sites C18 and C19 which are downvalley from the other Mr. Cook sites,  under somewhat lesser rainfall and grassland vegetation. The Black Birch    117    Qciers,   ~  : !:::::ii :  i  .Hermitage   ~  A    ID                        I  /  mOr~           N  ". ~_.  /     d  .o          5km    Fig. 1. Locations of the Ben Ohau Range and the Mt. Cook area, South Island, New Zea-  land. Study areas are shaded. Detailed locations of the soil sites are given in Birkeland  (1982) but approximate locations are: localities C8, C13, C14 and C20 are north of the  Hermitage; locality C1 is northeast of the Hermitage; localities C18 and C19 are about 7  km south of the Hermitage; and all localities designated B are along Whale Stream   TABLE I  Oo  Field data for Holocene sol|s, Ben Ohau Range  Approx.    Location1     Horizon     Depth    Color,        &gt;2 mm    Texture:  Structure    Boundary  Parent material  age (yr.)                                (cm)      dry           (%)  100       Bll           A             0--5     5Y 5/1        85         S*        0            a,s         Till  2B1          5--20   5Y 7/2       50         S         0           c,s  2B2         20--41    5Y 6/1        50         S*        0            c,s  3Cu         41--58+  5Y6/1        75         S*        0  3000       B9            A             0--7     10YR 5/2     75         L*        2,f,gr        a,w        Loess/till (2)  Bw           7--18    10YR 5/2     75         L*        1,f,sbk      a,w  2C1         18--29   10YR 5/3    75         SL       1,f,sbk      c,w  2C2       29--40+  2.5Y 5/3    75       SL      0  4000       B19           A             0--10    10YR 3.5/2    0         SL        2,f,gr        a,s         Loess/till (2)  Bw          10--22   10YR 5]3     10         L         1,f,sbk       c,s  2C         22--67+  2.5Y 6/3     25        L       0  4000       B10           C             0--15    10YR 5/3      0         L         1,f,gr        a,s         Loess/buried loess/  Ab          15--22    10YR 5/2      0         L         2,f,gr        a,s         mixed loess and till  Bwlb       22--36   10YR 6/4      0         L*       1,vf,sbk     c,s         (2)/tin (3)  2Bw2b      36--54    2.5Y 7/5      25         SL        3,m,abk     a,w  3Bw3b      54--60    10YR 4/3     85         LS        0            a,w  3Cb         60--90+  2.5Y 6/3      85         LS*      0  4000       B27           A             0--7     10YR 4/2      0         L         2,f,gr        a,s         Loess  Ej            7--13   10YR 5/3      0         SiL      m           a,s  Bwl        13--29   10YR 6/4      0         SiL       1,f,sbk      c,s  Bw2         29-60    2.5Y 7/6      10         SiL       2,m,abk     a,w  9000       B4            A             0-6     10YR 4/2      0         SiL       2,f,gr        a,s         Loess/till (2)  Ej          6--10   10YR 6/3     0        SiL      2,f,gr      a,s  Bw         10--26   10YR 6.5/6    0         SiL      2,f,abk      c,s  2Bw         26--41    10YR 5/3     85         LS        0            c,w  2C           41--53   2.5Y 5/3      85         LS        0            c,s  2Cu?        53--63+  5Y7/3        85         LS        0  9000       B5            A             0--3     7.5YR 5/2     0         SiL       2,f,gr        a,s         Loess/mixed loess  E            3--14   2.5Y 8/2       0         CL*      1,f,sbk      a,w        and till (2)/till (3)  2Bsl         14--25    10YR 4/6     10         CL       1,f,sbk      c,w  7.5YR 4/8                SiL  3Bs2         25--45+  10YR 4/6     25         SL        2,f,abk     For locations see Birkeland (1982).  : * Denotes field-estimated texture; all other textures are taken from data in Table III.   III.    TABLE II    Field data for Holocene soils, Mt. Cook area  Approx.   Location      Horizon     Depth,   Color,        &gt; 2 mm    Texture  Structure    Boundary  Parent material  age (yr.)                          (cm)    dry         (%)  100      C13          A            0--3    10YR 5/2      0        LS       0           a,s        Eolian sand/till (2)  2Cu          3--18+  5Y 7/1       75        S        0  500      C14          A            0---4     10YR 4/2      0         SL       m-~gr       a,s         Eolian sand/till (2)  2C           4--20   2.5Y 5/2     75        LS       0           c,s  2Cu?        20--40+  5Y 6.5/2      75         S         0  1200      C8            A            0--12   7.5YR 4/2     0         L        m~gr       a,s         Loess/till (2)  2Bw        12--41   7.5YR 4/3    75        LS       0           c,w  2C          41--71   2.5Y 7/2.5    75        SL       0           c,s  2Cu?        71--87+  5Y 7/2.5      75         LS       0  5500      C19          A            0--15   10YR 5/2     0        L        2,f,gr       a,s        Loess/mixed loess  2Bwl       15---61   10YR 5/4    50        L        1,f,sbk      a,w        and till (2)/till (3)  3Bw2       61--141+ 10YR 5/5    75        LS       0  8000      C1            A            0--10   10YR 5.5/2    0         CL       2,f,gr        a,s         Loess/mixed loess  E           10--22   10YR 6/3     0        L        1,f,sbk      c,s        and till (2)  Bsl          22--49   10YR 7/6      0         CL       2,m,abk     c,w  Bs2         49--66   10YR 6.5/8   50        CL       2,m,abk     c,w  Bs3         66--111+ 10YR 6.5/8   50        SiL      1,f,abk  8000      C20          A1           0--18   10YR 5/2     0        CL       2,f,gr       a,w        Loess/mixed loess  Ej          18--29   10YR 6/3      0        CL       2,f,gr       a,w        and colluvium (2)/  2Bs         29---70   10YR 7/6    10        SiCL     2,m,sbk     c,w        colluvium (3)  3Bw        70--93   7.5YR 4/5    50        SL       0           c,w  3C          93+      2.5Y 6/2.5    50        SL       0  9000      C18          A            0-5     7.5YR 5/3     0         SiL       2,f,gr        a,s         Loess/mixed loess  Ej            5--11   10YR 6/4    10        SiL      1,s,sbk      a,s        and till (2)/till (3)  2Bs         11--45   10YR 7/8    25        CL       1,s,sbk      a,w  3Bw        45--60   10YR 7/5    75        SL       0           a,w  3C          60-75+  5Y 7/2.5     75        SL       0    120    Stream site (C20 at Mt. Cook) is on a 30slope, whereas all other sites are  relatively stable moraine crests or flat surfaces. Erosion of these latter sites  seems to have been slight.    METHODS    Field and laboratory    Field descriptions, as well as texture, follow those of the U.S.D.A. (Soil  Survey Staff, 1975), with some modification. Soil horizon nomenclature is  largely the new U.S.D.A. nomenclature, C and Cu are for oxidized and un-  weathered C horizons, respectively, and j is used for those horizons in which  the defining properties are weakly expressed (Canadian Department of Agri-  culture, 1974; Guthrie and Witty, 1982; Birkeland, 1984). Particle-size anal-  ysis was by sedigraph particle-size analyser, pH is for a 2.5:1 water-to-soil  mixture, the methods for organic carbon (Walkley-Black), acid-extractable  phosphorus (Pa) and organic-bound phosphorus (Po) are from Blakemore et  al. (1977), and Fe and A1 are for the oxalate-extractable portion (McKeague  and Day, 1966).    Indices    Several indices are used to portray changes in soil properties with time.  The indices are for the field and laboratory properties of the profiles.  Bilzi and Ciolkosz (1977) and Harden (1982; also Harden and Taylor,  1983) have developed indices for profile development based on field descrip-  tions, and the latter one is used here. The calculation of the Harden index is  too involved to duplicate, but basically the steps are as follows:  (1) Characterize the parent material. For till, use data on the youngest,  presumably unweathered, till; for loess, use data on silt from the active  floodplain. Using the unweathered floodplain silt for all loess parent material  could create problems because some loess could have been derived from  eroded soils in the region. There was no way to adequately solve this prob-  lem during this project.  (2) Assign points for the differences between the properties of the soil  horizons and those of the parent material.  (3) Normalize the values in (2) for each horizon by dividing the latter by  the maximum value of the point scale for that property; this provides a scale  ranging from 0 to 1.  (4) Sum all the individual values in (3) for a horizon and divide by the  number of properties.  (5) Multiply (4) by the horizon thickness.  After the above calculations, there are several ways to obtain the profile  development index. Harden (1982) sums the data for the individual horizons  in (5). Because most profiles are described to different depths, however, a    121    soil described to greater depth may have a greater soil development index on  this factor alone. There are two ways to adjust for uneven depths, and both  are used here. One is to divide the profile index sum by the depth of the pro-  file, producing a weighted mean profile index (Harden and Taylor, 1983).  The other is to increase the thickness of the lowest horizon in all but the  thickest soil in a local soil sequence so that all profiles have the same thick-  ness (Birkeland, 1984). Such maximum thicknesses in this study are 75 cm  for the Ben Ohau Range and 141 cm for the Mt. Cook area. The main prob-  lem with the latter manipulation is the assumption that the properties of the  lowest horizons of all profiles continue to those depths, and this may not be  true for all soils. Whichever calculation is used, however, higher values in the  profile index denote stronger soil development.  Two color indices are used, and both are similar to the extent that the  Munsell notation is recalculated to a single number. One is the Buntley-  Westin (B-W) color index (Buntley and Westin, 1965) in which hue is con-  verted to a number (7.5YR = 4; 10YR = 3; 2.5Y = 2; 5Y = 1) which is multi-  plied by the chroma. The other is rubification (Harden, 1982) in which the  color of each horizon is compared with that of the parent material, and a  shift in hue toward redder colors (change one hue page) and a shift in  chroma toward brighter colors are each assigned 10 points. Only the dry  colors were used in the calculations here, whereas Harden advocates using  both dry and moist colors. With both indices, values were calculated for each  horizon and these multiplied by the horizon thickness. Because of the prob-  lem, mentioned above, of profiles described to uneven depths, values for the  lowest horizon were recalculated so that all profiles in each sequence are as  thick as the thickest profile. These numbers were then divided by the thick-  ness of the thickest profile of the sequence. The resulting numbers of either  index provide a value for each profile, and higher numbers indicate greater  color development.  Laboratory data can be portrayed by a modification of the index of soil  anisotrophy (IPA) of Walker and Green (1976), here called mIPA (Birkeland,  1984). The concept is that ideally at time = 0 soil properties are isotropic;  that is, values are the same irrespective of direction (here we are concerned  with the differences in properties with depth). In time, however, soil proper-  ties change with depth, the profile becomes anisotropic, and the degree of  anisotropy increases with time. Walker and Green (1976) defined IPA as:  100  IPA = D  M  where D is the mean deviation of the sampled horizon from the overall  weighted mean value (M) of a particular property for the profile. The mIPA,  in contrast, takes into account variation from the parent material and is de-  fined as:  D  mIPA -  PM    122    where D is the numerical deviation of the particular property from that of  the parent material (PM). PM values can be obtained from young unweather-  ed tills, loesses or fine-grained materials in the source areas of loess. Values  are calculated for each horizon, multiplied by the horizon thickness, data for  each horizon summed to give a profile value (after the thickness of the low-  est horizon is increased so that the thickness of all profiles matches that of  the thickest profile in the sequence), and that value divided by the thickness  of the thickest profile. Anisotropy and the value of mIPA should increase  with time.    RESULTS    Changes in field and laboratory properties with time    The progressive changes with time in both soil field properties and soil-  classification units are similar in both areas (Tables I and II). The classifica-  tion according to Soil Taxonomy (Soft Survey Staff, 1975) is only an ap-  proximation, because diagnostic laboratory data are not available. Soils  about 500 yr. old or younger have minimally developed A/C profiles and are  Cryorthents. The soil at locality Bll in the Ben Ohau Range is the youngest  to have a B horizon, and there it is recognized by coatings of silt and clay on  the tops of clasts. These coatings are interpreted as the result of loess infil-  trating coarse-grained till and are a common feature of alpine soils in areas in  which loess has been deposited subsequent to the deposition of the parent  material (Bums, 1980). With few exceptions, Bw horizons, here defined by  10YR or redder hues, take from 1200 to 3000 yr. to form; still older soils  differ from younger ones mainly in having increasingly stronger chromas  with age. Incipient E horizons (Ej)are recognized in 4000-year-old deposits,  and all deposits of 8000 yr. or older have E horizons. Most of these soils are  Cryochrepts, and several probably are Cryorthods (those at localities B5, C1,  and C18). Most of the older softs have a layer of loess at the surface, usually  recognizable by loam or finer textures and few or no clasts. Although there  is some suggestion of an increase in loess thickness with time, local differ-  ences in thickness are considerable; some profiles are formed entirely in loess  (e.g., profile at locality B27). Silt and clay coats are on the tops of clasts in  most profiles.  Selected laboratory data in general follow predictable trends of increasing  or decreasing with time (Tables III and IV). Most properties should increase  with time, but pH and Pa should decrease. The increase in clay with time is  mainly the result of loess accumulation. The values for pH tend to decrease  with time in softs in both areas. Organic carbon in the A horizon increases  with time, and shows substantial accumulation in some older B horizons.  The maximum % Fe and A1 for a profile both increase with time. The maxi-  ma for A1 and Fe are generally in the B horizon, and that for the former is  commonly deeper than that for the latter. Pa and Po display the depletion in    123    the former and accumulation of the latter, as is found in other studies  (Walker, 1964; Walker and Syers, 1976).    Changes in indices with time    Data for most indices were correlated with time using regression techni-  ques and 3 models (Bockheim, 1980):  Y = a + bX (linear)  y = aebX(exponential)  Y = aXb (power)  where Y is an index value and X is time. All models were evaluated and those  with the highest correlation coefficients (r) are considered to be most appro-  priate, as long as they are significant at either the 0.05 or 0.01 significance  levels.  Out of a possible 21 chronofunctions, 16 are significant at least at the  0.05 level (Tables V and VI, Figs. 2 and 3). Most data best fit the power  model with the remaining split between the exponential and linear models.  Both B-W color index and rubification give significant regressions and similar  trends for both areas. Equations for values of both ways to calculate the  Harden index are significant in the Mt. Cook area, but only one is significant  in the Ben Ohau Range. Again the trends for Harden index -- A are quite  similar for both areas. Several of the mIPA value vs. time plots are not signif-  icant, in particular clay and pH. Equations for mIPA values for organic car-  bon are significant in both areas, and the trends are dissimilar. The mIPA  values for A1 best fit the linear model in both areas and the trends are simi-  lar. Curves for mIPA values for Fe have a similar shape for both areas al-  though one best fits the power model and the other the exponential model.  In contrast, only the equation of mIPA values for Pa is significant in the Ben  Ohau Range. Finally, significant relationships were obtained for mIPA data  for Po in both areas, data for both best fit power models and the trends are  dissimilar. Overall, 8 significant relationships were derived for each area.    CONCLUSIONS    The data here support some of the conclusions of the regional review of  chronofunctions by Bockheim (1980). One is that the data can be fitted to  various mathematical models; of the 16 significant mathematical relation-  ships derived in the present study, 13 of them best fit the power model, 2 fit  the linear model and 1 the exponential model. Furthermore, of the signifi-  cant equations derived, 81% of the r's are significant at the 0.01 level. The  shapes of most of the curves seem defensible, but I have reservations on the  validity of the shapes of curves for mIPA--Fe for both areas (Figs. 2 and 3)  and mIPA-organic C for the Ben Ohau Range (Fig. 3). Theoretically, I  would expect these curves to flatten with time. More data points might be  needed to better define these curves.    TABLE III  Laboratory data for Holocene soils, Ben Ohau Range    Approx.  age  (yr.)    Location   Horizon    Percentages &lt; 2 mm    sand       silt        clay  (2---0.05  (0.5--    (&lt;0.002  mm)       0.002 mm) ram)    pH    Organic  carbon    A1  (%)    Ve  (%)    Pa  (rag %)*'    Po  (rag %)    100      Bll       A           --         --         --       5.3      0.3      0.18     0.31     70.0       2  2B1       96.7        2.5        0.8       6.2      0.1       0.29     0.42     64.5       2  2B2         --         --         --       6.2      0.1       0.17     0.24     68.7       2  3Cu         --         --         --       6.2       0.1       0.14     0.27     72.2       0  3000       B9         A            --          --          --        4.5       4.5       0.36      0.54      15.1      54  Bw         --         --         --       5.2       3.2       0.43     0.58       5.7     55  2C1       52.3       33.6       14.1       5.3       1.5       0.39     0.43     18.9     37  2C2        71.7        22.9         5.4        5.3       0.6       0.29      0.24      54.5      15  4000      B19       A         52.4       38.1        9.5       4.9      6.7       0.34     0.50     13.7     77  Bw        47.2       38.0       14.8       4.8       2.3       0.41     0.39     11.7     48  2C         43.7        44.8        11.6        5.4       1.4       0.45      0.38      17.4      34  4000       B10        C           33.9        41.3        25.4        5.2       4.0       0.69      0.83      11.6      63  Ab        32.7       42.4       24.9       4.8       2.8       0.39     0.75       9.4     53  Bwlb       --         --         --       4.5       2.1       0.67     0.82      6.3     54  2Bw2b     33.9       43.0       23.1       5.7       1.5       0.78      0.68       6.5      38  3Bw3b     76.3       18.5        5.2       5.8       1.7       0.99      0.33      40.1      42  3Cb         --          --          --        5.7       0.6       0.57      0.19      65.4      14    4000      B27       A          38.3       48.4       13.3       5.3       4.8       0.32      0.42      21.4      80  Ej         28.7       52.0       19.3       4.7       3.4      0.45     0.59       7.0     62  Bwl       20.9       65.3       13.8       4.5       2.3      0.66     0.85       5.9     54  Bw2       27.7       52.4       19.9       5.1       1.3       0.68     0.96      4.4     38  9000      B4         A          31.3       51.7       17.0       4.4       4.5       0.40      0.64      18.4      84  Ej         26.4       52.6       21.0       4.9       3.7       0.48     1.03     10.1     54  Bwl       21.4       63.4       15.2       5.1       3.1       1.09     1.75      4.7     63  2Bw2     76.2       20.6        3.2       5.4      1.6      1.19     0.38     45.6     29  2C       77.7      19.2       3.1      5.6     0.6     0.54    0.17     66.6     15  2Cu?     80.2      17.5       2.3      4.5     0.5      0.35    0.24    67.2     11  9000      B5         A          23.2       51.1       25.7       4.9       6.5       0.26      0.22       4.1      51  E          --        --        --       4.9      1.4      0.27     0.28      3.8     20  2Bsl      22.2      46.7      31.1      4.8      7.1      1.66     3.85     10.6     85  23.4       50.7       25.9       4.7       5.6       1.74      5.63       7.8      72  3Bs2     53.7      43.3       3.0      5.3     5.5      2.12     1.44     20.4    41    ,l 1 mg % = 1 ppm/lO.    t'~  O1    TABLE IV    Laboratory data for Holocene soils, Mt. Cook area*~    Approx.  age  (yr.)    Location   Horizon    Percentages &lt;2 mm    sand       silt        clay    pH    Organic  carbon    A1  (%)    Fe  (%)    Pa  (rag %)    Po  (rag %)    100       C13        A          80.0        15.5         4.5        5.4       2.6       0.11      0.22      33.8      17  2Cu      89.9       9.7       0.4      6.1      0.2     0.10    0.22     76.3      2  500     C14      A        70.0      22.1       7.9      4.8      8.8      0.17     0.39     18.3    64  2C         84.8       14.0        1.2       4.8       0.9       0.13      0.25      56.9       2  2Cu?      87.7       11.6        0.7       5.3       0.5       0.20      0.33      65.6       0  1200       C8         A          45.4        38.2        16.4        5.2       9.2       0.44      0.72      18.2      80  2Bw       74.8       22.2        3.0       5.1       2.5       0.48      0.79      11.9      42  2C         71.5        24.2         4.3        5.7        1.2       0.41      0.49      41.6      11  2Cu?      82.8       15.3        1.9       5.6       0.5       0.16     0.21     59.1       7  5500      C19       A         49.7       36.5       13.8       5.5       3.9       0.63     0.67     38.1     51  2Bwl      34.1       44.5       21.4       5.1       3.2       1.12     1.26     11.4     78  3Bw2      85.0       10.9        4.1       5.7       2.3       1.02      0.38      75.2      15  8000      C1         A          31.1       40.0       28.9       5.0       3.6       0.32      0.45       7.6      42  E         25.3       49.4       25.3       5.2       2.0      0.37     0.54       3.7     32  Bsl        24.8       42.6       32.6       5.5       2.2      0.81      1.53       4.4     41  2Bs2      23.8       49.1       27.1       5.4      2.8       2.14     1.25       8.9     51  3Bs3      27.1       60.4       12.5       5.4       2.4       1.49     2.08     12.1     60  8000      C20       A1        26.2       39.9       33.9       4.5       4.2      0.43     0.74      8.3     50  A2         24.8       42.5       32.7       4.8       3.0       0.46      0.72       5.1      46  2Bs        19.8       46.5       33.7       5.3       2.3       0.93      1.53       4.6      39  3Bw       73.6       17.5        8.9       5.5       3.0       2.02      0.63      18.9      45  3C         68.6       23.7        7.7       5.9       1.4       1.89      0.19      30.1      24  9000      C18       A          26.3       52.7       21.0       5.1       8.9       0.51      0.86      15.2      93  Ej         20.3       53.5       26.2       4.7       5.5       0.75      0.11      15.2      68  2Bs        20.8       49.5       29.1       6.0       3.2       2.64      2.01      54.2      32  3Bw      65.5      24.8       9.7      5.8      1.2      1.20     0.66     52.1     15  3C       71.8      23.7       4.5      5.7      0.4      0.47     0.46     69.5     11    *See legend of Table III.    Ob    TABLE V    Color and profile indices, and mIPA data for soil profiles, Ben Ohau Range and Mt. Cook area    Approx.  Location Color index*~       Harden profile index   mIPA values:  age  (yr.)                B-W      R          sum    sum for     Clay   pH  profile   a fixed  thickness thickness    Organic  carbon    Al       Fe       Pa       Po    Ben Ohau Range  100     Bll       1.2       2.0      0.02       0.01  3000     B9         6.4      31.5      0.28      18.3  4000     B19       6.5      31.6      0.24      17.7  4000     B10       8.3      39.3      0.24      18.4  4000     B27      11.2      53.5      0.37      27.5  9000     B4        8.4      38.1      0.28      20.7  9000     B5       15.8      63.7      0.41      30.6  5Y 6/1 (till)  Parent material value  5Y 7/1 (loess)    u  m  m    0.10       0.1  0.161     13.8  0.062    21.5  0.121     12.9  0.174    19.1  0.188    16.8  0.165    49.5  6.2 (till)  0.1  6.0 (loess)    0.8      0.3       0.04       1.0  2.0      0.3       0.47      26.7  2.9      0.6       0.79      41.0  4.9      1.0       0.55      32.1  3.2           1.6              0.93           46.3  5.2      1.3       0.42      33.5  16.0      6.8       0.79      43.5  0.10 (till) 0.22 (till) 72.2 (till) 1  0.15 (lss) 0.33 (iss) 90 (iss)    Mr. Cook area  100     C13       1.1       0.6      0.03       0.6  500     C14       2.3      11.7      0.19      19.6  1200     C8         5.5      26.5      0.19      20.8  5500     C19      13.1      53.5      0.28      39.6  8000     C1       20.3      77.7      0.36      51.4  8000     C20       9.1      47.2      0.34      39.3  9000     C18       9.8      40.6      0.24      22.8  5Y 7/1  Parent material value    0.2    0.002      0.3  0.4    0.124      2.9  1.0    0.100      6.5  4.4    0.097    12.8  1.6    0.109    11.3  1.7    0.109    11.0  1.2  0.060    7.4  usually 6.1 (till)   0.2  value of 6.0 (loess)  deepest  horizon    0.0      0.0       0.01       1.3  0.9      0.5       0.32       2.8  1.9      0.9       0.44      18.8  7.7      1.4       0.28      38.4  10.9           5.8             0.86           50.6  11.1      1.7       0.72      35.8  7.6             2.2               0.20             20.8    0.10 (till) 0.22 (till) 76.3 (till) 1  0.15 (lss) 0.33 (lss) 90  (lss)    ,1 B-W is Buntley-Westin and R is rubification.    128  TABLE VI  Regression equation data for plots of various weighted profile indices (Y) versus time (X)  Area*l     Property                    Model* ~     a             b             r ~    B          B-W color index            P            0.12         0.51         0.91"*  C          B-W color index            P            0.084       0.56         0.91"*  B          Rubification               P            0.074       0.74         0.94"*  C          Rubification               P            0.023       0.89         0.86**  B           Harden index-A.3           P            0.0011       0.65         0.93**  C          Harden index-A            P            0.0067      0.44         0.80**  C          Harden index-B* 3          p            0.055       0.75         0.74*  B          mIPA-organic C            P            0.00030     1.30         0.95**  C          mIPA-organic C            P            0.023       0.70         0.85**  B          mIPA-A1                   L          -0.70         0.0012      0.59*  C          mIPA-A1                   L           0.48         0.0011      0.88**  B          mIPA-Fe                   E           0.27         0.00027     0.65*  C           mIPA-Fe                    P            0.0000076   1.46         0.78**  B          mIPA-Pa                   P            0.0025      0.65         0.84**  B           mIPA-Po                    P            0.023        0.86         0.93**  C          mIPA-Po                   P            0.041       0.76         0.88**    ,i B = Ben Ohau Range; C = Mt. Cook area.  .2 Regression models used:  Linear (L):        Y = a + bX  Exponential (E):  Y = aebX  Power (P):         Y = aXb  (** means r is significant at 0.01 level, * at the 0.05 level.)  * 3A means data are for    sum         whereas B means data are for the sum for a  profile thickness                                    fixed depth.    Bockheim (1980) questioned whether soils reach a steady-state because  some properties continue to change over time spans of various durations. In  this study, curves for all properties still slope at 10,000 yr., so (a) attainment  of the steady state must take still longer, (b) we need data on still older soils  in the same general environment to see if the curves do flatten with time, or  (c) we need more data on soils of 0--10,000 yr. to better define the curves.  I suspect that organic C would reach a steady state within 10,000 yr. (Birke-  land, 1984), however, a different sampling scheme with a stronger emphasis  on factors important to A-horizon properties would have to be undertaken  to determine this.  Many studies indicate distinct variation in soil properties with climate  (Jenny, 1941, 1980; Bockheim, 1980; Birkeland, 1984), but perhaps certain  climatic thresholds have to be met for this to be reflected in soils. Because  the Mt. Cook area is both wetter and warmer than the Ben Ohau Range, one  might expect more rapid rates of accumulation or depletion in many soil  properties, and increases in indices and mIPA's for the Mt. Cook area. This is  not the case, however, as many of the curves for softs in both areas are rather    129    24  x  w  O 20  Z  n-  O 12  0 8  CJ  ".m  I  QO  9(  Z 7~  0   6C  U 4~  LL  O3  n-  o  I  I  X .3  W  0  Z  z  w  t--~ .!  n-  "r 0  6(  m  I  I  5(  X  W 4 Q  Z   3O  Z 2o  LU  Q  n- 1o  1- o    J  J  .j  J    J  .J  J  I    J  J  /    J    i               J  J  J  +    I        I  J  .j  j     J  J  /  /  I        !  2000     4000    I             I             I  *    .s  J  + j/     J    I    '~ 6  E 3    L _   4  I  ~2    0  6C  5C   ~c  II  3c    l  t  1  @           J  /  I  t  0            I  6     j  ,,....... J !    2(       +  J  ~c     J  L  00  '        2000     J  J  J    .J  J  J  J    J  J  j       J  J  J    J~    I     !  jJ  J  J      +    6o'~0  80'0o  1o000            40'0o  50'00  8&amp;0  ~0000  AGE                                 AGE    Fig. 2. Plots of relationships between various color, profile and anisotropy indices with  time, Mt. Cook area (data from Table V).    similar. Perhaps the combination of precipitation and temperature in both  areas results in a leaching regime sufficient to give somewhat similar soils,  and even greater climatic differences are required before consistent differ-  ences in soil data can be obtained. The study of Harden and Taylor (1983)  supports some of these conclusions, for they found similar Harden index val-  ues for profiles in soft chronosequences in a wide variety of soil-moisture  regimes.    130    16--  x  L~  O  Z I~  H  n-  o B  o       /  4    /  ,    /  rn 0         ~  z  O 6(  H  I'--  I,  m  0  .5  I  I  .4  X  O .3  Z  .2  z  UA  r'7 .!  n-   /  T 0  5O    40  C_)  0  I  30  I  CL 20  H  E  10    I  0    /    !  ,/  /    I        I    /    /  /    /    /    I        I        I        i           /  ,/  /  /  /    I        I        I    /  :  /  /  /  /  '      '      o  2000       4000       6 O0    /  /    i  /  /,    /  /  /    I  /  /  i  8000        0000    6  g_  H  E 2    0  i(  i.c  ~ 6  E  3  0  I  .B  g_  ~  .6  ~_ .4  .2    41  I 3,  ~_2,  E    ,  /  I    /  /    1    I    /  ,/  i  i  /  /  /    /  /  /  /    i        I    /    /  /  /    i        l  /  /    /    ,l        l  /  .11  &gt;/  /  /    0    '   o  2000    4 00  AGE                                   AGE    l    i  6000    /    8000     I0000    Fig. 3. Plots of relationships between various color, profile and anisotropy indices with  time, Ben Ohau Range (data from Table V).    In this latter context, pedologists might consider the threshold concept of  geomorphologists (Schumm, 1977, p. 7). The concept states that a gradual  change in external conditions might not show up as a response in the system.  With the continued gradual external change, however, a threshold might be  reached at which the system responds quickly and dramatically. Applying  the threshold concept to this study, perhaps the climate differences between  the Ben Ohau Range and the Mt. Cook area are not sufficiently great as re-    131    gards leaching to show up as a response in the system (i.e., systematic differ-  ences in the soil properties). Even greater climatic differences might be re-  quired before the softs show a better relationship with climatic regimes. In  support of the above, the rate of rock weathering of sandstone in the South-  ern Alps, as shown by the thickness of weathering rinds, is similar under a  mean annual precipitation that ranges from 90 to 750 cm (Chinn, 1981).  This concept of thresholds is new to pedology (Muhs, 1982, 1984), but  speculation on its applicability to soil studies seems interesting.  One problem with this study, and perhaps with many chronosequence  and chronofunction studies, is that soil-forming factors other than time do  not remain constant. In this study there are problems in assuming constancy  of parent material, vegetation and climate. Mineral composition of parent  materials is probably constant because regional bedrock type is fairly uni-  form. Parent material texture is not constant as many soils, mainly the older  ones, have a surface layer of loess of some thickness. Furthermore, the chem-  ical characteristics of loess as it was deposited at particular sites is unknown.  Some could have been derived from active floodplains and have been un-  weathered; this was the assumption used in calculating the mIPA's. Other  loesses, however, could have been weathered to various degrees. For ex-  ample, one interpretation for the increase in Pa content at the surface of  some soils in the Southern Alps is that loess deposition is taking place at a  rate faster than Pa is being depleted (Harrison, 1982). Vegetation seems rea-  sonably constant throughout the Ben Ohau Range, except that the Spodosol  at location B5 is at such an altitude that it could have been formed under a  former beech forest. Most of the latter forests were eradicated during wide-  spread fires about 700--1000 yr. ago (Malloy et ah, 1963). In the Mt. Cook  area, the problems in assuming purity in the chronosequence are (a) that  precipitation decreases downvalley as reflected in the vegetation change from  alpine scrub to grassland (localities C18 and C19) in that direction, and (b)  that any loess blown onto the sites could have been less weathered than that  in the Ben Ohau Range because of the proximity to the Tasman River flood-  plain, a major source.  In my opinion, however, most of the differences in soil properties can be  attributed to duration of pedogenesis. The bases for that opinion are two-  fold: (a) the significant relationships between properties and time; and (b)  the lack of major soil differences with the climatic contrasts reported here.  The scatter of the individual data points demonstrates that soils are not as  good as weathering-rind thicknesses for approximately dating deposits. More  sites with softs described to uniform depths might increase the usefulness of  soil properties and indices for dating.  Finally the soil formation rates in the New Zealand mountains, as re-  corded in morphology and chemistry, are among the more rapid ones for  mountainous areas. One study showed that the rates of accumulation of Fe  and A1 and depletion of Pa in New Zealand are more rapid than those for the  western U.S.A., the Canadian Arctic, and the Himalaya (Birkeland et al.,    132    1979). Comparably rapid rates also seem to have taken place in the moun-  tains of Alaska (Ugolini, 1966) and Norway (Ellis, 1980), under humid con-  ditions.    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS    I am grateful to many people for help in this project. C.J. Burrows showed  me the most promising field areas, and W.P. McSweeney and Karl and Robin  Birkeland assisted with the field work. A.C. Archer arranged for use of a  DSIR hut, and various run holders allowed us access to their land. Lincoln  College (New Zealand) personnel were especially helpful: Frances Fox,  Stuart Ledguard, John Thomas, and Larry Ward performed the laboratory  analyses,and helpful discussions were had with E.J.B. Cutler, A.S. Campbell,  P.J. Tonkin, and T.W. Walker. V.T. Holliday did some drafting, and E.E.  Larson helped with the computer graphics. J.T. Andrews, J.C. Bockheim,  and J.B.J. Harrison reviewed an early draft of the manuscript and D.R.  Muhs helped with the regressions. The work was supported by National  Science Foundation Grant EAR76-81241, a Faculty Fellowship from the  University of Colorado, and a Visiting Lecturer's stipend from Lincoln  College.    REFERENCES    Archer, A.C., 1970. Pedogenesis and Vegetation Trends in the Elefulvic and Eldefulvic  Zones of the North-East Ben Ohau Range, New Zealand. Ph.D. Thesis, Lincoln Col-  lege, University of Canterbury, New Zealand.  Archer, A.C., 1973. Soils and vegetation of Twin Stream catchment in the Ben Ohau  Range, New Zealand. In: Guidebook for Excursion 7, Central and Southern Canter-  bury of New Zealand, IX Congr., Internat. Assoc. Quat. Res., pp. 117--123.  Bilzi, A.F. and Ciolkosz, E.J., 1977. A field morphology scale for evaluating pedological  development. Soil Sci., 24: 45--48.  Birkeland, P.W., 1981. Soil data and the shape of the lichen growth-rate curve for the  Mt. Cook area (Note). N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 24: 443--445.  Birkeland, P.W., 1982. Subdivision of Holocene glacial deposits, Ben Ohau Range, New  Zealand, using relative-dating methods. Geol. Soc. Am. Bull., 93: 433--449.  Birkeland, P.W., 1984. Soils and Geomorphology. Oxford Univ. Press, New York, N.Y.,  372 pp.  Birkeland, P.W., Walker, A.L., Benedict, J.B. and Fox, F.B., 1979. Morphological and  chemical trends in soil chronosequences: alpine and arctic environments. Agron.  Abstr., 188.  Blakemore, L.C., Searle, P.L. and Daly, B.K., 1977. Methods for chemical analysis of  soils. New Zealand Soil Bur. Sci. Rept., 10A.  Bockheim, J.G., 1980. Solution and use of chronofunctions in studying soil development.  Geoderma, 24: 71--85.  Buntley, G.J. and Westin, F.C., 1965. A comparative study of developmental color in a  Chesnut--Chernozem--Brunizem soil climosequence. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. Proc., 29:  579--582.  Burns, S.F., 1980. Alpine Soil Distribution and Development, Indian Peaks, Colorado  Front Range. Ph.D. Thesis, University of Colorado, Boulder, Colo.    133    Burrows, C.J., 1973. Studies on some glacial moraines in New Zealand, 2. Ages of  moraines of the Mueller, Hooker, and Tasman Glaciers ($79). N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys.,  316: 831--855.  Burrows, C.J., 1975. Late Pleistocene and Holocene moraines of the Cameron Valley,  Arrowsmith Range, Canterbury, New Zealand. Arct. Alpine Res., 7: 125--140.  Burrows, C.J., 1980. Radiocarbon dates for post-Otiran glacial activity in the Mount  Cook region, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 23: 239--248.  Campbell, A.S., 1975. Chemical and mineralogical Properties of a Sequence of Soils  near Reefton, New Zealand. Ph.D. Thesis, Lincoln College, University of Canter-  bury, New Zealand.  Canada Department of Agriculture, 1974. The System of Soil Classification for Canada.  Canada Dept. Agri. Publ., 1455.  Chinn, T.J.H., 1981. Use of rock weathering-rind thickness for Holocene absolute age-  dating in New Zealand. Arct. Alpine Res., 13: 33--45.  Ellis, S., 1980. Physical and chemical characteristics of a podzolic soil formed in Neo-  glacial till, Okstindan, northern Norway. Arct. Alpine Res., 12: 65--72.  Gait, H.S., 1967. Sheet 20 -- Mt. Cook, Geological map of New Zealand (1:250,000).  New Zealand Geological Survey.  Gellatly, A.F., 1984. The use of rock weathering-rind thickness to redate moraines in  Mount Cook National Park, New Zealand. Arct. Alpine Res., 16: 225--232.  Guthrie, R.L. and Witty, J.E., 1982. New designations for soil horizons and layers 'and  the new Soft Survey Manual. Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J., 46: 443--444.  Harden, J.W., 1982. A quantitative index of soil development from field descriptions:  examples from a chronosequence in central California. Geoderma, 28: 1--28.  Harden, J.W. and Taylor, E.M., 1983. A quantitative comparison of soil development in  four climatic regimes. Quat. Res., 20: 342--359.  Harrison, J.B.J., 1982. Soil Periodicity in a Formerly Glaciated Drainage Basin, Ryton  Valley, Craigiebum Range, Canterbury, New Zealand. Thesis, Lincoln College, Uni-  versity of Canterbury, New Zealand.  Jenny, H., 1941. Factors of Soil Formation. McGraw-Hill, New York, N.Y., 281 pp.  Jenny, H., 1980. The Soil Resource. Springer-Verlag, New York, N.Y., 377 pp.  Malloy, B.P.J., Burrows, C.J., Cox, J.E., Johnston, J.A. and Wardle, P., 1963. Distribu-  tion of subfossil forest remains, eastern South Island, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Bot., 1:  68--77.  McKeague, J.A. and Day, J.H., 1966. Dithionite and oxalate-extractable Fe and A1 as  aids in differentiating various classes of soils. Can. J. Soil Sci., 46:13--22.  Mokma, D.L., Jackson, M.L. and Syers, J.K., 1973. Mineralogy of a chronosequence of  soils from greywacke and mica-schist alluvium, Westland, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Sci.,  16: 769--797.  Muhs, D.R., 1982. The influence of topography on the spatial variability of soils in  Mediterranean climates. In: C.E. Thorn (Editor), Space and Time in Geomorphol-  ogy. Allen and Unwin, London, pp. 269--284.  Muhs, D.R., 1984. Intrinsic thresholds in soil systems. Phys. Geogr., 5.  O'Connor, K.F., 1976. An Introduction to the Waitaki. New Zealand Man and the  Biosphere Report no. 1. Tussock Grasslands and Mountain Lands Institute, Lincoln  College, Canterbury, New Zealand, 90 pp.  Ross, C.W., Mew, G. and Searle, P.L., 1977. Soil sequences on two terrace systems in  the North Westland area, New Zealand. N.Z.J. Sci., 20: 231--244.  Schumm, S.A., 1977. The Fluvial System. Wiley, New York, N.Y., 338 pp.  Soil Survey Staff, 1975. Soil Taxonomy: A basic system of soil classification for making  and interpreting soil surveys. U.S. Dept. Agric. Handbook No. 436, 754 pp.  Sp6rli, K.B. and Lillie, A.R., 1974. Geology of the Torlesse supergroup in the northern  Ben Ohau Range, Canterbury. N.Z.J. Geol. Geophys., 17: 115--141.  Stevens, P.R. and Walker, T.W., 1970. The chronosequence concept and soil formation.  Q. Rev. Biol., 45: 333--350.    134    Ugolini, F.C., 1966. Soils. In: A. Mirsky (Editor), Soil Development and Ecological Suc-  cession in a Deglaciated Area of Muir Inlet, Southeast Alaska. Ohio State Univ., Inst.  Polar Studies Rept. 20, pp. 29--72.  Vreeken, W.J., 1975. Principal kinds of chronosequences and their significance in soil  history. J. Soil Sci., 26: 378--394.  Walker, P.H. and Green, P., 1976. Soil trends in two valley fill sequences. Aust. J. Soil  Res., 14: 291--303.  Walker, T.W., 1964. The significance of phosphorus in pedogenesis. In: E.G. Hallsworth  and D.V. Crawford (Editors), Experimental Pedology. Butterworths, London, pp.  295--311.  Walker, T.W. and Syers, J.K., 1976. The fate of phosphorus during pedogenesis. Geo-  derma, 15: 1--19.  Yaalon, D.H., 1975. Conceptual models of pedogenesis: can soil-forming functions be  solved? Geoderma, 14: 189--205.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           AbstractField and laboratory data for two soil chronosequences from the high country of the South Island of New Zealand suggest rapid soil formation rates. The areas studied are the Ben Ohau Range and the Mt. Cook area, where mean annual precipitation is about 1 and 4 m, respectively. Most soil ages are estimated from the thicknesses of rock weathering rinds. Soil chronofunctions are derived for indices that depict field profile and color development, and a modified index of profile anisotropy for laboratory data. Out of a possible 21 chronofunctions, 16 are statistically significant (at the 0.05 level) and 8 are from each area. Most (13) of the chronofunctions best fit a power model, and the remaining ones are split between linear (2) and exponential (1) models. Although problems exist in the purity of the chronosequences because other soil-forming factors are not constant, duration of pedogenesis seems to be the most significant factor in explaining the trends. Despite the large differences in mean annual precipitation between the two areas, many of the derived curves for property vs. time are quite similar. 