Roof Runoff Replenishment of Groundwater in Jinan, ChinaAbstractIn Jinan, China, which is named the Spring City of China, karst groundwater is an important water source for urban supply and maintaining spring flow. However, rapid urbanization in Jinan, China, has caused overexploitation of groundwater and an increase in surface runoff. Consequently, roof runoff harvesting and recycling via the aquifer is being considered to augment the recharge for this area. A pilot-managed aquifer recharge scheme with urban roof runoff was investigated as part of this case study to supplement groundwater recharge. This case study is intended as a pilot for the wider application of managed aquifer recharge at the University of Jinan. The pilot-scale system is composed of the roof catchment, first-flush removal device, regulating tank, filter tank, and recharge well; dimensions and operating parameters of each component were designed by laboratory experiment and hydraulic calculations. The quality of roof runoff is better than road runoff; however, it is still contains a number of hazards. The injected water quality must meet the quality standard for groundwater for the protection of potable groundwater quality. Barriers, or measures to protect water quality, within the treatment train include first-flush removal (first 6 mm rainfall) followed by sedimentation and filtration in a zeolite filter. Water quality monitoring of each barrier and geochemical simulation were used to evaluate the potential influences on groundwater recharge and quality. The rainfall, recharge quantities, and groundwater levels as well as water quality through the recharge process were monitored continuously in June to November 2012. All indexes of treated roof runoff were below the quality standard for groundwater, with the exception of turbidity. Geochemical modeling indicates there is some calcite dissolution after injection but this does not pose a risk to the operational lifetime of the recharge well. However, pretreatment of the source water still needs further improvement to decrease the turbidity to acceptable levels. In addition, water quality risk management is also required for sustainable long-term operation of the scheme.