Variations in efficiency of plastidial RNA editing within ndh transcripts of perennial ryegrass (Lolium perenne) are not linked to differences in drought toleranceProjected climate change is likely to subject key temperate grassland species, such as perennial ryegrass (Lolium perenne) to drought stress. Previous studies have shown that the NADH dehydrogenase complex (NDH) is involved with countering oxidative stress during environmental stresses like drought. We studied RNA editing within plastidial transcripts of the NDH complex in relation to the drought response of several accessions of perennial ryegrass. We found dramatic and reproducible differences in RNA editing efficiency between accessions, but efficiency was not influenced by imposition of drought stress, and a direct relationship between editing behaviour and drought response was not detected. Maintenance of healthy grasslands is essential for efficient livestock production, yet projected climate change is likely to place a heavy drought stress burden on key grassland species, such as perennial ryegrass (Lolium perenne). It is therefore important to gather an in-depth knowledge of the underlying plant response to this stress. The present study is focused on RNA editing (post-transcriptional nucleotide modifications resulting in altered transcripts) within plastidial transcripts of the NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase (NDH) complex (NADH dehydrogenase complex) in relation to the drought response of several accessions of perennial ryegrass. Previous studies have shown that the NDH complex is involved in countering oxidative stress during environmental stresses like drought. Owing to the nature of RNA editing within this complex, the RNA editing machinery could play a potential role in regulating the activity of the NDH complex. The investigation revealed dramatic and reproducible differences in RNA editing efficiency between accessions, but efficiency was not influenced by imposition of drought stress, and a direct relationship between editing behaviour and drought response was not detected.