The effects of neighbouring tree islands on pollinator density and diversity, and on pollination of a wet prairie species, Asclepias lanceolata (Apocynaceae).<ol><li>The Everglades (Florida, USA) is a mosaic of different habitats. Tropical and temperate trees grow on patches of high ground (tree islands) surrounded by lower elevation wetland communities (marl prairie).</li><li>Tree islands of various sizes provide nesting substrate, larval host plants and floral resources for insect pollinators. Herbaceous plants in the open surrounding wetlands may also depend on these pollinators.</li><li>We investigated pollinator diversity and abundances in both tree island and marl prairie habitats using transect sampling methods and estimated pollination success of the milkweed <em>Asclepias lanceolata</em>, an insect-pollinated marl prairie species, in relation to distance from and size of the closest tree island.</li><li>On a total of 11 bayhead tree islands, we found that insect diversity and abundance were greater on the edge of larger tree islands (20-30 m<sup>2</sup>) than on smaller tree islands (5-10 m<sup>2</sup>). Pollinator diversity and abundance in the marl prairie decreased with increasing distance from tree islands.</li><li>Pairs of potted <em>A. lanceolata</em> plants were placed in the marl prairie at distances up to 1000 m from small and large tree islands. Fruit and seed production were highest for plants placed less than 25 m from tree islands and decreased with increasing distance.</li><li>Our results suggest that tree islands are an important source of pollinators for the plants in the tree island and surrounding wetland habitats.</li><li>This landscape-based study illustrates how overall landscape structure affects important biotic interactions, particularly plant-pollinator relationships. Our findings have far-reaching ecological implications for the reproductive success of plants in small, isolated populations that may depend on insect vectors for pollination.</li></ol>