A Canopy-Coverage Method of Vegetational AnalysisThere is as yet little tendency toward standardization of the methods I used in vegetational analysis. Most workers can find at atea of agreement in that 4 mere taxonomic list for a piece of vegetation does not assume much synecologic impottance until each kind of plant is evaluated quantitatively, but the methods of performing the latter are varied, each having an ardent group of advocates. A major cause for this divergence of opinion is that objectives of investigators differ, as when one wishes an appraisal of the amount of merchantable timber on an area, another wishes to evaluate the influence of grazing upon the composition of a pasture, and still another desires to put on record as complete a description as possible of a piece of virgin vegetation before it is destroyed. A second cause of divergence in methodology is that all categories of plants are not equally amenable to appraisal by the same technique. Trees can usually be counted, but counting is impractical where rhizomatous and caespitose taxa' grow together in a community; line interception is excellent for cushion plants and low shrubs, but is impractical for annuals. Diffetences in the outlook of the investigator are also impottant. Some botanists seek only a table of statistics showing the present  composition of dominant trees in a stand, and in consequence ignore all stems under one inch or even under four inches in diameter. The statistic here seems to have become the end point in the process, yielding little to compensate for the labor expended in its attainment. Others look upon the same trees as a dynamic population and accordingly insist upon a type of data that will indicate successional trends. These workers keep separale the data for all age classes with the purpose of gaining clues as to the autecologic taits responsible for the different degrees of success of the various taxa in time and space, thus striving for an interpretation of the statistics. 'Ihe methods followed by these groups are likely to be different, because their philosophies and concepts differ. A fourth problem is raised by the perennial quest for a new method of getting accurate and meaningful data with a minimum expenditure of time. Actually less than one new technique appears in a decade, whereas each year 