Two New Species of Coronigoniella Young from Brazil with Taxonomic and Distributional Notes on the Genus (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae: Cicadellinae)Two new species of Coronigoniella Young are described and illustrated: C. osborni, sp. n., from SE. and S. Brazil (Espírito Santo, Minas Gerais, Rio de Janeiro, and Paraná states), and C. formosa, sp. n., from central W. and SE. Brazil (Goiás and Minas Gerais states, and the Distrito Federal). The presence of a sclerotized plate from the abdominal sternum VIII is reported in females of Coronigoniella for the first time. Taxonomic and morphological notes are given for C. spinosa (Osborn) based on specimens from its type-locality in Mato Grosso State. Tettigonia ruficaput (Walker), a species from Colombia previously considered of uncertain taxonomic position, is transferred to Coronigoniella. Possible host plants of C. osborni, sp. n. are Coleus sp. (Lamiaceae), Symphytum sp. (Boraginaceae), and Vernonia sp. (Asteraceae). The genus Coronigoniella is newly recorded from Alagoas, Bahia, Espírito Santo, Goiás, Minas Gerais, Paraná, and São Paulo states, as well as from the Distrito Federal, Brazil. A map showing the known geographic distribution of the two new species is presented. Resumo Duas novas espécies de Coronigoniella Young são descritas e ilustradas: C. osborni, sp. n., do sudeste e sul do Brasil (estados do Espírito Santo, Minas Gerais, Rio de Janeiro e Paraná), e C. formosa, sp. n., do centro-oeste e sudeste do Brasil (estados de Goiás e Minas Gerais, assim como o Distrito Federal). A presença de uma placa esclerosada do esterno abdominal VIII é registrada em fêmeas de Coronigoniella pela primeira vez. Notas taxonômicas e morfológicas sobre C. spinosa (Osborn) são fornecidas, com base em espécimes provenientes da sua localidade-tipo no Estado do Mato Grosso. Tettigonia ruficaput (Walker), uma espécie da Colômbia anteriormente considerada como de posição taxonômica incerta, é transferida para Coronigoniella. Coleus sp. (Lamiaceae), Symphytum sp. (Boraginaceae) e Vernonia sp. (Asteraceae) são possíveis plantas hospedeiras de C. osborni, sp. n. O gênero Coronigoniella é pela primeira vez registrado nos estados de Alagoas, Bahia, Espírito Santo, Goiás, Minas Gerais, Paraná e São Paulo, assim como no Distrito Federal, Brasil. Um mapa mostrando a distribuição geográfica conhecida das duas novas espécies é apresentado.