Volatiles of myrmecophytic Piper plants signal stem tissue damage to inhabiting Pheidole ant-partners.<ol><li>The major aim of this paper was to explore the mechanistic basis of induced defensive ant response in myrmecophytic <em>Piper </em>species and their ant-partner <em>Pheidole bicornis</em> by combining experimental trials and chemical analysis.</li><li>In field experiments, the response of <em>Pheidole </em>ants to simulated stem-damage of their host plant was documented. Their reaction to other myrmecophytic and non-myrmecophytic <em>Piper</em> species was explored by fixing respective stem sections onto inhabited <em>Piper fimbriulatum</em> individuals. After artificial damage to stems of <em>P. fimbriulatum </em>and stem sections from other myrmecophytic <em>Piper</em>, the number of ants increased to a maximum of 63 individuals on the damaged internode within the first 10 min. By contrast, no or only a poor reaction was elicited by stem sections from the selected non-myrmecophytic <em>Piper</em> species.</li><li>Solid-phase microextraction/gas chromatography-mass spectrometry identified 68 volatile organic compounds (VOCs) which were emitted from wounded stem bark of three myrmecophytic (<em>P. fimbriulatum</em>, <em>P. obliquum</em>, <em>P. sagittifolium</em>) and two non-myrmecophytic (<em>P. hispidum</em>,<em> P. riparense</em>) <em>Piper </em>species, comprising monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, simple aromatic compounds, and green leaf volatiles (GLVs, oxylipins). Despite considerable variation in the VOC profiles, an analysis of similarities (<span class=""smallCaps"">anosim</span>) classified the accumulation of the sesquiterpenes β-caryophyllene, germacrene D and emission of the oxylipin reactive electrophilic species (RES) compounds hexanal, <em>cis</em>-3-hexene-1-ol, 2-hexenal, 2-undecanone and 1-hexanol as characteristic of the myrmecophytic species.</li><li><em>Synthesis</em>. Field experiments showed that mechanical disturbance of myrmecophytic <em>Piper</em> stems is not sufficient to elicit recruitment and alertness of the ant-partner <em>Ph. bicornis</em>, but that specific volatiles released from the host plant are responsible. Analyses of the VOCs identified after simulated stem damage of three myrmecophytic and two non-myrmecophytic <em>Piper </em>species revealed differences in their VOC emission profiles: Only in the myrmecophytic species were induced stress compounds found, such as various oxylipin RES or the sesquiterpene β-caryophyllene, which are typically emitted after plant damage for interplant signalling. Some of these compounds (e.g. hexanal, 1-hexanol) are known to induce alerting and alarm behaviours in several ant species. Our study provides evidence that the VOCs of the <em>Piper</em> host plant may signal stem damage and induce recruitment and alert behaviour of associated <em>Pheidole</em> ants.</li></ol>