A review of advances in hydropedology for application in South AfricaAbstract Hydropedology is internationally a new and fast-growing science. It is therefore pertinent to take heed of developments in this regard to guide current and future research in South Africa. This paper aims to discuss the initiation and advances in the interdisciplinary science of hydropedology. Hydropedology has been defined to interlink pedology, soil physics, and hydrology to bridge scales and to transform soil survey data into soil hydraulic information. As such hydropedology could contribute to the understanding of various environmental and ecological issues. In this regard pedotransfer functions relate simple soil characteristics (e.g. morphological features) to more complex parameters (e.g. soil hydraulic properties) that are relatively difficult to measure. The hydrology of soil types (HOST), published in the United Kingdom to aid hydrological studies and analyses, is a good working example of a pedotransfer function. HOST is based on three conceptual models of water flow processes in the soil: soil on a permeable substrate with a deep aquifer (>2 m); soil on permeable substrate with a shallow water table (<2 m); and soil with an impermeable or semi permeable layer within 1 m of the surface. The three conceptual models are further subdivided into 11 models, which can be subdivided into 29 HOST classes. A useful tool for the summation of long-term soil water content data is the temporal stability of spatially measured soil water contents which is defined as the time invariant average of spatially measured soil water contents and offers a valuable method to study the relationship between soil and water. It has been used to reduce the number of measurements needed in catchment characterization and is therefore also a valuable tool in site selection. Understanding redox reactions in soil and the influence thereof on the development of redoxi-morphic colour patterns, are vital in discerning the relationship between soil water regime and soil morphology. Redoximorphic colour patterns are manifested as redox depletions and/or redox accumulations. The former is evident as grey matrices, cutans, mottles, or pore linings, while the latter is evident as Fe masses, pore linings, nodules, or concretions.