NITROUS OXIDE NITRIFICATION AND DENITRIFICATION 15N ENRICHMENT FACTORS FROM AMAZON FOREST SOILS.The isotopic signatures of <sup>15</sup>N and <sup>18</sup>O in N<sub>2</sub>O emitted from tropical soils vary both spatially and temporally, leading to large uncertainty in the overall tropical source signature and thereby limiting the utility of isotopes in constraining the global N<sub>2</sub>O budget. Determining the reasons for spatial and temporal variations in isotope signatures requires that we know the isotope enrichment factors for nitrification and denitrification, the two processes that produce N<sub>2</sub>O in soils. We have devised a method for measuring these enrichment factors using soil incubation experiments and report results from this method for three rain forest soils collected in the Brazilian Amazon: soil with differing sand and clay content from the Tapajos National Forest (TNF) near Santarém, Pará, and Nova Vida Farm, Rondônia. The <sup>15</sup>N enrichment factors for nitrification and denitrification differ with soil texture and site: −111‰ ± 12‰ and −31‰ ± 11‰ for a clay-rich Oxisol (TNF), −102‰ ± 5‰ and −45‰ ± 5‰ for a sandier Ultisol (TNF), and −10.4‰ ± 3.5‰ (enrichment factor for denitrification) for another Ultisol (Nova Vida) soil, respectively. We also show that the isotopomer site preference (δ<sup>15</sup>N<sup>α</sup> − δ<sup>15</sup>N<sup>β</sup><sub>,</sub> where α indicates the central nitrogen atom and β the terminal nitrogen atom in N<sub>2</sub>O) may allow differentiation between processes of production and consumption of N<sub>2</sub>O and can potentially be used to determine the contributions of nitrification and denitrification. The site preferences for nitrification and denitrification from the TNF-Ultisol incubated soils are: 4.2‰ ± 8.4‰ and 31.6‰ ± 8.1‰, respectively. Thus, nitrifying and denitrifying bacteria populations under the conditions of our study exhibit significantly different <sup>15</sup>N site preference fingerprints. Our data set strongly suggests that N<sub>2</sub>O isotopomers can be used in concert with traditional N<sub>2</sub>O stable isotope measurements as constraints to differentiate microbial N<sub>2</sub>O processes in soil and will contribute to interpretations of the isotopic site preference N<sub>2</sub>O values found in the free troposphere.