Relation between semen quality and rangeland diets of mixed-breed male goats.The impact of range plant toxins on the reproductive performance of female cattle is economically important to the livestock industry. Nevertheless, there is little information on the significance of toxicosis from range plants on semen quality in domestic ruminants. A total of 18 adult mixed-breed bucks under range conditions were used to evaluate the effect of diet composition (microhistological analysis of fecal samples) on some semen characteristics, and blood and fecal components in April and August. Forages in the buck diets were grouped into 2 classes: low or high levels of each plant in the buck diets. Bucks with higher proportion ofAcacia greggii, Flourensia cernua and Lindleya mespiloides in their diets yielded 23–50% less (p<0.05) semen than bucks with low proportion of these shrubs in their diet. Sperm motility was reduced by 3–8 percent units (p<0.05) by high levels of five rangeland shrubs in the buck diets. Bucks consuming high levels of Acacia greggii showed significantly lower percentages of normal sperm (92±10 vs. 96±3; p<0.05) than bucks with low intake of this forage. High proportions of Rhus virens and Solanum elaeagnifolium in the buck diet increased the percentage of normal sperm (5 units, p<0.05) when compared to bucks with low utilization of these forages. Increased intake of Acacia greggii, Dalea bicolor, Opuntia rastrera, Larrea tridentata andCowania plicata reduced percentage of live sperm by 5 units (p<0.05). Blood metabolites analysis showed that increased levels of Acacia greggii and Parthenium incanum were related to better nutritional status of bucks. Zn (−), Cu (−) and glucose (+) were significant predictors of semen volume (r2=0.30). Cu (−) and cholesterol (−) accounted for 37% of the variation in percentage of normal sperms. Forty-four percent of the variation in secondary abnormalities was accounted by Zn (+) and cholesterol (+), whereas fecal N, serum total proteins and creatinine positively affected percentage of live sperms (r2=0.37). These results indicate that semen quality and metabolic profiles of grazing bucks were sensitive to the ingestion of some Chihuahuan desert forages.