Contrasting physiological responses to excess heat and irradiance in two tropical savanna sedgesTrinidad's Aripo Savanna is a rare example of an intact tropical grassland. It is a living laboratory in which to explore the mechanisms used by plants to survive the stress of life in the full glare of the equatorial sun. We found that the dominant species, Lagenocarpus rigidus, avoids overheating not through higher transpiration or more reflective leaf surfaces (as expected), but by altering the size and shape of its leaves to suit each location. This plasticity in leaf morphology is combined with plasticity in cell membrane properties, which allows the leaves to tolerate periods of extreme heat. In the absence of these traits a closely related species Lagenocarpus guianensis, finds its range restricted to the shaded savanna edges where heat and light are less overbearing Tropical hyperseasonal savannas provide a rare example of a tropical climax community dominated by graminoid species. Species living in such savannas are frequently exposed to excess heat and light, in addition to drought and waterlogging, and must possess traits to avoid or tolerate these stress factors. Here we examine the contrasting heat and light stress adaptations of two dominant savanna sedges: Lagenocarpus guianensis, which is restricted to the sheltered forest edge, and Lagenocarpus rigidus, which extends from the forest edge to the open savanna. An ecotone extending from the forest edge to the open savanna was used to assess differences in a range of physiological traits (efficiency of photosystem II, cell membrane thermostability, stomatal conductance, leaf surface reflectance and canopy temperature depression) and a range of leaf functional traits (length : width ratio, specific leaf area and degree of folding). Lagenocarpus guianensis showed significantly less canopy temperature depression than L. rigidus, which may explain why this species was restricted to the forest edge. The range of leaf temperatures measured was within the thermal tolerance of L. guianensis and allowed photosystem II to function normally, at least within the cool forest edge. The ability of L. rigidus to extend into the open savanna was associated with an ability to decouple leaf temperature from ambient temperature combined with enhanced cell membrane thermostability. The high degree of canopy temperature depression seen in L. rigidus was not explained by enhanced stomatal conductance or leaf reflectance, but was consistent with a capacity to increase specific leaf area and reduce leaf length: width ratio in the open savanna. Plasticity in leaf functional traits and in cell membrane thermostability are key factors in the ability of this savanna sedge to survive abiotic stress.