Carbon sequestration and private rangelands: Insights from Utah landowners and implications for policy developmentThe management of private rangelands is important to the overall potential of terrestrial carbon sequestration in the U.S. Previous research has focused on the adoption of innovative range management and conservation practices, but little is known about rangeland owner decision making with respect to carbon sequestration. This study examined Utah rangeland owners’ current management practices in relation to soil carbon management and explored factors influencing their likelihood of participating in a carbon sequestration program. Data were collected from a statewide survey of Utah rangeland owners to assess the relationships between their demographics, landownership characteristics, awareness of and attitudes toward carbon sequestration, beliefs about climate change, and reported likelihood to participate in a relevant program. Thirty-seven percent of respondents were considered potential participants. Higher likelihood of participation was associated with dependence on livestock production, considering it a moderately or very important management objective, having an interest in learning more about it, and valuing its potential economic and climate benefits. Although education and outreach are generally considered important policy tools for promoting conservation, special efforts are needed in the case of carbon sequestration to develop innovative strategies to communicate its concept and related processes with rangeland owners without politicizing the issue. One approach is to tailor education and outreach messages to focus on the ecological benefits of carbon sequestration that are valued by many rangeland owners. Instead of developing new programs, carbon sequestration can also be incorporated into existing conservation programs as a management objective at both federal and state levels. Research is needed to further examine the perceived differences between carbon sequestration and other conventional conservation practices in order to improve the carbon sequestration potential of existing conservation programs and attract wider participation among rangeland owners.