Role of ethylene signalling in the formation of constitutive aerenchyma in primary roots of riceAlthough aerenchyma formed in the roots of some species can be promoted by ethylene, such roots also form a somewhat less extensive aerenchyma under well-aerated conditions. It has been unclear whether ethylene is involved in promoting this constitutive aerenchyma. To test this possibility a novel sandwich method was employed in rice roots. A more extensive aerenchyma was formed on the ACC-treated side. 1-MCP inhibited aerenchyma formation in the presence or absence of ACC. The results indicate that ethylene signaling is involved in aerenchyma development in rice roots and that this may include the regulation of constitutive aerenchyma. Although the extent of aerenchyma (interconnected gas-filled space) formed in the cortex of the roots of some species can be promoted by submergence and ethylene, such roots also form a somewhat less extensive aerenchyma under well-aerated conditions. It has been unclear whether or not ethylene is also involved in promoting this constitutive aerenchyma. To confirm the potential of ethylene to stimulate aerenchyma development and test the possibility that gas regulates constitutive aerenchyma, a novel sandwich method was employed in rice roots. This involved germinating japonica rice (Oryza sativa) caryopses sandwiched between two agar slabs with or without 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) at 1 µM. The roots were then grown for 4 days in the dark in the presence or absence of gaseous 1-methylcyclopropene (1-MCP), an inhibitor of ethylene action. Examination of aerenchyma development by light microscopy demonstrated a more extensive aerenchyma in cross-section on the ACC-treated side that also commenced closer to the root tip. In the presence of 1-MCP at 0.1 or 1 ppm, aerenchyma formation was inhibited in the presence or absence of ACC. 1-Methylcyclopropene also overcame ACC-inhibited root elongation. The results indicate that ethylene signalling is involved in aerenchyma development in primary roots of rice and that this may include the regulation of constitutive aerenchyma. In addition, root elongation was slowed in control roots in the presence of 1 ppm 1-MCP, supporting previous studies demonstrating that endogenous levels of ethylene stimulate root elongation.