Seed limitation in a Panamanian forest.<ol><li>The role of seed limitation in tropical forests remains uncertain owing to the scarcity of experimental evidence. We performed seed addition experiments to assess seed limitation for 32 shade-tolerant tropical forest species and monitored the natural seed rain of 25 of these species for 17 years.</li><li>One, two or five seeds were sown into 0.0079-m<sup>2</sup> plots for large- (<em>n</em> = 5 species), medium- (<em>n</em> = 5) and small-seeded species (<em>n</em> = 22), respectively. The experiment was replicated at 69 sites, placed in groups of three at 23 locations. Seedling establishment was evaluated after 1 and 2 years in paired seed addition and control plots. Natural seedling emergence and understorey plant density were also measured.</li><li>Median natural seed rain was 0.31 seeds m<sup>-;2</sup> year<sup>-;1</sup> per focal species.</li><li>Seed addition enhanced seedling establishment in 31 and 26 of the 32 species after 1 and 2 years, respectively. Mean number of focal species' seedlings after 2 years was 0.002 seedlings in control plots and 0.12, 0.37 and 0.60 seedlings in seed addition plots for large-, medium- and small-seeded species, respectively.</li><li>A 25 seeds added treatment increased seedling establishment by ≥ 2.0-fold over the five seeds added treatment after 2 years.</li><li>Community-wide recruitment and understorey plant density were strongly seed-limited. The natural density of understorey plants averaged 12 plants m<sup>-;2</sup> and was significantly less than for seedlings of the single focal species in plots with ≥ 2 seeds added 2 years earlier.</li><li>The number of established seedlings per seed added was independent of seed size.</li><li>Treatment (adding zero or five seeds), species identity and location all affected seedling establishment for the 11 small-seeded species represented at all sites, with treatment and its interactions accounting for 86% of the explained variation.</li><li>Our results suggest that seed limitation plays a dominant role in seedling recruitment and understorey plant community assembly in tropical forests. Although strong seed limitation may set the stage for species-neutral community assembly, the species differences in seedling establishment rate and its spatial variation demonstrate an important role for species-specific processes.</li></ol>