SPATIAL OCCURRENCE OF A HABITAT-TRACKING SAPROXYLIC BEETLE INHABITING A MANAGED FOREST LANDSCAPE.Because of the dynamic nature of many managed habitats, proper evaluation of conservation efforts calls for models that take into account both spatial and temporal habitat dynamics. We develop a metapopulation model for successional-type systems, in which habitat quality changes over time in a predictable fashion. The occupancy and recruitment of the predatory saproxylic (dependent on dead wood) beetle <em>Harminius undulatus</em> was studied in a managed boreal forest landscape, covering 24 449 ha, in central Sweden. In a first step, we analyzed the beetle's occupancy pattern in relation to stand characteristics, and the amounts of present and past habitat in the surrounding landscape. Managed forest is suitable habitat when ≥60 years old, and immediately after cutting, but not between the ages of 10 and 60 years. The observed occupancy of <em>H. undulatus</em> was positively correlated with the stand's age as habitat. We used a metapopulation model to predict the current probability of occurrence in each forest stand, given the spatiotemporal distribution of suitable forest stands during the last 50 years. Metapopulation parameters were estimated by matching predicted spatial distributions with observed spatial distributions. The model predicted observed spatial distributions better than a similar model that assumed constant habitat quality of each forest stand. Thus, metapopulation models for successional-type systems, such as dead wood dependent organisms in managed forest landscapes, should include habitat dynamics. An estimated 82% of the landscape-wide recruitment took place in managed stands, which covered 87% of the forest area, in comparison with 18% in unmanaged stands, which covered 13% of the forest area. Among the managed stand types, ≥60-year-old stands and 3–7-year-old clear-cuttings contributed to 79% of the total recruitment while 8–59-year-old stands only contributed 3%. The results suggest the following guidelines to improve conditions for <em>H. undulatus</em> and other species with similar habitat requirements: (1) the proportion of the landscape constituted by younger stands should not be allowed to grow too large, (2) the rotation period of managed stands should not be allowed to be too short, and (3) dead wood should be retained and created at final cutting.