The biology of Oncideres humeralis Thorms (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae: Lamiinae) and new Cerambycidae‚ÄìMelastomataceae host‚Äplant associationsBeetles in the genus Oncideres (Cerambycidae: Lamiinae) are girdlers and borers that can cause plant mortality and alterations in the recruitment and age structure of their host‚Äplant populations. Host‚Äplant association, oviposition behavior, development and insect associates of Oncideres humeralis were studied in southeastern Brazil. Oncideres humeralis Thorms used four species of Melastomataceae as host plants. Females oviposited in forks of branches and their larvae fed on the parenchyma tissue of the forks. Histological analyses showed that these sites were the softest parts of the branches and provided an entrance for newly hatched larvae. Females prepared their oviposition sites with their mandibles, and inserted their ovipositors into the slits to deposit one to three eggs under the bark. We found about six oviposition slits per branch and a mean of eight eggs per branch. The larvae bored into and grew inside the girdled branches. Larval development took 10‚Äì12 months. Another cerambycid, Temnopsis megacephala Germ, developed in the thinner sections of branches that had been girdled by O. humeralis and was thus considered a secondary colonizer. Resumo Besouros do g√™nero Oncideres (Cerambycidae: Lamiinae) s√£o serradores a brocadores e podem provocar mortalidade de plantas, altera√ß√µes no recrutamento e na estrutura est√°ria de popula√ß√µes de plantas hospedeiras. Associa√ß√£o com plantas hospedeiras, comportamento de oviposi√ß√£o, desenvolvimento e insetos associados a Oncideres humeralis foram estudados na Sudeste do Brasil. F√™meas colocaram ovos nas bifurca√ß√µes dos ramos e suas larvas alimentaram‚Äse do par√™nquima da forquilha do ramo. An√°lises histol√≥gicas mostraram que este local √© a regi√£o mais mole da forquilha do ramo e proporciona uma porta de entrada para larvas de primeiro est√°gio. F√™meas prepararam estes locais de oviposi√ß√£o com suas mand√≠bulas e inseriram seus ovipositores dentro da fenda para depositar de um a tr√™s ovos sob a casca. Encontramos cerca de seis s√≠tios de oviposi√ß√£o e m√©dia de oito ovos por ramo. As larvas brocaram o interior e se desenvolveram dentro dos ramos serrados. O desenvolvimento larval requereu de 10 a 12 meses. O. humeralis Thorms. usaram quatro esp√©cies de Melastomataceae como plantas hospedeiras. Outro cerambic√≠deo, Temnopsis megacephala Germ. desenvolveram em ramos mais finos n√£o colonizados por O. humeralis, e foi considerado um colonizador secund√°rio.