Performance of Sheep and Goats Fed Arctostaphylos canescens With and Without Polyethylene Glycol Supplementation.<em>Arctostaphylos</em> <em>canescens</em> Eastw. is considered an important element in the chaparral fire matrix and an invasive plant in coniferous forest plantations in California. Previous studies reported that dry matter intake of <em>Arctostaphylos</em> was low, presumably because of its low nutritional quality and high condensed tannin (CT) content. We hypothesized that intake and digestibility of <em>Arctostaphylos</em> could be increased by the provision of a tannin-complexing agent polyethylene glycol (PEG). This study determined the effects of PEG (MW 4000) supplementation on intake (I) and digestibility (D) of <em>Arctostaphylos</em> in goats and sheep. Polyethylene glycol was added to drinking water at four levels (0.3%, 0.15%, 0.05%, and 0%) of body weight (BW). Alfalfa pellets were used as diet supplement at 1.5% of BW. Nutritional quality of <em>Arctostaphylos</em> was low as compared with alfalfa pellets. <em>Arctostaphylos</em> crude protein (CP) levels were low (4.5% vs. 17.9%) and CT concentration was high (23.1% vs. 0%), whereas estimates of in vitro organic matter digestibility (OMD, 36.6%) and metabolizable energy (5.1 MJ·kg<sup>−1</sup> dry matter [DM]) in <em>Arctostaphylos</em> were almost half of those found for alfalfa pellets (70.3% and 9.5 MJ·kg<sup>−1</sup> DM). A curvilinear increase (<em>P</em><0.05) in nutrient intake (per g·d<sup>−1</sup> and per kg BW<sup>0.75</sup>) was observed in goats and sheep as PEG levels increased, although a linear increase (<em>P</em><0.001) was observed in CP intake (g·d<sup>−1</sup>) of <em>Arctostaphylos</em> by goats. Addition of PEG curvilinearly increased (<em>P</em><0.05) digestibility of DM, CP, and neutral and acid detergent fiber, but quadratically increased (<em>P</em><0.05) that of OM in goats and sheep. Incorporation of PEG in drinking water at the level of 0.15% BW in sheep and goats was effective to maximize inactivation of CT in <em>Arctostaphylos.</em> However, the success in adopting this practice as a useful tool in vegetation management programs will depend on the cost-benefit ratio.