Elevated CO2 enhances biological contributions to elevation change in coastal wetlands by offsetting stressors associated with sea-level rise.<ol><li>Sea-level rise, one indirect consequence of increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>, poses a major challenge to long-term stability of coastal wetlands. An important question is whether direct effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on the capacity of marsh plants to accrete organic material and to maintain surface elevations outweigh indirect negative effects of stressors associated with sea-level rise (salinity and flooding).</li><li>In this study, we used a mesocosm approach to examine potential direct and indirect effects of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, salinity and flooding on elevation change in a brackish marsh community dominated by a C<sub>3</sub> species, <em>Schoenoplectus americanus</em>, and a C<sub>4</sub> grass, <em>Spartina patens</em>. This experimental design permitted identification of mechanisms and their role in controlling elevation change, and the development of models that can be tested in the field.</li><li>To test hypotheses related to CO<sub>2</sub> and sea-level rise, we used conventional <span class=""smallCaps"">anova </span>procedures in conjunction with structural equation modelling (SEM). SEM explained 78% of the variability in elevation change and showed the direct, positive effect of <em>S. americanus </em>production on elevation. The SEM indicated that C<sub>3</sub> plant response was influenced by interactive effects between CO<sub>2</sub> and salinity on plant growth, not a direct CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization effect. Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> ameliorated negative effects of salinity on <em>S. americanus</em> and enhanced biomass contribution to elevation.</li><li>The positive relationship between <em>S. americanus </em>production and elevation change can be explained by shoot-base expansion under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> conditions, which led to vertical soil displacement. While the response of this species may differ under other environmental conditions, shoot-base expansion and the general contribution of C<sub>3</sub> plant production to elevation change may be an important mechanism contributing to soil expansion and elevation gain in other coastal wetlands.</li><li><em>Synthesis. </em>Our results revealed previously unrecognized interactions and mechanisms contributing to marsh elevation change, including amelioration of salt stress by elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and the importance of plant production and shoot-base expansion for elevation gain. Identification of biological processes contributing to elevation change is an important first step in developing comprehensive models that permit more accurate predictions of whether coastal marshes will persist with continued sea-level rise or become submerged.</li></ol>