Long-Term Vegetation Productivity and Trend Under Two Stocking Levels on Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland.Vegetation changes were evaluated over an 11-year period (1995-2005) on 2 light- and 2 conservative-stocked Chihuahuan Desert pastures in south central New Mexico. Grazing treatments were applied to the pastures over a 5-year period from 1997 through 2001. Pastures were not grazed in the 1995-1996 and 2002-2005 periods due to drought. During the 1997-2001 grazing period, grazing use of primary forage species averaged 29% and 40% on light- and conservative-stocked rangelands, respectively. Grazing intensity was consistently higher on conservative-stocked than light-stocked pastures. During our study heavy grazing occurred only in 1 year on pastures with conservative stocking. There were no differences in species or species categories (grasses, forbs, shrubs) of autumn standing crop and basal cover between light-and conservative-stocked pastures. Standing crop of total vegetation and perennial grasses showed large fluctuations among the years due to variable rainfall. Under both treatments, total herbaceous standing crop was unchanged, but perennial grass standing crop declined by over 50% when the last 3 years of study were compared with the first 3 years of study. Broom snakeweed (<em>Gutierrezia sarothrae</em> Pursh), a poisonous half shrub, increased in standing crop and cover during the study. Basal cover of total perennial grasses declined less under light than conservative stocking during the study period. However, climatic conditions exerted the overriding influence on vegetation standing crop and basal cover. Our study indicates that light stocking in the Chihuahuan Desert does not increase perennial grass production compared to conservative grazing but it could have a small benefit in maintaining perennial grass cover during drought. We believe our findings have broad application in the Chihauhuan Desert, but caution they might not apply well to other arid rangeland types.