 New records of Bathynellacea (Syncarida, Bathynellidae) in North America: three new species of the genus Pacificabathynella from Montana, USAThree new species of the genus Pacificabathynella Schminke and Noodt, 1988 are described from groundwater aquifers in glaciated North America (Montana, USA). This is the first time that this genus, known previously only from the state of California, has been documented in Montana. Pacificabathynella and Paradoxibathynella Serban, 2000 are the only genera that show sexual dimorphism in thoracopod VI. Pacificabathynella kalispellensis sp. nov. has several unique features: the setal formula of the antenna (0/2+exop/3/12/6/8/5); the setal formula of the maxilla (7/4/7/6); the presence of an epipod on thoracopod II; tufts of setulae and abundant setae on the basipod and endopod of thoracopods I to V; the epipod of thoracopod VIII female three times longer than the basipod; three smooth setae on the exopod of the female thoracopod VIII; eight spines on the endopod of the uropod and the endopod longer than the sympod, whereas the opposite is typical. Pacificabathynella stanfordi sp. nov. has several unique features: only five setae on the exopod of thoracopods II to VII, while six setae are common in the genus; only six setae on the second segment of the first pleopod; five spines on the endopod and seven setae on the exopod of the uropod. Pacificabathynella ruthae sp. nov. is the largest species and has several unique features: antennule equal in size to the antenna, whereas in the rest of the species of the genus the antenna is larger; the projection of the inner lobe of the male thoracopod VIII is bidentate and there are six spines on the endopod and nine setae on the exopod of the uropod. The three new species have slight differences in the pars molaris of the mandible and in thoracopod VIII of males, and there are other minor differences between the females and the species Pacificabathynella sequoiae. The new taxa, together with the new genus Montanabathynella described separately, represent a 30% increase in North American taxa. Considering the glaciated landscape and the fragmented nature of alluvial aquifer habitat, we believe that there is a profound lack of critical knowledge of the biogeography and biodiversity of syncarids in North America.