Soil respiration of the representative artificial forests during the minor growing season in the hilly region of North-ChinaSoil respiration of two representative artificial forests during the minor growing season in the hilly region of North-China, in case of 30 years old Platycladus orientalis and 25 years old Ouercus variabili, were analyzed. Soil respiration rate was measured by Li-8100 automatic monitoring system, and the soil temperature and soil water content was measured by AR-A-ECH automatic monitoring system from Nov. of 2005 to Mar. of 2006. The main results are as follows: ( 1) For both the two artificial forests, soil respiration rate,( SRR) in clear-cloudy day was markedly higher than that in overcast day,but the diurnal variation of SRR was not apparent under the two weather conditions. Daily SRR changed significantly, and characterized with that SRR decreased sharply from November to January of the next year, and maintained at a relatively low value in February, and then increased rapidly after the middle of March. Snowing made SRR rise varying. extents during this season. The average SRR of Platycladus orientalis and Ouercus variabili were 0. 61 mu mol . m(-2) . s(-1) and 0. 39 mu mol . m(-2). s(-1) respectively in the whole minor growing season. (2) Significant relationship were found between the two artificial forests SRR and soil temperatures at the 0, 5,10,15 and 20 cm depth from the soil surface (p < 0.01), which could be well described by exponential equations, and, the best significant relationship happened at the 5 cm depth, where Q(10) of Platycladus orientalis and Ouercus variabili were 2.280 mu mol . m(-2) . s(-1) and 1.602 mu mol. m(-2) . s(-1) respectively. SRR was also correlated with the soil water content (p < 0.01), the regression equation for Platycladus orientalis was linear, but multinomial for Ouercus variabili. SRR was significantly related to soil temperature (Ts) and soil water content ( SW) at 5 cm depth. Ts was the most important factor that effected on SRR for both the two artificial forests through comparing the partial coefficient of Ts and SW at the 5 cm depth.