Effects of mineral characteristics on content, composition, and stability of organic matter fractions separated from seven forest topsoils of different pedogenesisMineral topsoils possess large organic carbon (OC) contents but there is only limited knowledge on the mechanisms controlling the preservation of organic matter (OM) against microbial decay. Samples were taken from the uppermost mineral topsoil horizon (0 to 5 cm) of seven sites under mature deciduous forest showing OC contents between 69 and 164 g kg− 1 and a wide range in mineral characteristics. At first, organic particles and the water-extractable OM were removed from the soil samples. Thereafter, Na-pyrophosphate extractable organic matter (OM(PY)), assumed to be indicative for OM bound via cation mediated interactions, and the OM remaining in the extraction residue (OM(ER)), supposed to be indicative for OM occluded in mechanically highly stable micro-aggregates, were sequentially separated and quantified. The composition of OM(PY) and OM(ER) was analyzed by FTIR and their stability by 14C measurements. The OC remaining in the extraction residues accounted for 38 to 59% of the bulk soil OC (SOC) suggesting a much larger relevance of OM(ER) for the OM dynamic in the analyzed soils as compared with OM(PY) that accounted for 1.6 to 7.5% of the SOC. The FTIR analyses revealed a lower relative proportion of Cdouble bond; length as m-dashO groups in OM(ER) compared to OM(PY) indicating differences in the degree of microbial processing between these fractions. Correlation analyses suggest an increase in the stability of OM(PY) with the soil pH and contents of Na-pyrophosphate soluble Fe, Al, and Mg and an increase in the stability of OM(ER) with the soil pH and the contents of clay and oxalate-soluble Fe and Al. Despite the detected influence of soil mineral characteristics on the turnover of OM(PY) and OM(ER), the Δ14C signatures indicated mean residence times less than 100 years. The presence of less stabilized OM in these fractions can be derived from methodological uncertainties and/or the fast cycling compartment of mineral-associated OM.