Genetic diversity of an Azorean endemic and endangered plant species inferred from inter-simple sequence repeat markersPicconia azorica is an endangered endemic species of the Azores whose hard and high density wood is very appreciated for the production of toys, agricultural tools, furniture and religious statuary. Its renewed economic interest represents a good opportunity for establishing conservation programmes. To contribute with information useful for the decision making we performed the genetic analysis of 230 samples from 11 populations collected in three Azorean islands. The majority of the genetic variability was found within populations and no genetic structure was detected between populations and between islands, indicating that the oceanic barriers do not greatly affect gene flow. Knowledge of the levels and distribution of genetic diversity is important for designing conservation strategies for threatened and endangered species so as to guarantee sustainable survival of populations and to preserve their evolutionary potential. Picconia azorica is a valuable Azorean endemic species recently classified as endangered. To contribute with information useful for the establishment of conservation programmes, the genetic variability and differentiation among 230 samples from 11 populations collected in three Azorean islands was accessed with eight inter-simple sequence repeat markers. A total of 64 polymorphic loci were detected. The majority of genetic variability was found within populations and no genetic structure was detected between populations and between islands. Also the coefficient of genetic differentiation and the level of gene flow indicate that geographical distances do not act as barriers for gene flow. In order to ensure the survival of populations in situ and ex situ management practices should be considered, including artificial propagation through the use of plant tissue culture techniques, not only for the restoration of habitat but also for the sustainable use of its valuable wood.