Rapid root closure after fire limits fine root responses to elevated atmospheric CO2 in a scrub oak ecosystem in central Florida, USA.Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) often stimulates the growth of fine roots, yet there are few reports of responses of intact root systems to long-term CO<sub>2</sub> exposure. We investigated the effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on fine root growth using open top chambers in a scrub oak ecosystem at Kennedy Space Center, Florida for more than 7 years. CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment began immediately after a controlled burn, which simulated the natural disturbance that occurs in this system every 10-15 years. We hypothesized that (1) root abundance would increase in both treatments as the system recovered from fire; (2) elevated CO<sub>2</sub> would stimulate root growth; and (3) elevated CO<sub>2</sub> would alter root distribution. Minirhizotron tubes were used to measure fine root length density (mm cm<sup>-;2</sup>) every three months. During the first 2 years after fire recovery, fine root abundance increased in all treatments and elevated CO<sub>2</sub> significantly enhanced root abundance, causing a maximum stimulation of 181% after 20 months. The CO<sub>2</sub> stimulation was initially more pronounced in the top 10 cm and 38-49 cm below the soil surface. However, these responses completely disappeared during the third year of experimental treatment: elevated CO<sub>2</sub> had no effect on root abundance or on the depth distribution of fine roots during years 3-7. The results suggest that, within a few years following fire, fine roots in this scrub oak ecosystem reach closure, defined here as a dynamic equilibrium between production and mortality. These results further suggest that elevated CO<sub>2</sub> hastens root closure but does not affect maximum root abundance. Limitation of fine root growth by belowground resources - particularly nutrients in this nutrient-poor soil - may explain the transient response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>.