Seasonal Niche Dynamics in Coexisting Rodents of the Brazilian CerradoMicrohabitat selection, diet breadth and overlap in seasons of low and high population density were used to evaluate the likelihood of interspecific competition in a rodent assemblage of the cerrado, a tropical savannah of Brazil. Four species of rodents – one Echimyidae and three Muridae – were live-trapped from September 1985 to September 1986 in a 1.32 ha grid in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Microhabitat preference and space niche were measured by captures in six microhabitat categories, and food niche by the relative proportions in the feces of monocot, dicot, seed, and arthropod remains. Clyomys bishopi, a herbivore, was the most specialized species in diet and microhabitat, whereas Oligoryzomys eliurus and Bolomys lasiurus were the most generalist species in microhabitat and diet respectively. Overall, species had different microhabitat preferences. Breadth and overlap in microhabitat preference were higher in the high-density season, whereas breadth of diet was higher in the low-density season. Microhabitat breadth and mean microhabitat overlap were positively correlated between species, but not diet breadth and mean diet overlap when C. bishopi was excluded. Interspecific competition for microhabitats is unlikely, but could occur for food between the three murid species in low density seasons. Resumo Seleção de microhabitats, largura e sobreposição de dietas em estações de baixa e alta densidade foram utilizados para avaliar a probabilidade de competição interespecífica num agrupamento de roedores do cerrado. Quatro roedores – um Echimyidae e três Muridae – foram marcados e recapturados de setembro de 1985 a setembro de 1986 numa grade de armadilhas de 1.32 ha, no Estado de São Paulo, Brazil. Preferência de microhabitats e nicho espacial foram medidos por capturas em seis categorias de microhabitats; nicho alimentar pelas proporções relativas de restos nas fezes de monocotiledôneas, dicotiledôneas, sementes e artrópodes. Clyomys bishopi, um herbívoro, foi o mais especializado em dieta e microhabitat, enquanto Oligoryzomys eliurus e Bolomys lasiurus foram os mais generalistas em microhabitat e dieta, respectivamente. As espécies tiveram preferências distintas por microhabitats, com excessão de C. bishopi e B. lasiurus. Largura e sobreposição em preferência de microhabitats foram maiores na estação de alta densidade, enquanto largura de dieta foi maior na estação de baixa densidade. Largura e sobreposição média de nichos foram correlacionados positivamente para microhabitat, mas não dieta. Competição interespecífica por microhabitats é improvável, mas poderia ocorrer por alimento entre as três espécies de murídeos em estações de baixa densidade.