Comparison of field methods for measuring soil respiration: a static alkali absorption method and two dynamic closed chamber methodsThe objectives of the, present study were to compare the static alkali absorption (AA) and dynamic closed chamber (DC) methods for measuring soil respiration, and to evaluate the effects of methodological differences on estimating annual mean soil respiration rate in a natural forest. For the AA method, we used Kirita's method [Jpn. J. Ecol. 21 (1971) 119] using an alkali-soaked sponge disc that covers nearly the same area as that covered by a chamber. For the DC method, we used both the LI-6200 system (DC-62 method) and the newer LI-6400 system (DC-64 method) (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA). Comparative measurements were conducted on five occasions during the study period (November 1998-October 1999) at a Quercus serrata forest in Japan. Daily mean soil respiration rates,obtained by the AA, DC-62 and DC-64 methods for a 24 h period were in the ranges 205-578, 147-629 and 165-734 mg CO2 m(-2) h(-1), respectively. The daily mean soil respiration rates obtained by the AA method were 79-128% of those obtained by the DC-64 method. When the daily mean soil respiration rate obtained by the DC-64 method was below 300 mg CO2 m(-2) h(-1), the daily mean soil respiration rate obtained by the AA method was an average of 26% higher than that obtained by the DC-64 method. When the daily mean soil respiration rate obtained by the DC-64 method was above 300 mg CO2 m(-2) h(-1), the daily mean soil respiration rate obtained by the AA method was an average of 19% lower than that obtained by the DC-64 method. However, at the present site, there was a little difference between the two methods as for estimating annual mean soil respiration rate, and therefore the AA method improved by Kirita [Jpn. J. Ecol. 21 (1971) 119] is suggested to be a useful method for estimating annual mean soil respiration in the forest. The daily mean soil respiration rates obtained by the DC-62 method were systematically 10-24% lower (an average of 15% lower) than those obtained with the DC-64 method, and the annual mean rate was lower than that estimated by the AA method. (C) 2002 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.