Long-term changes in organic carbon and nutrients of an Ultisol under rice cropping in southeast ChinaIt is well known that the availability of nutrients in red soils (equivalent to Ultisols and some of the Alfisols and Oxisols in the soil taxonomy of USA) changes after conversion of upland to irrigated rice (Oryza sativa L.) production, but long-term changes in carbon (C) and nutrients are not well documented. To characterize changes in C and nutrients in paddy fields on a Quaternary red clay (clayey, kaolinitic thermic typic plinthudults) during long-term rice cropping, we measured total C, nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P) and potassium (K), particulate organic matter (POM), N in the POM, potential mineralized N, available P, as well as other properties (pH, exchangeable cations, effective cation exchange capacity (ECEC), aggregate stability) in the plow layer (0–15 cm) of 66 rice fields with rice-cultivation time ranging from 2 to 100 years. Total C, N, and P distributions were also determined in six soil profiles with rice-cultivation times of 2, 5, 19, 48, 68, and 100 years, respectively. Significant increases in organic C, total N, and P concentrations in plow layer were found in the first 30–40 years of rice cropping, accompanied by increases in available P and potential mineralized N, exchangeable Ca, Mg, Na, base saturation, and water-stable aggregates, and decreases in total K and clay content. The C/N ratio of organic matter tended to decrease in the first 20 years of rice cropping, and remained constant at approximately 10, whereas the ratio of humic acid to fulvic acid (H/F ratio) increased gradually to about 1 after 50 years of rice cropping. Long-term rice cropping elevated C, N, and P in the plow layer and increased accumulation of C, N, and P in the subsurface soils. The results indicate: (i) long-term rice cropping improved soil fertility as evidenced by neutralization of soil acidity, and increases in ECEC, organic C content, and H/F ratio; (ii) imbalance of fertilization by high N and low K, as revealed by decreased soil K and increased soil N; (iii) long-term rice cropping caused downward movement of organic C, N, and P, which may result in environmental impacts.