ADAPTIVE REVERSALS IN ACID TOLERANCE IN COPEPODS FROM LAKES RECOVERING FROM HISTORICAL STRESS.opogenic habitat disturbance can often lead to rapid evolution of environmental tolerances in taxa that are able to withstand the stressor. What we do not understand, however, is how species respond when the stressor no longer exists, especially across landscapes and over a considerable length of time. Once anthropogenic disturbance is removed and if there is an ecological trade-off associated with local adaptation to such an historical stressor, then evolutionary theory would predict evolutionary reversals. On the Boreal Shield, tens of thousands of lakes acidified as a result of SO<sub>2</sub> emissions, but many of these lakes are undergoing chemical recovery as a consequence of reduced emissions. We investigated the adaptive consequences of disturbance and recovery to zooplankton living in these lakes by asking (1) if contemporary evolution of acid tolerance had arisen among <em>Leptodiaptomus minutus</em> copepod populations in multiple circum-neutral lakes with and without historical acidification, (2) if <em>L. minutus</em> populations were adaptively responding to reversals in selection in historically acidified lakes that had recovered to pH 6.0 for at least 6–8 years, and (3) if there was a fitness trade-off for <em>L. minutus</em> individuals with high acid tolerance at circum-neutral pH.<br><br><em>L. minutus</em> populations had higher acid tolerances in circum-neutral lakes with a history of acidification than in local and distant lakes that were never acidified. However, copepods in circum-neutral acid-recovering lakes were less acid-tolerant than were copepods in lakes with longer recovery time. This adaptive reversal in acid tolerance of <em>L. minutus</em> populations following lake recovery was supported by the results of a laboratory experiment that indicated a fitness trade-off in copepods with high acid tolerances at circum-neutral pH. These responses appear to have a genetic basis and suggest that <em>L. minutus</em> is highly adaptive to changes in environmental conditions. Therefore, restoration managers should focus on removing environmental stressors, and adaptable species will be able to reverse evolutionary responses to environmental disturbance in the years following recovery.