Developing clear-sky, cloud and cloud shadow mask for producing clear-sky composites at 250-meter spatial resolution for the seven MODIS land bands over Canada and North AmericaA new technology was developed at the Canada Centre for Remote Sensing (CCRS) for generating Canada-wide and North America continental scale clear-sky composites at 250 m spatial resolution for all seven MODIS land spectral bands (B1–B7). The MODIS Level 1B (MOD02) swath level data are used as input to circumvent the problems with image distortion in the mid latitude and polar regions inherent to the global sinusoidal (SIN) projection utilized for the standard MODIS data products. The MODIS 500 m land bands B3 to B7 are first downscaled to 250 m resolution using an adaptive regression and normalization scheme for compatibility with the 250 m bands B1 and B2. A new method has been developed to produce the mask of clear-sky, cloud and cloud shadow at 250 m resolution. It shows substantial advantages in comparison with the MODIS 250 m standard cloud masks. The testing of new cloud mask showed that it is in reasonable agreement with the MODIS 1-km standard product once it is aggregated to 1-km scale, while the cloud shadow detection looks more reliable with the new methodology. Nevertheless, more quantitative analyses of the presented scene identification technique are required to understand its performance over the range of input scenes in various seasons. The new clear-sky compositing scheme employs a scene-dependent decision matrix. It is demonstrated that this new scheme provides better results than any others based on a single compositing criterion, such as maximum NDVI or minimum visible reflectance. To account for surface bi-directional properties, two clear-sky composites for the same time period are produced by separating backward scattering and forward scattering geometries, which separate pixels with the sun-satellite relative azimuth angles within 90°–270° and outside of this range. Comparison with Landsat imagery and with MODIS standard composite products demonstrated the advantage of the new technique for screening cloud and cloud shadow, and generating high spatial resolution MODIS clear-sky composites. The new data products are mapped in the Lambert Conformal Conic (LCC) projection for Canada and the Lambert Azimuthal Equal-Area (LAEA) projection for North America. Presently this activity is limited to MODIS/TERRA due to known problems with band-to-band registration and noisy SWIR channels on MODIS/AQUA.