Agriculture Vulnerability to Climate Change in a Snowmelt-Driven Basin in Semiarid ChileAbstractThe Limarí River basin is one of the most important watersheds in north-central Chile (30°S). Its headwaters lie at the top of the subtropical Andes (>5,000  m above sea level) and the river flows westward into the Pacific Ocean over a length of approximately 200 km. This basin has a marked snowmelt-driven hydrological regime and, in spite of the arid conditions that characterize this region, holds more than 50,000 ha of highly productive agricultural land thanks to its irrigation infrastructure and three interconnected reservoirs. Like many semiarid regions around the world, north-central Chile is expected to become warmer and drier during the 21st century as a consequence of ongoing anthropogenic climate change. The associated reduction in streamflow, changes in hydrograph timing, and enhanced evapotranspiration will undoubtedly threaten agriculture in the Limarí basin and elsewhere in semiarid Chile. In this paper, the effect of temperature and precipitation on surface hydrology, performance of water infrastructure, and irrigation coverage in the Limarí basin is investigated by using the water evaluation and planning (WEAP) model. WEAP was calibrated by using current climate and agriculture patterns, and then forced with a set of 30-year-long climate scenarios, each of them obtained by adding a temperature and precipitation perturbation to the historical time series. This delta approach allows (1) determination of the sensitivity of selected variables to climate change, and (2) obtaining a projection of the effects in irrigation coverage expected for the near and far future (2010–2040 and 2070–2100, respectively). Both aspects are investigated for agricultural districts with varying access to irrigation infrastructure and groundwater; this exercise highlights the relevance of added storage and innovative conjunctive use of surface and groundwater resources for improving the resilience and adaptability of irrigated agriculture in the face of a changing climate.