Vegetative growth and cluster development in Shiraz grapevines subjected to partial root-zone coolingGrapevine roots can be exposed to a range of temperatures at any particular moment because the root system can explore large volumes of soil over great depths and distances. A split-pot experiment was designed to assess how vegetative and reproductive development respond to partial and whole root-zone warming following winter dormancy. Simultaneous cooling and warming of parts of the root system slowed shoot elongation, leaf expansion and berry development compared to plants with a fully warmed root-zone, but not to the same extent as those with a fully cooled root-zone. Heterogeneity in root-zone temperature both vertically and horizontally may contribute to the uneven vegetative and reproductive growth often observed across vineyards. An experiment was designed to assess whether the warmed half of a grapevine root zone could compensate for the cooled half in terms of vegetative growth and reproductive development. We divided the root system of potted Shiraz grapevines bilaterally and applied either a cool or a warm treatment to each half from budburst to fruit set. Shoot growth and inflorescence development were monitored over the season. Simultaneous cooling and warming of parts of the root system decreased shoot elongation, leaf emergence and leaf expansion below that of plants with a fully warmed root zone, but not to the same extent as those with a fully cooled root zone. Inflorescence rachis length, flower number and berry number after fertilization were smaller only in those vines exposed to fully cooled root zones. After terminating the treatments, berry enlargement and the onset of veraison were slowed in those vines that had been exposed to complete or partial root-zone cooling. Grapevines exposed to partial root-zone cooling were thus delayed in vegetative and reproductive development, but the inhibition was greater in those plants whose entire root system had been cooled.