PLANT AND MICROBE CONTRIBUTION TO COMMUNITY RESILIENCE IN A DIRECTIONALLY CHANGING ENVIRONMENT.To understand the role biota play in resilience or vulnerability to environmental change, we investigated soil, plant, and microbial responses to a widespread environmental change, increased nitrogen (N). Our aim was to test the plant–soil threshold hypothesis: that changed biotic structure influences resilience to accumulated changes in N. For six years, we removed one of two codominant species, <em>Geum rossii</em> and <em>Deschampsia caespitosa</em>, in moist-meadow alpine tundra in Colorado, USA. We also manipulated nutrient availability by adding carbon (C) or N, separately and in combination with the species removals.<br><br>Consistent with our hypothesis, <em>Geum</em> was associated with soil feedbacks that slowed rates of N cycling and <em>Deschampsia</em> with feedbacks that increased rates of N cycling. After a four-year initial resilience period, <em>Geum</em> dramatically declined (by almost 70%) due to increasing N availability. In contrast, <em>Deschampsia</em> abundance did not respond to changes in N supply; it only responded to the removal of <em>Geum</em>. Forbs and graminoids responded more positively to <em>Deschampsia</em> removal than to <em>Geum</em> removal, indicating stronger competitive effects by <em>Deschampsia</em>. The changed biotic interactions appear to have community-level consequences: after six years of <em>Geum</em> (but not <em>Deschampsia</em>) removal, evenness of the community declined by over 35%.<br><br>Increased N affected the soil–microbial feedbacks, particularly in association with <em>Geum</em>. Microbial biomass N declined at higher N, as did the activities of two C-acquiring and one N-acquiring extracellular microbial enzymes. In the presence of <em>Geum</em>, N fertilization slowed the activity of phenol oxidase, a tannin-degrading enzyme, suggesting that microbes shift from degrading <em>Geum</em>-derived compounds. In the absence of <em>Geum</em>, acid phosphatase activity increased, suggesting increased phosphorus limitation in association with <em>Deschampsia</em>.<br><br>With continued N deposition forecast for this system, these results suggest that initial resilience of <em>Geum</em> to increased N will be overwhelmed through elimination of microbial feedbacks. Once <em>Geum</em> declines, the loss will indirectly facilitate <em>Deschampsia</em> via competitive release. Because <em>Deschampsia</em> exerts strong competitive effects on subordinate species, increased <em>Deschampsia</em> abundance may be accompanied by a community-wide drop in diversity. We conclude that plant–soil feedbacks through the microbial community can influence vulnerability to exogenous changes in N and contribute to threshold dynamics.