TREE SPECIES AND MYCORRHIZAL ASSOCIATIONS INFLUENCE THE MAGNITUDE OF RHIZOSPHERE EFFECTS.ous research on the effects of tree species on soil processes has focused primarily on the role of leaf litter inputs. We quantified the extent to which arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) and ectomycorrhizal (ECM) tree species influence soil microbial activity and nutrient availability through rhizosphere effects. Rhizosphere soil, bulk soil, and fine roots were collected from 12 monospecifc plots (six AM and six ECM tree species) planted on a common soil at the Turkey Hill Plantations in Dryden, New York.<br><br>Rhizosphere effects were estimated by the percentage difference between rhizosphere and bulk soil samples for several assays. Rhizosphere effects on soil microbes and their activities were significant for ECM species but in only a few cases for AM species. In AM tree species, microbial biomass, net N mineralization, and phosphatase enzyme activity in the rhizosphere were 10–12% greater than in bulk soil. In ECM tree species, rhizosphere effects for microbial biomass, C mineralization rates, net N mineralization, and phosphatase activity were 25–30% greater than bulk soil, and significantly greater than AM rhizosphere effects. The magnitude of rhizosphere effects was negatively correlated with the degree of mycorrhizal colonization in AM tree species (<em>r</em> = −0.83) and with fine root biomass (<em>r</em> = −0.88) in ECM tree species, suggesting that different factors influence rhizosphere effects in tree species forming different mycorrhizal associations.<br><br>Rhizosphere effects on net N mineralization and phosphatase activity were also much greater in soils with pH < 4.3 for both AM and ECM tree species, suggesting that soil pH and its relation to nutrient availability may also influence the magnitude of rhizosphere effects. Our results support the idea that tree roots stimulate nutrient availability in the rhizosphere, and that systematic differences between AM and ECM may result in distinctive rhizosphere effects for C, N, and P cycling between AM and ECM tree species.