Effect of nitrogen fertilization on soil CH(4) and N(2)O fluxes, and soil and bole respirationThe effect of nitrogen addition, through deposition or fertilization, on ecosystem processes responsible for storing and releasing greenhouse gasses (GHG) CO(2), CH(4) and N(2)O are poorly understood. We measured the effects of winter application of 200 kg N ha(-1) to a near-end-of-rotation coastal Douglas-fir stand on soil CH(4) and N(2)O fluxes, soil and bole respiration (R(s) and R(b), respectively), and soil CH(4) and N(2)O concentrations. Fertilization resulted in a significant decrease in CH4 uptake and changed a small uptake of N(2)O to significant emissions. Based on the average reduction of 2 mu mol m(-2)h(-1) CH(4) uptake with N fertilization, from an average of 4 mu mol m(-2)h(-1) I with no N fertilization, the approximate first-year annual reduction was estimated to be 2.8 kg CH(4)ha(-1). In comparison, net annual increase in N(2)O emissions with N fertilization was 17.6 kg N(2)O ha-1. Calculations showed that fertilizer-induced net GHG emissions due to the reduction in CH(4) uptake and the increase in N(2)O emissions was 0.07 and 5.3 t CO(2) ha-1 equivalents (CO(2-Eqv)). respectively, indicating that the reduction in CH(4) uptake was much less important than the increase in N(2)O emissions. Contrary to expectation, the annual loss of 17.6 kg N(2)O ha(-1) from this winter application of N was slightly higher than the 15.7 kg N(2)O ha(-1) loss following spring application of N in the previous year. N fertilization also resulted in small increase in soil respiration, confirming our previous results. Temporal dynamics of Rb matched those of soil respiration and N(2)O fluxes. Fertilization resulted in a small but persistent increase in Rb over the first 4-5 months. While soil temperature was the main control of soil N(2)O and CO(2) fluxes as well as R(b), CH(4) uptake was better correlated to soil water content, i.e.. soil gas diffusivity and gas exchange with the atmosphere. (C) 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.