The influence of climate on CO2 and CH4 emissions from organic soilsBoth carbon dioxide and methane, major contributors to the greenhouse effect, are produced by soils as the end-products of decay of organic matter, In response to global temperature changes, decomposition processes may increase, creating the potential for a positive feedback mechanism. CO2 and CH4 emissions from two peat sites in Scotland were monitored and related to temperature and moisture. Bad a Cheo is a deep Sphagnum bog in 'The Flow Country', Caithness with a small area planted with Sitka spruce and Lodgepole pine. Glensaugh is a hill blanket pear at the edge of the Grampian Mountains, the primary vegetation being heather with a mixture of grasses. A wetter area also contained Sphagnum. CO2 emission rates at both sites showed a marked seasonal pattern and parallelled the ambient soil temperature, Values ranged from 10 mg C m(-2) h(-1) in the indigenous bog area at Bad a Cheo in March to 190 mg C m(-2) h(-1) in the adjoining forest area in July. At Glensaugh values in the dry area tended to be about 40% greater than those in the wet area while at Bad a Cheo those in the forest plantation were on average 90% greater than those in the indigenous bog area. The effect of temperature was modelled using the Arrhenius equation. The resulting activation energy varied between 81 kJ mol(-1) for the Bad a Cheo bog area to 124 kJ mol(-1) for the Glensaugh wet area. Q(10) values were estimated as 3.3 and 6.1, respectively. These seemed to be greater than many published values for mineral soils. Significant CH4 emissions were only found for the Bad a Cheo bog area and ranged from being undetectable in January to 1.05 mg C m(-2) h(-1) in September. Linear regression using the Arrhenius model showed that only 23% of the variation in CH4 flux could be explained by temperature with a Q(10) of 2.8. Using the responses to temperature as determined above it was possible to estimate the increase in carbon dioxide emission from these sites for any given rise in annual mean temperature (Delta T), For Delta T = 2.5 degrees C the increase in CO2 emission was 36% and 59% for the Bad a Cheo bog and Glensaugh wet areas, respectively. For Delta T = 4.5 degrees C, a doubling of CO2 emissions was predicted which, when extended over the global range of pear and organic soils, could have a significant effect on the contribution of soil carbon to atmospheric CO2. Repeating the above calculations for methane gave an increase 60% for Delta T = 4.5 degrees C. However, the main effect on methane would be due future changes to the moisture content. Land use changes such as drainage and afforestation can also have a major effect in reducing methane emissions.