Leaf litter production and decomposition in a poplar short-rotation coppice exposed to free air CO2 enrichment (POPFACE).The capacity of forest ecosystems to sequester C in the soil relies on the net balance between litter production above, as well as, below ground, and decomposition processes. Nitrogen mineralization and its availability for plant growth and microbial activity often control the speed of both processes. Litter production, decomposition and N mineralization are strongly interdependent. Thus, their responses to global environmental changes (i.e. elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, climate, N deposition, etc.) cannot be fully understood if they are studied in isolation. In the present experiment, we investigated litter fall, litter decomposition and N dynamics in decomposing litter of three <em>Populus</em> spp., in the second and third growing season of a short rotation coppice under FACE. Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> did not affect annual litter production but slightly retarded litter fall in the third growing season. In all species, elevated CO<sub>2</sub> lowered N concentration, resulting in a reduction of N input to the soil via litter fall, but did not affect lignin concentrations. Litter decomposition was studied in bags incubated <em>in situ</em> both in control and FACE plots. Litter lost between 15% and 18% of the original mass during the eight months of field incubation. On average, litter produced under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> attained higher residual mass than control litter. On the other end, when litter was incubated in FACE plots it exhibited higher decay rates. These responses were strongly species-specific. All litter increased their N content during decomposition, indicating immobilization of N from external sources. Independent of the initial quality, litter incubated on FACE soils immobilized less N, possibly as a result of lower N availability in the soil. Indeed, our results refer to a short-term decomposition experiment. However, according to a longer-term model extrapolation of our results, we anticipate that in Mediterranean climate, under elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>, soil organic C pool of forest ecosystems may initially display faster turnover, but soil N availability will eventually limit the process.