A preliminary phylogenetic analysis of the New World Helopini (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae, Tenebrioninae) indicates the need for profound rearrangements of the classificationAbstract Helopini is a diverse tribe in the subfamily Tenebrioninae with a worldwide distribution. The New World helopine species have not been reviewed recently and several doubts emerge regarding their generic assignment as well as the naturalness of the tribe and subordinate taxa. To assess these questions, a preliminary cladistic analysis was conducted with emphasis on sampling the genera distributed in the New World, but including representatives from other regions. The parsimony analysis includes 30 ingroup species from America, Europe and Asia of the subtribes Helopina and Cylindrinotina, plus three outgroups, and 67 morphological characters. Construction of the matrix resulted in the discovery of morphological character states not previously reported for the tribe, particularly from the genitalia of New World species. A consensus of the 12 most parsimonious trees supports the monophyly of the tribe based on a unique combination of characters, including one synapomorphy. None of the subtribes or the genera of the New World represented by more than one species (Helops Fabricius, Nautes Pascoe and Tarpela Bates) were recovered as monophyletic. Helopina was recovered as paraphyletic in relation to Cylindrinotina. One Nearctic species of Helops and one Palearctic species of Tarpela (subtribe Helopina) were more closely related to species of Cylindrinotina. A relatively derived clade, mainly composed by Neotropical species, was found; it includes seven species of Tarpela, seven species of Nautes, and three species of Helops, two Nearctic and one Neotropical. Our results reveal the need to deeply re-evaluate the current classification of the tribe and subordinated taxa, but a broader taxon sampling and further character exploration is needed in order to fully recognize monophyletic groups at different taxonomic levels (from subtribes to genera).