Ecosystem CO2 flux over two growing seasons for a sub-Boreal clearcut 5 and 6 years after harvestWe measured the ecosystem-level growing season CO2 fluxes for a 6-year-old vegetated sub-Boreal clearcut from 24 May to 20 September 2000, and compared the results to CO2 fluxes from the same clearcut in 1999 (27 June-3 September). Two independent approaches were used to measure ecosystem CO2 flux for both years. A Bowen ratio energy balance (BREB) method was contrasted with a second approach using component fluxes. The Component model approach was based on scaling up from regressions relating in situ CO2 flux measurements for conifer seedlings (Picea glauca x engelmannii), as well as representative herbaceous (Chamerion angustifolium), woody (Lonicera involucrata) plant species and soil surface CO2 efflux to microclimate conditions. The BREB method and Component model estimated the clearcut to be a source of CO2 6 years post-harvest (24 May-20 September 2000) in amounts of 142 g C m(-2) (1.4 t ha(-1)) and 103 g C m(-2) (1.0 t ha(-1)), respectively. The positive net ecosystem CO2 fluxes over the growing season resulted from a large soil surface CO2 efflux (686 g C m(-2)) that surmounted the photosynthetic CO2 uptake for the clearcut. The photosynthetic CO2 uptake partially compensated for the soil surface losses: the conifer seedlings, herbaceous plants and woody shrubs were estimated to uptake -96, -315, -172 g C m(-2), respectively. The results of 2000 contrasted with those of 1999. Over a comparable period of measurement (27 June-3 September), the clearcut was a sink for carbon in 1999 (-22.4 g C m(-2) using the BREB method and -85 g C m(-2) using the Component model) and a source in 2000 (65 g C m(-2) using the BREB method and 44 g C m(-2) using the Component model). The growing seasons of 1999 and 2000 experienced similar photosynthetic uptake over this same interval (-423 and -422 g C m(-2), respectively). The main difference between the two field seasons was an increase in the soil surface CO2 efflux from 1999 to 2000. In 1999, the soil surface CO2 efflux was 338 g C m(-2) and in 2000 the flux was 38% higher (466 g C m(-2)) for the same period. The results indicate that while there was notable inter-annual variation in CO2 fluxes, particularly the soil surface CO2 effluxes, this young regenerating sub-Boreal forest (less than or equal to6 years after harvesting) is a net source of CO2 when the entire growing season is considered. (C) 2002 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.