The impact of leaf rust on spring wheat in the winter rainfall region of South AfricaIn a field trial established near Malmesbury in the Western Cape during 1999 the effect of Puccinia triticina on yield and quality of the bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) cultivar SST 75 was determined. Information on the efficacy of different foliar fungicide treatments in controlling leaf rust was also obtained. The fungicides bromuconazole (140 g a.i. ha−1), epoxiconazole/carbendazim (112.5/112.5 g a.i. ha−1), flusilazole/carbendazim (100/50 g a.i. ha−1), flutriafol (125 g a.i. ha−1), propiconazole (100 g a.i. ha−1), cyproconazole (40 g a.i. ha−1), tebuconazole (187.5 g a.i. ha−1), and tebuconazole/carbendazim (125/100 g a.i. ha−1) were sprayed in single applications at either growth stage 16 and 37, and in double applications at both these growth stages. The application of the eight fungicides at both seven and flag leaf stages resulted in a mean decrease of 65% in the AUDPC, calculated for leaf rust severity. In the control plots 23% siftings (seed <1.5 mm) were obtained followed by 20%, 13% and 12% for the seven leaf, flag leaf and combined seven and flag leaf treatments, respectively. Combined seven and flag leaf treatments resulted in a mean yield increase of 56%, followed by 50% and 15% for the flag leafand seven leaf treatments, respectively. Over treatments applied, yield increases varied from 24% for bro- muconazole to 53% for epoxiconazole/carbendazim. Yield was negatively correlated with the AUDPC (R = −0.88 [77% of variance accounted for]). The application of the flag leaf and combined seven and flag leaf treatments resulted in a significant increase in the hectolitre mass (kg hi−1). Protein content, over fungicides applied, varied from 12.5% for the combined seven and flag leaf treatments to 12.8% for the seven leaf treatment. The results of the study emphasised the economic importance of leaf rust as well as the value of controlling foliar rust diseases genetically.