Pasture degradation decreases organic P content of tropical soils due to soil structural declineDegradation of tropical pastures on highly weathered soils is linked to soil structural decline and associated losses of organic matter, which could both also affect soil phosphorus (P) dynamics and availability. Our aim was to elucidate these linkages by examining the effect of pasture degradation on the contents and forms of P contained within aggregate size classes and macroaggregate fractions (collectively referred to as soil structural components). We conducted a study on nine farms in a deforested part of the Colombian Amazonia, each farm with degraded and productive Brachiaria spp. pastures. Topsoil (0–10 cm) samples were separated by wet-sieving into aggregate size classes, and macroaggregates were further separated into occluded fractions. Soils and structural components were analyzed for concentrations of total P, available P (extracted using anion exchange resins), NaOH–EDTA extractable organic and inorganic P, and enzyme-hydrolyzable organic P (simple monoester-like, DNA-like, myo-inositol hexakisphosphate-like) in the NaOH–EDTA extracts. Degraded pasture soils had significantly fewer large macroaggregates and more microaggregates, both with significantly lower organic P concentrations (in mg P kg− 1 of structural component) than those in productive pasture soils. At the same time, total and extractable inorganic P concentrations in bulk soil and structural components did not differ between pasture types, suggesting a shift from organic to non-extractable P upon degradation. Soils under productive pastures contained 37% more organic P than degraded pasture soils (in mg P kg− 1 soil), mainly in large macroaggregates. The organic P concentrations were strongly correlated with C concentrations across all soil structural components, suggesting similar stabilization mechanisms for organic P and C. In bulk soil and most structural components, around 60% of organic P was enzyme-hydrolyzable. The lower contents of all enzyme-hydrolyzable as well as enzyme-stable organic P in degraded vs. productive pasture soils indicate a reduction of all organic P classes during pasture degradation. The large macroaggregates and, in particular, microaggregates occluded within this fraction were identified as an important site for organic P storage. Our results highlight a linkage between soil structure and organic P, both of which can play an important role in maintaining the productivity of pastures established on highly weathered soils.