Root traits and soil properties in harvested perennial grassland, annual wheat, and never-tilled annual wheatBackground and aims Root functional traits are determinants of soil carbon storage; plant productivity; and ecosystem properties. However, few studies look at both annual and perennial roots, soil properties, and productivity in the context of field scale agricultural systems. Methods In Long Term and Conversion studies in North Central Kansas, USA; root biomass and length, soil carbon and nitrogen, microbial biomass, nematode and micro-arthropod communities were measured to a depth of one meter in paired perennial grassland and cropland wheat sites as well as a grassland site that had been converted to cropland using no tillage five years prior. Results In the Long Term Study root biomass was three to seven times greater (9.4 Mg ha−1 and 2.5 Mg ha−1 in May), and root length two times greater (52.5 km m−2 and 24.0 km m−2 in May) in perennial grassland than in cropland. Soil organic carbon and microbial biomass carbon were larger, numbers of Orbatid mites greater (2084 vs 730 mites m−2), and nematode communities more structured (Structure Index 67 vs 59) in perennial grassland versus annual cropland. Improved soil physical and biological properties in perennial grasslands were significantly correlated with larger, deeper root systems. In the Conversion Study root length and biomass, microbial biomass carbon, mite abundance and nematode community structure differed at some but not all dates and depths. Isotope analysis showed that five years after no-till conversion old perennial roots remained in soils of annual wheat fields and that all soil fractions except coarse particulate organic matter were derived from C4 plants. Conclusions Significant correlation between larger, longer roots in grasslands compared to annual croplands and improved soil biological, physical and chemical properties suggest that perennial roots are an important factor allowing perennial grasslands to maintain productivity and soil quality with few inputs. Perennial roots may persist and continue to influence soil properties long after conversion to annual systems.