Soil nitrogen in relation to quality and decomposability of plant litter in the Patagonian Monte, ArgentinaIn two consecutive years, we analysed the effect of litter quality, quantity and decomposability on soil N at three characteristic sites of the Patagonian Monte. We assessed (i) concentrations of N, C, lignin and total phenolics and the C/N ratio in senesced leaves as indicators of litter quality of three species of each dominant plant life form (evergreen shrubs and perennial grasses), and (ii) N, and organic-C concentrations, potential N-mineralisation and microbial-N flush in the soil beneath each species. Rate constants of potential decomposition of senesced leaves and N content in decaying leaves during the incubation period were assessed in composite samples of the three sites as indicators of litter decomposability. Further, we estimated for each species leaf-litter production, leaf-litter on soil, and the mass of standing senesced leaves during the senescence period. Senesced leaves of evergreen shrubs showed higher decomposability than those of perennial grasses. Leaf-litter production, leaf-litter on soil, and the mass of standing senesced leaves differed significantly among species. The largest variations in leaf-litter production and leaf-litter on soil were observed in evergreen shrubs. The mass of standing senesced leaves was larger in perennial grasses than in evergreen shrubs. Nitrogen, organic C and potential N-mineralisation in soil were higher underneath evergreen shrubs than beneath perennial grasses, while no significant differences were found in microbial-N flush among life forms. The initial concentrations of C, N and total phenolics of senesced leaves explained together 78% of the total variance observed in the dry mass loss of decaying leaves. Litter decomposition rates explained 98%, 98%, 73%, and 67% of the total variance of soil N, organic C, net-N mineralisation, and microbial-N flush, respectively. We concluded that leaf-litter decomposition rates along with leaf-litter production are meaningful indicators of plant local effects on soil N dynamics in shrublands of the Patagonian Monte, and probably in other similar ecosystem of the world dominated by slow growing species that accumulate a wide variety of secondary metabolites including phenolics. Indicators such as C/N or lignin concentration usually used to predict litter decomposability or local plant effects may not be adequate in the case of slow growing species that accumulate a wide range of secondary metabolites or have long leaf lifespan and low leaf-litter production.