Carbon sink function of sedge and Sphagnum patches in a restored cut-away peatland: increased functional diversity leads to higher production.<ol><li>Cut-away peatlands devoid of vegetation form a persistent source of carbon (C) to the atmosphere. The restoration of the C sink function in such areas can be facilitated by raising the water table. Planting vascular plants and <em>Sphagnum</em> may hasten the restoration process further. However, little is known about the effects of different species on the restoration process.</li><li>We studied carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) exchange in stands of different plants in a restored cut-away site over two growing seasons to quantify their ability to form a C sink. We sampled five different types of stand: monocultures of <em>Eriophorum vaginatum</em> and <em>Carex rostrata</em> (pure plots), mixtures of <em>Eriophorum</em> or <em>Carex</em> and <em>Sphagnum</em> mosses (mixed plots) and control plots without vegetation. We applied the closed chamber technique to gather CO<sub>2</sub> exchange data for modelling of gross photosynthesis (P<sub>G</sub>) and ecosystem respiration (R<sub>E</sub>). Finally, we used the models to reconstruct the seasonal net CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of the stands formed by different plants.</li><li>While the control plots without vegetation were sources of 20-71 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup>, all the vegetated plots acted as C sinks during both growing seasons. The monostands of <em>E. vaginatum</em> and <em>C. rostrata</em> created sinks of 23-114 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup>, while the mixtures of sedge and <em>Sphagnum</em> mosses resulted in larger sinks of 75-186 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup>. The larger sinks of the mixed patches were due to the lower respiration/photosynthesis ratio.</li><li>To eliminate the effect of differences in water table and the abundance of sedges between the patches, we reconstructed the CO<sub>2</sub> exchange for constant water table and vascular leaf area for all plots. The simulation further supported our result: the mixtures of sedge and <em>Sphagnum</em> mosses were clearly more efficient in sequestering CO<sub>2</sub> than pure sedge stands.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications.</em> The increased functional diversity in a cut-away peatland site resulted in higher net ecosystem exchange. When restoring cut-away peatlands, reintroduction of <em>Sphagna</em> is recommended after the colonization of vascular plants to hasten the formation of a sink for C.</li></ol>