Changes in snow cover characteristics over Northern Eurasia since 1966Current snow state descriptions and estimates of major snow characteristics (snow cover duration, maximum winter snow depth, snow water equivalent) up to 2010 have been recorded from 958 meteorological stations in Russia. Apart from the description of long-term averages of snow characteristics, the estimates of their change that are averaged over quasi-homogeneous climatic regions are derived and regional differences in the change of snow characteristics are studied. In recent decades, the Russian territory has experienced an increase in snow depth, both winter average and maximum snow depths, against the background of global temperature rise and sea ice reduction in the northern hemisphere. The first generalized regional characteristics of maximum snow water equivalent in the winter season have been obtained. According to field observations, an increase in water supply has been revealed in the north of the East European Plain, in the western part by 4.5% (10 yr) – 1 and in the eastern part by 6% (10 yr) – 1. This characteristic also increases by  ∼  6% (10 yr) – 1 in the southern forest zone of Western Siberia and in the Far East. Snow water equivalent in central Eastern Siberia increases by 3.4% (10 yr) – 1. From snow course observations in the forest, a tendency for a decrease in water supply (–6.4% (10 yr) – 1 is only found in the southwest of the East European Plain. Snow cover characteristics, being a product of several climate-forming factors that simultaneously affected them, change nonlinearly and different characteristics may and often do change differently with time. Therefore, one cannot assume that having information about the trend of one of the snow characteristics implies knowledge of the trend sign of others. In particular, whilst during the past four decades over the Russian Federation most snow cover characteristics—including the most important of them responsible for water supply—have increased, the only quantity that is reliably monitored from space (snow cover extent) has decreased, but in the last two decades this decrease has ceased. These tendencies are opposite to those observed in Canada and Alaska.