Seasonal patterns in post-dispersal seed predation of Abutilon theophrasti and Setaria faberi in three cropping systems.<ol><li>Post-dispersal seed predation is an important source of mortality for arable weed populations that can potentially contribute to ecologically based management strategies. The extent to which cropping practices influence rates of seed predation is not well established.</li><li>Removal of <em>Abutilon theophrasti</em> and <em>Setaria faberi</em> seeds by predators was measured in 2-year (maize/soyabean), 3-year (maize/soyabean/triticale + red clover) and 4-year (maize/soyabean/triticale + lucerne/lucerne) crop rotations in Iowa, USA, during 27 48-h sampling periods conducted during the 2003 and 2004 cropping seasons.</li><li>Predation of <em>S. faberi</em> seeds was equal (eight sampling periods) or greater (19 sampling periods) than predation of <em>A. theophrasti</em> seeds, but the influence of crops on seasonal predation patterns was generally similar for the two weeds.</li><li>Seasonal patterns in seed predation were crop-specific and complementary. In maize and soyabean, seed predation was low in spring, high in summer and low in autumn. In triticale-legume intercrops, seed predation was high in spring, low in summer and moderate in autumn. In lucerne, seed predation fluctuated from high to low, matching the periodic harvest and regrowth cycle of the crop.</li><li>Measurements of crop canopy light interception taken in 2004 were positively correlated with rates of seed removal for both <em>A. theophrasti</em> (<em>r</em> = 0路54, <em>P</em> &lt; 0路001) and <em>S. faberi</em> (<em>r</em> = 0路25, <em>P</em> &lt; 0路001), suggesting that vegetative cover promotes weed seed predation.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications.</em> The results indicate that crop vegetation can be managed to promote weed seed predation. Diversified farming systems that include a range of phenologically dissimilar crop species are likely to provide the greatest opportunities for weed seed destruction by predators.</li></ol>