Soil-atmosphere exchange of greenhouse gases in a Eucalyptus marginata woodland, a clover-grass pasture, and Pinus radiata and Eucalyptus globulus plantations.Soils provide the largest terrestrial carbon store, the largest atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> source, the largest terrestrial N<sub>2</sub>O source and the largest terrestrial CH<sub>4</sub> sink, as mediated through root and soil microbial processes. A change in land use or management can alter these soil processes such that net greenhouse gas exchange may increase or decrease. We measured soil-atmosphere exchange of CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O and CH<sub>4</sub> in four adjacent land-use systems (native eucalypt woodland, clover-grass pasture, <em>Pinus radiata</em> and <em>Eucalyptus globulus</em> plantation) for short, but continuous, periods between October 2005 and June 2006 using an automated trace gas measurement system near Albany in southwest Western Australia. Mean N<sub>2</sub>O emission in the pasture was 26.6 &mu;g N m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>, significantly greater than in the natural and managed forests (< 2.0 &mu;g N m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>). N<sub>2</sub>O emission from pasture soil increased after rainfall events (up to 100 &mu;g N m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>) and as soil water content increased into winter, whereas no soil water response was detected in the forest systems. Gross nitrification through <sup>15</sup>N isotope dilution in all land-use systems was small at water holding capacity < 30%, and under optimum soil water conditions gross nitrification ranged between < 0.1 and 1.0 mg N kg<sup>-;1</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>, being least in the native woodland/eucalypt plantation < pine plantation < pasture. Forest soils were a constant CH<sub>4</sub> sink, up to -;20 &mu;g C m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup> in the native woodland. Pasture soil was an occasional CH<sub>4</sub> source, but weak CH<sub>4</sub> sink overall (-;3 &mu;g C m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>). There were no strong correlations (<em>R</em> < 0.4) between CH<sub>4</sub> flux and soil moisture or temperature. Soil CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (35-55 mg C m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>) correlated with soil water content (<em>R</em> < 0.5) in all but the <em>E. globulus</em> plantation. Soil N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from improved pastures can be considerable and comparable with intensively managed, irrigated and fertilised dairy pastures. In all land uses, soil N<sub>2</sub>O emissions exceeded soil CH<sub>4</sub> uptake on a carbon dioxide equivalent basis. Overall, afforestation of improved pastures (i) decreases soil N<sub>2</sub>O emissions and (ii) increases soil CH<sub>4</sub> uptake.