Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), part II: the Australian and southwest Pacific faunaAbstract The Australasian and southwest Pacific species of Oxyscelio (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae s.l.) are revised. A total of 80 species are recognized as valid, 13 of which are redescribed: O. atricoxa (Dodd), O. concoloripes (Dodd), O. flavipes (Kieffer), O. grandis (Dodd), O. hyalinipennis (Dodd), O. magniclava (Dodd), O. mirellus (Dodd), O. montanus (Dodd), O. nigriclava (Dodd), O. nigricoxa (Dodd), O. rugulosus (Dodd), O. shakespearei (Girault), and O. solitarius (Dodd). Oxyscelio glabriscutellum (Dodd) syn. n. is placed as a subjective junior synonym of O. rugulosus. Sixty-seven new species are described, many representing new distributional records for the genus - O. aciculae Burks, sp. n., O. anfractus Burks, sp. n., O. bellariorum Burks, sp. n., O. bicoloripedis Burks, sp. n., O. brevitas Burks, sp. n., O. catenae Burks, sp. n., O. caudarum Burks, sp. n., O. circulorum Burks, sp. n., O. clivi Burks, sp. n., O. clupei Burks, sp. n., O. conjuncti Burks, sp. n., O. contusionis Burks, sp. n., O. corrugationis Burks, sp. n., O. croci Burks, sp. n., O. cuspidis Burks, sp. n., O. densitatis Burks, sp. n., O. dissimulationis Burks, sp. n., O. divisionis Burks, sp. n., O. exiguitatis Burks, sp. n., O. fluctuum Burks, sp. n., O. foliorum Burks, sp. n., O. funis Burks, sp. n., O. gressus Burks, sp. n., O. hamorum Burks, sp. n., O. incisurae Burks, sp. n., O. lenitatis Burks, sp. n., O. leviventris Burks, sp. n., O. limbi Burks, sp. n., O. liminis Burks, sp. n., O. linguae Burks, sp. n., O. lintris Burks, sp. n., O. livens Burks, sp. n., O. mystacis Burks, sp. n., O. nasi Burks, sp. n., O. nitoris Burks, sp. n., O. obliquiatis Burks, sp. n., O. oblongiclypei Burks, sp. n., O. obturationis Burks, sp. n., O. oculi Burks, sp. n., O. palati Burks, sp. n., O. pectinis Burks, sp. n., O. pollicis Burks, sp. n., O. proceritatis Burks, sp. n., O. productionis Burks, sp. n., O. radii Burks, sp. n., O. rami Burks, sp. n., O. rupturae Burks, sp. n., O. sarcinae Burks, sp. n., O. scismatis Burks, sp. n., O. sciuri Burks, sp. n., O. scutorum Burks, sp. n., O. sepisessor Burks, sp. n., O. sinuationis Burks, sp. n., O. sordes Burks, sp. n., O. spatula Burks, sp. n., O. stipulae Burks, sp. n., O. stringerae Burks, sp. n., O. tenuitatis Burks, sp. n., O. truncationis Burks, sp. n., O. tubi Burks, sp. n., O. umbonis Burks, sp. n., O. uncinorum Burks, sp. n., O. valdecatenae Burks, sp. n., O. velamenti Burks, sp. n., O. verrucae Burks, sp. n., O. viator Burks, sp. n., and O. wa Burks, sp. n. The fauna is divided into nine diagnostic species groups, with five species unplaced to group.