Multi-Objective Operations of Multi-Wetland Ecosystem: iModel Applied to the Everglades RestorationAbstractThe Everglades is a complex, multiwetland ecosystem that is heavily managed to meet often-competing flood control, water supply, and environmental demands. Using objective measures to balance these demands through operational protocols has always been a challenge in the multibillion-dollar restoration plans for the ecosystem. Physically based models have been the primary tools for planning efforts but for such a complex system, they are laborious and computationally intensive. Development of optimal operations based on iterative runs of these models is a great challenge. This paper presents an inverse modeling framework for formal optimization suited for wetland system operations that helps overcome such limitations. Labor-intensive and computation-intensive physically representative models are emulated in each individual wetland area using an autoregressive artificial neural network with exogenous variables. Using prescribed inflow, outflow, and meteorological input data, such hydrologic model emulators aided by a dimension-reduction technique provide targeted spatial and temporal predictions for water level (stage) within each area of the Everglades, while excluding computation processes that are intensive but insignificant to the predictions. This computer software uses the augmented Lagrangian genetic algorithm technique (subject to linear and nonlinear constraints) to steer predictions of stage spatial variability within individual wetlands towards corresponding desired goals (including restoration targets). In the augmented Lagrangian genetic algorithm, flow releases are coded as the decision variables to be optimized subject to budget, intrahydraulic conveyance, flow capacity, and upstream storage constraints. Optimization is performed by dividing and solving a sequence of subproblems using the genetic algorithm procedures of initialization, selection, elitism, crossover, and mutation. As part of the process, Lagrangian and penalty parameters are updated, and optimization terminates when certain stopping criteria are met. Applying the technique reported in this paper to a specific Everglades restoration plan (the River of Grass Project) showed a sound hydrologic model emulator prediction when compared to the physical model for all wetland areas. Feeding optimal releases predicted by the computer software into a physical model showed equal or better matching of the restoration target with different release patterns compared to that of the physical model base run scenario. Results show that hydraulic conveyance limitations play a significant role in Everglades restoration. Also, results show that employing an adversity tradeoff matrix presented multiple so-called optimal solutions with different optimization weights and a powerful negotiation matrix.