Antipredator defence mechanism in the amphidromous shrimp Xiphocaris elongata (Decapoda: Xiphocarididae): rostrum lengthPredators may affect prey through inducible defences that can alter prey phenotype. The shrimp Xiphocaris elongata exhibits a short rostrum (SR) in the absence of fish predators and a long rostrum (LR) in their presence. The long rostrum in X. elongata is inducible by the predatory fish Agonostomus monticola (mountain mullet). Our objective was to test whether the long rostrum is an effective antipredator defence against A. monticola in different stages of predator–prey interactions (i.e. choice, attacks, bites, rejections, handling time and survival). We conducted behavioural experiments in fish tanks in which we fed A. monticola simultaneously with (1) one LR shrimp and one SR shrimp, or (2) one LR shrimp and one shrimp which originally had a long rostrum but whose rostrum was cut (LR[S]). We scored the fish behaviours in terms of choice, unsuccessful attacks, bites, rejections and handling time. We also conducted mortality experiments in closed artificial pools in which we exposed (1) 10 LR and 10 SR shrimp or (2) 10 LR and 10 LR[S] shrimp to A. monticola, and quantified shrimp survival after 24 h. In the trials with LR and SR shrimp, A. monticola tended to attack SR shrimp first. LR shrimp were unsuccessfully attacked, bitten and rejected more than SR individuals. Handling time was higher for LR shrimp. The mortality experiments show higher survival of LR shrimp. In the trials with LR and LR[S] shrimp, A. monticola tended to attack LR[S] shrimp first. Unsuccessful attacks were similar for LR and LR[S]. There were more bites and rejections and longer handling time for LR shrimp. Survival was similar for LR and LR[S] shrimp in the mortality experiments. This study provides evidence in support of the hypothesis that the long rostrum in X. elongata is an effective antipredator defence against A. monticola by conferring benefits in most stages of the predator–prey interactions.