Maintaining yields and reducing nitrogen loss in ricewheat rotation system in Taihu Lake region with proper fertilizer managementAbstract In the Tailake region of China, heavy nitrogen (N) loss of ricewheat rotation systems, due to high fertilizer-N input with low N use efficiency (NUE), was widely reported. To alleviate the detrimental impacts caused by N loss, it is necessary to improve the fertilizer management practices. Therefore, a 3 yr field experiments with different N managements including organic combined chemical N treatment (OCN, 390 kg N ha1 yr1, 20 organic fertilizer), controlreleased urea treatment (CRU, 390 kg N ha1 yr1, 70 resin-coated urea), reduced chemical N treatment (RCN, 390 kg N ha1 yr1, all common chemical fertilizer), and site-specific N management (SSNM, 333 kg N ha1 yr1, all common chemical fertilizer) were conducted in the Taihu Lake region with the farmers N treatment (FN, 510 kg N ha1 yr1, all common chemical fertilizer) as a control. Grain yield, plant N uptake (PNU), NUE, and N losses via runoff, leaching, and ammonia volatilization were assessed. In the rice season, the FN treatment had the highest N loss and lowest NUE, which can be attributed to an excessive rate of N application. Treatments of OCN and RCN with a 22 reduced N rate from FN had no significant effect on PNU nor the yield of rice in the 3 yr; however, the NUE was improved and N loss was reduced 2032. OCN treatment achieved the highest yield, while SSNM has the lowest N loss and highest NUE due to the lowest N rate. In wheat season, N loss decreased about 2848 with the continuous reduction of N input, but the yield also declined, with the exception of OCN treatment. N loss through runoff, leaching and ammonia volatilization was positively correlated with the N input rate. When compared with the pure chemical fertilizer treatment of RCN under the same N input, OCN treatment has better NUE, better yield, and lower N loss. 70 of the urea replaced with resin-coated urea had no significant effect on yield and NUE improvement, but decreased the ammonia volatilization loss. Soil total N and organic matter content showed a decrease after three continuous cropping years with inorganic fertilizer application alone, but there was an increase with the OCN treatment. N balance analysis showed a N surplus for FN treatment and a balanced N budget for OCN treatment. To reduce the environmental impact and maintain a high crop production, proper N reduction together with organic amendments could be sustainable in the ricewheat rotation system in the Taihu Lake region for a long run.