Estimating aboveground biomass using Landsat 7 ETM+ data across a managed landscape in northern Wisconsin, USAAboveground biomass (AGB; Mg/ha) is defined in this study as a biomass of growing stock trees greater than 2.5 cm in diameter at breast height (dbh) for stands >5 years and all trees taller than 1.3 m for stands <5 years. Although AGB is an important variable for evaluating ecosystem function and structure across the landscape, such estimates are difficult to generate without high-resolution satellite data. This study bridges the application of remote sensing techniques with various forest management practices in Chequamegon National Forest (CNF), Wisconsin, USA by producing a high-resolution stand age map and a spatially explicit AGB map. We coupled AGB values, calculated from field measurements of tree dbh, with various vegetation indices derived from Landsat 7 ETM+ data through multiple regression analyses to produce an initial biomass map. The initial biomass map was overlaid with a land-cover map to generate a stand age map. Biomass threshold values for each age category (e.g., young, intermediate, and mature) were determined through field observations and frequency analysis of initial biomass estimates by major cover types. We found that AGB estimates for hardwood forests were strongly related to stand age and near-infrared reflectance (r2=0.95) while the AGB for pine forests was strongly related to the corrected normalized difference vegetation index (NDVIc; r2=0.86). Separating hardwoods from pine forests improved the AGB estimates in the area substantially, compared to overall regression (r2=0.82). Our AGB results are comparable to previously reported values in the area. The total amount of AGB in the study area for 2001 was estimated as 3.3 million metric tons (dry weight), 76.5% of which was in hardwood and mixed hardwood/pine forests. AGB ranged from 1 to 358 Mg/ha with an average of 70 and a standard deviation of 54 Mg/ha. The AGB class with the highest percentage (16.1%) was between 81 and 100 Mg/ha. Forests with biomass values >200 Mg/ha accounted for less than 3% of the study area and were usually associated with mature hardwood forests. Estimated AGB was validated using independent field measurements (R2=0.67, p<0.001). The AGB and age maps can be used as baseline information for future landscape level studies such as quantifying the regional carbon budget, accumulating fuel, or monitoring management practices.