Limited evidence for short-term succession of microarthropods during early phases of surface litter decompositionSuccession of microarthropods during the decomposition of organic matter is an important concept in soil biology. However, few studies have tested whether the pattern of microarthropod colonisation during decomposition is independent of season. We investigated the pattern of colonisation and dominance of microarthropods on decomposing organic matter placed at two different times. Litterbags containing canola leaf or stem material were placed on the soil surface of a Western Australian agricultural field in July and September 1999. They were collected weekly to fortnightly until November. A final set of bags was collected in May 2000. Mass loss and nutrient contents (C, N, Ca, K, P and S) were measured at each sample time. Microarthropods were sorted to order and the mites to species level. Nematode abundance was determined at each sample time. Mass toss of the leaf and stem material was similar between the two placement times (congruent to33% and 15% ash-free dry mass lost over 33 days from leaf and stem material, respectively), although the dynamics of nutrient Loss for some elements was different between the two placements. However, over the dry summer, material placed in September continued to lose nutrients whilst there was little additional loss from the material placed in July. A similar pattern of dominance of microarthropod and mite species was found on the leaf and stem material placed in July with the succession of dominant animals more rapid on the stem material. Nematode abundance appeared to increase as populations of microarthropods declined over time. Populations of microarthropods on the material placed in the September samples never achieved similar levels of abundance to that of the July samples, and the dominant fauna groups were dissimilar to those in the July samples for the same degree of decomposition. Our data indicate that the early phase of surface litter decomposition is not a successional process in terms of the microarthropod community irrespective of season and, that abiotic factors are more likely to be determining nutrient toss from organic matter within particular seasons. (C) 2003 Elsevier GmbH. All rights reserved.