The impact of deforestation and pasture abandonment on soil properties in the wet tropics of AustraliaLimited information exists on the changes in soil properties, particularly from the wet tropics of Australia, under long-term abandoned pasture, which was previously grazed and was established on deforested tropical rainforest. This information may be help in successful forest reestablishment. The objectives of this study were to assess the cumulative impact deforestation, grazed and abandoned pasture on selected soil physico-chemical properties from (i) an abandoned pastureland and (ii) a recently planted rainforest (PRF), planted in the abandoned pastureland. The experimental site is a field in the Northeast Queensland (NEQ) wet tropical region of Australia. This site was deforested approximately 70 years ago and brought under unfertilized grazed pasture for 30 years. Subsequently the grazed pastureland was abandoned and remains un-grazed for 40 years. A section of the abandoned pastureland was planted, 10 years ago, with native forest species, involving different combinations in five treatments in a completely randomised block design. A nearby undisturbed rainforest is used as the background against which assessment was carried out. Soil samples from 0- to 15-cm depth were collected in July 2000 and analyzed for nitrate-N, ammonium-N, total N, total soil organic C (SOC) and labile-C, pH (in water and CaCl2), electrical conductivity (EC), exchangeable Ca, Mg, Na, K, and Al, and bulk density. Compared to the rainforest, the N and C concentrations of different forms under abandoned pasture and PRF were significantly less, exclusive of the total N under abandoned pasture. More specifically, the SOC under the abandoned pasture was 37,600 mg/kg compared with 74,800 mg/kg under rainforest and 27,000 mg/kg in the PRF. The exchangeable Al under rainforest was 8.5 c molc/kg compared with 42.4 to 80.2 c molc/kg under abandoned pasture and PRF. In general exchangeable cations (sum of Ca, Mg, K, and Na) under the rainforest were higher than the abandoned pasture. Soil under the abandoned pasture and PRF are more acidic by 0.5 to 1 units than the rainforest. Higher bulk densities under abandoned pasture and PRF led to 0.03% to 0.07% reductions in total porosities. Though we did not anticipate the soil under the abandoned pasture to recover 100% in 30–40 years, the results indicate that 40 years under abandoned pasture or 30 years of abandoned pasture plus 10 years under PRF was not sufficient to bring about substantial improvement in soil properties comparable to the rainforest. This implies the resiliency of tropical soils, in general, to recover from deforestation and cultivation induced degradation is poor.