Spatial distribution pattern of a clonal species: effects of differential production of clonal and sexual offspringThe spatial distribution patterns of genets and ramets within populations are expected to change as a function of the frequency with which clonal species recruit different types of offspring (sexual and clonal). We used an integrated approach to study the spatial arrangement of clonal plants by combining molecular and ecological data using Opuntia microdasys as a study system. The species is able to produce two types of clonal (plantlets and cladodes) and one type of sexual (seeds) offspring. Additionally it is found in three habitats that cause differences in the ability of each type of offspring to establish. In 2007, all individuals in the three habitats (162 in BH = bajada, 264 in IDH = hill-piedmont, and 136 at HPH = interdunes) were tagged and mapped. Amplified inter-simple sequence repeats (ISSR's) were used to determine the multilocus genotype and relatedness of each individual ramet using 120 polymorphic bands (104 in BH, 128 in HPH and 180 in IDH). The spatial distribution pattern of genets and ramets was analyzed with the Hopkins test and spatial autocorrelation analysis. For all habitats we found that O. microdasys displayed a spatial distribution characterized by clumps of aggregated ramets, but habitats differed in the number of genets present. As for other clonal species a strong positive spatial autocorrelation exists within 20 m, although all analyses suggest that adjacent ramets are genetically less related to each other or belong to different genets, that is, ramets of different genets are intermingled. The spatial arrangement of genets and ramets in O. microdasys between habitats closely matches the frequency of establishment of each type of offspring (e.g. the more clonal areas are clumped groups of related individuals). These results confirm that in two habitats (BH and IDH) clonal recruitment had been more common than in the other habitat (HPH).