Nitrite-driven nitrous oxide production under aerobic soil conditions: kinetics and biochemical controls.Nitrite (NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup>) can accumulate during nitrification in soil following fertilizer application. While the role of NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> as a substrate regulating nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O) production is recognized, kinetic data are not available that allow for estimating N<sub>2</sub>O production or soil-to-atmosphere fluxes as a function of NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> levels under aerobic conditions. The current study investigated these kinetics as influenced by soil physical and biochemical factors in soils from cultivated and uncultivated fields in Minnesota, USA. A linear response of N<sub>2</sub>O production rate (<img alt=""""inline image"""" src=""""http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/store/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2007.01389.x/asset/equation/GCB_1389_mu1.gif?v=1&t=h8de8tdf&s=4ba8237ecd6c4b44bd1d3d8f4660f5387f7fd409"""" class=""""inlineGraphic"""" />) to NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> was observed at concentrations below 60 &mu;g N g<sup>-;1</sup> soil in both nonsterile and sterilized soils. Rate coefficients (<em>K</em><sub><em>p</em></sub>) relating <img alt=""""inline image"""" src=""""http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/store/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2007.01389.x/asset/equation/GCB_1389_mu2.gif?v=1&t=h8de8tdg&s=ae84a3591d102776b5c96f6b39cdd28a1e9eca10"""" class=""""inlineGraphic"""" /> to NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> varied over two orders of magnitude and were correlated with pH, total nitrogen, and soluble and total carbon (C). Total C explained 84% of the variance in <em>K</em><sub><em>p</em></sub> across all samples. Abiotic processes accounted for 31-75% of total N<sub>2</sub>O production. Biological reduction of NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> was enhanced as oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) levels were decreased from above ambient to 5%, consistent with nitrifier denitrification. In contrast, nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-;</sup>)-reduction, and the reduction of N<sub>2</sub>O itself, were only stimulated at O<sub>2</sub> levels below 5%. Greater temperature sensitivity was observed for biological compared with chemical N<sub>2</sub>O production. Steady-state model simulations predict that NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-;</sup> levels often found after fertilizer applications have the potential to generate substantial N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes even at ambient O<sub>2</sub>. This potential derives in part from the production of N<sub>2</sub>O under conditions not favorable for N<sub>2</sub>O reduction, in contrast to N<sub>2</sub>O generated from NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-;</sup> reduction. These results have implications with regard to improved management to minimize agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O emissions and improved emissions assessments.