Calibration and validation of hyperspectral indices for the estimation of broadleaved forest leaf chlorophyll content, leaf mass per area, leaf area index and leaf canopy biomassThis article aims at finding efficient hyperspectral indices for the estimation of forest sun leaf chlorophyll content (CHL, 츽췃g cmleaf칙춛2), sun leaf mass per area (LMA, gdry matter mleaf칙춛2), canopy leaf area index (LAI, m2leaf msoil칙춛2) and leaf canopy biomass (Bleaf, gdry matter msoil칙춛2). These parameters are useful inputs for forest ecosystem simulations at landscape scale. The method is based on the determination of the best vegetation indices (index form and wavelengths) using the radiative transfer model PROSAIL (formed by the newly-calibrated leaf reflectance model PROSPECT coupled with the multi-layer version of the canopy radiative transfer model SAIL). The results are tested on experimental measurements at both leaf and canopy scales. At the leaf scale, it is possible to estimate CHL with high precision using a two wavelength vegetation index after a simulation based calibration. At the leaf scale, the LMA is more difficult to estimate with indices. At the canopy scale, efficient indices were determined on a generic simulated database to estimate CHL, LMA, LAI and Bleaf in a general way. These indices were then applied to two Hyperion images (50 plots) on the Fontainebleau and Foug츾춷res forests and portable spectroradiometer measurements. They showed good results with an RMSE of 8.2츽먞췃g cm칙춛2 for CHL, 9.1츽많 m칙춛2 for LMA, 1.7츽맔2 m칙춛2 for LAI and 50.6츽많 m칙춛2 for Bleaf. However, at the canopy scale, even if the wavelengths of the calibrated indices were accurately determined with the simulated database, the regressions between the indices and the biophysical characteristics still had to be calibrated on measurements. At the canopy scale, the best indices were: for leaf chlorophyll content: NDchl=(925칙춛눾710)/(925+710), for leaf mass per area: NDLMA=(2260칙춛눾1490)/(2260+1490), for leaf area index: DLAI=1725칙춛눾970, and for canopy leaf biomass: NDBleaf=(2160칙춛눾1540)/(2160+1540).