Spatial patterns on the sagebrush steppe/Western juniper ecotoneAnalysis of the spatial patterns of woody plants is important to better understand the ecological processes that govern the worldwide expansion of woody plants across semi-arid ecosystems. Second-order characteristics of a marked spatial point pattern of western juniper ( Juniperus occidentalis subsp. occidentalis) were analyzed using Ripley’s K-functions and the pair-correlation function g. The marked point process of crown diameters was produced via two-dimensional wavelet analysis of a fine scale aerial photograph at the woodland-steppe ecotone in the Reynolds Creek watershed in the Owyhee Mountains, southwestern Idaho. Colonization of J. occidentalis stems from mature juniper trees growing in rocky, fire resistant areas. Although these areas introduce components of natural heterogeneity within the landscape, the selected study area is situated within a single soil type, and we modeled the expansion of juniper plants into previously juniper-free sagebrush steppe as a homogeneous point process with constant intensity. Through this research we have identified two statistically significant spatial scales characteristic of J. occidentalis on the woodland/steppe ecotone: (1) We observed inhibition between J. occidentalis plants at distances <15 m, resulting in a regular pattern, rather than clumped or random. This short-distance inhibition can be attributed to competition for water and other resources. Recruitment of young J. occidentalis occurs significantly more often in a direction away from older plants, maximizing the utilization of water and light resources, and perpetuating the spread of the species into previously juniper-free shrub-steppe. (2) J. occidentalis on the ecotone exhibits significant clustering within a 30–60 m radius. Bivariate point pattern analyses provide evidence that, within a distance of 50–70 m, there is a spatial dependence in tree size such that medium trees are more likely than small trees to be close to large trees. We attribute these phenomena to the fact that juniper seeds are commonly dispersed by berry-eating birds with small territories (0.3–1 ha). Beyond a distance of 50–70 m, juniper plants are randomly distributed, suggesting that additional long-range seed dispersal processes are at work. We further acknowledge the importance of including a reference to spatial scale when formulating hypotheses in statistical analysis of spatio-temporal point patterns.