Associations between carbon isotope ratios of ecosystem respiration, water availability and canopy conductance.We tested the hypothesis that the stable carbon isotope signature of ecosystem respiration (<em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub>) was regulated by canopy conductance (<em>G</em><sub>c</sub>) using weekly Keeling plots (<em>n</em>=51) from a semiarid old-growth ponderosa pine (<em>Pinus ponderosa</em>) forest in Oregon, USA. For a comparison of forests in two contrasting climates we also evaluated trends in <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> from a wet 20-year-old Douglas-fir (<em>Pseudotsuga menziesii</em>) plantation located near the Pacific Ocean. Intraannual variability in <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> was greater than 8.0&permil; at both sites, was highest during autumn, winter, and spring when rainfall was abundant, and lowest during summer drought. The <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> of the dry pine forest was consistently more positive than the wetter Douglas-fir forest (mean annual <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub>: -;25.41&permil; vs. -;26.23&permil;, respectively, <em>P</em>=0.07). At the Douglas-fir forest, <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub>-climate relationships were consistent with predictions based on stomatal regulation of carbon isotope discrimination (&Delta;). Soil water content (<em>SWC</em>) and vapor pressure deficit (<em>vpd</em>) were the most important factors governing <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> in this forest throughout the year. In contrast, <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> at the pine forest was relatively insensitive to <em>SWC</em> or <em>vpd</em>, and exhibited a smaller drought-related enrichment (&sim;2&permil;) than the enrichment observed during drought at the Douglas-fir forest (&sim;5&permil;). Groundwater access at the pine forest may buffer canopy-gas exchange from drought. Despite this potential buffering, <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> at the pine forest was significantly but weakly related to canopy conductance (<em>G</em><sub>c</sub>), suggesting that <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> remains coupled to canopy-gas exchange despite groundwater access. During drought, <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> was strongly correlated with soil temperature at both forests. The hypothesis that canopy-level physiology is a critical regulator of <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C<sub>R</sub> was supported; however, belowground respiration may become more important during rain-free periods.