Interannual Herbaceous Biomass Response to Increasing Honey Mesquite Cover on Two Soils.This study quantified herbaceous biomass responses to increases in honey mesquite (<em>Prosopis glandulosa</em> Torr.) cover on two soils from 1995 to 2001 in north central Texas. Vegetation was sampled randomly with levels of mesquite ranging from 0% to 100%. With no mesquite covering the silt loam soils of bottomland sites, peak herbaceous biomass averaged (±SE) 3300±210 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> vs. 2560±190 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> on clay loam soils of upland sites (<em>P</em>=0.001). A linear decline of 14±2.5 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> in herbaceous biomass occurred for each percent increase in mesquite cover (<em>P</em>=0.001). The slope of this decline was similar between soils (<em>P</em>=0.135). Herbaceous biomass with increasing mesquite cover varied between years (<em>P</em>=0.001) as did the slope of decline (<em>P</em>=0.001). Warm-season herbaceous biomass decreased linearly with increasing mesquite cover averaging a 73±15% reduction at 100% mesquite cover (<em>P</em>=0.001) compared to 0% mesquite cover. Cool-season herbaceous biomass was similar between soils with no mesquite, 1070±144 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> for silt loam vs. 930±140 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> for clay loam soils, but averaged 340±174 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> more on silt loam than on clay loam soils at 100% mesquite cover (<em>P</em>=0.004). Multiple regression analysis indicated that each centimeter of precipitation received from the previous October through the current September produced herbaceous biomass of 51 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> on silt loam and 41 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> on clay loam soils. Herbaceous biomass decreased proportionally with increasing mesquite cover up to 29 kg · ha<sup>−1</sup> at 100% mesquite cover for each centimeter of precipitation received from January through September. Increasing mesquite cover reduces livestock forage productivity and intensifies drought effects by increasing annual herbaceous biomass variability. From a forage production perspective there is little advantage to having mesquite present.