Sagebrush Control: At What Canopy Cover Is It Economically Justified?We determine the economic threshold level for big sagebrush control based on 18 yr of forage-response data from an experiment conducted in Carbon County, Wyoming. We analyze the impacts of climatic variables and treatment site characteristics, such as sagebrush abundance levels, precipitation, and understory composition, on forage response and threshold level. We find that sagebrush canopy cover levels, April precipitation, May soil moisture, and understory composition are statistically significant factors in explaining forage response to sagebrush treatment. Forage yield across treated and untreated plots for 10 canopy cover levels, ranging from 4% to 40%, are analyzed via panel data regression techniques. We further investigate the impact of variability in precipitation and understory characteristics on economic outcomes of sagebrush control by analyzing three scenarios. Scenario 1 uses actual forage response data that include all variability from precipitation and understory composition. Scenario 2 uses regression-predicted yields across plots assuming average precipitation and soil moisture conditions. Scenario 3 uses regression-predicted yields assuming average precipitation, soil moisture, and understory characteristics across plots. Net present values based on value of grazing (for estimated yield differences between treated and untreated plots assuming 50% forage utilization) compared to treatment cost across sagebrush cover levels are estimated across these three scenarios. Results indicate that the economic threshold level of sagebrush infestation for the study period was between 8% and 24% for the analyzed scenarios. This indicates variability in precipitation and understory composition impact forage response and the resulting economics of sagebrush control. We conclude that range managers should consider potential control site characteristics and long-range weather forecasts when contemplating sagebrush control.