Water, temperature, and vegetation regulation of methyl chloride and methyl bromide fluxes from a shortgrass steppe ecosystem.Temperate grasslands are considered to be a significant sink for CH<sub>3</sub>Br, although large uncertainties exist about the magnitude of this sink because of a paucity of field measurements. Here, we report the results of a combined field and laboratory study that investigated the effects of water, temperature, and plant community composition on CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br fluxes in a semiarid temperate grassland. A novel stable isotope tracer technique was also employed to deconvolute simultaneous production and oxidation of CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br. Net and gross fluxes were measured from different landforms (ridges, floodplains) and cover types (grass-dominated, shrub-dominated) to capture a representative range of hydrologic regimes, temperatures, and plant communities. In field experiments, net CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br uptake was observed at all grass-dominated sites (-;400±77 nmol CH<sub>3</sub>Cl m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup> and -;3.4±0.9 nmol CH<sub>3</sub>Br m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup>), while net CH<sub>3</sub>Cl emission (439±58 nmol CH<sub>3</sub>Cl m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup>) was observed at sites dominated by the shrub <em>Atriplex canescens</em>, indicating that this plant is a strong CH<sub>3</sub>Cl producer. Gross CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br oxidation were comparable with estimates from other dryland ecosystems (507±115 nmol CH<sub>3</sub>Cl m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup> and 9.1±2.2 nmol CH<sub>3</sub>Br m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup>), although CH<sub>3</sub>Br oxidation rates were at least five times lower than those observed in more mesic temperate grasslands. We suggest that estimates of the temperate grassland CH<sub>3</sub>Br sink should be reduced by ≥19% (≥1.8 Gg yr<sup>-;1</sup>) to account for the weaker sink strength of semiarid environments. Identification of <em>A. canescens</em> as a 'new' CH<sub>3</sub>Cl source may have important ramifications for the global atmospheric budget of CH<sub>3</sub>Cl, given the global distribution of this plant and its congeners and their widespread presence in many dryland ecosystems. Laboratory experiments revealed that soil water was the chief regulator of CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br oxidation, while temperature had no observed effect between 14 and 26 °C. Oxidation rates rose most rapidly between 0.4% and 5% volumetric water content, suggesting that methyl halide-oxidizing bacteria respond strongly to small inputs of water under the very driest conditions. Soil drying and rewetting experiments did not appear to affect the oxidation of CH<sub>3</sub>Cl and CH<sub>3</sub>Br by soil microorganisms, which are presumably adapted to frequent wet/dry cycles.