Cadmium accumulation and partitioning in               Ocimum basilicum               as influenced by the application of various potassium fertilizersPotassium (K) is one of the major essential nutrient elements whose application of organic or nano-chelate-fertilizers has received increased attention recently. Cadmium (Cd) contamination in agricultural soils and environment is increasing due to the over-application of Cd-containing phosphate fertilizers. But few studies have been carried out on the environmental influences of K-nano-chelate fertilizers especially on Cd-polluted soils. Therefore, the effects of K-fertilizer application in different rates (0, 100 and 200 mg kg−1 soil) and forms (KCl, K2SO4 and K-nano-chelate) on Cd content and partitioning in Ocimum basilicum grown on an artificially Cd-contaminated calcareous soil (with 40 mg Cd kg−1 soil) were studied under greenhouse conditions. Cadmium decreased shoot dry weight (SDW), but did not affect root dry weight (RDW) and no consistent trend was observed with applied K. Cadmium increased shoot and root Cd concentration or uptake. KCl and K2SO4 increased shoot Cd concentration compared to that of control, whereas K-nano-chelate did not affect it. In Cd-treated soils the mean value of Cd translocation factor (ratio of Cd concentration in shoots to that of roots) decreased by 60% as compared to that of the control. Application of 100 mg K-K2SO4 and 100 and 200 mg K-nano-chelate increased the Cd translocation factor by 49, 59 and 112% in Cd-treated soils, respectively. In Cd-treated soils, greater amounts of Cd accumulated in roots. K-nano-chelate could mitigate the adverse effect of Cd on SDW and Cd accumulation in plants grown on Cd-polluted soils, so the risk of Cd entrance to the food chain is reduced (however, in Cd-untreated soils, K-nano-chelate increased the Cd translocation factor higher than other K sources). In Cd-polluted soils KCl was the most inappropriate fertilizer that may intensify Cd accumulation in plants. However, it may be useful in the phytoremediation of Cd-polluted soils.