Two new Andean species of Neocorynura (Hymenoptera: Halictidae: Augochlorini) with notes on their biologyWe describe and illustrate the male, female, and pupa of two new species of Neocorynura from the Colombian Andes, and provide information on their nesting behavior, host plants and social organization. Nests of Neocorynura iguaquensis sp. nov. Smith‚ÄPardo & Gonzalez and N. muiscae sp. nov. Smith‚ÄPardo & Gonzalez were found in flat or vertical banks, and contained one to three adult females. The percentage of multi‚Äfemale nests varied considerably from 8.3% to 40% of the total of dissected nests at different times in 2000 and 2003. The ovarian development, wing and mandibular wear of females in the nests with two or more females indicated that they were the offspring that remained in the nest before dispersal or a mother and a newly emerged daughter. Pollen taken from the nest cells and scopae of museum specimens showed that both species rely heavily on pollen of asteraceans and may be active year‚Äround. Details on the nest architecture and comments on the phylogenetic placement of both species are also provided. Direct observations on the multi‚Äfemale nests are required to determine whether or not such nests contain temporary assemblages or truly semisocial colonies. Resumen Describimos e ilustramos el macho, hembra y pupa de dos especies nuevas de Neocorynura de los Andes colombianos, y proporcionamos informaci√≥n sobre su biolog√≠a de nidificaci√≥n, plantas hospederas y organizaci√≥n social. Los nidos de Neocorynura iguaquensis sp. nov. Smith‚ÄPardo & Gonzalez y N. muiscae sp. nov. Smith‚ÄPardo & Gonzalez fueron encontrados en el suelo, en √°reas planas o barrancos verticales, y ten√≠an de una a tres hembras adultas. El porcentaje de nidos con m√°s de una hembra vari√≥ considerablemente desde 8.3% al 40% del total de nidos disectados a diferentes meses en el a√±o 2000 y 2003. El desarrollo ov√°rico, desgaste de las alas y mand√≠bulas de las hembras en los nidos con dos o m√°s hembras indicaron que ellas fueron las cr√≠as que permanecieron en el nido antes de dispersarse o una madre con la hija reci√©n nacida. El polen tomado de las celdas de cr√≠a y escopas de especimenes de museo mostr√≥ que ambas especies dependen principalmente de asteraceas y que podr√≠an estar activas todo el a√±o. Tambi√©n oferecemos detalles de la arquitectura del nidos y comentarios sobre la posici√≥n filogen√©tica de ambas especies. Observaciones directas de los nido con m√°s de una hembra son necesarias para determinar si tales nidos son agrupaciones temporales o verdaderas colonias semisociales.