Local-scale synchrony and variability in mast seed production patterns of Picea glauca.<ol><li>Mast seeding is the synchronous and highly variable production of seed by a population of plants. Mast seeding results from the behaviour of individuals; however, little is known about the synchrony of individuals at local scales.</li><li>We address two primary questions at a within-population (17-36 ha study plots) and individual level: (i) How variable is seed production between and within years? (ii) How synchronized is seed production between individuals?</li><li>We monitored annual cone production of 356 <em>Picea glauca</em> (white spruce) from 1990 to 2005 within four plots spanning a total distance of 5.3 km in the Yukon Territory, Canada.</li><li>Spearman correlations (<em>r</em><sub>s</sub>) were conducted to test for synchrony. Overall, the trees were moderately synchronous (mean <em>r</em><sub>s</sub> (± SE) of 0.52 ± 0.14), and synchrony was statistically detectable (<em>r</em><sub>s</sub> &gt; 0) over all distances. Individuals &lt; 75 m apart were highly synchronous (0.64 ± 0.18), and correlations dropped to 0.33 ± 0.07 for trees &gt; 3 km apart. There was considerable variation in cone production patterns among pairs of individuals.</li><li>The number of mast years per plot varied from one to three. During a mast year, many individuals within plots produced large cone crops, with more variability between individuals in low mean cone years. Individual trees had dominant endogenous cycles varying from none to 1-5 years. Forty-four per cent of trees had no significant lag, 23% a negative 1-year lag, and 20% a positive 3-year lag. Basal area did not influence lags, but trees with higher mean cone production throughout the study were more likely to have a 3-year lag compared with no lag.</li><li>The scale of highest synchrony coincided with the scale at which the dominant seed predator in the area, the territorial red squirrel (<em>Tamiasciurus hudsonicus</em>), operates. This may be the scale at which selection for synchrony occurs.</li><li>Based on high synchrony locally, high synchrony within a mast year, and multiple lags in cone production by individuals, both available resources and strong weather cues appear to play roles in the observed patterns.</li></ol>