Dual role for an allelochemical: (±)-catechin from Centaurea maculosa root exudates regulates conspecific seedling establishment.<ol><li>Plant allelopathic compounds may have other roles than interspecific interference. We investigated whether (±)-catechin, a phytotoxin exuded from the roots of the exotic invader <em>Centaurea maculosa</em> (spotted knapweed), is also one of the factors that regulates <em>C. maculosa</em> recruitment.</li><li>Adding activated carbon, which adsorbs organic compounds, to soil around <em>C. maculosa</em> adults in the field increased seedling density by 78% 25 days after sowing, and by 34% 32 days after sowing, suggesting that soil-borne compounds inhibited or delayed recruitment.</li><li>Analysis of field soils near mature <em>C. maculosa</em> revealed that they can contain exceptionally high (±)-catechin concentrations (mean = 1.55 mg g<sup>-;1</sup> dry soil, with 60% of samples containing ≥ 1.0 mg (±)-catechin g<sup>-;1</sup>).</li><li>In laboratory experiments, treatment with ≥ 1.0 mg (±)-catechin mL<sup>-;1</sup> reduced seedling root elongation by &gt; 50%, indicating that field concentrations are sufficient to inhibit <em>C. maculosa</em> recruitment. Provided that 10% methanol was used to maintain (±)-catechin in solution for &gt; 1 day, treatment with ≥ 1.0 mg mL<sup>-;1</sup> also reduced <em>C. maculosa</em> germination by &gt; 70%.</li><li>(±)-Catechin maintained in solution with methanol did not significantly reduce <em>C. maculosa</em> seed survival, suggesting that inhibition of germination was due, at least in part, to delayed germination rather than to seed mortality.</li><li>Depending on the solubility of (±)-catechin in soil and on the duration of its effects on recruitment, <em>C. maculosa</em> may avoid intraspecific competition or regulate the timing of seedling establishment by reducing seedling growth or postponing germination in response to its own phytotoxin.</li><li>Chemical regulation of <em>C. maculosa</em> recruitment, as demonstrated here, suggests a dual role of (±)-catechin as an allelochemical and an autoinhibitor. The potential for a single plant root exudate to influence both inter- and intraspecific interactions emphasizes the complex effects that plant secondary metabolites may have on plant population and community structure.</li></ol>