Bypassing Determination of Time of ConcentrationAbstractReanalysis of the records, upon which the 120-year-old Rational Formula is based, reveals that the published linear relationship between rainfall duration and the ratio of peak discharge to the product of rainfall intensity and watershed area can also be replaced by a logarithmic regression. Such a regression is found, with reasonable correlation, suitable for two-dimensional laboratory watersheds, for four experimental urban watersheds, and for five small watersheds in Israel. Combining this regression with a power-law regression between rainfall intensity and duration, associated with any given recurrence interval, yields a general relationship between the variables. From this and through simple mathematical operations, the maximum discharge associated with that recurrence interval is determined. The variables in the new equation are watershed area and the empirical parameters of the regressions. Application of this equation bypasses determination of the highly influential time of concentration, which is an immeasurable variable and for which varied surrogates are used. It also saves determination of the coefficient C of the Rational Formula. Yet, it requires preparation of regional models for estimation parameter values of the logarithmic regression. Application of the proposed method on the outdoor watersheds, with intensity-duration-frequency curves for representative meteorological stations, yields realistic results. The application for one of those watersheds, with an observational period of 40 years, reveals a wide difference between the prediction through the proposed method and that through statistics of recorded peak discharges. The difference is attributable to association of recurrence intervals of rainfall intensities with peak runoff discharges. The difference is reduced by use of statistics for rainfall intensities during the subseason of high discharges rather than during the entire rainy season.