Belowground competition and the response of developing forest communities to atmospheric CO2 and O3.As human activity continues to increase CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>, broad expanses of north temperate forests will be simultaneously exposed to elevated concentrations of these trace gases. Although both CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> are potent modifiers of plant growth, we do not understand the extent to which they alter competition for limiting soil nutrients, like nitrogen (N). We quantified the acquisition of soil N in two 8-year-old communities composed of trembling aspen genotypes (<em>n</em>= 5) and trembling aspen-paper birch which were exposed to factorial combinations of CO<sub>2</sub> (ambient and 560 &mu;L L<sup>-;1</sup>) and O<sub>3</sub> (ambient = 30-40 vs. 50-60 nL L<sup>-;1</sup>). Tracer amount of <sup>15</sup>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> were applied to soil to determine how these trace gases altered the competitive ability of genotypes and species to acquire soil N. One year after isotope addition, we assessed N acquisition by measuring the amount of <sup>15</sup>N tracer contained in the plant canopy (i.e. recent N acquisition), as well as the total amount of canopy N (i.e. cumulative N acquisition). Exposure to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> differentially altered recent and cumulative N acquisition among aspen genotypes, changing the rank order in which they obtained soil N. Elevated O<sub>3</sub> also altered the rank order in which aspen genotypes obtained soil N by eliciting increases, decreases and no response among genotypes. If aspen genotypes respond similarly under field conditions, then rising concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> could alter the structure of aspen populations. In the aspen-birch community, elevated CO<sub>2</sub> increased recent N (i.e. <sup>15</sup>N) acquisition in birch (68%) to a greater extent than aspen (19%), suggesting that, over the course of this experiment, birch had gained a competitive advantage over aspen. The response of genotypes and species to rising CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> concentrations, and how these responses are modified by competitive interactions, has the potential to change the future composition and productivity of northern temperate forests.