Metabolic and transcriptional regulatory mechanisms underlying the anoxic adaptation of rice coleoptileRice is a unique crop plant since it can survive under anoxia condition by flooding and also germinate and grow up to coleoptile through its distinctive adaptations. Despite several decades of research on this topic, the current knowledge on the molecular machinery of rice under anoxia is very limited. Therefore, we unraveled the possible regulatory mechanisms by resorting to systems biology approach which combines the metabolic modeling and transcriptome analysis. Such integrative analysis highlight the critical role of MYB, bZIP, ERF and ZnF transcription factors in up-regulating the fermentation and sucrose metabolism genes to generate sufficient energy for cellular growth. The ability of rice to germinate under anoxia by extending the coleoptile is a highly unusual characteristic and a key feature underpinning the ability of rice seeds to establish in such a stressful environment. The process has been a focal point for research for many years. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying the anoxic growth of the coleoptile still remain largely unknown. To unravel the key regulatory mechanisms of rice germination under anoxic stress, we combined in silico modelling with gene expression data analysis. Our initial modelling analysis via random flux sampling revealed numerous changes in rice primary metabolism in the absence of oxygen. In particular, several reactions associated with sucrose metabolism and fermentation showed a significant increase in flux levels, whereas reaction fluxes across oxidative phosphorylation, the tricarboxylic acid cycle and the pentose phosphate pathway were down-regulated. The subsequent comparative analysis of the differences in calculated fluxes with previously published gene expression data under air and anoxia identified at least 37 reactions from rice central metabolism that are transcriptionally regulated. Additionally, cis-regulatory content analyses of these transcriptionally controlled enzymes indicate a regulatory role for transcription factors such as MYB, bZIP, ERF and ZnF in transcriptional control of genes that are up-regulated during rice germination and coleoptile elongation under anoxia.