Land-use legacy and the persistence of invasive Avena barbata on abandoned farmland.<ol><li>Exotic species invasion onto abandoned farmlands has been linked to an increase in the availability of soil nutrients after cultivation. <em>Avena barbata </em>Pott. (hereafter <em>Avena</em>) is an exotic annual grass that invades old-fields in south-western Australia and persists for decades after abandonment. We hypothesized that the competitive ability of <em>Avena</em> against native woody seedlings is increased on old-fields affected by P-fertilizer residues.</li><li>We tested this hypothesis in a pot study by growing single native seedlings in competition with increasing densities of <em>Avena</em>, at old-field and pre-agricultural levels of soil P. Then, we planted the same four species, <em>Acacia acuminata</em> Benth., <em>Allocasuarina campestris </em>(Diels) L.A.S.Johnson,<em> Eucalyptus loxophleba</em> Benth. subsp. <em>loxophleba</em> and <em>Hakea recurva </em>Meisn., into plots within an old-field affected by P-fertilizer residues, and removed <em>Avena</em> from half of the plots. Also, as water availability limits seedling establishment, particularly in the presence of <em>Avena</em>, we compared the establishment of seedlings planted into microcatchments to improve water availability with that of seedlings planted into level sites.</li><li>We found that P enrichment did not substantially enhance the ability of <em>Avena</em> to compete with any of the native species that we tested in pots.<em> Avena</em> was the superior competitor against all four native species at both P levels.</li><li>In the field, the chances of native seedling establishment were markedly improved by the removal of <em>Avena. </em>Microcatchments improved the survival of <em>E. loxophleba</em> subsp. <em>loxophleba</em> in competition with <em>Avena</em>, but not that of the three other native species. In the absence of <em>Avena</em>, microcatchments made inconsistent or little difference to the survival and biomass of the planted native seedlings.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications</em>. Reducing soil P will not be sufficient to promote species coexistence on old-fields because <em>Avena</em> remains competitive at low soil P. The combination of the land-use legacies, reduced native seed supply and the introduction of an invasive species that is a superior competitor regardless of P availability, all contribute to the persistence of this invasive species on old-fields in south-western Australia. The restoration of the historic ecosystem will require intense effort and there is a risk that planted communities will be prone to re-invasion.</li></ol>