MITIGATING EXOTIC IMPACTS: RESTORING DEER MOUSE POPULATIONS ELEVATED BY AN EXOTIC FOOD SUBSIDY.The threat posed by exotic organisms to native systems has led to extensive research on exotic invaders, yet management of invasives has progressed relatively slowly. This is partly due to poor understanding of how exotic species management influences native organisms. To address this shortfall, we experimentally evaluated the efficacy of an invasives management tool for restoring native deer mouse (<em>Peromyscus maniculatus</em>) populations elevated by exotic species. The exotic insects, <em>Urophora</em> spp., were introduced in North America for biological control of the Eurasian invader, spotted knapweed (<em>Centaurea maculosa</em>), but instead of controlling <em>C. maculosa</em>, <em>Urophora</em> have become an important food resource that doubles <em>P. maniculatus</em> populations, with substantial indirect effects on other organisms. We hypothesized that herbicide suppression of <em>Urophora</em>'s host plant would reduce the <em>Urophora</em> food resource and restore <em>P. maniculatus</em> populations to natural levels. Prior to treatment, mouse populations did not differ between controls and treatments, but following treatment, <em>P. maniculatus</em> were half as abundant where treatment reduced <em>Urophora</em>. <em>Peromyscus maniculatus</em> is insensitive to direct herbicide effects, and herbicide-induced habitat changes could not explain the <em>P. maniculatus</em> response. Treatment-induced reductions of the <em>Urophora</em> food resource offered the most parsimonious explanation for the mouse response. Multistate mark–recapture models indicated that <em>P. maniculatus</em> survival declined where <em>Urophora</em> were removed, and survival rates were more correlated with variation in population size than movement rates. Other demographic and reproductive parameters (sex ratios, reproductive status, pregnancy rates, and juvenile recruitment) were unaffected by treatment. These results suggest the <em>Urophora</em> biocontrol elevated <em>P. maniculatus</em> survival, and the herbicide treatment restored mouse populations by removing the exotic food and reducing survival. This work illustrates the importance of mechanistic understandings of community and population ecology for improving invasive species management.