OXYGEN ISOTOPE RATIOS OF WATERS AND RESPIRED CO2 IN AMAZONIAN FOREST AND PASTURE ECOSYSTEMS.The oxygen isotope ratio (δ<sup>18</sup>O, SMOW) of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> is a powerful indicator of large-scale CO<sub>2</sub> exchange on land. Oxygen isotopic exchange between CO<sub>2</sub> and water in leaves and soils controls the δ<sup>18</sup>O of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>. Currently there is little empirical information on the spatial and temporal variation in the δ<sup>18</sup>O of leaf and stem water in tropical ecosystems. We measured the seasonal dynamics of δ<sup>18</sup>O in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and water in different ecosystem compartments in both primary forest and pasture ecosystems in three different regions of the Amazonian Basin of Brazil (Ji-Paraná, Manaus, and Santarém). Within regions, the source (stem) water δ<sup>18</sup>O values for primary forests and pastures were similar; neither vegetation type exhibited distinct wet–dry season patterns. Daytime leaf water isotope ratios were strongly correlated with predictions of the Craig-Gordon model. The δ<sup>18</sup>O value of leaf water was positively correlated with leaf height above ground because of associated variation in vapor pressure deficit and the δ<sup>18</sup>O of atmospheric water vapor within forest canopies. Consistent with these observations, the δ<sup>18</sup>O value of leaf cellulose was positively correlated with forest height. Leaf water from pasture grasses was more <sup>18</sup>O enriched than leaf water from forest vegetation. There was a tendency for daytime leaf water to be more enriched in <sup>18</sup>O during the dry season, reflecting generally lower humidity conditions during the dry season. Nighttime measurements of the oxygen isotope ratio of ecosystem respired CO<sub>2</sub> in both forest and pasture vegetation were not consistent with values expected for CO<sub>2</sub> in equilibrium with stem (soil) water, despite nighttime vapor pressure deficits close to zero. Apparently, the δ<sup>18</sup>O of leaf water lagged and did not attain isotopic equilibrium at night. Thus, the deviation of nighttime δ<sup>18</sup>O values of ecosystem respiration from that expected from a CO<sub>2</sub> efflux in equilibrium with soil (stem) water increased as δ<sup>18</sup>O values of ecosystem respiration became <sup>18</sup>O enriched. Discrimination against CO<sub>2</sub> containing <sup>18</sup>O (ΔC<sup>18</sup>OO) during photosynthesis was calculated based on measured leaf water δ<sup>18</sup>O values. Forests had consistently higher modeled ΔC<sup>18</sup>OO values than pastures. The daytime isotope effects we calculate for photosynthesis and respiration were consistent with previous model predictions of a strong depletion of <sup>18</sup>O in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> over the Amazon Basin of Brazil.