In situ angular measurements of thermal infrared sea surface emissivity—Validation of modelsIn this paper, sea surface emissivity (SSE) measurements obtained from thermal infrared radiance data are presented. These measurements were carried out from a fixed oilrig under open sea conditions in the Mediterranean Sea during the WInd and Salinity Experiment 2000 (WISE 2000). The SSE retrieval methodology uses quasi-simultaneous measurements of the radiance coming from the sea surface and the downwelling sky radiance, in addition to the sea surface temperature (SST). The radiometric data were acquired by a CIMEL ELECTRONIQUE CE 312 radiometer, with four channels placed in the 8–14 μm region. The sea temperature was measured with high-precision thermal probes located on oceanographic buoys, which is not exactly equal to the required SST. A study of the skin effect during the radiometric measurements used in this work showed that a constant bulk–skin temperature difference of 0.05±0.06 K was present for wind speeds larger than 5 m/s. Our study is limited to these conditions. Thus, SST used as a reference for SSE retrieval was obtained as the temperature measured by the contact thermometers placed on the buoys at 20-cm depth minus this bulk–skin temperature difference.SSE was obtained under several observation angles and surface wind speed conditions, allowing us to study both the angular and the sea surface roughness dependence. Our results were compared with SSE models, showing the validity of the model of Masuda et al. [Masuda, K., Takashima, T., & Takayama, Y. (1988) Emissivity of pure seawaters for the model sea surface in the infrared window regions. Remote Sensing of Environment, 24, 313–329.] for observation angles up to 50°. For larger angles, the effect of double or multiple reflections on the sea surface produces discrepancies between measured and theoretical SSEs, and more complex models should be used to get accurate SSE values, such as the model of Wu and Smith [Wu, X., & Smith, W.L. (1997). Emissivity of rough sea surface for 8–13 μm: modelling and verification. Applied Optics, 36, 2609–2619.].