Waves and synchrony in Epirrita autumnata /Operophtera brumata outbreaks. I. Lagged synchrony: regionally, locally and among species.<ol><li>In 1990-2003, during a complete 10-year outbreak cycle, the synchrony of the birch defoliating outbreaks of the geometrids <em>Epirrita autumnata</em> and <em>Operophtera brumata</em> was studied quantitatively in the northern part of the Fennoscandian mountain chain (the Scandes). Data were supplemented with similar data from 1964 to 1966 and historical information. A 30-year series of field data from one locality in southern Scandes made possible interregional comparisons.</li><li>In 1991, outbreaks started in north-eastern Fennoscandia and moved westward like a wave and reached the outer coast of north-western Norway in about 2000. This wave is a new observation. In the same years, a previously documented outbreak wave moved southward along the Scandes.</li><li>Outbreak periods have usually occurred around the middle of each decade. Seemingly unrelated population peaks at the decadal shift 2000 were reported from islands at the coast of north-western Norway. They are shown here to have been the final ripples of the east-west wave.</li><li>At some localities, <em>O. brumata</em> peaked 2 years after <em>E. autumnata</em>. A lag of 1 or 2 years also occurred at the locality in southern Scandes. This interspecific time lag is a new observation. In accordance with the north-south wave, a time-lag of 1-2 years occurred between the fluctuations of northern and southern <em>E. autumnata</em> and <em>O. brumata</em> populations.</li><li>The population peak of <em>E. autumnata</em> occurred 1 year earlier at one locality than at a nearby locality. This pattern and particular altitudinal shifts of the <em>O. brumata</em> population density at these localities repeated in two outbreak periods. This indicates that, for example, local climate may modify outbreak synchrony between nearby localities.</li><li>At the same localities, <em>O. brumata</em> peaked first at one altitude and 1 or 2 years later at another altitude. This vertical lag is a new observation.</li><li><em>E. autumnata</em> shows fluctuation traits similar to some other cyclic animals, e.g. the larch budmoth in the European Alps, some European tetraonid birds and the Canadian snow-shoe hare. These similarities (and dissimilarities) in intra- and interspecific synchronies and causes of <em>E. autumnata</em> and <em>O. brumata</em> synchronies, regionally, locally and among the two species are discussed.</li></ol>