Source components and interannual variability of soil CO2 efflux under experimental warming and clipping in a grassland ecosystem.Partitioning soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux into autotrophic (<em>R</em><sub>A</sub>) and heterotrophic (<em>R</em><sub>H</sub>) components is crucial for understanding their differential responses to climate change. We conducted a long-term experiment (2000-2005) to investigate effects of warming 2°C and yearly clipping on soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux and its components (i.e. <em>R</em><sub>A</sub> and <em>R</em><sub>H</sub>) in a tallgrass prairie ecosystem. Interannual variability of these fluxes was also examined. Deep collars (70 cm) were inserted into soil to measure <em>R</em><sub>H</sub>. <em>R</em><sub>A</sub> was quantified as the difference between soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux and <em>R</em><sub>H</sub>. Warming treatment significantly stimulated soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux and its components (i.e. <em>R</em><sub>A</sub> and <em>R</em><sub>H</sub>) in most years. In contrast, yearly clipping significantly reduced soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux only in the last 2 years, although it decreased <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> in every year of the study. Temperature sensitivity (i.e. apparent <em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> values) of soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux was slightly lower under warming (<em>P</em>>0.05) and reduced considerably by clipping (<em>P</em><0.05) compared with that in the control. On average over the 4 years, <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> accounted for approximately 65% of soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux with a range from 58% to 73% in the four treatments. Over seasons, the contribution of <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> to soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux reached a maximum in winter (&sim;90%) and a minimum in summer (&sim;35%). Annual soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux did not vary substantially among years as precipitation did. The interannual variability of soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux may be mainly caused by precipitation distribution and summer severe drought. Our results suggest that the effects of warming and yearly clipping on soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux and its components did not result in significant changes in <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> or <em>R</em><sub>A</sub> contribution, and rainfall timing may be more important in determining interannual variability of soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux than the amount of annual precipitation.