Estimating and mapping crop residues cover on agricultural lands using hyperspectral and IKONOS dataCrop residues left on agricultural lands after harvest play an important role in controlling and protecting soil against water and wind erosion. One challenge of remote sensing is to differentiate crop residues from bare soil and crop cover, especially when the residues have been weathered and/or when the crop cover phenology is more advanced. Several techniques for mapping and estimating crop residues exist in the literature. However, these methods are time consuming and not suited for quantitative evaluation. They have the disadvantage of being less rigorous and accurate because they do not consider the spectral mixture of different materials in the same pixel. In this study, the potential of hyperspectral (Probe-1) and multispectral high spatial resolution (IKONOS) data were compared for estimating and mapping crop residues on agricultural lands using the constrained linear spectral mixture analysis approach. Image data were spectrally and radiometrically calibrated, atmospherically corrected, as well as geometrically rectified. Pure spectral signatures of residues, bare soil and crop cover were manually extracted from image data based on prior knowledge of the fields. Percent (fraction) cover for each sampling point was extracted using unmixing and validated against ground reference measurements. The best results were achieved for the crop cover (index of agreement (D)=0.92 and root mean square error (RMSE)=0.09) adjusted for the impurity of the endmembers canola, pea and wheat, followed by the wheat residues (D=0.76 and RMSE=0.12). Considering only the wheat residues in fields with a canola crop, D increases to 0.86. The soil fractions were generally underestimated with D=0.72, and no significant improvements could be made after adjusting for the shadow effect. The estimations from the IKONOS data were poorer for the same cover types (residues: D=0.40 and RMSE=0.24; crop: D=0.51 and RMSE=0.38; soil: D=0.58 and RMSE=0.29). Relative to the IKONOS data, the better performance of the hyperspectral data is mainly due to the improved spectral band characteristics, especially in the SWIR, which is sensitive to the residues (lignin and cellulose absorption features), soil and crop cover.