Herbivory drives zonation of stress-tolerant marsh plantsEcological studies of plant distributions along environmental gradients, such as plant zonation in salt marshes, have primarily focused on abiotic stress and plant interactions (competition and facilitation). A decades-old paradigm is that the stressful and benign boundaries of salt marsh plants are determined by abiotic stress and competition, respectively. Although consumers have long been recognized as mediating algal and sessile animal zonation in the rocky intertidal, their role in generating plant zonation in salt marshes remains largely unexplored. We examined the zonation of two annual succulents, Salicornia europaea and Suaeda salsa, along an elevation gradient in a northern Chinese salt marsh, with and without manipulating the common herbivorous crab Helice tientsinensis. Salicornia occupies waterlogged, low-salinity habitats, whereas Suaeda dominates non-waterlogged, hypersaline habitats at higher elevations. We first conducted a pot experiment crossing salinity, waterlogging, and competition, followed by a field experiment with removal of competitors, and found that neither waterlogging nor salinity stress explained the absence of either species from the other's zone, while Suaeda competitively excluded Salicornia from the upper non-waterlogged zone. We then conducted field and lab herbivory experiments, which showed that Helice preferentially grazed Suaeda at waterlogged low elevations and that Helice grazing on Suaeda increased with waterlogging. These results reveal that while competition plays a role in the zonation by excluding Salicornia from the upper Suaeda zone, crab grazing limits the success of Suaeda in the lower Salicornia zone. These findings challenge the idea that plant interactions and abiotic stress are sufficient to explain marsh zonation in all cases, and highlight an overlooked role of consumers, a role potentially general across diverse intertidal ecosystems. Future models of plant distributions should consider how consumer pressure interacts with plant interactions and abiotic stress across environmental gradients.