Sustainable production of azadirachtin from differentiated in vitro cell lines of neem (Azadirachta indica)Neem possesses immense medicinal properties and has immediate application as ecofriendly, biodegradable biopesticide. All these properties are because of a structurally complex bioactive compound Azadirachtin, mainly present in seeds. However, it could not be exploited to its full because of heterogeneity in compound production due to out-breeding in nature of the plant. This is the first elaborate report on systematic studies on azadirachtin biosynthesis where different redifferentiated and dedifferentiated in vitro cell lines of A. indica (neem), obtained from various explants, were utilized. All cell lines were found positive for the compound with significantly higher azadirachtin yield of 2330 µg /g DW was obtained from redifferentiated cell lines established from zygotic embryo cultures. The study, demonstrates the possibility of consistent biosynthesis of azadirachtin in bulk under optimal growth conditions. Azadirachtin has high industrial demand due to its immediate application as an ecofriendly, biodegradable biopesticide and also due to its various other significant bioactivities. To date, the only commercially feasible way to produce azadirachtin is extraction from seeds, but their availability is very limited as the tree flowers only once a year and only one-third of the fruits are collected due to operational problems. Further, due to the strict out-breeding nature of the plant, the seeds are highly heterozygous, resulting in inconsistent metabolite production. Therefore, in the present study, to achieve sustainable production of azadirachtin, dedifferentiated and redifferentiated calli derived from various explants of neem—zygotic embryo, leaf and ovary—were investigated for their potential to biosynthesize azadirachtin. High-performance liquid chromatography analysis of the in vitro cell lines showed the presence of azadirachtin in all the samples tested, the content of which in cultured cells varied with explant source and cell differentiation response. The presence of azadirachtin in samples was further confirmed by positive electrospray ionization mass spectroscopy. The zygotic embryo cultures of neem accumulated much higher amounts of azadirachtin than leaf and ovary cultures. Furthermore, organized in vitro callus cultures (redifferentiated) supported higher azadirachtin biosynthesis, while unorganized callus cultures (dedifferentiated) supported the least. The maximum azadirachtin content of 2.33 mg g−1 dry weight was obtained from redifferentiated immature zygotic embryo cultures.