Differential drought tolerance in tree populations from contrasting elevationsWater-use efficiency, leaf area and leaf gas exchange of cowpeas under mid-season droughtIntra-specific variability in biomass partitioning and carbon isotopic discrimination under moderate drought stress in seedlings from four <italic>Pinus pinaster</italic> populationsGenetic differentiation of intrinsic water-use efficiency in the Hawaiian native <italic>Acacia koa</italic>Changes in growth, gas exchange, xylem hydraulic properties and water use efficiency of three olive cultivars under contrasting water availability regimesTo what extent is altitudinal variation of functional traits driven by genetic adaptation in European oak and beech?The photosynthetic drought physiology of a diverse group of southern hemisphere conifer species is correlated with minimum seasonal rainfallGeographical variation in morphology of <italic>Quercus petraea</italic> (Matt.) Liebl. as related to drought stressUnderstanding plant responses to drought—from genes to the whole plantPhotosynthesis under drought and salt stress: regulation mechanisms from whole plant to cellPhylogeography of <italic>Pinus tabulaeformis</italic> Carr. (Pinaceae), a dominant species of coniferous forest in northern ChinaMorphological and physiological responses of two coffee progenies to soil water availabilityBiomass partitioning, morphology and water status of four alfalfa genotypes submitted to progressive drought and subsequent recoveryCarbon isotope discrimination and water-use efficiencyPotential growth and drought tolerance of eight desert grasses: lack of trade-off?Mesophyll conductance to CO<sub>2</sub> and leaf morphological characteristics under drought stress during <italic>Quercus ilex L</italic>. resproutingMesophyll conductance to CO<sub>2</sub>: current knowledge and future prospectsImproving water use efficiency in grapevines: potential physiological targets for biotechnological improvementTranscriptional and metabolic profiles of <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> L. genotypes in response to a PEG-induced water stress<italic>In situ</italic> measurements of carbon and nitrogen distribution and composition, photochemical efficiency and stable isotope ratios in <italic>Araucaria angustifolia</italic>Physiological and morphological adaptations in relation to water use efficiency in Mediterranean accessions of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>Physiological responses to gradual drought stress in the diploid hybrid <italic>Pinus densata</italic> and its two parental speciesPhysiological responses of tagasaste to a progressive drought in its native environment on the Canary IslandsPopulation differentiation and plastic responses to drought stress in the generalist <italic>Polygonum persicaria</italic>Drought tolerance and water-use efficiencyGermination and seedling growth of five species from tropical dry forest in relation to water stress: impact of seed sizeAntioxidative defense system, pigment composition, and photosynthetic efficiency in two wheat cultivars subjected to droughtEnhanced drought-tolerance in the homoploid hybrid species <italic>Pinus densata</italic>: implication for its habitat divergence from two progenitorsDrought responses in Aleppo pine seedlings from two wild provenances with different climatic featuresGrowth and transpiration of Japanese cedar (<italic>Cryptomeria japonica</italic>) and Hinoki cypress (<italic>Chamaecyparis obtusa</italic>) seedlings in response to soil water contentGrowth and physiology of <italic>Picea abies</italic> populations from elevational transects: common garden evidence for altitudinal ecotypes and cold adaptationA global study of relationships between leaf traits, climate and soil measures of nutrient fertilityWater deficits are more important in delaying growth than in changing patterns of carbon allocation in <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic>Hydraulic constraints limit height growth in trees at high altitudeDrought stress response in <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic>: growth and physiologyCarbon isotopes and water use efficiency: sense and sensitivityExpression of the Nicotiana protein kinase (NPK1) enhanced drought tolerance in transgenic maizePhotosynthesis, dry matter accumulation and distribution in the wild sunflower <italic>Helianthus petiolaris</italic> and the cultivated sunflower <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> as influenced by water deficitsVariability of water use efficiency in grapevinesBiomass partitioning and root morphology of savanna trees across a water gradientDifferential responses of lipid peroxidation and antioxidants in the leaves of drought-tolerant <italic>P. acutifolius</italic> Gray and drought-sensitive <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> L. subjected to polyethylene glycol mediated water stressDifferentiation in populations of <italic>Hordeum spontaneum</italic> Koch along a gradient of environmental productivity and predictability: plasticity in response to water and nutrient stressResponses to water stress of gas exchange and metabolites in <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> and <italic>Acacia</italic> sppNatural variation for drought-response traits in the <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic> species complexPopulation differences in water use efficiency of well-watered and water-stressed western larch seedlingsAltitudinal differences in the leaf fitness of juvenile and mature alpine spruce trees (<italic>Picea crassifolia</italic>)Estimation of biomass and net primary productivity of major planted forests in China based on forest inventory dataF.M. and T.T.X. contributed equally to this work.<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Tim J. BrodribbThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.To investigate the differential drought tolerance between populations of <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> from high-elevation (HP) and low-elevation (LP), seedlings of these two populations were subjected to a gradual depletion of soil water availability with a series of traits related to growth and water use efficiency being measured. From our results, we found that all the measured variables from the HP were affected less by drought compared to those of the LP, and most aspects of the HP were canalized against drought stress. We thus drew a conclusion that the two populations responded differentially to drought stress with the HP showing higher drought tolerance than the LP.To predict the ecological consequences of climate change for a widely distributed tree species, it is essential to develop a deep understanding of the ecophysiological responses of populations from contrasting climates to varied soil water availabilities. In the present study, we focused on <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic>, one of the most economically and ecologically important tree species in China. In a greenhouse experiment, we exposed trees from high-elevation (HP) and low-elevation (LP) populations to low (80 % of field capacity, FC), mild (60 % FC), moderate (40 % FC) and severe (20 % FC) water stresses. Leaf gas exchange, biomass production and allocation, as well as water-use efficiency, were measured during the experiment. Increasing soil water stress clearly decreased the relative growth rate (RGR), total dry mass (TDM), light-saturated photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>), stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), total water use (TWU) and whole-plant water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>WP</sub>). In contrast, intrinsic water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>i</sub>) and carbon isotope composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C) both increased significantly with increasing soil water stress for both populations. Only in the LP did the root/shoot ratio (R/S ratio) significantly increase when the water stress increased. A strong positive correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> coupled with a reduced intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>) probably suggested that stomatal limitations were the main cause of the decreased <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>. However, all the measured variables from the HP were affected less by drought compared with those of the LP, and most aspects of the HP were canalized against drought stress, which was reflected by the relatively higher RGR, TDM and WUE<sub>WP</sub>. Overall, the results suggest that the two populations responded differentially to drought stress with the HP showing higher drought tolerance than the LP, which was reflected by its faster seedling growth rate and more efficient water use under drought conditions.Water availability is a crucial factor that limits the growth, development and distribution of all plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C8">Chaves <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C35">Ordoñez <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C47">Wu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and its importance will only become more pronounced in the future due to human-caused climate change resulting in more frequent and severe drought events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C24">IPCC 2007</xref>). Therefore, to predict the ecological consequences of climate change on the widely distributed tree species, detailed knowledge on their ability to cope with varied water availability is needed within and among populations.Low water availability (drought) affects the performance of plants by affecting their morphological, physiological and biochemical, as well as transcriptomic and proteomic processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C1">Anyia and Herzog 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C22">González-Rodríguez <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C11">Dias <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C18">Foito <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C21">Gao <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C31">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C43">Tomlinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). A gradual depletion of the soil water leads to the stomatal (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) and mesophyll (<italic>g</italic><sub>m</sub>) conductance being reduced, and this is believed to be the primary drought stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C16">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C9">Chaves <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C20">Galmés <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C46">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), which causes the water loss to be reduced, but this also results in the rate of photosynthesis being reduced due to reduced CO<sub>2</sub> in chloroplasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C16">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Photosynthesis can be further limited by metabolic impairment due to increasing drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C16">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Drought can also lead to reduced growth and biomass production, while also altering the allocation pattern of biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C12">Erice <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Water-use efficiency (WUE) is one of the most important indicators for evaluating the tolerance of plants to water stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C29">Kozlowski and Pallardy 1997</xref>). At the leaf level, WUE can be defined as the ratio of the net photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>N</sub>) to <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> (WUE<sub>i</sub>, intrinsic water-use efficiency), and an integrated measurement of WUE<sub>i</sub> can be reliably assessed by the carbon isotope composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C, a measure of the <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C ratio in plant tissues compared with air) as it has a linear relationship with the intercellular to ambient CO<sub>2</sub> ratio (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>/<italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C13">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C6">Brodribb and Hill 1998</xref>). Factors that affect <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>m</sub> can thus influence <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> and subsequently the relationship between WUE<sub>i</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C16">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C39">Seibt <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C15">Fleck <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Water-use efficiency at the whole-plant level, defined as the ratio of actual dry matter production to water consumption (WUE<sub>wp</sub>), represents a large spatial (whole plant) and temporal scale (whole growth period) water use that is closely associated with the physiological processes of plants, such as photosynthesis, respiration and transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C17">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). If a plant has a greater WUE, it is expected to be able to survive environments that are more arid better than a plant with a lower WUE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C25">Jones 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C3">Ares <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C19">Franco <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).<italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> is an endemic pine species from China which is one of the most economically and ecologically important tree species in the northern part of the country and covers a total area of 228.10 × 10<sup>4</sup> ha. Particularly in arid and semi-arid areas, it plays an important role in reforestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C51">Zhao and Zhou 2005</xref>). Due to its wide geographical distribution and long life span, populations <italic>of P. tabuliformis</italic> are exposed to a wide variety of drought stresses that has likely led to the adaptation of natural populations to locally distinct environments. Therefore, determining how populations have adapted to varied soil water conditions will enable a greater understanding of past differentiation while also enabling better forest management and restoration in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C48">Yong <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). In the present study, two populations of <italic>P. tabuliformis</italic> from contrasting elevations were selected and subjected to a gradient of soil water contents, due to the species having occurred over a wide range of elevations from 100 to 2800 m above sea level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C10">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Relative to populations growing at lower elevations, tree populations from higher elevations generally exhibit reduced growth, smaller and thicker leaves, higher leaf nutrient content per unit area, higher fine root production and higher allocation of biomass to roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C34">Oleksyn <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C28">Körner 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C50">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C5">Bresson <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C37">Petit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The differentiation in these physiological and morphological traits has been thought to be an adaptation to enhance photosynthesis and water-use efficiency while increasing the resistance to the limited water availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C34">Oleksyn <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C28">Körner 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C5">Bresson <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Therefore, we expected that the two populations would show differential responses to varied soil water availabilities, with the population from the high elevation (HP) having a higher drought tolerance than the low-elevation population (LP), which would result in a higher growth rate, biomass production and water-use efficiency under limited water conditions.Seeds of <italic>P. tabuliformis</italic> for use in the present study were collected from two locations: Xiahe (35°33.85′E, 102°13.60′N, 2810 m Alt.; HP) and Zhengning (35°31.18′E, 108°29.51′N, 1444 m Alt.; LP). The corresponding mean annual rainfall values in the two areas are 516 and 623 mm, while the mean annual temperatures (MATs) are 3.6 and 9.6 °C, respectively. These seeds were germinated and grown indoors for 1 year in a tree nursery, and 112 seedlings of each population with no statistical differences in height and size were transferred to Yuzhong, Gansu Province (35°56.61′N; 104°09.07′E; 1750 m Alt.), and immediately replanted into 6-L plastic pots (28 pots, four seedlings per pot) filled with the same weight of a homogeneous mixture (peat and perlite, 1 : 1 by volume). Another 12 pots were prepared in the same way but without seedlings and these were used to determine the evaporation of water from the soil. The soil surface in all the pots was covered with a small quantity (c. 2 cm) of perlite to minimize evaporation. The maximum field capacity (FC) for watering the pots was determined gravimetrically according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C40">Shou <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> with some modifications. All pots were periodically watered to FC for 2 months after repotting to allow the seedlings to become established. The seedlings were grown for the rest of the study in a canopied and naturally lit glasshouse, the roof of which was closed at night and on rainy days, but opened during any day it was not raining. The sides of the glasshouse were always open for aeration during the whole experiment, so that the temperature inside the glasshouse was closely linked to the outside ambient temperature.For each population, 20 pots were selected and divided into four lots of five pots each (low, mild, moderate and severe water stress treatments). The remaining pots were used to determine the initial biomass. Water stress treatments were achieved by watering to 80 % of maximum FC, 60 % FC, 40 % FC and 20 % FC. All water stress treatments reached the target FC in 7 days from the beginning of the experiment. Soil water content was maintained by weighing the pots every 2 days, recording the water loss and re-watering to the designated water level immediately. The soil water contents before and after watering were maintained at 54–60, 45–50, 34–40 and 22–25 % for the treatments, respectively. The experiment lasted for 134 days from July to November, and during the whole experiment no fertilizer was added at any point and no plants died.On 3 sunny days (15 August, 15 September and 15 October) during the experiment, the light-saturated photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>), stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) and intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>) were measured on sun-adapted needles using an LI-COR 6400 infrared gas-analyzer (IRGA, LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA). The light level was maintained at 1500 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> using an LI-6400-02B LED light source (10 % blue light) and the external CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was maintained at 370 μmol mol<sup>−1</sup> using a CO<sub>2</sub> injector (LI-6400-01). The ambient and internal temperatures and vapour pressure deficits were 31.03 ± 1.18 °C, 3.18 ± 0.53 kPa and 31.50 ± 0.11 °C, 3.35 ± 0.20 kPa on 15 August; 27.00 ± 1.08 °C, 2.52 ± 0.17 kPa and 27.67 ± 0.35 °C, 2.83 ± 0.32 kPa on 15 September and 21.30 ± 0.83 °C, 2.20 ± 0.17 kPa and 21.89 ± 0.22 °C, 2.31 ± 0.14 kPa on 15 October, respectively. At least four replicates for each treatment per population were measured and measurements of two individual seedlings in one pot were considered as one replicate. Needles were marked and cut after the last measurement for area determination using an LI-COR-3000A planimeter (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA). The WUE<sub>i</sub> was defined as the ratio of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> to <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>. The mean values of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> and WUE<sub>i</sub> measured on 3 days are presented in this paper.Due to possible within pot effects, such as competition for resources, each pot was considered to be a single replicate with the four seedlings’ measurements being combined for determining the growth and water use. To estimate the biomass production during the experiment, three pots (12 seedlings) from each population at the beginning of the experiment (<italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub>) and four pots (16 seedlings) at the end of the experiment (<italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub>) were harvested. From each pot, the four seedlings were bulked together and divided into three parts: leaves, stems and roots. The three biomass parts were dried for 48 h at 80 °C in an oven, weighted and then the weights were divided by four to determine per plant values from the per pot values. The relative growth rate (RGR) was calculated using the following formula: RGR = (ln<italic>W</italic><sub>2</sub> − ln<italic>W</italic><sub>1</sub>)/(<italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub> − <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub>), where <italic>W</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>W</italic><sub>2</sub> are the dry weights per plant at Day <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub> and Day <italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub>. The root/shoot (R/S) ratio was also calculated. The WUE at the whole-plant level was calculated as WUE<sub>WP</sub> per plant = (<italic>W</italic><sub>2</sub> − <italic>W</italic><sub>1</sub>)/<italic>T</italic>, where <italic>T</italic> is the total transpired water use per plant (TWU) between <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub>.The oven-dried needle samples were finely ground with a Tissuelyzer (Retsch, Haan, Germany), and the carbon isotope composition of the needles (δ<sup>13</sup>C) was determined by combusting the samples in an elemental analyser EA1108 (Carlo Erba, Milano, Italy) coupled to a Finnigan Delta Plus isotope mass spectrometer (Thermo Finnigan MAT GmbH, Bremen, Germany) at the Key Laboratory of Western China's Environmental Systems (Ministry of Education), Lanzhou University. The carbon isotope composition was calculated relative to the Pee Dee Belemnite (PDB) standard as the ratio (‰): δ<sup>13</sup>C = [(<italic>R</italic><sub>sample</sub>/<italic>R</italic><sub>standard</sub>) − 1] × 1000, where <italic>R</italic><sub>sample</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>standard</sub> are the ratios of <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C in the sample and the standard, respectively.The variables including LDM, SDM, RDM, TDM, RGR, R/<italic>S</italic> ratio, TWU, WUE<sub>wp</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C were analysed using the general linear model (Proc GLM) to test the effect of the populations, water treatments and their interactions. Leaf gas exchange parameters, including <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> and WUE<sub>i</sub>, were analysed by the GLM with the measurement time as a covariate. When the differences were significant, a multiple comparison of means (post-hoc Tukey's honestly significant difference test) was carried out. Before the statistical tests were performed using the SPSS software package (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), the homogeneity of the data was determined.Growth, biomass production and allocation as well as water use of <italic>Pinus tabuliaeformis</italic> from a HP and a LP under various soil water conditions (80 % of maximal FC, 60 % FC, 40 % FC and 20 % FC). Each point represents mean ± SE. The letters indicate statistical differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the water treatments, populations and the interactions between them.Comparison of all variables measured in the experiment. The <italic>P-</italic>values are presented for the watering treatments, populations and their interactions. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Relative growth rate and R/S ratio in two populations of <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> from a HP (black bars) and a LP (white bars) under various soil water conditions (80 % of maximal FC, 60 % FC, 40 % FC and 20 % FC). Scale bars represent mean ± SE. The letters indicate statistical differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the water treatments, populations and the interactions between them.Means of light-saturated photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>), stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>) and intrinsic water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>i</sub>) measured on 3 days (15 August, 15 September and 15 October) in two populations of <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> from a HP (black bars) and a LP (white bars) under various soil water conditions (80 % of maximal FC, 60 % FC, 40 % FC and 20 % FC). Each bar represents mean ± SE. The letters indicate statistical differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the water treatments, populations and the interactions between them.Relationships between light-saturated photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) and stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) as well as between WUE<sub>i</sub> and carbon isotope composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C) in the two populations of <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> from a HP (filled circles) and a LP (empty circles) across water treatments. The coefficient of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) and significance are shown for each regression.Carbon isotope composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C) in the two populations of <italic>Pinus tabuliformis</italic> from a HP (black bars) and a LP (white bars) under various soil water conditions (80 % of maximal FC, 60 % FC, 40 % FC and 20 % FC). Each point represents mean ± SE. The letters indicate statistical differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the water treatments, populations and the interactions between them.Water availability as a growth-limiting factor was demonstrated in the present study, as it caused significant reductions in RGR, TDM, LDM, SDM and RDM in both populations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB1">1</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F1">1</xref>). Comparatively, the HP showed a higher RGR and TDM from the mild to severe water stress treatments than the LP, and the differences were highly significant (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB1">1</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F1">1</xref>). These results support the previously published work that various growth responses within and between species were due to drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C4">Bacelar <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C7">Bruschi 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C31">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Research has also revealed that plants with higher drought tolerance exhibit less growth inhibition and had relatively higher growth and biomass production than drought-sensitive ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C30">Loggini <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C44">Türkan <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Therefore, these results suggested a higher capacity for the HP than for the LP to sustain growth and production under water-limited conditions.Drought affects plant growth by influencing the leaf gas exchange rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C49">Zhang and Marshall 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C4">Bacelar <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C31">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C38">Sapeta <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). A reduction in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>m</sub> as well as metabolic impairment are considered to be the main causes of the depression of photosynthesis in the face of drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C16">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Accordingly, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> of the two populations significantly decreased after exposure to drought stress, and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> was strongly positively correlated with <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F2">2</xref>). From this it was possible to surmise that stomatal closure caused by drought stress resulted in the <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> being reduced under drought conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F3">3</xref>), and the <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> in both populations being reduced at the same time supports this conclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C32">Michelozzi <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). However, compared with the gradual decrease of <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> in the LP, only severe water stress induced significant reductions in those two parameters in the HP. Even under extreme water stress conditions, the HP had higher <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> values than the LP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F2">2</xref>). These results indicated that the leaf gas exchange in the two populations responded differently to the drought conditions, and that the apparent ability of the HP to maintain higher photosynthetic rates may allow it to grow more rapidly under water-limited conditions. This conclusion is supported by the above results that the HP exhibited a higher growth rate and biomass production than the LP under water-limited conditions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB1">1</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F1">1</xref>).The WUE<sub>i</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C significantly increased in both populations with decreasing water availability, and the WUE<sub>i</sub> was positively correlated with δ<sup>13</sup>C (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU069F3">3</xref>), which was similar to the results of previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C13">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C26">Jones 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C49">Zhang and Marshall 1994</xref>). The WUE<sub>i</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C of the LP gradually increased from the low to severe water stresses, whereas these two parameters for the HP only showed significant increases under severe stress treatment (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB2">2</xref>). The higher WUE<sub>i</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C values in the LP than in the HP under mild, moderate and severe water stress treatments were mainly due to the relatively small changes of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> in the HP under drought conditions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB2">2</xref>). These findings support the hypothesis that populations will be less plastic if they come from an environment that is dry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C45">Volis <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C23">Heschel <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C2">Aranda <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> also reported lower plasticity to environmental changes in the HP than in the LP.With respect to the WUE at the whole-plant level, the WUE<sub>wp</sub> showed an opposite trend to the WUE<sub>i</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C, with both populations recording a significant drop between the low and moderate stress treatments, and a further significant drop between the moderate and severe stress treatments for the LP (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB1">1</xref>). These findings confirmed previous observations by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C42">Tomás <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C17">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> that there are large discrepancies when scaling-up WUE measurements from the leaf to the whole-plant level. Several structural and physiological processes, such as canopy structure, transpiration by plant organs other than leaves, respiration by leaf during the night and by stem and root during the whole day, will lead to a decrease in the WUE<sub>wp</sub>, but not influence the leaf-level estimates. However, the HP showed a significantly higher WUE<sub>WP</sub> than the LP in all water treatments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU069TB1">1</xref>), which indicates a higher potential to survive water-limited conditions by efficient water use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C25">Jones 1992</xref>).It is widely accepted that a reduced water supply will result in an increased partitioning of biomass in favour of root growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C14">Fernández and Reynolds 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C27">Khurana and Singh 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C33">Nagakura <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), but not all studies have found this (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C36">Osório <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C43">Tomlinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Curiously, in the current study, an increase in the R/S ratio was evident in the LP, whereas in the HP there was no detectable change, which indicates that a loss of plasticity for this character might have been an advantage for existence at higher elevations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C41">Sobrado and Turner 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU069C2">Aranda <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).This study indicated that increasing water stress had a significant effect on leaf gas exchange, biomass production and allocation, carbon isotope composition and water-use efficiency in both HP and LP. However, the two populations differed significantly in their responses to drought stress: the HP appeared to be less affected by water stress than the LP as far as the examined variables were concerned, as well as the exhibited TDM, RGR and WUE<sub>L</sub> in the stress treatments. The results supported the hypothesis that there would be different drought tolerance levels in the two populations with the HP having a greater tolerance.This study was supported by grants from the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">National Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (Nos <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">31260166, 31170571 and 31360185</grant-num>).The research design and preparation of the manuscript are credited to F.M. T.T.X. contributed to data collection and analysis. M.F.J. mainly contributed to the seedling cultivation. C.M.Z. contributed to conception of the study and suggestions for writing the manuscript.None declared.The authors are grateful to anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments on the manuscript.