 Apple EIN3 BINDING F-box 1 inhibits the activity of three apple EIN3-like transcription factors  Cellulase activity in developing apple fruits  Ethylene and fruit ripening  The  Arabidopsis  EIN3 binding F-box proteins EBF1 and EBF2 have distinct but overlapping roles in ethylene signalling  Activation of the ethylene gas response pathway in  Arabidopsis  by the nuclear protein ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE3 and related proteins  Ethylene signal transduction  Role of the genes  Md-ACO1  and  Md-ACS1  in ethylene production and shelf life of apple ( Malus domestica  Borkh)  A genomics approach to understanding the role of auxin in apple ( Malus × domestica ) fruit size control  Red colouration in apple fruit is due to the activity of the MYB transcription factor, MdMYB10  A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood  Plant responses to ethylene gas are mediated by SCF(EBF1/EBF2) dependent proteolysis of EIN3 transcription factor  Genomic nucleotide sequence of a ripening-related 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase gene ( MdACS-1 ) in apple (accession no. U89156) (PGR97-066)  pGreen: a versatile and flexible binary Ti vector for  Agrobacterium -mediated plant transformation  Transient expression vectors for functional genomics, quantification of promoter activity and RNA silencing in plants  Melon EIN3-like transcription factors (CmEIL1 and CmEIL2) are positive regulators of an ethylene- and ripening-induced 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid oxidase gene ( CM-ACO1 )  Mining the apple genome reveals a family of nine ethylene receptor genes  Global gene expression analysis of apple fruit development from the floral bud to ripe fruit  Co-ordination of early and late ripening events in apples is regulated through differential sensitivities to ethylene  The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequences  A full-length cDNA encoding 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase from apple  An apple ( Malus domestica  L. Borkh cv. Granny Smith) homolog of the ethylene receptor gene  ETR1   Recent advances in ethylene research  Analyses of expressed sequence tags from apple  ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE5 encodes a 5′→3′ exoribonuclease required for regulation of the EIN3-targeting F-box proteins EBF1/2  EIN3-dependent regulation of plant ethylene hormone signaling by two  Arabidopsis  F box proteins: EBF1 and EBF2  A genomics approach reveals that aroma production in apple is controlled by ethylene predominantly at the final step in each biosynthetic pathway  SEPALLATA1/2-suppressed mature apples have high auxin and reduced transcription of ripening-related genes  The genome of woodland strawberry ( Fragaria vesca )  Nuclear events in ethylene signaling: a transcriptional cascade mediated by ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE3 and ETHYLENE-RESPONSE-FACTOR1  The role of ethylene and cold temperature in the regulation of the apple POLYGALACTURONASE 1 gene and fruit softening  The genome of the domesticated apple ( Malus × domestica  Borkh.)  An enhanced transient expression system in plants based on suppression of gene silencing by the p19 protein of tomato bushy stunt virus  Null mutation of the MdACS3 gene, coding for a ripening-specific 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase, leads to long shelf life in apple fruit  Survey of the expression of genes for ethylene synthesis and perception during maturation and ripening of ‘Sunrise’ and ‘Golden Delicious’ apple fruit  Differential regulation of EIN3 stability by glucose and ethylene signalling in plants  Silencing Sl-EBF1 and Sl-EBF2 expression causes constitutive ethylene response phenotype, accelerated plant senescence, and fruit ripening in tomato  Kiwifruit EIL and ERF genes involved in regulating fruit ripening  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited  Mining the apple genome identified four  EIN3 BINDING F-BOX  genes, two developmentally regulated and two constitutively expressed. One ( EBF1 ) was found to reduce the activity of three apple  EIN3-like  genes  Fruit ripening in  Malus ×  domestica  (apple) is controlled by ethylene. Work in model species has shown that following the detection of ethylene, the ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE 3 (EIN3) transcription factor is stabilized, leading to an increase in transcript accumulation of ethylene-responsive genes, such as  POLYGALACTURONASE1  ( PG1 ). In the absence of ethylene, the EIN3 BINDING F-box (EBF) proteins rapidly degrade EIN3 via the ubiquitination/SCF (Skp, Cullin, F-Box) proteasome pathway. In this study, we aim to identify and characterize the apple  EBF  genes, and test their activity against apple EIN3-like proteins (EILs).  The apple genome sequence was mined for  EBF -like genes. The expression of  EBF -like genes was measured during fruit development. Using a transient assay in  Nicotiana benthamiana  leaves, the activity of three apple EILs was tested against the  PG1  promoter, with and without ethylene and EBF1.  Four  EBF -like genes in apple were identified and grouped into two sub-clades. Sub-clade I genes had constant expression over fruit development while sub-clade II genes increased in expression at ripening. EBF1 was shown to reduce the transactivation of the apple  PG1  promoter by the EIL1, EIL2 and EIL3 transcription factors in the presence of ethylene.  The apple  EBF1  gene identified here is likely to be a functionally conserved  EBF  orthologue, modulating EIL activity in apples. The activity of EBF1 suggests that it is not specific to a single EIL, instead acting as a global regulator of apple EIL transcription factors.  Ethylene is involved in a wide range of developmental processes in plants including seed germination, cell elongation, sex determination, fruit ripening, senescence and leaf abscission, as well as biotic and abiotic stress responses ( Abeles and Biles 1991 ;  Barry and Giovannoni 2007 ;  Lin  et al.  2009 ). The ethylene response pathway can be briefly summarized as follows: the pathway is thought to be predominantly linear, consisting of ethylene receptors, which in the absence of ethylene constitutively repress the activity of the MAP kinase CONSTITUTIVE TRIPLE RESPONSE1 (CTR1); this modulates the activity of ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE 2 (EIN2), which results in the destabilization of the ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE 3 (EIN3) transcription factors. In the presence of ethylene this pathway is repressed and EIN3 is stabilized, initiating a transcriptional cascade leading to an ethylene response ( Chen  et al.  2005 ).  In the absence of ethylene, EIN3 is short-lived with a half-life of &lt;30 min due to rapid degradation through the ubiquitin/Skp, Cullin, F-Box degradation pathway ( Guo and Ecker 2003 ;  Yanagisawa  et al.  2003 ). In  Arabidopsis , two redundant nuclear localized F-box proteins, EIN3-BINDING F BOX PROTEIN1 (AtEBF1) and AtEBF2, were shown to target EIN3 and a functional homologue EIN3-like 1 (EIL1) for degradation ( Guo and Ecker 2003 ;  Potuschak  et al.  2003 ;  Binder  et al.  2007 ). Loss-of-function  ebf1 ebf2  double mutants had high levels of EIN3 protein and consequently exhibited a constitutive ethylene response ( Chao  et al.  1997 ;  Potuschak  et al.  2003 ). While EBF1 and EBF2 in  Arabidopsis  are constitutively expressed over plant development, they both show an increase in expression with exogenously added ethylene, and over-expression of  EBF1  resulted in reduced EIN3 levels leading to an ethylene-insensitive phenotype. These results suggest that the  EBF -like genes are controlled, at least in part, at the transcription level ( Potuschak  et al.  2003 ).  In tomato, two  EBF -like genes have also been identified:  EBF1  and  EBF2  ( Yang  et al.  2010 ). Consistent with the results in  Arabidopsis , silencing of either gene resulted in plants that were indistinguishable from controls, indicating that they are functionally redundant. The results suggested a feedback mechanism whereby suppression of one  EBF  gene resulted in an increase in transcription of the second. As in  Arabidopsis , a constitutive ethylene response phenotype was observed when both  EBF1  and  EBF2  were silenced in tomato, including accelerated fruit ripening ( Yang  et al.  2010 ). However, unlike  Arabidopsis , the expression of tomato  EBF1  and  EBF2  was not constitutive, with a transient decrease in expression at the onset of ripening (mature green), and consistent with  Arabidopsis  both showed an increase of expression with ethylene and a decrease with auxin ( Yang  et al.  2010 ). Tomato  EBF1  appeared to be less affected at the transcriptional level, while  EBF2  appeared to be more transcriptionally variable ( Yang  et al.  2010 ).  In the fleshy fruiting apple, ethylene plays a key role in the control of fruit ripening. The importance of ethylene in apple fruit ripening was confirmed with the suppression of the ripening-associated ethylene biosynthesis gene  ACC OXIDASE 1  ( ACO1 ). In these apples, no ripening-associated flesh softening or aroma volatiles are produced ( Schaffer  et al.  2007 ;  Johnston  et al.  2009 ). Owing to consumer requirements to maintain a firm texture, many commercial apples have been selected for low ripening-related ethylene. This has been achieved in part through the selection of lines with disrupted ethylene biosynthetic gene  ACC SYNTHASE  ( ACS ), leading to longer storage capacity and slower softening ( Harada  et al.  1997 ;  Costa  et al.  2005 ;  Wiersma  et al.  2007 ;  Wang  et al.  2009 ). Owing to the importance of ethylene in fruit ripening, much of the molecular biology research conducted in apple has been focused on ethylene biosynthesis and response. One of the earliest genes cloned from apple was the  ETHYLENE RESPONSE 1  ( ETR1 )-like receptor ( Lee  et al.  1998 ), along with the ethylene biosynthetic gene  ACO1  ( Lay-Yee and Knighton 1995 ). Subsequent work identified four other receptor-like genes, a  CTR1 -like gene, an  EIN2- like gene ( Wiersma  et al.  2007 ) and three  EIN3 -like genes ( Tacken  et al.  2010 ). With the release of the complete apple genome sequence ( Velasco  et al.  2010 ), there is now a growing literature studying whole gene families ( Devoghalaere  et al.  2012 ), which has led to the identification of three further receptor genes in apple ( Ireland  et al.  2012 ).  While five  EIN3 -like genes have been identified in  Arabidopsis , ethylene signal transduction occurs predominantly through the action of two of them, EIN3 and EIL1. Originally identified through an ethylene-insensitive phenotype, it was proposed that EIN3 acted by binding and activating the promoters of the AP2/ERF class of transcription factors ( Solano  et al.  1998 ). Since this study, it has been shown that EIN3-like transcription factors are likely to be involved directly in the activation of a suite of ethylene biosynthesis and response genes ( Huang  et al.  2010 ;  Tacken  et al.  2010 ;  Yin  et al.  2010 ), and transient assays suggest that EIL2 and EIL3 in apple may be involved in the up-regulation of key apple ripening genes such as the cell wall hydrolase  endo-POLYGALACTURONASE 1  ( PG1 ) ( Tacken  et al.  2010 ).  Owing to the importance of the  EBF  class of genes as key controllers of the ethylene signal transduction pathway, this study used the apple genome sequence to identify  EBF -like genes. One  EBF -like gene ( EBF1 ) was cloned and tested for the ability to inhibit the activity of three EILs in a  Nicotiana benthamiana  transient assay.  Apple EBF-like genes.  Gene expression levels from a fruit development cDNA series ( Janssen  et al.  2008 ) were determined via quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) using the Lightcycler480™ (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). Primers for  PG1 ,  ACO1  and  EIL1-3  are as described in  Tacken  et al . (2010) , and for  ACTIN  as described in  Espley  et al . (2007) . Primers to measure the expression of each of the  EBF  genes were as follows: EBF1F, TCGCAAGAGGTCTCGCATCAGC; EBF1R, CCTCGCCTCCAGGAATCCGT; EBF101F, TTCCTGCTTGGGATTGAAAGATG; EBF101R, GCTCCAGTTGAGGGCAAAGC; EBF2F, AGGTTGTGCCCTCAGCTACATAATA; EBF2R, ACCAACGACACAACTGCTTTATCC; EBF102F, GCCCTCAGCTCCATAATGTAGACA; EBF102R, CCAACGCCATAACGACTTCATCT.  All reactions were carried out in quadruplicate using SYBR ®  Green Master Mix (Roche) according to the manufacturer's instructions with  ACTIN  used as the reference gene, and the qPCR products sequenced to verify the amplification of the correct gene.  Tobacco plants were grown in the greenhouse for 2 weeks under long-day conditions until at least two leaves had developed a surface area of at least 1.5 cm 2 .  Agrobacterium tumefaciens  GV3101 transformed with promoter fragments in the pGreenII 0800:Luc vector and the pSOUP helper plasmid ( Hellens  et al.  2000 ) and  Agrobacterium  containing the candidate  EIL s or  EBF1  fused to the  CaMV35S  promoter in the pART7/27 transformation vector were suspended in 8 mL of infiltration buffer ( Hellens  et al . 2005 ) to obtain an optical density at 600 nm of 0.6  Agrobacterium . The leaves of young  N.  benthamiana  plants were infiltrated with two aliquots of 500 μL of combined  PG1  promoter/ EIL / EBF1  at a ratio of 1 : 3.5 : 3.5. In the controls,  Agrobacterium  containing either the  EIN3 -like genes or  EBF1  was substituted for  Agrobacterium  containing an empty  CaMV35S  promoter construct ( Voinnet  et al.  2003 ;  Hellens  et al.  2005 ). Plants were grown for 3 days and then four independent leaf punches were assayed using a Berthold Orion Microplate Luminometer (Berthold, Bad Wilbad, Germany) according to the specifications for the dual luciferase assay ( Hellens  et al.  2005 ). Luminescence was calculated using Simplicity software, version 4.02 (Berthold). To minimize the effect of background activation levels, only readings with a Renilla value of &gt;1000 were included in the analysis. These infiltrations were repeated three times and the averages of these experiments are given. Significant differences were calculated using analysis of variance.   Alignment of the EBF1 protein sequences.  The four predicted apple EBF proteins were aligned. The conserved F-box domain (red) and the 13 leucine-rich repeats (LRR—green) are shown underneath.   Phylogenetic alignment of members of the EIN3 BINDING F-box (EBF) family proteins from different plant species.  A phylogenetic tree was generated using PHYML; values given are bootstrap percentages (1000 replicates). EBF-like proteins from apple ( Malus domestica— Md), strawberry ( Fragaria vesca— Fv), poplar ( Populus trichocarpa— Pt), tomato ( Solanum lycopersicum— Sl),  Brassica oleracea  (Bo), rice ( Oryza sativa— Os) and  Arabidopsis thaliana  (At) were compared with AtFBL4 and AtTIR used as outgroups.   Expression patterns of  EBF -like genes over apple fruit development, compared with other ethylene-related and ripening genes.  Expression of  EBF1 ,  EBF2 ,  EBF3  and  EBF4  was measured in cDNA derived from fruit tissue over the course of apple fruit development by qPCR. Expression levels are shown relative to the  ACTIN  gene. Expression levels of  ACO1 ,  PG1  and  EIL1 -3 are reported in  Tacken  et al . (2010) .   The transactivation of the apple PG1 promoter by EIL1 to EIL3 with and without EBF1.  A dual luciferase transient assay system was used to examine the activity of EBF1 on the transactivation of the  PG1  promoter by EIL1, EIL2 and EIL3 with and without exogenous ethylene (100 μL L -1 ). Transactivation was measured as a ratio of luminescence from the luciferase activity compared with an infiltration control measured by Renilla activity. Controls are the  PG1  promoter and an empty vector control; error bars represent the S.E.M. ( n  = 4). Letters depict bars that are significantly different with a  P  value &lt;0.05, and an asterisk indicates significant levels of inactivation ( P  &lt; 0.05).  A rapidly growing number of plant genomes have now been sequenced, giving researchers a valuable insight into these organisms beyond the traditional model species. While these genomes allow researchers to look at features that are unique to different and often commercially important plant species, it is important to translate knowledge gained from model systems to these species of interest. In this study, we build on the growing literature of ethylene-related genes in apple ( Lee  et al.  1998 ;  Wiersma  et al.  2007 ;  Tacken  et al.  2010 ;  Ireland  et al.  2012 ) by the characterization of the  EBF -like genes. Interestingly, in apple there are four  EBF -like genes, consistent with the genome duplication, while the closely related Rosaceae species strawberry has two. In the model species tomato and  Arabidopsis , the  EBF  family is encoded redundantly by at least two genes. In  Arabidopsis  the two  EBF  genes fall into sub-clade I, while tomato has one gene in each sub-clade (Fig.  2 ).  In  Arabidopsis, EBF1  and  EBF2  mRNA is constitutively expressed ( Guo and Ecker 2003 ;  Potuschak  et al.  2003 ) and has been shown to be targeted for degradation by EIN5 ( Olmedo  et al.  2006 ), suggesting that mRNA levels are actively regulated. In tomato,  EBF1  is constitutively expressed with  EBF2  showing considerable changes in expression over development and in different treatments ( Yang  et al.  2010 ). From this observation it was suggested that as  EBF1  had a more consistent level of expression, it was providing the steady-state level of EBF, and fluctuations of  EBF2  allowed the plant to respond to the environment. In apples, the two classes of  EBF -like genes appear to follow the same pattern with sub-clade I genes ( EBF1  and  EBF101 ) showing little variation in expression, while the sub-clade II genes ( EBF2  and  EBF102 ) both increase as the fruit begin to ripen. Although the sub-clade I tomato gene  EBF1  had a more consistent level of expression, it did have lower expression in mature green fruit. This was not observed in the expression pattern of  EBF1  in apples, though as this drop was transitory in tomato, there is a possibility that a similar drop in apple would be missed in a less detailed time series experiment (Fig.  3 ).  In this study, three apple EIN3-like genes were tested in a transient assay for activity against the  PG1  promoter. All three apple EILs had reduced activity against the  PG1  promoter, in the presence of EBF1, showing that the apple EBF1 was not specific to a single EIL. The non-specific nature of the EBFs is consistent with the  Arabidopsis  EBF1 and EBF2, where both interact with EIN3 and EIL1, again suggesting a lack of specificity in these F-box proteins to individual EIL proteins.  An F-box gene  EBF1  was identified in apple, the predicted protein product of which clustered with EBF-like protein s  involved in the ethylene response in other plant species.  EBF1  negatively regulated activation of  PG1  by the apple  EILs , consistent with the degradation of EIN3 by EBF1 and EBF2 observed in  Arabidopsis  and tomato. These results also suggest that apple EBF1 acts as a functional EBF upon multiple members of the EIL family of transcription factors. This work suggests that the  EBF -like genes in apple are likely to play a crucial role in the control of ethylene-related fruit ripening.   The following additional information is available in the online version of this article   –Text files of apple  EBF  DNA sequences and predicted proteins.   Apple EBF1 GenBank accession no. JX512439.  This work was funded by  The Agriculture and Marketing Research and Development Trust of New Zealand (AgMardt) ,  The University of Auckland, New Zealand  and the  Foundation of Science and Research Technology (FRST)  contract  C06X0705 ; Pipfruit, a juicy future.  The project was conceived, executed and the first draft written by E.J.T. Sequencing, cloning and expression analysis were undertaken by E.J.T. H.S.I. and Y.-Y.W. This work was part of E.J.T.'s PhD project funded by AgMardt PhD scholarship (NZ), supervised by and edited by R.J.S. and J.P.  We thank Dr Jason Johnston for his advisory role in this work.  None declared.  The complete references with the full list of authors for Shulaev  et al.  (2011) and Velasco  et al.  (2010) are as follows:   Shulaev V, Sargent DJ, Crowhurst RN, Mockler TC, Folkerts O, Delcher AL, Jaiswal P, Mockaitis K, Liston A, Mane SP, Burns P, Davis TM, Slovin JP, Bassil N, Hellens RP, Evans C, Harkins T, Kodira C, Desany B, Crasta OR, Jensen RV, Allan AC, Michael TP, Setubal JC, Celton JM, Rees DJ, Williams KP, Holt SH, Ruiz Rojas JJ, Chatterjee M, Liu B, Silva H, Meisel L, Adato A, Filichkin SA, Troggio M, Viola R, Ashman TL, Wang H, Dharmawardhana P, Elser J, Raja R, Priest HD, Bryant DW, Jr, Fox SE, Givan SA, Wilhelm LJ, Naithani S, Christoffels A, Salama DY, Carter J, Lopez Girona E, Zdepski A, Wang W, Kerstetter RA, Schwab W, Korban SS, Davik J, Monfort A, Denoyes-Rothan B, Arus P, Mittler R, Flinn B, Aharoni A, Bennetzen JL, Salzberg SL, Dickerman AW, Velasco R, Borodovsky M, Veilleux RE, Folta KM. 2011.  The genome of woodland strawberry ( Fragaria vesca ).  Nature Genetics   43 : 109–116.   Velasco R, Zharkikh A, Affourtit J, Dhingra A, Cestaro A, Kalyanaraman A, Fontana P, Bhatnagar SK, Troggio M, Pruss D, Salvi S, Pindo M, Baldi P, Castelletti S, Cavaiuolo M, Coppola G, Costa F, Cova V, Dal Ri A, Goremykin V, Komjanc M, Longhi S, Magnago P, Malacarne G, Malnoy M, Micheletti D, Moretto M, Perazzolli M, Si-Ammour A, Vezzulli S, Zini E, Eldredge G, Fitzgerald LM, Gutin N, Lanchbury J, Macalma T, Mitchell JT, Reid J, Wardell B, Kodira C, Chen Z, Desany B, Niazi F, Palmer M, Koepke T, Jiwan D, Schaeffer S, Krishnan V, Wu C, Chu VT, King ST, Vick J, Tao Q, Mraz A, Stormo A, Stormo K, Bogden R, Ederle D, Stella A, Vecchietti A, Kater MM, Masiero S, Lasserre P, Lespinasse Y, Allan AC, Bus V, Chagne D, Crowhurst RN, Gleave AP, Lavezzo E, Fawcett JA, Proost S, Rouze P, Sterck L, Toppo S, Lazzari B, Hellens RP, Durel C-E, Gutin A, Bumgarner RE, Gardiner SE, Skolnick M, Egholm M, Van de Peer Y, Salamini F, Viola R. 2010.  The genome of the domesticated apple ( Malus x domestica  Borkh.).  Nature Genetics   42 : 833–839. 