 Population genetics of purple saxifrage ( Saxifraga oppositifolia ) in the high Arctic archipelago of Svalbard  Evolution in the Arctic: a phylogeographic analysis of the circumarctic plant,  Saxifraga oppositifolia  (purple saxifrage)  Molecular diversity and derivations of populations of  Silene acaulis  and  Saxifraga oppositifolia  from the high Arctic and more southerly latitudes  Growth forms and sepal hairs of the purple saxifrage ( Saxifraga oppositifolia : Saxifragaceae) in North America related to chromosome records and DNA information  Frequent long-distance plant colonization in the changing Arctic  The purple saxifrage,  Saxifraga oppositifolia , in Svalbard: two taxa or one?  TCS: a computer program to estimate gene genealogies  Floral herbivory of  Dryas octopetala  by Svalbard reindeer  Aerial dispersal of invertebrates over a high-Arctic glacier foreland: Midtre Lovénbreen, Svalbard  Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study  Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows  Glacial survival does not matter: RAPD phylogeography of Nordic  Saxifraga oppositifolia   Haplotype richness in refugial areas: phylogeographical structure of  Saxifraga callosa   Promiscuity in populations of the cushion plant  Saxifraga oppositifolia  in the Swiss Alps as inferred from random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD)  Winter habitat-space use in a large arctic herbivore facing contrasting forage abundance  Phylogeography of the Arctic–Alpine  Saxifraga oppositifolia  (Saxifragaceae) and some related taxa based on cpDNA and ITS sequence variation  Genetic enrichment of the Arctic clonal plant  Saxifraga cernua  at its southern periphery via the alpine sexual  Saxifraga sibirica   Coldest places on earth with angiosperm plant life  Causes of the genetic architecture of south-west European high mountain disjuncts  Ecological significance of different growth forms of purple saxifrage,  Saxifraga oppositifolia  L., in the high Arctic, Ny-Ålesund, Svalbard  Frequency of local, regional, and long-distance dispersal of diploid and tetraploid  Saxifraga oppositifolia  (Saxifragaceae) to Arctic glacier forelands  Development of microsatellite markers for the Arctic  Saxifraga oppositifolia  (L.) (Saxifragaceae) using inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) primers  Inference of populations structure using multilocus genotype data  Recent air-temperature changes in the Arctic  Glacial history of  Saxifraga paniculata  (Saxifragaceae): molecular biogeography of a disjunct Arctic–Alpine species from Europe and North America  Reindeer grazing on Nordaustlandet, Svalbard  MLGsim: a program for detecting clones using a simulation approach  Bumblebees at an alpine site in northern Sweden: temporal development, population size, and plant utilization  Reproductive ecology of  Saxifraga oppositifolia : phenology, mating system and reproductive success  A cladistics analysis of phenotypic associations with haplotypes inferred from restriction endonuclease mapping and DNA sequence data. III Cladogram estimation  CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice  Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics  Tales of the unexpected: phylogeography of the Arctic–Alpine model plant  Saxifraga oppositifolia  (Saxifragaceae) revisited  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Using DNA markers and sequencing we investigated patterns of genetic variability in purple saxifrage,  Saxifraga oppositifolia  in the isolated Arctic Svalbard archipelago. Purple saxifrage is a circumpolar, ecologically and morphologically variable species with a wide range of habitats. Population genetic structures showed that both genetic variation and differentiation levels are modest, outcrossing is the main mating system, and dispersal and gene flow are important, likely accountable to strong winds and human and animal vectors. Different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate) did not possess distinct genetic composition.  We investigated patterns of genetic variability in  Saxifraga oppositifolia  in the isolated Arctic Svalbard archipelago. The genetic analysis included genotyping using nine polymorphic microsatellite markers and sequencing of the nuclear internal transcribed spacer region. Among populations, mean allele numbers per microsatellite locus ranged from 2.0 to 2.6, and 9 % of alleles were unique. Observed ( H  O ) and expected ( H  E ) heterozygosities averaged 0.522 and 0.445, respectively. Typically negative but non-significant  F  IS  values (mean −0.173) were found in  S. oppositifolia  populations.  F  ST  values were relatively low (mean 0.123). The Bayesian structure analysis provided additional information on population genetic structures. Seven out of 11 studied populations, including populations located both near each other and far apart (distances 5–210 km), showed relatively homogeneous clustering patterns, while one population located on a slope in the main settlement of Longyearbyen possessed a unique genetic structure. The Mantel test proved that there is no significant correlation between genetic and geographical distances. Different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate) did not possess distinct genetic compositions based on microsatellite variation. Internal transcribed spacer sequencing revealed 12 polymorphic sites. Among 24 sequenced Svalbard samples, eight haplotypes were detected, none shared by the mainland samples. Population genetic structures of  S. oppositifolia  in Svalbard show that both genetic variation and differentiation levels are modest, outcrossing is the main mating system, and dispersal and gene flow are important, probably attributable to strong winds and human and animal vectors.  In natural environments, organisms are typically exposed to several stress factors simultaneously, and the stresses are often most pronounced in extreme habitats, such as those at high latitudes and altitudes. For instance, Arctic plants may encounter many unique environmental factors, such as drought, permafrost, nutrient leaching, cryoturbation, extreme temperatures and short growing seasons ( Körner 2003 ). The extent to which an organism is able to deal with stress determines the limits of its ecological amplitude. It is well established that biological systems are dynamic: genetic variation enables adaptation through selection, while in small and isolated populations random evolutionary processes, such as genetic drift, may become strong. The consequences of evolutionary actions will be visible in the pattern of genetic diversity and differentiation of populations.  Purple saxifrage , Saxifraga oppositifolia,  is an Arctic–Alpine early flowering perennial herb. It is a circumpolar, ecologically and morphologically variable species with a wide range of habitats. It probably has the widest global distribution in the family Saxifragaceae ( Webb and Gornall 1989 ).  Saxifraga oppositifolia  grows in dry to moist soil and from sea level up to 4500 m in the Alps, including the coldest known places with angiosperm plant life ( Körner 2011 ). It is also mentioned as the northernmost vascular plant species, having been found up in northern Greenland at 83°15′ ( Gjaervoll and Rönning 1999 ).  Saxifraga oppositifolia  is not endangered at the moment, but climate change, the potential warming or drying of northern areas, and increased UV radiation could become a threat in the future ( Körner 2003 ). It is self-compatible but mainly outcrossing and depends on its pollinators, which are mainly bumblebees ( Bombus  sp.) ( Stenström and Molau 1992 ;  Stenström and Bergman 1998 ). However, there are no bumblebees in some Arctic regions, such as Svalbard, where the pollinating insects are probably mainly small insects of the order Diptera ( Coulson  et al.  2003 ).  Previous population genetic and phylogeographic analyses on  S. oppositifolia  include random amplification of polymorphic DNA studies by  Gabrielsen  et al.  (1997)  and  Gugerli  et al.  (1999) , amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) studies by  Alsos  et al.  (2007) ,  Kropf  et al.  (2008) ,  Müller  et al.  (2012)  and  Winkler  et al . (2012) , restriction fragment length polymorphism investigations ( Abbott  et al.  1995 ;  Abbott and Comes 2004 ) and studies based on cpDNA and nuclear internal transcribed spacer (ITS) sequences ( Holderegger and Abbott 2003 ;  Winkler  et al.  2012 ). All these DNA studies have used universal binary markers or sequence data. On the other hand, our study utilizes microsatellite markers that we recently developed for  S. oppositifolia  ( Pietiläinen and Korpelainen 2010 ), which, besides allowing precise genetic analyses, make it possible to draw conclusions on the effects of mating systems on population genetic structures.  In this study we aimed to reveal patterns of genetic variability in  S. oppositifolia  in the isolated Arctic Svalbard archipelago. We hypothesized that (i) populations possess low levels of genetic variation and are genetically differentiated due to the colonization history and small population sizes and consequent effects of genetic drift, (ii) inbreeding and heterozygote deficiency are negligible due to supposedly prevalent outcrossing, and (iii) founder dynamics combined with gene flow from various sources has generated an admixed genetic structure in populations exposed to considerable human interference when compared with pristine populations. Since  S. oppositifolia  is morphologically variable and presents different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate;  Aiken  et al.  2005 ), even within populations, we also investigated whether such morphological features have any relationship with the pattern of genetic variability. In addition, we compared nuclear ITS sequence variation of plants from Svalbard and more southern mainland regions of distribution in order to reveal relationships among plants across a wider geographic area.  Sampling sites, coordinates and numbers of samples collected from each  S. oppositifolia  population in Svalbard, studied using microsatellite markers (MS) and ITS sequencing (ITS).  The study area of  S. oppositifolia  in Svalbard. Sampling details are given in  Table 1 .  We determined the population genetic characteristics of the populations using the following nine polymorphic microsatellite markers developed for  S. oppositifolia  ( Pietiläinen and Korpelainen 2010 ): SaxJC, SaxS1C, SaxS2C, SaxT9C, SaxT10C, S1_2, S4_2, S8_2 and S21_2. In genotyping, one of the primers in each primer pair was fluorescently (FAM, HEX or TET) labelled. Amplifications were performed in 5-µL reactions, containing 0.5 µL of DNA (about 5 ng), 2.75 µL of ddH 2 O, 0.5 µL of 10× buffer, 0.1 µL of dNTP mix (10 mM), 0.15 µL of DyNAzyme II DNA polymerase (Finnzymes) (2 U µL −1 ) and 0.5 µl of both primers (5 pmol µL −1 ). The polymerase chain reactions (PCR) were carried out as follows: DNA denaturation at 94 °C for 4 min followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 94 °C for 45 s, annealing at 46–60 °C (depending on the primer pair) for 45 s, and elongation at 72 °C for 1 min, with a final elongation at 72 °C for 10 min. For genotyping, PCR products were first diluted with ddH 2 O. Following this, 2 µL of each sample were pipetted into a 96-well plate, and 8 µL of standard (MegaBACE ET400-R, GE Healthcare) diluted with ddH 2 O (1/45) were added. The plates were then run with the MegaBACE 1000 DNA Analysis System (Amersham Biosciences). Genotyping results were then analysed with the MegaBACE Fragment Profiler 1.2 (Amersham Biosciences).  To complement microsatellite analyses, we sequenced 24 samples from Svalbard (Table  1 ) and five samples from mainland Norway for the nuclear ITS region using primers ITS1 (5′-TCC GTA GGT GAA CCT GCG G-3′) and ITS4 (5′-TCC TCC GCT TAT TGA TAT GC-3′) ( White  et al . 1990 ). Sample sizes of populations LYR and KIN were larger (5) because LYR was of special interest due to the expected great anthropogenic influence, while KIN was an opposite example. The amplified region covered the whole distance from the end of the 18S rRNA gene to the beginning of the 26S rRNA gene. Polymerase chain reaction amplifications were performed in a total volume of 20 μL containing 2 μL of DNA (about 20 ng), 13 μL of ddH 2 O, 2 μL of 10× buffer, 0.4 μL of dNTP mix (10 mM), 0.6 μL of Dynazyme II DNA polymerase (2 U μL −1 ) and 1 μL of both primers (5 pmol μL −1 ). The PCR cycle was similar to that in microsatellite genotyping, but the annealing temperature was 50 °C. Amplification products were run on a 1 % agarose gel, and the DNA fragments were excised and purified prior to sequencing using the E.Z.N.A. Gel Extraction Kit (Omega Bio-Tek). Purified DNA samples were sequenced at Macrogen Inc. using PCR primers. Internal transcribed spacer sequences were aligned with CLUSTAL W ( Thompson  et al.  1994 ), and any variable sites were recorded.  Based on microsatellite data, we calculated mean numbers of alleles per locus, mean observed and expected heterozygosities ( H  O  and  H  E ),  F -statistics estimators  F  ST  and inbreeding coefficients  F  IS , and conducted Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) testing for all loci with χ 2  tests, and performed a Mantel test to discover possible relationships between genetic and geographical distances, all using Arlequin v3.5.1.2 ( Excoffier and Lischer 2010 ). The Bonferroni correction was applied for the tests. In addition, we performed a Bayesian analysis of population structure using the software Structure 2.3 ( Pritchard  et al.  2000 ) to determine the number and the distribution of genetic clusters among all samples. The correlated allele frequency model was used, which assumes that at each locus allele frequencies are correlated. With this assumption, the model infers a population structure with  K  number of clusters based on the genotype data. An admixture model was applied. At each stage, the analysis was repeated with different values of  K  (range 1–15) to discover the value with the highest estimate of log-likelihood probability (ln Pr( X | K )) of the data. For each value of  K , 10 independent runs were conducted with a burn-in length of 100 000 iterations, followed by a data collection period of 10 6  iterations. Furthermore, to identify the correct number of clusters ( K ) that best explains the data, Δ K  values were calculated according to  Evanno  et al.  (2005) .  Since vegetative propagation is a potential mode of reproduction in  S. oppositifolia , we used the Excel Microsatellite Toolkit ( http://www.animalgenomics.ucd.ie/sdepark/ms-toolkit/ ) in each population to distinguish plants with a common clonal ancestry from plants sharing the same microsatellite-based multilocus genotype (MLG) by chance. When MLGs were found more than once in a population, the software MLGsim ( Stenberg  et al.  2003 ) was used to calculate the  P  SEX  values (probability that two individuals would share the same MLG by chance) and to simulate the corresponding critical values for the significance level  P  &lt; 0.05. To obtain the critical values for the test statistic,  P  SEX , the number of simulations was increased until stable critical values were reached.  We constructed haplotype networks for the ITS sequence data, including all our own data and comparable sequences of the same species available in GenBank, using the network building software TCS 1.2.1 ( Clement  et al.  2000 ), which uses statistical parsimony (95 %) and the genealogical reconstruction algorithms of  Templeton  et al.  (1992) . Indels were treated as a fifth state and coded as a single mutational event.  Identical MLGs were found in all populations, except in BIS and FLO. The total percentage of MLGs was 21 % of all genotyped individuals. In most cases the number of plants sharing the same MLG was two. However, according to the simulated critical values of  P  SEX , obtained using the program MLGsim for each population with MLGs, none of the MLGs were likely to represent clones ( P  &gt; 0.05). Therefore, no further adjustments due to MLGs were made for the data set.  Within-population genetic diversity in  S. oppositifolia  populations in Svalbard based on nine microsatellite markers.  A , mean number of alleles per locus;  H  O , observed heterozygosity over loci;  H  E , expected heterozygosity over loci;  F  IS , fixation index over loci.  Assignment of individual samples of  S. oppositifolia  to five different gene pools as inferred by Bayesian clustering analysis. Results shown (A) for all 11 populations and (B) separately for plants with compact (C), intermediate (I) or trailing (T) growth habit. Population details are given in  Table 1  and Fig.  1 . The question mark (?) means that growth habit was not recorded.  Haplotype network showing the relationships among 24 ITS sequences from Svalbard (Sv), five ITS sequences from mainland Norway (No) produced in this study and a total of 11 ITS sequences from mainland Norway (No), Austria (Au), Italy (It), Spain (Sp) and the USA (US) available in GenBank. The sizes of the circles and squares are proportional to the numbers of sequences with the same haplotype. Small squares on connecting spans indicate minimum numbers of individual mutations.  Genetic characteristics of species impact their capacity to maintain their populations and colonize new areas. The presence of genetic diversity is especially important for plant populations in highly stochastic environments like the Arctic. The Arctic climate has been warming and the surface air temperature has increased, especially in the Atlantic region around the Svalbard archipelago ( Przybylak 2007 ). More new areas for colonization are made bare by the retreating glaciers, and early successional species like  S. oppositifolia  may benefit from this.  Müller  et al.  (2012)  have actually shown that  S. oppositifolia  is a plant that can rapidly colonize new deglaciated areas without losing genetic diversity. In addition,  Alsos  et al.  (2007)  have suggested that past recurrent glacial cycles during the geological history have probably selected for a highly mobile Arctic flora in places like the Svalbard archipelago. The high levels of genetic diversity found in several species previously studied in Svalbard are consistent with the view that multiple long-distance dispersals have occurred ( Alsos  et al.  2007 ).  In the present study, although 21 % of the genotyped samples possessed MLGs that were identical to another MLG in the same population, none of the MLGs were likely to represent clones ( P  &gt; 0.05) based on the testing of the  P  SEX  values obtained. However, potential smaller clones were excluded on the grounds of the random sampling strategy. Among populations, mean allele numbers per locus ranged from 2.0 to 2.6, and only 3 out of 32 alleles (9 %) were unique. Observed ( H  O ) and expected ( H  E ) heterozygosities averaged 0.522 and 0.445, respectively. The expected heterozygosities and allele numbers indicate a modest and relatively even level of genetic variation. In a previous AFLP-based study on  S. oppositifolia  in the Alps and Pyrenees and Sierra Nevada,  Kropf  et al.  (2008)  discovered  H  E  values varying regionally between 0.110 and 0.163, but such low values may be attributable to the different types of markers used. Also based on AFLP markers,  Müller  et al.  (2012)  found genetic diversity values varying between 0.19 and 0.29 in glacier foreland populations in Svalbard. However, variability comparisons on  S. oppositifolia  between the present and previous studies are difficult, as the present study is the only one utilizing microsatellites.  Typically negative but non-significant  F  IS  values (mean −0.173) found in  S. oppositifolia  populations indicate that outcrossing is the main mating system despite the species being self-compatible and dependent on its pollinators. At individual loci, significant heterozygote deficiencies were rare (5 %) but excesses were more common (23 %). The typical pollinators of  Saxifraga , bumblebees ( Bombus  sp.), do not occur in Svalbard, where it needs to rely on other available pollinators, such as insects of the order Diptera ( Coulson  et al.  2003 ). Previously, besides the absence of bumblebees, geographic isolation by mountains and fjords as well as strong winds have also been hypothesized to lead to reduced cross-pollination ( Stenström and Bergman 1998 ). However, the population genetic structures we detected do not indicate that crosspollination would be rare.  Relatively low  F  ST  values (mean 0.123) indicated a fair level of gene flow between populations occurring in different parts of Svalbard. Relatively low levels of differentiation have also been found in  S. oppositifolia  by  Kropf  et al.  (2008) , who in an AFLP-based study reported Nei's genetic distances of 0.022–0.030 between regions in mountain areas in Central and Southern Europe. Previous genetic work on other  Saxifraga  species utilizing AFLP markers has revealed high levels of differentiation.  Saxifraga callosa  was studied in the Alps and showed extensive differentiation ( G  ST  = 0.899) ( Grassi  et al.  2009 ), which indicated limited gene flow among refugial areas.  Saxifraga cernua  and  S. sibirica  were investigated with AFLP markers in the Ural Mountains and were found to possess considerable levels of differentiation,  F  ST  values equalling 0.452 and 0.362, respectively ( Kapralov  et al.  2006 ).  Besides  F  ST -based differentiation measurements, the Bayesian structure analysis provided additional information on the population genetic structures. Seven out of 11 studied  S. oppositifolia  populations (FOR, ENG, ED, NYB, END, KIN and FLO), including populations located both near each other and far apart (distance variation 5–210 km), showed relatively homogeneous clustering patterns. Another set of three populations (BIS, BOH and BRE, pairwise geographic distances 52–206 km) resembled each other, while population LYR, located on a slope next to a new housing area and building sites in the main settlement of Longyearbyen, possessed a unique genetic structure. It is likely that the human-mediated colonization history and dispersal have been extensive, and that is reflected in the present genetic composition of  S. oppositifolia  in Longyearbyen. As expected from the Bayesian structure results, the Mantel test results proved that there is no significant correlation between genetic and geographical distances.  Different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate) of  S. oppositifolia  did not possess distinct genetic compositions based on microsatellite variation. For instance, population BOH containing mainly compact individuals and population BRE containing only trailing plants were genetically quite similar ( F  ST  = 0.070). Yet, earlier research on growth and reproduction patterns in  S. oppositifolia  has indicated that morphological variability is adaptive ( Brysting  et al.  1996 ;  Kume  et al.  1999 ). As the present work is based on the use of putatively neutral microsatellite markers, genetic differentiation at adaptive loci remains unobserved if not linked with the studied loci.  Sequencing of the nuclear ITS region revealed 12 polymorphic sites. Among 24 sequenced Svalbard samples, a total of eight haplotypes were detected, none shared by the mainland samples. One major Svalbard haplotype (46 % of samples) was found in seven populations (BIS, FOR, BOH, LYR, BRE, KIN and FLO), which are located at distances 9–198 km from each other. Among the five samples sequenced for LYR, four haplotypes were found, two of which were unique among the study material. Based on the network analysis conducted, one of the unique ITS sequences of LYR appeared to descend from a haplotype discovered among samples from mainland Norway. These observations also support the view of the distinct colonization history of the LYR population. Among the nine mainland haplotypes, the Norwegian ones were related to each other or Svalbard haplotypes, except for a sample from Hordaland in southern Norway, which was identical to a haplotype also found in mountainous areas of Italy and Spain. Otherwise, the haplotypes from Austria, Italy and Spain were relatively closely related, while the haplotype revealed for the two samples from the USA was distinct. An increased sample size in mainland Europe, especially in Norway, could have provided a more precise insight into the relationship between Svalbard and other populations. Recently  Winkler  et al . (2012)  discovered in their plastid sequence study that the haplotype of the single Svalbard sample of  S. oppositifolia  was also found in mainland Norway, Greenland, Slovakia and Switzerland.  In a related species,  Saxifraga paniculata ,  Reisch (2008)  discovered that Arctic populations contained less AFLP variation and fewer chloroplast haplotypes than populations from other regions of the distribution. The present study on  S. oppositifolia  indicates a fair level of haplotype diversity in the Arctic Svalbard populations. The ITS region as such is not supposed to be especially useful when studying larger-scale phylogeography of  S. oppositifolia  because of its largely unresolved topology with low statistical support ( Holderegger and Abbott 2003 ). Yet, the moderate variability of the ITS region detected in our study, eight haplotypes just within Svalbard and nine additional haplotypes among the small set of samples from mainland Europe, provides interesting implications for phylogeographic studies on different geographic scales. For comparison,  Winkler  et al . (2012)  discovered 27 haplotypes in a global study on 114  S. oppositifolia  individuals based on plastid sequence data (psbA–trnH and trnTF intragenic spacers).  Strong winds in the open landscape, sea currents, drift ice and dispersal by vectors, such as humans and birds, may explain the present phylogeographic and population genetic patterns of  S. oppositifolia . Small seeds are dispersed by the winds across the glaciers and whole plants have been known to float great distances on ice ( Hultén and Fries 1986 ;  Holderegger and Abbott 2003 ). It has also been reported that local reindeer forage on  S. oppositifolia , particularly on its nutritious reproductive shoots ( Cooper and Wookey 2003 ), especially in the northern parts of the archipelago where moss and lichen are scarce ( Staaland and Punsvik 1980 ). Although Svalbard reindeer tend to remain in the local home range area, individual animals migrate regularly and plant dispersal may be more common than expected ( Hansen  et al.  2009 ). Previously,  Alsos  et al.  (2007)  proved by AFLP fingerprinting that long-distance colonization of Svalbard by  S. oppositifolia  has occurred repeatedly and from several source regions, probably by wind and drifting sea ice. Evidently, establishment limits distribution more than dispersal.  Population genetic structures detected in  S. oppositifolia  in Svalbard revealed that differentiation levels are modest, and that dispersal and gene flow are important phenomena within Svalbard, probably attributable to strong winds and human and animal vectors. The nine polymorphic microsatellite markers used and ITS sequencing are useful tools when examining population genetics and phylogeography of  S. oppositifolia  on different geographic scales.  Financial support was obtained from  Kuopion Luonnon Ystäväin Yhdistys Foundation  and  NordForsk .  M.P. collected most samples, conducted all laboratory work and part of the data analysis and manuscript preparation. H.K. collected some samples and conducted part of the data analysis and manuscript preparation.  None declared.  We thank Dr Tove Gabrielsen, who provided plant samples from mainland Norway. 