Baleen hormones: a novel tool for retrospective assessment of stress and reproduction in bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>)Use of alternative matrices to monitor steroid hormones in aquatic mammals: a reviewGlucocorticosteroid concentrations in feces and hair of captive caribou and reindeer following adrenocorticotropic hormone challengeCortisol levels in hair of East Greenland polar bearsMeasuring environmental stress in East Greenland polar bears, 1892–1927 and 1988–2009: what does hair cortisol tell us?Validation of a shed skin corticosterone enzyme immunoassay in the African House Snake (<italic>Lamprophis fuliginosus</italic>) and its evaluation in the Eastern Massasauga Rattlesnake (<italic>Sistrurus catenatus catenatus</italic>)Stable isotopes in southern right whale (<italic>Eubalaena australis</italic>) baleen as indicators of seasonal movements, feeding and growthPlasma and urine levels of electrolytes, urea and steroid hormones involved in osmoregulation of cetaceansWhales, Ice, &amp; Men: The History of Whaling in the Western ArcticCorticosterone in feathers is a long–term, integrated measure of avian stress physiologyStructure and functions of keratin proteins in simple, stratified, keratinized and cornified epitheliaWild red deer (<italic>Cervus elaphus</italic>, Linnaeus, 1758) population status assessment: novel methods using hairPractical Nonparametric StatisticsHair cortisol levels as a retrospective marker of hypothalamic–pituitary axis activity throughout pregnancy: comparison to salivary cortisolAnalysis of endogenous cortisol concentrations in the hair of rhesus macaquesThe assessment of cortisol in human hair: associations with sociodemographic variables and potential confoundersClimate change impacts on marine ecosystemsHeritability and genetic correlation of hair cortisol in vervet monkeys in low and higher stress environmentsFeather corticosterone of a nestling seabird reveals consequences of sex-specific parental investmentNon-invasive stress and reproductive measures of social and ecological pressures in free-ranging African elephants (<italic>Loxodonta africana</italic>)Age and growth estimates of bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>) via aspartic acid racemizationA new way to estimate the age of bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>) using ovarian corpora countsAnatomy and physiologyAnalysis of fecal glucocorticoids in the north atlantic right whale (<italic>Eubalaena glacialis</italic>)Overcoming the challenges of studying conservation physiology in large whales: a review of available methodsDetermining pregnancy from blubber in three species of delphinidsVariation of bowhead whale progesterone and concentrations across demographic groups and sample matricesFeather coloration in museum specimens is related to feather corticosteroneNon-breeding feather concentrations of testosterone, corticosterone and cortisol are associated with subsequent survival in wild house sparrowsReproductionElevated corticosterone in feathers correlates with corticosterone–induced decreased feather quality: a validation studyTime course of cortisol loss in hair segments under immersion in hot waterAge estimation for young bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>) using annual baleen growth incrementsStatistical modeling of baleen and body length at age in bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>)Evaluation of hair cortisol concentration as a biomarker of long–term stress in free–ranging polar bearsA new framework for assessing the effects of anthropogenic sound on marine mammals in a rapidly changing ArcticSexual maturation in male bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>) of the Bering-Chukchi-Beaufort SeaDevelopment of the HPA axis: Where and when do sex differences manifest?Hair cortisol and the risk of acute myocardial infarction in adult menGlobal distribution and conservation of marine mammalsImplications of arctic industrial growth and strategies to mitigate future vessel and fishing gear impacts on bowhead whalesAssessing reproductive status of right whales (<italic>Eubalaena glacialis</italic>) using fecal hormone metabolitesEvidence that ship noise increases stress in right whalesCalving intervals of bowhead whales established through photographic identificationsStress-linked cortisol concentrations in hair: what we know and what we need to knowElevated hair cortisol concentrations in endurance athletesDetermination of sex hormones in rat hair after administration of testosterone propionate and estradiol valerateEffects of stress on reproduction in non-rodent mammals: the role of glucocorticoids and sex differencesBlue whale earplug reveals lifetime contaminant exposure and hormone profilesElevated content of cortisol in hair of patients with severe chronic pain: a novel biomarker for stressMeasuring cortisol and DHEA in fingernails: a pilot studyExcreted steroids in primate feces over the menstrual cycle and pregnancyAssessing individual systemic stress through cortisol analysis of archeological hairFlow-dependent porosity and other biomechanical properties of mysticete baleenHair cortisol as a potential biologic marker of chronic stress in hospitalized neonatesThe comparative anatomy of baleen: evolutionary and ecological implicationsBiostatistical Analysis<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Baleen samples from sixteen bowhead whales contained measurable cortisol and progesterone, and both hormones demonstrated significant correlations with sex, age class and reproductive state. Analysis of hormones in baleen shows promise as a novel tool for retrospective analysis of stress and reproductive physiology of large mysticete whales.Arctic marine mammals are facing increasing levels of many anthropogenic stressors. Novel tools are needed for assessment of stress physiology and potential impacts of these stressors on health, reproduction and survival. We have investigated baleen as a possible novel tissue type for retrospective assessment of stress and reproductive hormones. We found that pulverized baleen powder from bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>) contained immunoreactive cortisol and progesterone that were detectable with commercially available enzyme immunoassay kits. Both assays passed parallelism and accuracy validations using baleen extracts. We analysed cortisol and progesterone at the base of the baleen plate (most recently grown baleen) from 16 bowhead whales of both sexes. For a subset of 11 whales, we also analysed older baleen from 10, 20 and 30 cm distal to the base of the baleen plate. Immunoreactive cortisol and progesterone were detectable in all baleen samples tested. In base samples, females had significantly higher concentrations of cortisol and progesterone compared with males. Cortisol concentrations in older baleen (10, 20 and 30 cm locations) were significantly lower than at the base and did not exhibit correlations with age-class or sex. Progesterone concentrations were significantly higher in females than in males at all baleen locations tested and were significantly higher in pregnant females than in non-pregnant females. Four of five mature females showed dramatic variation in progesterone concentrations at different locations along the baleen plate that may be indicative of previous pregnancies or luteal phases. In contrast, all males and all immature females had uniformly low progesterone. Baleen hormone analysis is a novel approach that, with further methodological development, may be useful for determining individual longitudinal profiles of reproductive cycles and stress responses.Arctic marine mammals are faced with increasing exposure to a variety of ecological and anthropogenic stressors, particularly climate change and associated increases in seismic exploration, oil and gas development, ship traffic and fishing activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C16">Doney <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C39">Pompa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C40">Reeves <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C35">Moore <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The potential impacts of these rapid environmental changes on stress physiology, reproductive physiology and related population-level effects are largely unknown. Moreover, such physiological responses are particularly challenging to assess in the case of mysticete whales (baleen whales), which are difficult to study with standard physiological techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C24">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).Assessment of steroid hormones in novel tissue types offers a potential solution. Conservation physiologists are increasingly exploring different tissue types, as diverse as urine, faeces, hair, blubber, respiratory vapour and earwax, to measure steroid hormones relevant for addressing questions of stress physiology (e.g. adrenal steroids) and reproductive physiology (e.g. oestrogens, progestins, androgens; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C1">Amaral, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C24">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C26">Kellar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C48">Trumble <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). In whales, the progestin content of faeces and blubber has been used to diagnose pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C41">Rolland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C25">Kellar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C26">2013</xref>), and elevated faecal glucocorticoids have been shown to reflect exposure to various acute and chronic stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C42">Rolland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C24">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).Mysticete whales have a unique tissue type that has not previously been explored for steroid hormone analysis, i.e. baleen. Baleen is a stratified, cornified epithelial tissue consisting of long, overlapping, fringed plates that grow downward from the upper jaw (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C22">Haldiman and Tarpley, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C10">Bragulla and Homerger, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C55">Young, 2012</xref>), which collectively form the whale's filter-feeding apparatus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C22">Haldiman and Tarpley, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C53">Werth, 2013</xref>). It has recently become clear that most cornified epidermal tissues in vertebrates contain detectable steroid hormones; this has been well demonstrated in human hair and fingernails, mammalian fur, bird feathers and shed snakeskin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C9">Bortolotti <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C50">Warnock <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C2">Ashley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C13">D'Anna-Hernandez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C30">Lattin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C4">Bechshøft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C5">Berkvens, 2013</xref>). The steroid content of these cornified tissues appears to reflect circulating hormone levels accumulated during tissue growth, e.g. human hair cortisol content reflects adrenal activity of the previous few months, whereas feather corticosterone content reflects adrenal activity that occurred during feather molt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C50">Warnock <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C30">Lattin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C44">Sharpley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The glucocorticoid content of these tissues correlates significantly with exposure to known stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C54">Yamada <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C49">Van Uum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C17">Fairbanks <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C45">Skoluda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) and also with consequent physiological impacts, such as reduced growth and body condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C30">Lattin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C34">Macbeth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C27">Kennedy <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), reduced investment in offspring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C18">Fairhurst <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), increased disease susceptibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C38">Pereg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and mortality risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C28">Koren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Most research to date has focused on the adrenal glucocorticoids, but preliminary results indicate that reproductive steroids are also measurable in cornified tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C28">Koren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C46">Snoj <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C11">Caslini, 2013</xref>).Baleen steroid analysis may offer two unusual benefits as a conservation physiology tool. First, baleen grows continuously from the whale's upper palate; newer baleen is added gradually at the base, and the oldest baleen is steadily worn off at the distal end (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C6">Best and Schell, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C32">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C55">Young, 2012</xref>). In mature bowhead whales (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>), for example, ∼15–20 cm of baleen is added per year, and a single plate may be 4 m long; thus, one baleen plate from a mature bowhead may represent a continuous physiological record of approximately the past 20–25 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C33">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; N. Lysiak, personal communication). (Immature animals have shorter baleen and faster baleen growth rate, and would be expected to have maximal baleen growth records of ∼10–15 years depending on age; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C33">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; N. Lysiak, personal communication). Baleen might therefore contain information on longitudinal profiles of past reproductive cycles and physiological events that occurred during the last decade or two of the whale's life. This is of particular interest for bowhead whales, in which reproductive cycles are still poorly understood; for example, current estimates of calving intervals are based on only three observed cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C43">Rugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>). A second potential advantage of baleen is that there exist historical archives of baleen plates that date back to the era of commercial whaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C8">Bockstoce, 1986</xref>), as well as modern archives of baleen collected from whales that were stranded or taken in aboriginal subsistence whaling. Steroids in cornified tissues often remain detectable in specimens stored long term; museum specimens of hair and feathers that are decades to centuries old have been found to have detectable steroid hormones that demonstrate physiologically relevant patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C52">Webb <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C4">Bechshøft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Therefore, the possibility exists that baleen hormones could be used as a valuable tool for retrospective comparisons of steroid profiles in past vs. present-day populations, for example, comparison of inter-calving intervals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C52">Webb <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C4">Bechshøft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C27">Kennedy <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).The aim of this study was to evaluate the feasibility of baleen as a novel sample type for assessing patterns in stress-related hormones (cortisol and its metabolites) and reproductive hormones indicative of calving cycles (progesterone and its metabolites). Our specific goals were as follows: (i) to develop methodology for pulverizing baleen and extracting steroids; (ii) to determine whether immunoreactive cortisol and progesterone are detectable in baleen samples; (iii) to validate cortisol and progesterone immunoassays for baleen using standard parallelism and accuracy tests; (iv) to assess patterns of baleen cortisol and progesterone at the base of the baleen plate in relationship to current physiological status (e.g. pregnant vs. non-pregnant females); and (v) to assess hormone variation at different locations along the baleen plate, as a preliminary investigation to determine whether baleen might contain a record of past physiological events.Locations in Alaska at which baleen samples were obtained from landed bowhead whales. Ten whales were sampled at Barrow, three whales at Kaktovik, two at Savoonga and one at Gambell.Sampling of a baleen plate from a bowhead whale (<italic>Balaena mysticetus</italic>). A DeWalt 18 V cordless power drill equipped with a circular hole saw was used to excise discs of baleen from four locations: the base of the plate (bottom of photograph; most recently grown baleen) and at 10, 20 and 30 cm distances from the base (i.e. progressively older baleen).Baleen cortisol and progesterone data for 16 bowhead whalesAbbreviations: F, female; M, male. The lengths 0, 10, 20 and 0 cm are distances from the base of the baleen plate; 0 cm is the most recently grown baleen and 30 cm the oldest baleen tested.<sup>a</sup>11B3 categorized as pregnant based on presence of large corpus luteum and enlarged uterus; however, abdomen was not opened at time of harvest, abdominal organs were frozen the next day, and presence of a fetus could not be confirmed.Baleen plates were from six males and 10 females (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>). Four of the females were pregnant at the time of harvest. Sexual maturity and reproductive state were defined on the basis of body length and relevant anatomical findings at harvest (i.e. testicle size, ovarian morphology), as follows: immature males &lt;13.5 m body length; mature males &gt;13.5 m; immature females &lt;13.5 m; mature females &gt;13.5 m or large ovarian follicles present; and pregnant females were identified by presence of a fetus and/or placenta at harvest, or (if uterus not opened) large corpus luteum and enlarged uterus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C29">Koski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C20">George <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C36">O'Hara <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Final sample sizes were five immature males (the largest three of which were likely pubertal; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C36">O'Hara <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), one mature male, three immature females, three mature non-pregnant females and four pregnant females (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>).Sample preparation and extraction methods were initially tested on a single baleen plate from a North Atlantic right whale (NARW, <italic>Eubalaena glacialis</italic>). Isopropanol rinses (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C14">Davenport <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C2">Ashley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C3">Bechshøft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) were not used, because pilot trials showed that such rinses had no effect on apparent cortisol content of NARW baleen (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary Information</ext-link>).We tested the following nine different methods of pulverization on NARW baleen: (i) hand-mincing with scissors (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C14">Davenport <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>); (ii) mortar and pestle; (iii) mortar and pestle with liquid nitrogen; (iv) hand-mincing followed by mortar and pestle; (v) commercial blade grinder; (vi) commercial tobacco grinder; (vii) commercial spice grinder; (viii) laboratory tissue homogenizer (MP Biomedicals FastPrep 24); and (ix) rotary electric grinder (Dremel Model 395 Type 5) with a flexible hand-held extension and tungsten-carbide ball tip. The Dremel produced the finest baleen powder with the highest apparent cortisol concentration (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary Information</ext-link>), indicating superior extraction of hormones. Subsequently, all bowhead whale baleen samples were pulverized with the Dremel grinder, with the resulting baleen powder collected on a weigh paper underneath. For the 2-cm-diameter baleen discs, several areas around the disc were pulverized to obtain a representative sample; for the 40-cm-long strips, a 2-cm-diameter area at the base was pulverized.Pilot trials on 12 bowhead samples indicated that 50 mg samples of baleen powder sometimes had undetectably low cortisol, whereas a 100 mg sample mass always had detectable cortisol (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary Information</ext-link>). Therefore, 100 mg of well-mixed baleen powder from each sample was weighed to the nearest 0.0001 g, poured into a 16 mm × 100 mm borosilicate glass tube, capped, and stored at room temperature until extraction within 2 weeks.Extraction of steroids from baleen powder followed a consensus protocol derived from the hair and feather glucocorticoid literature (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C14">Davenport <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C9">Bortolotti <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Briefly, 4.0 ml of 100% methanol was added to 100 mg of baleen powder, vortexed for 20 h at room temperature and centrifuged for 15 min at 4000<italic>g</italic>. The supernatant was pipetted into a separate borosilicate glass tube for drying, and the pellet was rinsed twice more to recover additional hormone. For each rinse, 1.0 ml of 100% methanol was added to the pellet, vortexed for 30 s, centrifuged for 15 min at 4000<italic>g</italic>, and the supernatant was transferred to the drying tube. The combined supernatant was dried under air blow in a ThermoScientific Reacti-Therm III set at 45°C. When the volume reached &lt;0.5 ml, another 1.0 ml methanol was added to rinse down the walls of the tube, and the sample was again dried. Once fully dry, samples were reconstituted in 0.5 ml of assay buffer from the progesterone assay kit, transferred to a cryovial and stored at −20°C until assay within 1 week of extraction.We tested parallelism and accuracy of bowhead whale baleen extracts using a cortisol enzyme immunoassay (EIA; catalogue #K003-H1) and a progesterone EIA (catalogue #K025-H1), both from Arbor Assays (Ann Arbor, MI, USA). These two assays were selected based on previous successful use with faeces and respiratory vapour from other baleen whales. Cortisol rather than corticosterone was tested based on evidence that cortisol is probably the major circulating glucocorticoid of baleen whales (R. Rolland, unpublished data; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C7">Birukawa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). The manufacturer's reported assay specifications are as follows: for the cortisol assay, sensitivity = 17.3 pg/ml, limit of detection = 45.4 pg/ml, intra-assay precision = 8.8%, inter-assay precision = 8.1%; cross-reactivities, dexamethasone = 18.8%, prednisolone = 7.8%, corticosterone = 1.2%, cortisone = 1.2% and all other tested steroids &lt;0.1%; and for the progesterone assay, sensitivity = 47.9 pg/ml, limit of detection = 52.9 pg/ml, intra-assay precision = 3.2%, intra-assay precision = 5.7%; cross-reactivities, 3β-OH-progesterone = 172%, 3α-OH-progesterone = 188%, 11β-OH-progesterone = 2.7%, 11α-OH-progesterone = 147%, 5α-dihydroprogesterone = 7.0%, pregnenolone = 5.9% and all other tested steroids &lt;0.1%. This progesterone assay uses the antibody previously reported in faecal hormone literature as ‘CL#425’ (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C41">Rolland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). For both assays, the manufacturer's protocol was used except that standards for the cortisol assay were made with the progesterone assay buffer, based on technical advice from the manufacturer.Progesterone assay parallelism was tested using three separate baleen extract pools from pregnant females, non-pregnant females and males. These three pools were serially diluted in assay buffer and assayed alongside known-dose progesterone standards. Due to low cortisol content in most baleen samples, cortisol parallelism was tested using a single pool from samples containing the highest cortisol content in a pilot assay. This ‘high-cortisol’ pool was serially diluted in buffer and assayed alongside the cortisol standard curve. Results were plotted as the percentage bound vs. the logarithm of relative dose, and the slopes were compared for parallelism of the linear portion of the curve. Based on parallelism results, all subsequent samples were assayed at 1:4 for progesterone and at 1:1 (full-strength extract) for cortisol; these dilutions were chosen to fall near the 50% bound on the standard curve, the area of greatest assay precision.Assay accuracy was assessed by spiking standard curves with an equal volume of a ‘low-progesterone’ pool (samples that had low progesterone in a pilot assay) diluted to 1:4, or a ‘low-cortisol’ pool (samples that had low cortisol in a pilot assay) at 1:1, and assaying alongside standards spiked only with assay buffer. Results were plotted as the observed dose vs. known standard dose and assessed for linearity, slope and <italic>y</italic>-intercept.All assays were performed in duplicate, with a full standard curve in each assay, non-specific binding wells in quadruplicate and ‘zero’ (blank) wells in quadruplicate. Any samples with &gt;10% coefficient of variation between duplicates, or with the percentage bound &lt;10 or &lt;90%, were rediluted accordingly and re-assayed. Multiple samples from the same whale (e.g. base, 10, 20 and 30 cm samples) were assayed simultaneously in the same EIA plate, except for an initial set of 12 base samples that were assayed on a separate EIA plate.Data were analysed using InStat 3.0b for Macintosh OSX (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). Assay parallelism was assessed with <italic>F</italic>-tests on data for the linear portion of the curves. Assay accuracy was assessed as follows: (i) goodness-of-fit of linear regression line on expected vs. observed dose (e.g. <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> should ideally be &gt;0.90); (ii) slope within 0.7–1.3; and (iii) good match of <italic>y</italic>-intercept to the apparent dose when the pool was assayed alone. Cortisol data were normally distributed and therefore analysed with parametric tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C56">Zar, 2009</xref>). Progesterone data were highly skewed and could not be normalized with common transformations, and were analysed with non-parametric tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C12">Conover, 1999</xref>). Differences between males vs. females and non-pregnant vs. pregnant females were analysed with Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests or Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-tests. Patterns in hormones at different locations along a baleen plate (base, 0, 20 and 30 cm) were analysed with repeated-measures ANOVA (with Tukey–Kramer <italic>post hoc</italic> tests) or Kruskal–Wallis tests. Data are presented as means ± SEM for normally distributed data or medians for non-normal data. The significance level was set at α = 0.05.Validation results for pooled baleen extracts from bowhead whales for cortisol (top) and progesterone (bottom). Note close parallelism of the serially diluted samples to the standard curves (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>C</bold>; linear portions of curves shown), and accuracy graphs that are relatively straight, with slopes close to 1.0 (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>D</bold>; equation of best-fit linear regression line shown).Boxplots of baleen cortisol and baleen progesterone at the base of the plate (recently grown baleen) in male (<italic>n</italic> = 6) and female bowhead whales (<italic>n</italic> = 6 nonpregnant and <italic>n</italic> = 4 pregnant, total 10). Note that progesterone is shown on a logarithmic scale.Cortisol content was significantly higher in the base samples than in three distal samples (older baleen at 10, 20 and 30 cm), but the distal samples from the same animals were not significantly different from each other (within-individual; <italic>F</italic><sub>3,10</sub> = 12.166, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 for <italic>post hoc</italic> comparisons of base vs. any other location; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>). Furthermore, in contrast to the sex difference seen in the base samples, males and females did not exhibit significant differences in cortisol at the 10, 20 or 30 cm locations.Baleen progesterone at four different locations along baleen plates from bowhead whales (<italic>n</italic> = 11). Left panel, males (blue) and immature females (green); the single mature male is indicated with filled blue circles. Right panel, mature females; continuous lines and filled symbols indicate two females that were pregnant at the time of harvest; dotted lines and open symbols indicate females that were not pregnant at harvest. Note that two of the nonpregnant females have elevated progesterone concentrations in older baleen, possibly indicating prior pregnancy. The base location is the most recently grown baleen; the 10, 20 and 30 cm locations (i.e. centimetres from the base) represent progressively older baleen. Note the logarithmic scale on the <italic>y</italic>-axis.In the baleen plates that were subsampled at multiple locations, all four males and both immature females exhibited consistently low progesterone (&lt;20 ng/g) at all locations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU030F5">5</xref>). These six animals had slightly, but significantly, higher progesterone at the base location compared with the other three locations (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,5</sub> = 11.007, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0004; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU030F5">5</xref>). In contrast, four of five mature females showed extreme variation in progesterone, spanning one to three orders of magnitude within a single individual, at different locations along the baleen plate (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU030F5">5</xref>). Mature females exhibited no relationship of progesterone with baleen location (<italic>Fr</italic><sub>5,4</sub> = 2.040, <italic>P</italic> = 0.6522), and progesterone was occasionally very high even in the oldest baleen tested (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>). In the two pregnant females that were tested at multiple baleen locations (whales 10S1 and 11B3), both had extremely high progesterone at the base and 10 cm locations, and the smaller whale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C10">10</xref>S<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C1">1</xref>) also had very high progesterone at the 20 cm location.Our results indicate that immunoreactive cortisol and progesterone are measurable in bowhead whale baleen using commercially available immunoassay kits. Both hormones appear to reflect physiological parameters of interest, such as sex and reproductive state, with baleen progesterone exhibiting variation consistent with occurrence of past pregnancies. To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of successful measurement of steroid hormones in baleen from any species of whale.The higher baleen cortisol levels found in females compared with males, at the base of the plate, is reminiscent of sex differences in circulating glucocorticoids seen in many mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C47">Tilbrook <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C37">Panagiotakopoulos and Neigh, 2014</xref>). Sex differences in cortisol have been documented in other cornified tissues as well (e.g. polar bear hair, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C3">Bechshøft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C34">Macbeth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; human hair, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C15">Dettenborn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In the present study, the highest baleen cortisol levels detected were in pregnant females. Female mammals commonly have elevated glucocorticoids during pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C19">Foley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C13">D'Anna-Hernandez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and a similar pattern has been documented in faecal glucocorticoids of North Atlantic right whales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C23">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Although preliminary, our results indicate that baleen, at least at the base, may preserve a hormonal signature of adrenal activity in bowhead whales.Cortisol concentrations were markedly lower in samples taken from older baleen (10, 20 and 30 cm) compared with base samples. This pattern was also noted in progesterone data, but to a lesser degree. Cortisol is one of the most polar steroids, whereas progesterone is relatively non-polar; it may be that cortisol is more likely to leach from baleen into seawater. Human hair loses some cortisol upon immersion in hot water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C31">Li, 2012</xref>), and it is unknown whether a similar process might occur in baleen immersed in cold seawater over months. However, any such leaching does not seem to continue beyond 10 cm, because the 10, 20 and 30 cm samples had similar cortisol concentrations. If loss of hormone to seawater does occur, baleen from the core of the plate may be protected from any such loss. Our samples consisted of a mix of surface and interior baleen; future research could compare surface vs. core baleen separately. Additionally, assay of other adrenal steroids that are less polar than cortisol, such as corticosterone and aldosterone, may prove fruitful for distinguishing periods of higher adrenal activity in older baleen.The dramatic variation in baleen progesterone profiles of the mature females suggests that baleen may contain an endocrine record of pregnancy. The progesterone profiles seen in individual females are consistent with estimates of bowhead gestation length and baleen growth rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C29">Koski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C32">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Baleen growth rate in bowheads slows with age; for the animals sampled in this study, baleen growth rate was estimated at ∼19–20 cm/year for the smaller, younger females and ∼17–18 cm/year for the largest and oldest female (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C32">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C33">2012</xref>; C. George, personal observation; N. Lysiak, personal communication). For example, in the smaller pregnant female, 10S1, the 20 cm sample was probably grown ∼12–13 months prior to death, while in the larger pregnant female, 11B3, the 20 cm sample was probably grown ∼13.5–15 months prior to death. Given an estimated gestation length of 13–14 months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C29">Koski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>), it therefore makes sense that the smaller female had high progesterone that spanned three locations (base, 10 and 20 cm), i.e. her 20 cm sample was probably grown during pregnancy. In contrast, the larger female had high progesterone that spanned only two locations (base and 10 cm, but not 20 cm); thus, her 20 cm sample may represent pre-pregnancy. Although these patterns are preliminary, they suggest that baleen may retain an endocrine signature of prior pregnancies and that baleen should be investigated further as a potential retrospective record of past reproductive cycles.We note, however, that there was one pregnant female (07B12; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>) that had much lower base progesterone than the other pregnant females (though still higher than all non-pregnant females; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU030TB1">1</xref>). This female was in early pregnancy, as determined by small fetal size (C. George, personal observation). Lower progesterone levels might be characteristic of early pregnancy. Alternatively, it is possible that the base sample of this female may not have been taken precisely from the growth zone, due to fraying at the base of the plate (see Materials and methods) and may represent pre-pregnancy.Overall, these data indicate that baleen progesterone should be investigated further as a retrospective record of prior reproductive cycles in bowhead whales. Baleen hormone data could be coupled with ovarian analysis (e.g. corpora-albicans counts; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C21">George <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and may provide an alternative, and much-needed, method of estimating inter-calving intervals and reproductive cycles in baleen whales. Sampling at more locations along the baleen plate, ideally coupled with stable isotope analysis to discern annual cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C32">Lubetkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), could help match adrenal and reproductive hormone profiles to season and year.The processing and extraction methods presented here provide an introduction to the technique, but should not be regarded as a final protocol. Future experiments should include tests of other extraction methods (e.g. methanol vs. ethanol, vortex duration, extraction temperature), with the goal of maximizing extraction of steroids from baleen powder. High-performance liquid chromatography or related techniques could be used to confirm the chemical identity of steroids present in baleen, as it is possible that immunoreactive steroids detected by EIA antibodies are not necessarily pure parent hormones; unusual tissue types sometimes contain uncommon steroid metabolites and/or conjugated steroids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU030C51">Wasser <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>). Furthermore, additional antibodies and other quantification methods should be tested. Other steroids could be tested as well, particularly testosterone, estradiol, aldosterone and corticosterone.Variation in hormone content in different sections of the baleen plate should also be investigated, e.g. lingual vs. labial edge, dorsal surface vs. ventral surface and surface vs. core of plate. Potential contributions from any non-baleen dried tissue that adheres to the sample should be evaluated, as should variation between plates from different locations in the mouth (left vs. right side, anterior vs. posterior plates).In conclusion, baleen steroid analysis represents a new tool that shows great potential for retrospective assessment of patterns of physiological stress and reproductive cycles of baleen whales. Of particular interest is the availability of historical baleen samples in museum archives (samples collected during the era of commercial whaling) that could be used for comparisons with present-day population data. Additionally, if this method proves reliable, continued collection of baleen from modern populations may allow population changes to be tracked through time (e.g. potential shifts in average inter-calving intervals), as well as assessment of potential impacts of ongoing climate change and increasing human activity in the Arctic. In sum, hormone analysis of baleen could provide an innovative means to evaluate long-term trends of stress and reproduction in whale populations exposed to a changing marine environment.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary material is available at <italic>Conservation Physiology</italic> online</ext-link>.This work was supported by the NSB [contract #2012-165 to the New England Aquarium] with funding from the NSB/Shell Baseline Studies Program.We are grateful for the co-operation of the many whaling captains and crews (Barrow, Kaktovik, Savoonga and Gambell) and the Alaska Eskimo Whaling Commission for their support and assistance in sampling landed whales. We thank the many North Slope Borough (NSB) DWM staff and Gay Sheffield (UAF MAP) for assistance with sample and data collection. The NSB DWM Director Taqulik Hepa, NSB Mayor Charlotte E. Brower, and the Steering Committee of the NSB/Shell Baseline Studies Program provided support for this study. Michael Macrander of Shell provided important support, comments and guidance. We are also grateful to Jodie Treloar (New England Aquarium) for laboratory assistance, Elizabeth Burgess and Nadine Lysiak (New England Aquarium) for valuable input on the manuscript and Brooke Wikgren (New England Aquarium) for production of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU030F1">1</xref>.