Altered neurotransmitter function in CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed stickleback (<italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic>): a temperate model species for ocean acidification researchRapid evolution of cold tolerance in sticklebackEnhanced schooling performance in lateralized fishesLateralization of detour behaviour in poeciliid fish: the effect of species, gender and sexual motivationMechanism of anion permeation through channels gated by glycine and &gamma;-aminobutyric acid in mouse cultured spinal neuronesPatterns of acid-base regulation during exposure to hypercarbia in fishesImpaired learning of predators and lower prey survival under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>: a consequence of neurotransmitter interferenceOcean acidification slows retinal function in a dameselfish through interference with GABA<sub>A</sub> receptorsLong-term climate change: projections, commitments and irreversibilityBehavioural asymmetry affects escape performance in a teleost fishThe cost of hemispheric specialization in a fishOcean acidification disrupts the innate ability of fish to detect predator olfactory cuesElevated carbon dioxide affects behavioural lateralization in a coral reef fishEffects of ocean acidification on learning in coral reef fishesCO<sub>2</sub>-induced ocean acidification increases anxiety in Rockfish via alteration of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor functioningFishes in high CO<sub>2</sub> acidified oceansBehaviour disturbance in a temperate fish exposed to sustained high-CO<sub>2</sub> levelsOcean acidification impairs olfactory discrimination and homing ability of a marine fishReplenishment of fish populations is threatened by ocean acidificationImpact of global warming and rising CO<sub>2</sub> levels on coral reef fishes: what hope for the future?Behavioural responses to simulated bird attacks in marine three-spined sticklebacks after exposure to high CO<sub>2</sub> levelsNear-future carbon dioxide levels alter fish behaviour by interfering with neurotransmitter functionThe three-spined stickleback as an environmental sentinel: effects of stressors on whole-body physiological indicesOcean acidification erodes crucial auditory behaviour in a marine fishLateralized fish perform better than nonlateralized fish in spatial reorientation tasksSurvival with an asymmetrical brain: advantages and disadvantages of cerebral lateralization<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Behavioural changes in the stickleback caused by near-future CO2 levels can be restored by treatment with gabazine, revealing an involvement of the GABAA receptor ion. Importantly, these effects can be conveniently studied in the stickleback, with a sequenced and annotated genome and exceptionally well-characterized behaviour and physiologyStudies on the consequences of ocean acidification for the marine ecosystem have revealed behavioural changes in coral reef fishes exposed to sustained near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels. The changes have been linked to altered function of GABAergic neurotransmitter systems, because the behavioural alterations can be reversed rapidly by treatment with the GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor antagonist gabazine. Characterization of the molecular mechanisms involved would be greatly aided if these can be examined in a well-characterized model organism with a sequenced genome. It was recently shown that CO<sub>2</sub>-induced behavioural alterations are not confined to tropical species, but also affect the three-spined stickleback, although an involvement of the GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor was not examined. Here, we show that loss of lateralization in the stickleback can be restored rapidly and completely by gabazine treatment. This points towards a worrying universality of disturbed GABA<sub>A</sub> function after high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure in fishes from tropical to temperate marine habitats. Importantly, the stickleback is a model species with a sequenced and annotated genome, which greatly facilitates future studies on underlying molecular mechanisms.Burning of fossil fuel continues to increase the atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> level, widely affecting the ocean chemistry in a process commonly referred to as ocean acidification. According to the fifth assessment report from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change in 2013, the atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> level may reach 800&ndash;1150&emsp14;&micro;atm within this century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C8">Collins <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>), and the resultant increase in oceanic CO<sub>2</sub> levels is now recognized as a serious threat to the marine ecosystem.Initial experimental studies on the effects of these near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels on fish behaviour have focused on tropical species, suggested to be more sensitive to carbon chemistry changes owing to their high metabolic rate and therefore high CO<sub>2</sub> exchange with water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). These studies show that sustained exposure to such near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels causes an array of sensory and behavioural alterations in coral reef damselfishes. The alterations observed include reversed olfactory and auditory preferences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C17">Munday <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C11">Dixson <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C24">Simpson <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>), loss of behavioural lateralization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C12">Domenici <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), loss of learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C13">Ferrari <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), increased boldness and activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C18">Munday <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>) and reduced temporal resolution in the retinal response to light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C7">Chung <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).It has recently become clear that the behaviour of temperate fish also may be affected by elevated CO<sub>2</sub>. It was found that the three-spined stickleback (<italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic>) displays decreased behavioural lateralization, learning, boldness and curiosity when exposed to 990&emsp14;&micro;atm CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C16">Jutfelt <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Moreover, the Californian rockfish (<italic>Sebastes diploproa</italic>) shows increased anxiety when exposed to 1125&emsp14;&micro;atm CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C14">Hamilton <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).For the coral reef fish, the neural mechanisms causing behavioural abnormalities have been found to involve altered function of the &gamma;-aminobutyric acid (GABA) neurotransmitter, because normal behaviour can be restored effectively by a moderate dose of the specific GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor antagonist gabazine (SR-95531; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C6">Chivers <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C7">Chung <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C14">Hamilton <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> suggested that the increase of anxiety in the Californian rockfish is linked to altered function of the GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor.&gamma;-Aminobutyric acid is the major inhibitory neurotransmitter in vertebrate brains. The GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor is an ion channel with conductance for Cl<sup>&minus;</sup> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C4">Bormann <italic>et al</italic>., 1987</xref>). A net inflow of these negatively charged ions into the postsynaptic neuron will cause hyperpolarization of the neuronal membrane that counteracts depolarizing excitatory input. When exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, fish regulate their acid&ndash;base balance to avoid acidosis by accumulating HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup>, accompanied by a release of H<sup>&plus;</sup> and Cl<sup>&minus;</sup> to the water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C15">Ishimatsu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C5">Brauner and Baker, 2009</xref>). It is likely that such ion-regulatory mechanisms lead to altered transmembrane Cl<sup>&minus;</sup> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup> gradients in the brain during high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure, which in turn cause a reversal of GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). It is also likely that the ion-regulatory changes and/or changes in GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor function involve complex long-term perturbations, such as altered gene expression, because the behavioural dysfunctions are manifested only after several days of high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure and persist for several days after normal CO<sub>2</sub> levels have been restored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C19">Munday <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).Our ability to characterize the physiological and molecular mechanisms linking elevated CO<sub>2</sub> to altered GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor function would be greatly enhanced if studies can be done in a model species with a sequenced genome and well-characterized behaviour, life history and physiology. Clearly, the three-spined stickleback is such a species if it can be shown that the behavioural effects of high-CO<sub>2</sub> displayed by this fish are linked to the GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor. Consequently, the aim of this study was to test whether the loss of behavioural lateralization seen in high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed stickleback can be reversed by treatment with the specific GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor antagonist, gabazine.The experiment was conducted in accordance with Swedish law and regulations and approved by the Ethical Committee on Animal Experiments in Gothenburg, Sweden (ethical permit numbers 100-2010 and 151-2011).Adult marine three-spined stickleback (<italic>G. aculeatus</italic>) were collected using a hand-trawl in the Gullmars Fjord (58&deg; 15.781&prime; N, 11&deg; 29.815&prime; E) on the Swedish west coast and kept at the nearby Sven Lov&eacute;n Centre for Marine Sciences (Kristineberg), University of Gothenburg (Sweden). After being sedated using 2-phenoxyethanol in seawater (0.5&emsp14;ml&emsp14;l<sup>&minus;1</sup>), fish were tagged using subcutaneous implants of fluorescent elastomer tags (Northwest Marine Tech. Inc., Shaw Island, WA, USA), allowing us to keep track of individual variables measured during the experiment.Fish were divided into eight groups and transferred to eight 80&emsp14;l aquaria with either control or high-CO<sub>2</sub> water. Initially, four fish were put into each aquarium. During experiments, the fish were kept with a 14&emsp14;h&ndash;10&emsp14;h light&ndash;dark cycle and fed twice a day <italic>ad libitum</italic> with frozen <italic>Artemia</italic> sp. nauplii (Kordon Golden Gate, Hayward, CA, USA). At the beginning of the experiment, fish weight was 1.30&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.230&emsp14;g and standard length 46.50&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;2.219&emsp14;mm (mean&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SD). Subsequent weight and length measures are given in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov018/-/DC1">Supplementary Figs S1 and S2</ext-link>.Water chemistry data measured daily (pCO<sub>2</sub>, salinity and temperature) and twice weekly (alkalinity and pH<sub>tot</sub>), during the 50&emsp14;day exposure experimentAbbreviations: pCO<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure of carbon dioxide; pH<sub>tot</sub>, total pH. The pCO<sub>2</sub>, alkalinity, salinity and temperature were measured, while the total pH was calculated with CO<sub>2</sub>calc (USGS, St Petersburg, Florida, USA). The data are presented as means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SD.The double T-chamber used for the behavioural lateralization test. Each individual was encouraged to swim in the runway, and the preference on the left or right turn was recorded.The behavioural lateralization was retested in the same individuals on day 50. This time, the fish were tested twice, once immediately before and once immediately after a 30&emsp14;min treatment with gabazine. The treatment involved placing each fish in 200&emsp14;ml jars containing 50&emsp14;ml seawater with gabazine (4&emsp14;mg&emsp14;l<sup>&minus;1</sup>; Sigma-Aldrich Co., St Louis, MO, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C7">Chung <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C14">Hamilton <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).Length and weight were measured on days 0, 10, 20 and 50 and analysed using a two-way ANOVA followed by Sidak&apos;s multiple comparison <italic>post hoc</italic> test.Lateralization indexes were calculated for each fish according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C12">Domenici <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>. In short, the mean for absolute lateralization indices (<italic>L</italic><sub>a</sub>) reveals whether there is a significant lateralization at the population level regardless of direction of turn by individuals, and it is derived from the relative lateralization indices (<italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub>) by removing any negative prefix (individuals with a majority of left turns yield negative <italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub> values).Differences in the absolute lateralization between control and high-CO<sub>2</sub> fish on day 40 were analysed using Student&apos;s two-tailed <italic>t</italic>-test.To analyse the effects of high CO<sub>2</sub> and gabazine on day 50, two-way ANOVA with Sidak&apos;s multiple comparison test as the <italic>post hoc</italic> test was used. Values are given as means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM if not otherwise stated.(<bold>a</bold>) Relative lateralization index (<italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub>) of fish after 40&emsp14;days of treatment. (I) <italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub> in control fish exposed to 442&emsp14;&mu;atm CO<sub>2</sub>; <italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;12. (II) <italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub> in the CO<sub>2</sub> group exposed to 992&emsp14;&mu;atm CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;13). Comparison among groups was analysed with the <italic>F</italic>-test. (<bold>b</bold>) Absolute lateralization index after 40&emsp14;days of treatment, revealing loss of lateralization after high-CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. Carbon dioxide had significant effects on absolute lateralization (Student&apos;s two-tailed <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.034). Values are means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM.(<bold>a</bold>) Relative lateralization index of fish after 50&emsp14;days of treatment. The values of <italic>L</italic><sub>r</sub> are shown for control fish exposed to 442&emsp14;&mu;atm CO<sub>2</sub> before (I) and after (II) being kept in seawater containing gabazine (4&emsp14;mg&emsp14;l<sup>&minus;1</sup>) for 30&emsp14;min (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;11) and for fish exposed to 992&emsp14;&mu;atm CO<sub>2</sub> before (III) and after (IV) being kept in seawater containing gabazine (4&emsp14;mg&emsp14;l<sup>&minus;1</sup>) for 30&emsp14;min (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;12). (<bold>b</bold>) The absolute lateralization index after 50&emsp14;days of treatment in high CO<sub>2</sub> was fully restored by GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor antagonist treatment. The treatments had a significant effect (two-way ANOVA, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.0269). &ast;<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05.Lengths and weights over the experimental period did not differ between control fish and fish exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (two-way ANOVA, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.797 and 0.884, respectively; see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov018/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link>). During the 50&emsp14;day experiment, five control fish and four high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish died from unknown causes.The result of the gabazine treatment shows that altered GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor function is underlying the behavioural abnormalities displayed by stickleback after exposure to high-CO<sub>2</sub> levels, exactly like previous findings in coral reef damselfish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) and, recently, in rockfish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C14">Hamilton <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).Previous studies on coral reef damselfish (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C19">Munday <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) have shown that the behavioural effects of high-CO<sub>2</sub> treatment set in only after several days of sustained exposure and persist for several days after the high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure has ended, suggesting that alterations in gene expression may be involved. This could include changes in expression of genes for proteins involved in ion and pH regulation as well as the GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor itself. Exposure to high-CO<sub>2</sub> water has been found to reduce the response of the retina to fast stimuli, probably by altering the function of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C7">Chung <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>), and one may speculate that if other retinal functions are also altered this could contribute the loss of behavioural lateralization observed in this study as well as in previous studies on other species.Most importantly, the present study suggests that the stickleback will provide us with a very useful model that opens up an avenue of experimental studies, including the examination of underlying molecular changes. For instance, transcriptomic studies will be aided by the annotated genome of this species, and we can also envision transgenerational studies, because this species can be bred readily in aquarium populations.The three-spined stickleback is regarded as fairly tolerant of various environments, thriving in both freshwater and seawater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C23">Pottinger <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C22">&Ouml;stlund-Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C1">Barrett <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>), suggesting an extraordinary ion-regulatory plasticity. Nevertheless, its neural functions are apparently sensitive to sustained exposure to predicted future CO<sub>2</sub> levels, as shown by the complete loss of behavioural lateralization in the present study, in the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C20">N&auml;slund <italic>et al</italic>. (2015)</xref> and in other behavioural tests by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C16">Jutfelt <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</xref>.Behavioural lateralization is thought to be a consequence of hemispheric specialization in the brain, allowing animals to carry out parallel processing and simultaneous responses to different stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C3">Bisazza <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C10">Dadda <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In fish, the left optic lobe is connected to the right eye and vice versa, leading to a corresponding specialization of the eyes. If the right eye is, for example, focused on observing potential threats, pointing the head to the right and turning to the right allows the right eye to observe possible threats coming from behind. At the same time, the left eye can be focused on a different task, such as acquiring resources. Improved schooling performance, escape response, orientation and cognitive tasks are other suggested advantages of brain asymmetry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C2">Bisazza and Dadda, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C25">Sovrano <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C27">Vallortigara and Rogers, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C9">Dadda <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Loss of lateralization may therefore possibly affect fish fitness and survival.Initially, it was hypothesized that highly active fish with a need for rapid oxygen uptake, and therefore large respiratory surface areas, would be more at risk for being affected by increases in the water CO<sub>2</sub> level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV018C21">Nilsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). The reason for this is that a large respiratory surface area should also lead to a fast release of CO<sub>2</sub> from blood to water, approaching an equilibrium with the ambient water, making the blood carbonate system more sensitive to ambient changes in CO<sub>2</sub>. Indeed, fish in general have relatively low internal levels of CO<sub>2</sub> in comparison to air-breathing animals owing to the high solubility of CO<sub>2</sub> in water. Consequently, few would have regarded the stickleback as particularly vulnerable, because it is not a &lsquo;high-performance&rsquo; species with a particularly high rate of gas exchange with the environment and because it is able to tolerate a wide range of environmental conditions. A worrying aspect of the present study is therefore that it indicates that altered GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor function in response to sustained environmental hypercapnia may affect virtually any fish, at least in marine habitats.At present, we do not know to what degree natural selection will be able to counteract neural effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in the relatively short period during which oceanic CO<sub>2</sub> levels have been projected to reach close to 1000&emsp14;&micro;atm. What the present study shows is that individual acclimation is unlikely to be of help, because the behavioural change was in no way reduced after 50&emsp14;days in the high-CO<sub>2</sub> environment.<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov018/-/DC1">Supplementary material is available at <italic>Conservation Physiology</italic> online</ext-link>.This work was supported by <grant-sponsor>the University of Oslo</grant-sponsor> [to G.E.N. and F.L.], <grant-sponsor>The Formas Research Council</grant-sponsor> [to F.J.], <grant-sponsor>The Swedish Research Council</grant-sponsor> [to F.J. and G.E.N.] and <grant-sponsor>the Royal Swedish Academy of Science</grant-sponsor> [to F.L.].The study was conceived and designed by G.E.N. and F.J. Experiments and measurements were executed by F.L. All authors contributed to writing the paper.The authors thank Erik Lindstr&ouml;m for help with fish collection, rearing and water chemistry.