 Habitat specificity of a threatened and endemic, cliff-dwelling halophyte  Dry coastal ecosystems of Portugal  Plant community changes as ecological indicator of seabird colonies' impacts on Mediterranean Islands  Origin of reciprocal translocations and their effects in  Clarkia speciosa   Experimental taxonomic studies in the  Arabis holboellii  and allied species  Ranunculus sect. Auricomus in Bayern und den angrenzenden Gebieten. I. Allgemeiner Teil  Résultats de deux excursions géobotaniques à travers le Portugal septentrional et moyen IV. Esquisse sur la végétation dunale  The role of ecology in biological conservation  The role of alien plants in the natural coastal vegetation in central-northern Spain  Arribas da faixa costeira de Cascais. Projecto de Recuperação de Habitats  Karyology of  Limonium  (Plumbaginaceae) species from the Balearic Islands and the western Iberian Peninsula  Assessing the residual effects of  Carpobrotus edulis  invasion, implications for restoration  Tipos de Vegetação e adaptações das plantas do litoral de Portugal continental  Biogeografia de Portugal Continental  Sintaxonomia da vegetação halocasmofítica das falésias marítimas portuguesas (Crithmo-Staticetea Br.-Bl. 1947)  An overview of the Pegano harmalae-Salsoletea vermiculatae Br.-Bl. and. O. Bolòs 1958, vegetation class in continental Portugal  The application of the Habitats Directive in Portugal  Vascular plant communities in Portugal (Continental, the Azores and Madeira)  On the conservation of natural habitats and of wild fauna and flora  Seed production and dispersal in the non-native, invasive succulent  Carprobrotus edulis  (Aizoaceae) in coastal strand communities of central California  Root profile and competition between the invasive, exotic perennial,  Carprobrotus edulis  and two native species in California coastal shrubs  Rarity and threat relationships in the conservation planning of Iberian flora  European Commission: seventh updated list of sites of community importance for the Mediterranean biogeographical region  Conserving taxonomic complexity  Die gattung Limonium im südwestmediterranen Raum   Limonium  Miller  Plantas endémicas do litoral de Portugal Continental  Plant life history traits of rare versus frequent plant taxa of sandplains: implications for research and management trials  A multivariate approach to plant community distribution in the coastal dune zonation of NW Denmark  How successful are plant species reintroductions?  Plant conservation: old problems, new perspectives  Reticulate evolution and taxonomic concepts in the  Ranunculus auricomus  complex (Ranunculaceae): insights from morphological, karyological and molecular data  Complex hybridity in  Isotoma petraea . 1. The occurrence of interchange heterozygosity, autogamy and a balanced lethal system  Breeding system and ecological traits of the critically endangered endemic plant  Limonium barceloi  (Gil and Llorens) (Plumbaginaceae)  Plumbaginaceae  Relevant plant recovery programmes. Conservation management of plant micro-reserves and ecological restoration  Molecular phylogenetics of  Limonium  and related genera (Plumbaginaceae): biogeographical and systematic implications  National inventories of crop wild relatives and wild harvested plants: case-study for Portugal  The meaning of mainland Portugal beaches and dunes' psammophilic plant communities: a contribution to tourism management and nature conservation  Burial of plants as a selective force in sand dunes  Bioclimatic mapping using geostatistical approaches: application to mainland Portugal  Evaluation of the stress-inducible production of proline in transgenic sugarcane ( Saccharum  spp): osmotic adjustment, chlorophyll fluorescence and oxidative stress   Fitossociologia e Paisagem da Bacia Hidrográfica do Rio Paiva/Landscape and phytosociology of the Paiva River ' s hydrographical basin   Europe, ecosystems of  Study of the evolutionary relationships among  Limonium  species (Plumbaginaceae) using nuclear and cytoplasmic molecular markers  Historical and biological determinants of genetic diversity in the highly endemic triploid sea lavender  Limonium dufourii  (Plumbaginaceae)  Grouping and prioritization of vascular plant species for conservation: combining natural rarity and management need  Impact of the invasive  Carpobrotus edulis  on  Armeria pseudarmeria  at Cabo da Roca  Plant invasions of protected areas in Europe: an old continent facing new problems  Seven forms of rarity  Mapa de series, geoseries y geopermaseries de vegetación de España. Memoria del mapa de vegetación potencial de España  Molecular and morphological differentiation in  Limonium dufourii  (Plumbaginaceae), an endangered Mediterranean plant  Male fertility versus sterility, cytotype, and DNA quantitative variation in seed production in diploid and tetraploid sea lavenders ( Limonium  sp., Plumbaginaceae) reveal diversity in reproduction modes  Epigenetic rather than genetic factors may explain phenotypic divergence between coastal populations of diploid and tetraploid ( Limonium  sp.; Plumbaginaceae) in Portugal  Absence of geographic structure in European populations of  Rubus fruticosus  L. complex using chloroplast DNA microsatellites  Tsunami relics on the coastal landscape west of Lisbon, Portugal  Evaluating approaches to the conservation of rare and endangered plants  Intraspecific chromosome number variation: a neglected threat to the conservation of rare species  Structural and numerical chromosomal polymorphism in natural populations of  Alopecurus  L. (Poaceae)  The contribution of population and community to conservation science  Evolutionary and plant geographical aspects of chasmophytic communities  Genetic diversity and floral dimorphism in  Limonium dendroides  (Plumbaginaceae), a woody  Canarian  species on the way of extinction  Invasion by South African  Carpobrotus  (Aizoaceae) taxa in the Mediterranean Basin: the effects of insularity on plant reproductive systems  Consistent performance of invasive species within and among islands of the Mediterranean basin  Distribution and conservation status of littoral vascular plant species along the European coasts  Ecological and evolutionary opportunities of apomixis: insights from Taraxacum and Chondrilla  Local and regional assessment of the impacts of plant invaders on vegetation structure and soil properties of Mediterranean islands  Hierarchical grouping to optimize an objective function  Genetic bottlenecks and dysgenic gene flow into re-established populations of the grassland daisy,  Rutidosis leptorrhynchoides    Guest Editor:  Adele Muscolo  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Coastal cliff-tops are specific saline environments, where only highly specialized halophytes can thrive. Limonium spp. are commonly found in these ecological conditions, many of them being considered as threatened or with an unknown conservation status. The habitat requirements of Limonium multiflorum, an apomictic halophyte endemic to western Portugal, were investigated. Results showed the species narrow habitat specificity as well as its intolerance to competition with invasive alien plants. We conclude that in situ conservation of this rare and vulnerable species emerges as a priority in order to ensure that its biodiversity is not lost.  Coastal areas and other saline environments are major contributors to regional and global biodiversity patterns. In these environments, rapidly changing gradients require highly specialized plants like halophytes. In European coastal cliff-tops, rocky and sandy seashores, and saltmarshes, typical halophytes from the genus  Limonium  are commonly found. Among them, the aneuploid tetraploid (2 n  = 4 x  = 35, 36, 37)  Limonium multiflorum , endemic to the west coast of Portugal, is an interesting case study for investigating the ecology and conservation of a halophyte agamospermic species. Although it is listed in the IUCN red list of threatened species, information on its population size or rarity, as well as its ecology, in some respects is still unknown. Field surveys in the largest known population were performed (Raso cape, Portugal) in order to determine habitat requirements and conservation status. A total of 88 quadrats were monitored, 43 of which contained at least one  L. multiflorum  individual. For each sampled quadrat, four abiotic and four biotic variables as well as two spatially derived variables were recorded. Principal component analysis and cluster analysis showed narrow habitat specificity for this species which appeared to be intolerant to competition with invasive alien plants. We conclude that  in situ  conservation in a local ‘hotspot’ of this rare and vulnerable species emerges as a priority in order to ensure that biodiversity is not lost.  Habitat assessment is a fundamental requirement for species conservation. Attempts to set plant conservation priorities revealed the need to consider attributes such as species ecological specificity, geographical rarity and rate of threat ( Domínguez Lozano  et al . 2003 ;  Pärtel  et al . 2005 ). Furthermore, a study on plant life history traits in rare versus common  taxa  also showed that infrequent species exhibited a narrower geographical range and more habitat specialization than their common relatives ( Farnsworth 2007 ). Thus, knowledge on habitat requirements of a rare species is crucial, in particular in the case of agamospermic species (defined by an asexual breeding system) ( Domínguez Lozano  et al . 2003 ), to help establish the best conservation methods.  In Europe, coastal vegetation presents lower diversity values when compared with other world regions ( Mucina 2013 ) but European dry coastal terrestrial habitats, which include maritime rocks, sea-cliffs and coastal slopes, show higher values in terms of plant diversity ( van der Maarel 1993 ;  van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996 ). Among the best represented flowering plant families of these habitats are the  Plumbaginaceae  with nearly 90 % of coastal species, including most members from the genus  Limonium  ( Kubitzki 1993 ;  van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996 ). This cosmopolitan halophytic genus comprises annual and perennial species found on cliff-tops, rocky and sandy seashores, and saltmarshes ( Erben 1993 ;  Kubitzki 1993 ). These habitats are an important source of endemics ( van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996 ), and nearly 37 % of all typical littoral species are considered threatened either because they have an extremely local distribution or because they are in decline as a result of negative human impacts in coastal areas ( van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996 ).  Knowledge of habitat requirements of threatened populations from rare species selected for conservation is crucial for assuring their viability ( Simberloff 1988 ;  Brussard 1991 ;  Schemske  et al . 1994 ;  Heywood and Iriondo 2003 ), since the establishment and expansion of a species is dependent on growth under favourable ecological conditions (e.g.  Baumberger  et al . 2012 ). Increasing a species' survival prospects through reintroduction or reinforcement (increase population size and diversity) of native species ( Akeroyd and Wyse Jackson 1995 ), and knowing ecological processes in combination with demographic and genetic processes and breeding systems is therefore essential ( Godefroid  et al . 2011 ). However, objective data for documenting habitat preferences of rare plant species are relatively scarce, in particular those on ocean-exposed high cliff-tops subjected to salt spray transported inland by wind ( Salisbury 1952 ;  Maun 2004 ;  Frederiksen  et al . 2006 ).  The Portuguese coast is known for the richness of its flora due to a singular biogeographic position ( Braun-Blanquet  et al . 1972 ;  Asensi  et al . 1993 ;  van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996 ). About 35 % of all Portuguese Natura 2000 habitats consist of coastal habitats, including Atlantic ocean-exposed cliff-tops ( Costa  et al . 2007 ;  Martins  et al . 2013 ). These locations present the original flora and vegetation on limestone, sandstone and marly clay areas, and include the rare and endemic cliff-dwelling  Limonium multiflorum  ( Erben 1978 ,  1993 ;  Costa  et al . 2000 ;  Espírito-Santo  et al . 2012 ). This species is listed in Annex II of Habitats Directive ( Council Directive 92/43/EEC 1992 ) and in the IUCN red list of threatened species ( IUCN 2013 ), and most of its known populations are located in Portuguese NATURA 2000 Sites of Community Importance ( EC 2013 ). Although  L. multiflorum  is considered a Portuguese crop wild relative ( Magos-Brehm  et al . 2008 ) and has an assessed conservation status of ‘Least Concern’ in the IUCN red list ( IUCN 2013 ), information on its ecological preferences, essential for recovery plans, especially population restoration, population augmentation or population reintroduction is lacking.  In the present study we assessed habitat requirements for  L. multiflorum . Two main questions were addressed: (i) What are the main abiotic and biotic variables favourable for its persistence? (ii) What is the vegetation cover and respective species composition associated with its presence?  Map of  L. multiflorum  distribution in the western coast of Portugal.  Schematic drawing of the quadrat sampling of  L. multiflorum  in the coast of Raso cape.  Thermopluviometric diagram based on the weather station in the coast of Raso cape. The red line corresponds to mean monthly temperature (°C) and the blue line corresponds to mean monthly precipitation (mm).  Wind regime diagrams based on the weather station in the coast of Raso cape during  L. multiflorum  flowering peak (May–July).  Field surveys used a grid of 10 × 10 m quadrats which was overlaid over the aerial photographs of the site and later transferred to the site using global positioning system (GPS) receivers. A total of 88 quadrats were surveyed, 43 of which contained at least one  L. multiflorum  individual (presence quadrat) and the remaining 45 were randomly selected quadrats containing no individuals from this species (absence quadrat) (Fig.  2 ). The random selection procedure was performed using R software's ‘sample’ routine ( R Core Team 2013 ). In quadrats where  L. multiflorum  was present censuses were carried out from April to June 2013. For each sampled quadrat four abiotic variables, namely rock formation (RockForm), cobble (Cobble), coarse sand (CoarseSd) and fine sand (FineSand) (all expressed in %), were recorded. Four biotic variables related to vegetation cover (Coverage) as well as invasive non-native species (INNS) cover, dead organic matter (lignified or not) (DOM) cover and litter (Residues) cover were also estimated (expressed in %) in each quadrat. To facilitate data collection, each quadrat was then sub-divided into sub-quadrats of 1 m 2 , and the percent coverage value obtained for the sub-quadrats of the same 100 m 2  quadrat were averaged. Two spatial variables, distance from coastline (Dist_coa) and mean quadrat slope (Mean_slo), were also derived using the ArcGIS ®  10.0 software, by ESRI.  To define  L. multiflorum  habitat requirements we performed a principal component analysis (PCA) on the resulting data matrix using abiotic, biotic and spatially derived variables. In order to discriminate the vegetation structure and composition in the monitored quadrats, a cluster analysis using Euclidean distance and Ward clustering method ( Ward 1963 ) was performed using the set of quadrats containing  L. multiflorum . To ensure that the group of quadrats (clusters) had the same influence from the environmental variables, Kruskal–Wallis tests of variance were performed ( Sokal and Rohlf 1997 ;  Zar 2010 ). To complete habitat characterization of  L. multiflorum,  the most frequent and abundant plant species within each cluster was defined as described in  Baumberger  et al . (2012) . The mean coverage of each species within each group was also calculated. All statistical analyses were conducted using the STATISTICA software (StatSoft V10). Bioclimatic and biogeographic nomenclature followed the proposals of  Rivas-Martínez (2007) . Taxonomic nomenclature followed  Menezes de Sequeira  et al . (2011) .  On the western coast most  L. multiflorum  populations occur at inaccessible cliff sites and/or show very small size ( Róis  et al . 2013 ). Under these circumstances, this study was conducted at the best accessible site and on the largest known population for this species, in Raso cape. Study site rocks were bare of vegetation up to ∼7–8 m asl, due to strong exposure to Atlantic storms and waves over the years.  Two first axes of PCA based on  L. multiflorum  presence and absence quadrats. Red symbols mean that  L. multiflorum  was recorded whereas blue symbols signify that it was absent. Axis 1 represents 44.8 % of variation, and Axis 2, 19.7 %. CoarseSd, coarse sand; Cobble, cobble; Coverage, vegetation cover; Dist_coa, distance from coast; DOM, dead organic matter cover; FineSand, fine sand; INNS, invasive non-native species cover; Mean_slo, mean slope; Residues, litter cover; RockForm, rock formation.  Mean values ± standard error of abiotic, biotic and spatial-related variables in each of four environmental groups based on the presence data of PCA. Bold letters within a row indicate non-significant with post hoc multiple comparison Tukey's test ( α  = 0.05;  P  &lt; 0.001).  P  value &lt;0.001. ns, non-significant; CoarseSD, coarse sand; Cobble, cobble; Coverage, vegetation cover; Dist_coa, distance from coast; DOM, dead organic matter cover; FineSd, fine sand; INNS, invasive non-native species cover; Mean_slo, mean slope; Residues, litter cover; RockForm, rock formation.  Mean coverage (%) of the most frequent species in each of the four environmental groups (clusters) based on the presence data of PCA.  Cluster dendogram of the four clusters containing  L. multiflorum . The dissimilarity between groups was calculated based on species variables using Euclidean distance and the Ward aggregation method. Cluster definition 1 accounts for a high percentage of  C. edulis  (&gt;65 %); Cluster 2 by a moderate percentage of  C. edulis  (&lt;35 %); Cluster 3 is defined by  A. welwitschii  (9.67 %) and  P. incurva  (21.33 %); and Cluster 4 represents quadrats with the highest  L. multiflorum  frequency (0.84 %).  Vegetation composition also varied between clusters. Cluster 1 was dominated by  Carpobrotus edulis  with a coverage percentage &gt;65 % whereas Cluster 2 presented a moderate coverage of  C. edulis  (&lt;35 %). In this cluster significant mean coverage was observed for psammophilous species like the perennials  Armeria welwitschii  and  Elymus farctus  subsp.  boreo-atlanticus . As for Cluster 3, significant frequencies of the perennial  Limonium ovalifolium  and the therophyte  Parapholis incurva  were revealed. Finally, Cluster 4 which had the greatest coverage percentage of  L. multiflorum  (0.835 %) of all clusters appeared to be associated with chasmophytic species such as  C. maritimum , and other perennials like  Frankenia laevis  and  Inula crithmoides .  In this study we show that  L. multiflorum  grows on sea-cliffs preferentially up to 50 m asl in karstic crevices within exposed rocks more or less filled with substrate, or on shallow soil above the rock strata and on scree slopes. The presence of  L. multiflorum  was favoured by the presence of rock formation, cobble, low percentage of vegetation coverage, low frequency of invasive non-native species and closest distance to coast. In fact, as pointed out by  Warming (1909) ,  L. multiflorum 's preference for salt-rich rock crevices seems to be a strategy to use such locations as refuges, thus avoiding competition with many other coastal plants that are unable to colonize such habitats. Furthermore, as it happens in endemic  Limonium  spp., populations tend to be fragmented and usually show low population sizes as a consequence of many social and economic activities like urbanization, tourism and traffic ( Rodríguez  et al . 2003 ;  Palop-Esteban  et al . 2007 ;  Suárez-García  et al . 2009 ;  Khan  et al . 2012 ;  Róis  et al . 2013 ) on their habitats. This is also the case of  L. multiflorum  ( ICNF 2013 ), in particular, in the Raso cape population (A.F. and V.S., unpubl. res.).  Vegetation composition significantly differs among the four floristically defined groups. Cluster 1 is dominated by the alien plant  C. edulis  with  E. farctus  subsp.  boreo-atlanticus 's due to nitrophilous coarse sand dunes corresponding to  Elytrigietum junceo-boreoatlanticae  association ( Costa  et al . 2012 ). The presence of  L. multiflorum  in this cluster can be explained by 5 % of rock outcrop, uncovered with sand. Cluster 2 includes the farthest quadrats from the sea where rock depressions filled up with fine sand and cobble appear. In this cluster  A. welwitschii ,  F. laevis  and  L. multiflorum  predominate. This cluster presents a poor floristic composition, as it happens in the previous cluster, due to invasion of  C. edulis , possibly related with the proximity to roads (higher nitrification) .  Cluster 3 is typically formed by species of rocky substrate, with a high slope and direct influence of wind loaded with salt. Here  L. ovalifolium ,  C. maritimum ,  A. welwitschii ,  F. laevis ,  L. multiflorum ,  P. coronopus  form the perennial community  Limonietum multifloro-virgati  ( Costa  et al . 1998 b  ,  2012 ). In their clearings  P. incurva ,  Medicago minima ,  Andryala arenaria  form the poor, annual association  Parapholido incurvae–Catapodietum marini . Also, the presence of  Lotus creticus  is due to coarse sand. Cluster 4 also exhibits species that constitute the  Limonietum multifloro-virgati  association ( Costa  et al . 1998 b  ,  2012 ), namely  C. maritimum ,  L. multiflorum ,  I. crithmoides ,  F. laevis ,  P. coronopus . The referred species are at their ecological optimum in this rocky sea-cliff cluster although a small percentage of coarse sand explains the presence of  E. farctus  subsp.  boreo-atlanticus  and  L. creticus.  Plant survival in this ecological context is difficult due to low availability of fresh water, low level of essential nutrients and the abrasive action of strong winds laden with salt and increasing conditions of extreme dryness ( Costa  et al . 1998 b  ). To overcome this some plants respond with adaptations, such as adopting the hemicryptophyte or therophyte life forms, presenting succulent leaves and/or salt glands in the leaves ( Warming 1909 ;  Costa 2001 ;  Grigore  et al . 2014 ).  Our results show that both native and non-native vegetation cover are negatively correlated with  L. multiflorum  presence, emphasizing its preferences for sites where competition with other species is low. Among the species having a greater negative effect in their persistence is the exotic, invasive, crawling  C. edulis . This species commonly invades coastal habitats in Mediterranean Europe forming mantles on maritime rocks, cliffs and sand dunes ( D'Antonio 1990 ;  Traveset  et al . 2008 ;  Pyšek  et al . 2013 ) competing directly with native plant species, suppressing the growth and establishment of other plants ( D'Antonio and Mahall 1991 ;  Vilà  et al . 2006 ), altering certain soil parameters ( Vilà  et al . 2006 ;  Conser and Connor 2009 ) or creating litter accumulation on the soil surface ( Molinari  et al . 2007 ). Although  C. edulis  seems to develop well on rocky substrates at sites where seagulls' ( Larus  sp.) nutrient-rich droppings are frequent (M.D.E.-S., unpubl. res.), in our study it seems to compete mainly with species showing preference for sand substrates. Remarkably, some littoral species show strong resilience to  C. edulis  invasion, like the narrow endemic cliff-species  Armeria pseudoarmeria  ( Pinto-Ricardo  et al . 2010 ) or other  Limonium  spp. ( Snogerup 1971 ;  Suehs  et al . 2003 ;  Campos  et al . 2004 ).  For the effective protection of the rare and endemic  L. multiflorum  not only ecological data but also life story, demography and genetic data should be taken into account to ensure that maximum genetic variation is preserved. In this context, one of the factors to be considered in conserving  L. multiflorum  is related with chromosome polymorphisms since euploid and aneuploid cytotypes occur within populations ( Róis  et al . 2012 ). Although, it was first described as an unbalanced aneuploid tetraploid (2 n  = 4 x  = 35) ( Erben 1978 ), both unbalanced and balanced tetraploid cytotypes (2 n  = 4 x  = 35, 36, 37) and diverse karyological polymorphisms were found within and among populations, with greater variability in the Raso cape population ( Róis  et al . 2012 ). This has also been observed in other  Limonium  taxa (e.g.  Castro and Rosseló 2007 ), and even in a variety of genera from different plant families (e.g.  Brassicaceae ,  Böcher 1954 ;  Campanulaceae ,  James 1965 ;  Onagraceae ,  Bloom 1974 ;  Plumbaginaceae ,  Erben 1978 ;  Poaceae ,  Sieber and Murray 1981 ;  Ranunculaceae ,  Borchers-Kolb 1983 ). These cytological differences should be considered to ensure that maximum genetic variation is preserved. Furthermore, the resultant combination of incompatible cytotypes could result in the failure of reintroduced plants to reproduce and may bring reproductive instability to augmented populations ( Young and Murray 2000 ;  Ennos  et al . 2005 ;  Severns and Liston 2008 ).  Noticeably, male sterility and gynodioecism are found in plants from experimental collections ( Róis  et al . 2012 ) and field plants (Heike Sprenger and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). However, these plants are capable of producing large numbers of viable seeds with variable ploidy levels, as revealed by flow cytometry seed screening ( Róis  et al . 2012 ) and reproduce through apomixis (A.S.R. and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). This form of uniparental reproduction is found in ‘taxonomically complex groups’ like in other  Limonium  spp. ( Erben 1978 ;  Palacios  et al . 2000 ;  Lledó  et al . 2005 ) and also in dandelions ( Taraxacum  spp.;  van Dijk 2003 ), blackberries ( Rubus fruticosus  agg.;  Salvini  et al . 2006 ) and in  Ranunculus  spp. ( Hörandl  et al . 2009 ), which generates a diverse mixture of related individuals ( Ennos  et al . 2005 ).  While some  L. multiflorum  populations are located in natural parks (Parque Natural Sintra-Cascais) and other areas under legal protection (e.g. Site of Community Importance—SCI Sintra/Cascais PTCON0008; SCI Peniche/Sta Cruz PTCON0056), in the past decades no information on population size along its distribution range has been available. However, we hypothesized that population decline might have occurred due to increasing urban development in the coastal areas and the impact of tourism. For instance, in Raso cape, sightseeing tourists, sports fishing and other socio-economic activities, together with competition associated with invasion by non-native species are cumulatively leading to population decline (V.S., A.F. and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). Notably, methylation-sensitive amplified polymorphism (MSAP) data from  L. multiflorum  natural populations reveal low levels of genetic/epigenetic diversity ( Róis  et al . 2013 ). Altogether these data mean that none of the populations analysed could restore the genotypic diversity observed in any other  L. multiflorum  population. Hence, habitat protection emerges as the top priority to prevent population extinction of the narrow-specialist  L. multiflorum . For the conservation of this species, management actions such as those referred by  Laguna  et al . (2013) , namely limiting access to populations, for example, the experimental exclusion of herbivores by means of fences to protect populations of  L. dufourii  in ‘Marsh dels Moros’ (Spain) and to perform selective removal and control of invasive species ( Laguna  et al . 2013 ), are required. Other technical solutions could be population reinforcements, reintroduction or establishment of new populations, the goal of which is the introduction of new specimens. In the case of  L. multiflorum , attempts to create new populations through experimental actions like sowing seeds directly  in situ  did not prove to be successful (A.D.C. and V.S., unpubl. res.) but population reinforcements by planting newly produced specimens using seed stock that originated from the same natural populations (e.g. Raso cape) appears to give better results ( Caperta  et al . 2013 ). Complementary  ex situ  conservation actions for this species such as collection and storage of seeds preserved in João do Amaral Franco Seed Bank (Ajuda Botanical Garden) have also been conducted ( Caperta  et al . 2013 ) with the hope that the genetic diversity contained in these collections could be representative of natural populations. Thus, to conserve  L. multiflorum , it is preferable to develop small, localized experimental actions as  Laguna  et al . (2013)  pointed out. In fact, only moderate success is reported for reintroduction projects due, for example, to insufficient long-term monitoring following reintroduction and/or lack of understanding of the underlying reasons for decline in existing plant populations (e.g.  Godefroid  et al . 2011 ).  According to Rabinowitz' scheme ( 1981 ), in which species were classified into categories according to their geographic range, habitat specificity and local population size,  L. multiflorum  can be classified as a ‘classic rarity’ since it presents both narrow geographic range and narrow habitat specificity, thus being considered a restricted endemic. Furthermore, species' populations observed throughout its entire range consistently present small sizes and low levels of genetic diversity as revealed by population genetic and epigenetic studies using MSAP markers ( Róis  et al . 2013 ). Taking the above into consideration, as well as diverse social-economic impacts exerted on its populations, we considered that  L. multiflorum  deserves a status of ‘Vulnerable’ in the IUCN red list.  As already pointed out for other ‘taxonomically complex groups’ ( Ennos  et al . 2005 ), conservation of rare and endemic  L. multiflorum  is best achieved by facilitating evolutionary interactions among its members that generate and maintain their taxonomic biodiversity.  Our work was funded by  Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia (FCT)  (Portugal) ( PEST-OE/AGR/UI0240/2011 ).  A.D.C.  (Researcher,  CBAA/ISA) and A.S.R. (SFRH/BD/62542/2009  grant) were supported by  FCT .  A.D.C. and P.A. designed and coordinated the study. M.D.E.-S. coordinated the fieldwork and A.D.C., M.D.E.-S., A.P.P. and A.S.R. performed the fieldwork. A.F. and V.S. processed the raw data and carried out statistical analysis. J.C.C. and M.D.E.-S. performed the phytosociological analysis. A.D.C. and P.A. drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.  None declared.  We thank Manuela Rodrigues (Volunteer), Ana Cortinhas (CBAA/ISA) and Vanessa Mendonça (CBAA/ISA) for help in field work, Jorge Cadima (ISA) for help in defining the experimental design, and the anonymous reviewers for all the helpful comments and suggestions. We thank the Instituto da Conservação da Natureza e das Florestas (ICNF) for providing permissions for field work. 