Nitrification inhibition activity, a novel trait in root exudates of riceDirect N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from rice paddy fields: summary of available dataDenitrification coupled to nitrification in the rhizosphere of riceInfluence of different cultivars on populations of ammonia-oxidizing bacteria in the root environment of riceSite-specific nutrient management for intensive rice cropping systems in AsiaScreening of allelopathic activity from rice cultivars by bioassay and field testSoil texture effect on nitrate leaching in soil percolatesControlled release technology (Agricultural)Nitrification inhibitors from the root tissues of <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic>, a tropical grassBiological nitrification inhibition by <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> roots varies with soil type and inhibits nitrifying bacteria, but not other major soil microorganismsNitrogen mineralization, immobilization, and nitrificationVarious players in the nitrogen cycle: diversity and functions of the microorganisms involved in nitrification and denitrificationOrganic anion exudation by lowland rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) at zinc and phosphorus deficiencyBioluminescence assay using <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> for rapid and sensitive detection of nitrification inhibitorsSuppression of nitrification and nitrous oxide emission by the tropical grass <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic>Reducing environmental risk by improving N management in intensive Chinese agricultural systemsComparative kinetic analysis of ammonium and nitrate acquisition by tropical lowland rice: implication for rice cultivation and yield potentialMineral-nitrogen leaching and ammonia volatilization from a rice-rapeseed system as affected by 3,4-dimethylpyrazole phosphateEvolution of dinitrogen and nitrous oxide from the soil to the atmosphere through rice plantsAnaerobic ammonium oxidation discovered in a denitrifying fluidized bed reactorNitrification inhibitors in agriculture and horticulture: a literature reviewScope and strategies for regulation of nitrification in agricultural systems – challenges and opportunitiesNH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> triggers the synthesis and release of biological nitrification inhibition compounds in <italic>Brachiara humidicola</italic> rootsEvidence for biological nitrification inhibition in <italic>Brachiaria pastures</italic>QTLs for cell-membrane stability mapped in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) under drought stressResponse to zinc deficiency of two rice lines with contrasting tolerance is determined by root growth maintenance and organic acid exudation rates, and not by zinc-transporter activityDetection, isolation and characterization of a root-exuded compound, methyl 3-(4-hydroxyphenyl) propionate, responsible for biological nitrification inhibition by sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>)3,4-Dimethylpyrazole phosphate (DMPP) – a new nitrification inhibitor for agriculture and horticultureThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Screening numerous genotypes for nitrification inhibition activity provides first evidence that root exudates of rice can slow the nitrification of ammonium to nitrate in soil. This offers promising possibilities for exploiting molecular and genetic tools to improve nitrogen use efficiency by inhibiting wasteful nitrification.Nitrification is an important process in soil--plant systems for providing plant-available nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>). However, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> is less stable in soils compared with ammonium (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) and is more easily lost through leaching, runoff or denitrification. This study tested whether biological nitrification inhibition (BNI) activity is present in the root exudates of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) and also the extent of variation between different genotypes.The BNI activity of root exudates was estimated by a bioluminescence assay using a recombinant <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> strain. Afterwards, the effect of a single application of concentrated root exudates and that of exudates deposited in the rhizosphere soil was tested on BNI using soil incubation. Soil was added with (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and water to reach 60 % of the water-holding capacity and incubated at 30 °C for different periods. Amounts of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> were determined using a continuous-flow auto-analyser.In an initial screening experiment, BNI activity in the exudates of 36 different rice genotypes was evaluated using a bioassay based on a recombinant <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic> strain. Significant genotypic variation was detected with the upland cultivar IAC25 demonstrating consistently high BNI activity, while modern lowland varieties like Nipponbare or IR64 exhibited lower activity. Subsequent experiments ruled out the possibility that BNI activity is simply due to non-specific (solute) leakage from roots. Soil incubation studies with concentrated root exudates of IAC25 showed significant reductions in NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> formation. This effect was confirmed by detecting lower NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> levels in incubation experiments using rhizosphere soil obtained from IAC25.Our results provide first evidence that root exudates of rice can reduce nitrification rates in soil. Having shown this for a model crop, rice, offers possibilities for further exploitation of this phenomenon through molecular and genetic tools.The process of nitrification, in which ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) is converted to nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>), is a key soil process that provides plant roots with the nitrogen (N) form that is preferentially taken up. However, when nitrification occurs rapidly, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> supply may exceed plant demand. Such excess soil NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> is easily lost because NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> is less tightly bound to the soil compared with NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>. Losses of the highly mobile NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> due to leaching, runoff or denitrification can amount to 60 % of applied fertilizer N in coarse-textured soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C6">Gaines and Gaines, 1994</xref>). Such a reduction in N use efficiency represents a large economic cost, estimated to be around US$ 15 billion annually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C21">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). In addition, off-site movement of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> can also cause environmental problems such as groundwater contamination and eutrophication of surface water. Nitrogen lost by gaseous emission, as the powerful greenhouse gas N<sub>2</sub>O, contributes to the climate change phenomenon. In general, the regulation of nitrification to a level in which nitrification rates are in synchrony with NO<sub>3</sub> uptake by plants may alleviate these problems and help achieve a more sustainable modern agriculture.Nitrification can be generalized as a two-step process wherein the initial oxidation of NH<sub>3</sub> to NO<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup>, considered as the rate-limiting step, is followed by the oxidation of NO<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup> to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>. Historically, the former step was believed to be carried out solely by chemolithoautotrophic ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (AOB), represented by the genus <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic> spp., and the latter step by chemolithoautotrophic nitrite-oxidizing bacteria, represented by the genus <italic>Nitrobacter</italic>. However, recent evidence, reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C11">Hayatsu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref>, suggests that the process is much more complex, involving autotrophic Archaea nitrifiers, heterotrophic nitrifiers and anammox bacteria, which convert ammonium and nitrite into N gas under anaerobic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C19">Mulder <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>). Adding to this complexity is the potential for plants to stimulate or inhibit each of these groups specifically or as a whole.Numerous compounds that interfere with nitrification have been identified, but very few of these have been used successfully as synthetic nitrification inhibitors in agriculture and horticulture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C20">Slangen and Kerkhoff, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C28">Zerulla <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). The additional cost and variability in the effectiveness of synthetic inhibitors because of site-specific factors, such as soil type and weather conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C7">Goertz, 1994</xref>), have limited their wide adoption. Recent research suggests that plant root exudates can inhibit nitrification in soil, as shown for the tropical grass <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C22">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). This opens possibilities for using biological nitrification inhibition (BNI) as a low-cost <italic>in situ</italic> biological alternative. The BNI potential of root exudates has often been estimated by using a recombinant <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> strain (harbouring <italic>luxAB</italic> genes from <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic>) in a bioluminescence assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C13">Iizumi <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C14">Ishikawa <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). This methodology has been used extensively in characterizations of BNI-related processes, including the identification of putative specific inhibitor compounds in roots of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> and sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C8">Gopalakrishnan <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C27">Zakir <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C22">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).Biological nitrification inhibition has first been described in detail in <italic>B. humidicola</italic>; however, this is a rather minor crop that is typically grown with little or no application of N fertilizers. It is therefore highly desirable to identify BNI in a crop that (i) is of major importance, (ii) receives large amounts of N fertilizer and thus contributes significantly to the environmental problems associated with nitrification and subsequent N losses in leaching and denitrification, and (iii) lends itself to detailed physiological and genetic studies due to the availability of a variety of genetic stock and molecular tools.Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) is not only the most important food crop in the world and the biggest ‘consumer’ of N fertilizers in Asia, but also its N fertilizer use efficiency is rather low, often not exceeding 35 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C4">Dobermann <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). Equally important is the fact that rice has become the cereal model organism because of its relatively small genome size, the availability of several whole-genome sequences and relatively easy tools for genetic manipulation. If BNI activity could be detected in some rice genotypes, exploiting this novel biological function might be rapid with potential applications reaching beyond rice to other cereals. The objectives of this study, therefore, were to elucidate whether BNI activity is present in root exudates of rice, to further characterize this activity in contrasting genotypes and ultimately to confirm the inhibitory effect in soil.Seeds of rice genotypes were sterilized with a solution containing 2 % NaOCl and 150 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> for 5 min, rinsed with distilled water, and incubated at 30 °C. The germinated seeds were then transferred to a net floating system containing 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Subsequently, 14-day-old seedlings were grouped in bundles of three to five plants and transplanted into a solution culture box containing half-strength modified Yoshida solution (nutrient concentrations at full strength: N 2.86 mM (as NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>), P 0.05 mM, K 1 mM, Ca 1 mM, Mg 1 mM, Mn 9 µM, Mo 0.5 µM, B 18.5 µM, Cu 0.16 µM, Fe 36 µM and Zn 0.15 µM; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C26">Yoshida <italic>et al</italic>., 1976</xref>). After 10 days, the nutrient solution was changed to full strength. The pH was monitored regularly and adjusted to 5.5–5.8. In experiments with a long growth period, solutions were changed every 2 weeks.Plants were transferred from the culture solution containers to jars, where their roots were rinsed consecutively with distilled water and trap solution (1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl and 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>). Finally, the root mass was carefully immersed in a 1-L dark bottle containing trap solution for 24 h to collect root exudates. The pH was monitored every 8 h during the 24-h collection period and readjusted to 5.6 ± 0.2 with HCl or NaOH if necessary. After 24 h, the root and shoot tissue were saved for dry matter determination. The trap solution was evaporated to dryness using a rotary evaporator (Buchi, V-850, Switzerland) at 40 °C, then re-suspended in 100 % methanol and re-evaporated twice. Finally, the concentrated sample was suspended in 1.0 mL of 100 % methanol and passed through a syringe-driven 0.22 µm membrane filter (Millex, Millipore, USA). The filtrate was completely evaporated in a centrifuge evaporator, re-suspended in 50 or 100 µL of dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and 2 µL used in the BNI bioassay. Controls for the trap solution were subjected to the same procedure as for the sample (drying and dissolving in DMSO).The BNI was assessed using a recombinant <italic>N. europaea</italic> strain that carries a luciferase gene (<italic>luxAB</italic> derived from <italic>V. harveyi)</italic> and a <italic>Kan</italic> resistance gene that enables the growth of pure cells on media containing the antibiotic kanamycin. The recombinant strain produces bioluminescence under normal growing conditions due to expression of the <italic>luxAB</italic> gene. Reduced bioluminescence in whole cells that are challenged with known nitrification inhibitors and toxic compounds is possibly caused by the immediate decrease in reducing power in the cell due to the inactivation of ammonia monooxygenase, as well as by the interruption of other cellular metabolic pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C13">Iizumi <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>).<italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> was cultured in a mineral medium (referred to as P medium) with the following composition (in g L<sup>−1</sup>): (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> 2.5, KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> 0.7, Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> 13.5, NaHCO<sub>3</sub> 0.5 and MgSO<sub>4</sub>·7H<sub>2</sub>O 0.1, and (in mg L<sup>−1</sup>) CaCl·2H<sub>2</sub>O 0.005, Fe-EDTA 0.001 and kanamycin 0.025. After a 7-day culture period at 30 °C in dark conditions, cells were harvested by centrifugation, re-suspended in fresh P medium and adjusted to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 1.3–1.4 in a spectrophotometer (SmartSpec Plus, BioRad).In the bioassay, a mixture of 200 µL of bacterial cells, 2 µL of sample (root exudates dissolved in DMSO), 198 µL of distilled water and 100 µL of P medium was incubated at 25 °C for 30 min. A 100-µL aliquot of the mixture was added to tubes containing 2.5 µL of 10 % (v/v) <italic>n</italic>-decyl aldehyde, and the bioluminescence (light-emitting reaction of luciferase) of each sample was then measured using a Gloma 20/20 luminometer (Promega, USA). Four relative light unit (RLU) readings were obtained for each sample. Each sample had three independent replications. Biological nitrification inhibition activity in samples was compared with that of DMSO (the organic solvent used in sample preparation) and of the synthetic nitrification inhibitor allylthiourea (AT, at 0.22 µM), which causes around 80 % relative inhibition in the bioassay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C23">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>).Thirty-six genotypes of rice (including wild relatives, traditional and cultivated) were screened for their nitrification inhibition (NI) potential (Experiment 1) in two consecutive years. Some background information on the 36 genotypes is given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/plq014/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Additional information Table S1</ext-link>.Plants were cultivated hydroponically for 60 days in a greenhouse with three independent replicates per genotype. Root exudate collection and processing, and BNI estimation based on the bioassay were carried out as described in general experimental procedures. Subsequent experiments tested the effect of plant age and trap solution composition (1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl and 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) on BNI activity in root exudates. Seedlings were grown for 21, 28, 35, 50 or 70 days, and exudates collected for 24 h (Experiment 2).In Experiment 3, seedlings were grown for 28 and 35 days, and root exudates were collected in trap solutions containing either NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> or NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> (1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl or 1 mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, both with 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>). The effects of plant age and trap solution on BNI activity were then determined by the BNI bioassay as described above.In Experiment 4, the relationship between potential unspecific leakage and BNI was determined as affected by genotype (IAC25 vs. Nipponbare) and trap solution (1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 1 mM KNO<sub>3</sub> or distilled H<sub>2</sub>O). Plants were grown for 30 days and the pH during exudate collection was controlled at 5.5 ± 0.1 using a pH stat system (NPH-660 NDE, Nissin, Japan). Root exudates were collected in a 3-L trap solution. One half of the total volume was evaporated to dryness and used for the BNI bioassay, while the other half was concentrated 100-fold (from 1.5 L to 15 mL) using rotary evaporators. At 100-fold concentration, no visible precipitation was detected in the sample.To detect unspecific leakage, the composition of root exudates was analysed for the presence of low-molecular-weight organic acids (LMWOAs) and inorganic ions, and for electrical conductivity (EC). Malate and citrate were chosen as representatives for unspecific leakage of organic acids, and their concentration was measured following the protocol of the malate and citrate enzymatic bioanalysis (r-biopharma, Roche). Inorganic ion composition of root exudates was analysed by an inductively coupled plasma emission spectrometer (ICPE-9000, Shimadzu, Japan). The ion composition was first examined qualitatively to determine which ions were detectable, and then quantitatively to quantify their variation. Several ions were detected; however, as Ca, K and Na were part of the trap solution, only Mg was included in the result. Calibration curves were prepared in agreement with the estimated amount for each detected ion using ICPE standards (Wako Chemical, Japan).Relative electrolyte leakage (REL) was determined as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C24">Tripathy <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref> with some modifications. In brief, REL = (EC of trap solution after 24 h collection − initial EC from trap solution)/EC maximum (EC of autoclaved tissue: 120 °C for 20 min). Electrical conductivity values were measured using a hand-held EC meter (Yokogawa, Japan).Two soils were used in this experiment. A brown lowland soil was collected in Saitama Prefecture, Japan, whereas the second soil was collected in central Italy (Lazio region). The properties of soils were as follows: for the Saitama soil, pH (H<sub>2</sub>O) 5.6, EC 148 µS cm<sup>−1</sup>, total C 0.95 %, total N 0.7 %, clay 12 %, silt 26 % and sand 63 %; and for the Lazio soil, pH (H<sub>2</sub>O) 6.3, EC 183 µS cm<sup>−1</sup>, total C 0.8 %, total N 0.9 %, clay 28 %, silt 60 % and sand 12 %.The net nitrification rate of the brown lowland soil was determined using an aerobic incubation procedure. Five grams of soil were placed in a 50-mL centrifuge tube and concentrated root exudates from Experiment 4 were added (1.2 mL) in conjunction with distilled water (0.3 mL) containing (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (in a final concentration of 120 mg N kg<sup>−1</sup> of soil) in order to reach 60 % of the water-holding capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C18">Mosier <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>).During collection of the root exudates, the pH of the trap solution was maintained at a constant level around 5.5 by a pH stat controller; thus the pH of the concentrated extract (compared with the original) did not change significantly. However, the EC of the exudate solution increased significantly from an original value of 0.2 to 1.2 mS cm<sup>−1</sup> after concentration. Therefore, solutions with EC values (based on NaCl) similar to that of the samples were used as a control for the EC effect. The initial soil weight was recorded and water loss was monitored by weight difference and readjusted by adding distilled water. Finally, the tubes were covered with perforated parafilm and incubated at 30 °C for different periods (referred to as standard incubation). Samples were extracted for each time point with 2 M KCl (soil:solution ratio 1:10). The soil–KCl solution was shaken for 1 h followed by filtration through filter paper, and the extracts were measured for NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> using a continuous-flow auto-analyser (model Autoanalyzer 2; Bran + Lubbe, Hamburg, Germany).The shaken slurry method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C10">Hart <italic>et al</italic>. (1994)</xref> was used to measure nitrification in soil amended with exudates. We used this procedure to test the activity of nitrifying bacteria in soil after root exudates were added. Ten grams of fresh soil were mixed with 98.5 mL of a buffer solution and 1.5 mL of concentrated exudates in a 250-mL Erlenmeyer flask to make slurry. One hundred millilitres of buffer solution without exudates were used as a control. In all treatments, the final concentration of buffer solution was 1.5 mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and 1 mM PO<sub>4</sub><sup>3−</sup>. Slurry was shaken on an orbital shaker at 180 r.p.m. to maintain aerobic conditions. After 2, 6 and 24 h, an aliquot of 10 mL was taken from each flask, centrifuged for 5 min at 10 000 r.p.m. and then analysed for NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> as described above. The assay was replicated three times. This procedure was carried out using both the Saitama brown lowland soil and the Lazio soil; however, potential nitrification was much lower than expected based on standard incubation experiments done with Saitama brown lowland soil (see above), and results are therefore only reported for the Lazio soil. Probably, the pH of the incubation buffer was not suitable for the Saitama soil (pH 5.6), causing inhibition of the nitrifying bacteria activity.Seeds of the two genotypes were sown in small pots containing brown lowland soil (350 g). Previously, the soil was supplied with 120 mg N kg<sup>−1</sup> as (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. There were three plants per pot and each treatment had five independent replications. Watering was done conservatively to avoid anaerobiosis throughout the growth period. After a 40-day growth period, the root system of plants had penetrated the entire soil volume in the container and the experiment was terminated. Soil from the top and external side of the block was removed and discarded, and the remaining block soil was then stripped off from the root, referred to as rhizosphere soil. Root tissue was also collected and the dry matter recorded. Subsequently, soil was incubated using the standard incubation procedure as described above, but without the addition of concentrated root exudates.Data were analysed by ANOVA and mean values were compared using the least significance test (LSD). Experiments for genotype screening and characterization had three replications, while soil incubation had five independent replications.<bold>Biological nitrification inhibition activity in the root exudates of rice genotypes expressed as a percentage of NI (Experiment 1).</bold> Data correspond to the average of three independent replicates for two consecutive years as described in Materials and methods. Four consecutive readings were taken for each replicate. The dashed line indicates significant differences of the genotypes from the blank (LSD at <italic>P</italic>≤ 0.05).Wild relatives of cultivated <italic>O. sativa</italic> were present with three accessions (one each of <italic>O. nivara</italic>, <italic>O. brachyanta</italic> and <italic>O. glumaepatula</italic>), but none showed particularly high BNI activity. Several genotypes with known high allelopathic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C5">Fujii <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>) were included in the screening to test whether allelopathy and BNI are related. Although some allelopathic genotypes such as Awa-Akamai and Midori-mai (both ancient Japanese rice cultivars) showed high BNI activity, others such as Soujya Akamai and Dular had average activity. In general, the degree of variability for bioassay results was rather high among replications. One of the most stable genotypes in this regard was IAC25 and as it also showed the highest overall BNI activity, this Brazilian improved upland cultivar was chosen for further experiments. As contrasting genotypes with low BNI activity, we selected Nipponbare for the availability of its genome sequence and IR64 since it is probably the most widely grown rice cultivar.Average BNI activity in four experiments conducted with rice material of different plant ages (Experiment 2)<sup>a</sup>AT unit refers to 80 % relative inhibition in the NI bioassay caused by AT (at 0.22 µM), as explained in Materials and methods.<sup>b</sup>Values in parentheses represent standard deviation.Effect of two different ages (28 and 35 days old) and two trap solutions (1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl or 1 mM KNO<sub>3</sub>) on NI. Inhibition was measured based on NI bioassay (Experiment 3)<sup>a</sup>Based on the relative bioluminescence rate of sample and control, as explained in Materials and methods.** refers to significance at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.01.Effect of trap solution on the NI activity, LMWOAs and ion concentration of root exudates of two rice genotypes after 24 h collection (Experiment 4)<sup>a</sup>Significant difference between genotype means (<italic>n</italic> = 3) within trap solution, based on LSD. * and ** refer to significance at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 and 0.01, respectively.<sup>b</sup>Significant difference for the comparison of trap solution means across genotypes, based on LSD. * and ** refer to significance at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 and 0.01, respectively.<sup>c</sup>REL: relative electrolyte leakage refers to the relative variation of EC during exudate collection divided by the maximum EC (EC of autoclaved tissue).Correlation coefficients for the association between NI and REL (%), and leakage of malate, citrate and Mg (Experiment 4)*Significant at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05.<bold>Proportion of total N in nitrate form in soil samples incubated for 7 and 35 days (Experiment 5).</bold> Soil samples had been mixed with root exudates of rice genotype IAC25 or with NaCl solutions of different ionic strength. Values at <italic>t</italic> = 0 refer to the initial nitrate percentage in the soil before addition of exudates/solutions. Different letters indicate significant differences within sampling times (LSD at <italic>P</italic>≤ 0.05).<bold>Nitrate accumulated in soil incubated for several hours with root exudates of two rice genotypes (Experiment 5).</bold> Soil was incubated following the nitrification potential method. Control refers to soil incubated without exudates. Different letters indicate significant differences within sampling times (LSD at <italic>P</italic>≤ 0.05).<bold>Percent of total N in nitrate form in rhizosphere soil of two rice genotypes after incubation for 7 and 14 days (Experiment 5).</bold> The initial nitrate in the untreated soil was 20 % (as indicated in Fig. 2). Different letters indicate significant differences within sampling time (LSD at <italic>P</italic>≤ 0.05).Recently, Subbarao and co-workers identified potential BNI in the root exudates of a number of plant species using a bioassaytargeting <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C23">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Subsequent studies demonstrated the potential for the pasture grass <italic>B. humidicola</italic> to inhibit nitrification on a significant scale under field conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C22">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). In our study using rice, the screening of a broad range of genotypes for their NI activity using the <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic> bioassay resulted in the identification of genotypes with contrasting BNI activity in their root exudates. Higher BNI activity was more likely to be found in traditional and/or upland varieties, whereas modern high-yielding lowland varieties such as IR64 or Nipponbare tended to have lower activity.No compelling evidence was found to support the hypothesis that BNI is a non-specific allelopathy phenomenon, as not all genotypes of known high allelopathy potential (red rice) were superior to other cultivars in BNI. However, little is known of the allelopathy potential of many of the varieties tested, including the best performing genotype, IAC25, and it is therefore difficult to reach any definite conclusion on this topic without additional experiments evaluating the allelopathy of IAC25 and others. Subsequent experiments on a subset of genotypes differing in BNI activity further characterized their potential under various conditions. More mature plants showed lower BNI per root weight than young plants, indicating that BNI is influenced by plant growth stage, as reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C27">Zakir <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref> for sorghum. This trend is likely to reflect a relative decrease in the proportion of physiologically active root tissue in maturing root systems. It therefore appears likely that the release of BNI substances from roots continues throughout the plant growth stages studied here.In order to treat BNI as a plant-induced process, it is important to confirm that the activity seen in exudates of rice is not simply the result of non-specific leakage. The negative correlation of BNI with REL observed in this study is a first indication that the BNI induced by rice is not a consequence of arbitrary leakage. However, the direct inhibition of <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic> by high salt concentrations in the trap solution could confound the interpretation of these results. We have tried to adjust EC values for the amount of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> or NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> remaining in the trap solution after the 24 h collection period, but have not been able to account for any increase in EC contributed by companion ions or ions exuded to maintain charge balances upon uptake of respective N forms. A more reliable estimate for the presence of leakage may therefore be any unusually high concentration of the LMWOAs malate and citrate. Both were detected in the exudates of IAC25 and other genotypes, but at concentrations considered normal or low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C12">Hoffland <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C25">Widodo <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, genotypic differences for LMWOA concentrations as well as correlations between BNI and malate and citrate were not significant. The same was observed for concentrations of Mg, a cation that had not been supplied in the trap solution and may therefore be an additional indicator of leakage. It can thus be concluded that the BNI activity detected here was not the result of unspecific leakage.An important aspect of this study was the inclusion of soil incubation experiments to validate the preliminary screening of root exudates in the bioassay. A single application of concentrated root exudates to a brown lowland soil showed a transient inhibition of nitrification: BNI was apparent in soil 7 days after application of rice root exudates, but by 35 days there was no significant difference between the applications of exudates or control solutions. The decrease in BNI after 7 days may be due to the progressive degradation in BNI-related compounds by soil microorganisms. Therefore, it would be interesting to see whether continuous application of a lower concentration of root exudates has a sustained inhibitory effect.The BNI effect of exudates was confirmed using a slurry incubation experiment, where 1.5 mL of concentrated exudate also induced BNI, though only in Lazio soil. A more suitable buffer for Saitama soil would be necessary, as mentioned in Materials and methods. The trends regarding genotypic effects for BNI identified in the screening study were also apparent in rhizosphere soil, with nitrification being slower in rhizosphere soil collected from IAC25 compared with Nipponbare. At this point, the exact mechanisms by which rice root exudates inhibit nitrification are not known. In studies on BNI activity of <italic>B. humidicola</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C14">Ishikawa <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref> detected a decrease in AOB population size in an Andosol soil, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C9">Gopalakrishnan <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> found no differences in AOB counts. To shed more light on the effects of BNI in soil and whether other AOBs such as <italic>Nitrospira</italic> and <italic>Nitrosococcus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C11">Hayasu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>) are affected similarly to <italic>Nitrosomonas</italic>, it would be important to validate the effect of BNI exudates on AOB population sizes by molecular methods, particularly because AOBs are generally recalcitrant to cultivation in artificial medium.Nitrification rates in paddy soils are lower compared with typical upland soil due to the anaerobic soil environment, which largely restricts nitrification to the top soil layer and to parts of the rhizosphere where oxygen leakage from roots supports non-specific aerobic microbial processes, including nitrification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C2">Arth <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C3">Briones <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). Further reductions in nitrification may therefore not be necessary since NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> uptake by rice appears to be beneficial, particularly if high yields are to be attained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C16">Kronzucker <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Nevertheless, N losses due to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> leaching and denitrification remain a concern in paddy rice production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C1">Akiyama <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C15">Ju <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). This would indicate a need for optimization of nitrification rates, and BNI could represent one tool in achieving this. It should be stressed at this point that the target of BNI in rice would not be to completely eliminate nitrification, but ideally to achieve a balance between NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> supply via nitrification and plant NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> uptake. That NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> leaching can be reduced via application of synthetic nitrification inhibitors in lowland rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C17">Li <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>) suggests that an analogous biological inhibition of nitrification would also be beneficial to rice growers and the global environment.The overall aim was to establish whether BNI can be detected in rice at a sufficiently high level to warrant further studies that can take advantage of the molecular tools and genetic stock available for this cereal model crop. With specific BNI activities ranging from 13 to 65 AT units g<sup>−1</sup> root dry weight (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ014TB1">1</xref>), we have shown that some rice genotypes can have BNI activities that compare with <italic>B. humidicola</italic>, or sorghum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C27">Zakir <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>), even though reported peak activities were highest in <italic>B. humidicola</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ014C23">Subbarao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). That BNI activity could be confirmed in soil incubation studies further suggests that this phenomenon should be exploited further in rice. To identify compounds responsible for the BNI activity detected in rice exudates and to employ molecular methods to investigate whether such exudates specifically affect relative population size or activity of soil nitrifiers will be key next steps.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/plq014/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following additional information is available in the online version of this article.</ext-link>Table S1. Wild relative, traditional and cultivated geno- types of rice used for inhibition activity screening.P.N. was supported by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) postdoctoral fellowships.All the authors contributed to a similar extent overall.None declared.We thank Taro Matsuda for technical support.