 Interactive effects of elevated temperature and CO 2  on two phylogeographically distinct clones of common reed ( Phragmites australis )  Image processing with ImageJ  What have we learned from 15 years of free-air CO 2  enrichment (FACE)? A meta-analytic review of the responses of photosynthesis, canopy properties and plant production to rising CO 2   The response of photosynthesis and stomatal conductance to rising [CO 2 ]: mechanisms and environmental interactions  Is stimulation of leaf photosynthesis by elevated carbon dioxide concentration maintained in the long term? A test with  Lolium perenne  grown for 10 years at two nitrogen fertilization levels under Free Air CO 2  Enrichment (FACE)  Physiological and anatomical characterisation of  Phragmites australis  leaves  Thermal acclimation and the dynamic response of plant, respiration to temperature  CO 2  evolution during the last millennium as recorded by Antarctic and Greenland ice  Root system adjustments: regulation of plant nutrient uptake and growth responses to elevated CO 2   Growth of  Lythrum salicaria  and  Phragmites australis  plants originating from a wide geographical area: response to nutrient and water supply  Plasticity of  Lythrum salicaria  and  Phragmites australis  growth characteristics across a European geographical gradient  Photosynthetic response and adaptation to temperature in higher plants  Photon yield of O 2  evolution and chlorophyll fluorescence characteristics at 77K among vascular plants of diverse origins  Genetic diversity, ecophysiology and growth dynamics of reed ( Phragmites australis )—introduction  Effects of single and multifactor treatments with elevated temperature, CO 2  and ozone on oilseed rape and barley  An investigation into the effects of nitrogen on growth and morphology of stable and die-back populations of  Phragmites australis   Taxonomy, chromosome numbers, clonal diversity and population dynamics of  Phragmites australis   Geographic variation in growth responses in  Phragmites australis   Yield response of  Lolium perenne  swards to free air CO 2  enrichment increased over six years in a high N input system on fertile soil  Survey of thermal energy dissipation and pigment composition in sun and shade leaves  Different genotypes of  Phragmites australis  show distinct phenotypic plasticity in response to nutrient availability and temperature  Clone-specific differences in  Phragmites australis : effects of ploidy level and geographic origin  Photosynthesis-irradiance relationships in polar and temperate phytoplankton populations   Phragmites communis  Trin  Climate change 2007: the physical science basis  Effects of elevated CO 2  on below-ground processes in temperate marsh microcosms  Does enhanced photosynthesis enhance growth? Lessons learned from CO 2  enrichment studies  A phylogeographic study of the cosmopolitan genus  Phragmites  (Poaceae) based on AFLPs  Exploring the borders of European  Phragmites  within a cosmopolitan genus  Elevated CO 2  effects on plant carbon, nitrogen, and water relations: six important lessons from FACE  Combined effect of elevated CO 2  and temperature on the growth and phenology of two annual C 3  and C 4  weedy species  A global comparison of grassland biomass responses to CO 2  and nitrogen enrichment  Effect of climatic gradients on the photosynthetic responses of four  Phragmites australis  populations  Chlorophylls and carotenoids: pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes  Differences in pigment composition, photosynthetic rates and chlorophyll fluorescence images of sun and shade leaves of four tree species  Vascular plant responses to elevated CO 2  in a temperate lowland  Sphagnum  peatland  Interactions between increasing CO 2  concentration and temperature on plant growth  Issues and perspectives for investigating root responses to elevated atmospheric carbon-dioxide  Growth response of  Equisetum fluviatile  to elevated CO 2  and temperature  Sugar repression of photosynthesis: the role of carbohydrates in signalling nitrogen deficiency through source:sink imbalance  Interspecific variation in the growth response of plants to an elevated ambient CO 2  concentration  The growth response of plants to elevated CO 2  under non-optimal environmental conditions  Rapid light curves: a powerful tool to assess photosynthetic activity  Seventeen years of elevated CO 2  exposure in a Chesapeake Bay wetland: sustained but contrasting responses of plant growth and CO 2  uptake  Adaptation of pea to elevated atmospheric CO 2 : Rubisco, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase and chloroplast phosphate translocator at different levels of nitrogen and phosphorus nutrition  Cryptic invasion by a non-native genotype of the common reed,  Phragmites australis , into North America  Long-term acclimation of plants to elevated CO 2  and its interaction with stresses  Responses of wild C 4  and C 3  grass (Poaceae) species to elevated atmospheric CO 2  concentration: a meta-analytic test of current theories and perceptions  Integration of photosynthetic acclimation to CO 2  at the whole-plant level  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  One European and one Mediterranean  Phragmites australis  genotype (DK clone and ALG clone, respectively) showed distinct aboveground growth and physiology in response to different treatment combinations of elevated CO 2  and temperature according to their genetic background. The DK clone was the most responsive clone.  The aboveground growth, physiological and biochemical parameters of two clones of the cosmopolitan wetland grass  Phragmites australis,  grown at four treatment combinations of temperature and CO 2 , were investigated to elucidate whether their climate response differed due to inherent differences in their ecological adaptation. The two phylogeographically distinct  P. australis  clones (DK clone, European genetic background; ALG clone, Mediterranean genetic background) were grown for 151 days in phytotrons at 19/12 °C (day/night temperature) and 390 ppm CO 2 , and at elevated temperature (+5 °C) and CO 2  (700 ppm) with treatment factors alone or in combination. The ALG clone had 2–4 times higher aboveground biomass, higher light-saturated rates of photosynthesis ( P  max ), maximum electron transport rates (ETR max ) and Rubisco activity, and higher photosynthetic nitrogen-use efficiency than the DK clone. The DK clone, however, produced more shoots, leaves and side-shoots, and had 9–51 % higher specific leaf area and 15–39 % higher leaf nitrogen concentration than the ALG clone. Although elevated atmospheric CO 2  alone barely affected the aboveground growth of the two  P. australis  clones, simultaneously elevated temperature and CO 2  stimulated growth and aboveground biomass. Overall, elevated CO 2  stimulated photosynthesis, but the clones responded differently to a concomitant increase in CO 2  and temperature, depending on the phylogeographic background of the plant. The DK clone showed overall stronger responses, and can be considered the more plastic of the two clones with respect to CO 2  and temperature. Thus, the DK clone may be better adapted to climate change than the ALG clone, at least in the short term.  Temperature and atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) are key environmental parameters affecting plant growth, development and function, and both have changed in the recent past. The concentration of atmospheric CO 2  has increased from pre-industrial levels of ∼280 ppm to &gt;390 ppm and is predicted to increase further, possibly reaching 700 ppm by the end of the 21st century ( Barnola  et al.  1995 ;  IPCC 2007 ). Simultaneously, the global average surface temperature is predicted to increase by 0.6–4 °C compared with the beginning of this century ( IPCC 2007 ).  As CO 2  is a direct resource in the photosynthesis process, elevated CO 2  is predicted to stimulate plant growth under adequate nutrient supply ( Poorter 1993 ;  Wolfe  et al.  1998 ). However, the experimental evidence of this is inconclusive ( Ainsworth and Long 2005 ;  Rasse  et al.  2005 ;  Kirschbaum 2011 ). Long-term exposure of plants to elevated CO 2  has in some studies resulted in a stimulation of productivity and growth ( Wand  et al.  1999 ;  Lee  et al.  2010 ), but in other studies no significant effect has been observed ( Milla  et al.  2006 ;  Kim and Kang 2008 ). During long-term exposure to elevated CO 2 , leaf photosynthesis may be acclimated to the elevated CO 2  and hence not elevated, but even down-regulated. However, dependent on the carbon demand and growth capacity, the light-saturated rates of photosynthesis and carbon uptake have also been shown to be stimulated ( Ainsworth  et al.  2003 ;  Tuba and Lichtenthaler 2007 ). Temperature effects on plant growth can, however, be far more distinct than the effects of CO 2  ( Ojala  et al.  2002 ). Since the effects of CO 2  and temperature on photosynthesis and respiration may counteract each other, the combined effects may differ from those of either factor alone, especially for C 3  plants ( Morison and Lawlor 1999 ). As climate factors will change concomitantly, understanding their combined effects on a species is crucial for predicting future plant responses.  Wetland plants play a crucial role in ecosystem functioning. Therefore, understanding their responses to changed climate conditions is fundamental for predicting the consequences of global change in aquatic habitats. The common reed,  Phragmites australis  (Cav.) Trin. Ex Steud., is often the dominant plant species of wetland communities.  Phragmites australis  is a perennial, emergent wetland grass that has probably the widest geographical distribution of any flowering plant and is able to acclimate to a wide range of growth conditions ( Haslam 1972 ;  Clevering and Lissner 1999 ). It is found in oligotrophic as well as eutrophic habitats, waterlogged or flooded soils in freshwater and saline wetlands, playing an important role in lake shore protection, habitat provision and wastewater treatment ( Clevering 1998 ;  Brix 1999 ). Differences in ontogeny, shoot morphology, physiological and biochemical processes, and growth characteristics have been reported for several  P. australis  clones native to distinct geographical habitats ( Clevering  et al . 2001 ;  Lessmann  et al.  2001 ;  Bastlova  et al.  2004 ,  2006 ;  Hansen  et al.  2007 ;  Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). The species generally shows high phenotypic plasticity when introduced to an environment distinct from its natural habitat ( Lessmann  et al.  2001 ) and even appears as a vigorous invader, as seen in North America, where an aggressive lineage has invaded salt marshes along coastal New England, threatening marsh habitat quality for wildlife ( Saltonstall 2002 ). Acclimation and plasticity in response to changing environments and climate indicate a high potential of  P. australis  to sustain its fitness under future climate change scenarios. However, it is unknown how growth and photosynthesis of distinct  P. australis  clones are responding to future climate change scenarios, i.e. the simultaneously elevated atmospheric CO 2  concentration and temperature.  The aim of this study was to assess the effects of elevated temperature and CO 2  alone and in combination on aboveground growth, physiological and biochemical parameters of two contrasting  P. australis  clones. The clones originated from two different phylogeographic lineages, namely the European temperate  P. australis  gene pool and the Mediterranean gene pool ( Lambertini  et al.  2006 ,  2012 ). The two lineages were shown to be genetically distinct in the aforementioned studies, and their confined latitudinal distribution ranges suggest different ecological adaptations. Therefore, the two clones may respond distinctly to climate change and the single climate factors may affect each clone in a dissimilar manner. We hypothesized that the two clones would respond differently to temperature and CO 2  due to their inherent differences in ecological adaptation. Moreover, since  P. australis  has a strong carbon sink capacity, i.e. a large carbon uptake capability due to its large vegetative biomass production and development of tillers and side-shoots, we hypothesized that elevated CO 2  would stimulate plant growth under non-limiting nutrient conditions.  The response of two clones of common reed ( P. australis ) to elevated temperature (+5 °C) and elevated CO 2  (700 ppm) was studied in a phytotron system with treatment factors operating separately or in combination. The treatments were set up in four physically and electronically separated gas-tight walk-in chambers (6 m width, 4 m length, 3.1 m height) of the climate phytotron Risø Environmental Risk Assessment Facility (RERAF, DTU, Denmark).  Each of the chambers was equipped with separate ventilation systems and individual control of light, temperature, humidity and CO 2 . Two fans mounted on opposite sides in each chamber ensured air mixing. A 16/8-h day/night light regime was provided by high-pressure mercury and halogen lamps supporting the natural sunlight entering through the transparent glass roof and outside wall, resulting in a daytime irradiance of ∼400–600 µmol m −2  s −1  (photosynthetic photon flux density, PPFD) at the base of the plant pots. Sunrise and sunset were simulated during the first and last hour of the day-light regime by a gradual change in the light intensity. The relative air humidity (RH) was controlled at 65/80 % (day/night).  The four treatment combinations were (i) ‘Ambient’, (ii) ‘Temp’ (elevated temperature, +5 °C), (iii) ‘CO 2 ’ (elevated [CO 2 ], ∼700 ppm) and (iv) ‘Temp + CO 2 ’ (elevated temperature and CO 2 ). The ‘Ambient’ treatment, which served as a control, simulated present Northern European early summer season conditions with 19/12 °C day/night temperatures and ∼390 ppm CO 2 . The measured concentrations of CO 2  in the growth chambers were slightly above the intended set-point levels in the ‘Ambient’ and ‘Temp’ treatments, especially during the night. This may be a consequence of negligibly increased respiration from the plants and soil.  The two clones used in this study were chosen from a large collection of live  P. australis  clones, kept in a common environment at Aarhus University, Denmark (56°13′N; 10°07′E), for at least 6 years prior to this study. A clone from a coastal stand close to Aarhus, Denmark (56°12′N; 10°29′E) (DK clone) and a clone from an oasis in the Sahara desert close to Guebbour, Algeria (28°29′N; 6°41′E) (ALG clone) were chosen for this study. The two clones were selected based on their phylogeographic relationship. The DK clone possesses the alleles of European temperate  P. australis , whereas the ALG clone belongs to the Mediterranean gene pool of  P. australis . The two phylogeographic groups within  P. australis  were identified by amplified fragment length polymorphisms ( Lambertini  et al.  2006 ) and chloroplast DNA sequences ( Lambertini  et al.  2012 ) and described as temperate European and Mediterranean  Phragmites  ( Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). The Mediterranean  Phragmites  extends in its distribution throughout Southern Europe, North Africa and the Middle East. Differences between the two clones are therefore driven by different evolutionary pressures in their native distribution ranges.  Clones were propagated by layering of shoots horizontally in water for 35 days to initiate adventitious shoot growth at the stem nodes. When adventitious shoots were 150–200 mm tall and had developed roots, the stems were cut at both sides of the nodes and the resulting replicate plants planted in 3.5-L pots containing a commercial peat. The plants were then acclimated for 3 weeks in one of the growth chambers at the ‘Ambient’ treatment conditions, as described above. Plants were fertilized weekly with 0.5 L of a nutrient solution containing a commercial fertilizer with N–P–K values of 6–1–5 (Substral ® ; The Scotts Company, Nordics A/S, Glostrup, Denmark). Additional micronutrients were added to the nutrient solution from a micronutrient stock solution (Pioner Mikro Plus with Fe; Brøste, Lyngby, Denmark) in concentrations of (in µM) 0.02 B; 2.2 Cu; 24 Fe; 9.1 Mn; 0.5 Mo; 2.8 Zn. Additional iron (Fe 2+ ) was added to the nutrient solution as Fe(II)SO 4  (∼0.59 mM) right before every fertilization. Between fertilizations, the plants were watered with tap water. Tables holding the plants were rotated within the growth chambers weekly and between the chambers bi-weekly, to avoid undesired chamber effects.  The experimental set-up was a 2 × 2 × 2 factorial design with the factors being clone (DK vs. ALG), temperature (19/12 vs. 24/17 °C) and CO 2  concentration (390 vs. 700 ppm). Ten replicates of each clone were used in each of the four treatments ( n  = 10 for all measured parameters). One replicate of the DK clone in the ‘Temp’ treatment died and hence was removed from all statistical analyses ( n  = 9 for all parameters from the ‘Temp’ treatment, DK clone). The experiment was run for 151 days after the initial acclimatization period.  Numbers of shoots and leaves per plant were counted at the start of the experiment (Day 0) and after 52 days when the aboveground biomass was harvested. The number of leaves per plant included all fully developed leaves. Absolute shoot and leaf production rates were determined as the difference between the final and the initial number of shoots and leaves, respectively, divided by the growth time (52 days). The cumulative length of all shoots per plant was measured at harvest, and the number of side-shoots developed at the shoot nodes was counted. All plant fractions were dried to a constant dry mass at 80 °C in a ventilated oven to determine the final aboveground biomass. The pots with the cut stems containing the roots and rhizomes were kept in the treatment chambers for an additional period of 99 days, and were watered and fertilized as described above. The new shoots that developed from the rhizome system were used for photosynthetic measurements after 95–99 days of re-growth.  Photosynthesis of the third or fourth youngest leaf of one shoot per replicate was measured with an ADC LCA-4 infrared gas analyser (IRGA) equipped with a Leaf Microclimate Control System (ADC BioScientific Ltd, Hoddesdon, UK). The leaf chamber was air-conditioned at the respective growth temperature and placed on a tripod to ensure stability during readings. The leaf chamber was supplied with air from inside the growth chamber drawn from a height of 3 m above the floor at a flow rate of 300 µmol s −1  by the built-in air pump of the IRGA. Light was supplied from a white halogen source (Portable Light Unit, PLU-002, ADC BioScientific Ltd, Hoddesdon, UK) at an irradiance (PPFD) of ∼1800 µmol m −2  s −1 . The maximum light-saturated rate of photosynthesis ( P  max ) was estimated as the average of five readings that were logged after a stable CO 2  assimilation rate was reached.  The third or fourth youngest leaf, which was also used for measurement of photosynthesis, was photocopied and the area determined by ImageJ v. 1.43, a Java-based image analysis software ( Abramoff  et al.  2004 ). The dry mass after lyophilization of the leaf that had been photocopied was determined prior to pigment analysis, and used to calculate the specific leaf area (SLA; the ratio of leaf area to leaf dry mass). Concentrations of total chlorophylls (Chl a  and Chl b ) and total carotenoids (xanthophylls and carotenes; C (x+c) ) of the same leaf used for photosynthesis and SLA measurement were analysed by photospectrometry after extraction in 96 % ethanol according to  Lichtenthaler (1987) .  Total carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) were analysed for 1.5–3.5 mg of ground leaf material with a CHN analyser (Fisons Instruments, Model NA2000, Rodano, MI, Italy) and expressed on a % dry mass basis. Photosynthetic nitrogen-use efficiency (PNUE) was calculated as the ratio of  P  max  to leaf N concentration.  Total activity of ribulose-1.5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco) was analysed in the third or fourth youngest leaves of two or three shoots of the same age in each replicate (all leaves from the chosen shoots pooled from each replicate plant). Entire leaves were cut in the light and frozen immediately in liquid nitrogen. The frozen plant material was ground in a mortar containing liquid nitrogen. Approximately 0.1 g of homogenate was further ground in a chilled mortar with 5 mL of extraction buffer containing 50 mM bicine (pH 8), 0.1 mM EDTA-Na 2 , 10 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 10 mM isoascorbate and 2 % (w/v) polyvinylpyrrolidone. Rubisco activity was determined in an assay solution consisting of 50 mM bicine (pH 8), 0.1 mM EDTA-Na 2 , 10 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM DTT and 19.25 mM NaH 14 CO 3 . After the addition of ground extract, vials were incubated for 5 min before activation with 0.5 mM RuDP (ribulose 1,5-diphosphate). The reaction was stopped after 60 s with 6 M HCl. All reactions were carried out at 17 °C in a total volume of 500 µL using 6-mL vials. Samples were dried at 60 °C for 24 h and afterwards re-dissolved in two drops of 6 M KOH and 1.2 mL of ultrafiltered water. The amount of radioactive decay energy was measured by liquid scintillation counting (Liquid Scintillation Analyzer, Tri-CARB 2100 TR; Packard, Meriden, CT, USA). The concentration of Chl (a+b)  in the extract was analysed using 96 % ethanol (µg Chl (a+b)  mL −1  ground extract) and used together with SLA to convert the Rubisco activity to a leaf area basis.  Data were analysed by the General Linear Model procedure using Type III sum of squares with the software Statgraphics Centurion XVI (Statpoint Technologies, Inc., Warrenton, VA, USA). Data were tested for variance homogeneity using Levene's test and, if necessary, log-transformed to ensure homogeneity of variances. The third-order interaction term was suppressed.  A rotated factor analysis was conducted on all results. The number of factors was restricted to three, and the factor scores after Varimax rotation were used for interpretation of the data variability.   Summary of three-way ANOVA (F-ratios; d.f. total=78) showing the effects of clone (ALG vs. DK), temperature (19/12 vs. 24/17 °C) and CO 2  (390 vs. 700 ppm), and their interactions on growth and physiological parameters of two  P. australis  clones.   P  max , maximum light-saturated rate of photosynthesis;  F  v / F  m , potential quantum yield of PS II;  α , effective quantum yield; ETR max , maximum rate of electron transport; SLA, specific leaf area; C (x+c) , total carotenoids; C (a+b) /C (x+c) , ratio of chlorophyll a and b to total carotenoids; PNUE, photosynthetic nitrogen-use efficiency; d.f., degrees of freedom. Significance level (in bold): * P  &lt; 0.05; ** P  &lt; 0.01; *** P  &lt; 0.001.  Mean (±S.E.) final aboveground biomass (A), cumulative shoot length (B), shoot production rate (C), leaf production rate (D), final number of side-shoots (E) and leaf dry mass content (F) of two distinct  P. australis  clones (DK clone and ALG clone) grown at four different treatments (‘Ambient’; ‘Temp’, elevated temperature, +5 °C; ‘CO 2 ’, elevated CO 2 , ∼700 ppm; ‘Temp + CO 2 ’, elevated CO 2  and temperature +5 °C).  The CO 2  concentration did not affect any growth or biomass parameter, except for the leaf dry mass content, which was higher at elevated CO 2 . The leaf dry mass content was also affected by a clone × temperature interaction, as the ALG clone had 5–26 % higher leaf dry mass content at elevated temperature, compared with ambient temperature (Fig.  1 F).   Photosynthetic parameters (mean values ± S.E.) of two distinct  P. australis  clones grown at different CO 2  concentration and temperature treatments.  The four treatments were ‘Ambient’; ‘Temp’, elevated temperature; ‘CO 2 ’, elevated CO 2 ; ‘Temp + CO 2 ’, elevated temperature and CO 2 .  The SLA, PNUE, photosynthetic pigments, leaf N and C concentration (mean values ± S.E.) of two distinct  P. australis  clones grown at the different CO 2  concentration and temperature treatments.  Mean (±S.E.) chlorophyll concentrations (Chl a  and Chl b ) in leaves of two distinct  P. australis  clones (DK clone and ALG clone) grown at the four different treatments.  The DK clone had 15–39 % higher leaf N concentration than the ALG clone, but the ALG clone contained more carbon (3–6 %) than the DK clone (Table  3 ). Plants had 19–23 and 11–33 % (ALG clone and DK clone, respectively) higher N concentration at ambient temperature compared with elevated temperature. The carbon concentration of both clones was affected by a CO 2  × temperature interaction. When grown at elevated temperature, both clones had higher C concentration at ambient CO 2 . At ambient temperature, elevated CO 2  resulted in higher C concentrations.  The ALG clone had up to three times higher PNUE than the DK clone, but the DK clone showed the strongest CO 2  response by having 28–349 % higher PNUE at elevated CO 2 , as opposed to the ALG clone (23–57 %; clone × CO 2  interaction). Also the PNUE was affected by a CO 2  × temperature interaction, as the response of PNUE to CO 2  mostly occurred at elevated temperature, with the PNUE being highest at elevated CO 2 .  Factor loadings for Varimax-rotated factor analysis of measured parameters of two distinct  P. australis  clones grown at different CO 2  concentration and temperature treatments. a    a Variables with high loadings are shown in bold.   Factor scores of Factor 1 against Factor 2 (A) and Factor 1 against Factor 3 (B) of a rotated factor analysis of two distinct  P. australis  clones (DK clone and ALG clone) grown at the four different treatments.  Factor 1 has high loadings for shoot growth, photosynthesis and leaf C content; Factor 2 has high loadings for pigments, Rubisco activity and yield  α ; Factor 3 has high loadings for the final aboveground biomass and cumulative shoot length, leaf N concentration and C (a+b) /C (x+c) .  The aim of this study was to evaluate to what extent two phylogeographically distinct clones of  P. australis  respond to elevated temperature and CO 2  concentration, as single abiotic factors or in combination. We hypothesized that the two clones would respond differently to a change in these climatic parameters, due to their genetically inherent differences in adaptation to distinct climatic origins.  It has been postulated that the genetic variation in  P. australis  has arisen in response to the latitude of its geographical origin ( Clevering  et al.  2001 ;  Lessmann  et al.  2001 ;  Bastlova  et al.  2004 ).  Clevering  et al.  (2001)  showed that  P. australis  originating from higher latitudes, such as the DK clone, developed a higher number of shoots and leaves, and larger SLA compared with genotypes from lower latitudes, such as the ALG clone. In the present study, the DK clone and the ALG clone not only differed in most plant traits measured, but also responded differently to CO 2  and temperature for many of the parameters, as was hypothesized. The ALG clone had the highest aboveground biomass development but the aboveground biomass of the DK clone increased more than that of the ALG clone in response to elevated temperature. Temperature affected the Chl a/b ratio as well as C (a+b) /C (x+c)  more in the DK clone than in the ALG clone, which is visualized in the factor analysis (Fig.  3 A). The DK clone also demonstrated a stronger response to elevated CO 2  with increased PNUE,  α  and  F  v / F  m , whereas the ALG clone only responded to elevated CO 2  with a lower SLA, as shown in the ANOVA interactions. Hence, the DK clone showed an overall stronger response to future climate change factors than the ALG clone and can therefore be considered the more plastic of the two clones with respect to atmospheric CO 2  and temperature. Higher phenotypic plasticity of the DK clone with respect to temperature has been shown previously, when compared with the ALG clone ( Eller and Brix 2012 ).  An often observed response to CO 2  enrichment is acclimation of the initial stimulation of photosynthesis and down-regulation of the Rubisco activity due to feedback inhibition caused by the accumulation of carbohydrates ( Paul and Driscoll 1997 ). In C 3  plants, the acclimation of the photosynthetic capacity to elevated CO 2  after long-term exposure is often seen as a decrease in the maximum carboxylation rate of Rubisco ( V  cmax ) and the ETR max . However, despite this down-regulation of the photosynthetic capacity, the net carbon uptake can be enhanced by elevated CO 2  ( Leakey  et al.  2009 ). Contrary to the growth and aboveground biomass parameters in the present study, most of the analysed photosynthetic parameters and pigments, as well as the PNUE and C content, were affected by CO 2  or interactions of CO 2  with either clone or temperature. This physiological response to CO 2  could be expected, since  P. australis  generally uses the C 3  photosynthetic pathway ( Antonielli  et al.  2002 ), where carbon uptake is saturated at a much higher internal CO 2  concentration than in C 4  plants, for which elevated atmospheric CO 2  has no direct effect on carbon uptake under favourable conditions ( Leakey  et al.  2009 ). At ambient temperature, the two  P. australis  clones showed higher Rubisco activities at elevated CO 2  compared with ambient CO 2  concentration. Plants with Rubisco-limited photosynthetic capacity, such as the plants in this study, have a larger potential for CO 2  stimulation of photosynthesis because the increased CO 2  both increases Rubisco carboxylation rates and depresses photorespiration ( Ainsworth and Rogers 2007 ). Since no down-regulation of Rubisco activity, ETR max  or  α  was observed in our study, photosynthesis of the two clones did not acclimate to the increased CO 2  concentration. A possible reason for this is that the plants in the present study had sufficient nutrients. Acclimation of photosynthesis has been reported to be more marked in nitrogen-limited plants exposed to elevated CO 2  ( Riviere-Rolland  et al.  1996 ). This may be due to nitrogen allocation away from Rubisco, mainly towards root growth to increase nutrient acquisition ( Wolfe  et al.  1998 ).  Contrary to our expectations, we did not observe any increase in the aboveground biomass or the other measured growth parameters of the two clones grown at elevated CO 2  in the present study, despite the fact that  P  max ,  α , Rubisco activity and PNUE were stimulated in the ‘CO 2 ’ treatment.  Kirschbaum (2011)  pointed out that an increase in photosynthesis will not necessarily lead to an equivalent enhancement in growth, but that the potentially gained carbon may be utilized differently. The transformation of photosynthetic carbon gain into aboveground growth might be inefficient due to a lack of shoot sink capacity (i.e. tissues that can incorporate the excess carbon) and the influence of other limiting factors, such as a shortage of water, nutrient or light. In the present study, only aboveground biomass was investigated. The general observation from studies on root growth under elevated CO 2  is that root growth is stimulated, resulting in an increase in the root to shoot ratio ( Norby 1994 ;  BassiriRad  et al.  2001 ). Since we did not quantify the belowground biomass, it cannot be ruled out that elevated CO 2  in the present experiment had a stimulating effect on root growth or that a surplus of assimilated carbon was stored in rhizomes. Under field conditions, overwintering rhizomes serve as carbon storage to support shoot growth in the following spring. This might lead to an underestimation of the response to elevated CO 2  in short-term experiments ( Norby 1994 ). The lack of an aboveground biomass response to elevated CO 2  in the ‘CO 2 ’ treatment observed in the present study cannot be explained by insufficient fertilization, since plants in the ‘Temp + CO 2 ’ treatment reached a higher biomass under the same nutrient availability.  Enhanced growth of shoot biomass ( Daepp  et al.  2000 ;  Rasse  et al.  2005 ) as well as total plant biomass ( Wand  et al.  1999 ;  Poorter and Perez-Soba 2001 ) has often been observed in plants grown at elevated CO 2 , especially C 3  plants, at least in the short term and at non-limiting nutrient conditions. However, for the  P. australis  clones, investigated here it was only in combination with higher growth temperature that elevated CO 2  resulted in increased aboveground biomass. In the ‘Temp + CO 2 ’ treatment, the increased availability of respiratory substrates and increased enzyme capacity due to the elevated temperature presumably resulted in higher respiration rates, which in combination with the higher rates of photosynthesis could result in higher growth rates ( Atkin and Tjoelker 2003 ).  In the present study, the two  P. australis  clones responded differently to growth temperature with respect to final aboveground biomass, with the DK clone being more responsive to temperature than the ALG clone. Plant species with a large geographic distribution, such as  P. australis , may have different optimum temperatures and acclimation potentials ( Berry and Björkman 1980 ). The low  P  max ,  α , ETR max  and Rubisco activity of the two  P. australis  clones in the ‘Temp’ treatment suggest high rates of photorespiration at the elevated temperature, due to the enhanced oxygenation reaction of Rubisco impacting the C 3  pathway of photosynthesis ( Berry and Björkman 1980 ). However, the fairly constant  F  v / F  m  ratio, which is close to 0.8 in healthy vascular plants ( Björkman and Demmig 1987 ), indicates that the plants in the ‘Temp’ treatment were not stressed. Moreover, the leaves were acclimated to adequate light availability as judged from the Chl a/b ratios, which were generally higher than those of typical shade leaves ( Demmig-Adams 1998 ;  Lichtenthaler  et al.  2007 ). Hence, despite the slightly lower photosynthetic parameters at elevated temperature, the growth and aboveground biomass were not negatively affected. A similar response has previously been observed for the two clones ( Eller and Brix 2012 ).  Carbon dioxide and temperature interact in their effects on plants. Elevated CO 2  can counteract the negative effects of high temperature ( Lee 2011 ) but high temperatures may also offset the stimulating effect of elevated CO 2  ( Clausen  et al.  2011 ). Although interactions between temperature and CO 2  occurred for some photosynthetic parameters, the pigment ratios, C (x+c) , Chl a  and the leaf C content, no interaction effects were seen on growth and biomass. All growth and biomass traits were only affected by temperature, except for the leaf dry mass content, which was highest at elevated CO 2 , probably due to the slightly higher C content. Nonetheless, since the climate effect on growth may first be seen after long-term exposure that will reveal the contributing role of the belowground biomass to the perennial growth of the species, CO 2  and temperature interactions are very important aspects of future climate change for the two investigated  P. australis  clones. The general observation in our study was that the effects of temperature were diminished under elevated CO 2 . The quantum yield ( α ), PNUE and some photosynthetic pigments were low at elevated temperature but only at ambient CO 2 . Hence, elevated CO 2  seemed to offset the negative effects of elevated temperature.  In conclusion, although in the short term a future rise in atmospheric CO 2  to 700 ppm was found to barely affect the aboveground growth of the two  P. australis  clones investigated, most of their photosynthetic parameters responded positively to elevated CO 2 , and their SLA decreased as a commonly observed response to elevated CO 2 . Elevated temperature produced an increase in aboveground growth, regardless of the atmospheric CO 2  concentration, suggesting that the ubiquitous range of  P. australis  will persist in the foreseeable warmer world. Further studies of total biomass production as well as biomass allocation to specific plant parts are needed to elucidate the overall growth responses of  P. australis  to a changed climate. The responses to temperature and CO 2  concentration investigated here depended on the genetic background of the plant. The DK clone showed the strongest responses and may, due to its higher plasticity, be the clone better adapted to climate change. As our study shows that distinct  P. australis  clones respond dissimilarly to climate factors, in the future it would be worth investigating the responses of other clones of the same phylogenetic background that have a significant impact on their ecosystems. This would, for instance, be appropriate for native and invasive clones of the species, especially in North America, where co-occurring clones are competing and the invasive  Phragmites  threaten the ecosystem diversity.  This research was funded by the  Danish Council for Independent Research—Natural Sciences , via a grant to H.B., and  Aarhus Graduate School of Science .  F.E. carried out the experiment and drafted the manuscript. H.B., C.L., L.X.N. and L.A. participated in the design of the study. All authors helped to draft the manuscript and read and approved the final manuscript.  None declared.  We thank the Risoe Environmental Risk Assessment Facility (RERAF) for hosting the experiment, and the staff at RISØ-DTU for their kind support and taking care of the experimental plants. We also thank Professor Otto Stein for linguistic corrections. 